Good morning, everyone.
My name is Hari Aramshetty.
I'm a software engineer at Flexport.
I'm thrilled to hear today as we dive into
mastering cloud cost efficiency, strategic
optimization for cloud native success.
In today's session, we'll explore not
only the traditional cost optimization
methods, but also how to leverage
FinApps principles to drive smarter
financial management in the cloud.
Whether you're a developer, Operations
expert or financial professional.
There's something in here for you.
So let's get started So here's a
quick overview of what we will cover
today We'll set a stage by discussing
why cost efficiency is critical
in today's cloud environments.
We'll examine the key pain points
in managing the cloud expenses and
how FinOps provides a framework
to address these challenges.
I'll walk you through the actionable
strategies from resource rightsizing
to budget forecasting that will
blend the traditional techniques
with FinOps best practices.
We'll discuss design considerations
that ensure your applications are
both scalable and cost efficient.
I'll share real examples where
FinOps practices led significant
savings and improved governance.
We'll conclude with a step by
step roadmap to implement these
strategies within your organization.
Optimizing cloud costs is more
than just cutting expense.
It's about driving better return on
investment and fueling innovation.
When we control our spend effectively,
we free up resources to invest in new
technologies and business opportunities.
FinOps fosters a culture of collaboration,
Where finance, operations, and engineering
regularly share insights, set joint
cost targets, and adjust resource
allocation strategies in unison.
For example, when unexpected costs
spikes occur, the engineering team
works alongside the finance to
understand and rectify the issue,
while operations implements automated
policies to prevent recurrence.
This unified approach not only streamlines
cost management, but also drives smarter
decision making across the organization,
ensuring that every team, is both informed
and accountable for their cloud spending.
With continuous monitoring and real time
analytics, FinOps enables us to predict
and manage expenses more accurately.
Organizations that master cloud
cost efficiency can reinvest their
savings into growth initiatives
leading to stronger market position.
Essentially, by adopting FinOps, you are
not just saving money, you are setting
the stage for sustainable innovation.
Managing cloud costs comes
with a lot of challenges.
Cloud providers offer many pricing
choices like pay as you go,
reserved plans, and spot pricing.
which can make it hard to know
exactly what you will pay for.
Each option has its own benefits
and drawbacks, making it a
challenge to pick the best one.
This complexity often means businesses
must keep a close eye on their
usage to avoid unexpected bills.
Often companies buy more computing
power or storage than they really need,
which means money on unused resources.
On the flip side, if they don't
use the resources they have,
It's actually wasting money.
This balance is key to managing
the cloud cost efficiently.
Without proper process in place,
each team might set up its own cloud
resources without talking to others.
This can lead to a lot of duplicated
work, wasted money and missed chances
to share and optimize resources.
In short, a lack of
coordination often results in
inefficiencies across a company.
Without proper visibility, it's hard to
know exactly where your money is going.
This is where FinOps makes a difference.
It promotes a culture of shared
responsibility, encourages regular
cross functional reviews, ensuring
that every team understands and
manages their part of the cloud space.
Next, we will look at strategic
cost optimization framework.
Our framework for cost optimization
is built on four key pillars, each
enhanced by FinOps principles.
Start by checking how much you spend on
cloud services, And how you use them.
This gives you a clear starting point and
shows where you can make changes right
away Using data to help you see spending
patterns and set goals for incremental
improvement Start by matching your cloud
resources to your actual needs a practice
We call right sizing and consider reserved
capacity for workloads that run steadily
You can go for RA shopping with your
cloud account This helps ensure that you
aren't paying for more than you need.
Also use Phenom's practices to regularly
review your spending and adjust your
budget based on how much you actually use.
First, set clear policies for
managing cloud costs and use tools
to automatically track spending.
Like tagging.
These tags help you to see which
engineering organization or
project is using each resource.
Then form teams from different
departments to take shared
responsibility, keep track of spending
and make sure the process is followed.
Continually track spending with
dashboards and analytical tools.
Use FinOps reporting to proactively manage
costs and adjust strategies in real time.
This cyclic approach of Optimize, govern
and monitor is critical to achieve
sustainable cost efficiency in the cloud.
Next, we will take a look at
cloud native best practices
for cost efficiency and finops.
When it comes to cloud native design,
building cost efficiency into your
architecture from the start is the key.
Here's how.
Adopt microservices and containerization.
These technologies allow you to build
modular, and scalable applications
that can dynamically adjust to demand.
Using microservices means breaking
your application into smaller
independent parts that work together.
Each part can be updated or scaled on
its own, making the system more flexible.
The containerization packages are
These parts into easy to move units.
So your application can quickly
adjust to the changes in demand.
Another way we can do this is
leveraging serverless architectures.
Serverless computing means you don't pay
for the running servers all the time.
Instead, you only pay when your code
is running or handling a request.
This approach helps you save
money by eliminating costs
for unused idle capacity.
Another strategy that we can use
is implementing auto scaling.
This enables your system to automatically
scale resources based on demand, a
process that should FinOps metrics.
Moreover, Integrating FinOps in your
design process means designing for
cost transparency from the start.
This means every team member from
the developers to the financial
analysts can see how design decisions
impact the bottom line, try for more
informed cost effective decisions.
So let's take a look at key cost
optimization and FinOps strategies.
Let's dive into some of the
practical strategies that blend it.
Traditional cost optimization
with FinOps best practices.
Resource site sizing.
So used detailed usage data for
FinOps dashboards to understand
your current resource utilization.
So that CPU or memory for your containers
or EC2 machines and see how much is an
ideal time and how much is the usage time.
So adjust your resource allocations
dynamically based on real time
demand to avoid over provisioning.
You can also take a look at
reserved or spot instances
based on the workload types.
Reserved instances.
Reserved instances are ideal for
predictable, steady workloads.
They offer a significant cost savings
by committing to a long term usage.
That means, for example, you have a Kafka
cluster, which you need always running.
You use reserved instances
for that type of workloads.
There are spot instances.
that are great for transient or flexible
workloads, allowing you to capitalize
on lower cost during the off peak times.
This can be used for lower
priority schedule jobs that we
run in a distributed system.
The other thing that we can
do is automated governance.
Tagging is a key part
of automated governance.
Implement tagging and cost allocation
policies to monitor and control spend.
Leverage automation tools to
enforce these policies consistently.
for in AWS, you can take a look at
as service control policies, SCPs.
Let's take a look at
tools and technologies.
For cloud cost and FinOps management.
There is a robust ecosystem of tools
designed to help you manage cloud
costs and implement FinOps practices.
Tools like AWS Cost Explorer,
Azure Cost Management, GCP Cost
Insights offer clear dashboards
that show all your cloud spending.
They break down your costs.
By different categories such
as service region or team.
This makes it easier to see where
your money is going and find ways to
save tools like cloud custodian and
terraform help automate the management
of your cloud class by Using code
to set up rules and controls With
infrastructure as code, you can manage
resources and policies automatically
without the need of minor intervention.
This ensures that cost saving measures are
always in place and consistently followed.
This means that you can set rules for
how your resources are used and have
those rules automatically enforced.
Using these tools makes it easier
to manage costs and reduce mistakes.
Advanced analytics and machine learning
help you predict your future cost.
They can also spot unusual
spending from early on.
This gives you time to fix
the problems before they grow.
FinOps tools like Cloud Health
and AppTO give you detailed
insights into your cloud spending.
They help teams from different engineering
orgs work together on managing costs.
Using these tools creates a strong
unified system to keep your cloud
spending optimized and at all the time.
Now let's look at two real world examples
that illustrate the power of FinOps.
In one case, we have a product team
that was consistently overspending due
to overprovision compute resources.
They had three instances of like
overprovision VMs, which were like each
application was using less than CPU.
And they had a database server,
which was vertically scaled.
Much more than they ever needed.
So what did this team do?
So they implemented right sizing
and established a regular FinOps
reviews, ensuring that their team was
accountable for their resource usage.
What was the outcome of this?
this proactive approach resulted
in 30 percent reduction in cost
and a significant improvement
in resource efficiency.
So let me take you on another case
study where there was a business unit
that had budget constraints due to
unmanaged resource drop, with various
teams deploying resources independently.
By centralizing governance, enforcing
strict tagging policies, and holding
cross functional financial reviews, they
improved visibility into their spending.
What was the outcome of this?
The BU not only achieved
significant cost savings, but also
established a sustainable model
for continuous cost management.
These examples underscore how
integrating FinOps practices can
transform your cloud spending from
reactive to proactive process.
Now let's take a look at
building a road map to cloud
cost optimization with FinOps.
So building a roadmap is
essential for long term success
in cloud cost optimization.
Here are some of the steps that you
need to do in order to get this working.
First, assessment.
So begin by auditing
your current cloud spend.
Use FinOps tools to establish
baselines and immediately identify
immediate areas for cost savings.
Planning.
Define clear cost goals and
key performance indicators.
This is also the time to form your cross
functional FinOps teams, bringing together
FinOps, operations, and engineering.
The next is implementation phase,
where roll out the cost optimization
strategies and FinOps practices.
We have discussed today.
Focus on automating governance,
right sizing resources and leveraging
reserved and spot instances.
Last and not the least,
monitoring and iteration.
So using dashboards and regular FinOps
reviews to monitor progress and iterate.
Adjust your strategies based on real
time data and evolving business needs.
Ensure that your cost
optimization plan aligns with
your overall business objectives.
Secure executive sponsorship to help
drive the culture shift necessary for
a successful FinOps implementation.
This roadmap is designed to be iterative
and adaptable, ensuring that your
business cloud cost management practices
remain effective as your business grows.
Drawing from industry experiences
and my own journey, here are some
of the best practices and lessons
learned from a FinOx perspective.
Integrate early.
So incorporate cost considerations
at the design phase of your projects.
to avoid expensive reworks later.
Continuously monitor resource
usage and adjust allocations
based on FinOps insights.
Ensure that every team understands the
financial impact of their decisions
through training and shared dashboards.
Avoid one size fits all.
Everyone has their own needs.
Each team is different
from a different team.
Some teams have different requirements.
In compute than other teams.
So tailor your Fino strategies
to the specific needs and
usage patterns of each team.
Leverage automation.
Automation reduces manual errors and
ensures consistency in policy enforcement.
By embedding these practices into your
operational culture, you create a dynamic
environment where cost efficiency is
part of the DNA of your organization.
all for your time and engagement today.
I hope you found these insights into
cloud cost efficiency and FinOps
both informative and actionable.
If you'd like to continue this
conversation or have further questions,
please don't hesitate to reach out.
You can connect with me on LinkedIn.
Have a wonderful day and thank you again.