Hello, everyone.
My name is Mihaela Guitarsa.
Happy to be with you here today.
Thank you to the organizers for giving
me the opportunity to share what I love
and what I've learned into my experiences
and challenges that I had along the way.
At my core, I'm an engineer and I also
like, even though it seems being an
engineer and someone that does some
public speaking, it's not really going
together, but I really like to do this
and Besides my interest in software
and technology, I like to research
and prepare content that I gather from
my experiences or from things that I
would have liked to know at some point.
And I didn't have anyone to tell me.
And I wrapped this in my presentation
and, opened the conversation
in events like this one today.
So thank you to the organizers
for having me again.
And.
I hope that we have a beautiful
conversation or that I at least
challenge you a bit to go outside of
your, your area of looking at things.
Why I'm saying this because today's
conversation, it's going into the area of
Not so much technicalities, but the way we
are looking at the problems and challenges
that we encounter every day, the way that
we organize our work, the way we think
about ourselves as developers, I'm trying
to open the conversation about how we
are interacting with, with our work and
with our challenges on, on a daily basis.
So I want to open the conversation
with a little exercise, an
imagination exercise, basically.
Think that you're standing at the
base of a towering skyscraper and you
marvel at its intrinsic design, right?
Every element in the structure,
it was meticulously planned.
Each element is serving a
purpose in the overall structure.
Now let's think about the
architect who designed that.
How they had to envision
all those interactions.
How their building is going to stand
We stand the test of time and face
storms and all sorts of challenges,
serve its occupants, how everything
was so purposeful thought of in order
to have the best structure in the end.
So starting with this mindset,
we can transform the way
we are building software.
Taking this kind of concepts from another
field encourages us to think beyond the
immediate, to consider the long term
impact of our decisions, and to create
systems that are not just functional, but
resilient, and scalable, and enduring.
I want to for your attention.
tasks to stay with this
analogy in our mind.
We are not just coding, we are building
something of a digital skyscraper.
Let's explore how we can build
them with the same level of
care, creativity, and foresight.
Because as programmers, we often
find it challenging to step back
and see our products like we are
looking at a building, right?
Most of the time we are deeply
engrossed in our tasks, and unlike
physical construction, we don't have
the same boundaries, very strict,
very exact boundaries, right?
Software development does not
have the same limitations.
We have freedom and we have flexibility to
push these boundaries, actually push the
boundaries of what's possible in the end.
So despite this freedom, when we discuss
perspective and way of thinking, we tend
to stick to familiar patterns, rules,
and we rarely venture outside the box.
And even when we do, We may not
really embrace new ways of thinking,
we feel comfortable to stick to our
existing beliefs, but by breaking
the cycle through reflection.
We can adopt the growth mindset
that leads to better decisions and
a more fulfilling work experience.
And mindset in this case refers to
attitudes and beliefs that shape the
way we approach work, the way we solve
problems, the way we tackle challenges.
It's the lens through which we view our
abilities, tasks, and potential for work,
and the way we actually face challenges.
Brace for impact when difficult situations
appear and when we're discussing mindset,
we cannot stop, we cannot avoid stopping
actually and looking at ourselves.
And if you've ever thought, okay,
I'm just not good at algorithms.
I'll never understand this framework.
Instead of, I don't understand
this yet, but I can figure it out.
You are tapping into fixed mindset.
Because this perspective
limits your growth.
It creates a mental barrier
to learning and adaptation.
Developers with a fixed mindset shy
away from challenges, fearing that
failure will expose their limitations.
In contrast, a growth mindset
is the belief that abilities and
intelligence can be developed through
dedication, learning, hard work.
People with a growth mindset
embrace challenges and view
failures as opportunities to learn.
So we need to be very honest with
ourselves and see exactly where we are.
And I'm not asking you right now to tell
me, okay, what, where are you, where do
you find yourself more, but more like
I want you to be honest with yourself.
Because in the end, the scope
of this discussion is to set
a starting point for growth.
And since we're discussing about
starting point, I think it's a good
thing to bring to discussion a story.
And I heard a while ago, I think I was,
I don't know, doing some volunteering
and someone told me, so I don't
know who is the author, whoever is,
copyrights to you, credits to you.
But the story goes like this.
There were some people
on the breaking stones.
And then there is this man that was
going towards the hill and he got curious
and asked one of the people, okay.
What are you doing?
And that person was very
focused on the artwork.
And they were bothered by the question.
No, they didn't like to be
disturbed from their work
because they were very dedicated.
And yet he answered and
said, I am breaking stones.
The man got very curious and he went
to another and to another until at
some point he got a different response.
Because this last person that he asked
told him, I am building a castle.
As developers we grow new faces, right?
Sometimes we simply complete tasks and
we are just so focused in that area
that we complete the entire context.
So we are breaking stones.
Okay.
On other times, we are interesting
in understanding the system and going
beyond the task and trying to understand
the business, maybe very dedicated,
trying to improve and so on, which
is like building castles, right?
There are many reasons
this imbalance happens.
Sometimes it's the organizations
where we are working.
Sometimes it's the limitation to
information, to the right information.
Lack of options, fear, burnout,
not caring about a project.
this is a reality that we
have to be honest about.
Or maybe we're just the right,
the wrong person for the job.
this happens.
But I feel that we are so
impacted by outside factors and
we are so overwhelmed with it.
Checking some sort of what is the image
of the great developer at some point,
like we have that thing with the effective
developer or efficient developer.
Should I be an effective developer,
one that takes time to ensure
code is clean and scalable and
documented, or should I be an
efficient developer that I implement,
I loadbox, I deploy, I, this approach
allows me a faster time to market.
And, I'll just focus on speed,
skip this part with extended
documentation and meetings and so on.
We are trying to comply with some
patterns, but sometimes we have to look
at ourselves as professional despite the
context in which we are at some point.
So add our skills.
And again, I dare you to be honest
and use the circle of competence
to understand what are your
strengths, your limits and expertise.
Using this mental model in the end, it's
about focusing on what you know well and
recognizing where your knowledge gaps are.
And in this way, you can work
effectively with your expertise
while expanding it over time.
So we can start from the
inside circle, right?
Identifying that.
Seeing what are your strengths, what
technologies, languages, patterns,
you truly understand at a deep level.
Be honest about your limits.
Stay focused on your areas of expertise
while delivering on current projects
because this allows you to build
confidently and produce high quality work.
When presented with tasks outside
your circle, collaborate with others,
whose strengths complement yours.
People that inspire
and you can learn from.
While you're going outside in the
circle, outside of your, the stuff you
know, identify knowledge gaps or areas
of interest that you want to grow into.
Set clear goals.
practice.
Take on projects that stretch
just outside your circle but
are manageable with effort.
Of course, we're going in through
this process, we're having this
process, taking into consideration.
Helps you avoid a situation of
overextending your, and having
overconfidence, because you must be
cautious about assuming you're skilled
in areas just because you've been working
at some point with something similar.
And there is this cognitive bias, the
Dunning Kruger effect, where it is
demonstrated by this psychologist, a true
series of experiments that People with
low ability or knowledge in a specific
area tend to overestimate their skills,
while others with higher ability often
underestimate their skills, right?
So this keeps a balance for
you to know exactly where
you are and don't overextend.
I'm sure that each of you had a
situation at some point where you had
to deal with someone that was having
this bias and you were just so you
know, maybe pissed about the fact that
they are being so confident when you
know exactly how things should be.
So don't be that person.
On another part, there is this mental
barrier that we need to be careful about.
Because even if we don't realize, this
is something that is very powerful
and limiting at the same time.
Because, let's say, if you identify as a
NET developer, you are a NET developer.
You are stuck.
Right?
in your mind, you are a
NET, or Java, or whatever.
It doesn't matter.
You are an ex developer.
But if you are identifying as a
developer who is using X, it can be
NET, Java, whatever, you suddenly can
be a programmer that knows and can
learn and can try other things too.
Just think of situations where you, maybe
someone in your company and said, okay,
we don't have a project right now that
it's using the skills that you have.
But look, there is this opening
in here, something that we think
that might be interesting to you.
technologies are going
to evolve, so try to not.
identify with them, try to keep your
mindset fluid in this area and don't
block yourself into a, a bubble.
The circle of competence isn't
just about recognizing your skill,
it's a tool for growth in the end.
When you understand where you excel and
where you need to improve, you can make
better decisions, you can work on yourself
constantly and become not efficient
or effective or, all sorts of labels.
But be a developer that is
bringing some impact in your work.
We've been discussing about the inner
circle, and we've been discussing
about that, circle where we know what
we don't know and we want to grow.
But we also touched the areas
where we think we know something,
but we actually don't know.
But how about that outside
circle, the thing that we
don't know that we don't know?
How do we tap into that area?
that area that I think that is the
area of blind spots, It's difficult to
understand the system we're a part of
precisely because there are blind spots.
We can't see what we are looking for.
We only see them at some point where
we have, we have somebody porting from
production or something like this.
And a way to do this, I found, of
course, a lot of the conversation
that we are having today has a lot
of points from the book, that can
be found also in the book, but.
This precisely got my attention because
these are three things that if we work
with are going to help us see the blind
spots that we have, to reveal those
blind spots and, at least minimize
that area if not completely, reveal it.
be that, of course, we are discussing,
I was mentioning the book, which is
the great mental models by sheen purge.
And in the book, we have this three,
factors, perspective, ego induced denial
and distance from the consequences.
We need to approach problems with
different perspectives, even if it goes
on different models, mental frameworks.
We are going to discuss today some mental
models and some example of mental models.
So this is one area where we
need to expand our knowledge.
Then we need to lay low on the ego
and be honest and ask for help and
accept that we are continuous students.
And we need to face and stay close
to the consequences of our decisions.
When we are making
decisions that we are not.
Assuming the consequences were, we
create that broken window effect, just
as an urban environments where one
broken window left unrepaired signals
lack of care and invites more damage.
So also in our work, small
RSO issues in our code.
our mindset, our processes can accumulate,
leading to bigger problems over time.
If we don't address these issues as early
as possible, we risk letting all sorts of
poor practices and blind spots take root.
So it becomes harder and
harder to solve problems.
And going further in the
perspective part, because this is
maybe the most powerful of them.
You know how in school we are learning.
are learning about different areas, right?
We are learning about physics
and biology and math and all
psychology, economics and so on.
And we are, we've been learning
and creating this way of
thinking in departments, right?
But in the real world, we need to
combine these departments because
problems in the real world are
not Divide it so precisely, right?
So we need to work on our
multidisciplinary mindset,
because if we don't, we miss
the full picture of a problem.
And our next step is not going to be the,
the closest to the best, if not the best.
If a single worldview dominates
our thinking, we'll try to explain
every problem through that lens,
even if it's not the right fit.
the old saying with, to the man
with only hammer, everything
looks like a nail, but not.
It's not like this in this, in this world.
We need to understand the complexity
of the world and we need to understand
how important it is to, draw knowledge
from, from different models and different
perspectives and different fields.
In an example, and actually the
first mental model that I would
like us to discuss today is the
Swiss army knife approach, which is
Charlie Munger's way of thinking,
Charlie Munger's way of thinking.
Basically, he believed in having
wide, a wide range of mental models,
similar to having many tools.
as we have in a Swiss army knife.
And these metal models, of course,
come from different fields, from
different perspectives, and they
help us see challenges from different
approaches, approach them from different
angles, to find the best solutions.
And if we think, if we go into a forest,
with a botanist, real estate agent and
a yoga trainer, of course, each of them
is going to see a different perspective.
Maybe the audience is going to
be marveled by the nature, right?
Exactly.
How about details from the nature and,
appreciate it and think about how we
can, we need to keep this as untouched
by human, action as possible and so on.
A real estate agent may be thinking more
from the perspective of a business, right?
How he could sell this, how, this could
be a very good place for having a, a
building, a neighborhood and so on.
Then the yoga trainer might be thinking
about the energy and what is happening
in their house session would be so useful
to have in there and to really let our
bodies and mind to use the energy from
there in order to have a great experience.
Each of these perspectives captures
a part, but not the whole picture.
And if we rely on a specific
discipline, we develop gaps.
Yeah, those blind spots
that we were talking about.
You can add up, of course,
there is a confirmation bias,
which makes things even worse.
Next, a mental model that challenges to
look a bit at how we are considering,
the materials that we are using or
the way that we are organizing our
work is the map is not a territory.
That refers to the idea that
abstractions like, diagrams and
some schemes, that we are doing.
Yeah.
or any representation are not
the same as the reality itself.
So any model or map that we create
to understand something is a
simplification and doesn't capture
every detail of real world system.
And this applies directly to software
development where we work with diagrams,
for example, and requirements and
models that not fully represent the
complexity of the system itself.
And we can think, for example, Let's
say we are, a very careful developer,
that follows, the project specification,
document closely, but then when
testing in production and, having
our solution in the real world, we
encounter some unexpected issues, right?
So using this model helps us
recognize that the specification.
The document, the map, yeah,
it's not the same as the actual
running system, the territory.
No matter how detailed the
specification is, it will miss some
real world behaviors or edge cases.
And by acknowledging
this, we remain cautious.
We implement retesting, including those
edge cases that we were mentioning,
to ensure that the actual software
performs as intended in the real world.
The third mental model that I
want us to touch today, it's
the second order thinking.
And I would like to start by
there is this effect,
all the cobra effect.
Basically, the story goes that when
the British colonial government in
Delhi wanted to reduce the number
of cobras in the city, they offered
a bounty for every dead cobra.
Initially, this seemed like a good
idea, but in time, there were some
individuals that realized that
they could breed cobras and they'll
kill them for the bounty, right?
And increasing, of course, their profits.
This was not a good idea
since the government found
out and stopped the program.
Yeah.
After discovered this unintended
consequence of, of their program.
And in response, the cobra breeders, of
course, having no use for the snakes,
they released them causing the cobra
population be even worse than before.
So this unintended outcome is
recognized as the cobra effect.
And actually this is, if we look
carefully, we see the consequence and
the consequence of our decisions in the.
consequences of the
consequences of our decisions.
And this is exactly what the second order
thinking mental model touches, because it
encourages us to look beyond the immediate
consequences, to understand their long
term effects, as well as ripple effects
that might arise from these decisions.
And let's again take an example
in software development.
Let's say that we are part of a team that
is being assigned to work with, e commerce
platform, And of course, The thing that
we do, we are focusing on delivering the,
the core functionality of the platform.
Ensuring that the basic features
like, think first, right?
Basic features like product search,
checkout, payment, work smoothly, right?
Maybe we even think about, okay, let's
prioritize performance and speed to give
users a bra, fast browsing experience.
This is the first thing that
we are considering, when
we are here in e commerce.
Okay, but these are the
first order thinking.
This is an example, again,
take it with a grain of salt.
But if we go a bit more into
details, we can actually consider
those second order effects.
Yeah, we can start thinking beyond the
immediate functional requirements and
think, okay, but what happens if spikes?
if traffic spikes dramatically.
Yeah.
What happens if part of the system fails,
for example, the payment component.
And if I have to add new features,
features to this, will it be easy?
Will it be hard for
the business to evolve?
How things will be?
By asking this kind of question.
So going a bit beyond to the
second order concerns, we can
see other important factors.
a service like scalability, the
need for availability and fault
tolerance, performance under load,
security and compliance, and so on.
this, this mental model helps us
exercise, considering the ripple effects
of our decisions, and help us identify
and prioritize Characteristics that
will ensure long term success, right?
It prevents us from focusing on
short term functional goals and,
helps us handle future challenges and
opportunities with minimal, disruptions.
an interesting part about,
about us, and we are discussing
before, about this when talking.
about blind spots is that we cannot
understand a system that we are a part of.
And relativity involves understanding
that things are not absolute and often
depend on context or perspective.
Yeah.
So my all time favorite example or
situation for this is when we have
to choose from or technology language
and application for an application.
Doesn't matter technology
language approach.
Doesn't matter.
I remember some years ago, we were
not sure if this dispute since
still is, but there is what is best.
Java, what is best.
React or Angular, which is the
best, has the best approach, how
we are going to work with it.
things like this, like what has the most
advantages, which one is the best, where?
Instead of asking what's the best
programming language, how about, I
think, what is the best programming
language for this specific project?
The best language is relative
to the skill set of the team,
projects, requirements, timeframe.
There's no absolute best answer.
What matters is the context
in which the decision is made.
Then, instead of always striving for
brilliance or perfection, it's often more
effective to focus on avoiding mistakes.
In the context of software, for example,
this could mean focusing on common
pitfalls and making sure to avoid them.
For example, let's say that you
have a deadline, a very aggressive
deadline, you did not expect this.
Things have changed in the project.
What we are going to do, instead of
thinking, okay, what are the best
practices to follow to meet this deadline,
those, magazines that are then giving you,
10 steps to be the best manager, 10 steps
to be a productive developer, and so on.
Instead of looking for these 10 steps
to ensure that we meet the deadline,
how about we apply inversion, right?
And ask what common mistakes
we need to avoid that could
make us miss the deadline?
What did we do the last time
when we missed the deadline?
Let's avoid doing that.
Start from that point.
Then, by deliberately avoiding
these common mistakes, you increase
the chances of success rather than
just looking for the best way to
do it without being validated.
You already validated what are the worst,
the worst things that you can do to not
be the deadline for sure in the past.
Start from there.
Focus on ensuring that simple
errors don't derail the project.
Then moving forward, you know how we
have this tendency of Thinking that
the more complicated something or the
problem that you're facing, or the
more complicated the solution that we
are giving you, the more complex, the
more, important we are because we don't
know the same thing as everyone else.
So we end up becoming really good at
something specific just to stand out.
And sometimes we actually find or
look for complex, resolutions for
our problems just to make sure that
others can easily understand it.
But besides that, to make sure that
we stand out with our complex way of
looking at things, our outcomes raiser.
It's a concept that suggests that
when faced with multiple competing
solutions, the best starting point
is to start with the simplest one.
If your project is not, explicitly
asking for the most complex solution,
start with, with the simplest one.
And we have a lot of examples in software.
I'm sure that you've been thinking
about at least three since I
opened the conversation about this.
But what I can say to wrap up this is
to avoid overengineering solutions in
both development, design, architecture,
design for simplicity and usability
and focus on straightforward solution
during debugging and problem solving.
And, a simple, more focused
approach is easier to use and
it's easier to build upon.
of course, again, take
it with a grain of salt.
Check the context of your.
situation, problem, whatever it
is, and try to build step by step.
to see exactly what kind of approach
you need to do, but don't respond out of
ego, which we're mentioning a bit before.
Of course, we've touched today
some mental models and there
are a lot of mental models.
I actually encourage you to look on
it and see, but it's not about knowing
them, knowing as many as possible.
It's about being open and learning.
Yeah.
We need to.
move away from solving immediate
tasks and start thinking holistically
about the systems we build.
And these kind of models help us navigate
complexity and make better decisions.
And they allow us to design software that
does not only solve current problems, but
is adaptable for future growth and change.
So I'm going to leave you
with this beautiful code from
Alexander, which I think it's the
essence of a developer's mindset.
When you build a thing, you cannot
merely build that thing in isolation.
You must repair the world around it.
understanding that every piece of
software contributes to a larger system.
So just to close the
circle, build castles.
Don't just break castles.
Don't just break stones.
Think about your, your
work from this perspective.
I want to very much for staying with
me today and for listening to my talk.
I hope that I was able to.
to open some question for you or
some areas that you would like
to explore further and yeah,
reach out and let's discuss.
Thank you very much.