Hello, everyone.
I hope everyone is doing well.
Welcome and thank you for joining
the session on AI Driven Chaos
Engineering, Automating Resiliency
Testing with Predictive Insights.
Shreeman Yaram, Senior Engineering
Manager in Test at Coupa Software.
I specialize in AI, automation, and
resiliency testing, including focusing
on DevSecOps and security testing.
Over the years, I have worked
with distributed systems.
I'm going to talk about what
is Chaos Engineering and AI
driven testing strategies.
Helping teams to build more
reliable, failure architectures
and infrastructures as well.
focus is on making chaos engineering
smarter in today's session,
instead of just breaking the
system to see how they fail it.
believe AI can help us
to predict the future.
failures, automate chaos testing, and
continuously improve system resiliency.
I'll walk you through how AI can enhance
chaos testing, shifting us from reacting
to reacting the failures, anticipating and
preventing them before they impact users.
Let's dive in.
Introduction to chaos engineering
and most of us would be knowing
what is chaos engineering.
But let us take a moment and let us first
recap and refresh our knowledge on what is
basically chaos engineering is all about.
Chaos engineering is all about
testing system resiliency by
intentionally introducing failures.
We want to intentionally introduce the
failures and see how the system of waiting
for someone, something goes wrong in
production, we do is we try to simulate
real world failures in a controlled
way and see how the system responds.
the purpose we want to identify
the weaknesses before they cause
the actual issues in the production
for our users, for our customers.
Be proactive.
Testing different failure scenarios,
we can fix the problems early while in
the development phase itself and make
our system more reliable rather than
seeing these problems in production.
its core, the key principle, at its
core, engineering, chaos engineering
follows one principle, embrace
failure to build robust system.
Instead of fearing of failures, we can
use them as opportunity to learn, adopt,
and improve the system resiliency.
This approach helps us to move from being
reactive, fixing things when they break,
to being proactive, designing the systems
that can handle failures gracefully.
all about the chaos engineering.
While many of my colleagues, many of the
speakers have already covered what is
kiosk engineering and all sort of things,
it's a, I don't want to stress on that,
but I want to show you how the traditional
kiosk testing is being done and why it's
not enough and why we need to use AI
that could take us into the next level.
Challenges in, in predicting
real time failures.
Unpredictable failures.
Even with all the kiosk testing we
do, unexpected failures still happens,
often at the worst possible times.
Engineers, SREs, DevOps, SecOps teams
work hard to anticipate issues, but
real world systems are unpredictable,
and failures can still slip through.
One big challenge is complexity.
Because why it happens?
Because of the complexity.
Modern systems are made up of
countless services, dependencies,
and external integrations like
AWS, S3s, what, you name it.
In the microservices world, people use a
lot of third party software, third party
systems and they integrate with them.
As the scale predicting every possible
failure mode becomes nearly impossible.
And then there is a cost,
both in time and resources.
Running continuously chaos testing
takes effort, infrastructure,
and careful coordination.
It's not always feasible to simulate
every failure scenario at scale.
It's impossible, basically.
So while chaos engineering is a
great way to uncover weaknesses,
it also has limitations.
The question comes.
How do we get beyond
traditional chaos testing?
How can we make it make this
process smarter and more efficient?
where the AI comes into the picture.
Let's dive in how AI can help predict
and manage failures in a better way.
When we Let's, before we go in deeper
about the idea, let's break down the
difference between the traditional kiosk
engineering and AI driven kiosk testing.
traditional kiosk engineering, the
approach engineer use usually takes is
manually fault injecting into the systems,
which we know, which the engineer knows
or which the team knows, a shutdown in
your server, adding a latency to an API.
or simulating a database outage or
simulating a third party system outage.
These tests are based on what an engineer
or what a team could think of it.
Meaning that we are relaying whole
on a knowledge and past experiences.
see a problem here.
The problem is We are not
covering the real world failures.
We do not know once the system
goes in production, what kind
of a problems we would face.
Real world problems, failures do
not always follow our assumptions.
Because systems are complex and unknown
failure can occur anytime and that
could slip through us, through from us.
Plus, because the, This
approach is most manual.
The scope is often limited, if
you see, because it's all the
engineering team's knowledge.
can only run a set of limited
real world test cases.
after that, the tests are done.
Engineer After the tests are done,
engineers have to manually try
to see the results, which takes
time and leaves a room for human
error, because when we introduce
manually It leaves a human error.
And there is the biggest issue.
This whole process is a reactive
approach and we are identifying
failures after they happen rather than
preventing them in the first place.
we do, but at one level, one
level, but not at a dynamic level.
Now, what else can we use to stop this?
Yeah, here is what my thought process on
doing this and we have started doing it.
Let's understand how we
can use AI driven approach.
Now let's use, AI to help
us to make it better.
of engineers manually introducing
failures, why not AI can simulate
faults based on the real world data.
What do you mean by the real world data?
We will come there, but let us see
what the real world data could help.
is just not following a
predefined test cases.
If you see in the traditional
approach, we go by knowledge.
Here, we want to go adaptive and
dynamically from the real world data,
we want to continuously monitor the log.
The real world data here is logs.
the real production logs, analyze
the traffic patterns, analyze how
the systems are behaving in the
production environment learn from the
past incidents to uncover the failure
patterns, which we are unfamiliar.
The teams are unfamiliar we
might not, be even aware of it.
For example, let's take an
example for this context.
I'm taking an example as a, in this
context as an e commerce platform.
E commerce platform has a suddenly traffic
spike during Black Friday, okay, AI can
observe how the infrastructure behaves
under such loads, detect subtle issues,
like maybe a payment service might be
a DOM or a shipping service may not be
supporting it and dynamically creating
those kiosks test based on those findings.
That means.
These learnings, what we have in the,
in the Black Friday's, things, we
want that data to be converted into a
machine, into a new experiments for kiosk
engineering testing and continuously
integrating into our CI CD process.
This means instead of repeating
the same old kiosk experiments,
AI adopts the test based on what
actually happens in production.
How?
Using a real world data.
What do you mean by real world data?
All the locks, all the system locks,
all the production locks we take and
we use AI to make it an adaptable.
again, it scales across different systems.
We can, since we, we have the production,
We have all the locks running continuously
and automates, we can automate the
entire testing lifecycle from injecting
failures to analyzing results and
even suggesting improvements as well.
Do you think this is the biggest shift?
Yes.
AI moves from reactive to proactive.
Using AI, now we are going from reactive
approach in the traditional one.
to a proactive approach.
Instead of waiting for a failure to
happen, which we do with the traditional
approach as well, where we have a
limited knowledge, where with the
limited knowledge we are thinking
and we are creating the experiment.
In the AI driven approach, we are using
the production logs to manifest and
create dynamic test cases as a part of
our continuous, loop, continuous loop.
So it anticipates risks and tests.
for them before they cause
the real world issues.
bottom line I want to say is traditional
chaos testing is like guessing what
might break and testing for that.
driven chaos is like watching what
actually break in the real world testing
for those patterns dynamically and as
part of our continuous development cycle.
AI makes chaos engineering
smarter in my view.
faster and more effective
and more resilient.
It makes us the system
to be more resilient.
Again, my suggestion is that
we don't, we should not leave
the traditional replacement.
it's not a replacement for
the traditional approach.
We should use AI as an extension for
what we are already doing it, what we
are already doing in the traditional way.
the knowledge base help us
to simulate the scenarios.
However, in the production, once
the system goes into the production,
use the production logs to become
more effective, run continuous
and improve your chaos testing.
And that's the philosophy that,
that says the, testing, continuously
improve your experiments.
That's exactly what we are doing.
But right now we are using
AI with that, with the real
world data and we are using it.
The best approach is, in my view, the
best approach or what I suggest is the
best approach is to combine both methods.
Keep running well designed manual
chaos experiments while using AI
to expand and improve upon them.
understand integrating AI to
predict and automate failures.
Now that we understood AI driven
Chaos engineering is more adaptive.
Let's break down how AI actually
makes this happen, AI for analysis,
learning from historical failures.
We talked about that.
We have a historical data
in the sense like historical
logs from multiple systems.
We have captured that.
The first step is to
analyze the past failures.
The very first step, we want
to analyze the past failures.
can go through historical logs, everything
from system crashes, slowdowns, error
spikes, CPU spikes, memory spikes, you
name it, and identify these patterns which
humans might have missed in their static
experiments, in the traditional approach.
Instead of relying on intuition,
what I would think is, AI can surface
hidden trends in failure data because
we have a large set of data from last
couple of months, last couple of years,
and use the data, go into deeper and
deeper to understand insights, how
the system may behave under a stress.
Again, for example, let's take,
our database, example, our
database frequently, black Friday
afternoon or on a Friday afternoon.
There could be slowdowns on the system.
On the weekends, we may not be using
it, so we are trying to bring it down
because these are external systems.
may not immediately notice this
pattern, but AI after analyzing
months of logs can flag that this is a
coincidence with a weekly traffic surge.
We don't, we know about our
internal system, we might have a
knowledge on our internal system.
But let's say a payment gateway
system we are integrating, that
knowledge may not be having the steam.
And that external teams, let's say Visa
or Mastercard, if you're using those
systems, they want to reduce, because of
their cost improvement plans, they want
to reduce on the weekends, the usage,
they want to have it as low, and they're
tearing down the servers on the weekends.
It's a hypothetical situation,
we are taking an example here.
That pattern we may not be able to know
until and unless we analyze the logs.
that's where we want our systems to
be very proactively acting on it.
And how do we handle this situation?
That's where the beauty of this
idea comes into the picture.
in other words, if a storm is coming,
if we know that storm is coming, we can
Let's prepare ahead of a time instead
of waiting to get it gone the rain.
Similarly, AI warns us about a
potential system failures before they
escalate, giving time, giving a team
a time ahead to enforce those areas.
Automated injections, kiosk experiments.
Now what we want is
smarter kiosk experiments.
So what first we did is AI analysis
and then we have predictive
modeling we want to give and.
forecast what could be failure, and
then we want to generate automatic
injections or experiments in chaos world,
we see it as experiments automatically
generating the chaos experiments.
Now that's the exciting part, right?
So AI does not just
predict it, acts on that.
on the insights that it learned
from analysis and modeling, AI can
automatically help us design and inject.
A targeted failure.
Areas that are more likely to break
based on the external factors need
not to be external internals as
well based on the traffic and all
those things dynamic in nature.
If AI detects that the payment service
is slow during a peak hours or during
weekends, learns on that pattern
and it can generate a controlled
latency into the service before
the real traffic search happens.
This model will allow the engineers to
test fixes before users are affected.
And this is a continuous process,
which we keep on learning.
on, on just to bring everything all
together, what we are trying to do
is AI learns from historical data
instead of relying on assumptions,
which we talked about In, in, in the
slide where we want to, where we are
trying to show the differentiation.
AI predicts future weak points
based on the past data, helping the
teams to stay ahead on the failures.
automates the chaos experiments, making
tests more relevant and effective.
means we are no longer ran, testing
randomly with the static knowledge.
We are running chaos experiment
where they actually matter.
that's the thing.
let's explore how AI driven chaos testing
can be integrated into a real world force.
And again, I just want to focus why
this works uses relatable examples
like database slowdowns, weather
forecasting, payment service issues,
shipping services, many shipping services
have been slowed down or we want to
take alternative shipping mechanisms.
All sorts of things are.
are really important for an
example of an e commerce.
connects AI role in each stage, we are
learning, predicting and acting it.
excitement while, keeping it
practical and easy to flow.
Now, if you see most applications, these
are the popular tools that they use it.
Okay.
And this is what, where
our entry point would be.
So key observability tools and
logs, if you see, to make AI driven
chaos engineering effective, okay.
We need the right observability.
we don't have a proper logging
mechanism, this is very hard to achieve.
Any application For troubleshooting
or debugging, the logs and the
observability tools are very important.
Tools like New Relic, Splunk, Elk,
CloudWatches, AWS CloudWatches.
There are hundreds of observability
tools, commercial, non commercial and all.
New Relic can help us to
monitor application performance.
Splunk can aggregate and analyze the logs.
And AWS Clouds provides deeper
insights into both infrastructure
and application health.
All these tools are individual tools
can help us to collect the comprehensive
data in and then passing it to the
AI model to learn from the real
world system behavior and finally
generate the experiments files.
Okay.
Now, here is what, I would
say, this is a model.
some of these things are,
at a very high level.
If you see from, the steps that,
what I'm trying to do it here
is first initialize S3 clients.
Here.
This could be replaced with your,
Splunk SD case or a New Relic SD
case, which could help us to get
the data from the real world system.
But for our reference, for a just
easy understanding, let's assume
that there is an S3 bucket, which
has all the system log, okay.
Or.
Or a job which will get the data
from this Splunk New Relic, you
name it, and then gets that into
the S3 and then, that's where, so
we are trying, I did a small sample
program to explain you how it works.
It should, it can be used.
So if you see line number, 8 to, 8 to 11
or, 12, say S3 client is equals to Boto.
I'm using here Boto, bucket name
and get, your S3 bucket and logs.
Okay.
Fetch logs file from S3.
So let us go bucket name, log file,
key file name and whatever the date it
is and read the CSV file and based on
the timestamp and all sort of things
you are trying to do a data frames
and Now converts the timestamp column
and into date format for a proper
time based analysis and again think
of S3 as I mentioned, think of S3 as
a jaint warehouse storing system logs.
section fetch can help you to
fetch all the logs and organize
them into a structure format.
Once again, I'm trying to tell, this is
a sample piece, which I'm trying to take
to get an idea of how we can use this
system and, the idea of using the existing
data or the historical data to do it.
There are many ways to do it instead
of S3, instead of Splunk, you can
use a fetching mechanism or you can
write a client separate code block
for this itself or a separate program
which will keep on fetching the
data and passes it to our AI model.
This you can do it.
This is just an example.
Then you define your feature for AI
analysis that as we talked line number 15
to 17 I would not such, 17 would help you.
Which will help you to understand the
key performance indicators, KPIs, like
CPI usage and response time and all
This metrics are like health indicators
for your system, like checking heart
rate, blood pressure and temperature.
And you can use what
other mechanisms as well.
Again, as I said, it's a just one.
And then detecting anomalies with AI.
Use the isolation forest.
I'm using the isolation forest here.
Okay.
Thanks.
and then, detecting the lysis.
If you see line number 20 to 22
is what we are talking about, that
label, on, a normal logs as normal and
lysis log logs as an normal anomaly.
Like for example, if it is info error
debug based on that, you can label it.
Okay.
it's it's oh.
It's If I have to take an example,
it's like airport security.
Most people pass through a normal,
but suspicious behavior anomalies
get flagged for a deeper inspections.
Okay.
Extract anomaly locks.
Now we use the anomaly locks,
filters the data set that only makes
meaningful and flagged anomalies.
then what we try to do is
finally line number 28 to 25,
you are trying to, inject it.
You are injecting the experiments.
That means if you see on the right
side, experiment is injected.
This is AWS FIS experiment I have
taken for a demonstration purpose.
And that could help us to
understand that there is a CPU.
Usage is high and this could
be applied and it's a regular
example I've taken for CPU, but
there could be many things, right?
DDoS attacks were happening and
that is causing much more slower and
that's where the CPU is increasing.
And how do we simulate that DDoS attacks?
Maybe fake up, use a faker library or
anything and fake up the calls so that,
this kind of scenarios you can build up.
finally, what we are trying to do
is we are trying to finally save
the experiment configuration file.
And, finally we are visualizing it
and, that's how we are trying to do.
The summary is fetching the logs from AWS.
That could be anything.
you can use, SDK clients like Splunk
clients and all sorts of things, and then
detecting anomalies, generating the fault
injections experiments, visualizing,
the display detected anomalies.
that's exactly what this
program is trying to do.
This approach automates,
chaos engineering, making
it smarter and proactive.
instead of relaying on
a predefined scenarios.
Now, overall summarizing the benefits
of AI driven chaos engineering.
So basically what we are trying to do
is proactive resiliency, anticipate
and mitigate potential failures.
We are trying to make sure instead
of waiting for failures to happen
reacting, we shift the predicting,
predicting it where it could
happen and we are preventing that.
AI kiosk engineering analyzes past
failures simulates potential issues
experimental files like AWS AI and
AWS FIS or other kiosk toolkits.
This will help us to strengthen.
And continuous streamlining the process.
Overall efficiency, streamline
testing through automation.
you take the previous ones, we
are, the traditional approach.
It is manual and also it's time consuming
to see what's going on, how it, the
application works and all those things.
With the ai, are preparing the
experiments dynamically based on our past
learnings, which also auto, which is like
analyzing the locks, detecting risks.
generating the fault, faults,
dynamical, experimentals, dynamical.
This reduce the needs for constant
human monitoring and allows teams to
focus on improving the system instead
of just reading it, of just testing.
Again, continuous
improvement is another one.
Since we are leveraging AI for insights
for ongoing system enhancements, can
learn from every test and every failure.
Making future predictions more accurate.
Again, instead of static testing, our
resiliency strategy adapts more over the
time, ensuring stronger, more reliable
systems and new challenging arises.
I close out, you can use
different models to predict.
In our example, I used random
forest, but you can use other things
which could be a time series models
which can understand and do it.
You could find many models
available online and search,
Google search could help.
And by close out thoughts, AI
driven chaos engineering is not
just about breaking the things.
It's about learning, improving
and building systems.
that can handle failures
before they even happen.
layer of testing we are adding
from a traditional versus AI.
By combining prediction, automating
and continuous learning, we are
creating a smarter proactive
approach to the resiliency problem.
you for attending.
If you have any, questions,
please feel free to send it to me.
Thank you.
Have a great day guys.
Bye.