Hello, everyone.
it's a pleasure to be here at con 42.
2025 discussing one of the most,
transformative aspect of modern computing
cloud database management systems.
So I'm Prashant Reddy.
And today I'll take you through
the evolution of cloud database,
highlighting their advantages,
challenges, and future trends.
So whether you're a database engineer
or architect or a business leader,
this session will provide valuable
insights into navigating the cloud
database landscape effectively.
So let's jump on the rise
of the cloud databases.
So traditional on premise databases
are rapidly being replaced
by, cloud based solutions.
So in fact, like the 90 percent
of the enterprises are expected
to migrate to cloud DBMS by 2025.
So there should be a question why the
answer is simple, the scalability,
flexibility and the cost reduction.
So the cloud, database market is booming.
and it's projected to
reach, almost like 68.
9 billion dollars by 2026.
Growing at a growth rate of 15.
7%. So the growth is a testament to how
organizations are trusting cloud platforms
to manage, their most, critical, assets.
So with this shift, It's essential to
understand how cloud databases work
and what makes them a game changer.
So let's jump on to the cloud
advantages, the scalability
and cost effect efficiency.
So the cloud databases
revolutionize the way we handle
the scalability and the cost.
So coming to the elasticity, I would say
the unlike traditional databases, Cloud
DBMS scales instantly from gigabytes
to petabytes within without downtime.
So this means the businesses do not
have to over provision the resources.
So saving money while saving the
money while ensuring high performance.
coming to the second one, I
would say the multi tenancy.
Cloud DBMS reduces the infrastructure
cost by almost 40, 60, 40 to 60 percent
compared to the on premise solutions.
and the organizations only
pay for what they use.
So benefiting from the enterprise
grade security and automatic updates.
So the serverless architectures
are to eliminate the infrastructure
management, which will be
reducing the DevOps overhead.
By up to 80%.
the platform which will take care
of the backup scaling and the
maintenance allowing teams to
focus on more over the innovation.
So these benefits, make cloud
databases cost efficiency.
I would say the scalable
and easy to manage.
So coming to the performance and the cost
savings, the real world impact, the impact
of the cloud databases on the performance
and cost savings is undeniable.
I would say like 300 percent
performance boost cloud based system
deliver faster query responses,
allowing real time analytics and
quick business discussions, decisions.
So 40 percent infrastructure
cost reduction, smart resource
allocation ensures there are no idle
capacity, keeping cost optimized.
So the 60%, 62 percent total
cost savings over three years.
So when factoring in the hardware,
The maintenance and operation
cost organizations see the
significant, financial benefit
with these compelling numbers.
So it's clear why companies are shifting
to cloud based, database solutions.
another challenging is the thing is
the migration and the vendor lock in.
of course, the cloud migration
is not without problems.
So two major concern I would include
them as migration complexity.
So 60 percent of the organization
faces challenges like data
integrity issues, downtime risk
and the schema compatibility.
successful migration basically requires
A careful planning, robust, a testing
and the strong execution strategies.
So vendor lock in, then the major
another concern is the vendor lock in.
62 percent of the enterprises worry about
being logged into a single cloud provider.
The only solution for that is implement
the portable architectures and
maintain the clear exit strategies to
prevent the dependency on one vendor.
So addressing these all challenges
ensures a smooth Cloud transition
and long term flexibility.
So coming to another thing is about
a security and high availability.
and building the trust.
So security and availability are
the two priorities of the cloud.
So security investments, cloud
providers invest heavily in the
advanced threat, detection, encryption,
and the compliance measures.
So to ensure the data protection
and coming to high availability.
Cloud database management
system solutions guarantee 99.
9 percent uptime down for sure and
higher, reducing the downtime and
ensuring the business continuity
by leveraging these capabilities.
Organizations can confidently move
to the cloud while keeping their
data secure and high available.
So as we look.
So basically, as we look to the
future trends, NoSQL and the hybrid
solutions, there are three key
trends are shaping the industry.
So the NoSQL in databases growing
in popularity for handling the
unstructured data and supporting
high volume transactions.
And the hybrid cloud solutions,
is the best of the relational
and NoSQL databases to handle
diverse data workloads efficiently.
And the cloud native applications,
more applications are being built
specifically for the cloud, utilizing
the serverless and the microservices.
architectures for improving resiliency.
So these trends continue to
define how business, store
manage and leverage their data.
So the demand for the
cloud database expertise.
has also reshaped the job market.
So the salary premium, the cloud database
expert, and 17 percent higher salaries
than the traditional, database, management
system professionals, and coming to
the industry demand organizations are
actively seeking skilled professionals
to manage their cloud database
environments and the career opportunity,
I would say the cloud database skills
are now essential for the career
advancement in the data driven world.
So investing in the cloud
expertise is no longer an optional.
It's a necessary for I. T. Professionals.
So from these, we can
the key tech takeaways.
The embrace embracing the cloud revolution
is to summarize the organization should
focus on three main key aspects to
leverage the cloud database effectively.
I would say the cost efficiency, security
and reliability and future proofing.
So coming to cost efficiency.
So the business can reduce total
ownership, cost by 62%, as I said
earlier, through the dynamic scaling
and the resource optimization.
So the coming to security and
reliability, cloud databases provide.
Enterprise grade security and high
availability, making them ideal
for mission critical applications
and coming to the future proofing
investing in hybrid cloud strategies
and cloud database expertise is
a crucial for staying competitive
in a rapidly evolving landscape.
So by embracing the cloud revolution,
Organizations can achieve a greater
efficiency, security and the innovation.
So coming to, so basically coming to
the navigating the cloud databases
landscape for the organizations
planning to migrate to the cloud,
we need to follow a couple of steps.
So basically, assess what we need.
analyze your database workloads,
compliance requirements
and peak usage patterns.
And, the next major important
step is explore the options.
So compare, cloud providers
with AWS, Azure, Cloud, Google
Cloud, and evaluating their cost,
scalability and, security features.
So the next major important
step is like pilot and migrate.
So that's, begin with a small scale pilot.
I would say 10 to 15 percent of
the data before executing the full
migration, implement the paddle
operations to minimize the downtime.
So that's a major, a step.
Every organization should be following.
So a well planned approach ensures
a smooth transition and maximum
value from the cloud adoption.
so from all these, the next steps, I
would say, stay ahead of the curve.
So to maintain the competitive,
Edge in the cloud database
management, we need to encourage
continuous learning within our team.
So regularly evaluate emerging
technologies to stay ahead of the
industry trends and, the partner build
the partnerships with the cloud providers
to leverage any new capabilities.
So cloud technology is evolving
fast and, and staying ahead
will be the key to the success.
So I would say, yeah.
So thank you all for
your time and attention.
I hope this session has provided you with
a valuable insights into the evolution
of cloud databases and how to navigate
the challenges and opportunities ahead.
so yeah, I would like
to hear your thoughts.
Let's open the floor for any
questions or any discussions.
Thank you so much.