Hi, everyone.
Good morning.
Good evening.
Hope you guys are doing good.
This is the raw.
Welcome back by another talk.
today we were talking about how we can
build API ecosystem for our organizations.
Definitely this will help us a lot.
again, welcome to this presentation on
integration AI driven analytics and API
ecosystem in nonprofit organizations.
Let's explore how this framework combines
advanced one on one analytics with
multi platform data synchronization.
We're going to talk about how we're going
to bring data from different social media
platforms into your existing database.
so let's see.
In today's world, there are a number
of third party vendors who can provide
their service to bring data from all
the social channels like Facebook,
LinkedIn, TikTok, YouTube, and all other
platforms, because they have already
predefined, scripts, the programs, right?
So they will provide the services.
it's.
Eventually it's our data, so they use
our, our credentials and whatnot, right?
And, they're going to charge,
yearly subscriptions, to
accommodate all the data needs.
So today I wanted to explain
and provide, different ways, to
avoid that, third party tools.
And how you can inbuilt it.
Your own platform data using this approach
to bring into your, the databases, right?
yes, definitely.
there is a scripting is involved.
and there are the technologies which
we need to accommodate this process,
which I'm going to discuss today.
But definitely this is, Maintenance free.
And, we don't have to pay, so many
dollars, on yearly basis, right?
If it is a one time, so
maybe we can consider it.
But what we need to do, we're
going to end up paying every
year for the same subscription.
So this solution is what we're
talking today, which will help
us to bring your data into your
database using these approaches.
assume that, assume that you
have the different data flows.
for instance, the data you're looking
for the Facebook, Instagram, LinkedIn,
Twitter, TikTok, Meta, all that,
all the social platforms, right?
that it VA media or,
organic social media, right?
Yeah.
what we are going to do if, as
you see, my screen here, so we
need the login details, right?
So we are going to build.
A script, with within the,
shehar, or no JS N right.
And then, we prepare that API and there
are the two options we can accommodate to
schedule that, the script, which or the a
PA which we build, and that will bring the
data and that convert into the CS three.
And they'll place it to the secure
location based on the, Based on
the target location, which we
described in our, the script, right?
And then, yes.
Okay.
Let's say, there are
a couple of scenarios.
First, yes, we need the login details.
The platform which you are
going to access, right?
And then, we need to prepare the
script, with either Shehar or the, node
Jason, with all that, a PE details and
endpoint and all those things, which
we are going to talk in a minute, huh.
and then, we need.
To prepare the script and it
will automatically download the
data from, the social platforms.
It's not only social platform like
any platform if you wanted to bring,
which is APA supported, right?
Eventually, these solutions
will work on that, right?
And, prepare that.
The API and if you wanted to go with the
window scheduler, or if you wanted to go
to AWS Lambda, right nowadays, like many
people are using the AWS services, right?
So it's again, it's not that expensive.
If you wanted to go to the AWS
Lambda, it's relatively very
cheap for the subscription, right?
For the scheduling, but if you don't want
to, if you don't have AWS services, it's
okay, but still you can use the window
scheduler right to trigger ever jobs.
And then, I will talk about how
to set up the, the scheduler also.
So then, the schedule will run.
And that will pick up the API, which you
have that script and that script will
talk to their source and then bring the
data and put it into the CSV location.
And from CSV to the database, so you
can use the AWS Lambda, or maybe you can
use another mechanism to the database.
Then from there, your BI analytics
come into the picture, right?
So now how this is going to work, right?
let's say, this is what, where we are
going to talk a little bit details, right?
as in that, as every a PA, which has
their own end points and based on
the KPA, which we are looking for.
So we need to make sure, And go
through that API documentation,
whether that is supported.
Yep.
If yes, then what are the pros and cons?
How we need to get the data.
So all this, application, they have
really, good API documentation.
We just need to go through
and get the data, right?
for instance, we're talking about
the, like maybe Sprout Social, right?
Sprout Social or the Meta ads.
So they have this process API.
and they'll provide that endpoints matrix,
and there are some other parameters,
which we're talking here, right?
So let's say if you're looking
for, a customer ID or the topic ID.
you need to go through that and get
those details and you can pass those
information into your script, right?
So before we implement the script.
what I do normally, right?
I use the postman to make sure how it is
responding, how the data is coming, right?
My numbers are matching with
the source or not, right?
So that is the tip I can
provide you here, right?
so before we move to the script, right?
And similarly, let's say if you're
looking at the meta ads and yeah,
metadata also has then not really a
good API, in the documentation and
they have some other parameters also.
We talk meta app, id, meta
pay inside fields, meta app
pay inside, pay Inside Limit.
And what not.
And similarly, if you're looking at
the Google Ads, they have that API
documentation and the endpoints,
and the Bing Ads, the Bing Ads,
I would say it's a little tricky,
but it's not that complicated.
so they have a really good documentation.
So there are other parameters.
Let's say if you see Google Ads, right?
The client ID, client secret,
and let's token endpoint.
So these are the other parameters
which we need to consider, right?
so once let's say, If you wanted to
bring entire universe from your social
channel, or if you're looking for the
specific metrics you wanted to bring
into your reporting platform, right?
So that's where we need to, we need to
have that final, the requirements, right?
So if you wanted to bring, entire
universe from the, source systems,
yes, you can absolutely, consider that.
And you need to prepare the script.
ba based on the KPIs, we are looking
for, so there are some key points
which we need to consider, right?
so how many KPIs we are bringing
and, if that, that KPA, which we
are looking for is supported by
that a PA or not, so that, that is
a first thing we need to do, right?
there are some KPIs, which, we.
Which, these platforms may not support,
but what we need to do in that case,
we need to raise a support ticket
to the, source platform, team, and
they will, provide those details.
But if, as long as, if that KPI is
existent, supported by the API, so you,
and you have that credential in the API
endpoints, you can go ahead and build it.
Another thing what we need to consider
is like the paginations, right?
so we need to make sure, the
paginations is rightly set up, right?
then the other point, other
important point is a majority
of the social, platforms.
So based on my observation,
the mostly refresh.
On, around nine, after
nine, am EST, right?
Like maybe if you schedule your, the
scheduler, before nine o'clock 9:00 AM
EST, so you may not see, up to date data.
and again, right?
this is based on the
documentation on my experience.
Maybe, if you have the different
needs on that scheduling and how.
How fresh data you are looking for.
I recommend you to, go through
the, the documentation and set
your scheduling accordingly, right?
the same approach will applicable for all
other the platforms, being it's a tick
tock or, LinkedIn or the Twitter, right?
only thing on the Twitter side,
the sentiment for the Twitter,
we need to focus on that.
if you have the requirement to bring
the sentiment from the, X platform.
So you need to make sure whether that X
platform is support, the sentiment or not.
Yeah.
these are the findings, which I
would like to share a value or
in a connecting with the API.
so then once we build the.
so what do we need to do?
we need to prepare the Windows
scheduler to bring the data
on schedule basis, right?
because you don't want to do
the manual every day, right?
so that's when the scheduler will help us.
It is a Windows inbuilt, the tool and
many, many People, you know, using it,
but it's pretty, pretty straightforward
to set up the windows scheduler.
so you're going to find the windows,
but the only thing is that you should
have the admin privileges to utilize
the scheduler, the features, right?
so open the windows scheduler
from, from your start.
program, and, and, they need to
create that task and look for the,
the script, which are the API, which
we developed to bring the data.
For instance, I like the Facebook, right?
If we prepare that API, using the
mechanism, which we talked before.
and place it into your, C drive or D
drive, where, wherever you want it to
utilize that program automatically.
And, the same mission, like use the
window scheduler, open the window
scheduler and go to the task and
create the, just give it a name.
And, you need to set A few things
they're like now browse that file
of the APA, which we created the
Facebook for instance, right?
And look for that and the set the
refresh timing and give that target.
let's say if you wanted to bring it
to the article or, Amazon redshift.
So create the same structure how you have.
In your file, so that way, this file,
the new scheduler will, refresh and
load the data into the same target file.
So you need to make sure you
define the target file as well.
So only thing you need to consider
here is when you're creating the
target file, make sure, data types
and the sequence, all that in the
same as you were, in your script.
So then, when you set up this, your
scheduler, make sure to run two, three
test runs, with a small amount of
data, and, and then that's it, right?
once you have the, the, scheduler runs
and create the data aggregate file,
it will go and roll into the table.
I just wanted to repeat, one more time.
Just, first thing we need to have
the valid, user login details.
And the second thing, we need to make
sure what KPIs, which we are targeting
to bring into your, the database.
And the third thing is
that KPIs are support.
by API or not, right?
That is another thing
which we need to do it.
So once we pass all these things, the
next thing is, try to, work on the
postman, So that way, If everything
is working fine, or if you see any
hiccups and whatnot, then, you need to
create that package, what we call it
as, the package of the API and bring
that package into your local system.
And then the next step is, create
the scheduler, and, before you
enable the scheduler, make sure
you create the target table, right?
In the scheduler, all what we
need to do is use that package and
define the target and define when
the scheduler has to be run, right?
So once you set up all
this, you're And run it.
So your data will come and
sit in your, the database.
Yeah, so that's pretty simple.
So this will work for
all other applications.
so that way, we don't have to opt,
other third party tools and paying so
much of dollars in, on a yearly basis.
So this is our data.
And yes, the technologies we need, one
we need, either C sharp, or, nor Jason,
that, and then, the window scheduler
is, I think pretty straightforward
and little bit, the CSL knowledge.
another key point is, you need to
have that admin privileges to say,
to enable the scheduler or they
create the table in the database.
Yeah.
So if you have all these
things, you can go to start.
And now let's talk about the impact of
digital transformation in nonprofits.
If you see the leading organizations
successfully adapted to the
AI and cloud based solutions
for donor management is 78.
2%. which is really, the good
number and efficiency improvement.
Yeah.
So greater productivity through
automated workflow and digital tools.
We see, around 56.
2 percent and, no overhead deductions.
It's closely close to 43.
8%. Engagement boost is 67.
4%. And the API integration, right?
If you see the API integration,
that's where we are almost in a 62.
7%. And a cloud infrastructure.
Yes, I would say, it's 45.
5%. API, AI driven analytics,
revolution, donor relationships,
private, donor retention or,
annual donations, predictions and
accuracy, mission learning models.
So all this will help us to, all
that AI driven analytics for donor
management system and, a little bit, on
the architecture level, like now, it's
a high volume data processing, right?
It's because, based on, on the
data, what we were using, right?
Our robust infrastructure
handles, for almost 4.
7 TB of donor monthly and
enabling real time decisions
making across all the platforms.
And enterprise media intelligency,
it's industry leading, which
if you see it's close 99.
9%, which is pretty high,
right up to while processing 1.
2 million daily media mentions,
ensuring comprehensive brand monitoring.
And there is a comprehensive social
analytics, the advanced processing 2.
3 millions, cross platform
social interaction, delivering
actionable engagement insights.
Performance, marketing analytics,
multi cloud, redundancy,
advanced executive framework.
Yeah, this all will, consider as a,
our system architecture overview.
we'd like to, spend a little time on,
AWS Lambda infrastructure performance.
I do see, the Lambda, performance
also really good, right?
the enterprise grid reliability is 99.
95%. And, lightning fast response is 95%.
Scalable performance is really good.
dramatic cost saving, I do see,
really, good number over there.
The advances are, Serverless architecture,
leveraging AWS Lambda, event driven
compute model, it's dynamically
allocating up to, 10 GB memory, and
executing functions with, almost 99.
9 percent availability across
multiple global regions, and scalable
performance, multi region, resilience,
yeah, so all this is, considered as
AWS Lambda infrastructure performance.
So then, let's talk about.
AI Powered Donor Analytics Platform,
it's a 360 degrees donor view,
processing, as I mentioned, like the 4.
2 TB of donors information
daily equivalent to 2.
1 million donor profiles,
which is pretty high.
Predictive Analytics Engine,
yes, it is analyzing, 3.
5. 3. 2 million donor behavior patterns
daily with 94 percent accuracy, right?
94 percent accuracy is really,
it's a good percentage.
The advanced research infrastructure,
executing, 234 complex queries daily with
a lightning fast 98 ms response time.
a simple neutral networks with 96.
5 predictive accuracy across,
diverse donors segment.
So real time data processing, yeah.
So the, this enterprise is great platform.
Harm is cutting edge.
Aye.
And distributed computing technology
to, to transform nonprofit
operations by processing over 8.
7 million donor interaction
monthly across, 2345 organizations.
And now if you're looking to 360 degree
donor view system, this is really
impactful for any organizations when
you have a 360 degree donor view.
exactly the donor, right?
where he is, how much healthy
he is, how much he's donating,
where else he's donating.
and all that information, right?
the instant social, intelligency.
And the precision error optimization,
a data driven reliability.
yeah, so this all will help us, you
know, to know better about your donor.
And the more we know about the
donor, the more we can, get the
funds, from the donors and some
predictive analytics engines, right?
Advanced data processing, Intelligent
ad integrations, dynamic donor
profiling, assembling machine learning,
architecture, real time data processing.
So if we consider all these things,
this really, help us, to have
that, really, good productivity.
They're the most effective analytics
engine established in our organizations.
Advances such infrastructure.
so this is nowadays, this really helped
us a lot to understand more, right?
the light, lightning, fast
processing, human, understanding
robust, add intelligency,
holistic sets, scalability, right?
so this will really, help us
advance such infrastructure.
digital analytics and API ecosystem,
the core platforms, like there are like,
seven, systems we can talk about the
core platform components, implementation
architecture, operational consideration,
restful API integration, scalability
framework, compliance and security
layer, and, performance telemetry.
At the conclusion,
transformative potential, right?
Our revolution digital analytics
framework has already demonstrated
extraordinary impact with participating
non profits seeing an average 47 percent
of increase in donor engagement and
a 42 percent improvement in retention
rate by seamlessly integrating AI
driven analytics across multiple
platforms and processing over 8.
7 million monthly donor infrastructure.
So we are empowering organizations
to transform data into meaningful
relationships and measurable results.
Yeah, so with that, so establishing
this, API ecosystem to bring the
multiple data, multiple, social.
Platform data into your, your database now
without relying on the third party tools.
it's really helped.
one, you can do a lot of cost
saving and to, it's your data.
You are owning your data on
your understanding the data.
and three, you can do, really,
good analytics, out of it.
Thank you so much, for your time.
Hope, hope you have, something,
useful, for your organization today.
Thank you so much.