Hi, everyone.
I'm Shashank Reddy Biravelli, currently
working in Walmart as a software engineer.
I'm excited to be here to dive into
a topic that holds immense value
for business across all industries.
How AI driven solutions are
transforming data quality management.
In today's data driven world, maintaining
high quality data is no longer just
important, it's mission critical.
Organizations often face
challenges in ensuring their
data remain accurate, consistent,
and complete across all systems.
Without strong data quality
management, there may be business
unreliable decisions, missing
valuable opportunities, and incurring
significant financial losses.
AI driven solutions are completely
transforming the way we validate, clean,
and maintain data at scale, making data
management not only more efficient, but
also more reliable than ever before.
The AI revolution in data
quality is transforming how
businesses manage their data.
Predictive validations use
advanced AI algorithms to analyze
patterns and forecast up to 95
percent of potential data issues.
before they affect operations.
Trastically reducing cost errors.
Automated cleaning systems continuously
monitor and cleanse data in real time.
Eliminating duplicates, standardizing
formats, and correcting inconsistencies.
with 99 percent accuracy.
Meanwhile, real time enrichment
engines automatically enhance data by
adding valuable content from trusted
sources turning simple records into
powerful business intelligence.
This level of automation and intelligence
ensures data stays accurate, reliable,
and ready for impactful decision making.
The tangible business outcome of AI driven
data quality management are significant.
Thank you AI solutions can improve
data accuracy by 40%, leading fewer
errors, more reliable reporting,
and more confident decision making.
They also reduce operational cost
by 35%, by automating manual data
quality process, which eases the
burden on IT teams and data analysts.
Additionally, AI systems process data to
50 times faster than traditional methods.
enabling real time quality monitoring
and instant correction of data issues.
These improvements result in more
efficient, cost effective, and reliable
data management across organizations.
Let's take a look at some real
world success stories where AI
driven data quality solutions
deliver impressive results.
A Fortune 500 bank reduced its manual
data cleansing by 77 percent from 120
per week using AI powered validations.
This change eliminated 2.
3 million in annual operational cost
and improved compliance accuracy to 99%.
And Automotive Manufacturing
implemented AI quality control systems.
across 12 global plants, achieving a 85
percent improvement in data accuracy.
This transformation eliminates
150k production errors annually
and reduced material waste by 4.
2 million.
A national healthcare network uses AI
to enhance patient data management.
boosting forecasting accuracy by 64%.
This improvement led to optimized staff
scheduling across 23 facilities, reducing
wait time by 40 percent and saving 5.
8 million in operational cost.
These examples highlights how AI driven
data quality solutions are creating
tangible value, driving efficiencies
and delivering significant cost
savings across various industries.
AI leverages cutting edge machine
learning models to process and validate
data at a speed of up to 850 kbps.
This enables instant anomaly
detection and pattern recognition
across massive datasets.
ensuring high quality data
is maintained in real time.
AI algorithms uses sophisticated
neural networks and assembled
learning techniques to achieve 99
percent accuracy in data validation,
correction, and standardization.
This ensures that data, regardless
of type or format, is clean,
reliable, and ready to use.
By combining deep learning with
predictive analytics, AI transforms
raw data into real time data.
actionable business intelligence.
This results in 40 percent more accurate
sales forecast, 65 percent better customer
segmentation and doubling of market
campaign ROI, empowering business to make
more informed and effective decisions.
These advanced AI techniques make data
quality management faster, more accurate,
and more valuable, turning data into
strategic assets for organizations.
Now let's take a look at some key
implementation best practices for ensuring
the success of data quality initiatives.
Start with a pilot program in one
critical business unit, validate the
results, then systematically expand AI
implementation to other departments.
Based on the lessons
learned and measurable ROI.
This gradual approach helps ensure
smooth adoption and minimizes risk.
Conduct thorough data audits
to identify your most valuable
and vulnerable data asset.
Focus AI implementation on data
sets that directly impacts revenue,
compliance and customer experience.
Ensuring that the AI system is aligned
with your business top priorities.
Establish clear KPIs and automated
monitoring systems to track AI
performance, data quality metrics,
and overall business impact.
Regular reviews and proactive
adjustments are essential to
maintain, optimize results, and
adapt to changing business needs.
By following these best practices,
business can effectively migrate
AI driven data quality solutions.
and achieve long term success.
Organizations that implement AI driven
data quality solutions see a 67 percent
reduction in system integration issues,
leading to an average annual savings of 2.
3 million in troubleshooting
and maintenance costs.
Companies typically achieve full
return of investment within just 14
months, with an average ROI 3 years.
This is driven by increased
efficiency, reduced errors, and
improved decision making capabilities.
AI driven data quality solutions result
in 45 percent faster time to market.
32 percent increased in
customer satisfaction and
28 percent revenue growth.
These outcomes are directly tied
to enhanced data driven decision
making and operational excellence.
These statistics highlight how
AI driven data quality not only
saves costs, but also accelerates
business growth and performance.
Now let's take a look at AI
impact on business intelligence.
AI Power Data Quality is transforming
marketing effectiveness, boosting
campaign performance by 56%.
This leads to 3 times higher conversion
rates and an average 40 percent
increase in return on ad spend.
Making marketing efforts more
cost effective and impactful.
Advanced AI algorithm enhance
customer segmentation accuracy by 70%.
Enabling hyper personalized experiences.
This results in 45% increase in customer
lifetime value, and a reduced in
churn by one third, driving stronger
customer loyalty and retention.
A automates data validations
and standardizations reducing
compliance, supporting time
by six 6% while achieving 99%.
This saves thousands of staff
hours virtually automating
costly complaints or ions.
and ensures organizations stay ahead
of regulatory requirements with ease.
These AI driven improvements in
marketing, customer engagement,
and compliance, not only streamline
operations, but also provide significant
boost to business performance across
Let's now focus on the future
of AI driven data quality.
Predictive AI algorithms will
transform data analysis by uncovering
hidden patterns and correlations.
This will allow organizations to
forecast market trends with up to 95
percent accuracy and gain deep insights
into customer lifetime value, enabling
more informed business strategies.
AI powered automated complaints
monitoring will transform data governance.
by detecting regulatory
violations in real time.
This will reduce complaints risk by
80 percent while ensuring ethical data
handling across global operations,
safeguarding organizations from
legal and reputational issues.
Real time AI data validation will
speed up decision making cycles
by 60%, empowering leaders to
make strategic decisions based on
continuously verified and reliable data.
High quality data streams
from across the enterprise.
This shift will result in faster,
more accurate decision making at
all levels of the organization.
The future of AI in data quality
management promises more accurate
predictions, stronger governance, and
faster data driven decision making.
Positioning business for greater
success in an increasing complex
and competitive landscape.
To wrap up, here are the key
takeaways from today's discussion.
AI is transforming data quality
management by significantly improving
accuracy, speed, and efficiency.
Enabling business to unlock the
true potential of their data.
AI driven data quality delivers real
world benefits such as improved customer
satisfaction, reduced operational cost,
and enhanced decision making capabilities.
which drive overall business success.
To stay competitive, organizations
must embrace AI technology.
By harnessing its transformative power,
business can gain a significant edge
in today's data driven landscape.
AI is no longer just a tool.
It's a game changer for
business that wants to make
smarter, faster, more efficient.
and more informed decisions.
Next, start exploring AI powered
data quality solutions today.
Begin by assessing your current data
quality challenges and identifying
areas where AI can bring the most value.
Focus on high impact data sets that will
yield the most immediate improvements.
Implement a phased approach, gradually
expanding AI driven solutions.
As you validate results and measure ROI,
by embracing AI driven data quality,
your organization will not only improve
operational efficiency, but also
unlock the true potential of your data,
positioning yourself for a significant
competitive advantage in the marketplace.
Thank you all so much for
being part of this session.
I truly appreciate your
time and attention today.
It's been a pleasure sharing
insights into how AI driven solutions
are transforming data quality.