Hello everyone.
Thank you for taking the time
to join me for my talk on
transforming financial workflow.
Harnessing automation in
multi cloud ecosystem.
My name is Navin Kavya.
I've been working at Couchbase as
director of data engineering and
have been working in the field of
automations and cloud technologies
for many years, helping organization
transform their financial processes.
All right, let me get started
with a quick question.
How many of you have faced tax
errors and missed deadlines or
after due manner reconciliations.
But you're not alone here.
But these challenges are too common.
But today, we will explore how
automations and multi cloud ecosystem
can help your financial workflows.
In this session, we are going to
talk about how we can leverage
cloud technologies, automations,
and integration to streamline
everything from reconciliations.
And we will also discuss how we can
integrate systems like Salesforce,
NetSuite and Avalaro to reduce tax errors
and also cut manual work, also making
your financial team much more efficient.
By the end, you will also see how
APL and microservices can become the
backbone of your financial operations.
All right, so let's learn about
the problems and legacy financial
systems in the next slide.
So let's begin by discussing the
current state of many financial systems.
So today, a lot of organizations
still rely on legacy infrastructure.
So this types of designs were built
years ago and you can also imagine
they were in build for this type of
automations and seamless integrations.
that we need today.
So let's take tax
reconciliations for an example.
A lot of companies still handle
tax data manually, entering it from
different sources, bringing it from ERP
systems, or it could be from software,
accounting software, or tax services.
So this process is 100 percent error
prone, and it's also time consuming.
And always, finance team
spends hours or even days.
verifying to make sure that
everything is compliant and correct.
this efficiency adds up quickly
when your systems aren't integrated.
And it creates bottleneck and also
increases the risk of mistakes.
So the good news is where, this is where
the automation can make a huge difference.
Let's take a look at the automations,
how it could solve real-time problems.
So now we have also
established the problems.
Let's talk about this solutioning part.
So automation can actually reduce.
A lot of manual work for your team has
to do by integrating your financial
systems and automating workflows.
You can actually eliminate
errors and improve efficiencies.
For example, let's say you need to
make tax data across different systems
with the right tool and automation.
In addition, the tax data can
be synced automatically across
platforms like Salesforce,
Avalara, NetSuite in real time.
So this actually ensures that
your data is always up to date,
accurate, and ready to use.
Also drastically reducing
the chance for tax errors.
So why automation isn't just an
automation, but it also improves accuracy.
So it cuts down on time consuming tasks.
Imagine eliminating the need
to manually check things and
reconcile data across systems.
With the right tool in place, your
finance team can actually focus on higher
level strategic activities instead.
So let's see some benefits of multi
cloud ecosystem and how API led
microservices could help, right?
So to really unlock the potentials
of automations, you actually
need the right architecture.
This is where multi cloud ecosystems
and API led microservices.
Come into play.
multi cloud ecosystems means you're
actually leveraging the strength of
different clouds providers, for example
Amazon, Azure or GCP depending on what
fits best for your needs whether it
is scalability security or performance
the multi cloud environments allow
you to customize the infrastructure
that best supports your operations.
So now, how do we connect all
these tools and platforms, right?
So the answer is using
the API led microservices.
so technically the microservices allows
you to break down your processes into
a smaller independent services, each
doing one specific task and utilizing
API are the glue that binds all the
services together, enabling seamless
data flow between platforms like
Salesforce, Avalara, Salesforce, Avalara,
Salesforce, Avalara, Salesforce, Avalara.
So this architecture isn't just
flexible, it's scalable and
designed to grow with your business.
So it also allows you the smoother
integrations and easier upgrades and
more reliable performance overall.
So let's talk about when
a sync fails, right?
So there are situations where a
sync fails between systems due
to various varieties of reasons.
It could be due to some data incorrect.
So how do we reconcile all of this to
ensure that systems stays consistent
across all the platforms, right?
So this is where actually
the data warehouse.
becomes a critical lifeline.
Imagine resolving over thousands of
invoices mismatched in just two hours
compared to usually takes 10 to 15 days.
So this kind of theoretical possibility
it's become reality achieved
by leveraging an ETL pipeline.
So what does this ETL pipeline does?
Technically.
So basically the ETL type
pipeline extracts the raw
data from various systems.
In this case, it extracts data
from Salesforce and NetSuites and
loads them into a central data lake
and it transforms it for analysis.
And we can use SQL and Python scripts
to compare data between systems,
flagging discrepancies for reviews.
And this scripts not only miss
identifies the mismatch, but also
load them into an automation tool like
iPaaS, ensuring that discrepancies
are resolved quickly and efficiency.
So this reduces a lot of
manual toil checking systems
to ensure the data are in sync.
By doing so, this consistency
is across all the platforms
and ensures data integrity.
So this approach.
This is not just saving time, but also
making, enhancing the accuracy and
reliability of your financial data.
Let's talk about how 98 percent
of tax accuracy can be achieved
utilizing APIs and iPaaS.
today, so one of the key challenges
companies face in tax management
is the risk of human errors, right?
When they're trying to reconcile,
text data across various platforms.
For example, like Salesforce,
Avalara or NetSuite.
So let's take a imagine a situation
where you are actually dealing with
a large volume of transactions.
across multiple systems, right?
For tax rates, product categories, and
tax exemptions might be actually stored
in a different systems and manually
updating each one can actually lead
to discrepancies and costly errors.
So these errors not only impact
the accuracy of your tax reporting,
but also can lead to penalties or
technically audit down the lane.
So this is where Utilizing the
API and integration platform as
a service come into the play.
By utilizing the iPaaS solution,
the companies can ensure that tax
data is automatically synced in real
time across all relevant platforms.
So this API actually facilitates a
seamless communications between systems,
ensuring that updates made in one systems
syncs over to another system such as
from NetSuite or Salesforce and reflected
instantly in Avalara for tax calculations.
So this results in 98 percent
improvement in tax accuracy
as automated reconciliation.
Reduces the risk of manual errors with
the integrations of this platform.
The tax rates and financial data
are always up to date and compliance
is maintained without the need
for the constant manual check.
What makes this possible is the
power of API led integrations.
So instead of trying to manualising
data between systems, API actually
enables systems to talk to each other,
ensuring that all your tax related data
is consistent, accurate, and up to date.
For example, let's take invoices
that is processed in Salesforce.
It's triggered an API to NetSuite
to update the financials.
And another call to Avalara
to calculate the right tax.
This way, the tax errors are minimized
and your team is no longer to waste time
manually checking for discrepancies.
So in this slide, why multi cloud
and iPaaS is unstoppable, right?
So when you're combining multi cloud
with iPaaS, it delivers the best of
breed setup, enabling you to leverage
specialized cloud provider for optimal
performance and cost efficiencies.
So rather than relying on a single
provider, you can actually select
the best tool for each function.
So whether it could be cloud storage
or a data processing or a security,
ensuring that every part of your
business operates at a peak performance.
Additionally, API led redundancy
is a key benefit of this approach.
By spreading workloads across
multiple clouds, you can actually
ensure business continuity even
in the events of an outage.
So failover workflows seamlessly
switch to an alternative cloud
provider if one experienced issues,
reducing downtime and preventing
disruption to your final operations.
So with multi cloud and iPaaS, your
workflows remains uninterrupted
and you can quickly adapt to
changing business need, making your
financial system truly unstoppable.
And this is your enterprise
architecture blueprint, where the
APIs and the microservices bridge
between systems and multi cloud
eliminates the single point of failure.
And it is just not an integration, it
is actually turning chaos into clarity
with the future proof foundations.
In this diagram, on the left side, it's
the product led growth, where the end user
log into the e commerce and they, Purchase
an order that syncs over to iPaaS.
iPaaS routes it to Salesforce.
An invoice is generated and with
the tax calculation from Havalero
and gets pushed out to iPaaS.
iPaaS takes the request and
sends it over to NetSuite.
and on the top most, you see there
are ETL tool that is constantly
extracting data from different systems.
and loading into jRiveros for analysis
purpose and also for reconciliations.
So in this slide, let's talk about some
tangible key metrics and how impact
of integrating automations and cloud
technologies into financial workflows.
Firstly, we achieved 50 percent
of reduction in manual effort.
This frees up your time
for more strategic work.
And the next, we actually
achieved 98 percent tax accuracy.
This reduces the risk of complaints
issue and the next 30 percent
faster revenue recognition
improves cash flow and agility.
And lastly, there's cost
saving from reducing errors
and resolving disputes faster.
Which of this matrix would you have
most impact on your organizations?
And here is your 90 days
path for automations.
And this roadmap allows you to
automate your financial workflows
from phase one, 30 days, you audit
and deliver an integrations blueprint.
In phase 2, 60 days, you actually
test the real time tax sync
and achieve data accuracy.
In the phase 3, all 90 days,
you ensure resilience using
multi cloud and ensures 99.
99 percent uptime.
So let me ask you this, how many of
you are planning to start an automation
project in the next three to six months?
So to wrap up, I hope you now see how
automations and multi cloud ecosystems
can revolutionize financial workflow
from reducing tax error to cutting
down on manual reconciliation work.
Automation can unlock
significant efficiencies.
So by leveraging API led microservices,
you can actually create an agile
scalable financial infrastructure.
That not only improves day
to day operation but also
supports long term growth.
So this strategic shift that empowers your
finance team to focus on high value work
and drive the success of your business.
So thank you for your time today
and I hope this session has given
you valuable insights on how to
modernize your financial operations.
Thank you.