Hello, welcome to today's
presentation on the QA ownership
mindset driving startup success.
In this session, we will explore
how adopting the, how adopting a
QA ownership mindset can accelerate
product success, foster better
collaboration, and ultimately
drive quality outcomes in startups.
Let's dive into the key concepts that
will help startups thrive through
integrated, integrated quality process.
Why is quality important for startups?
Startup success depends on building
reliable products that users can trust.
Quality ensures longevity, customer
retention, and reduced maintenance costs.
How a strong QA ownership mindset
accelerates product success.
QA must be integrated into every
stage of product development,
not just as a final check.
For today's case, Sims will focus
on collaboration automation and
continuous improvement principles
that will help, you to scale quality
through your start your startup.
Okay.
Next, why QA matters in startups draw
a lot of myths about QA in startups.
Common startup, miss,
is testing slow us down.
QA is only for finding bugs at the end.
this means it can be dangerous because
poor quality costs startups delay.
bugs in production, the bugs in
production, which are damage reputation.
And, high churn rate can result
from bad user experience.
That's why shifting QA left
is very important, is crucial.
QA should be integrated into
development from the start.
When QA is a part of the development
from the start, issues are caught sooner,
saving the time and money on the long run.
what is the QA ownership mindset?
QA is a shared responsibility,
not just a role.
How it differs from
traditional QA approach?
Traditional QA works as a separate
function, owner, but ownership
integrates QA into every role.
Impact of ownership on team
efficiency and product reliability.
It increases communication and
collaboration, leading to faster
and more reliable development.
Everyone in this team has a role
in ensuring quality, not just
those with QA in their job title.
For example, if we have some deadline,
even developers can take part in
testing in the full regression.
If you have test cases, they can help
you with, This is not for everyday
use, but sometimes it's a good idea.
Okay, moving.
The three pillars of QA ownership.
To make QA ownership a success,
we focus on three key pillars.
It's collaboration ensures all
teams are accountable for quality.
It is automation, which reduces manual
testing and increasing efficiency.
Thank you for listening.
It's continuous improvement.
It's learning from failures
to refined processes.
These pillars work together
to create a robust, efficient,
and quality focused team,
building a QA deriving
culture in startups.
we can do it by integrating QA into
every stage of the development lifecycle.
We need to encourage all team
members, developers, product managers,
and other roles to own quality.
Thank you.
Everyone should be aware and remember
about quality and user experience.
Creating a quality first mindset without
slowing down innovation is possible.
Quality doesn't need to slow
down the development process
if integrated properly.
15 left.
Testing early and often.
QA is not just about testing, it
plays a crucial role in validating
requirements before development begins.
If requirements are unclear or incorrect,
developers may build the wrong features,
leading to waste of time and resources.
QA acts as a second line of defense,
ensuring that what's being developed
aligns with business goals and user needs.
This proactive approach prevents
costly mistakes before they happen.
Making QA a strategic function
in product development.
Next.
QA as a business analyst, why it's matter.
Poorly defined requirements can
lead to major issues in development.
QA should catch these
pitfalls earlier as possible.
we need to check the requirements for
the ambiguous language, words like
fast or secure need clear definition.
We need to check for
conflicting requirements.
Sometimes business expectations
don't match technical feasibility
and how our system is designed.
We need to check for missing edge
cases, because overlooking rare but
critical user scenarios can cause
unexpected failures, and we need to
check for incorrect business logic.
Assumptions that don't match
real world behavior can lead
to a poor user experience.
Next.
Common requirements, pitfalls,
which QA should catch.
In order to ensure high quality
product development, QA professionals
must go beyond basic testing.
and take a proactive approach
to requirement analysis.
Here are four key techniques QA can
use to straighten requirements analysis
and catch potential issues earlier.
We need to ask what if.
We need to challenge assumptions
and consider edge cases.
We need to map user journeys,
visualize user interactions
to identify inconsistencies.
We need to compare with
industry standards.
Benchmark against best practices.
Benchmark.
Collaborate with stakeholders.
We need to validate logic with
developers and product managers.
Techniques to analyze requirements
like a business analyst.
QA professionals can analyze requirements
more effectively using these techniques.
Ask proactive questions instead
of waiting for issues to arise.
We need to stay updated on industry
trends to anticipate potential risks.
We need to communicate effectively
between business, development, and users.
We need to take ethical responsibility.
QA is about preventing
failures, not just finding bugs.
By thinking like a business
analyst, QA can ensure clarity and
alignment before development starts.
Role of developers in QA ownership.
Quality is not just QA responsibility.
Developers must actively contribute to it.
Developers should write unit and
integration tests to catch issues earlier.
Pairing QA engineers with
developers fosters collaboration
and improves test coverage.
The best teams understand that
quality is a shared responsibility,
not a separate phase.
The role of automation in QA ownership.
Automated tests help teams iterate
quickly without sacrificing quality.
However, a balance must be maintained.
Not everything should be automated.
Continuous testing in CI CD pipelines.
Integrating QA into CI CD, continuous
integration, continuous deployment,
ensures faster feedback loops.
So for this, we can use API tests
using Postman, Selenium, automation
with Selenium, Cypress, Playwright,
handling bugs and failures with the
QA ownership mindset.
With the QA ownership mindset,
we focus on having strong bug
tracking and triage process.
to ensure issues are dealt with promptly.
Learning from post mortem allows teams
to improve their systems continuously and
build resilience against future failures.
Automation tests should run in every
stage of the development pipeline.
This helps teams detect issues
before deployment, preventing
last minute surprises.
and well implemented CI CD process
removes testing bottlenecks
and enables rapid releases.
Bugs are inevitable, but how
we handle them is what matters.
Measuring QA success.
To ensure QA efforts are effective,
we need to track key metrics
by asking, these questions.
Defect leakage rate.
How many defects escape to production?
Test coverage.
Are all crucial scenarios
being tested or not?
Deployment stability.
Are releases smooth or do
they introduce frequent bugs?
By using data deriving insights,
teams can continuously optimize
their quality assurance strategies.
Actionable
steps for startups to foster QA ownership.
Here are two practical steps
that startups can implement
immediately to foster QA ownership.
Encourage collaboration between
developers, QA engineers,
and product managers.
Also, we can create a sustainable
QA ownership model that works
in our fast moving environment.
These steps will help build the culture
of quality through your organization.
let's move to the conclusion
and final thoughts.
In conclusion, QA ownership is a team
effort that drives startup success.
By integrating QA into every
stage of development, you foster
collaboration, enhance efficiency,
and ensure a reliable product.
I encourage you to take action and embed
quality into your startup's culture.
Thank you.
Thank you for listening.
If you have any questions,
feel free to ask.