Hello, everyone.
Hi, I'm Rinku, a senior software
engineer with extensive experience in
authentication and identity management.
Over these years, I worked with
multiple organizations, helping them
implement single sign on solutions
using OO2, SAML, and other protocols.
Today, I'll walk you through designing
a seamless FSO system, the challenges we
often face, and how to balance security,
performance, and user experience.
Not too long ago, enterprise
authentication was simple.
Each app had its own logging, but as
the business has scaled, users were
drowning in passwords and IT teams
struggled with security gaps, complaints,
risk, and access control issues.
the SSO solves these challenges,
but, implementing it correctly is
very critical as a bad SSO system
can become a security nightmare.
Two dominant protocols for our SSO today
are, The first one is OAuth2, which is
a token based framework widely used in
cloud and microservices architectures.
And other one is the SAML, an older
XML based standard, which is used in
enterprises with legacy applications.
Oh, is primarily used for a
authorization and is common in
mobile apps and web applications.
you have probably used it when logging
into website like Google, Facebook,
Orth instead of creating a new account.
And here is how it works.
The user tries to log in to an
app, known as the client app.
The app then redirects the user to
an authorization server, such as
Google or Facebook, to authenticate.
The user enters their credentials,
and if successful, the authorization
server grants the authorization code.
And the app then exchanges
this code for an access token.
This access token is used to
request protected resources from
resource servers, such as APIs.
And if the token is valid, the
resource server grants the access.
So in OAuth 2.
0, the user never shares their
password with the application.
Instead, the access is granted
through a secure token.
This makes OAuth ideal for scenarios
like logging in with Google or
accessing third party APIs securely.
Now let's talk about SAML, which stands
for Security Assertion Markup Language.
Unlike OAuth, which is focused on API
access, SAML is mainly used for single
sign on in enterprise environments.
For example, imagine you work
for a company and need to log
into multiple applications like
AWS, Microsoft, or Salesforce.
AWS, Instead of entering your credentials
repeatedly, SAML allows you to log in
once and access all these services.
And here is how it works.
The user tries to access the
application known as a service provider.
Instead of asking for a password, the
service provider redirects the user to an
identity provider such as Okta or Azure.
The user enters their credentials
on the identity provider login page.
If it's successful, the IDP generates
the SAML assertion, which is an XML
based authentication token, and this
SAML assertion is sent back to the
service provider, which verifies it.
If everything checks out,
the user is logged in without
entering their password again.
in SAML SSO, the authentication
happens at the identity provider,
and the service provider trusts
the SAML token to grant access.
This method is widely used in
corporate environments where the
employees need secure and seamless
access to multiple applications.
A seamless SSO solution is
not about logging in once.
It needs to be secure,
fast, and easy to use.
So if any of these areas are
neglected, the adoption rates drop
and the security risk increases.
The security is the backbone of
any SSO system, so we must protect
the identity providers and enforce
multi factor authentication where
necessary, and ensure the tokens
are properly encrypted and expired.
After a reasonable duration, the
token leaks or, repay attacks can
compromise the entire system if not
managed properly, the performance
is often overlooked in security
discussion, but it is just as critical.
A slow authentication process
frustrate the users and increases
abandonment rates by, caching tokens
and optimizing authentication for
so we can reduce the logging delays
and keep the experience smooth.
The user experience is what
makes or breaks SSO adoption.
So if users encounter frequent
login prompts, inconsistent UI,
or compatibility issues, they will
either bypass SSO or complain to IT.
A great SSO experience
should feel invisible.
The user must be able to log in once
and gain access to all necessary
systems without any interruptions.
While SSO enhances security by
reducing password fatigue and
improving access management, it also
introduces new security challenges.
Let's explore the key risk organizations
must address when implementing SSO.
If the identity provider is compromised,
every connected application is at risk.
Since SSO centralizes authentication,
An attacker who control, who gains
control of the IDP essentially gets
unrestricted access to all linked devices.
This is why securing the IDP with
strong access controls, MFA and
continuous monitoring is critical.
SSO relies on tokens instead of passwords.
While this improves the security,
it also makes tokens a high
value target for the attackers.
If an access token is stolen,
it can be used to gain access
to sensitive resources.
Even worse, replay attacks allows
attackers to reuse the valid
tokens to hijack user sessions.
Another major risk is man in the middle
attacks, where an attacker intercepts
token exchanges during authentication.
If connections between the user, identity
provider, and service provider are
not properly secured, an adversary can
steal or modify the authentication data.
Now let's talk about best practices
for securing your SSO system.
While SSO improves convenience, it also
becomes a prime target for attackers.
To counter these threats,
organizations must follow
strict security best practices.
First, we always use
short lived access tokens.
Tokens that last too long increases
the risk of being stolen and misused.
Instead We should use, we should,
issue tokens with a short expiration
time and use refresh tokens
to extend access when needed.
This way, even if an attacker
gains access to a token, it becomes
useless after a short period.
Next is a multi factor authentication,
which is a user's credentials are stolen,
MFA ensures that a second verification
step, such as a push notification, a
one time password, or a biometric check
is required before access is granted.
This dramatically reduces the
risk of unauthorized access, even
if a password is compromised.
Another security measure is token scoping.
Not all tokens should have
full access to all resources.
Instead, we should limit the permissions
of each token based on what the
user or application actually needs.
For example, a token issued to
read user data should not be able
to modify the system settings.
This principle, known as the principle
of least privilege, minimizes
the damage in case of a breach.
Finally, the security doesn't
stop at authentication.
Organizations must log
and monitor authentication
attempts for unusual behavior.
If we notice repeated, failed login
attempts, access from unusual locations,
or, tokens being used, abnormally,
we can take proactive measures such
as blocking suspicious sessions or
requiring additional verification.
By implementing these best practices,
we can significantly strengthen
the security of SSO systems while
maintaining a smooth user experience.
A poorly optimized SSO system
can cause slow login times and
unnecessary delays in applications.
Users expect a seamless experience and
any lag in the authentication can lead
to frustration and decreased adoption.
So let's discuss the three key strategies
to optimize performance in an SSO system.
First, we can improve the speed
by caching authentication tokens.
So instead of focusing, focusing users to
re authenticate every time they access a
system, we store valid tokens temporarily.
so this reduces the load on
backend identity providers and
allows for faster authentication.
Next, to handle high traffic and
prevent failures, we use load
balancing for identity providers.
This ensures that authentication
requests are distributed effectively,
preventing bottlenecks and
improving system reliability.
If one of the server experiences high
demand, another can take over seamlessly.
Finally, asynchronous token validation
is a powerful way to enhance performance.
Instead of making every authentication
request block the application, we
validate tokens asynchronously.
This significantly speeds up API
responses, ensuring that users can access
their applications without any delay.
By implementing these optimizations,
we can create a faster, more scalable,
and user friendly SSO experience.
A seamless SSO experience also means
reducing unnecessary logging prompts.
The user should authenticate once
per session without repeated logins.
The branded login pages can enhance
the trust and consistency by
matching your application's design.
Making the users feel they
are in the right place.
Finally, the session persistence
ensures users stay logged in across
services, avoiding disruptions
and improving workflow efficiency.
By focusing on these UX elements, we
create a frictionless authentication
experience that boosts the
user's satisfaction and adoption.
Many enterprises still rely on legacy
applications that don't support modern
authentication standards like OAuth 2.
0 or SAML.
So to bridge this gap, we use
SSO gateways, which act as a
translator, converting the OAuth 2.
0 or SAML request into
authentication methods that
the legacy system understands.
A complete migration can be disruptive.
So instead of a big bang approach, we
should gradually phase in SSO while
maintaining existing authentication.
Finally, before a full rollout,
it's crucial to test backward
compatibility to prevent system
failures and ensure a smooth transition.
SSO is constantly evolving and the future
of authentication is shifting towards
stronger security and user control.
And one of the major trends is the
zero trust model, where no user or
device is implicitly trusted and
the authentication is continuous
rather than a one time check.
Next, AI driven security is
enhancing authentication by detecting
anomalies in real time, identifying
suspicious logging patterns, and
preventing fraud before it happens.
Finally, decentralized identity using
blockchain technology is emerging.
This allows the users to control their
own credentials without relying on
central authority, improving privacy,
and reducing identity theft risk.
These advancements will shape the
next generation of SSO, making it more
secure, intelligent, and user centric.
Here are the key takeaways.
SSO is more than just reducing logs.
It's about enhancing security,
scalability, and user experience first,
choosing the right authentication,
protocol exclusion, all 2.0 for.
Finally, balance the security
performance and usability by
securing every authentication flow.
A well designed SSO system
strengthens security while providing
a seamless user experience.
Thank you so much for listening.
And if you found this valuable,
let's connect on LinkedIn or
follow me for more insights.
And I would love to hear your thoughts.