Thank you for attending this session
and, let me first give you a quick
introduction about myself and what I do.
so I work at a tech company in
Seattle, and I have more than
eight years of experience in, data
engineering, analytics, machine
learning, and cybersecurity.
I graduated from Northeastern University
in, and I have been working in this
field and I, apart from work, I like to
travel, I like to also try to learn new AI
models and try to fine tune those models.
So today we are going to cover
presentation on AI frontiers, deep
learnings, transformative impact.
We have seen a lot of deep learnings
advancements in reshaping industries
using reinforcement learning, generative
models, and these are being used in almost
all the sectors, including cybersecurity.
So let's dive deep into it.
so this slide provides you
about reinforcement learning.
So what do you mean by
reinforcement learning?
So reinforcement is something
you try to reinforce something
and try to make it more powerful.
So that's exactly the concept
of reinforcement learning.
So it is like a reward based
learning and it helps the AI based
system to overcome the errors by
using trial and error technique.
And most of the algorithms in this
space use pattern recognition and
using deep learning and strategic
decision making and neural networks
and all these kinds of models.
So they are based on reinforcement
layer based learning, where you
provide the rewards and then
using trial and error method.
It tries to generate a pattern and
improves the model as compared to the
supervised and unsupervised models.
And reinforcement learning is very
powerful and every year we are
seeing a lot of new advancements
using reinforcement learning.
Next slide over here is very important.
It goes through the
transformer based model.
So transformer based model, why it is
so powerful and why it is being used.
So let's dive deep into
a transformer model.
So transformer model is basically
a neural which kind of learns the
context, by tracking the relationships
in sequential data and words.
And it helps to overcome a lot of
challenges and solves a lot of problems.
Problems, and it is a
very fast working model.
It can be used in time series analytics.
It can be used in recognition.
It can also be used in kind of image
and image detection, as well as words,
predicting the words and translating a
sentence and a lot of other use cases.
There are, so in this slide,
let's go deep and understand the
architecture of a transformer.
transformer is basically
encoder and decoder algorithm.
And, how it works is, it has, it
has, these kind of attention function
where first it encodes the word.
Like for example, we look into a
particular example where we have to.
Translate a sentence
into another language.
So in this case, what will happen is we'll
provide the inputs in input embedding.
And from here in the encoder, it will
go into the multi head attention.
So attention function, it is a very
important function over here, and it
tries to take all the components, let's
say in the sentence we have eight to
10 words, so it will create these kind
of eight to 10 vectors and these kind
of vectors they are quite, it will
optimize and make these vector and then
it will go into this decoder function
where it has feed forward multi head
attention, and it also has masks, multi
head attention, and it will then try to
translate the word and then find out in
this use case, it will try to find out in
the language which we want to translate.
So it will try to generate the
words in that particular language.
And then finally it'll, try to optimize
and, generate the output words.
So this kind of, algorithm, why
it is being used and very popular.
because this transformer based,
ai, model, this is very faster and
powerful and it works, parallelly.
So other models we have
seen, they do not work.
as parallel as this model and, transformer
based, machine learning models because
they work way in parallel, it can
utilize the GPU like Nvidia's GPU and all
kinds of GPUs in a very efficient way.
So the GPU is utilized in an efficient way
and it can work very faster and it has the
ability to scale up and work very fast.
and the data sets which are being used
are scalable and quite scalable and
you can get the output quite faster.
Then any other, AI algorithm, CNN, RNN,
or any other algorithm, which you can use.
So another use case over here
is it can predict the next word.
So based on the words you write, the
algorithm will be able to predict.
Or what would be the next word?
So it would be in the same situation.
It'll use the encoder and,
decoders attention function, and
it'll try to edit the next word.
Now we come to time GPT.
So what is time?
GPT?
So time, GPT is, GPT based model.
It's a transformer based
time series analysis model,
which was developed by nla.
So this.
Small startup.
It has created a very good AI
model and it can be implemented
by a very small piece of code.
So it's a production ready generative
pre trained transformer for time series.
So this model can be utilized to you.
create time series analysis
and all kinds of things.
So you can look into all the other
time series analysis and then try to
use this model and it will provide you
with more accuracy and more accurate
results and it is much faster scalable
and it can help you to optimize the
time series and it just uses these
kind of small lines of code where you
import the Nixla client, use the API
key over here, then you utilize in
the Nixla client, you try to use that
and you load the data from, Python.
Any large data from URL, or a
CSV, and then use that data frame
and use the next Nixla client to
forecast and then use the forecast
function to develop the time series.
So implementation is much
faster as compared to any
other time series analysis.
And it is very efficient to use in detail
finance, IOT based applications in tech.
or cyber security as well.
So now we come to another slide.
This slide provides us
with the information about
convolutional neural network.
What do you mean by
convolutional neural network?
So basically, this kind of neural
network very popular and it is
being this kind of neural network is
being used for image related tasks.
It can also be used for autonomous
driving where it can analyze and
detect various obstacles on the road.
It can find out if there are
any people around the road and
detect various things on the road.
So basically it is optimized for image
related tasks and it can also be used for
video games and such kind of applications
and this is, these are the key components
of convolutional neural network.
Is the convolutional network,
then the third one is the fully
connected, layer over here.
And, we have the activation function
where it improves and creates the output.
So first we come to the pooling layer
where it Reduces the dimensionality
of the feature by summarizing the
re regions and by using techniques
like max pooling, and this helps us
to retain the important information
and also reduce the complexity.
Then we have the.
Pooling, the fully connected layer,
the fully connected layer is where
the high level features within the
function are used for classification,
regression, and various other tasks.
So in the fully connected layer, we use
high level features and it can be used to
optimize and create more better outcomes.
Then we have the activation function.
There are a lot of activation functions
which are used to improvise and introduce
some non linearity into the network
and then it also improves the neuron's
capability and those kind of things.
So convolutional neural network
is also quite extensively
used, in, neural networks.
Many of the use cases like self
driving cars and image related tasks
and for photography image and such
kind of optimizations convolutional
neural network can be used.
We also have recurrent neural network
which is another kind of a neural
network as compared to convolutional
neural network which I don't know.
Is mostly used for applications related
to anomaly detection and more kinds of
patterns kind of detection, and mostly
it is being used in cyber security.
Okay, so now we come to this
slide over here, which provides us
information about GA and BAs, so
generative adversarial networks.
these are generative kind of,
Algorithms and VAs are variational
auto encoders and, they have different
use cases right now and they are
very popular in anomaly detection.
So VAs are very important
in anomaly detection.
It can, anomalies, within cyber security.
So the good use case of VA is are in
cyber security where it can, detect
various kinds of threats, improve
the accuracy of your model, existing
model, and, analyze the patterns.
in cybersecurity, but mostly you need
to first use your, current tools.
You have SIM tools and various other
tools in cybersecurity, and then
try to use VAs and you can also
use R Ns for finding the anomalies.
Then we have photo realistic
images, so advanced styles for image
generations and all kinds of things
is AI algorithms can be used for
photo generating photorealistic image.
Now we come to the next slide.
So this slide provides information
about the AI powered thread detection.
and using graph neural networks.
So why do we need AI
based threat detection?
Because currently the threat detection
capabilities using cyber security tools
are a little bit limited and as more and
more threat actors are evolving, there
is a constant scenario where they can
use AI based tools to plan an attack,
DDoS attack and such kind of things.
In this scenario, if we use AI based
threat detection, it can help us to
mitigate such kind of threats and
provide us more patterns and with
results with improved accuracy and
also reduce the false positives.
But in this case, we
have to train the model.
In cybersecurity and compare the
results with the existing tools we
have Splunk or Exabeam and such kind of
tools and try to find the threats and
compare the threats with the AI based
algorithm and then try to find out which
would be the best algorithm to use.
Then we have graph neural networks,
which are, shaping and, detecting more
of security based monitoring, finding out
the patterns and improving the detection
capabilities and conventional methods.
So some of the important tools maybe
in next 5 to 10 years, we might see
a lot of, use cases of these tools
and these tools being applied in
security automation and improving
the threat detection capabilities.
So now the next slide provider
provides us with the AI
convergence and future direction.
So we have what were here, multi modal
AI, which is now seamlessly integrated
with multiple forms of input, vision,
speech, sensor data, creating more,
Intuitive and comprehensive solutions,
which are similar to human understanding.
Then we have Age AI, which is more
of algorithms working directly on
local devices rather than the cloud.
And Age AI, because it is working
on local devices, it is very fast.
And provides us with the good amount of,
privacy and more kind of faster response
and revolutionizing applications from
autonomous vehicles to healthcare devices.
But the, but now when we apply such kinds
of things in our, use cases, we need to
understand the ethical, considerations.
You have to work with the compliance
team within the company to make sure
that the AI models are working well.
They are not taking any customer data or
changing anything within your environment.
So be careful when using such kind of
AI models in cyber security or such
kind of other use cases you have and
try to make sure that these kind of AI
models are not having any impacts about.
Privacy or, any changing any
data governance framework.
So before deploying, so please try to
make sure the deployment of AI algorithms
are done in a more ethical consideration.
And now we come to AI's
transformative impact on industries.
AI will have a lot of transformative
impact on the industries.
It will be having autonomous systems and
of self driving vehicles with 99 percent
or maybe 95 or more percent accuracy.
Then it will be used in
drug discovery and it.
will try to create, drugs at a
more cheaper price as compared
to currently what we have.
And it will improve the pace in which
the drug discovery is being made.
So there will be cost benefit.
There will be a lot of
mass production of drugs.
Then we have, Medicines like these
kind of AI tools will generate a lot
of data points for the patients, then
take the inputs from the patients, from
the doctors and plan the treatment.
So AI based tools will provide
a lot of personalized medicines.
It will help the medical sector
a lot along with pharmacy
and autonomous systems.
So all kinds of these kinds of
algorithms like CNN, RNN, transformer
based models, they will help to
improve, various systems, along with
the drug discovery and medicines.
So next we come to, breakthroughs
and practical implications.
So deep learning algorithms, have.
evolved and they will try to evolve,
again and again, and they will
evolve further in next five years.
So right now we have
transformer based models.
Maybe in next few years, we might see
more faster, models than this, and,
it will help us to create more, Better
outcomes and take, data from various
diverse sources and try to create a
better kind of, outcomes with accuracy.
now we have, the AI advancements.
probably in financial intelligence,
then we have customer intelligence
and, various, various other places.
I can help us to reduce the down times and
response times, and, it can also provide
patterns, detecting patterns with accuracy
and enabling data driven strategies.
And, it will have also help us in
recommendation and such kind of things.
And we have to make sure that in all
of these things we do, we have to keep
in mind the ethics and governance.
We need to make sure that the governance,
data governance, and AI based ethical
considerations are looked into so
that they don't exploit anything or,
they change anything or put they can
take the customer data and utilize
it and, have, bigger kind of, issues.
working with compliance team,
data governance, and ethics.
ethical consideration also
needs to be looked into.
So when you look into, when you look
into such kind of things, AI models will
improve the accuracy and they will evolve.
And maybe by 2030, you might see better
outcomes using AI based algorithms,
using quantum AI and such kind of things.
that's it from my, side.
thank you for attending this session.
please do leave your feedback and also
try to connect with me on LinkedIn.
If you need to get more
information, I can help you out.