Hello, everyone.
This is Vivek Kumar, a senior
software engineer at FANG.
I am very excited to be here today
to talk about something that's
crucial for modern application
hosting, that is VPS and Docker.
We will dive into key differences, how
they impact deployment and scalability,
and also explore best practices.
Plus, I will also share a real world
success story about the Sue app and
how they optimize their infrastructure.
Let's get started.
First of all, let me give you a
snapshot of what we will cover today.
We will compare VPS hosting with Docker
container based approach and talk about
how Docker can improve deployment,
efficiency, team productivity, and
resource optimization, and don't worry,
I will keep it practical with insight
you can actually use sound good.
Here is our roadmap for today.
So first we will go through
the introduction to VPS and
Docker key differences and
deployment and team productivity.
Then we will also discuss about resource
efficiency and cost optimization.
We will also look for application
management and scalability, and we
will also walk through practical
example of su app migration.
Then.
We will also touch base on
Kubernet, the orchestration tool.
We will also talk about the best
practices for hosting application
and migrating to Docker.
Let's start by defining what
VPS and Docker actually are.
VPS hostings provide a dedicated virtual
environment on a shared physical server.
You can think of it like a renting
an apartment in a big building.
You have your own space, but
you are still sharing the
physical structure with others.
It's great for running applications
with stable infrastructure needs.
With VPS, you get a virtual
slash of a physical server.
You have dedicated resources
like CPU, RAM and storage.
It's flexible and gives you control,
but it can be resource intensive and
scaling is not always straightforward.
Now let's talk about Docker.
Imagine you or your belongings
neatly packed in a container that
you can move anywhere that's Docker.
Docker takes a different approach.
Instead of virtualizing hardware, it
allows you to package application and
their dependency into lightweight portable
container that can run consistently
across different environments.
This means you can run the same
application on your laptop, a test
server, or in production without
worrying about environment differences.
That's why it makes deployments
much more consistent and scalable.
Basically, containers share the host OS
kernel, which makes them lightweight.
Here is a quick comparison.
If you look at isolation, with VPH, each
server has its own full operating system,
providing complete isolation from others.
This means that if one server crashes or
is compromised, it won't affect the other.
On the other hand, Docker uses
process level isolation, where each
container shares the same kernel
as the host operating system.
While this provides some level
of isolation, it's not as robust
as having a full OS per server.
If you let's look at the resource usage,
when it comes to resource usage, VPS
requires a full operating system for
each instances, which can be heavy.
While Docker containers share the
host OS, making them lightweight.
Now talk about the portability.
Portability is a major
advantage of docker.
With docker you can create a
container on one machine and deploy
it to another without worrying
about compatibility issues.
This makes it easy to move
applications between environments,
such as from Dev to Prod.
VPS, on the other hand, requires
manual configuration and setup
for each server, which can be time
consuming and prone to errors.
Even for deployment and scaling
in Docker are automated, whereas
VPS often involves manual effort.
Now look at some differences
in terms of the boot time, auto
scaling, and cost optimization.
Imagine being able to deploy
your application under a second.
With containers, that's not
possible because it loads very fast.
By using lightweight Dix image,
you can get your application up
and running quickly without having
to wait for a full OS to boot.
This is especially important
for applications that require
fast deployment, such as real
time analytics or live updates.
One of the biggest challenges with
traditional VPS hosting is provisioning
the right amount of hardware.
Too little and your application may not
have enough resources to run smoothly.
Too much and you are wasting
money on unused resources.
With containers, you can
provision exactly what you need.
When you need it, this not only
saves you money, but also improve
efficiency and reduces waste.
Imagine being able to handle
millions of users with ease.
With containers, that's not possible.
By using this image, You can quickly
deploy new containers to meet changing
demands, ensuring that your application
remains responsive and performant.
This is especially important for
applications that experience sudden
spikes in traffic, such as gaming
sites, during live gaming sessions.
Let's move to the next slide.
Let's talk about deployment
and team productivity.
With VPS, setting up environments can
be time consuming and error prone tasks.
Developers have to spend time to manually
configure environments, leading to
inconsistency between dev and production.
But Docker simplifies this by
standardizing environments.
You get faster onboarding for new team
members and smoother CI CD integration.
This means your team can spend more
time coding and less time dealing
with dependent deployment headaches.
So basically it improves
also the team productivity.
Managing application with
VPS can be challenging.
You often need manual intervention
to scale and balance loads.
You might need to provision new
server Manually to cope with sudden
traffic spike Docker especially when
combined with orchestration tools
like kubernetes offers centralized
app management and easier scaling This
ensures better stability And performance
even under high traffic condition now
Now look at the next slide.
Let's take A look at this real world
example of how containerization
can improve efficiency.
We are going to explore the
case study of Su App migration.
The Su App was initially running
on 85 EC2 instances to support
various services such as search,
user management and authentication.
As you can see from the architecture
diagram on the left, each instance
was dedicated to a specific
service, which resulted in a lot
of wasted of CPU and RAM resources.
This is because each instance was
provisioned with a fixed amount of
resources, regardless of whether they
were being fully utilized or not.
This approach may have worked when
the app was smaller, but as it grew,
it became clear that this was not an
efficient way to manage resources.
The team was facing challenges
such as underutilized resources,
high costs, and difficulty scaling
to meet challenging demands.
So what they did?
They decided to migrate
to Docker and Kubernetes.
Let's take a look at new architecture
and see how it improves their efficiency.
After migrating to Docker and Kubernetes,
the Su F team was able to reduce the
number of EC2 instances from 85 to 67.
While maintaining the same
performance as you can see from
the updated diagram on the left The
new setup allows for more efficient
resource allocation and utilization
The result of this migration was a 20
percent reduction AWS cost That's a
significant improvement in efficiency.
By using Container and Kubernetes,
the team was able to optimize
resource allocation, reduce waste,
and improve the scalability.
This case study demonstrated the
power of containerization in improving
efficiency and reducing cost.
Now let's talk about what
makes all this possible.
That is Kubernetes.
As we discussed, containers are a
powerful way to deploy applications.
But as the number of containers
grows, managing them can
become increasingly complex.
That's where orchestration
tools like Kubernetes come in.
Kubernetes is an open source
container orchestration tool.
Restaurant platform that automate
that deployment, scaling and
management of containers.
With Kubernete, you can easily
manage hundreds or even thousands of
container across multiple host, but
what really set Kubernetes apart is
its ability to autoscale and self heal.
It's basically like a traffic
controller for your application,
ensuring everything runs smoothly.
So let's move to the next slide.
So what is more preferred, VPS or Docker?
The answer depends on several factors,
including project management approach,
microservice compatibility, web traffic
scale, budget, and deployment capability.
Both VPS and container orchestration
platforms support web and
mobile apps using microservices.
But containers offer better
service, isolation, and scalability.
When deciding between VPS and Docker,
team must consider infrastructure
cost, scaling expenses, and complexity
of managing the chosen solution.
If you have a simple application with
stable traffic, VPS might be enough.
But if you need dynamic scaling,
Or run a microservice architecture,
Docker is the way to go.
Think about your project
requirements, budget, and a long
term goal when making this decision.
Industry adoption varies widely.
VPS is preferred by web
publishers, e commerce websites,
and multi domain developers for
their web hosting requirements.
On the other hand, Docker is preferred
by corporate IP deployment in support
of web and mobile applications at a
scale in datacenter operations through
elastic cluster web server networks.
Now let's talk about some best practices.
For
VPS, using configuration management
tools like Ansible, Puppet and Monitor
resource uses to avoid overflow.
Provisioning for Docker use multi stage
build to reduce image size and regularly
update Docker image for security patches.
Don't forget to implement
orchestration tools like Kubernetes.
If you are thinking about migrating
to Docker, here are some useful tips.
Start by assessing and
reflecting your microservices.
To make sure you can build
docker or container out of this.
Develop a small prototype before going
all in to find out any issue early.
Use docker compose for testing
and multi container application.
Integrate with CICD pipeline and train
your team on Docker and Kubernetes
or whatever tools you are using.
Implement monitoring tools like
ELK, Prometheus, or you can use
any other tools as you prefer.
And finally, migrate gradually
using a hybrid approach.
To wrap up, Docker offers superior
efficiency, scalability, and automation
compared to traditional VPS solutions.
When paired with Kubernetes, managing
large scale containerized applications
becomes seamless and highly efficient.
So let's talk about the key takeaway
for today's Docker provides significant
advantage over VPS in terms of efficiency,
scalability, and team productivity.
By migrating to Docker organization
can achieve cost reduction while
simultaneously enhancing team
productivity, making it a powerful
choice for modern application
deployment and management.
We also look at.
The real world example today for the
sue app case study that proved that
magneting to Docker can lead to cost
saving and better resource utilization.
This demonstrates the real world benefit
of adopting Docker and Kubernetes for
containerized application management.
That's it for me.
Thank you so much for your attention.
I'm happy to answer any
question if you have.
Thank you.