Hello everyone and welcome to my session.
I'm Somnath Trewale and today we are
going to talk about maximizing business
continuity with Azure Site Recovery.
Little bit about me.
I spent two decades in IT and
I'm currently a Senior Technical
Support Escalation Engineer at
Microsoft, specializing in Azure
Backup and Recovery Services.
My job is helping organizations.
to build a stable business continuity
and disaster recovery solutions.
So let's get started.
Before we get into Azure Site Recovery,
let's take a moment and talk about
why business continuity is important.
When a disaster strikes, whether
it's a hardware failure, a cyber
attack, or even a natural disaster,
organizations need to be prepared.
A plan to minimize downtime and data
loss without a solid business continuity
strategy, recovering from disruption
can be slow, expensive, and chaotic.
That said, implementing
business continuity is not an
easy and has many challenges.
The organizations needs to consider
cost, complexity, and compliance.
What are the costs?
Running a secondary data center,
maintaining hardware, and managing
infrastructure expenses can be expensive.
And what is the complexity?
Restoring from tapes, Managing
multiple data centers and ensuring
software compatibility, can add
operational overhead and compliance.
Many organizations must meet regulatory
requirements, retain data for
specific periods, and ensure service
availability, all of which can be
challenging to manage effectively.
We just talked about the challenges
to implement the business continuity.
Now we'll take a look at how Microsoft
can help to overcome these challenges.
This is where Microsoft and more
specifically the Azure comes in.
Azure helps organizations to tackle
the challenges in several ways.
Reducing cost.
With Azure, you don't have to
pay for additional infrastructure
or for power, cooling, or IT
staff to manage a secondary site.
You can only pay what you use.
And with Simplified Disaster Recovery,
Azure Site Recovery automates failover
and recovery processes, so instead of
manual and a stressful recovery process,
you can restore workloads with just a
few clicks, ensuring the compliance.
Azure removes geographical
constraints, allowing businesses
to meet regulatory and compliance
requirements more easily by replicating
workloads across multiple regions.
And now, let's Scaling.
ASR supports replication across both
on premises and cloud environments,
whether you are running Hyper
V, VMware, or physical servers.
What is Azure Site Recovery?
It's a tool here to
safeguard your business.
You need a robust BCDR strategy,
one that only protects your data,
but also keeps your applications and
workload operational, whether the
disruption is planned or unexpected.
That's where Azure Site Recovery comes in.
ASR is a key part of Microsoft
Disaster Recovery offering.
Replicates the workloads from your
primary site to secondary location,
whether on premises or in Azure.
If a primary region goes down, workloads
can quickly fail over to the secondary
site, keeping your applications available.
Once your primary site is restored,
you can seamlessly fail workloads
back to resume normal operation.
ESR minimizes downtime and data
loss, making your business more
resilient to our disruptions.
We looked at Azure Site Recovery.
Now let's consider why
Azure Site Recovery.
With ASR, you get a single unified
solutions for disaster recovery.
Azure Site Recovery supports
heterogeneous environments like Hyper
V, VMware, or and even physical servers.
It also provides certified support for
enterprise applications like SharePoint,
SQL Server, Exchange, and Dynamics.
You can also do the disaster drills with
zero impact on a production environment.
It also provides industry leading
RTO and RPO, meaning your business
experiences minimal disruption
in the event of a failure.
Key concept in disaster recovery.
When we talk about disaster recovery,
two key metrics help to define
how prepared an organization is.
The first one is recovery point objective.
This tells us how much data loss is
acceptable in the event of failure.
Essentially, it's the maximum Age
of a data that can be restored.
A lower RPO means more frequent
backups or continuous replications
to minimize data loss.
Recovery time objective is the second one.
This measures how quickly
systems and services need to
be restored after a disruption.
It's a maximum Downtime a
business can tolerate before
operation must be back online.
One of the biggest advantage of Azure
Site Recovery is that significantly
reduces both RTO and RPO compared to
traditional disaster recovery solution.
With ASR, organization can
restore the business and critical
workloads in little as 15 minutes.
Minimizing operational impact and
allowing for a faster return to normal.
And also, ESR continuously replicates
data, ensuring that failover happens
quickly and with minimal data loss.
So I mentioned, the status report.
Now, some of you are maybe understanding
why I am having the status report.
Continuity even in the face
of unaffected disruption.
Why this matters?
By becoming a low recovery time
objective, near real time replication
and automated failover, Azure Site
Recovery ensures that businesses stay
up and running with minimal downtime,
without complexity and high cost of
maintaining a secondary data center.
With ASR, organizations can recover
faster, lose less data, and stay
compliant, all while leveraging the
power of the cloud for scalable,
cost effective disaster recovery.
Now, as we know, Azure Site
Recovery, supports Azure workloads,
Hyper V, VMware, and physical.
we are going to, deep dive into
the architecture of each one.
Let's get started with Azure
to Azure Site Recovery.
Recovery architecture.
Now let's talk about how ASR works
in Azure to Azure scenario and what
components are required to set it up
when running the workloads in Azure.
It's essential to have a disaster
recovery plan in place to protect
against unexpected outages, original
failures, or planned maintenance.
Azure Site Recovery enables.
Seamless replication of virtual machines
from one region to another, ensuring
business continuity with minimal downtime.
How it works?
ESR continuously replicates VMs from
primary region to a secondary region.
If there is an outage, your
workloads are already synchronized
and ready to run in another region.
In the event of failure, planned
maintenance, or a disaster,
you can failover to a secondary
region with minimal disruptions.
ESR automates this process, ensuring
quick and smooth transition.
Once a primary region is restored, you
can fail back to your original environment
seamlessly, ensuring normal business
operation with minimal data loss.
Now let's look at what all the
components are required to set
up the Azure to Azure scenario.
To set up Azure to Azure
disaster recovery, you need
the following key components.
The VMs running in primary region
that needs to be replicated to your
disaster recovery target region.
Now, we need the recovery vault.
The Recovery Vault, where Azure
Site Recovery stores metadata,
configuration details for a
replication, failover, and failback.
And now we need a replication policy.
This defines how often data is replicated
and retention of recovery points.
This helps.
Ensure that you meet your
recovery point objective.
That means RPO.
You need a target region, the secondary
region where your VMs will be replicated.
Microsoft provides paired regions
to ensure optimal disaster recovery.
And then you need network
configuration, especially VNet in
the target region to connect the
recovered VMs after a failover.
You need a subnet that mirrors
your primary region setup.
If you have a public IP, then you need to,
you need a connectivity after a failover.
So replication policy and recovery
plans replication settings to define
a frequency and consistency of the
replication and recovery plans.
to automate the sequence of failure
operations, including dependencies
between the applications.
Say, for example, if you have a, three
tiered application, like Tier 1, Tier
2, and Tier 3, whenever you are doing
The fellow from one region to another
region, you need to ensure that first
your active directory environment comes
in, then your database databases comes
online, and then your web application
comes online to, automate that process.
You can use the recovery.
Then you need a managed disk.
ASR supports managed disk, eliminating
the need to manage the storage accounts.
For enhanced performance, ASR replicates
data to a storage blob before writing into
the managed disk in the target region.
You also need Azure Automation
account, which is optional.
If needed, you can use the automation.
To run the runbooks to trigger custom
script during failover or Failback.
Since we already covered Azure to
Azure scenario, now let's shift our
focus to how Azure site recovery
helps to protect workloads running on
Hyper V by replicating them to Azure.
Many organizations.
still rely on premises infrastructure,
including Hyper V virtual machines.
While this setup provides a control
and flexibility, it also presents
challenges in terms of disaster recovery.
If an on premises data center
experience a failure, whether due to
hardware issues, natural disasters,
cyberattacks, organizations, need a
way to quickly recover their workloads
in the cloud to minimize downtime.
This is where ASR comes in.
How it works?
ASR continuously replicates
Hyper V virtual machines from on
premises environment to Azure.
This ensures that up to date
Copies of your workloads are
always available in the cloud.
If a disruption in a primary
environment allows ASR to failover
to Azure, instantly bringing your
critical application back online.
Once your environment is restored, You
can fail back workloads from Azure to
Hyper V infrastructure, returning to a
normal operation with minimal data loss.
What components are required to
successfully configure Hyper V to Azure?
You will need the following components.
The on premises Hyper V host.
The Hyper V service hosting
the virtual machines.
That need a protections.
ESR supports both standalone Hyper
V host, Hyper V clusters managed by
System Center Virtual Machine Manager.
We call it SCVMM.
Then we need a recovery vault as we
talked in Azure to Azure scenario.
Vault stores all the replication
and recovery settings.
These are the core component that manages
failover, failback, and recovery plan.
Thank you for listening.
Then we need ASR provider and agent.
If you are using SCVMM, you need
to install the ASR provider on
the VMM server, and if you are
using the standalone Hyper V host,
then install the ASR provider And
the agent on the Hyper V host.
The replication policy defines how
frequently data is replicated and how
many recovery points are retained.
This determines your RPO.
Then the, you need a RPO.
Azure target resources like managed
disks, VNet, and recovery plans if you
wanted to, automate some of these tasks.
We have already covered Azure
to Azure, Hyper V to Azure.
Now we are going to cover VMware
to Azure or Physical to Azure.
we have two versions of, VMware
one is classic and one is modernized.
classic is going to be deprecated
soon, so I'll not be talking that.
So now we are going to talk about
modernized approach to VMware or
a Physical to Azure site recovery.
Let's talk about how ASR helps to protect
VMware virtual machines and physical
servers by replicating them to Azure.
Many organizations still run critical
workloads on VMware environments
or on physical servers, whether
it is in their data center or
in a co location facilities.
While the setup offers control,
it also introduces challenges.
Scalability, cost, maintenance, and
most importantly, a disaster recovery.
Traditional recovery methods like
secondary data centers, tape backups,
manual failover processes are
often slow, expensive, and complex.
This is where Azure Site Recovery
modernizes the disaster recovery,
providing Cloud first automated
and cost effective solution.
How it works?
ASR continuously replicates VMware
virtual machines or a physical service to
Azure, ensuring near real time protection
without impacting the performance.
If an outage occurs, whether it's
a hardware failure, cyber attack
or natural disaster, you can fail
over workloads to Azure instantly.
Restoring services with
minimal disruption.
Once your on premises environment
is back online, you can fill back
workloads from Azure to Azure, sorry,
Azure to your VMware environment.
If it is physical to Azure,
Then you'll not be able to
fail back to physical servers.
In that case, you need to live in
Azure or you need to have an alternate
fail back with VMware option.
Now let's look at the key
components involved in VMware
to Azure or physical to Azure.
To set up VMware or physical to
Azure Site Recovery, you need
the following key components.
On premises VMware or physical servers.
These are the workloads
that need the protections.
Then we need, as usual, Azure That's
the heart of ASR, managing replication,
failover, failback, compliance settings.
All metadata will be stored
in Recovery Service Vault.
Then, in on premises, we need a
replication appliance, which can
be installed on Windows Server.
to handle data replication between
VMware or a physical servers to Azure.
And this appliance connects to a VMware
vCenter or a standalone ESX host to
replicate the VMs and manages replication
of a physical servers to Azure.
Then we need a mobility service or
mobility agent which will be directly
installed on a VMware machine or a
physical server To enable real time
replication to Azure in our target
Azure Resources, we need a vnet.
Once you fill out the vm, we
need a vnet to connect, and
then we need a managed disk.
ESR replicates workloads to these disks
for ENT storage and faster recovery.
Azure virtual machines.
Once fail happens, VMs are automatically
provisions based on the replicated data.
Then we need.
Replication policy and recovery plans,
which replication policy defines the
recovery point objective to ensure minimal
data loss and recovery plans, which helps
you to orchestrate the failure with the
recovery plans, brings services online.
in the right sequence.
Now we'll take a look at key
success factors pre implementation.
Successfully implementing Azure Site
Recovery requires careful planning,
training, and continuous testing.
A well prepared approach ensures
seamless disaster recovery and
minimizes operational disruptions.
Comprehensive planning.
Before deploying ASR, it's critical,
it's crucial to conduct thorough testing,
thorough assessment of your infrastructure
to ensure a smooth transition.
Key considerations includes infrastructure
readiness, analyze on premises and cloud
workloads to determine replication needs,
network capacity, Thank you for listening.
Evaluate bandwidth requirements
to prevent latency issues.
Compliance and security.
Map out industry regulations to
ensure your disaster recovery setup
meets the government's requirements.
Implementation and roadmap.
Define a structured A rollout plan
tailored to your organization need
through training ensure it teams
are equipped with right skills and
certifications in Azure disaster recovery
best practices and ESR management
cloud hands on training to familiarize.
Teams with failover and failback
procedures, troubleshooting,
and automation workflows.
Provide ongoing learning opportunities
such as Microsoft Learning Modules
and real world lab environments.
Regular testing.
Schedule monthly failover drills.
To validate workloads are resilient.
Conduct quarterly full scale
recovery simulations to assess
overall disaster recovery readiness.
Monitor system performance.
Continuously to maintain 99.
9 recovery reliability and proactively
resolve potentially potential issues.
Now let's look at a step by step guide
to implementing Azure Site Recovery.
In the assessment phase, if you are using
VMware to Azure or Hyper V to Azure,
Microsoft provides a deployment tool.
You can use it.
We call it a deployment planner.
You can run that tool for
a week on your environment.
To understand your workload dependencies,
network performance, business continuity
requirements, and, recovery time objective
and recovery point objective to align
with the business needs, identify
applications requiring high priority
protections, what planning you need to do.
Design the replication
architecture between on premises
or Azure to Azure environments.
Map application dependencies to
prevent failure during recovery.
Develop runbooks to automate
recovery sequences and
minimize manual intervention.
How you can do the deployment, set
up a recovery vault and configure
replication policies, enable source to
target VM replication with continuous
monitoring, and automate failover and
failback processes for seamless recovery.
Testing and optimization.
Conduct bi monthly failover drills
to measure recovery speed and
validate failover configurations.
Analyze performance metrics to
refine disaster recovery procedures.
Update recovery plans regularly based
on insights from real world testing.
Conclusion, strengthen the business
continuity with Azure Site Recovery.
At the end of the day, business
continuity is all about resilience.
Being able to recover quickly, minimize
disruptions, and keep operations
running smoothly no matter what happens.
Azure Site Recovery makes it possible by
providing fast, cost effective, and highly
reliable disaster recovery solution.
With recovery, Times up to 90 percent
faster and cost savings between 40 to 60%.
ESR eliminates the need
of expensive secondary
infrastructure while ensuring 99.
9 recovery success rates.
Beyond just efficiency and cost savings,
security and compliance are built in.
Giving organizations a peace of
mind, their critical workloads
are protected, whether they are
in the cloud or on premises.
Now is the time to modernize your
disaster recovery strategy by
leveraging ASRs automation, scalability
and enterprise grade capabilities.
You can future proof your business
and ensure seamless recovery.
And without any disruptions.
A big thank you.
I absolutely, I appreciate
your time today.
Thank you for joining me.
If you have any questions,
feel free to reach out to me.