Hi, everyone.
My name is Mohammad Ahmad Saeed, and
today I'm going to talk about chaos
engineering for resilient microservices.
First, let's look at a typical
microservices architecture.
as we can see in the diagram, we
have multiple microservices, and
each microservice has a dependency.
The two main dependencies for our
microservices are the databases,
and other microservices.
So for instance, in this diagram,
we have a microservice one, which
is dependent on the database one,
and it is also communicating with
microservice two via a queue.
But if we look at The communication
between microservice two and
microservice three, it is
happening, via a direct HTTP calls.
So the point to raise here is,
each microservice has dependency.
It can either be database or it
can be either, other microservices.
There are also other type of dependencies,
which will, we will look into it later.
Now let's look at what are our goals.
So we have three main goals here.
The first is to uncover
weaknesses in our system.
it can also include like identifying
single point of failures.
So what happens if one of the
microservice goes down or if the
dependency like a database, so if
the database, is overloaded, if the
database is responding slowly, so What
is the behavior of our microservices?
So that's the first goal.
We have to identify the
weaknesses in our system.
The next is to improve system robustness
and that actually means that we have
to make our system more robust and
strong and By increasing the stability
and keeping the performance within a
defined range So the performance of
every microservice is doesn't gets
worse and worse with time If anything
happens in the system the microservice
the performance of that microservice
It should stay within a defined range.
The third is to handle
unexpected failures gracefully.
So there can be a lot of
unexpected failures in the
microservices architecture.
the most typical ones are the
network issues, the dependency,
failures, the bad configurations,
the data consistency issues.
So there can be a lot of, failures,
a lot of different type of failures,
in the microservices architecture.
and In case of any failure, we should
ensure that the, that failure is
handled gracefully and one failure
doesn't take the whole service down.
Let's look at why is chaos engineering
critical for microservices.
So microservices are complex.
They have a distributed complexity.
Microservices, they have
like many moving parts.
which can be like APIs, which can be
databases, which can be messaging queues,
which can be a third party services.
So failure in one service can
ripple through the system.
That's one of the complexity that, that
is very necessary to actually, look into.
The next is the network dependencies.
So As we have seen in the previous
slide, microservices, they do
communicate over networks and networks
are prone to latency, a packet
loss, outages, there can be a lot of
stuff which go wrong in the network.
The third thing is the dynamic scaling.
So microservices, they often run in
the containerized environment like
Kubernetes, that dynamically scale.
And that actually makes it
harder to predict failure modes.
one example is, did this service
scale properly when there was
a lot of load on the system?
the next is the frequent deployments.
There is a continuous deployment
in microservices, like for
instance, microservice one is
getting deployed every day.
Microservice two is getting
deployed every week.
And actually that increases the
risk of reducing, sorry, the risk
of introducing, bugs or regressions.
with proper cross engineering,
we can make sure that.
If there is any failure in
the system, it doesn't take
the whole system down with it.
Let's look at what are the microservices.
So the very first is the service
failures and the service failures like
in, we have to basically simulate the
failure of individual microservice.
The most common one in every
system, at least what I have seen
is the authentication service.
So as soon as the authentication
service is down, it takes.
Most of the other services
down with it because they are
dependent on that service.
So here we have to test how the system
handles service availability or crashes.
So if one service is crashing, then is
the other service crashing or is the
other service like giving outage or not?
Then the network issues.
So in, in network issues, we can
introduce, latency, packet loss,
network partitions, and then we have
to test how the system behaves under
slow or unreliable network conditions.
The third is the dependency failures,
independencies failures, we can, like
similar dependence, dependency failure,
like databases, the message queues, the
message brokers, or the third party APIs.
And again, the goal is to make
sure that any dependency failure,
it is handled gracefully.
The next is the load and scalability.
So.
if one of the service is getting excessive
traffic, then, does it auto scale
and handle the load properly or not?
And what is the behavior of other services
which are depending on the service?
the next is the data consistency.
So if, in case of any like data corruption
or delays in the data replication, then
we have to verify like how the system
maintain consistency during failures.
The next is the configuration changes.
we are here, we are testing how the
system reacts to misconfiguration
or sudden changes in configurations.
Does it propagate and take everything down
with it or does it, handle it gracefully?
The next is the cascading failures.
So we have to simulate the scenarios,
where like one failure, it triggers a
chain reaction across multiple services.
Now let's look at what are the
principles of chaos engineering.
in Chaos Engineering, the very first
thing is to define a steady state.
which actually means that we have
to identify the normal behavior
of the system using metrics.
And those metrics can be like,
latency, error rate, throughput.
In normal circumstances where we are
with those metrics, of course, we cannot
be at zero like errors cannot be zero.
There will be some errors for sure.
so we have to first identify the
baselines where we are, where
the system is currently at.
And then the next step is to, then we
have to hypothesize about failures.
So it's more about like hypothesis.
So what do we think that, that
should happen when a failure occurs?
We can predict how our system will
behave And the third step is to actually
Introduce the controlled kiosk which
means we are going to simulate failures
like failures can be like network
delays server crashes then we have
to simulate this but they should all
be in a controlled manner The fourth
thing is to observe and measure.
After we have introduced the kiosk, now
we are checking the response of the system
and the most important thing is to ensure
that it can self recover because we are
doing all of this exercise on production.
The next thing is the automate
and integrate into CICD.
this is a very important step.
Once we have some experiments, chaos
experiments, we have to make sure
that we are doing them continuously.
They are happen, happening frequently.
And, that's the only way that we can
ensure that our service, microservices
are resilient because we are testing
them continuously in our pipelines.
Let's look at the popular
chaos engineering tools.
the very first and the very the
most famous is the chaos monkey.
So chaos monkey is It was developed
by Netflix and what this tool
does is it basically, randomly
terminate instances in production.
to be like, just to make sure that if,
for example, one service is terminated,
one service is killed, then what happens
to the other, other dependencies,
how the system behaves overall.
The next is the Kiosk Mesh, Kiosk
Mesh is the open source platform.
It was built by, it was built for
Kubernetes, but it is like really
powerful and flexible and it
supports diverse, fault injection.
And it also has a web UI
for managing experiments.
So we can manage and run and monitor
different experiments through a really UI.
The next is the Gremlin.
So Gremlin is, it's not an open source,
it's a commercial platform, opening
a wide range, of attacks that can
run against various infrastructure
components, including, Kubernetes,
cloud providers, and in, it also has
a very, user friendly, interface,
and it also has like very extensive
attack library, robust capabilities
and integration with monitoring tools.
it's again like very powerful tool
and it's, used, across the industry.
The next is the Toxy proxy.
So Toxy proxy is, mostly limited
to the network conditions.
it's an open source TCP, proxy to
simulate The network and system
conditions for chaos and resiliency
testing, it, it allows for fine grain
control over the network, impairments
and, network impairments and can
be used like with various tools.
So all of these, four tools,
these are like really powerful
and these are quite famous.
Let's look at the real world case
studies of chaos engineering and the
first example here would be slack as you
all know that slack is a very popular
messaging platform and it is used by
millions of users across the world.
So slack.
is basically conducting regular chaos
experiments to test the resilience of
their services and infrastructure overall.
And they also have like incident response
drills where Slack is using chaos
engineering to simulate incidents and then
checking the responses to those incidents.
By using this chaos engineering
to maintain their, and maintain
and test their infrastructure.
So slack was able to minimize, downtime
and, it made, they maintained a ready
to rival platform for each user.
I think their current reliability is
like 99 something, 99 point something.
Let's look at another real world
case study of Kiosk Engineering and
we can look at Azure Kiosk Studio.
So Azure Kiosk Studio is built by
Microsoft and it is a managed service.
It basically, it uses Kiosk Engineering
to help measure, understand,
and improve service resilience.
Here we can set up some experiments,
we can configure which faults to run,
and we can also select resources,
resources to run our faults against.
And it is used by, a lot of companies
to run experiments and improve
the resilience of their services.
Let's look at the benefits of adopting
kiosk engineering for microservices.
So the very first for any
business is the financial benefit.
in case of a down time, the businesses
suffer, the, if the platform is down,
let's consider an example of bank.
So if the banking system is down, it
will disrupt the whole, the, all the
customers of that bank and it can
result in a significant financial loss.
So here.
Using kiosk engineering to ensure the
stability and resiliency of our services,
we can, stop the, financial loss.
and the main thing is because
we are preventing outages.
The next is the technical benefits.
So technical benefits, means for
example, we have, reduced incidents.
We have less firefighting.
We have better on call experience.
and then, yeah, we have less
technical issues in our system.
And the third is the customer benefit.
So yeah, it's, pretty, obvious that if the
system is down, the customers will affect.
And, If the customers, they are not
satisfied with the platform, they
will just jump into another platform.
So here we are providing, a
better experience, the app uptime,
the, all of those, the system is
stable, the system is reliable.
So if there is no downtime,
customer will be satisfied and
their experience will be improved.
Let's look at the best practices for,
doing kiosk engineering for microservices.
So the very first is to start very small.
So select some non critical services,
and then, start, like looking
into running the kiosk engineering
experiments for that services.
I think this is very important
because we don't want to take
a very important service down.
While doing this exercise.
So start with very small start with
the service which has less usages,
which is non critical So once we have
selected the service, then we can run
the experiment in a controlled manner and
by controlled manner, I mean we have to
use like feature flags and also We have
to ensure that we roll back into a very
stable state if, if something goes bad.
So maybe we were expecting that, just
one, like one dependency, like just in
case of a failure of one dependency, it
will not have any severe consequences,
but the reality is the opposite.
So here we have to make sure that
we are using feature flags and we
are able to roll back if needed.
And then we have to.
Monitor everything like there
are a lot of observability
tools available in the market.
Like some of them are like
prometheus Grafana and elk stack.
So yeah, we have to make sure that
we are monitoring properly and
The next step is the automation.
the chaos engineering, should be a
regular part of the DevOps pipeline.
It should be running continuously.
It should be running on the pipelines.
It should not be, one in a year
or one in a month exercise.
It should happen regular, regularly.
That's the only way to
make it more useful.
And then we should have a recovery plan.
So we have to make sure then, we
are able to roll back and there are
some, self healing mechanism exists.
And that is basically to, for
example, if we are facing a failure,
then yeah, there should be a self
healing mechanism that exists.
Is helping us to recover from that failure
And yeah, that's it for today.
Thank you everyone.
I hope that this was useful Bye