Hello, this is Vamsi.
let me do, let me introduce myself.
so I have like overall 16 years of
experience in, cloud and platform
engineering, with special, with,
specialization in infrastructure
automation and digital transformation.
today I'm going to, give,
introduction, like session on,
mostly Like today's the world is
changing, evolving with, completely
into the multi cloud environments.
Like we are not locked.
With one cloud provider.
So like we are currently like, going
with the multiple cloud providers,
AWS like a, Azure and GCP and whatnot,
so it is very, challenging and like
implementing, security, across a multiple
cloud platforms actually for our hosting.
Or application infrastructure.
So today I'm going to most deep dive
into the DevSecOps strategies for
enhanced security and compliance
in this, multi cloud era.
so the shift to multi
cloud is accelerating.
So with, with organizational leveraging
diverse cloud platform, cloud
providers for agility and scalability
and redundancy, but securing this
complex ecosystem is critical.
So this presentation explores how to
integrate security seamlessly into
DevOps workflows, enabling organizations
to thrive in the multi cloud era.
So let's deep dive into it.
so we, let's discuss about
the importance of DevSecOps.
so we are at the two, two pillars here.
Like one is a shiftlet security and then
other one is a continuous integration
and, integration and delivery.
so what is shift left security?
DevSecOps fundamentally.
transform security by integrating it
from the earlier stages of development.
By embedding security practices through
the software development lifecycle,
teams can identify and remediate
vulnerabilities earlier, reduce costs,
and build security first applications.
This proactive approach creates a
collaborative and, collaborative
culture where security becomes
everybody's responsibility.
It's let's discuss about shift lifecycle.
Earlier, back in the days, back in the
days, we used to have a SDLC lifecycle
and when we used to have a, like a,
let's go to the, like a, if you have
a code, like a code developer and
then push to the higher environments.
We'll come to.
do the testing of, application and
even the security testing we will
be doing at the stage of, before
we even go to the production.
at that point of time, it's becoming
it will become, hard for any, it will
be, let's say, for example, if some,
something happens, let's say, for
example, if we identify vulnerabilities
at the stage of hey, we have a release
in next week or so, let's say, for
example, We will have hardly one
week to fix the security issues,
which will be difficult to do that.
in that case, we should have
a mechanism of identifying
the security vulnerabilities
in the early stages of SDLC.
So the shift left security approach,
which we, most of the organizations
right now adopting so that they can,
so that they can, do the continuous,
testing while they're developing.
so while they're developing,
that's about shift left security.
So another thing is like a CACD,
you might have, we are very much
familiar with CACD, since a decade.
It's a, it's more of automated
security, like what CACD, so how,
how can we integrate this automated
security and validations in CACD.
So here is the thing, automated
security testing and validation with
the CACD pipelines is like revolution,
deployment safety by incorporating
security scans and compliance,
checks and vulnerability assessments
directly into the automated pipeline.
Organizations can, confidently deploy code
faster while, robust security standards.
This systematic approach ensures
consistent security, practices
across all the deployments.
so it's more of so we like implementing,
security, scans and vulnerability
checks, like by introducing them
into the CI CD pipeline so that let's
say, for example, before deploying
to any code into the environment.
So let's see.
do the security scans and
compliance checks and vulnerability
assessments before even deploying
in, into the environment.
So it's a stage actually.
so it's like we, we were like
implementing, introducing, sec,
security steps, security scan
steps, before deploying to the
core, to the any environment.
so it's more of integrating, so we need
to integrate with the CSCD pipelines.
And, next thing is.
So the key, so let's discuss about key
principles of DevSecOps for multi cloud.
So that the three things actually.
so we need to discuss, we need to
deep dive into the key principles
of DevSecOps for multi cloud.
so we need to discuss about three things.
One is like a policy as a code
and, automated, secure testing.
And the third one is continuous
monitoring threat detection.
So when it comes to policy as
code, what is policy as code?
so the policy as a code is, means so
what it does is it transforms security
requirements into executable code,
enabling automated policy enforcements
and compliance checks across multiple
clouds, such as AWS, Azure and
Google cloud and other platforms.
This approach eliminates manual errors
and ensures consistent security standards.
And, and then, so when, then coming to
the automated, security testing, so what
it does it's, it, what it does is by
introducing automated security testing, so
it, what it does is embedded, it will, it
will provide comprehensive security scans
into your deployment pipeline, including
SAS, DAST, and, container security checks.
This project to approach catches
one of vulnerabilities before they
reach production and it will reduce
the risk and, and, reduce the,
total operational costs actually.
and another thing is when it
comes to continuous monitoring
and threat detection.
so by, by, by leveraging, AI powered
security tools, that provides
a real time visibility across
a multi cloud infrastructure.
So what it, with incorporating AI powered
security tools, this will automatically,
correlate security events and detects
anomal anomalities and enable rapid
incident, response and maintain, and
maintain robust security, posture.
And, so what are the benefits
of DevSecOps in multi-cloud?
so it's mainly provides
to two key, key benefits.
One is reduced compliance
violations and other one is a
faster time to market, let's say.
co compliance, reducing compliance
violence is so the, by implementing these
DevSecOps in the multi-cloud environments,
Seeing 40 percent reduction in compliance
violation through automated, security
checks and, standardized, control across
the platform, which is, Great thing.
And, other thing is a faster to market,
by automating security, processes
and shift left, by, by integrating,
by, let's say, let's, having a,
having the strategy of implementing
automation, automated securities
testing and, shift left approach.
so shift left approach and DevOps,
DevSecOps, principle, principles.
so by, by co correlating like, by
coordinating, by implementing and
coordinating, automation testing and
shift lift approach, and DevSecOps so
we can accelerate, development cycles
by 25% at least, while strengthening
the security through, continuous testing
and early vulnerability detection.
And so the next slide, are we
gonna discuss about addressing
multicloud challenges.
So we definitely in this growing,
fast phase, everybody or, every
company, every, it organization, any
application infrastructure is scattered
across multiple, Cloud platform.
so what are the challenges having
a multiple cloud platforms?
so one thing first, like
we have three, three, three
standards, like three challenges.
So one is like a vendor lock
in and the second one is a
cross platform, discrepancies.
And the third one is a
global compliance standards.
so let's discuss about
like vendor lock in.
so when, so we will be deploying,
so to, to address these challenges,
like what we have to do is to address
this vendor lock in, challenges.
So here, we need to deploy platform
independent architectures and,
standardized APIs to maintain
operational freedom across
cloud platforms while reducing
dependencies on proprietary services.
And the second thing is cross,
cross platform discrepancies.
So when it comes to this area, so we
need to establish a unified security
frameworks and automated compliance
checks to maintain, consistent
security controls and risk management
across diverse cloud environments.
And then, third one is,
global compliance standards.
so the, what we need to do, we
need to implement a comprehensive
data governance frameworks that
automatically enforce regulatory
requirements like A-G-D-P-R and HIPAA
while, enabling real time, compliance
monitoring across, cloud platforms.
So, let's come to the real world
examples of DevSecOps in multi-cloud.
So we have a two case studies.
So one case study is like a in a
fortune 500 retail and the second one
is a global, banking corporation So a
global retail leader with 20 billion
annual revenue transformed their
security landscape through DevSecOps
adoption by implementing, automated
security scanning and Compliance checks
across AWS and Azure environments.
They achieved 35 percent reduction
in compliance Violations cut,
security incident response, time
from, days to hours and accelerated
deployment frequency by days.
3x and so and coming to other global
banking corporation like A major
financial services firm like processing
over 1 million transactions daily
revolutionized their security approach
by integrating automated vulnerability
scanning into their CICD pipeline this
resulted, in detecting 40 40 percent
more security issues during development
and reducing production Instance by 60
percent and, decreasing time to market
a new feature by 21st percent while
maintaining strict regulatory compliance.
so these are the best, recent,
case studies, best, which will give
a real time DevSecOps, benefits
in multi cloud environments.
And the key, and let's come to the
key takeaways, for, with the DevSecOps
for secure and compliant multi cloud.
so one, like I can say
three, takeaways, takeaways.
So one is enhance a culture of
security, so what it does mean?
so with this, we will be
transforming organizational mindset
by integrating security practices
into daily workflows and making
cybersecurity a core value across
all development and operation teams.
And the second thing is
automated security testing.
So by implementing comprehensive
automated security scanning and
testing throughout CACD pipelines to
identify and remediate vulnerabilities
before each production, before they
reach even production environments.
And the third thing is
a continuous monitoring.
So here, we'll be, so we'll be deploying
advanced, threat detection systems
and real time security, analytics to
maintain, resilient oversight of your
multi cloud infrastructure and respond
rapidly to potential security, incidents.
And so let's discuss so far we
discussed, all high level, how, and
what and how to implement, these
principles and, and methodology.
but here in this slide, we are going to
discuss, that, tools and technologies
for, DevSecOps in multi cloud environment.
so three things we need to discuss.
So one is for cloud security posture,
one is like cloud security, posture
management, so which will CSPM will
continuously monitor and assess cloud,
security risks through automated
security assessments and compliance
monitoring and, real time mis confi,
misconfiguration detection across
the AWS Azure and GCP environments.
And the second thing is like a cloud
security information and event management.
so what SIA, will, this will, leverage, AI
powered analytics to correlate, security
data across cloud platforms, enabling,
rapid threat detection, automated incident
response and a comprehensive security.
audit trails for compliance reporting.
And the third one is which is
critical is a container security.
So today the world we are moving from,
monolithic to microservice architecture.
container, using containers
is like becoming and.
Part of a daily, daily
operation and development life.
So in this case, we'll be implementing,
automated, like we need to implement
like, implement automated vulnerability
scanning and runtime protection and policy
informants for Docker and Kubernetes
workflows, ensuring security container
deployments from, development through
production across all, environments.
And, the next slide like we'll be
discussing here is, the future of
multi cloud security and what are
the emerging trends like, here is,
three things actually like for, these
are the, these three, items are like
more of emerging and, we need to
implement in a, in upcoming future.
one is like a serverless security
and the second one is, artificial,
intelligence for security and
third one is zero trust security.
So when it comes to serverless security,
um, advanced runtime protection and
the functional level monitoring for
serverless, architecture to secure,
so we, so we need to implement
advanced, runtime protection and,
functional level monitoring for
serverless architecture to secure.
Cloud native applications and
prevent unauthorized executions.
And the second thing is the next
generation security, powered by AI
algorithm, like we need to, develop
next generation security powered by
AI algorithm that can continuously
learn from threats, predict potential
attacks, and automatically orchestrate
responses across multi cloud environments.
And the third thing is
like zero trust security.
it's contest aware security framework
like, that verifies every access
request, regardless of source and,
enforcing strict identity verification,
and, least privileged access,
access across all cloud services.
So these are the three things like
emerging trends, which, which we
need to, aware and look forward.
And what are the actionable steps
for implementing DevSecOps in
your multi cloud environment?
So there's the four, four action items.
Like one is what first most thing what
you need to do is access current security
poster like, for that, you need to
conduct a thorough, security audit across
all cloud platforms, identifying gaps
in infrastructure, applications, and,
processes while mapping potential attack,
vectors and, compliance requirements.
And the second one is, develop
security policies and standards.
Need to create a comprehensive security
frameworks aligned with industry
best practices establishing clear
guidelines for access controls data
protection and Incident response
across your multi cloud ecosystem.
And the third one is integrate security
tools and automation So here we need to
do is what we need to do is deploy and
configure automated security scanning and
vulnerability assessment and compliance
checking tools within your CICD pipeline,
ensuring seamless integration with
the existing development workflows.
And the fourth one, what we need,
and the next step is establish
continuous monitoring and response.
Here we need to implement real time
security monitoring with automated alerts.
Detailed logging and rapid response
procedures, enabling, proactive
threat detection and swift remediation
across all cloud environments.
And, securiting, securing the multicloud,
error is a, it's not a journey.
It's a, it's a journey.
It's not a destination.
securing the multicloud environment
is not just a technical challenge.
It's it's a transformational
journey, that detects continuous
evaluation and a commitment.
through this strategic implementation
of DevSecOps principle, organizations
can build resilient, security frameworks
that adopt, adopt, emerging threats while
maintaining comp maintaining compliance
across, diverse cloud platforms.
The proactive approach not only
protects virtual assets but also
Enables innovation, accelerate,
accelerates our deployment cycles
and, create a competitive advantage
in today's dynamic digital landscape.
thank you all for, attending
this, session and I hope you
enjoyed, my presentation today.