Good morning.
Good afternoon.
Good evening, everyone around the world.
My name is Mahita Adpa and I'm excited
to share insights on transforming
healthcare crisis management
through event driven architecture.
Before we dive in, picture the scenario.
A major pandemic is spreading rapidly.
Hospitals are getting overwhelmed.
Emergency teams are desperately
trying to coordinate resources.
Every minute spent waiting for real
time data means potential lives at risk.
Today I'll show you how we are changing
this pattern completely by leveraging
Apache Kafka and Elastic Stack.
Before we go further, let's understand the
importance of real time data a bit more.
Imagine you are a hospital administrator
facing a sudden surge in emergency cases.
You need to know how many beds are
available across your networks,
where your ventilators are, and how
much your hospital is understaffed.
With traditional software architecture
system, the data sits in silos
separately in different departments.
Updates are processed
in batches overnight.
Reports take more than 24
hours to get generated.
And by the time these reports reach the
decision makers, It's already outdated.
Healthcare leaders struggle to make
decisions and coordinate resources
with these outdated reports.
In crisis situations, even hours of
delays means potential lives at risk.
Some hospitals get overwhelmed
while others have excess capacity.
This real time data helps us
overcome these challenges.
The cost of delays isn't just
operational, it means human life.
Let's now talk about how we can
achieve this event driven architecture.
We can break the architecture
into four key components,
each playing a critical role.
The first, we need to capture the data
in real time from multiple healthcare
sources, like testing centers, IoT
devices, ICUs, and emergency departments.
The data flows continuously
and every piece of information
is available for processing.
For example, if a patient is admitted
in ER, that information is available
system wide in milliseconds.
This eliminates delays and provides
real time view for hospital capacity.
Once the data is ingested, we need a
system that can process millions of
updates per second without any bottleneck.
This is where Apache Kafka comes in.
Kafka processes millions of events
per second in sub millisecond latency.
This means every patient admitted, every
test results are available instantly.
Instead of waiting for the data to be
processed in batches overnight, Kafka
ensures that healthcare administrators
and first responders get live
updates as soon as the event occurs.
Processing this data is one thing,
but making sense of it is another.
That's where Elastic Stack comes in.
Elastic Stack helps us detect trends
and analyze patient influx and even
predict the future resource rates.
Let's say if a hospital is seeing a
sudden rise in emergency room admissions,
Elastic Stack can flag this trend in
real time, helping decision makers
anticipate shortages before they happen.
Finally, all the real time
data must be made actionable.
We provide live dashboards and instant
alerts to ensure decision makers can
access clear real time data insights.
If ventilator stock is dropping at a
critical level, the system automatically
alerts the administrator enabling them
to take immediate actions rather than
realizing the issue when it's too late.
By integrating all these four layers,
data ingestion, real time data
processing, AI driven analysis, and live
reporting, we are now building a fully
equipped event driven architecture.
Using historical real time data
and machine learning models, we can
forecast The supply and demand for
the next 48 to 72 hours in advance.
If a hospital is nearing full
capacity, the system automatically
triggers resource reallocation,
ensuring hospital staff and supplies
are where they are needed the most.
Predictive analysis doesn't just
optimize medical supplies, it
also ensures hospitals have the
right staff on duty at all times.
AI analyzes the patient admission
trend and adjusts nurses and doctors
schedules proactively, reducing staff
burnout and improving patient care.
For If an emergency department is
experiencing 50 percent increase in
admission due to a sudden outbreak,
predictive models proactively
reroute the ambulance to avoid
overwhelming of a single facility.
This ensures patients are distributed
across multiple hospitals efficiently.
Instead of reacting to a problem
after it happens, hospitals are now
predicting and preventing the shortage
before they impact patients care.
Hospital administrators now receive real
time alerts and actionable recommendations
based on AI driven forecasts, allowing
them to prepare rather than panic.
Now let's talk about benefits of event
driven systems and how they can shape the
future of healthcare crisis management.
By moving from batch based processing
to real time data streaming, we
unlock three key advantages that
directly impact healthcare efficiency,
decision making, and resilience.
With event driven systems, hospitals
reduce resource allocation time by 85%,
enabling them to process more tests per
day without compromising on quality.
Imagine a testing facility
that manually updates patient
results at the end of the day.
Now, with real time streaming, these
results are immediately available
across the system, allowing the
staff to quickly direct resources
where they are needed the most.
In crisis scenario, every second counts.
The longer it takes to get the insights,
the higher the risk for the patient.
Real time analytics now empower
healthcare leaders to make critical
decisions within minutes, instead
of waiting for outdated reports.
Consider a hospital administrator
tracking ICU capacity.
Instead of relying on a static
spreadsheet, they now have live
dashboards that highlight available
beds and real time, helping them
to route patients instantly.
Finally, a system is only useful when
it can handle crisis level demand.
During Emergency Peaks, our event
driven architecture, successfully
scales 10x times without any
downtime, ensuring hospitals have
continuous access to data at all time.
Our platform has 99.
9 percent uptime, allowing
resource teams to operate smoothly,
even under extreme pressure.
This level of scalability and resilience
is critical for modern healthcare systems.
Now that we understand the power
of real time resource allocations,
let's talk about the key factors that
make event driven architecture work
seamlessly in healthcare, i. e. data
integrity, security, and scalability.
Hospital labs and emergency response
teams generate massive amounts of data,
but if this doesn't communicate with each
other, we end up data in silos, which
slow down the decision making process.
Standardizing data formats are
crucial for real time processing.
Fast healthcare interoperability
resources and HLR protocols help unify
data streams across different platforms.
Imagine an ambulance is transporting
a patient with critical condition.
If a hospital system is integrated
seamlessly with the parametric reports,
doctors can prepare for the treatment
even before the patient arrives.
With the real time data comes a
lot of challenges of security.
Healthcare data is highly sensitive
and any breach can lead to compliance
violation and loss of patient trust.
Implementing end to end encryption and
role based access control, continuous
monitoring ensures Integrity while
allowing seamless information exchange.
We use TLS encryption and block
based access control logs to ensure
that only authorized persons can
access critical healthcare data,
ensuring privacy and compliance with
regulations like HIPAA and GDPR.
Scalability is the last
and most crucial part.
A well architected, event driven
system must scale dynamically to
handle a sudden influx without
any performance degradation.
Our system leverages auto scaling
Kubernetes clusters with serverless
computing to manage sudden spikes,
ensuring hospitals don't face any IT
failures when the patient load increases.
Now let's discuss how we can build
resilient emergency response systems
that go beyond real time data processing.
In healthcare crisis, resilience
is not just about uptime.
It's about ensuring the right
information reaches the right
person at the right time.
Resilient systems should be
scalable, intelligent, and intuitive
to handle unpredictable events.
Now let's talk about the
four pillars together.
First, we need a system that integrates
data from hospitals, emergency responders,
public health agencies, To a single
real time viewer, without integration,
the response team are left making
decisions with incomplete information.
During an outbreak, if a hospital
and a testing team center operate
in silos, resource planning is
inefficient by communicating
electronic health data records.
Emergency call systems and lab reports.
We ensure comprehensive situational
awareness, helping decision
makers to see the full picture.
Speed is critical.
We configure message queues and
event streamings to handle over
millions of events per second.
Ensuring updates are processed
in sub millisecond latency.
Imagine a hospital is sending.
Critical ICU bed availability
updates with event driven systems.
This information propagates instantly,
allowing ambulance team to read
out patient in real time instead
of relying on outdated estimates.
We integrate AI driven predictive
analysis To anticipate demand for
next 48 to 72 hours in advance.
Instead of reacting, we enable
proactive resource planning.
Using past crisis data, our models can
predict where the next shortage may occur.
can happen, whether it is ventilators,
PPEs, medical staff shortage, allowing
hospitals to take preemptive actions.
Finally, making information accessible.
We built real time dashboards that
alert healthcare teams to critical
changes, allowing them to take informed
decisions in minutes instead of hours.
If an emergency room reaches a critical
occupancy level, an automatic alert is
notified to the administrator to redirect
non critical cases to nearby hospitals,
preventing system overload and ensuring
patient gets faster possible care.
Combining data integrity, event driven
streaming, AI forecast, and real
time visualization, we create a truly
resilient healthcare response system.
The future of healthcare is now about
anticipating what's coming next and
acting before it gets escalated.
Here are four major innovations
shaping the future of
healthcare crisis management.
First one is the advanced
early warning systems.
One of the biggest challenges in global
health is detecting the outbreak early
enough to prevent them from escalating.
With AI powered monitoring systems,
we can analyze global health
data streams to predict disease
outbreak up to 14 days in advance.
This shifts from reactive to
proactive healthcare, which
can save countless lives.
The next one is the data
driven precision care.
Beyond outbreak detection, AI
is also personalizing treatments
for better patient outcome.
By analyzing individual patient's history,
their genetical profile, and the real
time health metrics, smart algorithms
can generate customized treatment
plans to improve recovery rate by 40%.
This level of precision was unimaginable
a decade ago, but today, it's a reality.
The third one is the
integrated emergency response.
A unified digital platform can now
connect hospital, labs, and emergency
teams in real time, reducing the
emergency response time by 60 percent.
Crisis management is truly effective when
hospitals Emergency responders and public
health agencies work together seamlessly.
Picture a hurricane hitting a major city.
Instead of hospitals working in silos,
an integrated response system allows real
time coordination, directing the ambulance
to available hospitals instantly.
This ensures no single hospital
is getting overwhelmed while
others remain unutilized.
Together, these advancements
are transforming crisis, giving
us faster, smarter, and more
connected healthcare systems.
We have covered a lot today from
challenges of outdated batch
processing to transforming to
powerful event driven systems.
Let's quickly summarize the three
major takeaways from this discussion.
Event driven architecture.
Traditional batch processing
causes delays that may cost life.
With event driven architecture,
we achieve sub millisecond data
processing with 10x scalability.
Ensuring critical health care insight
reaches decision makers in real time.
Instead of hospitals waiting for hours
for outdated reports to get generated,
the decision makers and the administrators
have live dashboards where they can take
a peek and decide for the next steps.
Data alone isn't enough.
We needed to make it actionable
by using predictive models.
We can forecast resource demands
up to 48 to 72 hours in advance
with 90 percent accuracy.
This means that instead of running out
of ventilators during crisis, hospitals
can proactively allocate and distribute
supplies before the shortage occurs.
The last one, and very
important, is the resiliency.
No system is effective if
it fails during high demand.
Our architecture ensures 99.
9 percent uptime even under extreme
surge, processing 100k events per
second without any disruption.
Let's discuss what are the next steps.
Here are three key steps that
organizations should take to move forward.
First is to access existing crisis
management system and identify areas
where delays and inefficiencies occur.
For instance, if hospital is still relying
on batch updates, it needs to move and
start using real time streaming systems.
To reduce the bottleneck and
improve response time next
to use a I driven analysis to
enable real time decision making.
Finally, scaling up resilient
infrastructure is a key system
must handle high data loads
without failure during peak crisis.
Hospitals cannot afford downtime
during pandemics is scalable.
Always on system is critical
for crisis management.
The transition to event driven
architecture in healthcare isn't
just a technology upgrade, it
is a fundamental shift on how we
respond to crisis and save lives.
As we move forward, adapting to this
approach will not only strengthen
our ability to handle pandemics
and health emergencies, But it will
also create more accessible and data
driven healthcare system to everyone.
We have technology, data, and
ability to make healthcare faster,
smarter, and more reliable.
But it takes commitment from healthcare
leaders, policy makers, and technologists
to implement these changes to scale.
Let's build a healthcare that doesn't
just react to crisis, but anticipates and
prevents them to real time intelligence.
With that, I would like
to end my presentation.
Thank you everyone for listening in
and hope you have a wonderful day.