Hello all.
Good morning and good afternoon all.
And this is Gopi.
And today we are going to discuss about
a seamless SAP SRM migration, achieving
30 percent of performance and gains.
basically this presentation
outlines a successful SRM,
SAP SRM migration strategy.
Focus on the key steps and
technology that led to a 30
percent performance improvement.
how do we are going to with that
and homogeneous migration strategy
using a backup and restore method?
Our migration leveraged in an
advanced backup and restore
methodology for the HANA database.
Implementing full system snapshot
and incremental backups, this
approach is guaranteed by 99.
9 percent data integrity while
maintaining a remarkable short
downtime window of under four hours.
And what is the tools we are going to use?
The tool SAP is recommended as WPM.
software provisioning manager.
By implementing SWPM 1.
0 with automated validation and
checks, we achieved a 35 percent
reduction in deployment time.
The tool built in error prevention
mechanism eliminated common migration
pitfalls, resulting in zero critical
incidents during the transaction phase.
Database optimization and leveraging HANA
in memory, in memory database technology.
HANA revolutionary in memory computing
reduced data retrieval time from minutes
to milliseconds, achieving a 40 percent
improvement in system responsiveness
and enabling real time analytical
for a critical business process.
The second one is
optimized query processing.
By leveraging HANA's column based storage,
and parallel processing architecture.
Complex queries now execute 5x faster,
while compression algorithm reduces
storage requirements by 60%, dramatically
improving overall system efficiency.
how the content server
enhancing document management.
Basically, this content server, we are
going to use that for document repository.
the content server 6.
0 patch 11.
If you implement the Content Server 6.
0 Patch Level 11, delivered at
25 percent of boost in a document
processing speed with enhanced indexing
capabilities, enabling subsequent search
across 10 plus millions of documents.
The upgrade reduces storage
requirements by 40 percent through
intelligent compression algorithm.
How the content security?
The content security basically
advanced encryption protocols and
role based access controls now
safeguards sensitive data with AES 256
encryption method we are going to use.
The system maintained detailed audit
trials and supports secure external
sharing with a time limited access token,
robust backend, and the power of MaxDB.
The Max db, one of the SAP, database, and
if you, migration 7.9, the MAX DB version
delivered enterprise grade scalability
with advanced buffer pool management
and the parallel query processing.
Successfully handling a 50% increase a
daily transaction volume while reducing
response to time by 40% high availability,
implement and redundant failover clusters.
With automated backup
systems achieving 99.
9 percent uptime with a mean time
between failures MDBF 8, 760 hours
of recovery time object to RTO of
under 15 minutes web servers and
IIS optimization and delivering a
superior user experience, improve a
responsive times and load balancing.
Basically, the IIS is used for.
image replication, advanced IAS
thread, optimization and catalog
mechanism, catching mechanism,
reduced average page load time from 2.
8 seconds to 0.
9 seconds, delivering 68
percent of performance boost
in user responsive times.
Implementation of HTTP
compression, further reduction
bandwidth usage of by 45%.
What is load balancing?
Implementing enterprise grade
load balancing with automatic
failover maintaining 99.
99 percent of optimum during peak
loads of 10, 000 plus concurrent users.
Dynamic content distribution across
multiple nodes reduces server load
by 60% While ensuring a seamless
user experience, what is the
migration process and key takeaways?
One is minimal downtime and
second one is data integrating.
How the minimal time,
downtime, will occur.
Strategic migration planning and
reduced system downtime to just 3.
5 hours, exuding during off peak
hours with zero impact of business
operations across global time zones.
How the data integrity works.
Achieved 100 percent of data accuracy
through rigorous validation, protocols
with automated checksums, verifying
overall 2 million of records,
and maintaining complete audit
trial throughout the transition.
what is the benefits, performance
gains, and business growth?
basically the 30 percent of performance
improvement, operational excellence,
and strategic business impact.
What is 30% of improvement
performance dramatically reduced
response time and enhance the system
throughout, across all modules.
Operational excellence.
Second one, 50% of a faster data
processing, 40% of reduction
in storage costs and 25% of
improvement user productivity.
What is strategic business impact?
Enabling handling of two
x transaction volumes.
Supported expansion into new markets
and reduce the time to market by 30%.
these improvements have, positioned
our organization for a sustainable
growth while delivering immediate ROI
through enhanced system performance
and operational efficiency.
What is the key strategy of for a
successful S-A-P-S-R-M migration strategy
planning, developing a comprehensive
migration roadmap with a clear milestone,
risk mitigation strategies and measurable
KPAs to ensure projects success
and minimize business distribution.
The second one is expert team and
build across Cross functional team
combining certified of SAP consultant and
experienced database administration and
seasoned project managers with a proper
migration expertise through testing
after migration, how the testing will
go implementation of rigorous testing
protocols, including unit testing,
integration testing and full scale
simulation to validate system performance.
Please.
data integrity and user experience.
Beyond the migration
continues optimization.
One is performance analytics and
second one is a strategic enhancement.
deploy real time monitoring tools to
track APIs, analyze system metrics.
And to identify optimization opportunities
through productive analyticals.
The second one is a strategic enhancement.
Execute, execute or schedule
system health checks, implementing
auto maintenance protocols, and
perform quality performance.
During the maintain peak time efficiency
conclusion, a future proof of SAP
SRM system through our strategic
migration approach, our cutting
edge technologies implementation.
Your SAP SRM system is now pushing
for exceptional performance with 30
percent of faster processing speed.
And the seamless scalability that
optimizes the infrastructure not only
address current operational challenges,
but it creates a robust foundation for
further growth, enabling your organization
to quickly adapt market changes, emerging
opportunities with enhanced security,
improved user experience, and streamlined
workflows with business equipment
to maintain its comprehensive edge.
While maximizing return our
investigation of years to come.
this is that SRM migration successfully.
Thank you.
Thank you for today.