Hi, everyone.
Hope everyone is doing great.
I'm Jayakrishna Vemuri.
I'm having more than 14 years of
experience in IT industry in implementing
high volume, high performance, large scale
investment banking products using multiple
database technologies like Oracle,
Sybase, Snowflake, Microsoft Azure.
I have a strong expertise in front
to back trading applications on how
they work and how you just perform
the reconciliation process for the
regulatory and reporting needs.
As part of my job responsibilities,
I was primarily involved in building
multiple applications using on
prem, hybrid and cloud technologies
with strong domain allies.
Today, we're going to talk about
driving precision and efficiency of
cloud based reconciliation applications
in investment banking domain.
as you all know, investment banking
industry operates on massive
scale of processing millions and
billions of transactions daily.
accurate and timely reconciliation
of financial data is essential
for compliance, risk management,
and strategic decision making.
So this presentation will explore
the transformative power of Cloud
based reconciliation applications
and their impact on the investment
banking and IT industry.
Let's get into that.
So first, I'm going to talk
about the current challenges with
traditional reconciliation process.
So Let's talk about how much time
consuming it's going to take.
So the legacy reconciliation often
involves, significant manual effort.
user has to perform the data analysis and
then prepare the data in the spreadsheet,
ingest the data, and once the data has
been loaded, so they have to perform the
Matching of the transaction between source
and target and identifying the expenses
and finally they prepare the reports.
This is so time consuming because
most of the process is manual and
even though they use tools, those
were not integrated properly.
So this can lead to delays in.
Closing the financial periods many times.
Second thing human errors as
we all do mistake at times.
So manual intervention always
increases the problem of errors.
such as like when you're adding some data.
You do some mistakes and we miss some
transactions and then sometimes we
perform the matching incorrectly and
then we may miss loading some data.
So whenever we do this can
result in delaying the process,
this and all human address.
And this can even potentially Go
into inaccurate financial statements.
The third one is disjointed systems.
So when we say disjointed systems
So this legacy systems, will have
there'll be multiple systems.
You have to integrate the systems We can't
integrate systems completely front to back
end to end the reason is Each system will
have different software different product.
Okay different external vendors like
Some people use this accounting software,
custodian services, banking systems.
So these kinds of fragmentation makes
it difficult to, get them into sync.
Which leads to most of the
problems next delayed information.
So most of the legacy systems
reconciliation systems
Typically rely on batch updates.
So which means they don't process
the data on real time So they
process the data on batches.
They are they upload the data.
So which means If user wanted to
perform the reconciliation, it will
not be real time most of the times.
So we can't perform the decision
making on the fly due to this
outdated and incomplete information.
And, the other point is
difficulty in audits.
So with all these problems, and
then, we don't have a proper end
to end integrated systems, and
there are many manual and, it's.
So we can't audit each and every step
due to many manual interventions, human
errors, and then disjointed systems.
So auditing the reconciliation
process becomes so cumbersome,
which it didn't increase the time
and cost to complete the audit.
These are the few challenges with
traditional reconciliation systems.
Now let's go into the features of
cloud based reconciliation system.
So first one is automated data matching.
So when we say automated data matching,
so we can design the cloud based platforms
to automate each and every process of
matching the transactions from Multiple
sources like sources can be banks, counter
parties, custodians and trading platforms.
The system compares the internal
records with external records.
So pre cancellation always performs
between two systems and, it
automatically flags if there are any
discrepancies for the user to review.
once this is automated, the data matching,
so most of the problem will be solved.
the second point is real
time data synchronization.
With our new cloud evolving
technology, the data to be
synced and updated in real time.
So this means that as and when the
transaction occurs, as and when user
posts something, there is, we can
do the reconciliation immediately.
And, it can even speed up the
reconciliation process completely as
we don't have to wait for anything.
As the system is system and data
is synchronized all the time.
And the third point is
integration of multiple systems.
So this is the key feature where these
platforms can seamlessly integrate with
the various internal and external systems.
Any source system, accounting
system, custodian system.
So if it is in cloud, if you configure
properly, so the things will be as
quick as possible and which will help us
break down the data silos and provide a
unified view of financial transactions.
and final thing is like reporting
once we perform the reconciliation,
obviously, we have to create the reports.
the cloud based systems
typically have powerful reporting
and analytic capabilities.
these tools allow firms to generate,
The comprehensive reports on the
reconciliation process and highlight the
issues in real time are very quickly.
Reports can be customized as user
require, needs and they can be
exported to other systems shared
with stakeholders and shared to
different, shared in multiple formats.
Everything can be done in a single click.
So once the report is unleashed,
and then the next thing is
audit trials and compliances.
So the most difficult part, is
audit trials and compliance.
So that too, for the financial
institution, maintaining accurate records
for regulatory reporting is very crucial.
So this cloud system maintains
the detailed audit trails of
all reconciliation activities
like Who made the changes?
When it was done?
How it was done?
If something is broken, how is it broken?
All this will be properly audited
in the cloud based systems.
This ensures complete transparency
and makes the process of auditing.
More straightforward.
and machine learning and a
integration, which is a key
concept in any of the cloud stuff.
So some of the advanced cloud
based reconstruction tools in cloud
incorporate machine learning and a.
These technologies can predict and
automatically resolve the discrepancies
based on historical patterns,
reducing human interventions, and
speeding up the process further
because it takes care of everything.
Those are the key features.
Let's come to the benefits of
cloud based reconciliation with
the features which we have.
First, increased efficiency.
So automating this.
Manual tasks like ingestion, data
matching, exception handling,
generating the reports and audit
trials, all this will be very quick.
Now, this leads to a quicker close
cycles and more timely decision making.
and reduce risk of errors.
So this old system, configure the
system properly, you develop something,
we produce it, this cloud platform
automate much of the reconciliation
process and reduce the manual entry.
The chances of human errors and
data mistakes are no more available
except for the coding, of course,
which means our manual errors
are minimized more efficiently.
And now, enhanced collaboration.
Cloud platforms are accessible
from anywhere within Internet
connection, facilitating collaboration
across multiple teams or even
multiple regions and locations.
This is especially useful for investment
banks and financial firms with global
operations across teams working remotely.
Next, cost optimization.
The time savings from cloud based
reconciliation can translate into
cost reductions, as expected.
Organizations can report around 60
percent faster monthly end closures.
So these month end reports,
month end closures are very
crucial for any financial form.
And they even realize approximately 50
percent in the manual introversion reduce
and the ability to reallocate 40 percent
of their savings in resource allocations
to improve the products even better.
So now, next point is better
complaints and transparency.
This cloud based reconciliation
systems are frequently updated to
meet changing regulatory requirements.
The built in audit trial features.
For this cloud provides clear visibility
into the reconstruction process making
it easier to comply with all regulatory
standards like GDPR and so on.
And major, very great benefit
is faster decision making.
With faster reconstruction cycles
and real time data updates,
decision making is, decision making.
Is very quick and this can rely on more
accurate and up to date financial data.
To inform business strategies
now, let's think about the
architecture of this reconciliation.
So If you if we just think any of the
reconciliation systems So data in this
we need to perform the load loading of
the data and then we have to build some
reconciliation system and then we have
to perform the Some tool to validate
and then we have to see some reporting
methodology It's like quite common, but
when it comes to cloud based thing, the
data engine, the system employs advanced
APIs, excuse me, and connectors to
ingest the data from multiple sources.
That can include trade confirmations,
settlement transactions.
And, real time market fits.
this features robust error handling
and data buffering capabilities.
which ensures during peak hours, we
can queue the data than, breaking the
system and go Oh, there's a huge data.
Oh, I can't handle the data.
Let's break it.
let's ask users to push only little
more data on a batch of dates.
So we don't have to do all of this.
So the cloud based systems can
easily scale up and scale down
if you architect it properly.
That's the power of cloud based.
And then once data is ingested, we
have to build a reconciliation engine.
So what does this do?
That system can be a high
performance matching engine.
So where we can configure the rules
and machine learning algorithms to
perform multivariate reconciliation
across So any kind of data sources.
Advanced pattern recognition
identifies complex expenses, while
the intelligent AI handles routine
matches, escalating only the exceptions
that require human interventions.
And user can comment, annotate however
they want, they can make the changes, they
can push the changes back to the system.
So we can develop reconciliation in
such a way that it's more powerful
for Front and back validations So
it's nothing but data processing and
validation this sophisticated etl extract
transform language So this is a normal
etl system, but when it comes to cloud
it is so powerful by using automated
workflows, machine learning algorithms,
which can detect any anomalies,
built in validation rules, to ensure
the data quality and completeness.
and then issue resolution and reporting.
An integrated workflow management
system streamlines exception
handling through automated routing
and collaborative resolution tools.
The reporting layer leverages Business
intelligence capabilities to generate
real time dashboards regulated
reports and Predictive analytics
that drives operational improvement.
So which means there is a issue We
can flag the issue and then send the
issue to corresponding user on an email
on Any kind of cloud based platform
where we can quickly check and then
perform the resolution accordingly.
We can send the reports in
cloud as much faster as we need.
So that's the architecture now When
we do the when we do some kind of case
studies in the real world So so there
are some invest bank Is investment banks.
So when they use the cloud-based
platform, for their reconciliation, they
within six months, they achieved 60.
60, not 60.
It's 70% reduction in manual processing
errors, cutting reconciliation time
from 44 hours to less than 45 minutes,
and their accuracy rates sold to 99%.
While reconciliation related
operation cost decreased by 40%.
So, more less operational cost, less
manual effort, more speedy approach.
So one of the company
have evolved with that.
So next, when it comes to hedge
funds, so a 10 billion hedge fund
revolutionized their portfolio
reconciliation through cloud technology.
The new system automatically resolves 92
percent of their position risk expenses.
within minutes compared to hours
when they do it perfectly or
days if there are any mistakes.
Real time monitoring now flags 90
percent of potential issues before
they impact trading decisions.
This dramatically strengthening
their risk management framework.
And, it is asset management company,
which is like 50 billion asset manager.
They streamlined the regulatory
reporting through this cloud technology
reconciliation, daily reporting cycle
shortened from six hours to 90 minutes,
while accuracy improved from 96 to 99.
8%. The company now handles three
times the transaction volume.
more than what they used to handle
earlier with legacy applications.
this is the scalability and it can go
even 10 percent as 10 times as well.
So this is the cloud based and
then what is the future we can
even think of using an artificial
intelligence, what it will do.
So next generation AI transforms the
reconciliation through intelligent pattern
because Transcribed Recognization and
machine learning advanced algorithms
automate the complex matching while
real time anomaly detection prevents
before they impact the operations.
This reduces the manual
intervention by up to 80%.
Yes.
When AI comes, any similar activities can
be detected automatically and based on
the historical data, it does, the pattern
matching and it speeds up the process.
And we can use blockchain technology.
This distributed ledger technology,
The reconciliation by creating
a single source of truth, smart
contracts, automated verification,
while immutable audit trials,
enhanced transparency and compliance.
Virtually eliminating the data
discrepancies between the parties.
The third point is data
analytics and visualization.
Now, everything will be dashboards,
reports, hit a single click of button.
They can just move from one
reconciliation to another reconciliation.
The interactive visualization that
highlights the trends and problems.
And it can even show us the predictive
models, forecast, potential issues,
which can be used for proactive
optimization of reconciliation workflows.
So what are our key
takeaways and our next steps?
So I believe we need to implement the
cloud based reconciliation solution
to reduce all this manual efforts
and, minimize the operation risk and
reallocate the valuable resources to.
Strategic initiatives than using
spreadsheets comparing taking more
time and second point is strengthen
the risk management established.
Robust data governance frameworks
and automated validation process
to ensure 99 percent of accuracy.
This meets the regulatory requirements
and builds stakeholder stress.
Yes, as and when everything
is automated and validated.
The chances of risk will be quite less.
And next drive innovation leadership.
Deliveries AI powered analytical and
blockchain technology to transform
the reconciliation from back office
function into a strategic advantage,
delivering the real time insights
and predictive capabilities.
Yeah, it transforms everything.
this is some, estimated changes
of the cloud based reconciliation
in investment banking operation.
So it, as we talked, it reduces
around 75 percent of manual effort and
improved accuracy in their systems.
And it lowered the cost,
operating costs also.
So it's all savings.
And,
more efficient, more
savings, and, more scalable.
And the conclusion, cloud based
reconciliation applications have
revolutionized investment banking
operations, delivering up to 80
percent reduction in processing
time, while ensuring unprecedented
accuracy in financial data management.
by leveraging intelligent automation and
real time analytics, companies are not
only streamlining their operation, but
also uncovering valuable insights that
drive the strategic decision making as the
financial landscape continues to evolve.
Organizations that go with these
transformative solutions will be in a
better position to scale efficiently by
maintaining the regulatory compliance
and, capture new opportunities.
Very quickly in this competitive world,
which will make their company growth
go more success and scalable very
quick as cloud based reconciliation
systems can be scalable as easy
as possible, as quick as possible.
And thank you.
First of all, I would like to thank
you for giving me these opportunities.
Thank you so much Con 42 for giving
me this opportunity and thank you for
listening to this great initiative.
And I hope this gives you some kind
of more insight on reconciliation
processes by using cloud based systems.
Thank you all.
Have a wonderful day.