Everything fails all the time is a famous
quote from Amazon's CTO, Werner Vogels.
This means that software and distributed
systems may eventually fail because
something can always go wrong.
So what happens when your containerized
applications face network disruptions?
So in this session, you will
learn how to proactively validate
your containerized applications.
Resilience.
using AWS Fault Injection Service,
a FIAS, turning potential network
challenges into opportunities for
strengthening your architecture.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Sunil Govindankutty.
I am an enterprise support
lead at Amazon Web Services.
I'm also a member of our Resilience
technical community, where I focus
on the chaos engineering area.
I'm excited to be here talking
today, talking to you today
about this particular topic.
Now let's see the agenda.
We'll start with an overview of
Amazon ECS and AWS Fargate options.
You have, to run container
workloads in AWS.
We'll then see some of the, network
faults that can happen that you
might have seen in real world.
We'll look at an overview of FIS and
the various features and components
that the service has and supports.
We'll also see a reference
flow of a chaos engineering
experiment triggered through FIS.
We'll then conclude with a demo of
a sample application that is running
containers on Amazon ECS using Fargate
and see what the application behavior
would look like in case of network faults.
ECS, or Elastic Container Service,
provides a managed platform that
provisions compute, network, and storage
that you need for your containers.
It manages the scheduling of containers,
the self healing of containers,
the auto scaling of containers.
And it integrates well with our,
container registry, the secrets manager,
the load balancing service, et cetera,
that allows you to focus on just your
application and your requirements
for containers and leaving the
management of the container platform,
the orchestration platform to ECS.
Now where do you run these containers?
So you have a few options.
One of them is AWS Fargate,
which is a serverless compute
platform for containers.
It runs each of the containers
in its own kernel and manages the
life cycle of the underlying host.
So you eliminate the need for customers
to upgrade, patch and to scale the
underlying hosts needed by the containers.
Now we'll see some of the core
constructs of the ECS platform.
One of them is a task.
So in, you specify the compute
requirements, your networking
requirements, the permissions, and the
configurations you need for one or more
of your containers in a task definition.
Then tasks are created from
this definition, matches all
of the attributes that you have
specified in the definition file.
And then I mentioned, the orchestration
activities of, healing, failed containers,
replacing them, managing the scaling of
the, containers, performing deployments
of latest code to existing containers.
All of those activities are managed
by, what's called a service.
And it also registers these
containers to load balancers
to accept the end user traffic.
Then you also have what's called a
cluster, which is a logical grouping
of services and tasks in an AWS region.
You can then use IAM or identity
and access management service.
to control the permissions of
users to these clusters and
its underlying components.
Now let's do a quick, take a quick
look at, networking for Fargate tasks.
Each task gets its own network interface,
its own ENI using an IP from a subnet that
you have provided to the ECS platform.
And then you can apply security
groups to a task that will control
the ingress and egress of the traffic
from the underlying containers.
In case that, you have a bunch of
containers running in terms of, a spike
in traffic or something like that, you
can attach secondary CIDR blocks to your
VPC to address that particular need.
Now we've looked at the, networking.
What are some of the, fault actions, fault
events that could happen in a real world.
One of them is latency, which is
a delay in communication between
services and their dependencies.
you could see behaviors like Network,
congestion or, a route change resulting
in latency or a DNS resolution, delay
that, again, resulting in latency.
And then you have network black hole
where packets are silently dropped.
Here you might see DCP
connections hanging.
You might see, loss of connectivity
between dependencies and.
You might not get an error
response from underlying
dependencies in an event like this.
Another flavor of a network fault is
packet loss, where the packets doesn't
reach their intended destination.
So with this, you might see,
retransmission attempts at the TCP layer.
You might see degraded
performance across your workload.
You might see, bursts or random
patterns of network packets
in your monitoring tools.
Now, given that, some of these, network
faults could happen or would happen
in your container environment, how
do you prepare for that eventuality?
That's where FIS, Fault Injection
Service from AWS, comes into picture.
It's a fully managed service for
running fault injection experiments.
It comes pre packaged with scenarios
of various fault actions that you can
take and run against your workload.
You can, run it through the AWS
management console or CLIs or integrating
with any tools of your choice.
So you can get started in a
matter of minutes, in fact.
And it allows you to test real
world conditions from as simple as
stopping off or termination of an
EC2 instance to as complex as a power
interruption in an availability zone.
FIS also fully embraces the concept
of safeguards that allows you to
limit the blast radius of your
chaos engineering experiments.
So you could Specify an alarm, and
if that were to go off, FIS will
stop all the experiment and the
fault actions it is performing and
then try to roll back those actions.
Now let's look at a reference
flow for the service.
So at a very high level, we start with
an experiment template that packages the
different fault actions and the targets
that will be affected by those actions.
and safeguards that you want to
enforce while running the experiment.
FIS then performs these actions on the
AWS resources that are specified as the
targets when you start the experiment.
You can then monitor the
experiment using CloudWatch.
FIS also integrates with Amazon
EventBridge, allowing you to use
a monitoring tool of your choice.
to observe the behavior of
the application in question.
And experiments, once started, will
automatically stop when all of the
actions specified are complete.
Or, as I mentioned earlier, you can
optionally configure an alarm, and if that
were to go off, the actions are stopped.
And once the experiment is complete, you
can, view the results to identify any
performance concerns or observability
issues or resilience challenges.
You could also then use the report
of Kiosk Engineering as an evidence
of testing to your compliance
group or a security department.
Now that we have seen, a high level
capabilities of FIS, let's take a sample
application running on an ECS cluster
and let's try to inject network faults.
So in this case, this sample
application is a CRUD API.
Running on an ECS Fargate cluster,
getting data to and from an RDS database.
So we will run NetworkFalse against
this dependency and see what the
behavior of the application looks like.
Okay, now you have the AWS
console where, We have our sample
application up and running.
So let's take a look at the
cloud formation stacks for our
application and its components.
So we have an app stack that contains all
the infrastructure components needed for
our application, including the ECS Fargate
cluster, the RDS database, et cetera.
And then we have a monitoring stack.
So one of the prerequisites with any
type of experimentation is that you
have an observability and monitoring
mechanism in place for your applications.
Otherwise, It's the old pre
false in the forest saying.
So for our sample application, we will
be doing the monitoring using CloudWatch.
As I mentioned earlier, FIS integrates
with third party monitoring tools
through EventBridge as well.
And then we have our experiment stack.
So the experiment stack contains
the various network fault actions
that we will be performing
against our sample application.
Now let's take a closer look at the
application stack and its outputs.
So one of the outputs is the API URL.
So this is the end point of our sample
API that we will be testing with.
Now, let's see how this
API behaves from an IDE.
Let's, do a get on this endpoint.
As you can see, the API
returns a few items.
So basically, the functionality
behind the API is to do Create, read,
update, delete operations for items.
And I was able to get a list of
items that are currently in the
database through this API call.
Good.
now the other thing we want to do,
one of the other prerequisites for
experimentation is load generation.
So as you start on the chaos engineering
journey, we recommend that You start
with the lower environment, whether
it's a testing or a staging environment.
And the challenge there is that
you might not have the real user
traffic in those environments.
So you need to generate some type of
synthetic traffic that mimics your real
production traffic so that when you run
these experiments, you get a sense of what
could happen in a real world condition.
So in our case, for the sample
application, I'm going to be using
the open source tool called Artillery.
to generate some synthetic
load against our API.
So basically it's just going to
do a, post action, against our
API endpoint for 20 minutes.
So let's go to our Cloud 9 IDE console.
and kick off that load generation script.
So you can see here, the load
generation tool is hitting our
API endpoint and getting a 201
item created HTTP status code.
That's good.
so let's keep the load generation
script running here while we go take
a look at our, ECS cluster, right?
So our Compute layer for, the API is, ECS.
So as I mentioned in the slides,
there are a few constructs with ECS.
One of them is a cluster.
So we have one cluster
running in this account.
With one service, and this service
has a couple of tasks that are
on the running state that is
supporting our application workload.
And each of these tasks
have two containers.
One is the application container, the app
container with the application code, and
the other is an SSM agent container, which
is one of the Prerequisites for running
network faults against an ECS Fargate.
Cluster, you can refer to all the
AWS public documentation around the
prerequisites for network faults.
So we have the cluster, the services,
the task, all of that is good.
now let's take a quick peek at our,
database layer, our RDS endpoint.
So you can see that, we have, a MySQL
database supporting our application.
And this is the endpoint of that
cluster and this is the port
the database is listening on.
So we'll be using this information
while we run the experiments later.
So now that we have looked at
the application architecture,
let's take a quick peek at our
observability tooling as well.
So we have a dashboard here.
That we've created through
our experiment stack.
Let's take a look at, let's say the last
15 minutes or so, we, yeah, where we've
started running some load generation
script against our application, right?
So it's still, catching
up with the observability
metrics for our, application.
So we'll, keep an eye on this,
let it catch up with the load
generation script while We take
a look at, the AWS FIS console.
So here you can see that as a part
of our experiment stack, we have
three, experiment templates created.
So one of them here is the network
latency, the other black hole, and
the other, the last one packet loss.
So these are the.
Various network faults we looked at,
during the, review of the slides earlier.
Now let's dive deep into this
network latency, experiment.
Let me just do an update of the
template so you can clearly see
the various components of it.
So the two key things, or
two key concepts we covered.
with an experiment template
is the action and the target.
So the action specifies the fault that
you want to test against your workload.
And as, I mentioned earlier, you can
sequence a bunch of fault actions or
you can run them in parallel or mix
them up, etc. So in our case, what
we're going to do is we're going
to run this network latency fault
action against our ECS cluster.
And as you can see here, you see
there is a bunch of services that
our, FIS service integrates with.
So right now, let's focus on
the network latency action.
And then based on the action that
you selected, you can specify
a certain number of parameters.
So for this latency action,
one item is the delay.
What is the latency
that we want to add to?
our network traffic between the
compute layer and the database layer.
So in this case, I'm selecting the
default which is 200 and then we're
going to run this for five minutes.
And you can see in the source So
in this field here, I've specified
the endpoint of our RDS database.
So that is the source that we
want to introduce latency for.
Now that we have specified all of
that information, let's take a look
at the second major component of
the template, which is the target.
So in our case, the target
is a set of ECS tasks.
We are specifying the ECS cluster name.
and the ECS service name to identify
the tasks that FIS should be targeting
for this particular experiment.
And, another key thing
here is the, permission.
So as I mentioned, earlier, you
can control the permissions and
experiment has through, IAM role.
And then controlling the blast
radius of an experiment is important.
So you can specify CloudWatch alarms
as stop conditions for an experiment.
So in this sample application,
you're going to leave that as blank.
So let's go back to the
experiment template itself.
So before we start running any
experiments, we want to make
sure that we understand the
steady state of our application.
so we have the prerequisites in
place in terms of observability
in monitoring and load generation.
The next thing is we understand the
steady state of the application.
What is the, output of the metrics?
What is the value of the key
metrics that we are interested in?
So let's go back and take a look at our
CloudWatch dashboards that should have
caught up with the load generation script.
So let's say in the last five minutes,
what does the metrics look like?
So as I, as we expect, there
are no errors from our API.
So that's the other thing, if there are
errors in an application that you are
trying to run experiments on, you might
want to pause that experimentation,
go back, and fix those errors, right?
So if you have known errors, you
would want to address that before
starting with any experimentation.
And then you can see here that we have two
key widgets that, we have identified for
observability of our application workload.
One of them is the API gateway latency.
So from a. System perspective, from let's
say a system operator perspective, what
does the application health look like?
And what are the measures
of those different metrics?
At the same time, you would want to
also understand the behavior of the
application from an end user perspective.
Sometimes there could be a disconnect
between what an operator thinks health
of an application is versus an end user.
So you would want to have a pane of
glass into each of those perspectives
to understand the system behavior.
So that's what we are
trying to demonstrate here.
So from an, system perspective, our
latency is around 22 to 25 milliseconds.
And the P90 value from an end
user perspective is around.
75 to 150 milliseconds.
So that's the steady
state of our application.
And hopefully these metrics are well
within the threshold that we have,
agreed upon with our end user, with
our application owners saying that,
this is the latency metric that, our
application will be running with.
We now have the prerequisites.
We have a steady state understanding.
Now the next thing before we run any
type of experimentation would be to
come up with a hypothesis, right?
Especially, in this case
with network latency.
So the network latency, our hypothesis
is that in the event of a latency in
the network path between our compute
layer and the database layer, we
believe that the overall latency
of the application would go up.
It would still be well within
the threshold of, what we
consider as healthier, healthy
state for our application.
So the latency would go up, it
will bump up, but it's going to be
well within the thresholds that we
have defined for our application.
So let's see if that hypothesis is going
to hold true by running this experiment.
So I'm going to start the experiment,
add a tag and then I'm going to You
know, provide a value for the tag.
So this will help us, differentiate
between the various runs of an
experiment in the event that, we are
attempting the same experiment multiple
times as we observe different things.
Now, once I start to start the
experiment, Aquarius is going
to ask me to confirm that.
And once I have that ready.
You can see the experiment going
through a couple of phases.
It starts with an initiating phase
where it collects all the resources
and everything it needs and then
moves into a running state and
then into either a failed state
or a completed state, in a minute.
And then if we look at our actions,
in for this experiment template, with
this experiment, we only have one,
action, which is a network latency.
That's going to be.
Also running.
we are running that for five
minutes in this particular case.
Now, if I look at the resources, if you
remember in the template, we only gave
the cluster name and the service name,
but FIS has identified that these are
the two tasks that it should be running
these latency experiments against.
So we've started this a couple
of minutes ago, so we'll give
the observability tooling a
minute or so to catch up as well.
Let's take a look at a couple of other
features and functions So here under the
timeline, you can see the various actions
FIS is performing and where they are.
So in the event of, multiple
actions, you would see them getting
queued up or running at any time
while the execution is ongoing.
And if there are any, log events
associated with that particular experiment
run, you can see that here as well.
So now that it's been a couple
of minutes, after we started the
experiment, let's take a look at
our, application monitoring tool.
So here our p90 values was in the
steady state, 75 to, 150 milliseconds.
Let's see how it has changed
with this experimentation.
Yeah, so you can see as expected
the average latency has gone up
from a system perspective and a real
user monitoring perspective, right?
So from 75 to 150, it's now gone up to 262
milliseconds, almost, double the measure
that we have seen initially and that is
continuously continue to trending up.
But, we can observe that
there are no errors.
The application is still
continuing to function well.
there are no errors being
returned, from a user perspective
or from a system perspective.
Now, the big question is, this increase in
latency, is that within the threshold that
we have agreed upon with our system users?
So that's a decision that you will
have to make with the stakeholder.
Say we saw the, that
the latency has gone up.
is that latency still acceptable
in an event like this?
If it is not.
You will have to take a look at
some remedial actions, right?
So if the latency were to go up beyond
a certain threshold, maybe fail over
your database from your primary to
standby or, something like that.
So those are the, Potential actions that
you can take with these observations.
Oh, let's go back and take a
look at that experiment template.
I think it should be
finishing up here, any minute.
so we'll let that, complete while we,
look at the next, experiment template.
So let's try the, black hole one.
So in this case, what we are doing
is trying to create a network
black hole between our compute
layer and the database layer.
So if I look at the action for this
particular experiment template, you
can see it is network black hole.
And what are the parameters
this action supports?
So again, we're going to
run it for five minutes.
And this is the port number that our
RDS cluster was listening at, right?
So I've specified that as one of
the parameters for this action.
And any TCP traffic coming into
that port will be black holed.
And then in terms of targets,
it's still the set of ECS tasks.
that will be targeted by our experiment.
Now let's go back and make sure our
previous experiment is completed.
Yes, it has.
And now coming back to the black hole
experiment, you already have You know,
the prerequisites, observability, load
generation, we've, looked at the steady
state metrics of our, application as well.
And now the next thing is hypothesis.
So what is our hypothesis for
this particular experiment?
So here, what we are saying is that if
there is a network black hole between
our compute layer and the database
layer, we believe our application is
going to recognize that, and it's going
to return a user friendly error code or
error message to the application users.
So now let's see if that hypothesis
is going to be valid or not.
Now before we do that, let's look at
our observability tooling real quick
and make sure that it is getting back.
Yeah, so once our experiment is complete
for latency, you can see that the metrics
are getting back to their original state.
So this will also help us give the
confidence that our application is healing
from that network latency event 30.
Okay, now let's go back to the
black hole experiment template and
start that, then give it a name,
then start the experiment.
So as we saw earlier, it's going to go
through a couple of phases, and, perform
the actions that we have specified.
And it's going to still target
those couple of ECS tasks that
are running our application code.
So we'll give this experiment a minute or
so to, impact these resources and we will
see, what our application behavior is.
So while that's happening, let's look
at the last template here, which follows
a similar construct, which is, in
this case, it is network packet loss.
So let's take a look at the
different parameters for
that particular action here.
So for the packet loss action,
one of the parameters you can
specify is the loss percentage.
So by default it is 7, but
you can, configure that.
And similar to the latency,
you can specify a source.
Where you would want to inject this
network packet loss for and another
important thing that I want to call out
in terms of sources is if let's say your
application is connecting to DynamoDB
or S3 and using them as the storage
layer, then you can just specify that
literal text in the sources And FIS
will kind, do the, IP resolution for
you and then make sure that any traffic
that is going out to DynamoDB and S3
is impacted by this network fault.
You don't have to, provide the IP range
for these services or anything like that.
The resolution of these literal
texts to appropriate IP addresses are
handled behind the scenes by DynamoDB.
And, like we did here, you can specify a
domain name of, let's say, a third party.
Let's say you have a dependency, an
application dependency that is on
premise or running elsewhere other
than AWS, maybe a SaaS product.
Then you can specify the
domain name of those.
end points of those dependencies that
your application might be communicating,
through APIs and add that here.
So what that would do is then,
inject latency or packet loss
into that particular network path.
So that will help you test and
validate, any potential network
faults that can happen with those
third party dependencies as well.
So let me cancel out the packet loss
experiment template and let's see
where our black hole experiment is.
Oh, okay.
let's see where the, experiment status.
I'm going to go refresh
the, dashboard here.
Oh, so now you can see that in the
event of this particular experiment,
We are seeing errors both from a user
perspective and from a system perspective.
API gateway is throwing 500 errors
and the End user in case in our case
artillery is actually seeing timeouts
So this was not the behavior that we
expected right, we were expecting that
in this case our Application will handle
that timeout that net black hole between
our compute layer and database layer
And return an appropriate error code or
error message or something like that.
So this is an important observation of
the application behavior that we want to
go back to the drawing board and correct.
So those are the two things, two network
faults that I wanted to show you today.
So we had a sample API application that
was performing, CRUD actions and we saw
the behavior of that application when
we injected network latency as well as
network black hole into that workload.
So with respect to latency, we
did see a spike in the average
latency and the P nine D value.
For that API endpoint, you would have
to take a look and see, if those metrics
are within the acceptable threshold.
And then in case of black hole, we do need
to do some work with our application to
identify that event and return appropriate
error messages to the end users.
So again, thank you for your time.
really had fun talking
about this topic with you.
Have a good rest of the day.