Hi, my name is Shanu Sahadevan, and
in this talk, Maximizing Android App
Efficiency, Proven Techniques for
Seamless Performance Across Devices,
I will share practical tips and proven
methods to help you make your Android
app run faster, use less battery,
and work smoothly on all devices.
Jetpack Compose and efficient
layout strategies can significantly
boost performance, reduce lag,
and enhance user experience.
Jetpack Compose simplifies UI development
with a declarative approach, making
code cleaner and easier to maintain.
It optimizes UI updates by
recomposing only necessary
parts, improving responsiveness.
It also reduces memory usage and
recompositions significantly,
ensuring smoother performance.
With built in state management,
Compose delivers high frame
rates and fluid user experience.
Deep layouts slow down the rendering.
By increasing CPU and GPU.
Workload ing view can cut rendering
times significantly, making the
uua faster and more responsive.
Efficient resource management helps
reduce app size and speed up loading
times for a better user experience.
Converting PNG and JPG majors
to cut file size by up to 55
percentage without losing quality.
This reduces APK size, improves download
speed, and saves storage with real world
cases, showing up to 3MB reduction.
Lazy loading defers non
essential resources, cutting
initial load times by 40%.
By loading images and heavy UI
components only when needed, apps achieve
faster first page render, improving
performance on mid range devices.
Optimizing app size ensures
faster downloads, lower storage
use, and better performance.
Android app bundles reduce APK
size by up to 35 percent by
delivering only the necessary code
and resources for each device.
This results in faster downloads,
lower storage use, and higher
installation success rates.
ProGuard removes unused code,
reducing app size by up to 90%.
It also optimizes bytecode,
enhancing security and
improving runtime performance.
Efficient memory management prevents
leaks and keeps apps running smoothly.
Using SparseArray instead of
HashMap reduces memory usage by 50
percent by avoiding auto boxing.
It's especially effective
for large collections.
Weak references help prevent memory
leaks by allowing cached objects to
be garbage collected when needed.
This reduces out of memory
errors by up to 40 percent in
production, improving app stability.
Optimizing network usage
reduces data consumption and
improves app responsiveness.
Retrofits built in caching cuts
network requests and reduces
API response times from 2.
5 seconds to 0.
3 seconds.
By reusing valued responses,
apps stay responsive and
even with poor connectivity.
OKHTTP caching with custom
interceptors lower data usage
and enable offline access.
A well configured disk cache balance
performance and storage efficiently.
When it comes to threading, efficient
multi threading keeps apps responsive
and smooth during background tasks.
Call in coroutines reduce UI thread
blocking, ensuring smooth animations,
and trends responsiveness during
network calls and image processing.
Also using Room Database with suspended
functions boosts data operation
efficiency, enabling seamless pagination,
real time updates, and offline
caching without affecting frame rates.
Optimizing battery usage helps extend
device life and improve user experience.
Smart week log management cuts battery
drain and ensuring background process
don't keep device awake unnecessarily.
Also, batching network requests
and deferring tasks to ideal
periods reduce CPU wake up time.
Using job scheduler and work
manager ensures tasks run only
when charging or on Wi Fi.
Android Studio Profiler helps identify
and fix performance bottlenecks
for a smoother app experience.
Track real time CPU usage, memory
allocation, and thread activity
to detect performance issues.
Use CPU sampling, heap dumps,
and network analysis to find
bottlenecks across different devices.
Apply Profiler Insights can cut
app load times by 40 percent
and reduce memory usage by 30%.
By implementing the techniques
discussed in this presentation,
you can significantly improve the
performance of your Android apps.
This leads to enhancing user
satisfaction to a great level.
Thank you all for
watching my presentation.