Hello everyone, my name is Lourduma
Reddy Thirumal Reddy and I'm SAP
Basics and HANA Administrator
with over 17 years of experience.
I am excited to welcome
you all to this session.
Today I will be talking about
the introduction and benefits
of running mission critical SAP
workloads on Microsoft Azure Cloud.
This presentation explores
the transformative
integration of SAP workloads.
with the Microsoft Azure Cloud Platform.
We will demonstrate how enterprises
can achieve significant cost
savings while maintaining more
than 19 percent of availability for
mission critical SAP applications.
Leveraging Azure's extensive
portfolio of critical solutions.
Here we are going to see the
main advantages of running
SAP workloads on Azure.
The first one is cost reduction Transform
your IT budget with Azure's intelligent
cost optimization, delivering up to 60
percent savings on operational expenses.
Our pay as you go model eliminates
over provisioning while automated
resource management ensures maximum
efficiency across your SAP landscape.
The next one is high availability.
Safeguard your mission
critical operations.
With Azure's enterprise grade
infrastructure generating more than
99 percent uptime through redundant
data centers, availability zones,
automation failover, and advanced
disaster recovery capabilities.
Our globally distributed network
ensures your SAP applications
remain accessible 24 7.
Here we will go through a
comprehensive ecosystem.
for diverse SAP workloads.
The first one is SAP HANA.
Accelerate your analytics up to 100 times
faster while reducing data footprint
by 98 percent while Azure's optimized
infrastructure for SAP HANA workloads.
Mainly M series VMs, which are
designed specially for memory
intensive applications like SAP HANA.
SAP HANA The next one is
SAP NetWeaver applications.
Transform your business operations by
seamlessly integrating ERP, SCM, CRM, and
other business suite applications with
Azure's certified infrastructure, ensuring
more than 99 percent availability.
The third one is S4 HANA.
Future proof your enterprise
with real time analytics.
AI powered automation and intelligent
process optimization while reducing
TCO by up to 45 40 percent on Azure.
Here we'll go through some
real world success stories
transforming SAP deployments.
Accelerated time to value.
Organizations achieve 40 percent
faster deployment times with Azure's
pre configured SAP solutions.
Reducing implementation from months
to weeks while cutting project cost
up to 2 million annually based on
customer's infrastructure size.
Enhanced business performance.
Companies report 75 percent improvement
in system performance, enabling real
time analytics processing of more than
100 TB datasets and supporting 100, 000
concurrent users With sub second response
times here, we'll see how sap workloads,
seamlessly integrate integration
Integrate with microsoft services.
The first one is microsoft infra
id Shenton security and simplify
access management With the single
sign on capabilities across your
SAP ecosystem, reduce IT overhead
while ensuring compliance through
centralized identity governance.
The next one is Power Platform.
Empower your teams to build custom
solutions without extensive coding.
Create interactive dashboards, automate
workflows, and develop mobile apps That
seamlessly connect with your SAP data.
The next one is Azure
Integration Services.
Connect your SAP systems with over
1, 000 enterprise applications
through pre built connectors.
Streamline business processes and
enable real time data synchronization
while maintaining data integrity.
And we'll see how can we do
scalability and flexibility for
growing business day by day.
Scale your SAP environments dynamically
with Azure's Elastic Infrastructure,
supporting growth from 50 to 50,
000 users while maintaining sub
millisecond response times and
more than 99 percent availability.
The second one is leverage
Azure's consumption based pricing.
To reduce infrastructure cost by up
to 40 percent With automated scaling
that optimizes resources based on real
time demand patterns this, automated
scaling will be helpful when a month
in process running or year in process
running when We need more cpu and
memory resources the Third one is
future proof your sap landscape With
instant access to enterprise grade
compute resources allowing you to
add New workloads or expand existing
ones in minute instead of months.
Now we can see What are
the options related to?
security and compliance enterprise grade
security and compliance achieve global
compliance with azure's comprehensive
certification portfolio spanning You
More than 90 regulatory standards,
including GDPR, HIPAA, and SOC 2,
Type 2, enabling seamless operations
across international market while
maintaining secure data sovereignty.
Protect your SAP workloads with Azure's
military grade security infrastructure.
Featuring 256 bit end to end encryption,
biometric authentication systems,
and real time threat monitoring
powered by AI driven analytics.
The third one is, strengthen your
security postures with Azure Security
Center's integrated tools, including
automated security assessments,
continuous compliance monitoring,
and advanced threat protection that
blocks, Over 99 percent of cyberattacks
before they reach your SAP systems.
Here we see the joint partnership
program between Microsoft and SAP.
The first one is joint innovation
achieved by collaborative development
of cutting edge cloud solutions
and AI powered enterprises tools.
Next one is certified solutions.
Rigorously tested and
validated architectures.
Ensuring optimal performance.
The next one is best practices.
Comprehensive guidelines from thousands
of successful implementations.
The last one is, achieving customer
success, dedicated support teams,
and proven migration frameworks.
Our 25 plus years of strategic
partnership with SAP combines
Microsoft's cloud leadership
with SAP's enterprise expertise.
This collaboration has resulted in
certified solutions that power over
90 percent of Fortune 500 companies.
SAP Cloud.
Delivering unmatched
reliability and performance
for mission critical workloads.
Through continuous innovation and
joint development efforts, we provide
organizations with a trusted path
to digital transformation while
reducing implementation risks
and accelerating time to value.
Here we see TCO, Total Cost
of Ownership Optimization.
The first one is reduced infrastructure
cost by cut down hardware and maintenance
expenses by up to 60 percentage
through Azure's pay as you go model.
The next one is optimized licensing cost.
Save 30 to 40% on software
licensing with Azure Hybrid
benefit and consolidated billing.
Third one is lower operational expenses.
You can achieve by decrease operational
cost by 30 percent through automated
management and simplified, IT workflows.
Transform your SAP landscape
economics with Azure's intelligent
cost optimization solutions.
Delivering an average 45 percent reduction
in TCO through automated resource scaling.
Simplified management and
integrated cost controls.
Our customers typically achieve
complete ROI within 18 months
while maintaining enterprise
grade performance and reliability.
Here we will go through some key
takeaways modernizing your SAP landscape.
Cost reduction up to 60 percent
Achieve significant savings through
optimized infrastructure and operational
efficiency Availability more than
99 percent Enterprise grade uptime
with redundant systems and automatic
failover and disaster recovery.
Faster deployment, more than 40%.
Accelerate implementation
with pre configured templates
and automation technologies.
And performance improvement more than 75%.
Enhance system responsiveness through
Azure's optimized infrastructure.
Here, we'll go how to empower
your digital transformation.
The first one is cloud strategy.
Create a tailored cloud
roadmap that maximizes ROI.
Incorporating your existing SAP
investments and future scalability needs.
Align technical capabilities
with specific business outcomes.
The next one is migration plan.
Build a detailed implementation
timeline with clear milestones.
risk mitigation strategies and resource
allocation plans include testing
protocols and business continuity
measures throughout the transition.
Thank you everyone for
joining the session.
Hope you enjoyed this session.