Hello everyone.
Welcome to real time personalization
at scale, neural ranking systems
and operational breakthroughs.
I'm Vedant Agarwal, Senior Software
Engineer working in Search.
Today, I will share how advanced neural
ranking systems enable personalized
recommendations to drive both operational
efficiency and real business impact.
In this session, our agenda is
organized on around several key topics.
First, we will cover our breakthroughs
in ranking, which includes both candidate
generation and precision re ranking.
Next, we will address latency
challenges, discussing how we can
achieve sub 50 millisecond response
times, which is a crucial factor for
ensuring a smooth user experience.
We will then explore the real time
constraints of processing millions
of interactions concurrently.
And finally, we will review the
business impact of these solutions
and look at emerging trends that
will shape future initiatives.
This overview is meant to
provide you with a clear roadmap
for the presentation ahead.
Real time personalization introduces
several technical challenges.
First, data inconsistencies and noise
are common, as user clickstreams and
transaction logs often contain variability
that can affect model accuracy.
Second, scaling becomes a critical
concern when processing millions
of concurrent interactions while
maintaining system responsiveness.
Third, model drift poses an ongoing
issue As user behavior evolves,
consider, for example, a sudden shift
in seasonal trends, our models must
adapt quickly to maintain relevance.
These challenges underscore the
need for agile and robust solutions
capable of processing high volume,
real time data effectively.
To overcome these challenges,
there is something as a two tier
neural ranking architecture.
The first tier, L1, focuses on candidate
generation using embedding based indexing.
Here, user behaviors and item attributes
are projected into a shared high
dimensional space, allowing for rapid
filtering of a vast number of items.
The second tier, L2, handles
precision re ranking using advanced
sequence modeling techniques.
such as LSTMs or transformers
to integrate both historical
data and real time signals.
This decoupled approach enables
us to optimize speed in the first
stage while ensuring that the final
recommendations are highly personalized.
For example, while L1 may retrieve a
broad set of items from a database of
over a million entities in a matter of
milliseconds, L2 refines this set to match
the user's current context accurately.
In our L1 candidate generation process,
we achieve significant performance
gains through embedding based indexing.
This method projects both user
behavior and item characteristics
into a shared feature space,
allowing us to employ approximate
nearest neighbor search technique.
For instance, our system can retrieve a
broad set of relevant candidate items in
under 10 milliseconds, even when querying
a corpus of more than a million items.
This rapid pre filtering is crucial as
it reduces the computational load for
the L2 ranking stage, ensuring that The
system remains both fast and scalable.
The efficiency of L1 is a foundational
operational breakthrough that enables
us to deliver highly responsive
and personalized recommendations.
Now, we move on to L2 stage, which
focuses on precision re ranking.
In this layer, we employ advanced sequence
modeling techniques using models such
as transformers or LSTMs to capture the
sequential dependencies in user data.
Music playing This approach allows
us to integrate both real time
session information and long
term user history effectively.
For example, by incorporating attention
mechanisms, the system can assign
higher weight to recent clicks compared
to older ones, ensuring that the most
relevant signals are prioritized.
This dynamic re ranking process, which
adjusts in real time to the user's
context, can lead to a significant
improvement in recommendation accuracy,
with an observed increase in click
through rates by approximately
20 percent as shown in studies.
Next, let us discuss latency
breakthroughs, and how we can
handle real time constraints.
The latest systems are engineered to
achieve sub 50 millisecond end to end
processing response times, ensuring
a fast result generation from user
action to recommendation delivery.
We can balance the inherent complexity
of our models with the need for
quick inference By simplifying
certain architectural components
without sacrificing quality, for
instance, by implementing optimized
inference pipelines with asynchronous
processing and caching strategies,
we can reduce latency from around 70
milliseconds down to 45 milliseconds.
Additionally, system scales
dynamically under load.
Thanks to auto scaling and load balancing,
which are continuously monitored in real
time to maintain consistent performance
at the heart of operations lies a
robust infrastructure and dynamic
feature engineering process, we can
utilize real time data pipelines.
Employing tools like Kafka and Apache
Flink to continuously ingest user
clicks and purchase data, ensuring that
our models receive instant updates.
Microservices architectures containerized
using Docker and orchestrated by
Kubernetes can enable us to maintain
modular scalability and fault isolation.
In parallel, feature engineering process
dynamic It generates features from
live data, such as current session
attributes, and applies advanced
transformations like normalization,
feature crosses, and depend meetings.
Observability can be maintained through
tools like Prometheus and Grafana, which
provide automated alerts to detect and
address performance anomalies promptly.
Going on to the next slide,
deploying and updating the
system seamlessly is critical.
Which is why we can have
robust deployment strategies.
We can maintain regular monitoring through
defined KPIs and automated anomaly alerts
to catch performance deviations early.
Automated retraining sessions can
be scheduled to address model drift,
ensuring that our models remain up
to date with evolving user behavior.
Our deployment processes, including
blue green deployments and rolling
updates can help us achieve zero
done down times during rollouts.
For example, we often can use canary
releases via Kubernetes to safely test
new updates before a full rollout.
Additionally, A B testing allows
us to gradually roll out features
and assess their real time impact
with these pipelines, tightly
integrated with our CI CD tools.
Finally, let's consider the
business impact of these operational
breakthroughs by refining ranking
accuracy and reducing latency.
We can directly improve the matching
of products to user intent, which in
turn can increase conversion rates.
Personalized recommendations have
also led to enhanced user engagement
reflected in longer sessions and
improved click through rates.
In practice, we have observed
quantifiable outcomes such as 15
percent increase in conversion
rates and a 25 percent improvement
in CTR in these different studies.
These metrics are tracked through
integrated analytics dashboards
that we can continuously
monitor and adjust our business
strategies to meet our objectives.
This is where the technical
part of the presentation ends.
But looking ahead, we can focus on
several emerging trends that will shape
the next generation of personalization.
One of these trends is multimodal
personalization, where we
integrate text, image, and video
data to gain richer insights.
For example, by combining visual cues
from product images with descriptive
text, our system can be made, can
make more nuanced, Recommendations.
We can also explore real time federated
learning, a decentralized approach
to model training that not only
enhances privacy, but also reduces
latency by keeping data local.
Additionally, we can enhance our
neural ranking by adopting next
generation deep learning models
to push accuracy even further.
Hybrid approaches are under
investigation as well, where rule
based systems are combined with AI.
offering improved interpretability
without sacrificing performance.
The long term vision should be to
continuously adapt to market trends
and evolving user behaviors supported
by ongoing R& D aimed at integrating
state of the art model architectures.
In conclusion, Today, we have
reviewed operational breakthroughs
in real time personalization.
We discussed how ranking innovations,
both the rapid candidate generation in
L1 and precision ranking in L2, work
together with latency optimizations
and real time scalability to produce
a robust recommendation system.
These technical improvements have
translated into measurable business
outcomes such as improved conversion
rates, higher user engagement,
and better customer retention.
As we look to the future, emerging
trends and next generation
personalization initiatives will
continue to drive our evolution.
Finally, thank you for joining
me on this presentation.
Feel free to connect with me on LinkedIn.