Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Con 42, Chaos
Engineering 2025 Conference.
I am Sandeep Batu, and I bring over a
decade of experience in building and
securing cloud and hybrid platforms.
I will be discussing about the
cloud security strategies in
an era of evolving threats.
Let's talk about how the digital
landscape is rapidly changing with
the cloud adoption, and, where.
Things are, where cyber attacks
are becoming increasingly
sophisticated as well.
So traditional parameter based
security is no longer enough to protect
organizations from these evolving threats.
Coming to the aspects of the cloud
security, let's talk about how
the accelerated cloud adoption is
transforming the industry where
94 percent of the enterprises have
embraced these cloud services.
which is an historic shift
in how business operates.
So industry analysts predict that by
2025, over 75 percent of the enterprise
workloads will reside in the cloud,
representing a transformation which
demands an equally dramatic evolution
in the, in how the security approaches.
And how the rising cyber
attacks is changing.
The industry.
So as the rapid cloud adoption
has created and expanded.
Attack surface, organizations are
now facing an alarming rate of, huge
cyber attacks daily, where we can
say that, there is almost an, every
attack for every 39 seconds, these are
not just simple breaches, but these
are like sophisticated multi vector
attacks, which can cost companies, huge
millions, for every incident out there.
So making Robo's cloud security
is not just important, but
also it's business critical.
So let's talk about The
shift towards the Zero Trust.
Zero Trust.
What exactly is Zero Trust principle?
implementing continuous verifications
for every user, device, and application
regardless of location, right?
So this is almost like never trust
and always verify approach where it
requires multi factor authentication,
real time monitoring, and granular
access control across all the resources.
And the next is the
reduced security incidents.
Organizations are implementing zero
trust organi Organizations implementing
zero trust architectures have witnessed,
dramatic 60 percent reduction in security
incidents, which includes preventing
unauthorized access attempts, detecting
insider threats, and Early, and also
minimizing the impact of PO potential
breaches through some of the micro
segments, strategies by implementing
net, network access controls or VPNs.
Next, let's talk about how the
identity access management is
helping some of these concerns.
One, by leveraging the advanced IAM
policies, where we deploy granular access
control with role based permissions.
and also leveraging the just in time
access, and also the automated privilege
management to create robust security
parameters around the critical assets.
And the next is the multi
factor authentication.
So implementing sophisticated multi
factor authentication, which includes
combining of like biometrics or
hardware tokens or time based codes.
So organizations using this multi
factor authentication reports that, 99
percent of fewer account compromises.
And also 67 percent of, reduction in
the breaches, which is pretty huge.
Next, let's talk about the leveraging
AI and machine learning for these
threat detections, accelerated threat
detection, where we'll talk about
how the advanced AI and ML powered
security tools enable organizations
to identify and respond to threats
50 times faster than the traditional.
manual methods.
analyzing millions of data points
in real time to spot potential
breaches before they occur.
And, talking about intellect,
intelligent behavior analytics.
some of this sophisticated behavior
analytics and pattern recognition,
helps in achieving, around like 76
percent reduction in false positives.
So allowing security teams to
focus on genuine threats while
maintaining the operational
efficiency will help organizations.
focus on the real threats.
Next we can talk about the
quantum resistant encryption
and blockchain technologies.
implementing some of the quantum resistant
encryption, which mostly focus about the
post quantum cryptographic algorithms,
which can withstand attacks from
both classical and quantum computers.
So these cryptographic algorithms helps
organizations in securing themselves.
So some of the advanced encryption
methods like lattice based or hash
based cryptographies, which helps
in ensuring that the data remains
secure even as, quantum computing
capability, capabilities evolve.
Next, we can also leverage the.
Blockchain technology.
So leveraging the distributed ledger
technology to create a tamper proof
audit trails and smart contracts for
all these automated security protocols,
which helps in decentralized approach,
ensuring that 99 percent of the uptime
of the resources and also or reduce
a single point of failure and then
provides cryptographic proof of data
integrity across the cloud environments.
If we are looking at the micro
segmentation, and so all the
securities right, so coming to the
micro segmentation, We can transform
the network security by creating
granular and isolated segments,
which can reduce the attack surface.
So this is almost like a zero trust
approach, which contains, breaches
and enables, precise access control,
and also cuts lateral movements of
the risk by implementing security
policies at the workload level.
And we can also leverage
the serverless security.
So which uses a native security
features in serverless architectures
to achieve both agility and protection.
So the function level isolation,
automated scalings, and also the event
driven security controls, all these
create a dynamic defense systems, which
eliminates most of the traditional
infrastructure vulnerabilities.
And also we can leverage the continuous
compliance automation, right?
We can implement automated
compliance check.
which streamlines the regulatory,
through the continuous monitoring
systems, which can scan, validate,
and document compliance requirements
in real time, and also reducing the
manual audit preparation, almost by
ensuring there is a 99 percent accuracy.
And the second is the real time risk
assessment, Deploy AI powered REST
detection systems, which analyze
compliance patterns across the
regulatory framework, which enables
organizations to identify and address
potential violations, even before,
things happen with these audits.
Next is a cost optimization, achieving
a significant ROI through all this
automated compliance process, which helps
enterprises savings, huge amounts annually
through the reduced manual effort,
fewer penalties and also optimized,
optimizing the resource allocation.
And coming to the industry best
practices and case studies, some of
the real world examples which dive
into the detailed case studies from the
fortune 500 companies, which achieved
99 percent security compliance through
cloud native security implementations.
which includes the financial institutions
which, which reduce the breach and
also some of the healthcare providers
which enhance the data protection
while improving the access speeds.
And some of the experts in the industry
says with the help of these strategies.
A lot of knowledge has been gained
and also security architects at
the leading tech companies have
successfully defended and against these
sophisticated cyber attacks as well.
And also some of these proven
threat detection models.
Helps in incident response
and also security architecture
which can immediately apply
to most of the organizations.
So some of the key takeaways and
also the actionable insights from
all these cloud security strategies
is one, implement the zero trust.
So transform your security posture by
adopting the zero trust architecture,
which reduces the breach by 60 percent
through continuous verification of
every user device and connection.
Second, how we can modernize the identity
controls, implementing the robust
identity access management frameworks with
biometrics, multi factor authentications,
which reduces the unauthorized access
by 99%, and also enhances the user
experience, around the MFA process itself.
And the next is, how we can
accelerate, with leveraging some
of the AI and ML algorithms.
So deploying the intelligent threat
detection, which are powered by AI or
ML to identify threats faster and also
reducing the false positive, which
enables the rapid incidence response.
around the real threats.
How we can secure the future using
the collaborative approach, right?
In, building the secure future
together is one of the core
principles for every organization.
So in today's interconnected
digital landscape, collaboration
and information sharing between
the organizations have become the
cornerstone for effective cyber security.
So we have to foster these partnerships
between the private enterprises and some
of the security researchers and also
we can create more resilient defense
against the sophisticated cyber threats.
So through shade intelligence coordinating
the how the incident response should
happen and also the collaborative
innovations we can build more secure
digital ecosystem for everyone.
Thanks for your time.