It's absolutely fantastic
to be here at Con 42 2025.
Thanks for taking the
time to join the session.
Today we're diving into a topic that
challenges traditional thinking about
reliability, which is the chaos first
mindset and not like laying back
and not being proactive about it.
So buckle up because it's going
to be fun and exciting ride
into proactive resilience.
So a little bit about me.
My name is Shahid.
I am a senior software engineer
at Harness and also the maintainer
and community manager at Litmus.
from time to time I also work
as an LFX mentor for the Linux
Foundation programs for Litmus Chaos.
So that's about me.
So what's the game plan for today?
We're going to start with a discussion
on internal developer platforms, IDP.
Why they're gaining so much
traction and why they matter.
then we'll move into the biggest challenge
in cloud native development, reliability.
The very thing we built our systems
for, yet struggle with so much.
From there, we'll introduce chaos
engineering, talk about the chaos first
principle and explore how it plays a
crucial role in platform engineering
We'll also see some of the tools And
a hands on demo as well, which we
intentionally have kept to break things
and on purpose And finally we'll discuss
the future where this space is heading
and how you can integrate chaos into
your own platform journey So let's go.
Before we jump into that, let's take a
step back and talk about what's really
happening in Cognitive Development.
Now, today, it's fast, it's dynamic,
and it's constantly evolving.
We've got CICD pipelines, DevOps, SecOps,
Configuration Management, Observability,
Analytics, and the list keeps growing.
And yet, despite all these
advancements, one problem still remains.
That failure is inevitable.
The more we distribute our systems,
the more dependencies we introduce and
the harder it becomes to predict what
will break and when there are a couple
of things, which I'll talk about later
as well, but there are things like.
cascading failures or failures due to
complicated architecture now imagine an
authentication service going down Suddenly
the payment systems user dashboards
and even notifications stop working
right because they're all dependent.
They're all dependent on it So this is
called a cascading failure and is a huge
problem in cloud native system In fact,
80 percent of cloud native applications
experience downtimes due to such issues
And, also instead of one big application,
we now have hundreds of tiny services
running across multiple clusters, which
talk to each other over networks, depend
on APIs, rely on different data stores.
And if something fails, figuring
out where, what, and where
can be incredibly difficult.
there's unpredictability,
and, unpredictability is the
default today, unfortunately.
containers can crash, nodes can go
offline, there could be network issues,
and, Everything is always changing.
So how do we build resilience
in such an unpredictable world?
The reality is failure is
no longer an exception.
It is a given.
And the question isn't how
do we prevent failures?
Rather, how do we prepare for them?
So that's where we start
shifting our mindsets.
Now let's talk about internal
developer platforms or IDPs.
These platforms are designed to
streamline developer experience,
enabling teams to deploy and manage
applications with minimal friction.
Think of them as self service
portals where developers can request
infrastructure, manage deployments,
and ensure governance without needing
to interact with multiple teams.
But here's the challenge.
IDPs work great when
everything is running smoothly.
The moment something breaks,
things can spiral out of control.
That's why integrating chaos
testing into IDP is critical.
It ensures that failures do not
just get handled after they happen,
but are proactively addressed.
Let's zoom in on the real issue,
which is cloud native complexity,
which I talked about before.
We have moved from monolith to
microservices, and while that's great
for flexibility, it also introduces
a massive reliability challenge.
Your code doesn't exist
in isolations anymore.
It's running on a web of interconnected
services, APIs, databases, third
party dependencies, and so on.
The problem is, when one thing fails,
it can trigger a domino effect.
And in cloud native world, these
failures are happening all the time.
So instead of just hoping for the
best, we need a new approach, one
that assumes failure from the starts
and prepare for it proactively.
Let's compare old school DevOps with
today's cloud native reliability.
Back then, we built a single application,
deployed it in maybe once a quarter
and had time to test things out.
Fast forward to today, we are deploying 10
times as many microservices at a lightning
speed across hundreds of environments.
And with all this complexity,
we have to ensure reliability.
So how do we even do that?
Traditional monitoring and
incident response aren't
really enough for us anymore.
And, we need to inject.
Chaos deliberately test failure scenarios
in real time and make resilience
an active part of our development
process Now outages are expensive.
They lead to financial loss reputational
damage frustrated users and whatnot
Some of the biggest tech giants have
experienced massive failures due to these
different type of issues And sometimes the
problem isn't even the application itself.
It could be Bad code unhandled edge
cases or even unexpected system load
there could be a series of cascading
failures, that can take down systems.
For example, a similar event happened
with Slack, where it impacted
thousands of businesses worldwide.
And during the incidents, during, whenever
incidents happen, service often lock too
much data or retry too aggressively, which
sort of overloads the system even more.
And this sort of results in users unable
to access the services, leading to all
this drop in trust and frustration.
Even with cloud providers and
Kubernetes, infrastructure is
never 100 percent reliable.
You could have device failures like
hard drives crashing, power supply
fail, or memory leaks building up.
And, a financial company recently lost
over, 55 million because of the failure
in one part of their infrastructure that
prevented transactions from processing.
Sometimes, it's not code or
hardware, but how we handle these
incidents making things much worse.
if auto scaling is not configured
properly, let's say, then service
crashing would not be even detected.
If teams do not have right alerts,
they don't even know sometimes
when something has gone wrong
until the user starts complaining.
Having an active channel of alerts or
having a good way around how you can
handle incidents is also something
that can trigger these things.
So what exactly is chaos engineering?
At its core, it's about
running control experiment to
simulate real world failures.
And you already know it because
you're in con 42 in chaos engineering.
So we're not going to spend too much
time on what is chaos engineering.
Rather, we'll talk about
the principles later.
So instead of waiting for a real outage to
happen, we just introduce feel a failure
ourselves and measure the impact and then
we learn how to recover quickly, right?
So that is our goal to build
something, build confidence in
our system and want our systems to
withstand unexpected disruptions.
Now, here's the big idea, the chaos
for the chaos first principle.
So instead of.
So instead of treating failures as real
anomalies, we assume they're inevitable.
And instead of reacting to failures,
we prepare for them up front.
By injecting chaos early and often,
we make resilience a core part of
our platform engineering process.
And this means fewer surprises,
faster recovery, and much
more reliable system overall.
Platform engineers are the backbone
of reliability in modern system.
But let's be honest, no matter
how well you design a platform,
unexpected failures will still happen.
Microsoft that's why chaos engineering
is a must have in platform engineering,
as it allows us to test system
behavior under failure conditions,
uncover hidden weaknesses, and also
continuously improve, our reliability
postures through all these different
components that you see right now.
Chaos engineering is not just a
testing practice, it's a mindset shift.
And by running chaos experiments, platform
engineers gain real insights into how
their system behaves under stress,
Now imagine deploying a new feature.
Wouldn't it be great to know how it would
react to database failures or network
latencies or certain spikes in traffic?
Now chaos engineering helps uncover
these weaknesses spot weak spots early.
With proactive resilience, we
can identify system bottlenecks
before they impact users.
We can improve incident response time
with well tested failure scenarios.
We can also ensure that our infrastructure
self heals and recovers efficiently.
This leads to more self sustaining
platform, actually, that can
handle real world uncertainty.
And whenever we are using IDPs
or platform engineering, we
are already thinking about it.
This is just, One more step down
the layer, one more addition to
what you're already thinking of.
Now, there are some fantastic
tools out there that can make
chaos engineering accessible.
Litmus Chaos, for example, is an open
source framework designed for cloud
native chaos engineering and Backstage,
on the other hand, helps organize
developer workflows really well.
Combined, these tools make it easier
than ever to adopt a chaos first mindset.
The future is fully automated, AI
driven chaos experiments that integrate
seamlessly into the development
lifecycle and so on and so forth.
but we're heading towards a world
where chaos testing isn't really
an afterthought rather It's like
a built in part of every platform.
So these are some of the tools we have
narrowed down to but it's an Not really
an exhaustive list and you can pick any
tools which sort of adhere to this goal
But for this presentation i'm going
to show litmus chaos and backstage
together Now before we jump into how
you can use these tools I want to talk
about the vision what we plan to do.
What is the ultimate goal of it?
So to truly integrate chaos into
platform engineering, we envision
a structured journey built
around the key, four key pillars.
Define and execute chaos experiments.
The foundational step is to
define chaos experiments that fit
your specific application needs.
This means identifying appropriate
failure scenarios based on your
infrastructure, whether it could be
cloud native, legacy, Linux based,
Windows, or even mainframe applications.
Initially, these experiments may be
executed manually to gain insights
into potential failure points,
but later they can be automated.
Chaos as a service.
The next step is to make chaos
engineering self serviceable.
By enabling chaos as a service,
teams can easily apply and disable
chaos experiments on demand.
This reduces friction, makes it
easy for application teams to
integrate chaos into their workflows.
And this helps greatly when people
are using platform, platform tools.
Automate chaos in CI CD pipeline.
Once chaos experiments are well
defined and serviceable, the
focus shifts to automation.
The goal is to integrate chaos
engineering into CICD pipelines as
well, which allows failures to be
tested with every release that we do.
Now with a push of a button, teams
can trigger chaos experiments and
validate the system resilience
before production or deployment.
Lastly, we enable observability
and automated chaos evaluation.
we already know observability is key
when we want to track certain metrics.
To understand the impact of chaos.
And before we jump in a quick mention
to Namtu, who is a maintainer who
helped with the litmus plugin for
backstage, which was just introduced
and, is working great for us.
Thanks.
Now it's demo time.
So let me explain the different,
three different aspects of this demo.
So we have the app configuration.
we have the entities, YAML, and
then we have a small Jeff, which
is showing you how it works.
So the app configuration YAML is where
you configure the target, which would
be your litmus URL, where litmus is
deployed for you, which would also require
a litmus authentication token, which
you have to export locally or in your
cloud provider so that it can access,
it can bypass, or it can authenticate
itself with litmus so that it can help
you with the chaos engineering flows.
I'll talk about how you can
get this auth code later.
and once you've done that, you go to
the entities YAML in backstage, where
you have to paste in an annotation
of the project ID of Litmus Kiosk.
So you can copy your project ID that
you're currently in, in Litmus, and
you can paste that for backstage
to understand which project you're
using to run your Kiosk applications.
So I'll show all of this
in a demo right next.
but there's other two, configuration YAML
that we need to modify and you see a small
GIF, which is showing you how things look
in the backstage and how you can go to
the actual workflows and check it out.
So with that, let's get started.
All right.
So this is our backstage plugin.
The URL is just litmus.
com slash backstage plugin repo.
You can either clone this repo or if
you already have your own repository.
You can add this package in
your web folder or like in your
application and then just modify the
entities And the app config file.
So with that, I think that should be
good enough But let me also go back
to visual code and show you the same
So you would have in your packages in
your app Package json, you would see
this, backstage plugin litmus So you
can use or install this package and with
that you would be able to modify your
entities yaml You And you would also
be able to modify your app config file.
So once you do that, we will quickly see
how we can modify this or create this
litmus auth token, and then use it or
export it and put in your external IP or
your IP of the, wherever litmus is hosted.
And then in the entities, you
can just put in your project
ID from your project as well.
So we have litmus deployed already.
So this is our litmus instance.
So we're in the LitmusCurse
portal right now.
So once you're in the portal, you
would see the admin or whichever
user you're logged in as setting.
So go to the account setting.
Once you do that, you will see
there's a API token section.
So from here, you can create a new token.
Once you create a token, you
can choose the TTL and you can
also give it to no expiration.
And then once you enter it, you will
be seeing the token created along
with the specific value of the token.
So feel free to.
copy that value and whenever you are
exporting or using the backstage app
Or like hosting the backstage app or
wherever you want to use it Just put
this litmus auth token this exact key
And export it with that value with
the key value that you just copied So
once you do that, you should be able
to authorize your litmus instance with
the backstage And we have a backstage
as well also running on the local port.
So it is localhost 3000 where Backstage
is running And since I have installed
the package, it's also showing me the
backstage litmus demo, which is configured
now for any reason, if you are new and
you want to get started with it, you
can follow our follow along tutorial
as well from docs or litmus kiosk.
io.
It explains in detail how you can
set up potato hair or this demo
application or any other queries you
have about might have about litmus.
So you can feel free to go
to the docs and check it out.
But for now, we'll just focus
on this backstage plugin.
So we already have this project.
Let me go into this component.
This is one configuration
right now because we haven't
done much wider setting.
So we'll see the owner, the system,
the type, the tags and everything.
How many, chaos hubs are there?
How many infras are there?
How many experiments you have run so far?
But let's go to the main one,
which is the litmus tag here.
The other tags you can work together and
build your own IDP solution out of it.
But for now, what we want to
focus on is the litmus tag.
So let's click on that.
You'll see there's a couple of options.
There's experiment docs.
There's the API docs.
We have the hub.
You have the community.
in the hub itself, you would see there's
a litmus chaos sub listed down, which
has different experiments, different
faults and the environment as well.
So if I click on this, it'll
take me straight to the hub.
Which is the repository of all the
different faults available for us to
experiment and play around with or
combine into different scenarios with.
So this is a list of the different
templates and these are the list of
the different faults that you can
use to create your own hypothesis.
So if I go to the generic one, let's
say Kubernetes, you'll see there are
different types of, Faults like power
off, node faults, or docker faults, or.
Pod memory hog or pod specific faults
so you can combine them and create
anything you want to so this is an
instance of litmus Which is pulled
into backstage and you can manage and
everything manage and control everything
from backstage itself for environments
We have backstage n which is again the
infrastructure a chaos infrastructure
where our which is enabled for us So if
I have to just show that to you, if I
just do a kubectl get pods in backstage
and backstage is the namespace where I
have deployed this kiosk infrastructure.
So you would see that we have our
execution plane components running here.
So this will be able to help you.
Execute the kiosk experiment also
detect if your application is present
in this cluster or not And since it
is deployed in a cluster wide access,
so any application demo application
Discoverable within this like present
within this cluster would be discoverable.
So if I just do kubectl get namespace,
you'll see I have a namespace called
demo and in the demo namespace itself
you will see that pot tattoo head,
our demo application is deciding.
If I do this, you will see that there's
a potato hat, potato head, potato main,
potato right, left arm and all that.
So these, this is a demo, application
and it is also in the same cluster scope.
So I'll be able to target this
demo application from, My,
backstage namespace as well.
So since everything is connected,
I'll just close them both and go back.
And I had already run one experiment
of deleting a hat and you can see the
experiments are also showing up here.
So from here itself,
you can see the status.
You can read on this again, or you
can visually like manually go to the.
So if I click on this, I should also
be taken to the same execution details.
And you would see that I have the
potato pod delete application I ran.
And I had a probe which is just doing
a health check if it's running or not.
just doing a health check to the specific
FQDN if it's healthy or not And it
did pass successfully because I was
deleting the hat But if I just had to
rerun this I will just rerun this for
an instant and come back to backstage
reload You'll see that another instance
of this has already started So this
helps greatly when you're just managing
everything from a single portal and for
us backstage would be that portal And
when you're modifying things in litmus
enabling githubs Managing multiple faults
Adding your own personal private hubs.
Everything could be managed right from
within this one single destination.
So this will be a single source from where
you can manage your own, chaos experiment,
experimentation application flow.
So that was what I wanted to showcase,
what I wanted to show to you.
And since this is anyways going to be a
simple pod lead, it will function fine.
If you had Grafana or any other
observability tool added with
Prometheus, you would be also
able to visualize the same.
So with that, I would just like
to finish on showcasing this and
just wanted to put an emphasis
on this backstage litmus plugin.
Now everything is also available as
part of the documentation as well.
So feel free to explore that.
But this is just empowering what
you can do when you have a platform
like backstage or when you have
an open source tool this which can
help integrate into your idp setup.
So let's jump back to the future slides
So what is the future for us now as
chaos engineering continues to evolve?
We must establish best practices
and industry standards So
here's what we envision.
A maturity model for chaos engineering.
So to develop a structured framework to
help organizations assess their current
level of chaos engineering adoption.
Now this model would also ensure
a clear path from beginner to
advanced chaos engineering practices.
And this helps orgs get like an overview
of where they are at and where they
have to go We also want chaos budgeting
and guardrails This would be another
framework which defines the acceptable
levels of disruptions or downtimes
for different components This helps
teams allocate resources effectively
while also ensuring experiments are
conducted safely Now lastly automation
and observability improvements too.
We want to enhance the automated
evaluation of chaos experiments Improve
observability frameworks to integrate
chaos engineering insights into your
own, their own monitoring systems.
So these steps will drive the future of
chaos engineering adoption in platform
engineering as well, specifically
making it essential, an essential
practice for platform engineers.
With that, I'd like to
finish my presentation.
Thanks for attending my talk today.
Here are a few links you can use to
connect with me or explore the project.
And thank you once more
for listening to me.