Good day, everybody, and welcome
to the show, where today I'd like
to talk to you about why people and
not yet another tool hold the key
to success in the tech industry.
So my goal today is to shift your
awareness towards a bit of a more non
technical field, because let's face
it, we're all pretty good at coding.
that alone won't make
you stand out anymore.
So I'd like to talk to you a bit
about the topic of skills beyond
code, which is let's say, So a mix
of soft skills, human skills, and
social hacks in the technical sector.
And, stay tuned, guys, because
you're gonna see that there's a lot
of untapped potential in that area.
let's go.
A short introduction about myself.
My name is Pierre Luigi Meloni, or GG.
And as you can hear from
my name, I'm from, Germany.
Yeah, schnitzel und sauerkraut.
I studied computer science and I made
my master in computer science, and I've
been in the tech industry for more than
20 years already, in the most various
jobs, most of the time in engineering,
and I had the opportunity to work with
very clever and interesting people, and
they taught me a lot, which you're going
to see throughout this presentation.
I am the founder and CEO of other
skills, which is an e learning academy,
especially for, tech specialists,
for the sector of skills beyond code.
when I started out, in my career,
pretty much like you, I guess
I fell in love with coding.
So that was the first thing,
even before I started studying.
And what I always wanted to do is, of
course, I wanted to build cool stuff.
Why not?
I love technology.
To be honest, I also
wanted to have a good time.
Because, I guess everyone of you knows if
you had to earn some money during study,
you had to do the most various jobs.
And I was in factories
and stuff like that.
And, The tech industry was promising.
They had like more comfortable
jobs, let's say it like that.
And of course, I wouldn't go as far
and say that I wanted to change the
world, but at least, I wanted to impact.
I wanted to influence the stuff.
I wanted to, get my ideas
heard and change something.
But then what happens?
You start going to companies,
you arrive in the industry.
And the first thing is you got
to deal with demanding customers.
And sometimes they want to, they
want you to produce stuff that
you really don't agree with.
And you're like, it's really not the best
solution, but you got to do it anyway.
Then you hit hierarchies and politics.
You find out that it's actually not
that easy to get thoughts through
and that stuff, that you got to use
your elbows from time to time even.
And the worst thing of all, you're
actually working with legacy more
often than you would want to.
Actually in our industry, more
of the time you are bug fixing,
maintaining, refactoring stuff instead
of building things from scratch.
And that it's Different than you would
have originally dreamed about the job.
what do you do when you continue
working somehow, like most people do?
You switch your focus.
You think about, okay, then
I want to earn more money.
I want to climb up the ranks.
I want to become a senior faster.
But still, inside of you,
that desire is still there.
You still want to influence
stuff, especially in your team
with the line management, with
the roadmaps and stuff like that.
You want to be heard.
You want your work to be seen.
You want it to be valued.
And most and foremost, at least it was for
me the way I wanted to do things right.
I want to do the right things
and I wanted to do things right.
And the problem in the tech world is
if you don't listen to the experts.
That means if experts do not have the
influence they should have, they're not
really heard and things are not done
right, what happens is technical debt
increases, efficiency of projects goes
down, the complexity rises over the time.
But the problem for us is we got
to work with that on a daily basis.
And the bad thing is if if you have
this feeling that you thought I
knew it before and I knew it better,
but I couldn't get them to believe.
And now we're in that situation and
everybody thinks yeah, it's your problem.
You built it.
And this really was
always a problem for me.
And that got tiring for me.
But then you realize, ah, no, excuse
me, what do you do then is, because
you want to change the situation.
What you do, you go to conferences
like these, for example, and
you look how the others do it.
And of course, most of the time you hear
like success stories and especially you
want to learn how the big companies do it.
So you look at all the methodologies
and all the theory behind it.
You learn how agile is done.
You start thinking, yeah, my
company might need a tribe.
We got to do it the
lean way and whatsoever.
And then of course, like 95
percent of all presentations and
conferences, they're about tech.
ah, they're using this disruptive
technology and everybody treats technology
as the problem and the solution,
which already is strange, right?
So you see how they do
it, how you should do it.
You start taking the stuff
in, into your company and
whatever, but what's the result?
Some things might get better, but most of
the time, does influence really increase?
Do you do things right?
are you being heard from now on?
Are you being seen as the expert?
Most of the time, not really.
And this is not the
only experience I have.
I guess many of you
can share that feeling.
And I saw it in so many companies.
I've been working in a couple of companies
and I've been consulted in many companies.
And that's really like a
common problem that I see.
Thank you.
And what I realized, the longer
you work in a company, that there's
always a certain type of person.
Sometimes it's a consultant,
sometimes it's a team member,
sometimes it's just a line manager.
Some people who have technical
expertise, but some are not, let's
say the brightest minds in the room.
But somehow they just know
how to talk and to sell.
I call them the sellosophers
or the noisecutives.
Really strong with bam,
buzzword machinery.
And they are somehow able
to influence management.
And they're also somehow able to fly
up the career ranks just like that.
And you sit there and you'd be like,
damn, I've been here for like forever.
Hardly anybody knows the
application better than me.
And now I get another boss who, where
I experienced knows less than me.
Technically, and this is
at least a tech company.
But there's this weird relation that,
that people are hurt that I just,
I don't know, louder or whatsoever.
And, Yeah, that's a strange thing.
at a certain point, this happened
to me early in, in companies.
It changed later on, but
I'm going to get to that.
But at a certain point, you're
going to make a cut in your career.
And you think about how it's going to be,
is it going to be tiresome all the time?
Of course, not all the time, but will I
run into these issues over and over again?
Or do I, at a certain point have to become
like, I don't know, like one of them?
So that was a hard thing to think about.
But then one day, there
was another consultant.
Actually, to tell you the story, I was
working at a company that made clinical
research, and I was a software engineer.
And, we had really some legacy,
technology, and this is why we had
consultants from time to time come in.
And there was, let's say,
yet another one that came in.
So history kept repeating and repeating.
But this time, there was another guy.
I remember that guy particularly
because, he was different.
His name was Steven, by the way.
And to put it bluntly, I would say
that he felt like he was one of us.
Actually, it was very calm and real.
So no buzz wording at all.
He was a real tech expert.
So he was a beast, I have to say.
And with us, he was nerdy, which is cool.
But I'm saying that because I've
never seen like a nerdy guy in the
management meetings having like
influence and telling them what to do.
But he did.
He was able to influence management
and get, let's say, get the right
things done, at least what we thought.
And, he was able to get the
change done that we didn't.
And, I remember a story one day.
I gave a presentation
in front of the team.
I had a great idea.
I remember the idea came to me at night.
Those are always the best ideas.
And I got up.
It was about refactoring.
It was a biggie actually, but
I had a great strategy in mind
and I presented it to the team.
And, like everyone loved it and they
were like, thumbs up, really good.
Yeah, we got to do that.
But it's a bigger one.
So you got to present it to management
as well because they have to, to seal it.
If it's good.
And I was like, yeah, great.
I take the presentation and I'm
going to show it to management,
made a date and stuff like that.
And then Steven found out about it.
He came to me, he checked the
presentation and he told me, don't do it.
And it was like, what?
What problem do you have?
And he was like, no,
postpone the presentation.
So get more time and you got to
change it because the way you're
going to do it, it's He said, it's
like giving a present, a presentation
in Chinese to an Italian audience.
They're probably not
gonna understand anything.
And what he said, you do this.
First of all, you got
to know your audience.
that means get into their heads.
Think about the KPIs, the key
performance indicators they have.
What are they expecting?
What are they looking for?
What are they not expecting?
And what do they don't want to hear?
What don't they need to hear?
And what might bore them?
Second, use their language.
Take imagery, take analogies and
that stuff from their domain.
So make it understandable for
them, make it relatable for them.
And the third tip, and that this is
one of the best I've ever gotten, was,
When you tell something like this, I
know we engineers, we tend to speak
about the solution and how great
the solution is and go into details.
And he said, do not
talk about the solution.
Make them understand the problem
and make them understand the,
the benefits of your solution.
that is a pretty different thing.
because, when you want to be
seen as the expert, no one should
tell you how you do your job.
It's okay if it's a black box.
If somebody understand that there's
a need, that there's problem and
that you have whatever magic solution
that is okay because you as an
expert say, yeah, that's the thing.
That's what I'm getting paid for.
And this is the benefit you have.
People are going to be happy, especially
when you present to management
because what are they interested
in numbers, facts, risk assessment.
Maybe, some money assessment
as well and all that stuff.
So this was a great tip he gave me, but
we're going into that a bit later as well.
And, yeah, so I did, I
prepared it that way.
It was the first time I didn't
know if it was okay or not.
But yeah, I had many presentations
before, but that was the first time I
went into a presentation with management
and I thought like, that was a success.
Thanks.
They got me, it was like interesting.
We had a nice conversation.
I could see in their eyes and they were
like, hey, that's a really good thing.
And I swear to God, it was the first
time the CEO got up and even applauded.
And he was like, see that?
That's the effort guys.
And I was like, yeah, hell, why not?
Cool, cool stuff.
But the best thing about it is this was
my aha moment where I realized, damn,
he can do it and I could do it as well.
And there was no magic behind it.
And then I thought about.
what he was really doing.
Because in the beginning, when I
thought about Steven, and I saw
his work of thorn like a case,
maybe just a magician, magical guy
who's I don't know, super empathic.
Or maybe it's just because he's old.
And I don't know, privileged,
and he's from extern.
So this is why they listen to him.
But that's really not the case.
Everything the guy had was like he
had a bucket full of clever hacks.
He had I don't know, let's say,
like a magic playbook of wisdom
for pretty much every situation.
Not only in the management
meetings, but also internal.
When you're talking to the team and that
stuff and how you prepare stuff and even,
when you go into technical decisions, he
just had, these little efficient hacks.
And I found out by watching him, I
don't know if he, he saw it that way
too, but that was the pattern I saw
that every hack he had was algorithmic.
It's take this playbook
and do it like that.
And guess what?
As an IT engineer, what are we good with?
Algorithms.
So if you break down the hacks in that
form, it's like everybody can do it.
So I started watching him and I
started noticing and I even watched
other people who did stuff like,
or at least where I thought they
had a good approach to things.
I wrote it down and I
started using that stuff.
And I tell you friends, that was a turning
point in my career, not only for, success
inside teams and what results we had.
Also, especially it was an ignition
for, Let's say, the guys I explained
before, the guys who seem to fly up the
ladders and I somehow found the turbo
how that works, but with a good feeling
because I wasn't buzz wording out.
So what happened is my influence level
grew and especially my trust level grew.
People saw me as an expert,
especially as a go to expert.
And that's a, that's an important thing.
We're all kind of experts, but the go
to expert is the guy you go to when you
need if you want to know something or
if you want to put somebody in charge.
And somehow among a group of experts
somebody shines out and this is
what happened from that moment on.
And of course I became, because
it's all social stuff, I
became a better team player.
And better team player means better team.
And better team means better results.
And that was really satisfying.
I got to tell you that.
And the interesting thing is, from
that moment on, you start being
seen on the radar for promotions.
And it's not like you have to
knock on doors somewhere else.
It's like people come to you because
they see ah, there's potential.
And we want to put the trust
in that person and let that
person go on with that topic.
That was a good thing, actually.
But, the best thing of all,
to be honest with you is, I
didn't have to change anything.
I was scared before, as I told you, it's
do I have to be tired some all the time?
Or do I have to, change
personality and become one of them?
It's no offense to nobody.
It's just, I'm not a native
speaker, so it might sound weird.
But the thing is, I was
always able to stay me.
And I was able to, put some
more of my thoughts into the
company and into the process.
And that's a satisfying thing.
So in short, the learning from that
episode in my life was that ironically,
the key to producing great code at
work and truly enjoying tech wasn't in
the code itself, but it was beyond it.
And my story continued.
I got hooked to this topic somehow
because it worked and it felt better.
of course, I wanted to
improve my skills beyond code.
First of all, to have a
better work life experience.
And second of all, because
you're never alone.
And I saw potential in others in my team.
So I also thought about, hey,
I'd like to teach these methods.
So why not?
But the problem I hit is the
journey started faltering.
because you, actually, you do not find
many appropriate teachings out there.
So what I did is I started coaching
seminars, attending coaching seminars.
I went to leadership trainings,
I made these career seminars,
I went to soft skill courses.
And don't get me wrong,
these programs are all great.
But somehow, I think for the
target group of software engineers,
they are not so suitable.
You know what I mean?
You So the thing is, what I
got is, first of all, I thought
they were way too generic.
it's nice knowing about theory that in
groups, someone can become the alpha, one
is the beta, the other one is the gamma.
That's all nice.
But where's my practical advice?
what do I do with it?
I want it shorter, faster.
I want these hacks, I want
to use it immediately.
Then second of all those things
were not really tech related.
there were people related.
That's fine.
But I wanted, this special
factor with the tech sector.
And third of all, the, most
of the teaching styles were
not really, compatible.
Give you an example.
that depends on, on, on what
you like, but I'm not really the
type for, group therapy, chair,
circle, role play stuff, Depends.
Maybe you like it.
Good for you.
I don't.
So for me, it was a bit incompatible.
And the next thing I thought
was it felt, it really actually
felt a bit like therapy.
I thought that the approach most of the
time was that you go there and people show
you that there's something wrong with you.
And here's the solution that you should
adapt and change your personality.
So there's always a feeling I got
there, but I always thought, and I still
think there's nothing wrong with me.
Just there's nothing wrong with you.
We're just the way we
are, and that's good.
It's just about how we interact with each
other, and I don't want to change myself.
What I wanted is, I wanted
to be me, remain me, but I
wanted to have an efficient
compatibility layer with the world.
And that's fine to have.
This is why there are interfaces for.
Do you get what I mean?
I want, I wanted exactly these hacks.
That I've been telling you about.
Like this, okay, what can I do?
How can we make the
interaction more useful?
But I want to stay me.
And, it was pretty specific
what I was looking for.
But it was a bit of a disillusionment.
Because unfortunately, there
was not enough suitable content.
And there were not enough
suitable learning methods as well.
So then one day, I was already
working, I was working in an e
commerce company and I was C level
there, which was actually pretty cool
and, stressy, but as a C level, you
have to know more about business.
And I wasn't really strong at that time.
So I was thinking about making an MBA.
The problem with an MBA is
that, it's really expensive.
It takes time.
It feels like going to university again.
So I wasn't too happy about that.
Yeah.
And then suddenly out of
nothing, I saw an offer from the
United States of an online MBA.
And it's called the Power MBA.
So I do not get money of them,
but if you hear me, send it
over 10 grands a day, please.
So no commercial here, but I got to name
it because it was really cool actually.
And it was an online school and
everything was online and everything
was based on videos on demand.
So it was pretty much my tempo.
I could do it whenever and wherever
I want, which I really like.
And it was well structured.
then the format was like, micro learning.
I don't know if you know it.
It's like these, small
bite sized chunks to learn.
It's like you do 15
minutes a day and not more.
And statistically, the learning
results are 20 percent better
than on traditional training.
And I approved that.
That totally worked for me.
And the other thing I found really
cool was that statistically, you
have 50 percent more engagement
because it's way easier to commit to
15 minutes a day than to two hours
a day or to like, a long lesson.
And, third, it was completely based on
expert interviews in real life situations.
Yeah.
And I liked that.
And that sparked a fire.
I liked the format of this course so
much that this was the moment where I
thought, I want to create my own company.
And I said, if they can do it
like that, why don't we create
something like that for skills
beyond code for the tech industry.
And so what I did, what we did,
at outer skills, we went out
and we started interviewing as
many experts as we could find.
So experts that we considered as real
pros, successful people in the industry.
And those were technicians,
like all levels.
Um, technicians, software
engineers and architects as well.
We talked to the C levels
and to managers in between.
And what we did basically is we asked
them for their top five advice, tricks,
Hacks, self improvement things that
they would have given themselves
at the beginning of their career.
And most of the time, people will
start telling you these stories like
I just told you with Steven, like
these epiphanies they had, like this
one advice, or the person gave me that
advice and it changed everything forever.
And most of the time, those advice
are really practical and just clever.
And we started collecting all that
stuff and putting it together.
And what we saw is that
there is a pattern in there.
So what we did is we, let's
say decrypted that pattern.
And we found the seven rules
beyond code for it success.
And the seven categories that we found in
that advice are first of all, it's about
vision and purpose, which means, You got
to have a certain vision and idea what
you want to do in your job because most
of the time people don't really know what
they're really good at or what they desire
and what they actually do not really like.
But the sooner you start thinking
about that stuff, the pathway you're
going to do is going to get clearer.
Second of all, because everything starts
with yourself, is self management.
How do you organize yourself?
And how do you, for example, handle
criticism and all that stuff?
And there are really good tricks
how to also little algorithmic
hacks how to handle criticism.
I won't show them to you today,
but you can check it out later on.
I'll give you a link.
And then the third one is tech ownership.
I want to go into detail
with that one later on.
The fourth one is, of course,
communication, because we're humans,
we're communicating all the time.
See, this is sometimes we forget
that tech is a people business.
people create solutions for other
people in collaboration with
people, using technology as a tool.
But it's still around for and with people.
And why it is with people is
the fifth one is collaboration
because you're never alone and
five people are stronger than one.
Number six is the mindset.
It's, career also has to do with, like
what kind of mentality do you have?
And number seven, of
course, is business acumen.
Everything is about business.
Even if you're working for an open
source company, there has to be someone
who has to pay your bills, right?
and what we did is we put all that
together in our tech career playbook
that we call the seven rules beyond code.
So I'm happy that we're, I'm happy
to say that we've been putting skills
beyond code on the map since 2023.
We're having customers in three continents
already, and we're selling to individuals
and teams, but enough of a publicity.
that was, Yeah, you got to say
something about yourself as well.
I'm with Skills Beyond
Code already for a while.
And, I see a bunch of false beliefs that
people have in their mind all the time.
Probably the biggest one is that
soft skills cannot be learned.
Either you got it or you don't.
People often, have this image of the
nerds in their mind and that stuff.
And we even have TV series like Silicon
Valley or The IT Crowd or Big Bang Theory.
And they're nice to watch.
They're fun.
And you somehow can relate to that stuff.
That's nice.
But it's also crap when you
talk about real soft skills.
Because soft skills are
not about personality.
You cannot learn to change your
personality and you shouldn't.
That's you.
that's who you are.
But what you can do is you
can change some behaviors.
I just showed you how it works.
This is the stuff we did with Steven.
It's you can still be you, but
you can use some nice hacks and
some of your knowledge, your
cleverness to like, behave better.
differently.
So that's a complete different approach.
Let me give you an example.
This here is a typical, photo
of me in a meeting situation.
I could sit, I could watch you do this
and this because I'm impatient and
I tend to be, let's say, impulsive
because I got Italian roots.
I got some fire in me and this
combined with German destruction could
become a hurricane from time to time.
The thing is, that Over the
years, I learned to see the
trigger and change that behavior.
And everything started with Steven again.
He watched me in meetings from time
to time and then he took me aside.
He recognized that and he gave me the
advice and he said, Listen, first of all,
you're not making nobody better with that.
Second of all, people will not like you.
And third, the results will
not get better that way.
this is a lose situation.
Change it.
And the thing he gave me was another small
algorithm, and it was the coin framework.
C for context, O observation,
I impact, N next steps.
I give you this example.
If there was a meeting where, let's
say, somebody used some wrong query
methods that slowed the application
down or whatsoever, I could sit there
in a normal mode and say, Oh, who the
hell did use these stupid methods?
You should know that better.
That fucks up our whole application.
I'm swearing.
Oh, but come on, this is the internet.
There are worse things there.
So you might be living with that.
And I would continue, Stupid
idiots, get that fixed, come on.
But that's crap.
That helps nobody.
That vented my steam off.
That's not okay.
I could say it with the coin framework.
Listen to that.
First of all, I could give context.
What am I talking about?
And I could say stuff like, during
my last code review, I checked the
solutions implemented in the new module.
Observation, what did I see?
I noticed that the current
implementation processes large
amounts of data at once, which might
not scale well as our system grows.
I for impact.
What do I see as a possible impact?
This could lead to slower response
times and increased resource
consumption, potentially affecting
user experience and system reliability.
And now give next steps.
This is the productive part.
Say stuff like, it might be helpful to
explore ways to process data in smaller
chunks or optimize resource usage.
Would you be open to discussing
potential approaches together?
I pretty much said the same thing, only
in a nice way, in a productive way, in
a positive way, that there might be a
positive outcome and nobody's offended.
Even if I wanted to, but I can
still offend them in my mind.
But it was totally easy, it's
just, it's another small algorithm
that changes the whole situation.
So this is about, you
cannot change who you are.
The Big Bang Theory is a nice
series, but Come on, it's a bit
different in the real world.
And the, the three most common
false beliefs we get besides, the
biggie I just talked to, told you
about is the first one is, my skills
are great, but my coworkers suck.
Like everybody, everybody
connects normally with my talks,
but the first thing they do is
they think about someone else.
It's yeah, he or she, they
don't have the skills.
Yeah, I can totally name a
situation with them, but they
do not think about themselves.
The second one is sounds pretty good,
but I don't want to go into management.
And the third one is the problem is
not my communication skills, but the
fact that management is not listening.
Okay, friends, let's
start with the first one.
whenever you think That you're
totally above the topic and the
others are not Think about it.
You might be running the risk to falling
into the Dunning Kruger effect Pattern
which means you think yeah, I'm really
expert here And I would not even challenge
that but the more you get into the
topic the sooner you start realizing
Hell, this is more complicated than I
thought and the real gurus are actually
real far away many studies have shown
that 80 percent of people believe that
they have above average soft skills,
but only about 20 percent actually do.
let me ask you.
If most people think, They
are above average, but
logically, that can't be true.
Where do you think they really stand?
Or where do you think you really stand?
Let's make an experiment.
Let me ask you, how do you
recognize a great communicator?
Think about it.
Most of the time, people will list
traits like listening, emotional
intelligence, and clarity.
And now I ask yourself, do you
consistently do all these things yourself?
there's a difference between knowing
about it, and yeah, that's obvious, that's
so clear, and actually implementing it.
There's a giant difference.
And let me give you another
huge statistic about that.
Have you ever heard
about the chaos report?
The chaos report is a large
study that gets conducted
like pretty much every year.
what they do is they screen about 5, 000
projects worldwide and the IT projects and
they categorize them in three categories.
The first one is successful, which
means it was done in time and in budget.
The second one is called challenged, which
means It's either in time or on budget.
And the third one is failed,
which means not in time, not in
budget or completely canceled.
Have an intelligent guess.
How many are successful?
For all of you who now think
five or 10, shame on you because
it's your industry as well.
For all of you who think 80 or up
against, no one thinks that reality
is it's 30 percent 30 percent of all
projects can be classified as successful.
Which honestly, friends from
engineer to engineer, that's a shame.
That's our industry.
Can you name another
industry with such bad quota?
Can you imagine plastical surgery going
in there and saying, 30 percent of
the cases is going to be successful.
it really sucks.
And on the other hand, it also means
that 70 percent of all projects are not
satisfying for the customer because they
did not get what they originally wanted.
but here's the crazy
thing about the statistic.
This statistic has been
going on since the mid 90s.
So the reliable numbers
are, I would say from 2000.
So for the past 25 years, the
numbers have hardly changed.
It's always around 30 percent successful
and always about the same amount of
what is not successful for 20 years or
now, almost 25 years, the same numbers.
Although.
Especially those, these conferences
tell you technology is getting
better and better every day.
Everything is disruptive.
Things are getting cooler and whatsoever.
But is there a change?
No, there is not.
And they also, look for
the reasons in this study.
And the reasons is people.
It's communication.
It's people business.
Like I told you, it's process now.
It's like people work with each other.
It's crazy thing, huh?
think about it.
Just let that settle.
Second false belief.
Sounds good, but I don't want to go
into management, so I might not need it.
friends.
That's pretty much a really false belief.
Because, It's not only in management
where you need skills beyond code.
I'll give you an example.
There's a statistic from the ICIMS
Hiring Institute, by the way.
It's like a huge institute that
puts people into labor that says
94 percent of all IT recruiters or
tech recruiters believe that people
with greater soft skills and skills
beyond code are way more likely to be
promoted than people with more years
of experience but weaker soft skills.
And a promotion is not only into
management, it's becoming a senior,
it's becoming an individual contributor,
it's becoming an architect, it's
becoming a tech lead and whatsoever,
it doesn't have to be with people.
So promotions are directly
coupled with skills beyond code.
Actually another statistic says that 75
percent of promoters would even cut an
interview short even if the tech skills
are supreme, but if the rest is not good.
And here's another one.
Even as a software
engineer, what do you think?
How much time do you spend in meetings?
What do you guess?
On average, that's an American statistic.
It's 53%.
I've seen that the German statistics are
between 40 and 50%, something like that.
Still.
let it be 35 in a good case.
It's still a hell of time that
you have to spend in meetings.
And think about it.
It's daily plannings, reviews, retros,
refinements, team meetings, emergency
meetings, blah, blah, blah, blah.
You can read it yourself.
That's a whole lot of time that
you have to spend in meetings.
And that's a whole lot of
time that can be frustrating.
And it could be so much better if
you had like nicer, nicer hacks
to deal with, with those moments.
And, the third false belief
is that, the problem is not my
communication skills, but the fact
that management is not listening.
first of all, if the fact is that
management is not understanding,
then it is your problem because
then you're not explaining well.
It's always easy to point it at
them, but that won't fix nothing.
You got to try harder there.
So then this is about, having a
different communication approach.
But I tell you what the, what's
the real thing behind that.
This thing has to do with
your expertise status.
Let's play a game.
Think about in your mind, think about
a doctor, a medic, medical doctor.
How does he or she look like?
Pretty much it's going
to look like that, right?
Person in white suit, like everybody
has the same image in their head.
I think it wouldn't go
too far away from that.
Now think about a car mechanic.
How does that look like?
Pretty much like this?
Like someone working under a car?
Like some oil over with tools
and gloves and stuff like that?
I guess so.
And now, think about a software engineer.
What do you see?
I googled the pictures, because
whenever you want to have the public
opinion about something, you can just
google the pictures and then you see
honestly, the picture that people
have in their mind about something.
And it looks like that.
It's like a creepy guy in the basement.
And what's the problem
with that situation?
think about it.
If you go to a doctor, And the
doctor tells you, listen, we're
going to make that kind of therapy.
You're going to take these pills.
We're going to do, we're going to make it
three weeks like that, then an operation.
You won't say, nah.
We skip two thirds of the
pills because of costs.
we don't do that.
We do it this way.
And if you do an operation, take a
bone here and save it over there.
You would never do that.
You would not even go to your car mechanic
and say, Hey, listen, why don't you
do it with duct tape and use some oil
from the kitchen that I have left over.
He would look at you and said,
get the hell out of here.
First of all, you wouldn't do it.
Second of all, they wouldn't do it.
But in our line of work,
My customer's king.
And, it's so easy to
make an, Um, to, English.
What are the words?
To make an exception.
Like, why don't you put in an if?
Why don't you skip the tests?
Why don't you do that?
it's just for the MVP.
We're going to fix it later
on and stuff like that.
We do that all the time.
And here's the problem.
If someone tells you how to do your
job, you are no longer an expert.
Listen carefully.
If someone tells you how to do your job.
You are no longer an expert.
And that's the problem with that.
Why are they not listening?
Because you are not
being seen as an expert.
And the way to shift
that is the following.
First of all, you as an
engineer, you own the how part.
Whatever idea, somebody comes up with an
idea, that's the why we have to do it.
Then some smart people think about it.
What exactly do we have to do?
And then there's the how part.
How does it get implemented
in a tech world?
First of all, nobody tells
you how to do your job.
You're the expert.
Shield that area.
The how is closed from now on.
Second of all, start influencing
the what and why part.
The sooner and earlier you get in,
the more benefit you will have.
Let me show you this way.
When you start a project, the earlier
you are in your project, the more impact
and influence you have on the project.
Okay.
But at a certain point in time,
you reach a point that I call
the point of no return, where you
cannot change, requirements anymore.
They're just, they're sealed.
And you missed your time to go
in there and change something.
Because you as the expert
might even change the world.
Because I know what you want to do.
But in the tech world, you
solve things differently.
You might even have a benefit from it.
If you don't, requirements are sealed.
No matter how stupid they are,
they'll just get approved.
And then you have to live
with something like that.
And at a certain point after that, nobody
will remember the planners anymore.
Because the planning part is
over, then the implementation and
the maintenance part continues.
So for most of the time of the
project, everything that people will
remember is, who built that crap?
You did.
So that means stupid decision,
you have to live with it, and
you will be blamed for it.
Even if you think it was never my idea,
I knew it better from the beginning.
Nobody listened to me.
Doesn't matter.
People will think you are the guy.
So get in early.
This is the motivation.
The sooner you get in, the better the
solution will be, the less technical
debt you might produce because you
as an expert have the hindsight to
think about it and the less pain
in the ass for your daily work.
And most important of
all, you remain credible.
So I see I'm running out of time,
which is why I got to come to an
end of this presentation slowly.
Nope.
Let me ask you a simple question.
If you reflect on everything you saw
today, if you did it how I did, how
we saw it today, do you think you
could be more successful with that?
Could that work for you?
if you used expert hacks, just like
the way I presented them today to tweak
your communication, to bridge the gap
between tech and business, i. e. make
them understand even non technical
people, bring them on the level,
make them understand, get them in the
game and improve your team play and
start changing and improving things.
Could that work for you?
the thing is, over the years, what
we saw that, people who skill up
beyond code First of all, for them,
it's the benefit you get from it.
For sure, it's a door opener for
better jobs and higher salaries.
We don't only know that statistically.
That's what people say.
And that's let's say, a
logical conclusion of that.
Second of all, you get a
competitive edge in the job market.
According to the springboard report,
last year's springboard report,
it was and they said that about
70 percent of people working in
the STEM field, technicians, lack.
important business skills,
business soft skills and skills
beyond their expertise area.
75 percent is a lot.
So if you skill up in
that area, that's a cheat.
You can cut the line for job applications.
you, can stand out in job
interviews and stuff like that.
You're a special one compared
to the three others next to you.
So one in four, that's actually
a nice thing for yourself.
It's an efficiency boost.
I, for myself can say I had a
way better work life experience.
And, a very interesting one, the world
economic forum said that by 2027.
Jobs will have changed so much
that in pretty much every job
you have to focus more on human
skills because that's actually what
really differentiates us from AI.
AI is pretty strong in pretty much every
task but on a human interacting level
even if it sounds good for first it's
still a machine so there will still be
humans working together and this is a
thing where you really could stand out.
What you could definitely get rid
of and that I can prove is you.
Being overlooked and ignored,
if that is important for you.
Not being understood and, trust
me, lots of meeting drama.
For me, the most important thing would
have been, it's most easy to say it
with a quote of Benjamin Franklin, which
says, Lost time is never found again.
So if I had a DeLorean time machine where
I could travel back in time, And teach
myself all that stuff, all the hacks
that Stephen had and all the stuff that
we found out later for the beginning.
Boy, that would have saved
me lots of gray hair.
Right now, in that light, I think,
and with my shorter hair, you don't
see it so much, and that is good.
But this is when my hair are longer, how
it looks like, and this is thanks to many
meeting situations, this I can tell you.
And so I ask you, like in every
presentation you will attend throughout
this conference and throughout many other
conferences, you always have two choices.
Blue pill and red pill.
First of all, do nothing.
And that's totally fine.
Without judgment.
You don't have to do anything.
You can just let it soak in.
Like more knowledge, okay?
And then continue with whatever you do.
And that's fine.
If you like to stay
invisible, again, no judgment.
Many people like that.
If you're more like an order taker,
If you, if you just basically want
to survive and have an okay time, and
if you like, if you prefer to keep
complaining, I'm allowed to say that.
I got Italian relatives and complaining
is a sport there that I can tell you.
So if that is the thing
for you, that's fine.
Take the blue pill.
But if you're more like somebody who says,
No, actually, I want to make a change.
I want to get active.
I want my career to grow.
I want my personality to grow.
And I want to start winning
things, especially at work.
Then take a leap of faith, get
active, do something about it.
This is really an advice
that I could give you.
There are many possibilities out
there to improve that skill set.
There's one that I can offer you and
I'd like to do that on my final, with
my final words here in that, conference.
So if I offered to take your skills
beyond code to an expert level to help
you boost your career in the next 30 days,
without you having to leave your home or
office and you can take the video course
whenever, wherever you want, on demand.
You don't have to sit through
long, boring lectures.
You only get concise and straight
to the point microlearning videos
and you probably don't even have to
pay for it because your boss has a
training budget for you anyway that you
shouldn't let go to waste, my friends.
Here's my question.
Would you take me up on that offer?
Consider it.
If you liked it, you can do it.
If, If you'd like to get more
information about that stuff, we
prepared a little PDF for you.
that you can, it's for free,
that has more information about
Skills Beyond Code in general.
And that gives you your
first how to tutorial.
And you can check it out
here under skillsbeyondcode.
com or just make a photo of that,
of that QR code and feel free
to download it free of charge.
You don't have to sign anything.
Friends, it was a pleasure.
Thanks a lot for having me
as a guest speaker here.
And I hope you enjoy the
rest of the conference.
And if you have any feedback or if
you'd like to get in touch, feel free.
I would be happy to do that.
enjoy the rest of the day.
Goodbye.