Hello everyone.
I'm Manke.
I currently work at Twilio as a director
of engineering, where I lead teams working
on predictive and generative AI products.
I'm excited to talk with you about how we
can enhance performance of large language
models by incorporating contextual data.
We'll also discuss how this approach
moves is beyond traditional pre-training
methods, creating much more powerful
and personalized AI experiences.
So first, let's start by exploring
the strength of large language models.
These models have impressive capabilities
when it comes to generating content.
They excel in conversational inter
interactions, making user interfaces
feel very natural and intuitive.
In fact, this interface.
Has been key to democratizing AI
across different user personas.
A prompt is now valent of a model.
They're also incredibly versatile
and performed remarkably well across
various tasks, including summarizations,
generating quote snippets, crafting
compelling copywriting, and more
recently even advanced reasoning tasks.
Despite these impressive strengths, LLMs
also come with some critical limitations.
For one, they're primarily
tamed on static data sets.
This means the information
they have access to can
become outdated or incomplete.
Additionally, LLM sometimes generate
incorrect or fabricated information,
what we often refer to as hallucinations.
Perhaps most importantly, without
contextual informations, LLM struggle
to deliver genuinely personalized
responses limiting their effectiveness
in many real world scenarios.
Let's look at a practical example of
a support chat bot to illustrate this
issue without appropriate context.
A large language model might
respond inaccurately or irrelevantly
because it doesn't have access to
the necessary information to tailor
its response Effectively, this
limitation underscores the importance
of incorporating contextual data.
The solution to this issue is
generally called retrieval,
augmented Generation, or rag.
The core idea behind RAG
is pretty straightforward.
The idea is to retrieve relevant
contextual information from various data
sources and integrate it into the prompts
we give to our large language models.
This process alone significantly improved
the models responses, making them a lot
more accurate, timely, and personalized.
Rag also enables the
inclusion of current data.
it can help inclusion of
specialized domain knowledge, even
proprietary knowledge basis can be
included as part of the prompts.
And most important in context of
today's discussion is its ability
to add custom, personal, contextual
information into the prompt to drive
hyper-personalized AI interactions.
However, as we've seen this example,
just simply combining LLMs with a very
generic knowledge base isn't enough to
drive depersonalization users expected.
We need something more targeted.
For instance, if you look at this
example, even though the sup, the AI
support agent has access to documents
relating to the return policy.
It doesn't have the personalized
context of the user leading to a
somewhat poor customer experience.
And this brings us to the concept
of customer data platforms or CDPs.
We'll see how CDPs, which are
traditionally known for marketing
use cases, can enable personalization
at scale effectively by providing
rich, personalized data that can
be used directly by AI systems.
And before we dig into more details
on how A CDP can be a powerful source
of contextual information, let's
first understand at a high level what
exactly is a customer data platform.
In simple terms, A CDP is a sophisticated
tool that gathers and organizes
customer data from a variety of
different sources and interactions.
And send it, sends it to,
downstream apps and destinations.
The sources could be your web
app, your chat bot, your, POS
systems or even your warehouse.
And the destination could be the
apps where you want to activate this
data, such as marketing automation
platforms, ad destinations, et cetera.
CDP is increasingly also create
a unified and very comprehensive
view of each individual customer.
enabling businesses to understand the 360
degree view of each customer in real time.
There are also nuances like identity
resolution across different platform
that help build rich user profiles.
Let's see how this would work in action.
So as the user interacts
with different applications.
The user profile gets hydrated,
allowing for deeper personalization for
subsequent interactions, and now in this
example, you can also see how the chat
experience also becomes very seamless
as the profile gets richer and richer.
So what we are seeing is that in
the context of AI applications.
CDP can act as a very powerful
personalization engine.
It allows AI applications to
access relevant and personalized
data effortlessly, and thereby
significantly enhancing the user
experience as we see with the example
that we have been taking so far.
Depending on the context
of the information, all you
need to do is pull relevant
information from the user profile.
Add to the prompt for the large language
models and then you're able to generate
a much more personalized response.
In fact, this is very similar to how
the memory feature in chat GPT works.
So if you have noticed within chat GPT,
you can add a lot of your preferences
or information about yourself as memory.
And what that does it, it enables
the models to maintain context.
Ensuring consistent and relevant
interaction over time, but CDPs can
go a lot further in terms of providing
a more comprehensive context across
different digital touch points, whether
it's an email interaction or an action
you performed on the mobile app.
So with the CDP and with
the cost of inference.
In large language models coming
down dramatically, we'll find that
companies can unlock capabilities
that require personalization at scale.
These would include one-to-one
personalized messaging, dynamically
personalized web experiences, and highly
effective customer support interactions.
Imagine having a customer support
that instantly understands your
context without needing extensive
background information, and that
is exactly what a CDP can deliver.
so far we have learned how A
CDP is sufficient for delivering
personalized experiences.
But now I wanna focus on how A CDP
is also necessary for improving
personalized enterprise applications.
And in particular, I want to emphasize
is why you need a more sophisticated
data infrastructure than just a key value
store to drive this personalization.
The first reason is very simply that
CDPs help break down information silos.
It's possible that customers, make
purchases on different platforms, and
these events are collected at different
touch points by different teams.
Similarly, it's also possible that
one team manages the web app and
another team manages the mobile app.
And the behavior is captured
differently across these two platforms.
Having a unified way of collecting
customer data and unifying that
data into customer profiles is core
to unlocking value from this data.
Using AI with real time data
capture and identity resolution,
you can build a pretty rich customer
profile for each of your users.
And finally, CDPs can also provide
the much needed data governance
for different types of data sets,
depending on their sensitivity.
So now that we have established
the need for personal context and
how CDPs can fulfill that need,
let's focus on different ways of
implementing this with the CDP.
So one potential or a
naive solution would be.
To embed all the available customer
profile information in each LLM prompt.
While this seems very comprehensive in the
sense that you would be getting all the
data that you have about that customer,
it often leads to very large prompts, and
thereby it increases the computational
cost and latency and ultimately makes
the solution pretty impractical at scale.
So depending on how large
your user profile is.
You could have a lot of characteristics
you're storing about your users, a lot
of behaviors you're capturing about
your users, and as a result, this
user profile could be pretty huge.
So now let's look at
another way of doing this.
So another approach of doing this
would involve selectively using only
specific and predetermined customer
traits or events from the user profile.
For instance, if I am talking to
a customer bought and asking for a
restaurant recommendation, if you know
that I have stored, the user's location
as part of the user profile, I can
fetch that and use that to provide more
tailored, restaurant recommendations.
While this helps reduce the prompt size,
it also severely limits the richness
of the personalization experience.
So first of all, it misses any other
relevant information that may be available
as part of the CDP or the user profile.
For instance, it's possible that there's
another team that is through some other
means recording favorite qz for each user.
Now, because as an engineer, while
implementing this feature, I did
not know that this particular
trait existed on the user profile.
I won't have a deliberate way of
including it in my implementation.
The other challenge is it
actually requires you to have this
comprehensive knowledge of what is
stored in the user profile and the
semantic understanding of everything
that exists on the user profile.
And this brings us to our final,
recommendation for implementation.
Is to dynamically retrieve just the
right amount of relevant customer
data based on the specific interaction
or the application context.
And how you do it is you take the
natural language prompt and you calculate
semantic similarity with different data
elements that exist on the user profile
in real time, and fetch that data and
inject that data into the LLM prompt.
So this solves the problem of
having a smaller context that
you're injecting in the LLM prompt.
It also solves the problem that you're
able to use all of the data that is stored
in the user profile without actually
having any prior knowledge of what existed
in the profile because you're doing the
semantic similarity check at runtime.
So this method is pretty efficient,
flexible, scalable, ensures
optimal use of all the data that
you have without compromising
on the personalization quality.
So let's wrap up our discussion
today with a few key takeaways.
First and foremost, whenever you are
building an AI application using large
language models for a lot of use cases,
that actually translates to solving.
A data infrastructure, data
quality, and data governance
problem in the first place.
Secondly, we saw that CDPs
provide a pretty compelling
option as a personalization
engine for large language models.
And finally, we saw how CDPs can
act as long-term memories for large
language models by deriving structured
information and storing them as user
profile and events and making them
available for large language models.
As and when needed for generating
hyper-personalized responses.
Thank you all so much for your
attention and engagement today.
If you'd like to continue this
discussion or have any questions on any
of the topics that we discussed today,
please feel free to reach out to me.
Thanks.