Hello everyone.
I'm Rustam.
I spent my entire career with telecom,
with big tech companies, launching
products and looking after products.
And today I want to share something
very interesting with you.
It's a retail evolution and
particularly it's cloud powered aspect.
Story that we will go through today
is basically around what is going
on currently in retail industry.
Where is the industry going and how.
Retail with the help of cloud will
be serving future needs of customers.
I will start with a storyline on a page.
It's always easier to have a
helicopter view on everything
that we will go through.
And the story is very simple and engaging.
First of all, cloud transforms retail.
There is no doubt about that.
And cloud makes it very
personal and very engaging.
It's also smart and scalable.
Pandemic, as we remember,
sped up that transformation.
You remember that everything suddenly
stopped and then went online where cloud
essentially helped cloud reinvented
the stores and it's now more, it's,
if it's a physical store, it's more,
experience hop rather than the traditional
store 10 years, 15 years ago, omni
channel is definitely driven by the
cloud and the customer journey, very
dependent on the cloud and the weight.
mixes the online and offline journeys.
And finally, future is advanced cloud
technologies with AI, with machine
learning, with the internet of things.
we will be able to see a much better
transformed retail going forward.
And part of that transformation we already
experienced today, but bear with me.
We will get there, in a couple of minutes.
Let's start with the
transformative role of the cloud.
So this is the.
market somewhere in London,
in early 20th century.
And this is also retail, right?
So this is the retail where you see
customers coming and going, picking
up what they want, strolling, going
through different stuff, checking
prices, et cetera, et cetera,
all in an offline environment.
That's the retail we had for centuries.
Now, it's rapidly changing quicker
and faster and quicker and faster.
And basically, the question in front
of retail, I think, is how to be
relevant, personal and delightful.
And that's a very big question
because now consumers are much more
picky and much more demanding versus
a consumer of 10, 15, 20 years ago.
And of course, cloud is
the catalyst for change.
If you look at the role of the cloud
for retail transformation, you will
see that it's innovation with advanced
technologies, such as AI and machine
learning, all those chatbots and,
smart stores, everything is dependent
on the cloud, retail analytic and
personalization is imperative right now.
Everything is in the cloud
and basically no one.
will be able to deliver top
quality service without a
cloud umbrella, helping them.
Omni channel, again, the way
offline and online are mixed.
Is it seamless?
Yes or no?
Everything dependent on the cloud.
Cloud delivers scalability and flexibility
so that retailers can very quickly
adjust, to, ever evolving customer needs.
And of course it's cost
efficient and agile.
So Without the cloud, I think retail, will
not be able to transform and to evolve
up to the standard of the new customer.
Today we will see where all the
world's best companies are going,
because I think it's very important
to just go through the cases and
this will give us, food for thought.
Of where does the next retail step
is leading us and let's start with
the Walmart because I think Walmart
is a great example of the company
that understood the importance of
cloud migration like 15 years ago.
So they started as early as in, 2010.
Always step by step evolving in that
process, partnering with, Microsoft
Azure, and we will get to that
platform a little bit, later during the
presentation, they launched different
solutions and even today, this cloud
transformation of Walmart is not done.
So it's ongoing.
And again, this giant, understands
that Without the cloud retail
will not exist going forward.
And even today it's, it will lose the,
I think the most of its competitiveness.
Comparison of pandemic, pre pandemic,
post pandemic, just to remind everyone,
so I will not pause on this slide for
long, but just a high level overview.
Before COVID, we remember
physical retail was dominated and
online was a supporting channel.
Now it's different.
So now everything is, driven by innovation
and physical retail becomes more,
experience up and online become essential.
So that's a massive difference
between what we had back
then and what we have now.
And omni channel.
It was mostly fragmented back then.
Now the experience of Omnichannel
become more and more crucial.
And it becomes, I think overall, at
least in the economies, economies
like, our economy here in the UK, it
becomes, seamless and really crucial
for, the proper customer experience.
And of course, we already mentioned the.
Cloud enabled agility, data analytics.
Now it's a must have.
So you can't, develop your retail.
You can't sell stuff.
Without cloud enabled, data analytics
personalization, it's simply not possible.
So let's now look at the role
of physical and online stores.
And I think the most important
thing is that now we only go to
physical store if we want to.
We never go there because
we have to, right?
We go there because we want to.
Everything can be ordered
online, more or less.
So if we want a special experience,
If we want touch and try only
then we choose Deliberately choose
to go to physical retail store
and to give you an example of shops beyond
shopping Let's start with the Nike live
stores example first of all, they provide
real time community engagement, which
means that you can come to that store.
Just look at this nice picture on your
screen and you can spend your time there.
You can discuss new
products with professionals.
You can choose your products.
If you want to, you can attend
an event hosted by Nike.
So it's a great concept.
We never had before.
Of course, it's, also data driven
personalization because cloud based
analytics tailoring everything to customer
preferences and purchasing behaviors,
Nike application, the smartphone one.
This is very important because.
the integration is crucial for
the right experience in the store.
And of course, Nike are deeply integrated.
So customers can reserve products,
they can access exclusive offers.
And if it's a Nike plus members,
they will get something very
special tailored exactly for them.
in store technology, also cloud
based in, Nike live stores, for
example, every sales person, people,
equipped with cloud connected devices.
They know in advance from customer
profiles, what to offer to that customer.
And of course, omni channel
integration is perfect online, offline.
You will not feel the gap there so you
can start your journey in Nike online
store and finish it in Nike offline store.
Everything is in place.
Then let's think for a moment of the,
about the evolution of online stores.
The key thing here, I think that
online shopping takes over offline.
That's definitely a fact, especially after
the pandemic, as we saw, three minutes
ago, if we think about this and I've put
a screenshot of, the, one of the biggest
and the best and most advanced retailers,
online retailers out there at the Amazon.
if we think about this, Evolution is,
first of all, scalability and flexibility.
online stores are easier to scale
operation, versus the physical stores
because of their online nature.
And with the help of cloud
technology, it's even easier.
Personalization, and again, I
already said a few times that
personalization is It is a must.
It's imperative now for modern
retail, real time data analytics
allow this advanced personalization
to work flawlessly for the customer.
everything is integrated,
seamlessly and especially the third
party services we know all the
payments, engines, the inventory
systems that retailers are using.
Everything is based on the
cloud and integrated seamlessly.
Of course, security and compliance,
the GDPR, everything is very
important and also cloud driven.
And of course, the enhanced
omni channel experience where.
Cloud technology delivers a
consistent shopping experience
across all the websites and
applications and physical store.
That's basically in five simple
steps, the key highlights of the
online evolution based on the cloud.
And here is another example.
So I think Shopify, it is a great
example of how empowering business
of all sizes to basically be able to
scale of how important this task is.
In case of the Shopify cloud platform,
first of all, it's a global scaling,
literally almost in any country out there,
becomes a portlet because Shopify has.
infrastructure dispersed across the globe.
Then of course, it's simplified
international expansion.
If you want to launch your store
after launching in the UK, say into,
I don't know, Ireland or in the EU,
Shopify will help you with that.
of course, that's also integrated,
commercial solutions when the cloud
based tools for inventory payments.
or shipping.
Everything is, provided to a retailer.
Customization and innovation also very
important because it enables businesses
to customize stores with apps and APIs.
And it's for all businesses out there.
So for example, you
need a 24 seven support.
You got it from Shopify platform.
You can lowering entry barriers
and, enable global success through
cloud based e commerce that way.
So that's an example of empowering
businesses of any sizes to scale
based on the cloud technologies.
Netflix, I think they are kings of
advanced real time personalization.
And I think that, as a great example,
Netflix can literally in the, in almost in
real time, offer based on your preferences
and the videos you viewed or, even the,
pages that you browsed when you were,
when you've been looking for a movie,
it can fine tune very personalized, very
you tailored recommendations for you.
And I think that capability of giving
advanced recommendations is very
unique for, for the modern retail.
It's something we've never had, or
even dreamt of 10, 15 years ago.
it's here today within the best
retailers and the best content
providers, such as Netflix.
And it's going to be more and
more important going forward.
Of course, they are also masters
of scalable cloud infrastructure
because it's content, right?
And it's.
I have heavy content, especially
if it's a 4k HDR movies, right?
So they can do that based
on their cloud solutions.
Of course, the user interfaces, they
have everything personalized from
artwork to previews and the layouts.
And it's under continuous improvements
because they test and refine and
leveraging AI and machine learning
to make New suggestions even better.
So that's the netflix example of real
time personalization Now let's switch
to omni channel and how it's enabled
by cloud I have nordstrom's unified
commerce example here how they sync
Inventory and customer data in online
and offline and basically if we go only
through highlights, of course, it's very
good for consistent customer engagement
because cloud platforms Unify marketing
and support across all the channels like
application online in store ensuring
that the No, some basically can assist
customers whenever and wherever they
need Of course, it's seamless some
seamless omni channel experience and
we already I think know how important
that is Remember the nike example.
It's unified customer profiles.
So All the data, customer data in
the cloud stored securely, but most
importantly, it's stored across all
the channels, like in a one storage.
So it's always in sync and it's unified.
of course, as a modern retailer, they
care about real time inventory updates.
And especially it's important for services
like, buy online, pick up and store.
And finally, last but not the
least, optimized order fulfillment.
So cloud technology turns stores, into
fulfillment centers, basically determining
the best location to ship, online orders
based on the location of the customer.
Now let's look at evolution
of retail with cloud.
I have targets predictive
analytics example here.
I think we all know target.
it's, massive, retailer, and they
really utilizing cloud to anticipate
customer needs and anticipation.
Also, it becomes more and
more important, going forward.
let's start with key highlights,
personalized marketing.
So they target.
target leverages, cloud based
analytics to process customer
data and create talent promotions.
They also, do very precise
product recommendation using
cloud algorithm algorithms.
So it's a, let's call it an
advanced personalization.
Of course, inventory is optimized
using the, cloud capabilities.
And cloud analyzes customer behavior,
which is also very important for
tailoring and anticipating the offers.
And of course the dynamic
pricing, because they work in a
very, competitive environment.
And adjusting pricing in real time
based on the cloud analytics is of
paramount importance for them Next
is an example of starbucks rewards.
So they are definitely mobile centric
And they are definitely instant and
so very personal real time updates So
the rewards and offers are instantly
synchronized across all platforms whether
it's In store, app, online, everything
is in sync based on your profile.
Personalization based on cloud
analytics deliver tailored promotions
based on your personal preferences.
And of course it drives up
customer satisfaction and loyalty.
Scalability, so millions of transactions
are handled smoothly and resources
scale automatically during peak times.
Omni channel integration.
Again, we will see it today multiple
times, the omni channel integration.
Rewards, seamlessly integrated across
the app, website, stores, and you
can flexibly redeem these rewards.
And innovation.
So basically, if you have a new feature to
roll out, you can do that very quickly and
with, protection of customer data in mind.
Let's now switch to
cloud integration today.
and I think that Microsoft Azure's retail
solution is a great example of how it's
working and helping, businesses today
because Scalable infrastructure and
advanced analytic tools is something
that retail really needs these
days Scalable cloud infrastructure,
when Azure automatically scales
computing resources based on demand.
And again, for retailers, it's
someone else's computer resources.
So you don't have to build data
set, a data center yourself
to analyze personalization,
run your CRM stuff, et cetera.
Advanced analytics and insights.
And that's also very important
because it's large data
volumes and having a swift.
Access to it, to having insights
on customer behavior, sales trends,
forecasts, pricing is very important.
Then personalized customer experience,
because Azure's AI deliver personalized
recommendations and tailored promotions.
Enhanced security and compliance.
Again, GDPR, so everything is
there and very secure with Azure.
and operational efficiency
and cost savings.
Infrastructure as a service
migrating to Azure reduces
capital expenditure on hardware.
As I said, you don't have to build
all those servers yourself to
improve your customer experience.
Then my next example, is related to AI
and cloud powered customer assistance.
And I think H& M virtual
assistant is just brilliant here.
So interactive AI customer
supports 24 seven, and it responds
to you in a natural language.
We all remember, and I guess we all
don't much like those chat bots.
We often hear when we call to
our bank or to our retailer.
So H& M is not the case.
Their chatbot is answering
naturally and that's called
natural language processing or NLP.
So that's a technology A cloud technology
that is very important going forward.
Personalized product recommendation.
Analyzing customer behavior and
preference stored in the cloud.
Virtual Assistant offers
personalized recommendation with,
aligned with individual style.
Efficient product search
with AI interpreting intent
to deliver accurate results.
So that's also very important.
AI Assistant based.
Scalable and reliable
cloud infrastructure.
Scalability is very important,
especially for the large retailers
like H& M and Seamless Omnichannel.
So today it's, Omnichannel, we've been
hearing this for multiple times because
this is of paramount importance the
way your app, your social media, your
assistant, your web, your offline store
is integrated in one seamless experience.
Now, let's have a look at the future
of cloud integration, and I think
Stitch Fix, AI recommendations is a
great example here for personalized
fashion suggestions from AI.
Every time we deal with fashion,
it's, it gets complicated
because fashion is personal.
Fashion is something.
Tailored only to you and data driven
personalization that StageFix provides
is really revolutionize this industry in
terms of collecting feedback preferences,
processing them in the cloud and then
understanding your personal unique
style, giving your, you, giving you
the unique, offers and suggestions.
Machine learning and algorithms,
offstage fix predict, basically fashion
items that clients are likely to take
based on your experience in the past.
Hybrid human AI styling, is AI
generated suggestions, basically
curated by humans with human judgment.
So basically ensuring that a tailored
experience, delivered to you,
based on AI plus human suggestions.
Then again, it's scalable cloud
infrastructure because the demand for
analytics and for data, became, becomes,
bigger and optimizing the inventory
manage, management, which also helps
drive up, customer satisfaction when.
Everything is available, everything
is planned, and the inventory
is there when customer needs it.
And Macy's example, so how Internet
of Things inventory tracking and
targeted advertising based on the
cloud is driving, their retail forward.
So first of all, it's real time inventory
tracking and they basically equip,
their shelves with RFIDs, technology
to monitor merchandise in real time.
It's also automated replenishment that
smart shelves that they have detect
low inventory and instantly notify,
store associates, for restocking.
Personalized in store marketing
Macy installs Bluetooth beacons.
to interact with the shopper's
smartphones via the application.
Of course, everything is with consent.
Enhanced customer engagement, because
beacons provide real time information, and
in retail, it's very important to be up
to speed, to be real time, because that
provides a much more engaging experience.
And data driven store optimization, data
collected from smart shelves and beacons
allow Macy's to analyze shopping patterns.
and product interactions.
Alibaba's new retail initiative
example, I think it's, we all know
Alibaba, it's a massive retailer.
they are well known for innovations
for blending, online and offline
and for developing online element.
So blending online and offline, commerce
using cloud is what Alibaba is doing as
part of their new retail initiatives.
first of all, it's unified
commerce ecosystem.
So they use cloud to integrate e
commerce platform, physical store and
create seamless retail environment.
It's data driven personalization
based on cloud analytics.
So all the customer behaviors and
preferences are being collected
and carefully understood.
So they get, customers can get
personalized offers, smart stores,
and internet of things integration.
They now launched what they call a
hammer fresh stores and internet of
things allowed them to in real time,
analyze and manage inventory and
provide interactive shopping experience.
Optimize supply chain and logistics.
Again, cloud based system.
Enable real time inventory
tracking and efficient fulfillment.
And enhanced mobile integration, where
mobile apps like Taobao or Alipay are
integrated with the physical retail.
Now, almost there.
Thanks for being with me.
Almost there.
Key takeaways and conclusion.
For me, it's very simple.
Retailer is either in the
cloud or out of business.
There is no other way.
So you either evolve and use all the
goodness, the AI, the cloud computing,
Internet of Things that we have.
Or you just will lose your customer who
will look for the right Cloud experience
somewhere else and key takeaways can
be summarized to five simple things.
First of all, we go to physical
store only if we want to.
Second, retail, retailer only as
good as it's online and mobile.
I think it's very important.
So you have to make sure that
your, online, store, your
mobile application is flawless.
Omni channel integration
defines customer experience.
And that's so true for today.
Predictive personalization is
imperative and AI is part of sales from
recommendation to support going forward.
So that's it.
Thanks for, being with me.
Thanks for having me.
And hopefully you enjoyed the
presentation and the case studies.
And if you have any questions, please
feel free to reach out via email.
Thank you.
Have a lovely conference.