Hi, everyone.
this is Pradeep Reddy Gupta.
I'm here to discuss, about cloud native
application and then its principles.
primarily Salesforce and its AI innovation
being leveraged as a cloud network
application and then how it's transforming
the AI, agentic AI in the CRM workspace.
And let's get into the agenda of this
discussion today and I'm going to
start with some introduction about
what is cloud native application and
then what its principles are and then
we'll deep dive into containerization
orchestration of these microservices
using cloud native application.
Kubernetes and then multicloud sub
multicloud support, metadata driven design
and how it's impacting or like improving
the scalability and performance of all
these SaaS applications behind the scenes.
and then at last, some Salesforce
agent AI in innovation, which
is called Salesforce Agent Force
built as cloud native application.
And then we'll end up some with
some conclusion note keynotes on it.
Thank you.
So introduction to cloud native
application, the cloud native
principles are main, back end
things that any cloud native
infrastructure app has to be built on.
So it has to be with some
containerization and then microservices
and then some orchestration.
And then for a metadata driven
support has to be there.
And then Salesforce platform AI is
indeed a cloud native application.
So it's leveraging all the
cloud native technologies.
to build and deploy services back in.
So those, the, it's offering a software as
service, but its infrastructure is built
on its own AWS servers, behind the scenes.
But it's offering all these through
orchestrations and then microservices
using Docker, containerization,
and then Kubernetes orchestration.
So if you look at this diagram,
any cloud infrastructure needs
to have all these containers.
All these backend services and
automation and then microservices
and modern metadata design.
So that's how any cloud native
app on an infrastructure works in
the behind the scenes platform.
There are cloud native principles.
So like I said, microservices,
containerization, orchestration, the
provisioning and then automation.
All of these are part and
parcel of this cloud native app.
So let's look into
containerization and microservices.
How Salesforce has transitioned
from a monolithic architectures to
microservices, and which are often
containerized and managed by Kubernetes,
which is the latest innovation.
And this allows for more agile
development, easier maintenance,
and better scalability of having
these platforms available on the, on
the servers, for all the customers.
By using microservices, Salesforce
can scale individual components of
its platform independently, improving
overall performance and resilience.
and then Kubernetes for orchestration.
If you think about, Salesforce using
Kubernetes is a, big microservices
platform behind the scenes, like on
its all environments, including both
on prem and public cloud deployments,
ensuring consistence and reliable service
deliverability for all its customers.
Kubernetes helps automated deployments,
scaling, and management of applications
aligning with cloud native principles,
primarily for automation and efficiency.
And then multi cloud support.
It can support all the multi clouds.
Salesforce has its own multi
clouds, and then they call us
like Salesforce Hyperforce.
It allows the platform to be
deployed on multiple platforms.
Public cloud providers like
AWS, Google Cloud, and Azure.
This flexibility is a hallmark of
cloud native applications, enabling
businesses to choose the best
infrastructure for their needs by
supporting multiple Cloud providers.
Salesforce ensures all its platform is
up running and easily replied and managed
across different environments without
significant reconfigurations because
it is supporting all multi clouds and
then it's all scalable and efficient.
And then when you talk about
metadata driven design.
Salesforce architecture itself is metadata
driven, and it's not dependent on like
on prem things, but it's all about more
dynamic and then more configurable, which
means most of its platform's functionality
is defined and managed through
metadata rather than hard coded logics.
The approach is more scalable
and customizable, and then
it's rapid in its development.
The metadata driven design, allows
easier integration with other cloud
native services, and then it can easily
integrate to other, SaaS applications.
And then scalability of performance.
So Salesforce cloud native design ensures
that the platform can handle large volumes
of data and then user traffic efficiently.
The use of distributed systems
and scalable storage solutions
like Salesforce database supports
high performance and reliability.
Which it means all possible
through the cloud native principles
that being followed in its
infrastructure behind the scenes.
And now let's dig into the
Salesforce agent force.
So Salesforce came up with a new
innovation in AI, which has been
investing as like Einstein and
then many other clouds in the past
to support all the CRM workspace.
Now they came up with the data
cloud and then agent force.
Both of them are, which are tightly
coupled with the CRM and then data and
then trust itself with the compliance.
So they all like, work hand in
hand to make, to ensure like the
virtual agents for customer service
or sales or marketing agents.
It's not it's replacing all the agents
jobs, but it's all about, an agent is
still working around the clock of the
business hours for all his customers.
It can be a chatbot.
It can be, any of those, on demand
support agents working virtually.
So that's how it's all.
But it's behind the scenes.
It's using data cloud and
then containerization.
The cloud native principles as
infrastructure built on AWS.
That's one of those, year.
let's dig into this, how these LLMs are
built on, the instant trust layer, what
they call, and then it's come up, it
comes with the data masking, and it comes
with a dynamic grounding, and then audit
trail, and then demasking, and then it
all also comes with a shield, and then
all the layers are like built on the SAS
platforms for which all behind the scenes
will be the, Cloud native application.
So this entire cloud itself
is Salesforce is built on it.
So at last I would like to conclude
this session with some conclusion.
By leveraging cloud native technologies,
Salesforce has been scaling its
services dynamically to meet
changing demand, ensuring consistent
performance for its users worldwide.
In summary, in a nutshell, Salesforce
cloud native principles by leveraging
containerization, microservices,
Kubernetes and admin editor driven
architecture to deliver scalable,
flexible and high performance cloud
applications for all its customers.
I hope you enjoyed this session.
and thank you very much for being with me.
And then I'm appreciating, and
giving thanking Conf42 platform
for giving me this opportunity
to leverage this content on.
Thank you.
Have a great day.