Hello everyone.
Today I'm going to talk
about migrations from on-prem
messaging systems to the cloud.
This is an introductory session
about messaging system migrations.
In this presentation, we're going to
discuss what a messaging system is,
the common pathways for migrating and
on-prem messaging system to the cloud.
The benefits of migrating.
Why you should consider going serverless
and the key factors or questions
you should discuss with your team.
Lastly, I'm also going to show you
some Python code to help you start
interacting with web MQ brokers as a
client and compare those interactions
with the Amazon SQS service.
So let's get started.
For a messaging system, there
are usually two categories.
The first is what we call
traditional message oriented
middleware or message brokers.
Typical examples include IBM
mq, active mq, or Web mq.
These are usually dedicated hardware
or infrastructure designed to
connect upstream and downstream
services to messaging transactions.
The other category is what we call cloud
native serverless messaging services.
For example, in Amazon Web services,
we have the Amazon SQS service and the
Amazon SNS service, which help with
queuing or broadcasting use cases.
Messaging system applications
are used across all industries.
The reason is that they allow you
to build loosely coupled, highly
scalable and fall tolerant systems.
Different industries, use them
in slightly different ways.
For financial services, we use
them for trades and transactions.
For retail, we use them
for auto processing.
For healthcare, they're used to retrieve
clinical data or patient records.
And for media, we use them for image and
video processing, just to name a few.
Some industries have slightly
different use cases and demand
for their messaging systems.
For example, in retail, you will usually
see a higher demand during peak hours,
like during weekdays, but then a lesser
demand during midnight or weekends.
Because of this difference, the
retail industry usually requires much
better scalability in terms of how
the messaging system is designed.
On the other hand, customers
from financial or government
organizations usually requires a
messaging system to be durable and
can be recovered during incidents.
But the good news is that all of
this can be migrated to the cloud,
and we see actual real world use
cases of these industries applying
their messaging systems to the cloud.
When starting on migration, you begin
with your own on-prem messaging systems.
However, when you maintain your
own on-prem messaging systems, you
soon realize the field drawbacks.
The first is definitely the
expense you have to manage.
Usually you have capacity
and operational cost.
Those are burdens you have
to deal with from the start.
For example, if you want to scale
up or double the capacity, you
need to spend additional budget on
provisioning more infrastructure just
to maintain the demand on your system.
Additionally, you will need to
allocate specific engineers with
specialized skillset to set up maintain.
Monitoring those messaging systems that
is a significant operational overhead
and can be difficult to scale up.
Therefore, a lot of organizations
decide to migrate their
messaging systems to the cloud.
There are a few different approaches.
The first is called D and shift,
where you essentially provision cloud
instances and try to mirror the same
environment you have on-prem to the cloud.
This is quite quick for migrations,
but there are some obvious drawbacks
we're going to discuss next.
Another approach is called
replatforming, which is moving
the system to a managed platform.
For example, in AWS, we
have the Amazon MQ service.
This provides additional benefits
compared to the lift and shift approach,
and is commonly seen with customers
who still want to use traditional
client broker interactions, but
want to reduce operational overhead.
Lastly, you have the cloud native
approach, which typically requires
you to refactor the client.
The benefit of this is that you get a
fully serverless architecture that allows
you to scale up easily without ever
having to worry about the need or demand
of your volumes or Drupal beforehand.
So scaling and maintaining of
the survey itself are now owned
by the cloud service provider.
For example, AWS, as I discussed
earlier, once you migrate from on-prem
to the cloud, your responsibilities
gradually shift more towards a cloud
service provider for on-prem services.
Then you own the entire server.
You own all of the responsibilities from
the very low end of the physical layer.
Storage, capacity management,
physical security, all of that up to
the application and business logic.
Everything is managed by your own team.
Now, when you move to infrastructure
level services like EC2, the physical
server and the provisioning of the actual
instances become the responsibility of
the cloud provider, you will still have
a shared responsibility for security.
Physical security is managed by
AWS, but you will still have to
manage infrastructure level and
configuration level security.
You'll also have to manage OS level
configurations, low level broker, engine
maintenance, and security patches.
All of that still has to
be managed by your team.
So there is still some
operational overhead.
That's why we have managed services.
Beyond infrastructure services where
you are already using cloud service
providers to manage the physical layers.
Managed services also handle low level
tasks like security and system patching.
This leaves your team with more
focus on capacity planning,
application and business level.
Next you go with service services,
let's say Amazon SQS or SNS service.
Your only responsibility becomes
the business logic itself.
Capacity and scaling are fully
managed by the cloud service provider.
It will be transparent for your client,
allowing you to focus entirely on
your business logic, confident that
the system can scale based on demand.
A serverless architecture has a few
benefits compared to traditional
infrastructure based messaging brokers.
First off, it allows you to
decouple infrastructure concerns
from the actual business logic.
Serverless architecture, as a
name suggests, is serverless,
so you do not need to worry
about scaling up the servers.
Scaling is managed by the service
based on demand pricing model,
therefore also changes to be on demand.
For example, back to the retail
industry I mentioned earlier where
there might not be a lot of volume
during weekends or midnights.
You don't have to worry about wasted
resources because it will automatically
scale down during low usage hours.
You are only charged for the API
calls you make to the service as
compared to keeping an entire broker
fleet running just to maintain
system operations during those times.
Serverless architecture also allows
you to maintain high availability
and resiliency because the backend
infrastructure is maintained and
managed by the cloud service provider,
in this case, the SQS or SNS service.
Now let's talk about different
migration strategies.
The quickest way to
migrate is called rehost.
This is quite straightforward.
You deploy cloud in and try to mirror
your entire system, the OS level
and the broker engine configurations
to match your own on-prem systems.
This means your application logic
will not change much and you have
a lot of customization and control
in selecting the type of os.
Broker engine or broker version you want.
However, because essentially only
the physical layers are moving to the
cloud, a lot of the infrastructure
and operational overhead is
still retained within your team.
You have to manage security, patching,
broker monitoring, and security Consider.
It'll also be a little difficult to
integrate with other services like
IAM Services or CloudWatch monitoring
to see if the broker is healthy and
operational or how many clients are
connected because those metrics are not
natively integrated within E two service.
That is where a managed
platform comes into play.
For example, you can use Amazon MQ
as a managed broker hosting platform.
There are a lot of benefits to this.
To start when you set it up, you will only
focus on a few key areas of configuration.
You will focus on the type of deployment
you want, whether it's a single node
deployment or cluster deployment.
Then you will configure the instance
size, but it will now need to configure
the OS version memory or CPU course.
All of that is now simplified
into the instant size.
You also don't have to worry about
integrations with monitoring services.
Those are natively integrated
and enabled by default.
When you want to s scale up in the future,
let's say you see your demand score
two or three times, you can simply edit
the broker to a higher instance size.
With just a few clicks and a reboot,
you will have a much larger instance
capacity in comparison if deploy
the same broker on EC2 instances.
You have to manage the
configuration yourself.
Go into the rapid MQ configuration
file and reconfigure the
memory usage and parameters.
All of that is now fully managed
by the Amazon MQ service.
That saves your team a lot of operational
overhead because it's a managed service,
security already follows best practices.
For example, it enforces
TRS transactions and allows.
To set up a KMS key to encrypt
your data at rest, security
patching and broker maintenance are
automatically managed by the service.
You can select a weekly maintenance
window, allowing the MQ service
to update and maintain the broker.
During that time, you might select
a time when it is not heavily used
like midnight, allowing the service
to automatically patch up and reboot
the broker for optimal performance.
Now let's take a closer look at
the Amazon MQ servicing detail.
First, it supports the same protocol
you commonly see in Rev MQ brokers,
such as a MQP, 0.9 0.1, and 1.0.
When you deploy a broker, it comes by
default with management plugins that
power the web MQ web console As far
as the shovel and federation plugins.
As I discussed earlier, you natively have
integrations with CloudWatch Matrixes.
This allows you to see how many clients
are connected, how many connection
channels are open, how much RAM
the broker is using, and how many
messages are there in the broker.
You can even see metrics at
destination level, like how many
messages are there in each queue.
Additionally, you'll have
data logs for the broker.
These logs allow you to see warnings or
error signs for further troubleshooting
and monitoring, just in case a
broker experience connection issues
or gets overwhelmed by traffic.
As discussed, there are two types
of broker deployments, single node
deployment, and cluster deployment.
Let's discuss both in detail.
For a single node deployment,
you have one instance deployed
in one availability zone.
From an availability perspective, this is
not quite ready for production use cases.
For example, if there's a downtime
in that availability zone, it usually
means you will use access to the broker.
However, it is cheaper compared to a
cluster deployment, making it ideal
for profile, concept or development
use cases, allowing you to set
up a broker while saving costs.
When you want to move into production.
We strongly recommend moving.
To a cluster deployment.
In a cluster deployment, messages are
mirrored across three different nodes
in three different availability zones.
Even if one of the availability
zones becomes inaccessible or one
of the nodes crashes, you still
have two other availability zones
for your clients to connect to
because the messages are mirrored.
No data will be lost.
This is a critical feature
for production and we highly
recommend organizations to use it.
Now let's take a look at how a Python
client interacts with revenue MQ brokers.
The first thing you want to do is set
up the basic connection parameters.
You will define the connection
protocols and parameters like
encryption through TLS 1.2.
Next, you define the connection
endpoint for the broker.
Then you set up the connection and
channel using the packet library.
The channel is essentially a
lightweight connection used by a
client or process to interact with
the broker as a producer or consumer.
Once the connection is set up, you can
define your producers and consumers.
For producers, you first need
to declare the destination
your messages are going to.
You can declare a queue defined by
name, and then send a message to it.
You can also send a message to an
exchange, but the default exchange
will simply route the message to
the queue using the queue name.
So it's essentially the same as sending
the message directly to the queue.
Because this is a connection based
protocol, you must make sure to close
the connection once you're finished
publishing or sending messages.
Otherwise, the connection will remain open
and waste resources on the broker side.
On the consumer side, you can
use a get message function
and specify the name of the Q.
You want to pull message form.
Once you get a message, you have
to use basic act, acknowledging
the message so the broker knows it
was received by the client and can
remove it from the broker side.
Without this acknowledgement,
the broker will eventually
consider the consumer application
inactive and close the connection.
So make sure to acknowledge messages.
After acknowledging and processing
the messages, always remember
to close the consumer channels
and the connection itself.
This ensures it is properly
closed, freeing up resources
for other connections.
For more marginalized services, or
if you want to embrace full service
approach, you must first refactor
your client and messaging systems
during this refactor, the first thing
to consider is separating the roles.
Processes, you need to clearly separate
the producers from the consumers.
The reason for this is to decouple them
when deployed in the cloud, allowing them
to scale independently and be updated
without dependencies on one another.
For example, if you have a backup
in a queue, you can scale up
your consumers without ramping up
additional producer connections.
You also want to understand
your massive delivery models.
You need to determine whether
you need point-to-point delivery
or a published subscribe model.
The difference between the two is simple.
When a message is sent to a destination,
do you want it to be received
only once by a single consumer?
Or do you want it to
be broadcasted across?
All consumers subscribed
to that designation.
Essentially, it's about whether
the method is processed once
overall or once per consumer.
From an MQ broker perspective,
you can handle both models
within a single infrastructure.
For publish subscribe, you can
use topics or exchanges depending
on whether you use MQ or Rev mq.
MQ Brokers also have queues for
point-to-point interactions, allowing
messages to be processed just once in
a run Robin manner across consumers.
However, when you move to serverless
solutions like Amazon SQS and SNS,
these are two distinct services designed
to handle different delivery models.
Amazon Simple Notification Service
SNS, uses a published subscribe model.
You have a topic, consumers subscribe
to that topic, and all consumers receive
the same message from the producer.
On the other hand, the simple Q Service
SQS uses a point-to-point delivery model,
allowing a message to be received and
processed only once by a single consumer
rather than across all consumers.
Now let's look at some example Python
code for interacting with SQS, and we
will compare it to how we interact with
Web MQ brokers, as I showed you earlier.
First with SQS, there's no
real connection management.
You only need to define or manage the
queues and then send and receive messages.
Because you don't have persistent
connection to manage, you can
focus more directly on the business
logic of handling each message.
To start, you can create a queue.
In SQS using the create queue
method, you define the name and basic
characteristics of the queue, such
as the message retention period.
Text and access policies.
You can then use the queue
name to get the queue handle.
You can also remove the queue
once you have the queue handle
by calling the delete method.
When working as a producer, you send
messages through the send message,
API call you first, get the queue by
its name to access the handle, and
then send a message to that queue.
You define the My body.
And can include various attri attributes
or texts attached to the message
such as trace IDs or other IDs.
On the consumer side, you
use receive message calls to
pull message from the queue,
similar to Rev MQ, where you
have to acknowledge the message
after you receive a message.
In SQS, you have to delete
it using a delete operation.
Once you get the message, you
receive a message handle, which you
use to call the delete operation
to remove it from the queue.
If you do not delete the message, it'll
return to the queue and become visible
again after a certain period of time that
it define when refactoring your client.
To move from a traditional method
broker to services like SQS or
SNS, the first thing to consider
is protocol compatibility.
A typical worker relies on
connection based protocols like
A MQP web sots, or open wire.
But when working with serverless
architectures, the protocol now
becomes H-T-D-P-S or GMS APIs.
These are API based connections,
not persistent connections.
You are making API calls to a
service to send or receive messages.
You also want to consider whether you
need strict message ordering or if you
can sacrifice a little bit of other
preservation for higher scalability.
For example, SQS offers standard cues
and FIFA first in first out queues.
FIFA cues.
Maintain the exact order of messages
while standard queues, provide
best effort ordering, but allow
you to scale almost infinitely.
Additionally, because these are serverless
architectures built within the cloud
ecosystem, you gain much more visibility.
For example, you can enable cloud
trial to lock all data requests.
This give you a detailed request
level look to see when the message
was sent, when it was received,
the origin IP address, and the user
roles involved allowing for far
better tracking and monitoring.
Furthermore, because these are native
AWS services, they integrate easily
with IAM or IAM, identity Center for
Authentication and authorization.
In contrast with Rev mq, even if
hosted on Amazon MQ service, you might
have to set up an LDAP server rather
than I am users or roles for the same
authentication and authorization purpose.
There are some limitations to be
aware of the migrating to SQS or SNS.
For example.
There's a default payload limitation of
up to one megabytes from message sites.
However, you can get around
this by using Java or Python
library extensions built by AWS.
Which allow you to have massive
message bodies up to two gigabytes by
utilizing the S3 service on the backend.
What this means is that when you send
a message through SQS or SNS, instead
of sending the entire payload, the
library uploads the message object to
an S3 bucket, and only sends a pointer
to that object within your message.
Producer transfers the pointer
as a message to the consumer,
effectively increasing your message
size limit from my one megabytes
all the way up to two gigabytes.
Those are some key factors to
consider the migrating your
message system to the cloud.
You need to understand the technologies
to see if there are any limitations,
constraints or changes compared
to your current environment.
You also need to plan how you will
handle authentication and authorization.
Your clients still need to engage
with the service, so understanding
the available security method
is critical to ensuring seamless
integration with the current systems.
You also want to consider
the deployment settings.
When deploying on-prem, you
have complete customization.
Once you move to managed services,
certain configurations are taken
out of your deployment settings and
managed entirely by the service itself.
Lastly, you need to understand
how you want to operate
and monitoring the service.
On-prem messaging systems, you
can connect directly to the
server to get a full set of data.
But in a cloud environment, it usually
depend on monitoring services like
CloudWatch, utilizing matrix and
logging to manage and monitor the
health of your messaging system.
That brings us to the
end of the presentation.
Hopefully you now have a better
understanding of the migration process.
From on-prem to the cloud.
We cover the overall benefits of
migrating to a serverless architecture,
the different pathways for migration,
and the fact that migration requires
both application level changes like code
modifications and adjustments to how you
operate at business and operational level.
Thank you.