Hello everyone.
My name is Sai Chiran, and today I'm
excited to talk about a technology
that is redefining how we connect and
communicate in an increasingly digital
world, software defined networking.
We are living in a world where
connectivity is no longer
a luxury, it's a necessity.
Consider this every second over
127 new devices are connected to
this internet from smart homes
and autonomous vehicles to remote
surgeries and industrial automation.
Our world is becoming more connected
and intelligent by the minute.
But with this growth comes a challenge.
A traditional networks
are struggling to keep up.
Today, I'll show you how SDN is not just
solving this challenge, but also paving
the way for the future of IOT and 5G.
This is more than just a technology.
It's a foundation of our
hyper connected world.
Let's discuss about
the rise of IOT and 5G.
By 2025, the number of connected devices
is expected to exceed 75 billion.
This rapid expansion of IOT ecosystems
presents unprecedented scaling challenges.
Demanding networks that are intelligent
and adaptive 5g further raises the
stakes with ultra low latency under one
milliseconds which enables Real time
applications like autonomous driving
and remote surgeries speeds exceeding
20 gbps Supporting high definition
streaming and immersive AR VR experiences.
Traditional network architecture
are rigid and hardware centric.
Unable to meet these dynamic demands,
this is where software defined
networking steps in by decoupling the
control plane from the data plane.
SDN enables intelligent
resource allocations.
Centralized control and
unmatched network flexibility.
Let's discuss about the
transformative paradigm in SDN.
SDN is revolutionary for
three primary reasons.
Centralized control.
SDN centralizes network management
through a single control plane,
allowing real time programmability
and efficient resource utilization.
This enhances operational
efficiency and enables rapid
implementation of network policies.
Number two, which is
dynamic resource allocation.
It intelligently distributes bandwidth
and computing resources as needed.
Optimizing network performance
even during peak usages.
Enhance flexibility.
SDN eliminates hardware dependencies
through software based network
configurations, allowing networks to
adapt instantly to changing requirements.
These capabilities transform
traditional static networks into
agile, programmable platforms that can
support the complexities of IoT and 5G.
Now let's move on to software
defined networking in smart cities.
In smart cities, SDN enables
intelligent infrastructure management
and operational efficiencies.
Reduced power consumption, smart
grids powered by SDN reduce
energy consumption by up to 40%.
Through intelligent load balancing and
real time resource optimizations, improved
fault detection, advanced software defined
networking, monitoring systems cut fault
detection times by 30 percent, ensuring
rapid response to infrastructure issues,
and minimizing service disruptions.
From adaptive traffic management to
efficient public utilities, software
defined networking plays a crucial
role in making urban environments more
efficient, sustainable, and resilient.
Now, let's move on to software defined
networking in an industrial IoT.
SDN is also transforming industrial
IoT by providing dynamic network
orchestration, real time monitoring.
It enables microsecond level
monitoring of industrial systems.
With predictive maintenance,
reducing downtime by up to 45%.
Automated control.
AI driven automation optimizes
production efficiency through
intelligent resource allocation.
This ensures ultra low latency
and seamless integration
of thousands of sensors.
And AccuTutor's enhancing productivity
and operational efficiency
in industrial environments.
Now let's talk about software defined
networking and 5G network slicing.
SDN is a key enabler of network
slicing in 5G, allowing multiple
virtual networks to operate on
the same physical infrastructure.
Enhance Enhanced Mobile Broadband,
which is EMBB, delivers ultra fast
speeds and massive connectivity for
high definition streaming, virtual
reality, and gaming experiences.
URLLC, which is Ultra Reliable Low Latency
Communication, which supports Real time
applications like autonomous vehicles,
remote surgery, and industrial automation.
Software defined networking intelligently
partitions the network into virtual
lanes, each tailored to specific
applications, ensuring optimal
performance and quality of service.
Now let's discuss about the key
challenges of software defined networking.
Despite its transformative
potential, software defined
networking faces several challenges.
Seamless integration.
Complex integration with legacy
systems and diverse communication
protocols is a significant barrier
and it comes with latency bottlenecks,
which where centralized control
architectures can introduce latency
in time sensitive applications.
Scalability.
As networks grow in complexity,
maintaining performance across distributed
systems becomes increasingly challenging.
Overcoming these challenges.
Requires innovative solutions in
network architecture Control mechanisms
and resource management to fully
realize software defined networks
potential Now, let's talk about the
edge computing integration in sdn
an effective approach to overcoming
latency scalability challenges Is edge
computing integration reduces latency?
By processing data closer to the
source, edge computing reduces round
trip transmission times by up to
60%, ensuring faster responses time.
Enhances responsiveness.
It supports real time decision making
for critical IoT and 5G applications.
Integrating edge computing
with SDN optimizes network
performance while maintaining
reliable low latency operations
for next generation applications.
Now, let's talk about
leveraging OpenFlow protocol.
The OpenFlow protocol is
fundamental to SDN implementation.
Standardized communication,
which provides consistent network
control across diverse hardware
through unified protocol standards.
Interoperability, which ensures seamless
integration between different vendors
networking equipment, and flexibility.
OpenFlow allows dynamic network
reconfiguration and real time
policy updates, enabling centralized
programming of network behavior.
This standardized interface enhances
network flexibility and interoperability
across multi vendor environments.
Now let's jump into software defined
networking impact on spectrum utilization.
SDN also optimizes spectrum utilization.
Which is essential for 5g and iot
environments 30 efficiency improvement
through dynamic spectrum allocations
Sdn maximizes bandwidth usage in real
time 2x network capacity intelligent
resource management doubles device support
while maintaining quality of service
these advancements maximize throughput
and minimize interference Supporting
the rapid growth of connected devices.
Now let's jump into software defined
networking, where the backbone of IOT 5G
convergence to conclude software defined
networking is a backbone enabling the
convergence of IOT and 5G technologies.
It reduces latency by up to 60%.
Through intelligent data routing,
optimizes data flows across
millions of devices, enhancing
efficiency and performance.
Scale seamlessly to support the
explosive growth of smart devices.
This transformative architecture
creates an adaptive ecosystem that
dynamically responds to changing demands.
enhances security and drives
the intelligent future of
digital infrastructure.
The future isn't just
about connecting devices.
It's about creating intelligent,
adaptive ecosystems that can
anticipate and respond to our needs.
Software defined networking is the key
to unlocking this feature, bridging
the gap between IOT and 5G to create
a truly hyper connected world.
As we stand on the brink of this digital
revolution, One thing is certain.
Networks will no longer
be passive pipelines.
There will be intelligent systems
driving innovation across every industry.
Software defined networking is
leading this transformation.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone for your attention.