Hello, everyone.
My name is Adrian Machado.
I'm a staff engineer at Zupelo API
management, and I wanted to talk
to you about why your API needs to
operate at the edge or the worldwide
edge, as it's sometimes called.
In this talk, I'm going to go over quite
a few things with regard to the edge.
So if you're not familiar with the
edge or serverless, don't you worry,
I'm going to cover that for you.
I'm also going to cover some
considerations and trade offs
that you should consider,
before you adopt the Edge.
It's not just like a silver bullet
that's going to improve the performance
of your APIs or microservices.
I'm also going to talk about why
APIs, specifically, are a good
Application of the edge, why they're
well suited to be deployed to the
edge or at least parts of APIs.
And then finally, I'm going to end
with a quick demo of an edge API
that I built, and it's going to help
showcase some of the trade offs that
I mentioned earlier in the talk, as
well as how you can debug performance
issues when building an edge API.
So let's jump into it.
So who am I?
I'm Adrian.
Like I mentioned earlier, I'm
a staff engineer at Zuplo.
I love writing about all things
API related, and I also create a
lot of open source API tooling.
One thing I created recently is called
RateMyOpenAPI, which is an open source
API governance and scoring tool.
I'm also a big fan of shoehorns,
just decided to throw that in there.
If you don't currently use a shoehorn
to put on your shoes, you should.
It's definitely a lifestyle enhancer.
I like to qualify.
The people attending my talks, just so
you don't waste your time, 20, 30 minutes
on a talk that you don't find useful.
So I think you'll enjoy this presentation
if you're one of the following buckets.
If you're like an API engineer
or developer that's looking to
modernize and legacy API stack
using the latest and greatest, I
think this talk is good for you.
If you're an executive, like a
CTO that oversees API development,
you're learning, techniques and
architectures to help improve API
developer experience at your company.
Whether that's internal APIs or external
APIs, but especially public facing
external APIs, this is a good fit for you.
If you're just looking to build an API
for the first time, and you don't know
the best practices and tools that you
should be using, this is also a good
talk to you, and this is not a very
introductory level, but it's a good
high level concept around the edge, so
it's not gonna get too in the weeds.
So let's start with what
exactly the edge is.
So when you typically deploy a
microservice or an API, your application
or API is deployed to a single region
or a data center that's EU West
one, or maybe that's NA East two.
Wherever it's deployed, it's
in some geographic, region and.
Unfortunately, we operate in a world where
our users can be anywhere, so all of these
requests from around the world need to be
routed through all these, undersea cables,
and eventually they get to the your data
center, and by the time the response gets
back, it's gonna have pretty high latency,
sometimes in the order of seconds.
If a call is coming from, let's say Japan
and hitting your data center in Munich.
So there are some ways of getting around
this that has have been explored in the
kind of application development space
slash front end development space,
CDNs, which stand for content delivery
networks, were created to host the
static content that is closer to users.
So think like images, JavaScript,
fonts, all of those will be hosted
in some local data center in Japan,
and when you load a web page, all of
those will be able to load faster, and.
those are typically chosen one because
there's static content, so they can be
essentially cashed and two because they're
typically large files that would take
a long time to deliver over a network.
But a problem arose, this is all
well and good for websites over
for dynamic content like code.
Your compute, essentially,
is going to be slow.
the actual processing of the website,
the rendering of the webpage, that
can't all be cached because it's
essentially rerun every single time.
a bunch of, CDN creators, like CloudFlare,
Vercel, who works a lot in the application
space, they all got together and they
formed like a working group called
WinterCG and they came up with this
idea around deploying Code to the edge.
When I talk about code, I'm primarily
talking about function as a service.
So if you're familiar with AWS Lambda,
for example, or Google Cloud Run, then
you'll know what function as a service is.
Essentially, it's just like an
isolated function that is spun up.
So realistically, it'll execute some
code and then It'll be essentially put
to sleep when it's done and another
request will come in and wake it up again.
So these are, this code is actually
distributed at the pop layer.
So it's essentially at the same
level that your CDN operates in.
And what's nice about this is it provides
like a lightweight runtime that typically
has a zero millisecond cold start.
When I was talking earlier about latency,
one characteristic we talked about was,
the round trip time to even get to the
data center, but if you don't have an
active instance of your application
or like essentially a warm VPC or a
machine, essentially, or server that
is, actively taking requests, if a new
one needs to be like spun up to handle
some requests, that's going to take
a lot of time, especially with how
heavy, Run times like no GS can be.
So what's nice about edge is
that typically this run time
is super lightweight and has
a zero millisecond cold start.
So not only are you close to your user,
your application code will actually wake
up and execute faster, which is good for
instant responses like APIs and web pages.
There are some tradeoffs,
though, with most Edge runtimes.
I'm going to go into some a little
bit later, but your bundle size, the
languages you can use, and even the
libraries you can use are limited.
And some examples of Edge compute
platforms include Clever Workers, as well
as the Vercel Edge for web development.
So now let's go into those tradeoffs
that I mentioned because the edge
might sound good, it sounds great to
be able to run your code essentially
as close to your customers as
possible, but it's not a silver bullet.
So let's start with the edge runtime.
So the edge runtime primarily
the one that I'm familiar with is
the one developed by cloud flare.
It's Currently limited to
JavaScript only right now with
some support for WebAssembly.
So if you're, someone developing an API
or application in Python or in Rust, for
example, you're out of luck unless you
can compile that down to WebAssembly.
Otherwise, if you're doing You know,
your basic work in like scripting
application, but not like Node.
js, you should be fine to run
your application at the edge.
there is some limited support for Node.
js libraries, but most of these
are done by hand by the Winter
CG group, so you can't just.
Import a Node.
js library and expect it
to work out of the box.
A lot of times if it, relies on like
TCP or other networking APIs that Node.
js exposes, it probably won't work.
And there's also limits on
the maximum bundle size.
I think It's something like 100
megabytes or 10 megabytes can
remember off the top of my head.
It depends on the platform
you're executing on and it
always changes over time.
But yeah, you can't have a massive
application running on this function
as a service, which is similar to
existing fast applications like Lambda.
I will say, though, that things
are getting a little bit better.
There are many libraries out there
that now have support, or they have,
essentially, an edge version of their
library that doesn't rely on Node.
js primitives.
And any library that's built to run in
the browser for JavaScript can typically
be executed at the edge as well.
Because the edge is essentially a
version of the V8 runtime that's
used in your browser, which is
why it's so fast and lightweight.
So aside from complications with
the runtime, a big factor on why or
whether or not you should use the
edge is where your data is located.
So your compute may be globally
distributed, which is super nice,
but your database and or data store,
wherever you're storing your data
is often not globally distributed.
And this results in actually.
pretty poor latency characteristic
when you're doing something like a crud
operation because you have to account
for not just the time to access your
function, but the round trip time from
like your edge location to your database
and then back from your database to
your edge function, which can often
lead to worse response times than if
you just Co located your function and
your database in a single data center.
It depends where the call is coming from,
but this is often the case due to routing.
You can also end up exhausting
connections to your database as well.
You can imagine, if you have users all
around the world, they're all invoking
all these different edge functions.
If you're doing something like
connection pooling, you can
probably easily exceed the number of
connections that your database allows.
And.
you might just end up stuck or locked out.
And again, this leads to worse latency.
I'd like to mention that there
are answers to all of these kind
of issues, and I'm going to start
covering some of them right now.
So this is an image that indicates,
demonstrates what I'm talking about.
You have this central function in
the middle here that's really nice.
But then, you have your
functions over here and you're
trying to return data to users.
And it's just a long trip from your
function to your server over here
and then back through your database.
the easiest to adopt way to
mitigate this problem is to
introduce a database proxy database.
A proxy is essentially a kind of layer
that will be like a gateway, to your
database, where the functions as a
service or edge functions will connect
to it instead of database directly.
And then this database proxy will
field all of these connections and
maintain its own pool of connections
to connect to the database.
So it won't exhaust the
connections to your database.
And you end up with crashing on
your Postgres or anything like that.
So there are solution managed solutions
out there like Prisma Accelerate.
I think AWS has something
called like RDS proxy as well.
And, this is like an easy solution
is you don't have to change anything
about like your database configuration.
From my understanding, you can just simply
start connecting to a proxy instead,
and it'll manage all the connections
from your edge functions automatically.
yeah, so like I mentioned, this is
good if you're like transitioning
from an existing database, and
you can also introduce caching at
the database proxy layer as well.
Rather than, using one of the
connection pools, if you if your
query is something that is cash,
then it could return it directly.
And that's the best case possible
is if your data is stored
somewhere close to your function.
There is another solution out there, which
is essentially having a global data store.
So that would be like distributing your
database across multiple regions, which
is very common in high scale systems,
I'd say, in order to minimize latency,
whether you're using the edge or not.
So you can use a specialized type of
database like Cassandra or CockroachDB,
which can be placed closer to your edge
function, not exactly in the same place.
Layer.
you can imagine you have a database for
Japan and then you have edge locations in
Tokyo and Osaka that will connect to that.
And it's going to be a lot less
of a round trip time to get there.
The trade off here is
going to be primarily with.
consistency, depending on
how you do your writes.
So if you're doing like asynchronous
writes, and this is just like a read
replica that you placed in Japan, you
can potentially have stale data because
it's going to take time for the writes
that happened in, let's say, Munich, to
propagate to your read replica in Japan.
if you do them asynchronously.
Or, you can have issues with latency.
If you're doing synchronous, right?
So if you hold on to your database
and your replica and lock it while
you're performing rights, then you
can have slow reads because of that
database replica might be locked
while you're serving API calls.
So there are definitely tradeoffs here,
but typically this can result in better
performance and kind of solves the issue.
just like a basic image of you have
your main data store somewhere in
North America distributed and Europe
and Africa and all over the world.
There's a third solution, which is
a little bit less common, I'd say,
but it's becoming more popular.
And that's the idea that you
know, your data should live where
it needs to live, where it would
provide the best user experience.
So in some cases, you can have data that
is hosted or cached at the edge itself.
And there are different
kind of use cases here.
So say you want to do some
sort of like blob storage,
some sort of like cash, right?
you can use a solution like Cloudflare's
R2, which is essentially an edge
distributed, edge, blob store.
if you want to do Database transactions
and want to have something like a per
user database or per instance database.
Maybe you want to have a database
that's specific to like a region for
GDPR compliance or something like that.
Then you can use D1 from Cloudflare
or Upstash to have an edge distributed
SQLite database that lives very close to
users and is locked to a certain region.
Lastly, if you want to do something
like, key value store, Redis and
Vercel both provide solutions for
their for like key value store, which
is, good for like configurations,
for example, that you don't want to
travel to a central location for.
But again, there are going to be that
kind of trade off of consistency.
So this is ideal for configurations or
data that doesn't get updated very often
or doesn't need to be like replicated, So
this is a happy path where each kind of
instance has its own database over here
and everyone lives happily ever after.
So that's a basic idea of the tradeoffs
of deploying an application to the edge.
But why should you deploy your API to the
edge or parts of your API to the edge?
when it comes to APIs these
days, especially public APIs, I
think performance matters a lot.
Your public API users can be anywhere.
And, this is by nature of
you actually have no control
over what your customers do.
Once give them like an API key, they can
deploy, their application, which uses your
API anywhere, whether your API customers
in Japan or China or in Africa, you don't
know where their customer is going to
be, but you're going to have to serve
all that traffic all the same, right?
And if you don't have good performance
characteristics in a certain region,
that can be like lost customers
for your company, for example.
and another thing that is nice
about APIs, I'd say, is how
compute heavy they can often be.
So I'd say like a lot of work done by
APIs is often just filtering out calls.
So that's, and I'll get to some
examples later, but like a lot of
time spent within an API, besides like
the actual like CRUD and like data
portion of it, is just like compute.
If you're doing a lot of compute based
work, that's good to actually move that
portion of your A P I code to the edge.
So to give you like an example of
the tail of two calls over here
on the left, we have an example.
If you're doing like a single region
where you know your data centers
history in Dallas, Texas and your A P
I calls coming in from Japan, you have
some customer over there essentially
just to do something like Yeah.
Authentication even if
you're denying the request.
Let's say they forgot their API key.
You have to travel all the way from
Japan over to Texas over here to do
your off handshake and then you travel
all the way back just to say 401.
It's not a very good experience.
Versus over here when you deploy to earth
or that's commonly known as like how
to deploy to the edges to point earth
because you deploy globally typically,
you essentially can have this edge
based proxy in front that can do stuff
like authentication, authorization, a
lot of again, the compute based stuff
that can result in like quick returns
of responses in case of invalid data
or invalid, like tokens are sent over.
So examples of work that can be done
at the edge that's compute heavy,
authentication and authorization unless
you, if you're, especially if you're
in housing this through something like
API keys, or, anything basically other
than using like a, like an identity
provider, if you're doing it, Yourself
or you're writing the code yourself
doing it at the edge is a lot faster.
You can respond with that for a wine or
403 so much faster compared to having
to travel all the way across continents.
If you're doing logging and
monitoring within your API,
doing that within the edge is.
Again, going to be faster.
it's just code being executed.
Request validation again is something
that's going to be a lot faster.
You can use libraries like AJV, for
example, or Zod at the edge, and
you can do schema validation of like
request body and filter out like that
request or SQL injections or any kind
of like bad stuff that like a WAF
would catch web application firewall.
so Bot filtering or bad actor filtering
or even filtering out agents these days.
you can do that all at the edge
as well, because that's all just
like computations being run.
More interesting to be done at the
edge is rate limiting, for example.
So rate limiting at the edge
will actually have a win effect.
The win, I'd say, is that since you're
doing it, since you're filtering
out at the edge, it doesn't make
it to your central service at all.
so wherever you're, Your actual like API
and microservices are hosted and that
reduces the number of requests going to
them, which frees them up for with more
resources to actual handle legit requests.
So you might actually end up with
like better latency by introducing
rate limiting for your customers.
And you also filter out, like
DDoS attacks and stuff like that.
The last one I want to mention
that is really good to be
done at the edge is caching.
So if your API is amenable to caching,
so let's say it's like a basic like trud,
that first call may take like a while
depending on where your data store is,
but subsequent calls to that Same API will
have like very good performance because
essentially it's stored at the CDN layer.
It's cash.
your user in Japan doesn't need
to, the request doesn't need to
leave Osaka to get like data.
So like refreshing a webpage, will
be very quick or navigating back to
a webpage that you previously loaded.
So I'd say like my ideal setup and
the one that I advocate for when
it comes to running APIs at the
edge is as follows, essentially.
You run all of those functionality
that I mentioned earlier at the edge,
and in that case, that should be done
probably at the API gateway layer.
So you should have, an API gateway
that can run at the edge, and that's
what I work on at Zuplo, actually, is
developing an API gateway that can run
at the edge, whereas your microservices
that actually, serve your API traffic
are hosted somewhere close to where
your data store is, and ideally
replicated across multiple regions.
So you would have, a read replica of
your database, as well as a kind of
like function as a service or Lambda of
your actual microservice hosted, one in
the US, one in Japan, one in Germany,
and you would have these, your gateway
distributed to specific cities like Munich
and in, I don't know, London and London.
Maybe the west coast of the U. S. And
the east coast of the U. S. you can do
a lot of that filtering at the edge,
but the computer is actually done within
some central server close to your data.
So you can minimize latency on this
kind of gives you a lot of freedom, too.
So you're not limited by having your
microservices be bound by like the
restrictions of the edge runtime.
You can write your code in like Django
or Python or whatever you want to do.
That's fine.
It's just that the gateway
layer would be written in like
JavaScript, essentially, or wasm.
And, Yeah, this is probably
like the ideal scenario.
I wouldn't say many companies run this way
yet, it's becoming, I'd say, increasingly
popular as APIs become like a product more
than just like an infrastructure piece.
And, a company like Scribe, for
example, that sells their API and runs
at a huge scale probably wants to,
pursue a solution similar to this.
as I promised at the beginning.
early in the talk, I'm going to give
you a quick demo of an edge API that
I built when I talk about an edge API,
essentially, I tried to have as much as
the code and the data live as close to me
as possible where my local data center is.
The application I decided to build here
is an ATM locator, so if you ever use
like a banking app, trying to find like
an ATM nearby, and you didn't use Google
Maps for some reason, I don't know why
you wouldn't, but, this is in every
banking app I'm aware of, essentially you
find all of the local, ATMs of Capital
One, let's say, nearby, and, what's nice
about this and like why I decided to
build this at the edge, a few things.
One, ATM locations, essentially,
essentially, They can be like
replicated in store at the edge
because, one like location of ATMs are
specific to a specific like region,
like you're not going to look at,
ATMs in London when you live in New
York, that just wouldn't make sense.
there's no reason why like
your data needs to be like.
totally replicated, for every single
user, and it's also really written
to like it takes a long time.
I assumed to install an ATM.
So the API or like the data store
for writing to a specific regions
ATM list probably doesn't happen very
often unless you have something like
I don't know, like downtime monitoring
or something like that of your ATMs.
But again, I'd say like the
number of right query is going
to this is going to be very low.
I also think that the performance of
this API is going to matter a lot.
Someone's probably, looking around,
probably needs cash quickly for settling
up like at the bar or they forgot their
credit card at home, but they have like
their debit card for some reason, and
they just want to find an ATM quickly.
they want to open up the app,
be able to find the closest
ATM super fast, navigate there.
In your instant time, essentially,
and another good thing about this, I'd
say, carrying off like the previous
point is that you can cash these
results super easily since again, it's
like very local and rarely updated.
So you can have a long lived
cash for best performance.
In terms of the data set I'm going to
use to build this API, I'm going to
use Capital One's Nessie Hackathon API,
which is essentially just a virtual bank.
it's like a subset of their
data, of their banking data,
including stuff like ATM locations.
And, one thing I'll mention is
that their API performance is
actually already really good.
The reason why I choose, chose
Capital One actually is because
I know they're a company that's
already adopted serverless and edge
functions for their APIs at scale.
And I'm just going to quickly
show you what that looks like.
Essentially, if you fire a request
against, their API, they can
return, something like 10 results.
They paginate it, but they return,
10 results in, 100 milliseconds,
which is pretty fast, given that, I
don't know exactly what this data is.
I'm just going to quickly Exit
out of my slides over here.
I'm going to pop over to
the Capital One website.
I'm going to call their API for ATMs
over here, and all you do is you can
put like a latitude and longitude
and then a radius in miles, and
then you just click try it out.
And on the right over here, it's going
to be a little bit hard for you to see,
but let me zoom in a little bit and pop
this open and you can see the response
we got back was within 171 milliseconds.
And probably if you click it a
few more times, it's even faster.
There we go.
Within 89 over there.
So that's a pretty fast API.
I'd say, this is like sub 100 milliseconds
average case, except the first one.
Probably that was the cold start.
That was talking about earlier,
there is probably a server that's.
like a sleep, up there, or maybe the
data store was just like further away.
And there, this is with caching over here.
So overall for, a hackathon API
that probably uses some production
infrastructure, this is pretty good.
Okay.
So now I'm going to try and
build my own version of this API.
I scrape the data set off of capital
one to get all of the list of ATMs,
and I'm going to build my own.
API locator, or sorry,
ATM locator at the edge.
So what's that going to consist of?
that's going to consist of the following.
We're going to have a simple Brazil
website that's hosted by, it's in Next.
js, hosted by Brazil, wherever
it's going to end up hosted,
probably somewhere in the U. S.
And that's going to call an API.
that I've set up and that
API consists of two parts.
It's going to consist of an edge
cache, which is going to cache
the results for me at the edge.
But before it does that and on the
initial call, it's going to invoke
essentially a simple edge function
that is connected to an API route.
This is done through Zooplo.
And then I need some
data to host the, ATMs.
So I have a D1 database over here.
That's the one I mentioned
earlier that Cloudflare produces.
That essentially is like a just highly
replicatable, distributed SQLite fork.
that's basically the gist of it.
you can read over this in case
any of that didn't make sense.
But, in the best case, I'd say is
that, Purcell just, Places the instance
of the website somewhere close by.
Zuplo finds an edge location that's
also close by, to perform the function.
And then, ideally, D1 finds a place to
put the SQLite database, also close by,
somewhere close by to those functions.
ideally, all three of these are close to
each other, and we have very low latency.
let's jump into it.
I have the sample over here.
This is my edge API locator.
I'm going to refresh it to
prove to you that it's real.
I have a demo location here
in McLean, Virginia, USA.
That's just where the dataset is.
And I'm going to search
for ATMs within five miles.
Just the same thing is like the
Nessie example that I showed
you earlier, and there you go.
We have some examples over here.
These are some of the
closest ATMs is able to find.
I guess there aren't that many
in McLean, Virginia there.
There are a few times over in Arlington,
but one thing you'll notice that
actually took quite a bit of time.
If you ever over here, I think they'll
tell you it took about, let's see.
That took about 1.
34 seconds, to get the results.
That's actually a lot slower
than what Capital One took.
If you remember, Capital One took,
essentially 90 percent less time,
about 134, milliseconds to get results.
why was that so slow?
Let's pop over back to the slides,
and we can start debugging things.
So in any, function as a service, there's
going to be some sort of slowness.
so we should try and debug it and try
to rule out what could be going on.
the initial call, like I showed
you, took between, 1, 000 and 2, 000
milliseconds, which is obviously too slow
for any, user, especially when I just
said we were prioritizing performance.
so here are some reasons
of what might be happening.
So the first one is that, D
one itself could be slow at
executing queries like this.
The sequel query is essentially
just like a between queries where
I have all these like latitude and
longitudes set up and have to find
like a all the results between these
two sets of latitudes and longitudes.
And, we can have a lot of data.
I think there's like
several hundred ATMs here.
that shouldn't be too much for, a typical
database, but I don't know how fast D1 is.
but, yeah, there are different ways of
debugging database slowness, for example.
And, probably introducing an index
based on longitude and latitude would
be the way to resolve that, if the
query is what's taking a long time.
their most likely suspect, I'd say,
is that D1 was simply placed on
an instance that's too far away.
and this is typically because
Cloudflare will only assign you a,
high value, high performance database
instance if you're sending, high
volumes of traffic, essentially.
So this is actually, this is not
very good for hobbyists that I say,
and, if I knew D1 did this before I
started building this demo, I probably
wouldn't have used, D1, but here we are.
the best way to get around this.
is probably the cache results at the edge.
So you have to make that round
trip as few times as possible.
The last thing to rule out, I'd
say, is API gateway latency.
that would be like, latency introduced
by the function as a service from,
Zuplo and compute that's being done.
And even just the routing
of, that API endpoint.
and probably, if, if that's the issue
over there, you should probably move to
another platform or move off the edge.
there's clearly something wrong.
Maybe you're, maybe you should just use
a different language than JavaScript.
I don't know what's going on there.
Let's, pop over here.
I've performed these kind of
tests already, just in case that
the demo didn't work and didn't
want to didn't want to bore you.
But essentially what I did is I made
a call to Cloudflare's API directly.
This API is essentially allows
you to access your database
for like reads and writes and.
Whatever types of queries
you want to perform.
this is my SQL query over here.
essentially I'm just selecting
star from my ATM list where
latitude is between two values and
longitude is between two values.
And I'm limiting down to ten results so
I can match what was done by capital one.
And here are my parameters, that's
my latitudes and longitudes.
don't worry about how I computed this,
there's a, there's something called like
the Habersine, algorithm to determine
latitudes and longitudes between two
points that are within a certain radius.
just don't worry about it.
But, what you should worry about,
I'd say, is these numbers in greens.
Green over here.
You can see the result size is not like
too large, just a few kilobytes, right?
The things to look at.
One, that query to Cloudflare itself,
so that's excluding the API gateway
or whatever latency it brings.
That took alone 830 milliseconds,
which is most of the time of our call.
I've run this a few times.
It can take up to 1.
2, 1. 3 seconds, for example.
So this is like the bulk
of our duration over here.
It's just the network request.
And if we were to look at What
the component of that network
request is it purely like network
latency or SQL code execution time?
What's nice about Cloudflare D1 is
that they actually send you back this
property called Duration where they
tell you exactly how long the query took
to execute and in this case it took 0.
24 and that's actually I think in second.
or maybe that's in, sorry.
Yeah, that's in milliseconds.
So it took 0.24 milliseconds
to execute that query.
So pretty much all of this was from
network agency and whatever is going on
in Cloudflare's, API, whatever they have,
going on like checks and authorization
or authentication, things like that.
Their API itself and accessing
over like a network, the
internet, is taking a long time.
So I suspect that wherever the D1
database is placed, is likely somewhere
that's like too far to actually
benefit from being at the edge.
This is again a result
of being at low volume.
So I'd probably use a different database
like SuperBase or Torso, for example, that
can be like distributed, but I have more
control over where it gets distributed.
So what I ended up doing is I added,
caching using something called
zone cache, which is a feature
that we use, at Zoopla, which is
essentially an edge, caching solution.
and basically what I decided to
do was cache based on the prefix,
so like the first few, digits
of the latitude and longitude.
what you do actually is when you remove
like the specificity of the longitude
and latitude or truncated essentially,
you're creating like a geo map.
so there's like a square, of Earth
essentially that's that all the
locations are going to be cached for.
So as long as you have like over 10
locations in your results for that
area, that's probably going to be the
same 10 results for everywhere within
that geographic block essentially.
and this cache is done at the edge.
I can show you the code, if you're
interested, it's all open source.
So I'll mention that later on.
But essentially I took all these
results for this, Geographic square,
cached at the edge, and this results
in calls that take a lot less time,
about 70 milliseconds on average.
And, that's pretty good actually.
that's faster than what Capital
One was doing on their API.
I remember, if you recall, it
took them about 89 milliseconds.
I'm gonna go and refresh this guy again.
Clear this out.
pop this over to the side and the first
call again, that's going to take a while.
It took 1.
84 seconds to make a second call that's
cached and look at that 25 milliseconds.
Let's make a handful more called.
Look at that.
All of these are like sub 40
milliseconds in terms of like response.
So that's half of what Cloudflare or
say half of what Capital One took to
respond with the same number of results.
And that's all a result of caching.
So as you can see, Your data's location
matters a lot when it comes to where,
if you should be using an API at the
edge or have your gateway at the edge
or data at the edge, your data store,
what you choose to use for it, and it
matters a lot basically in terms of
your first call, but for subsequent
calls, caching at the edge is almost
always a better solution, so much better
in fact that this is a mind boggling
fast, I should probably fix my slides.
I'd say around 40 milliseconds, which
is like crazy fast for an API response.
So that's it for my demo.
And that's it for you know why you
should run your APIs at the edge.
If you have any questions, feel
free to connect with me on LinkedIn.
This is the QR code.
You can scan over here.
If you have any, if you're interested
in seeing the code for how I wrote
this API, I've open sourced all of it.
Please send me a DM again on LinkedIn
if you're interested, and I'll see if
there's some sort of resources for the
conference I can share this in later.
You can also take a look at the slides,
I think, after the fact, in case
you're interested to get links to the
code or any of the images that I had.
Thank you so much for attending my talk,
and enjoy the rest of your conference.
See ya.