Hi everyone.
And thank you for being here today.
So my name is Max, and I'm excited
to talk about how data science and AI
are transforming the music industry.
So I spent over 10 years
working in data science across
telecom, FinTech and consulting.
I also had the opportunity
to lead research and analysis
at Warren Music Group.
And now I'm science lead at Metis.
So the music industry is evolving
rapidly and AI is playing crucial
role is that transformation.
So today we'll explore how cloud
native AI is driving innovation in
entertainment and music production.
So now that you know a bit.
More, about me and let me walk you
through, what we will cover today.
So before we dive into the
details here, a quick overview
of what we will cover today.
So what is the problem?
we'll start by discussing the key
challenges the music industry faces today.
so we'll talk about data and
understand, what the source, we have.
And, how they shape a decision making
introduction, to AI in the music industry.
the high level, we look at how AI is
used in various aspects of the business.
And, we'll make, two stops
on two, case studies.
So the first one, it's, uplift modeling.
So how AI helps optimize
marketing campaigns by
identifying high value audiences.
And the second one, it's AI driven
planning and marketing, optimization.
So we're using AI to predict
demand and optimize a budget.
And we'll talk about the impact
of AI on the music industry from
perspective of a cloud native.
So before we get into, let's
first break down what the music
business actually looks like.
So the industry operates
across five key pillars.
So the first one, it's, and
our, artists and repertoire.
So these departments, responsible
for discovery of new talent,
finding the next big start.
The second one, it's a recording
and, production, turning raw
talent into high quality music.
The next one, it's an
artist promotion marketing.
So the guys who are responsible for,
making people, more knowledgeable
and, actually hear the music.
the next one, when we already
promote our artists, our stars.
So we need to think about how to
release tracks and distribute that.
So getting music onto
streaming platforms and other.
Channels are of course, the
last one and, but not least.
So it's a step of
monetization and royalties.
So we need to ensure that artists
and labels as a warm is a group,
as ourselves, we get paid for the.
So each of these areas generates
massive amounts of data, and this is
where AI can play a huge role in making
processes more efficient and data driven.
But of course, this business
is not without challenges.
So let's talk about one
of the biggest ones.
we understand that AI in our
days is everywhere, but, we have.
To do something, but, sometimes, we
don't know and labels and artists,
know that, AI could be potential,
but the biggest challenge that, we
faced, we don't know the artists don't
know and the labels as well, where
and how to use it, more efficient.
So it's not just about adopting AI, it's
about making it work for real business.
And if that was not challenging
enough, there is another big hurdle.
so too much data.
So let's talk about it.
So AI is everywhere, but
there is, one problem more.
It's, data is everywhere.
in warm music group, so we have, over.
2. 5 trillion streaming data points, 15,
000, parameters tracked for analysis.
hundreds of tables about the artists,
about the track, about the album,
about the audiences, 180 companies.
Provide, different details, different data
and share this data with our music group.
So 10 billion transaction process
daily and growing every day.
So the problem is not having data.
The problem is making.
Sense of it.
and that's where AI, comes in,
but we need to know how to use it.
So where does all this
data actually come from?
So the first, main source, it's a DSP.
It's a digital streaming
platform such as, Apple Music.
Spotify, Amazon and YouTube.
So they provide insights into
user behavior, play counts,
skips and playlist, additions.
So of course, the most, one
of the most popular source
of data, it's a chart metric.
So chart metric is a tool that tracks
fun engagement across, different
platforms, the technical and, from.
Technician sites, we could talk about,
Librosa, so it's a non obvious, but
anyway, it's a one more source of, data.
Librosa, it's a Python library for
analyzing audio features, so it provides,
extraction, useful information like
tempo, pitch, and mood from tracks.
And also we use, SATATON.
SATATON is a data platform, which we use.
To identify rising stars, it combines,
streaming, social and radio data
to predict, breakthrough artists.
So now we actually understand
the data landscape.
So let's see how AI helps
solve real business problems.
So AI is solving two key types of
problems in the music industry.
It's, two different layers.
the first one it's operations.
And strategy, the second one, the
operations are responsible for
optimizing marketing and engagement.
it's a problem such as, segmentation,
A B testing, common channel marketing.
If we talk about strategy, it's a
separate division, which driving
business decisions, such as, stream
forecasting, churn prediction,
LTV modeling, and uplift modeling.
So each streaming, service.
Spotify, Apple music, YouTube keeps
its own, data and the main, one
of the main problems, we faced,
we can't track a listener across,
platforms, which limits how well
we understand individual behavior.
So that's why uplift modeling
and stream forecasting are
one of our key focus areas.
So it helps us measure and,
real campaign, despite.
These, limitations.
So let's look at how AI
supports the listener journey.
So AI supports every step of the listener
journey, started from, acquisition.
So acquisition.
It's a step which, led us to
understand who are the new listeners.
it's more about behavior
monitoring, onboarding, ideas
and the boarding strategies.
So the second one, it's a
development, the development.
Part, it's about how do
we keep them engaged.
it's a problem, which we're going
to address such as next best offer
or cross sell or up sell model.
The third one, it's a retention.
So when we already have the
user is, using our service.
we need to think about who's at risk
of living and responsible for, churn
and think about, LTV prediction.
And the last one, it's a reactivation.
how do we bring them back?
for example, if we found that the user
had a high churn, probability, and it's
a problem like a reactivation modeling.
or incentives.
So to tackle these challenges, we
focus on two key AI applications.
Uplift modeling for smarter marketing
and sales forecasting to predict demand.
Because these, two main problems.
Cover the main, part of our business.
So let's see how app uplift modeling
helps optimize marketing expense.
So basically, app uplift modeling help us,
measure the real impact of, advertising
and the optimize budget allocation.
So we analyze two groups, the user
who saw an ad and those, who did not.
So two A models.
Predict engagement for each group
and uplift is the difference
between these predictions.
It tell us where ads actually drive
more listens or clicks instead of
spending on user who would engage.
Anyway, we focus on those, where
ads make a real difference.
so maximizing impact and reducing wasted
spend actually what happens when we
apply uplift modeling in real campaigns.
So AI driven segmentation was used
to launch ads on TikTok and Spotify.
So the results showed a 30 percent
reduction in the cost of adding a
track to a user library compared
to traditional segmentation.
So this proves that AI, especially
uplift modeling could help us
optimize ad spend by targeting.
The right, listeners and improved,
efficiency and reducing, costs.
That's actually our main purposes.
So now let's take a look, at another
key AI, use case in our agenda.
It must be, and it will
be stream forecasting.
So stream forecasting, it's about,
Sales forecasting, actually.
So we need to predict how many
times a song, will be streamed as
a critical for plan because it's
critical for planning and marketing.
We built a three months forecasting
model using historical streaming
trends, track metadata and the process,
which we already mentioned today.
And additionally, we used,
around 700 features in total.
So the result forecasting
accuracy improved by 60%.
helping labels, allocate budgets
more effectively because, it's
becoming more crucial and more
important for warrior because warrior
consists of different, independent
label, such as Atlantic as well.
So now let's see how this
forecasting translates into a
smarter marketing investments.
So forecasting doesn't
just help predict streams.
It's also optimize marketing spend
because, when we build, model, we
need to understand that we need to
not only implement our solution.
We need to interpret.
the decision interpret, the model.
And, for that to answer on that
question, we built partial dependence
plot and partial dependence
plot, provide us key insight.
So more budget does not always
mean more streams because, after.
built in partial dependence, we found
that, oftentimes we're faced with a
plateau effect and plot effect shows where
additional spending stop being effective.
So by reallocating budgets
based on these, insights.
So we saved, 27 percent of, marketing
costs without losing performance.
And, we've built based on that model.
real cloud native AI platform
that integrates forecasting
seamlessly into business process.
So the first step, of our implementation,
it's a front end around on
Streamlit, which making predictions.
And, provide for, our business
units and business users more easy
to access, mathematical model.
And the next step, a fast API backend
connects the user interface with our ML
model and handling request efficiently.
So user.
Type specific, scenario in Streamlit.
So Streamlit send this request to FastAPI.
FastAPI launch ML model, ML model
score and predict all forecasts.
Send this forecast, in FastAPI back.
And, the model process
input features and return.
stream forecasts, in the
real time and show the real
forecasts in the stream lead.
So this architecture allows for fast
scalable AI driven decision making and
bringing real value to the music industry.
And, at the end of the day, it
all comes down to one thing.
So music has to win.
AI is not here to replace
creativity, but to amplify it,
helping artists and businesses.
Make smarter and data driven decisions.
And, our purpose and our main
objective, is build cloud native AI
solution that optimize marketing,
predict trends and maximize impact.
And we did it, but the real goal, of
course, it's connecting music with the
right audience in the most effective way.
So thanks for your time and feel
free to scan the QR code to connect.
And I'm happy to take any questions.