Hello everyone and welcome
to my presentation.
My name is Chakradar Sunkeswala and I
am engineering manager and specializing
in cloud infrastructure and security.
Today I want to share insights about
building a multi layered security
framework that not only addresses
today's threats but also scales for the
challenges we face in 2025 and beyond.
Why multi layered security?
Because the threat landscape
is more dynamic than ever.
Attackers are constantly probing
networks, APIs, and user endpoints
looking for the weakest links.
If you rely on only one or two
security controls, sooner or
later something will slip through.
But, by using a series of defenses
that reinforce each other, you reduce a
risk that a single breach can escalate.
During this talk, we'll explore the core
components of such a framework, ranging
from network security to AI driven threat
detection to zero trust and beyond.
By the end, you will have a practical
understanding of how each piece fits
together to create a robust shield
around your cloud infrastructure.
Over the past few years, the cloud
computing market has grown tremendously,
increasing into The hundreds of billions
of dollars in value and projected to keep
expanding at over 20 percent annually
with so many organizations migrating
critical applications to the cloud.
It's clear that security
must be the paramount.
The main challenge is that this
rapid growth has dramatically
increased the attack surface.
Each new app, each new data
store, each new endpoint becomes
a potential vulnerability.
Some reports indicate that nearly 43
percent of businesses have experienced
at least one significant cloud
security incident in the past one year.
The biggest culprit, culprits,
misconfiguration, inadequate
identity management, and
lack of effective monitoring.
In this environment, reactive security
strategies like patching after
the breach are simply not enough.
We need to be proactive.
Layered defenses capable, layered
defenses capable of identifying,
isolating, and neutralizing the threats.
Before they cause any real damage.
That's the focus of this framework.
Systematically reducing the risk across
every layer of your cloud environment.
Let's break down how a multi layered
framework is typically structured.
We look at several layers.
Network security, where we implement
firewalls, intrusion, detection,
prevention systems and segment networks.
Authentication and authorization.
Zero trust methods.
least privilege and strong
identity verification.
API security and monitoring.
Checking each request with
intelligent validation systems.
AI driven threat detection, machine
learning models spotting anomalies in
real time, resilience and recovery,
built in failovers, and rapid incident
response, and a thorough documentation.
By interlocking these layers, we
ensure no single point of failure.
The impact can be profound, studies how
organizations adopting these strategies
often see major reductions, sometimes
up to 90 percent in successful breaches.
They also report faster resolution
times and improved compliance.
Ultimately, robust security isn't
just about avoiding the attacks.
It's about fostering innovation
by enabling the teams to focus on
building great products without
constantly being worried about threats.
Let's talk, let's look
at network security.
Traditionally, every company tries to
protect a single perimeter, assuming
that everything inside could be trusted.
But that model fails in the cloud.
Today, attacks might originate internally
or come through compromised endpoints.
That's why we are shifting
to a zero trust model.
Where no user or a device
is implicitly trusted.
In a zero trust architecture, each
request, whether it comes from,
coming from inside your network or
outside, must be continuously verified.
We integrate AI driven traffic
analysis to spot unusual behaviors.
behavior patterns.
For instance, if a user activity suddenly
spikes at 3 a. m. in the morning from
the country where you have no operations,
we flag it or block it automatically.
Additionally, setting up a trip voice in
the network layer is highly effective.
These are specific threshold or
conditions that trigger alarms.
For example, if the data exfiltration
exceeds a certain rate, or a
sensitive resource is accessed
unexpectedly, it sets off an alarm.
The swift response prevents attacker
from moving freely once they are in.
The next critical layer is authentication.
Compromised credentials remain one
of the top vectors for breaches.
Therefore, we employ multi factor,
multi factored authentication,
short lived tokens, and strong
identity verification protocols.
We also classify users
and devices based on risk.
A low risk user operating from a
known location might only need a
single factor of authentication.
But a privileged administrator signing
in from a new or suspicious location
might require multiple steps, such as one
time password or biometric verification.
If we detect or suspect a compromised
token, we have an automatic kill switch.
That revokes session
tokens across the board.
This prevents attackers from leveraging
stolen credentials for extended periods.
Ultimately, trying an authentication,
tightly to the contextual risks,
ensures that only legitimate users
gain access and only to what they
specifically need to do their job.
Once the users are authenticated, the next
step is to ensure, to ensuring they are
only having the correct level of access.
We employ least privilege principles,
meaning no one gets more permissions
than they absolutely require.
This alone can drastically limit
how far an attacker can move
if an account is compromised.
Dynamic access control is the next
evolution where the systems adjust
the privileges in real time, based
upon the factors like unusual
location or high volume of requests.
if something seems off, we automatically
lock down key resources or prompt
for additional verifications.
Continuous auditing is also essential.
Logs are checked frequently, and
any deviations from the normal
usage patterns trigger reviews.
This real time feedback loop helps
maintain compliance, and it also gives
us crucial insights into how to refine
roles and permissions over time.
In the cloud native architectures,
APIs tie everything together.
They are only the prime
targets for the attackers.
That's why our framework emphasizes
rigorously on API security.
We validate requests at multiple points,
checking headers, payloads, security.
we validate requests at
multiple points, right?
we also ensure that each microservice
trusts only specific tokens or
request patterns, reducing the
risk of unauthorized calls.
Machine learning plays a big role in
spotting anomalies at the API layer.
If an endpoint typically receives 100
requests per hour and suddenly spikes
to 10, 000, we want an automated
mechanism to flag or block that.
We also integrate threat intelligence
feeds that list known malicious IPs
or suspicious domains, automatically
rejecting calls from bad actors.
By refining API security,
we tackle a huge surface.
attack, surface area for attacks.
This is essentially important when
microservices scale, as you may end
up with hundreds or even, sometimes
thousands of endpoints to protect.
Even with robust authentication,
authorization, and API checks,
threats can still slip through.
That's where advanced analytics come in.
We ingest logs through, from
across the network, combine
them with external threats.
threat intelligence and apply AI models
to detect anomalies in real time.
For example, if a zero day vulnerability
surfaces, a system may notice new exploit
patterns like specific error codes or
unusual memory usage across containers.
Automated responses then isolate
affected containers or force update
to mitigate the vulnerability.
If a breach does occur, Comprehensive
logging helps with faster
containment and root cause analysis.
We quickly see which user accounts
were accessed, which endpoints were
compromised, and which data was touched.
This clarity is vital for both legal
compliance and for improving our
defenses to prevent a repeat incident.
While detection and prevention
are crucial, so is resilience.
Our framework builds redundancy across
regions and providers, aiming for
nearly five nines of availability.
If one region is under heavy
DDoS attack or experiencing a
catastrophic failure, we can failover
automatically to another region.
Resilience also extends to quick recovery.
We define clear runbooks
for incident response.
Who does what, when and how.
Using orchestration tools, we
can revert to the known safe
state within minutes, minimizing
downtime and limiting any damage.
Another aspect of resilience is
adaptive security systems that
learn from each new threat pattern.
and update their models, firewall rules,
or access policies in near real time.
Over time, this continuous
learning cycle makes the entire
architecture even more stronger.
Let's talk about the bottom line.
Data breaches can be
exceedingly expensive.
Some estimates put the average
cost of breach in the millions of
dollars, factoring in direct losses.
legal fees, regulatory
fines, and the brand damage.
By implementing a thorough, layered
security approach, organizations
often see a dramatic, reduction
in their cost, sometimes up to 76
percent savings on incident response,
and faster mean time to recovery.
Additionally, robust, security often
leads to lower cyber, insurance premiums,
as insurers, recognize the reduced risk.
For companies that handle a lot
of sensitive data, these savings
can be substantial over time.
Beyond finances, you're also
safeguarding your reputation.
Maintaining a customer trust is
priceless, and a well publicized breach
can erode that trust very quickly.
To wrap up, we have seen how
a multi layered cloud security
framework can address the growing
challenges in cloud environments.
By combining zero trust principles,
AI driven threat analysis, strong
authentication, and continuous monitoring,
we create a defense that's flexible,
intelligent, and deeply resilient.
Looking forward, we will see advances
in areas like AI driven forensics, micro
segmentation for containerized workloads.
And adaptive identity management
that evolves with user behavior and
attacker become more sophisticated.
We must remain vigilant and
proactive, continuously refining
these layers to stay ahead.
Thank you.