Hey there, I'm Rizomatu, a backend
engineer, and today I'll be
walking us through distributed
caching and queuing in the cloud.
Let's get started.
So for folks who are new to all
of this, a cache is basically
a high speed storage layer.
The, temporarily who frequently
assess data to improve
performance and reduce latency.
So instead of going to a slow source,
let's say for instance, a database
file system or a standard API, every
time you request data that you know,
it's frequently assessed, you can
basically store a copy of that data
on a cache so that future requests
can be served and much faster.
This is the, typical setup
for most applications, right?
You have a client that makes a request
to the server, which then makes a
request to a database to fetch data,
which is then sent back to the client.
So this works just fine for most
applications, but on high traffic
systems, this doesn't scale well.
If it's not obvious already, the issue
with this kind of setup is that Over time,
the database becomes a bottleneck as all
clients requests get to hit the database.
This is, where we can leverage a
cache to scale this solution, right?
So basically, instead of the server
reaching out to the database each time
for data that we know it's, frequently
accessed, the server can basically
just reach out to the cache to say,
hey, is this record in the cache?
If the record is available in the
cache, The server just returns this
back to the client from the cache.
But in the case where the record isn't
available in the cache, the server makes
a request to the database to fetch this
data, writes back to the cache, then
return to the client so that future
requests can be retrieved from the cache.
This way we can improve the,
Read performance for clients
request to the server.
So if you're wondering already why,
retrieving data from the cache is faster
than retrieving from the database,
it's simply because, data on the
cache is usually written to a faster
storage, like memory, unlike data on
a database, which is written to disk.
So most times, as the application scales
and grows with time, a single caching
stance isn't enough to, manage the
load you have or your caching demand.
This is where distributed
caching comes in.
Basically, distributed caching spreads
cache data across multiple nodes, instead
of storing it on a single node or machine.
This ensures scalability, fault
tolerance, and prevents cache overload.
There are different strategies
out there for distributed caching.
We have sharding, replication,
load balancing, consistent
hashing, and some others out there.
But for now, I'll just focus on the
first three on this list because of time.
consistent hashing is a bit complicated
and, might take us a lot of time.
So what's sharding?
Sharding is a data replication technique.
That distributes cache data across
multiple nodes instead of storing
everything on a single, machine in
a distributed caching environment,
sharding ensures scalability and
efficient memory usage by dividing on
the cache data across multiple instances.
So let's say, on this, diagram, as you
can see, we have a cache router, which
is basically responsible for assigning
a cache request to the right nodes.
In this case, we have a range based on
sharding setup, which means that we assign
requests to nodes based on the key range.
For keys in range 1 to 1,
000, it's assigned to node A.
1, 000 to 2, 000, it's
assigned to node B and so on.
So basically what this does is that
the cache data is split across each
of these nodes, saving only a range
of these values or a range of this
key value pairs on a single node.
This way we can scale out our caching
system to support, more memory
space or storage space, basically.
So let's say we have a constraint
of five gigabytes per node.
By adding like two extra nodes, we're able
to, increase that limits to 15 gigabytes,
which comes in very handy for scaling.
Up next, we have replication.
Replication is also a data
partitioning technique.
Yes, that this duplicates cache
data across multiple nodes to ensure
high availability, fault tolerance,
and improve read performance.
It allows on cache systems
to continue functioning even
if some of the nodes fail.
So basically no, no node is
like a bottleneck in MOS.
replication setup.
So in this case, what we have on in this
diagram is a geo replication setup, right?
So we have a cache router that
is responsible for assigning the
right node to like assigning a
cache request to the right node.
So here we have primary node
A, which is basically the node
responsible for writes requests.
This is a master, secondary setup.
So basically the primary node is
responsible for writes requests and
I'm synchronizing the data across the
secondary nodes while the secondary
nodes are just there for read
request and optimizing read request.
So in this case, we're trying
to optimize for latency, right?
So what happens is that the
cache router assigns them a node
to a cache request based on.
A node that is closer to the, back
end or the user making the request.
So if a user is making a request from
Africa, we just simply route the, cache
request to the cache node in Africa.
If they're making a request from
Europe, we do the same thing.
So basically it is a way to improve
or reduce latency using, replication.
Up next, we have load balancing.
Load balancing evenly distributes cache
requests across multiple Cache nodes
to prevent overloading a single node.
This improves response time,
ensures high availability.
It also ensures that no single cache
node becomes a bottleneck in the system.
in this diagram we can see here
that we have a cache load balancer,
which is responsible for routing
requests to the correct node.
The data is then synchronized
across the other nodes, right?
Let's say we write a request, we, add
a cache value to node A, the data gets
saved to node A, then synchronized
to B and C just to ensure that if
a read request is routed to Any of
the other nodes, the cache data will
be available there for retrieval.
So basically the way most, load
balancing systems work is that most
of them use, there are different
algorithms out there, but a very
popular one is round robin, right?
Basically what the load balancer
does is that for each request,
it just sends it from one node to
another and that kind of stuff.
Let's say we have five requests to
our caching load balancer, right?
The first request goes to node A,
the second one goes to node B, the
third one node C, the fourth one goes
back again to node A, then, so forth.
So that's like how round
robin works in a nutshell.
Before I proceed, I would like
to mention that, the caching
strategies I've mentioned.
can either be implemented on the
application layer or they can be
implemented on the caching system
or comes with the caching system.
It's highly recommended to go with, a
caching strategy implemented on with
the caching system we're using, right?
If you're using Redis for instance, Redis
cluster has, sharding and replication out
of the box, which means you don't have to.
I'm going implement this by yourself,
you just have to configure your Redis
cluster to replicate or share your
data based on your requirements.
So these are some of the popular
caching systems out there.
The most popular ones are
Redis and Memcached, right?
So Redis is an open source,
in memory data store.
It also offers, advanced data structures,
replication, and sharding, and is widely
adopted for high performance caching.
So Redis is quite popular when you, when
a lot of folks hear caching, the first
thing that comes to their mind is Redis.
Then we have Memcached, which is
basically a simple key value pair
store that is, very fast for, lookups.
Some cloud providers out there do offer,
elastic, do offer custom solutions, right?
For instance, AWS has Amazon
Elastic Catch, Google Cloud has
Memorystore, Azure has Catch for Redis.
So basically these are just
similar with Redis Cloud.
These are just fully managed solutions.
So basically let's say you
use Amazon Elastic Catch.
This means that you don't have to bother
about the little details of managing your
Redis cluster or instance or whatever.
So same thing with
Google Cloud Memorystore.
This is managed like for you.
You just have to configure how
you want to scale your caching
system or your caching components.
Also, alternatively, you can go with
the self hosted approach where you
purchase a server online and run.
Ready.
So memcache DNAT and, connect
it to your backend system.
Although this can be a bit painful
to manage, but, if this meets
your need is also an option.
So that is it for caching.
what is a queue?
A queue is a messaging system that
enables asynchronous communication
between components by temporarily storing
messages until they are processed.
most times in your application
or on your backend system, right?
You have, different services that
needs to communicate asynchronously
to maybe carry on different tasks.
For instance, an example would
be, let's say you have, an
e commerce website, right?
Where you let users place an
order online and you send them.
a receipt to their email
after placing an order.
So basically, when a user sends a
request to place an order, you don't
really want to send them a receipt
immediately as that can be computationally
expensive to compile the receipts to
PDF and also send them a mail for this.
So one thing you could do is, have
a separate component or separate
service in charge of sending
mails or sending, PDFs or stuff.
to users, then the, your main
backend system sends a message to
the email components to compile
the mail and send to them.
So this way you separate like
the processing, keeping things
asynchronous and ensuring that
user requests are not delayed.
Having them wait for you to compile
PDFs and emails before showing them a
social message on your A PIO on a ui.
in a typical event driven
setup, we have a producer.
Which is responsible for publishing
events or text through a message queue.
Then you have a message queue.
Basically what a message queue does is
that it holds the tax on until there's
an available consumer to dispatch it to.
It's, most of them usually have a
first in first out approach, although
this othering isn't always guaranteed.
So just keep that in mind.
And you have a consumer, which is.
Basically a component or a system
that just picks up events from the
message queue or receives events from
the message queue and works on them.
And the example of the, e
commerce, receipts, example, right?
So you have a producer that is the
maybe order service sends a message
to the queue, then it gets consumed
by, your email or messaging service.
Basically to send the user the receipts.
the way most consumers work is that
they do, they subscribe to topics or
events on the message queue saying,
okay, I'm interested in this topic.
So when this kind of topics do come
across, it sends to the right consumer.
As your, demand for your queuing
system grows, bottleneck, right?
If all messages are routed.
Through that, single queue.
distributed queuing addresses these
challenges by spreading traffic
across multiple queue partitions.
This, allows for, high volume
asynchronous processing, and also
enables multiple producers and
consumers to operate concurrently,
ensuring scalability, resilience,
and, scale under high load basically.
So this is, a quick diagram just
explaining, what you could expect or
how distributed queuing works, right?
So in this case, you
have multiple producers.
Mind you, even in the previous
case of a single message queue,
you can have multiple producers
and multiple consumers as well.
This doesn't stop them.
So the main important thing here, is
the broker or load balancer, right?
This part of the system is.
It's basically responsible for taking
events from the producers and routing
it to the right rights and partition.
In this case, we have
six partitions, right?
Basically, this is a, skilled solution
saying, okay, we have this number of
partitions to accept as much messages
from the providers as we need, right?
So if the demand grows,
you simply just add.
More partitions to the broker and
the broker is in charge of allocating
which events get sent to a particular
partition and, determining how it
gets sent to a consumer as well.
So this way we can, scale our, queuing
components as much as we want by
simply just adding more partition or
removing partition if the load drops.
These are some of the popular
queuing systems out there.
We have Apache Kafka, which is a
high throughput distributed streaming
platform designed for real time event
streaming, and it's widely adopted for
its scalability and fault tolerance.
Then you also have RabbitMQ, which
is quite mature as well and, supports
complex routing and different protocols.
It's it's a very popular
queuing system as well.
Then you have NATS, which is a
Lightweight High Performance Messaging
System that, it's quite popular in
cloud native applications as it offers
some simplicity and low latency.
I would like to mention that The
distributed, queuing strategy or,
managing partitions is usually
done by the broker, which in this
case is RabbitMQ or Apache Kafka.
So most times you don't have
to go into the little details
of managing this by yourself.
But in a worst case scenario where
this don't meet your need, you
can simply, implement this on the
application layer or create a service.
for managing like your
distributed, queuing strategy.
So it's up to you, but it's best
to go with the strategy or the
implementation that comes with
your broker or queue load balancer.
Different cloud providers do
offer a queuing service as well.
AWS has.
Amazon SQS, Google Cloud has pops up.
Then Azure has service bot.
Alternatively too, you could run,
Kafka or RabbitMQ or nuts on a
server you purchased online and
connect your application through it.
And yeah, you could have that
Azure, although like similarly
with the cashing, I'm self hosting.
This could be a pain to manage and
scale, but this is also an option
in case Army meets your needs.
Thank you for sticking around.
If you enjoyed this talk, feel
free to reach out to me on
either LinkedIn or Twitter.