Hello, everyone.
Hope you're doing well.
First of all, thank you all for
taking time to join my talk.
Today I'm discussing about human
AI collaboration in food delivery.
This presentation mainly talks about
how AI artificial intelligence system,
will help in food delivery platforms and
what are the key benefits, and the areas
where we have to mainly concentrate or to
integrate AI in the food delivery chain.
So I will be discussing in this,
presentation, regarding communication
safety, voice ordering system,
advanced data engineering applications
and technical challenges with
their solutions, to integrate
AI in food delivery platforms.
So if you look at the food
delivery industry, there are
around 190 billion market size.
And also there is a
potential growth of 10.
8 percent annual growth through
2030, which can help improve if you
transform digital transformations
and changing the customer habits.
There are like 73 percent of the
mobile orders in past some years.
So you can understand How this
AI is important to integrate with
the mobile technologies as well.
So the food delivery industry has
transformed from a convenience to
a cornerstone of modern urban life.
This evolution is catalyzed by
the perfect storm of technological
advancement, shifting consumer
behaviors and growing premium places.
Place it to time efficiency.
Artificial intelligence has
become increasingly sophisticated.
It's not just enhancing existing service.
It's fundamentally remaining how
food delivery platforms operate
and interact with the customers.
So we are introducing one of the
application, which is a safe chat
place, which is AI powered communication
safety, which runs on advanced NLP
architecture, which can give you a 94.
3 percent accuracy in detecting
inappropriate content.
It also, do a high performance
processing of 1400 messages per
minute with less than 50 milliseconds
latency across five major languages.
So 82 percent faster incident response
compared to traditional human moderation.
And, 70 percent improvement in
driver satisfaction rating with
63 percent fewer communication
disruptors.
A enhanced voice operating system comes
with speech recognition, order processing,
efficiency, customer satisfaction.
in this, system seamlessly combines
advanced machine learning with a
strategic human oversight, transforming
restaurant operations by dramatically
cutting wait times and reducing error.
This sophisticated system not only
streamlines ordering process but also
enables staff to focus on delivery
exceptional customer service resulting
in measurably higher customer
satisfaction and retention as well
as improving the growth of the sales.
Advanced data engineering applications
also comes with, machine learning
infrastructure, process 15 petabytes
of real time data daily, and also smart
algorithms deliver 25 percent higher
search accuracy, AI driven suggestions
boost orders by 28%, and dynamic
routing cuts delivery time by 18%.
This engineering framework
harnesses enterprise scale machines.
learning to transform vast amount
of data into actionable insights.
This system offers millions of real
time signals to optimize every aspect
of our platform, from personalized
customer experience to fleet management,
establishing new benchmarks for
operational excellence in food delivery.
We, follow some, strategies
for the implementation.
one is, One is the data driven decision
making, which is leverage real time
analytics to track over 200 critical
performance metrics, enabling proactive
issues detection and automated
response protocol across operationals.
Orchestrate 800 simultaneous A B tests
monthly to optimize algorithms, resulting
in consistency, improved delivery
accuracy, and customer satisfaction.
Seamlessly coordinates 12 million
daily human AI interactions with
92 percent concordance rate.
ensuring reliable and efficient
service delivery while
maintaining human oversight.
There are technical challenges
majorly on scaling the system
and performance of the system.
So our system handles a strategic 2.
4 million concurrent transactions
per hour during peak times,
processing an exceptional 4.
8 TB of data hourly through our
distributed computing architecture.
This massive throughput requires
sophisticated load balancing and real
time data optimization techniques.
It also supports six major languages,
achieving an industry leading 93.
2 percent accuracy in natural language
processing and intent recognition.
Our advanced neural network continuously
learns from interaction to improve
cross cultural communication nuances.
There also we need to talk about
reliability, which delivers.
Enterprise grade reliability with 99.
95 percent uptime during peak
traffic periods through advanced
predictive scaling algorithm
and redundant infrastructure.
Our proactive monitoring system
anticipates demand spikes and
automatically adjusts resources to
maintain consistent performance.
So some more technical challenges
while integrating considerations.
So AI handoff orchestration over
72k seamless AI humans transitions
daily with AI industry leading 94.
8 percent context retention rate,
ensuring continuous service quality.
It also manages and synchronizes 2.
8 TB of mission critical
operational data hourly across
eight distributed geographical
regions with sub second latency.
We also need to talk about
privacy and security.
We safeguards 12 million daily
transactions through military grade
encryption protocols and real time threat.
detection systems.
You can see the, graph of the, some of
the key metrics where, sets relevancy
improved, customer satisfaction also
improved, order frequency, improved,
order value also improved, delivery
time reduction also down, and, operation
efficiency also improved drastically.
So we are also looking
for the future, trends and
opportunities, by integrating AI.
So there is an autonomous delivery, so
we can see like a revolution in self
driving vehicles are coming and AI
powered drones are transforming last
mile deliveries and promising faster
delivery times while reducing operational
costs and environmental impacts.
You can also, introduce, new technology,
called AR VR experiences where people
can, imagine how and what the food
look like and, how the, how it looks in
outstanding 3D details and take virtual
tours of restaurants and revelations
in the digital dining experience.
We can also implement our
personalized nutrition.
Where, Advanced AI algorithm
analyzes individual health metrics,
dietary preferences, and nutritional
needs to provide tailoring meal
recommendations that optimize both
health outcomes and dining satisfactions.
The final conclusion, technology
evolution, the integration of AI has
fundamentally transformed the food
delivery landscapes, setting new
industry standards for efficiency,
scalability, and customer experiences.
And there is a hybrid approach.
Our strategic combination of AI
automation and human expertise creates
a resilient operational framework that
maximizes technical capabilities while
preserving the essential human touch.
Continuous innovation, successes
in the rapidly evolving the space
depends on building a flexible, future
ready systems that prioritize user
needs while consistently adapting to
merge technology and market demands.
Not only this, we can improve the
customer satisfaction, reduce the
delivery timings, and, support, customer,
experience, and, give them, healthy
dietary recommendations based on their
habits and, improve the, very good extent
of the customer satisfaction and, improve
the sales of the, Food delivery chain
and so many other things by including
this AI into food delivery platform.
That's all for today.
Thank you so much for joining my talk.
Hope you find good information
in my presentation today.
all.