Hi everyone.
Good morning, good afternoon.
My name is pka.
I worked as PA vice president
at a city where I focus on large
scale data and cloud platforms.
Today I'll be talking about how
database designed is evolving in
the cloud native era, specifically
around partitioning indexing.
For decades, we have relied on.
Traditional database assumptions,
stable workloads, fixed
infrastructure, and manual tuning.
But in today's cloud environments
those assumptions no longer hold.
What I want to talk you through
today is how modern systems are
becoming adapt to intelligent
and increasingly self-optimizing,
leveraging concepts like adaptive
partitioning, learned indexes, and
machine learning inside the query engine.
So by the end of this session, you will
have a clear understanding of where
database architecture is heading and
how you can start applying these ideas.
So the first slide, as you see is
database evolution, partitioning
and indexing for Cloud native.
So let me start with the big picture.
This session is about how database
systems are evolving from rigid OnPrem.
Models to intelligent
cloud native architectures.
So the key shift here is adaptability
systems that can secure rebalance
and optimize themselves dynamically
without heavy manual intervention.
So let's move on to the next slide.
So this is the challenge with the legacy.
Database designs.
So the core problem is that traditional
database were built for predictability.
They assume stable workloads, fixed
hardware, manual tuning cycles, but
cloud environments are the opposite.
Workloads are dynamic.
Infrastructure is elastic,
and availability expectations
are extremely high.
This mismatch creates real
issues like latency spikes,
operational overhead, and Mr.
Deli.
So going to the next
slide is session roadmap.
So here, what we'll cover this session
builds a structure narrative from the
architecture foundations of cloud native
databases to the emerging role of machine
learning in self-optimizing systems.
So here is how we'll
structure this session.
First, we will define the problems piece.
Then look at the modern
partitioning strategies followed
by how indexing is evolving.
Then we will explore machine
learning in databases.
And finally, practical
takeaways you can apply.
So first goes with
partitioning, so partitioning.
Is no longer a one-time design decision.
In cloud native systems,
workloads shift constantly.
Traffic creates hotspots,
infrastructure scale dynamically.
So partitioning must continuously
adapt, not remain static.
So for example, like rapid parting
rebalances, data placement as
query patterns and traffic evolve.
Elastic scaling is like
handles rapid growth.
And shrinkage without manual rework
and high availability, which is
like preserve service continuity
during failures and live reshuffles.
And so the next slide is how from static
schemas to partitioning is happening.
So earlier partitioning stations were
made a friend like range hash or list.
But those stations
quickly become outdated.
Now, systems monitor real time,
query patterns and adjust partitions
dynamically without downtime.
So now we are learning about
key partitioning strategies
in cloud native systems.
So modern systems combine
multiple strategies.
Range partitioning is
for time-based queries.
Hash partitioning is for.
Even distribution composite
approaches for complex workloads.
It's no longer about choosing one.
It's about combining intelligently.
So this slide explains the elastic scaling
and high availability through partying.
So this is where a cloud native
partitioning really shines.
So key capabilities include
partition level replication,
dynamic short splitting.
Geo aware placement.
So these allow systems to
scale horizontally and maintain
availability even during failures,
which is a major cloud advantage.
So partition aware routing combined
with distributor replication enables
cloud databases to scale horizontally
with minutes adding capacity without
repartitioning the entire data
set, or taking the system offline.
So how, yeah, we goes like indexing,
which is chapter number two.
So indexing is no longer just a B three.
But traditionally indexing mean to
be a B three, but today's workload
especially vector search and analytics
require more advanced restructures.
So indexing is becoming adaptive
and even machine learning.
Is become driven by this technology.
Let's move on to next slide.
So transformation of
indexing architectures.
So we can see this index
evolve evaluation here.
We are seeing three strategies like
static B, B three, like static indexes
which are like manual and rigid.
So going to adaptive indexes,
which is partially automated,
like partial indexing, automated
suggestions, online re rebuilds.
And third one is like a learned
indexes machine learning driven
and es step reduces operational
overhead and improves efficiency.
So adaptive and
multi-dimensional indexing.
So what is like I explained before,
static B indexes force DVS to
predict query patterns upfront
and manually maintain structures.
And as schemas evolve, which
quickly breaks down in high
throughput cloud environments.
So here so these are like one is
like partition partial indexes.
Second one is covering indexes, and
third one is multi column indexes.
And fourth one is spatial
and inverted indexes.
These allow systems.
To optimize based on real query
behavior, not assumptions.
Going on with the next slide,
it is indexing trade offs,
the engineering reality.
So important point is indexes are
not free, so they improve our re
read performance, but increase
storage, add right overhead.
So indexing must be treated as.
Ongoing optimization problem,
not a one time decision.
But with respect to the cloud, like
automated maintenance, outand, like cloud
native engine use adaptive index advises
to identify new indexes, such nuance and
trigger background rebuilds without dis
disrupting active trans transactions.
Let's move on to the chapter
three, which is a lie.
Machine learning, workload management.
So in multi-tenant systems, the
workloads are unpredictable.
So machine learning helps by classifying
queries, allocating resources
proactively detecting anomalies
early, and this prevents performance
degradation before it happens.
So learned indexes, replacing trees
with models, which is interesting here.
It's just to validate these improvements.
We use benchmark tools like Royal
LTP Bench simulates real workloads.
iTune use EML to optimize configurations.
These help quantify the
impact of modern techniques.
Next slide is adaptive
query processing with.
Machine learning.
We see like traditional query
optimiz on static cost models
and table statistics that can
become sta as distributions shift.
So mission learning driven query, adaptive
query process, close scale by learning
from execution history and continuous
road refining execution plan selection.
So all these components work together.
Partitioning reduces queue indexing,
improves query speed and machine learning.
Continuous optimizes both now.
Ml machine learning driven
workload management, this is the
prediction challenge, like workload
classification, proactive resource
allocation, and anon anomaly detection.
So machine learning driven workload
managers address this by predicting
workload composition ahead of execution,
peer allocating resources and rout
inquiries to the appropriate compute
tire before contention develops.
Now we go for benchmarking, cloud Native
Performance Loyalty, DB bench, and iTunes.
So like I said before, the loyalty LT
bench and iTunes simulates real workloads
and iTune is machine learning to
optimize configurations, self optimizing
database putting it all together.
So all these components work together
partitioning reduces SKU indexes in
improve speed and machine learning,
continuous continuously optimize
both this create self-optimizing
system, as you can see in this slide.
Now going to the next slide.
So this is interesting, like impact on
developer productivity and DBA workload.
So for developers, less need
for manual tuning and faster
developments, I guess for dbs.
Reduce manual effort and more focus
on strategy rather than operations,
safeguards, quadras and
operational considerations.
So self-optimizing systems introduce
new failure alongside their benefits.
Production adoption requires skillful
go governance of when and how the
system is permitted to act autonomously.
Like rollback safety, human in
loop mode and threshold quadras
and upper observation first.
So these are like yeah we which
gives automation strategies.
Okay.
And so implementation path is observe,
advise, and automate selectivity.
So with this implementation path,
like a first unit, observe your
system, then enable advisory model,
and finally automate selectivity.
So this type of framework can improve
so improve all the hiccups with, on-prem
systems like moving into the cloud.
So just to wrap up like a cloud
native database or moving towards self
optimizing systems powered by adaptive
architectures and machine learning.
The key takeaway is this, the static
design is no longer enough and systems
must continuously learn adaptive.
Thanks for your time and
happy to take questions.
Thank you.