Hi, I'm Andre Spra, founding engineer at
Custard, and one of the biggest challenge
we've been facing for the last couple
of months was how to manage AI agents.
The complexity that gets involved
with running CPS and subagents being
spun across different CPS making
multiples parallel tool calls across.
Different services.
So we build agent CTL as a command
line based interface tool to allow
us to be able to manage agents
across different environments.
So the problem technically is like you
have hundreds of agents running across,
50 or so environments or within a single
environment performing multiples to
hundreds and thousands of tasks, and
all these agents need a way or us.
Operational side.
We need a way to be able to see
what are these agents doing,
which tools they're calling.
We need a way to have a full visual
view, unified view of extensive how
these agents are operating within
the environments, which data they're
attaching, which services they're calling,
which tools they're using, and we also
need to audit the reasoning behind.
Y they are doing Operation X and
Operation Y. So Agent CTL allows us
to define a state file, and then add
the different agents location within
the deployment environment and then.
We can auto discover, which
will automatically discover
the agents based on the file.
And also you can do discover, which is
like you pass it directly as a parameter,
which will automatically pick the agents
from wherever they are from the source.
And then this allows you to run
different c like commands that you can
interpret or interact with the agents.
Or see what the agents are doing
from logs to performance metrics.
Take this you are in a linex environment.
You run H top.
You want to see memory, you want to
see ram usage, you want to see disk
space and all those information.
So this is same thing, but now we
are more focused towards the deep
view into agents and then CCPs.
And then one of the things we
realized was more like, all
these agents need guardrails.
They need you need a way to be able to
validate whatever response, whatever
decision, whatever reasoning they're
making the data they're using.
Is it correct to inform or
prompt or the decision they
are basically making for that?
Angle or aspect there in the context
of the information they're trying
to retrieve or give feedback to
a user and all those information.
So all this now, this is what we pull as.
Metrics that now define the
SRE principles behind the whole
agent workflows that we run.
And we apply all the RE
principles patterns across all
the agents within our environment.
And the beauty of all
these is all these metrics.
We push them into the
different monitoring tools.
We have a lacking, we can.
We have dashboard that we see end
to end visibility into the agents
performing and all these things.
So now I'll just walk through
the CLI aspect agency agent list.
So this list, all the agents that,
right now available in my local machine
and agents that have been registered,
and if I do agent CTL dashboard.
So the dashboard shows me how the agents,
what they're currently doing real time.
Calls they're making which tools
they are calling within the cps.
Now we are connecting to casa, cps, we
have lama, we show studio and we can
see what exactly they're all doing.
And if we do, let's see,
Lama.
Agent it shows a LAMA agent
that we are running on it.
And then agent CTL, let's try something
like if you want to check the health.
Of all the agents that we have, you
can see the health status of the agents
that we're running currently, locally.
And you can also let me pick one
of the agents and then one of
the agents agency TL Sentinel.
And then we want to see logs and
then limit, let's say limits to
set that I can see the logging.
The agents are doing, but all
this is possible because we
are doing instrumentation and
elementary on the agent side.
So we are capturing all these metrics.
And then you can also build, we
talked about the SR principles.
You can integrate all this into
Grafana dashboards or whatever tool
you were using for your observability.
And you can have a deep view of all
the agents, you can integrate, SLOs,
sli, and then when you talk about
things like token usage hallucination,
you can monitor all those based on
how the agents are reasoning and the
beauty of all this, you can also.
Now do reasoning trust, which is more
like you narrowing deep into how the
agent is reasoning throughout the
context of response on the call or
the tools that calling and everything.
Information.
So you can see the audit trail and then.
You can see when the agent
is hallucinating at what
stage is hallucinating.
And you can also put where you're
talking about the confident
getting, which will now all alert on
hallucinations and things like that,
and see the reasoning chain across.
And then you can ate them and map them to
different metrics, performance metrics.
And then you can also have performance
metrics that you're just measuring
across the CPS and the agents that you
are managing across different fleet
of the environments that you have.
Yeah.
Also, the beauty of it, you can also
integrate things like GER to check the
different endpoints, the agents out, and
also the API or the CPS tools they're
calling and all those information.
So all that brings us to the aspect
of this is a simple goal-based tool
that you can easily run on your
own and it's really available on
the GI URL that's there and, yeah.
So we can connect on LinkedIn, and
I would like to give a warm thanks
to 42 for giving me this opportunity
to showcase how you can reduce the
complexity that exists within this new
field of agent to simplicity and how
you can bring in the survey principles.
Into managing agents and agentic
infrastructure for your organization,
for your projects and other environments.