And welcome to one more exciting
session on comfort to cloud native 2026.
Keep Coleman, run engineering compliance
with your abandoning your stack.
This is very different from my normal
speech stories because this is a journey
of us of our current topic because
I think it's very important to raise
this here because in the nowadays.
A lot of good rate engineering teams,
they have different challenges.
So this is like a basic introduction
for the people who would like to
understand the topic of compliance,
to get more interested in what
actually important right now for
working with the cloud in the Europe.
And actually share my thoughts, share
about the possible opportunities and.
So by technician for technicians to
share my technical use and for you, me,
Dimitri Laka, senior Cloud Operations
in engineer at Sage GHA in Austria.
So I'm very pleased to have you here.
And before we begin with the technical
part, I would like to take your
attention to one more important thing.
There is a short disclaimer.
So unfortunately I'm not
yet a legal professional.
I'm technically technician
with a different experience.
And please take it as an example for
motivation, for implementation and
for the further resources that you can
potentially find many articles from AWS
people, from major people, from data
center people, from legal consultants,
and build up your opinion on this.
This is to falsify your
visibility and just to see what
is happening, what is possible.
Thank you and.
Yeah, of course Ros from Vienna and I'm
very thankful to Mark to convert the
two team to a three day team for the
one more opportunity to present there.
And one more, very special talk
for this, as I already mentioned.
And I would like to thank you that you
are watching the, our sessions, all
the speakers at attending community
events conferences, cloud related
events coming a s community days.
And this is quote of Steve Jobs for you,
that technology alone is not enough.
It's a technology merit with the liberal
arts, merit with the humanities that
use the results that make our her think.
And without of you all this technical
topic would be not so interesting.
And just one more word about of me.
So I'm Mi Koka.
I am a s community builder.
I'm supporting, for organization for
a different a s staff in Germany.
I'm a s user group leader in Vienna,
so I'm crazy about all the IT technical
space, technology stuff, medicine stuff.
I am senior cloud operations
engineer at Sage, so we are
having lots of different products.
We are building HR systems many,
everything, whatever you might need
for the business management for the
different markets, and we have it for you.
Yeah.
And I have master's in
Silicon Communications.
I have bachelor in business management.
I've worked with AWS since 2020.
And I have various experiences also like
for on premises, for different clouds.
I'm currently also trying to analyze
offerings from European solutions
also to catch up with the Azure.
I hold six a s certifications
and if you watch done my.
Previous talks and comfort to Also, if
you have been to community days you might
know that I'm very keen on photography.
And even today I was photography,
so I have my camera nearby.
Yeah, and I'm very excited to have you
here, but we will have a very serious
speech there because please, virtually,
I would like to ask you to raise your
hand if you was told that AWS or any
kind of cloud is not compiled enough.
So this is.
The session about the engineering
decisions, and despite, I'm doing a
lot of a LS stuff, please don't forget
that I'm an immigrant and it was a
great opportunity to meet thousands
of amazing technicians from a s round,
but I love all the, like on premises,
OpenShift, key burns, Tokyo, I don't
know how many people or cloud native
people, because this is topic that.
Touches the very important point on
the day of instability in our lives in
political instability, supply instability.
We all know what is happening
with the RAM supplies, with the
development of data centers and stuff.
We would like to have a look on the
situation, how you can run your amazing
stuff and which situation was there.
And also please think for a second if the
endurance was really simpler to operate.
And I think this is a situation,
especially now, region hope to the.
Work with the data processing
data, security data stuff.
It's very actual topic because
we engineers, we have a lot of
pressure on this matter and yeah,
as I mentioned we have a very tricky
situation because us in the center,
the engineering teams, we have very
different push from the different sides.
And I try to visualize
it for, in this graph.
So first of all, it's of course
emotional because your product, they
have customers and they would like
to know where is the data, how is
it accessed, how is it processed?
And there is not enough I would say.
A lot of skepticism, not a trust,
lack of trust in general to usage of
the public clouds, deeper scalers.
And it comes with thousands
of small, of trades.
There are a lot of people on LinkedIn
who are writing a really good post.
They really appreciate it because
they raise important points.
But sometimes it just becomes too
emotional and it makes damage from both
technical business and perspective.
And it's not claimed from the legal side.
Yeah.
And also usually fear comes just
some strange marketing, so it's very
messy and we have to keep stay and
calm from political side and legal.
They are pretty tight knit and it's
important to work with the people who
know the stuff because there is a lot
of confusion from the things like.
Cloud Act, GD Power implementations,
tier implementations, there are different
analysis from different European
governments despite the unification within
the U and also from the technical side,
it's of course a matter from the people.
Yeah, like skilled people
who know, for instance.
Perfectly AWS Azure who know their
staff and data centers, and also the
different people who work with VMware.
And so different, many things.
But the problem is that only with a single
portion of just if we keep thinking.
With the small portions that, okay,
we can have the server everywhere.
We'll not have a growth, we will
not have a technological growth.
We'll not have this, boldness that will
drive the markets because there are a lot
of discussions on this plane, but even all
the robust decisions that have to be done.
To grow the businesses.
They're getting clocked also in
the technical circle, starting
that you cannot hire the people.
There is lack of knowledge.
You need to warm up everything.
There is a huge, a lot of questions
about managing the thing and all
these things from all four sites.
They're coming simultaneously to the
engineering teams and what do we want?
We want to ship.
So I have a very nice example,
three Magnifi places just to keep
it emotional for your understanding.
We have a castle in verus
and Ru house in Vienna.
And what might be like, I would
say, United between those things.
But it's very interesting.
So I see, and I know the cases when
companies are doing multimillion
migrations out of AWS Clouds, for
instance, for the public clouds,
they're ripping off different software
they're replacing with the open source
alternatives that are still have a very
big gap because of the lack of r and d
budgets and for instance, broke smokes.
It grown crazily.
It's now a great platform and I see many
VMware people trying to evaluate it.
So just an example that people who
are dropping good managed services
from the vendors and stuff and
start chasing with the cloud, and
they're afraid of the cloud act.
They're afraid of the things and
they think, okay, so basically we
will place our stuff there, but
we will have a managed service.
We will have kind of a result post
whatever we will place it in v
house, in, in our data will be safe.
But it isn't because
data residence is local.
You solve only one smallest
portion of the parcel.
And data ity is legal.
And I will cover the next slides of it.
But just to say it again, if for
instance, you place a hardware in,
the Bunker is in Munich, amazing city.
And if you have a system engineer
in Seattle who is do doing a managed
service for you and holds the admin
keys and controls the management plane,
you are fully also US jurisdiction.
Yeah.
And you don't have to avoid everything
that covers or ship from there, but you
must think instead of placing the data,
you must think wider, that you retain
operational control of the environment.
Yeah.
And following this geography does not
meet jurisdiction, so what does it mean?
First of all, it's jurisdiction
is about operational control.
Salary, not about physical
location or software origin.
Yeah.
For instance, they think only
if the servers are in Europe or
their location, they're safe.
But the problem is there is a very
rude misunderstanding on the concept
of the Cloud Act because Cloud
Act cover covers mainly service
providers and legal entities managing
the environment, not the software
developers who wrote the code, not the
people who are operating the thing.
So this is why there is a very.
Multi-layered, complex of the problems.
For instance, there is a quote that if
you use US software, we are exposed.
If you put the service in
the country, we are safe.
Yeah.
So for instance, if you buy the
licenses for the cell hosted software.
Yeah.
They are dropping some stuff
because of the back doors.
And this is actually the thing
which actually affects everything.
Because Q switches back doors, they can
be also included in the hardware and
the software and even in the cloud, for
instance, is completely European company
operated by Europeans and different stuff.
So they're also potentially not
safe because you can find the
recent Gartner review on the ity.
And they also outlined, because most of
the core providers, they are under this.
Yeah.
And so basically and.
On the other hand, we have another
companies who try to buy manager services
like, I dunno, VMware cloud in Italy as
OpenShift or some kind of Azure stock.
And see if the iron, the hardware
sits in the European Union, they are
fine, but the problem is throughout.
So other many things that
are also guessing involved.
And also physically all this results
in a huge misconception because
basically people think that data
resiliency is exactly the same thing,
like data ity, but data resiliency
does not make not much difference.
And what is important to understand
that the Cloud Act regulates
service providers, not the software.
And, basically most of the staff, which
for instance, build on your hardware,
operates in your data center, let's say,
is placed somewhere in, I dunno, Austria.
Yeah.
And people are Austrian or Germans
or I dunno, Swiss people as well.
Or Hai, whatever, doesn't matter.
They are, placed here.
And basically all the essence of
the cloud act that explicitly target
electronic communication service
providers and remote computing service.
So it basically targets the entity
that hosts and manages the data.
If you buy the software and run
here, then on your own metal,
there is no legal position.
To control of your data and you cannot
be compelled by United States variant.
Yeah, basically.
And simultaneously, on another
hand, you have a managed service,
which is in the US jurisdiction.
So the moment you shift to the managed
service, then the US entity takes the
control of the management plane, and now
they have a full right for exposure since
following the cloud deck, data, custody,
and control of the environment, then.
All this management plan, the
administrative credentials, telemetry
access, operational control.
If they have it outside of your
jurisdiction, then you're subject of it.
And the reality of control
plane is pretty simple.
They don't they for Cloud Act, it's
doesn't matter where use hosted there.
So basically they only care if any US
entity is involved in the process and have
any operational control over the subject.
And there is completely one more
thing that you have to understand,
that there is diction, attaches
to the entity, not to the data.
And what is very interesting, so you
might be get into the fear that Cloud
Act and S 702 is your main targets.
Why are you not able to run on deeper
scalers on the public clouds, on your
solution on the Europe, but in fact so
theoretical risks of this is quite low
because, for instance, a s is publishing
the statistical data that the last
variant, which is powered by Cloud Act,
and S 702 was issued in July, 2020.
And for instance, I think it's very tricky
that you are performing the full redesign
of what your IT infrastructure of your,
you're abandoning your familiar tools just
because you're taking a risk, which is
possible, but statistically not relevant.
And this is the same, like for instance,
you can always die by going out from
the apartment and get hit by the car.
Or for instance, you can
even die in the apartment.
You can get a heart attack or while
working with something or whatever.
There is always a risk, and you can only,
your target is to find the way, how to
minimize it and, basically what you must
not understand, you have to separate
capability from statistical probability.
And what I would like to take
your attention is Cloud Act
explicitly bypass geography.
IT state if US law enforcement.
Agency issues, a valid warrant.
Any US subject company, we must
turn over the data through its
possession, custodial, or control.
And it means everyone for the foreign
party who can makes the operation there
any kind of metadata that comes outside of
the region to start kind of their control.
So all the management layers
and the whole implementation.
This is something that completely.
Makes no difference for you
where it's hosted and very trans.
And what is interesting about S 700 tool,
so basically this thing, it drives the
core law that drives data entity because.
A section 702 of this law makes a
specific permit together data on non-US
citizen without an additional warrant.
And it was in April, 2024, expanded
with the definition of electronic
communication service provider.
And of course you could say that for
instance, GTPR is creating local lesions
that, for instance, it'll try to minimize
or even outreach or just the like.
Mitigate such kind of request because
basically, it'll create an legal overlap
and you might be safe because of it,
but how can you be completely sure
that some legal team of some staff
will fight for your interests there?
Yeah.
And there is some court battle, which
will be not covering this for you.
So basically.
When location makes no difference than
if you are having the management part.
And if US entities involved, you're
a subject for the surveillance.
And you might be also familiar
with the words Durant and IS two.
And this is a very interesting thing,
and this is also widely misunderstood,
the important point that none of them
are explicitly stating that you cannot
use the AWS Azure GCP, whatever.
It's more about more control and then
more about that you get more nature
with the things that you operate.
And most organizations, they are
starting to do a very expensive
migrations, expensive this, but
after all they need a tea around.
I a ance, sorry, not the
whole cloud migration.
And for instance, every time there
is any kind of new kind of regulation
directly from European Union is coming.
Yeah.
There is a huge wave of panic and what
is important to understand is that.
Dora cares about concentration
risk and access strategies, and
A two cares about supply chain
security and jurisdiction analysis.
Neither of them are saying it is
legal to use AWS AWS or Microsoft.
Yeah, and they demand.
Just demand that you
stop doing it blindly.
You can upgrade them, but
you have to be made major.
And if your compliance officer
says Dora means you have to
move out to the ian cloud.
Or someone promises, which is operated by
some, I don't know, two people somewhere
in the dust garbage and whatever it runs.
Yeah.
So instead of this, you need a new.
Compliance officer, obviously, and you
can rely that, you can cover this with
a transparent impact assessment and you
have a documented access strategy, strong
encryption, and if you need, basically you
need to take care of the governance, not
about the three year data migration plan.
And the core thing there is to deescalate
in regulatory planning because.
It's very often used to sell the Ian
clouds, which is actually not bad because
they're also doing an interesting work.
They're covering most of the services
that, I think 80% of the software
that we would like to run in on
the, in general, on the service, on
computers in the cloud, it can do,
but the problem is it mis tracked,
it's misused and it's fundamentally.
Not right, so they don't ban us clouds.
They mandate that you
understand your risks.
So Dora is basically applicable to
the financial service, to supply chain
risk to the concentration in Exit.
And Dora is Ensure is basically
covers financial institutions
that they can survive several it
disruptions because they're basically
a part of critical infrastructure.
Yeah.
They tell you to manage
your consideration risk.
And for instance, if something goes wrong,
it's down that you keep operational.
And for instance, if something
is completely disastrous, you
have an exit strategy and NAS
two, it's expanded cybersecurity
directly for critical entities.
And it's very important to understand that
basically, they want you to be pragmatic.
They want resilience, secure,
governed infrastructure.
They recognize that forcing a bank
to use a less major, less secure,
I don't know, whatever cloud
implementation even increases the
systemic risk, and it applies to
your organization as well because.
Kind of resilience, operational
maturity and I don't know,
level of technology offer it.
It's very p to lose it just because
of the legal misunderstanding.
And also please have a look on the slide.
Meanwhile, I am giving the overview.
So the next one, so the cork question
that you have to ask to the people, to
officers and stuff, you must understand
who operate the control plane because.
The real world application.
This applies to any platform re
regards of whose metal it runs on.
And even the things like managed
yeah, on your hardware or bring your
own key or bring your own hardware,
it does not mitigate the load.
If meanwhile, some us.
Post when they is managing
the application layer.
Yeah.
And if they are, as I mentioned, have
the root credentials, they can manage
the control plane so they have it.
Yeah.
And so every time you get pitched
about some vendor, you ask who operate
the control control plane because
basically you buy software licenses
and you are running the infrastructure.
It more or less save, but then
you hand over those operational.
Power to someone on the side who have some
external entity, which is not European
in this case, then you are exposing it.
So please don't confuse physical
on-premise hardware with digital serenity.
If the managed services operated
by someone, it's even worse
than, for instance, any kind
of public cloud or whatever.
So you have the same
systemic exposure risk.
And from the technical side, what
actually I would like to cover, and
this is why I have here, the very famous
Azures Cloud DE is saying that Cloud,
cloud, our cloud having only 5% of our
systems as an infrastructure is code.
The rest are our
infrastructure and PowerPoint.
And this is the situation that I would
like you to avoid because we it comes.
So a lot of managers, a lot of TCOs
business owners, they do calculations.
They see they will have to pay.
As much.
Like for instance, they have.
For like from the bare numbers
of the like hardware operations,
server renting and the stuff.
Yeah.
But basically spreadsheet will always
miss the human and operational task of,
and for instance, try to hire a senior
DevOps engineer by promising them that
they will look, work on some tricky.
Stack.
No one knows.
No one knows how to operate.
There is no community, there are
no some, I dunno, YouTube guides.
You cannot ask cha GBT
quote how to solve it.
Yeah.
And you'll miss great talents.
So for instance, type of working
with a bad new news thing,
you just give them whatever is
available and you'll miss a grade.
People who will probably make a positive
systematic effect on the whole thing.
And you'll also spend r and d
budget just because on you, instead
of improving the product, your
service, customer satisfaction.
Yeah.
Cycles of the developments.
You will spend money on the so
moving and trying to adapt services.
All this orchestration, conjunction, just
because they are separating entities.
Yeah.
And it's all costs that are coming.
From the translation period.
Also for, because you will have
to operate different environments.
You would need to upskill the people.
It's all huge area, big investment.
You lose the velocity.
You are losing the you are
hitting your time to market.
Yeah.
Of course you are also hitting
the meantime to recovery.
Some people could disagree with me and
it's okay, but because then you are not
putting all the X in the single thing, and
it also, it's about the DR environments.
But for instance, if you're
having seven SLAs, seven
escalation paths, seven vendors.
You need someone with a very strong
nerve to handle this, especially
if they have blast radio and for
instance, when for Google Cloud was,
for instance, down OVH Cloud was down,
or when something gets affected, you
run an AWS CloudFlare was affected.
It also was a kind of damage for you.
And it all makes more and more it all
makes more and more orchestration.
Yeah.
So once again, this breach sheet usually
looks at the compute costs, storage costs,
and maybe some migration consultants.
What it completely misses is the
human factor and operational tasks.
And if they think that some, I
don't know, risks, they are bigger,
that the UA team is not agile.
They cannot manage incidents,
they cannot more stuff.
They need to retrain worth this.
You can give it a try, but.
Please think about this twice.
Another point, as I already mentioned.
Yeah.
So you can really affect
your recovery times.
You can basically destroy all the
years of foundation that you are
building, and this is the most.
Tricky thing because people feeling
steady in the familiar environment
and this is a huge stress.
You might bring new people.
So this is will never result in the
planning migration times and drawbacks
that of this huge reconstruction.
They will, you'll see
them basically there and.
Basically, if you are affecting your
recovery time, your uptime, your
cross vendor management every time, so
this is basically compliance theater.
This is not something that the
major operation would look like
and to improve the situation.
AWS has done a very interesting thing.
So as maybe you are already aware,
in January, 2036, the European
Cloud was launched, but it's a very
huge project, which completely new
legal entity completely You operated
people, I'll say a lot of things
for Italy, our develop in Germany.
I'm familiar with the people and yeah.
Everything, metadata, cloud, trail, IM.
No resilience on outside exposure.
So it's certified for the Dora.
It's certified by the German authorities
because for, if you're a German company,
it already results both data placement
and data processing place for you.
So this is not just a region, this is
another cloud, which is built on already
familiar technology that AWS brings.
And, their core thing is there,
that partition is the perimeter.
And if you might have used AWS in Europe
before, it wasn't the global AWS partition
because you know that some of the data
is going to the US East one, right?
And here it never happens.
Everything stays within the
Branden Brandenburg region.
And, and this is a huge
fundamental change.
Yeah.
And AWS currently you have
only one region of presence.
AWS will keep it growing, so it'll
have will have additional small
regions in the nearby countries as
was already shared and announced.
And it solves the who of
Serenity and it makes you.
Almost much more fortified in
compliance matter without of
losing coffee or AWS stuff.
And there and why is it important,
if we might look here, we have this
table and I have here three outlines.
Why is it important?
You might see that, for instance, for
GDPR, that resiliency is basically
getting covered If you run in
Frankfurt or in Paris or in Ireland.
So it's all right from Dora.
A s supply suv, multi
Z, you are also covered.
And then by NIE tools, standard U
region you are basically covered.
This is by where.
But then the who comes.
So basically ESC might require
tier, so you don't need to
completely destroy everything as we
discussed on the previous slides.
Financial resilience, right?
So it might be applied for the
outpost because it's question for the
like exit strategy for the And nas.
Yeah, so basically it's covered
as well by European sewing cloud.
So this is an incremental improvement.
By outed trail, you have everything.
And they are the most complicated
part for Dora and NIS.
Most of the things that are supplied
by EC are sufficient, and they are
even sufficient in terms of the
classic Frankfurt region, right?
But for GCPR, you see the very, I know
not many people familiar what is XKS and
just quickly XKS, it's a implementation
for AWS, for the external key management.
And, so basically you have a device
that runs it HCM on your managed
location on your data center, and you
are having key keys placed there, but.
This is a very expensive joy
because you need the device.
You need also upskilling.
You need the things and to
completely falsify for, with the key
management lock you need this payer.
But I don't know, even the financial, I
heard only one financial institution use
this scheme for a very specific case.
Even they are very big.
Known financial institution.
They cover enough on the KMS.
Yeah.
So basically when auditors are knocking,
don't throw your hands and save, run in
a OS you need to express how you use the
technical opportunities and point them
which of the regulation points solve how.
And basically, yeah.
So if you have a look.
Once again, there is always a measure on
the control measure and you can do it.
So unfortunately, not
everything is perfect.
So still AWS hasn't done a
scheme, like for instance,
Microsoft has implemented the.
Management through the Chinese
company when yeah, they were
afraid to lose a huge investment.
That was it.
I was following the development
within the last few years.
It was huge commitment from everyone.
It was an amazing, huge job.
And it's very sad that by some people it's
called like a marketing gap and or the
whole marketing show, but I don't know.
It's too much investment
for the marketing show.
So the problem is it
heavily increases your.
Like position, like in terms of compliance
and for the 90% of the companies, it
might be more than sufficient, but
still Delaware, stills Delaware, and
this is why BSI said that the technical
splitting from the US management parity
sufficient French people, they said that.
So it's also political and French is
very strong on the cloud presence.
Yeah.
We know VH, we know the scale well
and they know also their business.
And this is a very important
point, why ECS is not a hundred
percent solution for everyone.
And this and partition as perimeter.
Yeah.
Unfortunately doesn't solve it
directly, but it makes it much
more harder because there is no
direct ownership of the region.
There is no direct supply chain
because everything is covered
through gym, bh like entity.
And for instance, if something
happens in the Frankfurt,
officials will come to them.
They will come to the AWS and say
okay, in Frankfurt you have something.
They will work it like us,
US government, US company.
Then here we will go to the gha, and then
GHA gets covered by the like German state.
They are getting covered by GTR
processes and all the stuff, and
it'll be much more complicated, but
still exposure is possible, but.
It's more than enough to keep operating
there and it's a good opportunity.
And let's compare it to the very
interesting case I have for you.
So there is a table and because I
will speak about the outpost on the
upcoming slides and you can see that
basically all post they have the same
coverage like normal ADOS region and,
a lot of people think that if they buy
outpost, place it in the data center.
It should be fine.
But no, you are having exactly the same,
all the same pack of issues with exposure
like you have in the normal a LS region
in ESC, you are only, you can pass the
benchmark for the French authorities
like you don't have onsite resiliency
if you are not in deland Germany.
And cloud Act is basically reduced because
you still have indirect parity, but the
rest of the main compliance for the kind
of NAS and Dora, you are compliant and
even, and if you bring the outpost, then
you're also compliant by that resilience.
So basically you have a very big pack of
things and they, where the things might
be escalated and involved and so on.
And if you would like to have more
understanding, I highly recommend you
to have a look on this website because
you can calculate your like use case,
your organization, your demands, your
whatever you would like, and it'll give
you which actually things are applicable,
because in some cases there is no other
choice like Uran eat bare metal yourself.
So please have a look and.
I would like to proceed with the case.
Why, actually, I decided
to do this presentation.
So let's talk about AWS outpost.
Why is it so interesting?
Because it was in consideration
so in many different places,
also by different projects.
I heard about people who
were considering them.
My teams many times they
were considering this.
I heard I was assisting my friend who
was as a as a, thinking about the alt
was by this particular case, we have
kind of platform enterprise customers.
Of course, for me it's a regulatory
environment because not only like
on the baseline of euros, there is
also additional data and gazettes
that are coming from the Austrian
government and team has amazing
experience in a s existing AWS staff,
muscle memory, infrastructure as
called runbooks tooling, everything.
And there is a danger that basically
customers, they are afraid to
operate in the public cloud.
And then we, and the data is
basically not in Austria and it's not
applicable by some additional special
cases that, or some certain data
they were processing in this case.
A pressure from regulations that
data stays local and business said,
okay, we can attribute from scratch.
Scratch.
Let's think we bring the outpost.
Basically we have a s our own data center.
And yeah, everything looks
because it's very logical.
Okay, we have a S here.
Data is safe, data safe, unfortunately.
It's not, and let me explain you why.
Because Outpost was initially built
like a solution for the low latency
edge compute so that for instance,
when those latency might cost you some
damage by performance or you might have
real, any kind of real time data flow.
Image processing, like for
telecom providers, actually
also using it on the edge.
And I know for instance, it's a lot
in United Arab Emirates is using
a huge number of outpost tracks
on the, and even to fortify their
data processing on AWS stack.
And for them it's all right.
Yeah, but compliance story
came for it later and com.
This is why it has a very, a lot of things
who are syncing the application of the,
so they perfectly solved the physical data
resiliency because I know even from one
of my jobs, they were customers coming.
We want to know that service in
this rack, in this building, in
this o city, in this country.
No way.
It solves it.
So all good.
And you have familiar
AWS hardware, everything.
APIs are the same services are the same.
And you have a good performance
because you're basically on site.
And basically you can, have you
can solve the need for a s but
not the operational serenity.
And because it doesn't solve, as you
have seen in the previous tables,
that the control plane metadata is in
the parent region, in which, in front
port and you have the direct exposure.
Yeah.
They're basically embracing
a extension of a region.
Thankfully, they can be applied
to ESC, but there is rather
another more complicated things.
Coming later.
So there is a management and by global
AWS team and as we have discussed,
it can be also a target for it.
And it's makes the direct cloud deck cloud
act exposure identical to you central one.
So where is the benefit?
You might ask me?
Yeah.
'cause basically there is no benefit
otherwise you run it together with a
CS basically you are overcomplicating
the usage of the Frankfort or
whatever standard AWS region.
And if you dive into the
outpost, you have no lambda.
It's somehow made with the iot core
that you deploy from your EC2 budget.
No, it's in no glue, no
SageMaker, no redshift for ai.
They supplied on the last reinvent
designated device, which you
can install in your data center.
No trends at gateways.
No.
A LB in KEKS is stripped down.
S3 has limits and it
sell additional payment.
So you have to be very.
Confident in your setup.
Basically, and you just cannot
have S3 because it'll bump your
pricing for this, the whole thing.
And basically you're having left with
a plain compute that looks like AWS,
but in reality, I don't know, it looks
even worse than the regular data center.
And we still were considering
it, so let's not think about,
talk about the bad things.
So we still try to understand
if it's applicable for us
because it's construction with
the European, Syria cloud.
It more or less fine.
So the first idea was to understand
how much of it do we need, because
obviously we have an issue.
We have to translate our
data center capacity to the.
Our post capacity, we have to do, perform
the stacking, select the instance types
put every, everything basically there.
And we are thinking how can we convert
the image set of VMware to the capacity?
The first idea was basically to go the.
Per VCPU, it was our hanging, and we
did in a few steps basically that we
made the baseline with the data center
in the region we benchmark from it.
Then we stepped up to the instances
that we will have on the outpost, and
then we were simulating the traffic.
So you can get it from, I know if you use
CloudFlare or any kind Edge network or
you know your customer patterns or you
have telemetry inside of your application.
And then we started to discuss, so
basically, which scenarios do we have
what is important because we wanted
to replicate the behavior of actual
user and, basically we outlined
what is important, which functions
are generating most of the load.
And we translated it because
I'm the Python person, even
before the clock times.
And basically I use the locals together
with the playwright and, based,
thankfully to the data we saw the fail,
fail rates, response times and RPS.
So the standard way proposed by
AWS, you bombard the API, this
is what we heard from the team.
But unfortunately it was not applicable
for us because we needed to see the
real user behavior of what data.
And we put one by one architecture DC AWS,
same databases, same application versions,
everything is the same installations.
And we did it.
One-to-one.
And then basically we decided,
okay, we use the Azure in Vienna
because it'll represent like
90% of our customer patterns.
And it does have no relation to AWS
and for instance, it'll be stupid
to benchmark AWS from AWS, even from
another region because there so many
things about a s global network.
And yeah.
So basically yeah, it was representing
the origin and and as a log generator,
locost is actually was pretty nice.
The only drawback together with a
playwright there not enough documentation
because then I had to, and after
recording of this thing that actually
was happening there it was not able to
come completely into, correctly interpret
the structure of the application.
So that's why quote code.
So we generated by web server
C code, we processed, converted
to the action pipelines.
It was good.
And another issue was that
on Azure Container Service.
Unfortunately Locust was suffering
from the synchronization issues
and but I still solved it and we
were able to handle the benchmarks.
And what is interesting.
We were basically as I'm already
mentioned, we're standing on the VCPU.
What is important gap here that when you
are doing the migration is that you might
have on the VCPU term, both real core.
And SMT thread and for some
applications, SMT thread, they are
basically even hurting the performance.
This is why you might prefer to run
on the real circuits real CPU course.
And in data center configs, we
actually do have the real course.
And in AWS you take four
vcps in static configuration.
It mostly might mean that it's two core
and four threats, and it still will give
performance books, but not the, to the.
Basically DME to the use of the
actual course because if I remind
you, if you are familiar with
what is the CPU pipeline, yeah.
You might know that it is basically
to get more efficiency out of it.
And we found out actually that on the
baseline, the against the region Yeah.
And against the thing.
The simulation that we have in data
center, they were plus, minus on the same
performance level with this same cbu.
Capacity.
And what is interesting for v
ps on a s they were performing
as fast, like real four cores.
But the main difference,
there was a lot capacity.
For instance, with the test with a
single user, the performance on Outpost
was quite good, comparable to the data
center and, the performance start to
degrade when more and more users and
actually VCP threat s and ts, they
were handling somewhere in the middle,
but they still couldn't compare.
This is why you are,
you should have on four.
The vpu that are HA performed
by the course on your VMware.
It would mean probably
for eight vpu, any AWS.
And it might also affect your
licensing for databases, for
operating system for the staff.
And this is very important to understand.
And then when we apply the actual
generation of the instances, we get
through the stacking of the outpost
because we can take either M instances,
C instances, and they actually benchmark
them as you see from the slide.
So it results basically
in performance increase.
But there were no magical post
performed, as good as a good data center.
And, what is more?
If with the CPUs it was
completely all right.
We were shuttered with the storage
because there is no IO two, there
are no I IO one and for instance, on
the sun attached to VMware, you might
have 200 K, 300 K iops, but on this.
You are limited only with the 16,000.
And for instance, if web application
was doing fine, some internal
database processing and stuff
that we have measured, they really
suffered from the performance
that even tripled doubled the job.
And to solve this, we could either use
additional levels of rates, trippings,
or additional levels of I don't know.
Tell me please.
So basically pull pulls for the
drives and you might also have an
opportunity to it would mean the
complete restructure and then lift and
shift becomes more complicated there.
And for instance you need to
also take it into account if
you would like to consider it.
What is also interesting there yeah, so
by performance, by this, we understood
that basically gains on the data center.
They were, we didn't wait because
you can ask AWS to give access to
Al Post and Al Post uses the same
hardware like in the region, and
you can come and try just to run it.
You can just simply spin up
a few instances and already
understand your baseline for
the performance and it's public.
In documentation.
You can have it thousands of megabytes
of reading, 16 thousands stool,
CPU generation, and you can see it.
But in our case, there were no
jump with additional drawbacks.
Yeah.
And what I would say that as I already
mentioned after we replace the instances
here there is always a gap in the AL
Post because it shapes with a m six I
for instance, generation of instances
and, and it was pretty much consistent,
but it's still behind of generations
that you might have in the actual cloud.
Yeah.
And baseline might be boom, 15, 20%.
And you might, you do a huge
commitment for the hardware, which
will be more expensive, more hard
to operate, and it doesn't really.
Give you much benefit through the,
against the, for instance, normal cloud.
So please think about it and in general
if you still would like to solve the
data resiliency with it, you might be
interested in running in the hybrid
way that only customer data, which
is, for instance, heating by the
regulation is running on the outpost.
But for the rest you plan it and for you.
It's impossible to make
one-to-one mapping.
We analyzed so many metrics that
are coming from different sources,
from the system, from observability
platform for the traffic statistics.
And we were not able one to one to the
lift and shift and then you want to
bring the cloud modernization during
this migration from data center, right?
So you still have, with the
amount of over provisioning.
That you are having there.
And basically, outpost destroys
all the benefits of the cloud
that you can dynamically have
savings, more power, less power.
You have to do excessive planning and
you will still hit double payments.
And you will discover actual your
capacity when you'll be already in
production and you'll have to pay for it.
And for the like for the business
itself, outpost brings in the
approval documents, card software
list migration services, right?
Which is maybe also can be done
by your migration team inside.
And, and yeah.
This is what visible for the
management level for us, for the
technicians, it looked like this.
That also is very power hungry.
It was taking a lot of power to require
a very specific cooling performance.
So you need to rely on the good.
Data center that will place it.
You need to do the high availability.
You would need to double the
racks and also double the cost
for the power and cooling alone.
Data center themselves, they might
be, first of all, physically and
then competitively able to handle
the installation of the outpost.
There are partners who are actually
running the, but for instance,
you must ensure that you do need
to do your team and data center.
They have to do lots of work
before you do the pre-installation.
Before AWS ships everything, you
need a good redundant uplinks.
You may also probably need external
firewalls or firewall on, on-premises, and
you need to have a person who might manage
it and for instance, you might lose.
Your DC certifications
when you bring it in.
And for also data center miles, be
sure that they provide enough of UPS
power generators, because those guys
I saw at many different data centers,
they have huge diesel generators.
Are you sure you're able
to supply it yourself?
You're basically not renting a compute.
In this case, you're trying to
build a data center in the very
uncommercial things just because for
some reason you want to use a s APIs.
And this is a thing you must consider
and still go back to the beginning of the
stock and analyze if ECS is sufficient
for you, or there is a chance you will
find a better solution that will make a
correct trade off for the implementation
of Outpost or the things that I mentioned
that you are conversing your experience,
your team to another technological stack.
So yeah.
As I mentioned a good data center
would give in the me if you would
like still to have a minimum
configuration of the outpost.
The good data center will give you
things that outposts will not give you,
ha oncall and you are basically moving
to operation on your own team are.
Sure that your team will be able to
perform the infrastructure management.
Yeah.
So ha is doubling the costs.
So amount of preparatory
work are the costs.
Maybe it's better to do the
additional consultancy with
the data officer and, yeah.
And what is very important here is
basically also there is a big trap
that comes from the beginning, why All
Post was made us, and don't forget,
this is an extension of the region.
It's a backup trap.
So for instance, your
compliance story says.
Video snapshots saying Frankfort.
You might ask me why this is easier,
because the standard AWS backup, if
you don't have S3 on your outpost it's
very expensive and it'll push all the
EBS snapshots with optimizations that
AWS doing, like in normal cloud, the
duplication this to the parent region.
Unfortunately this can be solved and
it would mean even if you go to VM
to Convault, they will say sorry.
We will really provide you
only file level backup.
Or they will rely and apply
their own optimizations of EBS
snapshots that will travel.
For instance to Frankfort, and
it's not applicable for you.
Why to mess up this if the
data is still landing there?
This is the first question that
you have to ask yourself, and it
would mean that you need to rely on
another parity that, for instance, we
were considering to use S3 storages
by local providers, for instance.
Like Exoscale in Austria
app has S3 packet offering.
So Azure BLO storage, they have a high
grade in gold also gold grade in Austria.
Yeah, but it's already what
I mentioned at the beginning.
It makes your SLA more complicated
and more and more things that
are supposed to be management.
They're coming to your team
and you're losing lot, lots of
good things and you might rely.
On basically a repeatability of your
environment, you drift will be very
expensive for you and also better.
Drift will be very expensive for you
and you must make sure that Ansible is
your friend and you can do the restore.
More complex.
Restore, because you cannot restore
the drive, the specific file, the
e tool you need to do the complete
rebuild of the environment.
And this is hits your
recovery and only end double.
They might, they thought that might
solve it, but through the EBS buffer,
but you still rely on external
parity and it does not look like.
And manage the service, so it
makes things even more complicated.
Also with the dr. So you need in the
DR rule, 3, 2, 1 for the backups that
you have three copies of two locations
and and if you do the DR somewhere
else, you're violating the resiliency
and this is not what you want.
And it basically, you doubling the
CapEx operational budgets to run
or double out post double disease.
Or you are basically having
a few strategies, right?
That you're accepting the cap, you
do the partial resiliency you have.
Awful odd times, or you are running two
separate environments in different things.
But then you might ask
yourself, why do I need this?
Why can't I just use
the local SW provider?
And this is the right question actually.
So if you're already building the
environment, maybe we should continue
and it'll cover you with all the burden.
And actually what I would.
Take your attention, which is highly
discussed currently in a east environment.
Unfortunately, it's a very painful
and tragic point for me, but the war
on the Middle East, it affected that,
the concept with the region and the
variability zone, it doesn't help
anymore because, for instance, Bahrain
is vanished from a s control plane.
All the damage through the damage and,
basically you cannot be sure even if you
rely on the few locations, you are safe.
So it would require much deepened pricing.
And of course, us with the cybersecurity
is a thing which is also having a
lot of pressure from the operation.
And you might ask us, what do we do?
And unfortunately there is no universal
answer that I can give it to you.
And it's the same with the photography.
When people are buying the camera
saying, please tell me the settings
how to, you are taking pictures,
but you have thousand situations.
This is why you need to take the points
from what I told you, analyze if the
Edge service is applicable for you,
if it solves your issue, if eecs.
Sufficient.
If that there is no universal.
It's like with a relat relationship,
I cannot tell you what to do with
your partner and we can only try like
a friend, to friend to navigate you.
And this is why I have a scheme.
So you need a decision tree.
So first of all, you need to understand
how strict is your operational ity.
So if it's not that strict, you
can live in the standard, I don't
know, AWS Asia GGP region, right?
Or if you have.
Then you are some specific
things that are intercepting,
then probably they're sold a CS.
Yeah.
If the data must physically
stay in your country Yeah.
Then you are thinking if it's
acceptable to you to stay in Germany
because gt PR is more or less unified.
European Union laws are
more or less unified.
Yeah.
Then you try, still try to outpost and
you accept the risks that I mentioned
and if the regulation repeats, yeah.
You are still trying to yeah.
If not, you are sticking to ECS or
ECS plus AL Post, or then you're
considering the accident, unfortunately.
And then this is the point
where it's important on the
immigration planning on things.
You do the cloud diagnostic tools and
even if you have the four oh stack, there
might be a replacement with the minor
changes, not with the complex changes, but
you must keep the architecture adaptable.
And this is the part which is
actually mentioned in knees and Dora.
So basically what I mentioned that
you maturely, you know your stuff,
you have an exit strategy, so
there is no, nothing tragic in it.
You might be just be flexible
and technical solution will come.
And you might ask yourself,
just let's do it again.
So regulator require forcing the
compliance team commit to commit.
Yeah.
You cannot just build an
architecture based on LinkedIn post.
You must ask your legal own compliance
team what is the situation, what
is demand from your customer,
and then your taking a decision.
Yeah.
Who has operational access
to your environment?
What is okay?
What exposes it?
Then you also consider it.
Dr. Dr it's very important
to deliver correct services.
This is the core thing of our work, but
it also must be correct to operate it.
And honestly, in some situation, good
local data center might be better than
the whole mess with the air services
route, for instance, as you can see.
So let's just quickly recap the talk.
Geography is not a
jurisdiction control plane.
ES exposure, not the zip code.
So Dora and needs require risk
assessment controls, not you
only cloud ECS is operational.
Soon externally might still
happen, but as we discussed,
three risks are more or less slow.
Yeah.
Al posts are solving physics, but
bring a lot of headache and they does
not solve the law and E-C-E-S-C with
the outpost, it's the most compiled.
Architecture possible with a s but
it brings a lot of overhead and
only benchmarking will bring you a
good visibility on your workload.
And, please keep in mind that
there is no direct translation.
There might be changes.
You need to falsify the baseline and work
out of it and ask the questions to your
regulator, to your team, to your bosses.
You must have to do it, and you
will find a solution and make a
decision on the whole information.
Thank you so much.
Thank you for your long talk.
I would be happy to stay in
court to discuss the points,
to share the experiences, and
please enjoy the comfort too.
There are so many.
Additional talks and I'm very
grateful to have you here.
So if you have any questions,
please reach me on LinkedIn and
on the staff and keep building.
You are amazing.
Thank you so much and have a nice
stuff and see you in the clouds.