Hello, everyone.
My name is Neetu Gangwani.
Today, I'm going to represent
energy efficient, cost optimized
serverless computing strategies,
challenges and future directions.
Serverless computing has transformed
cloud computing, offering remarkable
cost saving and operational simplicity.
However, the growing adoption
of serverless workloads raises
concern about energy footprints.
This presentation explores the
intersection of energy efficiency
and cost effectiveness in serverless
computing, highlighting innovative
strategies and addressing key challenges.
Join us as we delve into the future
of sustainable cloud computing.
Now let's see why the serverless
computing is in trend.
The main reason serverless computing is
in trend is because scaling on demand.
Serverless platforms dynamically
adjusts computing resources within
milliseconds, automatically scaling
from handling a few requests to
the millions without intervention.
This intelligence scaling ensures optimal
performance while preventing both resource
wastages and the application's bottleneck.
Another one is pay per use pricing.
With a revolutionary pricing model,
organizations only pay for precise
computation time in milliseconds.
This granular approach can reduce cloud
costs by 40 80 percent compared to
traditional servers, making enterprise
grade computing accessible to all.
Another one is Simplified Operations
By abstracting away infrastructure
complexity, serverless enables
developers to deploy 4x faster.
Teams can focus on innovation and business
logic rather than managing servers,
security patches, scaling, configurations,
dramatically accelerating time to market.
Next, Addressing the Energy
Footprints of Serverless
So first one is energy aware auto scaling.
Advanced machine learning algorithm
analyze historical workload patterns
in real time metrics to dynamically
optimize resource allocation, reducing
energy waste by up to 30 percent while
maintaining sub millisecond response time.
Another one is hardware
software co design.
Integration of ARM based processor and
simply specialized hardware escalator.
delivers up to 40 percent power
saving compared to traditional x86
architecture while custom firmware
optimization further energy efficiency.
Third one is function chaining
optimization intelligent function
orchestration reduces inter function
communication overhead by 50 percent
through strategic co location and
data caching while automated workflow
analysis eliminates redundant
compute cycle and memory operations.
Emerging Energy Aware Pricing Model.
So what is 40 percent is a reduction,
whereas 25 percent is the cost saving.
Advanced Carbon Aware Pricing Model
factor in real time energy cost and
environmental impact driving up to 40
percent reduction in data center power.
consumption through smart workload
scheduling and resource optimization
and 25 percent in the cost saving
implementation of AI driven
resources allocations and energy
monitoring tools results in 25
percent average cost saving enabling.
Organizational automatically
shift workloads to time and reason
with optimal energy efficiency.
Let's see the real world case
studies and success stories.
First one is retail.
A Fortune 500 retailer transformed their
Black Friday operation by implementing
serverless computing, handling 2.
5 million transactions per reducing
server energy consumption by 60%.
This resulted in 2.
1 million annual cost saving while
maintaining 100ms response time.
Healthcare, a national healthcare
network, revolutionized patient
care by processing real time health
data through serverless function.
This enables analysis of 50, 000
patients record per minute while
cutting energy usage by 40%, leading
the faster diagnosis and 800, 000
dollars in annual infrastructure saving.
Another one is financial services.
A global investment firm modernized
their trending platform using serverless
architecture, processing 100, 000
transactions per second with 99.
99 percent reliability.
This transformation slashed energy
consumption by 30 percent and reduce
transaction processing cost by 45 percent
while improving response time by 65%.
Let's see the challenges and opportunities
for the sustainable serverless.
First one is standardized benchmark.
Establishing industry wide
energy efficient metrics and
testing protocol is essential for
meaningful platform comparison.
Current benchmark varies by up to 40
percent across providers, highlighting
the urgent need for standardization.
Multi tenant energy measurement.
Accurate per tenant energy
attribution in shared environment
remains a critical challenge.
Advanced monitoring system must
track resource usage with 99.
9 percent accuracy while maintaining
performance and privacy standards.
Regulatory compliances organization
must navigate an expanding framework
of environmental regulations, including
the EU's Green Deal, regional carbon
Reporting requirements proactive
adoption of sustainable practice
can reduce compliance risk by 60%.
What are the future direction?
To build a sustainable
serverless ecosystem.
First one, technological innovation.
Pioneering breakthrough advancement.
In energy efficient serverless
architecture through quantum computing
integration, AI powered work to optimize
and next generation cooling system.
Second, industry wide collaboration
for ranging strategic Partnership
between lending cloud providers,
academic institutions and enterprise
stakeholders to establish universal
green computing standards and accelerate
sustainable serverless adoption.
Third, developer empowerment, cultivating
a culture of environmental responsibility
by equipping Developers with energy,
monitoring tools, sustainable metrics,
and practical guidelines for building
eco friendly serverless applications.
Let's go to the future.
The future of serverless, a
new era of sustainability.
First one, cost optimization.
Next generation serverless platform
will revolutionize cost management
through AI powered resource
allocation and granular usage based
on pricing, potentially reducing cloud
spending by up to 40 percent while
maximizing computational efficiency.
Another one, performance optimization.
Machine learning driven scaling
algorithm and containerized function
execution will deliver consistent sub 50
millisecond response time, enabling real
time application to handle million of
concurrent requests while automatically
balancing resource utilization.
Another one is environmental
responsibility, the
biggest responsibility.
The future of serverless embarrasses
sustainability through smart power
management, carbon aware scheduling,
and renewable energy integration.
Organizations can expect to reduce
their computing carbon footprint by
up to 60 percent while maintaining
optimal performance through
innovative green computing practice.
Let's see the conclusion.
A sustainable path forward.
First one, energy efficiency.
Implement next generation serverless
architecture with intelligent workload
distribution and automated resource
optimization to reduce energy consumption.
by up to 40 percent cost effectiveness,
deploy advanced monitoring system
and AI driven resource allocation
to achieve 30 percent cost saving
while maintaining peak performance
through intelligent scaling decisions.
Environmental impact drive positive
environmental change through
renewable energy integration.
Achieving carbon neutral
operations and supporting global
sustainability goals with measurable
carbon and reduction metrics.
Thank you.
Have a good one.