Hello, everyone.
I'm Venugopal Reddy Deepa, and I'm
really excited to be here today to talk
about topic that is shaping the future
of healthcare API integration and how
MuleSoft is playing a crucial role
in advancing personalized medicine.
So let's start with a big number.
So by 2025, the global healthcare
API market is expected to reach 62.
8%. Billion.
So that clearly signs that healthcare
industry is going towards the digital
transformation at an incredible phase.
but here is the challenge.
Hospitals, clinics, labs and pharmacies
all operates on a different systems
that they don't communicate effectively.
So what?
What does that lead to?
So doctor struggles to access the
patient complete medical history and,
test results being delayed due to the
disconnected systems and hospitals
realized on slow manual data entry,
increased errors and inefficiencies.
So ultimately, this issue slows down
the patient's care, increase cost and
lead to the poor healthcare outcome.
but, there are a good, what
are the good news is the API
integration is solving all this.
So with MuleSoft API integration
approach, hospitals and healthcare
organizations are seeing a 65 percent
reduction in the integration time.
So think about what does means,
what user to take months or years.
to integrate is now happening in the
fraction of time, allowing healthcare
providers to adopt new technologies,
faster, improve workflows and focus on
the patient instead of it challenges.
So in today's session, I will walk through
you through the biggest challenges in
healthcare data integration and how
new software integration approach is
solving these issues and how, AI and
real time, data and enabling personalized
medicine and real world case study where
API integration is transformed major.
Healthcare network and the impact of
diagnostics, cost savings and security.
So by end of the sessions, I hope
you will see the API integration is
not is just improving the healthcare
it, but it's transforming the
way we deliver the patient care.
So let's move on to next slide.
Okay, Before we talk about the
solutions, let's take a step back
and look at the major challenges
in healthcare industry today.
So despite advancing digital
health, many hospitals, clinics and
healthcare institutions still face
serious roadblocks when it comes
to share and access patients data.
So this challenges fall
into that category.
three key areas like data
fragment and legacy infrastructure
and regulatory complaints.
So coming to data fragments.
So one of the biggest
issues is healthcare.
Today is how scattered patients
treat is across multiple systems.
So 75 percent of healthcare organizations
struggle to connect patients
because across different platforms.
So a single hospital must coordinate
patients across 18 different
electronic health record systems.
So on top of that, hospitals
manage 450 terabytes of data.
patient's imaging data equivalent
to millions of medical images.
What does it mean?
So doctors many times don't
have full picture of, patient
health care in real time.
So imaging a cancer patient recording
being split across different hospitals,
labs, and pharmacies, if these systems
don't communicate, doctors might miss
critical test results or pass treatments
leading to delayed care and repeat tests
and potential diagnosis will happen.
So Without seeming way to integrate
data, patient care slows down and
error increases and costs go up.
So in the second one,
legacy infrastructure.
hospitals and health institutions
depends on technology to power
increase critical operations.
But here's the problem.
81 percent of healthcare institutions
are still running systems that
are 10, 8 to 15 years of old.
So These legacy platforms process 1.
2 million daily transactions, but they
were never designed for today's fast
moving and data driven environment.
So why this is a problem.
So this outdated systems create
bottlenecks, slow down the flow of
critical medical data when hospital
doctors and nurse spend more time.
navigating outdated software instead
of focusing on the patient care.
So in today's world where real time
data, saves lives, hospitals can suffer
to rely on slow disconnected systems.
So next one is regulatory complaints.
So keeping the patient's data secure,
healthcare is one of the most heavy
regulated industry because of patient
privacy laws, data security laws,
rules, and, strict compliance standards.
every healthcare.
Facility is responsible for
safeguarding over 280, 000 patient
records, and 92 percent of healthcare
organization report major challenges
in maintaining the compliance
across their integrated systems.
So these compliance challenges
cause critical project delays,
averaging 187 days, that's more
than six months of setbacks.
So why does this matter?
So non compliance can result.
Hi, T. Finds legal risk
and loss of patient stress.
So data breaches in health care cost on
average of 10 million per incident, making
security failures with incredible cost.
So at the same time, hospitals need
to share patients data securely
across different systems to
make sure doctors have the right
information at the right time.
So why does this matters?
And how do we solve these problems?
he's these challenges is.
Fragmented data or data system and complex
compliance requirements, all creating
roadblocks that slows down the healthcare
innovations and impacting patient's care.
So that's where API
integration comes into picture.
By connecting systems, automating
workflows, and making sure secure
data across APIs allows hospitals to
break down into CLEOs, modernization
infrastructure, and complying with
regulations without completely
replacing their existing IT systems.
And this is exactly
where API led approach.
makes a difference.
Now that we discussed the challenges
in the healthcare industry, let's talk
about the how MuleSoft API LateConnect
approach solves these problems.
So MuleSoft uses three layer API
architecture that creates a seamless,
secure and efficient healthcare ecosystem.
Instead of replacing old systems,
it connects them, allowing workflow
automation, a better user experience.
So system APIs, Connecting to the
legacy systems of instance data access.
So usually hospitals still rely on
the old disconnected systems, make
it difficult to retrieve patient
records and system APS act as a
bridge between the systems, allowing
data to flow securely and instantly.
So 75.
78 percent of reduction in data access
time, meaning doctors and nurses can
quickly retrieve a critical patient record
instead of waiting on slow manual process.
And this API standardized
complex medical data for mix.
Ensures that data from different
hospitals, labs and pharmacies can be
accessed in unified format that leads to
the faster diagnosis, quicker treatment
decisions and improve the coordination
between the health care providers.
So other layer process API
automates workflows and.
Treatment protocols will follow.
So process APIs plays a crucial role
in orchestrating clinical workflows and
automating complex health care processes.
So 63 percent of reduction in treatment
protocols implementing time, which
means that patient receives the right
patient faster and more efficiently.
This API reduction medical errors
by making sure in the lab results.
Prescriptions and treatments plans are
automatically updated across systems,
and they also automated insurance
claims process appointment scheduling
and, prescription, renewals, reductions
and workflows for medical staff.
on the other hand, experience
API enhancing user experience
and patient engagement.
So experience APIs make healthcare data
accessible in a simple, secure and user
friendly way for both So 82 percent of
increasing provider satisfaction because
doctors and nurses no longer have a
deal with slow, outdated interface.
So these APIs power personalized
patient protocols, allowing end users
to view their health records and track
medications and schedule appointments.
So why does it matter?
By combining systems, process and
experience APIs, MuleSoft creates
a fully integrated healthcare
environment where data flows
seamlessly between the hospitals,
labs, pharmacies, and patient portals.
And treatments workflows are automated,
reducing delays and human errors, and
doctors and patients have easily Access
to critical information, improving the
decision making, the case, outcomes.
So MuleSoft API led approach isn't
just about the IT, it's about
transforming the way healthcare
is delivered, make it faster,
smarter, and more, patient centered.
Let's move on to the other slide.
Okay, now that we have seen the MuleSoft
API led approach connects healthcare
systems, let's talk about how integration
is driving personalized medicine, where
treatments are trialized specifically to
each patient's unique healthcare profile.
Today, healthcare is shifting from one
size fits all treatments to data driven
personalized care and APIs are playing
a crucial role in making these problems.
So there are three major ways APIs are
transforming personalized medicine.
First one is real time data integration.
This is nothing but the fastest,
smarter, and decision making.
So one of the biggest challenges
in medicine is getting the right
data to doctors at the right time.
with MuleSoft API powered real time
data integration, we have processed 1.
5 million patient data
points every second.
this has resulted in 71 percent
patient, clinical decision making,
meaning doctors can act quickly,
improving the patient outcomes.
with better data availability, we
have seen 48 percent of increase in
early disease detection, helping catch
illness before they become critical.
Okay, and Treatments are now 62
percent more effective because they
are based on the precise data driven
care plans, televised to each patient.
So what does this mean for patient?
Imagine a heart disease patient
whose risk factors are identified
early, allowing doctor to start the
treatment before symptoms even appear.
That's where the power of real time
integration and patient data will come
into picture and advanced analytics.
So this comes as a AI powered
diagnostics and genetics insights.
So data alone isn't enough.
So we need advanced analytics
to extract insights and make
it actionable for doctors.
So our AI powered imagining systems.
process 920, 000 medical images
every day with 82 percent of greater
accuracy, helping doctors spot
small but critical details that
could be otherwise be missing.
So genetic data analysis is
now 88 percent faster, allowing
physicians to create a heavily.
targeted personalized treatment
plans for over 28, 000 patients
per facility each year.
So what does this mean for patients
is instead of writing weeks for,
genetic testing results, a cancer
patient can now receive a personalized
treatment plans with hours.
Improving, survivor rates
and treatment effectiveness.
So that one is clinical decision support.
that is nothing but AI
assisted smarter healthcare.
So with healthcare becoming a more complex
doctors need intelligent systems to
assist them in making the best decisions.
So our API driven clinical decision
support system is transforming
how care is, care is delivered.
So in, it handles 3.
2 million clinical.
Decisions daily with 98 percent
accuracy, helping doctors to
make the best possible choices.
treatment matching has improved by 68%.
Make sure in patient received
the most efficient care of
their specific conditions.
And most importantly, adverse drug
reactions have been reduced by 45%.
Thanks to smart, medical recommendations.
So what does it mean for
the patient, a patient with.
Multiple chronic conditions can
now receive a personalized medicine
plan that minimizes side effects
and improves the quality of life.
Okay.
Now, why this matters by integrating
real time patient's data, AI powered
analytics, and clinical decision support.
We are making Medicine more precise,
more efficient and more patient center.
So doctors get the data
they have instantly.
Patient receive personalized treatment
trailer to their genetic and health
history and AI powered insights to
help prove errors and improve outcomes.
So let's talk about the
unified data access.
So doctors now access 15, 800 patients
data points per consult consultation
compared to just 2, 900 previously.
So this means that physicians no longer
need To manually pull records from
different systems, they get all the
relevant data in one place instantly.
So faster access to critical
information lead to early detection
and better treatment decisions.
Example, imagining an emergency case where
a doctor needs to check a patient's past
imaging lab records and genetic makers.
Instead of searching a multiple
system, they get everything in one
unified dashboard in real time.
Other one is lab integration.
So it's a fast and more
accurate test results.
real time synchronization of lab data
has, accumulated diagnosis time by 74%.
So automated lab data integration
that just manually data errors,
ensuring doctors have the most up
to date test results in instantly.
So third one is imagine analysis.
This enhanced the radiology
and AI powered scans.
So MuleSAR platform enables real
time integration of imaging data.
So improving diagnostic
speeds and accuracy.
So imaging analysis accuracy has increased
by 82 percent allowing AI powered
tools to detect early signs of disease
like cancer and neurological disorder.
So false.
Positive has been reduced and minimizing
cancer treatments and anxiety of
the patients will be reduced here.
So third one is genetic analysis.
This is nothing but 88 percent
faster genetic data process
allowing for faster and more
efficient transform treatment plans.
So genetic makers are now analyzed
alongside lab and imaging data
providing a more compressive
approach to, disease treatment.
And, fifth one is, The
predictive analysis.
AI driven predictive analysis
help identify at risk patient
before symptoms even appear.
diagnostic error rate have
dropped by 63 percent reducing the
unnecessary hospital readiness.
And, With seeming less integration
of lab reports, imagining data and
genetical analyzing, MuleSoft platform
say define diagnostic in healthcare.
So doctors know receive a complete
real time patient profile, leading
to faster and more accurate.
diagnosis and, treatment plans
are trialized based on real
time data, improving outcomes.
So let's talk about diagnostics to the
next level with AI power technology.
So AI is revolutionizing healthcare and
doctors to detect disease early, analyze
genetic data faster and predict patient
outcomes with Unpredictable accuracy.
So by combining AI and real time data
integration, we are moving from reactive
in healthcare, treating disease after they
occur to proactive care and preventing
illness before they even develop.
AI can analyze 2.
1 million diagnostic images per day.
So this has led to thousands of
life saving early, interventions
preventing diseases from
progressing to critical stages.
And second is genetic analysis.
So generally key analysis has
transformed medicine, but analyzing
vast amounts of genetic data used
to take days of days or even weeks.
So now with AI driven genetic
analysis, our system achieves
99 percent of accuracy in.
genetic profiling, helping
identifying here data conditions
and treatment processing.
And the process is 32, 000 genetic profile
daily in under four minutes per patients.
So this means that doctors can instantly
Match patients with most effective
personalized treatment plans and,
and, prediction capabilities will
comes into picture like forecasting
patients outcome before systems develop.
So predicting patient comes user to
rely on past experience and intuition,
but no, I can analyze millions of.
clinical cases to forecast healthcare
risk with extreme accuracy.
So our prediction model modelizing
achieves 93 percent of accuracy in
forecasting patient outcomes with
30 days and system analyzes 4.
2 million clinical data points daily
providing proactive alerts to the doctors.
So this helps preventing complications
before they occur, allowing for
Early inventions and save lives.
And why this matters with AI
power diagnostics and we are not
just improving medicine, we are
changing the way healthcare works.
So doctors can detect disease sooner,
leading the early treatment and better
survival rates and genetic analysis allows
for prediction medicine, making sure every
patient gets the right treatment faster.
Let's talk about the slide.
Now let's move on from technology
theory to real world impact
with groundbreaking case study.
this case focus on one of the
America largest healthcare networks,
which includes 920 healthcare,
facilitates and serves as 13.
8 million patients annually.
So before implementing
MuleSoft APL integration.
This network struggles with slow
system deployments, high operation
costs, and outdated infrastructure.
however, by modernizing their
systems and streamlining integration,
the results were transformative.
68 percent of faster system integrations
from around 210 days to just 58 days.
Okay, Let's break down
to key achievements.
Let's break down to key achievements.
So before MuleSoft, deploying a
new system across facility took
210 days, almost like 7 months.
with MuleSoft API solutions, deployment
time was cut down into just 58 days.
A 68 percent improvement will happen here.
this allowed new hospitals, clinics,
and digital services to go live
with much faster, reducing the
bottlenecks in IT implementation.
So why does this matter?
Hospitals adopting new technology
can't offer long delays.
Faster integration means doctors
and nurses can start using new
digital tools soon and ultimately
the benefits to patient's care.
And by optimizing workflows and
automating data exchange between
hospitals, labs, pharmacies, and
insurance providers, the network served 9.
5 million annually.
So manual data entry was reduced in
processes like insurance verification,
patient records access, and
prescription fulfillment were automated.
Redundant IT maintenance cons were
eliminated, making decisions much
more cost efficient will happen.
And, within 18 months, the healthcare
network achieved a 182% written
on investment, one of the fastest
and highest in the industry.
See the cost of implementing MuleSoft API
was fully recovered with the first year.
The success set to a benchmark for
other healthcare organization looking to
modernize the systems without compiling,
replacing existing infrastructure.
So why does this matter?
So many healthcare organizations
hesitate to invest a new technology
due to budget constraints, but
this case study proves that API
integration is not It's an investment
with fast and, miserable returns.
So, this case study proves
that APLA connectivity is
more than just an IT upgrade.
It's just a fundamental shift
in how healthcare operates.
hospitals can integrate new systems
nearly 70 percent faster, making sure
they stay ahead in digital transformation
and Massive card saving allow for better,
resource allocation, improving all our
patient care, the ROI speak for itself.
So modernizing healthcare IT
infrastructure is not just beneficial is.
Essential for long term sustainability.
MuleSoft don't just improve
this healthcare network.
It's just set the stage of
smarter, faster, and more
connected future for healthcare.
Okay, let's move on to other slide.
Okay, let's talk about diagnosis.
So now let's see how seen API
integration transform system efficiency.
Now let's drive deeper into how
improved diagnostics, one of the
most crucial areas in healthcare.
How MuleSoft integration platform is.
ensuring precision speed up results
and improving the patient's safety.
So let's discuss about
accuracy enhancement.
So 48 percent of boost in diagnostic
precision and preventing over 52, 000,
15, 200 potential medical errors annually.
So this improvement has directly
contributed to better patient safety
outcomes, reducing misdiagnosis
and unnecessary treatments.
So why does this matter?
Diagnosis lead to delight on
incorrect treatments, sometimes
with life threatening consequences
with improved diagnosis.
Accuracy patients get the right
treatment faster and improve the survivor
rates at long time health outcomes.
processing speed.
So from 52 hours to just 5.
8 hours.
So before implementing use of solution,
diagnostics confirmation time took up
to 52 hours more than a. two full days.
I think.
No, this same diagnosis
are confirmed in just 5.
8 hours at an 89 percent
improvement happened.
So what does this matter?
So faster diagnosis means
for the treatment decisions.
A patient in emergency room does
how, days to wait for test results.
Getting a accurate diagnosis with
hours or even minutes can be life
saving and imagining analysis.
So a I. diagnostic imaging process.
1. 2 million medical
imaging images per month.
So 99.
85 accuracy rate, meaning few misdiagnosis
and more confidence in imaging results.
So false results have been reduced
by 62 percent and make sure that
patients aren't subjected to
unnecessary test treatments or stress.
So why does it matter with?
Traditional imaging errors or delays
in reading scans can lead to missed
tumors, undiagnosed fractures, or delayed
detection of life threatening conditions.
AI powered Imaginary makes
sure every detail is captured
with very Perfect accuracy.
So 71 percent of reduction in
diagnostics done around time for
critical cases, enabling rapid
interventions when every second.
So in conditions like strokes.
Heart attacks.
Every minute of delay increased the
risk of complications out there.
So with faster diagnostics, doctors can
immediately start life saving treatment
instead of waiting for lab results.
So doctors have access to
more precise real time data.
Patients have received a diagnosis faster,
leading to early treatments and AI power.
Imagine they just the false
treatments to improve the confidence
in results and critical conditions
are identified sooner, giving
patients a better chance of survival.
So this isn't just an idea, but it's
revolution in diagnostics, making
better outcomes of millions of patients.
So let's move on to other slide.
so far we have talked about how API
integration has improved the diagnostics,
treatment, accuracy and patient care.
But another major benefit is how
it enhances, efficiently, reducing
cost and improves the system.
Scalability.
So healthcare organizations deals with
millions of patients request daily and
it access that data is slow or efficient.
It directly impacts patient outcomes.
So new soft API let integration has
transformed how hospitals manage
patient records, cut development costs
and built a scalable infrastructure
that is ready for the future.
So let's look at three key
Improvements in this area.
So record access improvement.
So healthcare provider no access patient
records in just 28 seconds down for 5.
5 percent improvement here.
So this enables faster emergency
response, better decision making
and reduce wait times for patients.
The system no process 1.
2 million.
Patient records request party with 99.
995 percent accuracy, make sure in, real
and, secure access critical information.
So why does this matter?
So in an emergency room setting,
waiting every five minutes of
patient record could mean delight.
treatment.
So which instant access doctors can make
life saving decision faster, improving the
survivors and reducing the complications.
So second is development cost reduction.
So 14.
2 million in annual saving through
strategic system optimization and 58
percent reduction in development cost,
which eliminates unnecessary technical
depths created a more maintainable
future proof infrastructure that
benefit both providers and patients.
So why does this matter?
So many healthcare systems spends
millions of dollars maintaining outdated
IT structure by maintaining MuleSoft API
organization can eliminate efficiency,
reduce IT cost and, reinvest savings
into patient care and innovations.
the other one is
maintenance and scalability.
That is for future proof,
proofing healthcare systems.
So 72 percent of decrease in
system maintenance costs, reduce
the operational expenses, while
maintaining high system performances.
So 78 percent increase in system
scalability allows, hospital to
support more patient, integrate, new
technology and spend service without
medical infrastructure, limitations.
So this makes sure seamless HIPAA
compliance across all access
points, keeping patients data secure
without slowing down the workflows.
So why does this matter?
So as healthcare system continues
to grow and handle large amounts of.
data.
They need scalable, efficient
and secure solutions.
So this transformation makes
health care provider can expand
innovative and improve patient
experience without worrying about I.
T. Limitations.
So why this matters for
future of health care?
So doctors and nurses get patient
recover faster, enabling Care and more
informed treatment decisions and hospital
save, millions in it costs, allowing
them to allocate more resources to
patient care and advanced technologies.
So a scalable infrastructure may.
Sure healthcare organizations are ready
for future innovations, say driven
healthcare and, expanded patients needs.
this isn't just a short term improvement,
it's a long-term transformation,
creating a faster and more efficient
and future-proof healthcare systems.
So let's just work on other slide.
okay, as a healthcare organization,
expand the digital capabilities,
security and compliance,
become more critical than ever.
So patient data is among the most
sensitive information in the world.
And a single data breach can lead
to financial penalties and legal
consequences and loss of patient trust.
So that's why MuleSoft APL8 integration
is built in enterprise grade security
and strict compliance measures and making
sure the data is protected, monitored,
and accessible only by the right people.
So let's explore a five key security
pillars that make it possible.
So first one is end to end encryption.
So MUSEF secures patient's data with
military grade encryption, providing 99.
9995 percent protection effectiveness.
So it handles 4.
8 million sensitive transactions
daily, ensuring patient records
remain private and secure.
So why does this matter?
So encryption makes sure that even
if data is intercepted, it Remains
unreadable to unauthorized user.
So this level of security meets and
exists healthcare industry standard
protection, patient confidentiality,
and data governance coming to data
government's 91 percent of improvement
in data quality metrics, reducing errors
and inconsistency in medical records.
So 76 percent of reduction data handling
violations ensures, hospitals compiles
with strict data protection policies.
Why does this matter?
Clean, accurate data is
essential for patient safety.
Error in medical records can lead to
misdiagnosis or incorrect treatments.
Controls.
preventing breaches.
14, 200 role based access
permissions per organization.
Make sure only unauthorized personnel can.
Access specific data.
So 80, 82 percent decrease in
security breaches caused by
unauthorized access attempts.
So why does this matter?
So not even hospital employees should
have access to all patient records.
So MuleSERP.
enforces strict role based control
to prevent unauthorized access.
So this makes sure that one doctor,
nurse, and unauthorized staff can
see the information they need.
Nothing more, nothing less.
And audit log.
So AI powered threat
detecting and monitoring.
We can.
Think about in this case.
So monitoring 3.
8 million security events
daily, identifying potential
threats in real time.
So AI power detection systems
providing 99 percent 99.
8 percent accuracy, proactively
flagging suspicious activity
before it becomes a breach.
So why does this matter?
So cybersecurity and healthcare
organization has increased by 58
percent in the last five years.
Real time monitoring makes sure that it.
Threats are detected and stopped
before any damage occurs so hospitals
can quickly investigate and respond
to potential security incidents,
protect patients data and maintaining
trust and HIPAA complaints.
So 97 percent of reduction in
complaints incidents due to the
automated regulatory monitorings.
So process is 62 6.
2 million complaints verification daily.
Make sure constant.
Adherence to industry regulations.
So why does this matter?
Regulatory compliance is complex
and manual processing can lead
to address fines and legal risks.
So with automated compliance check,
hospitals can make sure they meet HIPAA
and other health care security standards
24 by 7 without extra manual efforts.
Why this matters for
healthcare organizations.
So patient records are encrypted,
protected, and accessed only
by authorized personally.
So security monitor runs 24 by 7, detects
threats with near perfect accuracy.
So regulation compliance is automated,
reducing the risk of violations and fines.
So with MuleSoft API led security
framework, healthcare organizations
can confidently, MuleSoft.
com Embrace digital transformation
without compiling on, privacy,
security and compliance.
Let's move on to other slide.
Okay.
As we wrap up, let's take a step
back and look at the big picture.
How MuleSoft API led
connectivity is fundamental to
transforming healthcare delivery.
We have covered how MuleSoft platform
improves diagnostics, enhancing
patient record access, strengthening
security and reduces cost.
It is core.
It's this transformation
is about one thing.
Better patients care.
Let's summarize the three key ways.
This technology shaping the future
of healthcare integration success.
So this means no more
delays, no more missing data.
Even healthcare provider has access
to the full picture in the real time.
Microsoft did not just connect
systems is just connected care
and personalized messaging.
MuleSoft has become the backbone
for personalized medicine.
So AI driven analytics allows
healthcare providers to trailer
treatments based on the genetics,
medical texture and predictive models.
So this leads to higher therapy
effectiveness, fewer side effects
and better long term health outcomes.
So this is just, this isn't
just a digital transformation.
It's a medical transformation.
And future ready healthcare.
So built for the
innovative and the growth.
So MuleSoft industry leading
security protocols, make sure.
patient's data remains protected
even as digital health care expands.
So why does this matter?
Health care is constantly evolving,
and hospitals need technology that
can adapt to their new advancements.
With MuleSoft, organizations are future
proofed, ready to embrace emerging
innovations in AI, robotics, and
digital health care transformations.
So this isn't just solving
today's problem, it's
preparing health care for next.
Decade and beyond.
So final thoughts about
this transformation.
Healthcare delivery, for integration
medicine to future ready.
Healthcare moves of 80 year
late connectivity, setting a
new standards in the industry.
This isn't just about the idea.
Upgrades is about the saving lives.
Improving patient experience and making
health care more efficient and accessible.
So by embracing digital transformation,
we are not just improving the hospitals.
We are reshaping the future of medicine.
So the future of medicine is connected,
intelligent and Patient focused and
MuleSoft is the leading the way.
Let's move on to next slide.
So that brings us the end
of this session today.
So we explored how MuleSoft APLA
integration is transforming the
healthcare from breaking down data
cellulose and improving the diagnostics
to enabling the personalized testing
and future proofing healthcare systems.
So this is more than just technology.
It's about Empowering doctors, enhancing
patient care and ultimate saving lives.
I appreciate your time and attention.
And I hope this session has given
you valuable insights into how API