Today's topic is AI Powered Predictive
Analytics for Multi Cloud Management.
Artificial intelligence and
cloud computing are converting to
revolutionizing as organizations
manage cloud resources.
This presentation explores the
transformation impact of AI driven
solutions across the resource management
operations and operational technologies.
Discover how loading technology providers
are leveraging AI to enhance the
cloud platform's driving efficiency.
Point performance and cost optimization
learn how this technological convergence
or fostering innovations, operational
excellence across the diverse industries.
So resource management revolutions, we
can divide this topic into, two parts.
Like the first one is the dynamic
scaling and the second one is
the automated provisioning.
The dynamic scaling advanced AI
algorithms analyze the historical
patterns on real time metrics.
To predict resource demands with up to 95
percent accuracy, this intelligent scaling
automatically adjusts cloud resources
within seconds, maximizing the performance
during the traffic spikes while
reducing the cost by 30 to 40 percent
during the low utilization periods.
The second part is automated provisioning.
AI driven provisioning system orchestrates
resource deployment across complex
cloud environments in minimum instead
of hours, minutes instead of hours.
The automation eliminates the
configuration errors, cuts deployment
time by 80 percent, and the, and ensures
It's consistent resource allocation
across the entire cloud infrastructure.
By harassing AI predictive capabilities,
the organizations are fundamentally
transforming their resources,
management, and management strategies.
The combination of, Precise dynamic
scaling and intelligent automated
programming report 40 percent
lower operational cost and 99.
9 percent resource availability and
five times faster the deployment
cycle, proving that AI powered cloud
management is not just an improvement,
it's a competitive necessity.
The next topic is optimization
strategies enhanced by AI.
So work done, I, we can divide
the whole topic into three parts.
The first one is workload placement, cost
optimization, and security optimization.
AI, in the, while we go with the
workload placement, AI algorithm analyze
the resources requirements, network
latency, and performance metrics to
automatically distribute workloads
across the cloud infrastructure.
maximizing efficiency and throughput.
Cost optimization machine learning models
continuously monitor resource consumption
pattern automatically identifying,
identifying the unutilized assets and
recommending strategic adjustment to
the pricing types and the instance
types, the security optimization.
Advanced AI systems leverages
the pattern recognition and
behavioral analysis to proactively
identify the security and MLTs.
Automatically implementing
the predictive measures.
before breaches occurred by integrating
AI into cloud optimization, organization
achieve unpredictable levels of operation
efficiency, advanced algorithms for
continuously to balance the performance
cost and security, delivering up
to 40 percent cost saving while
maintaining the peak performances.
This intelligent approach of cloud
management transforms traditional
infrastructure into a self optimizing
system but adopts a real time
challenge in the business network.
The next one is the transform.
The first part is predictive maintenance,
advanced AI algorithms analyze
the system performance to forecast
potential hardware failures, enhancing
proactive maintenance, scheduling the
maximizing, and operational efficiency.
The second part is anomaly detection,
a sophisticated AI systems continuously
monitor cloud environments for
irregular patterns and deviations
from the normal behavior enabling
early invention before minor issues
escape into the major problem.
Automated remediation.
Intelligent AI systems swiftly
diagnose and autonomously resolve the
operational issues in cloud environments.
It's dramatically reducing the
manual intervention and accelerates
the problem, problem resolution.
Leading technologies
providing Embraer CIM.
Amazon Web Services, Azure, Google
Cloud are the now leading technology
providers in the Embraer CIM.
So Amazon Web Services leads within
SageMaker, enabling organizations
to build, train, and deploy machine
learning models at scale with automated
workflows and built in security.
On the other side, Azure Microsoft
comprehensive services include advanced
natural language processing, computer
vision and automated machine learning
and making AI accessible to Thank you.
enterprise to all the sizes, Google Cloud.
While coming to the Google Cloud platform
combines its AI research expertise
within expertise ready tools, offering
pre trained models and customize the AI
solutions that reduce the time to market.
Major cloud providers are revolutionizing
the enterprise adoption through The
innovative platforms integration.
Their AI powered solutions democratize
across all advanced capabilities,
enabling business to implement the
predictive analytics, automotive
complex, and workflows, and develop
custom AI applications without
extensive data science expertise.
This transformation is accelerating
digital innovation across the industries
while reducing the implementation
barriers and operational costs.
business implications of AI in the cloud,
so there are three levels if you see the
pyramid of the triangle, the top of the
iceberg is like competitive advantage,
the second one is the operational
exchange and the core is the cost savings.
The coverages The convergence of AI
and cloud computing has significant
business implications, organizations and
can achieve cost savings throughout the
optimized resources utilization, and hence
the operational excellence and automated
process, and gain competitive advantage
leveraging AI innovations, embracing AI
in the cloud, drivers growth and position
business in the long term sources.
Driving innovations on AI powered cloud.
So there are new products,
improved services, and,
enhanced customer experience.
AI powered clouds drive innovative by
enabling the creation of new products,
improving the existing services, and
enhancing the customer service experience.
AI algorithms analyze vast amounts
of data to identify the trends
and opportunities and loading.
Innovative solutions.
These solutions transform industries
to deliver uploaded value and embrace
AI to unlock the new possibilities
and stay ahead of the competition.
In the enhanced operational excellence,
there are, three categories like
automation, efficient and accuracy and
automation transform the operation by
integrity, automating the repetitive
task, enabling your workforce, workforce
to focus on innovation strategy and
high value and activities that don't.
Drive business growth and efficiency.
Maximum operational efficiency through AI
powered resources allocation, predictive
maintenance, and intelligent workflow
optimization that reduces the cost
and accelerates the delivery times.
Accuracy achieve the unprecedented
levels of precision by leveraging
AI analytics and capabilities of
data driven decision making, quality
controls, and risk management.
Creating new opportunities
across the industries.
The Healthcare, Transportation,
and Manufacturing.
The Healthcare AI revolutionized
healthcare through the advanced
diagnostic algorithm, precision
medicine, and intelligence of patient
monitoring systems that dramatically
improve the treatment outcomes.
The transportation domain all transformed
mobility with self driving vehicles,
predictive maintenance systems, and
intelligent traffic management that
enhances safety and efficiency.
In the manufacturing, AI
revolutionized manufacturing.
through real time quality control,
predictive maintenance, and
dynamic supply, supply chain
optimization that, minimize the
waste and maximize the product.
The powerful fusion of AI and cloud
computing is catalyzing the unprecedented
transformation across the industries.
In healthcare, AI sophisticated algorithms
are not just improving diagnostics.
They are revolutionizing the patient
care by enabling personalized treatment
plans and early disease detection.
The transportation sector is wishing
a paradigm shift in the AI powered
autonomous vehicles and smart traffic
systems and leading to safe and
more efficient mobility solutions.
In manufacturing AI driven automation,
predictive analytics dynamically
boosting the productivity while
reducing the operational cost.
This technological advance are not just
improving the existing process, they are
creating entirely new business models
and revenue streams that were, that are
reshaping the global economic landscape.
Key takeaways, AI revolutionized
that, cloud operations.
That the second thing is industry's
leaders set to new standards and
transformative business outcome.
AI powered, AI powered algorithms
optimize the reduced allocation,
automated scaling decisions, and
enhancing the security monitoring.
And delivering up to 40 percent
improvement in operational efficiency.
Industry leaders set new standards.
Major cloud providers are enabling AI
capabilities into their the core services
enabling the predictive maintenance
and intelligent automation and advanced
analytic and enterprise customers.
Transformative and business outcomes
are organization leveraging AI and
cloud environment repeat accelerated
innovation cycles with 30 percent
reduction on in operational costs and
breakthrough the opportunities in customer
experience and product development.
The integration of AI into cloud
management represent a fundamental
shift in how organization innovative
by combining AI predictive capabilities
with the cloud scalability and
business are achieving unpredictable
levels of efficiency and agility.
The convergence not only optimize the
current operation but also unlocks
a new possibilities for growth
enabling organization to thrive in an
Increasingly distal first, first one,
the next steps
conduct comprehensive audit for
your existing cloud infrastructure
include resource utilization
patterns and performance metrics
map critical business process to
identify high impact opportunities
for intelligence and automation.
Avaliate and benchmark leading AI
powered cloud solutions against
specific organization needs
and objectives are developed.
And execute phased AI implementation
strategies prioritizing quick
wins while building towards
a long term transformation.
Success in AI driven cloud management
requires a method, methodical, strategic
approach begin with a through assessment
of your current, infrastructure to
establish a clear business identifier
of optimization opportunities.
Systematically evaluate where AI can
deliver the most significant impact
considering both immediate efficiency
gains and long term strategy advantage.
By carefully selecting the, implementing
the AI solution that align with the
specific needs, you can accelerate your
digital transformation journey while
maximize return of, return on investment.
Thank you.
Thanks everyone for the, for the
opportunity, thank you everyone.