Welcome to the session.
today we're going to talk about current.
It's an open source project.
That's aimed at simplifying Cuban these
cluster processing at scale, right?
So all of us who've been in the
DevOps world know what a pain it is
to, probably in a cluster, right?
You have to come up with, an optimal
way to do it at scale, and to manage,
complex Configurations as well.
So Codent solves this problem.
in the session, we're going to look at
the challenges and we're going to see
what difficulties are there in platform
engineering and then approach Codent.
And towards the end of it, we'll
see, Codent in action, right?
So I'm Bharath.
I'm in the OSPO team at Monantis.
I'm a senior software dev and
an open source contributor.
Been working in and around
Kubernetes for a while now.
Let's get started.
So we all know how the cloud was
supposed to be right, but very quickly
It got into this maze where everything
became just so much complex And even
kubernetes which started as a very
basic project quickly grew and although
it is the ecosystem, is what makes
it today the ecosystem has become so
big that It's super complex, even for
an experienced person in this world.
That's why we need a simplified
streamlined process, which we
call platform engineering today.
And for enterprises specifically,
when you look at platform engineering,
if I have to sum up, what are
the key things that you look for?
Developer self service
is extremely important.
So having a dedicated DevOps team
that's as big or even bigger than your
development team is not scalable anymore.
So you've got to have
a self service portal.
Where your dev teams and your QA teams
and your security teams and all the
other teams can manage the infrastructure
themselves with the platform engineering
being the backend You also need
operational simplicity If you don't have
that then providing this for multiple
teams across your company becomes
extremely difficult Customizations is
again another important thing because
like I said, for different teams,
the requirements will be different.
So without changing the core model,
having the option to customize is
what, brings this whole process
about for platform engineers.
And visibility and control, again, at an
administrative level, this is extremely
important to manage your clusters.
And then, last but not least,
security and compliance.
Every company is going to follow it.
that's a primary, these days.
So given all these challenges,
there's a growing need for
multi cluster configurations.
So for a platform engineer, you need
multi cluster configurations for multiple
things, such as AM and work nodes or multi
tenancy, edge devices, IOT, and so on.
Now, when you look at the market and see
what are the options available for me
to accomplish this, Then if you don't do
anything that's always an option, right?
So if you don't do anything, your
infrastructure costs grows up and up.
And before you realize you're
paying like huge cloud bills, right?
Then let's take it like a basic step
ahead with DIY open source tools.
of course, there's been so many
tools for cluster provisioning and
maintenance in the open source market.
But then there's always this.
Learning curve, that's,
that comes with it.
And then you gotta understand each
tools and you gotta understand how one
tool works with another integrations
and configurations and all that.
And then of course, you have
the problem for extending it
to your on premises as well.
Then if I have to take it another
step further, there are proprietary
solutions, but the proprietary
solutions obviously come with expensive
licenses and they're quite limited
to the options that they provide.
And more often than not, two years,
three years down the line, what's
going to happen is that without,
you looking at it really hard, you
are in a vendor lock in, right?
And if you have to expand to
multiple clouds, and it becomes
really difficult at that point.
So to solve all these problems,
we are presenting an enterprise
grade open source solution, right?
That's cost efficient and that's
customizable and it's completely in
your hands and your control, right?
And it works on multiple public
clouds as well as on drum.
This is where Codent comes in, right?
At a very high level,
we have three things.
Cluster management, state
management and observability.
So the cluster management, what I mean
by that is, how are you going to manage
multiple clusters across clouds at scale?
That level of cluster management
is taken care of by Codent.
State management talks about the
day to operations when you deploy or
need to deploy multiple applications
across your clouds in a single click.
That's your state
management and then comes.
Observability.
So when you have a working operation,
clusters and workloads and apps
running on it, the one thing that's
100 percent needed in this world or any
world is really observability tools.
So we're baking this into the
current ecosystem without having
to rely on external resources.
We have to again do
configuration yourself.
All this is that so open delivery
is used and you can just use
it right from the package.
So before jumping there, just one
last thing about the golden paths
that's often talked about in DevOps.
So everybody wants to perfect this.
Every company, every team is looking
to move as close as possible to
a golden path, although you can
always argue there isn't one.
But right.
Having something close to that
is still a lot of success.
It still saves you a lot of effort, money,
and it gives you a repeatable process
for maintenance as well as scalability.
So especially when you have a
choice of multiple clouds, then this
becomes extremely important as well.
A quick look at the Codon architecture.
So at a high level, like I said,
there are three components.
One is the cluster management, one
is the state management, and then
you have the observability stack.
So with the cluster management,
what happens is we use
upstream capi controllers.
So Since this is completely open
source, the underlying technologies to
make this happen is also open source.
Based on the cloud, we have
the CAPEX controllers as well.
CAPA for AWS, CAPZ for Azure,
CAPV for VMware, and so on.
We deploy the upstream CAPI controller,
as well as the cloud specific
controllers, onto your management.
Cluster along with that will
be the Cosmotron controller.
So K0s and Cosmotron form a core part
and this entire architecture wherein
we use that for controller management.
So this becomes your management
cluster wherein the KCM controllers
and a bunch of other components
that are related to current along
with the upstream components.
Are running on the management cluster
and right here in the management
cluster for state management We
have sveltos controller So sveltos
like I said is for managing the
states and deploying applications
across multiple clusters, right?
again, this is an open source project
and it's Integrated into codent so
that all you need to do for example If
you want to provision or deploy cert
manager across all your clusters Then
all you need to do is include search
manager in the configuration file.
And that's that's automatically deployed
to all the clusters And that is what's
shown, here on the right side in the child
clusters So in the child cluster along
with all the kubernetes add on services
that you'll find You'll also see that
this is felt as agent that's operating
there To talk between your child cluster
and the management cluster, right?
How you accomplish this entire thing
is by defining something called as a
cluster deployment We'll look at this
in detail when I go to the demo part
But just briefly I want to mention
that your entire cluster configuration
will be controlled and monitored using
this cr called as cluster deployment
and to facilitate the Configuration
of the clusters based on the cloud.
We have multiple cluster templates
and to facilitate the applications
configuration, we have service templates.
So the example that I gave you earlier
about cert manager is an example of
a service template and example, let's
say you want to deploy it on AWS.
That's defined as a
cluster template, right?
So this is a very overall
architecture of, Got it.
So now let's go into the demo and
just before we go into the demo.
I want to open the documentation
and just briefly go through this so
if I Look at the installation part,
right?
So we have a help package.
like I said, you need
a management cluster.
It could be kind or it could be running
on any other infrastructure as well.
for simplicity, you can try kind to
run on your laptop or any VM and then
all you got to do is do a helm install.
Of, of the KCM, right?
Once you do this, a bunch of
components are installed, like I said.
The controllers, the Cosmotron
controllers, a bunch of other KCM stuff.
And then we proceed to define
our, cluster templates and then
define the cluster deployments.
So now let's jump into the
terminal where in I already have
a kind cluster, right?
And if I do this, you'll see that
there are all these namespaces.
And if I do this, you'll see all
the parts that are up and running.
So it's exactly the same.
Like I mentioned, there's
an alive kind cluster.
All the controllers and Cosmotron
and other components of KCM, right?
And the next thing, by the way,
that's this.
So kubectl hyphen and KCM system is Ka.
And if I do cluster template
get, here you go, you see all
the different cluster templates.
So these are pre packaged
templates that are available for
you to try based on the clouds.
So we have for AWS EKS and
then AWS and then Azure EKS and
Azure OpenStack and vSphere.
Similarly, you have service templates and
by default, a bunch of service templates
are baked into the management cluster.
when you install it, the other Helm shot.
some of the examples are these, right?
So all you've got to do is specify
this in the cluster deployment.
So just to show you how that looks
let's take a look at a shore.
These are all the files
that you typically need.
not all of them, but I'm
going to show you one by one.
You'll need a secret.
All these instructions are
provided in the docs, by the way.
So the instructions are segregated.
Or cloud provider and it's slightly
different for cloud provider based
on how they expect the credentials
to be set up and all that So example
aws you have these keys for azure
you have something different, right?
you've got to create You've got to
create a service principle based on the
subscription ID and for OpenStack, again,
it's all these variables and similar,
similarly for vSphere as well, right?
essentially, there's a secret.
yml file and then there's
a credential file.
this credential is referenced by
the secret and cluster identity is
also referenced by the credential.
cluster identity is a file.
That is a cr of azure cluster
entity and it references these
stuff now Finally, let's take a
look at the Cluster deployment.
So i'm defined two
cluster deployments here.
One would be a basic cluster with
One control plane and one work node,
right and it uses minimum cpu Okay,
and then there's another control under
the cluster deployment pretty much
a similar configuration but I have
used A gpu enabled cluster, right?
I've applied both these things.
Just to show you the other bit
as well For aws you have all
these things as well, right?
So aws How you have to choose?
Is if to choose the instance
type based on what you want.
So here i've chosen an instance
type Which is a gpu enabled worker
node if you don't want a gp enabled
worker node It's absolutely fine.
All you got to do is select something
like this to three dot small t three
dot medium Whatever is your requirement
and similarly for open stack as
well Now i'm going to show you the
kind of objects that we work with.
So Since i've already
ran this Here you go.
So when you list the cluster deployments,
you'll see something like this, right?
Let's go ahead and list one of them
and Do if no yaml, there you go.
It's as simple as this So this is where
you mentioned the cluster template
and this is where you mentioned the
credential and this is where you
mentioned the configuration that's
specific to you and this is completely
customizable if you look at you can
look up the documentation for all the
various, fields that are available.
and that's that so as to show you another
example, let's look at the open stack one
So there's an identity ref.
There's a specific to open
stack cloud And then there's the
control plane configuration the
work configuration and then the
template so on and so forth, right?
So this is our private cloud.
So some configuration that's related
to that has to be provided All right.
now that we've seen the cluster
deployments, and like I mentioned,
it's all Capi objects, right?
So you can see the Capi object
being created underneath,
right?
So you'll have the AWS cluster,
Azure cluster, OpenStack cluster,
and you will also have the AWS
machines, and Azure machines.
And open stack machines, right?
And finally if I have to do a machines
Then as you can see it's listing all
the machines that are available on the
cluster to access this cluster it's as
simple as getting the secret so Ka like
I said is in the kcm system namespace.
Let's look at all the secrets in the kcm
system There's a bunch of secrets, but
what we're interested in is the secret
that has kube config appended to it.
So for every cloud, you have a kube
config and I've exported them all.
I think.
Let's also export this and
let's also export this.
Now, if I go here and do this.
Now I'm in the Azure context.
I do this.
There you go.
I have a single worker node
and a single control plane node
and it's up and running, right?
Similarly for AWS.
Alright, there you go.
Last but not the least
for OpenStack as well.
All right, so you have
all these notes, right?
So you know, it's as simple as
that and on the cloud You can see
that these machines are provisioned
here Similarly for a short as well.
So as you can see this one is
using the standard one and this
one is using instance type that
has gpu support as well, right?
So that's running the tesla t4
nvidia chip Then aws has these So
essentially, it's as simple as this,
end of the day, what you need to do
is define your cluster deployment and
specify the configuration and Gordon
takes care of it end to end, right?
yeah, you have the KCM repository.
It's completely open source.
You can go take a look.
Contributions are absolutely welcome.
We have a slack channel as well.
It's updated here.
yeah, that's pretty much it.
Thank you.
Thank you for listening.
Bye bye.