Hi, I'm Go pa, a staff software engineer
at ServiceNow, where I work within the
financial service operations domain.
My team builds specialized applications
for the banking industry with the
focus on dispute operations and
integrating with major car networks.
One of the key areas I'm
passionate about is leveraging.
AI to transform and streamline
the dispute management process,
making it faster, smarter, more
efficient for financial institutions.
So that, let's get started
with the presentation.
I hope everyone can see my screen.
So today I'm going to walk you through
how we can make use of combination of
graph engine networks and transformers
deployed on a cloud native architecture
to tackle one of the most frustrating
problems in the payment industry.
Friendly fraud.
Let's start with why this matters.
Friendly fraud is when a real customer
makes a real purchase and then dispute
their bank to get their money back.
It like a niche problem,
but the number staggering.
Between 60
fraud.
Over 48 billion annually, and that number
keeps growing as eCommerce expands.
Now, understanding the problem,
so why is this so hard?
The answer is the purchase itself
looks completely legitimate.
The card is valid, the card order, the
transaction goes through without a hitch.
Goods are delivered.
Then weeks or sometimes months
later, the card holder files
a dispute through their bank.
By that point, the merchant
has already shipped the product
and has no way to reverse it.
Traditional fraud controls
work at a point of sale.
They are trying to catch bad
transactions before they happen.
But with friendly fraud, the
bad things doesn't happen
at the point of sale at all.
This temporal gap is what
makes it so difficult.
So limitations of current approaches.
Current detection systems fall
into two gaps, both fall short.
One is rule-based systems.
The old school, it says
old school approach only.
Catches between 23 to 31%
of friendly fraud cases.
They rely on rigid predefined thresholds
that fraudsters quickly learn to work
around traditional machine learning
does better somewhere in the 38 to.
45 percentage range,
but it's still limited.
These models need engineers to
manually craft the features and they
struggle to model the complex web
of relationships between cardholders
merchants and devices, or how these
relationships change over time.
So what is our framework?
We combine two powerful techniques.
The first one is temporal
graph, attention networks.
These models, the relationships between
cardholders, merchants, devices, and
transactions as a graph, and they learn.
Which connections are suspicious?
Second, a transformer
based sequence model.
This looks at the cardholder's
transaction history over time and
picks up on behavioral patterns that
suggest someone is systematically
giving the dispute process today.
These two components catch patterns
that neither could find on its own
understanding the payment ecosystem.
Let me give you a sense of the scale here.
A real world payment graph is
in just accounts and merchants.
It includes devices, IP
addresses, physical addresses.
Behavior fingerprints.
We are talking 50 to a hundred million
cardholder accounts, 15 to 25 million
merchant entities and anywhere from
10 to 50 billion edge connecting
them connecting each other with a
hundred to 500 million new connections
being added every single day.
Representing this as a graph lets us spot
things like fraud rings, where multiple
accounts share the same device or address
schemas that are invisible if you're
only looking at individual transactions.
So what is the graph structure?
We have the graph has.
Three main categories of nodes, accounts,
devices, and merchants at the top level.
Transactions and IP addresses in the
middle and physical and digital addresses.
Rounding it out.
The edges between these
nodes are timestamped.
They capture when a purchase happens,
when a device was used, when a
merchant was visited, when an address
was associated with an account.
That time awareness is what let's
us detect fraud patterns that
evolves slowly over weeks or months.
So graph attention mechanism here is
the clever part of the graph component.
Not all connections in the
graph are equally meaningful.
A graph attention network learns
to assign dates, attention scores.
To each relationship, so
suspicious connections
naturally raise to the surface.
For example, if multiple accounts
are using the same device or
IP address, that's a red flag
for a coordinated fraud ring.
If a card holder is repeatedly disputing
a transaction across completely
different merchants, that's cross
merchant pattern getting highlighted.
The model patents from data.
We don't need to hardcore
rules for each one.
So transform sequence
it process each cardholder
fiction history as a sequence.
And to figure out which transactions
are most relevant for predicting whether
a new one will Bees always value.
Crucially, the model learns
these patterns automatically.
No one has to sit down and write a
rule for each behavioral signature.
Now, coming to evaluation metrics, before
I get to the results quickly on how we
measure performance, we use three key
metrics, precision and recall, precision.
Tells us how often are fraud flags or
actually fraud recall tells us what
fraction of real fraud we are catching.
We want both.
High A CU score gives us the threshold
independent view of how all the
models separately separates legitimate
transactions from fraudulent transactions.
Higher is better, obviously, and.
Cost optimization.
We tune our detection threshold to
balance the cost of false positive,
which is annoying a real customer
against the cost of a misused
fraud case, a real financial loss.
So some of the benchmark results,
the results are meaningful
compared to traditional machine
learning system running at say
30, 38 to 47 percentage detection.
Our graph attention
approach reaches 67 to 78%.
That's a 40 to 65% relative improvement.
And compared to rule-based systems we see.
35 to 45% reduction in false positives.
That means few are legitimate customers
getting their cards flagged and lower
operational costs for the dispute
teams re reviewing these alerts.
Deployment challenges.
Now, having a model that works in research
is one thing, but deploying it at issuer
scale is a different challenge entirely.
You're talking about graphs with tens of
billions of edges that need to stay fresh.
As hundreds of millions of new connections
are arriving daily transformer influence
needs to happen in near real time, and
you need to manage all of this while
keeping latency low data consistent, and
the system highly available, managing it.
Database and an inference pipeline
together at this scale requests
serious infrastructure thinking.
Now coming to cloud native
architecture, three, cloud native
principles get us there first.
Distributing processing.
We use distributed graph
databases with participated.
Partition storage and compute
clusters to parallelize the
work across billions of edges.
Second segmentable calibration, rather
than using a single global detection
threshold, we tune the model separately
for different merchant categories and
transaction times, which significantly
reduces false post use in each segment.
Third, Kubernetes based auto-scaling.
This gives us the ability to handle
traffic spikes without manual intervention
and self-healing infrastructure.
Keeps the system at 99.9% uptime.
And real time human in loop.
One thing we have found is that the model
improves over time when humans stay in the
loop, fraud review teams look at cases,
the model flags and takes decisions.
Was this actually fraud or not?
Feedback into the training pipeline?
This accomplishes two things.
It keeps reducing false positives
over time, so legitimate customers
are increasingly protected from
unnecessary frictional, unnecessary
friction, and it helps the model adapt.
As fraudsters find new tactics.
Automation and human expertise
are in competition here.
They make each other better.
Real world impact,
putting it all together.
The framework delivers on three
dimensions that matters to the business.
Number one, better detection with fewer
financial, number two and better customer
experience because real customers
get fewer and fewer unnecessary.
Architecture, scalable, maintain,
and as transaction volumes grow.
And
so summary of, presentation
friendly fraud is a large
growing and genuinely difficult,
and.
Cloud infrastructure makes this
deployable at real scale and keeping
humans in the loop ensures that the
system keeps improving in production.
Thank you.