Hello, I'm Andrey Stroganov.
Thank you for joining me in my talk
about performance and scalability
challenges to reassemble classifiers
on heterogeneous platforms.
Specifically, we will be talking
about heterogeneous CPUs.
Those are the CPUs that we use
every day in our mobile devices.
We use Big Little Architecture,
which combines high performance
cores with energy efficient
cores within a single processor.
Initially, this technology came
from a mobile market where power
efficiency is crucial, and now
heterogeneous CPUs are gradually making
their way into the server segment.
Heterogeneous CPUs can dynamically
allocate workloads to the appropriate
cores, their applications can range from
lightweight microservices to resource
intensive data processing tasks, and they
are an attractive option for data centers.
Transcripts can be used to access
any of the following formats.
We will experiment with two popular
machine learning models, random
forest and gradient boosting.
Both of them use decision trees under
the hood, so let's do a quick recap.
A decision tree is a tree like
structure which makes the decisions.
Based on, feature values.
Here we see a small decision tree
with three features, humidity,
temperature, and wind speed.
And in each node it has a
feature and its splitting value.
if humidity is about 90 percent we
go, right and if let's say temperature
is about 15 degrees, we'll go left.
And the prediction is that it is raining.
in practice, the decision
trees are quite larger.
They use more features, but a single
decision tree is a weak predictor.
So we usually, utilize the ensembles.
for instance, we can take multiple
trees and train each of them on a
random subset of training data set.
The resulting structure
will be a random forest.
Another approach is to train a
sequence of decision trees so that Each
sequential tree would try to compensate
prediction inaccuracy of previous trees.
this structure would be a
gradient boosting machine.
Both of them are widely popular.
They have Implementations in such great
libraries, as ONNX, xg, boost and Live
GBM, but due to their branch in nature,
they are usually processed on CPUs.
We don't use NPUs or GPUs for them.
there might be some obstacles
when we port these algorithms
into heterogeneous setting.
And these are our experimental settings.
We will use weather forecasting data set
with 21 numerical features, an octa core
CPU with one very fast core, three slower
cores, and four energy efficient cores.
Our models will have up to 100
decision trees, and they will
be processed using ONNX Runtime.
Here we see the stock performance of
Random Forest using several threads.
On X axis we see the data size,
and 1 denotes 1 million samples.
On Y axis we see the
inference time in seconds.
Blue line here is the performance
of a single thread algorithm.
If we add additional thread,
we got much better performance.
So let's add another two threads.
This one here is the result of
predicting using four threads.
We again improved performance.
Adding two additional threads,
we get the best performance.
But if we try to add a couple
more threads, we see that
performance gets worse.
And this is a concurrency penalty.
So the problem is that we can't
be sure how, how many threads we
should take for a good performance.
And these are results for gradient
boosting in stock performance.
We see that the problem stays.
This one is single thread
performance, and if we add additional
thread, we get best performance.
Adding more threads results
in worse performance with huge
concurrency penalty for using.
And, let's note that we got very
small performance boost here, 1.
2 times.
In order to improve performance, let's
see how usually random forest and tree
ensemble classifiers are multithreaded.
If we have enough trees, we can
process each tree in a separate thread.
For instance, if we have 9 trees and 4
available threads, then we can take 4
trees, process them in parallel, take
additional 4 trees and process them,
and then we will have only 3 trees.
And so we will use second approach, when
we split dataset into several batches,
and each batch is processed in parallel.
in different thread using a decision
forest consisting of three trees,
but both these approaches imply
that our CPU cores are about equal,
but in heterogeneous setting.
It is not entirely true here.
What can happen if we run equally
demanding tasks on different course?
So let's see this setting.
We have four course in our CPU core.
A is fastest and core B. is two times
slower, and we have two slowest cores, C
and D. And if we put, equally demanding
tasks on A, on these cores, then we see
that core A finishes its job very fast.
And we'll do nothing and core
B will finish a bit later
and also will be idling.
And we will have to wait for cores
C and D for finishing their tasks.
And there is more realistic scenario
in case 2 when cores help each other,
so when core A. finished its task
one, it took the unfinished part of
task three from core C, and then it
took unfinished part from core D.
This schedule is more compact, but
we still see that some cores idling.
So can we do better?
Yes we can.
We can use.
A worker pool pattern, when we split
our data set into very small batches,
the size of the batch should be,
so small so that, the slowest core
would process it in reasonable time.
And we use, several
workers in several threads.
Each worker takes the batch,
processes it, and requests next batch.
Here we see that core A took batch
1, core B took batch 2, core C took
batch 3, and core D took batch 4.
When core A finished processing
batch one, it took batch five,
then it took batch six, by that
time core B finished batch two and
requested next available batch seven.
This schedule is far more compact.
And these are the results of using
worker pool pattern in random forest.
We see that adding threads
results in better performance.
So this is single thread performance.
This is two thread performance.
Four thread performance.
And this is six, seven and
eight thread performance.
We see that system couldn't give us
more processing power, so in, all these
three cases, we get, same performance,
but there is no concurrency penalty here
and we have better performance overall.
These are results for gradient boosting.
Again, we see that when we add
additional threads, the performance
increases and the best performance
there is when we use eight threads
and we have no concurrency penalty.
We have four times performance boost.
So as we said, we use small batches around
four hundred to eight hundred samples
we don't want to use very small batches
because we will waste some processor
time for handling the queue and we
don't want to use very large batches.
So to sum up We saw that porting of
software to heterogeneous CPUs may
require some architectural changes
to fully utilize computing potential.
We demonstrated that stock
multithreading architecture may
inefficiently utilize heterogeneous
CPU and discussed reasons for this.
We demonstrated how to solve this problem
using worker pool pattern, and we got
four times to five times performance boost
for random forest and gradient boosting.
I thank you for your attention and
I'll be glad to answer any questions.
Goodbye.