Hi everyone.
I am man, and I am glad to be
speaking at C 42 Cloud Native.
Today we are going to talk about
digital onboarding, but not just as a
user experience as the architectural
foundation of trust in financial systems.
By the end of this, you will have
a practical framework for building
onboarding that is compliant
and auditory from day one, not
patched together after the fact.
A little context about
where I am coming from.
I have spent nearly 14 years as an
enterprise web architect, especially
on large scale financial platforms.
The through line in all of that
work has been the same question.
How do you take a regulatory requirement
and turn it into the architectural
design that the system actually enforces?
Not.
Just documents on paper.
That's the lens.
I will bring the everything today.
So why is onboarding different from
every other part of financial platform?
Because this is the moment the
legal relationship begets when a
customer goes through onboarding.
You are establishing consent
boundaries, granting access to regulated
services, and creating a record.
That a regulator might
examine years from now.
It's not just a UX flow, it's a
simultaneously designed challenge,
a compliance obligation, and a
occurrence problem all happening
in the same interaction.
And errors here are not a cosmetic.
They carry real regulatory and legal
consequences, and that is what makes this
worth and getting light architecturally.
Let's talk about what regulators actually
expect today because the has moved.
It's not.
Enough to say we have collected the data.
Regulators now want to know how it
was presented, when it was sure, what
version the customer saw and what the
system state was at the exact moment.
K-Y-C-A-M-L-G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A-C of pb.
Each of these maps to be a
specific architecture obligation.
The system must be able to prove
what happened, not just store data.
That distinction between storing
data and proving what happened is the
core of everything in this session.
Here is where the most system
fail, and honestly, it's more
common than we would expect.
Complaints get treated as
surface face layer, check
boxes, models, form validations.
It's looks compliant, but underneath the
architecture was not built to support.
Consent data stored as mutable
database, state exception, path
vaulted or center afterthoughts.
The system works fine until it faces an
audit and then it can't be defined itself.
What happens?
Audit gaps.
Distributed services that each
have their own version of what
happened during onboarding.
Inconsistent records manually.
Reconstruction under pressure.
The fix is not more documentation.
It's embedded compliance
into the architecture itself.
Not applied on top of it after the fact.
To address this, I use an approach
I call integration integrity.
The idea is straightforward.
Every material interaction in your
fa financial onboarding flow should
produce verifiable, auditable
evidence, not as a side effect.
As a first class output of the
system, this frameworks rest on
three pillars, the cons, constant
and disclosure, progressive identity,
insurance and exception handling.
I walk through each one.
The first pillar is consent and
disclosure, and I want to reframe
how most team think about this
right now in the most systems.
Consist is a ui.
Click the user checks a checkbox.
You store a bullion in the database.
Job done.
That's not say, that's not a defensible
consent needs to be compliance regard.
Every disclosure interaction should
be formally defined artifacts carrying
the version of the disclosure that
was showed a timestamp of when it
appeared the user's explicit response
and the system state at the moment.
The way you make this durable
is append only event logs.
Consent events are emitted as
immutable records never modified,
only appended so years later.
If regulator ask what the customer
actually saw and agreed to,
you can answer immediately, no.
Or reconstruct answer the second pillar.
Is identity and this one creates
a real problem in microservices.
Architectures that are not
always obvious upfront.
Identity verification
is not one time gate.
It's progressing.
You gather evidence incrementally
for email first, then document
upload, then maybe biometric, and the
assurance level increases as you go.
Low risk access, early high capabilities
unlocked as confidence grows.
But here is the catch
in distributed systems.
If that identity state is not
consistently propagated across service
boundaries, different services start
acting on stale or inconsistent
data, it that creates policy gaps.
Places where the system thinks
a customer is verified when
they are not, or vice versa.
The solution is treating identify
assurance as the first class attribute.
In the odd context, when verification
succeeds, its emits on observable.
Even that downstream service consumes
to update their own enforcement posture.
No service cases, every service knows.
The third pillar is exception
handling, and this is the one IC teams
get wrong most often in production
things fail session timeouts,
network interrupting third party
KYC providers going down with flow.
These are not edge cases.
These are on Tuesday, but in a
financial onboarding context.
What?
What feels like a technical
issue is actually compliance risk
when the flow is interrupted.
Loosely coupled service can be ED in
their understanding of state partial
compliance, create legal ambiguity.
Is the customer onboarded or not?
That is not a UX bug.
That's a compliance instant.
So we designed for this explicitly saga
patterns and orchestration engines.
Coordinate multi-step workflows with
compensating transactions that handle
failures gracefully and every exception
path, not just success, gets captured
in the audit log with the same Rigo.
Lemme pull all three pillars together
in a cloud native architecture.
For consent, upend only event logs.
Tools like Apache Kafka work well
here, paid with immutable storage
for identity assurance levels.
Travel as JWT clients
propagated across every service.
Call for orchestration.
Engines like AWS step, functions,
or temporal coordinate.
The saga workflows and the audit log
captures everything, success, failure,
and how each failure was resolved.
Let me make this concrete.
A customer opens a savings account.
They read the terms and GTPR
disclosure, every interaction
captured as an immutable event.
They verified their email, low risk
access, granted, they uploaded ADD Id
document assurance level updates in the
JWT claims, funds transfer unlocked.
Then the third party KYC provider.
Times out thus saga or files
a compensating transaction.
The session passes,
partial state is preserved.
The customer gets a clear
notification, the cause, the
reservation, and the both logged.
No gap, no ambiguity.
That's what a defensible onboarding
record looks like because complaints
was built in not bolted on.
The last piece is governance because
the cloud native systems are built to
change and complaints has to be served.
That change every service update.
Every infrastructure migration, every
new team onboarding is an opportunity
for compliance to quietly ERO if
it is not treated as an explicit
architectural input, documented
version, and God not assumed to
be preserved by individual teams.
So let me leave.
Leave you with five things to take away.
One complaints must be
structural, not a layer.
You add something you designing.
Two.
Consent is a record, not
a checkbox washing it.
Timestamp it, make it mutable.
Third, identity assurance
is continuous propagate.
It is a first class
attribute across services.
Four exception or compliance events.
Audit them with the same rigor
as success path, and five.
Governance must evolve
with the system compliance.
Integrity is not something
you achieve once.
Thank you.
I really appreciate your time today.
This gives you a practical way
to design system that remain
explainable and defendable over time.
Happy to connect and keep
the conversation going.