Hello, comp 42.
My name is Ryan Vila.
I'm the harness feature Management
Experimentation advisory director.
I work with customers who are
implementing feature management
experimentation as practices within
their product engineering organizations.
I also help them utilize the
harness module of the same name.
Today I had the pleasure of talking
a little bit about one of the key use
cases behind utilizing a feature toggle.
Which is around cloud migration
or re-platforming of any type.
Hopefully I can add to probably what
is your existing knowledge around
future flags with an added perspective
of where measurement comes in and
how your teams might leverage it.
First, let's start with the
actual migration itself.
Obviously migration.
Represents risk.
It also should represent, of course,
opportunities for your organization.
There are often failure modes that
are represented within migrations
that can be limited or prevented.
First, there's a big bang cut over.
This is obviously when you treat
a deployment as a release and
something's a hundred percent
turned on in a migration event.
It's a little more complex because
sometimes people think of one element of a
migration and then they cobble it together
with other elements of the migration.
Let's say a UI change with a pipeline
change, with a new service, and they
try to couple all of those various
events together in one big cutover,
which creates tremendous risk.
And problems for an organization if
there's a problem with one of those three
or various components that are involved.
The second failure mode is around a
rollback path, meaning as I progress
inside my migration, do I have an
opportunity to pause that migration
or maybe take a step back in that
migration, or is it simply forward only?
This creates, of course, a lot of
friction for an organization, a lot
of tension for an organization because
they're not certain that they wanna
start something if they can't actually
stop it or recover from its progress.
The last failure mode is an inability
to control the blast radius,
so who the change is affecting.
At any given time is not mitigated,
and so when something is deployed, it's
also released, and if there's a problem
inside that release, it means a hundred
percent of your traffic or your users
are actually exposed to that problem.
What we wanna think about is how
can we turn a migration event into
more of a controlled experiment?
We're gonna start with a little bit of CS
1 0 1 here and just do a quick refresher
on the pattern that we're following,
which is the strangler fig pattern.
A term coined by Martin Fowler
many decades ago at this point.
So I'm not rehashing anything new
here, but I always feel education.
You're either learning something
new or you're affirming
something you already know.
In the strangler fig pattern it
is about controlling the flow of
traffic, let's say, into a service.
Being able to direct that flow of
traffic, let's say, to a new service
that might be being deployed in
parallel to an existing surface during
that bifurcation of the traffic.
Teams should have opportunities to measure
either qualitative or quantitatively
the changes in the two streams or
the differences in the two streams.
This should then inform the teams
about the efficacy and performance
of the change as it ss ultimately
leading to your ability to then
retire the pre-existing service.
And remove that debt from
your application, A fairly
straightforward approach.
Unfortunately, many organizations still
fail to do a more gradual replacement
of old services with new services.
So what does a gradual
replacement look like?
We're all familiar with a
canary release of course.
Or some sort of percentage based
release or some sort of incremental or
progressive rollout of a capability you
might start, for example, with taking
a particular release or a change and
exposing it to your internal users.
This allows you, of course, to
do some internal validations
before anybody external to your
organization is exposed to the change.
You might build on top of that exposure
with test accounts utilizing synthetic
traffic, if that's something that's
available to you and your teams.
Or you could start to engage with
QA organizations in your customer
organizations that are trusted partners
to provide feedback qualitatively
on the nature of the change.
As you progress beyond, let's say,
individual targets of a change,
you then wanna start thinking
about what's a small release mean?
And I could have probably phrased
this in a number of different ways,
my experience working with a variety
of organizations is small, is defined
in a number of different ways.
Sometimes it could be 1%, for example,
that would be a very incremental release.
Of my traffic, I could focus my
release on one zip code or one region.
The definition of small is gonna
come from you and your customers
understanding what's the smallest
blast radius that I can go into
production with, and still have an
opportunity to measure potential impact,
particularly potential negative impact.
As I progress past this initial footprint,
I want to ensure that I'm of course
measuring at every step of the process.
So what I measured at small, I should
continue to measure because we all
understand that from a performance
perspective, it might not be a problem
at 5%, it could be a problem at 6%.
And so you wanna make sure that you
are measuring constantly in your
release pattern before, of course
you reach general availability.
So again, you wanna measure frequently.
I often say think like a load test for
those of you who've done performance
engineering in your current life
or a past life, meaning everything
from one to a hundred percent.
Is a test of scalability and ensuring
that the, that there's no instability
that gets introduced because obviously
if there is any instability, you want
to be able to pause or potentially
revert back and revert back.
If you look up at the top, doesn't
necessarily mean kill the release, right?
It could be just a problem
at a particular scale.
And so you might wanna move from
your measured ramp stage to your
act small stage, or you might
wanna go from your act small stage
back to your test account stage.
It could be disruptive sometimes to
just immediately kill everything.
If there's not an opportunity to just
go back, scale back, learn a little
bit more, and then re progress.
Now what do you watch at a 1%?
First, an easy comparison would be
what's my existing service and what's
my new service, and what are the metrics
associated with that existing service?
And am I seeing an improvement?
Am I seeing reduced latency?
Am I seeing a reduction in error rates?
Is my throughput increasing?
It depends on the nature of the change.
But the idea is that you don't necessarily
want to aim for a lift and shift
concept, meaning what I had yesterday
is exactly what I want tomorrow.
You're spending a lot of time and
resources into this migration.
It would make sense to actually
improve on metrics that are
important to your organization.
You can look at your error budget.
How much of that budget is being
spent in your small release?
Does that seem as you scale it out
to a hundred percent, that would be
an appropriate error rate to get to?
A hundred percent?
Obviously, cost comes into mind.
Your existing service might have
built, been built on legacy technology,
legacy behavior, hopefully in a
new service that's being deployed.
The question of can we do it?
At a reduced cost has entered the
equation and you could start to do
some measurements working with your
finops teams to understand what
is the cost that's occurring now
compared to what we had previously?
And then last is cohort behavior.
Looking at your data in the aggregate,
meaning if I turn things on for,
let's say a region might mask.
Particular challenges of your customers?
Unless I can look with greater
granularity across key cohorts.
So for example, let's say I
release something to Ireland.
Let's say it's change to an API
that my mobile application calls.
I might not just wanna look at the
1% that's exposed to the change,
but I also might wanna understand
what my iOS experience is versus
my Android experience, or if I'm
using some sort of react native.
I'd wanna compare within those
experiences to ensure that the
aggregate isn't hiding some problem.
It might be more specific
to a slice of customers.
That's just as important as the aggregate.
Now, you all might be saying
I measure all of these things.
We measure costs.
We have a finops organization
that's constantly evaluating what's
being deployed and what's running.
We have, of course, our operations
team, which is looking at dashboards
related to performance and error rates.
And so what's the difference
that we're talking about here?
We're getting to the difference
of measuring versus monitoring.
Monitoring is incredibly important.
Building observability is incredibly
important, but when we're talking about
small incremental changes inside of the
system, you have to imagine that in the
production world there's a lot of noise.
And so for example, if there's a
2% error rate in the production
world, that might be high.
Of course, it depends on the
size of the organization.
But it might not be to the level to
really get anyone's attention, right?
That might just be the sort of
ebb and flow of error rates that
exist inside the system today.
If we change the paradigm of how we
measure things, meaning from the point
of migration where I'm introducing a
change and I measure from that point
of change, I might be able to create
a different picture of the effect
that I'm introducing in production.
So now if I'm looking across my
migration and I'm introducing a feature
into production, and it's of course
going in with many other changes that
might be existing at any given time
inside production, if I'm measuring
from the point of change, that 2%
error rate becomes a 40% error rate.
That, of course, is a
clear problem signal.
That should enable organizations
to take action, right?
Trigger some alert based on this data.
'cause you top probably wouldn't
do it based on 2%, but certainly
40% warrants some scrutiny and
potentially some fast remediation.
I wanted to walk through actually, one of
our scenarios that, that we did at split.
Split was a. Feature management and
experimentation company acquired
by harness a couple years ago.
And as a B2B platform, we're constantly
evaluating our data pipelines.
We're ingesting petabytes of information
every week from our customers.
We're analyzing that
information in real time.
It's important for us to be
able to not only ingest it,
but process that information
efficiently and cost effectively.
We had the benefit.
Of having a pretty strong increase in
customers and therefore in the amount
of data that was coming into our system.
In this case, we had, a single batch
job that was sequentially processing
request and messages that were coming in.
But unfortunately we had a bit of
a hockey stick of growth, which had
a direct linear impact on our cost.
Something that really
couldn't be supported.
We also had quality issues with our
inbound integration, where our customers
who were uploading information, wanted
to implement their own quality checks
to make sure the information that
was being sent was being received
correctly and in a timely manner.
So our approach was we wanted to build
a new pipeline, something that allowed
us to scale horizontally and vertically.
Be able to handle those
message cues not sequentially.
We also wanted to have greater targeting
in terms of how that pipeline approach
worked, so we'd be able to differentiate
between different message traffic that's
coming in, and we needed the, then
the ability also to turn off traffic
if we needed to for any given reason.
We utilized a feature flag.
To essentially direct traffic from the old
pipeline into the new streaming pipeline.
So this flag actually wasn't a
feature flag, it was for routing
our infrastructure traffic.
The result, we were able to
reduce our cost by about 80%.
Our processing time went from a 10 hours
to 15 minutes for the same 50 gigabit.
Payload.
We were able to migrate inside of a
quarter, inside of three months with
zero customer impact, and we were
able to improve the quality of our
pipeline, giving our customers the
observability that they were looking
for so they could implement their
own quality checks in their jobs.
Yeah, I always feel like I
should add a cautionary tale.
This isn't gonna be necessarily specific
to a migration, but flags obviously
provide a strong purpose in migrations.
But there can be some things that
expose you to additional risks
that I just wanted to call out.
First.
Stale flags.
You always wanna make sure.
That a flag follows a lifecycle,
and that you have policies and
governance implemented around your
flag implementation to both detect
as well as mitigate the presence
of stale flags inside your system.
These stale flags could potentially
cause harm in the future as someone
either removes the flag or accidentally
toggles the flag trying to determine
the behavior or the nature of the flag.
It is important that in a flag
where you might have to scale back
versus just kill that you've tested
all the conditions of that flag.
Oftentimes flags have various different
states they can be on, they can be off.
Sometimes there's a state
of a flag that's a default.
Meaning if there's some sort of problem
inside the flag evaluation, there should
be a code control behavior for that flag.
Teams must test each of
those fallback mechanisms.
Teams should apply governance across their
environments, and they should ensure that
the configurations define, let's say, in
a staging environment, match those in.
Production.
If you maintain flags inside of a
DR and there's a grand rollback, you
also want to ensure that the flag
definitions existing in production
at that time match those in DR.
Or are in an off state unless they're
a hundred percent deployed, right?
There's a number of different probably
scenarios you'd wanna work through,
but the key thing here is to make sure
that you understand your definitions.
And you control that drift.
Where you need to last is ownership.
Ambiguity.
Make sure that as flags are utilized, the
team that operates the flag understands
their ownership responsibility.
Ambiguity in owner ownership
creates ambiguity in action.
And so if there's a negative event
occurring, and the process for
removing that negative event is
to potentially toggle flag clear
ownership says who should do it, and
they would understand the results
of them killing or changing a flag.
State.
I always mention, flag
controls a change, right?
Do I show a feature?
Do I use a new pipeline?
Do I deploy new API?
But the flag itself is a change.
It is its own code and therefore should
be tested as code in all of its states.
And it should be cleaned up like any other
code where if it no longer has a use, it's
no longer being called then it shouldn't
no longer of course be carried forward.
So what are some things that
you can do coming outta here?
Most of us have some migration that we're
involved with today, or that's upcoming.
How are you gating?
That new path.
If that service already exists and
you're optimizing it or creating
a new version of it, what are the
elements of it that are changing
and are those elements controlled?
Second, if there's a problem related
to that migration, what happens?
Do we revert back to just the old service?
Do we scale back on the new service?
What flag makes that change?
I ask who can do it at 3M?
But maybe a more modern question
would be, how can I automate that
kill switch inside of my flag?
And then the last question
is, what's your rollback SLA?
So go going from, we have a
problem to our own solid footing.
What's the amount of time that
your organization has to exist
in that fugue state before
everyone's back into that known?
Good.
I hope you've found
this talk informational.
I hope it's been valuable.
Hopefully there is something
that was learned from it.
If you wanna continue the
conversation, we'd welcome you to.
Take our ebook of this name.
We'll reach out.
We'd love to continue this conversation.
Again, my name is Ryan Vela.
It's been a pleasure speaking
with you, and I hope you have a
wonderful rest of your conference.
Thank you.