Hi everyone, and welcome to my session.
Azure Techs unpacked real world
threats and lessons learned.
Let's jump right into it.
The talk is inspired by real world threat
intelligence, specifically to Microsoft
Digital Defense Report, MDDR 2025.
Yes, it's inspired by a report.
Bear with me.
It's not a replica of the report, but
rather a practical walkthrough of the
techniques it highlights translated
into something you can use in your
day-to-day work or personal life.
The MDDR is an annual
publication released since 2020.
The latest edition from 2025
is available in three formats.
The full report, 85 pages, a
government and policymakers
version, 15 pages and CISO version.
The highest level overview at 13 pages,
so choose your own reporting adventure.
I'll link the report directly on this
slide, and there's also podcast referenced
in the report if you'd like to go deeper
and maybe subscribe to its RSS feed.
The report itself is based on an
enormous volume of telemetry from
Microsoft's ecosystem, and it gives
us a global view of how attackers
are evolving, especially how they're
leveraging ai and more importantly,
what is actually working for them.
And one of the most important insights
is this modern MFA is still considered
to reduce the risk of compromise
by more than 99% despite the death.
Over 97% of identity attacks
today are still passwords
spraying or brute force attempts.
Attackers are not giving up
on credentials yet, but at the
same time, attacks are evolving.
Attackers exploit authentication
flows, tos and sessions, trusted
applications and even user behavior.
So the shift we're seeing is
very clear from password attacks
to identity and session abuse.
And this is exactly where many
environments are still catching up.
From my own experience working as a
security engineer in Microsoft 365
environments across ID defender, XDR,
and purview, I have seen this firsthand.
Waves of login attempts in the logs,
different ips, different geographies, same
pattern, and sometimes you'll notice a
specific user agent showing up repeatedly.
One example is BAV two ROPC.
This user agent is commonly
associated with password spring
attempts using legacy authentication.
It bypasses modern MFA controls by
design, and what you'll typically
see in the logs is repeated failures.
Error code 553 and
eventual account lockouts.
Behind that is usually automated
tooling and a distributed attacker
infrastructure of linked to access
brokers or nation state activity.
And here's the key problem.
The legacy authentication
may still be enabled.
So while identity attacks are becoming
more sophisticated, many of them
still succeed because of basic gaps
in configuration and visibility.
And fixing those is not
always straightforward.
Disabling legacy authentication,
for example, sounds simple, but in
reality it can break old applications,
scripts, and forgotten integrations.
So organizations delete and attackers
can try to take advantage of that window.
So even in this intersection, let's
start with something practical.
You can check right?
First for account brute force
attempts in Microsoft Defender
for cloud apps, policy management,
threat detections activity policy.
Select the unusual frequency of failed
logs for your environment and define the
appropriate alert or governance action.
Though I have to say, the report
also mentions attacker's approach
with slow password spray trying
multiple passwords over an extended
period to avoid such detection.
For legacy authentication in
Microsoft, enter ID monitoring
and health sign in logs.
Filter by client app legacy
authentication clients.
Third in the Microsoft 365 admin center.
Go to settings org.
Settings.
In the modern authentication flyout,
you can verify if access is allowed
to any basic authentication protocol.
S and TP POP three E map, for example.
Enter id, conditional access.
Check the reporting status of policies
blocking legacy authentication across
exchange, active sync, and other clients.
Also, you might want to consider
blocking countries where your
organization never does business and
limiting possible activities from
unmanaged or non-compliant devices.
After thorough testing, of course.
And fifth in ID monitoring
and health workbooks.
Review sign-ins using legacy
authentication obligatory.
Microsoft Disclaimer here, if
anything has been moved around in
the interface, track down the most
recent and relevant documentation.
If you don't have the privileges to access
any of these settings, it might be for
good reason, or it might be time for a
collaboration or peer programming session.
Use your best judgment.
Sure.
Okay.
Now that we've covered that beyond
password spring, the report highlights.
That novel attack paths are emerging
constantly, especially in hybrid
environments where on premises
and cloud identities intersect.
And that's exactly what
the stock will focus on.
We'll walk through 10 real world.
Fairly novel attack techniques observed
in the report, including social
engineering and initial access, identity
takeover and persistence and cloud
native post exploitation techniques.
For each one, we'll break it down
from the attacker's perspective and
how to defend against it in practice.
With that, let's move to
the meat of the session.
Let's start with something we
all think we understand phishing.
In email, people are already a bit
cautious, but in collaboration,
tools such as teams messages feel
internal, casual and trusted.
So attackers don't need to
break technical controls first.
They just need to blend into the
conversation, and that's what makes
attacks via collaboration tools.
Now, here's the twist.
Email is often the first
step with email bombing.
For example, attackers can flood
your inbox with spam, creating
noise, confusion, and urgency, and
then right after that, reach out on
teams or even follow up with a call.
They can falsely represent
themselves as help desk or IT
support and try to wish, as in voice
phishing, think something like.
We see unusual activity on your account.
Let's fix this quickly,
and you jump on it.
And at that moment they have
the trust and urgency they need.
From there, they can guide the
user tool, start a Windows quick
assist session, click on a link,
download and install a tool.
Malicious, of course.
And just like that, they've
moved from an external message
to the devices local user access.
A very common pattern looks like this.
Spam emails flooding the inbox,
then followed by teams contact
and call to action like a
Windows quick assist session.
Groups like Storm 1811 have been linked
to campaigns that abuse teams to gain
access and deploy follow one activity.
Now, most users are already
trained to spot phishing in email.
Compare the sender display name with
the email address, however, over links
and avoid unexpected attachments.
But what happens when this
moves into teams, you need to
translate that same awareness.
So let's talk defense.
Control teams exposure.
Limit external communication
where possible, and monitor
for impersonation attempts.
Advocate users make it very
clear that, for example, it will
never ask you to start quick.
Assist or install tools through teams,
then secure teams, messaging and calls,
making sure that users can report
suspicious messages directly in teams.
Messages are scanned for unsafe
links and disallowed content.
End users can report suspicious calls
explaining what raised their concern.
Also limit approved software
including RMM, remote
monitoring and management tools.
So only approved tools should be used
and anything else should raise a signal.
Let's move on to the next technique.
Click Fix is a technique where the
attacker represents a fake error or
issue, and then guides the user to
resolve it By using a keyboard shortcut
to open a Windows run window, then
paste and run obfuscated commands.
That phishing page adds in the background
to their clipboard, which ultimately
leads to mother being executed.
It's a form of social engineering
that takes advantage of a very human
instinct, the desire to fix a problem.
So how does the user
actually get to this page?
The attacker creates a situation that
feels urgent, technical, and easy to fix.
It might be a fake pop-up.
Verify your human prompt, a login issue,
job application or assessment submission,
or a support message, something
that looks just legitimate enough.
And then it tells the user to do
something very specific, copy and
paste the command to fix the problem.
At that moment, the user presses win
plus r paste the command and hits enter.
From the user's perspective, they're
fixing an issue, but in reality,
they're executing something like
PowerShell or mta, which then pulls a
malicious payload directly into memory.
There's no obvious download,
no file sitting on the disk.
It's often a file list process,
which makes it much harder for
traditional tools to detect.
And with just a few keystrokes, the
attacker can steal credentials and
establish persistence in the environment.
We've seen multiple real world
campaigns using this exact approach, for
example, from groups like Storm 1865.
And there have been phishing campaigns
impersonating trusted brands like
booking.com, where users were
guided into executing these commands
and ended up with multiple types
of credentials stealing malware.
There have also been cases where
attackers used fake collaboration or
productivity platforms like Notion Style
websites to deliver similar instructions.
And in other variants, attackers have
also spoofed Google Recapture and
Cloud Flares turn style solution.
From a systems perspective, this
can look like a legitimate user
is deliberately running commands.
So how do we defend against
something like this?
The first layer has to be
user awareness Training.
Users need to understand that a text
like this exist and copying and pasting
commands from a known sources is just
as risky as clicking a malicious link.
Then there's the technical side.
You want visibility and control
what users are allowed to execute.
Especially scripts and commands
coming from untrusted context.
One approach here where possible
is to use constrained language mode
to limit PowerShell abuse, then
review startup and outrun apps, and
finally hardened the environment.
Overall limit exposure to malicious sites.
Use hardened repeatable configurations
for operation systems and enterprise
controlled browsers such as Enterprise
Microsoft Edge with Microsoft Defender
Smart Screen, which can provide
multiple security features including
security update requirements and data
compliance policies, and with the
flashy warning, reduce the chances
that the user ever lands on one of
the these attacker controlled pages.
Let's move on to the next technique.
So let's move away from user-driven
attacks for a moment here,
attackers don't trick anyone.
The focus is on public facing
vulnerabilities and risk configurations.
An old unpatched public facing application
or underlying instance, metadata
service configured against up to date
best practices, valid secrets in IDE
extensions or mobile applications,
a misconfigured, API endpoint,
anything reachable from the internet.
And reality is these are
being scanned constantly.
Attackers use automated and AI
enhanced enumeration at scale,
looking for anything that stands out.
Open ports outdated services, exposed
admin interfaces, misconfigured
storage, weak authentication.
The moment the surface is scratched,
the weakness usually doesn't
stay on that surface for long.
Vulnerabilities are changed and weaponized
quickly, and the window between disclosure
and exploitation keeps shrinking.
Ransomware operators and bottle net
distributors rely on this model.
This can broadly find something exposed.
Can access exfiltrate mine, create
persistence for themselves, or they try
to sell that access to someone else.
For example, the CLP Ransomware Group
exploited a previously unknown SQL
induction vulnerability in MoveIt
transfer managed file transfer solution.
Internet facing mood transfer web
applications were infected with a
web shell, which was then used to
steal data from underlying databases.
In modern environments, a tech service
includes the entire DevSecOps pipeline
code, and its direct and transitive
dependencies, workflows on the developers.
Local workstations used
add-ons and extensions.
Security of the code management
Solution Infrastructures.
Code Docker and Kubernetes manifests.
CICD, workflows, secrets management
solutions, storage and container
registries, deployments, applied
networking and drift policies, static
and dynamic security scanning, even
monitoring and alerting systems of it.
Initial thought of CICD pipelines might
be that they're inherently secure and
resilient even nowadays when they can be
AI assisted, but they still can be abused.
There was a case involving a supply
chain compromise where an attacker
found a vendors cloud secret and started
tampering with their GitHub action.
Instead of deleting or adding to their
code base, they made a subtle change.
They modified an existing script to
call onto an infastructure payload
and that had a ripple effect.
The payload then harvested credentials
across a wide range of accessible
SH keys kit configurations,
AWS Azure GCP credentials.
Kubernetes Secrets Docker,
configs, CICD tokens.
This kind of attack is difficult to
spot because it tends to blend into
trusted processes and containers are
another critical piece of this puzzle.
Many compromised containers are attacked
within the first 48 hours of deployment.
That tells us attackers are not
just scanning the existing services,
they're also watching for the new ones.
The moment something is deployed
and exposed, it becomes a target.
In Kubernetes environment, crypto mining
is still one of the most common outcomes.
It's fast automated and profitable.
So what we can do to defend
against this first, it's starts
with visibility inventory.
You need to know what is actually exposed,
not what you think it's exposed, but what
is reachable from the internet right now.
Public facing services, APIs, storage
accounts, hardware and software assets,
meet your name to it, need to be
continuously discovered and tracked.
Consider best practice approach for
threat modeling integrated into your
pipelines and for your use case.
For example, embedding Mozilla's rapid
risk assessment RA stride or past
considerations could help prioritize
the risk and ensure security decisions
are repeatable, transparent, aligned
across teams, and a consistent
part of your security culture.
Treat misconfigurations with the same
level of attention as vulnerabilities.
In many cases, they are the entry point.
Things like unauthenticated, Kubernetes,
axis unencrypted data trust, orally
promising configurations can be just
as dangerous as an existence of a
public exploit For CVE, that's where
strong DevSecOps practices come in.
This means repeatable
configurations, scanning manifests,
hardening across image layers.
Tools like Dock, Cuba, bench and Checo,
for example, help enforce infrastructure
and security best practices.
Secrets management is
another critical area.
Credentials that are often exposed in
code pipelines or configuration files.
Tools like Travel, HOK and Talisman
can help identify these before
attackers do, but only if they are
integrated into your pipelines.
Not used as a one-time scan.
At the same time, blindly pulling
the latest versions of third party
vendor integrations introduces risk.
You could pin and verify third party tools
used in your pipeline, then pull them
into internally controlled registries
through a controlled update process where
new versions are reviewed and promoted
rather than automatically consumed.
Runtime monitoring and
alerting are equally important.
Use cloud native services to secure
your cloud environment directly.
Use tools like Microsoft
Defender for Cloud.
Were available, patch and harden
applications, and limit unnecessary
public exposure wherever possible.
Continuous visibility after deployment
is needed with threat detection
and automated response in place.
While many attacks happen early.
Long tail attacks are real and
they target environments that are
no longer being actively watched.
Plan for recovery as well.
Maintain secure, isolated write ones.
Read many backups that cannot be
modified, and ensure that you can revert
to a last known good configuration.
Lastly, but not least here, another
powerful layer is collaboration
with the security community.
Public and private vulnerability
disclosure programs and bug bounty
programs allow creative security
researchers to test your environment
from an attacker's fresh perspective
and uncover issues that internal teams
might miss and provide real value.
Let's now look at one of the clearest
examples of how identity attacks
have evolved beyond passwords.
In device code phishing campaigns like the
one conducted by storm 2372, the attacker
initiates their login to a Microsoft
account, requests a device code for their
device, and receives the code there.
So there is no spoofed infrastructure
here, no fake login page.
There is no traditional
credential stealing.
Instead, they trick the victim into
entering attackers code themselves.
Once they do that, the system grants
access to the original session and issues
access and refresh tokens to the attacker.
The way they do this is
through very realistic alerts.
The attacker might start by contacting
the target over platforms like
Microsoft Teams Signal, WhatsApp,
often posing as a relevant or
trusted individual to build rapport.
Then they sent what looks like
legitimate messaging invitation
or collaboration request.
When target clicks the link, they are
guided into a device code authentication
flow that looks exactly like a
normal Microsoft signin experience.
From the user's perspective,
everything checks out.
They are on a legitimate
Microsoft login page.
They entered the code they were given.
They complete MFA, and
that's the key moment.
The user thinks they are signing
in for themselves, but they're
actually completing authentication
for the attacker's initiated session.
At that point, the attacker receives
valid access and refresh tokens.
No password is captured.
MFA is technically satisfied.
The attacker now has a fully
authenticated session and can access
anything the user has permission to.
They can also move laterally, sending
additional phishing messages from the
compromised account to other users inside
the organization, making the attack even
more convincing Now, how to defend against
something like this first control the
exposure of the device code flow itself.
If your organization doesn't need it,
block it or restrict its usage where
possible through conditional access.
So in enterra id, conditional access
authentication flows, device code
flow, block access if it is required.
Monitor closely in antra Signin
coming from device code flow.
Use ID signing logs and risky signing
reports to detect unusual device code
authentication activity, especially
from unexpected locations or patterns.
Third, focus on token based detection.
Look for anomalous token usage, unexpected
device registrations or activity that
doesn't align with usual user's behavior.
User awareness still matters here,
but in a slightly different way.
In traditional phishing, users are
taught to check whether the login
page is legitimate, but in this
case, the page is legitimate, the
domain is correct, the certificate
is valid, and MFA works as expected.
So those usual checks won't help.
If the user receives a message asking
them to enter a code or complete a login,
they didn't initiate it themselves,
especially as part of an external meeting
invite or so-called support request, that
should raise suspicion because in this
attack, the risk is not a fake login page.
It's been tricked into approving a
real login, but for someone else.
Finally, if compromise is suspected,
revoke tokens, force the authentication
and sign the user out of all sessions.
Let's now move into what happens after
authentication, because this is where
many modern attacks actually live.
This is session hijacking, and
the key idea here is very simple.
The attacker doesn't need your password
if they can take over your session
when a user logs in successfully using
their credentials and MFA, the system
issues, tokens, this can be access
tokens, refresh tokens, session cookies.
From that point on, these tokens,
grant access to applications and APIs.
They act as proof that
authentication has already happened.
So the system stops asking for
credentials, and that creates
a very important shift because
whoever holds that token can use it.
The system trusts the token as proof
that authentication already happened,
but it doesn't continuously verify.
Person behind it, and that's the gap.
And this is something Microsoft's MDDR
also highlights the need to move beyond
one time authentication and toward
continuous identity verification.
That means looking at behavior over time.
Things like access patterns, data
usage, or even signals such as
typing or interaction patterns.
If something changes like a finance
user, suddenly accessing large volumes
of engineering data, that should trigger
authentication or additional approval.
So how do attackers
actually get these tokens?
There are a few common paths.
One is still phish, but not in the
traditional password stealing sense.
Instead, attackers use techniques
like adversary in the middle,
phishing evil, gen X, for example,
to capture session cookies.
After the user has already
authenticated, including after MFA,
another common path is stel malware
or malicious browser extensions.
These can extract tokens directly
from browser storage, things like
session cookies, local storage
or memory, depending on how the
application handles authentication.
Web vulnerabilities also play a role.
Cross aid scripting, for example, can
allow malicious scripts to read tokens
or session data from the browser.
And in certain cases, cross site
request forgery can abuse an already
authenticated session to perform
actions on behalf of the user, even
without directly stealing the token.
From a browser perspective, most controls
are actually not in the user's hands.
Settings like HTP only cookies or
how tokens are stored are defined
by the application, not the browser.
Keeping the browser updated using
browsers hardened via enterprise
policy and containerizing.
Browsing context may also help reduce
exposure, and tokens can leak through
Compromise tools, pipelines, logs,
or memory scraping on endpoints.
Tokens.
Hard coded in code or configuration
of files are still something
attackers actively look for.
Once the attacker has the token,
they don't need to log in again.
At least they bought themselves
some time in the environment.
They don't trigger MA, they
don't need the password.
They simply use the token
and continue the session.
This is exactly what we see
in the real world attacks.
Groups like a PT 29 have used
token and session abuse in cloud
environments to maintain persistent
access without real authenticating.
These techniques are often combined
with phishing or infas malware forming
part of a broader identity attack chain.
Now, how do we defend against
this as usual in layers?
First, reduce the chance of token misuse.
Conditional access policies can enforce
that authentication only happens from
compliant devices or trusted networks.
That way tokens are not issues to risky or
unmanaged environments in the first place.
Second, protect the tokens themselves.
Token protection, also known as token
binding cryptographically ties tokens
to a specific device using mechanisms
like the primary refresh token.
This means that even if a token
is stolen, it cannot be replay
from another device threat.
Continuously evaluate the session
continuous access evaluation.
CAE allows the system to reassess the
security posture during an active session.
If something changes like a location
shift or risk is considered as
increased access can be revoked without
waiting for the talking to expire.
Fourth to make memory scraping harder
on endpoints, enable credential
guard local security authority LSA
protection and the defender rule that
blocks credential stealing from lss.
Roll this out in audit mode
first, then enforce them and
pair them with conditional access
and token session revocation.
So stolen material is less useful even if
an endpoint is compromised and detection.
Monitor four session anomalies,
things like the same session being
used from different locations,
unusual token usage patterns, and
unexpected device registrations.
Again, if you suspect token
compromise, revoke tokens, force
three authentication, and sign the
user out of all active sessions.
Let's now look at another identity attack
that can go under the radar, but can be
just as dangerous as credential theft.
This is consent phishing, or often
called illicit consent grant attack.
Here the attacker is going
after user's permissions.
Practically the attacker registers an
application in their own attackers,
Microsoft Azure tenant, so anyone can
register an app and request permissions,
like reading emails, accessing files,
or interacting with Microsoft graph
APIs, for example, something like chat
read or mail read might be requested.
Claiming those are needed for the
app to work as expected, which
sounds harmless enough on service.
Then comes the social engineering part.
The attacker sends a phishing email or
embeds a link into a trusted looking
website or even uses collaboration tools.
The user clicks the link and is redirected
to a Microsoft consent screen, and
that's where the key moment happens.
Instead of being asked for credentials,
the user is asked to grant certain
permissions of attacker's choice.
It might say something like.
This app would like to read your
mail and access your OneDrive.
Please approve.
And because the screen looks legitimate,
many users simply click accept.
At that moment, the attacker doesn't
get the password, they don't need it.
The application receives an authorization
code, exchanges it for access and refresh
tokens, and now the application has
API level access to the user's data.
And that access is persistent, even if the
user receives their password and MFA is
enforced, user granted their permissions.
Application continues to operate
in the background, accessing
files or exfiltrating data.
This is why this attack is so effective.
It operates entirely within
the rules of the platform.
It abuses trust, not vulnerabilities.
And we've seen real world campaigns
where threat actors use this
technique to gain long-term access
to Microsoft 365 environments.
In some cases, malicious apps were used
to harvest emails, temper with storage,
or maintain quite persistence over time.
And because this is still less common
than traditional fishing and a fairly
novel approach and you are not trained
and don't recognize it as a threat.
So what to do about it?
First, visibility in Microsoft,
Android, D. You can track this in
audit logs by looking for events such
as consent application or permission
grants, which indicate that a user or
admin has authorized an application.
Second governance.
Not every user should be able to
grant permissions to any application.
You can restrict consent
applications, limit permissions to
low risk scopes, or require admin
approval for anything sensitive.
Risk-based, step-up consent is especially
useful here, where suspicious requests
automatically require admin review.
Third, continuous review
applications and their permissions
should not be a one-time check.
They need to be audited regularly.
What apps exist in your tenant?
What permissions do they
have, who granted them?
And are those permissions still justified?
And then there's detection and
response services like Microsoft
Defender for cloud apps.
App governance can help identify
risky oral applications, unusual
behavior, or excessive permissions.
If something suspicious is found, the
response needs to be as soon as possible
and alerting and first response,
preferably automated disabled application,
revoke its permissions, invalidate
tokens, and assess the scope of impact.
And one more important piece that
often gets overlooked is reporting.
If you identify a malicious or
suspicious oil application, it is
not just an internal issue, it's
something that should be reported.
The Microsoft Security Response
Center, MSRC, investigates abuse
and malicious activity related
to Microsoft hosted services.
There is a dedicated reporting portal
where you can sub submit info about
suspicious of apps and help prevent
further abuse across the ecosystem.
So the key takeaway here is this.
Attackers don't always need credentials.
Sometimes they just need your permission.
Let's now look at another area
where many still have a false sense
of security, and that is one time
codes and temporary access passes.
A temporary access pass tap is
a time-limited passcode that an
administrator can generate for a user.
It is commonly used for onboarding
or when a user loses access to
their authentication methods.
Now, here's the key detail.
A type is considered a strong
authentication method, which means it
can satisfy MFA requirements on its own.
So if an attacker manager just
obtain or generates a tab for
user, they don't need the password.
They don't need to trigger MFA.
They can sign in directly, and this
is where the real risk comes in.
The weakest point is often not to do
technology, but the process around it.
For example, if an attacker can
successfully impersonate a user and
convince the help desk to issue a
temporary access pass, they've effectively
bypassed the entire authentication chain.
No phishing pages needed, no
malware, just social engineering.
This is why type abuse is often
quite and difficult to detect.
It looks like a legitimate
recovery or onboarding flow.
Now let's move on to one time
passcodes, especially SMS based
OTPs, which are still widely used.
These have been around for years
and are familiar to everyone.
You enter a password, receive
a code on your phone and enter
it to complete authentication.
One scenario here would be when an
attacker already has the username
and password, often from phishing or
previous breaches, they attempts to log
in, which triggers an OTP challenge.
Then they call or message the victim
pretending to be from IT support
or a bank and say something like,
you're seeing suspicious activity.
We just sent you a quote.
Can you read it back so we
can secure your account?
And in that moment, the user
hands over the second factor.
From the system's perspective, everything
is valid, correct password, correct.
OOTP access is granted.
Another scenario would be sim swiping
as one of the most well knowns.
This is when an attacker takes
over your phone number by moving
it onto a sim card to take control.
Once that happens, all calls and
SMS messages, including one time
passcodes are delivered to the
attacker instead of the victim.
There are well-documented real world
cases where insiders, employees or
contractors of mobile carriers have
helped facilitate these attacks.
For example, a T-Mobile employee was
arrested around 20 22, 20 23, after
performing dozens of unauthorized sim
swaps using internal systems in exchange
for payment from external attackers.
In another case, a telecommunications
manager admitted taking Bries to
carry out SIM swap operations.
There have been organized criminal
rings where mobile carrier employees
were part of the operation.
So in those scenarios, the
attacker doesn't need to
convince customers support.
They already have someone on
the inside, and at that point,
seam swapping becomes trivial.
If it's sent over SMS consider
it's not a foolproof secret,
it's just a message in transit.
The European Union Agency for
Cybersecurity anda actively
advises against relying solely on
SMS based one-time passwords due
to their susceptibility to sim
swiping, interception and moer.
Even time based on the passwords,
like those generated by
authenticator apps are not immune.
If an attacker can trick the user to
click approve where they didn't initiate
the login process or into getting the
user to enter their OTP code into a
phishing page, they can still gain access.
You've seen this in real world attacks.
Groups like Lapso use MFA fatigue
and repeated push notifications to
pressure users into proving access.
Other campaigns rely on OTP
interception or social engineering
to achieve the same outcome.
So how do we defend against this?
First, we need to control where
these mechanisms are used.
Temporary access pass
should be tightly scoped.
If you don't need it, disable it.
If you do, use it limited to
specific users or scenarios.
Enforce short lifetimes and prefer
one-time use, and most importantly,
secure the service desk process.
Strong identity verification adds
to help desk is critical because
that's where tap abuse often starts.
Second, reduce reliance
on weak OP channels.
SMS based occupational be considered
strong authentication anymore,
especially for high risk scenarios
where possible move to modern fishing
resistant methods which cannot be
intercepted or replayed in the same way.
Third monitor authentication behavior.
Look for unusual OTP requests.
Repeated MFA prompts or sign-ins that
don't align with standard user behavior.
In Enterra id, this means reviewing
sign-in logs, authentication methods
usage, and risky sign-in reports.
And finally, user awareness
still plays a role here, but
it needs to be very specific.
Users need to understand that one time
codes are not just verification steps,
they are credentials in that moment.
If somebody asks for that code,
they're effectively asking for access.
So if a user receives a code they
didn't initiate or someone asks them to
share it, it's not a support process.
That's an attack, and it
should be treated and reported.
As such.
When we talk about identities, most
people immediately think of users,
employees, admins, internal guests.
In over the past few years, organizations
have invested heavily in protecting
these identities with MFA conditional
access and risk-based controls.
But modern environments also rely
heavily on non-human identities.
These are the identities used
by applications, services,
scripts, containers, Kubernetes
pot virtual machines, and CACD
pipelines to access resources.
In Microsoft environments, these show
up as application registrations, service
principles, and managed identities.
And the key difference is that these
identities currently cannot perform MFA.
They often rely on secrets, certificates,
tokens, and in many environments they
are granted very high privileges so that
automation can work without friction.
That combination makes them
extremely attractive to attackers.
Because once an attacker compromises
a workload identity, they can act as
that trusted service inside the Azure
environment in real world attacks.
For example, in the storm 0 5, 58
campaign, attackers were able to forge
authentication tokens for a non-human
entity and access Microsoft Cloud
services, including email data by
abusing identity and trust relationships.
These attacks don't look
like traditional bridges.
There is no obvious malware
and no phishing email being
clicked in that moment.
An application might have access to
read storage accounts, access key vault,
deploy infrastructure, at least to
somehow interact with Microsoft Graph.
And over time these permissions are
rarely reviewed and they can accumulate.
From a system perspective, it
can look like an application
needs them to do its job.
Now, another important point, workload
identities often lack a proper lifecycle.
Unlike users, there is
often no clear ownership, no
expiration, no regular review.
Identities get created for a project,
and then they stay there with permissions
long after they are needed, and
that creates a large attack service.
So how do we defend against this?
First, we need visibility.
What workload identities
exist in your environment?
What service principles?
What managed identities?
What applications, what permissions
do they have and who created them?
Second, apply list privilege.
Just because an application
can be granted, broad access
doesn't mean it should.
Limit permissions to exactly what is
required and nothing more, especially
when it comes to sensitive resources
like Key Vault, Azure Logic apps, blob
storage or scouring directory data.
Third, protect credentials
properly if secrets are required,
store them securely, rotate them
regularly, and never hard code them.
Fourth, use conditional access
for workload identities where
possible monitor sign-ins.
Look for anomalies such as
unusual locations, unexpected
API usages or spikes in activity.
Microsoft Enter ID protection,
provides detection for risky
workload identities, including leaked
credentials, suspicious API, traffic and
anomalous service principle activity.
That gives you a way to
detect when something is off,
even if no user is involved.
But just a quick note here,
features like this depend on
your Microsoft licensing model.
For example, Microsoft Andra workload
ID is currently considered as an
additional offering with its own pricing.
So coverage and visibility may vary
as user identities become harder to
compromise, workload identities are
becoming the next easiest path in.
If you secure your users, but ignore your
applications, you are leaving a critical
part of your identity surface exposed.
Let's talk about location
proximity and MFA Fatigue attacks.
Most modern identity systems, especially
in Microsoft enter environments, don't
just evaluate a username and password.
They look at context.
Where is the user signing in from?
What device are they using?
Is this location expected?
And is this behavior normal?
And based on those signals, conditional
access policies decide whether to
allow access, block it, or require MFA.
Attackers understand this very
well, so instead of trying to break
authentication, they try to blend into it.
One technique is location,
proximity, mation.
This means the attacker tries
to make their login attempt look
like it's coming from location
close to the legitimate user.
This can be done through proxies, VPN
infrastructure or even compromised
infrastructure near the user.
We've also seen more
creative proximity scenarios.
For example, attacks leveraging local
virus technologies like Bluetooth.
While less common in enterprise identity
attacks, Bluetooth and other short
range channels can be with malicious
intent, intercepted and abused.
Another real world example is
when attackers compromise Soho
routers by modifying DNS settings.
They can position themselves
between the user and cloud services.
This enables adversary in the
middle attacks where authentication
traffic is relates through attacker
controlled infrastructure while
still appearing legitimate.
Now combine that with MFA fatigue.
In this scenario, the attacker already
has the correct password, often from
password spring or credential leaks.
They trigger repeated MFA prompts,
authenticator push notifications, SMS
approvals or voice calls, for example,
where enabled over and over again.
Eventually the user gets tired,
confused, or assumes it's a
glitch and approves one request.
That's all the attacker needs.
What makes this effective is how
simple approvals can work when
approval is just in a single click.
Users can make a decision without
context from the approval window.
They might not know 100% what they're
approving or where it's coming from.
Even a small percentage of users approving
these requests is enough at scale.
Now, from a detection perspective, signal
almost like impossible Travel can help.
A user appearing in two distant locations
within minutes, but attackers are
adapting and by using location proximity
techniques, they try to stay just close
enough to avoid triggering those alerts.
So the challenge becomes
distinguishing slightly of normal
behavior from legitimate activity.
Now, how do we defend against this?
Conditional access policies
should evaluate sign-in risk,
device compliance and behavioral
patterns, not just static rules.
Second, prevent blind MFA approvals
with number matching or similar, forcing
the user to enter a code from the login
screen if they initiated the login at all.
Third monitor for patterns
repeated and failed.
MFA prompts paired with unusual
sign-in attempt locations or spikes
in authentication attempts could
all be indicators of MFA fatigue.
Fourth plan for failure scenarios.
Talent lockouts are real operational
risk, especially during MFA attacks or
misconfigured conditional access policies.
Consider best practices, like every
environment should have at least two
global administrators with different MFA
methods and emergency break glass accounts
that are excluded from conditional access.
Without that, a combination of attack and
misconfiguration can lock out the entire
organization and for personal accounts,
there are also practical mitigation steps.
Adding an email alias and making it
the primary signin identity can reduce
exposure to MFA bombing because attackers
targeting the old username will no
longer trigger authentication prompts.
Disabling Passwordless Signin also removes
push-based approvals as an attack service.
It doesn't fix a leaked password,
but it significantly reduce the
noise and the risk from repeated
MFA prompts at the moment.
And let's wrap up with attacks and
defenses for today's session with what
happens after an attacker gets in.
At this stage, the goal is control,
persistence, and staying invisible
long enough to achieve the objective.
This is where many underestimated risk.
Post exploitation very often looks
like normal administrative activity.
The Azure environments, for
example, there is a built-in
feature called Azure Run Command.
It's designed for legitimate operations,
troubleshooting virtual machines when RDP
or H isn't available and running scripts
through remotely through the VM agent.
From a cloud operations perspective,
it's incredibly useful, and from an
attacker perspective, it's perfect.
Because once they gain sufficient
permissions potentially through one of
the previous attacks we have covered
today, they can execute power show
or shell command directly on virtual
machines without needing to drop
obvious malware or open inbound ports
for people just coming into the field.
This is what we mean by living off
the land or here living off the tent.
And from a logging perspective,
this can look like a legitimate
administrator running a script.
Co strike is one of the most commonly
abused postex exploitation frameworks.
It enables encrypted command and control
in memory, execution, lateral movement,
or without leaving clear traces on disc.
But attackers don't rely on a single tool
in packet allows them to use legitimate
protocols like SMB and VMI for remote
execution, which often looks like normal
administrative activity tools like Azure.
Home Extend is further on the cloud
site mapping relationship between
identities, roles, and resources to
identify privileges, escalation paths,
tools like Sliver and Broad throttle.
Take this further by Mimicing normal
HTPS or DNS traffic to evade detection.
At the same time, post breach techniques
are evolving, dynamic group manipulation,
and attempts to weaken visibility
through audit log tampering, we are
seeing increased abuse of RMM tools
for persistence and remote control.
Wal means to execute actions
using built-in system
binaries and even B-Y-O-V-D.
Bring your own vulnerable drivers
where attackers load vulnerable
drivers to disable security controls.
And one of the most concerning
trends is the rapid rise of Tels.
Traditionally seen as post exploitation
tools, malware, families like Lua,
redline, Vida, atomic, Steeler, and ER are
now being used as initial access payloads.
They harvest credentials, tokens,
and session data early in the attack,
accelerating everything that falls.
So how do we detect this shift from
signature based detection to behavior?
Look for things like unexpected
Azure run command execution, and
scripts being run on virtual machines
outside of normal chain windows.
Access to Elsa's memory
registry, dumping or credential
access patterns or endpoints.
Outbound tunneling or unusual
data transfer patterns in Azure,
specifically, activity logs become
critical monitor operations, like run
command, role assignments, service
principle changes, and any unusual API
activity talking usage patterns and
identity changes such as unusual session
reuse, dynamic group rule updates or
unexpected directory modifications.
Then prevention limit.
Who can execute actions like run command.
These permissions should
not be broadly assigned.
Apply the same principle to identity
controls, review and restrict who can
modify group membership, dynamic group
rules or service principle permissions.
Second, application control if only
approved tools can run with Active
and UpToDate Microsoft Defender.
Attackers have less chances to introduce
frameworks like Cobo Strike or Sliver.
Third hardened endpoints.
Features like core isolation can
help protect against credential
theft and memory based attacks.
Fourth, reduce the opportunities
for living of the land monitor and
restrict the use of building tools like
PowerShell, VMI and remote execution.
Utilities, we are not
blocking them entirely.
Make their usage visible and controlled.
For example, services.
Like Azure Monitor workbooks and
interactive reports might come in handy
here, and finally have backups that
are stored securely, isolated from
the environment, and regularly tested.
Because if an attacker established
persistence, your ability to
recover cleanly becomes critical.
Ensure logs are centrally collected and
protected from modification, so attackers
cannot easily erase their activity.
Let's close the session by enforcing
the main idea behind everything we've
covered today across all these examples.
Whether it was device code, phishing,
session hijacking, illicit consent
grants, or abuse of workload
identities, the pattern is consistent.
Attackers are not breaking authentication.
They are using legitimate flows,
trusted services, and built-in
functionality just in ways they
were never intended to be used.
That's why the focus has to shift.
It's no longer just about
protecting passwords.
It's about understanding how trust is
established in your environment and how
that trust can be misused over time.
If we summarize it simply, attackers
combine social engineering token
abuse and cloud native features
to move through environments while
looking like normal activity.
And that's what makes detection
harder because from the outside,
a lot of this looks valid.
So what are the top three
things to focus on first?
Reduce unnecessary exposure.
Disabled legacy authentication.
Restrict authentication flows like
device code where possible and apply
list privilege consistently across users,
applications and workload identities.
Second, monitor behavior, not just logins.
Look at how identities are
used after authentication.
Things like unusual token usage,
unexpected a p activity, or
changes in roles and permissions.
So plan for it, validate it through
simulated exercises, and have response
actions ready, automated where possible.
Third, prepare for
persistence and resilience.
Assume some level of access will happen.
Protect your logs from tampering.
Make sure you have isolated, tested
backups so you can recover to a known
good state and have a strategy in place
to prevent tenant or account lockouts.
Now, in terms of staying current,
this space evolves quickly.
Microsoft's Digital Defense report
their Threat Intelligence podcast.
Defender XDR Threat Analyst report were
available and their security RSS feeds
are some of the best places to follow.
The security community also plays
a big role here, sharing their
research, attack techniques, defensive
strategies, and asking questions
about incidents in real time.
And one file, no reminder.
If you come across suspicious
activity or potentially
malicious application, report it.
Microsoft has dedicated portal through
the Microsoft Security Response Center.
And reporting helps improve
detections not just for your
environment, but for others as well.
And with us.
Thanks to Conf 42 Cloud native
2026 organizers for having me.
And thank you all for joining my session.
Let's stay in touch on LinkedIn.
Bye for now.