Hello everyone.
You know something interesting
happened recently in the utility
space, a large utility rolled out
an AI model to predict outages.
Everything looked great.
Smart meters, weather
feeds, historical data.
Previous complaints, et cetera,
until one day the model failed
to predict a major outage.
Thousands and thousands of
customers impacted call centers
have been flooded with calls.
Executors were pulled into
war rooms, and here's the most
interesting part that stands out.
It wasn't the model.
It was not the algorithm, it was
not the ai, it was all about data.
The company did not have AI problem.
They had governance problem.
The paper titled Cloud Native
Data Lifecycle Governance for
Trusted AI and BI Systems.
It is one of the most practical
researches that I did.
To develop this blueprint for implementing
end-to-end governance across distributed
hybrid and multi-cloud environments.
From secure ingestion
to auditable deletion.
Hello, I am Karthik.
I work as a senior product manager
at Austin Energy, and I manage Cupra.
IS and VOC emergency data platforms.
In this session, we'll
be covering five topics.
The problem itself how do
we identify governance gaps?
How do we define governance?
At the very beginning.
The lifecycle that I came up
with, architectural layers ai,
incorporating AI and observability
some of the safe safeguards and
key takeaways from my experience.
On to the next slide.
I wanna talk about problem for a brief
couple of minutes because making everyone
understand the problem is one of the
most, most important things for a product
manager to convince the leadership.
In my experience, most
organizations based systems that
deploy a lot of models across.
Or spanning across different multi-cloud
environments or multi-cloud providers.
And then ask, how do we guard this?
You have everything you define, like what
is the product that you want to implement?
You deploy them in the production.
And now here we are trying to
work backwards to define the
question, how do we go this?
This leads to fragmented ownership.
That means there is no clear
accountability across the boundaries or
the data that is coming from the beginning
to the production, the actual real data.
What are the Com compliance gaps?
The industry that I work in
has G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A and TCPA.
HIPAA is automatically comes
across different industries.
You have to have.
Compliance gaps defined that
require provable data, lineage,
and then lack of trust.
Everybody is now talking about AI
and how we can incorporate AI to make
our productivity make to go over to
make our productivity go up, right?
AI and BI models trained
on ungoverned data produce.
Messy outputs, and I told you
the story about the utility space
that I recently worked on and the
projects that I worked so far.
It's all messy outputs.
So introduce regulatory and governance
definitions right from the beginning.
Okay.
And one other important.
Statement that I wanna make is AI
that everybody's talking about is
only as good as the data behind it.
If the data is not good,
your AI makes it look bad.
Moving on to the next slide,
let's talk about the framework.
Governance is not a layer.
It must be embedded in each
of the steps in your process.
In the blueprint that I've come
up with, you have four layers,
ingestion, classification,
accessibility, and tiered storage.
Effective governments must be embedded
in each and every of these phases
to make sure that it is not a layer
on top of this end-to-end process.
Makes it easier for any organization or
an individual to work on governance gaps
and make sure that applied in each phase
it's like building a chain of custody.
Okay, let's talk about layer one.
It's ingestion, secure
ingestion patterns that scale.
Ingestion, in my opinion, is the first and
most critical governance control point.
Cloud solutions or cloud native
architecture must enforce data
validation, encryption, and provenance
tracking at the point of entry.
That means that the gate, before the data
gets in, you need to apply the governance
patterns for the governance practices.
Enforce a structure at the schema level.
Enforce the structure at the
transformational level and make sure
that the data is cataloged for each
of the every attribute before the
bad data gets in and it spreads.
We validate this at the entry.
If you don't validate at ingestion, you're
scaling the scaling bad metadata faster.
Okay.
Moving on to stage two
classification and cataloging.
Once your data enters environment,
it must be class classified using
AI or ML models and any of the
predefined business intelligence
models that your organization has.
Keep those engines ready so that the.
AI or the models or algorithms
do the heavy lifting, right?
Humans can't keep up with the scale.
That's the reason we have to use
this ML and AI models to make sure
that the classification is done.
Catalogs are defined and the
policy governance policy is
applied at each and every stage.
Classification should be continuous.
Layer three or stage three,
access, control and ownership.
You need to understand from
an organizational perspective,
who owns your data.
If you are coming up with multiple answers
for this question, then there's no clear
ownership defined in your organization.
So in most of the organizations that
I work with, data steward, data owner,
domain owner, and platform team, these
are the different divisions of data have
their ownership for different departments.
Also, data should not
be accessed by everyone.
You have to apply some access controls,
which are role-based access controls
for the data sets that you define,
or the data pipelines that you define
Without ownership, governance fails.
I wanna spend some time
on this particular slide.
It's a deep dive on tiered storage,
architecture, and dynamic allocation.
This framework I've come up with
in when I was starting my career,
and I wanted to make sure that I
understand my data because when I
see the data, it tells me a story.
I, and I believe all
the data is not equal.
You have different tiers, which
I'm defining here right now.
My first one is Archive Tire.
It's a long-term immutable storage
with cryptographic audit trails.
This is one of the most secure
data that I'm talking about.
Let's talk about social security.
Let's talk about other, in India.
Those are the long term immutable storage
data, core tier, infrequently access
data with automated lifecycle policies.
It this happens to be rate data, but you
need to make sure that competence has
been defined for these tier data as well.
Warm tier.
Operational data supporting
scheduled bi loads and with balanced
cost and across latency controls.
It is occasional operational data.
For example, if one of the operations
failed during an emergency event
in utility space, you need to have
operational data tier is that, is
supporting your workloads to make
sure that the prediction happens.
Correctly or accurately.
And the most important and the
biggest of all, is hot tier data.
It's an active AI or data pipeline
load with low latency access.
That means it's for daily use.
Take example of a EM as advanced database,
advanced data management system, which
is used by almost all the utilities
across the country in the United States.
I feel that both strict RAC and
real-time monitoring rules for this data
because it is hot data and this is one
of the most important components for
utilities to come up with or predict
the next outage or any planned outage
or any failures that are going to
happen in the system, it's gonna catch.
AI role, AI enhanced validation
and anomaly detection.
Traditional rule-based data quality
checks cannot detect any schema
drift any variations that are using
in the data on a daily basis and
any behavioral change in data.
So to do the heavy lifting, most
of the organizations use machine
learning or AI models to be able
to do the heavy lifting for that.
One of the most important and
key things for organization is to
have self-organizing frameworks
for the defined data pipelines.
That means you have to make sure that.
The four layers that I just talked
about should have observability
defined at each layer so that you
can remediate, you can automatically
prepare for any issues and any feedback
that comes from the data that has been
flowing through the data pipeline.
Okay.
Let's take a minute here.
Defining safeguards, automated
retention and auditable deletion.
Deletion comes into play when
the governance is tested.
You have to have retention
policies by design itself.
So when AI does the data classification
for you, make sure that the data
tier that I talked about have,
compliance flags define, so
that means you are incorporating
the policy at the design stage.
Data should exist in multiple places,
and it does exist in multiple places.
Can you prove it's gone?
I'm not sure you should have
auditability defined in each of layers
or the faces that I talked about.
To make sure that the retention
policies are taken care of and at
the same time, any data that is
deleted or kept should be auditable,
which is, I think my last statement.
You can see automated retention and
dele deletion mechanisms accelerate
regulatory response times and reduce
the manual burden on governance and
compliance teams a key operational.
Gain in large scale
multi-cloud environments.
That's really important.
Till now we have talked about
implementation or the blueprint itself.
Now let's talk, take a deep dive
into the implementation itself.
What are the phases that
my research paper talks about?
Phase one is foundation.
Phase two is ingestion and access.
Phase three is intelligence
layer, which is ai, and phase
four is lifecycle automation.
How do we automate one,
two, and three phases?
I wanna stress one important
distinction right in the phase is
that do not do everything at once.
Stage it.
Make sure that in the foundation
phase, make sure that the
ownership is taken care of.
Meta data is defined, and classification
taxonomy is being defined because
in the third phase, you're
talking about AI classification.
How does AI classify it without
having any rules applied to it?
So you have to make sure that the rules
are all defined on the foundational
layer to make sure that the other phases.
Work in line, and it's been synchronized.
Phase two is ingestion and access.
Implement secure ingestion practices.
Make sure that chemo drift, any data
changes, any attributes that are going
to be added in the next ingestion
phase are to be taken care of.
Phase three is intelligence, which
is which you all know AI and MO.
Make sure that your AI and ML models
are secure and have incorporated all
the foundational layer rules that
are defined and does the job for you.
Phase four is automation.
You have to automate your basis
depending upon the tier data.
All the retention and auditable policies
have been applied at each and every stage.
Governance is a maturity.
It comes with implementation of governance
right from the beginning at the gate.
You prac, you practice making a
habit of doing this at the very
beginning so that you don't have to
worry about after the deployment.
Governance maturity is built,
not acquired after deployment.
Cross cloud consistency.
I've been stressing about this since
the very beginning of my presentation.
Multi-cloud and cross cloud,
multi-cloud is having a GCP Cloud,
Google platform, Google Cloud platform,
Microsoft Azure and AWS Cross Cloud is.
Multi-cloud plus different types of
architect cloud architecture, meaning
it can be a private cloud, it can be a
hybrid cloud, or it can be a public cloud.
So make sure that all the policies
that are you're trying to define as
part of this governance blueprint
is defined at the code level.
Have a unified platform for
auditing and a one stop shop catalog
for cross cloud environments.
Okay.
Last but not least, I wanna talk about
few key learnings from my experience.
Cloud environments is the future with AI
incorporated in each and every phase of
the data lifecycle that I talked about.
It's not a project.
I feel governance blueprint or
governance process incorporated in
each and every layer is a discipline.
It's an engineering discipline.
Embed it in each of the process.
Don't overlay it.
You don't earn trust from ai.
You need to make sure the principles
are defined with the foundational
layer, so that the thrust is end.
In each of the phase, fill the deployment
and make sure that you
you face your delivery.
Do an incremental start with
ownership, classification, add
intelligence, and then automation.
Don't do it all at once.
Thank you everyone for
listening to my presentation.
I hope I made it engaging for you.
Because I don't want to talk
through the slides to read all
the paragraphs or sentences.
I just wanna make sure that you
understand my experience and what
are the problems that I'm trying to
define and the probable solutions.
Thank you so much.
I.