Hello, everyone.
I am thrilled you are here as I present my
defense on using microservices in the ever
evolving world of software architecture.
Microservices have been
both celebrated in question.
In this presentation, I will discuss the
benefits of microservices, address common
critiques, and explore how they can be
effectively adapted in your organization.
if they even make sense for your needs.
But before we proceed, let's examine how
microservices meteoric rise turned into a
journey through scrutiny and skepticism.
We kick off the journey by diving into
what I like to call the era of hype.
Spanning from about, 2014 to 2018.
During this time, microservices
were not just a new architectural
style, they were a revolution.
The tech world was
buzzing with excitement.
Microservices were hailed as the
silver bullet that would solve
all our software development woes.
Every conference agenda was packed
with talks on microservices.
Tech blogs and industry magazines
featured headline after headline.
Things like microservices, the future
of software architecture, why monoliths
are a thing of the past, and unlock
unlimited scalability with microservices.
The promise was alluring.
Break down your bulky, monolithic
applications into small, independent
services that could be developed,
deployed, and scaled autonomously.
It was like going from steering a
cumbersome cruise ship to piloting
a fleet of agile speedboats.
Companies like Netflix and Amazon
were poster children of this movement.
They share compelling success stories
about how microservices enable
them to innovate rapidly, deploy
hundreds of times a day, and scale
effortlessly to meet global demand.
Developers and architects worldwide
were eager to jump on the bandwagon.
The idea that we could overcome
the limitations of monolithic
architectures was exhilarating.
It felt like we had finally found the
key to unlocking unlimited agility and
efficiency in software development.
Microsoft Mechanics I attended conferences
where speakers passionately declared that
microservices were not just an option.
They were a necessity for any organization
that wanted to stay competitive.
Phrases like infinitely scalable,
highly resilient, and built for the
cloud era were the mantra of the day.
Adopting microservices became
a sort of badge of honor.
Organizations proudly announced
their transition plans.
Job postings saw engineers
with microservices expertise
as a top requirement.
It was as if not embracing microservices
meant being left behind in the
annals of outdated technology.
But amidst this excitement,
there was often little discussion
about the challenges that might
come from such a transformation.
The focus was squarely on potential
benefits, with less attention paid
to the complexities of distributed
systems, data management across
services, or the operational overhead.
It was a time of unbridled optimism.
The industry was caught up in a
whirlwind of innovation, eager to
discard the old and embrace the new.
Now, before I continue further,
let me confess that I was a skeptic
during the first part of this time.
I remember 2016, sitting in a
job interview, being asked about
my thoughts on microservices.
Now, having extensive experience
with service oriented architecture
and large enterprises, I confidently
said, I think they're overhyped and
this enthusiasm will fade very soon.
needless to say, I did not get that job.
Ironically, in my next role, I found
myself implementing microservices because
they were perfect for the project at hand.
Since then, I have built several
microservice based solutions.
Through these experiences, I
quickly realized that microservices
hold a incredible promises.
But they also introduced
significant complexities.
And it wasn't just me.
Many organizations began
sharing similar insights.
This brings us to the next
chapter of our journey.
How the initial excitement
gave way to rising skepticism.
As the industry grappled with the
practical realities of microservices.
As the initial excitement around
microservices began to settle, a new
phase emerged, this rising skeptic phase.
Expanding from about 2018 to 2022.
Now here, organizations
had eagerly jumped.
on microservices, on the
microservices bandwagon.
But they started to face
unexpected challenges.
The promise of infinite scalability
and seamless deployments were met
with the realities of increased
complexity and operational overhead.
Implementing microservices was not as
straightforward as many had thought.
There was issues such as
distributed, distributed systems.
Inter service communication issues
and data consistency problems.
Developers found themselves spending
more time on managing infrastructures
and debugging complex issues
rather than building new features.
The microservice architecture introduced
a myriad of new components service
registers, API gateways, load balancers
that required expertise and maintenance.
Moreover, the operational
cost began to rise.
Running multiple services meant
increased resource consumption, from
computing power to monitoring tools.
The simplicity of deploying a monolith
gave way to the intricacies of deploying
and orchestrating numerous services.
Organizations started to question
whether the benefits outweighed the cost.
Was the shift to microservices
delivering on its promises?
Or had we underestimated the challenges
inherent in such a transformation?
Prominent voices in the tech community
began expressing their concerns.
Articles with titles like, the
microservice trade off, monoliths
strike back, and the hidden cost
of microservices started appearing.
Renowned software architects
shared their experiences, pointing
out that microservices were not
a one size fits all solution.
They emphasized that without proper
planning and deep understanding of
the domain, microservices could lead
to more problems than they solve.
Some common critiques include,
breaking down applications into many
services was causing unnecessary
complexities and over engineering.
Increased, network calls leading
to performance bottlenecks.
Ensuring data consistency across services
became a significant challenge and
caused data management difficulties.
And end to end testing was complex
due to numerous independent services.
The initial enthusiasm was
giving way to prudence.
Teams realized that microservices
demanded a cultural shift,
not just a technical one.
It required cross functional teams,
developed DevOps practices, and a strong
emphasis on automation and monitoring.
Many began to ask, was adopting
microservices the right
choice for our organization?
And do we have the necessary
infrastructure and expertise
to manage this complexity?
This period of rising skepticism
wasn't necessarily negative.
Instead, it represented a
maturation in the industry's
understanding of microservices.
We moved from seeing them as a silver
bullet to recognizing them as a powerful
tool that requires careful consideration.
It was time for reflection and
recalibration to assess when and how
to use microservices effectively.
Continuing our journey, we strive against
the phase that I refer to as losing faith.
Spanning the last couple of years,
during this past, during this period,
the skepticism that had been rising
began to solidify into outright
doubt, for many organizations.
The challenges and complexities
encountered led some to question whether
microservices were the right path at all.
We were hearing about organizations
that had initially invested heavily
in microservices began to reassess
their architectural choices.
For some, the operational burdens,
talent shortages, and unrealized
benefits led to decisions to scale
back or even abandon microservices
in favor of alternate architecture.
Architectures.
Articles and thought piece, pieces
emerged with titles like it's
time to abandon microservices.
The microservice retrospective.
Was it worth it?
And embracing the model
of the modular monolith.
Prominent tech leaders voiced
their concerns more openly.
They highlighted cases where microservices
had led to project delays, increased
costs, and performance issues.
The complexity of microservices
required specialized expertise
that was hard to find.
The industry began to acknowledge
that microservices were not
a one size fits all solution.
Without the right tools, culture, and
resources, microservices could become
more of a hindrance than a help.
Common reasons for losing faith
included overwhelming complexity due
to sheer number of services being lost.
unmanageable.
Teams lacked the necessary
experience in DevOps, distributed
systems, and cloud infrastructure.
Existing tools did not adequately
support microservice needs, and
organization structures were not
adapted for independent services
development and deployment.
In some cases, organizations made
the difficult decision to revert
to monolithic architecture or
adapt a modular monolith approach.
They sought to regain control over
their systems, reduce complexity, and
focus on delivering business value.
This period is marked by a
sense of disillusionment.
The lofty expectations set during the era
of hype had not been met for everyone.
The pendulum has swung
from excitement to fear.
to skepticism.
And now for some to abandon it.
Now, having traversed the highs of the
hype and the lows of the skepticism and
the challenges that led some to lose
faith, we now stand at the brink of a
new era, the era of intelligent maturity.
This phase is about leveraging
experiences, embracing best practices,
and implementing microservices
where they make the most sense.
It is a time to use microservices,
but use them wisely.
And only when they actually make sense.
Advancements in tooling, the improved
orchestration platforms, enhanced
monitoring solutions, and robust
security practices are contributing
to smoother microservice operations.
Importantly, there is a deeper
understanding of when and how to
use microservices effectively.
Organizations recognize that
microservices are not a universal
solution, but a powerful option
when applied to the right problems.
This era represents a time of
mastery and innovation where
microservices are unleashing the
power that they have been promising.
But as we move forward, organizations
are poised to harness this full
potential microservices, driving
unprecedented innovation and
delivering exceptional value.
Now that we explored the evolution of
microservices, let's shift our focus on
how we can apply these lessons to maximize
their benefits, for our organizations.
Here's what we're going to cover
during the rest of this presentation.
We'll begin by comparing various
architectural styles, including
monoliths, interior architectures,
modular monoliths, and microservices,
to understand their strengths,
weaknesses, and ideal use cases.
With that context, we'll cover the
core benefits of microservices,
and why they are a compelling
choice for modern applications.
Following that, we'll candidly discuss
Common critiques and challenges
associated with microservices,
providing a balanced perspective.
Afterward, we'll explore practical
strategies and best practices to
overcome these challenges and ensure you
can adopt microservices successfully.
Then I reflect back on the four primary
architectural styles I introduced in
comparing architectural styles to provide
guidance on, on how to pick the right
architectural style for your next project.
Finally, I will wrap up with key
takeaways and consider how you
can apply these insights to your
own organization moving forward.
By the end of this session, you will
not only understand why microservices
still matter, but also gain practical
insights on how to leverage them
effectively, alongside other architectural
options in your own organization.
Hey, wait a second.
We've been chatting all this
chat about microservices, and I
still haven't introduced myself.
My name is Chad Green.
I'm the Senior System Architect
with 35 years experience in software
development and architecture.
throughout my career, I have had
the pleasure of working with a
variety of technologies, but my true
passion lie in microservices, event
driven architectures, serverless
computing, and API first designs.
I have helped organizations from
nimble startups to global enterprises
navigate the complexities of modern
software architecture, enabling
them to build scalable, resilient
systems that drive innovation.
Outside of work, you'll often find
me in my Lego room building intricate
Lego sets or updating my Lego city.
I find it gives me a fresh perspective
to my professional life and lets
me step away from thinking about
complicated software architectures.
Feel free to connect with
me after the presentation.
I would love to hear your thoughts or
answer any questions you might have.
Now that you know a little bit about me,
let's jump back into our exploration.
And to truly appreciate the advantages
of microservices, it's essential
to understand how they compare
to other architectural styles.
So let's begin by comparing
architectural styles.
But before, let's talk about what
we're talking about when we mean
architectural styles in the context
of software architecture development.
An architectural style is essentially
a blueprint, a set of principles
and patterns that guide how we
structure our software systems.
It shapes how components interact,
how data flows, and how the system
scales and evolves over time.
Choosing the right architectural
style is crucial because it
influences several key aspects.
How well can the system
handle increased load?
How easily can the system
be updated or modified?
How effectively can your
team develop and deploy code?
It impacts everything from
development speed to systems ability
to adapt to future requirements.
In our discussions today, we'll be
exploring four prominent architectural
styles, monoliths, n tier architectures,
microservices, and modular monoliths.
By understanding the strength and
weakness of each, we'll better, we will
be better equipped to make informed
decisions about which style aligns best
with our organizational needs and goals.
First up, we have the classic
monolithic architecture.
A monolith is essentially a single
unified application where all the
components are interconnected and
interdependent within one code base.
Let's talk about the
advantages with this approach.
Monoliths are often simpler to
develop and deploy, especially
for small teams or projects.
Internal calls within the application are
faster than calls over a network, server.
over a network between services.
With all the code in one place, it
is straightforward to trace through
the code and find and fix issues.
However, monoliths come
with significant challenges.
Scaling a monolith means replicating
the entire application, even if only
one part needs additional resources.
A small change requires reapplying the
entire application, which can slow down
the release cycle and increase risk.
As code base, as your code base grows,
it becomes more complex and harder for
developers to understand and modify.
And making significant changes
or adapting new technologies can
lead, can be challenging without
affecting the entire system.
Think of a monolith as
a big block of marble.
It's solid and sturdy, but if you need to
change, if you need to make a change, you
have to chisel away at the whole block,
which can be time consuming and risky.
Monolithic architectures can work
well for small applications or when
you need to go to market quickly.
However, as your application
and team grows, the monolith
can become a bottleneck, slowing
down development and deployment.
Understanding the monolith strengths and
weaknesses help us appreciate why other
architectural styles, like microservices,
have emerged to address these challenges.
Next, let's explore n tier architecture,
also known as layered architecture.
In an n tier architecture, the application
is divided into logical layers or tiers,
each with distinct responsibilities.
Typically, layers like the presentation
layer handling the user interface.
The business logic layer, where
the core functionality resides.
And the data access layer,
managing transactions, or
interactions, with the database.
This separation brings several advantages.
Each layer is focused on a
specific task, making the system
more organized and maintainable.
Layers can be reused across different
applications, saving development
time, saving development time.
Teams can specialize in individual layers,
improving efficiency and expertise.
However, n tier architectures
also present some challenges.
Layers are often closely connected, so
changes in one layer can impact others.
Making the system less flexible.
Scalability typically happens
at the application level, not
at the individual layer level.
Limiting the scalability options.
And data likely is passing through
multiple layers, which can introduce
latency and affect performance.
You can think of NT architecture
like a layered cake.
Each layer depends on
one, on the one below it.
And together, they create the whole cake.
What?
If there's an issue within one
layer, it can affect the entire cake.
N tier architecture often offers
more structure than a monolith,
bringing organization and clarity.
However, it can still face challenges
with scalability and agility,
especially in the environments
where requirements change rapidly.
Understanding NTR architecture
helps us see how software design
evolved to address the limitations
of monoliths, leading us closer to
architectures like microservices.
Now.
Let's dive into microservices,
the architectural style, at
the heart of our discussion.
In a microservice architecture, an
application is composed of a collection
of small, independent services.
Each service focuses on a
specific, business capability
and operates autonomously.
These services communicate over well
defined APIs, often using protocols like
HTTP, REST, gRPC, or messaging systems.
Let's explore the
advantages of microservices.
Now, each service can
be scaled independently.
If a particular service experiences high
load, you can allocate more resources to
it without scaling the entire application.
Teams have the freedom to choose
the most scalable technology or
programming language for their language.
Services can be updated, deployed,
and rolled back individually,
which accelerates development
cycles and reduces risk.
And if one service fails, it doesn't
necessarily bring down the entire system.
This improves overall system resilience.
Of course, now, there are some challenges.
To include, managing numerous
services requires a sophisticated
infrastructure and robust DevOps
practices, including containerization,
orchestration, and monitoring.
Dealing with network latency,
load balancing, and service
discovery adds complexity.
Inter service communication can fail
due to network issues, requiring
strategies for retries and fallbacks.
Ensuring consistency across networks.
Services is complex.
Transactions that span multiple
services are harder to implement,
often requiring eventual consistency
and compensatory mechanisms.
And testing individual services
is straightforward, but end to end
testing becomes more complicated due
to the interactions between services.
You can think of microservices
as a fleet of small boats
instead of a single large ship.
Each boat operates independently
and can navigate its own path.
This provides greater
flexibility and agility.
But coordinating the fleet requires
effort and sophisticated communication.
Microservices are powerful for
large, complex applications that
need to scale and evolve rapidly.
They enable organizations
to innovate faster and adapt
to changing business needs.
However, they demand a mature
organizational culture and
technical infrastructure, including
automation, continuous integration
and deployment, such as CICD,
and comprehensive monitoring.
Understanding both the benefits
and challenges of microservices is
crucial to making informed decisions
about whether the architectural
style fits your organization's needs.
Now finally, let's explore modular
monoliths, an architectural style
that offers a middle ground between
monoliths and microservices.
In a monolithic monolith, in a
modular monolith, We have a single
application that is divided into
distinct independent modules.
Each module encapsulates specific
functionality and maintains
strict boundaries, communicating
internally within the application.
So advantages?
first off, clear module boundaries
make the code base easier
to understand and maintain.
Developers can focus on
specific modules without wading
through the entire code base.
Since all modules run within
the same application process,
intermodular communication is
fast, avoiding the network latency
associated with microservices.
You deploy a single application, which
simplifies the deployment process compared
to managing numerous microservices.
And a modular monolith can serve as a
stepping stone, towards microservices.
If needed, modules can be
extracted into services over time.
Of course, there are
challenges to consider.
Scaling is still done at
the application level.
If one module requires more resources,
you have to scale the entire application.
Changes in one module
necessitate redeploying the whole
application, which can impact
deployment, frequency, and risk.
Without strict discipline, module
boundaries can erode over time, leading
to tight coupling between modules.
And a failure in one module can
still affect the entire application,
since all modules share the same
processes, same process space.
So we can think of a module monolith
like a well organized toolbox.
Everything, is in one place, but each
tool or module has its own compartment.
it's organized and efficient,
but you have to still, you still
have to carry the entire toolbox.
Even if you only need one tool, modular
monoliths offer a balanced approach.
They, They bring structure and
organization to your code base without
the operational overhead of microservices.
For many applications, especially those
not requiring extreme scalability or
independent scaling of components,
a modular monolith can provide the
necessary flexibility and maintainability.
Understanding modular monoliths
helps us see that there's more
than one way to achieve separation
of concerns and scalability.
The best architectural choice depends on
your project's specific context and needs.
Having explored the spectrum of
architectural styles, from the simplicity
of monoliths to the organization
of interior architectures, the
flexibility of microservices, and the
balance of modular monoliths, you've
gained a comprehensive understanding
Of their strengths and challenges.
Each style offers a unique advantage,
but as we have seen, they also come
with their own set of trade offs.
This begs the question, what makes
microservices stand out as a compelling
choice for modern applications?
Now let's dive into the core
benefits of microservices and
understand why this architectural
style has become a cornerstone
for modern scalable applications.
We'll explore how microservices
can transform the way we build,
deploy, and manage software, offering
unparalleled advantages in scalability,
flexibility, and resilience.
By the end of this section, you will see
how microservices address the challenges
we have discussed and why they are a
powerful tool in the Architects Toolkit.
One of the most significant benefits
of microservices is scalability.
In a microservice architecture,
each service is a separate component
that can be scaled independently
based upon its specific demands.
This means if one service experiences
increased load, say, like the payment
processing service during holiday,
shopping rush, we can allocate more
resources to just that service without
scaling the entire application.
This approach optimizes resource
utilization and cost, ensuring that
we're not over provisioning resources
for services that don't need them.
Additionally, microservices
support elasticity.
With modern cloud, platforms
and orchestration tools like
Kubernetes, Kubernetes services
can be scaled automatically in
response to traffic patterns.
This approach allows applications to
handle varying workloads seamlessly,
scaling up during peak demands,
or scaling up during peak times
and down during lulls, which is
both, efficient and cost effective.
To illustrate, consider an e commerce
platform during Black Friday.
The product catalog and checkout services
can scale out to meet the surge in demand,
ensuring smooth user experiences without
overtaxing the other parts of the system.
In essence, microservices enable
us to build applications that are
flexible and responsive, capable
of growing with our user base
and adapting to changing demands.
Another crucial benefit of
microservices is fault tolerance.
With microservices, applications are
composed of multiple independent services.
This service isolation means that if one
service fails, it doesn't necessarily
bring down the entire application.
For example, if the recommendation
service on a streaming platform
encounters an issue, users can
still browse and watch content.
The failure is contained.
This isolation reduces the risk of
systematic failures and enhances
overall system scalability, leading
to more resilient applications.
To further strengthen fault tolerance, we
implement various resilience strategies.
These include retry policies to handle
transient errors, circuit breakers to
prevent repeated attempts to failing
services, and fallback mechanisms
to provide default responses.
We also use timeouts to prevent services
from waiting indefinitely for a response.
A design for graceful degradation.
Ensuring the applications can continue
to function in a limited capacity
if certain services are unavailable.
By incorporating these strategies,
microservices can withstand the
failures and continue to provide
essential functionality to users.
This fault tolerance is essential
for applications where uptime
and reliability are critical.
Next, let's explore how microservices
enable Independent deployments, a game
changer for modern development practices.
In a microservice architecture, each
service is a separate deployable unit.
This means teams can update and
deploy their services independently
without needing to coordinate with
other teams or wait for a synchronized
release for the entire application.
This capability leads to
faster release cycles, updates.
rather, whether they're for new
features or bug fixes can be
delivered to users more quickly,
providing a comprehensive advantage
and improving customer satisfaction.
Moreover, reduced deployment
risk is a significant benefit.
Deploying smaller incremental
changes lower the likelihood of
introducing system wide issues.
If there's a problem with a deployment,
it's easier to roll back and fix.
without impacting the entire application.
Additionally, microservices
offer flexibility in scheduling.
Teams can deploy when they are ready.
aligning releases with business
priorities and market demands.
Without being tied to lengthy release
cycles or waiting for other teams
to complete their work by enabling
independent deployments, microservices
support more agile and responsive
deployments practices, aligning
perfectly with modern day DevOps
and continuous delivery approaches.
Another core benefit of microservices is
team autonomy, empowering teams to work
effectively, efficiently and innovatively.
In a microservices architecture,
we organize around autonomous
cross functional teams.
Each team owns the entire life cycle
of their service, from development
and testing to deployment operations.
This ownership encourages
accountability and fosters a strong
sense of pride and responsibility.
This structure enables
parallel development.
Multiple teams can work
on different systems.
or different services at the same time
without stepping on each other's toes.
This concurrency accelerates
development and fosters innovation
as teams can progress independently.
Additionally, microservices can
facilitate faster decision making.
Teams can make techno technology and
implementation choices that best fit
their services need without waiting
for the company wide consensus or being
constrained by a single technology stack.
By promoting team autonomy,
microservices reduce dependencies
and bottlenecks between teams,
leading to increased productivity
and a more agile organization.
This empowerment not only accelerates
development, but also enhances
team morale and job satisfaction.
Now let's explore how microservices
offer flexibility in technology choices,
empowering teams to select the best tools
and technologies for their specific needs.
First off, microservices
enable polyglot programming.
Since each microservice is a
separate entity, teams can choose
to, the most appropriate technology
stack by pro, by it, be it
programming languages, frameworks,
or databases for their service.
This means that one service might be
written in Java, another in Python,
and js, each optimized for its purpose.
This flexibility allows
teams to leverage strengths.
of different technologies, optimizing
performance and efficiency for
each service's unique requirements.
Second, microservices in, foster
innovation and experimentation.
Teams are encouraged to adapt,
to new and emerging technologies.
Where they make the most sense,
experimenting without risking the
stability of the entire system.
This facilitates continuous innovation
as teams can implement cutting edge
solutions in their services, driving the
overall advancements of the application.
Third, microservices
reduce technology lock in.
By avoiding a monolithic technology
stack for the entire application,
organizations minimize dependencies on
a single technology vendor or platform.
It is easier to replace or upgrade
individual services as technologies
evolve, enhancing the system's
longevity and adaptability.
This means your applications can stay
current with technological advances
without requiring a complete overhaul.
Overall, the flexibility in technology
choices provided by microservices
not only optimizes each services,
each service, but also empowers
teams to innovate and adapt swiftly
in the ever changing tech landscape.
Finally, for now, let's, we have
how microservices enable alignment
with business goals, enhancing
organizational agility and effectiveness.
First, microservices support organization,
organizing around business capabilities.
In this model, each microservice
is designed to handle a specific
business function or domain.
For example, in an e commerce
platform, separate services might
handle inventory management, payment
processing, and customer reviews.
By structuring services this way,
we can enhance collaboration between
development teams and business units.
Teams have a clear understanding of
their, of how their work directly supports
business objectives, fostering a more
integrated and purpose driven approach.
Next, we have autonomous
cross functional teams.
These teams comprise of the necessary
skills developers, of developers,
testers, operations, to develop and
operate their service end to end.
This promotes ownership and
accountability, as teams are fully
responsible for their services success
from conception to deployment and beyond.
This structure improves
responsiveness to business needs.
Teams can quickly implement changes or
features in their services, aligning
development closely with business
priorities and customer feedback.
Finally, microservices
enhances business agility.
By aligning organizations and teams
with businesses, Business capabilities.
Organizations can accelerate the
delivery of new features that are
more impactful to the business.
Microservices enable rapid
adoption to market changes.
If a new organization or new opportunity
arises or a competitor introduces a
feature, teams can respond swiftly
without being hindered by the
complexities of a monolithic system.
The agility, reduces time to market
for innovations, giving organizations
a competitive edge and ability to meet
customer expectations more effectively.
In essence, microservice bridge the
gap between technology and businesses.
Encourage ensuring that
the technological efforts.
Are directly contributing to business
goals and enabling organizations to
thrive in a dynamic market environment.
So as we have explored, the core benefits
of microservices are scalability, fault
tolerance, independent deployments,
team autonomy, flexibility in technology
choices and alignment with business goals.
We have showcased their
transformative potential.
These advantages enable organizations to
build resilient, agile, and innovative
systems that can adapt to changing
demands and drive business successes.
However, like any architectural
style, microservices come with
their own set of challenges.
It's important to acknowledge that while
the rewards can be substantial, the
journey isn't always straightforward.
In this next section, I'm going
to address several of the common
critiques of microservices.
While there are many critiques,
in the interest of time, I'm going
to focus on the top five that
most organizations encounter.
As we look into these critiques,
you'll notice common themes that
highlight the inherent complexities
of implementing microservices.
These critiques resonate strongly with
me because I have seen how overlooking
these challenges can lead to unsuccessful
microservice implementations.
By understanding these challenges up
front, you will be better equipped
to determine if microservices
align with your architectural
needs and organizational readiness.
Maybe there's too much
complexity in the implementation.
To make it, feel worth the effort.
Ultimately, by understanding
these challenges, you'll be
better prepared to navigate the
journey and reap the substantial
rewards of Microsoft can offer.
Much like a journey through
uncharted territory.
Microservices offer a great reward,
but also present obstacles that
must be navigated carefully.
microservices increases
operational overhead.
There is the added complexity in
deployment, monitoring, and maintenance
compared to monolithic architecture.
first off, the critiques
are very much correct.
Microservices do add
operational complexity.
This complexity stems from the need
to orchestrate Multiple services,
each potentially with his own set of
dependencies and resource requirements.
It requires robust infrastructure
and tooling to handle aspects like
service discovery, load balancing,
scaling and fault tolerance.
To adjust these challenges, various
approaches and tools are available
across different cloud platforms.
For container organization,
Kubernetes is the way to go.
It's a powerful platform that can
handle large scale deployments and
offers extensive customization.
Services like Azure Kubernetes
Service, better known as AKS.
Amazon Elastic Kubernetes
Service, better known as EKS.
And Google Kubernetes Service,
sometimes known as GKE, provides managed
Kubernetes clusters in the cloud.
These services offer managed Kubernetes
environments for deploying and
scaling containerized applications.
For monitoring and logging, tools
like Prometheus, which excels at
metrics collection, and the Elk Stack.
which includes Elasticsearch,
Logstash, and Kibana are ideal for
logging, aggregation, and analysis.
They offer robust solutions to tracking
performance metrics and analyzing
logs across multiple services.
However, in my experience, especially
when working with organizations
that have standardized Microsoft
technologies and Azure services, or
the other clouds and their compatible
technologies, I have found that
leveraging native tools provided
by the cloud platforms can greatly
simplify organizational complexity.
Instead of managing kubernetes
clusters ourselves, we have
utilized Azure Container Apps, a
serverless container hosting service.
It abstracts away the underlying
infrastructure, allowing us to deploy and
run containerized applications without the
overhead of managing Kubernetes directly.
This approach, reduces operational
burden as Azure handles the
orchestration, scaling, and maintenance
of the underlying resources.
It lets us focus on developing
our services rather than
managing infrastructure.
Similarly, services like AWS Fargate
and Google Cloud Run offer serverless
container platforms providing similar
benefits on their respective platforms.
Additionally, we have turned to
serverless offerings like Azure
Functions, AWS Lambdas, and Google
Cloud Functions to enable us to run
code in response to events without
provisioning or managing servers.
This approach abstracts away much of
the infrastructure management, allowing
development teams to focus on writing
code that delivers business value.
Azure Functions allow us to deploy
individual functions that can
scale independently and respond to
specific triggers, making them ideal
for event driven architectures.
For monitoring logging, I have found that
Azure Monitor with Application Insights
and Log Analytic Workspaces provide
comprehensive insights into the health
and performance of our applications.
This tight integration within the Azure
ecosystem simplifies setup and management.
Other cloud providers offer similar
integration tools, such as AWS CloudWatch
and Google's Cloud Operations Suite.
other, I'm sorry, automation
and CD pipelines are essential
across all platforms to manage
operational complexity, effectively.
Tools like Azure DevOps and GitHub Actions
have been invaluable in automating our
build, test, and deployment processes.
Likewise, AWS CodePipeline and Google
Cloud Build provide robust CICD
capabilities on their platforms.
By leveraging these serverless
offerings, monitoring tools, and
automation platforms, have been able
to mitigate much of the operational
complexity associated with microservices.
In conclusion, while microservices
introduce operational complexity,
selecting the right tools and platforms
can align with your organizational
needs, and, simplify management,
enabling you to fully leverage
the benefits of microservices.
So whether you're using Azure, AWS,
GCP, or another platform, it's important
to evaluate the services they offer.
Like serverless functions, container
platforms and logging solutions to reduce
overhead and streamline operations.
Another significant, critique
of microservices revolve
around the challenges inherent
in distributed systems.
Breaking an application into multiple
services introduces complexity
in how these services communicate
and maintain data consistency.
Firstly, let's discuss network,
the network complexity.
Some of the issues we have, have
within microservices include
handling network latency and
ensuring reliable communication.
between, services can be complex.
Inner service communication adds
overhead, and network issues
can lead to unexpected failures.
We also need to manage load
balancing to distribute requests
effectively across instances.
Secondly, there is the issue
of data consistency to include.
Ensuring data integrity across multiple
services is more challenging than with
than with, than within a monolith.
Managing transactions in a distributed
environment can be difficult, as
traditional ACID transactions do
not easily extend across services.
This can lead to data anomalies and
conflicts if not properly handled.
To address these challenges, there
are several strategies we can employ.
One effective approach is to is
using asynchronous communication.
By leveraging messaging queues and
adopting event driven architecture,
we can decouple services.
This reduces dependency on the
immediate availability of other
services, improving resilience.
Services communicate by sending and
receiving messages asynchronously,
which can help us manage network
latency and improve fault tolerance.
In my experience, focusing on
serverless and event driven design,
such as Azure Functions and Azure
Service Bus, provide a robust way to
implement asynchronous communication.
These services enable us to build
reactive systems that respond to
events that as they occur without
tight coupling between services.
Implementing retry policies and
circuit breakers is also crucial.
Retry policies allow services
to handle transient failures by
retrying operations after a delay.
Circuit breakers help prevent
cascading failures by stopping,
attempts to communicate.
with a failed service
after repeated failures.
These patterns improve system
scalability and resilience.
Adopting eventual consistency
models is another strategy.
In distributed systems, it is
often acceptable for data to be
temporarily inconsistent to achieve
better scalability performance.
Implementing patterns like event
sourcing and CQRS, or Command Query
Responsibility Segregation, can help you
manage data consistency across services.
These patterns allow services
to update independently and
synchronize changes asynchronously.
However, it's important to recognize
that while these strategies mitigate
certain challenges, they can
introduce additional complexity.
For example, event driven architecture
can make it harder to trace the
flow of data and understand the
system's state at any given time.
Balancing consistency, availability,
and scalability requires careful
architectural consideration and deep
understanding of the trade offs involved.
Some organizations use service meshes
to manage inter service communication,
providing features like traffic management
and, security and observability.
While these services meshes
can be powerful, they also add
another layer of complexity.
In my work, I have found that for many
applications, especially those leveraging
serverless and event driven architectures,
a service mesh might not be necessary.
Instead, focusing on designing for
asynchronous communication and using
managed services can simplify the system.
Ultimately, addressing distributed
systems Challenges in microservices
requires thoughtful design and the
right set of tools and patterns.
By implementing strategies like
asynchronous communication, retry
policies, and eventual consistency,
we can build systems that are robust,
scalable, and capable of handling the
complexities of a distributed environment.
Next, we'll explore another common
critique, data management and consistency.
Diving deeper into how we manage, how we
handle data across distributed services.
And in microservice based systems, data
is often spread across multiple services,
each with its own database or data store.
This leads to complexities that are
not present in a monolithic system.
First, ensuring the data consistency
across services is more complex.
Managing transactions that span across
multiple services isn't straightforward.
Traditional asset transactions do not
extend easily in a distributed system.
This can lead to difficulties in
maintaining a single source of truth.
Data may reside in multiple
places, and keeping it synchronized
requires careful planning.
Organizations often struggle with the
idea In a microservice architecture,
data will be in multiple locations, and
that's okay with the right practices.
Understanding and embracing
this reality is essential.
how do we address these challenges?
One key strategy is embracing
eventual consistency.
Except that data might not be instantly
consistent across all services.
Design systems to handle temporary
inconsistencies gracefully.
Recognize that eventual consistency can be
a strength and not necessarily a weakness.
By accepting that data will become
consistent over time, we can build
more scalable and robust systems.
This requires a shift in mindset,
but opens up new possibilities
for performance and resilience.
Next, we can implement specific
patterns to manage distributed
interactions and data consistency.
The Saga pattern is one such approach.
It manages distributed transactions
by breaking them into a
series of local transactions.
Each service plat, performs its local
transaction and then pushes an event
or message to trigger the next action.
If a failure occurs, compensating
transactions are to undo the
changes made by previous services.
This way, we maintain overall data
consistency as transactions are
executed to undo the challenges or
the changes made by previous service.
This way, we maintain overall
data consistency without relying
on distributed transactions.
Another powerful platform, or
pattern, is event sourcing.
Instead of storing just the current state,
we store all changes to the application
state as a sequence of immutable events.
The current state is reconstructed
by replaying these events.
This ensures a single source of truth,
through an authoritative event log.
Event sourcing provides a clear
audit trail and can simplify
debugging and compliance efforts.
To implement these patterns
effectively, we can leverage tools
and frameworks that support messaging
and event driven architectures.
Apache Kafka is a, is a popular
distributed event streaming platform
that enables building real time
data pipelines and applications.
Cloud specific implementations like
Azure Service Bus, Azure Event Hubs, and
AWS Kinesis offer similar capabilities
with seamless cloud integration.
These tools allow services
to communicate via events,
facilitating data synchronization
and consistency across the system.
By adopting these patterns and
leveraging them, appropriate tools, we
can now overcome the data management.
Next, we'll explore another common
critique, testing complexity, and
discuss how to navigate the challenges of
testing in a microservices environment.
With multiple services interacting, end
to end testing becomes more challenging.
Coordinating and verifying the behavior
of numerous components can be complex.
There is also an increased need for
extensive integration and contract
testing to ensure services interact
correctly and adhere to agreed interfaces.
But here is the opportunity.
Because we've, separated everything into
independent services, we can better test
the individual pieces of business logic.
When testing a shipping service, for
example, we do not have to worry about
how the payment service works, at least
not until we get into integration testing.
This separation allows for more focused
and effective unit testing, ensuring each
service functions correctly in isolation.
Integration testing is important
in any architectural style,
but crucial in microservices.
By thoroughly testing the interaction
between services, we can catch
issues early and ensure smooth
collaboration between components.
Moreover, comprehensive testing
is not just about finding bugs.
It is about finding, building
confidence amongst users.
stakeholders, they need assurance
that what we are deploying will
also will work as intended.
In microservices, there's a lot of
happening underneath the covers,
including services that stakeholders
didn't even explicitly ask for, but
are necessary to realize their vision.
Testing gives us the confidence
that these unseen components
are functioning correctly.
To navigate these challenges, we need
a comprehensive testing strategy that
includes multiple levels of testing.
Unit testing, testing individual
components in isolation to
verify their correctness.
Next we have integration testing,
verifying that services interact
correctly with each other.
This is a vital in microservices.
Contract testing, where we ensure
services adhere to agreed upon interfaces.
And end to end testing, where
we test complete user flows
using, through the system.
These are essential.
for validating the entire
application behavior.
In terms of tools, PACT facilitates
contract testing by allowing us to
define and verify services and contracts.
It's something I've been
exploring and shows promise in
reducing integration issues.
For end to end testing, tools
like Playwright and Selenium
offer modern, automate UI testing.
While these tools can be more
fragile, implementing them
correctly ensures they add value.
But remember, they are at
the top of the pyramid.
You've built up to other testing before
depending on end to end testing, giving
it a strong foundation to rely on.
However, this isn't a
presentation about testing tools.
The key takeaway is the importance of
comprehensive testing to ensure we are
deploying reliable software and instilling
the confidence with our stakeholders.
By continuously testing our code at every
stage, we catch issues early and reduce
the risk of defects reaching production.
In summary, while testing complexity
is a valid critique of microservices,
it presents an opportunity.
By leveraging comprehensive testing
strategies, we can assure our services
not only work individually, but
also function seamlessly together.
This thorough approach to testing builds
confidence amongst our stakeholders
and helps us deliver robust, reliable
software that meets their needs.
Okay, one last critique I want to
address today is the skills and
expertise requirements they demand.
Now, my first response to people raising
this type of critique is, boo hoo.
If you are afraid of the need to
learn, then software development
might not be right for you.
If your team has a hard time with
this, then you need to work on that.
But let's get back to the point.
Some of the challenges normally
associated with microservices is that
microservices necessitate a higher level
of expertise in DevOps, distributed
systems, and cloud infrastructure.
And they are not wrong.
Teams need to understand complex
architectures, deployment
processes, and the nuances of
managing distributed systems.
Additionally, there is a
steep learning curve for teams
transitioning to microservices.
This transition requires a significant
mindset shift and adapt, adaption
to new practices and tools.
However, this critique, while valid,
should not be seen as a negative.
In any architectural style,
continuous learning is essential,
even with legacy systems.
New techniques are needed
to solve evolving problems.
Encouraging continuous learning
and professional development
within the team is crucial.
Your company should foster a
culture of growth and development.
And we need to promote the idea that
learning is a key part of being a
professional in software development.
In fact,
software development professionals
who do not want to learn
are truly not professional.
If one doesn't want to learn,
then perhaps software development
isn't right for the right path.
To support this continued learning, we
can leverage various external resources.
For example, we can, utilize training
programs, workshops, and certification
courses to upskill the team, access
online resources, communities, and
mentorship opportunities to stay current
with industry trends and best practices.
By embracing these resources,
we can assure our teams have the
necessary expertise to succeed
in a microservices environment.
It is important to advocate for
the continuous learning, not just
as a necessity, but as a positive
aspect of our professional growth.
Learning new skills and staying updated
with industry advancements not only
enhances our capabilities, but also
keeps our work engaging and fulfilling.
In the fast paced world of technology,
standing still is not an option.
We must keep moving forward.
And that means embracing the
learning curve and turning it
into an opportunity for growth.
as we've explored, the common
critiques of microservices, operational
complexity, distributed system
challenges, data management and
complexity issues, testing complexities,
and the higher skills and expertise
requirements are all valid concerns.
Thank you.
However, each of these challenges
can be effectively addressed with the
right strategies, tools, and mindsets.
By embracing testing strategies,
fostering continuous learning,
implementing patterns like saga
and event sourcing, and leveraging
appropriate tools and frameworks, we
can overcome these obstacles and harness
the full potential of microservices.
It is important to recognize that while
microservices introduces complexities,
they also offer significant advantages
in scalability, resilience, and agility.
The key is to navigate these
complexities thoughtfully and
thoroughly and strategically.
Now that we've addressed the common
critiques and challenges of microservices,
let's shift our focus to strategies for
successful microservices implementation.
In this section, we'll look at
practical approaches and best practices
that can help you effectively adapt
microservices within your organization.
We'll explore actionable strategies
such as leveraging automation and CICD
pipelines, implementing robust monitoring
and observability practices, and fostering
a culture of continuous improvement.
By adapting these strategies,
you can confidently navigate the
complexities of microservices
and unlock their transformative
potential for your organization.
To make the most of our time
together, I have grouped the
strategies for successful microservice
implementation into thematic areas.
This approach will help us understand
how different aspects of adaption
work together to create a cohesive and
effective microservices architecture.
We'll begin with culture and
organizational strategies.
As the foundation of any successful
microservices implementation lies in the
people and the organizational mindset.
Let's see how embracing a DevOps
culture, fostering continuous
learning, and aligning teams with
business capabilities can set the
stage for microservices success.
First, let's talk about
embracing the DevOps culture.
In the context of microservices,
fostering a DevOps culture is crucial.
It involves breaking down silos
between development and operation
teams, and encouraging collaboration.
By forming cross functional teams that
own services from development through
deployment and into operations, we promote
a sense of shared responsibilities.
This ownership means teams are accountable
for the entire life cycle of their
services, which enhances accountability
and encourages higher quality outcomes.
Automation is a key
aspect of DevOps culture.
Implementing continuous learning
and continuous deployment pipelines,
steering lines the development
process and reduces manual errors.
Tools like Azure DevOps, GitHub
Actions, or Jenkins facilitate
this automation, allowing teams to
deploy changes rapidly and reliably.
Embracing a DevOps culture not only
improves efficiency, but also enhances
collaboration and communication
across your organization, laying
a microservices implementation.
Next, let's focus.
or let's explore the importance
of fostering continuous
learning within your teams.
Microservices require teams to
be proficient in various areas
like distributed systems, DevOps
practices, and cloud infrastructure.
Therefore, promoting, professional
development is essential.
Encourage team members to upskill
and learn new technologies by
providing access to training programs,
workshops, and certification courses.
Build a learning culture means
fostering an environment where, where
learning is valued and supported.
This can be achieved by hosting
regular tech talks, workshops,
or lunch and learn, events.
Yeah, lunch and learn sessions where
team members can share knowledge and
learn from one another, participating
in industry conferences, webinars and
community events can provide valuable
insights and network opportunities
by fostering continuous learning.
You empower your teams to tackle
the complexities of microservices
with confidence and innovation.
Finally, let's, discuss aligning teams
with business capabilities by organizing
teams with around business domains.
Each team owns microservices, related
to Pacific, business, functions.
This alignment enhances domain
expertise within the team and
fosters a sense of ownership over the
services they develop and maintain.
It also facilitates better communication
and collaboration between technical
teams and business stakeholders.
When teams understand the business
context and objectives, they can make
technical decisions that directly
support and advance business goals.
Empowering autonomous teams by granting
them the authority to make decisions
about their services encourages agility.
Teams can respond more quickly to
changing business needs and innovate
without unnecessary bottlenecks.
By aligning teams with business
capabilities, you ensure that your
microservices architecture is not only
technically sound, but also strategically
focused on delivering business value.
In summary, focusing on culture and
organizational strategies is vital for the
success of microservices implementation.
By embracing a DevOps culture, fostering
continuous learning, and aligning
teams with business capabilities,
you create an environment where teams
are empowered, collaborative, and
aligned with the organization's goals.
These cultural and organizational
functions enable technical strategies
to flourish, paving the way for robust
and effective microservice architecture.
Now, having established a strong
foundation with cultural and
organizational strategies, we can now turn
our focus to the technical best practices
that microservices implementation.
In this section, we'll explore three
key strategies, beginning with clear
architectural vision, implementing
effective testing strategies, and
investing in monitoring and observability.
These practices are practical, are crucial
for building a resilient and scalable
microservices architecture that can
meet the demands of modern applications.
First, let's discuss the
importance of beginning with
a clear architectural vision.
A well defined architecture vision is
crucial for the development and evolution
of your microservice architecture.
To start, it's essential to define
the service boundaries using
techniques like domain driven design.
This involves identifying bounded contexts
and ensuring each microservice aligns with
specific business capabilities, creating
a cohesive and modular architecture.
Developing a comprehensive
plan is equally important.
Create detailed architecture diagrams
and documentation that outline the
overall structure, scalability,
security, and integration considerations.
Finally, it's crucial to
communicate the architectural
vision with all stakeholders.
Ensure everyone understands the
goals, principles, and reasoning
behind the architecture to
align efforts and expectations.
A clear architectural vision serves
as a roadmap, guiding your team's
efforts and ensuring a structured
approach to building and maintaining
your microservices environment.
Next, by implementing
effective testing strategies.
we can ensure the reliability and
stability of your microservices.
A comprehensive testing approach
includes multiple levels of testing to
cover various aspects of your system.
Start with unit testing to test
individual components in isolation.
This ensures that each service
functions correctly on its own.
Then, move to integration testing to
verify interactions between services,
ensuring they work together as expected.
Contract testing is crucial for ensuring
service interfaces meet expectations.
Finally, perform end to end testing
using tools like Playwright or
Selenium to validate the entire
system flow from start to finish.
Automating these, These tests in
CICD pipelines ensure they run
continuously and catch issues
early in the development process.
Focus on the critical paths in high
risk areas to prioritize testing
efforts where they matter the most.
Ensuring that essential functionality
is thoughtfully validated.
By implementing a comprehensive
automated testing strategy, you can
enhance the reliability and stability
of your microservices architecture.
Now, finally, let's discuss
the importance of investing in
monitoring and observability.
Effective monitoring and observability
are crucial for the main, for
maintaining the health and performance
of your microservices architecture.
By starting start by centralizing,
logging and monitoring using
integrated tools like Azure Monitor and
Application Insights or AWS CloudWatch.
These tools provide a comprehensive view
of your system's health and performance.
Implementing distributed tracing
to track requests as they flow
through multiple services.
This helps you pinpoint
issues and understand the
interaction between services.
Next, step, set up alerting and dashboards
to proactively monitor your system.
Establish alerts for critical issues
so you can respond quickly and create
dashboards that visually visualize
system health and performance
metrics, making it easier to spot
trends and potential problems.
By leveraging observability data, you
can enable proactive issue resolution.
Use the insights gained from monitoring
to identify and resolve issues before
they impact users, continuously improving
your system's performance and reliability.
Investing in monitoring and
observability practices ensures that
you have the visibility and tools
needed to maintain a resilient and
efficient microservices architecture.
In summary, technical best practices
are essential for building a
successful microservices architecture.
Begin with clear architectural vision,
provides a strong, will provide you with a
strong foundation for your microservices.
Implementing effective testing strategies
ensures reliability, stability, while
investing in monitoring and observability.
helps maintain system health
and performance by incorporating
these best practices.
You can navigate the complexities of
microservices and create a robust,
scalable and efficient architecture.
Now, having covered the technical best
practices, let's now focus on process,
on processes and tooling that can enhance
your microservices implementation.
In this section, we'll explore
three key strategies, leveraging
automation and infrastructure as
code, utilizing containerization
orchestration, and utilizing
appropriate tools and techniques.
These processes and tools are essential
for streamlining operations, ensuring
consistency and maximizing the efficiency
of your microservices architecture.
First, let's discuss leveraging
automation and infrastructure as code.
Automation and infrastructure as
code, or IAC, are crucial for, for
ensuring consistent and reliable
microservices environments.
By automating infrastructure,
provisioning, using tools like Terraform,
Azure Resource Manager, or ARM, BICEP
templates, or AWS CloudFormation.
You can define and manage your
infrastructure declaratively.
This approach ensures that your
infrastructure is consistent
across all environments and reduces
manual configuration errors.
Next, streamline deployments using
CICD tools like Azure DevOps.
GitHub actions or Jenkins.
Automate your deployment processes.
and this will reduce manual
errors, increase reliability
and allow for faster iterations.
Automation and IAC provide consistency and
repeatability across development, testing
and production environments, ensuring
that your microservice operates reliably
and without configurational drift.
By leveraging these processes and
tools, you can enhance your efficiency
and reliability of your microservices.
Next, let's explore utilizing
containerization and orchestration.
Containerization ensures
consistency and portability across
environments, different environments.
By containerizing services using Docker,
you can package microservices with all
their dependencies, ensuring they run
consistently, regardless of environment.
For managing and orchestrating these
containers, Kubernetes is a powerful tool.
Whether you use AKS, EKS, or
GKE, Kubernetes ensures your
microservices are scalable, highly
available, and efficiently managed.
Additionally, serverless platforms like
Azure Container Apps, AWS Fargate, or
Google Cloud Run offer serverless options
that reduce operational overhead while
providing The benefits of containerized
nation and orchestration by utilizing
containerization orchestration, you can
improve the scalability and portability.
and manageability of your
microservice architecture.
Finally, we have the importance
of utilizing appropriate
tools and technologies.
Selecting the right stack is essential.
Choose technologies that align with
your team's expertise and project
needs, ensuring that they are
compatible and can integrate seamlessly.
Leveraging cloud services can
significantly reduce operational burdens.
cloud native services Offer
scalability, reliability, and ease
of management, allowing your teams
to focus on developing features
rather than managing infrastructure.
Implementing observability
tools is crucial for monitoring
and debugging microservices.
Tools like open telemetry and, or Jagger
provide distributed tracing capabilities,
ensuring you gain insights into how.
Request flow through your system
and identify potential bottlenecks.
By utilizing tools and techniques,
you can create a robust, scalable, and
efficient microservice architecture
that meets your project's demands and
aligns with your team's strengths.
One last thing I want to cover before
wrapping up is a quick synopsis of the
four main architectural styles I brought
up at the beginning, and a quick comment
about when to use one over the other.
When considering architectural styles,
it's important to understand the different
strengths and weaknesses of each.
let's take a quick look into this
comparison, comparison matrix.
Monolithic architectures are generally
simpler to and faster for, smaller
projects, but they have limited
scalability and fault isolation.
Maintenance becomes complex
as the application grows.
In tier architectures offer moderate
scalability and fault isolation by
separating concerns into different layers.
It's suitable for medium to large
applications with clear ties
but becomes unnecessary complex.
Modular monolith architectures
improve scalability and fault
isolation by organizing the
application into well defined modules.
This approach is faster for
meeting complexity projects
and easier to maintain.
And microservices excel in scalability,
fault isolation, and deployment
speed for large, complex projects.
However, they require skilled teams
and can be highly complex to manage.
To provide a clearer perspective, let's
look at real world examples of where each
architectural style is commonly used and
why it makes sense in those contexts.
Monolithic architectures are often used
by early stage startups due to their
simplicity and quick development speed.
For example, a startup developing a basic
e commerce platform might use a monolithic
approach to get to the market quickly.
N tier architectures are well suited for
large enterprises with complex business
logic and multiple user interfaces.
For instance, a banking scenario our
banking, solution might use a, an
interior architecture to separate the
user interface, business logic and data
access layers, insurance, scalability
and maintainability medium sized
businesses, with growing complexity
and might benefit from a modular.
architecture.
An example is an online retail
company with separate modules
for inventory management, order
processing, and customer service.
This approach allows them to
maintain a single deployable
unit while managing complexity.
Now, large tech companies with complex
scalable systems often use microservices.
For instance, Netflix uses a microservice
architecture to handle the immense load
and complexity of delivering streaming
services to millions of users worldwide.
This approach allows for independent
scalability and fault isolation.
Now, these real world
examples are just examples.
They are, there are many
situations where any of these
architectures might be a good fit.
The importance is to scrutinize
your organization's needs and
determine the correct architectural
style for each particular solution.
Not one's fits all.
And just because you use one architectural
style for one solution doesn't mean you
always have to, or should, use the same
architectural style for other projects.