Hi everyone.
Welcome to Con 42, cloud Native 2026.
I am Barika Joli, and this is a talk
about responsible agent AI for equitable
and sustainable cloud native telecom.
This talk draws from my research
on the societal implications of
deep learning and agentic ai,
especially in telecommunications.
As we move from 5G to six G, these
systems are taking over decisions
that engineers used to make directly.
The question is whether we are
governing that transition Responsib.
The stakes are high and
the shift is fundamental.
Network engineers previously
handled spectrum allocation, fall
detection, and power management
through direct evaluation.
But as we move from 5G to six G
evolution, these responsibilities
now transfer to algorithms processing
massive data sets in real time.
It is a transition from human
control oversight and human
in the loop to progressively
independent decision frameworks.
5G densification demands more
base stations, higher frequency,
and intensive signal processing.
Six G will push autonomy even further, and
therefore responsibility has to keep pace.
We'll cover four areas today.
First, the connectivity divide,
2.6 billion people remain under or
unconnected, and how AI allocation
panels can widen this gap.
Second bias at cloud scale.
Historically skewed training
data propagates inequity
through orchestration layers.
Third, sustainability balancing
real time power optimization
against the computational cost
of large scale AI inference.
Fourth, an integrated governance framework
embedding fairness, transparency,
accountability, and carbon reporting
into autonomous network operations.
The world today is still
divided by connectivity.
The numbers from the research show that.
4.5 billion people have high speed access.
1.5 billion have limited connectivity,
and 1.1 billion have no access at all.
Sub-Saharan Africa alone accounts for.
Much of that 1.1 billion.
This is not just a coverage gap.
It shapes access to education,
telecommunication, healthcare, economic
opportunity, and civic participation.
Telecom communities, typically
direct investment towards
high revenue urban areas.
When AI systems learn from that historical
pattern, they risk interpreting low usage
in underserved regions as weak demand
rather than the result of inadequate
infrastructure bias at cloud scale.
This is what the paper
calls algorithmic redlining.
When automation inherits qu.
AI resource allocation models trained
on historical data mirror decades of
uneven infrastructure spending and
hidden biases in cloud native systems.
Those biases do not remain confined,
and they spread across distributed
orchestration layers at machine speed.
How does bias scale in cloud native
orchestration bias to training
data feeds into models that
produce huge allocation policies.
These policies are then deployed
automatically across edge nos.
The result is systematic coverage gaps
that reinforce the original data bias.
Each layer amplifies upstream bias.
For example, a skewed signal example, a
skewed reward signal in a reinforcement
learning agent can translate into
neglect of underserved regions.
How does bias work in action?
This is a completely hypothetical
situation, but is grounded in
documented patterns from the research.
For example, a national operator
can train an RL agent across 10
years of investment data to automate
base station capacity planning
across, for example, 500 edge nodes.
What can go wrong?
The rural regions with historically low
usage get systematically de deprioritized.
The agent interprets low demand as weak
signal and not inadequate infrastructure.
Due to the drawbacks in the data
coverage gaps widen at machine
speed before a human can notice.
These can be fixed.
For example, we can add coverage equity
thresholds as hard RL constraints.
Geographic fairness audits at
each deployment stage, and these
have shown to re result in rural
coverage improving by 23% while
urban efficiency gains are preserved.
The sustainability paradox.
Reinforcement learning can cut idle
base station energy significantly by
replacing static capacity planning.
With dynamic optimization based on actual
usage, traditional networks run at peak
power regardless of traffic demand,
wasting energy during low usage periods.
AI can fix that, but training large scale
models requires intensive computation
across distributed data centers,
sometimes consuming electricity compared
to small cities during peak phases.
The net environmental impact depends
on whether efficiency gains outweigh
the AI footprint, and that balance
varies across deployment context.
There are two forces attention here.
Efficiency gains versus
ai operational costs.
Digital twin simulations let operators
validate efficiency strategies
in virtual environments before
physical deployment, reducing trial
and error and unnecessary resource
expenditure using multi-agent systems.
Coordinate and distributes
optimization across network components
for rapid localized decisions.
But once required, there is a huge AI
operational costs for inference, for
computation and constant relearning.
Now, this is where the challenge is
that we ensure that AI infrastructure
enabling these gains, does not negate them
through unchecked compute consumption.
And this leads to the core
argument of the paper.
Governance cannot be audited
into existence after deployment.
It must be architected from the ground
up, and that means fairness, checks at
model validation, carbon tracking across
training, and influence policy enforcement
in CICD pipelines and accountability
hooks at every orchestration layer.
What does an integrated
governance framework looks like?
There are four pillars to
this transparency and audit.
Explainable AI decisions logged
at every orchestration layer with
immutable audit trails accessible
to regulators and operator.
Second fairness evaluation, and that is
allocation assessments that test models
against demographic and geographic equity
metrics before and after deployment.
Third, accountability mapping.
And this includes clear responsibility
chains across cloud native microservices,
every and automated decision
traceable to a responsible owner.
And finally, carbon reporting.
Measurable sustainability tracking
integrated into CICD pipelines,
quantifying the carbon cost at
every model, update and inference.
Workload governance is not
a checkpoint at the end.
It needs to be embedded into
every cloud native pipeline.
It is continuous woven into every stage
from training data curation through.
Live operation and
post-deployment observability.
The paper emphasizes that technical
safeguards alone are insufficient.
Organizational commitment and cultural
alignment play a decisive role.
Incentive structures should reward
equity and sustainability outcomes
across performance efficiency.
Cross-disciplinary collaboration
among engineers, social scientists,
and policy experts is critical.
This can be easier said than done.
Therefore fairness must be encoded as a
technical requirement, not left as vague.
Policy intent.
This means embedding coverage equity
thresholds as hard constraints directly
into reinforcement learning reward
functions, running geographic distribution
audits before deployment is approved,
and conducting demographic parity
checks both before and after rollout
without these guardrails optimization.
Will default to prioritizing high revenue
areas ongoing fairness assessments
Should then verify whether platforms
are delivering equitable outcomes across
demographic regions and groups alike.
I want to talk about something that often
gets lost in responsible AI conversation.
The assumption that ethics and
governance slows things down.
The argument here is exactly opposite.
When done right, responsible AI
is actually an enabler of faster
and more durable innovation.
Let's break down what that
looks like in practice.
When governance frameworks are
designed to align fairness and
carbon accountability with concrete
networks, performance metrics, you stop
treating them as competing priorities.
Instead, they reinforce each
other and the outcome is value.
That scales not just
commercially, but socially.
That's a meaningful
distinction for operators.
Thinking about long-term positioning.
The second point is about
regulatory readiness.
Auditability is often treated as
compliance burden imposed after the
fact, but if you build it into the
system architecture from day one,
it becomes a structural advantage.
Operators who have done this can
respond to new regulations more
quickly and significantly lower cost
than those scrambling to retrofit.
Third and perhaps the most
unup underappreciated is trust.
At network scale, AI systems,
touch regulators, communities, and
enterprise customers simultaneously.
Transparency isn't just good ethics.
It's a relationship asset.
It reduces friction with regulators,
builds community confidence and gives
enterprise con customers the assurance
that they need to commit to your platform.
The closing argument here
and ties it all together.
Fairness, accountability and respect
for human agency cannot be treated
as soft criteria that yield whenever
technical performance is under pressure.
They must set at the same level
as performance metrics from the
very beginning of the design
process, not bolted to the end.
I want to close with three takeaways that
I hope you carry out of this session.
The first is that bias
skills with automation.
When training data reflects historical
inequities, and that data is used to
drive automated decision making across
cloud native orchestration systems,
those inequities don't just persist.
They propagate at machine
speed and at network scale.
Therefore, fairness cannot be a
soft guideline, and it needs to
be engineered into the system
before it ever reaches production.
Okay.
The second takeaway is that
sustainability requires net accounting.
The power optimization gains that AI
driven network management delivers
are real and they MA matter, but
they're only meaningful if we
are also measuring, managing, and
reporting the AI footprint itself.
The energy cost of training
inference and continuous operation
across the full system lifecycle.
Partial accounting is not accountability.
The third takeaway is the
most fundamental governance is
not an architecture decision.
We need to embed transparency,
accountability, fairness, evaluation,
and carbon reporting directly
into cloud native pipelines before
agents can reach production.
Thank you for listening and
thank you for your time.
This research is ongoing and I welcome
questions, feedback, and collaboration.
You can find me on LinkedIn or reach
out to me through the Con 42 platform.
If you're further interested
in the talk for today.
I have linked the article in the slide.
Thank you.