Hello everyone.
I am, first of all, I'm glad to be here
speaking at Con 42 Cloud Native 2026.
Today I'd be talking about this
topic beyond Dashboards, deep Dive
Network observability with EBPF.
So I work on Kubernetes
platform team at Salesforce.
Pretty much, I live and breathe
Kubernetes Cloud native every single day.
So the topic that I'm gonna be
talking about is not an abstract one.
It's basically my day-to-day
work is based out of this.
Before Salesforce, I was working at
Microsoft developing, distributed,
and scalable application
in cloud networking domain.
I know how hard it is to debug on-call
issues when things are on high stake.
Quick question before I dig deeper.
Have you ever been on call,
pulled up your dashboards?
Everything is green and end users
are still having a terrible time.
This gap between the dashboard says
Fine and something is clearly broken.
That's what this talk is all about, and
by the end of the session, you'll know
exactly why that happens at the Never
clear and what you can do about it.
So here's the plan for today.
We start the problem, why your
dashboards lie at the Never Clear.
Then I'll quickly cover
monitoring versus observability.
Because these two words mean very
different things and sometimes
are used interchangeably.
Then we look at what IP tables
is, which is more of a traditional
approach now and what they can and
cannot see through the traffic.
Then we'll go into EBPF first,
understand in very simple way, and then
get into a little bit of technicals.
I'll walk through the architecture of two
open source tools, retina and c cilium,
which are based on EBPF technology, and
show you real data from a benchmark.
I ran on A-W-S-E-K-S cluster and
close with a three step blueprint.
You can go apply this week
in your environment too.
Let's get into it.
So now let's talk about the problem.
Think, let's say you are on
call, a support ticket comes in.
Users are getting 500 errors on,
value while using that service.
Revenue is dropping.
You pull up the dashboard.
CPU seems normal.
Memory seems totally fine,
and error rate is almost 0%.
Everything is green, so
you start digging more.
You check logs, nothing obvious.
You check traces.
Requests are going in, something
in the middle isn't responding.
No error, no alert, nothing.
Then you dig deeper and figure once
you figure it out, that there's
a network policy rule which was
dropping traffic between two services.
No logs was emitted, no alert fired.
The package just disappeared,
and this isn't a rare edge case.
The three failures, morts
that I have personally seen
in productions are as follows.
First one silent drops, a policy
blocks traffic, and there is no
log, no trace, nothing about it.
The second one, DNS timeouts, there's
always a risk condition when a pod
is starting up for a few seconds.
It's when it's sim is spinning up.
Lookups fail for that amount of time and
your monitoring has no idea about it.
The third one is wrong.
Backends are set a label chain Somewhere
in the deployment, traffic is getting
routed to a different at all, and
there is no information about it.
These are in bugs and Kubernetes.
This is what happens when you
monitors, only watches what you
told it to watch in advance.
These are the major problems which
you're trying to tackle in this talk.
So before we talk about the solutions,
I wanna make sure we are on the
same page with respect to monitoring
versus observability, as these things
are changed interchangeably a lot.
So monitoring is like the
check engine light in your car.
Someone decided in advance.
If oil pressure drops below x, turn on
the light works great for the problems
you have, which have been seen before.
But if something unexpected goes
wrong that nobody anticipated light
stays off, you have no idea about it.
Observability, on the other
hand, it's, is it's different.
It's more like having a mechanic
who can look under the hood
and tell you what's happening.
Even the things you didn't predict.
Now talk about tap, talking
about the networking layer.
Monitoring means you have counters,
for example, total request per
second error rate, maybe latency.
These are all you can have monitors for,
which is u pretty much useful, but it
doesn't tell you which specific pod made
a request or why a packet was dropped.
Which DNS name took a lot of time and
like what was the latency of that?
Specific DNS request observability at
the never clear means flow level records.
Every connection individually.
What was the sore spot?
What was the destination spot?
What happened?
And if it was dropped, exactly
what was the reason for it?
That's the bar we are trying to hit.
And the reason we haven't been
hitting is that like the traditional
approach, which is IP table
space, cannot help us get there.
I wanted to give you a, like a little bit
of under a background on how Kubernetes
networking has traditionally worked.
IP tables.
If you ever looked at IB table rule,
like it's a giant linear list and every
packet walks down the list linearly
one by one works fine at small scale.
Four things break down
as it starts growing.
First it gets slow more.
Never.
Policy rule means longer
lookups per packet.
There's a published I triple research
on this Latency measurably degrades as
root count goes up at real production
scale with hundreds of service.
This matters a lot.
Second thing is it's shallow IP
table only sees IP addresses and port
numbers, like pretty much layer three
and layer four kind information.
No HDP paths, no DNS queries, no GRPC
service names and all, all like, all
pretty much like all layer seven stuff,
completely blind at the application layer.
The third issue is no identity.
IP table cease ips, not bot names.
Even if you know something was
dropped, you don't automatically
know which bot it, it basically
dropped, or which po basically
dropped that packet or like that flow.
The fourth thing is, it hurts
like a lot in incidents.
Drops are completely silent.
IP table drops a packet.
There's no log, no event, nothing.
The packet just disappears.
So look at the right column.
Those are the same exact questions which
like, which comes up in the real incident.
Why the traffic between these spots stop.
What data queries are timing out
is why network policy actually
doing what it needs to do.
None of those are answerable
with IP tables alone, you need
something that goes deeper.
So EBPF is the answer for this.
But before I explain what it is, let
me just tell you what it gives you.
Look at the right column.
Seven questions that used to be impossible
to answer Mid incident, which part
related initiated this connection.
You can answer that now with EBPF.
Why did the packet get dropped?
You get the exact kernel level
reason, not just a guess.
What services does Pod X depend on?
You get a life flow map, not
what you config says, but what's
actually happening right now is DNS.
The reason the call is low.
You can see individual DNS
queries per PO with latency.
Is my network policy working?
Watch it in real time.
The word like if it's getting
forwarded dropped or like whatever.
The reason is what HT TP path
is generating five oh errors.
You get application layer
visibility without touching the app.
Which parts are talking to the internet?
Egress visibility.
It's right there.
And like all of these without
a sidecar on every pod, without
changing application code, without
restarting anything, three things.
EBPF unlocks on the left.
Peripheral records, DNS, visibility, drop
reason, telemetry, those are like the
basic building blocks for any application.
So that's how A BPF agents
lives in your cluster.
So let's say there are three nodes,
node one, node two, and node three.
On each node you have your app
pods at the top where your actual
workload is sitting below them.
Highlighted in teal is the A BPF agent.
So basically this is a demon
set Kubernetes schedules one
copy on every single node.
Automatically.
You add a note, the EBPF agent shows up.
Let's say you have 200 nodes.
You get 200 EBPF demon set agents.
Below.
Just below that is, is the Linux
kernel with the hook points where
the EBBF programs attach and watch
every, everything flowing through it
without changing any kernel level code.
So these EBBF programs are very
lightweight programs that gets hooked
onto some kernel events or calls.
The agent that's then sends
to data to four places.
Flow records to Hubble Relay.
That's what powers the CLI and UI
metrics to Prometheus, then dashboards
in Grafana, and then using CLI.
You can see live flows
by running the command.
Hubble.
Observe your app.
Pods have no idea the agent is there.
You haven't changed even a single
line of code on the application.
The visibility just appears.
Now let's look at the specific tools
to do this, starting with Tino.
Soa, which was open sourced
by Microsoft in 2024.
It's designed only for observability.
Doesn't replace your CNI.
Doesn't enforce policies.
Just keeps a watch on the traffic.
So data flows from top to bottom.
Let's talk about major kernel
hooks that are configured ina.
First one, TC Hook is triggered for
every ingress and egress packet.
And the second one, K prob
gets called for each TCP rent.
Third one socket filter is
triggered for DNS and the
fourth XDP for any packet drops.
Once this event hook is triggered,
then inside the agent ring buffer sent
data from kernel to application spas.
Then IP to POD mapping
is taken taken care.
And then finally, these
metrics are aggregated.
Aggregated and send eventually to
Prometheus, then Prometheus, like we
can have Grafana dashboards running
and the Hubble CLI respectively taking
all these metrics and showing you in UI
or like the CLI, whichever you prefer.
What clever thing here is it m like this
retina agents image data in Hubble format.
So if you have the Hubble CRI already
installed in your Kubernetes, you
can use it with retain immediately.
The key design trait
to remember is IP two.
POD mapping happens in user
space, not at the kernel level.
He hence it's not able to properly
track identity for the package flowing.
That's what creates the identity gap.
You'll see in the screenshots
in the coming slide.
It's not a bug, it's how they kept
it a lightweight and CNI agnostic,
but it has its own consequences.
On the other hand, Celia, which we'll
be talking in the next slide, is able
to track the identity for each bot
through its cryptographic endpoint model.
So that's the a diagram of
cilium and Hubble together.
It's similar, but I did that
for The comparison can be drawn
directly for both these tools.
But the difference here is you
see that purple box in the agent,
the endpoint identity model.
So when a pod start, cilium
gives it a cryptographic
identity based on its labels.
And every EVPF program in the
kernel shows this identity,
not user space after the fact.
It's a kernel itself.
So when a packet moves from pod A to
pod B, the kernel already knows about
both pods, both sides of every flow kit.
Results automatically.
No filter needed at all.
That flows into the EVPF policy engine
for enforcement into the flow event,
drink buffer, and through the L seven
protocol parser, which gives you SGDP
method path status quo GRPC service
names none of that exists int that's
where CDM becomes powerful when we need
L seven level information and visibility.
In the S sgt P level, Hubble sits
on top relay UI with a live service
graph and command that interface.
So here I have a architecture comparison
side by side for both Uha and Cilium
plus Audible SOA is just an observability
tool and is CNI agnostic when, while
cilium can be a standalone CNI or
an observability plugin when used in
a chaining mode with any other CNI.
Just giving you a heads up for
the specific scenario, I use C
Lium in training mode because I
was using A-W-S-E-K-S cluster,
which has its own vp C, and I.
Taking from identity model perspective,
retina correlates ips in user space.
C DIUM does it in kernel.
That's why C Dium shows identity
clearly for the packages flowing.
While Rina is not able to show that from
L seven visibility perspective, Rina
doesn't have it there much cilium does.
S-G-T-P-G-R-P-C, everything at
the application layer when coming
to resource cost uses 47% less
memory per note and barely moves.
CPU under load.
CDM costs more because
it's doing much more.
That's the trade off.
So both the tools were tested on real
A-W-S-E-K-S cluster, sequentially, same
workload that is like almost 500 QPS of
sustained data was flown between the pods.
The result is right after right here,
retina, 47% less memory per node.
CPU was basically flat
under 500 QPS of load.
On the other hand, cilium 31% CPU
spike under the same load, more
memory because it's processing
per flow identity on every packet.
Screenshots on screen like our, the
actual cube, CTL, top parts output,
not a tool, not simulated, but
these are from the real environment.
I ran.
Both left.
One is a cilium and the
right one is a retina.
You can see like the CPUN memory
for each pod that I ran on.
Now talking about the results, if
you see left, it's a Hubble ui.
If with cilium.
Live service dependency grant for traffic.
We generated load generator
taking, talking to the test server.
Look at both sides.
Source spot, destination pot.
Fully resolved.
Every flow shows port protocol word and
it updates in real time on the right.
If you see it's traffic from retina,
which got, I mean got through basically
Hubble observe with a from pot filter.
DNS flows, TCP events.
All, everything is visible.
But look at the destination column.
I know it might not be visible from there,
but it says World raw ip, not a PO name.
That's the identity cap I was
talking about in previous lights.
Retina can see the packet, cannot
automatically name the destination.
The bottom bar Prometheus
metrics are accurate.
CLI with filters works fine, but
it just don't rely on the UI for
identity abstraction attribution.
So here's a complete picture in one table.
The pattern is simple.
Both tools give you basics like
flows, DNS, visibility, drop reasons.
The cap opens at identity and L seven
level source and destination pods.
It's partial for aina.
If you need information on HTP method
and Path C, lium is the only solution.
Then same foundation, but different depth.
I mean if I were to sum,
I would say pick retina.
If you are already on Prometheus and
want Lowcost network traceability and
L seven is not a requirement much.
You can set up this, five minutes
with helm if you're starting
from zero, this is the move.
Pick C when you need accurate pod
identity on both sides of a flow when
you are debugging SGTP or GRPC issues
more often when you need to know which
service is calling which, and this
they aren't just a permanent choices.
You can start with get baseline
visibility, migrate to C when requirements
grow, pick what's right for you today.
So like these three steps you
can use to get the observability
in your own clusters.
First DLA Latina, only two basic helm
commands needed just five minutes.
You start seeing T CCP flows and
DNS in Prometheus right away.
You would have to configure
Prometheus to scrape the retina.
Retina metrics from the, like
the porta agent exposes to.
The second one is run hobble.
Observe from pod.
To your pod, basically to trace the
pods activity run, Hubble observed
verdict, dropped in an incident.
Anything which is getting silently
blocked shows up immediately.
You can debug, debug if any packets are
getting dropped very easily through that.
Third one is you need, if you need
to level up at C in chaining mode.
If you already have a Kubernetes
service with a different CNI, for
example, in my case, I have used a WSE
case, so I had to use CM in chaining
mode by putting the property CNI
chaining mode equals to A-W-S-C-N-I.
This keeps V-P-C-C-N-I doing
all the IP address management.
Cilium adds identity aware, L
visibility on top, which becomes
very powerful observability.
Four takeaways for this talk is EVPF
is the only lightweight solution to see
the full picture of the network layer
without any performance degradation.
Retina is a lightweight, great starting
point for network observability tool.
C DM is more smarter, more identity
aware, more L seven level information.
And when you need to go a little
bit more deeper into L seven layer
seven level information you need.
C Lium network Observability
is not an option anymore.
As cluster grows prebuilt,
dashboards stop big enough.
You need more level of information.
So it is a necessity going forward now.
EBP based network observability is
becoming like a standalone infrastructure.
The question isn't whether you need it.
It's which tool fits
where you are right now.
With that, I would want to conclude that.
Thank you so very, thank
you so very much everyone.
I hope you guys found it informative.
If you guys have any questions, concerns,
or want to discuss this more, happy to
connect on LinkedIn or through my email.
Thanks again.