Okay, welcome to my talk.
Secure your cloud automations.
I'm Leo Fisher.
I'm from the Netherlands.
I work as a consultant At OGDI
do stuff with AI automation, clo.
I just like to tinker with technology.
I'm also an organizer of the, it's the
Dutch user, community or user group.
So I like to do stuff with
PowerShell and this is also why
I'm an Azure MVP for PowerShell.
You can connect with me on LinkedIn.
There's a QR code on screen
if you wanna connect.
And at the bottom you will see my
website or the csops.com and you can
find me at the socials at Auto SalesOps.
I share things about automations,
about other things I find
about personal projects I do.
So if you're interested
in technology in general.
Feel free to connect, and if you
have any questions afterwards,
you can always connect with me and
send them to me, either the socials
or LinkedIn or up my website.
So today I'm gonna talk about cloud
automations and how we can secure
them, but why would we actually
do automations in the cloud?
Because we can also run
them on premises, right?
Automations in general, they will give
us the possibility to shift left tasks.
So if I have a automation for something,
which normally would've been done
by say, assist admin or somebody
with high privileges, by creating an
automation, I can limit the scope.
I can make sure that it can be performed
by somebody with lower permissions,
like a surface desk person or whatever.
They can also be used
to perform maintenance,
especially in cloud platforms.
There's a lot of APIs you can connect to.
There's a lot of different possibilities
to automate and to make your whole
infrastructure easier to manage with
a site, reliability, engineering,
platform engineering, or any other
way of managing your cloud platform.
Adding these automations is often a must
have to set up your environment well.
And in the cloud it's easy to use
consumption based billing where on
premises, if you want to run automations,
you would need to set up some kind
of compute and make sure that it's
there all the time because it's not
really possible to set something up on
premises, which is only sometimes there.
You could do stuff with a Kubernetes
cluster or whatever on premises and
spin up containers when you need them.
This is a lot more complexity and
you would still need to provision
your whole infrastructure for the
peak you need at some point, because
it would need to fit the pick load.
You will bring on it and a lot
of times maybe you're not running
automation, so you're not using it.
It will just be there
wasting money in the cloud.
You can do this consumption based
and only pay when you actually need
it due to the large scale of it.
And also in the cloud.
There's a lot of possibilities
to integrate with different
platforms by using connections
to different cloud platforms, to
different systems which exist.
You can very easily create an
automation which connects with
many different systems from your
ticketing system to your monitoring
system, to your security system.
Often it's very easy in the cloud
to connect with all of them either
by low code or high code solutions.
In this presentation, I will mostly
focus on automations using PowerShell.
Which is a scripting language,
which is somewhere between
the high code and low code.
It's mostly because PowerShell is used
a lot by people who are managing these
platforms, especially Windows platforms.
I will also be mostly focusing
on the Azure platform, but most
of the things I will show you
have equivalent options in either
G-C-P-A-W-S or other cloud platforms.
We'll first look at the easiest
solution, just a scheduled script.
So with a scheduled script, we
often have some kind of runner,
either a VM or something else,
which just performs a simple task.
In this case, I want to have a scheduled
script, which just retrieves some
information from a storage account.
So let me show this to you here.
I've got the Azure portal.
And in here I've created a storage account
and I can go to the storage browser, to
the tables, to the automation table, and
let me remove this entry and create an
entry with the roki tree and the value.
Hello.
Cons 42.
And we're gonna insert it.
So I've created an entry in this
table, and now I'm going to FIAs code.
And here I've got a
small PowerShell script.
This script can run on a vm, it
can run on any kind of compute.
It's not really the easy
billing consumption theory yet.
It's a very simple version of.
Compute of automation because during
this presentation, I will slowly go to
more advanced versions of presentations
and show you the pitfalls which you can
run into while when using this, and this
is often the first step of automation,
there is like a connection to Azure.
We will retrieve the storage table.
Then I'll determine the date one hour ago.
And here I perform a query towards the
storage table to get me all entries from
the last hour, and I show them in a table.
I'm already connected to Azure, so when
I run this I, we get here the entry back.
Hello?
Cons 42.
So this is a very simple
version of a script.
And when you're running it on a vm,
there's already one nice thing you can
use in Azure or other cloud platforms, and
it's using man using a managed identity.
I was running this on my machine
and I already logged into Azure
just to make it easy to show.
But with a managed identity,
you can give an identity to this
virtual machine and run scripts.
Instantly from this virtual
machine authenticated against
this managed identity.
This makes your authentication
scheme a lot easier already.
If you wanna do it, it's as simple as
just changing this to identity and now
it will use the managed identity and
Azure will handle this all for you.
Doing this.
There's not really logging.
I could create some kind of
logging on my machine, but I
might want to make this logging.
Logging a bit more interesting.
And also, what if a script fails?
I've seen it too many times that somebody
is running an automation and inside
this automation, for example, we're
retrieving data, but when the script
fails it, the next time it'll try again.
And maybe it works for some reason.
There might have been an outage in Azure.
There might have been some authentication
issue, and it's resolved the script
runs and it forgets part of it
because, for example, in this script,
I retrieved the entries from the last
hour, and if it doesn't run one time
and one hour later, it will run again.
It missed the entries
of one specific hour.
So what I often recommend is when
you're using these kinds of scripts.
You can start enhancing
the scripts already.
You can do this when running in more
consumption based systems or when you're
running on a machine, and you can use
systems like application insights.
Within application insights.
You can add logging, you can
send your logs instantly here
and trigger alerts on it.
If something happens, you
can trigger an alert on it.
You can create easy dashboard
from it where you can see.
If the automation run how well
they ran, how long it took, other
information you want to send.
I will show you this in a moment,
and I'm using an Azure key fold to
store specific values, for example,
secrets or other things I want to use.
So I've got these managed centrally.
If at one point I need to replace
the machine, I need to send the
script somewhere else, or I'm running
it on a virtual machine skillset
or on containers, which spin up.
I can make my scripts stateless.
I can make sure that these variables
I need are stored inside the key vault
and I only retrieve the ones I need.
So let me show this to you, Sarah.
For example, here I've got my key vault.
I've got a variable called the
check date, and that there's
like previous versions of this.
And if I look at the newest
version and I show the value.
It shows the time this script last ran,
and I've altered my script to first
retrieve this threshold I'm calling it.
So it's retrieving the check date
from the key vault, and I'm using this
threshold to determine my new timestamp.
So I will only retrieve the.
Entries from my table
since the last time it ran.
So if it's, if the script failed
for what, some reason this value is
not updated, so the next time it'll
retrieve all previous instances again.
And here on top, I've got my telemetry.
So I'm using the PowerShell
module called Telemetry Helper.
Which personally I think is a very nice
module, and this creates a very easy way
to integrate with application insight.
I can initialize it.
I can set up some configuration,
and I can add the connection string.
The connection string
here is in plain text.
I could also store this
in a key fold if I want.
We're can look at this
later, but this one.
Is for at the moment quite open
because from many different
places I want to send stuff there.
I could also manage this
with managed identity and so
on, or keep it more locally.
And then I send a trace where I say the
VM or the script has started, I send
another trace where I tell 'em what
the, where I tell what the threshold is.
We found I send another trace.
Where I say how many results I got,
and in the end I send a trace where
I say that I stored new thresholds
because at the end I'm setting
the new value for the check date.
Now, if this would be a very long script
I would need to make sure what I'm doing
here too is to get this threshold value.
I'm taking the as early as possible
because if the script would be very long
and took 10 minutes to execute, it would
be possible that in the meantime, new
entries would've been added to my table.
And the threshold is only calculated
after I've done all the mutations.
So I would want to add this
threshold just after I'm starting
retrieving the other one.
So I know that.
Once I've queried my database,
then I'm setting the threshold.
So everything after my query will be done.
In the next one, there might
be some small overlaps.
These are, there are
ways you can fix this.
If you look into this more,
if I run this from here.
And it takes a small while we
again see the hello Con 42.
And also here I've got
my application insights.
And in here we should see
that there's now some traces.
So this is like just a small moment ago.
Here we see ads.
This time, believe me, this
is just the time I run it.
So you can see when this was prerecorded,
it says the script was started.
It gives me the threshold.
So it says, take
everything from this date.
It got one result, and it
says to set the new threshold.
So these things are set in here.
If I just go to the application inside.
It also shows me some
easy dashboards already.
I could even go into performance and get
some small insights about how long it took
because it takes all the traces and if I
have a trace at the start and the trace at
the end, it just knows that, oh, the time
in between those are all added together.
So you run for this time.
So I can also see how long my script ran.
Application inside gives me the
give me this desk watch for free.
Or almost for free.
I'd pay for some of the storage, but a
lot of this, you don't pay much for it.
So this really enhances
already your automation.
But we can do better than this because we
can also run our automation really more
in a consumption based there in the cloud.
And we could can do this with
an Azure automation account.
So let me show this to you.
An Azure automation account is
a resource you create in Azure.
So here I've got my resource group
and it's just an automation account.
The name is always a little bit confusing
because it has account in the name
just as where the storage account.
It's a place where you manage the
things in here, you can create
something which is called a runbook.
Here, I've got a runbook and we can
view the code and it's very simple.
It just says Hello worlds.
I could, if I want, just
start the runbook here.
It'll run.
It'll queue up.
Because this is running
on shared infrastructure.
It is completely secure, but it
will now find a place to run it.
Once it's found this place, it'll.
Set it up and start running it inside.
Now you see it starting
inside a automation account.
You can create runbooks in
different ways and different types.
So you can do like a power shell,
a python, and there's also like
the graphical ones, I believe
the graphical ones are going away
eventually, so I would recommend
using the PowerShell or Python ones.
And you can also select
the versions you wanna use.
So let's see if our run was complete
and now we can see it was completed.
And we can look at it, we can look at
the output and we see the, hello, what
a storage account, or,
sorry, not a storage account.
A automation account can also
have something called a web hook.
So when I have this automation, I can
create a web hook here, and with this
web hook, I can actually start this
automation from a different place.
So here, for example, I've got
a example script where I've
got the URL of the webhook.
I'm gonna invoke it here.
I've got a small loop to wait until.
I've got output, and then once I've got
the output, I will write the output.
You'll see here that there's
like a token in here.
Don't worry.
This token will be changed by the
time this recording is online.
But if you have this token,
you can run this web hook.
This is like a secret in the URL.
This can be very useful if you are, for
example, using systems like Surface Now,
top Desk, or any other ticketing system.
There's often possibilities inside
these ticketing systems to instantly
trigger automations based on
actions happening in the systems.
So if people press a button,
it could send some inputs to
the automation and manage it.
So with this, you could create
it, and if I run it, we'll
have to wait for the output.
I made some visual notes that it's
still running by adding dots behind it.
And now if we look at it, we
should see that another job has
been queued and it will execute.
And once it's done
executing, we will see it.
Let me go here already and
then we'll see the results.
So these Azure automation
accounts, they're quite nice.
They can also use managed identities.
So if I want to connect
to different systems.
I can again, use a managed identity
to easily reach these systems.
And there's building logging already.
It's only for 90 days.
After 90 days, the logging will
be removed, but in a lot of
cases, 90 days is plenty of time
with these kinds of automations.
Now, I showed you already in my code
that there were secrets exposed in
the form of the token, and here we see
now that the output was hello world.
Okay, but this token I want
to get, I want to remove.
So again, we can use a key fault
just like I did before.
I can set up a key fault the key
vault while we have the secure
web hook where inside I store.
The token, so now it's not in my code.
I can have this code in source control
easily or whatever, and I don't have
to worry about the token being inside
the source control inside my code.
The key vault can man can connect
via managed identity or other PLA
or other authentication schemes.
I can retrieve this WebBook URL, and
then invoke the WebBook and run it again.
So if we run it, it will start
running again and we will soon see
that another job has been queued.
So this is a nice way to start it.
And this kind of web hook this
kind of request to the key
vaults can often also be done by.
Systems, top desk or whatever, because
it's just an API call so they can retrieve
it as a parameter and then use it.
Sometimes it's not possible, but
then you would need to make sure
that you store this WebBook in
a safe way inside these systems.
Sometimes you don't have the choice.
We will look at some other systems
later, how we could maybe improve
this even more with different systems.
You do need to keep in mind that.
If you're also sending data there, you
can send it via arguments that this is
going over the internet in this situation.
So if you're sending very important data,
you might want to look into creating
some kind of network integration.
If you have a storage account, it
is possible to connect your storage
account also to your Azure networks.
This way you could make sure that
this information is sent inside your
organization instead of outside.
If you set it up in the right way, this
would make it a bit more safe again.
And if we now look at the output, we also
see that we've got the hello world again.
Now let's go into K three and
K three is the Azure function.
So we started with just a virtual
machine where we run our codes on.
Then we went into an automation account,
which is like a surface from Microsoft.
It manages all of it for us.
And this is like the kind of in
between version where I want to
wrap my own code just like I did,
but I want to just have the code,
don't worry about the other stuff.
And it's a bit more of a high code
solution than the automation account.
As a user, I just connect to the
Azure function again, and when we
look at it, I can create like a
function app and Azure function app
you can create in a consumption tier.
You can also run it on an app service
plan, which will have resources available
and you can run multiple systems.
On a surface plan.
So if you have some websites and so
on, they can share these resources.
I'm running on a easy consumption
tier, which is very cheap, and in
here I've got the automation one.
And if we refresh it, will it load?
Yes, it will load.
So in here I've got a,
the parameter which will.
We triggered, we've got a
small right host, which says
that it's being processed.
We take the query name from the URL and
we send back Hello the name and that it's
triggered successfully if the name has
been given and else we just send back a
normal message and then we send it back.
This is a very simple script and if you
create a PowerShell function app, this is
the script you will get from the start.
I think I changed it slightly, but it's
almost a default one, so you can get
like the URLs from here year, and there's
like function keys and the function keys.
They are like an API key.
If you send along this API key,
you can authenticate do it.
So if we look at this one,
we see that we have the URL.
Then again we have a code, and
then we send along the name.
So this code, again, is a secret.
We don't want to have the secret in.
Our code.
But for this first example,
let's just see if it works.
We will also see that it works a lot
faster than the automation account because
it doesn't have to spin up so much.
It's very simple containers.
It's spinning up and it's
almost instantly there.
You can build a complete backend
for a website or whatever.
Azure functions if you want to.
And here we've got back the hello
world because we send along world,
but if you would send along Con 42 and
run it, we should get hello Con 42.
Now, of course again, it
can use diminish identity.
It has logging built in.
Actually, it has very nice logging
because if we look at the logs here,
we can actually log in real time.
It needs to connect for a moment, and now
if we keep this open and run it again.
And everything goes well.
We see actually all the things
happening here inside our screen,
so all the logs being done.
So it's a very easy one to
also troubleshoot because you
can just see what's coming in.
These logs are saved in application
inside, so you can also look at them.
If we go back to the
application insights here.
We will see these same logs we just
saw in the application insights
because I send it to the same table.
This API key.
We had this function key.
If we want, we can
create new function keys.
We can have multiple
function keys for the same.
Endpoint we create.
So we couldn't give anyone
who uses it a different, API
key, a different function key.
If one is compromised or whatever, we
can remove it or we can renew it and
make sure that they get a new one.
And like I said, it almost starts
instantly, but the authentication,
it's just by this API key
and not via a user account.
And in some cases.
We want to do this via a user account.
So here you can see again
the pros and accounts.
If we want to do our authentication
via a user account, we could add
something called API Management.
In between,
with API Management, I can create an API.
And in the backend I've got my Azure
function app, this Azure function app.
It's also stored in here.
I can look at it.
I can I believe look at
authorization credentials.
And it has like the key.
So the key we were using, I can
store inside my API management.
Where it's stored safely, and I
can create a different endpoint.
In this endpoint.
I could just open up for every
anyone, so anyone could connect to it.
But what I did, and I did it
on the all operations, I added
what's called a validate J watt.
So in this API call, I said that.
I want to validate if a JWT token, a JWA
take token is added, and if it's, if this
is not added, it should fail to call.
So if we go here and I would remove
the headers here and call this,
it takes a short while, and
then we should get a timeout.
It could be that it's working
due to the headers maybe already
being stored inside my run space.
Let me check.
It's still running,
but I think we're getting a timeout
because it's taking way too long.
And this timeout, it can take a while.
So what you see here is it did run.
So let me quickly clear the headers.
So let's set headers to zero or to null,
and let's run it again.
And now we see a unauthorized.
Because the headers was running tests
before and the headers were already there.
So you've seen already what
happens when it does work.
I can show you again if I run this,
it's just brings back the hello world.
I can still add the world to it
because in this automation I set
up that it's allowed to pass along.
See the queries.
So this way I can add user
authentication to my automation.
And this token I can store in many ways.
I can maybe in some systems and the a
username and password, or I can use a
service principle or whatever to create
this token and send it along via als.
And make it even more secure.
So these are like different
tiers of solutions you have.
And remember, no solution is perfect.
There will always be
better and worse solutions.
And with these automations, you will have
to be aware that sometimes you don't have
to go for the most complicated version.
In some cases, just running your script
on a VM is okay, especially if you don't
have to do it that often and you have
some kind of management machine available.
In a lot of cases, you want to look
beyond just a normal automation tool.
We have the Azure automation account,
we have the Azure functions, but
by adding application insights, key
faults, API management and so on,
we can string these things together.
To create a way more resilient and
stronger system, and I now shown you
different techniques you can use and you
could combine these all together to make
your automations secure and resilient.
I hope you enjoyed this talk.
If you have any questions, you can
ask them via the channels or on
my LinkedIn socials or whatever.
On my blog, I write about stuff like
this, and normally I would also hand
out stickers, but online this is a bit
hard, so if you ever meet me in person
somewhere on my blog, you can also find
where I will be speaking in person.
Next, find me if you like this sticker
or the one you saw at the start.
I've always dreamt of just going on a
holiday while my work continues because
I've automated myself and that's my
goal before I quit with working in it.
Not sure if we're gonna make it,
but with the inventions of AI and
so on, it's starting to look better
and better that we can go this way.
Thank you for listening.
Enjoy the rest of the conference
and I'll see you later.
I.