Hello all, so let me introduce myself.
so I have overall 15 years of IT industry
experience with a robust background
across financial technology, digital
marketing and automobile sectors.
I excel in platform engineering,
reliability engineering and DevSecOps
SaaS operations and service delivery.
My expertise includes multi, Tenant
SaaS applications and cloud native
microservices and streaming data platforms
complex event processing, event stream
processing and cyber security Like
today we are stepping into the future of
fleet management, where transformative
technologies are reshaping, the way manage
and operation operate vehicle fleets with
the integration of artificial intelligence
and the internet of things and Kubernetes.
We unlock new possibility of
efficiency and safety fleet
management is the process of managing.
let me introduce about
What is fleet management?
Fleet management is the process of
managing a company's vehicles and
assets through their life cycle.
The goal is to improve efficiency and
reduce cost and increase performance.
The fleet care, fleet management
itself like Itself introduced
is a process of improving the
efficiency and cost and performance.
how about integrating AI, like AI and,
IOT along with this fleet management
and along with the Kubernetes, like
cloud native solutions like Kubernetes.
So picture, like in a picture of
world where AI predicts maintenance
needs before issue rises and IOT
optimizes routes in real time and
Kubernetes scales operations seamlessly.
This convergence can reduce, reduce
operational cost by, up to 30
percent improve vehicle reliability
and enhance driver safety.
so let's deep dive into this actually.
so let's deep dive into that, it actually.
So So, how AI is transforming
fleet management?
if you see the, the current, diagram,
and if you see that, you have the company
vehicles, let's say if you have a,
ambulances, or, maybe, a trucks, like a
company will be having trucks, and, the
companies will be having, companies like
Uber, A any other, any, carpet companies,
having their own vehicles, so what happens
is, like we need to, obviously like com,
fleet manage manager, like fleet managers
should able to, see the dashboards,
like what's going on, what's going on,
with the tire pressures and, vehicle,
tire, tire pressures as well as fuel and
certain things like a fuel and maintenance
like, they have in the dashboards.
So based on that they will try to take
the decisions of buying the new vehicles
or do the maintenance and improve
proactive performance measures So we
should see in the dashboards actually,
you know We should see what's going in
the dashboards and we should get an alerts
actually that's how it is right now when
it comes to like how AI is Revolution
in this whole process, so artificial
AI is revolutionary revolutionizing
We how we manage optimized vehicles.
So through advanced Learning
algorithms and predictive analysis.
So AI enables decision making automobiles
complex operation task The transformation
is helping fleet managers to reduce
costs and improve safety and maximize
efficiency At an unprecedented, scale.
So it's, so what, it's more of because
of algorithms, predictor, by using AI and
predictor, AI with predictor algorithms,
we can easily, we can, we can easily, we
can, we can simplify the decision making
and, and automate any complex tasks.
so this is about like how, AI
transforming fleet management and,
next coming to the next slide.
so how, So due to the rise
of, fleet management, there
are two things are happening.
One is a predictive maintenance and
other thing is, efficiency boost.
So when it comes to predictive
maintenance, a drives advanced,
advancements in, predictive
maintenance and reducing vehicle
downtime by at least 40% and advanced.
and advanced algorithms analyze the
engine data to forecast potential
issues before it even occurs.
So that's a big, that,
that's a big, big thing.
that, that really big thing when it
comes to the, vehicle maintenance.
It's and again, it, coming to
the efficiency boost AI overall.
operational effi, improve the operational
efficiency with organizations experience
improving, improvements of around 30
percent and smart systems optimizes
routes, schedules and, resource
allocation real time, like smart systems
such as like IOT devices are going
to optimize the routes and, schedules
and resource allocation real time.
So this is really, big change.
so IOT internet of, IOT means
like internet of things.
So how it is, so which is really useful
in real time tracking and monitoring.
IOT provides three things,
like one is enhanced safety and
another one is transparency and
third one is risk reduction.
So when it comes to enhanced safety,
IOT enables real time tracking of
vehicles and condition, and condition.
Monitoring enhancing of, fleet safety
and they're coming to say transparency.
IOT enabled sensors offer
increased transparency.
This provides a clear view of
fleet operations and it comes to
the third thing, a risk reduction.
Like now companies using IOT reporting
25 percent decrease in risks.
This is due to enhanced
monitoring and data.
. And, let's, coming to the, third, third
key component, which is a Kubernetes.
So like in Kubernetes, how,
how Kubernetes, powering modern
fleet management infrastructure.
So we, because we need infrastructure
in, IT we need infrastructure and a for
running ai, predictor, fleet management.
We need, so we need it in edge
computing for which is essential.
E even in, essentially in even in a
fleet management right now, so how
fleet care, how a Kubernetes is,
revolutionizing this whole process,
it is, using, so if you see, so what
Kubernetes is doing, it's an underlying,
key backbone of all these things, so
because if, backbone of these things,
so what it is providing So Kubernetes
provides a central, containerization
and resource management capabilities for
robust, robust fleet management systems.
And, and, second thing, it
comes like automated deployment.
See, so Kubernetes, provides seamless
scaling, automated deployment of
applications and microservices for real
time data processing, which is for IoT.
And third thing, resource optimization,
and has the resource utilization and
efficiency management of computing.
Resources for AI and IoT operation.
And the third thing is it provides
security and flexibility, flexibilities.
so when it comes to security and
flexibility, it isolates environments
with an multi environment support.
Like a cloud on prem hybrid for secure and
adaptable operation, which is very key in
fleet care management So when it comes to
the scalability kubernetes allows seamless
scaling of application microservices
that process large volumes of iot data
In real time, it's really like IOT data
is the key for a fleet management and
to get the a real time data Of a vehicle
so and when it comes to the deployment
it can automate deploy kubernetes can
automate deployment Scaling operations
in fleet management ensuring that
updates and new features are continuously
integrated and delivered and also
Kubernetes provides resource efficiency.
Kubernetes enhances resource utilization
by effectively managing computer
resources essential for processing
AI models and handling IoT data.
And the fourth thing is
isolation and security.
With its containerization feature,
Kubernetes provides isolation
environments for different applications,
enhancing security and reliability.
And flexibility.
It supports various environments.
such as cloud, on prem hybrid and making
it adaptable, changing data processing
and AI requirements in fleet management.
In summary, Kubernetes serves as a
backbone for deploying and maintaining
robust, scalable, and efficient systems
necessary for the dynamic field of
IoT and AI driven fleet management.
And coming to the success story
of AI predicting, breakdowns.
So transform, transformative
AI integration.
Our cutting, like cutting edging,
our cutting edge, machine, system
revolutionized fleet management by
processing an unprecedented, 500, 000
data points from real time vehicle
sensors, comprehensive engine diagnostics,
and detailed maintenance history.
Histories to spot emerging
mecha, mechanical issues before
they become, critical failures.
And second thing is game
changing predictive power.
By harnessing the power of advanced
algorithms, the system delivered
an enhanced 90 percent success in
forecasting mechanical failures
two weeks before they occurred.
This breakthrough enabled fleet managers
to schedule maintenance strategically,
virtually, eliminating unexpected
breakdowns and their associated costs.
And third thing is
dramatic financial impact.
The result, spoke volumes.
Like organization deploying this AI
solution captured an average of 2.
3 million in annual savings.
The, the gains came from eliminating
emergency repair premiums.
Strategical, scheduling maintenance during
off peak hours and maximizing vehicle
uptime enhanced fleet productivity.
Another success story, like
IOT, like about IOT, like how
IOT improving fuel efficiency.
So one is like a vehicle, diagnostics.
And second thing is fuel savings.
And third thing is a
sustainable operations.
So when it comes to the vehicle
diagnostics, real time IOT sensors
monitored, engine performance,
deliver, behavior and routing
efficiency and leading to, data driven
optimization of fleet operations.
And then coming to the fuel savings.
Implementation resulted 20 percent
improvements in fuel efficiency,
saving an average of 150, 000 annually
per, vehicle, per 100 vehicles
while reducing maintenance costs.
And, the third thing is,
reduce sustainable operation.
Reduce carbon emissions by 20
25%, equivalent to removing 50
percent cars from road annually.
while meeting, stringent environment
compliance standards and coming
to the success story of Kubernetes
scaling operations when it comes
to the fleet care management.
seamless deployment, one is seamless
deployment and second one is scalability
and third one is reliability.
when it comes to, seamless, deployment.
Kubernetes orchestrates orchestrated
flaw a flawless deployment across
multiple cloud environments
reducing deployment time from Days
to minutes while maintaining 99.
99 up time And the second thing is
scalability fleet operations scale over
3300 within six months Handling peak loads
of 10, 000 concurrent vehicle connections
without performance degradation.
and third thing is reliability.
System maintained 99.
99 percent availability throughout
scaling with zero critical incidents
and automated failure, failover,
ensuring continuous service delivery.
The future in, data driven, up to,
so the data driven, so the four key
pillars like here is optimization,
efficiency, safety, and intelligence.
optimization is something like continuous
improvement through predictive analytics.
And, we can, achieve optimization
using continuous improvement
through predictive analytics.
And, efficiency can be achieved
by streamlining operations and
resolution, resource utilization.
And that thing is like we can
achieve safety with enhanced
risk management and prevention.
And fourth thing is intelligence
by achieving data driven
decision making foundation.
The powerful combination of AI
and IoT and Kubernetes creates
a comprehensive ecosystem for
intelligent fleet management.
This integration enables real time
data analysis, predictive maintenance,
and automated decision making.
Transforming traditional fleet
operations into agile, efficient,
and future ready systems.
coming to the multi cloud, deployment,
so we are three things here,
like a flexible cloud strategy.
Dynamic scaling, enterprise reliability.
so when it comes to flexible cloud
strategy, deploy and manage solutions
across AWS, Azure, Google platforms, while
maintaining united control visibility.
And second thing is dynamic scaling.
Automatically scale Resources up and
down based on demand and ensuring
optimal performance while controlling
costs and across all cloud environments.
And, third one is enterprise reliability.
Achieve 99.
99 percent uptime distributed
architecture and automatic failover,
keeping your operations running
smoothly across multiple regions.
This is very, this multi cloud
deployment is really critical,
adaptable in, fleet care management.
So coming to the actionable
insights and coming to the road map.
So three, there are three strategic
phases on proven methodology.
The methodology deliver results
through three focused phases.
One is a comprehensive fleet
management and second one is a
seamless technology deployment.
And, third one is continuous
performance, optimization.
So coming how many days to get success?
so experience transformation in just 90
days with, with accelerated implementation
program, featuring weekly milestones
and, measurable KPI, improvements.
And, with this combination of
IOT AI and, Kubernetes, we can
achieve, success in 90 days itself.
And, and, like most of the clients
consistently achieve 20 percent
improvement in operational efficiency
through AI powered automation, real time
monitoring, and predictive analytics.
And, embraced, transformative technologies
like, AI lever, leverage AI intelligent
algorithms to optimizing fleet care,
fleet management and predict maintenance
needs through unprecedented accuracy.
So for, and coming to the IOT, transform
your fleet with real time vehicle
monitoring and data driven insights from.
smarter decision making.
And third one is Kubernetes.
Build resilient, scalable infrastructure
that adapts to growing your fleet while
ensuring seamless data management.
key takeaways and next steps.
The powerful combination of AI, IoT
and Kubernetes create a transformative
foundation for moderate fleet management.
Delivering, predictive maintenance, real
time monitoring, and scalable operations.
Begin your digital transformation
journey by identifying key pain
points, selecting pilot projects,
and improving these technologies in
phases to ensure sustainable success.
Organizations can embrace these
innovations now will gain significant
competitive advantage through
improved efficiency, reduced
cost, and enhanced safety metrics.
And, thank you for, attending my, session
for, about this fleet care, management,
along with IoT, Kubernetes and, AI.
Thank you.