Hello, my name is Brian Loomis
and I'm with Progress Chef.
I'll be speaking with you today about
the practicalities of using open
telemetry and telemetry in general
to provide feedback given business
metrics and on operational systems.
We've built a prototype, which
I'll share with you, based on
some specific needs of operating a
software as a service, SaaS service.
Logging and tracing fine for small
numbers of customers and for direct
developer interaction debugging, but
they have some limitations when it
starts getting into larger systems, and
especially with regard to understanding
customer behavior within the context
of what they're licensed to use, and
maybe some limits on those licenses,
and with automating the scalability
of large clusters of services, right?
So when we get really big Those
logs get similarly big, and they
actually can't really drive as
much sort of high level behavior.
recognizing that OTEL and OTEL like
systems have some press out there
indicating they're hard to implement, we
found it pretty approachable, and we'll
try and give you some idea of the specific
types of metrics we're trying to collect,
how we're using tracing, and events to
make those actionable and to achieve
superior performance on our services.
Let's take a look at what's coming up.
There's a quick agenda.
We'll talk about topics in roughly
this order here, a little bit about
traditional one way telemetry and some of
the challenges we're hoping to overcome.
We'll talk about our design
with feedback loops included.
And that's a key concept in there,
that the telemetry is going to
drive some other services and other
events elsewhere in the system.
Our example application, how enterprise
systems work and what we need from a
licensing business metric perspective
to show back to the customer.
Or our tenant in SAS, and then we'll
wrap up with some final comment.
The data we've collected through telemetry
is pretty important in driving two
very important pieces of the business.
One is obviously revenue, and the
other one is customer satisfaction.
Those two are.
Pretty tightly coupled, right?
Our solution, the Chef 360 system
that we're putting this into is a
multi tenant SaaS application, right?
Meaning we have multiple organizations
and each of them may have one or more
tenancies or I would say operations
and data subdivisions to them.
And the whole solution operates on
a consumption based billing, right?
So truly as a service that you
order up a certain quantity of.
Operations that you want to achieve.
Fundamentally, we want the SAS customer
to dynamically change their demand
proportional to where they see value.
In DevOps, this means going from
a limited prototype, evaluating
functionality and maybe some candidate
workloads in a limited capacity, to
increasingly broader use across the
enterprise, eventually having the most
critical systems under management.
Often this is tens or hundreds
of thousands of machines to us.
The customer buys in incremental
workloads of the operations they perform.
Seeing value in new cases as the system
adoption grows, as they add more machines,
as they add new types of jobs in our case.
This presents unique challenges to
the standard MELT model of how we
traditionally look at logging, right?
Events are usually tied in that model
to very small, smaller than business
increment type operations, right?
So maybe an API usage, but not
necessarily a single operation
that the customer is paying for.
Or they're very strongly correlated
with the logical implementation
and not the business value.
Meaning that sometimes we're tracking
events and logging based on an API.
But that's not really what
the customer is paying for.
We may be tracking things on.
A CPU basis or a disk space
basis, but the customer may be
ordering a very different units.
Tracing similarly is constrained
often to non production debugging
because it's so verbose.
And even that logging is often too
voluminous to support any actionable
insights for either the service
provider, our team, or for our customers.
And the final issue that we were
facing was really that We're not
being responsive enough at scaling
for large numbers of tenants, right?
We'd often have to have them wait for a
little while until we provision some more
hardware or whatever it happened to be.
So it's, there's a delay between when they
want to scale up their demand and when
we actually provision it to address this.
We developed a telemetry driven
approach that provides visibility
into the license features and the
number of operations, maybe the demand
quantum that the customers ordered.
And that enables us to dynamically
scale our workloads, and it also
enables us to bill very accurately.
So I'll keep going here.
This is a typical, maybe an
enterprise application life cycle.
And certainly true for enterprise grade.
SAS applications, right?
A customer is going to purchase
a tenant, a tenancy in the
application through maybe a license
or a transaction in a ERP system.
They may install the app, it may be
hosted in the hosted SAS service,
or it may also be available on prem.
It may be in their cloud, right?
Through an AWS marketplace or an Azure
marketplace, or maybe in an air gap
environment, even further removed from
maybe internet accessibility, right?
Now, for your application, you want
to have your application behave
the same way everywhere, right?
And so that's going to be one theme that
we see coming through this is that our
telemetry structure is exactly the same,
whether any of these cases are true.
If the application is multi
tenant like ours, then you then.
There possibly is more than one
tenant per organization, right?
A customer may have a tenancy for
maybe manufacturing in Asia and one
for manufacturing in Europe, and they
may be separate, possibly the same
org, but also more likely they're going
to be multiple tenants in there from
different organizations that need.
Really significant privacy and
security walls between them.
And so one of the keys also is that
our telemetry can't bleed through,
from one customer to the next customer.
And maybe not even between one tenant and
another tenant within the same customer.
Once provisioned, each tenant
is going to have users which
perform their operations, right?
The license may grant them a certain
quantity of these, an as a service, right?
You're ordering on demand in
billable chunks, maybe, tranches,
or maybe by feature set even.
Whatever they'd like to purchase, right?
They may want this feature,
but not this other one.
And that may change over the
lifetime of their license, right?
It may be updatable.
If you're thinking in app purchases,
yes, that's certainly true.
Probably bigger things than Candy
Crush power ups, but maybe more like
DevOps minutes in our case, in Chef
360's case, by the thousands, right?
So you may order in chunks
of big computing power.
These are some of the events
we want to capture, right?
We want to know what these are,
and we want to translate them into
metrics to show usage over time.
We also want to know how the system,
the underlying system, is performing.
When this increased load gets put
on, so we're going to take metrics
on the average load and that could
be as simple as communities metrics.
In more complex terms, we call these
aggregate events, and they inform
our customer usage specials, goes
back to the customer, tells them,
Hey, you're licensed for 500 units.
You're getting close.
We're going to throttle you
down as you get closer to that.
Maybe you're at 95 percent
of your capacity and you're
going to hit a limit there.
we'll also show that back to the
customer on a dashboard that Brings
these hotel events and metrics
back to them for full transparency
control from their side, right?
We want them to see the workloads
in business terms, right?
We want to see it in units of measure that
they're buying, not necessarily what we're
charged as the service provider, right?
We may be billed for CPU minutes or
disk space or something like that,
but the customer is actually buying
something that's different, right?
They're buying a capability.
In business terms, right?
There are buying DevOps
minutes or number of jobs.
We typically build and show 360 biological
job running on a customer node, which
we call the job node, strangely enough.
okay.
And that's our per instance measure that
they can scale up or scale down, right?
They don't necessarily care how
much, how many EKS containers
are running in the background.
We want to abstract our platform cost
effectively from what the customer is
actually buying as a service, right?
So why don't we do non
Otel type solutions, right?
Why do we go to the extra
trouble of adding Otel in here?
And so our typical scenario that we're
dealing for when I say like enterprise
grade solutions, imagine you have a
customer that has 100, 000 containers
that only last for a few minutes each.
It's a very dynamic environment,
scales up and down very quickly.
some of those particular nodes
that we would call them, execute.
Very quickly, and then
they disappear, right?
They get dehydrated.
They're ephemeral, as we call them.
these are some of the questions that
we realized that we're asking ourselves
as we're going down this OpenTelemetry
journey, and why OpenTelemetry?
You think of like how many times you've
just, shipped a system to production
that has had debug tracing turned on.
You're like, just in case something
goes wrong, I'm just going to turn
on all the logging and we'll scale
it down if there's, a need to scale
it down and just take less logs.
But, we're designing for the doomsday
scenario where we have to have all
the logging all the time, right?
And, this gets worse obviously with
distributed systems because you have.
Uncorrelated logs, right?
You have to bring them all together
somehow that may have come from different
time zones and they're interleaved,
might call this data dog diving.
I don't know.
He's making that one up.
But also we have to realize that
someone's going to have to look
through all these logs, right?
So Even though we may be taking in
a lot of trace information, a lot
of debug on every API call, on every
request, every response into the system.
Fundamentally, at the end of the
day, your developers are then
your tier three support, right?
If something goes wrong, the developer is
going to have to look through this massive
data and try and intuit something better.
I would also argue, without a, an
intelligent assistant on that or some
way of parsing that, that becomes
really Unscalable really quickly.
Imagine you have a hundred customers
that are feeding into a SAS service log.
figuring out where that one customer was,
when they had an issue is looking for the
proverbial needle in a haystack, right?
How many times have you just
bolted on events, every time
an API is called, right?
Every time an endpoint gets hit.
you may be logging an awful lot
of data, but you're also probably
logging the request and response.
Do you go through and actually
take the time to, apply privacy
filters to that export right before
it gets out to maybe the service
provider or something like that.
And in many times when we go, Oh,
customer, you just go ahead and collect
all the logs and then you implicitly
tell us that we can see everything in
those logs and you just ship them to
us, you zip them and FTP them over to
us and we'll take a look at them, right?
It's a very asynchronous process, but
it also doesn't provide any privacy.
And in a multi tenant environment, this
is very important, because we're going
to want to do things like auditing events
and show the customer who had access
to do what thing at what point in time.
And we're looking at a multi
tenant log scenario, unless
we've parsed them out by tenant.
Another one we run into a lot is
how many times do you then go, okay,
I've got this big body of log files.
I'm going to have to put a reporting
solution on top of it, right?
I've got to build a dashboard.
I've got to do all this stuff.
And then you realize, Oh, wait,
there are tools out there.
And other people seem to be able to do
this a lot easier than I'm able to do it.
And then you go, okay, what if that
log file isn't actually answering the
question, the fourth bullet on here, what
if that telemetry is not useful to the
rest of the people in your organization,
it's useful to developers made to
troubleshoot a particular debug instance.
to find a bug or something like that.
But what about the next time the customer
comes up for a licensing discussion?
And you want to be able to show
them, Hey, you've been using,
80 percent of your allocation.
Do you want to buy another 10 percent
or something like that so that
you have enough capacity to grow?
We're not collecting those metrics.
What we're collecting is a lot
of very low level APIs, right?
And this drives some very
particular customer behaviors.
I put a couple in here.
The customer may overbuy, in which
case they're spending a lot of extra
money on their solution, which kind of
looks like shelfware to them, right?
And they go, Ooh, maybe, when budgets
get tight or something, maybe I actually
go in and evaluate like how much I'm
spending on this solution over here.
or they have, Even worse behavior that
they limit themselves and they go, I
don't want to go back to procurement
and add another quantum of things.
And so they're taking themselves
like they're constraining their own
value because they can't see how much
they're using that solution, right?
And they don't want to go over
because that would be very
difficult organizationally.
And they'll not even ask you the question
of could I get better service, right?
And so both of these, when I say the
business metrics get impacted and
Your revenue as a service provider
gets impacted because the customer
is holding back from the conversation
you really want to have, which is,
can I pay for just what I'm using for?
Okay, and then in the last one,
it's more of an operational concern.
we call this the horizontal pod or
auto scaling only gets you so far.
What do you set your pod size into?
If you're adding multiple
customers in there that are
variable sized and may get bigger.
Over time and may eventually either
themselves or the combination of
these customers may exceed the
reasonable size of the cluster, right?
You have vertical pod auto scaling.
You can add more physical nodes.
You can get monolithically bigger.
But how do we actually get real
auto scaling that can burst out?
Here we're sharing the architecture
diagram behind our solution,
showcasing a multi stage telemetry
processing basic dashboard.
On the far left side, you'll see the
license service, which talks to our
tenant provisioner service, which then
allocates capacity in one of many,
potentially many Kubernetes clusters for
the new tenant based on current usage.
for requested usage.
If the customer gets larger, too large
for a single cluster, we want them to
burst the next available cluster and have
that automatically be created for them.
Telemetry is captured identically
on prem as in our SAS service.
Multiple clusters will feed into
a local telemetry dashboard for
a single organizational customer.
This is then optionally anonymized
and fed to a global hotel collector
operated by Chef and Progress, which
allows our organization to monitor
any on prem clusters, which opt in
and all of our own SAS clusters.
There's three things to note with this.
Really, the first one is the lines
backwards going between the local
collector and the provisioner allows
for feedback when the cluster gets full
at capacity and causing a new cluster
to be spun up and new workloads then
to be allocated to that new cluster.
Cluster number two, for instance, and then
the second piece of feedback there is the
global collector can send a signal back.
Overbilling to tell the customer
they're actually close to exceeding
their contractual limit and see if they
want to upgrade their licensed usage.
The third thing to note here is that
basically we have the same tiered
pattern for any customer type.
Our home chart does not change if we
deploy on prem in AirGap or in customer
supply cloud or cloud hosted by us.
It's the same exact pattern.
The customer would get on prem
everything up to that orange local
customer telemetry dashboard.
And then we would still have some of
the global services wrapping this, but
otherwise they get everything in the
middle of this picture and they operate
exactly the same way and they can see all
of the telemetry that they want to see.
This sort of talks a little bit about the
sample application that will be out there.
This is just a sample
hotel implementation.
It's roughly equivalent to the prototype
that were, it shows all the items that
are in the diagram just before this.
And.
Really, the differences here are
in the bottom bullets there, our
application, our main application is
a bunch of scratch containers that
are written for AWS EKS, they're in
Golang, and so our hotel implementation
is in Golang, not in, not in NET.
NET seems to be an easier one to
present to people and has a really good
wall and everything, you'll be able
to download the code samples from the
repository and the references here.
Just to quickly go through
this, there's a client tool that
asks for jobs to be submitted.
it basically runs for multiple customers.
It simulates demand into the system.
the ones in parentheses I'm not
supplying, they would typically
be part of this service, but a
routing service or a load balancer
basically that takes those clients.
request and puts them in the
right clusters where that
job was deployed, right?
Obviously we'd have to talk to the
provision service to go, okay, where
did customer with tenant A and this
particular workload or license go to?
oh, that's over in cluster five, right?
So that routing service, we leave
as a exercise to the reader.
We have the job service.
which takes client requests and may
have some limits implied, right?
So it goes, okay, you are only
licensed to five operations.
So we'll cap you at that point.
And then we will not take requests
after that point, but it also has
its own internal capacity, right?
So that once it gets full, it's
expecting that the load balancer or
the provisioner is going to redirect
all that load to a new cluster.
the cluster management service itself,
and we just talked about that, which
will provision new clusters when
once at capacity or near capacity.
And then finally, on the outside, the
observability platform that you might
bolt on to your telemetry service
might be a Prometheus or a Grafana
or something to visualize this so
that an operator can go, okay, what's
actually going on in my cluster?
Might bring in the Kubernetes metrics
as well, CPU, disk, network load, things
like that, as well as the business metrics
that we're getting from the hotel side.
Coming over here, I wanted to show
you just a quick, animation here.
And I'll see if I can
play this video here.
I did this in chat GPT.
So apologies for the, the simple
nature of this and everything.
I put the prompt in,
the repository as well.
So you'll see that out there.
If you want to do your own animations
and things like that, this basically
shows a red and a blue customer.
Each with a limited number
of jobs that they have.
eventually the starting cluster
gets full of requests and
bursts out to a second cluster.
And you'll see that blue eventually goes,
Oh, wait, I'm limited by number of jobs.
I don't want to have to wait like red
customer did to start my next one.
I actually just want to go ahead
and bump up my license and you'll
see all of blue's jobs then come in.
So I'll just play this
quickly for you here.
The red has to wait for
you to submit his next job.
Red wanted a total of eight,
so it's done for right now.
Let's see what blue does.
Ah, blue asks for five more.
Has a little more space in there.
So his are just going to go into cluster
number two, which is a little bit bigger
size than maybe cluster number one was.
And there we go.
Blue is done.
There
we go.
So talk a little bit here about the
differences between where we were, our
legacy solution and our new solution,
and especially the types of metrics
that we're able to track right now.
And I apologize, I just probably
blow this up on your screen to
see a little bit of the detail and
everything, because there was so much
stuff that we really added in here.
Really three big things to note here.
One, we're using tiered
hotel collectors, right?
So one set of collectors
will forward those with OLTP.
OTP, sorry, over to another, the
global hotel collector as well, right?
It gives us a chance to anonymize
data before sending it on to
the next stage of processing.
Also lets the customer who's in control
of that local one to opt in to letting
us see some, none, or all of their data.
Having that local on prem collector.
Let's the customer also manage
their own telemetry, but if there's
an issue, they can change how
much they're sending us, right?
And then we can, we could be opted in
to help troubleshoot and then they can
dial it back when they're all clear.
And the third thing to note here
is that the business metrics of job
nodes, the sizing of a job, right?
Our sort of quantum, the little red
and blue dots from before, right?
How big or small it is compared to
the capacity of the cluster lets
us decouple the actual cluster.
The customers running on from the
service that they're buying, right?
They're buying a set of those dots.
They're not buying whether it's in
cluster number one or number two.
They may be on a portion of one
cluster and maybe in there with other
tenants that sort of fill it up.
Or they may spend multiple clusters
because they've gotten very large.
Or they may even decide that
they want to move some workload
and expand on Prem or whatever.
vice versa from on prem into
the cloud to gain efficiencies.
That way the customer is paying for the
operations they need, not more or less.
Okay, so can you do this in logging alone?
You can.
I think for all the questions that
we brought up here, it's Locking
is certainly an easy solution, but
it does have a couple drawbacks.
Ones that you're going to have to
write some code, some bits around, that
OpenTelemetry really gives us for free.
it doesn't help us, for instance, when we
get to implementing privacy and auditing.
The logs are they're low tech, right?
They're shared between organizations
at a very granular level.
You want to be able to get
rid of privacy PII in there.
You want to be able to
provide traces for debugging.
You don't want all the other noise
that's going on from maybe other
tenants in the infrastructure, even if
they are from the same organization.
Telemetry processing
can give us that, right?
And can aggregate some of the things
that we would normally track as Five,
10 different API calls in a row to go.
That's one count on a business metric.
That is one operation that we
would bill you for basically helps
us as a SAS provider as well.
Isolate customer data
from each other, right?
So that helps as well, because we'll
have a little customer ID on there.
The other thing is that remember we
talked about customer buying behavior.
We don't want them to
behave irrationally, right?
We don't want them to overbuy because
they're afraid they're going to run out.
We don't want them to limit their usage
because they're afraid they'll run
over in terms of billing or they'll
have dynamic billing applied to them.
We provide customers basically a
flexible mechanism where they can buy
chunks of, Quantum of operations, right?
So you can buy 500 or a thousand or in
chunks of reasonably useful increments,
but then that any set of increments
mirrors their actual usage, right?
So they see steps up in their licensing.
It's not a gradual curve or any sort
of performance problem where they miss,
Maybe submit a giant job and then they
realize, oh, that wasn't the job I wanted
and it spikes their load and we don't
have a way to go, wait, let's hold off
on that one and have that discussion with
the customer and go, is that really what
you wanted to do and get them into the
plan that they're really looking for?
what we don't want to have is a mismatch
between billing and what they're at, what
value they're actually seeing, right?
So the business metrics give us
that aggregation, that abstraction.
Okay.
And then finally, of course, on the
troubleshooting side, our operators
already knew with our previous
implementation, having 100 customers
in the same logged cluster, it's
tough to follow a single logical
operation through that, right?
Much less through one server.
But then if you think of 30 or 40
containers where you're having to
aggregate, cross them and trace
between them what really happened,
and you don't want to bother the
other 99 customers in that cluster.
Okay.
So some technical notes
on the prototype here.
We're using simple hotel emitters
and collectors, the local collectors
followed by a global collector again.
each of those is a container that can
embellish those input events, the tracing
and the metrics, and create other events
as part of feedback to the manager
processes, like provision and billing.
Decoupling our cluster capacity
from logical customer deployment
helps solve the HPA only gets you
HPA only gets you so far problem.
Horizontal pod autoscaling, right?
If a customer needs 500 scale units
and we can only get up to 100 per
cluster, then our provisioner knows
that he has to put another 4 out there.
There's some things we
don't do yet, right?
So there's some things that will
be totally transparent with moving
workloads between cloud and on prem.
That's tricky.
That's not an easy thing.
It's not something that hotel
necessarily gives you out of the box.
pinning allocations from that
provisioner to specific clusters.
So you need to stay in a GDPR region
or have some special licensing like
that, or also putting true AI in
there, or maybe machine learning to
make intelligent provisioning choices.
Those are all areas for us to grow.
Again, to summarize new versus old,
this is at the business level here.
we're using tiered OpenTelemetry.
This helps us grow with our
customers and very transparent.
We have the same code base for
on prem as our hosted service.
And it's a multi tenant solution
where the customer sees their own
dashboard and controls how much they
want us as a service provider to see.
Between this and another complementary
on prem solution, we can bring
business metrics together.
With the customer licensing and
Kubernetes performance data to show
a more complete picture back to the
customer so they can take their own
appropriate action and really self service
based on what they want to use, right?
Isn't that the whole purpose of telemetry?
And finally, I'm going to
say, we picked open telemetry.
There are a lot of other
solutions out there.
Prometheus, Datadog, Splunk,
a lot of these will enhance
logging to a great degree.
We didn't want something specifically
that would add extra load onto
the services that we're doing.
It had to be something that was native
in the service that it could emit
telemetry, but it wasn't an extra
burden to have on there another.
Either a pull mechanism or a,
an agent of some sort that's on
there that's also running, right?
And wasn't really, I would say cloud
native, but really not container friendly.
So finally here, this shows
some resources for the talk.
An OTEL getting started
in NET, really easy.
Takes five minutes.
an OWASP logging checklist.
so if you haven't been out to the security
site and seen what you should log and what
you shouldn't log, it's a good example
of what the security folks might ask for.
And our repository.
For our dot net sample, the
one that I wrote, and that
will be available by the month.
If you shoot me your email,
I'll notify you directly.
Otherwise, just follow the space and
you should see the update when it hits.
and then finally, the documentation
of the Chef 360 system.
If you want to understand some background
of what we don't want to talk about
jobs and runners and things like that.
Okay, and that actually should
be GA within days of this
talk as our hosted service.
So we're pretty proud of that.
Finally, thank you for
listening to this talk.
We wish you a very helpful and inspiring
conference 42 from Brian and Chef.
Goodbye.