Good morning, everyone.
Today, we're going to discuss DevOps
meets AI, automation cloud native
infrastructure with intelligent tools.
Why use AI in DevOps?
DevOps is all about the speed,
automation, and continuous deliveries.
But as the system becomes
more complex, the traditional
method struggles to keep up.
So AI brings intelligence to DevOps
to predict failures, optimize
cloud resources, automate tasks,
strengthening securities, and so on.
With AI, we can achieve higher
efficiencies, reducing downtime
and smoother operations.
What is the need for AI in DevOps?
So the challenges in traditional DevOps
are manual overload, complex natives,
security, and AI will enhancement with
intelligence monitoring, automated
security, and reduce the downtime.
Here we have some AI driven automation
in cloud related infrastructure.
Key AI capabilities.
Predictive analytics.
It detects the system
failures before they occur.
So that's much easier to
downtime the occurrence cause.
And self healing system.
So when it predicts itself,
heals and automates, then
resolute revolves the issue.
And smart auto scaling adjusts
the resource dynamically.
AI security and compliance
proactively prevents the threat.
You have some key technologies in ai.
AI, and DevOps is powered
by cutting edge technologies
that include machine learning.
AI learns data to predict
failures and improve automation.
Natural language processing NLP helps AI
understand and generate humanlike text.
Computer vision, AI can
analyze and interrupt virtual
data for monitoring systems.
Robot process automation, RPA,
automates repetitive DevOps tasks.
Deep learning uses advanced neutral
networks to make intelligent decisions.
These are technologies that enable
AI resolution, DevOps workflow.
Some real world examples
in AI, that's for Netflix.
It optimizes cloud performance for
seamless steaming and coming to Google it.
It detects and increases the
security for proactive threats.
And when we talk about AWS, it
automates the infrastructure management.
And while with GitHub it, it is used
with AI assisted coding, helps the
DevOps team to be more productive.
Let's discuss about some key
benefits of AI in DevOps.
So AI brings several key benefits out of
it, in which the faster software delivery,
that is like it automates testing
and deployment for quicker releases.
an improved reliability AI predict
failed use enhance system stability
better security AI continuously
monitor for threats and vulnerabilities
Optimized resource management AI ensures
efficient cloud usage reduces the
cost enhanced developer productivity
AI assisted coding speeds of
deployments Challenges of AI in DevOps.
While before in the before slide, we
have discussed some of the advantages,
but also that comes with the challenges.
Data quality and availability.
AI needs the high quality
data for accurate predictions.
Integration complexity.
Merging AI into existing DevOps
pipeline can be a bit difficult.
Security and privacy concerns.
AI systems must be secured,
compiled for the regulations.
Skill gap.
Teams need expertise in both AI and
DevOps for successful adoptions.
Overcoming these challenges
require careful planning,
investment, and upskills.
Future of AI in DevOps The future of AI
in DevOps is exciting with advantages
like AI powered autonomous DevOps, i.
e.
AI driven systems that
self manage and self heal.
Hyper automation, i. e. combination
of AI with automated tools
for zero manual interventions.
AI driven security operations,
i. e. AI continuously detects and
responds to the cyber threats.
Smarter CI CD pipelines.
AI optimizing the entire
software delivery lifecycle.
As AI technology evolves, it
will be further enhanced DevOps
efficiencies and innovations.
Some key takeaways.
To summarize, AI is transforming
DevOps by automating,
predicting, optimizing processes.
Leading companies like Netflix, Google,
AWS are already leveraging AI in DevOps.
AI improves speed, security, efficiency,
but also prevents challenges like
integration and data quality.
The future of AI in DevOps
is promising with smarter
automation, self learning systems.
The future of AI is promising and it
will definitely shape the future into
a software and operational theme.
Here are some references where
these information were taken from.
So coming back to the conclusion, AI
is revolutioning DevOps by improving
automation security efficiencies.
As AI continues to advance, it
will further enhance DevOps, making
software development operations
more intelligent, effective.
Thank you for your time.
I'm looking forward for your questions.