Welcome to the secret to
handling dynamic secrets.
It usually starts with,
a security requirement.
Your security team realizes that you've
been running in cloud for quite some
time, and it's no longer sustainable
to copy paste a bunch of API tokens
and database passwords across different
applications that you've been developing.
So they tell you have to migrate
everything to a secrets manager.
And this seems, mostly easy, I
guess you have to just find every
single instance of a secret and
paste it into a secrets manager.
But it turns out this is a
little bit more complicated
than someone might think, right?
The minute you centralize secrets
in a secrets manager, whether
it be an API token or a database
password, your application now has
to go retrieve it over the network.
And there are a number
of concerns with this.
Whether you're a platform engineer or
developer who is responsible for managing
their own cloud native application
and the infrastructure underneath it.
There are a number of concerns
you might have with an application
reaching out to a secrets manager,
whether that be network connectivity
or just generally the availability
of your password and API token.
And it turns out it gets a little bit
more complicated than that, right?
What happens when you have
to rotate the secret, right?
Imagine you have a security
requirement number 208 or something
that means that you have to
rotate that secret every 30 days.
now you have to coordinate
with your application.
Your application has to reload, reconnect
to the secrets manager, and connect
to the second version of the secret.
Ultimately, after some buffer period of
maybe four or five days, you'll delete
the old version of the secret just to
make sure your application is working.
This works Okay, for maybe one
application, if you're just managing a
single application that's connecting to
the secrets manager, but what happens
when you grow your environment and now
you have multiple applications waiting
to connect to a secrets manager to get
an API token and a database password?
it's a little bit challenging to
figure out which applications need
to retrieve which password, which
applications need to access the API token.
And if you ever have to rotate this
password or this API token again,
you now have to make sure that
every single application that is
potentially using this shared API
token and password have to reload.
Now there are a couple
solutions around this, right?
And the first is, trying
to automate some of this.
I spend a lot of my time automating
and trying to figure out better
workflows for building security into
applications and infrastructure.
And it turns out that there's one really
big secret to doing dynamic secrets.
And when I talk about dynamic secrets,
the ability for an application to
handle a new secret that it has to use.
The secret is actually investing
in some developer enablement.
There is no magical tool, and
unfortunately, no magical workflow.
That will automatically do this for you.
Unfortunately, this requires an
investment into enabling developers,
providing better documentation.
It also means that you have to understand
the patterns that are involved in
order for an application to support
and a constantly rotating secret.
The reality is, in a cloud native
application, you have to be responsible
for handling dynamic configuration.
You expect any dependencies
to change, right?
And why shouldn't we depend, why
shouldn't we make sure that we are able
to depend on an ever changing secret?
The answer is, we need to have a little
bit of a paradigm shift in how we develop
our applications to handle secrets.
Traditionally, we are very used to
having one secret that we never touch
and hopefully will never have to change.
But in a cloud native environment, that's
not possible to expect that, right?
From a security posture perspective,
you want to make sure that you are
rotating your secrets on enough
of a frequency so that you do not
have to worry about someone using
those credentials or an unauthorized
service using those credentials.
So investing in developer enablement is a
big portion why you have to have some kind
of secret and handling dynamic secrets.
As I mentioned before, there are some
categories of secrets though, right?
We traditionally think of a static
secret where we manually copy and
paste this somewhere, probably
into a secrets manager, and then
we manually delete the old secret.
This is all done manually.
And this works perfectly fine.
You treat a secret like a key
and a value, and you inject it
into your application, right?
Now, more and more platforms, especially
in the cloud native environment,
are offering rotated secrets.
This means that automation
retrieves and stores the new secret.
And you manually decide to
delete the old secret, right?
So this is more common if maybe
you're seeing a managed database or
some other managed service that's
offering an API token or a password.
It will help rotate it
for you on your behalf.
You'll just have to make sure
in your application that you're
able to consume the new secret.
Finally, there's the dynamic secret.
The dynamic secret means automation both
generates and revokes the old secret.
I'm going to be showing HashiCorp
Vault, which is a secrets manager.
In as a demonstration of some of these
patterns, but dynamic secrets do exist
quite a bit across large cloud nativist
states in which you've built significant
automation to handle this, right?
So if you have a dynamic secret,
automation will generate the new
secret for you, and it will revoke the
old secret on some kind of cadence.
These are the three categories.
It goes from more manual to,
of course, more automated.
It doesn't mean that every secret is
going to fit into a dynamic secret, right?
You can and you will have secrets,
even in a cloud native environment.
That are static.
And that's because there are some systems
that will always have an API token that
you need to manually and go and generate.
Unfortunately, this is part of
the systems that we work in.
It's part of integrating systems
in a large organization as well.
So you will always have some kind
of static secret, but more and more,
especially as you have, services
that are enabling the rotation of
API tokens using an API, you will
get something like a dynamic secret.
Today, we are going to learn more
about dynamic secrets, but the
patterns that you learn here do
apply to static and rotated secrets.
That's because we are trying to describe
patterns for the most extreme scenario in
which most secrets are rotated frequently
and you expect them to change, right?
So if we're talking about patterns for a
dynamic secret, the same rules will apply
to static and rotated secrets, mostly
because this is about how an application
reacts to a secret dependency change.
So what does it mean to
handle a dynamic secret?
There are three parts to the workflow.
An application must get the secret.
This is actually divided
into two substeps.
The first is authenticating to the secrets
manager and then, using the secret, right?
So once you authenticate to the secrets
manager, you can get the secret and
you can use it in the application.
The second part of the workflow is
actually about changing the secret.
The secrets manager or maybe
yourself will change the secret.
You'll rotate or expire the secret.
In the secrets manager, the application
has no awareness that you've done this
unless you tell the application that you
have actually changed the secret, right?
And telling the application that you've
changed the secret means you either reload
the application or the application detects
the change the secret and reloads code.
This is very important to know,
especially if you have dynamic secrets.
These three parts of this workflow
are required for any kind of workflow.
rotation or any kind of changing secret
that you have in your application.
It's not much different than let's say
if you had dynamic configuration, right?
If you have an application that is
retrieving dynamic configuration
from a configuration server, this
workflow looks pretty similar, right?
Authenticate to a configuration server,
retrieve the configuration properties.
If those configuration properties
change, then you must reload, right?
It's a common enough pattern for any cloud
native application that's built to be
cloud native, but we just typically don't
treat secrets like this because, secrets
don't change as often, or traditionally
we haven't changed them that often.
So the pattern still applies even
if you're doing a static secret
or you're doing a rotated secret.
It doesn't have to be dynamic.
Patterns for dynamic secret can be broken
down into two, two separate patterns.
The first is that the application
is agnostic of the secrets manager.
What does this mean?
the application doesn't request
secrets from the secrets manager.
It doesn't connect to the
secrets manager at all.
Actually, it refers to a separate process.
The separate process authenticates to
the secrets manager and then injects it.
We'll go more into this.
a little bit later.
Then there's the
application aware approach.
The application itself is aware
that there's a secrets manager and
it needs to make an API call to the
secrets manager to get the secret.
So this means that you use some
kind of API or SDK request.
Both patterns are valid.
I do hear a whole number of debates
on whether or not one is better than
the other, and I can certainly tell
you there are benefits as well as
disadvantages to each, and we'll cover
some of that in more detail once we
describe some of the technicalities
and the differences between the two.
So let's start with application agnostic.
As I mentioned before, application
agnostic means that there is
a separate process that is
handling the authentication and
the injection of the secret.
Usually this injection is in the form
of environment variables or files.
You get to choose.
Most applications are more familiar
with environment variables, and so
the application will read the secrets
from the environment variable.
Overall, it's a pretty
straightforward process, right?
You've got a separate controller or
separate process that is going to handle
interfacing with the secrets manager, and
the application doesn't have to change.
Nothing has to happen.
It just continues to read from
environment variables as it wants to.
This works pretty decently for
a number of applications across
many different frameworks.
It works really well for older
applications that you might
replatform into a container,
but you don't necessarily want
to refactor the code, right?
So when the password or the API token
changes, the separate process, handles
the retrieval of the new secret.
The separate process is constantly
monitoring the secrets manager.
It could be on a schedule, or it could
be some kind of event subscription.
And it's going to retrieve the new secret,
re inject it into the environment variable
or file, and then the application picks it
up from the environment variable or file.
Application frameworks like Spring Boot or
NET, they do have some kind of live reload
configuration properties from a file.
So that means that you can reload the
application once it detects a difference
in the configuration properties or file,
which makes it more straightforward.
If you have a programming language
or framework that you're not sure
if it supports live reload, you
may have to write it yourself.
But effectively, you would be
looking for a file difference or
some change the environment property,
and then you would be reloading.
Now, there are other ways that
you can think about doing this.
And it's not just, going to involve
some kind of separate process.
if you are on Kubernetes, for
example, We're going to do this.
if you're on Kubernetes, for
example, you may have a separate
process that actually reloads the
application on your behalf, right?
The application itself doesn't have
to do a live reload, doesn't have
to detect a difference in the file.
Instead, you can have some kind
of separate process reload the
application for you, right?
It could, either kill the process
that the application process ID that
the application is running on, or it
can send a signal to the application.
I need you to refresh something.
a good example of this that I'll mention
is that if you are using the spring
boot actuator, in the spring boot
framework for your development teams,
the actuator has a refresh endpoint.
You can make an API call to refresh.
values in the application, right?
Other frameworks do have some kind of
refresh capability as well that you
can maybe build as an API endpoint
and then expose that for your separate
process to handle the reload for you.
So you don't have to necessarily
support that in the application itself.
You can do that outside the application.
So once it reloads, then it will
get the new secret, and that's
pretty much all it needs to do.
This is a pattern that's
pretty common for Kubernetes.
If you are running on Kubernetes, you
often will find that there's a number
of Kubernetes operators out there.
That will load in external
secrets from something.
it will load in an external
secret from a secrets manager.
It will handle the
authentication on your behalf.
It will retrieve the secrets that
you need, and then it will inject
the secret as a Kubernetes secret.
So the Kubernetes secret can be
added as a file volume or it could,
be added as an environment variable.
In newer versions of Kubernetes, it is
suggested to add them as volume amounts.
but not every application supports,
reading from files and there are some
things that you do have to refactor
on the application side in order
to potentially read from a file.
Most applications standardize, at least
in the past, in the past on environment
variables and expect to do environment
variable injection as a default.
So there's, there are two
choices, but both are supported.
So you can do a Kubernetes
secret as a file, or Kubernetes
secret as environment variable.
I'll show the environment
variable example.
So the important thing is that this
application is a Spring Boot application.
it's not as relevant, but it's
important to recognize that it is a
Java application, and it does expect
to have environment variables like a
database username, a database password,
a static payments processor username,
and a static payments processor password.
All of these in my Kubernetes
manifest for my deployment are
injected by environment variable.
I read the value from a Kubernetes
secret called payments app database
with the key username, with the
password, and everything else.
So there's two separate
secrets that I'm referring to.
One is for the database and
one is for the processor.
And so these are things that maybe
I keep default in my application.
I expect to read them as
environment variables anyway.
And so I don't really have to do any
significant refactor in my application.
One important thing to know is that
the database password here is being
stored in Vault, and being generated by
Vault dynamically, while the processor
password is going to be static, so
it's stored as a key value pair.
I'll show how both get processed
and injected into the Kubernetes
secret, but there will be two.
Important thing to also note is that
again, this is a Spring Boot application.
I'm reading from environment variables.
I could very well render this asset
of application properties as a config
map or something else, but I'm just
injecting them as environment variables.
The next thing that I'm going
to do is I'll just check that
my operator is up and running.
the operator that I'm using today
is the Vault Secrets operator.
The Vault Secrets operator works
with HashiCorp Vault specifically,
although there are many other operators
that you'll find that inject secrets
from other secrets managers as well.
But the operator pretty much does
the function of authenticating
to Vault on my behalf.
which is why I have a custom
resource called vault auth.
It uses a Kubernetes service account.
And then I can define exactly what
secrets I want to retrieve from vault.
This is pretty, standard of
a pattern in terms of custom
resources across Secrets Manager.
So you'll define what
kind of secrets you want.
If it's a static secret,
this is a key and a value.
and this key value, is a password and
username for my payments processor
that I've stored in my Secrets Manager.
So I'm able to retrieve it as I need to.
And I will define my secrets
destination as payments app processor
and refresh after 60 seconds.
This is a pretty frequent refresh,
you might not need 60 seconds.
You could be 30 days, you
could be 15 days, right?
I don't suggest you do 60 seconds unless
you have a secret that always changes.
And finally we have a
rollout restart target.
there are Kubernetes operators
out there that do support
some kind of rollout restart.
They leverage the Kubernetes rollout
capability that you can target
a deployment, a daemon set, or a
stateful set, and it will restart,
the application on your behalf.
This, Mivalt secrets
operator does support that.
So I'm targeting my
payments app deployment.
So anytime the secret changes,
it will roll out and restart
the application for me.
And the dynamic secret is, very similar.
The diff difference is that I am getting
a username and password dynamically
anytime I request it from Vault.
So it's going to be a unique database,
username and password each time.
So I'm going to deploy the custom
resources related to the secrets so that
I can hopefully see that a secret has been
created, with those custom resources, the.
The operator is going to
create two sets of secrets.
One is for a processor and that
has the username and password.
The other is the database.
So we'll check out the processor first.
You'll notice there's a
username and password field.
We also have the database as well.
One thing to know is that if you
need a different format, you don't
want username password like this.
You want them in a file somewhere.
There are some operators that
allow you to have a custom
resource definition that sort of
templatizes the file type you want.
I'll apply the deployment, which we're
going to call payments application.
And it's going to start up with an
initial database username and password.
In the logs, I do print them out.
Do not print your username and
password in plain text in logs, but
I'm doing this for the sake of example.
So when it first starts up,
it's going to have 971, a suffix
of 971 for its username, and
a password prefixed with 084.
And we're going to wait for a little bit.
this will expire after three minutes,
not every database password you'll
want to expire after three minutes.
most of the time you'll want to
set it on a much shorter cadence.
I'm doing this for the sake of example.
so the way that Vault works is
that it has dynamic credentials.
These credentials have what
is called a time to live.
Vault will lease a certain set of
credentials for a certain amount of time.
And then after that certain
amount of time, it will revoke and
expire the credentials for you.
It is something that
you have to monitor for.
You do not get any real awareness
of whether or not the secret
will expire unless you actively
check, how long it's been, how
long that secret has been around.
So the lifetime of the secret
is controlled by Vault.
you can check out the
logs for the operator.
You'll notice that there was a rollout
restart failure when it initially started
up, but there's no indication yet that
it's going to retrieve a new secret.
So we'll just keep waiting
until the secret gets rotated.
It's been about a minute and a
half and so it's your time out.
Just about now.
if you are not familiar with dynamic
credentials and this is the first time
you're working with a lease, I recommend
that you wait for the lease to be two
thirds of the way through its lifetime.
after two thirds of its
lifetime, then rotate.
So it gives you a little bit of time,
to expire the old credentials and
make sure that you've actually your
application works, but you'll notice
that the new app, the application has
restarted and there's a new set of
usernames and passwords for the database.
So this one ends in 099 and
there's a password of Q9S.
So that is how you can do an
application agnostic approach.
there are some benefits to the
Of course, you don't have to
refactor your application, right?
My application could still happily use,
environment variables from Kubernetes
secrets, and it was none the wiser, right?
Everything else was
handled by the operator.
The operator reauthenticated and helped
me roll out and restart pods on my behalf,
and it issued a new username and password
for a database on my behalf as well.
This is pretty nice.
It means I don't have to go looking
for where these database usernames
and passwords are being referenced.
Instead, what I have to do
is just Make sure that it
connects to the secrets manager.
it makes things a lot easier
from a development perspective.
Now, not every development team wants
to do the application agnostic approach.
and there are a couple of reasons for why
they would not necessarily want to do it.
I encounter a number of developer
communities who prefer to
do everything in the code.
And that's because their application
is particularly performance sensitive.
There are some significant
performance requirements.
That means that they do not accept
any latency, even though Kubernetes
rollout restart is a rolling update.
meaning it's not going to roll
everything, roll every pot at once.
It is going to do it gradually.
it is not sufficient from a performance
standpoint for the application.
So some development communities prefer
to build in the connection to the secrets
manager within the application itself.
Other times it's partially because
they might be developing a developer
community that is being supported.
They might be developing a cloud
native application, but it doesn't
necessarily run in containers.
and so the result is that I
have no choice but to interface
directly with a secrets manager.
they don't have an external
automation process or external
process that can handle the
authentication and injection, right?
Instead, the application itself
has to do everything on its own.
So what is the application aware pattern?
The application aware pattern
is a little bit different.
And then the application now has
to be aware that a new secret, it
needs to retrieve a new secret.
This is a bit nuanced, right?
It's not so easy to tell an application
or for an application to understand,
Oh, this, the old credentials are
going to expire, now I need new ones.
it's not quite intuitive, right?
So there are a couple
patterns to understand.
The first is that in your
code, your application needs to
authenticate to a secrets manager.
Then it needs to track expiration.
There are two ways in which
their code could track
expiration for a secret, right?
So imagine you have database
password version one.
you can set a timer for database version
one, database password version one, and
say, okay, I know that it will be done.
It will be gone in three minutes.
So at two minutes, I am going to
get a new set of secrets, right?
or you can subscribe to events.
So this could be a queue that someone
has put together and they're saying, Oh,
I'm going to make sure that I have, some
kind of event that's getting published
that gets sent to my application.
My application will subscribe to that
event and recognize that this new, this
new set of secrets is going to get,
is going to need to be created, right?
because there's some event that's
saying it's going to expire.
So there are a couple important facts
about this that you have to keep in mind.
The first is that you need to
gracefully shut down any connections.
If you're using an API token or
a database username and password
to connect to a database or any
kind of third party service.
You need to gracefully
disconnect everything.
And this is something I have to emphasize
with developers, especially as I work
with them, then even working with platform
teams who have to enable developers,
I'm often talking to them and saying,
are, do you have any kind of graceful
shutdown or some kind of connection
handling so that you can disconnect
everything that's using the old password?
And they're like, I didn't realize that.
I thought I would just shut it all down.
it turns out you do want to
make sure you're gracefully
shutting down those connections.
And then you can inject new
credentials for new connections.
And then if, let's say the secrets
manager goes down, you do have to handle
retries within the application as well.
So there are a number of patterns you have
to consider as you do a code refactor.
So there's a lot more, logic that you have
to include in your application if you're
doing the application aware approach.
Okay, so we'll take a look at what this
looks like, from an ideal perspective.
Spring Boot is very nice because
it offers two, I guess one, one
library that allows you to inject
the credentials from Vault, into your
configuration, and then it does offer
an SDK for you to interface with Vault.
So it's very convenient.
the first, library that you'll probably
work with is the Spring Vault library.
The Spring Vault library is the base
SDK or base API call to Vault itself.
And then there's Spring Cloud Vault.
Spring Cloud Vault uses Spring
Vault and Spring Cloud Vault injects
configuration properties on your behalf.
So it will retrieve information
from Vault and then inject it into
configuration properties for you.
And they're both really fantastic
examples of good patterns for doing
an application aware approach to
connecting to secrets managers.
And so that's why we're using them today.
But you'll need to add these
dependencies into your application.
Now, if you're using something
like Go, NET, any of the other
language frameworks, you may not
find something that exists, right?
Some libraries do handle
retries, some libraries don't.
do your research, double check
which libraries are able to handle
retries on your behalf, which ones
do injection for you on start up.
and make sure that you are verifying
whether or not those behaviors are
something you're going to need to
write or your development team needs to
write in your application or otherwise.
so there's quite a bit of
research that you'll need to
do in order for this to happen.
I'm including the Spring
Cloud Vault, config, library,
which injects configuration
properties, into my application.
And I'm going to be injecting the static
secret as well as a database secret.
In my application properties,
the biggest thing that you have
to define is authentication to
vault, which are lines five and
six, which is the secrets manager.
There are other ways in
which you can define.
Some kind of authentication if you need
to your secrets manager in this case
This is a configuration property that
you'll set for the library itself But
if you're using other libraries for
other secrets managers, you may find
some differences the other thing that
I do is I have to set a configuration
server to point to my secrets manager.
Again, this depends on the
library that you're using.
I'll enable the database secrets that
I'm going to retrieve as well as key
value secrets that I'm going to retrieve.
Again, these are more
specific to Vault itself.
So check your library for your
secrets manager to determine which
attributes you need to enable.
I've already stored the secrets in Vault.
So we'll pull up the secrets.
I'm sorry.
They're not at that secrets.
They're not at that path, but they are
going to be in the secret path that is
going to match the application name.
and I've.
I already stored them as formatted as
spring application properties, right?
So custom.
staticsecret.
username are custom properties
that I'm defining, and they are
in the form of spring properties.
You can choose not to do this.
I'm just doing this for convenience,
especially as I'm using the
Spring Boot application framework.
So once I set all of that up,
I can now, refactor my code.
if you, again, if you have other
frameworks that you're using, they don't
have an SDK like this or they don't have
a library like this for your use, you
will have to build some of this yourself.
You will have to go and authenticate
to Vault or a secrets manager,
retrieve the secret, and inject it.
so once you, once you get that process
done, the second thing you need to
do is, of course, handle a refresh.
and as I mentioned before, a second
part of the workflow is, detecting
when things need to be refreshed.
the first is that if you have a
static secret, you might choose
to do a scheduled refresh.
And a scheduled refresh works perfectly
fine, especially if you have a password
that's not going to change that often.
Now, if you have a password that
you're planning to change every 10
minutes, This might not be ideal, but
for a more simplistic implementation,
you can just schedule delay and
then refresh the application.
In this case, I'm using what
is called a spring, spring
applications context refresh.
And what this will do is refresh
the application context for me.
I do have to tell it what
objects to refresh and.
Exactly what needs to be recreated,
but it will issue what is
called a context refresh for me.
Again, you can change this to do some
kind of event subscription if you want to.
for example, you can detect whether
or not a secret has changed in
the Secrets Manager, publish that
event, and then your application can
subscribe to it, but most secrets
just can handle a scheduled refresh.
They don't need to have a
real time event based refresh.
The other thing that you might want
to consider, especially for dynamic
secrets, if you know that There
is a secret that's going to expire
within a certain period of time.
Let's say three minutes.
you can of course create some kind
of event system for you to find
some kind of lease expired event.
so in this case spring Vault has a
secret lease expired event as a lease
listener that I can, I can subscribe to.
And then if I detect a secret
lease expired event, then I
can refresh the application.
So this is the second way to do it.
Again, if you're using a static secret
or a rotated secret that has some kind
of frequency, like lower frequency
in rotation, you could probably
just do a scheduled task to reload.
The application with that secret,
or if you have a requirement for
a more real time approach, you can
do some kind of event subscription,
and that's what this is showing.
Either way, both patterns do work.
It's just a matter of making sure
that you are able to implement
it properly in your code.
So after you've set up some kind of
refresh mechanism, whether it be on a
schedule or you're subscribed to some
kind of event, the next thing you do
need to do is identify how to reload.
all of your objects, right?
and that's where this is probably the
most important part of the code refactor
that most development teams and platform
teams that I work with tend to forget.
I'm going to enable scheduling,
since I am scheduling a task
to reload a static credential.
the most important part that I would say
developers and platform engineers when
we're talking about dynamic secrets.
The ones that kind of forget is
actually refreshing the credentials
into objects that are using them.
What I mean is that it's not enough
to, for the application to refresh and
reload those usernames and passwords
into some kind of property list.
You need to re inject those properties
back into any objects that use them.
Good example of this is
like data source, right?
in a Java data source.
It needs to connect to the database
and it needs a username and a password.
I have to recreate the entire data source
with the new username and new password.
This is incredibly important because
if I don't, then my application will
continue to use the old username
and old password to continue
connecting to the database since.
It's not been refreshed.
The entire object has not been refreshed.
So I use what is called a Spring,
Spring Boot's refresh scope annotation
to basically let Spring Boot know you
need to refresh this entire object and
you need to make sure that you're using
the latest username and the latest
password from properties and rebuild
the entire data source on my behalf.
The underlying implementation does
a graceful shutdown of connections.
so I don't have to necessarily
implement that myself.
But if, again, you have a framework
that is not Spring Boot, and you have
a framework that you have to implement
this all yourself, you do have to have
some kind of graceful disconnection
capability built into the code base.
and you can do that by abstracting
that into a library, some library
that you've written yourself.
but do keep in mind that it's not just
a combination of detecting the event of
needing to refresh or change the secret.
The secret itself also needs to get re
injected into any, client connection
or data connection that's using it.
So those are two critical, pieces
of the workflow that I often see
are forgotten, especially when we're
talking about, refreshing applications
to account for dynamic secrets.
All right, so I'm going to run
the application, just to show
exactly what this looks like.
unlike the, Kubernetes example
that I showed, this will refresh
within the application, meaning
the application does not restart.
It just simply reloads the, credentials.
So the first database credential
has a username suffix of 8443 and
a password prefix of F A. And I
have an expiration of two minutes
for these database credentials.
So after about two minutes, this
application is going to rebuild the data
source with a new set of credentials.
What's important to recognize about a
number of the, these applications that do
have, are aware of the secrets manager.
You do have to handle any retries.
if let's say the secrets manager
is not on, not online, and you
can't connect to it, right?
You have to make sure that you can
cache the secrets, existing secrets.
If the secrets manager is offline, it's
not going to rotate the secret for you,
so things are fine for the most part.
the biggest problem is actually whether
or not the application itself can cache
these secrets, especially if you're doing
some kind of scheduled refresh, right?
you don't want to override
the previous secret.
Ideally, you want to keep the old
secret cached until you can reconnect
back to the secrets manager.
The other important thing to know is that
if you are doing this within a framework
that doesn't handle graceful shutdown, you
will have to handle the graceful shutdown.
Make sure that you're clear on what
that sequence looks like and make
sure you're clear on what handling
you want in your application.
it's not necessarily
just databases, right?
So we've now got the database
credentials refreshed.
I'm going to create, make an
API call to the application.
in the case of Spring, you have
to make an API call, in order for
it to reconnect to the database.
So it rebuilt the secret with
a new set of secrets, right?
Different, suffix you'll notice for
the username and different password.
it's got a new username and password
and now it's restarting a Hikari
pool or a database connection pool.
and so all of these are quite
important steps in the process.
Especially if you have
application aware approach.
All right.
So I didn't mention before there
are benefits and disadvantages to
each with application agnostic.
You're able to support many
languages and frameworks and you're
maximizing platform automation.
So I see this pattern quite a
lot in the kubernetes ecosystem.
most of the time when you have
heterogeneous programming language
types, different types of containers
running in a kubernetes cluster.
most languages.
Codebases don't really want the
work of refactoring, their code
in order to support a live reload.
and for the most part, the availability
of the application will depend on
the number of instances you have.
Most of the time you're running multiple
replicas of the application in Kubernetes
or some kind of cloud native environment.
So a rollout, that has like a rolling
update capability is not going to disrupt
the application significantly, right?
So the good news about application
agnostic approach is that you can
maximize your platform automation.
This makes it a little bit
easier for it to be maintained
by a platform engineering team.
However, there are reasons that I've
seen for people to do application aware.
There are organizations that I've
worked with who Standardized on very
few languages and frameworks, right?
They're all committed to spring boot
or they're all committed to dot net,
and they would rather invest in code
libraries or their own libraries to
handle all the code because they prefer
to control the performance as well as
the behavior of their applications.
In response to changes to
dynamic secrets, right?
And so the availability will
depend on the code base.
You're only as good as the
code that you've written from
a performance standpoint.
So there's a lot of testing involved.
There are a lot of patterns going
back and forth and trying to evaluate.
A lot of stress testing involved
when there's a third party or a new
library that's being introduced.
but if there are a few languages, only
a few languages that are approved,
and most applications are being
developed in a single language, then I
do see organizations who go with this
application aware approach, and they
would rather refactor the application.
The, downside is that it
doesn't maximize code refactor.
So you do have to take some time.
So refactor your code base to
handle and reinject the secrets.
And this is something
that is not going to be.
Let's say, abstracted away by a
platform team building like us the
equivalent of, let's say, like Spring
Cloud Vault for their chosen framework.
it is something that has to be
done within the application itself.
And I think that's the challenge
that I typically encounter with
development communities and
organizations who are trying to do this.
they're saying, Oh, I, I know I
need to reload this object with a
new username and password, but I've
done it in a nonstandard way and
we've had this code for four years.
It's not like I'm going to change it.
So there are some nuances there and
that most of the time platform teams
are trying to navigate and understand.
it does minimize platform automation,
so there is a good benefit in some
ways to this in that if your platform
is particularly resource constrained,
you don't want to be, adding more
separate processes to your cluster
to your container orchestrator or
something, this application aware
approach is a way to alleviate some
of the burden and put it into code,
but there's two approaches to it.
The cloud native approach, of course,
is to think about doing this from an
application agnostic perspective, meaning
that the application itself should not
have any significant or understanding
of the interface to the secrets manager.
But there are reasons for folks who do
want to do application aware, even if
they do have a cloud native application.
Before you choose either application
agnostic or application aware, though,
if you're a platform engineer or
you're a development team that's the
center of excellence for things, or a
developer community who's, trying to
standardize and trying to figure out
what's best, Do assess your applications.
I think this is the biggest
mistake that I've seen.
Most folks don't really know
what applications are running.
Document what your run times are,
where are the applications running,
how they're running, are they in
containers, are they not in containers.
There are a lot of systems that don't
have containerized applications and it's
a mix of the two, ideally in cloud native,
of course, we take we tend to, we tend
to think of cloud native as containers
only, but that's not always the case.
you is possible on occasion to have
an application that follows some
cloud need of principles, but not
necessarily running in a container.
And so do assess the runtime.
Do assess the frameworks
that you are using.
And if you're using spring boot, then
you have a lot of libraries available
to you that handle injection as well
as authentication to secrets managers.
There are many of them, and there are
very, they are very convenient to use,
but make sure you understand their
behaviors if you have, other frameworks
that don't necessarily support a
retry, doesn't support any kind of
interfacing with your secrets manager.
You may have to write some
additional code on your own.
So you do have to assess
what frameworks exist.
And then availability requirements.
Some applications do not, do not perform
well, with an application aware approach.
they are, and they perform better
with an application agnostic approach.
So they are horizontally scalable.
They are able to be reloaded and
rolled out with a rolling update.
Oops.
With a rolling update,
while others do not, right?
So it's dependent on your availability
requirements for your application.
And then finally, secrets.
Secrets, there are many types.
So you know, we talked about database and
API credentials, but secrets injected into
applications can range from certificates.
to some other kind of identification
that allows access, right?
if you have, let's say, AWS and
you're on a cloud service provider,
they may have their own unique,
authentication and instance information,
metadata information and things
like that for you to authenticate.
And you also want to document the
rotation frequency of secrets that
are being used by your application.
I would say most of the time, I don't
get a solid answer on what the rotation
frequency of application secrets are.
Most of the time I get, an
explanation of, we only rotate
it on demand, which is never.
We've kept this secret around for
three years and we've never touched it.
and that's perfectly fine.
It's just good to document, which
secrets you may expect to rotate
more frequently and which types.
Database credentials, for example, you
may expect to be, asked to rotate them
every 30 days from a security perspective.
certificates, you could have
a lifetime of 10 years, but
certificates themselves also expire.
and certificates, may have a rotation
frequency of 5 years or a year,
depending on the certificates.
documenting how these secrets are working
within the application is very important.
Doing this discovery phase will help
alleviate a lot of the questions and
inform whether or not you should be
thinking about an application agnostic
approach or an application aware approach,
when you think about having, dynamic
secrets or any kind of interfacing
with secrets in your application.
And finally, developer enablement.
After all, I said that
was the main secret.
all of the patterns that I taught here in
this session, you can take back, right?
Take back and build
documentation around them.
These are the most common
patterns that I've seen.
For developers to inject secrets
into their application and handle
more dynamic or dynamic secrets that
are changing more frequently, right?
so document these common patterns,
organize the workflows and
articulate and communicate them
to your development communities,
learn them for yourself as well.
and provide lots of code examples.
Most developer communities within an
organization or who are trying to build
their cloud native application, they
do want a lot of code examples, right?
Office hours are pretty critical,
and I would say do one or two live
refactors with certain development teams.
This has been really helpful.
in my experience, because you get a sense
of what the development team patterns are,
and you also get to identify any pitfalls
that you might not have thought about.
a good example of this, as I was working
with a develop, a development team,
and they had some specific patterns in
Spring Boot, and they didn't use beans.
They didn't use the annotation
for Bean, which meant that refresh
didn't quite work right for them.
it was good to understand
what they were looking for.
other teams that I had worked with,
they are using, let's say, GraalVM or
Native Image, and they couldn't use
Reflection, Java Reflection, right?
we had to write some code from scratch,
to help, detect whether or not those
credentials were changed and then refresh,
refresh these objects by local proxy.
like I said, this sounds maybe complicated
or if you're not familiar with Spring.
doesn't make any sense.
But the reality is there are
only patterns that you're going
to find during live refactor.
and it's good to learn those new patterns,
identify what the development communities
are using, what they're not using.
and it's helpful to build videos
around certain patterns, as well.
I think a lot of the, platform teams
that I've worked with, they're like, Oh,
can we just make a video out of this?
Like we'll just cut and,
cut away some of the pieces.
But the most important thing for us
is we just want to make sure that we
distribute this to our developer community
so they can see this live refactor.
And finally, from a development
perspective, you may have to build
new interfaces in order to support
this paradigm of dynamic secrets.
sometimes you don't have frameworks
that support a retry, a proper retry.
Other times You know, there are new
frameworks out there that are coming out.
and then you can't, you just don't have
the ability at that point to support
retrieval from secrets managers, right?
So you have to write your
own API and SDK for it.
so build the interfaces if you need it
and certainly assess any exceptions.
there are a number of communities
that I've worked with who went
down the application aware path,
only to find that it doesn't
really work for their application.
maybe a small portion, like 20
percent of their applications.
And so they'll end up doing
the application agnostic
approach for that 20%.
This happens for, maybe not
necessarily cloud native
applications, but applications
that Cloud Native, the Cloud Native
environment runs or accesses, right?
These are services that are not Cloud
Native themselves, but are heavily
dependent on by a Cloud Native service.
these could be date, older databases,
or they could also be, older APIs.
So do assess any exceptions
that you do have.
You will have a combination of
not application aware, but also
application agnostic approaches, right?
Because not every framework
will support it and not every
application will be able to interface
directly with the secrets manager.
And similarly, in the application
agnostic approach, you might not find the
capability exists in your runtime, right?
Depending on the container
orchestrator you're using or just
workload orchestration in general.
Finally, that's the end of The Secret.
it's a lot.
It's a pretty big secret, actually.
but I'm trying not to keep
it a secret any longer.
So if you do have any questions,
you're welcome to reach out to me.
All this material is
available on my webpage.
So feel free to review it and distribute
it to your own development communities.
If you're a developer who wants to handle
dynamic sequencing your application,
hopefully you have a sense of the
patterns that you need to implement.
If you're a security team or a
platform engineering team that needs
to identify and assess and educate
your development community on how to
use a centralized secrets manager.
hopefully this provides some valuable
information on how to improve the
overall adoption of your secrets
manager and make it a little
bit easier for your developers.
Thank you.