Hey everyone, welcome to today's
session from chaos to clarity
data lakehouse architectures.
So before we dive in, let me ask how
many of you have worked with data lakes
or data warehouses and how many of you
have faced challenges with scalability,
cost, governance or analytic performance.
So you're not alone.
enterprises are generating
more data than ever before.
So think about this every day
companies produce petabytes of
data from customer transactions to
mission logs by 2025 Global data is
expected to exceed 180 zettabytes.
That's more than double today's
volume So what's the problem here?
The traditional systems just can't
handle this explosion efficiently So
how do we turn this chaos into clarity?
That's where the data lakehouse
architecture comes in, which combines the
best of data lakes and data warehouses
into a single scalable platform.
So in this session, I will walk
you through why traditional systems
struggle, how lakehouses solve
this issue, and what makes them the
future of enterprise data management.
So let's get started.
So imagine a large retailer processing
millions of sales transactions daily.
So their data includes structured
purchase records, semi structured weblogs,
and unstructured customer reviews.
If they use a traditional warehouse,
they must constantly restructure
data before analysis, which might
delay insights and increasing costs.
So in the similar way, billions of
online transactions, supply chain
updates across global warehouses,
customer behavior data from clicks
and purchases, unstructured data from
chatbots, emails, and customer support.
So all this adds up to petabytes
of data every single day.
And guess what?
It's only increasing.
So data is expected to
grow 2x every two years.
So what challenges we are
running into this, right?
The number one is the scalability issues.
Most legacy systems just aren't
built for today's data explosion.
As data grows exponentially,
traditional databases slow down.
Struggle with query performance
and become expensive to maintain.
And the second challenge
is the structure problems.
Data lakes are meant to store raw data,
but without proper governance, they turn
into data swamps, which are unmanageable,
disorganized, and hard to query.
And the third challenge is the analytics.
So traditional data warehouses
require expensive infrastructure and
rigid schemas, making it difficult
to adapt to new business needs.
They are great for structured
data, but struggle with semi
structured and unstructured formats.
So at the end, like business needs a
system that is scalable, flexible, cost
effective and optimized for analytics.
That's where the data lake house come in.
So what is data lake house?
It's a modern data architecture
that combines the strength of both
data lakes and data warehouses.
So let's take a closer look at the
components that make lake houses work.
The first is the storage layer.
Optimized with open formats like
Apache Iceberg and Delta Lake
for scalability and efficiency.
Secondly, the metadata layer.
Ensures schema evolution, indexing,
and cataloging, making data
easier to discover and query.
Third, the processing layer.
Uses Apache Spark and SQL engines to
enable real time and batch processing.
And lastly, the governance and security.
Supports role based access, encryption,
and audit logging for compliance.
So by integrating all these layers, lake
houses solve the problems of both lakes
and warehouses, making data management
faster, smarter, and more cost efficient.
So what do we give the strengths of
both data lake and warehouses, right?
From data lakes, you get the
scalability, cost efficiency, and
support of all data types, right?
Like the structured, semi
structured, and unstructured.
From data warehouses, you get
performance, asset compliance, schema
enforcement, and optimized querying.
Think of a lake house like
a well organized library.
A traditional data lake is like
a warehouse full of random books,
messy and hard to find anything.
A data warehouse is like a neatly
organized section, but limited
in space and expense to maintain.
So a lake house, it's the best
of both worlds, organized,
scalable, and efficient.
So why does this matter?
Enterprises can scale from terabytes to
exabytes while maintaining performance,
unified storage and compute layers,
eliminate unnecessary data duplication.
So support for AML workloads without
additional data transformations.
So cost is a big deal.
When managing enterprise data, lake
houses help organizations reduce
storage and compute costs by up to 30%.
But how right scalability like scale
from terabytes to exabytes without
losing performance essential for aml
and real time analytics Second the
optimization 30 cost savings through
smart data management techniques reducing
unnecessary data movements And thirdly
governance maintain data quality and
compliance while keeping costs low
Data remains structured and accessible.
So the scalability, efficiency, and
governance, three pillars that make
lake houses, the go to choice for
modern enterprises, for instance, a
financial service company saved millions
annually by replacing their costly
traditional warehouse with a lake house.
Reducing redundant storage and processing
costs by optimizing tied storage.
So a major concern with data lakes is
that they lack ACID transactions, which
means data consistency isn't guaranteed.
So which the lake houses
will solve this issue, right?
With Atomosity, ensures transactions
are all or nothing, preventing
partial updates that can corrupt data.
Consistency, data remains in a valid
state before and after updates.
Isolation, concurrent
transactions don't interfere,
maintaining accuracy, durability.
Once committed, data stays permanent,
even if the system crashes.
so why does this matter,
for enterprises, right?
Enterprises can ensure data reliability
even at scale, like supports critical
applications like fraud detection
and real time financial transactions.
Now, for an example, think about
an e commerce company processing
thousands of orders per second.
Asset Compliance ensures that
even in case of a failure, orders
are never lost or duplicated.
Data is constantly evolving,
new sources, new business
requirements, new regulatory needs.
Traditional warehouses struggle
with schema changes, but
Lakehouses handle them seamlessly.
Firstly, we plan, assess current schema
needs and anticipate future changes.
Second, implement.
Deploy schema updates without downtime.
Third, validate.
Ensure data consistency
and query compatibility.
Fourth, monitor.
Track performance and adapt dynamically.
this flexibility allows organizations
to integrate new data sources
without disrupting workflows.
Moving to the next slide.
Lakehouses aren't just
about storage, right?
they enable real time
analytics using Apache Spark.
For instance, with the speed, process
petabytes of data with sub second
latency for real time decisions.
Secondly, flexibility.
Runs both BI dashboards and ML
models on the same infrastructure.
Unified platform.
Handles streaming, batch processing,
and interactive queries efficiently.
So whether it's fraud detection,
recommendation engines, or supply
chain optimization, Lakehouse
delivers insight in real time.
For example, a ride sharing company
uses lake houses to analyze driver
locations, ride requests, and pricing
data in real time, ensuring dynamic
fare adjustments within seconds.
So traditional ETL process
is expensive and slow.
Lakehouse has solved this by
enabling in place data processing.
First, with the ingest,
direct ingestion from multiple
sources without pre processing.
Data transformations happen directly
within the Lakehouse using SQL and Python.
Third, with the low immediate
data availability for analytics.
So this reduces infrastructure
costs, eliminates unnecessary data
movement, and accelerates insights.
As an example, a healthcare company
reduced patient data processing time from
24 hours to just 30 minutes by eliminating
redundant ETL steps in their lake house.
So in most enterprises,
data is locked in silos.
Different departments struggle
to access relevant information.
Lake houses solve this by
creating a single source of truth.
By, with secure role based
access to all data sources.
Powerful search and metadata tools
to find the right data instantly.
Seamless collaboration across departments.
So by democratizing access, businesses
boost efficiency and innovation.
So at the end of the day, data is only
as valuable as the insights it delivers.
So with the Lakehouse infrastructure
and architecture, 30 percent cost
reduction is expected through
optimized storage and processing.
And 90 percent faster queries, thanks
to the advanced indexing and caching.
So from predictive analytics to AI
driven insights, lakehouses help
business make smarter, faster decisions.
All right, so let's recap.
Here's why lakehouses are game changers.
Lakehouses scale from terabytes to
exabytes while keeping performance high.
They eliminate ETL inefficiencies
and enable real time analytics.
They ensure asset compliance
and strong governance for
enterprise grade reliability.
So they reduce infrastructure costs by 30
percent while driving AI driven insights.
So they bring governance, compliance,
and security to enterprise data.
So in short, lake houses provide
the clarity, efficiency, and
innovation Enterprises need to
thrive in data driven world.
So the future of data is here
and it's built on lake houses.
So thank you for joining me.
Let's keep pushing the boundaries
of what's possible with data.
I hope this session has given you
new insights on how to optimize
your enterprise data strategy.
Thanks again.
And I'll see you next time.