Hello everyone.
I Amani.
I'm a senior data scientist.
It is a pleasure to, be here today to
discuss how a transforming procurement
and supply chains procurement is no
longer just about sourcing supplies.
And managing contracts.
it has evolved into a strategic
function that drives efficiency, cost
savings, and risk management here is
playing a major role in automating,
processes, analyzing data at scale
and improving decision making.
The goal of this.
How AI improves efficiency and cost
optimization in procurement, real world AI
applications, supplier selection, contract
management, and demand forecasting.
These are the real world applications,
challenges, companies face in AI
adoption and how to navigate them and
the future of air power procurement
and next steps for businesses.
By end of this talk, you understand.
Why AI is not just an option, it is a
necessity for procurement teams looking.
Stay ahead.
procurement has traditionally
been manual, slow, and reactive.
AI is changing that by
making a procurement faster,
more s and cost effective.
let us see what efficiency gains we get.
AI powered automation is
eliminating repetitive.
Time consuming tasks from purchase order
processing to supplier evaluations.
studies show that AI can reduce
procurement processing times
by 37%, allowing teams to focus
on high value decision making.
Cost savings.
procurement is not just about
spending, it is about spending wisely.
AI power spend.
Analytics help businesses identify
hidden efficiencies, inefficiencies,
negotiate, Better contracts and
optimized costs, leading to year 15 to
20% reductions in procurement expenses.
In short, AI's shifting procurement from
operational function to a value driver.
in the real world Impact, let us see
how AA is, impacting the real world.
traditionally, supplier selection was
based on a relationships, historical
performance and manual research.
Yay.
Enhance, enhances this by analyzing.
Market trends and historical performance.
AI powered supplier selection
has increased accuracy by 42%,
helping procurement teams reduce
risks and negotiate better deals.
when it comes to contracts
management, procurement teams
handle hundreds of contracts making
manual contract review a bottleneck.
AI solves this by automating contract
review and highlighting the risk areas
in the contract, reducing the processing
time by 60% through AI powered analysis.
Enduring compliance and faster approvals
leading to shorter procurement cycles.
and now let's look into
demand forecasting.
Poor demand forecasting leads to,
lower purchasing are stockouts, yet
even forecasting models, analyze,
sale, trends, supplier performance.
And external factors will
increase accuracy from 70% to 95%.
These enables procurement teams
to reduce excessive inventory,
improve supplier coordination,
and minimize procurement delays.
Now let us look at the
challenges, in AI implementation.
Mostly like a data privacy.
Here I relies on massive amount
of procurement data, which raises,
security and compliance risks.
So organizations must ensure, regulatory
compliances like G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A-E-T-C,
also protect supplier.
And financial data from cyber threats,
build trust with the stakeholders by
implementing transparent AI models.
78% of the organizations
site, data security concerns
as a barrier to AI adaption.
Addressing these issues is a critical
for successful AI implementation,
legacy system integration.
most companies use waler ERP procurement
systems, AI integration requirements,
middleware solution to connect the
world and new systems phased adoption
plans to summarize, disruptions
flexible architecture to enable AI
driven procurement with 65 Center of
Enterprises are struggling with AI
integration work on these challenges.
Overcoming these challenges is a
key, mostly with, they can overcome
by going on instead of, rollout.
Now let us see how ai, I, powers the
contracts, like the smart contracts.
one of the most exciting innovation in
procurement is AI powered smart contracts.
These contracts use, black could use
blackchain and AI driven validations
to automate, contract execution.
why do smart contractors matter?
like for a fraud prevention, AI detects
irregularities and, prevents manipulation.
smart contracts automatically
enforce, terms and ensure that,
company policies, these contracts
are adhere to the company's policies.
and also the faster processing here
reduces contract validation time by 85%.
Teams to focus on
negotiations and sourcing
bottleneck, and.
Now let us see how AI helps in
manufacturing, AI manufacturing
procurement by predicting
maintenance needs and avoiding
supply chain disruptions.
Optimizing production plan
with AI driven demand analysis.
And to reduce the delay delays, automating
supplier coordination, we can use the.
In the retail sector, the
procurement faces inventory
management and demand challenges.
Here it can help here by enhancing demand
forecast for, better, stock control.
Automating inventory replenishments
based on the real time data,
personalizing supplier strategies to.
and now let us see how the, AI in
procurement can help technology
companies, in this, tech industry.
AI streamlines, the vendor selection,
optimizing it, procurement, helping
businesses to automate, contract
analysis for software and cloud services.
Analyze, complex service
segments to optimize, spending.
Now, let's see how AI
helps in, sustainability.
AI helps organizations reduce this
carbon footprint by optimizing supply
selection for sustainability, reducing
waste through predictive analytics,
minimizing logistics emissions,
leading to a 28% reduction in carbon.
Now in the risk mitigation, AI
powered early warning systems.
Like the risk management softwares detect,
supply chain risks with 85% accuracy.
This helps businesses proactively
mitigate risks before disruptions
occur, and hence supplier reli,
reliances and maintain, operations.
Now the AI driving strategies for
procurement, like beyond automation, AI
is transforming strategic procurement in
three key ways, data driven decisions.
Here turns the raw procurement
data into actionable insights.
Enable better forecasting and
supplier selection, and in
supplier relationship management.
Yeah, answers suppliers, tracking
predictor risk assessments
and engagement strategies.
S sourcing, yeah, helps in
procurement teams to optimize
strategies, reduce costs, and
improve supply chain resilience.
With procurement with ai, the procurement
is no longer just about transactions.
It is about strategy, intelligence,
and long term value creation.
In the future of AI power procurement,
AI adaption will continue to
expand, but businesses must focus
on maximizing the cost savings.
AI driven procurement saves, 3.58 millions
annually for small and medium enterprises.
Enhancing data security.
78% of businesses demand
stronger AI governance.
65% of enterprises struggle
with adoption, requiring,
structured implementation plans.
Instead of just buying the off the
shelf software under straightaway
using it, they should have,
structured, implementation plans
now.
To summarize what we had discussed
so far, like AI is optimizing
optimizes procurement with
efficiency, cost reduction, and
importantly risk management, AI
powered supplier selections, contract
automation, and forecasting Our.
Game changer actually.
Yeah.
Overcoming challenges like data privacy
and system integration is crucial.
We also discussed about AI driven
smart contracts and predictive
analytics will define the future of the
procurement companies that adopt ai.
Now we'll lead the next era
for strategy procurement.
Thank you all for time today.
AI reshaping procurement in.
We have just a few and the pace
innovation is only accelerating.
If you would like to continue
the conversation, feel free to
reach out to me on LinkedIn.
I would be happy to discuss AI
power procurement strategies and
how businesses can leverage this
innovation for compared advantages.
You can connect with me on my LinkedIn.
I appreciate your time and.