Hello everyone and good day.
I'm Srijan Reddy Anugu, a
technology manager with 20 years of
experience in emerging technologies.
My expertise spans across SAP,
cloud computing, and integrations,
and I currently work for
ADM in the Cincinnati area.
Thank you for joining this conference
on cloud based data integration.
Today, I will be sharing the best
practices, discussing the challenges,
and unveiling innovative strategies
for modern data driven ecosystem.
Let's dive into the topic.
Cloud based data integration
is a game changer for companies
that work with different kinds
of data in today's digital world.
In this talk, we will cover how these
systems have developed, what benefits
they offer, and the best ways to use them.
We will also see how cloud platforms
have improved older methods by making
data management more scalable, easier
to access, and more cost effective.
So let's talk about the evolution
of the cloud data integration.
So initially it was a traditional
on prem data integration systems.
In the early days, companies used data
systems installed on their own hardware.
The systems were reliable, but limited
by physical resources, needed a lot
of memory money upfront, and couldn't
easily grow with increasing data needs.
So the example for on prem are, the
SAP data services, the Informatica
ETL, the Dell Boomi, StrapLogic,
then, hybrid cloud strategies.
Companies then started using a mix
of on prem and cloud solutions.
Today, about 89.
3 percent of fortune 500 companies use
hybrid systems, spending an average of 12.
7 million a year.
This approach combines the
security of local systems with
the flexibility of the cloud.
So the examples for that is, again,
a cloud SAP data services system,
Informatica ETL, a Dell Boomi, a SnapLogic
ETL system, and Apache NiFi, and AWS
Glue also supports the hybrid scenarios.
Then the evolution of the
cloud native solutions.
Now the modern cloud native platforms are
best in terms of speed and reliability.
They can process data in just
2.3 milliseconds on average, and
maintain a 99.997% reliability
rate across different data types.
This makes it easier for
companies to handle complex data
tasks quickly and accurately.
And again, the example
for this of the AWS glue.
The AWS Data Factory, Google Cloud
Data Flow, SAP Data sphere, and
the application integration tool,
S-A-P-B-D-P integration tool.
Okay.
Now let's talk about the market
dynamics of this cloud platforms.
The cloud integration market is
quickly becoming DOM dominated
by three main platforms.
Making up almost 80% of the total market
share AWS leads with a 34.2 market share.
Thanks to its early start
and broad range of services.
AWS started in 2005, between 2005
to 2008, and Microsoft Azure is in
second place with 27.8 Azure as.
Picked up a lot in, last five
years, showing an impressive growth
of 42 percent year over year.
And Google Cloud Platform holds 16.
4 percent of the market,
excelling in the artificial
intelligence and machine learning.
Together, these platforms
handle a massive 7.
84 trillion integration
transactions every day.
About the same as processing all the
data in the Library of Congress every 3.
2 seconds.
So what are the key, benefits of
using this, cloud based integrations?
So the first thing that comes
is, elasticity and scalability.
So in a traditional on prem system,
scaling up a system, scaling
out or scaling up is a big task.
It's a downtime and it
affects the business.
With the cloud systems, it is on the fly.
and, we can.
Set the settings up such that if the load
is more the autoscale scalability happens.
So scalability is one
of the primary factors.
And global accessibility.
So there are many data centers for AWS
Azure, Google, Alibaba, and Oracle Cloud.
So they are omnipresent across the globe.
So because of those data
centers, the data accessibility.
is the core component, right?
So the speed increased,
the reliability increased.
And next, the cost optimization.
Moving to cloud integration
can significantly cut costs,
especially for security.
Organizations can reduce their security
expenses by nearly 60 percent compared
to traditional on premise solutions, with
average security coming in at only 3.
27 per GB of data processed.
Now, let's talk about What happens by
following the best architectural practices
for cloud native tool integrations?
So it reduces the
deployment failures by 72.
3 percentage Through automated testing
and standardized workflows and it
enhances the resolution speed by 58.
6 with better monitoring and the
automated rollback and enabling
in near continuous delivery with
95 percent weekly deployments to
streamline the deployment pipelines.
These tools leverage containerization.
orchestration and automated workflows
to accelerate deployment speed
and maintain high reliability,
allowing teams to respond more
effectively for the business needs.
And the another one, the modern
microservices architectures
transform cloud computing by
dividing monolithic appliances.
into independently scalable services.
This approach significantly
enhances deployment flexibility,
system reliability, and operational
efficiency, especially in large
scale cloud environments where
traditional architecture faces
challenges with complexity and scale.
Now, how is the data quality?
and governance in cloud
native architecture.
So automated data validation,
smart validation tools have
reduced data issues by 87.
3 percent and boosted
data consistency by 92.
1 percent across various system
parts making operations smoother
and analytics more reliable.
Compliance management.
Modern cloud systems have streamlined
compliance, cutting audit operation
time by almost 74 percent and
increasing audit success by 41.
2 percent.
This means companies can meet strict
rules while reducing extra paperwork.
Metadata management.
Advanced tools for managing metadata
have sped up data discovery by 68.
5 percent and improving data tracking
accuracy by nearly 80 percent.
This gives organizations a clear view
of the data flow, helping them make
decisions quickly and with Confidence.
Real time processing capabilities.
What do we get with this real
time processing capabilities?
So low latency.
Our system process data almost
instantly, taking just 8.
7 milliseconds for complex events.
It reliably delivers messages with a 99.
997 success rate.
So data loss is nearly eliminated.
High throughput.
It can handle huge amounts of data.
Processing 2.
8 million events every second, a 312
percent improvement over old systems.
This boost makes real time analytics
possible on a large scale systems.
So that is the reason why OLAP and
OLTP supported systems are built now.
Edge computing with edge processing.
We reduce response times by
over 90 percent globally.
Our distributed systems maintain
data accuracy with a 99.
999 percent consistency rate, ensuring
reliable performance everywhere.
Now, let's talk about some
common challenges and the
solution for those challenges.
So the common challenges are data silos.
Performance optimization
and security and compliance.
So coming to the data silos, using
schema matching and mapping techniques,
improves data integration accuracy by 64.
2 percent and cuts down manual work by 57.
8%. Performance optimization.
Query optimization frameworks
reduce data retrieval time by 47.
3 percent on average while
keeping data consistency at 99.
95%.
Security and compliance.
Multi layer security frameworks
lower security incidents.
By 92.
4 percent with only a minimal
increase in data access time, just 3.
7 milliseconds by using this cloud
native data integration solutions.
So now let's talk about the future trends
in the cloud based data integration.
So right now we do have
cloud based data integration.
What's the future of the
cloud based data integration?
First thing we could talk about
is AI argumented integration.
AI is the buzzword now.
So new AI tools can speed up
integration work, cutting development
time by over half, and improving
error detection significantly.
This lets developers spend more
time on important projects instead
of routine troubleshooting.
And second one is, advanced meta
management, metadata management, right?
So metadata is the heart of any company.
So for that, the modern metadata
systems automatically match data
formats with high accuracy, greatly
reducing the need for manual setup.
Tasks that used to take weeks
can now be done in hours.
The third, that I could talk about is
intelligent data quality monitoring.
So real time monitoring systems are
now much better at catching and fixing
errors quickly, ensuring data stays
reliable and useful across all platforms.
So the quicker we fix the
data, the quicker solution.
The business gets the data
immediately and the decision is
made immediately based on the data.
To conclude, transformative impact.
Cloud based data integration
represents a fundamental shift in
data management, offering substantial
improvements in efficiency, cost
optimization, and performance.
Best practices.
Success is closely tied to implementing
architectural best practices,
particularly adopting cloud native tools
and microservices based architecture.
The future outlook, the emergence of
AI driven integration capabilities and
advanced automation tools suggest a
future of increasingly intelligent and
self optimizing integration process.
Thank you everyone for joining
today and listening in.
Appreciate your time.
Thank you.
Have a good day.