hello everyone, my name is Mohammed
Waqas and I am a lead technical
product manager at QALY I have an
experience of more than eight years
in the product management industry.
primarily I am a software engineer.
and I've done my post
graduation in management.
So I've transformed myself to a product
manager for the past six years now.
And, I'm quite excited to
present this topic at this
amazing conference, Conf 42 2025.
so let's start, let's jump right in.
So today I'm going to talk
about how you can optimize your
product, your businesses, and your
methodology of product management
using multi tenancy architecture.
I will be sharing some strategies and
some insights around how businesses.
can transform themselves from
traditional architecture to multi tenancy
architecture and save tremendous cost
when you have to scale to hundreds
of thousands of users and you do
not have to spend on every single
customer when you have to onboard them.
So let's dive right in.
so what is multi tenancy architecture?
It is the architecture where multiple
customers All tenants, in this
case, share a single infrastructure
while maintaining data isolation.
This is very important that they
maintain their own data isolation.
I'm going to talk more about that.
but, it, this architecture basically
enhances scalability, cost efficiency,
and operational effectiveness, if
obviously it is incorporated properly.
Moving on, just a bit of a graphical
representation of how a single tenant
versus multi tenant looks like.
So if you see on the left, you have
multiple customers, customer 1,
customer 2, and customer 3, and they
all share their separate instances
and their separate databases.
But if you see on the multi
tenant structure, you have three
customers who share the similar
interfaces, similar instances, and
they all share single databases.
but their own isolated frameworks,
which is something that I'm
going to talk later as well.
So this is how graphically it looks
and even if you see on the picture,
you can see how we are cutting down
three instances to one just in the
case of having three customers.
Now imagine having hundreds
and thousands of customers.
potential costs when you move from
single tenant to multi tenant.
the key benefits of this entire
infrastructure is extremely
lower costs, easier maintenance
and updates, and faster scaling.
Now, if I can take this moment
here to talk more about how you can
make it easier to maintain, make
easier updates, and faster scaling,
but keeping your data isolation.
So basically when you have so let's take
an example, okay, you have a product
that is Let's say an erp for example
And you have to deploy the exact same
functionalities for 20, 000 customers
with the exact same functionalities, but
their own white labeled themes or their
own logos or their own color grading.
in, instead of deploying this
entire software on multiple AWS EC2
instances, for example, what you can
do is you can potentially keep your
entire code base in one instance.
And then what you can do is you can
keep On the database side, I'm not
going to go deep on the technicalities
of the database security, but you can
easily make database isolations using
AWS databases as well, so that you can
protect the data for each customer.
Now what you're doing is, every time a new
customer comes in, all you do is, you just
create the separate database or a data
isolation pocket for your new customer,
but they all share the same instance and
you can do horizontal scaling for your
set, Instance basically that you have for
your code base and then it automatically
scales when you have more customers that
the server cannot handle, but you're
not spinning up separate instances
every time a new customer is onboarded.
So what it does is it actually
saves you tons of cost.
However, it has its own challenges,
which I'm going to talk a bit later
on, but now I'm going to talk about
a few case studies that I personally
saw, happening in the industry.
One of the companies
is called Grandstream.
They had their tenant setup,
which was a single tenant setup.
Every time a new client is onboarded,
they had to spend almost 232 hours
to set up a new instance, to set up
the entire infrastructure, to set
up all the configurations, and it
was extremely high operational cost.
so what they did is they
basically migrated their entire
instances to multi tenancy.
Resulting in new tenant setup time
to be from 232 hours to 106 hours.
They migrated the clients
in less than 76 hours.
The bug fix time is very crucial because
now you're not fixing bug on hundreds
of thousands of different instances.
You're just fixing bug in one instance
and rolling it out to all your clients.
So what this does is it may maintain
your bug fix time from five hours to
let's say one and two and a half hours.
And this is extremely optimized
when you're talking about scale.
So obviously the investment,
is a separate topic.
But the one thing that I found online
is that they, they had huge monetary
uplift whilst they migrated as well.
talking a bit about Salesforce as well,
they had similar structure, they had
single tenant system, they migrated to
the multi tenant, they have not shared
any, figures for their, for their changes,
but because a company of that magnitude.
If they are moving from single
tenant to multi tenant, you can
understand the importance and the
benefits of this architecture is.
some of the companies, Shopify,
did, the transformation from single
tenant to multi tenant as well.
if you imagine Shopify, it's
just a single functionality where
you can set up multiple stores.
Now they have a similar mindset
that, hey, if you have one
instance, we have multiple shops.
And we have similar
functionalities for all the shops.
Why not keep it multi tenant?
That's a few examples of how
people have actually migrated from
single tenancy to multi tenancy.
And they've had huge uplifts in revenues.
They have huge cost savings,
optimizations, less time in
bug fixing, more, flexibility
in scaling, and obviously some
great long term benefits as well.
one more example, sorry, it's Uber.
Uber again did the same thing.
If you see, Uber had multiple products,
multiple, restaurants, if you talk about
Uber Eats, using similar architecture.
So they did the same, and again.
You can clearly understand that a name
like Uber, if they are going multi
tenant, again, stresses the value.
if I'm going to, to basically move to
quickly and the key benefits is I've
already talked more about, on the fast
onboarding and scaling, but operational
simplification, reduced complexity,
cost efficiency through shared resources
are just a few benefits of moving
from single tenancy to multi tenancy.
But it do has its challenges.
Sometimes, there's a concept of security
and data isolation risk as well, but now
with this modern infrastructure and modern
data security architectures, it has been
proven that you can put up huge, Sorry,
more detailed, data security parameters.
And this risk is now slowly and
gradually being mitigated because
this was a huge risk for any big
player to move to multi-tenancy.
But now I've seen that, there are a lot of
solutions that basically encrypt the data
end to end, and it's very easy to avoid
this risk in the scalable architecture.
There are some performance management,
and user allocation issues.
there are some scaling issues as
well, but I've seen again that, every
single cloud provider is now providing
extremely beneficial solutions
to tackle these problems as well.
again, balancing tenant customization
with simplicity is quite crucial.
because as I said, you are now managing
one single, instance, basically.
Now, the benefits are huge, but if, if
you don't have a fallback solution, if
you don't have a proper backup solution,
then it can become a huge problem as well.
as I said, it looks easy, it sounds
good, but it requires proper planning,
proper arrangement, and proper
resources to basically migrate from
single tenancy to multi tenancy.
best practices I would say is again
just from my own experiences is you
have to make sure that your data
security is absolutely top notch.
This is absolutely something that no
no customer basically will compromise
on, you have to optimize performance.
You have to be very crucial
when it comes to your backups.
You have to be very crucial when it comes
to best practices, both for front end
and for backend and for DevOps as well.
You have to be very sure to have a proper
backend management solution for user
role based access and feature flags.
Feature flagging is very crucial
now because now you are managing.
One single instance and you have
hundreds of thousands of clients.
You have to make sure your feature
flags are properly implemented
because sometimes in some businesses
you might want one feature to just
be available for a few customers.
You need to make sure your feature flags
are properly managed, properly optimized
and that you have properly implemented
that in your code base as well.
You can also use third party
solutions for feature flags but
that's something that is a business.
decision and a product decision.
the future of multi
tenancy is pretty simple.
I think, with the data security, solutions
out there, with the scalable optimization
solutions out there, I don't think
any large scale solution can operate
without the concept of multi tenancy.
It's very crucial that you
understand and evaluate the
importance of this at An early stage.
the key takeaways I would say is that
it's a game changer it's not new.
It's very old, but now it's getting
mature with data protection policies
with the end to end encryption And I
think the case studies clearly shows
how it's very important for any business
to understand this architecture.
Thank you so much for your time.
And, I'm really glad that I get
to make this talk and, feel free
to connect with me on LinkedIn.
and I'll obviously.
share my details, with
the conference organizers.
So if you need, that obviously let
me know, find me on LinkedIn and I'll
make sure to accept your requests and
answer any questions that you want.
Thank you so much.
Have a nice day.
Bye bye.