Hi, this is Sandeep Dhargula.
I'm a senior software engineer
and welcoming you all who
have joined in CONF42, CloneA2
2025 conference on my talk.
And here I'm going to present my
topic on AI driven fraud detection.
And I'm going to explain how AI
is transferring the way financial
institutions prevent fraud and
financial crime by leveraging predictive
analytics and behavior based model.
And AI is set to
revolutionizing financial fraud.
detection.
So this fraud detection
market is projected to surplus
dollar 190 billion by 2030.
It's a big, huge number.
And by the end of this section,
everyone will get all the info how AI
is driving significant reduction in
financial losses and inefficiencies.
Let's dive into predictive analytics.
in predictive analytics, AI algorithm
analyze billions of transactions
daily to identify fraud patterns
with unparalleled accuracy.
These advanced models can achieve
detection rates as high as 90%.
The processing transactions
in milliseconds.
So this improvement drastically
reduces false alerts and
enhances operation efficiency
compared to traditional systems.
And real time insights, AI
continuously adapts by learning
from new fraud patterns.
So keeping financial institutions
based ahead of emerging threats.
This dynamic learning capabilities
allows organizations to remain
compliant with regulatory standards.
by affecting combating evolving fraud
tactics and reduced false positives.
Unlike traditional system, which
can generate up to 50 percent false
positives, AI powered fraud detection
reduces false positives to under 10%.
So this precision enables security
teams to focus on genuine threats,
streamlining investigations and
enhancing customers satisfactions.
Let's drive into behavior based models.
Here in the behavior based model,
AI tracks and analyzes user behavior
in real time, processing thousands
of transactions per second.
By comparing current activity against
historical profiles, AI can quickly flag
anomalies like unusual international
wide transfer, changes in transaction
location, or abnormal purchasing
pattern across multiple platforms.
So here, the product to fraud prevention.
So AI systems are designed to identify
and address suspicious behavior
pattern before fraud escalates.
Since over 60 percent of fraud originates
from irregular behavior, early detection
is crucial in reducing financial
losses and maintaining customer trust.
So in significant loss reduction,
so financial institutions that
implements AI driven behavior
monitoring have seen up to 40 percent
reduction in fraud reduction losses.
So in sectors like such as Banking
and e commerce these transactions
in into millions of dollars saved
revenue So while improving the customer
experience by minimizing false alert
And financial gains like using AI,
financial institutions like JP Morgan,
MasterCard and Goldman Sachs are deployed
sophisticated AI system to revolutionizing
their fraud detection capabilities.
These organizations are investing
millions of dollars on AI artificial
intelligence to protect the trillions
of transactions across the global market
and improve their detection using AI.
And demonstrate 30 to 50 percent increase
in the fraud detection accuracy while
processing the transaction 60 percent
faster than the traditional methods.
And real time, real world results.
So early adoption of AI fraud detection
has reported up to 60 percent reduction
in false positives and 40 percent
decrease in fraud related losses.
Let's go into machine learning.
And machine learning and data analysis
is a key backbone of AI fraud.
Detection systems.
So it processing vast data sets and
evolving to handle new fraud tactics.
So these system analyze intricate patterns
and correlations that human might miss
analyst might miss so it accuracy rate
is more than 95 And enhance the security.
So AI iterates, leveraging capabilities
significantly strengthen fraud
prevention, ensuring that systems
adaptable to increase complex threats by
continually refining detection methods.
And AI offers more robust security
compared to traditional approaches.
And here, the real world impact
was AI powered fraud detection
has demonstrated up to 50 percent
improvement in detection accuracy.
And while processing transactions 60
percent faster than conventional methods.
So financial institutions adopting
AI prevention billions of dollars
in potential fraud, which some banks
reported like over 2 billion in
fraud prevention in a single year.
That's a big, huge number.
So let's continue with the anomaly
detection and anomaly detection.
He's AI advanced anomaly detection system
continuously monitoring transactions
and instantly flag suspicious behaviors
that deviate from established patterns.
So this real time monitoring allows
for immediate risk assessment, enabling
quick responses to potential threats
and strengthening fraud prevention.
Here are the three categories
of anomaly detection.
The one is baseline establishment and real
time monitoring and alert generations.
Let's drive into real
time risk assessment.
In the real time risk assessment,
AI system assess risk in real time.
offering immediate insights and allowing
financial institutions to take shift.
protective actions when suspicious
activities are detected.
this protective approach ensures
that fraud is mitigated before
it cause significantly harm.
three type of detections.
in risk management, they are
showcasing here in three categories.
One is transaction analysis and
risk scoring and automated action.
And building a robust strategies, building
robust fraud prevention strategies are
By using AI transformation, by using raw
data into actionable insights, enabling
organizations to prevent fraud, detect
threats early, and respond swiftly.
By implementing multi layer defense
approach, institutions can reduce
financial losses, increase operational
efficiencies, and maintain a secure
environment for legitimate transactions.
And the key Importance of three
type of categories have the
strategies, DOPA strategies.
One is data governance and second
one is model validation and third
one is continuous monitoring.
Let's dive into actionable insights
here in the actionable insights that
transform raw data into powerful action
steps through AI powered fraud analysis.
Our comprehensive approach helps
organizations not only prevent
potential threats, but also
reduce the financial losses.
So these are the three actionable
insights, strategies, prevention,
detection and response.
And the project growth as I mentioned
that the detection fraud market is
growing to 190 billion dollars by 2030.
It shows this graph shows indicates
from 2024 to 2030 it's gradually
increasing the detection fraud market.
And let's go into key
intakes, key takeaways.
AI driven fraud detection system
can reduce financial losses
by up to 60 percent through
early detection of threats.
with behavior based models, machine
learning, and real time monitoring,
Yeah, offers unmatched accuracy in fraud
detection, ensuring that organizations
are better prepared to combat
increasing sophisticated fraud items.
strengthening the security, AI ability
to continuously adopt and learn
from data enhanced security methods,
ensuring robust production against
emerging threats by providing real
time monitoring and instant responses.
And AI helps financial institutions
maintain both high security
and smooth customer experience.
And thank you all who
have joined the call.