Hello, everybody.
Thank you for joining this session.
Thank you for investing one hour
of your personal time to find more
about cloud, about AI, and how we
should modernize, how we should
prepare our cloud solution for AI.
My name is Radu Mvulevic, and for the next
50 55 minutes, I'm going to turn We'll
talk about AI, we'll talk about cloud,
we'll talk about how we can modernize,
how we can prepare our applications that
are running on top of cloud for AI to
ensure that the system can work, can
provide data, can process the triggers,
the events that are generated by the
AI solution, and in the end, how AI
can be part of our cloud ecosystem
without having an impact, a negative
impact on our end to end solution.
Before going forward, I would
like to please introduce myself.
My name is Radu.
Radu Gomogulev.
I was born down the school, live and
work in a beautiful city called Cluj
Napoca, in the middle of Transylvania.
And in my part time, I'm
investing time in communities,
learning, and in enjoying coffee.
I'm also Microsoft Azure MVP,
Microsoft Video Director.
If you want to contact me or to have a
chat with me on this topic or on all other
topics, feel free to reach me on LinkedIn.
Why cloud is important for me is
because my journey on cloud started
in 2019, and from that moment in
time, I was involved in different
projects on AWS and on my computer.
You will see that most examples that
I will provide in these sessions are
error specific, but the same service.
have a one to one vendor, AWS,
or a system on Google Cloud.
you will find good mention of
the service that we are talking
about today in all public vendors.
What is my mission?
What is my mission for today?
Is to discover together with you how
the cloud architecture of an AI system,
and now I'm not covering or I'm not
focusing On the AI books, but in the
most of the cases, we are using more
or less out of the shelf services.
We're just changing the model, playing
with the models in the cloud, but
hosting that service is already done.
The challenge is when we're doing
the integration, AI component goes
in our cart and how we need to
ensure that these two can leave
work, bring value to the business.
It doesn't make sense to talk about where
is Cloud 2024, where we being at the
end of 2025, what is the current impact?
What is the future?
We already know that we are
at the beginning of the cloud.
I say that we don't even know
what will be the real impact.
in five, ten years.
We just hear different things,
not only from the software,
but also from the hardware.
Autonomous cars, it's already here.
We already hear about half a million
robots will use AI maybe in a few years.
We don't know where we'll be.
We need to build systems that
can work, can interact, and
can communicate in a good way.
in a scalable way with AI services.
I think that now we're in a phase like
we've been with data analytics in 2020.
Why I'm saying this?
Because I see an analogy in 2020,
which had data layer on the system,
not fully ready, hard analytics.
Now in
2025, I find us in the same situation.
In the same situation, but
not for data analytics.
For ai, for the workload that AI is
bringing pressure, that is putting on
existing system, on systems that in many
situations were migrating maybe in 2020,
maybe in 21, 22, if the shift OnPrem to
cloud or in a way that let's push it,
let's push it, and maybe sometime in
the future we'll have enough time to.
to do modernization or to apply
the best practices and well
attached framework that AWS Azure.
I remember that I was talking about
serverless, about computation flavors that
you can have in cloud a few years ago.
And I was saying that we have
20 30 different flavors of
containerization of serverless in AWS.
And now this is just a snapshot of end
of 2024 of a part of the AI services
that Microsoft Azure is offering.
And this is only the beginning.
It's
not only training among customers.
Now, using AI nowadays means To know to
select, maybe an out of the shelf plasma
service or a service solution that a cloud
web or a third party is providing that is,
that is solving your need, your problem.
You don't need to train a model
to do text to speech or speech
to text or to do, document and
text extraction from a document.
Ah, if something already exists, why not
paste a service or in a different way?
There are two core services
that are mostly used, especially
when we talk about Azure.
We have this bunch of
services, extraordinarily good.
And we have OpenAI and Azure ML.
That, of course, each of them
come with a studio and so on.
why they are relevant?
First of all, Let's understand a
little bit the technical scope.
OpenAI is for when you have a pre
trained model, you don't do any kind
of customization, you just focus on
taking the pre trained model, you do
the, Integration based on the API.
You don't need data scientists.
You don't need MLOps, things like that.
No training required.
You just take out of the shelf and
build a code assistance, or the content
generation, a shellpot, and like that.
They work perfectly.
I would say in 90 percent of the
cases, this is what you're looking.
On the other side, you have the Azure
Machine Learning, where The thing
that you use to work with Azure OpenAI
and the existing system cannot do too
much because most of them might be
developers, infrastructure people,
security, testers, and so on, data people.
They are great.
They are awesome.
But when you are using Azure Machine
Learning, then you do the training.
means that you need a data scientist.
You are focusing only on the model itself.
It is a project inside the program.
A program might be a full end to end AI
solution for a specific business stream.
One of the components is building
All the ecosystem that needs to be
around the part and another team,
another project is building that model.
Why this is important?
Because cloud, we already know,
it's not only virtual machines.
AI, and to have a real impact to the
business, it's not only the model.
At the moment when you start to put an
AI service or an ML Inside your solution,
you also need to create a bunch of
other services that we'll talk later
on today to be able to support this.
To expose the API, to manage the
payload, the trigger that they will
handle, access management and so on.
This is what I want to do today.
let's start step by step.
What are the limitations of AI in
the cloud and the challenges and I'm
not referring here for physical or
technical challenges of AI, but the
real challenge is do a full integration
of an AI component in an existing
ecosystem, cloud ecosystem without
or ensuring that you don't have a
direct impact on the current business
use cases and to not have a downside.
Or to not create bottlenecks.
And also, to be able to supply to
that AI solution all the resources,
all the flows that are required to
be able to respond to the AI needs.
Now,
AI comes with a lot of challenges.
Data security, privacy, bias of AI,
ethical consideration, complexity,
the technical limitation, the legal
challenges, and the regulatory compliance,
and of course, how it would impact
the work that we are doing today.
I want to highlight one or two of them
because I think these are very important.
Volume and sensitivity of data.
Sensitivity of data is not only to ensure
that the AI can crunch what is allowed.
only, but also refer to the person
that would use that a service that you
are putting inside the system would
be able to see and access only the
information that they are allowed to.
A very basic example, a database
with salaries, the classical
problem of HR and financial.
And you need to ensure that people
can ask, let's say, to a GPT.
And to get data only for, or only
for financial information regarding
the people that they are managing.
Not of their managers, not of
people from different departments.
In Excel, we have
different ways to do this.
In the database, we have different ways.
In order to ensure that the same
thing is happening when building AI.
Volumes are important.
When we say volume, we are referring
that AI needs to crunch data.
It is putting a high
pressure on your system.
You need to ensure that your data,
your repo, can manage that volume.
Going with data, because this is
the thing that I want to highlight,
is data governance and compliancy.
A lot of time, I would say, small to mid
sized companies didn't have to manage
and to create a catalyst for data.
to understand what kind of data
they are storing, what can be
shared with you, who, and so on.
And there is a shock, I would say
even cultural shock, in the moment
in time when they realize that we
need to create a catalog of our data.
Why is it a shock?
It's not because it's hard to do,
it's because of the cost and the
complexity is coming with that part.
A nice thing that I really like regarding
job displacement and human workforces
At the beginning of 19 19, 5 19, and we
used to have people that was, that were
throwing guns in your wind in the morning
and sure that people would wake up.
to go in the factories.
Think about AI, might reinvent
the jobs, the workforce.
In the end, we will equal, but
this is a topic for another
session in a different course.
Next, together with you, I would like to
highlight five key areas of modernization.
It needs to be tackled, needs
to be covered, needs to be
considered when we talk about
putting AI inside existing systems.
There are more than five,
but these five I want to do.
First one is scalability
and performance bottlenecks.
Scalability of the works.
We need to have systems that can
scale, that can provide to the AI layer
all the resources that are required.
GPO, for example, other
type of computation, memory.
performance bottlenecks
sometimes are forgotten.
Because the bottlenecks don't
come all the time from the AI.
The bottleneck is generated
because AI is trying to do too
many queries to an API endpoint.
Or he's generating too many
triggers because event would be if
we have an event driven approach.
But too many triggers
to some API endpoints.
And the system is not able to
manage all of them, and we start
to see, let us see, we start to see
bottlenecks that in the end might
create a butterfly or a domino effect.
The second thing is the data
seal and how you can govern.
The government part we
already touched a little bit.
data catalogs, and how you keep the
data secure, what kind of data you're
exposing, having the ability to
control what you provide to different
users and to different environments.
Because in a very sensitive
industry, you might prefer the bot
to respond in a specific way if,
the user is using a secure device
that is part of your organization.
And if the same request is coming
from a public endpoint, from the
internet, from a non secure device,
you might have a different response.
Simplified or having your IP kept.
Data seals is another thing.
Data seals means that you have your data,
you have your repos in multiple places.
Because you have an organization
with a lot of departments.
Because you might have 100 factories
or 1000 factories around the globe,
and each factory has their own repo.
And if you want to run something
globally or across all organizations,
then You need to decide how you create
a data lake that is ready for AI.
It's not impossible.
It doesn't mean all the time that you
need to copy all the data in place.
You should do anything.
And you should avoid that model.
AI service to access multiple, repos that
are across different locations and so on.
And in the end.
In the same way, you find solution how
to create a reporting dashboard and
views that differ at production line,
where details at the factory level,
more, the granularity is bigger because
you have a factory manager directly
looking at the data at global level.
Again, more, more granular or with
a bigger , because you don't want
to have . All the details, similar
principles would be applied.
So four solutions and for the
data that is consumed by ai,
and now we go to the third one.
What is the right balance between
innovation and compliance?
How important and what kind of borders?
To define from the co compliancy,
from the governance's point of view,
to give enough liberty to freedom, to
give enough freedom for innovation.
There's something that is different
from organization to predict,
but governance is required.
But so at the same time, AI
gives you the freedom to search.
Combine information in a different way,
and this is from where innovation comes.
Finding the right balance between
these two, it's a challenge.
The fourth thing is how you move,
how you, manage the cost of the
AI and the full cloud ecosystem.
What is the, what is the line between?
Sacrificing performance or accept that
you have a latency or maybe the AI system
is not aware of everything but would
allow you to keep posts under control.
It's for example like if you are using
your Application Insights at the beginning
when you're starting to use it, you
say, oh yeah, I will keep everything,
everything installed and after a few
days or weeks you realize, oh my god,
Application Insights cost me almost as
much as the computation and database.
Exactly, this is the context for
the performance in the context.
And the last thing is about deployment,
about agility and efficiency.
And you have the models, you have the
MLOps, and you need To ensure that you
can deploy them easily all in, in all
environments, you can easily create the
full ecosystem that you're looking for.
So what are the key of,
personally, and that's my personal
opinion, is the key of success
of an AI system that is running
inside cloud is not only AI.
Partially, an important part is
about application modernization,
ensuring that you are using not a state
of the art services and architecture, but
you are using the right cloud services,
the right approach in the cloud that
would allow to have a scalable, efficient
system that can work together with
AI, keeping the cost under control.
and deliver business
value to the end customer
without affecting other business
streams or dimension of your solution.
How can we achieve this?
From the five areas of modernization
we can derive that we are talking
about scalability and performance.
Features like auto scaling based
on Real internal metrics of the
systems are knowing exactly when
you need to scale for how much.
What is the upper limit and when you
need to scale down, it's very important.
If you ever tried to find the right
balance of the scaling system, when
you should trigger the scaling for
how long and so on, you already
know that it's not as easy.
And even nowadays, in many situations,
scaling decisions are taken manually.
You have alerts, somebody from the
support is looking at the alerts,
and decide what needs to be done.
The second thing is data
integration and management.
We've talked about data savings.
We've talked about that we need to unwind.
On the market, there are a lot of data
lake solutions and warehouse systems.
What is important before putting data?
The key before putting the AI is
to ensure that not only you bring
everything under the same umbrella, but
also the data, structure on structure
data, is exposed in such a way that
the AI service, the AI model, is able
to understand and is able to crunch.
The next component is about
flexibility and agility.
You need to have the capacity, you need
to provide to the team the ability to be
able to deliver, to release in different
specific environments, dev environments,
testing environments, reproduction
environments, as easy as possible.
The AI service, their ML model,
anything that is related to the
system that they are building.
As you have, for example, the capability.
to do 10, 15 releases in the
development environment per day.
The same agility is required for the
ML models, or for the AI services
that are working, because the team
needs to have the ability to test, to
see how it behaves in an environment,
to get the output, and then to do
any kind of modification or changes.
Easy to say, much harder to implement.
I remember in 2024, at the beginning,
almost, I think in the same period of
time, February, March, I was saying
that yet we don't have the right
tool and the level of maturity of
the truth is not enough to be able to
work with a, to work with the cloud.
Now in 2025, I would say that the tool
that we have now available on the market.
are pretty much sure they're not perfect,
but we start to have that development
ecosystem that is allowing us to design,
build, operate any services, any models
in production and non production.
When we talk about these tools,
don't think about tools that are
related to training the models.
No.
I want to talk about the tools and the
capability to secure, to do data catalog,
to do compliancy checks of AI services
and what are exposing through them.
We have nowadays more and more
AI solutions that are capable to
integrate, are capable to communicate
with, let's call them enterprise.
I'm referring now to
Atlassian, Jira, Confluence.
SharePoint, to OneDrive.
Because in the end, you don't want
to write your own custom integration.
You just want more or less
to do a drag and drop.
As you are consuming an APN from, let's
say, regarding, the train schedule,
the same thing you want in an APN.
that is already available from ClassyARM
or from Microsoft that allow you to
crunch access information that is
available on SharePoint based on your
role, based on your grade, based on
the group that you're part of or office
and create a response specific to it.
There are many others that we will touch
more or less in the next half an hour.
Security and Compliancy, where I
would like to highlight, let me, I
would like to highlight policies.
Policies, from my perspective, are
one of the most important, terms.
Of security when to close the
efficiencies and we'll come back in a
few minutes to this are very important.
Many people don't realize the real cost
and the real impact integrating on a
solution only after taking a production.
the running cost?
Double.
And, at the moment in time, there might
not be too many options to take action.
Interoperability is exactly what we
were talking about with the example
of SharePoint, with Atlassian.
And, the last thing about real
time analytics, basically,
the operationalize of AI.
Also about this topic, we will
come back in a few minutes.
Now, what are the keys of AI
monetization?
I prepared some services.
As I said, I'm giving examples from Azure,
but you will find the second dimension.
The service on AWS and on Workflow.
The things that are crucial,
and indirectly, we touched
them in the previous slide.
Why do you think that they are crucial?
Because at least with what we have on
the market, on, on 2024 and the beginning
of 2025, they need more or less to
be dead products or similar products.
Yeah, most of the products are similar,
it's just different implementations.
One of the most important ones is
Azure Kubernetes service, or any
other flavor of modernization like
approach where you have your workload.
And why?
One of the biggest problem is
how you manage the workload.
Because inefficient managing
workloads could create problems.
Create issues regarding scaling,
regarding latency, and how
you manage your resources.
You need in the end a solution
where you can, when you create
a cluster, 200, 500 nodes.
and you don't, and not all
the nodes are the same.
You have nodes with GCP capability,
with different GCP power.
Other with CPU, other
for memory intensive.
And in the whole ecosystem that you're
building, you have the capability to
specify that workload goes on GCP, on
GCU, that workload goes on specific
AMD interprocessors, that goes on
ARM, that goes on different types.
And this gives you the, this gives you the
flexibility to the full orchestration that
only, not only, improve the performance
of the systems, but also you can run
them more smooth, more cost efficient.
Because in the end, you have a system
that's scalable, you deploy resources,
even if they're pretty complex, it's
more easy to stick them on the right
nodes type, and you don't end up in a
situation where you use Expensive and
very powerful nodes for simple and basic.
the second thing is selfless.
When I say selfless, for example,
Azure Functions, I'm not thinking
about running your AI stuff in service.
You could do that problem.
One of the biggest problem, the
biggest challenge is that a complex AI
system can generate is all the events,
all the triggers that are generated
You might say, oh, you go to an
API, but you might have to fix
what, how you would manage them.
You can go very easily on an event driven
approach where you have the AI that is
pushing events and behind the events.
You have some functions, you have some
serverless approach that is triggered in a
moment in time when there are two events.
And then you can scale up
or down based on your needs.
It's up to you if you run your serverless
in your own cluster or you go in a more
serverless approach and you pay per
consumption or in a combination between.
In the end, you need an event driven
approach plus a serverless approach.
approach for ensuring that you can
dynamically scale and manage that work.
The third component that I see
relevant is the ability to ensure
that you avoid as much as possible.
You can train your AI model and
your AI service can efficiently
access data as close as possible
to the location where it's running.
The other needs to do a lot
of requests across multiple.
This is where a data lake
approach is the right way.
There are a lot of tools on the market.
One of the services that I
really enjoy is Vital Fabric.
And why?
Because it brings under the
same umbrella the full journey
for a piece of data from the
moment in time when it's ingested.
It's different transformation
has applied to them.
It's stored until the
moment when it's ingested.
Somebody's access and based
on a catalog, what is access
and in the end are high or is
using mysotherapy or something similar to,
and, in a seamless approach regarding data
access, data transformation, and having a
catalog and understanding of what data is
stored and who should access different.
We know already that AI.
it's about using, data.
Three or four years ago,
everybody was saying data is gold.
And now, we can, we have the
area that on top of data can
extract the value of the content.
And we want to expose it.
Exposing, it's not done
directly from that area.
Exposing the data requires
classical, like an API.
like a load balancer, usually a
level 4 balancer, if you go with me.
And more nicely, maybe an
Azure Application Gateway.
Because, first of all, you want to
protect yourself from the people.
You need to ensure that you can balance
the traffic, you avoid downtime,
and the performance are acceptable.
Having a load balancer like Azure
Application Gateway gives the ability.
to manage the latency and to balance
the traffic and also, protect you
from different type of attack.
Because having, for example, application
gateway, is the, with what helps you.
Let's say that we have the AI
service, you have a API layer,
that you're on top of that, and
you have other application gateway.
Well, a web based attack is
happening, all that load.
It's the application gateway and the load
balancer, meaning that the computation
available for your business or AI model
will remain available for your own use.
It will not be consumed by different
systems that would protect you from this.
We are talking about real time.
We are talking about the streaming events,
about triggering different activities.
Azure events have about one.
Any other approach of an event
based solution is important
from two perspectives.
One is the ability to allow an AI
solution to trigger and to scale
up the number of Actions that he
wants to run might be actions as
looking in a different location.
Might be actions like
triggering, for example, closing
a door or securing a house.
On the other hand, when we talk
about AI, everybody is talking
about real time, near real time.
If you have a system that is modifying
all the time, then you need an ability,
you need the capability, to ensure.
that you are receiving a
change in that, update.
To be able to implement a real time
data ingestion system, receive a
stream of updates, you would need to
go with an event streaming approach,
and use a service like Error Info.
Because you're not only scaling, also,
you can be aware, or your solution
can be aware in near real time.
regarding what is happening around.
The last service that I would
like to highlight is copy, joking.
It's about catalog.
It's about the data catalog.
Because you need to do, you need
to have the governance layer.
You need to ensure that you
know exactly what kind of data
you have, who can access it.
If you need to be compliant
with different regulations, you
need to understand all of this.
This can be achieved only
through a strong data governance
layer, through a data catalog.
Azure Purview goes hand in hand with
different data repos and with different
repos Microsoft has, gives you the ability
to do two things, to do the catalogs
and to do the governance of your data.
Meaning that you can control and you can
be sure that the AI service and the people
that are using your AI are accessing only
the data that they are in the right way.
And also, you can track the
level of data accessibility that.
Each flow or each person is access.
Now, again, for the last few
months, we already talked about
that AI is increasing a lot.
Workloads automatically, the cost
can put pressure on other systems.
It's pre translated, but
how you can track that.
And you need to understand exactly
the current spending of your
cloud infrastructure versus The
business value that is brought.
If the business value is high enough,
you might not care about the, your cloud
infrastructure doubled, but the business
value is four times more than before.
This is something that you would do.
How you can implement, the
ability to understand and
track and to optimize the cost.
These are true human principles, where
you have three important components.
Governance, optimization,
and strategic alignment.
At this phase, I was not able to identify
a tool or a service, only one that you
will say that is covering everything.
It's usually a combination.
Even the ones that are cloud agnostic.
Even if you have one dashboard,
behind the scenes they're using
one or multiple services from each
event or for multiple ways how they
collect, monitoring, and so on.
If we split between governance, cost
optimization, and strategic alignment,
when we talk about government, we
talk about governance, we talk about
management, we talk about meaning.
that you gain visibility.
You understand the cost you have to take.
When we talk about cost optimization
in the space of cloud, we talk about
different ways how you can optimize
the spending, like Azure reservations,
both instances, different licensing,
quotation, but also we are talking about
services like Azure Advisor, similar to
it, that can advise you how you can take
different actions, all different stuff.
to be able to reduce your costs.
And the third component is strategic
alignment, where tools like Azure
Automation can give you the ability to
have different automated triggers actions.
This can help you to take
control of your spending.
Now, we talked about, we talked
a lot about AI, how different
solutions should look like.
I really like this component
diagram of Azure services
that is provided by Microsoft.
Why I really like this?
Because if you take a look
and if you zoom this diagram,
that there are only to OpenAI.
Nevertheless, around them, there
are many other services that
needs to be configured, needs to
run, to be able to serve the AI
capability that is generated by them.
It's not just putting AI service.
And you say, okay, I'm done.
No, exactly.
As when you build a cloud solution,
you don't just put a virtual machine,
put on this virtual machine, the
workload and you say, I'm done.
No, you need to consider all the
other things that are around.
measure a p management or, for the, to be
able to ensure that, you manage the API
you are exposing and you do versioning
of the a p and that are exposing of okay.
Solution that they're building.
You have.
web apps or something else, when
we are, when you talk about how you
can, do some logic around what you're
exposing from the daily service, you
need to do access management and to
ensure that people can access only the
information and the content that they
are allowed through your AI system.
You have the secret, so you need a key
vault or a different flavor of vault.
You need to connect because that
solution don't run by herself.
It is integrated in a full stack
solution, meaning that you would need
secure connection with your subnet.
If you go in a hub spoke topology,
then you might have a spoke or
you might define something like
a sub landing without specific.
to how you do the AI integration
on specific applications
or domains and so on.
And then things start to
get more and more complex.
building a cloud solution is not only
about building a virtual machine.
The same thing is applicable for AI.
Running an AI solution inside
cloud is not only about.
taking an AI service and running it.
Now, let's go with an example,
a very basic one, because I want
to highlight what is the process
that we should have in our mind.
When we prepare our
current application for AI.
Let's imagine a traditional e
commerce application, a classical
monolithic one, that was hosted on
prem, and was migrated with success
in Azure Analytics and Shifting.
Everybody is happy.
You bring business to the customer.
consumption is Okay, nobody's complaining.
That's great
to be able to connect to services you
need to do, you need to break down the
application into microservices to be able
to scale and to have a better mobility.
You need to ensure that the data
storage and the processing capabilities
can support a workflow, can scale,
you, will not affect, affect the
e-commerce platform because you just
started to use the AI behind the team.
you have implemented all the
DevOps practices that are needed
to be able to deploy easily the
AI service, the models, and so on.
And
you can do some recommendations based
on the capability for the users.
Now, to be able to obtain all
of this, you starting a journey
in a modernization journey.
If you take a look, for example, on
cloud adoption and cloud modernization,
is providing for a p and you'll
find that it's very similar.
It is the same route that
gives you scalability.
Ensure data.
That you have a link for,
analytics for any reporting.
The first part is that is the
microservice architecture.
you're, breaking the, you do
the modernization of your data.
You might go with your data
file factory with fabric, with
startups, or with data lake storage.
It's up to you, but it's important
to do the data modernization layer
to ensure that you have more or less
a link that your, that you have a,
that you have a governance on top
of your data and you have academy.
They're crucial.
Then you need to streamline the
development, testing the deployment
through demo, and also to ensure
that you're using ARM templates or
Terra form to be able to build the
infrastructure that is required for.
The fourth thing is you're in
the phase when you can start
to integrate or AI service.
You might go with open AI, with
machine learning, with Azure
Databricks, but it's not only because
this is what I want to talk about.
Here, you start to use a
keyboard, you start to use a
wheelbarrow, something similar.
you put maybe a traffic manager, you
start to create, if you remember,
if you go back to this diagram, you
are starting to build this space.
Until at that moment, in all the
previous phases, you just created
the ecosystem that can scale, that
can run with success, the solution.
And then, you need to think about
operational, you need to think about
monitoring, you need to take into account
how you can have an effective monitoring,
and how you implement all the practices
to be able to track, to be able to
improve performance and reliability.
This is a simplified journey.
And there are three crucial steps.
One is the modernization.
Second is building the AI component
with all the other services
that are required around it.
And the third one is the operational part,
not only of your solution, it already
should exist, but also of your AI part.
Now,
if we do a step back and we would
have or issue today's session, I would
say that there are nine components
that I would like to, we are talking
about and we need architecture.
We need to be able to have a dynamic
scaling, meaning service computing.
We need data lake, data
catalog, data modernization.
We need to implement principles.
We, we need to ensure that also we have an
event driven approach for data processing.
For
other models, especially the
pre-trained one, we can find a
lot on the market and services.
This one might be a good option.
Security compliancy are important,
and in the end, we need the
right observability layer, level.
What are the final thoughts, for my,
for this session is that AI is part
of our life for a few years, not
something that started 200 years ago.
We should expect that, AI services will be
integrated and will be part of our lives.
Most of the softwares and digital
services and, think about co pilot.
It's in our part.
What do you say?
Word.
There are other services, like
AI, all around us.
And to be able to use it, to be
able to integrate it, we need to
ensure that we do the optimisation
exercise of the cloud system.
We do the right modernisation to be
able to handle the workload, the payload
that AI generated and best practices
that we were ignoring in the cloud space
until now, nowadays, become mandatory.
event driven approach, data driven,
and real time analytics are part
of the modernization path that
we need to take to be able to
ensure that we are building a
cloud solution that can use Be used
and communicate with a service.
Thank you.
Thank you for joining me.
If you have questions, also, you
can reach me later on LinkedIn.
And thank you for the team
that organized this event.
And thank you for you that you join.
Thank you and have a great day.