Hello, everyone.
Welcome to corner 42 cloud native 2025.
I am Arun Pandian, a technology
infrastructure specialist, and I'm
going to talk about how a unified
multi cloud monitoring solution can
deliver comprehensive observability
across diverse cloud service providers.
So in the agenda, I will talk about the
importance of multi cloud monitoring,
and then the core components off multi
cloud observability and what are the
tools that can be integrated and deployed
in multi cloud monitoring, best practice
that can be leveraged, and at last the
future trends in cloud observability.
I'll start with the complexities
in managing multiple clouds.
Organizations are rapidly adopting
multiple cloud platforms to
leverage their unique strengths.
But they also inherit a set of
operational challenges that can
significantly impact their ability to
monitor, secure, and optimize these
multi cloud environments effectively.
First challenge is data
silos and fragmentation.
Each cloud provider typically
comes with its own monitoring
and logging systems or solutions.
As a result, these solutions can
create fragmented data and making it
difficult to derive holistic insights
without a centralized approach.
The second is the latency
and performance bottlenecks.
So organizations collect or gather
real time data from globally dispersed
networks, and those networking
complexities can introduce service delays.
The third one is compliance
and security visibility gaps.
So each provider offers distinct
controls and default configurations.
So uniformly enforcing security and
compliance policies across all the
cloud environments can be challenging.
And at last, the scalability and
cost management, the volume of
the logs and metrics grows, grows
exponentially on a daily basis.
so the expense of, storing, managing and
analyzing the data, can become complex.
The next I want to talk
about, the importance of,
unified multicloud monitoring.
The first is the consistent,
we can achieve the consistent
operational visibility.
A centralized monitoring approach,
enable, comprehensive visibility and
understanding of what's happening within,
within multiple cloud environments.
So this holistic view makes it
easier for teams to track performance
trends, detect anomalies, and maintain
healthy application or service levels.
The next is the Simplified Incident
Response and Lucas Analysis.
So whenever an issue occurs,
it is essential to resolve
it quickly to meet the needs.
the, MTTR metric, the mean time to resolve
and the unified monitoring solution help
us to consolidate logs, metrics and events
at one particular place, to reduce the
time spent on, in analyzing the data.
So this streamlined approach, help,
teams, to identify the issues or
problems quickly, drive resolution.
and even avoid prolonged
service descriptions.
The next is the enhanced reliability
and infrastructure resilience.
So if we, by continuously monitoring or
tracking the key performance indicators,
the KPIs, we can proactively fix
issues before they become critical.
So the insights that are gathered
highlight patents, highlight
the patents or irregularities.
That, help the teams, to, intelligently
scale, decisions, an auto scaling and then
also support the preventive maintenance.
And, next one is the streamlined
security and compliance monitoring.
So security and regulatory requirements
can become complicated when multiple
cloud products are involved.
So a unified view is required to help,
standardizing monitoring practices
across all the cloud platforms.
and detect suspicious activities instantly
and meet the compliance requirements.
And at last, the cost optimization
and resource efficiency.
the multi cloud monitoring solution,
offer comprehensive visibility into
cost and resource consumption that
allows teams to make informed decisions
about the capacity planning, cost
allocation and optimization approaches.
The next I will go over the core
components of, the core components
that are involved in a multi
cloud observability solution.
The first one is, the data collection.
Here we can aggregate the logs, metrics,
traces from diverse cloud environments
and, utilizing, agent based or agent less
solutions to capture every critical event.
So this continuous stream of raw
telemetry data, that supports, the
analysis and also support to create a,
robust observability, solution or system.
The next one is data
processing and correlation.
here, if you use the advanced analytics,
machine learning and even correlation,
we can transform the data into context
rich, insights by identifying the
patents, anomalies, and dependencies
across, distributed services.
So this refined data set, gives, teams
the ability to diagnose issues quickly.
Accelerate the root cause analysis
and, and decision making in
complex multi cloud, landscapes.
The other component is
observability and visualization.
So with interactive dashboards,
health checks, and alerting
capabilities, so we can achieve the
real time visibility into application
performance and infrastructure status.
so these unified views help, teams
to spot trends, isolate bottlenecks,
and maintain seamless services.
application, delivery, by, showcasing the
system's relationship and dependencies.
The next is automated,
remediation in incident response.
so whenever the anomalies or
threshold features occur or
detected, automated playbooks or
self healing mechanisms, are enabled.
So that helps us to resolve,
issues before they escalate.
So this integrated incident
response mechanism or approach.
Ensure minimal downtime by,
orchestrating the alerts, on call
schedules and, collaborative workflows
for rapid problem containment.
And at last, the security
and compliance monitoring.
so we can continuously scan
the telemetry for suspicious
activities or policy violations.
reinforcing proactive threat
detection and compliance
adherence, in multi cloud, setups.
So through seamless integrations
with, security frameworks and
automated compliance checks, teams
can uphold a stringent government,
governance, mitigate risks and
satisfy the, regulatory requirements.
there's a reference or a sample
architecture that can be even used.
to design a unified, monitoring
system for multi cloud environments.
So the first layer is,
data collection layer.
the unified monitoring solution
can support multiple cloud
environments, including major
service providers, AWS, Azure,
Google Cloud, and even private cloud.
So each cloud provider generates
logs, metrics, and events that need
to be monitored for performance,
availability, and security.
The next is the monitoring agents.
So the agents are deployed across
different cloud environments to
collect the observability data.
So these agents gather log metrics and
even data from various cloud native
services and infrastructure components.
Then next is the data aggregation layer.
Here, the data is categorized, like
the observability data is categorized
and processed by specialized components
like log collectors, that handles the
logs generated by the applications,
infrastructure, and cloud services.
And the other one is
the metrics aggregators.
Here, it processes and normalizes
performance related metrics.
the last one is the
event stream processors.
this helps manage and analyze event driven
data streams for real time insights.
And the next one is centralized
monitoring and analytics.
So all the collected and processed
data is sent to a centralized
monitoring and analytics platform.
So this layer is responsible for,
correlating different types of
data, detecting anomalies, and
even identifying the patents,
patents for, proactive monitoring.
The second last is the observability
and alerting mechanism layer.
So these layers generate alert
alerts based on anomalies, security
breaches, or failures, system failures.
So they'll create real time
dashboards for visualizing the system
health and that is an entrance.
And at last, we have
the incident management.
Here are the alerts from the system or.
Are fed into ITS and tools, for
ticketing and incident resolution.
here the next is, I'll talk about
the tools, that can be, integrated or
deployed, in multi-cloud environments.
first either we can use the
open source, tools or like
commercial SaaS platforms, tools.
So open source tools such as like
Prometheus, Grafana, Jagger, open
Telemetry and SaaS platforms.
So Datadog.
New Relic, Grafana
Cloud, Dynatrace, Plunk.
in terms of deployment, the open
source tools requires manual setup,
configuration and maintenance.
But the SaaS platforms are
fully managed or completely
managed by the service provider.
it is also easily or quick
to deploy and scalable.
also, in terms of scalability, open
source tools are horizontally scalable,
but requires careful planning of
capacity and resource allocation.
But for SaaS platforms, it is
automated elastic scaling, and
also it supports elastic scaling in
response to resource usage, and the
vendor handles the capacity planning.
for the cost wise, open source tools
are typically free, with cost rising
from the self hosting infrastructure,
or storage, compute, networking,
and even the maintenance and the
scaling cost grow, with the usage.
And also the SaaS platform's cost is
subscription based, cost can increase
with the data ingestion and storage.
Next is, the best practices
that we can follow.
For, implementing, robust, unified
multi cloud monitoring solution.
yeah, first we can define a centralized
observability strategy to establish a
unified observability framework, that
consolidates the logs, metrics, and
traces from all the cloud environments.
And next we can adopt, a multi
layered data collection approach.
to collect telemetry data
across infrastructure
applications and network layers.
And we also can normalize and correlated
data across cloud environments to
standardize the diverse data formats.
And even under correlate the
metrics, logs and traces.
to create actionable insights
and prevent any blind spots.
we can also implement a vendor
agnostic observability platform to
integrate seamlessly with cloud service
providers to avoid any vendor lock in.
And, it is, possible to embed
observability into CICD workforce
to, for proactive monitoring,
automated anomaly detection, and
even faster incident resolution.
During any critical deployments.
Also, we need to strengthen the security
compliance monitoring, to safeguard the
workloads or any application deployments
across multi cloud environments.
So the last I'm going to talk
about the future trends in cloud
monitoring and observability.
The first is the AI driven
observability and anomaly detection.
So many organizations leverage some
AI driven solutions like AI powered
analytics and machine learning models.
for transforming the observability by
automatically detecting, anomalies,
predictive failures, and even enabling,
some self healing capabilities
in, in multi cloud environment.
the next is the observability in
the serverless and edge computing.
if, when the workload shifted to
serverless architectures and edge
computing, observability solutions
should evolve to provide, real time
visibility, into those, these ephemerals.
EAL resources and highly
distributed environments.
The next is eeb, EBPF, and the kernel
level monitoring is mainly applicable
for the Linux, OS operating systems.
so EBPF is revolutionizing the cloud
monitoring by enabling deep, lowered
visibility into system calls, network
activities, and application behavior,
directly at the Linux current level.
the next is the shift level
observability for DevOps and Sari.
So if we, apply observability early in the
software development life cycle, so it,
allows DevOps and SRE teams to proactively
detect issues, optimize the performance,
and even ensure the reliability
from the beginning, reliability
of the systems from the beginning.
And at last, the security
driven observability, that's
a COPS plus observability.
So this allows, security, cloud
security teams to integrate security
insights into observability pipelines.
to enhance threat detection,
compliance enforcement and a
proactive risk management across,
cloud native applications.
Thank you.