Hi everyone, this is Srinivas Rautumala,
I'm a senior customer engineer helping
customers in the cloud journey.
I'm here to talk about Azure landing zone
and how it benefits the organizations.
Azure landing zone is a key element for
a successful cloud adoption journey, as
it establishes the platform competence
and helps organizations successfully
migrate and innovate in the cloud,
whether the organizations are building
a cloud native applications or building
applications for Azure virtual machines.
Azure landing zone lets organization
build a strong foundation.
Without any delay, let's
jump into the topic.
Before we dive deeper into the Azure
landing zone itself, we need to
understand where does the landing
zone stand in the cloud journey.
Cloud Adoption Framework is a
Microsoft best practice guidance
for organizations looking to
migrate, modernize, and optimize
their cloud environments on Azure.
The CAF has been divided
into several phases, such as
define strategy, plan, ready.
adopt, govern, manage, and secure.
The first is defined strategy.
It's about defining the business
objectives and justification
for moving to Azure.
it's about aligning cloud
investments with business goals.
In the plan phase, organizations
will be assessing the current IT
landscape and workload dependencies.
In the ready Organizations are
preparing the Azure learning
zone, establishing a subscription
model, and configuring policies.
This is, the phase in cloud
adoption framework where we
are going to dive deeper today.
Migrate phase is about, executing
migration plans using tools like
Azure Migrate, Azure Site Recovery,
and Database Migration Service.
Governance is about establishing
a governance framework using
Azure Policy and Azure Blueprints.
And in managed organizations needs to
implement tools like Azure Monitor, Azure
Log Analytics, Workspace, Application
Insights for proactive monitoring.
Last but not the least is secure.
Security is a very important
in the cloud journey.
It's about identifying security and
compliance requirements, deploying
cloud posture management tools like
different cloud and same tools like
Sentinel to keep the environment secure.
Why do we need a learning zone?
It's important to have a strong
foundation when we are building the
infrastructure, for example, like
building a house or a bridge or a stadium.
The same logic applies to
building the cloud infrastructure.
The strong foundation will enable
organizations to build a secure, scalable,
and a well governed cloud environment
that accelerates deployment while
ensuring compliance, security, and best
practices for The enterprise workloads.
What is Azure Learning Zone?
Azure Learning Zone is a conceptual
architecture, which the organization
used to build their Learning Zone.
This will make the organization
more agile, and the Learning Zone
architecture will help them grow
their footprint in Azure with ease.
Learning Zone will also
enable them embrace automation
and integration with ease.
Key benefits of the Learning Zone is
agility, scalability, and it's secure.
So this is a very, common topic
and a very important, discussion
we have with the customers, whether
they need a single subscription
versus a multiple subscription.
Organizations often, go with multiple
subscription to avoid a per subscription
resource limit and to better manage
and govern their Azure resources.
It's important to define a
strategy for, scaling your,
applications, in the subscriptions.
Subscriptions have defined
limit for some resource types.
For example, the number of virtual
networks in a subscription is limited.
When a subscription approaches
these limits, organizations have
to create another subscription and
put additional resources there.
Azure Management Groups are top
level containers in Azure hierarchy
that helps organizations manage
access and policies and compliance
across multiple subscriptions.
We can segregate the workloads using the
management group like what you're seeing
in the picture that's on the right.
Based on environments such as, prod,
pre prod, development, QA, etc.
We can apply these policies based on
different environments at the management
group level, so we don't have to
manage the subscription individually.
Also, applying the RBAC policies
is much easier when we have
such a management model.
so we can control who has
access to which resources.
Let's look at the key challenges
when working with our customers and
partners, where we have received the
feedback on some challenges they face.
When starting with Azure,
customers are being accustomed
to a traditional IT architecture.
The cloud model can get lost in the
translation between the technology
concepts and security models.
On the top of the architectural
challenges, there are challenges
with operating models.
Traditional delivery and management
of IT services is not compatible
with the cloud operating models.
Lastly, our customers and partners
have desired for control of their
cloud environment and compliant
platform that generates trust.
What you are seeing here is the Azure
landing zone conceptual architecture,
which shows what are the things the
organization might have to be deploying
in the landing zone architecture.
Not all, not all organizations
might need this big of a design.
Depending on the size of the
organization, we can simplify this a bit.
On the top, it starts with, the identity,
which is also, called a secure tenant.
The organization then, will be
creating different management groups,
underneath the tenants, and, they
are the logical containers for
separating different, workloads.
First, we start with the root group.
What you're seeing here.
And, then we create, management
groups underneath it.
Such as the platform, learning
zone, and the sandbox containers.
Under the platform, we have identity,
management, and connectivity.
Under the learning zone, different
departments will be creating
their own workloads, for deploying
their resources in Azure.
Each container, under the platform
such as, Identity has its resources
related to Identity, gets deployed
under the Identity subscription.
Let's say an organization is having
Active Directory servers, they'll
be, deploying that Active Directory
servers under the Identity subscription,
which you're seeing on the left.
Under the Management subscription,
resources are, resources
such as, Log Analytics, Azure
Policies are, gets deployed.
And in the connectivity
subscription as well.
you are deploying the network
resources such as, VPN Express Route
and this, connectivity, subscription
will become the hub for your network.
Organization might also follow
different approaches, to get, to
get to the end State organization
might, be of different sizes.
Organization might be building
just a platform subscription.
And under the platform subscription, they
will, they might be deploying all the
identity management and network resources
underneath it because they are very small.
They might also build a couple of
learning zones for their workloads.
And some of the customers might have
hundreds of subscriptions, for different
departments, which who might follow
this, the conceptual model lasses.
So these are the different stages that the
customer might be in the cloud journey.
First is the start stage.
The customers are brand new.
They are, they want to move towards an
accelerator architecture with landing
zone accelerator, which I'm going to dive
deeper into this in the latest slide.
Organization might be in the align stage.
Organization have built their design.
but they would like to align
with the best practices.
The organization can review
the design areas and assess
what parts need to be improved.
In the enhanced stage, customers
might, like to enhance their enterprise
case landing zone with some tweaking.
Let's say they would like
to build a better governance
or even make it more secure.
Let's start on the cloud journey by
looking at our Greenfield deployment.
The term Greenfield means the
organization don't have anything running
in Azure, and they are planning to
migrate their workloads into Azure.
Are they going to build
their workloads from scratch?
Some organization might have, might
be doing some testing, in Azure,
but they don't have a production,
any workloads running in Azure yet.
If the organizations are in this
phase, it is much easier for them to
build a landing zone from scratch.
How are they going to
build a landing zone?
We have, we offer several options.
which we are going to
see in the next slide.
Azure Learning Zone Accelerator are,
so Azure Learning Zone Accelerator
are a ready made deployment
experience for organizations where
conceptual architecture, fits in
with the operating model and resource
structure they are planning to use.
Organizations can choose, the design
which which they want to deploy using
the Azure portal based deployment
to provide full implementation
of the conceptual architecture
using that portal based interface.
let's look at in detail how to
deploy, the landing zone accelerator.
Organization can use the portal based,
accelerator which you are seeing at
the top to deploy the landing zone.
Organization can also use ARM
template, Bicep, Terraform to
build a landing zone design.
On top of this, partners can build
organizations, sorry, partners can
help organizations, in building the
learning zone through automation.
The term brownfield, means they're already
running their workloads, organizations
are running their workloads in the cloud,
but they would like to make changes,
since they have, their requirements
have changed over the period of time.
Let's say they built their learning
zone with only 10 applications in mind.
Now they are expanding their portfolio
to 100 and like to make changes so that
they can run those 100 workloads without
any challenge, without any challenges.
Let's look at what are the
common approaches in learning
zone implementation look like.
Organizations seek to align with the
target state, target state architecture
by looking at our client structural
alliance architecture, which we
discussed earlier and come up with
tweaks to align with our best practices.
Some of the areas they can focus on is
implementing Azure policies for better
governance, building management groups,
hierarchy, implementing ad backed
policies, enhanced network architecture,
and centralizing the security model.
Alignment might involve such as
moving resources between subscriptions
or building more subscription to
implement the required best practices.
In the enhanced stage, organizations
have already built an enterprise
scale landing zones and are liking to
make few changes to the landing zone
architecture to make it even better.
The areas they can focus on is
governance, management, and security.
They would like to define a business risk.
and convert those risks into policies,
monitor violations, and remediate them.
The organization can use the security
tools, such as, to reduce the security
risk and ensure they are prepared for any
security incidents if they were to occur.
I would like to summarize what
we, what we discussed today.
First, I talked about, the
cloud adoption framework and its
importance in the cloud journey.
Where does the landing zone
fit under the CAF framework?
We also looked at the Azure landing
zone conceptual architecture
and how does the design of each
components, such as the management
groups, and various subscriptions.
We looked at the landing zone deployments
options such as, portal, deployment to
portal, ARM, Bicep, Terraform options
to build landing zone architecture.
I also discussed about various stages the
organization might be in, in the cloud
journey based on how they have to build
or tweak their learning zone architecture.
Thank you very much.
I hope you got a good idea about the
learning zone and its importance.
Thank you.