Hi everyone.
I'm Dreama Badel, and I work as
a software engineer for at Adobe.
So today I'm going to talk about something
that every engineering team depends
on, but rarely talks about which is the
invisible systems behind production.
These are the systems that
power everything that we build.
For example, APIs, microservices,
data pipelines, cloud
infrastructure, and whatnot.
What is most interesting is
when the systems work well,
they almost always go unnoticed.
But when something fails, for
example, service times out or
deployment fails, or dependency fails.
Then suddenly everything becomes visible.
So we are constantly building and
maintaining these complex systems, but
still we do not fully understand them.
So the question I want to explore
today is how do we engineer the
systems effectively, and more
importantly, how does AI help us
in building this complex system?
So now let's look at
the broader landscape.
So in the past decade, enterprise
software has evolved dramatically.
We have moved towards microservices, micro
front and cloud native infrastructure
real time distributed systems.
But all of these, and yeah, all
of these systems have opened
up incredible capabilities.
We can now scale globally.
We can deploy continuously.
But at the same time, the shift has
introduced lots of complexity as well.
And that's actually a trade off.
So instead of one system, now we have
hundreds of interconnected components.
And with this, the real bottleneck
is not infrastructure, it's
actually human cognition.
In the typical enterprise
environment, we have hundreds of
services front end data pipelines.
No single engineer has a complete
mental model for all of these.
So what happens is we operate
on a partial understanding.
We probably know our services, we
know a few dependencies, but beyond
that, that things become really fuzzy
and that's when it becomes risky.
Complexity does not disappear
just because we don't see them.
It actually accumulates, and that's
why I call it as invisible complexity.
So it's always there, but only
becomes visible when something fails.
So when system complexity grows
faster than team understanding,
we start to see the issues unfold.
Things like slower development
cycle, longer debugging time,
increased incident frequency.
And this is where AI
becomes really interesting.
So in this session, I will
walk you through three pillars.
First is AI driven knowledge systems,
then AI assisted development, and then
AI enabled testing and onboarding.
Each one of these addresses the
different layer of complexity, but
together they form a unified approach
to building scalable engineering system.
So now let's look at the first pillar,
which is AI driven knowledge system.
So every organization
accumulates a huge amount of
institutional knowledge over time.
Think about everything that gets created.
For example, API contracts, the
key documentations design docs.
PRD.
So all of these are incredibly
valuable, but still it's not
centralized and not easily accessible
when you actually need them.
So answers already exist somewhere,
but engineers still have to spend
a lot of time trying to find them.
All of these create inefficiency
and lots of context switching.
So instead of building on top
of past knowledge, we end up
recreating it again and again.
Let's talk about how that
looks like in a practice.
Imagine you are working on a
feature and you want to understand
how a certain service behaves.
So what would you do?
You probably look through documents.
You look at the code.
Maybe old tickets and you ask someone.
So all of these step has a cost,
not only in time, but also in focus.
Every time you have to switch the context
and it takes an effort to get back.
So a lot of time is spent on just
navigating the information and not
on actually building or designing.
So let's see how AI can help here.
Under the hood, this is powered
by retrival based approaches.
So instead of relying on what the model
already knows, it retrieves relevant
information from your actual system.
Because an enterprise environment,
generic answers are not useful.
You need answers which are specific
to your architecture and which are
aware of all your dependencies.
And based systems make this possible.
They bridge the gap between static
knowledge and real time context.
So instead of starting from scratch, you
are actually starting from an experience.
And that is a huge shift because
a lot of engineering in efficiency
comes from solving problems
which have already been solved.
So AI helps us break that
cycle by making institutional
knowledge immediately available.
Now let's look at the next pillar,
which is AI assisted development.
So if you look at the typical development
cycle, lot of times not spent on
solving complex problems, but instead
it's spent on writing boiler plates,
creating a test plan, fixing small
issues, validating things repeatedly.
And this is not where
engineers add more value.
So what AI does is it shifts that balance.
It moves engineers from low level
execution to high level thinking.
So instead of focusing on how
do I write this score, the focus
becomes what is the right design?
What trade off should I make?
And how will this scale?
And this is where human
expertise really matters because.
AI can generate the code, but
it cannot fully understand the
long-term system behavior business
context or architectural tradeoffs.
So this shift is not doing about
less work, but instead it's
about doing more meaningful work.
So now let's look at this in practice.
So AI can generate service scaffolding,
it can auto complete complex logic.
So just three factors, right?
Unit test and validate patterns.
And it does this in real time.
While you are actually coding,
so you don't have to look up for
the syntaxes or debug trivial
issues, you can stay in the flow.
And that is important because.
Engineering productivity
is not about speed.
It's also about maintaining the focus.
So traditionally engineers used to
spend lot of time in writing boiler
plates syn tank syntax, corrections,
or repetitive reviews cycles.
But with ai, all of these can be
automated and we can focus our time on.
What really matters, which is creating
system design, making architectural
decisions, or cross team collaboration.
Okay, now let's look at the
third pillar which is AI
enabled testing and onboarding.
So most of the teams believe that
they have good test coverage,
but when something breaks in
production, it's almost always
something that was not tested.
Sorry.
And the reason is not because engineers
don't care about testing, but traditional
testing methods have limitations.
It's fundamentally predictive.
We write tests based on what we
think might go wrong, but and we test
expected inputs and non edge cases,
but the production system don't
always fall in a predictable way.
So the gap is that we test what
we imagine, but system fails
in what we don't imagine, and
this is where AI can be helpful.
It shift testing from being
predictive to being data driven.
So instead of asking what
should we test the question
becomes what has failed before?
What are the highest
risk areas in the system?
So AI can analyze past failures
frequently change code, and from
that they can identify patterns
which which humans can miss.
For example, if a certain
combination of services has failed
before, then AI can recognize
and prioritize testing around it.
If certain piece of code is changed
frequently, then it's highly likely
to be unstable and AI can target it.
So instead of writing tests from scratch,
we are learning from systems own history.
We can break this down in three steps.
So first is analyzing AI can scan,
scan historical data, and tends
to find where things can go wrong.
The second is generate where
it creates test scenarios that
specifically target failure, prone
logic and service interactions.
This kind of tests are
harder to think manually.
And third is validate and improve.
So where AI can validate this test, and
over time it can know which tests are
actually needed and which are redundant.
So testing actually becomes
continuous learning system.
Now let's connect this to onboarding.
If you have ever joined a large
engineering team, then you know
that first few weeks are spent on
trying to understand the system.
What all services exist, how
they interact with each other,
what are the dependencies, who
owns what, et cetera, et cetera.
And most of this knowledge
is not written anywhere.
So onboarding becomes slow and
dependent on senior engineers.
Now imagine replacing this experience
with something like new engineer joins
and instead of digging through dogs.
They can ask how does the
authentication works in the system?
And in response, they can get a
walkthrough of services, key dependencies,
and all the important pieces.
So this is what AI enabled
onboarding looks like.
It is faster and also contextual.
So if we zoom out what we talked
about across these pillars
are not isolated improvement.
It's a shift in how entire
enterprise system operates together.
Engineers basically becomes the decision
makers, and AI becomes the execution.
So key idea here is that AI
is not replacing the platform.
Instead it's acting as an
intelligent layer across it.
If I want to summarize, then I
can say that knowledge becomes,
queryable development becomes higher
level, where more time is spent
on architecture and designing,
and then testing becomes smarter.
Where it's driven by real world
failures and not just assumptions and.
Onboarding becomes faster because
context is always available.
So when we combine all of these,
we don't just improve productivity.
Instead we fundamentally change how.
Engineering team operates.
So most critical system in our
organization are not the one user
interacts with you most often.
They are the ones that are behind the
scenes, the invisible system that makes
everything possible and for the most time.
We have been dealing with that manually.
But with ai, this system is easily
accessible, variable, and scalable.
So it's not happening by
replacing engineers, but by
amplifying what they can do.
Thank you.