Hello, everyone.
My name is Mikkel Mark Heine and I'm
here to introduce you to SpinCube.
SpinCube is an open source project
which streamlines developing,
deploying and operating WebAssembly
workloads in Kubernetes.
It is a collaboration between Microsoft,
LiquidReply, SUSE, and Fermion.
Fermion is the company I represent,
and I'm the head of product at Fermion.
SpinQube is part of the Spin
framework, together with Spin.
Both of these are open source projects,
which are in the process of being
donated to Cloud Native Computing
Foundation, where they've both
been accepted as sandbox projects.
Spin is the development tool that
you can use to build WebAssembly
microservices and web application
using a serverless application model.
And with Spin Cube, you are able
to run spin applications really
efficiently inside of Kubernetes
because they're powered by WebAssembly.
So Spin Cube has already seen adoption
where, for instance, size has been
using Spin Cube with Microsoft's
Azure Kubernetes service to create
really fast, scalable, applications
that can run a high density.
While still, making it more easy
to operate these applications.
So they've actually done proof of
concepts and have been running,
applications where they're able to
put, to bring down the compute cost
with 60 percent without any doing trade
offs in terms of their performance.
So let's maybe unpack how all
of this works and what can
lead to these amazing results.
So to give you an overview of how these
things fit together, I mentioned that
Spin is the open source project that you
would use for developing applications.
Now, when you have a Spin application
created using Spin, you can run
these things like Kubernetes using
SpinCube as a free open source project.
Fermion also provides, some
hosted, options using Fermion
Cloud that's fully managed.
And we also have an enterprise, a set
of enterprise features around SpinQube
called Platform for Kubernetes.
Part of that being that you can
achieve in higher densities of
what we have with Kubernetes.
But we're not going to
get into that today.
We'll mainly focus on SpinQube
as an open source project.
So SpinQube consists of
four different pieces.
There is an operator to help,
translate the application model,
or application framework that Spin
is, into a Kubernetes, language.
So basically, Spin applications ends up
running as, pods, and through deployments,
and having services, all these native
Kubernetes resources that we all know.
But we have the spin operator sitting
as a wrapper around all of this that
enables you to easily translate between
the concepts you use in a spin application
and the concepts inside of spin.
It's actually optional to use the
spin operator and you can just create
your deployments, yourself referencing
spin applications as OCI images.
But as we start to unpack all of this,
and you'll see some details in a live
demo, you'll get a better understanding
of how these things fit together.
The runtime that enables us to run spin
applications really efficiently inside
of Kubernetes is part of a container
D shim called container D shim spin.
So basically, at the container D,
the container runtime layer, install,
install the shim on your node that So
we are able to cont, to tell container
D that in the case that we want to
run a spin application, a web assembly
application, we are actually not gonna
use your regular container runtime.
We are gonna use a different shim,
for running the web assembly.
Which means that you won't see your
regular C groups and all of that on
your nodes as you run the WebAssembly,
and part of this is how we can get
to higher density in some of those
scenarios inside of Kubernetes.
There's also the Runtime Class Manager.
Really, the Runtime Class Manager
is here to help ease up the
configuration set of Container D.
So in particular, if you have Kubernetes
clusters where you rely on auto
scaling, and adding extra nodes into
your cluster, having a, configured
runtime class manager enables you to
set up your nodes, dynamically, to
be able to run the Spin applications.
And the final piece of all of
this is the SpinKube plugin.
So part of the Spin, developer
tool, there is a CLI.
And basically the SpinCube plugin
makes it really easy to transition
from local development, scaffolding
YAML to pushing your spin
applications into OCI registries.
And we'll get to see that again
once we get into the demo.
let's try this out and let's take
a look at, how this all works.
And I'll start by basically
creating a small application.
so let's transition over here.
Okay.
Let me just give you a few references
as we go along, so you have those.
Spin Framework has its
own GitHub organization.
we're still in the process of moving
everything over from where these
things, were previously, as part of
all this, the contribution into CNCF.
But you can see you have, Spin, the
development tool, as one repository, and
then you have some of these components
that I talked about, like the Spin
operator that contain a DCM Spin, Runtime
Class Manager, and then there are various
SDKs for Spin that are also part of this.
So SpinFramework is a good
place to go in GitHub.
SpinCube has its own
documentation, which is spincube.
dev or website.
So basically spincube.
dev contains all the
documentation you would need.
There are a few blog posts in here
as well for certain scenarios.
And we'll get back to some of
these as we walk through building
an application with SpinCube.
And when you need to build an
application with SpinCube, you
need to go to developerferment.
com for now, which is where
the spin applications are.
The spin application, sorry, the
spin documentation is to be found.
And the reason why I'm saying for now is
because again, part of the transitioning
and contribution into CNCF, these
things may move around a little bit, but
Definitely stay on Spin Framework GitHub
and we'll be able to guide you there.
You'll also be able to find both Spin
and SpinCube channels inside of the
CNCF Slack, where you can reach out
and interact with maintainers and other
people that are part of the community.
Okay, so with all of that in place,
let's actually try and With this,
built in application that we can
run inside of a Kubernetes cluster.
So the few things that I have prepared
here is I already have a cluster running.
This is a local K3D
cluster that I've created.
if you want to run this in Microsoft
AKS, there is a marketplace offering
where you can easily configure SpinCube.
And on the, SpinCube documentation,
there are a lot of, guides in terms of
how to get these running on, Kubernetes
clusters and micro caves, Azure, Ranger
desktop, and just in general, how
you can install spinQube with Helm.
And if we really quickly want to run
through this, we rely on cert manager.
In order for Spin Cube to run and
then we install the runtime class.
Previously K was operator.
that's the one the runtime class manager
enable us to, to install container D.
And then, we can go and get some CDs in.
There are a few custom resources we need
for the spin operator, the Spin Runtime
classes and the Spin app executor and.
Finally, there's a Helm's Yard to
basically install the spin operator,
and I guess that should be it.
Now we got to the point where we upgrade
and uninstall, but let's not do that now.
We want to try this out first.
So hopefully you get this idea that
even though there are a few things
you need to set up, all of these are
regular things you would expect from
Adding this kind of, frameworks and
functionality into a Kubernetes cluster.
So I have already done all of that,
and if I can find my, cluster again,
you can see, beyond CertManager, what
I have is I have the spin operator
installed down here, and I also have,
Jaeger installed, so I can, maybe we
can look at some traces as we go along.
Okay, so that's all that I have
inside of my cluster for now.
so before we get into how this all
works inside of Kubernetes, let's just
quickly create a spin application.
the way that you create a spin application
is basically, there's a spin new command.
you use the template
to create applications.
In this case, I'm using a template.
that will, that is set up to take HTTP
requests and is written in TypeScript.
let's just call this HTTPS.
We're going to name
the application CONF42.
And, let's go into the directory and
let's take a look at what we have.
a few things got created for us.
Main thing is the spin.
toml file which describes our application.
I think the main thing to be, to
take a note of here is you have this
concept of HTTP paths or triggers.
So there is a wildcard route, meaning all
HTTP requests coming to this application,
is being handled by this one WebAssembly
component here that is named CON42.
And CON42 is basically a WASM
file, so a WebAssembly binary file.
I'm not going to spend time going
more into the details of the
whole JavaScript to WebAssembly
and how these other things works.
you can find a wealth of
information on Fermion's Spintube.
Sorry, Spintube.
On Fermion's YouTube channel.
where, we have a lot of videos that
sort of help you understand even the
WebAssembly part and all of that.
So if you want to dive more into the
development pieces and how this all works,
I highly recommend go and check those out.
All that is just interesting, to
know here is that Spin has a concept
of this application manifest, which
is what I'm showing you right now.
the other thing that we have is
then obviously our JavaScript.
And just for the sake of making this
a bit easier to, grok, let's do this.
I'm just going to run an npm
install, so that I get my,
all the, the npm packages that I need,
in this case, I need this router.
to give you an idea of how these spin
applications, like we talk about them as
serverless, but basically what this means
is that we have a, an event listener,
in this case, an HTTP listener that
you implement here, and in the case of
using, this idi router, But basically
what we do is you can set up various
functions that reply to various HTTP
requests based on the routes being called.
So basically in the case that
we call a route, we're just
going to say, hello, universe.
Actually change that to CONF42, and let's
make the capsulization of that correct.
So if we'll send an HTTP request to the
route, we'll just say, hello, CONF, and we
will say, slash, hello, slash, something.
We will reply with hello to
whatever we passed in on that path.
All of this is just stuff that happens in
this IDI router, which is a JavaScript,
library that you can use, but I hope it
gives you a sense that spin applications
are meant to, they're basically
triggered by HTTP event, they're going
to do their thing, they're going to
shut down again, and we will see how
we can use that in terms of scaling
things and so on a little bit later.
Okay, so this is
basically our application.
Let's try this out by
using a spin build command.
So now what is happening is we're going
to take the JavaScript and through a set
of build tools, we will have a WebAssembly
WASM file coming out on the other end.
Which gives us a lot of the
benefits of portability.
They're small, they're secure, because
they're run inside of sandboxes,
and they start up really fast.
And we can see that if we do spin
up, which actually loads our,
spin application, and now we can
call the spin application locally.
And you can see, hello con 42, and if we
do hello there, you can see hello there.
Okay.
So that's pretty straightforward.
We actually have a small,
spin application now.
Powered by WebAssembly, it can
reply to a few different, paths.
Okay, we want now to get
this into Kubernetes.
usually what we would do with containers,
and the workflow is similar, because,
really one of the core, objectives in
terms of how we wanted to design SpinQube
was to just make it, make sure that
WebAssembly became You could say a first
class citizen inside of Kubernetes.
So when you want to, which means
that, when we need to distribute
this application, for instance,
we rely on OCI to do that.
So if you have an OCI registry
already today, that will be
compatible with moving the spin
applications into Kubernetes clusters.
And you'll see that once we get a
little bit further down in terms of
how the CIDs and all of this work.
Okay, so now we want to use the
SpinCube plugin, so I just want to
make sure again that I build the
latest version of my spin application.
I'm just doing that because I've sometimes
forgotten how to do that, forgotten that
I wanted, sometimes I forgot to do that.
Okay, then we're going to use a
command called spin registry push.
So basically now I can push the spin
application into a container registry.
And I am going to use, let's do
this, I'm going to use TTLSH.
This is an ephemeral publicly
available container registry or OCI
registry, which is really nice when
you want to do demos like this.
So what is happening now is Spin is
going to take my WebAssembly application,
the manifest that were created, and any
configuration that I may have, package
those as three individual layers into an
OCI image, and push it to this registry.
What's really important here is
that's the only thing we're pushing.
we're not, We're not creating
filesystem, whole layers of filesystems.
Dependencies are not brought in
because they're already compiled
into the web or simply binary.
So if we go ahead and
actually inspect the image.
That we have inside of, inside of, our
registry, we should be able to see that
the only thing in here, I'm just going
to move up so you can see, there's a
bunch of annotations, oh, I even got
my name in there, which is nice, and
you can see there's a small config.
json, which is 209 bytes, then we have
our WebAssembly, which in this case is 12
megabyte, we can strip and we can compress
this even further, but it's only a 12
megabyte binary that we're moving in and
then some, the actual spin application,
manifest as well, which is 534 bytes.
That was the toml file that I showed you.
that's really all that there is there.
there isn't a bunch of layers with,
with, dependencies and other things
that I need to bring us along.
And this is all that we're
going to move around.
And this is one of these things where
WebAssembly is super interesting in terms
of having smaller images, and having,
fixed binaries that we actually move.
Okay, now the next thing I'm going
to do is I'm going to use, command
to easily create my, my deployment.
So in this case, I'm going to say,
spinkube scaffold, so basically scaffold
the YAML that I need, use the container
image, path that I just created, that I,
which I pushed to and put this in an app.
yaml file.
So if we look at this file, you can
see we have a Kubernetes YAML where
we are using the spinkube dev API.
So this is part of the custom resource
that are being created as we deploy it.
we created the custom resource
before that this is part of the whole
SpinQ project, where we actually
have a SpinApp resource in here.
this very much looks like how you would
create a, container, or deployment.
More actually, in terms of we have
replicas in here, and I think I mentioned
earlier on, you can consider this spin
app resource to be a way to try and
easily translate what we saw in the spin.
toml file, because we'll do that a little
bit later by adding variables in here.
there is a, there's an easy transition
between these two, but they're all end
up just being deployments and containers.
deployments and pods, sorry, containers.
Okay, so now that I have this,
let's move over and give this app a
YAML file to a Kubernetes cluster.
And what we'll see is, first of
all, we can go and take a look
at the spin app, where we now
have this con42 spin app created.
So this is the spin app
resource I'm looking for.
We want to have two, and we can
see two of those already now.
we can see the description
in here, basically.
What we expected, or what you can also see
is there's actually a deployment created.
So again, we're creating
a real deployment.
We could have chosen to really just
create the deployment if we wanted to.
But that sort of takes the spin
operator out of the picture.
And there are various things that
we use the spin operator for.
For instance, here I'm able to
have a cluster wide OTIL endpoint.
That I create, which means that I
now have a Jaeger instance in here.
So all my spin apps will automatically
adopt that hotel configuration.
So there's some benefits you
can get from all of these.
so yes, highly recommend using
the operator and using the spin
app resource for doing this.
we also have a service
that's set up for us.
So what we can try and do in
here is we can go ahead and
port forward to our service.
Let's do 80, 80, because.
That's the way, that's what I normally do.
And if I don't, something will go wrong.
We've now created this port forward, which
means we can go back here, and we can then
curl to 8080, and you can see helloConf,
and we can do hello there, and I just
need to get my spelling There you go.
And now we have hello there, and
hello here, so on and so forth.
We can see this all works
as it works locally.
So that's it.
We've actually taken a spin
application that we created, from
scratch, used TypeScript, and saw
we can run this locally, easily,
and compiled this into WebAssembly.
We created an OCI image that
we pushed, created the spin
app resource inside Kubernetes.
And there it is, and there it is running.
Let me go back and just, I
want to do, let me check.
Oh, we can see there are actually
two pods behind this, right?
You can see there are the two pods
being created in here, and this is also
where we can go ahead and find our logs.
There's an open telemetry error.
Let's just not think about that,
but you can actually see that we
did hit the, we did hit the spin
application in one of these pods.
I think one thing that I wanted to show
you around the Jaeger instance is that I
have Jaeger set up in my cluster as well.
And if I go ahead and just look at,
something that Spin is doing for me,
we can see that, not that long ago,
we were actually hitting the Spin
application, and you can see we have the
whole OTIL configuration being in here.
We were getting the, there
was an HTTP GET request.
for the root and what happened is
that SpinCube then executed this
awesome component called Conv42.
So just to give you an idea again of
how much work that's actually been
put into make it really easy to give
a lot of the stuff that you say, these
are just like table stakes today.
You want to have a hotel, you want to
have all of these things, and it's really
easy to get this set up and running
with SpinCube and your Spin application.
Okay, moving ahead from that.
actually, let's just do a quick
recap of what happened here.
So we did spin new to create
a new application, spin
build, created a WebAssembly.
Registry push this into OCI.
You can use any OCI image you want.
If you have a private registry, which I
hope you have, I think it's spinregistry.
login.
And then you would basically be able
to log into that before you push.
And all of these can easily
be run in a CI setup as well.
There are actually GitHub actions
that exist out there to do
all of these things with Spin.
And then we did kubescaffold as a
nice little tool to scaffold our
YAML and applied that to our cluster.
What happened when we
applied it to the cluster?
the resource was being put
into the API server as a, as
a spin app custom resource.
The operator picked that one up,
created deployments and services, and
now we have that spin app running.
in a pod, but in the pod, the
runtime class managed to make
sure the container DCM is there.
So we are actually executing using
the container DCM spin and not
using the regular container runtime.
And, and yes, that's it.
I was just thinking about how we
can actually, I don't think there's
an easy way for me to show that.
but that is how that works.
I think what we can see, actually,
if we did a, if we looked at the
actual part, we should be able
to see in here that, lemme check.
You can see the runtime class.
We use this wast time spin we two.
And basically that runtime class is what
informs container D that we want to use.
The spin runtime wasnt Time is part
of, is wrapped inside of spin, but
we only use the spin, V two version
of the runtime to actually run this.
It's not being run, in a normal container.
Okay, let me go back and showcase
another scenario we have.
We have this application now, and
let's just try and see how this,
again, how having an application
like this, using something as simple
as providing a variable to our
application, how all of that works,
with a regular, Kubernetes, workflow.
What I would do in a spin application
to begin with is that I need to
add a variable into my, spin file.
So basically what I'm going to do in
here is I'm going to say that I have
a variable, for my spin application
called myVar, and there's a default
value to that, which is cont42.
Then the other thing I can do inside of
spin is I can say as part of my component
down here, so the Hello, it's not
called HelloCount42, it's just Count42.
Part of this component variables, there's
a variable that I want to pass on to my
component, and the variable that, or the
string that I want to use for this, comes
from the MyBar that is created up here.
So basically what this enables is
inside of Spin, I can now go to
my file, and I can do two things.
I can import, if I get the import correct,
a way to get variables using the spin SDK.
And then the other thing that
I've done in here is I've just
prepared a small piece of code.
Let me do this, and I think I will need to
do an npm install to get the package in.
And let me just check what's
going on, get rid of that one.
Okay, so what I did in here in my code,
iterated as I eat this, I imported the
variables from the spin SDK, and now I'm
setting up another path in the router
saying if someone calls me on slash bar,
I will basically private my bar is, and
then I'm going to get my variables from
the my component bar, which is the one
that we just added into the tomo file.
And now that we have this created here,
let's go back and do a spin build.
We're going to rebuild our application
and then we can do a spin up again.
So basically run this application.
And if we.
let's do 3000 and then var, you can see we
get the default value, which was cont42.
I can also set this var by using
spin underscore var basically.
If I set that environment variable
when I run spin up, I've now
provided, the variable and you can
see my var is now something else.
That was the local story, to get an
idea of how these things, work together.
Now, what I want to do is I want to push
this into my cluster, so I'm just going
to make sure I have the latest build.
Once I have that, we
can do a registry push.
Let's do version 2.
So we're going to push the new
compiled WebAssembly, the new, spin.
toml that still has that
default value in it, CON42.
but what we will do is we'll just
bypass that for now, and then we'll
actually provide a configuration.
through the, the app YAML that we have.
So we don't need to create this again.
We can basically just go in here and we
can variables as easy as, oops, as this.
So let's say we have variables.
And we have a variable called
myvar and oops, I just want to
make sure we get indents right.
Let's say the value is kubernetes
because we're in kubernetes action.
Let's say the value is spinq.
that's more nice than
what we're doing here.
you need to remember
to update the version.
Okay, so basically we now have updated the
spin application, the spin app resource
definition to pull in the new version of
the image, and we provide variables, so if
we do buy this, we can go back and we can
see that we have new containers creating,
and we should soon be able to see that it.
The previous versions being taken
down and so at least I think we have,
this was the new version, let's check,
yeah, we have one which is version two
of our image and we should have two,
oh, that was refreshing, yes, we now
have two of the new versions running,
so we got those quickly deployed.
let's go and check if our
forward is still set up.
It's not, let's do this forward to the
service once again, and we can go over
here and we can now curl an 8080 and we
would expect to see five hours spin queue.
Okay.
So that was one scenario where
basically, again, wanted to show how,
variables can be added and other things.
You can obviously have the variable
being pulled from a secret.
if we take a quick look
at the API documentation.
for the spin app, you can, actually,
instead of doing that, let's
just look at an example because
I think that's more interesting.
it's easier to see.
assigning variables.
in this scenario, basically, this is
part of the spin configuration for
the example that's going through here.
what we did in the spin.
toml file.
But basically, what you can see down
here is, how you can use both config
maps and secrets to provide this.
And then this would be what
the spin app would look like.
So you have, this is what I did, an
inline variable, but we could also
have the variable be, from a config map
reference or from a secret reference.
And all of this would look very familiar
to how you would do this normally in
deployments, when working with containers.
regular containers inside
of the Kubernetes cluster.
Okay, let's actually do check on this
one because we did see, you can see
this was the trace from where we were
actually using the get, so you can
see spin is fully, instrumented and
then we can see we're actually calling
another, method inside of the spin
SDK to actually get the variable.
which was pretty quick in terms
of how that variable's gotten.
And if we want to dive even
further into this, because why not?
What we can see is that the way
that all of this sort of ends up
being set up is that the actual
pod, I am, let me just check.
We're looking at the pod right now.
The actual pod has the,
let's see if we did the YAML.
The actual pod has that spin variable
myvar set up as an environment
variable, which is the same way that
I got this environment, this variable
injected when I ran things locally.
So again, gives you an idea of how
the operator works and what value it
adds inside of the whole stack here.
Okay, let's try something a little bit
more fancy because part of the, part of
the benefits we get from using WebAssembly
rather than containers is how quickly
they can scale because the small size,
how quickly we can pull them in, but also
how fast they will actually start up.
so a good scenario would be
something like combining this
with, scaler, inside of Kubernetes.
So what I will be doing now is I, let
me just check because I think, yeah, we
already have KEDA running in our cluster.
I think what we can, so what I
will do is based on the tutorial
that you're able to find.
over here in the SpinCube site, which
is, called Scaling SpinApps with
Kubernetes Event Driven Autoscaling.
So basically using KEDA.
this is an example that walk you through
how basically there is an application
that, that creates a lot of CPU load.
But obviously using KEDA, you can scale
based on CPU load, you can scale based
on observing, queues or other things.
I think even object stores, there's a
whole bunch of stuff that KEDA can do.
but again, because everything at
SpinCube is so integrated into how
Kubernetes works, most of the Kubernetes,
ecosystem and most of those projects
that are out there will actually just
work out of the box with SpinCube.
so what I've done is I've created,
I've added KEDA into my cluster right
now, and all of that is something you
can do inside of this, this article.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm just
going to apply this, KEDA scaled object.
Basically, this is KEDA's way of saying,
Oh, actually, this is the application.
Sorry, I'm going to add the application
to begin with, and then I'm going to
create a kitter scaled object, which
basically is the one that is monitoring
the spin app, changing it between
one and 20 replicas based on CPU
and based on 50 percent utilization.
So that's the threshold for
when we add another replica
when we take down a replica.
So the few things that we
need to do here to make this
work is to go to our terminal.
And first thing we're going to
do is we're going to apply the.
The sample application and the next
thing I am going to do is I am going to.
By the scaled object, so if we
quickly go over here, we can
see we now have a Keda spin app.
we actually had minimum one.
I believe we could change this to zero.
We'll try that.
We have outer scaling set to true.
readability curve is one.
I think we would have
to Whoops, we got stuck.
Let's get out of here.
this one says minimum one.
Anyways, let's not do this now.
Maybe we can play around
with it a little bit later.
I just got myself all excited about
whether we could actually, whether
we could actually do that or not.
Anyways, let's go back
and monitor the spin app.
We have that here.
I think if I do ctrl R,
that will be refreshing.
So we can see we have one of the
Keda spin apps running already,
translated into one part.
So what I'm going to go do now
is I'm just going to create some
requests to the application.
Before I can do that, I need
to set up a port forward.
So let's set up a port
forward to the service.
let's do 8081 and back and
take a look at the spin app.
We have it and then we can go over here
and now we have load and we should fairly
quickly start seeing that more parts needs
to be spin up of the data application.
Let's go and take a look at The pods
over here, we can see CPUs at 429.
Oh, there you go.
Okay.
Now things are starting to happen.
We got a bunch more of the cater apps.
and if we come back, we
can see we're now at 4.
And we should gradually see this changing.
Let's just go back and stop
some of these HTTP requests.
we got nine responses back.
This is not a case of performing.
This is just a case of
showing how these things work.
And you can see that this all works.
We got extra parts.
We got more of these spin apps running,
inside of our Kubernetes cluster.
And I don't quite recall whether
the app will actually ever stop
again or will just keep increasing.
but at one point we should see that the
number would cool down and we'll then
have a fewer of the spin application
instances of the web application.
that was a few examples of how you can
get started, looking at, using variables
and other things, and also how this
works really well with other projects
like OpenTelemetry Stacks, Jaeger in
this case is what we saw, we saw, and
even Kubernetes Event Driven Autoscaler.
we might actually see, yeah, this
is the CPU load, but we can see a
bunch of those coming in as well.
I don't know whether those will
actually ever complete or not.
a few resources to go for, spincube.
dev.
And you can get to learn
a lot about SpinCube.
developerfirmian.
com is a good place to get some spin
documentation and Spin Framework
on GitHub is the place that you
go and take a look for this.
Okay, so hopefully along the way
I've, you've got the idea that,
SpinCube like just easily flows into
your regular, way of working with
Kubernetes and your workflows you
have around CI, CD and all the other
things you can do around Kubernetes.
There's obviously the question of
why do we need spin WebAssembly
applications in Kubernetes.
And I think there are, four, four very
particular things that you want to,
want to consider, and why I think this
is super relevant, and why I think this
is a way that we can, bring even more
value and then so on into Kubernetes.
first of all, as I showed you, the
spin applications are really small.
So comparing to a lot of containers
where you potentially bring in a lot
of dependencies and all of these,
you have a single binary that needs
to bring and you potentially have
some configuration and maybe you have
some data that you bring as well.
But a hello world spin application
that's not written in JavaScript,
but written in Rust, could be as
small as a few hundred kilobytes.
that's the OCI artifact that
we need to juggle around.
So this gives us a lot of great
opportunities in terms of, if we need
to run these things and we want to use
Kubernetes as a workload manager or
scheduler, even in environments that
have little compute capacity and power,
this is something that can potentially
make that work with Kubernetes, so
you don't have to rely on containers.
Another part of this is that
the WebAssembly components start
in less than a millisecond.
um, the way, actually the execution
model, we haven't really talked about
it, but the execution model in this,
in, in the world of, of spin and
WebAssembly is that the component, and
maybe we want to go back and look at
this file just to give you a, you have.
What I mean, let's look at this.
So you can see that there is this,
the way that a spin application is
defined in here, we have this idea of,
or this concept of a component, right?
So we have an HTTP trigger
that maps to a component.
The component is the WebAssembly file.
So I can easily create applications where
I have multiple of these components.
So each WebAssembly file represents,
a different path on the route or
a different set of functionality
inside this application.
Whenever a request hits our application,
what happens inside of the runtime is
that the WebAssembly binary is loaded.
The request is handed over in
memory from the host to the guest.
The guest in this case
being your application.
It's handing the request and then we're
unloading the WebAssembly module again.
Which means that if you had four or
five different WebAssembly modules in
here, for each request, only the mod,
only the modules that needs, or the
components that needs to be loaded are
the ones that are going to be loaded.
And that we will use, for this, which
also means that as soon as the work
is done, the WebAssembly is unloaded.
So it's only the host runtime that
takes up memory on your Kubernetes node.
And this is where the density that
we can get from running WebAssembly
actually comes from is that
there's a very low, minimum, memory
assumption that is taking place.
And there are even ways, and this
is where some of the enterprise.
Add ons that we built at Fermion
come into place where we can get
fully rid of the memory footprint.
so basically truly scale to
zero, as part of, as part of
this, as part of how these run.
But that's another very, important
thing and a lot of value that I think
SpinWebAssembly applications will
bring into Kubernetes through SpinQube.
And there's the third thing,
which is that sandbox.
So this is the security part of this
WebAssembly component is a sandbox
and is denied access to resources
on the system, which means that it
does not have access to file system.
It does not have access to memory outside
of its own memory, linear memory that's
provided by the host at, when it's loaded.
Also, you have to explicitly grant
access to HTTP endpoints or other network
endpoints that you want to access.
So there's a way inside the spin.
toml file where you provide access to
particular API endpoints, whether that's
a SQL database, a Postgres database,
a Redis endpoint, a Valkey endpoint.
an HTTP endpoint, you have
to do that explicitly.
So this is a nice operational
runtime decision that you can make
of, which endpoints are available
for the actual application.
And finally, you have the portability,
cross processing, architectures and
operating systems, which means you can
swap out the underlying node processing
architecture without having to produce
separate pipelines and deploy artifacts,
meaning that the same OCI image Could
run across X 64 and ARM 64 devices.
so if you're able to use some of
those in your at cloud environment
or other environments where you
run, Kubernetes, you don't need to
deal with multi arc images and all
these multiple build pipelines.
The same Web MD binary, we actually.
In one compilation would run across all
of these processes and architectures.
So again, it dramatically simplifies,
I guess the scenario would be if you
have a workload where you can utilize
things like spot instances, or what
they're called in cloud, you can really
subscribe to spot instances provided
as ARM instances, x64 instances.
There's a lot of opportunities there to
also have some cost savings associated.
So with that being said, I hope
this gave you a good idea of what
SpinCube is, how it works, its
relationship to Spin, and some of the
benefits you'll get from using this.
So I highly recommend go
and check out spincube.
dev.
Spin documentation is on firmware.
com slash spin for now.
And thank you so much for listening.
Have a great day.