How to embedded computer vision in the
warehouse workflow and the reduced spare
parts mismatched as receiving by 99%.
Why I choose this case today?
There is a lot of
decision discussion about.
Artificial intelligent, but in my
view, the most interesting cases
are not the ones where a neural
network produced an impressive demo.
The most interesting ones are the
technology is actually embedded in the
real operation processes and starts
delivering measurable business value.
What is exactly the kind of
case I want to talk about today?
This is a, not just a story
about AI solving problem.
It is a story about how a computer
vision solution was embedded
into a real warehouse workflow,
how it operated in production,
and what engineering trade offs.
Had to be made to ensure well, the
system was not only intelligent, but
also reliable, scalable, and useful
for people on the warehouse floor.
The cases came from a manufacturing
company supplying equipment and
spare parts to the mining industry.
As the first glance, the task seemed
fairly local, reduced the number of
receiving errors, but in reality it
became a very good example of how
an AI service can become part of an
operational chain and start affecting not.
Only the warehouse itself, but
also inventory accuracy, service
quality, maintains process, and
overall business risk, business
context, and the problem itself.
The company was dealing with
a high volume of imported.
Shipments.
The warehouse regularly receives
spare parts and component from
overseas suppliers in advance.
The warehouse knew which part numbers were
expected because all of that information
existed in purchased orders, spec
specifications, and shipping documents.
But.
In practice, the same issue
keeps happening again and again,
mismatched during receiving
according to the paperwork Once.
Part was supposed to arrive,
but in reality, a very similar,
yet different part was diluted.
Instead, sometimes the
suppliers made a mistake.
Sometimes part numbers were mixed up,
and sometimes one items was shipped
under the description of an hour, and
this is where the specific matters.
This were not completely different parts.
What anyone could identify immediately,
this were very similar components
where the difference could be
minimal, a different free type.
It says different of just one or two
millimeters, slightly different geometry.
A different fit, a different engineering
tolerance, or a small variation
in body configuration for a person
without taking precise measurement
of comparing the item against catal.
This part often looked identical.
But from a business point of view,
this was not a similar spare part.
It was a different SKU and error.
And that mean receiving error.
Incorrect inventory records a
risk of ising the wrong part.
Maintenance, risk of equipment,
downtime, and additional cost.
Why this problem could not be solved
by discipline and instruction alone.
Usually when a business sees
a problem like this, the first
reaction is not tight and control.
Tell the Warehouse to be more
careful and to our instruction.
Ask employees to compare
items against Catal.
Introduce one more validation step.
But in our case, that was not
enough because the problem was
not that people were doing job,
the problem was in the nature of.
Process itself.
The warehouse was aberration under
a high volume of incoming shipments.
Limited time for receiving a strong
pressure on turnaround times, a high
cost of delays, and at the time, same
time, a very complex spare part catalog.
A warehouse operator simply does
not have unlimited time to inspect.
Every part, open technical,
ALS search documentation, take
measurement, and consult experts.
If every questionable item had
not be checked that day, the
warehouse would never meet.
Its receiving speed targets.
So the process had fallen into
a classic operational trap.
The business wanted both speed and
accuracy, but a human working manually
could not consistently provide both at the
same time for such complex product range.
What was the point when
it be became clear?
That's what we need was not just an now
produced, but a decision support tool
directly at the point of receiving.
We did not define the risk
as let's implement ai.
We defined it as let's reduce
the probability of error
exactly where the error happens.
What is an important difference.
Because if you start with the
technology, you can easily
build something impressive, but.
Useless.
If you start with the process,
then both the architecture and the
implementation logic immediately
become much more practical.
The core idea was simple.
At the moment of receiving the
warehouse operation should have
access to a fast digital tool that
helps determine where the actual.
Physical part matches the
expected part number in our words.
The system had to function as a
verification series, not simply
recognize an object in an image, but
compare the image of the part, the
expected part number, the technical
characteristic, the catal description.
With all features and historical
data from similar cases.
In a sense, we were building not just
a computer vision model, but an AI
assisted receiving core flow receiving
process, and hench by algorithmic
verification, how the solution was
structured at the architecture level.
To simplify it, the architecture
consisted of several logical layers.
The first layer, it's data.
The system used several different
data types at the same time.
Photo of parts, CATA images.
Text all description, technical
specification, item master data,
historical receiving and error records
and information about which part
number was expected in the shipment.
This was a critical point.
We understood quite quickly that
an image alone was not enough away.
Because some difference between
parts are just to be too subtle.
In some cases, two items are
almost visually in this gable and
reward context, such as the SKU,
the specifications, the product,
family, all the catalog attributes.
The model may make the wrong call.
What is why the solution was designed
from the beginning as multi-med in the
practical engineering sense, not just
to see, but to see in context the second
layer, the recognition and machine engine
at this level, the problem analysis.
Analyzed the image of the part
and compare it against reference
patterns for the expected item and
for the closest alternative items.
And the logic here was not binary.
We did not force the system to
always answer only yes or no.
Instead it returned confidence
level, the most likely part number.
A list of similar alternatives
and the disgusting futures the app
operator should pay attention to.
This was a very important
engineering choice because in a
real production workflow, the most
dangerous system is not the one that
occasionally he stated, but the.
One that make confidence,
make the first layer.
Workflow integration, the
service was embedded directly
into the receiving process.
A warehouse operation operator
would take a photo of the
part of, or upload an image.
The system would receive the
shipment context, perform the check,
and return the result in a form.
What was easy to interpret?
And the real challenge here was not
to create a nice looking AI interface.
The challenge was to fit into the
warehouses normal way of working
without and reduce friction.
If the solution shows the operator
down, people stop using it.
If it require too many
steps, we start by pacing it.
If it produced result that difficult
to interpret, we do not trust it.
So we designed the system as a quick
step inside the receiving workflow,
not as a separate, complex produced.
Why human in the was essential.
One of the key lessons from this project
was that is in this kind of process you.
Should not design AI as a fully
automotive system from day one.
A lot of presentation talk about complete
automation, but in a real operation
environment, especially one where errors
are expensive, it is usually much wiser to
start without a human plus system model,
which is a human in the loop approach.
Does that mean the system did not
replace the warehouse operation?
It augmented the operator
at high confidence.
It confirmed the match
at medium confidence.
It flexed risk and requested
additional verification.
At low confidence, it routed
the case into an expected flow.
This helped us solve
several problem at once.
First, it improved reliably.
Second, it helped us build
trusts with users much faster.
Third, it created a feedback
loop that could be used to
improve the system Our time.
Because every ambitious case
was not only an operation issue,
but also a new training example.
Now let me move to the more
interesting part, especially
for an engineering audience.
When we talk about produce production ai,
the production is not only model accuracy,
the question is how the system behaves
under the real operation conditional and
what tradeoffs you are willing to make.
In this project, there were
several major trades off the first
trade off accuracy versus speed.
If you try to perform the deepest possible
validation for every single part, the
receiving process becomes too slow.
If you make the system too fast and too
shallow, the risk of error increases.
So we did not optimize the
solution of for accuracy alone.
We optimized it for
usefulness within the process.
In our words, the system had
to be accuracy enough to catch
problematic cases and fast enough
not to break the rhythm of receiv.
The second trade off automatic
decisions versus controlled escalation.
We could have forced the system to
always make a final decision, but that
would have created dangerous, false
positive and false negative in age cases.
Instead, we introduced confidence
thresholds and escalation scenarios
where confidence was high.
The process moved quickly.
Their confidence was not sufficient.
A human measurement step or an
additional Catal check was triggered.
Yes, this is not the magic of full AI
automation, but it is the right kind
of industrial engineering The thought.
Third trade off scalably versus maintain.
Any system can be made very intelligent
if you keep additional, adding more
and more complex team, but eventually
it become impossible to maintain what
is why architect end to remain model.
Reference data separated matching
logic, separated workflow, separated
expression handling, separated
quality monitoring, separated.
The kind of decomposition is, would
allow the system to scale across a
growing part, catal without during,
into monolith that nobody can support.
The third trade off user trust
versus black box behavior.
If the system simply says not a
match, the user does not understand
why, and if the user does not
understand why trust disappears.
What is why it was importantly,
not only to provide a verdict,
but also to show explainable cues?
What to look at the difference is
why the item was flagged a risk.
The reduced the resistance to
adoption and made the system more
than just a controlled barrier.
It became a real assistant.
When we say was the solution
worked in production, we do not
just mean that the model showed
good metric on a test data set.
We mean the system became part of
real operation, workflow and started
living under the rules of that
workflow, and that is a completely
different level of requirement.
The service must be available
during working hour.
Without disruption.
Disruption.
The response must come, came back quickly.
Integration error must
not block receiving.
Failback scenario must exist.
Exceptions must be handled.
Quality must be monitored.
Model errors must be understood.
Reference data and master
data must be updated.
Any changes in the spare parts
catalog must be supported.
This is exactly where many ai any issues
fail because building prototype is much
easier than building a working service.
In our case that mattered most
was the solution was designed from
the start, not as a laboratory
model, but as a process component.
That means operational support,
maintain the, and integration, the
considerate from the very beginning
business impact and why it matters.
The result of the
implement was very strong.
We reduced spare parts, mismatch
and receiving by 99%, but I would
face size with the number of itself
is not the only important part.
What matters just as much
is how the process changed.
Dependency on the experience of
a specific employees was reduced.
Receiving quality became more consistent.
The number of this dispute cases
decreased, and when the accuracy
improved the risk of errors.
Pro propagating downstream was
reduced and the process became
much more manage manageable.
And that, in my opinion, is what
real in this Trio AI is about.
When the technology does not just improve
one logic local metric, but makes the
entire operational chain more stable.
Thank you.