Hello, everyone.
My name is Shubham Gupta,
and I am an analytics and AI
leader at Noblesoft Solutions.
First of all, I would like to thank
Conf42 for inviting me as a speaker
for Cloud Native 2025 conference.
I'm very excited to talk about
my topic, which is agentic AI
and blockchain autonomous systems
for next generation innovations.
So folks, let's dive in.
I will begin my presentation by,
referring to some key points from
Sam Altman's, three observations.
Sam Altman is the CEO of OpenAI, the
company responsible for creating ChatGPT.
So he says that AI intelligence
scales with resources.
So the more computing power, the
more data and the more inference you
provide to AI systems, the smarter
and more intelligent they become.
Another key point.
is that the cost of AI drops by a
factor of 10 every year, which means
that AI is becoming cheaper and also
getting commoditized and is no longer
accessible only to big tech companies
as it was happening a few years ago.
So what this means for
2025 and beyond, right?
So AI is no longer playing a passive role
in the decision making process, but it
is slowly becoming a virtual co worker
who can actively collaborate with you.
And we are already seeing this disruption
in software engineering already.
Now, what is agentic AI?
agentic AI refers to autonomous
software agents capable of decision
making with minimal human intervention.
These agents do not merely react,
but they proactively execute
strategies to solve complex tasks.
what is agentic AI again, right?
agentic AI is the future
of autonomous intelligence.
Now, as you can see in the diagram,
it has six key components, context
awareness, goal setting, processing,
decision making, ethics and
governance, and then autonomous action.
Autonomous action is a very
important word here, right?
these AI agents operate on the core
principle of autonomous operation,
goal driven behavior, context
awareness, and self improvement.
They feature an autonomy engine
that enables self initiated
actions and resource management.
these AI agents use adaptive learning.
to continuously evolve
through reinforcement learning
and pattern recognition.
It incorporates a decision matrix
for real time risk assessment
and scenario simulation.
It maintains ethical boundaries
through a dedicated governance layer.
It integrates with other AI agents,
through a collaborative ecosystem.
It also represents the next
evolution in AI, which is moving from
reactive to proactive intelligence.
here is the day to day
use case of, AI agents.
AI agents can proactively
take actions here.
They can post, the content on
different social media platforms.
They can decide what to post,
when to post, where to post,
how to post, so that you can get
maximum engagement on your content.
So you can see that, these AI agents
are proactively making decisions.
so now let's learn a little
bit about AI agents, right?
So they have six core components.
The number one is learning system.
so these AI agents build comprehensive
knowledge base and then it adapts
its learning method continuously.
Then comes goal framework.
So the framework sets
very clear objectives.
It takes progress against these.
targets or objectives, and it
ensures that alignment happens
with those intended goals.
Then comes reasoning engine.
reasoning engine processes
complex logical operations.
Um, it makes decisions
based on available data.
It solves problems through
systematic analysis.
It maintains consistency in logical flows.
Then comes memory system.
So the memory system manages
short term information storage.
It maintains long term
knowledge retention.
It handles efficient
information retrieval.
It integrates various
memory types seamlessly.
Then comes interaction layer.
this layer manages
communication interfaces.
It processes API requests.
It generates appropriate responses.
and then finally, we have
safety protocol, this protocol
implements ethical frameworks.
It enforces, constraint systems,
validate actions and outputs, and it
also ensures safe operation boundaries.
Now, let's dive into the
agentic AI architecture.
in this architecture, we
have six key steps again.
Number one is learning.
Then comes adoption.
Then comes action.
Then comes anticipation.
Then we have efficiency.
And then refinement.
learning, like we discussed,
it constantly ingests new data.
and it's training itself continuously.
dynamically updating its knowledge base.
When it comes to adoption,
the architecture implements
continuous feedback loops.
When it comes to actions, the system
demonstrates initiative and task
execution, generating strategic responses
to the challenges, and capitalizing on
the opportunities when detected, right?
Then comes anticipation.
So through forecasting capabilities, risk
assessment protocols, and trend analysis,
The system stays ahead of emerging
patterns and potential challenges.
Then comes efficiency.
So the architecture maintains peak
performances through optimization of
processes, smart resource allocation,
and continuous performance tuning.
And then finally we have refinement.
So the system ensures excellence,
operational excellence through
continuous improvement cycles,
dynamic adjustment capabilities,
and rigorous quality assurances.
Now, let's see how these
AI agents work, right?
So it starts with input processing.
So the system processes natural
language inputs from users.
It also interfaces with
the external system.
through API request, then we
have knowledge based integration,
where these agents step into
comprehensive domain knowledge.
it understands user specific
context for personalization.
Then comes task planning.
So the agent analyzes
specific goals to achieve.
It breaks down complex
tasks into sequential steps.
Is it then efficiently allocates available
resources and then it says task priorities
based on importance and urgency, right?
then comes reasoning engine, right?
So the system applies logical
inferences to draw conclusions.
It identifies patterns
and complex data sets.
Then comes tool integration.
So the agent connects with
external tools through APIs.
It processes data using
specialized processors.
It leverages external services
for enhanced capabilities.
It executes custom functions
for a specific task.
Then comes, execution engine, right?
So the, System org, is designed to
handle multiple tasks simultaneously.
It handles errors with fallback options.
It maintains state across operations.
It validates results for accuracy.
Then comes response generation.
the agents select
optimal, response formats.
It ensures quality.
It determines the best delivery methods.
And then it incorporates user
feedback for improvements.
Then comes system monitoring.
So the agent takes key
performance metrics.
It monitors for potential errors.
It analyzes users usage patterns.
It maintains system health checks.
And then finally, we have security layer.
so here, system verifies
user authentication.
It manages authorization levels.
It ensures data privacy compliance.
And it also maintains detailed audit logs.
Now, here is another way to
explain how AI agent works, right?
we have input sources.
So the system ingests data
through three primary channels.
number one is knowledge based
integration for foundational information.
Number two is user queries
for direct interaction.
And number three is API calls for
external system communication.
So then each input stream feeds into
the central processing pipeline,
which is AI processing pipeline.
So now In this stage or in this layer,
the agent processes incoming information
through sophisticated analysis systems.
It parses natural language,
structures data formats, and
prepares input for deeper processing.
Then comes, reasoning layer.
So the cognitive core applies
advanced reasoning capabilities.
to the analyzed data.
It synthesizes information from multiple
sources, identifies patterns, formulates
logical pathways to solution, and this
forms the basis for decision making.
And then finally, you have,
decision making, which is, The
agent evaluates possible actions
based on process information.
It weighs alternatives,
consider constraints, and
selects optimal approaches.
This ensures that the response aligns with
the user needs and system capabilities.
Then comes, task execution.
Here, the system implements chosen
actions through its It's execution
engine, it manages resource
allocation, handles concurrent
operations, and maintains operational
consistency throughout the process.
Then comes agent collaboration.
So multiple AI agent systems work in
concert to achieve, complex goals.
They share information,
coordinate actions.
and leverage collective capabilities
for enhanced problem solving.
Then come response generation.
So the final output synthesizes
results from all previous stages.
It then formats responses appropriately,
ensures clarity and accuracy, and
delivers information to the optimal
channel for user confirmation.
So now let's talk about the
difference between AI automation,
AI workflows, and AI agents, right?
So AI automation, as we have been seeing
in the past, it just executes predefined
scripts with some fixed rules, right?
So Zapier email integration
could be an example for this.
Then comes AI workflows.
These workflows manages complex
processes with defined decision points.
So a good example here could be
Netflix recommendation system.
And then finally comes AI agents.
these agents create autonomous
solutions through intelligent reasoning.
One example of this could be
automated inventory management
and supply chain management.
And we will go over this,
example a little bit later.
So now, after going over, AI
agents, now let's dive into
the blockchain fundamentals.
So a blockchain is a distributed
e routable ledger that records
transactions across multiple
nodes in a peer to peer network.
Now, what is the benefit of
using a blockchain, right?
So the main benefits are
decentralization, meaning the
information is not centrally stored.
It is scattered across
several different nodes.
Data, once recorded, cannot be changed.
the system is transparent, meaning
everyone, accessing the data.
sees the same information and
it's safe and secure because
of, consensus mechanisms, right?
again, why blockchain, right?
it removes single point of failure,
it ensures data integrity and
transparency, it enables trustless
environments, and then it facilitates,
secure peer to peer transactions.
And the key strengths of blockchain,
namely decentralization and immutable
record keeping are very important when
data must be verifiable and tamper proof
across multiple stakeholders, right?
so here is a blockchain
architecture, right?
here we can see that there are
different types of blockchains.
We have consortium blockchains,
we have public blockchains, and
then we have private blockchains.
These blockchains use
different consensus mechanisms.
when they need to add a new
block in the blockchain, right?
So it can either be proof of work
or it could be proof of a stake.
Now, we have gone through AI agents.
We have, understanding about blockchain.
So now let's see why we should combine
AI and blockchain together, right?
So AI and blockchain can work
together, very well to achieve
autonomous innovation, which is
where the future is heading, right?
first of all, data integration for AI.
So AI models often rely
on very large data sets.
So blockchain here ensures
data accuracy, data quality,
authenticity, which actually, make
these AI models more reliable.
Then comes autonomous agent coordination.
So for example, for complex tasks, we
might have many decentralized agents.
that needs to coordinate with each
other, without a central authority.
So in this case, combining AI and
blockchain can work very well.
then come smart contracts
for decision enforcement.
So agentic AI decisions can be executed
automatically via smart contracts.
Thereby reducing the
chance of fraud, right?
And then come auditability
of AI decisions.
So immutable records of decisions
made by AI agents can be stored on
the blockchain for future auditing.
so all these, characteristics make
this combination a really good
combination for autonomous innovation.
So here we can see that, AI.
is provided with extensively real
world data, which it uses to generate
insights, and then it triggers on chain
transactions, through smart contracts.
Then these smart contracts, record the
transactions on the blockchain, making
them available to all stakeholders, right?
here we can see that once the transactions
are recorded onto the blockchain, all
stakeholders access the same information
no matter where they are situated.
so now let's see some important
use cases of, AI and blockchain
innovation together, right?
So it can very well be used in supply
chain management where AI agents
optimize logistics and blockchain
provides, immutable record keeping.
Then we can use AI agents and blockchain
combo and decentralized finance.
We can use them in healthcare data
sharing and then energy grid optimization.
Now, as I mentioned before, let's
go over the AI and blockchain
and supply chain management.
So enterprise systems and IoT
sensors generate data, which
is then fed into the AI engine.
or AI agents to generate
insights and alerts.
Now, based on these insights, a smart
contract is triggered to record payment on
the blockchain, ensuring all stakeholders
have access to the same real time data.
now in this case, you can see we
have manufacturers, suppliers,
retailers, and then we have transport
providers, then we have warehouse.
So all of them are accessing
the same copy of data, which is
coming from blockchain ledger.
and it is the source of
truth for everyone here.
Now, when it comes to feature outlook,
we can use, AI and blockchain in
AI use case, where AI competition
happens very close to the.
Source of data, it can help in federated
learning where AI runs on multiple
devices without exposing sensitive data.
Now, AI innovations, what is
the road ahead for us, right?
So by 2035.
one person may have access to the
intellectual capacity of an entire 2025.
This is crazy, right?
and then new form of work will emerge.
very different from today's job.
So it will transition from knowledge based
economy to an allocation based economy.
AI will be integrated into everything and
then smart will become the new default.
So with these pointers in mind, I
would like to conclude my session.
I would like to thank all of you
for listening to my presentation
and I wish you a good day.
Thank you.