Hello there.
This is Santosh Kumar Rai.
Welcome to Conf42 Cloud Native 2025.
Today's topic is revolutionizing
health care with data engineering.
The integration of data engineering
is transforming personalized medicine.
Data engineers ensure the
collection, integration, and
analysis of vast data sets.
Glencians can make real time,
evidence based decisions
using data driven approaches.
So there are four main components of
the data engineering roles, collection,
integration, processing, and analysis.
The collection enables the automated
gathering of structured and
unstructured health care data from EHRs.
And the integration, seamless imaging
of disparate healthcare system and data
format while maintaining data integrity,
quality and HIPAA compliance standards.
Processing, real time data transformation
and transcending using advanced ETL
pipelines to prepare healthcare data
for immediate clinical use and analysis.
And the fourth one is analysis.
This is the implementation of
machine learning and statical models
to extract actionable insights.
enabling data driven clinical decisions
and personalized treatment plans.
And what are all the advanced data
engineering techniques that have
been used for the better performance?
Number one is a real time ETL pipelines.
Number two, scalable cloud architecture.
Number three, AI driven analytics.
The real time ETL pipeline.
This enables continuous process
of patient data streams for
immediate clinical insights.
This will facilitate rapid response
in critical care scenarios.
Scalable cloud architecture.
This deploy flexible infrastructure that
dynamically adopts to process massive
healthcare data sets while maintaining
HIPAA compliance high availability.
AI driven analytics leverages Machine
learning algorithms to analyze
complex medical data, identify early
disease indicators, and generate
personalized treatment recommendations.
Structuring and analyzing diverse data.
Genomic sequencing, electronic
health records, medical
imaging, IoT based monitoring.
So how genomic sequencing is.
Analyzing complete DNA profiles,
generating over 200 gigabytes of
actionable genetics insights per patient.
Electronic health records.
These longitudinal patients history,
including treatments, medication, and
outcome for informed decision making.
How medical imaging is helping in terms
of using the new technology, which
delivers high resolution diagnosis,
visualization through x rays.
MRIs and CT scans for precise analysis.
IoT based monitoring.
This streams continuous vital signs.
and health metrics from wearable and
medical devices for proactive care.
What are all the impacts
on the precision diagnosis?
So AI diagnostic systems, this will
reduce the medical errors by 30
percent and the machine learning models
enhance patient's risk assessment by
50 percent enabling early intervention
and preventive care strategies.
Integration of AI driven diagnostics
results in 40 percent faster treatment.
Initiations and 25%
better patient outcomes.
We'll look at the case studies
for early disease detection.
So initially we collect the data in terms
of integrating genomic data, clinical
records under real time monitoring
system to create a comprehensive patient
profile across 50 plus health indicators.
And we look in the pattern
recognization, applying the advanced
machine learning algorithms to
analyze the potential data detecting.
This is markers with a 94 percent
accuracy through neural network
analysis, predictive modeling.
So leveraging AI driven predictive
models to forecast disease.
Progression six to 12 months in advance,
enabling proactive treatment, planning
and risk management, improved outcomes.
We can achieve 40 percent faster
diagnostics time and 35 percent reduction
in late stage disease progression through
early detection and intervention stages.
Another case study is about
AI assisting drug discovery.
Here we will process over 100
million molecular compounds.
And the chemical interactions
daily reducing the candidate
identification done by 60 percent
through advanced AI algorithms.
And the target identification is
to utilize machine learning to
analyze protein drug interaction
across 100, 000 potential targets,
achieving 85 percent accuracy in
predicting therapeutic effectiveness.
Clinical trials, reducing traditional
drug development timeline from 10
years to 4 years through AI optimized
trial design and patient matching
result in 40 percent cost reduction.
This is another case study with
a real time patient monitoring.
So we monitor the data streaming,
processing via 1000 plus vital signs
per second from wearable and bedside
monitors for comprehensive health track.
Anomaly Detection AI algorithms
analyze patterns to identify
critical health changes with 95
percent accuracy within seconds.
Intervention This enables
rapid response teams to reduce
critical event response by 60%.
Leading to better patient outcomes,
alerting the smart notification systems,
prioritize and deliveries, urgent alert to
the right health care provider instantly.
And what are the challenges in terms
of data security and compliance?
So the first one is the trust and
then the compliance and the security.
So these are the three main data security
and compliances we have to consider.
the healthcare data security demands
robust production of sensitive patient
information through state of the
art encryption and access controls.
Strict adhere to HIPAA and GDPR
regulations requires comprehensive
documentation, regular audit, and
careful management data access protocol.
Building and maintaining patient
trust depends on transparent
data handling practices.
ethical AI implementation and
clear communication about how their
information is used and protected.
So the healthcare industry faces
increasingly cyber security threats with
data breaching costing an average of 9.
2 million per incident.
Organization must balance the need
for data accessibility with engine
security measurement measures.
While ensuring compliance with evolving
international regulations and what
are the challenges while we harmonize
or integrate or standardize the data.
Healthcare system currently uses
over 40 different data standards,
making standardization critical
for ensuring consistent data,
quality, and reliable analysis.
Integration across disparate systems
like EHRs, lab systems, and imaging
databases remain a significant
challenge with healthcare organizations.
spending an average of 500, 000
annually on integration effort.
Harmonizing data format is essential
for enabling seamless data exchange with
studies showing the standard standardized
data format can reduce analysis time by 65
percent and improve diagnostic accuracy.
40%. So here we see a data diagram of
expected improvement with personalized
medicine in terms of reduced adverse
reactions and also improved treatment.
And what are the actionable
insights for precision healthcare?
We talk about build robust infrastructure,
leverage advanced techniques.
address key challenges.
These are the three actionable
insights for the precision health care.
So when we talk about the built robust
infrastructure, deeper and scalable
data architecture that ensure HIPAA
compliance, data and storage system
and automated backup protocols to
handle increased volume of patient
data, leverage advanced techniques.
So implement the real time ETL
pipelines and AI powered analytics.
to process patient data streams, enabling
rapid insight generation and predict
modeling for improved clinical outcomes.
Address key challenges.
Proactively tackle security
vulnerabilities through end to
end encryption while establishing
standardized data protocols to
enhance system interoperability
across healthcare networks.
Thank you very much for your time.