Hello, everyone.
My name is Prashant.
And I've been working for more than
a decade as a logic design engineer.
It's an honor to be here today
to talk about a topic that is
becoming increasingly important
in our connected world.
The intersection of hardware
security and artificial intelligence.
I would like to guide you through
some of the core ideas behind dual
state hardware security models.
Why they are critical in the rapidly
evolving AI era and how these
models can help protect sensitive
data and critical systems from
the multitude of emerging threats.
We are at a crossroads where AI's
power to transform industries and
everyday life intersects with the some.
Sometimes overlooked vulnerabilities
and hardware can introduce.
Let's dive in.
The first point I would like to
emphasize is that AI isn't just
another software application.
AI is fundamentally different
from traditional systems because
it involves high speed data
processing, specialized hardware
accelerators, and complex algorithms.
These advanced components open up
new possibilities for innovation.
But they also increase the attack
surface for malicious actors.
When we scale up our capacity to
process data, we are also scaling up
potential entry points for attacks.
Hardware level exploits are no
longer the realm of science fiction.
They are real, tangible threats
that can undermine even the
most sophisticated AI solutions.
We often focus on the software
vulnerabilities in AI pipelines,
misconfigurations of libraries,
inadequate encryption, or insecure APIs.
But hardware vulnerabilities can be much
more, much harder to detect and remedy.
Once compromised, a piece of hardware can
be extremely difficult to fully repair
because it forms the foundation on which
all software security measures rest.
If your hardware is compromised,
every layer above it, your operating
system, your applications, and even
your AI models could be at risk.
In other words, hardware is the bedrock.
That's why strong hardware security
protocols are absolutely non negotiable
in this new era of AI driven innovation.
To illustrate, Consider high profile
vulnerabilities like Spectre and Meltdown.
These exploits took advantage
of speculative execution
features in modern processors.
Something previously thought
to be a purely performance
focused aspect of CPU design.
They showed that even innovations meant to
speed up computation can become an avenue
for data leaks if not carefully secured.
As AI continue to demand greater
performance from processors and
GPUs, we must stay vigilant about how
performance enhancing features might
inadvertently introduce security gaps.
Address space
partitioning, a foundation of trust.
One of the most fundamental aspects
of secure hardware platform is robust
hard address space partitioning.
When we talk about address space
partitioning, we are referring to
the division of memory into distinct
regions, secure versus non secure.
This concept ensures that cryptographic
operations, sensitive key storage,
and mission critical codes execute
exclusively in protected memory zones.
While user level applications and
other non critical processes run in
separate, lower privileged areas.
Why does that matter?
Okay, imagine you have
two rooms in a building.
One is a vault and the other
is a regular office space.
You want to ensure that only authorized
personnel can enter the vault.
If you design the building so
that the vault can be reached.
only through multiple locked doors,
each requiring a unique key or code.
You are effectively creating
a layered security model.
In hardware design, specialized components
like memory management units or security
controllers serve as these locked doors.
They ensure strict separation
between what's trusted and what's
not, blocking unauthorized access
attempts as the silicon level.
Not only does this approach prevent
direct data theft, it also mitigates
the spread of malicious code or
ransomware by containing threats.
If malicious software compromises one area
of the system, address based partitioning
can stop that threat from splitting
into the rest of the environment.
In the context of AI, where large
datasets and complex models are often
in use, this segregation is crucial for
safeguarding both the data itself and the
proprietary algorithm that organizations
rely on their competitive edge.
Secure boot, establishing a trusted,
Next, let's talk about secure boot.
Secure boot ensures that every component
in the boot chain from the moment
you power on your device to the point
at which the operating system loads
has been cryptographically verified.
This process typically involves
digital signature cryptographic
hashing and Authenticated code checks.
Why is this so essential?
Because once the system boots, software
based security measures take over.
If the foundation is already
compromised, the entire security
structure is built on shaky ground.
In practice, secure boot
might work like this.
Upon.
power up.
A small piece of firmware anchored into
hardware checks the digital signature
of the next stage of the bootloader.
Only if that signature is valid
does it allow the bootloader to run.
The bootloader in turn verifies the
OS kernel or other critical system
components using the same principle.
It's a cascading chain of trust.
If one link is broken, everything
that follows is flagged or
prevented from executing.
This mechanism is incredibly effective
at blocking rootkits and other low
level attacks that Attempt to hide
from security tools by loading
before the OS is fully operational.
In AI systems, ensuring that every
layer is authenticated before it runs
is doubly important because tampering
at the boot stage might enable an
attacker to manipulate AI processes.
undetected or even compromise
the data your AI models rely on.
Even with a secure boot
process, the job isn't done.
Systems need continuous
runtime integrity checks.
Throughout a device's operation, advanced
algorithms monitor from, for anomalies
in memory access, execution flaws.
and stack behaviors.
If something deviates from the
established baseline, the system can
take immediate action, whether that's
alerting an administrator, blocking
certain processes, or even shutting
down to prevent a larger breach.
One of the execute exciting
development here is the use of
machine learning in anomaly detection.
Instead of relying on static rule
sets that might not catch new type of
attacks, AI based monitoring solutions
can learn from historical data about
what constitutes normal system behavior.
Then they quickly flag events
that deviate from that baseline.
Picture a constant real time
audit of everything happening
at the hardware level.
When an irregularity shows up, like
a process attempting to read or
write to a secure region of memory.
that triggers a deeper analysis
or a direct counter measure.
This continuous vigilance approach
is particularly important for
AI workloads that run 24 7,
handle large quantities of data.
and require stable system performance.
Building on the concept of address
space partitioning, address
level boundary markers provide an
extra layer of separation between
secure and non secure processes.
You might have heard of ARM
Trust Zone or Intel's SGX.
These are specialized technologies
that create physically or logically
isolated enclaves on the chip.
itself by running critical
security operations in a
separate hardware isolated zone.
The system maintains a high
level protection even if the main
operating environment is compromised.
These boundary markers enforce what's
known as the principle of least privilege.
Only the processes that genuinely need
access to critical data or operations
can gain entry and even then only
through rigorously controlled interface.
If attackers try to escalate privileges
or perform side channel attacks,
these enclaves and security monitors
serve as an additional barrier.
Raising the cost and complexity
for any malicious actor with AI.
These enclaves can securely store and
process private data, such as encryption
keys or unique model parameters,
ensuring that sensitive assets remain
protected at the hardware level.
We have already touched briefly on how
machine learning can bolster security,
but let's explore that a bit more deeply.
AI driven anomaly detection has become
a powerful tool in security operations.
It's particularly relevant in
hardware security for a few reasons.
First, hardware level events can
generate a tremendous amount of
telemetry, performance counters.
memory accesses logs, cache
uses patterns, and more.
These data points can be analyzed
by machine learning models to spot
subtle patterns that might elude
traditional signature based approaches.
Second, because AI systems often have
predictable workflows like training,
inference, or data Pre processing.
An AI driven security module can
develop a clear sense of normal
behavior for each workload type.
The moment something useful, unusual
happens, such as privilege change,
privilege level change, without
authorization or an abnormal frequency
of memory reads in a secure region,
the anomaly detection system can
flag it for further investigation.
This level of precision can stop
attacks before they escalate.
Finally, AI's ability to evolve alongside
new and emerging threats makes it ideal
for hardware security environments.
Attackers continually adapt their tactics.
Static rules can become obsolete.
With an AI based monitoring solution
that learns from new data in real time.
System can adapt at the same pace.
This arms race of AI versus AI might
be inevitable, but a sophisticated
hardware level defense provides
defenders a robust starting advantage
in addition to real time monitoring.
Periodic validation routines are crucial.
Self tests at regular intervals verify
that memory boundaries remain intact.
Cryptographic keys haven't been
tampered with, and no unauthorized
or corrupted code is running.
These validations act like a system
wide refresh, reaffirming the
hardware's trustworthiness even
if the system has been operating
continuously for days or weeks.
For AI driven systems that might be
training on new data sets performing
batch inferences, these checks
ensure that the environment hasn't
been quietly subverted over time.
By regularly recalculating cryptographic
hashes or verifying digital signatures,
we reinforce the chain of trust
initially established by Secure Boot.
This layered approach Secure
At startup, continuous runtime
checks and periodic validations
goes a long way toward creating a
resilient hardware security posture.
If we step back and look at these
individual components, address
space partitioning, and secure boot
runtime checks, boundary markers,
anomaly detection, And periodic
validations, they come together to
form what we call a dual state models.
Essentially, there are two separate
states in which processes can
operate secure and non secure.
This dual state design
is particularly valuable.
in the AI era for three main reasons.
Intellectual property protection.
AI models and algorithms can
be extremely valuable assets.
A dual state model isolates
the proprietary model or
data in a secure zone.
Making it much harder for attackers
to steal or reverse engineer.
Data security.
By encrypting or segregating sensitive
data in the secure zone, organizations
can better comply with regulations like
GDPR, HIPAA, or others, and maintain user
trust by preventing unauthorized accesses.
Resilient operations.
Even if the part of the non secure
state becomes compromised, the secure
state can detect and contain the threat
that reduces downtime and isolates the
impact of any breach, allowing critical
AI operations to continue safely.
From protecting intellectual property,
To safeguarding personal health
data, a dual state architecture
makes it exponentially more difficult
for attackers to gain a foothold.
While it's not a catch all
solution, it raises the cost and
complexity of attacks significantly.
Let's not forget another critical
factor, supply chain security.
As AI hardware becomes more specialized,
organizations often source components
from multiple suppliers around the globe.
Each link in the supply chain
can introduce vulnerabilities.
From counterfeit chips to tempered
firmware and a compromise at the supply
chain level can defeat even the strongest
security measures at run time to tackle
this issue, more organizations are
pushing for greater transparency in the
manufacturing process techniques like
secure device identifiers temper evident
packaging and formal attestation processes
can help verify that hardware hasn't
been altered before it arrives in your
data center or on your production floor.
In the context of dual state security,
if we can't trust the underlying
hardware from the very beginning,
We compromise the entire stack.
Therefore, supply chain security
is increasingly considered an
essential step in creating a
truly trustworthy AI environment.
We have covered a lot of,
okay, we have covered a lot of ground and
I would like to close by taking a look.
Okay.
Yeah.
By taking a look at the horizon,
AI systems are only becoming
more sophisticated and deeply
embedded in our daily lives.
As their importance grows, so does
the creativity and determination of
adversaries looking to exploit them.
Some areas that demand our
ongoing attention include quantum
resilient, resistant encryption.
As quantum computing becomes
more practical, it threatens
traditional cryptographic techniques.
We need to adopt encryption schemes that
can withstand these quantum attacks,
particularly for hardware components
intended for use over a decade or more.
Neuromorphic computing defenses.
Neuromorphic chips mimic the neural
structures of the human brain and can
significantly boost AI performance.
Yet, they also introduce
new attack vectors.
We need specialized security strategies
tailored to these emerging architectures.
Cross industry collaboration.
Collaboration among hardware vendors,
academic researchers, and industry
consortia can drive the creation of
common standards, best practices,
and open hardware from firmwares.
Sharing threat intelligence
across organizations helps us stay
one step ahead of adversaries.
We should also consider the growing
trend of edge AI, where small
devices, IoT sensors, smartphones,
and other edge computing devices
handle critical workloads locally.
These devices can be even more vulnerable
due to power and resource constraints.
As AI increasingly move to the edge,
ensuring robust hardware security in those
compact environment will be paramount.
Okay, in summary, a layered
security approach that starts at the
hardware is absolutely essential.
If we want to build AI solutions that
are both innovative and trustworthy, dual
state architecture secure both processes.
Continuous monitoring and AI enhanced.
Anomaly detection all play a
critical role in the puzzle.
By implementing these measures, along with
rigorous supply chain checks and ongoing
validation, we can protect intellectual
property, guard sensitive data, and
ensure the resilience of systems that
increasingly control everything from
healthcare diagnostics to autonomous
vehicles and financial trading algorithms.
As we move forward, it will
be a collective effort.
Security is never the responsibility
of just one department or one industry.
It's a shared obligation of hardware
engineers, AI researchers, data
scientists, and policymakers.
Our objective should be to make
security a fundamental design
requirement, not an afterthought.
Only then we Can we confidently
harness the AI's enormous potential
without putting at risk the very
data and processes we aim to improve?
Thank you so much for your attention.
I hope this talk has shed some light on
the importance of hardware security in
the AI era and how dual state models can
help us address the challenges ahead.
I'd be, I would be more than
happy to take any questions.
Thank you.