Hello everyone.
I welcome you all to this
presentation on stable Coins as
Cloud Native payment infrastructure.
Let me ask you a question right
now, today, how long does it take
to send money from a company in
London to a supply in Jakarta?
Now, if you go through the
traditional correspondent banking
system, swift intermediary Banks
currency conversion, the an, the
answer is two to five business days.
Am I right or not?
Now, and it costs somewhere between
20 and $40 in fees every single time.
Now, consider this, I can send
A-U-S-D-C stablecoin transaction
on polygon in under five seconds
for less than a 10th of a cent.
Now that's not a demo,
that's not a white paper.
That is production infrastructure
handling real money at scale right now.
In 2025, stable coins processed
around $28 trillion in real
economic transaction volume.
Now that's more than 20 times PayPal and
approaching three times that of Visa.
Today I'm gonna show you why stable
coins are not just crypto hype.
They are the first cloud native payment
infrastructure, and I'm gonna show you
what cloud architects need to actually
build for the next settlement layer.
Let's start with first principles.
What does it actually mean for payment
infrastructure to be cloud native?
Now, traditional payment rails like
Swift, a CH, and card networks were
built in the 1970s and around eighties.
Now, these were designed for batch
processing, not event streaming.
Now they have business hours,
they have settlement windows,
they have cutoff times.
You cannot spin up a new currency pair
the way you spin up a Kubernetes pod.
A stable coin is simply
a digital token pegged.
One is to one pro fiat currency,
usually the US dollar, but running
on a programmable blockchain.
It has four properties that
make it genuinely cloud native.
Number one programmability.
Now settlement logic
lives in smart contracts.
You don't call a bank,
you call code number two.
It's twenty four seven
and 365 days available.
There are no weekends
on Ethereum or polycon.
The rails never sleep.
Number three, global reach from day one.
Now, any wallet address anywhere in
the world is a valid destination.
No correspondent bank required.
And lastly, composability.
You can build financial products on
top of stable coins the same way you
build microservices on top of APIs.
The two dominant stable coins
today are USDT, which is
Tether and USDC from Circle.
Together they represent over
about 260 billion in market
cap, triple the value from 2023.
The market cap just crossed about
300 billion in total, which places
stable coins alongside systematically
relevant financial markets.
And with the US' Genius Act now in
full enforcement, signed into law
in mid 2025 and entering a critical
compliance phase this month we
finally have a federal framework
that defies stable coins as payment
instruments and not just securities.
Now this changes everything
for institutional players.
Now let's get into the
infrastructure realities.
I want to walk through Polygon because
it's the best case study we have for
taking a blockchain from a scrappy scaling
solution to an enterprise payment rails.
Now, what's the technical evolution?
Polygon started in 2017 is Matt
Network, basically a side chain Ethereum
that lets you do cheap transactions.
Now by mid 2025, it had processed
over 4.2 billion total transactions.
In February of this year, it
hit an all time high of 204
million monthly transactions.
Now here's the key upgrade story
because this maps directly to
cloud infrastructure thinking.
Between September, 2024 and
March, 2026, Polycon executed
six major technical upgrades.
Three are worth calling out,
specifically the Heim Doll V two upgrade.
Now this overhauled the consensus layer
migrating from legacy tender to com BFT.
Now for cloud architects, think
of this as a database engine sw.
It reduced transaction finality from
minutes to approximately five seconds.
Now that's, the difference between a
rest API with the three second timeout
and one that hangs indefinitely.
The next one was the view upgrade.
Now this introduced a new block
production model, stateless validation.
No reorgs near instant finality maximum.
Thera put, jumped to 5,000
transactions per second.
No reorgs is critical in
payment infrastructure.
Mind you, reorg is like a distributed
system rollback that you did not ask for.
Last one was the giga gas roadmap.
Now, in February of this year,
polygon raised its gas limit
from 65 million to 110 million,
pushing capacity to 2,600 TPS.
Currently with a roadmap to a hundred
thousand TPS visa level thorough putt.
Now for context, visa handles about 1700
transactions per second on an average.
The other architectural piece
worth understanding is the ag
layer, which is the polygons cross
chain interoperability protocol.
Now this is their answer
to the multi-cloud problem.
Just as enterprises run workloads,
across AWS and GCP without users
really caring which cloud they're on.
The ag layer lets transactions flow
across multiple blockchains seamlessly.
Liquidity doesn't just fragment.
Users don't have to think about
which chain they're on now.
Polygon payment processor volumes
grew around 409% in 2025 from.
About $389 million monthly to
around 2 billion by January, 2026.
Now, their partners now include
Stripe Relu, which is Europe's largest
FinTech processing up to 1.2 billion
on Polygon flatter wave, and shift
four, which processes $200 billion
annually in traditional payments.
They also made two strategic
acquisitions coin me and Sequence
for $250 million explicitly to build
what they call the open money stack,
a full stack payment platform with on
and off ramps compliance and custody.
In January of this year, they announced
the vision of bringing all money on chain.
Now, in September, 2021, El Salvador
became the first country in the world
to adopt Bitcoin as legal tender.
Now, president Bule launched
a government sponsored digital
wallet called Shiva Wallet.
Now, that was Salvadorian slang for cool.
The government built an entire national
payment system in roughly three months,
suite with a $30 Bitcoin giveaway
to every citizen who signed up.
Now, what happened next is a
masterclass in what not to do with
payment infrastructure and it maps
perfectly onto cloud native lessons.
Now on day one, the app crashed and the
lower identity verification was broken.
Transactions fail on
the Lightning network.
Within the first 50 days, the
system had experienced multiple
outages and more than 2000 cases
of stolen identity were reported.
Now, Shio had access to the national
ID database, but had no data
protection legislation to go with it.
Now, a study by the National Bureau
of Economic Research found that whilst
54% of Salvadorians downloaded the
wallet, only 20% continued using it.
Later data showed that eight
out of 10 Salvadorians.
Weren't using Bitcoin at all, and
just about a percent of the total
remittances involved crypto assets.
The government eventually bought an
alpha point to stabilize the backend.
By early 2025, the plan was to
either privatize or shut down.
SHI won entirely.
Now, what are the cloud architecture
lessons to be learned here?
At the onset, what went wrong?
Technically, let me translate
this into cloud native terms.
No load testing has scale.
A national payment system serving
millions of citizens simultaneously
with a financial incentive to sign up.
That's a traffic spike that
would stress any infrastructure.
There was no chaos engineering,
no graduated rollout.
Single point of failure on identity.
Now the system relied on the national DUI
database with no redundancy or fallback.
When that integration failed,
the entire onboarding flow died.
Lesson number three, there was no
observability of the lightning network.
Shiva used Bitcoin Lightning
for fast payments spread.
No real time visibility into cloud, into
channel liquidity or routing failures.
Users just got cryptic errors.
Number four.
Volatility exposure without hedging.
The Genius Act equivalent
did not exist then.
And Shiva users were holding Bitcoin,
watched the $30 drop to $25 while
they were still trying to log in.
And the last lesson here, there was,
there's just no offline fallback.
A significant portion of Salvador
left reliable internet access.
The system had no graceful degradation
for low connectivity environments.
You know the lesson is not that
blockchain payments don't work.
The lesson is that payment infrastructure
at national scale requires production
grade engineering from day one.
You cannot ship an MVP for
a country's payment system.
What should have they built instead?
Stable coins, not volatile Bitcoin p
the dollar with proper reserve backing.
Automated compliance,
real time monitoring.
Graduated rollout.
The infrastructure that's only now
becoming available through Polygon
Circle and Chain Link ecosystem.
Now, let me get practical.
What does a production grade stablecoin
infrastructure stack actually look
like for a cloud of architect?
The layer one is the
on chain observability.
Think of this as your
CloudWatch for blockchain.
The challenge is that blockchains
generate an enormous amount of event data.
Every transaction, every smart contract
state change every fee spike, and you need
to make sense of it in real time, right?
The graph protocol is the
elastic search of on chain data.
You define subgraphs, essentially
query schemes that index
specific smart contract events.
Now, when you need to know
the current USDC supply on
polygon in real time, the graph.
Gives you a graph, ql, an API,
that answers in milliseconds.
Think of it as replacing the
Kafka consumer that you tried for
off chain event streaming, with
a decentralized indexing layer.
Now, chain link, proof of reserve sits
above this for fi back stable coins.
You need to cryptographically verify
that the off chain reserves, which is
the actual dollars in a bank account,
match the tokens in circulation.
Now Chainlink does this with a
decentralized Oracle network that
automatically reports verified collateral
data on chain in near real time.
Now this replaced manual monthly
attestations when uscs reserves
are being verified continuously.
That is the equivalent of a
continuous integration pipeline
for your balance sheet.
Now the second layer is
the compliance as a code.
The Genius Act requires monthly
reserve disclosures, KC K ycs A
ML Controls and Issuer Oversight.
The old way was a spreadsheet
and a compliance team manually
reviewing transactions.
The new way now is Chain Links automated
compliance engine, which embeds compliance
logic directly into smart contracts.
Now KYC rules, jurisdictional
restrictions, counterparty
eligibility, all of these become
code and not just a process.
The analogy for cloud architects
is terraform for compliance.
Instead of manually configuring
fire firewall rules, you declare
compliance postures code.
Now Chainlink, CCIP, the cross
chain interoperability protocol then
enforces the these rules across chains,
including configurable rate limits.
And risk management monitoring
for cross chain transaction flows.
The layer three would be
the custody and settlement.
Now custody is where blockchain
meets traditional finance and where
most enterprise implementations
get complicated, you have,
you've got two models here.
One is the multi signature custody.
Now transactions require multiple
cryptographic signatures before executing.
Think of it as a two
person integ integrity.
And forced in code
rather than just policy.
Now, providers like fire blocks and
bitco build entire platforms around
this model with MPC, key management,
multiparty computation, so no single
server ever holds a complete private key.
The second is the institutional
custodians with federal C charters.
Now digital has held an OCC Federal
Bank Charter since 2021 with the OCC
lifting a consent order in August, 2025.
BID O received OCC
approval in December, 2025.
The repeal of SAP 1 21 removed
capital requirements that had
made crypto custody prohibitively
expensive for traditional banks.
Now this opened the door for Citi, BNY
Mellon and Goldman Sachs, all of whom
are now building for operating custody
infrastructure for digital assets.
Now the layer four is the API and
the event streaming architecture.
Now for cloud architects, the
hybrid integration pattern
looks something like this.
Your existing systems, the ERP,
the Treasury management banking
co connect to a payment hub.
That hub.
Routes transactions through either
traditional banking rails or stablecoin
rails based on rules like cost speed,
destination, country counterparty.
Settlement finality events are streamed
via Kafka compatible consumers from
blockchain nodes, or indexed through the
graph and consumed through QL circles.
Cross chain transfer protocol
gives you native zero slippage,
transfers of USDC across 20 plus
blockchains through a single API.
Now Stripe launched stablecoin funded
subscriptions on Polygon October, 2025.
It's production, not just Peter.
Now I wanna talk about why banks are
scared and what that means for you.
Let me talk about threat vector.
The traditional finances losing
sleep sleepover because it has
direct architectural implications.
Federal Reserve modeling shows that
even moderate stablecoin adoption
could reduce bank lending by $190
to $408 billion as deposits migrate.
The Genius X Enforcement phase, which
enter critical implementation this
month is already being called the Great
Deposit migration by financial analysts.
Some forecast put potential
capital shift at $6 trillion.
The mechanism is simple.
Stable coins offer near instant
settlement 24 7 availability
and dramatically lower fees.
Transaction accounts like current
accounts, operating accounts are mostly
vulnerable because stable coins, primary
utility is as payment instruments.
Mills younger crypto native users
don't see a reason to hold money
in a bank when a digital wallet on
their phone does the same job better.
So how are banks responding?
Three strategies are emerging.
Number one, become a custodian.
BNY Mellon, Goldman Sachs, Citi Group
are all becoming custody infrastructure.
The Rationale Genius Act issuers need
to hold reserves somewhere regulated.
Banks want to be that somewhere.
Number two, issue your own stable coin.
Now, JP Morgan rebranded is.
Onyx division to Conexus, and it's now
deploying a JPM coin on public blockchains
like base Wyoming became the first
US state to issue a blockchain based
stable token In August, 2025, so far
became the first national bank to issue
a stable coin and a public blockchain.
Integrate, do not replace
Volante Technologies and others.
Offer payment hub platforms where banks
can route transactions dynamically.
Legacy rails or blockchain rails
from a single API source Low core
integration, not a blockchain first.
Re right now for cloud architects,
this means your clients, whether
they're banks, fintechs, or an or
enterprise treasuries, will increasingly
need hybrid payment infrastructure.
You need to know how to
build it in section six.
Now I wanna talk about some concrete
patterns for cloud architects.
Let me close with the actionable patterns.
These are the things you should
be able to walk away and apply.
Pattern number one, multi-region
validator orchestration.
Running your own validator notes.
This is Cuban's blockchain Consensus.
You want multi-region deployments,
AWS and US East one GCP in Europe
West with health checks, automatic
failover and stateless validation,
so notes can be replaced without
disrupting consensus Participation.
Polygons view operate made
this significantly easier
with stateless validation.
Pattern number two is reserve monitoring
pipeline CloudWatch for on chain reserves.
Combine chain link proof of reserve data
feeds the graph subgraphs for real time
supply indexing and your existing alert
infrastructure set alerts on reserve ratio
deviations if the verified re reserve
drops below 99.5% of circulating supply.
That's a PagerDuty event That
is standard SRE practice applied
to financial infrastructure.
Now, pattern number three is
compliance as scored with CCIP.
Use chain link CCIP to enforce
compliance rules at the protocol layer.
Define your K-Y-C-A-M-L practices as
smart logic contract, jurisdictional
block lists, transaction size
limits, counterparty, white lists.
Commit them to version control.
Run them through your ci cd pipeline.
Test them against a hard hat test
nut before mainly deployment.
This is Terraform for Compliance
Infrastructure as code, not process.
Now, pattern four is event
streaming for settlement finality.
Don't pull the blockchain.
Subscribe to events.
Use a Kafka compatible event bridge.
Several providers offer this or
build a lightweight consumer.
That subscribes to Ethereum Polygon
node web socket, APIs for transaction
confirmation events when a settlement
transaction reaches finality emit an
event to your downstream order management
system, treasury, leisure, or ERP.
The latency difference between
polling and event driven is where
your competitive advantage lives.
The last pattern is the
hybrid custody model.
For most enterprises, you don't
need to build custody from scratch.
Use an institutional custodian
like fire blocks Anchorage
for production key management.
Expose it through your existing treasury.
API Surface route.
Low value, high frequency transactions
through hot wallets with MPC, key
management route, high value, low
frequency transactions through cold
storage with multisig approval workflows.
This mirrors the tiered storage
patterns you already know.
Let me bring this back to
where we first started.
Traditional payment trails took
decades to achieve global scale.
SWIFT was founded in 1973, A
CH launched in the US in 1974.
There's still the plumbing.
Most of the world's money
flows through stable coins.
Built product, production grade,
globally accessible payment
infrastructure in just five years.
Chain analysis projects that by 2035
annual stablecoin transaction volume
could reach 1.5 per trillion, and
that surpasses the entire currency
cross border payments market.
Whether or not you believe that
forecast the direction is clear.
The questions for cloud architects are
no longer should we explore blockchain.
They are actually the following.
How do we observe on chain
financial infrastructure, the way
we observe cloud infrastructure?
How do we write compliance policy
as core rather, and process?
How do we build hybrid custody
models that meet institutional risk
protocol requirements, and how do
we connect the settlement finality
events to existing data pipelines?
Shi O showed us what happens to you
when it get, when you get it wrong.
Polygon showed us what's
possible when you get it right.
The infrastructure is here, the
regulatory framework is here, the
institutional capital is here.
The only question is whether
cloud architects are going to
build the next settlement layer
or watch someone else do it.
Thank you so very much for listening in.
I'm happy to take questions and I'll have
on chain dashboards, reserve monitoring
ts, and infrastructure diagrams available
if you wanna dig into the specifics.
Thank you very much.