Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 Cloud
Native session 2026.
I'm Raja Singh, Ramdas,
senior Technical Architect.
At IBMI turn high level digital
strategy into operational reality.
I specialize in transforming fragmented
legacy silos into unified, secure, and
modular platforms, having led large
scale shifts across diverse industries.
I designed flexible architectures.
That solve today's problems and
scale for tomorrow's growth.
Today we are going to talk about
a future threat due to quantum
cryptography and how to secure
multi-cloud APIs against quantum threats.
As con quantum comput computing
matures traditional encryption
phases, unprecedented risks.
To ensure the integrity of multi-cloud
environments, organizations
must proactively shift towards
quantum resistant architectures.
Traditional encryption that we have
relied on for decades is facing a terminal
threat as quantum computing matures.
Today, we'll outline how organizations
must prioritize the transition to
quantum resistant protocols to protect
their most sensitive multi-cloud data.
The threat is not merely theoretical.
We are currently facing the harvest
now decrypt later phenomenon where
attackers capture encrypted traffic today.
To decrypt it.
Once cryptographically relevant quantum
computers become available, this
necessitates an immediate shift in our
long-term data protection strategy.
If your data has a long confidentiality
horizon, like trade secrets,
health records, or strategic
plans, that data is already at risk
of being exposed in the future.
Our current public key infrastructure,
specifically RSA and Elliptic
Curve cryptography rests on
mathematical complexities that
are vulnerable to short cellar.
In a post quantum era, these traditional
encryption standards will no longer
provide sufficient security margins.
A EST 2 56 symmetric encryption
and hash functions can survive
from quantum computing.
If larger key sizes are used, so
what quantum computers actually
break, we naturally focus on north
South traffic gateways, but the
quantum resistant perimeter is
just a false sense of security.
If the interior is weak, E space traffic
is just as vulnerable to harvest now.
Decrypt later.
If a hack is already inside
your network, they're quietly
collecting your internal secrets.
Our hybrid connectivity cloud two
on-prem often relies on legacy VPNs.
These bridges are frequently the
most neglected and therefore the most
exposed parts of the infrastructure.
Finally, we have to look at
the certificate infrastructure.
If our internal CAS and MTLS are
in migrated to quantum resistance
standards, the antitrust model
collapses from bottom up as architects.
We have to remember that a quantum
proof front door is useless.
If the hallways inside are wide open.
We must secure the entire journey
and not just the entry point.
There is no single migration
path for cloud platforms, mobile
applications, third party communication
layers and legacy systems.
They all use different
TLS implementations.
Unique considerations are required
to prevent them from quantum theft.
To start with, we need to
perform a risk assessment.
There are multiple phases on
risk assessment framework.
We start with a discovery phase
followed by prioritizing and
creating migration backlog.
We don't migrate everything at once.
We find the hidden risk, prioritize
the data with the longest shelf
life and build a roadmap that.
Treats cryptography as a core
part of our technical depth.
Let's review the risk priority
with a three dimensional view.
The first dimension is the data.
Confidentiality.
Lifetime data that must stay secret
for decades is our top priority.
The second dimension is API criticality.
We look at the revenue impact regulatory
scope, and data sensitivity of each API.
The final dimension is
migration feasibility.
We separate near term actionable
items from long horizontal projects
that require vendor coordination
or full architectural redesign.
We are guided by NIST post Quantum
Cryptography Standardization Project.
N stands for National Institute
of Standards and Technology.
After years of work, the new rules for
cryptography has finally set in stone.
Now that there are stable official
guides to follow, companies can start
using these tools without worrying about
future changes or technical confusion.
We have moved past the era of uncertainty.
With a clear path forward.
The mandate for Enterprise
LE leaders is simple.
Prioritize your transition.
Now.
Postponing post quantum readiness
is no longer an option in a
standardized cryptographic landscape.
Here's the new standards on the nist
post Quantum cryptographic portfolio.
ML chem allies replaces
R-S-A-E-C-D-H for handshakes.
Its fast and uses Logic Keys.
ML DSA, allies de Lithium is
a new standard for digital
signatures, S-L-H-D-S-A Allies.
Pinks is a hash based backup that provides
a valuable diversity of assumptions.
F-N-D-S-A Allies, Falcon provides lattice
based signatures with compact size.
All these have which stood extensive
public crypto analysis with a selection
of algorithms like BER and d Lithium,
we now have a vetted framework to begin
modernizing our cryptographic stack.
We recommend a hybrid approach
running classical and quantum
algorithms In parallel, an attacker
must break both to succeed.
There's an unexpected flaw in
the post quantum cryptography.
The classical encryption
still provides the backstop if
classical is broken by quantum.
Post quantum cryptography
provides protection.
Session keys are now derived from a dual
combination of ECDH and ML chem protocols,
which gives multi-level protection.
This slide covers the high level
maturity model for cryptographic
agility, which is our force multiplier.
We need systems where we can
update algorithms via configuration
rather than rewriting the code.
By hiding libraries behind stable
interfaces, future migrations
will be dramatically easier.
This maturity model includes five levels,
level one hardcoded algorithms, level two.
Library abstraction layer level three.
Centralized certification management
level four, algorithm choices as
configuration and level five automated
agility with full observability.
Let's consider the performance cost.
Now post quantum cryptography is not free.
Larger keys means increased
handshake size and potential
delay on high latency networks.
We can offset this using session
resumption connection, pooling
and HTTP two or HTTP three
multiplexing to ensure accuracy.
It is essential to benchmark these systems
within live production environments.
Migration roadmaps are
divided into four phases.
Phase one.
Is the fundamental foundation
phase for inventory frameworks
and library selections.
Phase two is the high priority phase with
hybrid S for sensitive external gateways
and critical E-Space service mesh traffic.
Phase three is a rollout phase for low
priority APIs and partner integrations.
Phase four is the hard cases phase
for legacy architectural mitigations.
Long tail client compliance.
So how is the organizational
dynamics Looks like this is
a program and not a project.
Post quantum migration touches
networking, security, platform
engineering, development, partner
management, and procurement.
This is a multi-year program,
not a one-off project.
It touches everyone from platform
engineering to procurement.
This will require sustained
leadership support to maintain
momentum across years of migration.
Angu Bty regarding timelines
does not relieve us of the
responsibility to act today.
The time to begin is now harvest now
and decrypt later is happening today.
The standards are ready.
NIST FIPS 2 0 3, 2 0 5.
Releases are published and stable.
Library support is maturing rapidly.
Migration takes years.
Even if you start now, the transfer
will take years to complete.
Cleaning up your encryption fixes old
mistakes and makes you safer right away.
This quantum threat is real.
The tools are available to block
them, and the time to begin is now.
Let's take action before it is too late.
This brings us to the
end of today's session.
I hope these insights offer
a valuable perspective on the
evolution of Alti Cloud security.
I look forward to connecting
again in our next session.
Until then, thank you and goodbye.