Welcome everyone.
Thank you for joining today's
session on innovative approaches
to security, micro segmentations,
impact on cloud environments.
My name is Venkata Nethinuri and it's a
pleasure to be part of cloud native 2025.
Over the next 40 minutes, we will
explore how micro segmentation is
changing the game in cloud security.
By end of this talk, you will
understand why traditional security
models need to evolve and how micro
segmentation can significantly bluster
our defenses in cloud environments.
Without any delay, let's proceed further.
Before jumping into the actual topic
of micro segmentation, let's take
a step back and see cyber security
challenges in the cloud environments.
Modern cloud architectures are
highly dynamic, applications
and data spread across different
data centers and multiple clouds.
This brings increased complexity
and new vulnerabilities.
Traditional security relied on a
strong perimeter, like a firewall at
the network edge, but the cloud era,
the concept of a fixed is fading away.
Now, the reason because this is because
attackers are continuously finding
ways to pass the perimeter defenses.
And once they are inside too often,
they can laterally move to other
systems without being detected.
And that's a huge risk.
So we must evolve to, we must evolve
beyond just the perimeter defense.
while firewalls and border security
are still necessary, they don't, like
they are not sufficient to protect,
they're not sufficient on their own
to protect the cloud environments.
Think of this as securing a building.
It's not enough to guard the front door.
And if once inside every room or
vault is wide open, we need inter
barrier, internal barriers as walls.
This is where micro
segmentation comes into picture.
Microsegmentation is an innovative
approach that breaks the cloud network
into many small and isolated segments,
each with its own security controls.
So instead of assuming that everything
inside our network is secured and trusted,
microsegmentation enforces trust nothing
and verify everything strategy internally.
This aligns perfectly with
the zero trust security model.
Now, the objective of this session is
to understand what microsegmentation is
and how it differs from the traditional
network segmentation and discuss why
it is crucial for cloud security and
how it addresses the challenges like
insider threats and lateral movement.
We will also go over the components
or key components and best practices
for implementing microsegmentation,
in cloud environments, especially
with a few real world examples
as well, case studies as well.
And, last but not the least,
we look at the future trends,
including how automation and AI
can enhance micro segmentation.
So overall, by the end of this session,
both technical and non technical audiences
we have in the, in today's, discussion
should have a clear idea of what micro
segmentation impact on cloud environment,
cloud security, and, Get some practical
insights on using it effectively.
what actually is micro segmentation?
so micro segmentation, is a granular
security strategy that isolates
workloads and applications within
the network to minimize the risk
of lateral movement by attackers.
Now, unlike the traditional network
segmentation which divides the
network into large sections using
VLANs, firewalls, or subnets.
Microsegmentation operates at a
more refined level, securing the
individual workloads, containers, or
even, specific application processes.
This ensures that even if the
attacker gains access to a part
of the network, they cannot easily
move into other critical systems.
The key principle of the
microsegmentation is that to apply
identity based least privilege access
policies to control network traffic.
between the workloads.
instead of solely relying on the IP
addresses, instead of solely relying
on the IP addresses, micro segmentation
uses contextual information like,
application type, user identity,
workload tags, and security
posture, etc. to determine whether a
connection should be allowed or not.
This perfectly aligns with zero trust
security, zero trust security model.
which assumes that there no and
that no entity inside the network
should be trusted by default.
Now, how does micro segmentation work?
Now, how it works is basically micro
segmentation works by enforcing
strict access control between
different segments of the network.
Now, it can be implemented
through host based firewalls,
hypervisor based controls.
Cloud security groups, or software
defined network solutions.
These mechanisms basically allow
organizations to define and enforce
security policies dynamically,
ensuring the workloads can only
communicate with authorized services.
For example, let's say a segmentation
policy might permit a web server
to talk to application server, but
not directly a database server.
This reduces the risk of data breaches.
drastically, especially coming to
the cloud and hybrid environments.
Microsegmentation is particularly
useful as traditional network
perimeters no longer exist.
Yeah, they no longer exist because cloud
workloads are dynamic and static firewall
rules may not be effective in controlling
the traffic cloud native security
controls like AWS security groups.
Azure, network security groups, NSGs,
or Kubernetes network policies allow
organizations to implement software
defined micro segmentation, ensuring
basically this ensures that the
security policies follow workloads,
even if they move or scale up or down.
Now, next let's move and go ahead and
look at a sample implementation of
a micro segmentation architecture.
So if you see in this, if you see
in this diagram, this basically,
demonstrates a micro segmentation
architecture where network resources
are divided into isolated segments
micro segment 1 and micro segment 2.
The purpose is to limit unauthorized
communication and prevent lateral
movement of the thread, of the threads.
Each micro segment contains three
layers, web layer, application layer,
and database layer, representing
our traditional enterprise, typical
enterprise network structure.
This implementation of micro segmentation
ensures we can see that only authorized
communication happens between the
tiers, reducing the security risk.
Now, the logical routers and
perimeter firewalls provide
high level of network severity.
But the real strength of micro
segmentation, as you can see, comes
from the next generation firewalls
placed at each segment's boundary
enforcing strict security policies.
with this, basically that, traffic
between the micro segments is tightly
controlled, meaning that even if
the attacker compromises a workload
in one segment, they cannot freely
move to the other segment without
passing through the security controls.
as we discussed earlier as well, this
security model aligns with the zero
trust model, ensuring all traffic is
verified and the security policies
enforce least privilege access between
the different applications and components.
yeah, let's go ahead and see what are all
the key differences between traditional
security, versus micro segmentation.
Now, for decades, traditional network
security models have relied heavily
on perimeter based defense, perimeter
defense mechanisms, such as firewalls,
intrusion detection systems, and VPNs.
The goal of the perimeter security is to
block unauthorized access at the network
boundary itself, assuming that, everything
inside the network is inherently trusted.
While this approach worked well in
static and on premise environments,
today's modern cloud architecture
and sophisticated cyber threats
have rendered this as insufficient.
The biggest limitation of perimeter
security is that once the attacker gains
access past the firewall, they can often
move freely within the internet network.
This is because traditional networks
are flat, meaning, The systems inside
the perimeter have unrestricted
communication with each other.
let's say if an attacker exploits
a vulnerability in one system, they
can laterally traverse to other
critical systems escalating their
attack and accessing sensitive data.
This type of lateral, this type of
movement, we call it as lateral movement,
a key tactic used in, various, Attacks
basically such as advanced persistent
threats, APTs we call, and random attack,
ransomware attacks, and insider threats.
Now, we have seen, as we have seen
in the previous slide in the image,
let's say we have a cloud hosted
e commerce application with three
types, web tier, application tier, and
database tier, with micro segmentation.
If a attacker, if a hacker exploits a
vulnerability in the web server, they
might be able to move laterally into
the application and Database starts
gaining access to, sensitive customer
data without the micro segmentation.
However, with micro segmentation,
each tier is strictly isolated
with well defined access policies.
This compromised web server
cannot directly affect or connect
to the database, preventing
unauthorized access, even if the
attacker is inside the network.
This segmented approach provides
multiple security benefits.
A few of the key benefits are prevention
of lateral movement, minimized attack
surveys, damage containment, and
compliance, and it also helps with
compliance and governance like meeting,
meeting with regulatory compliance
PCI, DSA, CIPA and GDPR by basically
ensuring that the secure workloads,
sensitive workloads are isolated.
Now, in the cloud and hybrid, security,
as micro segmentation is adaptable
and to dynamic and software defined
environments where workloads are
more frequently move up and down.
it's a key advantage of
the micro segmentation.
that's all let's move on to the
next slide where we have key
benefits of micro segmentation.
I feel we have discussed the key
benefits in the previous slide, but
let's look at a, let's look at, let's
look at the key benefits briefly.
the first one is granular access control.
Okay.
Now we can tailor the security policies
at the workload level, ensuring that
only authorized users and systems
can access the specific resources.
With this, we are reducing the attack
surface by isolating the workloads.
micro segmentation minimizes the potential
targets for the attacker and, overall we
are preventing the lateral movement, okay?
So if a segment is compromised,
attackers cannot easily, move across
other segments within the network.
So these benefits, okay?
These benefits, make the cloud environment
more resilient, to the cloud threats.
Now, let's see what are the key
components of micro segmentation.
micro segmentation basically
relies on three key components.
One, policy enforcement.
Number two, visibility.
And number third one is the automation.
These components work collaboratively
and together to create a robust
security framework that isolates
workloads and monitors traffic and
also adapts to network changes.
Now.
Let's, take a step back and look,
these three components individually.
The first one, policy enforcement.
This uses identity based rules
rather than just IP address,
IP, based on IP addresses.
Instead of static firewall rules
that rely only on IP addresses, micro
segmentation basically implements the
segmentation policies that may block
legitimate traffic, segmentation policies
that are defined based on work at
workload attributes, such as application
identity, security tags, or user roles.
Now this ensures that the policies
remain effective even as the workloads
move or scale in the cloud environments.
The next thing, the key component
is the visibility because without
measuring the effectiveness or,
without measuring the internal traffic.
to understand the communication
back pattern and detect anomalies.
we, we need that metric in order for
us to implement, micro segmentation.
Without proper visibility,
segmentation policies may block
legitimate traffic as well.
and leave critical systems exposed.
Now, in order to, in order for us
to do this, we need to perform deep
packet inspection, flow monitoring,
and also adapt to AI driven analytics.
AI driven analytics, what else, I
can think of, yeah, basically these
all help us identify, the security
risk and, optimize the policies.
The third one is automation.
Now as the cloud environment itself
is dynamic, the policies must adapt
dynamically as the workload changes.
Now this is to prevent
misconfigurations and security gaps.
As we all know, cloud environments
are highly dynamic and workloads
frequently spin up and down.
Automated micro segmentation solutions
continuously access the network traffic.
Enforce real time security controls
and minimize manual intervention.
overall, these are the key
components of the micro segmentation.
In the next slide, we will see what
are all, the different steps that we
need to perform, to implement, micro
segmentation in cloud environments.
One thing I would like to mention
is start with a phased approach.
Okay, now we are not required
to segment everything at once
because it can lead to a disaster.
The first step would be to map application
dependencies and network flows.
And the second step is to define
security policies based on
the actual traffic patterns.
We may not be able to derive actual
traffic patterns, but, estimated
traffic patterns, to a good level
of, degree of accuracy should work.
and deploy segmentation in monitoring
mode first to detect any issues.
And once we deploy the segmentation in
monitoring mode and we let it run, soak
in there, gradually enforce the policies,
starting with non critical workloads.
Now, the best practice would be to
involve cross functional teams and
testing policies because, common
pitfalls that I have seen are like over
segmentation leads to broken applications.
And it's a best practice to avoid
static rules and use dynamic policies
that are just with the environment and
always review the, regularly review
the policies to ensure that, they
still align with the business needs.
Now let's take, let's go ahead
and, review a couple of, use
cases of this micro segmentation.
The first use case that I can
think of is, financial services.
One of the industries that have benefited
immensely with the microsegmentation
is the financial services.
This is because financial institutions
handle large, high amount of sensitive
data, which includes customer
information and transaction records.
A breach in a financial service
can lead to a significant
financial and reputational damage.
microsegmentation allows these
institutions to separate critical data
from less sensitive systems, protecting,
more sensitive data and, most valuable
information, I would say, and minimizing
the potential exposure of a data breach.
Similar to this, the next industry
that I can see more benefitted
is the healthcare industry.
Protection of patient data is the
paramount and health organizations
must comply with strict regulatory
frameworks such as CPI and all.
in order to, in order to ensure
by segmenting the cloud, by
segmenting the cloud networks,
This segmentation minimizes
the risk of breach affecting
sensitive health data for sure.
but that doesn't mean that it comes
without any challenges and considerations.
There are definitely few challenges
and considerations that we
need to take into account while
implementing microsegmentation.
because microsegmentation is dividing your
network into smaller segments, we need to
carefully plan the implementation strategy
to avoid any operational disruptions
and ensure that the segmentation
policies remain effective, over time.
Now, the first challenge
is the complexity.
Now, implementing micro segmentation
requires a deep understanding of
the network architecture on how
applications interact and all.
Organizations definitely must map
out the communication between the
workloads, identify dependencies
and define granular policies.
The reason for this is because
without proper planning, the risk
of blocking legitimate traffic
or creating security gaps that
attackers can exploit is very high.
the next is the performance overhead.
The reason why there will be definitely
performance overhead because adding
multiple layers of security can
sometimes impact workload performance,
especially in high traffic environments,
because firewalls, security agents
and access control mechanisms require
quite a bit of computational resources
to inspect and filter the traffic.
Now, in order to overcome this
organizations must carefully optimize.
Security policies and monitor
system performance to balance
security and efficiency.
without adding more latency issues.
And the last but not the least
is continuous monitoring.
Because the cloud, and we are talking
specifically about the cloud here.
So as the cloud environments
are highly dynamic.
With the workloads constantly
changing, scaling up and down.
Microsegmentation policies.
must be regularly updated to
accommodate these changes.
The risk is, if these policies become
outdated, they can either block the
essential traffic or leave security
gaps that again attackers can exploit.
continuous security audits and AI driven
policy automation can help policies
align with evolving infrastructure.
Apart from these, there are a few more
challenges such as operational overheads.
Because managing a huge number of
micro segments across the cloud, on
premise, or hybrid environments can
significantly add administrative burden.
Now, without automation, manually
defining and enforcing security rules
can become overwhelming as well.
the organizations have to, and must
leverage orchestration tools and
integrate segmentation with DevOps.
Workflows to reduce this complexity
and few other challenges can be user
resistance and change management because
developers and IT teams may initially
resist strict segmentation policies,
especially if it impacts the productivity
and slows down the application development
or creates, heat on the performance.
like there could definitely be resistance.
And misconfigurations
is one of the key risks.
because we need to make sure that, the
implemented automation policy validation
and regular segmentation audits need
to be performed effectively in order to
detect and avoid any misconfigurations.
these are the few challenges
and considerations.
Now.
What are the best practices of
implementing like the best practices we
have touched upon this in the previous
slides, but let's have a quick look the
best practices are like start with the
security audit by auditing the current
network to identify what vulnerabilities
and understand the communication pattern
between the workloads is the key thing.
The next thing is zero trust
use zero trust as foundation.
The micro segmentation strategy has to
be built on a zero trust model, where no
entity is trusted by default and access is
granted only when properly authenticated.
The third thing is automation.
Usage of automation tools to dynamically
adjust policies as cloud environments
grow or change, ensuring the security
scales with the business needs.
is a key best practice, I would say,
and in the market right now, there
are several, tools available for
implementing micro segmentation.
A few of them are like VMware, NSX,
Cisco, Tetheration are some of the
leading platforms that offer comprehensive
micro segmentation capabilities.
and as the topic is cloud native
for cloud native environments
like AWS security groups and Azure
network security groups allowed.
users to implement segmentation
directly in the cloud platforms.
and the last thing is the integration
of micro segmentation with SDN software
defined networking is another key trend,
allowing greater agility and scalability.
And basically choosing the right
tool, depends upon the size,
complexity, and specific needs
of the cloud infrastructure.
let's look at what are all the
future trends, future of cloud
security with micro, what are
the trends of, micro segmentation
in the future of cloud security.
Let's have a quick look.
basically automation and AI.
We are seeing a rise of AI powered tools,
that can automatically detect threats and
adjust security policies in real time.
so AI driven micro segmentation
solutions will enable.
effective, predictive threat detection,
allowing organizations to proactively
block any suspicious activity before
it escalates, and evolving threats.
Cyber threats are threat, evolving
threat landscape, cyber threats have
continued to grow in sophistication,
which means that micro segmentation
strategies or any security strategy for
the matter of fact, also must continuously
evolve to stay ahead of the attackers.
Because attackers are increasingly
leveraging AI and continuous automation
to conduct lateral movement and
various other kinds of attacks.
Because making real time security,
analytics and behavior based
segmentation has become essential.
Now, the future implementations
of micro segmentation will need to
incorporate continuous risk assessments.
Because that will ensure, policies
adapt dynamically based on new threat
intelligence and attack vectors.
And it's also coming up more in IOT and
edge compute, edge computing devices.
And, especially in the cloud native
and multi cloud adoption patterns.
this we are seeing a lot of trend.
The, so with this, let's, look at
the conclusion and key takeaways.
to conclude, microsegmentation offers a
significant leap towards, securing a cloud
environment by allowing organizations
to create granular and isolated
segments within the cloud environments.
This does by reducing the attack service
and preventing lateral movement and
providing granular control over access.
Microsegmentation offers much
stronger security posture.
with this, thanks for the opportunity.
And, this is my contact information.
Please feel free to, drop me an
email or connect with me on LinkedIn.
Happy to, answer any questions, as well.
Thank you.
Have a nice day.