Hello.
my name is Prashant.
I work as a principal member of
technical staff at Salesforce.
and I'm going to talk about how to
use Kubernetes for machine learning.
so let's get started with it.
so this is, this will be
the agenda of our session.
We'll be talking about, the introduction.
Then we'll be talking about why water is
Kubernetes and why we need Kubernetes.
We'll also touch upon the concepts
of the machine learning lifecycle
and the benefits of using
Kubernetes for machine learning.
And then we'll try to discuss some of the
core concepts of, Kubernetes, especially
from a machine learning point of view.
we'll also try to understand some of
the core platform tools that have been
developed on Kubernetes, which are
very specific to machine learning or
deep learning, where we'll be talking
about cube flow to be very specific.
Cube Flow is just not a framework.
It's a platform combining
multiple different tools together.
We'll just look at, a simple
training example that, we can
use, on Kubernetes with cube flow.
then we'll be talking about some of
the best practices and real world
use cases, and we'll be ending
the session with future trends.
it's going to be a little bigger session.
I'm going to concentrate on a
lot of theoretical concepts.
hopefully one day I'll get a chance
to, present my workshop with Con 42.
and having said that, let's move on.
as most of I think by now, with all the
chat Gpt, Claudes and other Lums out
there, there is an AI revolution going
on and with this create AI revolution.
there comes the need of great
infrastructure too, and the
optimal usage of infrastructure.
saving the costs at the same time,
saving the energy at the same time,
and doing things more ethically.
And, we will talk about, how we can
do this with Kubernetes, how we can do
all these things that I've been talking
about with Kubernetes and why Kubernetes
is a pivotal concept or a pivotal
framework, or a pivotal platform for
doing machine learning or deep learning.
just to revise a lot of bottlenecks
that happen with machine
learning and deep learning.
The traditional infrastructures
that a lot of these organizations
have are, face, a lot of issue when
they need to scale up or scale down.
especially in scenarios where there's
a huge traffic that is coming to them.
now how to handle this and
all is what we are gonna talk
about this se in this session.
let's move on to the next slide.
what does Kubernetes, I think most of
you who are listening to this session
might have already worked on Kubernetes,
or you might be new to Kubernetes.
But yeah, for someone who is really new
to Kubernetes, Kubernetes is an open
source container orchestration platform.
that's a bigger word, but if anyone of
you have already worked with Docker,
you already know about containers,
but Kubernetes allows you to take
the concept of the containers to next
level by automating a lot of things.
It introduced the concepts of,
it introduces the concepts of
deployments, rollbacks services.
Stateful sets, demon sets and other
thing, a lot of other things into it.
but what does Kubernetes
bring to the table?
By, by orchestrating this containers, the
first thing is it simplifies the process
of running your applications right?
You can simply run your application
by packaging it as a docker image
and writing a couple of VL files.
It is also very reliable in the sense
that when you deploy your application to
Kubernetes, it takes care of it, it does
the autoscaling, it does the horizontal
autoscaling, the vertical autoscaling.
it takes, it makes sure that, it tries
to keep your application as much as
possible and scale it appropriately.
It has, it does container rollbacks,
container restarts, container, crash.
Look bags when a crash look back
is happening when you're coming.
What I mean by crash look back is when
your container is failing for some reason,
it tries to bring back the containers.
So the key features of Kubernetes,
although I'm not trying to list
all of them here, given the space
constraints and everything else, is it.
It supports automated deployments.
You, there are several tools out there
like Helm, customize several other things
that allow you to package your, package
your deployment, and allow you to do
different kinds of automated deployments.
It allows service discovery
through its services.
It has a built in load
balancer that is service.
It comes in the form of a service, as
it spoke about, it has self-healing
and fall tolerance, so it does, it
make, makes sure that it maintains
a minimum number of replicas.
and it also brings up the new
number of containers required.
Minimum number of pods required.
POD is the basic unit
of operation Kubernetes.
and finally it takes care of
resource management and scaling.
I. Before we go and talk about why
machine learning has to be done on
Kubernetes, or what are the benefits of
doing machine learning or deep learning?
When I say deep learning,
everything from neural networks
to self attention to transformers.
why we should be doing that on Kubernetes?
We'll just try to quickly understand
at a very high level of how a machine
learning lifecycle looks like.
And machine learning lifecycle
starts with data, right?
You get the data from your
customers or from your, from
whatever data sources you have.
You try to clean that data or
prepare the data for training, right?
Preparing data is a multi-step process,
but, but at a very high level, preparing
data involves scaling your parameters,
bringing them all to the same scale.
converting the alpha numerics or
alphabets into numerics and so on, right?
So that's what the data
phase is all about.
And then you do the
training on the data, right?
So you choose the appropriate.
Training model to train your data.
And there are several hundred algorithms
which are available out there.
Platforms like hugging Face host
a ton of models that you can use.
then you perform the
model validation, right?
You check for the performance
accuracy, the confusion,
metrics, everything else, right?
You check for how well
your model is performing.
And finally you deploy a model
into production, for deployment,
also for model deployment also.
There are several tools that are available
for deploying your models into production.
and once you deploy your models
into production, you spend
time monitoring it, right?
You try to monitor your model, and
then you repeat the process back again.
You keep fine tuning your models
every day with newer data or
you have a chron schedule.
And according to chron schedule,
you keep refining your data.
Now let's talk about the problem, right?
So what is the current problem?
What is the problem?
If you don't use Kubernetes, or if you're
trying to do machine learning on your
own massive, massive machine learning
on your own first party clusters.
Now first thing is data volume, right?
as more and more data as you start saving
more and more data, obviously there's
a lot of strain on your infrastructure.
You have restore this data somewhere,
you transform this data somewhere.
Now you can always provision the
entire infrastructure at once.
Keep the infrastructure
empty and just do it.
based on, based on the kind of,
the volume of data you receive.
You can also end up having a very
small infrastructure and you end
up receiving large volumes of data.
All right.
And how does Kubernetes solve it?
Let's talk about it in the upcoming slides
and the computational intensity, right?
a lot of, deep learning models on
neural networks today required a GPO.
Having said that, would you really
buy all the GP ahead and keep it
on your first party data centers
or anywhere, or anywhere on the
cloud in the form of EC2 machines.
So that, that's a lot of, lots
of cost to your company, right?
So how do you handle this
computation industry?
There are lows and highs.
During the peak periods, you might
require a lot of GPU, a lot of CPU, but
during the non-peak period, you don't
require a lot of GPU, a lot of CPU.
You wanna save your cost.
There's also deployment complexity, right?
So when you deploy a machine
learning model, you need to
have an inference endpoint.
You need to have a proper influencing
backend where you deploy a model.
So again, the.
During peak periods, how do you handle it?
You have to, everything has
to be scaled very efficiently.
And finally, the co, the cost involved
in all these kinds of resource management
that we have been talking about, right?
so we have to efficiently allocate
resources to all these workloads.
Which is very important so that you
can maximize the performance and you
can reduce the cost at the same time.
Now, this is a general problem with
any scaling machine learning workloads.
It does.
I'm not saying that Bernet is going
to solve all these problems for you,
but Kubernetes allows you to make
right decisions and it provides you
several avenues by which you can
easily solve all these problems.
and then, yeah.
now a question about why I should use
Kubernetes for machine learning, Um.
the first thing is scalability, right?
As you saw, as you're speaking about, you
can dynamically scale up and scale down.
we'll have a couple of other slides which
talk about benefits, but at a, roughly, at
a very high level, scalability, resource
management, portability and automation
are the four biggest things, according
to me, which Kubernetes provides you.
Now let's dive deep into
each one of those, right?
So first is scalability, right?
as I said, during the peak
periods, you might want to scale,
you might want to auto scale.
autoscale vertically, you want
to, you might want to autoscale
horizontally or you might need
to introduce GPUs right now.
Kubernetes with Kubernetes, right?
You can have, for example, if you're using
E case cluster or something on, Google
Cloud or something on Zoom, You already
have this cluster at your disposal and you
already have this nodes at your disposal,
but depending upon your cost model, you
will be charged only if you use them.
So during your peak periods,
you can use the GPU.
Kubernetes makes it very easy through its
Yamal file and a couple of annotations it.
Easily allows you to target by
using tames and tolerations and
Kubernetes allows you to target
the right nodes that have the GPU.
It allows you to perform auto scaling.
It allows you to perform
horizontal scaling.
You can set several, you can
set several parameters, several
attributes based on which you want
to perform the horizontal scaling.
In fact, there are.
Third party CNCF.
platforms are tools like kda.
Kda is Kubernetes event driven
autoscaling, so it allows you to autoscale
based on, different kinds of factors.
Okay.
Now, from a resource management
perspective, how does Kubernetes help you?
If your organization of your company is
already using Kubernetes, you might have
a bunch of microservices running on your
Kubernetes already, then you are you.
You're an apt company for running machine
learning workloads on your Kubernetes.
Kubernetes has the concept of resource
quotas that allow you to rested the
amount of resources you can use.
When I say other source,
CPUs, you can use.
Per namespace.
if you're a large, very large
organization, you can segregate, a co.
You can segregate the groups inside
the, into sub organizations or groups
inside the organizations into namespace.
For example, your finance and sales
could use different namespace.
They can keep submitting the machine
learning workloads to their own
namespace without encroaching the others.
Others, others, resource quota
or others resources, right?
For example, finance will not go and
use the, sales resources and sales
will not go and use the finance
resources, as I said earlier.
You also have node selectors things
and tolerations that allow you
to target specific nodes, where,
specific nodes, where you can perform
machine learning or deep learning.
And when you require GPUs, right?
that is what that is.
That's how Kubernetes helps you from
the resource management perspective.
from a portability perspective.
So Kubernetes, you write all,
whatever, what Kubernetes functionality
you're going to write, you're going
to write in terms of YAML files.
If you're going to define your cus
own customer source definitions,
you are going to use co files.
Now these are pretty much.
Independent of the cloud or wherever
you're going to deploy them, let
it be on-premise, cloud, or hybrid.
You'll still be working with same set
of YAML files, the same set of customer
source definitions, which themselves are
YAML files and a combination of co files.
So there's a huge portability if even
if you shift your cloud provider or
if you want to move your on-premise,
on-premise Kubernetes cluster.
There's a huge portability
when you work with Kubernetes.
Okay, so having, we have discussed some
of the, discussed some of the basics of
Kubernetes, but, let's try to understand,
some of the core concepts of Kubernetes.
And these are very core.
some of you might already know this.
I. From a machine learning perspective,
there are four things that we
need to do know about, Kubernetes.
Having said that, this is not
the entire list, I'm just trying
to put the four important.
There are several other, built in
resources that Kubernetes provides, and
there are several hundred projects in
cloud native compute foundation, CNCF,
that work around the Kubernetes ecosystem.
For example, the Orgo rollouts, which
allows you to roll out your, which
makes it rollout deployment where the
rollouts very easy or rollbacks very easy.
There are.
Hundreds of, CNCF providers out there
who built a lot of, resources around
machine learning and Kubernetes.
But for our session today, we'll
discuss the four most important
things, the pods, deployments, visas
and namespace POD is the smallest
deployment unit in Kubernetes.
as, and deployments are the ones
that bundle all your pods together.
They allow the pods to be, they
decide the number of replicas.
a pod can have.
They allow the auto scaling, horizonal,
auto scaling, and vertical scaling.
the services are the ones that expose
your deployments to the outside world.
And obviously we spoke
about namespaces earlier.
They allow you to logically group,
your logically group your resources,
which just by improving the isolation
and as well as the security, it
also allows the proper resource
management, of your Kubernetes cluster.
So four things, pods, deployment,
services, and namespace are the
basic things, at least what you want
to know when you're working with,
Kubernetes, and machine learning.
As I spoke about pods,
deployments and services.
These three comprise the three main
things, that, Kubernetes, these are the
fundamental things that anyone should
know when working with Kubernetes.
And of course with the machine
learning workloads that we
are going to discuss about.
Now there's one more thing which
is really important, right?
Kubernetes has this concept of
persistent volumes and persistent
volume classes and storage classes.
So these allow you to store
persistent data, when you're trying
to interact, when you're trying to
interact with Kubernetes classes.
for example, if you have
submitted a machine learning
job to Kubernetes cluster.
And it, you want to do some kind of
checkpointing at some time, right?
You want to store your intermediary
model or intermediary, parameters.
that's where the persistent
volumes, persistent volume
claims and storage classes shine.
And they're so easy to use that it's like.
Like any other, sourcing Kubernetes,
it's nothing but a Yamal file.
And of course, there's
a vendor tie up, right?
But that is handled by annotations.
And same goes with storage classes, right?
These are the concepts that
allow you to store your data.
When machine learning workload is
running, when you want a checkpoint,
when you want to store your
parameters, when you're actually
running your machine learning model.
So all these, all these three
help you to maintain some kind of
persistent state when your machine
learning workload is running.
In fact, these three are not very
related to machine learning workload.
They're related to.
They're also related to any
kind of, any kind of, um.
workload that you're trying
to run on Kubernetes.
Okay.
We spoke a lot about, Kubernetes.
We try to understand what is,
what are the basics of Kubernetes.
We try to understand what are the basics
of machine learning and, why we should
be using Kubernetes for machine learning.
Now you can go in and build your
own framework on Kubernetes, and
you can run your machine learning.
Workloads over there.
But there are several proven, tools
out there that allow you to run your
machine learning workloads on Kubernetes.
They just don't allow you to run.
They also allow you to visualize, do
an auto ml and several other things.
Very easy.
And now one of those very, very
famous tools that is gaining
traction these days is Q Flow.
It has been there for a while, but it's
gaining a lot of traction with the,
with the new LMS and foundation models.
Is Q Flow.
So Q Flow is an open source machine
learning toolkit, which simplifies
the deployment and management
of machine learning workloads.
So it is specifically
targeted for Kubernetes.
It has several key features, Q Flow,
and we'll be talking about each
one of them in the upcoming slide.
It has several key features.
It has training operators,
built-in training operators.
it has its own built-in serving
infrastructure called as Kerv.
It has a Python library that allows
you to write pipelines and it
also has a model storage model.
It also allows you to store the models,
and several other benefits, right?
There's several key features that
we'll be talking about in the
upcoming slides, as I said, instead
of building your own framework.
There's an open source initiative, that
came up from a lot of successful projects.
and, Q Flow makes it very easy to build
and deploy and manage your machine
learning models, and it accelerates
the AI development life cycle, Q Flow.
Again.
Q Flow is a game changing platform
for machine learning, on Kubernetes.
Okay, now we'll try to talk about
each one of the components on Q Flow.
Unfortunately, I couldn't put a
lot of examples here in the slides,
but, definitely as I said, we'll
have workshops so in the future.
But, what are the different
kinds of Q flow components?
The first component of Q Flow
is training operator, right?
There's a built in training
operator in Q Flow.
there is, there several building.
You can run a TensorFlow job.
You can run a job, you can run ANet job.
So these training operators allow
you to specify your training.
In the form of, in the
form of a YAML file.
Now it's a YAML file that could
run across any cloud on-premise.
as, as long as it has, it has a
Kubernetes cluster to run on it, you
can just interact with the training
operator since it's a YAML file that
Kubernetes understand you can interact
it with using by your cube cuttle file.
The training operators is one of
those things which easily makes,
which easily makes, running your, um.
running your training, you just need
to follow a specific contract and
create an image out of it and create
the yamal file out of the image.
The second important component
is the q plus serving.
So once you have built your model
and you've trained your model and
you've validated your model, you
want to deploy your model somewhere.
And that's where the Q plus
serving comes into picture.
It has a standard Python, API.
It also has the Yamal files that you
can use to expose your Q Flow serving.
And there's also something called
a model mesh that provides high
performance, scalable model serving
with intelligent routing, right?
So the it's, and it's beneath the
KF serving, but on the top you have
q plus serving, which allows you to
serve your models very efficiently.
so Q Flow pipelines, right?
So this is the third most important model.
In the Q Flow pipeline, there's
nothing but it's a Python.
It's a Python framework that
allows you to define your machine
learning workflow, orchestrate
it, so obviously you try to come.
It allows you to define your
entire machine learning lifecycle
in the form of a Python script.
Having said that, it also has a YAML file.
You can do it, the YAML file also, and it
allows you to track the performance also.
But you, when we say track, you can
also actually do an auto ML by using
something called a s CIB in Q Flow.
And, but we'll talk about PIL later.
But this Q Flow pipeline is a third
component, which plays a pivotal
role in writing your entire pipelines
end-to-end pipeline in Python.
And then you can use, you can deploy
the Python pipeline and run the Q flow.
Okay, so what does the lifecycle of, a
machine learning workload look on Q Flow?
We define a Q Flow job.
In this case, I took an example of a
TensorFlow job, and you can define it
by using a Python script or a YAML file.
We submit the job to
the Kubernetes cluster.
We monitor the progress by using the
Q Flow ui, and we finally deploy the
model by using the Q Flow serving.
And, we deploy the model.
And of course, once you've deployed the
model, you can actually, use the model for
inferencing by using the Q flow serving.
So this is the data addition steps
that we have already discussed.
it involves, working with data sources.
Then, you fetch, you
get the, all the data.
I'm just trying to go through step by
step guide of how you want to do the
machine learning on your Kubernetes.
you start with data sources.
You fetch data from
different data sources.
You do different kind of
data transformation on it.
You try to clean the data, remove the
alphanumeric characters, alphabetic
characters, scale everything to one
level, and then you finally come
out with a set of features, right?
That's what is called feature
engineering set of features for
your machine learning model.
Now then you do the machine learning,
then you do the actual training.
You define the training job, you
specify the resources that you want
to use for the specific, training job.
Again, the training Q Flow has its
own training operator that you can
use for, performing the training.
You specify the resources and find,
you validate the model by using
the Q Flow pipeline components.
and at the end, once you
have the model ready, you.
Try to serve the model
by using the KF serving.
I just went into some
of the internal details.
You need to create an inference,
service resource to define
your model serving deployment.
You specify the model, especially
where the model is located.
And finally, you deploy the model by
using the KF serve, which provides
your rest endpoint, or this is the
rest endpoint you can reach out to
through your Kubernetes service.
A gateway, which is associated with
the cloud, which with the cloud,
with the cloud gateway, right?
So you can reach that, reach from
an external, source to your, to your
serving endpoint on Kubernetes cluster.
So what are the best practices for
optimizing machine learning on Kubernetes?
one, one thing is there's
always, you have to choose the
right, right resources, right?
and again, this is not something
you can come up at one shot.
You have to experiment and play
around with it to choose the
right kind of resources, right?
And.
Use the GPUs, right?
Optimize the usage of GPUs, right?
So having said that, don't make
all your workloads run on GPUs.
You can optimize, the GPUs by using proper
teams tolerations on node selectors.
and you can just run those workloads,
which really require the GPO, right?
For example, the deep learning
with billion of parameters
or billions of parameters.
And finally, you need to keep
monitoring your monitoring
the performance of your model.
And there are several ways we can
monitor the performance, right?
You can keep constructing the
accuracy, you can keep constructing
the confusion matters as precisions,
recalls, et cetera, to keep, you keep
monitoring the performance of your
application and you keep training
your model, on a regular basis.
Okay, so what are different
resource allocation strategies?
I want to have a separate section
for this, especially because, we
have to understand what are the
right resource allocation strategies.
Now, one of the.
One of the basic things that you can do
is you can have static resources, right?
You can have always hard code,
your resources, but there is a
concept called a dynamic allocation
that allows you to allocate your
resources based on the workload and
find there is autoscaling, right?
You can do horizontal autoscaling
or vertical autoscaling depending
upon the number of factors, right?
You can also use some of the resources
from CNCF that allow you to do
the auto scaling based on external
factors like your queue sizes.
Your database sizes, some event
that happens outside of your
Kubernetes, Kubernetes, cluster.
So there are three different ways.
Basically we can do autoscaling,
the static allocation, the dynamic
allocation, and autoscaling.
Okay, and we already discussed about this.
Keep having your metrics.
Keep pumping your metrics.
Keep looking at your metrics.
Have proper alerts around your metrics.
Collect and analyze your logs, right?
Make sure that you collect and
analyze your logs so that you
can catch any potential problems.
have metrics or key performance indicators
that keep monitoring the health.
Of your ML applications, and if something
degrades immediately give an alert so
that e even before it starts degrading,
you can have warning alerts, you can have
critical alerts so that your teams can
become, can actually have a look at it
and, and try to resolve the issue before
it becomes a real production issue.
what are the different
security considerations?
I know till now we have spoken
about, the other kind of things,
apart from security, right?
So we have covered every other
aspect except the security now.
Again, since you're using
Kubernetes, Kubernetes has a
very great security mechanism.
It has built in authorization in
the form of RBAs ABAs, and you
can use authentication, right?
You can securely access to your
Kubernetes, by using certificates.
And of course you can include the data.
So all these are really
built into Kubernetes.
I'm not going into the fundamentals
of Kubernetes, but Kubernetes has
several tools like CER Manager, you can
use service meshes like STO Linkerd.
Or, or different other kinds of
service measures that allow you to
achieve this different authentication,
authorization, encryption, because
you're working on Kubernetes,
all that is taken care for you.
so two real world use cases that I
really want to talk about, right?
I'm not going to name any company over
here, but I think I. finance services and
healthcare AI are really gaining a lot
of, are really gaining a lot, a lot from
using Kubernetes for the machine learning.
So financial institutions really
use Kubernetes to deploy and
scale the fraud detection models.
Similarly, the healthcare providers
use Kubernetes to deploy and scale
medically image analysis models, right?
so Kubernetes is.
Gaining a lot of traction across
these industries, as the foundation
for scalable and label machine
learning deployments, right?
So these are a couple of real world
examples where in fact we do a lot of
those things for, we build a platform
and we do a lot of those things
for, the other platforms that are
there within our own organizations.
As you said about there are
financial services, right?
A lot if by the, in these days, I
think any financial organization
or a health organization should
have a Kubernetes cluster and
maybe having a Kubernetes cluster.
They might be moving towards an
idea of a Kubernetes cluster to
deploy their own microservices.
And since they all, if they already
have a Kubernetes cluster, they can use
the same Kubernetes cluster for, for
their machine learning work workloads.
And it really helps a
lot of things, right?
For fraud detection, for risk
management, for customer analytics.
So all this is where, Kubernetes and
machine learning workloads together can
help, in the financial services, as we
spoke about in healthcare, this medical
imaging, drug discovery, personalized
medicine, although all these are
not that related to Kubernetes, but.
Kubernetes allows you to make all this
very easy, very streamlined, focusing
on performance and minimizing the costs.
Now, before I wrap up, there's
some future trends that we are
going to talk about, right?
There is serverless ML on Kubernetes.
There is something called a scale native
that is coming up that is going to offer
the serverless platform on Kubernetes.
Function as a service, right?
which is gaining a lot of traction.
You can deploy individual ML functions
directly and even driven, architecture.
And that's what I was talking about,
Kubernetes event driven architecture, kdi,
you can go and look out for it on CNCF.
So all these are really evolving.
KDI is pretty much stabilized these days.
all these are really evolving
and providing, a lot of benefits
for someone who is trying to, use
Kubernetes for machine learning.
And thank you so much.
You can always write to me,
for any of your questions.
I'm available@prashant.one six@gmail.com.
please do mail me if
you have any questions.
I'll try to reply back to
you as, as soon as possible.
and that's what it is, right?
So we have discussed about,
Kubernetes and how it.
How it is the foundation, how it is
becoming the foundation of scalable ai.
what all it does is what we've
discussed in this section.
and, I really want to thank everyone
for listening me to this session,
for listening to this session, and
thank you con 42 for providing me an
opportunity to talk in this session.
Hopefully, I'll do a great workshop
in one of the future upcoming
Con 42, sessions if possible.
But again, thank you so
much for listening to me.