Hello everyone and welcome.
I'm Somnath Trewale and today we are going
to deep dive into Azure Site Recovery.
A modern cloud native approach to a
disaster recovery that's transforming
the way business ensures resiliency.
Disaster recovery has came a long way,
and I think it's important to first take
a step back and look at how we got there.
In the early 2000, a disaster
recovery was a. Completely a manual
process, backup tapes, secondary data
centers, and long recovery times.
It may take around 24 hours or more
just to bring a system back online.
Then we saw a virtualization
change the game Hyper V VMware.
These technologies helped
to reduce recovery times to
hours and made testing easier.
Now, we entered the new era,
cloud based disaster recovery.
With Azure Site Recovery brings
instant failover, a few minutes
RTOs, and intelligent orchestration.
The flexibility and scalability of
the cloud mean business can Achieve
a resilience without a complexity
of a traditional infrastructure.
Now let's talk about the
architecture of Azure Site Recovery.
If you are running Azure VMs,
our application is seamless.
No additional infrastructure is needed.
The Azure Site Recovery
agent will be installed.
on the VM and it will replicates the data
to the target region in a VMware to Azure
scenario that requires an on premises
appliance and a mobility agent on the
virtual machines or a physical server for
a smooth migration and Hyper V to Azure.
It's even simpler with Azure
Site Recovery Provider.
And if you are dealing with
the physical servers, a setup
is similar to VMware using the
process to handle the replication.
This flexibility ensures that regardless
of your environment, ASR can fit.
into your disaster recovery strategy.
Planning is a key to a disaster
recovery implementation.
A solid framework includes understanding
which applications are mission
critical by assessing the workloads
and validating the infrastructure.
Making sure you have the bandwidth,
latency and the initial syncs
are optimized, and you can do
a testing failure scenarios.
Either it's a planned or unplanned or
a test failures to ensure everything
works when it matters most, creating
a recovery runbooks, detailed step by
step recovery guides to your teams.
This structured approach.
helps to eliminate surprises
during a real disaster.
Let's talk about the replication.
Azure Site Recovery uses multiple
strategies to keep the data in sync.
A real time block replication
mirrors the data as changes happen
and keeping the RPOs closer to zero.
Our intelligent push architecture
comprises and duplicates data and
reducing the network overhead.
Database to sync engine only transfers the
change data, optimizing the performance.
VSS integrated snapshots ensure that
applications like SQL and SAP remain
consistent during the failover.
This means organization can
maintain business continuity.
with a minimal data loss
and near instant recovery.
A recovery process and here where
things get really interesting.
Enterprise workloads using Azure
Site Recovery can achieve 15 minutes
RTOs and near real time 30 seconds
RPOs mean almost no data loss.
A customer can deploy Deployments
have shown 76 percent reduction in
downtime, which is a game changer.
ASR also integrates deeply with Azure
Monitor, Azure Automation, giving
you real time insights and failovers
and enterprise grade data protection.
And, If you are running a mission critical
apps like SAP, Oracle or SQL, ASR ensures
they meet RTOs without missing a bit.
Let's talk a cost.
One of the biggest advantage of Azure
Site Recovery is the cost efficiency.
Traditional data recovery requires
a secondary data centers, dedicated
hardware, and a constant maintenance.
With ASR, 40 to 60 percent on disaster
recovery costs, thanks to pay as you go.
pricing and elimination of,
secondary site expenses.
And with a built in scalability,
business can protect up to 10,
000 incidents with auto scaling
and intelligent load balancing.
Key recommendation.
So what are the key takeaways?
of ensuring a successful
ASR implementation.
Comprehensive planning.
Start with well defined strategy.
Regular testing.
Validate your disaster recovery
plan with frequent failover drills.
Stop training.
Your team needs to be
confident in managing ASR.
Integrated monitoring.
Use a real time alert to stay
ahead of potential issues.
A well executed ASR plan can be
the difference between business
continuity and prolonged downtime.
Future directions and finally,
where is this all heading?
We are seeing AI powered recovery
automations that predicts the
failure before they happen.
Post quantum cryptographic
security to protect their data.
Seamless edge to cloud disaster recovery,
ensuring IOT workloads are protected.
And keep Kubernetes integration making
cloud native application disaster ready.
With 99%.
Recovery success rate.
I just said recovery is the
front of enterprise disaster
recovery and business resilience.
Disaster recovery isn't just
about reacting to outages.
It's about being prepared.
Minimizing downtime and ensuring business
continuity with Azure site recovery.
We are seeing organizations achieve
faster recoveries, lower cost and a
future proofed resilience strategy.
Thank you all for joining today.
I hope this session helps you
take more strategic approach
to modern disaster recovery.
Thank you once again.