Yes.
Hello all.
So before we begin, I have
a quick disclaimer here.
I would like to clarify that
this presentation is based on my
personal research and insights.
I am in no way speaking on behalf of
Amazon Web Services, and the views
expressed here are solely my own.
The stock is independent of my role at AWS
and is focused on exploring how blockchain
can enhance incident management.
Thank you all for joining today.
today to me at Con 4 42.
I'm Ju Sal and I'm excited to share my
insights on how blockchain is changing
the way we handle incident management.
In my current role at Amazon Web Services,
I focus on solving complex problems
related to large scale system incidents.
Through this experience, I have seen first
firsthand the challenges that come with
managing security and operational risk.
so this presentation today explores
how blockchain can make these processes
more secure, efficient, and transparent.
So before we, before we begin, you
will, notice a QR code on this slide.
So you can justcan it and visit my
portfolio and connect with me later.
Now, let's get started.
our, uh, now to set the stage, we'll
first, look at the difficulties faced
in existing incident management.
Then we will ex. Blur how blockchain helps
solve this problems and how different
industries are applying this approach.
From there, we will break down its impact
on the security audits and compliance.
We will also look at a case study
showing real world results and
wrap up with challenges, future
possibilities, and key takeaways.
With all of that in mind.
Let's get started by understanding
the struggles organizations face
when dealing with incidents.
it's handling incidents in, modern
businesses is far from simple.
With rapid dig or digital growth,
companies are dealing with more
connected systems than ever.
So this increases risks.
Can get harder to track and
respond to security events.
So traditional methods, rely on central
databases, which can be altered, delayed,
or even, lost in the critical moments
as businesses and across regions.
managing incidents across multiple,
locations becomes even harder.
So this is where blockchain
comes into picture.
By offering a way to seek Howly
record and share information without
a central authority, it changes how
we approach event, security events.
Let's take a closer
look at how this works.
at its core,
blockchain provides a shared record that.
No single person or company can alter.
So this is done through a system that
records every action in a way that
ensures honesty and accuracy Another.
Q benefit is automation.
S smart contracts.
All self running programs help
trigger responses automatically,
reducing delays and human errors.
So these features make
blockchain a strong option for.
For ending, security events, especially
in industries where reliability and
trust, are at utmost importance.
But what makes it, truly
unique is its ability to create
records that cannot be changed.
So let's explore that next.
so one of the, one of the
biggest concerns in incident.
Handling is proving of
what really happened.
So records can be altered,
deleted, or manipulated, leading
to disputes and compliance issues.
Blockchain eliminates this risk by keeping
an unchangeable record, so each event is
stored in a way that, that no one can edit
or remove, ensuring full accountability.
So this feature is not just useful.
it's essential for industries that require
accurate records such as finance and
healthcare, but security is about more
than just keeping the records intact.
It also means making sure only the
right people have access to it.
So let's move on to that.
Power system is one that keeps.
Helps out unauthorized users while
giving the right people easy access.
So blockchain does this in three key ways.
First, it, it uses encryption to make
sure data is protected at all times.
Second, access is controlled using smart
contracts, which grants permissions
automatically based on rules.
Oh, finally, blockchain both follows
a security model where every action is
checked before it is allowed, making
unauthorized access nearly impossible.
So this security benefits help
organizations gain trust and reduce risk.
But another, major
concern of this business.
Of this business is, of following
the government and industry rules.
So that's what we will discuss next.
F for many businesses out there,
following rules is just as
important as protecting data.
So mistakes can lead to
fines or legal trouble.
this is where, blockchain makes compliance
easier by, by actually creating the
records that are always accurate and
available for review, automated tracking
and ensures that every action is logged,
reducing the need for manual reports.
Okay, so this helps.
This helps business prove they
are following rules without
spending extra time or effort.
But how do we make sure that the
system itself is working correctly?
that's where audits come in.
So our well structured.
System needs, regular
checks to stay reliable.
blockchain auditing is done in four ways.
First, there is only ongoing
improvement where security measures
are updated based on new threats.
Second, there's a compliance
verification to make sure
industry rules are being backed.
Third, the system's daily operations are.
are reviewed to check for inefficiencies.
And finally, the technology
itself is tested for weeks.
So by following this process,
organizations can ensure
that our blockchain setup is
always working, is expected.
now let's see how different
industries are applying these ideas.
Companies in finance, healthcare,
and security are adopting, adopting,
blockchain, rapidly than others.
So, although banks, we use it to
track transactions without risk
of fraud, hospitals rely on it
to keep patient records safe.
security of firms use it to
monitor threats in real time.
Each of these industries, benefits in, in,
in its own ways, but they are all, share.
but they all share a need for,
reliable and care systems to understand
our, understand blockchains, really
impact, let's actually, go through,
Go through a real world case study.
uh, large financial companies
struggled with slow response
times and our data tracking.
So before blockchain, resolving
an issue took almost two days.
So after switching to blockchain, this
dropped by 72% compliance reporting,
which was manual and time consuming.
It's also, also, became 89% faster.
So this case proves that blockchain
is not just an idea, it actually
delivers measurable improvements.
However, No system is perfect.
So let's discuss some challenges that
come with adopting this technology.
Oh, so while, so while blockchain
has, its, has its clear benefits, it
also comes with some, hurdles, setting
up a new system requires investment
training and a shift in company culture.
Indeed.
Creating blockchain with older
systems is another challenge.
So despite these obstacles, businesses
are finding ways to overcome them
by starting small and scaling up.
and then, and then looking ahead, let's
see, let's see, no where the, where
this blockchain is headed in the future.
So blockchain is evolving
alongside artificial intelligence
and connected devices.
all, all together, these technologies
will help, predict problems before
they happen and ultimate response, but
even further, and the will, the future.
research will focus on, on
making blockchain easier
to use and more adaptable.
Organizations that start using it
now will be in a strong position.
As these advancements unfolded.
so this, this brings us
to end of this session.
I share all of your time and interest if
you'd like to explore this ideas further.
scan this QR code and
then connect with me.
I look for, to hearing, hearing
your thoughts and answers.
and answering any of your, any
further questions that you have.
So thank you again and have a great day.
Bye-bye.