What is now changing all
going towards AI development?
Everyone is talking about ai.
What this all about.
I'm going to go over context awareness
on the AI development, unlocking the
next web engineer productivity for you.
I'm Goov Kumar from Amazon.
I've been here in Amazon for last
15 years into different software
development roles, and I'm gonna help
you understand what context awareness
is and how it's gonna help and reshape
the next engineering way of productivity
that is coming along the journey.
Alright, let's go.
So the AI development
shift is already here.
Productivity target is increasing.
Everyone expecting that productivity
will increase by five x, 10
x. How we gonna achieve it?
Let's dive deep into it.
Engineering effort that once took weeks.
Now it's in days, like months
into weeks, and less than
that, the baseline has changed.
The expectations have increased across
all leaders, all business leaders,
all together around the world.
AI assisted development is the
core of the technology right now.
If people are not doing it right now,
we have to take our steps and start
learning and get into this world.
There is no getting away from this.
This is the real new phase of
development that is coming along teams
that delayed option risk of falling
behind our productivity standards
and evolution of the industry.
The coaching is no longer.
Whether to adopt AI workflow,
but it's how to make use of it
and how to be more productive.
Alright.
Let's go to the next slide, which
talks about the critical bottleneck.
What are the context lost?
Whenever we do the development,
we often do in isolation.
We do our work and we forget
about it the next time we pick the
work after weeks, after months.
If other developer in the team has to
pick the work, same context laws happen,
the best abilities we do, the knowledge
setting transfers, but that takes a good
hit on overall the context possible.
So most of the air development
operates in a stateless environments.
So now every new time someone has to
start, the new session will start here.
Or in the session.
On the machine.
No memory.
Almost no memory on the projects,
architecture, trade offs,
standards, business use cases.
The, we can record it.
We can record it or, the spreadsheets,
script, documents, or SharePoints.
But developers have to come
back and go through that again.
There is no direct context
available there for developers.
So developers end up rebuilding the
same mental model over and over again
before tool can be useful, before
tool can be rerated, restructured,
redeveloped to the next level.
So a lot of onboarding time is
needed here to get to the to
the next level of the software.
And that's where the context come
into picture at present in the.
Traditional methodologies of software
development, the context losses is very
big challenge getting things move fast.
The reation of the task,
that's is really cost, right?
So the time is lost.
Restating requirements, explaining
the boundaries, correcting
suggestions, how to take next steps.
What was the reason why certain
decisions were made, why we took it
hit, why we took hidden and latency.
Why we had this matter error code.
Why did not put this logs, why we have put
that change, this all have a context and
that get lost if not properly documented
in the next phase of development.
So the core bottleneck is is not the
rock capability for someone to do the
development work, but it's the continuity
until AI can reliably retain and apply
project context over time, it will
remain strong at isolated task, but
weak as sustained engineering work.
Alright, let's go next and find
how we can have our context
building development in AI world.
Alright, so why is lately
stateless AI create friction?
Repeated reestablished meant lost
architecture memory, and reduce
collaboration depth in the repeated
reestablishment developers manually
reexplain policy structures.
Constants and conventions at the
start of every AI interaction, a
compound tracks on productivity, right?
So I'm moving from very
traditional software development
to to a basic AI development.
Even in the basic AI development, we give
prompts, we write something that memory is
not there whenever we come back or someone
else is doing the development work.
That memory in that process is lost.
All together, the context is lost.
Not rather, I should
remember the context is lost.
So the lost architecture memory, hard one.
Design decisions trade-offs made during
the earlier sessions are invisible on
the AI in sub condition interactions
leading to inconsistent suggestions
that your AI tool will give you.
So it's really important for AI
tool to understand what is under,
what constraints I'm working.
What was the previous history that was.
Taken for the software development, what
are previous decisions which we taken and
how we have to move forward from here.
That's lost architectural memory,
which theres, if you don't follow
a proper contextual development
work, reduced collaboration depth.
Yes.
This is one of the biggest challenge as
we do more collaboration in a very wide.
Team.
Small startups, yes, small and individuals
can do it, but in a, in an environment
where we have to do a lot of collaboration
with other sds without persistent context,
the AI assistance will not give you the
enough ideas or we'll be unable to reason
about the long term project evolution.
Un enforced team level
conventions reliably.
It also helps on putting the team,
conventions, the team and the developers,
conventions, team conventions, the
leadership conventions all together,
principal engineers coming into a
picture and they're saying, this is the
right way of doing, putting the code
structure, and that is what we want.
That is what the context we want
while doing the development.
Let's see how we can do it.
Solving the context problem.
So a practical three pillar framework
for enabling context awareness.
AI workflows cross the F, so
developing lifecycle is the pillar
of how we can build the context.
First thing, the first pillar.
Let's talk among the three pillars.
Let's talk about the first
pillar, living context, artifacts.
We have to maintain the
dynamic version context for ai.
It should not be static.
It should be version context for ai,
which team members can collaborate.
You can extend that and that
will be a living document rather
than just a static document.
So it's important.
It's a living context, artifacts.
Alright, let's go to the next pillar.
Standardized prompt templates, reusable
consistent prompts for reliable outputs.
In a team where there are multiple
SDS working, you want the best
productivity coming out from all the sds.
How do we do that?
We need to develop standardized, prompt
for the repeat tasks that we always do.
That person being on call solving
tickets going and finding details.
About a project solving same repetitive
problem again and again, looking at the
logs, diving deep in the architecture,
finding out why threats are taking
so much consumption in the service.
All these things, there are standardized
prompts that can be developed across
the team, which are reusable and
very consistent and very accurate
that we can have and if, and that is
something we all need to have for our
core productive output from templates.
Now a structured session handoff.
This is very interesting, but the
third pillar is a clear transfer
of context between sessions.
This is the AI interaction that needs to
happen for between the sessions, and that
is how the context comes in the picture
and the compounding, and it compounds
over the period of time, and that's how
we are going to see the productivity.
It's productive doesn't
come simply by using ai.
It comes by efficiently using
ai, by having the context into
the problem that you're solving.
Alright, now living project context
artifacts, let's talk about what is
a living project context artifacts.
So it's about maintaining continuously
updated document that serve as the AI
persistent memory for your project.
Capturing architecture decisions, coding
conventions, domain terminologies,
and key trade ops as they evolved.
So there are concept of architectural
decision records, which are
kept current domain glossaries.
And constant catalogs reviewed and
version control alongside code.
This is a really important one,
like reviewed and version control
alongside code that we need to have.
So three important aspects, right?
Just to repeat myself, architecture,
decision records, domain process,
and constant catalogs and reviewed
and version control alongside code.
So when the contact artifacts are treated
as first class engineering assets, right?
This is no more an optional thing.
This is not an secondary thing.
This is a first class engineering asset
that you all we need to have in our core
development practice, in the best software
development practice through the AI world.
We need to do AI tools can reason about
your systems with the same depth as
senior team members, reducing onboarding
time and improving suggestions,
quality across every interaction.
So this is very interesting, you being
a leader or being software developer.
Pay attention to this.
When you treat your artifact as
a first class engineering assets,
when I say artifact, your contact
artifact can give you the answers.
Has a senior member in
the team would give you.
That means you will not have so
many meetings with the engineer.
Senior engineers.
You will have reduced workforce workload
that on that particular person and
onboarding time will drastically reduce.
Everyone will become more independent.
We'll drive their own chain of thoughts
coming from the answers, which typically
would like, like a senior member, and
the team has answered it, improving the
quality of the development work and the
consistency, and that puts the pace on
the overall development work for the team.
Alright, let's go to the second pillar,
the standardized prompt templates ple.
We need to replace ad hoc
prompting with structured templates
in the AI development work.
Anyway.
Simplistic AI development work.
We all write prompts.
We write ad hoc prompts, and we ask AI
to give me an answer that's traditional
way, that's old way of doing it.
Now to improve the productivity, it we
have to replace these ad hocs prompting
with the structured templates that
embeds architecture and domain knowledge
altogether, which helps improving the
productivity and helping AI to give
the right answer for the software
development work that someone is doing.
Prompt engineering becomes the team
practice, not an angel with skill.
Prompt engineering has to be fenced
with the template of the structure
that you need to give, right?
Templates and code, project
constraints and standards, right?
It shared across the team for
consistent AI output and versioned.
And I created like internal tooling.
So pay attention to what the
standardized prompt templates.
This is a really important one,
like a standardized prompt.
Templates are important ones, which
can be shared across team members.
Everyone can use this template
and everyone is using.
And once we have the template,
the best part of having a template
that no one has to rethink how to
write, they have a way to start.
And as I always say, if
you have a way to start.
Getting the work done
is not a big problem.
How to get started is the biggest problem.
Template.
Solve that problem and that helps improve
the productivity, that helps sds take
right next steps or SDS on anyone.
Product manager, software,
develop manager, anyone.
Take the right next steps
and move towards the prompt.
Alright, let's go to the next and the
third pillar, structured session handoffs.
Here we need to implement
deliberate handoff practices that
allow AI collaboration to persist
effectively cross development cycles.
So progress made in one session is never
lost In the next end of the session
summarizes capturing decisions made,
standardized context, reload sequences,
start sessions, shared handoffs,
artifacts stored in the team repositories.
Alright, so what did we
get out of this pillar?
Structured session handoffs and
implementing like handoff practices
that allows AI collaboration to persist
effectively across development SI
lifecycle is so important altogether.
So end of session summarizes the capturing
decisions made standardized context reload
sequences at the start of the session.
So when we talk about session handoffs,
making use of AI and doing this handoff
to the next person is so important.
It helps.
Make the context live.
It helps bring the output and
hand over a up to hand over to the
next person who is doing the work.
Alright.
Where AI development is headed,
emerging infrastructure for
persistence, ai, collaboration.
So here's the key part.
Persistence, AI, collaboration, stateful
AI environments, persistent tool use,
state and cross session reasoning.
It's all about the memory which can
live and the, not the memory part, but
some are memory, but the co the but the
collaboration that can live forever.
Is we are talking about all the
collaboration through the context
that can live for a very long time
and that can easily be passed.
AI can understand better, the
framework can be right, the
templates can help in the process.
So stateful AI environment
with the context we get to
the stateful AI environments.
So new infrastructure efforts
enabling agents to retain memory
context and decision history.
Cross sessions, eliminating
cold start friction entirely.
Persistence tool use state
agents that maintain tool use
state across interactions.
Aware of prior API calls trust results
and code changes made in earlier sessions.
That's what it means
for a persistent tool.
Use state crossing cross sessions
reasoning AI systems, capable of reasoning
about long-term project evaluation,
enforcing consistency across sprints.
Identifying pattern drift
over time helps everyone.
Alright, context aware AI across
the development life cycle.
So we have coding, testing,
documentation, code, reviews.
These are typical process
that we all go through.
So context awareness AI does
not accelerate a single phase.
It compounds the value across every
state of the engineering workflow.
We all have learned the simple
interest versus compound interest.
This is where it comes to the picture.
This context awareness
is the compound growth.
It's not a simple growth, it's a
compound growth that we will see.
AI gives a simple growth.
The context awareness gives the compound
growth that we all need to have in the
evolving AI world, and that's how we
are going to get five x productivity
increase, 10 x productivity increase
across next few months and years to come,
not years, weeks, and months to come.
I'll take my word back.
When the AI understands your
architecture, your conventions, and
your history, it becomes a genuine
collaborate collaborator for us, for
you rather than a generic assistance.
So it is not more ai, no assistant, it's a
collaborator that we all need to interact
and producing output that fits our system.
Your system from day one, right?
Let's go to the next one.
Making it a team practice.
It is important that we do
not keep it individual, make
we make it the team practice.
As a manager, as the leader, we
need to make sure that context
awareness is spread across the team.
Sharing the artifacts, creating
a template, making sure everyone
is using those templates.
The architectural summary, which can be
spread, creating a team shared prompts,
which can be used by the team members
to get the same consistent information
as a junior member will get compared to
a senior member will have in his mind.
So it is really important that we
flow this information, we flow this
as a practice to the entire team.
It helps strengthen the collaboration
and adding and removing the
friction altogether in the team.
Alright, patterns to
take back to your team.
What are the things we need to take back?
Audit your context gaps.
Go back and find out.
Is our team, is your team doing that?
Context based development work.
Identify where developers are
repeatedly doing the work.
Again and again, re-explaining the
project context to the team members.
That's where the context can help.
Can help and repeatedly
re-explaining project context.
The AI tools.
These are the highest leverage
starting points for the for you, for
is to now your first three prompts.
As I always give physicians, everyone, we
can't handle a hundred things at a time.
Focus on first three
things that we can handle.
Pick the three most common AI tasks on
your team and build, share architecture.
Embedded a template for each of them.
Create your living context, artifacts.
Share with the A DI template
and a domain glossary.
Keep them low.
Co-located with code and review
with every we print instrument.
A session handoff ritual, agreed on
a light weighted end of the session.
Summary format, store summaries
where the whole team can use them
as a context relate, reload inputs
on their work what they need to do.
Alright, keep key takeaways, context
loss limits, ai, as I mentioned earlier,
simple versus compound interest.
Using context gives compound productivity.
If we don't use this will be a
simple productivity that we'll get.
Stateless AI interactions.
Cap productivity solving context is the
highest leverage investment and we need
to have the context in the developments.
Three plus one system living artifacts.
Standardized prompts and structured
handoffs turn AI collaboration
into compounding values.
The infrastructure is arriving.
Stateful, AI and persistent memory
are emerging teams with strong
habit today will adopt them fastest.
Alright, la The new AI native engineering
era starts now this whole new era,
which is starting thread, sorry.
Agents, teams that you can
build where agents will have.
Their own memory agent team, where agent,
all agent, all your agents will know about
each other, how others are performing.
They have, they will share
memory to each other.
So they, this world is changing with
respect to how we share the context.
The sharing context is a fundamental model
that we all need to understand, implement,
and AI internally is also implementing
the same thing with respect to the
agents that is going respond across.
Generic versus team agent.
So AI, native engineering
era is, it starts now.
It's already there and
it's a cultural shift.
It's a change that we all need to adopt.
Treat context as a shared
asset, preserve institutional
memory, and make knowledge easy.
Touse, that's the whole intent.
That's where we want to go.
It makes our life easy.
At the same time, improving the
productivity in a compound way.
Capture intent, standardized
prompts, and design for continuity.
The teams that do will move
faster, collaborate better,
and build a lasting edge.
This is normally an optional thing.
This is what we need to have context
is context sharing, context building.
Building through the template, sharing
with the team is critical for this era.
We all need to live with
it and this is that.
This era changing, this era
changes already started.
Now let's go and build this
shift among our team members,
among our all organization.
Alright, thank you everyone.
Thanks for coming and
listening to my slides.
Thank you and hope to see you soon
and good luck on AI development.
Thank you.
Bye-bye.