Hello and welcome to today's presentation.
We're gonna touch upon a very
timely topic to today's agentic AI
era, intent-based orchestration.
As we stand here in 2026, the era
of standalone chat bot is over.
We have transitioned into a unified
era of unified AI ecosystems, a fluid
collaborative environment where AI
agents aren't just static tools.
But our interconnected nodes, our goal
today is to master the orchestration of
these nodes, specifically focusing on
the delicate balance between autonomous
action and human accountability.
So let's dive into it.
Currently, the enterprise AI landscape
is a bunch of tangled cable cables.
It has been a byproduct of business
units building their own desperate
agents that do not communicate.
This leads to fragmented point
solutions that don't just partially
solve the problem, but also creates
cognitive overhead for its users.
This manifests in two ways.
First wi solutions, which break
even with the slightest change in
process or when queries get complex.
Second is the intelligent stacks.
This is the high cost and
latency that's incurred.
Where we overuse massive large language
models for simple yet repetitive
tasks which leads to a premium cost
for a reasoning that a smaller model
could have easily handled, and it
creates an unsustainable operational
overhead or the platform owners.
Finally the users just get frustrated
with too many agents to handle and stitch
and orchestrate manually and adjusting to
what the agents can actually accomplish.
Let's look at a real world example.
Consider the workflow of an
employee onboarding process.
In the current world, the
human manager is the glue.
They have to work with multiple
automated processes that work in
the it, HR and finance domains.
Sometimes integrated and
sometimes fragmented.
Not for fully automated where the
manager has to go and stitch these
different processes together to
complete a certain onboarding process.
Even its slightest variation to
onboarding that is off the predetermined
pathway breaks the process.
But in the agentic future, we move
to an orchestrated intent here.
Using semantic flexibility, the
agent understands the underlying
goal, which is onboarding a new hire.
Even if specific steps change,
the agent's able to adapt to
the new situation and scenario.
And gracefully handle the change.
The orchestrator coordinates multi-agent
workflow that adapts to live data,
allowing the manager to shift from
a manual coordinator to a strategic
overseer well within a govern network.
To solve these challenges, we must stop
thinking of AI as a tool and rather
think of it as an architecture pattern.
As shown in this layered cake.
At the bottom of the architecture
is enterprise tools, which
is your foundational data and
enterprise applications that
you work day-to-day with.
And on the top layer is the user
experience and the channels through
which the users interact with your agent.
The middle layer is the
unified orchestration layer.
This is the brain of your enterprise.
It interprets the user's intent.
Plans decomposers and plans the tasks and
routes it to appropriate agent, executing
the workflows contextually aware and
specific to your company's policies.
When we talk about multi-agent
ecosystems, there are six key
components to it, in my opinion.
The first one is the intent,
inter intelligence, which allows
decomposition of a complex
query and planning of the steps.
Second is the multi-agent orchestrator,
which acts as the harness layer to
bring together the task specific
agents that are underneath it with
the required tools and knowledge.
The third component is the
specialized agent pool.
This provides task specific agents
that have the necessary tools and
knowledge for their scope of work.
And the fourth one is
tools and skill registry.
And this registry provides the
necessary tools, or it's one single
catalog of the necessary tools.
Rather all the tools in the
enterprise and skills that agents
can use to accomplish their.
Next is the adaptive memory.
This is a very important layer when it
comes to multi-agent ecosystems because it
ensures that context is shared across the
agents and handoffs are smooth, and when
there needs to be a pause it makes sure
that the state is managed accordingly.
And then finally, is the human in the
loop policy gate very important for
building trusted enterprise solutions.
It ensures that high stake actions
are paused for human review.
It ensures that every request, the,
this entire pipeline ensures that every
request is understood, planned, and
executed with the safety protocols.
Let's let's talk about the
intelligence stacks for a moment.
To eliminate intelligence tax, it's
important to have a smart router.
That prioritizes cost and reasoning depth.
The router should apply a cost logic fork
that routes simple low reasoning tasks to
cheaper small language models and complex
high reasoning tasks with that deal with
a lot of ambiguity and are in the path
of critical workflows to high to large
language models with high reasoning.
Obviously higher cost.
This makes, ensures that the system
is set to scale in a cost efficient
manner, and there are no cost surprises
in a live production environment.
Let's look at how the orchestrator works.
The orchestrator here
is the harness engine.
It uses gold decomposition via
prompt chaining and breaks down a
massive objective into manageable
subtasks before any tool is invoked.
It runs through a lift reflection loop
where the reasoning engine critics its own
plan and makes the necessary adjustments.
After the plan is finalized and
validated it uses agents and tools and
CPS to then execute on those tasks.
This ensures that the responses are
based on a clear vetted out process.
And they are grounded in the knowledge
of your enterprise and live data
and not with some model static data.
Now let's look at the
adaptive memory architecture.
To move beyond static automation, we
have to evolve from basic session storage
to a multi-layered adaptive memory.
At the top is the session context
that tracks immediate session
activities and manages a agent handoff.
In the middle is the experience store.
That is used to remember
successful reasoning paths from
past executions and is able to
apply that for future executions.
And in the foundational layer
is the in context knowledge.
Rather than relying on stale internal
model training, we use rag to surface
the exact realtime facts needed for the
current task and bring them right into
the agent's context in addition to rag.
It also brings in a lot of contextual
information about the user about the
time or about the business to make sure
that this process that every decision
that the agent takes is contextually
relevant and highly accurate.
Now, let's move forward and see how our
employee onboarding process looks like.
With a multi-agent framework the
onboarding supervisor operates
with within an agent harness.
Issues, formal contracts
to the task specific bots.
As you can see, these contracts enforce
resource bound executions so that
the agents don't fall into expensive
in finite loops, or even worse, take
actions that they're not supposed to.
At the edge of every handoff we use agent
ask to intercept for potential errors.
For example, if the IT agent identifies
a need for confidential system access,
but did not justify it, there is a gap.
The harness clarifies the intent before
it executes on the on provisioning the
access, creating a system wide risk.
And because this access is high
stakes, the harness triggers
a cascading human in the loop.
Pause.
It persists the distributed state of the
entire agent, ecosystem and hierarchy,
providing a human to come and take action
while it presents this to the human,
it also provides a IM trajectory of
immutable audit trial, which makes clear
of the agent's actions thus far so that
the human can now review and approve
the action once the human approval is.
Is done.
The supervisor agent then goes
about finishing the workflow in
an autonomous way, finalizing,
provisioning, and payroll set up.
So with this way we ensure that
it's semantic, it's intent based,
yet there is a human in the loop
to ensure that system does not
autonomously act on high stakes action.
Now let's talk about the user
experience aspect of this.
As you can see, the agentic backend is
very fluid and it only makes sense to
have an agentic frontend to to the user
to be able to use such a complex system.
These front ends.
So it brings us.
To a state where now we need
generative ui, which means that
these UI components are essentially
front end skills, just like any
other skill in the skill registry.
And using APIs, they can be
brought to the user's ui.
So for example, if the user's working
on a data analytics workflow or
looking at a finance risk report, the
UI morphs into a dashboard type of.
Framework.
Whereas if the user is working on a HR
onboarding checklist, the UI transforms
into a document centric view in real time.
This makes e, this makes it easier
for any user to interact with
such a dynamic agent ecosystem.
Okay, so now coming to the very important
aspect of multi-agent ecosystem is evals.
Accountability is a
first class citizen here.
Trajectory evals should be
utilized whenever possible to
score the agent's actual path.
This needs to be done against
a predetermined policy graph to
ensure that the agent did not just
find an answer taking any possible
path, but actually sticked to an
approved path to complete its job.
This is achieved to
immutable audit trials.
So one, we have the predetermined path
in as a policy graph, and then we have
these immutable audit trials that track
every single action taken by the agent.
This provides transparency
required for regulatory compliance
and enterprise wide trust.
So moving forward let's look at
what it takes to realize this
in an enterprise environment.
What is the roadmap to such
a multi-agent ecosystem?
For enterprises?
I've split this into
four different phases.
So phase one is foundational.
It's the foundation of
intent and retrieval.
So these are simple AI agents that
work on a smaller set of intents
and can provide answers grounded in
the enterprises data and knowledge.
Phase two is orchestration.
This is where we are able to
orchestrate multiple agents.
And that work with tools and there
comes the need for a registry and
yeah, agent registry and harness.
And phase three is bringing in
the accountability breakthrough.
This is where we bring
in high stakes action.
Introducing high stakes action does
require human accountability and approval.
So without this the agent ecosystem
will be only confined to simple tasks.
Now, with agentic workflows that have
state management and human in the loop
built in, you can now expand your agents.
To high stakes action as well.
And once after this is phase
and govern scale and govern.
Ensuring that the agents are built for
scale and there is strong governance
to continuously evaluate the agents
trajectory and catch any rogue behavior
by the agents and stop it right away.
Governance becomes a very
important aspect when we get
into enterprise wide deployments.
As we can see the, there's
been a tremendous evolution
to reach the, to the state.
Not long ago we just had reactive q and
A pods that does single turn actions.
Then we evolved into
conversational assistance.
That have session context and are
more conversational for the users to
retrieve knowledge or take action.
It then evolved into tool augmented
agents to take real time action.
And now we are in the era of auto
autonomous agent network, where at
this level, multi-step workflows
with state management and human
checkpoints are baked into the system
and it allows for long horizon tasks.
To be completed across multiple
business domains simultaneously.
So to conclude, let's look at the
key takeaways from this presentation.
The any AI strategy must focus on
four critical points, number one.
Unified through orchestration.
This is necessary to be intent-based
and to end the cycle of fragmented
solutions and agents and avoid
the tangle cable problem.
Second is prioritize reasoning over
training the semantic flexibility
does and will help eliminate the
rigidity problem and make sure
that your agent remains successful.
In real world scenarios, which
always does not have a set path.
Three is implement human first governance.
This is where it's we build the
capabilities to have human in the
loop process and trajectory evals that
helps build trust and accountability
into the organization, and finally
eliminate the intelligence tax through
smart routing and to be cost efficient
and self-correcting in the process.
So by building an agent harness layer
that is cost aware and self-correcting.
We ensure that the AI platform drives
ROI rather than technical debt.
So it's time now to move from isolated
bots into governed multi-agent system.
Thank you for joining.