Hey, good morning, everybody.
My name is Praful Kondiru.
I'm a software engineer with over
10 years of experience building
distributed and scalable systems.
And I'm excited to be here today.
in my session, we'll be exploring
more about, cloud native
resilience, and I'll talk a bit.
More about how I build scalable and fault
tolerant systems and hope my experience
would have valuable lessons for you.
by, you may ask what, what does cloud
native resilience actually mean?
and short answer for that is we
mean designing systems that not only
scale efficiently, but also maintain
their performance and availability,
even when unexpected issues arise.
during this talk, we'll
cover several key areas.
I'll first start off by
introducing cloud native concepts.
and then I'll move on to talking
about the core design principles
that support resilience.
and the most important topic of
all is talking more about the
role of Microsoft's architecture,
containerization, and automation.
and finally, we'll dive
into some practical code
examples and demonstrations.
so yeah, this presentation is geared
towards tech professionals like yourselves
so you can expect in that, content
along with some hands on examples.
please feel free to note your
questions you have and we can
you can shoot me an email, if you
have any questions at the end.
but yeah, my goal is to equip you with all
sorts of practical insights and techniques
that can apply that you can apply to
build robust and fault tolerant systems
in your own cloud environments so yeah,
so without further ado, let's get started.
So yeah, so like I spoke
in My previous slide.
so on this slide i'll walk you through
the agenda for today's session.
So we'll start with an introduction to
Cloud Native Concepts, the fundamental
ideas behind building resilient systems.
Next we'll discuss the key design
principles that help us build fault
tolerant applications, such as redundancy,
loose coupling and graceful degradation.
Then we'll explore a little bit more
about the microservice architecture
And, how breaking application to do
smaller independent services can actually
Boost resilience and scalability.
Following that, we will cover
containerization and orchestration
tools like Docker, Kubernetes that
kind of simplify deployment and
management of cloud native systems.
And finally, I'll talk a bit more about
like the CI CD pipelines and monitoring
tools just to make sure, when a system
crashes, like how do we recover It's
super quickly in a dynamic environment.
and you'll see you in most of
the slides I have like code and
demonstrations to help you understand
the practical nature of this.
Yeah, let's come get started with
the first intro So let's define what?
Cloud native actually means right?
So people throw this word cloud
all over the place But I initially
didn't like a couple of years ago.
I didn't know what it actually meant
but yeah, so when I when you say cloud
native, it's actually an approach to
building and like running applications
that kind of fully Exploit the
advantages of like cloud computing.
so this means like designing applications
to be like super scalable, elastic and
resilient right from like the ground up.
so there are a lot of like ways
to achieve this and this is
what my talk today will cover.
So also talking a bit more about the key
characteristics of cloud native systems.
Is like I mentioned, the scalability
part of it, which is to like effortlessly
handle increases in workload, by
adding more and more resources.
elasticity is another property
of like cloud native systems,
which kind of dynamically adjust
resources based on demand.
and finally resilience which is
essentially maintaining performance
and like availability even in the
face of failure So these are like
the main characteristics of it.
and The benefits with building cloud
native applications are like, obviously,
faster innovation, like it's super quick
to deploy to cloud, obviously, and along
with it, we can cheaply utilize resources.
We can like smartly scale up and
scale down based on the demand.
if on a certain day, there's going to be
like a million customers to a website.
You can pre compute and scale your
resources to that extent, and on
off days, you can scale it down.
So you're efficiently using your
resources and not turning on your compute
for 24 7, which is a waste of money.
so yeah, moving on, okay.
Why resilience actually matters?
So why does this matter?
so how do I define resilience, right?
So essentially, like I mentioned,
the ability to handle and recover
from failures gracefully, and
why does it actually matter?
So we need high availability for our
systems so that we can ensure that
applications remain accessible, which is
crucial for like user satisfaction, right?
Or else we wouldn't want to like, lose
our customers just because our website is
down, and also the business impact of it.
It's huge.
because like reduced downtime translates
directly to Lower, lower financial
losses on improved service reliability.
and finally, like I mentioned, the user
experience as a user, I don't really want
to see huge websites like Amazon done.
So it like severely impacts
the user trust and experience.
so yeah, in the following
slides, we can discuss more.
On the design principles that help
achieve this level of resilience
and i'll show you how these Ideas
are actually implemented in like
real world examples yeah moving on.
So so yeah in order to build Brazilian
systems, it's essential to incorporate
Key design principles from the start.
so as an engineer when you're building
a cloud native application some
of the things that You would need
to remember is along the lines of,
redundancy, by duplicating crucial
components, the system can like continue
operating even if one instance fails.
So that's what you call talk people.
You hear people talk about
like horizontal scaling, right?
You got to have like multiple
copies of the same server where
your code is currently deployed.
Cause if one of the servers goes
down, you could essentially.
Move all the traffic to another server
and prevent any downtime to your website
and another important principle is
loose coupling and what I mean by that
is like We got a design systems where
components have like minimal dependencies
on each other And ensure that failures
in one area doesn't really cascade and
bring down the entire system So this is
another prime principle of like resilient
systems and also I have to fail fast.
just because I don't wanna sit and
deal with a server that is down and
restart it and who knows how long it's
gonna take me to restart and in the
meanwhile I don't want to keep my user
waiting so I'll have to transfer All
the traffic to like another server.
And, this is what I mean
by graceful degradation.
I don't want users to like, just see a
404 on the screen and just be like, Oh,
this website isn't really useful to me.
but yeah, so another thing is
the monitoring and like automated
recovery part where we got to build
a robust tool mechanism where we
are continuously monitoring what
is going on with our website.
And can have smart automated
systems to detect when there is
like peak traffic and automatically
scale your website up or down.
so moving on to the next one, we
can, at this point, I feel it's,
in right time to dive into what
is a microservice architecture.
so when you talk about cloud native
microservices, it's thrown around a lot.
Why, you may ask, right?
So in a microservices setup, an
application is broken down into Extremely
small and like loosely coupled services
that kind of magically just work together.
there's a lot of work behind
obviously like this intermingling
of all these different modules
and microservices, right?
and each of the service should
be designed to perform just as
like extremely specific function.
It can be as simple as Oh, add
these two integers and spit out
the output and transfer that
information to another service.
this way each service is designed to
perform a specific function and it
makes it extremely easy to develop,
test it, deploy it, and also debug it.
debugging it is easy 'cause I know when
something fails, which particular service
to go to, to actually go and debug.
so yeah, so like you, you could see,
the benefits, on, on, on a screen.
so independent deployment, right?
So services can be updated without
affecting like the entire system.
Scalable, right?
So like I mentioned in some of the
previous slides, you can scale up and
scale down your service like individual
services, based on the traffic that's
coming in or the volume of users or the
volume of the compute that you need.
you can say your application has 10
microservices and that one of your
microservices is, facing a lot of intake
or like volume is like rising too much.
You could specifically just
scale that single microservice
and you should be good.
you're saving money, like all
the other services, but not
unnecessarily scaling it up.
yeah.
And finally, the third one
is like isolation, right?
If one specific service fails,
you don't, it doesn't really bring
your whole system down unless
it's like a core service, right?
Where, for which users come and use a
website, but yeah, isolation is like
super crucial to like maintaining
the overall system resilience.
but yeah, so yeah, in the, so in
a moment I'll show you like a code
example, that kind of demonstrates how
a basic microservices is implemented.
I'll talk about how these independent
service interact and support like
a resilient architecture So as you
could see on the screen, this is a
super simple microsoft Architecture I
implemented using like java and spring
boot on this slide we have a basic code
snippet that kind of Illustrates how
to create like a restful service So in
this example, the greeting controller
that you see here, it's annotated
with at rest controller, which kind of
indicates that it'll handle web requests.
Now, for example, web requests, as in
when a user, say clicks on a button and
API is called to the backend, right?
So this is the controller
that kind of handles that.
so inside this controller, like
another annotation called at auto
wired, annotation to like inject.
Greeting service, which is responsible for
all the business logic so essentially you
know the forward slash greet annotation
maps like the http get request to the
greet endpoint And essentially when this
endpoint is hit The get greeting, method
is called and essentially this method
returns a simple greeting message called.
Oh, Hey, oh, hello cloud native world.
yeah, so essentially what I want to
explain here is by separating the
controller from like the service
layer We cannot achieve a loose
coupling between the components And
this design not only like simplifies
development and testing, but also
reinforces like fault isolation, right?
yeah, just a basic example, just
to give you a rough idea of how
Microsoft actually looks like.
but yeah, moving on.
so yeah, so the next concept that I really
want to talk about is containerization.
So whenever you're developing
cloud native applications, one of
the thing you should remember is.
I'm building it as a microservice
from the ground up and the
next thing is containerization.
And what I mean by that is like a
method of packaging an application
along with all of its dependencies
into a single self contained unit
is essentially called a container.
so that.
And the purpose of this is we ensure
that the application runs reliably
regardless of where it's deployed, right?
and yeah, so like I mentioned on
the screen, some of the benefits
is like consistency, isolation,
and like portability and docker.
You guys would have come across
docker a lot where you would have
come across terms like dockerization,
which, which basically means that.
I essentially am placing a service
in a closed container something like
docker along with all the dependencies
that the container That the service
needs so that and upgrades happen
automatically to all the dependencies.
So I don't need to worry about Oh, what
if this dependency is not upgraded yet
and it fails my system So those are
some things that I wouldn't worry about
if I docker my dockerize my system.
So yeah, so moving on just a super
quick like demo of What I mean by
containerization a microservice using
docker So essentially step one create a
microservice right of your cloud native
applications step two If you need to
dockerize it so on this slide, you'll
see a docker file that kind of defines
The steps to build our container, right?
So essentially you'll see open JDK image
Which is essentially a Java application
And a work directory command to set the
working directory of the container The
jar file which is essentially all the
dependencies that are needed You'll see
the expose function informs docker like
which port the application will use
and in this case port 8080 and finally
the entry point for it to run, right?
and essentially This is the, the most
common file of a docker container.
And we would need this to actually run
the application and essentially how
you would run it is just do a build
command on this, which essentially call
a docker build and greeting service,
which will basically create a docker
image called tagged greeting service.
And when you run this, when you'd
say something like, Oh, docker run
greeting service, it starts a container.
and it essentially runs the service.
So in the interest of time
moving on, so then, with our
Microsoft is now containerized.
So the next step is how do we
manage and orchestrate this
containers at scale, right?
so this is where Kubernetes
comes into picture and you
may ask, what is Kubernetes?
So kubernetes is a really powerful
orchestration platform that kind
of automates deployment scaling
and like management, right?
so we need we definitely need automatic
scaling for all our cloud native
applications because kubernetes can
dynamically adjust like the number
of Instances that are running it can
monitor the health and like self heal
based on if a certain instances up
or down And essentially it has this
whole like functionality to efficiently
resource, manage different resources.
so yeah, it's really different,
important that we use Kubernetes along
with, Doc, Docker and microservices.
And essentially all we have
Kubernetes, like you could see
is we essentially have pods where
we have these containers running.
And essentially, there are various
commands that kubernetes has
which will help us like deploy
and maintain these services
so moving on to this slide where
we'll focus on like the automation
strategies to enhance kind of system
resilience so So for any cloud native
application, we need to focus a lot on
like system resilience and building CICD
pipelines, like automate testing and
run your build through a CICD pipeline.
So that's, so as soon as you deploy
some kind of code, we need an automated
service that kind of builds a jar
out of the service and then runs a
bunch of automated, tests around it
and make sure it is production ready.
Without this we can deploy a service
and without any testing involved.
What if it just breaks it, right?
So that'll just mess up the whole service.
So we don't want that.
So we'll have to build out CI CD pipelines
for this And also we need a bunch of like
self healing infrastructure that kind
of auto scales Based on load restarts
whenever the service is done so like you
could see on the screen, there are a lot
of monitoring integration systems like
Prometheus, Grafana, and, ELK stack,
on Amazon for like proactive alerts.
so yeah, so moving on.
So this is like a super high level of
how a CI CD pipeline might look right.
If, if you guys use Git in, in your,
daily work, you would notice that
we have like several branches, main.
so whenever you want to create
a pull request, you push a code.
And once you like, do submit
your CI CD pipelines take over.
They run a bunch of like
unit tests, automated tests.
if it's, if it's a mobile
platform, it generates an APK.
And it does a bunch of like screenshots.
So these are really important,
to make sure none of it breaks.
And like on the screen, there
are a set of commands, this is
essentially a settings file.
So there are a lot of jobs that
are run and you can modify it to
such an extent that you can run
your application on any service.
For example, you can run it on Ubuntu,
you can run it on like a Windows or a
Mac and make sure your application runs
properly on like different services.
Moving on, we will discuss how
integrating monitoring and self healing
capabilities helps the resilience
of cloud native systems, right?
so yeah, so monitoring
different metrics is useful.
just cause we can see how our
system is CPU memory and the network
utilization, And we want to make sure
none of this goes beyond a point.
and if it does, we need to have things
in place to make sure our instances
or our containers aren't overloaded.
So we have like several tools, and set
up called Prometheus for collecting
different metrics and like alerting our
SRAs or developers just to make sure
that if a service is being overloaded, we
got to go in and do something to fix it.
and Grafana is pretty useful for like
visualization, like dashboarding as well.
yeah, but yeah, so moving on.
So let's quickly talk about, like
a real world case study, right?
so let's look at say, like a
major e commerce platform, like
Amazon that kind of migrated
to a cloud native architecture.
This is.
Super hypothetical.
so let's say initially the phased a lot
of like frequent downtime like scalability
issues during like peak load times And
like really slow deployment process
But once they adopted like a cloud
native approach, they re architected
the whole system into microservices
Containerized their applications
using docker And implemented like
a robust CI CD pipeline along with
monitoring using Prometheus and Grafana.
So this way Some of the lessons that they
learned was like, oh building resilience
from like ground up is super essential
for maintaining high availability,
especially in a dynamic cloud environment.
And obviously continuously monitoring
and like feedback loops are crucial for
ongoing improvements and like a quick
recovery from unexpected failures.
So this case study definitely underscores
like the importance of integrating these
practices to build systems to make your
cloud native application like scalable.
Yeah.
so yeah, so that brings us to
the end of this presentation.
to quickly recap, we explored the
fundamental principles of like
cloud native, resilience, right?
So including the benefits of
microservices, containerization using
Docker, the automation using CI and CD
pipelines and monitoring using Grafana.
yeah, thanks for coming to my talk.