Welcome, everyone.
This is Vinod Manamala, and
I'm a senior data scientist.
Today, I'll show you like how AI
powered digital twins can transform
the manufacturing operations.
I'll also share the practical
solutions from real factories that
I saved like millions of dollars.
Now, let's start by looking
at what we'll cover today.
So here's our plan for today.
we'll start with why digital
twins often fail in factories.
Then I'll share five patterns
that actually work, supported
by a real, use case study.
And, we'll also end with the practical
tips you can use immediately.
So first let's, examine why so
many digital twin projects don't
deliver the expected value.
most digital twins fail in
factories for simple reasons, right?
so they can't handle the messy
reality of manufacturing.
That's the first thing.
And they don't adapt
to changing conditions.
And they also ignore, sensor uncertainty.
And, they try to model everything at once.
And, and they also break
when, the network fails.
So these problems cost like
real money when production
stops or the quality drops.
Now let's look at the first
winning pattern that actually
solved many of these challenges.
The first winning pattern is what
I call the even first architecture.
So instead of tracking, fixed dates,
here we track, every event that happens
and calculate the states as needed.
So this records complete history and helps
you trace problems back to their source.
In a chip factory, this solved,
major headaches with tracking wafers
through rework processes and saved,
countless hours of troubleshooting.
And, on the next slide, I will examine
how AI can be taught to understand
time in manufacturing processes.
The second pattern is AI
that truly understands time.
In manufacturing, different time periods
matter depending on what you're making.
Our system uses special neural
networks that learn which time
periods matter most for each process.
This improved prediction accuracy by
27 percent and spotted problems hours
or days earlier, giving operators time
to fix issues before causing, scrap.
So this is really important.
And now, next, let's look at how
we can make these models adapt
automatically to changing conditions.
So the third pattern here,
which is basically the models
that adapt automatically.
Actually solves a big
problem with AI in factories.
Knowing when to learn
and when to hold steady.
That is the, that is a big problem here.
Our solution adjusts
learning rates automatically.
During stable production, it increases the
learning to catch these subtle changes.
And during unstable periods, it increases
learning to avoid overreactions.
So this reduced the false alarm by 62
percent and kept the models accurate by 3.
4 times longer without, manual retraining.
Now, let's talk about how to deal
with another major challenge.
basically it's the uncertain sensor data.
The fourth pattern here
addresses the sensor reliability.
The factory sensors get dirty,
drift out of calibration or fail.
And our approach here is very
honest about uncertainty.
The system here calculates the, confidence
levels for every prediction, and tells
the operators when, data looks suspicious.
When the data is questionable, it falls
back on physics based rules, and this
cuts the false alarm by 45 percent
while catching the actual problem.
Now, let's look into the, fifth pattern,
which addresses how manufacturing happens
across multiple timeframes simultaneously.
The fifth pattern here, recognizes
the manufacturing that happens
at many timescales at once.
Our solution here tracks processes at
multiple timescales, like simultaneously,
and, this found problems that would
be invisible otherwise, right?
in one factory, we discovered morning
temperature fluctuations were slowly
degrading, a small catalyst over weeks.
And, the system can connect a
brief even from, weeks, that
happened, weeks ago to a quality
problem that's happening right now.
this is pretty, amazing.
And, now let's see, like, how these
patterns work together in, in a real
semiconductor factory, in a real use case.
So let me show you how these
patterns worked in a real semi,
a real semiconductor factory.
So their problem was
handling the wafer rework.
so when wafers need to repeat like
certain process steps, and, they found
this was like really problematic.
So their first, digital twin actually
lost track of wafers and got confused.
So we implemented like an event
based system with AI for like
defect detection, anomaly detection
and process relationship mapping.
So this resulted in 94 percent accuracy
predicting, reworks that were needed.
And also like 12 percent
yield improvement and also 4.
2 million in annual savings.
Now let's take a closer look at how,
AI actually worked in this factory.
So here the, AI had two key components.
First is the defect detection using
the computer vision, which analyzed
the wafer images with almost 99.
2 percent accuracy for, critical defects.
Second, the process relationship,
the process relationship mapping.
Connected over, 1, 200 process parameters.
So this revealed, cost effect
relationships nobody knew existed.
And, the engineers who were working
there could ask, what would happen
if you change this temperature
and get realistic predictions
before making, the actual changes.
Now, let's talk about some practical
implementation tips, starting
with how to handle, all these
data, these systems generate.
The factories generate, enormous
data, often terabytes daily, right?
you can't keep it all, but you
can't just delete it either too.
our approach here is keep high
frequency data for 24 hours.
and save hourly summaries for months.
The smart part is automatically,
detecting and preserving the anomalies
while compressing the, the normal
data when nothing happened, generally.
And this reduces the storage needs by
almost, by 78%, while keeping 95 percent
of the analytical value from those data.
So the next implementation challenge
we need to address is the, the network
reliability in these factory environments.
And, let's see, like, how we can
handle these, network problems.
The factory networks, they fail
constantly due to, equipment
interference and maintenance.
and maintenance is the biggest
problem, in, day to day activities.
our solution here, what we did
was, It puts the intelligence at
the edge, next to the equipment.
So the edge devices are like, they
run lightweight AI models, and
they work independently during the
outages or, during the maintenance.
So when the network reruns or when they
come back online, they automatically
sync with the, the central system.
So this happened in a chemical plant
and we achieved like almost 99.
97 percent uptime despite all
these frequent network issues.
Be it like, the equipment
interference or a maintenance process.
Now let's also discuss how to keep the
AI models performing well over the time.
So basically here, We're going to talk
about the ML model lifecycle management.
So the AI models in the factories degrade
over the time as processes change.
So our system continuously monitors
model performance, and also it detects
drifts in the models automatically.
So the new models are first tested
in something we call it as the shadow
mode, before gradually taking control.
So this reduced the, by doing this
we reduce the engineering time.
on model maintenance by almost 67%.
And extended the model life almost by 3.
4 times with almost consistent performance
across all the product changes.
Now let's look at how the
physical loss can make those AI
predictions like more reliable.
the manufacturing must
follow like, physical loss.
You can't create or destroy
mass or energy, right?
So here our system combines like AI
flexibility with physical constraints.
So this ensures the predictions
obey the real world rules, even
in conditions never seen before.
In a chemical reactor, for
example, this approach reduced
the impossible predictions by 94
percent 94 percent and improved the
performance in new situations by 72%.
making this operation really safe.
So now let me wrap up with key
takeaways from, today's presentation.
to summarize, the key takeaways
here, the basically use even based
architecture for complex manufacturing.
and the second key takeaway
is like implement AI that
understands time and uncertainty.
Third key takeaway is like build
systems that adapt automatically, right?
And the fourth key takeaway is like
design for real world challenges like
network failures that we spoke about.
And the fifth key takeaway is
measure success by business impact
and not by technical metrics.
And also start with a focus problem
and then you can expand on it.
So these are my key takeaways
and thank you for your attention.
And I'm happy to take questions.
on my, using my email ID, you can
connect with, also you can connect
with me on my LinkedIn profile
that you can see in the bottom.
so I'm happy, we met on this
Conf, 42 conference and I'm
hoping to catch up with you guys.
Thank you.