Hey everyone, this is Srinidhar
Lakkaraju and I'm going to present
AI powered dynamic risk scoring
for e commerce transaction.
This presentation introduces an
innovative framework for dynamic
risk assessment in e commerce fraud.
detecting, using machine learning and
advanced machine learning techniques.
We will also explore how combining
reinforcement learning, Bayesian network,
and real time processing architecture
addresses the modern fraud detection
challenges and significantly improves
the accuracy of detection while
enhancing the customer experiences.
As e commerce reaches
unprecedented scale, close to 5.
7 trillion dollars in e commerce
volume globally in 2024.
The fraudsters have been
deploying increasingly
sophisticated attack strategies.
The fraud attempts have
been increased to 1.
8 percent of overall online revenue.
The Redistone Static Square scoring
systems have become dangerously
inadequate, particularly In the face
of a staggering 307 percent surge
in account takeover attacks, while
businesses invest heavily in fraud
prevention, allocating close to 15
20 per customer, they face a critical
challenge maintaining robust security.
without compromising the seamless shopping
experience that modern customers demand.
And also we have seen close to 6.
4 billion losses in card not present
fraud across the major online platforms.
So our approach is the dynamic
approach to the e commerce security.
So we want to have four
different phases of it.
The first being the multi layer
validation in which each transaction
is passed through interconnected
AI validation gates, which combines
with the rule based checks along
with the machine learning analysis.
We use the advanced ML models where we are
processing the 3, 700 data signals in real
time, which includes transaction patterns.
It's user behavior.
and merchant risk profiles.
We want to do real time behavior analysis
where we want to see the advanced
device fingerprinting and network
analysis to detect suspicious patterns.
VPN usage and the bot
activities within milliseconds.
And we want to continuously, evolve.
So we want to have a self optimized
models that automatically adapt
to the new frauds tactics.
while learning from the transaction
outcomes and emerging threat patterns.
Our cutting edge architecture delivers
enterprise grade fraud prevention
through three synchronized layers.
Each component is engineered
for maximum performance.
seamlessly processing massive
transaction volumes while maintaining
strict latency requirements.
This robust foundation enables real
time risk assessment while automatically
adapting new to new threats, setting up
new standards for e commerce security.
So these three layers are
the data ingestion layer.
In this layer, we process over
42, 000 transactions per second.
with sub 200 milliseconds, ensuring
a real time fraud detection at scale.
The AI ML processing
engine, which powers 1.
7 simultaneously user session
through intelligent load balancing
and automated resource optimization.
And the third one is a
dynamic threshold management.
We execute 872 smart threshold
adjustments hourly, which allows us
to continuously adapt to the emerging.
Fraud patterns.
The reinforcement learning
implementation is network aware.
It has a network of strategies which
is distributed system of 200, sorry,
2847 nodes which can process close
to 47, 000 transactions per second.
The sophisticated architecture
has dramatically improved There is
detection accuracy by 42 percent.
The advanced feature engineering
can go through a deep analysis
of 3847 unique transaction
characteristics or features which
allow us to detect the fraud with 99.
4 percent accuracy Our system analyzes
the monitoring pattern across 847
distinct feature to identify suspicious
activity with unprecedented precision.
The optimized risk reward function.
Our holistic reward system
balances multiple critical metrics
including the false positive.
The fraud detection, customer
satisfaction, and network performance.
This balanced approach has driven
us a greater percent of improvement
in our overall system effectiveness.
The combination of vision
network architecture.
delivers industry leading fraud
detection by combining massive
scale real time processing with a
sophisticated probabilistic model.
The system not only processes transactions
at unprecedented speed, but also
continuously adapts to new fraud patterns,
maintaining sub millisecond latency
while achieving a very good So the real
time processing is able to handle 47,
000 concurrent transactions per second.
With being up, using the 10847 distributed
nodes, we try to utilize the project
interference, which kind of leverages
these, interconnect decision nodes.
managing the 12, 647 dynamic
probabilistic relationships.
We have the feature processing
where we are able to analyze the
847 risk indicators in millisecond
to achieve to a fraud detection.
This allows us to have real time
updates as well where we are
adjusting all this 847k risk,
indicators, and the probabilities.
per second to have an understanding or
create a base for emerging patterns.
And then, the way we process these
risk variables transactions using the
advanced entropy reduction, we are able
to identify the emerging patterns as well.
The implementation of our AI powered
dynamic risk score system has delivered
exceptional improvements across
all critical performance metrics.
Most notable, we achieved a dramatic
33 percent reduction in false
positive rates, dropping from 2.
4 percent to 1.
42%, while simultaneously increasing
our fraud detection rate by
33 percent to reach industry
leading 99 percent accuracy.
Customer experience has been
remarkable enhancements as well.
The satisfaction score surging
from 30 percent to 75 percent
the improvement in the partial Attribute
or this improvement is partially because
of the processing time Where we have
reduced our processing average time to
27 Close to now 600 milliseconds and
Also have the reliability or the system
validity to be close to four nines
Ensuring that our service is active for
our customers and it's not going down
We have seen a challenge with
our data imbalance since these
fraudulence data are very or have
an extreme balance where only 0.
12 to 0.
27 transactions are fraudulent.
So making it much more difficult to
inherently identify or detect any action.
To solve that, we implemented a
sophisticated broad line smooth algorithm
combined with adaptive synthetic
sampling to balance data representation.
So we intelligently re sample the 3.
8 million transaction hourly to achieve
a near perfect balance instead of
having a data imbalanced where we
have 51 percent legitimate cases and
we have 48 percent fraudulent cases.
While doing this allows us to
increase our fraud detection accuracy.
By 48 percent for the minority
cases while Maintaining the
exception low false positive rate 2.
3 percent.
The real time processing architecture
enables us to do high speed processing
Able to have massive data handling
provide real time updates and also
increase the overall performance
of the system we are able to now
process close to 2, 000 concurrent
transactions per second with industry
leading Sub to 20 millisecond response
time, ensuring the seamless customer
experience, able to efficiently manage 4.
2 terabytes of transaction data per
hour across distributed nodes while
maintaining the enterprise grade 4.
9 system reliability.
The advanced materialized
view architecture.
Refreshes every, 200 milliseconds
or close to 200 milliseconds,
delivering an 84% reduction in query
latency for instant fraud detection.
This allows us to have the real
time updates and allows us to real
time call, call the fraud data.
We have able to have, receive, or
cut the processing time by 67%.
While delivering a boost in the
transaction and throughput capacity.
So that's a major improvement
in our performance
The model drift management.
We continuously monitor all
the features across these 847
model parameters Crossing 2.
8 million predictions per hour.
We do a real time evaluation which
allows us to achieve 99 accuracy in
the drift detection with immediate
response to the performance regression.
We process these distributions across
different sliding window anywhere
from one hour to 90 days which allows
us to have more defined path or more
defined way to identify and define
the accuracy and also detect the
false positive or the fraudulent data.
We also do A B testing, where we
utilize the 12 parallel valuation
groups, each of them processing 2.
7 million transactions daily, which
allows us to come up with the newer
detection and enable us to do the
deployments in both A B fashion.
In conclusion, our revolutionary
AI powered risk scoring system
has transformed the e commerce
detection by processing 4.
2 terabytes of transaction data.
hourly with 99 percent
accuracy in drift detection.
By combining reinforcement learning
with Bayesian network, we have created
a solution that not only detects frauds
at a very unprecedented precision,
but also scales dynamically to handle
growing transaction volumes while
maintaining a superior performance matrix.
We're able to do an adaptive security,
where we are able to advanced Risk
assessment system in which you can
automatically calibrate the security
levels keeping the system up and
also reducing the customer friction
We have improved the accuracy.
So we have achieved 47 increase
in the fraud detection precision
while maintaining a low 0.
3 percent false positive rate Which
protects both the merchants and
the customers We have enhanced the
transaction processing time to sub 220
milliseconds response time and handled
1, 892 concurrent transactions with
close to zero degradation in the system.
And our system is future ready
in the sense where we are able to
self optimize the system monitors.
monitor the 3847 features across
these 87847 model parameters, ensuring
us to continuously adapt to the new
emerging fraud patterns, allowing us
to keep in sync with the newer fraud
patterns that have been emerging
and able to take action accordingly.
Thank you all.
Hope you like the presentation.