Hello everyone.
My name is Tuka.
I'm a software engineer at Microsoft.
For more than 20 years, I have
worked on large scale platform and
infrastructure systems, especially
systems where distributed workflows
and reliability are non-negotiable.
Today I want to talk about
interoperability by design
for cloud native workflows.
Here is the promise.
If we design interoperability as
an architectural strategy, not
a late stage integration task,
we can reduce complexity, avoid
lock-in, and make workflow systems
easier to operate at scale.
We will start with a problem landscape.
Then I will introduce a practical
five plan framework, and finally,
we will walk through implementation,
guidance, and outcomes.
In this slide I'm going, I'm gonna
talk about the cloud native landscape.
The cloud native development has become
the default for modern enterprises.
Containers, microservices, and
distributed systems are now the
foundation for buildings scalable
applications, and Kubernetes has emerged
as the defacto orchestration standard.
Across much of the industry, this
shift brought major benefits.
It enables rapid deployment.
It supports horizontal scaling
and it abstracts infrastructure
so teams can move faster.
But Cloud Native also introduced a
new class of coordination challenges.
A single product, it
actually dos of services.
You must coordinate work
across service boundaries.
You must track state and retries
across multiple systems, and you
must re, and you must reason about
a workflow that spans APIs, events
skews, and multiple run times.
So the question becomes how do
we keep these workflows portable?
Observable and reliable
across environments.
In the next slide, we'll talk
about challenges of fragmentation.
In practice, cloud native
ecosystems often become fragmented.
I want to highlight three
common PLA patterns.
First is vendor locking
organizations becomes dependent.
Proprie propriety APIs
or managed services.
Over the time, migration becomes
costly and complex, and switching
decisions become constrained.
Second incompatible tooling, different
platform use, different workflow
engines, orchestration tools and
data formats teams, and up building
custom adapters and glue code just
to connect essential components.
The third one is siloed workflows.
Workflows remains isolated across
environments, across clusters,
across clouds, or across teams.
That isolation prevents unified
observability, consistent governance,
and seamless end-to-end data flow.
The net effect is that engineering efforts
shifts away from delivering features and
toward maintaining integration depth.
In this slide I'll talk about
why interoperability matters.
Interop interoperability matters
because it is one of the few
strategies that systematically
reduce this integration depth.
If tool and services share standardized
contracts, and we eliminate the need
for constant custom integration,
operational overhead goes down, and
teams can focus on delivering business
value rather than maintaining adapters.
Interoperability also enables portability.
Workflows can move across cloud providers
and environments more predictably.
The flexibility improves decision making
teams can optimize for cost, performance,
compliance, and reasonable requirements
without rewriting the entire platform.
So instead of treating interoperability
as a connector problem, we treat it as
a first class architectural property.
In this slide let's talk about
the five plane framework To make
interoperability, practical, I use a
simple model, the five plane framework.
Think of these as five layers where you
can define clear contracts and choose
standard standards inter intentionally.
Plan one, which is workflow definition
plan two, that is execution and
state plan three is integration.
Plan four is observability and lineage.
And the plane.
Five.
Waste packaging and deployment.
If you design each plane explicitly,
workflows become more portable, more
measurable, and easier to evolve
in the slides.
Let's talk about workflow definition.
Plane.
The workflow definition plan
established how workflows are
declared versioned and shared.
This is the foundation.
If the definition is not portable, you'll
pay the cost in every downstream plan.
The key idea is here
declarative specification.
Instead of encoding workflow logic
in a runtime specific format, you
define it in a portable structure.
Standards that help include.
The CNCF serverless Workflow Specification
for Workflow definition, open AI for
services, inter service interfaces,
and Jason Schema for validation
and contract inform enforcement.
This plan is also about worsening
discipline use contract first design.
Treat workflow definition as
artifacts in source control.
Manage schema evolution intentionally
so that change does not break
interoperability in short, define
workflows in a way that can be shared and
executed without translation overhead.
Let's talk about execution and state plan.
The execution and state plan manages
the runtime lifecycle of workflows.
This include orchestration, durable
state, checkpointing, and recovery.
In dis in distributed systems, failures
are normal, but interoperability
requires that workflow can still
behave predictably when system
fail, retry, or partially complete.
So you need to, so you need
durable state management.
You need checkpointing.
So workflows can pause and resume safely.
And you need principles like exactly
one execution semantic where appropriate
or well-defined item potency pattern,
where exactly once is not feasible,
standard and conventions in even
driven systems such as cloud events
for structures, even structure.
Help define help different
engines and services interpret
state transition consistently.
So when this plane is designed
well, workflow recover gracefully
and the system becomes silent
across infrastructure boundaries.
In this slide, let's talk
about integration plane.
The integration plane defines how
heterogeneous systems communicate
across services, APIs, and data sources.
This is where fragmentation
typically hurts the most.
Interoperability here starts with
the standard contracts for events.
Cloud events provide a consistent
envelope and metadata model.
For a synchronous interfaces,
a sync API can define message.
Message driven interactions.
For restful services, open ai.
Open API defines requests response.
At conventions, then you apply
consistent connectivity patterns.
Services meshes provide informed service
to service communication behaviors,
security and policy enforcement.
The API Gateways provide a
controlled entry point for
translation, routing, and governance.
The result is fewer, one of the
adapters and less time spent
building custom connectors because
systems can speak a shared language.
Let's talk about OB
observability and Lineage plane.
The observability and lineage
plane provides unified visibility
across distributed workflows.
Interoperability is difficult
to sustain if you cannot see
what is happening end to end.
A strong foundation here is standardized
tracing metrics and logging.
Open telemetry is a widely adopted
approach for traces, metric, metrices,
and logs and W three C. Trace context
help propagate context across systems, so
telemetry can be correlated even across
different vendors and run times lineage.
Add another dimension.
It captures the journey
of data through workflow.
Through actual workflow stages, what
produced it, what transformed it, where
it moved, and how it was consumed.
That matters for compliance,
debugging, and optimization.
When observability and lineage are
standardized, teams can reduce resolution,
improve reliability, make workflow
behavior audible across environments.
Packaging and deployment plane.
The fifth plane is
packaging and deployment.
This plane ensures the artifact deploy
consistently across environments,
across environment development,
basically staging and production,
and potentially across clouds.
Container standards matters here.
The OCI specification provide
portability for container images
across any compliant runtime.
Then you need consistent
deployment artifacts and workflow.
Helm charts can package
and Kubernetes deployments.
Customize overlays can manage
environment specific customization,
and GitHub's approaches can drive
repeatable, declarative deployments.
This plane also benefits from
immutable infrastructure principles.
If deployments are reproducible
and rollbacks are predictable,
operation, operational risk, decrease.
So packaging and deployment are not just
ops, they're, they are a core part of
interoperable work, workflow design.
The CNCF standards across the five planes.
The CNCF ecosystem provides a key
building blocks for vendor neutral design.
Kubernetes API provide a
consistent control plane model.
Open telemetry supports
standardized observability cloud
events, helps standardize event
play, even payload structure.
The OCI enables portable
packaging and workflow oriented
standards and project support.
Portable orchestration patterns.
The main point is not that
any tool solves everything.
The point is that standard
reduce frictions and help your
architecture remain compatible
with the broad ecosystem over time.
Let's talk about performance benchmarks.
Let's talk about, first,
let's talk about outcomes.
Interoperability is not.
Not only about governance, it can lead
to measurable performance improvements
when API contracts are standardized,
translation overhead between components
can drop, that can reduce end-to-end
workflow latency when even formats
are consistent with cloud events
and native end time integration.
Even processing throughput can
improve significantly and when
observability is shared across systems.
You can eliminate redundant
agents and duplicate pipelines.
Improving resource efficiency and
cost important note is treat these
as representative outcomes that
depend on architecture, workload,
and implementation details.
The practical takeaway is that
interoperability is often a
performance and efficiency multiplier,
not just a standard checkbox.
In this slide, let's talk
about reliability, outcomes.
Reliability improves when
workflows have standard execution
and state management principles.
With durable state and checkpointing,
workflows can resume from last
known safe point after failure.
Automatic recovery and failure mechanisms.
Component outages do not
necessarily translate into
end-to-end workflow outages.
Cross region replication pattern
can support continuity and
better recovery objectives.
Interoperability can also
support multi-cloud consistency.
If OB observability, state conventions
and contract remain consistent,
workflow behavior can be made more
predictable across environments.
The key message is standardized contrast
contracts, reduce ambiguity, and ambiguity
is often the enemy of reliability.
Architectural blue blueprint,
here's the reference blueprint
that ties the planes together.
Start with an API gateway
as a unified entry point.
It can handle protocol translation,
routing, and rate limiting.
Then use a service mesh for
consistent service to service,
communication, security, identity
policy, and traffic management.
For even driven systems, use a cloud
events compliant messaging backbone.
Workflow orchestrator connect
through standardized APIs.
State management uses distributed
cloud agnostic storage patterns and
observability is integrated end to end
using open telemetry instrumentation.
This blueprint is intentionally modular.
You can swap implementation without
changing contracts when standards
are designed in two planes.
Implementation, roadmap.
Roadmap, how do you implement this is.
This in real environments.
Two parts.
Existing systems and greenfield
systems for existing systems.
Start with an audit.
Compare current workflow
definition against standards.
Identity integration points where
standardized contrast can read.
Replace bespoke adapters.
Migrate incrementally, plane by plane.
So you reduce risk and implementer
observability early so you can
measure progress and detect
regression for greenfield systems.
Adopt the five plane
framework from day one.
Select standard aligned tools, design
portability into contracts, and build
observability and lineage in the, in
from the start, not as an afterthought.
In this slide, we can talk
about the key takeaways.
Let's summarize the key takeaway.
Interoperability is a core
architectural strategy, not a feature.
The five plan framework
makes interoperability,
actionable, and miserable.
C-C-N-C-F standard support,
vendor neutrality and ecosystem
compatibility and contract for design.
Contract first design enables
modular pluggable systems that
evolve without constant rights.
When you apply these principle
consistently, teams can improve
scalability, reliability, and
operational efficiency, especially
as workflow become more distributed.
Thank you so much for
your time and attention.
I hope this framework helps you design
more interoperable cloud native workflows.
I'm happy to connect and discuss patterns,
tradeoffs, and implementation approaches.
Thank you.
I.