Hello everyone.
Welcome to conference
42, cloud Native 2026.
I'm Shadi.
I'm an alumni of University
of Southern California.
Today I'll present my research on
behavioral analytics for realtime
fraud prevention in financial industry.
The research was primarily focused on
how intelligent signatures and adaptive
analytical frameworks are revolutionizing
the current world risk space.
This work was also recently published in
SAR Council General of Multidisciplinary.
Let's start with the evolution of
fraud detection in financial industry.
So traditionally, parameter based
systems relied heavily on static
thresholds and predetermined rules.
As an example of a rule, if a
transaction exceeded a certain amount
or occurred in an unusual location,
then it would trigger an alert.
These systems, however, were only
able to achieve 45% detection rates
while generating false alerts close
to 37% of the time, and with an
average response time of 95 seconds.
Fast forward, if you look at the
modern fraud prevention systems, which
have completely shifted from this
approach, these systems currently
create dynamic user behavior profiles
by continuously analyzing navigational.
Patterns across individual
digital platforms.
They do capture device fingerprints
that uniquely identify hardware
configurations and transactional sequences
that reveal user spending habits.
This enabled financial institutions to
detect anomalies earlier with greater
precision achieving 87% detection rate
with close to 7% false alerts and.
The average response
time of eight seconds.
This isn't just incremental improvement,
but it's a shift of the industry from
a reactive approach to a proactive one.
Let's look a little bit deep to
understand how these systems exactly work.
Behavioral sign signatures are built from
four primary dimensions, starting with,
we have the navigational patterns here.
The systems track through.
How a user moves through digital
interface, like analyzing
their click sequences page flow
preferences and interaction time.
So the idea here is to basically capture
how uniquely a user navigates, and this
creates a distinctive digital footprint.
Second, we have the keystroke dynamics.
Here, advanced algorithms are employed
to capture typing rhythms such as how
long a user presses a particular key, and
what is the flight time between different
key strokes and any error correction
patterns that basically format distinctive
biometric signature for a particular user.
Third, we have device
fingerprinting, which basically.
Is a module where the users.
Comprehensive profile of
device characteristics such
as the operating system.
What's the browser configuration, what's
the screen resolution and any installed
plugins are checked to basically
evaluate if this transaction is coming
from any of the trusted devices that
the user has had transacted earlier.
Finally, we have the
transaction sequences here.
The system analyzes.
The user spending patterns like merchant
preferences and transaction timing
and also the amount distributions.
The idea is basic here is basically
to, by capturing these, the system
tries to identify if there's any
activity that is deviating from
the user's previous behavior.
And this slide is the initial slide
that we discussed on the evolution
of the fraud prevention in financial
industry just to highlight the,
using the latest approach in, in.
In fraud prevention, the detection rates
have come up from 45 to 87%, and then the
false alerts reduced all the way to 7%.
This basically means the industry
or the institutions are reducing
the friction to customers, so not
not flagging too many transaction
and enhancing the user experience.
The response time is drastically reduced
from 95 seconds to eight seconds.
And a key thing to note here is
basically the cost savings that
have gone up from 2020 2% to 76%.
This demonstrates that
systems aren't just effective.
They're basically becoming more
efficient, reducing manual review
requirements while improving the outcome.
Now let's understand a little bit
of how the framework is set up
for establishing these systems.
The analytical frameworks that power
these sort of systems are basically
multi-layered at the foundation.
Machine learning algorithms continuously
learn from transaction data,
supervised learning techniques like.
Decision trees, random forest and
gradient boosting algorithms establish
classification parameters by looking
at the label data that contains both
legitimate and fraudulent examples.
As a second layer, we have the anomaly
detection where unsupervised learning
algorithms continuously evaluate
emerging patterns against established
here, such as various clustering.
Algorithms and various
clustering techniques that
are used to identify subtle.
Irregularities that might signal any
sophisticated attacks designed to bypass
their traditional detection systems.
And finally, we have deep learning
algorithms like L SDMs and CNNs that
basically look for any sequential patterns
that deviate from the user behavior.
And they're also very good at
looking at spatial relationships,
especially with multidimensional data.
And these systems also incorporate
something called Shap, which is basically
an explain, an explainability module,
which basically explains why an algorithm
had decided with a specific outcome.
This basically enables analysts
and also business to a deep dive
and see what exactly is happening
with a particular user or where
the deviation seems to happen.
This slide talks about more on the
contextual intelligence because algorithms
alone aren't enough for adding context for
aren't enough to analyze user behavior and
add and adding context actually enhances
the approach More so modern systems
deploy the contextual intelligence,
which basically looks the user profile.
As a whole, rather than examining isolated
data points to start with, for example,
we have the location consistency here.
The system looks for the
location where the location and
against user movement patterns.
The system, for example, flags something
which is impossible tra to travel like.
If a transaction originates in New
York and the follow followed by
another transaction that originates
in London in just 30 minutes later
while accounting for both legitimate
travel patterns and VPN usage.
Secondly, we have environmental
context, which basically looks
at a user transacting time
zones, the connection types, and.
System basically looks for any sort
of wifi network or if the login is,
if the logins or the transactions
are originating from an UN from an
unfamiliar IP address in high risk region.
Finally, the device identifiers
that basically leverage advanced
fingerprinting to track trusted devices
and flag unauthorized access from
unfamiliar hardware configurations.
This multidimensional approach
basically improves precision while
reducing the false positives.
This slide talks about the real
time architecture that's needed
to enable this sort of monitoring
and flagging any unusual activity.
So it all starts with data collection
layer, which continuously captures
behavioral signals across a user
across a user transaction touchpoints,
which is basically you can, we
can assume that there are over 50
different signals per user transaction,
including transaction patterns.
Then the data flows through the
analysis engine where advanced
algorithms like neural networks look
at look at and leverage advanced
edge computing methodologies that
distribute analytical capabilities
across endpoints to minimize the
latency in analyzing these transactions.
As a third step, we have the risk scoring
that occurs in real time where for each
transaction, the fraud probabilities
are calculated and based on the context
there are also dynamic thresholds
that are, that do adjust based on
individual user profiles or as a, as a.
As a group that are classified
based on user demographic regions.
And this sort of builds a composite
risk score which is then evaluated
for a user's or a transaction risk.
And finally an automated response
gets executed in order to
prevent prevent the transaction.
If the transaction seems.
Or block the transaction or challenge it
with a step up authentication that happens
to further evaluate if the transaction
is originating from a legitimate user.
This proactive approach minimizes
not just financial losses, but
also reduces disruption resolution
burdens to the fraud detection teams.
The slide here discusses on how these
systems continuously learn and adapt.
First, we have the behavioral biometrics
that basically capture physical
patterns when a user interacts.
And then it also captures any
cognitive patterns that, that
basically increase decision making
speed and any navigation patterns.
Secondly, we have self-learning
capabilities where algorithms through
automated feedback and validation,
keep learning continuously.
A pat pattern recognition leads to
model refinement, which further feeds
back into the performance validation.
And these systems tend to adapt in
days rather than multi-month manual
update cycles of traditional systems.
Finally, we have the predictive threat
anticipation where historical patterns are
evaluated and compared against the current
user behavior and they're prevented.
If any anomalies are prevented
before they even materialize.
And based on this, also the institutions
start to risk forecast and their
systems enable them to be proactive
rather than have a reactive response.
Finally, to conclude, I would
like to highlight the key
takeaways from this research.
First, behavioral analytics fundamentally
transformed fraud detection.
Meaning dynamic profiling enabled 87%
detection rates with just 7% false alerts
while drastically improving compared
to the traditional rule based systems.
Second, contextual intelligence
enhances precision by incorporating
situational variables like location,
device, and environmental context.
Third, we have the real time prevention
that delivers measurable results,
stopping threats in milliseconds
and minimalizing, and thereby
minimalizing financial exposure
before transactions even complete.
Finally, fourth as a fourth component,
we do have the adaptive systems
that ensure future readiness through
self-learning, that keeps learning
rather than, monthly manual cycles,
which reduces the learning to almost
within days and and helps predictive
analytics that and anticipate emerging
threats implementing these intelligent
adaptive frameworks significantly.
It enhances the customer
experiences, experience and also
improves the operational efficiency
for financial organizations.
Finally the future of fraud
prevention is behavioral,
contextual, adaptive, and real time.
Thank you, and thank
you for the opportunity.
Feel free to reach reach out to
me on LinkedIn for any questions
or any feedback on the research.
Thank you.