This is Bhaskara Biraka, CSN
technology leader with extensive
experience in designing and
developing enterprise applications.
My expertise spans distributed
system, microservices, and cloud
platforms, including AWS and Azure.
I have proven track record in
leading across the functional teams,
architecting scalable solutions.
And optimizing system performance,
passionating about innovation.
I continuously leveraging
emerging technology to drive
efficiency and business impact.
Today my topic is adapting
AI in insurance industries.
Artificial intelligence is a
resolutionized insurance industry, driving
the transformative advancements across
the key processes such as underwriting,
claim management, fraud detection.
And customer engagement.
This presentation will provide
the comprehensive technical
framework for the implementation in
insurance, highlighting practical
deployment, strategy, the real world.
Outcomes and a solution to the challenges
attendees will gain the actionable
insights into the leveraging AI to
improve the efficiency, accuracy and
customer satisfaction while positioning
their organization for sustainable growth
in an increasingly digital landscape.
So EIA powered underwriting systems.
Underwriting system is one of the key
module in the insurance industries.
enhance the risk assessment.
advanced machine learning algorithm
analyzing over 1000 data points
per application improve the
risk assessment accuracy by 85%.
This system utilize the neural networks
and gradient boosting to process
the structured and unstructured
data including the medical records.
Credit, credit histories and IOT censored
data, enabling more, non censored
risk stratifaction, stratification,
sorry.
reduced processing time, automated
underwriting systems, achieved 70 percent
reductions in the processing time, cutting
policy insurance from the week to hours.
Natural language processing extracts the
relevant information from the documents
instantly, while parallel processing
capabilities enable the simultaneous
evolutions of multiple applications to
dramatically increase the throughput.
Improved the accuracy.
Deep learning models.
Reduce the human errors by 92
percent while increasing the
pricing, pricing precisions by 76%.
By continuously learning the from
historical claims data and real time
market conditions, this system optimize
the premium calculations and reduce
the loss ratios by an average of 18%.
Directly improve the
insurer's bottom line.
AI in a claims management.
Accelerate the settlement processing.
Advanced predictive analytics frameworks
have reduced the average claim
settlement times from 30 days to just 4.
5 days, and 85 percent improvement.
Machine learning algorithms analyze
the historical claim data, policy
terms, and risk factors to instantly
validate the claims and calculate
the optimal payout amounts.
Enhanced Customer Experience
The implementation of AI
driven claims processing has
driven customer satisfaction
scores from 72 percent to 92%.
The real time claims status updates,
automated communication workflows, and
faster settlements have resulted in a 45
percent increase in policy renewal rates.
And a 38 percent rises in
the customer referrals.
Precision Damaged Assessment So the state
of the art computer vision algorithm,
powered by deep learning neural networks,
have a revolutionized damaged evaluation.
Assessment times have dropped
from 48 hours to just 2.
4 hours.
While achieving a 98.
5 percent accuracy in the damaged
estimation, this system processes
over 10, 000 images per day.
Analyzing the damaged pattern across
the multiple insurance categories.
Fraud Detection Systems
High speed processing.
Advanced AI powered fraud detection
system analyzing over 125k
transactions per second using the
parallel processing architecture.
This system employs sophisticated
neural networks to identify suspicious
patterns and anomalies in real time,
enabling immediate intervention when
the potential fraud is detected.
Enhanced Accuracy.
Leveraging a deep learning algorithm,
our fraud detection system achieves a 99.
fraud tolerant activities.
The system's multi layered neural
networks continuously learn from new
data veterans, adapting to emerging fraud
tactics while maintaining the exceptional
precision in the threat detection.
Reduce the false positives.
Through the sophisticated feature
engineering and ensemble learning
techniques, false positives or rates have
been reduced to an industry leading 0.
05 percent.
This breakthrough ensures minimal
disruptions to legitimate the transaction
while maintaining the robust security,
resulting in improved customer
experience and operational efficiency.
Computer Vision in the Clients Processing
Reduced assessment times Advanced Computer
Vision Technology Accelerated Damage
Assessment by 95 percent Revolutionizing
the Clients Process Sophisticated AI
algorithm analyzing the high resolution
images and video footage of damaged
assets to generate the precise repair
cost estimation within the minutes.
Improved the accuracy, the state
of the art computer vision system
achieves an unprecedented 98 percent
accuracy in the damaged evolution.
This system leverages the deep
learning model to detect and classify
even microscopic damaged patterns,
ensuring the consistently precise claim
estimation across all types of assets.
Real time insights.
Our cutting edge infrastructure
process an industry leading 1.
5 million clients daily, delivering
comprehensive analytical insights with
response times under 200 milliseconds.
This transformative process
capability enables instant decision
making and sets new standards
for client handling efficiency.
Predictive analytics for
the real time insights.
A real time data analysis.
Our advanced predictive analytics
engine processes an unprecedented 1.
5 million clients daily.
Leveraging the sophisticated AI
algorithms to analyzing the complex
data sets, the system continuously
monitoring 50 plus data points per
client, enabling the instant risk
assessment and automated decision making.
Lightning fast response time.
With the industry leading query,
latency of under 200 milliseconds.
Insurers can access the critical
insights 75 percent faster
than the traditional system.
This unprecedented speed enables the
real time fraud detection and instant
client validation significantly
improve the customer satisfaction.
Data Driven Optimization By
harnessing predictive analytics,
insurers have achieved a 40 percent
improvement in operational efficiency.
The system's AI powered
forecasting, the enabling process.
Precise resource allocation,
reducing the processing cost by 35
percent while maintaining the 99.
9 percent accuracy in the risk assessment,
economic benefits of AI
adoptions, cost reductions.
Yay.
Automation slashes
operational cost by 38%.
Through the intelligent process
optimization, mission learning algorithm
reduced their manual processing
time base and percent while cutting
error rates from the 12% to under 1%
improved the NPS customer satisfaction
source with the net prompter scores.
Jumping 48 points from plus 12 to plus 60.
Climb processing time drops from
seven days to just to 24 hours.
Driving unprecedented, customer
loyalty and, word of mouth growth.
Enhancing profitability.
AI implementation delivers the 31.
2 percent ROI within the 18 months.
Companies reported average
profit margin increases of 15.
3%. Combined 2.
5 million annual, cost saving with 23
percent higher customer retention rates.
Data Management Challenges Data
silos, data quality, data security
Insurance companies face critical
data management hurdles that directly
impact their AI effectiveness.
Legacy systems create data silos
that isolate up to 80 percent of
valuable customer information across
departments, making it nearly impossible
to build comprehensive risk profiles.
Poor data quality
compounds this challenge.
With inconsistent formats and outcomes.
Outdated records leading E two
A model that can, misclassify
the risk by up to 30%.
Furthermore, stringent data security
requirements mandate the state of the
art encryption and access control to
protect the sensor to customer data
as the average cost of insurance.
Data breach now exceeds 4.2 millions
legacy system integrations.
APS, microservices, middlewares, legacy
system integration requires a carefully
orchestrated technical approach.
Modern APS serves as a secure
gateway, enabling standardized data
exchange between the traditional
systems and AI applications.
While maintaining the data integrity,
microservice architecture break down the
complex integrations into the manageable
independent component that can be updated
without destructing entire system.
Robust middleware acts as a
translator between the legacy.
Databases and new AI platforms
ensure seamlessly communication
and data transformations.
Performance and Optimization and
Distributed Processing Spark,
Kafka, and Hadoop Modern distributed
processing frameworks revolutionize
insurance data operations.
Apache Spark in memory processing
accelerates complex calculations by
45%, while Apache Kafka real time
streaming capabilities enable instant
data flow between the systems,
cutting operational costs by 82%.
Supporting these technologies, Microsoft's
architecture breaks down the monolithic
system into manageable components.
Slashing implementation time by 85
percent and virtually eliminating
the system downtime with a 97
percent reduction in outages.
Explainable AI Frameworks Explainable
AI framework revolutionized insurance
operations by transforming the
complex algorithmic decisions into
transparent, interpretable insights.
This cutting edge system leverages
sophisticated visualization tools and
natural language processing to break
down the AI decisions into clear.
Step by step reasoning path
with an outstanding 95 percent
regulatory adherence rate.
These frameworks generate the
comprehensive audit trials
that document every factor
influencing automated decision.
From risk assessment variables to
climb the processing parameters.
The implementation of explainable
AI has proven transformative
for the customer relationships.
Driving an 85 percent reduction in
disputes through the detailed, jargon free
explanations of underwriting decisions
and claim assessments by bridging the
gap between advanced AI capabilities and
human understanding, these frameworks
have become indispensable tools for the
insurers committed to build trust while
maintaining technological innovations.
Thank you so much.