Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining.
I am Malika Machu, a DevOps architect.
We are here today to discuss something
that touches every person on this
planet, how we produce food, but we are
looking at it through a new lens, how
cloud native AI is taking agriculture
from a traditional industry into ai.
Highly intelligent, autonomous future.
The challenge agriculture
is facing a perfect strong.
We have two PDA growing population
while dealing with labor shortages,
climate changes, and shrinking margins.
Here, the real quicker farmers
generate numerous volume of data,
but they lack a unified system.
To act on it.
They are swimming in data, but solving
for intelligence, digital transformation,
we are entering a major technology
shift by combining cloud stability.
Yay, autonomous robotics and blockchain.
We are not just making
a small improvement.
We are redefining the entire
field to for journey to be more
religion, agile and efficient.
Cloud native data pipelines.
It all starts with the data backbone,
the nervous system of the farm.
We collect continuous stream.
Of data from iBot sensors, drones,
and satellites without this
cloud native pipeline to process
that volume in relaying time.
And of the high level AI we are
discussing would be possible
AI, precision and farming.
Once the data flows, we move.
From just having information to making
surgical decisions, AI analyzes soil
health and irrigation needs in real time.
Instead of a one size fits all approach,
farmers can take precise action that
increases productivity while massively
reducing waste mission learning.
For yield production.
Mission learning brings foresight by
training models on multi-seasonal data,
weather, soil, and planting history.
We generate incredibly
reliable yield forecast.
These predictions drive everything from
logistics and stopping to market pricing.
Anonymous missionary and robotics labor
S are critical operational challenge.
Robotics and autonomous systems
are file filling that gap, handling
repetitive and precision driven.
Task 20 by four by seven because
they are cloud connected.
We can manage this entire fleet
remotely and ensure consistent
throughput, blockchain and transparency.
Transparency is now a market expectation.
Blockchain creates an immutable record
from seed to self tracking, every step
planting, processing on the logistics.
Builds consumer trust and
makes food safety responses
almost hundred percent secure.
Deep learning agriculture data is complex.
We all know that it is a spite in
new oriented, deep learning uncovers
those patterns, individual to the
human high, transforming those
signals into actionable insights.
And automate ions in the field.
Smart irrigation water is
our most critical resource.
High voltage driven irrigation ensures
it is used only when the crop truly,
these systems automatically respond
to soil conditions and can even delay
cycles if rain is in the forecast.
Aligning sustainability with productivity,
ai quality control, and food safety.
Quality control is now air driven.
Advanced imaging detections and defects
and predictions reduces in real time
on a high volume production lines.
This protects consumer safety
and ensures compliance.
At a speed minimal
inspection simply cannot test
architectural overview.
When you look at the big picture,
these are not just random tools.
These are all layers of
a unified architecture.
Data flows from sensors up through the
infrastructure, into the AI models,
and finally out to the business system.
This is the blueprint for the
intelligent farm safeguards.
With this much tech comes a
major responsibility on us.
AI in agriculture must be explainable.
Operators need to trust
every very recommendation.
We also need a strong data governance
and systems that stay religion.
Even if the pumps goes offline,
implementation part, this
transformation follows a phase approach.
You start by connecting your sensors,
then move to analyzing with ai.
From there, you automate with
robotics, and finally, integrate
across the entire supply check.
Each phase builds the
mentation of the next.
Key takeaways.
If you take anything else today,
remember these three points.
Data is your most strategic asset.
A combines volume over time, and
automation solves real operational pain.
Ultimately, sustainability and
productivity go hand in hand.
Thank you for your time.
The future of agriculture
is not just digital.
It's intelligent,
autonomous, and data driven.
And second, thank you for every time.
Have a great day.