Cloud infrastructure decisions are
too often based on personal taste and
experience, and that makes a problem.
What is good for large, mature systems
is too expensive and complex for early
stages, while early stage shortcuts
will block system growth one day.
In addition, cloud vendors release
new features constantly, making
custom solutions obsolete or risky and
previous assumptions not valid anymore.
And that's a real problem that
doesn't have Magic solution and
my presentation will look what
practically could be done about this.
Welcome to cloud native 2025.
My name is Asher Sterkin.
I have about 40 years experience.
Previously, I served at different
senior engineering positions
and large multinationals.
And today I'm mostly focused on
advanced cloud architecture solutions.
Both details could be found
on my social networks.
Let's look what is included in making
decision about cloud infrastructure.
What we need to decide about trust.
We need to decide about
cloud, what cloud to use.
It could be WS, Azure, GCP,
smaller player like CloudFlare.
Some people believe that Kubernetes
is a real cloud, while what we
call cloud, actually hardware.
The Kubernetes true cloud is running on
the top of a kind of philosophical debate.
What is right?
What is wrong?
Once we decided about cloud
platform, let's say AWS, there
are a lot of choices to be made.
What compute platform we need?
Virtual machine, serverless lambda
function, container based solutions
like Kubernetes or ECS, maybe more
exotic options like step functions.
How we store data.
Which kind of database we need.
Relational, non relational, blob storage.
What kind of internal
communication we need.
Peer to peer message queues,
PubSub infrastructure, streaming.
What kind of external
interfaces we expose.
Just load balancer or API gateway
or maybe GraphQL supporting AppSync.
We need to make decisions
about system observability.
How log files are produced.
How metrics are collected.
How alerts are raised.
How they are processed.
How history is kept, for
example, cloud, cloud watching
Amazon and, Athena for query.
We need to decide about
automation infrastructure,
how we deploy cloud resources.
It could be cloud formation of
Amazon, CDK, cloud, cloud development
kit, more Kubernetes focused helm.
more generic terraform or its open source,
version or open tofu or more sophisticated
orchestration platform like Lummi.
There are decisions to be made about
development environment, separating
cloud solution architecture and software
development Architectures wrong approach.
Cloud SDKs are sup supportive for
particular round time environments,
be it Python, no GS, java t net, or.
On the top of them, there are multiple
programming languages, and all this
combination will determine how much
CLI we will need from the cloud.
Very seldom we could come up
with one clear cut choice here.
How we make decisions, or let's
say, how we are supposed or
expected to make decisions.
We are expected to make decisions fact
based, as a kind of rational process.
What workload of the system we expect,
what server level, service level
agreements we need to support in terms
of latency and throughput, what security
requirements are, what cost constraints
are, what time to market we need to
address tomorrow or one year from now,
and what brownfield constraints we need
to deal with because very seldom we
deploy completely clean slate solution.
In reality, decisions are made not this
way, as I mentioned in my introduction.
It's based on faith, what we believe
is right or wrong, or a certain kind
of bias towards a particular choice.
Experience, if something worked for
me in my previous project, I will most
likely push towards this option for
the next one, whether relevant or not.
There are certain likes or
dislikes and fashion hype.
And one extremely dangerous
is so called trust.
High, tight person, opinion.
Senior manager who believes, who know he
knows or she knows what's right or wrong.
Very often based on who
he's playing work with.
A more effective approach to that
challenge would be set based engineering.
At the beginning, we
know very little about.
Many aspects of the system, what external
interfaces exactly we will need to
deal with, how much load we will have,
maybe security changes will change,
or even target market will change.
So we need to evaluate the
number of candidates and keep as
many options open as possible.
Eventually we will converge to
smaller number of configurations.
Very often, usually reflecting different
environments we need to operate in, like
developments, test stage production.
One configuration will
be locked for production.
However, based on feedback and
metrics collected, we will most
likely need to come back to stage
one and evaluate new candidates
or re evaluate previous candidates
and start this whole process over.
This presentation is titled
Focus on Core Value and Keep Up.
Cloud infrastructure flexible with
ports and adapters is a architectural
pattern, sometimes called hexagonal
architecture that allows to separate
infrastructure and application to keep
them separate and Prevent the influence
of infrastructure on core value.
This pattern was introduced
by Alistair Cockburn and
published in this seminal book.
Very highly recommended.
The pattern contains several parts.
The first one, we isolate application
completely from infrastructure.
The application logic doesn't
know anything about what
infrastructure it will run on top of.
This is achieved through
well defined ports.
in ports or out ports for system
inputs or outputs, ports are
slightly more than interfaces.
It's a collection of interfaces
with the same technological choice
and data that flows through them.
Every port might have multiple adapters
implemented on top of different
infrastructure, and adapters are plugged
into system through ports by configurator.
Configurator could be static or on.
In the book, they use a sample
application called BlueZone, which is
actually a parking lot where drivers
buy tickets and inspectors check
whether cars are parked valid or not.
We will use this application
in our conversation.
The process is supposed to start with use
case analysis, answering the very simple
question why the system exists, what
kind of value it delivers to its users.
In our case, we have two use
cases in this application.
One is buy ticket for car initiated
by car driver and communicating with
payment service, credit card maybe.
The second one is checking card
initiated by parking inspector.
Use case actors provide strong
input for what kind of primary
ports the system needs.
Primary driving ports are for
actors initiating use case.
In this case, for Car driver and
parking inspector and, primary driven
ports for external services we need
to use, consume, like payment service.
So we have primary, primary ports
derived from use case specification.
Use case event flow specification
will provide an input.
for secondary ports.
If we need to store some data somewhere,
we need a database, so we need to
define a secondary port for database
and not lock ourselves into a corner
with a particular database choice.
On the other hand, in this particular
application, we need to know what
the current time is to put it
on the ticket and check whether
the ticket is expired or not.
So we have secondary driven ports.
Actor interfaces, more detailed technical
specification of how we are supposed to
communicate with actors will most likely
determine which protocols we need, be it
REST API, GraphQL, or maybe open system to
system integration through MQP protocol.
Use case SLAs in terms of throughput and
latency plus data schema stability will
define what kind of database, what type
of database is most suitable for that.
If you have a stable, relatively
stable schema and need a lot of
flexibility for ad hoc queries, a
relational database like Postgres
will most likely be the best choice.
However, if we have a very flexible
schema, a document database like
MongoDB might be a better option.
And if we have very high throughput,
low latency requirements of the system,
columnar based, non SQL database like
Cassandra might be better choice.
Cloud platform itself is very
often determined by so called
supplementary specification.
Customers specify what they need.
Regulators tell us what
clouds we could use.
Legacy systems to integrate with will
determine which cloud we can use.
And so that comes from a
supplementary specification.
Once we have cloud decided upon, time
to market considerations will push
towards adopting native serverless
options from that cloud platform.
For example, Lambda and API gateway for
compute or Lambda and AppSync for GraphQL
based interface or MQ service for MQB.
Serverless Aurora for Postgres,
Serverless DocumentDB for Mongo,
Serverless Keyspace for Cassandra,
and most likely CDK, Cloud Development
Kit for orchestration and deployment.
It's just much easier to put stuff
together and deploy using that, this
set of options than anything else.
However, when we deploy to production, we
start collecting metrics, we start getting
feedback, and it might be the system is
too expensive, or not performant enough,
or there is a certain feature gap, and
then we start considering alternatives.
For example, NEON database as an
alternative to Aurora for Postgres,
or Atlas database for Mongo, or
Datasex Cassandra for Cassandra.
We may discover that we
have stable load, high load.
And Lambda is not a good choice anymore.
And switch to Kubernetes
behind load balancer.
And that will determine what
kind of automation we need.
Maybe Helm.
And maybe we need, we have more
sophisticated needs for deployment
operation and switch to Pulumi.
The book suggests certain
canonical structure for application
to reflect that pattern.
Keeping application logic.
Adapters and ports in separate
folders, in separate packages.
It's a very high level structure.
Details depend on which domain
we are developing software for,
what programming language we use.
What business model we have, whether it's
software as a service or cloud independent
software vendor and what is core
technology, whether it's infrastructure
or application services like e commerce
versus, let's say, cyber security.
To sum up, Ports and Adapters
architectural pattern is really very
powerful tool to deal with uncertainty and
flexibility in complex software systems.
Very often we don't know enough
at the beginning and we will
need to make our choices later.
Almost for sure.
This is just the beginning.
What I presented here is
just the tip of the iceberg.
If you are interested in more details and
more detailed discussion, drop me a line.
Here are my details on, social networks.
Thank you for your time and
attention and hope to see you again.