Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining me today.
My name is Mohit Mittal.
And today I'm going to talk about NLP.
NLP, Natural Language Processing, is
a subfield of artificial intelligence
that enables machines to understand,
interpret, and generate human language.
The need of NLP emerged due
to the complexity of human
language filled with ambiguity.
context, idioms, and variations.
Historically, NLP research dates
back to 1950 when Alan Turning
proposed the Turning Test to
evaluate machine intelligence.
Early NLP efforts involved rule based
systems, but these had limitations due
to the complexity of human language.
Over the past two decades, the rapid
growth in data, computing power, And
machine learning algorithms have propelled
NLP into real world applications.
Today NLP is used to chat, is used
in chatbots, voice assistants,
search engines, translation services,
sentiment analysis, shaping how
humans interact with technology.
This session will deep dive into the key
techniques and advancements that have
transformed NLP into what it is today.
Growing impact of NLP.
The NLP market has
experienced remarkable growth.
In 2018, the market was valued
at around eight billions, and by
2022 it has surge to 26 billion.
The projected CHER of
21.4% from 2023 to 20.
30 signifies that NLP is one of
the fastest growing AI segments.
To put this into perspective, the market
size in 2018 was 8 billion, journal
8 billion, in 19 it grew up to 11.
6 billion.
2020. It was 16.2 billion, then
2021, it grew up to 20 point 21.3
billion and 2022, it's 26.4 billion.
Healthcare has been a key driver in NLP
adoption, contributing 15.2 of the 2%
of the total market leveraging NLP for.
medical records, analysis, predictive
analysis, and clinical decision support.
Cloud based NLP deployments now
account for 60 percent of the industry,
highlighting a shift towards more
scalable and cost effective solutions.
The increasing integration of NLP
across finance, retail, and legal
sectors further drives demand,
making it a critical AI technology.
Moving on to next slide where we
are going to talk about advancements
in large language models.
What is LLM?
Large language models or LLM are
a subset of NLP models trained on
massive data sets to understand
and generate human like text.
The evolution of LLMs can be tracked
back to the earlier models where
Word2VC 2013 which introduced
vector based word representations.
Later, transformer based architectures
like BERT and GPT 3 revolutionized NLP by
enabling deep conceptual understanding.
GPT-4 launched in 2023.
Further improved contextual
reasoning, creativity, and logical
consistency in generated text.
LMS have been tested
across various domains.
If you talk about medical diagnosis,
researching human level accuracy in
medical text analysis is around 90 to 95%.
Legal document review.
where we are automating
contract analysis with up to 92.
percent of accuracy, conversational AI,
enabling chatbots, virtual assistants
to provide human like responses.
With the rise of zero shot and few
shot learning, LLMs can now perform
new tasks without extensive retraining,
making them highly adaptable.
Moving on to next slide where we are going
to talk about core NLP components is a
it's a four four step ladder you can say
where the top one is text tokenization.
Tokenization is a process of
breaking text into smaller units.
which can be words, sub
words, or characters.
This step is essential for language
models to understand and process it.
There are different types of tokenization.
Word based tokenization which
splits text at word boundaries.
Subword tokenizations like, BPE.
Wordpiece breaks words into smaller
meaningful units to handle unknown words.
The another one is character
based tokenization, which splits
text into individual characters
useful for language like Chinese.
The next letter is part of
speech tagging, POS tagging.
POS tagging assigns grammatical label to
words such as noun, verbs, adjectives.
This helps NLP models understand
sentence structure and meaning.
For example, run can be
a noun, a morning run.
or a verb I run every day and POS
tagging helps in differentiating them.
The next is named entity recognition.
We also call it NER.
NER identifies real world entities such as
names, locations, organization, and dates.
Example, in Apple, INC is
headquartered in California.
NER identifies Apple Inc as a
company and California as a location.
That's how NER helps.
The last one is pre processing.
Pre processing involves
cleaning and normalizing text
to improve model accuracy.
The common steps include removing
stop words, lower casing text,
and handling misspellings.
Proper pre processing can enhance
model performance by up to 30%.
Now, what is tokenization in NLP?
Tokenization is the fundamental step
in NLP that converts unstructured text
into structured data for processing.
The choice of tokenization technique
impacts model accuracy and efficiency.
Traditional word based tokenization
struggles with compound words and
different language structures.
Subword tokenization methods
like Byte Pair Encoding, or BPE,
have reduced vocabulary size and
improved pre verb recognition.
Effective tokenization enables models
to handle languages with complex
morphology and new words efficient.
Moving on to next slide where we are going
to talk about what is sentiment in NLP.
Sentiment in NLP refers to the
emotional tone expressed in a text.
It can be classified into categories
like positive, negative, neutral.
Early sentiment analysis
use predefined word.
List that struggled with
a sarcasm on Context.
Machine learning approaches
improved sentiment classification
by learning and label data sets.
Advanced model like BERT now
understand contextual nuances and
perform sentiment analysis by over
90% Advanced Sentiment Analysis.
Multitask learning enhances accuracy
by understanding overlapping emotions.
Multilingual sentiment analysis
ensures consistent sentiment
detection across languages.
Hybrid approaches combine rule based
and deep learning models for better
sarcastic Moving on to next slide,
language generation breakthroughs.
The introduction of transformer
based models has revolutionized
language generation.
Attention mechanisms help models
maintain context over long passages,
improving coherence in generated text.
Training techniques like teacher
forcing have accelerated model
learning by 40%, which nucleus
sampling has reduced repetitive.
Text generation by 60 percent real
world application of NLP powered
language generation include automatic
text summarization, where new models
now achieve near human performance.
These advancements are paving the
way of AI generated context in news,
education, conversational AI applications.
Now talking about
implementation considerations.
Deploying NLP at scale requires
addressing several critical Considerations
Computational requirements Optimized
decoding algorithms can reduce inference
latency by three times, making real
time processing more efficient.
Data quality High quality preprocessing
can improve entity recognition
accuracy by up to 12 to 15 percent.
MLOps practices Automated model monitoring
ensures model perform optimally and detect
degration up to 92 percent accuracy.
The ethical considerations, biased
detection frameworks help ensure
NLP systems are fair, unbiased.
These factors are essential for
organization looking to integrate
NLP solutions effectively.
Challenges and future directions for NLP.
Despite advancements, NLP
faces several key challenges.
Factual accuracy.
Like large language models sometimes
generate incorrect information,
but new fact checking mechanism
have reduced errors by 45%.
Domain specialization, custom NLP
models for specific industries like
healthcare, finance are achieving
85 percent accuracy in maintaining.
Precise terminology, ethical AI
development, privacy enhancing
techniques such as federated learning
are reducing data security risks by 60%.
Addressing these challenges will
shape the next NLP of NLP models.
What's the future of NLP?
NLP is rapidly evolving and will continue
to transform industry in coming decade.
The next phase will see improvements
in multilingual capabilities, better
context understanding and more
advanced AI human collaboration.
Responsible AI development, ethical
data governance and scalable
solutions will be the key factors in
ensuring the positive impact of NLP.
Thank you so much for, pulling
your time out, giving me time
to present my views on NLP.
I am looking forward to your
questions and future discussions.
Thank you so much.