Hi, everyone.
Welcome to my talk today.
We are going to talk about something
amazing, something cool, something
that I think we all struggle with at
some point that is cloud complexity.
Before we dive in, let
me introduce myself.
My name is Dennis Thoma, and
I am a dev rel at Kumulos.
That means I spend my time helping
developers like you navigating
cloud native technologies,
simplify infrastructure, and most
importantly, avoid unexpected
cloud build that make your CFO cry.
So let's jump right in.
All right, let's talk about chaos.
Who here has deployed something to the
cloud thinking it's a small update?
And boom, your select
notification explodes.
Yeah, it's happened to me.
One morning, I pushed what I
thought was a simple change.
Within few minutes, alert was firing
off like a New Year Eve's firework show.
And we all know that the worst
part will at the end of the month.
And, cloud building can sometimes
feel like a mystery novel.
You never know the ending,
what is going to happen.
And, as you can see in this slide, there
is a picture which shows before and after.
And in my case, before was a nightmare
of hidden cost and confusions.
I thought that it, this can't be right.
This was when I knew I
had to find a better way.
So, this was my wake up call.
Cloud itself isn't the problem.
It's how we manage it.
I realized we need only three things.
First one is Transparency, like
know exactly what we are paying for.
And second one is simplicity, like
cut down complexity in configurations.
And last one is flexibility.
No vendor logins and no more headaches.
Imagine this full visibility
into your cloud resources.
Like turning on the
light in the dark room.
It was sudden realization for me also.
Like it was like switching from an old
telephone to the latest smartphone.
As you can see on this slide, there
is a picture which shows you are
going from old telephone to latest
smartphone in the digital world.
And suddenly I was in control
instead of my cloud controlling.
So this is where Cumulus comes in.
Let me tell, let me tell you
about our real world case.
One of our clown client was
struggling with unpredictable cost.
and multiple vendors.
Every month was a surprise bill for
him and that's not good for him.
With QMLESS, we switched to our model
to the fixed cost and no metering model.
Instead of getting bill for every single
operations or every single resources,
we used a simple predictable unit based
system called QMS, QMLESS Compound Unit.
It was like turning a chaotic
file of papers into a neatly
organized filling cabinet.
And like, switching from paper
minute font plan to unlimited data.
suddenly cloud spending became as
predictable as Netflix subscriptions.
After everything, I learned that
I have come with three colder
suits for the cloud sanity.
First one is simplify.
Complexity doesn't, does
not make you smarter.
It's just make you troubleshooting harder.
Imagine this is a assembling
IKEA furniture without the
manual, but with not the fun.
And the second one is transparent.
You wouldn't order food at the restaurant
if they refused to show you prices.
Could cloud should work the same thing.
And the last one is, stay flexible.
No vendor should own your
infrastructure choices.
Keep your options open just
like keeping backup snacks in
your case of meal disappoint.
The benefits are like less
stress, predictable budgets, and
more time for the innovations.
Who wouldn't want this?
Of course, we all want this.
And so At the end, here's
the takeaway key points.
The cloud doesn't have
to be a source of stress.
With the transparency, simplified
management, and the freedom to
choose what's best for us, we
can turn into a powerful ally.
As the cumulus says, that cumulus shows
us that it's not about fighting the cloud.
It's about mastering it and like,
as you can see in this slide,
there is a guy who is thinking
what is happening on the earth.
And after he get know about the
cumulus, now he is just a chill guy.
He can enjoy by himself.
So thank you.
All right, let's wrap up this.
I hope you enjoyed my talk
and found it eye opening.
Since this is a pre recorded conference,
if you got any doubts, questions,
or just wants to chat with me, feel
free to ping me on the social media.
You can find me on LinkedIn and Twitter.
I'd love to hear your thoughts.
Thank you so much for your time.