Hi everyone, and thanks for joining.
My talk today is called
MCP Servers and Fire.
My name is Alex Bena.
I'm founder of Swart
View Security Company.
What I want to do in the next 15
minutes or so is take a practical
look at MCP based cloud systems
from a security standpoint.
There is a lot of excitement around MCP
right now and the excitement is justified.
It makes AI systems much more useful
because it connects them to real
tools, real data, and real workflows.
But the moment we do that, we are no
longer talking only about model quality.
We are talking about access,
execution, trust, and control.
So the central question, of
my talk today is very simple.
When MCP becomes part of cloud
architecture, where does the
real security risk come from?
I will walk through that step by step and
finish with a set of practical defenses.
Before we get into technical
part, let me quickly explain
the annual I'm coming from.
I work at the intersection
of application security.
AI Security Cloud Security, d FFC ops.
So when I look at Skyrocket and MCP
which has close to a hundred million
of monthly, the loans of which SDK
and active public MCP servers and
counted in tens of thousands today.
I do not mainly see a protocol trend
or a shiny new integration standard.
I see a place where trust and
privilege are starting to concentrate.
That's why I care about the
architecture layer so much.
In my experience, the most
dangerous problems in the systems
like this one often do not come
from dramatic coding mistakes.
They come from seemingly reasonable design
choices that create too much our or to
little validation or to little visibility.
So the goal of my talk
is not abstract AI hype.
It's practical threat modeling
and practical defensive guidance.
Let's start from the basic
picture, an MCP server seats.
Between a client and a set of
external capabilities, it can expose
tools, resources, prompts, and data
sources through a standard interface.
From engineering standpoint
it's indeed very elegant.
It gives you interoperability modality
in a cleaner way for AI systems to
interact with external functionality.
But from a security point of view,
the important detail is different.
The moment the server advertises
capabilities to an AI client, it
becomes part of the trust bounding.
It becomes an access layer, and
in many cases the execution layer.
And that all that means it has to be
treated like privileged infrastructure.
This slide makes the mechanics
point even more explicit.
You can think of MCP server
as a capability container.
It tells the client what it can do.
Maybe it can scan the code, maybe it can
validate policies, maybe it can pull some
data lead resources or trigger actions.
It also gives the client one
unified protocol for discovery
and invoke in those capabilities.
That's very useful, but it also means
risk starts to concentrate in one place
because now, trust, permission, execution,
logic and external reach all being brought
together behind just one interface.
So yes, MCP improves modality, but if you
design the boundary badly, it also can
centralize risk in a very efficient way.
So here is the premise.
MCP is increasingly becoming a control
layer between models, tools, and
cloud services and control layers
are always security sensitive.
They do not just move data around, they
shape what can be accessed, what can
be triggered, and what kind of action a
simple request can eventually turn on to.
So MCP servers are not just connectors.
They part of execution pass.
And once that execution pass is
exposed and exposed to multiple
systems and tied to real privileges.
The Blast radios grows very fast.
That's why I think MCP deserves
much more attention from security
teams than it is getting today.
So where does the risk really come from?
Big part of it is that traditional
cloud security assumptions do
not fully fit the, this model.
In the normal service to
service flow, we usually analyze
one API calling another API.
Here the chain is much, much more fluid.
A user talks to our model.
The model may use an agent.
The agent uses an MCP client.
The client calls an MCP server and
the server reaches a tool or an API.
And at very step parameters can change.
Scope, can widen privileges,
can quietly expand.
So the real question is not whether
one end point is secure or not.
The real question is whether intent is
being constrained across the whole chain.
That's why I keep saying
the most dangerous MCP
weaknesses are architectural.
A team might tell you
the code is give you it.
Auto notification exists.
Connectors are in place and tested,
and the cloud service is hardened.
That's fine.
But still, that doesn't mean the system
safe if the overall design gives too
much power to the wrong boundary or
mixes trust in a in the wrong place.
Or exposes tools too broadly, you
can still get systemic risk even when
the implementation looks acceptable.
So the real issue are things like
overprivileged access, weak isolation.
Insecure tools, exposure, misplaced
tri trust between components
and weak validation of what is
being requested and executed.
That is the level where the
biggest problem turn to show up.
To make this easier to work with,
I would like to group MCP issues
into practical classification.
First identity and access problem, like
weak out identification, talking misuse,
confused identity, overly broad scopes.
Second, trust bound failures
and unsafe delegation.
Hidden privilege changes implicit
trust between the model, the client,
the server, and downstream tools.
Short tools and connector exposure.
Too many callable actions
overly powerful connectors.
We control over what gets registered
and invoked force isolation, failures,
cross tenant leakage, cross environment
drift, shared contact context abuse, Fs.
Validation and execution flows like prompt
injection, context injection, unsafe
parameter handling, dangerous rights.
And finally, visibility and control gaps.
Vca auditability, vca,
approval logic, weak monitor.
Again, this helps security teams move
from from work and so on to something.
They can actually assess
and pri prioritize.
Prioritize.
If you look at real attack pass as they
usually emerge as chains, for example,
injected context influences the model.
The model selects a tool and the MCP
server ends up performing a risky
read that exposes sensitive data.
Or Wix server identification allows an
authorized co to access exposed tools or
a compromised connector abuses a trust
execution pass into another system.
What matters here is that each
individual step may look small,
but when you change them together,
the outcome becomes high impact.
That is the pattern I
want people to notice.
Low friction invocation on one side and
high drastic execution on the other side.
Cloud deployments make all of which even
more signals, public exposure increases
Reachability, aAL infrastructure makes
attribution and forensics harder.
Secrets and tokens tend to
spread across agents, connectors,
environments, and automation.
Layers and trust often drift between
development stage and product
production stages in ways that are not
obvious until something goes wrong.
So yes, local MCP helper can
absolutely be risky, but a cloud
hosted MCP server is different.
It can become part of a shared control
plane with real permissions, real data
access, and real operational impact.
That's why Cloud MCP should be treated
as security sensitive infrastructure,
not just as an integration layer.
So what does safety
design might look like?
First, we should treat MCP as
a privileged execution pound.
Again, we should separate read path
from right path, and I assume that right
actions need much stronger controls.
Second constraint tool choices,
scopes, and allowed parameters.
Broad, generic power is
convenient, but it also risky.
Third, we should validate, not just draw
inputs, but context and execution intent.
The question is not only was the
request is valid, as the question is,
was the result in action makes sense.
And should be allowed force the
explicit confirmation gates for
dangerous or irreversible operations.
And finally, pre, we should
preserve isolation between tenants,
agents, services, and environments.
Saved by, by default has to be part of the
architecture, not something added later.
On the operational side,
the goal is not perfection.
The goal is to reduce number of
abuse, pass limit, blast radios, and
make risky behavior visible earlier.
In the practice, that means strong
ification and short-lived credentials.
It means scoped authorization for
every tool and every connector.
It means a low list for actions and
resource classes where that is realistic.
It means audit trails for MCP calls
and for the downstream effects.
Those call created.
And it means many talking that
is aligned to AI enabled abuse
scenarios, not just normal API errors.
If a team does those things well
the result is pretty concrete.
Let me close on the main point.
Cloud MCP servers.
Can enable really powerful a AI
integrations, but they should
be tweaked as security sensitive
infrastructure from day one.
The key risks, architectural
trust, privilege, isolation,
exposure and validation.
Practical vulnerability
classification help helps teams
focus on what actually matters.
And safety deployments depend
on proactive design, not just
after the fact monitoring.
If there is one mindset
I would leave with you.
It is this.
Do not ask only can the
model call the tool.
Also ask what our so is being
created by that connection and
how tightly it is controlled.
Thank you very much.