Hello, my name is Paweł Skrzypek, and
today I would like to present some update
regarding the Nebulus meta operating
system for the cloud computing continuous.
What is it, how it works, and who is
using that, and with what results.
My name is Paweł Skrzypek,
I'm a cloud architect, and I'm
participating in this project.
short again, short agenda.
I will start with the description of
what is the cloud continuum and why
we are using this cloud continuum.
Probably most of us is using it
currently, even without using
the name of the cloud continuum.
I will tell a little bit more
what is meta operating system.
That could be quite new approach for
the building Cloud systems, and then
I will provide information and update
regarding the Nebulas project, what it
is, what is the purpose and how to use,
the project, and finally, I will show the
use case application on Fallows fund, AI
based investments funds, which is using
cloud continuum to do the, algorithmic.
based, investments.
So that's a very short, agenda.
Let's start.
I will start with some definition.
Yeah.
What is the cloud continuum?
And, I think the best definition is
that cloud, cloud continuum is simply
the extension of the traditional
clouds to cover the multiple
entities, which provide analysis.
Processing, storage, and
data generation capabilities.
And in fact, many more things, especially
running the components and so on.
And what constitutes this cloud continue?
the most important elements are
obviously public clouds or generally
speaking clouds, Fog, IOT devices,
which are connected to the clouds.
data centers and private clouds
'cause some of the application are
still running and, probably will be
running in the private data centers.
Private clouds, edge sites, multi access
edge computing, so multiple small, smaller
data centers, located near the users.
And the same for the, micro data centers,
which allow to, to deliver the computing.
It is closer to the users.
So to minimize the . So all of that could
conti co constitute the cloud continuum.
obviously there are multiple other
models like multi clouds, which
means the usage of two or more.
public clouds, hybrid clouds, the mixed
usage of the public clouds and non
public private cloud and cloud continuum.
You can imagine as it's a mix
and match all of these models
across of whole continuum.
So that's the reason that the
name is the Cloud Continuum and
why we need the Cloud Continuum.
As I already said, most of the application
of modern application currently using the
Cloud Continuum, for example, all of the
application deployed to the smartphone
or smartwatches or other devices
are using the Continuum because the
computation is usually done in the cloud.
But the data gathering data.
input and output is done on the
application on the smartphone and
smartwatch also with the current,
computing capabilities of the devices.
Some of the processing is done also
on, on devices, but the most and.
most heavy processing, is done
in the cloud or private cloud.
And using the Cloud Continuum, we can
optimize usage, the application, and
achieve the best possible experience
and utilization of available resources.
Because we can minimize the latency,
especially the latency to the user.
We can optimize the usage of the resources
and we also can benefit, on the, devices
with the power and computing power
of the big data center or big cloud.
One more definition, the last
one is the meta operating system.
Meta operating system in our case
is the operating system which
extends beyond the one server or
One cluster and is shared across the
multiple, devices across the clouds.
That's the reason that we, use that
name because the idea behind the Nebulas
project is to deliver meta operating
system for the cloud continuum.
It is also the name of the
project funded by European
Union in Horizon Europe program.
So it's a research project and it aims to
deliver that kind of the meta operating
system for cloud computing continuous.
the consortium consists of multiple
research organizations, industry,
companies, as well as the end users of
the application, which, provide the use
case application to test the project
and to check, Capabilities of the meta
operating system in real life application.
I will tell today a little bit
more about the one application
delivered by Onfalos Fund.
what Nebulus is doing?
The first thing is, To develop the
appropriate modeling methods, which allows
for describing the cloud continuum, as
you already know, the cloud continuum
contains multiple type of the clouds,
devices, data centers, and so on.
So we need a unified method to
describe this cloud continuum to
provide the application requirements.
to be able to describe and
modeling the application
requirements for the different.
different types of the resources and
also to model the data streams, so how
to use and connect the data streams.
Obviously, everything should
assure the quality of service of
the provisioned service services.
And then.
Nebulus delivers the optimizers, so
ability to compare different available
offerings in the cloud continuum and
using the multi criteria decision making
methods to select the most optimal set of
the resources for the given application
and to continuously reconfigure the
application in the cloud continuum.
to achieve the best possible efficiency
of the use of the application.
Nobles also covered the security,
because the security aspect is
critical for the cloud continuum,
and also introduced the novel smart
contract based service level agreement.
Yeah, because as we can see in the cloud
continuum, we have multiple, service
providers, public clouds, private
cloud, telecom provider with the private
data center, Mets, location and also
the communication and other things.
And we also have the IOT devices.
So the, security and some kind of
the service level agreement is.
critical, to achieve the expected
efficiency of the application
in the cloud continuum.
How Nebulus is built.
As you can see, that's a very
general overview of the high
level architecture of the Nebulus.
That's the critical elements,
core of the Nebulus.
And here is the execution
layer of the Nebulus.
Nebulus is based fully on
the Kubernetes cluster.
So the idea of the Nebulus is to
deploy application to the various
Kubernetes cluster, which are.
It could be located in the different
location, it could be the public cloud,
it could be the private data center,
and it could be the MEC location.
And Nebulas is able to optimize the
usage of the resources of these clusters.
and to deliver and deploy automatically
application to the given clusters, then
to fetch the metrics, so the measurements,
how application is working, what is
the quality of the service, what is
the response to the user, what is the
processing capabilities, and based on
that reconfigure application if needed.
to improve the so called utility function,
goal function, which measures, the
efficiency of the application deployment.
More information about the Nebulas
architecture and features is
provided on the Nebulas website.
There are multiple technical reports
with the detailed description.
so please, visit and review.
if you are interested in using Nebulus,
Nebulus is fully open source, based
on the Mozilla Public License 2.
0, so it could be downloaded and used, for
any purposes without any additional costs.
But Nebulus is not only
about the producing software.
Nebulus project also offers
the open access research.
There are multiple excellent
research papers in the field
of the cloud continuum, cloud
optimization, and deployment.
we are also focusing on the cloud
continuum dissemination and education.
training and last but not
least is the open calls.
In the Nebulas project we have two
runs of the open calls in total is 1.
35 million euro fund available for
the for nine grants for the nine
outside of the consortium companies and
organization who wants to use the Nebulus.
The first round of the
OpenCourse was launched in 2024.
content is just open for submission.
you can find the link here.
So if you have the application,
which is using the cloud continuum,
and you would like to try Nebulus,
it's the best way, because, the,
adaptation of the application to the
Nebulus could be found that in the.
open course projects.
So we are looking for
that, good application.
It must be the existing application,
which is using the cloud continuum
and wants to deploy on the nebulous.
And that's generally the aim of the
Nebulus projects, to, accomplish the
research contribution, especially
in the realms of the cloud, Fog,
and Edge procuring, and to develop
the advanced methods and tools
which enable secure and optimal
application deployment to the cloud.
continue.
so that was about the Nebulus and here
we have the use case application and the
use case application is Onfalos Fund.
It is the alternative investment
funds registered in Luxembourg
and the uniqueness of the Onfalos
Fund is that it's fully operated.
by, automatically by AI
algorithms, which, control the
risk and manage the investments.
Onfalos Fund is operating
since January, 2022.
So it's over three years of the life.
track record, audited, and Onfalos
fund uses cloud continuum to maximize
the efficiency of, its investments.
the most of the computing power is
located in the cloud, in the cloud.
ONOS fund is using two clouds, AWS and
Ner, so it's a multi-cloud configuration.
also, ONOS fund is using the private
data center, so it's quite complex
infrastructure and it's directly
connected to the broker, so it could
be considered as the, connections.
and here we can see the results
of the Onfalos Fund in the period
since January 2022 till now.
so as you can see, Onfalos Fund,
outperforms all benchmarks, yeah, even
the NASDAQ S& P 500 with the great
strong up run in the last period,
in the longer term that the AI based
investments is just more reliable and
also have the much lower drawdowns.
So as you can see, maximum drawdown
of the Onthalos is 3 percent and
maximum drawdowns of the NASDAQ is
over 30%, assuming start in the,
beginning of the January 2022.
And the volatility of the
results is much lower.
And that shows the
power of the technology.
That also shows the power
of the Cloud Continuum.
yeah, so if it's interested for you,
if you find that useful, and, you
would like To use the nebulus or to
start in the open call, please follow
us on, Twitter, YouTube, and LinkedIn.
also visit the Nebulus, cloud website.
There are a lot of information, and as
I said, open call is, open second round,
or the open call is open for submissions.
So if you have the, application,
which is uses, cloud continuum and.
IOT devices and you want to
test it with Nebulus, with full
funding of the cost of adaptation.
That's the unique opportunity
to participate in the second
round of the Nebulus open course.
And if you want to educate in the
cloud continuum or or, other specific
topics, I strongly recommend to visit
the Nebulas Cloud website and, check the
available, reports and training materials.
Thank you very much.
That's all from my side.