Hello, my name is Akim and today I will be
talking about foundation of P2P networks.
Thank you for joining my talk.
I hope, this talk will
be interesting to you.
And today I will be talking about
P2P networks and how they work, how
they can be used in the real projects
and what benefit they bring in our
world and the application we built.
Okay.
Let's start with the.
features, of decentralized P2P networks,
the first feature is, that each member of
the network is equal to any other member.
What does it mean?
For example, in our regular client server
model, where there is a server and there
is a client, the server defines rules,
its API, permissions, and other stuff,
and regulates which client can connect
and which cannot connect, and so on.
And the client, has to abide to
those rules, otherwise the client
cannot connect to the server.
And this inequality, doesn't
apply in P2P networks.
Because in P2P networks, each peer
is equal, and each peer can connect
to others without any limitations.
The second feature of the P2P networks is
that each member communicates to others
directly, meaning that For example,
if there is, three peers, A, B, C, A
connected to B and B connected to C,
and at some point A wanted to connect
to C, it cannot go through B peer.
It has to ask B, do
you know, peer named C?
And B says, yes, I know,
here's, his address.
And then after obtaining an address,
The peer A can connect to C, peer,
and communicate to it directly.
So they cannot use B as a proxy.
Okay.
And the application which utilizes those
P2P networks, they can Like, do a lot of
useful things, for example, distributing
processing power between many peers in
the network, or distributing storage.
And we're not talking about avoiding
bans or limitation based on country
or other kinds of regulation.
So that was networks are
really wonderful in terms of,
distribution and, like new concepts.
So let's, talk about their, components
and describe each one separately.
So overall, there are four components
I decided to underline in this talk.
It's, P2P protocols.
It's application level
protocols, the first component.
and actually this is a very.
big component in terms of, the P two P
protocols, unite a lot of internal stuff.
We'll talk about it.
okay.
And besides p P two P protocols,
there's a second component.
Peer discovery.
it's about finding and
other peers in the network.
Also transports and naturals.
We'll talk about all of this in detail.
On the next slides, let's
start with P2P protocols.
What are those?
Those are an application layer
protocol, which defines basic component.
In P2P networks, each P2P networks
have to, implement, a couple of, I
would say not a couple, a dozen of,
protocols, a dozen of, interface.
Like peer identity, addressing,
messaging, connection logic, peer
discovery, peer routing, and other
stuff, handshakes, transport, and a
lot of other things, and all of those.
Depending on their implementation,
build a structure for P2P protocol.
And also good to mention libP2P
ecosystem, we'll talk about it later,
which, provides basic implementation
for most of these, interfaces.
And, a lot of modern P2P protocols
actually built on top of libP2P.
let's carry on.
There's, Next concept of, P2P
networks is a peer discovery.
It's all about, finding
other peers in the network.
and connecting with each other, like in
the picture demonstrated on this slide.
so when the new peer appears in
the network, first of all, that
peer, has to find other peers.
Otherwise, it cannot do
any useful work for us.
to do That peer would use peer discovery
mechanism implemented in one or other way.
the very popular, peer discovery
mechanism is, for example, Translates,
translating a global message, through
each peer in the network that new peer
has appeared and other peers try to
contact it and share their information
or there are bootstrap peer which has
known and there are bootstrap peer
which has like known list of peers in it
and the newly created peer can connect
to the bootstrap node and ask for the
list of closest network participants.
And after the peer discovery, there is a
very similar challenge is a peer routing
is, actually, when a newly created peer
has to find a way to other peers to
connect through them, to find a like road
and, go through one or other and third,
and peers to reach their destination.
And usually it's implemented by
maintaining a specific routing table,
which is, which has a graph like
structure and used for this purpose.
Okay, that was the second component.
The third component is transport.
transport is, data transfer
protocols like TCP or UDP.
they have, alternative, although,
those two are very popular
and used almost everywhere.
And, good alternative would be
Quick protocol, which, actually an,
implementation, which is layered
atop of UDP protocol and acts like
a WebSocket, WebSocket with UDP.
And also there are modern protocols
like WebTransport and WebRTC,
which are efficient ways of
communication in browser environment.
Very useful.
They're used for data transfer,
for example, video transfer.
And they are really efficient
in this, in these cases.
The fourth mechanism of, P2P networks
I chose to talk about is NAT traversal.
it's a mechanism that allows communication
between public, peer, and peer to peer
networks like laptop connected to home
Wi Fi router, for example, if you like
have a laptop and you're working on it,
and you want to interact with outside
world with the deployed network on some
public machines somewhere in the world,
those public, servers cannot reach you
because your laptop is behind your router.
And, to overcome this, you would,
you can try to configure your Wi Fi.
router, to allow some, to allow accepting,
external connection to your laptop.
But this is difficult for many
users, so that's why, natural
cell mechanism was designed.
there are quite, A few ways to implement
that and very popular one is just
setting up a really public peer, which
are accessible to your private network.
And, if your laptop point to,
interact with the P two P network,
your laptop have to connect that.
Relaypeer and keep a long live
connection and while your laptop keeps
a connection Other peers can communicate
first to Relaypeer and Relaypeer
just redirect data package to you
without Interacting them in any way.
yeah.
that's how they work.
Let's, move on.
good examples of P2P networks.
first example is IPFS.
Also there is a BitTorrent.
Those two protocols are really, popular.
And they're used for file sharing.
Though they are slightly different.
Also there is a Fluence Network Protocol,
which I want to talk today about.
And also very popular Ethereum,
Decentralized Blockchain Protocol.
I hope almost all of you know about it.
The first the first protocol
I want to talk is IPFS.
What is IPFS?
IPFS is distributed system for
storing and accessing files,
website, application, and data.
I would say almost anything
which could be saved, in storage.
And IPFS, means
interplanetary file system.
Okay, let's, let's look at
the IPFS in more details.
yeah, as I mentioned, IPFS as a P two P
networks, it's used for storing data and,
the good use cases is that, for example,
you can store your file in A-I-P-F-S
and that file would be distributed
to any other P of IPFS in the world.
And for example, if, we choose
some, popular centralized
server like Google or Amazon.
And they have some limitation for file
sharing in some countries through IPFS.
You can, avoid those limitations and share
your file everywhere, where internet is
available and other use case would be
much faster, downloading of the file.
Which is also utilized by BitTorrent
protocol, because if your file is deployed
in many places, like many peers in the
network, you can open connections to all
those peers and start downloading them.
content for them simultaneously,
which greatly speeds up, speed
of downloading that file.
there are also a lot of other
features listed in that websites
and, implementation details,
and I really recommend you guys
checking this, IPFS protocol.
It has really cool documentation,
but now let's move to the.
Next slide, and next slide is
about Fluent Network Protocol.
That protocol is about,
workload distribution.
for example, if you want to build
a report or do some computation or
heavy calculation, solve complex
math, sorry, solve complex math
problem, you can use a Fluent Network
Protocol, which can distribute your
calculations and optimize them.
Let's see how it works in detail.
there is a documentation of
Fluence network protocol.
there are some features
like it fast, secure.
let's see how it works.
actually Fluence network
is built of, peers.
Some of these peers are providers which
provide, as you can judge by their name
and provide computer powers and allow
you to utilize that computing power and.
clients, client peer, which
can also work as a providers.
but they also send, like a request
or, express a desire to do some work.
for example, in this, very small
snippet of code, The workload is
very simple, it's just setting status
online, just updating the string, but
it could be much more complicated.
And there is also a specific language,
written for interacting with peers in
that protocol, it's called Aqua language.
And, it, allows specifying execution
model and, allows one to choose a peer
where that code should be executed.
And that's just, really top of
an iceberg of that language.
But the main idea of that protocol
is that, user first write the
code and specify execution model.
And after doing that, the, protocol
allows, the protocol executes
that code and distribute your
workload on many different nodes.
Why is this protocol useful?
It's because it's decentralized.
if you distribute your work through
Fluence, you do not rely on.
Central provider like Google or Amazon,
which can change, like requirements
or conditions and you have to abide.
Otherwise, you have to change your
architecture to other providers,
which could be really time consuming.
and also using Fluent Protocol is
cheaper because there is a free market
and each peer can participate in that.
protocol by proving that it
has necessary powers to execute
your code and other features.
there is also cool documentation, here,
and there are many example projects.
influence, protocol ecosystem.
for example, right now I'm looking
at FRPC substrate example is, it's
a example of application, which,
connects to the centralized apps
and allow, distributing, their.
Access to the RPC, to the
blockchain gates, so we won't talk
about it in details right now.
But if you are interested, feel
free to follow this website, just
Google Fluence and see how they work.
And now we're getting
back to our presentation.
the next slide is about,
additional information.
It's actually about, libp2p.
let's look a bit, what is libp2p.
Like I mentioned before, libp2p
is a great foundation for building
your own, decentralized protocol.
It has a implementation for, many
different, many fundamentals.
Which, almost every, every
decentralized protocol consists of.
For example, it's addressing,
peer discovery, peer routing,
peer identity, peer, info.
There's also some transports.
Secure communication, stream
multiplexing, and a lot of different
stuff, which I mentioned today.
Some of this stuff I mentioned,
some of them I didn't mention.
yeah, it's really good to go
through the documentation.
At least there's some introduction,
passages, and just get a
basic understanding of what
it is and how you can use it.
I believe that's it.
That's all, for today's talk, thanks for
listening guys, see you soon, that's all.
Thank you.