Hello everyone.
Welcome.
I want to talk about something.
A lot of us in the enterprise
analytics space keep running into.
Our design systems just aren't
keeping up with the complexity
of what we are building.
By the end of this talk, I want to leave
you with a framework, a seven layer model
that gives us a much better way to think
about building and scaling these systems.
But before we get into it.
Let me introduce myself.
I'm Sonali Creative
Director at LB Networks.
I have spent over a decade working
across enterprise platforms, so what
I'm about to share with you comes from
real experience watching design systems
work, watching them break and figuring
out what it actually takes to scale them.
When the data is huge, the users are
diverse and the stakes are very high.
Let's get into it.
Alright, so let's start with the problem.
If you have worked on any enterprise
analytics platform, whether that
is telecom, financial services,
healthcare, or infrastructure, you
have already seen these patterns First.
Fragmentation, different teams build the
same charts and dashboards from scratch.
There's no shared component
library that actually handles
what analytics teams need.
So what end up ends up happening
is you end up with a five
different version of the same line
chart, all slightly different.
Second visual drift.
When there's no shared systems, every
team starts making their own decisions.
Things like colors, scales, access
labels, how to display thresholds.
The result is that two dashboards in
the same product can look like they
were built by two different companies.
They don't sync together at all.
And third, governance gaps.
Nobody owns the definition of a metric.
Nobody owns the versioning of a component.
Access control is bolted on after the
fact instead of being part of the system.
And when something breaks
or changes, there's no clear
path for who's responsible.
These are in small problems.
They compound over time and they get
worse the bigger your platform gets.
So it's better to solve from the
very beginning than wait until later.
Now, the standard answer in our
industry has been design systems
and design systems are great.
The typical model has three layers.
You start with primitives, which
is your design, tokens, colors,
spacing, typography, the raw
values of your design system.
In the middle, we have components,
and components are things like
buttons, inputs, cards, models, the
reusable pieces that actually build
the whole component, whole library.
And the last is patterns or semantics,
how those components come together into
a page layout and interaction flows.
This model has been incredibly
successful for consumer apps.
If you are building a social network,
an e-commerce site, a SaaS tool,
three layers will take you very far.
It gives you consistency,
reusability, and a shared language
between design and engineering.
But enterprise analytics
is a whole different beast.
Now, here's where it all falls apart.
Tables.
Tables break at scale.
Your standard table component was
designed for maybe a few hundred rows.
But enterprise platforms routinely deal
with hundreds of thousands, even millions
of rows, virtualization, streaming,
lazy loading, and none of that is built
into a typical design system table.
So what ends up happening is team
builds their own solution, and
now you have lost the whole point
of having a shared design system.
Visuals get unreadable.
A chart that looks clean and elegant with
a hundred data points becomes unreadable
mess with a hundred thousand points.
The three layer model has no option
about aggregation strategies,
sampling, or progressive disclosure.
It just gives you a chart
component and wishes you good luck.
Scalability is the core gap.
The three layer model was
built to optimize for visual
polish and interaction design.
It was not built to
think about data volume.
Query delays are the cost of rendering
a million row data set in the browser,
and maybe the most frustrating part
is there's nothing drop in and go.
You can't just grab a component
off the shelf and have it
work with your data pipeline.
Your metric layer or access controls
teams end up stitching libraries
together by hand, and what you get
is something which is very hard to
maintain, is inconsistent and doesn't
flow together with your entire product.
We know why it breaks, so now let's
talk about how to actually fix it.
So what I'm proposing
is a seven layer model.
It keeps the foundation of the three
layers we already know, but extends it
with four additional layers that address
the realities of enterprise analytics.
Let me walk you through the
stack from bottom to top.
The bottom two tokens and UI
components are familiar from the
previous three layer design system.
That's the most design systems already
cover, but layers three through seven
are where the real work happens.
Let me take you through each one of them.
Layer one is your design token foundation.
This is where everything starts,
the atomic values that every
other layer references to, but
for analytics, tokens need to go
beyond the usual colors and spacing.
You need dedicated data visualization,
color palettes, sequential scales,
diversion scales, categorical
scales, purpose built for
readability in charts and dashboards.
You need density modes.
A dashboard packs much more information
into a smaller space than a typical mobile
application or any other app screen.
Your token should adapt titrate, spacing.
Smaller type, denser layout
depending on the context.
You also need semantic tokens
that carry meaning not just blue
and red, but threshold exceeded.
Anomaly detected.
Target met.
The token layer should encode
intent, not just appearance.
And these tokens should compile
to every platform you ship on.
CSS, iOS, Android, Figma,
from a single source of truth.
One definition, many outputs.
Layer two is UI components, things like
buttons, inputs, selects, models, tabs,
breadcrumbs, the standard toolkit.
This layer is important and it should
be built entirely on top of your tokens.
No hardcoded values.
Every components pull its own
colors, spacing type from layer one.
But here's the key thing to
understand about this layer.
These components are unaware of data.
A button doesn't know whether it's
filtering a million rows or submitting
a form and input doesn't know if it's
selecting a metric for consumer products.
This layer plus tokens is
usually enough for analytics.
It's just the starting point.
This is where most design systems stop.
We need to keep going.
Layer three is where
things get interesting.
These are data components, UI elements
that know they're handling data at scale.
This is your virtualized table
that can handle a million rows
without choking the browser.
This is your query builder,
your filter panel metric
picker, your dimension selector.
These are components that
understand data types.
That know how to paginate
stream and lazy load.
They are stateful by design.
They handle loading states, empty
states, partial data error boundaries.
They don't just render data.
They manage the whole life cycle
of getting it, displaying it, and
recovering when things go wrong and
the support personalization users
can configure columns, save views.
Set defaults without breaking
the shared definition underneath.
This is the layer that most
directly addresses the table.
Break at scale problem.
If your design system doesn't
have data where components.
Your team will build their own,
and then you have lost consist.
Okay, next is layer four, which
is visualization primitives.
And I want to be clear,
this is not a chart library.
This is the layer below the charts.
These are the building blocks that
charts are assembled from things
like scales, legends, grits.
Tooltips.
These are the composable pieces that are
put together to create a line chart, a bar
chart, a scatter plot, or even a heat map.
This layer defines your visual
encodings, how data maps to position,
color, size, and shape, and it does
so with accessibility, built in
colorblind, safe palettes, pattern
fallbacks, screen reader support.
It also handles the hard problem of
what to show when you have more data
than pixels, aggregation rules, sampling
strategies, level of detail switching.
These decisions shouldn't be
made ad hoc by individual teams.
They should be encoded in the
system, and it includes interaction
perimeters, things like Zoom, brush pan.
Linked highlighting basically the
building blocks of how users physically
interact with a visualization layer five
is I think, the most underappreciated
layer and possibly the most important.
This is semantics and interpretation.
What does the data actually mean?
Here's the scenario that happens in
every enterprise analytics platform,
I have seen three different teams
build three different dashboards.
All of them have a metric called revenue.
None of them calculate it in the same way.
One includes refunds and other doesn't.
One uses net, one uses gross.
One calculates it daily, while
other calculates it weekly.
The semantic layer solve this.
It's a single source of truth for
what each metric means, how it's
calculated, and what units it uses.
It also encodes thresholds and benchmarks.
What's a good value?
What triggers an alert?
What's the target?
These rules should live in the
system not in someone's head, and
it creates a shared vocabulary.
When a designer, a data engineer, and
a product manager say, churn rate, they
should all mean exactly the same thing.
This layer makes that possible.
Layer six is workflow patterns.
This is about how users actually
explore and interact with the software.
The flows, not just the screens.
Drill down and drill across.
A user sees a spike in a summary chart
and wants to understand why they click
to go deeper from country to region,
from region to city, from city to store.
The system should have a
standard way to handle this.
Cross filtering.
When you select a segment in
one chart, every other chart on
the dashboard filters to match.
This sounds simple, but doing
it consistently and keeping the
performance across platform is hard.
It should be a pattern, not
something every team reinvents.
Explore to dashboard.
A user does some ad hoc analysis.
Find something interesting and
wants to save it as a persistent
dashboard that they can share.
That transition from exploration
to artifact should be smooth and
standardized and comparative views,
period over period, segment over
segment, baseline versus actual.
These are fundamental analytics workflows
and there should be patterns in the
system, not custom implementation.
Layer seven is governance, and I
put this at the top intentionally
because without governance, everything
underneath is just a component library
that will eventually drift apart.
Governance has four pieces.
First, an ownership model, every
metric, every component pattern
has a named owner, not a team.
Not a slack channel a person.
Accountability prevents drift.
Second, versioning discipline.
When someone changes the definition
of a metric, that's not a bug fix.
That's a change to history.
It needs semantic versioning, migration
paths, and clear communication.
Third access and sensitivity
controls, data classification,
and role-based access.
Should be part of the design
system itself and not something you
bolt on at the application layer.
And fourth, a contribution workflow.
How do new components get proposed?
Reviewed, accepted and maintained?
How do old ones get
deprecated and retired?
This needs to be a defined
process with quality gates.
So here's how it all fits together.
Think of it as a pyramid.
At the base, you have your design tokens.
The widest layer, the most foundational,
everything out of depends on these values.
UI components sit on top of
the tokens, data components
sit on top of UI components.
And visualization.
Primitive primitives sit
on top of data components.
Then you get into the higher order layers.
Semantics give meaning to
what the lower layers render.
Workflow patterns define how users move
through the system, and governance sits
across the top, providing control and
accountability for the whole stack.
Each layer has a clear job.
Each layer depends on the ones below it,
and you can adopt them incrementally.
You don't have to build all seven at once.
Speaking of which, let's talk about how
you'd actually adopt this foundation.
Start with design tokens and governance.
These are the cheapest layers
to implement, and they give
you the highest leverage.
Tokens give you consistency from day one.
Governance gives you the
structure to grow without chaos.
Data scale, invest in data components
and visualization primitives.
Next, this is where your
users feel the pain most.
If your table can't handle the data
and your chest are, and your charts
are unreadable, nothing else matters.
Semantics.
Then unify metric definition across teams.
This is organizational work as
much as it is technical work.
It takes time, it requires buy-in,
and it's worth every minute.
Then patterns, and finally,
layer in workflow patterns.
Don't try to prescribe these upfront.
Watch how users actually use the system.
When you see the same flow repeated
across three teams, that's when
you codify it as a pattern.
So let me leave you with four
things to take back to your team.
One.
Three layers are not enough for analytics.
The standard primitives
components and patterns model
was built for consumer apps.
It ignores data volume, semantic
complexity, and organizational governance.
Second, seven layers give you the full
picture tokens, ui, data visualization,
semantic workflow governance.
Each has a clear job and
none of them are optional.
If you want a system that actually scales
three, governance is not a nice to have.
It's the difference between a
design system and a folder of
components that nobody trusts.
Ownership, versioning and access
control are what make the system real.
And four, start at the edges.
Work inwards, tokens and governance.
First, data components
next, and patterns last.
You don't need to try to
boil the ocean at once.
The bottom line is this, build
systems that scale with your
organization, not just with your data.
Pick one painful layer and fix it.
Track reuse rates, consistency
scores, and time to dashboard.
If you can't measure whether
the system is working, you can't
improve it and govern consistently.
A design system without governance
is just a component library.
With good intentions.
So that is all I had to share.
Thank you for listening and I would
love to hear how you're thinking
about this in your own platforms and
what's working, what's not, where's
you're seeing the biggest gaps.
You can find me on LinkedIn and thanks
again and enjoy the rest of Con 42.