Hi everybody.
I'm Greg Lind, CEO, and founder of.
build these a software
architecture as a service, company.
We have, open source products
and, products, labs, which is our,
product management through ai.
And, Product managers,
human as human oversight.
Also, managing partner at Open Build where
we do, open source management programs
and mentorship programs for junior
developers to senior and senior to CTO.
but we're here to talk about,
radical therapy for software teams.
we wrote this book over the last
couple of years, but the focus on
it, was really about transparency,
and how to use that as a team, tool
to build for, successful teams.
it's a lot about the fusion of dev
and product teams, which is also
what we've built into Build Link.
it's a big.
milestone for us because we've
also added that to our, AI built-in
knowledge for our product manager.
So you can actually use the tool and
get some insights from the book as well.
but we'll go into in depth
today a little bit about.
How to get started with,
radical transparency as well as,
therapy for your software teams.
and we will get a little more,
deeper into what those mean.
So radical, obviously for us, it
means something that's, fundamental,
changing something at a drastic
and a far reaching effect, right?
not radicalness in Jeff, right?
So we're not talking about surfers,
we're talking about radical.
It's a big change.
And therapy.
obviously I'm not a licensed therapist,
but I do see a lot of, software
developers in my, as a manager
and as I work with as colleagues.
that need help often, outside of work
sometimes, but related to work, having
to deal with things and you start to
feel, if you've ever managed a team
or if you've ever managed a product,
you know how it can feel sometimes.
Like you're also helping.
I. Folks through struggles, you're helping
them, to build their trust, accountability
with them and with each other.
so a lot of times you feel like
a professional therapist, right?
But maybe you just play one on TV
or play one in product management.
So we'll go into a
little bit more on that.
but let's start with the transparency.
specifically the principles, but
transparency, first off, which is really
just about open communication, encouraging
clear and honest dialogue with each
other and with your team as well as
with the larger organization, right?
Transparency, however you're working, if
you're on a startup or a big organization.
Having a clear and transparent
process as well as, open dialogue
with the rest of the organization's
only gonna help remove blocks.
I think the other side of this is
data-driven decision making, right?
So collecting data and using it
for how, for your product to make
it better as well as help to even
improve your process and your team.
So part of this is about taking things.
From Agile and other things like that
and adapting it to use it in a cloud
native way, a microservice driven way
maybe, but also multi repository way.
And how to use that to better
make decisions when you get data,
and be able to apply that to
your decision making processes.
Part of that's feedback, ongoing feedback
throughout your process from your team,
as well as eventually your customers
and bringing that into the process.
And then, inclusivity and diversity.
I. diversity in terms of perspectives, as
well as, diversity in terms of the types
of folks you're bringing into your team.
ensuring that all of
those voices are heard.
and really part of the diversity
approach to this is also about just
getting those different ideas, right?
Hearing, different perspectives gives
you a better product as long as you're
willing to actually adapt and use those.
and then bringing your backlogs.
Product backlog and merging it
with your developer backlog, right?
So having one process where everybody's
seeing where everything's doing
it, and that's a lot of what we do
with product labs at ly, but it's
also just about a simple way to do
that in terms of process overall.
So we wanna break down silos.
Be more efficient.
promote cross-functional communication,
collaboration, and then share insights
between DevOps, product teams,
managers, developers, all of that,
transparency, optimization, and,
reduce your time to market, right?
Build something, do it
quick, and then, but focus on
quality and focus on feedback.
That's really the best approach
for this is, and starting with that
is data-driven decision making.
So helping you to make decisions faster.
one of the best ways to do
that is to get feedback, And
bring that into your process.
And then you are also getting higher
engagement and retention that way.
People that feel invested in a product
are people that feel like their voices
are heard in the process, as well as
just feedback in terms of what they
like about the product and what they
would like to see in the future.
you're also reducing
conflict and resolution time.
When you're bringing in, you can show
a data point and you can show how
to get through a conflict by just.
Showing to them, to a team member,
to a, a customer, to a manager.
If you can show them data,
they're obviously gonna be
able, much easier to persuade.
So some companies that bring this
decision making process and radical
transparency in Atlassian's a great one.
Google has a great, process where they
bring in, Teams and cross-functional
teams that share, developers to
share members across each one, right?
So they move back and forth.
They all have the same process,
but they learn from each other
by sharing team members across.
Zappos is another one that had the
same sort of process and, Trust
and ethical AI implementation.
IBM and their fairness, 360 and Netflix
and their responsible AI toolkit.
I'm not sure how much they're still
implementing that at Netflix anymore,
but, they do have some great processes
around how to, bring responsibility in ai
and that helps you bring, better data and
better decision making processes, right?
So key steps.
Establish a culture of open communication.
again, that means, sharing what
you've done right from day one.
the scary thing for developers when
they come work with us at LY is,
day one, you need to commit code.
I. It doesn't matter what type
of, product you're working on
that we need to see that commit.
Go into a branch, that's your branch
and you're gonna get feedback on it.
It's gonna be a little scary at first.
it's definitely unusual for some.
But, we also focus on,
positive feedback, right?
And making people feel good
about those steps, getting those
first movement into this process.
Again, data decision making
processes accessible.
So that means, not only
do you need to share.
What you're doing, but how you
came to that decision, right?
So where did that come from and how to
make that more accessible is just by
opening up your process, opening up your
backlog to your team, to your customers.
everyone should have access to
that and encouraging that feedback
and asking for it, asking for
criticism, hopefully constructive.
but certainly within your team, you can
ensure that it's constructive criticism.
And then, introduce transparent
performance and compensation policies.
So a lot of team conflict, doesn't
revolve around compensation, but
within an organization, within a
management, if somebody's unhappy,
usually it's because of compensation
or it's because of people that they're
having to report to or sometimes
too many people to report to, right?
So being transparent around
performance and how to get better.
And sharing those compensation policies
and showing people how to move forward
both within your team and within
your organization, and then integrate
those transparencies into product
development along with AI ethics, right?
So everyone's using AI for something now.
you need to make sure that when you're
testing that ai, it's not just about.
the LLM that built it, right?
You need to test it both from your
production standpoint to see what
people are, actually sending to
your ai, models and then also from
your own, processes and tools.
How are you actually testing it before
it goes out, and how are you making
sure that those ethical compliance
tools are embedded in that process
so that you're making sure that.
It's not weighted in one direction
or that it's not, doing something
that you don't even know when
it's suggesting to your customers.
let's talk a little bit about
enhanced innovation and problems.
So diverse teams bring
very perspective, right?
So what we wanna look for in diversity is.
Innovation, right?
So in diversity helps drive
innovation and problem solving.
So diverse teams bring varied perspectives
leading to more creative solutions
and better decision making processes.
Stronger team performance and
productivity in inclusive teams
prove, this is a McKinsey report that
showed that 35% better performance by
leveraging different experiences and
skills versus non-inclusive teams.
That means.
If you have a team that's diverse and
has a lot of different perspectives,
you're getting better performance as well
as a better product out of that, right?
And as a variety of skills.
Along with that, better representation
and market reach, a diverse
team reflects the reality of who
you're trying to sell to, right?
So the, if you want to build something
that's user friendly and competitive,
diversity's gonna help with that, right?
Who's this guy?
This the cheerleader, right?
So what, when we say we're talking
about, Being positive, right?
And we're talking about being, an
encouraging person on your team.
It doesn't mean go out and be rah,
yay, and super positive all the time.
it means trying to keep your team
positive by helping them with ways that
help sometimes, especially software
developers aren't comfortable, talking.
Communicating.
But helping them get out of their
shell, helping them get out and
be part of the team is important.
And that means doing that in a careful
and thoughtful way, and not in a,
in your face kind of way, right?
So team morale is important.
You wanna focus on trust.
Safety when somebody's in that team
promote transparency and with team
members, but also try to reduce the stress
and workplace anxiety around it, right?
Encouraging open communication
with daily check-ins.
Those can be online in Slack,
which most people are doing now.
If ideally, you're doing it
face-to-face so that you can
adjust, right there real time.
But if you're not, online is great as
long as people are actually reading.
Those contributions.
A lot of times when we do Slack check-ins,
I'm the only one that reads those things
and you, that's great because I can
help remove some blocks and then I can
go back through and make some changes.
But you really need to get your
team involved in making sure that
they're reading that as well.
Celebrate wins and reduce
burnout and frustration.
A clear one of the goals around.
This whole process has been to
help people feel more comfortable,
within teams and feel like they
have a path forward, and upward.
And one, the, one of the ways to do
that is, is to really celebrate and
show growth, but also really focus
on folks that are down like that are
having a rough time helping to bring
them up, both from your process and
your giving them clear goals, but
also just from how you work with them.
What tools are they working with?
Maybe they're getting, Over, burdened
with too many tools, or maybe they're,
they don't have the right tool yet.
so a lot of it's about that as well.
And then empowering folks with
autonomy and ownership, right?
Employees have access to
information and decision making.
They feel more accountable and invested
in their work, and that helps them.
To feel like they're part of
that team, they're part of that
product and they wanna see it grow.
They want to see it get better, right?
So you wanna run a product like
a lean startup and run a startup,
like an open source project.
How do you do that?
And why would you do that?
One?
It encourages sharing work openly
and asking for feedback, right?
That's what open source projects want.
Like maybe they aren't great about
adapting to it, or they get overwhelmed
by it a lot of times, but that is
what they want and that's how we wanna
bring that process back to a startup.
Same thing with the startup.
A project that you're working on
inside your organization, right?
A larger organization still needs to feel
like there's communication, like there's a
path forward, for everybody and promoting
a community that, con contributes
to that creates innovation, right?
Every organization wants
to have innovation.
They wanna drive that in their
products, in their projects, and
that means bringing that process in.
And emphasize the importance of
building inclusive communities while
you're doing that helps you bring
innovation, but also helps you bring
everybody along with you and embrace
competition, build new markets, right?
you don't, just because I.
Something existed already, doesn't
mean you can't make it better.
Why not build a better mousetrap?
I hate that analogy of don't try to
build a better mousetrap, but the
reality is there's plenty of products
that are okay, but they don't quite fit.
So make the product you want.
And if it's not in the marketplace,
go out and do it in the open.
Start sharing it right away, or build
your dream product and then share it.
Obviously you wanna bring the users
along with you as much as you can,
as early as you can, but I. Don't be
afraid to build something just 'cause
there's already a version of that.
I, my least favorite thing that
people say to me about, but
this tool already does that.
Yeah.
But it doesn't fit for my needs.
And that's okay.
they're gonna want competition
'cause it opens up their market.
So we want to, we wanna
focus on innovation.
We wanna focus on getting things better.
That means going ahead and building
some that better mousetrap.
You said opposite example of someone
who built something very privately, a
potentially very innovative product.
but everything was hidden from the
users and it was difficult for every,
everyone involved to understand.
'cause there was no transparency.
So Theranos a very.
Famous story for most people in the
startup world, really in any product
world, was built behind closed doors,
hiding things from investors because
they weren't making the progress that
they thought they would, trying to keep
it proprietary everywhere they could.
And using the old fake it till you
make it approach, which in the end.
Really came back to bite them.
So transparency would've helped a
lot from the very beginning, right?
Building something from the start.
Who knows where they could be?
Now?
now, I don't know if they, I obviously
was not involved in this, but I don't
know if they had a better product
in mind and it just didn't come
through or the idea was to fake it.
But I don't think so.
I think they were trying to build
something truly revolutionary and it just.
One person had too much control,
hid things, and was just not
able to make it happen, right?
So lesson learned, hopefully
for a lot of people.
so let's talk about the
radical process, right?
So we know Agile, scrum, lean,
all of these different, tools.
and they work great for a
lot of different situations.
but I think.
In a cloud native environment,
there's some things that
are missing in that, right?
I think, one of the things that
we wanna focus on in our process
is building trust with the product
team and the development team.
agile tins and Scrum tends
to separate you out, right?
You've got the pigs and the
chickens and all the different
things that they talk about there.
And the reality is we're all
coming, need to come together
to build that product, right?
But not everybody needs access
to everything all the time.
But they do need some sort of
idea of what's going on, how
to work with that product.
They want to be able to ha put their
voice into it, but they want, they
wanna feel like it's constructive
and they're not interrupting.
So clear communication, bringing the
process back to the development cycles,
but also bringing it back to the product
management cycles, the marketing cycles,
the design cycles, all of that into one.
Radical process, right?
Where we're building
everything from the start.
We're not building artifacts, we're
not building documentation necessarily.
We're building a product that means
stakeholders are included from the
beginning, and that's developers
are stakeholders too, right?
Product managers are stakeholders, as
is management, and C-E-O-C-F-O, all
of those people, especially marketing.
Need to be involved in at certain steps.
So the more clear you are, the more
open you are from the very beginning,
the easier it is to bring them in.
aligning your team across all of
these different silos helps to
remove those silos when you need it.
And then bringing that feedback
in, right Surveys, bringing in
through, process tools, bringing in
through direct demo days, so that
you can actually show progress.
and when you make a mistake,
be open about it, right?
And let people know.
'cause the worst thing that can
happen is there's a mistake out there.
There's a bug that brings
down part of your application.
Hopefully just part of it, not all of it.
and.
You didn't tell anybody and they
find it, it's much easier if
they know ahead of time, right?
It's hard.
It's a hard lesson to learn, but that's.
The best thing you can do.
And then when you do make that fix and you
do get that first release out, celebrate
that with your team, with your users.
again, don't be a cheerleader, but
just, acknowledge those wins because
they're sometimes few and far between,
but you still wanna be able to show
that the team's making progress, So
it's not about the tools necessarily,
but it is also about the tools, And for
us, building labs where we do product
management and communication, that our
whole process is about removing those
silos and letting people in without
having to directly connect them.
So one of my least favorite.
Problems is when a CEO has access
directly to a developer, right?
Or a developer is asking
questions of a product manager.
They don't know how to answer that, and
so they go to the CEO or the manager and
have them talk directly to the developer.
that can be distracting for everyone
involved, and nobody wants to be involved
at that level necessarily when they're
thinking about high level things.
So bringing, breaking down those
silos, sharing code from the very
beginning again, like we talked about,
and then communicate through Slack
or whatever tool you like, but making
sure that is updated consistently
and everybody has access to it.
Now bringing philosophies and politics
and everything else into a, an
organization is not a good idea usually.
But I think when you're talking about
finding the team that fits best, right?
And openly communicating, like some of
that is about stakeholder inclusion, but
it, some of it's also about transparency
and why are you involved in bringing that,
that up right from the very beginning.
So open communication.
Builds trust, right?
With customers and your team.
Transparency tends to attract
like-minded individuals, people
that also like transparency and it
brings loyalty to your employees.
I think you, loyalty can
be a bad word for sure.
I. You don't like, but what you do
want to have is people that want
to see that product succeed, want
to see your organization succeed,
including them from the very beginning.
That's how that happens, right?
So start small, really gradually
scale up your transparency efforts.
but don't be afraid to bring it to your
organization, whatever that size it is,
and start to get buyout from the top down.
open build is a product and
a organization that's really.
dear to me in terms of its approach
to open source, helping open source,
as well as helping developers learn.
So it's a thing that's missing a lot in
organizations right now is, mentorship.
So open build is a place to
do that if you're interested.
again, check out the GitHub
repository, come back and talk to us.
we're expanding quickly with that.
We've got a lot of different developers
going through that process, and
we're always looking for more.
the Product Foundry again, build Lee
is focused on all of the ideas that
are inside of the Radical Therapy book.
but it's also partly, built
around a process that's
documented in that book as well.
if you're interested in learning more
about Build and our Foundry program for
startups as well as just products in
small, who wants to learn more, and, yeah.
Thank you very much for listening.