Good morning, afternoon, everyone.
My name is Sampa ou.
I am a senior technical advisor
at Microsoft, where I work on the
front lines of Azure infrastructure
support, helping enterprise customers
troubleshoot, optimize, and operate
complex cloud environments every day.
Over the past several years, I have seen
firsthand how cloud operations have.
Today I want to share what the
transformation looks like from the
inside, not as a product page, but
as an operational reality that's
changing how my team and I work.
Let's get started.
The title of this session is AI
Augmented Azure Ops, Co-Pilot for
Intelligent Cloud Resource Management.
The key phrase here is augmented
not automated, not autonomous.
This talk is about how artificial
intelligence and human expertise work
together to manage, diagnose, and optimize
Azure environments at enterprise scale.
Everything else shared today is
grounded in real operational experience,
what works, what does not, and what
teams should know before adopting
AI assisted tooling in production.
Let's start with the problem.
Azure today spans hundreds of services
and thousands of resource types.
When an incident occurs, an engineer
might need to check the virtual
machines configuration, look at the
attached discs, review network security
groups, inspect metrics in Azure,
monitor query logs in log analytics.
And trace dependencies across
resource groups all before they
even begin root cause analysis.
That's the manual navigation
overhead we deal with daily.
On top of that, telemetry is fragmented.
Metrics are in one place, logs in another,
configuration, data in yet another.
There is constant context switching.
When you scale that across hundreds
or thousands of resources, operations
trial becomes the dominant cost,
not the infrastructure itself.
What teams really need is faster
root cause identification,
unified visibility, and reduced
cognitive load on routine tasks.
That's the gap.
Copilot is designed to fill here.
What we will cover today.
First, I will walk through the
problem space, why traditional cloud
operations are struggling to keep up.
Then we will look at co-pilot's,
architecture, how it combines large
language models with live Azure Telemetry.
Next, AI and observability.
How contextual diagnostics and natural
language interfaces change the day-to-day.
Then the piece I feel most strongly
about human oversight and safeguards.
And finally, practical implementation,
guidance, and key takeaways you
can apply in your own enrollments.
Let me break this down into four specific
pain points I encounter regularly.
First manual navigation overhead.
To diagnose a single virtual machine
issue, an engineer may need to traverse
10 or more portal blades, multiply
that by the number of incidents in a
day, and you see how time compounds
second fragmented telemetry as you
monitor log analytics, resource graph.
They're all powerful tools, but they don't
naturally talk to each other in context.
You, the engineer, are
the integration layer.
Third dependency blind spots.
Understanding how a change in a storage
account affects an app service that
depends on it across subscriptions that
requires deep environment knowledge
that not every team member has on
day one and forth operational to.
Routine tasks, like right sizing
VMs, reviewing policies and triaging
alerts consume a disproportionate
amount of engineering time that
could be spent on higher value
architecture and optimization work.
So how does copilot
change this as its core?
Copilot introduces a natural language
interface directly integrated
into the Azure control plane.
Instead of navigating to the metrics
played, selecting the right resource,
choosing the right metric, and setting
the right time range, you can simply
ask, show me the CPU trend for this
virtual machine over the last 24 hours.
But the real differentiator is
not the natural language part.
Each, the copilot is grounded
in your live environment.
When it answers, it's not giving
you a generic wristband from the.
Training data.
It's pulling from your actual resource
configurations, your actual telemetry,
your actual policy state and critically.
This is a human AI collaboration model.
Copilot augments your judgment.
It does not replace it.
Engineers retain full control.
Let's go a layer deeper
into the architecture.
Think of it as three concentrate layers.
The outer layer is the Azure
control and response layer.
This is where live telemetry, resource
manager, APIs, and resource data live.
The middle layer is the
natural language interface.
It receives your queries, captures
context, like what resource you're
looking at, and passes that to the core.
The core is the LLM engine.
It interprets your intent, performs
a reasoning over the context
provided and generates a response.
The critical insight here is that
the LLM alone is not sufficient
without the outer layer grounding it.
In the real infrastructure state,
you would get generic answers.
The architecture ensures that
every response reflects what's
actually happening in your systems,
not generalized assumptions.
This is the slide I want you to remember.
If you remember nothing else.
Governing is what makes
AI operationally useful.
A generic AI can tell you what might
cause ICPA ground A can tell you your
specific virtual machine is hitting its
UNC cash throughput limit because these
specific disks are at their IOPS ceiling.
The grounding sources include Azure
Resource Graph for live inventory and
relationships as you monitor log analytics
for performance metrics and logs.
Resource manager APIs for current
configuration and policy state
and diagnostic telemetry for
edge and cloud health signals.
Without this grounding, you
have a chat bot with it, you
have an operational copilot.
Now let's talk about what this looks
like in practice contextual diagnostics
through conversational ai, this is
where copilot collapses multiple tool
pivots into a single interaction.
We can query configurations, ask
about which emission sizes, network
rules, scaling settings without
navigating the portal manually.
You can analyze performance surface
CPU, memory latency metrics in context
so you understand whether observed
behavior is normal or anomalous.
You can understand dependencies map
how resources connect and how a failure
in one end compound could propagate.
And you can drive optimization, get
targeted context aware, right sizing and
cost reduction recommendations based on
actual usage, not theoretical benchmarks.
This is where the daily
operational value is most tangible.
Let me give you some concrete
operational scenarios.
Instant triage.
Why is my app service showing
elevated latency in uset s?
Copilot surfaces 11 metrics, recent
configuration changes and dependency
health In one response configuration
review list, all storage accounts
without private endpoints, you
instantly query policy compliance
across subscriptions without writing
a single KQO query Cost optimization,
which VMs in my dev environment have
been underutilized for three days.
Actionable right sizing recommendations,
and this extends beyond traditional cloud.
Copilot can help manage troubleshoot
arc, enable infrastructure.
At the edge.
The common threat is that natural
language becomes the universal
interface for cloud operations.
Now, and I want to be very direct about
this, copilot is a collaborative system.
Human engineers are not
removed from the loop.
We define the quality, reliability, and
trustworthiness of AI generated insights.
In my role, I see this daily
telemetry validation engineers.
Must verify that the signals copilot
references actually reflect system
behavior, not misleading noise.
Design review.
When copilot faces architectural
suggestions, it takes a technical
advisor's judgment to evaluate whether
that recommendation fits the customer
specific constraints, SLAs in business
context and troubleshooting guidance.
The internal runbooks and
playbooks we build as.
Experienced engineers help
guide AI reasoning toward
operationally sound recommendations.
AI is only as good as the
human expertise surrounding it.
AI and production demands governance.
Without it, AI generator
recommendations can mislead engineers
introduce configuration rift or
bypass change management controls.
So what safeguards does copilot
implement first explainable responses.
Copilot surfaces the reasoning
and data sources behind each
recommendation so engineers can validate
before acting second, read first.
Design copilot queries and explains.
It does not make changes.
Changes are always initiated and
confined by a human operator.
Third, Azure are back integration.
Copilot cannot surface data.
The user is not authorized to view.
It respects existing
role-based access controls.
These are not optimal futures.
They are what make AI assisted operations
enterprise ready and trustworthy.
So how do you get started?
My advice, go incremental.
Don't try to adopt AI across
every workflow on day one.
Step one, establish telemetry baselines.
Ensure Azure Monitor, log, analytics
and Resource Graph are fully configured.
Co-pilot's quality is directly
proportional to the quality
of your observability data.
Garbage in, garbage out
applies here more than ever.
Step two, start with diagnostics,
use cases, instant triage
configuration queries, policy reviews.
These are tasks.
Where AI exploration delivers immediate
value with minimal operational risk.
Step three, build internal guidance.
Develop prompt patterns and internal
playbooks that help your team get
reliable, relevant responses in
your specific and environment.
Step four, expand to
optimization workflows.
Once your team is comfortable extend
co-pilot's role to cost optimization,
capacity planning, and proactive
reliability recommendations always
with human review at each step.
Four key takeaways I want
you to leave with today.
One.
AI augments not replaces.
Human engineers remind the decision
makers and the essential quality layer.
Two context is everything.
Grounding in live telemetry and actual
configurations is what separates
useful insights from generic output.
Three.
Governance enables trust.
Our back explainability and
audit trails are non-negotiable
for enterprise adoption.
And four, start small, iterate fast.
High frequency, low risk tasks first.
Build guidance, validate, telemetry,
and expand based on results.
Before I close, I want to emphasize that
what I have shared is not theoretical.
This is the operational reality.
I leave every day at Microsoft
helping enterprise customers
manage some of the most.
Complex Azure environments in the world.
AI is not replacing the
enterprise or expertise we bring.
It's amplifying it.
And I believe the teams that embrace this
human AI collaboration model earliest will
be the ones best positioned to operate
at cloud native scale with confidence.
Thank you all for your time today.