Hello, good morning and welcome to
Conference 42, Cloud Native 2025.
My name is Krithvi and we are going
to discuss today about demystifying
cloud technologies, harnessing scalable
data analytics for enterprise growth.
So today we are going to discuss
about cloud technologies and how we
can, how enterprises can leverage
the advantage of cloud computing and,
and then, improve their business.
Transform your businesses with
cloud powered data analytics.
Discover how modern cloud solutions can
drive innovation, optimize operations,
and accelerate your enterprise
digital transformation journey.
cloud computing, so it comes
as, as a package components.
So main components are
infrastructure as a service.
Platform as a service.
Cloud compute technologies are
revolutionizing how enterprises
handle process and extract
value from data analytics.
So real time analytics
organizations can now analyze.
data in real time, enabling instant
business insights and data driven
decision making as infrastructure
as a service enterprises, enterprise
grade computing resources on demand,
offering scalable virtual machines
and stories that grow with your needs.
so in this enterprises
need not to investor.
Much on their infrastructure.
So they just, utilize, utilize the,
storage that they needed at the beginning.
So and then increase as
their business grows.
So platform as a service, cloud offers
pre configured environment, environments
and tools that, dramatically reduce.
Deployment time, enabling
teams to focus on innovation.
So here, it, there would be a pre
configured or pre, pre developed tools
so enterprises can use those tools and
then, they are ready made available.
readily available and, they can
use the software, so instantly.
They don't need to invest, time,
buying new softwares or, or to
cover their business requirements.
Cloud service models.
Cloud, computing offers three
service models that provide different
levels of control and functionality.
So infrastructure as a service,
IAAS, called IAAS, provides on demand
computing resources, including, servers,
storage, and networking, offering
maximum control over IT infrastructure.
So in this way, so the companies need
not invest on their infrastructure in the
beginning, second, platform as a service.
The cloud offers, cloud technologies
offers a complete cloud based development.
environment, removing infrastructure
management overhead to speed up
application development and deployment.
Third, a software as a service
delivers ready to use applications
via internet, eliminating installation
and maintenance while providing
immediate access to software.
So software will be, readily available,
so you don't need to, invest on,
softwares, So Infrastructure as a
Service, Scalable Infrastructure.
So, Infrastructure as a Service,
delivers virtualized computing resources.
Through internet, giving enterprises
full infrastructure control without
hardware management or head.
So hardware will be managed by
the cloud systems cloud, companies
so that, uh, clients or business
owners, they don't need to, spend
money on that platform like, aws.
Easy.
Two google cloud com.
Google Cloud, compute engine
provide a secure global distributed
computing power that enables high
performance analytics while maintaining
enterprise security standards.
Scalable, when it comes to scalability,
instantly just computing resources
to match workload, demand of.
business or company that needs
more resources on demand so they
can increase their, resources.
so, for a specific period, and then they
can, decrease, their resources so that,
they, they have the flexibility, of, using
more resources when needed and, Reduce
the resource size when it is not needed
so that they can optimize some of the
cost, our resources and when it comes to
flexibility, custom configured operating
systems, security and performance
settings so we can always configure,
security components and performance
settings as per the business needs.
So it has, got more flexibility
so you can implement, on demand
security, additional security
features, and performance settings.
So cost effectiveness when it comes
to, pay only for those resources used
while eliminating the capital expenses.
So, organizations and enterprises,
they don't need to invest.
more in the beginning, so they can
only pay, for the services they, use,
not that, entire, services that comes
as a package, platform as a service,
so it offers accelerate development,
so development and deployment,
platform as a service, platforms
accelerate application development.
example include Microsoft Azure App
Services, AWS Elastic, being tack,
reduce time to, insight, by up to 40%.
So rapid deployment, quickly
deploy and manage applications.
So deployment time would be.
So shortened.
so it's, it's very, it takes less
time to deploy automation, automate
the data pipeline task so you can
automate the processes so that, so
you can, you can schedule, To run them
on a specific, time where whenever
the more resources are available or
based on the, availability time, which
suits your business, collaboration,
enhanced team collaboration.
So, you can collaborate, With our
different teams, which works, which
availability will be 24 by seven.
So, you can collaborate, with multiple
teams working from different time zones.
Software as a service,
real time analytics.
SAS applications, empower
business with real time analytics.
Salesforce and Google
Analytics are popular options.
Improves operational efficiency
by 30 percent or more.
Data visualization.
Visualize data for better insights.
so it comes, with a pre configured or
pre analytical tools, or pre configured
analytical tools, which Gives, more, most
of the business analytics, capabilities,
on demand and in a ready mode.
ready made, ready made, package.
So, you can, use, those, pre configured
or pre, pre configured, tools and, you
can visualize the data, on our demand.
AI driven insights.
Leverage AI for, smarter decisions.
it also comes with the
AI, algorithms, tools.
which, gives much more, insight, of the
data so that the users can understand.
They can do calculations, they
can do some predictive analytics.
So, they can, businesses or users
can, understand, the data in a much
more simpler and, effective way.
Operational efficiency,
streamlined business process.
operational efficiency is more,
as, these are proven technologies
or proven tools and, stream,
streamlined business processes.
Cloud Analytic, use cases.
Cloud based analytics is
revolutionizing how enterprises
extract value from their data.
Organizations leverage advanced
analytics to drive strategic decision
making and operational excellence.
Here are three transformative
applications that demonstrate
the power of cloud analytics.
First one is predictive modeling.
So leverage machine learning to
forecast market trends, demand
patterns and business outcomes
with unprecedented accuracy.
So second one is a fraud detection.
Use real time pattern recognizing to
protect against financial fraud and
security threats across digital channels.
Third, third example is custom customers.
Segmentation.
Analyze behavioral data to create
precise customer segments for
personalized, marketing campaigns
and improved, conversion rates.
Forecoming, cloud challenges.
So obviously there would be challenges
when shifting from traditional,
traditional, onshore or traditional,
infrastructure to cloud infrastructure.
As organizations migrate to cloud,
they face critical challenges that must
be strategically addressed to ensure
successful digital transformation.
Understanding and proactively
managing these challenges is essential
for maximizing cloud benefits.
Security.
Protecting sensitive data from cyber
threats and unauthorized access.
While maintaining business
continuity and customer trust.
Second is a compliance meeting complex
regularity requirements across different,
jurisdictions while insurance data
sovereignty and privacy standards.
Cost optimizing cloud Spending through
proper resources allocation, preventing
unexpected expenses and maintaining
budget control, which is most important.
If you don't plan these, resources,
I had you may end up spending
more budget on the cloud services.
So this is a critical challenge that
many of the organizations will face.
But it can be optimized.
It can be controlled with
much planned with a good plan.
Successfully navigating
these challenges requires.
A comprehensive strategy that balance
security measures, regularity compliance
and cost optimization efforts.
Organizations must develop
robust frameworks and policies
to address each, aspects while
maintaining operational efficiency.
Strategies for, cloud governance.
effective cloud governance
requires a comprehensive
framework that ensures security,
compliance and cost optimization.
and optional, optimal resource
utilization across your
organization's cloud infrastructure.
Success depends on implementing well
defined protocols, establishing clear
accountability structures, and maintaining
vigilant oversight of cloud operations.
Organizations must balance Agility
with control by creating scalable
governance mechanisms that adapt
to evolving business needs while
maintaining strictly security standards.
Maximize cost and
performance optimizations.
Maximize return on investment
through resource optimization.
Continuous monitoring and compliance.
Track usage patterns and
ensure regularity alignment.
Foundation policies and standards.
Establish a core governance framework.
The future is cloud based, so most
of the companies are enterprises.
They're shifting, towards the cloud
based as, it reduces, their operational
hands, especially maintaining the
infrastructure and, software services.
By 2025, a remarkable 83 percent of
enterprise data workloads will migrate
to cloud, making a fundamental shift in
how organizations, manage and process.
Information cloud platforms are
driven business operations by
streaming, seemingly seamlessly, in
introducing AI and machine learning
capabilities, enabling organizations
to automate complex process.
predict market trends and
deliver personalized customer
experiences at scale.
Through cloud powered business
intelligence, companies can transform
raw data into actionable insights.
Enabling real time decision making,
predictive analytics and data driven
strategy, and development across
all organizations level in cloud.
in this graph, you could see, cloud-based
applications, is, expected to grow.
our out, our out phase,
on, on, on premises.
On for instance, services.
So, here are key takeaways.
Cloud technologies transform
enterprise data analytics by enabling
scalability, real time insights and
advanced automation capabilities.
Choose the right service model,
infrastructure as a service, platform as
a service, software as a service based
on your organization's specific needs.
for control flexibility
and managed services.
Implement robust security measures
and maintain regularity compliance
through comprehensive governance
frameworks and continuous monitoring.
Drive business value by optimizing
cloud cost through efficient resource
allocation, automated scaling, and
strategic work, workload management.
Thank you.
Hope you understand my concept.