Welcome everyone.
I'm SJ Opin Kani Technical
Program Manager at Walmart.
I have two years of experience working in
drone deliveries and autonomous vehicle
deliveries for Walmart and integrations
with Google Wing, Zipline, and Drone Up.
Today we are going to explore how
autonomous delivery and multimodal
fulfillment systems are reshaping
the future of Cloud Native Commerce.
Over the next 20 minutes, we'll
journey from the core problem driving
this transformation through the
technologies, enabling it to the cloud
native architectural patterns that
make it all work at enterprise scale.
This is a topic I leave and
breathe every day at Walmart.
We are not just talking about
theory, but actually deploying
these systems in production.
Let's get into it.
Here is our roadmap for next 20 minutes.
We'll start with the problem.
Why last mile delivery is fundamentally
broken and what's driving the
urgency for autonomous solutions?
Then we'll drive into three core
autonomous modalities, how they
work together in multimodal systems
and cloud native architecture.
That makes it all orchestrate reliably.
We'll be honest about the barriers.
Regulatory infrastructure and
environmental, and I'll walk you
through the risk analytics framework
we use to make deployment decisions.
We'll close with real world
industry deployments and a
look at where we are headed.
Let's start with the scale of the problem.
Last mile delivery.
That final link from distribution
center to doorstep accounts to 40 to 50
percentage of total logistical costs.
This is not a small inefficiency.
It's a structural tax on
every e-commerce transaction.
There are four compounding pressures.
First, cost, labor and fuel dominate
last mile spend, and driver wages
continue climbing second scale ceiling.
In dense urban environments, congestion
creates routine inefficiencies that no
amount of driver scheduling can solve.
Third, reliability.
Human workforce variability means SLA
Promises are hard to keep consistently.
Fourth, environmental cities from
London to Los Angeles are imposing
low emission zones that are making
traditional diesel delivery vans.
Operationally restricted to our
windows are becoming the expectation.
Autonomous delivery is not just a
efficiency play, it's a survival strategy.
I. Sidewalk robots are the
most pub, publicly visible
autonomous delivery technology.
They are compact platforms
designed to operate on existing
pedestrian infrastructure.
No new road access or
airspace authorization needed.
Their operational suite spot is
hyperlocal, typically one to five
miles from a fulfillment node
carrying payloads around 15 pounds.
Perfect for groceries, pharmacy
items, and convenience goods.
They move at walking space,
which means they are safe in
mixed pedestrian environments.
The cloud dependency is critical.
These robots rely on low latency, 5G
or lt, or time obstacle detection,
remote supervision and routing updates.
Loss of connectivity is a failure mode.
The platform must handle gracefully.
The technical challenges center
on unstructured environments,
steps and curb cuts are obstacles.
Snow covered sidewalks, construction
diversions, and crowded pedestrian
zones all require sophisticated
real-time path planning.
GPS Signal degradation in urban canyons
means these robots must rely on sensor
fusion, combining LIDAR cameras and tric.
Rather than GPS alone, despite
these challenges, sidewalk robots
represent the most immediately
deployable autonomous delivery solution
for defense urban environments.
Drones represent the most disruptive
delivery modality because they
simply bypass the problem that
ground-based fleets can't solve.
Congestion.
The value proposition proposition
is not straightforward.
Fly to point, deliver in under 30
minutes and do it independent of
whatever is happening at ground
level with traffic for origin.
Deliveries of lightweight items,
pharmacy orders, over the counter
medications, forgotten grocery items.
Drones are unmatch.
But the constraints are real.
Payload is limited typically
around five pounds.
For most commercial platforms.
Weather sensitivity is significant and
the regulatory landscape is complex.
Federal aviation agency
governs most US operations and
beyond visual line of sight.
Authorizations, which are
needed for scale are granted
sparingly and wary by corridor.
The cloud integration point is the
unmanned traffic management system, UTM.
Operating drone fleets at scale requires
real-time airspace, conflict resolution,
weather monitoring, and dynamic rerouting.
This is inherently a cloud native problem.
If sidewalks, robots are the most
visible, and drones are the most dramatic,
autonomous trucks are the most mature.
The reason is straightforward.
Highway driving is fundamentally simpler
than urban or pedestrian environments.
Route predictability dramatically
reduces edge case complexity.
Fixed warehouse to store corridors mean
the autonomous system can be trained
and validated to a non environment.
The result, fully driverless, commercial
deployments are already in production.
Walmart's partnership with
Gatti is the proof point.
Autonomous box trucks move goods
between Walmart facilities on fixed
middle mile route in Arkansas.
No safety drivers.
No human redundancy.
This is not a pilot.
It is production.
The economic cases compell.
An autonomous truck amortizes its
capital cost over hundreds of thousands
of deliveries while labor cost scales
linearly with volume For human driven
alternatives, fleet orchestration
is the cloud native layer that
makes this work scale telemetry,
ingestion, dispatch optimization,
remote oversight and predictive
maintenance, all require distributed,
scalable crowd infrastructure.
This is where things get really
interesting and genuinely hard.
Multi-model orchestration means
coordinating handoffs between different
autonomous systems in real time serve.
Robotics and wing are piloting in Dallas,
which is the leading real world example.
A sidewalk robot picks up packages from
a micro fulfillment node and furries them
to an auto loader station At the station.
Packages are transferred to drones
that complete the aerial final
delivery to the customer's door.
This approach.
Plays to each technology strengths,
the robot handles the segment where
ground navigation is straightforward.
The drone handles the final delivery
where speed matters the most, and
ground obstacles are bypassed,
but the coordination challenges
substantial transfer station handoffs
require sub minute arrival position.
Realtime scheduling must account for
order velocity, robot availability.
Weather and drone capacity simultaneously.
All agents, robots, drones, cloud systems
must share a consistent view of state
and when any modality fails, a system
must reroute without dropping orders.
Even driven architecture, shared
state management and fault tolerance.
Platforms from cloud native engineering
are directly applicable and essential.
Now let's get into the architecture.
There are three layers that
every autonomous fulfillment
system must address.
At the top, the cloud orchestration
layer, this is the brain.
It handles fleet management order,
state telemetry, ingestion for dozens
of hundreds of field agents, route
optimization and remote supervision.
This layer must be horizontally scalable,
highly available, and observable.
Every major cloud native A
applies here, microservices, even
streaming distributed databases.
The middle layer is edge coordination.
This is where low latency
decis decisions get made.
When a robot needs to avoid
a pedestrian, it can't wait
for a round trip to the cloud.
Edge compute handles local routing
decisions, obstacle resolution,
and cross platform handoffs.
The edge layer must operate
with partial cloud connectivity.
It cannot fail when
network conditions degrade.
The bottom layer is the fleet, the
physical agents, robots, drones,
trucks, all carrying onboard edge
compute sensors and activators.
They communicate up to the edge
layer and cloud, execute decisions
locally and report state continuously
the four design principles that
make this architecture production
grade modality, obs abstraction.
So orchestration is
delivery agent agnostic.
Graceful degradation.
So single mortality failures don't
cascade even driven coordination.
So subsystems scale independently and
unified observability, so you can trace
any order across any agent at any point.
Regulatory recommendation is arguably the
biggest barrier to autonomous delivery,
scaling, and unlike technical challenges,
you can simply engineer your way past it.
For drones, the Federal Aviation
Agency governs the US airspace.
Commercial operations require part 1
0 7 certification and beyond Visual
line of sight operations, which are
necessary for fleet scale delivery
require individual waivers that are
granted inconsistently across corridors.
Remote ID is now mandatory
adding another compliance lever.
For autonomous trucks.
While a federal framework exists,
state level permits are still required.
In many jurisdictions, Arkansas,
Texas have led the way in regulatory
acceptance, which is why you see
the most advanced deployments
concentrated here for sidewalk robots.
It is genuinely a city by city patchwork.
San Francisco and New York City have taken
very different approaches, weight limits.
Speed variations, permitted
zones all vary by municipality.
The implication for cloud native
systems, regulatory compliance
must be baked into the platform.
Geofencing must enforce regulatory
boundaries in real time operations
in different jurisdictions, require
different rule sets dynamically applied.
This is a software problem as
much as it is a policy problem.
Two more barriers deserve
attention, infrastructure and
environment on infrastructure.
Autonomous delivery requires
physical and digital prerequisites
that simply don't exit at scale.
Yet reliable.
5G or LT connectivity
is known, negotiable.
These systems cannot operate in
areas with poor connectivity.
Coverage.
Drone landing zones need to be established
at delivery endpoints, which is
challenging in dense urban environments.
Charging stations for robot and drone
fleets need distributed placement across
service areas requiring city coordination.
And sidewalk surface quality
directly impacts robot performance.
Infrastructure that was not designed with
autonomous robots is in mind, creates
operational friction on limitations.
This is a constraint that's
often underestimated.
Drones are grounded in high
winds and heavy precipitation.
Lidar and camera performance degrades
in rain, fog and low light snow
covered sidewalks or obstacles for
wheeled robots, the cloud native
implication, fallback orchestration,
must be built into the platform from
day one when weather ground drones.
The system must automatically
reroute to ground modalities.
SLA commitments must be dynamically
adjusted based on real-time
environmental conditions.
Static delivery promises are incompatible
with weather dependent autonomous systems.
Effective deployment of
autonomous delivery requires
structured risk assessment.
We use a four quadrant framework
that requires operational, technical,
strategic, and marketing market risks.
Operational risks are the day-to-day
concerns, platform failures.
Handoff timing issues, fleet
reliability, during demand spikes
and remote supervision latency.
These are the risks you manage with Fleet
Redundancy, SLA, buffers and Fallback
protocols, technical Risks Center on
Sensing and decision making stack.
Sensor degradation in weather, GPS loss,
cybersecurity vulnerabilities, and edge
cases the model has not seen before.
Mitigation requires sensor
fusion, adversarial testing,
and conservative operational
policies for degraded conditions.
Strategic risks are the planning horizon,
challenges regulatory uncertainty
making capital allocation difficult.
Technology obs excellence,
risk, and the timing question
of first mover versus follower.
At Walmart, we take a portfolio
approach betting across multiple
technologies and partners, rather
than committing to a single bet.
Market risks include labor opposition,
public trust, insurance frameworks,
and infrastructure dependencies.
These are often underweighted in technical
conversations, but are frequently
what delays or derails deployments.
The framework also supports scenario
analysis, evaluating deployment
outcomes under alternative risk
realizations, which feeds directly
into Go NoGo decisions for new markets.
Let's grow around all of this in
what's actually happening today.
Walmart and gat.
This is the clearest proof of
production ready, autonomous delivery.
Fully driverless commercial trucks
running Middle mile roads in Arkansas.
No safety drivers.
This is not a pilot.
It's ongoing commercial operation.
Walmart and Wing, the world's largest
commercial drone delivery expansion,
operating in the Dallas Metro.
30 minute delivery targeting
for lightweight packages.
This one is actively scaling seven 11
and neuro suburban convenience delivery
Using custom-built autonomous vehicles,
the use case alignment is excellent.
Small local time-sensitive
orders map perfectly to
autonomous vehicle capabilities.
Serve robotics and wing.
This is the Multimodel pilot that is
generating the most innovation, interest
and robo mart worth mentioning as the
most conceptually differentiated model.
Rather than delivering products,
the store comes to you.
What's notable across all of these,
they are not just experiments, they
are generated real operational data and
informing architecture decisions that will
define the next generation of fulfillment.
The business case for autonomous delivery
is isn't just about the technology,
it's about economic trajectory.
This chart illustrates
the crossover dynamic.
Across costs.
Human driven delivery costs
trend upward as wages rise.
Autonomous delivery costs trend downgrade.
As technology matures and scale
increases, these curves are
converging and in many middle mile
applications, they have already crossed.
The 24 bar seven operations advantage is
significant and often underappreciated.
Autonomous systems can smooth
demand across the full day night
deliveries without premium pay.
Off peak utilization of fixed
assets, human operated delivery
concentration concentrates in narrow
windows due to labor constraints.
Creating artificial demand
spikes, geographic expansion
is a real revenue opportunity.
Rural areas with dispersed poli
populations are currently uneconomical
for traditional delivery Drones eliminate
the per stop labor cost that makes low
density route financially prohibitive.
And the competitive lock-in dynamic
is important for timing decisions.
The retailers and logistics companies that
move first, accumulate operational data.
Build regulatory relationships
and establish customer trust.
The companies that will wait
face the cost of replicating what
early movers build organically.
The question is not whether to
invest in autonomous delivery.
It is when and with what
portfolio of technologies.
Let's look at the
trajectory in three phases.
In near time now through 2027,
we are in the foundation phase.
Pilots continue expanding geographically.
Middle mile fully autonomous delivery
will be the norm for leading retailers.
Regulatory frameworks are
beginning to stabilize.
Multimodal handoffs are being proven
in select markets from 27 to 2030.
The scale phase, last male autonomous
systems grow in urban and suburban areas.
Drone networks expand to suburban
delivery corridors where regulatory
approval is more achievable.
Infrastructure investment
accelerates as successful.
Pilots demonstrate ROI
in from 2030 to 2035.
Full integration.
In major markets, autonomous
delivery ecosystems become
the primary fulfillment model.
30 minute delivery transitions from
premium service to baseline expectation.
Micro fulfillment centers combined
with autonomous last mile, become
the dominant retail structure.
Let me close with four things I want
you to take away from this session.
First.
Autonomous delivery.
Is production ready today?
Not in five years, not
as a research project.
Fully driverless commercial
operations are running right now.
The question is no longer if it's
how fast and with what architecture.
Second, multimodal coordination is
the next competitive differentiator.
Optimizing a single delivery
modality gets you efficiency gains.
Orchestrating multiple
modalities intelligently.
Robots handing off to drones, trucks,
seeding micro fulfillment nodes gets
you a step change in what's possible.
Design your orchestration layer to
be modality agnostic from the start.
Third, cloud native
architecture is not optional.
The systems that make autonomous delivery
work at enterprise scale telemetry,
ingestion, distributed state management.
Edge compute, unified observability
are cloud native problems
with cloud native solutions.
This is the engineering domain where
the competitive advantage gets built.
Fourth, the barriers are navigable.
Regulatory complexity, infrastructure
gaps and environmental constraints
are all real, but they are solvable
with a systematic framework.
The right market partnerships
and staged deployment planning.
The future of fulfillment is autonomous,
multi-model, and cloud native.
The infrastructure decisions you
make today will decide whether
you lead that future or follow it.
Thank you.