Hey everyone, my name is Maximilian
Kawek and I want to welcome you all
to my talk on how to run powerful,
scalable, and ultra budget apps on AWS.
First, I wanted to say
a few words about me.
I am a full stack AI software engineer
at Perlin with around five years
of experience in the field, and
I've worked with plenty of various.
different technologies I've started
with monolithic infrastructures,
Java and standard databases.
Then I moved on to more of the modern
tech stack with plenty of cloud computing,
also serverless infrastructures,
microservices, and all of the newest bits.
And today I wanted to talk to
you a little bit about what I've
learned, especially on how to.
minimize the costs, without sacrificing
too much, of your time in regards to
development, but also, in regards as to
scalability and also the possibility of,
the possibilities of the infrastructure
that you would actually develop.
Now, I just briefly wanted to
mention the agenda of the things
that we'll talk about today.
And in general, we'll be trying
to answer the question on how to,
basically focus on ultra budget AWS.
Is it possible?
And if so, what are the possible
downsides of the, of this?
thing of this idea of this concept.
And then we'll also in the meantime,
talk about the key components of the
infrastructure, how to do the cost saving
techniques, most, most efficiently.
And also what are the possible trade offs.
I also have one, real world
breakdown, a cost breakdown prepared
from one of our applications that
we're running at our company.
And yeah, let's get into that and
we'll talk about all of those things.
So why UltraBudget?
Who is it for and why should
you even care about this?
So if you're a multinational,
corporation, which spends thousands of
dollars every month on AWS, additional
20, 30, or 50 probably won't make
that big of a difference to it.
But if you're a cost conscious team
or an indie developer, or someone who
just wants to develop a side project
or an MVP, then Ultra Budget is
definitely in my opinion, the way to go.
And it's.
It's can prove to be an additional
perk that you can deliver such quality
product and such maintain easy to
maintain product at such low costs.
And we of course need to look and
tackle the challenges of traditional AWS
setups, which the biggest thing is that.
If you basically let AWS manage
everything and you want to have everything
provisioned all the time, then this will
of course be reflected in your AWS bill.
So we need to keep those
two things in mind.
And my solution to this is to basically
strategize how to use which services.
And basically, you can supply
them with cheaper or even free
alternatives in some cases.
here you can see the architecture
overview that I want to present to you.
as you can see, it's one of the
probably simplest and easiest
solutions to deploying a full
stack web application on AWS fully.
But what I want to emphasize here
that as you can see, it's still like
quite modular and quite expandable.
So for example, it's not, the type of
all in the one solution, like Amplify,
which AWS tries to encourage you to use.
And where you're basically then fully
locked in, not even to the vendor
as AWS itself, but rather to even
the specific service and it's quite
difficult to migrate out of it.
So what I definitely prefer on my end
is to basically modularize the things.
And, yeah, I just like to
quickly go over this overview.
So as you can see, for example, for my
type of ultra budget AWS infrastructures,
what I always use is, I use GitHub
actions for the DevOps pipelines, which
basically deploy the whole application.
And I don't need to worry about
all of the, infrastructure for it.
It's quite simple and efficient.
Also, it's free as is important
in this regard in this topic.
And what I then do is I use AWS as
CDK, which is basically a really simple
infrastructure as a code tool where
you can, declare all of the components
needed, the connections between them,
pass the information between one
and the one and the other, and then
you don't basically need to go into
AWS console ever to set anything up.
And what I have inside of there is
the actual AWS infrastructure that
I want to show to you, show to you.
And yeah, as you can see, first of all,
we're like going, through the whole flow.
What we have is we have a front
end, which is in my, manner, usually
a React application hosted in an,
basically stored in an S3 bucket,
which is then connected to CloudFront.
This, yeah, I suppose we'll go
into the detail in a little bit.
So I will just go briefly
between, through the whole flow.
This then communicates directly
with Cognito, using its JavaScript
libraries, like Amplify, but not to.
not to mistake it for the actual
AWS Amplify tool, service, which
are a little bit, which are,
the, disconnected in this regard.
it's this, it then connects, it then
sends a REST request, but of course
you can use, every type of API you
can possibly imagine with this.
And then it sends a REST
request to API gateway.
which, works as a middleman
for, our authorization layer.
And it takes a little bit of the, of
the accountability and all of the, also
a little bit of the responsibility of
handling the actual request from the
Lambda, which it then directs it to.
So basically API gateway,
I have set up as a proxy.
And then it's, it proxies this,
requests to Lambda, which is one
of the more interesting things
that I want to talk to you about.
But this Lambda is also running an AWS
Lambda Power Tool, module inside of it.
Which is a really useful Python
package that I will introduce
to you in just a second.
And then of course, this Lambda
API is your main center of the
backend of the application.
And then it can connect
to whatever it needs to.
In this example, I
wanted to show you that.
for example, for some cases, which
we'll discuss in a second, I'm,
connecting it to DynamoDB and in some
other regards, it needs to communicate
with an EC2 instance with, for
example, PostgreSQL installed on it.
So regarding the specific bits of the
infrastructure that I wanted to talk.
to you about a little bit more in detail.
first of all, we've got the front end,
which is hosted on an S3 bucket and then
connected to CloudFront and those two
components are connected to Cognita.
So this gives us a really like
bare bones, simple structure
type of hosting of static files.
Because after you build your node
project, it can be hosted as such.
for example, on an S3 bucket.
Then what we use is we use the
CloudFront, service to provision,
to give us basically HTTPS for free.
that's one of the things, if you
don't have the domain yet set
up, it's the, simplest solution.
And other perks that it offers
is, for example, the global
caching and fast access.
yeah, there is, it's basically
a free or a really cheap
because it's only cost you per.
hundreds of gigabytes transferred, but
unless your website weighs it on, it
won't be a problem in this scenario.
And those components communicate with
Cognita, which handles user sessions.
also the authentication and it.
provides you all of the necessary
keys to actually communicate with
the rest of your application.
Next, we're going to briefly talk about
the core backend of our application,
which is running AWS Lambda with the AWS
Lambda PowerTools package on top of it.
And what Lambda is it's basically a
serverless cloud computing platform.
which, enables you to run your code
basically virtually for free, unless
you're using it, for hundreds or
thousands of hours every month.
And, yeah, what are the
biggest advantages of it?
Why are we picking it right here?
comparing to some other,
like more traditional.
Types of applications like running a flask
or a Django or fast API Python application
on an EC2 instance or running it in a
cluster and managing maybe those, training
them to scale them down to zero when there
is no traffic on the, on your platform.
what Lambda does is it offers us great
simplicity for those type of solutions.
Also, you don't need to worry about.
any infrastructure management at all.
And it's automatic scaling is
perfect because it basically
doesn't run when it's not called.
So once you're even, once your request
finishes, it's processing in this
Lambda, it will come back to zero
and it won't cost you any more money.
And there are a couple of challenges,
of course, to keep in mind.
some of them are, as mentioned here,
for example, as you can see, the cold
starts where you, if you've got a really,
I would say heavy in size Lambda and,
plenty with plenty of large files, you
then need to keep in mind that it will
take a little bit longer, a couple
seconds, for example, if you haven't
started your Lambda in production.
in an hour, or if there were no requests
hitting it, then it needs a second to
basically heat up and to come back to
life and to serve your users, still.
And the other things are
the stateless execution.
So there isn't any, if there isn't
anything like a server session, basically
on Lambda, because every request is
handled as a total separate entity.
And of course there are some
deployment memory limits.
So you can't basically host
huge applications with plenty of
dependencies and packages on it.
You need to keep all of
those things in mind.
And what is Lambda Power Tools?
It's a great package that
I've stumbled upon recently.
And, before I introduce it, I want
to, briefly explain to it, to you
what is the biggest challenge in
my opinion when developing APIs on
Lambda without packages like this.
And it's basically the boilerplate code.
So when you're hitting
an AP, an AWS Lambda.
You need to somehow manage the requests,
the types of requests, the bodies of
those, the methods that are being used,
the paths that are being sent to, because
if you have a lambda as a proxy, basically
every request that your frontend sends to
an API, it goes to this one single lambda.
And how I did this once in the past, which
I definitely regret is with a huge list
of L if statement, basically checking the
string paths parameters and basically be
the whole code base being a huge mess.
And, yeah, there, there are a couple
of ways to, to of course, omit that
and to make the development process
much nicer and much more develop,
developer friendly, I would say.
one of those that I used for a
moment is basically, using Flask, or
fast API on Lambda, which are like
wrappers that allow you to write.
flask like code with the
function decorators, specifying
paths and methods and basically
handle it that for the Lambda.
But this is a really, I'd say, messy
workaround, which, incurs additional
issues and potential bugs because you
don't like flask wasn't built for that.
So you're just, launching this.
It's like trying to launch this package,
that is meant to run on the server.
And that was built to run on the server
in a stateless cloud environment.
So you basically, definitely
misuse this quite a lot.
And, it's just unnecessary,
a huge dependency for that.
And what is AWS Lambda Power
Tools is basically the perfect,
replacement for all of those things.
And what it is, it's an AWS developed
tool that allows you to write a Flask
like code and FastAPI like code, but with
the Lambda thing being in mind first.
So they basically did, build this exactly
for this to simplify the, procedure of
writing code on lambdas and to simplify
it and to make it much easier to debug,
to run, and to maintain in the future.
And, some of it's.
features that are available to every one
of you is my favorite one, which is the
event handling, which I just described.
And then it also enables you to make it
a little bit easier for your application
to keep track of logging, tracing.
Also, we've got some neat Python specific
features like validation, parsing, typing.
So your whole code makes
much more sense right away.
And now I wanted to talk to you a little
bit about different database solutions
that I'm considering every time I'm
building an infrastructure on AWS.
And first I wanted to introduce you
to DynoDB, which is a simple NoSQL
key value based database, which is
my preferred solution for anything.
that can be a reliably run on it.
and what it is I would probably
compare it to, a Lambda in terms
of, in the realm of databases.
It allows you to pay only for the
traffic also, of course, for the storage.
but unless you're, gathering
huge amounts of data.
Still, again, it won't be a cost.
You probably will be kept in
the three tier limit of AWS.
And it allows you to also forget
about the whole infrastructure,
the whole setup, and you only pay,
for the amount of traffic and the
amount of data that you actually use.
And it's also really efficient.
It has really low latency and it
allows you to be really flexible.
So.
objects can, different differ between one
table and another, of course, that, this
can lead to some challenges in production.
Great applications.
If you really need to, have all of
the data structures properly, then
you need to keep the, storage of the
model somewhere, but this can still
be done in your applications code.
So it can be aware of which, fields,
are, for example, always present
there or, and which might be missing.
Of course, you can still run
migrations on this table, but those
are done using, just using Python
scripts that you can execute there.
And another, type of database that
you can run, of course, with still
having the budget in mind is, at least
in my example, PostgreSQL on EC2.
the default way suggested for, by
AWS and by most users is to, use
RDS, which is relational database
service, or, yeah, service.
And, the biggest challenge with that
is it's quite difficult to keep, to
make it cheap and to make it not,
costs like at least 15 to 20 per
month, even if you don't use it at all.
If you don't have
anything running on there.
And, the answer to that, in my
opinion, is, self hosting a database.
Because you can, what you can do
is you can run a really cheap EC2
instance that will cost you, even
the free ones do well enough, I would
say, but if you decide for a little
bit more of a powerful one to handle
more connections, for example, to the
simultaneous connections to the database.
Then still, it will cost you about
two, three, 4 maximum per month, and
then you've got an unlimited basically,
database, unlimited in terms of traffic,
of course, because for the volume, you
will still need to pay a little bit.
the biggest challenges of that, of course,
are the maintenance and backup management.
that you need to do on your own and that's
basically the cost of, not paying AWS to
do this, by themselves on using our, RWS.
But in my opinion, it's still worth
it because once you set it up, then
you can basically forget about it.
And yeah, if you have a low traffic
application that needs an SQL
database, that might be the way to go.
it also allows you to, of course,
be a little bit more custom
and to adapt it to your needs.
So for example, if you need some vector
stores or those types of things, you
can easily install them there as well.
And that's something that
DynamoDB wouldn't allow you to do.
And, yeah, to finalize my talk and to
show you a little bit of an example
cost breakdown and the summary, it's
basically, as you can see, this is a
receipt from AWS bills, to one of our
applications that, we are currently
in a building in an MVP phase.
And as you can see, the total cost of
the whole application was 3 per month.
That's something that's
now easily achievable.
If you follow all of the principles
that I've mentioned, of course,
adapting them to your needs.
Of course, if you have, much
more traffic than we did, then
it can be a little bit higher.
But, yeah, unless you go, from one day
to another, scaling the application for
hundreds and thousands of active users,
nothing like this should or could happen.
And yeah, this is basically
the summary of my talk.
So I wanted to show you how to run the
ultra low, low total cost application.
As you can see, this is.
It's easily a production ready system
that you can introduce to your client
and yeah, unless they need to make it
much more future proof or unless they
need to implement their own hundreds
of thousands of custom functionalities
using specific services, then you can
rely and basically build on top of that
base architecture that I showed you.
yeah, the serverless is the
way to go in my opinion.
in this.
regard, if you're not going to, if you
don't want to spend most of your time
worrying about how to set everything up
and how to maintain it and back it up, I
would say, yeah, using as much, as many,
serverless services is the way to go.
Unless of course, those are the
expensive ones that you will be paying
24 hours a day for just being present
there like RDS, which we tried to omit.
And yeah, there are a plenty of
services that are budget friendly
and it can be cost efficient if you
try it, if you try to be with it.
And I think that would
be the end of my talk.
Thanks a lot for listening to
me, listening to my presentation.
I hope you liked it and I hope
to see you all in the future.