Hey everyone, thank you
for joining me today.
So today we're going to talk
about something exciting.
How cloud native analytics is
revolutionizing the way we use big data
to drive real time product insights.
So in this session, we'll explore
why traditional analytics fall short,
how cloud native approaches make a
difference, and how this transformation
can drive business success.
So let's dive in.
So now that we've set the stage,
let's take a quick look at
what we'll be covering today.
So we'll start by discussing
the Big Data Challenge.
as in why businesses struggle
with traditional analytics.
Then we'll define cloud native analytics
and how it enables real time insights.
Next, we'll explore why real time
analytics matters, followed by the key
technologies that make it possible.
Then I'll share a real world example of
Uber, showing how they use cloud native
analytics to drive business success.
Then we'll go through an implementation
roadmap for businesses, outlining
the steps to get started.
We'll also touch on challenges
and considerations, because no
transformation is without obstacles.
Finally, we'll wrap up by
looking at future trends and
summarizing the key takeaways.
So we are in an era where data is being
generated at an unimaginable scale.
Every day, businesses, devices,
and users generate about 328
million terabytes of data.
What's the challenge?
Traditional analytics and their systems
weren't designed for the speed of volume.
They often rely on batch processing,
meaning decisions are based on
historical rather than real time data.
So this gap between data
generation and actionable insights
creates a real business problem.
And that's delayed decision making.
Missed opportunities and inefficiencies.
So cloud native analytics
is a game changer.
Unlike traditional systems that struggle
with scaling, cloud native solutions
are designed from the ground up to
handle massive, dynamic workloads.
They leverage serverless computing,
meaning you and only you use resources
when needed, making it cost effective.
They use containers and microservices,
making them modular and scalable.
And most importantly, they enable real
time streaming analytics, allowing
businesses to act on data instantly
rather than waiting hours or even days.
So why does real time
analytics matter so much?
Because in today's world, being
fast is being competitive.
Take Netflix or Spotify.
Real time analytics drive their
personalized recommendations.
And think about fraud detection.
Banks need to act on suspicious
transactions immediately,
and not hours later.
Even product teams benefit from this.
So companies using real time insights
can tweak and improve their offerings
based on live user feedback.
So to make real time analytics
possible, we need the right
technology stack firstly.
That's number one, event streaming
tools like Kafka or AWS Kinesis.
are able to process massive
amounts of live data.
Number two, serverless computing
ensures resources scale automatically,
which optimizes cost and performance.
Number three is data lakes and
warehouses, which act as the foundation
storing vast amounts of data, which is
structured or could be unstructured.
And number four is AI and ML. And they
really supercharge analytics by turning
raw data into predictive insights.
So whether it's forecasting
demand, identifying risks, or
personalizing experiences, AI
and ML are where you look at.
So now let's take a look at Uber.
I think this is a perfect example
of real time analytics in action.
Uber doesn't just use static pricing.
Instead, they analyze demand in real time.
And if a major event occurs
Ends and demand quickly spikes.
Uber's analytics engine instantly adjusts
pricing to balance supply and demand.
They use Kafka to stream millions
of riot requests per second and
Flink to process them in real time.
Finally, they use Databricks
for deeper insights.
And what's the result?
Smarter driver allocation, reduced
wait times, and optimized pricing.
This is all thanks to
cloud native analytics.
So how can businesses actually implement
real time analytics in a practical sense?
This is not about ripping
and replacing old systems.
It's about strategically modernizing.
Step one is to identify where
your data is coming from.
Customer interactions, IoT devices,
transaction logs are just a few sources.
But there could be many more.
Step two.
Step two is implement real time
ingestion tools like Kafka or Kinesis.
Step three is to store data in
a scalable cloud data lake, so
no more rigid databases anymore.
Step four is to use serverless computing
and AI to process this data efficiently.
And step five is to surface insights
through real time dashboards and
alerts, so teams can act immediately.
Now, of course, no transformation
is without challenges.
So what are the top challenges we can see?
Number one is latency issues can arise
if data pipelines aren't well optimized.
Number two is cost management
can be very critical.
So real time analytics can be expensive
if not, architectured efficiently.
And number three is data security and
compliance could be a big concern,
especially in highly regulated industries
like banking, finance, and healthcare.
But with careful planning, businesses can
navigate these challenges effectively.
So looking ahead, we're going to see even
more innovation in real time analytics.
Edge computing will push real time
analytics closer to the source, whether
it's through IoT devices or smart sensors.
AI driven automation will further
reduce human intervention, and this will
enable fully autonomous decision making.
And multi cloud strategies
will become the norm.
Allowing businesses to be more
resilient and avoid vendor lock in.
So to wrap up, cloud native analytics
isn't just a buzzword, it's a necessity
for businesses looking to stay ahead.
Organizations that embrace real time
insights will outpace competitors,
optimize their operations, and
deliver superior customer experiences.
Now it's the time to invest in
the right technologies and start
your real time transformation.
That's my time.
Thank you.