Hey, everyone.
I'm Shesanath Bala Venkata.
I'm a senior manager and I build
data products and that takes care
of data engineering with Comcast.
So today's talk is about cloud computing
cost shutdowns, how we will save
millions of OPEX dollars optimizing
AWS EMR and Databricks workloads.
So let's dive into the talk.
So
the agenda for today's talk is We'll
dive into what is Databricks and what
are the Databricks cost optimization.
Then what is AWS EMR?
What are different types of
AWS EMR features is available
and offerings are in market.
And we'll look at what are
the AWS EMR cost optimization.
So what is Databricks?
So Databricks is a cloud based
unified analytical platform, which
is built on top of Apache Spark.
so Databricks build, bring, ease of
use on top of Apache Spark, where it
has like a lot of, UI capabilities
on top of it and it has, it can
leverage for data engineering and
machine learning and huge, data, big
data processing and the key features.
Of the Databricks are
Apache Spark optimizing.
So in, if you see like open
source, Apache Spark was a
Databricks version of Apache Park.
It's more optimized and you'll see
lesser errors running, huge workloads.
you'll not see the workers dying in
middle when running on, Databricks.
And it offers, one a feature
called the data Lake.
Where it, provides ACID
compliant on your data set.
Like it's more of a OLTP
offering from Databricks.
So Delta is more of like, whenever
there is a change happens on your,
system, it will capture that and it
will maintain the metadata for it.
And you can pull the transaction
information and it supports the ACID.
And it supports,
cellulose compute as well.
This is a new feature,
which they launched.
And as I said, Databricks can be,
offered on any client, cloud, provider
like AWS or Google Cloud or Azure.
So right now, there's three offerings
are there and this Databricks will
provision on top of it and you
will process the data for your
computer analytical, combinations.
And it offers a collaborative notebooks
where you can go and write your
notebooks and you can deploy that.
Whether it's for data engineering
or for data science or ML workflows.
As I said, it's a multi cloud
support, like where you can
have AWS Azure or Google Cloud.
that's the key features.
if you look at the bottom there is a
picture for where it has, Databricks,
and it will do the governance with all
these, cloud providers, and it provides
a business intelligence, data warehousing
solutions, AI, ML, data science solutions,
ETL, and real time data processing
and, orchestration, within their tool.
why we will use, Databricks?
right?
So that's a good point.
one of the biggest advantage with
Databricks is like cost optimization,
where you can run your workloads
using Databricks and you don't
have to worry about provisioning
these clusters, how, where to get
these resources and all of that.
You simply focus on your
business use case and Databricks.
We'll take care of orchestration
and provisioning of these resources.
It's a high performance.
So one of the thing is, like I said,
it's an optimized version of Spark.
And it has their engine called Porton
engine, where it runs a SQL and Spark
updates for particular use cases.
Not all use cases are supported with
Porton, but that's really extensively
a performance compared to General
Spark and it's written in C So it,
it optimized the memory really good.
Then, it's a collaboration friendly
where you will write your notebooks and
you can share across engineers and it
can, in real time you can do, real time
development and seamless integrations
with all these cloud providers.
So that's on a high level, like what
Databricks is offering right now.
Then, we look at, Databricks
optimization into like multiple layers.
It's not like one simple, Point where
you can optimize there are multiple
ways we have to do it So the first one
is like we need to review EBS usage.
So what is EBS, right?
So whenever you launch your Node or
cluster the data when it processed right
the whenever it goes out of the memory to
start writing to the disk So most of the
nodes comes with the internal disk itself.
If it is not there, it'll
use the AWS EBS, storage.
So most of the time it's a default
storage available on the nodes.
So if you look at, disk storage
is used for shuffling, as I said,
and checking your instance type,
allocate disk is very important.
So when you use i3, 4x
large workers has 3.
6 TB of local storage.
So we don't have to use.
EBS volumes if you are using inodes, but
still people go on provision EBS volumes
where you're paying additional cost of it.
So EBS cost for job is like storage
cost plus IO cost and snapshot
cost and data transfer cost.
Everything comes into EBS.
So it might look very small initially,
but when you're learning a huge
amount of jobs and we are paying in
millions, this one contributes a huge.
And when you can tweak this one,
you can save up to 50 to 80% of
your, savings, understanding,
auto scaling pitfalls, right?
So saving up to 28% is, is possible.
So basically like whenever
we have fluctuation in data
and it's seasonal, right?
We don't like how much data we'll get in.
So normally what we do is like
we'll go and enable autoscaling,
but whenever job goes on Autoscale,
whether it's a upscale or downscale,
it keep on calling the config where.
Keep the calling for config is
a cost related thing, right?
So don't use this auto scaling
unless it is really required.
If it is, if you know the history
of the job, keep it simple.
Keep the, not dynamic
and static resources.
That way you can save on the auto scaling.
Reduce AWS config cost.
This is like subsection of auto scaling.
as I said, like previously, where whenever
you keep on calling this AWS config, From
Databricks, it, it creates a lot of cost,
recurrently for upscale or downscale of
your resources, whether it's EBS volumes
or increasing the, adding the nodes
or reading the nodes, anything, right?
it's always, uses the cost and
it'll, it's a bombard to the job.
So it's always recommended to
use, right appropriate instance.
That's the next point.
So most, more appropriate workloads
from M node to I nodes, if it is
like where you can get like internal
volume, where it'll help, with the
EBS volume on top of it, you can
know what's the cost savings or cost.
Breakdown for M node versus I node, right?
So choosing the right
instance is the key here.
we miss a lot of savings by
choosing the wrong instance.
for example, M5, 4x versus I3, 4x large.
both has it own, you need to understand
like why we are choosing this instance
rather than simply blinding, and
going with the, recommendation.
So we need to have like really good
understanding of choosing instance.
The last one is spot versus on demand.
most of the workflows, it depends
upon if you are running a higher
SLA job, then you can run on demand.
If you are having a
lower SLA job, bank on.
A cheaper, spot instance where
you will go and bid for the
instance and you'll get it.
But the chances AWS can terminate
if they get a bigger bid is high,
but still you have a lower as a job,
which can be resilient if you restart.
And if you run one more time,
still you will save money.
So this happens very rarely
in AWS instance where someone
comes and grab your resources.
But still you can save
a lot of money on that.
so there are a few other Optimization
challenge things which we can do right
so using the right number of shuffle
partitions So the key with any of
your workloads particularly the data
workloads is like we should not have
The shuffle and the amount of data
written to the disk and amount of data,
shuffle or the IO should be very minimal.
So we need to look at like,
when you're doing huge amount of
aggregations, like group by joints
or reduced by key, the key should
be distributed across all the nodes.
The power of distributed computing
can be utilized to the fullest.
So the partitions is very important.
How many shuffles we can
do is very important.
Most of the engineers know
about this one, but most of the
time they overlook this one.
And we need to look at the UI and see
like how much data is being spilled,
how much data is being shuffled
over the network and all of that.
Spark has a really good UI
to showcase all of that.
So it's always recommended to
have two types of number of cores.
That keep it up, keep that
as your shovel partition.
That way it's like you want to distribute
across all the nodes and caching, right?
Like people overly use caching,
even though it's not required.
so Spark is a DAG where
it recollects everything.
So if you want to cache it in
middle so that it'll read, it
will not recollect the entire DAG.
look at the, UI to understand like how
much activity is happening with, garbage
collector, how much cache is required
and all of that, and use cache properly.
And, duplicate is one of the
biggest problem where, you may see
all the data going into one node,
or maybe the key is not unique.
So there are multiple ways you can,
reduce a duplicate before you process
it, get all the duplicates into one
data frame, process all remaining
everything and just union it.
There are like multiple
ways you can do it.
One of the technique is called
salting, where you will take the
key, add a unique value to it.
That way you can make sure that
the key is distributed across all
the nodes and it can process it.
So this kind of, there are a lot
of, ways you can eliminate the
duplicates and reduce the cost in
running these jobs for a longer time.
And, the last one is establish a
robust, data life cycle and cost system.
So different life, life cycle policies
on this, data sets and how much these
jobs need to run and all of that.
That's very important.
And you need to keep
monitoring these jobs.
So sometimes like we might think
okay, this might be using this
much if it is having enable
with auto scaling, all of that.
We don't like all this.
small nitty gritties of what's
happening with the job breakdown.
So we need to look at all of that and
keep a key and that and keep an alert
on it If it crosses that threshold
hit alert and start looking at like
why the job is performing like that.
So let's now Dive into what is AWS EMR.
So AWS EMR is a cloud based
Databricks processing offering from
AWS where you can run Spark based
or Hive based jobs on EMR, right?
it's equivalent to, like,
when Hadoop started.
they released this EMR Elastic
MapReduce where you can launch your
MapReduce jobs or Hive jobs on it.
And it'll run on EC2 instance and
it evolved over the time and a lot
of companies and a lot of teams use
this one for different purposes.
So there are three flavors to, AWS EMR.
I'll talk about the difference in a
minute, but I just want to explain like
what are the three flavors we have or
three offerings we have on, AWS EMR.
One is like the legacy EMR on EC2.
That's when you have a large,
large scale, workloads and you
need to process all of that.
You will use, EC2s, but like the
cluster management is like very tedious,
provisioning, scaling, and monitoring
is like very hard if you want to,
if you're doing with, EMR on, EC2.
Then the second offering is, EMR on
EKS, where you'll launch your EKS
on EMR, on EKS, like electric, cu
Kubernetes services, where you'll
run all these jobs over there.
the problem with this one is
like it's more complex to set
up the entire, infrastructure.
So that is a problem, but like the
scaling up and managing the workflows
and running the workflows is like very.
you can do it at a scale.
The third one is EMR Ferola.
This is a new offering which started
hitting the market from last couple
of years where you can do on demand,
pay for the usage processing.
The only problem with, several CM
R is you'll not have much control.
if you want to tweak something or if
you want to change some configuration
is little td little, complex.
So apart from that, serverless,
CMR is a game changer as of now.
as I said, if you look at,
the differences, right?
The coastal, the cluster control.
On EMR on EC2 is little high, then
EKS is medium, then serverless
is like pretty much low, but we
don't have much control on that.
Scaling wise, manual, you can automate on
EMR, EKS you can automate and serverless
EMR is like completely fully automated.
The best for large scale UTL, for EMR
workloads, AML container kind of jobs.
Ad hoc or busty jobs where you'll
use, serverless CMR cost efficiency.
if you look, if you are going for, this
is where the key cost savings, you can
see most of the workloads, which we
have migrated from server EMR to, server
serverless, sorry, EEMR on E, EMR, uneasy
to do so as EMR, because that's where
we have seen a lot of cost savings.
And, you'll pay for what you use, right?
That's the same case
for other two as well.
But like in serverless, you
don't have to worry about it.
It's pretty much following the
model of Databricks where you
don't have to worry about like
the provisioning and all of that.
You just say what you want and
focus on your business use case
and AWS will take care of it.
As I said, ease of use, obviously.
As always, EMR wins the game, but, EKS is
more complex, but it has if you read the
provision it's to wonder, and, EMR on EC2
is like a traditional thing where it's
like moderate versus hard ease of use.
we look at how we can save.
On, AWS EMR cost optimization.
So the right size cluster based
upon the workload, patterns, right?
So that's the same kind of thing.
What we were talked previously
with, Databricks as well.
Like you need to choose the
right, worker type, and like node.
To provision your jobs.
And one of the biggest thing is like the
Graviton based instance, reduced by 20%.
That's a game changer as well.
Because this Graviton based is a kind
of chip, which is built by Amazon.
And we, they don't have the property
to pay anything on Intel based chips.
that's a game changer for AWS where the
Graviton, runs much faster and they don't
have to pay anything on top of that.
And they give the savings
to the, customers.
Dynamic autoscaling for
efficient resource allocation.
As I said, the similar kind of things
what we have seen with Databricks, like
we should be very careful with autoscaling
where your jobs are being processed.
So we should optimistically
use the autoscaling.
We don't have to do it.
Keep it normal, keep it static, and
don't have to enable autoscaling.
The third one is, optimizing spark
performance, as I said previously,
shuffle is very important where you
will not do a lot of IO over the
network or will not write any dis
data to the desk and where you don't
have to read anything, that, that
kills the, importance of Apache Spark.
So look at that one.
Dynamic allocation of Spark executor,
ensuring optimal usage per job, need to
be implemented and parallelism settings
need to be optimized so that your,
Then, as I said, serverless
EMR was a CKS compute.
we, what we have seen is like, if
you have a, based upon the job type,
if you have a, job type, which is
like lower in SLA and don't need,
it's fine if it fails and restarts.
And, based upon that kind of
thing, you can select what
kind of, EMR you can choose.
But like we have seen serverless EMR
saves a lot when you're tweaking and
running on it with Graviton chips.
So we recommend trying serverless
EMR in that instance and data
storage and access optimization.
Like S3, when you read and write
from S3, there is a cost to it.
And the asset, like how
Delta is offered, AWS.
It offers who do your eyes work for?
Asset, compliant, datasets.
optimize that to the fullest because like
whenever we have the asset file system,
like the files keep on growing whenever
there's a, transaction happened on it.
So we need to vacuum it.
We need to clean it and
we need to keep it like.
Certain versions so that it will
not create huge amount of data.
So that's again a game changer there
Adjusting the retentions on this s3
objects not just leaving it alone Will
do a huge cost savings then automating
cluster shutdowns and scheduling.
We have seen this huge this issue
with AWS emr particularly Where the
cluster will be up and it will never
be shut down or it'll be kept on up.
We keep on running even though
there is no workload running.
So we should be keep on, as I said,
like k alerts on all these workloads.
If it crossing certain threshold,
it should be alert and we should be
debugged and see what, what's really
going on with the SLA and what is
going on with the, TCO reports.
So we need to look at that to
identify what's going on there.
So that being said, hope the talk is.
giving some information of like how
you can optimize your cloud workloads.
And, if you have any
questions shoot me and,