Hello everyone.
Welcome to this talk on writing
efficient and long running workflows.
As part of this topic, we'll go over
how we can write long running and
fault tolerant workflows with minimal
effort using some of the open source
and cloud native tools available.
Before we deep dive a
little bit about myself.
My name is Siddivarma Vaigiraju.
I'm currently working as a
software engineer at Microsoft.
And previously I worked with oracle
In my five plus years of experience.
I worked with different cloud native
tools like ubernetas open telemetry
and orco And I also worked with
petascale petabyte scale ingestion
systems like observability systems.
In my free time, I love to contribute
to open source and go on hikes.
This is my LinkedIn and email.
Please feel free to reach out to me if
you have any questions or suggestions
regarding the talk, or if you want to talk
about software engineering in general.
Coming to the agenda.
We'll first look at the problem
statement or the scenario at hand.
Then we look into what are some of the
difficulties or what are some of the pain
points when working with the scenario.
Then we look into how distributed
application runtime, one of the open
source tool or dapper helps solve them.
Third, we'll look at a live
example and then conclude the talk.
workflows are not new concepts.
They have been there for a while
and we have been writing these
workflows for a while as well.
There are mainly two kinds
of workflows, I would say.
One is the long running workflow
and the other is Short running
workflows with long running.
They can be your etl jobs extract
transform and load jobs that take
data from a place transform it and
then Store them on a destination
store now These can run for multiple
hours and, or multiple days as well.
Then, we have the short running
workflows, which are your CI or CD jobs,
or your integration tests, and so on.
One common characteristic among all these
workflows is having a retry mechanism
and a way to save and retrieve progress.
Let's look at one such scenario.
Imagine you have a storage account
and the storage account has a bunch of
files, maybe around 10 files, and each
of the files have around 100, 000 rows.
And those 100, 000 rows
attribute to VM IDs.
And my goal is to fetch The
instance details or the service
details that this VM belongs to.
For example, the VM one might
belong to service a VM two, might
belong to service B and so on.
Once we start processing, let's say we
have 10, 10 files and we FET the first
file, processed the a hundred thousand
dose, and then we came to the second file.
Processed the 50, 000 rows and then
the pod somehow dies because this
whole thing is running in a pod.
When the workflow restarts, if I
have to start from the 0th offset
again in the second find, that
is a lot of redundant processing.
That means, in addition to the
50, 000 rows that I did not
process, I'm processing the 50,
000 rows I have already processed.
Again, will this strategy scale?
That would depend on the number of files.
For example, if there are 20 to 30 files,
maybe in a day, then yeah, definitely.
It should not be an issue.
But if there are around, if the number
of files are around hundreds or in
the order of thousands, then this
strategy will definitely not scale.
The reason being with cloud
workloads, Failures are inherent
part of, are inherently part of it.
And for every failure, if we just
start from scratch again, that
strategy is not, of course, optimal.
One way to fix it is, what if I can,
If I do the checkpointing at the offset
level, so whenever I download a file, I
checkpoint which file I have processed
till and till which offset so that when
I, when the pod recovers from a failure,
it is able to Go to the store, pick
up the offset that it has previously
processed and start from there, right?
That is an optimal strategy and
that will of course reduce the
amount of reprocessing we do.
So what we have concluded is towards
building a checkpointing engine.
Now is checkpointing, is building
a checkpointing engine really easy?
You have to think about schema.
You have to think about
how the transactions occur.
the underlying database.
What is the versioning
strategy for the schema?
How will observability work?
And what happens if the
checkpointing engine fails?
Will you also fail your workflow?
all these things are something
we will have to consider.
And building such an engine that is
agnostic and works with multiple different
workflow types is a multi month effort.
How do we fix this?
If I think about it, checkpointing
is not something new.
It has been there for a while
and we are not the first
service to use this strategy.
I want, so there are two things I
want to, there are two things I need.
First, I want to recover from failures.
And second, I want to abstract away the
concept of building the checkpointing
engine and see if there are any
out of the box solutions available.
This is where there are A bunch of
different open source tools available
and one such open source tool is
distributed application runtime Or dapper.
Simply put, this is an engine that runs
as a sidecar along with your service
and does all the necessary actions.
For example, if you have 3000 pods
running and your service is deployed in
the 3000 pods, then you have the dapper
sidecar running along with your sidecar.
Along with the service
in all these 3, 000 pods.
If you look at the architecture diagram
here, we have the application itself,
which is nothing but our service.
It can be written in any
programming language.
Go, Node, Python, NET, Java, and so on.
Then, you have the sidecar.
Now, your service communicates with
the sidecar using the HTTP or the
gRPC APIs, because the communication
is through a HTTP or gRPC.
It makes the workflows
programming language agnostic.
That means your service can be in
any language and the sidecar can
be in a different language as well.
Along with the work, along
with the scenario we discussed.
Dapr also supports some
other features as well.
One such feature is the service
to service invocation API.
It is normal that we call any
downstream or upstream services.
As part of our workload, maybe we call
identity To authenticate or authorize the
request and so on And some of the things
that are required when you're calling
the api is retry strategies and also You
want to make sure your service has the
permissions to call the specific API.
All of this can be offloaded to the
Dapr Service to Service Invocation API.
What you need to do is just call the
Dapr sidecar, and sidecar takes care
of the retry strategies and any of the
permissions required to call these APIs.
Then, you have the publish
and subscribe pattern.
This is also a common pattern that is
used as part of our distributed systems.
Now, you can configure the runtime
to produce and consume to a message
broker of your choice and deliver
the events to a specific API.
That is also something Dapr supports.
And today, what we'll be
discussing is about Dapr workflows.
With the Dapr Workflow building
block, you can write fault tolerant
and long running workflows with
most of the things abstracted away.
For example, the thing we
discussed is checkpointing.
The Dapr Workflow engine
inherently takes care of this.
How?
Let's take a look at that.
Coming to the Dapr Workflows,
there are mainly three things.
First is the Workflow SDK.
Because The checkpointing is taken care by
the workflow engine and it needs, and for
that it enforces certain rules that the
app, that the application needs to follow.
SDK is the one that curates those rules.
It has certain set of interfaces and
contracts that your service needs to
follow so that the workflow engine can
automatically do the checkpointing.
Then you have the workflow engine
itself, which the SDK talks to,
to notify the progress made till
now and the workflow engine stores
the progress in the state store.
The state store is simply put a database
where the, pro, where the data is stored.
The state store can either be a Cosmos
DB or Redis or Firebase or Cassandra.
Now, one good thing here is Tomorrow,
if tomorrow, if you have to change the
state store, it is as easy as changing
the state store, building block.
You just have to change the, YAML file.
That is configured and everything else.
The workflow is workflow takes care of
the reason for this is the state store
in Internals are not exposed to the
SDK the dapper runtime takes care of it
Now, let's look at what a dapper workflow
looks like the most basic unit in the
workflow is called an activity That is
the one that actually performs the action.
For example, if you have to call a
specific API or do some complex business
logic, that is performed in the activity.
Then a workflow is made
up of multiple activities.
So you can think of the workflow
as an orchestrator and activity as
the one that is doing the action.
Now, if we consider the scenario we have
discussed previously, where we have a,
where we give a storage location and the
activity has to perform, has to retrieve
the service details of the particular
VM, the in, there is each workflow
or activity has an input and output.
So the input in this case is
the object store file name.
That we are passing to the workflow.
Now, there can be one activity that
can return all the rows in the file.
Then each individual activity has input
as the VM ID and output as a service name.
For example, if there are 100, 000 rows,
then there will be 100, 000 activities.
And each of this activity would
have the input as the VM ID and
the output as a service name.
So we also discussed that,
the dapper workflow is able
to resume in case of failures.
So what ends up happening is for each
input activity combination, the progress
is saved inside the stage store.
For example, for VM1 and for activity
A, if there was an output, the
progress is stored in the stage store.
When there's a failure, what ends up
happening is Dapper would check For this
combination if there is already an output.
So after For example after for this VM
ID VM 1 if you have already performed
the activity when there's a failure
and the workflow resumes Dapper already
knows that for this combination.
There is already an output available.
So instead of Performing this activity
again, it would just return the output.
That is how it, it is able to
checkpoint and resume without
performing the activity again.
In order to better understand this,
let's look at a small example.
As part of this example,
this is what we'll do.
We'll first understand what the
workflow console app is doing.
Then we'll run the Dapr sidecard.
Third, we will look at the We
will run the workflow console app.
Fourth, we will create
an artificial failure.
And fifth, we will run the app
again to see that it resumes
from the previous failure point.
Okay, starting with the first step.
What we see here is a dependency injection
with registering workflows and activities.
As part of registering workflow, we have
Multiple activities and as we discussed
previously, workflow is nothing but the
orchestrator for the activities inside it.
The first activity here takes the
file path as input and returns all the
rows in the file as list of strings.
For example, if there are 10
rows, then we return 10 strings.
Then for each of them, because
they are the VM IDs, we are gonna,
we are going to pass them to the
VM metadata fetch activity to get
the corresponding service details.
Because there are 10 rows, there will
be 10 activities created with the
input name and activity combination.
For brevity purposes, I am not making
an API call but just writing a console.
writeLine to make sure, we know when the,
when this activity has been triggered.
Similarly, there is a console.
writeLine trigger here as well
which happens when the rows
are fetched from the file.
Once this is done, we set the
environment variable for dapper grpc
port to be 4001, so that once the
console app starts up, it communicates
to the dapper sidecar on this port.
Then, we get the workflow metadata
instance, sorry, we get the
dapper workflow client instance.
Schedule a workflow here, the
using the name of the work, name of
the workflow, and then the input.
Input from where the content needs
to be read and the instance ID
name, which is unique per workflow.
Then we wait for it to start and
finally wait for it to complete.
This is what is happening
as part of the console app.
Now let's start our side card.
This is the command we used to
run the Tapper side card here.
I'm specifying the HTTP port to be 3
5 0 0 and the GRPC port to be 4 0 0 1.
Awesome.
The sidecar is up and running.
Next it is time to run our service.
So I remove the break point here.
I'll remove the break point here as well.
Now from the console, what we see is
we have fetched the VM data and we
have fetched the row from the file.
So we completed fetching
the rows from the file.
Now.
If I stop the app here and
resume it, I should not see this
activity being executed again.
That means, I should also
not see these console.
title lines again.
Now what we'll do is because
we have already scheduled the
workflow, we'll not schedule it
again and then we'll run the app.
So what we are seeing here is it takes
a bit of time to, for the workflow app
to itself start, but once it starts,
you will see that it directly goes
to the second activity and does not
start the start fetching rose from
the file again because for that input.
And the file name, for the input
and output combination, Dapr already
determines on the state store
that the output already exists.
So as you can see here, we are,
we have not seen the output of
fetch rows from file here again.
We have just seen that we
have fetched the VM metadata.
So that means when the Dapr
workflow resumed, it did not
start from that activity again
because it already determined.
That activity is already complete and
it resumed from the next activity.
What you're seeing here
is an example of a setup.
That my team uses when running dapper
on kubernetes so when we Install dapper.
We also get the dapper sentry service,
which is responsible for distributing
certificates And so on and then there is
also the dapper placement service which
is responsible for distributing your
workflows or the activities inside the
workflows across multiple dapper hosts.
And then, the dapper itself
running in the side pod has to
communicate to the state store.
In this case, it is the Azure Cosmos DB
state store using the managed identity.
And then finally, All the metrics and
logs coming, all the metrics and logs
coming from the Kubernetes infrastructure.
are sent to Prometheus for metrics
and application insights for logging.
And when running on Azure, it is generally
recommended to use managed identity.
And one thing to keep in mind
when using the MSI is the
dap, dapper container takes.
A bit more time when authenticate with
msi So the default timeout would not
work and you have to configure And
you have to increase the timeout value
to conclude we talked about the problems
we run into when Use when running
workflows, for example, how we need
quick recovery and how checkpointing is
something that is abstracted away and
looking for out of the box solution helps.
Then we looked into how Tapper, in
addition to other building blocks,
the workflow building blocks
helps curate long running and
fault tolerant workflows with it.
Eventing mechanisms, and then
finally, we looked at how we can run
Dapr in the Kubernetes environment.
That's it, folks.
I hope you enjoyed the talk,
and I hope you enjoy the rest
of the conference as well.
Thank you.