Hello everyone.
I'm Han from Dell Technologies and Q.
Today I'll be speaking about even driven
validation for cloud native resilience.
The central idea about this
presentation is that the cloud native
system, especially in healthcare.
Become too dynamic, too distributed,
and too interdependent to be validated
by using traditional manual approaches.
What used to work in slower, more static
enterprise environment no longer works
when you're dealing with microservice
API container, distributed data flow
and realtime operation dependencies.
In healthcare, the challenge become
even more important because residency is
not just about infrastructure of time.
It directly affects
operational continuity.
Uh, clinical workflow compliance brochure.
Reliability of the system, uh, reliability
of system people depends on every day.
So in this talk, I'm gonna walk
through the problem, explain why
traditional validation falls shot.
I introduce a board, support this
framework, uh, show how it works in
a cloud native model and, and close,
uh, with the operation value and
future direction of this approach.
So to understand why even driven
validation matters first, we need
to understand the complexity of
environment we are trying to protect.
Um, healthcare cloud native ecosystem
are no longer made of simple monolithic
application with predictable interface
now because now they include,
uh, thousands of microservice.
Extensive APIs, multiple containers
or synchronous data pipeline
and cross platform dependencies
that are constantly changing.
In practical term, one
enterprise can have.
Um, uh, one enterprise can have
interconnected service planning, EHR
system, telemetry platform, lab system,
pharmacy building, and, um, multiple
interface engines all linked through
multiple protocol like so G-R-P-C-H-L
seven, formatting, et cetera, et cetera.
So when you put all of that together,
the issue is not, uh, simply
scale in the traditional sense.
Issue is dynamically com uh, dynamic
complexity, the fact that the system is
always moving, always updating, and always
depending, depending on something else.
And always, uh, the risk of
failure that can propagate, uh,
propagate across multiple chain.
So that is why validation can no
longer be treated as a one pen
check or a scheduled afterthought.
It has to become continuous,
contextual, and deeply integrated
into the operating model itself.
So this leads directly to the core
challenge in ensuring healthcare
reliability, uh, traditional validation
method are fundamentally needed to create
for rapidly evolving cloud architecture.
Uh, they were created for environment
where release cycle was lower.
Uh, dependencies were easier to
map, and most failure domains
were relatively isolated.
In modern cloud native system,
the dependencies are broader.
The change, uh, change happens
continuously in the blast.
Radis of failure can be much larger.
So these environment growing, uh,
growing complexity, traditional value,
uh, traditional validation increases
the likelihood, likelihood of downtime
and delays, incident resolution, make
maintenance and management more difficult.
In a regulated environment like
healthcare, the risk is even greater.
Um, a failed interface or missed,
uh, upstream dependency does not
just affect application health.
It can disrupt downtime downstream
workflow and create more comp,
uh, more compliance exposure, and
generate operational uncertainty
at the exact moment when
organization need more confidence.
So the challenge is not
only on technical scale.
It is an inability of the old
system, um, or old validation model
to keep in phase with speed and
interdependency of a newer system.
So there are three major
limitation of a traditional
validation that makes this clear.
First is reactive testing.
Uh, manual and periodic testing
are inherently reactive and slow.
In most case, teams are validating
after a symptom appears or after
alert fire or after a user is.
In pa, user impact is already visible.
That means organization
is always responding late.
Second, limitation and scalability.
These approach simply cannot
scale with the phase of Kubernetes
deployment, uh, containerized service
and distributed release cycle.
Number of service grows, so do so,
do the number of relationship between
them, um, and a manual validation cannot
reliably cover the dependency draft.
Third limitation is a compliance risk.
When a validation is outdated
or incomplete, uh, incident
detection is delayed.
Evidence collection becomes fragmented,
and organization pays a larger
difficulty proving, uh, the right
control button pays at the right time.
So if I have to summarize this,
uh, slide in one sentence, it would
be Traditional validation is true.
Slow for resilience, too limited
for scale, and too weak for
modern, uh, compliance demand.
This is exactly why we
introduced purposeless framework.
Is a cloud native, uh, even driven,
modern, um, even driven automation
framework designed to transform
validation from a manual activity into
a continuous operation capability.
So instead of waiting for engineers
to check after a suspected issue.
The platform response to, uh,
response to a realtime event, and,
uh, continuously validate the system
behavior across the environment.
Uh, it's designed to integrate with
existing infrastructure, so, so
that the organization do not have
to rebuild everything from scratch.
The goal is not to disrupt the enterprise,
uh, enterprise, but the goal is to create
a scalable validation layer that works
with what exactly, uh, uh, already exists.
While addressing intelligence,
speed, and resilience, um,
at the architecture level, support
Plus is built around realities
of cloud native operations.
Um, it begins with a event in ingestion
at, uh, it begins with event ingestion
of high volume streams that ma uh, that
matters because in modern platform,
most successful or most useful
operation signals comes from events,
uh, deployment, signal ramping events,
elementary changes, queue behavior,
workload drift, and dependency status.
Those signals feed into meta
driven validation rules.
That means the validation is not just
hard coded in number two, insert.
It is a policy driven and a aware
of system context and protocol
type and service criticality
and also interface behavior.
The framework then uses distributed
orchestration across microservice.
So validation can happen in
power rather than serially.
Uh, this is a major shift from
manual validation where engineers
often check one component at a time.
The serverless component are used
where elastic, elastic scale makes
sense, and a Ks provide an efficient
deployment model so that the framework
can run close to the workload.
It is validating overall result
is an architecture, uh, that is
responsive, more modular, scalable,
and aligned with the way the modern
cloud native system are actually built.
So, uh, support plus inter support
plus implements simultaneous
validation workflow trigger
triggered by real-time emails.
Uh, the significant change from legacy
model is that, um, this is one of the
significant change from the legacy model.
So in all model validation, workflow
often start because of the human notices
a problem or because a schedule process
begins in, um, in this model, the workflow
starts by itself, um, uh, because the
system itself recognizing even that
has a code and validation is needed.
Now, uh, they even could be a department
or path cycle, a configuration
change, a latency anal anatomy, or a q
blockage or another operational signal
that indicates of a potential risk.
Excuse me.
So because these workflow run within
Kubernetes native environment and
control loop, they are designed
for both responsive and ness.
They can handle higher load, increasing
operational, increasing system of
complexity, and faster change rate
without sacrificing the speed or accuracy.
So this is a validation becomes real time.
And this is not just a foster execution,
uh, it is a different trigger model,
uh, different orchestration model, and a
different level of operation awareness.
Support plus delivers value
through three major features.
Um, one is detection,
remediation, and compliance.
First is direction.
The platform use machine learning
and real time monitoring to identify
anomalies, uh, generate alerts.
Predict description before
they become viable failures.
This is similar to the baseline
driven anomaly model, uh, described
in the first gen where pre interface
behavior is learned over time and,
uh, deviation as code before hard
outage happens second remediation.
Second is remedi.
So Footless can respond automatically
using protocol of biologic rather than
relying on generic one-off, uh, size,
uh, one-off size that fits all actions.
For example, one failure type may
require RY logic and circuit for
another may require a Q consumer
restart, and none of them may require
a service recycler full recovery.
Third is compliance.
The platform supports continuous
audit readiness by generating
validation evidence as part of
a normal operation, rather than
forcing teams to reconstruct it.
Data that reduces complex, uh, compliance
risk and improves accountability.
The, so the framework does not stop
at telling you there is a problem.
It detects a problem, it
acts on the problem, and it
documents a problem in a way.
That, uh, support regulated, uh, supports
are regulated at enterprise operation.
This slide compares traditional validation
and even driven validation side by side.
Uh, the traditional validation
is manual, periodic and reactive.
It depends heavily on human effort.
Uh, usually happens on a schedule.
Often identifies a problem only after
the being affecting the environment
that leads to delay inefficiency,
uh, in resolving issues, and that
also may lead to a P one tickets.
So even driven validation work
differently, it is automated,
continues and proactive.
Instead of waiting on a person
to initiate the check, the system
validates its response to live
events and changing conditions.
This means the issue are surface.
Uh, earlier, uh, dependencies are checked
more concisely and resilience become
part of the flow of operation rather than
something layered, uh, on after the fact.
If I were to destroy the
difference, simply, I would say
this, um, traditional validation.
Ask, did something already
break, uh, even validation.
Ask what's changed?
What is at risk and what
should we verify right now?
One of the strongest proof points
in the presentation is improve, uh,
improvement in the system availability.
Uh, this slide high highlights a
30% improvement where, which signals
the practical impact of event driven
validation on cloud native resilience.
Uh, important point is not just
the percentage itself, but.
What created it?
When a validation becomes automated, even
driven and integrated into operational
workflow, the organization catches
issues earlier, uh, response faster and
reduce number of conditions that would
otherwise, uh, mature into visible outage.
And in healthcare, better availability
supports, uh, continuous, uh, supports
continuously of care, uh, smoother
clinical operation and stronger confidence
in mission critical, uh, systems.
So this slide focus on
operation efficiency gain.
So support plus created a unified
validation platform, um, by consolidating
and, uh, consolidating monitoring and,
uh, remediation into one in that matters
because fragmented operations or expense.
When clean use, disconnect tools for
validation, monitoring, remediation
reporting, they lose the time and
handoff, uh, and in interpretation
and, uh, uh, reput to coordination.
So the unified platform, uh, the
unified platform changes there.
So it gives a team a clear view of system
behavior, um, uh, helps them track the
performance signal, uh, more consistently.
And make it easier to identify
where improvement is needed by
reducing the complexity of managing
multiple system and processes.
Support plus creates a more cohesive
workflow that saves time, um, minimalize
operation error, and also allow team to
spend, uh, more energy on, uh, engineering
reli and reliability improvement rather
than replicate your validation efforts.
So this slide gonna summarize
three benefits in three dimension.
One is resiliency, scalability,
and compliance First.
Uh, resiliency improves because
the framework supports self-healing
and faster restriction management.
Instead of waiting for a human to
investigate every signal, uh, the platform
can validate continuously and classify
anomalies, and in some case, can execute
the right remediation automatically.
Second, scalability improves because
the validation model can keep up,
uh, with, uh, microservice velocity
and cloud native environment.
Uh, continuous integration,
continuous deployment.
Uh, 1D works safely if the validation
can move at the same speed as challenge.
Third, uh, compliance improves because
automation reduced the burden of, uh,
burden on the team while still maintaining
consistency, traceability, and readiness
for audit and regulatory review.
Um, taken together these benefits
show that even driven validation is
not just an efficiency improvement.
It is, uh, it is a strategic capability
that strengthens the operating model
across technology processing governance.
So this implementation roadmap
show how organization can
adopt this framework in stages.
Uh, phase one begins with a pilot
project focused on integrating
even stream efficiently.
This is where organization grew, uh, the
model, the validation, and even source
and establish initial control point.
Phase two expands the approach across
services, uh, scaling validation workflow
into a broader set of system domains.
Um, phase three adds automated remediation
and compliance measure moving, moving the
platform from observation into action.
Phase four focuses on continuous
improvement and system extension, allowing
the framework to mature as an environment,
uh, uh, mature as the environment evolve.
What important, what is important here is
that the path is incremental organization
do not need to solve every validation,
um, every validation problem in one step.
They can start with targeted value, um,
build competence, and then scale the
model into broader resilience capability.
That, uh, staged approach
is one of the reason this
framework is practical and, uh.
Um, uh, this framework, the
framework is more practical for
real enterprise environment.
Um, when we look ahead, future, um,
when we look ahead, future validation
strategy will have to evolve alongside
with cloud native architecture.
So new pattern emerge validation
framework will need to extend those
pattern as well, that include new
workload types, new service traction,
new automation boundaries, and
new form of operational telemetry.
Um, this is also where AI and machine
learning can play a bigger role.
AI and ml predictive model validation,
um, uh, a and ML make more, uh,
more predictive validation, more
powerful by helping the system detect.
Deviation before performance
or compliance is impacted.
The future is not just about validating,
uh, whether a system is up or down.
It is about understanding, changing
behavior and anticipating risk,
and, uh, correlated signal across
dependencies, uh, and acting early
enough to prevent larger incident.
So the future validation strategy
will be more adaptive and more
predictive and, uh, more tightly
embedded into cloud native life cycles.
Alright, so yeah, thank you
for all of your attentions.
Uh, the key message I wanna leave with
you is that traditional validation does
not scale with cloud native complexity.
Especially in a high stake environment
like healthcare, whereas even driven
validation often offers a better
model, uh, the one that is automated.
Continuous in proactive by design,
uh, support plus demonstrates how
that model can improve resilience, um,
streamline operations and uh, support
compliance, and also create a strong
foundation for reliability at scale.
So as the system become more
distributed and more dynamic, the
validation itself must become more
intelligent and more responsive.
That is the shift that this framework
is designed to make possible.
Yeah, so, but the Thank you everyone,
I'll be happy to take any questions.