Hello, everyone.
Welcome to cloud native 2025
from conf 40 to conference.
I'm Gayatri Jehanmohan.
I am going to talk about Kubernetes
for industrial IOT ecosystem.
I'm a software engineer at Microsoft
and we'll get into the talk today.
So the first thing I want to talk about is
what are the different architecture that
is out there for industrial ecosystem?
So the first one that I want to
talk is the monolithic architecture.
So in monolithic architecture, as you can
see in this diagram, that every layer in
the architecture is very tightly coupled.
So they are all deployed
in one single unit.
So what it does is all these, layers like
the device layer, which is the one which
closer to the devices and sensors, and
the second layer is the data tion layer.
And then the third layer is the business
logic unit, the actual processing.
Part of it, and then the UI layer,
all these are very tightly coupled.
So what happens is when anything goes
wrong, it affects the whole application.
So this is an example of a
monolithic, architecture.
Let's talk about the other architecture,
which is famous out there, which is
getting more popularity these days.
And it was also implemented in a lot of
technological industrial technological
solution is microservice architecture.
So microservice architecture is
very different from monolithic.
You can see in this, in this diagram
that each of the microservice, you can
think of it as a simple, small program,
which is running and it does, it has
have a single responsibility principle.
So all of these microservices are
independently deployable services.
So meaning that if this is.
doing one operation, it doesn't
affect the other microservices
that is running parallelly.
So all these, microservices
are loosely coupled.
And say if one microservice is using
another tech stack, it doesn't necessarily
have to follow the same tech stack.
So every person can develop that,
develop their microservices with the tech
stack that they are comfortable with.
So because of this, architecture, these
microservices application can be scaled
because if you want to add another
microservice, you can pretty much add
that, which makes it more resilient
because if this microservices goes down,
then you can pretty much add another
one and the resilience is very good.
It also makes the fault isolation.
So if this microservices is not running
properly, or if there is some issues,
it's not going to affect the entire
system like the monolithic architecture.
It is also very DevOps and
continuous integration and
continuous deployment friendly.
you can keep on deploying new versions
of the microservices very easily.
now that we have seen both the type of
architecture, let's see which one is
better for the industrial IoT ecosystem.
first let's talk about
the monolithic part.
In the monolithic, there is
a single point of failure.
if say for example, the business logic
is no longer working, then what happens
is it doesn't it does affect the whole
thing, so it doesn't give time to recover.
So you need to wait for the
whole system to recover.
which makes it, not a comfortable
situation for large industrial ecosystem.
So you have to wait.
There's a lot of downtime.
And also there is very, less chance
for scalability because in order to add
another app or another new technology,
you have to wait for the downtime.
So also it makes it very difficult to
integrate with any modern solutions.
For example, if you want to add a, an
app to use the AI models, then you have
to ensure that you have to test it and
ensure that everything works and make
sure that the application is down for
some time, add it and then get it back.
It is only suitable for small scale
operations, but for industrial operations,
it's not at all profitable because the
scale of the number of devices in the
industry and the number of factories
that you want to add, if it's a lot,
then monolithic will definitely fail.
And also latency is very
critical in industrial ecosystem.
If any of the machine goes down,
you want to be notified very
quickly and with no downtime, which
is not supported in monolithic.
So that's why monolithic is not.
going to work for industrial ecosystem.
So what works then?
Which is the microservice architecture.
The reason I'll get into it
later, but before that we should
look into what are the different
architecture in the microservice
architecture itself available.
So one is the Kubernetes based
microservice architecture and other is
serverless and other is traditional VMs.
These are the top three ones.
We'll get into the
features of each of them.
So first is the Kubernetes,
powered microservice architecture.
The feature of it is pretty much, you can
imagine like an opera concert where the
person is standing and understanding who
has to go first, the guitarist or pianist.
The similar is like the
Kubernetes environment.
It is a very, automated orchestration
for container deployment.
So it's an open source
one, open source software.
So it also gives automatic
scaling and self healing features.
So it is widely used during, during a
large scale industrial application, and
also most of the apps are cloud native.
And also, it's good to use Kubernetes
environment when you need high
resilience as well as high observability.
So the next, type of
architecture is serverless.
The serverless, you can imagine
like a small serverless function
running the cloud, just like
Azure Functions or AWS Lambda.
So those functions are
mostly event driven.
So whenever some changes happens in the
database or the user interface, then
those serverless functions get deployed.
So they are very fully managed
and also it scales automatically,
but it is very lightweight.
So you don't have to wait
for the whole service to run.
It can do its function
and then finish it off.
So only when there is an event.
So this is a serverless type
of microservice architecture,
which is also widely used.
And also now we have the traditional
VMs, which is, like you can
deploy all your services in a VM.
But, you have direct
control of your hardware.
You want to ensure.
That, hardware resources are fully
optimized and you go for this method.
And, also these, the solution is widely
preferred during, legacy constraints.
So you have an old software running
and you want to keep them in that VM.
And also there's security reasons because
you cannot deploy it in the cloud.
So you have it in the traditional
VM, bare metal software.
So understanding all these
three microservice architecture,
let's get into the detail of.
Why kubernetes environment is really
good for the industrial IoT ecosystem.
So we'll get into five
reasons why it is really good.
So let's talk about the first one,
which is scalability and resilience.
So as I said, kubernetes is an open source
container deployment and orchestrator.
So it's, it's open source is
developed by Google in the beginning
and then it was open source.
Now it's very widely used.
So some of the properties of
Kubernetes is it has auto scaling
feature, which means that it can
support horizontal or vertical pods.
Like you can add pods whenever
you have a high workload.
So it can adjust the workload dynamically.
So if you don't have that much
workload, you can scale it down as well.
So scaling up and scaling down is such
a good feature, which makes it very
easy for industrial ecosystem because
things are changing very quickly.
As well as it has self
healing properties, which is.
Automatically, it restarts if
any of the failed services are
not working as per expectation.
So that it can have zero downtime.
You will pretty much not even notice that
there's something, some services have gone
down because Kubernetes will ensure that
the resources are moved automatically.
Because it makes it a very
compelling reason for critical
industrial applications, right?
and also multi node failover.
In, Kubernetes, if one node fails over,
then the other nodes takes over because
it creates multiple redundancy across and
also ensures that the, that it is in the
device on prem as well as in the cloud.
So it makes it a very good, solution
for scalability and resilience purpose.
The second is.
For IoT, for industrial IoT, you
have a lot of devices running on
the edge, cloud, as well as on prem.
which all these scenarios
are supported by Kubernetes.
And also there are lightweight
Kubernetes like K3S and micro kubernetes.
They can run on very low
power industrial gateways.
Because you need some gateways
very close to the industry.
And this Kubernetes is capable,
this lightweight Kubernetes
are capable of running.
in the industrial gateways as well.
And there is also multi cloud support.
for example, you can deploy
in AWS as well as in Azure.
You don't have to go for all
or nothing cloud scenarios.
that makes it a very compelling reason
for industry because you might, you might
want to use one cloud for one purpose
and another cloud for another purpose.
this all makes it a very compelling
reason to also go for, given it
is microservice architecture.
And the third one, which is a more
important one in today's world, because
this is security is getting more traction.
So in Kubernetes, it has like
role based access control.
So only person who needs to get the
access will get the access and other
person have either a read or a, very fine
grained control access can be also given.
with RBAC support in Kubernetes.
And also we have network policies,
autologging and monitoring.
All these are taken care by the
Kubernetes orchestration itself.
So the industry don't have to go
and look for it and do extra stuff.
And the fourth one, which is another
important aspect, is the observability.
We want to know what's going on in
the industry, whether if you need
a maintenance, if you need, if you
need immediate action into something
like The machines are heating up
and we need to ensure the cool down.
All these things can be really
done real time and Kubernetes
makes a very compelling reason.
The reason because it supports Prometheus,
Grafana, all these advanced logging
metrics and alerting system, which makes
it much, much easier for industrial
ecosystem to take actions immediately and
then serve the customers in the right way.
Which is for the developer aspects.
So anytime you want to deploy a new
version and ensure that you want to
deploy it very quickly, test it out.
Then the continuous integration
and continuous deployment
support in Kubernetes is amazing.
Also, you can roll any updates, for
example, if the new version is not
supporting, then you can go back to
the older version in a minute of time.
And also there is blue green deployment,
which is basically A B testing, where you
can test out blue, another solution, a
green, another solution, and ensure that
Which one is working fine before going
to production you can check it out and
ensure that everything is smooth So this
kind of gives no downtime scenario because
everything is tested out before you go
into the production environment So all
these five are reasons are very compelling
to go into the kubernetes So now I'll
get into the benefits of it, right?
Because we have seen all these things,
but what does it mean in numbers?
What does it actually do?
So we have four, big numbers.
One is first is the
faster deployment cycle.
As I mentioned, right?
It has Kubernetes and it
enables continuous delivery.
So you can roll updates.
in a matter of, less time
than you would imagine.
And also, if there is any security
patches that need to be applied,
it can be done very seamlessly.
we also, you will have no
downtime, which makes it very
easy to do faster deployments.
And also, if you want to deploy
only one, component and you want
to not affect the other one, then
also it is a pretty good, solution.
making it overall 40 percent faster
than the monolithic, architecture.
So the next one is the uptime, which is
one of the favorite part, because you will
not even notice if anything goes down.
So the self healing
capabilities are amazing.
And also Kubernetes has this
way of offloading the workloads
across different nodes.
It makes it well balanced.
So when one node goes down, the
other node takes over, making
it a very quick healing time.
And also it reschedules the
workloads based on node availability.
Making sure we have very less,
impact on any things that go wrong.
And third one is the reduction in cost.
So the cost part is, can be looked
into the optimization, right?
Whenever we don't use much,
we want to make sure that we
are scaling it down, right?
in the monolithic, it's not possible.
The whole full fledged architecture
needs to be running all the time
in order to serve the customers.
But in the case of kubernetes,
then if you don't have that much
workload, then you can tone it down
or tone it up based on your needs.
And also you can set the node to
occupy a certain type of memory
and resources, making it a very
constrained environment for the node
so that you're not over utilizing it
so that your budget is not crossing.
And also the same goes for
agent cloud environment.
You can dynamically scale up
and down, making it a very.
A good reason to switch because it can
give you a lot of money that is, that
gets saved in the operational cost.
And the fourth and the main
important thing is fault isolation.
we talked about like how much, Kubernetes
can actually move the workloads around
so that you don't see the impact at all.
So the entire system is
intact and still running.
And also there is another feature
in kubernetes, which is namespace
isolation as well as pod isolation.
So ensuring all the services are managed,
separately, so that if one thing is
changed, it doesn't affect the other one.
So overall it gives like 3x
improvement in fault isolation.
And finally, I have a case study for
you, which is Azure IoT Operation.
All this theory and concepts is actually
implemented in an actual product.
Microsoft has recently launched this
product called as Azure IoT Operation.
And we're going to touch base on
the architecture a little bit.
So here you can see in the
left most side is the factory.
So the factory is going to have
all these cameras, IP cameras and
different standard of cameras.
And then there is
something called as OPC UA.
It's also another standard
where it can, get details of the
edge devices in different ways.
Like it can be a truck,
it can be a gateway.
Excuse me.
So all these are the different,
devices that exist in the camera.
And all these workloads needs to be
managed using Kubernetes environment.
So Azure IoT operation is not just a
microservice architecture of Kubernetes,
but it also has an event driven
mechanism of using a highly available
and highly scalable MQTT broker.
So you can also use Azure Arc services
like machine learning, app services, etc.
And also it is, you can use the different
Azure infrastructure services like
Defender, Monitor, etc. So this is
the whole Azure IoT operation which is
enabled by Azure Arc. And also it has
the highly available broker as well as
data flows, which converts your data
format from one to another format so
that you can process in the cloud.
So once this data comes through from the
broker, you can manage it in the cloud
using different cloud, data visualization
and pipeline like fabric, even grid and
hub storage, data explorers and so on.
So these are all cloud based
application and you can use also
Power BI to look into the data in
a way that you like, filter it.
And also there is an operational
support where the operator can see
the whole deployment end to end.
So this is an example of,
Kubernetes orchestration in action.
This is actually getting
deployed in industries today.
And the main features of it
is like it's built up recent
Kubernetes native application,
which is what we talked about.
We are seeing that live in action.
It's highly scalable, resilient,
as well as extensible and making
it all secure from end to end.
Also, it lets you manage Edge services
and resources from the cloud, as I talked
about, using Azure Arc. And also, it can
integrate the customer workloads, to a
platform to create a unified solution.
it also supports GitOps, so making it easy
for deployment and also rolling updates.
And it integrates with, as I said,
the data service pipeline like
Event Hub Grid, making it very easy
to integrate with the cloud and
ensure post processing is easier.
And as I said, it includes a highly
industry grade, edge native MQTT broker.
So it powers even the
event driven architecture.
So you're using a kind of like a
hybrid, Kubernetes as well as event
driven in the Azure IoT operation.
So yeah, that's all for this talk.
If you have any questions, please
reach out to me on LinkedIn.
Thank you so much.