Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 Cloud native.
My name is Sandeep Ur.
I'm an AI ML engineer with
over 15 years of experience in
building production systems.
And in last several years I focused on AI
infrastructure and multi-agent systems.
And today I'm gonna talk about
engineering, production grade
multi-agent systems in cloud.
So here is something I consistently
hear from every team that is
moving beyond Asian prototypes.
They're all hitting
the same four problems.
First is orchestration complexity.
The moment you have more than
one agent, you have coordination
logic, and that logic grows fast.
It spans services.
It spans agent layers, and if you do not
design it deliberately, it becomes the
most fragile part of your entire system.
Second is a latency compounding.
Every single agent hub is a round trip.
Think about it.
An LLM call a tool, call
a handoff to a next agent.
A four agent system can easily turn
a two second request into a 22nd
one if you're not careful about it.
The third is the failure
propagation, and this one has
actually broken production systems.
What happens is one agent partially
fails and it's corrupt output.
Whether that is in complete, wrong or
hallucinated gets passed into the next
agent as if it's perfectly valid input,
and that creates a cascading failures
that are nearly impossible to Deepak
without the right instrumentation.
And these are the six things that we
are going to cover in today's stock.
Let's get into it.
So if you have built an AI agent demo,
you know what it looks like when it works,
clean requests, model reasons through it.
Tools get core and response comes back.
But the production exposes
everything that the demo hides.
Contact Windows overflow.
A conversation interface that works
beautifully for a 10 turn interaction
starts failing at 40 turns because now
your model is trying to reason over
50,000 tokens of conversation history.
A single model cannot specialize.
You are asking one agent to handle
order lookup, escalation, logic
resolution, drafting, and customer
communication, all in one reasoning chain.
These are genuinely different tasks
with different optimal approaches.
A model that tries to be a
specialist at all of them end
up being mediocre at each one.
Failure collapses everything,
and there is no isolation.
A tool called fails, a prompt
goes sideways, a model step, and
the entire interaction fails.
And because there is no isolation,
there is no independent scalability.
You cannot scale your escalation logic
independently from your status lookups
because they're all the same process and
in the platform I'm drawing from as a
volume and the workflow complexity grew.
Three things failed in sequence.
The reasoning change grew too long.
The context windows floor met conversation
and tool reliability collapsed.
A model being asked too many things to do.
One reasoning chain started
making errors across all of them.
Wrong parameters, missteps
and confident sounding, wrong
answers, and zero fault isolation.
A single pronged failure could
derail an entire workflow.
No isolation meant no recovery
path, and here is the insight
that drove the entire redesign.
The problem was not that we
needed a smarter model, we
needed a better architecture.
Orchestration architecture, and
for the orchestration decision,
you have two broad options.
Centralized orchestration,
which means one orchestrator
agent that directs everything.
It decomposes the incoming tasks, routes
them to the specialist agents, manages the
state and controls the execution order.
It always knows what is happening
across the entire workflow.
And then you have decentralized
forms where the agents coordinate
themselves through shared state
message passing and peer to peer.
There is no central authority.
The swamp sound really attractive
on paper as they maximize the
parallelism, and there is no single
point of failure and all of that.
But here is what I've seen in practice.
The emergent behavior in
swarm of autonomous agents
is extremely hard to predict.
When two agents produce ity or puts,
there is no resolution path, and when
something goes down, tracing the cost
through a web of P two P interactions
is significantly harder than in
a centrally orchestrated system.
So my verdict for the operational
workflows is centralized orchestration.
If your agents are influencing the
real business operations or updating
records, you need deterministic
control flow and clear accountability.
And yes, the orchestrator acts
overhead, but it is worth it.
The traceability and the
predictability you get in return
absolutely justify the complexity
an of the orchestrated architecture.
There are five layers here, and
each one has a very specific job.
At the top, you have
the orchestrator agent.
This is the coordinator.
It receives incoming requests,
decomposes it into tasks and routes
those tasks to the specialist agents
and assembles the final response.
And importantly, it never
executes the domain logic itself.
Its only job is to delegate.
Then you have the specialist agents.
Each one is grounded.
It receives only the context.
It is.
It needs for its specific function.
It owns specific tools.
It never reads the state
owned by a sibling agent.
Then the tool layer, and this uses MCP,
the model context protocol, standardized
access to the tools, built a tool,
civil ones, and any agent can use it.
Then the A two A, the agent
to agent protocol for cross
service agent communication.
This is framework agnostic, meaning
the land graph agent can call AC crew,
AI agent through the same interface.
And finally, the response aggregator.
This validates and finalizes everything
before it reaches production.
Think of it as a last gate.
The key thing about the separation
is that each agent operates on a
well-defined context window, and
when something goes wrong, you
know exactly which agent owns it.
We have four patterns for
the fair yield domain.
Isolation first is a circuit breaker.
Every agent call is wrapped
in a circuit breaker.
When an agent starts failing above a
defined threshold, the breaker opens,
the orchestrator stops routing to the
agent and routes to a fall backing step.
This prevents re tries forms, which
is what happens when a degraded agent
keeps getting hammered with re tries.
Second, the agent sandboxing.
Agents operate in an
isolated execution context.
No state is shared in
memory between the agents.
All inter agent communication go
through a durable message bus.
Third, the timeout budgets.
Every single agent call now
carries a hard timeout that is
propagated from the orchestrator.
When an agent exceeds its budget, the
orchestrator routes to a degraded mode.
Slow fail is better than no fail.
And fourth is a fallback
reasoning path for critical flows.
We maintain a simplified fallback agent,
a lower capability with minimal tooling.
When a primary agent fails or times
out, the fallback activates, the
response quality might be a little
lower, but the service continues
graceful degradation over heart
failure every time observability.
If you instrument a multi-agent
system with a standard infrastructure
tools like CPU Mam latency, error
rates, you will have metrics that
look completely healthy while the
system is producing the wrong outputs.
The correctness of the multi-agent
system depends on the path of the
reasoning, not just the outcome.
An agent can written a well-formed,
technically valid response that
represents a completely wrong reasoning,
and the metrics cannot catch that.
Request latency was fine.
CPU were fine.
Error rates were zero, and
output was still wrong.
So what you actually need to observe
is a different set of things entirely,
which agent was invoked and why.
What context was passed to each agent
and critically what was omitted,
which tools were called which
parameters and what they return.
How the orchestrator resolved the
situations when two agents produced
conflicting outputs and the full
reasoning chain across all hubs,
not just the entry and the exit.
The way you get this is by instrumenting
each agent with a structured trace
schema, and you correlate all those
traces through a shade identifier
that propagates across all hopes.
So when something breaks, you
can reconstruct a complete
reasoning chain, not just where
it started and where it ended.
Every single decision in between
standard distributed tracing tools
like Azure or zipkin are excellent, but
they record that the Agent B was score.
They do not record what Agent B decided.
For multi-agent systems,
you need both layers.
Local versus cloud.
Running a multi-agent system
locally is a solved problem.
Spin up a local model.
Agents in Python process use a
SQ L light for checkpointing.
It works and it is great for
development, running it reliably in cloud
infrastructure at scale, under concurrent
load across rolling deployments.
That is fundamentally a
different engineering problem.
Let me work you through what
actually changes state persistence.
Sql, like locally, but in production.
You need Postgres or something
that is distributed tool access.
In process function calls locally,
but in production, these become
containerized MCP, microservices
agent communication, localized
calls locally, but in production.
These are A two A servers that are running
as cloud functions or Kubernetes ports.
The orchestrator a single process locally,
but the stateless containers in production
with all state living externally.
Inference, local model locally,
but managed inference behind a
gateway like light LLM in production
and the cost zero locally and
very much non-zero in production.
Every single one of these is a
deliberate architectural decision.
None of them are optional, and there
are three failure modes unique to the
cloud deployment that nobody talks about.
The first one is the
token cost compounding.
Four agent system with five tool calls per
agent is 20 or more LLM calls per request.
At cloud pricing you need per agent token
budget unfolds at the orchestrator level,
not as a guidelines, but as hard limits.
Checkpoint state and rolling deploys.
When you deploy a new version.
In flight, workflows are
checkpoint against the old schema.
If anything is changed,
they may fail to Alize.
Treat your checkpoint format
has public APIs, version it
from day one and cold start.
Latency agent containers can
take 30 to 60 seconds to cold
start production request rates.
User will wait.
You have two options.
Keep the containers form which
cost money or design fallback
parts that tolerate the delay.
And these are the tools that we have
validated as part of the technology stack.
Land graph for orchestration, stateful
agent graph with builtin, checkpointing,
conditional routing, and nato.
Human in the loop in drop support MCP,
the model context protocol for the tool
integration A two A. The agent to agent
protocol for agent coordination as
inference, gateway, unified model access
with rate limiting fallback routing,
cost tracking across multiple providers.
L views for the observability
and deeper value for evaluation.
Now, these are not the
only tools for each layer.
The patterns are what matter.
These are just the current best in
class implementations of those patterns.
Use whatever fits your stack.
Governance.
Governance is not a
compliance teams problem.
Once autonomous agents start
influencing production workflows,
it is engineering requirement.
You design it in, or the
system is not production ready.
Three patterns that
are all non-negotiable.
Output validation.
Gates, every agent output passes
through a schema validation
before hitting the production.
Invalid outputs are rejected and
logged, never silently applied.
Human in the loop thresholds.
Low risk decisions proceed autonomously.
High risk ones Go to a
review of our human approval.
Get the threshold right and you
have both efficiency and safety.
And I mutable audit logs.
Every agent decision that results in
a production action is persisted with
full context, the reasoning, the tools
invoked and the intermediate outputs in
regulated industries, this is a difference
between the deployable system and the
one your legal team will not sign on.
So let me close with six principles.
The problem is engineering
problem, not prompting.
If your system is unreliable, the
answer is almost never in the prompt.
It is in the architecture.
Centralized orchestration,
answer overhead.
The predictability and the traceability
justify the coordination Cost
observability must be decision aware.
Infrastructure metrics alone
cannot tell you what went wrong
in multi-agent reasoning chain.
Cloud deployment is a
different engineering problem.
Token cost compounding, checkpoint
migration, cold start latency.
None of these exist locally
designed for them from the start.
And governance is a first class concern.
Once the agent touch production or
put validation, human in the loop.
Escalation and audit
logging are non-negotiable.
Three tensions.
He will always have to navigate.
Latency versus accuracy,
autonomy versus auditability,
generality versus reliability.
You just get better at calibrating them,
build the systems that you can trust.
Thank you so much for listening in,
and I'm happy to take any questions.