thanks for the opportunity to talk about,
the library, Yeah, I in, disturb payments.
Basically, it's a great opportunity here.
so I want to continue.
I want to, take this time and then
thank you everybody, who is having,
the session and then who is attending
the session and then hope, after the
session, you guys get to know more
about why we need AI in disturb payment
security and this current world.
So I wanna I'll basically.
Go through some of the slides I have.
so yeah, let's get started.
So the global, digital payment
market is rapidly basically
expanding and throughout the world.
And we are projecting this, payments
will exceed 15 trillion dollars by 2027.
That's a huge number.
Growth is basically followed by
increasing the number of factors,
something like, contactless transaction,
evaluate and black chain based system.
So this kind of stuff.
And then, however, this is like
a lot of, the pros comes with
the cons and something like that.
There are some, cyber threats,
online frauds that are happening.
And then, that, that's a huge number
that we are talking right now.
That number may reach by 48
billion annually by 2025.
So this presentation explore basically,
the artificial intelligence is
transforming to still a. Payment security.
So why we need, artificial intelligence.
we'll basically dive in, into the
realtime fraud detection, predictive risk
analysis, and adapt to threat migration.
We'll showcase how a power
module, out perform in,
traditional methods and discuss.
Emerging things like quantum secure
inscription and adversarial AI ism.
So paving the way for several
digital financial ecosystems.
I'll move on to the next slide.
so the AI fraud detection, there
are like a different type of
fraud detection that we could do.
something like, I can explain something
like deep learning and all of my new
So deep learning, when it comes to
deep learning, it's a neural network,
and a deep learning algorithm.
It's a kind of revolution, I would
say, and then, which basically detects
the fraud by analyzing millions of
transactions that happens in real time.
And achieve the And 80
percent of improvement over
traditional root based system.
So these sophisticated models adapt and,
learn few new fraud pattern continuously.
and then when it comes to anomaly
detection, advanced mechanism,
advanced machine learning algorithm
process, complex transaction patterns.
Use behavioral and constrictional data to
identify suspicious activities and then
with more than 98 percent of accuracy, and
this precise dramatically reduce the false
alter while catching the genuine threats.
and then let's move on to
the productive analytics.
That's a, and then there's a final
1 by analyzing the history of fraud
patterns, and imaging the threats.
Basically, so AI powered protective
models enable financial institutions
to prevent fraud before it occurs.
Basically, when something is happening,
something is fraud happening.
Basically, it, AI basically detects
this, and then the fraud is then
saving the estimated savings.
using AI, it's 12 billion
annually in potential losses.
yeah, this is huge, 12 billion annually
to save using the AI and why traditional
security system rely on the rich rules
that, fraud ensures can study, explore,
but AI power solution continuously
evolve to counter new threats.
we can detect the things before it happens
and then we can save a lot of money.
So basically, we doing, deep learning
algorithm Excel and, detecting
the suitable patterns across the
billions of data points and enabling
real time fraud prevention that
adopts imaging the attack vectors.
So the intelligence and learning
approach not only minimize the financial
losses, but also enhance the customer.
Trust by providing, frictional,
it's secure transaction, basically.
yeah, move on to the next one.
So let's talk about the real
time transaction monitoring.
So there are like three things we
could do, reduce a fraud incident
and then biometric integration and
then frictional experience, right?
So basically when it comes to the
reduce the fraud incidents, using the
advanced, AI monitoring system, and then
we can achieve basically reduction of
30 percent of fraud incidents and then
saving the financial incidents over 2
billion annual across the globe networks.
That's a huge number, 2 billion and
it's across the, global networks.
And then the second.
Thing that we could do biometric
integration, multi factor biometric,
authentication combined, facial
recognition and then fingerprint
scanning and then behavior
analysis created and what's well,
implemented security still with a 99.
9 accuracy.
that's very close to 100.
So 99.
9 accuracy where.
We can basically detect and then,
we can use a biometric integration.
that's what we can do.
And then, frictional explore experience,
smart, bio biometric verification,
complete authentication in under 0.
3 seconds, maintaining robust
security while delivering the
seamless payment experience.
That rate is, the card.
I'm gonna buy 25%.
That's a huge number there.
And then the economy and then
where transactions occur a million,
milliseconds, the real time monitoring
serves of the different payment security
or algorithm process over 100, 000 data
points per second, where it flags lot
of suspicious pattern, which allows.
We're allowing the, legitimate
payments to go through, and then we
can cut off the, theran, the kind
of fraud payments we can cut off,
and then we can save a lot of money.
yeah.
And then, yeah, this is, we can use
these kind of realtime transaction
monitoring over traditional method
to detect the fraud transaction.
And let's move on to the next one.
So the AI enable.
blacks and security.
So basically you can do the
A. I. In black chain security.
You know how, it's very big
deal with black chain security.
So the enhanced privacy, you can do the,
enhancing the privacy and then, federating
the learning and then secure transaction.
So basically there are, enhancing privacy,
I powered zero knowledge proves enables
secure verification of transactions.
Without revealing sensitivity details
and protecting the user privacy
while maintaining the transparency.
So basically, in nowadays, the privacy
is most interesting and then most thing
that people think about sharing that data.
by enhancing the privacy using
the AI and AI, which saves, a lot
of stuff, and then it gives us.
And hence, the zero knowledge proof
enables security verification.
and then federated learning by
training the AI models basically
across the distributed networks while
keeping data locally and, federated
lending enables financial institution
to collaborate securely without
compromising the customer data.
So basically.
You, whether compromising the customer
data, you can basically, go ahead and
use the AI models and then, teach them
or, guide them, train the AI models
and then get the, max, maximum out
of it for the customer that's using
the federated lending and then secure
transaction AI algorithm continuously
monitor the blockchain transactions.
And detecting anomalies and potential
threats in real time while maintaining
the immutable audit trails.
So the secure transaction, basically
using the AI, in the real time, you
can detect the frauds just like that.
And then you can save a lot of time, money
for the customer and for the institutions.
yeah.
And then the, the.
Convergency of blockchain and then
AI created a powerful foundation for
next generation payment security.
this is the future.
So we're basically AI and enhanced
blockchain native security feature
by adding the intelligent threats.
And detection and then privacy presuming
mechanism, through advanced techno
techniques like zero knowledge proofs
and then federating the learning and
then financial institution can now share
insight and valid transactions while.
Maintaining strict data privacy standard
and leading 60% of detection in security
breaches and full, with global privacy.
Yeah, that, that's what
we can do with blockchain.
AI, let's move on to the
next one next topic here.
And this is basically a case
study case studies in the industry
leaders by industry leaders.
so chargeback, reduction, leading, bank
have achieved a 40 percent reduction
in the chargeback prior and then, and,
savings over a hundred million annually
through AI powered transaction validation.
Use AI validation, and then
which basically saves 100 million
annually, in the banking sector,
basically, or you take any kind of
sector and then improve the speed.
So everybody want to work very speed.
Everyone want to get the
results, in a time manner.
So global payments processes plus
a report 20 percent of 25 percent
improvement in transactions.
That's a big number.
25 percent is basically.
You are basically improving the secured
payment methods by 25% and processing
over hundred thousand transactions per
second with, with the enhanced accuracy.
So basically, you're doing with
using the, the, whatever industry re
selling the hundred hundred thousand
transaction per second, enhance security.
Basically, this is a power to system
have reduce a false positives.
By 60 percent while blocking 99.
9 percent of fraudulent transactions.
it improves the 60 percent of the false
positives, where, so that, something
we usually get false positives nowadays
with using the traditional method.
significant improvement
in customer satisfaction.
And then these partner improvements.
Implementation by, these are all
pioneers implementation by major
financial institution demonstrate
the, transformative power of AI
payment security, but combining
mission learning with the traditional
security measures and then.
These organizations have not only
strengthened their fraud detection at
the same time, the, they enhance the
customer experience and then get the,
faster transactions and then get the
payments done very easily and they said,
this is all like a blueprint border
financial industry adoption strategy and
then let's move on to the next slide.
the reduction in charge backfired.
If you look at the graph bank here.
Fitech B and payment process C, where
AI power, fraud detection system
have demonstrated the remarkable
success in combating chargeback
fraud across the financial sector.
You can see here and then leading the
industry, a bank achieved an immense
42 percent reduction in fraud rental.
Chartbacks through implementing advanced
mechanic machine learning algorithm.
So you implement the machine learning
algorithm in the payment level.
And then basically, it will basically
deduct the 42 percent of the fraud,
parental transactions or chartbacks.
And then the FinTech B, if
you look at the FinTech B, a
solution delivered 30 percent of.
Decrease in the fraud under claims
while payment process see until
then system drove a substantial
of 40 percent improvement.
So that's a big number 40 percent
improvement that gives that shows that,
what is the reduction in charge back
for and then these results not only
represent significant cost saving.
Potentially, millions of
dollars annually, basically.
but also shows how AI driven
security solutions are, basically.
all the AI driven security solutions,
how it is helping the payment
system to basically improve the,
institutions, financial, and then,
of course, the customer service
to and the customer experience.
if you look at the advancement
in transaction speed,
this is fascinating stuff.
AI powered, payment system.
Our revolution transaction process across
the final sector, leading the transaction,
the lead, leading the transformation is
company X with a remarkable 27 percent
reduction in the processing time and
enable near institution payments, instance
payments for millions of customers and
company Z follows flows to 25 percent
improvement while the company Y, okay.
Achieves a 23 percent boost.
So if you look at the numbers,
these are good numbers, which
has the customers, which had the
institutions, they're all using the
algorithm and, optimization, they're.
Payment and then, customer experience.
And then this is all the significant
improvement, translate directly
enhance customer satisfaction.
So reduce the transaction amountment and
then stronger competitive and advantage
advantageous in digital payment landscape.
yeah, let's move on to the next slide.
So the next generation security, we
were, we are talking about the next
generation security where basically
what coming so quantum security
encryption implementing the post quantum
cryptography algorithm and then latency.
based inscriptions and to safeguard
the financial data against,
future quantum computing threats.
this is all in all quantum
security encryption.
We can do that.
And then we can basically,
you know, we can basically,
safeguard the financial data.
And, the adversarial AI defense,
deploying the sophisticated, neural
networks and defensive algorithm to
detect and, neutralize AI powder attack
targeting payment system, basically.
So if you improve the adversarial
AI defense based and the deploying
the sophisticated neural networks.
and defensive algorithm to detect
the neutralized AI power attack.
Any AI power attack we can basically
cut down, and then, target, which
basically target the payment
system, which is very important.
And then enabling the AI, that is
called, XAI, and then integrated advanced
model, interpretation, technique, and,
transparency frameworks, to ensure AI.
discussions.
all the decisions are traceable and then
complete with a regulatory standard.
So the next generation AI
security using this three topics.
And then we can basically advance
the security of each payment
and get the things done easily.
And then basically this basically
provides and then avoid the threats.
to the future, next generation, or
any payment stuff, that's coming
to the, any institution, any,
especially financial institutions.
together, this innovation from
a robust foundation for the
future of payment security.
yeah.
the interesting topic right now, why we
need, we spoke about AI and then, cyber
attacks, and then, but the important
point, why we need to use AI instead of
the tradition way that is our traditional
method that we are using right now.
Very interesting thing, right?
So yeah, using the ai, the of traditional
matter offers several advantages that
can signifi significantly, improve the
performance efficiency, the scalability.
So yeah, these are the
things that, you can improve.
And then here are the, and some of the,
few things I'll go over right now, and
then so that, you guys understand, why we
need ai, Instead of the traditional method
that we have right now in any, financial
institute or any transactions, any payment
transaction that we are using right now.
So the first thing is
automation of repetitive tasks.
AI can handle repetitive and then mandate
task much more efficiently than human,
which basically you can automate the
task and then you can get the results.
Better than what we are doing by
traditional method, which is done
by humans right now, this allows the
employees to focus on, high level
discussions, and then making creativity
and improving overall productivity.
whenever you're using the AI, which
basically does the automation on
the repetitive task, and then which
will helps the all the employees.
Who is working in the institution,
which helps the productivity and
then taking a good decisions and then
making, the all productivity good,
improving the productivity basically.
and then the 2nd thing we can do is
speed and accuracy using the eye.
A system can process a large amount
of data quickly and accurately,
unlike a traditional method, which
is very useful for, a lot of,
manual stuff that we are doing or
traditional stuff that we are doing.
And then this analysis, sometimes
human may, face the error, but, in AI,
you can handle tasks with a, greater
precision and real time, which is,
like I mentioned in the previous slide
is You know, it's just like a false
positive, you can basically have a lot
of false positive using the AI and then
using, this, and then you can speed up
the transaction and the scalability,
this is the biggest thing right now.
It is scalable is the biggest
thing in any institution.
a business grow at traditional
methods may struggle to keep up with
increasing volume of data and demand.
And, yeah, if you look at the numbers
right now in any in the world.
The payments, the digital payments are
increasing a lot, and then the scalability
for institution is the biggest thing.
So if you look at the demand
is very high day by day.
So A can scale to handle vast
amounts of data and complex tasks
without compromising the performance.
So making it ideal for large
organization or, those with a
rapid growth, like I mentioned.
If an institution is increasing their
rapid growth, you can basically,
make sure that you're using the
AI and then it will basically help
you finding the things for you.
And then, that's a good thing.
And then, of course, cost
efficiency, while there might be
upfront cost implementing the AI.
But over the time, it can reduce the
operational cost by automating the
task and then, reducing the errors
and, streamlining the workflow.
This can lead long term, savings and
then better allocation of resources.
data driven insight, AI can,
analyze large, data sets and
then uncover the patterns.
Or friends that would be difficult or,
what I'm going to say, time consuming
for the human to spot, sometimes,
we, we do a lot of errors with a
human error that happens everywhere.
it's, it's sometimes it's time consuming
as well when we do some kind of error.
So with AI.
we can save a lot of time and then,
this leads to more information, informed
decision making and then improved for
forecast and ability to take, proactive
actions or steps that can, that can
give a lot of time to the organization
and then good customer experience and
personalization AI enable highly me.
Personalized experience by analyzing
individual user behavior, for example,
AI driven recommendation, engines
like, those used by Netflix, Amazon
right now provide the user a tailored
solution, which difficult to achieve
with the traditional approach.
So when you're basically watching
a movie and then when you're doing
something in Netflix, Amazon,
you'll get the solution, which.
Right now, it's, compared to if
you use a I, what we are doing
in a traditional method, you'll
see a lot of improvement in that.
yeah, that's about why we need
to use the instead of traditional
way that we are using right now.
Let's move on to the next slide.
Though, yeah, quantum security encryption.
so as a quantum computing advanced at
the unprecedented pace, you look at the,
world right now, everybody, and then
most of the people are fascinated about
the quantum, computing, what it does.
What and why we need quantum computing.
I'm also very fascinated about
quantum computing and then so
it presents a critical challenge
to the digital payment industry.
So today encryption methods,
which they've got a billions of
financial transaction could be
rendered absolute and which powerful
quantum computer become a reality.
And this looming thread has
sparked the Development of
quantum security encryption.
So the revolutionary approach to
protecting sensitivity financial data.
So leading financial institutions
are already exploring the
breakthrough solutions, latency
based cryptography, which.
Create the mathematical problem and that
even quantum computer can't easily solve
the other promising approaches including
code base and multivariate Cryptography,
so there are a lot of issues in using
cryptography right now Which basically
even you know using the cryptography
sometime we fail, but Yeah, a lot of
interest in going with crypto right now,
each offering unique difference mechanism
and then against quantum attacks.
So by proactively implementing
these quantum resistance method,
bank and payment, provide can
future proof their security,
infrastructure and maintain the trust.
Of their customers, in a increasingly
complex technology, technical landscape.
yeah, let's move on to the next slide.
adversarial AI defense, in digital,
payment, landscape, criminal, the
cyber criminals are increasing,
increasingly using adversary AI.
To our smart security system, these,
sophisticated attacks, work by,
manipulating the transaction data.
For example, let's say, just in the,
adjusting purchase pattern or transaction
timestamp in a way that appear normal
to AI fraud detection system, but
actually fraud and also think of it.
As a creating a blind spot in a
vision and allowing a transaction
to slip through the notice.
So financial institutions are
fighting back with a robust advice.
a different strategy in the AI.
Now, financial companies or financial
institution thinking about how to
use AI through addressing training.
Basically, you're training the AI
and then you're giving the, you're
supporting with a lot of data as
systems exposed, simulated attacks
and building the resistance,
vaccines, strengthen the immunity.
yeah, this is how an adversarial
AI defense should work.
And then, that helps
a lot of institutions.
So the key takeaways, from this,
from this meeting or from this,
stuff, what I'm trying to do is
AI is essential, basically, and
then it's a continuous adoption.
So we're getting into AI world.
we're starting which the AI is.
helping in all the way and every
sector, but keep the customer data,
secure and then keep the payment,
keep the digital mechanism secure.
We need AI, which basically AI basically
solve a lot of problems, especially the
payment, payment securities enabling 99.
9 accurate and a percent of
accurate fraud detection.
And that's basically.
It's not, it's a huge number, 99.
9, fraud detection is very huge number.
And then it happens in, hours
to milliseconds right now.
So using the AI, you can get that accuracy
in milliseconds and continuous adoption.
Of course, the, any organization,
anything investing emergent technology,
quantum resistance and encryption
and adversarial AI defense to stay
ahead of evolving cyber threats.
First of the collaboration, cross industry
partnership, threat intelligence, sharing
the networks are vital for detecting the
emerging attacks, pattern and developing
the standardized security protocol.
yeah, so the integration of AI
payment security as more optional,
optimal, optional to the emeritus.
Basically, we have to use it.
It's essential right now.
What we are seeing the AI
is getting in all sector.
we have to take this and we have to adapt
the technology and then we have to use it
for a good reason and then make sure that
it is helping the And then it's basically,
we are talking about the transaction
right now, the payment transaction.
It has so much.
And then by taking those, concrete steps,
the audits and, regular security, the
organization can build a foundation for
secure and resilient payment system.
For future for tomorrow.
Yeah.
that's conclude my session on
the, how are we going to use AI?
Why are you, why it is so useful?
and then, why we need AI, and then how
it is helps to secure the data, the
customer, and then giving the basically
more productivity for the employee.