Welcome everyone.
Today, I wanted to take you on a
journey into the art of building long
management stacking systems that combine
modularity, scalability, and simplicity.
I have learned that the most
resilient systems often operate
invisibly, allowing businesses to
thrive without constant firefighting.
Let's explore how to achieve this harmony.
Back end architectures
have come a long way.
We started with simple, monolithic
systems that were easy to
understand but hard to scale.
Today, we work with cloud native,
distributed systems that serve
global users in real time.
However, this complexity often leads to
systems requiring constant maintenance.
How do we build systems that
scale without becoming a burden?
Modularity is the key.
Microservices allow teams to build,
deploy, and scale independently.
However, the goal is not
microservices for their own sake.
Design around your business dominance.
If your application doesn't need
microservices, don't force it.
Complexity can grow fast
if we are not careful.
Cloud providers offer managed services
that handle infrastructure concerns
like scaling, patching, and backups.
Serverless computing takes this further
by abstracting servers altogether.
This allows developers to
focus solely on business logic.
Yet a serverless isn't a silver bullet.
Hold starts and time
limits can be constraints.
Often a hybrid approach works best.
In modern software design, event
driven architectures have become a
critical approach to building scalable,
responsive, and resilient systems.
Unlike traditional request response
architectures, EDA enables services
to communicate asynchronously,
ensuring flexibility and efficiency
in handling unpredictable workloads.
One of the most significant advantages
of event driven architectures
is asynchronous communication.
Instead of directly invoking
other services and waiting for
responses, the system generates and
publishes events that interested
consumers can process independently.
This decoupling allows services to
operate at their own pace without being
blocked by slower components, leading to
improved responsiveness and reliability.
To facilitate this asynchronous
event flow, systems use event
blockers like Apache Kafka.
AWS EventBridge and RapidMQ.
These tools act as message intermediaries,
ensuring that producers and consumers
remain loosely coupled, which means that
the services do not need to be aware of
each other's existence, and the consumers
can process events at their own speed.
Without overwhelming upstream services,
systems can evolve independently,
making them more maintainable.
For example, in an e commerce platform, an
order placement event can trigger multiple
downstream processes, like payment
processing, inventory update, shipping
initiation, customer notification,
etc. And each of these events listens
for the event and acts independently.
Improving scalability and fault isolation.
One of the biggest challenges
in the modern architectures
is high load scenarios.
Event driven architectures naturally
support backpressure, which is a
mechanism that prevents the system from
being overwhelmed by incoming requests.
This is crucial for maintaining
system stability under spike loads.
Kafka and Sibila systems provide
mechanisms like consumer lag
monitoring and rate limiting,
ensuring services do not process
events faster than they can handle.
Since consumers process messages
independently, they can scale services
horizontally by adding more consumers.
to distribute the load dynamically.
If a sudden surge in the traffic
occurs, such as a flash sale on
an e commerce website, additional
consumers can be spun up automatically
to handle the increased event flow.
In today's digital landscape,
the scalability is not just
a feature, it's a necessity.
The application must handle
unpredictable traffic, growing user
basis and fluctuating workloads by
maintaining performance and reliability.
The scalability ensures that a
system can efficiently grow or
shrink in response to demand without
compromising speed or availability.
A key principle of scalable architecture
is designing stateless applications.
So in a stateless system, each request
is processed independently without
relying on stored session data.
Any instance of the application
can handle any request and scaling
horizontally, which means adding more
instances, is straightforward as there
is no dependency on local state storage.
For example, in a microservices based
e commerce platform, the stateless
services like authentication, order
processing, and inventory management can
be deployed across multiple instances.
Since, they do not store session specific
data, they can be dynamically scaled
up or down based on traffic volume.
Manage user sessions.
In a stateless architecture, the
developers use external storage solutions
such as, or for session cing, database
backend storage for persistent user,
and jwt, which means the J to for.
or stateless authentication,
where the session data is
embedded in the token itself.
By ensuring that the applications
remain stateless, we eliminate
bottlenecks and make scaling seamless.
As traffic increases, distributing
incoming requests efficiently across
multiple instances is crucial.
Load balancers act as traffic
directors, ensuring that no
single server is overwhelmed.
There are different types of load
balancing strategies, which include round
robin in which each request is distributed
sequentially to the available servers.
The least connections in which the
requests are routed to server with
fewer active connections and weighted
load balancing in which the servers
are assigned different weights based
on their capacity directing more
traffic to high performing instances.
The popular load balancers include
AWS Elastic Load Balancer for
the cloud environments, Nginx for
premises deployments and Cloudflare
for global traffic distribution.
The load balancing enhances the fault
tolerance as failed instances can be
automatically removed from the pool
while new instances take over seamlessly.
Even with load balancing, a static
infrastructure is insufficient
for handling spikes in demand.
The auto scaling allows systems to
dynamically adjust computing resources
based on real time traffic patterns.
The auto scaling groups monitor
key performance metrics such as CPU
utilization, memory usage, network
traffic, and request per second.
When the threshold are
exceeded, additional instances
are spun up automatically.
On the other hand, during low
traffic periods, excess resources
are deallocated to optimize cost.
For example, an online streaming
service like Netflix experiences
peak loads in the evening.
Using AWS Auto Scaling, they can deploy
more instances in real time and scale
down overnight when the demand decreases.
Autoscaling is most commonly used with
cloud native services like AWS Autoscaling
Groups and Google Cloud Instance Group.
By integrating autoscaling, businesses
reduce operational costs while ensuring
high availability and optimal performance.
Observability ensures system reliability
by providing deep insights into
application performance and behavior
through logs, matrices, and traces.
The tools like ELK Stack, AWS Cloud Watch
help us to capture and analyze logs and
system health in real time and thereby
reducing the troubleshooting time.
The distributed tracing with open
telemetry allows developers to
track requests across microservices.
pinpointing bottlenecks efficiently.
The smart alerting systems like PagerDuty
can notify teams about anomalies before
they escalate into critical failures.
By integrating observability into your
architecture, you can proactively detect,
diagnose, and resolve issues, minimizing
downtime and enhancing user experience.
Avoiding common pitfalls in software
design ensures maintainability
and long term success.
Overengineering leads to unnecessary
complexity, making systems harder
to debug, scale, and maintain.
Therefore, simplicity should
be always prioritized.
ignoring legacy systems can
create integration roadblocks.
Instead, adopt a gradual migration
strategy or, wrap them with
APIs to extend their usability.
lack of documentation causes
confusion and slows down development.
So clear up to date documentation ensures
smooth onboarding and knowledge transfer.
By focusing on practicality.
seamless integration and
thorough documentation.
Teams can build efficient
and sustainable systems.
Scalability starts with choosing the
right database for your workload.
NoSQL databases like MongoDB and
Cassandra excel at handling large scale
distributed data with high write output.
The relational databases such as
PostgreSQL, now enhanced with JSON
support, Provide a structured query
while allowing semi structured
flexibility, making them a hybrid
solution for evolving applications.
Blindly adopting a database trend can
lead to inefficiencies, so it's crucial to
evaluate data consistency, query patterns,
and scaling needs before making a choice.
A well planned database strategy ensures
optimal performance, maintainability, and
cost effectiveness as your system grows.
Building adaptable systems ensures
long term stability and smooth
evolution as requirements change.
Feature flags enable controlled
rollouts and instant rollbacks,
allowing teams to test new
functionality without disrupting users.
API versioning and continuous refactoring
prevent breaking changes and keep
the codebase maintainable, reducing
technical depth and ensuring seamless
integration with future enhancements.
Invisible infrastructure means a
system that runs smoothly without
drawing attention, allowing both
users and developers to focus on
functionality rather than maintenance.
Modularity ensures that components are
loosely coupled and easily replaceable,
making scaling and updates seamless.
Automation eliminates manual
interventions, enabling self healing
systems, efficient deployments,
and reduced operational overhead.
By prioritizing simplicity, teams
can build resilient, scalable
architectures that enhance agility and
innovation while minimizing complexity.
At its core, technology exists
to drive business value, not just
to implement the latest trends.
The true measure of success lies in
building resilient, scalable systems
that support long term growth while
minimizing maintenance overhead.
By focusing on stability,
adaptability, and efficiency, we
ensure that architecture remains
an enabler for innovation rather
than a source of complexity.
A well designed system doesn't
just keep up with the change, it
also anticipates it, allowing the
businesses to evolve with confidence.
Thank you all for your
time and attention today.
I hope you found valuable
insights that you can apply to
your own backend architectures.
And if you'd like to continue
the conversation, feel free to
connect with me on LinkedIn.
Let's keep learning and
building great systems together.