Hello everyone.
Thank you for being here today.
Today we are going to dive into
an exciting and transformative
topic, microservices architecture
in cloud native systems.
We will explore how microservices
have evolved The key principles
behind them, challenges in their
implementation and best practices
that industry leaders follow.
By the end of the session, you
will have a solid understanding
of microservices and how they fit
into modern cloud environment.
Let's get started.
What is microservices architecture?
To begin.
Let's define microservices
architecture in simple terms.
It is an approach to software
design where an application is built
as a collection of small loosely
coupled services that work together.
This is a huge shift from the traditional
monolithic way of building application.
And it's crucial in cloud native
environments for a few key reasons.
the first is it allows application
to scale more efficiently.
It, speeds up development cycles.
It enables rapid deployment
and continuous delivery.
Throughout the session, we will
unpack these ideas and see how they
play out in real world applications.
Let's take a moment to talk about
monolithic architecture and traditional
software development applications
are built as a single unit.
While this approach works well for smaller
projects, as applications grow, monolithic
structures become difficult to maintain.
Here are some key
challenges with monoliths.
A large code base makes updates
complex and time consuming.
Scaling requires redeploying the entire
application, which is not efficient.
Slower deployment cycles make it harder.
To quickly roll out new features.
This is why companies are shifting
towards microservices, which
allow teams to develop, deploy,
and scale services independently.
It's a game changer for
modern software development.
So when does it make sense to transition
from monolith to microservices?
If application is growing and
becoming difficult to manage,
microservices might be the answer.
If you need independent scaling for
different components of your application,
if DevOps and continuous deployment are
priorities for your team, this shift
requires careful planning, but when done
it brings incredible benefits in terms
of agility, resilience, and scalability.
To successfully design microservices,
we need to follow some key principles.
SRP, the Single Responsibility Principle.
each service should do
one thing and do it well.
This keeps services
lightweight and maintainable.
Lose coupling and high cohesion.
Service should be independent but
still work together efficiently.
The API first approach.
All communication should happen
through well defined APIs,
making integration smoother.
Domain driven design services
should align with business.
capabilities, ensuring better
organization and maintainability.
Keeping these principles in mind
will help us build scalable and
efficient microservices architectures.
Now let's, look at the core components
that make microservices work.
Service communication.
This can be synchronous.
With REST or gRPC for real time
interactions or asynchronous
message use like Kafka or for
the decoupled communication.
Service Discovery ensures that
microservices can dynamically
find and interact with each other.
API Gateway acts as the entry
point managing security,
load balancing, and routing.
Database per service.
Each service should have its own
database to maintain independence.
Together, these components create a robust
and efficient microservices architecture.
To deploy and manage microservices
effectively, we use some key technologies.
Containers and Kubernetes.
Containers like Docker package
microservices, making them portable.
Kubernetes automates deployment,
scaling, and management.
Serverless and function as a service fast.
This allows microservices
to execute on demand without
managing the infrastructure.
CICD pipelines.
It automates testing,
deployment, and updates.
Enabling continuous
integration and delivery.
These tools help streamline development
and ensure that applications
run smoothly in production.
Of course, microservices come
with their own set of challenges.
Data consistency and
distributed transactions.
Managing transitions across
multiple services can be complex.
service communication, choosing
between REST, gRPC, or message
brokers impacts performance.
Security.
Implementing authentication,
authorization, and zero
trust security is crucial.
These are some of the biggest hurdles
teams face when adopting microservices.
But with the right strategies,
they can be effectively managed.
Monitoring services is critical
for maintaining performance
and debugging issues.
Key tools include, Promethesis
and Grafana, used for collecting
and visualizing metrics.
OpenTelemetry, a standard
framework for observability.
We also focus on logging to track
events in the system, tracing
to follow requests as they move
through the different services.
metrics, to monitor
application performance.
observability ensures we can
detect and resolve issues before
they become the major problems.
Let's take a look at how industry
leaders have successfully
implemented microservices.
Netflix, one of the
pioneers of microservices.
They transitioned to this model to
handle massive scalability requirements.
Uber, originally built as monolith
Uber moved to microservices to
improve agility and manageability.
these examples show that,
microservices are not just a trend.
They are a necessity, for
companies operating at a scale.
As we wrap up, here are, some
key takeaways for implementing
microservices successfully.
Start small and evolve.
Don't try to migrate everything at once.
Begin with one service
and expand gradually.
Automate everything.
CICD, testing and deployments
should be fully automated.
Design for failure and resilience.
Use retry circuit breakers and
fallback mechanisms to handle failures
gracefully, which is resilience.
Continuous learning and adaption.
Monitor performance, collect feedback,
and keep refining the system.
By following these best practices,
organizations can fully leverage
the benefits of microservices.
Brings us to the end of our discussion.
Microservices enhance scalability,
agility, and resilience, but they
require careful planning, security
concentrations, and robust monitoring.
I hope this session has provided you
with valuable insights into designing,
deploying, and managing microservices
in cloud native environments.
Now I'd love to hear from you.
Do you have any questions?
Thank you for your time.