Hello everyone.
I am Abdul Hamid Mohamad, a certified
software engineer with over nine years
of experience in full stack development,
IoT integration, and cloud technologies.
I have worked with major enterprises
like 7 Eleven, Deloitte, and
Resoltech, helping business modernize
their back end architecture and
scale application efficiently.
Today we will discuss microservices.
So let's proceed.
Have you ever struggled with scaling
applications, deploying features,
faster or maintaining system stability?
Imagine deploying updates every 11.
7 seconds, just like Amazon and Google.
That's the power of microservices
and today I'll show you how they are
revolutionizing modern web development.
In this presentation, we will explore
why microservices are replacing
monolithic architecture, the real world
benefits of microservice adoption,
how organizations can transition
successfully to microservices.
Let's dive in the rise of microservices.
The shift to cloud native architectures
is now the industry standard.
84 percent of enterprises have already
embraced cloud native architectures.
Making a fundamental shift in how
applications are built and deployed.
Since 2020, microservices adoption has
surged by 50 percent year over year.
Netflix is a prime example.
Running over 900 microservices to deliver
167 million streaming hours daily.
That's equivalent to 19, 000
years of content watched.
So why are companies adopting
microservices at this scale?
Let's explore their agility and speed.
Organizations that transition to
microservices experience massive
improvements in development
agility and deployment speed.
77 percent of companies report faster
development cycle, enabling quicker
innovation and market responsiveness.
23 times more frequent deployments
shifting from monthly releases to
multiple daily updates, 65 percent of
reduction in production failures, thanks
to fault isolation and best better
system resilience with microservices
businesses can experiment, innovate,
and adapt faster without being
considered by monolithic bottlenecks.
Core principles of microservices.
What makes microservices so powerful?
They rely on three core components,
resilience and recovery organizing report,
a 92 percent improvement in meantime to
recovery, reducing downtime and enabling
faster issue resolution, faster deployment
cycles, team achieve 75 percent shorter.
development cycle allowing parallel
deployment of independent services,
continuous integration and deployment.
CICD microservices support modern DevOps
pipeline ensuring automated testing,
faster deployments and smoother rollout.
The result, more action and
better customer experience.
the speed of updates.
Companies like Amazon and Google are
setting a new standard for deployment.
Every 11.
7 seconds, a new code update is deployed.
No scheduled maintenance windows,
just continuous improvements.
Critical security patches and new future,
new features are rolled out instantly.
This shift means business can stay
ahead of security risk and deliver
new feature faster than ever before.
Now discuss the benefits of microservices.
Microservices unlock three key benefits.
Scalability, maintainability.
71 percent of enterprises handle
More than 100, 000 concurrent users
with reduced cloud cost by 30%.
Teams can scale individual
services independently, eliminating
performance bottlenecks.
Maintainability 68 percent of developers
report 75 percent faster update cycles.
Bug fixes are deployed 37 minutes
after discovery instead of 24
hours delays in monolithic system.
Microservices are not just a
technology trend, but they are
business enabler adoption rate.
Microservices are the future of
modern application development.
63 percent of enterprises have already
deployed microservices in production.
29 percent are actively planning
adoption within the next year.
Only 8 percent of organizations
remain undecided with 92 percent of
businesses enabling microservices.
Their transformation is unstoppable.
So let's discuss how you can
transform your architecture,
how you can use a microservices.
There are three basic simple steps,
conduct a throw architecture audit,
identify bottlenecks and dependencies,
establish clear performance benchmark.
In your plan, design resilient
microservice aligned with business
goals, define microservice boundaries
and API contracts, develop a
strategy with risk migration plan.
Implementation.
Start by transforming low
risk, high impact service.
Implement monitoring, automated
testing, and CICD pipelines.
Optimize performance with real
time feedback and iteration.
Now, let's go with real world
case study, e commerce platform.
Here is how one e commerce
platform transform its
performance using microservices.
Before microservices, 48 hour deployment
cycle with frequent system wide outages.
could handle only 1, 000 concurrent
users with 3 second page load time.
8 hours of monthly downtime
due to full system updates.
After microservices, deployment
time reduced to 15 minutes
with 0 downtime updates.
Platform now supports 50, 000
plus concurrent users with 200
millisecond page load time.
99.99% uptime with three
time faster feature delivery.
The result, faster
innovation, better user.
Our key takeaways microservice provide
three game changing advantages, agility,
scalability, and maintainability.
Agility provide faster deployment.
Reduce time to market up by 75%
in scalability application can
handle 40 time more traffic while
reducing infrastructure cost.
Is in maintainability, isolated
services, cut debugging time by
over 70%, allowing faster updates.
Here are our final thoughts.
Microservices are not just
architectural upgrade.
There are fundamental shift in
modern software development.
So the question is your organization.
Ready to make the shift.
If you're looking to accelerate
development, scale application and
stay ahead in the digital economy,
let's connect and discuss how
microservices can work for you so that
you can evaluate, plan and implement.
Your current architecture
can identify pain points.
And plan your microservice roadmap,
ensuring seamless migration,
step by step testing regressively
while scaling gradually.
Thank you for watching.
Microservices are transforming the
future of web architecture with agility,
scalability, and maintainability.