Hello everyone.
Welcome to this session.
My name is Elizabeth Fontes.
I am developer advocate on a,
and I am part of the identity.
So let's start the session from today
is when RAC hallucinate numbers.
So graph rack for persist answer.
And this session is part of six
block I already released and all
this block are talking about how you
can avoid a Gen hallucination five
technique to stop AI agent for failure.
And the first one is the one
that the session is about.
The second one is semantic tool selection.
So you are going to build a vector
store with files for all your tools.
So when you invoke the engine is
only going to use the tools that
the engine needs for the query
that you send for this agent.
Because before to go to the engine, the
query is going to go first for a vector
store when you are going to have all
your tools inside that like a vector.
The third one is multi in validation,
so execute validator and click pipeline.
So you will use.
Some agents to validate the
answer that before to send it
to your customer, for example.
Then you have neuro symbolic
guardians hard rules.
The LLM cannot bypass, and when
you have some more not so hard
rules, you can use a core steel.
So you can self-correct
instead of failure.
And the last one is production deployment.
So when you can use all this technique
together to build a real engine in
complete production in less than
10 minutes, because we are always
building engines inside or machine.
But what happen when you want to build a
real agents and put in the productions?
So this block probably is
going to help you with that.
Let's start it, the first one, graph
rack, and let's see what I have here.
So U Rack agents seems smart.
Until you ask it to come something.
For example, how many
hotels have swimming pools?
Your agent search its documents,
finds tree reads the numbers, and
says approximately four or five.
And the real answer is what?
Hundred 33.
So come on this.
This is no close miss, that is fabricate
numbers delivered with full confidence.
And it happened because Vector search
returns the most similar documents.
Not all the documents there, your
agent answered from 1% of the data.
The agent never have all the
data to answer your question,
and graph rack fixes this.
So instead of searching by
similarity, it converts your
documents into knowledge graph.
So every hotel, for example, have.
Rooms and amenity and all of
that becomes a node, a note.
So when your agent needs account,
it writes a strict query and the
database runs like a accounts query
across every node in the graph.
And it, the engine only
use three documents.
The engine is going to use all of them.
So using the normal rack, the engine
estimate from whatever chunks it retrieve
with full confidence and it's wrong.
It's not okay.
So now with graph rack, the engine
queries, the graph, the database
computes and is, you are going
to have the exact, the answer.
And when the data does not
exist, graph rack returns empty.
No fabrication.
So the A is not going to
fabricate an answer for you.
So these are the ties
of rack hallucination.
So we have fabricated statics, we
have incomplete retrievals, and out
of content, out of domain fabrication.
Answer for you.
So let's see.
In this session we are going
to build two different agents.
The first one is going to use a simple
vector store, and we are going to build a
tool capable to do retrieve to for this.
Knowledge base, a vector knowledge
vector, store knowledge base, and we are
going to add that tool for our agent.
And our agent is going to
have the capability to do
retrieve to this vector store.
And the second one is a graph rack agent.
And we are going to build a tool capable
to do the retrieve or capable to do the
queries in this graph knowledge base.
And this tool is going to give
the capability of our to do to.
Que And to have the knowledge
graph as a store as knowledge
base is a little I know, complex.
And so first we need to
build a vector graph store.
And we, in this demo, in this
code that I'm going to share with
you, you can use the bill graph
application Python application.
So we use Neo four J. Simple
knowledgeable pipeline.
So this pipeline.
It allows you to know hardcore schema
so you don't have to create a manual
schema because it use a LLM, a large
UAL model that reads each document
and discovers the entity types itself.
So for example, hotels room, many
policies, service, it extracts
the relationships between them.
And entity resolution merge duplicates.
For example, outdoors pools and
swimming pool becomes one because
at similar, and the duplication is
what makes the count query accurate.
And in this demo, in this code,
you are going to to find two
different build graph application.
One capable to build a graph store, vector
store only using the 10% for all data.
And if you want to build a more
gear app, you can use the normal
with the full documentation.
There are 300 hotels there.
I recommend if you want to test, if
you want to build this application, I
recommend you to use the light version
because it's going to be more fast and,
eh, now we need to do the query, like the
query for this, eh, for this knowledge
graph, for this, eh, with the agent.
Receive a question, it does
not search, but similarity.
Remember in Knowledge Graph
we don't search by similarity.
It writes a CY query and the cipher is
a Neo four J query language is similar.
SQL for graph, something like that
is not the same, but it's something
like that and the schema in the tool.
I will show you it's dark stream,
so it dark stream grounds.
The LNM it knows exactly which no types
and relationship exists, so it can know
invent and no type that is not there.
So it is, it's like doing a query.
And here you can see the text to Cy Flow.
So it use the, when you receive the
question, the LLM reads the schema
from the tool Duck Street and it
generates a valid cy query and the
database execute it across every node.
So it's a database execution.
The LLM is going is only going
to generate the cipher query.
It's going to be a query, and it's not
to be the retrieve or some document.
For example, the only LK tops
document three, whatever.
It's going to returns you the exact
results and the LLM can no fabricate
because the database either has the data.
Or it does not.
So the LLM is going only to receive
the query results is yes or no.
This is your number and.
This is something important because
when you do a normal rack, you do LLM,
it receive it's receive the retrieve of
this query, and you, LLM need to do the
aggregation for all this information.
So the LLM need to understand
all the chunks in your retrieve,
and each chunk is tokens.
Tokens that you have to pay
for, and then the diesel LLM is
going to generate the answer.
When you do a query, you are only going
to receive the information that you need.
And now let's see the
live demo in this demo.
I'm using a strands, a framework,
SDK, this framework I'm using Python
because I'm Python person, but we
have now a Strands a in TypeScript.
So you can use D framework
using type three as well.
This framework is completely
open source, but A is the owner.
We are the maintainer of this code, and we
have a lot of people in the community that
they are doing poor requests, for example.
We have a lot built-in tools inside
this framework, and if you, I don't
know, if you start to test this
framework and you have an idea to
improve it, you can do a pull request.
I can, I want to show you the link later.
So let's go to the code
here in this code.
In this repository that will share
you with you in a moment, you are
going to find all the techniques
that a I just mentioned and how
you can deploy these all techniques
into productions using a in core.
A in core is a service only to
agents to put agents in production.
So we have a lot of
amazing things in size.
Agent Core, I'm not going to talk
about Agent Core right now, but.
Agent court help you to put
your engine in a container.
So every time that you invoke the
engine, you are going to invoke
this container and you only going,
you only pay for what you use.
You don't have to have this container
forever there and it have memory.
Short, short term
memory, long term memory.
It have engage with lawsuit.
You to build MCP service.
Look, there is a lot of
things that I have here.
Please don't see it and, okay.
This is my notebook.
I you can find here all the applications,
but because we don't have a lot of
time, I going to run my notebook.
Let me close off this.
I think that this is, okay, so here
all this technique are basis in papers.
So I did our search and I learned
a lot about how you can about
genetic hallucinations, but.
When you read the paper,
you don't have the code.
So the idea is to build code that
allows you to avoid this, to avoid
hallucination using this technique.
So here you are going to find
all the code for this technique.
So let's.
Because Strands agent is
completely open source.
Remember, told you there is open source
I can use OpenAI as my mother provider.
I'm looking for a website.
I want to share with you
the Strands agent web.
So I'm using open ai, but you can
use a bunch of model provider here.
Of course Amazon veteran, that is our
model provider inside S Ropy Google.
And the modification that you have to
do is super simple to change the model
provider, you need the requirements.
Of course.
Let me show you and,
okay, let me run this.
I already have my open AI key.
I import my STRs library engine
that allows me to build the engine
and tool that allows me to build
the tools InSpa for this engine.
And because I'm using
OpenAI, I import this.
So for this, I need the requirements.
I need.
STRs, OpenAI.
Neo four J because I'm using Neo
four J as my knowledge graph.
And to understand this graph and
to create the nodes, I'm using open
AI as a model provider as well.
So for the Vector store,
I'm going to use files and.
So for the embedding model for
the vector store, I mean using
a simple semantic transformer.
This is a open source embedding model
that you can install and you can
put it and you can use, you don't
need to spend more money for that.
And okay, I have all my
nail four J information.
I have my nail four J here
running in my computer.
A local nail, four J
here, you can see him.
He's running.
It's the same, see my,
yeah, it's the same.
And, okay, I'm going to run this.
I have my models, my driver.
So I'm building the vector store in Fine.
We take a little moment.
So meanwhile here with this tool
decorated, I create the tools.
Yeah.
In the history, I have 300 documents.
Yeah, mine two probably.
I have some, what I say, I have
some duplicates in the first one.
And for this, when we build a tool from
Strands, we need to pull the tool ator,
and then all the code is in the tool.
It understand that code just right there.
It's regardless to this tool.
So this is the tool that unlocks
my aim to do the vector search
in the files vector store.
And the other one is the tool that
allows my agent to execute cyber query
against the hotel knowledge graph.
So this is my context.
Yeah.
You need to build a cy
query, blah, blah, blah.
So this is the driver, all the
code that this tool needs for.
And for create my, this is my agent.
This only lines of code.
Here are my agent, and I put a name.
This is my prom.
This is the tool and this is the model.
For example, if I want to
change the model, I can do that
only, put in a new for that.
When we use the Strands agent
framework, let me show you.
We use the agent loop.
Agent loop is this.
The agent loop is when you send
the input and you send the context.
For example, if you have a chat
history, you need to send the chat
history and you involve the agent,
and the agent is not most that.
In application is a, is only code
that use the LLM to reasoning.
So when you involve A, the LLM
is going to receive all the
tools that have available there.
So it's going to say, oh yeah, for
answer this question, I can use this.
Select the tool selection.
Then it execute the tool, the code
of this tool, and it receive an
answer and then give us the response
so you have the agent ready there.
So you already.
Eh, in both the saying once and in the
agent loop, if you want to change the
model, the prom, whatever you want inside
of this agent application, you can do it
in the second invocation, for example.
And you don't, you can, you are
not going to lose all the context
of the previous invocation.
So that's one thing
that STRs have for you.
You can change everything inside
the engine, in the loop, in the
next loop, in the next invocation,
so you don't lose the context.
All the other invocation.
You don't lose the chat history, the tools
the tools in vocation history to only.
Can change the model if you want.
For example, if you want to use
if you want to use a specific tool
with a different model, with a
different LLM, you can do that.
And all that is in the
trans documentation.
How you can learn, how you can
change the model, how you can
change the problem as well.
Everything is there and I'm not going
to talk about that, but I think it's
something important that you must know.
And my second agent turn me here for
my graph agent is the, is si similar,
but the only thing that I have here,
the only different is the other
tool, the queries knowledge graph.
So this is ready?
Yeah.
And I think I didn't run this out.
Now I want to run this and Yeah.
Sorry, I already run in, in a moment.
Let's see.
Okay.
Three.
Okay, one over.
So let's test the first one,
the aggregation, the first test.
So I going to use the two engines
and I'm going to send the same pro.
What is the average Yes.
Rating across all hotels in Paris.
So I run this and send this query.
Let's see.
I already told you when I asked to
a normal agents, a normal eh, rock.
It's only going to give
you the three, or, eh.
And K types can similarity,
answer for the question.
So the answer is going to be
basic only in the retreat.
So this agent only found
two hotels in Paris.
The question was Paris?
Yes.
So it's going to give me the
answer for these two hotels.
So it's send the question, it retrieve,
I need the retrieve and it find that
we have Paris and I don't know, I
don't know how to pronounce that.
The, in the LM, it's build a mathematical
application to give me the answer.
So if my model is not good at doing
mathematical calculation, probably I'm
not going to have a good answer here.
And for the graph rack
one, this is the rack.
Let me open this for you.
I, it's better.
It's less it is a small one answer.
The average guest rating
across all hotel is Paris in.
Paris is blah, blah.
I don't wanna see a dude, but.
M Yes.
Rough graph.
Half knitting, aara, so
across all me hotels.
So rack need to do manually calculates
from phone dogs and it can miss someone's
so that he can miss some hotels there.
Now let that county
you going to run these.
How many hotels have
swimming pools as amenity?
The same basing of the information
found there are no hotel.
Listen in Paris and blah, blah, blah.
And a huge answer for the raf for the
graph I have, there are no hotels as
offering swimming in Paris as a minute.
I think I'm bringing the answer twice.
So this is the only
answer that I have here.
That's it.
I only use this amount of
token to answer this question.
And for multi hub reasoning, the
question is what are the room types
of and price for the highest rating?
So we have here, what are the room
types in price of the Hyatt Hotel?
The Hyatt Riding Hotel in Paris is.
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And this database, it doesn't have
the prices number, so we only have
hotels and some information rooms.
We don't have price, for the first
one, he send me the hide, blah, blah.
We have a huge answer here and probably it
recommends me, no, we may contact hotel.
Okay, for the rack it says the hide ready
hotel is blah, blah, blah, whatever.
The guest ready room price
information is not available.
It send directly, it is not
available, so the room type
offer a lot information there.
What we see here, RAC finds hotel
but cannot, no traverse to room
data, graph rack, traverse, hotels.
And if I have the room data, it
can see, the room knows via cipher.
Have a, like a more complete answer here.
And for the four, the test four
we have out of domain detection.
So tell me about hotels in Antarctica.
Spoiler, there is no hotels in Antarctica.
Let's see, so for rag, I couldn't
find specific information about
hotel in Antarctica in the
available information, whatever.
I can give you a general overview.
All the information that it's
going to give me here, it's fabric.
K for this LLM is fabric.
K for the open AI modern I'm using here.
I didn't ask your recommendation.
I asked you a specific question.
Tell me about hotels in Antarctica
using the information that you
have in this knowledge base.
My they want all of me to complete me.
I. The Raf tell me there are no
hotel listening Antarctica in the
database if you have another specific
question and from blah, blah, blah.
No, they, no, I, no, I, there are
no hotel listening Antarctica,
so yes, RAF hallucinate.
It's fabricate info that when
the data is not available
there in graph Rack is honest.
No hotel is in Antarctica.
I don't have that.
So that's it.
It's a super short demo.
Let's come back to the deck.
When should you use graph
rack for persist queries?
Aggregation, multiple reasoning
across entities is data where you
need a very recover answers and.
When you should use Stick With
Rag because you know it's not so
bad when you need semantic search.
A structured text like FU matching simple
lockouts where you do not need to count
or aggregate the best production system.
Probably you can use both graph
rack for structural queries
and rack for open end search.
Is always going to depend
on your use case and.
Thank you.
In the first QR code you are going to
have my blogs and my old information.
And the second one in the resource
one, you will find all the repositories
trans documentation, a and core and
csat, where you can give me five times
if you want, if you enjoy this session.
So I hope to see you in
another session and thank you.