Hello everyone.
Welcome to this com 42 cloudnative
session on life of a packet in Amazon EKS.
My name is Do Tim Rap.
I'm a solutions architect at AWS helping
global financial services customers
architect scale and optimize their
business applications on AWS Cloud.
My background is in networking
and security infrastructure
engineering, and I've been in the
industry for over 20 years now.
in the past, throughout my career,
I worked at various systems
integrators and vendors such as
Nortel Networks, Brocade, and VMware.
In, I've been in different roles in like
network solutions architect, network
support engineers, solutions engineer.
And Solutions Architect.
Recently in this session, I will walk
you through the various packet walks in
Amazon EKS, diving deep into the container
network traffic forwarding in Kubernetes.
Here's a quick disclaimer, basically
stating that all the points that
I'm providing in this session,
I've observed and obtained, using
public tools and anything that I
mention in the session represents
my own opinions and not my employer.
So I'm gonna.
Quickly touch upon Kubernetes and
Amazon EKS, high level architecture.
I'm gonna talk about Kubernetes
network model and port connectivity.
I'm gonna do deep dive packet
walks, and then I'll introduce
Kubernetes services and ingress.
And, with those concepts, introduced,
I'll do some more packet walks.
there are things that I kept out of
scope in the interest of time, but
also to emphasize the foundational
concepts, for you to focus on.
So let's start with
Kubernetes architecture.
Kubernetes is comprised of two main
components, a highly available control
plane, which is comprised of two or
more nodes and a data plane, which could
be comprised of thousands of nodes.
And within the com control plane,
there's an API server, which exposes the
Kubernetes API to the external world.
It's the front end for the
Kubernetes control plane.
And then there is HCD, which
is the key value store that
keeps all the configuration and
state of the Kubernetes cluster.
And then there is scheduler
which decides on which node an
application port should run.
There is controller manager, which
is comprised of various controllers.
And in Kubernetes, a controller's
responsibilities to make sure that the
actual resources implemented in the
cluster always matches the desired state,
which the admin and the developer defines.
There is cloud controller manager, which
embeds cloud's specific control logic.
It allows the Kubernetes cluster to
provision cloud native resources.
Provision, monitor and remote, and
also remove those resources required
for the operation of the cluster.
All these components in the control plane
are implemented with high availability.
There's a lead reelection process
that takes place for each of them, and
within the data plane, you would have
the worker nodes where your application
workloads run in the form of Kubernetes.
Pos, keep in mind that a pod in Kubernetes
is the smallest deployment unit and.
A pod can consist of multiple containers.
There's an agent called culet running
on each node, and it's responsible
to run the pods, which are assigned
to the node and check their health.
And lastly, there is cube prox
agent running on each node.
It configures and maintains network rules
with regards to the traffic destined to
a Kubernetes service, a concept which I'm
gonna explain later on in the session.
Let's now look at how this architecture
is implemented in Amazon EKS.
The control plane is implemented in your
VPC, sorry, in A VPC, which is owned
and managed by the Amazon EKS service.
It's spans across multiple AZs.
It runs a minimum of two API
server instances, which also
run the cube scheduler and cube
controller manager components.
There are three eight CD instances,
which are spread across all three
AZs, and one thing to mention is that.
These, control plane notes,
these instances actually run in
an AWS autoscaling group, EC2
autoscaling group for simplicity.
Reason, I kept it out of
the scope of this diagram.
The Kubernetes API is exposed
to the public internet by an
AWS network load balancer.
So next is data Plane.
In the data plane, you run
your work nodes in your VPC.
The way these work nodes
communicate with the Kubernetes
API is through the cross account.
Eni, also called X ENI that are
implemented across at least two A. Let's
explain the Kubernetes network model.
Kubernetes imposes a few
fundamental requirements.
Each port gets its own IP address In
Kubernetes, pods can communicate with each
other without na, as a network address.
Translation, agents on a node can
communicate with all the ports on that
node, and a pod can consist of basically
multiple containers in Kubernetes.
It would have a loop back interface.
The containers would communicate
with each other through this loop
back interface in a pod, and this is
also called localized communication.
The port would also have an E zero
interface and the containers in the pod
would communicate with the other resources
through this eight zero interface.
Let's now look at how
pod connectivity works.
So you have the network interface of
the node itself, which runs in the
root network, namespace of the node.
Then you have a separate dedicated
networks namespace for the pod.
The way the pod network namespace
is connected to the root network
namespace is through a Linux construct
called V pair and a V interface.
The same approach is used for the other
pods on the node as well, and the way
the V interfaces connect to the Linux IP
stack differs across different solutions.
This is because various computer
environments may have different
connectivity characteristics
and requirements, and because of
that reason, Kubernetes itself
does not own the configuration
of the port connectivity part.
Instead, there's a specification
called Container network Interface,
CNI, in short, which leverages plugins
to implement port connectivity.
There are default.
CNI plugins like Loop Back Bridge, IPV
lan, as well as third party plugins like
Calico Cilium or Amazon V-P-C-C-N-I-C-N-I.
Plugin is basically an executable
file which runs on each node and it
is responsible for various tasks.
It adds and deletes the
network interface of the pod.
It calls the IPAM plugin to assign an
IP to the network interface of the port,
and also it sets up the V pair to connect
the PO network namespace to the host.
This is, how it looks like with EKS
and what tasks The VPCC and I perform.
EPCC and I implements
the pod connectivity.
It leverages either the secondary
IP address or prefix mode
capabilities of the EC2 service.
In order to assign an IP to the pods
from the VPC Sider, basically, in
essence, the pod ips are mapped to the
specific Ennis and as scale grows VPCC.
And I also needs to add or delete Ennis
on the node to make sure that there are
enough available ips, for the ports.
E-P-C-C-N.
I also configures the respective
routing entries in the node and it
also configures routing and ARP entries
in the pod network namespace as well.
Let's examine various interfaces
on the node and the pod.
So we got two ENI on this note, and
when you look at the pod network
interfaces, there's a look back interface.
and eight zero interface as
mentioned previously, and notice
that the subnet mask of the eight
zero IP in this pod is slash 32.
So routing table of the pod is set up with
a default gateway of 1 69, 2 54 0.1 0.1.
And this is basically the next top IP
that is configured as a local next stop.
With the Scope Link perimeter,
the Our Pantry for this default
gateway IP is configured as a
manual entry by the V-P-C-C-N.
I notice the m notation
in the flags mass column.
And when you check the interfaces of
the node, you would notice that the
default gateway Mac address you have
seen in the arc table of the port
earlier actually belongs to the V
interface in the root network namespace.
So the interface ID you see here on
the top right is the actual V id.
We will now examine ingress
and egress traffic on a node
with ports in this diagram.
PO 50 ones IP is a secondary
IP on ENI one and PO 60 ones.
IP is a secondary IP on ENI two.
Let's imagine traffic
coming ingress to the north.
Destined for PO 61 ip, the node
performs a root lookup in its policy
based routing table and matches the
traffic to the highlighted entry.
And that entry requires to perform a
root lookup in the main routing table.
So in the main routing table.
The traffic matches the highlighted
entry and the traffic gets
forwarded to PO 61 at this stage.
Notice the third entry in this
main routing table please 'cause
it's for the direct connected
subnet on the eight zero interface.
This will become relevant
in the next packet.
Walk.
Next, let's imagine traffic generated by.
PO 61 would send traffic
to a destination IP.
In the VPC, the node performs a
route lookup in its policy-based
routing table and matches the
traffic highlighted in the entry.
And that entry requires to perform
a root lookup in the routing table.
Number two, in that routing
table, there is only a single
entry for the default gateway.
Through ENI one, which
is the secondary ENI.
So the traffic will be sent through
ENI one to the default gateway.
And this is regardless of
whether the destination of the
traffic is on the same subnet as.
PO 61 or not.
'cause there's a single routing
entry, which points out through
routing table, number two.
And in that routing table.
Number two, that single routing
entry just points out to the E one,
which is the ENI two in on this, no.
So let's now look at port to
port traffic on the same node.
Pod 51 generates traffic
destined for Pod 61.
Notice the source Mac is the
pod 51 Mac, and the destination
Mac is the V interface.
Mac.
The note performs a root lookup in its
policy-based routing table and matches
the traffic to the highlighted entry.
And that entry requires to perform a
root lookup in the main routing table.
So in the main routing table.
The traffic matches the highlighted
entry and the traffic gets
forwarded to the pod 61 through
the respective V interface source.
Mac becomes the V Mac and the destination
Mac address becomes the PO 61 Mac.
This time we will look at.
Port to pod traffic across nodes PO 51
generates traffic destined for PO 81.
The node performs a route lookup in its
policy based routing table and matches
the traffic to the highlighted routing
entry, and that entry requires to perform
a root lookup in the main routing table.
And in the main routing table, the
traffic matches the highlighted entry.
'cause the pod 80 ones IP is on
the same subnet as the ENI one
interface of the node and the
traffic gets forwarded by the node.
Notice the source and destination
max become the ENI max ENI
of the respective notes.
The receiving note performs a
root lookup in its policy-based
routing table and matches the
traffic to the highlighted entry.
and then that entry requires to perform
a root lookup in the main routing table.
So in the main routing table, the
traffic matches the highlighted entry
and the traffic gets forwarded to.
The pod 81 through the
respective V interface.
So here, source Mac becomes
the V Mac and the destination
Mac becomes the pod 81 Mac.
Now let's have a look at the return flow.
So POD 81, response to the
previous request from PO 51.
The node performs a route lookup in its
policy-based routing table and matches
the traffic to the highlighted entry.
in that, and that entry
requires to perform a route
lookup in the routing table.
Number two, in the routing table two, the
traffic matches the highlighted entry,
so the node actually sends the traffic
to default gateway, even though port
81 and port 51 are in the same subnet.
This means if a pod.
Is a secondary IP of the secondary NI.
Then the traffic would always be
sent through the default gateway.
This would apply even if the port
and the destination is on the same
subnet as you can see on this diagram.
Then the default gateway forwards
the traffic to the other node.
The default gateway here that
you see would be the VPC router
that is maintained and run by AWS
implicitly to you as the end user.
So the receiving node performs a
root lookup in its policy-based
routing table and matches the
traffic to the highlighted entry.
And that entry requires a root
lookup in the main routing table.
In the main routing table.
The traffic matches the highlighted
entry, and finally the traffic
gets forwarded to the port 51
through the respective V interface.
So now I'm gonna explain the concept
of, called Kubernetes service.
Imagine we have a Kubernetes,
deployment manifest shown at the top.
This deployment manifest basically
represents a stateless microservice
application, which has three
identical pods also called replicas.
These pods have labels as metadata, which
are just like resource tags in AWS, and
each port is running the same application
on the same port like TCP port 80.
And in a typical scenario, you
would expose your application
to other applications and
sometimes to external clients.
So this in the Kubernetes, context,
this brings up an interesting point
because where you would need to
consider how to make these individual
pods in the application accessible
in an efficient and optimum way.
Because in Kubernetes, every pod gets its
own IP address, but pods are considered
to be FML rather than durable entities.
So meaning that when any of the pods
in this application, one gets killed or
terminated as a result of a failure or an
upgrade, then the deployment controllers.
automatically would instantiate new POS
as replacements in order to match the
actual state to the desired state, which
is the controller's main job, however.
The new ports would come with a
new ip, and this sequence of events
might happen thousands of times, in
a day due to the, nature of the agile
software development principles.
Hence, there must be a stable and
consistent way to access these, respective
microservice applications at a single
address every time in a seamless manner.
So that takes us to the what piece.
So a Kubernetes service, in essence, is
an abstraction, which basically groups the
pods together based on label selectors.
Here you can see the pods, which have
the label of name called on App one
become part of the Kubernetes service.
The Kubernetes service provides.
A front end for those pos and pos
are actually called endpoints in
Kubernetes service terminology,
and yet another controller.
Called Endpoints Controller is
responsible for keeping an up-to-date
list of these endpoints in case of
any failures or instantiations making
the application highly resilient and
Kubernetes service constructs supports
T-C-P-U-D-P and A CTP protocols.
So any request that comes into the
inbound to the DNS name or IP address
of the service basically gets forwarded
to one of the ports that is part of that
service or that is backing that service.
Sometimes it's called.
So it's just like a load balancer.
So there are different types of,
Services, Kubernetes service types such
as cluster ip, not port or load balancer.
These service types address
different communication patterns.
We will now go through those
communication patterns one by one.
Now service type cluster ip.
This is the default
service type in Kubernetes.
It's used to expose your application
on a service virtual IP address that
is only internal to that cluster.
So this virtual IP is
the same on each node.
And it's not shared or announced
anywhere than the cluster itself.
So access to this service is
only from within the cluster.
And let's take further,
into how it's implemented.
When you post a cluster IP type of
service manifest to the Kubernetes A
PIA component called Q proxy, which
exists on all the nodes, watches the.
Kubernetes API and detects that
a new service is just configured.
Then it configures the virtual IP
address of the service and a bunch
of forwarding rules in Linux IP
tables on every node, and at this
stage, you have the service available
for access from within the cluster.
On a side note.
Kubernetes has its own DNS, which
automatically assigns an internal DNS name
to each service using a predefined format.
So when a request comes to the
service, I. Virtual IP on a given
node, it'll be destination netted
to the IP address of one of the
ports, which is part of that service.
The algorithm for this is round robin.
And as a side note, Q proxy functionality
can be implemented using other
data plane options such as, Linux,
IPVS, IP Virtual Server, or EBPF,
extended Berkeley packet filters.
This can enhance the characteristics
of this load balancing algorithm
and decision, although for
simplicity purposes, it's
not depicted in this diagram.
Keep in mind that.
The pod that is part of the application
two and the port and the pod that
is part of the application one.
These can be on the same note and
this flow could still be the same.
So let's do a packet work in this
scenario to understand that better.
PO 51 generates traffic destined
to the service virtual ip.
The IP table is on Node 51.
Performs three tasks at this stage.
First one is load balancing the traffic
to one of the PO ips part of that service.
And in this instance, it sends the
traffic to PO 71, but it's extremely
important to know that as shown in
this diagram, even if there was a
pod part of that service running
on the same node, which is node 51.
IP tables load balancing algorithm could
still send the traffic to Port 71 or
any other remote port IP tables does not
differentiate between local and remote
ports, which are part of that service.
So the second task, is that IP tables also
applies destination net to the traffic.
Third task is since IP tables
is a stateful engine, it
keeps state of the flows.
It needs to keep state of the
flows, so it marks this flow to be
able to match any return traffic.
The node 51 forwards the traffic
to node 71 and notice that
the IP becomes about 71 ip.
And note 71 traffic gets
forward to apologies.
Note 71 traffic gets forward to Port 71.
Now keep in mind that in this
scenario, IP tables work alongside I.
All the policy routing tables
and other routing table logic
that we explained previously.
Another thing worth mentioning
is Port 51 would not know the
services virtual IP out of the box.
It would first.
Need to resolve the services
DNS name to its virtual ip.
So for that, it's important to highlight
that the Kubernetes DNS itself actually
runs on a cluster IP service as well.
So in reality.
To walk you through it really quick, what
happens is Port 51 in this topology would
generate a DNS request for the respective
services DNS name, and then that DNS
request is also sent to the Kubernetes
DNS services virtual ip, which then.
Gets load balance to one of the DNS
ports in the cluster, and then port 51
would receive the virtual IP address
of the Kubernetes service that it
wants to access from the first place.
So let's have a look at
the return flow here.
Port 71 responds to the previous
request from PO 51 and then.
Node 71 forwards the traffic to node 51.
The IP tables on node 51 first
identifies this traffic as return
traffic of an existing flow.
So it applies source net or
snet in short to the traffic.
And it basically swaps the source
IP of the packet with the virtual
IP of the service because Port 51
originally was communicating with
the Bernet service, virtual ip, not
Port seven one directly, and then
this traffic gets forwarded to PO 51.
Let's explain what
Northport type of services.
Northport is basically used to
expose your applications to external
resources for testing purposes.
It's built on top of cluster ip.
All the characteristics that I
mentioned for the service type
cluster IP apply here as well.
But there are also additional points
that enabled node port capability,
so let's explain how that works.
You post a note port type of
service manifest to the API.
The Q proxy watches the API and detects
that there is a new service and then it
configures forwarding rules and network
address translation rules in Linux tables.
But this time it actually configures
an additional rules for two reasons.
First.
To process the requests that come
to a specific port on the node and
second to forward those requests
to the actual Kubernetes service.
Keep in mind that the port
configured, on the nodes are all
the same on every node and the port.
That port has to be from a specific
range, which is shown on the top
right hand side of the diagram here.
So let's do a packet walk in the
Kubernetes service type note port.
This time request comes from
an external client or service
destined to the norde port.
On note 51, the IP tables on
note 51 performs four tasks.
This time it first load balances
the traffic to one of the pod ips.
Part of that service.
And as mentioned in cluster IP section,
please keep in mind that even when there
is a local pod on North 51, part of that
Kubernetes service, IP tables may still
forward the traffic to a remote po.
And in this instance, let's assume
that it sends the traffic to Port 71.
It then applies destination net or
dnet to the traffic, and it then has
to apply snet or source net to the
traffic as well to implement symmetry
for the flow, basically, so that the
client would not receive the response
traffic from the port IP directly.
Which would break the flow 'cause the
client originally is communicating
with the north port of the North 51.
So since IP tables keeps the state
of the flows, the fourth task is IP
tables marks this flow to be able
to match any future return traffic.
Then note 51 forwards
the traffic to note 71.
The node 71 then forwards the
traffic locally to the pod 71.
Now it's worth mentioning that the client
IP would always be S netted or source
netted, even when the destination pod was
running on the same node with Port 51.
Something to keep in mind.
The return traffic would look like this.
Port 71 responds to the request.
The note 71 forwards
the traffic to note 51.
The IP tables on Note 51 first
identifies the traffic as return
traffic of an existing flow, and
then it applies both destination net.
Swaps the destination IP with the
Port 51 IP and also apply source net
swaps, the source IP as the service
virtual ip, and then the non 51
sends the traffic back to the client.
The downside of the node port
is that you are supposed to
send the requests explicitly to
the node IP on the node port.
This means you need to figure out the
IP address of the individual nodes and
keep track of them in case of one of
the nodes fails, or you know you need
to do perform upgrades, et cetera,
and then additional consideration.
Would be how to distribute the client
requests across different nodes.
Sounds we need an external load
balancer 'cause that would be
the perfect solution to cover the
node failure or upgrade scenarios.
Let's look at how, the load
balancer type of service, is used.
So load balances type of service,
is we use this type of service
to expose the applications to
clients external to the cluster.
It's built on top of the node port,
and when you post the load balance
type of service manifest to the API.
As you can see, all the things we have
explained previously is configured
within the Kubernetes cluster and work
exactly the same way to be more specific.
Requests that hit the node
port on any of the nodes get
forwarded to one of the ports.
But this time Kubernetes expects.
An external component to detect the
new service and configure external
load balancer on the fly so that
load balancer starts forwarding the
requests from the clients to the nodes.
That external component.
Is a Kubernetes controller called
Service Controller, which comes as
part of the Kubernetes distribution,
the open source Kubernetes, code.
It's actually a controller bundled
within the controller manager component
that I mentioned when I was introducing
high level Kubernetes architecture.
And, AWS currently maintains
two such controllers.
One is the one that I just mentioned,
service controller, which comes as
part of Kubernetes out of the box.
And the other one is
AWS load ER controller.
Which is a Kubernetes special interest
group, SIG in short project on
GitHub that anyone can contribute to.
You can install this AWS load balance
controller to replace the service
controller as it has additional
capabilities such as Kubernetes,
ingress support, and also target type
IP support, both of which I'm going
to explain later on in this session.
Kubernetes service is a layer
four construct, so it does not
address layer seven load balancing.
So whenever you configure a service type
of load balancer, then the controller
provisions and AWS classic load
balancer type of elastic load balancer.
So this service controller that you see on
this slide, it is capable of configuring
classic load balancer by default.
And classic load er is
a legacy type of load.
Er, it can also configure,
a network load er, as well.
And, the network load balancer
is, it can perform health checks
against the node port on each node.
So here you see that we are instructing
the service controller to configure an
NLB to provision an NLB rather than.
CLB, the legacy type of load balancer,
but in short, Kubernetes service
type is for layer four traffic.
So let's do a packet walk with
the load balancer scenario.
The request comes from an external client
or service destined to NLB listener,
port on the listener IP Lord er has
all the nodes in its target group and
performs health checks on the node port.
And important thing to know, here is
that old nodes, including the ones
which do not have a pod, part of that
respective service would look healthy.
So all the nodes would, look as
healthy nodes in the network.
Node balancer target group, which
means node 51 would also be a
healthy target from NL B'S point
of view, ready to receive traffic.
So let's assume that NLB
forwards the traffic to note 51.
So note 51 receives the
traffic on its note port.
And rest of the flow would be
almost identical to the node flow.
The node port flow that we saw earlier,
the IP tables on the node 51 performs four
tasks, and as you can see, the destination
Kubernetes service, there are no ports on
Node 51, part of that Kubernetes service.
So what would happen is the.
note 51 when it receives the traffic
on a sport and when the IP tables on
Note 51 performs its tasks, the IP
tables on Note 51 first load balances
the traffic to one of the port ips.
that is part of that service.
And keep in mind that I'm showing the
most suboptimal forwarding scenarios
in this session intentionally.
If there is a local port on North 51
part of the respective service, then
IP tables may select that local port
as the destination, or IP tables may
still select Port 71 or any other
remote port as the destination.
So there is no guarantee
that it'll always.
Pick a pod that is part of the
service that is on the same node
where you received your traffic.
But let's assume that IP tables picks
the POD 71 as the destination pod
being part of the destination service.
So next thing is the IP tables would
perform dnet destination net to swap
the destination IP with the Port 71 ip.
And also.
It applies IP tables applies source
net so that it swaps the source IP
of the traffic with the Node 51 ip.
So lastly, the IP tables marks
this flow to be able to match
any feature return traffic.
So note 51, then forwards the
traffic to note 71 and note 71
when it receives the traffic.
It forwards the traffic
locally to port 71.
Now let's look at the return traffic.
Port 71 responds to the request.
The node 71 forwards
the traffic to note 51.
The IP tables on no 51 first
identifies this traffic as return
traffic of an existing flow, and
it then applies both destination
net and source net to the traffic.
And then North 51 sends the
traffic back to the NLB and NLB
responds back to the client.
Let's now tackle this suboptimal traffic
pattern that I keep repeating from the NLB
to the North 51, which does not have any
local port that is part of that service.
So previously we saw that there could
be traffic tromboning happening between
the NLB, then across nodes and the pod.
In addition, the traffic also gets
source netted to achieve flow symmetry.
So in the cloud, that tromboning actually.
Manifest could manifest itself as a
gross AZ traffic across availability
zone traffic, which could add latency and
also could incur data transfer charges.
So external traffic policy.
Is a Kubernetes feature that can
be configured in the spec section
of the Kubernetes service manifest.
And when it is set to local, basically
the load balancer would send requests
only to the nodes, which have pods that
are part of that Kubernetes service.
So basically, this feature makes sure
that the traffic would be forwarded
to the pods local on those nodes only.
And additionally, the traffic no
longer gets snotted by the note, so the
application can see the actual client ip.
So let's do a packet walk to
better understand this scenario.
Client sends the traffic to the
NLV, and this time the load balancer
performs an additional health
check on a port different than the
node port if the respective node.
Does not have any local pods that are
part of that Kubernetes service, then this
additional health checks fail on the node.
So in our case here, this
means that NLB would never load
balance the traffic to node 51.
And let's assume that NLB load balances
the traffic to North 71 on its north port.
This time IP tables on North 71
load balances the traffic to the
local port, which is port 71, and
it would not pick a remote port.
It just applies destination net.
Lastly, the traffic gets forwarded
to the POD 71, but as you can see
there is still IP tables process.
On Note 71, which basically swaps the
destination IP with the Port 71 ip.
So can we make it even
more efficient than that?
Let's look at that.
That is possible with a feature called
Target ip, or Target type IP feature
of the AWS Elastic Load balancers.
If you deploy.
And use AWS load balancer controller
instead of the service controller, which
comes out of the box with Kubernetes.
Then target type IP
feature is fully supported.
So basically for this feature, you need
AWS load balancer controller in this mode.
The ports that are part of the service
become targets in the target group
of the AWS network load balancer,
and neither the note port nor the
IP tables is used in this scenario.
However, you need to keep in mind the
ELB elastic load balancer service quotas.
'cause if you have, for
instance, a service of 99 500.
Ports, then it could, this could
lead to many targets being part of
the same target group on the A ELB.
I'll provide the ELB service quotas
link at the end of the session.
So let's do a packet walk
and see the difference here.
Client sends traffic to the NLB listener
IP on the listener port ER has the
pos as targets in its target group.
And let's assume that the.
NLB sends the traffic to Port 71
North 71 receives the traffic,
but this time IP tables does not
play any role for this traffic.
'cause the destination IP and the
IP that is already port 71 ip.
So the traffic gets forward to port 71.
it's worth mentioning that in this
session, the assumption is default
settings are used with the load
balance, with the network load balance.
So in this flow, you might
have noticed that the source
IP becomes the NLV ip, however.
If the application needs to track the
client ip, then this can be achieved
by enabling the AWS network, broadband
attribute called Preserve client ip, which
is an other, not notation, annotation,
sorry, in the Kubernetes service manifest.
Having said that, let's move on to
the last topic, which is ingress.
So you may be asking, Wasn't what we just
investigated with North Port or load er.
Also ingress traffic.
the way Kubernetes community, uses
the, ingress in the terminology is
a little bit, slightly different.
Ingress is a different
mechanism than service.
Ingress is to implement layer
seven load balancing and routing
rules, such as host name, URL,
path based routing, definitions.
And as seen in this manifest here,
it enables you to expose your
Kubernetes services through HTTP or
Htt PS route here HT TP requests,
to order service would be forwarded
to the, sorry, the HTTP requests as.
Slash order would be forwarded to the
order service and requests like slash
rating would be forwarded to the rating
service in this ingress manifest.
That's the definition.
So when you apply this manifest.
To the Kubernetes API.
Just like in the previous section,
Kubernetes would expect an external
component to implement a load
balancer, which can process the client
traffic according to the layer seven
routing definitions that you put
in place, that external component.
Is a custom controller provided
by the respective solution.
So I talked about AWS load ER controller,
provisioning an AWS network load balancer.
Previously.
In this context, AWS load ER controller
is also capable of provisioning
an AWS application load balancer
to fulfill the Kubernetes ingress.
Request.
So let's do a quick and simple packet.
Walk with the ingress.
as well,
this will be a scenario where target type
IP is used, as I mentioned previously in
this mode, the pods that are part of the
service become the targets of the AWS
application, nor neither nor port nor
the IP tables is used in this scenario.
Let's do a packet walk
and see how it looks like.
So we do have an ingress manifest applied
on the top left and also a cluster
IP service manifest is also applied.
So client sends the traffic
to the A-L-B-A-L-B decides to
load this traffic to port 71.
A LB always applies SNA to the request.
So the source IP always is the A LB ip.
You cannot pre, you cannot preserve the
client IP through a LV, but you can use
if, capabilities like X forwarder in
the HT TP headers and then the, node
itself would bypass the IP tables.
It does an IP tables does not
perform anything, and the traffic
gets, the packet gets forwarded
to port 71 on the node directly.
Let's examine the return flow
PO 71 response to the traffic.
And then again, IP tables is just,
bypassed the node, sends the traffic
to the application node balancer,
and then the application node
balance sends the traffic back to
the client again with its own ip.
Let's stitch it all together in
the context of AWS completely.
So client sends a DNS request for
an application DNS record, let's
say portal.example.com, and the
domain is hosted on Route 53.
Portal example.com record is
an alias record on Route 53,
and it points out to the A IB.
So Route 53 actually responds with a
multi value where all the public ips
of the A LB would be in the response.
Client picks one of the public ips
in the DNS response and sends the
actual request to the application.
Let's say the client picks
the public IP number three.
In this scenario, internet gateway
would apply destination net.
To the request by swapping the destination
IP of the traffic with the private IP
of the A LB in availability, zone three.
So basically here, the original
destination IP in the client request
was public IP number three, but the
internet gateway swapped that with the
private IP of the A LB rather than the
public IP of the A LB. The private IP
of the A LB would be the destination.
of the traffic and a LB performs a
load balancing decision and decides to
forward the request to one of the pods.
It could be any of the pods in
the, any of the available zones.
It's important to note that by
default, cross zone load balancing
is enabled on a LB. So A LB may
decide to forward this request to
any of the pods in the other AZs.
That's the reason.
But if you'd like to force a LB. To
forward the requests to the availability
zone, local resources, then you can
disable the cross load, cross zone
load balancing feature if you'd like.
So to make it easier for the novice, user
or admin, everything works out of the box
with V-P-C-C-N-I, especially in terms of.
When I say everything,
let me rephrase that.
Everything as in PO generated traffic,
PO initiated, PO generated traffic
would always work in V-P-C-C-N-I.
The reason is out of the box,
V-P-C-C-N-I applies SNET source net
to all the pod initiated traffic,
which is destined to external subnets
or non V-P-C-C-D, CIDRs or siders.
So when put in this slide.
The 1 92 1 1 68, 1 51 ip, the port
sends some traffic destined to a
public IP on the internet VPCC, and
I automatically swaps the source IP
with the nodes primary E and i's.
primary ip, which is DOT 50 in this
scenario, again, it swaps the source IP
of the traffic with the nodes primary,
Ennis primary ip, which is DOT 50.
In this scenario then.
dot 50 source IP gets source netted
again, but this time by IGW to
the, public IP that is, that which
is associated with the DOT 50 ip.
As the public subnets always
mapped the instance IP to a
public ip, so this is the way.
Code initiated.
Traffic automatically always works.
I am sharing additional resources
on this slide, especially when
it comes to cross AZ traffic.
How to?
Localize the traffic within each az, even
when the Kubernetes traffic patterns are,
as, complex as this or as hope by hope.
like this, please have a look at the,
these resources, which I believe it
would help, tremendously help you, and
especially E Ks Best Practices Guide
also goes through some of the scenarios
that I mentioned here with that.
Thank you so much for joining my session
today and I hope you find it useful.
Thanks again and have a great day.