Hi, everyone.
Daniel Moya here.
In this session, we will
talk about Dimensigon.
It's a decentralized automation tool
that enables RESTful API in all your
servers, and it has a command line
interface that is so cool because it
has a tab and you can autocomplete,
you can quickly Distributed commands,
pull software from anywhere to any
other place and create orchestrations
so fast with just few commands.
Dimensicon is our company name, but
it's also the name of this technology.
We also call it DM and this serves very
much when you have two or more, subnets.
Or data centers that are connected through
very specific points, and you want to
manage them as a unique group of servers.
We call that a dimension.
Yes, this we can easily,
do inter server operations.
So we can do operation one in server
one over here, another one over here.
Or also coordinate when some event
is triggering an, an automation that
it helps to execute something on
the other side of, of the network.
Also, we can execute a ADOC
or standalone automations.
And also we can distribute, do
distribute commands that we will
see this functionality further.
About the architecture, we have one
repository in GitHub that it contains
all these three components at the moment.
dmCore is a Python flask,
it enables the RESTful API.
The elevator, it upgrades when there is,
detect, there is, another new version.
Inside the network, then it spreads
the new version to the others.
If of course you configure as such,
DL is a common line interface that
translates all your commands into
restful API to interact with the DM core.
And we have a plan for, adding the web
manager, graphical user interface to build
a metadata that it's in the data in the
distributed database that we implement.
In Docker, we can create the
subnets with this command here.
And after that, we create
our bridge container that is
connected to both subnets.
And later, we can create also our
containers from each subnet that
represents a datacenter or a separated
network that you have in your company.
Coming to SSH, we can
just execute all this.
You will create quickly the five
containers we can connect to our
first to create the dimension.
Let me show you in the
presentation in the dimension.
In Dimensiigon, we create
with Dimensiigon new.
This is like a cluster, as we
say, it is a group of servers.
Usually, our recommendation is
to create one per life cycle.
The production, pre production or
development is the best way you can
do for organization and for security.
Coming back, we can Sect DM zero VASH
minus L to load the environment in here.
It will ask for the root password, but
it's not root from operative system
is root inside the command line.
And you will see that just we
put something for the test.
It will provide us a join token.
This we can use in any other machine.
For example, here we
can go to the other one.
And nsx it dm1 bash l In here
we can do Dimensigon, join.
We have to see from the
first, this first subnet.
We copy paste and the token.
In here, of course,
it's not yet listening.
So we have to do no hub,
Dimensiigon in background.
There you go.
Then we can just join the
Dimensiigon, the Dimension.
Once we join, I will repeat this
operation to the other servers.
When I am done, we will continue.
As you will receive this message of join
the dimension, the other joins you can
execute, of course, from the other nodes.
But in this case, as we have
one node as a bridge, I will
execute them all from the DM0.
For this training, we recommend
using Docker and we can simulate two.
Networks with one server in
the middle that will act as a
bridge is very easy with docker.
We can imagine this network, for
example, as one cloud provider
or one data center on this one.
It can be.
I can represent another data center.
On prem, cloud, it doesn't matter as
long as you understand that these servers
didn't have a communication with these
servers and the communication goes through
DM for our automations and everything
we can create it as, two networks in
Docker and then create our machines.
this, this image is a
very publicly available.
You can pull it at any
time for each new server.
You have to secure them and see gone.
Token.
There are three ways of executing this.
Another one is through RESTful
and from the command line.
Or, and this one as
well, from the DM core.
It generates a token for a new server.
The token can be used only once.
So we have to generate one token for
each new server from any other server
that is already part of this group.
Adding the last one.
We have to copy our token as before.
We are using the second subnet.
And then it's playing about.
The decentralization and
distributed management.
When we are adding each of these
servers, we can administrate from
any of them, any other or all the
others, all of them as a group.
This is called a dimension dimension.
This cluster, then it's already with
some logics to handle the split brain
in case there is a network instability.
And also it has mechanism to
keep the metadata consistent
between the surviving group.
This is all a distributed database
built on top of SQL Alchemy.
Coming back to our command line, we
have now all the servers up and running.
You can see here that there is a. That
D shell where it contains at the moment
just the username and server default
to connect because you can Download
the software and connect to another
server Where is running the mensegon
and not exactly to the local host.
You can do that.
In this case, we just, Dcl, we are not
yet connected, but we can do login safe.
Then when we input our password, you can
see here that our token will be safe.
And next time we can
directly execute by tap.
We can execute any of this command.
We are already log in.
First of all, we will do the status.
You see with the tab, it auto completes.
For example, I use this.
And we have, this is the
version of the catalog.
This is the metadata of the database.
And the server is in here.
Yes.
We can continuously add the others by tab.
And the important thing is to see
the catalog and to control that the
catalog should be in the same version.
If not, We have something to
execute, the manager catalog refresh.
This will detect if there is a new
catalog in the network and it will
pull the catalog to our location.
You have to execute this manager catalog
refresh from another server where it's
in a minor version or an older version.
Then it will retrieve the latest
catalog from any of the networks.
Additionally, it has a mechanism
to auto update the catalog when
it has found a new version.
You will find this into the nohub or
the loch from the dimensicon process.
Coming back to the presentation, once
you have two or more nodes, it's more
interesting because you can have Some
commands that make sense when you have not
only one server, but more to administrate.
DCL was the, was developed on top of
Promptoolkit with other components that
you may see in the repository or the PYPI.
And we will go through all the
different commands that we have here.
But first of all, I want to
Explain more about our units.
The hierarchy that we have is one,
orchestration is one automation.
We can create the steps inside and step.
We have to define actions to have some
sort of reusability so we can reuse these
actions into many other orchestration.
We can also reuse orchestration as
one step into another orchestration.
Also, we have a step and do the step
and do we have to define in which
condition we consider than the that the
orchestration is failing and then it
will execute the step and do also in
the order that we wish to, to execute.
We have a repository that we call
orchestration library in there.
We wish that everyone can share their
JSON that, it can they can easily be
imported into the command line interface.
And once you import the JSON,
you can navigate through the
command line interface through
the steps and modify them.
If you modify an orchestration, there is
a versioning mechanism that it will create
a new version of the orchestration instead
of overwriting the current version.
This is made for consistency.
between your automations.
So you know that there is
some immutability to the
version that you were using.
And in case someone creates
a modification, it's a new
version inside the catalog.
As explained before, there is a catalog
that it's spreading over your network of
servers that you manage with Dimensiigon.
These Is when you create something,
new that can action, orchestration,
lock federation and software
that are added to the library,
any of these operations will it.
Higher the watermark of the catalog and
with the time it will be distributed.
If there is a need for immediate
distribution due to an orchestration
execution or so, then it
will come in the background.
Let's jump into our first demo.
We will create the typical
hello world of this.
Very simple, just with the,
A command line interface.
This is a summary of
what you have to type.
Let's go into the SSH to
test it with the D Shell.
At D Shell, first of all, we have to
create the action that we will use to
populate one step into the orchestration.
Then we have to just type action create.
You see, I can tap and also I can
use the minus H in any sub option.
Then we can do action create.
We need a name that it can be a hello
world to make it the same as example
and then type shell some comment here
we can shell python ansible then we can
easily integrate with any playbook in
ansible and there are some special call
request and also we have some other
internals that I will show you later.
then as, as such, we will start then
in any, in any command, we can just
type minus H. We will see our options.
We can preview what we are doing.
Instead, there is an interesting minus
H because you can see All the parameters
here that you can modify, apart from the
name, the version, the type we can, we can
modify and go to all the other type that
from what we have initially, configured
the expected is standard out or also
the expected, the expected return code
and some other more complex parameters.
Topics that we won't
discuss in a hello world.
Then from here, we can
just simple set code.
The easy here we will do in
vi echo and then hello from
we can directly use variables.
We have also a vault.
Okay, let me put an exclamation.
Then like this, we can just save it.
Then in here, we can preview
and also we can submit.
Submit will create a new
item in the repository.
Then it will make the catalog to
higher the watermark a bit more.
When we submit.
We got some ID.
Pay attention to this 880.
Then, for example, if we
do action list and by name.
We will see that we have
some other internal actions
that we will explain later.
But our hello world is there.
Then we can, of course, list
and see the contents of this.
Of course, you can action and
then load from a JSON in here.
It will be a file with the absolute.
path and you can upload actions
defined by any other colleague or so.
Then when we have our action already we
can go into org then we see our options
we can list we may not have anything at
the moment but we are about to create
it a hello world also with the same name
has no problem with the it's a different
type of entity then When we have a, oh
yes, I did a list, hello world, there
is no list, hello world, we have to do
a create, hello world, then over here
there is nothing more that we need to
modify or create, name, hello world,
Then in here is a bit more options.
We have also the step option in this step.
We have to start with
the step and do or undo.
We can define in any order
they undo first or whatever.
We will define the order also
later in case we need an undo.
But then let's do our first
step do to move forward.
We see a one on the command line.
Then when we have this, we can select.
Action, look, I will copy paste, select
minus eight, set action template ID,
then when we are here, I can just tap
and we see our ID with the translation
of the name we, we gave in the
action definition is a version one.
When we select this, we
can just also preview.
We see our, our guy there and submit.
With it, oh yes, of course,
save first, then submit.
With this operation we create
our first orchestration.
Then we can org list by name, hello world.
We have this orchestration.
Also we have the detail that
it provides in the steps.
Our action that we define
type shell and what it does.
Yes.
Okay.
So in this regard, when we need to
create more, we can do it or copy.
You will create the version
two when we need to load from
a JSON file, we will do a load.
Yes.
And that's it.
And also when we do a copy and
a tab with the orchestration.
Yes.
Then we can, we have
one option called dump.
If we do the dump, we can do dump h,
dump, hello world, hello json, yes.
And then we can exit and exit over
here and you will see, hello world.
This will be our definition that we can do
the orchestration load and load this file.
But we haven't had to
create the JSON in the past.
So we generate JSON, but from command
line is like we navigate them easy.
Then we enter into this shell and
now we can simply do the same.
Orc run the options here.
There are some options to put
parameters and some options for the
vault where we have the secrets.
Of course, we have the scope that you
can create secrets that are usable only
in production or in other environments
in case you have similar, same, other
environments in the same dimension.
At least this way you can, select.
Secrets from different, dictionaries.
Yes.
Then in this case, we just run.
We will put our orchestration
and we have the target.
We can put Exactly as such one, two nodes
or three nodes, for example, these three
nodes and then with the enter we will just
hit and it will run in these three servers
you see here important is that
you quickly see the server
and success equal true, okay?
Then we see from it is like this.
apart from it, I will show you another
way of just executing that very simple
statements at once in all the servers
you wish from our presentation.
I record then an output for your review.
You see the output is, also there are
interesting stuff for the return, code
and the parameters that were passed
and some elapse time of how it was
executed, on the runtime or at the end.
You have some sort of summary
of success through for the
automation that, orchestration.
Okay.
And the, on all the target
that has been a success.
Is it similar to Ansible?
We come back to the next
topic is distributed commands.
You can do a command shell that is enabled
this shell with the delta and then select
the target of what servers it will have
to complete with the tab and any upcoming
command will execute in all the servers.
Let's try it.
Here in the shell, to execute our
distributed command, we are tab, we
do in tab all the time to use the
help in any command or sub command,
you will get a very nice help.
And then in command, we use shell.
And we put the target.
Now we are using the tab,
abusing on the tab all the time.
Then we will just use two servers
for having a very short, output.
Then when we are here, it's as easy
as tabbing, as using any command.
Yes, we can use this command
and query everywhere.
Or to double check that our
Systems are ready for the upcoming
automation that we will run.
Some sort of preparation.
It helps very much for it or
troubleshooting in many servers.
This, it was useful first time with some
distributed shell in Exadata, one of the
ones that has some experience with Oracle.
And from that idea, that is also a Python,
we came into these distributed commands.
Coming back to the presentation, the
next topic could be the software library.
The software library, we can add a
software in any host in our network
and use it in any other place.
It will pull the software or one off
or on demand from a orchestration.
As you can check with the help,
you can do a software add or
list or also software send.
We will try here in another demo that
we will send a software that we will
put, in the DM four that is isolated
by DM one and the software will be sent
to the DM one through proxy in DM zero.
We can do a quick demo and do a
one-off transfer from server DM
four to server DM one as we don't
have the software in DM four.
Let's place it first and
DM four.
It's this one, then we can copy
software like this to dm4 with
our alias for the machine 200
megabytes, then we have to still
modify the ownership of the file this
we can do a quick one off
demo of how to transfer.
Let's of course put the software first
into dm4 and then transfer it to dm1.
In docker, we have to first do the copy
software installer to dm4 and then later
we just need here the container to change
the ownership of the file when we have
this we can quickly connect for the
registration to this to the node that
it has our software dm4 bash minus l
then when we have our software correct
permissions You can go in this shell.
Let me check it out.
If we have already, we
don't have the token.
So to do a low auto login, it's
very comfortable, the login safe.
Then we have the token and we
can do the software at instead of
going directly, I would do minus
age to show you the help software.
We don't have any, you know, in the list.
So we do the add the family test.
It can be the name dummy
software version 1.
0 and file the absolute the
absolute path just like that.
And we add the software.
The, the dictionary or catalog
in this note will rise.
Its high watermark.
Yes.
This, we can see actually in here we
are in the 65, have to be a bit quick.
Also, it can.
Yeah, we see this one is like
23rd February at 712 and on
the other note we have another
dictionary is not yet up to date.
Anyway, we can see the software.
List, for example, if I
either ID or name, we will see
something nice, dummy software.
Then we see that our dummy
software, it has this size in
bytes and it has a checksum and we
can use the software by this ID.
as you can see, there is a for
orchestration and another moment
we will explain, the list by name
and we have these orchestrations.
The one of sent software.
We can execute a known in any other
orchestration is a native type in.
The schema, the schema would be the
YAML that you have to buy, build
with the following, parameters.
But the required ones are just a software
and in the server that it will come, yes?
And more or less, it executes
this part internally.
then with the software, we can go
in software, send, it's a one off.
Then in here, we have our software.
Before that.
Minus age.
We have first the destination path.
let's use temp.
The software ID is this one.
It will translate, which is very easy.
And then the destination server.
We have it in the server DM four
that if you remember is the DM. 65
ending with the containers is a bit
not that easy as in your company
with some meaningful server names.
But here with the containers, we
have also this automated names.
And then another that is not
the 65, for example, in this one
before we transfer it, we can go.
Also to that server.
Actually, we were in that C40.
So in the C40, we will see that they have,
no, their software is not there in TMP.
So when we do this, and we have no
other, we can still put the foreground,
so it will wait, and this command will
wait until the software is successfully
transferred, and also the forward that it
will overwrite it if it's already there.
Then, let's go like this.
This, it's happened because, the,
the software is not existing.
In destination, which means we just have
to, manage the catalog at destination
is sometimes we have to do this.
We can go to destination and let's
see here in this in this software,
you will see that there is nothing
list, nothing, but we can do manager.
Catalog refresh.
This should pull the
catalog from the other node.
No catalog found.
Then we have now we are software list.
Now we have it.
So as we have pulled the new
version, we can retry this
And now we have a transfer ID.
That was so fast.
I'm repeating the test.
So when you have a software sent,
we click it, we have our transfer
ID, go to transfer list ID.
And then with this ID,
we have no info in here.
Let me see from here.
We come here, transfer list.
Last one is in progress.
Let's check it out what we have there
because we have the same 101 chunks.
it's, in here, in temp,
we have all these chunks.
They are being transferred one by one.
Then they are, being, joined.
And when they are joined, it forms
the final binary file You see?
I have less now and now is
finally the file is mounted back.
This, what has happened is very
interesting to understand the
possibilities of this technology
with the software when you
use it one off, of course.
It's just a matter of some comfort, but
if you, if we use it with automation,
it can be something like, one step
we pull the software to whatever,
whatever number of, distant servers
that we wish, install it and do a post
installation steps into other actions.
Yes, what has happened in here is that
we have transferred a software that is
in one location that is not directly
communicated with another location.
Yes, this is interesting for many
companies that they have some software
in another part of the company and
it's sometimes difficult to mount
an NFS from one place into another.
So this way with the proxy, we can
just skip all the network difficulties
and just pass the software from
one place to another on the fly
via an orchestration as well.
Before we try more complex
orchestrations, let me do a quick
catch up over all the commands we have.
Action, we already said that is a part of
a step that is inside an orchestration.
Command is a distributed command.
Environment, we can list the environment.
We can also set or set or get variables.
This can also be used by inside
the orchestrations as well.
But for secrets, we have the vaults
that we will come in another moment.
Exec is executions.
We can list executions.
In this case, we had in
the past the hello world.
For in in the past we execute
that was a sex success and it
was a cute in that servers here.
Okay.
see control C control L. Then we continue
here exit nothing luck Federation.
We will come to this topic of subscribing
to a law or to a directory that it will.
Replicate its content of the log
from many directories everywhere,
to one other or other locations.
log, this is just to the login inside
the application that we can modify here.
inside login we have still the
save or to login only once.
or to another username also we can
create, but this is a more advanced topic.
I will create some users.
then in the manager we have a two minutes.
The catalog refresh.
To manage the locking mechanism,
we can ignore one server, mark and
unignore to include it back into
the, clustering, locking mechanism.
Yes.
Also, we can show.
How is the status?
For example, we can show a status of
this is unlocked for catalog operations
for upgrade or for orchestration
executions when there is one that we
decide to lock to and don't enable
concurrency for because we we have
very critical orchestration running.
We can just see it here.
Also, we have the orchestrate
orchestrations where we list or
create, or we copy or we load
from Jason or we just run it.
interesting at the
moment now just to list.
I see that we have the hello world only.
The other ones are the internal
actions that we saw in the past.
How are the actions?
We see in the list by name, I want
to explain the Ascent software.
It executes, insert an orchestration.
This would be like, we in one step, we
define one action as Ascent software.
And then in that one, we will have
to pass the parameters of in the
destination and in which server.
Destination directory where
it would be sending software.
Wait servers is where you want an
orchestration to stop in the middle
of another server, provisioning until
the server is added to DimensiGone.
Orchestration, you want to wait,
you want, no, you want to create
an orchestration inside an
action, then this you can specify.
Wait route to server.
When you add a server, it has to be
an existing route to reach the server.
It's a second level of adding a server
when it's inside the catalog already.
delete servers, you can wait until
a server is no longer part of
the dimension, of the dimension.
Then it means that you can
continue because something
was executing there, whatever.
And our, our action there, that we have
used in the same name orchestration.
Then cancel here, and after
this we have the pin command.
We can ping any number of nodes here to
understand if they are up and running
with Dimensiigon, not the server itself.
In servers there are
some interesting stuff.
We can list the servers.
We can delete the server from the
dimension, the dimension, and we
can see its roots is interesting.
We are right now in the DM0.
So we can see the roots.
Yeah, they are not that much
interesting because this one
can reach all the servers.
Cost is the number of jumps that it has.
And this we see that is our server.
So, but let's go to the server.
We see the routes from here.
Also, the, this one, yes, this one
is isolated in, is like in one corner
from one of the two networks that we
have one network, another network.
Then if we list the routes, we
will see that in this case, we
have two servers that they are
accessible through a proxy server.
That is our server that we are,
we were connected right now.
And another.
Two servers that it can connect
directly is, of course, one is the proxy
server and another one is the network
that we have in the same network.
This is interesting in the
servers and still on the list.
We saw that we can have some details.
So by name, let's say if I
put some details, yeah, we
can see what is the gates.
So for each IP, it's, listening for
each IP on the server to upcoming,
yeah, upcoming connections.
This is interesting also.
Then let's clean again.
About software.
We can see from the software
library what we have there.
Yeah, like for my ideas.
We have just one.
You want when it taps with with one it
out of resolution resolution to just
one and I. D. In this case, if we have
more, we will see, tabular, options.
Yeah, that we have in the status.
We are used at the
beginning of this tutorial.
yeah, we can query.
The status of other.
Also, we can include the detail,
just if we query two, you
will see that just querying.
We see the catalog that is in sync
with the others, and we see that,
the other notes are registered
as alive, not in coma in coma.
It can be when also they are
like you stop the domestic on
service and also the neighbors.
And we have, in this case, these two
networks, the ID and the server name,
and the other one, it has another
network here, and this one is kind of
interesting to see when it was executed.
And also, the version that
is running of the software.
This is also managed by the elevator.
Apart from it, we have
the sync that in that one.
To be honest, this one,
I, I don't, I don't know.
I don't remember for this.
What is this for?
Because, I would have to, double
check with the documentation.
The sync, the transfer we
already saw is the transfer list.
In this case, we have two completed one.
It was too fast.
I was not able to show you
just the chunks that are being
transferred on the other one.
We saw it on how it was completed and
also apart from the time transfer.
I like I like very much the vault
and by double purely braces inside
the code of a python or in in
shell, we can specify secrets.
Thanks.
And these secrets are accessible
by the dictionary vault
dot and the variable name.
Then, of course, here we don't have,
but we can define a scope of to list.
And in this regard, it's just that simple.
No, wait a moment.
I have a vault list.
Nothing.
Of course, we have a vault, right?
Minus eight, then we can just say,
okay, right, let's go broad and
variable name can be, so my username
from a database and the password.
Yes, and as you see here, the
global is the default scope.
It's already connecting
with the other nodes.
And spreading the word about this secret.
Actually, if we see now from this node
to another, we see now a new version.
And with the time, in a matter
of 5 minutes, it will spread the
catalog to the other machines.
We see in the vault, list.
And well, in the case we
don't indicate the scope,
we have nothing listed because for
security we have configured this
way, but if we include the scope, we
see the script directly with this.
With the value as well, so that
it can be changed, it can be
changed with the configuration.
That's all, that's, so far the main
commands that we can use around.
Of course, around the orchestration,
there are many options with the command
line in how to define and how to,
the copy, something that we will use.
To, generate the version two of the
our hello world and continue with the
tutorial, but to keep it short this
time is better than we just refresh some
of the concepts that we explained so
we can come with a So, Nice idea about
what we have instead of complicating
more with some more examples.
Remember that the
orchestration is made of steps.
We define the actions beforehand.
We can, we have shown only the action
shell, but also there is an ansible.
Playbooks you can integrate.
Python directly and another
orchestration made of whatever,
steps or also the internal method.
As we saw, the software sent are
wait for servers, this kind of
things, and yeah, require also some,
testing from your site if you wish.
there are some complex logics that can
be, execute as a parallel processes.
If you have one or more
steps depending on one.
It means it can be executed in parallel
and also it works as well for the undo.
So if you have, one number one,
if it fails, it will execute step
seven, as undo number two, number 10.
Will be executed in parallel
if number one is successful.
Number two, if it fails, it will
execute the number 11 as undo.
And number three, it has a more
complex undo as it can also
execute first undo number four.
Then if successful number four, it
will execute number five and six on.
As you can see, number five goes off.
It has also number eight.
And after that, number nine, this
This kind of situation that can
be easily defined with the command
line as well as we mentioned.
This is a polyglot, technology.
So when you combine steps using
a different language or even,
Interfaces from different technologies
like a chef or a terraform from
another machine, et cetera.
So you can combine a polyglot and have
something very easy and fast defined.
Thanks for joining this
presentation of the mensegon.
if you have any questions,
please feel free to contact me.
I am, I have the LinkedIn
link in my profile in conf42.
Thanks and goodbye.