Hi, everyone.
My name is Ravi Chandra,
principal salesforce developer
and architect at Temple V capital.
Today.
I am thrilled to share how I have
transformed the borrower experience by
building a seamless and responsive loan
application portal on experience cloud
that is built on lightning platform.
This initiative wasn't just
about modernizing our technology.
It was about creating an
intuitive, efficient and accessible
experience for our borrowers.
In this session, we will explore the
key challenges, technical innovations,
and measurable improvements that
made this transformation possible.
Coming to the challenges,
desktop only limitation.
Before our transformation, we faced
significant challenges with our legacy
desktop only loan application system.
Accessibility was a major issue.
40 percent of our borrowers
could not complete loan
applications on mobile devices.
User frustration was another pain point.
A frequent timeout and compatibility
issues led to 65 percent increase
in support tickets with users
spending an additional 2.
5 hours to complete the loan application.
Lastly, we struggled with high
drop rates, 58 percent of user
abandonment applications midway,
often during complex form submissions.
These challenges were made it
clear that we need modern and
mobile friendly solutions.
Coming to Responsive Design Access
Anywhere, our solution was a fully
responsive borrower portal accessible
on mobile, both on iOS and Android OS.
Tablets and desktop.
For mobile users, we introduced
a touch optimized interface
for on the go loan application.
Tablet users benefited from an
intuitive experience, ideal for
reviewing and filling out applications.
Desktop users retained access to advanced
tools for detailed loan application
reviews and document management.
This multi device approach ensured a
seamless experience, allowing borrowers
to interact with their clients.
The portal anytime, anywhere coming
to the key portal functionalities
to create an efficient and user
friendly loan application portal.
We introduced four major functionalities.
Firstly, real time document uploads
allow users to secure submit.
Securely submit and track
their documents with automatic
validation, ensuring completeness.
Secondly, e signature integration
streamlined the process, reducing
paperwork and cutting closing time by 80%.
Thirdly, personalized dashboards
provided borrowers with a clear,
customized view of their loan status.
And upcoming tasks.
Finally, the in app messaging
enabled direct secure communication
with loan officers, reducing the
need of email and phone calls.
These features significantly
improved the borrower experience.
Coming to faster loan processing
time, one of the most significant
improvements was reducing loan processing
time for our underwriting team.
With automations and process
enhancements, we achieved a
30 percent process speed gain.
Previously, application took an
average of 25 minutes to complete.
Now the new portal borrowers can
finish the process in just 15 minutes.
Not only this improvement, not
only enhances efficiency, but also
improves borrower satisfaction by
eliminating unnecessary delays.
Coming to the technical improvements
to make this transformation possible.
We focused on three key
technical improvements.
Firstly, we eliminated 98, 95
percent of our system errors through
advanced error handling and automated
testing led to non zero downtime.
Secondly, we adopted mobile first
design, which increased mobile
application completion rate by 60%.
Finally, we redesigned the interface.
With a user centric approach, reducing
average application time from 45 minutes
to just 15 minutes, while maintaining
a 98 percent user satisfaction rate.
Eco friendly digital solutions.
Beyond improving efficiency,
our digital transformation also
contributed to sustainability.
We eliminated over 100, 000
pages of paper annually through
digital document processing.
By automating manual workflows,
we reduced processing time by 75
percent while conserving resources.
Additionally, our shift to paperless
operations and energy efficient systems
decreased our carbon footprints by 40%.
These changes align our commitment
to environmental responsibility
and operational efficiency.
Reduced support calls.
Our new loan application
portal dramatically improved
customer service efficiency.
Support calls related to
technical issues dropped by 40%.
Thanks to our self service feature
and an intuitive interface.
With fewer borrowers needing
assistance, our support team could
focus on more complex customer needs.
This in turn led to a 35 percent boost
in customer satisfaction score, showing
that the improved user experience
directly contributed to happy borrowers.
Coming to user expectations,
throughout this transformation,
we learned several key lessons.
First, gathering user
feedback was crucial.
Regular surveys and interviews
revealed that 78 percent of users
prioritized mobile accessibility.
Secondly, iterative design was essential.
We made five major UI improvements
based on borrower's feedback.
Finally, thorough testing ensured success.
We tested the loan application
portal with over 5, 000 users
across multiple devices, resulting
in a 92 percent satisfaction rate.
These lessons helped us build in
a platform that not only meets.
but exceeds borrower's expectation.
Leveraging analytics to continuously
optimize the borrower experience.
We leveraged Einstein analytics
in Salesforce in three key areas.
Firstly, we tracked user behavior to
analyze completion pattern and navigation
flows, improving the application process.
Secondly, we identified and addressed.
Drop off points, reducing
the abandonment rates by 45%.
Finally, we monitored performance
metrics like load times and response
rates to ensure a seamless experience.
This data driven approach allows
us to refine and enhance the.
Portal continuously coming to mobile
first approach our loan application.
Our loan application portal
followed follows a structural
mobile first development cycle.
We started by designing with
mobile users in mind, ensuring
an optimal experience for the 76
percent of borrowers who access.
Our services via mobile devices.
Next, we rigorously test the platform
across multiple different devices to
maintain functionality and usability.
Finally, we continuously optimize
based on real time user data,
improving performances, load
times, and touch interactions.
This approach guarantees a seamless
experience across all mobile devices.
Coming to key takeaways.
In summary, our responsive design
transformation has resulted in 92 percent
user satisfaction rate across all devices.
Our mobile first approach now effectively
served 76 percent of borrowers.
Data driven analytics helped us
reduce abundant rates by 45 percent
while our paperless initiative
cut processing time by 60%.
While continuously user feedback and
testing from 500 plus borrowers, we
have successfully built a platform
that puts borrower experience first.
These results showcase the power of
innovation in financial services.
Lastly, I wanted to thank
you all for your time today.
I hope this presentation provided
valuable insights into how a responsive
and user centric approach can
transform the borrower experience.
If you have any questions,
I'll be happy to answer.
Let's continue the conversation and
work together to drive innovation
in cloud native financial services.
Thank you.