Hello everyone.
My name is Gary Wan, and I have over
a decade of experience in backend
development and database management.
Throughout my career, I have
worked with companies like Journal
Electronics, TCS, Wipro, Nike, NMI.
Presently, I'm working with Bank of
America as an application programmer,
we focusing on building scalable
and high performance backend system.
Today I will be talking about
optimizing backend API performance
user demands fast response from APIs.
A slow API can lead to poor user
experience, reduce retention, and
a negative impact on your brand.
Today we are going to explore
the best practices for improving
API speed and efficiency.
I will be talking about caching
connection, pooling pagination, payload
compression, and asynchronous processing.
By the end of this session, you
will have a clear understanding
of how to optimize APIs for better
scalability and responsiveness.
Our agenda will be, I will be talking
about why API performance matter.
What are the common a p
performance bottlenecks?
Then the five techniques, which
I mentioned in the introduction.
And lastly, what are the key
takeaways from this session?
A P performance is very crucial in
any application for several reasons.
User experience fast.
API provides a smooth and
responsive user experience.
Slow.
API can lead to frustration and a negative
perception of the application Scalability.
performing APIs can handle more requests
concurrently, allowing the application
to scale efficiently under heavy load.
Poorly performing API
can become bottleneck.
Limiting the application's ability to
handle increased traffic, reliability,
performance issue can sometimes
indicate underlying problems in the
application, such as inefficient code,
database bottleneck, or a source leak.
Addressing performance concern can
improve the overall stability and
reliability of the application.
Resource utilization efficient
APIs consume fewer resources like
CPU Memory network per request,
reducing infrastructure cost, and
improving overall system efficiency.
Business impact in many cases,
API performance directly
impact business metrics.
For example, faster API can lead to
higher conversion rate, increased sales,
and improved customer satisfaction.
What are the common API
performance bottleneck.
Now let's examine some common
bottlenecks that affect API performance.
Database queries are the
operations that retrieve or
modify data from your database.
They are often the most time
consuming part of your API Logic.
Poorly designed or executed database
queries can result in slow or inaccurate
data delivery, high resource consumption
and security vulnerabilities to
optimize your database queries You.
You can use indexes, join filters,
pagination, and caching high latency,
which is caused by synchronous logging
and processing, which means log
events are recorded and processed in
a coordinated manner, which ensures
that the logging operation is computed
before any further processing occur.
Effectively creating a wait and see
approach where the system pauses until
the log is fully returned before moving
onto the next step, preventing potential
data inconsistencies or misinformation.
Large compressed payloads leading to slow
data transmission, excessive database
connection, causing resource contention.
It means significant amount of time was
being spent in creating and closing a
database connection, redundant client
request, increasing server load.
It means a situation where a client
sends the same API requests multiple
times, unnecessarily overloading the
server with identical data, which often.
Cause issues like poor client
side logic, network glitch or user
interaction that trigger repeated
requests for the same information.
Lack of caching resulting in repeated
database hit means that the API does
not store previously retrieved data
temporarily resulting in each request
needing to be processed from scratch by
the server, leading to slower response
time, increased server load, and a less
efficient user experience, especially
when leading with frequently access data.
Now that we have identified the
key performance issue, let's go
over the solutions pagination.
When dealing with large data sets,
fetching all records at words
can lead to slow API response
and high memory consumption.
Pagination helps by retrieving
data in smaller chunks, improving
performance and user experience.
I will be talking about
three techniques here.
Offset based pagination, cursor based
pagination, and page-based pagination.
Offset and limit pagination.
These techniques involve using
two parameters, offset and limit.
The offset parameter determines the
starting point or the position in the
data set while the limit parameter
specifies the maximum number of
records to include on each page.
Cursor based pagination.
Instead of relying on numeric
offset, cursor based pagination
uses a unique identifier or token
to mark the position in the dataset.
The API consumer includes the
cursor value in subsequent request
to fetch the next page of data.
Page-based pagination.
In this technique, it involves
a page parameter to specify
the desired page number.
The API consumer requests a specific
page of data and the API response with
the corresponding page along with the
metadata, such as the total number
of pages or total records count.
Using Spring Boot built in pagination
support ensures that only a subset
of data is fetched per request.
Reducing server code.
Server load.
I have attached a small code snippet
from the spring boot where you can
use, where you can see that I have used
a GA mapping and a page able is sent
as a request and page as a response.
Asynchronous logging.
Synchronous logging can slow down APIs
because each log entry requires input
output operation performed on disk.
By switching to asynchronous
logging, we can reduce blocking
and improve response time.
Asynchronous logging in Java involved
decoupling the logging operation
from the main application thread.
Which prevents performance bottleneck
caused by input output operation.
This approach enhances application
responsiveness spatially under
heavy load libraries like Log back,
log four J needs to offer built-in
support for asynchronous logging to
configure asynchronous logging in.
Log back use Async append tag in
your log back XML configuration file.
This allow logs to be temporally stored in
memory and return to disc asynchronously,
which improves a API efficiency.
caching in Java involves
storing frequently access data
in temporary storage location.
You can call it as a cache to enable
faster retrieval in subsequent request,
thus improving application performance.
The cache act as an intermediate
layer between the application
and the original data source.
For example, database or external service.
You can see I have attached a
small snippet where you can see
an annotation cacheable is used.
It is a Java annotation, which
is used in spring framework to
enable caching for method results.
When a method is annotated with add
cacheable, spring intercepts a method.
Call and check if the result for the
given argument is already cached.
If it is, the cache result is return
and the method is not executed.
Otherwise, the method is executed.
The result is cache, and then return.
Caching helps in reducing the
load on the database and improves
API response time significantly.
Payload compression, large
responses can slow down APIs.
By compressing payload using
techniques like Z zipp broadly,
we can reduce the amount of data
transmitted over the network.
Z Zipp, it's a widely used compression
algorithm that is efficient
for text-based data, broadly.
Generally provide higher compression
rate shows compressed to Zzi, but
may have slower compression speeds.
Few consideration.
CPU usage, compression and decompression
can be CPU Intensive operation.
It is important to balance
compression levels with performance
requirement network overhead, while
compression, it reduces payload size.
The overhead of compression and
decompression should be considered,
especially for smaller payloads.
The compatibility, which ensures that
both the client and server support
the same compression algorithm
error handling, implement proper
error handling for compression and
decompression failure security.
If the payload contains sensitive
information, consider using encryption
in addition to compression a small.
Configuration has been attached,
which is being used in Spring Boot.
This configuration enables response
compression, reduced bandwidth
usage, and improving API performance.
Connection, pooling connection.
Pooling in Java is a technique
used to manage and reuse database
connection, improving the performance
and efficiency of the application
that interact with the database.
Instead of creating a new connection every
time data access is needed, a pool of
connection is established and maintained.
When a connection is required, it
is borrowed from the pool used and
then returned to the pool for reuse,
minimizing the overhead of repeatedly
creating and closing connection.
The benefits of connection
pooling are improved Performance.
reduce overhead of creating and closing
connection resource management, which
means efficiently managed database
connection, preventing resource
exertion and scalability, which enables
application to handle a large number of
concurrent requests, the best practices.
We can use ARI CP for optimal
performance, or we can use tune pool
size based on the traffic pattern.
hi.
Config has been attached here.
Connection, pooling, minimize
overhead, ensuring the database
queries execute faster and efficiently.
Lastly, the key takeaways
from this session.
Monitor and profile API.
Using tools like Pros and Grafana,
implement caching and payload compression
for faster response, optimize database
queries and use connection pooling
to enhance performance leverage,
asynchronous processing for logging and.
Test and scale APIs
proactively to handle P loads.
Adopt API gateway and rate
limiting to manage high traffic.
By following these practices, you can
build high performance APIs that scale
efficiently in a cloud native environment.
Thank you so much.
Thank you all for attending this session
on optimizing backend a P performance.
I hope you found it insightful.
You can also connect me on LinkedIn.
I. Thank you.