Hi everyone.
I'm Vishal Mahala, a security
architect with more than 10 years of
expertise in building, designing and
implementing resilient architectures.
That's not just detecting threats,
but with the proactive approach,
leveraging AI and automations,
building security applications.
That is with shift left focus
and something that is very
simple to understand and easy.
For small scale business owners to adopt
into their day-to-day business operations.
Today I'm here to introduce my product
idea security in your pocket, a mobile
first AI driven risk assessment tool
for small scale industries primarily.
Let me ask you this question.
What would a typical digital
footprint of a small scale
business owner would look like?
Even if this question is for a
typical business owner, they might
not be able to capture all the
digital endpoints, plugins, payment
processors, everything under one foot.
They're no longer working with a fiscal
store or a basic web application.
Their ecosystem is completely
distributed Cloud native,
though they don't realize it.
Here's where the actual problem lies.
Enterprise tools are so sophisticated
and always are built with the primary
focus of big tech forms with lots of
dedicated security teams designed for
their own selves and consumer tools.
On the other hand, is.
Good enough for a personal
security, but a small scale
doesn't fit into a consumer tool.
The risk is not limited, but they
could not even adopt for a fully
grown enterprise tool with the
limited resources be to monetary to
no awareness about what a typical
security vulnerability would look like.
What could it impact their to
their business and not sure
about how to fix that even.
We are here today to discuss the shift in
focus and also how this tool approaches
security from business owner's perspective
when we have limited resources.
Security in a pocket in your pocket
is as simple as having a soc analyst,
a threat advisor, and a security
consultant right in your pocket.
Whether you are a
developer, a business owner.
Or a leader who would like to look at
your threat landscape from a thousand foot
level, this tool best fits your needs.
Enterprise tools have complex
ownership models, dev Ecop pipelines
and dedicated security teams.
They're far two complex to adopt
them for a five business person
who is handling the multiple roles
such as a marketer influencer.
Accountant, whatnot.
The four systemic gaps is where
this tool will primarily try
to address to the very least.
As a business owner, I would like to
have a complete picture of why what
my attack surface would look like.
What are all the forgotten APIs?
The shadow ai, that
lot of charge GBTs and.
Perpetuity like tools introduce
unmonitored cloud buckets and the
invisible exposure that you don't know
exist, you could not save it, secure it.
So this tool aims at providing
a unified console where all
the cloud assert visibility as
provider for any business owner.
Secondly, in small businesses, there is no
single point of ownership that takes the
responsibility between a business owner,
a web developer, or a security engineer.
So we would focus at translating
the vulnerabilities into a very
simple language, jargon free, free
from CV and CVSs scores, and leaning
on to a language as simple as.
Why is this risk important to me?
We are also targeting to have focus
areas about integrations where
a lot of third party risks and
multimodal agent communication.
Identity propagations and
plugin integrations are have
always overlooked to the last.
We would like to translate the
misaligned security solutions into
their actual actionable insights
in their day-to-day operations.
We are approaching this
tool in a multi-layer.
Operationalization where
we would initially look at
the asset discovery phase.
Like I said, you cannot
protect what you cannot see.
So this first layer of framework will
focus on automatically detecting your
endpoints, your Shopify stores web pages,
and ensuring the business owners have
continual discovery of their research.
Attack vectors and how the platform
changes day by day with the new addition
of endpoints and new integrations.
This will include websites, APIs,
endpoints, SaaS tools, or even simple AI
applications that you might need for your
Instagram automation and DM automations.
A second layer is where we look
at the vulnerability, detection,
and identification process.
So the responsibility is often
spread just to the business
owner in a small scale business.
Okay.
The first layer is asset discovery, where
a cloud native platform, the assets are
heterogeneous and are loosely coupled.
You cannot protect what you cannot see.
Unlike in tradi traditional enterprises
where each application grows through
a periodic security assessment,
every time there is a change in
infrastructure and a huge team who
is able to capture them with a.
Manual reviews and security architecture
assessments for small scale businesses.
Business owners will not have
the capability to assess how each
marketing a marketing application or
a simple DM automation is increasing
the attack ex exposure surface.
So this automated discovery will
enable them to map not just.
Identifying the assets, but
constantly evaluating if there is
a change in their security posture.
Once we know what the digital assets
are in the second layer, we are
focusing at identifying the known
vulnerability patterns, missed
security configurations, any flaws
and weakness in the authentication
frameworks exposed to services.
Missed permission, permissive
IEM, roles, et cetera.
For technical perspective, the
vulnerability might look like what
the is risk is, what would be the
criticality risk category, et cetera.
For a business owner, the same would
look maybe like a, how long will my
business have to face the downtime.
The framework here is not limited to
identifying the core vulnerabilities.
It looks at configurations, exposure,
state dependency from one model to
the other, and practical cloud native
risk that comes from, not just from
the software loss, but also from
privilege errors and misconfigurations,
which is a major advantage for
the small scale business owners.
The third layer is where the framework
shifts from a mayor assessment
to operationalizing security.
A one time scan can give you the
current time snapshot, but a continuous
monitoring then enable you how plugins
or chain updating a permissions
drift, how new endpoints appear over
time, and how the SaaS connectors are
added and configurations accumulate.
If monitoring is not continuous,
then the security state degrades
silently between one assessment to
the other, but before, even before we
realize this framework is addressing.
Baseline detecting deviations,
correlating the deviations with the
known risk patterns, and then notifying
the owner in the plain language.
It turns basic security
into static validation.
In layer four is where the AI correlates
and detects its intelligence based
on different isolation metrics.
A publicly accessible API.
It's just a moderate risk and so is an
excessive or scope, but if overlapped,
scoped, taken place, the reach, if
the over scoped token reaches the
exposed API, the combined attack
may be met materially score severe
than a signal individually does.
It also includes two additional features
of translating the risk into a simple,
plain language and then prioritizing it.
This helps a lot of security engineers
and developers to step into a common
incremental zone instead of spending
their time in random arguments on why
is this risk a priority when it is not
applicable to my system in specific,
we are not writing tons of policies and
enforcing them on developers, even when
the business criticality did not comply.
Rather, we are taking business use
cases into picture and correlating them.
So it's more like a practical guidance
and valuable insights than mere risk list.
The fifth layer is where we translate the
business aligned risks into risk scoring.
CVV scores and tech severity systems
might be useful for us already trained.
Security team or a development
team, but it's a major abstract
when it comes to business leaders.
This framework focuses on scores based
on impact decisions and the business
objectives rather than in terms of
revenue exposure, customer data trust,
regulatory obligations, and operational
disruption, not just CVV scores.
The last layer is where we
continuously monitor if the
security poster remains same.
And the continuous attestation is
like an automated evidence, so it's an
inbuilt audit already in the first place.
And it auditing is a continuous
process I kept in the framework
and not not a need on basis.
Last, but not the least, the
major operation regulating the
risk is still in the human loop.
But only the heavy lifting process
took place for reducing noise, for
reducing friction making as a technical
risks, more business aware and creating
risk translation without any manual
effort from the owner, but still
accommodate risk ownership scanning
correlating lives with the human loop.
In a nutshell.
This is an attempt.
To demonstrate that continuous cloud
native securities achievable for
a small scale businesses without
requiring dedicated team and a
complex tooling End of picture.
With this I leave.
Thank you for your time and
attending this content today.
We welcome any questions
and open for feedbacks.
Thank you so much.