Hello everyone.
My name is Naveen and I work as a Senior
Network Reliability Engineer and today I'm
going to talk about how we can optimize
Kubernetes networking with Selium and BGP.
This is the agenda of
my presentation today.
We're going to start with
an introduction to Selium.
We're going to talk about BGP and how
you can integrate BGP with Selium.
We're going to go through two use
cases and we're going to end the
presentation with some key takeaways.
Let's start with what is Seleum.
Seleum is an open source system and
it uses eBPF based networking security
and observative layer for different
cloud environments like Kubernetes
and also major cloud providers.
So if you see on your right,
there's a Kubernetes node and Seleum
agent will be deployed In it, it
uses Daemonset to deploy, Seleum.
So it's deployed across all
the nodes of your cluster.
what are the benefits of using Seleum?
the first one is performance.
Now, you can use eBPF as I mentioned.
It's basically a small programs that
you can embed into your linux kernel
and you manipulate to increase your
performance and do Other things that
can benefit your service So let's say
if you can apply network policies and
so you don't have to rely on ip tables
and which will significantly improve
the performance of your service And
the second one is network security.
Now you can have more control,
granular control for your application.
you can provide network
policies as I mentioned before.
And, You can say which services
can talk to each other.
So for example, service A can talk
to service B, but service A cannot
talk to service C. So it leverages
the concept of zero trust and gives
you the exact access that you need.
The third one is scalability.
Now, with Celium, and we're going to
talk more about this in the next few
slides also, you can leverage PGP to
scale your services across multiple
clusters and multiple clouds or regions.
And the last one is observability.
Euclidean uses Hubble to capture metrics
from your services, your cluster, so
that you can use it when there is any
connectivity issue and, or any other issue
you have, you can go to this metrics and
figure out the root cause of your, issues.
So let's talk about BGP now.
What is BGP?
BGP is a Border Gateway Protocol.
It is a routing protocol which
can be used to exchange routing
information between networks.
different companies, if they want to
talk to each other, they can have BGP
session between each other to exchange
routes or within a large, company,
you can have multiple networks and
they can talk to each other using BGP.
So if you look at the diagram here,
you have router one and router two.
Each network is uniquely
defined using a number.
Which is called autonomous system number.
So in this case if you see say 65,
001 and 65, 002 Let's say there
are two different networks now to
exchange routes to communicate with
each other They need to create a bgp
session and exchange those routes.
Let me give you an example so that it
makes more sense to you now Let's say
you are part of an ISP and, you're home
and you have an ISP that you're connected
to and you want to access Google.
com.
Now, how will your ISP
know how to reach Google.
com?
your ISP needs to have, a session, a
BGP session with your, with Google.
So that the Google subnets can be
advertised to the ISP and now you
as a user of that ISP can go to
Google server, get your website.
And that's how the whole internet is
connected to each other using BGP.
in this case, how do
we use BGP with Celium?
let me show you the diagram first, and
then we can talk about the benefits.
If you see on your left, you
have Kubernetes node, which is
running Seleum, and it will have
a Seleum agent running GoBGP.
GoBGP is an open source system
that is written in Go, and it
leverages that to create a BGP
session with a network device.
And if you see on your right, you
have the network device is talking
to the CEM, CELIUM agent, which is
running GoBGP and running a BGP server.
And your subnets from, let's say,
pods can be advertised to your
network devices through CELIUM.
what are the benefits?
Like, why are we doing BGP
integration with Zillium?
it will enhance your redundancy.
Now, you will have network
availability and fault tolerance.
If you, have a service across
clusters, it's advertising the same IP.
If one cluster goes down, you
can Failover to the other one.
We're going to talk a lot about this
during the when I talk about the use
cases The second one is direct service
exposure now your external services
They know about the subnets you have
in your Kubernetes cluster and can talk
to it directly without having multiple
components in between, let's say, for
example, NAT, which you can increase
the latency of your communication.
Third one is reduce latency.
Your BGP helps you with something called
regional affinity and If you have your
service running in, let's say, US and
Asia and you have a user in Asia, your
request goes to the nearest cluster
and uses the shortest path leveraged
by BGP to go to the nearest cluster.
So now you have reduced latency.
The last one is scalability.
You can, BGP can handle
millions of routes.
So if you have, even though if
you have large scale deployments
with thousands of subnets being
advertised, BGP can easily handle it.
So this is a perfect, protocol
to leverage, to advertise
routes from Kubernetes clusters.
Now let's go through some use
cases of using BGP with Xelian.
The first one is direct port
to external communication.
On top you see a traditional SNAT
approach where you have pods on your
left and they are converted, translated
into the node IP and then it's
advertised to the external services.
In this case, it's legacy payment system.
And, in the bottom you have Celium and
BGP approach where we are advertising all
the pod IPs directly to external services.
So the legacy payment system
knows about all the subnets and
can communicate directly with it.
the boards.
Help you to communicate then why we
should be prefer CLM with BGP approach
the benefit is now you can preserve
the original pod IPs throughout the
communication Which will simplify network
troubleshooting significantly If you have
connectivity issue For a service within
the cluster with an external, let's say,
legacy payment system, you know exactly
which subnet you have to troubleshoot
or which part IP to troubleshoot.
Instead of figuring out which service
behind the NAD is having an issue
going through it and will take so
much time to troubleshoot, you will
have better security auditing and
you know the exact parcel that is
communicating with the external service.
So you can order each
service individually.
And now you can also have
security, security troubleshooting.
If a security policy was misconfigured,
you exactly know which pod IP is
having connectivity issue, and
you apply, you fix the policy so
that everything is back to normal.
And the last one is an obvious
one, which is reduce latency.
Now, if you remember, The top approach
has NAT implemented in between.
in case of BGP with Celium, you
don't have any NAT overhead, which
will significantly reduce your
latency and improve your performance.
The second case is multi
cluster load balancing.
I know there's a lot of things going on
here, but I'll try to explain it to you.
If you see, we have a U.
S. cluster, a Kubernetes U.
S. cluster, you have Kubernetes APAC
cluster, and you have EU cluster.
Let's say you have your streaming service
deployed in each of these clusters.
They're going to be
advertising 10, 100, 1 to 10.
This IP is being advertised
from each of these clusters.
And we're going to be using BGP to
advertise these routes to the network.
Let's say you have a U. S. client
and it's requesting, let's say in
this case it's Netflix, and you want
to play A movie, it will create a,
the client will create a request.
It will go to, it will try
to find the shortest path.
And in this case, it's US cluster.
So that will be your primary path.
But what if that fails?
So you need a backup.
So in this case, if you see
here, this is the backup path.
Going to the eu cluster So each cluster
will have its own primary and backup
path And if let's say us cluster goes
down us client can go to eu Yes, the
rare the latency will increase but
the service is still running which
is super critical and you still The
client can still watch the movie What
are the benefits of using BGP here?
now you have native load
balancing without external LPs.
You don't need to have another load
balancer to distribute the traffic.
The network itself can take
care of load balancing for you.
The second one is automatic
failover between clusters.
As I mentioned now if us goes down your
request can go to any other cluster
Reduce latency due to regional affinity.
We talked about this before so we're
going to talk about it again If you have
a us client talking to us cluster If you
send a request, it will always try to
find the shortest path go to us cluster
And, you will have reduced latency.
If that goes down for some
reason, then we will go to AU.
Part optimization based on BGP metrics.
BGP has a lot of ways to manipulate, your
path to your, service in the cluster.
And, for example, if you have let's say
routes coming from, if you look at the
example from here, if you have, let's say
two backups, you have the primary as US
cluster, EU, and APAC of backups, what if
I want to prefer the pack of EU because
it's the newest one, and then apac, so
I can have some metrics manipulated.
So that the backup is EU
and then it could be APAC.
this use case, one of the concerns is
you can have imbalance of load balancing.
What if you have, let's say
your clusters are spread across
regions and one of the clusters.
It's getting more traffic now because of
that, you're going to have more traffic
going to that one specific cluster
instead of distributing across clusters.
So you have to be very careful with
it and test it holistically to ensure
that you don't face this issue.
So let's end the presentation
with some key takeaways.
The first one is plan your IP
addressing as early as possible.
If you, throughout this presentation,
you must have realized that, we have,
we want some subnets to be advertised.
but we don't want some of them,
advertised to the network.
you, this can become complex when you
have very large, Kubernetes clusters.
Spread across regions.
So you have to plan everything properly
to ensure, that you don't, complicate
this too much and create issues.
The second one is start
simple and then expand.
Start with a single cluster.
Have a service running.
Advertise that to your network
and see if it's able to, you know.
if your external clients are able to talk
to your service directly and try to have
deployed across nodes and then, shut down
one of the nodes and see what happens.
Is it able to fail over?
Have stress test after doing all those
tests and ensuring that you are able
to do it in production, then start
thinking about how you can have multi
cluster topologies or multi region
topologies and leverage BGP for that.
And the last one is obviously security
no matter what you're doing in technology
security is super critical in this case
you can have Security for bgp sessions.
You can have something as simple as a
password to ensure those bgp sessions
are secure And always use raw filters To
avoid advertising unnecessary networks.
If you have a network within your cluster
that you don't want to advertise, and
let's say someone leaked it by mistake,
then you need to have some filters in
your network, ensuring that you just
drop it, and not create an outage.
it's super critical to, go through
these key takeaways, and ensure that,
it doesn't become complicated, and, all.
It doesn't create an outage for you So
with that Thank you so much for listening
to my presentation I hope this was
useful if you have any questions You can
reach out to me on linkedin and i'll be
more than happy to help you Thank you