Hello, everyone.
I'm Shaun Kumar Nendrambakar.
I'm a seasoned SAP Cloud and S4
HANA software developer consultant
with over 15 years of experience
in information technology,
specializing in SAP technologies and
implementation across healthcare,
retail, and oil and gas industries.
This presentation explores SAP duals
offering Rise with SAP, Grow with SAP
represent a strategic pivot in the
enterprise resource planning, customized
to business at different stages of growth.
While rise with SAP targets large
enterprises undergoing digital
transformation grow with SAP focus
on the needs of mid sized companies
looking to scale efficiently.
The future of cloud ERP is rise
with SAP an innovative business
transforming offering aimed at
Simplifying and accelerating the
transition to SAP S4 HANA Cloud.
It provides flexible deployment
models and cloud options that cater
to exclusively needs of organization.
Inspiring the modernization of their
enterprise resource planning system,
these innovative solutions combine
cloud based ERP capabilities with AI
powered features to enable the digital
transformation and drive business value.
Through solutions like SAP S4 HANA
Cloud and SAP Business Technology
Platform, SAP has enabled organizations
to modernize their operations and
embrace digital transformation.
This presentation provides a comprehensive
analysis of the distinctions between
the public and private editions
of SAP S4 HANA Cloud within the
RISE and Grow with SAP framework.
Analyze their architecture, use
cases, advantages, and limitations.
Rise with SAP, empowering
large enterprises.
Rise with SAP fundamentally transforms
enterprise scale digital operations.
This complete solution combines cloud
ERP with AI powered business intelligence
and industry specific capabilities,
all unified in a flexible subscription
model that grows with your enterprise.
By streamlining complex transformation
into manageable steps, it enables
large organizations to innovate
faster while minimizing their risk.
Let's look at the key components and
value proposition key components.
The platform integrates
mission critical tools.
S4 HANA cloud powers
core business process.
Business process intelligence delivers
real time operation insights and automated
migration tools ensure smooth transition.
Industry specific solution address
exclusive market requirements
while the SAP Business Network
connects you seamlessly.
With suppliers, partners, and
customers to optimize your entire
value chain, value proposition.
Accelerate your digital transformation
while maintaining the business continuity.
The platform cloud architecture enables
instant scalability and provides complete
control over your digital ecosystem.
With a transparent subscription pricing,
rapid deployment options, and proven
ROI metrics, Rise with SAP delivers
immediate business impact while building
the long term competitive advantage.
Let's discuss Grow with SAP
scaling mid market businesses.
Grow with SAP accelerates digital
transformation for dynamic mid sized
business through a revolutionary approach.
By integrating proven industry
best practices, With pre configured
processes, companies can transform
their operations and achieve
enterprise grade efficiency in weeks.
Let's look at key features and benefits.
Key Feature At its core, the solution
harnesses the robust capabilities
of S4HANA public code, enhanced
with cutting edge AI analytics.
And intelligent automation organizations
can rapidly deploy their ideal solution
using industry specific configuration,
templates and implementation wizard
and drastically reducing setup
complexity and time to value.
Let's look at benefits grow with SAP
delivers enterprise class capabilities
without enterprise level complexity or
cost through its transparent pricing
model and modular architecture companies
can begin with essential functions and
scale seamlessly as they grow, preserving
the agility of mid sized business
while accessing the sophisticated tools
previously reserved for large enterprises.
Let's discuss Comparative
Analysis, RISE versus GROW.
Choosing between RISE and GROW with SAP
is a strategic decision that can define
your organization's digital future.
This comprehensive comparison empowers
decision makers to align their
choice with their organization's
exclusive requirements, ensuring
optimal return on investment.
Let's look at key differences,
RISE versus GROW feature.
Target audience, RISE with SAP,
global enterprise requiring
sophisticated multi market solutions.
GROW with SAP, agile mid sized
companies ready for rapid expansion.
ERP solutions feature, fully
featured S4 HANA cloud with
comprehensive deployment flexibility.
Whereas GROW with SAP, optimized S4 HANA
public cloud with ready to run process.
Implementation speed.
Rise with SAP Strategic Deployment
through Business Transformation.
Grow with SAP Accelerated Go Live
with Industry Tested Templates.
Customization feature.
Deep customization capabilities
for complex business models.
Grow with SAP Smart Standardization
with Essential Adoption Options.
Yeah, pricing model.
RISE with SAP, dynamic subscription
aligned with enterprise growth.
GROW with SAP, transparent mid
market optimized pricing structure.
Both solutions delivers SAP's remarkable
excellence through different approaches.
RISE empowers large enterprises
with unmatched flexibility and
depth for complex transformations.
While GROW accelerates mid market success
through efficient, prone implementation.
This strategy implementation ensures
the organization can choose the
path best to support their digital
ambitions and operational scale.
Let's discuss technical
architecture and deployment models.
Let's look at first Rise with SAP.
Delivers unmatched flexible through
multiple cloud deployment options.
hybrid, public, or private, allowing
enterprises to maintain full
control of their IT infrastructure.
Integration with SAP BTP opens up
powerful possibilities, develop custom
solutions, harness AI driven insights,
and expand system capabilities as needed.
At its core, SAP HANA's revolutionary
in memory database technology
process data up to a thousand times
faster than traditional databases.
enabling instant analytics
and real time decision making.
Let's look at Grow with SAP.
Leverage is a state of the
art cloud architecture where
multiple companies securely share
infrastructure, dramatically
reducing IT costs and complexity.
Includes an extensive library of
200 plus APIs ready to use, making
it simple to connect with essential
business tools and external services.
The system Integrate adapts to your
company's growth, whether you are
adding a user or processing more
transactions without requiring
a technical manual intervention.
AI powered features in SAP S4 HANA Cloud.
Let's explore how AI powered
features in SAP S4 HANA Cloud are
transforming business operations from
automation to predictive insights
and intelligent digital assistance.
These innovations are designed
to enhance efficiency, optimize
decision making, and drive growth.
Intelligent automation transforms
your operation with AI powered
automation that eliminates up
to 80 percent of manual tasks.
Our intelligent system automatically
handles everything from invoice matching
to inventory management, freeing
your team to drive strategic growth.
Predictive analytics.
Make data driven decisions with AI
powered forecasting that achieves
95 percent accuracy in cash flow
predictions, leverage advanced machine
learning to anticipate maintenance needs,
optimize operations, and identify new
business opportunities in real time.
Let's look at conversational AI.
Accelerate productivity with SAP Copilot,
an intelligent digital assistant that
transforms how you work, get instant
answers to complex queries, receive
proactive insights and benefits from
personalized recommendations that
becomes smarter with every interaction.
Let's discuss business
benefits of AI integration.
Enhanced decision making.
Accelerate strategic decision by 60
percent with AI powered analytics.
that convert complex data
into clear action plans.
Fortune 500 companies report 45
percent fewer costly mistakes
when using AI driven insights.
Cost optimization.
Slash operational expenses by
35 percent through intelligent
automation of routine tasks.
AI powered predictive maintenance
prevents costly breakdowns with
90 percent accuracy, extending
equipment lifetime by up to 20%.
Personalized user experience.
Drive 40 percent higher user engagement
through intelligent interface
that evolve the each interaction.
Companies achieve 50 percent faster user
adoption rates with AI powered contextual
assistance and smart recommendations.
Resilient supply chains.
Eliminate 30 percent of stock
out incidents while optimizing
inventory levels to save 25
percent in carrying costs.
Leading manufacture report.
85 percent more accurate demand forecast
using AI driven supply chain analytics.
Let's discuss industry specific use cases.
First, healthcare.
Transform patient care delivery
through intelligent workflow
optimization that reduce wait time
by 35 percent and ensures optimal
staff deployment across departments.
AI enhanced predictive analytics
monitor medical supplies in real time,
manipulating critical inventory levels
with 96 percent accuracy to ensure
uninterpreted patient care delivery.
Let's look at Retail Use Case,
transform customer experiences with
AI powered personalization engines.
That analyze shopping patterns to
deliver customized recommendations,
driving a 30 percent increase in sales
conversion, smart inventory management,
leverages machine learning to optimize
stock levels, reducing carry cost by 20
percent while maintaining the industry
leading 98 percent product availability.
Oil and gas use case.
SAP S4 HANA cloud provides a
robust digital foundation for
oil and gas organizations.
Enabling real time inventory
tracking, optimized logistic, and
enhanced customer behavior management
through data driven insights.
By improving order fulfillment,
reducing storage costs, and
minimizing downtime, it streamlines
operations across the industry.
The HANA Cloud with Generative AI
has further transformed the sector.
Transforming operational
efficiency across upstream,
midstream, and downstream segments.
Let's discuss implementation
challenges and mitigation
strategies in SAP Cloud Adoption.
Transitioning to SAP Cloud
Solution offers transformative
benefits, but implementation comes
with its own set of challenges.
Let's explore three key hurdles businesses
face and how SAP advanced tools and
strategies effectively mitigate them.
First, data migration challenge,
legacy system contain inconsistency
data, incompatible format and
potential integrity risk, making
migration complex and time consuming.
The mitigation strategy, SAP leverages
SAP Data Intelligence to automate data
validation, cleansing and transformation.
This approach achieves 99 percent data
accuracy, reduces mitigation time by 40%.
ensures zero business disruption
by utilizing AI driven automation
businesses can ensure smooth and
secure transition to SAP cloud
without compromising data integrity.
Let's look at customization
needs challenge.
Every organization has specific workflows
and business requirements that standard
SAP functionalities may not fully address.
Over customization can lead to
higher cost, system instability,
and challenges in future upgrades.
The mitigation strategies here, instead
of deep customization, SAP recommends a
modular extension approach using SAP BTP.
This method provides customization
solution without altering the core
system, reduces the customization
cost by 35%, ensures future
scalable and system stability.
By utilizing the SAP BTP businesses
can extend functionality without
compromising upgradability,
ensuring a future proof system.
Let's look at change management challenge.
Adopting SAP Cloud means new process, new
workflows, and user adaptation challenges.
Resistance to change
can hinder adaptation.
reduce efficiency and impact
ROI mitigation strategy to
drive seamless user adaptation.
SAP recommends structured change
management initiatives, including
role specific training programs,
digital adaptation platforms with
interactive guidance, continuous
user support to address concerns.
This approach has proven to achieve
90 percent user proficiency,
reduce support tickets.
By focusing on proactive training and
support, organizations can accelerate
adoption, enhance productivity,
and maximize SAP cloud value.
Let's discuss future directions
in SAP Cloud Computing.
AI and machine learning expansion.
SAP's enhanced AI capabilities will
integrate advanced language models.
and learning algorithms directly
into core business processes.
Companies can expect 40 percent faster
data analysis, 60 percent more accurate
demand forecasting, and automated
workflows that reduce manual tasks
by up to 70%, fundamentally changing
how teams work and make decisions.
Sustainable and Green Cloud.
SAP's Green Cloud initiative targets
100 percent renewable energy usage
by 2025 and 80 percent reduction
in data centers energy consumption
through AI optimized operations.
The platform will provide real time
carbon footprint tracking, automated
sustainability reporting, and actionable
recommendations that have helped early
adopters reduce their cloud related
emissions by an average of 45%.
Let's look at IoT and edge computing.
Next generation IoT integration will
bring computing power closer to the data
source, reducing latency by up to 90%.
Manufacturing plants can process sensor
data locally, enabling real time quality
control and predictive maintenance, while
retail locations can instantly analyze
customer behavior and inventory levels
without relying on central servers.
Let's look at hyper personalization.
Future industry cloud solution
will analyze over 1, 000 customer
data points in real time to deliver
truly personalized experience.
Companies implementing these tools
have seen 85 percent improvement
in customer engagement, 40 percent
high conversion rate, and 60 percent
better customer retention through
AI powered product recommendation
and customized service interactions.
Conclusion.
Embracing the future of ERP.
Rise with SAP and grow with SAP S4 HANA
Cloud transforms enterprise operations
by offering flexible, scalable solutions
that reduce IT complexity by up to 40
percent while accelerating the innovation
cycles across organizations of all sizes.
AI driven innovations through
advanced AI capabilities.
Organizations are achieving 30
percent faster decision making,
45 percent improvement process.
Automation efficiency and unprecedented
level of personalized that directly
impact bottom line results.
Strategic adoption, forward thinking
organization implementing these cloud
solutions are experiencing faster digital
transformation success rates and gaining
sustainable competitive advantages through
improved agility, real time insights
and enhanced customer experiences.
Thank you for joining me today.