Hello  everyone,  my  name  is
Ijeoma  Eti  and  I  will  be
talking  on  optimizing  cache
usage  in  Docker  Build.
About  me,  I'm  a  software  engineer
and  I'm  very  passionate  about
sharing  knowledge  through  writing.
I'm  also  an  active  contributor
to  the  open  source  community.
And  then  you  can  connect  with
me  on  LinkedIn  or  Twitter.
Twitter.
let's  get  started  by
talking  about  why  Docker
builds  can  feel  very  slow.
So  one  of  the  biggest  pain,  um,
points  with  Docker,  with  Docker
build  is  that  even  the  smallest  code
change  can  trigger  a  full  rebuild.
That  means  you  are  often
rebuilding  parts  of  your  application
that  haven't  Even  changed.
And  this  can  significantly
increase  view  times.
So  without  optimization  of
your  docker,  docker  will
usually  run  through  unnecessary
steps  again  and  again.
Wasting,  um,  the  compute  power.
Right.
And,  um,  if  you've  ever  worked  in  a
CI -CD  environment,  this  is  usually  a
very  real  problem  because  it  causes
a  very  long  build  time  and  slows
down  your  testing  or  your  deployment,
which,  um,  ultimately  reduces
the  entire  developer  productivity.
And  no  one  wants  to  really  sit
around  waiting  for  use  to  finish.
When  they  can,  like,  they  could
be  shipped,  uh,  they  could
ship  features  really  quickly.
So  why  does  this
optimization  really  matter?
First,  it  speeds  up
the  development  faster.
And  also,  it's,  um,  Allows
developers  to  iterate  and  test
their  changes  really,  really  quickly.
So,  um,  also  it  helps
save  money,  right?
Cause  when  you  have  a  faster  build,
it  means  that  you  won't  have  to
spend  a  lot  of  compute  power  which
can  reduce  infrastructure  costs.
Um,  so...
Yeah,  understanding  docker  build.
So  now  let's  take  a  closer  look
at  how  docker  build  actually  work.
So,  um,  the  first  thing  is  that,
uh,  when  you  start  building,
docker  loads  the  build  context.
So  when  you  run  a  docker  build,
like  it  gathers  all  the  files
in  the  directory  where  you  are
building  the  image  and  these
files  make  up  the  build  context
and  can  impact  the  build  process.
So,  um,  the  next  thing  that  it  does
is  that  it  passes  the  Dockerfile.
So,  Docker  reads  this
instruction  in  the  Dockerfile
and  executes  them  one  by  one.
And  then,  um,  the  next  step  is
that  it  creates  an  immutable  layer.
So,  just,  these  are  like  sets
of  instructions  in  the  Dockerfile.
Why  do  you  need  the
expression  for  change?
That's  because  for  each
instruction  in  the  Dockerfire,
you  create  a  new  layer  and
then  these  layers  are  immutable.
So  once  they  are  built,
they  do  not  change.
So  also,  the  last  thing  that
happens  is  that  Docker  uses
caching  to  P -Dop  rebuild.
So,  rebuild  like  when  you  need
to  build  your  Docker,  your
application  again  using  Docker.
So,  Docker  just  reuses  the  unchanged
layer  to  avoid  redundant  processing
and  making  your  build  much  faster.
So,  this  is  an  example
of  a  Docker  file.
And,  um,  let  me  just  break
this  down  really  quickly.
Um,  we  have  the  first  one
that's  from  Python  3 .1.
Right?
So,  this  is  like  the  base  image.
Ideally,  you  could  use
like  an  Alpine,  which  is...
Um,  um,  um.
Copy  all  the  content
from  the  requirements.
CX  T  file  first.
So  this  is  like  Python.
Projects,  right?
And  then  it  sort  of  installs
the  dependency  and  this  step
is  you  can  be  cashed  if  the
requirement  of  TXT  doesn't  change.
So  like  if  you  do  not  add  any
new  stuff  to  the  requirement,
any  new  model  to  the,  or
package  the  requirement  of  TXT.
It  doesn't  install  more  dependency.
And  then  the  next  thing  is
that  it  copies  the  rest  of
the  application  files,  right?
And  then  it  defines  the
command  to  run  the  application.
So  this  is  like,  um,  what  happens.
So,  um,  but  there's  one
very  important  thing,  right?
The  order  of  the
instruction  really  matters.
So  if  you  place,  um,  placing
copied  or  requirement  your  txt  and
running  pip  install  would  first  help
docker  to  cache  the  dependencies
separately  from  the  application  code.
And  this  avoids  unnecessary
reinstalling  dependencies
when  only  code  changes.
So,  um,  now  that  we've  really
understood  the  fundamentals,  let's
explore  ways  to  optimize  caching.
For  even  faster  build.
So,  how  does  caching  work?
Now  we  understand  how  docker
builds  work,  Um,  let's
just  talk  about  caching.
So,  which  is  one  of  the
most  important  ways  docker
uses  to  speed  up  builds.
So,  what  is  docker?
Um,  basically  docker  cache
Docker  torrentships  on  a  larger
new  layer  and  dorch  it  on
changed  steps  whenever  possible.
At  least  we  avoid  rebuilding
the  parts  of  ebenage  that
haven't  changed,  making
the  build  much  faster.
So,  for  example,  if  you  want  to
install  a  dependents  independently
of  a  docker  file  and  they  haven't
changed,  docker  reuses  previous
built  layers,  instead  of  running
the  application  process  again.
Concepts  in  layers  caching  and  like
each  instruction,  the  Dockerfile
creates  a  layer  and  some  layers
can  be  cached  while  others  can't.
So  let's  go  over  the
table  in  the  slides.
Um,  from  the  previous,  um,  slide,
I,  I  showed  you,  uh,  a  Dockerfile.
Um,  so  here  I'm  just  going  to
talk  about  the  layers  that  can
be  cached  in  that  Dockerfile.
Um,  Um,  we  have  um,  um,  the
from  Python,  um,  um,  Swaraj,  3.
um,  1  zero,  um  that  is  cacheable.
Um,  Um,  So  eh,
uh ,ride.
change  often,  right?
So  docker  usually  caches  this  part.
So,  um,  the,  the  step,  um,
for  copying  the  requirement
of  txt  is  also  cacheable.
So  this  step  is  cached  as
long  as  like  the  requirement
of  txt  remains  the  same.
And  then,  um,  if  the  requirement
of  txt  hasn't  changed,  docker
will  reuse  the  cache  dependencies.
Um,  so  the  command  to  copy
the  entire,  um,  application
code  is  usually  not  cacheable.
And  this  step,  um,  copies  all  the
files  basically  in  the  directory.
And  if  any  file  changes,  this
step  breaks  and  the  cache  is
forced,  um,  this  step  breaks  the
cache  and  is  forced  to  rebuild.
So,  that's  what  happens.
So  this  is  why  it's  important  to
structure  your  Docker  strategically.
So,  um,  The  problem,  why  docker
builds  can  become  inefficient.
So  even  with  caching,  docker  builds
can  be  very  slow  and  here's  why.
So  one  thing  is,  um,  small
mistakes  in  the  docker  file
can  invalidate  the  cache  and
forcing  unnecessary  rebuilds.
So  another  thing  also
is  the  structure.
So  if  the  instructions  are  not
properly,  um,  ordered,  um,  this  can
also  force  an  unnecessary  rebuild.
So  another  thing  is,  um,
frequent  dependency  change.
So  if  you  are  constantly  updating
your  dependency,  it  means  that  you're
forcing  Docker  to...  Um,  um,  um,
um,  um,  um,  um,  um,  um,  um,  um,
um,  um,  um,  um,  um  Um,  um,  Um,  Um,
Um,  Um,  Um,  Um,  Um,  Um,  Um,  Um,
Um,  Um,  Um,  Um  Sous -titres  réalisés
para  la  communauté  d .org  So,  yeah,
so  some  common  pitfalls,  uh,
like  I  already  said  earlier,
uh,  your  order  of  instructions.
Then,  um,  another  thing  is
using  add  instead  of  copy.
So  this,  like,  extracts
files  unnecessarily.
But  copy  uses,  like,  So,
um,  use  copy,  like,  um,
unless  downloading  archives.
So,  like,  try  to  avoid  using  add.
Um,  sorry,  um,  try  to  use  add
instead  of  copy  every  single  time.
And  then,  um,  any  changes
invalidates  the  cache.
So  be  very  explicit
about  your  copied  files.
So,  um,  you  can  try  to
always  use  the  wildcard.
Best  practices  for  optimizing
docker  build  using  cache.
Um,  structure  a  docker  file
for  maximum  cache  reuse.
Um,  so  another  thing  is  you
need  to  place  table  instructions
before  the  frequently  changed  ones.
And  then  you  can  use  the
multi -stage  build  to  reduce
the  final  image  size.
So  you  only  want  to  keep
what's  necessary  in  the  final
image,  um,  to  reduce  bloat.
And  then,  make  sure  to
leverage  the  docker  ignore  to
reduce  the  build  context  size.
So,  exclude  any  unnecessary
file  that,  um,  that  could
slow  down  the  build.
Um,
another  thing  we  want  to  do  is
we  want  to  use  arguments  as  the
arg  instead  of  environment  variable.
And  because  arg  is  always
available,  it's  only  available
during  the  build  time  and
it  keeps  your  image  cleaner.
Um,  so  we  can  see  from  the
Dockerfile  that  I  placed  here  and  we
see  how  it  was  properly  structured.
So,  um,  Erm,  erm,  This  is  optimized
because  the  dependencies  are
copied  first  and  so  they're  cached
separately  and  then  the  application
files  are  copied  last  so  preventing
unnecessary  cache  invalidation.
Erm,  so,  There  are,  This  is
the  basic  caching  instructions
or  caching  techniques.
So,  in  the  next  slide,  I'll
be  talking  about  advanced  Sous
-titres  réalisés  para  la  communauté
d .org  Caching  techniques.
So  now  we've  covered  the
basic  caching  techniques.
Um,  um,  there  are  some  really
advanced  caching  techniques
and  that  is  using  the
mouse  for  building  cache.
So  one  powerful  way  we
can  speed  up  things  is  by
using  mouse  for  caching.
So,  um,  BindMount,  um,  or
VolumeMount,  um,  can  help  persist
dependencies  across  build  and
reduce  a  redundant  installation.
So  we  can  add  the  mount,
um,  equal  to  type,  and  equal
to  type  cache  with  buildkit.
And  this  allows  Docker  to  cache
immediate  build  without  creating
unnecessary  layer  and  this  would
help  to  improve  the  performance.
So,  um,  We  can  also  leverage
external  cache  sources,  right?
Um,  one  of  the,  um,  Docker  has
a  build  X  for  distributed  caching
and  this  allows  caching  to  be
stored,  to  be  shared  across
multiple  platforms  and  environments.
So.
Um,  yeah,  I  just  placed  a  code
on  how  to,  an  example  of  how  to,
um,  stop  build  cache  in  a  registry
so  every  new  build  can  reuse  it.
So  this  ensures  that  the  build,
um,  ensures  the  build  reuse  the
cache  layers,  making  them  much
faster,  especially  if  you're
working  in  a  CI -CD  environment.
Um,  so  another  thing,  uh,  when
you've  improved  your  cache  layer
properly,  you  want  to  measure
or  debug  the  build  performance.
And,  um,  There  are  different  ways
of  checking  it  or,  um,  so  one
way  it's  by  using  the  docker
build  progress  plane  and  this
shows,  um,  it  just  gives  you  a
more  detailed  outputs  to  check
if  the  layers  are  being  reused.
And  you  can  also  use  the  docker
history,  um,  this  would  basically
list  image  layers  and  their  sizes
to  see  what  exactly  is  cached.
So  if  you  want  to  analyze  the
docker  image,  you  can  use,  you
can  also  use  the  docker  history,
you  can  use  the  time  docker  build,
and  this  should,  this  measures
like  the  duration  to  track  if
you're,  if  you're,  if  there's  any
improvements  in  your  docker  history.
um,  using  all  these  tools
it,  it,  it  helps  like,
um,  spot  any  inefficiencies.
Um,  and  then  it  can
keep  your  beauty.
It  can  make  your
build  run  really  fast.
So,  um,  dokr  builds  in  conclusion,
dorket -build  is  very  essential
for  speeding  up  builds  and
it  reduces  the  resource  usage.
so  by  structuring  your
dockerfiles  effectively  and
avoiding  common  mistakes  and
utilising  advanced  techniques  like
i  mentioned,  using  the  build
-ex  we  can,  um  significably,
significantly  recite  Ficantly
improve  the  build  performance.
And  the  next  step  after
doing  all  of  this  is  to,
um,  apply  this  in  your  real
life,  in  your  real  project.
And  then  also  try  to,  um,  analyze
if  your,  your  build  time  or  analyze
if  the  caching  works  properly  based
on  the  technique  I  explained  earlier.
Thank  you.