Hello, thanks for joining.
today we will be navigating
the world of API gateways.
So I hope you enjoy, let's get started.
over the years, applications
have transitioned from
monolithic architecture to.
microservices and cloud
native environments as the
number of services grows.
So that's the complexity of managing
API traffic, security and performance.
So, in the scope of, these, presentation,
we will answer the question.
What is API gateway?
Why do we need them?
Then we will, compare, five,
open source API gateways.
And, in the end of presentation,
we will look at, future trends
of, developing the, API gateways.
Yeah.
let's get started.
why do we actually need, API gateways?
There are, a lot of challenges
that, modern systems face every day.
the first is, uncontrolled API traffic,
then, security risks, performance
bottlenecks, and, lack of observability.
So API gateway tries to solve.
those problems.
So API gateway, is a reverse proxy
that sits between clients, which
are users, applications, or external
services and, backend, services acting
as a centralized traffic manager.
it controls how API requests
are routed and authenticated,
transformed and monitored.
API gateways are essential in
microservices architecture, cloud native
applications, and distributed systems.
as I mentioned before, it solves those
problems, the problems like traffic
management and request routing.
API gateways route incoming API requests.
to the correct backend services based on
URL paths, headers, query parameters, user
identity, and other, requests, properties.
they also support L7, AKA application
layer, routing for REST, gRPC,
GraphQL, WebSockets, and even.
TCP, UDP traffic, and they
also provide traffic splitting,
enabling, AB testing, blue green
deployments and canary releases.
API gateways also, improve performance,
by load balancing requests across
multiple backend instances, by
caching frequently used responses.
By compression, to reduce response
payload size and also request response,
transformation like, changing headers,
payloads, or protocol versions,
and, also, they act as a central
security layer for all API calls
implementing, authentication mechanisms
like OAuth2, JWT, OpenID Connect.
MTLS and, many others.
and they also, provide detailed,
analytics for, on API traffic, like
metrics collection, logging, tracing,
and they usually provide real time,
dashboards for, API traffic insights.
and they're usually,
extensible and customized.
they provide built in
plugins for rate limiting,
authentication, logging, and so on.
And, they also provide you with
the capability of, writing your,
own custom plugins to extend.
the functionality.
so we will, discussing, in the scope
of this presentation, we will be
discussing five, open source, solutions.
And, but first we would need
to answer, why open source?
Why I chose, open source API gateways
in the scope of, this presentation.
So first of all, it's a cost effective,
large, enterprise, enterprises save
millions annually, by switching from
commercial gateways to self hosted
open source solution solutions.
also, it's, transparent.
So no black box.
So you can, See the code, you can, I don't
know, add, your own feature or bug fixes.
and, and it's community driven.
open source projects usually evolve
faster than commercial products
and, large developer communities
contributes new features regularly.
So we will be discussing five,
open source API gateways.
And, I chose, Apache API 6, Con,
Tick, Kraken D and, Glue Edge.
So let's start with the first.
Apache API 6 is an open source,
high performance API gateway built
for cloud native, multi protocol
and high throughput applications.
It provides dynamic configuration,
rich, plugin support.
While maintaining, ultralow latency.
so key, technical details
you can see on the screen.
it's written in, open rest
team in Jinx plus, logic.
it's, licenses, Apache 2.0, which
means that it's, fully open source.
storage options is, etcd and, files
configuration options, admin API, YAML
files or declarative configuration
like, Kubernetes, CRDs if deployed
to Kubernetes, plugin system.
contains built in plugins for security,
traffic control, observability, and
transformations, and it supports
custom plugins written in Lua,
Go, Python, and WebAssembly.
For security authentication, and
authentication plugins, they have, OAuth2,
OpenID Connect, JWT authentication, API
key based authentication, and many others.
For observability, they have
metrics collection with, Prometheus
plugin, also OpenTelemetry.
data doc and, for distributed
tracing, skywalking.
And, I want to, I want to
pay your attention that this,
presentation, it contains the links
to the official documentation.
Of API, of API six and,
other gateways as well.
So you can, go, to these links
and, see what they actually provide
because, obviously I couldn't,
add, everything to this present.
presentation, it would
be, not readable at all.
So I just, mentioned the main
things and, hot reload is supported.
So you can apply dynamic updates
via admin API without restarting.
You can add, plugins, you can change
your routing configuration and so on,
and it will not require the restart.
So let's move on to the
second API gateway, it's Kong.
It's also a high performance open
source API gateway designed for
scalability, security, and extensibility.
It's built on Jinx and OpenResty.
It offers a powerful Plugin system,
multi cloud compatibility and
enterprise ready security features.
licenses, Apache 2.
0, as previous one, for storage, options,
they support, DBLS, storage, they,
support, their own storage, connect,
also you can use, database like Postgres.
For, persistence, and, yeah, for
configuration options, the files are
available, Kubernetes CRDs and, admin API.
plugin system, has over 50, built in
plugins for rate limiting, caching,
security, traffic, traffic control, and
it also supports, custom plugins written
in Lua, Go, Python, and WebAssembly.
among the authentication plugins
they have OAL two JWT OpenID
Connect, L-D-A-P-A-H-M-A-C, and,
other authentication mechanisms.
For observability, for metrics,
they support Prometheus,
OpenTelemetry, Datadog, and
Zipkin for distributed tracing.
They also support hot reloading via
admin API and you can also apply
dynamic updates without restarting.
So The next, gateway is, TIC, TIC,
is, a high performance open source
gateway designed for scalability,
security, and multi protocol support.
it's built in Go, not, Lua and
Jinx like previous API gateways.
It provides native GraphQL support,
authentication, and rate limiting.
And flexible deployment option for cloud,
hybrid and on premises environments.
as I said, it's written in Go, high
performance and multi threaded.
The license is MPL.
For storage, they use Redis.
It's used for caching, rate
limiting and state management.
And, also optionally for,
dashboard, for analytics, they,
use MongoDB and, SQL, database.
So configuration options are admin API.
and declarative configuration using,
JSON, YAML, or Kubernetes, CRDs, plug
in, system has, built in middleware,
plugins for security transformation
and observability, and, it supports,
supports custom plugins in Go.
Python, and JavaScript,
Lua, and also WebAssembly.
they provide a lot of authentication
plugins like Vauth2, JWT, MTLS,
authentication tokens, and, like
advanced rate limiting plugins, throat
link, quota enforcement, many others.
You can see, by the link provided in the.
presentation, for metrics, they
support Prometheus open telemetry,
data doc, and also just visit, the
links and, you will see the whole list.
I want to also mention.
that, this, gateway supports,
GraphQL, natively, and also, gRPC
proxying and, transformation.
TIC supports hot reloading
via API and dashboard dynamic
updates without restarts.
the next, gateway In the list is
Kraken D. It's a lightweight, high
performance API gateway designed for
API aggregation, request transformation,
and stateless architecture.
It's built in Go as well.
It's optimized for low latency
microservices, offering high scalability
with minimal resource consumption.
yeah.
the licenses, Apache 2.0,
storage option, is, stateless.
So they don't require any, database,
configuration options, are, files.
Jason O or IL files.
and, you can also actually, specify
configuration in environment variables
and, in Kubernetes, CCRD if, deployed
to Kubernetes, they, have the middleware
based architecture for plugins and you
can write your own plugins, using, go.
They also provide.
Provide the, JWT validation, plugins,
API key authentication, MTLS, Auth0,
like a lot of, plugins for authentication
mechanisms, for, monitoring Prometheus,
OpenTelemetry, Datadog, and many others.
interesting that, they do not
support, the hot reloading.
they have this option, but, on
their documentation, they say that,
it's not recommended for prod.
It can be used only for,
development, purposes.
And the last but not least, API gateway
in the list is, Glue, Edge, it's high
performance cloud native API gateway built
on Envoy proxy designed for Kubernetes
multi cloud and hybrid environments.
It offers a deep integration
with Kubernetes, advanced
traffic control and enterprise.
price security features.
So yeah, it's written in Go, built
on Envoy Proxy, multi threaded.
The license is Apache 2.
0, so also fully open source.
Storage options are Docker for.
Storage options are, sorry,
files, file based configuration,
like YAML, or Kubernetes CRDs.
Configuration options is declarative,
declarative configuration via
Kubernetes CRDs, or Helm charts.
Yeah.
And, you can write plugins, In
goal, among the security and
authentication, plugins, they have
the O2 JWT authentication and LDAP for
observability, for metrics support.
they have Prometheus, Grafana,
and, Datadog, plugins.
sorry.
they also support the hot reload
and zero downtime, configuration.
yeah, when, choosing an API
gateway performance is a critical
factor, especially for high traffic
applications, microservices and
latency sensitive workloads.
here's how the API 6, Con, Tick,
Kraken D and Glue H compare.
In terms of latency and, throughput.
So I, I ordered, those API gateways,
from, the fastest ones to slowest.
of course, like I, I looked at the
benchmarks, on their websites and,
I looked at the information on the.
internet, and, it seems like
the situation is like this.
API 6 is the first, is the fastest
API gateway because, it's built, on
open resting Jinx and Lua JIT, it's,
optimized for ultra low latency.
this G Jett, compilation just in time
compilation in Ji, it runs, plugins
faster than traditional Lua used by Kong.
So Kong, is, the latest,
the last in this, least.
so why is D fast cracking D is optimized
for API, aggregation and stateless
performance make it ultra fast.
So it's it's fully written in Go.
no scripting overhead, unlike Lua
based gate, gateways, it's stateless.
so no need for etcd, Postgres or Redis,
and it's designed for API aggregation.
It merges multiple API calls into
a single, response efficiently.
And it's, it has the high
concurrency, thanks to coroutines.
It can handle thousands
of, simultaneous requests.
with, low resource usage.
so why is tick a strong performer?
tick balances, performance
and extensibility.
It's built in go and u and
usually, in, many properties,
go is, faster than law based.
gateways.
yeah, it's optimized for security heavy
workloads, but it's slightly slower than
API 6 and cracking D in a raw performance.
yeah, glue edge optimized for Kubernetes.
It's built on and avoid proxy.
And so provides strong
Kubernetes native performance.
it's highly optimized for L7
routing, and, yeah, it's best suited
for Kubernetes heavy deployments.
And, why is Korn slower than, API 6
is because, it's based on OpenResty
without JIT, JIT compilation.
So slower than API 6 and it relies
on Postgres, for persistence.
That's database latency, but, it's
worse saying that DBLS, mod improves
performance, but it's still not as fast
as APS XO or Kraken D. And it's, it also
contains like a strong plugin ecosystem,
but plugin execution, adds overhead.
And you can see, I specified here, the.
Links to benchmarks, those are,
benchmarks in their official sites.
and, some of those gateways
provide, versus like comparison.
APS six, versus cone, crack, crack and D
versus cone and versus tick versus cone.
it, it can be useful like, day here.
they use, different, machines,
different configurations.
So it's hard to say who, who is, the
best, but this is the general picture.
And, if you see the.
Con benchmarks, they had, done a
lot of, a lot of tests in a lot of,
machines, with different configurations.
So worth checking.
So the second thing I want to
mention is WebSocket support.
Cracking D, doesn't support it
in, open source version, only in
enterprise version, for gRPC cracking
D, doesn't support it as well.
and also, the license for TIC, you
may have noticed that, it's MPL and,
it's, less permissive than, Apache.
2. 0, and I think that it's also
useful to see, which customers,
like which, technologies use,
those, gateways in production.
So here's the list and maybe it
will help to, to make decision,
when choosing the right gateway.
yeah, let's move on to the final part.
So future trends, as modern
applications evolve, API gateways
must adapt to new challenges in
performance, security, and scalability.
And here the key feature,
Trans shaping API gateways.
So first is a AI powered API gateways
like, AI will predict traffic patterns
and auto scale APIs dynamically.
And, AI driven, anomaly detection
will prevent failures before.
They impact users.
and I saw actually in the documentations
of those API gateways that API 6
and con also already look in this
direction, but, and they already
have some plugins for this, but.
Those plugins are just, simplifying
access to LLLM, providers.
So they, work, only on transformation,
like adding headers, transforming,
requests, body to, to make the.
requesting those, APIs,
more eff efficiently.
yeah.
So the next thing is, Kubernetes,
gateway AP API replacing, ingress.
as, as, and, I actually checked
this, last year and, gateway, API
but by Kubernetes was, in beta.
But, now it's not.
they provide the gateway API and, this
gateway API will, replace traditional,
ingress controllers that, have, some.
Trade-offs.
So a, Kubernetes gateway, API, aims to
resolves, to resolve, those, trade-offs.
yeah, API Gateways will fully integrate
with Kubernetes NA native net networking.
and actually.
glue h and con ingress
controller are early adopters
of the Kubernetes Gateway API.
The next thing is GraphQL
and gRPC native support.
REST APIs are no longer the default.
It's the standard more API gateways
will support GraphQL and gRPC natively,
including GraphQL query introspection
and validation, gRPC proxying with
real time transformation, GraphQL
caching and schema enforcement.
And, I already mentioned this, TIC has
full GraphQL support and API 6 offers
GraphQL rate limiting and query filtering.
And the last but not least is API
monetization and marketplaces.
So companies are turning APIs
into revenue generating products.
so API gateways will provide, built
in, monetization, including billing
and API usage metering, subscription
based API models and, self service
API portals for developers.
for example, TIC and Con
Enterprise, already offer.
yeah, this is it for my presentation.
I hope you enjoyed it and, maybe
took, some, something, useful for you.
so yeah.
If you have any questions, or, I provided
the link to, my, LinkedIn account and,
yeah, here the references, the links to
references I used, for, this presentation.
yeah, thank you for attention.
I hope you enjoyed it.