Hey guys.
It's nice to see you all again.
My name is Matan Taf,
co-founder CTO of Rapido.
we started Rapido about, three years ago
when we saw companies struggling with
managing fleets of databases on the cloud.
Today we will dive into why
there are so many fleets.
We're not gonna talk about Kubernetes.
We're gonna talk about cloud
in cloud native architectures.
We're gonna talk about the stepson
of every CloudOps organization, the
databases, and why today's way of
managing databases in the cloud.
In micro services cloud
native environment is broken.
So let's dive a little
bit into the problem.
So cloud native and multi-tenant
apps change the way people
are consuming databases Is.
As opposed to what they used to do.
one of the biggest concerns when managing
a multi-tenant app is the noisy neighbor,
issue that could essentially make one
service interfere with another service.
this is why auto scaling and scale
out capabilities are very valuable
in cloud native environments.
And.
The only piece that doesn't
autoscale within the entire
stack is gonna be our databases.
managed services like RDS also
helps organization to shift the.
More responsibilities to developers.
So they write the queries, they use oms.
in many cases the specific dev team
is in charge of managing a specific
database and so on and so forth.
on the other side of the scale,
we still see operational teams,
needing to, take care of databases
and make sure that their uptime.
Cost and performance are
actually going to rock.
and generally creating this situation
where on one hand we have the SRE
team, the CloudOps teams that are
living in a world of minutes, right?
So they need to respond now, they need
to do it, efficiently, and it has to.
Work.
It has to be determined.
So we see that CloudOps teams are
essentially in charge on infrastructure
costs, on, on database SLA, on the
uptime of the database, as I said
before, and on performance, right?
Like when queries are running slow.
The customer facing team will
typically reach out to the cloud
of Gu CloudOps guys, right?
on the other side of the scale, as I
said, we see, developers or dev teams
that are in charge of other things, right?
They need to deliver new
features, they need to work fast.
Um, they need to make sure that
the code, that their code is
running efficiently and so on.
and they have.
Almost 100% of the impact on the database.
So on the one hand, we see these guys that
are living in timeframe of days, right?
Like they always need to wait
to another dev cycles and they
have all the impact, right?
They generate the query.
That will hit your database
in the end of the day.
And on the other side, we have these
guys that typically have to take the
consequences of what these guys are doing,
of what the dev is doing, essentially.
this is a situation which is not healthy.
It makes SRE and CloudOps teams
like not to meet their KPI,
and face a lot of trouble.
Managing databases, right?
so the type of issues that we see that
sre, and cloud ops teams are facing
today, start with visibility, right?
if I am living in a multi-tenant, I manage
a fleet of databases, the first problem
is how do I see what is the most pressing
issues across my fleet of databases?
How do I know where is the slowest query?
How do I know where was
like the latest CPU spike?
Or where do I have.
CPU spikes that are getting close
to the edge and jeopardizing by SLA.
So all these activities when managing
a fleet of databases, are very hard
and by definition, put cloud ops teams.
Being responsive or being reactive
instead of being proactive and
respond and preventive and respond
to issues before they actually
rise and take the database down.
So we see that when managing a fleet
of databases, there are completely
different set of challenges that
CloudOps teams has to manage, especially
when they don't have the DBA skill
sitting within their teams typically.
And even if they do, it's not easy.
This is why we built a
platform addressing this.
Operational problem that CloudOps
teams have when managing a fleet of
databases, which always impact the
business in various ways, it's gonna
impact your business, in performance
of your application on SLA of your
application, on your AWS bill.
So all these KPIs are actually
something that RAPIDO can solve
for you, and we address directly
that operational challenge.
In a nutshell, you would like your,
ideal tool, to be able to gain
observability across multiple instances.
There are some tools that
do that in the world, right?
They, you have Datadog, DBM, you have,
SolarWinds, you have, I know that New
Relic released recently a new tool
for managing a fleet of databases.
All these tools are in
charge of one thing.
They do only one thing, and that gives
you, it's to give you observability.
The other things that you would
like, the platform that manages your
databases to have is automation.
You want the ability to cache queries to
protect your database from CPU spikes to,
accelerate slow queries to, optimize the
underlying infrastructure cost, right?
so above and beyond anything,
improve resiliency and improve.
The underlying costs, The automation.
So Rapido is the only tool
in the world that does that.
And today, I'm gonna show you a live
demo of how it actually works in action.
What you can see here is a CPU graph
of one of our biggest customers.
they had, couple of hundreds
of RDS instances in that
size, various sizes, but.
By and large eight Excel, which they
grew all the way up to that, right?
So they started like one Excel.
They had C-P-U-C-P-U Spike, CPU.
Spike is emergency.
They go ahead, they increase the
infrastructure, the underlying database.
They hit the roof again,
they increase it again.
And always in twofold, right?
Like when you work with RDS, you gotta
increase your infrastructure by, by 100%.
Like any scale up, here.
What happened when they
started to use Rapido?
So with that emergency, they inserted
RAPIDO to their R five eight XL instance.
It was exactly three or four
months ago, last December.
and as you can see, only by
inserting Rapido with couple of
rules, the CPU baseline dropped
from 60 to 100% to 20 to 30%.
so they really.
Moved away from the danger zone,
from the area where something can
get wrong with the replication.
at this point you can see that they
decided to shrink 30 DB instance.
And as you can see, the baseline went a
bit up, from 20 to 30 to flat 30 maybe.
they started like to shrink it again.
and then you can easily see
that, the baseline grew.
But even when they were 75% smaller,
I. Then day one or when, day one, when
Rapido got in, you can see, you can still
see that they didn't even reach the 50%,
they didn't shrink it one notch further
because it was not that significant.
like once you, you reduce
75%, you are very happy.
and they saved like in total
more than half a million dollars
per month on compute of RDS.
How exactly that magic happened.
Let's move and see Rapido in action.
Okay guys, so this is the Rapido
console, as you can see it.
Here we have the master dashboard.
As I told you, Rapido master dashboard
will always be focused on showing
you the most pressing issues across
your entire fleet of databases.
So I will see the average query
time across all my databases.
I can always drill down
sort by average duration.
I can see that every line item here
is essentially, the average query
runtime on each database or on
each schema, if you're using my SQL
terminology on, a DB instance, right?
so you can easily see that my demo DB
is by far the most, low or the slowest.
Database in my fleet.
I can drill down and
see a specific queries.
So if I'm gonna sort that by max
duration or, you know what, by
count you can actually see what
is the query that is generating
most of the stress on my database.
So you can see that my demo DB on database
classic models, I'm sorry, on database.
It's already again by Max.
you can see that my demo DB on
database demo actually has a query
that is running for 333 seconds.
Sometimes you cran on one second so we
can actually see that there is like a.
Parallelism issue.
You can see that the query is
select sql calc found Rose.
So this is like a calculation
query, that is taking time, right?
So again, I'm looking
from the bird eye view.
I dive in and see the specific
query on the specific instance
on the specific database that
actually generated all the stress.
You can do the same trick
with locks and blocks, right?
any lock that took place on
my database, you can see here
flat list of all the locks.
When I group by, you can see that
this Postgres database is the one
with the highest amount of locks.
when I go again in group by a locking
thread, you could actually see which
query is generating most of the locks,
and you can see that's a specific
update that is generating most of the
locks across all my database fleet.
So again.
The whole notion is go from the bird eye
view, dive in and see what is the root
cause or what is the most pressing issues.
This morning on my database,
everything you see here is in
context is in context of 12 hours.
I can go and look on 48
or three or whatever.
and as you can see, there is like a
stubborn server here, like out of my.
Entire fleet.
There is one database story.
Let's go back here.
There is one database
here, it's called Demo db.
You can see that it's constantly,
not constantly, but at least for the
last few hours, it ran on 99% CPU.
So we have a CPU spike on that database.
and at this point we wanna
go from a historical view.
To a real time view.
So here I can just navigate
to my instances view.
I can sort by CPU.
And as you can see, dev DB here
is still on 100% CPU utilization.
By the way.
The great thing here, you can
manage Postgres MySQL instances
in the very same pane of glass.
you can see that we have queries
running here two minutes, right?
So it's not only high CPU, but
there are actually performance
issues on that specific box.
I can click.
Drill down and see what is
happening on that specific
database in real time, guys, right?
so this is like refreshing
every three seconds.
Obviously it's modifiable, but currently
it's, refreshed every three seconds.
If I stop grouping by, you actually see
a flat list of all the queries running
on that box right now in real time.
We see like queries of two minutes.
We see query of 1 56.
so we see some issues here.
If I group by again, you can
easily see that it's one query.
That is generating most of the stress
or two queries that are generating
most of the stress on my database.
And, I wanna do something about it, right?
so if I look on that select star, I
can actually see that it's running, but
it's not like the slowest thing, right?
It's not very slow.
On the other hand, the cow
crows are actually what is.
My database, as you can see here, like
at the top, you can, one of the great
things, about Rapid and typically, when
you, explore, performance issues, you
really are, you are really interested, to
see what happened, One hour ago, right?
Or two hours ago.
so using that tool, I can easily go
and navigate back in time and see
what happened one hour, two hours ago.
And I can always go back to life, right?
So if I go back to life, I can
literally select the problem.
You can see with your bare eye
how the problem start, how the
problems started to compound here.
And I can go and look second by
second and keep the, The group by.
And as you can see here, we
had four executions of that.
We in one execution of the select.
if I go five minutes
ahead, we 19 executions.
I go.
Few minutes ahead.
you can see that we have 50, 50 or
47 executions, and then I had 50
executions and so on and so forth.
So you can easily see how the problem
started, like to compound on my database
and build, a real issue here right now.
One of the things that I can do is go
back to real time, pull the trigger.
Kill the query that is generating
the stress on my database from the
very same spot that I had the idea
that something is wrong, right?
So you can easily see how it's
gradually going back to 50 14,
but it'll spike back again.
I know my app, this application
is throwing that query on
my database over and over.
so you can see it's growing back to
16 and 19 and so on and so forth.
So what I wanna do.
Now is to be preventive.
I wanna make sure that issue
is not going to interfere.
I still, and I still see the select star.
I don't like that select star, but we have
like more urgent issues to take care of.
And that's the select SQL Cal found Rose.
So what I'm gonna do now, I can
copy that query text and I can
go to the world of automation.
And guys, this is where.
Any other product in the world, right?
So we show you what's
happening on your database.
We know that you are operational team.
You don't have time to, f around,
yeah, sorry about my French, but
you don't have time to, to f around.
And then what you really have
to do is to solve the issue.
You have to address the
issue right away, right?
So this is where you can see like
the cortex rules and the ability
to deploy preventive rules.
What I wanna do is to limit that query.
Right there.
So this is the name of the
rule, and I can now look on
multiple ways, multiple triggers.
So we have a rule engine here,
rule-based engine that can
do all kind of things, right?
I can look on a query pattern
and I can say whenever someone
is doing a. That query.
Or as a matter of fact, I
don't care about the limit.
I use a wild card here.
I don't care about the table.
So whenever someone is doing
select SQL caulk found row, I
wanna trigger an action, right?
So I'm gonna call the rule limit
SQL caulk found row right now.
I can do it on a specific time of the day.
I can do it 24 7.
Let's keep it 24 7.
and what do I wanna do when that,
sorry, I. Oh, I lost my text.
let me grab that again.
It's still running.
Sure enough.
I'm gonna grab that.
Gonna go back, build a
new rule query pattern.
gonna use wild card on
the limit and on the.
You know what?
Let's forget about the limit.
Like anything, anyone that does
electrical cal, I don't care
if it does limit or not, right?
so I wanna go whenever it's like
that, I wanna go and block it, right?
So when I do block,
this query will not run.
I can block it only on
certain times of the day.
Block it between 7:00 AM and.
6:00 PM or 4:00 PM I can do
it only on weekdays, right?
So if it's like some kind of
a mambo jumbo, oap, analytics
query, I can allow it.
Do it on weekends, during do
it in the middle of the night.
Don't interfere with my business.
This is an o TP database, right?
eh, I can be a bit more, Gentle and I
can say rate limit or throttle, right?
so in that case, let's choose throttle.
eh, let's give this real name limit,
Dave.
Limit steep cock farm grows.
I'm gonna save that guy.
Now it's active between.
We're not in the right time.
So let's enable a rule that I prepared
before and let's disable this guy.
And now guys, I'm gonna go
back to my database, right?
So demo DB still a hundred percent CPU.
I'm gonna drill down.
I'm gonna select that query.
I'm gonna move that message, kill that
query, and let's see what happens.
Now.
Now what I expect to see is that
my database will go back to a low.
Execution amount.
And as you can see, sure enough, it's
running two times in parallel, right?
We have various rules that
you can deploy with Rapido.
Some of it I showed you here.
Some of them are related to controlling
database connections, limiting users.
Limiting tenants.
So you have all kind of activities that
you can do with rapido to mitigate stress.
I can for instance, take that nasty query,
I told you that I don't like that query.
So I can take that query
and say, you know what?
If that's what you
execute, let's cache it.
So using rapido, you can
say Cache that query, right?
I didn't select text.
with me.
Let me copy the text here.
I go to automation.
I go to add a new rule.
Query, query whenever
that query takes place.
use the table based invalidation.
Table based invalidation means
that whenever someone is going to
update the versions table, I will
go and invalidate my cache and make
sure that the data in the cache is
coherent with what's really going on.
So guys, this is.
In a natural, what Rado is all about.
I encourage you to hit me
and ask questions over email,
over Slack, over, LinkedIn.
I'm available in all medias.
I look forward to get your
questions, sending you warm
wishes from New York City.
Take care.
Bye-bye.