Speaker 4: Hello, I'm Srikanth Uddanti,
senior manager at Charles Schwab.
I manage multi-terabyte database
clusters at Charles Schwab.
So today I'm gonna cover the topic modern
distributed databases, its architecture,
DevOps, and operational trade-offs
So the first and foremost, we need
to understand the challenges with
the monolithic databases so that we
can solve the problems when you go
to the real-world modern databases.
So the most of the challenges that
we face with monolithic databases
are high availability, in a sense.
So they can scale vertically
but not horizontally.
So what it leads to is they lead
to single point of failures.
Global distribution.
So the global distribution of the
monolithic databases, they can
lead to latency and consistency
suffer a lot across the regions.
And real-time processing.
In the modern world, all the
applications will receive
millions of transactions per day.
So a vertically scaled platform suffer a
lot with the throughput, and they cannot
process millions of transactions per day.
So now we need to understand these
challenges, and we can discuss
how we are going to solve these
problems with the NoSQL databases
So as part of this session,
I'm gonna cover four topics.
So topic number one,
foundational concepts.
So what is a CAP theorem?
Their replication models
and sharding strategies.
Topic number two, consensus protocols.
So Raft and Paxos algorithms used
for fault tolerance and availability.
So topic number three, DevOps automation.
So what kind of methodologies
that we can use to automate
and manage database clusters?
Topic number four,
security and governance.
Zero trust, certificate authentication,
and distributed key management for
security and governance So to begin with,
we need to understand what CAP theorem is.
So this is the fundamental concept of
building the databases, where it can be
relational databases or NoSQL databases.
This is the fundamental theorem
that we need to understand.
So what CAP theorem stands for?
C stands for consistency, A
stands for availability, P
stands for partition tolerance.
So as we see the Venn diagram on
the right side, so consistency,
availability, and partition tolerance.
So none of the databases can
achieve all three together.
If we build a database, we
need to have a trade-off.
So we can either achieve
consistency, availability, or
consistency, partition tolerance, or
availability, partition tolerance.
So we cannot achieve all three together.
So these traditional databases are DBMS.
They can have consistency and
availability together, but not
partition tolerance So when coming to
the MongoDB or DynamoDB, Cassandra, so
these NoSQL databases, consistency and
partition tolerance can be achieved.
So these databases can be scaled
horizontally, so they can bear
with the partition tolerance.
So they can handle the partition tolerance
So the definition of a
consistency is every write.
For example, a replication factor of two.
So the consistent database, it
guarantees the replication factor.
So when a record is written, so it
makes sure that with a replication
factor two, it makes sure it is
written twice before committing to the
end user Coming to the availability.
So every request receives
a response as part of this.
So none of the user request will go
vain And coming to partition tolerance.
So the system operates despite
there are network partitions.
So the databases are scaled in such a way
that, and designed in such a way that they
can be able to handle network partitions
So how can we build the
databases on top of CAP theorem?
So here we cover replication
models, single leader,
multi-leader, and leaderless.
Single leader.
So to take an example, MongoDB follows
single leader replication strategy.
So all the writes go to the primary node.
So what it means, all the read-- all
the writes hit the same node, and
eventually they go to the replica nodes.
So that is the benefit of single leader,
but the caveat is it creates a bottleneck,
and it's a single point of failure.
So if a primary node is failed all of
a sudden, and if there are any writes
ongoing on and then they are not yet
replicated to the replicas, they are lost.
So we need to handle the edge
cases Next, multi-leader.
So the databases which have
multi-master concept, they can write
simultaneously to the multiple nodes.
So all the partitions are horizontally
scaled and distributed across
all the nodes and can be able
to handle writes simultaneously.
So they enable geo-distributed writes, but
introduces conflict resolution complexity.
Next one, leaderless.
So here in this concept, any
node can accept reads and writes
using quorum-based consistency.
So this architecture maximizes
availability but require careful
tuning of read and write quorums
Sharding strategies.
So there are various sharding strategies.
So range-based sharding, hash-based,
and directory-based sharding.
So range-based sharding it follows
a strategy of splitting the data by
continu-- by contiguous key ranges.
For example, if there are humans, the
scale, their age of one to hundred,
if I would like to retrieve the
people whose age is one to twenty.
So what it does is the range
goes to the same shard.
So that is the benefit of
this range-based sharding.
Hash-based sharding.
So this is, this hash-based
sharding has some of the benefits
of distributing the data across
multiple nodes using a hash function.
To take an example let's take Amazon
and then Amazon receives billions
of orders a day across the globe.
An order ID is unique,
and it can be anywhere.
So f-- so any user, they can search
their orders with their order ID.
When they get into the, their, when
a user logs in and get into his
account, so he can be able to retrieve
all the orders, and they can view
the orders by clicking an order.
So every order has an order ID,
and the order ID can be hash-based.
So it's a unique key, and it can be
hash-based and then the orders are can be
stored anywhere on the nodes and can be
retrieved with the hash-based algorithm.
Next concept is directory-based.
So it uses a lookup table to map keys
to shards So it provides us flexibility.
The lookup table becomes a critical
dependency with this methodology
Next, understanding the protocols.
Raft.
So how do we achieve the consensus?
So here, if we observe this image,
the snapshot, so the critical
part here is the leader election.
So let's take an example of MongoDB.
An operator and administrators can define
the me-- define the methods or define
the principles of how to achieve, how
to elect an, a leader based upon its
priority, based upon its geographical
location we can choose a leader.
So once the leader is ach-- is
elected, so he will be the primary.
And there will be a replication
between the primary and replicas.
So there will be a def-definitely
a replication lag between
the primary and replica.
But what's gonna happen is
whenever a write is written to the
primary, so it writes to the oplog.
So eventually, they will get
replicated to the secondaries.
So the secondaries can be on
the same zone, or it can be in a
different region, different zone.
So it depends upon our our design
strategy, our deployment strategy.
And then once the log is replicated,
so it's gonna commit and apply.
In the sense, if we say a replication
factor of two, then what it means is
that the user will receive a successful
write only after it is written twice.
Meaning it is written to the
primary and it should be written
to at least one secondary
Next one, Paxos versus Raft.
Paxos algorithm or Raft algorithm.
So Paxos algorithm is used by
multi-master a-architectures.
So they're highly flexible, and they're
mathematically proven, but they're a
little difficult to achieve because
of the complexity in the algorithm.
So multi-Paxos is required
for practical log replication.
So what it means is that in a database
of multi-master architecture, so
a record with a replication factor
of two, the record can be written
in parallel both to the two nodes.
So that is the benefit.
That is the fast that we can achieve.
And then it will make sure the write
is replicated the write is written.
A, a record is written to two nodes
before committing to the users
So these are the basic design principles
for the modern NoSQL databases.
And next, we are gonna
discuss DevOps automation.
So how can we automate to avoid
manual intervention for operations?
Infrastructure as a code
for data operations.
So treating database infrastructure
as versioned, so declarative code
eliminates configuration drift,
accelerates environment provisioning, and
enables audit trails for every change.
So Terraform and Pulumi gonna
help to provision the resources.
For example, if I wanna if I'm
gonna deploy the database over
a cloud, so Terraform will help
to provision the resources.
And configuration management.
So once the infrastructure is
provisioned, so how we are gonna set
up the clusters and eventually how
we are gonna manage the clusters.
So Ansible and Helm charts enforce
consistent tuning parameters, and
they help manage the clusters.
Continuous deployment.
GitHub's pipelines automate schema
migrations, rolling upgrades, and canary
inroads with automated rollback gates.
So the GitHub's pipelines will help
achieve continuous deployment strategies
So these are the deployment
patterns for databases.
There can be zone isolation strategies
that can be followed or blue-green
cluster strategy that can be followed.
To take an example, a database
cluster can be built in one region
across the regions in multiple zones.
And then when we perform a maintenance,
so it can be performed in one zone,
one region at a time to make sure
we are to make sure we don't deploy
to all regions and make some mistake
and then disrupt the operations.
So it follows the blue-green strategy,
so where a deployment is performed in one
zone per region a single day or at a time.
So once it is proven that the
deployment is successful, the other
zones can be touched on a different day
This way we can achieve the
successful patterns, successful
deployment patterns Reliability
and scalability through automation.
So the automation helps to avoid manual
interventions and making manual mistakes.
And it can help achieve ninety-nine
point nine nine percent of target
uptime, and there will be zero toil.
And the automated runbooks reduce the
MTTR compared to manual incident response.
So these patterns encode operational
knowledge directly on the control
plane and enable self-healing
behavior without human intervention
Coming to security and governance.
Zero trust infrastructure for databases.
So there are three concepts
that we can discuss here.
So one is mutual TLS.
So what it means is that when a
client application tries to connect
to the database, so it's mutual TLS.
So what it means is that the client will
present a certificate and the database
will authenticate the certificate.
And database will present a certificate
and client will authenticate.
So it's a mutual authentication from both
the client and database point of view.
And the same can be achieved
over the database layer as well.
So there are multiple nodes within
a database cluster, and each
node talk to each other on mTLS.
Next one, identity-based access.
So once the database connection is
established, so how can we achieve
the user can can read or write to the
appropriate collections or tables.
So role-based authentication
will be achieved here, and the
concept of privilege, least
privilege will be used here.
So what it means is that the application
connecting to the database, they
can be able to read or write to
only the tables which they need to.
They will not be having access to
any other tables for which they
don't need write-- read and write.
And finally, audit logging.
Every operation in the sense whatever
the schema changes, whatever an operator
performs a action on the database, all
the admin actions can be written to
the audit log to make sure if s-- if
a mistake happens, how it happened.
So it will help in root cause analysis
So as part of certificate based
authentication, so there will be
certificates, multiple certificates
that need to be created, and there
will be lifecycle management.
So there are certain
something like Venafi.
So they can help certificate management.
So we can create certificates in in
Venafi, and they can be deployed across
the applications and database layer.
So it helps the handshake appropriately.
And distributed KMS.
So what it means is that
key management systems.
So in the modern world or the cloud,
there are secret managers that that are
available to help store the keys safely
and manage them Finally, we need to take
a look at the operational trade-offs.
In the sense, so what
do we want to achieve?
So does our use case needs strong
consistency or high availability?
As we discussed in the first slide
about CAP theorem, so we cannot achieve
both consistency, partition tolerance,
and availability to-- partition
tolerance, both at the same time.
So we need to have a we need to
understand our use case, and based
upon our use case, we need to analyze
whether strong consistency suits me
or high availability suits my use case
So key takeaways as part of the discussion
is understand the CAP theorem and align
your business SLAs accordingly and
understand the use case properly and
identify whether the strong consistency
or high availability suits your use case.
And once the database deployment strategy
is defined, so make sure the operations
are all automated to avoid manual toil.
And make sure you have security built
in across this deployment strategy
and the database architecture to make
sure the-- all the applications, all
the client applications and databases
are securely connected to each other
So that's all for today.
Thank you so much for listening.
Thank you