Speaker 22: Hi, everyone.
I'm Bharath Karumuri, and
thank you for joining me today.
I'm a data science and AI leader
with over twelve years of experience
building analytics, machine
learning, and AI solutions across
healthcare, marketing, and technology
in both Fortune five hundred
companies and startup environments.
A big part of my career has been
working at the intersection of technical
innovation and business impact,
building both scalable data products
and operationalizing ML solutions.
My most recent work has been with
generative AI, RAG pipelines,
and AI governance frameworks, as
most of us today who are trying
to build innovative solutions.
Over time, that work has taught me that
the difference between an interesting AI
demo and a reliable AI product usually
comes down to the system behind it.
So in this talk, I want to focus on the
system, how we connect data pipelines,
database, DevOps, MLOps, governance,
and cloud-native architecture to
build an AI platform that actually
works in production Since this is a
recording and not a live room, I'm
going to keep it very conversational.
Think of this less like a presentation
and more like me sharing battle-tested
lessons with fellow practitioners
over coffee, just with better slides.
With that, let's dive
into the talk for today.
From data pipelines to AI products,
I want to focus on problem many
enterprises are facing right now.
They are very good at building
experiments, but not always as
good as turning those experiments
into dependable business systems.
We are in a moment that nearly
every organization is excited about
machine learning and generative AI.
The challenge is no longer just,
can we build a better model?
The real question is, can we
build a system that is reliable,
observable, governed, scalable,
and actually useful in production?
That's what the talk is about today.
Let's start with the core gap.
Most enterprises have data, most have
models, some even have strong proof
of concepts, but only a smaller group
has production-grade AI that can be
trusted inside real business workflow.
And that gap is actually not
because the data scientists are
not smarter enough or because the
cloud tools are not powerful enough.
It is because the connective layer,
the engineering layer, is missing.
We often have isolated analytics,
unreliable pipelines, and then there is
a governance gap between both of them.
Then we wonder why the AI experiences
falter or feel very brittle.
I like to joke that enterprise AI
often looks amazing in PowerPoint
and little nervous in production.
That nervousness usually comes
from weak plumbing, so there is no
connective tissue between the both.
Here is what we are going
to talk about today.
First, I'll talk about database
DevOps as the backbone of scalable AI.
Then I'll move into resilient cloud-native
pipelines, followed by MLOps practices
that make deployment faster and safer.
After that, I'll cover generative
AI and RAG architecture, because
LLMs are powerful, but they become
much more useful when connected
by governed enterprise data.
Then I'll close with governance, quality,
observability, and what it means to
scale AI for real-time decision-making.
So if you like your AI with a
side of operational discipline,
you're in the right session.
One of the key ideas in the presentation
is that AI systems are only as reliable as
the data infrastructure underneath them.
If your schemas drift silently,
your data contracts are fuzzy,
and your pipelines break without
warning, and model quality is already
compromised before anyone starts
tuning any of these hyperparameters.
Database DevOps brings
software engineering
discipline into the data layer.
That means continuous integration
from data schema versioning
and automated testing.
Instead of treating pipelines like fragile
one-off scripts, we start treating them
like version testable production assets.
In other words, before
asking, " How good is a model?"
We should probably ask, "How
trustworthy is a system that we feed
the model into?" I break database
DevOps for AI into three pillars.
The first is continuous integration for
data, which means automated validation,
schema contract testing, and data quality
gates built into every pipeline change.
The second is schema evolution management.
Enterprise data changes constantly, and if
your downstream features or applications
cannot adapt safely, then every schema
update becomes a mini heart attack.
Version backward compatibility
schema management reduces that risk.
The third pillar is
pipeline observability.
You want end-to-end lineage,
SLA monitoring, and alerting
across every transformation step.
If the system is important
enough to drive decision, it is
important enough to watch closely.
Next, let's move into the
resilient cloud native pipe.
A production pipeline should not
behave like a mystery novel where
the ending surprises everyone.
It should probably be a very
modular, testable, and boring
in the best possible way.
This deck highlights key principles
here: idempotency, modularity, fault
tolerance, and versioned data sets
Idempotency means you can rerun safely.
Modularity means each stage
can be deployed and tested
independently of each other.
Fault tolerance means one bad event
does not bring the whole system down.
And versioned databases or datasets give
you reproducibility when someone asks,
"Why did the model behave differently
last Tuesday?" When someone asks
that question, we should be able to
answer that by getting the previous
version, comparing, and then testing
and pre-- giving them the right answer.
That question always comes on a Tuesday,
by the way, if you're wondering.
Now, this is where MLOps enters.
MLOps closes the loop between
experimentation and production by
treating models as deployable engineering
assets rather than research artifacts.
The presentation calls out model
versioning, automated CI/CD, and
canary or shadow deployments.
Those are critical because they create a
safer path from notebook to production.
Instead of making deployment a
dramatic once-a-quarter event, you
make it a managed, repeatable process.
A model in a notebook
is a science project.
A model with testing, monitoring,
rollback strategy, and
deployment controls in a product.
So now we get to the part where everyone
wants to talk about generative AI.
Large language models are exciting,
but in enterprise setting, they become
truly valuable only when grounded
in clean, governed, reliable data
infrastructure, and they're guarded.
Without that grounding, the
experience can be flashy but shallow.
You may get persuasive answers,
but not dependable ones.
This is why generative AI architecture
should not be discussed separately
from data engineering and governance.
I sometimes joke around saying that LLM
without good enterprise data is like
hiring a brilliant intern and then locking
them in a room with outdated blinders.
You'll still get enthusiasm, but
not always the answers you need
That leads naturally to RAG.
This deck makes a strong case for
why RAG is often a better enterprise
pattern than fine-tuning alone.
Freshness, auditability, cost
efficiency, and governance.
Freshness matters because retrieval
lets you surface up-to-date enterprise
knowledge without retraining every
time your source system change.
Auditability matters because each answer
can be traced back to the source document.
Cost efficiency matters
because fine-tuning every
domain variation is expensive.
And finally, governance matters because
access controls on the data layer can
extend into the AI response layer.
That combination is incredibly powerful.
It means your AI system can be smarter,
cheaper, and more accountable at the
same time, which is a rare triple
win in enterprise architecture.
That's the focus.
Now, a phrase I really like from the
deck is, " You cannot govern what
you cannot observe." That applies
equally to data as well as the models.
Governance here includes data quality
gates, end-to-end lineage, access
and compliance controls, and unified
models and data observability.
In practical terms, that means
validating schemas, checking nulls
and drifts, tracking the data from
raw sources to prediction, masking
PII correctly, and monitoring not just
latency, but also the business impact.
Governance should not be bolted on
after AI system is already live.
At that point, governance
becomes archeology.
It is much better to build it into
the architecture from day one.
Observability across the stack This slide
is especially important because AI systems
really fail with a dramatic explosion.
More often, they fail very quietly.
A feature could go stale, a
distribution shifts, latency could
creep in, accuracy slips, and then
the business trust could erode.
This deck breaks observability into data
layer, feature layer, and model layer.
At the data layer, you monitor pipeline
SLAs, schema drifts And quality scores.
At the feature layer, you
watch distribution shifts,
freshness, and missing values.
At the model layer, you look
at drift, latency, accuracy,
and downstream business KPIs.
Silent failure is the enemy here.
A visible outage is painful, but a
wrong answer delivered confidently
at scale is usually worse.
Think about banking, think about
safety for an automated driving car.
So those are the examples that you
need to think about when you're
thinking about silent failure.
Next, let's shift from batch intelligence
to real-time decision platforms.
The point here is that modern decision
systems increasingly need sub-second
inference, event-driven feature
computation, and seamless integration with
both transactional and analytical system.
That is very different operating model
than a traditional overnight batch report.
You're now supporting kind
of decisions in the motion.
Now just n- not analyzing them
in hindsight after the fact.
And yes, that means your
complete architecture choice
suddenly matters a lot more.
" We'll fix it later," becomes a very
expensive sentence in real-time systems.
So how do we tackle that?
This slide lays out some key
enablers for scalable real-time AI.
Online feature stores, streaming
pipelines, model serving infrastructure,
and hTAP style integration between
operational and analytical systems.
Online feature stores
support low latency lookups.
Streaming pipelines, on the
other hand, keep features fresh.
Model serving infrastructure gives you
auto-scaling endpoints with latency
budget and resilience patterns.
And hTAP integration helps AI
decisions sit inside the operational
workflow instead of living in a
disconnected analytical corner.
The larger point is that every
component needs to be independently
scalable and observable.
One slow dependency can break
the real-time contract from the
whole experience So what should
the audience walk away with?
First, treat data, models, and
infrastructure as version assets.
That mindset shift is foundational
to operational maturity.
Second, database DevOps
is not optional for AI.
CI for data, schema governance,
and pipeline observability
are not nice to have anymore.
They are part of the
production foundation.
Third, governance and observability
must be built in from the start.
If you want AI systems that
are auditable, trustworthy, and
sustainable in production, you cannot
retrofit those qualities later.
Thank you for spending the time with me.
My hope is that this session reframed
enterprise AI a little bit more, not
just a modeling challenge and not
just LLM challenge, but as a systems
challenge