Speaker: Hello everyone,
I am Zeeshan Khan.
Most company think they
have a hiring problem.
They think they have a solution
which is not efficient.
They think it is recruitment
dependent or a recruiter dependent.
They think it's slow.
But in reality, they don't
have a hiring problem.
They have infrastructure problem.
Every hiring interaction
creates data, resume, interview,
engagement, and tons of people work.
But most organizations never
turn that into intelligence.
Today, I'm going to show how
modern data architect transform
hiring from static workflow into
predictive and self-improving system.
I am Zeeshan Khan, HR technology leader,
which help organization convert their
vision into reality through technology
Organization no longer compete
only for the product and pricing.
It's not just about their growth
and pricing at this particular time.
Talent started playing equal
important piece in it, in their
growth, in their innovation.
End of the day, employees
are happy, employee perform
well, will do a better job.
To make that happen, every step in
hiring generate lots of paperwork,
which I mentioned previously,
interaction, and all the data which
we get and store becomes silo.
So despite h- you and the
organization having data,
decision are still very far away.
The real issue isn't a- about
data availability, it's lack
of enabled infrastructure.
You don't have infrastructure,
you don't have an AI.
You don't have AI, you will not
be able to do a proper prediction.
So it become obvious when we look at our
current system that it's not working.
And we think, the organization
think, "We need a new ATS system.
We need a new, better product.
We need a better technology."
But they forget and they
over simplify the process.
But the major thing is, the solid
foundation they need is the data
and it become obvious that we don't
have the data and it cause issue.
So let's talk about that
Current leakage system.
ATS never designed for intelligent.
They are built for compliance.
They are not built for
intelligence, as I mentioned.
They work in silo.
We do a candidate searching, we do a
resume parsing, we do interaction, we
do interview, we do compliance training.
Put every bunch of their data
stored in different places.
All those different places
never talk to each other.
All are stored in a
different kind of database.
All are not defined and structured
together via the system of record.
We have dashboards, we have multiple
reports in our current ATS system, but
the real issues start, no real-time
insight, no predictive analytic.
So what does a modern hiring
system actually look like?
Let's talk about it
If you are able to have five layer,
which I'm able to come up here, if
you define your process in five layer,
if you achieve all those five layer,
you will able to make that happen.
We can think of hiring system
evolving across multiple phases.
So those layers are those.
Starting from very business workflow
tracking, which is administrative
layer, to our optimized and north
star self-optimizing ecosystem.
So let's break it down all layer.
Each layer increase
sophistication, automation,
risk re-remediation, governance.
So one stack another.
Once you build that infrastructure
base, you will have a great system.
You will have a product which work amazing
for you and which is work amazing for your
AI agent, and it will give you a better
predictive and everything will be amazing.
Let's break it down how
actually this happen.
Administrative At first level,
system are purely operational,
which we have to do it, right?
With that is the core value of any task.
They manage tasks.
They track job post, interview,
hire, the basic core ATS.
The basic core administrative
work we need to have.
That's our administrative job.
The ne- next layer will be data
enrichment, which will be our
HRIS system, our ATS system, CRM.
What are they are?
They are the one who are the
binding, who are the connector
between all those things.
They are the one who come up with all
the process and define in one place.
The, they are the one who will
be funneling it on performance.
Still descriptive, not predictive
So let's do third layer,
which will be NLP embedding
Understand intent.
So instead of understanding just using
and filtering the… Based on the data,
reading the data, understand between
the line and put it across multiple way.
Job description, resume, what is there?
They are the bunch of lines of
data, but it should not just be
read it, also understand it ChatGPT.
You talk as an, as a human person.
Whatever you're thinking about
it, you code it, you write
it, prompt it, and hit Enter.
It analy-analyzes and give
you the predictive answer.
Same thing is that we
are talking about here.
Skill graph.
Once you have the job
description, job profile, please
assign skill on those jobs.
Please assign and assess
skill of your employees.
What it will do, it will
make your system more robust.
Now you have a system which connect
with skill-based organizations, connect
with job, connect with the operational
task, connect with the employee.
It help us… It help the
organization with internal mobility.
It help the team between
the career pathing.
So that is a very important piece, which
is the fourth sk- layer in the system.
Vector search.
Think about this as the one in which
you can do search based on anything.
It's not just the keyword or the
filter, keyword-based search,
it's a thought-based search.
Let me give you an example.
Instead of you just go ahead and
search for, "I need someone in
New York," or, "I need someone in
this area with Python language,"
or with product manager job title.
That will gi-give you the result,
but the result are very superficial.
I have to correct myself,
not very superficial.
It will be more based on those
filter which are defined.
Instead of that, if you think about that
I am looking for someone with the product
knowledge, someone who have the title, but
at the same time have a understanding and
to an implementation of product, that will
give you a more ca- skilled candidate,
and thus, the result will be more
actual accurate, which you are looking
for that particular job description.
So that's a vector search.
But understanding is just the first step
Predictive hiring is something
which we all targeting for.
Now system can predict outcome.
Once you define those five layer, the
next goal will be predicting hiring
Your organization able to secure a
new project, and you are going to
start that project in next six month.
And you quickly realize that
you don't have the skill.
How you realize it?
System tell you that we have won the
product, we have run-- won the project,
we have this many tasks which we
need to perform in next three year.
And based on your database, based
on your AI agent will go in the back
end and the agent will read how many
skill we have in the organization,
how many resource are currently
available, and where is the skill gap.
So that's a workforce planning.
Where it come, then it predict
we have a gap of this many skill.
Now agent will go back, do a search
for those skill which they need.
It predicted this for this project, we
have this many skill resources need.
Go in the database of current
employees, search for it.
If you have internal mobility
option, look into internal candidate.
If you have the option of
in candidate pool, look into
the current candidate pool.
If not, create a new job requisition,
post it, and started looking for in
your job portals That is the great
outcome every organization looking for.
Who is likely to accept my opportunity?
Who-- Where is hiring getting delayed?
So that we can optimize it,
make the process improvement.
What skill will be needed for now, for
six month, for a year, and for ten year?
This real-time data pipeline and
continuous model update will make
your organization very productive,
make the daily life very great.
So if the candidate is facing issue,
if candidate is not interacting
with you, it will signal you out.
What are the issue which you
are fa- facing in the product?
It will error you out.
You read those and make the
improvement And let's talk
about the most important stage.
And again, this is something
everyone will need.
Self-optimizing talent ecosystem.
This is where the AI is
doing amazing thing nowadays.
Reading himself, reading the data,
and optimizing the performance itself.
Hiring become a continuous
learning system.
Every decision feed future decision.
The system optimize itself across
hiring, retention, workforce planning,
and it give you a better result
and performance will increase.
Whenever we are talking about
AI, it create a new challenge,
especially in talent acquisition.
Governance.
Governance become very
critical at this phase.
Let's talk about the core infrastructure
which is enabling this, and then
we'll go back to governance again
The two thing which make your
life easy or which help you
to become the self-optimized
learning system is skill graph.
As I mentioned previously, assign
the skill on job profile, assign
the skill on the infras-- sorry.
Assign the skill on the employees, assess
them, assign the skill on your task.
Assign the skill on your learning.
That will give you the path
and easy accessibility to work,
easy accessibility to predict.
Let think if you have a system which
will read that for you to be go
into a next phase of your career,
you need to have this many skill.
For this skill, based on your
skill, these are the learning path.
Having a learning path for each
employees tailored for them.
If you are a hundred thousand
employee company and you have a
hundred thousand career path, it's
impossible if you use any tool.
But with AI, we can make it happen.
Because the database, the infrastructure
you build have that information, and
it will tailored s-career path for
everyone based on your requirement,
based on the skill which you don't
have, based on the skill which you
have and that your career interest is.
Internal mobility.
Organization will able to
search the candidate internally
rather than going outside.
Retention.
The most difficult topic is retention.
The most organization facing is there's
no way we can reduce the retention rate.
You can retain it, the employees by
giving them the opportunity internally,
m-giving them an innovative way to
work, g-creating a flex team where
they can work on one area, when they
are done, move to a different area.
So the skill graph will do that.
Skill model will help you with that.
Vector database Powerful, simple
search Success depend on data quality,
real-time update, and ability to explain.
Let me give you a very basic example.
An electrician could be
matched to a technician role.
They have a similar skill,
maybe they have a similar
certification, but they can do it.
So system will read it and do it.
Instead of searching for solar role, solar
technician role, that result will be very
narrowed down and maybe not a correct one.
So the system-- Sorry, vector database
will make that happen, and it make that
happen in a such a way like product
manager surface candidate, we were able
to find by just writing, "I'm looking
for someone with the ownership across
the system which were developed it
from a design to implement to output."
So if those kind of is your use cases,
those kind of something which you are
able to achieve, you will make that
happen But the thing which will cause
the issue here will be p-poor models.
You need to have a good data in it.
You need to do a proper indexing on
the, your database so that the data
is stored and properly formatted and
defined, to a categorized format.
And you need to explain them
and index them properly.
To make this work in real time This is
the option which we are going to follow.
Event-driven architecture.
Mo-modern system operate using
event-driven architecture.
Instead of batch work, batch job, decision
happen on the go because they are the
one who take the data real-time and make
the system work and move things easily
Candidate disengagement service.
High priority candidates.
Labor shortage.
Let's assume if you see that the
candidate is losing interest in this
job, you will get a notification and
because you will get a reasoning behind
it, so your TA can easily fix it.
And the candidate which you are going
to lose is now ready to and accepted
an offer The life of TA becomes so easy
if you're able to predict it upfront.
High priority candidate.
From a s- candidate pool of thousands,
it will give you top five in one search.
Labor shortage.
If we d- predict what is the labor
shortage in your current organization
and outside of your organization, you can
predict and hire f- in advance or do a
research in advance and block them so that
your project will be available on time.
Diversity imbalance.
Monetizing that will
also cause so much issue.
So all this can be predicted in a
real-time basis, and the outcome will be
a great productivity for an organization.
But this will come with great risk.
All this will a- able to happen because
of AI, but AI come with the big risk.
Governance.
Governance is one thing which
doesn't go if we are talking
about talent acquisition.
AI system in hiring must be tightly
governed As I mentioned initially, all the
ATS system are built first on the concept
of governance and then built on top of it.
Something similar we have
to think here as well.
Bias detection Understand
why decision happen.
If AI is giving you some decision,
ask it, and we-- you need to see
why the AI agent give that answer
with the proper explanation.
You ask me for a product manager, look,
who can help us-- with me with the
solar planning, solar product planning.
Then it will mention that this particular
candidate, which I'm referring, have
th-this degree, have experience in
solar planning, is a electrician,
have worked on this, and give all
the background story to prove it.
That's a good system.
That will happen if you have
that, all that option enabled
in our vector database.
Remember we talk about that.
So all that is possible, and we
have to have this explainability
option in the system.
Human oversight.
I cannot emphasize more.
Human oversight is must.
Is must.
AI is a supporter.
AI is not a replacement of a human.
So never think AI will
replace human in this area.
It is supporting the human to make a
better call, and you have to keep the
human in loop in all the processes.
That will make your life very easy.
Model accounting.
Validating accuracy and compliance.
You will have to audit your
system, make it accurate.
That will amplify your operation.
That will make your life very easy.
Now, with governance in mind,
wh-which bring us to collaboration
As I mentioned, the future of hiring
is infrastructure plus judgment.
The goal is not to replace recruiter
with our AI agent, but to augment
them with AI processed scale, human
provide judgment, governance, fairness.
Just buying the n- new ATS system
will not going to help you.
Just think about a new HRIS
team will not going to help you.
The system is not the only
thing which causing the issue.
The thing which you need is better data,
better decision, strong governance.
As I mentioned, strong governance and
human acco-accountability So what we have
learned from the enterprises development?
You need to have better data,
better decision, strong governance,
and human accountability.
Human in the loop
Three things stand out to
me when I implement this in
my previous organizations.
Data quality matter more than anything.
Garbage in, garbage out is real.
That's why it's keep we
hearing this term everywhere.
Yes, garbage in, garbage out is real.
So data quality matter.
That is the most important thing,
just as important as governance So
data quality, modernize incremental.
So layering the data for infrastructure
in such a way data is stored
in a proper structure format.
Otherwise, your system will be
not be optimized, keep buffering.
You have to have your data in a proper
layered improvement stabilized properly.
Governance.
Data quality, properly
storing of a data, governance.
Governance we have
discussed multiple time.
Enhanced govern-governance will always
make the organization more improve and
help you to im-- optimize your solution.
Building that trust, that's the most
important-- another important piece.
We have dashboards, we have the real-time
data, but leaders are-- don't believe it.
So what is the point of building
a system when no one use it?
So building a trust is very important.
And how you can gain it?
If you give them the explainability,
which we talk about in our previous
slide, give the reasoning behind it.
We are recommending you, and this is
the data to point, and this is the
data to to support those evidence.
This is the evidence to support this.
So those things are important.
Once you have imp-- trust in your
data, you can make a better decision
very quickly, and it will help
your organization to grow fast
The future of predictive AI.
AI in hiring will increase definitely.
This is the area where
we interact the most.
This is the area where human
connection and networking is the key.
We are hearing from last decades.
But right now, this-- in this
area, we have the most agents.
From hiring, from predicting,
from parsing to scheduling, we
have multiple agents available.
System must be auditable, but these
are the thing you have to consider.
The next generation system with
enterprise have a better governance,
transparency and accountability, and
which will make your life very easy.
The architect decision will be driven
by compliance, not just by capability.
So let me leave you
with one final thought.
The future of hiring is
infrastructure and judgment.
The-- It's not just the
better software, it's better
infrastructure and better decision.
Driven by both data and human judgment.
Human way have to be there in the
loop to make a better decision.
Thank you, everyone.