Speaker 13: Hey everyone,
and welcome to CON42.
I'm Muthumalliyappan Ramanathan,
senior software developer at DoorDash.
Today we are going to explore a
critical architectural frontier
in modern data engineering:
operationalizing semantic consistency.
We will look at how we can apply a
robust DevOps framework to achieve
truly reliable cross-engine analytics.
Let's dive in The multi-engine reality.
The reality of modern landscape is that we
no longer live in a single engine world.
To satisfy strict latency SLAs,
massive data volumes, and high diverse
workloads, organizations run multiple
distributed compute runtimes in parallel,
such as Spark, Trino, and Snowflake.
We choose these because different
engines excel at different query shapes.
For example, ETL pipelines, ad hoc
exploration, and real-time dashboards
all favor distinct runtimes.
But this architectural flexibility
introduces a massive hidden challenge.
SQL compatibility is not always
similar to semantic consistency.
Here is the core problem we face.
SQL compatibility does not
equal semantic consistency.
Just because a query successfully
compiles and executes across every engine
in your stack does not mean it returns
the exact same answer on every engine.
This is a silent risk that fundamentally
threatens data reliability.
So where does this divergence hides?
It hides in the subtle intentional
design choices of the engines themselves.
Let's look at what are those.
First, type handling.
Implicit casts, numeric precision, and
integer overflows differ across engines.
Second, null semantics.
How null values propagate through joins
and aggregations varies drastically.
Third, aggregation behavior.
Simple things like floating point
summation, order or distinct, count
edges c- count edge cases diverge.
And finally, optimizer decisions.
Query rewrites can silently alter
row inclusion or result ordering.
Over time, these compound into
massive analytical drift The
same query, three answers.
Imagine feeding this exact same SQL
string into Spark, Trino, and Snowflake.
Because of the discrepancies we
just discussed, you can easily end
up with three different answers.
This creates silent data
reliability failures.
The worst part, standard SQL
linting and basic schema tests
will completely miss it So what's
the core concept of the framework?
It's the analytical intent.
To solve this, we need an innovative
shift in how we build data pipelines.
We must introduce analytical intent
as a first-class abstraction.
Instead of writing engine-specific SQL
syntax, we define what the query is
supposed to mean entirely independent
of the underlying execution layer.
This relies on three pillars.
First, intent definition, where we declare
logical meaning in engine-agnostic terms.
Second, a semantic layer that translates
the intent using deterministic rules.
And third, validated execution to
guarantee semantic equivalence on whatever
target engine we choose Let's discuss
about the canonical semantic layer.
This brings us to the
heart of the framework.
Here, logic is defined exactly once.
Engine-specific dialects are
deterministically generated from
this layer, meaning humans never
author dialect-specific SQL directly.
This completely eliminates
handcrafted query drift and preserves
a single source of logical truth
CI/CD integrated validation workflows.
This is the crucial part of the framework.
A semantic layer alone is not enough.
We have to operationalize it.
Semantic guarantees must be rigorously
enforced at commit time rather than
discovered late on a production dashboard.
Let's look at how we build this
into a modern DevOps pipeline.
Embedding validation in the pipeline.
By shifting left, every single code
commit or schema change triggers
an automated validation workflow.
The pipelines runs a semantic diff
and executes a cross-engine dry run.
An equivalence assertion test guarantees
the outputs match before allowing a merge.
This ensures semantic drift is caught
as a PR blocker, not a production data
incident Semantic testing strategies.
Let's discuss the four quest--
four core testing strategies.
Traditional data testing validates
data shape and freshness, but semantic
testing validates actual meaning.
We implement four primary strategies.
Equivalence tests to assert
identical results across engine
pairs using a reference dataset.
Null boundary tests to
evaluate statistically rare but
semantically critical null paths.
Precision regression tests to keep
floating point aggregations within a
strict tolerance using engine upgrades.
And translation snapshot tests
to pin generated SQL and detect
unintended compiler changes.
Now let's see some of the observability
patterns for semantic drift.
Of course, data production, data
protection shouldn't stop at merge time.
Production pipelines require continuous
runtime observability to catch drift
before it corrupts downstream metrics.
We do this by simultaneously
executing queries across engine
pairs, comparing result fingerprints,
alerting on metric divergence, and
using lineage-aware attribution to
instantly isolate the root cause.
Trust as an operational property.
Ultimately, data reproducibility
and trust are not operational
features you simply tra-track on.
They are core operational properties that
you must actively enforce through robust
process engineering, automated tooling,
and a cultural commitment to semantic
rigor Operational resilience outcomes.
When data team adopt this framework,
the outcomes are highly measurable.
We achieve absolute reproducibility,
meaning queries yield identical answers
regardless of the execution runtime.
We see early detection, blocking
semantic drift in CI, and saving
hundreds of hours on incident response.
And finally, we establish pristine
governance with an auditable
version-controlled repository
of our core business logic.
Let's see the framework in summary.
To summarize the framework, we decouple
logic via a canonical semantic layer,
enforce equivalence through CI/CD
validation, and continuously monitor
runtime drift with observability.
This enables data organizations
to confidently adopt heterogeneous
engines, treat semantic guarantees
as code artifacts, and execute
seamless engine migrations
without sacrificing correctness.
So what are the key takeaways?
As we wrap up, I leave you
with three key takeaways.
SQL compatibility is
necessary but not sufficient.
Engine design details cause silent drift.
Treat analytical intent as a
first-class abstraction by separating
your logic from your dialect.
Move your semantic guarantees directly
into your CI/CD pipeline Thank
you so much for your time today.
This framework has fundamentally shifted
how we look at multi-engine reliability,
and I would love to open the floor to hear
your thoughts and answer any questions.
Let's discuss.
Thank you.