Speaker 25: Hi, my name's Jason Lester.
I'm a cloud architect at Capgemini,
and I'm here today to talk about
doing more with cloud APIs.
So I think the first thing I want
to say is, what do when I talk
about a cloud environment in the
context of this presentation?
So a cloud environment is a virtualized
platform provided by some of the
major hyperscalers, Amazon, Azure.
And what they do in order to allow
you to manage that environment is
provide you with a simple, easy-to-use
web-based interface that allows you
to quickly get up and running with the
environment, deploy compute instances,
deploy databases, configure networks.
The interface is designed to be intuitive.
It's designed to allow you to
get up and running very quickly.
And yes, you can go and do training
and learn about more complex features.
But what they've done is they
have specifically built that
interface to make it easy to use.
There's drop-downs, there's calendars
and various other functionality
to make your life easier as
a user of the cloud console.
However, what they've done in the
background is they have generally designed
a bunch of APIs which do the actual grunt
work of creating an instance or creating
a network, and then built the console
on top of it During this presentation,
I'm gonna give you a few examples.
My examples are mainly gonna be around
Oracle Cloud, 'cause that's what I use.
However, all of the concepts of
the presentation are completely
valid for AWS, Azure, and GCP.
Please bear with me if those are the
clouds of your choice, then this is
all still relevant to you So I talked
about APIs, and the APIs tend to
have more functionality, but what the
vendors have done is they've simplified
the use of them through the console.
So not all of the features of the
API are available in the console.
The great benefit about an API
is that with a bit of coding, you
can daisy chain APIs together.
I think about it like Legos or
something like that, where you
can take two components, put them
together to make something that is
more complex than either of them.
A great example is use an API to get
some information about a database,
then use another API to take that
information to build another database.
The hyperscalers have provided
program interfaces for Bash, Python,
Java, .NET framework, and a whole
bunch of other things to allow you
to quickly get up to speed using the
programming language of your choice.
However, bear in mind that the APIs
are very dangerous and there's a lot of
things you can do with the APIs, as I
said, that you can't do in the console.
Not only that, because you don't have that
visual representation of what's going on,
sometimes it's possible to get lost in the
data and accidentally cause damage that
you weren't expecting simply because you
didn't have that visual representation.
So before you use the APIs, be very
careful and be aware of what you're doing.
I would suggest trying to do things in
a, an environment with a lower level of
security so that you don't delete your
production environment, for example
APIs, the most common type of API is
probably a REST API, which is a web-based
interface, and you can invoke web-based
APIs using products like Postman.
Bear in mind that the biggest
challenge with REST-based APIs
tends to be authentication.
So in the case of Oracle,
there is an authentication API
which will generate a token.
So you have to generate a token, then
you use that token to then be able
to invoke the next part of the API.
So you have to pass a lot of information
to that authentication API to get it
to… Every time you want to do it,
you've got to invoke that, you've got to
generate that token, and you've got to
generate a token every time you use it.
The vendors have thought about this,
and so what they've done is they've
created compiled versions of the API,
which they call the CLI, which does
a lot of the complex things for you.
So in that case, that one there OCI
compute instance launch, which will
create a new compute instance in
Oracle Cloud, and you don't have to
pass any authentication information.
It's all done.
You will have generated a config
beforehand, and it just uses that
config over and over again, which
makes your invoking of that command
line interface significantly
easier So what exactly is the CLI?
As, as I said, the CLI is a combined,
in this case, Linux binaries, so you
could stick them onto a, an Oracle
Linux box, a Red Hat Linux box, CentOS.
It works on most of the
main Linux variants.
There's also Windows versions available,
and those are available for across all
of the cloud providers not just Oracle
Cloud, which I've got the demonstration
of here, but Azure, Amazon, they all
have their own command line interface.
The idea is that you can simply
invoke, and this one, OCI compute
instance list will list all of the OCI
compute instances in a compartment.
You pass it a bunch of parameters,
and in this case, it returns
all of the data in JSON format.
So there's a lot of metadata there, a
lot of data that you can't see in the
console, a lot of information that you
don't get available in the console or
at least not as easily in the console,
and it's all available here in JSON
format But what information can you get?
You get the basic, same sort
of basic information that you
can get through the console.
In an inventory, how many
databases have I got?
How many databases are in a compartment?
How many compute instances
are in that region?
What were the build dates?
What's the status?
Statistics like CPU memory.
And you can also get much more
complex statistics, performance
statistics, what, what's my CPU doing?
And cost statistics, very important things
which you can't often see in the consoles.
You have to dig around a bit to get
that sort of information So I've got
an API or a command line interface.
I want to extract the data.
What am I gonna do with it?
There's a couple of
things you can do with it.
As I said, you can use the APIs as
building blocks and create a program
that will extract some data, do something
with it, pass it on to the next part.
You can load it into a database
and this is what I did there.
So I-- we created a table called OCI
instances in a database, and we extracted
all of the data about the OCI instances
in our tenancy and put it into a database.
And there's lots of other things you can
do and lots of other reasons you can do
it, but the great thing is once you've got
that database into a database, once you've
got that data into a database, you can
then start doing clever things with it.
For example, pointing AI at it to
analyze trends or to analyze changes.
And the, there are other interesting
uses, things that the console doesn't do.
So in Oracle, for example security
is managed by we create a group,
you create a policy statement, allow
group tester A to manage compute
instances in compartment main test,
and then you assign a user to a group.
And so by looking at user, I can
see what groups they're in, but I
can't see what permissions those
groups inherit without going through
all of those policy statements.
However, if I want to extract all of that
data, I can stick it into a database, and
by then doing a joins on a few tables, I
can say, "Show me exactly what privileges
this user has in that database or in
that tenancy or in that compartment."
Not only that, because we now have it in
a database, we can do clever audit things
with it that you can't do in a console.
So for example, if I'm scraping
the metadata about what permissions
people have on a regular
basis, I could do a what if.
What ha-- what permissions did
this person have last month?
Now, all of that information is available
in the console, but what you would have
to do is you have to see what permission
they have today and then backtrack through
all of the audit changes to see what
permissions that person had last month.
But if you store it in a database,
you can do that analysis.
So if, for example, you're having to
do some forensic analysis on, "Hey,
there was a change made a month ago.
Can someone tell me who had access to
this system a month ago?" It's really
easy to find that out because you've
got all the information in a database.
And remember, once it's in a database,
we've got a lot of other tools that
will allow us to play around with it for
example, AI On top of that, what we did
was we used a tool called Oracle APEX.
Some of you may be familiar with it,
Oracle Application Expe- Express.
And we built some applications on top
of that metadata, which provide us with
a much more user-friendly, and in some
case, developer-friendly interfaces.
So one of the big things that a lot
of our customers want to do is they
wanna shut down environments when
they don't use it, and you can save a
significant amount of your cloud spend
by shutting non-production environments
down when they don't use them.
So I might decide to shut the dev
environment down at 6:00 PM every week
day, and leave it down on Saturday
and Sunday, restart it at eight
o'clock on the morning on a weekday.
But then a developer comes in
and wants to work on a Saturday.
We could give the developer the ability
to start and stop the environment
through this interface without them
really having to understand the
technical criteria of being able
to start and stop that environment.
Not only that, we could
include workflow processes.
So perhaps to start the environment, they
would need to… It would send an email to
a manager to say, "Can you please approve
that user Bob can start this environment
on a Saturday?" And that will cost £100
to run it on a Saturday, for example, and
the, somebody can make a decision on that.
Not only that, you can do more
complex things with start and stop.
So for example, if you have a database
and an application server, you always
want to start the database first and
then the application server, and you
usually want to shut down the application
server first and then the database.
And by creating hierarchical groups,
again, this is just metadata in a
database, we can define the order in which
multiple environments can start and stop.
So the database starts, and it doesn't
try and start the application until
it has confirmed that the database is
up and running, and similarly won't
try and stop the database until the
application server is already down
Okay hopefully you've got some
useful information and some ideas
on how you can use more APIs.
There's lots of information out there.
As I said, I did a lot of my
examples were about Oracle.
Oracle isn't the only cloud vendor
out there, and every cloud vendor
has a command line interface
and a whole series of APIs.
I, I've included some things in my blog.
So if you go to
jasonlesterdba.wordpress.com, I talk
about how to use those APIs and how
to get the m- the information out.
Again, it's very Oracle-centric,
so I apologize for that.
But it might give you some ideas if
you're m- more interested in Azam- Amazon.
And if anyone wants more information,
please feel free to reach out to me
either by email or you can attach
to me in LinkedIn and I'm more
than happy to answer any queries.
So thanks for your time today and
enjoy the rest of your conference.