Speaker 9: Hi, everyone.
My name is Renato Lozo, and today I
would like to talk to you about five
lessons from playing with serverless
database for the last five years.
So-
My serverless database journey so far.
I've been playing with AWS technology
for the last fifteen years.
That doesn't make me an
expert, that just make me old.
But I've been playing with serverless
databases on AWS for quite a few years
now, and my journey has been like that.
That's not the CPU of my database,
that's not the ACU of my database,
that's my happiness, my up and down
with serverless technology on the cloud
I say that I like to play
with serverless databases.
I actually mean really playing.
About four years ago, I presented a
session at the re:Invent in Vegas,
where I tried to do- draw the New York
City skyline using Aurora Serverless
v2, and that's what I achieved.
Why did I try to do that?
The idea was to show that with
a database that is serverless,
you really have elasticity.
So what you consume is really
predictable according to what you do.
So that's what I tried to achieve, and
that was not the only time I tried to play
with elasticity on serverless databases.
This is a Tour de France.
I love cycling, and this is using
DynamoDB, trying to see if I could
replicate one of the most famous tops
of the Tour de France using DynamoDB.
Let's go back to our main topic.
Elasticity has been a topic for not
just the last five years, not since AWS
introduced some serverless of features.
I've been playing with RDS for over
a decade, and the challenge to scale
the database has been always there.
You always have the problem that
you don't always want to have the
database always available for peak
load overprovision, or risk that at
ten PM, I'm not saying the usual two
AM, either at ten PM is quite annoying
if your database is saturated and y-
you-- it doesn't automatically scale up.
So this is how I did it a few years ago.
I was just using the command line
and some Bash scripts, actually
some Python as well, and tried
to just scale using CloudWatch.
So you monitor your instance, your
Aurora instance, your RDS instance,
and you scale it up and down
according to certain metrics that
I will call it the how to scale…
the poor how-to scaling.
Of course, that introduce some downtime,
of course, has some risks, but that's how
you can do it to automate your scale up
and down to according to your capacity
But I've been playing for really now
over five years with what Amazon calls
serverless database, and I've learned a
few lessons there, and I would like to
share them with you today But the key
message is that what we are gonna try to
cover today is that serverless database
remove the capacity management, but
they don't remove database engineering.
We'll see th- what that means in a second.
So first lesson, serverless
is just an adjective.
What do I mean by that?
Let's just start with what is serverless?
I don't want to go through what
is ser- serverless database.
Yeah.
Probably scale down to zero is
one of the requirement usually.
A managed database, I don't have to
pass the operating system hopefully.
I pay for what I use.
Yeah there are different
definition, different constraints.
But even in the name Amazon in
the last few years have introduced
different services that you can call
serverless in the database space.
If you think about that, the very first
one was as Aurora Serverless v1, the
GA in two thousand and eighteen, and
that's basically an upgraded version
of my simple auto-scaling script.
Was doubling the capacity
every single time.
That's now deprecated,
it's out of question.
But that was the very first
database serverless that ma-
managed MySQL and PostgreSQL
database that was called serverless.
On the same year, it
was DynamoDB On-Demand.
Note, there's no serverless
tag there, it's just Dynamo.
And that was Dynamo On-Demand,
you pay for the request you do,
and that's purely serverless.
It's there today as well.
It's a bit more expensive,
but it provides what you want.
You don't have to decide up front how
much capacity you want for your tables.
You just pay for what you use.
Great.
Then there are things like Amazon
Timestream, two thousand and
twenty, and go on and so on.
I like to highlight that Serverless
v2 that went GA in two thousand and
twenty-two in April, took one and a half
year to go from preview to GA. And that
highlighted… I like that not because
guys, developers at AWS are lazy, but
because scaling in a transparent way as
a relational database is a big challenge.
There were a couple of years, two
thousand and twenty-two, twenty-three,
when serverless was the main word,
the buzzword in the cloud world.
So AWS was attaching that word to any
scalable service, saying that it was
serverless with big argument about
scale to zero, doesn't scale to zero.
And actually, even the Serverless v2
took a couple of more years to reach the
point that it can really scale to zero.
Last year, probably now we are in a
AI buzz, Amazon queue, then no queue,
new names, kilo, whatever else.
So the serverless word disappeared a bit.
So new services start to have
Amazon DSQL that doesn't have
serverless in the name at least.
So Don't argue what is serverless
just according to the name.
Some services that are called serverless
but don't scale to zero, so they are not
really technically serverless database.
DocumentDB serverless doesn't
scale down to zero, actually.
And there are, if you think about that,
some service that AWS introduced many
years ago, the foundational service of
AWS that you pay for usage, you can store
data, and you can call them serverless.
They were like Amazon S3, SQS.
That's where the word, the magic word
was simple instead of serverless.
And even Amazon Athena has been
there for a decade now, and
is a… You can use SQL on S3.
You pay for what you use.
So technically you can build a serverless
engine perform your SQL queries there
without having the word serverless.
So don't think too much
about the serverless word, if
something is serverless or not.
Just think if it's elastic and if it
achieves what you need to achieve.
Now, lesson number two:
storage is underrated.
What do I mean by storage underrated?
It's actually, two very different things.
The first one is pretty obvious.
It's easy to explain.
If you look at the marketing compare, if
you look at Aurora Serverless v2, that's
how AWS introduce and advertise it today.
It says, "Aurora Serverless v2 scales
instantly to s- support even the most
demanding application, delivering up
to ninety percent cost saving compared
to provision for peak capacity."
Ninety percent is whatever you want it is.
It could be, you could claim
ninety-five, ninety-nine.
Why not ninety-nine point nine?
It really depends on your use case.
If you think you have an ava- a website
that scales crazily, has a peak load
once a year, I don't know, I love
running, so marathons events, for
example, probably you save a lot if
you just do it serverless and you don't
provision the entire year for peak
load, but that's a bit unrealistic.
And what I mean is that when you think
about Amazon and Lambda function,
yes, you can think about the cost
of the Lambda service, of the CPU.
But when you think about serverless in
term of stor- or in term of databases,
you have to think that CPU is only
one of the component of your database
This is a production database in the
last few years that I've managed.
Those are monthly costs for
CPU, storage, and backup.
As you can see, going up, storage
and backup now exceed compute.
And when I think where I have to
optimize, where I have to work, I
have to work on how to optimize the
storage, backup, better handling.
And that's simple GP3.
I'm not even using fancy
storage, more expensive storage.
That's what you get.
So don't overthink about CPU and
serverless because the storage is
there, you pay for it, and it might
be that the serverless component of
the CPU is not your main problem.
But that's not the main reason when
I say that storage is underrated.
I have to do a little demo that
I might do in a second, but this
is the backup cost over time.
You can see that the backup costs tend
to go up because my application is very
successful, and the costs keep going up.
I might do some optimization sometime,
optimize table at the table to reduce
them, but there's still a cost.
But that's not the main reason I
say that storage is underrated.
So let's do a super simple experiment.
Let's take three different databases.
Let's take Aurora Serverless v2 with a
minimum of half ACU, so the minimum you
can do without scaling entirely to zero.
Aurora provision using the r8g large,
so the very last generation available.
Cool.
Very same instance
class for RDS for MySQL.
And I allocate even four hundred
gigabyte of storage on RDS just to make
sure that I have the best default IOPS
I can have on a GP3 default volume.
So now I want to do a very simple test.
In those three databases, I want to
insert a hundred thousand record.
You can insert one
million, whatever you want.
I just want to do it one at
a time in a single thread.
It's a component, of course, so pure SQL.
And I'm using the default configuration.
I don't want to tune
anything in my database.
That's cool.
Simple game.
So how I'm gonna do it?
I can do it from the client, MySQL client.
I can use a JDBC driver.
I can… But I don't want
to intervene from outside.
I just do it even simpler.
Let's create a procedure.
Let's call it Renato demo.
That just loops hundred thousand
times and insert the record.
I just put some random value there
just to make sure that the value is
not the same for every single record.
And let's run it.
My procedure is gonna take time to insert
that hundred thousand record one by one.
Very cool.
How long do you think it's gonna take?
Milliseconds, seconds, hours?
In ideal world, in a serverless
world, I would say it should be
instantaneous because I would
like to just pay for usage.
So I would like to say scale up as
much as you p- can." But reality is
behind there's still an engine, so
it's probably s- gonna take some time.
But Let's see how long it's gonna take.
I would love to do a quick demo,
but we don't have the time.
So let's see the numbers.
Here is the main reason I'm
saying that storage is underrated.
Aurora storage architecture
matter much more than serverless.
So Aurora is a fork, is optimized for S3.
In the Aurora provision,
it takes two, three second.
In a serverless v2, three, four
seconds to insert 100,000 record.
How long does it take for RDS?
Five minutes.
Can I reduce that changing
a bit of configuration?
Yeah, to two minutes to a
minute maybe, but I'm not going
down to couple of seconds.
Is that the real difference
between the two databases?
Not really.
My use case is pretty insignificant.
There's no real use case, no shopping
cart, no nothing, where you really
insert the record at the database layer
without any latency from the client.
So that's a bit unrealistic, but that
shows you anyway in a counterintuitive
way that we shouldn't think too much
about the difference between provision
and serverless, and think sometime a
bit more about what kind of storage we
are gonna use, how it's gonna store--
how our storage is gonna perform.
That's much more significant.
And yeah, that has been done using
the latest version of the serverless
that they call Generation 4.
That has been even r- has a faster
ramp up, but still it takes seconds
to insert the record, and it's
still less it's not as fast as the
provision one for a large instance.
Anyway, so again, lesson number
two, storage in most cases
matter much more than CPU.
While when I go to the coffee machine or
I go to a conference, I hear people just
talking about CPU Number three, cost.
Cost for serverless need a crystal ball.
And that's not because AWS or any cloud
provider are evils and they want to
charge you more than what you expect.
It's just that first problem you
have is if you don't know how your
workload performs on a serverless
database, try to forecast ACU or
DCU, whatever unit your database is
using, by just using the baseline of
your provision cluster is useless.
So just don't take that provision
cluster and say, "Oh, I'm moving
to serverless, so I can predict
how much I'm gonna save or how much
I'm-- more I'm gonna spend in CPU."
It's not gonna work like that.
The reason is, this is an example using
my Athena that we mentioned before, just
to check the component in my billing.
For a single instance, for a
single cluster, I have over
one thousand component in one
month, in month of thirty days.
And that's because you
really pay for what you use.
So there's CPU, there's data
traffic, there's multi AZ, there's
how much backup you have, there's
what kind of storage you're using.
You have to try it yourself And that
doesn't apply just to Aurora Serverless.
DSQL, the new Postgres distributed
database, we talk to that a bit later,
is now of course generally available.
It's a quote from last week in AWS,
and the very first complaint was nobody
knows how much it costs, especially AWS.
You can… You get charged for DPU.
DPU is, has four or five different
component, and basically it's just guess.
You have no idea.
That's probably a bit too harsh,
but reality is you have to try it.
You have to move maybe a
replica on a Aurora Serverless
v2, for example, on a replica.
I have a serverless replica,
see how it goes, give it a try,
see the cost, and go for that.
And there's a very interesting
recent article about un-unveiling
Aurora DSQL pricing, and I love that
summary is that one thing for sure,
DSQL is cheaper than they expected.
The smart-- the price is smart to cover
AWS margin for most type of abuses,
and the reason is pretty simple, is
when I say that AWS is not a, any
cloud provider is not just to try to
overcharge you adding weird component.
It's just that they cannot just charge you
for example, CPU, because people might…
It really depends on
the query you're using.
So they try to compare, to compound
different aspect like write, read almost
only if a database is cross-region,
cross-region traffic, there's traffic
in, traffic out, and everything else.
So give it a try.
You cannot simply… If someone tells me
upfront that without knowing my database
that, "Oh, my database, if I move it
to serverless, I'm gonna pay more, I'm
gonna pay less, I'm gonna save fifty
percent," it's basically just guessing.
He has no idea.
No one has any idea until they try
Now, number four, compatibility.
Compatibility is a bit of a gray area.
What do first of all, is first, when
you think about managed databases and
compatibility, you have to try to guess
that you can start with foundation.
So for example take Postgres, take MySQL.
You can put it on EC2 or a
container, whatever you want.
You have full control of
the community edition.
That's the maximum flexibility you have,
compatibility minimum locked in because
you can move it out the way you want.
Even the most challenging part
of moving out of the cloud for
databases is moving the data.
It's not much the compatibility
in term of syntax.
RDS was-- had been there for
over a decade, is a step further.
Amazon Aurora even more
because it's a fork.
There's less flexibility.
There are less things you can change.
Mi-- less control on the minor version.
Then you reach serverless.
The more you go with Aurora Serverless
v2, the less control you have.
And almost all the SQL,
there are some compromises.
For example, foreign key is not there
yet, and a few other things that makes
it harder to say it's fully compatible
and… But it's fully managed, and the
more you leverage managed service, the
more you leverage the cross-regional
scalability, the more you have to
give up a bit on the compatibility
And as well, yes everyone tells you
that they are compatible, of course.
Keep that with a grain of salt.
If we-- Postgres compatibility may
be until your extensi- your specific
extension you want isn't supported.
Or maybe MongoDB is compatible until maybe
until your aggregation behaves slightly
different and it breaks your application.
Or what is MySQL?
Compatible, but then maybe
operationally it's very different,
that you cannot use third-party tools.
And here brings the point as well,
when you read advertisement of
people that claim compatibility.
Compatibility means many
different things at the same time.
Wire client protocol, SQL query
language, that's usually what they
try to focus on those presentation,
tell you that part is covered.
Feature and behavior, so you
might just have a subset that is
compatible, but it's just a subset.
But as well, operational
ecosystem or as well version.
Maybe you use DocumentDB, but not
all version of MongoDB are supported.
Just recently they had version eight,
but for many years there was no
support for intermediate version.
But that's one key message for
someone that, like myself, has
been mostly on the MySQL world, is
that everything in the relational
side is converging to a Postgres.
I'm simplifying here a bit as well.
If you think it's not the case that the
main language for the latest serverless
version of AWS is PostgreSQL compatible,
not MySQL compatible from day one.
And on the MongoDB side, there's
actually DocumentDB IO, that's the new
Linux Foundation working on DocumentDB.
That was from last year.
And the idea is to converge on that side.
So that's… If you think-- if
you're concerned about compatibility,
take those two main direction.
But the last very important point that
I've learned is one big discussion is
should you go horizontal or vertical?
When you mean serverless,
what do you mean?
You can mean two different things.
You can mean that you scale horizontally.
So DynamoDB, you have sharding
hidden behind that shard your table.
Great.
Amazing.
You might have a hot table, hot
partition, but that's a different story.
DSQL, same direction.
On the other side, you have Aurora.
Aurora Serverless v2, and v1
as well, of course, was, is a
vertical scaling of your database.
You can add some read replica, you
can have global, but the main concept
is your database scales vertically.
The size of your, for example, DB
buffer pool scales according to
the size, and it's vertical scaling
Both serve different purpose.
Not everyone needs the same.
You might need horizontal
scaling, you might not need it.
Why is important horizontal scaling?
Because we surely think about
moving, think about boxes.
It's usually easier to move smaller
boxes, many partitioned a different
way, than one just big box.
But is that vertical scaling
bad serverless or not really
serverless, as someone claimed?
Not really.
Most workload are very much
fine with a single instance.
They go up quite a lot.
You can go up to alpha theta of
memory, and you have a lot of
read replica on Cascade, Aurora,
if you want, that you can scale.
There's quite some room to go
vertical on a public cloud provider.
So to recap a bit, main goal here
is to focus on give up a bit the
concept is serverless, that is more
a buzzword, and think a bit about
for databases, more about elasticity.
What you want is that, of
course, your storage is there.
Ideally as well, your storage
shrink according to what you use.
So you pay for the storage you use.
You don't have to
pre-allocate the storage.
That's the easiest part.
But for the CPU and for memory and
anything else, think a bit more
about something elastic, that you
pay for what you use, but don't
think too much about is serverless.
Because yes, a server is still there.
I would like to close here with a
sentence that I'm taking from Aurora
Serverless v2 documentation from AWS.
What they state is one common complaint,
one common issue is that after a
while, your database doesn't scale
down to zero, doesn't scale down to
the minimum capacity you have set up.
Cool.
What they tell you is there are bugs
in life, there are memory leaks, so if
the database still doesn't scale down
to the minimum capacity configured,
then your serverless database, you
stop and restart the database to
reclaim any memory fragments that
might have built up over time.
Stopping and starting a database
result in downtime, so we
recommend doing this sparingly.
So basically, you're saying my
original approach to stop and start
the database to scale it up and down,
yeah, results a bit of downtime.
So we are a bit back to that one.
But jokes apart, I don't want to make
any joke about that, but it's just the
message here is that you have to remember
that behind a serverless database,
there's still a serverless engine.
There's a server engine, there's still
a MySQL somewhere, there's still a
Postgres somewhere running, and you need
to know how that works to really take
advantage of that So the key message is
leverage managed serverless database.
Sometimes even not serverless
one is good enough.
But also work on the
concept of elasticity.
But you have to… Before taking advantage
of them, you have to really understand
what runs behind under the hood.
Because you might be that you create a
perfect serverless scenario, and then
you have a simple cron job or a simple
MySQL event that keep your database
always at the same CPU, and you're
overpaying the hosts because you have
no idea what's happening behind, and you
blame this, the serverless algorithm.
With that on, a big thank you.
It's been a pleasure to b-
to join the conference today.
Goodbye.