Speaker 16: Hi, welcome to Conference
Forty Two's talk, Database DevOps:
CD for Stateful Applications.
I'm Steven Atwell, a director of product
at Harness and the product manager
behind our Database DevOps product.
I've been giving this talk at several
conferences recently, including
Postgres Conf, as well as SRE
Day in Seattle about a month ago.
The team behind Conference Forty Two also
puts on a series of global meetups called
SRE Day, so we're gonna go ahead and use
the recording from that SRE Day event.
This will allow those of you who
are not able to join us in person
in Seattle to still enjoy the
same content and hear questions as
they were asked during the event.
If at any point after watching this you
have questions on database DevOps, you'd
like to discuss your use cases, then
please feel free to reach out to me.
I'm happy to dive into those
questions and help you get answers.
And always happy to have a conversation
with a practitioner in the space.
With that, let's go ahead
and get started on the talk.
Speaker 17: Awesome.
So as you all heard earlier, I'm Stephen.
I'm a product manager at Harness.
I work on our database DevOps product.
I've been a product
manager for about a decade.
Before that, I was a software engineer.
Go back far enough, I was in IT operations
working as a DBA, working in server
support, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
So in our space, I've probably
done it at some point.
I am going to chain onto
that Gable AI talk, actually.
I'm gonna be talking about making
a database schema change, and
we're gonna be using a real world
app that one of my partners built.
And it's a barbecue app.
So we- they've got a
fictional barbecue chain.
So it's got a JavaScript front
end and uses Postgres on the
back end, runs on Kubernetes.
And we're gonna be going ahead and
making a change because there've
been some kind of bad things in the
scheme of this app over the years.
What all are we using?
Hey, we've got a couple Harness products.
We're gonna be using Harness
CD and Harness DB DevOps and
Harness… I'm blanking on the name
of our AIQA, but our AIQA thing.
And we're gonna be using
GitHub for our source control.
We are gonna be running on Kubernetes.
We're using a Portworx storage
layer, which allows you to easily
replicate data between environments
without taking any downtime.
And we're gonna be using
Postgres for our database.
We're also gonna be using
several LLMs throughout this.
So specifically, we're gonna be
using primarily Claude, but also a
little bit of OpenAI on the back end.
How do you do a database
change with no downtime?
If anyone here has ever done database
change, doing it with zero downtime and
zero data loss is really hard because
let's say you have a column and you wanna
split it out into two new columns Version
A of your app is running and version B
of the app is running at the same time,
and they're just writing to the columns
they're gonna see different things.
So that's a problem, and it tends to
result in people needing to take downtime.
A lot of companies that I talk to
aren't using our database DevOps stuff.
They get to where they're able to
do production deployments for their
stateless stuff many times a day, but
they're still doing once a month, once
a quarter for their database stuff,
and half the time it's entirely me.
There's a reason for that.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna
… For our app layer, we're gonna be doing
blue-green and canary deployments.
In our staging environment,
we're gonna do a blue-green.
In our production environment,
we're gonna do a canary.
Both of those deployment methods run
the old and new version of the app in
parallel with some traffic going to
each of them, and that allows us at the
app layer to have no downtime, but that
forces that our database change needs
to be backwards compatible between them.
So we're gonna talk through how we
do that safely in the database layer.
And again, database consistency
is critical because if one version
of the app is seeing different
data than the other version of
the app, this is a real problem.
I will move that to my left
hand, which hopefully makes me
gesture less with that hand.
So a little bit about the
history of this application.
It used to be hosted via
using Mongo as its database.
It isn't anymore.
And real world story, last year, we got
a version from the developer that was po-
ported to Postgres, and we were going,
"Oh, okay. Cool. Let's go do an update
version of this talk that's on Postgres."
And we were gonna add a column to it.
We used to talk about changing a table
and splitting a city comma state column.
But we looked at the schema and every
table in the database had two columns.
One was named ID, the other was named doc,
and d- doc is a serialized JSON object.
I don't know if any of you are
Postgres experts, but this is
not how you should use Postgres.
So we got a little ambitious and went,
"I don't know how to fix that with zero
downtime. Let's see if AI does." So
we're gonna, we're gonna fix this schema.
The basic plan for today's talk, we're
gonna take this JSON column, we're gonna
split it down into a separate column
for every field with zero downtime.
The flow of the demo I'm gonna show
you, we're gonna start by asking
an AI to fix the database, 'cause
I don't know how to write that SQL.
I don't know about you, but
I'm not that good with SQL.
We are then gonna go
and validate the change.
The way we're gonna validate the
change is we have a test automation
that is automating the application's
UI, and it is going to log into
our barbecue restaurant app.
It's gonna place an order.
It's gonna go to the new version,
make sure the order shows up, place
another order, go back to the old
version, make sure it shows up.
So we know any edit we do
on the new version shows up
on the old, and vice versa.
Sorry, actually, we're gonna
do that down, down zero.
Here we're just gonna
do a basic validation.
We're gonna commit the change to Git.
I mentioned Portworx earlier.
So this talk has its start because
I used to work at a company where
90% of our bugs we only found if we
tested with production customer data.
And if you go back in time six
years, it was really hard to
clone all your customers and do
customer data-specific tests.
So cool, we're gonna clone all
our production data to staging.
We're gonna do all of our
testing on top of that data.
If there is something specific to prod,
we'll catch it in staging, and then when
we hit prod, we'll know everything's safe.
In staging, we're gonna do a blue-green
deployment, so we're gonna spin up the old
and the new version of the application.
And the database consistency tests
we're gonna do are gonna be comparing
these two versions, making sure they are
seeing the same data while modifying the
So with that, I wanna
show y'all a quick demo
How is the font?
That is, we probably wanna make
that font a little bit bigger.
Can people see that all right in the back?
Not really.
Set that down because now
I don't need those fields.
Just to save us a couple minutes, I typed
this prompt in before I started, and what
it is doing is it's saying, "Hey, the doc
column of our orders table is JSON text.
We gave it an example row.
Please update this table to
have a separate column for
each name in the JSON string.
Column names should match the
column names in the JSON string
exactly and be all lowercase.
Ensure data is kept in sync
between the current columns and
the new columns, and that the
fields are the same for every row.
Do not add any constraints or indexes."
And got a couple things to make sure
my demo works consistently every time.
On the right-hand side here, we can see
the change we generated, and this test and
preview button in the lower left that's
cut off because I zoomed in too far.
I'm gonna click that button, and
what that's doing is it's kicking
off a, an automated process
that's validating this change.
Basically doing a dry run, so it's com-
running against a real database, computing
the SQL this change is gonna run, pu-
putting it through some governance
rules, making sure everything looks okay.
If it passes, it's going
to open a PR for us.
While that's running, I wanna talk
through this change and how we actually
do this class of database change.
So step one, hey, we need
to add all those columns.
They come in with no data, but
if we don't have them, we're
not gonna be able to do this.
And similarly, if for some reason we
need to roll this back, we're gonna
wanna make those columns go back away.
So cool, step one, pretty simple.
Step two, things are getting
a little bit more complicated.
So for step two, we are setting up a
trigger, and this trigger is basically
a code that runs in the database
any time any- anyone edits the data.
It is going, and if anyone edits
that doc column, it is going and
updating all of those columns we
just added so that they match.
That ensures data
consistency in one direction.
And again, on rollback, we'll
go ahead and remove the trigger.
For our next change set here, we are
gonna go ahead and set up a trigger
that goes in the opposite direction.
So if people edit the new version, it
also syncs back to the JSON doc column.
For the record, first time I ran this,
I didn't even realize that Postgres had
these handy JSON functions that make
this all fairly straightforward to do.
And this is all written by AI After
we set up the triggers we've got a
bunch of data in these tables already
so we need to go ahead and copy them.
Now, something I'll point out
in the copy is you never know
how large those tables are.
Our barbecue restaurant
chain, multinational,
billions of rows of records.
So cool, we don't wanna run this
whole thing in a transaction, so we're
gonna go ahead and do small changes
here, not one giant transaction
And that went ahead.
And so that's high level our change
and those triggers are gonna make
sure everything continues to look
the same in both places I'm gonna go
ahead and check on that validation
pipeline we've got running really fast
Speaker 16: Yeah.
Speaker 17: Yes, definitely
So I'm doing this to one table in place.
So we are adding additional columns
that have the new fields and there
are de- like, you can definitely do
this class of thing instantiating
a second table, syncing the two
tables on primary key as well.
Same basic approach works
Our validate's running a little bit slow
at the moment, but it's almost there.
So we're currently, we pulled down the
existing database definition from Git.
We're merging our change in.
We're running a validate
and update preview.
So I mentioned governance checks
earlier, so I've got a couple governance
checks defined in this environment.
So you can see right now
I've got some policies.
In this case, it's literally just
making sure we never drop table data
in production, and hey, we're not doing
anything that would do that, so we passed.
Nice and simple.
When that finished, we got a link
back to our pull request, and
I'm gonna go ahead and merge this
So with that merge, that's gonna kick
off our CI/CD pipeline, and this CI/CD
pipeline is gonna run that deployment
flow we walked through earlier.
Quick refresher, we are going to start
by pulling down all the production data,
putting it in our staging environment so
that we're testing with production data.
If you are doing this, a
couple caveats to be aware of.
Some companies have different security
rules for production versus staging.
If you're doing this and you're
doing anything sensitive with your
product, make sure your staging
environment has the exact same controls
as your production environment.
If it doesn't, there's also
various anonymization layers you
can run on data as-- when moving.
I'm not doing any of that here.
If anyone wants to have a conversation
about any of that, happy to dive
into it after the talk as well.
This is gonna go ahead and pull
down that change using that Portworx
layer that I mentioned earlier, and
then once it finishes, we are going
to stand up the database, the new
version of the database, and then
the new version of the application.
That's gonna take about a minute
longer, so whilst running, any-
anyone have any questions on
anything I've touched on so far?
So Chris Crowe helped me build this
demo, and we regularly give it together.
And the Frank the Pig is also the Port
Works Barbecue Restaurant CEO, and I had
meant to bring him with as my co-speaker
today, as Chris unfortunately is… While
he is local, is currently in Europe.
But yes, yeah.
I think the one I had the automation
open was probably opened by me, but
it's entirely possible that it's
Speaker 16: under his username.
Speaker 17: So there are several
different patterns I see for
testing database changes.
The vast majority of companies
I've talked to do it by hand.
You can do better today.
Here I'm doing it through a UI.
That's pretty rare because it takes
a lot of time to write those tests.
I also have a lot of customers who do
things like, hey, packaged alongside their
database change, there's a SQL file that
is a test, and they run that SQL file.
And for example, I've got one customer who
has like a stored procedure in all their
databases that takes a SQL query and a CSV
and runs the SQL query on both ver- run
SQL query, make sure it matches the CSV.
There's a few approaches like that.
Cool.
So we're- we've moved on to
doing the database schema change.
These green rows at the top on the
right-hand side here that barely
show up as green on the monitor,
these three rows are slightly green.
Those are the new records
we've a- we ha- have added.
We can see that I authored them a
high-level summary of what they're doing.
And these database tags, these are
rollback points to ensure we can
roll back any change we need to.
And if I click into one of these, I
can see that full change as it exists
in Git or the exact SQL we actually
compiled that to and ran against it.
So cool.
We've applied that change.
We touched earlier on governance, so we
did also run that same policy here while
deploying to our staging environment.
And we were just talking about testing.
So the vast majority of companies
I don't do end-to-end AI testing.
Here I'm gonna do an end-to-end AI test,
and the specific test I'm gonna do was
also authored via AI because that's
the new hotness these days, as I'm sure
I'm not the only one who's realized.
So over here on the right,
we can see the test.
So the test is going to… Oh,
Speaker 16: I need to hit Play.
Speaker 17: The test is gonna
go ahead and log into the new
version of the application.
And the two versions of the application,
you'll notice as it goes through, one
of them has smoke in the background.
So cool.
We just placed our order on one version.
We're now gonna hop over to the
other version of the application.
We're gonna place an order.
We're gonna make sure they both show up.
So cool.
Those are the orders we
currently have on version one.
Hopping over to version two,
you'll notice the smoke background,
so that's how you can tell the
difference between the two versions.
We're gonna place a food order again
We've placed our order, and we're
gonna go make sure both orders show up
And why do people not do
this class of testing?
Because it takes time to write the test.
It took me about 15
minutes to write this test.
It was, again, via
English language prompt.
So we just placed that, that additional
order, and we're making sure they are
showing up on… I feel like we looped
back to the beginning a second ago there.
But This is not using
Playwright under the covers.
I believe there is an
integration to Playwright, right?
This is using Harness' AI
test automation product
So cool, we've got both of
those orders showing up.
Then we'll hop o- back over to the
other version, make sure they're
there as well, and cool, they are.
So everything passes, and we
can move on to production.
So cool, we took advantage of that
blue-green deployment in staging so
that we could talk to both of those
versions simultaneously, and then
that test was literally making sure
the two apps were looking at the same
data, even though we were making a
fairly large change to th- this table.
Going back over to the Gable AI talk,
we might very well have other systems
that are talking to this beyond just
our app, and that's okay because both
of these columns are still there.
They still have the same data.
So we can now go use Gable.
We can look at that graph.
We can figure out which
services we need to update.
Once they're updated, then we can go make
the old column and the triggers go away.
So cool, we're, we are
fully backwards compatible.
We've deployed to staging.
We finished our blue-green
deployment, shut down the old version,
and we're waiting for a manual
approval before we go on to prod.
So I'm gonna go ahead and issue
that approval, and this is gonna
kick off our production deployment.
For our production deployment, we're
gonna do something very similar.
We are, instead of doing a
blue-green, we're gonna do what's
called a canary deployment.
If anyone's not familiar with canary
deployments, just like with the
blue-green, we stand up the new version
and the old version in parallel, but
we slowly increase how much traffic
we're sending to the new version.
Once it's all over, we shut down
the old version, and we monitor the
application health metrics during
that slow increase in traffic to
make sure everything stays healthy.
So this is gonna go ahead and run
through that same deployment process
Yes
So specif-- most of this runs on anything.
The database can be on anything.
For this demo, I am running
my database on Kubernetes.
The-- specifically, the database
DevOps version of the delegate
currently is Kubernetes only.
There's a ECS version
that's shipping next month.
So by the time you care- … there,
there will be other options.
But current- currently, it is
Kubernetes only for that one piece.
Every- everything else doesn't care.
Cool.
So we went through that
same deployment check.
Now I'm gonna call out, we're
doing that policy enforcement
in all of the environments.
Some companies have policies
that only affect prod versus dev.
So cool, you can allow your dev-- we can
allow our devs to have more flexibility.
And similarly, the more places you're
checking things, the less likely it
is something slips through the cracks.
In this particular case, for this
particular demo, my prod policy
is set to only affect prod.
A very common pattern I see in my
c- in my customer base is where they
will have a prod policy that will
fail in prod but will warn in dev,
at which point it runs through but
finishes with warnings, and they can
see that, hey, they got this warning.
Great question.
So we finished our database deployment.
We're currently doing that canary
deployment with p- slow traffic
roll-up, and in just a moment,
that's gonna be done as well.
We finish sending over traffic,
and we shut down the new version.
So cool.
We've fully deployed our
new version of our database.
This w- this canary was managed entirely
under the hood by Harness, which we can
do across multiple deployment techs.
In this case, I was going to Kubernetes
but also we'll do it fully on all
of AWS, all of GCP, et cetera.
There's also a native Argo
integration, so if you're using Argo
That's the demo.
Happy to go into more questions
about databases or barbecue.
If you wanna play order your own
barbecue, these are the URLs,
pass.pxbbq.com or pass staging or the
new version anytime I run the demo, and
I'll be running it again on Thursday,
is pass-staging-preview.pxbbq.com.
Feel free to place your own
order if you are interested.
Otherwise any questions
about databases or barbecue?
Do you get barbecue or is it like- So
I keep telling my marketing department
when I give variants of this talks,
they need to bring me barbecue.
It hasn't happened yet.
I did at a conference last year,
get bacon candy, and today we have
canaries that are grill-your-own-canary
in the back, and it…
They have a bit of a rubbery texture, so
you might not wanna actually eat them, but
you could make barbecue canary in theory.
Any other questions?
Cool.
Thank you.
If you think of anything you'd like to
ask later on I'll be back in that room
and happy to dive into your use cases or
other conversations about this as usual.