Speaker 18: Everyone, today
we're going to talk about ethical
DevOps for AI data pipelines.
Thank you for joining my session.
My name is Dharmendra Ahuja, and
here today I'm going to talk about
how engineering teams are embedding
the fairness transparency, and
accountability in our data pipelines
and and also the measurable gains
they achieve by implementing ethical
AI DevOps in their data pipelines.
So today we are going to talk about it.
So but before we start with this I
wanted to know, ask and brainstorm.
I would request you to brainstorm, like
how many people are using ethical AI
DevOps in their pipelines right now?
And and second question we need to think
about is what happens our AI system makes
like a biased detect-- decision at scale.
So in twenty twenty-three itself, a
healthcare AI misclassified risk for a
forty-five percent of minority patients
due to bias in the training data.
And a hiring algorithm screened
out like qualified candidates
based on the historical patterns.
And because of that they,
that, that is a glitch.
And due to this kind of issues
the average cost of an AI ethics
failure is thirty-seven point
five… three thir- three point
seven million dollars in remediation.
And al- there is also an cost which
is unseen, which is like irreplaceable
trust damage, which is happening.
So today we are going to talk
about several items here.
So we will be talking about the
shift why the speed is not just--
speed alone is just not enough.
We need to have ethical
risk in AI pipelines.
What are those?
We'll l-look into it.
We'll be looking into embedding the ethics
into CI/CD pipelines and what are the
cloud-native architectures for ethical AI.
We'll be talking about
a healthcare case study.
We'll be talking about governance
challenges and best practices.
And also, we'll be seeing like
what are the futures and the next
step of the ethical AI, right?
So right now we are going to
talk about the shift, right?
So there was a shift from the traditional
DevOps to the ethical DevOps, how it
happened and why do we need to do it.
So in traditional DevOps, we
have a speed and reliability, we
have a CI/CD automation, right?
We have uptime and performance.
We have code quality gates, right?
This is what we have seen
in our traditional DevOps.
But in ethical DevOps, we want to check
whether the… whatever the things
we have implemented, are they fair?
And we want to make sure
there is no bias to it.
So we are trying to detect
the bias in, into it.
We are trying to implement the
privacy in the design itself.
We are trying to implement explainability
frameworks, and we are trying to
implement like ethics as a code
governance in our ethical DevOps.
So now let's the evolution.
Let's see the evolution of how
the DevOps is evolved into MLOps
and from MLOps to ethical DevOps.
In DevOps, we have CI/CD pipelines,
we have automated testing, we have
infrastructure as a code, and we
have a monitoring and alerting.
This is what we have seen
in traditional DevOps.
In MLOps, we are trying to use the models.
So we are trying to version the models.
We are trying to create
the data pipelines.
We are trying to look into
the experimental tracking.
We are also trying to deploy the models.
But ethical AI DevOps is
an extension to it, right?
To extension to MLOps.
So we are trying to detect
the biases in the models.
We are trying to look
into the privacy controls.
We are trying to look into the
explainability, like we should
be able to explain what the model
is doing and why it is doing.
So the explainability is also embedded
here in, in ethical AI DevOps.
And also, we are continuously monitoring
the ethics also So let's see what
are the ethical risk in AI pipelines.
So in the-- So there are some risk here.
So one is like bias in data.
So historical inequalities in dataset can
cause models to reinforce like harmful
patterns against undeserved groups, right?
There could be a bias in data.
We have seen in like we discussed
the twenty twenty-three example.
So there's, there was a bias in data.
There is privacy violations, sensitive
records medical, financial, and biometric.
These are the sensitive records, and
it will require like strict governance
to prevent unauthorized exposure.
So we want to make sure these records
are not landing in unsafe hands, right?
Third one is model drift.
Model will behave responsibility
at launch, but it will degrade
over the period of time as
the human interaction changes.
So the, there could be a drift
in the models we will see.
And fourth one is lack of explainability.
So black box models undermine
regulatory oversight, and it will-- and
stakeholders' trust in high-stake domains.
So we should be able to ex-- The AI
should be able to explain like why it
is doing and why-- and what it is doing.
So most of the models have black
box, so that is a issue that, that's
what we are trying to solve here.
So how we can embed ethics
into the CI/CD pipelines?
So we can embed ethics into the
CI/CD pipelines at four stages.
First one is code commit.
So in code commit we are
running policy as a code rules.
It is a scan for data handling violations,
and it will… and the bias flags.
So if there is any bias, it will flag it.
Second one is build and trust.
So automated fairness test
will validate disparate impact
across the demographic groups.
So that's why we have automated
fairness test in place.
Third one is stage gate.
So stage gate is more of ethics
threshold check, like a block deployment,
and if a bias metric exceed the
limits, it will be looking into it.
Fourth one is the production.
So it-- In the production environment,
we are continuously monitoring and
checking for the drift, and it will
trigger the automated rollback.
If there's any drift observed, it is
going to do the automated rollback.
So governance as a code expresses
like a policies as a machine-readable
rules, and it will block the unapproved
deployments, and it will enforce
fairness thresholds, and it also it will
require explainability documentation.
That's what we have been s-seeing so far.
So now the observability, ethical
observability is a multilayer concept.
So we have infrastructure.
We have a infrastructure layer,
we have a data layer, right?
We have a model layer, and
we have a business layer.
So infrastructure layer, we have a
compute, network, container health,
we have a database performance.
So these are the things we
observe in infrastructure layer.
In data layer, we are checking
whether data is fresh and
the schema is consistent.
There's no drift to the schema, and also
we are checking sensitivity data also.
That there should not be
any sensitivity exposure.
And third one is like mo-- we are
observing the model now, so we are
looking into the quality bias indicators.
If there is any bias indicators,
we are looking into it.
We are looking into the quality,
prediction quality, and we are
looking into the explainability,
which we saw earlier.
So we are looking into that.
Also, we are trying to observe that.
Fourth one is the business observability.
In business observability, we are
checking for user trust metrics,
how the user is-- whether the user
is trusting our system or not.
So we are looking into it, we are looking
into the regulatory compliance, and we
are also looking into the stakeholder
feedback as part of the business layer.
So every layer is feeding
to another layer, right?
So now we are going to talk
about the real-time response
and automated remediation
Fajn, na věnotu
So now how we can-- what triggers the
alert as part of the observability
which we have seen, and what is
the automated remediation to it?
So there are several triggers
which will generate the alert.
So we will see if there's a prediction
imbalance, it will trigger the alert.
If there's any demographic disparities,
it is going to trigger the alert.
And if there's any unauthorized
data access in the system,
it will trigger an alert.
And if there's any instability
or there's any data corruption,
it is going to trigger an alert.
So these are the alerts we have
defined, but there could be an automated
action associated with that, right?
So if there's any bias they've
observed in the models, it will
roll back automatically, right?
If there's any suspicious data streams,
we have seen that, okay, there's any
suspicious data, then it is going to
quarantine that suspicious data streams.
Third one is privilege.
We-- If we can see there's any access
privilege issue, and then it is going
to roll back that access privileges,
and it will revoke it dynamically.
And it is going to co- compliance the
alert, expla-- escalate workloads.
If there's any compliance alerts we
have seen, it is going to escalate the
workloads to a-address those alerts.
So now we are going to discuss about the
cloud-native architecture for ethical AI.
So there are four components to it.
We are trying to build the
containerized workloads.
We are trying to reuse the ethical
validation, which will be serving
as a package, as a container, and it
will ensure the consistency across
all the environments, whether it's
a dev staging, test, and production.
So we are trying to make sure that
all the environments are consistent
so for that's the reason we are
creating containerized workloads.
And then we are doing
Kubernetes governance.
We are creating policies, engines, and
will-- and we are trying to isolate the
networks, and we are trying to restrict
the access also and trying to create
an audit logging standards at scale.
The third one is event-driven processing.
So we are trying to create streaming
platforms which will be basically
continuously monitoring, and also it
is going to look into the predictions.
Security events, it's
going to look into it.
And also it will look into the compliance
logs for real-time observability.
Fourth one is the
infrastructure as a code.
In infrastructure as a code, we have
ethical controls embedded directly
into our deployment templates, and we
are going to improve the scalability,
consistency, auditability, and
governance reproducibility as part
of the infrastructure as a code.
Now- Now we are going to discuss
about the case study of the healthcare
client where the ethical AI was
implemented in clinical platforms.
So there were some challenges i-into
it and there were some solution
associated with those challenges.
So the challenge the first challenge
was, like, inconsistent data quality
across clinical systems, right?
That is a challenge we have seen.
Second challenge was privacy
concerns around patient records.
And third challenge was, like, a
black box diagnostic recommendation.
And fourth challenge was, like, a slow
incident response and compliance gaps.
So there was a-- for each
challenge, there was a solution.
We there was, it was found.
And there was a automated
ingestion validation, right?
That is a solution for the
inconsistent data quality.
There wa-- when there was a privacy
concern around the patient records
they created a privacy-centered design
to, to address it that challenge.
Third challenge was a black box
diagnostic recommendations was there.
So for that explainability
frameworks were created so that we
can address why it is done that way
and what is the reason behind it.
And the fourth challenge was,
like slow incident response
and compliance gaps were there.
So for, to address that challenge,
there was a continuously ethical
hacking, ethical monitoring was
done to, to address that challenge.
So that organization redesigned
its AI delivery pipeline to address
those challenges using ethical
ethical AI DevOps principles.
And also, it, it helped in measurable
improvements in our trust, privacy,
and response times with the help of
that So during this process there
was-- there are outcomes, right?
The outcomes is better trust
improve in-- improvement in
trust, privacy and resilience.
So with the help of this solution
which was implemented, we im-- we were
able to to ca-- achieve end-to-end
encryption and automated anonymization
a-and role-based access improvement.
And it helped the patient
data protection, right?
And there was explainable AI.
So feature importance analysis
and clinical reasoning summaries
helped in clinical validated
AI assisted recommendations.
Third one is faster response.
So continuous monitoring with automated
ad-- with automated alert reduced the
operational disruption and it helped
with the incident response time.
The fourth one is the clinical trust.
So transparent decision traceability,
it help confidence among healthcare
professionals and also the stakeholders.
So the business case is like,
what is the ROI of ethical DevOps?
So the ROI is reduction in bias.
So seventy-three percent reduction
was im- was realized i-in, in the
bias-related incidents after CI/CD
was integrated once the ethics was
integrated into CI/CD pipelines.
There was a two point four times
faster regulatory audit completion
with governance as a code.
Third benefit we saw is fifty-eight
percent reduction in model remediation
cost with early e- ethics detection.
And there was a three point
seven million average cost of a
single AI ethics failure, which
we are solving this problem.
This data is given by MIT Sloan
in twenty twenty-four So now in to
address these issues which we have
earlier we discussed earlier and
what are the solutions we discussed.
So to, to address the challenges and
the solutions, we have governance
frameworks in place which will help
to achieve these solutions, right?
So we have key stakeholders and
key governance pillars which
are required to achieve that.
So as part of key stakeholders, we need
to have data engineers, we need to have
compliance officers, we need to have legal
advisors, we need to have security teams,
we need to have executive leadership
and domain experts as key stakeholders.
And we need to have key
governance pillars, right?
We need to have ethical review
boards which will evaluate high-risk
deployments and sensitive data usage.
Third one is-- second one is auditability.
So data lineage and model version
histories and incident logs, right?
So for that, we need to have
auditability framework defined.
And third one is a regulatory alignment.
So we need to have privacy,
we need to have transparency,
fairness, and data sovereignty.
So we need to think of all these
terms when we are create- trying to
create the governance frameworks.
And these are the people who must be
involved in creating these frameworks
so whatever we discussed so far,
it is not a magic bullet, right?
So every challenge so there are
challenges and there are trade-offs to it.
So speed and governance.
So ethical checks add like a
pipeline complexity, but alert
detection prevents like a large
disruption downstreams, right?
So there are false positives.
Excessive alerts can cause
fatigues, and it can erode the
trust in our monitoring systems.
Thresholds must be like
continuously refined, right?
Third one is fairness complexity.
Different fairness metrics can conflict.
Organizations must align definitions
with their ethical responsibilities.
Fourth one is cost and culture.
Observability infrastructure
requires investment, right?
We-- Organizational resistance
requires leadership support and
education in the organization
about the observability, right?
So these are the trade-offs we have.
So what are the best practices
for the implementation?
We need to prioritize by risk.
We need to focus governance on high
sensitivity and high impact system first.
We-- There is a data sensitivity,
we have a regulatory exposure,
and we have a human impact, right?
Second is integrate ethics early.
We should embed ethical
validation during system design,
not just after the deployment.
We don't-- We want to be proactive
in this, and we want to integrate
ethics early in the game.
So early integration will
reduce the remediation cost.
Third one is automate wherever possible.
We should-- Manually
governance does not scale.
Automated validation should
be standard CI/CD component.
Fourth one is maintain human oversight.
We need to have a critical decisions in
healthcare, finance, and public safety.
It will must remain retained
like a human review mechanism.
We need to because in the healthcare,
finance, these areas, we need to have,
human oversight, which is mandatory.
Fifth one is about building
transparent communication.
We need to have a-- clearly
communicate how AI operates and what
data is used and how incidents are
managed so that we can strengthen
the stakeholder trust in the system.
So now what is the
future of ethical DevOps?
The future is like
auton-autonomous governance.
AI-driven platforms will dynamically
adapt governance policies based on
changing operational conditions, right?
We have a federated learning.
Privacy-preserving techniques will
allow a col-collaborative model training
without centralizing sensitive data.
We have ethical benchmarking.
We will have a standard frameworks
which will emerge to to evaluate
fairness and transparency and
accountability across AI systems.
Then fourth one is the AI regulation
expansion governance worldwide are
developing like comprehensive AI laws
and early ethical DevOps investment
will help to ensure we are ready.
So what could be a next step, right?
We should-- This week, we should
start understanding our AI pipeline
for bias and risk and identify
your highest risk ML model.
And this month we should add like
a fairness checks to our CI/CD.
We should form like a
cross-functional ethics working
group, which we discussed right now.
And this quarter we should be thinking
about how we can implement governance as
a code for data pipelines, but also define
our ethical thresholds and alert policies.
So ethical DevOps is not
a, like a one-day project.
It is an ongoing culture
of responsible engineering
So the future of AI is-- depends
on not only on the innovation
speed, but on the ability to deploy
intelligent system responsibly.
And ethical DevOps provides like a
foundation for achieving that balance.
So it so it helps to
detect the bias earlier.
Automated validation in CI/CD
catches the issues before production.
Governance as a code operationalize
regulatory requirements, so it
is strengthen the compliance.
The third one is building lasting trust.
Transparency and accountability creates
like a confidence across stakeholders.
So speed and ethics are
not opposites, right?
The most efficient AI systems and teams
are the most ethical ones So now we
have a question, so and the discussion
about-- and the food for thought.
So as a ethical AI experts, we should
think about what are the ethical risk
exist in our current AI pipelines.
We should evaluate that.
We should mature in our govern--
We should check how mature is your
governance frameworks today, and
what prac-best practices we would
like to implement first, right?
And I would like to thank
you for joining the session.
The question is not whether AI will
transform our industry, it is whether the
transformation will be trustworthy or not.
Thank you