Speaker 19: Hello, everyone, and
welcome to this talk, RAG in Production:
Challenges, Techniques and Solutions.
My name is Alejandro Duarte.
I'm an engineer,
basically, at MariaDB PLC.
MariaDB is one of the leading
open source relational databases,
and it has quite a lot to offer.
But today we're gonna explore
something very specific, which is RAG.
And take a look at this hallucination
by certain AI model, right?
It is suggesting to add glue to pizza.
All right?
At least it says non-toxic
glue, so I guess that's nice.
Now, how about this one?
How many rocks should I eat?
Eating at least one small rock per
day is recommended because rocks
contain minerals and vitamins that
are important for digestive health.
All right?
So the whole hallucination,
it's hilarious.
And you will find many of these
examples everywhere, where LLMs
just make up things, and they say
these things as if they were facts.
Okay?
So one of the best techniques for
preventing LLMs hallucinating like this
is RAG, or Retrieval-Augmented Generation.
So it's no surprise that RAG is growing on
interest over time, especially in the last
few years 'cause developers want to learn
how to do this correctly, and also because
there are many challenges here, right?
It's not that easy, so you have to
go there and find some solutions.
Now, fortunately for you, I have packed
all these things in a single talk,
and I hope this helps you delivering
RAG solutions with ease in the future.
We're gonna talk about this,
and for that, here is the plan.
First, I'm gonna give you an
introduction to RAGS- RAGs, so
that we are all on the same page.
Then we are gonna do a deep dive into
the challenges and techniques in, on, on
each part of an, of a RAG architecture.
And we are gonna architect a solution
that tackles all these challenges
and uses some of these techniques.
And I'm gonna show you one implementation
of such an architecture, kinda with a
demo because it's gonna be screenshots,
but it's gonna work out pretty nicely
as this is online, I don't know if
there is gonna be a a bit for questions
and answers, but you can always reach
out to me online if you have questions
or you want to get in touch about the
topics that I'm gonna show you today.
So let's get started with
retrieval-augmented generation.
And you can think of retrieval-augmented
generation as a technique to construct
context specific to each query, right?
So the context, it's very important.
It's what makes your model use data
that's real or maybe data that's
private, that the LLM was never
trained on and this kind of stuff, so
that it doesn't hallucinate things.
This goes beyond prompt engineering, and
maybe it's an alternative to retraining
your own models, as it just provides
the context right there for the LLM.
You n- you don't need to do
anything else with the model, right?
You just need to find that context
and append it to the the prompt, the
input that you are sending to the LLM.
I took this definition
from this really good book.
I highly recommend it.
So let's talk about context, because just
like in the transformer architecture,
where we say attention is all you need
because of this famous paper published,
I think it was in 20 17 that talks about
the transformer architecture, right?
In RAG, we can say context
is all you need, right?
And at the core of it, RAG is like
prompt stuffing, oversimplifying.
We're gonna see why I'm
saying oversimplifying later.
And so somewhere in your application, you
are gonna have a prompt template, right?
Something like this, maybe a
question and a placeholder for
the question that's formed by…
with the information that comes from
the user, or sometimes even directly
whatever the user typed somewhere.
And then the context, which is
some fetched data that's relevant
to that question, so that when
you create an instance of this
template in order to send it to the
LLM, could look like this, right?
The question would be,
for example, what is ABC?
And then the context should be
something that talks about ABC so
that the LLM makes a good prediction
or shows a good output, right?
Now, the key here is that fetched data.
How do we get that data that's
related to the question?
The answer is information retrieval
algorithms and techniques one of which
is vector search, for example, or you
can use text search or any other kind of
algorithm technique system, whatever it
is that goes and finds the data, right?
We're gonna see these a bit
more in detail in a moment.
And so there are two phases
of RAG at the macro level.
So the first one, it's like a-
an ETL pipeline where we… the
most important thing is that
we calculate vector embeddings.
We're gonna see how
this works in a moment.
And then we use those in phase
two for retrieval and generation.
More importantly here for us,
it's the retrieval part, right?
So where we fetch that content
using, again, the calculated
vec- vector embeddings.
So let's see these now in
more detail each phase.
Phase one, ETL pipeline, and for
that I'm gonna use an example, a
product recommendation chatbot.
You can find the code for this
example on Git- on GitHub.
It's a Java implementation.
It uses no framework, so you
understand exactly what's going on.
Obviously AI frameworks help with this.
And so there you have a program.
It could be a service,
whatever you want to call it.
I call it program.
It's a process that's running
somewhere, and I call it compute vectors
because what it does is exactly that.
It's gonna calculate those vectors, vector
embeddings that I was talking about.
And also I have a database,
in this case MariaDB, with
one table, the products table.
So we can take one of these rows here
in this database, which is a product,
and take the title, description, price,
and whatever else we want from this
product, concatenate those values
into a single string in our program,
and then send that to an embedder.
This is the an embedder endpoint.
An embedder is something that produces a
vector, so that's what it returns, right?
And this vector represents the semantic
meaning of whatever we send to it.
In this case, we sent information
about a product in our database.
So that vector, which is a series of
numbers, is going to encapsulate the
semantic meaning of that product,
and we're gonna use that fact in a
moment, and I'll show you how that
works So we can take this vector, store
it here in the in the same row, for
example, in a different column, and
now we iterate over all the products.
So all the products have a vector,
which is again, each product has a
semantic representation that describes
the product, and we can use that
fact later on phase two which is the
retrieval and generation phase, right?
So this is another program or service,
whatever you want to call, chat demo,
and the user is gonna interact with that.
So let's say they type, "I
want running shoes," right?
And this is gonna suggest some
products that are related to
what the user is asking for.
So we can take that string, "I want
running shoes," send it to the same
embedder which could be provided
by OpenAI or any other provider
or you might be hosting these
locally on your infrastructure.
It doesn't matter.
It's gonna return a vector.
And this vector we are not gonna store
in our database, but we're gonna use it
to construct a SQL query that compares
all the vectors in our database with that
new one that we just created from, "I
want running shoes." And because the way
vectors work is so that vectors that are
closer together in this hyperspace, they
represent semantically similar things.
So we can order by that distance in
this hyperspace and then get, for
example, the three that are more
similar or closer, which means also
similar to, "I want running shoes."
So we take these three products and
then we build our prompt for the LLM.
This time it's a
different endpoint, right?
That's why the arrow is going
somewhere else in the icon here.
So we say, "I want running shoes. Here
are the available products. Suggest some."
So you use your template there to place
with the placeholder for the input and
the placeholder for the fetched data.
Okay?
So now the LLM has less chances of
hallucinating, and we can return
something meaningful to the user.
Now, if you want to learn more
about the what vectors actually
are, and why is it that there are
numbers there, is it an array?
Are they float point floating point
numbers, or what kind of stuff?
Or wha- what is each dimension here?
Each number represents something or what?
These kind of questions and how it
actually encapsulates meaning I recommend
this video, which you can find in
the official MariaDB YouTube channel.
So you go to youtube.com/mariadb,
and you'll find these videos there.
So Introduction to Vector
Embeddings and Vector Search.
I highly recommend watching that one
if you need a refresher on this topic.
All right.
So now let's go through the challenges
and techniques in building RAG
applications or applications that use
this kind of architecture or techniques.
So for that, I'm gonna
bring Doom Guy, all right?
It's gonna tell us how difficult or how
easy maybe it is to implement a RAG as
we go through the same example, but we're
gonna make things a bit more complicated.
At this point, Doom Guy is just
smiling, even laughing, because this was
ridiculously easy to implement, right?
In fact, if you implement this
in Java with Spring AI that's
the compute vectors program.
That's all.
So it's not a whole lot.
And I'm gonna go through the details
of this code and just want to show
you the dimension the the number
of lines that might be required
for this simple use case, right?
And that's just a Hello
World of RAG, okay?
One table.
We have the vectors right there.
Everything it's very simple.
So we don't think about scalability.
We don't think about anything
really, the format of the data
that's stored in the products table.
We don't care about that.
This a Hello World example, right?
It works so that it makes you
understand the basics of it, but
this is not real life, right?
Things could get a bit more complicated.
For example
We have previously used just one SQL
table in our database, but what if we have
to do not only that, but we need to use
information for creating these vectors
that comes in a form of PDF files, XML
files, DOCX files, JSON files, plain text.
You get it, right?
It's gonna be a little bit
more complicated, right?
So we need to take into account
the nature of these documents.
So let's take PDF for a moment, and we're
gonna pretend to send a, say, 300-page
PDF document to an embedder so that we get
one single vector and pretend to use, with
that single vector, all the individuals…
individual ideas that are
laid out in this document.
We need to split this somehow, right?
We need to divide the text.
That's called chunking
in this talk, right?
These are synonyms, but
we're gonna use chunking.
And we're gonna chunk the whole document.
Here, I'm showing the
first three chunks, okay?
We create one vector per each chunk.
And now in… at this moment, we
will have three, but as we continue,
we will have maybe hundreds of
vectors for this single PDF file.
So we can use the individual
bits in the document.
So let's suppose this PDF starts with,
"I left my wife a note," and the first
chunk gets cut here, "I left my wife."
So we have lost the original meaning of
the document, and not only that, we are
conveying false information, hopefully.
And this won't work well.
We need something else.
And so we need to think about, and
one of the techniques to solve this
kind of problem is overlapping.
But then Doom Guy got the first
hit, because now you see we need
to think about these things.
We need to think about the
nature of our document whether
this is a good strategy or not.
We need to decide on that, and
we'll have to implement this.
And yeah frameworks help with this,
but you'll have to configure it, and
you'll have to make the right call to
the API and this kind of stuff, right?
So the code starts to grow.
And this this call overlapping-
And it works for certain
kind of documents, right?
Now there are multiple strategies.
For example, we can use something
called a recursive strategy, which
uses first it gets a big chunk I
don't know, so for… just to give
you an example, like the full page.
It's still too long, then
maybe that's too long, right?
So we cannot create a vector for this.
Let's use paragraphs.
So it, it cuts somewhere else smaller
and smaller and maybe this is still too
big, but now let's go with sentences.
And so now it's yeah, the size is fine.
We can create a vector for that, okay?
So that's called recursive chunking.
A- and it works with, via ex-
expressions that divide the context
based on a sequence of characters.
For example, you can imagine if
there are two new lines so that
there is one visible empty line,
that could be one big chunk, right?
So you can use that at the beginning
and then maybe, hey that's too big.
What if we just cut with one
new line and so forth, right?
And then maybe a full stop or something.
That's how it actually works.
So that's recursive.
Or we can let an LLM decide
where to cut each chunk.
And of course, I'm showing
here only the first chunk.
You will continue through the
whole document, like I said before,
and end up with tons of vectors.
And LL- LLMs are very good at this, okay?
But this will… this would add some kind
of latency because you need to make an
extra call per each, Chunk calculation,
and that, that would be a bit expensive,
whilst the other methods are super quick.
Okay?
But this is very precise you will have
to use this in some cases, depending
on the nature of your documents.
So you get it.
There are many different kind
of strategies to chunk the data.
All right, so there are libraries,
modules APIs I don't know for each
programming platform or language.
And these help with manipulating
these kind of documents, especially
multi- multiple formats, right?
We just covered PDF, but
there are other formats.
So you can do that with several
libraries or modules or whatever it's
called in your programming language.
However, there is some complexity there.
Now, when we're ingesting this
is called ingestion, right?
Take the actual physical documents,
whatever the nature of the storage
is, SQL, PDF file, XML file, whatever
it is, and store it somewhere in our
database so that's ready for chunking.
That's ingestion.
So when we're doing that, we might
want to do that from HTTP or maybe
from a directory in the file system.
Moreover, we can have multiple users.
The con- we can create the
concept of users, and each
user has its own directory.
Why that?
Maybe we want to reuse this from
multiple small applications,
from multiple microservices.
Or maybe it's a bigger application.
It's not a microservice, but it
contains many use cases for sure.
So maybe we don't want to
interfeed, interfere with
the data of another use case.
We might want to create different
users for this, and each one
will have its own directory.
So this kind of stuff we will
have to implement at this point
when we're ingesting documents.
Or we might have to ingest from S3, right?
So there are multiple ways.
Sometimes we might have to get
all of them available, right?
We don't know.
Now the compute vectors level, when we
are computing this stuff or processing
this data, we might have to take into
account things such as batch processing
and transformations of our documents
especially adding metadata, right?
The name of the file, when it was
ingested, th-this kind of thing,
and maybe making it the- or doing
layout-aware ingestion, right?
Because you can imagine that if we…
Imagine you have a PDF file, and it has
a a really messy structure with different
columns, sometimes one column, sometimes
multiple, sometimes some columns on
top, and then m- a full block of texts
on the lower page part of the page.
And so if you select, just imagine
that you select with a mouse
pointer, you select all the text,
copy, and you paste somewhere else.
I bet you have seen that sometimes
the order of the text, the the
way it was pasted is not correct.
You cannot read it, right?
These kind of things you will have
to take into account when you are
processing the ingested documents.
And when you're calling an external
system here, it's when we are calculating
the vector for each chunk, right?
You will have to consider things such as
orchestration challenges, especially here.
There are many, but especially related to
RAG right here and these kind of AI models
error handling and maybe retries, right?
Automatic retries.
You don't want to implement that on
every single use case of your application
or on each microservice that you
create or each application that you
use with a solution like this, right?
And security challenges again,
there are many, but especially
here because there could be a data
movement outside your environment.
And when we are storing the data, the,
both documents that when we are ingesting
and when we are chunking it, when we
are creating the chunks and storing
the the maybe you want to store a-
actually each chunk so you can use it
later, you will have to do that, right?
You will have to implement some sort
of document management and chunk
management meaning like a CRUD, create,
read, update, and delete operations
for both documents and and chunks.
And maybe add some versioning
data so you can update these
documents e- more easily later.
This kind of stuff will be in place there.
Okay, so phase one was a whole lot of
of challenges and we only… I guess
we touched the surface, but I tried
to show the most important parts here.
And you saw that each line
has its own challenges.
Now, let's move to phase two,
retrieval and generation.
And here, the main thing is that you
will have to ask yourself, "Hey, do I
need an additional vector database or
an extension for my database because it
doesn't support natively the v- vector
data type or vector insertion and vector
index that you will need if you have
millions of vectors in your database?"
Then if the answer is yes, then that's
gonna hit the guy really badly because
that adds a whole lot of complexity.
You are adding a new system to your
architecture, so you know that's
gonna be like you have to check the
license, the release cadence, the
quality and assurance policies, the
compatibility with whatever you're using.
The… Maybe you have to introduce
a new connector to this kind of
database or driver or whatever it's
called in your programming language or
library for connecting to it, right?
And all sort of things, basically, right?
In fact I recently discovered that
pgvector is maintained by one person.
So pgvector is the extension for
Postgres that allows it to store
vectors and do a vector search.
It's maintained by one person,
so that means that the bus
factor risk of a pgvector is one.
Now, I'm not saying that m- the
project's at a danger of disappearing
or anything, but it's one of the
metrics that you will have to evaluate
somehow or c- or helps you visualize
risk or understand, rather, risk.
So that's the bus factor.
If you want to learn more about
what the bus factor is I have this
article that you can find online.
And I also, I calculated the bus
factor risk for these databases, and
I found that MongoDB, MariaDB, and
Redi are at a really good level here,
so there is no high risk with them.
Pretty interesting stuff.
You can find out the results
for other databases there
if you are curious about it.
And there is a tool that you
can use to calculate the risk
factor of any project online.
Sorry, on GitHub.
So it's pretty cool All right.
Now, if you need an additional vector
database or e- or extension, that,
that's gonna introduce challenges, right?
Like installing, updating, operating
this thing, understanding this thing
configuring it, all that kind of stuff.
It's a whole lot of work.
It's complexity.
And like I said, that
hits Doomguy really badly.
But where is MariaDB?
So MariaDB supports vector and
vector search in a vector index
that's really powerful and fast, and
with really high recall natively.
So you don't need to install anything
else if you're using MariaDB.
In fact, Doomguy just
starts smiling again, right?
However, that smile is not gonna
last too long because, again, we have
orchestration and security challenges
here when we're invoking an external
service that we covered before.
When we are sending these SQL query
here to compare the vector that comes
from the input of the user, right?
The one that we are not storing to all
the vectors in our database, there is
gonna be some challenges because that's
custom SQL, and we might have to maintain
quite a lot of SQL here po- possibly.
Although I love SQL, and SQL is super
simple to understand and it has a
whole lot of complexity of course.
It's, it has so many things
depending on which database.
But you will have to create this custom
S- SQL anyway, and also because this SQL
query is the one that's gonna dictate
what kind of search you are doing, right?
So the retrieval part would be are
we gonna use vector search for this?
Which is where I explained before.
Yeah, we might want to use that.
All right.
That's not too difficult.
But what if that doesn't work well?
What if we want to do keyword search?
So instead of using a vector index,
we want to use a full text index,
for example, in the case of MariaDB.
That compares actually tokens,
or not tokens, but more like
the keywords, like the literally
the text that you type, right?
So it doesn't understand meaning, and
sometimes it's better, especially with
identifiers that don't that don't have
any semantic meaning at all, right?
So for those cases this
is a better strategy.
Keyword search over vector search.
You might want to search by an
identifier of a product or whatever
is that it represents in your
business logic, in your domain.
Or even better, we might want to do hybrid
search, and then we can use It is a way
to combine the results of both techniques,
and then you combine them using something
called a re- reciprocal rank function
so that you can actually compare them
and then pick the top results here.
Kind of a best of both worlds.
Now when again, when we are invoking an
external server service, orchestration
challenges here, particularly
this is the LLM, remember, it's a
different arrow, different point
in the, in, in OpenAI in this case
or whatever provider you're using.
Particularly here to handle
partial results, right?
Because we might want to show each
token as it's being generated by
DLM back to the user so that they
start to see something right away.
And security challenges
that we explained before.
So AI frameworks help with all of these,
of course but you will have to learn
not only the concepts and the vocabulary
used on each AI framework, but also the
relationships between each construct,
like classes and methods and functions
and constants and so forth, like for
configuration and this kind of stuff.
So in the end it's all code that
you will have to to maintain, right?
Because of that reason, it makes sense to
create a solution, a RAG solution, right?
And that's what we are gonna see
here, how to create a solution that's
reusable by each use case of a large
application or for each microservice
or a small application, right?
And when you investigate or research
about RAG, you find the literature,
and sometimes they refer to something
called like a naive RAG, which
is… There's nothing wrong with it.
It's just the most straightforward idea
that you can think of to get the context
that you need for the prompt, right?
Sometimes it's right there, like in the
products example that I show, right?
So it's just right there, so
it makes sense to, to use it.
Sometimes it just comes from a
unique place, and it never changes.
The requirements are not gonna
change too much in the future.
So we can just implement a RAG
at that level manually, right?
Like a case per case.
That would be like a bit like, It's called
I think, a naive RAG in the literature.
But there are other levels, and the
most important one for me, the most
useful one, it's a good compromise
here, it's to have modular RAG.
And here is a, an example of
such kind of architecture.
Now, the… I said an example because
obviously in software development you can
have multiple ways to architect solutions.
So this is just one of those.
All right?
And this mimics the RAG pipeline, right?
The whole, all the steps in RAG
And so that you have first one module,
which is the document ingestion module.
It should support incremental
ingestion through SQL file system
S3 storage, multi-format obviously,
and layout-aware extraction.
And for that, you can use something
like Docklein if you want to do
it locally, which is available
for Python and Java, I believe.
But I bet the other platforms should have
something similar, if not the same name.
There, there's gonna be something similar.
Or if you want to use something that
could be a bit more powerful and it's
ready to consume, you can use Lemma
parse, but then you have to trust
those guys because you will be sending
your information to their servers.
Now, you have… This module should
also deal with all the metadata
extraction and the document
storage and versioning, right?
And then the second module is the
chunking module, and it should
support multiple strategies because
not all documents are the same.
So you should be able to configure
which strategy you want to use
depending on the nature of your data.
So of course, it should support at least
a fixed sized chunking that we saw.
Sometimes that's more than enough.
A recursive, right?
The one that kind of goes from
large chunks to smaller chunks.
Semantic, which is calling an
LLM to decide how to do it.
Sentence, which is using some kind of
dividers in the text to, to detect where a
sentence ends, or token for cost control.
These kind of strategies could be could
be needed depending on the use case.
And sometimes you will need, like I said,
different in a s- in the same application,
different strategies depending on
the data that you're ingesting.
And it should allow you to
configure chunk size and overlap
as well as store the metadata.
Now, the module… The third module
here is the retrieval module.
It should handle the input to vector
embedding, that it's the input from the
user, whether it's a click or… And
you get the data from the context of
that click, or whether it's something
that the user typed then you have
to convert that to a vector, right?
So you can compare with all the
vectors that you have calculated in
the chunking with the chunking module.
And it should do well the
information retrieval.
So that's Or keyword search, vector
search, or hybrid search at least,
because sometimes like I explained
before, one is better than the other.
And remember, we need high
quality retrieval here.
That's key.
We don't want the LLM to hallucinate.
We cannot tell our users to add
glue to pizza or eat rocks, right?
And something I didn't explain before
is that you can add a phase like a step,
called the cross encoder re-ranking,
and this is at the retrieval level or
the retrieval part of the pipeline.
This basically reorders the
results so you get the best.
Sometimes 'cause you can do a
retrieval and get like a whole
or a big number of chunks, right?
But or you can get all of them, right?
That would be, It's the information is
there, but it doesn't make sense, right?
It's like sending the whole
document again to the, to a system.
We don't want that.
We want to save on, on costs and send
as little information as possible.
Also because then the LLM has
less chances of hallucinate.
Anyway, the cross encoder re-ranking
step will reorder results, evaluating
the relevance to the actual input.
And so for that, there are
libraries and services.
If you want to do it locally
have a look at something like
Flash Rank or eq-equivalent.
It's for Python or equivalent
on any other platform.
Or use a more advanced service
like Cohere, ready to consume
and maintained by, by these guys.
But again, you will have to trust
them for the same reasons that I
mentioned for Ollama parse, right?
And this retrieval method should
also allow you to do some kind
of metadata-based filtering so
that you can discard quickly
chunks and whole documents.
Now, the generation module is the
one that integrates with your LLM,
and you m-might have to support
several providers here, right?
So all the main ones,
because models are…
they change so quickly that… And you
really want to be using the best, right?
You want to… the
competition is crazy, right?
So you w-want to use the best model
that there is available, and you
might have to change, change of
provider or something like that.
Or if you have very sensitive information
that you cannot send to any other service
or outside your infrastructure, then you
can use something that like Ollama and
host your own modules sorry AI models.
Now, the generation module should also
construct the prompt with the retrieved
con- context from the previous module,
and maybe handle citations, right?
So that we can show the user,
"Hey, these these answer came from
these documents. You can go and
double-check that." It should handle
their LL- LLM response, right?
All the, the output, right?
The tokens and support
streaming for real-time display.
All right, so there's
a fifth module of sort.
I don't know how to place these
in this kind of architecture.
I place it as a kind of fifth
meta module or something.
It's it's a bit like everywhere which sh-
should maybe coordinate the end-to-end
invocation of the RAG pipeline, because
sometimes we might want to do the
whole thing at once, or maybe we want
to do document ingestion and chunking
in one step, and gener- and retrieval
and generation in another step, right?
Totally makes sense.
That's what most applications
are gonna do anyway.
So there should be something that allows
us to, to glue together these two, right?
Automatically for us.
And it should manage also maybe
asynchronous processing, because when
you are ingesting documents… And we're
thinking about this architecture, we're
gonna ingest thousands of documents
and create millions and millions of
chunks with their vectors, right?
So this should scale so… And
also it should be possible to do
these kind of ingestions, right?
At this level, at this size.
And we need to add some
asynchronous processing, right?
So we can, hey, just ingest all
documents I place on S3, right?
And I'll be checking whether
it's ready or not and notify
the user, for example, right?
And it should also… remember error
handling and retries, it should be
incorporated somewhere in here, and
maybe provi- provide the status monitor
of how things are going, and maybe a
health endpoint, this kind of thing
everything should be secure, of course.
So we need to add authentication
and authorization appropriately,
and maybe support multiple users
as well for different use cases and
applications, each one with maybe
with their own configurations.
So the way you pack these, where…
or do you deploy these, would you pack
it in one service, one single service?
Could be a microservice, right?
So it's one process that you can
scale then for example, horizontally
to add more processing power.
And the part be- here is that it should
connect to a vector database, right?
To store vectors and do the
retrieval part, so vector search.
And of course your database
should support full text as well.
Now, it should connect to an
embedder to calculate the vectors
and an LLM to generate the output.
All of these should be also be
exposed to services through a REST
API that application developers and
machine learning engineers can use
for building their own solutions.
And so that's what we did at MariaDB.
We call it MariaDB AI RAG.
It connects to MariaDB.
Anything MariaDB could be a single server
or a full cluster of many MariaDB servers
with high availability, maybe front-ended
by the powerful MaxScale database proxy.
Anything MariaDB and we have also
added a, an an MCP server, which
allows AI agents that you build or
you use to consume, especially their
retrieval part of MariaDB AI RAG.
Okay?
So that's a pretty powerful and
elegant architecture that we have
built that's ready for you to use.
You just have to invoke the REST API.
Configure three things there, right?
Maybe a couple more, and then consume
a REST API from your applications.
This scales to hundreds and
hundreds of documents, thousands
and thousands of documents and
and users as well as vectors.
Vectors could be millions
of vectors stored here.
So MariaDB AI RAG is an enterprise-grade
retrieval augmented generation solution
that integrates with MariaDB to
provide AI-powered document processing,
semantic search, and natural language
generation capabilities using the
ar- architecture that I just showed
you and all the features that I
show you in the modules, right?
The modular architecture to RAG, we have
implemented all of it and maybe even
more because this project continues to
evolve and new versions are being released
and probably developed as we speak.
Now, this solution, I see
it as a microservice really.
So we can use all the techniques that
we have learned and tools for managing
microservices deploying them observing
them, scaling them, all of this.
Currently it's deployed using a
simple Docker Compose file, right?
And it's part of the
MariaDB Enterprise platform.
And here are some of the products, right?
So the Enterprise Server for
production-ready workloads,
the Enterprise Cluster for high
availability and this kind of stuff.
They're really powerful.
MariaDB MaxScale database proxy.
I really love this product.
It has so many cool things.
It can even transform your MariaDB
relational database onto a NoSQL database.
So you can, for example, connect
an application that uses MongoDB.
You can use the… You didn't have
to change anything in the application
except the connection string,
and point it to MariaDB MaxScale.
And MaxScale's like a front-end for
all the the back-end of databases
which are relational databases.
And then you have NoSQL and SQL
database data in a single database.
So you can do joins with this,
with a single SQL query of
NoSQL and SQL kind of data.
That's pretty cool.
You have the MariaDB Enterprise
Manager to manage a fleet of database
servers, MariaDB database servers.
Really powerful.
I also have a video on this one on
YouTube if you are curious about it.
It has great US experience.
It's very similar of that of
MaxScale, which I really like.
And you have the Kubernetes operator,
ColumnStore for analytics, and Xa
for real-time analytics, and, as
well as an in-memory cache powered by
Great Gain, which is the enterprise
version of Apache Ignite, right?
All of this is available with Maria,
with the MariaDB Enterprise platform.
And of course, you have MariaDB
IRAG and the MPP server as well.
Obviously, it's an enterprise
platform support is available.
So let's go to the kinda demo.
All right?
And I happen to be the author of
these three books about Java framework
called Vaadin, which is pretty cool.
I really recommend checking it
out if you are a Java developer.
And and I'm writing a new book now.
I've been writing it for now
for, like almost two years
'cause I'm not using AI for this.
I'm using AI, but I'm not
using it for creating the text.
I'm typing each single word on this book.
I don't want to…
I want this to be created by
an engineer for engineers.
So if you like MariaDB, if you like this
talk, if you are curious about databases,
if you want to learn the basics of
databases, this is also the book for you.
So go to mariadb fordevelopers.com.
Scroll down that page, and if you
like what there is a form there
that you can use for subscribe to
our notification, so I send you an
email when the ebook's available.
But this is work in progress, so
I'm gonna use this one, all right?
Practical Vaadin.
Because there I placed this
photo of this really cute dog.
So I went to ChatGPT and I asked,
"What breed of dog is used in one of
the examples of the book Practical
Vaadin?" And it gave me the famous
lazy dog phrase or pangram, right?
Pangram is a phrase that has
all the letters in the alphabet.
So yeah, maybe I used that in the
book, and that bit, that chapter, that
section is available somewhere online.
So it found that.
But that's not what
I'm looking for, right?
That's not really what I asked.
And Gemini just hallucinated completely.
I have no idea what it's talking about.
This is not the right answer So I figured,
hey, let's create a solution with MariaDB
IRAG to find out more about this dog.
And yeah, I could have used ChatGPT
and upload the PDF file, and then it
will find a solu- the answer probably
in the 300 pages that this book has.
But that means that I just sent all that
number of tokens, so it's not scalable.
If I wanted to do something like this,
if I want to have thousands and thousands
of questions per hour about this book,
then I will have to upload the whole
book every single time in my application.
That's not scalable.
Doesn't make sense.
Again, this is RAG.
It's gonna take the chunks.
We're gonna retrieve the exact
information from the PDF file, or we
could ingest thousands of books here,
and it's gonna find the right one.
So it's super cool.
So I'm gonna use that to find
more about the dog, right?
And here I have two virtual machines.
One in f- in, on which, in which
I'm running, on which I'm running
MariaDB Enterprise Server, right?
And the other one, the other three panels,
I'm running everything that's oh, or I'm
gonna show things related to MariaDB IRAG.
So I have separated these in two machines.
So here I'm gonna show you
the configuration file.
These might have changed now with
the latest version, so don't pay too
much close attention to exact syntax,
but more like the ideas, more the
things that you can configure here.
All right?
So let me maximize this.
And the first thing you'll see is that you
can create a default admin user, right?
So I'm using admin@test.com
and password pass.
So I I can use the solution later.
Now, I'm also configuring
database connection, right?
So the host, the port, the user
password, and also the name of the
MariaDB database or the schema.
Database and schema, they
are synonyms in MariaDB.
In fact, in SQL, you can say, for
example, create schema MariaDB IRAG,
or create a database MariaDB IRAG.
Both are equivalent.
So here I'm passing that name.
So I created that before.
I just create… I just run literally
that sentence, that statement.
And then you will have to
configure the API keys, right?
The solution supports OpenAI,
Gemini, Google, Anthropic and others,
depending on what you are using, right?
Or OLMA if you want to host
it in your own infrastructure.
You can also configure that in this file.
So here I'm using Gemini, and here
I'm configuring the name of the models
and for the embedder, the number
of dimensions that it should use.
Now, this solution creates a bunch of
tables to restore the information, and
there are two tables that you might want
to customize their n- their names, right?
So the documents and the chunks,
and I call them RA- just like
that, documents and chunks.
Don't use… Don't do that in production.
Use something more descriptive.
But for this demo, that's
gonna work pretty well.
All right.
Here on this panel, I have the MCP
server running, or the logs rather.
It was running before, but
these are just the logs.
But we are gonna ignore that panel.
I'm not gonna use the MCP
server in this session.
Here, I'm running the actual
API, the RAG API process.
Or actually not running, I keep
saying that, but what I mean is
I'm showing the logs of this.
This was already running before
I took these screenshots.
The important bit's that's running there,
we can see the logs, so we are gonna
be able to see what's going on, okay?
Okay and that there is a URL, the
IP address where this is running,
and port 8000, which is… All
this is of course configurable.
So let's go there in our browser, port
8000, and we'll see the Swagger UI,
which is a UI for your REST services.
In this case, for MariaDB RAG.
So it shows the schemas, and it
shows the endpoints, and it shows
documentation, and it allows you to
invoke those visually from your browser.
But you can use any other tool that allows
you to basically call a REST endpoint.
First thing, we need to authorize to
get a token, so I'm gonna use admin
and pass, and then the solution, it's
gonna get the token, and then it's
gonna inject this in an HTTP header in
any subsequent requests to the service.
And so let me collapse all
this, and that this kind of
mimics the RAG pipeline, right?
With documents ingestion chunking,
retrieval, and generation.
And there are some other groups here
of endpoints like health system, right?
To check the the status
of this application, and
then authentication for…
well, to get the token and create,
create a new token and then authenticate
with your, with the service.
User management because it allows
you to create different kind of
users for different use cases or
applications or whatever you think
a user would mean in your domain
or in your architecture rather.
But even domain, I don't know.
Then you can do it with
the set of endpoints.
And documents, it's for ingestion,
management, sharing, 'cause you
can share documents between users.
The chunking we… That's
pretty clear what it is for.
And retrieval search is where you
retrieve the chunks, and generation
where you actually call the LLM
for get a prediction or the output.
And there's the orchestration thing
that we're gonna use in a moment.
So let's go to documents and do an ingest.
An ingestion, right?
So for this, I'm gonna click this button
here, try out, so we enable the form.
I click on choose file, and then
I select the PDF file, right?
Now I click execute, and as you
can see down there, it says curl.
It's just equivalent to doing that, right?
This is what's happening here.
This application is now needed.
Swagger UI is not really needed.
I hope you, you get that, right?
So it's just invoking this e- endpoint.
And it immediately shows this.
One document has been
queued for ingestion.
It it immediately returned that.
So we can go to our back-end,
and we see that effectively
something has started to happen.
And meanwhile, we can go to our database
and show the databases, and I see MariaDB
RAG there, which is what I created before.
So let me use that schema or
database, MariaDB RAG, and then
show the tables in that schema.
So I see the chunks and the documents,
which is what I configured in the blue
panel there in our configuration file.
So everything looks correctly.
And in order to check the status
of the ingestion, I can run this.
Select ID and status
from the documents table.
And by the time I run this
query, it… the process was
already completed, the ingestion.
So we can get back to our endpoints, and
now we're gonna do the chunking, right?
So we ingested the information.
It's in a format that's easy
for the algorithms to chunk.
And we're gonna do that.
So try out to enable the form,
and we can change these defaults.
For example, I reduce the
chunk size and overlap.
But actually, defaults work worked better.
But I wanted to show you that
you can do that at the… when
you're calling the the endpoint.
And I'm using the chunking
method recursive, okay?
So the one that kind of goes
and finds from big to small.
Size of of chunk to calculate the vector.
All right.
Address hole is for the semantic chunking,
which the solution also supports.
Now I click execute, and I
immediately get all documents we
own have been queued for chunking.
And I'm saying again immediately
because I want to highlight that
this is asynchronous, right?
So it's running in the background,
and we can use other in- other
endpoints to check the status
of this chunking process, right?
But since we're engineers, we can go
to the backend and see that in the logs
something's happening, looks correct.
While we can select the number
of chunks, we count the number
of chunks in the chunks table.
So the number of rows will
indicate how many we have.
So at first there are zero chunks, and
this, as I run this query repeatedly
again and again, it the number starts to
increase until the process is completed.
We ended up with around four
hundred chunks, each one with its
own vector and stored in MariaDB.
Okay, cool.
Back to the endpoints now.
We're gonna do the generation part, right?
So this is when we do the retrieval
and generation part of the RAG system.
So we click on try it out.
We introduce our query here,
what breed of dog's used.
We can specify the document IDs.
I knew it was number one,
so I'm gonna put number one.
But you can leave it empty to use all
the documents and hence all the chunks,
or if you know which documents are
relevant, then you can do that as well.
And you can specify a
retrieval method, right?
So we're gonna use hybrid search.
It's pretty cool.
Top K is the number of ch- chunks to
retrieve, so I'm gonna use ten here.
There are things that I'm gonna go through
that right now, but you get the idea.
Now I click execute, and after one
or two seconds, we get the answer.
The breed of dog the breed of dog used
in one of the examples of the book
Practical Writing is an English bulldog.
The dog's name is Draco.
And if we go to the book, we see that
his name is Draco, a funny, friendly,
and sometimes hectic English bulldog.
So it got it right.
This was Gemini again, which
hallucinated, I showed you before.
This time, Gemini didn't
hallucinate because we're using RAG.
So pretty cool.
We can continue to ask questions about
this book and we don't need to reingest
or recalculate chunks or anything.
They are ready in our database.
This book is lives in our
database securely, right in
MariaDB with all the chunks.
And all the vectors, so
we can do the retrieval.
And we will be sending to the to the
LLM only the bits that are relevant
to every question that we make, right?
However, if I remove everything, all the
data, and I start all over again, because
I used three, four endpoints before we
could have done this in one single call.
That's the full pipeline endpoint here.
So I'm gonna show you just for…
s- so that you get an idea.
Remember, you don't have to do
this because the documents are
already ingested and chunked.
But if I undo everything, I could
have done this just in one step.
It's just that would be be too boring.
It's just one step, right?
It's that easy to use
Smart HTTP AI, right?
So we choose the file, and then we type
our query, and then top, top K, and then
maybe the retrieval method, hybrid search.
And we arrive, or the LLM
arrives to a correct answer.
Now, the wording is different because
LLMs are are gonna produce different
output every time you ask something,
even if you ask exactly the same, right?
They are not deterministic unless you
use temperature equals zero, which
you could have in this solution.
There was a parameter somewhere there.
I di- I don't know if you catched
that, but it would be possible.
But I didn't, so I was gonna
use different words, right?
But the answer is correct.
English bulldog.
The dog's name is Laraku.
It's even adding the name here.
All right.
So let me pause here for a
moment so I catch my breath and
what we just did there was we
invoked a full RAG pipeline with
automatic not automatic, but with
authentication and authorization.
All of that was handled for us.
We just had to authenticate.
Automatic error and retry logic,
asynchronous document ingestion, this
case PDF, but with the option for
other formats or even a SQL query.
What else?
A recursive chunking with overlap
with the option for fixed size,
sentence, and semantic, and token.
Metadata and versioning was handled
by us automatically by this.
The information is stored in database.
And with the hybrid search retrieval.
And what else?
You can monitor these, you can scale,
you can ingest thousands of documents,
create millions and millions of vectors.
It's scalable
We could have use S3 or add a reader
ranker and maybe do some monitoring
and reporting and show how the partial
result or streaming of the output works.
But you get the idea.
Everything is ready
there for you to consume.
So I don't know about you,
but I find these pretty cool.
We call it RAG in a box.
So MariaDB AI RAG is currently in
beta, but it's feature complete.
If you are watching the recording,
maybe it's now actually not in beta
anymore, so please go check that, and
you can try it out with this URL if
you want to get inspiration on how
to build your own solutions or even
better, if you want to already use
these and not reinve-vent the wheel.
The documentation, you
find it at mariadb.com/docs
That's what I want to show you today.
These are my coordinates.
Please feel free to contact
me anytime you want.
Thank you