Speaker 26: Hi, everyone.
Thanks for joining.
I'm Ankur Aggarwal.
I'm a software engineer
at Meta, where I work on
privacy-preserving AI infrastructure.
Today, I want to talk about something
that I think is one of the most
important unsolved problems in the
agentic AI stack, which is: How do
we secure the data flows between
AI agents and databases, especially
when those agents are running inside
confidential compu-compute environments?
That's a mouthful.
So let me break down what actually it
means over the next twenty minutes or so.
Let's start with the problem first.
Over the past couple of years,
confidential computing has made enormous
progress Thanks to Meta, we now have
trusted execution environments, TEEs,
that can run full large language model
inside verified isolated enclaves.
The model runs, and nobody outside
that enclave can see what it's doing.
That's good.
But here's the thing.
The moment that model needs to do
something useful, for instance, query a
database, call an external API, or invoke
a tool, the security boundary collapses.
Think about it.
You have spent millions
of dollars engineering an
isolated enclave for inference.
Then your model issues a SQL query over a
plain text connection to a database that
has no idea it's talking to an enclave.
All that security work and the data
just walks out through the tool layer.
This is the gap we are going to--
we're going to talk about today.
Now, you might be thinking, "Okay, but
we always had APIs calling databases.
What's so different about
agentic AI?" Three things make
this fundamentally harder.
First, multi-step reasoning.
Unlike a traditional API call
that's fire and forget, an agent
executes long reasoning chains.
It might issue ten, fifteen, twenty
tool calls in a single workflow.
Each one of those is a potential
data exfiltration vector.
It's not one door to guard,
it's a hallway full of them.
Second, live databases access.
These agents aren't just
reading static files.
They're querying structured
enterprise data in real time.
Health records, financial
ledgers, legal documents.
The sensitivity of what's being
accessed is extremely high.
Third, and this is a subtle
one, cumulative leakage.
No single query reveals everything.
If you look at any individual tool
call, it might seem fine, but across a
fifteen-step workflow, sensitive context
accumulates in the model context window.
You can reconstruct a complete patient
record or a financial profile from
fragments that individually look harmless.
This is a new class of privacy risk
that traditional access controls
w- weren't designed to handle.
So let's discuss our roadmap for today.
We'll, we'll be covering four things.
First, why standard MCP, that's
the Model Context Protocol,
breaks in secure environments.
Second, I'll introduce Confidential
MCP or CMCP, the extension
we have designed to fix this.
Third, we'll go deep on two key
primitives: the anonymization transform
layer and the attested egress policies.
And fourth, we'll talk about
operational realities because
architectural diagrams are great, but
production is where things get real.
So let's strive-- let's dive in.
Let's first discuss about what an MCP is.
For those who are unfamiliar with it, the,
the Model Context Protocol is Anthropic's
open standard for connecting LLM agents
to external tools and data sources.
It's a great protocol.
It defines how an agent discover tools,
calls them, and get results back.
It is becoming a de facto
standard in the agentic AI space.
However, and this is a critical
issue, MCP was designed for
connected, trusted environments.
It assumes that you are in a world
where endpoints can be freely inspected
and where transport is inherently
trustworthy, where you can dynamically
negotiate capabilities and runtime.
None of those holds inside a TEE
operating under zero trust assumptions.
When every interaction must be
authenticated, constrained, and privacy
preserving by design, standard MCP becomes
a liability at the enclave boundary.
It can expose metadata, weaken
policy enforcement, and create
integration gaps that are very
difficult to close after the fact.
What we need is a protocol layer
that treats the enclave perimeter
as a hostile external interface,
not just at productive time, runtime
And that's exactly what we built.
Let me get specific about
where MCP breaks down.
There are three fundamental weaknesses.
Number one, transport security gaps.
Standard MCP connection use TLS, which
is fine for encryption in transit,
but TLS cannot prove enclave identity.
It can't tell you the server on the
other end of that connection is actually
executing inside a legitimate TEE.
You need mutual attestation for
that, and MCP doesn't have it.
So you end up with an encrypted channel
to do something, and you don't know what.
Number two, dynamic
schema and tool discovery.
Tool schemas and database schemas are
dis-- uh, are discovered at runtime.
The agent says, "What tools
do you have?" And the server
responds with a full manifest.
In the confidential
context, this is a problem.
That schema metadata is itself sensitive.
It reveals what data exist,
what columns are available, and
what the structure looks like.
You've just created an unauthenticated
channel through which sensitive
information can leak before any
actual query is even executed.
And number three,
authentication mismatches.
MCP's credential model
assumes ambient identity.
OAuth token, API keys, bearer tokens,
but these don't have ambient identity.
They have attestation.
They can cryptographically prove what
code is running inside them, but they
can't just present a bearer token
the way a regular service would.
MCP has no native support for
attestation-based credential
delegation, which means you're
left with awkward workarounds
that undermine the security model.
These three weaknesses together mean
that standard MCP is not a good fit
for purpose-- for that purpose in
confidential compute environments
So what do we do about it?
We introduce confidential MCP or cMCP.
cMCP is a backward compatible extension
to Anthropic's model context protocol.
I want to emphasize that
word backward compatible.
If you have existing MCP
tooling, it still works.
We are not asking anyone,
anyone to rip and replace.
cMCP adds new capabilities
on top of existing protocol.
It's designed specifically for LLM
agents operating inside trusted
execution environments that need
auditable, privacy-preserving
access to tools and databases.
The design draws on architecture
validated by Meta's WhatsApp private
processing system and our broader
confidential computing practice.
And it introduces three new primitives.
One, a three-zone service topology
that defines clear trust boundaries.
Two, an anonymization transform
layer that controls what data
the model can actually see.
And three, a tested egress policies
that enforce what can leave the enclave.
The first primitive is a
three-zone service topology.
Zone one is the untrusted client zone.
This is where external requests
originate, the user, the application,
and whatever is invoking the agent.
We treat this zone as fully untrusted.
Zone two is the confidential enclave.
This is where the CMCP runtime
and the LLM agent live.
The zone enforces attestation.
It's the only zone in the entire
topology that has visibility
to raw, undeduced data.
Everything that happens here is
cryptographically verifiable.
Zone three is the data plane.
This is where your databases
and tool servers live.
They serve queries, but
only attested queries.
They verify that the request is coming
from legitimate enclave before responding.
The key insight here is that zone
boundaries are enforced cryptographically.
This isn't, this isn't just a logical
separation on a network diagram.
Only attested policy-bound
traffic may traverse the enclave
perimeter in either direction.
Zone one never sees the raw data.
Zone three only responds
to verified enclaves.
Zone two is the control checkpoint
where all privacy logic is applied.
If you are familiar with the classic
DMG pattern in net-network security,
this is the confidential computing
equivalent, but with cryptographic
enforcement instead of firewall rules.
The second primitive is the
anonymization transform layer, or ATL.
The ATL sits between the LLM agent
and the raw database response.
When a database returns data
to the enclave, it doesn't
go straight to the model.
It passes through an ATL first
The ADL applies what we call
entropy-bounded controls.
These determine how much
identifying signal can pass
through any single tool call.
What does it mean in practice?
Three things.
Token-level suppression of PIIs, bef--
which means before database results enter
the model context window, the ADL scans
for personally, personally identifiable
information and suppresses it.
Names, Social Security numbers,
email addresses, phone numbers, these
get redacted or replaced with token
before the model ever sees them.
Entropy budgets.
This is where it get
int-- it gets interesting.
We don't, we don't just look
at the individual fields.
We track the cumulative information
entropy across an entire workflow.
Remember that cumulative leakage
problem I mentioned earlier?
The entropy budget addresses it directly.
Even if each individual field passes the
PI check, the system enforces a ceiling
on how much total identity information
can accumulate across multiple calls.
If the budget is exhausted,
subsequent queries are either
blocked or further restricted.
And the last one is auditable transforms.
Every single redaction, every
suppression, every transform is
logged to the attestation record.
This means you can go back after
the fact and prove exactly what the
model saw and what was withheld.
That's critical for compliance
and for incident response.
The third primitive is
attested egress policies.
This is the enforcement mechanism.
It works in three stages.
Stage one, policy authoring.
This is operators.
That's your security team,
your compliance team.
Define, define type egress rules.
These specify which fields can leave
the enclave, at what cardinality,
and to which downstream recipients.
Think of it as a fire-firewall
rule set, but for data semantics
rather than network packets.
Stage two is the enclave binding.
Here's what makes this different
from a regular policy engine.
The policies are cryptographically
bound to the enclave measurement at
boot time via remote attestation.
That means they literally
cannot be modified at runtime.
An attacker who compromises the runtime
cannot weaken the egress policy.
It was baked in at boot, and
the attestation proves it.
The s-stage three is
enforcement at egress.
Every single outbound response, everything
that tries to leave the Zone two is
evaluated against the bound policy.
If it doesn't comply,
it's blocked and flagged.
No exceptions, no override,
and no just this once.
This gives you something very hard to
get in traditional systems: provable
tamper-resistant data flow control
at the boundary of your AI system
Okay.
Now let's, l-let's discuss something,
uh, from the real-world environment.
Architectural diagrams are beautiful.
They look great in slide decks,
but production is where systems
actually prove themselves.
And deploy-- deploying CMCP in
production surfaces challenges
that the diagrams won't capture.
In practice, you are reconciling CMCP
with the existing database infrastructure
that wasn't designed for attestation.
You're tuning for latency and throughput
in systems that have tight SLAs.
You're dealing with deployment
pipelines, observability, access
control, and incident response.
It also requires
organizational challenges.
You need clear ownership.
You need disciplined rollout procedures.
You need operational runbooks.
Privacy infrastructure is not something
you deploy once and walk away from.
Let me talk about the three biggest
challenges we have encountered.
First and foremost,
operational challenges.
The challenge one is the query
overri-- q-query overreach.
This one actually surprised us.
Smaller open source models and
hon-honestly, even some larger ones,
have tendency to over-request data.
They issue broad select star patterns
when they only need two columns.
They request entire tables
when they need a single row.
This violates a minimum necessary
principle, and it means the ADL is
doing a lot of heavy lifting to redact
the data that it-- that should never
have been fetched in the first place.
The lesson here is that
ADL alone is insufficient.
You also need query normalization, a
layer that rewrites or constrains queries
before they even reach the database.
Think of it, think of it as a
least privileged query planner that
sits between the model's intent
and the actual SQL execution.
The challenge two is one that I've
already covered before, but, but diving
deeper into it, cumulative context risk.
I mentioned this earlier as
a theoretical risk, but in
production, we can quantify it.
Each reasoning step leaves residue
in the model's context window.
Across a fifteen-step workload--
workflow, the aggregate context
can reconstruct a record that no
single step would have exposed.
We have seen cases where a model
couldn't access a patient's name
directly, but after querying date of
birth, ZIP code, diagnosis code, and
prescription history across separate
tool calls, the combination was enough
to uniquely identify an individual.
This is why the entropy
budget is so critical.
It is not about individual queries, it's
about the cumulative information gain.
And the challenge three
is performance overhead.
If you look in the real world,
attestation hand, handshakes, ATL
transforms, and policy evaluation
all adds significantly to latency.
You're talking about fifteen to
forty milliseconds per tool call,
and sometime even extending up to one
hundred to two hundred milliseconds,
depending upon the complexity of
the policy and size of the response.
For, for batch analytics, that's
negligible, but for real-time data
systems with sub-hundred millisecond
SLAs, you need to think carefully about
pipeline design, precomputed attestation
caches, lazy policy evaluation,
and response streaming are some of
the techniques that we have used to
bring this down to acceptable levels
Moving on, one of the most
compelling aspects of CMCP is that
the attested egress policy is, are
designed to be regulation-aware.
What does it mean?
It means you can encode regulatory
requirements directly into the enclave's
boot configuration as policy templates.
For healthcare, HIPAA's minimum
necessary standard can be
expressed as an egress policy.
Only the fields clinically
necessary for the agent's task are
permitted to leave the enclave.
For financial services, GLBA's data
sharing restrictions and GDPR cross-border
transfer controls can be encoded.
If a query result would cross a
jurisdiction boundary, the policy can
block it or require additional redaction.
For legal attorney-client privilege
constraints can be enforced.
An agent doing contracted intelligence
wor- work can be prevented from
surfacing privileged con- co-
communication in its output.
The key point is compliance
is not a separate system
you bolt on after the fact.
It's baked into the cryptographic
boot measurement of the enclave.
It's provable, auditable,
and tamper-resistant.
Let's look at some of the key
takeaways, and I want to leave
you with three key takeaways.
Take, takeaway number one: TEE plus
MCP does not equal secure by default.
If you're running LLM inference
inside a trusted execution environment
today and connecting it to a database
via standard MCP, you have a gap.
Confidential inference protects the model.
It does not protect the data
flowing to and from that model.
The access layer must be
independently hardened.
Take, takeaway number two:
CMCP is backwards compatible.
You don't need to throw away
your existing MCP tooling.
CMCP adds the attestation,
transform, and egress layers on
top of what you already have.
Adoption is incremental,
not revolutionary.
And takeaway number three:
egress policy is a control plane.
If you take one architectural idea
from this talk, let it be this.
Enforceable cryptographically bound
egress policies are the primitive
that makes AI data fl- flows
auditable and compliant at scale.
Without them, we are relying
on model behavior and hope.
With them, we have verifiable guarantees.
That's it for me.
Thank you for all your time and attention.
If you are building agentic systems
that touch sensitive data and, and
let's be honest, if you're at a database
DevOps conference, you're probably,
you are, you are working on it.
I'd love to learn about how these
ideas might apply to your stack.
Thank you so much.
My name is Ankur, and you've
been a great audience.