Speaker 8: Hi, everyone.
I'm Ritwik Pandya.
I manage engineering teams focused
on large-scale payment platform at
the leading financial institution.
Today, I want to talk about
the problem many of us have
seen in the production systems.
There is sudden p99 latency spike
during the peak hours, where the
response times jumps nearly four-fold.
I'll walk you through a single
architectural shift around the
deterministic routing and the data
locality, which significantly can improve
the system behavior, delivering higher
throughput and reducing the tail latency
by, say, fourteen-- fifty-nine percent,
which we saw, all on the same hardware
and the same database infrastructure.
So here's the story.
Our base p99 latency was around
twelve milliseconds, and during the
peak hours, it jumped to forty-seven
milliseconds, nearly four times slower.
Transactions started timing out,
clients retried automatically.
Retry piled up on top of the
existing load, and very quickly, we
were dealing with the retry storm.
The SLA alert fired, pagers went off.
At first, it was obvious answer to be
that, "Hey, add more nodes." So we did.
But latency didn't improve.
In fact, it got slightly worse.
That was the key insight.
The problem wasn't the capacity,
the problem was the coordination
overhead caused by the randomness.
Every request was l-landing on
the random node, while the actual
data often lived somewhere else.
So each transaction triggered the
extra coordination, cross-node
lookups, replication waits,
log checks, cache misses.
The system was spending more
time cor- coordinating the work
than actually doing the work.
Think of it like a hospital where
every patient is assigned to
the random doctor on each visit.
The doctor doesn't have your record
locally, so they first fetch the
files, call the departments, verify the
context, and then begin the treatment.
That's effectively what our
database was doing under the load.
So we ask a simple question: What
if every transaction could land to
the node that already has its data?
So before getting in the solution,
it's worth grounding this why
the latency actually matters.
In transactional systems, latency
isn't the performance metrics.
It's directly translate
into the business impact.
There was a well-known pattern across
the industry, and Amazon reported that
every additional hundred millisecond
of the latency impacted revenue.
Google observed measurable query drop-offs
with the few hundred millisecond delay.
Same goes with other top industry vendors.
We saw the same effect operationally.
When our P99 climbed up from
twelve millisecond to forty-seven
millisecond under the peak load,
about three point two requests,
percent requests began timing out.
And every failed transaction had a real
downstream cost: retries, operational
overhead, customer friction, SLA exposure.
At our scale, even the few
percentage points become
materially expensive very quickly.
At same time, the business was focusing
nearly twice transaction growth over
the next year, but the infrastructure
budget wasn't doubling with it.
So simply scaling horizon-
horizontally by adding more nodes
wasn't a sustainable answer.
That constraint focused us to
rethink architecture itself,
not just add more hardware.
So this was our baseline
architecture where we started.
A client request hits to load
balancer, and the load balancer
selects an application node randomly.
Let's say node one.
But the data for the transaction
may actually owned by node three.
So node one now has locate the correct
range of leaseholder, coordinate
across the nodes, wait for replication
acknowledgment, acquire locks, and only
then execute the transac-transaction.
Every additional network hop adds latency.
Every coordination boundary introduce
the queu-queuing and contention.
Over the time, four major
problem become obvious.
First, every request effectively
rediscover data locally from the scratch.
The request path had no awareness
where data already lived.
Second, writes triggered synchronously,
cross-node coordination happens.
Transactions spend significant time
waiting for-- waiting on replication
and consensus na- overhead rather
than doing the useful work.
Third, utilization become uneven.
Some nodes saturated while
other remained underutilized.
We were paying for the cluster capacity
we couldn't ef- efficiently consume.
And the fourth one, under the
peak concurrency, lock contention
become increasingly visible.
The queue depth grew, retries increased,
and the tail latency amplified rapidly.
This is actually a default behavior
of many distribus- distributed
systems under the random routing.
A moderated load, it works reasonably
well, but as concurrency increases,
the coordination overhead starts
dominating the request path
We tried to instrumentate the
entire request path under-- and to
understand where those forty-seven
milliseconds were actually going.
And the result were honestly surprising.
Around twelve milliseconds were
spent just re-resolving metadata
and determining where data lived.
Another eighteen millisecond went
into cross-node coordination,
replication, acknowledgments, et cetera.
Lock contention contributed roughly
eight millisecond under concurrency.
Connection management and
network overhead added ano-
other another four milliseconds.
So when we added everything up the
real insight became o- obvious.
The most of the latency wasn't the
computation, it was coordination.
The system was spending majority of its
time locating the data, synchronizing
the state, waiting for locks, and
coordinating across the nodes.
Only small fraction of the request
path was actual transaction execution.
A useful analogy is say, a restaurant
where the kitchen spend nearly all
of its time coordinating the orders,
locating in-ingredients, and handling
work between the stations, and only tiny
portion of actual-- actually cooking food.
At some point, adding
more cooks doesn't help.
The operational overhead itself
becomes the bottleneck, and that was
the architectural realization for us.
We didn't need bigger system.
We needed system to coordinate less.
And just to be precise, these
numbers are the representative
attribution from the distributed
tracing and span-level analysis.
Percentage decomposition is never the
mathematically perfect in the practice,
but the proposition were consistent
and reproducible across the runs.
That become the turning point of
discussions with the leadership
because the optimization opportunity
was suddenly very visible
Now, one architectural decision
changed everything for us.
Instead of routing transaction randomly,
we started routing each transaction to the
node most likely to already own its data.
Routing decision were deterministic
based on the key hashing, and the
execution was in parallel with isolated
worker pools to avoid shared contention.
That becomes core architecture principle
behind the entire system, and now
underlying idea itself isn't new.
The system like Dynamo introduced the
partition-aware routing years ago,
and later research such as Calvin
explored deterministic transaction
scheduling at the database layer.
What we found interestingly was applying
the same locality principle earlier in
request path and applic-- and at the
application and routing layer itself.
Because once the request arrives near
the correct data from the beginning,
an entire category of coordination
overhead start disappearing.
There will be a fewer metadata lookups,
fewer cross-node hops, better cache
locality, lower lock, lock contention.
So the real gain real gain wasn't about
inventing faster algorithm, it was about
eliminating unnecessary movement of data
and coordinating that never needed to
be happen in the first place itself.
A few quick words on why this approach
works particularly well in the
modern distributed data-databases.
Most distributed databases today already
optimize around the locality internally.
They partition data into ranges and shards
replicate those ranges across the nodes,
and use consensus protocol like Raft to
coordinate ownership and consistency.
The important realization for us was, if
the database is already locality-aware
internally, the application layer
should stop behaving randomly.
Under traditional random routing,
request lands on any random nodes,
and the database spends additional
time forwarding the request,
resolving the ownership, coordinating
replicas, and managing cross-node
communication Solution is deterministic
routing that changes everything.
By routing the request based on
the same partition key used by the
database and application increase the
probability that request arrives near
the node already coordinating that data.
That redu-reduces unnecessary hops,
improves cache locality, lower
coordination overhead, and shorten
the critical transaction path.
The database still hurdles
correctness, replication, failover,
rebalancing, and consensus underneath.
We are not replacing the
distributed coordination here.
We are reducing how often the system needs
expensive coordination on the hot path.
This broader principle shows across many
distributed systems, from the Dynamo-style
partitioning to locality-aware
databases like Spanner, CockroachDB,
You have ByteDB, TiDB, and others.
So how could we actually implement this?
At the conceptual level, the
routing logic is sup-surprisingly
simple and very bookish in a way.
That take your transactions primary
key, hash it, and map that hash
to one of the node in the cluster.
Simple.
And that hash tells the application
which node should handle the request.
So in that way, there is no random
load balancing, no request path
metadata lookup will be there, no
guessing where the data might live.
And because the routing is
deterministic, the same key
consistently lands on the same node.
That consistency is what creates locality.
Now, in production, we don't
actually use naive modulo hashing.
Modulo works fine in examples, but behaves
badly when the cluster membership changes.
For example, if you add or remove a node
and suddenly the most of the keyspace
gets remapped, that creates massive cache
churn and unnecessary redistribution.
So instead, we use consistent
hashing with virtual nodes.
With consistent hashing, when the
node is added or removed, only a
small portion of the keyspace moves.
This is the same foundation idea used
in Akamai, Cloudflare, Dynamo-style
partitioning, and large-scale
distribus-- distributed caches.
Once we introduced the deterministic
routing, the several benefits
started compounding naturally.
Request bitten-- requests become
predictable, metadata resolution
disappeared from the hot path, cache
locality improves because same key
repeatedly hit the same execution path,
and load distribution stayed relatively
balanced because the hashing spread
keys uniformly across the cluster.
One important caveat here
the choice of key matters.
The routing key needs to be stable, high
car-- high cardinality is needed, and
closely aligned with your access pattern.
You don't want to hash on something
mutable, and you definitely
don't want keyspaces with only
handful of possible values.
Otherwise, you simply move the bottleneck
instead of eliminating it so now routing
solved only one part of the problem but
execution was the other half, right?
Because deterministic routing alone
improves the locality, but it-- if
all requests still execute through the
shared execution path, connection simply
moves somewhere else in the system.
So we paired deterministic routing
with thread-to-node affinity.
So this is second fold
of the solution here.
Say thread zero primarily handled
work for node zero, thread
one for node one, and so on.
Each worker thread own its
own dedicated connection pool
to its assigned node group.
No shared pools, no cross-threaded
coordination during the connection
ac-acquisition, no l-lock contention
around the pooled resources, and this part
mattered more than we initially expected.
Our first implementation actually used
shared connection pool across threads.
Under load, we performed terribly.
Thread spend surprisingly amount of
time containing the pooled connection,
waiting for the synchronization
and fighting each other internally.
In some scenarios, contention
become worse than the original
single-threaded baseline.
Again, the restaurant analogy here.
If every waiter can serve every
table, they constant-- constantly
cross paths, interrupts each other,
and compete for the same space.
But if each waiter owns a dedicated
section, movement become predictable
and collisions largely disappear.
That's effectively what
thread affinity gives us.
The round-robin scheduling kept work even
evenly distributed across the workers.
Asynchronous input/output
prevented threads from the
blocking on the network wa-waits.
Persistent connection eliminated the
repeated setup and teardown cos-cost.
So now let's talk about the operational
side of this Because we are not optimizing
the algorithm here, we are, and in such
systems, we run them on Kubernetes.
In our case, we realized this thing
very rapidly or very quickly that
default Kub- Kubernetes behavior is
often optimized for general availability
and not for the tail latency.
And that's where we tried to-- we took
s- say four configuration decisions here.
One is stateful sets of database layer.
Distributed database rel-rely
heavily on stable network identity
and persistent storage, and that's
where stateful sets help us.
It gives us predictable predictable
pod identities, durable volumes,
and safer rolling updates during
the quorum-sensitive operations.
The second one is node affinity.
So we try to co-locate the
application workloads a- as close
as the database nodes, and in some
cases, you can say that it's the
same zone, same rack, and same NUMA.
And that less network distance shaved
a few millisecond off in the request
path which kind of helped us out a
lot with P99 and P nin- 95 latency.
The third one is autoscaling based on
the latency-aware signal instead of CPU.
Y- because default HPA policy
typically reacts to the CPU
utilization, but in general, CPU
is often lacking the indicator for
transactional latency problems.
So he- this is where the
latency-aware signals helped us a lot.
And the finally th- the next configuration
what we try to do is guaranteed QoS.
So we set CPU request equal to the limit
of the latency-sensitive workloads and
that that configuration helped us a lot.
So after moving the critical
workload into guaranteed QoS or,
quality of service, latency various
dropped notice significantly and the
tail behavior becomes more stable
Now here are a few results which
I would like to mention here.
S- P50 latency dropped around
eighteen milliseconds to eight
milliseconds, so it's about fifty-six
percent of reduction, right?
P95 went from thirty-four
millisecond to fourteen.
P99, which was the metric hurting us
operationally the most, dropped from
forty-seven millisecond to nineteen
millisecond which is our primary
example where we started all this story.
So roughly fifty-nine
percent improvement here.
And throughput improved
even more dramatically.
So overall, with all this configurations
decisions we saw a significant
improvement in our application.
Few of the concepts here might be very
specific to, CockroachDB side of things,
but the same principle is applied to any
of the modern distributed data store.
So systems like Amazon DynamoDB,
the partition data by the stable
partition key is already there.
The distributed SQL systems like
TiDB, YugaDB, or other distributed
ranges, tablets, or region
across the nodes using similar
locality-aware concepts internally.
The implementation details might vary
that some use Raft groups, some use
placement rules some use partition
map or tablet leaders, but the
architectural data or architectural idea
is consistent across all of them, that
data already has the placement strategy.
The closer your application routing
aligns with the placement strategy,
the less coordination of the s-
system performs on the hot path.
It give, it will give you the advantage
in terms of there will be a fewer
cross-node hops there will be a
better cache locality there will be a
lower coordination overhead, and more
predictable tail latency will be there.
Overall, it will benefit the system.
Now In, in my experience there were
three major lessons I can talk about.
Fun-- first one is the deterministic
routing without the resiliency is fragile.
Our initial implementation was extremely
straightforward, say, which I also
talked about, that hash the key, route
to the target node, execute the request.
And operationally, it worked great
until the node failed, right?
So at that point, every request
mapped to the to that node immediately
start failing, and customer
impact was visible within seconds.
So we evolved the routing layer
to become a replication-aware.
If preferred target was unavailable,
the request could fail over
to the another replica already
hosting the same key range.
We introduced s- a small temporary
queues for in-flight requests
during the failover windows.
And the key lesson key thing here
was the predictability is valuable,
but predictability without graceful
degradation becomes a liability.
The second learning here is The
parallelism without isolation can
actually reduce the throughput, right?
Our first multithreaded implementation
used shared connection pool because it
looked more resource efficient on paper.
In reality, threads spend huge amount of
time contending for the pooled connection
and synchronize the resources internally.
And under the load throughput
actually dr-dropped below the
single-threaded baseline, as I
mentioned in my previous slide also.
The fix here was isolating the
execution path, dedicated connection
pool per workers thr- worker
thread and per-node affinity group.
That changed the system
behavior completely.
The third one is default
Kubernetes behavior, often
hostile to low tail latency.
Our staging benchmark looked ex-excellent,
but the production latency consistently
ran about fifteen milliseconds
slower under the comparable traffic.
We spent weeks investigating network
paths, databa- database tuning, garbage
collection, even tracing overl- overhead.
The real culprit turned out to be a CPU
throttling from the Linux scheduler.
Because our workloads were running
in burstable QOS, the kernel
was throttling container once
they exceeded the quota windows.
That scheduling jitter was the
leaking directly into our P99 latency.
Once we moved the latency-sensitive
services to the guaranteed QOS by setting
the request equals to limits, the tail
latency stabilized drama- dramatically.
So this, these were few of our learning
and, few of the things which we improvised
later I also want to very clear about
the limitation of this approach.
The deterministic routing is powerful,
but it's not a silver bullet.
There are several scenarios where
the model starts breaking down or
requires additional operation handling.
First, say, hot partition.
It's a well-known DB problem.
If one tenant, one merchant or customer
suddenly generates where, heavy
amount of traffic, all that traffic
still hashes the same execution path.
And deterministic routing improves
locality, but it cannot automatically in
parallel put the single hotkey, right?
At that point, we need additional
strategy splitting the partition,
introducing sub-sharding or isolating
hot tenants onto dedicated capacity.
Second, leaseholder movement and the
corresponding kind of rebalancing.
So in distributed databases, ownership of
the ranges or partitions is not static.
The leaseholder move during the failover,
balancing, and topology changes.
That means the routing layer is operating
on the probability and not the certainty.
Sometimes the request lands
exactly where you want it.
Sometimes it lands near the
right replica and requires
the additional hop internally.
So the routing layer has to be-- has to
tolerate the misses gracefully, right?
In our case, we added retry-aware
routing and the fallback path for
scale lo- locality assumptions.
The third third one is multi-key
and distributed transactions.
Our biggest gain come from the
common case where the requests
primarily operate on a single
partition key or a localized dataset.
If transactions regularly spans more
shards, ranges, or tenants, then
coordination overhead still exists and
relative improvement becomes smaller.
The fourth one is topology
and rebalancing complexity.
So As the cluster scale node changes,
range range change rebalance happens.
The traffic distribution
evolves over the time.
Maintaining the locality awareness at the
application layer introduces operational
complexity around the observability
partition movement, and adaptive balance.
So we need visibility into where
the data actually lives and how that
placement changes over the time.
So we need to monitor it very closely.
S- so the important takeaway
is deterministic routing is the
optimization for the common path.
It improves locality, reduces a- avoidable
coordination and makes the system more
efficient under the normal high volume tr-
traffic patterns But it does not replace
failover handling distributed transaction
coordination hotspot management or
capacity planning under squid workloads.
So
So where are the opportunities
to for improvement, right?
So first is adaptive rebalancing.
So traffic patterns are never static.
Over the time, some tenant
becomes significantly hotter than
others, and static partitioning
eventually creates imbalance.
So one area we are exploring is
dynamic rebalancing, automatic how
we can make it more auto in nature.
So automatic redistribution, heavily
accessed of heavily accessed key ranges
without interrupting the live traffic.
In some cases, that may even
isolating the extremely hot
partition onto dedicated capacity
that could be one of the solution.
The second is multi-region
deterministic routing.
So today, locality mostly exists within
the cluster or regional boundary.
The next step is extending that
routing awareness across the region.
Instead of routing requests to any healthy
node globally, the system can we can
prioritize to the nearest region, right?
So the most likely to already host
the relevant data or leaseholder.
The third one is routing-aware failover.
So traditional failover mechanism
typically redirect traffic towards
any available healthy node.
But in distributed system, not all
healthy nodes are equally optimal, right?
So we can-- We are continuing to evolve
the routing layers, so failover decision
remain locality-aware redirecting requests
towards the replica already close to the
affected key ranges instead of introducing
unnecessary coordination after the failure
event wherever problem started, right?
Yeah that's still, one
version is still there.
The fourth one is deeper
observation integration.
That's one of the
biggest opportunity here.
Which keys are becoming hot?
Which ranges are producing
elevated tail latency?
Which nodes are consistently
becoming coordination bottlenecks?
The earlier system
The earlier system can detect locality
imbalance sooner it can respond before
user visibility degradation occurs, right?
But across all this enhancement, the
underlying principle remains unchanged,
that computation becomes more efficient
when the request execute clo- as close
as possible to the data they need.
Everything else is essential
refinement around the core idea.
Now what you as an audience
can do here, right?
So check your database's
partition strategy.
Check the keys and try to get the sample
data how many transactions or how many
hits you get on the node for those keys.
Set Kubernetes resources request
limit to your latency-critical pods.
Try to come up or, measure the P95 and
P99 compare before and after and see
how much impro- improvement is there.
And, Instrument the node hit ratio
track the percentage of request
landing on the correct node and try
to optimize those numbers there.
So that, that could be a good start.
And then based on that, I think and few
of the approaches which I just talked
about some configuration decision
could be taken and definitely there,
there will be a hu-huge improvement
could be seen after implementing that.
So yeah thanks.
Thanks, everyone.
Thanks once again.
Myself, Ritwik, and yeah, I would
like to connect you on LinkedIn.
Here is my LinkedIn URL.
So definitely looking forward
and thanks once again, CON42,
for giving me this opportunity.
Thank
you.