Speaker 3: Hi, I'm Sulabh Jain,
and welcome to the to this session
at Conf42 Database and DevOps 2026
I'm going to present here the topic
on the cloud-native core systems
database and DevOps for the insurance.
So today we are covering something
specific that sits at a specific
and undeserved intersection,
database architecture and DevOps
practices in the insurance industry.
Three things that don't often
gets discussed together, but it
should absolutely be discussed.
So if you're working in the insurance
industry, this topic is for you
So before we discuss the architecture,
let's talk about why this is urgent.
What is the problem statement?
So in the insurance industries
the pressure of modernizing is
not gradual, it's compounding.
So there are three forces in the insurance
industry which are hitting simultaneously.
Regulatory pressure compliance
mandates are tightening.
Audit trail needs to be precise and
available, always available on demand.
Change windows that used to
stretch month are narrowing.
The platform that is hard to change
quickly is a legal liability,
not just a technical one.
Now, the next thing is
the digital competition.
So because of the, entries of the
insurtech they build a cloud-native
application from day one and then
they do not have any legacy to carry.
Those insurtech companies, they are
just shipping in days and not quarters
and then resetting the com-- the
customer expectation in the progress.
And then the third thing is obviously
the catastrophe scalability.
Hurricane, for example, occurs or
the wildlife events hap-- wildfire
events happens it generates
massive sudden claims spike.
Monolith platform cannot observe
that kind of elastic, elastically.
So w-- that results in the backlog in
the customer friction, then that's the
worst moment that the company faces.
So together it creates this is what I
call the modernization imperative, right?
The architecture has to change,
but the question is how?
So What does the legacy constraints
actually look like in practice?
Slow release cadence.
In a monolith system, every change,
every small change touches everything.
A fix to claim adjudication, for
example any logic to claim adjudication
triggers a full regression cycle
across the entire application.
Dep-deployments are infrequent
because the blast radius of
any change is simply too large.
Limited agility.
The new underwriting rule or
claims workflow change requires
coordinated release across all
the application database the
integration layers simultaneously.
By the time the coordination complete, the
business needs, maybe they have changed,
so they, they have often moved on.
And the third thing is
scalability ceiling, right?
It requires the vertical
scaling, bigger servers.
These are always expensive and bounded.
And true horizontal elasticity
that kinds that absorbs a cat
event requires, it requires the
fundamental and architectural change.
So all three trace back to the
same root, tight coupling, like
monolith system t- tight coupling.
There are, physical databases
or the servers availability
that's again, a lot of expenses.
So with this session, this is what we
are trying to undo and then see what
we can change in our architecture.
The microservice decoupling w--
in the insurance data domain.
So basically, this is a fundamental
shift in microservice architecture.
That is the data ownership.
Each service that just does not
own the business logic or the
code, it also owns the data domain.
In the insurance, these domain map
directly to the core business functions.
For example, the policy service that
owns the policy life cycle, it may
have the versioned API, independent
scaling and then, when the policy volume
spikes up, then, the systems or the
microservice is set up to scale either
in or scale up scale out or the scale
up Similarly, the claim service that
owns everything from first notice of
loss, FNOL, through the settlement.
It scales elastically during a
catastrophic event without touching
either billing or the underwriting.
The failure in claims is isolated,
so it does not, it, it does not
affect the policy or the billing.
The policy issuance or the
submission process remains the same.
Similarly, the billing service, it
manages the premium collection, the
payment reconciliation, et cetera,
that could be fully isolated.
A billing outage does not block
either the policy or the claim
So this isolation actually creates
the resilience when service shares a
database, a slow query in any of the
system that downgrades everything.
Any schema change in one of the area
that might break the other areas too.
The data ownership with the service
level is what makes the independent
deployment, the independent
scaling, and then independent
failure recovery actually possible.
With this having this monolith
kind of system, this is
not theoretically possible.
So with that, what we-- how
we solve is, containers.
We can create the containers to
solve the consistency problem.
Package each microservice within o- within
its own runtime dependencies in Docker,
and it runs identically everywhere,
laptop to the staging to the production.
No one can say that, "Hey it's
working on my machine," but,
it doesn't work on production.
But w-with this containerization,
we can actually solve that problem.
Starting from laptop to
all the environment, the
environment remains the same.
But are those containers alone enough?
Maybe not.
You need the orchestration
layer, and that's the Kubernetes.
So in the insurance specifically the four
Kubernetes capabilities that matters.
Horizontal pod, the, that is
auto-scaling scale pods, count
automatically based on the metrics.
Any catastrophe event hits, claim
index spikes, additional pod spin
up without, without waiting for
the for anything else, right?
The pod disruption budget that
guarantees minimum pod availability
during node maintenance.
Zero downtime maintenance becomes routine.
The namespace isolation enforces
hard security boundaries between
regulated and non-regulated workload
at the platform layer, so it is
not left for individual teams.
Now, the rolling deployment with
automated rollback that means the
new version released progressively.
It, failed health check
triggers automatic rollback.
So literally there is lo- no manual
intervention so two point specific to
database workload, which are multi-zone
cluster deployments that protects
against the availability zone failures.
And the next one is the StatefulSets
with persistent volume claims that
gives database pods stable network
identities and durable storage.
Containerized databases work correctly
alongside the stateless services
Now the infrastructure as a code is
where your operational reliability
becomes the systematic rather than
excuse me, rather than dependent
on the, the strong individuals.
So in this case, every resource,
be it networks, clusters, database,
or, IAM Identity Access Management
policies, it lives in version-controlled
code in the same repository as
the application it supports.
So everything regarding the infrastructure
that stays in the same repo.
It has four stages.
Define.
Okay.
What it does is it defines the databa-
infrastructure and the database
schemas that describes in the Terraform
or Pulumi or the cloud formation
alongside the application code.
So there is a, there is infrastructure
layer set up into the same repository.
So there is no separate ops knowledge
that lives only in someone's head
and, that creates a dependency
on that particular individual.
The next one is review.
So pull request that triggers the
automatic plan and then, diff reviews.
Policy as a code tool like OPA or the
Checkov that enforces security and
compliance before anything merges.
Compliance is the review process and
not the bolted on the, at the end.
The, now the next stage is apply.
So now that the changes are reviewed,
changes go through the CI/CD pipeline.
State files track drift, and
then rollback is a code convert.
It's like a code reverse.
It's not a manual
undocumented intervention.
It is automatic.
Even the road, ro-- the rollback
of the code is automated.
And then the last one is the audit.
So every change is timespan-- timestamp,
the attributed, it is tracked.
It can be reviewable in Git.
And whenever, any audit happens,
whenever any regulator requests
a complete change history, it is
already available immediately.
So what is the result?
The dis- disaster recovery
becomes a drill and not a crisis.
Environment drift, it disappears,
and then your infrastructure is as
trustworthy as your application code
The CI/CD.
The CI/CD is, considered an important
process or important step in this process.
What I call it as a delivery heartbeat
that makes everything else work.
So it has four stages in a well-designed
insurance platform pipeline.
So what it-- First thing is the automated
functional testing, unit testing,
integration, and then the UAT testing.
It runs on every commits, validating,
for example, underwriting rules, the
premium calculation in terms of claims.
It, it validates the claims
adjudication logic before every code
reaches to a shared environment.
A degradation that caught
here takes minutes to fix.
If it caught in, for example,
in production, it takes days or,
may carry compliance implication.
So the next one is the
performance and load testing.
So synthetic load test, for example that
simulates the catastrophe-like situation
where the load spikes up gradually in
case of the claim volume in the pipeline.
A service that passes functional
test but degrades under the
hurricane level code where the claims
volume spikes up, exponentially.
So that means your
production code is not ready.
So this particular stage with the
performance and load testing, it catches
it before even the live incident occurs.
Security scanning.
Statics or dynamic scans like SAST or
DAST or dependency scanning the container
image scanning these are all automated
and it gets data on every commits.
Shift left means the compliance
is built into the dev- development
process and it is not scrambled
when the audit team arrives.
So everything is documented.
We have the records and everything so
that we can present it to the audit team.
The last one is the progressive delivery.
What is progressive deliveries?
We cannot-- So if something is not looking
wrong, it will automatically roll back.
The code is promoted as it
passes different levels.
And then, this is what is called the
the progressive delivery So what is the
effect of this entire, setting up this
entire process is the deployment goes
from, from the quarterly war room to a
routine multiple time or weekly activity.
So this particular cadence is
how you speed the gaps with
the with those insurtechs.
Now, the next one is in my slide
is the event-driven architecture.
So let me describe the failure
mode that event-driven architecture
is designed to prevent.
Your claim intake service calls
fraud detection synchronously.
It sends a request and waits.
During a catastrophic event,
fraud detection is under the
load because, because of the,
claim submission spikes up.
It slows down.
Every claim request now waits.
The queue builds.
The mobile apps times out.
The slowdown is one of the
downstream service cascade into
multiple platform-wide outage.
That's, that is called the
synchronous coupling, right?
One slow service can take
the entire chain down.
It has the widespread downstream impact.
This event-driven architecture that
actually breaks it to, let's say, the
claim intake happens, it publishes
a domain event, and in that domain
in- domain event it will say the
claim intake received to a stream.
Then the fraud scoring, the adjuster
assignment, and the customer
notification each consumes that event
and independently, and then, they work
or they process on their own pace.
So for example, in, in that case,
if the fraud detection falls behind,
claims intake does not notice.
Ev-- these events are durable
and there's nothing lost.
So claim, so claims intake, for example
it happens, it publishes an event.
Being a consumer of the fraud detection
service that consumes that event,
that can process independently and it
can take on their own time in case of
the platform choice, Kafka for high
throughput ordered or durable streaming.
This is ideal for claims event sourcing
and audial grade audit-ready grade logs.
EventBridge for serverless
event routing with native AWS
integrations that is suited for the
partner ecos- ecosystem patterns.
There are key relig- resilience
pattern that matters here.
Event sourcing.
This is the state built
from an immutable event log.
What it means is it is critical
for claims audit trails and
then the regulatory replay.
CQRS, it separates the read and write
model, so reporting scales independently
and the transactional processing.
The dead letter queues.
Basically what is it?
These are the failed event capture for
retry, and there is no silent data loss.
Saga pattern.
Saga pattern is compensating
the transaction, handles the
partial failure in multiple step
workflow like policy issuance.
And then the circuit breaker.
It is for the downstream failures
isolated or preventing cascade
across claims or billing.
These are the few key patterns
those needs to be implemented
Now in the insurance, the partner
ecosystem like MGAs or aggregators
or insurtechs or reinsurers they
are the important stakeholders,
similar to our internal platform.
The quality of the API that surfaces and
that determines actually how effectively
your participate in, in that ecosystem.
First of all, design first contracts.
Basically, we write the OpenAPI
specification before implementation
begins as a design artifact and
not the generated existing code.
Consumer team validates against the
spec early the spec, and then it
is catching the incompatibilities
before the integration environment.
Once it is published, the
spec is the source of truth.
Breaking the changes, it requires
a version one with a new version
and, with a deprecation timeline.
So that means the partner who, let's
say, who are on version one, they
are not surprised and, they now have
that timeline to move to version two.
And then, any new partners they
can be migrated to version two.
The security and governance
are centralized at the gateway.
So OAuth 2.0 or mutual TLS is for external
traffic, service mesh handles internal
east or west mTLS or retry logic, and
the traffic policies between services.
So consistent informants is
not re-implemented per service.
It is implemented for, for all.
And basically, in this case, in the
business way of basically what happens
is the part- partner onboarding that
usually takes like months now, it comes
down to a days where, you know, because
we have the well-documented design
contracts, we have the security and
governments centralized at the gateway.
So all these things ease the
partner, the new partner onboarding
Moving on to the next slide.
This is the modern observability,
seeing across hundreds of services.
So when a single business transaction
travels dozens of microservices and
data stores, traditional log-based
monitoring breaks down completely.
You need three pillars working together.
First is the centralized logging.
The structured log from every
service or the container and the
database flow to a central platform.
Correlation IDs that may link every
log line to its originating request.
So you can reconstruct exactly what
happened during an incid- incident
occurred in this big distributed system.
The distributed tracing, open telemetry
instrumented traces that captures the
full span tree of a claims transaction
from API gateway through policy surveys to
fraud check and through a database write.
A claim adjuster reports the databases,
let's say, the dashboard is slow.
So traces that, will take you from the
vague complaint to a specific service, to
a specific query within probably a minute.
The third thing is the
metrics and alerting.
So rate metrics per service rate,
errors, and duration that combines
with the business level SLOs, and
then actionable alert with context.
So that, that helps to not become those
alerts noisy within threshold reaches.
So and then one non-negotiable instrument
from day one is the observability.
Observability cannot be retrofitted
into a distributed system.
So basically, if we skip this to
ship faster pay many times it-- what
happens is like it's over in production
incident and, that cannot be diagnosed
now let's talk about the distributed
data consistency and schema evaluation.
This is a slide where that separates
the team who succeeds at microservice
from teams who do not, because this
is the distributed data management is
generally hard, and it's decision you make
here have a long-lasting consequences.
When-- Because when each service owns its
own database, you lose the safety net of
transactions spanning multiple entities.
You have to design explicitly
for your consistency model.
Eventual consistency is acceptable, but
for many, insurance read paths design
your UI and downstream processes to
tolerate a brief lag, So basically,
do not fight with the distributed
system, but, work parallelly with it.
The Saga orchestration handles
partial failures in the multi-step
process like policy issuance.
Each step has a compensating transaction
if something downstream fails.
The outbox pattern that guarantees
at least once event delivery
alongside the database writes
without distributed transaction.
It is reliable bridge between your
data store and your event stream.
The schema evaluation is the operational
reality of the live distributed system.
So these four practices that makes
zero downtime schema changes possible.
The expand contract pattern for column
changes, consumer-driven contract
tests for schema compatibility
validation the blue-green database
migration for large table changes,
and a schema registry to enforce
compatibility in in on Kafka topics.
So basically get this layer s-- the
shared database between the services
are the most common way a microservice
migration quietly becomes the
distributed monolith now the-- let's
talk about the modernization roadmap
from legacy to the cloud-native.
So basically, it is a
four-phased approach.
So everything we have covered so far that,
that can feel so overwhelming, as a whole.
But the, it is the way to make it
like traceable is to go incrementally
and not a big bang rewrite.
So each phase should have its own
planning and the design and the,
and their implementation phase,
and then we gradually, move from
legacy to a cloud-native approach.
So there's one pattern called a
strangler fig pattern, that build
new microservices alongside while you
are keeping the legacy or core alive.
And then you gradually migrate
the traffic as you grow
confidence in your microservices.
Each phase that delivers, deliver
working software and measurable outcomes.
So this is what a sustainable moment look
like, and this is a multi-year program.
So what are those four phases?
Phase one is a foundation.
So basically, in this phase one,
what you s- what you do is basically
containerize the existing application.
You establish the CI/CD pipeline.
You establish the, the base IaC
base, pipeline or the baseline.
And then you do a
centralized observability.
No architecture refactoring yet.
Build, just build the operating model
and then safety net first, right?
Moving on to the phase
two, where you decompose.
What it means is you extract the
high pain domains like claims or
billing as a standalone microservices.
Introduce event streaming for decoupled
communication, and then migrate to
managed clouds, cloud databases When
you build the confidence in phase
two, then move on to phase three,
which is called the scalability.
Deploy the service mesh adopt GitOps
to for the platform operations expand
microservices boundary coverage,
and also enforce the API contracts
across all partner integration.
And then the fourth--
phase four is optimize.
Now fine-tune your auto ex-- auto-scaling
policies in, in terms of to handle the
catastrophe-like scenarios, implement
SLOs, the basic alerting and, et cetera.
So basically, you monitor the traffic, you
have the auto-scaling enabled, et cetera.
So in that's your last phase.
So each phase basically will have
your clear definition of done.
That clarity is what will keep, the
company in confide-confidence, the
business, users in the confidence
So now what are the key takeaways?
So four principle to carry out of this
session starts with operating model,
build CI/CD and observability before you
decompose the monolith system because the
teams needs a safety net first, right?
They the automated testing, the
deployment automation the production
visibility before basically you
are setting the base layer to
allow them to move fast and safely.
So this is bas-- this is the
foundation before the decomposition.
Then the next thing is
decouple data domains.
So what it calls is the DDD,
domain-driven design, and the
bounded contexts are your map.
Each service owns its own schema.
The cross-domain queries are
solved through events or APIs.
Never run through shared database.
Shared database are how microservice
migration, in that case quietly fails.
So that will-- that might become
your distributed monolith system.
Avoid having a shared database.
And You always design for the
failure and not just for the uptime.
So you always keep the failure in mind.
So apply the, implement the
circuit breaker, saga pattern, dead
letter queues chaos engineering.
These are just not the edge
cases, these are the architecture.
Build that muscle memory before
the next catas-catastrophic event.
Test it in production.
And then the last thing is invest
in people as much as the platform.
You always keep upskilling your people
build that culture the trust and,
the cross-functional team ownership.
These are just not the, soft concern.
These are the prerequisite for
the infrastructure So cloud-native
transformation in insurance is
achievable and well precedented.
These patterns are proven.
The technology is ready.
What it requires is the deliberate
choices in architecture, in tooling,
in your people that they are actually
most important, who are doing the work.
So that is all for the session today,
and thank you so much for watching.
If you have any questions feel
free to post me or shoot me a text.
Thank you so much