Speaker 6: Hey everyone,
my name is Sheena Yapchan.
Super excited to be here today.
In today's talk, I'm gonna be
talking about when database
risk stays hidden: closing the
visibility gap in data operations.
I think talks like this are super
important because sometimes it's just
little tweaks that can make a big impact
in how we do things and processes,
and this is something that I've seen
in many different organizations,
especially in the tech world.
So let's get started.
I'm gonna share my screen
so we can get started.
I hope you've enjoyed
the rest of the talks.
I'm sure they've been great, and
you've been able to gain something.
But let me just put this to full screen,
and we will get started So again, when
database risk stays hidden, closing
the visibility gap in data operations.
So the shift in database DevOps is
no longer just about tools, right?
It's about communication,
trust, timing, and visibility.
I've seen this where, there's no
communication, the trust isn't there,
it's bad timing, or there's no visibility.
And a lot of this is human error, right?
Or human miscommunication.
And this is why talks like this are
so important because we can have
the best processes, the best tech-
tech, the best software, but if we
don't have the human aspect of it, it
falls apart and it becomes expensive.
So this is why talks like
this is super important.
It's something that I've seen in
many organizations, and it's needed
to talk about so that we can move
forward with confidence and create
a win-win situation for everyone.
So systems are more
connected than ever, right?
We're not just working with
isolated systems anymore.
The system that you have is
basically an ecosystem that can
make decisions, can affect clients.
And so one hidden issue from your
system can imp- impact the customers,
the teams, the timelines, the trust,
and most important, the revenue.
So again, having a system
isn't just a system on its own.
It becomes an ecosystem in your
organization that can affect customers,
teams, timelines, trust, and revenue.
So this is why it's so important
because it's more than just a system.
It helps you make the business decisions.
It helps you, serve clients
in, in, in a proper way.
It helps you build more revenue so
that it can help the company grow
or help your organization grow.
So here's a real risk.
The real risk is not always
what teams do not know.
The real risk is what stays hidden, right?
Sometimes someone already saw the
issue but never made it to the
right conversation, and this is
where the visibility gap happens.
So if that's ever happened to
you, you're not the only one.
We've gone through that.
In fact, as kids, we tend to… If
we get in trouble, we tend to hide
what we did from our parents because
we don't wanna get in trouble.
But the problem is-- with that is
that the more we hide it, the bigger
the problem is, and then our parents
would get mad even more because we
said it too late versus early on.
It's the same concept, right?
If you see an issue, you don't say
anything, it becomes bigger, right?
Maybe in the beginning it was
small, but the more withhold
information, the more you don't
say anything, the bigger it gets.
It gets more expensive and then,
you have to start from scratch.
So this is the real risk.
Somebody may see it and
are afraid to say anything.
Some of them may see it and think someone
el- someone else is already taking care
of it when really it still stays hidden
and it becomes a bigger problem than we
expected So visibility protects the work.
A lot of people have this
misconception of visibility.
So visibility is not about attention.
It is about protection.
It's about making sure the information
reaches to the right people before it
becomes a bigger problem again, right?
It… You don't want it to be
a bigger problem because you
saw it and didn't say anything.
You wanna make sure that, you detect
the problem early on and say it in front
of the right decision makers, the right
people, so that they know that, this
is an issue that we need to deal with
right away, and if we don't, there's
gonna be consequences for all of us.
So again, visibility is not about
attention, it's about protection.
It's protecting you, it's
protecting the organization,
it's also protecting the client.
So it becomes, a whole cycle and, when
done right, it can really lead teams
in a better way and the work becomes
better and again, it beco- you know,
we create win-win situations So here's
where the risks are often hidden.
So risks can stay hidden in incident
response, migration planning, performance
conversations, re- reliability reviews,
postmortems, and team handoffs.
So if you ever dealt with this,
again, this is something that's
more common that we realize, it's
just not talked about enough.
And this is so important because,
again, it's just one little thing
that we can tweak that can really
create a big difference, right?
And I'll be sharing more
on how we can do that.
So the visibility gap in this
space is between what the technical
team sees and what decision-makers
understood in time to act.
You may see it, but if the
decision-makers don't understand it
or don't see it, then nothing happens.
We wanna make sure we bridge that
together so that you can find the
solution to that problem that you've
been seeing or that issue, and
we don't have to delay anything.
And again everything runs a lot smoother
than s- trying to stay hidden or
thinking that, they already know there's
a problem when really there isn't.
Again, this is more common that we
real-- than we realize, and I've
done a lot of talks about this.
A lot of people have mentioned,
yes, sometimes it's just a little
miscommunication or people assuming
things or people not trusting the system.
There's a lot of things that can affect
it, but we're gonna go through it as
well So why human readiness matters?
We talk a lot about being tech ready,
especially with AI on the rise.
Everyone's talking about you need
to be AI ready, you need to be tech
ready, you need to be future ready.
And yes, those are important,
but the most important thing we
need to do is to be human ready.
Because in the end, who's gonna
use all these systems, our
products and services, is humans.
And human readiness is the part
that helps teams communicate, trust
each other, make decisions, and
move forward under pressure, right?
It's not the tech, it's our abilities,
our skills, and being human.
And so this is a more, for me, a bigger
conversation because, there's gonna
be a lot of things that will come
up as we go, and we need to be ready
for whatever life brings us, right?
The pandemic was a big wake-up call
when it came to human readiness, right?
We didn't know if the world was gonna end.
We didn't know what was gonna happen.
It was really bleak.
But because we were hu-- we had
human readiness, we were able to
pivot, we were able to figure it
out, we were able to work remotely.
We were still able to connect through
technology because we were able to
trust the process, trust in each
other, and move forward in spite of it.
And if we can move through a pandemic,
we can move through anything.
And this is why human readiness is so
important in-- especially in tech, right?
In tech, results happen when we
put human readiness in it, when we
can trust ourselves, trust in the
system, when we can trust in being
more innovative, when we can trust
putting our ideas into action.
You-- again, you can have the best
strategies, the brest-- the best
strategies, the best tech the best
processes, but, if people aren't willing
to take action or aren't willing to
put themselves in it, nothing happens.
And so this conversation is actually
more important than we realize,
and it's not talked about enough.
So confidence is not
about being loud, right?
You don't have to be the
loudest person in the room.
I know you may have felt that way.
I did too.
When I first started my confidence
journey, I thought I had to
be loud and boisterous and
be out there, but, it's not.
It's about being able to say what needs to
be said when it needs to be said, right?
It's about being okay with who you are.
And so the more we can see what
confidence is, really is we can
move-- we can show up as who we are.
We can show up with sharing what needs to
be said so that we can solve the problems
right away instead of delaying the issue.
So I wanted to share a
framework that I've created.
It's called the VISIBLE framework.
It's my framework to human readiness.
It's about helping you see…
it's about helping you become
seen, heard, and understood.
And so it's derived from seven
pillars, and each pillar is
derived from the word visible.
So each letter represents something.
So V is for voice, I is identity, S is for
spotlight, I is inner work, B is belief,
and L- L is leverage, and E is elevation.
And I'll go through each one of
them, but I just wanted to give you
a quick overview of this framework.
And so we're gonna start with voice.
So this is really important because
a lot of the issues that I've
found for many organizations was
just a communication issue, right?
So here's one thing.
Can people raise concerns early?
Voice is about creating space for people
to say what they are seeing before
it turns into a bigger issue, right?
I've seen people who have seen the
issue but didn't say anything because
they were afraid that they might get
in trouble, or they were afraid maybe
they weren't right, or they were
afraid to, just s-say something, right?
You'd be surprised how many people
I talk to, professionals, who are
in meetings and are afraid to share
their ideas, share their concerns
because of that fear, right?
And it can stem from our childhood, right?
We go to school we raise our hand up to
answer something, and if we don't get
the correct answer, we get laughed at.
But… And that can take
on to our adult life.
So this is why it's so important to create
safe spaces where people can share their
concerns early or, find different ways to
help them share that concern because maybe
speaking up isn't the iss- like if they're
still having a problem with speaking
up, then maybe having an anonymous
suggestion box, email, or one-on-one
to really help them be comfortable in
sharing their voice, sharing the issues
early on so that doesn't delay and it
doesn't become bigger than it needs to be.
So again, can people raise concerns early?
Think about that, right?
What does that look like
in your organization?
Are people still scared to speak up?
Are-- You know, does-- Is-- Do you
create an environment where it is
safe for them to raise concerns early?
So again, voice I is identity.
Do people see themselves as
part of the re- reliability?
This is important, right?
If they don't think they're part of it,
they're not gonna share anything, right?
So when people understand that
their voice is part of the bigger
picture, they're more likely to
speak up when something matters.
So if they don't think they're part
of the solution, if they don't think
they're allowed to contribute anything,
or if they don't see themselves as
part of the team, they're not gonna
be willing to make the first move
or even share that there's an issue.
So it is important to create a space
where they know they're part of the
picture, they-- we identify as a team
and move forward so that, they have
the con- confidence and the courage to
say the things that matter the most.
S is for spotlight.
What needs more attention right now?
So spotlight is about
knowing what deserves focus.
So if you have an issue and you're
not spotlighting the issue, then no
one's gonna talk about it, right?
No one's gonna find the solutions
or even bring it up in meetings.
So it is important to spotlight
what needs to be taken care of,
what issue needs to be solved,
and how we can tackle it early on.
So the more you spotlight it, the more
people are willing to see, "Okay, I see
that someone mentioned this like 10 times.
We need to fig- we need to fix it because
clearly there's a, there… it's creating
chaos, and we need to fix it right away."
So again, spotlight what deserves more
attention right now I is for inner work.
What keeps people silent?
I think this is 80% of the work
because a lot of people don't
realize, the issues that we go
through is from the inside out, right?
Maybe it's our upbringing or the
traumas that we've been through
or, the past incidents where it's
stopped us from moving forward.
Like for me, I grew up in Asian culture,
so we weren't always taught to speak up.
In fact, especially as a woman, we've been
told to, do as you're told, never make
any noise, and stay in the background.
And so speaking up and being visible
is actually a lot harder, right?
Because we're not taught to be seen.
And so I had to unlearn a
lot of things and relearn new
things to be where I am today.
I never would have thought I'd be
speaking on stages or doing videos
like this because, again, I was… Back
then, I was so afraid to show myself.
I was so afraid to put myself out
there 'cause I just thought, I needed
to just stay in the background, never
make any noise, and do as I'm told.
So sometimes people don't speak up because
they're afraid of being wrong or, they're
going through something or or they're,
they've, there's been past incidents
that prevents them from doing that.
But the hidden concerns do not disappear.
Just because we don't say anything
doesn't mean the problem goes away.
Again, it's important to help
people, work through that, right?
Ask them, "Why are you afraid of, speaking
up? Why are you afraid of resisting?"
When we can figure out what the root
cause is, it'll be easier to solve
the, to help them and correct it or not
correct it, but, pin tweak it so that
they can move better, move forward and
that, they move with confidence, right?
So again, 80% of the work is the inner
work, so that means being able to
do personal development every single
day or being able to read good books,
be surrounded by like-minded people.
Because when the concerns are hidden
and they don't, no one talks about
it because they're afraid of being
wrong or afraid to even share it, it
becomes an expensive issue, right?
It becomes more expensive
than it needs to be.
And investing in helping your team with
personal development, with helping with
their inner work will be a better RO-
ROI than keeping it hidden B is belief.
Do people believe their
concerns will matter?
This is big, right?
'Cause if they don't think what they
share, you believe in it, they're
not gonna say anything, right?
People will not raise concerns if
they believe nothing will change.
Because I've seen this time and time
again where people have s- voiced their
concerns, nothing happens, and then
they never share anything ever again.
Because if the first time they weren't ab-
nothing happened, it becomes worse, then
to them, what's the point in sharing it?
So you have to have a space where
people do believe that the, their
concerns matter, that you found
a way to help them guide through
it so that, you build that trust.
And I think trust is so important because
without that trust, the team falls apart.
It's important to work together, and
i- the biggest con- the biggest thing
to do that is by building trust.
So to create trust, you need to
build a culture where people know
their voice will be taken seriously.
And I've seen this time and time again
where teams with, high trust level, they
work together, everything is great, but
if it's the opposite, it becomes toxic.
It's every man for themselves,
and we don't want that, right?
We wanna make sure that you work
together cohesively so that you're
able to tackle the issues early on
and, say, and help, your clients, the
team, the organization, and so on.
So again, do people believe their
concerns will matter, right?
So think about that.
And as… if you, if there, if your
environment is not that, not that
great, where they don't believe that
if they s- share anything, something
will happen, then they're not gonna
keep on bringing things up, right?
So again, create that trust, build that
culture, help them realize whatever
concerns they have, it is serious,
it is something of value, and that y-
we'll, you can work together for it.
And, it's not saying that you'll
have every solution for it, but at
least they know that you put in the
effort to figure it out and work on
it versus not doing anything at all.
L is for leverage.
How do we work smarter, not just harder?
This is a big one because I've done a
lot of talks, and one of the biggest
issues was that even though people
are in teams, they work in silos.
They try to do everything themselves,
and there's no point in having a team
if you're doing everything yourself.
So it's important to work hard-
work smarter and not just harder.
So working smarter means being able
to create better communication habits
so risk is easier to see early.
We don't wanna, try to do
everything ourselves because
that's how burnout happens.
That's how you get exhausted,
and you end up creating more
problems than it needs to be.
But when you can learn to work smarter,
have tools, resources, and networks
to, leverage that to… that impact
or to, make your work a lot easier
and build a bigger impact, then, it's
a win-win situation for all of us.
So think about it.
If there's a… if there's someone
in your team that is good at one
thing help them focus on that.
And then, if you have another team
member that's better in a different
section, then help them focus on that
so that you don't have to figure out
how this one person does everything.
You help them find their strengths
and elevate that strengths
and, how they can make a bigger
impact based on their strengths.
So again, how do we work
smarter, not just harder?
We don't want to be able to have
everyone be overworked, right?
Be the one-man show.
You're in a team for a reason because
you have different skills and talents
that nobody else has, and by combining
them together, that's how you can
create win-win situations, be able to
solve issues properly and early on.
And last but not least
is E's for elevation.
How do we turn insight into action?
Elevation is when technical
concerns become something people
can make a decision from, right?
You have the tech, you have the
data, but how can they translate
that into decisions and elevating it
and taking things to the next level?
So when we elevate the message,
we help people see why it matters.
So it is important to, again be
able to see… say it in front of
the right people, in front of the
right decision-makers, so that
issue can be tackled early on.
So that was the VISIBLE framework.
If there was a pillar that made sense for
you or you think, "Yeah, I think I need
more work on this," feel free to share it.
Would love to know.
Because again, the… most
of it isn't a tech issue.
Ninety percent of it is
a human issue, right?
Not being able to say it out loud,
not being able to trust each other,
not being able to spotlight it.
So being able to tw- just do small tweaks
to be able to see the issue and work on
it, it helps you out in the long run.
So here's three visibility gaps
that you've probably gone through
that's more common than you think.
So again, the signal
is seen but not shared.
We've seen that, right?
You've seen the issue, but you don't
take action 'cause maybe you assume
somebody else has already tackled
it or you're afraid to speak up.
Another one's the issue's… the
issue is shared but not understood.
So here's also where
communication comes in.
If you if you say something that
the other person can't understand,
they're n- then they're not
gonna go out there and tackle it.
It also needs to be clear communication
'cause not everyone is technical, right?
You have to also communicate it in a way
that someone else will understand, right?
I remember talking to somebody who was in
cybersecurity, and so when I asked them
what they do, they were talking about
the technical side of cybersecurity.
And for me, if I-- if you explained
that to me, I would just look
blank because I don't understand
what you're saying, right?
I don't know the cybersecurity terms.
I don't know the iss- you know
the terms that you normally use.
But, it… But then, the person explained
it to me in a way that made sense for me.
Something like, "If you wanna make sure
you want your info to be protected,
have pri- have privacy, not have,
any malware, I help you do that."
So just something simple like that, right?
So again, the issue is
shared but not understood.
Make sure you have clear communication
and also terms that helps them
understand why this issue is needed
to be done or why, it, it matters.
And then the consi- the concern is
understood, but no action taken.
So again, there's a lot of reasons
why there's no action taken, no clear
communication channels, not being trusted,
not having, not being part of the bigger
picture, or maybe it's not spotlighted.
But these are more common
that you real- than realize.
And so when we can figure out these
visibility gaps, we can find ways
to solve it, find solutions to it.
So here's some migration example
that I wanna share with you.
Instead of saying, "We should be
fine," you can say, "Here are the
risks, here is the impact, and here's
the decision we need." So that's more
specific and, Because when you say,
"We should be fine," then people are
like, "Okay," and then nothing happens.
But if you're more clear and more
specific, then we're like, "Okay,
tell…" "Now that I know what the
risks are, this is what we need to
do." Here's an incident example.
When pressure is high,
clarity matters even more.
So during incidents, people
do not need more confusion.
They just need clear ownership.
So what does that mean?
Having clear updates, clear next
steps, clear decisions, right?
If nothing is clear,
nothing happens, right?
And clarity is so important.
If they know the set of instructions, the
next steps, decisions, the updates, then
they're more willing to tackle it, right?
Because if you don't give them a
clear f- path, then they're not
even gonna take the first step.
Here's a postmortem example.
So having a strong postmortem
ask what stayed hidden too long?
And it's not just about what broke, but
it's also about what's not seen, what's
not said, what did not reach and what
did not reach the right people in time.
So it's not just about what stayed
hidden, there's actually a lot of factors.
And again, all of this adds up, right?
Because if you don't, if you don't
s- if you don't spotlight what's
not seen, if you don't say anything
if you don't say it in front of the
right people, then nothing happens.
And then the issue becomes bigger
than it needs to be, it becomes
expensive, and then, you're s- you're
working on a bigger problem that
necessarily didn't have to be a big
problem when it was tackled early on.
And so here's a communication
shift I wanna share with you.
It's important to move from just technical
detail only to talking about risks,
impact, trade-off, decision, and timing.
So it's more than just technical, right?
It's all these as well.
So when you add all these
together, it helps them see things
from a different perspective.
Here's a simple visibility statement
that you can share as well.
As of today, say, "Here's
what we are seeing.
Here is why it matters.
Here is the possible impact.
Here are the options, and here is the
decisions we need." So I hope this
visibility statement helps you out, so
when you're going through a problem or
you have an issue, and you need to find
a way to communicate, just remember this
statement, Here is what we are seeing.
Here's why it matters.
Here's the possible impact.
Here are the options, and
here's the decision we need.
So what do human ready
teams do differently?
So human ready teams speak earlier,
listen better, translate risk
clearly, make decisions faster,
and build trust under pressure.
And this is all so important, right?
Because again, ninety percent of the
reasons why there's, big issues is really
because of not talking about being human
ready, not being able to talk about
these issues where you need to speak up,
you need to speak earlier, have clear
communication, spotlight the issue or be
able to leverage it or build that trust.
All this is so important when
you're working with a team, right?
Because this, these are people that
you work with every single day.
And if you don't have that re-- that trust
or be able to have a safe space where
people can speak early can make decisions
faster, then nothing happens, right?
And then it becomes a bigger
problem than it needs to be.
So leaders can start asking,
"What are we not seeing yet?
What are people afraid to say?
Where are signals getting stuck?
And who needs this information sooner?"
So again, what are we not seeing?
What are people afraid to say?
Where are signals getting stuck?
And who needs this information sooner?
And here's what teams can practice.
You can create simple
habits for visibility.
I always believe it's small,
actionable, daily steps that
yield the r- great results.
You don't need to overcomplicate it.
Keep it super simple.
So have clear escalation paths,
have better risk language,
have regular check-ins, right?
H- Like being able to have these
regular check-ins is important th--
because then you know what level
they're at and what needs to be done.
Having shared ownership and
having earlier conversations.
The earlier, the better, right?
When we ha-- When we can see
the issue, we, y- it, you just
be able to share it, right?
Share it, practice having earlier
conversations, 'cause that could be
a big, cost saver than you realize
just by sharing the issue early on
And here's the bigger picture.
Database real- reliability
is not only technical.
Again, it is human, 'cause in
the end it's humans who use it.
It's… we're the ones, creating these
technical systems, these processes.
So it's also important to ta- sh- share
about what I what I talked about today,
the communication issue, the trust, the
leverage, the belief, the inner work.
All this matters in the technical space.
So when… Here's a closing remark.
When s- risk stays hidden, teams react.
When risk becomes visible, teams can lead.
That's a big difference, right?
So this is why the visible framework
is so important, and being able
to put the human aspect in this
is more important than we realize.
So here's the final thoughts.
The future of database DevOps will
belong to teams that can make risk
visible before it becomes expensive.
So I hope you enjoyed
today's presentation.
And if you'd you can scan this barcode.
It goes to all my social
media, websites, books.
It'll also… If you'd like a copy of this
presentation, you can go to this link.
Just enter your information,
your email your email, and it'll
get sent straight to your inbox.
So I hope you enjoyed
today's presentation.
I hope this was a little
bit of an eye-opener.
And feel free to connect with me, and
I can't wait to connect with you, and I
hope you enjoy the rest of the conference.
Bye for now.
Bye for now