Speaker 2: Hello all.
I'm Surya Anankalapalli, working
as software engineer at Microsoft
with twenty plus years of
experience in the software domain.
Today I'll be talking about DNS
resiliency from database standpoint.
During the session or while watching
the recording, if you have any
questions or require any clarifications
on what I'm talking, feel free
to reach out to me via LinkedIn.
More than happy to like discuss,
clarify anything after the session.
Jumping onto the topic,
database resiliencies.
Active-active DNS strategies
for DevOps and failover.
That's the topic we'll be deep diving
today in the next ten to fifteen minutes.
The problem nobody talks
about in the database world.
The stale records, the propagation
lag, or operational complexity.
We don't want customers to see stale
records when you have something point
to dead ends, and the propagation
lag or any operational complexity due
to so many manual updates which are,
like, handled at the database layer.
Your database replication is solid, your
failure automist is tested, but when
o-on an outage hits, the DNS becomes a
bottleneck, which we don't want to be.
We'll talk in the next couple of slides
on how to handle that, how to tackle that
via multiple active-active DNS providers.
What this session covers.
The DNS architecture, the database
integration, the practical
patterns, and observability.
These are four things which
we'll be covering at high level
in the next couple of minutes.
Traditional DNS models and their limits.
Traditional DNS, we have single provider
and which means single point of failure.
When one DNS is impacted due to
some DDoS attack or anything as
such, there's an impact to all the
customers who are relying on that DNS.
We have seen that historically multiple
times in the last couple of years.
We have DNS outages
across multiple providers.
So when the primary DNS… the pattern is,
like, when the DNS goes out, the customers
go and flip to the secondary DNS manually,
and during that time, the customers will
be, like, seeing the stale records, and
they have some data replication lag,
and for multiple minutes or hours in
cases where the customers are impacted.
To mitigate that, the strategy what
we should enforce all the database
systems to have active-active
multiple provider DNS strategy.
So in this case, instead of relying
on one provider, we can have
more than one provider serving
the customer's DNS traffic.
So two is typically standard.
We can have more than two.
The reason why we don't prefer to
have more than two is operational
cost and due to variance of the
technology and the propriety dealing
of the routing and multiple things.
It's really hard to scale
across more than two.
So two is-- more than two is not
uncommon, but it's two is more
standard, which I want to say.
So single DNS provider is a silent
dependency that can outlast a database
failure by minutes, which is not
what we desire our customers to see
Okay, what is active-active
DNS, and why is it needed?
So when you have two or more DNS
providers serving authoritative
responses simultaneously, it's
not oh, serving as a standby.
If one goes down, it's not
like second comes into picture.
Both will be serving the
traffic simultaneously.
No single point of failure.
If one provider like degrades,
other continues serving records
without any intervention seamlessly.
Real-time monitoring.
The way the active DNS works is based
on the real-time health routing.
And the customers also have the
global distribution where each
provider's anycast network reduces
the latency for geographically
distributed database clients.
Depending on where the client is, so the
records are catered based on the close
proximity where the customers reside in
How DNS integrates with
database replication.
This is a sequential process
where everything is governed
by the health check.
So a continuous health check on both the
providers, and during the health check,
if anything is observed, like one provider
goes down or one provider is unhealthy
or not reachable, then we automatically
update the DNS to the secondary
provider and promote the replicas.
What are replicas here on the
primary replicas that will be
promoted to the secondary and
reroute all the clients seamlessly
from provider one to provider two.
All this automated,
governed by health checks.
So DNS is not just a naming layer.
It's a traffic control plane, which
is governed by the health checks
Read-write routing at DNS layer.
Write endpoint.
Single CNAME or re-weighted
reco- weighted record always
point to the current primary.
And this will be updated immediately after
converting from primary to secondary.
Read endpoint.
It's a round robin or latency weighted
record across health replicas.
Scale reads without application changes.
Geo-routing directs clients
to the nearest health replica,
reducing cross-region read latency.
That's the regional endpoints.
So you have three things, three
endpoints for the DNS layer.
One is the write endpoint, which should
be always be updated immediately on
promotion to the secondary provider.
And read endpoint, which is like
round robin latency weighted, which is
carried across like multiple endpoints.
And re- regional endpoint,
geo-routing directs clients to the
nearest health replica, reducing
the cross-region read latency.
Health checks.
This is the engine of automated failover.
You have multiple…
When you say health check, it's
not specific to like one probe.
It's a TCP probe, HTTP probe,
and you have the replication lag
monitor, node drain detection.
All this cumulatively makes up
the health check and the engine
for the automated failover.
Is an active DNS only, is only as fast
and reliable as health checks driving it.
If the health checks takes forever or not
reliable, the active DNS doesn't work.
So also we should ensure like all the
health checks are not, health checks
are not at the like surface layer.
It should be at the application layer.
And the check interval and failure,
the threshold determine your effective
R2-- RTO And replication lag thresholds
prevent promoting stale replicas.
Node role detection avoids routing
writes to read-only replicas.
So it's not one is important than
the other, but all those are equally
important to ensure the engine of
automated failure works as expected
Synchronizing configuration
across providers.
So all those DNS like records are
stored somewhere in the source
of the Git or config store.
So the two things which should
be like the things in place of
configuration sync pipeline are
drift detection and sync engine.
Drift detection is to alert on
any divergence from one provider
to other provider, and also you
have sync engine, which always
keeps both the providers in sync.
These two are the like heart of
it, like drift detection, identify
any like anomalies, alert, and go
and have a plan to go and fix that.
And sync engine to ensure like
always both the like providers are
in sync from the DNS standpoint.
So always consider DNS records as code,
and they're stored in a version control.
It should be deployed via CI/CD
pipeline to ensure there is no
propagation delay or any like config
issue or synchronization issue as such.
Okay, operational patterns.
Reducing recovery time objectives.
So what is the TTL strategy?
We should also like balance between the
TTL and resolver load and provider limits.
Some providers have a limit on
how many reco-- how many hits it
can take per minute or per second.
So if we have the lower TTL, the number of
requests hit in the provider like to use,
which is we don't want to hit the throttle
the provider and get get an impact.
Also ensure it should
have negative caching.
Should have configured like lower level,
lower SL-SLO, lower TTL for SOA, so that
whenever we have a NX domain, we don't
want to persist that for longer duration.
Having lower SLO TTL ensure
like NX domain response are
not cached for longer duration.
Pre-warming records.
We don't want replicas to go on keep…
We need to keep the replica endpoint
records live and healthy at all times,
even before a failover is needed.
We don't want to act at the point of time.
We need to have the replicas
always have the required data
without acting on on time.
Manual DNS changes.
The other thing is the automation, right?
So manual DNS changes during incidents
are too slow, and also there is a very
chance, very high chance of like fat
fingering when you do the manual changes.
Have automation-first mentality in
first, which will ensure like in
case of any outages, any changes any
outages to one provider, the flipping
over from primary to secondary DNS
happens automated way without any
manual intervention Observability
across DNS and database state.
So three pillars for the observability
are DNS query metrics, replication lag
visibility, and failover event testing.
Tracing, sorry.
The DNS query metrics will determine
the track, the resolution success rate,
how many-- how much is the success
rate when the prime-- the customers
hit one of the DNS against the other.
So that governs which is the healthy
DNS compared at that point of time.
The replication lag visibility.
Expose replication lag as a metric
that both your database monitoring and
DNS health check systems can consume.
And the failover event tracing.
Log every DNX-- DNS record change with
timestamp, trigger health checks, state,
and database node to let time of change.
So having these three observed in
consistent way will ensure we have
proper metrics, everything in place,
and have active-active DNS in effect.
Global failover, the
multi-region considerations.
Write fencing.
Ensure only one region
accepts writes post-failover.
So when you have failover between from
primary to secondary, we don't want to
blast all the regions with the writes.
We need to ensure one-- only one region
accepts the writes post-failover, so
that, like, when you flip back to the
secondary provider, the synchronization
from one region to other becomes seamless.
A DNS alone can't split--
prevent split brain.
Coordinate with the database
own fencing mechanism.
That's also equally important to
ensure write fencing both at the
DNS layer and at the database layer.
Latency versus consistency.
Geo-routing optimizes read latency
but introduces replication lag.
So you need to ensure what is
the acceptable lag depending
on the customer base, right?
So we need to ensure we
need to be consistent.
Also, we shouldn't be, like,
too much latency due to that.
So that's a trade-off between
latency and consistency.
It depends on what the end customers
needs are Okay, so we talked about all the
good things, what we should be doing, how
to do it in the last couple of minutes.
So few things we should consider
to avoid, or pitfalls which
we should fall into, right?
So one thing, don't assume oh, having
lower TTL is not faster failover.
So lower TTL is good in some sense.
At the same time, we should also
consider the provider's limits as such.
Having lower TTL will ensure more records
hitting the custom-- hitting the provider
DNS, which might not be, like, scalable
always Health checks that are too shallow.
The health checks, we talked in
deep about what are health checks,
how to do that, and not at the one
point which the health check should
be like considered holistically.
The TCP layer, the DNS layer,
the HTTP layer, everything.
So also we need to ensure
those are not shallow.
The shallow health checks might be always
be, like, responding healthy, but you
need to ensure the application layer
level health checks are also considered.
Oh, the other thing is
provider API rate limits.
Each provider have
different API li-limits.
You don't want to throttle the provider
with high number of requests and
throttle them and cause an outage.
That's something which to consider.
So this directly linked to the TTL,
which you define for the records.
Having a lower TTL have high API calls.
Having a high TTL, we
have lo-lower API calls.
And the last thing is
about having a runbook.
Active-Active reduces DNS as
a single point of failure, but
providers themselves can degrade.
Have a manual fallback documented
Okay, we're coming to
the end of the session.
Some of the key takeaways
of the session are DNS is a
first-class reliability concern.
It's not an option.
So you need to treat it with
the same rigor as replication
topology and failure automation.
So DNS is a first-class reliability
that can't be ignored or taken as
a low priority compared to others.
Active-active eliminates a single--
DNS single point of failure.
So always consider having more
than one provider always serving
the traffic all the time.
Health checks must
reflect database reality.
So health checks shouldn't be shallow.
Make it like a deep level health check
to ensure the application level health
checks, the T-- the TCP protocol check
checks, and the HTTP protocol checks.
And automate every failure path.
You can't take the… anything
manually and cause an outage.
You can't fat finger and cause an
outage, which is very much undesired.
These are four key takeaways.
DNS, first-class reliability concern.
Active-active DNS is a single point…
eliminate a single point of failure.
Health checks must reflect database
reality, not at the shallow level.
And also automate all the patterns.
Okay.
From that, I come to
the end of the session.
It's nice to-- Yeah, thank you, everyone.
Thanks for watching it.
If you have any questions or
any follow-ups, feel free to
reach out to me by the LinkedIn.
Thank you.