Speaker 7: Thank you for joining me today.
My name is Sampath Rao Madarapu.
I am a senior technical advisor
at Microsoft, where I work on the
front lines of Azure infrastructure
support, helping enterprise customers
troubleshoot, optimize, and operate
complex cloud environments every day.
Today, I am going to take you through
how Azure Copilot is transforming the
way we do diagnostics, resource control,
and intelligent cloud operations,
especially for database and DevOps
teams Let's start with problem.
Azure today supports hundreds of
services and thousands of resource types.
If you're managing database workloads,
whether it's Azure SQL, Cosmos DB,
or PostgreSQL, you are dealing with
interconnected configurations where even
small changes can cascade across services.
The human cost is real.
DevOps and database teams spend
enormous time context switching between
the Azure portal, CLI, monitoring
dashboards, and documentation.
When an incident hits, you are
under pressure to do root cause
analysis while juggling fragmented
tooling and scattered telemetry.
And here, the scaling challenge.
Institutional knowledge, the kind that
tells you this error pattern means
check the connection pool, is hard
to scale across teams and regions.
This is the exact gap that
Copilot is designed to fill.
So what is Azure Copilot?
It's an AI-powered assistant
embedded directly into the
Azure management experience.
It transforms complex
operational workflows into
natural language conversations.
Three key things make this powerful.
First, natural language interaction.
You can converse with your cloud
environment in plain English.
No need to memorize CLI syntax or
navigate through five portal blades.
Second, context awareness insights.
Copilot understands your specific
resources, configurations, and workloads.
It's not giving you generic
cloud documentation.
It's grounded in your actual environment.
Third, unified operational view.
You can explore resource relationships,
summarize configurations, and
investigate metrics from a
single intelligent interface.
Ask questions, get answers, take action
without leaving your context Behind the
scenes, Copilot brings together three
layers: large language models that
interpret your natural language queries
and generate actionable responses,
Azure control plane data, live resource
metadata, ARM configurations, and
subscription topology that inform
everyone response, and real-time
telemetry, performance metrics,
diagnostic logs, health signals, so
Copilot reasons about current system
state, not just historical snapshot.
This combination is what makes
responses specific and operationally
relevant rather than generic Let me
highlight three core capabilities.
Conversational resource exploration.
You can ask questions like,
"What my virtual machines in my
subscription are not passed?" Or,
"Show me all SQL databases above
eighty percent DTU utilization," and
get structured answers instantly.
Performance investigation.
Copilot correlates metrics from
Azure Monitor, Application Insights,
and resource diagnostics to
surface bottlenecks and recommend
remediation in plain language.
Service relationship mapping.
Understand how your resources depend
on each other, from app services to key
vaults to SQL backends, without manually
tracing ARM templates or network diagrams.
Now, let's dive into the first
major chapter, diagnostics.
When incidents occur, time
to insight is critical.
Traditional workflows require correlating
logs from multiple sources, pivoting
across tools, and interpreting
metric trends under pressure.
With Copilot, instead of drilling
through five portal blades, you
simply ask, "Why is my app service
returning five oh three errors?"
And receive a sys-synthesized diagnostic
summary with root cause hypothesis.
Copilot also enables proactive
anomaly detection, surfacing issues
like memory pressure, connection
exhaustion, or unusual query
patterns in database workloads
before they escalate into outages.
And beyond diagnosis, it provides guided
remediation, concrete next steps like
scaling actions, configuration changes,
or policy adjustments, all grounded in
your specific resource state This slide
illustrate the workflow transformation.
Before Copilot, diagnostics
meant navigating multiple blades,
cross-referencing logs in log
analytics, checking resource health,
and correlating timestamps manually.
After Copilot, you have a single
conversational interface that
synthesizes all of that into one
coherent diagnostic narrative.
The time savings are dramatic.
What used to take an hour of
investigation can now take minutes.
Chapter two is about resource
control and cloud governance.
Configuration summarization lets
you ask Copilot to summarize any
resource, virtual machines, SQL Server
instances, AKS clusters, and get a
structured human-readable overview.
This is especially valuable
during incident triage or when
onboarding engineers who need rapid
context on unfamiliar resources.
Policy and compliance queries let
you query your environment for
deviations from governance baselines.
Copilot can identify non-compliant
resources, surface policy violations,
and suggest remediation aligned with
Azure Policy and Defender for Cloud.
Think about use cases like
identifying untagged or misconfigured
resources, validating RBAC role
assignments at scale, or surfacing
cost optimization opportunities,
all through natural language.
This is where it gets particularly
relevant for this audience.
Database engineers and data platform
architects benefit from Copilot's deep
integration with Azure Data Services,
Azure SQL, Cosmos DB, Synapse Analytics,
PostgreSQL, and MySQL, and so on.
Query performance analysis.
Investigate slow queries, identify missing
indexes, understand DTU versus vCore
utilization through natural language.
No need to manually parse
query, store, or DMV output.
Security posture review.
Ask Copilot to audit database
firew-firewall rules, encryption
settings, and audit configurations.
It surfaces gaps against security
best practices instantly.
Capacity scaling guidance.
Get recommendations on
right-sizing database tiers,
elastic pool configurations, and
read replica deployments based
on actual workload telemetry.
And backup recovery validation.
Verify backup policies, retention
windows, and geo-redundancy configurations
across all your database resources
with a single conversational query
Now, I want to emphasize
something important.
Copilot's intelligence does
not emerge from AI alone.
There is critical layer of human
expertise that shapes, validates, and
continuously improves the recommendations.
This happens in four stages.
First, telemetry mapping.
Engineers validate that the current
metrics and signals are mapped to
the right diagnostic scenarios.
Second, behavior review.
Technical advisors like myself review
system outputs for accuracy and
operational relevance, identifying edge
cases where AI responses need refinement.
Third, guidance authoring.
Trusted troubleshooting runbooks
and resolution patterns are embedded
into Copilot's knowledge base.
This translates hard-won operational
experience into reusable AI guidance.
And fourth, continuous validation.
Feedback loops from real-world usage
into model grounding and prompt
tuning, keeping recommendations
current as Azure services evolve.
This is the human-in-the-loop
approach that makes production AI
trustworthy Trust is the foundation.
For AI-assisted operations to be
adopted in production, engineers
need to trust the recommendations.
Copilot is grounded in your data.
Responses cite the actual telemetry and
configuration supporting its conclusions.
Reasoning is transparent.
When it surfaces an issue, it explains the
evidence so you can verify and validate.
And critically, the human
is always in the loop.
Copilot presents recommendations
but does not autonomously execute
destructive or irreversible actions.
The design principle is clear.
AI-driven recommendation must
remain accurate, transparent,
and operationally reliable.
The human engineer is always
the final decision-maker.
Copilot strengthens observability across
three dimensions: signal correlation,
synthesizing fragmented data, and logs
from Azure Monitor, log analytics,
resource health into a coherent picture.
Alert contextualization.
When an alert fires, Copilot
immediately provides context on what's
affected, what changed, and what
historical patterns are relevant.
And cross-service visibility,
understanding cascading impacts
like failing backend database
affecting upstream API latency.
Cloud governance is only effective
when it's actionable in real time.
Copilot bridges the gap between
governance policies and day-to-day
operational decisions, from cost
optimization and security compliance
to change tracking and workload health.
It provides a single intelligent lens
across the full governance spectrum
Let me leave you with four key
takeaways to bring back to your teams.
First, faster diagnostics.
Copilot compresses diagnostic
workflows from hours to minutes
through natural language correlation.
Second, deeper observability.
Signal correlation across Azure
Monitor and Log Analytics gives
you a unified contextual view that
makes anomalies visible earlier.
Third, stronger governance.
Natural language queries against
live resource state make compliance
checks accessible to the entire
team, not just specialists.
Fourth, human plus AI partnership.
Copilot augments, never
replaces engineering judgment.
Validated telemetry and human-authored
guidance ensure recommendations
stay st- trustworthy in production.
If you're ready to explore, start in Azure
portal, enable Copilot experience in your
subscription, and begin with a diagnostic
query on your most complex workload.
I hope this has given you a clear
picture of how Azure Copilot
can accelerate your workloads.
Thank you all for your time