Speaker 15: Hi, everyone.
My name is Kamini Murugappuppathi,
and I'm part of Wonderboat Analytics
Private Limited here in India.
And I am very thrilled to be
presenting at the Conference
forty-two Database DevOps 2026.
the topic I'm gonna be discussing
with you is the cloud-native data
architectures for real-time marketing
analytics in the database and DevOps space
Here's the agenda we will be going through
as we, progress through the, presentation.
So without any further ado, so if you
think about in modern marketing, the
advantage does not belong only to a
company that collects the most data.
we know almost every company
today is doing just that.
They're collecting lots of data.
for example, they collect website visits,
mobile app activity, email clicks,
ad impressions, CRM data, purchase
history, customer support interactions,
you name it, anything about marketing
that they are already collecting.
But the real advantage, belongs to
the company that can actually use
that data while it is still fresh.
for example, imagine a customer or even
you browsing an online fashion store.
You look at a pair of shoes, you
click on a discount offer, you add
the shoes to the cart, but then
you just leave without buying.
So in the olden days, where the
old batch-based system, was live,
we may understand this behavior
maybe tomorrow morning after the
whole night data load finishes.
But by tomorrow, the customer
has already left and bought the
product from your competitor.
So in a real-time system,
we can act immediately.
We can update that customer's profile,
place the, place them into a cart
abandonment audience segmentation,
show them a personalized offer, or even
trigger a recovery email within seconds.
So the question is no longer
how much data do we have?
The real question is, how quickly
and reliably can we turn this
customer behavior into action?
So again, for many years,
marketing analytics was built
around this batch intelligence.
Data would be collected during the
day, processed overnight, loaded into a
warehouse, and analyzed the next morning.
That worked when marketing
decisions were very slower.
But today, customer behavior
is happening in milliseconds.
A page view, a cart abandonment, an app
notification, these responses can all
change what the business should do next.
This is why real-time marketing
analytics needs a new foundation, a
foundation that covers event-driven
pipelines, cloud-native infrastructure,
and DevOps practices applied not just
to application code, but also to the
data pipelines, database changes,
schemas, and machine learning models
Right?
so let's begin with why traditional
pipelines may break down, right?
So there are three major problems.
The first is latency.
Latency simply means delay.
any delay in data costs
you your business, right?
So if a customer abandons a cart at
ten AM and the marketing team can only
sees-- see the data the next day, like
in a whole batch-based processing, that
business has lost the chance to respond
to that customer at the right moment.
So the second problem is fragmentation.
So marketing data comes from many
different systems: websites, mobile apps,
Google Ads, Meta Ads, you name it, CRM
tools, email platforms, support platforms.
Each system has its own format and timing.
So trying to combine all of
this only through batch ETL
becomes slow and difficult.
The third problem is scalability.
Marketing workloads are unpredictable.
A flash sale, a festive campaign,
an influencer promotion, or a
product launch can create huge
spikes in traffic all of a sudden.
So one minute the website must be--
might be having normal traffic, five
minutes later, thousands of customers are
clicking your website, browsing, adding
cart, purchasing, all at the same time.
So static infrastructure
cannot handle this well.
So this is why we need
event-driven architecture, and
it becomes all the more important
So in an event-driven system, every
customer action is treated as an event.
A page view is an event, a click is an
event, adding an item to a cart is an
event, completing a purchase is an event.
Each event is captured immediately
and sent through the data platform.
So when a customer views a product, that
event can update a dashboard, refresh
the customer's profile, or even help
the recommendation engine understand
what the customer is interested in.
When a customer clicks an offer, that
can be used as A/B testing, campaign
measurement, and behavioral scoring.
When a customer abandons a cart, they
can even trigger a recovery campaign.
So instead of looking backward at what
happened yesterday, the businesses can
act while the customer is still active
Okay.
So now let's talk about
the data storage layer.
So a data warehouse such as Snowflake,
BigQuery, Redshift is like a very
well-organized office filing cabinet.
It's excellent for clean, structured data.
So if, say, for example, a marketing
manager wants to ask what was our
revenue yesterday, or which campaign
generated the most conversion, a data
warehouse is a good place to answer that.
Snowflake, for example, can store clean
marketing data and support dashboards.
But again, marketing data is
not always clean and structured.
Clickstream logs, raw app events,
product images, creative assets, customer
journey data, all these sort of data
are messy and are semi-structured.
So this is why data lake is useful.
A data lake is a large storage area where
we can keep raw data in different formats.
But if you only want to use a
data lake, it may not be fast or
organized for business dashboards.
So this is why many organizations
are using a lakehouse approach.
So a lakehouse will combine the best
of both worlds, so it gives us the
flexibility of a data lake and the
analytical power of a warehouse.
So for example, raw clickstream events
can be stored for future machine learning,
while clean campaign and revenue data
can be queried quickly for dashboard.
So the… in simple terms,
warehouse helps us report, the
lake helps us store raw behavior.
The lakehouse helps us report,
learn, predict, and improve
from the same foundation.
So now let's move on to
the streaming pipelines
So at the center of many
real-time systems is Apache Kafka.
So Kafka is like a live message highway.
So every customer action
becomes a message.
so for example, a customer viewed a
product, a customer abandoned a cart-
cart, customer added item to a cart.
So Kafka receives these messages
and sends them to different
systems at the same time.
One system may update real-time audience
segments, another system may update
the recommendation engine, another
may trigger a marketing campaign.
So the important thing there
is that these systems do not
need to wait for each other.
So Kafka allows many downstream systems
to consume same events independently.
So on top of Kafka, stream processing
tools such as, Apache Flink, Spark
Streaming, AWS, Kinesis process
the data while it is moving.
So Kafka carries the events,
Flink or Spark Streaming
processes the events, right?
Snowflake or another warehouse stores
and analyzes the clean data, right?
so this is where real-time audience
segmentation becomes very important
So audience segmentation simply
means grouping customers based
on who they are, what they do.
So for example, our customers
who viewed shoes but did not buy,
customers who added items to a cart,
customers who are active right now.
So in real-time marketing, these
groups should be updated immediately.
So if a customer abandons a
cart now, we do not want to add
them to the segment tomorrow.
We want the segment to be updated now.
But this creates a technical challenge.
So in a streaming environment, thousands
or even millions of customer profiles
updates may arrive every second
So the system cannot slowly
scan every customer one by one.
It needs smarter ways to find
the right customers quickly.
So this is where specialized indexes help.
So let me explain this in a simple way.
So an index is like the
index at the back of a book.
So instead of reading the whole
book, you go to the index and
quickly find the page you need.
In real-time segmentation, we
need advanced indexes because
the questions are more complex.
So first, we have inverted index.
an inverted index is keeping
like a ready-made list.
One list may contain all
customers interested in shoes.
Another list may contain all customers
who clicked a, discount ad. So when the,
marketing teams, hey, ask who are the
customers who are inter-interested
in shoes and also clicked on the
discounted ad, the system does not
check every customer individually.
It rather compares these ready-made lists
and finds the matching customers quickly.
Second, we have bitmap indexes.
these indexes are a yes or no checklist.
So for each customer, the system may
just track simple behavior flags.
Clicked ad, yes or no?
Added to cart, yes or no?
Purchased, yes or no?
So computers are extremely fast at
checking these yes or no patterns.
So if the campaign, system asks, "Hey,
find everyone who clicked the ad, added
to cart, but did not purchase," bitmap
indexes can answer that very quickly.
Third, we have materialized views.
A materialized view is like
preparing the answer in advance.
So for example, marketing teams often
ask the same questions repeatedly.
How many users abandoned carts today?
Which campaign is driving
the most purchase?
So instead of calculating the same
answer again and again from raw data, the
systems keep a pre-computed result ready.
So when the dashboard asks the question,
the answer appears almost instantly.
So this is why, real-time marketing
analytics is not only a data
engineering problem, it is also a
data-based architecture problem.
So we need the right storage,
the right streaming pipeline,
the right indexing strategy.
But technology alone is not enough.
This is where DataOps becomes essential.
the same principles that made DevOps
effective for software delivery must
be applied to data platforms too.
So in software DevOps, we
use version control for code.
In DataOps, we need version control
for schemas and pipeline definitions.
in DevOps, we used automated testing.
In DataOps, we need a automated data
quality validation and regression testing.
In application delivery,
we use CI/CD pipelines.
In database analytic environments, we
need CI/CD for database migrations.
In software operations,
we monitor services.
In DataOps, we monitor
pipelines, freshness of data,
schema failures, consumer lag.
This matters because real-time systems
have no overnight maintenance window.
Data is always moving.
Customers are always interacting,
so the system cannot simply, stop
because the schema needs to be changed.
So that leads us to schema
evolution without downtime.
So in a streaming system, we
cannot stop everything at midnight
and make the change manually.
So data, as I said, is always
moving, customers are always active.
So this is why schema evolution
must happen without downtime.
A safe way, approach is
expand, migrate, and contract.
so first we expand by adding
a new field in a safe way.
Then we might migrate producers
and consumers gradually.
Finally, when the old version is
no longer needed, we remove it.
So this sort of allows the system to keep
running while changes are introduced.
a schema registry helps
enforce these rules.
It prevents one team from accidentally
publishing a data format that
breaks another team's pipeline.
the same idea applies to
machine learning models, right?
in marketing, machine learning models
may predict which customer is likely
to buy, which product to recommend,
or which customer may abandon.
customer behavior is constantly
changing, so models need retraining.
But we cannot just replace a model
suddenly and hope it works, right?
which is why,
zero time downtime model
training is very important.
So zero downtime model retraining allows
us new models to be trained in parallel,
validated, and gradually introduced,
monitored, and then promoted once stable.
So a blue-green or canary deployment
strategy can shift traffic gradually
from old model to the new model
while still monitoring performance.
Auto ML can take this further
by automating the featuring--
feature engineering, model
selection, hyperparameter
tuning, and retraining cycles.
So when drift is detected, retraining
can be triggered automatically,
reducing drift to time, deployment
time from weeks to even hours.
Okay.
so now let's talk about scaling.
So marketing workloads, like
I said, are spiky by nature.
Reactive auto-scaling is often too slow.
So inf-infrastructure only scales
after traffic has already surged.
Users may experience slow dashboard,
delayed personalization, or
even missed campaign triggers.
So a better strategy rather
is prova- proactive scaling.
For example, event ingestion rate
can act as a leading indicator.
If the event bus starts receiving a
sudden surge in activity, that may
predict incoming query load at the
warehouse or segmentation layer.
The system can then scale
query infrastructure before
the spike even reaches it.
So the goal is not just to
survive peak load, the goal is
to actually maintain consistent
latency throughout the peak load
Observe- observability is
what makes this possible.
So a batch job usually succeeds or fails.
A streaming pipeline is more subtle.
it can degrade gradually.
Consumer lag increases, schema
failure rises, data quality erodes,
model predictions drift, and by the
time a traditional alert fires, the
business impact may already be visible.
That is why streaming observability
needs to focus on leading indicators.
So consumer lag tells us whether
processes are keeping up with ingestion.
Schema failure rates reverse-- reveal,
upstream data quality issues before
they corrupt downstream models.
P99 query latency exposes
pressure on critical dashboards.
Model drift metrics show when predictions
are no longer behaving as, expected
in distributed systems, consistency
needs to be intentional.
Not every marketing event
carries the same business risk.
A misclick may be okay.
A duplicate purchase record may not be.
All right
so applying global strong
consistency everywhere creates
unnecessary performance overhead.
So instead, organization should
apply selective consistency.
strong consistency may only be
required for, financial transactions,
purchase attribution or deduplication.
Eventual consistency may be okay
for behavioral streams like click
tracking and audience scoring.
causal consistency is useful
where ordering matters, such
as session stitchi-stitching
or funnel reconstruction.
but, full global
synchronization is not required.
So this selective approach
allows us to balance correctness,
latency, and also throughput
cost optimization is,
another major concern.
Real-time systems, become expensive
if cost is not treated as operational
metric right from the beginning.
at the infrastructure level, spot
or preemptible instances can reduce
costs for batch workloads where
interruption is okay, acceptable.
At the query level, result caching,
caching materialized views and
automated query controls can
prevent expensive ad hoc queries.
at the data level, tiered storage policies
can move older or less frequently accessed
data from high-performance storage
to lower cost storage automatically.
in real-time architecture, cost
observability should sit beside,
performance observability.
You cannot optimize, what you cannot see
privacy is also becoming very
central to marketing analytics.
federated learning,
offers one path forward.
So instead of moving raw customer
data into a central system,
models can be trained locally,
in a browser or within
a partner environment.
Only model updates or gradients
are shared with central aggregator.
This, enables us some use cases such
as, cross-publisher audience modeling,
collaborative filtering, and on-device
per-personalization while reducing
the need to share raw user-level data.
So how should organizations
implement this?
there are three broad paths.
The first is complete
cloud-native transformation.
this means starting fresh with
event-dri-driven architecture,
CI/CD, managed infrastructure, and
cloud-native services from the beginning.
this gives the most coherent long-term
architecture but is usually only best
suited for new platform initiatives.
The second is hybrid migration.
This is where enterprises operate today.
Stable workloads remain in, on batch
pipelines, while latency-sensitive
use cases move to streaming.
This will allow the… This
approach allows the teams to
build expertise incrementally.
The third is incremental modernization.
Organizations introduce cloud-native
components into an existing on-prem
architecture without the full migration.
this minimizes disruption, but the batch
bottleneck often remains at the boundary
So from production deployments,
few lessons are clear.
Infrastructure as code
should be used from day one.
Manual provisioning creates
inconsistency and makes recovery harder.
Data quality infrastructure must
be built before analytic models,
because in real-time systems, bad
data pro-propagates instantly.
Stream processing should be
containerized, monitored, and
supported by automatic rollback.
Schema registries with compatibility
checks are essential to prevent
silent upstream breakage.
And finally, team must stress test
well beyond expected peak load.
Many streaming failure models
only appear under pressure.
so to conclude, cloud-native
data architecture and Data DevOps
together represent a qualitative
shift in marketing analytics.
This is not simply faster
version of yesterday's batch
processing, batch reporting.
It is a different
operational model completely.
It requires deliberate data
foundation using lakes,
warehouses, and lakehouse patterns.
It requires real-time indexing strategy
built for dynamic segmentation.
It requires mature CI/CD for
schema, pipelines, and models.
And it requires operational
discipline around observability,
consistency, privacy, and cost.
So organizations that build
reliable, scalable, high performance
real-time analytic platforms
will operate with a fundamental
marketing intelligence advantage.
They will not be waiting for
overnight batch jobs to complete.
They will be learning,
adapting, and acting while
customer intent is still alive.
thank you so much for, letting me present