Speaker 23: Hi.
Firstly, I want to take this
opportunity to thank you all
for being in this session.
Myself, Ilavarasan Asokan.
I work as an Oracle database
administrator, and I have almost
fourteen-plus years of total Oracle
database work experience and almost
like fifteen-plus years of total IT
work, professional work experience.
And apart from the Oracle database
administration, I worked on Postgres
database administrator as well.
And for the past five to six
years, I've worked managing the
databases in AWS environment
and Azure environments as well.
As part of the database administration
activity, I worked on almost all
the aspects of database, right from
installing the software, patching,
upgradation, and working with the
application users on day-to-day user
request and migrating the databases
working on the performances related
to the databases and the SQL queries.
And also like I worked on big scale
migrations, almost like databases
size, sizes ranging from five
DB to almost fifty DB databases.
And this is about me, and
without wasting much of the time,
let's get into this session.
So today's topic is about
AI-driven da-database DevOps.
So firstly, like what
this topic is all about.
So when you say AI database DevOps,
the use of artificial intelligence and
machine learning to automate, optimize,
and manage database changes within the
software deve-- delivery pipelines.
So it applies the speed and continuous
integration and continuous delivery, CI/CD
principles of DevOps to the databases.
Which allows teams to deploy
schema updates and manage data as,
as securely and reliably, and as
reliably as the application code.
So the key ca-capabilities, if you see
it involves intelligent schema migrations
and automated query optimization and
anomaly detection, automated rollbacks.
And the core benefit that we can
achieve with this method is the faster
time to market and also like proactive
maintenance and enhanced compliance.
Also, if you see the AI-driven
database DevOps, it's all about
the-- from the predictive tuning to
the autonomous database management.
And So till now, if you see like for
the past few years back, like the
way we have managed the database, it
always been the traditional approach.
So if you see the traditional
approach, we have been we would
have faced multiple challenges with
respect to the traditional methods.
If you see as part of this traditional
method, we as DD-DBAs spend most of
the times in query optimization and
performance profiling, and also like we
manually ma-maintain the indexes, and
we manually manage the storage as well.
And also if you see the performance
related issues, whenever we get
some kind of problems with respect
to the application or the database
it's always been like reactive.
So it's as a result, there has
been always a pressure whenever
we work on those kind of issues.
And also like the incident recovery
and always the issues that we work on,
it always we see the we do the RCA.
So it's almost like a
post-mortem analysis.
So the modern challenges that we
face with respect to the-- there
is continuous deployment increase
database complexity exponentially.
So whenever there's some kind of
changes very frequently happening
with respect to the code, all that,
so like it can increase the complexity
and also like a workloads shift
dynamically in cloud environments.
So in recent times, like we have
started seeing like lot of databases
hosted in cloud environment.
So with each cloud, like the work
previously when compared to the on-premise
environments, like the workload that we
pattern is almost like dynamic in nature.
And also like the issues are manual
tuning, and sometimes it cannot
keep pace with the DevOps velocity.
With DevOps, like it's almost
like it's everything is automated.
So that advantage we
can get with the DevOps.
And also it's almost like the reactive
monitoring leads to delayed and costly
incident response So the next slide.
So over here, it's like we are
going to see the things like what
the traditional method DBML model
that we have followed till few years
back, and how this AI-driven DevOps
model can add advantage to the work
that we do on day-to-day basis.
So from reactive to predictive operations.
So the shift to AI driven DevOps replaces
slow manual workflows with intelligent
and continuously optimizing systems.
So with this, the goal is like the
intelligent systems that predict
issues before failure occurs,
optimize continuously, and improve
the deployment reli-reliability.
So using like the traditional manual
tuning and the threshold alerts,
whenever we get some kind of alerts,
then only we start to work, and as
a result, it's a reactive scaling.
So whenever there is some kind of changes
that's needed, when we want to scale
up the things, like it's a reactive
approach that we are following over here.
So also like on day-to-day basis, like
we can see like the static indexing
approach, that is what we follow.
And it's very much all the things that
we do is human-centric troubleshooting.
So with AI-driven DevOps model,
so the-- almost all the things,
most of the things are automated.
So the optimization things
that we do is automated and
it's predictive intelligence.
With this actually like we are like
using the AI and ML capabilities
to our advantage and for the
business, in turn, it helps a lot.
And forecast-based scaling.
So adaptive index.
So it's the with the help of this
AI-driven model, so we can do the adaptive
indexing and AI-assisted remediation.
So since AI and ML is already integrated
with the operations on day-to-day
work that we do, so which like the
AI helps in gathering the information
on various workloads and other things
related to the databases, which in
turn helps and to focus a lot of the
things, and it can provide a remediation
or a solution for the futures that we
are about to encounter in the future.
So in the next slide, so we are going
to see about the core components
of AI-driven database DevOps.
The core components, it's going to be
the predictive workload forecasting
and automated index optimization
and AI-based anomaly detection
and semi-autonomous operation.
So with the predictive workload
forecasting, so it's like going to-- we
are going to anticipate future resource
demand and prevent bottlenecks before
they impact production, which is very
much important in the times like this
play would contribute a lot to the
work that we do on day-to-day basis.
And automated index optimization with
this, like it's going to be reinforcement
learning adapts indexing strategies
dynamically to evolve query patterns.
So based on the query patterns and
all those things that the application
is using, so like the AI driven
model can provide the automated
index optimization approaches.
So the third one is going to
be the AI anomaly detection AI.
So with this we are going to detect
abnormal behavior early and dramatically
reduce alerts fatigue for on-call teams.
So this is going to be an very
good advantage for the people who
are doing the on-call support.
So in the midnight, we don't know at
what time in the traditional approaches
like unexpectedly some kind of issues
or incident can turn up and get--
can become a nightmare for the d-DBS.
And with this AI-based anomaly detection,
so well in advance we can detect the
things, the future problem that we are
going to encounter in the database, and we
can take the actions prior to the instance
whenever it's about to happen, yeah.
So semi-autonomous operation.
So with this, like the
continuous feedback-driven
optimization with human-in-loop
governance and trust controls.
So as part of the continuous
feedback-driven optimization, so
along with this, like our human
interaction is also going to be there.
So with this, like we can govern, and
we can control the things, what all is
needed and what is best suited for us.
So in the next slide, it would--
we are going to see about the
AI-based workload prediction.
So how it works.
So ML models continuously analyze
historical and real-time signals
to demand-- to forecast demand.
So historically, workload patterns
and CPU utilizations are analyzed on
regular basis based on the pattern
the individual users perform or
what's happening on the database.
IO throughput and deployment schedules
and traffic behavior and seasonal trends.
So with all these things the ML models can
gather the details and which will be used
as input for for the workload prediction.
So models used.
So if you see like LSTM, so which
is like Long Short-Term Memory
networks and in some-- and also the
proactive allocation is there with
this prediction model and also like
smarter scaling and better planning.
So proactive allocation, so with all
the d-- data that this gathered and we
can predict like in future if we want to
allocate any kind of allocation is needed,
resource allocation needs to be provided,
a provision that gives an idea for that.
And also like smarter scaling.
So it's a data-driven
infrastructure deci-decisions.
So based on the data that is
gathered, so we can take a call
whether we want to scale up or not.
And also in turn, this
benefits with better planning.
So workload forecasting
aligned to release cycles.
So next are the workload
predictions in DevOps.
So AI teams, how the
AI team helps the DBs.
So the first is like anticipate workload
spikes before they hit productions
and also like allocate infrastructure
proactively, not reactively, and
reduce operational uncertainty
during releases, improve deployment
readiness and release confidence.
So how the-- it can benefit us
practically, how the practical
applications are there because of this.
So if you see like e-commerce
traffic surges and flash sales.
So for online websites where the
e-commerce website, for them it's going
to be of great use and also like batch
processing, schedule optimization.
So for this also like it will
play a critical role and also
like feature release and canary
deployment planning, cloud cost
optimization through right sizing.
So in the next slide, we're going
to see about the automated indexing
using reinforcement learning.
So in the traditional like
way, like what are the problems
associated with the-- with this?
So in the traditional method,
index maintenance is highly
manual and time-consuming.
So based on the SQL patterns and the
application usage, we DBAs have to
manually gather various information,
and we need to manually maintain all
the indexes and then in case of any
performance related issues, we need to
manually involve us-- ourself like and
which is highly time-consuming and also
there are high chances that we might not
come up with effective indexing as well.
So workloads evolve continuously,
making static indexes obsolete.
So with some-- at some point of time,
the amount of data in the databases could
be of one TB or two TB, for instance.
Over the period of time, like three,
four years down the line, the database
size can grow up to few more TBs,
like ten TB or something like that.
In those scenarios like static indexing,
the indexes that has been created
manually might not be as effective when
the database sizes-- size grows up.
So this is one of the challenges
because of the traditional approach.
And also like incorrect or
bloated indexes increased
storage overhead and slow writes.
So how this challenge is solved
using the AI-driven approach?
So reinforcement learning agents
continuously observe query behavior, then
recommend, create, and retire indexes
autonomously, delivering optimization
without constant DBA intervention.
So with the datas that has been gathered
over the time, so the AI-driven approach
can take care of the things like it can
recommend and create and automatically it
can choose which index can provide better
performance for the database operations.
So with this it's going to be a boon
for the database work that we are in.
Slide.
So benefits of AI-based indexes.
So with-- because of this, we are
going to achieve the faster query
execution times and better storage
utilization and continuous learning.
So we see like faster query
executions because of the AI-based
indexing, like optimal index.
Indexes reduce query latencies
and improve application response
times across read/write workloads.
So also like the next thing is
like better storage utilization.
Redundant and unused indexes
are automatically identified and
removed, freeing valuable storage.
So and there is the continuous learning.
So systems dynamically adapt to
applications changes, improve
analytical query handling over time.
So the next one is like
AI-powered anomaly detection.
So in the traditional monitoring,
like the gaps are excessive alert
noise drowns out real instance.
So we would have configured lot of alerts.
Sometimes like we might get
based on the alerts that we have
configured the traditional approach.
There can be like of all the
hundreds of alerts like or few
alerts that we have configured.
So which there could be a few of
the alerts which can't be a real
issue at all, but along with those
incidents, there will be like some
alerts which are like very critical.
So when it's all mixed up, sometimes we
mi-- because of this, like we might miss
the actual alert, which is very critical.
So delayed detection extends
meantime to lead a recovery.
So this is one of the other problems,
and subtle performance anomalies
goes unnoticed until failure.
So this is the other problem that we face
with the traditional monitoring approach.
So how the AI-empowered anomaly detection
empowers us is what AI monitors.
So query latency and execution
behavior, CPU, memory, and I/O
re-resource utilization, and transaction
patterns, and system anomalies.
So it's going to monitor
all of these things.
And technologies, if you see like
it going to be time series analysis
and clustering algorithm and deep
learning anomaly detection models.
So using these approaches and we have
with all the inputs, and we can achieve
faster and smarter incident response.
So with all these things, like we
can detect the problems earlier.
So AI surfaces anomalies before they
escalate into production anomalies,
production incidents, reducing the
meantime to recover significantly.
And also reduced alert fatigue.
So intelligent alert filtering
eliminates noise, ensuring engineers
only respond to high signals and
actionable alerts, which is nothing bad.
Like we are going to get the
alert which are very critical
and the actual incidents only.
Getting rid of unwanted things.
So the next thing is, identify issue
discovery, detect deadlock scenarios,
execution plan regressions, and
unusual access patterns automatically.
And also which it also like
improves the reliability.
Continuous observability drives
greater op-- greater operational
stability and system-wide resilience.
And the next one is the embedding
AI into CI/CD workflows.
So how we are going to integrate
all these things into the DevOps,
CI, continuous integration and
continuous deployment workflows.
So DevOps provide the-- these
benefits like faster deployments.
Whenever we deploy manually, like there
is time thing, like excessive time
consumed because of the manual efforts.
So with the DevOps, like we are
able to deploy we are able to
make the deployments faster.
So AI validates database changes
pre-release and also like
greater release confidence.
So with the integrating all those things,
so we can it provides greater release
confidence, performance baselines enforced
automatically and reduced disruptions.
So intelligent rollback
decision minimizes blast radius.
So it doesn't-- whenever there's
an impact, it's not wider like--
so wherever like because of this,
like we are minimizing the incidents
or alerts, like all those things.
So continuous optimization, feedback
loops improve every release cycle.
So AI integrated pipeline shift
database reliability left, catching
issues before they reach production So
real-world implementation challenges.
So although there are a lot of
advantages with this, so in order to
implement the changes in our real-time
projects, there are challenges as well.
So the challenges can be like
continuous learning requirements.
Or here, like models require continuous
regular retraining as workloads evolve.
Stale models produce
misleading recommendation.
And also the next one is like data
quality issues, inconsistent telemetry
and fragmented monitoring systems degrade
model accuracy and signal reliability.
So the third is the
legacy system integration.
So older platforms often lack modern
APIs, making automation support limited
with-without significant re-engineering.
So although there are a lot of
businesses which are fine running
with the legacy systems, so in order
to integrate all those AI and driven
approaches, so all those things,
these challenges will be there.
And fourth one is the governance
and org-organizational trust.
So teams require oversight mechanisms and
transparent AI reasoning before trusting
automatic autonomous recommendations.
So since this is an evolving technology,
so there is a continuous governance and
oversight is needed to see and validate if
everything is going through as expected.
So automation versus human control.
So risks of full automations.
So incorrect optimization decisions in
edge cases, so performance regressions
that are difficult to trace and unexpected
operational behavior in production.
So sometimes like when there are some
mistakes or something, if it is not
going well as expected, so these are
the things that we can encounter.
So recommended as human-in-loop.
So A suggests although like-- A
suggests-- so recommendation surface
with context and context scores.
And once the suggestions are there,
like we humans need to validate.
With that, we ensure that high-risk
changes require explicit explicit
approvals and gradual adaptation
presented in evolving technology.
So we have to adapt things gradually.
So automation expands
as trust is established.
So the best practices: shadow
mode testing before live changes.
So before any changes we are
implemented in production, so
shadow mode testing needs to be
performed in the lower environments.
So controlled rollout
with blast radius limits.
So whenever we are rolling it out,
whenever things are not going expected,
so the impact should be minimal that like
it doesn't disrupt the entire business
activity or disrupt the whole system.
So progressive trust building
through measurable outcomes.
So things need to be taken one
step at a time so that, like we
gather the trust So roadmap through
semi-autonomous data-databases.
So stage one is observability.
So comprehensive telemetric
collection and baseline behavior
modeling across all database tiers.
So stage two is AI recommendation.
So AI surfaces optimization
suggestions, human engineers
review and approve all the changes.
So although all the changes is like
AI recommends, we humans need to
intervene and see like whether the
changes what it's suggesting is optimal.
So the third is the stage
three, the low-risk automation.
So routine maintenance task
and safe optimization actions
executed without manual approvals.
And stage four is
semi-autonomous operations.
So AI-driven scaling, semi
self-optimizing index, predictive
remediations with governance guardrails.
So in the next slide, we're going to
see the future of database DevOps.
So in the future, it's going
to be from reactive approach
to the predictive approach.
AI transforms operation from
firefighting to forecasting.
So smarter scaling, predictive forecasting
drives better capacity planning.
And next is adaptive index.
Reinforcement learning continuously
optimizes query performance.
So last one is the
resilient observability.
AI detection improves incident
response and system stability.
So the future of DevOps is intelligent
collaboration, human setting intent,
AI executing with precision and system
that continuously improves themselves.
So with this, we are coming
to the end of this session.
And lastly, I also want to take this
opportunity to thank you all for
staying with me in this entire session.
Thanks a lot.