Speaker 12: Hi hi everyone.
This is Naga Bellamkonda.
I have 15 to 16 years of experience
in managing databases and managing,
administering, architecting databases
both in on-premise and in AWS Cloud.
I have a very good experience in managing
Oracle, Postgres Redshift, Aurora
Postgres, MySQL, SQL and NoSQL databases.
So today I'm going to talk about what
is the impact of AI in database tuning.
So the AI-driven database
tuning in DevOps.
So it's a real-world lessons from
self-optimizing systems, drawing
from production deployments in
finance, e-commerce and healthcare
So why manual tuning can't keep up?
So if we encounter any issue in production
systems, the manual tuning to identify
the root cause, it may take hours and
sometimes it may take days to determine
the root cause of the production issue.
So there is a gap in identifying the
root cause, so where the business
continuity may disturb in such cases.
To speed up and to cope up the latest
trends, the performance degradation from
a bad deployment begins within a minutes.
Manual database tuning operates
on timescales of hours or days.
The core problem: modern DevOps
environments deploy continuously
and scale dynamically.
Traditional tuning was built for
a world that no longer exists.
The gap between the speed of change
and the speed of remediation is
precisely where self-optimizing
systems deliver their greatest value
Beyond monitoring, we need to adapt
continuously to improve and to stabilize
the production database architecture.
So in order to achieve that, the
self-tuning database systems do
more than alert the ca-- they act.
The shift is from reactive troubleshooting
to proactive continuous optimization.
Workload monitoring is a continuous
analysis of query patterns
as they evolve in production.
Index management can be done through
automatic index creation and removal
based on observed access patterns.
Query optimization, execution plan
selection refined continuously
in historical workloads.
Resource allocation, memory, and compute
adjusted dynamically to match demand.
Security patching, automated patching
with minimal downtime and full audit
trails Where we deployed, there are
three sectors, three distinct challenges.
Each require a different entry
point into AI-driven tuning.
In case of finance, query plan regressions
causing SLA breaches after releases.
The need, the plan stability
at deployment speed.
E-commerce, workload spikes
around promotional events.
The need is to be like a proactive
scaling, not reactive scrambling
in order to in order to handle
very high load during particular
particular events or days.
And healthcare, strict regulatory
compliance requirements.
The need is the auditability
before automation.
So these are the challenges that
we-- any DBA can encounter in the
real world when we are supporting
databases in different projects
When it comes to the financial services,
stopping plan regression at the gate.
So it means when we notice that
the the query is picking the wrong
plan it means the query execution
times will increase, so which leads
to the performance degradation.
So the actual problem lies in execution
plan regressions following application
releases caused intermittent failures
in transaction processing detected only
after production users were impacted.
What we built, how we handle
these kind of situations.
So the AI is providing
like different options.
One among those is like AI-driven
query plan monitoring embedded
directly into the CI/CD pipeline.
Regressions detected within seconds
of deployment and automatically
rolled back to stable configurations,
which we can roll back quite
easily by building CI/CD pipelines
So when it comes to the e-commerce
predicting the surge, the problem:
static overprovisioning was expensive.
Reactive scaling was too slow
for promotional traffic spikes.
By the time the system responded,
revenue was already lost.
So what we built.
So machine learning models trained
on historical promotional patterns
connected to the marketing events
pipeline for advanced signals.
Resources were allocated before
traffic arrived, not in response to it.
Instead of reactive, it could be
a proactive way of approaching
of way of dealing the load on
the database or infrastructure
How are we going to build the architecture
when it comes to the healthcare?
Building trust before automating.
The problem, any automated
configuration change required a
full auditable approval trail.
Early automation would have
created compliance risk
even when technically sound.
What we build.
A staged approach.
AI recommendations surfaced
through a review dashboard first.
Only after demonstrating reliable, aware,
a low-risk reversible change automated
with complete audit logging throughput
How machine learning improves queries.
AI-driven optimization moves
beyond static rules by continuously
learning from real workloads.
The system improves because it observes
the consequences of its own decision.
Observe, recommend, adopt, and test.
So this loop architecture is what
distinguishes genuine self-optimization
from sophisticated alerting
Three failures that reshaped our approach.
Model staleness.
A major application refactor
shifted query patterns faster
than the model could adapt.
Degraded recommendations went
undetected for nearly two weeks.
So transfer learning limits.
A model trained in one environment
did not port cleanly to a similar
client, so residual gaps required
weeks of fine-tuning to close.
Integration complexity.
Connecting AI engines to existing
CI/CD pipelines and change management
systems consistently took longer
than building the models themselves.
So any technical sophistication without
operational integration delivers no value.
So So, also in order to handle this, so
we are, we-we are going to design the
indexing automation that we can trust.
So automated indexing is high
value and a high risk, so
architecture is what make it safe.
So before we implement in the
production system, so we can test
this automated index creation in
non-production environments to
make sure that it gives the exact
and output to handle the workload
and in order to fix the regression
performance tuning-- query regression
and performance tuning improvement.
The shadow evaluation first.
New recommendations tested against
replayed production traffic before
any promotion to live systems.
Full change provenance.
Every change tagged with the model version
and workload context that generated it.
Rollback is non-negotiable.
One-click rollback built into
the pipeline from day one, not
retrofitted after the first instant.
Post-change monitoring.
Write performance and lock
contention observed immediately
after every automated index change
You cannot automate what you cannot see.
That's exactly every automated change
was logged with full context and
surfaced in the same dashboard teams
already used for deployment monitoring.
Teams often frustrated tr-- sometimes
if the automation breaks, so there could
be a major impact to the performance
in the production architecture.
So every automated change was logged
with full context and surfaced in
the same dashboards teams already
used for deployment monitoring.
This is very important.
So teams trusted the system because
they could always see what it had done.
Recommendation rationale.
Why the model generated each
specific recommendation.
Model version.
Which model version produced the
change, enabling regression analysis.
Shadow validation.
Results from pre-production
testing against replay traffic.
Deployment timestamp.
Precise timing for correlation
with upstream deployment events.
Observed impact.
Post-deployment performance delta
fed back into model training.
And this is very important in order
to determine what are the changes
that we are embedded and what are the
consequences that we are going to face.
So this architecture and this model
gives us overall picture how we
are going to handle and how-- what
we are anticipating our workload
and how are we going to handle it
So in the real time, so the
real-time query log analysis,
there are three components in it.
The open source toolkit that powered
all three deployments is built
around a closed feedback loop:
ingestion, optimization, deployment.
The closed loop between deployment
outcomes and model training is what allows
the system to improve continuously rather
than re-degrading as workloads evolve
Four things we would change.
Invest earlier in
telemetry infrastructure.
So data quality limits
recommendation quality.
Build reliable pipelines
before building models.
Stay in recommendation mode longer.
Automating before organizational
trust is established creates incidents
that set back adoption by months So
i-i-instead of implementing a recommend
more longer, so automated before
organization's trust is established.
So that would leads to creating
incidents and production system breakup.
So in order to avoid those things
whatever that we are implementing
in step two, so just to be trust is
established creates incident that
set back adopt- adoption by months.
This is we have to be very careful before
we make any changes in the production
architecture, and that's what it explains.
So define retraining
triggers from day one.
So formal accuracy thresholds and
retaining schedules along in the-- belong
in the initial design, not as reaction
to the first model's stateless incident.
And finally, and fourth one,
design every change as reversible.
This is very important.
Whenever we… in the real world, whenever
we are doing any changes in the production
systems, we need to prepare both
implementation plan and rollback plan.
In the event of a not successful
outcome, we should be in a position
to roll back the changes in the
production system in order to establish
the stable and a prior to changes.
So if we are able to roll back as, as
soon as possible so that we can make
the production system, we can bring
the production system back to life.
That's what this design every
change as reversible is very
important in order to make change
in the production architecture.
So if you cannot roll back it cleanly,
you should not automate it yet.
That is what it says.
Reversibility is a precondition,
not a stretch goal.
That's very important.
Whatever changes we are making in
the production, you should be able to
reverse it within the minimal time.
So that could-- that, that will really
help to avoid any production downtime.
This is very important
So there are four stages
for getting started.
Stage one: instrument and baseline.
Deploy telemetry.
Build workload models.
Take no automated action.
Build insight and trust.
And in stage two: recommendation driven.
Surface AI suggestions in dashboards.
Humans approve all changes.
Begin in the feedback loop Stage
three: automate low-risk actions.
Define a bounded category
of reversible changes.
Full audit logging and rollback required.
Stage four: progressive expansion.
Expand automation based on demonstrated
reliability, human approval for schema
changes and irreversible actions.
And sometimes if we are making any…
Most of the times, if we are making any
changes, either we need to have a rollback
plan or in case if you're making any
data changes in the production system,
the best way is if it is on-premise
Oracle, you should take the backup.
If it is on-premise Oracle, we should be
able to take the backup of the schemas
or tables individually, either through or
either through data pump or physical copy.
If it is AWS, better we take snapshots
in order to restore in the event
of any production corruption or any
unwanted outcomes post-deployments.
So this is what it explains.
And when it comes to the final slide,
what a success actually looks like.
The organization that succeeds
with AI-driven database tuning
are not those that deploy the
most soft-- sophisticated models.
They are those that build the operational
discipline to deploy, monitor, and iterate
on AI systems within the constraints
of real production environments.
The goal is not fully
autonomy for its own sake.
It is the right level of automation
for each action type, maximizing
efficiency while preserving human
control over risk and decisions.
Engage now.
The field is moving quickly.
Early movers build the institutional
knowledge that compounds over time.
Learn from failure.
Teams that document and share
failures, not just successes,
advance faster and more safely.
Own the future.
The teams engaging today will operate
the data systems that define the next
generation of enterprise architecture,
which is not only defining, it also leads
to the successful production systems--
stable and successful production systems
with minimal or with no downtime.
And thank you for giving this opportunity
to present and to talk on the latest AI
trends on AI data database-driven tuning.
Thank you