Speaker 5: Hello, everyone.
My name is Sirisha Ayagari, and
today I will be speaking about how
artificial intelligence and modern data
pipelines can transform SAP pricing
from static rule-based systems into
intelligent real-time pricing platforms.
Traditionally, SAP pricing has
relived-- relied heavily on condition
records, access sequence, and manually
maintained pricing procedures.
These approaches worked well for
the stable business environments.
But today, enterprises operate in
rapidly changing markets where pricing
decisions must react instantly to demand
changes, competitor pricing, inventory
availability, and customer behavior.
In this session, I will explain
how organizations can modernize SAP
pricing using AI, streamlining data
pipelines, DevOp principles, and clean
core SAP extensibility, extendable--
extensibility while still keeping SAP
as the trusted transactional backbone.
Let me move on to the next slide.
So in this slide, let's
discuss the problem.
Let us first understand
the core problem here.
Most SAP pricing systems today are
still static, but pricing rules
are manually configured and updated
to transports and change cycles.
Because of this, organizations often
react too slowly to the market conditions.
The first challenge is
rule-based constraints.
Pricing logic is optimized for
past business conditions rather
than live, live market signals.
The second issue is
lagging market response.
Traditional pricing tables cannot
dynamically respond to the competitor
price changes, demand spikes, or supply
chain dis-disturbances in real time.
The third issue is operational overhead.
Pricing teams spend significant
efforts managing exceptions,
approvals, overrides manually instead
of allowing intelligent system to
automate these decisions continuously.
As organizations become more digital
and global, this static pricing mode
becomes increasingly difficult to scale.
Let me move on to the next slide.
So the most under-modernized
enterprise component.
These days pricing is the most
under-modernized enterprise component.
One of the import-- One important
observation is that enterprises
have modernized many areas such as
finance, procurement, and supply
chain management using cloud
technologies and DevOp practices.
However, pricing remains one
of the most-- one of the least
modernized enterprise components.
In many organizations, pricing
pipelines are still dependent on
the manual governance cycles, static
configurations, spreadsheet-driven
updates, and delayed transport releases.
This creates a major gap
because pricing directly impacts
revenue, profitability, customer
competitiveness, and business agility.
My argument in this presentation is
that pricing should now be treated as
a real-time intelligent pipeline rather
than a static configuration exercise
So let's move on to the next slide.
So in this session, I will
cover four major areas.
First, I will explain why
traditional rule-based pricing
breaks at enterprise scale.
Secondly, I will discuss a hybrid
architecture where SAP remains
the transactional core while AI
becomes the optimization layer.
Third, I will explain how real-time
data pipelines continuously ingest
signals such as inventory levels,
customer demand, and competitor pricing.
Finally, I will discuss
op-opera-operationalizing machine learning
in production using DevOps principles
such as model deployment, drift detection,
observability, and rollback strategies.
Let's-- Let me move on to the next slide.
Why rule-based pricing breaks.
Rule-based pricing works effectively
when business environments
are stable and predictable.
However, modern markets
are highly dynamic.
Customer behaviors changes rapidly,
supply chain fluctuates, and
competitors update pricing continuously.
Traditional SAP condition records
and pricing procedures were never
designed to adapt this level
of volatility in the real-time.
As pricing logic grows more complex,
organizations face increasing
version lag, meaning the system
reflects outdated assumptions instead
of current business realities.
At the same time, exception
handling increases dramatically.
Manual override and approval
flows create operational depth and
making pricing process increasingly
brittle and difficult to maintain.
So- Let's move on to the next slide
The limits of SAP condition records.
This slide explains the core limitations
of traditional SAP SD pricing.
The first limitation is version lag.
Any pricing table updates usually
require change requests, testing
cycles, transports, approvals.
This process may take days or even weeks.
The second limitation
is context blindness.
Traditional rules cannot easily
incorporate live business signals such
as real-time inventory, competitor data
feeds, or predictive demand models.
The third limitation is
exception proliferation.
Over time, organizations accumulate
many special condition, conditions,
overrides, and custom logic scenarios,
creating technical debt and making
pricing, pricing logic fragile.
This is why organizations
need more intelligent and
adaptive pricing architecture.
Let me move on to the next slide
So the hybrid architecture.
Instead of replacing SAP, the
recommended approach is to
build a hybrid architecture.
In this model, SAP continues to serve
as the transactional system of record
responsible for order processing,
pricing execution, audibility.
Audi-- Sorry, auditability
and financial compliance.
An external AI layer acts
as optimization engine here.
It analyzes business signals, predicts
op-optimal pricing outcomes, and
provides recommendations back into SAP.
This approach preserves clean core
principles because SAP standard
functionality remains stable while
innovation happens extremely through
approved extensibility mechanism and APIs.
Let me move on to the next slide.
Architecture overview.
This architecture has three major layers.
The first layer is SAP transactional core,
which handles order execution, compliance
validation, and financial posting.
The second layer is the integration layer.
This acts as a bridge between the
SAP and external AI engine using
APIs and BAdIs extensibility points.
The third layer is AI optimization layer.
AI optimization layer or the AI
optimization engine, which performs model
interference, pricing recommendation,
and risk adjust-adjusted decision-making.
A very important point here is that
AI does not replace SAP authority.
SAP still validates and commits
all final pricing outcomes.
Let me move to the next slide.
Clean core compliance via BAdI.
One of the most important
enterprise architecture principles
today is clean core compliance.
SAP strongly ec-encourages customers
to avoid modifying standard
SAP code, instead use approved
extensibility frameworks such as BADIs.
So in this model, BADIs act as controlled
extension points where custom pricing
intelligence can be injected safely.
For example, the pricing preparation
logic, net price calculation, and the
manual pricing control mechanism, this
all can be achieved at the BAdI levels.
And few of the BAdI levels that are
a-available right now with the clean
core concepts are the condition
value determination, where we
can use the pricing_prepare BAdI.
For net value calculation,
we can use pricing complete.
So the external AI engine communicates
through these extension points,
allowing SAP to maintain upgrade
safe and cloud ready while supporting
advanced intelligence pricing behavior.
Let's move on to the next slide.
Real-time data pipelines.
AI pricing systems are only as effective
as quality and freshness of the data.
This chapter focuses on building
real-time data pipelines that continuously
injec-ingest enterprise signals.
Example, SAP SD order history,
inventory availability, customer
behavior, competitor pricing feeds,
and demand forecasting systems.
Instead of relying on stale batch
processing, the AI engine continuously
receives the live business context
and can therefore make more
intelligent pricing decisions.
Let's move on to the next slide.
Designing the pricing data pipelines.
This slide explains the technical
design of the pricing pipeline.
First, enterprise signals from SAP
systems are streamed using technologies
such as CDC or SAP Integration Suite.
Second, external market feeds
are integrated into the pipeline,
including competitor pricing
APIs and macro indic-- ma-- and
macroeconomic macroeconomic indicators.
Third, streaming infrastructures
such as Apache Kafka or IBM even
IBM Event Streams provides low
latency, scalable event processing.
This architecture allows organizations
to move to move from periodic pricing
updates to continuous intelligent
pricing optimization solutions.
Let's move on to the next slide
Operoni-- Op-Operationalizing ML,
machine learning in production.
Building a machine learning
model is only the beginning.
The real challenge is operoni--
operationalizing machine learning safety
in enterprise production environments.
This requires DevOps principles
such as controlled deployment,
monitoring, rollback strategies,
observability, and governance.
Organizations must ensure that pricing
models remain accurate, explainable, and
stable even as business conditions evolve.
Let's move on to the next slide.
ML model DevOps.
This slide explains the operational
life cycle of machine learning models.
The life cycle includes training,
validation, deployment, and
monitoring Each model version must
be fully traceable to its feature
schema and training dataset.
Drift decision mechanisms continuously
monitor whether production data
distributions are changing in ways
that could reduce model accuracy.
Automated rollback capabilities
ensure that if performance degrades
or latency thresholds are exceeded,
traffic automatically reverts
to the last stabilized model.
This allows organizations to manage
AI systems with the same rigor as
enterprise software deployments.
Let me move on to the next slide.
Auditability, consistency,
and performance at scale.
In enterprise pricing, governance
and auditability are critical.
Every AI-generated pricing recommendation
must be logged together with the model
version, input features, confidence
scores, and the decision context.
This supports financial
complements-- compliance and
regulatory review requirements.
Consistency is also important.
Distributed caching ensures that
SAP applications serve-- servers
return identical pricing results
within the same transaction window.
Finally, the performance matters.
Modern interference frameworks can
achieve sub-hundred milliseconds
response times while maintaining
enterprise scale throughout.
Let's move on to the next slide.
So what are the key takeaways here?
I would like to conclude
with three major takeaways.
The first is pricing is
fundament-fundamentally
a pipeline problem.
Modern pricing system requires
streaming ingestion, governance,
and continuous optimization.
Second, clean core
architecture is essential.
Organizations must innovate
with introducing technical depth
in S. Machine learning must be
operationalized like enterprise software.
Models should be versionized,
monitored, validated, and governed
with same discipline as the
production applica-applications.
The future of SAP pricing is
not static rule management.
It is intelligent, adaptive, AI-driven
decision systems integrated through
clean core enterprise architecture.
Water glass, light
So thank you everyone for
attending this session.
I hope this presentation provided
insights into the AI into how AI
streaming architecture and Clean Core
SAP exten-extensibility can modernize
the enterprise pricing system.
I would be happy to discuss the
architecture patterns, SAP extensibility
approaches, pricing optimization
strategies, or enterprise AI integration
questions during the Q&A session.
Thank you.