Speaker 14: Hello, everyone.
Good morning and good evening.
Glad to be part of Conf forty-two
to speak to you all today.
Let me introduce myself.
I am Muthu Saravanan, director of
experience design at Mindpros, where
we build citizen-centric portals and
apps for federal and state governments.
I also play an advisory role for a few
tech companies and startups, primarily
focused on AI-enabled experience design
and digita-digital transformation.
I also hold an IP and trademark
for HAX, which I will explain
in the upcoming slides.
And today, I'll be sharing about
how human and AI experience
bring structure, judgment and
reliability in DevOps development.
I'm recalling a situation that we
experienced some time ago while I was
part of a database team, and their
biggest frustration was the speed.
They could not do migration fast
enough because the pipeline is a major
bottleneck and needed more automation.
And after a series of discussion,
they brought in a specific tool
and it actually resolved the speed.
They could generate mi-migration
faster than before and scaffold
schemas better than before and
write queries at an incredible pace.
AI has dramatically accelerated the
database engineering and DevOps, but
unsure about the human experience
and how AI-driven delivery remains
reliable, explainable and trusted.
The skill is a major shift, and that's the
shift I wanted to be talking about today.
Okay, we resolved the speed problem,
but in doing so, we have uncovered
a much harder problem, like how
do you trust what AI builds?
And for years, the database team primarily
constrained by the capability and how
to automate deployments fast enough,
how to manage migration, and can the
pipeline scale with the business demand?
Earlier, velocity was the KPI,
but now AI change the equations.
AI tools can generate schemas much
faster, optimize queries, write
migration scripts, and automate
operational workflows almost instantly.
So the bottleneck is no
longer can we build it.
Rather, should we build it this way?
Because fast output is not the
same like a trustworthy output.
In database systems, inconsistencies
compound over a period of time that
quietly degrade the performance in
which we cannot even notice it until
it's a major issue or major bottleneck.
And one incorrect schema decisions
can survey for years, and a poorly
reviewed migration can cascade
into different production systems.
I call this emerging
problem as experience debt.
Similar to technical debt, but
more dangerous in AI systems
because it accumulates invisibly.
And here are the three major symptoms.
And first one is inconsistency creep.
Without governance, every engineer
interacts differently with AI tools.
They build different prompts, make
different assumptions, and create
more different validation standards.
Eventually, the team end up building
and sharing an inconsistent engineering
language, and that is going to
create a ch-chaos among the teams.
The second is amplified data risk.
AI-generated SQL may appear
syntactically correct but may end up
introducing security vulnerabilities,
index regressions, locking issues,
or perhaps integrity failures.
The third is erosion of trust.
This probably the biggest problem
compared to all the three.
When engineers stop understanding
on why AI has produced certain
output, they move into two extremes.
Either they blind-blindly trust or reject
it totally, and either of it leads to
both technical and operational failures.
And this is where HAX actually comes in.
HAX stands for human and AI experience,
a structured approach for adopting AI
intentionally across DevOp operations.
HAX also defines the lines between
where should humans retain authority
and where should AI accelerate
work, and how accountability flows
across the delivery lifecycle.
This framework classifies
the responsibility in two
distinct layers: HAX and IAX.
HAX is where humans and AI operate with
clearly defined expectations HX defined
areas where human experience is not
compromised by automated experience.
End of the day, it is a user who
uses the system should find it
easy, intuitive, and friendly.
These are not the tasks that AI can't do
it, but a human judgment is fundamentally
required because the decisions carry
long-term organizational consequences.
For example, in system architecture
AI can recommend scaling patterns,
but that does not understand
organizational politics or future
acquisition plans or business shape--
business strategy shapes, et cetera.
And in data modeling, schema
design is not just a structure.
It encodes the business meaning.
A naming convention mistake today
becomes a reporting problem for
the next four or five years.
And the governance is also another
critical domain where compliance,
access control, data classification,
audit accountability cannot be
simply delegated to the systems.
It requires human interventions
and the human thought.
And finally, the critical reasoning.
During production incidents humans
synthesize the context from many
sources from the team history, risk
tolerance business urgency, and
customer impact, and all of these stuff.
All these things cannot be
managed by the AI alone.
It requires the fundamental
human thought process.
In a nutshell, humans
decide, and AI elevates it.
Now, let's look at the facets
of AX, the AI experience layer.
The six facets defines where AI
actually adds value at the highest
across the DevOps lifecycle.
During detection, AI excels at anomaly
detections, identifying drift patterns
which humans most likely miss all this.
While predicting, AI can focus migration
risks, capacity growth query specs, and
even create or limited bottlenecks Scale
is where the repetitive operational
work becomes highly automated, like
index recommendations, connection
pooling, and pipeline orchestration.
During synthesize, AI does an
incredible job in consolidating the
information about telemetry, logs
documentation, and it can even change
history into a useful and operational
information or knowledge repository.
While executing, AI can automate
deployment workflows and migrations,
but only within the governance
boundaries which are defined
by the humans or the users.
And finally, ethics.
This is an increasingly important
aspect, especially in an enterprise
environments where transparency becomes
a part of engineering reliability.
Coming to the crux, HAIX operates
better through six stages across
three phases of delivery methodology.
That is a discovery,
design, and development.
Most organizations adopt AI tools
first and think about governance later.
However, HAIX reverses it.
It defines accountability first
and then accelerate executions.
Let's dive into the phases.
Discovery is where most
human-centric activities are engaged.
It requires human-to-human connections
to understand the ground reality,
emotions, business context, apart from
identifying the constraints and the
risk typically the users are facing it.
And this is managed through
stakeholder interviews, system
inventories, and the risk assessments.
At the same time, AI assists this
phase by synthesizing information
and generate insights out of raw
data and other surfacing patterns
typically the humans might miss.
Moving on to the design, and design
is where humans and AI collaborate.
The human engineers define and own
the overall experience, build schemas
and architecture decisions, and AI
assists by running the validation
checks, suggest index strategies, diff
crafting pipeline and scaffolding.
But nothing move forward
without the human approval.
Think of AI as a junior engineer
who does the research but
shouldn't be making the final call.
All lies with the human engineers.
Moving on to the development, and
here is where the AI takes the lead.
AI drives migration execution, schema
versioning, and deployment automation,
and human engineers monitors and retain
and override the authority at every step.
In the final stage, AI synthesizes all
the telemetry and observability data.
Engineers validate it and feed the
corrections back into the system.
That feedback loop is constantly
happening, and this is what
makes this a living process
instead of a one-time setup.
One of the most important aspects in
HAIX is the clarity of boundaries, what
human owns and what AI is used for.
When AI responsibilities becomes
ambiguous, teams started failing.
If everyone assumes AI is
responsible, then no one owns outcome.
And that's the reason HAIX explicitly
maps where human intervention and
approval is mandatory and where
AI makes a safe contribution.
This transforms AI from a black box
into a governed engineering participant.
Here is the most important part
many people tend to overlook,
which is knowledge artifacts.
Most organizations underestimate the
value of standardized knowledge artifacts.
Without the standardized artifacts,
every engineer end up creating their
own prompting style, define their
own validation logic, and build
their own AI workflow patterns.
To overcome operational challenges,
knowledge artifacts has to be standardized
and establish new guidelines on how
project teams adopt AI with curated
prompt libraries runbooks, and
tool-specific interaction patterns.
In the future, an organization's
competitive advantage is not just on
the AI models, but it's on the knowledge
re-- knowledge artifacts and the
organization memory they have defined.
Here are some of the key takeaways that
will leave you with three final ideas.
First, speed is not the
goal, but reliable speed is.
The winning ones are those who
not just move faster, but also
know what they are shipping.
And second, humans and AI
are better together, but only
with the clear boundaries.
Either we let AI do everything
or we don't trust with anything.
The answer is in the middle.
Define exactly what
each is responsible for.
Third, start where you are.
You don't need a perfect
framework on day one.
A shared prompt library and a
validation checklist will get
you further than what you think.
Human and AI capabilities
are not competing systems,
but complementary system.
We have to understand the balance between
this and work together for larger benefit.
Organizations that succeed with AI are
not necessarily the ones automating
the fastest, but creating the clear
accountability structures between
the humans and intelligent systems.
We finally come to the closure.
Thanks everyone for your time.
Start asking, "Should we build this
way?" instead of, "Can we build
it?" In whatever the case, HAIX
is the way to answer the question.
I hope this session is useful to you.
Thank you once again and glad to
answer any specific questions.
Thank you.