Speaker 10: Good morning, everyone.
My name is Vyatham Maheswaran.
I'm excited to talk about a topic that is
reshaping the financial world faster than
most organizations real-time payments and
what they meant for database engineering,
DevOps, and infrastructure design.
We are living in a world
where the expectation
shift from batch
and infrastructure pattern
And the DevOps and security
practices that keeps the system safe
Let's not wait anymore.
Let's start with chapter
to run in batches process transaction
at the end of the day or we may be
waiting few hours to complete it.
That world is completely gone.
Today
S, SEPA instant.
All these rails operate 24 cross seven,
365 days with sub-second expectation.
There is no such thing as
off-peak hours anymore.
There is no maintenance
window at 2:00 AM, 3:00 AM
You catch up pressure defines
modern payment systems.
Subsequent processing transaction
must be settled in milliseconds,
and it should not wait for seconds
or minutes to complete it, right?
So near zero downtime.
Planned downtime is no longer accepted.
Continuous load.
Traffic spikes are
unpredictable and constant.
This is a new baseline that the
world is expecting for, and it has
forced us to rethink everything from
the architecture to observability
Real-time payments are
not just domestic anymore.
So modern payment rails face continuous,
continuously add regulatory jurisdiction
transforming US domestic payments.
UPI in India processes billions
of transactions monthly.
Pix in Brazil and SEPA Instant in
Europe are pushing financial inclusions
and cross-border interoperability.
This system spans continuously
on regulatory frameworks
and settlement models.
That means interoperability, real-time
validation, and schema-driven data
exchange are no longer nice to have
They are operational requirement.
So as part of today's session and roadmap,
what we are going to cover is from batch
to real-time, the architectural shift
driving event-driven systems, database
engineering, consistency models, schema
evaluation, and high throughput writes.
Infrastructure patterns like
microservices, Kubernetes, active-active,
multi-region deployment zone, DevOps and
operability with zero trust security,
AI-driven monitoring and fraud detection.
And what we are going to take away
from this presentation that we built
is settlement from batch to
event-driven architecture.
So how do we build a system that
can keep up with transforming
batch to the continuous?
shift from batch processing to
even Batch systems, you might
process datas on a schedule.
In real-time system, every
transaction is an event that must
be processed the moment it happens.
So this is where event
streaming platform comes in.
Apache Kafka gives us durability,
distributed event logging
with exactly once semantic.
NATS and RabbitMQ provides
lightweight, low latency
messages for real-time pipelines.
Kafka partition model
is especially important.
It lets us scale horizontally while
preventing pre-account ordering, which is
critical for the financial consistency.
You cannot process a
debit before a credit.
You cannot reorder events.
So Kafka gives us that guarantee
That streamings become the backbone
of entire payment flow: ingestion,
validation, fraud scoring,
settlement, notification, everything.
So when there is a producer, so
all events have been produced,
and then it is streamed.
So Kafka takes care of producing
that events and then storing
it in the topical pages.
And the other side, a
consumer will be there.
When there is an event trigger happening,
the consumer will take that event
and then it will start processing.
So we no need to trigger
manually, and it is going to be
completely on the event-based one
Database engineering
for real-time payments.
Now let's talk about the
heart of the system: database.
Real-time payments pushes
database to their limits.
We need the right consistency model.
Strong consistency is essential for
certain payment types like ledger update,
transactional flow maintenance, and
eventual consistency may be acceptable for
downstream analytical or notifications.
The key is to choose deliberately.
Don't let the database choose for you.
Second most thing is zero
downtime schema evolution.
You cannot take the system offline
to run migrations, so you rely on
backward compatibility, strict schema
changes, feature flagging, schema
registries, rolling deployments.
This allows you to evolve your data
model without breaking real-time flows.
Third important thing is
high throughput writes.
The real-time rails generates
enormous write pressure.
To handle this, you need write-optimized
storage engine, connection pooling,
idempotency key, retry safe operations.
Idempotency is especially
important in a distributed system.
Retries are inevitable.
You must guarantee that the transaction
is processed one and only once, even
if the request is sent multiple times
Next part we are going to
talk about is ISO messagings.
So ISO 20022 has a global language.
So this ISO 20022 is more
than a messaging format.
It's a schema-driven data model that
enables rich remittent information,
automated straight-through
processing, real-time validation,
global inter- interoperability.
It adopted by CEFT, CEFA, FedNow, and RTP.
If you are building a payment system
today, ISO 20022 is a foundation
Talk about the infrastructure
patterns for always-on system.
Let's move on the infrastructure.
The real-time payment demands architecture
that are resilient, self-healing, global
distributed, horizontally scaling.
Three patterns that is dominating
all these aspects are microservices.
In microservices, we
isolate the failure domains.
For example, if a fraud service
goes down, then it should not
bring down the settlement process.
So both should be separated, and then it
has to run on its own individual servers.
So microservices provides
this piece of it.
Next, we are going to
talk about Kubernetes.
Kubernetes gives us auto-recovery,
rolling deployment, horizontal
pod scaling, consistency, runtime
environment It's the operational
backbone of modern platform of AWS.
Next one is going to be very
interesting, like active-active
multi-regional database.
This is where the things get
very interesting about talking
about the active-active strategy.
So if your applications are deployed
into multiple regions, then it
increases the availability standpoint.
So your active-active architecture
allows multi-regional writes with
consensus-based conflict resolution.
This eliminates single point of failure
that keeps the system available even due,
due to a regional breakdown or outage.
If one region goes down, the second
region will be able to take the
transaction space and then start running.
So consensus algorithm like
Raft Box makes it possible.
Raft uses leader following model that
easier to reason about operability.
Procs underpin system like spanning
and uploads DB, providing strong
correctness and guarantees.
Third one is fraudulent fault tolerance
Based write ensures that even if a
minority of node fails, no data is lost
You cannot secure what you cannot see.
So first of all, you have to see what
is the problem around it, then only
you can secure how to remediate it.
In real-time payments, observability
isn't optional, it is a safety net.
You need distributed tracing using
OpenTelemetry to trace a payment
across dozens of microservices.
So metrics and alerting are essential to
do latencies, percentiles, throughputs,
and error rates becomes your primary SLAs.
So that you maintain a metric
and alerting system for it.
Structured logging, that is a
essential one to be there for
all your architectural patterns.
So every logging must be tied up with a
correlation ID, so you can reconstruct
the entire lifecycle of an transaction.
For better pursuit, you can start adding
your regions, countries, and cities to
the logging standard so that it'll be
very easy to identify and diagnose in
seconds instead of waiting for an hours.
If something goes wrong, then seeing
the logs where it originated and
then the correlation ID associated
to it, so we can track down and
then do the analysis in seconds and
then get to the root cause for it
Next one we are going to talk about is
AI-driven monitoring and fraud detection.
Fraud detection in real-time
payment is an unique challenge.
You cannot run a 500 millisecond
model in a system that must
respond in under a second.
So you rely on streaming
feature engineering, lightweight
models, edge-based interface
Real-time scoring pipelines.
The fraud engine must operate within
a transaction's own latency budget
Zero trust security and compliance.
Security cannot be bolted on later.
It must be embedded from day one.
Zero trust architecture, every service
or user and APIs must be authenticated
and authorized So that we ensure that
complete security is being provided
for an application when there is
an user intervention or when they
are trying to breach the system.
Network location is
not a trusted boundary.
Even within inside networks,
they can breach it, and then
they can hack the system.
So you have to be well authenticated
and authorized before accessing
any of the applications.
The second thing is PCI and DSS.
So encryption at rest and in transit
should be ensured for the protection of
card-related datas and all the PII datas.
Tokenization and strict access control
should be provided so that we ensure
the right peoples are accessing the
data, and they have a privilege to see
the deta- data and to operate on it.
PSD2, strong customer authentication
and secure open banking APIs.
Compliance becomes an architectural
constraint, not an afterthought
What matters most?
Let's wrap up with four key takeaways.
Designed for events, not for batch.
Event systems that is going to be
streamed on the platform with exactly
one semantics are going to be the
backbone for real-time payments.
Consistency is deliberate choice.
Understand your consistency
model and enforce it explicitly.
Observability is not negotiable.
Instrument everything like traces,
metrics, logs, alerts, monitoring,
everything you have to be properly
instrumented when on each and
every phase of your development
and monitoring and alerting.
So security must be
embedded, not bolted on.
Zero trust, PCI, DSS, and PSD2 shapes
your architecture from day one.
Real-time payments are here,
and that is only getting faster.
The organization that succeeds
will be the one that treats data,
infrastructure, and observability
as a first-class citizen With that,
I'm concluding all my presentation.
Thank you, guys