Speaker 20: Hello, everyone.
I'm Ahmed Tariq, a cloud DevOps engineer,
and in this talk, I will cover how to
make schema migration safer in CI/CD
and where AI should assist without
taking over production decisions So
the title of my presentation is Schema
Migration in CI/CD: When AI Helps, When
AI Hurts, and How to Tell the Difference.
Let me start with a simple question.
How many times have we seen a deployment
go perfectly smooth, but the real problems
come from the database change behind it?
The code deployed, the pipeline
was green, the health check passed,
and then production started failing
because a migration locked a table,
a backfill went too long, or a
rollback wasn't actually possible.
That's the problem space for today.
Schema migration are different from
normal deployments because they
touch persistent state data that
lives beyond a single release, and
when that goes wrong, recovery is
far harder than just redeploying.
Now, as AI is entering this workflow
too, reviewing SQL, summarizing
pull request, drafting runbooks.
That can be useful, but it's
dangerous if we treat AI output as
production-ready without review.
So this isn't just a hype talk.
It's not about letting
AI run your migrations.
Please don't do that.
At, That can be really terrible.
It is a practical field guide.
By the end, you will have a clear
way to think about three things:
how to make pro-migration safer in
CI/CD, where AI generally helps, and
where AI should stay advisory because
engineers fail on production still.
So my second slide is why migration
aren't like app deployment, right?
Let's start with a core problem.
A stateless deployment is
built around reversibility.
You build an immutable artifact, a
container, a binary, deploy it, and
if it's brick, you re-point traffic
to the previous version, right?
Blue-green deployment, canaries, feature
flags, and mature patterns they are
like the CI/CD patterns that we have.
Schema migration break
those assumptions, right?
A migration doesn't deploy a new artifact.
It mutates shared
persistent production data.
So if it rewrites data incorrectly, drops
a column too early, or lock a critical
table, you may have no clean rollback.
And here's the key, the one line
to remember: You can roll back the
code, you cannot always roll back
the customer data being wrong, right?
There are a few ways by which
you can do that, but obviously,
that will cost you a lot.
You have to have some free replicas if
you're using AWS or any other cloud.
And that, that costs an additional layer.
Obviously, that is always in
the backup and recovery plan.
But sometimes the point-in-time
recovery can miss some things, right?
So that's why database need a
different level of discipline.
A migration that passes staging It
passes in staging can still fail
in production because obviously on
production we have live data, more table,
different traffic, downstream consumers.
You forget about it, right?
It's that engineers are careless
or hu- or humans you can say.
After all, they are humans, right?
So in my slide three the
common failure modes.
A few failure modes that show up
again and again, like for example,
very common is lock- locking DDL.
A small locking change, an alter
table or a hot table that live writes.
The database takes a lock, that app
times out, the connection pool fills up,
or a tiny migration is now an incident.
Irreversible rollback, and we love to say
just roll u- roll it back, but if you drop
a column or run a destructive backfill,
everything, reverting the migration file
does not bring the old state back, right?
And if it does, then it can be a
hurtful procedure to bring back all
the stuff that you have lost during
the, a failed migration, right?
Sometimes it work, and but
sometime the data corruption
is also on the words, right?
Environment drift, staging has
ten thousand rows, production
has four hundred millions.
Things are huge when it's
come to the difference.
Plus, where historical data from
five years ago, staging process,
production fails, and different words
are wearing the same name as, right?
And on staging you have
a testing data, right?
Dummy values, right?
And if you're dumping from production
to staging staging still possess
the old outdated data, right?
And a big bang change, new code needs new
column or old code can't handle it, and
the schema can't change safely, right?
That coupling removes
your saved exit path.
And the scary one, the silent
data loss that is terrible really.
A type conversion, truncate
values, the migration succeed,
but the data is corrupted.
Data corruption is very crucial.
Maybe you have done all the
things right CD runs perfectly,
but the data got corrupted.
And for example, if you're in a fintech
and if your data got corrupted, it
means like you're using like a millions
of transactions can happen per minute.
That can be really
problematic for you guys.
So in my next slide, I'm just
telling you like how-- what kind
of a good CI/CD includes when you
are doing the schema migration.
So what should a good
CI/CD include, right?
It has six stages as you can see.
The first one is linting.
Static check on the schema, SQL,
and catch the obvious fix, right?
Unsafe type changes, missing indexes
or destructive operations, right?
And number two do a dry run, okay?
Don't rely on your-- on a laptop
or a, or a tiny staging database.
If it matter, test against the
production like a data, a clone
to to estimate the duration or to
log the behavior or the impact.
The number three is the
automated test, right?
And this is I think very important
when it's come to the QA and test
the migration with the application.
Make sure it's running on the production
or on some sort of a staging environment
and where relevant or both old and
new code can be working because safe
migration need a window where, the both
latest and the new code exists, right?
And the fourth one is I think one of
the most importance, the approval gate.
A human has to review it, right?
You can't just run the test
cases and just do the small check
and just ship it to production.
It can be very critical, right?
The human reviewers not to touch not
to catch the mechanical mistakes.
The pipeline should have caught
them, obviously, if the pattern
is written perfectly and according
to the requirements, right?
It's just for the judgment, just
to make sure that, okay, the things
that we are going to deploy on
production have a final review.
It's just like a PR review where
the senior guy comes and review
the code, and the senior guy
come and review the database.
It's the same thing.
And the fifth thing is deployed Ship it.
Run it on a controlled way, right?
Not a manual command from someone's
ter-terminal at 11:00 p.m. That
can be really terrible, obviously.
And final is sixth one,
which is the post checks.
You must check everything, each and
everything, all the data processes,
all the flows, and make sure
that the data is not corrupted.
There's no any malfunction in the code.
And if there is any then you have
to be, make sure that you have the
proper mechanism to roll back, right?
The principle is automate
the mechanical checks.
Reserve the human human approval
for the accountable judgments.
Tool can vary Flyway,
LiquidBase, GitHub Actions.
It's up to you which CD you want to use.
You can use the cloud-native, so on.
But the tool matter less rather
than a proper operating model where
the things can be re-repeatable and
reviewable and observable, right?
So in the next slide we're just
talking about safe patterns, right?
Now the safest pattern is to
expand, migrate, and then contract.
One of the most important ideas in this
talk is the goal to avoid big bang changes
that can really c-collapse your production
and that can affect your business, right?
So the pros- the way is, the key is to
split the migration into phases, right?
The first one is expand.
Add the new structure in a backend
compatible way, a nullable column
or a new table or an index, right?
Old code and new code can both still
run and nothing destructive, right?
The second one is to migrate.
Move the behavior to your
right to old and new fields.
Backfill in batches, switch
reads behind a feature flag.
The behavior cha-change is decoupled
from the schema change, so you can pause,
monitor, or, you can also roll back
without destroying the old path, right?
And the third one is contract.
Clean up.
Only after you know the old
path is unused To remove the
legacy column or the con, right?
The destructive step happens the last.
That's the whole point, right?
You can't just do it at the first, or
you can't just do it in the middle.
It has to be in the last when you
are sure that, okay, all the things
are working now, they are all-- they
are checked, the QA has been run, and
there's no accident reported, right?
So the pattern is simple:
add safe, a-add safety, move
gradually, and remove later, right?
I think that… I know that's the boring
part, but the boring part is what we
want for our production database, right?
And the next slide is about a safe
customer status column, right?
Let's say it's a sort of
example which I've added.
Let me, let's make it concrete, right?
We need to-- Let's say we nee-we
need to add a customer, right?
Customer status column to a high
traffic customer table, right?
And there are like hundreds of
millions of rows and life and several
services are depending on it, right?
The unsafe version, add a column,
backfill the whole table at once, deploy
the code that depends on it, then drop
the old field quickly to look clean.
That's how small tickets become a
massive incident reviews, right?
The safer version follows the migrate
expand, sorry, expand, migrate,
and then the contract part, right?
One we just first should add
a nullable column, right?
As you can see here.
And when-once you add a nullable
column, no defaults, right?
No full table rewrite.
And verify lock behavior for your engine.
Postgres MySQL, SQL Server
don't all behave the same.
You have to be very conscious about
when you are doing some changes.
Now, the dual second
part is the dual part.
Code writes both the old
fields and the new one.
Both paths are valid.
So if something breaks, the
old path still exist, right?
Three, backfill in batches.
Not all at once, right?
And not doing one, one chunk and
then waiting for the whole eternity.
Not a heroic query.
Rate limited chunks while
watching replication log time and
latency, which is very important.
This is where teams get ready and
push the batch size too hard, right?
So you have to be very concise when
you are coming up with a batch size.
It has to be like proper one, not
a big one, not a small one, the one
that can really fulfill your needs.
And the fourth one is switch
reads behind of a feature flag.
Now rollback isn't a data
revert, it's a flag flip, right?
That's the difference between a
controlled recovery and a panic one.
Five, verify with observability, right?
Error rate clean, latency stable,
data corr- correct, data is
correct, and old path is unused.
Six, contract later.
Now you drop the field.
The things are working you have migrated
the data, everything's working fine.
You have done the QO cycle, it's working.
Now remove the old field.
That destructive operation is a
safe one because you know- That
ordering is the whole game, right?
A safe migration isn't just run a
safe statement, it's a safe sequence.
And in my next slide you can see
these are some validation gates before
the production that we can have it.
And so there are like
five validation gate.
The static analysis, which we discussed
previously, which is a linter, flag
risky, locking DDL misses indexes,
recursive loop, and unsafe type changes.
And number two is a dry run clone.
A productive size clone answer the
real question, how long it will take?
Does it logs?
Does it count the replication logs?
And number three is a test suite where
the application test the new schema,
both old and new path are being tested.
Valid schema isn't enough.
It has to be the valid
application lifecycle site.
So we can see how the data is
performing when the application
is live and up and running.
And the fourth one is
the rollback rehearsal.
So you just do a sort of a rehearsal,
making sure that if anything goes
south, you have something, you
have a plan that really works.
The fallback plan should really work.
And the fifth one is a human approval.
An accountable engineer who has a
knowledge of database, how the things
are working, who understand all the flows
should come and then have a look on it.
And the principle mechanics, machines
own the gates, one to four, but the last
one that belongs to the human one, right?
And another important part
is the observability, right?
This is also very important.
You can't call a migration
safe if you can't see what is
happening behind the scenes, right?
Observability is a part of a release plan.
Before, capture a baseline,
former latency or replication
lag, error rate, CPU, connections.
Without it, you are just assuming, right?
Okay, this happened or that happened.
That is terrible when it
comes to the production.
And during, watch the signals
that predicts the incident.
Continuously monitor the things when the
production is the, when the CI/CDs are
performing the data migrations, right?
And that is really helpful.
So check for any replicas, don't
fall behind, lock and why…
lock and wait time is correct.
And query latency, also make
sure that is between the P
ninety-five and P ninety-nine,
which are the standards, right?
And because average hides the
pain error rate tied to the
new schema, backfill progress.
If you can't estimate if it… if
you can't manage it add saturation,
CPU and IOPS are very important
databases writing red X and out
So these are very important point.
And after that don't declare
the victory immediately, right?
Let it cool down make sure that the
things are working and the users are
not reporting any behavior unusual
behavior that can cause problems.
And you can use multiple tools that
can provide us the some sort of ab-
really good observability, I will say.
Prometheus can be do-- can be used.
Grafana is one of them.
Datadog is also.
And if you're using some cloud
providers, for example, AWS,
you can also go for the advanced
performance monitoring as well, right?
These are really good metrics that can
help you to see what migrations will form
and you can also see like when the latency
moves, so you know what what it was,
what your migration was doing and what
was happening during the process, right?
And now we have talked about like how
the things are working, what should be
the flow, and then there are other part
where the AI generally helped us, right?
Now AI, it's everywhere.
It can generally help.
The mistake isn't using AI, it's
using in the wrong places, right?
Re-reviewing the drifts,
reviewing the difference.
AI look at the migration
in the service version.
Is this type change risky?
Can it lock a table?
Is that rollback unclear?
It doesn't approve.
It appears that human… it
actually prepares a human reviewer.
It provides a thing summarize the risk.
It turns a dense pull request in
a plain language brief, right?
For example this adds a column, backfills
the rows and changes read behaviors.
Main risk log durations or you can
say incomplete backfills old consumer
still using the previous fields.
So these ca- these types of things can AI
provide and it summarizes stuff, right?
And the next one it can also do, it can
also generate the test cases for you edge
cases, n- for the null values, invalid
statuses, historical loss, practical
backfills, and the engineer then review
it and curates and owns them, right?
And it can also draft a sort of
a runbook for you A first pass of
deploy steps, rollback steps, checks.
So you can have everything
docu- documented.
You are not just here and
there when the things go wrong.
You have proper documentation,
so you know what to follow
and what not to follow, right?
And then the post-incident
analysis, that is very important.
And it can be really helpful
in, in that case as well.
And summarizing the timelines and
creation logs, it can review the
logs and tell us about any issues.
It can also review the metrics
and tell us about any insight.
It speeds up the understanding but it
doesn't really replace the human, right?
And notice and and one more thing
is that the prompts that you are
giving to the AI when setting up the
AI has to be like very important.
You can't just really rely
on AI-generated prompts.
I think these prompts has to be I
think reviewed by the stakeholders.
By by stakeholders the senior engineers
who have who have the understanding of
the whole database, so you know, like
what's happening and what to write, right?
And the reviews can be like,
"Review this migration for the
for the locking, data loss, and
rollbacks," and don't approve it.
And first, do the conversation with a
human, make sure that we're on the same
page, and then do the things, right?
So the key phase Do not approve it.
AI is just an advisor that
is made by you, right?
To facilitate you, not
just to replace you.
It produce the risks and the questions,
and a human decides what to do.
And this is the good
part of the AI, right?
And where is the, the bad part can
also comes with the AI part, right?
And we all know that AI
can be dangerous, right?
Because it is not perfect.
It is not 100% perfect.
It do have some you can
say problems, right?
It drifts, it has hallucination, and
now the sharp edges, AI dangerous.
And when you forget what
context AI doesn't have.
No production context, it can't see
your traffic data volume or business
criticality unless you tell it.
So when it say this looks
safe compared to what, like?
Okay, it's saying okay, it's… If you
if the AI model does not have the context
of what you're building and how you're
building it, it is really hard for you
to just really tell you about things.
It can verify the syntax and it can
tell you like, "Okay, everything's
working fine," because you know what?
The syntax is right, but
maybe the flow is incorrect.
So you have to give him something, some
understanding so that it can understand
like if it-- if the AI is comparing
the current data with something, then
make sure that, that documentation,
that whatever instructions are correct.
It can misread the data dependencies.
A drift-- a drift doesn't show
every downstream customer.
Reporting jobs, AVL pipelines
triggers the billing systems.
Hallucinated rollback advisory.
This is very serious because
this is a problem with the AI
that it hallucinate and drift on
for the complex things, right?
So it may confidently suggest a
rollback that itself isn't destructive,
but might not be required, right?
Just drop the new column
and resolve the old one.
Maybe not.
Maybe not, right?
Maybe senior engineer doesn't
want that in that way.
And when the old path has already been
diverged in an inc- in an incident, right?
Confident but wrong is worse than silence.
It misses business impact, right?
A billing table isn't just another table.
AI doesn't know the weight of your
data unless that context is built in.
Unchecked decisions making the hard line
AI must never auto-approve or auto-apply
in a-- especially in production.
That can be really bad for
anyone if the AI is approving the
things in a production, right?
Because AI doesn't know about,
what's happening on the production?
Yeah, he has the context, but still
live data and all that, AI still can't
be dep- relied for that part, right?
Because production decision
needs accountability, and AI
really can't be accountable.
At the end of the day, AI is
just a tool, just a product,
and we are using it, right?
So use AI to review, summarize
understand the logs and the metrics,
but don't let it, you know what,
approve or execute the stuff.
And and yeah.
Next one is the decision framework, right?
So where does AI belongs?
There are like three questions.
Blast radius.
Who break if this is wrongs, right?
A low traffic internal table or a
customer billing or a order table.
One service or a whole pattern.
Reversibility.
Can we undo this without data loss?
That is really important.
Are there any flag, any forward
fixes or is the data permanently
changed and once it's run, right?
And human judgment, does this
need the business context?
Because humans have the more
understanding of the product than
the human than the AI, right?
And they can spot the patterns, right?
And approval, they can do
the approval, and they can be
accountable for the approval.
And the AI is not a decision maker, right?
The metrics Low risk and easy to reverse.
Automation with AI
assistance is reasonable.
High risk, but easy to reverse.
Staged rollout plus human approval,
low risk but hard to reverse.
AI drifts or reviews.
An engineer's own is high
risk and hard to reverse.
Human-led AI advice, but
you need rehearsal, right?
Explicit approval and
strong observability.
The point isn't to, the point isn't
to ban AI, it's to place it correctly.
And AI, can help you think faster, right?
It has optimized the way you
can do the things, right?
And but it shouldn't remove the
accountability from the engineers, right?
Engineer still has to
own the things, right?
And the next one is the
how to make it real, right?
Practical implementation is very
important, and you have to design the
whole structure, like how to do it.
And let's make it practical.
If you want to improve database
delivery, one, you have to make
make follow the pattern, right?
Which is make expand
contract your default.
Add first, move gradually, remove later.
Two, add a migration intro to
the CI/CD fail to f- to point
out the risky patterns, right?
And the third, a dry run, which is
very important even with the code
and/or even with the database.
Run the me- meaningful migrations
on production size clone.
Four require a written
review rollback, right?
Or a forward flip plan, right?
And the fifth one is a gate production
behind explicit human approval.
And focus on judgment, right?
And the sixth one is keep
environments in sync, right?
You don't make sure don't make
it each of your environments
like too drift apart, right?
And seven is ins- instrument each
and every migration metric, so you
know if anything goes wrong, like
what was the root cause, right?
And AI auto-approve or auto-patch
should be not, Recommended.
Boring and not neg-- non-negotiable tenth
is to name the accountable engineer so you
know who is the senior guy, who you should
reach out to if things goes bad, right?
Because that person will have the
all the context that can, that person
can spot the issues and because that
person has built the things, right?
And if you're building something,
like what is the what is the riskier
part or what is the part that is not
really strong or that can cause issues.
And one critical first step is do
not-- do two change things, right?
Add a migration inter dry run the
risky migrations in production-like
data, and that's where a lot of
inc-incidents or the issues lie cheaply.
You can spot them all, right?
So that was the whole point of
that migration strategies and how
you can use a CI/CD to perform the
migrations from staging to production.
Let me close with this
with the main takeaway.
AI assist, and engineer
still owns the production.
You can't really replace the
engineer from the production.
That's the whole talk in one sentence.
Migrations are risky because
they change persistence state.
CI/CD makes them safer with
repeatability, validation,
visibility, and control approval.
AI can help with reviews, risk
risks detection, test ideas, run
books, and incident analysis.
But it should not be the
production-ready decision maker.
The pipeline makes the migration safer.
The human make them accountable.
And I think that's the point.
So if you remember three things, expand,
contract by default, automate the gates,
AI advises, never decide it, right?
Again so that's the whole point
of this whole presentation,
and thank you for listening.