Speaker 21: Hi, everybody.
My name is Amarachi Hannah Chua, and
today I will be, presenting this topic,
which is, can a Kubernetes operator
replace a database administrator?
And it's basically the outcomes of an
experiment that I did, which lasted a
couple of days, which spanned a couple
of days, and I'll be telling you the
findings of these experiments that I did.
So what does a database administrator do?
They, one, they failover
when a primary dies.
Two, they monitor replication lag.
Three, they manage storage pressure.
Four, they execute versions upgrades.
Five, they maintain backup and recovery.
So this-- throughout this entire
experiment, I'm going to be working
through different scenarios to figure
out if an operator can do this.
And the operator we'll be using
will be the CloudNative PG operator,
which would watch over our PostgreSQL
cluster and try to keep it in the
state that we declared automatically
without any human intervention,
without us lifting a single finger.
But is that actually possible, and
what is the limit of this premise?
So this is the description of my setup.
I am going to be using Talos Linux
operating system managed by Omni.
If you don't know what Talos Linux
is an immutable operating system,
and by immutable, this means that
we cannot SSH into our nodes.
And this is a lot of how
production nodes are run.
And this is really great for this
particular experiment because the
operator has to be the end all and be
all, and we cannot at any point SSH
into this node to intervene humanly.
So hopefully, the operator
would see this through.
And we'll be using Kubernetes version
one point three five and have four
nodes scheduled on AWS, which actually
was very problematic at some point
because I kept running into cost issues.
And as I see it now, I-- as I see
this, I squint a little bit because
I'm like, "Oh, dang, costs." So
I had to shorten it a little bit.
Instead of the original thirty, it
ran for about sixteen to twenty days.
And the operator we're going to be
using will be the CloudNative PG
operator, and the database will be
Postgres sixteen, version sixteen.
And through the course of
this experiment, I upgrade the
version to version seventeen.
So the experiment is
split into six scenarios.
One, if we kill the primary pod,
does the operator recognize that
we've killed this primary pod, and
does it fail over automatically?
Two, if we drain the node that is
running the primary, can it reschedule
a new replica across different nodes?
Three, if we fill the disk on the node
that's probably holding the primary to
the breaking point, does it detect that
this is happening, and does it give us
the tools to mitigate this or to reduce
this storage pressure so that the disk
does not fill up to its breaking point?
Four, if we pause replication in
one of the different replicas in the
Postgres cluster, and then the replicas
fall behind of the primary, does the
operator recognize that the replicas
are falling apart or falling behind?
And does it give us the tools to help
these replicas get up to date with
the right updates in the primary?
Five, if we trigger a major
version upgrade, does it work?
And how efficiently does this work?
Six, if we try to back up our database
and do point-in-time recovery, can we
actually successfully back this data
up, and can we restore this data?
So let's get right into it.
This is my nodes.
I have four nodes, one control
plane node and three worker node.
And then I have my database cluster,
which is three-- which has three
instances, and they're all, as
you can see, in a healthy state.
And the primary in this instance
is the experiment DB one primary.
And you can see all the three pods
running, and all the three pods in the
database cluster are running, and they're
healthy, and they have no restart.
So this is what we're working with.
Bear in mind that the the
primary at this point in time is
the experiment DB one primary.
So let's get started.
Scenario one, kill the primary
pod This is the first experiment.
So what did I do?
I deleted the primary, which was
the experiment DB one, right?
And I deleted it using kubectl delete pod.
And I took… And I investigated
and saw how long it took for
the operator to recognize that
the primary has been killed.
And how long did it take to promote
a replica to become the new primary.
So this is what happened.
The experiment DB one went from
successful to-- from running to
terminating and to completed.
And experiment DB two was then
promoted to the primary, and a fresh
experiment DB one pod was created.
And all this took about eleven seconds.
And at the end of this, the cluster
was back to three over three healthy.
It had all three healthy instances.
So what did the operator do?
The operator detected that the primary
pod was gone almost immediately,
and it promoted the most up-to-date
replica, which is the experiment DB
two instance in the database cluster.
And he updated the internal service
routing so that any write would go
to the new primary instead of the
old primary that we just killed.
And it spun up a new experiment DB one
to replace this instance that we deleted.
And this is very similar to what a
database administrator would have done.
They would have checked the standby
WAL, Write Ahead Login replay position,
and found the most up-to-date replica,
and they would have promoted the
most up-to-date replica and then
verified that the connection layer
routes to the new primary, which
could be the experiment DB two, and
then provision a new standby replica.
So I guess the verdict is… Not I guess.
The verdict is that, yes, the operator
did this and did it beautifully
in eleven seconds, and it did not
require any human intervention.
But here's where it gets a little tricky.
But yeah, before we get there,
we can see screenshots from this.
We have-- we had-- we deleted the
experiment DB one pod, and you can
see in the get pods watch logs that it
goes from terminating to initializing
to running in eleven seconds.
And you can see that it then-- the cluster
becomes three out of three healthy, with
the new primary being experiment DB two.
As you can see, before it was experiment
DB one that was the primary, but now
it's changed, and all three pods in the
database cluster are running and running
well It gets a little bit tricky in the
scenario two, which is that we drain the
node that is running the new primary,
which is experiment DB two, and we see how
efficiently does the operator recognize
that this is happening and fixes it.
If you don't know what it means
to drain a node, to drain a
node, you have to first… If
Kubernetes first cudden standard.
And cuddening means that you're
not-- you cannot schedule any
new workload on that node.
So that node becomes tainted.
And then Kubernetes evicts any existing
node that wa-- existing pod or existing
workload that was working on that node.
So what I did was I first did a
kubectl get pod wide to see which
node that our experiment DB two,
which is the primary, was running on.
And if you can see in the previous
slide, you can see that experiment
DB two is running on this IP
172.31.40.42 node And then I drained
that node, and this is what happened.
Yes, the primary got evicted,
but the operator recognized
that the primary was evicted and
immediately promoted experiment
DB 1 to become the primary again.
The problem, however, is that experiment
DB 2 was stuck at pending for about
26 minutes, and this was because of
the PVC node affinity conflict, right?
The the experiment DB 2 was writing
to a storage, a piece of storage
that was present on the node that we
just tainted and said that we cannot
schedule any more workloads on it.
So as, and as, because of the PVC was
already bound to that volume, it could
not be scheduled on another node because a
different node would not have that storage
that was present on the previous node.
So this is what happened.
The operator recognized that the
primary was evicted and immediately it
failed over to experiment DB 1 and the
cluster stayed available throughout.
E-even though that the cluster
was only available two instance
out of three instead of a regular
three instance out of three.
And it did attempt to reschedule
experiment DB 2 on another node, but
it failed because it could not resolve
this PVC node affinity constraint.
So what would the
database administrator do?
They would have understood the storage
topology before draining any node and
they would have verified that, okay
these PV-PVCs are not bound to any
local storage that we are going to miss.
Maybe they could choose like a cloud
storage or whatever storage that could--
that would be better in this scenario.
And they would have planned the
switchover first, promote a replica
explicitly, then drain the former
primary without any or jetting.
And if we required a local storage,
they would have planned for that
data to be receded after that drain.
So maybe I shouldn't be so hard on the
operator for not recognizing this and
probably used a different sort of storage.
But I would say the result,
I would say it was partial.
The failover was automatic, but
the self-healing was blocked
by local storage node affinity.
And you can see it here.
You can see that, yes, all three…
By the way, these are two
different terminals opened.
One terminal was watching over what was
happening, over the events of the po--
the cluster and seeing what was happening.
So when I drained, you can see I drained
this node here using kubectl drain.
The node was first cordoned,
and it then evicted every single
existing pod or workload on that
node, and then drained that node.
But you can see that it was stuck
at pending for a while Because-- and
when we tried to get this experiment
DB cluster, you can see that it only
had three-- it had-- even though
it had three instances up, only
two were ready, and it kept waiting
for the instances to become active.
But the good news was that the
operator failed over the new
old primary to experiment DB 1.
So experiment DB 1 took over from
experiment DB 2 as the new primary,
but experiment DB 2 never got up.
You can see it here.
It was stuck at pending for a while.
And if you check the events, you
can see that It could-- there was no
available nodes for these pods to get
scheduled on because out of the four
nodes we had, one had an untolerated
taint, which is our control plane node.
One re- was unschedulable, and that
was the node that we just evicted
and we just drained and cordoned.
And by cordoning, we instructed
Kubernetes to not schedule any
more workload on that n-node.
So that node was unschedulable.
The two had the two did not match the
persistent volumes node affinity and as
thus could not receive this workload.
And so you can see it here.
It got stuck at pending
here for about 26 minutes.
But then what I had to do was I
had to uncordon the node and say,
"Okay, it's fine. You can schedule
more workloads on that node." And
immediately the pod came back and
began to… and was running in the same
minute and the cluster became healthy.
Great.
So now we have scenario three.
If we fill the disk of the
node that is holding the pod
until it breaks, what happens?
What would the operator
do in that scenario?
So what I did was that I exec into
the experiment DB1, which is now at
this point the primary, and I wrote
about 8.4 gig of da- junk data, and
this was about 64% disk utilization.
Then I wrote another four gigabyte
of junk data to push the disks
towards 90% utilization, and I
watched the status throughout.
And this is what happened.
At 64%, the operator reported
that the cluster was in a healthy
state, so there were no alerts
or no, no change in its events.
At 90%, the pod, the primary pod
crashed and the operator recognized
that the pod had crashed and
triggered an automatic failover.
But Kubernetes had to had to intervene
and it tainted that node with a taint
of disk pressure NoSchedule, meaning
that you cannot schedule any more
workloads on this node because it's
done, it's filled, it's okay, it's fine.
Leave that node alone.
And then as thus, because of the
PVC issues and everything, the node,
the pod, a new pod was not created
to replace this pod that crashed.
The pod gets, kept getting stuck
at pending and kubectl… And we
could not, of course, we could
not SSH into the node and try to
manually delete data or anything.
So what did the operator do?
The operator stayed completely
silent through 64% to 90%.
There was no warning, no changes in events
or anything, but it did detect that the
primary had crashed and triggered an
automatic failover to experimentdb2.
But because we could not clean
this data up, the pod kept getting
stuck at pending for a while.
So what will a database
administrator do in this scenario?
Database administrator would have set
up discrete usage alerts at 70%, 80% and
90% thresholds on every database nodes.
And when you start getting the alerts,
you would have investigated, okay,
what is causing this usage, this
spike in disk usage and proactively
cleaned or cleaned up space before
hitting a crash or stop whatever is
causing this spike in disk usage.
You could-- And addi-additionally, a
database administrator would have had
a documented runbook for disk full
scenarios in case they happened in
prod and would have a sort of foolproof
way of fixing this or dealing with
this whenever they encounter this.
What was the result?
There was no warnings, no nothing,
no change in events, and recovery
needed human intervention because
the operator could not provide it
could not provide what you need to
recover from disk breaking, from over,
from overutilization of your disk.
You can see it here.
We had all three database instances
running and the cluster, the database
cluster was in a healthy state with
the primary being experimentdb1.
And I wrote about 8.4 gig data into
this disk and filled it up to about 64%.
And yeah, once I filled it up again an
additional nine-- to around 90%, you
can see that one of the pods crashed and
we only have two pods or two instances
ready out of the three instances.
But we had a new primary now.
The new primary is experimentdb2.
So yeah, it got stuck at pending for
a while and this is because of, if you
check the events of why this pod was
not getting scheduled, you can see that
zero over four nodes were available.
Two nodes did not match the
persistent volume node affinity.
Two nodes had untolerated taints, and
those two nodes were the cl-- control
plane and the node that Kubernetes
had tainted because of disk pressure.
And you can see it here,
taint DiskPressure.
And you can see the time it was
added So I would give this to the
database administrator, of course.
I don't think that the operator
could have handled it as well as a
database administrator would have.
Scenario four is if we pause
replication and create lag.
Basically, if we pause one of the
replicas and st- and it became--
it started lagging behind with
the information in the primary.
Basically, it wasn't up to date
with the information in the primary.
Is the operator going to see into
this event that was happening?
And is the operator going to give you
the tools to remedy this scenario?
So what I did was that I picked a replica.
I exec into experiment DB three
replica, and I stopped it from
receiving any write-ahead logging.
So I did wal replay pause, and I muted
the replica, and I stopped it from
receiving any write-ahead logging.
And I wrote about one million
rows of data to the primary.
And I checked to see, and I
ensured, and I checked to see if
this replica was really behind.
So what would happened was that
experiment DB three, which is the
replica that I just paused wal replay
on, it fell behind about a hundred and
two MB, behind the primary that is.
But if you checked the cluster sta-
cluster status or cluster event, the
cluster was still in a very healthy state.
There was zero reaction from the operator,
and you could not sync to any event.
But if you try to see the replication
lag, you can see that we had
almost one million… Basically,
the replica was very behind.
And once I resumed the wal
replay, the replica caught up
to zero lag almost instantly.
So what the operator did
not detect the lag at all.
There were no alerts, no events, no
status change, and continued reporting
the cluster as healthy throughout.
It has no built-in mechanism to
monitor or alert replication lag.
So the operator is really good at
seeing pod health, but not necessarily
Postgres level replication state.
What would a DB, a database administrator
do differently in this case?
The database administrator would
probably have set alerts over different
thresholds and figure out if your
replicas are lagging significantly
behind and to investigate the cause.
What is causing this lag?
Is it a network issue?
Is it a pod resource pressure?
Is it an intentional pause?
If the lag is too large A database
administrator might give up on that
replica and create a new replica from the
primary instead of letting it catch up.
And yeah, so Operator is-- the verdict
is Operator is blind to replication
lag, and there might be a gap
that exists at a PostgreSQL layer.
And you can see it here.
We have the pods all running.
And once I exec into the primary
into the replica, the experiment DB
three replica, and I paused the WAL
replay, I can see that… And I wrote
a bunch, I wrote a, about a million
rows of data into the primary, and
nothing is still running perfectly.
There are no-- everything, the
cluster is still in a healthy state.
There is no, there's not any information
that would signify that maybe you
would want to look into that the,
that there might be any-- there
might be something afoot, right?
And you can see that when we do check
out the lag, you can see that there's a
byte lag of this ma- of this much data.
So I had to exec back into the pod
and replay and resume the WAL replay,
and the byte lag was zero zero.
There was no lag once I resumed
once I resumed the write-ahead
logging replay on the e- replica
The fifth scenario is can we do a
major version upgrade from Postgres
version 16 to Postgres version 17?
So what I did was that you have
to first confirm that, okay, we
are indeed running Postgres 16.
We're running Postgres 16.13.
And I patched to change-- I did
keepcity up patch to change the
image name from Postgres 16.13 to
Postgres 17.6, and I just watched the
entire event and the cluster status.
So what happened was that all three pods
were terminated simultaneously, and a
major upgrade job was spun up, and a
primary started on-- And the primary
restarted on Postgres 17 in about 47
seconds, but a new two fresh replicas
were created from the primary, which was
experiment DB five and experiment DB six.
And yeah, it was indeed Postgres 17.6.
So what did the operator do?
The operator terminated all instances
in a controlled, coordinated shutdown,
and it restarted a primary, the primary
on the new Postgres 17 image and
discarded the old replicas and cloned
fresh ones from the upgraded primary.
What would a DBA do?
A DBA would have planned a
maintenance window a week in advance.
It will test the upgrade on a
staging cluster first to ensure
that, okay, we're not running into
some sort of compatibility issues
or anything, or having bugs that
are detrimental to our cluster.
And it will take a full backup before
even starting this upgrade, just in
case something goes wrong mid-upgrade.
And then it will validate the
upgrades check and then cut over
traffic to a new instance, to
the upgraded version instance.
So I guess if you want to
look at it a little bit, the
operator did do really well.
It it upgraded the cluster in about
47 seconds, but a DBA, a database
administrator would have been more
meticulous with this version upgrade just
to make sure that nothing went wr-wrong.
So you can see I was indeed running
Postgres 16.13, and I did patch it.
And you can see the events.
The cluster went from upgrading
to a Postgres major version,
which was the primary.
The primary was getting upgraded.
And then when-- Once the primary was
running The cluster the operator created
new replicas from cloning the primary and
the cluster became in a healthy state.
So the last scenario is the backup
plus point-in-time recovery, which I
think is the most important scenario
or which is a very important scenario.
So what I did was that I patched the
cluster with the S3 backup config
using the Barman object store.
If you don't know what Barman is a
backup management tool that CloudNativePG
uses under the hood to manage
backups and archiving and whatnot.
So I did create a sort of backup and I
backed up my data to an AWS S3 bucket and
I watched it get-- I watched the data in
my database get backed up and I deleted
the data from my cluster and I tried to
create a new cluster with the data that I
backed up, basically a recovery cluster.
And this is what happened.
The backup did complete in eight
seconds and uploaded this data to S3.
There was a little bit of issues
that, that I ran into and I
will explain a little bit later.
And the recovery cluster did spin up, but
the point-in-time recovery failed because
of the WAL segment was not found in S3
and the operator kept restarting in a
recovery pod in a loop for about one hour.
And the reason why is that this operator
did not there was no-- WAL archiving was
not configured at cluster creation time
and it wasn't something that was enforced.
So it did trigger the backup, base backup
data and uploaded it to S3 automatically.
But WAL, because WAL archiving was
not backed up at the exact same
time that we were backing up the
the data You could, we could not
replay this data that we backed up.
But— and so it was a continuous
failure that went on for about an hour.
So what would the
database administrator do?
The database administrator would have
configured Write Ahead Logging, WAL or
WAL, however you like to pronounce it.
I feel awkward with
the way I pronounce it.
Archiving from day one and
not as an afterthought.
And they would have first verified
that recovery was working before
before testing it in production.
And they would have monitored
backup age and WAL archive lag
as part of the normal operations.
And they would have maintained
a documented RTPO or RTO or RPO
and test against it regularly.
So base backup did not work base backup
worked, but point-in-time recovery failed,
and because of the WAL archiving, which
must be enabled at cluster creation,
but it's not enforced and, yeah.
So you have this data.
So I did try to back it up, and as you
can see, this is like a test data that I
was using to try out backup and recovery.
And you can see the error that came up
when I was trying to create a recovery
cluster from the data I backed up.
And this was as a result of WAL
archiving that did not work So yeah,
that was heartbreaking a little bit.
But yeah, this is the very first,
this is the beta of my experiment.
I might do a lot more about-- Yeah,
I might do a lot more in seeing
how much we can self-automate
without human intervention.
So what is the verdict?
The verdict as… The simp- the simplified
version of the verdict is that the
operator does not replace a database
administrator, but it does replace routine
execution of database administrating work,
and it does a very manual, repetitive,
reproducible work like pod failover, major
versions upgrade, replica provisioning and
cloning, self-healing after pod failures.
But human is still crucially important
in scenarios like storage topology
decisions, replication lag and monitoring
and alerting, disk full recovery
on any immutable OS and like that.
So work i-- while archiving and
backup architecture planning.
So that is it for me.
Thank you so much for having me.
And if you'd like to connect, here
are my socials @ thisamarachihanacho
on LinkedIn, Instagram, TikTok.
And if you have any questions if there,
if this is going through, I will be
in the comment section or anything.
But thank you so much for having me.
This has been an honor.
Thank you.