Speaker 11: Hi, everyone.
I am Neil Chatkamwar from Intuit, and
I'm presenting my independent research.
I'm excited to be here at Conf forty-two
Database DevOps twenty twenty-six.
Today we are going to dive into a
cutting-edge topic, prompt-driven
microservice and database evolution.
Specifically, how we can leverage
large language models for automated
schema migration and DevOps delivery.
Let's start by framing the problem
that we're trying to solve.
The reality is the traditional
change management can't keep pace
with the demands of the modern
microservice architectures.
We see four major issues that
slows down and increase risk.
The first we have a schema drift.
This is when the application and
the database changes evolve out
of sync, which inevitably breaks
contracts across service boundaries.
Second we encounter manual bottlenecks,
like engineers are still handcrafting
migrations API updates, and rollback
scripts, and this is tedious process
is slowing down every release cycle.
Third, there is an issue
of ambiguous requirements.
The core business intent often
gets lost in the translation
between business stakeholders,
developers, and data engineers.
Finally, all these issues compound
into a significant deployment risk.
When we push unvalidated schema
changes into distributed systems,
the result can be outages, data
loss, and critical rollback failures.
These are the core challenges
that the LLM-driven framework is
designed to eliminate To tackle these
problems, we introduce a new paradigm.
Instead of the costly high-friction
process of manually writing
migration scripts and boilerplate
code, engineers can simply express
their intent in plain English.
Our framework takes that natural language
requirement and handles the rest of the
heavy lifting, from schema evolution to
API generation, and even test scaffolding.
This fundamentally changes the
engineer's workflow from coding
boilerplate to reviewing and
approving generated artifacts.
Here's a quick look at our agenda today.
We will begin by detailing the
architecture o-of the prompt-driven
framework covering prompt
interpretation, semantic validation,
and type-safe code generation.
Then we will discuss database-aware
transformation, focusing on
automated schema evolution with
backward compatibility guarantees.
Following that, we will look at the
unified DevOps pipeline that aligns
application and database changes.
We will spend some time on safe releases,
which includes automated test generation
and robust rollback strategies.
Finally, we will cover practical
integration, showing you how you can
fit this LLM-driven automation into
your existing pipelines today So at
the heart of the solution is our core
architecture, the prompt driven framework.
The system is broken down into three main
sequential layers, each with a discrete
responsibility to catch errors early.
It starts with a prompt interpretation,
which parses the natural language
input and extracts the user's intent.
Next is semantic validation, which
detects the ambiguity and enforces
consistency across services.
Only after validation do we proceed
to code and a database transformation,
where we generate type-safe code
and unnecessary schema migrations.
These-- this layered approach ensures
that the errors are caught before
they propagate into production
migrations or any API contracts.
So let's talk about layer one.
It encompasses both a prompt
interpretation and semantic validation.
The intent extraction step uses the
LLM to parse the natural language
identifying key elements like entities,
relationships constraints and specific
change type, whether let's say it's
an add, a modify, or duplicate.
Critical to safety is ambiguity detection.
Any conflicting or underspecified
requirements are immediately flagged,
which prevents the downstream failure.
So we pause there, and then
we wait for a human to resume.
Finally consistency enforcement validates
cross-service contracts and shared
data models against existing schema
registry before we proceed to generation.
And this is where the latest coding
agents are like, they thrive on this,
and they are very popular because of
this usage, and it's very effective
in this space Moving to layer two.
We execute type-safe code
generation using best in the--
best of the class coding agents.
The framework generates fully
production-ready microservice code
significantly reducing developers' effort.
This output includes API
contracts detailing endpoint
definitions, request response
models, and versioning strategies.
Everything that there was before is
carried on, and all the changes are
documented and also diffed all across.
It also produces data access layers if
needed, such as repository classes that
are perfectly aligned with target schema.
We get service logic stubs,
scaff-scaffolded business logic
ready for a quick engineer review and
comprehensive integration tests, which
are automatically generated to cover
happy paths and critical edge conditions
Now to the layer three, which is perhaps
the most critical for database safety.
Database-aware schema transformation.
Schema evolution is the highest
risk step, so we address it with a
multi-guarantee transformation layer.
First, we ensure backward compatibility.
The generated migrations must
preserve existing API contracts
and consumer expectations across
different service versions.
This is non-negotiable.
Second, we enforce data integrity
through constraint analysis, actively
preventing destructive operations like
drops, column drops, and type changes.
Unless there is an explicit human
approval gate, we don't do a
follow-through on any of those actions.
Finally, every migration
artifact includes rollback plans.
A tested version pinned rollback script
generated at the same time as a forward
migration, and this is a game changer.
Like coding agents are especially
good at generating the compensation
scripts, so we use them very effectively
in this framework The most dangerous
pattern in database DevOps is running
application code and schema changes
through separate, uncoordinated pipelines.
Our unified pipeline
eliminates this gap entirely.
The flow is as all-- as follows.
The engineer or the stakeholder
submits a prompt which is a
natural language requirement.
The system then generates all
artifacts, service code, API specs,
migrations, and tests atomically.
These pass through a validation gate
requiring semantic checks a schema
dry run, and an integration test pass.
All of this is generated.
Only then do we proceed to a
coordinated deploy, releasing
application and database changes
together with full rollback coverage.
To guarantee safe releases, every
generated artifact must successfully clear
a four-layer validation pyramid before it
can even reach the deployment pipeline.
Failures at any layer immediately halt
the pipeline and return structured
feedback to the engineer for correction.
That's where the human in the
loop comes into the picture.
The checks include schema
syntax validation, where the
code is parsed and linted.
Next, semantic consistency checks verify
cr- cross-service contracts against
the schema registry and everything.
Crucially, we perform a dry run execution,
applying the migration against a shadow
database clone so that we can be really
sure that what we're doing is right.
Lastly, integration tests, which
are auto-generated, must pass in CI
before the artifact is promoted The
rollback strategy and-- is founded
on three key safety mechanisms.
First, atomic artifact pairs.
Every forward migration is
generated alongside its inverse.
The two are version pinned and stored
together, ensuring that a rollback is
always planned and tested action, never an
afterthought, which is generally the case.
Second, the expect-- expand contract
pattern is enforced to preserve service
reliability during multi-phase rollouts.
We introduce additive changes first,
and then destructive changes are only
performed after consumer adoption
of the new schema, which is fully--
after it's fully confirmed as well.
Finally, to remove manual intervention
during critical deployment windows,
health check failures post-deployment
automatically initiates the pre-generated
automated rollback trigger scripts
so that we are safe, and we go
back to the previous known state.
This ensures a very swift
and reliable system recovery
Now to the closing the gap.
One of the most underestimated costs in
the feature delivery is the translation
overhead between the business intent
and the technical implementation.
This framework drastically improves
the collaboration impact across teams.
Business stakeholders can simply express
requirements in natural language.
They don't need any SQL
or API design knowledge.
Developers can benefit by reviewing
the approved and approving generated
code rather than wasting time
authoring boilerplate from scratch.
And finally, the data engineers
can shift their focus to a higher
value work like governance and
optimization instead of having to
handcraft th-these routine migrations
Now to the best part, which is
the practical integration, right?
That's more exciting.
So you don't have to rebuild your entire
DevOps toolchain to incorporate this.
This framework is designed to fit
into your existing pipeline today.
For CI/CD integration, it exposes a
CLI and a REST API, allowing you to
easily drop it in any Jenkins, GitHub
actions, or Git-GitLab pipeline as
a generation and validation stage.
For schema registry compatibility, it
works seamlessly alongside established
tools like Confluent Schema Registry
or AWS Glue, consuming and publishing
schema versions without disruption.
Crucially, we maintain a human-in-the-loop
gates which is the main safety
net of this whole system, right?
At this point for any agentic system,
which means approval gates at each
layer keep engineers in control.
LLMs accelerate generation, but the
engineers still own the critical
decisions to promote them to production
Now, to wrap up, there are three key
takeaways I want you to remember.
Just three.
First natural language is the interface
of tomorrow, believe me or not, right?
So requirements expressed in plain
English drive the full stack changes
with respect to service code, APIs,
migrations, and tests, and all of
this through a single validated flow.
Second, safety is non-negotiable.
Our layers of semantic validation and
schema dry runs and atomic rollbacks
and human-in-the-loop gates make
sure that everything is up to the
proper versioning and also is rolled
back if there are system failures.
And these-- we also make sure that these
speed gains do not come at the expense
of our system reliability, which is bad.
Third, if it fits your pipeline today,
the CLI and API integration points
make adoption incremental, meaning you
don't need to rebuild existing DevOps
toolchains to realize meaningful gains.
So that's all I had.
Thank you for listening, and
thank you for letting me present.