Speaker 39: Hello everyone, and
thank you for joining my session
at Conference 42 DevOps 2026.
My name is S Kand.
I work at Dish Network, LLC as a
senior engineering manager leading AI
engineers and automation engineers,
where I focus on bridging AI systems with
secure and compliant DevOps practices.
Today I'll be sharing a framework
I call the AI trust trade, a
practical approach to deploying
reinforcement learning, federated
learning, and explainable AI safely
in regulated production environments.
The goal is simple to help DevOps
team shape AI systems with the same
level of confidence, traceability, and
control that we expect from any critical
software system, but without showing
down, without slowing down innovation.
Okay, and let's start get started.
The real challenge is in deployment.
Let's start with what's really changed.
A few years ago, deploying
AI was the big challenge.
Now, deployment pipelines have mature.
We have Kubernetes CICD infrastructure
as code, and that works beautifully.
The real challenge now isn't about
getting models into production.
It's ab.
It's about operating them
safely once they're there.
AI is moved from experimental
research projects to powering
financial supply chain and customer
facing systems system that directly
impact compliance, risk and trust.
So the new frontier for DevOps is
about safe operations at scale.
Ensuring privacy by design, maintaining
audit auditability, and having
the ability to roll back instantly
if models drift or disbe behave.
Next slide.
Now I'm introducing the AI trust
trade to tackle these challenges.
I introduce what I call
the AI trust trade.
Three complimentary pillars for
trustworthy AI operations at.
Reinforcement.
Learning.
Learning, federated
learning, explainable ai.
So I will get into in
detail about these three.
On high level, what is
reinforcement learning?
Which enables adaptive decision
making that evolves with the
environment, but must stay within
defined control boundaries.
What is federated learning, which allows
organizations to collaborate on model
training without sharing sensitive data.
Explainable ai, which ensures
transparency, accountability, and
confidence in every decision made.
These three approaches together
form the backbone for responsible,
scalable AI in DevOps pipelines.
Let's get into deeper into each category.
Let's start with reinforcement
learning through a DevOps lens.
Let's start with
reinforcement learning or.
In simple words, in a DevOps context,
RL isn't just a research tool.
It's becoming a way to
continuously optimize operations.
For example, in portfolio
optimization, RL dynamically
reallocates assets while respecting
risk and compliance constraints.
In risk management, we can have
automated circuit breakers that
react to volatility in real time.
And in supply chains, RL can optimize
inventory and routing based on
live demand and disruption signals.
The key is building guardrails into or
L pipeline, so the system learns safely
without creating un intended consequences.
So we cover three three examples.
Portfolio optimization, risk management.
Supply chain.
Let's get into operational
requirements for RL systems.
From an operational standpoint, RL
requires a completely different level
of governance compared to static models.
What are those?
Policy versioning, safe exploration,
reward monitoring, meta risk detection.
What does policy monitor mean?
Every reward function.
Exploration policy or constraint must
be version controlled for traceability.
Safe exploration.
We test new policies in shadow mode before
exposing them to real users or assets.
Reward monitoring.
We continuously validate that
learned behaviors align with business
goals and don't exploit loopholes.
Meta risk detection.
This means.
Watching for second order
risk, like reward hacking or
unexpected emergent behavior.
In short, we treat the learning process
itself as something we must observe,
govern, and roll back if needed.
So now I'll get into federated learning.
So federated learning, privacy,
preserving collaboration.
Now let's move on to federated learning.
Which is becoming essential
for industries where data can't
leave its original boundary.
Think bank, think banking, telecom,
healthcare, e-commerce, whatnot.
Fair data learning lets each organization
train models locally on since two data,
while only sharing encrypted updates.
Using secure aggregation, we combine
the updates into a global model
without ever exposing the raw data.
This is the most important.
The result is a system that learns
collectively benefits from diversity
and stays compliant with privacy laws
now move to production pipelines.
For Feder learning to run Feder Learning
in production, we need a DevOps grade
pipelines with four modal versioning,
secure aggregation, drift detection.
Performance validation I'll get
into deeper into each category.
What is model versioning?
So every model update is cry
cryptographically verified and traceable.
Secure aggregation using homomorphic
encryption or secure multi-party
computation, drift detection, so
drift detection to identify when
local models start to diverge.
As I discussed in previous slides.
Or when man malicious
updates are introduced.
Performance validation is very important.
Ensuring the global model performs fairly
and consistently across participants.
This ensures that the federated
system is not just private, it's also
auditable, stable, and reproducible.
Next one.
N. Now the third pillar, and
also most important CO, is
explainable AI or simply Xai.
As AI influences high stakes decisions,
we need to answer why a model made
decision, not just what it decided.
Explainability serves three key needs,
regulators, engineers, stakeholders,
and customers, regulators who require
transparency and auditability.
Engineers.
We are engineers who need
rabbit debugging, tools,
stakeholders and customers.
Most important people who expect
fairness and accountability.
With explainability built
in, we accelerated trust and
troubleshooting at the same time.
Now we'll talk about embedding
explainable AI in ci cd pipelines.
So how do we operate
operation operationalize.
Explainability in DevOps pipelines three.
Ti three.
Like three things that we need to
make sure Predeployment checks,
runtime explanations, explanation.
Monitoring predeployment checks.
It ensures each new model version
maintains stable and interpretable
feature attributions runtime explanations.
This generates justifications
for every live prediction
stored for audit and debugging.
Explanation.
Monitoring tracks the consistency
of explanations over time.
If feature important suddenly
shifts, that's an early wanding
sign of drift or data issues.
This very important monitoring part.
In essence, we treat interpretability as a
first class decision in the CICD process.
So now we talked about reinforcement,
federated, and explainable.
Now getting to the governance.
Which is important.
Governance and observability are
where DevOps principles shine.
Using policy as code, we can
embed compliance rules directly
into deployment pipelines.
Things like modal approval workflows
or explainability thresholds.
Drift dashboards, let us visualize
distributions and prediction
shifts with automated alerts
and rollbacks, progressive roll
rollouts like canneries or AB tests.
Allow us to validate not only
accuracy, but also fairness and
interpretability before full release.
These practices, these three
practices keeps AI releases
both agile and compliant.
So next, talk about reproducible
training and model lineage.
What I mean by that, so Reproductivity
is the foundation of trustworthy ai.
Every dataset.
Hyper parameter and codependency
must be version control.
This is very important.
Training environments should be
containerized and deterministic,
so we can recreate any model on
demand with end-to-end lineage.
We can trace every model from data
injection to deployment, linking
experiments, configurations,
and infrastructures.
This is what makes audits and
root cause investigations actually
feasible in complex AI systems.
So next, this is very important
topic I want to talk about.
The reason is monitoring
meta in production.
A lot of people will make neglect
this one, but I will, I would highly
emphasize on this, even with all that,
AI systems can still face hidden risk.
Three big ones to monitor.
Reward hacking, data
poisoning explanation, drift.
What is reward Hacking where or
agents find loopholes that technically
satisfy their goals, but break
business logic, data poisoning
where federated nodes contribute.
Updates, explanation drift, where
interpreted ability pattern shift
as septal, but powerful indicator
of data or model problems.
By tracking this meta risk, we
move from react to firefighting
by to proactive assurance.
As I mentioned, it's very important.
So next one.
Okay.
Practical blueprint.
A lot of people now understood what
is federated learning, explainable
AI and reinforcement learning.
But now where to start?
If you're wondering where to start,
here's a practical blueprint.
Start with pipelines.
Build A-C-I-C-D with
versioning and reproducibility.
First layering.
S integrate ness, drift, and
explainability checks into your gates.
Monitor proactively, as I mentioned
high, I give high importance to this,
include meta risk metrics that that was
discussed in previous slides, not just
performance release with confidence.
Progressive roll rollouts let
you shift safely and quickly.
This stepwise approach, lets
DevOps team bring AI online
without compromising trust.
Closing, unlock the power
of intelligent automation.
To wrap up the AI trust
trade is in just a framework.
It's a mindset.
It helps DevOps team balance
innovation with assurance, shipping,
reinforcement learning, feder
learning, and explainable AI systems
confidently, completely, and at scale.
Thank you all for listening.
I would love to connect afterward
and hear how you are thinking about
AI safety in your DevOps pipelines.
And I also love to hear from your
experience what practices are
you in, like using in in DevOps.
Oops.
Thank you once again.
With that, I would like to sign off.
Thank you.