Hi, my presentation is on DevOps at scale.
we have used a multi agent systems
to automate the build failure in
a very large enterprise setup.
this enterprise has about 315,
000 employees, 100 applications,
and a wide variety of stack as
you see in the table above, right?
We have different deployment models.
Some of it is on prem, some of it is cloud
native, some of it is a hybrid solution,
a variety of programming languages,
frameworks, databases, you know, some of
it is COTS products, some of us, and we
also have different kinds of containers.
So you see the variety, there's
quite a bit of, difference in their
heterogeneity in the character.
Similarly, when you look at When we
actually looked at the system and
studied a bit more about the distribution
of what caused the build failure.
And this we studied using five years
log, which was a goldmine, right?
We realized some things, right?
Some things about the commit size.
certain source lines of code,
if the commits lines is above
that, the failure rate increased.
certain pieces of information was related
to, you know, how these build failures
happen in certain times of the day.
Like weekends, we used
to have more issues.
End of the day, we used
and there were things of that nature.
Which is what we have listed, right?
Developer experience, the kind of CIC
CD pipeline maturity in each of these
systems, because some of these systems
were old systems, legacy systems, some
of them were relatively new, right?
And the project maturity
level was also different.
So that is why you see this variation.
Now, when we looked at it, we, we were
also curious to understand that given
these bend failures, How does it look
across various internal platforms?
For example, we had the finance platform,
we have healthcare, we have certain
things related to employee engagement, we
have, things like developer productivity.
So when you look at it, the finance
applications in this case, followed
by, had very high build failures.
And also those related to developer
productivity or employee engagement
and human resource, right?
So this is a distribution of the build
failures when we looked at from a domain
perspective, but we also looked at
it from a perspective of tech, right?
So Java, for instance, if you
see has a highest build failure
rate JavaScript and so on.
So this is an interesting fact, but
let's get into the next level of details.
When we looked into the next.
Level of details.
here.
I want to step back and talk
about our DevOps journey, right?
So, as I said, we were very fortunate.
Not everybody has this, but we
had five years worth logs, which
is about 500, 000 build logs.
Over five years.
And, and as I said in my initial
introduction, these were a hundred
enterprise applications, which
were running across 56 countries.
And there were a lot of users, right?
About 300 and 300, 000 users
were a part of the system.
So we took the logs and the first step
is to actually process these logs.
Now, what would you do when you find out?
process these logs.
First and foremost, all
of these were build logs.
We wanted to isolate those logs which
were related to the failures and
we got approximately 10, 000 logs
related to these build failures.
Right.
And then once we got that, we were
curious about the distribution
of the error pattern, right?
What are these errors?
Where are they occurring?
What are these other kinds of metrics
related to MTTR or cost and so on, right?
and also we wanted to
use this, source of data.
We cleaned it up.
We removed all, PII data, and
we used this to also create an
eval dataset, which formed the
basis for our evaluation chassis.
so these are things which
we did with our logs.
The next step which we worked on was
actually to build a agentic system, right?
But the agentic system
did not happen day one.
First, we were thinking that, you
know, why not use the frontier LLMs?
And use that for root cost analysis.
So we began with Azure OpenAI 3.
5 as the first model wherein we
build prompts using these logs.
So when we got this 10k logs, we
actually did a lot of post processing.
Which would help us understand the
domain specifics using which we would
use prompt and prompt engineering, right?
This was the first quick
method, which we employed.
Then we use drag to capture
the domain specific, right?
So then we improved
that a little bit more.
The third thing which we did is that
we realized that soon after, you know,
these models were continuously changing.
So we had, GPT 4.
Right.
And we were also trying with
Claude onthropic, right?
So in this case, we wanted to,
first of all, be able to support
the model swappability, right?
We wanted to make sure that every
time we knew this is a time when
models are perishable, every day
there is a better and better model.
So we wanted to build that infrastructure
which would allow us to swap these models.
And the other outcome of that was every
time you change a model, even within the
same family, the prompts may not work.
So we wanted to have a way in
which these prompts would work.
So those are things we started doing.
The next step, we realized that If
you really look at DevOps, right,
it is a case when there is, we
need a lot of reasoning abilities.
And I will talk about, you know, in a
DevOps situation, how there is a lot of
uncertainties and we do need a reasoning
system, in order to handle it effectively.
So we built a multi agent system.
Both for RCA and also
for issue resolution.
Let's take a step back and talk about,
first question I want to say is, What
is it that you need in an agentic AI?
You do not straight away jump
to an agentic AI because it
is going to cost you more.
Instead of one particular LLM,
you're going to have a set of
LLMs doing many different things.
There were two things I
think we need to be aware of.
One is these cost of these models
is going down year on year, right?
That's the first thing to notice.
And the second thing is all of these
model context length is increasing.
So today enterprises actually can use
frontier LLMs, much more effectively.
That's one.
The second part that's
related to the viability.
The second aspect which it is
related to is a feasibility, right?
So when you look at this graph.
Here are the various
maturity levels, right?
On one axis, it is the generality and
the second aspect is the performance.
So today when we looked at this system,
we were operating in this phase, right?
Wherein we built an agentic LLM, right,
with all the reasoning abilities.
So, that is where, and DevOps as I
said is a partially observable domain,
which means that there is always
this uncertainty and you may have to
take decisions based on uncertainty.
And when you have these kinds of
system where the data is incomplete.
And there's evolving, changes, right?
It could be a threats, it could
be performance issues, which you
hadn't expected, keep coming, right?
You do need advanced reasoning
capabilities to manage these
belief networks, right?
So that is also one of the reasons
which motivated us to move to agent AI.
The third part, what, what
did we land up doing, right?
So when you talk about
an agent system, one is.
As you see on the top, right?
So you do have the traditional
agents, which can actually take the
build failure and do a set of things.
We will double click on what were the
various agents we had, but these agents
must work with traditional tools.
For example, if you think about.
Static code analysis, code smell tools.
You could use a sonar cube, right?
You could use a tool for
providing insights from the
Git commit changes, right?
You could have a JIRA tickets
and conference to find historic
solutions, which people have used.
You could use things for
privacy protection, right?
So you want to take off from these log
anything, which is, you know, has PII.
to make sure that that
information is masked, right?
So you may have to use a variety of
tools, which is what we used, right?
On the top, you have, in this case,
we have four different agents.
Orchestrator is the master agent,
which orchestrates, the other agents.
And if you take the build agent
and I have double clicked, right,
what does a build agent do?
First of all, the build agent actually
analyzes, has many sub agents, right?
In this case, a build agent has a log
analysis agent, which will look at
the logs continuously, monitor the
logs to extract any failures, right?
Then there is a diagnosis agent, which
goes and analyzes this information,
which has been extracted, tries to
classify the information, Or categorize
the type of problem, which is a
performance issue, security issue,
why is it happening, and so on, right.
So it determines that.
The third part is a resolution
agent, which actually uses the log
and the variety of artifacts to say.
Hey, you know what?
This is a kind of resolution
which needs to be taken, right?
And the fourth is a notification agent.
So we build this complete, multi
agent system to address this, right?
Now what were the challenges?
Let's talk about some of the challenges.
we faced while building the system
over this, period in time, right?
First of all was this, today the LLM
really impacts the accuracy, right?
And every day, so the choice
of LLM is very important.
Second is every LLM you change, the
prompts are no more effective here.
If you see, when we use 3.
5, our accuracy was 82%.
Of course, we had other
metrics we measured.
when we moved to four, the accuracy
improved, but when we moved back to GPT 4.
0 mini, which the cost is very
less, our accuracy dropped because
the prompts would no more work.
Right.
So it's very important for us to make
sure that the prompts would work.
The second is.
Human evaluations are not scalable.
You need to have an automated
way for evaluation and that
is very important, right?
And for all of this, reasoning is a key.
You cannot have a system which does
not support reasoning because you're
dealing with a DevOps problem, right?
And Frontier models, remember,
cannot be fine tuned.
So if you really need to fine tune,
you need to create, An SLM, small
language model, where you can train
your, LLM with your custom data, right?
So keep that in mind.
So what we really built is, you know,
while we had the agent architecture,
but we also built certain components.
So first of those is an LLM hub, right?
What does an LLM hub do?
Helps you in selecting It helps
you into swapping these models.
So today you have a model, you change
the model, it helps you to change, right?
Besides this, you could also build your
own, find you in your own model, right?
So it helps you.
That's that's the first purpose.
The second is when you talk about
prompt management, as I said,
you know, here, when I walked you
through, so prompt operations.
Prompt evaluations is very important
wherein you need to make sure the
prompts do not fail with every
change of the underlying LLM.
That is important.
And the finally, the most important
thing, which I think all of you must
have to build trustworthy AI systems
is an evaluation chassis, right?
Evaluation chassis actually does the model
evaluation, In an automatic fashion, and
here we introduce a concept called as
LLM as an evaluator or LLM as a judge.
I will talk about that soon.
And this particular evaluation chassis has
an eval benchmark which we created with
the historic data after pre processing it.
Right, so these are some of the
things we will talk about very soon.
And I have left you some links
which you can always refer.
Okay, having seen this Let's come
to LLM as an evaluator, right?
So on the left hand side, what
you see is, let's suppose that
you have an input prompt, right?
And using one, the first
LLM as a candidate, you get
some kind of output, right?
Now as I spoke earlier, the
human eval, And human evaluation
is not a very scalable way.
So we are looking at alternate
ways in which LLM themselves
can be a judge, right?
So here the second LLM comes into play.
and actually produces an evaluation.
Now this evaluation
has two metrics, right?
The first metric is actually a score
which says that, you know, what
is the, what is the probability
that this, output produced by the
first, LLM is right or wrong, right?
And the second one is
the supporting evidence.
You just don't give a score.
You always give a supporting evidence.
So when you look at it and here I'm
taking, you know, this paper, when
you look at it, it has a benchmark.
It's a very interesting reading, right?
Let's suppose that, first LLM
was used to create a code, right?
And let's suppose that you
had used Claude Sonnet 3.
5, right?
And that is why you have a solver.
Since it's a coding task, right?
And you use Claude Sonnet solver.
Let's suppose that, the accuracy is 88.
1.
Right.
Now, what really happens is that if
you had another Claude Sornet as a
judge, right, to critique the way the
first, first, Claude model solved it,
then, this is a critique agent, right?
Critique is also a judge,
is also an evaluator.
to judge it, then you get a
different score, which is 64.
29.
Right.
So the same LLM when used as a solver
versus worst, when used as a judge
could have different performance.
And this performance also varies
between different kinds of tasks,
knowledge, reasoning, math, coding, you
know, all of them are very different.
Claude is best for coding.
And if you look at the
newer versions of GPD.
4 0 1, right?
They may actually have
much better scores, right?
One of the key observation is that the
ability to judge, to verify the solution
pairs, solution pairs is highly correlated
with its ability to solve the problem.
So if something is good at coding, it
will also be good at judging, right?
That's the key outcome.
Go to the last slide, which is, I would
do a key conclusion and results and, you
know, between Jan 2024 to September 2024
is when we were actually measuring the
impact of the new DevOps with agentic
AI over the hundred applications.
So when we looked at it, the
first metric which came down is
the mean time to resolve, right,
which was average of four hours.
This came down to 2.
2 hours, right?
This is a big deal.
The second thing is, you know,
these problems are never technical.
It is about humans, right?
imagine the DevOps team.
They do a lot of repetitive work.
Sometimes, you know, escalations
come in during, Christmas
times, Thanksgiving times.
Right.
When this in, especially in retail kind
of scenario, there are performance issues
which plague the systems, you know, the
team is always very stressed, right?
They do not know when
a problem will happen.
So in that case, the team
satisfaction went up dramatically.
that is a very important indicator for us.
The third thing is the
quality of resolution, right?
What is the chance that the response or
the resolution you gave indeed worked?
That is, the resolution quality
substantially went up by about 30%, right?
And the last of those is, Cost, right?
So you may think that today
without DevOps, an agentic AI,
let's suppose that you had certain
cost in terms of people, right?
And today, because of having agentic AI,
you change the cost structure, right?
But it becomes an operation expense.
And that came down by 25%.
Right?
This is also because with time, As
I walked you through in the earlier
slides, the cost of these models is
dramatically reducing year on year.
with this, I conclude, thank you so
much for this opportunity to present.