Speaker 3: Hi all.
This is Arvind Shaker, director
of Engineering at Twilio.
I have over two likes, building
and scaling distributed systems,
and today we're gonna talk a
little bit about reliability,
specifically AI powered reliability.
Without further ado, let's get into it.
Reliability these days is a
fundamental business requirement.
It directly impacts a
company's bottom line.
Imagine this, what will happen in
the US if 9 1 1 emergency services
is not available for a few hours?
Sounds disastrous, right?
Yep.
That is the case because today we are
all reliant on these kind of systems
being available all the time, and
it's a reasonable expectation for us
to expect the services that we use
to be up and available and reliable.
That goes same for any software that's
out there that's serving customers.
Reliability equals business continuity.
It is estimated that on an average
a minute of downtime is equivalent
to about $5,600 of revenue loss.
So with extended out outages, you
can imagine what would happen.
We saw what happened.
On October 20th and there was
an AWS outage in uscs fund,
this estimated that this outage
itself impacted millions of customers
causing tens of millions of dollars
of revenue impact across the globe.
So when systems fail, conversions
drop, customers lose trust and
competitors gain advantage.
So it is imperative that reliability
is an absolute need across all systems.
The reliability crisis.
So over the last, 10, 15 years.
We've seen the advent of microservices
architectures falling up.
So we started creating a
bunch of microservices.
We started breaking down monoliths.
And with that, what happened was
the complexity of dependencies
grew as we created more services.
Also, with that, what happened was
that an impact or a downtime or an
outage in one of these services,
the impact cascaded along and would.
It would cause widespread
outages somewhere else.
Also with, we pride ourselves
over the years in increasing the
number of deployments that you had.
So previously we used to
have, one or two deployments a
month or maybe even a quarter.
And these days we are doing multiple
deployments in a day when the
number of deployments increase.
The potential of vulnerabilities that
go into protection also increase.
So we are living in this kind of
a crisis today where the number
of systems, microservices that we
maintain increased, have increased.
The scale at which we operate
has increased the number of
deployments that we that we have
per day, that has increased.
And the interdependencies between
systems have also increased.
So how do we maintain.
These kind of systems today, right?
We have a set of monitors
that we have set up, right?
All systems have typically monitors,
and these monitors are threshold based.
For example, you would, alert
someone if if the number of five
X is that a system and that an a
PA throws goes beyond a threshold.
Or if the CPU spikes, beyond a certain
percentage, you alert something.
Anything with the heap or you have
different thresholds that we set
up for each of these monitors.
That's one, one way.
The second thing is when these thresholds
are broken through these monitors, we
start alerting people or what happens.
Whenever there is a bigger outage
when, say an entire region goes down
or a full system goes down due to some
infrastructure issues or networking
issues, the number of alerts that we get
from each of these monitors is humongous.
Say I'm on call and there is an outage
that's happening in, in, in a region that
we have deployed code and each of these.
Hosts that have these monitors, the
thresholds are broken, monitors are
triggered, and I start getting alerts
and I would be getting like a hundred,
200,000 alerts at the same time.
So what would I do at that point in time?
Which one should I look and
which one should I not look?
And that's called an alert storm.
And alert storm is disastrous when
you're on call because you wouldn't
know what to prioritize and what not to
prioritize root cause analysis, right?
So root cause analysis.
With the amount of telemetry that we
have today, we emit, some companies emit
billions, multiple billions, sometimes
trillions of transactions every day.
And how do you how do we analyze
all this data that's so that, that's
tremendous amount of data that we
emit these days and analyzing them
to even identify root cause analysis.
Matching data across these
systems becomes a nightmare.
Knowledge cycles.
So when these systems expand,
as systems grow, the knowledge
that we have inherently is not
usually documented across and not
documented in the standard format.
So these things stick into people's
minds, and then when people leave, the
knowledge goes away, the on-call burnout.
So we keep firefighting whenever
there are system outages.
We have these huge alert
storms that come in.
We keep firefighting, we keep looking
because we are not sure where the outage
is because of too many alerts that come
in and firefighting becomes a unknown.
We don't look at how do we prevent issues.
We look at how do we resolve
issues when, once they occur.
So that is the current state, and
these are huge limitations in the way
we handle support these scale systems.
AI is.
Is being seen as a panacea for everything,
but here we should be careful as
to how we use ai in AI operations.
So wherever we use AI in operating,
in operations while we maintain these
large systems, it's called AI ops.
Okay.
Now, where can AI help us?
So AI can help us, or ML can help
us in pattern detection, right?
Something has happened before, and if
the same pattern happens again, ML can
help us detect those patterns, right?
For example if if during
the holidays, see that?
The number of requests that we,
that an API gets on the system gets
increases during holidays, then
that's a pattern and it happens
every every year during the holiday.
These patterns are detected automatically
by ml, and we can definitely use ML
models to identify these patterns.
Then comes predictive analytics.
So once we see that, once we know there
are these patterns that are available,
we can also start predicting using ML
models when an event can reoccur or
when an event is going to occur, and
we can start alerting people saying
that, Hey, there is an event that's
gonna happen and let's take care of
that before the event actually happens.
The next one is intelligent automation.
So if you've already predicted
that something is gonna happen.
Or if, if you've seen the remediation
steps that we've already taken, when
these kind of issues have happened in
the past, we can automatically start
executing those remediation steps.
Using ML models and insights,
augmented intelligence, so insights.
So with the large number of data
we get out of, say, telemetry,
logs, et cetera, events, et cetera.
Instead of analyzing all this
data manually, ML models can
definitely help us there.
We can go a little deeper into this,
the reliability framework, right?
That's based on ML and ai.
So the, it's, it all starts
with anomaly detection.
So how does that work?
You have data that's coming out from
systems, and this data could be tele
metadata, it could be events, could be
logs, could be anything that's coming out.
And bringing all that data
together and analyzing them to
find anomalies is what ML can do.
So that's the first step.
Finding anomalies from all
the data that's coming out.
The second step is temporal
seasonal awareness.
So these models, when they're fed
with seasonal awareness in the sense
all the holidays that are coming up,
so during the Super Bowl match the
number of pizza orders could go up.
So that is something that's
seasonal, so you know that, okay.
That is a Super Bowl match
that's gonna happen this weekend.
And and I know that the number of
requests hitting my API is gonna go
high, and that is also an input to,
to ml. And the ML models are going
to use that to predict what traffic
patterns across these across the days.
Cross signal correlation
as we discussed before.
Metrics, logs, traces.
These are all different data now.
Bringing them all together and
finding patterns across this data is
important, and ML can help us do that.
Causality over correlation
cause and effect, right?
So we know.
So today what happens is humans
are the only ones who can find out.
This happened and any an incident happened
and this was the root cause, and we are
able to do that after a lot of analysis.
But ML models can do that
when they have all the data.
Okay.
So a pri a primitive approach to
this would be, okay, I have an
incident that's going on, another
incident in another organization.
Or say in a say in AWS or any other
company that I'm reliant on is
happening, so I can relate them.
So that is a primitive idea,
but beyond that, ML can identify
root causes, not just based.
On coincident events, it go, can
go much more deeper than that.
And continuous adoption
systems automatically adjust as
applications and workloads evolve.
So how do we build this for our systems?
The first step to use AI for reliable
operations is streaming telemetry.
Telemetry is important.
Real time collection of metrics logs,
distributed traces is super critical.
If you are not doing that today,
the first step in having a reliable
system and doing that through AI
is to stream the right telemetry
to have the right telemetry output.
Then once you have this data being
emitted out of a system, you could.
Implement or deploy ML models
that would analyze streaming data.
And doesn't mean that you have
to deploy heavy models to to
to analyze the streaming data.
You could be ate models and
you could keep it tiered.
So at first step you analyze
this data, like using lightweight
models and then aggregate that data
and then use heavyweight models
to to find to predict, to do.
To do predictions, to do
anomaly, detections, et cetera.
So it could be a layered approach,
but all this inference that we are
getting out should be near real time.
You cannot have an event that happens
now and then have these models run in
the background, and then after 20 minutes
or 30 minutes you have a prediction
or you have a detection of an anomaly
and then you start alerting people.
That is not how that
is not a useful thing.
So you should have near real
time inference of what's
happening in these systems.
Model performance.
So imagine this, right?
You have fraud detection, in credit cards.
This is one of the common
use cases for ML models.
You deploy ML models to identify a
fraud in a credit card transaction.
Imagine using the same model
that we developed 10 years ago.
It's not gonna work today because.
The fraud.
The ways in which fraud happen in
credit cards have changed over time.
So we have to keep updating, these
models and that's what this means,
and same thing applies everywhere.
So continuous validation ensures
model accuracy as systems and data
systems and data distributions evolve.
And you should have some
safe rollback mechanisms.
That we are seeing more false positives.
Then there should be an easy
way or mechanism to roll back
our model and deploy older ones
for safer for better safety.
So overall we should balance
real time responsiveness with
computational efficiency.
Moving on another area where you can have.
A very good bang for the bug using
AI ops is capacity management.
Say you as an example, let's take the same
example of of a Super Bowl match, right?
You know that a Super Bowl match is gonna
happen and you know that the holidays
are coming up, you know that the fabric
is gonna increase to your service.
What we do, we typically,
scale up our services.
Scale up the number of holes,
number of pos that we have, and
and handle the traffic accordingly.
How many of us are guilty of scaling
too much during these periods and keep
them scaled up because we don't know
what kind of traffic is gonna hit us.
And even though, our systems are highly
scalable, they can scale whenever
there is a, an increase in traffic.
The track, the scalability
doesn't happen immediately.
It takes a few minutes
for any host to put up.
So it doesn't mean that you have, say,
a thousand hosts now, and the next
second you're gonna have 2000 hosts.
It doesn't happen like that.
It takes time for us to scale up.
And during that time
then we are scaling up.
We customers may see issues in
terms of latency, availability, et
cetera, which is not acceptable.
So AI can predict.
When we need to scale up and preemptively
scale up when required, just in time.
It's like just in time scaling up,
but with a good sense of when it is
needed and how much scaling is needed.
And 92% SLO adherence is basically
what this means here, is that by
doing this, by using ai, we can.
We can adhere to SLOs 92% of the time as
we scale up systems preemptively using ai.
Similarly cost reduction.
As I said before, I'm guilty of
having scaled up systems, having
doubled the capacity and having
it scaled up without scaling down.
Even before for quite a number of
days when it was not even required.
So just in time scaling
would reduce the cost by 35%.
So super important.
This is a very important place
where AI can be used in, in, in
scaling systems, moving on smarter
detection and root cause analysis.
The first step is always
anomaly detection, right?
ML identifies deviations
from normal behavior.
So I'll give you an example.
You deploy a new version of software.
It was, to say a new divert, one person
or 10% of your traffic to the new version.
Now the question is, how is
the new version working when
compared to the previous version?
You cannot expose a hundred percent
of your customers to the new version
without knowing how it's performing.
So you divert a percentage of the traffic,
but you have to so analyze how it is
working compared to the previous version.
ML models can help us do that.
It can analyze how the old version is
working compared to the new version
and tell you what the differences are.
Signal correlation, again,
ML models can analyze.
Related anomalies across
services, logs, cases, et cetera.
So it doesn't have to be just
your logs or just your case.
It can do anomaly detection across
service logs, cases, et cetera.
Dependency mapping, real time
topology, understanding shows how
issues propagate through the system.
So with when we have hundreds
of thousands of microservices
supporting in the backend.
It can, ML models can help you
trace, trace the issue and it'll
also tell you how issues are
propagating through the system.
Blast radius analysis.
So when you do root cause analysis
after incidents, or even for
even for during design, we can,
it is always important for us.
To reduce the blast radius
in case of an incident.
So which can ML models can help us
identify quickly, identify which services
and users are affected by an incident,
and also will help us in designing good
systems with where, whenever there is
an outage, which will reduce the blast
release, root cause identification.
To be honest.
It's in the nascent stage now.
And but I think once the data that we
provide to these models are good enough,
then root cause analysis or root cause
identification is something that ML
models can definitely help us get better.
All these things reduce M-T-T-I-M-T-T-I
is being time to identify basically.
Identifying that there is an issue going
on so that you can do remediation quickly,
going to autonomous remediation.
So now assume that you are using AI to
identify that an issue is going on, right?
We have these anomaly detections, et
cetera, et cetera, and now we know
that there is an issue going on.
So what does.
What should the system do?
Ideally it would page an on-call
engineer and the on-call engineer would
say, okay, something is happening.
Let me go fix it.
And how does fixing happen?
We can use gentech mitigations
like Google has mentioned in their
Sari book, there are a few generic
mitigations that you could do.
You control back code, deploy.
See if there was a deployment that
happened, roll it back, see if there
was a bad host, replace the host
or take it out of load balancer.
So there are a few things
that, you could do, limit the
traffic, et cetera, et cetera.
So we know that generic mitigations can
quickly fix an issue without much thought.
Now when we know that there are only a
set of gender mitigations that can happen.
The question is, can that
be automated as well?
So you know that an issue is going on.
Can we have automated systems
that would resolve these issues as
well, that will fix these issues?
But the question is who can we trust
ML systems to make the decision of
executing these remediations or not?
And that's an evolving process.
So one step is, yeah, you've
identified the problem.
You can use genetic mitigations to
fix these problems, and ML models here
can give us a recommendation for what
kind of genetic mitigations to use.
Once we are comfortable with that, then
we can allow AI to execute these genetic
mitigations without, even paging everyone.
Human AI collaboration model.
That's what this is.
The AI suggests what kind of
remediation a human should do.
The human would validate that.
For example, if the AI suggests, okay
there is a high number of five Xs that
are coming out of this this new version
of code, I would suggest you roll back
the code, roll back a deployment that
happened, one hour ago, and humans
say, okay, yep, this makes sense.
Let me do that.
Or they can say, okay, ai, would
allow, would give the key to AI
and say, yep you execute rollback.
The AI executes rollback and
all that knowledge is captured.
It becomes a loop and
the AI slowly learns.
Yep.
Whenever this kind of issue
happens, you can do a rollback of
code if there was a deployment.
So that whole cycle keeps repeating till
the humans can move out of the loop,
and AI makes decisions automatically.
Things like, the future.
There are advanced anomaly detections
here where the anomaly detection,
comes through various different sources
into a single powerful representation.
Also we are seeing that models are
very good at even when ML models,
are dependent on past data, right?
And a large number of data.
A large number of events that happened
in the past to predict the future.
But we are seeing that few short
learning is also happening.
What that means is that even the rarest
and the most elusive failure modes are
also being predicted with these ML models.
And that is is really
coming up these days.
Moving on, right?
What is the overall impact?
Personally, I've seen a huge
impact in a few areas, right?
The first one is noise reduction.
Let me give you an example.
For example, if you're using, each
company uses different tools for
for monitoring, alerting, ticket
management, et cetera, et cetera.
You may be using.
A bunch of tools, say for example,
Datadog or Big Panda, Dynatrace, Splunk,
or PagerDuty no matter what the tools
are, all these tools are bringing
in ai, ai operations into the mix.
And one of the things that we did
was that we saw huge pager noise.
And as I mentioned before, an outage
would raise a bunch of would break
the threshold of a bunch of monitors,
and all those monitors would.
Send out alerts to the on-call person
and for every incident there would be
hundreds of pages that would reach the
on-call person, and the page storm would
cause more confusion than anything else.
So what we did was PagerDuty
had a had a feature to group.
These alerts into one so that the on-call
person doesn't receive as many alerts.
And you could intelligently group
similar alerts into one alert
and say, okay, I'm hearing, I'm
seeing a bunch of monitors failing.
Here is one alert for you and you
may want to look into this area.
That has really helped us in reducing
noise and alert fatigue in alert storms.
By 60%, which is huge.
So when an incident these days
happen, the number of pages that an
oncology has reduced so much, now
the oncology can go and focus on what
really matters and not focus on not
focus on acknowledging these pages.
We are also seeing a
huge reduction in mttr.
MTTR is meantime to resolution
basically when an incident is opened.
The time it takes to resolve the incident
to resolve the issue has reduced a lot
because with these tools are able to
correlate data between these different
data sources like tele metadata
traces, log, et cetera, and it's able
to narrow down on the area of impact.
So that is really helping all college
engineers to quickly go and identify
the areas where the problem is happening
and do mitigate and mitigate the issue.
I said alert fitting is one thing,
and then incident frequencies,
definitely decreased number of
incidents because we are able to
automate the remediation process.
Nobody gets, imagine this, right?
You, you're running tens of
thousands of servers and every
time there is a CPU breach.
Or, a host goes down, if an onca
unit gets paged just to replace
the host, then the on-call engineer
would never be able to sleep, right?
So these things are handled automatically
these days and it's become alarm.
So the number of incidents have gone
down as well, and the efficiency
of infrastructure we are seeing
pro slow progress in these things
because for better capacity planning.
I see, not all companies are using AI
to predict capacity, but I see a big
trend in in large companies that are
using AI to predict capacity and scale
and using that to scale of systems.
So definitely using AI in in the real
world is pretty impactful to business.
So what do we do?
How do we, what do we do to adopt this?
Visibility and anomaly detection
is phase one, so you cannot say, a
company that has not implemented any
of these things, it's very difficult
to do all these things on day one.
So what do you do is do
this in phases, right?
The first step is to emit
the right telemetry data.
So as long as you have data, the
right telemetry data that you emit.
That, that should help in, in, in ai.
So if you're not emitting the right
data, start emitting the right data.
That is step number one.
Step number two is use AI to,
to correlate all this data.
And build the dependency mapping
and reduce the investigation time.
You don't have to do this all by yourself.
There are these tools that will help
you do all these things, and most
tools that you use, as I mentioned
before, have got these features built
in these days, and which all you
have to do is to start using them.
Automation and prediction enable enabling
autonomous remediation for monitors.
That is the phase three because
as I said before, you cannot.
Rely on AI to make the
decisions on your behalf.
You can coach it so slowly you
can ask it to recommend what?
What could be a good remediation.
You can give it feedback.
Yep, this is good, this is bad, et cetera.
And slowly to learn.
And you get to a stage where
it can take decisions on your
behalf for the remediation as
well, and optimization and scale.
So expand the scope of
optimization will be based on.
For.
So first thing is the quality of data.
Make sure that phase one is good,
other things would fall in place.
We're coming to the end here.
So key takeaways, reliability is a given.
We expect reliability from
all the systems around us.
And reliability is dependent on data.
So if you've not done this.
Emit the right data, and AI can help
you with reliability, and AI can go
to an extent where it can it, it can
help in tradition, not just reaction.
So as humans, we are reactive,
but humans plus ai, we can make
predictions not just be reactive
humans plus AI outperform.
Either alone, right?
So humans alone or AI alone cannot work.
Humans and AI together would
perform, would outperform.
You know what?
Humans did all these years and
what's gonna happen in the future?
Reinforcement learning is a big thing.
Self-improving remediation
policies is that said before.
As you teach AI to, for the mediation.
The number of pages that non receives,
would drama drastically go down because
AI would be able to make decisions
on what remediation steps to take
and then give them automatically
digital twins, like deployments.
You would have a virtual environment
which would be validated by ai, and
then AI will tell you, yep, this
is good, and then move that to the
customers and causal reasoning,
causal reason, cause and effect.
So when there is a cause in one
area, it's gonna tell you what's
gonna happen and know what, how
it's going to affect another area.
So these are things that are
upcoming and would help companies
support the systems better.
So predictive prevention
is the new SR standard.
I hope you all love this session.
Thank you so much.
You'll have a good one.
Cheers.