Speaker 27: Hello.
Hi everyone.
This is Puja Ranjan.
I work in the software cloud providing
industry in the San Francisco Bay.
I have been working here for over a
decade and I'm very excited to be here
at the conference, 42 DevOps of 2026.
What a great way to start the year.
Without further ado, let's get started.
I'll talk a little bit about myself
and then a little bit about the
topic I'm trying to cover something
that's very fundamental for DevOps
and and yeah, you can reach out to
me and connect with me for questions.
So let me share my screen
and we will get started.
Okay, yeah, a little bit more
about me on the first slide.
As I've mentioned, I am focusing
on delivering enterprise scale
level SaaS software services.
I have worked across different companies
that provide different kinds of
microservices mostly in the B2B format.
My customers have largely been
other businesses educational
institutions, organizations, and
and yeah, other B2B businesses.
So coming to why am I choosing to
talk about what I'm talking about
today is because of the impact that
it has on software as an industry.
So all of us have definitely heard about
like sas, software as a service model
which is a cloud model where any software
that a provider builds is a built,
licensed, delivered, and managed by the
provider or the owner of the software
and it's delivered of the internet.
It allows the end user to access
applications via a web browser or.
They can have a subscription that
they can use and then install
or use that software locally.
What are the benefits of using
the software service model?
Obviously it helps you with costs.
So smaller vendors, businesses
do not need to worry about.
Building, maintaining,
shipping their own software.
Smaller businesses who are trying
to sell smaller items or were
trying to run some sort of analysis
or data sciencey algorithms.
They do not need to worry about, building
their own infrastructure, maintaining
that infrastructure from scratch worrying
about security, reliability, all of that.
How do we.
How do we provide this, all of these
things to an end user and then how
do we continuously keep providing it?
And then how do we maintain all
regulations and standards that are imposed
by different organizations in different
companies and different countries.
So that's the summary
of what we're gonna do.
What we're gonna talk about here.
So why is this topic important?
Question number one.
It's very important
because SaaS is a market.
Hager, a market grabber in terms of.
In terms of revenue all software services
applications, if you look at the numbers
that the companies in the Silicon Valley
gen rate the number is upwards of three
50 billion US dollars in annual revenue.
And this delivery comes at
the cost of promising like
availability, service availability.
So when we are talking about
a small vendor who wants to.
For example, host a small handcraft
website on an already existing platform.
They are agreeing to use that platform
as a service, and then the vendor
will have a contract for them.
Okay, we will keep your service
up and running for 99.9% of the
time, and this is the amount that
you will owe us for your usage.
Something like that.
A rental contract.
And also now this is the amount of
time we're saving through automation.
I'm gonna come to this a little later.
Before that, let's come to why is this why
is compliance and delivery all of these
important when you are a cloud vendor?
Working on the cloud provider
side, something that you will.
Deeply notice is that just
like every other software.
Delivery model software as a service
also follows like different different
stages of software delivery.
So if you are delivering SaaS for a, for
any, and any provider or vendor, what
you will see is that you have to follow
your SDLC steps, the software development
lifecycle steps one of the first one of
which could be your feature planning.
It could be followed by
architectural design.
And then we do talk about development.
We talk about automated testing,
we talk about deployment, and
then we talk about monitoring and
improving how the service works.
So here is where I would like to
get into a little bit of depth.
So as software in different stages
of software delivery, right?
There are different categories
of things that are important.
And these different and there are
different stakeholders to every specific
category that we're talking about.
For example, when we talk about the
first stage when we are trying to
gather requirements, like what is a good
requirement for a cloud vendor to deliver
it's usually gathered by a team of product
managers who have the nerve and the pulse
for what for what the market actually
wants, what the customer actually wants.
And these can, and a customer can
either approach them directly or there
are, and the current times, there's
so much AI tooling embedded into our
systems to determine what's the, what
next feature that the customer wants.
So we can stay ahead of the curve.
SOS data scientists.
Nowadays they use sophisticated tools
like large language data models to
define interesting patterns from
structured and unstructured data,
to predict the list of soon to be
most desirable software features.
And this can be in any industry
finance, healthcare, commerce
journalism, content creation.
Engineering, aviation planning
a travel, all these things.
So based on the data that's collected
in these stages, either through
automation or through or through
like direct customer interaction
a project plan is put together.
So we try to understand the
requirements that we're trying to build.
What's the target audience
that we're building for?
What's the projected adoption rate
that we think it'll be, and how will
that be accepted in the industry?
And how will we gather feedback basically.
So compliance now, if, now about
this rough stage, if we wanna
talk about how are we making
sure that compliance is in phase?
So compliance at this stage
usually is a bunch of legalities.
So there are contracts that are assigned
between customers and clients that
are some non-disclosure agreements.
Maybe it's more to do with the
legal side of things, but these
contracts usually enforce the
SLA that people are looking for.
And SLA is nothing but a
service level agreement.
It's regarding the availability
and scaling requirements
of a feature or service.
For example, a simple contract and
a clause could be like, Hey, I will
host my website on your platform if
you guarantee me 99.99% availability.
So what is 99.99% availability?
It's the difference between I would
say having a service up and running
like your website, up and running for
less than maybe four hours annually.
So there could be some downtime that could
be due to outages that the vendor could
have migrations or just internet blips or
any other performance related bottleneck.
But in a nine, 9.95% agreement,
what we would say is that,
Hey, we want the service to be
up and running for less than.
For always apart from like under
less than four hours per year.
But if you up the service level
contract and say, okay, now we're
gonna talk about 99.99% availability,
what you're saying is that we want
the service to be up and running for
less than maybe 50 minutes in a year.
So that's a lot of difference.
Although the number looks like pretty
similar, the difference is too much
because, for us to promise, and that's
why the most stable cloud providers are
able to provide most stable numbers.
So talking about, so this kind of
compliance and delivery standards that
have to be maintained, these level
contracts are assigned when we are doing
like feature planning in step one, we
are talking about, Hey, can we keep
the feature up and running for so long?
And if there is a, if there's a
deviation, then there are like
various clauses in the contract to
make up for the monetary losses.
Coming to the next stage software
architects, and now we're talking
about architectural design and review.
So now we have we have listed it out.
We know what we're trying to build.
We have an agreement with the
customer on what to build.
We have used certain AI and compliance.
Strategies to ensure that
everything is secured.
Now we're talking about what are we gonna
do when there are software architects?
When we are talking to about
designing the actual feature that
we're gonna deliver to a customer.
So software architects and senior
software engineers work to design
components of the feature or service.
There are multiple meetings and
sync ups to determine how are
we gonna do something like this.
You can say that there are, there
are unified modeling, language
diagrams and tools, chat bots that
you could use to actually write,
to actually draw these diagrams.
What you're trying to see is that,
hey, are we being able to draw a
good behavioral diagram, the sequence
of how data is gonna flow between
the different modules of your.
Of your classes how well an object
oriented system and or what kind of code
design patterns are you gonna use be the
builder pattern or the singleton pattern?
Abstract pattern.
There are a lot of tools that could be
used to automate the entire process.
That could be rgo, it could
bevis, it could be Autodesk,
and anything and compliance.
Compliance again at this stage would be
ensuring that everything that we are using
here is either open source or any third
party software that you're using here.
It's either open source which is
basically crowdsource software
for public consumption, or has
gone through proper licensed.
License, purchase procedures.
Compliance also involves like
doing a full security posture
review of the proposed software.
So we could send it to a
security design team internally.
And most organizations have a full
fledged security team that would do a
full fledged analysis of whatever service
or feature that you're trying to ship.
And they will tell you why.
Should you do or should you not do
what you're doing to make sure that
we are not exposing the service or
any of these hosting requirements
to any sort of vulnerabilities?
There could be denial of service,
there could be cross side scripting.
We do not want any of this to happen,
and that's why full review is conducted.
If any leaks are found, then those.
Then the design goes back to the
architecture board, and then all
these features are reviewed again
and ensure that we are complying with
all the security postures within the
provider's organization to ensure that
we're not delivering anything that
is vulnerable to security attacks.
So stage three here is largely
where you're actually trying to
build it, that this is when the
engineers become a lot more involved.
So we're talking about
software development time.
These will be people who will come
in, build their specific tool.
They will use programming languages,
Java, Python, c plus, any version
control system maybe GI per force.
Yeah.
Here a list of some tools
that are usually used in this
process that can be seen here.
So you're gonna use so SaaS delivery
systems heavily rely on application
program interfaces like APIs to enforce
the right bound boundaries of abstraction
between a user and a service interaction.
And companies invest heavily in
building and automating APIs.
So that's one thing.
And API specification generation
is also a specific tool set that
most companies have internally.
They have their own
internal versions of it.
So when we are trying to develop the
feature that a customer was asking us, or
something that was driven by the market,
how do you ensure that you are compliant?
To industry standards country level
standards, how do you ensure that
everything's compliant so that
we can uphold the quality level?
It's usually largely depends
on, in the development stage.
It largely depends on using
very good coding pro practices.
So proper data abstraction,
automated generation of.
Maybe unit tests and validating a
smallest functional component in
code like writing tests to validate
every small component, every feature
set, every code path in the flow is
important and reiterating to ensure
that the design document is agreed upon.
If you are making a change, if it feels
technically infeasible or feels like
it's exposing a vulnerability, it can go
back to the architects or the security
organization for a re review and.
And then the design document is revised,
and then we can go ahead and make the
new changes that developer is proposing.
Then there are code, so CICD is, this
is exactly where CICD actually starts.
CICD actually means continuous integration
and continuous delivery ecosystem.
Here is when, so once.
Once a developer is ready with
this new feature, or while he's
working on this new feature, he can
continuously keep pushing his code
into the company's remote repositories.
And from there we can
request for code reviews.
Code reviews are done to maintain the.
The standards of compliance.
So if there are, if coding is reducing
something that's, that might cause a
data leak or an, or a security leak.
Then in the modern, the current
times, there are a lot of.
AI code chat review bots that would
prompt and that would fix it, that
would prompt you the changes that
would make suggestions and sometimes
even fix like suggest small random
fixes in your, in, in, in your code.
And then it also goes
through another round of.
And then there are like linter tools.
Yeah.
There are linter tools that bots look at.
It's like a bot that, cleans up
the code cleans up code like spaces
instead of tabs, checks for code
vulnerabilities, like outdated
package versions that could become.
Security threats.
So there are a lot of scanner tools
that run inside the system to make sure
that we don't push either a vulnerable
version or any package dependency
that could cause a security breach.
Peer engineers are also heavily
involved with this process.
They hold a code review.
Quality par pull requests are approved
after thoroughly reviewing them, and
then merge into the main after merged
into the main master repository.
After all these checks are complete.
So stage four is where compliance, so
going back to this diagram these steps.
So now what we are saying is
that we are building a code.
We are making sure that we have gathered
our requirements from product teams.
We have had several design meeting rounds.
We've done all of that.
We are now into development.
We are almost code complete.
Our product is almost ready to go
out, but that is where we we start
looking at another very critical
phase in this process, which is
called the comp quality deliverable.
So how do we automate and test
everything that we are building?
We need to write comprehensive test suites
to validate functionality, performance,
compliance requirements, and so on.
So in this stage, what we are doing is
that we are shifting our focus on quality.
What we are seeing is that now we are
gonna conduct like very rigorous tests,
functional tests, integration tests,
regression tests and security tests.
We're gonna write test code
using J Unit, moca, JMeter, A
lot of these tools out there.
Some of these auto also auto
generate some amount of code.
And then we are gonna run these
tests on the new code that we have
written, and we'll gonna run it on
the code that was existing to make
sure that we haven't introduced a
new bug in this process of building.
We, there are again, and there are
different code coverage tools like Clover.
What they ensure is that we
are at least maintaining code
coverage in terms of testing.
The lines of code that we have written
at least 95% or above code is it's the
standard industry practice that we do.
We want test coverage
that goes across like.
Always above 95%.
So we know that our the code that
we're shipping out is less buggy.
So I would like to actually,
yeah, let's talk about this
a little more, to understand.
Software testing.
I would say there are two broad
categories, so we want to ensure that
because these are paid customers that we
are shipping to as a vendor you want to
ensure that code that you have written
is very thoroughly written and tested.
There are two categories here broadly
black box testing and white box testing.
What you could say black box is where the
component that is being built, whatever
feature or service that you're building
is treated as just as a functional unit.
So without any, without worrying about
any internal implementation, your test
cases are purely designed based on the
product documentation that you have,
like the end to end user functionality
that the service is supposed to provide.
And then you do some stress tests to
ensure that there are no outliers.
So central organizations cloud providers
these days use orchestration services
like Kubernetes to Containerize and
Alize, the running of functional tests.
And to continuously keep running
it in their production environments
back to back all the time.
And no button click is required.
It's totally touchless.
And, or you can use like Aron job
sequence program, something like Aron
job sequence into your systems to
make sure that tests run against, your
production environments every few minutes.
That's what black box testing does.
And then when we talk about white box
testing here we are also, yeah, so
these are the all the testing dependency
checks, static analysis that we do if
we talk about white box testing now.
So white box testing is, more evolved test
plan and focuses on code workflows, and it
makes sure that you catch issues like an
finite loop null point or exception, and
you prevent the wastage of crossing time.
Sustainability is a big deal,
so we'll talk about that later.
But we want to write.
Code that is optimized and that has
the minimal amount of execution time
to, so for the user can have a faster
processing time and faster reaction time.
And that will mean that we are providing
you with a good user experience.
And we are also optimizing the usage
of the underlying hardware that we are
that we are hosting the service on.
So talking about certain standards
that now when we talk about compliance
and when it comes to, so in us most
of the times there are a bunch of,
we spoke quite a few data governance
standards, but there are two specific
standards that I would like to call out.
One is the SOX compliance standard.
It's like a federal regulatory standard
that all SaaS provider companies all
cloud provider companies have to stick to.
And this act enforces that robust
testing of software components
with clear defined end results.
And goals have to be documented in your
system, and they have to be available
if and when, and audit it happens.
So every ticket, every feature
that you're building should have a
well-defined acceptance criteria.
On when is this product or the service
declared or acceptably complete, for the
end user, that criteria has to be defined.
And then you have to explain
how do you meet that?
And then these, and you have to document.
You can document them in any form.
You can have any internal tool for
documentation, or we could use standard
tools like Jira where they come in
with these specific fields and you
can document those answers there.
And these results have to be available
all the time for audits if needed.
There's another compliance standard
that a lot that's really important,
especially for companies that
provide any sort of federal services.
So the United States a lot
of cloud providing companies
or database companies or.
A third party company provide
services to the federal government.
And of course, data there is highly
secure and has to has to be, has to jump
through a lot more security loopholes for
anybody to even get access to deploy or
maintain a service for these customers.
But the one standard that they
specifically ask for is a VPA compliance,
which is called a voluntary product
accessibility template Compliance.
What happens, the requirement of
this template is that they want us
to keep any service or any offering
inclusive to people who have any
visual or audio deficiencies.
So you are supposed to conduct a
other test of your software system and
you could use tools like the screen
reader, and then you are supposed
to document all your results into
an accessibility conforming report.
And generate generate like screenshots
of all your service endpoints that
are accessible to a customer show.
How, and this applies to the UI bits
of it, so not the API interactions,
but the UI part of whatever you
are delivering to a customer.
All those things have to be access.
So the, these standards have to
be met, and that's why there are
different, again, there are different
tools that companies use to to make
sure that these standards are met.
And again, these can be audited
at any point of time, and you will
have to be ready with reports.
And these these compliance certifications
are regenerated every year.
So the evaluation could happen
at random time, but they
definitely happen year after year.
So yeah, we spoke about service
reliability bit at the beginning.
What's the difference
between 99.99 versus 99.95?
Some what's, why are we trying to
automate these, all these workflows here?
So just to wrap up that last stage,
and then I want to tie this back
into this one, into this stage.
So when now that you've built and shipped
your service, you're ready to ship it
out you're using, you, you are gonna go
and do some CICD kind of deployment where
you use a deployment tool, GitLab Bamboo.
You build it, you use Python bash
strips to provide assert logic, confirm
that all automated tests have passed.
You're now pushing it using your,
you may might want to do some
low test using Locust or J Meter.
And then so that you can spawn
like millions of process threads
or user threads per second and
mimic like, how would a real end
user perform in these situations?
Once you have, and this is essential
for us to confirm that our SLA
that we are prompting, the customer
will actually be available.
So compliance standards not only apply
to successful availability, but also
to the latency of server requests.
So every request response that is expected
to succeed within 500 milliseconds.
So if you're saying that 70% of
calls and address 70% of the API
calls or UI call made by a customer,
a request made by a customer
should take under 500 milliseconds.
And after all these rigorous tests.
We are now deploying our software.
Once it passes these tests, we are now
deploying it to every customer region
or like a geographical region where our
data centers and warehouses are located.
The final stage where we have now
deployed a service and we are getting
customer feedback, we're trying to
improve again, at any point, the SDLC
lifecycle goes back to stage one to stage.
Here.
Yeah.
So once we have tested production
monitoring is happening now at any
point, it can go back to in the loop
for the stages, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 again.
So we continuously keep improving
and optimizing our service while
maintaining our service, like
productively operationally to keep
production, operational usage data and
metrics are the most important thing.
So tracking it is.
Possible by doing, by
using tools like Grafana.
You can save your data in for data
warehouses and then you can mine it
for interesting usage patterns that are
tools like CCA that are help, that will
help you pre-process this data and then
feed it to data models and then find
interesting correlations that are several
services out there in the market that
help you run these kind of analysis.
Compliance.
At this stage is largely like data
handling, governance, every possible
access control, isolation between
customer and data, and between
customer data, so it's implemented.
Logging tools are audited for
privacy software upgrades, dependent
packages, version upgrades, or
constantly deployed to ensure
latest and best security posture.
Horizontal scaling is possible
sometimes because you want
to add more configurations.
Or add more servers to the fleet to deal
with the growing requests of servers.
And then vertical scaling is possible.
Sometimes we just add more memory and
more processing to an existing server.
So this, all the scaling of this
is dependent on the predicted load.
We get this load information from
all the AI tools that we run.
Tools like Jira, sd, they help us
like set up alarms if something
goes wrong, if our service.
If there's less disk space list on the
left, on the stove, for example, it can
alarm us and tell us like, Hey, you just
have 30% memory available on this one.
So these are so data governance.
So once we deal with all these challenges
or we continuously keep dealing with all
these challenges in production monitoring,
why do we deal with all of these now?
The point of managing all these
automations and trustworthy delivery is
for these three, three strong reasons.
One is trustworthy delivery.
So we are, we want be sure that we
are compliant in every way so that a
customer can place that full trust in
us and position, and we could be one
of the strong players in the market.
The second is to save engineer time.
Because production, because really
production and maintenance is an
ongoing effort, it's constant.
It never ends.
It never ever ends.
And in a cloud providing company
like engineers spend over 30% of
the time just maintaining software.
And then there are full DevOps
teams deployed for this.
So we want to save the time, but we
want to keep it very we want to keep
it very streamlined and we want to
keep optimize and we want to keep
automating everything that can be.
Automated.
So this, our build to our, the
time that it takes for us to build
something and to ship something
is very minimal and very optimal.
And of course for
scalability in the future.
So given that every cloud riding
company is actually just growing and
growing, and there are several there
are several different, the data centers
that we are expanding to globally.
You want to minimize the amount of
time it takes for you to build in
one region and then ship and deploy
to every other region in the world.
Yeah, that's the summary of how
things work in a cloud provider
setup for a SaaS company.
The key takeaways usually are that,
yeah, you start working on these
compliance requirements as early as
possible, integrated into every step
of your journey as you are going
through development and shipping.
You put it under monitor, you.
Have quantifiable metrics that
you measure at every point of
time you instrument your code.
You surface out all these all these.
Metrics that you need to keep your service
to measure the quality of your service.
You automate as much as you can, free
up more engineer time, and have a more
streamlined way of deploying things.
And that automatically brings us to the
four point, which is sustainability.
So the less time you spend, the more
optimized your hardware and your
software is the smaller your carbon
footprint will be, and you will continue
shipping things to your customers on
time in the most efficient manner.
Yeah, that's pretty much it for me folks.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you DevOps, for letting me present.
Talk to y'all in another conference.
Thank you.
Bye.