Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Con 42, DevOps 2025 conference.
I am Sandeep Bajju, and I bring over
a decade of experience in building and
securing cloud and hybrid platforms.
One of the most pressing topics
in tech today is the cloud
infrastructure security, how it's
transforming industries and the
unique security challenges it brings.
I'm excited to share some of
the innovative Cloud security
strategies that tackle these
challenges and help secure the cloud.
Let's dive in and make the
most of this exciting session.
Just a disclaimer, the presentation slides
information I shared today represent
my own personal views and speaking for
myself and not on behalf of my employer.
So now let's talk about
the cloud driven future.
By 2025, 75 percent of the enterprise
data will be created and processed
in the cloud, enabling the real time
insights and accelerating digital
transformation across the industries.
As the cloud adoption is increasing,
94 percent of the enterprises are
already leveraging cloud services,
such as driving, Cost optimization,
scalability, and business agility.
So, the cloud adoption is becoming a
core pillar for competitive advantage
and operational resiliencies.
So, as adoption increases,
so as the cyber attacks.
So, organizations face thousands
of cyber attacks on average daily.
So the strengthening of cloud
security and implementing the advanced
threat detection are critical for
protecting the sensitive data.
What exactly is the
Zero Trust architecture?
You know, Zero Trust assumes all users
and devices are untrusted by default.
So, the continuous verification and
contextual access control ensures
security at every point of access,
whether it's internal or external.
Some of the important models are,
trust nothing, verify everything.
So, if we take the multi factor
authentication, or Risk, real time risk
analysis, or identity access management.
All these systems continuously verify
every access request, ensuring that
only authorized entities gain access.
Next is the continuous authentication,
which is an ongoing process based on user
behavior, device health, location, which
is like adapting in real time to changes.
This is like a dynamic approach which
prevents unauthorized access post login.
We can talk about the micro segmentation
which is more like isolating the systems
into the smaller segments using techniques
like VLANs, Software Defined Networks,
Network Access Controls, ensuring that
least privileged principle and granular
control over data flows, and reducing
the, you know, lateral movement in the
event of a breach or attack vector.
When we talk about the advanced
IAM methods, This is nothing but an
identity access management methods.
There are multiple authentication methods
out there which are like single sign
on, certificate based authentication,
passwordless authentication, token
based authentication, hardware tokens.
And some of the commonly used
mechanisms are Biometric authentication,
which leverages the unique physical
traits like fingerprints, facial
recognitions to enhance the security.
You know, combined with encryption
and machine learning algorithms,
the biometrics offer a high level
of fraud resistance and accuracy.
Next is the multi factor authentication,
which requires multiple forms
of verification like password.
One time code, you know, which provides
a multi layer defense, making it
harder for attackers to access accounts
and move laterally within systems.
Next is the adaptive access policy, which
is like a real time context aware policies
which dynamically adjust authentication
requirements based on, you know, user
behavior, device security, and location.
optimizing the security, you know, without
compromising the usability of the systems.
Next is how we can leverage the AI and
ML in the cloud security, which is by
using AI driven threat detection, which
can process millions of security events
per second, you know, which enables the
identification of some of the important
or attacks like zero day vulnerabilities.
ransomware attacks, you know,
which helps in responding 50 times
faster than traditional methods.
Next, for the behavior analytics,
you know, we can leverage the machine
learning, which can continuously monitor
user activities, which helps in creating
that baseline behavior profiles.
so, which helps in, identifying the
anomalies like, accessing the sensitive
data from unusual locations, you know,
trigger instant alerts to prevent
insider threats and account takeovers.
We can also use the AI based
security tools, which can reduce
false positives up to 50 percent
as compared to the traditional
signature based security systems.
which allows, you know, security
teams to focus on the real threats,
improving the response time and
also the operational efficiency.
And, you know, we, how, next we talk
about like how we can leverage some of
the quantum resistant encryption methods.
Yeah, you know, like pulse quantum
algorithms, which counter the potential of
quantum computers breaking the classical
cryptographies like RSA, ECC, post quantum
algorithms which leverages problems
that quantum systems can't solve easily,
such as like lattice based cryptography,
multivariate quadratic equations.
So if you are looking at an NIST
approved algorithms, which ensures the
robust quantum resistant encryption,
which provides, future proof protection
against the quantum threats, which is
more powerful than current systems.
We can also look at the hybrid
cryptography method, which is like
integrating the traditional RSA or ECC
methods with lattice based cryptography.
which creates a dual
layer encryption model.
So this approach provides the
backward compatibility with
existing systems while preparing
organizations for the quantum era.
So the hybrid cryptography facilitates
a smooth transition without
disrupting the legacy encryption.
We can also use the key management
method Which is like leveraging the
advanced hardware security models,
you know, like HSMs, which are
basically a cryptographic key, which
were like basically a cryptographic
keys are stored securely with 256
bit entropies for robust randomness.
Automated key rotations and zero knowledge
proofs, you know, which provides the
additional layer of security, ensuring
that data remains protected even in
the face of quantum computing advances.
Cryptographic agility, which is basically
like allowing the quick adaption.
to evolving threats by enabling rapid
updates to the encryption algorithms.
So this agility ensures that even as
quantum computing grows, organizations
can transition seamlessly to the,
seamlessly to post quantum algorithms
without system downtime or security risks.
Next, we can talk about
like how we can leverage.
or how we can integrate blockchain
into the cloud security.
One is using the immutable logging,
which uses blockchain's distributed
ledger, ensures that, you know,
the security logs are tamper proof,
providing immutable, verifiable
records for all the cloud activities.
Once a data is Once a data is stored,
you know, it cannot be altered,
you know, ensuring a transparent
audit trail for detecting and
investigating security incidents.
Next is the smart contracts.
So, smart contracts can automate
security policy enforcement, which
includes the access control, encryption
standards, and data sharing rules.
So they verify conditions like, you know,
device health, locations, credentials
before granting or denying access.
So if these are executed on a
blockchain, they ensure the policies
are transparent and tamper resistant.
Next, we can look at the decentralized
identity, which puts users in
control of the personal data.
where the data is stored in a
secured, distributed ledger.
So, which is like cryptographically
verified identities, which ensures
only authorized parties can access
this sensitive information, reducing
the centralized data breach risk and
also prevents the identity theft.
So some of the micro segmentation
strategies are network mapping, which
helps organization gain a comprehensive
understanding of their infrastructure.
By identifying and categorizing these
assets and traffic flows, network mapping
ensures that security vulnerabilities
are identified, threats are mitigated,
and performance is optimized.
We can also look at the policy creation
which helps defining the granular
security rules for each segment.
Policies like least privileged access
ensures that users, devices, and
applications only have access to essential
resources like securing sensitive data
and ensuring the regulatory compliance.
We can look at the segmentation
implementation, which divides networks
into smaller and isolated zones, so
ensuring the data is protected even if an
attack will compromise one of the segments
like VLAN and software defined networks
or network access controls, which enforce
strict communication policies between
these segments, so preventing the lateral
movement and reducing the attack surface.
We can also implement continuous
monitoring, which ensures that all
segments are secure and compliant.
This will help systems detect suspicious
activities and potential breaches,
providing continuous feedback to
adjust segmentations and also improve
security posture as new threats emerge.
Next is the serverless architecture,
which offers scalability and cost
efficiency, while it represents a unique
challenge in securing dynamic FML, you
know, securing dynamic FML components
like functions, APIs, and even triggers.
So securing these components involves
creating a model that address the
absence of underlying infrastructure.
So making the traditional security
approaches difficult to apply.
If you are looking at the functional
level security, which is composed
of stateless, isolated functions,
which gets triggered by events.
So securing them involves applying
granular IAM policies, least
privilege access, and also the
RPAC to restrict resource access.
So the best practices such as like input
validation, output encoding, and also the,
you know, function isolation, minimizing
the risk like injection attacks.
Okay, so for multifunction
environment, ensure that breaches
in one function don't lead to that,
that important lateral movement.
Next is the API Gateway production.
So the API gateway is like an entry
point to the serverless functions.
You know, securing it requires strong
authentications, like AU or API, keys
and, and authorization to control access.
So we can also do additionally like rate
looting or throttling, which prevents
the DDoS attacks while integrating a
WAF, which is like a web application
firewall, which protects against
vulnerabilities such as SQL injections.
So the monitoring the API traffic, which
helps in enabling the quick detection
of suspicious, suspicious patterns and
also the unauthorized access attempts.
Next is the event driven, which
are triggered by actions like
HTTP request or, you know, file
uploads or database changes.
You know, the security involves like
applying policies that responds to these
event driven activities in real time,
such as like logging, data encryption, or,
you know, alleging on abnormal behavior.
Anomaly detection can be done using
the machine learning, which can
identify the patterns of the potential
attacks like You know, function
triggered by the unrecognized source.
You know, events can be monitored and also
the policy thresholds can be set to block
the malicious activity before execution.
Next is the, you know, these serverless
functions often rely on external
libraries or services which can introduce
vulnerabilities, which is nothing but
a third party dependency scanning.
So we can do the continuous scanning
of these dependencies, ensuring that
vulnerabilities are detected and patched.
Like tools like Static Analysis or
Dependency Scanners, which automatically
assess the health of the third party
code and identifying the outdated or
insecure libraries and also preventing
vulnerabilities from being incorporated
into your serverless ecosystem.
Next is how we can use the
continuous compliance automation.
So, automating the compliance ensures
that organizations consistency,
I mean like consistently adhere
to all the regulatory frameworks
without relying on manual audits.
So, by leveraging the automated tools and
cloud native services, we Organizations
can maintain compliance at scale and
also in real time, by reducing the manual
errors and also the audit overhead.
So the automated compliance, which
is nothing but like starts with
defining the policies which align
with the specific regulations
of the organization or industry.
You know, these policies are
translated into machine readable rules.
which can be integrated into
infrastructure as a code templates
and also the cloud configurations,
you know, compliance parameters
include like data encryption, access
controls, system configurations.
So, so up by automating all this
policy enforcement eliminates the
human error and also ensures the
consistent adherence to the security.
and also to the regulatory requirements.
We can also use the real time
compliance monitoring which scans
systems for policy violations or
deviations from regulatory standards.
So using the AI driven analytics
and cloud native monitoring tools,
organizations can track, you know, changes
in system configuration, user access.
data patterns, you know, this
enables the immediate detection
of issues like unencrypted data,
unauthorized access or vulnerable
systems, you know, which ensures a
proactive approach to the compliance.
And also the automated remediation,
which helps in detecting a compliance
violation or You know, also automated
remediation systems, you know, initiate
the corrective actions such as reversing
the configurations or applying patches
or restoring the access control settings.
You know, if you are integrating
this with your CI, CDE,
Workflows or pipelines, right?
Which enables the continuous
compliance during the development,
testing, and production cycles.
This also helps in reducing the response
times and ensures that violations are
addressed before they escalate, minimizing
the risk of penalties or data breaches.
Automated tools can generate real
time compliance reports that provide
detailed, accurate overview of the
security configurations, patching it,
history, and also the, policy adherence.
So these reports are like the audit ready
and which can be generated on demand
to simplify the regulatory assessment.
So they offer pretty much like a
transparency and provide a comprehensive
record of actions which can be taken
to achieve and maintain compliance.
So that's streamlining the audit
process and also reducing the
workload of the compliance issues.
So some of the key initiatives are like
embracing the Zero Trust architecture.
You know, in Zero Trust model,
as we said earlier, no entity is
trusted by default, whether it's
inside or outside of the network.
So the identity centric approach, which
ensures that all requests, whether
from users, devices, or applications,
right, are Everything is authenticated,
authorized, and continuously verified.
So the principle of least privilege
access, which ensures that only
necessary resources are granted, you
know, minimizing the attack surface.
So to implement Zero Trust Organizations
must apply some of the strategies
like multi factor authentication.
Role-based access controls,
microsegmentation and continuous
monitoring that ensures every in
interaction is validated and locked.
Next is leveraging the
AI and ML capabilities.
So AI and machine listening are, you
know, rev revolutionizing the security by
enabling the predictive threat detections.
You know, by analyzing the, the
large data sets in real time.
So these technologies can identify
anomalous patterns or potential
threats even before they occur.
So the behavior analytics powered
by AI can spot insider threats.
You know, it also detect deviations
from normal user behavior.
improving the detection rates and
also reducing the false positive.
The ML model also assists in some of
these machine learning models, right?
It also assists in automating,
vulnerability identification and
also the incident response, which
helps security teams to stay one
step ahead of all these attackers.
And Nexus, you know, preparing for
quantum computing threats, you know.
It's like future proof your
infrastructure, guys, by implementing the
quantum resistant encryption protocols
and also maintaining, the crypto
isolity in your security frameworks.
Also, automate the compliance process.
We have to streamline the security
operations by implementing the continuous
compliance automations, which helps in
reducing the human errors and also ensures
that, you know, in real time, it adheres
to all the regulatory requirements.
So with this, I would like to reiterate,
I would like to Retreat and conclude
that some of the key takeaways to off,
you know, it's more like offering a
road map to help your organization
stay ahead of evolving security
threats, you know, is to fall and
also the compliance challenges, right?
is to follow all this emerging
technologies like quantum computing
and also by taking proactive steps.
Where you can build a more
resilient, adaptive, and future
proof security infrastructure.
Everyone, you know, thanks for your
time for attending this presentation.