Hello, I would like to invite you today
for this talk about quiet engineers.
If you feel you are an introverted
person, don't be afraid.
Neither this equation nor Paradise
Lost was dashed off by a poorly
animal, when Fred Gallagher said.
My name is Tomek, and I'm an introvert.
Alright, I'm a quiet engineer.
I would prefer that way.
So I'm an introverted person.
Why am I talking about
introvert or introverted person?
You will find out in a second that
introverted person has some tendency, but
it's not the, the name of this person.
Let's focus for a second for
this guy, Carl Gustav Jung.
He is the person who defined the
introversion and extroversion.
So he said that introversion is
an attitude type characterized
by an orientation in life through
subjective psychic content.
So we are, as introverted people,
we are looking inside of us.
And extroversion, he defined as attitude
type characterized by consideration
of interests of the external object.
So we are looking outside of our world.
So that's two definitions, right?
He didn't say about
introverts and extroverts.
He said about introversion
and extroversion.
And, everyone has both extroverted
side and introverted side,
with one being more dominant.
That was a big, surprise for me,
because at the beginning of my career,
I wanted to think about myself as
an extroverted, as an extrovert.
I'm an extrovert, I speak a lot,
but on the other hand, when I did
some tests and, and assessments,
it, it said that I'm an introvert.
I'm an extrovert.
So I said, Oh, no, I don't
want to be an introvert.
I know that introvert introverts are
not promoted in the companies and so on.
So I was a little bit, unhappy about it.
But when I was reading about
introversion, extroversion, I
found out that actually I have some
extroverted part of my human being and
introverted part of my human being.
So I saw that introversion is a continuum.
There is no A or B.
Great.
You are an introvert.
You are not an introvert.
As an engineer, when I think
about continuum, I see this.
So when I think about the spectrum,
I see the visible spectrum of light.
As you can see, visible
colors from left to right.
From, there is also a
spectrum of not visible.
waves like gamma rays, X rays, and
so on, radio waves on this side.
But let's focus on this visible
spectrum of, of electromagnetic field,
which is light, which is colors.
So, we are moving on the
spectrum from left to right.
And my introversion actually can be
colorful, can move in some situation
to the more introverted me, and in
some situations more extroverted me.
So I like it.
I use this analogy to, to myself.
And then I realize that I also have
the other dimensions of extroversion.
And also I can be more extroverted
in some situations and less
extroverted in some situations.
What a relief!
I don't know if you feel that,
if you realize that, but for me
as an engineer who is introverted
and also working in a corporate
environment, that's a huge relief.
I still can do a lot with my introversion.
And just after that, I realized,
I read about the ambiversion term.
So ambiversion is when you have
some extroverted characteristic and
some introverted characteristic.
That's a relief, right?
So I'm not an introvert.
I'm ambivert with those two spectrums on
introversion and extroversion moving on
in terms of it depends on the situation.
Wow.
Amazing.
I even have the animation
here to show my happiness.
okay, so that's one aspect.
I can move on this introverted,
extroverted spectrum and realizing
which type of situation triggers me
to be more active and which situations
triggers me to be less active.
The other part is those four red
lights, four lights, I have it here.
So, the theory from Jonathan Chick.
He defined four types of introversion.
So if we are looking for just one
spectrum, introversion spectrum,
from left to right, he also
defined four types, which is also
helpful for me as a quiet engineer.
So there are four of them.
Social introversion, thinking
introversion, restraint introversion,
and anxious introversion.
As easy as it sounds, social
introversion is the introverted
person who can be with, with other
people, can attend social, activities.
It doesn't drain him or her,
but at the same time, he or she
recharges her batteries or his
batteries outside of this event.
So you can, for a certain extent,
go to the social activities.
As an introverted person, I'm
this kind of person, and then
you can, Recharge after it.
The thinking, thinking, introverted
introversion is the introversion when
you like to think deeply about some
topics, especially alone, but you know,
spending a lot of time thinking about it.
For me it is, for example, preparing
the talks for the audience.
When I'm preparing the talk, when I
think about what I would like to tell
you, it's my time just without, just
with me in my room with my notes.
And that's beautiful flow state I have.
So that's the thinking introversion.
Restrained introversion is the third
aspect of introversion, when I'm sort of
in some situation afraid of the social
activities and I want to not engage.
I want to step back and say, Hey,
today I don't have the energy
to speak with those people.
So that's restrained introversion.
Sometimes I can have more
energy, sometimes less.
And anxious introversion.
This is the last one.
When we are, when our nervous system, not
we, but our nervous system is so afraid
of the situation that we don't want to
even think about interacting with people.
We are anxious about it.
Why am I telling you that?
Because when we put those introversions,
those four types of introversions,
into the equation, This diagram, we
can say that sometimes we can challenge
ourselves or try ourselves, if you
will, to move from one type to another.
Like, for example, restrained introversion
or restrained introverted person.
I can be today a restrained introverted
person, but I can try to Challenge myself.
I'll try to exercise to be more
social in the social part to
attend more events to attend.
maybe at the beginning, less crowded
events, but to get extra mile to,
to be in this the other type the
same with thinking introversion.
If I'm restrained, Maybe first step is
for me to be with myself and to think
about deeply about some, some problems.
We as developers, as engineers,
will usually do that, right?
That we would love to spend all day
thinking about our, riddles, our problems
in our code, and the anxious introversion.
What I, why I'm showing you that
here because it's rather, it's very
difficult for anxious introversion to
move to just to social introversion.
You would need to move through that.
Middle middle restraint introversion.
So this is obviously just
a theory and the model.
We know that, you know, we love models
because as engineers, because models
put our thoughts into the boxes.
But at the same time, we are
human beings and we are not
just as easy as those models.
So I'm just showing you
that for the inspiration.
But obviously this is, this is something
that we need to try, try for ourselves.
Now, Dr.
Gallagher also said that most
people with social anxiety want
to engage in social settings.
But fear of rejection or judgment
prevents them from doing so,
typically to their own disappointment.
I can tell that when I was more anxious in
the past, when I was small in the school,
a small kid in the school, I wanted to
be part of this social, very active life.
But I just had a fear of rejection.
So when I sort of, fight this fear
and realize how I can overcome
this fear, it helped me to be a
more social, introverted person.
Because when we have other people,
the presence of other people triggers
emotions into our nervous system.
It's It's important to
know that this is not us.
This is our part of us.
So our nervous system and it can be
triggered by other people presence
because we may be afraid of judgment.
For example, what they
are thinking about us.
Our brains cast the reality checking
if there are any danger situations.
So for example, when someone will
look differently on you, you will
say, or your brain will say, Hey,
I'm afraid of this situation, so I
better not to engage in conversation.
Things like this.
and nervous systems has a
tolerance to external stimulus.
So we just need to realize what's our
balance and level of these stimulations.
The question I had in my mind was that
are we born or made more introverted?
Was I born introverted person?
Or during my childhood
I was made introverted?
And there are research
that says it's 50 50.
I know that doesn't help a lot.
But actually it helps me because
then I realize that it's not
like 100 percent heritable.
I can determine, I can try
to change determination of
those 50%, so it's promising.
I would like to introduce you to
this, or introduce this person to you.
Susan Cain.
She's the author of the book, Quiet.
And, this is the book as a subtitle
says, the power of introverts in
the world that can't stop talking.
I really recommend you to read that book.
when I read that as I introverted
engineer, I was like, wow, right now
I know what to do, how I do it, how
I react and how can I help myself.
So I can, share some, tips and
tricks with you from this book
and also from my, from my life.
So what are the benefits first?
As for me as an introvert, for others
as a, as an introverted, person.
I meant benefits that others have
that I'm an introverted person.
the first one, engineering benefits.
So, as engineers, we have deep technical
expertise, deep technical knowledge.
We want to spend some time, very,
maximum amount of time learning about
us, learning about our, knowledge
about, our world, about technology,
programming languages, and so on.
We have analytical and methodical
thinking, which means that we can
solve a lot of difficult problems.
And that's our job, actually,
in the company, right?
To solve a lot of difficult problems.
We are detail oriented, in terms
of technical problems as well.
So we can very deeply understand
and have the very focused,
narrow focused concentration.
What are the programming benefits
then for our companies to
hiring us as a quiet engineers?
We are strong individual
contributors, very much so.
If we have the task, we will do that.
No matter what, I mean, we are
very motivated to dig into the
details, contribute to the task by
having individual point of view.
we do code reviews, right?
so, first things first, our code is high
quality usually, because that's why we
are so focused, it's so important for
us that we pay attention to details.
We, the code part is very high, but
also we have mechanism of code reviews
when we Now, it's, it's difficult for,
quiet engineers because usually what
we do in the code reviews, we put a lot
of comments to the pull request, right?
We review the pull request, we put
a lot of comments, we send back.
I had a situation in the past when
two guys, two engineers, were sitting
next to each other, desk to desk, and
during one week, they put like 100
comments to this code, to this pull
review, pull request with a code review.
Because they had difficulties
to speak with each other, right?
So, we are good in reviewing things, but
then we need to also think about speaking
to each other, not just typing comments.
Operational excellence.
Obviously, we would like to do all
the things in the best possible way.
So, we can say that if we are introverted,
Quiet engineers, we will do our excellent
job in coding and we are persistent.
You know what?
You are closing.
You try to close the laptop at 5:00
PM going out the, the office, but then
this difficult bug that you have in your
mind, how to solve it, keeps you, awake
during diet, for example, because we are
persistent to better, to to, to solve it.
What are the leadership
benefits for, for the company?
For us, from us as a, quiet engineers,
we, when we are the leaders, we
give the autonomy usually because we
don't want to, micromanage people.
We don't to overstep on
their shoes, on their toes.
So we give autonomy usually to people.
And sometimes we are frustrated that
we don't have the autonomy as leaders.
So that's why we are
fighting for autonomy.
Our leadership is thoughtful because
as introverted people and this
thinking introversion aspect if we
have it We think a lot about the
situations that we have with people.
We think about the people we are usually
Mindful about people so this thoughtful
leadership and then it moves us to the
conflict resolution and mediation some of
us Have this ability to resolve conflict.
So See and hear different opinions
and mediate between each other.
That's really important in the IT
environment, in the corporate environment.
And this is big additional
aspect that we have.
The innovation and
creativity in group projects.
So on one side, we don't want to or have
less tendency to talk a lot during group
projects, but at the same time, When we
have some thought in our head, creative,
innovative thought, we will explain that.
We'll tell, tell the people that.
It's so important for us that we will
add this creativity part to this group.
Obviously now if we are more
anxious, we may feel afraid of being
judged about this, this thought.
So that may be difficult, but if we
overcome this fear is a huge asset that
we bring to the table because we have some
innovative ideas that some other people
may not have because our brain just work
that way that we are so deeply focused.
We would love to think a lot about
the problems and then we can come
up with creative solutions and
building inclusive work cultures.
So if we are, if we are mindful about.
about people, about what they
feel, how they may be perceived.
We also can bring the
inclusive work culture.
Obviously, that's not one
on one, just like this.
But if the mindful aspect of our
quietness brings it as a possibility.
And obviously retrospection,
we love retrospection in our
Agile world and DevOps world.
We love retrospecting.
Do you want, do you know what I mean?
Do you like it?
Like, we love thinking about what,
especially what went wrong, right?
What doesn't work and so on.
But, but that it brings the
possibility to improve things as well.
. Alright.
and other benefits that I have here is
the benefits from the CEO perspective.
I work, from, with the
many CEOs executive levels.
And what are the benefits
they can have from you guys?
It's critical.
So the first benefit is critical missions.
Usually the company there
is one person, one engineer.
who has so big trust established
with the CEO or CTO that this is
a person from critical missions.
When CTO, for example, has the idea
to develop something or need to prove
something in front of the board, he or
she will not come to the team and say,
Hey, I know you have the agile process.
I have some requirements.
Could you put it and
prioritize it for me, please?
And so on.
He will or she will grab one
person who is very trustworthy.
We're ineligible and despite this person's
role, it's the, I mean, official title,
this person role is to develop, for
example, proof of concepts for CTOs.
It's not, again, it's not official,
it's not like a written role, but I
observed that every single executive
has this person in the company.
When they need some in depth research,
they will come to this person.
When they need a huge market analysis,
or deep market analysis, put it that
way, they will come to this person.
So this person is like a
sensor to the CEO or CTOs.
Losing this person is a big deal, so
they will not afford to lose this person.
Okay, what are the tools that
we can use for individuals?
There are some tools that
I use tips and tricks.
First things first, save the mental
energy before important meeting.
So when you have important
meeting, don't just plan.
And that was my my challenge
that I had before that I was
planning my day in the calendar.
So from time perspective,
do I have time for it?
Okay, I have.
And then, before very important
meeting that I had, I was dragged
into some conversation because I
had a time in calendar, but then I
realized that I lost a lot of energy.
And I didn't have this much energy
for my next important meeting.
So, save mental energy for those meetings.
Prepare for such meeting, I guess
that's obvious, but we need to
remember about that as well.
Come early before the meeting.
That's, usually very important
before big, bigger meetings.
Because when you come early,
you can, be, let's say, first
or second person in the meeting.
And then you have some time to adjust
your attitude or adjust your mood to
accommodate more contact with more people.
More people will be joining you.
They may ask you about, about something.
So you will not be the one, triggering
the conversation, which is also important.
involved in doing things
during large gatherings.
So when you are on the large, big
gathering, and you are afraid of
speaking with people, that's okay.
You can just Involve yourself in
some activities that are happening.
For example, if there's something
going on with the microphone
and someone is helping, someone
is setting up the microphone,
you can help him or her, right?
When there is something with the,
with the PC, the PC needs to be
established, needs to be set up.
You can help a person to set up a PC.
So, things like this.
And, have a, have an exit strategy.
So when you would like to leave
the meeting, remember before the
meeting to set up an exit strategy.
For example, I just can be one
hour on this meeting because
I need to do something else.
Or it's with the meeting is less
important because meetings are shorter.
But if you are on the conference,
for example, you can say,
okay, I need to be here.
I can be here for two
hours and then I can leave.
I need to pick up my daughter
from, from school, for example.
Or I need to do some email work.
And when you say it out loud, you
will hold yourself accountable
to say, Okay, two hours passed, I
need to, I need to run right now.
So that's the, one of the exit strategies.
Leverage music.
So, that's my tip.
What I do before huge conferences when
I'm a little bit stressed, I find myself,
some time, like two, three minutes,
and I listen to my beloved music.
And I'm just with, you know, with the
phone and with the headset, and that's it.
And then I can try to recharge
some energy before the talk.
And obviously no coffee
before intense meetings.
That's that's that's for me.
I don't know how you react on coffee
and caffeine, but I don't like over
stimulate my nervous system with a coffee.
What I do also is preparing
for social interactions.
So I prepare some, opening conversation.
For example, when I'm on the event, I
know what will be going on the event and
I can ask, Hey, what do you think about
the presentation that will be going next?
Are you interested in that?
And then it's, the
conversation starts flowing.
So prepare some openings like this.
and then, Cultivate deep relationships.
So I know that there are many
people's on the big events.
But if you cultivate deeper
relationships, then you will
spend more time with one person.
Obviously, not the whole event,
for example, with one person,
but more time with one person.
And then you can feel more relaxed in
terms of socialization with this person.
For leaders, don't assume that you know,
ask questions, show people's strengths.
For example, when there is a
calibration going on or when there is
a conversation about other people's
strengths, show that you know.
Hey, this guy from my team has
this, this and that strength.
I know that because I observe
him, I spoke with him.
So show that to others.
Provide the private spaces to people.
So when you have introverted people
in your team, it's okay for obviously
for you guys to sit alone and work.
Obviously, sometimes there are
meetings that you need to, grab
yourself together, but then sitting
alone, working, that's also fine.
focus on quality of the work, not on
the speed, and, offer multiple ways
to interact, not just face to face
meeting, but also Slack, but also, pull
requests, but also emails, all the things
that can, improve the interaction, but
it's not just like direct interaction.
speaking will help, but
obviously you need to have also
some time for direct speaking.
And the one thing that people like
the most is talking about themselves.
So not to be scared that you need to, as
an introverted person, need to talk a lot.
you can give people space
to talk about themselves.
You can just ask, hey, what
are you proud of recently?
And people are, they are proud of
something, so they will tell you
and you will be able to listen.
That's the trick.
The other trick that, I've heard is
to transform apologize to thank you.
So not just saying, you know,
apologize I didn't, attempt this
event or apologize I, I'm late.
But say thank you for, your patience.
Thank you for replying
to me on that email.
Practice that.
It's very helpful at the end.
just a couple of thoughts
about high sensitive people.
so, I found the research at 70 percent
of high sensitive people have the
introversion aspect, so high sensitive
people we have, we have, I say, because
I feel like high sensitive person,
our nervous system is more sensitive.
And obviously sensitivity
may lead to overstimulation.
When I have a lot of different stimulus
around, a lot of different conversations,
notifications, I can be overstimulated.
Or my nervous system
can be overstimulated.
But, Sensitivity might lead
to vulnerability as well.
And, not sure if you've heard about Brenna
Brown and her talk about vulnerability,
but she says that vulnerability, when we
show we really are, brings the creativity
as well, because then we are not afraid.
When we show, when I tell you, for
example, that I'm an introverted person
and I had challenges with speaking with
people in the past, I'm not afraid of this
situation, and then I'm more creative,
because I don't, I'm not afraid off
being judged so I can come up with off
or show you all the ideas that I have.
So that's how the vulnerability
is connected with creativity
and also with gratitude.
We can then appreciate every single
moment in life, which helps us.
Not only jobs, but also in
the, in our private life.
And at the end, I would like to leave
you with this long, but very important
quotation from Susan Cain from this book.
And I will read it for you.
The secret to life is to put
yourself in the right lightning.
For some, it's a Broadway spotlight.
For others, it's an amply desk.
Use your natural powers of persistence,
consideration, and insights.
To do the work you love
and work that matters.
Solve problems, make art, think deeply.
Thank you very much for today's time.
I wish you all the best in this
conference and let's stay connected.
If you feel that you would like to ask
about anything, just drop me a line on
the LinkedIn and I will respond to you.
Thank you very much.