Hello, everyone, and thank you for
joining me today at Conf42 DevOps.
My name is Andrea Andriushan.
I'm a DevOps engineer at Analog Devices,
and I'm excited to talk about how we've
optimized the release process for Analog
Devices custom Linux distribution.
Named KyperLinux.
The software development life
cycle is all about improvement.
Iteration by iteration.
Every stage, including the release
process, benefits from refinement.
When done effectively, this ensures
that products reach customers
faster, with higher reliability.
Today, I will show you how we applied
this principle to KyperLinux and
the substantial results it brought.
Now, you may ask, what's our
custom Linux distribution?
Well, Let's answer this question
and tell you about ADI KyperLinux.
Kyper is the primary distribution for
product evaluation boards, including
reference designs, device drivers, and
a variety of development utilities.
Now, let's see how we improved the
release process on this complex component.
By the end of this talk, we'll
gain insights into what was the old
release process for Hyperlinux in
order to have a better understanding
of the changes that were made.
and how they impacted the product and
which are some of the major improvements
that we needed to integrate and why.
And also the current state of
our custom Linux distribution.
The traditional process was slow,
rigid, and prone to delays due to
lack of modularity and the high
interdependence between components.
All the software components were
built during image creation,
which meant a longer build time.
Another reason for the long release cycles
was the fact that software components
were released through Kyper Linux image.
With no modularity, a bug found in one
of the components delayed all of them.
After we identified the big problems
of the previous flow, we came up with
a few ideas that we then implemented.
These key modifications were creating a
stabilization branch from release of each
core software component, breaking down the
monolith structure for a better management
of the Linux drivers, libraries, UA
application, and user space tools.
And creating Debian packaging for
components that were previously mentioned.
Modular configuration for custom images.
And based on the other changes
mentioned, we can configure easier
the image before build time.
expand component level testing
with custom docker images created
from a Kyper Linux build image.
Improvements were also made on the
CI side by moving the automatic build
on GitHub Actions and introducing
PR templates and co donors for a
better overview of the new changes.
To kick off the improvements, we
introduce a dedicated stabilization
branch for every new release.
This branch is created from the
main branch and serves as a space
where the release is refined,
tested, and stabilized without
interference from ongoing development.
This approach allows us to focus
on preparing the release while
the main branch continues to
accommodate new features and updates.
The result?
Faster issue resolution, more focused
testing, and a stable release pipeline.
Based on the diagram below, you
can see that the master branch
serves as the main development
branch for new features and fixes.
Our next stable branch is created
by branching off from master.
This branch is dedicated to stabilization.
Ensuring that the code is closely
tested and prepared for release.
Fixes and updates are often pushed
to both master and nexttable
simultaneously to maintain consistency.
Once the nexttable branch is
considered ready for release, a release
branch or tag is created from it.
In most cases, new bugs are
found during release testing.
That's why a release patch will be created
after the fix is added on the branch.
After a release is finished, the next
stable branch is overwritten with the
latest changes from master to sync and
prepare for the next stabilization cycle.
Next, we moved away from a
monolithic release process and
separated the entire release into
smaller independent components.
In the past, everything was bundled
together and a bug in one area
could delay the entire release.
Now, components like software
tools, libraries, and boot
files are managed independently.
By breaking down the release
this way, we've eliminated
unnecessary interdependencies.
Each component can be developed, tested,
and released on its own schedule, leading
to faster iteration and reduced risk.
For each software component,
Debian packages are created
as a release artifact.
After that, they're uploaded to
our Linux package repository.
By using standard Debian tools,
we've simplified distribution and
made it easier for users to install
or roll back software packages.
But one of the most significant
steps we've taken to increase
flexibility is the introduction
of a modular configuration file.
This file allows users to build
custom images by selecting
the specific tools they need.
And even specifying the
version of those components.
For instance, If you're working on
a project that requires a specific
library version, you can specify that
in the configuration file before build.
Additionally, we've made it
easy to introduce new components
or additional dependencies.
With the help of an extra script,
users can add other compatible tools.
This approach not only makes the release
process more modular, but also gives
users the freedom to craft their ideas.
images with their exact
requirements, ensuring that no
unnecessary components are included.
Now, to improve reliability and
compatibility, we've implemented
our robust testing process
that works at two levels.
First, each component is tested
individually to ensure its
stand alone functionality.
This allows us to quickly catch and
address issues specific to that component.
Second, the components are
tested as part of the full
Kuiper image, but with a twist.
We've introduced lighter Docker images
that are built with the specific
dependencies required for each component.
These Docker images replicate
the Kuiper environment during
the development process.
By testing within this controlled
environment, We can, we can ensure early
compatibility with the final system.
This approach allows us to catch
integration issues during development,
rather than later stages, which
saves significant time and effort.
And if you want to know more about
our testing process, my colleagues
have two presentations about it
at this year's edition of Conf42.
Thank you.
Bianca is presenting a secure integration
of private testing infrastructure
with public GitHub repositories.
And Stefan's topic is Advanced
Test Harness Infrastructure for
Validating ARM and FPGA based systems.
To optimize our CI pipeline and make
the development process more accessible
and efficient, we transitioned
from Jenkins to GitHub Actions.
This move brought several benefits.
First, BuildLogs are now
openly accessible to all users.
increasing transparency.
Additionally, fresh build images
are automatically generated and made
available on GitHub as soon as the commit
is merged into the Kuiper repository.
This eliminates the need for users
to wait for an official release or
manually build the image themselves.
We've also expanded the
build configurations.
Previously, we only built
a 32 bit full image.
Now, we've added support for 64
bit architectures and introduced
both basic and full configurations
for each architecture.
This flexibility ensures that
users can choose the image
that best suits their needs.
To further improve collaboration
and code quality, we introduced
a pull request template.
This provides a consistent structure for
a contributor to describe their changes.
Additionally, we've implemented
the co donors feature in GitHub.
This ensures that relevant team members
are automatically assigned to review
and approve pull requests, speeding
up the review process, and maintaining
high standards for the code base.
These changes make the build
process faster, more flexible,
and more user friendly.
while also encouraging better
collaboration among developers.
Now, let's take a closer look to the
current state of our release process.
By using a configuration file, users
can now create custom images mapped
to their specific requirements.
They can select only the
components they need, ensuring
lightweight and efficient builds.
We've also shifted to build
each component independently and
releasing it as a Debian package.
These packages are uploaded to
analog devices Linux package
repository, which allows for
faster and more flexible builds.
This change also simplifies updates
for users, making, making it easier to
install or rollback components as needed.
By dividing the release cycles.
of individual components, we've
ensured that bugs in one component
don't block their list for others.
This approach simplifies the overall
process, minimizes bottlenecks, and
increases development efficiency.
Now, in the end, thank you all
for listening, and if you have any
questions regarding the presentation,
or if you need more details
about it, feel Do not hesitate to
contact me on email or LinkedIn.
And thank you.