Speaker 44: Hi, I'm, and I want
to talk to you about something
that might make you uncomfortable.
Those screen check marks we all love
to see in our CICD pipelines where
all of the tests are passing views are
successful, everything looks perfect,
but here's the truth, sometimes
everything can look green while
serious problems are hiding underneath.
I've maintained and contributed to several
open source repositories, both small and
large, and I've seen what happens when
teams put too much trust in automation
and not enough in human judgment.
Today I'm going to show you
what CICD can't catch, and more
importantly, what we can do about it.
Now I'd like to start with a
story from March 29th, 2024.
Andres Fre, a Microsoft engineer, was
doing routine performance testing.
The SSH into a WN system
and noticed something odd.
Authentication was taking a few
hundred milliseconds longer than
it should, and CPU usage was
spiking during the handshake.
Now that might not sound like much when
something that should nearly be nearly
in San suddenly fail off experience.
Engineers need to pay attention.
When he investigated, he found
that the test were passing.
CICD pipeline was screen, and the
code had gone through normal review.
So from the automation's point
of view, everything looked fine,
but something was very wrong.
That disconnects between what our
pipelines tell us and what's actually
happening is what this talk is about.
But before we go further, I'd like to
establish why I'm talking about this.
My name is Soda.
I'm a software engineer and
program organizer at Outreachy.
And my role has involved coordinating
code reviews across multiple
open source projects, some with
hundreds of contributors and
lots of pull requests to review.
And at that scale, you
start to see patterns.
You see your automation works
brilliantly, and you see where
it completely falls apart.
You watch trusted contributors emerge.
Reviewers get overwhelmed and burnt out.
And green marks creates a
sense of false confidence.
That experience is what I'm
bringing to the talk today.
But I'd like to frame
the talk in three parts.
The why, what, and how
Now, why does this matter?
This matters because CICD
can show green pipelines.
While there are fragile assumptions,
risky changes, and subtle regressions,
that can still slip into production.
So the automation doesn't
tell the whole story.
Now what's the problem?
Automation forces the rules we defined,
but it can reason about intent.
It doesn't understand context or
pick up on social dynamics or notice
when reviewers are over loaded.
These human factors become
critical as systems and sim scale.
Now the question is how do we fix it?
We are going to explore parent
automation with female safeguards,
structured reviews, risk checklists.
Stage rollout and a culture
that rewards slowing down when
something feels uncertain.
Now, let me clear this up front.
This is not an anti automation talk.
I love CICD.
I know how powerful and necessary
it's, but at the same time,
it's not sufficient on its own.
And that's why we are here to explore.
Now, here's a scenario you've
probably lived through.
The tests are green.
Your bids are successful, your
deployments complete without errors.
Everything your automation can
measure says you are good to go.
And then your users
start to report issues.
Now, this is the moment that
makes us question everything.
We followed the process.
We did everything right according to our
tools, but something still went wrong.
So this gap between automation,
confidence and production reality,
that's what we need to understand.
So let's go back to that story from March
and actually understand what happened.
This wasn't just a performance bug.
The exit YouTube's backdoor incident
has been widely described as one of
the most significant and sophisticated
supply chain attacks that we've
seen publicly discussed, and it
wasn't found by a security scanner.
It was found during routine performance
testing because it's small anomaly
triggered a deeper investigation.
Let's take a look at the timeline.
In 2021, someone who called themselves,
Han appears in the ex UTS project.
They make helpful contributions,
nothing suspicious.
Just another contributor trying to help.
By 2022 and 2023, after a year of
consistent quality work, Han gets comp
coming access and becomes a maintainer.
This makes perfect sense because
they've proven themselves
through legitimate contributions.
Then in 2024, the back is
discovered completely by accident.
Now, let take a look
at what's this bypass.
All tests passed.
Code was reviewed.
CICD was greened.
And so the question is
what's actually filled here?
It wasn't the test, it
wasn't the automation.
What field was trust management at scale?
This was a social engineering attack
that understood something fundamental.
Automation checks code quality, but
humans are supposed to check intent.
The attacker knew that if you build
trust over years, if you become part
of a team, eventually people will stop
scrutinizing your changes as carefully
because you've gained their trust.
This is the blueprint for
attacking software at scale.
Now, lemme break down what's
actually enabled this attack, because
it's not what you might think.
First, the maintainer was
overloaded and stretched thing.
Now, this is a common open source problem.
It's one maintainer and hundreds
of contributors, thousands of lines
of code to review, and eventually
maintainers get burnt out.
Second, subtle changes
slip through that time.
It wasn't one obvious factor.
It was incremental changes that
individually looked harmless.
Third.
A long, trusted contributor had
gained significant influence, years of
legitimate contributions, had built real
trust, and that trust was weaponized.
And finally, which is the
critical point, automation did
not see the social dynamics.
It couldn't detect that trust was being
systematically built and then exploited.
He couldn't notice that review
quality was degrading under pressure.
So these are human problems.
Cultural problems, organizational
problems, and no amount of automated
testing catches these issues.
So why do we fall into this trap?
Why do green check marks give
us such false confidence?
Therefore, main reasons.
First, green check.
Green checks feel like certainty.
There's that visual feedback that
is psychologically satisfying.
It gives us confidence.
Sometimes modern is warranted.
Second team scale faster
than review capacity.
You can hire 10 engineers and they
start Monday, but building 10 experience
reviewers that takes years review
capacity, lags behind team growth.
So we use CI as a approach.
Third deadlines push speed over caution.
When the pressure is on CI person
becomes the only approval gates
that really matters, it's green.
So we ship it and that becomes the reflex.
Fourth, we confus necessary with
sufficient CI passing is a necessary
condition for shipping code, but we treat
it like it's a sufficient condition.
It's not, and this is a logic
error that we make constantly.
If you've ever approved a pr,
mainly because CI will scream and
you're rushing, you'll be able to
understand this problems really well.
But before we go, define into the
problems, let's be precise about
what CICD actually does, because
this framing is very important.
CICD answers one question really well.
Does this code meet the rules we defined?
Does it compile?
Does the pass our test, follow our
style guide, satisfy our LinkedIn rules?
CIC is brilliant at
answering those questions.
It's deterministic, consistent, and
fast, but here's what it doesn't answer.
Is this change safe in the real world?
That's a very different question from
meeting from the question about meeting.
The rules that have been defined requires
judgments, context and understanding
what goes beyond the understanding
that goes beyond what we cannot admit.
So we need to stop treating
these as the same question.
Now lemme be absolutely clear.
And repeat.
Again.
I love CICD.
I think it's one of the best things
that has happened to software
engineering in the last 20 years,
because look at what it gives us.
Repeatable, reliable, build, same
input, same outputs every single time.
Consistent checks and LinkedIn style
enforcement and basic quality checks
are all automatic automated testing,
progression prevention at scale.
This alone has saved countless hours
and prevented countless books, faster
Deployments we can ship multiple
times a day instead of once a quarter.
This is transformative.
Reduce human error.
No more forgetting manual steps
or skipping items on deployments.
Checklists, this is all
revolutionary and because of
CICD that we are able to do this.
So CICD is very necessary.
I cannot begin to stress that enough.
But necessary doesn't mean sufficience,
and that's the key distinction
that we need to internalize.
Now, let me show you what CICD
fundamentally cannot catch.
Not because it's poorly configured,
but because these things are outside.
Its scope by design.
Number one, social engineering.
A trusted contributor changes employers.
Their priorities and their motivations
have shifted, but their trust level in
your repository stays exactly the same.
CICD can detect this.
Number two, subtle
performance regressions.
Your query works perfectly
with clean test data.
When production with millions of
rules, it does a table scan that
crushes your database test pass,
or production brand number three.
Integration behavior across system.
Your service passes all its tests.
It works great in isolation, but
in production, it causes timeouts
in three downstream dependencies.
Your test environment doesn't run about
number four, UX and workflow mismatches.
The feature works.
It does exactly what expect said, but
it completely breaks the user's mental
model of how the system should work.
Users are confused and frustrated,
but all of the tests are passing.
Number five, risky dependency changes.
You upgrade a library,
the upgrade is fine.
It brings in new transited
dependencies with non vulnerabilities
that your scanner miss because it
only checks direct dependencies.
Number six, misconfigurations
that look harmless.
You change one environment's very.
This is completely fine.
In staging, in production, under
real load, it causes memory
leak takes hours to surface.
Every single one of these is a predictable
systemic gap in what automation can
detect, and these are not edge cases.
These happen constantly.
Now let me show you something that
explains why the XE attack worked and why
these problems get worse as projects grow.
Trust doesn't scale linearly.
It breaks up predictable
points at five contributors.
Personal trust works perfectly.
You know everyone, you understand
their code style, their
judgments, their motivations.
Review is straightforward because
you have context for everything.
At PIP c contributors,
people are semi known.
You recognize the regulars, but
there are people you've never met.
Friction starts.
Okay.
Review takes longer because
automatic trust is gone.
At 500 contributors, your trust
model is completely broken.
Most prayers come from strangers.
You have no idea about their
motivations, background or skill
level, but you still need to
review and decide whether to merge.
This is where the exit ER was.
They were overwhelmed dealing with
hundreds of contributors burning outs.
That's when appeared with
the years of legitimate
contributions and offered to help.
So here's the paradox.
As your project succeeds and grows the
trust model that enabled that success
becomes your biggest vulnerability.
So why do these problems get
worse over time instead of better?
First, more contributors
equals more assumptions.
Every new person brings
different standards, background
knowledge, and risk tolerance.
Implicit understands in stone
transfer, they don't scale.
Second, automation
hides fragile processes.
When CI is green, it creates false
confidence that everything is fine.
Problems in your process, culture
and trust management become invisible
because your automation is passing.
So green check marks effectively
hide systemic dysfunction.
Third review becomes robust stamping.
Robust stamping.
When reviewers are overloaded with ETPs
in the queue, review becomes a checkbox.
CI passes.
CI Pass becomes the only criteria.
So you're not really reviewing
anymore, you're just making
the queue number go down.
Fourth, trust grows
faster than oversights.
We grant access based on velocity of
contribution as not the depth of review.
So someone makes 20 small PR that
look fine, do they get me rights?
Did anyone actually audit
those changes deeply?
Probably not.
So these aren't individual failures.
These are systemic dynamics that
emerge predictably as teams grow.
Now let's talk about the
organizational pressures that
make all of this worse pressure.
What review cues are a
hundred prs are waiting.
They are more coming.
Daily reviewers become the bottleneck.
Complaints starts about slow reviews.
Quality suffers under volume.
Pressure to approvals happen
under that time pressure.
The deadline is tomorrow.
The project manager is asking for updates.
The CEO mentioned this feature to
the board, so he start to approve.
Thankfully, understanding trust
in the test, caught any issues.
Pressure three, just ship.
It becomes a norm.
Speed becomes a dominance metric.
Velocity deployment frequency, cycle
time, these get measured and rewarded.
Caution is not something that appears on
the dashboard, so it stops being valued.
Pressure four, maintenance
becomes reactive.
All energy goes to firefighting.
There's no time for prevention,
process improvement or learning.
You are always in crisis mode,
cutting corners and skipping steps.
These pressures are universal.
So the question now is, do
your safeguards still work?
Despite these pressures, what
are the first thing that gets
sacrificed when pressure increases?
So let me show you specific processes
that break under pressure First
single reviewers for critical code.
One person approves
authentication changes.
One person owns payment processing.
One person handles infrastructure
when they are overwhelmed or on
vacation or leave the company.
All of that knowledge works out the door.
Second, unwritten tribal knowledge.
The rule rules and documented new
reviewers don't know which areas are
dangerous, which patterns are banned,
which shortcuts are acceptable.
Critical context exist only
in senior people's heads.
Third informal rules about approvals.
Who can approve votes?
It depends on what, on who you ask.
Trust is granted inconsistently, nobody
is quite sure what the actual standard is.
Fourth, no ownership for risky areas.
Security.
Infrastructure, data migrations,
performance critical code.
Everyone assumes someone else is
watching carefully, but ueah is nobody
is because nobody was assigned to.
Everyone just assumed someone else would.
This tribal knowledge problem
is nearly universal and it's
invisible until it breaks.
So we've talked so much about problems.
Let's talk about solutions.
I'm going to give you a
framework built on three pillars.
Think of these as complementary to
automation, not replacement for it.
Pillar one, review practices how you
actually review code, who reviews
what and what standards you apply.
Pillar two, process the structural and
technical safeguards you put in place
to catch what human review might miss.
Pillar three.
Culture, the attitudes, incentives,
and norms that determine whether
people actually use these
practices or route around them.
Under pressure, all three
need to work together.
Great process without culture
creates ignored processes.
Great culture if that process
doesn't scale, and neither works
if your review practices are weak.
So let's explore each one first.
Pillar.
Review practices are actually scale.
Here are four things you
can implement immediately.
Number one, second reviewer.
For high risk areas, things like
authentication, payments, security,
critical code, these need two
sign-offs from people with relevant
expertise, and this should be a
non-negotiable for critical paths.
Number two.
We teach reviewers to
avoid power concentration.
Don't let the same person review
the same author twice in your row.
Fresh eyes catch patterns, and this
prevents both intentional gaming of
trust like we saw in XC and unintentional
drift with standards gradually relax.
Number three, use risk checklist
before merge, before clicking,
merge, answer a series of questions.
Does this search both?
The new dependencies is
this is rollback simple.
Multiple yes answers signal
you should slow down.
Number four, separate fast
lane versus slowing peers.
Not everything means the same scrutiny.
Things like documentation, fixes, test
improvements, refactor full coverage.
These can move fast.
New things like new features, dependency
upgrades, performance optimizations.
These can move slower, so make this
distinction explicit and systematic.
So the key insight here
is not all code is equal.
Not all reviewers are equal, and
not all circumstances are equal.
You need differentiation.
One size fits all doesn't work at scale.
Second pillar.
Cultural safeguards.
This is where most organizations fail.
We can have great processes,
but if culture doesn't support
them, people route around them.
First thing, normalize asking
questions make I don't understand.
Can you explain?
Completely acceptable in code review.
It's not a sign of weakness or slowness.
It is a sign that you're
doing your job properly.
Number two, reward
caution, not just speed.
If your metrics focus only on velocity,
if bonuses are tied only to how fast
deployments are made, and if only the
engineers shipping the most features
get promoted, what behavior are you
incentivizing explicitly reward people
who catch issues before production.
Number three, document issues openly
when you make a technical choice.
Accept a trade off or wa a
requirement, write it down in the pr.
Whether it's in a commit message or design
doc, make sure that reasoning is visible.
And reviewable.
Number four, pair review trick.
Pair review.
Tricky changes for
genuinely complex peers.
Like things like major refactoring,
architectural changes, subtle
bug fixes have to reviewers
work together synchronously.
That way you can catch more
issues, share knowledge, and build
common understanding of quality.
Culture, its process every time.
So if your culture says, just ship it,
your processes won't be able to save you.
Now this slide is my
favorite in the entire deck.
The risk checklist you
can start using today.
So before merging any pier,
answer these questions.
Does this touch sensitive areas in the
projects like off or infrastructure?
Are any new dependencies being added?
Are had to test code paths changed.
Is back simple.
Is reviewer new to this area?
Does this rely on tribal knowledge?
Are we merging under time pressure?
What could go wrong if we are wrong?
Now, here's the key, yes.
Answers don't mean don't merge.
They mean slow down.
Get a second reviewer.
Add monitoring.
Plan the robot procedure.
Document your assumptions,
maybe even stage deployments.
That last question is the most important.
What could go wrong if we are wrong?
If you can't answer that question,
you probably don't understand the
change well enough to approve it.
So the goal isn't to prevent oral risks.
It's making risks explicit and conscious
instead of implicit and invisible.
Third pillar.
Technical and process safeguards
that extend CICD to catch what tests.
Count number one, canary deployments.
So don't go, don't just go straight
from test pass to deploy to everyone.
Deploy to 1% of traffic first.
Monitor it.
Watch for errors, performance issues,
user complaints, and scale up gradually.
Two post deployment smoke checks
after deployment automatically
run checks against production.
Are users able to log in?
Can they complete critical workflows?
Our response times normal.
These catch integration
issues that test myness.
Number three, monitoring types releases.
Every deployment should create
markers in your monitoring system.
This makes it easier to see if
error speed rates spiked after that.
Deploy.
Number four, dependency
and normally alerts.
When someone adds or grades a
dependency, automatically check How
many other dependencies does this bring?
How old are they?
Are there any known vulnerabilities?
How many maintainers this
catches supply chain risks before
they become X level problems.
Number five, error budgets
and rule back triggers.
Define them in advance.
If error rates exceed X
automatically rule back.
Latency exceeds.
Why Automatically roll back, no discussion
needed, just automatic roll back and
then investigate apps stopping depleting.
These aren't expensive or complicated.
They're systematic application
of one principle, which is
testing production or carefully.
Now let me show you what this
looks like in practice before
the PR arrives, tests run.
Merge.
Deploy four steps very fast or fragile.
Now, this is what our
after is looking like.
PR arrives, tests, run risk check
happens using our checklist.
Then it goes to appropriate
reviewers based on risk level,
then stage deployments, canary
first and gradual rollouts.
Then monitoring during rollouts
with automatic rollback triggers.
More steps.
Yes.
Slower maybe.
But here as what matters, low risk changes
still move fast through the fast link.
The only thing you've added is
overhead where risk justifies it.
And critically, you've also created
multiple opportunities to catch
issues before the cause problems.
This is defense in depth.
No single safeguard is perfect,
but the combination makes it much
harder for issues to sleep through.
You are not slowing everything down.
You are just select, you are just being
selective about where you add rigor.
So lemme bring this full
circle with four takeaways.
One, CICD is necessary but not sufficient.
Automation is powerful, essential,
but it's not the whole answer.
Two.
Risk grows quietly as project skill.
What works at five
contributors fails at 500.
So you need to be able to actively adapt
three people and process fill the gaps.
Automation counts, intent,
context, trust, judgments.
These require human solutions,
not just technical ones.
Four.
Safeguards don't need to slow delivery.
You can maintain velocity
while improving quality.
They are not in opposition.
Remember Andre's front on March
29th, 2024, he noticed something
that all of the automation risks,
not because he was smarter than
tests, not because he had better
tools, but because he stayed curious.
He questioned the green check marks.
That's what saved us from Execut.
Human curiosity, human
judgment, human caution.
So your automation will
keep getting better.
Your C-I-S-C-D will keep evolving,
but it'll never replace the
human who asks, wait, why?
When something feels off, build systems
that supports that human, that's how we
are able to build resilience software.
Thank you so much for watching.
I hope this has given you concrete ideas
to try with your own teams, and if you'd
like to discuss any of this further, you
can find me on LinkedIn and X as soda.
Thank you so much.