Hi, I'm Hemang and I'm a
software developer at amazon.
com.
I have a lot of experience in working
with machine learning models, which are
tasked to identify intellectual property.
such as logos, copyrights, or trademarks.
I worked on how to fine tune ML models,
how to recompile them, how to deploy
them in cloud environments at scale,
you know, to the likes of 20, 000,
transactions per second and setting up.
Human assisted AI frameworks, to enable
iterative development of ML models
and also improvement in precision
and recall of IP monitoring systems.
So today I'm excited to give a talk on how
human assisted AI is revolutionizing the
intellectual property monitoring space.
we'll talk about how human expertise,
along with machine learning models,
basically cutting edge AI, can help
improve the precision, recall, and
scalability of IP monitoring systems,
thereby allowing, organizations
to stay ahead of the curve and
protect their intellectual property.
Protecting intellectual property is one
of the key challenges and one of the
most important challenges for companies.
Estimates show that globally
companies take a one trillion dollar
loss due to use of counterfeit
goods and copyright infringement.
what we've seen is that in the
last few years, this number has
been exponentially increasing.
And that's majorly because of newer and
innovative techniques or technologies
that are available to bad actors.
one of which is Gen AI.
we've seen bad actors use generative AI
to quickly, you know, generate content
that's, infringing on intellectual
property of organizations and put it
out there on the web and, you know,
other channels, other media, and,
and thereby, you know, these, the
losses have just been increasing.
So because of these.
Companies need advanced systems which
actively monitor for, you know, illegal
use of their IPs and, take action.
This is where AI comes into the picture.
There are numerous models available
out there for different use
cases that companies can use.
in the IP detection space,
let's go over some of them.
One of the, one of the techniques is
to perform embedding based searches.
as opposed to keyword based searches,
embedding based searches are far
superior because, they're inherently
performing semantic searches, whereas
key keyword based searches are naive and
basically just string searches, right?
so.
There are models, such as the CLIP
model or, OpenAI's Dolly, which
helps generate embeddings for images.
These models can be used to convert
any entity, you know, such as text,
or an image into vector representation
or something that we call embeddings.
And these embeddings would have all the
contextual understanding of the entity.
Similarly, you generate embeddings
of your query, your search query,
and perform a similarity search.
So this can be used for, you know, use
cases such as identifying similar images
and similar content to detect potential
infringements of your copyrights.
another method is using
natural language processing.
There are state of the art models
such as BERT and Roberta, which
are amazing in analyzing text.
So these models can be used to, you know,
if I were to give an example, identify if
the usage of the term apple in a sentence.
is in context to the fruit
apple or the company apple.
such use cases can help analyze
text for copyright violations
or trademark infringements.
then we have the vision suite of models.
there are models such as
the YOLO family of models.
YOLO stands for you only look once.
so the YOLO V5 or YOLO V7 models and
the newer models such as the VIT models,
also, short for vision transformers.
These models are really good in
analyzing an image holistically.
so these can analyze image
and detect unauthorized use of
logos, trademarks, and so on.
Then comes the large,
large language models.
In the last two to three years.
Large language models
have picked up immensely.
There's been a boom going on and these are
basically models which have been trained
on humongous amount of data, almost to
the likes of the entire internet, right?
so these models have, these models
have enough context already.
They can be used to solve
really complex problems.
You can just give it a research paper
and ask it to do a plagiarism check.
Or you could give them, give these
models an image and ask the model to
identify, you know, if the image has
illegal use of a brand's logo and so on.
But AI has its own limitations as well.
AI cannot use, cannot be used
in standalone because there's
only so much it can do.
Artificial intelligence is excellent
at detecting known patterns and
statistical anomalies, but it does
not do really well in the unknown.
if I were to give you an example,
for example, let's take LLMs,
LLM being trained on, you know,
almost The entire internet's data.
It would be really good in identifying,
you know, the use of Nike's logo or
adidas's logo, but if tomorrow I were
to launch my own company and create
a create my own logo LLM would not be
able to identify the use of my company's
logo in you know, images all over the
internet because It would not have
been trained on On on the data which
includes my logo, right so ML models
can only perform in cases where, they
have context or they have, the, the,
the knowledge on taking decisions.
the other problem that, you know, LLMs is.
The problem of hallucination, for the same
query, for the same request, it can give
you different answers in different times.
Then, you know, that's when these are
cases where, the LLMs or models are not
confident enough to take a decision.
So human expertise.
A human is far, has far more
superior contextual understanding
and can take judgment in complex
situations whereas the AI cannot.
So what we propose is a amalgamation
of human expertise along with
AI's capabilities to create IP
monitoring systems that are superior
in terms of precision and recall.
A very basic, approach to this
would be, you know, a human machine
collaboration where you let the machine
take potential decisions, you let
the machine take, make inferences,
but you do not take, decisions.
automated actions based on,
you know, just the ML model.
Let the machine learning
model give you an output.
And then a human reviews the output
of this machine learning model.
So when I say human, it would be
an expert in that domain who is,
flagging and, Re verifying the
output of the machine learning model.
So based on the human output, you
can take actions, for the certain
situation, for the situations.
And also now you have a golden
set of data that can be used
to fine tune your ML model.
And create the next
version of your ML model.
So this is what we call active learning
where the machine or the model is
actively learning from the human.
There are two main advantages
of active learning.
One is improvement in precision and
the other is improvement in recall.
By improvement in precision, what
I mean is the model is now better.
at tasks which it was previously good at.
So say there are situations which the
model was able to identify, but there was
some false positives, in the output of
the model, which was audited by the human.
The next version of the model will
no longer have these false positives.
So the model has now become
better in situations which
it was doing okay at before.
This is what we call
improvement in precision.
Improvement in recall is basically
the model is now able to identify
new patterns, which it was
previously not even able to detect.
So these are better edge case
handling that the model is able
to do in the newer versions.
If I were to give an example, say
we have a logo detection model.
the model was previously able
to accurately identify logos
of brand X, but not of brand Y.
The human audits the data and
annotates the images with, which
have the logos of brand Y as well.
This data is fed back into the model and
the next version of the model is trained.
The new version of the model will
now be able to identify logos
of both brand X and brand Y.
So these are newer situations that
the model is now able to identify.
So this is what we call
improvement in recall.
what we generally see is when we
compare, you know, just a ML model,
in contrast to a framework where
we have a human AI, human AI setup.
in the human AI setup, we generally
see that there's a 20 percent increase
in precision and almost a 25 percent
improvement in recall over time.
And these numbers just keep increasing.
Increasing with more the
number of iterations there are.
So how do we make this human
AI framework more scalable?
There are two components to it, right?
the human component and the AI component.
To make the AI component scalable, the
best strategy would be to deploy your
machine learning workloads on the cloud.
There are multiple cloud service providers
out there, such as Microsoft Azure, Amazon
Web Services, Google Cloud Platform, and
these have numerous services, which are
at your disposal, available out of the
box for, different parts of this pipeline.
for example, they offer compute
services where you can containerize
your machine learning workloads.
Or, ML code and deploy it on
instances which can be auto
scaled based on your traffic.
At times of peak, the number of ML
instances increase, and then there's
no peak or there's hardly any traffic.
Your ML instances threat use, this is not
really possible in on premise solutions.
they offer a lot of data
integration services as well.
So you could host all your human
audit data on, NoSQL databases in the
cloud and this, these databases can
automatically be ingested or linked
to your machine learning, instances
or machine, machine learning pipelines
on the cloud, which act, and this data
could act as the training data for
every, every new version of the model.
Now, how can we make the system scalable?
from the human angle.
The goal over here is to reduce dependency
on the human as much as possible.
And the human should have the least
number of human touch points as possible.
so what happens is that over time with
few, few iterations of the system and
few model versions, you would see that
the model is performing really well
with high precision and high recall.
in certain use cases.
for example, if I had a logo detection
model, the My model would start performing
really well in identifying logos on
shoes But it might not be very well on
identifying logos on bags so now A human
no longer needs to see the output of the
model For where all the images are that
of shoes because you have a high accuracy
in that Product category, and you're going
to let the model take automatic decisions
and actions for those categories.
So what you then do is you let the AI flag
what is important for a human to review.
So in the shoes category, you would
let AI to take automated actions.
But in the backs category, you would
park all the decisions for human audit.
You would, accumulate all the human
audits across all the different
product categories, which the model
is not able to accurately determine.
And then you would have an algorithm
that prioritizes the human audit.
You would pick, you know, categories
that are important for your use case,
and then let the human only review
those use cases or those, audits.
Okay.
And so now you have technically reduced
the number of audits that a human
has to do, and you feed that into the
next version of the model training.
So thereby you have now reduced
the dependency on the human as well
and made the system more scalable.
by doing this, by offloading, you know,
What we generally see is by offloading
40 percent of the workload from the
human, you're still able to maintain
95 percent of precision in most cases.
So, yeah, in a nutshell, the
human assisted AI, combination.
Has a lot of benefits, especially for
brand protection and IP monitoring.
we see improved precision, high amount of,
recall and very less false positive rates
than, you know, a human assists an AI.
So what should be the mental model
of someone who is implementing
a human assisted AI framework
for IP detection use cases.
So step one is to.
Assess the entire IP, IP evaluation
framework as it stands today.
Identify which parts of your system
are good at taking automated decisions,
and which parts are not that good
and need some input from the human.
because only the parts which have
high false positive rates, would
be the parts where, Step 3 would be
to develop an integration strategy,
which basically means that, like,
where would a human audit the data?
You would need some sort of a user
interface which outputs, which
displays the output of the model
and where, where human auditors
can come and audit the data.
All you then need to figure out what the
output data of this audit would look like.
And it should be seamlessly
integrated with the ML model.
What the, the form of input that the
training of the ML model can take so
that all of this output is readily
fed into the system, for training
of the next version of the model.
You would then have to train the
teams on how to audit this data
and finally train your ML models.
The audit and, retraining of the model
should be monitored and repeatedly
iterated over to see like which
parts of the system you have achieved
the accuracy that you want so that
human test points can now be removed
from those parts of the pipeline.
So yeah, that was the end of my talk.
thank you so much for attending my talk
and feel free to, reach me on LinkedIn if
you have any further questions about this.
Thank you.