Speaker 6: Hello everyone, and
thank you for joining me today.
My name is Baska.
I'm a senior developer and team lead.
I am also an I Triple E Senior member
with the Southeastern Michigan section.
Over the past 15 years, I have
been working on CI ICD pipeline,
develop automation and enterprise
scale software delivery systems.
Today I want to talk about, shift
that is quietly, but fundamentally
changing our industry, how the
software is written, how it's
delivered, and how it must be secured.
The title of this session is
Shift Left shield A Ecop Playbook
for AI Era, CICD Pipeline.
This is a practical blueprint
for securing the modern pipelines
without compromising the speed.
In the last few years, tools like
GitHub copilot or and Chan GTP, have
moved from being experimental helpers
to everyday development companions.
They write code, generate, test,
create scripts, and E one suggests
the infrastructure configurations.
That acceleration is exciting, but
it also introduce a new reality.
Our pipeline are now trusting the
code that no signal single human,
fully wrote or reviewed end-to-end.
So the question I would like to
us to explore today is simple.
How do we secure the software
when the software is increasingly
written by the machines?
For decades, software
security was built on.
A basic assumption.
Code is written by the humans.
We hired the developers, train
them, receive their codes,
and held them accountable.
Today that assumption has changed.
AI assisted coding and automated
code generation have fundamentally
transformed the software development
tools like GitHub, copilot and chat GTP.
Now write the significant
portion of the production code.
This dramatically accelerate the delivery,
but it also introduced the security
challenges that traditional DevSecOps
practices were never designed to handle.
The attack surface has exposed
expanded beyond the human return code.
AI generator snippets.
Automated dependency updates and
machine learn configuration now
flow through the pipelines often
without the scrutiny they deserve.
Understanding these new threats
vectors is first step towards building
the resilience resilient, and the
secure CICD system in the AI era.
This slide highlights the new risk that
comes with the AI assisted development.
First prompt injection attacks.
Malicious actors can manipulate the AI
coding assistant through the carefully
crafted comments and documentation,
causing them to generate the vulnerable
code or expose the sensitive data.
Second, training data poisoning.
AI models trained on a public repositories
may learn and reproduce this insecure
patterns, duplicated libraries, or
even the hardcoded credentials that
slipped into the training data.
Third, automated dependency confusion.
When AI suggests package names,
attackers can exploit the typo, sweating
to insert the malicious libraries
directly into the build pipeline.
And finally, osculated malicious code.
AI generated code reviews may miss
the sophisticated obs techniques
that experience the human
reviewers would normally flag.
These risks are not hypothetical.
They are already appearing in a modern
supply software supply chain attacks.
The
impact of the previous slide
mentioned risk is already visible.
The recent industry research shows
that 78% organizations have experienced
at least one software supply chain
SEC security incident in past years.
At the same time, AI tools now generate
an estimated 40% of a new enterprise code.
That means potential blast
radius of compromised AI assisted
workflow has never been hired.
Traditionally, security gates catch known
vulnerabilities, but they are blind to the
subtle risk embedded in AI generated code.
The real challenge today is not
just preventing that bad code, it is
ensuring that traceability, maintaining
the provenance, and building the
confidence in a, in and increasingly
automated development workflow.
In simple terms, we must prove what we
deploy is what we intended to build.
Please bring us to the foundation
Shift left Security shift left means
embedded security directly into
the development workflow instead of
adding it at the end of the pipeline.
This slide highlights the three key
principles, secure by design, embedding
the security directly into the
development workflows, early detection.
Identifying and remaining the
vulnerability as early as possible.
Automated enforcement, automating
the security policy enforcement.
Shifting left means production protection
is built into every development phase.
From realtime code scanning to
dependency, validation, making
security strong, yet seamless for
the developers, the goal is simple.
Security should feel natural
to the developers, not like
an external checkpoint.
When done correctly, developers
move fast, and security keeps
space silently in the background.
To test the software, we must know
exactly what goes into the every
build and where it came from.
This slide combined two critical ideas.
Software build of materials
means SBOs and build provenance.
First.
SBO generates the comprehensive machine
readable list of every dependency
and build time to use to build it.
When responses are generated automatically
and integrated with the vulnerability
databases, we gain the immediate
visibility into the supply chain.
Risk policies can then enforce which
components are allowed into our pipeline.
Second Bill Provenance uses the SLSA
frameworks to create the verifiable
records of who built an artifact when it
was built and under what condition signed.
Bill Attestations are immutable.
Go along ensures the artifact reaching
the production is exactly what was
built with no tampering in between.
In simple, Toms SBOs tells
us what is inside provenance
tells us where it came from.
Together they establish the
trust in a software delivery.
Once we have the visibility
and the provenance, we need
a consistent enforcement.
Policy as a code frameworks
defines the security requirement
as version and testable code.
We define the policy in a code.
We test the policy logic in A-C-I-C-D.
We enforce the policy at commit,
build, deploy, and run time, and
we audit and refine them over time.
This ensures the security enforcement is
consistent, repeatable, and automated.
Without slowing down the
developers, security becomes
engineering, not the paperwork.
System are high value targets.
If attackers com compromise a built
environment, they gain the perfect
position to inject the malicious
score into every artifact we ship.
Hardening requires the
multiple layers of defense.
Container isolation ensures each
build runs in a clean, imperial
environment with the minimal privileges.
Infrastructure as a code makes the build
configuration auditable and reproducible.
Artifact signing creates the
cryptographic proof that the artifact
have artifacts hasn't been tampered with.
After the build together, these
controls the significant, significantly
reduce the build system risk.
This slide shows how infrastructure
as a code strengthens the security
build environment should be
destroyed and recreate for every job.
Preventing the persistent compromises
build processes must follow
least privileged access using the
scope credentials and realtime.
A time limited tokens network should be
segmented, isolating the build system
from production and limiting the external
connectivity to the approved sources.
These control prevent the persistent
attack and limit the lateral
movement inside the infrastructure.
Modern CICD platforms runs.
Run build is disposable
container environment.
This prevents the attacker
persistence and limit the blast
areas if the build is compromised.
Complementing the isolation artifact
signing, using loop tools like
co-sign or sign store established
the cryptographic proof that
artifacts hasn't been tempered with.
After the bill only verified and
authorized artifact or artifacts proceeds
through the pipeline into the production.
Key insight, isolation limits.
The blast radius signing provides
the very favorable providence.
Together they provide the
defense in depth for software.
Supply chain
security is only about, is not
only about the prevention, it
is also about the detection.
This slide shows the
monitoring across the pipeline.
The code commit, scan code
and validate the signature.
Add the dependency
resolution, purify the checks.
Sum and detect the typo.
Add build execution.
Monitor for anomalies and ex
exploitation and artifact publishing.
Validating the his poem and
provenance add deployment.
Enforce the signature and policy checks.
This creates the continuous visibility
across the entire software lifecycle.
Here we see the real world indicators
of supply chain manipulation, behavioral
anomalies, such as unusual bill
duration, unexpected network traffic
or unauthorized changes to build the
scripts Technical indicators such as
unsigned commits, mismatched package
checksums, missing SBOs data or
artifacts without valid provenance.
These patterns allows.
Teams to detect manipulation teams
before they reach the production
For Dave SecOps to be sustainable
security must be fast automated
and seamlessly integrated.
We shift security into the IDE, so
issues are caught before the commit.
We parallelized security scans
with the functional test.
We provide the actionable feedback
so developers know exactly
how to mitigate the problems.
This ensures a strong protection without
blocking the developer's productivity.
A strong security program is measurable.
We aim to detect the issues in
under two minutes, limited the
vulnerabilities in under 10 minutes.
Maintain nearly hundred percent artifact
signature coverage and achieve zero supply
chain Indic incidents in production.
These metrics demonstrate how security
enhances delivery velocity through
the automation and fast feedback.
These slides summarize
the practical approach.
Start with SBOs and provenance.
Implement the policy as a
code hard build systems.
Monitor for anomalies
and major and iterate.
Security posture must evolve to
match the AI assisted automated
and faster software sub delivery.
AI assisted development.
Is here to, automation will only grow.
That means our security
practices must evolve with it.
When we shift left, we build the
security into the development.
When we shift right, we protect the
production with the variable trust.
This is how we move fast without losing
the confidence, integrity, or trust.
Thank you so much for your time.
I truly appreciate your attention today.
If you have any questions, thoughts,
or would like to continue this
conversation, this is my LinkedIn profile.
Please feel free to connect with me.
I would be happy to stay,
connect stay in touch.
Thank you so much.