Speaker 25: Oh, my name is Ika.
I'm a senior consultant at Microsoft.
Today, I will walk through practical
ways to reduce alert storms and
improve meantime to respond in
your security operation center.
The presentation slides and information I
share today present my own personal view.
I'm speaking for myself and not on behalf
of my employee, Microsoft Corporation.
Today is about speed and sanity.
We all know the feeling of the SOC
or other on-call engineers get built
in alerts and the truly important
signal arrives disgusted as noise.
This deck is a particular pipeline
that turns through alerts into fast,
consistent resolution using only
Microsoft Native building blocks.
We'll walk through four stage
first correlation group related
alerts into a single incident to
responders walk coherent case.
Second first mile automation the
safe, repeatable steps you should do.
The moment an incident is created
like enrichment and the routing.
Third AI systems are using security
pilot to summarize answer questions
and generate recommended actions.
So analysis time collapses.
Fourth measurement, an executive
score cut that shows MTTR Time set
by automation and trend lines that
per roof improvements over time.
So by then you should have a blueprint
you can implement incrementally.
Start small to measure, then expand.
So here is the path.
We start with the why.
Alert storms are not just annoying.
They directly inflate MTTR
because humans spend time charging
noise instead of a soft impact.
Then we go through the pipeline
as a simple mental model.
So correlate alerts into incidents,
automate the safe first steps, use AI to
accelerate analysis and measure outcomes.
Next, we'll zoom in on correlation
across three surfaces sentinel
correlation and fusion.
Four multi-stage attacks, the
founder XDR incident, correlation,
and merging across endpoint identity
email and cloud app signals.
And for us, RE Azure Monitor
Smart Groups that cluster related
alerts to reduce paging noise.
After that, we look at first mile
automation, where logic apps, playbook,
scandal, enrichment, dedupe, and routing.
So we'll then add security pilot as
an analysis accelerator, so summaries,
guided responses and natural language
that trans questions into KQL and hunting.
Finally, we'll end with measurement
and the real scenario walk through,
plus a pragmatic error out plan.
So this goes not become an error
ending transformation project.
Yeah.
Okay, let us define the enemy.
Alert storms are not a lack of tooling.
They are a lack of attention bandwidth.
A useful mental model is that
humans can do deep thinking on
a handful of cases at a time.
But most environments generate
thousands of alerts daily, thousands.
One commonly cited survey number is
an average on 3,832 alerts per day and
throughly, 62% of alerts going unattended.
Unattended alerts 62%.
When that happens, the system
becomes self-reinforcing.
Responses get burned, they start ignoring,
and the organization gets slower.
For us, E, the pattern is the same.
One root cause triggers dozens of symptoms
across metrics and monitors, and you
get paged for each symptom for security.
Different stage of Antech across
email identity and endpoint, but if
those are not stitched together, you
lose the narrative and you lose time.
MTTR is basically the sum of
detection, triage, analysis,
coordination, and remediation.
If the first three are noisy and manual,
everything downstream is delayed,
so our goal is to collapse the time
to understand with correlation Safe
Commission and AI assisted analysis,
and to prove E two is merchant.
This is the whole story in one slide.
I hopes for our purposes is simply
operations work that are assisted by
machine intelligence and automation.
With humans still accountable
for decisions, humans already
accountable for decisions.
Step one is correlation.
If you do not nurture related signals,
every downstream step was forth.
The goal is one incident with a shared
set of entities and a coherent timeline.
Step two is first mile automation.
Think of it as the checklist you wish ran
itself the moment an incident arrives.
Pull threat intel.
Four indicators.
Attach user and device contact
tag and route to the right team.
Open the ticket post to teams
and suppress obvious duplicates.
Step three is AI assistance.
Security cap pilot is useful
because it compresses analysis and
communication summaries, guided
response later, or language questions,
and become queries and draft reports.
The key is that it provides
advice, not anonymous action.
Step four is just measurement.
If you cannot show MTTR improvements
and time saved, the program will stall.
The scorecard is also a feedback
loop to tune rules and playbooks.
Correlation is the first level
because it detects the root cause
of alert storms fragmentation.
If the system presents 40 separate
alerts that are rarely one event, your
team does 40 micro investigations,
creates 40 tickets, and repeats
the same context given 40 times.
That is pure West.
When we correlate, we
trade volume for fidelity.
The object people work becomes
an incident, an actionable group
of related alerts with a shared
set of entities and a timeline.
That is why correlation tends to
improve both analyst experience and
response speed on the Microsoft stack.
Correlation happens in a few places
depending on the signal type.
Sentinel can correlate across many sources
and has fusion for multi-stage scenarios.
Defender XDR correlates across the
Microsoft 3 6 5 security domains and
can merge incidents into a broader
campaign for SRE Azure Monitor Smart
Groups cluster related alert, so the
on call engineer gets one page of a
situation, not a page per symptom.
That's good.
Once relation, once correlation is
in place downstream, automation is
safer because you are acting on high
confidence data that already has context.
Sentinel is the correlation workforce.
When you need a CM view across many
sources, the headline feature is fusion,
a correlation engine that use scalable
machine learning to detect multi-stage
attacks by finding combinations
of behavior across the tech chain.
Then you rate a single incident
that contains multiple alerts.
But do not overlook the simple
level incident grouping at
the analytics rule level.
If a rule is noisy, you can often fix
the experience by grouping adults into a
single incident by entity and time window.
A hundred failed Logons can become one
incident with a clear story rather than
a hundred tickets and melted analyst.
Yeah.
Hundred tickets for
just for the same logs.
It's crazy.
The result is that incident.
You open press, reach, context
entities related alerts, and
the beginning of a timeline.
So that makes the next
step Automation reliable.
The playbook can run, enrichment
taking and notification the
moment incident is created.
One more nuance.
Sentinel is moving toward the
defender portal for Unified SecOps.
That doesn't change the architecture,
but it improves the single pane of glass.
Experience one console
on the tools inside.
It's very useful.
Defender XDR is powerful because
it correlates across the Microsoft
3 6 5 security domains, endpoint
email identity, and cloud apps.
Incident correlation engine decides
whatever a new alert should attach to
an existing incident, start a new one,
or even merchant incidents if it detects
the part of the same broader campaign.
This matters because multi-stage attacks
are early leave in one data source.
At Fish is email telemetry.
Execution is endpoint telemetry
and privilege Escalation
shows up in identity signals.
If this land has separate cases, you need
a human to connect them, and humans are
slow at graph problems when under stress.
Especially on press, so don't be stressed.
The unified security operation story
becomes even stronger when Sentinel is
integrated with the Defender Portal.
You can see sentinel incidents and
data alongside defender incidents
in one queue that reduces tools
switching and accelerates ation.
The key takeaway correlation is not
only about reducing volume, it's
about building a defensible narrative
that helps responders make faster
decisions with higher confidence.
The security world does not own
alert storms, so SRA has the same
beast, just we different clothes.
One reliability incident often produces
an explosion of symptoms, alerts.
CPU latency, error rates,
auto skates, gateway, health.
If you page, if your paging system
treats each symptom as a separate
emergency, you end up with a paging storm.
Azure monitor has AIOps features
that help starting with smart groups.
Smart groups use similarity and
co-occurrence patterns to cluster
related alerts into a single group.
So responders focus on the situation,
not the individual symptoms.
Azure Monitor also offers anomaly
detection and dynamic thresholds that
adapt to normal patterns, which reduces
false alerts and systems change.
The key point for the session, SecOps
and ARI can share a common pipeline.
The telemetry differs, but
the workflow is the same.
Correlation to reduce NOS,
automation to enrich and road AI
assistance, to accelerate analysis
and measurement to keep improving.
The same part.
Once incident exists, we can automate the
first mile, the immediate repeatable steps
that should happen in the first minute.
The key phrase is save by design.
We want automations that build trust.
Note automation that goes
downtime or fail contained.
Reasonable first enrichment Attach
threat intel for indicators.
Pull users and device contact checks if
the same entity has appeared recently
and added context to an incident.
So responder starts ahead.
Second duplication.
Even with good correlation,
you will still get.
The system should consistently
suppress obvious duplicates
grouped by entity and time window.
And if you out close duplicates,
keep the evidence trail so
analyst can what happened?
Third, routing severity and
ownership should be automatic.
Where possible notify through teams or
paging open and ITSM Deacon and push there
and reach context so humans do not have
to retype or copy past, just copy past.
Ground race meta.
Start with read only enrichment.
Log every action, and for any
containment step, make it reversible
or require explicit proof.
Reversible is the key word here.
This is the punchline.
Architecture.
Automation and AI are
not competing approach.
They are complementary.
Automation is deterministic and fast.
Perfect for structured tasks.
Line enrichment AI is good at
summarization, master evidence,
and suggesting next steps.
A practical pardon is to
trigger a logic up playbook.
When a sentinel incident is created,
the playbook extracts the incident and
loops over and types like IP address.
Accounts, hosts and
processes for each entity.
It can run deterministic enrichment
like reputation lookup or pulling
data device compliance from intern.
Then it calls security copilot via the
logic app connector, sending a prompt
that asks for incident overview and
entity analysis and mitigation steps.
Finally, it posts the results back
into the incident as a command.
Now the human sees a structure
summary immediately that shortens
the time to understand, which is
often their real bottlenecks and TR.
This should not be treated as magic.
You still review AI output and you
still design prompts and guard rails.
But as a workflow, it's enormously
effective because it front loads
analysis and documentation.
Security capital is most valuable when
it reduces two expensive activities,
analysis time and communication time.
Instead of reading call logs and
alert metadata, you ask a question
and get a structured answer.
Ference I density in context.
In practice, you use it in two ways.
First interactively during an
investigation, ask for a summary, ask what
else to look at, ask for KQL to answer
hypothesis or ask for an executive report.
So you can just ask it in the.
Ordinary language.
Second, proactively call
copilot from a playbook.
So every new incident gets an initial
AI summary attached as a command.
Automatically.
Copilot can also help
with query generation.
If you do not remember the exact table
or field name, you can describe what
you want and let it draft the query.
Then you validate and run.
So you really do not need to
know KKO very well for it.
That's a huge speed boost for less
experienced responders, and it
helps senior responders move faster.
A key governance note compile provides
analysis and recommendations, but it does
not autonomously change your environment,
your playbooks, and your human decide
actions, which keeps the pipeline safe.
If you want the leadership support
you need proof, not anecdotes.
Yeah, it doesn't help.
The most important metric is MTTR,
key Metric, but it's more useful when
sliced by severity, by category, and
by where that automation was involved.
Microsoft Sentinel has strong analyst
views, but executive dashboards often
require custom workbooks or exported data.
A common approach is to pull incident
identifi the sentinel rest API, stored
in a custom log analytics table, and
then build a workbook that calculates
KPIs like average resolution time
incidents by severity, closure
reasons, and automation time saved.
Do not obsess All perfect
measurement on day one.
Start with a few metrics that are easy
to compute and hard to argue with.
M-T-T-A-M-T-T-R incident.
Count by severity and
time saved by automation.
Then add depth, false positive
rates, categories, and trends
after specific journey change.
So move by the very small steps in this.
Most importantly, read the
scorecard as a control loop.
If a certain incident type keeps
taking hours, that is hint that
your enrichment is missing context
of your own books and incomplete.
The dashboard tells you where to invest.
Next,
let us put it all together
with a realistic scenario.
A user receives sufficient email defender
for office detects that fish soon after
defender for endpoint detects suspicious
process on the same user's device.
In parallel identity protection facts,
animals, behavioral for the same account.
So we know that device was
affected without correlation.
This becomes three separate cases,
across three tools, and potentially
three teams with Defender XDR,
correlation and Sentinel ingestion.
The system recognized the shared
entities and likely attack
sequence and produced one incident.
One, no three.
That is the first win.
The second win is first mile automation.
As soon as the incident exists,
playbooks run, they pull thread
into of the URL hash or IP address.
They attach user and device context.
They wrote the right team and notify.
Depending on your policy, they can
take a reversible containment step,
like isolating the endpoint or forcing
a password to set, for example.
The third win is copilot.
A prompt book generates
a structured summary.
What happened?
Effective entities and
recommended next actions.
That summary is attached to the incidents.
So the human starts with narrator.
That combination collapse the
first 15 minutes, which is
often where MTTR is decided.
AIOps programs fail when
they try to boil the ocean.
The trick is sequencing, start
with baseline and hydrogen.
Measure your current MTT and
MTTR identity, your top no
detections, and apply grouping and
tuning so humans are not drawn.
Then introduce safe automation.
Begin with read only enrichment playbooks
because they cannot break production
and they immediate safe analyst time.
And routing and ticket creation
document rollback steps for
any action that change state.
Next layer in copilot acceleration.
So standardize a few Pro
books like executive summary
and investigation summary.
Attach outputs to incidents
of the knowledge is preserved.
Trained analyst to validate our
output rather than blindly trusted.
Finally run an optimization loop.
Review the scorecard, pick the incident
categories with highest MTTR and bill
playbooks and run books for those.
Expand the same approach to other
e alerts and on call patterns.
Governance is essential.
Use list privilege entities, versions,
and review playbooks like code and
define explicit criteria for when
automation can perform containment and
when it must require human approval.
Let us close with a
simple set of takeaways.
First, correlation is the front door.
If you are still dealing with alert
by alert work, everything else is an
efficiency page over a structural problem.
Second, first mile automation is
where you get immediate MT TR.
Improvement, remission, enrichment,
routing, the duplication,
and safe containment steps.
Remove the early minutes of manual.
Third security compiled is best used
to compress analysis and reporting.
It turns messy evidence into
narrative and suggest next actions.
When you attach those outputs back to
the incident, the whole team benefits and
you build a knowledge based over time.
Fourth measurement is the
difference between a cool
demo and an operating model.
The scorecard makes the
improvements visible and tells
you where to invest next.
Finally, the safest way to
implement this is incremental.
Start with one high
pain incident category.
Apply correlation and grouping.
Add one enrichment playbook, add compiled
summary, measure MTTR before and after.
When that works, just repeat.
This is how you go from alert storms
to fast count consistent resolution.
Thank you very much.
Ask me questions on my page.
I was glad to see you.
It.