Hello, everyone.
I'm Babita Kumari, senior
software engineer at Microsoft.
Today, I'm excited to discuss innovative
cloud architectures, revolutionizing
enterprise operations for AI integration.
We will explore how AI and ML are
transforming the way business operates
and innovate, driving efficiency,
and creating new possibilities.
In this presentation,
I'll cover four key areas.
Advancement in AI powered
cloud architectures.
A case study showcasing
real world applications.
Best practices for designing
innovative architectures.
Future developments shaping
enterprise operations.
So without further ado, let's dive in.
Let's talk about key advancements.
AI and ML are reshaping enterprise
cloud architectures through
these three pivotal advancements.
First one is productive
resource management.
Enterprises nowadays are using AI
to dynamically allocate resources,
achieving up to 91 percent accuracy.
Thanks.
In resource management and also minimizing
waste with automated scaling, machine
learning enables systems to adjust
resources automatically during peak uses,
and that improves efficiency by 67%.
Last but not the least, intelligent
security, AI driven threat detection
models now prevent up to 99.
7 percent of potential security breaches.
which provides unmatched
reliability and trust.
So these advancements enable
any enterprise to be agile,
efficient, and also secure,
which is the topmost priority.
So now let's talk about
multi cloud frameworks.
Most enterprises are now embracing
multi cloud frameworks, combining
both public and private clouds.
So public clouds like Azure, AWS ensure
scalability and 99 percent uptime,
hosting the majority of workloads.
Whereas private clouds offer more secure
environments for like credit sensitive
data, ensuring compliance and control.
So this hybrid approach balances
flexibility, performance,
and also cost effectiveness.
So let's talk about what are the
four key layers or key components
for any modern cloud architectures
The first one is data processing
layer which handles up to 100, 000
transactions per second and this
ensure real time insights Then next
comes the AI and ML integration layer.
It supports over 1.
5 million daily intelligent operations
and it helps in automated decision making.
The security framework is the
most important one as well.
So it gives and implements zero trust
models, safeguarding sensitive data, and
achieving industry leading compliance.
Monitoring and analytics is
also very key, player here.
So real time monitoring ensures 99 percent
of time and predictive uses, reservations.
So each layer is essential for delivering
high performing and reliable systems.
So, let's talk about a, case study of
a global manufacturing corporation.
So we'll talk about these
principles and actions.
The challenge we faced was a global
manufacturer based efficiencies in
supply chain, which costed around 12.
3 million annually.
So we implemented a AI driven
predictive analytics and real time
monitoring to improve decision
making and reduce downtime.
The solution was to include predictive
analytics and also add monitoring which
can help in more insightful decision
making and can reduce the downtime.
The outcome were transforming 47
percent downtime reduction and 4.
2 million in annual savings
and a 52 percent improvement
in supply chain reliability.
This use case or this global manufacturer
corporation case study demonstrates How
AI can drive a very miserable impact.
Now let's talk about the best practices.
So to replicate such a success,
consider these three best practices.
Access infrastructure regularly.
Evaluate your cloud setup to ensure it
aligns with evolving business needs.
It's not like one time setup is done
because we ever evolve our needs.
Then we need to access
infrastructure, whether it's meeting,
whether we need, more or less.
so we need, we should be accessing
the infrastructure regularly.
Then gradual migration strategies.
But if very huge enterprises,
This is the best approach.
Transition workloads incrementally to
reduce risk and maintain continuity.
Also define success metrics like
clear KPIs such as cost reduction,
system reliability, and uptime.
And measure and guide progress
and keep on doing that.
So all these three steps
keep on doing that regularly.
These steps provide a foundation
for scalable and efficient systems.
We have to be on top of this.
So make sure we are measuring and
guiding progress and taking benefit
of anything which is coming in future.
Let's talk about the integration strategy
like I was mentioning in the last slide.
So scaling AI requires a dynamic part
parameter adjustments, optimizing
performance for workloads ranging
from low to high demand, and then
robust monitoring frameworks.
Real time monitoring predictive
analytics for proactive uses.
And issue, proactive issue and resolution.
So this is one, also one of the
important factors to be considered.
Let's talk about continuous improvement
or continuous performance optimizations.
Leveraging AI to fine tune
systems for evolving requirements.
So such strategies maximize the potential
of any AI powered architectures.
Looking ahead, we see exciting trends,
looking ahead, we see exciting trends
receiving the enterprise landscape.
Quantum computing integration,
which involves the quantum 8 ML
models, will enhance computational
capabilities, bringing up to
200 percent efficiency and gain.
So the future is really bright.
Let's talk about multi
cloud orchestration.
This is happening even now, but in
the future it will be a seamless
collaboration across platforms,
which will improve operational
efficiency even more by 95%, 94%.
And the edge computing revolution.
The real time data processing at the
edge will boost reliability to 99.
99 percent enabling faster,
And smarter decision making.
These advancements will redefine
how any enterprise operation
in the years is to come.
We are definitely looking forward
and, as I said, the future is
looking really great in this.
And the trends are going to reshape
how any enterprise operations is
going to be in the many years to come.
To summarize, AI powered cloud
architectures deliver 40 45
percent improvements in operational
efficiency, which is a huge.
And then 35 50 percent is in
cost reduction, 60 70 percent in
system reliability enhancements.
Like I said, this technology is
the largest one in the world.
Transformation.
They are more about empowerment
and driving business to innovate
and grow at the same time.
At Microsoft, we are committed to
building this type of solutions
and enable any enterprise to thrive
in this rapidly evolving world.
Now, thank you so much for your attention
and I look forward to your questions.
Please feel free to connect with me.
I'm available on LinkedIn.
And from this conference, you
could also get my contact details.
So looking forward for any questions
you have and we'll be happy to help.
Thank you so much.