Hi.
And welcome to this presentation
on 15 Essential Metrics for NGINX.
I'm Dave McAllister.
I'm the Senior Open Source Technologist
here for NGINX, which is part of
F5, and I've been involved in the
open source scene since longer
than it's been called open source.
I'm glad to be here at the COM
42 DevOps presentation to talk
about a project that's incredibly
important in today's internet world.
Nginx, of course, is one of the most
popular web servers, and as you can
see from the Netcraft survey, we're up
there running about 39 percent of all of
the state of computers as of November.
Netcraft runs this monthly.
I don't have the latest numbers for
December at my fingertips, but not only
that, not only does Nginx support HTTP
servers, indexes files, HTTP 2, HTTP3 and
supports SSL, TSL, SNI, FastCache, etc.
It can also be reverse proxy.
It can be a load balancer.
And in fact, as a load balancer, it's
also supports in band health checks.
But many things can impact
the performance of NGINX.
You can see an increase in request.
You can see higher disk
throughput or network throughput.
You might be starting to run out of
resources like CPU or memory, or So, your
applications, your web applications may
actually have problems in them as well.
Monitoring is essential.
In our DevOps world, we need to be
able to look and understand what's
happening at all times with our
applications, as well as how we are
feeding that to our client base.
And let's start by talking
about collecting the data.
Now, Nginx has two categories.
characterizations of projects.
One is the Nginx open source core
project, and the metrics there
are gathered through this, this
thing called status stub module.
And over on the right, you can see
basically you add this single line.
to your nginx.
conf file, and you now will have
the ability to grab those metrics.
There's eight metrics plus a
health check inside of here.
Nginx Plus, which is a commercial
project, so I'm not as familiar with
it, adds an API endpoint to query
specific metrics, and it has a lot of
metrics, somewhere around 130 or so.
And they get into far more details
and drill into more things.
Both these offerings have the ability
to scrape logs so that you have even
more capability of pulling metrics
and pulling data out of those.
And while your choice of
visualization is left up to you,
we use Grafana heavily internally.
The NGINX Plus project does have
some built in dashboard capability.
And with that, let's step
to the next part of this.
You're going to hear me hammer
this, but the most essential
metrics You need to track, depend
on your specific goals and needs.
This is a set of metrics that will cover
a lot of general cases, but you may need
to go deeper into certain characteristics.
But keep in mind, these metrics
are not an absolute must do.
They fit to a very common general
purpose case of running NGINX.
Your mileage may vary.
aligning these things with the various,
capabilities, we have request metrics.
We can look at those as,
how do we get things, what's
happening going to the server?
Response messages, how is the
server feeding back to it?
And so on down into things like
caching metrics, SSL metrics,
because they do take performance
hits, as well as security metrics.
Security is incredibly
important in today's internet.
And so all these things feed
together to help us understand what's
happening with each of these pieces.
So with that, let's take
a look at the next set.
Let's start with active connections.
Obviously, this metric indicates
the number of currently active
connections in your server, but it
helps you understand the load that
is being placed on your server.
It helps you start looking at things
like, does it scale your resources?
Are your configurations running optimally?
Do you need to handle
traffic more efficiently?
It can lead to things like
understanding load balancing structures.
How many active things are coming in
as a baseline for what you need to
do to make NGINX perform efficiently.
NGINX was built on the concept of
performance and efficiency all the way
back when it was undertaken to solve
what was then known as the 10k problem.
With this, there are two variables.
The first one, connections
active, is in nginx open source.
You can also, if you're using nginx plus,
use the connections, underscore, nginx
underscore connections active, which is an
API input to which you can grab metrics.
All of these metrics I'm talking about,
with the exception potentially of
the health check, are most used in a.
Strip chart model.
In other words, a time series display
aggregated together so that you can
best understand what's happening to
the underlying system at any given
moment request rate, which is the next
piece inside of this request rate.
Obviously, it's the number of requests
that are being handled per second.
So this starts getting into
not just the connections.
How many things are per second?
pinging you at a time.
This is how many things are
being asked of you at a time.
And it helps you understand
your traffic problems.
Most of the time, you're going to see this
in a time series display as a sawtooth.
During the day, things will go up.
During the night, things will go down.
But not always.
And because of this, You can start
looking at how to balance both your
resources and your load balancer against
your traffic patterns, but sudden
spikes in request rates can indicate
certain things that you need to be
aware of, such as a traffic search.
Did marketing decide that they're
going to start offering a new
special between the hours of 3 a.
m.
and 6 a.
m.?
Is there an attack going
on against your system?
Has somebody launched a
DDoS attack against you?
And with this, in both cases, the
variable of choice would be requestTime.
And requestTime is going to show you,
basically, the number and how many
are being used on a per second basis.
Important metric to have, because it is
the thing that is driving the engine.
So response time, so if you think about
this, the one before request rate,
response time says how long is the server
taking before it sends things back out.
So response time metrics are not just
the process of your request, but also if
it processes and sends something through
to an upstream server, In other words,
you're using a microservices approach.
You've got another application.
You're pinging something
else for data, a database.
This is going to indicate to you how
long it's taking before it is ready
to send a response back to the client.
This lets you understand how well
your applications are running, as
well as start identifying bottlenecks,
particularly in a microservices basis.
So once again, it's not just the serve web
server, it's also the upstream servers.
And again, here you're going to want
to combine request time, how long
things are taking, with response time.
How long do things take
when they're coming in?
before they go back out?
And you can think of this sort
of as an endpoint measurement
in a microservices, viewpoint.
We now know how long between
activities that are happening.
And again, in open source, use request
time and upstream response time to give
you those two pieces of information.
As much as we'd love to be
able to say everything was
perfect, there's always errors.
That's why we have so much focus on
our DevOps monitoring environments.
It's because something
is likely to go wrong.
I used to do a talk on the Murphy's
Laws for observability, and that's one
of the things that's always very true.
Something will always go wrong,
probably at the worst possible time.
So monitoring error rates, in
this case, is mostly looking
for 400 and 500 status codes.
And it's crucial for identifying
those errors that exist with
servers or with your applications.
Again, keep in mind that most of
our web environments are no longer
just sending static pages out.
They're connecting to applications, and
they're connecting to databases, they're
connecting to other things behind this.
However, when you start seeing
a high error rate, it can mean
a lot of different things.
But the place to start checking, very
honestly, is the denial of service
attack, to make sure that you aren't
being attacked from the outside.
Look at application bugs.
Is the application doing something wrong?
Or do you simply have a mis
configuration, something that's causing
a breakage between the incoming client.
and the server, or as we
return that information.
And here status is your
variable of choice.
Status will give you that
particular set of information.
We do still have to consider
our underlying resources,
CPU and memory usage.
NGINX uses resources And even
though it is designed to be small,
efficient, and highly performant,
you may still need to optimize the
resources, especially as loads grow.
And so looking at these can start
telling you what your resource
optimization, whether you need
hardware upgrades, as well as
helping some of the planning aspects.
Here with open source, we recommend
using system monitoring tools,
top H top VM set and NGINX plus.
provide specific endpoints to allow
you to look at what process CPU
is being used by NGINX and process
memory is being used by NGINX.
But in any case, it's important to
look at what the underlying structure
is as you are building these out.
SSL handshakes are also equally important.
And in fact, in many ways, the SSL
handshake is something that But
we can't live without these days.
So the SSL handshake, for instance,
lets us start looking at how well we
are driving things as they go through.
The long handshake time usually means
there's a configuration problem.
And so if something's taking
a long handshake between these
things, it can also mean that
your hardware is running slow.
And that will be indicated by the
previous one looking at CPU and memory.
Nginx, Open Source, and Plus
both provide variables to look
at that handshake time frame.
That's incredibly crucial these days.
We need these secure connections.
This will let you know that your
secure connection is not slowing
down your requests and responses.
And then, as we move through, throughput.
to quote John Mashey, one of my favorite
computer scientists, bandwidth lives
forever, or, sorry, latency lives
forever, throughput costs money.
And so if we overscale or underscale,
it's costing us money in one ways.
So throughput measures the total
amount of data that is sent to clients.
And it helps us understand our data flow.
That data flow is crucial because
we have to be able to handle
that required bandwidth at peak.
And so understanding our peak
loads in terms of connections,
request rates, and throughput.
mean that we can understand how best to
balance our resources, particularly for
instance in a Elastic environment, be it
a Kubernetes environment or something else
that can scale up and down based on load.
Keep in mind that throughput is
also one of your limiting factors.
Your limiting factors are going
to determine the ultimate point
of contact to what you are.
ByteSent for Nginx open source,
plus will give you this information.
I don't know if it's nginx, open source,
or plus will give you that information
so that you can best understand what's
going on in the throughput basis.
And then finally, blocked request.
I'm thinking of this is finally maybe not
blocked request can help you identify.
potential security threats.
You have to worry about
things that are blocked.
If you see a high number of blocked
requests, you got possibly an ongoing
attack, somebody trying to penetrate
your system, or you may have a bunch
of just unauthorized access attempts.
This does not always mean
some outside malicious actor.
It can be as simple as configuration
error or security policy being
a little over tweaked for this.
Status again will tell you that
your blocked request is going here.
With Nginx Plus, you can get a specific
security blocked request count.
And those will help you understand,
really, whether you're going to
need to break off the attack or
to revisit your security policies.
Oh, and cache hit ratio.
If you're using Nginx as a reverse
proxy, you really do want to have it
hit the cache as much as possible.
Far more efficient, faster,
more performant, better,
all of the above for this.
However, if you're getting a high
cache rate hit, it means you're
getting lots of things from the cache.
That's good.
That reduces the load upstream.
It means your response times are faster.
And we know that users really
only care about their request.
Whether it succeeded or
failed, and how long it took.
And so the more you can cache, the
happier your users are likely to be here.
Upstream Cache Status in Nginx
Open Source will tell you that.
So there are these great metrics.
So what?
They're just a bunch of numbers.
So let's take a look at some of
the ways that these metrics might
actually apply and indicate it.
let's take a first scenario on
monitoring active connections,
and you've got a spike.
You can see baseline active connections
about 500, normal distribution
varies by about 10 percent up and
down, but all of a sudden you've
got a spike that's hit to 1500.
So your spike is substantial, and
your spike is probably going to
be a serious outlier condition.
Is it a traffic search?
Did marketing start doing a special?
Did, for you, those of you who
are, long enough back to remember
Slashdot, maybe you got Slashdotted?
All those things suddenly mean that
you're going to see a lot of activity.
And because you're now getting more
active connections, it's likely that
your request rate is rising, or your
response rate is going to be slower,
and possibly even your error rate.
You don't have the same thing.
And those are all caused by
an active connection spike.
But, it could also indicate a DDoS attack.
Crosscheck your 4 0 4 and four
oh threes to see what's going
on with those error cases.
You might also suddenly be
running out of limitations.
Maybe something has happened that your
load balancer is trying to do some weird
things in re reflecting things to a single
system rather than multiple systems, and
so your spread is not quite the same.
So you may need to look at resources
that are underlying this structure.
Scenario 2, also in Active
Connections, a gradual increase.
Same baseline, same normal operation.
But now, all of a sudden,
your numbers are increasing.
Oh, and sorry, there's a typo.
I left out a zero on the one.
100 should be 1000.
And the request rate goes up.
Equivalently, the response rate goes up.
The error rate goes up.
Maybe this is a good thing.
Maybe you're growing the number of
people that are using your system.
That's a good thing, which means
that you need to look at planning
and scaling your resources.
Here you can use the gradual increase,
looking at throughput, looking at
requests, looking at response times,
to start planning What you need to
adapt to add the resources necessary.
Maybe your systems are getting saturated.
Maybe you're running out of memory on a
subsystem and it can't handle the load
and therefore it's slowing down, which
is going to slow down everything else.
So you need to look at whether or not
your underlying system structure is
capable of meeting the structures.
And then if you're in a ephemeral
environment where you can be elastic
behavior, are you scaling correctly?
Because are you scaling to such a
point that you're not scaling an
application microservice correctly?
Or maybe your load balancer isn't
recognizing new services as they come on.
And then.
Also in connections, all of a
sudden things are just bouncing
all the heck over the place.
You don't quite understand, but
you look at this thing and your
connections are going, 400, then they
double, then they drop down, then they
triple, and then they go back to the
mean, and you're all over the board.
And each of these things, by the way,
does tend to impact the other things.
More connections usually means a
higher request rate, which means
usually more response time, which
can mean an increase in errors.
But, you've got intermittent traffic.
Where is the intermittent
traffic coming from?
Again, is it something periodic?
And you will see these slopes.
All of a sudden, somebody has decided
that they need to run a report
and it's hitting your system and
eating all of the resources talking
to your data repositories here.
Or, you've got a bunch of batch
work that's suddenly being
kicked off for whatever reason.
Or, again, you've been slash dotted
or you've got a marketing attempt.
But something is causing
the activity going here.
It doesn't necessarily
mean an outside force.
It could be a load balancing issue.
Your load balancer needs to be
looked at the configuration so that
you can make sense that the load
balancer is handling the traffic
appropriately to be able to pass the
traffic to the resources as necessary.
And then Your applications can bottleneck,
and remember those bottlenecks can
be outside of your application.
Likewise, in, for instance, a Kubernetes
environment, you may actually be looking
at your application being perfect, scaling
correctly, but being put into a node, a
pod, that has a noisy neighbor problem,
who's eating all the memory, even though
your application is perfectly correct.
Your application will show up
as the problem, not the one
that's eating all the memory.
Look at your underlying structures
and underlying resources.
So let's now take a look at the other one
that I talked about, a blocked request.
And the reason I want to talk
about blocked requests is that
quite often, it has to deal
with the security aspects here.
Active connections, but you can see
down here, your blocked requests
are running about 5 per minute.
That's actually, not
too out of the ordinary.
Maybe even a little low at times here.
And you're running 4 to 6.
Regular basis for operations
and all of a sudden your blocked
request scale by a factor of 10.
There is something going on and this
is usually one of the three things.
It's a security threat.
Somebody is attacking your system
and here go back and looked at that
status issues to see what's going
on and seeing if you're getting
a lot of failed authorizations.
inside of here.
You may have changed
something in your firewall.
You may have changed a WAF configuration.
Check for recent changes because
those recent changes may be blocking
things that are false positives.
And those false positives not only
can be from a configuration change.
But maybe you've set up a whole new
series of security rules that are looking
more deeply at the incoming connections.
If you have security rules, you've
also got configurations for those.
And so blocked request spiking is
usually some level of security threat.
but it can also be generated by
internal problems or internal concerns.
Same thing for a gradual increase.
You might have become
a target for attackers.
You may have just suddenly
shown up on somebody's radar and
they are beginning to scale up.
And a tag here up your security.
Again, looking at the other
features and other functionalities,
your requests are going up here.
Is your status still staying the same.
Your security rules can play a role
here, but it can also be a bot approach
that somebody's botting you to death
for this or again, your resource.
So this could be suddenly
slowing things down.
You or not accepting things
the same way they are.
Remember that blocks still take resources.
So as your blocks start going up, then
all of a sudden your performance may
decline because you're no longer capable
of meeting the needs of these things.
lots of different pieces that can happen.
But it's very important to
understand this gradual increase.
And then, high variability.
Similar structure.
Bouncing the heck all over the place.
Bouncing all over the place.
Blocks request 5 to 30 to 10 to 40 to 5.
This is an intermittent
attack, more than likely.
Somebody is just probing.
And it could be a malicious actor.
It could be an automated script.
It could be botting coming in to you.
But nonetheless, something from
the outside is probably doing this.
And it's most often seen through
load balancer or proxy issue.
Because of a blocking structure, you
end up with an inconsistent load.
If you're blocking, you're
not passing through.
And therefore, your load balancer
is not quite sure how to load
balance because it's got a lot of
things coming in, but not all of
them are being passed through here.
In this case, you might want to take a
look at what your load balancer structure
looks like in its configuration basis.
You can also look for application
misconfigurations or Maybe you have
some vulnerabilities that somebody is
taking advantage of just every now and
then hoping to slide underneath you.
While I've talked about metrics, I
also want to bring up, OpenTelemetry.
OpenTelemetry module for NGINX is an
open source project that brings the
OTEL tracing environments through NGINX.
Fully supports W3C trace,
OTLP, gRPC formats.
And we did this because NGINX's number
one concern is performance and efficiency.
And we looked at the current
modules that were out.
Out there.
We found that most of them had a 50
percent hit on request performance,
and that was unacceptable.
So we wrote our own native
module performance hit.
It's about 10%.
Tracing always hits your performance.
Sorry guys, it does for this,
but 10 percent is not too bad.
Now, the nice thing is that this is
set up inside of your Nginx application
configuration, so it doesn't require
any separate structures or work.
Inside of here.
It allows you to
dynamically control traces.
You can use cookies, you can use
tokens, you can use variables.
And that tracing means you can turn it on
and off, scale it up and down as you need.
And so without stopping your
environment, you can actually
control your tracing throughput.
short answer, the client request
comes in, the request goes into the
application that feeds back to NGINX
and NGINX sends the request back.
NGINX is the open telemetry collector
which via OTLP can send it off to
an OTEL collector which then can go
into your web app, it can go into
your storage, it can be displayed by.
Almost everything these days because
everybody is using open telemetry.
Likewise, open telemetry now supports
metrics and logs, and you will see
those also becoming available, as
part of our expansion into, more
monitoring capability for the NGINX,
open source core and NGINX plus.
So here's a quick example.
of the configuration, load the module
into it, you set up the exporter
point, which is basically you're
talking to the OTEL collector, you
tell it to listen in on it, and then
you say, I want to see the traces.
TraceInject, and ProxyPaths.
So each of these pieces, and it has the
ability to do sampling structures of all
sorts, and because you can enable and
disable via a variable, you can have it
on and only turn it on when you need it.
The other side is Prometheus.
And Prometheus is pretty much
de facto metrics structure.
Prometheus, Nginx Prometheus
exporter is an open source exporter
that takes Nginx metrics into a
form that Prometheus can scrape.
And it reads either the open source
side, through the status module,
or it can read the PLUS API.
You can see, find it there.
It supports the open source core, the
PLUS product, but it also supports the
two Kubernetes projects in Gridscape
Controller and Gateway Fabric.
And here you can see things like,
I can now see the types of things,
how it's set up, and this allows
me to bring, again, metrics into a
common vernacular so that they can be
displayed through your choice of tools.
concluding, we've looked at
some key metrics for Nginx.
Remember, they are Basic
and generic is structure.
It's a starting point.
Your mileage may vary.
The things that are important to
you are dependent on what your
outcome, desired outcome is.
We looked at some scenarios, a couple
of them around haptic connections
as well as blocked connections here.
And We did underlie some of the
hardware concerns and software concerns.
In a microservices environment, it's
not just enough to know that your
server, web server, is working well.
You also need to know that the
upstream servers are working well
in conjunction with your web server.
And it's not just the metrics.
My favorite quote, and I'm going to
still use it here, the most effective
debugging tool is still careful thought.
Coupled with judiciously
placed print statements.
Today, those print statements are our
metrics, our traces, and our logs.
They give us the ability to use our
own insight and our own understanding
of our environments to make sure
that what we deliver is what our
clients and our users are looking for.
And with that, My thanks
for, joining in today.
You can find docs on performance for
open source, as well as plus, here.
My slides are always on GitHub
and check me out on LinkedIn.
I also mentioned two open source
projects that you may be interested in.
The Nginx Prometheus Exporter and the
Open Telemetry Module for Nginx, both
which are available through our GitHub.
And with that, thanks again, and
enjoy the rest of COM 42 DevOps.