Hello, everyone.
This is Narendra Boggarapu and
welcome to this presentation
on how the cloud technology is
revolutionizing open banking, enhancing
consumer engagement and providing
security in the financial industry.
Today, we'll explore the transformative
impact of the cloud solutions
that are not only driving higher
engagement from the customers,
but also fortifying the security
measures within the dynamic industry.
Let's dive into the
open banking revolution.
Currently, 87 percent of the financial
institutions are either implementing
or planning open banking initiatives.
This shift has led to a remarkable
71 percent increase in the customer
engagement and a significant
43 percent decrease in customer
acquisition costs, proving that
open banking isn't just a trend.
It's also reshaping the
financial landscape.
Cloud technology enables substantial
innovation within the financial services.
We are seeing 2 billion monthly
API calls managed securely between
banks and the third parties,
facilitating new products and services.
This innovation leads to a 56 percent
improvement in customer satisfaction
and extends financial product access by
34 percent to underserved population.
Enhanced financial management through
cloud powered open banking has led to
a 62 percent rise in the adoption of
personal financial management tools.
Additionally, there is a 47 percent
improvement in financial literacy rates.
Coupled with a 38 percent increase
in the competition among financial
service providers fostering
a healthier market trend.
In terms of security, open banking
under cloud cover offers military
grade protection, achieving a 99.
99 percent prevention rate
against unauthorized access.
Our robust encryption ensure that
customer data remains secure.
A critical factor in maintaining
trust transparency and
customer consent are paramount.
We are reaching a 91 person customer
satisfaction rate regarding the
transparency of our consent protocols
Compliance with critical regulatory
requirements like psd2 is non negotiable
Ensuring that customer confidence is never
compromised Open banking is breaking down
traditional barriers reaching underserved
population and enhancing competition
This not only fosters innovation, but
also improves the customer experience,
ensuring services are more integrative
and responsive to the customer needs.
Let's look at some success stories.
A fintech startup used open banking
APIs percent growth by offering
innovative lending solutions.
Similarly, a traditional bank increased
its senior customer base by 45 percent
through user friendly open banking tools.
And a major bank boosted engagement
by AI powered financial advisor.
However, challenges persist.
We address data privacy with advanced
encryption and strict access controls.
Legacy systems integration is managed
through innovative middleware solutions,
ensuring seamless connectivity.
Moreover, we continuously update
our frameworks to meet evolving
global regulatory standards.
Looking ahead, the integration of AI and
blockchain promises enhanced predictive
analytics and transaction transparency.
Moreover, we are working towards
global standardization of APIs,
which will facilitate seamless
cross border financial services.
To conclude, cloud powered open
banking is a game changer, driving
innovation and enhancing security.
and prioritization customer satisfaction.
As we move forward, these technologies
will continue to shape the future
of global financial services.
Thank you for attention and I
look forward to your questions.
Thank you.