Speaker 11: Good morning.
Good afternoon, everyone.
I'm
Speaker 12: Gu Deep Gill
technical leader at Cisco Systems.
Thank you for joining today.
I'll shared a practical way to build
security into your DevOps pipeline for
AI workloads so you get strong protection
without giving up deployment velocity.
Imagine it's a normal Tuesday.
Your team ships a small update to an a i
endpoint, maybe a recommendation model,
LLM assistant, an image classifier.
It's simple release until
it becomes a feature.
Everyone depends on.
Traffic ramps.
Customers are happy, leadership
is thrilled, and then the pattern
changes, not an outage, not a crash.
Just request that.
Feel a little too curious.
That's the moment the session is for.
I'm going to talk about why AI
shift security from static code.
To runtime behavior, but
next donation firewalls.
Add beyond IP and port rules.
How to wire NGFW controls into CICD and
runtime, and how to roll it out safely.
Monitor first, then
enforce, then optimize.
So let's name the tension.
Every modern team fails.
Talent, velocity versus security.
Let's meet Maya.
Maya runs a DevOps team.
They deploy.
They deploy several times a day
because the business expects
it, and honestly, it works.
Shipping fast is a competitive
advantage now Miro.
Rook is not trying to slow anyone down.
Rook is trying to prevent the headline.
Here's a conflict.
Traditional security is
built like a toll booth.
It assumes changes are rare
and traffic is low, but Maya's
world is a multi-lane highway.
If every release must stop for a
manual review, two things happen.
Delivery slows and trust breaks down Teams
route around the checkpoint just this
month, and that becomes shadow security.
You have seen the symptoms.
Temporary allow rules
that never get removed.
One off exceptions.
With no owner earth
approvals, done with no audit.
Trail security controls that
only exist in production because
they're too painful earlier.
And with ai, the tension spikes.
You're not only protecting
code anymore, you're protecting
the model, the data pipeline.
Prompts and unstructured input
where runtime attacks live and
the outputs which can accidentally
reveal more than you intended.
So the requirement changes from
approve occasionally to validate
continuously, security has to move
at DevOps speed, or it won't be used.
Okay.
Why does AI make this harder
than a normal web app?
AI systems are powerful, but they
have a very different security
personality than traditional apps.
First inputs and unstructured.
In a typical app, inputs
are forms and fields.
In an AI system, the input might be a
paragraph of text and image or audio
Ambiguity is a part of the design,
which means old school validation rules
taught help much, and unstructured
input is exactly where attackers love
to hide instructions inside normal
looking text payloads that look.
Harmless to RegX rules.
Prompts that try to trick a system
into breaking its own rules.
Second outputs are non-deterministic.
With classic software, you
can baseline behavior easily.
Same input, same output,
but AI can be probabilistic.
That complicates testing,
monitoring, and even incident
response because reproducible bug
is not always straightforward.
Third, the model is high value.
IP intellectual property.
Your model may represent months of
training time and competitive advantage.
And attacker doesn't need your training
data if they can learn enough by
observing your model through its API.
Fourth, the pipeline matters.
Poisoning does not always show up on day.
Sometimes it's septal, a bias, a back
door, a behavior that only appears later.
Data province becomes a security
requirement, not a paperwork.
Exercise.
Finally.
New attack classes show up at run time.
Prompt injection, AL inputs
membership inference.
The theme is the attack surface
is no longer just static code.
It's a production behavior.
Maya thought she was shipping software.
Suddenly she's operating.
A living system that learns, peruse, and
gets poke at in ways normal apps don't.
So what kind of control can
understand behavior, not just sports.
That's where next generation
firewalls come in.
Let's talk about the difference
between a traditional firewall
and a next donation firewall.
In a plain language, a
legacy firewall is created.
One question, is traffic
allowed from this IP to that ip?
But in cloud native AI environments,
those data change constantly.
Bonds move services, scale ips are
temporary, and the real question
becomes, what service is this?
What API, is it calling?
Who is making the requests?
What's inside the request?
And is this behavior normal?
That's what Next Generation Firewall
brings in layer seven awareness,
understanding APIs and application
protocols, payload and content inspection,
spotting malicious content and exfil
patterns, Terra inspection strategies.
So encryption does not become
invisibility, behavioral anomaly detection
because AI threats are often novel.
Identity context, policy based on
workload, service, identity, not
network location, a legacy firewall.
You can think it as checks the address on
the envelope, whereas the next donation
firewall can also understand what kind
of delivery it is, who signed for it,
and whether the contents match policy.
So this is the moment R stops being the
checkpoint and becomes a person who gives
Maya guardrails that don't break velocity.
Now you might say, we already
shift left, we scan everything.
True, but it's not enough.
Shift left.
Security is one of the best things
DevOp brought to the industry.
We scan code dependencies,
containers, ISC, and that
absolutely prevents incidents.
But let's go back to Mayas Tuesday.
Everything in CI is green.
No critical cvs.
Terraform looks compliant.
Hand charts validate,
so the release ships.
Spend time passes and
runtime Reality shows up.
An egress path is misrouted and a
service can talk to places It should not.
A workload has more
permissions than intended.
A microservice becomes an unexpected
bridge for lateral moment.
API users slowly shifts into abusive
patterns, a time delayed condition
triggers unexpected behavior.
These are the problems that
don't look like bad code.
They look like perfectly valid behavior
used in a. Bad way and AI amplifies this.
A model serving service might
suddenly become a high value target.
A connected to a data store
might become an X Excel part.
A new feature flag might expose
an internal endpoint, so the fix
is not shift left versus runtime.
It's sport.
Shift left plus shield.
Right next donation firewall becomes
a continuous control plane in
production, enforcing policy while
the system is actually running.
So how do we embed this without bolting
it on Here is integration framework.
Comprehensive next donation
firewall integration.
Think of this framework like
weaving security into the fabric of
delivery, not adding it at the end.
There are five pieces and
they work best together.
First, identity based
access control policies.
Talk about services and roles, not ips.
The survives.
This survives Cuban needs.
John.
Out scaling and multi-region deployments.
Policy is code with ci validation
firewall policy lives in kit.
It gets reviewed, tested,
and promoted like software.
This is how you eliminate mystery
rules and configuration drift.
Next, crypto traffic inspection strategy.
We decide what to decrypt and
inspect based on risk and compliance.
Selective targeted visibility
not to grip everything.
AI specific threat detection is the next
rules and baselines tailored to model
serving, training pipelines and inference
APIs, extraction signals, injection
patterns, and suspicious behavior.
Alert optimization and aggregation
because a noisy system gets ignored,
we want high confidence signals that
engineers trust and ca can act un quickly.
Simple mental model.
You can think as CCI.
CD is where we prevent and
standardized runtime is where we
observe and enforce continuously.
So Maya gets speed and repeatability.
Luke gets enforcement and auditability
and both gets few late night surprises.
Now, before we enforce anything,
we need a safe rollout in line
versus out of event, let's talk
about the safest way to introduce
a control that can block traffic.
Inline is powerful.
The next donation firewalls sits
directly in the path and can allow
block or modify traffic in real time.
That's full enforcement.
Great when policies are mature, but
inline also carries operational risk.
Misconfigurations can create down time,
so you don't start then there blindly
out of band is your learning mode.
Your mirror traffic to the next donation
firewall so it can inspect, build
baselines, and show you what it would
have done without impacting production.
This is a trust building phase.
You learn, but normal looks like
at different times of day, but
to release data, day traffic
looks like which services are
chatty for legitimate reasons.
And what performance
headroom you actually have.
When you do move in line, say
the reassuring part out loud.
You design for high availability,
clear failover behavior,
and performance budgets.
Security can't be fragile, single
point of failure, so Maya may wonders I
can't risk breaking production and may.
Say good.
We want, we'll botch first, tune
only then enforce the critical parts.
So to make any of this table
in cloud native environments,
we anchor policy on identity.
Identity based access
for dynamic environments.
In modern environments, IP
dresses are not identity.
They're temporary coordinates in
Kubernetes and serverless systems.
Parts restart, node scale services move,
and IP based rules becomes the BRI fast.
So we switch the anchor from where to who?
Identity becomes the new parameter.
Where does that identity come from?
Service mesh identity.
MTLS Certificate.
Proving a workload is who it says it is.
API, gateway Identity.
OAuth tokens.
M-T-L-S-A-P-I.
Keys validated centrally.
Cloud Workload identity.
Im roles and managed
identities attached to compute.
What does this enable?
Least privilege at the service level.
This service can call that endpoint
using this method for this purpose.
So my inference service should talk to
the model, store and feature store, but
it should not have open egress to the
internet with identity-based policies.
That rule travels with the
service across clusters,
regions, and auto-scaling events.
And bonus benefit here is audit.
It becomes easier when an alert
fires if you don't see a random ip.
You see a real identity
engineer can act on.
So once the identity is the foundation
policy can be treated like code.
That's where CICD integration shines.
Here's a mindset shift.
Firewall policy should
not be a special case.
It should follow the same
discipline as application code.
Policy as code means policy
lives in version control.
Changes come through pulled requests.
CI runs automated checks.
Deployment is synchronized
with infrastructure changes.
Rollback is coordinated
with application rollback.
When do we testing CI syntax?
Validation Issued bars.
Conflict detection.
Two rules fighting each other for
forbidden patterns, like overly
broad egress compliance checks,
like where data is allowed to go.
Drift detection, but running matches.
Get now.
Maya's team adds a new microservice
endpoint in the old world.
They will open a ticket, wait days,
push a heart change in the new world,
open a pr that includes the service
change and the policy change and run
tests automatically review once, deploy
together and roll back together if needed.
This is how security becomes
boring in the best way,
predictable, repeatable, auditable.
Now let's do, now let's zoom into
AI specific threats, starting
with the one that treats your
AP API like a copy machine
protecting AI APIs,
model extraction attacks.
Model extraction is a unique risk.
Attacker does not need access
to your training pipeline.
They can learn a surprising amount
by querying your interference API
repeatedly and systematically trying
to map behavior from the outside can
look like unusually high query volume.
Very uniform automated request shapes
repeated probing of edge cases.
Loss of requests that don't match
Normal custom workflows spikes from new
identities that appear and disappear.
Now, Maya sees the user, Maya
sees the users, uses graph,
and thinks great adoption.
Luke looks at it and thinks
that pattern is not human.
What can NWS do here?
Rate limiting and quotas detect
suspicious sequences and exploration
patterns, automation and bot blocking
signals, reduce accidental information
leakage, and the key operation
ideas is graduated enforcement.
You don't want to break legitimate
customers who are simply heavy users.
So you start with first detect,
then one next throttle, and then
you challenge, and then you block
based on a confidence and impact.
So treat your model API like a
premium resource because it's now the
extraction, tries to copy the model.
Prompt is action, tries to
take control of the model.
So how do we protect LMS
from the Prompt Injections?
LMS have a charming flaw.
They are designed to follow instructions.
That's why they're useful, and
it's why Prompt Injection exists.
Prompt injection attempts often try to
overnight system instructions, trick
the model into revealing sensitive
context, manipulate tool, use austere
outputs into unsafe territory.
How to explain simply is it's
social engineering, but aimed at
the model, at the network layer.
Next generation firewalls can
help in four practical ways.
Prompt sanitization signals pattern
based detection of obvious instruction,
override attempt, luque baselining, prompt
length structure, abnormal correctors,
sudden format changes, output monitoring.
Were visible indicators of data leakage.
Identities with the repeated, rejected
jailbreak like patterns, get thro out.
Network controls are one layer.
You still need application guardrails.
Strong system prompts, tool permissions
as safe by design workflows.
So if your LLM can call internet
tools like a ticking system, a CRM
or a database, the biggest risk.
The biggest risk is not only what
it says, it's what it can reach.
Identity-based network policy can
ensure the model service cannot
directly access seeker stores metadata
endpoints or sensitive databases,
even if a prompt tries to trick it.
So now almost all of this traffic
is encrypted, so we need visibility
without sacrificing performance.
Encryption is a win.
It protects users and data in transit,
but it also creates a visibility gap
that can hide inside encrypted sessions.
The goal is not decrypt everything.
The goal is to crypt what matters based
on risk, compliance, and practicality.
We want selective visibility,
not blanket surveillance.
So high ation and crypto offload
are the few tactics that we can use.
So inspection keeps up with throughput.
Next, selective decryption
focus on high risk parts.
Internet facing sensitive APIs.
Session optimization review
sessions and reduce handshake
overload, ate pinning awareness.
Some apps will reject inspections.
Those may need exemptions or
out ofAnd monitoring, capacity
planning, defined performance
budgets, and size for peak traffic.
Now let's go back to Maya Miami Wonders.
Will this slow us down?
You may support by saying only if
we design it like an afterthought.
We design it like production
infrastructure with metrics,
load tests, and headroom.
Pesty planning is a security requirement.
If the control can't keep
up, people will bypass it.
And while we are planning the
Speaker 11: present, we also need
to plan for the crypto future.
PQC Redness.
Speaker 12: Let's do a
quick thought experiment.
If you had sensitive data that
must remain confidential for 10
or 20 years, what would you do?
If someone could record it today
and crack it later, that's.
The risk we call harvest now
decry later, even before large
scale quantum machines exist.
High value encrypted
data can be collected.
What does readiness look
like in practical steps?
Build a cryptographic inventory.
Where RSA and ECC are used, identify
long lived sensitive data flows.
Those are the highest priority pilot
hybrid approaches were available.
Classical plus post quantum
together during transition
plan for performance impact.
Larger keys and more competition
means you measure early.
Your next, ensure your next
generation firewall platform
can evolve by firmware software
updates to support new algorithms.
This is a planning message,
not a panic message.
Should don't migrate everything overnight.
You start with pilots, measure
and prioritize systems handling
long-lived, sensitive data.
So Maya wants to ship this quarter.
RU wants to make sure the data is
still protected years from now.
So we go in phases.
Now let's come back to day-to-day
reality alerts, because security
that cries falls gets ignored.
If your alerting system is
noisy, people stop trusting it.
It's like a smoke alarm that goes
off every time you make toast.
Eventually someone disables
it to avoid that outcomes.
Baseline first out of band monitoring
teaches you normal behavior.
Use a normally coding.
Not every deviation deserves an alert.
Aggregate events.
Into instance, tell a story.
Instead of dumping logs, enrich
alerts with context service, identity
criticality, destination repetition,
and recent deployment changes.
Continuous tuning feedback loops
improve precision over time.
Make it tangible within.
Some example, alert narrative.
For example, service interference,
API identity, surface account change
context, deploy version 1.2 0.3, 10
minutes ago, absorbed unusual egress
to new destination confidence high.
So justed action.
Confirm destination.
Block if un unapproved or rollback,
that's an alert an engineer can act on.
This matters.
For DevOps adoption.
My team will only embrace security
telemetry if it helps them decide quickly.
Not if it creates a second on-call job.
Luke's best moment is when an engineer
says, this alert is actually useful.
So what's the practical rollout?
Here's a roadmap you can
take back to your team.
Let's close this story.
Maya and Luke dot fix this with
one giant security project.
They do it in phases and
each phase earns trust.
Phase one outand monitoring four
to eight peak middle traffic.
Build baselines.
Tune detection, blue performance
assumptions drive false positives down.
Phase two policy as code plus selective
enforcement approximately six to 12 weeks.
Move policies into Git validating ci.
Begin in line enforcement on low risk path
practice rollback like a
fire drill, so it's a calm.
When you need phase three, AI specific
detections, eight to 16 weeks add
protections for moderate extraction,
prompt injection patterns, and ai.
API of use expand coverage with
graduated enforcement, phase
four performance optimization.
Most quantum pilots.
TS inspection throughout
an expression if needed.
Start PQC redness testing for long LI
lived sensitive data deployment velocity.
Unchanged or improved because
policy changes are automated.
Pause, positive rates drops over time,
not up Latency stays within budget.
Clear audit trail for
security policy changes.
Fear emergency allow all exceptions.
So main key take takeaways are security
can be continuous and automated
without slowing delivery shift left
is necessary, but runtime protection
is where real exploits happen.
AI changes the threat model.
So controls must be identity
aware and behavior aware.
Security works best when it moves at
the speed of DevOps because it's a built
into the system, not bolted on later.
Thank you.