Speaker 33: Hi, I'm Ragu.
I work as a senior software engineer
at Expeditors in Global Supply chains.
Minutes of failure can cost hundreds
of thousands of dollars, and most of
the time we don't hear about these
failures from our monitoring tools, but
we hear about them from our customer.
Today I'm going to talk about how
to move from reacting to failures.
Two, predicting them and preventing them.
Modern supply chains are
not just applications.
They're made up of APIs, carriers,
iot devices, weather systems,
warehouses, and don't fade alone.
They propagate from one
system to the other.
A small delay becomes a missed.
A missed pickup becomes a missed.
A missed flight becomes a customer impact.
Traditional monitoring tools answers
one question what went wrong?
Say for example whenever something
happens, we have these monitoring
tools triggering alerts only after
the performance has already declined
and leaving the team responding to
problems rather than preventing them.
And root cause discovery.
During impact, engineers must diagnose
issues via customer experience disruption,
increasing the pressure and extending
the re resolution time, cascading
failure, complexity, multiple failures
occurring simultaneously, obscure
the original root cause, and making
diagnosis exponentially more difficult.
External signal blindness, critical
external factors like weather events.
Carrier operational issues and
traffic patterns remain invisible
to application level monitoring.
The result would be teams spending
their time firefighting incidents
rather than preventing them from
occurring in the first place.
So what is Predictor Observability?
Predictor Observability is
observability with the foresight.
So we learn from the failures instead
of waiting for the system to fail.
We learned the failure behavior, so
we look at the historical pattern
analysis, analyzing the past instance
to identify recurring patterns and
failure signatures, real time telemetric,
continuous monitoring of system metrics,
logs and dis distributed traces, and
integrating weather carrier status
traffic, and other environmental factors.
Which are outside of the applications,
proactive actions enabling
intervention hours or even days before.
It's the difference between a smoke
detector and a fire prevention.
The goal is not better dashboards.
The goal is to have fewer incidents.
How should the architecture of
this observability look like?
There are five integrated layers
working in concrete to transform the
raw signal into actionable intelligence.
Real time observability signals,
foundational layer, capturing metrics,
logs, traces and events from all
system components in real historical
pattern analysis, time series databases
and analytical engines, identifying
recurring patterns and seasonal trends,
external intelligence integration.
APIs carrier status speeds and traffic
data and market indicators and risk.
The internal telemetry, predictive
processing engine, machine learning models
and statistical algorithms, detecting
anomalies and forecasting failures.
Action orchestration.
Automated response system triggers
alerts and running remediation playbooks
and coordinating human intervention.
Events.
Flow into the events, flow into
the streams and predictive services
learned from the behavior models.
Forecast Orchestrations enables actions.
Our prediction systems are allowed to
fail, but are not Our production systems,
event driven architecture for prediction.
Event driven architecture provides
the foundation for scalable, resilient
predictive systems by using streaming
backbones like AP Apache Kafka and
AWS Kinesis Prediction Logic operates
independently from the production
systems, and so the fine main things
that is happening is stream streaming
backbone, Kafka or Kinesis, handling
millions of events per second.
Continuous signal ingestion, real time
data from all system components and
external services, real time anomaly
detection, immediate pattern recognition
and deviation identification, decoupled
prediction services, independent
scaling and evolution of ML models.
Prediction logic never impacts
the production stability, failed
predictions or isolated incidents
and not systemwide outages.
Why Microservices?
Microservices gives you the independent
Scaling Machine Learning Inference
Services scale separately from core
business logic technology evolution.
Update prediction algorithms without
touching production code failure,
isolation prediction service failures
don't cascade to operational systems.
Team autonomy.
Data science teams deploy
models independently.
And what about the
distributed tracing power?
Casual dependency mapping.
Understand how services
depend on each other.
Failure propagation prediction
forecast how issues will
cascade through the system.
Intervention window estimate.
Calculate how much time
exists before impact.
Bottleneck identification,
pinpoint where failures originate.
This architectural approach ensures that
predictor capabilities enhance rather
than compromise system reliability.
Let's take a simple example.
Transportation network failures.
Say for example, there is
a severe weather event.
That disrupts the transportation
networks causing cascading
delays across the supply chain.
Traditional approaches detect
these issues only after the
shipments are already delayed.
So the new thing, what we are going
to do with the predictive analysis
is we'll take the weather forecast
integrion, the severe storm prediction
in major transit corridors, and we
look at the traffic patterns like
how much will be the delay in.
For during those situations, it might
be usually like four to six hours.
And we also analyze the carrier routes if
the routes carrier routes are on the same
path with respect to the weather forecast.
And we might try to get alternate backup
carriers instead of the carriers that
are going to be affected and due to this.
Three to six hours early, we
will, we are going to get three
to six hours of early warnings and
we can reduce the delay by 90%.
The second scenario is ca Carrier,
API Degradation third party carrier.
A PS gradually slow down, creating subtle
performance degradation that eventually
cascade into system-wide failures
by the time traditional alerts fire.
Downstream systems are already
experiencing timeouts and errors,
predictive signals, response time trends
showing consistent increase about 20 to
30 minutes, error rate acceleration from
0.1 to 2% or short timeframes, seasonal
patterns indicating peak hour degradation.
Likelihood correlated slowdowns
across multiple API endpoints.
Detection a P response time trending
upwards 30 to 60 minutes before failure.
Threshold prediction.
ML model forecast complete degradation
within 45 minutes based on acceleration.
Pattern action, circuit breaker,
activated caching, layer enabled
backup carrier routes prepared outcome.
Cascade prevented user experience,
briefly delays instead of complete outage.
The third scenario would be
cold chain sensor failures.
Say for example, refriger refrigeration
failures in temperature control
logistics can result in hundreds of
thousands of dollars in spoiled products.
Traditional monitoring de
detects failures only after the
temperature thresholds are breached.
Often too late to save the
cargo with the new system.
First, we analyze the temperature,
variance detection, SubT inconsistencies
in cooling patterns identified.
Then we rate of change analysis,
temperature, drift, acceleration
signals, compress compression issues.
So we check the rate of change in the
temperature sensor consistency patterns.
And with the ch rate of change
data, we also compare with the other
compressor datas to find the anomalies.
Cross validation across multiple
sensors reveals anomalies.
So what this leads, so this leads to
predictive alert, 15 to 30 minutes
warning before critical threshold.
And vehicle diversion reroute to the
nearest facility for product transfer.
And that will save, give us time to
prevent the spoiling of the cargo and
loss prevention and product is saved.
Does the same ML model
work for all the alerts?
The answer is no.
We need to have different
types of alerts for different.
Time timeframes, say for example,
short term is the ones which
are like the live data crossing.
The live data and the hours need to be
between 15 to 60 minutes and medium term
is like one to six hours and long term,
maybe with the days or weeks coming to
the short term, the ca, they capture the
temporal dependencies in time series data.
And rapid detection of out of
control processes for use case,
immediate system health degradation.
And coming to the medium term,
combine multiple weak predictors for
robust forecast, handle seasonality
and holiday efforts in time series.
Feature importance for interpretable
predictions, use case transportation
delays, and API degradation.
Long term, so long-term are something
like we, we analyze both the short
term and medium term and come up with
a plan for the long term analysis.
Say for example, with these
disruptions, we are going to make
changes to the capacity planning
and seasonal demand shifts,
model explainability, and trust.
Why trust matters.
Operators will not act on black box
predictions, especially when those
actions involve significant operational
changes or resource allocation.
Automation requests clear
justification for every decision in
high stakes logistics and enrollment.
A single false post can cost
thousands in unnecessary routing.
A missed prediction can cost millions
in lost product or customer penalties.
So some of them are SHAP values.
Quantify each feature contribution
to individual predictions, showing
exactly which factors throw the
alert, feature importance, rank input
signals by their predictive power
across all historical incidents.
Attention visualization for neural
networks display, which time windows the
model focused on when making prediction.
Counterfactual explanations.
If the a p response time has
stayed below 500 milliseconds,
this alert would not have fired.
Operators receive actionable, credible
predictions with clear reasoning,
enabling confident decision making,
and higher automation adoption
rates, automation decision framework.
Not all predictions should
trigger the same response.
A risk based framework determines
when to automate, when to involve
humans, and when to simply alert
fully automated risk level.
Low conference required greater than 95%.
Example, cash warmup, request
throttling, circuit break activation.
Rational actions are reversible, low
cost, and have proven effectiveness.
Alert only risk level, high
confidence required less than 80%.
Examples.
Major infrastructure changes, vendor
escalations, customer communications.
Rational high stakes decisions require
full context and strategy consideration.
Showman in that loop.
Risk level, medium confidence
required 80 to 95%.
Example, carrier rerouting inventory,
relocation and scaling conditions.
Rational significant operational impact
requests, human judgment and approval.
This framework evolves our time as
confidence improves actions initially
requires human approval, can graduate
to full automation as trust builds
through the demonstrated accuracy.
Measuring the business impact.
So what's the impact of the
system and on the business?
So the impact is we are going to
avoid ma major incidents prevented,
and we have we also have a cost for
the system investment and we have a
cost for the annual cost avoidance
and we have the return of investment.
Same.
And these are some of the numbers which
I collected with few of the scenarios.
And it clearly states that investing in
those these systems is going to prevent
the incidents a lot, but even though there
is a cost for it, and the key metrics
are prevention window hours of advanced
warning gained before outage impact.
Severity reduction, decrease
in the customer facing downtime
and service degradation.
Percentage of predictions that don't
materialize into actual incidents and
propagation of automated responses
that successfully prevent outages.
Reduction in the time between failure,
initiation and alert, coming to
the conclusions and key takeaways.
Predictive observability fundamentally
shifts reliability engineering from
reactive firefighting to prevent
maintenance, preventive maintenance.
By detecting failures, signatures before
they manifest, organizations can transform
potential outages into non-events.
Paradigm shift move from reactive
incident response to proactive
disruption prevention through
early detection and intervention.
Transform outages early detection,
converts major incidents into
minor hiccups, protecting customer
experience and business continuity.
Scalable architecture, event
driven systems combined with
explainable ml, create resilient
trustworthy prediction platforms.
Proven results demonstrated
effectiveness across S Networks, a P
ecosystems, and IOT sensor deployments.
Implementation path.
Start small with low risk use cases,
validate prediction to build trust,
then progressively automate responses.
And finally, the best incident
is the one that never happens.
Thank you for giving me the opportunity.