Speaker 14: Hello everyone.
Welcome to com 42.
My name is Simran Kadri and
I'm a senior network lead.
Today I'm presenting infrastructure
as code for Enterprise Network and
I will be focusing on automating
SD and zero trust architect.
This session is draw from real
world implementation across
example site like nuclear, solar,
wind, and enterprise data center.
As they are managing
thousands of network devices.
Let's start journey for
today's session and I will be
covering three main area today.
First, why additional networking is
broken and costing companies money.
Second, how infrastructure is code
fixes this problem with real example
from production environment and third.
I will be giving five practical step
to follow for your infrastructure.
So let's begin.
Let's begin our journey with the problem.
We will be discussing the
problem first, then the solution.
The traditional network management is
fundamentally broken at enterprise scale.
Imagine, for example, we
have 500 network devices.
And a security page need to
deploy across all of them.
What traditional, across required
as such as into each device,
copy the configuration, paste,
and repeat this 500 times.
This going to take a week
or more than a month?
And one typo.
You have to start it over.
So let me tell you what, what happened.
Reality.
In reality, configuration ship
silently destroy network reliability.
And device dives from their
intended state over time and making
troubleshooting nearly impossible for
engineer and changes that should be
taking a minute, actually takes day
due to manual coordination, change
approval, and implementation windows.
And when things break, there is
no quick rollback capability.
You stop undoing these changes and
restoring from outdated backup.
So what industry demand.
Meanwhile, business demand
totally opposite business demand,
deploy the network changes
globally in a minute, not day.
And maintain the zero security gap
with consistent policy enforcement and
provides seamless connectivity across
on premises and multi-cloud environment.
And this gap between the current
capability and business requirement.
It's what we are going
to addressing today.
Let's focus on the solution.
The infrastructure as code fundamentally
changed the network management.
So instead of configuring device
manually, you write a code that
define your design network state.
And instead of coping change work
correctly, you test them automatically
before the deployment in the production.
And instead of manual fixes when problem
occur, you deploy the correction.
With one click and this approach
based on four four core principle,
I will be explaining one by one.
The first is declarative configuration.
You define what you want network to
look like and the system determine
how to achieve that strength.
Second version, control.
Every change is track in gate.
Why?
To provide a complete history and
one common rollback capability.
Third, automated validation error code
before the production deployment, not
after customer are getting impacted.
You might be having thousands
of employee at your side.
Four.
Continuous deployment from code
Commit to production deployment.
It should happen automatically
with zero memory staff.
So in our environment,
managing over 500 side what?
Previously it took three
days, five days a week.
Now it's completing 15 minute
with 95% rate of success rate.
Let's discuss this SD Sdwan architect.
Let me explain how this work with
Sdwan using Cisco Web Taylor.
Web Taylor is a vendor I will be taking.
Example of, as an example
for better explanation.
So the architects, this architect
had three main component.
We manage V smart and V router.
We manage serve as a centralized
brain, which is handling the
policy, orchestration and
configuration management.
And what vs.
SMART does vs smart act as a control
plane making a routing decision
and managing the overall network.
And V Edge router we deploy
at every site as a data plane.
And V Edge router help executing the
policy and forwarding the traffic.
So the key advantage
here is centralization.
What it's mean when you change
a policy once in a, we manage
it's automatically updated.
Thousands of Azure router.
And your engineer don't
need to do a SSS session.
No copy pastes required, no
engineer intervention is required.
And when we are onboarding a new site,
the entire network configuration,
including routing security policy and
monitoring, it's deployed automatically
in instead of several layers,
declarative config.
Here the transformation are in
practice, what traditional approach,
500 line of CLA command, which can,
which may be error point for GI and
inconsistent and modern process.
One YML template, which should be
version control and reusable across
all your side and the process.
And this process has
three main step, step one.
Define the template.
For East side type, we, let's say we
have a nuclear site, so we should be
having a template for nuclear side
with strict security requirement.
And for solar side and solar side, which
have a scda SCADA system, it should
be isolation isolated and wind inside
with remote monitoring specification.
Step two, store everything in a game.
In gate every Modi every modification from
your engineer, you should log, logged in
with the explanation and change required.
Pull request re, which should be
reviewed by your senior management
or higher level of engineer.
Step three CICD pipeline.
This handled the deployment automatically.
Syntax validation run first.
Security compliant.
Check execute next and if valuation
passes deployment process to the target
devices via API Calls and let's say
if anything failed deployment, this
deployment should stop immediately.
The result.
Deployment that took me several days.
Now it's completing in few minutes.
So how GitHub work workflow
implementation work.
So here, how a real network
change flow through the system.
And there are several steps I
will be explaining one by one.
Step one, the pool sation.
This should be mandatory and
engineer need to add a new
wheel, for example, at any site.
So instead of logging into a router
and they create a, they should create a
branching gate, edit the YML configuration
and commit the changes with the, with
descriptive message and an engineer
should be having a open pull request.
Step two pull.
Step two is automated testing trigger.
Okay, so why ml? Why ml? Change The
syntax and policy compliance should be
validated by engineer to ensure that
change meet the security standard and SIM
simulation testing should be deployed.
We deploy there.
In a virtual environment, we
should mirror exactly same as
your production environment.
And all case result should be posted
as a comment in the poultry class.
Step three, peer review.
Senior engineers should examine the
business justification, security
requirement, implementation approach.
Read.
In reality, this validation is catches
the logical and design issue that
automation might be missing in step four.
Can redeployment this be begin this.
Begin after the approval
change, deploy to one or two.
Test site first, and the system
monitor for 30 to 60 minute.
And if metrics look good, deployment,
continue, it go by phases, 10%, then
50%, then a hundred percent of that site.
And let's say if anything fails.
Rollout, stop and Automated
Rollback restore the previous
state of the configuration.
Step five.
Production deployment with
the continuous monitoring.
Why that?
Let me explain you why first, the real
time dashboard should be there to track
the progress and health checks should
run continuously because if any trigger,
we should be having immediate alert.
In our home monitoring system and
this workflow really transformer
transform the operation from three
to five days of change cycle with
higher rate to same day automation
deployment with 95% of success rate.
Let's move ahead and move to
interesting topic of this session.
Zero trust.
Zero trust, security represent
a fundamental shift in
network security thinking.
I will be explaining while.
So the old model said,
trust but verify zero.
Trust says, never trust, always verify.
And this based on three core principle.
Principle one is verify
explicitly what it's mean.
Authenticate and authorize every
connection request regardless of source.
In practice this mean every
user device application must
be get getting authenticated.
Before accessing any resources in
your environment, authentication
required a strong method.
The method like multifactor
authentication and certificate and
authorization is continuous not one time
principle to least privilege access.
Grant only the minimum required
network access for each workload.
For example, ice cada system at VIN
side, which only communicate with the
specific control server and it has no
access to cooperate email, HR database and
unrelated to the system and 0 0 0 trust.
And four.
This through policies principle three.
Assume breaches.
Design security controller, assuming that
attacker are already inside your network.
This mean segment, your network.
So compromising one device doesn't
enable literal movement to other
and encrypt all device, including
internal traffic and monitor
continuously and detect the anomaly.
Why?
Because in, in environment, if, let's
say example for wind side, if device got
compromised, the attacker cannot reach
to corporate system at all or other
sites of your infrastructure because
each site should exit in own isolated
securities zone micro-segmentation.
Microsegmentation makes zero trust
operation at a scale level and
the four I will be giving four.
Real world example from
the production deployment.
First, consider the ADA system.
ADA system is isolated.
Example, we have a wind turbine, solar.
I inventor, which control
are completely isolated.
From your co-op network, SCADA
devices communicate only with the
authorized control server, have no
internal access and cannot reach
to cooperate email or file share.
Even if a taker compromise a co
they cannot reach to his ADA system.
Second application segmentation.
Database tires are separated from
application and presentation layer.
Web.
Web server cannot directly
access the database.
It's only able to access
through approved APIs.
Third user contacts based policy
access change based on user
identity, device compliance,
status, location, and time Also.
Let's say, for example, an engineer
accessing a from cooperate network
during business hour on a managed device,
which are allowed to the network, but
when same engineer from the public
wifi at nighttime on a personal laptop,
it should get denied and it should
require additional authentication.
Fourth traffic prioritization with.
With quality of surveys, the
mission critical is CATA traffic.
Always get a priority even during
attacks and wi voice traffic never
suffer latency or a packet loss.
My so microsegmentation deliver both
security and performance together
routing protocol automation.
Enterprise network run multiple routing
proco protocols across different domains.
In real world network, you will see
BGP for internal age and service
provider connection, E-I-G-R-P or OSPA
for campus and branch routing and the
OSPA for data center fabric routing.
The problem.
The problem is each protocol
has different configuration.
Configuration metrics and behavior.
Behavior, right?
So managing them manually across thousands
of network devices might be error problem.
So automation solve this through
continuous protocol optimization.
The system adjusts the routing
metric based on real time telemetry.
Let's say if link experience high
latency or a packet loss is, it's
automatically increase the cost.
So the traffic.
Prefer the alternate part.
Redistribution policy are optimized
automatically to prevent the
routing loop and suboptimal part.
The past selection are based on
application requirement, voice
traffic, route over low latency
fiber link both data transfer
use low, lower cost link only.
Let's take a real example.
Example wind side at a wind side,
ru at wind side, running A BGP
with ISP and OSP internally.
So automation continuously
monitored this link quality.
When ISP link degraded BGP automatically
fell over to secondary ISP without any
manual intervention of the engineer.
And if internal OSPF link fail,
the protocol reverts in a second
and we should be having immediate
alert in a monitoring system.
Let's move ahead and see the
network data center networking.
A CI fabric, the Cisco A CI represent
a shift in a data center networking,
and this based on three key pillar.
The first is application
centric policy model.
Traditional networking
is device centric, right?
But you configured v learn on switches.
You require access list on
fireboard and routing on router.
But a CA is application centric.
You define the policy based on application
requirement and a CA, translate them
into device configuration, which
should be automatically, and you never
configure any individual search code.
It should be automated.
Second spine lift.
Fabric architect.
Every leaf switch connect to
every spine, switch in full mass.
If any leaf can communicate with any
other leaf, it should be to hop maximum.
This provides consistency, low
latency, and high bandwidth.
The VXLAN overlay.
Which enable a mess in massive scale
environment with many millions of
endpoint and thousands of VLANs.
Third, API driven management.
Everything in a CI is API driven.
The third pillar, API driven management.
So everything in a CI is API driven.
You can integrate Terraform,
ible, and Python grid.
CICD pipeline automatically provision
the network resources as a part of
application deployment and you can query
the fabric for real time health metrics,
traffic flow, and policy compliance.
A CI integrate with S Dwan controller,
and when you deploy an application in a
data center, a CI provision the network.
And as driven policy update automatically
to allow the branch offices to access
the application and security policy
are enforced con consistently from
branch router to the data center core.
Let's see how cloud integration work
here in modern enterprise enterprises.
Which using AWS Azure Cloud Network and
some of them may be having a private
data center and your network automation
must suppose this reality, I will
be explaining three key integration
point first, AWS integration.
The AWS Transit Gateway Connect
multiple VPCs and on premises
network through a central hub.
So instead of managing point to
point VP internal between every VPCs.
And every site, everything
connect to transit gateway.
And when deploy a new site with the
Sdwan router, it automatically establish
the VPN channel on AWS transit gateway
and the site instantly have access to
cloud hosted monitoring application
without any manual configuration of VPNs.
Second Azure Cloud connectivity.
Azure virtual van provide hub to spoke
architect means connecting multiple
region on an on-prem premises site,
and Azure automatically manage the
routing between the spoke via hub
and automation script created and in
a virtual van connection, and when
deploying a new site, so policy based
routing directed traffic appropriately.
Third.
The policy consistent
across all the environment.
So this is the most critical benefit.
The traditional setup configure on
premises net firewalls, AWS security
group, zoom network security group.
Separately, this lead to policy are drift
and security gap and compliance failure.
Maybe the solution is define the
policy once in centralized engine.
Or automation, translate them into a
platform Specific configuration, for
example, is SCADA system communication.
This SCADA communicate only with
the control server on port 5 0
2, and it's enforce identically
on premises in AWS and in Azure,
monitoring play a crucial role.
So automation without the monitoring.
It's like we are walking blindfolded.
You need a real time visibility
to detect the issue proactively.
And this based on four key metrics.
I will be explaining one by one,
the first interface utilization
and the error rate we collect.
For example I am taking example
of our side, so we collect the
interface statistic every 60 seconds.
And if utilization exit 80%, the electric,
it should be if error rate spike,
incident ticket, open auto automatically
in our engineer support group.
Second application performance
metric, which include
latency, packet loss, and gt.
We continuously measure the latency
between the site and the I-P-S-L-A
probe and the net flow data.
And if latency exceed the threshold, we
investigate routing path and the link
quality Third security event correlation.
Our SIEM ingest log from firewall,
SD event controller and switch
machine learning model, detect
the anomaly, like a sudden traffic
spike or a normal IP address.
Which should trigger the
alert in monitoring system.
Fourth, policy compliance validation.
We continuously validating the de.
The device that run on approved
configuration and security policy are
consist consistently applying alert.
If configuration drift occur, the alert
trigger and automated remediation can be
reapplied to the correct configuration.
All telemetry fit into our into monitoring
platform, providing end-to-end visibility
from application layer to the physical
infrastructure when issuer detected.
Automated alert are trigger in engineer
queue and incident ticket are a
automatically with the help of run
book guide, troubleshooting it, get
addresses, and if the issue is known.
Automated remediation exit execute
without the engineer intervention.
Let me give the five takeaway
from the today's session, and by
following this, you also can implement
implement the SD in your environment.
So five action enable, five actionable
item steps you should follow to implement.
Implement in your environment.
Take away one.
Start the version control.
So before automating anything,
migrate the existing network
configuration into a gate repository.
Pick one device type and export
the configuration and commit them
into gate with meaningful folder.
Restructure and establish a
process where any configuration
change must be committed to gate.
And this cause nothing.
To implement, what benefits are I take?
Take away tool, build a validation
framework before deploying any changes.
Validate, validate them, automatically
implement pre-deployment testing,
including syntax checking policy,
compliance, checking and simulation
testing in virtual environment.
And this validation really catches
80% of the error before going into
production or before going to live.
Take over three.
Adopt gradual rollout
with canary deployment.
Never deploy changes to
all device simultaneously.
Deploy one or two test device first,
and then monitor first 30 to 60 minute,
and then roll out to 10%, 50%, and
then a hundred percent at each stage.
Automated health check, which should
be there, which validate the success.
Gross gradual rollout.
Limit that blast the radius of failure.
Take away four.
Integrate the monitoring earlier.
Deploy com Comprehensive
monitoring before the automation
to establish the baseline matter.
You need to know your network
normal behavior before the
automation changes to it.
And automation is only safe
when you can detect the issue
immediately or in instantly.
Take away five automated
rollback procedure.
Ensure automated rollback capability for
rapid recovery from the failed development
and maintain the previous configuration in
Git so you can always revert to the last
known good state of that configuration.
And test the rollback procedure
regularly before, before going into
the production production so that we
won't be having any false incident.
I must say start small, pick
one, use case, prove value,
and then only scale this work
across more than 500 side for us.
You also do it too.
So thank you so much for your time today.
To recap, traditional networking is
broken infrastructure as code fixes it.
You can start today with your version
control, the Journey to Automate.
Policy driven zero.
Trust network infrastructure
is achievable.
So start small and then go for scale.
I hope this session provided practical
insight and actionable strategy
for implementing infrastructure as
code in your network environment.
Thank you so much.