I'm Jorge, Platform Engineer
and Consultant at Petalim.
Over the next 30 minutes, we will
be talking about bringing your
data up to the Data Lakehouse.
If you don't have any of those two, no
worries, this talk is actually for you.
We will be discussing the
benefits and challenges that
may, lay ahead of your path.
And if you are already on your way, or if
you are very deep into this topic, I think
this talk will also spark your interest.
I encourage you to stick around,
maybe also share some of your
thoughts in the, in the comments or
throughout, throughout the conference.
and yeah, hopefully we can learn from
your trials and tribulations as well.
The thesis of this talk is twofold.
it is a well known fact that companies
face recurring challenges whenever
they engage with data projects, whether
it is because of inconsistencies in
data quality or, delay on insights
delivery or misalignment between
stakeholders and developers.
My opinion is that applying
DataOps and embracing Data Lake as
architecture is not just another
fix that some engineers, cooked up,
but it is rather a paradigm shift.
That not only systematically addresses
these issues that I mentioned, but also
thrives inside delivery and trust in data.
I don't know.
Is that arguable, polemical?
Let's find out together.
My hope is that you walk away from the
talk, understanding what DataOps is, why
it matters, and how it approaches the
problems that it says, that it addresses.
But more important than the boring what,
why, and how, what I really want to share
with you is some of my, appreciation
for the topic, some of my justified love
for it, so that you hopefully walk with
more perspective on the huge opportunity
that this, topic represents for the
organization, or your personal career.
About my personal career, I've been
working on data related projects
for the last six years, different
layers of the stack, everywhere from
platform to real time data analytics.
I have consulted literally
a dozen organizations.
and supported them on their IT journey.
And over the last, 24 months, been in
love with this topic, trying to find ways
to introduce DataOps to my daily work.
To keep the conversation very, pragmatic,
very down to earth and easy to follow.
I would like to start by telling you
the story of Fixit Incorporated, a
fictional company that has issues
with their own, own existing current
data infrastructure and are trying
to introduce DataOps to address them.
We will also see the grand
vision behind DataOps.
but when we want to start
understanding better what it is.
We'll need to touch on some key concepts,
although a little bit technical, we will
still always keep, on, on the horizon.
These three core fundamentals
for the business, namely cost
performance and understandability so
that we force ourselves to measure
how much better we are doing than
whatever is already out there.
We will then move on to the more
spicy, I would like to say, part
of the talk, where we will discuss
typical technical and organizational
challenges that you may face when
you want to embrace, full, DataOps.
We will then conclude with some
summary, and I'll give you some
pointers so that you know where
to go next if you decide that you
want to, join us in this adventure.
Without further ado, let's start.
So to understand why DataOps
is so important, right?
It makes sense to first try to
understand what are the problems
that it's trying to address.
To illustrate this, I will
tell you the story of Fixit.
This is a interplanetary megacorporation
with a headquarters on Earth.
They recently hit their
500, 000 employees mark.
They are deep into research
and development, aerospace
engineering and space mining.
They poised themselves as data driven and
cutting edge, and therefore they recently
hired their first ever chief data officer,
who launched a digital transformation
program to grow, to drive growth.
Now, central to this initiative is
the data engineering department,
which has around 400 employees and big
investments on cloud native compute,
storage, and martian BI tooling.
So the CDO, TechSavvy as he
is, starts by mapping out the
technological landscape in the company.
What he recently quickly finds
out is that All of the departments
have very well defined boundaries.
They all use their own
date, sorry, tables.
and essentially, the organization has
grown organically in that sense without
any, top level alignment of any sense.
They are all subject matter
experts on their topic.
yet they rely on data from
each other to actually perform.
Now the CDO wants to know how this works.
Organic growth, which, by the
way, is a situation in which many
companies find themselves, also,
without really realizing it.
we want to see how this organizational
growth has impacted the typical
workflows inside the company.
So let's take one example.
Let's talk about customer support reviews.
Let's assume that one of our customers,
the Fixit customers, he or she
buys one of these deep space mining
techniques, technologies or equipments.
There is a technical issue.
They place a ticket on the support desk.
One of our colleagues helps
them solve the issue, hopefully.
And afterwards, we get a
review of how well we did.
Now, Fixit wants to know, If any of this
review information can be used to drive
improvement on the customer support.
The way that they decide to do this
is using sentiment analysis on these
reviews that we got from the customers.
alongside with some other signals.
the issue here is that data is at the
moment on a relational data database
system managed by the customer success
department, but it needs to reach
the data science team, which are
the experts on sentiment analysis.
The data science team doesn't have
direct access to this data, nor
the expertise or resources to move
the data to where they need it, and
therefore they rely on the data union
department who builds a pipeline.
that copies this data and puts
it into a data lake for the data
sciences on a hourly basis, let's say.
The data scientists, they get the data,
they start performing the modeling,
generate predictions, and then they
push this to the fifth step, fifth
and last step on the pipeline, a BI
report, which itself will likely have
some kind of caching or some storage.
and then on top of which the
visualizations are built.
The manufacturing managers then
can look at this information
and take decisions accordingly.
Now on the paper, this approach might
seem very straightforward, right?
Very intuitive, nothing complicated here.
But if you look with a more
clinical eye, you will start
seeing some issues cropping out.
For example, There is at least
one hard data copy that we know
of between steps two and four.
This is where the data engineers, not
knowing exactly what they're moving
around, they just know that they need
to get data from one place or the other.
They don't complicate their lives,
they simply copy it as it is.
and put it somewhere else.
we also see there is no centralized
point of orchestration for
the whole sequence, right?
So if something fails on a step
two, there is very little chance
that the people sitting on step four
will have visibility over that, let
alone the ones who are consuming the
dashboard, at the end of the stream.
Finally, since we have multiple different
tools interacting, some of them being
RDS, some of them being data lakes.
Some of them being via reports,
we can presume already that
there will be different formats.
So data will be transformed into different
formats or three different formats,
at least throughout the whole process.
And that is inefficient, of course.
What happens then when all of these
issues are corping up in one workflow?
And we look at a scale when we start
looking at all the possible use
cases that the company has already
built or is planning to build.
The CDO, knowing that no amount of
documentation will help him wrap his
head around this situation, decides to
do a full, review, a full, let's say,
interview process of the company to try
to extract knowledge from the, colleagues.
So he sends out a survey.
And some rigorous questions.
Let's see what comes out of that.
The CEO tells us that the IT architecture
grew organically over the years.
there are site data silos everywhere.
We kind of suspected this
already, so nothing new.
The head of data engineering
tells us we maintain hundreds of
pipelines, moving data between all
departments, cyclically dependent even.
Okay, this is already new information
and not a good news, actually.
That means that if in an event there
is an issue with some pipeline there
is a chance that multiple pipelines
will go down, all at the same time.
the new recruits from Data Science tell
us that there are many obscure, column
names, transformations across data stores.
Even after six months of
onboarding, there is still,
let's say, ongoing training plan.
Thank you.
No doubt, this is frustrating for the
recruits, but also for the recruiters who
have to invest six months of training,
even before they start seeing any tasks
delivered by these new colleagues.
Head of IT tells us that, indeed,
there are too many systems
and many permission schemes.
The monthly bid is also unpredictable.
So not only we have, we only have we
little visibility on costs, but also
security is, hard to enforce due to the
complexity of permission is skimming.
Finally, the managers, the, the poor
dashboard users, all of this comment
actually is far more, let's say generic
than what the others mentioned, I
found it much more insidious, right?
There is some very, dark evil
lurking behind of his statement.
He says, can I trust
data in this dashboard?
Last time I checked, it looked funny.
It also takes forever to load.
So this means there is not only
a user experience problem here,
but also trust is broken, right?
my question, or it begs the
question, when, their incident,
this incident was, happening.
And it took three hours to solve it.
Would it also take only three hours to
recover the confidence of this user?
Most likely not.
Perhaps three months.
Perhaps even three years.
So all the information is in.
our CDO has tabulated all the,
the key findings into one table.
Across the board, we see data silos
everywhere, multiple copies and formats,
no single access control scheme.
Metadata management is parts, or is
a topic in part of the whole stack,
but not in some others, which means
we have a huge blind spot towards the
side of data ingestion and storage.
And orchestration and
monitoring is not centralized.
At least we should be happy
there is some in place.
That's it.
But this is far from ideal, right?
And at this step, the CDO takes, some
time and ponders the question, What
if we introduce DataOps, and mold
it into a data lake architecture?
How would that look like?
What would it bring us?
Well, in an ideal scenario, we could
cross out all of this complexity, right?
By first of all, introducing
a single lake, a single data
lake where all data resides.
This will in turn enable us
to guarantee that there will
only be one hard copy of data.
well, besides any backups for, disaster
recovery, but there is no necessity
to do hard copies of data in between
stages of a workflow since we know that
everything relies, everything resides
in one single place, in one single lake.
This also enables us to start
thinking about centralized metadata
management, a single, pane of
glass for managing metadata.
We can also think about, single data
format, or enforcing a single data format
at some point, hopefully an open source
format that will allow us to further
develop our own tooling in the end.
Without really thinking about,
vendor locking or, licensing.
we have additionally now the
opportunity to talk about centralized
orchestration and monitoring, and
last but not least, centralized access
management, management, whether we
do this via traditional, access, role
based access control or more fancy tag
based access control using metadata.
But in practice, is that even possible?
How would that look like?
And more importantly, what would that,
entail, for costs, performance, and
understandability, which are the core
fundamentals that we want to, let's say,
upheld from the business side of things.
Well, let's take a look at that.
We will need to start with a data lake.
In simple words, we might
have different business tools.
Some of them might be third
party, but all of them will
write data to a single location.
And this is actually a natural
response to these tendencies that
we see on system integration, right?
Because of the, sheer amount of
unstructured and semi structured data
when compared to the structured data
that we actually would like to have.
but that's actually not a bad
thing, given that the modern data
platform cost models favors, storage.
so meaning storage is cheap when
compared to pre cloud, It also opens
up the opportunity for us to enforce,
as I mentioned, this open source data
format, ideally something like Iceberg
or Data Lake, which are not only widely
supported, but extremely high performance
because of their binary nature, and
that also support now ACID operations
or ACID operations, let's call them.
This simply means that you can
read and write to these files.
without having to worry that you
will compete with write and read
operations from other users.
Every operation is atomic and therefore
there is no chance to collide.
This is a very well known principle of
relational database systems, actually.
We can further improve our situation by
bringing into the scope staging schemas.
And this is actually when the strength
of the system starts to ramp up.
Think about it like this.
We start with very raw data that
needs to be refined until we have
a final product which is ready
for the business to consume.
Now we know what these typical
refining operations are.
All that we need to do is to put them in
very well defined stages and execute them.
The good thing of having these
stages well defined is that if
something goes wrong, we know exactly
where to look for the problem.
We also have these smaller
steps, essentially a lot
of steps, very small steps.
And this incremental process allows us to
simplify troubleshooting, extremely, yeah.
To give you an example, suppose that
we have a staging stage where You or
stage with staging models when we where
we do only language translation for
the column names and the table names.
Additionally, we do some
enforcing of data type formats.
So if a column is a string, but
contains a date, then we save that
as an actual date object on database
and save some performance and costs.
Then we introduce another stage,
intermediary stage, where we
enforce, the actual open source
formatting that we wanted.
Maybe we add some partition and
some compression for the files.
since now our files are stored in a
much more performant format, we can
also think about, introducing data
quality tests and freshness tests.
Moving forward, we go
into the curated stage.
or some, however you want to like
it, however you like to call it.
here where we start building business
objects or entities that have some
meaning for whatever comes afterwards.
And all of this can be done
while orchestrating the
interdependencies between the models.
That means if some business
object requires two of the role
models, we can ensure that the
role models are updated before.
the business object.
All in all, this is very easy to
build, troubleshoot, and version.
And this is the key word here.
we are not really dividing data
into development, testing, and
production, like it's usually done.
Rather for us, everything is
production, but the same way we want
to test a new feature on application
and roll out a new version of it.
We do the same with the tables.
I want to create something new, a new
column for whatever business reason.
Then I can just create a new model next
to my previous one with a new version.
Let's call it B2.
and then I am ready to test, right?
I, of course, we need to communicate
to my, consumers down the line.
At some point, maybe I want to
deprecate my previous version.
So we need to let them know, Hey,
please migrate to the new one.
at this point, if necessary, right?
point that I forgot to mention
here, this orchestration between
the model dependencies, there are
tools already available for this.
There are a few, I want to recommend
dbt simply because it's open
source and he has a huge community.
We will talk a little bit
more later about them.
The next step into our, stack,
is actually bringing the house
to the lake, in the lake house.
By this I mean introducing a warehouse.
Why we want to do this?
Well, think about it like this.
If the staging schemas are the
perfect place for data exploration,
the warehouse is the perfect
place for data exploitation.
This is because warehouse, technologies
or solutions have much more
computational power, and they can help
you meet this time critical use case.
Like if you need to get a report on, on,
very frequent interval, and you need these
queries to really complete on due time.
Here we can also think about introducing
more fancy materialization strategies.
So, like, incremental
models, that means upserts.
So, not to completely overwrite
tables or, yeah, just introduce some
of them, but rather, update, rows
that are already existing on it, so.
as well we can, introduce more fancy
tooling that comes out of the box
with this, technologies, for example,
machine learning based queries or some
statistical transformations that might
be required for whatever business reason.
And here I need to make a point.
There are multiple data warehousing
solutions, but not all of them are able to
read and write directly into the one lake.
So, If we want to upheld the principles
that we are trying to build here, we
need to stay, or we want to choose select
carefully this tool so that we don't
build a new silo on top of the lake.
The cherry on the top for
us will be white tables.
And I'll tell you why.
First of all, there are
benchmarks I showed that in.
modern warehouses, querying white
tables is 50 to 25 percent much more
performant than running joins on tables.
They are also extremely intuitive for
the analysts and the business users,
so that they can actually really
get very fast to the results, right?
They don't need too much onboarding
to start, utilizing these tables.
Hence.
Reducing all this cost
of, high labor, right?
the, the BI tools also sometimes tend to
ask you for white tables as their input.
So, you can even think about them as
more or less as a requirement depending
on which BI tooling you're using.
the caveat here is that you might
of course end up with duplicated
columns in some white tables.
For example, you might have some
table with conversions on some tables.
Time range and some other table where
there are also conversions, but in
maybe less granular monthly basis.
And of course, you need to make sure that,
the users understand that conversions
can look different in different
tables and that there is metadata
that they can choose or they can use.
I'm talking about, catalog,
glossary, and lineage.
This should all be information that
should be available to the users so
that they can trace back all the changes
from the beginning of the data lake
all the way to their consumption layer.
that way you can preemptively
answer any questions that may crop
up, any doubts that may crop up
in the daily work of the analysts.
And that brings me to
the challenges, right?
So, we discussed already
all the benefits of this.
from terms of cost performance and
understandability, but it's still there
is a chance you will not be able to
make this pitch in your organization
and get a thumbs up right away.
Some typical technical challenges are,
for example, existing learning, long
running licenses with enterprise tooling.
maybe you get past that
and start implementing.
DataOps, but you introduce
way too much trivial testing.
This is to be fair, also something
that you will see in other
areas of software development.
but it gives you this false sense
of security that, might backfire.
we also highlighted that there is
no dev test and production stages.
We just have everything as production
with versions on the products or
on the tables or on the models.
Here what is critical is to
have good communication, right?
So if you, create a new version of your
model and don't properly communicate, you
might end up pulling the rock underneath
somebody, and this is hard to estimate
the blast radius that it might have.
Finally, one that I see often is
Although I think self explanatory at this
point, you should always try to build
a mock up, right, of your use cases.
Even if it's an Excel
sheet with dummy data.
But as a pre step to align yourself with
the stakeholders, which is one of the
core principles of data house practices.
but sometimes it's rush, it's, yeah,
it's brush off all under the table just
to, you know, get faster to the results.
Now, all of this, I think, can
be addressed with a call head.
However, the organizational side of things
may look different because, yeah, people
not always, operate with a call head.
Some comments that you might come
across are, the conversion reports
you build are not matching with one
of the ones from the other team.
So, this is this discrepancy
that I mentioned.
You can end up with two different
white tables, with the same metric.
but with different versions
of this information.
Somebody can also mention, cool,
but I'm not a technical person.
Why don't you talk to the engineers?
huge misconception here
of what DataOps is.
As I mentioned, this is a principle,
or one of these principles
is that you want to align the
stakeholders with the engineers.
And therefore, this is a joint effort.
From the side of the engineers,
you might also hear things
like, Hey, we have to work with.
Tool X for so many years.
Now you want me to change to tool Y.
But at the end of the day,
the, the only thing that is
constant is in life is change.
I think everything, everyone can agree
with that and DataOps is built for that.
It's embracing change,
and staying nimble, right?
To stay, stay on your toes, always ready
for whatever comes out of the curve.
Because piece of requirements will change,
KPIs will change, data will change,
sources will change, tools, people, and
best practices themselves might change.
but the, the whole idea is that
you, come up with a translation for
DataOps that fits your organization.
You put it to the test, you
review, and you make it better and
better and better, iterate over.
Small steps, but very quick steps.
Putting it all together, Data Lakehouse
and Open Source Storage Formats are
the natural response to the trends
that we see in system integration.
And they are, beneficial for us
from a cost perspective because
they take advantage of the building
models of modern data platforms.
they essentially trade more of the
computational costs for the storage
costs, which in turns are lower.
we talked about why tables are,
they're intuitive and performance.
even their, their, pervasiveness due
to requirements from the BI tooling.
we also mentioned they have a downside
because they are denormalized,
but the benefits outperform this.
Issues, let's say metadata, I
cannot stress it enough is the key
to removing silos, is really the
key to boosting understandability.
And given the fact that the cost
of a skilled labor are still
high and will remain high, the
understandability is a huge factor.
on your cost control.
So the more intuitive, the more easy
it is for people to find information
on a self service manner, the
better you are off for the future.
Finally, DataOps, as I
mentioned, is a paradigm shift.
It's not just something that
the engineers cooked up.
is the way that you treat data, metadata,
and how you adapt to change itself.
If you are interested to learn a
little bit more about this topic,
I can recommend a few things.
First of all, take a look at the DataOps
Manifesto, 18 principles, very clear to
the, direct to the business question.
You can also read the best practices
from the dev, devs from dbt.
As I mentioned, DVT is an open source
tool is very opinionated, but the
documentation is very well written and
the engineers will tell you every time
they take a decision why they do it.
So you can internalize, right, the,
the, the fundamental behind it,
instead of just falling blindly
into whatever the tool offers you.
I can also recommend you check
out the book from Dave Fowler.
And this is called Cloud Data Management,
Four Stages for Informed Companies.
It's an open, free book.
You can find it online.
It's a, it's a good read.
And, yeah, also maybe join
the community on Slack.
dbt community is, is very active.
very humorous at times.
I think there is upwards of 70,
000 people right now in there.
And, yes, you will always find somebody
with answers to your questions as well.
That's all I have for you.
I appreciate your time, your time.
And yeah, I hope to see
you on the next one.
Cha cha.