Speaker 46: Hello.
Good morning, good evening.
My name is, I'm working as a senior
technical manager in HC Tech.
Today I'm going to discuss about
operationalizing predict Analytics
in education by combining lops
DevOps strategies for scalable
ethical students success.
So first, what is predict?
So predicting unknown future by using
techniques like data mining, machine
learning by analyzing the current
data to create the future outcome.
So Yammer Labs is a displaying
that applies DevOps principles in
the machine learning lifecycle.
So we can see this in this session.
So the educational data challenge
opportunity, so digital learning
platforms not only generates
grade and attendance and also
generate huge volumes of behavioral
performance and engagement data.
So always raw data does not deliver any
meaningful sites if we harness it well.
So this data can help us to
predict challenges yearly and also
improve student success at scale.
So the reality educational institutions
struggle to transform preq models into
relatable production ready systems.
That's a gap between experimental
insights and operational deployment.
Which are robust DevOps
and MOPS practices.
So there are some advantages of ML lops.
So the ML lops brings reproducibility
so we can test the results of our model.
Then it also brings scalability
and monitoring and governance.
So from experimentation
to operational impact.
So experimental models is happening
in the development phase, like
proof of concept analytics in the
notebooks and sandbox environments.
So in production systems the models can
be scalable for a huge volume of data.
And can be monitored and gone by
ML pipelines integrated with the
different educational workflows
and some of the measurable outcomes
or improved student retention rate
engagement and student success at scale.
So this session bridges the gap between
data science, experimentation and
DevOps driven production deployment.
So the machine learning
toolkit for education.
There are many models available to
make predictions in educational domain.
So here I highlighted
some of the key models.
The first one is binary classification.
So binary classification is a
supervised learning technique.
It's used to break categorical outcomes,
like pass or fail at risk, or not at risk.
So in those scenarios, so logistic
regression is a statistical model
used to break probably outcomes of
a no patents by using input factors.
So logistic regression can be used for
possible predictions of the students.
Okay.
The next one is ensemble methods.
So random forest and grade interesting
are the high performance models.
So the random forest models make
predictions by combining the
results of many individual trees.
So here the prediction is by averaging
for progression models and by majority
work for classification models.
So the goal is to reduce the
variance, which is over fitting.
And the gradient boost make
predictions by combining many
beacon models in a shake shell way.
So here the final predictions
is by the sum of all the trees.
So the goal is to reduce
bias, which is under 30.
So the next one is networks,
which is time dependent model.
So long short term memory and
recurrent neural network accesses
capture temporal landing patterns.
So this model can be used for
multi semester performance
trajectories of the students
see advanced analytical approaches.
So unsupervised learning.
So in unsupervised learning
usually we don't have any specific
target for predictions, but the
grouping and clustering techniques
are any new or complex patterns.
The, there are a couple of key techniques
came means and hierarchal methods.
So the K means is used to group students
in a cluster by similarity levels.
And hierarchal methods is used
to group students students at
the different similarity levels.
So basically it's nested.
So neutral language processing is
used for sentiment analysis pipelines.
So in natural language process the
unstructured data is transformed
into such a format to make some.
To make some decisions and
performance forecasting.
So gradient boosting models predict
final outcomes early in the term.
So here we can see some of the critical
factors determining predict accuracy.
So the first one is data
quality and complexness.
So during any pre-processing steps, if we
see numeric missing values we can impute
with mean values and any categorical
values can be labeled with unknown.
And also there is some normalization
techniques to form the data
consistent across records.
Some of the techniques are
zero to one transforms.
Z transforms under long transforms.
The next one is future
relevance and engineering.
See raw data, transform raw
data into meaningful features.
So those features is very useful
to make accurate predictions.
So temporal considerations it's
it's for a time-based data.
So that timeline based data should
be lined properly in the right
order with the right timings.
The next one is sample
size and class balance.
So sample size refers to the
data points to train the model.
So always the large samples give
reliable patterns and higher
accuracy and smaller samples
increased noise noise and or fitting.
So the next one is model
complexity and interpretability.
High complex models can capture
can capture relatable patterns
and also achieve higher accuracy.
And the interpretability is the
key in educational domain which,
which shows which shows the
relationship between input and output.
So here we can see the evolution metrics
for educational predictive models.
So selecting the right metrics is crucial
for evaluating any predictive models.
So here we can see like the
classification materials is used to
evaluate the classification models.
So here the Confucian metrics shows how
well a classification model performs
by comparing ax actual, and, al labels.
So these four labels are created
from the Confucian Matrix.
This is the foundation to evaluate any
classification materials listed here.
Accuracy, precision recall,
F1 score, ROC, and a OC.
So here we can see some of the metrics
used to evaluate regression models.
So this metrics is used to measure
how well the model predicts
continuous value and also how close
predictions are to actual outcomes.
Some of the metrics are
mean, means quite error.
Root means quite error and
coefficient of determination.
So here we can see DevOps foundations
for machine learning success.
So any machine learning systems
deliver real value when they are
built on strong DevOps principles.
So the first principle is data versioning.
So here the data set so there.
It's used to track dataset
lineage, and any schema changes
and any transformations.
So the tools like DVC data
version control it's similar to
GI for YAML and data pipelines.
It's used to version dataset
and also it's used to track any
changes in data futures and models.
The ML flow is a machine learning
lifecycle machine learning
lifecycle flow to track to
track package and deploy models.
Next one is future engineering pipelines.
So here this is used the future logic.
This is here is to ensure the future
logic is consistent with being
training and inference environments.
The next one is C-A-C-A-D.
Pipeline for machine learning is
used to implement automated testing,
validation, and deployment workflows.
Next one is model monitoring.
If any model is deployed in prediction
and so that should be continuously
monitored to track prediction
latency, net quality, and directions.
So here we can see the typical ML
ops, DevOps pipeline architecture.
So there are six different core
layers of this architecture.
So the first one is data management.
So this layer choose the data used in
the training and inference environments.
It's properly ent and
validated and also documented.
So the next layer is model development.
So this is where experiment
experimentation happens in a
reproducible way and also model ing
and parameter units are happening here.
So model deployment.
So this is where DevOps
meets machine learning.
So ca creating ca CID pipelines
for morals, and also creating
automated testing gates and
creating development strategies.
And the next layer is model monitoring.
This is the most important
layer of machine learning.
So here we can track performance,
drip fairness, and alerts.
The next layer is in
protection and automation.
This is the operational backbone layer.
So the containers are used
to bundle bundle codes and
dependencies and libraries.
And then the process is used to automate
model deployments and auto-scaling
and load balancing processes.
So governance and compliance
is the key in educational any
many other regulated domains.
So to implement privacy
and audit processes.
So that's all about this architecture.
So here we can see some of the
infrastructure key points that show
scalable and there is reliable ML systems.
The first one is performance.
So unique high performance models
and real time inference systems.
Usually require more GPUs on autoscaling
services compared to batch pipelines.
So the next one is cost efficiency.
The cost efficiency.
It's about delivering impact without
overspending on any compute services.
So in this case serverless and spot
instances or good considerations.
And reliability, student facing
systems require high availability
and any failover in the system
should be up and operating quickly.
So detecting and managing model drip.
So while drip meters and
syndication, so usually the models
are trained on historical data.
So whenever any new data arrives
in the production environment,
the model performs poorly.
So deep direction systems are used to
compare statistical properties of training
data against production inference.
So if there is any deviation,
it is flagged before it
impact any production quality.
So governance, so always fairness,
transparency and privacy are
essential because they ensure our
systems treat equally everyone.
So the first one is fairness welded model
across different subgroup subgroups and
also implement bias mitigation techniques.
The next one is transparency.
So transparency is to show how our model
works and also show how and why prediction
occurs so that the stakeholders can
understand it and trust the decisions.
So we can deploy explainable
techniques like shaft and lime.
So the next one is privacy, is
to implement implement secure
and restricted role-based access
controls to comply with ffa.
So FFA is federal law that products
privacy of the student records.
And GDPR, it's for European Union.
So auditability and
responsible deployment.
So model cuts are used to document
how the models build and then and
what is the intended user, the
models so we can document those
information in the model cards.
So for auditability model
cards is the backbone.
And automated validation is used to
verify fairness, privacy, and the
performance before prion deployment.
So the next one is human in the loop.
So human in the loop is also in the
design approach where human remains
actively the key in the key points in
any machine learning and AI decisions.
Audit trials are to log
predictions, sessions and outcomes
for audits and compliance.
So the final step is integration
with the student support services.
So real time decision support.
So any prediction prediction output
flow must be integrated with management
platforms and the dashboards.
So far, these, the a p driven
architecture can be implemented to
integrate data from models, output
to the dashboards, actionable alerts.
So transfer model outputs into
task list for advisors, tutors,
and support for decision making.
Continuous feedback and model evolution.
So this are, this is the standard
steps in any of the many of the
software development lifecycle.
So the first one is deploy,
monitor, collect feedback,
and the last step is irate.
So retain models with updated
data and updated futures
with improved architectures.
So production ML systems
are never finished.
Continuous improvement loops and
choose model remains effective.
Practical guidance for implementation
always start with clear use cases.
Define specific intervention workflows and
success metrics before building models.
Building Cross al teams combined data
scientists develop engineers, domain
experts, and compliance officers invest
in structurally lops tooling monitoring
platforms and governance frameworks,
prioritize ethical considerations,
fairness, transparency, and privacy.
Delivering scalable ethical
impact driven analytics.
See, at the end, operationalizing
operat analytics and education is
by combining strong ops practices
with the ethical governance so that
institutions can deploy the morals
that are scalable and trustworthy.
So this approach measurably improves
student retention rate engagement,
success and success at institution level.
So that's all about this session.
So if record, we can collaborate
together to build analytics system in the
educational domain by combining machine
learning and strong DevOps principles.
Thank you.