All right.
Thanks for watching my session.
this is culture is still a challenge.
I am Mandy Walls.
I am a developer advocate,
DevOps advocate at PagerDuty.
I'm always happy to chat about stuff.
I'm not going to be talking
about PagerDuty today.
Always happy to chat if you
want to reach out to me.
I'm M Walls of PagerDuty.
com.
Or, I'm LNXCHK, mostly on Blue Sky.
and you can always reach out on LinkedIn.
So, this is a topic that I've been
thinking about for a long time.
I wrote this white paper, Building a
DevOps Culture for O'Reilly in 2012.
So, yeah, we've been
at this a while, right?
DevOps being sort of this combination
of tools and people and processes
and how it sometimes gets hung up.
And still gets hung up, right, on the
cultural bits because organizational
culture is a challenge, right?
It's hard.
It's, it's something that,
it can be different from,
organization to organization.
It's different in different countries.
it's different in different
kinds of organizations.
so we're going to explore some stuff and
hopefully you'll find it interesting.
So the first thing to really get a
grounding on is what is culture, right?
Okay.
You think about, if you ask your
friends, like, about the companies
that they work for, right?
What's the culture like over there?
What kinds of things do you hope to learn
about when you ask that question, right?
What, what is the culture,
what's the cultural mean to you?
about that organization.
And how folks respond is
going to vary hugely, right?
sometimes it's going to be
like unequivocally positive.
It's great.
We have A, B, and C.
maybe they mention things like
the PTO policy or the benefits
or the opportunities for learning
and all that great stuff.
Sometimes the answer will be negative.
The hours are long, the projects are
poorly run, the customers want too much,
and the sales team is over promised.
There were no raises, you
know, things like that.
And, those are obviously things that are,
are negative and reflect into not only the
organization itself, the value, the things
that your employee friend kind of values.
Sometimes you get these answers like, it
depends, it depends on the department.
It might depend on the
absolute team manager.
Some people might have amazing, wonderful
experiences working for the company,
while others find it absolutely.
demoralizing, right?
So the central organizational culture is
so weak or so unsupported that doesn't
reach every team in the company, right?
Often that is because of weak
leadership or overburdened leadership,
just the size of the organization.
We're in an era where some of the
organizations we work for are some of
the biggest that have ever existed.
And there's a limit to how much
people can really keep track of.
And that applies to our executive
leadership as well as You know,
a line manager that has 20
to 30 direct reports, right?
There's just a lot going on.
So things happen and they kind of fall
apart or get frayed around the edges.
So culture is felt in what the
organization rewards, what behaviors it
tolerates, what things it punishes, right?
How it enforces customs
or agreements, right?
All these things.
Over time, the culture becomes In
addition to that, a framework for
how the organization solves problems.
We, as an organization, value innovation.
So we may over, sort of over
optimize for innovation, versus,
you know, taking a harder look at
maybe revitalizing an older project.
Some of these things happen, right?
It forms the basis of the sort of,
What is, but also why is, right?
It becomes a story of the organization,
of the decisions that have been
made, of some of the people that
have been there a long time.
Like, why is that person still here?
Like, there might be a story there, right?
so when DevOps first emerged, and we're
talking about, what, 15 years ago now?
it was in response to dysfunctional
culture and technical organizations.
Dev versus Ops, combined with this,
like, pathological disdain for users
because what are they doing other
than messing things up for us, right?
DevOps really tried to show a better
way, but it hasn't, I'll say it
hasn't panned out for everyone, right?
so folks make changes around the
things they have influence on.
And if you're on a technical
team, that ends up largely being
things like tooling, right?
And so unfortunately, Some of those teams
are still struggling to make time for all
the other stuff that has to go into it.
So, the culture is really
to be human, right?
It's how we are.
We are a social species.
And as humans join together, they
create norms and patterns and
relationships and this sort of
scaffolding for how things work together.
And that is the culture.
Culture.
Right.
The hard part about actually
investigating it is you don't always
understand like where, where it is.
That's the joke with the, the
fish in the fish bowl, right?
An older fish swimming
by two younger fish.
He says, morning boys, how's the water?
And the younger fish are
like, the hell is water.
You don't even realize
you're in a culture, right?
It becomes so ingrained and just
the way things are that it's hard to
like disarticulate, which pieces are.
cultural pieces and where
did that culture come from?
Is it organizational?
Is it national?
Is it something that is, you
know, regional to the place
where you're actually located?
And, and some of those things
can be, super hard to deal with.
But, the good part is, it's
been around for a while, right?
So, going back, and not just back
15 years to the beginning of DevOps,
let's go back to the Hundred Years War.
And this is 13th century
France, all right?
And I will admit that because
I am an American and had, U.
S.
high school history, did not learn
anything really about European
history after the fall of Rome until
1492, because obviously the most
important thing the Europeans ever
did was send ships to the New World.
Right?
Because why would you care
about what happened in between?
so, the Battle of Crecy was
part of the Hundred Years War.
I first heard of it on an episode
of Midsummer Murders, if you're
familiar with that TV show in the UK.
and it was all about the, the descendants
of people who had fought in the battle.
But we'll get there.
So, the Battle of Crecy, was
related to the secession of England.
the kingdom of France.
So the French king died, he didn't have
any sons or nephews from his brothers.
He had a nephew from his sister
who happened to be the king
of England at the time, right?
And England In the 13th century is
kind of the poor relations, of France.
and then you've got the, his cousins,
the dead king's cousins in France,
a whole bunch of them, plus a number
of other, like, dukes and rulers, and
for some reason the king of Bohemia
was there because he was bored.
You know, it's just kind of crazy.
But, so the English arrive
in northern France, right?
They cross the Channel, They land
in northern France, and they're
just kind of marching through.
They know there's going to be a
battle at some point, it's not like
these things are planned, right?
It's just kind of like when the armies
merge, there's going to be a fight.
And they're burning and pillaging along
the way, but they come upon Crecy.
And you can see from the picture, there's
this hill in this, in this area, and they
take this up as their defensive position.
They know they're not far
from the amassed French army.
And they found this defensive
position, just happens to be here,
and they're like, this is where
we're going to pitch our battle.
This looks like a good place to do it.
So, they put up their defensive
positions, they've got, you know, some
siege engines of some sort, but like
also, cavalry and their secret weapon.
Which, funnily enough, their
secret weapon is the Welsh.
So, you can see from the
picture there in the foreground,
are, dudes with bows, right?
Not just any bow.
This is the Welsh Longbow.
The Welsh Longbow is about two
meters tall, it's about six feet,
and it takes like 85 foot pounds
of pressure to pull the thing.
It really, really requires
a lot of strength.
Out of that weapon, though,
The projectiles are amazing.
legendary, archer could, shoot a man on
horseback, go through his leg, through,
through his saddle, kill his horse, right?
That's how powerful these things were.
The French did not know about the
Welsh Longbow when they marched
into the field to start this battle.
They arrive sort of midday.
The English are expecting them to be
like, Ah, we'll start the battle tomorrow.
It's gonna be dark soon.
You know, you know, it's too late.
We'll start the battle in the morning
when everybody's fresh and had breakfast.
The French are like, No,
we're doing this now.
And they just start
marching onto the field.
Um, the Welsh just start pulling
arrows after arrow after arrow.
And, A well trained longbowman
can fire like a dozen or more
of these things a minute, right?
They're just like going straight at it.
It's amazing, right?
And they're just plowing
through the French and the
French have no idea what to do.
There's some walkie talkies.
They've got all these like weird leaders.
They're not really allies
of a permanent sort.
They're kind of like temporary alliances
while this battle is being fought
against the English and then they're
going to fight against themselves
later anyway to figure all things out.
So, they're not really an army
the way we think of it, right?
There's no one person definitely
in charge of absolutely everything.
There's Philip, who is sort of the
presumptive heir, and he's marginally
in charge, but he's not in the front.
So some of his cousins, some of these
other folks, are out in the front, and
the French culture at the time, much
like we find other sort of medieval sort
of cultures that, you know, you kind
of think about in sort of an infectual
term, is to die in battle is to die
with honor, and they just go for it.
And they are mowed down
like they are grass.
And Phillip's like, Well,
we should probably retreat.
There's no way to do that.
They don't want to do that anyhow, because
to die in battle is to die with honor.
So, in the end, of
course, the French lose.
Right?
They had not expected to lose.
They outnumbered the English somewhere
between 7, 000 and 15, 000 militants.
No one really knows how many folks were
there because some of them are just like
farmers who were out for a jaunt and
it was like it was August so it's kind
of slow time on the farm or whatever.
The French had amassed an army of like
20 to 30, 000 men, right, and they
were just decimated during this battle.
They had nowhere to go
with their assumptions.
They assumed they were going to
go on to this field of battle and
it would be hand to hand melee.
Because that's what they were doing.
That's what had been the path of
battle for, hundreds of years, right?
Because the French and English have
always been at each other's throats.
Instead, no.
Whole new paradigm.
Changed the format, changed the face
of war in Europe until the introduction
of gunpowder like 150 years later.
These longbows.
So, changed all assumptions.
about how you were going to approach the
problem of going into battle with English.
But the French had no prior experience or
prior scaffolding to make new decisions
based on the change of circumstances
when they were met with this new weapon.
So there's a whole
other story, about this.
I found it really interesting.
it was in an episode of a podcast.
I will link to it at the end of
the episode, the end of my talk, so
that, you can listen to it as well.
But it's super interesting, right?
But like As you're thinking about
this, you're thinking, Ah, that's
a, that's a 13th century, man.
That's hundreds of years ago.
And, at the time, the biggest
organizations on the planet were probably
the Catholic Church and these armies.
And these armies weren't
permanent standing armies.
They were just kind of like, you grabbed
who you could grab, who was available
on some campaign you decided to run.
They weren't drilled armies.
Right?
The Longbowmen, the Crossbowmen, the
Cavalry, they'd been trained, but most of
them weren't professional soldiers, right?
They were just kind of a ragtag bunch
of folks that got caught up in it.
So, a lot of things about organizations,
organizational behaviors, even go back
as far as, like I say, the 13th century.
So that makes it hard, right?
That gives us a place to sort of
hang our expectations of what we can
learn from organizational behaviors.
So We know there's a lot of things
that end up being super difficult
about culture, and you have probably
lived this, especially if you
are sort of mid career, right?
And we know that McKinsey has looked
at this, and McKinsey, interestingly
enough, Like, whatever you think
about McKinsey, they've been in
everybody's business for over 100 years.
Like, they've been studying all
of this stuff for a very long
time in the modern era, right?
In the era of the emergence of
large corporate structures, right?
So, post industrialization, this
corporatization, all these kinds of
things that come into play, right?
And there's a lot of different
research, especially mid century,
mid 20th century research on how
Different kinds of organizations
and different kinds of management
styles all relate to this, right?
Because you've got, like,
hierarchical structures that
sort of adopt from military and,
like, all kinds of other things.
So there's been a lot of work on this.
So, McKinsey, though, really has
found a lot of sort of interesting
data on why culture actually matters.
And it's not like we're all
going into battle, right?
But culture does correlate
with performance.
60 percent higher returns.
For folks that they've found have
better cultures on whatever their
scales they're looking at, 200
percent of the bottom quartile.
Like, there's just a lot of things
that lead into better performance
of an organization based on how
the culture operates, right?
What you reward, what you punish,
how you establish norms, those
kinds of things all play into that.
Culture, very hard to copy.
Products and services.
Super easy to copy.
I can sell you the same thing, but I might
not be as successful as you are because
the culture of my organization is poor.
And that relates to, it sort of
trickles down into bad employee
experience, bad customer experience.
All those kinds of things are
downstream of that, right?
McKinsey has found that as well.
Healthy culture facilitates adaptability.
You want to be adaptable.
When the battle changes, when the
circumstances change, if your culture says
we only value the things we have always
done, it's not going to help you, right?
70 percent of change initiatives fail.
That's a big number.
70 percent of those are
for cultural reasons.
So, You can do the math.
70 percent of 70 percent is
half of all change initiatives
fail because of culture.
You may have lived through this, right?
Like, I am sure there are people
watching this now who have absolutely
lived through failed changes, failed
transitions, failed initiatives about
whatever because some piece of the culture
was standing in the way, some value.
that was being strongly held
was in opposition to the
change that needed to be made.
Happens all the time, right?
And then unhealthy culture leads
to underperformance or failure.
Happens often enough, right?
Things just kind of fall apart.
So, culture, top of mind.
It is a topic of discussion and research.
There's dozens of articles
published in business journals.
all the time, right?
About impacts of culture, how to
influence culture, how to change
your organization's culture.
There's no magic quadrant
for culture, right?
It just kind of arises from any and all
of your interpersonal relationships.
And it can be influenced by things
like where you grew up, your faith
community, your educational background,
foundational experiences that you've had.
You know, influenced your values
and beliefs, and that all plays a
part in how you fit into a culture,
what you bring to a culture, and how
you're able to influence that culture.
And sometimes in tech, we think
about, you know, organizations that
start out as maybe a monoculture.
This is all Silicon Valley
kind of organization.
It's half a dozen white guys
who all went to Stanford.
They're bringing in a limited
number of perspectives and a
limited amount of knowledge about
the world at that point, right?
And that influences the culture
and, and things that are there.
but organizations now sort of know
that, you know, it's kind of important.
That's why all these headlines are here.
They're all taken from the
Harvard Business Review.
I think I have more here.
Yep, this one, this one right
here is from July, August 2024.
The headline is Build a Corporate
Culture That Works, right?
One that isn't broken.
and this one is November, December
2024, so only a few months later.
And this one is We're
Still Lonely at Work.
It's Time for Companies to Take a
Different Approach to Culture, right?
They're everywhere.
Culture is important to
somebody writing papers.
but the hard part is like, noting that
McKinsey's findings That half of all
transitions fail for cultural reasons.
Recognizing that culture
is hard to change.
Like all these articles that have this
promise to help you build a more learning
culture, or build more curiosity into your
culture, or more resilience, or whatever
the vocabulary word of the day is.
It's going to be hard, right?
It's going to be super difficult.
And there's a good chance
that it's not going to work.
So, what are some of the Components
when we're thinking about culture, maybe
we're thinking about how this culture
isn't working for our goals, right?
What are the things that we're looking
at that are symbols of the culture?
So, this model is from Edgar Sheen.
There is, I will say, dozens
of models about culture.
You can pick your favorite.
I'm going to talk about
another one in a minute.
This is just an interesting one.
Eggersheen was a,
psychologist and, professor.
He did a lot of the foundational
research in what we now refer to
as organizational behavior, right?
So, again, something that kind of
started middle of the 20th century,
really got going in the 80s.
You're thinking about, like, the goal
and, Toyota and all those kinds of things.
All that, Deming kind of era
really started to bring a lot of
focus in on this and a lot more,
academic attention, we'll say that.
so Sheen organized
culture into three levels.
Basic assumptions make up the foundation
of your organization's culture.
These get formed over time as team
members work together, how they interpret
behaviors when they're interacting,
things like events and activities, they're
deeply embedded, right, to the point
where they're almost taken for granted.
it's a main part of like the water
in the fishbowl, right, the team
members don't even really recognize.
they're going to be things that have
been in the organization a very long time
that most folks don't consciously notice.
They're just, you know, they're there.
A new person might recognize them, right?
And maybe comment on them.
So.
Before I joined PagerDuty, I was at Chef.
And if you were a part of the sort of
DevOps movement when Chef was around,
you know, Chef was very sweary, right?
Adam, Jacob was very sweary, so we
kind of all took lead from that and
kind of, kind of sweary culture.
PagerDuty not so much, right?
Like, it's kind of different.
And as someone who does a lot of public
speaking, you want to, you know, I
want to sort of recognize the culture
of the company that I represent.
And so, you know, I was like, oh,
well, we're, do we swear here?
Am I right?
Can I use a swear word?
I don't know.
Maybe.
Might be okay.
But not something that they
had consciously recognized
when I asked about it, right?
Because it hadn't really
been part of the culture.
Then you've got values,
that middle layer, right?
These are the things the
company says about itself.
Sometimes mission statements,
things like that, right?
But also public statements that they make.
They're visible things, right?
they might be aspirational in some ways.
These are often the part of the
organization that we unconsciously sort
of associate with the word culture.
things like commitment to diversity,
work life balance, commitment to the
environment, maybe they are B Corp
or triple bottom line kind of place.
Like those things are
all part of their values.
And the most visible layer of culture
sort of floats on the top there.
And these are artifacts
that are produced, right?
A lot of them are easily
recognized by people even outside
of the organization, right?
Like commercials or advertisements, right?
But they're also identifiable to
people within the organization.
Not only because they wrote them,
maybe, but because they're part of the
whole feeling of, of things inside.
these can be your mission statements.
They can be formal procedures.
They can even be things like the
Walmart cheer or dress codes, right?
every now and then a big corporation
kind of pops up with somebody
rebelling against their dress code.
it's part of the cultural
artifacts there, right?
When we look at culture more generally,
we often find that, It may be easier
to divide cultural characteristics into
what's visible and invisible, right?
So you might get like a dotted
line in between, sort of down
the middle of that values layer.
it's sort of less of a breakdown than what
Sheen has made in this particular, model.
We see the visible characteristics
of local culture, like actual
society culture all around us, right?
You're going to get things like
the arts, history, religion,
all have cultural impacts, the
built environment even, right?
If you're like a fan of 99 percent
Invisible Podcast, like there's a lot of
good chunks in there about, oh, well, this
park has benches, but there's armrests
there, so nobody can sleep on them.
Like that's a choice based on
culture prioritization, right?
You also get invisible things like
work ethic, decision making, social
rules, gender roles, even kinship.
Like some places, have closer
relationships with kin that are sort
of further out in their, family tree.
Like that's all part of, of culture
that things are sort of just are.
They've evolved over time, probably with
reason, but they're just kind of there.
But we do have a place where.
You want to think about occupational
versus organizational culture,
and this is super interesting.
the work that Sheen did with
this, he was looking at chemists.
So people with the white powders
and the clear liquids and the
mixing and the munching and the
spectrometers and all that great stuff.
They sort of find that a particular
occupation, might have its own set of
cultural characteristics independent of
the organization any of those particular
practitioners might belong to, right?
So you've got chemists, they are
doing their work in a lab, right?
And a chemist that works for, say,
Eli Lilly versus Merck versus maybe
Johnson Johnson, they probably
have more in common to each other.
than they do to other folks in other
departments of their organization, right?
And you see this when you maybe
attend conferences, right?
Software engineers, other folks in our,
tech industry have our own sort of norms
and things that we find interesting,
tools that we use that have nothing to
do with anyone else in our organization.
And one of the One of the interesting
pieces about having large organizations
is you get a lot of these, right,
sort of micro, occupational cultures.
so it's, it's another place where
things sort of have like a push pull
relationship, like the organizational
culture versus what I actually identify
with as, say, a software engineer, right?
Because even the folks in this
picture here, right, I have no
idea what they're working on.
This is a stock photo that we
picked up somewhere, right?
And Even though I have no idea what
they're actually working on, like
that dude on the right, he's got his
laptop and he's got two screens up.
On his rightmost screen,
looks like an IDE, right?
So I can have some idea of how he's
actually doing his work, based on
the tools that he's using, right?
Because I can relate to that, as a, as
another professional in that industry.
And you can get pictures in your mind
of, You know, this sort of generic
software engineer, but you can also
do that with nurses or lawyers or
auto mechanics or the folks that work
in your finance department, right?
They kind of have this idea
of how they do their work and
what they sort of relate to.
And I think this is part of where sort
of DevOps has gotten hung up, right?
we've been trying to change
sort of occupational cultures
in a way that not everyone's
been maybe on board with, right?
Right.
And it takes time, it probably takes
generational shift, like it does
for other things in society, right?
You want to change the cultural norms
around how women are treated, or how,
homosexuals are treated, or anything else.
Like, it takes generational change.
and if you think about what a software
engineer might have expected to be
doing as their job in, say, the late
1980s, versus what it looks like now.
Things are drastically different, right?
We're no longer putting software on CD
ROMs and putting it in a box and shipping
it to the customer and saying, good luck.
And if you have help, if you need help,
there's this consultant over here that
you can pay 1, 000 an hour and they
will help you with this thing because
we're not going to do it, right?
And most of us are no longer
shipping that kind of software.
We're now shipping things that are
available sort of as a service that
changes the relationship, right?
Changes how we interact with our users
because they're no longer at the other
end of a shipped box of software, right?
They're at the other end of
a network connection and it's
much more real time, right?
And so that has required a lot of change
across the industry for, especially for
us folks who've been here for a while.
And hopefully we start to see with
newer generations and younger folks
joining the industry that things are
just done this way because it's the way
we've always, we now do them, right?
We now have SRE teams and we have dev
and ops sort of working together to
make better products for our users
because it's just, that's just the
way we've always done it, right?
So, the occupational culture
is super interesting and as
that work sort of continues in
academia, I hope it will continue.
see a lot more, interesting
things out of that.
Another model that I hope you have
heard of, right, because it comes up
quite a lot, I like this one because
It, to me, it feels like, again, show my
age, the equalizer on a stereo, right?
You can pump the treble up and move the
bass here, and like, there's the mids,
and you can kind of structure yourself,
what does your team look like based on,
all of these, sort of characteristics
on this Western model as well.
it's, and I think this one too is
helpful For folks at many levels in an
organization, because it, it, it sort
of refocuses you on your actual team
and the things that your team is doing.
And for, especially for individual
contributors, I think there's a lot
of pieces here that are approachable
for individual contributors.
Versus needing a lot of
executive buy in for things.
So if you haven't looked at the Westrom
model before, it's three basic levels,
or three types, categories of, cultures.
And Westrom pulled this out of research
that was done in, medicine, right?
So again, not in tech, right?
She was talking about chemists, this
was talking about healthcare, right?
But thinking about, three
different kinds of cultures, he
breaks them down as pathological,
bureaucratic, and generative.
And pathological seems
psychotic, almost, right?
No cooperation.
If you've got, you know, bad
news, like it's your fault that
you brought the bad news to them.
Nobody takes responsibility for anything.
Nobody's allowed to talk to anyone else in
their department until they go up to their
manager, and they talk to their manager,
and they talk to their manager, and then
has to go back down the other side, right?
Very dysfunctional.
Super dysfunctional.
bureaucratic.
Rule oriented.
Maybe you've worked a place like this.
Maybe it feels that way because you
work in finance or something like that.
It's kind of like more
rigid than other places.
there's a little bit of
coordination sometimes.
A little bit of cooperation.
Messengers are kind of ignored.
It's going to be somebody
else's problem or like some
executive has to make a decision.
We're not going to even
think about it right now.
You have very narrow, well defined
responsibilities, and you're not really
allowed to get out of that box, right?
You're kind of doing your thing.
Bridging may be tolerated.
You can talk to folks on the other
team in service of important things,
but, like, don't get too close, right?
Don't collaborate.
Like, you could maybe talk to them a bit.
Failure leads to justice, and
novelty leads to problems.
Like, you know, Thinking about
innovation and change and those
kinds of things is like, smack down.
kind of hints to why 50 percent of change
initiatives fail for cultural reasons.
The last one, generative,
performance oriented, right?
High cooperation.
You don't know what you don't
know, but the person in the next
team might know something, right?
So you want to be able to, Freely
associate with anybody who might
have the information that you
want or need for your project.
Messengers get trained.
How do we find information
that needs to be shared?
How do we appropriately share it?
What is the pathway for
things being, put together?
Risks are shared.
Bridging is encouraged.
Failure leads to inquiry.
Why did this happen?
This is your, learning
organizations, right?
This is where you've got incident
management comes into play.
We wrote a postmortem.
What did we learn about this thing?
And novelty gets implemented.
We want to try it, right?
We value culture, or value innovation
in our culture, so we're going
to try some things out, right?
So we're working on it that way.
As you read through these, you can
kind of get a picture of, yeah, as
an individual contributor, Like, you
can do some of this stuff without,
like, an explicit thing kind of
pounded into your head by a director.
You can talk to people in other teams.
You can publish the things that you've
learned during a failure, right?
You can put it on the wiki,
you can talk about it, you
can put it in a Slack channel.
Like, all of these things are really
approachable, so if you haven't read
through the Western, paper, the original
paper is only like five or six pages long,
super good to get a handle on that one.
And just kind of Look at it from
the perspective of, yeah, we want
to get to generative, recognizing
that we might be pathological or
bureaucratic about different things.
You might already be generative about
some things, but it all helps sort
of move things along and get you to
a place where the culture is working
for you and not against you as your
organization continues to grow.
So.
Part of the, the, the issues then
that, that sort of come up, I mentioned
as, as part of the occupational
culture, but tech in, in most places
is really, it's outcome based, right?
culture is judged by a lot of
employees based on how they're
able to deliver on their tasks.
Can they get work done?
It's a simple answer, yes or
no, most of the time, right?
Are there arbitrary or
capricious blockages?
Is somebody just sitting in your
way for the hell of it, right?
Like, oh, we've got a change review
board, but it only meets once a quarter.
That's useless, right?
Do goals and priorities
change all the time?
You're not really sure what you should
be working on and all these million
different things that come at you.
We have a lot of resources and tools to
help us diagnose and Get around some of
those stumbling blocks and impediments
we find in a lot of organizations.
But culture is really a
slow moving ship, right?
Like I said, it might
take generational change.
Some places, right, there might need
to be some turnover in some teams.
you find a lot of folks who identify
with, you know, culture version 1.
0.
Right?
That you want to deprecate.
the folks who stand in the
way of sort of every decision.
Right?
And sometimes that even means
running outdated versions of
software they can't secure anymore.
Or paying a long term contract
to the vendor because you don't
want to get off of something old.
and I often refer back to John
Willis CAMS or CALMS model.
Right?
It was originally CAMS and he
added lean to it for CALMS.
you can still find this post, on
the Chef blog from 2011, right?
What DevOps means to me was
the title of that, right?
and when we think about where we want
to get to with DevOps, where we want
to get to as practitioners, as members
of organizations, as folks who want to
facilitate Improvement, innovation, and
resilience, and all these things that we
talk about from the technical side, right?
What needs to come along
with us on the cultural side?
That C in that model is
absolutely the hardest one, right?
I often find that teams are good
at the other pieces because it's
based around tooling, right?
When we don't know what to do,
we can buy a new tool, right?
If we're stuck, we can maybe
try and buy a new tool.
Folks can find themselves a
language or platform to focus
their automation efforts into.
There's lots of that stuff now, right?
You can follow recommended practices
for metrics and observability.
And it's changed!
Like, things are way different
now than they were in 2011 when
the original post was written.
Absolutely.
But they are, in many
ways, so much better.
And there's so much more variety and
things available that you can make use of.
You can also publish.
Like, sharing is much easier now, right?
Everybody's on some kind
of chat tool all the time.
And it may have been HipChat or, or
whatever in 2011, you know, pour one out.
But, you've probably got a wiki.
You probably have some way
to publicly post something.
You might have an internal engineering
blog where you can share things, right?
We want to get do not repeat yourself from
the micro level in code to the macro level
in the things that we're learning, right?
And that all comes from creating
metrics and sharing things.
And that hopefully comes out, right?
You can do posts and reviews, you
can do brown bag discussions, you
can create a community of practice.
Even if it's just like half a
dozen folks in a Slack channel like
sharing posts, they're fine, right?
All that good stuff
comes out of it, right?
Yeah.
So that challenge sticks there
in that, let's see, that culture.
Especially for small teams and large
organizations, culture kind of feels
like an impetuous barrier that you're
like banging up against all the time.
and fortunately we can use some of these
description models to help us improve
things at maybe a micro cultural level.
Westrom's model.
To figure out what things we can change
and influence to improve our culture.
We can use some of the things from
Sheen's model to say, Okay, here's
what the organization is telling us.
Here's what it's published.
Here's how that fits or doesn't
fit with what we need to do to
make our, make our goals, right?
There's also some additional interesting
things, that have come out in the
last, I think, 10 years, dozen years.
one of those is microcultures.
And, this is a place where things are sort
of related to occupational cultures, but
in a more, less organized sort of way.
It's, it's super interesting in, in
a couple of ways in that, some of
the early research on microcultures
was actually done on Slashdot.
If you're old enough to have been on
Slashdot in the early days, because
it was a large community distributed,
but completely opt in, right?
We think about the things that,
that, Influence us the pieces of
culture that we kind of inherit
as, as we live through our lives.
A lot of that stuff is sort of
non opt in, non optional, right?
You live in it, right?
You didn't pick where you were born.
You didn't pick what country
you lived in as a child.
You didn't pick what your
faith community was as a kid.
All those things sort of like
built up into your sort of
internal representation of culture.
When we get to large online communities,
though, which influence a lot of what
we do in technology anyway, I think
Reddit or Y Combinator and other things
like that, even online, Twitter or Blue
Sky, whatever, that's all opt in, right?
Everyone who's there has sort of chosen
to be there for some reason or another.
And that sort of twists the way
the cultural norms kind of happen.
And Right?
They're not necessarily there
because they were part of a social
requirement, or it wasn't because
there were food borne illnesses, right?
The culture around food
consumption can change.
Any of those kinds of things might
have been like completely set up in
opposition to whatever prevailing culture
might have been there at the time.
So, super interesting.
There's a lot more work
being done in microcultures.
but they're narrowly focused, right,
on smaller groups of people organizing
around smaller sets of shared interests.
And, a microculture might be easier to
influence and make improvements on, right?
because you've got, like, maybe,
you've got a microculture maybe on
your team, or, maybe your team and,
like, a handful of other teams that
work on the same sort of platform.
Right?
If you're an application engineering
team working in Python, maybe
you've got another half a dozen
teams that also work in Python.
They're just working on
different kinds of applications.
There might be a place there to
influence a microculture around
behaviors for how you work on Python
and how you deploy those things.
And there's a lot of, you know,
Western model components that
can help you there, right?
The, the bridging and cooperation
and all that kind of stuff can all
help improve things along the way.
So, it's a lot of work, right?
if you're struggling with how your
organizational culture is impacting
you, impacting your job, unfortunately,
most of the time, the easiest thing
to do is to find a new place to work.
Because changing microculture
in an organization, super,
super difficult, right?
Because it's probably been that
way a very, very long time.
Or you can work to improve your
microculture and your local team and,
be kind of safe and secure there.
So there's, you know,
there's options, right?
Hopefully, for you out there.
so, lots of interesting
things to think about.
lots of reasons why we're
still thinking about them.
Right?
15 years on.
And, and why, we're still kind
of getting hung up on stuff.
And nothing makes me sadder than
reading the DevOps subreddit.
And listening, er, reading about some
people's struggles, in, in the practice.
And knowing that, yeah, we've
been at this for a while, but
there's still a lot of work to do.
So, culture.
It's how your organization
connects, right?
It's how people connect as humans.
It is in your organization.
It is in your personal life.
It is everywhere, right?
It's built on assumptions,
values, artifacts.
You can improve it, but not always
across the entire organization.
So you can make, you know, changes to
your local team culture a lot more easier.
And some things about it are just silly.
You know, this screen capture is
a social media post and the top
line is you can gauge a company's
culture by how robust and unhinged
the Slack emoji repertoire is.
And the bottom one is this joke, right?
It's another screen capture from
Slack that is someone posting, Hey
team, I have some bittersweet news.
After an incredible one year at
Ramp, this company, I decided
to continue working at Ramp.
Like, you totally, they
had you in the first half.
You thought they were leaving, right?
So, the whole thing is a joke that, I'm
leaving on Friday, I'll be back on Monday.
And, but it's just kind of
framed up as a departure, post.
And then, the emojis are insane, right?
They're everywhere.
It's all kinds of stuff.
so.
Lots of ways to sort of gauge culture,
how fun it is, how robust it is, and lots
of ways to influence it down the road.
So some resources for you,
if you'd like some homework.
you've got Cautionary Tales, The
French Knight's Guide to Corporate
Culture, from Tim Harford.
again, this is a great podcast series,
it runs a couple of series a year.
Tim Harford is an
economist based in the UK.
and, very knowledgeable
on a lot of things.
And it was, there was a derivative
of that on a different show.
and that one is titled Blood and Gold.
And that's Dan Snow's, podcast.
And I forget what his
show is actually named.
and then you've got a whole
institute from, Professor Sheen.
He sadly passed away in 2023.
But his son keeps this running.
And his, papers and, and
other resources are there.
very much.
at sheenocli.
org.
Culture, four keys to why
it matters from McKinsey.
Another interesting one to take a look at.
Sort of a foundational paper
from the folks at McKinsey there.
The, summary paper from, about
Westrom from IT Revolution.
the original paper at NCBI, then
National Library of Medicine at NIH.
And another sort of basic one, right?
What is organizational culture
and why should we care from HBR.
So, Those are sort of some basic
ones that I like to give to people.
If you haven't read the
Westrom stuff, start there.
That's the easiest one to kind
of grok and get a look at.
So, hopefully that was helpful for folks.
I'm always happy to chat with folks
who are struggling with things around
their culture, especially since I'm
a PagerDuty now, around incident
management, automation, post incident
reviews, going on call, you know.
Even as a basic sort of assumption,
because lots of folks aren't into that.
So hopefully you enjoy the rest of the
sessions you watch at, Conf42 DevOps,
and I'll see you somewhere else.
So, take care.