Hi, I'm Sushil Prabhu Prabhakaran.
The topic that I'm going to
talk about is military digital
transformation, cloud AI integration
and smart workflow orchestration.
Here we emphasize on accelerating
strategic advantage to the cutting
edge technologies and also how
we are transforming military
operations with cloud computing, AI
and smart workflow orchestration.
There has been an unprecedented
improvements with respect to
the strategy capabilities.
First, there has been a 43 percent
increase in the operation efficiency.
Second, 67 percent increase in
respect to how quickly and faster
the decision making has been made.
Third, there has been 2.
5 times increase in the real
time situational awareness.
Meaning that, whenever, an actual scenario
comes with respect to the, field, how the
military or the defense team enacts to it.
And the last is the 70 percent
increase with respect to
enhanced predictive analytics.
This has been achieved through the
way the, the data has been, used
with respect to the models and the
algorithms that has come up with
the enhanced predictive analysis.
The next one we're talking about
is how the cloud AI integration
has enhanced data processing.
So this has two sections.
First one is the improved capabilities.
Second one is the smart workflow impact.
So when it comes to the improved
capabilities, so the advanced cloud AI
systems has delivered a very good 85
percent acceleration in respect to the
battlefield data processing speeds.
And, the critical mission response times
have also been slashed by criticism that
has enabled the commanders of the army
men to make faster and more informed
decisions in high stakes situations.
The other, we see, the other, enhanced
data processing is like what we
saw in the smart workflow impact.
So through the intelligent operation
and the predictive analysis, the
military logistics and supply
chain operations have achieved.
70 percent greater efficiency, by making
sure it has used the vital resources
that has reached the frontline units
with unprecedented speed and precision.
The AI driven additional support
system, I can split into four parts,
more like a pyramid structure.
So the first one at the top comes as the
threat detection accuracy, which is 91%.
So the big, the systems, the AI cloud
vision systems are, structured in such
a way that, either, thread comes in,
through online or the real battlefield.
It quickly identifies and acts
accordingly and in such a way
that, the real, our of the military
team, enacts and blocks the threat.
So that's the, top one.
The second one is the enhanced
situational awareness, which I
basically, in the few slides back I was
talking about the real time situation.
So how it quickly, enacts and then it
acts according to based on the situation.
The third one is the
faster decision making.
So, the, it enables the commander's
argument to make a quicker decision
and then, apply those accordingly.
The fourth one will be the
improved resource allocation.
So this one is more related
to how efficiently it uses
the available resources.
And this in turn reduces the,
cost, overall cost as well.
So the next one, we see
how, the integrated solution
had a real world impact.
First one, right, it has had a 3.
2 times, increase in the military
effectiveness, meaning, it had
an impact of cloud AI integration
overall operational capabilities.
Second one is 38 percent cost
reduction with respect to the resources
being used More efficiently that by
decreasing the operation cost through
the optimized resource utilization.
So there have been a lot of, case
studies, so more like successful
implementation across various
military branches and operations.
In the next one, we see how, it has
revolutionized the military training.
First one is the 61
percent improved readiness.
Thank you very much.
So, they do have some enhanced
personal preparedness through the
AI powered simulations, meaning
that every individual has their own
capabilities, and, how efficiently
that individual can be trained, this
AI powered simulation does that.
Second one is the, reduced training time.
So, there we have some accelerated
learning curves, which very, very
much focuses Only on the focus only
on the main objectives and it is more
personalized AI training programs as well.
The third one, realistic scenarios,
they have a lot of AI generated
simulations, that, that helps
in, battling the real situations
with respect to, how they battle.
So these AI generated
simulations play a crucial part.
this slide we're seeing
how we're strengthening the
cyber defense capabilities.
So 90 percent prevention rate, is
a key factor, like the, all the
air power systems have blocked
the potential security breaches.
next one is the 76
percent faster response.
How quickly they respond to situations
has had a tremendous impact.
So this has reduced incident response
times through AI driven threat analysis.
Next is the continuous learning.
So these AI systems have
a wall to encounter.
emerging cyber threats.
So they keep on learning as they
interact with their human beings.
So it's more like a
machine learning method.
So they keep evolving.
So here we see the implementing
challenges and solutions.
The first one, the top thread has
always been the data security.
So the expectation is 99.
99 percent of the time to be
achieved with advanced protocols.
The second one is the ethical framework.
We need to make sure the AI
deployment, takes place in a more
ethical way for military operations
and should not be misused.
So that's an important track factor.
Third one is the integration.
So, all the AI cloud integration,
when they, integrate with the
existing medicine, it should be
seamless rather than making it tough.
So that's, again, a very
important challenge.
So the return on investment
here has been at least 4.
1 times, with respect to the
investment on cloud AI technologies.
And then there has been increased
capabilities with respect to
improving the strategic advantages
of modern warfare scenarios.
The next we have the cost savings,
so which has a long term reduction in
operational expenses, and then future
proofing, preparing for evolving
military technologies and threats.
So, as we all know, the future
prospects and ongoing developments
are taking place as we talk the
AI robots on the real battlefield.
The advanced drone technologies and
many other technologies with respect
to AI cloud are being developed
and are being used as we talk.
So, we are basically embracing
the digital military revolution.
It has had a transformative impact
with respect to the cloud AI
integration and has been reshaping
the modern military capabilities.
That has been a continuous innovation
with respect to the ongoing development
of AI development technologies.
And then there has been strategic
imperative with respect to adoption
of crucial, that has been crucial for
maintaining inventory superiority.
Thank you.
That ends my presentation.