Speaker 37: Talking about how cloud
native architecture, DevOps, and
analytics can transform compliance
from provider network governance.
In healthcare compliance is often
seen as constrained, but with the
right foundation, it becomes a driver
for sustainability efficiency and
better member access and building
compliance centric systems at scale.
Everything I shall share to today
comes from real world healthcare.
It challenges
regulatory pressure is growing faster.
CMS requirements have grown
significantly in recent years.
While expectations are on cost
control, sustainability and member
experience continues to raise.
Organizations have moved to cloud.
Platforms have already seen
a meaningful gains in cost
efficiency and sustainability.
But ma, but many ha, many are
still struggling to modernize
the compliance itself.
Speaker 38: There are three main
Speaker 37: challenges.
Regulatory changes continuously
in and legacy systems struggle to
provide audit level transparency.
When compliance is manual
and fragmented, the risk and
operational drag increases together.
This is where the cloud native
architecture becomes critical.
Traditional on-premise systems are slow
to scale and expensive to maintain.
The cloud native DevOps environment are
distributed, resilient, and designed to
continuous changes for compliant systems.
The flexibility is not,
is no longer optional.
It is essential.
Once the foundation is in place,
the interoperability is key.
Regulatory data from CMS state mandates
and internal rules must be unified
data driven analytics, transform
from data into insights while cloud.
Native pipelines enables
continuous updates in real time
validation across the environments.
This approach delivers a real results.
We see a strong network
advocacy monitoring, and
faster provider onboarding, and
significant reduced audit risk.
Automation shifts compliance from active
reporting to proactive governance.
Analytics directly impacts
provider governance.
Higher directory accuracy reduces
claim denials and administrative
friction clean continuously.
Validated data leads to better
member experience and higher
satisfaction across the networks.
Credentialing is one of the biggest win.
Automated intakes, parallel verification
and real-time compliance checks
dramatically reduce onboarding time.
Provider moves from applications
to network activity activation
faster with a fewer hands off.
DevOps make all these
sustainable version controlled.
Compliance changes.
Automated.
Automated testing proceeds data
integrity during regulatory updates
and continuous monitoring helps detect
compliance drift along before audits
reliable directories compliance, improve
Speaker 38: directory transfer.
Transparency
Speaker 37: into better member outcomes.
Modern system create
transparency for everyone.
Regulators get realtime dashboards,
provider gets self-service visibility,
and member gets accurate information.
A shared source of truth reduces
the friction across ecosystem.
These transformation helps in
phases, starts with assessment,
design, scalability, architecture,
migrate incrementally, and optimization.
The key is minimizing distribu
while enabling long-term.
Agility to summarize the cloud and
DevOps enable regulatory agility
and analytics turn compliance
into governance intelligence.
The results are measurable, lower risk,
better efficiency, improved member
access, and intra optimal system.
Provider, a scalable function for future.
Thank you for your time and
you have enjoyed my session.
If you have any questions,
I'm happy to take it.
Thank you.