Speaker 5: Hello people.
My name is Avi Vinta.
I am very happy to speak to you
about the AI driven vectorized
motor health monitoring for any
industry for industrial applications.
And I would firstly like to thank
the conference 42 for giving me
this opportunity to speak with
you all, a little about myself.
My name is Avi.
I go by Avi Nasta.
I am currently a principal at MongoDB,
where I manage strategic relations
and partnerships with the SI ecosystem
pertaining to the IOT and the ai.
Industry.
I have close to 20 plus
years of experience now.
I have graduated as an electrical
engineer from my bachelor standpoint
and did my master's in mechanical.
By the virtue of that, I'm an
electro mechanical engineer.
And I'm happy to speak to you guys
about my passionate subject, which
is the motor industry, the electrical
machines, and the reliability around them.
Let's go back, I think, jumped
up, slide let's understand what
we are gonna speak today about.
If you really look upon the motors motors
have existed for several decades now.
The very virtue of a motor runs
on a principle where, you have
an electrical field and you put a
magnet in that electrical field.
There is motion or kinetic motion
developed by the magnet in there.
Now when you look into this this
this particular technique, there
is no rocket science there.
It has been well established and
proven but the nature of a motor has
been an integral part for all of us.
The way we clean our dishes, we
use a dishwasher that has a motor.
If you look at our washing machine
that has a motor, your, our heating
equipments, our cooling equipments,
the HVAC industry uses a lot of motor.
And there are industrial applications for
them, which goes into compressors, which
are required in a lot of factories today.
We need conveyors, we need
automation, we need robotics.
All of the places, it's it is a
requirement and it that has become
a foundational component of whether
we want it or whether we don't.
So what happens with that?
With that foundational
component, anything goes wrong.
There are down times, there
are catastrophic problems.
There are issues and the list goes
on and on, which is a integral part
of the complexities that keep coming.
Now the research or the thesis that
I have developed upon works upon the
reliability of these machines and also
predicting the reliability of these
machines, using certain techniques.
Now, one also has to understand that
these machines by the virtue are
foundational, but are also very commodity.
When you look into these particular
motors these motors, could lie in
the bracket of DC and AC motors.
This thesis that I have performed is
predominantly on the AC motors, although,
the BLDC motors, which are the brush
brushless DC motors and the switch
reluctance motors also come into this
arena of the thesis that I have performed.
Let sorry.
Now let's understand the construction
of these motors, before that let's break
down the entire construction of a motor.
Like I mentioned to you it works
on a very simplifi days principle.
You have an electrical motion
being electrical current that is
given to them to, to an equipment.
This particular equipment gives
you current take motion, and this
kinetic motion, could be rotary, you
can then translate that to linear.
Or more complex mechanisms.
Now, if you look into this entire chart,
and if I have to break this down as a
block diagram, you have an input, you
have a process which is basically your
motor, and you have an output, which
is basically your mechanical motion.
Now if you really look into all
of this the way you can basically
identify what are the areas on, on
these motors, could be based on the
design specifications of the motor.
So if the motor was desired
to run at a particular RPM.
It was desired to run
at a particular torque.
All of that is something that is available
with the motor, with the specifications,
and you can configure them using a drive.
The other aspects, could be, they have to
be positioned into specific environments
and you can measure the temperature
around it, the vibration around it.
And the electrical signals, which are
very foundational and many of the motors
today go through that particular process.
Then, you have alarms that come in,
saying that, hey, if the motor is
not performing well and, there is
an emergency stop, you can basically
have threshold based alarms around it.
Saying that, Hey, this has to
operate in a certain temperature.
It has to operate in
a certain environment.
And, you can basically set up those
alarms and they are existing today.
And the the way on this, the
predictability has been predominantly
by the intelligence of a person who
has been working on this particular
industry for several years.
Based on that, one can imagine.
Looking at a motor he or she can
understand that there are emerging faults.
And that is a signal and you
go and do the prediction.
But net, if you look at all
of the scenario, all of these
things, were done in isolation.
They were done in silos,
buckets, or in one.
Ability to identify
based on the experience.
One has experienced.
So there has not been the ability
to stitch in all of these inputs and
create an AI model to tell you when and
where and how the motors can go fault.
Now the approach that we, we identified
to, to solve this was basically taking
all of the layers that were foundational.
We spoke about the temperature,
we spoke about the vibration, we
spoke about the input currents we
spoke about the design conformance,
we spoke about one's intelligence,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
And, we basically try to create
a multi-layer decision process.
And that becomes my first point,
which is multi-layer diagnostics.
Second is, the ability to take the data
that is coming from specific sense points.
It could be a sensor that you have
incorporated in internally, or it could
be the soft sensors and identifying them.
To a particular failure point
or to a maintenance point.
And using the power of mathematics
in the form of vectors and
ai, is the second point.
Which we studied upon.
And the third was, to take the
layers of diagnosis or the layers
of decision making integrated with
what can be extrapolated and creating
an intelligence model around it.
So again, let me give this down in a
much more easier manner for you all.
There is this motor, the motor
has its own ways of of identifying
what can go wrong in it.
And to that, there are several methods
that are already been in practice.
We are taking those methods and creating
a automation through ai, to identify
what could be these failure points.
So let's break it down.
The way I broke down the block diagram
for us the first, is the input block.
Then you have the process block,
and you have the output block.
And let's call the
entire thing as a design.
Now the first analysis that you
know, or the layers that you are
speaking about for decision making
comes from the design conformance.
The design conformance basically indicates
to how is the motor supposed to behave?
What is the talk, whether it is being
driven on a 60 hertz signal, whether it is
to be driven on a 50 hertz signal whether
it's a four pole machine, whether it's a
six pole machine whether all of this has.
A good load condition.
Does it behave good on
a no load condition?
How does it behave on
a full load condition?
And creating the thermal
behavior patterns around it.
Predominantly this kind of a test which
is called design conformance test.
Is validated, through a circle diagram.
Where, you basically plot the the
thermal profile, basically put the
load, no load and load conditions.
And I'm sure, whoever's an electrical
engineer would've gone through their labs
and they know what a circle diagram is.
And, based on that you can basically
identify what is the motor supposed
to do and whether it is doing the.
The actual theory now, when you try to
take all of that data and digitize it
in the form of a data platform, that
becomes your design signature analysis.
Now, in the design signature
analysis, you're validating what
the talk requirement should be.
This could be an integral part of
a drive, and you're taking that
information or you can measure them.
Self, the RPM we are speaking of the
mechanical adjustments that you're trying
to do, in terms of whether it has been
fixed properly, whether it has been
housed properly and things like that.
The thermal behavior, because
many of these motors, come with
an integral thermocouple devices.
So you know, you will identify whether
these motors are going beyond a particular
threshold or not, and so on and so forth.
So that is the design signature analysis.
And this is layer one of multi-layers
that we were speaking about, which is
where you do this particular analysis.
Second.
Again, coming back to that block
diagram, you remember, you had the
input, you had the process, and
you had the output in the input.
You basically try to feed
in mostly a current, right?
That's how the motor works.
When the current is fed into the motor,
you basically identify whether it is
a 60 hertz motor or 50 hertz motor.
And based on that you
basically try to identify.
What pole machine it is, it's a
four pole or a six pole machine.
And on there, you basically know that
you have a constant voltage and to that
con constant voltage you're feeding in
current that's how the motor works, right?
And in this scenario, you basically
use the power of fast for your
transform, which is FFTs to identify.
The the FOIA transform of the
sinusoidal wave that you are feeding in.
Now, the sinusoidal wave
in this particular scenario
is got to be a pure wave.
Suppose, it's a sinusoidal wave, and
if you try to give sinoc sinusoidal
wave into a phosphoria transform you'll
basically start seeing harmonics.
You'll start seeing harmonics at say
this was a 60 herdz sinusoidal wave.
You'll start seeing them at 60 Hertz, then
you'll see them at one 20, then you'll
see them at 180 two 40 and so forth.
Now that's how the
mathematics has to behave.
But when you try to put the sinusoidal
wave, through the motor and when you're
trying to measure, there is a back
EMF that is generated by the motor
because every motor is also a generator.
Let's remember that.
And when there's a back MF these
sinusoidal waves, get a distortion.
Now when you take the fast four year
transform and you basically have
a current sensor and this current
sensor is fed, to your Fast four year
transform on your MATLAB or any of the
tools that you're using, you'll start
seeing that there is a spike at 60,
there's a spike at one 20, there's a
spike at 180 and but along with that.
You have side bands.
Now, your appearance on this,
would look like there is a one
60, and then you have these side
bands that are associated to it.
And many a times, these side
bands are considered to be noise.
And, we, I we eliminate that.
Right now in this particular scenario,
what we basically identify to do is, let's
call this particular pattern with the main
spike and the side bands as a signature.
Now this particular signature is
very unique to a motor that has
been produced and has to adhere to a
certain design conformance right now.
Now, I and assume that this
particular motor is going through
its own life cycle, it's losing its
stock, it's losing its attributes,
of what what it should behave like.
The side bands change.
So the side bands, could.
Change in amplitude, or
it can change in width.
And that's where, you identify
that there's something going,
something really wrong with E motor.
And you can identify those
and compare those harmonics to
identify anomalies in a motor.
So again, let me give you the layer one.
Layer one was on design conformance.
Layer two is, you're identifying what can
go wrong inside a motor through the input.
Now let's get to the layer three.
Now, like I mentioned, every
motor, has got an output.
Now this particular output is
what you measure the motor for.
How good the motor is, that's how the
output and the behavior of the motor is
supposed to work for a particular thing.
Now in this particular case, when you
look at the motor or when you hear the
motor, there are certain reactions to it.
There is a certain amount of noise
that is generated on these motors.
And these noise is not necessarily
only audio, it could be thermal, it
could be vibration, and so forth.
So when you try to house the
motor and when you keep them in
play there is a lot of, thermal
outburst that happens in a motor.
When you touch a motor, it becomes hot.
And, suppose, you know how much hot
it is becoming this could be a good,
could be a good example, from the
region that I come in, India, the way
we would know the blenders are getting
over overloaded, was the sound of the
motor or, touching these, the surface of
the blender, which would get very hot.
And we would immediately get to know
that there's something wrong here.
Either we need to reduce the
load or, basically get basically
get the changes done on it.
So it's the same principle, if you,
I imagine instead of a human being,
you have a sensor there or a soft
point, where you can identify the.
The vibration, you can identify the noise.
Best example, you're driving a
car and there's some rattling
noise that comes in your car.
The first thing that you as a human
being, would identify this saying
that, Hey, there's something wrong.
It could be because my dashboard not
doing well, or my seats are squeaking,
or there's something wrong with.
My engine, same scenario.
We are trying to now
apply that on a motor.
There's something going wrong with
a motor, it could be in the form of
vibration, it could be in the heat,
it could be in the sound and the
efficiency itself and that, we are
trying to categorize them as reactions.
Now, all of these reactions
could be absolute data.
It could be raw data and it
could be unstructured data.
Now storing all of this unstructured
data, you can basically pull them
into a document model in a database,
and then try to retrieve them.
The possibilities are endless.
But, the layer three basically
identifies the the reaction around it.
Now, what do you do with
all this information, right?
You had layer one, which was
giving you design conformance.
You had layer two, where you're
basically using current signature
patterns, to identify the default.
Then you have layer three
and you'll be like, Ari, how
many more layers do you need?
You're speaking about
multiple layers here.
Now the fourth layer that we are speaking
about is integrating all of this together.
It's basically trying to create
an A plus B plus C, equals
to some kind of an anomaly.
And that's where the beauty
of the vectorization comes in.
And that particular layer we speak, we, we
call it as the aging signature analysis.
Now in the aging signature
analysis, you have a baseline.
We, you remember I was speaking about
the standard signature patterns.
And then from there, you basically
are pumping in more data.
You're trying to extrapolate data from
design, through your current signatures
through your reaction, and you're
trying to create a algorithm around
it to identify points of failure.
So let's take an example here.
There is this particular motor
which was operating to, to run
in a compressor application.
Now, compressor applications are pretty
discreet, it was, the motor was being
leveraged as a limited anger talker.
And it was rotating at a particular load.
And suddenly, you identify that the
compressor values, were getting were
getting skewed up, which was ultimately.
Hampering the entire the plant operation.
And in this, what you basically identified
was my compressor is not doing well.
In a old environment, you would go
basically get the new compressor,
new motor, you'd replace all of
them, or, based on your knowledge,
you would do one or the other.
Now imagine a point where, you
have data that is coming from your
concurrent signature analysis,
which basically is speaking about
the motor and the motor health.
Now, based on the reaction, you're
basically identifying the application
that happened to the motor was at fault.
And the design conformance
saying that, your motor has to
behave in a particular manner.
Now that information from design flowing
in through input flow or current.
Flowing into the out the output could
basically tell you the aging trend
of the motor and that aging trend,
could mean bearing wear wear and tear.
It could mean winding losses.
It could mean resistance changes.
It could mean the overall
installation integrity.
The installation takes a
beating at a particular point.
Now, rather than changing the
entire system now, what are the
pointers that are spoiled in it?
Before they are getting spoiled and, you
have a predictive maintenance that can
be taken care on those particular meters.
So that's where stitching this information
from layer one to two, to three to
four which I call it as aging signature
analysis, becomes very important.
Now let's speak about how all
this data is flowing today.
There is the power of sensors.
Most of the sensors are inbuilt.
Again just be, take in mind, all
these motors are commodities.
They are bought by k. Or pounds and not
necessarily, to, to a specialized value.
There are specialized motors as well.
Please don't get me wrong there,
but, many a times, the amount of
r and d that they would do on a
particular motor would be very limited.
So what do we have to do with, we have
to take the power of the existing sensor.
And vectorize the data around it.
Vectorization is the most important part,
so you get the basic information in terms
of temperature, vibration, elect the
electrical inputs and so on and so forth.
Then vectorizing that data using the
power of mathematics to vectorize
and identify what could happen with
this particular vector on vibration.
What could be the.
The effect they could
the cause and effect.
And identifying early detections of
failure, becomes much more critical.
Now it's not given that, if you have
this data and you vectorize them,
you'll get the early detection.
Early detection has to be associated
with similar measurements and
similar defects and anomalies.
That the system keeps learning.
And as it keeps learning more
and more, the early detection
becomes a lot more predictable.
Now so like I was mentioning, creating
a platform, that keeps building upon
these anomalies, learning upon these
anomalies and creating these patterns the
trends around it you know are something
that we you know we identified them
through our con continuous learning
loop now this continuous learning loop,
leveraged a lot of database and I'll use
a lot of document models of database.
So there was a lot of unstructured data.
We could take photographs, videos,
and, try to pump in as much data as we
could and streamline that particular
data onto an AI path in creating models
around it using vector models around it.
To identify the specific failures, like
the ones that I was just mentioning
to you about, what are the operational
benefits and outcomes, just imagine,
the economics of a, of an industry
where, you have zero downtime coming
because of electrical machines.
So I've given you an example on
a rotating electrical machines.
You can use this for anything in,
in the electrical environments.
Currently we are doing more research
around it and, we would be having.
The you know the loads, no.
Typically an electrical motor is an
inductive and a capacitive node load.
We are trying to do this on pure resistive
loads, and more complex loads as well.
But what does that mean
from an operational benefits
and outcome standpoint?
We have more predictable we have
a preventive maintenance model.
That means, you don't have
to do firefighting after the
event has happened or occurred.
You can do it much before you have
reduced downtime, in, in specific
environments and factories, and
you have enhanced reliability.
So that means your systems
are a lot more reliable.
And the underlining benefit is the overall
cost advantage because of the workflow.
Streamline a streamlined, a workflow
that, we've been able to create with this.
So again, from a DevOps alignment
standpoint, there is data-driven
decisions, there is continuous monitoring
that is happening and learning,
and there is resilient operations
that is driving this philosophy.
I just spoke about it,
the implementation for.
For considerations include
an existing sensor network.
I taking the inputs from the sensor
network and creating a data architecture
a data platform, so to speak.
And from there, creating a system
integrated view and from there,
creating AI models and from that
AI models, basically feed in
information, for whatever application
you would like to do that.
That was about my presentation.
I would be very happy
to answer any questions.
Like I mentioned, my name is Avi.
I go by Aviana sister.
I am the principal at MongoDB
currently managing the strategic
relations and partnerships for
our system integrator market.
Looking forward to speaking with you all.
Thank you again, and
thank you for your time.