Hi there, and welcome to my
session on API first developments.
So my name is Tiago and I'm the
head of developer relations at Reli.
io, where we're building the next
generation internal developer portal.
I've been in the industry for
more than 15 years and I've worked
in very large corporations like
Microsoft, AWS, and PagerDuty.
I'm passionate about solving problems
with code and I love open source.
I've been a contributor and a maintainer
for many years and I really love it.
You have my contacts here
so feel free to reach out.
I must confess I'm more active
these days on LinkedIn, but feel
free to reach out in any of them.
So in this session, we'll explore
API first developments in how it
can supercharge your software's
potential in unpredicted ways.
And I specifically, wrote unpredicted ways
because one of the things that I felt like
more impressive in following this approach
is of course, like there's a bunch of
benefits, but the fact that you can
easily adapt and build new, capabilities
in front ends, is just impressive.
So in this session, we will talk about
the benefits, real world applications,
and some of the best practices and
things that I've learned along the way.
So first thing.
is what is API first development, right?
And so there are a lot of,
different definitions out there.
And depending, who's talking about the
topic, you might see some people focusing
more on the design side of things.
There are others that will
focus more on the development.
I will try to provide like a more
agnostic, perspective to the problem.
Man's.
maybe a bit higher level, but this
is the definition that I feel like
resonates with both sides of the thing.
So API first development is a
strategy that prioritizes the design
and development of APIs before
building the actual application.
So how does this look like, right?
And so I'll start with, the approach
that we have today, like the
traditional code first approach.
And this is just an example, right?
And it might change depending on how
you structure your teams internally.
and.
Basically, this example covers like
a scenario where you have two teams,
front end team and a back end team, that
will need to work together in order to
build this new feature, this new product
that you are about to release, right?
And how this typically goes, and
this is my, of course, my personal
experience, is when you have a new
product that you want, a new feature
that you want to release, you typically
Start working on an MVP, right?
And if this is like a product that
has like a specific front end, if
it's like a web application or mobile
application or whatever it is, you
typically start with the front end, right?
And so you have the front end team that
goes and builds like the first mockups.
So some first, version of the
API that eventually like a
design team, shared with them.
And so they start to write codes.
You have all the nice.
different components on screen.
You can start to experiment with some of
these scenarios, but there will be a point
in time where, this team will realize
that they need access to data, right?
and so in order to move forward, they
will need to create like a mock request
or something similar to simulate the data.
that is coming from the API, right?
And so this will allow them to
move forward, but they know that
this is just a temporary thing.
And so the typically, if this is a
separate team, you'll see like in a
very, in most of the organizations,
you'll have, the front end team to
create a ticket to a backend team, right?
So this is something that will
go, on the backend teams backlog.
they are busy.
and so you will need to wait, right?
So as a front end, as a front
end, developer building this
feature, you'll need to wait for
the backend team to be available.
And this might be just
a few hours, a few days.
Typically it goes like up to a few
weeks or something like that, right?
And so the front end team will
not be waiting, for them to,
for them to build these API.
that they have requested, they
will continue to work right and add
more complexity on their APIs on
their front end, the development
and basically, simulating these API
requests that they will be making.
So none of these will actually.
call APIs or interact with real data.
They will have mock data.
They will basically have
temporary code that they will
need to work on in the future.
But there will be a point in time
where the front end team and the
back end team will get together.
to agree on the API contract, right?
And one of the things that I've seen
happen like most of the time is that
the expectations from the front end
team will not be met by whatever the
back end team will need to build, right?
There are typically like challenges
in not having access to the data
that the front end team wanted
because the data just doesn't exist.
or, there are some security, limitations.
that the front end team didn't
take into consideration.
So there's.
Typically the need to reinvent a little
bit, the way that you access these,
the data through the APIs, right?
it's not necessarily the case like
every single time, but it's something
that I see very commonly happening.
So they will agree on an API contract.
And at this point in time, the backend
team will start to work, on the
specific, on the specific API, right?
And the way to unblock the front
end team as fast as possible,
because at right now they will be
waiting, for the API to be ready.
so the way to do this is typically
is through, the creation of a
basically exposing an API mock,
to the front end team, right?
This takes time because you
just agreed on an API contract.
You need to create all the like
the API specification, potentially
provide some documentation.
that's what you would ideally do.
Provide some documentation as well.
but just get something that provides like
all the different endpoints that you would
provide in the production, ready API, but
it's just not connecting to the API still,
to the database still, it's just using it.
mock data, for the time being, right?
But once you get that out,
you'll publish that will be
available for the front end team.
And this is where, typically if there
is like a huge difference between, the
expectations of the front end team and
the API contract that was agreed on.
typically this involves
a bit of refactoring.
So you need to, the front end
team will need to refactor.
the existing codes to comply
with the agreed API contract.
And so the backend team will continue
to develop because this is still an
API mock, they will need to write
the API code that interacts with
the database, with the different
data sources that you might have.
They need to write the test.
They need to write proper documentation
and they will make it once again,
available, through the intermediate
environments like dev staging and
eventually reaching production and the
front end team will do exactly the same.
and once that happens, it's
available to, to, to the end user.
or potentially available
to the end user, right?
So in this approach, you see a
lot of back and forth, right?
And that some important decisions like
agreeing on the API contract are made
in the middle or already throughout the
process of developing and writing code.
Which is not ideal, right?
Because there's a lot of time
wasted, on, refactoring codes.
There's, like additional complexity added,
to the process that wasn't, Necessary.
So if we think about an API first
approach, you'll see some tasks
here that are common in common
with what I showed you before.
So one of the main things that
changes in the API first approach
is that we introduce collaboration
way earlier in the process.
And so you will definitely spend a bit
more time in this first step where we
are all working on the API contract.
We all need to agree on what's.
are like the use cases that
we are tackling so we can
get to the API contract.
but the next steps will be much faster.
There are no like.
Waiting times.
so the dependencies are reduced a lot.
And so this is one of the
advantages of API first approach.
But let's look into this,
this example in more detail.
So in this case, I have a backend
front end and the products
owner, involved in the process.
we could have designers and the UX team
involved, in many other teams that might
be involved in this specific feature.
it's not just usually just the
front end and the back end.
That's why I represented
the product owner as well.
And so in the first step, they will
all need to agree on the API contract.
So they will discuss the use
cases that the product owner.
brings up front, they will discuss
like how the developers and end users
will interact with these specific APIs.
And one of the reasons why I also included
the product owner, in this first step
is because in an API first approach,
the API is actually a product, right?
You should approach it as a product.
So you would manage it as like
your front end application,
as your mobile application.
it's a product, right?
Even if it's not exposed externally
for other people to use, should still
be approached as, as a product, right?
and so in this first step, you would, work
together, you probably take a few days or
weeks to get into a final API contract.
But once that's done, you'll get
the back end team already working
on creating the API mock, and making
it available to the front end team.
And so at this point in time,
the front end team Is ready and,
actively working on writing the
code for this application, right?
At the same time, the backend is involved
in and, basically working on, creating
the production ready, API and the front
end team is doing the same, right?
So you don't have wait times.
Since the moment that you start writing
code, there are no more wait times, right?
And there's, of course, like some
back and forth because, when you start
working on the front end, you might
have some feedback on how, or like this
API should return result in slightly
different way or something like that.
There's always the need for some
tweaks, but you are working as a team.
You are involved in the process of.
Bringing these, product
to your customers, right?
so there's like less frustration
in the process, because the
collaboration started earlier.
You all agreed on one thing.
And so you build towards that.
And in the previous example,
That's not the case, right?
Because you have the front end team asking
for something, then the backend team
potentially not being able to deliver
that because of some limitations that
are not even, their responsibility, but
then front end team becomes frustrated.
The backend team becomes frustrated and
the end result is not the same, right?
So in this case, basically you see that
once the, the teams agree on the API
contract, the process is more streamlined.
So there's.
still, collaboration, but it's more
effective collaboration and the
end result will be much better.
so once they develop the features and
everything's production ready, they will
push the code to production in that code
becomes available for the end users.
So I feel like it's.
easy to see the benefits
of these approaches, right?
And in order to get that, there are a few
key principles to take in mind, right?
I could mention a few others, but for
me, these are the three main, principles
that you should take into consideration.
The first one is design first,
second one collaboration, and the
third one user centric, right?
So for the first one, APIs
should be designed thoroughly
before implementation begins.
And this is like the main ingredients
for the success of the, of this
process that we are talking about.
So if we have some kind of things
that weren't figured out during
the process, they will show up.
Later on, in these will cause
entropy and then you need to go
back into the design stage, right?
So make sure that you invest the time
that is necessary in the design stage
So you can basically have something
to work with and that leaves no
questions for any of the teams, right?
So this is really important.
The second one is around
collaboration, right?
So cross functional teams can
collaborating since the beginning
of the process is also key.
for the success of this operation, right?
If you don't have these teams
collaborating since the beginning,
they will feel like they were
left out and they are just doing
tasks for the other team, right?
That's not the case.
Your API is a product and that API
will interact with other products.
And so this is really
important to, to be clarified.
And so that's why you should
bring teams, really early in
the game and then user centric.
This is really important because
sometimes, so we've all been there.
we feel like we have figured out
like the, what the users would
like to see in the product, right?
That's not always the case.
In many cases, that's not
the case at all, right?
And so focus on the needs of end users,
talk to end users, talk to potential
customers, and talk to the developers
who will consume the API, right?
In some cases, if you are talking
about like an internal API, these
might potentially be the same.
But if you are talking about external,
an external API, that's not the case.
exactly the same.
And so you need to talk to people.
You need to focus on what
they are trying to achieve.
Otherwise you will be building
something that people don't want.
And so they will not use it.
That's as, as, as clear as that.
but there are some benefits of
course, otherwise I wouldn't
be, talking about the topic.
There are a few benefits that, and
I just mentioned five of them here.
These are some of the ones that I feel
like are, more relevant, in the process.
So the first one is on,
parallel software development.
So as you already, you already saw
that collaboration is a big thing here.
And I focus a lot on not
having teams waiting on others.
So teams working concurrently API
contract and eliminating sequential
dependencies is great benefit from my
perspective, it's always challenging
when you have people waiting for other
teams and what you typically do is that,
okay, these guys are really expensive.
So you cannot have them just
sitting there doing nothing.
So you will put them in other projects.
You'll put them working on other features.
And this causes a lot of context
switching for developers, right?
And it's really confusing.
It takes a lot of time for
developers to, to that.
So if you If you are able to streamline
the process, it's way better,
you'll get much better results.
Then you have improved
developer experience.
So since you have standardized
these kind of API, you have
something that is well documented.
you have, something that will, accelerate
the developer understanding of your APIs.
So this is really important because no
developer in the world will use an API
that is like not properly documented,
that doesn't, that they will need to
invest hours to learn how the API works.
So that's not a thing.
So focus on kind of standardizing,
and documenting your APIs.
to provide, a better developer experience.
Then you have the accelerated
development process.
And specifying the API up front
enables faster prototyping.
So it's crucial for the front
end teams in this case, to build
their own, like their front end.
for, for their application
building on top of your A.
P.
I.
And it's also a really good way
to validate, some systems that you
might be building some prod new
products that you might be building
or some integration with your A.
P.
I.
So let's say you have a web
application and you now want
to build a mobile application.
So you can quickly build a mobile
application if you have an API exposed
already, that provides you access
to the data that you want, right?
There's also the reduced
risk of failure, right?
So early API design catches potential
integration issues before they
become costly problems, right?
So they, this, like
identifying the issues.
Earlier in the process makes
it less expensive, basically
requires, less rework.
And, that's if you developed, develop
some feature on top of an API that
is not well designed, there will be
like a lot of hacks in your code and
that you need to basically, remove
that during the rework process.
And if the developer
that built that feature.
doesn't work for the company anymore.
It takes a lot of time for other people
to learn, what they've done, just,
to cover, the limitations of an API.
So focus on designing your API
properly and making sure that you
identify the issues earlier on.
And then, of course, the optimized
development costs, we already
touched on, the rework part of it.
so the fact that we focus on,
designing the API properly, from
earlier on, basically minimizes
the rework that is necessary.
Reduces communication overhead, right?
So if we are building on top of an API
that is well documented, we don't need
to talk to other, to the other team.
So it's time that we are saving.
It's time that we are saving
the other team as well, right?
And it also prevents technical depth.
So once again, if we are building acts
on our, codes just to cover for, some
kind of limitation on the API side, it's
always, it's always something that, is
not great in technical depth is one of the
main problems that we have, these days.
that is preventing many
companies from moving forward
and adapting, more interesting
processes and technologies, right?
try to avoid that.
and now I just wanted to
give you some examples.
I'll start with some
examples from, from, Relia.
io, so the company that, I represent.
And, so we follow this API first
approach, and this actually
allowed us to develop further
integrations, in a much easier way.
and we actually were, able to onboard more
customers to our platform because of this.
So I'll give you, like five
examples of things that we have
done or are actively doing.
at this point in time, building
on top of our API, right?
So first one that you see on the
left is a Kubernetes operator, right?
So we built this Kubernetes operator
after identifying that this was a common
pattern, for the customers that we were
onboarding into our platform, right?
So companies using Kubernetes.
using GitOps that had everything as code.
So we could actually populate
with the Kubernetes operator.
We could populate our software catalog
in a much streamlined way, which
allows us to save a lot of time.
So instead of have spending weeks,
making sure that the software catalog
is properly mapped and everything's
on boarded and all of that, We
could do this in hours now, right?
So it's just a matter of making sure
that Kubernetes operator is properly
deployed in your Kubernetes clusters.
You have all the definitions, your,
blueprints deployed in your environment.
And we are automatically getting this
information and it's getting synced.
in real time.
Another thing that we, started
working on is actually a Visual Studio
Code integration because one of our
values is to be where developers are.
And so if you can, do most of the
tasks to interact with, with rely
directly from Visual Studio Code,
things like, for instance, executing
a self service action or actually
see information from your software
catalog, related to your specific,
to a specific service that you are
managing, it's much, much easier, right?
So you don't need to move into, to go
into the web browser to actually see
information about, your services, right?
You also have Terraform, of course,
builds on top of our APIs, and we use
it to provision, new environments, and.
The next one is on Raycast.
I don't know if you know about Raycast,
but Raycast is basically, it's basically
a launcher for macOS and soon available,
in iPhone and Windows as well.
but basically it's something
that allows me just by clicking
command space to interact with
Many applications integrations
that I have in one of them is rely.
io.
So I can see, information
about my services directly
from basically any screen.
So I'm, I can do it
from my, from a desktop.
I don't need to open.
Visual Studio Code or a
browser or anything like that.
I can interact with, Reli.
io directly from my desktop.
And of course, like everyone else
in the world these days, we are
also investing in AI, in AI agents.
And so we are building that
on top of our REST APIs.
And one thing that I must mention here
is that we haven't changed our APIs,
to, support any of these integrations.
so of course we are adding new features,
we are adding new endpoints and all
of that, to allow new scenarios and
new features that we are building.
But we haven't changed our APIs just
to support any of these, integrations,
which is pretty cool because you can just
quickly, in a couple of hours, you want
Build a VS code integration, interact
with extension and integrate with our
APIs and with rely without any problem.
So that's pretty cool.
and just a couple of examples
from our customers as well.
So this was before we actually
build our Kubernetes operator,
but we were onboarding a customer.
that already has, like a Kubernetes
operator framework running.
They had blueprints for things
like, teams and systems and domains.
And so they had everything that they want
in code that they wanted to send to rely.
So why reinvent the wheel?
So they just made a quick change on
the, on their Kubernetes operator.
and they started sending this information
to rely once again, using Gaur.
using our, APIs, they were able to
do this in a couple of hours and
everything is kept in sync at all times.
Right?
And the other scenario is another
customer that wanted to integrate,
a security platform that we didn't
provide, a built in, plugin, for yet.
And so the option here was, we can either.
They could either wait for a few weeks or
months, depending on our, prioritization,
or they could integrate with our REST API.
And so what they did was that this
security tool, was, basically,
tracking security, security violations,
in their, in their platform.
They would send this information
into Logstash and Logstash
would basically parse.
That's, that information
in send it to rely.
io.
This was only possible, because we
had a well designed REST API that
is flexible enough to accept all
types of, blueprints in our platform.
and because of our
extensible data model, right?
So this allowed them to
just in a couple of days.
implement an integration that we would
potentially, take weeks to deploy in,
in production in our, plugin catalog.
So these are two scenarios, real
scenarios from customers, and this
is actually, something that, we are,
using with other customers as well.
So as you can see, like the Kubernetes
operator, we actually, are using this to
onboard other customers to our platform.
because we learn from the customer, use
case and we are implementing this and
using this with our, with other customers.
So some of the best practices
here, very high level.
So the first one is
defined, clear, and concise.
API specs, right?
So it's really important to
follow the standards, right?
So there's a lot of documentation out
there on how you should build APIs.
so the naming conventions and
using the right methods, giving
the right HTTP return status.
So all of those things, right?
Define clear, Concise API specs.
It's really important.
Keep API simple and easy to use, right?
So don't go, overboard.
just once again, focus on the standards.
If the API is not simple,
people will not use it, right?
So just make sure that it's easy to use.
It's flexible enough.
And, you'll have
developers using your API.
Otherwise it will get more
challenging to get adoption.
The third one is on API
documentation, right?
So API documentation is really important.
Even if it's just like the open API
spec that you provide to developers,
just make sure you have it.
Please do and there are a lot of tools
out there that allow you to generate
these documentation in an automated
way, like the open API spec and code
snippets for all your specific methods
for different programming languages.
There are a lot of tools out there
that will allow you to provide top
notch documentation for developers.
prioritize that.
Documentation is really
important if you are looking to
get people to adopt your API.
The next point here is around
automating API testing and validation.
So it's really important to have this
information or the APIs tested properly.
If you are doing APIs that are just
exposed internally, like impact is
not that big when compared to having
external APIs, but still it's really
bad experience if you are providing
a product to a customer and the
product is not working properly.
And so focus on having automated tests
for your API and make sure that, you
have a lot of tests and good tests
actually that test something and
test the behavior of the API, right?
The last point here is around,
monitoring API performance and usage.
It's really important.
Specifically for external APIs to
monitor the performance in the usage is
a really bad experience when you have
an API endpoint that is taking one or
two seconds to return a result, right?
So you should keep the
latency of your APIs.
to the minimum possible,
it should be fast.
It should be simple to use,
but it should be fast as well.
And you can only know if they
are performing, if you monitor
the performance of your APIs.
Also, you should monitor
the usage of your APIs.
Once again, this is important for
internal, usage, internal APIs, but also
for internal, for external, APIs, because
with external APIs, for instance, you
will start to see some new trends, some
new, some new usage of your APIs, right?
So you will see people starting to create
integrations with, let's say, DevOps,
let's say Azure DevOps integration.
They are calling your.
endpoint from Azure DevOps to integrate,
with, directly the pipelines with,
with, with your products, for instance.
And so this is something that you
will need to monitor the usage on.
And so you will learn about new scenarios
that you can potentially prioritize
during, your, process of deciding
where to invest your time next, right?
So this is really important.
So it's not only the performance, but
it's also the usage of these APIs.
It will allow you to define where you
invest your time to get better returns.
And so one thing I want to make clear, I
mentioned this a bunch of times already
in the presentation, but one thing that
I want to make clear is that the focus of
building an API as a product is that you
must focus on the developer experience
and usability of the API at all times.
No more APIs that have a bunch
of tricks to call them properly.
APIs have been designed
for many years now.
There's a lot of best practices out
there, a lot of standards out there.
It's just a matter of following them.
So it's not like you need to
reinvent the wheel at all times.
They have already, invented a
lot of people have invented this.
And of course there, there's always new
things coming up, but most of the things
I would say like 95 percent of the work
is already done, so just, read about it.
and, follow the standards
and just a quick recap.
So we close this, so adopt
an API first approach.
If you are looking for improved
collaboration, faster time to
market, greater extensibility in
better development experience.
So these are.
Some of the things that I feel
are really, important in the
goals of the API first, approach.
So if you see, if you follow this
approach, you will see, some of
these benefits really quickly, right?
And just a call to action.
so consider API first approach in
your next project, something that
would like to challenge you on.
and.
Start small, iterate fast, and you
will see the great results in the end.
Thank you.
you have my contents once again
here, feel free to reach out, in
social media and, see you next time.