Hello, everyone.
My name is Abdul Hamid Mohammed.
I'm thrilled to present my fascinating
topic, Internet of Everything.
How IoT is transforming industries
throughout intelligent connectivity.
A little more about me.
I'm an Oracle Certified Associate
Software Engineer with over nine years
IoT integration, cloud technologies,
and full stack development.
Throughout my career, I have worked
on solutions that improved operational
efficiency, enhance customer experience,
and enable digital transformation.
Today, I'll guide you through
how IoT is revolutionizing.
Industry globally.
Internet of everything.
How IoT is transforming industry
through intelligent connectivity.
IoT
is more than just a buzzword.
It's about intelligent connectivity
where devices don't just connect
but work together to revolutionize
industries over the next few minutes.
We'll explore IoT impact in
components and how it's paving
the way for an exciting future.
Let's talk about IoT market
growth and grow global scale.
IoT is growing at a pace
where we never seen before.
Think about smart cities, places where
traffic is optimized with IoT sensors.
Energy usage is more efficient
and life is more sustainable.
Now, consider the numbers.
The IoT market is projected to hit 1.
39 trillion and is expanding by 25%.
You know why?
Because businesses are realizing
the immense potential of IoT to
automate processes, reduce cost,
and better delivery experiences.
And it doesn't stop there.
15.
14 billion devices are already
connected today, collecting
and sharing data in real time.
By 2030, this number will double,
transforming how industry operate.
So here we'll talk about
IoT growth, global impact.
And how it is explosive.
IOT isn't just about connecting devices.
It's about creating systems
that drive industries forward.
For example, in healthcare,
IOT is enabling remote patient
monitoring, ensuring better outcomes.
In manufacturing, IOT
powers smart factories.
enhancing efficiencies and
precision and for cities it build
intelligent infrastructure for energy
grids to transportation system.
What's incredible is the scale.
By 2030, IoT connections
will be nearly double to 29.
4 billion, all supported by technologies
like 5G and cloud computing.
Here we'll talk about core
components of IoT ecosystem.
To understand IoT, we need to
break it down into core components.
So we have sensor, actuators,
Gateways, and finally, a cloud platform
sensors are the eyes and ears of IOT.
They collect real time data from
environmental changes to operational
metrics, think of them as the foundation.
Accurators are the hands that take action.
They execute commands, whether
it's adjusting a machine or dimming
lights in your smart home gateways.
Gateways process and secure data at the
edge, ensuring IOT system works smoothly.
They are essential for reducing
latency and maintaining security.
And finally, the cloud platform.
Cloud platform bring everything
together, enabling advanced IoT.
Analytics and scalable operation.
This components work in harmony
to deliver the magic of IOT.
So we'll talk about how IOT
is doing a real world impact.
Now let's talk about
IOT changing our world.
In healthcare, IOT has cut
monitoring costs by 35%.
Imagine a wearable device, alerting
doctor, before a complication arises.
That's the power of IOT.
In agriculture, IOT has increased
crop yields by 28 percent.
Sensor monitors soil conditions
while automated irrigation
optimizes water usage.
In smart homes, IOT is saving 23
percent on energy by adopting lightning,
heating, and cooling to your preferences.
They aren't just stats.
They are life changing
innovation happening today.
Sensors.
Technology and its growth.
So let's deep dive into
sensors, the backbone of IoT.
Today, we have 64 billion sensors
collecting data across industries.
What's driving the growth?
Maturization and affordability as
sensor becomes smaller and cheaper.
They are finding their way into
more applications from variable
health monitors to factory machines.
By 2028, the number of
sensor is expected to hit.
125 billion.
Unlocking insights at a scale
we can only imagine today.
Data, actuators act on
it in manufacturing.
Actuators power precision robotics and
automated assembly lines delivering 99.
9 percent accuracy.
But actuators aren't limited to factories.
In homes, they are behind the smart
thermostats saving 32 percent on
energy or wearable health monitor
tracking multiple vital signs.
The actuators market is
booming projected to hit 86.
6 billion by 2025 as
industry automate further.
So we'll talk about gateways.
Gateways are the unsung heroes of IOT.
They ensure device communicates
seamlessly and securely.
They process 75 percent of IoT data
locally, enabling real time decisions.
They secure data with enterprise
grade encryption, blocking 99.
9 percent of unauthorized accesses.
And they filter and compresses data,
reducing cloud transmission cost by 40%.
Without gateways, IoT systems would be
slower, less secure, and more expensive.
Now let's talk about cloud
platforms, the backbone of IOT,
where all the heavy lifting happens.
Cloud platform manages 80
zettabyte of data annually.
That's equivalent to streaming
40 billion hours of HD videos.
They allow IOT systems to scale
seamlessly from hundreds to millions
of devices while maintaining 99.
99 percent of uptime.
It's not just about scalability.
The cloud also enables
advanced analytics where AI and
machine learning process is 2.
5 quantatillion bytes of data daily.
Offering pre detective insights
with 85 percent accuracy.
So here we'll talk about
IOT connections and speed.
IOT is growing at an incredible pace.
Every second, 127 devices
connect to the internet.
Every day, 10.
9 million devices joins IOT ecosystem,
transforming industry in real time.
This rapid expansion is building
vast network that enables smart
cities, industries, and homes.
So now let's talk about
navigating the IoT landscape.
So how can business adopt IoT effectively?
Here are simple roadmap.
Accesses needs start by identifying,
Inefficiency IoT can address.
Where can automation or
data insights create value?
Choose components.
Select reliable and scalable
devices that fit your goals.
Implement security.
Deploy robust security protocols
to protect sensitive data.
Analyze data, use advanced analytics to
turn raw data into actionable insights,
driving continuous improvements.
Now we'll talk about
the future is connected.
As we look to the future, IoT is set
to revolutionize every aspect of life.
Imagine smart cities where autonomous
vehicle glide seamlessly through
traffic or personalized healthcare where
devices predict and prevent illnesses.
By 2030, IOT will integrate billions
of devices driving real time decision,
driving real time decision making
and unprecedented automation.
This isn't about technology evolution,
it's transformation that will
improve quality of life globally.
Thank you for joining me on this
journey through the Internet of Things.
IOT is not just shaping industries,
it's shaping our future.
If you would like to discuss.
This further feel free to
connect with me together.
Let's embrace the possibility IOT offers
and build a smarter, more connected world.