Speaker 31: Hi everyone, this is
Prima an from Amazon and I'm an
implied scientist at Amazon who works
in developing forecasting models
for capacity planning, inventory
planning and some other few things.
Today we are going to talk about
agent cost and autonomous AI system
that I have built that enables our
planners, especially who works in
capacity planning and analysts to in
to use autonomous AI system to create
forecasting models and deploy them.
And we'll talk about forecasting at scale.
Specifically for DevOps the
DevOps forecasting challenge
there is in traditional op there
are some traditional obstacles.
Capacity planning requires usually
multiple data science expertise.
Data scientists, planners, operational
engineers and the, these kind of
people are usually very expensive.
How to get the get and get hired and to
maintain their cost related to the models.
And then there is mo manual model.
Management consumes valuable time
usually, for example, if you have to.
Retune since the accuracy is going bad,
then you have to go back in, do analysis.
If there's different types of data
that has been added, then you have
to go back in and do manual analysis.
So these are some of the
challenges that we fail.
We see this static approach fail, that
evolving for evolving infrastructures.
For example you are adding more
cube clusters or more containers,
or more resistors, container resist.
Then you have to make sure
that everything is in the line.
Performance monitoring, lack predictive
capabilities, meaning when you are
monitoring the performance of your
stack, you do not know what is
going to happen day from today, day
from day after tomorrow, and so on.
So you have to make a system ready
to take care of these things.
And there is like real operational impact.
DevOps team faces constant
pressure to predict resources.
For example, how much compute they
would need to run applications,
especially if there are multiple
spikes they are anticipating.
For example, if there's you are
working in a company where you are
selling something in a holiday season,
more so your traffic will be higher.
So preventing that.
And then making sure that if you
predict your capacities in real time,
you are able to scale up very quickly.
And and basically cost optimization
related to infrastructure as well.
You can maintain and you can maintain
very complex ML systems, like how
much you compute need, how much
you need compute for inference.
Where you wanna save your data at.
So we are proposing a solution an
autonomous AI forecasting system
that you can plug into the database
where you have all your data and
it can learn different patterns and
do time series forecasting for you.
Agent cast, it's a fully autonomous AI
agent, agentic based approach where you
don't really need any human intervention.
You and just plug in the agent with the
data that you're getting in real time.
It could be streaming data, it could be
batch data, and it will learn from it.
And it is generate forecasting
based on the patterns that it sees.
It's DevOps native, so technically
you can just plug in and it'll do
all like predictive planning for you.
And it's continuously adaptive means as
soon as you see system is getting more
intermittent data or more sparse data,
it'll adapt to it and you can scale it
to adapt to different type of capacities.
For example, if you are writing more data
to some drive, it can predict disc usage
and memory usage and apps and whatnot.
So it's com.
Continuously adaptive.
It's a comprehensive model toolkit.
It has bunch of machine learning
models, deep neural network models.
For example, we use temporal
fusion transformers.
We use nbs.
We use LSTM and GR use and
transformer based models.
So it has whole suite of models
because we don't know what kind
of data we are gonna get in.
So agent decides what is the
best approach to take based on
the data that you are getting.
There are machine learning
approaches such as XG Boost and
for example if you have more d.
You have more independent variables.
Xeg boost kind of model works
better where you wanna do a very
simple forecast, Rema or automa, A
simple hold winters can work better.
So it has statistical model machine
learning models and deep learning
models, and it picks up based on the
data and performance on the data to
see what is the best model to use.
Intelligent adaptation in action means
it has context aware intelligence.
Agent doesn't really rely on pre-trained
models because it looks at your data
runs model to do training, hyper
parameter tuning and everything else
finds the best loss metric for you.
For example, are you looking for
me, RSME, or other kind of metric?
If you have your custom metric that
you wanna look at then it looks
at that, it discovers patterns
in your application usage or it.
It discover patterns in spikes and
it figures out what's noisy, what's
actual trend, and based on that, it
does forecasting and it does it with
pretty pretty good precision as well.
It can do multiple
forecast horizons as well.
For example, if you're planning one
month out or six months out, you
just have to change the forecast
horizon for the agent and it will.
It'll take care of it.
Figuring out what is the best look
back period for this kind of forecast.
And it also does probabilistic forecast.
So instead of doing 0.5 forecast
where you're just getting one
point at a time in time, it does
your P 10, P 50, P 70, and P 90.
So it just gets you a
probabilistic distribution rather
than just a point forecast.
The reason it is also like DevOps
centric is because when you're doing
probabilistic approach, you can also see
how much variance you are expecting in
your demand or what other things you need
in the cycle to adjust your forecast.
So it gives you different
distribution metrics.
Different level of deciles actually.
So it eliminates also like
manual hyper parameter.
Like you don't have to provide
a grid search manually and
run through different models.
It based on the data decides
a grid search for you.
And it has probabilistic methods
within the hyper parameter tuning
that finds the best hyper parameter
tuning based on each iteration.
And it is very seamless to integrate
into your continuous integration
and continuous deployment pipelines.
You just have to upload the code of agent
and plug in to the current workflow.
And it just creates the bells and
everything else to run the models.
It is find seasonal variances on its own.
What's trend, what's noise?
What's long range dependencies
and provides forecast based
on your infrastructure needs.
It has enterprise grade
reliability because.
You really don't need
any manual intervention.
It has its autonomous operational
capabilities, so it's running on its own.
It's performing daily or
weekly iterations of training.
It checks the wave in real time or
me, or RMS in real time, like how the
forecasted and based on that, if it is
deviation from what is the acceptable
norm of forecast, it like creates creates.
New training system where it retrains
hyper parameter optimization in,
then it like creates the final model
that is then used for inference.
So that's the autonomous operation.
As I said, it constantly looks for what's
the need of cap capacities, how much
hardware you need, how much info you need.
It does that continuous monitoring
and also keeps running different
kind of error metrics to figure out
that the forecast is not deviating,
it's a production ready agent.
You just have to plug into your
current workflow and it works fine.
Versatile forecasting horizon it
can do high frequency monitoring
real time infrastructure metric
with subnet granularity for.
Immediate operational insights.
For example, if you are running
a cube cluster where you're
running multiple parts, you are
up scaling to multiple parts.
It can identify that spike
in the time series trend.
And based on that, it can forecast
and tell how much whether, how long
and how much you need your info to be.
To be to be up.
And one of the reason, most of these
services on cloud have auto-scaling.
Versus what is the need of this is this
kind of forecasting system is like, auto
scaling is typically very expensive.
You can enable auto scaling and
that might work well for you, but
at the end, when you get the final
bill, it's gonna be very expensive.
So usage of this kind of
system where you are uploading.
Forecast from this agent into your
yam l configurations to get the
infrastructure scaling up or down
Is price wise beneficial and it
reduce cost related to your infra?
It also just like longer
medium term planning.
So like it can do how many, cPUs
or GPUs you need based on the
kind of task you're performing.
Whether it is a app based system you
are running on, or you are running
a ML based system, it can do both
long range capacity, like it can do
monthly to quarterly, up to three
year forecast easily based on the
pattern that it has seen historically.
There are multiple
components to agent cast.
First is automatic discovery.
Based on the time series data that
it reads from the data sources
it's does what is the best kind
of model for the time series data.
If you have a problem where you have
multiple independent variables and
medium or short term horizon forecast
ML based system like XGBoost or linear
model might work best where you have.
A really long range forecasting
need a temporal fusion
transformer or a DAR based model.
That might work because it can easily
detect dependencies in the long range.
Horizon long range time series
model evaluation is based on
you running multiple models.
You are checking mean absolute
error, may mean absolute percentage
error, rms, a bunch of other metrics.
You can also define custom metrics for
evaluation, and it finds the best model.
For it and a lot of time it can
also do ensembling of models.
Like maybe just not one model works
best for you, but combination of
two or three model works for you.
It can do ensembling as well and give you
the best results ensuring there is no over
referring to your time series forecasting.
It has intelligent selection
based on the analysis performed.
It can.
Find the best performance metric,
whether RMSE is the best way or
some other like MA is the best.
If you want to capture more
variance between your time series
forecast, you'll use RMSE, which
captures roots squared route.
If you want to do like a point wise
forecast, MA is more absolute, or ma
is more absolute, it can figure it
out that autonomous deployment is, it
deploys these model into production
environment, whatever it finds, whether
it is single model or ensemble model.
And it also performs continuous
evaluation of the model.
Based on that, it can
do continuous evolution.
If you need to rerun hyper
parameter tuning that can be added.
If the nature of data changes, it can
rerun the whole suite of models to find
what is the best model for the newer data.
It has real DevOps application from
infrastructure monitoring how your
CPU usage or GPU usage will look like.
Memory usage will look like if
you're expecting more spike.
It can predict how much more you need
based on more cost optimized manner
rather than just doing auto scales.
It can also be if you have network higher.
T traffic network usage it can enable
potential bottlenecks failure, and
it can give you the right forecast
for your infrastructure so that you
don't run into potential bottlenecks.
Capacity planning it's long term,
so like you can tell within one
year or two year horizon, how many.
What your infrastructure need
would be for different components
of your infrastructure.
And it can also do like
predictive maintenance.
So if you are seeing degradation
over time, it can do re rerun of
model, figuring out what's the
best model for the latest data.
It's built for DevOps scale.
So you can do different kind
of automated versioning.
You can do rollback capabilities.
If you are not liking them
all, you can roll back.
You can disable the inference system.
There is AB testing bill so you can
deploy in one system and leave one
system without the deployment and see
which system is performing better.
So you can perform all
kind of ab testing as well.
It can do performance monitoring, as
I said, like it can do wave monitoring
over time of the real time forecast in.
In the system, and it can tell whether, if
you're degrading and it can automatically
decide whether it needs to retrain the
model or find newer model it's scalable.
So your architecture is
like very distributed.
Everything from individual microservice
to enterprise wise deployment can be done.
Whether you're running on a simple
application or multi microservice
kind of application, it can be
plugged into both the systems.
The autonomous advantage is more like you
don't really need any human intervention,
so you don't need to hire a data
scientist or a statistician to run and
retrain and figure out what's the best.
Best model for your system.
It can do on its own.
It has its own probabilistic brain
that that it uses to make decisions.
It can reduce operational overhead.
So rather than, somebody telling, Hey,
we don't really like this model to
the statistician or data scientist,
it can decide all those things on own.
So like communication over churn.
It is reduced.
That's reducing the operational overhead.
Faster.
Time to value means as soon as
you deploy the model, it starts
generating forecast from quickly
like plugging into your system.
And that helps you get reduced time
from very starting point to getting
the forecast that is finally being used
to make decisions of your DevOps team.
What you'll see today is like
autonomous workflow demonstration.
Watch, agent cast discover, evaluate, and
deploy models without human intervention.
And this is the expectation of the agent.
Some of the examples involve
forecasting, CPU, utilization, memory
consumption, network traffic patterns.
Do you, are you planning to see Spike?
So things like if you're expecting higher
traffic load balancer scale up, scale
down and then the integration walkthrough
into the current into the current.
DevOps pipeline you can transform
your predictive operations
with using the agent cast.
The future of DevOps forecasting
is enabling based on AI agents that
can perform autonomous forecasting
without human intervention.
So reducing human decision making.
Human workflows and it
needs to work on its own.
Figure out bottlenecks.
Figure out what kind of utilization
are you or capacity are you expecting
short term, medium term, and long term.
And also do predictive maintenance of
the workflow, which is to understand
if you need to scale up, scale down.
It looks at also the vape and
map and RMC, what based on the
type of data you have to, to.
To produce the best solution
for your DevOps scaling issues.
So yeah, scale, infrastructure, auto
automation across your infrastructure,
not just like on-prem, but it can
also do cloud and any other hybrid
approach that you might have.
This is agent gas.
Thank you very much for joining in.
And I'm honored to present my AI agent,
autonomous AI agent for forecasting
to this elite group of people.
Thank you very much.
Okay.