Well, hi, everyone.
Amir here from Sensor.
I'm the co founder and chief product.
I'm very happy to, be part
of this session in COM 42.
DevOps 2025.
the name of this session is
Kubernetes minus the blind spots.
We're going to focus around how to
solve our Kubernetes observability
challenge challenges and how that
becomes a little bit easier when you
can incorporate real time topology.
so what are we going to cover today?
First of all, all of you,
most of your Kubernetes users.
So, you know, it's great.
But it's also very hard to troubleshoot.
we will delve into why it's hard.
To troubleshoot when we go a little
further, we were going to connect it
with the challenges of traditional
observability toolkit, meaning if you have
the classical logs, matrix, whatever, why
that coming alone is not enough in modern
dynamic environments, we're going to
cover the concept of real time topology.
How it different, how it different from
dependency mapping, what to do, why
and how to implement it in real life.
We'll give a few real world use cases
and try to tie in the concept of topology
into, into one of your tools, into
one of the tools in your toolkit with
regard to the troubleshooting process.
We will see why eBPF is
a very important enabler.
with regards to that, why the use of
EBPF, EBPF tools, EBPF open sources,
can yield the very, can yield very high
benefits, to, enable the implementation
of real time topologies, and eventually
a few tips of how to get started,
whether it will be with a commercial
tool or, with an open source tool.
So as we know, Kubernetes is great.
We use it.
We understand what we use it.
Sometimes we don't
understand what we use it.
But it brings a lot of
interesting challenges with
regards to troubleshooting.
There's a few, a few reasons to that.
First and foremost,
the distributed nature.
Like, there's no need to explain, but
when we used an, when we used to an
implemented monolith, they had a lot of
problems from operational perspective.
They had a lot of problems from managing.
these, these big piece of code, but
from other aspect, they were closed,
they were easier to debug with the
distributed nature of Kubernetes.
A lot of things happen.
But first of all, we have a lot
of more moving parts and do.
Kubernetes is very uniquely situated
because it's a software layer, but it's a
kind of a software infrastructure layer.
In reality, when there's an issue and
the kubernetes based deployment, it takes
time and it's not that easy to understand
whether it is an application issue.
Or a Kubernetes issue, meaning
how do you differentiate, this
blur, the blurred line, between
application and infrastructure issue.
The second one would be the dynamics.
the ephemeral environments or, the
ephemeral, nature of Kubernetes
environment, which pods are coming up.
C put are coming up, port
ports are going down.
CICD pipelines are causing configuration
changes are coding causing code changes.
It's, of course not that easy.
to track that, which also it's also
adding more complexity, more complexity
when we're trying to cope with
travel shooting, complex networking.
A lot of the things that Kubernetes
does is to create obstruction upon
obstructions upon obstructions.
You can deploy two pods
on the same server.
You can deploy two pods in adjacent
servers, but Kubernetes will try its
best to make it seems like they're
all one part of the same application.
And that, in real life, can
create a lot of troubleshooting,
troubleshooting cumbersomes.
So elements like for DNS or proxies
or the CNI plug in, which eventually
creates A flat networking model
between them are also adding to
the, adding to the troubleshooting,
troubleshooting complexity.
Eventually, it's not that easy to do.
Sniff the network or look at each and
every packet and understand what is
going on just by, by means of the, the
sheer obstruction layers that kubernetes
is imposing into the deployment shared
resources, and noisy, noisy neighbors.
Of course, if we were.
In a world in which I have complete
control over the infrastructure, meaning
that when I'm looking at a pod, or
I'm looking at an application part,
I don't need to account for what the
infrastructure is doing, whether the
infrastructure directly or Because of
another deployment, which is situated
on the same note and by itself can cause
metrics and cause other, other telemetry,
other telemetry to be very noisy.
So all of that is adding to the
to the aggregate complexity.
if you will, black box or black boxes.
Meaning things that I
don't really control.
This could be infrastructure pieces,
pods, which are pods, which are
third parties, which I'm using or
containers, which are third parties
and automation complexity by itself.
We touched it.
We had a lot of other sessions in the
past about how CST pipeline by itself
is essentially a noise generator
when coming to troubleshooting.
The fact that I'm trying not only
to troubleshoot or trying to shoot
at the target, but that target is,
All the while, also, also moving.
so I think in, in very high terms,
that should give you a glance
about, the different elements
which are the cause of complexity,
with regard to troubleshooting.
We gave an example of logs
on the right hand side.
I think logs are a very good example when
speaking about distributed environments
because you're looking at a single
point in time in a single element.
And I always say it, the problem
with logs is that they require more
logs and rarely on the same place.
The challenges with the observability
toolkits as they exist today.
so a lot of these,
observability toolkits were.
Actually, born, raised, nurtured, for, for
the world of, for the world of monolith.
So, a lot of things that, started
there, like matrix and log and traces
are really Coming from a world in which
you should have a complete view over
your application or your environment
and as we touched Touched on before
that's how that is something which is
a massively changing Massively change
when looking at distributed environment
metrics Everybody knows the concept,
but we're looking at some sort of
some sort of a quantity Or a number.
Usually it's there to track
some sort of a performance, a
performance, telemetry aspect.
So they allow you to track trends
or to see absolute values, but
eventually they're just numbers.
You have nothing to do with them if
you don't have some higher context
to what they mean, to what they mean,
in, to what they mean in the current
time or in the current situation.
For example, what's causing
this spike in the CPU usage?
There's a lot of other questions that
you need to answer that will help you
understand whether the spike in the CPU
usage is something, worrisome or just
normal behavior of the application.
logs to the very course.
They can provide you some granular detail
about an issue, but they're fragmented.
You see bits and pieces of logs from
various elements in the system, and
there's no one else other than an engineer
that can tie together whether log A on
point, on point A and log B on point
B has anything to do with one another.
Or generally, are there
correlated, to the same issue?
for example, I have a pod,
I have an issue in a pod.
What would that mean on
a downstream element?
For sure, we'll see logs there, but how do
I do the logical connection between them?
it's an interesting, an
interesting question.
A good example would be losing
a connection to a database, from
a client pod, and then seeing
the log on, the database pod.
There is a connection
to, to be made there.
traces.
which is, oftenly, oftenly
used, to go and go over, a lot
of these type of, challenges.
So they show service, interaction.
The real question is, how
do you put them in place?
And what is the effort,
to put them in place?
Meaning essentially
instrumenting the environment.
It could be easy for some element, which
already supports it, but for legacy
code or for other types of code bases,
it could be a challenge by itself.
eBPF, of course, is a technology
that could help a lot with that.
But achieving really traceable
code on a high scale, high scale
environment is, is not that easy.
Very similar to getting
coverage, coverage on code.
so, essentially, what we see in a lot
of environments, people have, they
want, to instrument the environment,
but the gap, to get the environment
fully instrumented is very, very large.
moving forward, let's speak about
the concept of real time topology.
I think just for a basic
understanding, all of us.
Always has some sort of a chart.
It could be something that we drew.
It could be an architecture slide or
architectures chart of the environment.
And the reason behind that is
to give us the overall context.
Right.
There's a lot of moving part, but
if I want to capture in a glance
what the system is doing, how
it's built in high level terms.
So for all of us, the concept of
using a chart is very, very natural.
Another concept which was
evolved throughout the years is
the concept of dependency net.
Maybe I can create some sort of a static
chart but dynamically generated chart
updated in updated in some sort of a low
time interval, and create some sort of the
view, which mimics what the environment
looks like, at least in the in the last
couple of minutes or in the last couple
of hours, real time topology as we will
touch it is like the involvement on that
into something which is fully dynamic.
Real time topology in that aspect
should provide us the context
required to eliminate blind spots.
I want to generate more, more,
more, bits and pieces of context.
And help me understand how the
metrical part traces parts logs part
are really connected in real life
and what should come into my mind.
And with that real time topology is one
of, one of the most important tools.
What is it?
If we'll try to summarize it, it's
like map of system relationship in the
Kubernetes case, it will be encompassing
all the cluster layers and then spaces
layer going to the more granular
elements like pods and services.
From the software perspective, most
of the time, if it's a complex enough
and smart enough, smart enough, real
time topology, it will incorporate
the infrastructure, element each in.
It could go even much higher and show
the interactions, but not only the
interaction as a line from here to
there, but also really, these are the
type of APIs, the type of information,
the type of transactions that are
traversing between the elements.
Why should it matter?
Why should it matter to us?
The ability to do this logical
connection, of course, gives us an
element that we would have been doing
in the troubleshooting process anyway.
If I have an issue, let's say an
API which now returns an error.
What I would do as an engineer is
start and backtrace that and try to
follow a logical, a logical line.
My API is Bringing an error to the user.
So it's probably experiencing,
experiencing some sort
of an issue by itself.
What would be the cause of that issue?
Let's look at the log.
Let's look at the metric.
If I understand that, let's backtrace.
One step before that, could it be that
something like a database transaction
couldn't be completed or it couldn't
free the value and so on and so forth.
And we're starting to essentially build
a path on a graph or a path on topology.
So the concept should be clear
because essentially we're mimicking
the natural way of thinking for
engineers, which is the backtracing.
So that allows us to connect individual
points into some sort of a more.
Full view.
How does it work?
so essentially we're taking or
we're continuously updating, the
real time topology to reflect the
real time changes, new services,
new deployments, new interactions.
And that allows us to grasp this,
massive amount of data in, in a way,
which is, easy to, easy to present.
Let's give, let's give an example.
What we see in the following example
is the real time topology, in this case
generated by eBPF, which allows us to, to
track both external services, something
which is not part of our deployment,
but also deep dive into the structure
of Kubernetes, looking at namespaces,
looking at the deployments and the
pods, and even the interaction between
them to the protocol or API level.
So for sure, if later was, we'll discuss
it, if something happened here, metrical
evidence, log evidence, trace evidence,
being able to, being able to project that.
On the topology could, explain a lot
of things or as part of the elimination
process in troubleshooting allowed
us to focus on the right things.
Let's give, let's give an example.
Let's think about a kubernetes,
kubernetes, kubernetes pod, which is
failing on readiness could happen because
a lot of recent, a lot of reasons.
And let's say it's failing due to,
IO, it's failing due to storage.
It could be a local storage.
It could be, by the way.
An external storage.
Database in that aspect is a storage.
Any sort of, an external,
external repository would
be, a storage in that case.
Being able to see that on a graph, being
able to connect the dots, understanding
that there is a correlation between how
this pod, readiness in this case, prose
is behaving with regards to an element
is connected to, it's much easier to
deduct when you have a real time map.
I'm connected to.
This database, this storage
element, so on and so forth.
Logical for me to look at that.
so with regards to that, mapping the real
topology or mapping the pod dependencies
allows us to start and shrink the
amount of element that we're looking at.
And in that case, it allows
us to understand that we need
to focus on certain aspects.
For in this example, The desire, which
is really, really, really the root cause
and then eventually decide what to do,
either adjust the probe configuration
or change other configuration, enable,
enable, enable different storage
or other storage configuration.
Another example, which a lot of time,
or a lot of you have faced in the past
is throttling, especially throttling
when there is changes in the dynamics
of the deployment going up or down.
for example, in this case, the scenario.
We're speaking about an application,
which, which is under high traffic.
This usually in a lot of deployment,
there will be a connection between
the amount of traffic to the size
of the deployment through a load
balancer, through whatever other means.
But essentially what we're looking
at here is the triggering of an
HPA, of a Port Authorized Scaling.
but eventually a lot of the
time the deployment will scale.
It doesn't mean that the
infrastructure scale at the same pace.
Or is well enough ready in
order to absorb the scaling.
And a lot of time in this
situation, we see things like
throttling, the number of pods.
Has changed, but eventually we're
looking at, throttling from the
infrastructure, perspective.
And even though we scaled, we get into a
scenario in which we get malfunctions or
we getting into the, the specific pods
not being able to handle, handle the load.
how does it, how real time
topology will help here.
So of course, one being able to.
Visually see that being able to
see the different interaction,
visualizing the resource allocation.
Are there?
More nodes or nodes group, being
allocated as part of the code scaling.
and that would enable teams together
with the other, other observability
telemetry data, to either adjust the
resources or limit the bandwidth or.
To do whatever it takes in order
to, in order to solve it, but just
the ability to understand that
this is an infrastructure issue.
This is not an application issue is, of
course, already, at least 50 percent 50
percent steps toward towards the solution.
Misconfigured network policies, something
that we've all seen and suffered from.
I think it's a very easy case
to understand how topology can
help because the fact that real
time topology is in many aspects.
Very similar to a network topology map.
So I think it's an easy
aspect to understand.
And other aspects, like we spoke about
before, which are real time topology.
Topology is not only logical
connectivity, it could also be
infrastructure connectivity, or
whatever connectivity, but I think
this one is very easy to comprehend.
So, for example, we have a pod or a
microservice deployed, and it failed
to communicate with another service.
And it doesn't even have,
even have to happen.
It could happen sporadically,
but could happen because of the
configuration change in real life.
the complexities of getting into this,
this scenario could be almost infinite.
that's happening because
of a network policy.
It would be very hard.
Or very hard without real time topology
to either comprehend that that is the
issue or more than that, understand
which adjacent services I should look at.
it could be also very hard to debug
only with something like logs.
Right.
There is a lot of sessions going on.
It could be any single session,
which, which is failing, which
will give us an issue here.
So really, the lack of detailed logs
or visibility or traces, if that
specific path is not, instrumented
in the, in the deployment, it's a
very hard scenario to, to diagnose.
But the ability here to have the service
to service mapping, looking at the APIs,
maybe on the topology itself, mark.
When there's an issue in one of
these paths, be another great,
another great, idea, to do that.
but the ability to, to show that or even
understand it might be here because.
I see logical connectivity, or I thought
there should be a logical connectivity,
but there is none, meaning that this
could be really a network policy issue.
it's a great example for, for the use
of that and the amount of automation
that, you can put around it.
can expose a lot of these,
a lot of these cases.
So what enables real time topology?
essentially, there's ways to implement.
It could be done with things
like distributed traces if the
environment is instrumented, that
essentially following the distributed,
distributed traces path could be a
tool to create real time topology.
The one we're focusing on
here is, of course, the use of
EDPF and with the use of EDPF.
the ability to dynamically
create a real time topology.
eBPF, I think, today, most of you
already, already understand it.
It's a piece of technology, a part that's
natively supported by, the Linus kernel,
extended Berkeley packet filtering.
Essentially, the way to think about
it is a small type of VM or feature
within the kernel that allow us to run
or safely run Low level instrumentation
code beats or pieces of code, which from
one hand are instrumented and the kernel
on the other hand, will bring data to
user space, kind of benefiting from,
both of, both of the world, main uses.
So of course traffic analysis.
That was the original.
used for eBPF, the ability
to trace network requests,
messages, packets, sniff them.
Of course, the most classical use, the
importance for topology is the ability
to track APIs and the ability to, and
the ability to, and the ability to
trick, essentially any kind of, session.
infrastructure, app and
performance monitoring.
So it's not only the ability to hook
into, the networking stack, but also
the ability to hook into kernel calls
or to hook into application calls.
These are very important because it
allows eDPF to create a granular, more
granular level of instrumentation.
What kernel calls are being called could
be important for a lot of use cases.
What application calls are being
issued by the application could
be important for things like
opening encrypted streams in HTTP2.
It could be the use of
open sources and tracing.
That's essentially how to auto instrument.
pieces of code.
If I can find in memory those
function calls, of course, I can add
I can at the trace point and enable
that enable that instrumentation.
And all of these things which are very
relevant to observability are naturally
very, very important for security with
a change of the use case networking
through enforced network policies and
infrastructure and app call to Protect
or detect misbehavior, misbehavior
with regards to things like open source
usage or kernel usage, resource usage.
So a lot of similar aspects, but the use
cases on top are very much different.
So why does it matter?
eBPF, of course, enables
deep observability.
It's also native in Linux.
In my perspective, that's maybe one
of the most important things, it's
like the native tool being, put there
in order for people implementing
this type of, this type of mechanism.
it's, invaluable, for complex
distributed environments, both from
security and observability perspective.
So why is eBPF ideal
for distributed systems?
there's a lot of, building blocks to that.
put a little bit of a caveat, caveat
here, also very, very, dependent on
the implementation itself, but on the
forefront, if you're doing it right.
The ability to implement low latency
monitoring, small pieces of eBPF code,
bringing the relevant data, capturing
the right element from the network
pockets can allow us to discover
the environment and understand the
connectivity without creating confusion.
Latency overhead, or without creating
other aspects, which will implement the
overall performance of the application.
Enhanced visibility, so the ability
to go and discover, or to go
and instrument specific elements
which are important for us.
It could be, It could
be distributed queues.
It could be database transaction.
It could be whatever is important enough
for us to deep dive into and we don't have
necessarily an alternative to monitor it
at a fine level, at a fine granular level.
Improved efficiency.
So, as a building block,
security, observability.
What have you, it can reduce the need
for other or specific diagnostic tools.
So being able to use eBPF as a
building block to build the rest of
the chain makes, makes a lot of sense.
We already see it, by the way, not
only from a visibility perspective,
but eBPF is being used on the
platform to implement many things.
So it could be load balancers, it
could be, it could be, service meshes.
The observability tools, security
tools, and the scalability.
this being a very native, Linux, Linux
supported, Linux supported technology
being basically automatically enabled on
each and every node, is super important.
Maybe on a different aspect, the
ability to implement it not only for.
Physical node, but for example,
implemented for, other ephemeral, other
ephemeral, technologies with sidekicks or
things like that, can allow us to create
a more consistent, observability approach.
auto discovery.
so in auto discovery, we're
going one layer above it.
It's not auto discovered.
Only I will call it the data, but it's
how we connect this data to a data
model, something which takes it one
layer above it and could allow us start
would allow us to start and speak about
things like hierarchies or structure or,
or create a more formal way of defining
that, that would be the first aspect.
And, of course, with that, things like
the use of machine learning or the use
of pattern matching in order to take.
the data from Kubernetes in order to take
the data that we get from eBPF and match
them or mesh them together to create not
only a dynamic graph but to put this data
modeling on top of it and essentially
creating something which is repeatable.
This is a pod, this is a new pod or a
new service, we have a node group or
we have we have identified a part of
our application which is a database
or a business logic and then again and
again and again even when data changes
still have it in the, still have it in
the same format, without essentially
requiring, requiring any, manual updates.
common pitfalls.
even though the concept is relatively,
relatively simple, it still, it
has a lot of, a lot of ways to
get, to get in the wrong direction.
one, incomplete instrumentation.
Eventually, we're trying to
create a graph or we're trying
to create or look at a chart.
The chart will be as good as the data
which is there creating the chart.
So missing critical data like logs
or API or events or any other data
eventually will create an incomplete
view and it will not be used.
So it's important not only to think
about what data should go into there.
Of course, eBPF can help with
that, but also to have in mind
what is the most important parts
to have there to begin with.
Stale topology maps.
I think in many aspects, the
tendency maps are maybe suffering
from that exact problem.
Kubernetes environment or any distributed
environments are constantly changing.
If the topology updates are not, Automatic
and sure if you're not being updated in a
quick enough cadence, then the risk of is
the risk is, of course, taking decision
today on yesterday's data, assuming
the topology can solve everything.
I think the most trivial one, but
topology is, it's very powerful for
troubleshooting, but it's rarely a
smoking gun, meaning what it gives you
is it gives you the more context that
you need in order to go in the direction.
of the root cause, but by
itself is not a root cause.
It's just a way to formalize or
to model the observability data.
Above that, or a layer above that, that's
the entirety of the concept of AIOps.
Assuming that I have that, and assuming
I can extract this context, Can I now
go and automate the root cause process,
or go at least, into a process which
allows me to lower the amount of alerts
that I have and go in the direction
of, in the direction of the solution.
Tips for getting started.
Assuming you want to do it by yourself
or with a combination of open source
tools or with commercial tools,
which allow, remember the metadata.
Yeah.
You can create, or help yourself,
and choose a strategy with
regards to creating, to creating
the data, the dynamic topology.
But the Kubernetes metadata,
it's eventually detects things
like labels or names or config
maps or events in Kubernetes.
If you're putting them on the real
time topology, that's eventually how
you populate that, with, Populate
that with the most important context.
Yeah, I have the structure now.
I also have everything on top automate
the topology map So when you're
looking and scrubbing for solutions,
the dynamically up the topology think
about these elements How fast are they?
How fast are they updating?
Do they take into consideration of the
Kubernetes data, the infrastructure
data, how fast they are to respond to
frequent state changes, and eventually
avoid context binding pitfalls.
Environments are large,
environments are complex.
It might be beneficial not to try and
model anything, everything, and not to try
and put everything in there to begin with.
It's our role as engineers to
understand the Pareto rule.
What are the 80 percent of things
that are important enough for me, to
look at, and then expand the process.
It could be good enough to start with
something which is Relatively small
or relatively small, but sufficient to
give me the view that I need and then
go and go in and enlarge that as the
system involved or as I have, have I
have, as I have more resources to do so.
I hope you enjoyed that.
If there's any question,
just shoot us an email.
and I really enjoyed having
this session with you.
Thank you.