Hello everyone.
Happy New Year.
I'm Jaspreet Kumar.
Welcome to the session on data driven
mobile app performance optimization.
Mobile applications play a
pivotal role in our lives today.
No matter how innovative an
app is, its performance can
make or break user experience.
In this session, we'll deep dive
into The strategies and tools that
enable you to deliver high performing
apps, from reducing load times and
optimizing resources to leveraging
AI for proactive issue resolutions,
will cover everything you need to
create a seamless user experience.
The need for speed.
Let's start with a critical insight.
Speed is everything in
the mobile apps today.
Performance is no longer a luxury.
It's a necessity.
Research shows that more than half of the
users are likely to abandon an app if it
takes more than three seconds to load.
That's a huge loss of potential users.
Users expect speed and any delay in speed.
can translate to lost engagement, lower
retention, and missed opportunities.
The solution lies in
focusing on two key goals.
First, 30 percent optimization goal.
It can reduce app size through
resource compression and
efficient asset management.
Second, targeting 50 percent
or more improvement in speed.
By implementing techniques like lazy
loading and progressive rendering,
these strategies not only make
your app faster, but also ensure a
smoother and better user experience.
So the speed is everything that matters
today along with the performance.
Optimizing app size.
Optimizing app size plays a crucial
role in improving in improving
performance and user experience.
One of the easiest wins in performance
optimization is reducing app size.
Large apps not only discourage
downloads but also consume more
device storage and that can lead to
potential uninstalls from the users.
Resource optimizations by applying
Advanced compression algorithms to
images, videos, and other assets.
We can reduce their size by great
extent while maintaining the quality.
Code minification by streamlining
source code through advanced
minification techniques.
Removing unnecessary codes,
comments, extra space, unused
variable, and reducing removing The
files which are not necessary, it
makes the app leaner and faster.
Dependency management.
By auditing and eliminating redundant
libraries and leveraging tree
shaking techniques to remove unused
code, we ensure that only essential
components remain in the app.
These steps collectively
result in smaller, faster,
and more user friendly app.
Lazy loading techniques.
Lazy loading is a key strategy for
improving perceived performance.
The principle is simple.
Prioritize what's most important.
Load what users need
first and defer the rest.
Critical UI components should load
first within the first second, creating
an optimal first contentful paint.
For non critical elements, APIs like
IntersectionObserver can dynamically
load images, scripts, or other
resources as the user scrolls.
We can further enhance the
visual experience by using
progressive loading techniques.
For instance, SkeletonScreen gives user
A preview of the layout while content
loads and blur up effects make image
loading transitions seamless together.
These techniques ensure users
remain engaged even during
resource intensive operations.
Efficient data management is fundamental
for maintaining a responsive app.
It ensures your app runs smoothly.
And responsively, caching
is the first step.
Implement start caching strategies to
store excess data locally, reducing
server requests by up to 40%, and
cutting average load times from 2.
5 seconds to 1.
5 seconds or more.
Utilize both memory and disk
caching for optimal performance.
E Synchronous CPU Processing
Leverage background threads and
event driven architecture to
process UI updates independently,
maintaining 60 FPS responsiveness
even during intensive data operations.
Implement debouncing and throttling
for smooth scrolling and animations.
Monitoring and analytic tools.
Effective monitoring and analytics are
the backbone of data driven optimization.
Optimization is impossible
without insights and this is where
monitoring tools come into play.
Tools like firebase performance monitoring
tools track metrics like startup
times, HTTP requests, frame rates,
network slowness and other metrics.
These insights pinpoint bottlenecks
down to the milliseconds
and performance of the app.
New Relic adds deeper visibility
by providing distributed tracing
and code level diagnostics,
custom dashboards, further enhance
our monitoring capabilities,
allowing us to set thresholds.
and receive real time alerts.
These tools ensure that we are
always aware of app health and
can proactively address issues.
Predictive AI and Anomaly Detection.
AI is redefining performance optimization.
Predictive AI systems analyze real time
data to detect anomalies and patterns.
enabling us to resolve issues
before user experiences them.
This proactive approach reduces
crash rates extensively and
improves user satisfaction.
Moreover, real time data collection and
advanced algorithms continuously learn
and adapt to evolving usage trends.
These systems are not just reactive,
they are predictive, empowering us to
stay ahead of potential problems and
deliver a seamless user experience.
Harnessing telemetry insights.
Telemetry insights offer a window into
your app's performance in the real world.
By tracking technical metrics like API
response times, memory utilizations,
battery consumptions, and other metrics,
we identify areas for optimization.
Behavioral insights reveal how
users interact within the app,
highlighting popular features
and pinpointing pinpoints.
Finally, operational altimetry ensures app
stability by monitoring crashes, errors,
and other anomalies in the real time.
Combining these three dimensions
of insights gives us a holistic
view, enabling us to make
informed data driven decisions.
AP Testing for Continuous Improvement A
B testing allows us to validate changes
and ensure they have a positive impact.
We start by forming hypotheses
based on data insights.
Control tests are then deployed to
user segments to compare variations
and metrics like load times,
interaction rates, and feedback.
are monitored over a defined period
of time based on the results.
And once we identify the better performing
variant, it's implemented across the app.
It can result in improvements of
up to 40 percent in key metrics
like retention, engagement, user
satisfaction, and that can drive in more.
users into the application, improving
the users into the application and, app
improvements like user satisfaction.
AI driven monitoring systems.
AI driven monitoring systems are the
future of app performance optimization.
They bring unparalleled efficiency
to performance optimizations.
These systems analyze millions
of data points, improving anomaly
detection accuracy to 95%.
Machine learning models predict issues
well in advance, enabling proactive fixes.
Automated diagnostics trace
performance bottlenecks to their
source, reducing debugging time.
by up to 60 percent with real time
monitoring of over 100 metrics.
The systems ensure that your app
remains fast, stable, and reliable.
Impact on user retention and revenue.
Optimized performance has a
measurable impact on business metrics.
Faster load times can lead up
to a 7 percent increase in user
retention within the first 30 days.
Revenues can grow up to by 10 percent
or even more driven by smoother
user experiences that encourage in
app purchases and subscriptions.
Perhaps most importantly, user
satisfaction jumps by 30%.
As reflected in surveys and app
reviews, these outcomes highlight
the value of a data driven approach
to performance optimization.
Key takeaways.
To conclude, let's focus on key takeaways.
First, prioritize
performance from day one.
Make speed and efficiency a priority.
The co development principles, even a 15
percent improvement in load times can lead
to a 35 percent increase in retention.
Leverage data and AI insights
to guide every decision.
Harnessing real time analytics and AI
insights Make data driven decisions that
consistently improve app performance
and user satisfaction metrics.
Adopt continuous improvement and
optimization practices like implementing
A B testing using concrete metrics and
user feedback to guide decision making.
Each optimization decision last stay
ahead of any issues in the app deploy
AI powered monitoring systems to detect
and resolve potential performance
issues before they affect your users
maintaining optimal app health.
By implementing these
strategies, you can create apps.
that are not only high performing
but also delightful for the users.
Thank you for being part of the
session on data driven mobile
apps performance optimization.
I hope you have gained valuable
insights and actionable strategies
to enhance your apps performance.
Thank you.