Speaker 34: And in embedded system, we
are often told we must choose either
deterministic, realtime behavior,
or intelligent AI driven systems.
Today I want to show you
why this trade off is false.
Hello, one second.
I am Raja, a senior
software engineer in A SML.
I work in realtime embedded system where
missing deadlines are unacceptable, yet
intelligent and becoming unavoidable.
So let's move on to the next one.
So this is called the embedded
paradox or embedded AI paradox.
Let's start with the core challenges.
Limited compute.
So that means we cannot have enough power
or we cannot have powerful CPUs or CPUs.
So embedded system is made for only one
task to do so we cannot have more power.
And that too, we have light.
Or tight memory budgets.
So we cannot go for a lot of memory
because then that becomes more expensive
and that is also not easy to handle
as well, because we want to do limited
time things in limited time actually.
So that is where the
time comes to picture.
So millisecond latency.
So anything goes beyond here
until a little bit in the time.
Then time is a big catch problem there.
So embedded system is always
bound within the time limit.
So I can say that millisecond
latency requirements, like in
real time system, the AI decision
that arrives, let, it's a failure.
It has to be on time in traditional ai.
Optimizes for accuracy and throughput.
Real time systems optimize
for predictability.
Let's move on to the next one.
So introduction to ai, sorry,
ri, introduction to re A IF.
So there was a little bit
of hiccups here and there.
So REAI chemic kind of thing.
Anyways, so let's go ahead with
introduction to a sorry, one second.
R-E-A-I-F.
This challenge led to the decision.
Of RE A IF, the realtime
embedded AI framework.
A re A IF is built on a simple principle.
AI must adopt the realtime
constraint not break them.
So here you can see that lot
of, interface, user interface,
web client, mobile client,
they all are trying to access.
And this is the biggest thing, like an
application server that is the ai, but
ev, everything sits here and that takes
the decision of where to go and where
to then grab the data and all that.
So it has to happen in the real time.
So it provides intelligent functionality
without compromising reliability.
Safety or responsiveness.
The goal is not maximum intelligence.
The goal is predictable intelligence.
So AI is the main, the biggest
factor for AI is not to maximize
the intelligence, but we have to
be more and more smart actually.
Okay.
So that we can understand what
is going to happen next, what
it's going to happen next.
So charge G pt, the way it works
actually, so similar to that.
So next, move on to the next page.
Architecture overview.
So the real time AI framework follows
the hierarchal design philosophy.
The system is organized into three
layers, operate in a synchronized
control loop, precipitate precipitation
layer perception layer, sorry,
perception layer, cognition layer.
Execution layer.
So perception layer, the perception
layer handles deterministic sensor
acquisition and pre-processing
sensor fusion ensures that all data,
it's time aligned and reliable.
So everything has to be
in a time-based actually.
So that's the main thing.
And cognition layer.
The cognition layer performs AI interface
using embedded, optimized model.
And, these models are quantized
and hardware accelerated
to ensure bounded latency.
So the latency is the major factor here.
Okay, so the key idea here is coordination
without sacrificing determination.
So basically you have to determine
what is going to happen next,
what might going to happen next.
So we need a lot of examples lot of,
in our models actually, so that, it
keeps on working on that actually.
So the execution layer, as I told
you, like it has to be more of free.
Every action is scheduled and verified.
So next, move on to the next one.
Which is basically hard hybrid
architecture when natural
questions come to our mind,
why not just Python everywhere?
Because Python is not, that is
one of our favorite language.
Everybody likes that.
You just writing English, you're not
writing programming language when it
comes to Python, actually, and it is
very easy to write the code in Python
and understand the Python and all that.
But Python, let me say, Python is
an excellent and rapid development
and AI workflow, but it is not
suitable for a hard realtime system.
So hard I've been here.
I want to give you some kind of
example of what is the hard realtime
system and soft realtime system.
Hard realtime system means if
something has been meant to be
completed in, supposed in two
millisecond, that has to be completed.
Completed in two milliseconds, but
soft railing, the realtime system
means something has scheduled
to be reached on time, but if it
gets delayed, that is also fine.
Like we have message.
Or text messages in the phone.
Sometimes we send now, but it
is it reaches around 20 minutes
later, that's still fine.
But in the real time in hard, real
time, systems that is not acceptable.
So in real time AI framework, c
plus forms a deterministic core.
It handles control loops scheduling,
sensor fusion management, mystery
memory management, and hardware access.
Python is used for, Python is used for
model development, training, pipelines
and analytics optimized bindings
connect, optimize optimized bindings.
Connector, two worlds
with minimal overhead.
The hybrid approach each gives us
both performance and productivity.
As I told you in c plus we have again
sensor fusion pipelines, deterministic,
and we have task scheduling.
We have process scheduling, we have
memory management, we have shared
pointers, and we have nowadays
we have c plus 11, C plus 30.
17, 23, 20. Which makes the c plus was
also easy to write and write the code.
And it is, it is more secure safety
and it is more of working towards
getting more robust system actually
and where, whereas Python is always for
training the module and data analysis.
Training pipelines, advanced analytic
analytics and visualization, and all
those things you can do in Python.
And that is also a biggest
advantage, by using Python.
So next slide.
So embedded intelligence talk.
Let's say making this, making making this
work request, aggressive optimization,
quantized, CNN, reduced memory usage by.
Up to four times.
Preserving accuracy, hardware
acceleration, using our neon and GPUs,
provide up to 10 times interface,
sorry, inference 10 times inference
speed ups, compile times scheduling.
Random time uncertainty.
Lock free.
Yeah, lock free.
Queues eliminates priority inversion
and synchronization bottleneck.
So I would like to give you one
example of priority inversion.
So priority inversion.
What is, what does that mean actually?
So priority inversion is
basically, like one task.
Has given highest priority or the
task has given lowest priority.
So what happens?
Lowest priority task is doing some work
and higher priority task is coming.
But it cannot able to take that work
because lowest priority is already
accessing that particular module or that
particular resource, so it cannot able
to take what it has supposed to take.
So now what to do
actually, now what happens?
This high spare task inherits, its.
Priority to low priority task and then
low priority task gets higher priority
task, and then it does its job and
lifts the resource and gives the task
priority to highest priority task again.
So that is bit complex thing, but I
hope I could able to make that, I make
that thing to understand to you guys
anyways moving on to the next one.
Every optimization exists in one
region to protect real time guarantee.
So all this optimization we are doing
to protect our real time guarantees.
Move to the next one.
So this is energy, our operation.
Performance alone is not enough.
Energy matters.
Basically.
So dynamic voltage scaling reduces power
consumption during load demand periods.
Intelligent hibernation shuts down
a new subsystem without impacting
wake up latency memory pooling
eliminates fragmentation and
reduces energy port transaction.
This mechanism extend
operational endurance without
violating time constraint.
So the thing is that if something
we are not using like in a computer.
We are not using computer.
The computer was going into hibernation
more so that it can save the battery.
And yeah, so in real time also
like something, we are not using it
for a long time, we can move it to
hibernation thing so that we don't
have to really reuse the battery.
Actually, like if you
see language, Tesla cars.
Or all these, battery operated, I,
items, they basically have they basically
have energy saving mechanism actually.
Okay, so next, move on to the next one.
So are we missing something or no?
So now moving this one, so it is nothing
but our manufacturing applications.
So that is nothing but
industrial applications.
Yes.
So in manufacturing environment, real
time AI framework enables a real impact,
actually vision guided precisions,
assembly chips, sub millimeter
accuracy with the 99.7 success threat.
So if you see nowadays, Google Maps.
And all.
So as soon as you miss one exit,
it automatically, it just within
a fraction of seconds or within
few seconds very limited time.
It just tracks you know how far you
went, so you went to a different road
so it can reroute in a different way.
So similarly, those kind of things.
And in vision, guided precision, like
nowadays, automotive the cars, so
when the cars are going on the road.
So they see which is
in the front actually.
So immediately they take the decision
whether I have to go to right or left
or I have to be on my lane or something.
So those decisions, it has been taken.
So those kind of things, we can take
the advantage of those learnings.
And we can, proceed actually at real
time inspection increases throughout by
35% while reducing the false positive.
So by training our models and all,
we can, get rid of all these false
positive things actually, and predictive
maintenance reduces unplanned downtime.
60% maintenance reduces.
Unplanned downtime by 60% through
continuous system health monitoring.
This proactive approach optimizes
operational efficiency and extend
equipment lifespan so that basically,
in the downtime, if you're continuously
checking the health monitoring, in
monitoring the health, this could
able to optimize the operational
efficiency and extend the equipment
lifespan in the defense applications.
So in the defense applications, nowadays,
everywhere, every country is trying
to go beyond, do something extra.
Do something extra.
So in defense environment, reliability
is non-negotiable actually.
So there, the real hard, real time.
System comes together without, in my
previous slides I told, hard realtime
system and software, realtime system.
So this is where the hard
realtime system comes.
Now, if you want to hit
somewhere, you have to use, you
have to use that in real time.
And where system and you have to be there
and you cannot go somewhere else as well.
So there GPS, location it has to be
a hundred percent or near to 99.99%.
Okay, anyways.
Moving on.
So real time AI framework
supports autonomous navigation
in GPS in GPS denied environment.
Through sensor fusion, swarm
coordination emerge from distributed
deterministic decision making.
Systems were evaluated in
contested scenario with a dynamic
obstacle and bandwidth constraint.
I want to the next one.
So implementation and tape time.
So c plus.
This is my favorite topic actually,
how to implement because I'm a
developer, so I basically know,
develop the core and let's see.
So yeah, c plus sensor fusion.
Loops are to one kilohertz
with AF scheduling.
So that is one of the scheduling.
When it comes to scheduling,
we have to be very careful.
With respect to priority
priority scheduling.
Or the round run scheduling
and all those things.
We have to take care.
The different threats comes into picture.
That is a multithread data acquisition
for con, concurrent sensor input, adaptive
calm filtering for state estimations.
Then we have inference latency
is under eight milliseconds.
AC actuator jitter remains
below 50 milliseconds.
These numbers matters, especially
for safety certifications.
So next is future capabilities.
Looking forward, a, sorry.
Looking forward re digital time
AI framework opens the door to
federated learning, neuro moic
hardware and formal verification.
It also enables intelligent workload
distribution between edge and cloud.
The next one.
So key takeaways.
So what did what?
What did we learn from here?
Basically?
So let me leave you with three takeaways.
Deterministic control and
adaptive AI can coexist.
We believe that, right?
So next one, embedded optimization.
Max.
Realtime ai.
Practical energy.
Our energy, our decision, oh, sorry.
Energy.
Our design ensure sustainability in field.
Okay
and I think I forgot why I missed one.
That is product production.
Production ready blueprint validates
across industrial and defense application.
A ar real time.
Provides a practical framework for
next generation autonomous system.
And that's all from my end.
Thank you so much.
And ai, sorry again, I'm just
getting confused with these words.
But anyways real time, ai f. It is
not just a framework, it's a blueprint
for next generation for the next
generation embedded intelligence.
Thank you so much.