Speaker 2: Hi everyone.
I'm Akha Prana from Intuit.
Today I want to talk about a topic
that most of us only think about
when things are already going
wrong, that is regional failover.
Specifically how failover becomes
exponentially harder in modern
microservice architectures where
you're not just dealing with stateless
APIs, but databases, async pipelines,
bad jobs, and routing layers.
All of which behave very
differently during failure.
This talk isn't about a
specific product or tool.
It's about patterns we learned
while trying to make failover
predictable and ideally boring.
Here is a high level agenda.
We'll go over problem
statement and motivation.
Then we will align on few
principles and mental model.
Then we are going to talk about platform
architecture outcomes and key takeaways
Before we go into architecture or
solution, I want to level set on the
problem we are actually trying to solve.
By now, I think we can
all agree on one thing.
Outages are normal.
Cloud regions fail.
Managed services have bad days.
Even highly reliable systems
eventually hit failure modes.
They didn't anticipate what really
hurts business and customer isn't
outage itself, it's the recovery.
When recovery is slow, manual and
chaotic, customer trusts erodes quickly.
So the real question isn't
how do we prevent outages?
It's how do we recover from them.
In a predictable way.
Microservices gave us a scale
and velocity, but they also
changed the failure landscape
during a regional outage.
You're not just failing over one thing.
APIs might come up quickly,
but background workers may lag
databases, may need promotion.
Async pipelines may replay or stall,
and all of these components have a
different recovery characteristics.
The key lesson we learned is this,
your system only recovers as fast as
the slowest workload in the stack.
So when we look at major
incidents, the outage itself is
really the most damaging part.
What actually determines customer
impact is how quickly and predictably
the system recovers and under pressure.
Humans become the weakest link,
not because they are bad ingenious,
but because of stress, fatigue and
incomplete information lead to mistakes.
This is why automation and standardization
matters so much in disaster recovery.
In many organization, failover
vol evolves organically.
Each team builds what they think
is good enough for their service.
Over time, you end up with dozens or
hundreds of different DR strategies.
The problem isn't that these
solutions are bad individually.
The problem is that they
don't de, they don't compose.
During a real outage, fragmentation
turns into confusion, and
confusion turns into delay.
So runbooks are often treated as a
safety net, but during a real outage,
engineers are context switching,
debugging incomplete signals,
and coordinating across teams.
That's a terrible time to
follow a multi-page checklist.
The more your recovery depends on
human memory, the less reliable
it becomes, especially at scale.
Now that we have talked about
the problem, I want to go over
a few principles that went into
building disaster recovery platform.
When we say boring failover, we
are not minimizing its importance.
We mean that failer should be so
predictable and well-rehearsed,
that it doesn't require heroics.
No one should be scrambling for runbooks.
No one should be manually scaling
clusters at 3:00 AM boring.
Failer is a sign of engineering maturity.
One of the design principle
is declarative intent.
The biggest shift we made
was moving from imperative
procedures to declarative intent.
Instead of telling teams how to fail
over, we asked them to declare what
they need, capacity dependencies,
data requirements, and criticality.
The platform then owns the mechanics.
This removes a huge cognitive burden.
From service teams and creates
consistency across the organization.
Another design principle is
to fail over the entire stack.
A partial failover is usually
worse than no failover.
If your API fails over, but your
async workers don't, you can corrupt
state or build up massive backlogs.
We learned that failover has to
be treated as a full stack event.
That is compute, async,
workload, data, and routing layer
executed in a coordinated way.
Anything less creates hidden risk.
Remember that failover
is not a point solution.
It needs to be end to end.
So standardization doesn't mean
treating every workload the same.
A customer facing API has very
different recovery requirement
than a nightly batch job.
The key is providing a common
framework where services can
express those differences.
Declaratively, the
platform adapts behavior.
Without teams reinventing the wheel.
Another design principle
is prescale capacity.
Another major source of downtime is
cold capacity in the secondary region.
Instead of guessing how much capacity
we might need, we prescale based on live
traffic patterns from the primary region.
That way when failover happens,
capacity is already there.
Now recovery becomes more about traffic
movement, not infrastructure readiness.
Compute can usually be restarted.
Data is where things get dangerous.
Promoting a database or cache
involves consistency, ordering,
and correctness guarantee.
Automation here isn't about
speed alone, it's about safety.
By encoding these steps into the
platform, we reduce the risk of human
error during high stress incidents.
Traffic routing is often treated as
the final step, but it's actually
a core control mechanism, whether
you use DNS or a service mesh.
Traffic should move based on health
signals, not manual decisions.
This makes failover, observable,
reversible, and far less risky.
Traffic routing becomes part of
the system, not an emergency lever.
One mistake we often see is
treating phlo like a switch.
In reality, it's a workflow.
You scale, promote, validate health,
shift traffic and verify things.
Skipping steps is how incidents
turn into big outages.
Remember that toggles don't
recover systems, but workflows too.
So up to this point, we have talked
about problems and principles.
Now I want to ground these
ideas in a concrete system.
So let's look at Dr procedure
yaml example for an active passive
microservice that uses our database.
So in this example, we have four stages.
So stage one, as you can see, is a
Prescale East stage that basically
pre scales Kubernetes PO in the
failover region and matches the
capacity with existing region.
This is done by updating
HPM and replica value.
Stage two is promoting database
to primary in failover region.
Stage three is about dialing traffic
in failover region, and the last
stage is a stage four, which is
resetting HPM and replica value.
Two original value so that teams
don't pay for extra compute
costs after traffic reduces.
All these stages run in a sequence
that is stage two starts after
stage one has completed, and so on.
So let's take a look at
high level architecture.
So here there's a user who
is executing a DR. Plan.
Using ui and this DR.
Plan has three stages.
That is prescale, dial and reset.
It sends requests to the backend.
API, backend.
API Starts state machine.
State machine sends event to Kafka Topic,
as you can see on the screen, Prescale
stage has been sent to Kafka topic.
We have different agents like database
agent that performs failover operation
on a database, and we have capacity
agent that analyzes compute capacity
and performs scaling operation.
After agent receives event in Kafka
topic, the right agent picks the
task or the stage and it creates
a lock in SEMA for service.
Now state machine pulls.
For SEMA four service lock status
only after SEMA four is unlocked,
it sends the next stage to Kafka
topic ensuring consistent execution
of stages in the expected order.
So on every Kubernetes cluster there is
in cluster add-on running that prescale
spot on receiving pre-cal request.
Those agents also rely on
external monitoring tool to
verify status of every action.
For example, after pos have pre
scaled metrics and monitoring tool
should reflect that information.
This gives an indication for agent to
unlock SEMA four so that state machine
can safely proceed to next stage.
As you can see, platform has both
frontend and backend component.
Frontend component is built using
React, and for backend component,
we are using Golan and Python.
Let's go over safety and operation that
turns a fast failover into a reliable one.
So speed alone is in the goal.
Fast but unsafe failover can
be worse than staying down.
Guardrails like health
gate dependency validation.
They ensure we only move traffic
when the system is actually ready.
And equally important,
every step is reversible.
So automation only works
if the system is ready.
That means requiring healthcare
dependency check and drift detection.
We must eliminate Dr. Only Confis.
No special flags You flip once a year.
Production should always be failover.
Already.
Failover shouldn't depend on hope.
Regular game days completely changed
how teams think about failover because
it's automated and standardized
drills are low stress and repeatable.
The first time you fail over should
never be during a real outage.
So to wrap things up, I want to step back
and talk about outcomes and takeaways.
So antipas to avoid intrude ad hoc strips.
Ad hoc gear solutions don't
usually fail during design.
They fail during execution.
Inconsistency.
Cognitive overload and
untested assumptions show up
at the worst possible time.
Standardization isn't about
control, it's about safety.
So when failovers is
standardized, a few things happen.
Recovery gets faster.
Operational overhead drops.
Teams spend less time preparing for
disasters and more time building features.
Most importantly, incidents become
manageable instead of chaotic.
So one unexpected benefit of
standardizing failover was
the cultural shift it created.
When ingenious trust the system,
they are more willing to practice,
experiment, and improve it.
So failover stops being
something people fear.
And starts being something they understand
that confidence compounds over time.
If there's one message to take away, it's
this standardized failover across all
workloads and use declarative intent.
Also, prescale capacity
intelligently and practice regularly.
Boring, fail lower is a key
sign of a mature system.
Thank you everyone.
Feel free to connect with me via email
or LinkedIn if you have any questions.
I.