Hi everyone and welcome.
I'm very glad to be here
at Conf42 DevOps 2025.
This is the first Conf of the year.
Today I want to talk to you about how
you can pimp your Kubernetes job shooting
skills using something called KCPT.
We'll explore how this AI powered tool
can bring real time insights and help
you resolve your key issues faster.
And more effectively, but before we
get started, let me do a quick intro.
My name is, Cocella AKA cloud dude.
I'm a founder and principal
consultant at cloud thrill.
I have almost, roughly two
decades, almost two decades of
experience in IT and Oracle tech.
I know specialize in multi
cloud operations, DevSecOps,
and a tiny bit of AI inference.
there's not much more to say that
I'm a huge cloud and automation fan.
And I share all my labs
and discoveries on my blog.
now it's cloud.
ca slash blog.
And in my GitHub repost, that's, github.
com slash workdba.
That's not a handle.
Sorry about that.
I'm also the host of TechBeats
Unplugged podcast since a year,
which I'm very excited about.
you can find a cool episode where
I hosted Kelsey Hightower, chilling
about DevOps for almost two hours.
So, please, check the QR code.
If that content, speaks to you.
Okay.
No, that we're done with the intro.
Let's get, to the reason
why we all here today.
Right.
Which is the agenda.
So why are we going to talk about today?
Well, first, we'll talk a bit about,
context and compare, what AI is
good at, versus a traditional job
shooting methods and challenges.
Then in Section 2, we'll learn
more about what's KSGPT, really.
We'll explore key features,
benefits, along with some specs
and AI backends and installations.
Then in Section 3, we'll dive into
all the KSGPT commands you need
to work with and describe basic
and the operator architecture.
Because, you know, there's a CLI and
there's also in cluster, installation.
And finally, we'll have some fun with
a little, demo that I will be, running.
So I hope you will like it.
Okay, but let me start
with the memes, actually.
So Of course, AI, today is stirring up
endless headaches across tech industries.
I don't know if you heard, but Mark
Zuckerberg recently announced AI will
replace his mid level engineers by 2025.
That's a scary thing to tell
your engineers if you ask me.
But hey, this is the same guy who burned
almost 50 billion dollars on Metaverse.
Remember?
so who's right?
will AI replace your job?
Maybe, maybe not, but it
certainly won't hurt you to use
AI today to do your job better.
at least that's my opinion.
On the flip side, you don't want to
completely depend on GPT for your
technical growth in the company, right?
Cause it's not healthy and
fundamentals are still important.
So the key is, is really finding
the balance between the two.
all right, done with the
meme, back to business.
I am not going to talk about what is
AI, but it's important to highlight
some key events or concepts, right?
This is just a language model history.
That's like a timeline of what
happened, and, and when, but I could
also, explain the, We can start
to explain neural networks, right?
So what is a neural network?
Well, neural network, is a network
that helps analyze different, complex
data like text, image, video or audio.
but there are many types of
networks depending on, on the data.
The type of data that you have, right?
For example, for analyzing images,
you'd have to use CNN, which is
Convolutional Neural Network.
This is also used in your
test labs to avoid obstacles.
For text, you would need to use RNN,
which is Recurrent Neural Network.
That's the ancestry, the ancestor
of, recurrent language models.
Right.
The back then there was no record, for
example, of the order of the words,
and he couldn't handle large texts.
So it would forget the first word
by the time it gets to the last one.
Right.
And it was also running sequentially.
So what really happened after that period?
Well, although OpenAI opened up shop
in 2015, what's considered the game
changer in these LLM journey is the
introduction of Transformers architecture.
Sure.
Right back in 2016 and 17, by
researchers from Google and your
University of Toronto, the paper was
called attention is all you need.
And this really marked the shift
from the sequential to self
attention, bringing, More features
like, positional encoding for word
ordering, which is very important.
and also attention, which allows to
more accurate translation, of the words.
Let's say, for example, you
take a sentence, in English,
European union, right?
You would like to translate into French.
Well, in French, it's not
neutral, like in English.
It's l'Union Européenne.
Right, so this is a completely
different gender, right?
So the attention is attaching the
right gender link between the words or
flipping them due to the training data.
You also get self attention that allows
the underlying meaning of the words.
I'm talking about grammar, Gender
and tense aware and context aware
synonymous, all that kind of stuff.
And this is on top of handling huge data
sets of gigs and gigs and terabytes.
So the transformer was the discovery, the
big breakthrough that laid the groundwork
for subsequent groundbreaking models up
to the GPT, and nowadays models, right?
And beyond.
Right that there's a link, actually in
the slide, if you want to learn more and
dive deep into it, into the timeline,
but bottom line is the transformers is
why, we're, using GPT chat GPT today.
Right.
So I hope he was, was informative
enough and he gives you, he gave
you a glimpse of the timeline.
Now let's talk about what AI is great at.
It is of course, very good at.
Pattern recognition, looking at
the repetition of a lot of noise,
translation, translate noise into a
signal, and prediction, predicting
the next token, for example, right?
But that's also funny because the
problems we usually struggle with as
SREs and KS clusters are also pattern
recognition, translation, and prediction.
Right.
For example, when you consider the
failures from your workload, the nodes,
the back end and how to actually spot
these patterns, we have also challenges
in how to find out how did something go
wrong and why, which can very be very
complex in Kubernetes clusters, right?
How to correlate those
errors throughout the stack.
The stack, we also have trouble
forecasting or, do some capacity plan.
And, let's say you have a stateful set.
Like I'm just like showing an example.
You have a PVC failure, because
something went wrong with, any other
layer, like the storage, right?
when this happened, You got a lot of
reasons that could lead to this issue.
I'm taking, one managed cluster
in the cloud, for example, OCI.
It could be in any, cloud managed cluster.
let's say that issue that you can have
in a PVC could be because of the wrong
storage class, or it could be because of
the, block storage used with, Was used
with the wrong file system like xt, four,
XT four instead of XFS, for the PV with
the CSI plugin, or somebody just went to
the console and, changed the parameter,
of the file storage that was dynamically,
generated or created by CSI plugin.
So all these can happen
can be the source of your.
Issue.
But how do we correlate all this today?
Like, oftentimes it's painful as
this involves very deep knowledge,
and in every layer of the stack.
And obviously, right?
So once you pass the euphoria of day
zero after deploying a cluster, moving on
your application in your, in your past,
with time, then you realize how painful.
It is to troubleshoot clusters in
production, and the more clusters grow in
size and complexity, the more difficult
spotting the root cause of issues becomes,
especially when multiple components are
added every day from different teams
like ingress, storage, services, CRDs,
operators, you name it, are involved.
Each time you add a Helm chart
or an operator, things can break.
And of course, first thing you do.
Is check the error message or
traces, but they're often cryptic.
Like you wouldn't even know where
the problem is coming from while
sifting through the piles of logs.
thing is many Kubernetes issues
are Linux issues under cover.
You have sometimes you limit issues.
You got system D config issues
and always issues, right?
And the sheer volume of
logs and events and metrics.
In Splunk or any other login system
that needs to be analyzed makes
the remediation painfully long.
And that leads to, that will
slow down your operations or
causing even longer downtime as
we all experienced in the past.
And to make matters worse, all
the best SREs that you have,
they hold that knowledge of.
How every piece works, but could never put
that into paper or documentation because
it's so immense, they don't have time or
it's based on a decade of, experience, so
it stays in their head forever and never
shared with the junior, junior series.
Right.
So imagine how challenging the onboarding
could be, or the first day on call for
a junior, pretty, pretty challenging.
I, I, I must guess.
and, as shown here, once the failure
happens, we have only limited window,
to filter the signal through the noise
and God knows we have a lot of noise
sometimes to get the clarification.
Right?
So this is the kind of issues, a
conundrum, SRAs find themselves
into, during the troubleshooting.
But what is interesting also is
that there is always a pattern that
can be extracted from these use
cases, throughout the lifecycle
of the cluster or of the workload.
So what if we can?
Codify those repeatable conditions
for those failure mods, in order
to get closer to a best guess or a
best effort, type of advice, right?
So what can we do about this?
Well, fortunately for us, some people
start to work on the issue and this,
inspired, people like Alex, John, Alex
Johnson, and a bunch of, maintainers.
I had to create case you pt.
So what is case you pt really?
Well, simply put, it's just a tool that
scans your cluster diagnose and triage
your issues and enrich it, using L.
L.
M.
S.
Or A.
I.
Backends.
Even if you're not seasoned
expert, think of it as a guru.
That would filter the relevant info
from the noise on your behalf and come
up with advices, to fix your problems.
Right.
Sounds like magic, right?
So in a nutshell, this project is
an open source project that was
donated to CNCF, I think a couple
of years ago, with more than 92
contributors, 6, 000 stars in GitHub.
Feel free to give it a star too.
And it allows fast reach with
AI health and issues analysis.
The best part, it has an SRE
experience codified into 19 analyzers.
We'll talk about it,
deeper, in the next slide.
and it converts the complex signal
into understandable suggestions.
This is like the best part where
like you get the, the suggestions
that is, understandable and
ready to use as solution.
It also supports over 12 AI endpoints.
I'm saying 12, but maybe,
it got bigger, right?
So think of any type of, AI endpoints
you could, you could imagine, right?
So, they support open AI, local
AI, cohere, hug and face, all
online, other cloud AI solutions.
I'm saying talking about Azure
open AI, Amazon bedrocks,
Google Vertex, OCI gen, AI.
So the, the whole package.
And last but not least, security,
because security is important.
So KCPT also integrates with,
dynamic scanning tools like Trivi
for a CVE review or scanning,
which is, which is pretty cool.
It's also, integrated with Prometheus.
I will talk about, further
plugins, in the common, slides.
But, as I say, like case GPT
gives the Kubernetes, Kubernetes,
superpowers to everyone, right?
So, because it makes the process so
easy through a one liner instead of a
sick and through like so many commands
that it becomes a no brainer, for
anyone who's stuck and needs help with
Kubernetes, anywhere, no matter how
junior, you could be, and this can
save you, tons of hours, that for sure.
Key features of KGPT.
Well, the bottom line needs to
remember is everything is built around
work smarter, not harder, right?
So we already said that it's,
it has a codified SRA knowledge,
the guru part, that knows what to
look for, where to look for it.
And also the AI would cut through the
noise and give you that suggestion.
That's not all.
Because case GPT is only paper
with AI to improve the text output.
The real secret though, real secret
sauce is the built in analyzers.
And there are 19 covering most
of Kubernetes resources, right?
So we can see here you have a replica
set service, ingress, stateful set, node,
network policy, pod deployments, PVCs.
Cheers.
You name it, right?
So all of those are actually, analyzers.
They call them filters as well.
The we're a low, case you PT to get
the information needed from, those,
primitives from the API server.
Right.
And the good thing is that you can even
build yourself, new and custom analyzers,
if you want to, because it's supported and
you can contribute back to the project.
So that's, that's the cool part of it.
Right.
And then we have anonymization.
So we know that usually, even when you
have an issue with troubleshooting,
with vendors, they can allow
you to sanitize the content.
You don't want to send your sensitive
data, to, to your funder, let
alone, open AI or cohere, right?
So case GPT offers a way to mask the data.
As you can see here, you have the
error reported during the analysis.
We have a stateful set with a full name.
Right.
So that's the original data.
That's not, that's not masked and
what GPT does when you specify the
anonymization, it will mask that data.
That name will be masked before being
packaged into the payload and then sent
to the AI, back end once it's received
and then the variances run on that
input, the AI back end would send back
the information and GPT We'll actually,
process that solution return to the user
and amass the data that was amassed.
As you can see here, you can
see that the final output return
to the user has the right NAM.
So the user would know which
resource are we talking about.
Right.
So that's, the cool part, but be
aware that, some analyzers, not
everything is masked, unfortunately.
So you get, some resources like advance,
replica said pod PVCs aren't, which might,
be problematic in some situations, but.
What option do we have
to solve the problem?
Well, I do have one and that's just
me, but you can go fully private using
local LLMs because you can have an
inference server in the, in the, in
within your data center and you wouldn't
have to worry about sending, sensitive
information to open AI or cohere because
everything is within your data center.
So.
That's more safety.
Anyway, we also have remote caching.
So remote caching also allows to
afloat the cache data to a remote
storage service like S3 or Azure
Blob Storage, stuff like that for
persistency and also sort of relief.
your server, from, storage pressure.
I'm talking specifically for
cases where you have, case GPT
installed as an operator, right?
So you will just, move that storage
out of your nodes, in order just to
release a little bit of, of space.
Right.
And what are these?
Why are these data?
Right.
I was first asked myself,
like, what kind of data can be
cached and can be offloaded?
Well, it could be the analysis results.
It could be, the diagnostic
data, and it could be the key.
It's config data, right?
So specifically for in
cluster installation, right?
and then, we have the integration.
I already spoke about the integration.
you have integration with Prometheus,
which allows case GPT to leverage
real time metrics in order to
give more insights, more concept,
context to the air back end so
they can get the best solution.
Right.
So we could scrap those
metrics from Prometheus server.
And you can, also leverage
Trivia with the integration.
So you can scan the cluster for, potential
vulnerability, and also configuring
misconfiguration, cases as well.
So, and, and I actually could have
put, other plugins cause it's,
also supporting, Kyverno and Kera.
As well, just so for you to, to know,
and, the way to activate, an integration,
is through a simple command, which is
KGPT integration, activate, trivy, and
then right after that, you can just.
do a filter list, filters list,
and then you can see, that
you have two new analyzers.
They're not analyzers really,
because they're linked to the, the
plugin that was integrated to it.
That's why you have the
parentheses and integration.
so you can run, two types of
analysis, which is a vulnerability
report, and for CVS and a config.
Audit report as well.
And that might prove to be very useful if
you want to do everything in one location.
And of course the LLM AI backends,
you can see the list in here.
It's very, very exhaustive.
but if you find a backend that was not
listed or support, feel free to open
an issue or reach out to the team.
But to be honest, I'm pretty
okay with this list because
it's very, very exhaustive.
So.
That, that makes, that makes me happy.
If I want to choose an AI backends
any day or change it, I'm sure
I'll find it in the, in the list.
I just want to share an example.
Let's say OCI generative
AI from Oracle cloud.
what you would need to do
is have a credential to.
have access through API
to your cloud provider.
And then, the second command
is, KCPT auth add backend.
You specify the type of
backend, which is OCI.
And then you'd already
have a model, before.
So you specify the ID of the
model and the compartment, ID as
well, which is like resource group
in Azure or a project in, GCP.
So it's pretty straightforward.
Really straightforward, and right after
that, you can use kcp to analyze issues
to be solved and use the explain flag and
the back end to specify which back end
you want to use to get your solutions.
In terms of installation,
very straightforward.
Again, cross platform.
If you wanna install in Red
Hat, or Enterprise Linux
Fedora, there are RPM available.
if you can run a brew install if
you're in Mac os, or you can, install
in Ubuntu through a Dian package.
You can even install Windows.
And in WSL within Windows as well.
So it's pretty, ubiquitous
in terms of, installations.
And all you need after that actually is
have access to your Kubernetes clusters,
have a context, through kube config.
And after the installation of kcpt,
you may need to, eventually, if
you have access to a backend that
requires an API key, need to create
your API key, as you can see here.
I just chose OpenAI, but it's.
It's pretty, it's the same everywhere.
they now recommend to have project API
keys, maybe for, sort of a security,
purpose, or, you know, to keep track
of all the keys that you create.
And once you create that key, you
run case you beat the off, add.
And you specify the back end.
You don't need to specify open a
back end because it's a default one.
So if you run case you beat the off ad,
it will just ask you for the open a I
key by default without even specify an
open a I once this done, you can see that
the status off the the authentication
or the back end is now active.
That means that you can use it to
explain, On top of the analysis, right?
So you can run the case you pt,
analyze and you put you add the explain
flag plus the back end flag again.
Open AI doesn't require to put the,
dash B open AI, because it's the default
one, if you don't specify any, it will
go directly to use your open AI back.
And if it's defined.
One more thing to notice as well.
So once you, you, installed case
GPT and once you added one back
end, there is a configuration that
is stored, in your user directory.
So let's take unique linux.
For example, it's under, the
home directory dot config
case GPT case GPT dot yaml.
And, one thing you need to know is.
The API key is stored
in plain text, right?
So that's, one of the
things that I, noticed.
So like there is no, encryption
currently, enabled in order to sort of
mask, that, type of, type of secret.
Right.
So you got to be mindful of this, or
maybe try to play with the privileges
of this file or use an elevated
user in order to run GPT eventually.
and again, I also always have my
solution, my option, which is, the, just
go fully private and use, local LLM,
inference, within your, data center.
And when you have that, you
don't need a, an API key.
You will just have like SSL configured
and you have firewall and then
you'd be, safe on that matter.
You won't have to store any API key or
there, there won't be any secret sprawl.
All right.
In terms of CLI is that
it's straight to the point.
All right.
No fluff, just what you need.
so in terms of commands, it's
just like 10 beautiful and
easy, easy to remember commands.
So let's explain a few useful commands and
flags so we can focus on, on what matters.
The first one we just
described, it is the auth.
Right.
If you want to add a back end,
we did that with open AI, right?
You can add list and remove AI back end.
and after that, you can eventually
get some, appearance from your
back end when you were in case you
beat the second one is analyze.
So analyze, would just allow you to
find problems within your communities
cluster and provide you with a list
of issues that need to be resolved.
Right.
So it's like, events or
logs on steroids, right?
It will just show you the
issues that need to be resolved.
It will not reply.
It will not give you, solutions.
Why?
Because at this point, you're not
connecting to your AI backend.
So right, right here, there's just
a list of issues that are listed
through the KGPT with the analyze.
After that, you have the filter filter.
We said that we already said that
we have 19, analyzers, right?
So you have to specify which analyzer.
Analyzer you want to run because sometimes
you have a multi cluster environment
or you have, many namespaces, different
teams with, 20 teams with thousands
of, of, resources, different type.
Across the cluster.
So you don't want to run just the analyze.
Explain, especially if you
add explain, which is crazy.
So you want to run it based on every
type of resource in your cluster.
You want to be a bit more specific, right?
Just to reduce the amount of time
it will take and also reduce the
amount of output you will get, right?
Because if your cluster is filled
with issues, then like you would take
three or four or five pages, right?
And that's not what you want.
And now, this one is special because
this is where the magic happened, right?
So explain or dash E, is the
explain through AI, right?
So this, is the flag that would, trigger
the communication with your AI backend.
Right.
So from this point, you're
actually starting to pay.
If you added your API key from OpenAI
or code here, if you run a command,
analyze, and you edit, explain, that's
where you communicate with the AI
backend and get some info, right?
So before, you won't pay any, but at
this point, that's where the counter
actually is starting to run, right?
Because it's an API call
to your AI back end.
After that you have back end, obviously,
because sometimes, you configured, you
happen to have, you know, good for you,
cohere, anthropic, and, I don't know, it
could be even grok if you want to, right?
You have all, all of them defined.
And you can choose which back end.
The default one is OpenAI, but nothing
stops you from using another one.
And one of the advantages is that you're
actually building your own benchmark
based on the quality and accuracy
of the solution that are provided.
So like you can compare OpenAI with
Anthropic and see Which one is answering
better to you, depending on the use case.
And, you can also think of it
as a second opinion, right?
So it's like when you go to a
doctor, doctor says, yeah, we,
we need to go for amputation and
you're like, Oh, you know what?
I might need another, opinion.
So I, I, I may, I may ask another
doctor just, just to be sure.
Right.
So that's also very interesting feature.
We talked about integration to activate,
remove, or list the integration tree, V
or whatever, all the plugin, available.
And then we have, dash D or,
with doc, this one is cool.
Cause it's a no brainer.
sometimes you just want to
attach the documentation.
So wherever you show or a filter
analyzer, you choose, you can add dash D
and then it gets you the documentation.
The info, the documentation related
to the resource you're trying to
find a, a solution to, which is,
which is kind of, kind of cool.
So instead of a Googling, you'll just
having it, in the same command anonymize,
we talked about anonymized, it allows you
to, you know, mask your sensitive data.
And then we have namespace, right?
I already talked about the filter, so
you can filter the type of resource.
But how about filtering the namespace?
Because sometimes you have so many
namespace, in a cluster because
there's so many teams, right?
So, but if you're actually.
Just responsible for one namespace.
There was an issue in a namespace
and you want to check, or get some
solutions regarding an issue with
that resource in that namespace.
That's your, your, your, your go to shop.
Actually, this is my, my favorite,
company in namespace and filter
is like the best you can think of.
which is, which makes it very, very
more specific and granular in, in
your research and also it's faster.
for getting the answer.
this one is new.
this is, the stats, flag, which,
actually, is only available since,
the version three, 43, not before.
Right.
So it's very recent.
addition, and this will allow you to
display statistics of each analyzer run.
Right.
So, you can just show like how long
it took you to run the analyzer for
this or that, that type of resource.
You can see here that some
of them take milliseconds.
I'll attack seconds to minutes
depending on your workload.
But it might be useful if you're
trying to troubleshoot case
GPT analysis at some point.
So that's that's kind of cool.
All right.
so in terms of
architectures, there are two.
I already talked about the CLI, right?
So the CLI, you can install it in any
operating system, but it's everything.
It's process based.
It's within the host where you run it.
Right.
It's not inside the cluster.
So it's a binary, as you can see here.
So you can have within the binary,
you have the analyzers and when you
run it, analyze and you filter pod,
one of the analyzers, will be chosen.
And that analyzer has, actually a
bunch of, a bunch of, primitive.
Actually, that it gets from the API
servers, related to the, the type of
analyzer, as you can see here, like you
have the pod list advanced status, right.
And all this is actually, sort of
gathered, compacted, and then given
into making it easier to build results.
so he can send it into package it and
send it as a payload to your AI provider.
Right.
So analyzer.
Fetches the data,
organizes it, packages it.
You've got the built results
that can be run with the MNLize.
And then if you added the
explain, it will send all this
information to the AI provider.
The inference, would occur on that input.
And then at the end, the enriched
results are sent back with the solutions.
That's actually the main
loop of KHCPT with AI.
And at the end, the user has
access to, those final suggestions.
Right.
But there's also case GPT
operator, architecture.
Why?
Because this is, this happens when
you, you install it in cluster.
This is what we call in
cluster installation.
Right.
So I'm just trying to, to
actually show you the components.
So we have the case that I will
explain case GPT config case GPT.
Operator.
And then we have the
deployment with the analyzers.
Right?
And oops.
So this has access to the API server,
as I explained with the binary
version, and you will have also access
with whatever integration that is
available, like Trivi or Prometheus.
So we'll scrap the data, the
metrics from Trivi, from Prometheus.
You can run Trivi, scans, Through
GPT, through case GPT, and then the
analyzers will just build those, results,
send them to the, API for inference.
And then after that, it will
bring back the analysis results.
One thing you need to know is
that there is a requirement
to install the kshpt operator.
So the requirement is to install
the operator through the Helm chart.
So this does nothing,
just install the operator.
Then you will need to create a secret to
store the API key of your AI provider.
Why?
Because the CLI, right?
You don't have to do it anymore.
We don't have to store it
or do it interactively.
like with, the CLI with the binary,
everything is stored within the cluster.
So API key has to be a
secret right after that.
Then you can install the config object.
I also talked about KGBT config, right?
So this object, which is a
KGBT resource, can be run.
It's just a manifest that you will
run and will help, the operator create
a deployment and a bunch of CRDs.
And if you want to upgrade, you
just change the value of the
version of KGBT in that manifest,
and it will upgrade it for you.
automatically, and then, so the
operator will allow you to hold
primitives that contain the suggestion
return from your AI model, right?
So instead of having the result
when you run the command in CLI,
now it is stored within special
CRDs that are called results, right?
So these CRDs are called results,
resources, and they can even
be sent to a Grafana dashboard.
I can see here on the left side.
Right.
It can be sent to Grafana so you
can see it within, one of the
dedicated dashboard if you enable
it, in your Helm chart, right.
That would be super nice because
instead of like running kubectl
to get the results, you can have
access in a web browser, right.
And, just, want to show you.
Like the format of that kind of
resource, here, it's a simple example.
So we try to, deploy a pod with,
like a fake or wrong name of, image.
And then this can happen, automatically.
So we didn't have to run anything.
as opposed to the CLI.
And after that, it was directly sent
to AI and then AI got the information
and then send back some suggestions.
As you can see here in the solution,
check the image name, ensure the
image exists, blah, blah, blah.
and this is basically like a
simple back of Poland image, issue.
but that just shows you that, these
resources will be created automatically.
and then it will be just, Pylab
actually as a resource, ready
to be accessed, instead of just
running a command separately.
This is not a diagram, just, just
to show you that the PHP deployment
has, pods where the analyzers would
run and communicate with the API
server and the inference API server.
There's also a way to connect with,
do remote caching and also send
notifications to Slack as well.
Right.
So it's pretty much integrated, to
be honest, I was going to run a gif,
but, there's no way I can play it.
So this is the last frame.
As you can see here,
we have two resources.
We have the controller, controller manager
operator, and we have the deployment,
when you, deploy the case GPT config.
demo time, right?
So, hopefully I, I'm sorry again, if I
took too much, but, I really want you to
have, enough background on the tool and
also, on the challenges and, and AI and
every single, feature or, or, or use case.
but I, I may do something fun.
And right now, maybe I, we
can play something, we can run
some commands for you, right?
Let me see what I can play.
Right.
Okay.
So, I think, what we can do here
may be is what I want to tell you
is that, right now in my terminal,
I, One of the prerequisites is
installing kcpt and also, I have a
kube config that is already set up.
I have access to a managed cloud cluster
within OCI and my version of kcpt is 0.
3.
48.
That's the most recent one, right?
And now we can start to play with it.
So one of the first, command that I
may, need to run is, kcpt auth list.
Right.
You can see here that nothing,
there's a default open AI,
but nothing is configured yet.
Right.
But if I run it here, this is not the
terminal when I, when I already configured
my back ends, I have open AI that is
defined and Olama also that is defined.
Okay.
Right.
So, but if I wanted to enable
something, I could, enable,
Olama because I have actually a
bunch of models that are running.
They're all, quantized models
that are running within my laptop.
I have like a, just a tiny,
graphical card, but they can still
run and I can use it with case GPT.
Easily, right?
So what can we do?
Well, in my I'll share
my repo with read me.
You can see here that there is
a way to add the new back end.
So I'm just copying it here.
So what that means is that I'm
choosing all I'm as a back end.
I'm choosing the model.
Because, this is llama
three latest, right?
I want to specify the model and also
I'll specify the end point, right?
So if I click here, I come here, right?
I could run this, right?
All I'm, that's as straightforward
as it can get, right?
If I do off list right now a second time,
you can see that, Olama has been enabled.
Now we have Olama that is active, right?
So it's enabled, but let's
get back to like the kind of,
analysis that we can, run.
Right now, simple example, I'm not
going to do something crazy, right?
So we have, just, pod and I put
the, that wrong, image name, right?
And I tried to deploy it, right?
And it was in a specific, I call the
broken namespace just to, be sure, right?
See, so if I get the pods in
here, we can see that we have a
image pullback of already, right?
So the first thing you can do
is, yeah, I can run it here.
And then if I run it, it
will actually, no, not this one.
Okay, so I specify the back end,
which is Olama, and then it will run.
And if I duplicate this one,
right, see here, it's taking its time
because Obviously it's locally run.
so it's taking his time
and I'm sharing my screen.
So I think, there's a kind of,
it's capping out a bit, but I can
also do that and call in, open AI.
Cause, I also happen to have
that backend active, right?
So let's see, see, so like this one was
super fast because it was open AI, right?
And then it would just tell you.
That's the ANA analysis part.
And then here we gives you,
gives you the solution.
Same thing that we, you've seen, earlier.
I didn't want to do more right?
But in the mean meantime, I can
actually run, the last thing I could
run is this one vulnerability report.
Right?
I can do this and I can
try to explain it, right?
And if I explain it, I can use
open AI to explain it as well,
but it might take some time.
Right.
So if I do with that explanation,
it will just list all the CVS,
that are actually, triggered in
my, or existing in my cluster.
You see how many we have.
Right.
But if I want to run the, the inference
on it, just to have the suggestions,
this is the kind of CVS you can have.
With the solution.
So the green part is the response
from Olama eventually, right?
Cause there you go.
So this one is Olama and we
have more or less the same.
See, like this is an answer from
a local open source model, right?
And this, this was from, open AI, right?
So they're not depending
on the issue, right?
But of course there's a better
quality when you pay from open AI,
but it tells you that you can run.
Easily a local, appearance, if you
want to sort of, manage your, your,
your expenses, when you use a local
for specific issues and open AI for,
others, but this is just an example.
Let's say, for example, the CVE,
45, 3, 3, 7, you see, it's about.
I think it's about OC4G
or something like that.
So if I come here, it's really hard
to see what is need to be done.
Right.
But the advantage here is that KCBT
leverage, Trivi and then Ascent.
The message or like the, the payload
to AI, and then your LLM would just
give you some, solutions, right?
As you can see here, update Apache
log for G J to version two 19,
consider using a more secure login
library, blah, blah, blah, right?
So this is the kind of information
that it can give you, whether
it's analyzing, resources based
on issue, as I said, right?
Or, Based on vulnerability
or misconfiguration, right?
So I think I'm done with the demo.
I don't want to do more than this
because it's already too much.
And, the new project that the team
has is called a sketch nest, right?
So what is, sketch, sorry about the name,
but like, what is a sketch next is a
Kubernetes scheduler that uses insight
from KCPT to make a intelligent, decision
about where to place your workloads,
instead of a default scheduler scoring,
that is existing, by default, like
the vanilla version of your scheduler.
You can use a sketch next in order to
like smartly, place your, your, workload.
So maybe you don't have any topology
key defined, for example, so sketchness
will, will actually just help you,
like dynamically, schedule, the
resources based on like recent events.
which is not always, maybe accessible
to the, basic, so the, the default
scheduler, because they rely on
like, some very basic scoring.
So this is the, the curing project
that is integrated also with kcpt.
So, feel free to give it a, a look.
but in the meantime, thank you everyone.
I know it was too much.
If you want to reach out to me.
Again, I, I work at cloud thrill.
I can reach out to me on Twitter
or, LinkedIn, dot com as well.
This is my GitHub repo.
So thanks everyone.
And, that was amazing to be with you.
Appreciate it.