Speaker 42: Hi everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 and logistics,
as well as in federal space.
And the topic for my today's
talk is observability as a.
Platform contract and how can we
implement a zero code instrumentation and
enforce it through S-C-I-C-D pipelines?
We're going to dive into different
problem statements, what exactly the
problem statement we're trying to solve.
What are the various solutions along
the way and how we have solved this
in our organization, which can be
helpful and useful for not only our
organization, but various organizations
and industries along the way.
So with that context, let's dive in.
So before we dive in.
Let's understand what's the state of the
observability today which means we have to
understand what is the problem statement,
what are we trying to solve, and what
are the pain points in the industry
and in various organization today?
So as you see on the screen, maturity
of the state of the observability today.
Lies between these four blocks, and
to give you an, when we talk about
observability various organization have
purchased and licensed various different
observability tools starting from Datadog,
new Relic, Prometheus, Grafana, and
many others, many million other tooling,
different variations of tooling along
the way, which means every single tool.
Would need a manual instrumentation, which
implies if you have to find a certain log
or a trace or a metric, or any alerting
you want to create, it should be coded
somewhere in your solution or in a part
of your application, which means it's
a part of the manual instrumentation.
And if you think from.
At retrofitting this solution into
existing organization or large enterprise
organizations who have millions and
millions of lines of code, it's very
difficult task, a very daunting task,
which means if a part of a code is not
instrumented, or you have not added a
line of code, which then generates a
trace or generates a log, et cetera,
it's a very inconsistent coverage.
So only those part which we
instrumentation has been added.
Would get the coverage.
Everything else becomes a
blind spot, which results into
a very reactive debugging.
When the fire comes or an incident
comes, you become a very reactive way
of looking at things which means safe.
Your instrumentation was already coded.
Some part of it is coded
and some part is not.
So if the issue comes in a very
different part of your stack where it
was not covered, it becomes a reactive
approach of, Hey, let's go fix this.
So it's a very reactive way of looking at
things, which can add a lot of frustration
and a lot of incomplete solution.
And team silos is also big one
which talks about how current
teams platform teams would tell.
Or think from a mindset
perspective, we do not understand
the application codes context.
We do not understand what part
of the code should be covered
and should not be covered.
And from an application team's
perspective, they may say it's a part
of the platform team's responsibility.
So that creates a very siloed approach
towards how we look at observability.
So overall, if you look at these four
pillars, it becomes a very incomplete.
Solution as well as a very
disturbing culture, as well as
very disturbing and frustrating
experience from platform perspective,
from an application perspective
and from a business perspective.
It becomes a very challenging when
it comes to reactive debugging, which
means it's a cost to the company.
So various organizations, even the larger
enterprise, the larger the enterprises.
The bigger the problem, the bigger
the scale of the problem becomes.
So that is the core of the talk
today, and this is the problem
statement, which exists not only one
enterprise, but many enterprises and
how we're going to solve for this.
So let's go into how
we're going to solve it.
So as we talked about the
problem statement, which exist
in various organization and
enterprises, let's now dive into
what does the new model look like?
It's called platform contract.
And the core idea behind this is how
can the platform contract elevate our
observability from an opt-in heroics
to an explicit platform responsibility?
How do we transform it into a
guaranteed, which is provided to
every service in exchange of the
kind of falling paved road, right?
The approach for this is to
make observability as a first
class platform rather than.
An afterthought bolted
into the individual teams.
So it doesn't mean if you have added
a core observability as part of your
stack or a part of your application, you
would still get that observability as a
platform contract, which then results into
a standardized instrumentation, patents.
It results in a consistent signal
collection across various services, so
that as a business, as an organization.
You get visibility into all the
services rather than just some opt-in
services, which had a thought of
observability as a first class citizen.
You also have a measurable reli
requirements, reliability requirements,
which is meeting your SLOs and meeting
your SLAs with your external customer.
And then also there is a federated way of
doing a compliance verification as well.
So these are.
The platform contract which
we're talking about as an
observability first class platform.
And which would then result into
all of these outcomes as well.
So let's also now dive into what
does it means when we talk about
this platform contract in detail.
So as we talked about.
The platform contract, let's now
understand how does it tie together
with the service layer and the contract
layer and guaranteed observability.
So if you look at the
diagram here you would see.
Four core rings where one is platform
layer, another is service layer or
an app layer, and the contract layer,
and then the guaranteed observability.
So if you look at the top two platform
layer as well as the service layer, they
are tied together with the contract layer.
And then if you look at the
service side as a outcome of this
model a service, which is an.
Service or an application would
get an observability as a outcome
of this platform contract model.
So in a nutshell, if you have to
understand this the core idea behind this
is a service would get a comprehensive
observability without writing a single
line of instrumentation code to get.
Observability in terms of the logs,
the traces, the metrics kind of
database call visibility and all
the observability artifacts and the
platform would handle the collection of.
All of these observability
metrics for you, right?
And the contract layer would define
the expectation in terms of what
should be the core expectation in
terms of whether it's S-L-A-S-L-O,
how the platform should behave, or
the service should behave, et cetera.
The contract would define those
expectation with respect to
the observability in this case.
And then.
To make sure we enforce this as a
compliance, A-C-I-C-D, which is continuous
integration and continuous deployment.
Will become very handy for us to make
sure it is it is observed, it is enforced,
and it is compliant so that it becomes a
first class citizen in every single time.
And then we're gonna dive into
a little bit onto zero code
instrumentation architecture.
Next.
So let's see.
What does the zero code
instrumentation architecture look like?
So if we start looking into a zero
code instrumentation architecture,
there are three core pillars or
core components of the zero code
instrumentation, architecture,
automated instrumentation, runtime
side cars, and base container images.
So let's talk about each one by one.
So what does automated
instrumentation mean?
It means we'll have open telemetry
agents and framework configurations,
inject telemetry across languages
and protocols without code changes.
As a developer or an application team or a
platform team, you have to write zero line
of code for this instrumentation to work.
That's why it's called
auto instrumentation.
So there are various different
frameworks, Java Spring Boot Letter,
or any other framework you're using
as a language, whether to come
from java.net or other languages.
So these agent has multi-language
support and they can be injected and
configured according to what is needed.
So that's why it's automated.
In, in, in that way.
You do not have to manually write
any line of code or observability
stack to work, and inside card
pattern would basically capture.
Network traffic, it would
capture database query, it would
capture message interaction.
It would capture your web
traffic and all the component.
And if you look think from a
application standpoint, starting from
a web layer to the middleware to a
database query, you get a visibility.
For your stack end to end, not just
web layer, not just middleware, not
just database queries, but end to end.
And then there is a way to
correlate a web traffic to a
database query to a middleware.
And so you get an end-to-end visibility
with these run time side cards.
And then you can build a lot of
alerting along the way in terms of
those metrics traces, as well as the
logs and from the platform layer.
If you talk about base container images.
You as a platform team would ship a
pre-configured images, which has baked
in observability component, which
ensures the consistent deployment.
What does it mean?
It means your base images, which are being
used for deployment of the service or an
application to the production systems.
It would have observability baked
in, which means we have enabled.
Open telemetry agents, we have
enabled, what ports would it listen to?
We have configured what kind of
metrics, traces, logs would be
enabled disabled based on that.
So that as an application team,
as soon as you create a PR and
merge your PR and the pipeline
fronts and it gets that base image.
Your observability is already baked
in to that system, so that's why it
becomes a zero code instrumentation.
It abstracts away all the information
from the application teams.
And if you look at the diagram
below, your application code goes in,
instrumentation layer comes in terms
of the base container images, and then
that has already baked in information
about your observability components.
Observably backend gets executed, and
then at the end of this infinity loop
this cycle, you can analyze and improve.
How do you want to now configure?
And then you'd start getting the
results as part of your stack.
Whether you have a tool called Datadog,
new Relic, Grafana or any other million
other tooling available, you can start
analyzing and improving those results as a
part of this instrumentation architecture.
As we talked about the zero code
instrumentation framework, now the next
question comes out, how do I support my
application teams or my platform team?
What kind of languages do I
support and how do I, Hey, we
are in A-W-S-G-C-P versus Azure.
How do we get this working?
So good news.
It is available for multi-language
as well as multi-cloud.
And I understand the reality we live in.
We live in a very heterogeneous
environment, which definitely re requires
a strategic planning along the way.
So that's why when I talked about
Opal Telemetry agents, it has
support for automatic instrumentation
starting from Java, Python, node.
Go T net and many more languages
including PHP and others as well.
And when you talk about cloud agnostic
solutioning we have given done a
consistent deployment across AWS
Azure GCP using portable containers
and standardized collectors.
So if you use docker containers and any
of those technologies behind the scene,
it can be deployed to E-K-S-A-K-S-G-K-S.
With the very cloud agnostic approach
and for our organization, we have
instrumented successfully instrumented
200 plus services across three
cloud with 99.2% and more coverage.
Which gives us a good confidence
in terms of multi-language
and the multi-cloud reality.
So it becomes a very widespread
solution, which all the
organization can benefit from.
As we talked about the multi-language
and the multi-cloud support, it's always
important to, it's also important to talk
about the observability contracts and
the first class artifacts it generates.
So if you look at the diagram on the slide
the core component would be defining.
The contract definition, we defined
the signal requirements as a
specification and the validation tool,
and think this from a platform as
well as from the service perspective.
The idea here is we want to have.
A very low noise and high impact signals.
So we want to understand what signal
would define a service to be reliable
up as well as the co deficiency, or if
the system is down, what would that be?
And then from an SLO specification,
it's a service level.
At a service level, we need to define.
What kind of SLAs?
SLOs we want to define which means
whether we want to have a 99.9% uptime,
whether we wanna define P 95 latency.
So all of those becomes a manifest
and pipelines, which is basically
version controlled agreement.
So think of this as think of this as
contract, which sits alongside your
manifest as well as pipeline, and they're
very much version controller agreements.
And then.
As a result of this contract would
transform your vague reliability goal
of, Hey, my website or my service is
slow versus fast into a measurable
and enforced agreement that integrate
directly into your deployment pipeline.
Then you can go with a confidence and
say, my website's P 95 latency is.
Point three millisecond, 0.1
millisecond, so on and so forth.
So rather than this vague goal of
being a fast and slow, you can pinpoint
to that data with the artifact.
So that's the core objective of
these observability contracts.
So as we talked about
observability, contracts we
should also start thinking about.
How should we enforce those through CICD?
So think of contract enforcements
similar to CICD enforcement for
security protocol if, or a testing
protocol, or say for example, if your
repo has a testing framework and the
test coverage is not about 75 to 80%.
We fail the pipeline.
So similarly, these observability
contracts should also be
enforced through CICD.
So take the typical example
of your source code.
Your code is committed, it is pushed
the changes are pushed to the repo.
The contract validation which is the
core component of this where you would
verify schema and the a PA contracts.
The contracts get validated.
You would also do instrumentation
check to ensure the observability hook
exists the pre-baked in image exists,
and then the pipeline moves forward.
So the core element behind
this is if the contract.
Is the validation fails or schema fails,
or contract enforcement or contract
validation fails in the pipeline.
There should be a way to
fail the pipeline similar to.
If the test coverage is not
more than 75% or if there is
a core security vulnerability,
and then the pipeline fails.
Similarly so think from a mental
model perspective, your contract
enforcement through CICD, similar
to how a testing or a security or a
vulnerable bug would be enforced to
the, through the continuous integration,
continuous deployment pipeline.
As we talked about.
Some of the enforcement through
the CICD, the another objective
or a question we would ask is.
What are, what is the data telling us?
What kind of results have we seen with
those changes in our organization?
So the diagram on the slide right
now talks about in the left hand
side and the right hand side around
before and the after of this.
And then the first.
AF talks about the manual and
fragmented approach, and then, and
the right hand side talks about the
automated and the unified approach.
The numbers we have seen is from the
SLO, which was at 23% before, and the
meantime to respond was 45 minute.
Both of those numbers has
significantly improved.
I would say there is a 60 to 70%
improvement on those numbers.
And not only those numbers have improved,
but we have also seen our failed
deployment has gone to 12%, which was
at a very high rate of 30 to 40% before.
And then similarly, manual rollbacks are
78% less now, where we'd have to manually.
Roll back anything, which means we
have now higher confidence in terms
of deploying our services because we
have observability in place for those.
So that observability gives us a
good confidence of deploying with
confidence, less failure rate our.
Time to respond for incident has improved
significantly, and our SLO metrics have
improved drastically, and our customers
are much more happier with those results.
So these are some of the results I wanted
to share so that it gives perspective
on what are the key metrics to look
for when you think from a success
metric or KPIs to define to your
leadership in various organization.
And then how, and.
It would apply to different organization
in a different way, but there is a
costing related to number of resources
allocated to it, number of licensing
allocated to it, and specifically if
you can save developers time in terms
of the failed deployment and rollbacks.
That itself translate into multimillion
dollars every single year, depending on
the different organizations and different
enterprises and the cost saving of that as
the enterprises becomes larger and larger,
the and exponential in that case as well.
As we talked about some of
the results in a brief way.
So let's zoom a little bit around
what does it mean from wake targets
to the measurable agreements?
So as we touch a little bit around
being a web being a slow website
to the fast website or to a slow
service, to a fast service or
somewhat available to available.
In terms of P 95 or P 99 response time,
and then what is our meantime to respond
to a specific service or incident.
So the core idea behind SLOs
is from big target to vegetable
agreements for our customers.
For our stakeholders, for
engineers, for platform to everyone
in the organization, right?
So when we talk about these
numbers, so what we have
achieved is 99.9% availability.
Which basically target encoded
directly in the contracts.
So 22.
50 millisecond latency when it comes to P
99 or P 95 in terms of the time enforced
for the latency SLO, when it comes to the
added budgets, when in the range of 0.1%,
and when it comes to the reduced MTTR
talking about 73% in terms of after the
contact was implementation implemented.
So if you look from a very traditional
versus a contract based approach,
we're talking about manual as
tracking, which means not only.
We have a wastage of time in terms of,
we don't have a way to measure it, but
even measuring it manually wastes more
time for the developers and the teams.
We have a lack of automated SLO
enforcement 80% or more, which is, I think
for us it was like 85% or plus incident.
SLO context in terms of db layer, web
layer, middleware layer, and how does
it translate into incident and how do we
respond back to with a better context.
So that's a traditional
approach, flaw flaws.
And when we talk about contract based,
a hundred percent are deployments.
Are SLO correlated to correlate?
Takes 10 to 20 minutes and to
identify root cause it could be
anywhere between five to 10 minutes.
So that very much contract based numbers,
which gives us a good confidence in terms
of deployment, in terms of coating issue,
in terms of identifying root cause.
So we take away the vagueness from
the equation and convert that into a
measurable agreement when we follow
visibility with the platform contracts.
As we talked about some of the
numbers in the previous slide.
So let's start looking into how does the
release automation integration would work?
What kind of deployment
strategies would be implemented
when it pertains to contracted?
The overall baseline is the following.
So you have a baseline capture,
which means you basically current
record your current SLI performance
before deployment begins.
Canary deployment is usually a good way
to, to look at this because the core
idea behind canary deployment is you
route a very small percentage of your
traffic to a new versions, new version.
So let's say for example, if a service
teams comes back with a new version, you.
You deploy in a canary deployment fashion,
you start from 5% of your traffic split,
or it can be 1%, 2% de depending on
what the organization is comfortable
with or the teams are comfortable with.
But let's say for an example, you
start with a 5% split, and then
based on that 5% split, you can also.
An SLO evaluation.
So compare your canary metrics against
your baseline or your production
live traffic, which is 95% of
your traffic and burn rate policy.
So based on those two metrics, you
would be able to understand what my P 95
latency is, what my metrics look like.
Have we improved our SLO?
Have we not improved our SLO?
So basically testing this feature.
In comparison with your SLO evaluation
and if your numbers look good, you promote
and then increase the traffic to 50% and
then a hundred percent, which is full
rollout, which is a successful release.
And if it does not satisfy your
SLO requirement or degrade your
SLAs and SLOs, we can roll back.
And then only 5% of the test of
the traffic was exposed to it.
You tested it and then defined.
So that not only gives you confidence
in your deployment, but it also
tells you your SLOs and SLAs and
how your website is performing.
So it not only gives you a good.
A way to look at your services.
It also improves your SLOs and
you can make these real time
decisions based on these metrics.
So not only your.
Taking away the vague nature of the
reliability metrics, but also taking
away the vague nature of how you
deploy with confidence so that gives
you a good baseline to deploy with
confidence and to deploy with better
SLOs as well as we looked into.
The deployment patents and the confidence
with the SLO contracts in in, in
connection with community deployment and
how it helps in the confidence of the
deployment with respect to SLOs and SLAs.
Let's also look into accelerated
in incident response.
So a kind of streamlined
resolution before and after, right?
So from a symptom to root
these unified workflows.
Would use existing traces, existing
metrics, which would help us in rapid
identification of problematic changes.
So as we talked about doing a Canadian
leases of 5% or 10% or 1%, depending
on your organization's foot level.
As the new data would
start coming into this.
So we would have a way to
automatically correlate to a specific
deployment through a version tag.
Say a version one is deployed
and version two comes in and
version two has 5% traffic split.
As we connect these different versions,
this degraded SLI would then get tied
to that particular version tag and then.
If you have to do a trace analysis,
a trace, if you have to expand a
little bit is basically multiple
span, collection of multiple span.
So you drill into a specific span.
It would show where was the web
call, where was the middleware call,
where was the database call, and
what, and not only where was the
database call, what was exactly the.
The database query, which ran and
based on advanced observability
tools, you can also connect into
what query ran for what second, and
whether that was indexed or not.
Adding Datadog and many other tools
provide that kind of capabilities
where you can actually enable the
database monitoring, which then.
Talks about and it has a flamed graft.
It has a spam graft.
You can replay many of those and have
a lot of correlation along the way.
Which gives you a very
accelerated incident response.
I have personally been in many
of the situation where we had
an incident and then I would, I
was able to pinpoint directly.
From timestamp perspective, from
database query perspective, as well
as from a web call perspective.
So I was able to take a query, run it
back to an application code, was able
to tie together to what deployment
tag was culprit for that incident.
And then also going back to.
The application code to a to a
GitHub in terms of what exactly
was the application code, which
was responsible for that error.
So giving you that level of
visibility would accelerate the
incident response tremendously.
Would used to take you a hundred
percent of the time, would literally
take you 10 or 15% of the time.
So it's a huge saving in terms
of the incident response and.
Not to mention whenever the incident
happens, 50 or a hundred people
joining the call and taking arts to,
to resolve has a huge cost downside
to it, or potential to it as well.
So it, it gives you that accelerated
incident response in many ways.
So it's a win-win
situation when it comes to.
Your deployment confidence as well as
accelerated incident response as well.
So as we talked about the accelerated,
it's the incident response.
It's very important to talk
about the adoption pattern that
worked for us and can work for
various different organization
and enterprises along the way.
Core components or core pillars you
would see is the pilot expansion and
scale in different implementation phases.
In the pilot phase, I would start
with two or three, which would take
roughly around somewhere between
four to six weeks and expansion
would be 20 to 10 to 20 services,
two to three months of timeframe.
And then as you start measuring the
result of pilot result of your expansion.
You would have early adopters,
you would have some teams which
has done a little bit of exploring
along the way, and you have done
some experimentation along the way.
You have some learnings along the way.
What works for your organization
and what does not work.
Your work, work for your organization and
some constraints to work with in terms
of security, adoption, different teams,
different adoption practices, et cetera.
And then that's the point when you take
these learnings and then scale, which is
an organization wide ongoing, and then.
Start with gradual introduction,
which is start with pilot services,
expand and avoid any roadblocks.
And then when we start to scale,
you also want to start doing
in engineering train training.
So start with educating teams on
SLO through workshops, through
different documentation, through
embedded platform engineers.
What worked for us was an
organization-wide workshop,
so we would engage.
Two to three teams, every workshop
starting from a signup sheet,
we would engage two or three
different teams in a workshop.
And then we would pick up their use
cases, the metrics they're interested
in the traces they're interested in, so
that it becomes interesting enough rather
than a generic training or generic talk.
And it solves their use cases
and problems and service level
metrics, which gives them, which
keeps them engaged and involved.
In the process, and when one team
starts seeing the results and problems
being addressed, that's when the
adoption becomes contagious and it
starts scaling out very rapidly.
So that was one of the lessons which
we learned through the workshops,
keep it very pertaining to two
or three teams, target specific
problem statement for that service.
Team and let it expand from that point.
Have early adopters, champions,
and then start clear, start
creating community along with a
good documentation along the way.
So I think gradual introduction and
training with a specific use cases was
the adoption pattern which works and
then can be very well implemented in
many organizations and enterprises.
As we touched a little bit on around.
The adoption pattern, which
works I wanted to share about the
implementation across various industries.
I, I've been involved in starting
from financial services to
retail as well as in logistics.
In financial services, we have achieved
99.9% of traceability across 2.3
million daily transactions in retail.
Maintain 99.95% uptime
during Black Friday with.
X normal traffic using
added budget policies.
An e-commerce platform used added
budgets to balance the feature velocity
with customer experience during.
Peak shopping periods, we're
talking about 12 x 13 x, 14 x of
the usual traffic into the retail
and then e-commerce space as well.
Even in the logistics and maritime
instrumented four 50 plus microservices
with zero code changes, which
reduced our deployment time by 40%.
So these are various industries I've been
part of where we've implemented this.
So that's why it gives us
a good confidence that.
The adoption pattern works and then,
and the results also come through.
So these are some of the, kind of
the examples and some of the data
that I wanted to share for all of
us as to to use and learn from.
So we talked about adoption pattern,
we talked about some numbers and
some of the things we have done.
The million dollar question
is, how does this blue.
Print work for our success, right?
For platform observability.
So this is, if you look in another diagram
on the right hand side, these are some
of the blueprint or kind of paved road
we should look into, which would give
you, so these core five points, right?
Which would give.
The blueprint for the success in
your organization and navigation
through your organization for platform
observability, zero code instrumentation
deployed zero code instrumentation
with open elementary agents and
base images, defining contracts.
Define your SLOs definition,
your signal requirement.
Work with your application
teams on what are the high.
Signal, low noise signals, which
are critical for the success, bread
and butter of that service, CICD
integration, have a validation.
Gates enforce those gates along the way.
Production monitoring.
Have SLO tracking have added budgets along
the way, which will help to balance out
and for the SLO tracking whether we are on
track or not, and continuous improvement.
Continue to improve, start small,
iterate over it over and over again
until you get to the final destination.
So these are the kind of blueprint of
the success which would one by one.
Day by day, iteration by
iteration can be improved on.
And then these are the core pillars, which
would help us to get to the final state
of platform observability with zero code.
So once we follow those blueprint, what
is the end outcome we're looking at?
So let's look at if we enable
this at organization wide
scale, what are we looking at?
We're looking at a measurable reliability.
We are looking at continuous improvement,
we're looking at safe velocity and
we're also looking at the team autonomy.
And if you start looking back to the
problem statement we started with was.
These four pillars in terms of
there's a team silos that is not
very difficult or easy way to deploy
confidently with automated rollback.
And then how do we make sure our manual
instrumentation where the insufficient
coverage, et cetera, et cetera.
So the laundry list of
problems is a huge to tap into.
So four pillars of coverage,
manual instrumentation, and then.
How do you deploy with confidence
and team autonomy and very
fragmented solution overall.
So this is what gives you that enable,
that will enable the organization wide
scale with 99.2% of service coverage,
73% of faster MTTR from 45 minutes to 12
minutes for your incident or meantime to
respond confidence of your deployment.
85% or more, which is SLO driven releases,
would give you that confidence, which we
talked about during the canary releases
and how we can deploy with confidence
and 40% or more faster delivery,
which means you reduce the manual
validation, you rely on SLOs and you
rely on them service level agreement.
And then we can have a faster
delivery along the way as well.
And.
If you have questions around, I'm
more than happy to discuss this, how
to implement observability contracts
in your organization as well.
And with that, I would like to conclude
my talk here at Conference 42 DevOps 2026.
This is my LinkedIn link.
I would also share that in
the presentation as well.
Happy to connect over the LinkedIn.
Reach out if you have any questions or any
implementation details or would love to
have a discussion around observability.
I'm more than happy to connect,
discuss, and share ideas and even
help on the implementation side as.
So I'll look forward for many
other talks during the conference.
I hope this was helpful.
This was worthwhile your time, and I'm
looking forward for many more conferences
and other panelists to to share idea,
ideas and thoughts along the way.
So that was my talk at Con 42 DevOps 2026.
Thank you so much.
Have a wonderful rest of the conference.