Speaker 35: Hi everyone.
I'm Roxanne Fisher CO and co-founder
of In Shift, and today I'm very excited
about speaking about the importance of
context when it comes to your production
systems and especially context.
We, a graph knowledge graph when
you speak about infrastructure
and production system.
And happy to deep dive into it.
First of all, I just want to put
on myself, I am one of the of any
shift we build AI on call engineers.
So we are going to streamline debugging
and find root cause analysis when you
have like complex systems, production
systems between different sources of the
data and we actually build this graph.
It's context engineering for
your infrastructure and to them.
I'm not exactly going to speak about
our product layer at any shift, but
more about the tech that we create
underneath, which is this graph
to illustrate the point and the
important of context and graph databases.
I'm going to use a first example on how.
The context and why it's so
important to have one when it
comes to your infrastructure.
The first one I'm going to take is about,
it's going to be about infrastructure as
code generation and why it fail short when
you don't have the right context of all
the last past years, models have become
extremely good at generic team code, but
when it comes to infrastructure code.
It often falls short or there
some limitation, and I'm
going to try to explain why.
The example I'm going to take here is
going to be very simple example for a new
one with familiar with infrastructure and
for the one who are not, let me explain.
When you deal with infrastructure
score, you're going to
deploy infrastructure with.
Code files and one of the framework
that is one of the most wellknown is
star from a easy thing that you could
ask a general developer or like at
least depending of like how sensitive
infrastructure is to create a VPC
peering connection in Terraform.
To actually create a peering between two
VPCs your own, your company one, and an
external one, which could be something
that is done as code for Terraform.
So let's see how it goes, depending
of how you try to complete this task.
What I'm showing here would be a
piece of code, which could be written
by a general developer, no ai.
Simple kind of very use
case with bad practices.
Where you can see here that the VP
C Ping between two VPCs is going
to be out coded by the developer.
It got through the AWS console or any
kind of console to different ideas
and going to create the connection.
This is very bad practice because
you are going to create values
which can break dependencies.
When your infrastructure
gets more and more complex.
So now let's see how the same
task would've been done by an
LLM, let's say GitHub copilot.
What you can see here is that with
the latest changes and updates of lms.
The quality of the outcome would be
pretty good, and GitHub copilot, for
instance, will know that it doesn't
have, it cannot do accurate values,
which should use dependencies.
In this case, it would be the
best practice, but it misses the
real value to make the connection.
What GitHub copilot will try to do next
is to then take into account like those
missing values and try to create them.
Because it doesn't have the context of
what the idea of my VPC is or where it
is defined in another repository, it is
going to try to create a new one, which is
realistic in term of code, but completely.
Not which is complete in term of
code, but completely not realistic.
And in this case, because we didn't have
the context of my entire infrastructure,
which can be huge, the LLM falls short.
Now the question is, can cursor
or any ai, IDE can do it normally?
Such Id.
Take into account multiple repositories
and able to make those connections.
In my case, this is what should
have been done by Cursor.
I have created this new VPC Ping
connection and what I want is that
I'm referencing for it viable to
another repository with my own VPC,
with my and with the remote states.
The thing is, if I come back to my earlier
example where my junior developer has
created in the past, at the beginning
of my company some accurate values
in this case, this value is only a
value that refers to a cloud resource.
It doesn't refer to anything else.
In that case, cursor cannot, in any case,
make the connection, the dependency link
between this article value, which is
part of my code very often, or when I
have like multiple integrated modules,
two, my remote PC in another repository.
This is the case because cursor
cannot do the reconciliation
between cloud data and code.
It doesn't have the context.
I am actually going to skip the
live demo and speak straight away
about how we could get this context
through a live knowledge graph.
First of all, just to give some
context a graph database is another
structure database structure,
which is not the control.
Which under a graph actually
can represent different identity
entities for nodes and edges.
In the case of your infrastructure,
it makes total sense because your
infrastructure is a graph and your
nodes represents different entities.
VPC, ims, per nodes, containers that
actually can be linked by different
type of connection, for instance.
An IM can be linked to an IS
two instance and an ECI two
instance can belong to A VPC.
So that would be a very easy and
small represe of your infrastructure
as a graph that you can see here that
represent versus instance service
type accounts, providers, et cetera.
At the end, your infrastructure.
Production systems is a huge monster,
which is actually a connection
between your cloud providers,
Kubernetes containers, code bases,
vis data, et cetera, et cetera.
The more deep and rich this
knowledge graph is, the better.
Imagine you have all the
metadata on top of it.
So how is my life data
defined in my code base?
Who owns it?
Who did a commit on it?
What is my metadata in
term of like timeline?
Then I can ask with ai very deep question
such as which instances like EC2 instances
or pods are experiencing high CPU usage
over the last 24 hours, and what are the
dependencies or service dependencies?
And you can go even more deep because
you have access to all this information
in reality.
Your graph, your infrastructure
as a graph is much more complex.
So it's even like still a small snapshot
of what we do at any shift, which is
like this representation of a graph of
infrastructure as a graph, and at the
end it can be 10 of million of nodes when
you also take versioning into account to
create this graph is complex how to do it.
The first thing to create such context
would be to recreate this entire
pipeline by using a graph database.
We use Norfor internally at any shift.
You can use, for instance, Neptune
on AWS or Ola kind of providers.
Once you have decided on your
graph database as a technology,
you need to define your ontology.
Your ontology actually correspond to
how you're going to build this graph.
In term of structure, what are going to be
the nodes, what are going to be the edges?
It's a very complex work because
imagine you need to create a common
ontology for different cloud providers.
You need to have a similar representation
for A-W-S-G-C-P and Azure, so your AI
will be able to treat them as equivalent,
even if the definition are not the same.
Once you have created your ontology.
We need to populate this graph.
So to do each integration is
going to be slightly different.
How do you scrub the data?
How do you update the graph?
And each of them can be taken separately.
So for instance, for AWS, you can
connect to different APIs, do some scan
of the resources, but also like use
cloud trail to have live updated data
for like graph, which is super fresh.
This is where the artwork comes from.
Having the clean and structured
data is something that takes a lot
of time, especially when you have
like multiple integration and source
of information as written here.
It's time heavy on how to maintain,
but gives particularly good context.
The other solution, which is
also pretty good at some lower
scales for startups and scales.
To use Mt. P servers, MCP servers model
context protocols, actually very easy
way to connect your LLM to data sources.
S for instance, have amazing MCP servers
and by connecting your credentials.
To those cps and using them within
your AI tools, AI agents, you can
easily get some very useful context
to answer to the question that
you want to have an answer to.
Such as that, what is my life data?
What are the resources that ai,
what are the resources that are like
under like heavy load or usages?
But at the end, this solution, which
is really straightforward, would be
limited if infrastructure is too big
because an SP server is just an API and
each time you make an API call, you can
just archive a limited amount of data.
If you really want to understand in
one call, all the dependencies, all the
relationship, all the history on one
specific request, you need first to have
this huge cache, this huge database of
how infrastructure actually looks like.
In this example, in this slide,
I've actually tried to show
how you can build this graph on
a subset, on a small example.
The example here is how to create a
mapping between your cloud data, let's
say A-W-A-W-S, still, in this case,
your states and new Terraform code.
The case here is to be able to understand
what has drifted in your infrastructure.
So what has been correctly defined in
your code and what has not been, and
which resources in your cloud can be
considered as shadow it or drifted.
To do you need to create reconciliation
between the graph in your cloud.
So what actually really
exists in your cloud?
What has been defined in your
code and what is actually like
this inter intermediate cache
layer in your Terraform state?
To create this graph, you have two steps.
First, you need to pass the data, and
then you need to populate the graph.
So in the first case, you need to
pass the data for AWS for Terraform
States and for your Terraform file.
Using the different ideas to make
some reconciliation and to create
some links between the entities.
So you're going to use the same idea for
your cloud of sources in the Midwest.
To the Terraform entity in your
Terraform States and then to the
Terraform entity with its code
definition in the Terraform file.
Once you have been able to
make this mapping, you need
to to put it in the graph.
You need to build the graph and be
able to update it live, but actually
once the first step has been done,
the second one is much easier if you
don't have to if the scale of your
infrastructure is not too big and if your
amount of change is like quite limited.
And actually that's the end in 15
minutes, which was the maximum.
But, so in conclusion, what I want
to emphasize here is that when it
comes to your production system, and I
wanna speak about context engineering.
Context is key and it should
be represented as a graph.
Your different services, if that
forms within your infrastructure
and your application can and should
be represented as a graph which
is way more dense in information
than just a relational database.
The AI can be direct because we
really need, when we speak of AI
to have this context to create some
quality code and quality debugging.
And that's it for me.
Thank you so much and have a great day.