Speaker 26: Hello everybody.
My name is Paul Lo Halda.
I'm a technical architect in Cognizant.
Today I'm going to discuss about
the AI e power CICD implementation,
based on and with the predictive
DevOps, which is faster and release.
So that is all about.
The difference between the traditional
CICD deployment for the DevOps versus
the IPO CICD implementation, which
implemented predictive analytics.
Four, the implementation.
So in this session today, I will
discuss about what are the advantages,
what are the barriers, what are the
implementation of EI power, CICD, and
how it is differ from the traditional
development implementation approach.
So I'm going to the next
slide, which is the agenda.
Of our today's session.
Today's session, we'll going
to discuss about the problem
context, predictive DevOps, concept
architecture, process flow, and impact
for the I-C-I-C-D implementation.
I'm going to the next step where we will
discuss about all the detail about the.
Our today's topic, CICD,
implementation for the AI powered
CICD deployments for the DevOps.
Okay, so I'm going to the next one
where I will discuss about in the
detail why there is some barrier.
There is some problem, there is
some limitation, there is some
failure, why traditional CICD
breaks that we need to understand?
Okay, before we are going to
implementation, the AI implemented
CICD deployment automation,
we need to understand why.
The traditional CI CT breaks, so
there are different kind of thousand
reason among which I have collected
five six reason, which are more
vital to deployment scenarios.
First one is the reactive
monitoring, which alerts the
fast after the damage is done.
Second one is the late failure detection.
Third one is the human heavy trigger edge.
Third one is the pin.
So I provide all the detail and all the
steps for that in the right hand side.
Architecture diagram.
If you see from the rea reactive
CICD two, predictive DevOps.
In the traditional CICD, there is some
safe build, deploy test and there is lots
of failure that might occur for the late
detection after impact of the alert logs.
It is a badge processing system for
most of the application and system.
So after code there might be
possible that some error occurred
and the L alert and logs.
Has been triggered after impact
due to the batch running.
So in that case, the failure occurs, but
we have a late detection that will cause
thousands, billions of dollar impact, as
well as the money impact to the business
organization and the business users
suffers a lot for that particular impact.
So these are the few reasons
why traditional CICD breaks.
So these schemes as a background,
why we'll implement the predictive
CI DevOps using CICD automation ai.
So that is the background
of why we'll implement this.
Now I'm going to the next slide.
The slide is all about what
predictive DevOps means.
Predictive developments like if a
intelligent flow or in inte system,
which collect the data from different
system, which has different degree of
data, normalize it, then temperature
it and normalize properly, and
then harmonize it cleans the data.
To make available to the
predictive layer model.
In the layer model, they apply AI logic.
Then they, or they apply the machine
learning algorithm on top of that.
Then a process data pipeline
to different kind of gates.
This predictive DevOps is not
only intelligent flow, but it's
actually in intelligence system or
application where risk's prediction
before execution happened after
that EIE assisted system took.
Picture based on the TBS system data.
Previous step data, feedback driven
automation then took place after the i
tion or AI logic applied to the model,
and then after the model generate the
accurate actual result, the feedback
driven automation has happened.
To provide that data to propagate,
reroute the data and different kind.
And then if there is a difference
between the data or actual result and the
forecasted result or predicted result,
then the deviation, which is the error
co patient, is Ted to the predictive
layer again, in the Model yourself two.
Run, learn that model so that after
running the model, similar wave,
multiple loop, the model minimize the
air coefficient and the difference
between the actual and the forecasted
or predictive result became very less
difference and it's very accurate.
So that is how the
predictive DevOps works.
Now I'm going to.
The high level system overview, if you
see the system overview, the signal
after from the signal system flow goes
to signal model decision actions, okay?
Where the signal means it's collect,
as I told already, different kind
of temperature data, different
kind of non harmonized, different
kind of non normalized data
from different source system.
So sort system, like you can say,
log file metrics, test data, PR and
intra health, which are required to
monitor the system, which are required
to monitor the deployment production.
Testing and other SIT testing
system, all these things as provided
as a input data to the model.
So in the model before implementing
the model and before implementing apply
the logic and the algorithms, machine
landlords to those models, the data
is need to be clean and harmonized,
and the data need to be normalized in
the proper way so that we can have.
Apply proper machine learning
language to that particular data.
So one of the, kind of the scenarios
like the calibration calibrate
the data and then the calibrated
the data to get the actual result.
Then after applying the model
and we get that decision.
After the power output has generated,
we got the decision and then it flow
to the pipeline to process further.
And as I told earlier, what is the
deviation and air coefficient that has
been routed to the model itself for
continuous learning and improve the
model to get the proper act forecasted
and predicted data, which should be.
It's very similar and very nearly to
the data value of the actual data.
Okay?
The core principle is the system
improves continuously through a closed
loop learning cycle where outcomes
can became more accurate and actually
visible to the business system
based on the intelligence driving
decision and decisions made by the.
Logic applied to the model.
The next one is the CIC data source.
As I told you, that is a different kind
of data, which is, that is available
as a input for that particular,
in this particular scenario, like
build logs, test result, pipeline
metrics, pr, metadata level.
So all these things
represent as a data, okay?
The data.
I can say one thing here that
technology must serve acuity and
inclusion, not efficient alone.
So that is why we, I want to tell that
all the system with different kind of
data of different kind of, normalization
and things we need to harmonize properly
to get the data in a equal me shape
or equal manner to serve as equity.
So that is how the CRCD data source occur,
and serve as a proper in input level data.
Now I'm moving to the next one, which
is the ingestion and telemetry layer.
So in the telemetry layer,
what is the purpose of the
ingestion of the telemetry layer?
Anybody can ask.
So the purpose of the initial
layer is that it act as the data
foundation of predictive data of
continuously, I think the data from
the input parameters and prepare
the real diamond historical signals
from CICD system and infrastructure.
So it'll collect, as you see in
the last log that all the data
has been collected from different
log files, different data sources.
For the CICD pipeline, all the
data has been act as a, the real
time and historical signal from
CICD system and infrastructure.
So there are different kind
of core capabilities for that.
One is agent and collector.
Agent, which kept, as I told earlier,
kept a log matrix events associated
with different kind of application
and different kind of system, which
are going to deploy in the CIC tool,
deployment and running environment.
In incorporated in the system, different
kind of streaming and batch ingestion,
which supports both real-time pipelines
and batch uploads, normalization.
And transform heterogeneous data
into undefined model ready format.
So if you see the right hand side,
I have provided all the data.
Have provided all the step by step for the
ingestion and tele layer where it comes.
If you see the in the emission pipeline.
After ingestion pipeline, after
getting the data agent collect the
data from different log system tric and
events, it is pushed to the ingestion
pipeline, which streaming the data.
Batch processing and
normalization enhancement.
So this is normalization, enrichment
schema, alignment and context tagging.
All the normalization and
enrichment done based on the
data after ingestion pipeline.
Then model ready telemetry layer
comes in picture, which take the
the unified and trusted data.
So this is the best pillar by
which we can assure that the
data prediction will be accurate.
With the reliable,
undefined, unified telemetry.
Now I am moving to the next slide,
which is feature engineering.
So feature engineering also is a step
of that DevOps, predictive DevOps
and ai, C-D-C-I-C implementation,
which purpose is mainly to.
Change this signal, trend,
windows, and an baseline.
There are other purposes also,
but these three are normally,
more impactable to the system.
So there is other core capabilities, which
includes agents and collectors, streaming,
band, batch, anomaly, waistlines.
So these are all the steps and all
the objects and prostitutes of the.
Feature engineering.
Feature engineering plays a ATE role.
You know how to minimize the risk,
to minimize the signal data by
changing the signal it code call by.
There is set process, which is
like code complexity, dependency
analysis, component nature.
So this kind of process helps to
get those restricted result and.
To accurately measure the
risk and the other parameter
to proceed to the next step.
So this is a very vital step of
our imple, of our implementation.
So the next one is, as I already
told, that AI analysis transform the
raw CIC data into predictive feature.
So in this portion, AI analysis,
it took say vital role.
In that particular implementation?
No, I am providing the model
later Model layer is the purpose
of the forecasting layer.
In the model layer.
It'll where, as I told, we have to apply,
we'll apply the model we'll apply the
machine learning algorithm, train the
data based on the historical data or.
Similarly data here I can, I have
given an example of time series,
forecast model, and other data
predicted pipeline outcomes.
And the prioritize.
Prioritize the, prioritize the
al layer gate and al layer.
These are the all the
steps for the model layer.
In model.
Basically summarize what we will
do based on the historical data we
upload different kind of algorithm,
different kind of AI logic on top of
that to get the predicted data for the
particular application or deployment.
So that is all about that.
Now I'm moving to the
next slide, which is.
Which is about model layer anomaly.
An limitation means the anomaly
layer, continuously monitor, CICD, and
runtime signals to identify abnormal
patterns are the enabling to active
intervention before propagate failure.
So this is all about the out outline
and abnormal data, which are not
in different kind of pattern.
So we use different kind of log pattern
detection, so some kind of outline.
Outline.
You can see in every
data, in every system.
But what we can do using different
kind of logic, different kind of
tactic and technique and tactics.
We will outline those abnormal patterns
and those data, which may cause
error and may lead to the failure.
So that is all about the
process of anomaly detection.
In the right hand side, I have
provided all the details slips
of the anomaly detection, which
is a baseline behavior model.
Anomaly detection engine, early warning
signals and vision and response layer.
All the particular each and every step
are also subclassified into different
processes like baseline behavior model
have two main processes, which is normal
log patterns and expected metrics range.
So animal detection surfaces weak
signals before they became failures.
Now I am moving to the next slide,
which is the risk scoring engine.
Purpose of the risk scoring engine is
it acts as a engine of the predictive
device by synthesizing the output.
What it do from the different model,
it produce a signal context, a this
signal for each pipeline execution.
And there are some different kind of core
functionality of combined model output,
aggressive forecasting, anomaly score, and
historical signal into unified risk view.
And there is another one core
function like context dev scoring.
So these are all the different
tapes and different process which
use for the risk scoring engine
and inside the risk scoring engine.
So it used the, it, its
main activities like it.
If it is used for multiple signal to
trust, based on the logic in the different
kind of vision, to take the different kind
of decision and push those different kind
of multiple signal to different model.
And on top of that, we used to generate
the output data to get the actual output.
So why it matters, it eliminates
fragmented signal, enables
consistent explainable durations,
balance speed with safety.
So engine, this is one of the
most important steps and important
part of the predictive DevOps.
So it's, it is role of the vision engine.
So how did, does the particular in
Dday role in the predictive DevOps,
in a contextual manner, it insight
into clear actionable pipeline vision,
ensuring the right balance between
C speed, safety and reliability.
If you see the division engine, there is
different kind of policy, different kind
of risk threshold consists evolution by
which this maintain the different kind
of, and monitor the different kind of.
Metrics like speed,
safety, and reliability.
Okay, so there is different kind
of co responsibility associated
with the decision engine, which is
gate or hello pipeline execution.
Determine whether the pipeline
stage should proceed, pause, or be
blocked based on the risk threshold.
Okay?
There is different others
also recommended intelligent
escalation rules, white matters.
Okay?
So as I told you, if you see
the right hand side, there is
yellow pipeline gate pause.
All the, after going to the decision
engine and the PO applying the
rule, different kind of policies
and rule, different kind of
parameter, like this threshold, we
applied different kind of context.
We applied for the evolution process.
After that, the output data go to the
pipeline and different kind of gate
and different kind of CICD pipeline.
Action has been.
Taken place.
If it is successful, all the data
accurate, then it is deployed.
Otherwise, it is red outted
to the model to learn the
model and get the actual data.
So why it matters?
So it prevent risky deployments review.
So this is a very vital point.
It always used to prevent risky
deployments, reduce unnecessary failure
and details, and keep human in the
loop only when needed, otherwise not.
The reasoning in terms the risk
intelligence into control action.
So this here, nothing.
But if you see, I have tried to.
Describe the end-to-end predictive dev
of flow, purpose of the end-to-end flow
the end-to-end flow components like
coaching, trigger, signal collect, analyze
production, execution, and addition action
pipeline and outcome feed, landing loop.
So why it is used?
What is the purpose?
So it is used.
From code change to deployment, combining
data intelligence edition and automated
action, there are different kind of other
action on, so other parts it is used
the basic purpose, which it is used,
I have already mentioned in our slide.
So there is different kind of
outcomes, which is separate releases,
faster feedback, scalable DevOps
operation, predictive DevOps.
Connect intelligence, automation and
learning into one continuous system.
So in the right hand side, I
provided the detail step by step,
like CO could commit, pull request.
Then CICD, data and telemetry step
after that, the AI model forecasting and
anomalies, then the cooling and addition,
then gate islet, then action layer.
Then the deployment and
the runtime monitoring.
There is pipeline integration.
Also, how pipeline integration take
picture after the previous step.
There are different kind of key
integration characteristics, which
includes work within existing tool, like
there are different kind of tools, but.
In different scenario, we'll
apply different kind of tools.
This is purely based on the business
scenario and the business requirement.
No CICD replacement.
Existing pipeline and workflow
remain unchanged in that case.
Lightweight integration method
here, different kind of comes
in picture and play a vital
role in that particular process.
Operation advantages.
There are different kind of operation
advantages for that this step is there.
So among them, I have noted down few
steps, like these few advantages,
like faster rollout with minimum
risk, no returning of team,
immediate value without disruption.
So this is all about predictive
DevOps enhanced pipeline without
replacing existing CICD systems.
Predictive maintenance predict is health
cluster capacity, node failure prediction.
These are the all the
predictive maintenance state,
which I already provided.
So predictive maintenance
is better than cured.
If you see.
Using prediction.
If you predict that particular
system is going to down or
particular log file is not going
to come tomorrow, then it's better.
We can identify and fix that particular
problem before ahead of tomorrow
to get the accurate results so that
our business will not interrupt
and not delay, and will not stop.
So prevent outages, it'll, if we
do use this predictive feature,
then it'll prevent outages with
early maintenance before issue.
So this is the end to end.
I provided commit, predict,
act, deploy, and learn.
This is the continuous lin loop,
which I told like it's kindly the
enforcement lining kind of thing.
When there is a marginal
difference between the actual
forecasted and the predicted
data, what it does, it sends the.
Output again to the different
error coefficient again to
the model to tune that model.
And similarly it loop one by
one until it'll, the result is
very close to the actual result.
So that is all about the
continuous learning loop.
As you see, I put all the diagram, how
it works and order the component for
the predictive intelligence system.
This is predicting get
smarter with every cycle.
That's why what I was trying to tell,
like every cycle after we push the air
ion again to the model to learn and turn
the model, the gap between the actual
and forecast and predictive data getting
very less and are getting very closer.
There is some operational
benefits for that.
One of the, which is the reduced MPTR
stable pipelines and less firefighting.
So these are all the pillar of
a particular good system using
predictive type of platinum.
There are different kind of processes
and different kind of rules, logic.
Using which we can stable the pipelines
and get the faster recovery for the
system and application with lower,
oops noise, lower business impact.
This is, and we get the finally
operational excellence on, based on
the reliability and predictability to.
Business impact business.
Business impact is if we have some
predictive predictive DevOps on top
instead of the traditional DevOps
and deployment environment, we can
release the item and release the
production deployment faster, lower
the risk, higher the confidence.
Then the next one what I
put some kind of, you know.
Some kind of command, which
used for the CICD actions.
Everybody knows that.
So nothing to, go through that
for the sample purpose I just put.
So it is a key picture what we are
taking away from this particular.
Presentation and particular talk.
So the main idea is that predictive dev
representative shift from the relative
deliver to intelligent, proactive software
operation powered by EI and automation.
So it is far better than the
traditional system and application.
So there is, I always say that
prediction is better than a reaction,
which is the key tip for this
message and the AI augmented DevOps.
Not replaces it.
And automation must be this.
C. These are the some key features
and key takeaway we'll be taking
from this particular talk.
So all this thing I have learned
provided like learning system
outperforms static pipelines.
Continuous feedback, ensure the
system improves with every release.
Strategic insights.
This is all about the predictive.
All about that.
DevOps with ai, CICD implementation.
Thank you for watching
the particular session.
Thank you.
And thank you.
I would like to thank you to the
organizer for this wonderful opportunity.
Thank you
so much.