Hey guys, my name is Pradeep Gaddamedi.
I'm a site reliability engineer
at a startup called Radar.
So, every day brings new
challenges and victories.
And here I'll share my adventure
in deploying monitoring and logging
platforms in the cloud without breaking
the bank, as budget could be the
constraint for many startups and not
everyone can afford paid versions.
so with that, I'm gonna
go over my agenda today.
So, I just did my introduction,
and I'm gonna, next time I'm
gonna de discuss about, you know,
how to deploy the cost effective
monitoring and, logging solutions.
And then I'm gonna talk a
little bit about the automation.
And then, you know how I did set
up the S-L-A-S-L-O-S-L-I monitoring
dashboards, and I'm gonna discuss
my experience with incidents.
you know, in my organization
and then, about the toil and,
you know, time constraints and
challenges and how I manage them.
So, let's diri dive into it.
So the first thing, you know, and I
wanted to discuss is the software.
You know, open source software and
the infrastructure we choose for
monitoring and logging infrastructure,
or in fact, any other setup.
So, especially when your company or
the startup which you're working for
is a budget constraint, obviously
you want to choose, you're compelled
to choose the open source version.
So the main important, You know criteria
we need to keep in mind is always research
a lot before we actually choose this
software and also check mark all the
requirements which your organization
needed that and then then choose
the software Let me take an example.
So I did choose elastic search For
logging and I did set up elastic search
on virtual machines and everything
went fine You there was, there
were some problems I encountered.
So, I cannot send Slack alerts
from Elasticsearch because
only paid version, allows it.
So, since I was using open
source, I can't send Slack alerts.
So, I have to, you know,
use a workaround for that.
So, I wrote a Python script and then,
I used the kibana server log and
then you know filtered the alerts and
used a slack web hook and then you
know Sent it to the slack channel.
So it was kind of a Backdoor way.
So that's an example, but there could
be something more important for your
organization So make sure like you
check mark all those requirements
before choosing any open source,
you know, and that way like, Yeah.
And there is, and, and, and next,
like, choosing the right hardware.
So there is, there are certain
ways where you can save some money,
by choosing the correct hardware.
you have to identify the correct
platform to run your application in.
And, also the, you have to
compare the cost with different,
components available in the cloud.
I mean to say different infrastructure
available in the cloud and decide based
on the cost and, you know, You have to
weigh in advantages versus cost when
I did elastic setup I actually read
through their documentation and I found
like not all the instances require
the same amount of memory or CPU.
So some instances consume less, some
consume more, like master nodes doesn't
doesn't require a lot of, resources.
So I use the virtual machines which
are of less skew for master nodes,
whereas the data nodes, they are CPU
intensive because there are a lot of
data comes in there and then a lot of
indexing and searching happens there.
So I have chosen virtual
machines with high CPU.
So, you have to, look at, you had
to weigh in the, advantages and
disadvantages and, you know, which
costs you more and then choose
accordingly and try to save costs there.
That's all about, you know,
how do you, select software
and hardware, to save the cost.
So let's talk about the automation.
So, so far I've talked about logging
and I installed all of the monitoring
components I choose again for monitoring.
I have chosen open source.
Grafana, Prometheus, Mimir, InfluxDB.
So all those components, I installed
it on a Kubernetes cluster.
either it could be monitoring or logging
solutions, everything I use Terraform.
It's better to go with, you
know, Terraform or Ansible.
Ansible I use to configure
the Elastic instances.
So, actually creating, sometimes you
feel like, okay, creating infrastructure
manually, you know, It's very easy,
but you know in the long run, it's
not a good practice because you You
might you tend to forget the whole
process how to create or if something
happens it's going to take time And
the documentation could be tedious,
you know, there are a lot of things.
so it's better to go with Uh, I mean
any automation of any kind terraform
ansible or any other automation And for
my dashboards for my grafana dashboards
You I, I use CICD, and then I, I checked
in them, checked in the code in, Git
and then use CICD that way, like if
anybody messes with Grafana dashboards.
I can recreate them, by
running the CI CD pipeline.
And I used Helm Charts to
deploy, you know, monitoring
components into Kubernetes.
So all this, you know, using automation
at first could take some time, or, it
could seem, I mean, it could seem a little
bit hard in the beginning, but, in the
long run, they are really useful, and
That makes your system very resilient.
All right.
So, yeah on the same context
I would like to highlight like
in my elastic search cluster.
Let's say i'm running out of I
mean my Data nodes are growing.
There is a lot of logs coming in.
All I have to do is like adding some
entries new nodes in the terraform and
run it And that way it just creates
those data nodes in just few minutes.
So So automation makes things
really easy Let me discuss a
little bit about SLA, SLO, and SLI.
I know these are very, important
parameters in DevOps world.
Let me start with SLI.
SLI is basically, the metric that
measures how well a, service performs.
Based on that metrics, you know,
you basically set up SLOs and you
come to some you know, you also
set up SLAs with the customers.
So how do you basically
Go with setting up SLIs.
So, I mean I I did basically, Set up a
lot of SLIs, but what I recommend is, you
know, start with the basic level So if
you have VMs or if you have if you are
running some pipelines data pipelines,
you know So set up the basic alerts first
instead of going with the fancy dashboards
That way like you cover the basic
stuff, you know There are a lot of slis.
In fact, like you can set up availability
latency error rate throughput saturation
traffic you know, they all help you
decide on SLOs But when you're starting
up right, you know in a startup, I
think saturation is the important SLI
We should first focus on saturation
indicates how full a service is, you
know, it could be measured to various
resources resource metrics such as cpu cpu
load memory usage or network bandwidth,
you know saturation helps predict
and prevent potential You performance
degradation, degradations this way.
we make sure our system is well designed
to support the load before we consider
setting up other SLIs like error
rate, availability, or throughput.
All right.
So let's move on to, incidents, you know,
incidents, happens, there are basically,
in every, you know, in DevOps world.
And then There are two types of
incidents, there are some self
inflicted and some natural incidents.
The reason I call self inflicted
incidents is because, you
know, there could be some toil.
Toil is basically the repetitive manual
work that could be automated, you know.
And, you know, that could prevent an
incident, you know, occurrence of an
incident or setting up proper alerts for,
you know, those, the, I mean, setting
up proper alerts for the infrastructure
could prevent some incidents.
Let me take an example.
So I was really, I had time
constraints and I have a lot to do.
So I miss setting up the, Alerts
for disk on elastic and every time
the disk failed Slash temp disk.
I manually went in and you know
cleaned it I could have automated but
I have my own reasons for not doing
that Like I said, time constraint.
So one day, like an incident
happened and, you know, I had to
manually go and fix the stuff.
So, so this repetitive
task that's called toil.
So we should address toil.
So basically we could,
there are various ways.
Maybe we could create a separate
project, separate JIRA tickets and
work as a team to address toil.
and set up proper alerts to
prevent these self infected events.
And there are some natural, incidents
which, which actually occur.
So, when natural incidents occur,
proper, you know, root cause,
root cause analysis and proper
post mortems are really important.
And moreover, we should
play blameless game.
So, because blamelessness is
very important, to the success
of a team or organization.
So post mortem should be blameless.
And, for RCS, we generally follow a
five, why methods you could search
for five, number five, why, root
cause analysis in Atlassian JIRA,
or you could Google, you will, that
basically applies to any scenarios.
So basically you ask the same
question five times until you
get to the bottom of the problem.
So if the disc fails, you
say white field, and then.
Okay, the disk was not scaled and white
not scaled and there was no time white
but there was no time for the DevOps,
then it could be a you know planning
issue then You will get to the bottom of
the issue after you question five times
so you could follow such strategies To
you know improve rcs and push buttons.
Finally, let me discuss about toil
time constraints and challenges
So, workload, workload is, one
important aspect, in DevOps.
So you might, you might be already,
overburdened with a lot of, you know,
vast amount of work to get to be
accomplished in limited timeframe,
commit only to what you can realistically
handle and set clear expectations to
avoid the stress of overcommitting.
while it's not, always
possible not to overcommit.
And if in any urgent task, you know
requires you to implement a solution
with minimum functionality inform
management about the limitations of
the setup, this change this ensures
they do not, you know, perceive it
as a perfect and Resilient system.
So let me take an example So I have been
given like a week or two to set up like
complete logging and monitoring system So
I had to take a hard decision and set up
a system which was not resilient Which was
a single point of failure but You know, I
made it clear to the team and management,
like the system I'm going to design is,
you know, could fail back at any time.
So we were in an agreement, you know,
that way, like, if some surprises come, I
mean, when the system fails, there are no
surprises to the, you know, management.
So, also, you know, like proper tracking
proper tracking where jira, system
jira tickets or you know Whatever
the ticketing system you use, right?
that will help you track the issues that
will help your track track your work and
then Even that will showcase your work
that way like Management understands like
what you're working on and what is the
workload you could take more and that
actually helps you You know, organize
your work and reduce the stress level.
yeah, proper tracking and
documentation are also critical.
So you basically document whatever
you do and you basically transition
to other teammates that way, like you
don't get disturbed when you, while
you're on vacation, or, you know, some
of the important, You know, aspects you
should consider, in the DevOps world.
Alright, so these are some
of the, you know, learnings,
I, learned in this startup.
like I know I'm still learning.
We are all, we all are learning.
So, please let me know if
you guys have any questions.
please feel free to, send me
an email or please feel free
to connect me on LinkedIn.
Alright, thank you very
much for listening.
You guys have a good day.
Bye-bye.