Good morning.
Good afternoon.
Good evening, everyone.
This is Vinod Dupatturi.
I had more than 11 years of
experience in financial domain.
Currently, I'm working as a
senior software engineer in one
of the largest card based company.
Thank you for joining us today.
Today's topic is financial fraud.
We are at a pivotal moment in the
evolution of the financial sector in
a world where digital transactions
are omnipresent and the threat we
face are not only growing in number,
but also in a sophistication.
Today, I'm excited to share how
artificial intelligence is not just
enhancing our ability to combat the
fraud, but also revolutionizing it.
Let's discuss the elephant in the
room, financial fraud, which is a
massive issue, costing business and
consumers globally around like a 5.
4 trillion annually, which is a
significant drain on a global economy
that affects everyone from small
business to large institutions.
Is the financial fraud what it is?
country, it impact would rival the GDP
of a major economic power, showing both
the idiosity of the fraudsters and the
weakness in our traditional systems.
Talking about the traditional
systems, fall short in identifying
the fraud detection, but AI powered
systems are transforming the field
by achieving AI powered 97 percent
accuracy in the detection of the fraud.
These systems also reduce the false
positive by 63%, saving millions
in transactions and building trust,
which is an essential asset in the
financial sector, where trust drives
customer engagement and loyalty.
Behind the statistics are the real
people, businesses and economies.
False positive disrupt legitimate
transactions while undetected fraud
leads to financial loss and eroded trust.
This discussion highlights AI as a
necessity for the modern financial
security with a dual goal, reducing
economic losses and enhancing operational
trust and efficiency worldwide.
Let's discuss about the fraud
detection followed by Prevention
and finally implementation.
Let's jump into the fraud detection.
There are like multiple ways of
fraud detection such as supervised
learning, unsupervised learning
and deep learning neural networks.
First we will cover the
supervised learning.
What is the supervised learning?
Supervised learning is Key AI technology
for combating financial fraud.
Using labeled historic data to teach
models how to detect fraudulent patterns.
Picture an ever vigilant agent analyzing
over 100 million, millions of records
carefully, categorize the transactions.
These Training enables AI
to detect fraud with 99.
9 percent accuracy.
Supervised learning works in real
time, identifying fraud as it
happens and preventing fraudulent
transactions from completing.
This not only safeguards the assets, but
also boosts efficiency, allowing financial
institutions to handle high transaction
volumes securely and without any delays.
In essence, supervised learning
turns data into practice.
Powerful fraud detection tools.
It adapts and evolves with the new
data and emerging fraud tactics and
staying ahead in ever changing threats.
Now super, we are done with
the supervised learning.
Let's jump into the unsupervised learning.
What is unsupervised learning?
Unsupervised learning plays a
pivotal role in exposing hidden fraud
patterns, detecting emerging threats
without relying on the labelled data.
Unlike traditional systems, it identifies
irregularities in unclassified data
by uncovering new fraud elements.
tactics as they arise.
This ability enables early detection
of unknown threats with a 42 percent
improvement in the fraud identification
rate, which is a transformative
leap in the financial security.
By proactively addressing fraud,
unsupervised learning prevents significant
loss and strengthens customer trust in
financial systems, constantly evolving.
This technology learns from
everyday transactions and anomalies
staying ahead of increasingly
sophisticated fraud strategies.
Finally, deep Neural networks are the
advanced brain power enabling us to
analyze data on an unprecedented scale.
Each transaction becomes a detailed
data point, crossing through
multiple layers of analysis.
These networks analyze over 10, 000 data
points per transaction in a millisecond,
detecting patterns, anomalies that smaller
systems or similar systems can't detect.
might miss.
Beyond identifying known fraud patterns,
deep learning uncovers complex signals of
emerging threats, achieving 70 percent,
sorry, 76 percent reduction in the card.
present fraud.
This technology provided robust, scalable,
and real time fraud detection systems
that not only reacted to the fraud,
but also anticipate and prevent it.
Integrating deep learning
into fraud detection is a key.
Game changing leap solidifying our
position as the leaders in the financial
security and ensuring unmatched protection
for millions of users worldwide.
Real time fraud prevention system.
One, our real time fraud protection,
system Process an incredible 100k
transactions per second, delivering
unmatched speed and accuracy, which
is critical for the financial sector.
Transactions are analyzed under 50
milliseconds, faster than a blink,
ensuring smooth processing for
legitimate activities that, and instant
actions against potential threats.
This performance is powered by advanced
algorithms and high performance computing,
like comp, quantum computing despa
designed to handle continuous and high
volume traffic effortlessly the systems
operate 24 by 7 with constant monitoring
and instant alerts and providing the
round the clock protection and vigilance
by detection and responding to the
threats almost instantly we enable
customer trust reducing disruption
and significantly lowering the risk
of financial loss from the fraud
Till now we have covered detection.
Let's dive into the
fraud prevention methods.
Behavioral
biometrics and device fingerprints
combines the technology and human behavior
to create a robust shield against fraud.
Behavioral biometrics analyze a
unique pattern such as Typing rhythms,
mouse movements, and the scrolling
habits to continuously authenticate
users and reduce unauthorized access.
For example, unusual changing the
typing speed or patterns during the
transaction can signal the potential
fraud, enabling a quick action.
Device fingerprints add another layer
of the security by Explaining the device
details such as the operating system,
hardware, IP errors, and identifying the
suspicious and or unfamiliar devices.
Together, this technology
reduces the account overtake
attempt by 89 percent accuracy.
Seamlessly security that protects
without disrupting the user experience.
By understanding this behavior, this
device integrations, we deliver a
high security while maintaining a
personalized and smooth journey.
Synthetic identity detection.
What is a synthetic identity detection?
Synthetic identity detection or a
theft is a sophistication form of
fraud where Criminals combine fake
information to create a new identity,
making detection more challenging.
Our advanced learning algorithms, and
analyze data from multiple sources,
identifying inconsistency in the data
like social security number, credit card
history to detect the fake, identities.
With 94 percent success rate in
identifying synthetic fraud, Before
they you, they are used our system
protects financial institutions
and prevent broader economics and
harmful of personal information.
This approach has saved estimation of 3.
2 million billion dollars have
avoiding both the direct cost for
the fraud and lengthy investigation
and legal processes that follows.
By leveraging the data science and
mission learning, we are setting
a new standards in the fraud.
Prevention, staying ahead
of evolving threats.
We also prioritize ethical data
use and compliance with the global
regulations, ensuring the balance between
the security and the user privacy.
Last one.
NLP.
NLP stands for the Natural
Language Processing.
Natural Language Processing is a powerful
AI tool in combating phishing, which
is a common and deceptive cyber threat.
Phishing attacks mimics
legitimate communication to
steal sensitive information.
Our NLP system analyzes over
a million daily interactions.
to detect suspicious
patterns and contents.
NLP understands the language modulations
identifying the red flags like urgent
calls to action or unexpected requests for
personal information with high precision.
With a 98 percent success rate in
blocking phishing attempts, our technology
safeguard users identifying financial
institutions from sophisticated scams.
As phishing tactics evolve, so does
our NLP technologies and continuously
learning and adapting to them.
to detect new threats by integrating NLP.
We proactively anticipate and neutralize
phishing attacks, ensuring a trust
and security in our digital age.
Okay, so far we are done with
the detection and the prevention.
Let's dive into the implementation of it.
Implementing AI in the fraud
detection requires a comprehensive
approach, starting with the strict
regulatory compliance to ensure
the transparency and adherence to
the global financial regulations.
User experience remains a top priority
with AI systems designed to provide
robust security with maintaining
seamless and user friendly interactions.
Continuous learning is a center for our
strategy, enabling AI models to adapt
to the new threats, learn from the
real time data, staying ahead in ever
changing financial fraud landscape.
Cross functional interactions is a key.
innovations involved, collaboration
across IITs, ITs, security, business
units to ensure a unified innovation
approach to fraud preventions.
This holistic strategy combines
compliance, user focus, adaptability,
and the net teamwork to efficiency.
effectively leverage AI in
safeguarding financial systems.
Results and future outlook.
Our AI powered fraud detection systems
have delivered outstanding results with
a 91 percent customer satisfaction rate
reflecting trust in our security measures.
Fraud investigations have been cut by
73 percent showcasing the efficiency
and effectiveness of our AI Looking
ahead, we envision the future of
AI driven, adaptive, and customer
focused security that not only is
responsible for a fraud, but also
predicts and prevents it proactively.
As leaders in this journey, we are
shaping the future of financial
security with AI advancements.
Thank you.
Have a great day.