Hello, my name.
Hello, my name is Natalie Tapa,
and welcome to my talk on the
impact of Internet of Things
on supply chain cybersecurity.
Just to give you a background of
my topic, supply chain is Basically
the network of processes, people
and resources involved in producing
and delivering a product or service.
This involves the acquisition of raw
material, distribution and storage,
transportation, Until the item or
service gets to the final user.
So it's typically all the stages
involved in the value chain.
Whilst Internet of Things connects
physical devices with sensors, softwares,
and platforms to collect and exchange data
over the internet, enabling automation
and efficiency in various applications.
And cyber security is the practice of
Protecting this softwares, this system and
this platform from unauthorized access.
Cyber attack and damage the Internet
of Things and supply chain management,
the global supply chain management
empowered by the Internet of Things
is transforming with unprecedented
efficiency and connectivity.
So over the years, supply chain operation
globally have seen massive improvement
in productivity, courtesy the use of
Internet of Things and It's a very
real operation and stages according
to statistics that, 2021 internet of
things market is projected to reach 1.
1 trillion by 2026 with a cut of 24.
7 percent from 2021 connected devices.
12.
3 billion in 2020 is expected to
exceed 30 billion by this year 2025.
Smart homes.
Over 70 million smart home by this
year 2025 boost, boosting demand
of Internet of Things devices.
Industrial Internet of Things is
expected to generate 15 trillion in
value by 2030, enhancing efficiency.
And in healthcare, Internet of Things
connected medical devices is expected
Billion dollars in 2021
to 182 billion by 2027.
The role of internet of
things in supply chain.
So Internet of Things connect produces
distributors and customers globally.
This also.
Enhance efficiency and
visibility in it operations.
How does the internet of things
transform supply chain management?
We could talk about efficiency,
which, real time tracking of shipping
companies, we've seen most shipping
companies, with RFID and GPS.
some companies have like barcodes
or pallets to track or consignment
at any given point in time.
We have automated inventory management
also in warehouse where shelves have
sensors that when an item is taken off
a particular shelves, it records the
type, the color and the quantity of
this item taken off, which actually
informed the decision on the item.
What needed to be stocked and
when example as could be made of e
commerce companies like Amazon that
uses robots in stocking its shelves.
We have pharmaceutical companies
using thermometer that record specific
temperature and it's Storage space
and also coaching companies, and
this goes a long way to improve
decision making and quality.
We have predicting maintenance for
machineries where machines have sensors.
example could be the automotive industry
where the sensors informed when That
machine needs a maintenance or an update.
we have been connected things, you
know, by With the help of Internet
of Things collecting all this data,
informed decision making by industry
players, and also help in predictive
analysis to mitigate risk and disruption.
So according to Morgan Stanley, Automation
World Industrial Survey, AlphaWise,
some companies share their benefits
from Internet of things in the supply
chain operations, there was an improving
operational efficiency, which A seed, 45%.
There was an improving productivity
by over 30%, creating new
businesses opportunity by nearly
30%, producing downtime by 27%,
maximizing asset utilization by 26%.
Ability to sell product as serviced by.
18 percent reducing assets life cycle
cost by 18 percent enhancing worker
safety by 15 percent enhancing product
innovation process by 13 percent and
better understanding of customer demands
by about 8% So this basically shows
how Internet of Things impacted these
various companies, these various sectors.
there are also some dark side of
Internet of Things and supply chain.
And that is what we're here to talk about.
And so some of them could be,
key vulnerabilities like lack of
standardization in the Internet of
Things devices, expanding attack
surface with billions of devices
and sensitive data exposure.
For example, the solar
wind bridge in 2020.
So what happened in 2020 is that around
Late 2020, there was a backdoor ingestion
into updates, which affected thousands
of customers, including governmental
agencies and Fortune 500 companies.
We could also talk about the data
on over 3, 000 airbus suppliers,
and this is a giant thing.
aircraft manufacturing, industry,
their data, the data of Over 3, 000 of
their suppliers was linked or attacked.
There is also an example of
MirableNet attack on crebs,
cameras, and routers in 2016.
So how do we balance innovation
and risk in connected work?
In a connected world, balancing
innovation with risk requires
integrating robust security into
every layer of Internet of Things and
supply chain operation by prioritizing
resilience alongside technology.
process.
So it is encouraged that as much as
companies are investing in innovation,
there should be a thought to invest
in security measures to protect
or safeguard these innovations.
Some of the strategies to protect Supply
chain operation from cyber attack include
the adoptation of net zero architecture,
where it should be assumed that every
device or network may be compromised.
Hence, there is a need to
implement strict access control.
Also, enhance endpoint security
by encrypting Internet of Things
devices and ensure regular update.
There is also a need to collaborate
with vendors for security design.
So as much as, I mean, there is,
investment towards robot software to
use or what platform, there should be
a collaborate, a collaboration between
this, other companies that develop
secure, platforms or software to protect.
the supply chain system.
Other strategies include improve
visibility where the use of
artificial intelligence to determine
anomalies and also implement
blockchain to secure records.
It's also advisable to create Share
to create share security standard
and join intelligent platform.
So this is basically collaboration
among industry players.
You know, to share information, to
know the latest happening, where
the latest attack is happening, and
what needed to be done, or what is
the latest safeguarding measures
that everybody needed, to know of.
Future outlook.
So we can talk about autonomous vehicle
and self healing logistics network.
Predictive risk management with artificial
intelligence and Internet of Things.
Collaborative framework
for cyber security.
So, There is also a call to action where
Internet of Things, as much as it offers
massive opportunity, as much as it is
helping to improve productivity and
efficiency, it is also requiring reports
of security, prioritizing cyber security.
Alongside investment that have been made
towards innovation and also collaborating
with government agencies, industry
players and tech leaders, basically
all stakeholders involved in this
cyber attack or safeguarding, Internet
of Things and supply chain operation.
Thank you.