Speaker 51: Hi, my name's Gian
Wild and I'm here to speak about
how security and accessibility can
be friends at Comp 42 DevOps 2026.
I'm coming to you from Australia, and
firstly, I would like to acknowledge
the Gro people as the traditional owners
of this land who still have a strong
attachment to the land I'm currently on.
This presentation can be accessed
at the accessibility OZ conferences
page, which is at www do accessibility
oz.com/about/conferences.
If you go to the accessibility
OZ website, you can see the about
section at the top here, select
about, and then select conferences.
You can see that I have an upcoming
conference, which is Comp 42 DevOps.
That will be moved to under
past conferences and events,
and you can access all the
information that I talk about here.
This is a photo of our team at
CSUN in 2018, which is, wow, eight
years ago now, which is kind of
terrifying if you think about it.
This is about two thirds of my team,
and one of the things that I wanted
to do when I started accessibility
Oz is I wanted support people by
employing people with disabilities, as
well as of course, making accessible
websites and doing accessible testing.
So.
Over the last 15 years, almost 15
years that we've been operating, we've
never had under less than 60% of our
staff having some kind of significant
disability that affects their daily life.
And if you have a look at us, we
all look quote unquote normal.
And that's important to realize
that people with disabilities
are often hidden in plain sight.
You won't know if
someone has a disability.
Please don't ask.
It's very rude.
Now, over the, as I said, almost 15
years that we've been operating, we've
had staff with dyslexia, moderate
vision impairment, severe vision
impairment, epilepsy, migraines.
Physical impairment, fibromyalgia,
multiple sclerosis, Crohn's
disease, post-traumatic stress
disorder, autism, and long COVID.
I myself have long COVID, which
uh, has definitely put a pin in
my traveling to conferences, but I
still try and participate as I can.
Another thing to realize is that it's
not just about vision impairments.
A lot of people, especially if they're
new to accessibility, talk only
about screen reader accessibility.
That's, uh, absolutely
important and essential.
But the largest group of people with
disabilities who use the web are actually
people with cognitive disabilities.
So it's really important to involve
all people with disabilities.
When you're talking about accessibility.
So a little bit about me.
Why should you believe
anything I have to say?
Well, I started in 1998.
I like to say, I know if you've
seen a presentation from me before,
you'll have heard this joke a
number of times, but I like to say
I started when I was five years old,
but that's not actually the case.
I worked on the first accessible
website in Australia, and I
created Australia's first automated
accessibility testing tool.
I spent six years as an invited expert
to the W three C WCA two working group,
working on the web content accessibility
guidelines, version two, I worked
on the Melbourne 2006 Commonwealth
Games and every Commonwealth Games
since then, and I spent five years
managing usability and accessibility
services at Monash University.
I left Monash University in 2011 and I
founded Accessibility Oz. We were released
the products, Aus Player and Azat.
I spoke at the United Nations
on web accessibility in 2015.
I was inducted into the Australia's
Hall of Fame as accessibility
person of the year in 2019, and I
am currently the chair of the mobile
Accessibility Testing Guidelines.
So let's get into it.
Let's talk about security.
So I wanna start with an anecdote.
In 2018, Angus Taylor, who's an
Australian politician, produced A PDF,
which said that the city of Sydney's
annual travel budget was $15 million.
So who cares if the annual travel budget
for a city council is $15 million?
Angus Taylor had been criticizing
the Lord Mayor of Sydney over
emissions based on this PDF, and so
supposedly the City of Sydney's annual
report, which was available on their
website, said that the city of Sydney
spent over $15 million worth of.
Travel when if you looked at the actual
original PDF, it was only $6,000.
So council proved that the annual report
on the website firstly had never changed,
had always said that they'd only spent
$6,000 on international travel, and that
Angus Taylor had produced a adopted PDF.
So why is this important?
This is important because a
lot of people think that the
reason to use A PDF is security.
You need to use A PDF because
no one can change it and
therefore it's a secure format.
But that's really not the case.
Uh, if you look at this
particular example.
It's very easy to alter A PDF,
and it's something that I'm sure
a lot of us have already done.
So in our disability discrimination
advisory notes, which is an Australian
document, they specified that some
file formats provide mechanisms
for enhancing the security of
documents by preventing unauthorized
editing, copying, or printing.
Some of these mechanisms are not
compatible with accessibility for
people with this disability and document
authors should ensure that security
features do not prevent access to
the document by assistive technology.
So this is basically turning the
security feature on and off with PDS.
This is not an issue anymore, but it is
something that has been talked about.
If there are concerns about ensuring
the authenticity of material published
on the web in multiple formats,
then a statement should be included
that specifies which format is to be
regarded as definitive or authorized,
and noting that additional formats
are being provided to maximize access.
But if we think about it,
what's more secure than a PDF?
Of course, I know none of you can
answer me, but what's more secure than
a PDF an HTML webpage on your website?
I can tell you right now that I can
doctor A PDF that you give me, but
I cannot hack into your website and
change the data that's on your website.
So the City of Sydney could prove
that that PDF was dock because
they had uploaded one document
and one document only to the CMS.
And they could prove through the CMS
details that that document hadn't changed.
So once again, something that you might
think you need to use because of security
provision is not actually the case.
Now you know that PDFs are
not a way to provide secure
information and H TM L website is.
Let's talk about capture.
I know a lot of security consultants
and the argument I always have
with them is about capture.
So capture is basically a way to
make sure that bots don't fill out
your forms and submit them with,
you know, random information.
Now, when it comes to WIC a, the web
content accessibility guidelines,
there is a specific requirement.
Regarding capture under 1.1 0.1
non-text content, and it says all
non-text content that is presented to
the user has a text alternative that
serves the equivalent purpose except
for the situations listed below.
And one of those
situations is the capture.
If the purpose of non-text content is to
confirm that content is being accessed
by a person rather than a computer.
Then text alternatives that identify
and describe the purpose of the
non-text content I provided.
And alternative forms of capture using
output modes for different types of
sensory perception are provided to
accommodate different disabilities.
But despite what the W three says or
because of it, which we'll see in a
moment, every capture is inaccessible.
Every capture, yes.
Google's one.
Yes.
Even Google's one.
Especially Google's one.
And the reason why is because
the recapture that Google
has created only pops up.
If it thinks you're a bot.
Guess what always comes across as a bot?
A screen reader, reader, so it will
always be triggered when a screen
reader user comes along and the
Google's recapture does not have an
audio recapture, or the audio recapture
is so bad, it is inaccessible.
So I have a number of friends
who cannot use the Google.
And funnily enough, despite what
success Criterion 1.1 0.1 says,
the W three C agrees, and this is
from their document about captures,
and I will tell you what it says.
Captures are a controversial topic in the
accessibility community, as is described
in the paper Inaccessibility of capture.
Captures intrinsically push the edges
of human abilities in an attempt
to defeat automated processes.
Every type of capture will be unsolvable
by users with certain disabilities.
However they're widely used and the
web content accessibility guidelines,
working group believes that if
captures were forbidden outright,
websites would choose not to conform
to a CAG rather than abandon capture.
So basically they're saying, Hey, we allow
you to have capture 'cause we really want
you to follow a cag, even though we all
know that it's not an accessible feature.
Websites abandoning WIC A would
create barriers for a great many
more users with disabilities.
For this reason, the working group has
chosen to structure the requirement
about capture in a way that meets the
needs of most people with disabilities,
yet is also considered adoptable
by sites requiring two different
forms of capture on a given site.
Ensures that most people with disabilities
will find a form they can use.
Some users with disabilities will
still not be able to access sites
that meet the minimum requirements.
The working group provides
recommendations for additional steps.
Organizations motivated to conform to
WA should be aware of the importance
of this topic and should go as far
beyond the minimum requirements
of the guidelines as possible.
Also, if you think about it, an audio
capture, which is where you press a little
button and it says, J. Q, capital C is.
Also inherently inaccessible.
So firstly, most bots can
interpret speech, so the audio
is often quite distorted and
therefore quite inaccessible.
And also audio captures are one and done.
It's very transient.
You hear it once and it's done.
Whereas a visual capture is persistent,
it's always there and you can look at it,
whereas audio capture, you hear it once.
And it's gone.
Therefore, it's gonna be inaccessible to
users who have memory problems or people
who don't have memory problems and just
can't remember a string of six letters.
Uh, and then the message turn on, the
audio capture may not be accessible.
The next thing to talk about
is accessible authentication.
Now, this was included in Wcad
2.2, which was released in October,
2023, and they're going even further
and they're saying basically.
Captures are inaccessible again.
So the requirement, this is
at aa, so this is something
that everyone needs to follow.
The requirement is 3.3 0.8 accessible
authentication, minimum standard.
A cognitive function test such as
remembering a password or solving
a puzzle is not required for any
step in an authentication process.
Unless that step provides at least one of
the following, an alternative, so another
authentication method that does not rely
on a cognitive function test mechanism.
A mechanism is available to
assist the user in completing
the cognitive function test.
Object recognition.
The cognitive function test is
to recognize objects and go,
Hey, that, that's recapture.
That's great.
And I have something to
say about that in a moment.
And personal content.
The cognitive function test is
to identify non-text content the
user provided to the website.
So the user uploaded a photo
and you show them six photos.
They have to choose the
one that they've uploaded.
And they say within this requirement,
if a capture is used as a part of
an authentication process, there
must be a method that does not
include a cognitive function test
unless it meets the exception.
If the test is based on something
the website has set, such as
remembering or transcribing a
word or recognizing a picture.
The website provided that would
be a cognitive function test.
Recognizing objects, or a picture
that the user has provided
is a cognitive function test.
However, it is accepted at the AA
level an object in this context,
which is allowed an object.
In this context means the general
English definition, a material thing
that can be seen and touched and
can include vehicles and animals.
If the test goes beyond recognition,
EG multiply the number of
cats by the number of dogs.
That does not meet the exception,
but it does go further.
Says some forms of object rec
recognition may require an
understanding of a particular culture.
For example, taxis can appear
differently in different locales.
Therefore this is an issue for
many people, including people with
disabilities, but it is not considered
an accessibility specific issue, which
is interesting 'cause it's basically
saying, Hey, we know people aren't gonna
be able to use it, but you can use it.
You know, we'll allow you.
So this requirement seems to specifically
allow Google Recapture, but if you
look back on that W three C capture
document, you'll see that they still
say it's completely inaccessible.
So really you have to avoid capture.
Don't use capture.
So everyone convinced captures bad.
Capture's bad, non capture's good.
So what do you do instead?
If you must have a capture, you
must provide more than two mo
modalities of capture for a given
action and make sure they work.
And so if you have an audio
capture, make sure it's something
that the user can repeat.
Put in an email and they'll send the
capture to you, that kind of stuff.
Or provide access to a human
customer service representative.
Notice I say human who can bypass
the capture or do not require
captures for authorized users.
Better alternatives are
multifactor authentication.
Human test questions.
IE Is fire hot or cold?
The person has to write hot
Is grass green or purple?
They have to be very basic questions.
Honeypot traps, which are
fields that must be left blank.
They're hidden from all users.
Make sure they're hidden from
screen reader users as well.
And if they're filled out,
then don't accept the form.
There's also things like service side,
spam filters, service side validation.
Other options include things like,
uh, confirmation page, screen
after the form submission that
says, here's your information.
Are you happy to submit this?
You know, timestamp your forms.
If the form is submitted
faster than humanly possible,
odds are it's a spam bot.
Uh, proof of work, JavaScript
code, heuristics of the
user, limited use accounts.
So there's a lot of different
ways, and that's only some of them.
If you need to convince someone
else without making them watch this
presentation, uh, have a look@tinyurl.com
slash A one one Y. Dash capture.
So that's tiny url.com/a1 y dash capture.
Okay, so let's talk about forms.
There's a bunch of different WCA
requirements that can be quite
complicated, uh, including 2.2 0.1.
Timing adjustable, 3.3 0.1.
Error identification, 3.3 0.3.
Error suggestion, 3.3 0.4.
Error prevention, legal financial
data, 3.3 0.7, redundant entry, and
3.3 0.8 accessible authentication
minimum, which we just talked about.
So I'm gonna go through and give you
some examples of these so you know, not
what to do or you know, what not to do.
First is 2.2 0.1.
Timing adjustable for each time
limit that is set by the content, at
least one of the following is true.
One turn off.
The user is allowed to turn off the
time limit before encountering it.
Two, adjust.
The user is allowed to
adjust the time limit before
encountering it over a wide range.
That is at least 10 times the
length of the default setting or.
Three, extend.
The user is warned before time expires
and given at least 20 seconds to extend
the time limit with a simple action.
For example, press the space bar
and the user is allowed to extend
the time limit at least 10 times.
Or for real time exception.
The time limit is a required
part of a real time event.
For example, an auction and no
alternative to the time limit is possible.
So this is an example here.
It's, um, an iPhone app and it's
about to, uh, time out and it
gives you a little popup and it
says, do you want one more minute?
Remind me in 15 minutes, Eric,
ignore the limit for today.
So it provides both options to
turn off or extend the time.
Here is another example, a popup
that says, are you still working?
And it's got a little timer starting
from one minute and it's counting down.
You are about to be logged out due to
inactivity, and there are two buttons.
Log out and keep working.
This is another example.
Wanna stay logged in.
You are about to be logged
out due to inactivity.
Uh, two buttons.
Sign out, stay logged in.
Time remaining before sign
off one minute and 28 seconds.
And there are two more exceptions,
which is the essential exception,
which is the time limit is essential.
And extending it would
invalidate the activity.
So, for example, think of a CPR test.
You can't give someone extra time,
you know, to save someone's life,
they have to do it within the, you
know, the first minute or et cetera.
Uh, that's an an example of an essential
timeout or a 20 hour exception.
The time limit is longer than 20 hours.
So the next requirement is
3.3 0.1 error identification.
If an input error is automatically
detected, the item that is in
error is identified and the error
is described to the user in text.
So this is an example here.
It looks like there's an error message,
but quite frankly it's not very helpful.
So you can see the card number there is.
Not a real card number.
The error message says, please enter
your payment information to continue
when the error message should really say,
you know, your card number should be 16
digits, or something along those lines.
That kind of error that we see there is
at least better than this error, which
is invalid product 8 9 3 B nine four
A 90 D 4 9 2 1 6 D 4 2 6 CD available.
You see how annoying that was.
That's what a screen reader would read,
and that's only, you know, the top three
lines of say, a 20 line error message.
So definitely provide better
error messages than that.
The next requirement is 3.3 0.3.
Error suggestion.
If an input error is automatically
detected and suggestions for
correction are known, then the
suggestions are provided to the
user unless it would jeopardize the
security or purpose of the content.
So note that it says if you can't
provide suggestions because it
would jeopardize the security of
the content, then you don't have to.
So WAC has thought about security.
This is an example here.
Please enter birth year
in four digits, EG 1974.
So it's the EG that is
the error suggestion.
And so people can see that their
birth year of 81 is not okay because
they have to put 19 before it.
Also, if it's a common mistake, then
you know, make that clear to the user
and tell them what they need to do.
Here it says Error, unknown error.
Check the detailed error
for more information.
I mean, that's not great, but here
it says, candidate has already
been invited to take the same test.
If you want to re-invite, cancel
the invite in your hacker rank for
work account first, so it tells
you exactly what you need to do.
So that's an error suggestion as well.
Then we have 3.3 0.4 error prevention,
legal, financial data for webpages that
cause legal commitments or financial
transactions for the user to occur
that modify or delete user controllable
data in data storage systems or
that submit user test responses, at
least one of the following is true.
One reversible.
So submissions are reversible.
Two checked data.
Entered by the user is checked for
input errors and the user is provided
an opportunity to correct them.
And three or three confirmed a
mechanism is available for reviewing,
confirming, and correcting information
before finalizing the submission.
So this is especially important.
If someone's going to delete something.
So having a popup or something along
the lines of this which says, are
you sure you wanna delete this post?
You know, cancel or delete.
Are you sure you want
to publish this post?
Um, et cetera.
Those are the kind of
things that you need to add.
Or a page which shows everything and
says, Hey, is this what you wanna submit?
So next we have redundant entry
information previously entered
by or provided to the user
that is required to be entered.
Again, in the same process is either
auto-populated or available for
the user to select except when.
Reentering the information is essential.
The information is required to ensure
the security of the content or previously
entered information is no longer valid.
So once again, this is something
that you can do, but if it's
gonna mess with your security too
much, you don't need to do it.
And so the kind of example here
is auto complete, having auto
complete for email password address.
Uh, that kind of stuff is gonna
make using your forms a whole
lot more accessible and shouldn't
mess with your security too much.
So thank you for coming today.
I hope this was helpful.
I hope this was useful.
Please feel free to have a look
at this presentation again at
accessibility oz.com/about/conferences.
And if you need any accessibility
help, we're happy to help you wherever
you are in the world, we have.
Clients everywhere in the world.
You can check us out on
accessibility oz.com or email
us at inquiries ENQ UI, RIES.
Or if you wanna spell it the American
way, you can, it's still get to
us inquiries@accessibilityoz.com.
Thank you very much for your time.