Speaker 7: Hello everyone.
Welcome to a Driven threat screening for
5G PF with automated risk mitigation.
Let me introduce I, nu
principal, SDT at Microsoft.
Most of the folks working in
telecom world or cloud native
infrastructure have this in mind.
How do you actually secure
UPF or 5G network at scale?
So we we look at this problem from
an AI point of view how we can
actually, solve or prevent the attacks.
To A-A-U-P-F in in any kind
of, 24 bar seven operations.
During the talk, if you disagree with me
in any of the topic, please feel free to
contact me at my email bin k26@gmail.com.
I'll be happy to answer
you your queries anytime.
And also, I have a disclaimer
here to make the presentation
slides information I share today
represent my own personal views.
I'm speaking of myself and not behalf
of my employer, Microsoft Corporation.
Okay, let us start.
As 5G Network adoption is in increasing
largely across the world and most of
the food 5G footprint is evolving.
Along with that there is an
unprecedented attack also security
threats in these networks as well.
So it's very important to look
at and secure the networks.
What are the pro what are the gaps today?
So you have, some of the protocol gaps.
The the protocol is complex.
There are some loopholes in
the, signaling and data plane.
So this can be exploited by the
attackers to get into the network.
And as 5G Network by and
large is virtualized.
It's a service based architecture.
And along with the adoption
of the cloud and Kubernetes.
There are there are other surface
areas that attackers can exploit.
Slice misconfigurations.
You actually look at some
of the slices configured.
There are been, there has been an
historical data suggests that some
of the misconfiguration can lead to.
Some of the exploitation by the users.
So they'll look into
these aspects as well.
So these are the main, couple of threats
that we high level we are identifying
and trying to solve the problem.
So let us understand
what is the user plane.
User plane function is
the heart of the network.
It carries massive
amount of data at scale.
And this basically the packet from
the user recommend is transferred to
the external networks through UPF.
UPF forms an essential part of
your service based network on any
mobile mobile service providers.
So let us look into air driven,
multi risk scoring framework.
So what it is, let's dive into that.
So how are we going to solve the problem?
So basically, traditionally you have this
signature based risk mitigation approach.
We are not looking at that
with ai coming into picture.
So you are actually looking at some of
the parameters like behavioral analysis,
geographic context temporal indicators.
Volumetric metrics and
historical intelligence.
These are the five, parameters that
historically AI can look into and
consider all these factors and data.
And, you can give a score to each of
the session and, make that session as
can be classified as a threat or not.
Let us look into the behavioral analysis.
Behavioral analysis is basically
when a session is user is, created
or session is created in the network.
Look at how the the session behaves,
like session duration what are the packet
sites sent through the system, et cetera.
Collect all these details and continuously
monitor, monitor the patterns how it
evolves and give you, give the session a
score high risk score medium, a low three
levels of risking scoring me mechanism.
You give it to each of the
session and then, predict.
This can be a potential threat the same
way, a geographical context historically,
from places where the threat has been
detected, and monitor or classify
any of the sessions originated from
those areas as high risk, sessions.
Temporal indicators like time built,
pa, time-based patterns, et cetera.
Activity, videos, all those things can
be considered and all metric metrics.
How long, how much data or how much usage.
And then there are, there
has been these ddo attacks
resource congestion, et cetera.
And also you bring in some of the
historical intelligence patterns to it.
Basically, past attacks, past nature,
and you have this entire database of.
All the past attacks that you can leverage
for the AI driven, monitoring system.
Lemme move into the next slide.
As I said the beyond signature based
detection from the traditional approach
we actually going into, going into a
driven approach wherein you actually feed
into the system with all the data that
we collect threat patterns, behavioral
context and then risk assessment detects
the, evasive ma massive techniques and,
multifactor correlation during the call.
Let us see how this happens in real time.
So in real time you actually collect
a form continuous loop, right?
Basically a data addition from the real
time traffic and telemetric collection.
You have the premises data, lot of
other, EDR or the CDRs from the call.
Calls, you just basically fit into
the system and analyze the patterns
evolving from those sessions.
Then you have a risk scoring
mechanism where, as I said, you
basically give the, scoring for
each of the sessions how risk it is.
If it is highly risk category, then you
put at higher risk score and then take
based on that, you classify the threats.
And you have response actions.
Not only you are just not monitoring the
system, but you actually have the response
actions automated through the, pipelines.
So you have the mitigation pipelines.
When the threat is classified and
threat you prevent those threats.
If it is identified, then we have
a human element attached to the
system where an analyst is trained.
And then given all the, knowledge, to
go and execute the response actions if
the session is classified as a threat.
And as this model is
continuously evolving.
You learn it, adapt it, and
continually, continuously learn
and, expand the the areas where
this attack surface has happened.
And coming to the pipeline, sorry,
pipelines that we have created it's a
tiered automated in a mitigation pipeline.
You have this the, four levels of
operations, like when you have this
enhanced monitoring, collect all the
datas from Promethease databases,
either E-D-R-C-D-S or whatever we
have, and monitor this and then,
apply the once threat is identified,
you apply the traffic shaping.
So you have these policies
all written as part of the
pipeline, as a response action.
Initially when the threat is, and when a
session is identified as a threat, you.
Basically apply some some of the initial
rules like traffic shaping qs adjusting
the QS for those malicious calls.
And then you, once you identify
the session, that's highly risk.
It can be potential threat, you
just isolate isolate the session.
And next stage is to
completely terminate it.
Yeah, so our AI system is basically,
enforcing the policy at large.
So you have all the rules return in
there and then also, these rules,
Al already rules are written that's
actually fed into the system.
And then even AI can, proactively
suggest the new rule is required
to enforce some of the policies.
So this is done at large scale and any
any threat mitigated through the system.
Let's look at some of the operational
benefits to the DevOps teams in this case
since we have all the pipelines in the,
in ready and automated response actions.
SRE teams or DevOps teams can highly
leverage from these pipelines.
So our first, as all
reduce the alert statics.
You have reduced alerts even
if the there is a alert before
feeding into the an analyst review.
Some of the automated action is
already performed when a threat
session is ed as a threat.
I'm not going deeper into this
because you already know there is a
faster insulin response due to this.
Benefits, one of the benefits and
operational consistency and continuous
improvement as well during this pipelines.
So what is the result of all these,
all of this actually once you have
this continuous monitoring system
and an AI agent sitting on in your
network, which continuously monitoring
and takes action whenever there is a
threat potential threat to the network.
And since it's rapid and adaptive
learning, you actually improve the
efficiency of the a the AI driven system
and and secure the network completely.
So we have all these systems all these
pipelines all these agents created.
Now how will we actually, integrated
this in the DevOps work workflow system?
The framework is in place.
Yeah, everything is in our compatible
with the kit GitHubs basically
containerized it and then know
place it in your environment.
Promethease metrics for automation.
It's an open source, and this
can be, used for the performance.
Tra tracking open Telemetry
is integrated into the system.
API first design, which is
basically a classic case for,
helping the CICD pipeline and
Kubernetes friendly deployments.
So this is another area which is
actually makes easy integration
to the DevOps workflows.
Getting started like how we want
to actually, put it in the system
how this works in in an environment
where already, it's running.
So we start slowly and gradually scale
into a, an, a full scale, full-fledged
automation execution or operation thing.
First establish a baseline where
you actually deeply observe.
Learn the system, learn the network.
And slowly, adapt to the situation
where, which is a good call, bad call.
So instead of, going and, suddenly
starting it, so we give it one or two
weeks or a month that can be tuned or that
can be fed to the system before in hand.
And then once you have the.
Baseline establishment, your
two, your policy definition based
on the know telemetry pipeline.
What are the data collected?
And have this analyst trained and ready
to e once you, he wants to intervene in
case there is a, there is an intervention
read then you actually in a scale to the
full system where you actually gradually
automate everything and fully hand it
over to the AA driven operation system.
So let us call this as a 5G of security
operations because it it it helps
to monitor the network at scale.
You don't have to worry about,
deploying different agents at one
different log geographical places.
You can have agents completely
monitoring your entire network
with different geographical places.
So this is very efficient.
Method of securing to network.
Since it's continuously feedback,
the system is fed into the system.
Basically the entire system is secure
when you have deployed it in your network.
So with that I'm closing this talk.
If you have any questions, please let
me know how this is being implemented.
I'm happy to answer these questions.
Thank you.
Thank you for, watching this
and let me know anything.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you for time.
Thanks.
Bye.