Hello everyone, my name is Anil Kheri
and today we are gonna talk about how
healthcare can be changed using Salesforce
Health Cloud and how we can revolutionize
healthcare delivery using the CRM Cloud.
So over the past few years, as we all
know, healthcare sector has been under
immense pressure to, to enhance patient
care while improving personal efficiency.
So this discussion is based on a
comprehensive study on multiple
clients who has delivered,
their, health, healthcare, using
health cloud, infrastructure.
so this is being conducted
between 2022 to 2024, across
multiple healthcare facilities.
So, you know, it examines how
the implementation of Salesforce
health cloud has transformed care.
So, let's talk about, let's start
with the challenges healthcare,
organizations face today.
So, these include fragmented patient
data, inefficiencies in care coordination,
delayed response time, and care
gaps that can lead to complication.
Additionally, healthcare systems
struggle with operational inefficiencies,
resource mismanagement, and
compliance with stringent regulations.
These challenges not only affect
patient outcomes, but also
burden healthcare providers with
rising cost and inefficiencies.
So our study analyzed Salesforce
health data cloud implemented across
diverse healthcare environments and
produced some remarkable results.
So if you see here, the patient case
satisfaction, scores has increased by 26.
4%, so which rose from 78
to 91 in the first year.
Facilities where Facilit, the Health Cloud
was used and also the care coordination,
which means the time spent on care
coordination was reduced by 75%, from
48 hours to, 12 hours, enabling faster
interventions and better outcomes.
And also based on response time, the
response times were reduced by 83%.
So that means the communication
between the provider's office
and the patients have reduced
significantly, when people were using.
So this, this also, you know, we can
also say that, people who are using
health cloud were also implementing AIs
in, in giving their responses or, you
know, in, providing claims, so that you
don't have to talk to an actual person,
for, for your, issues to be resolved.
So you can just probably chat with
an AI bot, when, you know, you have
certain queries with your, users.
with your provider.
So, and also, if you look at like,
there is a care gap, identification.
So in, in that also the times have
reduced, significantly, from, like there
is an increase in the gap, which, which,
which, which enabled healthcare providers
to take preventive actions and deliver
more holistic and personalized cares.
And also.
The key additional, performance
indicators, as I said, you, the
response time, has been increased,
has been decreased, and also the care
gap identification has been increased.
So what are the critical, success factors?
So, the critical, success factors,
here are comprehensive staff
training, phased deployment
approach, and cross, collaborations.
So the comprehensive So the
training programs, increased the
system and operation rates by 85%.
Within six months, ensuring teams could
fully utilize the platform capabilities.
And also, by rolling out the
system in stages, starting with
pilot programs, organizations
reduced disruptions by 75 percent
compared to the traditional methods.
And also the cross function collaboration
alignment between IT, clinical, and
administrative teams ensured that this.
that needs all of stakeholders,
were paved away for smoother
implementation and operation.
So by this, what happened with the
cross functional collaboration, what
happened was that people who were
using different systems were under one,
under one, one umbrella, which was the
healthcare, the health cloud platform.
so what happened in this is they
were able to easily communicate and
get answers from cross, cross teams.
so the dependency
So, this is the practical implementation
framework and also I want to
talk about, like how healthcare,
how, Salesforce played a critical
role, in, achieving these results.
So 360 degree patient view.
So by consolidating patient data
into a single view, providers were
able to deliver more personalized
care and proactive care management.
Automated alerts and reminders help
prevent care gaps, ensuring patients
stayed on track with their care plans,
and also streamline communication,
securing messaging between care team
members, improve coordination, enabling
Seamless communications and reducing
errors and also data driven insights.
So powerful analytic tools within
health cloud supported better
clinical decision making and enabled
providers to identify patterns and
trends and areas for improvement.
So the health cloud matrices, were
giving a lot of, insights, to the,
provider, from the patient's previous
So they don't have to go through like
each and every notes that they had.
But, you know, they were able to,
look in a confide report form or
a dashboard form and then get much
of the information from there.
So beyond improving, care, Health Cloud
delivered substantial operational and,
compliance, benefits, such as, you
know, automation, reducing redundancies
and improved, resource allocations,
leading to a 32 percent reduction in
operational overhead in the regulatory
compliance, built in security.
Features, HIPA compliant data management
and role based access controls
and regular compliance training.
Ensure patient data, were protected,
and adherence to regulations.
These features were critical in
building trust with patients and
safeguarding sensitive information.
So the call to action.
So, so if you see here, how, how
can, healthcare organizations.
Replicate this success, like
who are not using CRM is
assessing their current systems.
where, you know, start by evaluating
the existing workflows, identifying
inefficiencies and understanding the
needs of the organization and also to
engage stakeholders, stakeholders, which
include clinical administrative and it
teams early in the planning process to
ensure alignment and buy in and also
to develop a tailored, strategy, You
know, customizing, the health cloud
implementation to meet their unique needs.
and, the organization needs.
And also commit to the, continuous
improvement, regularly gather feedback,
and also, you know, analyze performance
metrics and refine, processes
to sustain, long term benefits.
So, I just want to, conclude saying
that Salesforce Health Cloud has
proven to be a game changer for
healthcare, you know, significantly.
improving patient outcomes,
enhancing operational efficiencies,
and streamlining compliance.
So by leveraging this CRM technology,
healthcare organizations can not only
meet today's challenges, but also
future proof their systems for tomorrow.
And, thank you, everybody.