Speaker 13: Hello everyone.
My name is Harris Peter Pacoin.
I'm from Google.
It's a pleasure to be with you
here today at Con 24 DevOps 2026.
I'm a staff SRE at Google, and I
have been with Google for 11 years.
Today I am excited to share about
a comprehensive case study titled
from Lift and Shift to Kubernetes,
A two phase DevOps Modernization.
This talk is not just about moving
workloads to the cloud, it's about
the strategic evolution of a mission
critical enterprise application.
And we will explore that.
We'll explore the technical hurdles,
the strategic decisions, the operational
outcomes of such a large transformation.
This transformation is for a legacy
ticket management system and will
transform this through this journey.
Into a high performance
cloud native service.
Every cloud migration is a journey with
many learnings, and whether you are
starting your journey now or you're in
knee deep in the trenches of Kubernetes,
I hope this blueprint serves as actionable
insights for your modernization efforts.
To understand a journey, we should
start at understanding the challenge.
The existing service was an on-prem
service running on VMware and had
been running for over two decades.
It was a large, monolithic application,
tightly coupled with many integrations.
This was one of our core business
function services that is used day in
and day out for more than a hundred
thousand tickets every single day.
When this tightly coupled
monolith application service
stops, the business stops.
The services was upgraded more than a
decade ago from on-prem physical machines
to VMware and for more than a decade
after that, it was not upgraded at all.
When this project started, it was running
on aging VMware infrastructure and had a
very large Oracle database at the backend.
Both the cache, the application
stacks were globally deployed
to reduce latency for users.
Over the years, the architecture
has devolved into complex web
of interdependencies, along with
growing number of customers and other
critical systems that depend on this.
The technical debt made even minor, risky
minor updates, risky and time consuming.
Every single operational
change was a bottleneck as the
transaction volume started growing.
The complex dependencies made everything
such as even a routine maintenance, as
such as patching, software upgrades, and
any releases, a challenging thing to do.
So our goal was very clear, transform
this monolith into a containerized
platform, minimizing disruptions, but
we needed a method which was methodical,
measured, and above all risk covers.
So we came up with this
two phase strategy.
To manage the risk, we decided
against a Big bang approach.
The two phases were phase one, which
was a lift and shift the lift and
shift to Google compute engine.
The object was very simple.
So move the existing architecture
from Google, from on-prem into
Google Compute Engine as is.
Why do we do this?
Because it allows us to exit the
VMware infrastructure more quickly,
and more importantly, it allows
us to establish a performance
baseline for the cloud environment.
We wanted to see how the app would
behave in a cloud infrastructure.
Before we added the complexities of
containers, we preserved the existing
architecture as much as possible.
The goal here wasn't innovation yet.
It was more about stability.
So by moving the VMs into cloud,
we could let go of the dependencies
of VMware and establish a baseline
performance for adding the
complexities of containers later on.
Phase two was more about the modernization
the cloud native transformation.
Once we were stable on gc, the
hard work of containerizing the
application moving into the GKE.
And then solving the data layer
problem, we could approach
this more as a phased approach.
It'll allow us to isolate the
variables that change and ensure
that if anything goes wrong, we could
easily pinpoint which layer of the
stack was responsible for the issues.
So let me delve a little
deeper into phase one.
Phase one was all about precision.
So we broke it down into four critical
steps, dependency, mapping, parallel
deployment, continuous application,
and almost zero cutover time In
dependency mapping, we didn't just look
at the code, we looked at the network.
We used the discovery tools
to map every integration point
and communication patterns.
You'd be surprised how many zombie
services or undocumented APA calls
exist in a. 10-year-old monolith.
We then use this data to chart out all
the dependencies and understand systems.
It depends on and systems
that dependent on it.
Secondly, we built the cloud
environment as a parallel environment
to the on-prem environment.
This wasn't just a
sandbox, it was a mirror.
This parallel deployment made
sure that the live service was
never disrupted or ever impacted.
Thirdly, continuous replication.
We used Oracle's native replication
technology to keep both the
cloud databases in sync with
the on-prem VMware environment.
This ensure that when we were ready
to move the data when we were ready to
cut over, the data was already there.
This was very necessary because
the database, as I mentioned,
was a very large database.
And finally about the cutover.
We use DNS and load balancer redirects
to make sure that the traffic was
moved over in a controlled manner.
Because the environments were
identical in architecture and the
stack, the data was kept in sync.
When we were ready to cut over,
we also had the option to fall
back very easily if we needed to.
And keeping the data in sync all the time.
Made sure that the cutover
is only a matter of minutes.
How we measured the success of phase one?
So as I mentioned, phase one was a
very critical step in our journey.
Once we were on GCE, we didn't just keep
the lights on, we measured everything.
We gathered comprehensive baseline
metrics on application latency.
System throughput, resource
utilization, and we know exactly
how the monolith performed on cloud.
These numbers gave us a
success criteria for phase two.
So we essentially set a bar for our
future cunet system that had to, and
that bar we wanted to either meet or
exceed through the transformation.
So our immediate win with phase
one was more about rapid resource
provisioning on cloud scaling,
improved performance on G cvms.
And given the dependency mapping
work that we had done in phase
one, we had a lot more efficient
maintenance operations after phase one.
Phase two was the
Kubernetes transformation.
With our baseline established
and stable, we entered phase two
where we got the opportunity to
do the cloud native redesign.
This was the modernization phase.
As I mentioned.
We wanted to make sure that the
service could serve the business
efficiently for many years to come.
And also, we wanted to take the
opportunity to use all the cloud best
practices and cloud SRE tools available.
In this phase, we transitioned
from VMware machines to cloud
VM machines to containers.
We moved the workload to Google, GK
and began the work of modernizing
our data layer, which is the
Oracle database into Postgres.
This phase allowed us to find the, unlock
the benefits of DevOps, like I mentioned,
rapid scaling, automated recovery.
Streamline, CACD pipeline,
improve security and many more.
And I'll talk about all of
these in the coming slides
on database migration.
This was perhaps I would say the most
hardest hurdle for us from moving
from Oracle to Cloud SQL PostgreSQL.
This was not a simple export
report, like we'd had to rewrite
a bunch of the Psql packages.
This was custom.
Manage complex time zone
conversions, character set,
missile element, handle data type.
And given the size of the data, this was
not a trivial challenge that required
a lot of careful planning and execution
which was many months in the making.
We utilized change data capture
to keep the databases in
sync during the transition.
It required a lot of cycles
of doing performance tuning.
And multiple rounds of load testing
to ensure Postgres could match
the high concurrency throughput of
the original Oracle environment.
And being on cloud, we could spin
up resources in a matter of minutes,
run a load test, and destroy them.
So using Terraform, we declared our
whole stack and that made cloning for
load testing environments a lot easier.
For monitoring and troubleshooting.
We used cloud native monitoring tooling,
which was a huge advantage here.
Next I'll talk a little bit
about security on Kubernetes.
Security is a zero trust game, so
we implemented fine grain network
policies to control port, to
port communications on premise.
We had to rely on a hard perimeter.
But in GK we controlled over 200
distinct communication parts.
So the dependency analysis we had done in
phase one helped us land this fine grain
network security boundary definition.
In phase two, we started from a less
restrictive network policy definition,
and as we monitored the traffic, we
made this more restricted with fine
grain protocol aware segmented traffics.
The cloud-based tooling
made this possible.
On GCP, we have fantastic network
traffic monitoring software allowing
us to map all the routes, gave us a
lot of deep insights and made traffic
monitoring possible and much, much easier.
Now let's talk about disaster recovery.
In our legacy environment, deer was a
large and manual and high anxiety process.
It involved periodic backups measuring
recovery times in hours and even days.
And we rarely tested a full scale
scenario because we were not confident
of getting to a recovery state.
When we moved in phase one, our
dear strategy matured because
we moved from manual backups to
automated persistent disc snapshots.
And we were able to
restore them and test them.
And this was a huge step forward
because we were able to document
everything and have automation to do
the spin up of new VMs, reattaching
disk, and reconfiguring networks.
Once we reached phase two with gk,
our entire DR philosophy change
because we moved from a model of
recovery to model of resilience.
So in GK, we implemented a
multi-region deployment strategy.
And we use gks Natives capabilities
for backup of GK, ensuring that our
container configuration secrets and
stateful data sets were all replicated
across geo geographic borders.
And then we had infrastructure code,
like I mentioned which helped us
rapidly build and deploy environments.
I want to emphasize the importance
of a full scale recovery exercise.
As part of our launch, we did a bunch of
what we call wheels of misfortune, where
we test out the recovery of the system
that allowed us to move from theoretical
models of recovery time objectives and
recovery point objectives, and document
them and testing them before co life.
Made sure that we had a well-documented
procedure that we could follow in
case we had a disaster recovery.
Scenario,
some of the lessons I'd like to share
what worked for us and what didn't work
for us and what we would do differently.
I think the sequencing of choosing
a two phase approach is something
that everyone asks us multiple times.
Is it really worth doing it?
But the biggest reason for
doing that is risk decoupling.
If you want to change your infrastructure,
which is moving to cloud, and you
want to change your runtime, which
is moving from VMs to containers, and
you want to change your data layer,
moving to Postgres or Cloud sql.
All at the same time.
It's a recipe for something
to go wrong, right?
And then when troubleshooting such
a service, it becomes very complex
because you are trying to figure out
where they should happen between a
network configuration, a resource
limit in a pod, a syntax cetera, or so
decoupling them and doing phase one as
a lift and shift helped us isolate the
cloud infrastructure variables first.
So in phase one, by moving to
cloud, we would then show that the
cloud infrastructure fundamentally
worked well for the service.
And as I mentioned, it allowed
us to measure the baseline, and
this was our insurance policy.
It allows us to prove to the
stakeholders that cloud was just as
stable as the VMware environment,
and also gave the project team a
breather to design the modernization.
And like I mentioned.
The modernization effort is a lot
more easier with cloud native tools.
And there are lots of these
tools for cloud networking.
Im models Kubernetes Manifest
Istio service meshes.
So decoupling is one of the key reasons
why we chose the two phase approach.
Let's talk about some of the
things that we would do differently
if we were to do this again.
One of the hardest thing I mentioned
was doing the data change, right?
The data migration from
Oracle to Postgres.
And if we were to do this differently,
maybe we would start the database schema
simplification work stream much sooner.
We spent a lot of time in phase two
fixing the Oracle specific things
that needed to change to Postgres.
Maybe if we had started this much
sooner, maybe even in phase one, and
let it land in phase two, that would've
been a lot better I would think.
Secondly, observability, we waited
until phase two to implement some of
the more advanced distributed tracing.
In hindsight, we should have
instrumented our monolith with tracing
before phase one having those traces
even in the lift and shift phase.
Would've helped us identify a lot of
these latency jitters much easier.
And on cloud there's a lot of
excellent tooling to help us do that
and that would've also benefited
operating the service after phase one.
Long story short, the key takeaway
here is your migration sequence
should be designed to build confidence
both in the system's performance and
your team's ability to manage it.
So don't be afraid to take the slower
phase route if it guarantees a success
arrival which has all the benefits that
you want to get out of the project.
So now I'll talk more about the SRE
parts of operating in a containerized
workload as we move to gk some of the
valuable lessons we learned of operating.
At scale.
Firstly, resource management.
In the VMware world, we were always
used to over provisioning because
we wanted to make sure there was
enough headroom for the service In
Kubernetes that's not a great recipe.
We wanted to use the best practices,
which involved learning to set requests
and limits based on our 95th percentile.
And the success metrics we gathered in
phase one helped us set those values
in a much more well-managed way.
Before we launched, we also were able
to implement gks Autopilot feature to
help us fine tune these over time and
grow as the businesses associates.
Secondly, the deployment strategies,
we moved away from maintenance windows.
So by using gks tested
slow rollout deployments.
We could spin up a new version
of the system new version of the
containers run through the tests
and then flip the traffic as they
move as they're being deployed.
If there was a new bug detected,
we will roll back and the load
balancer toggles away automatically.
Thirdly, observability in a monolith, we
usually had logs in multiple locations,
and it was always a challenge to go
fetch those logs and look at them and.
Correlate them with each other.
In Kubernetes.
Logs are all centralized on Google
Cloud logging these logs are all
aggregated and helps us process pers
and troubleshooting much faster.
Without these logs in a central area,
it's almost like a flying blind.
So the central logging through
GKE is really advantages.
And finally on state management.
So one of the most significant
mind shift mindset shifts we
had when moving from VMware to
Kubernetes is how we handle state.
So in our legacy VMware environment, we
had every server was essentially a pet.
We had a name, an IP address.
We had data tied to that machine and
then we had to manage that machine.
But with gk, everything is deployments.
So you have to manage the
state of those deployments.
They're both stateless
assets and stateful assets.
So clearly drawing the boundaries
around each of these asset groups and
managing them as states is the way to go.
And this will allow you to
scale horizontally and survive
failures a lot more easier.
The next thing I want to
talk about is security.
So security in a cloud native
environment is not a perimeter
you build your application around.
It's a series of layers.
So you'll build layers
and layers of security.
Like I mentioned in the legacy
VMware setup, it was all
about defining a boundary.
And if you're inside that network
boundary, you are trusted.
But if you're outside, you're not trusted.
In gk, that model is very obsolete.
There's a zero trust architecture and we
had to break it down by these pillars.
You have identity access.
So we moved away from long list
service accounts, which were
essentially latent credentials.
And we implemented G Clear's
workload entity, which allowed
us to have a service account that
access a Google IAM service account.
It also meant our pods get
short-lived, automatic rotated tokens.
This allowed us to have
the least principle, the
principle of least privilege.
And if a pod doesn't need to write
to a Google Cloud storage bucket,
essentially, like we wouldn't permit
that through the identity account.
Secondly the network controls, like I
mentioned, in phase one, we had these
broad firewall rules, but in phase two,
we implemented G K's network policy rules.
This allowed us to micro segment
at the individual port level.
We were able to map all the traffic
between the 200 different pods
and the communications that they
had, and we were able to define.
How these pods should interact
with each other very specifically.
And we also were able to implement
like the default deny policy such that
even if one pod is compromised, that's
the only border in which the attackers
trapped onto Thirdly, container security.
We shifted left, which means that
we were able to build all our.
Control container security well
ahead into the development cycle.
So we implemented image
scanning for vulnerabilities.
We were able to implement
binary authorization.
So these would prevent vulnerabilities
even before it hits the container registry
from where your images get deployed.
So even in the build cycle, we were
implement, we were able to implement
these controls so that the images
were, are tested before they reached.
Production.
Finally, data protection.
We shifted from manual certificate
management, automated MTLS, so
all data and transit and all data
at rest is increment encrypted
with the customer managed keys.
And those keys were all managed
by us in the GCP projects.
So some of the practical takeaways that
I'll mention as I wrap up, I want to
leave you with these four areas that
will make any modernization successful.
So start with the dependency mapping.
This is one of the most
underrated areas for SREs.
It's necessary to understand the
network flows, the application flows.
And discovering hardcoded ips later in
the migration is a recipe for disaster.
So understanding who all depend on the
system, which systems does this system
depend on, is really necessary measure.
So this is all the telemetry, all
the metrics, all the baselines
that you need to build SREs
have the three basic metrics.
Which are errors, throughput and latency.
So measuring that is a
great starting point.
Also, having a good set of baseline
metrics ensures that you don't run into
those conversations of someone feels like
the app is slower with the migration.
Having a baseline metrics helps you
to have more objective data-driven
conversations rather than subjective.
Feedback from customers and
like I mentioned, plan for
the database complexities.
Applications are easy to rewrite and
re-architecture data is a lot harder.
As we moved from our experience, it
took us a lot of time to do this part.
There are many cycles of
repeated performance testing.
And feasibility that needs to happen
to get to the point of completion.
So start early and if you end up
finishing sooner, you can always use
the time for more performance tuning.
And lastly, like I mentioned testing
your disaster recovery scenario.
I cannot stress this
enough, having a system.
That is only theoretically set
up for a disaster is a liability.
Like I mentioned at Google,
we periodically run wheels of
misfortune, disaster recovery
testing cycles, where we break things
on purpose in real environments.
And if we challenge our teams to go ahead
and try these disaster recovery scenarios
within the RTO test the playbooks,
and then write re retrospectives on.
What went wrong.
So testing your DR periodically is a
fantastic way to ensure that you have
high confidence in your DR strategy.
And like I mentioned, modeling,
modernizing any legacy
application service is a marathon.
It requires patience, a phase strategy,
and a relentless focus on automation.
By decoupling the migration from
transformation, we reached a goal of.
Minimal downtime and a service that
is ready for many decades to come.
Thank you so much for your time today.
I'm happy to answer any
questions if you have any.