Hello everyone, my name is Prashanth
and I'm working as a staff RTL design
engineer with 12 years of experience
in VLSI design and development.
Today I'm thrilled to present
revolutionizing HPC architecture
where we will explore how advancements
in interconnects, system on chip
integration, and energy efficient
designs are transforming high
performance computing systems.
Let's begin by examining the
HPC market's remarkable growth.
High performance computing leverages
multiple computers to perform complex
calculations and data analysis that exceed
the capabilities of a single machine.
It is widely applied across science,
engineering, businesses, and other fields.
The global HPC market is
projected to reach 55.
6 billion by 2026.
growing annually at 7.
5 percent rate due to increasing
demand from areas like AI, scientific
research, and big data analytics.
Modern HPC systems managing workloads
spanning over 100, 000 processing
cores have enabled breakthroughs
in fields such as climate
modeling, drug discovery, and AI.
and astrophysics.
In the era of artificial intelligence
with innovations like chat gpt hpc
systems are pivotal for training
neural networks by processing massive
data sets optimizing models and
significantly reducing training times.
These advancements support distributed
computing innovations driving the
development of larger and more
sophisticated AI architectures.
The rapid growth necessitates
new architectural innovations
to handle increasing, increasing
workloads effectively.
Scalable interconnects are essential
in ensuring high speed data transfer,
seamless parallel computing, reduced
latency, and efficient scalability,
empowering HPC systems to address complex
applications with unmatched efficiency.
Interconnects are the backbone of
HPC systems, enabling high speed
communication between components,
and their evolution has significantly
impacted real world applications
and problem solving capabilities.
Previous interconnects supported
speed up of up to 100 Gbps, which
while impressive, introduced
latency at the millisecond scale.
This was sufficient for many
traditional HPC applications like
basic weather simulations, genome
sequencing, or engineering simulations.
However, these speeds limited the
real time processing and scaling
required for emerging fields such as
AI training and big data analytics.
Early stage climate modeling could analyze
broader weather patterns, but struggled
to simulate localized events like
tornadoes or urban heat islands due to
data transfer and processing bottlenecks.
Today's interconnects deliver speed
of up to 400 Gbps with sub microsecond
latency, representing a four times
improvement in bandwidth and a drastic
reduction in communication delays.
This enables.
Faster, more accurate simulations
and support emerging technologies
like AI, real time big data analysis
and high fidelity simulations.
The large scale AI models
like GPT are trained faster
and with greater efficiency.
Real time updates and adjustments during
training are feasible, drastically
reducing model development times.
Training a model like Chad GPT,
which previously took weeks,
can now be completed in days.
This improves access to cutting
edge AI solutions in healthcare,
finance, and customer service.
These interconnects enable
population scale genomic analysis,
facilitating personalized medicine
by identifying genetic markers
and potential treatment faster.
Not just that, you would see advancements
even for material science and engineering.
The real time simulations
of materials under stress.
or in extreme conditions enable industries
like aerospace and automotive to design
safer, more efficient components.
Engineers can now simulate the
aerodynamics of an entire vehicle
in hours, instead of days, speeding
up the design and testing cycle.
This leap in interconnect technology
allows HPC systems to address
problems previously considered
computationally infeasible.
Revolutionizing fields from
AI to personalized medicine
and global climate solutions.
Such advances in interconnects are
crucial for scaling HPC performance, but
energy efficiency is equally important.
Let's delve into low power SoC designs.
Energy efficient SoC designs are
redefining HPC capabilities by balancing
performance and power consumption.
I have highlighted these as some of the
most important parameters in SoC design.
Power reduction.
Modern designs achieve up to 75
percent power savings compared
to traditional architectures.
For example, Cloud providers such
as AWS use custom SOCs like Graviton
processors, reducing energy costs
while maintaining high availability.
Performance density, delivering 2.
5 teraflops per millimeter square, a three
times improvement over discrete solutions.
NVIDIA's SOC based GPUs are used
in AI workloads, such as autonomous
driving, enabling real time
processing in compact modules.
Integration, CPUs, GPUs, and FPGAs
are now integrated on a single chip,
enhancing efficiency and functionality.
For instance, AMD's EPYC SOSes combine
processing and memory bandwidth, allowing
data centers to consolidate tasks and
reduce server footprint significantly.
These innovations enable HPC
systems to achieve high performance.
computational throughput without
excessive energy costs, paving the
way for advancements in AI, scientific
simulations and real time analytics.
Now let's look at how packaging
technologies support these achievements.
To overcome scaling limitations,
advanced packaging methods have
revolutionized chip integration.
3D stacking This increase increases
integration density by vertically
stacking chip components, reducing
interconnect distances, for example, HBM
high bandwidth memory used in NVIDIA GPUs
employ 3D stacking to deliver ultra fast
memory access for AI and HPC workloads.
Chiplet designs allow modular
assembly of components, improving
yield and enabling scalability.
AMD's Ryzen processors use chiplet
designs to combine multiple CPU cores
with high efficiency, significantly
enhancing multi core performance while
keeping manufacturing costs manageable.
Such packaging innovations are critical
for building the next generation of
HPC systems, enabling breakthroughs in
fields like climate modeling, genome
analysis, and large scale AI training.
HPC advancements have transformed
how we approach complex challenges
across industries, supported by these
advanced packaging technologies.
100 million transistors per millimeter
square is achieved through 3D
stacking and chiplet designs, enabling
more powerful and compact systems.
For example, AI training models
like GPT, Leverage dense 3D stacked
memory to process petabytes of data
efficiently, reducing latency and
enhancing throughput in data centers.
40 percent improvement over conventional
2D designs, overcoming traditional
Scaling limitations and supporting
scalability and energy efficiency.
Weather forecasting systems now
utilize HPC platforms with these
innovations to run higher resolution
models that predict climate
changes faster and more accurately.
These achievements provide the
foundation for next generation HPC
systems driving breakthroughs in
areas such as personalized medicine,
real time financial modeling, and
autonomous vehicle simulation.
Which we will explore next.
Next generation HPC systems are
designed to meet the demands of
increasingly complex workloads.
These systems provide high performance,
delivering exceptional computational
power for diverse and intensive workloads.
For instance, Frontier, the world's
first exascale HPC system, enables
simulations of molecular dynamics for
drug discovery, achieving performance
levels surpassing one exaflops.
Energy efficiency, maintaining power
consumption within a sustainable
envelope of under 30 megawatts,
critical for large scale data centers.
This efficiency is exemplified by
systems like Japan's Fugaku, which uses
energy efficient arm based processes
to balance extreme computational
power with low energy costs.
Scalability, architected to grow
with modern application demands.
Ensuring seamless
adaptation to future needs.
Cloud providers like Microsoft,
Azure, HPC Incorporate, flexible
scalability, enabling research teams
to add compute resources dynamically.
Supporting projects like genome
sequencing or AI model training
without infrastructure bottlenecks.
Let's look at some of the
real world applications.
Although we talked about so many
high computing products in earlier
slides, let's just take a look at
a few more real world applications.
Scientific computing facilitating
complex simulations in physics,
chemistry, and biology.
For example, HPC systems are used to
model black hole dynamics in astrophysics
or simulate protein folding in drug
discovery, drastically reducing the
time needed to for breakthroughs.
AI training.
Accelerating the development
and deployment of advanced
machine learning models.
For instance, OpenAI's models like
GPT rely on HPC platforms to train on
trillions of parameters, enabling state
of the art natural language processing
and computer vision applications.
Data analytics.
processing massive data sets for
actionable business and research insights.
Retail giants like Amazon use HPC driven
analytics to optimize supply chain and
personalize customer experience, while
Genomic Research Institute analyzes
terabytes of sequencing data to
identify genetic markers for diseases.
With a 60 percent performance per watt
gain and a 3 times computational density
increases, these systems enable faster
drug discovery by modeling billions of
compounds, accelerate AI breakthroughs
like autonomous vehicle navigation,
and process real time financial
analytics or fraud detection, all while
significantly reducing energy costs.
Let's now look at some of the
challenges these systems face and
future directions for innovations.
Thermal management, high density chip.
Chips generate significant heat,
necessitating advanced cooling solutions.
For instance, liquid immersion cooling is
being adopted in data centers, reducing
power usage by up to 30 percent compared
to traditional air cooling, while thermal
aware chip designs prevent performance
degradation under heavy workloads.
Interconnect scaling.
Achieving data transfer speeds beyond
one terabits per second with minimal
latency is essential for complex workloads
like AI training and simulations.
Optical interconnects, such as silicon
photonics, offer high bandwidth
and lower energy consumption,
enabling seamless communication in
next generation HPC architectures.
Software optimization, advanced
tools and frameworks must fully
utilize heterogeneous resources
like CPUs, GPUs, and FPGAs.
For example, NVIDIA's CUDA and AMD's ROCM
frameworks allow developers to optimize AI
and scientific workloads, achieving up to
10 times performance improvements through
efficient workload distribution and risk.
resource management.
Addressing these challenges require
collaborative efforts across academia,
industry, and governments, ensuring
the continuous evolution of HPC
systems to meet future demands.
We kind of talked about the industry
impact all across our talk and covered
these points in one way or the other.
You can put most of those, those
technology breakthroughs in exascale
computing and AI acceleration category.
While all the big tech giants are working
on these systems, they are committed
to reduce the carbon footprint of
the data centers and supercomputers.
Computers like Google and Microsoft
are investing in renewable energy
power data centers and adopting carbon
neutral strategies such as utilizing
liquid cooling and AI for energy
optimization, reducing emissions
while maintaining performance.
HPC systems are driving
innovation, competitiveness,
and productivity across sectors.
For example, they enable small and medium
enterprises to leverage advanced analytics
for market insights, boost manufacturing
efficiency through predictive maintenance,
and accelerate R& D in industries
like pharmaceuticals and aerospace.
Such contributions make HPC
systems indispensable for
tackling global challenges and
fostering technological progress.
Now let's conclude by looking
ahead to the future of HPC.
HPC systems entering a
new era of innovation.
Marked by advancements in interconnects,
SOC designs, and packaging technologies,
the focus remains on sustainable
computing, balancing performance
improvements with energy efficiency by
integrating AI driven energy management.
For example, metadata centers use AI
for dynamic workload optimization,
achieving up to 38 percent energy savings.
Collaborative research.
Building strong partnerships
between academia, industry, and
government to drive breakthroughs.
Initiatives like the European
Processor Initiative aim to
develop energy efficient, scalable
processors for exascale HPC systems.
Fostering innovation in
fields like climate modeling
and personalized medicine.
These efforts ensure HPC systems remain
at the forefront of science, technology,
and industry, solving today's challenges.
from pandemic response modeling to
autonomous systems development while
paving the way for a sustainable
and technologically advanced future.
Thank you.