Speaker 50: Hey everyone.
I'm Vlad a software engineer
with over 11 years of experience.
And last few years I was working
mostly as a platform engineer and as
an observability engineer, helping
teams to observe their systems.
And today we're going to talk a little
bit about AI agents for incident
response and different parts of that
side, like the good, the bad, the ugly.
So let's start and let's
start with a good part.
Modern ai, like it's
growing with a huge speed.
So like few years, like no one even
knew it exists and it'll grow like that.
But yeah.
Since people start seeing like great
value and integrating it into like their
process as companies, yeah, they see the
value and they do it like fast and fast.
And AI itself is also.
Growing really fast and many observability
platforms, tags, they start also
using ai, creating like AI agents
inside integrating AI in their flows.
And yeah, it happen everywhere.
So it's like for commercial stock, like a
data dock incident, AI pager duty agents.
Honeycomb, MCP and like New Relic AIOps.
And it also helps in open source when
you just get this open source platform.
Like you commonly use I don't
know, Lockkey tempo or a
LK stack or anything else.
And you can connect your AI agent.
Like whatever it is, like clo cursor,
like custom agent Codex or you
can use like also cloud solutions.
They also provide their agents
like Grafana one for example.
And it happened really fast
and with high impact usually.
And we can see that like over 62.
Percent of organizations started
implementing of different AI
agents half of them running pilots.
And yeah, it's a growing trend.
So like few years ago, no
one even thought about that.
And why it is helpful and why people
start even thinking about that.
One of first think of okay, if you are
sitting and working and like you get like
your lots of like slack washing or some
kind of alerts or need some investigation.
I don't know, like databases
slow or like some services
down or like jobs are failing.
So usually like we have some kind of
like common process to investigate.
It could be like rely on alert itself
on our stacks that we use, kind.
Knowledge that we know about the system
knowledge of other people about business
or anything like how system works and
how it's supposed to work, and general
knowledge about okay, how this tool works.
And yeah, usually you got like some
kind of if we talk about alerts, let's
say something is wrong, you most likely
have to and want to have some kind of
alerting for that, and you get alert.
You sometimes have, sometimes
you just know what to do,
like some kind of playbook.
So what to do in this case.
And after that you need to gather
information like what actually happening
potentially, like from multiple systems.
Correlate together.
So it means okay, here I
have this piece of data.
Here I see logs.
Okay, the service is failing.
And I see like in metrics, CPU
is high and something like that.
Or like memory is high and
yeah, you can provide a fix.
So okay, we just need to increase memory.
I don't.
Something like that.
But what if in this
flow we just inject ai?
So usually each of those
tab take some time.
Okay.
We need to understand the context,
check, what to do if we don't.
We are not sure.
We don't remember anything like that.
Gather all the information,
understand what happening and fix it.
But yeah, if we allow AI to do
those, like kind of initial analysis
and like correlation and gathering
all the data and providing us in
like simple format like we can.
Skyrocket our speech to like
investigation and fixing problems.
And if we talk about like minor incident
in it can free engineering time to
spend for something more important and
like just reaction to some kind of.
Alerts I don't know, sometimes can be
noisy, but yeah, whatever can happen.
And in case of some kind of measure
outages to faster gathers information
assume some fixes, understand potential
core reasons, and save company more money
because like usually like high incidents,
it means like business doesn't operate as
expected and it can result as money loss.
Yeah.
In this case it's mostly you can
save lots of time on gathering the
data and improve your like option
to response to this incident.
And usually how it's done
particularly I saw it many companies.
So you have your AI.
Like agent, it could be like custom
agent or like many companies I've
used personally a lot like CLO code
or Cursor agent or some use Codex.
I wrote also some kind of smaller
agents like custom ones for part.
Like use cases, but usually you need
to connect your AI to like different
systems because AI itself, okay.
It'll be like child GT itself.
Okay.
It can research some information, help
you with understanding some kind of how
particular system works or like what
problems what solution to the problem.
Can be applied, but to make it more
like autonomous and powerful you usually
want to connect it to your systems.
And for this just two years ago, you
usually wrote your like, tools, how to
connect to that particular API and like
lots of people did it in different ways.
And like they wrote their
own codes, but a year.
A little bit more than a year ago, a
period like such, think as an MCP and
like it's model context, protocol.
And it's started standardization how
AI can connect to external systems
and lots of like platforms for
observability, including open source.
Like for they allow to connect their
AI agent with such MCP servers.
To the platform.
So for example, you can connect
to your Slack and search for I
don't know, a similar discussions
that happened like a year ago.
Similar incident or like to Jira
to see what was the ticket and why
potentially could fail after deployment
or Datadog with lot, lots of information
there about, telemetry data like
Confluence as a knowledge source.
Also, Grafana has lots of telemetry data,
honeycomb, elastic search like PagerDuty
to understand page itself or GitHub to
have the success to caught and see what
actually can fail if it's like a service.
So lots of.
Impact, lots of speed up.
AI agent can really great gather
all the information, analyze it,
and provide you with some solution.
But yeah, that's a great part about AI
with great parts can go also a bad part.
When you start implementing it, it's
great, it's fun until it is not so it.
Not always work as you expected.
So one of the big problems
is like it can go as deep as.
F It can sometimes, and you need to
limit it because like you can get into a
rabbit hole when it's always try to get
data, analyze it, try to get more and
analyze it, and try to get more and try
to fix something, or try to do something.
And that potentially can go into probably
not infin, but almost infinite loop.
And they try to change
crash, change, doesn't work.
And yeah, it can get stuck
analyzing strange things.
Of course, like you need to have a great
foundation to inject AI because as a
popular phrase, garbage in, garbage out.
It means like you have to provide.
A great data for your AI agent.
So it can understand, okay,
I understand how to get the
data I got from the systems.
I can analyze it and based on that
analysis, I can provide some kind of
like summary and what to do next because
yeah, without that, if you don't have
like good alert and good telemetry
collection, good, access to that data.
Yeah, it's most likely won't work
because if you cannot use that
AI probably also won't use it.
Also it's important to
understand like what and explain
it and what they should do.
And usually as your system grows,
also like context of your system and
knowledge about your system grows.
And like you have like tools for
login, for metrics, for tracing,
for some kind of knowledge.
You have your code, you have I don't
know your like, workflows and jobs and
everything like AI cannot know everything
without training extras that you,
companies don't usually rely on that.
So you need to provide a good
context on how your system works and
how it can analyze what happened.
And, best practice is usually
like to sculpt your agent to some
particular scope of work and do more
a swarm of agents or like cruise.
And it's, it works much better because it
can focus on one particular thing, analyze
logs and collect that and gather metrics.
Gather like some kind of.
Event that happened, and after that
some analytical agent can, okay I
know how to analyze this data and
based on this playbook and also
data I collected, and you have an
orchestrator that can like orchestrate.
So for example, if you use like CLO code,
it usually can be like multiple agents.
Underlines it, execute your query, and
yeah, without that, like you can face
like lots of contexts lower quality
of responses, and yeah, it can just
start providing you with strange data.
And also like with when agents face
something unknown, like failures that.
And it doesn't know how to do.
Of course there are like lots of like
public information and it's great that
AI can understand that and provide
you a solution, but like such kind of
uncontrolled creativity and also not
always great because it can as provide
you with some kind of good solution.
Also, it can provide you with
a bad solution with a mass.
And you start collecting those like errors
and problems with times that can cause
much bigger problems like an incident.
With such things it had to be
reviewed and being under control and.
Explained, and of course one I think
we mentioned like we want to put
like to our agent as many information
as much information as possible.
But the problems that our AI agent is like
with limited context, even some million.
Tokens that some model provides.
It's sometimes not enough.
So you need to manage the context, okay?
Like your logs can be like,
utilized of data and you cannot
just use that as is an AI agent.
And you need to like
use tooling around that.
So cps, for example can help you
to substitute those logging, no
substitute, reduce those login volume.
Let's say or yeah, you can provide
your AI context that, okay, if you
have this incident at this particular
time, please use this particular time
and like plus minus 10 minutes or
something like that to understand if it's
enough information to investigate him.
If you need more, you can try to extend
that, but yeah, it depends on cases,
but yeah, you need to limit those stuff.
Because otherwise it'll be just okay.
I reached my contact.
I don't have any information
and yes, that's it.
I just burning tokens.
And yeah, so it was mostly about
like problems that we can face
and we need to control, but
there are also like ugly parts.
So like the problems that like can go over
itself and can cause much higher problems.
So one of the big problems that recently
start raising, it's like engineers trust.
Yeah.
Without verification.
So you just stamp, approve what?
Okay, I like this
solution, or I don't care.
Yeah.
I just like Gomo with clo mo with
CLO coat or anything like that.
And you start just, okay.
Do is this?
So I have did like some projects where
I just didn't know any line of quote
and the structure of the project itself.
It just wrote something.
But it's, yeah, it's fine for small
systems, small projects when yeah,
it start growing and you add like
such kind of stuff to your system.
It can collect errors pretty fast.
It can like eventually
cause much higher incidents.
Yeah, and this like human in the loop,
like it stopped working because even
because of that, because yeah, people
just stamp and they don't check,
and it's happen more and related
problems, it's like senior engineer,
like skills degrade because like they
start using it much more and like they.
Not always check it and junior
engineer cannot learn because okay.
Some companies, especially a few years
ago, like they start, okay, why do
I need senior, like junior engineer
if I have senior engineer with ai?
And yeah, that goes like gap in
knowledge that sometimes companies
will have some trouble to renew.
Yeah.
And companies already started to upskill.
People in this, but yeah, it's still
like a new problem that had to be checked
and as a one, it's not only related to
observability or engineering, so yeah,
generally like new way of attacking
and security problems with the system.
Mostly it's related to application, but
it's also can be related to observability
because it's important to limit your like
agents in scope and don't provide it,
like to, don't allow it to do everything.
Everything because there are
like such thing like prompt
injection and it's something like
SQL injection like 20 years ago.
So yeah.
You, some kind of malicious prompt
can be injected even in your
logs if you look at some kind of
request or anything like that.
And that can eventually someone can put
such request into your logs and you can,
during investigation, pick that up and
execute some kind of malicious comment,
send some kind of data or execute some
actions that will expose your data or do
some kind of other stuff and we can like,
definitely see that trend is growing.
So there are like almost six
times more like in injection
attacks, prompt injection attacks
than was like before in 2025.
So yeah, it's a huge problem and it's
still like just starting to grow.
Because it's a new one.
But yeah, of course, company.
Think about that.
And they start doing different practices.
So they limit the scope of where AI can
have an access, can internet requests
or like what tools it can access.
Read on the mode and like it
needs an approved for everything.
Yeah, so lots of stuff
to work around that.
But yeah, it's one of the.
Big problem people had to work with.
So eventually yeah AI will continue
growing and where it's right now we can
trust it for this, like data gathering,
data like aggregation, analyzing.
Recognition of different patterns
and like faster investigation and
those emission analysis it can do.
Yeah, because it if you explain how
to do that it can do it really great.
But you still need to verify, basically,
like you have to verify everything
because yeah, you cannot fully rely
because of the problem I mentioned before.
But yeah, of course like you
can rely on it, but like you
cannot rely fully and verify.
You need to verify anonymous
execution because if you like not
verify what it's doing, it can
collect like a reward pretty fast.
And like you cannot like rely at
the moment on high risk actions.
So yeah, you have to approve it
and to check if everything goes.
As a plan.
So that's why there are lots of
processes in companies that like require
another engineer to verify engineer's
work just because of the same issue.
So not rely on a single point of failure,
like in this case, like someone commits
something and you just approve it.
And yeah, like new incidents and
most likely in current situation.
Yeah.
Usually you have to be this,
make this final decision.
But yeah, you can rely on AI on
some kind of basic analysis because
it's like usually helps a lot.
And yeah.
So at the moment.
No, you can think about AI as a not
replacement, but like more like a pilot
or, I like to think about that as a
kind of ai, as a like force multiplier.
I just extend your capabilities, like
in times it can scale productivity, like
decision making and impact you can make.
But with one caveat, it just
multiply everything if you don't
control it, it'll multiply your
mistakes rules you collect and risks.
Yeah.
As we know with great power comes great
responsibility and we have to remember it.
But yeah, I totally AI and I'm using
it every day and yeah, it's, growing is
huge, but it have to be under control.
So yeah.
Thanks for listening.
Okay.