Hello everyone.
Greetings of the day.
My name is Karthik Akinnapelli and
I'm hoping you're all doing well.
Today, I'm excited to share the
results of a trial conducted to
evaluate a new oral antibiotic in
comparison to Emprixiprofloxacin.
So why late?
Let's dive into the study
and look at its key findings.
So before we jump into the trial
information, let me give you a
little bit background of this trial.
So why new antibiotic?
There is a growing concern about
increasing fluoroquinolone resistance in
real world settings, which significantly
limits treatment options for uncomplicated
urinary tract infections in outpatient
setting, which leads to hospitalization.
Now why sulopenum?
Sulopenum is the first oral
theopenum antibiotic specifically
developed to combat multi drug
resistant gram negative uropathogens.
Neuropathogens are nothing but pathogens
responsible for urinary tract infections.
Now about this study.
This is a phase 3 double blind study
evaluating the efficacy and safety of
a five day course of sulopenum compared
to the standard three day regimen of
ciprofloxacin in adult women with UUTIs.
Coming to the end point, the primary
end point is a robust composite measure.
assessing both clinical symptom
resolution and microbiological
eradication at the test of cure
visit which is day 12 in the study.
Now let's look at enrollment overview.
A total of 1672 women were enrolled in
the trial of which 1660 participants
were qualified for the safety
population, meaning they received
at least one dose of study drug.
Whereas 1072 participants
qualified into microbiological
intent to treat population.
This is where the primary
endpoint is evaluated.
The criteria to qualify into
this population is that the
baseline pathogen should have
at least 10 to the 5 CFU per ml.
CFU is nothing but colony forming units.
Now, key findings.
Essertia coli was the predominant
pathogen accounting for approximately 85
percent of all infections in this study.
Of these, 27 percent demonstrated
non susceptibility to ciprofloxacin.
That is pretty high rate.
Now second most common pathogen
identified was Klebsiella pneumonia.
Now, looking at resistance
insights, around 13.
5 percent of the total isolates were
extended spectrum beta lactamase
producing, ESBL producing organisms,
indicating multi drug resistance.
Now, let's look at efficacy results.
in non susceptible pathogens.
Sulopenum demonstrated clear superiority
over ciprofloxacin in treating non
susceptible pathogens with a significant
treatment difference in efficacy of 26.
6 percent and a highly
significant p value.
Now, in susceptible pathogens, sulopenum
did not achieve non inferiority.
The response rate for sulopenum was 66.
8 percent in solo.
compared to 78.
6 percent in Cipro.
Now in overall study population combining
both non susceptible and susceptible
populations, solopenem achieved non
inferiority with the response rate of 65.
6 in solo compared to 67.
9 in ciprofloxacin.
So let's look at clinical response.
The study evaluated clinical
response at various time points
with the following key findings.
At initial evaluation at day
5 of the study, solopenem and
ceprofloxacin demonstrated
comparable response rates, 68.
7 percent solo versus 67.
3 percent in cipro.
At day 12, which is at, Primary
endpoint, solopenem showed similar
overall effectiveness in clinical
response compared to ciprofloxacin 81.
1 percent in Sulo versus 84.
1 percent in Cipro Whereas in the
resistant population, solopenem
clearly exhibited superior efficacy
83 percent in Sulo versus 62.
6 percent in Cipro Now they also evaluated
a follow-up period, which is day 28.
Both treatment groups maintained a
sustained clinical response confirming
the durability of the treatments.
Now with good clinical response, why did
Opinum did not achieve non-inferiority
in non susceptible pathogens?
This is because of a SP impact.
Like I said, while clinical response
rates are very comparable between
two treatment groups, the difference
lay in microbiological outcomes,
specifically the occurrence of ASB,
asymptomatic bacteria, which is
nothing but patients are clinically
clear, but has a positive culture.
Now, at day 12, ASB was more prevalent in
sulopinem group compared to ciprofloxacin.
15.
2 percent in Sulo versus 7.
8 percent in Cipro.
Despite the higher ASB rates,
patients in both groups demonstrated
equivalent clinical outcomes
during follow up period at day 28,
as we saw in the previous slide.
This is confirming the
durability of the treatment.
So what's the conclusion?
The higher ASB rates with Sulopenum
likely reflect the restoration of
normal urogenital bacterial flora.
rather than persistent infection
highlighting a potential
microbiological advantage.
Now, let's look at resistance emergence.
So, some of the key observations
include resistance development.
Following treatment
with ciprofloxacin, 41.
7 percent of initially susceptible
pathogens developed resistance.
very high percent indicating
significant selective pressure.
Now genetic changes in pathogens post
treatment some pathogens acquired extended
spectrum beta lactamase ESBL genes
compromising multiple antibiotic classes
and further limiting treatment options.
Now, looking at sulopenum MIC stability,
in contrast, MIC distribution for
sulopenum remains stable, demonstrating
a low risk of resistance development.
So what's the conclusion?
The contrasting effects on bacterial
resistance patterns underscored the
critical importance of antibiotic
stewardship and informed drug
selection in managing UTIs.
These findings highlight silopenum's
potential as a valuable option in
combating antibiotic resistance.
Now, let's look at safety profile.
So, both treatment groups showed
almost similar safety results.
Silopenum showed 25 percent
of adverse event rate compared
to ciprofloxacin at 14%.
And the most common adverse
event include headache.
which is 4.
2 percent in Sulo versus 3.
1 percent in Cipro.
And the next most common
adverse event found is nausea.
3.
8 percent in Sulo versus 2.
2 percent in Cipro.
Diarrhoea, which is GI
related, was significantly more
common with Sulopenum at 12.
4 percent versus 2.
5 with a mean duration of three days,
but 95 percent of cases resolved
spontaneously while 5 percent
required anti diarrheal medication.
Other GI effects include nausea and
abdominal pain, pretty much very
common with all antibiotic classes.
Serious adverse event
rates are also similar, 0.
7 percent in versus 0.
2 percent in Cipro and of the six
serious adverse events on solopenem,
only two were considered drug related.
And in the course of the study, no
deaths occurred and all the SOEs are
resolved by the end of the study.
Now, implications of empirical treatment.
Similar overall efficacy.
So, solopenum showed non inferiority
to ciprofloxacin in general population
as we seen in the previous slides.
Resistant advantage.
Solopenum showed superiority
to ciprofloxacin in non
susceptible population.
Reduce risk resistance.
As discussed in the previous
slide, solopenum demonstrated low
risk of resistance development
and giving a treatment option
for multidrug resistant UTIs.
Cellopenem showed effectiveness
against pathogens that are
resistant to multiple antibiotics.
Now, let's look at some study
limitations and considerations.
Limitations include, the study was
conducted before the implementation
of updated treatment guidelines,
which may affect its relevance
to current clinical practices.
The inclusion of ASB in the primary
endpoint may not fully align with
real world clinical practice patterns.
Now, short term follow up limits
the ability to assess the long
term emergence of resistance.
Coming to the key considerations, results
indicate that empiric use of ciprofloxacin
should be avoided in settings
where resistance rates exceed 10%.
Now, balancing the therapeutic
efficacy with the potential
for mild gastrointestinal
side effects is essential.
So lopinum offers a viable treatment
option for multiple drug resistant
urinary tract infections addressing a
critical gap in current treatment options.
Now, finally conclusions and further
future directions Solopenum has
demonstrated significant efficacy
in treating multi drug resistant
urinary tract infections, providing
a crucial alternative to existing
empirical treatment options.
Incorporating regional antibiotic
resistance data into clinical
decision making is essential to
optimize therapeutic outcomes.
The study highlights sulopenem's
potential to minimize bacterial
resistance development while
maintaining its therapeutic efficacy.
There is a critical need to further
investigate long term resistance
patterns and patient outcomes through
comprehensive longitudinal studies.
Finally, continued exploration
of sulopinem's implementation in
diverse clinical settings will
help refine its role in managing
multi drug resistant infections.
Thank you so much for giving me
this opportunity and take care, bye.