Hey folks, this is Matan.
I'm the co founder and CEO
of Rapido Technologies.
today I want to talk to you a little
bit about relational databases in the
cloud, the challenges that are coming
with the new era of microservices
and multi tenant architectures, and
why essentially in the cloud world,
managing relational database is Broken.
I'm grateful to be a
gold sponsor of con 42.
we're excited to be here and to, be
part of your community, at least for
the upcoming year, and learn more
from your insights, about the devil S.
R.
E.
Cloud engineering aspect of databases,
and hopefully to bring value to you.
multiple folks from this community
using the tools of Rapido.
So let's dive in.
managing relational databases
in the cloud is broken.
And why do we say that?
the cloud is introduced, companies
with new challenges related to
managing a auto scalable applications.
Kubernetes, auto scaling groups.
have all introduced.
dramatic flexibility, but severe
challenges in any shared everything
architecture like relational databases.
So in the end of your day, in the end
of the day, your application is able
to scale automatically by 1000 X.
But your database is a one monolithic
piece, that is very, very hard to manage.
So essentially, your.
Databases and your applications
in the cloud has evolved
and changed dramatically.
But the tools that are allowing the
DBMS itself has not changed at all.
and this is why we believe that the entire
way companies are managing relational
databases in the cloud today is broken and
introducing a lot of challenges related to
observability, SLA, Resiliency and costs.
the trend and I'm going to skip like
the previous slide, but the trend was
that in the past, companies managed
a small fleet of databases, right?
So on Prem, when you have few
monolithic applications, it is.
Relatively easy to manage
to manage your database.
You have a full blown DBA team, that know
exactly what they do on the databases.
the changes in the scale are not severe,
so it's not thousands of percents.
It's, 10, 12, 15%.
So sizing for the peak is not
hard, and it's not expensive.
and,
Due to these factors, managing
performance and, tackling issues,
was not hard as it is today, right?
uh, Meantime to detect meantime to
resolve databases issues was not high
back in the days when you had a full
blown DBA team when you had monitoring
systems that monitoring 5 to 10 databases
with a The disadvantages, of course, of
living in a monolithic world in terms
of time to market for new applications
in terms of flexibility, launching
new services, living in that world for
databases side of things was not too
bad besides the Oracle or my or or SQL
Server license that you had to pay.
In today's world, with microservices,
micro applications, in many cases,
thousands of micro applications, managing
tenants, became, became, managing tenants
became, great opportunity to accelerate
time to market for new applications, new
features, substantial flexibility, right?
Like building and deploying
new features became.
so fast that we deploy new features to
our SAS applications in many cases, you
know, every day and, we all rely on open
source databases like MySQL, Postgres,
and it became actually a great, A great
world for managing applications, but
alongside the improvements and the value
that we gained in the auto scalable
world in the cloud native world, a lot of
changes came to teams managing RDS, In the
cloud, so or relational databases in the
cloud, reducing when you manage a fleet
of databases, it is very hard to reduce
downtime and improve performance, right?
So tracking 5000 databases and
understanding where exactly.
your CPU is close to the edge.
It's not easy, right?
Gaining visibility across all
databases in a single dashboard.
This is something that many companies
are seeking to gain, but using the
current tools like RDS Performance
Insights or, or Datadog is not easy.
It's not easy to see that level of
visibility across a fleet of databases.
Finding and addressing relational,
finding and addressing slow queries.
across your entire fleet.
So this is hard.
And due to that, we see mounting costs
and many companies are just pouring more
and more money on databases in order, in
order to reduce SLA and resiliency issues.
And this really makes companies
becoming, so if you think about
a tool, a native tool in AWS
RDS performance insights, right?
It gives you visibility
only to one DB instance.
And when you look on one DB instance,
when managing a fleet of 5000
databases, you are by definition
reactive and not proactive, right?
And one of the things we always want to do
when we manage such an important assets,
like such an important asset, like our
databases is to be able to be proactive.
So even when you can find the root cause,
when you have a fleet of databases,
What can you do about it, right?
Sometimes you have legacy code,
you have a a, a low, you have a, a,
you have big r and d organization.
what can you do as an operational
team when you see A CPU or IO
spikes or a problematic query?
In the end of the day, the only
thing you can do is to ship that
to a, To your dev team, right?
So what we believe the ideal
tool, will have, right?
Like, what are the
properties of the ideal tool?
So the three pillars, of modern, Database
a management tool will be observability.
So improving observability across
thousands of instances, improving
resiliency with no code changes
and maintaining a sane coast.
On your database, right?
So, so if you will look on every
AWS or Google cloud bill, RDS
and cloud SQL typically be the
second or the third line item.
So observability, resiliency and cost
are the three legs of this tool when
managing a relational databases in the
cloud and, and missing any of them,
will not get you the results you need.
Now let's, let's dive a bit further into.
into observability, right?
So what is exactly, what is it
exactly that we miss today in
today's world in the existing tools?
So, so first, it's no longer
effective to have a look at each
database individually, right?
We need, we need a solution
that looks across all of our
databases and, and pools.
Pulls all the metric data into a
single consolidated view, right?
So, essentially, you need to see what are
my slowest queries across my entire fleet.
What, which DBs are, we want to see
the top CPU or the highest CPU load
right now across my entire fleet.
We want to see the highest memory IO
consumption across my entire fleet.
we want to set alerts and get notified,
if certain thresholds are hit.
we want to see.
whether we are running out of
database connections, right?
So db connections are limited.
And 500 or 5000 databases, being
able to track where do I have
shortage on connections is very hard.
So this is another
thing we want to manage.
we want to get visibility into table
locks and deadlocks across 5000 of
database, 5000 databases, right?
so, so these, these capabilities these.
Are something you must have when
managing a, a SAS application when
managing databases for SAS application.
the second pillar will be resiliency.
So, so.
The tool that you use must be able
to put guardrails, in place to
protect the databases from those
type of issues cause outage, right?
Like, when your CPU spikes, right, to
100%, you've got to be able to protect
your database from these spikes.
when bad queries are hitting your
database, you've got to be able to respond
fast and, and, and rewrite those queries.
In transit, when bad code is sending
too many queries or too many requests,
the same query over and over to your
database, you've got to be able to to
throttle that or to or to catch that
when you access idle connections.
you get, you get, you get ran out of
connections, you get run over, you
get ran out of availability, right?
So you've got to be able to
protect your database from.
From shortage of connections,
these capabilities must be a,
a, an integral part of of your,
your database fleet, right?
Of managing your databases in the cloud.
Now, on top of that, you
got to be able to not pour.
Tons of money on your
database to do that, right?
So you got to be able to make
sure that your CPU and IO costs
are not going through the roof.
You got to be, you got to have a
capacity, a capacity planned that
will not be based on your CPU spikes.
You got to be able to protect
your database from CPU spikes
that will kill your application.
So, so again.
Resiliency, observability, and
maintaining low costs or same cost in
the database are what you must have
when managing fleet of databases.
So this is guys when I
introduce Rapido to you.
So Rapido is a Platform
that allows company.
It is fully deployed in your VPC.
It allows companies with large
fleet of databases to manage a
managed visibility observability.
So, as you can see, rapid or scout, our
observability platform will connect to
all your Postgres and MySQL databases
and start aggregating data about their
processes about, Infrastructure metrics
like CPU IO memory and consolidate
them in one one pane of glass.
On top of that, we have cortex, which
is our automation layer that allows
companies to offload repetitive queries
from their database via a proxy and
also via the connections that we manage.
So you could you could
deploy caching throttling.
Our query, rewrite a lot of capabilities
in one tool in one platform.
So, so let's now let's now move
to a live demo of Rapido and
see the platform in action.
So guys, this is, this
is the Rapido console.
and as you can see, our master dashboard
will gain, will get you visibility
to the most pressing issue issues
across your entire fleet of databases.
let me move to 48 hours so
we could have more data.
Okay.
and and as you can see, these are the most
pressing issues across my entire database
fleet in the last 48 hours, right?
So we can see the top or the or the
slow or the average query runtime
across my entire fleet, right?
So the average query
runtime is 12 seconds.
But when I drill down,
I can see that I have.
some queries with average runtime of 120
seconds or two minutes, and I have some
queries with sub second or second runtime.
and again, every line item
that you see here is a query
on a database on a DB instance.
On top of that, you will be able
to see the top CPU consumers
across your entire fleet.
You will be able to see a
shortage on connections.
You will be able to see locks and
deadlocks across your entire fleet.
across your entire fleet.
in every column that you see, I just drill
down to my deadlocks, or to my locks view.
and if a group by we love the
group by capability, right?
So if a group by you can easily
see that my postgres database is
by far the most suffering entity
from looks across my entire fleet.
So using rapid, you can actually gain
visibility to postgres and my sequel
instances in one pane of glass, right?
So, My, my postgres database is the first.
All the others are, are my SQL database.
Now I can extend that and I
can see whether I'm facing a
transaction look or metadata look.
I can, I can aggregate
by, the current statement.
So I can see that there are 2 statements.
There is 1 update and 1 select
on my postgres database that
is generating a lot of looks.
at this point I can.
Use Rapido or a engineering
tools to fix that.
That's looking right now.
As you can see here.
we have, we had, we had, we had
a, a CPU reduction on multiple
databases, but we have one database
here that is running on 99 to 100.
CPU utilization most of the time.
Right now, at this point, guys, I can
move to the real time view of Rapido.
And as I mentioned here, you can actually
see a flat list of all your Postgres and
MySQL databases in in one pane of glass.
I can group by again and see
that they have one Postgres
instance and 11 MySQL instances.
And we can see that my demo database here.
It's a MySQL 8 database.
D.
B.
It's gravity on machine extra large.
I'm sorry.
Large with 100 percent CPU and shortage
of database connections, right?
So I have 100.
I'm sorry.
250 connections out of 250
utilized and I have a query of
five minutes on that database.
Now, clicking on that will allow
me to drill down and to see
what is happening in real time.
on that particular database, right?
So you can see that we have a very
repetitive query here, but the great
part is that you can actually see how
the issue started like to compound.
So looking 15 minutes ago and grouping
by again, we love the group by capability
here in Rapido grouping by showing me
that the SQL calc found rows function
from the parents table ran four times in
parallel moving a bit forward in time.
We can see that it spiked to 112, and
a bit further, we are looking at 230.
And if I go back to the live view,
You can actually see that currently
we have 237 queries running right
now with that specific syntax.
Now, using Rapido, I can
actually do stuff, right?
Not only gaining visibility, but
also pull the trigger and kill the
query that is generating the spike.
I know that killing a query is something
that you We'll probably think twice
before you pull the trigger on.
but when you have the ability to do
that, using Rapido will actually, be a
life saver because you could actually
remediate the issue on this boat.
Now, as you can see, I'm killing
the query, but, my application
throw it back again to the database.
So So this is not a very useful solution
to kill the query right there on the spot.
At this point, guys, I want to move
to the automation field of Rapido.
Let me, let me quickly
refresh my page here.
I'm going to, I'm going to go ahead and
log in again to my, to my application.
Let's give it a sec.
Yeah, I guess I loaded
my database too much.
There you are, going down to the
automation field, will show me
the vast amount of rules that
you can deploy using rapid.
So I can go ahead and cache query.
So using rapid, or you could
essentially deploy caching,
using table based invalidation.
So.
I did not copy the query.
Let me go go back to rapid.
Oh, and copy the query again.
so, by the way, as you can see
here, it's dropped and I lost
connection to the database.
So this is why I'm not having data
here, but as you can see, it started
like compounding again, and now the
query amount is growing rapidly.
Right.
So, so at this point, I
just copied the query name.
I'm going back to my caching
rules, and I can go ahead and,
deploy a cash rule, right?
A cash rule can, can be can be
based on a query or a table.
I can catch an entire table or a query.
in this case, I would.
Probably wanna cache these query.
I'm, I'm gonna choose a query
and, and, and look at this.
without us, we are, we are currently
the, only solution, or we enable
you to do something that you are
unable to do without rapido is,
is, is DevOps or, or SRE teams.
and it's to deploy a caching
rule on your own with no.
Business consequences, right?
Because if you use table based
invalidation, we will actually make
sure that the cache data will always
be coherent with your database itself.
Right?
So if I'm going to go ahead and save
that now, I have a query cache that
will essentially offload that query.
Now, that probably won't be the
great solution or the best solution
for this use case because this query
is, he's using current date, and it
essentially changes every nanosecond.
Right?
So, so at this point, I'm moving
to scout rules in scout rules.
I've already prepared a rule
that throttle this query to two.
So it will allow this a sequel called
found rose, To run only two times in
parallel and and look at this, right?
I'm I'm using here a wild
card on the limit, right?
So so it's it's a flat line.
Think about it as a flat line
using the wild card here that
essentially limits that query to
run only two times in parallel.
Now I'm going back to my my sequel.
It remembers the configuration I had.
And as you can see, the
problem compounds again.
But at this point, guys, I'm going to
go ahead and pull the trigger, killing
that process, and within within a few
seconds, you will see that it's gone.
And excuse me, and it's not
going to spike again, right?
So essentially, maintaining a
throttling rule will allow me and
you can already see it's starting.
starting right.
So now I have only two instances of
the simple calc found roles, right?
So my application keeps throwing the
query to the database, but now Rapido will
allow only two execution in power, right?
So you can see it right there going
back from 75 to 46 to 2, right?
So, yes, this is what Rapido is all about.
I hope.
This session was interesting.
I would love to dive further and
show you scout rules and alert rules.
So, so using Rapido, you can essentially
maintain a low footprint of connections.
You can maintain a policies that
will make your database more secure.
Sane, and, and not spiky.
going back to the presentation, feel free
to drop me an email at, mat at rapido io.
I would love to, extend the
conversation and discussion on
relational databases in the cloud.
So even if it's not related to
Rapido, I'm down with any discussion
about databases and I really hope
to meet you guys face to face soon.
So have a great day and take care.
Bye-bye.