Speaker 49: Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining me today
I'll be talking about privacy by
design for DevOps and data systems.
I'm excited to show you how we can build
secure and privacy respecting systems
without sacrificing usable user usability.
My name is Vivic Chidi.
I'm a data engineer and I focus on
privacy centric data architectures
and real time streaming.
I've spent many years working on privacy
aware systems and infrastructure, and
today at Con 42 DevOps 2026, we'll
dig into where privacy, compliance
and modern DataOps and DevOps
data engineering actually meet.
This goes way beyond
just ticking some boxes.
It's about rethinking how we build
our systems from the ground up.
And as a quick disclaimer, this talk is
no way affiliated with the company that
I work for, and nothing presented here
reflects my company's internal systems.
I'm just sharing what I've
learned from my own experience
working with data and privacy.
So why does this matter?
No.
Right now there are more than 140
countries that have active privacy
laws, and the average cost of data
breach hit about $5 million in 2024,
and that's the latest data that we have.
And $5 million is a pretty big number.
And here's something
that's even more alarming.
Researchers can re-identify
about 87% of Americans.
From just the zip code
date of birth and gender.
And this is not some distance theory.
This is actually happening right now.
Privacy isn't optional anymore.
It's a hard requirement for
any serious DevOps data system,
both technically for businesses.
So now what is privacy wear design?
Privacy by design is all about building
privacy protections straight into your
architecture right from the start.
So you're not trying to bolt it on at the
end, you're starting it from the get go.
And for DevOps developers, that means
layering privacy controls at every stage.
Of the data pipeline from collecting data
on the client side to storage backends,
to analytics, to processing, to deploying
pipelines, you're ensuring that there
is no data that is getting stored.
There's no private private data
that's getting stored, and privacy
needs to be baked from the get go.
Let's talk about core
privacy by design principles.
So there are four privacy principles
that I want to talk about.
The first one is be proactive.
So you anticipate and prevent
privacy issues before they pop up.
And the next thing is default to privacy.
Give the users maximum protection
automatically without needing
them to change their settings.
So if you are asking for users to
change things so that they become
private, or their data becomes private,
you're not doing something right.
Third thing is make privacy
a part of the design itself.
So you're not doing privacy as a last
minute add-on to check off a few boxes,
but from the get go analyzing what data
should be collected, what data should not
be collected, whether a data collection,
would make sense for your product.
But more than that, whether that collected
data would cause any privacy issues,
should that data get into the wrong hands.
So try to collect as little.
Data as you possibly can.
And finally, full functionality.
So not only are you collecting little
data, but while you are collecting
little data, are your apps still working?
Are your DevOps pipeline still working?
Like, how can you do that?
So let's talk about how this is possible.
So the first one is, let's talk
about anonymization models.
So key anonymity makes sure that every
record in your data sets blends in with
at least K minus one other records.
For example typical case 50
for, decent private systems.
So if your data looks just
like at least 49 others.
Then you are meeting care
anonymity, and this works well
for user analytics especially
when you do demographic analytics.
But you don't want to
expose individual data.
And the second one is L diversity.
This one takes it a bit more
further, so it makes sure that
even within those groups there
is a mix of sensitive attributes.
And this is crucial for stuff
like healthcare data where you
don't want anyone in a group
sharing the same diagnosis.
And let's talk about how
this can be put in practice.
Differential privacy, is a little
mathematical, but by adding carefully
calibrated noise to your query results,
you make sure that no one can tell if
a specific person's data is in the mix.
Epsilon data between 0.1 and one give you
strong privacy without ruining your stats.
And the main idea here is you
can't pick out individuals, but
you still see overall trends.
Give DevOps has some,
great tools for this.
Differential privacy.
You can use nor js to implement this.
And you can even do local
differential privacy in the browser.
This way you get useful analytics
and your privacy stays protected.
Let's talk about sdo, randomization
and tokenization as a next slide.
So pseudo randomization or
tokenization are essential when
you deal with personal data.
So pseudo anonymization swaps out
identifying fields for pseudonyms,
so you keep the links you need for
analytics, but hide real identities
and tokenization takes us further.
It replaces sensitive data with
the random tokens and stores real
stuff in a separate secure world.
So you are delineating your data
from one system to another, that
everything is not sitting in one place.
So somebody has to gain this additional
access to go bring that data together.
So your analytics will never touch
actual PII, but you can still get
insights and if you ever need to.
You re-identify the data, then you know
you can go back and join that data.
And you only do that for legitimate
reasons like customer support.
And then let's talk about
a few advanced techniques.
So if you really wanna to.
Cutting edge privacy.
Look at home morphic encryption.
It lets you run computations
or encrypted data.
You don't need to decrypt anything.
So imagine running a machine learning
model that stay accurate up to 95% while
the data itself never gets exposed.
And the second one is secure
multi-party computation.
This is basically your sharing data
to another system where that system.
Processes a bunch of data and your system
processes a bunch of data, and then
you're sharing that across the board.
And then let's talk about.
Integrating TPIs into
DevOps pipelines, right?
So data production and impact
assessments, data production, impact
assessments, DPIs is a continuous process.
It's not a one-time exercise and you
embed these directly into your CI
ICD pipelines into your workflows.
Contact automatic.
Privacy scans and ensure that
there's no PIN sensitive data that's
getting pushed into code commits.
You make sure that your pipelines
are gated by requiring DPI
approval before deploying changes
that process, personal data.
And you track these privacy metrics
alongside your performance and
security on a continuous mode.
So you surface that on a daily level to
find out what instances are occurring,
how many, accidental privacy pushes
are happening into your pipelines.
Okay.
And, the actionable architecture for
privacy versus systems is minimize the
data, collect only what's necessary,
I'm recapping what we discussed so far.
So collect only what's necessary and
encrypt the data wherever possible.
Do role-based access, control
and give access to the people
only who deserve it and need it.
Not deserve it per se, but need it, and
finally, there is an automated compliance.
You're not manually checking this stuff.
It's happening automatically by itself.
That's about it for this talk.
I really appreciate you listening to this.
Thank you so much and good
luck in building secure
Privacy Compliance Systems.
Have a great day.
Okay.