Speaker 29: My name is P Patel.
I'm a senior staff engineer at Equinix.
And today I'm gonna talk about how an
autonomous agent can build multi-cloud
infrastructure for you and take you
beyond ISC and prompt engineering.
The days of having.
All your workloads in on-prem are in a
single cloud provider, are long gone now.
Customers have their training
models in Nvidia Cloud.
They have their data pipeline in AWS
inference in GCP and their secret data
or secure data in in their on-prem.
And there is a constant need to
stitch them all together and that.
Complexity.
Every cloud provider has their
own tools, have their own way
of orchestrating patterns.
Some call it express connect,
some call it direct connect,
some call it cloud routers.
And these are all confusing jargons and
for DevOps team to understand all of this
and stitch together the network has been.
More challenged than ever before.
Clearly, there are tools for us.
Terraform came up with declarative
statements that said, we will
do infrastructure as code.
It will show what your, you can write
what your infrastructure is meant to be.
And Terraform Cloud said, okay, I'll
help you with maintaining the state and
maybe a little bit of reconciliation.
Lummi said, oh, you can write your
own code in whatever language you.
Familiar with, and we'll translate
that to infrastructure score across
companies and teams have built Kubernetes
operators and they've leveraged cross
plane to reconcile their infrastructure
because there is always a drift.
AWS said Cloud Foundation can do it.
But there is a lot of these different
tools out there, and not one solves all
the problem of easy cloud provisioning.
What comes with all of
this is fear of change.
Nobody wants to touch infrastructure
that seems so brittle that you make
one change somewhere, something
else goes out of the window.
There is always in
inconsistencies in reconciliation.
Your Terraform states says something,
but somebody did something on the
console that nobody knows about.
States are opaque, hard
to interpret what it is.
What it really translates to.
And then there is cognitive overload.
You have multiple different DSLs,
SCLs, APIs and different jargons
that people have to understand.
And lastly, the tribal knowledge.
We have all been there where you are
at the mercy of another engineer and
you're always hoping that engineer
never leaves because only he or she or
them know what it really stands for.
Luckily, yay has come to our sq
lms started telling us how to start
writing these programs better.
But LMS are nothing but
glorified template generators.
And a lot of teams have.
Claim to be used LMS and have been
agreed, or having believed to have
jumped on the gravy train of ai,
but we are still limiting ourselves.
The real answer is the autonomous
infrastructure agent that understands
multi-cloud, understands the history,
understands the syntax, understands
the correctness, understands
the configurations with minimum.
Infrastructure as code with LMS are great.
They speed you up, but
they're very limited.
They can only ate templates for you.
They cannot, in fact put
in all the values for you.
They do not have context
awareness, which means they're.
Their response and the templates that
are generated are at the mercy of how
good your prompt is, and you have to be
manually re verifying the templates or the
code generated in terms of correctness,
in terms of security policies and syntax.
And there is no operational
intelligence whatsoever in here.
So with my expertise and my
experimentation, I bring this vision
to the DevOps community of autonomous
infrastructure agent that transforms
your LMS from passive code generator
to continuously aware system that
understands your infrastructure.
That reasons on real time
and makes analysis, it does.
Autonomous actions on your behalf
orchestrates, cloud provider, cloud
constructs, and cloud resources.
It does self-correction when needed.
It optimizes your cost, your security,
and any preferences that you might want
your agent to do for your organization.
The core architecture is around rag
purpose-built ritual layer index
your cloud assets, configurations,
and dependencies across mul all your
cloud providers, transforming a static
model into a dynamic infrastructure.
The architecture pattern solves the
context window limitation and ensures
the agents have up to date information.
And not based on any old documentation
from the cloud providers.
Speaker 30: My pipeline is your judge.
Verify, validation, verify.
And the correctness
Speaker 29: with terms of relationships
and constraints that you have
put together as an organization.
It ensures all the security
concerns are taken care of.
Unnecessary reports are not open,
security groups are not overridden.
And then finally the compliance
check that something that comes
from InfoSec teams, for example.
I categorized building this
rack into three main categories.
One is specialized ritual.
The domain specific vector will store
infrastructure, metadata, configuration
templates it could be prior native
schema, relationship indices, and
then historical change locks will
becomes core reasoning for why a
particular decision has been made.
And then the real time synchronization.
This is where you get your cloud
fails, you get your activity logs
any drift detections you might have
set up that feeds into the agent.
And then the guardrail workflows,
the policy agent design with
mandatory checkpoints with human
in the loop for escalation.
When done correctly set an
autonomous infrastructure agent
can accelerate your deployment.
It'll go from minutes, it'll
go from hours to minutes.
Crossover orchestration would not
be as complicated and as scary as it
seems, and it becomes more natural.
And the self-healing operations is
where you get bang for the buck with
auto detections and auto remediations.
But that doesn't go with
saying that there are no risks.
You will run into context con context,
window constraints if the window gets
too large, but with the special ed
ritual and summarization strategies.
You can mitigate that identity.
Boundary failures, which is very scary.
Autonomous agents can get out of
control if not properly managed.
If you have least privileged models set up
and service accounts associated with them
you can mitigate that hallucination risk.
LLM agents think as they want.
None of us know how they
really think very well.
Having multi-stage verification
that we talked about.
And doing dry run validations can
prevent these catastrophic failures.
Agent level access, security
compromised agents can manipulate
the production infrastructure,
which is scarier than anything.
For me immutable audit trails
and an anomaly detections
can help us get past that.
Now that we know what we need to do, now
it comes down to how we want to do it.
Take a small step.
Start with building your RAC foundation.
Build a strong RAC foundation
based on your infrastructure.
State in your templates the
history, and states, whatever you
might have, and start from there.
Build a concrete verification pipeline.
Multi-stage pipelines for syntax
semantic security and compliance
that we discussed before.
And then deploy autonomous
agents with guardrails that
are centric to your workflows.
Deploy in low risk areas with high
reputation tasks and run it over and
see how it performs, and then you can
scale it up with proper governance.
I want to stress this.
I cannot emphasize security
and governance enough.
If we want to deploy an autonomous
agent that can run on our production
infrastructure, then access control and
auditing becomes the top most concern.
Start with least privilege.
Assignment model, and they
should always be time bound.
So have multifactor authentication
for your agents through service
accounts segregate execution
environment, workflows between the
cloud providers and your environments.
Continuous permission monitoring.
See agents themselves go rogue
and update their permission.
Take up enough concerns and protections
around iams audits and compliances.
Immutable logs of all the agent's
decisions becomes core to this.
Real time.
An anomaly detection on agent
behavior, autonomous compliance,
reporting and regulation in 2026.
Infrastructure.
Autonomous agents will
start becoming a baseline.
If you miss the boat, you will
fall behind deployment velocity.
Incident reduction and cost optimization
is something, are the metrics that we
accounted for, and this is where an
autonomous agent can be our best friend.
Infrastructure agents are not a
distance, are not in distant future.
They are right here.
It is up for us to make the deliberate
decisions to build rack powered
awareness, multi-stage verification
and governance agent agent design.
We can try to get for, or look or explore
some of the out of the box agents for
infrastructure management, but they
might not always do what we need because
every organizations are different.
Every requirements are different.
And until, and unless we train these
agents to do what we want for our
organization, we will always fall behind.
So take that step.
With that, I thank Con 42 and DevOps
conference for giving me this opportunity.
I hope you all enjoyed my talk.