Speaker 41: Hello everyone and
welcome to Con 40 two's DevOps 2026.
I am Riva p Shaker and thank
you for joining me today.
I'm excited to share with you a topic
that has become increasingly critical
in our industry as we navigate the
complexity of modern software delivery.
Today we are going to explore how
GitHub's observability and artificial
intelligence converge to create resilient
systems that automatically detect and
recover from failures significantly
reducing downtime and minimizing the
need for human inter intervention.
So this isn't just about automation for.
Automation's sake.
It's about fundamentally transforming
how we think about reliability and
resilience in our CICD pipelines.
Moving from reactive posture
to a truly proactive one where
our systems can heal themselves
before problems impact our users.
So let me tell you a small story.
Let's picture yourself as a
platform operations engineer.
And it's about 3:00 AM in the morning
your phone buses and you get alerted.
Another deployment has gone sideways.
So you scramble out of your
bed, open up your laptop, and
start the familiar archeology.
So you started to wonder like
what changed, who deployed
what where was the drift?
And honestly, this was my life
for years, and I know many
of you have been there too.
Today I want to show you how we can
write a different ending to that story.
So before we dive into the technical
content let me take a moment to
introduce myself and share a bit.
About my background.
I currently serve as a senior site
reliability manager, and I have been
fortunate to spend over 15 years working
across various domains in our industry.
I have played roles as a DevOps
engineer, cloud infrastructure designer.
A platform engineer and a
cloud native tech as well.
So throughout this journey, I have
worked on building resilient Kubernetes
platforms by implementing GI Ops practices
at scale working with organizations
that span multiple industries including
retail, finance, banking, and the
technology modernization initiatives.
So what truly drives me is the passion
for transforming how organizations
deploy and manage software in production
environments, and helping teams to move
more fragile manual processes to robust
automated systems that can withstand
the pressure of modern business demands.
When I'm not immersed in platform
engineering or writing pipelines I love
following auto sports and I explore
a lot into the fascinating world of
autonomous automotive engineering and
innovation, which increasingly shares
my parallels with the self-healing
systems that we will be discussing today.
So let me start by painting a picture
of the critical challenge that we face
today because understanding the problem
deeply is essential to appreciate the
solution that we are going to explore.
The statistics here are quite sobbing and
they represent a real pain that many of
you have likely experienced firsthand.
When we look at the production
incidents across the industry we find
that approximately 70 percentage of
them are caused by deployment failures
using traditional CICD pipelines.
Think about that for a moment.
Nearly three quarters of the issues
that wake up your on-call engineers
in the middle of the night aren't
due to infrastructure failures
or external factors, so they.
Our cost by the very process we use to
deliver value to our customers even more
concerning is that the average meantime
to recovery for failed deployments without
automation typically ranges from two
to four hearts, which in today's world
represents not just the revenue lost, but
eroded customer trust and competitiveness.
So the fundamental difference between
traditional CICD and what we are calling
modern platform comes down to one word.
It's the technical posture.
Traditional approaches are inherently
reactive, where teams scramble to
fix issues only after they have
already broken in production.
This creates a cascading series of
problems where manual interventions
create delays due to human errors
or the problems that compound to
initial problems and pile up overtime.
Which increases the incident
fatigue and also degrades the
team's performance and moral.
So in contrast modern platforms
take a proactive approach where
self-healing systems detect and
resolve issues automatically.
So this isn't about replacing human
intelligence, it is about argumenting it.
Allowing our engineers to focus on
innovation rather than fighting fires.
Through intelligent automation we
can reduce oil, minimize downtime,
and maintain reliability at scale
in ways that were simply impossible
with the manual processes.
This brings us to the critical
question that will frame
our entire discussion today.
So how do we move from what I call is
deploy and pray to deploy with confidence?
So how do we build the systems
that are resilient by design, that
can detect problems early and that
can take corrective action faster
than any human operator code?
So that's exactly what we
are going to explore today.
So in today's session we've, it
is designed in a way to give you
both a conceptual framework and a
practical insights needed to architect
resiliency ICD pipelines using
Tecton and Argo CD that can truly
heal themselves when problems occur.
So we are going to present a GI ops native
approach to self-healing deployments that
stands on three powerful pillars, each
essential to the overall architecture.
The first pillar is observability
which provides real time visibility
into our systems health performance
metrics and deployment status
across the entire platform.
So you simply cannot
heal what you cannot see.
And the comprehensive observability
is where, is the key foundation
upon which all the self-healing
capabilities are built.
So we need to know, not just that
something is wrong, but we need
to know what precisely what is
wrong and how severe it is and what
the broader context looks like.
The second pillar is the automation,
which eliminates the manual
toil and human error through
intelligent policy driven deployment
processes and recovery mechanisms.
So this goes beyond simple scripts
when we are talking about sophisticated
automation that can make nuanced
decisions based on multiple signals.
And which can execute complex recovery
procedures and also maintain detailed
audit trails for every action taken.
So the third pillar is the AI integration
where mission learning, power decision
making is done from the patterns in your
specific environment, and it optimizes
reliability at scale over, over time.
So this is where the system evolves
from simply responding to known failure
modes, to predicting and preventing
issues that haven't even occurred yet.
So our overarching goal today is to show
you how to drive reliability at scale
across modern Kubernetes platforms while
maintaining the development velocity
and reducing the operational overhead.
So these aren't just competing concerns.
They are synergistic when approached
correctly, and that's the paradigm
shift that we are aiming for.
So let me walk you through the
roadmap for our session today.
So you know what to expect and can see how
each piece builds upon the previous ones.
We will begin with the GitHubs
GitHubs fundamentals exploring
why GitHubs provides the essential
foundation for resilient deployments.
And why you cannot build truly
self-healing systems without this
declarative, git centric approach.
From there, we will move into resilience
patterns examining the key use cases
and the real world scenarios where
self-healing mechanisms prevent
outages before they impact the users.
Next we will take a deep dive
into self-healing architecture,
unpacking exactly how deployments can
automatically detect problems and fix
themselves without human intervention.
So to ground this in reality we will
then examine an airline industry
case study, a learning from mission
critical systems where downtime is
quite literally isn't an option, and
where the stakes couldn't be higher.
Following that, we will explore AI
integration in depth discussing how
to implement intelligent automation
throughout your CICD pipeline,
practical, and in a more achievable way.
We will then talk through the high
level flow of the complete architecture
of self hailing deployments, ensuring
you understand how all the pieces
fit together into a cohesive system.
Finally, we will conclude with the
best practices and the key takeaways
giving you actionable strategies that
you can begin implementing immediately
in your organization regardless
of where you are currently in your
current DevOps maturity journey.
So let's establish our foundation
by understanding what GitHub's
really is, because there is often
confusion about this particular term.
GitHubs is a way of implementing
continuous deployment for cloud
native applications that focuses
on a developer centric experience
when operating infrastructure.
So fundamentally it means using tools
that developers are relat familiar
with, particularly git and continuous
deployment tools to manage not just the
application code, but the infrastructure
and the configuration as well.
So there are four core
principles that define GitHubs.
And understanding these is
very crucial to everything else
that we will discuss First.
GIT serves as the single source of truth
for everything in your environment.
So this means infrastructure definitions,
application configurations, and policies
and all and other configs are all
defined declaratively in version control.
Providing a complete audit
trail and change history.
So when someone asks who changed what and
when Git gives you the answer instantly.
And Immutably.
So GitHub's relies on
declarative configuration
rather than imperative commands.
So you describe your desire state, not
the steps to get there, but the system
automatically figures out how to achieve
that state and maintains it continuously.
So this is a profound shift from
traditional operations where we
execute sequence of commands and
hope they work correctly in order.
Third is the automated reconciliation
that ensures continuous synchronization
between your git repositories and your
cluster guaranteeing that the actual
state always matches the decide state.
So this isn't a one-time deployment.
It is a continuous process where
Drift is deducted and corrected
automatically maintaining consistency
without manual intervention.
And finally everything is
observable and auditable.
So you have complete visibility into
what changed, when they changed it, and
why that particular change was made.
So every modification is tracked, reviewed
through a standard development practice
like pull request, and most importantly
and completely, it is reversible.
And now why does GitHub's matter
specifically for resilience?
So there are several
compelling reasons for that.
First, it provides instant rollback
capability, meaning any deployment
can be rolled back immediately
with a simple git revert.
And no complex procedures or
lengthy runbooks are required.
Second, you get built in change
management where every change goes
through a peer review via pull request,
ensuring quality and knowledge sharing
before anything reaches production.
And the automatic drift direction
means that manual changes or
configuration drift are identified
immediately preventing those.
Frustrations like he, it worked yesterday.
Scenarios that plague pretty
much the operations team when
someone makes an undocumented
change directly into the cluster.
So GitHub's eliminates this entire
category of problems by making
it impossible for the cluster
state to deviate from Git without
being deducted and corrected.
Now that we understand GitHubs
conceptually, let's look at the
specific cloud native stack that
implements these principles.
In practice, the architecture
consists of four key components
that work together seamlessly.
So at the foundation we have
our Git repository, which
serves as the source of truth.
This repository contains application code,
infrastructure definitions, and Kubernetes
manifest that describes everything
about your desired system state.
So this isn't just storing files
and git, it is treating Git as the
authoritative of how your entire
system should look like and behave.
Next we have our CI pipeline, which in
our case is implemented using Tecton.
So tecton is a cloud native solution that
everybody is aware about which handles the
building, testing and security scanning.
Stamping of images and
image promotion workflows.
What makes Teton particularly powerful is
that the pipelines themselves are defined
as native Kubernetes resources, meaning
they follow the same declarative patterns
and benefit from the same operational
practices similar to your applications.
So in the CI pipeline is responsible
for taking code from developers,
validating it thoroughly.
And producing artifacts that
are ready for deployment.
Then comes the CD controller
implemented with Argo cd.
This is where the magic of
continuous reconciliation happens.
Argo CD continuously monitors your
plus state, compares it against the
design state, and GI detects any drift
that occurs and enables automated
rollback when health checks fail.
So this isn't just a deployment tool,
it is an active reconciliation engine
that always works in the background
to ensure that your cluster matches
your kit repository, which will
internally depict your desired state.
Finally, we have the Kubernetes cluster
itself, where applications actually run.
This cluster has an integrated
observability stack that is
built built along with it.
So that can include various tools
like Prometheus four metrics
Grafana for visualization and open
telemetry for distributor tracing.
So these tools provide the real time
insights that enable self-healing cap
capabilities feeding information back to
Argo City and other components so they
can make intelligent decisions about the
health and behavior of your applications.
So let's, let me walk you through some
real world use cases that illustrate
the power of GitHubs in practice.
Because these scenarios represent
problems that many of you
are dealing with right now.
Understanding how GitHubs solves
these specific challenges will help
you see where you might apply these
patterns in your own environments.
The first use case is an automatic
rollback on health failures.
So imagine a scenario where a
new deployment introduces a sub
subtile memory leak, and that
isn't caught during testing.
So in a traditional environment,
this plays out painfully, the
deployment goes out, memory usage
gradually climbs the application
eventually becomes unresponsive and
the ops team gets paged about it.
And they will have to diagnose the
issue, identify which deployment
cost it, and then manually roll back.
So on the onset, like this entire process
typically takes around 30 minutes or more
during which your users are experiencing
degraded service or even outages.
With GitHubs Argo CD is continuously
monitoring the health of your
applications against defined thresholds.
So when it detects the degradation
pattern, it automatically initiates
a rollback to the last known good
version in under two minutes.
How good is that?
So often before even users even
notice that there was an issue,
the system heals itself faster
than any operator could respond.
The second use case can address
configuration, drift deduction pictures,
a scenario where someone on the team
needs to make a quick fix in production,
maybe adjusting a config map to a
change to change a connection timeout.
They make the change directly in the
cluster with Cube CTL because it's
urgent, and then they fully intend
to update the Git repository later.
But when they get pulled into
something else and forget, it is
as equivalent to the situation
in a traditional environment.
So in a traditional environment, this
drift goes unnoticed until the next
deployment cycle when suddenly things
break because the deployment overrides
that manual change that was made by
the ops team and nobody remembers what
was changed or why it was changed.
With GI Ops, this manual config map change
is detected within seconds because Argo
CDs that the cluster state has no longer
matches the MA matches your GIT report.
It can either alert the teams immediately
or depending on your policies or
your settings automatically Argo
can reconcile back to the Git state,
ensuring that all change flows through
your proper change management process.
So the third use case tackles
multi environment consistency.
Addressing that classic term works
on my mission syndrome that has
plagued our industry for decades.
I hope you all agree with me on this.
You have all experienced the
scenario where something works
perfectly in development but
fails mysteriously in production.
Often this happens because the
environments aren't truly identical.
They are subtile
configuration differences.
Different versions of dependencies
and manual changes that were made in
one environment but not the others.
With GitHubs the same Git commit
is promoted through environments
ensuring predictable behavior.
So your production deployment is
using exactly the same configuration
and manifest that worked in staging,
eliminating an entire class of
environment related failures.
So let me continue with three
more use cases that demonstrate
the breadth of problems that self
failing GI Ops systems can address.
So these scenarios go deeper
into the kinds of runtime
issues that are particularly
challenging to handle manually.
The fourth use case specifically which
involves a dependency failure handling.
Like when a database connection
pool becomes exhausted.
So this is particularly not a good
scenario because it often happens
gradually under load when new
requests start failing because they
can't get the database connections,
error rates climb up, but the
application pods themself appear
healthy because they are not crashing.
They're just unable to
serve the request properly.
In a traditional setup by the time
someone notices and starts investigating
you might have already lost ground
on a lot of significant traffic
and customer transactions with Argo
City monitoring not just pod health,
but application level metrics like
error rates and response times.
Can be helpful in detecting this
degradation pattern and automatically
rolling back to the previous
version while simultaneously
alerting the team about the issue.
So the system recognizes that
something about the new deployment
is causing a problem with the
database connectivity, and it takes
a corrective action immediately.
In the fifth use case, we can, we
examine like the cannery deployment
failures, which represent a
more sophisticated failure mode.
So you have deployed a new
version using a cannery strategy.
Initially routing just a small
percentage of your traffic to the
new version while keeping most
traffic on the stable version.
During the cannery phase you detect
elevated error rates or increase
latency in the new version.
So in a traditional setup, someone has to
be actively monitoring these metrics and,
and, have to make a decision about
whether the difference is significant
and manually haul the rollout.
So this might require constant human
attention and introduces the risk
of missing the signal in the noise.
With GitHubs and proper health checks
integrated into your cannery analysis,
the system automatically hals promotion
when the cannery version shows
degradation compared to the baseline.
When the traffic stays on the
stable version, an alert is sent to
the team, which with the detailed
metrics about what went wrong
and the problematic version never
reaches full production in this case.
So here we are preventing a
situation where what could
have been a major incident.
The 60 use case deals with the network.
Partition recovery which is
particularly relevant for distributed
systems running across multiple
clusters or availability zones.
Imagine a scenario where a network
partition temporarily isolates
a part of your infrastructure.
During this partition, some automated
processes or operator might take
changes trying to compensate for
what appears to be a fail note.
When the partition heals, you
suddenly have inconsistent state
across your infrastructure.
So traditional systems can get into
very confused states during these
scenarios requiring manual intervention
to reconcile the differences.
With GitHubs, once the partition heals
Argo CD recognizes that certain parts of
the infrastructure have been drift from
the desired state in Git and automatically
reconciles them, bringing everything back
into alignment without human intervention.
So the system records from partition
automatically because it always
has get as the authoritative source
of truth that it can return to.
So now let's examine the
architecture of self-healing
deployments at a deeper level.
Understanding how the various layers
work together to create resilient systems
in this architecture is built with four
distinct layers, each with specific
responsibilities that contribute to
the overall self-healing capability.
The first layer is observability,
which serves as the sensory
system for your platform.
This includes metrics collection
through Prometheus, log aggregation
through Loki or the ELK Stack and also
distributed traces using ager or tempo.
Together.
These tools provide comprehensive system
visibility, allowing you to understand
not just what is happening right
now, but also the historical patterns
and the context around that event.
Without rich observability, self-healing
is impossible because the system
has no way that it can detect a
problem or verify the remediation
action that actually worked.
The second layer is the analysis
engine, which takes all the
observability data and make sense of.
This includes health checks performed
by Argo cd the SLO and the SLI
monitoring metrics that compares
actual performance against defined
objectives and anomaly detection
algorithms that can identify unusual
patterns that might indicate problems.
This layer is responsible for identifying
issues before they escalate into full
blown outages, giving the system time
to take preventive action rather than
reaching our reacting to failures.
So the third layer is the decision
and the action layer where the system
actually responds to detected problems.
So this includes auto rollback
capabilities through Argo rollouts.
Autoscaling through horizontal pod,
auto scalers, or vertical pod auto
scalers, or even using a Kubernetes,
even driven auto scalers too
which is otherwise called a cada.
These these tools can be
used and helpful for most
sophisticated event driven scaling.
And for traffic shifting we can leverage
service measures like TO or linker D.
This layer embodies the self-healing
capabilities taking concrete actions to
resolve issues automatically based on
the analysis from the previous layer.
The fourth and the final layer is the
GitHub's reconciliation, which closes
the loop by updating git with any
remediation actions that were taken.
Creating a complete audit trail of
what happened and why it happened.
So this layer also handles
notifications to the teams, ensuring
that while the system is healing
itself automatically, humans remain
informed and can intervene if required.
This creates a perfect balance between
automation and human oversight,
where routine issues are handled
automatically, but the team always
has visibility and the ability to
make manual control when needed.
Let me show you what self-healing
mechanisms look like in practice
by walking through a specific
example of health-based auto
rollback with a progressive
traffic shifting will look like.
So this will help you understand
the detailed mechanism mechanics
of how these systems operate
in real deployment scenarios.
Argo rollout is a powerful tool
that extends Kubernetes deployments
with advanced deployment strategies
like cannery and bluegreen.
And what makes it particularly valuable
for self-healing is its ability
to monitor cannery deployments.
With progressive traffic shifting
and automatically rolling
back when health checks fail.
So here is how this works in practice.
So you start by routing just five
percentage of your traffic to
the new version, while keeping 95
percentage on the stable version.
So during this initial phase, the
system is closely monitoring three
categories of metrics, error rates to
see if the new version is generating
more errors than the baseline.
Latency measurements that can to detect
if response times have degraded and
resource usage patterns to identify
if the new version is consuming more
memory or CPU than expected in any of
these metrics exceed defined thresholds,
the rollout is automatically halted.
The system doesn't wait
for a complete failure.
It detects degradation early and
stops the promotion process before the
problematic version can impact more users.
If the cannery phase looks healthy traffic
is gradually increased, perhaps to 10%,
then to 20 percentage, and then to 50%.
With all the health checks
at each stage of the.
This progressive approach means that
even if a problem only manifests under
higher load, you can catch it before
it affects your entire user base.
So looking at the sample code
on this slide, you can see how
this is configured in practice.
So we define a rollout
resource that specify cannery
strategy with multiple steps.
Each steps can set ic.
Traffic wait pause for a duration to
collect the metrics and run analysis
templates that define the health checks.
The analysis template references
Prometheus queries that check your
success rate against defined thresholds.
So the crucial configuration
here is the auto promotion
enabled, which is set to false.
Which means that the system won't
automatically proceed to the next step
unless the analysis passes and rollback
on health check failures when it is
set to true, which enables automatic
rollback if any health check fails.
So this mechanism also extends
to resource auto scaling.
So where the system can detect memory
or CPO pressure patterns and scale
horizontally by adding more pods or
by vertically by increasing resource
limits, and then return to the
baseline when the load normalizes.
So this prevents resource
exhaustion, failures, and ensures
your applications to handle traffic
spikes without any degradation.
Now I want to share a real world
case study from the airline industry,
specifically focusing on a flight booking
system because this represents one of
the most demanding environments where
self-healing systems prove their value.
So this case study illustrates both
the extreme requirements and the
dramatic benefits that can be achieved.
The challenge facing this airline
was multifaceted and unforgiving.
First, they had a requirement for a 99.9%
uptime, which translates to a maximum
of 4.32 minutes of downtime per month.
This isn't a soft goal, so this
is a contractual obligation tied
to the service level agreements
with partners and customers.
Second, they need, they needed to
handle the peak traffic that could
spike to 10 times normal load during
holidays and special promotions.
So when customers are mostly likely
to be booking travel and when the
business generates a significant
portion of its annual re revenue.
Third, the system operates across
multiple regions and must handle
regional failures gracefully continuing
to serve customers even when the
entire data centers become unavailable.
And they need to operate in a highly
regulated industry where every change
must be auditable for compliance
purposes, requiring detailed tracking
of who made what, change, when, and why.
So the traditional approach where
they were using before implementation
GitHubs was plagued with problems.
Manual deployments had to be
scheduled during carefully
planned maintenance windows.
Which meant they could only deploy
new features or fixes at only specific
times, limiting their agility When
problems did occur rollback procedures
took 15 to 20 minutes, which
sounds fast, but was far too slow.
Given their uptime requirements,
those 15 minutes could represent
thousands of failed bookings
and frustrated cu customers.
So they also struggle with the
configuration drift between regions
where manual changes in one region
wherein properly replicated to the
others, leading to inconsistent behavior
and difficult to diagnose issues which
is perha perhaps like more concerning
and human error during emergency
situations was at a constant risk.
So when engineers are under
pressure to fix a production outage.
Mistakes happen and those mistakes
can be expensive and can compound
more to the actual original problem.
So the solution this airline implemented
during GitHub's principles transformed
their operations in fundamental ways,
and the results speak for themself.
They implemented multi-region GitHubs
with a single GIT repository serving as
the source of truth and multiple Argo
CD instances deployed in each region.
So this architecture provided automated
regional fail load capabilities
and eliminated configuration
drifts between regions entirely.
Because every region was
continuously reconciling
against the same GI repository.
So they adopted a blue, green deployment
strategy that enabled true zero downtime
deployments, where the new version
is fully deployed alongside the whole
old baseline version, and it gets
validated thoroughly, and then the actual
traffic is switched over instantly.
So this approach provided instant
rollback capability because if
anything goes wrong, you simply switch
traffic to the blue environment,
which is still running unhealthy.
So the traffic shifting decisions
were based on real-time metrics, not
just successful deployment of the
pods, but also the actual evidence
that the application was performing
correctly under production load.
The cell feeling scenarios
they implemented cover a
range of common failure nos.
Sorry, modes.
They can automatically scale databases
connection pools when pressure is
detected, preventing the connection,
exhaustion issues as we discussed earlier.
And they also have auto rollback
configured for latency spikes where
if the new version shows increased a
response time, it automatically rolled
back before the customers before.
The customers notice the issue.
So they implemented an automatic
regional traffic routing.
So if one region becomes degraded,
the traffic is shifted to healthy
regions without manual intervention.
They even have a memory leak deduction
that can automatically restart pods
when memory usage patterns indicate a
leak and buying time for the engineering
team to implement a proper fix.
The results achieved were remarkable and
exceeded even their ambitious targets.
Meantime to recovery was reduced
from 20 minutes to 90 seconds.
More than a tenfold improvement
over six months of operation.
They had zero manual rollbacks
meaning every rollback that was
needed was performed automatically
by the system faster and more
reliably than a human could.
So most impressively they
achieved 99.995% uptime.
Actually exceeding their already
stringent target of 99.99%, which this
improvement translated directly to the
business value in terms of revenue,
and customer satisfaction maintained
at the highest level, and also focusing
on the operational cost reduced by
eliminating after our emergency responses.
So now let's explore the
artificial intelligence.
How artificial intelligence and
machine learning can enhance
self-healing pipelines, taking them
from reactive automation to truly
predictive and intelligence systems.
This represents the cutting edge
of where the industry is heading.
And while not every organization
will implement all of these
capabilities immediately,
understanding the possibilities
helps you to plan your roadmap.
Intelligent anomaly deduction uses
machine learning models that learn the
normal patterns of your applications
and can also detect anomalies
before they turn into incidents.
So this goes far beyond simple,
threshold based alerts, right?
For example, the system might learn
that your application typically has a
subtile increase in your memory usage
or time that resets each day, and it
can distinguish between its normal
pattern from a true memory leak.
So if it can identify a subtile
memory leak 30 minutes before they
would cause an out of memory error.
Giving the system the time to take
preventive action like restarting the pods
with the new version ready to take over.
So the predictive rollback takes this
step further by predicting the probability
of failure based on historical patterns.
So the system might analyze a new
deployment and determine that it has
85% similarity to a previous deployment
that failed, perhaps because it, it
changes the same components or had
similar performance characteristics
based on this pattern recognition.
Recognition.
It can recommend a rollback
before any actual failure occurs.
Essentially learning from the past
mistakes to avoid repeating them.
The intelligent cannery analysis
are just the analysis duration
dynamically based on traffic patterns
rather than using fixed time windows.
So if you're running a cannery during
unusual traffic conditions, perhaps
during a major sale or a traffic spike
from a social media, the system can
extend the cannery phase to collect more
data before making a promotion decision.
So this ensures that you have
statistically significant data to
make informed decisions regardless
of when you happen to deploy.
So the root cause analysis capabilities
can correlate metrics, logs, and traces
automatically when an issue occurs.
So it can generate hypothesis about what
went wrong with your confidence scores
and suggest specific remediation actions.
This dramatically reduces the time
engineers spend diagnosing the issues,
allowing them to focus on implementing
fixes rather than directive work.
So the resource optimization
uses historical data to predict
resource needs based on deployment
characteristics the time of the day
of the week, and other patterns.
The system can automatically adjust
HPA and VPA parameters to optimize both
performance and cost, ensuring you are
not over provision, over provisioning the
resources during low traffic periods or
under provisioning during the peak times.
So finally security anomaly detection
can identify unusual deployment patterns
that might indicate a compromise.
Or it can flag potential security issues
before they are being exploited and
automatically block suspicious deployments
before they can impact your environment.
So this adds an important security layer
to your self-healing capabilities as well.
So let me walk you through the
comprehensive framework for
integrating AI driven intelligence
into your deployment pipeline.
So this architecture creates a
continuous feedback loop that observes,
learns and heals automatically.
And understanding how these
pieces connect together is
essential for the implementation.
The first phase is a continuous
monitoring phase where we collect
metrics logs and traces in real time
from all the components of the system.
So this includes tracking health checks
to ensure pods are responding correctly
monitoring the service level objectives to
measure whether they, we are meeting our
reliability objectives and also observing
resource usage patterns and establishing
baseline behavior for what normally it'll
look like in a specific environment.
So this baseline is crucial because
normal looks different for every
application and organization.
So the second phase is anomaly
deduction, where AI and mission
learning models compare the current
state against the established baseline.
This uses both static thresholds for known
failure conditions and dynamic pattern
reorganization for more subtle issues.
So the models are continuously learning
of what normal looks like and can
identify deviations even when they
don't cross predefined thresholds.
So this catches issues at the
traditional alerting might miss.
So the third phase is the risk
assessment, where the system
can calculate the probability of
failure based on multiple signals.
It determines the severity and the
potential impact of the directed
anomaly and decides whether to simply
monitor the situation, alert the team,
or take immediate automated action.
So this decision tree prevents alert fat
from false positives while ensuring real
issues that gets immediate attention.
So the fourth phase is the
automated remediation when
recovery actions are executed.
This might include triggering auto
rollback through Argo CD to return
to a known good version, dynamically
scaling resources up and down or down
to address the capacity issues or
shifting traffic away from problematic
instances or restarting the pods while
ensuring that no good images are used.
So these actions happen in seconds, far
faster than any human could respond.
So the fifth phase is the
GitHub's reconciliation, where the
system updates the Git with the
remediation actions that were taken.
Creates a comprehensive audit trail
showing exactly what happened and
why it happened, and also notifies
the team with detailed analysis
including metrics, logs, traces, and
recommendations for long-term fixes.
So this model ensures that automated
actions don't happen in a black box, but
they are fully transparent and auditable.
So the sixth and the final phase
is continuous learning, where the
outcomes of all the actions are
fed back into the AI models to
improve their accuracy over time.
The system redefines thresholds and
policies based on what works and
what doesn't continuously improvising
deduction accuracy with each instant.
So this creates a virtual cycle
where your self feeling capabilities
become more effective the longer
they, effective the longer they run.
So as we think about implementing
these self-healing systems there are
four core architectural principles
that must guide your design decisions.
So these principles ensure that the
self failing capabilities are reliable,
trustworthy, and continuously improving.
The first principle is the continuous
loop creating an unbroken cycle
of observe, detect, and then
decide, act, and then learn.
So this isn't a linear process
that ends after remediation.
It is a continuous cycle that
enters constant vigilance
and ongoing improvement.
So the system is always observing.
Always ready to deduct and
respond to issues and always
learning from what happens.
The second principle is full
automation for common failures,
so no human intervention.
No human intervention should
be required for routine issues
that the system has seen before.
The system responds instantly to
known patterns, preventing incidents
before they impact the users.
So this doesn't mean humans
are remote from the loop.
It means they are freed from the toil
and can focus on more novel problems
and strategic improvements rather than
fighting the same fires repeatedly.
The third principle is
complete auditability.
So every action must be recorded and
git and your observability tools create
by creating an immutable history for
compliance and debugging purposes.
So when, sometime when something happens
you can trace back through the entire
chain of events to understand exactly
what occurred, what decisions were
made, and what actions were taken.
So this is crucial, not just for
compliance, but for building the
trust in your self healing systems.
The fourth principle is self-improvement
where AI models learn from each
incident and continuously refine their
understanding and response capabilities.
Over a period of time, the system
doesn't maintain a static set of rules.
It evolves based on experience becoming
more accurate and detecting issues
more effective at as they resolve
them, as it encounters more scenarios.
So understanding the high level
journey from deduction to resolution
is critical for implementing
effective self hailing systems.
So let me walk you through the
practical steps for building these
capabilities in your organization.
So start with observability because you
simply cannot heal what you cannot see.
As we discussed earlier, before
automating anything implement
comprehensive metrics collection.
Log aggregation and focus
more on distributed tracing.
Define clear service level objectives
and service level indicators
that represent what healthy
looks like for your applications.
Ensure that you have the visibility
needed to detect the problems
quickly and understand their impact.
Many organizations make the mistake
of jumping straight into automation
without establishing proper observability
first, and they end up with the
systems that take automated actions
based on insufficient information.
Move to gradual automation rather than
trying to automate everything at once.
Begin with a manual roll gate in your
pipeline so humans can review each
deployment, add auto rollback, or for
your most critical services first.
Where the value is highest and
then the stakes are greatest.
As your team builds confidence in the
automated behaviors and refines the
health checks and thresholds, expand
the automation to more services.
So this gradual approach prevents
automation from making things
worse and allows your team to learn
and adjust as you go test your
healing capabilities explicitly
using chaos engineering practices.
And also intentionally inject failures
into your system to verify that
auto recovery works as expected.
So this might feel uncomfortable at first
breaking things on purpose, but it is far
better to discover problems with yourself
feeling pipelines during a controlled
test than during a real instant.
Practice your instant response
procedures during these chaos
experiments so the team knows what to
expect and how to intervene if needed.
Also maintain human oversight toward,
throughout the process thoroughly.
And initially, AI should suggest
actions and human should decide whether
to take them, audit all the auto
automated actions to ensure that they
are appropriate and they are effective.
Also maintain manual override capability
for unexpected scenarios where automated
responses might not be appropriate.
So the goal isn't to remove
humans from operations.
It is to argument human capabilities
and allow people to focus on
the problems that truly require
human judgment and creativity.
So to conclude, let me share some
best practices that have proven
essential for operational excellence
when running self-healing pipelines.
So these guidelines come from a real
world experience and represent patterns
that successfully organizations follow.
So GitHub's hygiene is
foundational to everything else.
Make small, frequent commits rather
than large and risky changes.
Always have better practice to write
clear commit messages that explain not
just what changed, but why it changed.
Providing context for the future
ERs implement proper branch
protection rules so no one can push
directly to production branches.
And also adjust the rules in your repo
to have code review for all the changes.
Treating infrastructure and
configuration with the same rigor where
you apply to the application code.
And these practices might seem
like a overhead initially, but
they do prevent far more problems
than they cause in the longer run.
So the progressive delivery practices
should be universal rather than
optional, and always use cannery or
blue-green deployment strategies.
Even for services you consider low risk
because you never know when a change
will have unexpected consequences.
So start with your low risk services
to build confidence and refine
your practices, and also monitor
closely during early deployments
and be prepared to adjust the
thresholds based on what you learn.
Gradually increase the scope of
automation as your team becomes
comfortable with the patterns and con
and confident in the health checks.
Documentation and runbooks
might remain essential even in
highly automated environments.
So document all self-healing behavior
so everyone on the team understand
what the system will do automatically
and and under what conditions.
Create detailed runbooks for h cases
that require human intervention.
Also share those learnings and
insights across teams to so that
the knowledge doesn't stay siloed.
Maintain UpToDate troubleshooting
guides that explain both how to work
with the automated systems and how to
make a manual control when necessary
and continuous improvement should be
baked into your culture and processes.
And also review incidents and near misses
regularly so that even the ones that
were handled automatically to understand
if there are deeper issues to address.
Tune the AI models based on actual
outcomes rather than assumptions.
Iterate on thresholds and policies.
As you gather more data about your
specific applications and usage patterns.
Conduct what is regular like regular
meetups with the team or like
regular retrospectives where the
team can discuss what's working, what
isn't, and what could be improved.
This commitment to ongoing improvement
ensures that your self-healing
capabilities become more effective
over time rather than stagnating
and getting stuck at a point.
I hope this session has given you both,
information, detailed information and
practical guidance for building the self
hailing CICD pipelines in your own stacks.
And I would love to connect with you on
LinkedIn to continue this conversation,
share ideas and experiences and support
each other as we all work toward
more resilient, reliable systems.
Let's stay connected and stay in touch
and learn from each other's journey.
That's my time.
Thank you for your time
today and con 42 for this.
Thank you Con 42 for this excellent
opportunity to share my experiences
with the DevOps community.
Cheers.