Speaker 23: Hello.
Good morning.
Good afternoon everyone.
Thank you for tuning in for the talk.
I wanted to talk about something that
probably keep a lot of us up at night.
Our CACD pipeline, we have spent
the last decade perfecting them.
We have got them deterministic.
We have got them fast.
We have gotten them reliable, and now
we have got a new variable in the mix.
The big question isn't
just how do we use it?
How do we actually make AI work in our
pipelines without breaking everything?
Because right now I see a lot of
teams trying to figure that out,
and honestly, it's terrifying.
You have a non-deterministic,
probabilistic agent trying to control
a deterministic infrastructure.
It's like oil and water.
Let's figure that out.
So why am I spending time on this top?
Why involving you in this journey?
For the last decade and a half,
I have been the guy getting the
calls when production goes down.
I started my career in an I ages of
ops debugging, dash being print jobs.
COBOL scripts have lived through
every shift, starting from the
manual batch script to puppet.
From VM to Kubernetes, I build
infrastructure at Meta where
I learned the religion of move
fast, especially at scale.
I saw what happens when you out
thousands of engineers to deploy.
Constant code has scaled platforms
at Wayfair, handling millions of
requests where every millisecond
count, every millisecond is a dollar.
I safeguarded high value transactions
at JP Morgan Chase and AM American
Express, where the rule was never failed.
I learned the cost of caution and
necessity of absolute pressure, why my
whole career has been one long argument
between speed and safety, and now with
generative AI entering the ops world.
The augment is getting even more louder.
Why is this relevant right now?
Because we are at a tipping point.
Every tool vendor is selling AI ops.
Every CIO wants gen AI integration,
but nobody talks about the
governance required to make it safer.
I want to share this car, but I collected
and the solutions that I have built, so
you don't have to learn the hard way.
Gen is how I propose.
We settle the argument between
speed and safety one and for all.
So let's look at the industry right now.
It's a bit of a paradox.
On the left, you see the promises.
McKenzie report says 88% adoption.
This is how many of us are.
Deploying AI right now.
Not piloting, not testing, deploying ai
right now, we are all changing that 55%
productivity boost that the benchmark as
a benchmark that co-pilot had promised us.
We want the speed.
We want to ship features
before our coffee gets cold.
But look at the right side, the price.
It goes to $13,000 per minute.
That's the average cost of a
production outage today or 2,100 hours.
That's just the recorded diamond plan.
Downtime of a major
platform like Jira in 2024.
And here is the number.
That's case me 7.2%.
The Dora report of 2024 says that
there is a drop in delivery stability
for the teams rushing to adopt ai.
Think about that.
We are coding 55% faster, but we are
breaking production 7% more often.
We are driving a faster car,
but we have taken off the seat
belts and the reason is simple.
We are trying to fit unpredictable
random agents into the pipelines
designed for a predictable binary logic.
This slide captures most, most
of the things especially the
deadlock we are currently in.
This isn't just a technical problem, it's
an existential one for DevOps at least.
The first one is unpredictability.
Let me walk you through an example
running a bad script today.
Exit code zero means successful tomorrow.
Running the same bad script.
Exit code zero means still
successful six months from now.
It is still successful.
Exit core, zero means successful.
But if you ask LLM to
optimize the Docker file.
Three times, fingers crossed, you
get three different qua files.
And in CACD pipeline variance isn't
a feature, it's a bug, it's a noise.
The next is the dis disruption.
Then human makes a mistake.
They usually break a feature,
maybe add to card button, click.
But when an AI makes a mistake.
Especially with an infrastructure access,
it doesn't just break the feature,
it demolishes the whole platform.
I seen this happen firsthand.
I was an AI agent originating
a Terraform resource division.
It just looked at a legacy service and
authentication handler and decided that.
It was unused because there
were no, any recent commits.
It tried to delete it.
That service authenticated
20 million users.
That wasn't a bug, that was a potential
to regionwide outage waiting to happen.
The only reason it doesn't, it
didn't happen is because we caught it
manually, but that almost movement.
Kept me up for a week.
The rec, reconciliation,
speed, and safety.
So we are stuck here.
Security teams try to flip the block
switch because they are terrified.
Developer find workaround
because they need speed.
We need to break this standoff.
So how do we do this?
To fix this, we have a fundamental, we
have to have a fundamental change in
our mental model of what, and AI is.
On the left is a legacy ai which
most of us are be using, and I'm
sure most of us have used it co-pilot
or co-piloting IPE or chat bots.
It's an external helper.
It has zero accountability.
If the code it suggested breaks
the bill, you broke the bill.
It's not the ai.
It's a tool like a fancy spell
checker on the right where
you need to go to generals.
This is a model, basically a
set of system practices or a
set of system principles that.
I suggest it's a pipeline
actor, basically.
It has a service account, it has
permissions, it triggers bill, it
can apply code, it opens its own pr.
I know it sounds terrifying, but
giving LLM as service account,
giving it the key of the kingdom.
But think about it.
How do we onboard a junior engineer?
We don't just give them a road access
on day one, we give them a sandbox.
We give them, you review every pr.
You don't let them deploy to production
on a Friday at a 5:00 PM without
supervision, gen ops is simply applying
the same rigorous mentorship model.
To our AI agents, we treat them as
employees that need supervision,
not the tools that needs running
to through the supervision.
I call it as four pillars of governance.
Think of this as a distal nervous system
of the AI contextualization, which
is basically a memory you use a rag.
Not just for docs, but for build history.
AI remembers every failure,
so it doesn't repeat it.
It need to know how we do
things here on our earth.
That is, we define the blast
radius of every change.
High risk means stricter rules.
We don't treat.
It typo.
The same as a database
migration can redeployment.
We never trust the AI fully.
We let it prove itself on a 1% traffic.
First.
Runtime assurance.
We need an immutable auditory
three basically for every thought
and every decision that AA makes.
Now, let's get deeper into each of them.
The context of air ingestion.
This is basically a flow where
we provide the context to ai.
The biggest failure or the
biggest mode of failure for AI
and DevOps, is it hallucination?
It's a lack of context.
How much of information do we provide and
how much of information can an EA use?
When it comes up with its next token,
it doesn't know what, it doesn't
know if you ask an AI to update the
payments, API, it uses its training data.
Maybe the data that, that it was
trained in 2024 or 2025, it has no
idea that you have already deprecated
the version to work at the last month.
So we build a system that acts
like an organizational memory.
We stack our extracts, build logs,
incidents, postmortem, incident
postmortems, slack threads, outages.
Basically we ize all of them.
And when an AI.
Prepares for deployment.
We intercept the prompt.
We inject the last 50 relevance build.
We inject the current
infrastructure state.
So AI isn't just guessing, it knows,
oh, last time someone tried to change
this config, it caused a memory leak.
We are effectively giving AI a
short-term memory to complement
its long-term training data.
This simple step eliminates about what
I call it as 95% of stupid errors.
Now let's move on to the next pillar.
Context helps, but it
doesn't guarantee safety.
AI is still probabilistic.
It can still take risk, so
we need strategic guardrails.
We introduce a concept
called blast radius score.
Before any code merges, we
analyze the dependency graph.
We ask if the change falls, how
big of a crater does it form?
Is it just a read me the blast?
Radius is one.
Go ahead.
Automat the code.
Are you changing a core authentication
library used by 50 other microservices?
The blast rate says 90% block it.
This requires human sign off.
We map this to an something
we call it as an error budget.
So what is an error budget?
Your login service, that's the critical
path, has a very tiny error budget.
Almost zero.
Zero tolerance.
The AI is on a thing.
Lease your internal admin
tool like your Wiki pages.
It has a huge error budget
outage of one hour or two hours.
It's fine.
They can experiment more freely and.
To make this more deterministic, we use
open policy agent OPA to enforce this.
The governance isn't a
PDF policy document here.
It's a code, it's a Boolean gate,
basically pass or a fa now let's talk
about the third pillar deployment.
Most team use gallery.
Okay, but they use the
canary in a very dumb way.
They just time wait for five
minutes, increase the traffic by 10%.
This is not engineering.
This is basically a hope.
Our canary is an SLO based.
We deploy for 1% traffic, a tiny slice.
The AI monitor its own rollout.
It watches the latency error rate.
CPU.
Memory IO operations.
If the latency drift by even two
standard deviations, the automatic
rollback triggers instantly.
We don't want a customer
to complain on a Twitter.
We don't wait for a PagerDuty alert.
The system kills the bad deployment
before human even wakes up.
We are shifting from
a mean time to repair.
To meantime of prevention.
So the pillar four, which is governance,
and for all the security folks who tuned
in, this is how you sleep at night better.
In a traditional audit, who means the
person who call, who created the change
in gen ops, who is a neural network model?
That creates a complaints nightmare.
So we built a centralized model registry.
Every single line of a code, every
config change generated by an
AI is cryptographically signed.
We record the exact model version.
Was it A GPT five, 5.1,
5.2, Florida 4.1, 4.5.
The exact prompt that was used, the
context chunk that was injected, this
creates an immutable audit trail.
If a vulnerability appears six months
from now, I can run one single query,
show me every service modified by Model X.
Using the prompt wire, I can trace the
thought process of the infrastructure.
Auditors are going to love this
because it actually makes more
transparent than a human change.
So this slide is the real
story, 55% faster cycle time.
And I want to be clear, this isn't just
typing fast, this is removing friction.
The AI handles the heavy lifting
config updates, the boiler plate
test, the documentation sync.
These are the things that drain your
senior engineer at Meta have built a tool
that turned a multi-hour onboarding task
into a five minutes automated flow, saving
95% of a reduction in operation overhead.
This means that your senior engineers
stop being a Yammer or a Jason spearhead
and start being an architect again.
And the governance, because policy
is a code, it cannot be skipped.
A tied engineer at a 2:00 AM
might choose to bypass a check.
AI cannot everyone.
Allows the zero incident.
That's great, but look
at this number, 14.4%.
This is the protection rate.
14.4% of the times ai, despite of
all of context, prompt engineering
tried to do something dangerous.
He tried to push a change
that violated an SLA.
He tried to merge a dependency
with the vulnerability.
Without gen ops, this 14.4%
would have been an outage.
They would have been panic, there
would have been revenue loss.
Instead, they are just sitting in a
log saying that blocked by governance
layer, the mechanism work, the immune
system that is built blocks the virus.
This proves that.
Safety and velocity are in opposite.
The only reason we can move fast
is because we know it's safe.
There is a safety net of 14.4%.
Okay, so what are the next
set of frontiers to summarize?
Why our current tool system isn't
enough Static code analysis.
This is something that only
checks for the code addressed.
It catches bad syntax, but
it misses the bad intent.
It looks for SQL injection vulnerability,
but it doesn't look for an end point
trying to delete the whole table.
Anomaly detection is reactive.
It tells you the house is on
fire after the smoke starts.
Gen ops is proactive.
We act at the moment of generation.
We evaluate the intent of the change
before it even becomes a full request.
We shift left past the bill, past the
commit, all the way to the thought.
And this is the blueprint.
It's a continuous learning loop
monitoring, basically the eyes
we watch, the AI proposals,
the system state analysis.
We run the blast radius calculation.
We check the Policy Engine Act, which is
basically the, or the governance layer.
We execute through a safety hardness.
AI never touches the production directly.
Learn the feedback.
Every time we block that 14.4%,
we feed it back to the memory.
The system learns from
its own near mistakes.
It gets smarter on every failure.
So we are getting close.
If you live here with three things.
Make them these three things.
Governance, ai, AI as a pipeline actor,
and embracing closed loop systems.
So when I say governance, when, let
me talk about an example, like breaks
in a Formula One race aren't there?
Just to make it slow.
They're there.
So that the driver can go 200 miles,
300 miles without any injuries.
Governance gives the confidence to speed.
The next is ai.
Stop treating AI like a text editor.
Treat it like a junior engineer.
Give it a badge, give
it its limit and audit.
Its well.
Embraced closed loop system, the day
of fire and forget scripts are over.
We need system that self monitor, self
correct, and learn from the mistakes.
The future of DevOps isn't just
about deploying code faster,
it's about deploying intelligent.
Safer.
We are building the nervous
system of the enterprise.
Let's make sure that it has
a brain, not just reflexes.
Thank you so much for your time.
I love to hear your horror
stories, success stories in a
chat comment, or on LinkedIn.
Let's learn from each other.
Take care.
Thank you.