Speaker 16: Hi everyone, my name is
Justice and welcome to my TED Talk.
I'm the co-founder and CT EO of Meta
Stable Labs, and we are building the very
first margin layer to prediction markets.
Before this, I worked as a senior
software engineer at Pay Stack and for
Context, pay Stack is like the biggest
payments company in the whole of Africa.
And just a few years back,
it was acquired by Stripe.
So at Pay Stack, I spent years building
and operating systems that processed
hundreds of millions of dollars
in transaction every single month.
So it's safe to say that I've been
on both sides of the story, building
features that look great in staging
and then watching production teach
you lessons you didn't ask for.
So today I'm going to talk about what
actually breaks in high traffic systems.
Why it breaks and the technical
habits that keep things
running when things go wrong.
And I'll try my best not to bore you guys.
And and I'll try not to
make this a shopping list.
Actually, I'm not going to
make it a shopping list.
So I'm going to talk about failure
mechanisms be because those
are like the same whether you
are on AWS or GCP or whatever.
So the promise of reliability.
So let's start with a simple truth.
Most outages don't begin with chaos.
They begin quietly.
And the problem is teams or
engineers usually look for chaos.
They expect an outage to say stuff
like service went down, or 500 errors
everywhere, or their terminal, all in red.
But real incidents at
scale start slowly, right?
So they often look like requests you
succeed, but on a slower pace, your
queues slowly grow and time out, creep up.
And while all these things are happening,
your metrics still look okay, right?
And then suddenly everything collapses.
So the real question isn't how
do we prevent all these failures?
The real question is how do we keep
the system stable while it's failing?
So let me say tell you guys
like a realistic example.
Let's assume is a normal
day at work, right?
Traffic increases.
Maybe you guys launched a new feature.
Maybe it could be a marketing
campaign, whatever it was.
So everything looks fine
for the first 20 minutes.
Then one dependency starts slowing down.
So it could be Postgres on the
heavier read or right operations.
It could be your red is getting hot.
It might even be a third party pro, a
third party provider with limiting you
because of all this whole new traffic.
You get one API request, for instance,
it calls service A calls your db,
which is proposed grace, and then
after that it calls service B.
Service B calls another service.
Now, if one dependency, if one of
these service gets slower, every
other 10 is affected, so your
average query time grows from.
A 15 milliseconds to
about 150 milliseconds.
So everything still works, don't get
me wrong, and it won't feel like a
disaster yet until you actually do
the mats in modern systems one user
action can trigger multiple calls.
Example, if a user loads the
dashboard on the front end.
And it calls the backend, which
in turn calls six internal tools.
For instance, each of these tools or
service hits the db, and if one starts
slowing down, it affects everything.
So if you have, let's assume you
make six calls and each has about
100 milliseconds cell latency, you
find out that your one will request.
Becomes 600 milliseconds very quickly.
And believe me when I say this,
several latency is the real killer.
Most teams look at average latency.
Average is going to light
to you at scale, right?
Average high stereo pen.
So if P 50 is 100 milliseconds, for
example, but P 99 is five seconds, users
are going to feel that five seconds not.
The 100 milliseconds.
So if you do enough requests, someone
is always living in that P 99.
Now the system becomes increasingly slow.
Developers then those what
feels reasonable, the add ries.
So what happens is the clients
retries, the service retries, the SEK
retries, everything attempts to retry.
Now, instead of making one request,
you are making two or three.
And here is the trap retries don't
reduce loads, retries, multiply,
load at the worst possible moment.
And this is called a retry storm.
So it turns slow dependency
into a dependency death spiral.
And this is how a quiet incident
becomes a full outage nest.
You hit the nest failure mode, which
I call connection, poor exhaustion.
If postgre grows sorry, if
postgre queries are slower.
That means connections stay longer and
your pool quickly grows to 50 connections.
Now on normal conditions, request complete
fast and connections return quickly.
But now queries take about 10 x longer.
So those 50 connections
are basically stuck.
Now you have incoming requests, right?
But then they keep piling up.
Because they're waiting
for the last co connection.
So eventually your service still looks
up, but it's effect effectively frozen.
Nothing works.
Your CPU might look fine, your
memory might even look fine, but your
system is essentially now a zombie.
So at this point, timeout starts firing.
And this is where many
systems are poorly designed.
Example of a bad timeout
behavior like could look like.
It doesn't time out at all.
So we request Hank forever or
timeout takes too long so you wait
30 seconds and block everything else.
Or it could also be that timeouts
don't cancel work at all.
And this last one is huge.
If you time out the request, but
the expensive query keeps running.
You have built a systems, a system that
bonds resources, doing work nobody needs.
So now users we try manually, right?
Clients also retry the services.
Also try to retry as well.
But all these retries are being called.
The DP instead is still doing work
for already canceled requests.
You get the points right?
So this is how systems die.
Politely.
No explosions just slowly ation slowly.
The whole system dies.
So when this is happening,
let's be very clear.
Your goal during an incident
is not to do a root.
Analysis to find out what's happening.
Your goal first is to stabilize
the system and protect us users.
So you want the system to shed load
degrade grace, fully stop doing
unnecessary work and become stable.
Only then do you try to find
out what happened, right?
So how do we actually do this?
I'm going to walk you guys through
some steps to step pattern the.
I use at work.
The first step is to limit concurrency.
High traffic systems fail when
they accept infinite work.
So one of the most un undirected
stability tools is this.
We only process any
number of these at a time.
Simple.
Make sure to limit concurrent requests.
Pine points, you can limit concurrent
DB queries and other stuff as well.
So this is basically
called a back pressure.
It stops the system from melting
itself, so it's better to return
a 4, 2, 9, 2, many request, or
even a quick, please try again.
Done to accept everything and
collapse because when you collapse,
everyone just soft suffers.
The next step is timeout,
but done properly.
A good rule for this is timeout should
be short, consistent, and layered.
Client time, sorry.
Client timeout might be
two to three seconds.
For a user request service to service
timeout might be 500 milliseconds to maybe
1.5 seconds depending on the endpoint.
And here is the most
important key timeout.
Most cancel work.
If a request times out, stop
doing any expensive work for it.
Cancel or pending DB queries.
Stop downstream costs, basically stop.
Everything for that particular re request.
So this one habit prevents
so many death spirals.
Now circuit breakers.
A circuit breaker means if a
dependency is failing or slow,
stop calling it for a bit.
This prevents your service from
spending all these resources hammering
something that won't recover.
It also creates like re recovery space.
So we have some space to
actually recover, right?
If you do this right, you prevent
cascading failure and protect
your own service from being
dragged down by sick dependency.
Now, the parts that suppress mature
systems from fragile ones is graceful
degradation during such scenarios.
Some features should
turn off automatically.
Not everything is equally important.
Example, in a payment infrastructure, we
all agree that authentication is critical.
Placing an order is also critical,
but something like a recommended item
widget somewhere is probably not.
So knowing this, you should
build the system to degrade.
You could self cashed data or return
partial results or even turn off
non essential stuff in payments.
For instance, if your analytics pipeline
is slow, you do not block payments.
Instead, you degrade worth
failing, not this transaction.
The next step is load shedding.
This is being intentional about failure.
You can shed load by rejecting
request early, dropping non-critical
background task sampling logs
instead of logging everything.
A line I always repeat all the
time is, it's better to fail
fast than to fail slowly because.
Slow failure destroys your system fast.
Failure keeps you alive.
And this essentially completes the
list of things I feel you need to
do next is things to watch out for.
So most teams have monitoring, but in
incidents, they don't know what matters
in the high traffic system, for instance.
You need to track four 10
like your life depends on it.
Latency, traffic, errors, and saturation.
And for latency, you need to
track percentiles, not averages.
So you want to see P 50, P 95, P 99,
and for each of these, you need to
see the error rates, the Q depth.
The DB connection usage, the trade
usage, the downstream core latency,
and so on, because incidents often show
up first as saturation, not errors.
And here is how quiet incidents show up.
So let's assume P 50 is stable.
P 95 creeps up a little bit.
But then P 99 spikes, right?
So what happens is Q Depth slowly grows.
DB connections approach maximum limits.
Our retries also increase as well.
Then suddenly everything breaks.
And when this happens, the right
alerts shouldn't be is the CPU high.
The right alerts should be.
What's the bond rate of P 99?
What is the Q growth rates?
What is the error budget bond?
What's the DB connection pool like?
Is it nearing exhaustion?
Marshall teams are lot on trends,
not bond rates, not raw thresholds.
So when things are failing,
loss alone won't save you.
You need to take one request
and ask where did this go?
And I call that a
distributor tracing, right?
Even if you have, even if you
don't have food tracing you
should do the basic things, right?
So you should know where you should check
the, for correlation IDs, structural
logs consistent timing and so on.
Then you can see, so in.
Instead of having like normal logs
everywhere, you could actually
see how long your API call took.
How long did it take service A to
get a response from the db, right?
Where exactly did your query get
stuck and so on, and this is how
you move from panic to diagnosis.
So let me say something controversial.
Many outages are not
prolonged by bad code.
They are prolonged by messy response.
I've seen in incidents where up to five
engineers are deploying fixes, right?
Nobody owns it.
Nobody knows what change.
Every fix introduces a new variable.
So yes, a simple step by step playbook.
I feel like we work.
I know we work.
The first one is name an incident lead,
so someone needs to be the coordinator.
That's very important.
The second one is freeze non-essential
changes and stop random deployments.
Totally stabilize the system.
You can do this by re reducing
loads, disabling some features
stop retries and so on.
The fourth one, so you can
attempt to restore safe services.
You can do this by rolling
back to the previous working
fashion or working deployment.
You can reduce the blast
reduce, for instance.
And the fifth one is only after stability
do you investigate the root cause.
The goal is to make incidents
boring, not exciting.
If you want reliability, you
don't start during the outage.
You start before the outage.
You design with failure in mind.
That means in dependency.
So when client clients re retry,
your system must not double charge or
double create, or even double execute.
And this means you should have
queues for expensive work.
Don't do heavy work in line in
the same re requests, right?
It also means bulkhead one failing
part shouldn't sink the entire ship.
Separate pools and resources
for critical parts.
It also means with limiting you need
to implement a with limit to prevent
your system from abuse and spikes.
And I'm going to end with this.
High traffic systems don't break
because engineers are careless.
They break because complexity
compounds faster than intuition.
And the most dangerous
incidents are the pirate ones.
The slow dependency, the creeping
cues, the retry storm, and so on, until
production becomes a fight, right?
If you want your system to
survive at scale, you must
put hard limits at on work.
Use timeouts that cancel.
Add circuit breakers degrade gracefully,
she load intentionally and so on
because production will eventually
test every assumption you've made.
And the goal isn't to avoid that test.
The goal is to build systems
that take it, that can take
it and recover without drama.
And this is the end of my presentation.
Thank you for listening.
You can reach out to me on
LinkedIn if you have any questions.
Thank you.