Speaker 18: Hello folks.
I'm Kian and I'm working
as a tech credit Oracle.
I'm here to talk about the most critical
challenges in modern platform engineering.
So how to execute a massive
infrastructure migration without
dropping a single customer request.
So the goal isn't just to replace the
old system and to with the new system.
The goal is to design for the jro
downtime, any enterprise, any high
high throughput saan environments.
This is not just a nice to have feature.
This is this is a commercially imperative.
So we are going to talk about a, I'm
going to talk about a case study.
So on how we successfully migrated a
critical legacy gateway to a modern,
highly available architecture.
The transformation was executed without
a single single service interruption.
The so this and this, the, this
case study has proven that a
complex infrastructure migration
can be possible with zero downtime.
So let's start by defining why we
have zero tolerance for downtime.
So when you process billions of
requests and using a platform, and
if you want to replace the platform
with the new platform, like you need
to copy all the functional, all the
functionality of the old system onto
the new system without any disruption.
So the.
The risks involved with that is
people usually use the synthetic
testing on the old system, and
like people write the synthetic
test, like unit test and integrate
integration test on the old system,
and they replay it on the new system.
And once the test pass, they
simply cut the traffic from
the old system, new system.
So that solution doesn't work if we have.
If you have a lot of undocumented changes
in the old system and there is a lot of
tribal knowledge in that went in there.
So what's the solution here?
So we realized that automated reliability
engineering and continuous validation
using actual production traffic like.
We'll work like these are the methods
to prevent service interruption.
So this led us to a strategy of a phase
rollout combined with advanced shadow
traffic validation framework that we
need to te that we use to test the
production traffic a safely and yeah.
So let's look at the system
that that we have to replace.
So the system that we are trying
to replace is a legacy monolithic
gateway based out of Ruby and ra.
So it has a session management and
authentication and authorization logic.
And also routing all together, jammed
in one in one service, in one monolith.
So the risks so associated with
this monolith is the blast radius.
One change in routing will, will, could,
if a routing, if there is an issue with
routing changes, that could severely
impact other concerns on the same service.
And there were also resource
concerns like the ruby and Symetra.
It's an open source and it
wasn't an advanced gateway.
So it is not leveraging the multi-core
compute resources that we've been using.
And also if at all we need
to scale a single concern we
have to scale this uniformly.
So that is a scalability issue as well.
And there was also an operat.
The operational risk was also mounting.
There was less expertise in the
in the company with the ruby.
And also there were a lot of
security vulnerabilities and yeah.
And these all these are the reasons why
why we want to replace a, this legacy
model with the modern architecture.
So the tight couple route architecture
was the root cause of our scalability
issues and and the operational risk.
The tight doubling of concerns meant that
like I said earlier that a minor update
to routing could impact could break the
authentication stack and vice versa.
And there was also a scalability
inefficiency as well.
And and this is training
the computer resources.
If at all we need to scale a
concern at the peak traffic, we
have to scale this uniformly.
So our objective was clear transition
to a modern enterprise gateway and
decouple the concerns while maintaining
the continuous service availability.
So by, we need to migrate this complex
service safely without any downtime.
So this is where the real challenge began.
So migration, like what are the
migration challenges and and validations
that that what are the challenges
and what are the validations that,
that, I'm gonna talk about them here.
Undocumented legacy behavior, like
moving away from the, like the
sea bottle to the new gateway.
There was a lot of.
Undocumented changes in the Legacy
Gateway where traditional testing
cannot catch if we run the test
cases on the new system and.
And then most danger dangerously.
And earlier I mentioned, we are
gonna use a shadow traffic or shadow,
replay mechanism to run the parity.
There the performance impact
was there, there could be
performance impact with that.
So if this shadow I I'll deep
dive into this shadow shadow.
Traffic framework in the latest slides.
So there was a performance issue
I'm gonna talk about like, how did
we overcome that performance issue.
So the performance impact is one, and
another one is like we need to come
up innovatively come up, came up with
a, which I work around to to skip
the double execution of the request.
And other one is we want to offload
the authentication logic to, to a
different independent microservice.
So these were the challenges
with the migration.
So let's dive into how the validation
the chart of framework will work.
This is the core technical
innovation that actually enabled
the downtime zero downtime with a
state marketing charter framework.
So we had to solve the double
execution problem as well.
So our solution was based on replay
mechanism that works in five steps.
There was a processor
on the legacy gateway.
And that processor whenever a, the Legacy
Gateway receives a request, it usually
process the request and by forwarding
the response back to the client, this
gateway will actually asynchronously
use a processor to run the parity.
So this processor will actually
copy the customer request and file
it on the new con gateway system.
And before firing that
it'll create a parity id.
And it also saves the downstream
response and also the client downstream
request and also the client response,
both of them in a NoSQL store.
And it fires the same request
with a, with the added query
parameter called parity id.
And it replace on the new system.
So when Congress use it, Kong.
Should do the same thing as the
Legacy Gate West does, and it
should forward to the downstream.
So to avoid if the request if the rest API
call is is read, then there is no issue.
But if it is, other than read, we
want to skip the double execution.
For that reason, we just.
We deployed a interceptor
on the backend system.
So whenever backend receives this request,
the intercept will, interceptor, will kick
in, and inter, whenever interceptor sees
the power DID, it basically reduce the.
Like downstream response from the cache.
And it, it responds to the Kong
gateway and Kong gateway operated
back to the legacy gateway.
And when everything is in place,
the, all of this the processor
built, run the parity and save the
differences in a NoSQL store pack.
So now now let's look at it.
I'm gonna talk about what are
these differences and all of
that in the latest slides.
So now let's look at how we
implemented this framework
across the in the migration.
Okay.
So the migration is it's an
eight phase implementation work.
The first one is planning
and provisioning.
We used a I used a Terraform and
and all of the routes in the old
Kite way have been coded in the,
in, in the YAML format for the conc.
And all the infrastructure
changes, everything.
We I used Terraform to, to document
for the deployment, and that's where
the planning and provisioning went in.
And once we have it ready I I
did the, they were benchmark
test results from Kong.
So we used them and we did I did some
of the low testing and then we, we
deployed Kong Kong as a separate cluster.
And then the next step is shadow
framework shadow framework,
like the validation part.
So here, the validation part.
While validating in the validation
basically we cannot validate entire
production traffic because if we
validate entire production traffic,
the traffic will double and the back.
We also have to.
Scale the backend, backend or downstream
systems to handle all of the traffic.
So for that reason we we sampled
we sampled the one fifth,
like one fifth of the traffic.
It gets replayed on the New Kong gateway
so that if we run this over the period
the, based on the probability, the
assumption is that all of the a p routes
and all of the functions will be covered.
So that's the idea here.
And the next step would be.
Authentication offloading.
So the plan is this one is a bigger topic.
So this we, I had followed the, taken
the similar approach to, to offload
this authentication and authorization.
Let's select to simplify that.
The next step is offload
the authentication.
Consent has been offloaded
to a new microservice.
And then and then testing.
Like I said earlier, we use the
sampling and we just replayed the
month, the traffic, and and after
that if this has been like once
the, once there are no differences.
We had incrementally rolled out and.
I rolled out the traffic from
Old Gateway to the new Gateway
and then we did the final cutover
and then retired the old gateway.
So that's the eight, eight phase
implementation framework that
we followed for this migration.
So let's look at now how the.
How that shadow traffic, like what has the
shadow traffic validation has revealed?
Okay.
We jumped little bit,
so the shadow traffic
findings were most critical.
So because because.
They revealed they're gonna reveal
the hidden production behaviors
and whatever the synthetic test
has has completely mi might miss.
So we performed two, two key verification.
First, we looked at downstream
system verification, downstream
request verification comparing the
request payload Kong sent to the
backend against the legacy system.
The legacy gateway was sent to
the backend, and another one is.
Client response validation, like what
the legacy gateway has been forwarding
to the clients for the same request.
And also how what Kong is
sending back to the clients.
And and the next one is
progressive sampling.
Like I said the plan was to
not run on entire traffic.
Rather to sample the traffic, like one
fifth of the we use a random function
to to divide the request id, and based
on based on that, like we implemented a
sampler to sample the traffic and so that
the processor will not run, replay the
request for for every every production
request is sent replay on the new system.
So using U using this.
So these results were used for the,
before the final to make any corrections
in the new gateway and before cutting
over the real traffic to the new gateway.
Let's look at operational
impact and benefits.
So the ultimate measure of success
for this project is that we achieved
zero customer facing incident despite
processing millions of request.
This wasn't just about downtime, it
delivered tangible business benefits.
We saw a cost reduction, 20% cost
reductions in the compute resources
because using the modern architecture.
Furthermore we deployed a vendor supported
platform that the vendor supports the
security vulnerabilities patches and there
were a lot of out of the box features that
comes from the vendor supported gateway
and also, like we were able to and the
vendor gateways it, it's compliant with
security so we don't have to do additional
work when it comes to the security.
So it is compliant.
And there were side effects
like automated deployments and
crucially the new architecture has
reduced the meantime to recovery.
And there were automated rollbacks
making the system more reliable.
So let's talk about that.
New architecture and fundamental changes.
Fundamental changes like
we can build and scale.
So let's dive into that 40% cost
efficiency because it is directly,
it is a direct result of moving
away from monolithic architecture.
The biggest driver was
independent scaling.
We no longer had to scale the entire
heavy ruby stack just to handle the
lightweight authentication checks.
By decoupling the authentication
workload we optimized the
resource allocation dramatically.
And secondly, we elevated the ruby
bottleneck, like not being able
to use the multi-core, and we got
more work out of less hardware.
And finally, we saw a massive
reduction in operational overhead
and vendor supported patches and
automated deployment pipelines.
So the efficiency gain was just one
time save wasn't just one time saving.
It is continuous benefit that, that is,
that funded the that, that is, that will
be funding the future innovation as well.
Let's look at the broader
architecture benefits this, that,
this transformation has unlocked.
So the architecture shift is foundation.
Now the authentication op concern
can independently scale and there
were multi-tenant capabilities.
And also we don't have to dual migration.
If the company brought in, another
acquisition or so like it, it
has multi-tenant capabilities for
suppose in the use case the company
acquired, bunch of other companies.
So we were able to use the same same
platform to route the traffic to their
backend services once the companies
merch and regarding compliance also,
the it is simplified because of because
of the vendor support and also we were
able to use the latest libraries, e
even if the vendor doesn't support,
we were able to apply patches if there
were any security vulnerabilities and
there was engineering velocity as well.
Because because we don't have to because
we are, we minimize the blasted Yes.
And.
And the number of unit tests that we
run when we deploy a change to a K two,
when we're deployed authentication the
meantime has substantially dropped.
So this has improved the velocity
of the engineering team as well.
So let's say like, how did we execute
it without a dropping a single request?
Let's see.
In the next slide.
So on what are the, what are
the key key success factors?
I.
Definitely the shadow traffic validation
is the is the key factor for the success.
And another one is incremental rollout,
just to avoid any just to reduce the
blast radius if something goes wrong.
And the infrastructure as a code.
The Terraform using Terraform
has speeded up the, planning and
provisioning of the new gateway easily.
And then automated analysis, like in
the traffic validation part, the we
were automatically able to evaluate
the differences between the old and
the new gateway and able to quickly
fix the problems in the, fix the
functional issues in the new gateway.
And then.
And then, yeah, phased implementation.
This phased implementation also
helped us maintaining the production
stability and and the throughput and
the transition, like we basically
reducing the blast radis as well here.
Here we are gonna talk
about the lessons learned.
The success factor we just covered
are around just a PA gateways.
They form a universal difference
or a blueprint for any complex
model to microservice transition.
The big key, key takeaway is that
for legacy system, the validation or
testing is the superior is superior.
It's, it definitely helped us.
The synthetic test, all of this would
have helped, but definitely would
have given the confidence that we
got from the validation and we have
also learned about the store on the
forward pattern is crucial for the
risk management and it also decouples
execution from the actual backend state,
ensuring that like the shadow traffic
doesn't execute one request twice.
And finally the validation
results also helped us to fix
the problems in the new gateway.
So yeah these lessons are
applicable whether you are.
Like these lessons will help not
just with the like I said the
authentication authorization concern
was separated from the legacy gateway.
We using the same pattern.
So this is not just for gateways.
This can be applicable when you're trying
to migrate any backend infrastructure any
backend rest a p kind of infrastructure.
So this can be applicable there as well.
And what does this mean for the future?
So in, in conclusion, this case study
validates the complex infrastructure
transformations can be executed while
maintaining while strictly enforcing the
service level objectives, we prove that
phase rollout and the traffic validation
enables a truly seamless migration.
The business impact was substantial.
We achieved zero downtime, delivered
over 20% in infrastructure cost
reductions, and significantly
enhanced our security posture.
This project provided a comprehensive
methodologist for industry demonstrating
like how to execute high stakes
migrations without service disruptions.
Yeah the core key takeaway
is invest in automated.
Automated reliability engineering and
the validation framework for these
kind of migration patterns or to
modernize any backend infrastructure
that, that relates to this pattern.
Okay.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Now I'm open for any questions and also.
Just in case, if you if you don't agree
or if you see any improvements just
find me on LinkedIn and connect with me.
We can chat over there.
Thank you.
Thank you for thank you for having me.
Bye.