Speaker 36: Hey.
Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining me at
conference 42 DevOps 2026.
My name is Ravi ba Ari from NetApp.
Today I'm excited to talk.
You talk to you guys about scaling
microservices development, a
shared cluster for developers to
deploy their work and effectively
delivering the SaaS work.
Before we go there, a
little bit, report about me.
I'm a lead software engineer
and architect at NetApp based
off of Greater Boston area.
So I've been with NetApp around 10 years.
Been working on SaaS
products from the beginning.
So I have experience in, developing.
Deploying and shipping the SaaS
products different features.
I've been working with Kubernetes
from about seven years.
So we ship the products like Argo CD
and GitHubs driven rapid deployments.
So we have very strong
platform and everything.
So most recently I've been
into more into ai, but this
presentation is a lot more about.
DevOps there is a little
bit of AI we will see.
So let's just jump right in.
Okay.
As microservices promise, scalability,
modularity, and rapid innovation.
Perfect.
For modern SaaS platforms.
Teams can deploy services independently,
enabling faster feature delivery.
But in reality, managing this environments
for development and testing is a nightmare
because there are hundreds of services.
Even a small change requires
thorough regression testing, leading
to complex workflows, cross team
coordination issues, and slow velocity.
Traditional methods just don't
scale efficiently, right?
So in the traditional module,
we have dedicated clusters.
We resource waste the
resources because of that.
And provisioning these
services is pretty slow, right?
So let's take a look at your
visual representation of it.
Typical, a traditional setup is
you have, on the top you have this
cluster with all the services deployed
of say, a hundred services, right?
You deploy a feature branch in it.
You take it for testing, you do all
the development in it and deliver off.
Once you're done and you keep doing
it, sometimes you don't do anything.
You keep these clusters that's gonna
take more out of your pocket, right?
They come with high cost and
you have alternate approach
of say, can rebuilds, right?
So let's see why they
don't work as well, right?
So they're designed for production
rollouts, not for development.
Because most of, mostly you have just
one can redeployment not as many as
you want or as many feature development
features you're gonna develop on.
And it is complications with stateful
services because when you have a can
rebuild, you can only manage up to
a certain threshold of complexity.
You cannot go beyond that.
So that's another problem.
And then what is the alternative for this?
So that's what I'm gonna talk about today.
So we are gonna use namespace
based smart isolation, right?
In a shared cluster.
It provides full safe separation
for any number of feature branches
simultaneously, while still sharing
unchanged services efficiently.
So I'm calling it STDP, right?
It's actually, just the name can
call it anything but the scalable
development deployment platform.
It uses namespace for isolation and
shared clusters for secure environments,
dynamic routing with the ingress and
with the wildcard routing and whatnot.
And also network policies
and other things.
We are gonna go a little
dive a little deeper into it.
This balance is the
speed, cost, and safety.
So let's take a little look at it.
So when a developer pushes a feature
branch the idea of ity P is automatically
creates a dedicated namespace and
applies your helm over rights or WhatsApp
or alternative for those and giving
each branch its own URL for testing.
So you have single cluster
but multi-tenancy, right?
And the proposed architecture, if
you see is so you have those shared
baseline cluster with all the unchanged
services, which are common across
all your feature branches, right?
It can be for some, it cannot.
It might be unique for some, right?
And then you have multiple name
spaces for each feature branch, and
you deploy only modified services
are the dependent services, right?
So that's the base idea a little.
Simplified, but we will talk a little
more details and you'll get an idea.
So the traffic routing is the key here.
So you use ingress rules, which are
generated and are dynamic and are with
wild card, and you do some flexible
verifications switch routing to test
against staging our production data by
leveraging compatible waste line setups.
So that is also a flexibility, so meaning.
You wanna switch between different
databases you can easily do here.
So that's also one benefit, right?
Without having to do, deploy
or, migrate the databases.
So that's also a good thing.
So on top of it, a web based portal will
make things more easy to use, right?
So I have a working demo.
I'll show you guys at end.
For now I'm just showing
you snippets, right?
Let's see.
Yeah, so at a high level
STTP has three layers.
A management portal for orchestration
and visibility, a service layer
integrating with CICD via helm and
Kubernetes infrastructure layer.
Optimizing for multi-tenancy, right?
A web-based development
portal simplifies this store.
Developers, qa, product owners can create
sandboxes, select baselines, and auto
generate namespace and ingress manifest
and network policies that they want to do.
And this portal fosters collaboration by
sharing feature previews across the teams.
Meaning, people can share their demos
across the teams, they can access and
they can see how the new feature is.
And just any other shared cluster, and
not just that, but also a place for you to
look at all the features find it easily.
The approach integrates
with CICD pipelines, right?
That's obviously key.
Where baseline baselines, auto
update you keep on updating your
baseline services with say production
or staging the way you want it.
And deploy feature branches.
Only when you have changes.
So there are like basically
these three layers, right?
Now just to demonstrate so you
initiate cluster, so names, network
policies, ensure feature name spaces
cannot talk to each other, only to
approve baseline services, right?
So the idea behind that is
you'll have an isolation between
these services, which are.
Modifying and they only talk to baseline.
That makes sure that you do not have
collision of services and you keep as
if it's a standalone service, right?
So that's the main point
of network policies.
You have to make sure that have
that you contain it, otherwise
you'll have complicated issues.
Okay, so the.
Payoffs, let's talk about that.
So you have a steam streamlined
development with less overhead because
you can just go to that portal, add create
new clusters, shared clusters, and start
making changes, push them, having qa,
test them, and review them with the PMs.
And all these things are like,
run the automation suit on
it and do whatever you want.
And then at end, once
you're done, you can just.
Simply get deleted.
So it's actually cost effective.
And the consistency in the
environment makes it easy for
you to switch between things.
And you also the earlier
I said the database, which
is also very useful, right?
So the SEC security is
also a good looking.
Up update your, role-based access, your
a Ws clusters and network policies.
You can add centralized secret management.
You can make sure that
there is no collision.
So those are the things
you need to take care.
So there are some issues with this,
with the specialist stateful sets.
Some configs are the
secrets et cetera, right?
Or you have some S3 bucket
blob storage or whatnot, right?
That is one of the challenge challenges.
So the most services are, stateless,
very easy to isolate most of the time.
But these services, which are the
outliers like the databases, ces,
and block storages introduce a side
effects if they're fully shared.
For example, somebody's trying to
add a new column that is not needed
are they're expecting a certain
column, which does not exist.
Or you are basically
corrupting the database, right?
So that's basically the biggest
problem in a shared cluster that you
might have already thought of, right?
So this risk include like data
corruption and interference across
the branches, which is not something
you would want to see, right?
That's not exactly how the production
or production with Cango, right?
So how do you balance.
The isolation for a safe
testing with efficiency, right?
So we handle this with
smart change analysis.
So the, you scan branches dev branches
the diffs of the dev branches to
detect stateful impacts, right?
If it's just a new endpoint with no
schema change, share the database.
If there is a migration, replicate
it to the namespace, right?
Tools include namespace, as for
segregation, ingress are service
mesh for routing connect connection
strings and cash isolation
via keys are instances, right?
So automation is a key.
So what I mean by that is, you can
manually select, pick and choose which
service needs to be replicated, which
service can be used by the shared service.
But if you can automate it with AI
now, because the LMS are getting
pretty smart and you can write a nice
agent that can pull all the diffs for
different repositories and figure out.
How the dependency can be and if
they need to be deployed separately,
meaning any straight full set, straight
full service are, do they have to
do, can they use a shared service?
So based on your change,
it can figure that out.
So for example, you have, imagine
you have three services, a front
end and a PL layer, like a middle
layer and a database, right?
So you made a change.
You added a new API.
End point and does not modify or add a
new table or column or example, right?
So you can just spin up a new API service.
Don't have to even replicate a UI service.
So you can still use a shared UI
service, shared database service, right?
You can just change the you can just
deploy the a p service, just one
service out of all three, right?
So imagine the same situation
in hundreds of services, so that
would save you a lot of time.
So the analysis in a little, if you wanna
visualize it, how it goes is, so first
you start analyzing the code changes.
So find out impactful
stateful services, right?
And then you can figure out which
service needs to be replicated in
the namespace, and which services can
be shared from the baseline, right?
And then based on these decisions, you
can create your ingress routing, right?
And then once you decide what
you wanna do, you can deploy.
So this is just a code simple and a
pseudo code to see how we can do it.
So figuring out if you have to create a
replica or can you use a shared service.
Yeah, so the platform in, so
for example, this is a dynamic
connection string routing where
we're on a variable injection.
So you can figure out, dynamically
add which route you can use
with the ingress routes.
And you can probably embed, you can
play with some environment variables
or you can have your portal or your
service that can add the manual routes
to the ingress, whichever works.
So resource quotas, just to make sure
you don't have some bad feature that
is hogging all the compute you have.
Just make sure you don't forget
about resource quotas, right?
Just, and that also helps you
contain any damage that they could
do in terms of, slow systems, right?
As I said.
You'll have to integrate with
the CICD pipeline for this.
So whenever you have a commit
trigger, you can build packages.
And as soon as you do that, you can
write an, you can talk to A-C-D-P-A a
PS to deploy the service or the changes.
And by analyzing what needs to be done,
and then you test and validate, you run
your automation suit for that, right?
Yeah, I've been using, by the way
this solution in NetApp in my team.
And it's been quite useful, right?
So it's saving us a lot of time.
The build happens.
You have the major study, as soon as you
deploy it, it's done in a second, right?
There is no provisioning needed.
You don't need to talk.
You can spin up new
clusters on the time of.
All the time whenever you need, and
you can just delete them if you're
not using it, so you just, when you're
testing, you just spin it up or you're
done testing, you just delete it.
You are not gonna keep it for a long time.
So your testing cycles
will be shorter as well.
And we are utilizing your resources
at the maximum efficiency possible.
So that's a big achievement, I would say.
So this enhances the
team collaboration too.
And some considerations
we already discussed.
So resource quotas, ingress
strategy and data management.
We talked about it.
You can add additional logging and
analytics on top of it and observe better.
So that's also something you can do.
So how do you adopt?
So before we go into adoption I would like
to show you some demo more quickly and
then we can just talk about some things.
Next steps that you guys can take, right?
So first, let's take a look at
this.
You guys can, okay.
I hope you guys can see.
Alright, so this is I will share
you guys the code for this.
Let's see if this works.
No, it's not.
Let me go to my BS code
and start this quickly.
If you don't mind.
All right.
So you can see this, i'm just
reading this existing clusters.
You can see the portal here, right?
All right so the idea of this so this
is a portal where you're creating
the dev shade clusters, right?
So here I can pick my
feature branch, for example.
User auth.
So this is my dev branch, so I can
choose to deploy a service from here.
For example, I choose to deploy just the
front end and the backend, not the a PR,
maybe just the a p not the backend, right?
And deploying it.
So you can see it's gonna deploy.
It's not provisioning a new cluster.
The cluster already exists,
which is a shared cluster, right?
So you can see now my demo
is up and running already.
Okay, so I launched it.
Let's see, what are we gonna get?
So you can see it says, I have deployed
a frontend service, which is user
auth and it has a backend service.
So let's figure out which backend
services by calling those API calls,
you can see that backend is the
default, which is the baseline.
But the a PA services from user, so
let's take a step back and let's do
the backend this time, but not the API.
So security auth.
Sorry.
Security patch.
And I deploy this one.
So let's see.
Once we have this up and
running, let's just launch it.
That's up.
Okay, so this is security patch,
and this time let me call all the
services so you can see now this time
baseline, EPA services, the baseline,
but the backing services, security.
Patch branch, right?
So UI front end is anywhere.
Security patch, right?
So you can deploy just the backend as
well, but you get the idea now, right?
So now I have the code base here.
I'll share the link with you guys.
This is just implementing a part of
the solution, but there's more to it.
A real solution requires
a lot more, right?
I can quickly take you guys with
the code, but I think I'll give you
access to the code as you can see.
But let me show you another
interesting thing, right?
Yeah.
So this is the rancher desktop.
I'm using my desktop for this.
So you can see the ingress routing.
I just wanna show you an example, right?
So we just created those feature
branch features deployments, right?
So you can see that, yeah, the
security patch is deploying both
frontend and the backend, but
the user odd branch is actually
deploying frontend and API services.
Only the routes are in routed like
this, but you also see the default
routing for the API to be the
base API and the backend to be the
base backend so that these feature
branches are routing properly, right?
So you get an idea.
So this is the, basically
the magic sauce on top of it.
You need so many layers
anyways but that's the idea.
So now let's talk about
the adoption, right?
So adoption is not easy if you
want to do it at once, right?
It has to be in a phased manner, right?
So pick and choose which services
are best suited, so put them in the
shared ones, which are easy to do.
For example, you have a UI
service, very easy to do.
Some services, very few dependencies.
They're easy to do.
There's some which are ful ones,
you wanna replicate them until you
get to a position where you can
actually share them as well, right?
And then you automate it.
You add the security and all the
things, and then keep scaling it.
Migrate one service at a time.
Yeah.
So this definitely transforms
the development workflow.
It definitely is gonna be very
useful for all the people.
And I have been using the solution that
I deploy across the teams Q and pmm.
They've been very happy with this and
I've been maintaining it from six years.
Keep on doing patches and updates.
The solution that I proposed is a
lot more complex one in this demo.
In this presentation, but, I
think that you get the idea.
Okay.
So your DA deployment portal is the
key, your command center for you.
You can make it, custom
tailored for you, right?
And then, yeah I think the
remaining slides are, pretty
much what we spoke earlier.
The demo you have seen just now,
and if you have any questions.
Do definitely send them across
to me, either via LinkedIn or my
Twitter or ex. So yeah, it was nice
presenting my idea to you guys.
I hope you like it.
If you have any feedback it is very
valuable to me, do share with me.
Thank you so much.