Speaker 4: Zero human AI
collaboration for reliable embedded
automotive control systems.
Reshaping driver assistance through
human-centered AI integration
Conference 42 DevOps 2 0 2 6.
The speaker introduction.
Raja Govin, army Senior Manager
Electronics r and d. Products INC
specialized in embedded automotive
control systems and AI integration
for safety critical applications,
leading research initiatives in human
machine collaboration and advanced
driver assistance technologies.
The challenge, the limit of traditional
automation, rule-based systems.
Excellent, predictable
scenarios, but struggle with
dynamic real world conditions.
Static decision logic cannot adopt to
realtime perception, prediction, and
involving environmental complexity.
Third one, limited context.
Lack situational awareness and
driver state monitoring capabilities.
The solution framework, human-centered
collaborative architecture, ai, and the
human cognizant operating as complementary
patterns rather than competing entities.
One, MULTISENSOR Perception, camera,
radar, and lidar fusion for comprehensive
environmental awareness two.
Driver state monitoring, gauge
tracking, physiological signals
and behavioral analysis.
Three.
Dynamic authority adoptive
allocation between human and AI
based on context and readiness.
The validation methodology, one.
Simulation testing.
Controlled virtual environmental
testing, thousands of edge cases,
scenarios and failure modes.
Two controlled experiments.
The laboratory settings with
the instrumented test tracks,
measuring precise system responses.
Three.
Naturalistic driving real world
validation across diverse conditions.
Driver popul license and
traffic patterns results.
Measurable safety improvements.
One.
The critical incident reduction.
Significant decrease in land departure
events across all test conditions,
lower collision rates in both simulated
and rail Scenarios, smoother takeover
behavior during authority transitions,
human factors, more calibrated driver
trust levels reducing over reliance.
Improved situational awareness
during automated driving.
Reduce the cognitive load
during complex driving tasks.
Multisensor perception performance,
future architecture significantly
outperforms signal sensor approaches
across environmental conditions.
Camera.
High resolution visible data for land
marking and object classifications, radar,
all weather velocity on the distance
measurements with penetration capability.
Lidar, precise 3D, spatial map for
obstacle detection and path planning.
The next one is driver state
classification Accuracy.
Advanced monitoring system achieves
90 percentage of accuracy in
detecting critical cognitive states,
one fat detection gauge pattern,
and physi physiological markers.
Two distraction reorganization.
Behavioral cues and attention monitoring.
Three.
Readiness assessment, realtime
capability evaluation.
The system architecture for model
productive and control integration,
the realtime performance,
multi second scale control.
Loom execution, maintaining
safety critical responsiveness.
The multi objective optimization
balances, competing demands, safety
constraints and avoidance, passenger
comfort, and right quality, energy
efficiency and system, long duty
regulatory compliance requirements,
multimodal feedback, architecture.
Diverse communication channel, reduce
cognitive load and improve respond
times during critical transitions.
One, the visible displays had some
displays and dashboard indicators
providing situational context,
auditory alert, the spatial audios,
cues, and voice notifications for.
Time critical information, haptic
feedback, steering wheel, and
seat vibrations for INT two
directional guidance, dynamic
authority allocation one.
Contact assessment, continuous
evaluation of environmental
complexity and risk factors.
Two.
Readiness monitoring.
Real time driver state analysis
and the capability determination.
Three.
Adoptive handoff seamless authority
transfer, preserving safety and
driver agency, the applications,
real world implementation scenarios.
One.
Intent aware, adaptive cruise control.
Predict driver our intentions and adjust.
Following distance based on traffic
flow and driver preferences.
Cooper V two V Coordination, vehicle
to vehicle communication extends
perception range beyond sensor
limitations and improves traffic
flow Efficiency DevOps integration.
The safety critical deployment
strategies are three.
One continuous validation pipelines,
automated testing frameworks, ensuring
regression free updates and maintaining
safety certification requirements.
Two system observability, realtime
telemetry, anomaly detection and
performance monitoring across
distributed fleet deployments.
Three, human-centered deployment.
Gradual rollout strategies with the
driver feedback loops and adopt to feature
enablement based on acceptance patent.
From automation to augmentation, the
future of automotive control systems
lies not in replacing human drivers,
but in merging machine position with the
human intuition to create more adaptive
and transparent mobility systems.
One machine perion Melissa
can react some times.
360 degree awareness,
consistent performance.
To human intuitions, contextual
understanding, ethical decision
making, create new problem solving.
Thank you.
Thank.