Hello, everyone.
Thank you so much for joining me today.
I'm Saily, and I've been an
esthete for almost 10 years now.
Over the years, I have worked on testing
a variety of systems, especially in
cloud and serverless environments,
and I've learned a lot along the way.
Today, I'm here to talk about mastering
cloud and serverless automation,
the esthetes guide to success.
I'll share some key lessons and practical
tips that truly work in this field.
I'd love to hear from you,
your experiences, thoughts, or
anything I might have missed.
I'll share my contact at the
end so we can stay connected.
So let's get started.
way we build and deploy software has
changed dramatically with the rise
of cloud and serverless technologies.
This shift demands a new, more
adaptable approach to testing.
As esthetes, we need to evolve our
skills and strategies to stay ahead.
Mastering cloud and serverless automation
isn't just a nice to have anymore.
It's a must for ensuring applications
are reliable, scalable, and high quality.
In this talk, I'll share strategies,
tools, and best practices that
can help you excel in cloud native
and serverless environments.
These approaches will empower
you to become a key contributor
to your team's success.
So why is cloud and serverless automation
so important in today's tech landscape?
First, the cloud environments are dynamic.
Cloud Infrastructures change
and scale in real time.
Automation is essential for
testing and validating these
changes quickly and reliably.
Second, cloud native applications
have complex dependencies.
They often involve multiple
interconnected services, and testing
these systems end to end, without
automation, can be a real challenge.
And finally, it's also
about cost and efficiency.
Automation saves time by
reducing manual testing effort
and speed up release cycles.
Plus, identifying defects early
can significantly cut costs.
With this foundation in mind, let's dive
into how we can master this critical area.
Let's start with infrastructure
as code automation.
If you're working in the cloud,
this is a must have skill.
ISE, or infrastructure as code,
lets us define and manage cloud
infrastructure using code, making
deployments consistent and scalable.
However, misconfigurations can
lead to issues like security
vulnerabilities, unexpected costs,
and performance bottlenecks.
ISE validation ensures that infrastructure
is reliable, secure, and compliant.
So what tools can we focus on?
We can start with Terraform,
AWS CloudFormation, or
Azure Resource Management.
here's some advice on automating
infrastructure as code.
Validating before deployment.
write tests to validate your ISE
templates before deploying them.
Tools like Teratest can streamline
and automate this process.
Next, enforce standards.
Use linting tools like Checkout
to ensure your code adheres to
security, performance, and benchmarks.
These tools can help maintain
coding standards across the team.
rollbacks.
Set up automated rollback
mechanisms for failed deployments to
minimize downtime and reduce risk.
for drift.
Regularly validate infrastructure drift
to ensure your configurations remain
consistent with your desired state.
Now let's move on to API testing
for serverless application.
APIs are the backbone of
serverless systems, enabling
communications between services.
Testing them is crucial to ensure they
work reliably under various conditions.
Why is this important?
APIs connect distributed systems
and serverless architecture.
Without proper testing, issues
can ripple through the system,
causing major problems.
By testing APIs thoroughly, we ensure they
function as expected, even under stress.
what are some tools we can focus on?
There's Rest Assured,
Postman, Neumann, Karate, etc.
There are some really great tools.
our IDE approach, Automating API Testing.
Start with functional tests to check API
responses, payloads, and status codes.
This makes sure the basics are working.
Next, move to integration testing to
see how APIs work together seamlessly.
Use contract testing to validate
dependencies between services
and ensure everything aligns.
Try fault injection to test resilience
and error handling by simulating failures.
Don't skip on security testing.
Validate things like authentication,
authorization, and input sanitization.
Finally, use schema validation to
make sure APIs meet specifications
like OpenAPI standards.
Now let's talk about performance
testing and optimization.
Serverless applications bring unique
challenges, things like cold start,
concurrency limits, and scaling behavior.
These can impact your app's
performance and user experience.
If performance isn't optimized, your
app might struggle during traffic
spikes or leave users frustrated
by delays caused by cold start.
Performance testing ensures your
app is both efficient and reliable.
Tools like Gatling, JMeter, Artillery,
AWS X Ray are great options for
testing serverless performance.
So here's how I'd
approach automating this.
user test traffic to test impacts
of cold start and concurrency.
Monitor key matrix like latency,
throughput, and response
time under different loads.
Use distributed testing tools
to mimic large scale and real
world user scenarios effectively.
Analyze results to identify
bottlenecks and fix them.
Test for scalability to ensure your
system can handle sudden traffic spikes.
Automate performance testing as
part of your CICD pipeline for
ongoing monitoring and improvement.
Next, let's discuss observability
and monitoring integration.
This is a, this is critical
for keeping systems healthy
and resolving issues quickly.
Observability provides real time insights
into how your system is behaving.
Without it, finding and diagnosing
problems can feel impossible.
But with the right setup, you
can catch performance issues,
errors, or failures as they happen.
Tools like Grafana,
Prometheus, Elk Stack, etc.
are powerful options for observability.
So let's see how we can
approach automating that.
We can set up automated alerts to notify
us of performance drops or failures.
Using dashboards to track key metrics
like latency, error rates, and uptime.
We can integrate observability tools
into CICD pipelines for immediate
feedback during deployments.
Leveraging distributed tracing to
understand how services interact
and pinpoint bottlenecks also helps.
Automating log aggregation to
simplify troubleshooting and ensuring
compliance is also very important.
Now let's dive into.
CI CD pipelines for cloud environments.
They are essential for
modern software delivery.
CI CD pipeline automation
and testing, validation, and
deployment is all a key part.
They help deliver software faster,
more reliably, while reducing
errors and simplifying development.
There are tools like Jenkins, GitHub
Actions, Circle CI, GitLab CI CD, they
are widely used and worth learning.
So here's how I'd automate this.
Embed automation tests in your pipelines
to validate code quality and deployments.
Use infrastructure as code
tools to quickly spin up and
tear down test environments.
Use canary deployments to test
updates in a controlled environment.
Use blue green deployments
for zero downtime releases.
Automate rollback mechanisms to
maintain stability in case of failures.
automated security and compliance
check to ensure your system
stays robust and secure.
Next up is fault injection testing.
This is a proactive way to
improve system reliability by
simulating real world failures.
Fault injection helps us find weaknesses
in our system before users are affected.
By intentionally introducing failures,
we can validate recovery mechanisms
and ensure the system is designed
to handle unexpected scenarios.
Tools like Chaos Monkey, Gremlin,
AWS Fault Injection Simulator,
Litmus Chaos are excellent for
creating fault injection tests.
So here's how we can automate this.
Simulate failure scenarios
like network latency, timeouts,
or service unavailability.
Test for cascading failures in
microservices based systems to
understand how dependencies interact.
failure scenarios to validate
your system's recovery and
self healing capabilities.
capabilities.
Integrate fault injection tests
into your CICD pipeline to make
this a consistent practice.
let's move on to security automation.
This is a critical part of
modern testing workflows.
As systems grow more complex, automating
security processes is essential
to stay ahead of vulnerabilities.
Security automation ensures
compliance with standards, identifies
issues early, and protects your
application from potential attacks.
Thank you.
So here's how we can automate this.
We can validate APIs for authentication,
authorization, and input sanitization.
We can automate vulnerability scans for
infrastructure as code templates and
container images to catch issues early.
We can test for common attack vectors
like SQL injection and cross site
scripting using automated tools.
Integrate security checks in the
CICD pipeline to ensure compliance
throughout development and deployment.
let's discuss about automated environment
cleanup, a practice that's often
overlooked, but highly important.
In cloud environments, Resources can be
left running unnecessarily, leading to
increased cost in cluttered environments.
Automating cleanup helps reduce
cost, prevents resource sprawl,
and keeps environment consistent
for testing and deployment.
Tools like Terraform, Ansible,
AWS Lambda are excellent for
automating cleanup tasks.
So here's how we can approach testing it.
We write test scripts to identify
and remove unused cloud resources.
We use lifecycle policies to automatically
delete old snapshots or unused objects.
We can schedule cleanup jobs to
run after deployments or test
execution to keep environments clean.
We can automate tagging and resource
tracking to manage resources more
effectively and simplify cleanup.
So now that we have explored the
key areas to master, We can shift
our focus to strategies for future
growth and continuous learning.
These are actionable strategies that will
help you to grow and thrive in this field.
The first one is keep
learning and get certified.
Start by building a strong foundation.
Take certifications on platforms
like AWS, Azure, or Google Cloud.
To understand the basics of cloud
computing, Next, we can dive into
serverless frameworks like AWS
Lambda, Azure Functions, or Google
Cloud Functions to see how they
work in real world situations.
Next, learning a programming language.
Choose a popular language like
Java, Python, or JavaScript
and focus on mastering it.
These are essential for creating
scripts, writing test cases, and
building automation frameworks.
collaborating with DevOps team.
Working closely with
developers and operations team.
helps align the testing
with their workflows.
By understanding how they operate,
you can integrate testing more
effectively and ensure better results.
Last, trying out open source tools.
Exploring open source tools to expand
your skill set can be very helpful.
Tools like Open Policy Agent can
help with policy compliance and
serverless frameworks are great
for local testing and debugging.
pipeline.
Now let's look, let's look at some
best practices that can help us
approach cloud and automations,
serverless automations effectively.
First, start small.
Focus on automating one part of your
pipeline, like API tests, and then
gradually expand to other areas.
Starting small lets you refine your
approach without getting overwhelmed.
Next, fail fast.
Catching issues early in the
development cycle is key.
Prioritize early testing to save
time and prevent problems from
escalating further down the pipeline.
tests modular.
Writing small, reusable, and
independent tests is very important.
Modular tests make debugging
easy and allows you to quickly
adapt when your system changes.
security.
Make security a core part
of your automation strategy.
Automate checks for APIs, ISE templates,
and serverless resources to ensure your
system remains secure and compliant.
Optimizing costs.
Keeping an eye out for the costs
of running tests, especially in
the cloud, is very important.
Monitoring and managing these expenses
will help you stay efficient and
avoid unnecessary overspending.
By following these best practices,
you'll be build automation framework
workflows that are scalable, efficient,
and secure, creating a strong
foundation for long term success.
Now let's wrap up with some common
challenges in cloud and serverless
automation, along with practical
solutions to tackle them effectively.
big challenges with cloud
infrastructure is that it is dynamic.
It spins up and down on demand.
This makes it tricky to
keep testing consistent.
So what's the solution?
Using ephemeral infrastructure.
Using tools like Terraform or
AWS CloudFormation to set up
resources on demand and ensure
consistency across your environments.
let's talk about cold starts
in serverless applications.
Serverless functions can slow down
during their first run because
containers take time to start.
fix this, we can use warm up scripts.
They keep the container active or
try caching strategies to reduce
latencies during critical operations.
lack of observability in serverless.
When we can't see what's happening
inside a distributed system,
troubleshooting issues become tough.
The solution is to use AWS
CloudWatch, Azure Monitor,
or custom logging frameworks.
They give us real time insights.
Distributed tracing is also great for
spotting bottlenecks between services.
Next, tool chain complexity.
Having too many tools for automation,
monitoring, and deployment can
make things messy and inefficient.
To simplify, pick a set of tools that
work well together and stick with them.
Make sure your document to
make sure workflow so your team
stays aligned and productive.
By tackling these challenges with
these strategies, we can build
a solid and efficient automation
system that works smoothly in
cloud and serverless environments.
Mastering cloud and serverless automation
is no longer just an advantage.
Microsoft It's an essential
skill for SDETs to thrive in
modern software development.
This journey requires a commitment
to continuous learning, hands on
experimentation, and collaboration
with cross functional teams.
With the right tools and mindset,
you, as SDETs, can play a pivotal
role in ensuring the success of
cloud native and serverless systems.
you so much for your
time and attention today.
I hope this session has given you
practical insights and inspiration.
I'd like, love to connect with you,
hear your thoughts, and discuss further.
So please feel free to reach out.
Let's continue learning and growing
together in this exciting space.