Hello, everyone.
Good morning.
Happy New Year.
My name is Praveen Paili, working
as a Senior Data Engineer.
Over the years, I got a chance to build
critical data pipelines, manage large
scale warehouses, and create automation
tools to tackle complex challenges.
As an organization continues to scale,
fostering a data driven culture is
essential for empowering informed
decision making across the organization.
Teams rely on data to drive
product development, optimize
operations, and shape learning.
However, the complexity and
fragmentation of data tools have
historically limited access to insights.
In today's data driven world,
organizations are under constant
pressure to make informed
decisions quickly and efficiently.
However, the need to
access data is increasing.
Quickly, often conflicts with the equally
important need to keep that data secure.
As you know, enterprises demand quick
and accurate data access to drive
informed data driven decision making.
Data democratization, making
data accessible to all teams.
has become a priority for organizations.
It also involves in security risks.
Security risk grows as access expands
with concerns about protecting sensitive
information and maintaining compliance.
The challenge lies in balancing
data accessibility and security
without compromising either.
A solution is needed.
to empower teams with data while
ensuring robust security protocols.
To address this, we are introducing
AskData AI tool, which is an AI driven
platform that democratizes data, insight
generation, and optimizes workflow
through natural language interfaces.
This tool simplifies data access
for both technical and non technical
teams by allowing anyone to ask
questions and retrieve accurate
data directly within their workflow.
This tool offers an AI powered
conversational interface that allows
users to access data intuitively
using natural language queries.
Our context aware agents are
specialized to understand diverse
data contexts, ensuring relevant
and accurate data retrieval.
We prioritize enterprise grade security
with role based access, control,
and protect sensitive information.
To revolutionize your data strategy, start
by assessing your current data landscape
to identify pain points and opportunities.
Explore AI powered solutions like AI
powered conversational interface, context
aware AI agents for improved data access.
The AI powered conversational
interface offers several benefits.
User can interact with the system using
natural language queries, making it easier
for non technical users to access it.
and understand data.
The conversational interface simplifies
the process of data retrieval, reducing
the need for complex query language
or technical expertise, which will
help to improve user experience.
It's, it speeds up the data access
process by allowing user to ask questions
and receive answers in real time.
Enhancing productivity and efficiency,
democratize data access across the
organization, enabling all team members
regardless of their technical skills
to leverage data for decision making.
The interface can understand.
the context of queries, providing
more accurate and relevant
results by context aware agent.
Context aware agents improve data access
by understanding a diverse data context.
They are specialized to comprehend
various data environments, ensuring
that the data retrieved is relevant
and accurate to the user query.
These agents can interpret natural
language queries, making it easier for
us users to access that data intuitively
without needing technical knowledge.
By understanding the context, these agents
can provide more precise context and
contextually appropriate data, improving,
improving the overall user experience
and efficiency in data retrieval.
This approach ensures that both technical
and non technical users can access the
data they need quickly and accurately.
These benefits collectively enhance
the overall data strategy of www.
microsoft.
com an organization by
making data more accessible,
understandable, and actionable.
Balancing security and
usability is crucial in today's
data driven environments.
By leveraging a role based
security process, organizations
can ensure users have seamless
access to the data they need.
Promote efficiency workflows
and decision making.
Maintaining Robust security and protect
sensitive data from unauthorized access.
Adhere to compliance and
regulatory standards.
Balance data democratization and
security enable broader access to
data for innovation and insights.
Implement strict controls to
safeguard critical information assets.
Achieving this balance ensures both
data accessibility and security are
aligned with the organizational goals.
Embrace continuous innovation.
to stay updated and, and, advancements
and evolve your data strategy.
The technical architecture deep day for
our, tool is our technical architecture
includes quadrant vector search for
efficient similarity based data retrieval.
We use hybrid search model that
comments vector and traditional
sets boosting accuracy by 20%.
Reciprocal rank fusion re ranks
results to improve the accuracy.
Relevance by 40%.
We have implemented a raven, ranking,
model, which improving performance by 40%.
We also integrated
charge up to four or it.
Which reduces query latency by 35%.
Key platform features, we majorly,
focused on enhancing AI platform.
So we used a quadrant vector search,
was deployed as a scalable vector
search engine, enhancing overall
search capabilities and enabling
hybrid and multistage searches.
Also implemented advanced filtering.
filtering for JSON collections support
was added for a advanced filtering
using quadrant query language enable
targeting filtering, such as including
only finance related data sets for
ask finance for a global, so which
also uses a team based, searches.
So.
We can restrict the access there and
only the respective teams can get their
data for their decision making systems.
Popularity and certification based
re ranking implemented a reciprocal
rank fusion approach which prioritizes
results based on the key indicators
like page popularity and certifications.
Cementing dataset collections, ask data
experts, Explorer generates data in sets
based on relevance and table popularity
and Hubble certification status.
Table sets can be applied to any
agent for efficient table suggestions.
Latency optimization, hybrid sets
model evaluation, and other tools.
And integration.
This will help, hybrid sets model
increase of accuracy by 20 percent
across multiple agents, scalable and
back end AI chatbots and batch mode.
This is a new service deployed for back
end services in a supercell environment.
GRPC integration also included
security, secure security and privacy
approvals for open AI process.
Integrations also, we also
integrated with Slack and Kafka and
other, tools, tools to, Enhance or
improve our product reachability.
So developed BFF and EA
components enabling faster
development and deployment cycles.
So enable real time feedback collections
to enhance service response accuracy.
And also include a Slack bot.
So which will help ask questions.
questions using a Slack bot, by plain
English so that users can get their
result back with the proper information.
We also included, logging and, user ID
propagations and improved traceability
for, logging so that security related
things also can be fall in place,
by looking at this logging process.
So improved accuracy and latency
enhanced the platform stability and user
experience by integrating the testing.
Added automation evaluation mechanism
improved accuracy by 20 percent latency
with 22 percent of the prompt engineering.
Caching and prompt responses significantly
improved latency with the cache and
reduced LLM cost for repetitive prompts.
Performed semantic cache
evaluation for accuracy.
The hybrid caching revamped lagging
and created a thread safe logging
mechanism throughout the application
to monitor and debug all requests with
the, with the idea and user mapping
with the full traceability implemented
guardrails limited chat history and the,
Context provided to the LLM agent to
a maximum of 8 conversation turns are
until the token limit is reached, which
helps reduce the latency and LLM cost.
Implemented a BFF model changes
to support a NuAsk data AIJRPC
gateway service on that.
These are the UI and the
Created you in a web web.
Next, with more than 75, 70 5% of unit
test coverages, support conversational
chat with rich market support and work
seamlessly across different screens.
Even logging and usability testing.
Also included in the, in the PLA platform.
So overall.
Our platform achieves 60 percent boost
in data discovery efficiency and 20
percent improvement in query accuracy.
We have reduced query response
time by 35 99 percent reduction
in unauthorized access.
We, we worked on enhancing the data
discovery, cementing data collection,
which is automatically analyze
tags and organize data set for
intuitive navigation and discovery.
And, we implemented, reciprocal, Raven,
ranking, ranking methods, that popularity
based ranking sets, ranks data sets
dynamically based on user engagement
metrics and collaboratively feedback.
Certification based re ranking evaluates
trusted data source through a re ranking.
Rigorous quality checks
and expert verification.
The major challenge was
data access versus security.
Modern enterprises need seamless
real time access to data instead
for agile decision making while
democratizing data access driven.
Innovation is crucial to balance
accessibility with robust security
protocols to protect sensitive
information and maintain compliance.
So we implemented Ravan
role based access control.
Our Ravan role based access control
system ensures 99 percent reduction in
unauthorized access, precise alignment
with IT rules, dynamic permission
updates, and granule access control.
Granule access control is fine
grained permission tailored to
specific application requirements.
Dynamics Rolex Assignment is the
ability to update roles based on
user activity, context, or roles.
Auditing and compliance also
implemented which logs and reports
for monitoring access and ensuring
compliance with regulations.
Integration support is compatibility with
external Identity providers like what,
Samuel and all, we also implemented our
tools to auto scale suitable for a system
with a large number of users, rules and
permissions and also cross functional
class organizations and cross teams.
So major challenge.
We unified disparate data sources
across the ecosystem to address
data integration complexity.
Optimizing our architecture
to handle over 15, 000 plus
concurrent customers and users.
Customized chat GPT 4 for
specific data context.
Implemented an intuitive UI
and comprehensive training
program to drive user adoption.
Three lessons learned from overall
this implementation of the tool.
Balance is the key.
It's crucial to democratize data access
while maintaining robust security.
Context is the matter.
AI agents must understand
enterprise specific data context
for accuracy and their responses.
Continuous improvement, regular model
updates and user feedback loops drive
platform evaluation and improvement.
of the, use of the tool, user centric
design, intuitive interfaces, and clear
documentation boost adoption rates.
Our future directions.
We are expanding to handle multi
modal data integration, including
images, videos, and audios.
Integrating with other enterprise
tools to tools and workflows
for cross platform synergy.
Implementing AI driven forecasting
and trend analysis for the
advanced predictive analytics.
Expanding to support queries in
implementing and queries in multiple
languages for global language support.
Thank you once again for
your time and attention.
I look forward to witness more
groundbreaking advancement in
AI and data in the near future.
Once again, thank you all.