Hello, welcome to Con 42 DevOps 2025.
My name is Ashok John Lagata.
I'm going to discuss revolutionizing
data center operations using
AI driven optimizations.
in this topic, we are going to discover
how AI and ML technologies have
transformed the data center operations.
And we also explore quantitative results
across our four critical domains.
Let's, without any delay,
let's get into the topic.
let's start with the
predictive maintenance success.
We have 47 percent reduction in critical
failures, using advanced AI and ML
technologies, dramatically reduce
unexpected equipment downtime through real
time monitoring and performance testing.
Predictive analysis, and then 72 hour
predictive warning time, and then 96
percent predictive prediction accuracy.
Let's go to the resource
optimization achievements.
coming to the utilization post, AI
powered systems, actually a 31 percent
improvement in resource utilization
rates, enabling data center to handle
40 percent more workloads, without
additional hardware investment and
latency reduction, advanced load balancing
algorithm, delivered 38 percent decrease
in Resulting in sub 10 millisecond
response time significantly enhances our
user experience across all applications.
Coming to the energy management
breakthroughs, we can say 42% Cooling
efficiency gain by deploying smart thermal
management systems, and then optimize
airflow patterns in real time, leveraging
AI to maximize cooling effectiveness
across the data center floor.
and then PUI reduction to less than 1.
25.
The industry leading power
usage, effectiveness,
achievement, and performance.
through AI driven load balancing and
intelligent resource distribution and
23 percent cooling cost savings, direct
operational cost reduction through
intelligence, cooling optimization
powered by deep learning models,
analyzing environmental sensors.
coming to the security, the
enhanced security framework, by
deploying AI and NMO, we can see 98.
5% Threat detection accuracy, our deep
learning security framework achieved
exceptionally precision in identifying
cyber threats, including data, data
attacks, unauthorized access attempts
and anomalous data patterns across
our distributed data center network.
And then 45 second response time.
Dramatically reduce, five minutes of
response time to just a 45 seconds,
enabling rapid containment of potential
breaches and maintaining continuous
data center operations and 0.
08 percent false positives.
this is a great breakthrough through
continuous model refinement and
advanced pattern recognization.
Our AI system maintain an industry leading
low false positive rate while monitoring
over 1 million security events daily
across our data center infrastructure.
Coming to the innovative
capacity planning.
So there is, there is a four
different steps to approach.
the whole, criteria of step one is the
data collection, the aggregated real
time server metrics, such as workload
patterns and infrastructure utilization
data across multiple data centers.
The step two is advanced analysis.
Process 500 million plus data points
through our machine learning pipelines to
identify usage pattern and growth trends.
The step three is predictive insights.
Generate 12 month capacity forecast
with 96 percent accuracy using neural
networks and time series analysis.
And step four is implementation.
Deploy automated infrastructure
scaling AI driven recommendations.
Coming to the financial impact.
Impactment.
Financial impact, sorry.
this 2.4 millions annual savings,
throughout optimized, throughout optimized
cooling hardware and maintenance.
and then 2 8 2 80 5%, return
of investment rate within first
18 months of implementation.
and then 3.2 millions, saving
in large facilities, of the
five megawatt plus operations.
coming to the, see these topics,
there is explanation for each.
going to the next slide, there is,
definitely there's an integration
challenges, from a traditional model to
the AI driven model, but AI driven, the
advantage of AI driven model is, for
example, dealing with legacy systems, For
example, if you take a migration, there
is, there's always a challenges, but using
AI technologies, we can reduce 19, the
maintenance time, the maintenance time
and then uptime, going to increase to 99.
9%.
And the data quality, the
implementing rigorous data validation.
protocols and standardization of
frameworks to transform desperate
data sources into a written farmers
across 50 plus enterprise databases.
And then skill gap can be reduced.
and then, cultural shift, from
traditional to the AI model is very fast.
coming to the case study snapshot,
this models are not only for the.
simple or small scale data center, this
is also, this can be easily implemented
from small to medium to the large.
coming to the future AI adoption
roadmaps, there is, four steps
we can take into the future.
Step one is edge computing integration,
implementation of distributed AI.
Processing at facility edges to enable
real time decision making and reduce
latency and then quantum AI hybrid
system, leveraging quantum computing
capabilities, algorithm, traditional AI
to solve complex operation, operational
challenges, and then autonomous data
center, developing self managing facility
within a system, handling all critical
operations and the maintenance sessions
and the AI driven sustainability,
achievement, Zero operations through
advanced AI, purpose resource management,
and then renewable energy optimization.
the key take, key takeaways,
transformative impact, a implementation
as reverse reverse layers to data
center operations through automated
monitoring and the predictive
maintenance and intelligence resource
allocation, resulting in an unprecedented
level of operational excellence.
quantifiable results, our AI solutions
have delivered exceptional ROI with
a 47 percent reduction in equipment
failures and 31 percent improvement
in the resource utilization and 2.
4 million cents in the savings.
And the continuous innovation for sure,
with the emerging technologies like
edge computing and quantum integration
on the horizon, we are poised to unlock
even greater operational efficiency and
sustainability gains in the coming years.
Thank you for giving me the opportunity.
Thank you very much again.