Hi everyone.
Welcome to my talk.
I hope you will enjoy it.
So let's start.
What I have prepared for you today is
a talk about environment as a service.
And I hope I will explain it well enough
to help you understand how with this
practice you can unlock innovation
and speed up product development.
Why I'm talking about this today for you?
Well, first of all, my
name is Caio Medeiros.
And, I have been playing as DevOps
human, a huge part of my career,
but also a software engineer.
So I'm going to talk from my
experience working with teams.
and in the last, six or seven years,
I, I had the chance to work with the
different teams and different companies.
So taking all this experience, I
want to explain this practice to you.
also I had the chance to start, being
ambassador for DevOps Institute,
platform engineering, do my, my
participations in the communities.
And I will be bringing the DevOps
Days to Santiago first time in
the history with some folks.
I hope if you have the chance to
join us here, and also with Open
Source Santiago, we are generating
some content, Time to time and we
are planning also to bring the key CD
if you are able to come to Santiago,
drink some wine and enjoy with us.
If you want to connect with me,
just scan my QR code and the
request to connect in LinkedIn.
So let's start with the talk.
And this is the structure
I prepared for this talk.
We're going to Check first what must
see behind the continuous improvement
process to unlock innovation inside
companies and improve the productivity.
And later we're going to talk about
what I have seen and how we can
go through the practice everything
environment as a service to help
organizations on that same path.
So the first.
I think I have seen there is, or what
Massey is, the adoption journeys of
these three main topics, the endless
adoption journeys, because again.
It's about the continuous improvement.
So continuous improvement is
not something with a clear end.
So it starts and probably
whenever I end or just will
stop for some specific reasons.
But what I have seen or people see
based on my experience is Agile
transformation processes to improve the
customer focus and the time to market.
DevOps adoption journeys to a customer.
Increase the productivity of teams
working throughout the software
development life cycle at the same
time, ensuring the reliability of these
products and the platform engineering
to ensure that the experience of the
engineers behind the agile and DevOps
adoption journey is the best one.
At the same time, is standardizing the
practices they will be implementing to.
You know, live the principles,
values of Agile and DevOps.
So to, to have a better understanding,
I wrote this, my vision of the software
development life cycle is just, a
small, or let's say macro vision of the
software development life cycle now,
a small value stream mapping where the
customer is in the beginning, right?
And all the needs or ideas of this
customer will come through the.
Ideation phase to later develop a
requirement, verify and promote to
production, an amazing product that will
solve all the needs of these customers
that, probably we know everybody know
that, Each of these phases, they have
a specific roles or sometimes specific
teams assigned with the ownership of
the specific phase or some of these
phases, depending on the structure
of the organization on how they did
the transformations that we have been
seeing in the last 10 or 15 years.
But definitely we still have some
organizations with teams that are creating
this wall of confusion between them.
Reducing all the possibility to
improve the productivity or the
reliability of their products.
They are generating with the
software development lifecycle.
So through this three main or most
popular adoption journeys, we're
going to see, People or the leaders
of these adoption journeys trying
to bring frameworks like Scrum.
The Scrum is the one that they have seen
is the most popular, to some frameworks
to scale, the adoption of agile inside
organizations like safe, trying to
reorganize in the teams in product.
Multidisciplinary teams where all
the different skills will be there.
So the ownership of the whole product
life cycle will be in inside the team,
reducing all the handoffs and delays
that we can have with other teams.
Obviously, the, the, the, the
restrictions will still exist.
That's why Scrum has the Scrum Masters,
and the Scrum Coach to improve the
communication between other teams, and
implementing the integration practice to
release every, two or one week, right?
that will help.
Definitely.
I have seen that has a good result.
I don't like at all all the different
specific details behind some frameworks,
but definitely it's something that
works for specific to improve specific
phases or specific parts of the
software development life cycle.
Later, when we talk about DevOps adoption
journeys, the most popular practices
we have seen, what people see in the
market is the implementation of CICD
and everything around CICD, right?
Continuous integration, continuous
delivery, and continuous deployment.
Trying to reduce the human
touch with automation, right?
To give the chance to
engineers to work on creation.
On put their minds on generate value,
moving left all or shifting, shifting
left all the quality and security
gates that usually we have later in
the software development lifecycle
process and promoting practices like
everything as a goal, testing automation
to reduce even more than human touches.
And finally.
Not only related to platform
engineering, but, for all the three
adoption journeys, we're going to see
AI everywhere, everywhere, because
with AI, we have, some success.
For use cases like generating, auto
generating the testing code to do unit
testing to your, regression test or
load test, helping developers to code
or engineers in general to code, to
create the infrastructure as a code
as well, if we need to talk about the
infrastructure or, operation side,
reducing the time to solve issues because
sometimes, People rotate to a lot in IT
world, so sometimes it's not the same
person, not the same engineer who needs
to fix an issue or who wrote the code.
So using AI we have seen that this
can be improved the time to solve
issues, to generate documentations
and some other use cases.
So even without this Different
adoption journeys focus on this
most popular practices or movements.
If we want to say that, we're gonna
see that not all metrics will be
showing as good as we want to, right?
In case of agile, some of the
ones, the metrics I have seen
is spring burnout, customer
satisfaction, cycle time, lead time.
And focusing on specifically in
the metrics that are measuring.
Time here when we talk about lead time or
cycle time, it depends really depends on
where you start to measure to really know
if the whole cycle is improving or just
part of the cycle, which is okay, right?
We can improve the whole cycle,
just improving some part, but
we're going to reach the end.
Some levels, we're going to reach
some level of improvement and
from there it will be hard to keep
growing, right, to keep improving.
And we're going to see this in
some, in an idea I have so in
the other section of this talk.
Later with DevOps metrics, we have
the Dora metrics, the most popular
metrics in the market, right?
Due to the Dora reports, the
state of DevOps reports, right?
there we have delivery time, the
volume and frequency, time to
restart, change failure rate, and,
the idea I want to broke with the
environment as a service, will not
be visible in some of these metrics.
And that's why I'm putting them here,
because, as well as, some agile metrics
and platform engineering metrics.
The in a pass on boarding time mean
time to unlock on resource allegation.
Sometimes they are just focusing
on show what is the current state
or where we are in with some
specific part of the flow, right?
So I want to invite you to
see what I saw there, right?
Because, A lot of organizations using
this matrix going through these three
adoption journeys and trying to implement
those practices we already talked,
discussed, they seem like, they see that
like they are, they are having success.
They are improving.
Everything is going good, but they have
so that developers are burning out.
Do some other reasons, some other holes
we can find in the software development
cycle because maybe I'm automating
everything after my commit push, my
commit and push to the core repository.
But what happens before if I need to
start a migration to cloud and, the,
the unique, support they have inside
organization is provisioning the
resources, but they need to go ahead
I need to go to other side to request
network configurations and I need to go
to other side to request certificates.
So everything it's in different teams
or even in small companies, the is
the same thing who wants to who must
own everything and manage everything.
So all these different holes will
generate problems in the flow that
cannot be solved with the traditional
We are at least the common practices.
We, I, I, I mentioned it before.
So what I, I, so, as main
problems, or if I need to put an
example of Some of these holes.
The first thing is lack of knowledge.
And, you're gonna say probably.
Yeah, it happens.
It's normal.
Lack of knowledge is something that we
can we will live with lack of knowledge.
It's a problem that we're
gonna have all time.
If we don't have the expertise inside the
organizations and thinking on in all 80.
It's a common problem even more and more.
But there I also have seen lack
of capacity, lack of budget.
That again, you may say it's,
they are common problems.
so to, to reinforce this problem that
probably you see, yeah, it's a problem
at the fact that I have seen, in with
some of the teams I have worked is,
They took from 3 to 24 months to adapt,
to really adapt new technologies.
So it's a, it's too much time, right?
If we want to innovate and be better than
competitors and win in the marketplace.
Same thing happens with the tractors.
People that is saying, if
it works, don't touch it.
Let's leave it there with the
speech, like, we are using, this
process or this standard because
we are used to do like that.
Or someone else told me I need to do
that and I don't know who decided this.
And the standard says that, have
you ever read the standards?
and also sometimes the standards
are, based on interpretation and
it can generate a lot of biases.
And the fact gives a story again,
because 70 to 80 percent of the
teams I have worked, they had
the tractors, they had the skills
to, start, in, improvement path.
And later, we have the bureaucracy
that, is one of the holes I want to
reinforce with the, Environment as a
service practice because the bureaucracy
generates a lot of burnout on teams.
the probably most of the organizations
are trying to solve this with platform
engineering and the agile and DevOps.
but, in the organizations they
have worked, mainly in the
bigger ones, even having years
working in the adoption journeys.
They still have some problems with
bureaucracy and the fact they cannot
look at the software development
life cycle as a whole process.
They just focus in specific
phases of the flow.
And the fact kills the stories again.
Some teams they have worked, they
waited during three to six months
to for their environments to just
start deploying some small POCs.
It's crazy.
That definitely will block any kind of
competence the organization can have.
So where to start with the environments
as a service and how to approach this to,
face the challenges and try to, solve or
remove the holes I mentioned that before.
The first thing is a start by name, there
is no way to improve if you don't know
where you are, that's part of my, my, my,
my pillars, my mindset, and they want to
share this with you before to even talk
about the practice because DevOps, Agile
and platform engineering practices have
been shared in the last years as something
that can be reused and definitely it can
be done, but, it depends a lot on the
reality of each customer company, right?
Sometimes, there are some practices
that will really help the organization.
Sometimes, they gonna do that
just because they want to have.
C I C D as an example, right?
So Gator data from the value stream is
important to understand if the efforts
you can put to implement some practices
will really generate the value expected
Gator the data, do some Gemba walks,
walk with teams, understand what they
are doing and understand these holes they
can have in the in the process and be as
much as possible open with your mind to
go fewer, even more to the left, right?
Or even more to the right, because
maybe there is the holes that is
really generating delays in your
software development life cycle.
So there, having that in mind,
let me introduce my understanding
of environment as a service.
Definitely, it takes some ideas and
principles from these three different
adoption journeys, the endless
adoption journeys I introduced later.
Before, sorry, which is Agile DevOps
and Platform Engineering, mainly DevOps
and Platform Engineering because the
teams to go and implement the practices.
And the mindset of DevOps, they're going
to need technology, they're going to
need, the environments where they will be
able to automate the deployments, where
they're going to be able to automate the
monitoring, and improve the practice of
DevOps and all the different roles in
between them, or even Before after them.
So if we take the idea of platform
engineering on generating platforms as
a product inside organizations based on
the needs and exposing them as a service
through API's, we're going to have an
example on how to implement environments
as a service because, What I have seen
here in the market working with teams is
usually they request for environments,
and the idea of environments is just
the resources, but it's not just that.
And when they reach production,
they discover that they are a lot,
they are, they have a huge gap on
non functional requirements and,
specific security conditions to reach
production, generating a lot of delays.
So I'm not talking about Infra
provisioning or configuration
provisioning, right?
This is just a small part of it, right?
it's not a matter of, putting as a service
the generation of a virtual machine
or to request a namespace environment.
I'm talking about, To
something greater than that.
Also, it's not just
reusable assets, right?
This is a common service that the
organizations are trying to implement
generating in their source communities
inside the organization to share, Small
pieces of technology that can be reusable
to to improve the activity of teams
and also very used by platform teams.
I have seen that the platform
teams are generating a lot of
community inside organizations to
avoid teams to reinvent the wheel.
But also, I'm not talking even.
of user management.
It's these three things are parts
of the idea of environment, right?
An environment.
It's a concept for me is everything you
need to put your software and make it run.
So that's the definition of environment.
I want to generate the shared
understanding between us right there.
It's everything that need a
team needs to start working.
On their, release of the software
they are developing of the
product they are delivering.
So it's a box with a lot of things inside.
Resources.
I'm talking about infrastructure
and configuration things.
Secrets.
Credentials to connect with the third
parties, services, databases, messaging
brokers, processes to understand how I can
promote my software to that environment.
What is the standards I need to follow?
What kind of authentication,
authorization, non functional
configurations I must ensure to
promote something to production
inside my organization.
The rights, the permissions to
my internal team, right, and also
other support teams to ensure that
this environment will be useful.
Assets to reduce the
reinvention of the wheel.
Ensuring that the teams
are using the right.
Tools, the right files, the right
configurations, and finally documentation,
which is, something, I have seen,
it's, one of the worst things that,
platform teams I had the chance to,
to work with, they, they must take
more care of documentation is, is the
way to solve the gap of knowledge,
adopting new platforms and environments.
It's something similar, right?
when we talk about the commendation,
it's, Achilles, fit, for every
product team, Because, since they
are focusing too much on generate
the product, sometimes they delay or
they forget to create documentation.
So environments will be
everything a team needs.
So, and also in specific organizations,
well, in each organization, the
needs of an environment will
be sometimes different, right?
So that's why I think the generation of
this environment should be a product.
An internal product and as fast as
you can provide these environments
will have the teams to not only
generate value throughout the software
development life cycle, but also
will help them to modernize their
applications in the future, right?
Some of the experience I had was, some
teams trying to move from, virtual machine
based environments to go to containerized
environments, and they Waste a lot of
time, like around three to six months
just waiting for the first environment
to do the first POC of that migration.
That's crazy.
Not, competitive at all.
Some, some other
takeaways I want to share.
For you today, in order to really
be successful, if you want to go and
try to implement the environmental
service with this, this, conception
of environments in your organization.
One of the things you must
take care is this is the costs.
So something we discussed a lot
with my my friend Francisco Meneses
in the last Q comes out Lake City.
Which is, if you want to give environments
to, to the teams, you, you need to
understand the money is, limited, right?
It's not a, endless resource.
So, here it's important
to make it visible.
If the information is there, if you
are monitoring the costs of generating
an environment, it's enough to
generate the shared responsibility.
And say you have your budget.
This is the costs you're going to have if
you request this environment and give also
the chance to have a trial plans, right?
Maybe I can request an environment
during one or two days to do a PLC
and I can have that environment in a
matter of minutes or one hour, maybe,
and remove all the burnout or all
the stress of waiting for an whole
environment just to be able to try.
That environment to try that technology.
Another thing which is super important.
I have seen makes the difference
between the success or not are the
failure is generating training.
Training, and observability enough
to, again, generate this shared
responsibility because we're going
to have different teams here.
It's not the same team which will
use the environment, who will be
providing this environment as a service.
Which can be even a platform
team who will be providing
this environment as a service.
So the different teams using the
solution of environment as a service,
they will need some training, some
preparation to use the platform.
And also they will be able, they must
need to see what is happening there,
to understand what is happening there.
So the team, That will be in charge of
generating the environment as a service.
They must ensure that the solution
is understandable with the logs.
It's generating the messages, right?
And also have a huge amount of
knowledge base to train the team.
Sometimes I will Try to correct what I
said on huge training knowledge base, I
will say, as better as possible to guide
the teams as fast as possible to start
using the platform and later, last but
not least, I think it's super important to
have a clear service level of agreement.
With the support team providing some
connection with the users of this
platform and the engineering team
working on continues improve this
solution of environment as a service
and the delivery time is a is a corner.
Stone that you must take
into account, right?
As I mentioned that before, the experience
I had with some teams waiting for months
to have the first environment, the
delivery lead time of releasing from
when I requested the environment to when
I have the environments in my hands can
make the difference between a company
that will win And release a new feature
to a company that will be the last one
releasing that feature in the marketplace.
So the last part of this talk is,
helping you to understand what kind
of tools you can use or what tools
I have investigated and tried to
implement environment as a service.
The first one is crossplane.
I had the chance to.
Talk with, Victor Fabric and
the last KubeCon Satellite
CD to discuss a bit about the
environments, ephemeral environments.
Well, cross plane is, control plane
to connect, to manage, providers of
infrastructure providers of configuration.
It's super useful because
you can define your.
On APIs, and it's highly extensible,
so you can manage the back end and
configure some controllers to manage
this environment, ephemeral environments
that I mentioned that before, or even
generate connections with some kind
of providers that are not Available by
default in the tool, definitely it will
help you to generate everything you need
for an environment as a definition and
orchestrate everything for you thinking
on those environments that are that are
related on where you're going to offer
a service later, deploy an application,
release a service, to, network service,
The other thing you have is, that I
think it's important is the technology
agnostic that some to some platforms
provides like a test cube test cube.
It's a platform that enable you to
orchestrate testing throughout the
software development life cycle.
And for testing, you
also need environment.
Right?
Environments as a service and test
cube can help you to generate these
environments as a service to do testing
to ensure that you can move this
feedback of, if your unit, functions are
working as expected, if your user flow
is, working as expected, if the load
is the expected for your application.
So with test cube platform, you will
be able to, radiate information.
Generating environments to on
demand to test your applications,
your solutions, your it products
with the execution on demand.
As I said, with reusable
assets, some of the things we
already discussed before, right?
As part of the environments, everything
I need to make my application work and
fully integrated with the whole software
development cycle life cycle, something
that the people is just, putting too
much focus like CICD, but also something
that people maybe is not doing too
much, which is continuous testing.
After deploying the production, I
can keep testing my application.
And with TestCube and the technology
agnostic that this platform
offers, I can cover most of the
technologies or almost technologies
I have inside our organization
to implement continuous testing.
And finally, the open cost, because
it's something I reinforce with the
takeaways, which is the FinOps visibility
of the costs to generate the shared
responsibility over the dispensers I have
when I are working with when I'm working
with the environment and be able to
have this, this option to work with any
vendor and see the costs in real time.
Right.
So joining all these three
platforms, I thought it's a
good way to start implementing
every environment as a service.
But if definitely if you need some
other solutions to complement this, it
depends on, on what technologies you
already have, but if you don't have, One
technology for one specific requirement.
You can find a lot of these options in
the cloud native computer foundation
landscape from where I took this three
important and amazing products, or
platforms, projects as you want to call.
So at the end, we're going
to have something like this.
It's my proposal, right?
Have a platform team with a product
called environment as a service platform.
Where are they going to provide different,
APIs where the teams will be able to
use to request their environment using
platforms like crossplane, testcube, open
cost to cover all the different aspects
I mentioned it right to generate an
environment, not only releasing resources,
not only generating a virtual machine
for a team, but also Put in there, the
certificates, the network configurations
and everything that is needed.
Same thing for a Kubernetes namespace.
so all these artifacts will be part
and will be needed to generate this
environment as a service solution and,
using automation, using platforms like
cross plane test cube and open cost,
the delivery time will be reduced,
but definitely you need to tell.
Think in the in the whole architecture
of your product, considering this
aspect, because I have seen teams that
are providing Kubernetes namespaces
as a service, and they are delaying
a lot on generate the environments
due to the resource management.
This is another thing
that must be considered.
finally, to Take to have success.
My let's share my, my success
keys for platform teams.
The first thing is focus on customer.
That's why I have this sign.
The first sign here, this
is coming from another talk.
If you want to, go deeper
on this, you can see.
Find that talking in YouTube.
the three practices I recommend to
have success with platform engineering.
The first one is focused on customers.
So the platform team must understand
who is their customer and how to
generate environments for them.
Because I mentioned it before, the
environment for one team maybe will
be different Of, environments to
other team in another company, right?
Because each company has different
standards, different, providers.
So that's important to understand
and identify your customer, identify
their needs and generate a platform of
environment as a service based on that.
The second thing is measure and
try to implement the practices
you are releasing as a service.
So if you use a tool, you will be a
customer as well and will be better
for you to get your feedback if you
are using the platform and you have
the same pains that other teams.
And finally, form a team.
Champions inside the platform team
where you have different platforms
totally integrated with each other with
artifacts specifically created for your
own company or your specific customer.
You're gonna need expertise inside and
one person cannot be expert in everything.
So form experts inside your team to
support each other with a T shaped format.
and, have a platform team
that can grow together.
So my closing comment is do not
just replicate what others did think
out of the box and discover the
continuous improvement never that
continuous improvement never ends.
Right?
And why I'm saying this because a lot
of people is just focused on On the
implementing the DevOps adoption journey
with CICD agile adoption journey with scam
or scaling with safe platform engineering,
generating the DevOps platform engine,
a DevOps platform with a lot of tools,
everything connected, but they forget.
about these other aspects that can heavily
impact on the time to market, right?
Just imagine, reduce the whole team stress
to go from idea to first touch in a matter
of minutes, in a matter of hours, right?
So let's say a team was requested
to generate a new product.
Amazing product.
And they want to test deploying the
first feature, and they just remember
that they require an environment.
So they go through this platform
and request the trial, right?
And they deploy some pieces of
software there and they can start
receiving feedback, celebrate.
That will be amazing.
I have seen a lot of stress
on teams do they don't have
access to their environments
in the time they are expecting.
So thanks for joining.
I hope you will keep
enjoying this com, 42 20 25.
I love to have this space
to share this idea with you.
And if you wanna want to go deeper
on this, you wanna talk about this
with me or some other people, feel
free to reach me out, in linking
and or in the chat of the event.
and see you soon for a next another talk.