Hello, everyone, and thank you for joining
me today at COM 42 DevOps conference.
My name is Stefan and I work as
DevOps engineer at Analog Devices.
I'm excited to present you today an
automated way of testing in hardware
across a wide range of platforms that
run different Linux distributions.
System level testing plays an
essential role for quality assurance
in the fast evolving landscape of
software and hardware integration.
A robust testing infrastructure is
required to ensure that individual
software components work together.
Key attributes like automation,
rigorous testing, and coverage
are some of the must haves for
achieving a reliable integration.
By implementing these best practices,
Organizations can deliver high quality
systems that meet user expectations.
A reliable test infrastructure
accelerates also test executions, but
most important, reduce the probability
of finding bugs in production phase.
The Linux distribution I talked about
is called Analog Devices Kuiper and it
is a free open source distro customized
for analog devices signal chain.
It comes pre equipped with essential
components like device drivers, pre
built boot files or FPGA, and Raspberry
Pi based solutions, as well as a
wide range of development utilities,
libraries, and project examples.
The system supports multiple hardware
platforms, AMD and Intel FPGA based
platforms, Raspberry Pi, and also NXP.
To streamline software management,
KyperLinux incorporates a
custom Linux package repository.
Simplifying software components
installation or update.
This is included by default in the
image ensuring easy of use for both
testing and production environments.
For more details regarding how Kyper
Linux releases got optimized, please
check Refining the release strategy
of a custom Linux distro that is also
presented at this edition of Comfortitude
DevOps by one of my colleagues, Andrea.
The continuous integration flow for
individual software components is handled
using classic CI tools, such as Jenkins,
ErrorPipeline, or GitHub Actions.
The CI builds software components
across various operating systems
and the resulting output binaries,
which might be Linux packages,
Windows installers, or just archives,
are stored in GitHub releases,
package manager, or internal server.
This streamlined approach not
only improves efficiency, but
also ensures traceability, version
control, and artifacts accessibility,
making it easier to integrate and
deploy them into larger systems.
The testing process in hardware
closely mirrors the one in software.
The workflow typically begins
with specific boot files being
written onto the hardware boards
to configure them for testing.
Tests are executed in parallel
across multiple hardware setups.
Reducing overall testing time
and increasing efficiency.
Because popular testing framework
available in the market even are designed
for application level testing or are
specific to a single hardware platform
we worked on creating our own testing
framework called Hardware Test Harness.
It is designed to unify testing across
a wide range of hardware platforms
enabling consistent execution
regardless of the hardware type.
Builds are triggered by pushes
or pull requests in GitHub.
Multiple repositories are monitored like
HDL, Linux, libraries or applications.
And changes from those will
trigger the entire testing process.
Let's see what happens
after the build passes.
The results binaries are saved on internal
servers, in this case JFrog Artifactory.
And then the main
Jenkins job is triggered.
The Jenkins job begins by downloading
the binaries from Artifactory and
writing them onto the hardware
platforms connected to each agent.
After this, the automated tests
are distributed and executed.
The tests are mostly written in
Python and have specific tags that
indicate hardware compatibility.
Let's see now why do you think we need
an intermediate Artifactory server.
this server is required
for several reasons.
The main one is that the hardware
test harness is distributed across
multiple physical locations, requiring
a centralized system to share binaries.
Another reason is to handle concurrency.
Since multiple repositories are
implied, this will act as a bumper.
And it also ensures better organization
and versioning of binaries,
making the process more scalable.
Another question may be why the Jenkins
agents need to be physical machines.
The primary reason here is that
these agents directly control the
hardware setups, including power
management, WART connections, Ethernet,
and in some cases JTAG interface.
Some of the build servers are also
physical machines, because builds require
significant computational resources or
paid licenses, as Xilinx or Matlab cases.
A good framework should be
adaptable to different types of
hardware and testing scenarios.
It should be modular enough to
accommodate changes, such as adding
new DUTs or modifying test cases.
Because there are implied multiple
repositories and multiple Jenkins agents,
there is necessary a test manager to
queue, distribute, and execute tests.
But let's go first through
some implementation details.
As main tool, there was used Jenkins.
It can be hosted independently without
relying on external servers, integrates
easily with tools like GitHub or
Artifactory, and benefits from a
large online community for support.
Additionally, features as Jenkins share
libraries, dynamic script language, and
resource logging mechanism proved to
be extremely useful in this context.
Another tool used is Nebula.
This tool was developed by us
and consists in a collection of
Python scripts that manage hardware
connections, such as sending word
commands, configuring Ethernet IPs,
sending files through SSH and so on.
In the event of a hardware setup failure,
we can physically reboot the system
and bring it back online using Power
Distribution Unit and USB SD card mobs.
Both of them are also controlled
through Python by Nebula.
As we added more harder setups,
we needed a tool to keep tracking
of all of the devices under test.
And that's where Netbox comes in.
It is a free open source tool,
originally designed for modeling
and documenting network racks,
but it also fits in our use case.
We use it to generate Nebola configuration
files, YAMLs that contain information
about each DUT, such as platform,
the board that is plugged into it.
Ethernet and serial addresses,
PDU outlet and USB connections.
The NetBox configuration needs to
be updated only when new duties
are added, removed or rearranged.
All data stored in NetBox is backed up
automatically in Artifactory and it can
be restored if something goes wrong.
Jenkins.
JAR library is a very good
way to centralize groupy code.
https: and reuse it in
multiple Jenkins pipelines.
It contains definition for common
functions and pipeline steps that can be
shared across different Jenkins files.
Improving in this way reusability,
modularity, and consistency.
We use it in multiple pipeline stages
to update agent tools as Nebula, to
send files to hardware setups, or
to run tests and collect results.
this structured approach ensures
an efficient process of updating
and maintaining the same
pipeline functionality across
all the test harness instances.
By combining continuous integration
with continuous testing, the
resulting diagram will look like this.
Behind it are over 100 CI pipelines
implied, implemented in Azure,
GitHub Actions, or Jenkins, and
about 15 physical build servers.
For most of them, besides build status,
the test result from hardware testing
is returned back to github pull request.
Some software components,
such as libraries, are tested
individually on hardware.
If all of the test passes, the
corresponding binaries are stored in
artifactory or Linux package repository.
For other components, the build
artifacts are first stored on internal
servers and tested afterwards.
In some cases, Linux packages are
created automatically at each push
and saved into the package repository.
Ideally, once all the software
components are packed as Linux
packages, those packages generated
by each CI run will be uploaded
automatically under testing environment.
So they can be installed on Kyper
for further testing or just used
internally as pre released versions.
On the other side, whenever
there are changes in the Kyport
sources, new Docker containers are
created, being used by other CIs.
This ensures that everything is
consistently built and validated
across multiple environments.
Let's see how results
visualization was handled.
The easiest way was to manually
verify status of Jenkins pipelines.
Of course, this method didn't give
us any details about what stages
Failed, and on which hardware setup.
So we switch to BlueOceanView.
It looks a bit better.
For those of you who don't know, the
BlueOcean is a Jenkins plugin that offers
a good visualization of parallel stages.
In this case, we could see the
status of all the stages on all
the hardware setups, becoming a bit
easier to know exactly what failed.
I still couldn't see all the details.
So next step was to convert results
into XML format and use JUnit
Jenkins plugin for visualization.
Even this method requires
logging into Jenkins and visually
inspect the results at every run.
So we have started to use
even more powerful tools.
Logstash for processing results,
Elasticsearch for storing them into
database and Kibana for generating graphs.
At this point, we also created a web
page with multiple dashboards and added
the ability to create and apply filters.
The new implementation eliminates
the need of going through individual
artifacts to check results.
But developers were still needed to
look over the graphs to check the
status before pushing their changes.
Actually in all of the above
cases, developers were still needed
to manually check the results.
Even if the results were shown in tables,
graphs, or dashboards, it was not feasible
to handle a big number of repositories
and pull requests in this way, so we
needed to close the loop completely.
An important step in the implementation
was to bind hardware test results
back to GitHub pull requests.
The main challenge here was to ensure
that private data from our internal
build and test environment, such as
internal IPs, Jenkins links, or any
other sensitive information, to not
be exposed in public repositories.
At the same time, it was very
important to provide sufficient
information about the build status
and testing results to aid developers.
To achieve this, multiple tools were
used to parse results, merging them into
the same tables with build statuses,
securely tunneling SSH connections,
and posting summaries via GIST.
With this system in place, we were finally
able to enable, require CI status to
pass setting from GitHub repository.
This ensures that only changes
that pass builds and don't broke
any test are allowed to be merged,
increasing the overall stability
and reliability of the code base.
We can dive deeper into this topic by
accessing secure integration of private
testing infrastructure with GitHub.
public github repositories presented
by my colleague Bianca at the
same edition of home 42 devops.
The final step needed to achieve a
fully automated testing framework was
to implement a mechanism for recovering
harder setups from bad states.
One common issue arises when boot
files produced by CIs are faulty.
In this case, harder setups can
hang during the boot process and
remain stuck in the unstable state.
The framework detects these failures
and attempts to recover the affected
boards through various methods.
As part of this process, we maintain
a set of golden files, a reliable
baseline of boot files that are
overwritten with the latest set
of files that passes successfully.
They serve as a fallback option,
allowing to set the hardware
systems back up and running.
And of course, to be prepared for
next set of files to be tested.
However, the rare scenario when
the hardware setups are physically
damaged remains the single situation
that requires manual intervention.
This recovery mechanism ensures that
the testing framework remains resilient,
minimize the downtime, and increase
the efficiency of testing framework.
Now that I have gone through
all the details, let's see how
the overview design looks like.
On the left side, you can see the
triggering mechanism, multiple
Jenkins files and Jenkins server.
The server manages the testing requests
queue, ensuring efficient resource
allocation and also merges results
from all test harness instances
and prepare them to be published.
Then are the Jenkins agents.
By deploying agents inside Docker
containers, we have successfully
connected multiple hardware setups
into a single physical machine,
optimizing resource usage.
Test hardness supports tests
written in different programming
languages as Python, C or Matlab.
Hardware boards are locked only when
the tests are running on them, otherwise
they remain accessible for remote
connections, allowing team members to
perform debugging and development work.
Test results are very well structured
and presented clearly, ensuring
that any defects are identified
and addressed in early stages.
This system increases efficiency,
maintains stability, and
enhances the overall reliability
of the testing process.
But let's see how the hardware
setup looks in real life.
This is how the prototype looked
in early beginning stages.
There were just a few hardware
boards connected between them
and lying around on a desk.
We were experimenting at that time
using Raspberry Pi as Jenkins agent.
and adding support for multiple platforms.
And this is how Test Harness looks now.
In conclusion, we have managed to
implement a very complex testing
framework that can be triggered from
multiple GitHub repositories, as well
as Jenkins, Cron, or even manually.
Hardware setups remain accessible for
remote connection, allowing team members
to perform debugging and development.
It supports multiple platforms and can
run tests written in different languages.
Resources got optimized by using Jenkins
agents inside Docker containers, and there
is a robust recovery mechanism in place.
Test results are well structured and
bind back to GitHub, ensuring that
bugs are found as early as possible.
The presented testing framework
is highly efficient, flexible, and
robust, designed for complex workflows.
It ensures software and hardware
integration, streamlining the testing
process, and enhancing the stability.
Thank you all for listening me, if you
have any related questions or need more
details don't hesitate to contact me.
Have a nice day, bye.