Speaker 43: Hello everyone.
My name is Ker.
I am an alumni of Usman City and
currently A-I-E-E-E Senior member.
The topic that I have today is about
DevOps pipelines for clinical AI that
is deploying real-time sepsis detection.
Now, why is sepsis a challenge and why
are we looking at the DevOps solution?
Sepsis, as you may be aware,
is a global healthcare crisis.
It claims approximately 11
million lives, which is, 20% of
all the mortality that we have.
What more, with every hour that's
gone, the chances of mortality
increases by approximately 8%.
So with the impact and the time
criticality, the question here would be,
can technology help in reducing these?
The answer pretty positive, yes.
When combined with process
and digital transformation,
it can, AI can improve the.
Clinical outcomes when embedded into the
redesigned care workflows and supported
by reliable, always on platform.
In these high risk settings,
we are talking about lives.
Modern dev ops and ML ops capabilities
can ensure speed, reliability,
observability, and zero downtime.
These are strategic enablers that
ensure insights reach clinicals.
At the moment, decisions have to
be taken this translating analytics
into measurable reduction and
preventable harm from sepsis.
So with this context, again, we are
seeing sepsis, a major healthcare crisis,
time criticality, really important.
If you don't have data, if
it's in buckets, if it's in
different ways, different sources,
it's going to cause problems.
And if there is downtime,
you're losing time.
And what is the impact here?
You're talking about lives
and every hour is impactful.
So it's very important that you
give this data at the right time.
Now coming to the phase wherein we
are trying to get everything done.
But does this is it easy in terms
of implementing of course not.
It comes with its own complexities.
So what are some of the
complexities you're talking about?
You're talking about
distributed healthcare systems.
You may have vendor systems, you may have
legacy electronic healthcare records, and
you also need real time streaming of data.
And that is through the data pipelines
that we have spoken about and.
This, of course, has to be very reliable.
You cannot have errors, so it should be
able to get data from all the pipelines.
And then what it needs to do is get into
a model, which should be, which you should
be, there should be validation for it.
And of course, compliance
is the key thing, right?
And while you're doing all this, it's
very critical that you maintain audit
history from regulatory perspective.
Now, coming again to the concept of.
You also have to have a
process in place, right?
You may have the data, but it
should also be embedded into
clinical and operational frameworks.
So you have the data, but then,
if you're not taking the data,
if there is no process and
actions are not taken at the at.
Based on all of this, then it's of no use.
So it should be used.
And the workflow should be embedded with
this aligned real time data that comes to
the pipeline and helps in decision making.
So with that challenges in mind,
are there any things that can any
you know, platform engineering
patterns to address these challenges?
This slide talks to that some of
the things that could be done is
the Kubernetes orchestration, which
will help in autoscaling and health
checks for distributed hospital
networks to t prediction services.
Then you have CICD with clinical gates,
which is basically continuous integration
and continuous deployment because you
want to have validations, you want to
see how the performance is, and if there
is any bias, you want to detect that.
So there is always a need for
continuous integration and
continuous deployment of of.
Data will basically automated
pipelines, again, coming to the
pipelines, why it's so important.
Observability framework so that
you monitor prediction, accuracy,
latency, data quality, real time
alerting for model drift or issues.
Infrastructure as a code, which enables
to provision, manage and recover
secure, compliant and highly reliable
IT infrastructure through automated
version control code, directly supporting
patient safety and clinical operations.
And the last important thing
is basically SRE, which is site
reliability engineering for healthcare.
And it's.
It's really critical to ensure
highly reliable, safe, compliant,
and continuous availability when
there are downtime also or errors
can directly impact the patients.
So it's very important
from that perspective.
So we again looked at the sepsis
as a impact, how important
it is to have timely data.
We looked at how technology can
help ensure the downtime is not
there and get you everything.
It'll be accurate.
Now, how do you do that?
You need to have pipelines.
And we saw some of the challenges
that you, it's not just the
hospital, but you may have vendor
systems like labs, et cetera.
You might have some
data on legacy systems.
You may also need to integrate
data from various sources.
And then as we went through all
those challenges, we needed to
have models which required to be.
Continuously validated.
And then we looked at some of
these tools which can help address
the challenges which includes the
Kubernetes orchestration, CICD, which
is again, continuous integration
and deployment with clinical Gates
Observability framework, infrastructure
as a code and SRE for healthcare.
And we'll go through some of
these in the following topics as
we go through the slides as well.
Coming back now.
So to be able to have that kind
of CLI cloud infrastructure for
realtime patient monitoring, right?
Real time is what we want to do.
We needed to have a processing timeline,
which is basic pipeline, sorry, I'm sorry.
Processing pipeline.
Which, which was a key thing
that we discussed so far as well.
And what that means is that there
should be cloud native architecture.
Process that processes real time
vitals of the patient, things like
heart rate, blood pressure lab
values, even driven microservices.
These ensure sub-second latency for
clinical critical clinical interventions.
And then when you're talking
about integration, again, we
looked at it slightly previously.
We are talking about automated clinical
workflows are triggered for clinical
events like sepsis alerting care teams and
suggesting diagnostic protocols, right?
You want them to be given
some kind of instructions and
whatever could help we do it.
And then comprehensive audit
trials is another thing that
we spoke about previously also.
Coming back to streamlining data
pipelines and processing patient vitals.
Now some of the things that will help in
streamlining data, archite architectures
that process, continuous page patient
vital science with minimal latency.
How some technologies like Apache Kafka
and cloud services es data from monitors,
lab systems and nursing platforms.
What more these platforms can
perform future feature engineering.
Aggregation and data enrichment
from the EHR integration.
Before AI models even interface.
They are designed to handle variable
patterns, internet and network
connectivity, and ensure data accuracy.
Very critical, right?
Because again, when you're consolidating
data, these are all real time
issues that you're talking about.
You could have data coming from different
sources with different data patterns.
There could be network issues
there, and we have to ensure that
there is data accuracy because
we are talking about lives.
Robust mechanisms like back pressure
management, product downstream services,
and maintain responsiveness during peak
time and peak demands and critical events.
That's super critical.
Then we spoke about EHR integration,
which is electronic health record to
be able to diagnose and cure a patient
if you don't have the health record.
It's going to lose a lot of time
because firstly, you wouldn't be
able to take the right decision
about the patient's health condition.
And then second thing would be
that it would be also you would
lose out a lot of time, which is
again, major challenge about sepsis.
We have already covered that before.
So electronic health record integration
is, as foundational for clinical ai
navigating diverse platforms with
proprietary data model and vari standards.
So what are we talking about?
We are talking about data extraction.
That's critical from all these systems.
It could be done via HHL seven
FH IR APIs or custom interfaces.
Then you need to
normalize the data, right?
You could have things which
are basically just not
representative of the right thing.
So transforming all this
heterogeneous data into standard
formats, handing terminology.
And missing values because what if,
you had say one day when somebody's
BP was 300 and usually his BP or her
BP is only 80, then you don't want
it to consider just one day, right?
You want to consider, but you don't
want to say average it out or something.
So you would still have the
data point, but you would.
Try to normalize the data to be a two
representation, and then you would have
quality validation which is basically
you would implement quality checks and
monitoring for accurate model interface.
Now, we spoke about.
Again, sepsis as a concept of
some of the technology challenges,
some things that will help us.
We spoke about, again, with respect
to pipelines, all of this that we
covered is, it's very critical in
terms of the data and in terms of
getting everything integrated properly.
And now what are the different phases
that we have in implementing these, right?
The first.
Phase would be the algorithm
development where models are
trained with retrospective data
optimized for sepsis detection.
So you would do the algorithm development.
Then based on the algorithm you would
also do a retrospective validation.
So you would do things like
rigorous validation of handout data
set across patient demographics.
And then you would do a shadow deployment
because you wanted to go slow and be
cautious, so you would do a shadow
development in terms of running the.
Shadow mode and then, generating
predictions without actu, without
actually doing the full scale deployment.
And then you would do clinical reviews in
terms of how the results are coming out.
You would do a canary release, which is
basically gradual release to small cohorts
with continuous adverse event monitoring
because you want to see how it's going.
And then you would go into full
production, which is basically
deployment across networks with ongoing
performance and drift detection.
So these would be the
phases that you would have.
As we do this, observability is
the most important thing, right?
You want to see how the data is
also performing in production.
So you would, how would you do that?
You would do that through things like.
You would do that through various things
like, prediction, performance metrics.
You would continuously assist
sensitivity, specificity, and alert rates.
You would have dashboards segment
performance to identify thrift across
demographics and clinical units.
You would have system latency
tracking which is basically monitoring
end-to-end latency from data
ingestion to client alert delivery.
And then you would define that would
also define acceptable thresholds
aligned with intervention windows.
So if you have some kind of
a threshold breach, then you
know how quickly it should be.
Escalated.
All that is what, and then the data
quality, you're talking about data,
you're talking about pipelines, data,
qualities of paramount importance,
so automated detection of missing
values and data completeness issues.
Alerts trigger when the data quality
falls below the threshold is super key.
Now model drift detection
and continuous validation.
So you looked at observability
and then model drift detection
and continuous validation.
Clinical AI models drift due to
evolving patient populations,
practice change and seasonal shifts.
Continuous validations compels life.
Prediction distribution against baseline
training data using statistical tests
if drift breaches the threshold.
Automated retraining or data science
team investigation is triggered
feedback loop with actual clinical
outcomes enabled, supervised model
updates, improving prediction accuracy,
and ensuring regulatory compliance.
So we spoke about model detection, drift
detection, and continuous validation,
and now we move into SRE practices
for life critical healthcare systems.
So what are some of the SRE practices
as error budgets for clinical ai
That is defining acceptable failure
rates, aligning with clinical impacts,
sepsis detection as you can imagine
will have a higher detection system
and the target is about 99.95.
Uptime with strict latency
percentiles balancing innovation.
Velocity against reliability requirements,
incident response protocols, structured
on-call procedures with escalation path
to DevOps engineers, data scientists
and clinical informatics team run
book's, document common failure
scenarios and remediation steps.
And then blameless postmortem.
Learning from incidents through
detailed root cause analysis focuses
on focusing on system improvements
rather than individual faults.
Documentation feeds continuous improvement
of infrastructure and processes.
Yeah, that's the last phase and it's
super critical because whenever there's
something that goes wrong, we don't blame.
We sit down, we think about it, what
the root cause was, and we try to
improve continuously because that's how.
Things get better.
Having said that, once you have done all
the deployment, you have been thorough,
you have continuously validated.
It's definitely going to help save
time and take decisions quickly, but
we just don't stop at where we are.
So we would just continue
with the blameless postmortem
and will continuously evolve.
Now, as you can see, we are moving from
a reactive to a proactive clinical care.
We are not doing things where.
Things have gone extremely
wrong, thankfully.
And we are trying to be as
proactive as possible, right?
And the criticality is immense.
So as you can see, modern DevOp
practices are transforming healthcare
from reactive treatment to proactive
care, enabling earlier intervention with
real time predictive analytics in areas
in the area, in various areas, right?
And here we're talking
about sepsis detection.
This approach prevents severe outcomes and
is crucial for any mission critical domain
where reliability impacts human outcomes.
Including fraud detection,
predictive maintenance, and
auto autonomous vehicle systems.
By applying cloud narrative architectures
and rigorous reliability, engineering
DevOps teams deliver practical clinical
impact at scale here because we are
not talking about just one patient.
It's the whole system.
And, if it's positive, how
many people it can help.
So that brings us towards
the end of the presentation.
Some of the key takeaways that we had of
is you have infrastructure as foundation.
You, we spoke about Kubernetes
streamlining and infrastructure
as a code, ensuring reliable.
Reproducible deployments
across healthcare networks.
We said validation gates really do matter.
Clinical validation, shadow
deployment, and canary releases.
Pro protest, sorry, not protest.
Pro protects us, right?
It protects us against regressions,
enabling continuous improvement of
clinical algorithm observability
beyond uptime monitoring.
Predictions, accuracy, latency
and data quality ensures clinical
utility and protects drift.
Model drift before patient impact.
Very key.
And then reliability engineering, which
is the last topic that we touched upon.
Then sari practices like error,
budget, and incident response ensure
operational excellence protecting
patients from system failures.
That brings us to the
end of the presentation.
Thank you again.
Just to iterate my name again
is, and we can go ahead with
any questions from here on.
Thanks.