Speaker 8: Hello everyone.
I'm excited to talk about one of the
biggest transformation that we all
are witnessing in our industry in
the DevOps and AI landscapes, which
is the shift to the subscription
based intelligent platforms.
This shift is not just a technological, it
is fundamentally reshaping how we design,
deploy, scale, and deliver AI driven.
Experiences today.
I will walk you through the architectural,
the operations part, the ML ops
practices, customer value, and the
future direction of this space.
So let's get started.
The convergence revolution.
This slide highlights the three primarily
focused area of conversing, which is
reshaping our industry First, DevOps
and continuous delivery have become
the backbone of modern software cycles.
Secondly, the subscription economy
has elevated expectations of for
ongoing improvements and value.
And third, the AI itself only.
Thrives when it is continuously updating
and retain all three reinforces each
other, creating a new operating model
that companies are rapidly adopting to.
Next slide is the platform
architecture foundations.
As we all know, the a successful
AI subscription platform must rest
on the four strong fundamentals.
Which is cloud infrastructure,
model management, data
pipelines and service metering.
Robust data pipelines ensure high quality
data following through the systems.
A cloud infrastructure gives a scalable
compute for training and inference
model management provides worsening
rollbacks when it is needed, and
the audits and experimentations.
The metering is essential for
predictable billing and planning.
Without these four data platform, the
platform cannot scale sustainability.
The next one we will talk about
where DevOps meets ai, dim ops.
ML Ops extends DevOps by introducing
model validations, fairness checks,
and continuous model assessment.
Continuous integration.
CI must integrate not only code,
but also data and model artifacts.
Testing needs to be deeper, covering
edge cases, Anders scenarios.
Finally, deployment must be gradual
to maintain reliability and, canary
rollouts and automated rollbacks
are essential to mitigate the risk.
How we can ensure the AI system
performance AI performance can
degrade over time due to data
drift or a drift in concept.
Data drift means the input
changes concept drift means
real world relationship changes.
Monitoring these coupled with proactive
alerting is critical for maintaining
trust and consistent user experience.
This is where continuous
observability of AI pipelines
becomes a non-negotiable practices.
Okay, so some thoughts on
continuous learning pipelines.
Continuous learning pipeline ensures
that our model remain fresh and relevant.
New data must be collected securely,
respecting privacy regulations,
retaining schedules, retraining
schedules Must consider cost
efficiency since training is expensive.
So this cost efficiency becomes very
critical factor and the deployment cycles
must be automated for seamless updates.
And finally, this feedback, integration
feedback, human in the feedback loop.
This is must be structured
to avoid reinforcing biases.
Some thoughts on data quality,
the foundation of AI reliability.
No matter how advanced our model is,
poor data will undermine everything.
So this slides emphasizes the importance
of validations, anomaly, finding
detections, and strong governance.
Stream processing allows us
to catch issues in real time.
And provenance tracking enables full
traceability, which is especially
important for regulated practices.
Now we will talk about
privacy and security measures.
As AI becomes more capable, it
also becomes a target differential.
Privacy ensures.
That individuals cannot
be reverse identified.
Great point.
Okay.
To consider.
And federated learning allows
training without moving data.
Very useful or very useful for healthcare,
financial services, or global enterprises.
Advers defenses protects against
deliberate manipulations of input.
Of or model extractions?
Operational.
What are the operational challenges?
When we are operating at scale?
Okay.
Primarily for cost management,
performance, debugging, team
collaboration, capacity planning,
running AI at scale is, not easy task.
Cost can rapidly increase and if
restraining is not optimized, debugging
becomes very challenging due to
interconnected nature of data algorithm
and infrastructure capacity planning
must balance training requirements
with real time inference and teams
must collaborate very closely.
Data sciences, ML engineering, DevOps,
and domain partners are all a need shared.
They all need to share the
tools and the language.
So compliance and accountability.
As it grows, it becomes very critical.
Regulations evolving faster
than they were GDPR and CCPA.
Is this requires a strong data management
practices algorithm transparency.
What it means that, especially it
is very important industry where AI
decision impact people, id people lives.
Machine unlearning is
an emerging requirement.
Removing specific data influences
from train models and audit
trails ensure traceability for
legal and operational reviews.
What are the customer success
strategies, which we need to follow?
For the AI subscriptions
platforms, customer success is
directly tied to the value ations.
We must translate technical
performance into business outcome.
A strong onboarding experiences
ensures customer integrate the platform
smoothly, uses analytics, helps us.
Understanding adoption, identify
frictions and productively reduce churn.
This is where product engineering
and success team works together
to drive a miserable impact or
to bring a miserable impact.
So few examples of industry applications
where AI, sub AI subscription platform
touches nearly every industry.
A few examples are here in media.
They improve content
discovery part in retail.
They personalized what user wants
and how user's shopping experience
can be enhanced in healthcare.
They enable more accurate
diagnostic while navigating
regulations in financial services.
Very sensitive and if
not handled properly.
I mean there are a lot of, there are
big chances to like impact people
directly because this is storing
the financial data and the financial
services they drive the fraud, right?
With the fraud prevention, the
risk management, this variety
demonstrated the worst reality and the
necessity of scalable AI operations.
Market dynamics talks.
What it means that we are seeing intensify
competitions across the AI ecosystems.
Cloud providers leads infrastructure while
the startups excel in specialization.
Pricing models continue to evolve towards
uses and outcome based like tiered
subscription, which is fixed model.
We are also seeing market consolidations,
but vertical specialization
remains a strong advantage.
Open source accelerates innovation,
which we always need, but increase
operational complexity, which is why
many companies may choose managed
services over open source solutions.
So what is the future trends?
Where we are heading
towards future trends?
Talks about that next wave.
AI will be defined by autonomy, will
be defined by multimodality, how we
democrat democratize it, and how a
repo our design is responsible enough.
AI agents will increasingly
handle multi-step tasks.
Multi-model AI will unlock.
Richer understanding and a
generation across formats.
No code and automation will
empower non-technical users.
Good, great stuff.
And responsible AI will shift
from aspirations to mandatory
practice across industries.
So future trends looks very
encouraging and, it'll, okay.
So how will navigate this
transformation journey?
To Succeed organization must balance
these five pillars, starting from
strategic vision, organization, culture,
technical capabilities, continuous value
delivery, and operational excellence.
Strategic reasons, cultural readiness,
technical maturity, operational
excellence, and continuous value delivery.
These all shift to subscription
AI platforms fundamentally
changes how companies plans
execute and measure success.
DevOps provides this velocity,
subscription provides the
incentive for long term value.
AI provides the intelligence.
So if we navigate all these
five aspects carefully.
I guess the future, which
we are talking about future
trends is, seems a possibility.
So this conclude my presentation.
Thank you all.
I hope this gave you a clear understanding
of how AI subscription models and DevOps
practices are converging to shape the
next decade of int intelligence systems.
Was more thank you.