Speaker 9: Hello and welcome.
My name is Gareth Hemsley.
I'm a product manager at Dynatrace.
I'm pleased to be here today to
talk to you about how you can
go from Zero to DevSecOps Hero
by extending Microsoft Center.
So the information presented in my
session today is based on our personal
experience and my own opinions,
not those of my employer mention
of any specific product or service.
Does not imply endorsement.
I also don't claim to be an
expert in all or in fact any of
the areas we'll talk about today.
An article published by the
Economist in 2017 highlighted
how data had surpassed oil as the
driving force of the global economy.
Just as oil fueled industrial growth
data now powers the digital area,
enabling companies like Google, Amazon,
and Facebook to dominate the market.
Of course, the value of data has
not gone unnoticed by bad actors.
According to the 2023 data breach
report published by Identity Theft
Resource Center, the number of data
breaches stayed fairly constant over
2021 and 2022 at 1800 public incidents.
But in 2023, data breaches reached
an all time high with 3,205 publicly
reported incidents affecting over 353
million individuals, marking a staggering
78% increase from the previous year.
This surge highlights our data has
become a prime target for actors,
as in organizations and individuals
increasingly rely on digital platforms.
According to the data breach report,
social engineering led the pack
accounting for 18.5% of breaches
followed by ransomware at 10.4%, malware
at 4.9%, and zero day tax at 4.6%.
What is unfortunately not
surprising is that 74% of all
breaches involve the human element.
This continues to underscore
the importance of addressing
human vulnerabilities such
as phishing, pretexting, and
other manipulative tactics.
Ransomware continues to be a lucrative
strategy for cyber criminals as
organizations are often forced to
pay to regain access to their data.
Unfortunately, today's operation teams
are not only challenged by attackers,
they're also challenged by complexity.
The digital landscape is growing
more intricate every day.
Organizations rely on multiple
tools and systems across on-premise,
cloud and hybrid environments.
This complexity makes it difficult
for operation teams to manage
oversight, leading to gaps in security.
Of course, the sheer volume
of data generated by modern
IT systems is also staggering.
With data flowing in from endpoints,
networks, cloud services, and IOT devices,
operation teams are inundated with
alerts, many of which are false positives.
This alert fatigue makes it harder
to detect real threats in real time.
Managing security operations
is also expensive.
The need for advanced tools,
skilled personnel, and continuous
training drives up cost.
Moreover, the financial impact of
breaches and compliance requirements
adds to the burden, making it
challenging for organizations to
allocate resources effectively.
Correlating events across multiple
sources in a world of fragmented data
is a monumental task without a proper
correlation, without proper correlation.
Critical insights are missed, and
teams struggle to connect the dots
between seemingly unrelated events.
According to the threat stack SecOps
report, 52% of companies admitted to
sacrificing cybersecurity measures
to meet business deadlines or
achieve faster product releases.
This statistic underscores a common
tension in the DevOps workflow where
the pressure to deliver quickly often
leads to cutting corners on security.
Organizations must recognize that speed
and security are not mutually exclusive.
By embedding security practices into the
DevOps pipeline, transforming it into
the DevSecOps pipeline teams can achieve
both agility and robust protection.
This, of course, requires fostering
a culture of collaboration between
development operations and security teams.
Alongside leveraging automation and
advanced tools to streamline the
processes without compromising safety,
the ultimate goal is to deliver
innovation at speed while safeguarding
against evolving cyber threats.
Microsoft Sentinel empowers SOC
teams by combining advanced threat
hunting, security orchestration,
automation, and response.
So saw capabilities.
Integration with external systems
to streamline the incident
lifecycle and remediation process.
Sentinel enables SOC teams to define
complex analytics rules to detect threats.
These rules can trigger automated
incident creation, ensuring that threats
are flagged and addressed immediately.
Reducing the time to
detection and response.
Central saw capabilities, leverage
playbooks and automation rules
to manage incidents centrally.
These tools allow teams to standardize
incident handling, automated re
repetitive tasks, and orchestrate
responses across multiple tools.
Automation reduces the manual effort
required for incident response, enabling
faster revolution resolution, and allowing
analysts to focus on more critical tasks.
The MATA Attack framework is a
globally recognized knowledge
base that maps adversary
behavior into structured tactics.
So what attack attackers aim
to achieve, and techniques
how they want to achieve it?
Microsoft Sentinel integrates
this framework to help SOC teams
identify and classify threats
within their environments.
Bylining hunting queries and
analytics rules to Mitre tactics.
Sentinel provides a clear and standardized
view of potential attack parts.
Sentinel's hunting queries are
grouped by a MA attack tactics
such as initial access, privilege,
acceleration, and data exfiltration.
This allows SOC teams to focus their
investigations on specific stages
of an attack, making it easier
to identify and mitigate threats.
Sentinel includes pre-built queries
designed to uncover potential threats.
These queries are mapped to
specific tactics and techniques.
Guiding analysts towards the
right data and helping them
uncover issues in the environment.
Analysts can sort and filter queries
by data source tactics or techniques.
This flexibility allows teams to
prioritize high risk areas and
focus on the most relevant alerts.
Microsoft Sentinel's content hub is a
game changer for SOC teams, providing
them with the tools and integrations they
need to protect their organizations in
an increasingly complex threat landscape.
By leveraging the centralized
marketplace, operations teams can
enhance their security posture while
reducing the time and efforts spent
on configuration and management.
Microsoft Partners can publish
their own connectors and solutions
directly to the content hub, making
it easier for their customers to
adopt and deploy these integrations.
This open ecosystem fosters
collaboration and innovation, allowing
organizations to benefit from a
constantly expanding library of tools.
So does Sentinel have the
vendor integration, which you're
looking for in the content hub?
If not, we can create it in
a couple of simple steps.
For example, take Dynatrace Runtime
application protection, which is
a security solution that detects
and mitigates sophisticated
threats like SQL injection.
JNDI Injection Command Injection
S-S-R-R-F attacks in real time.
It provides code level visibility through
its one agent technology, and enables
automatic blocking of detected attacks.
In this presentation, we're looking
for a vendor which exposes rest
APIs, which can be leveraged to bring
the vendors' insights into sentel.
In this case, Dynatrace provides APIs
to query all attacks as well as to
get the details of a specific attack.
So Microsoft Sentinel provides a couple of
options for building connectors to bring.
To query these rest APIs and bring
the relevant insights into centel.
First option is Logic Apps.
So these can be acquired
through the content hub.
They have fairly intermediate rest
API support, right when in a what
is what you get style interface.
But unfortunately, they require
additional Azure resources deployed
to their customer environment.
Another option is Azure functions.
These also can be acquired
through the Content Hub.
They have far superior rest API support
right in code, but unfortunately, they
also require additional Azure resources
deployed in the customer environment.
The
final option is Codeless
Connector framework.
These can also be acquired
through the content hub.
They have fairly limited rest a I
support, but no additional Azure
resources are required in the environment,
in the customer's environment.
So CCF is recommended as Microsoft
hosts and runs these connectors and
the end user does not have to deploy
resources in the Azure environments.
Our data connector will ingest the
raw JS N responses from our rest.
API.
Now when this happens, the
table schema, at least with
the Htt B data collector, API.
Previously the table schema was
automatically defined on ingest
fields were suffixed with their
type, for example, underscore
S for string and tables with
underscore cl for custom tables.
Today Microsoft Sentinel leverages
data transformation and the
advanced security information model.
For normalizing and
enriching ingested data.
This enables efficient threat
detection and investigation.
So now at ingest time, data collection
rules are applied during ingestion
to normalize and transform raw
telemetry, which we saw in the previous
slide into standardized formats.
This process ensures that data
is ready for immediate use,
reducing the overhead of processing
large data sets during analysis.
KQL transformations are applied
at this stage to filter, enrich,
and or structure data before it is
stored in log in links workspace.
At query time, the asim
parser comes into play.
It uses KQL functions to transform and
normalize data dynamically at runtime.
This allows SOC teams to analyze
data from multiple sources using a
consistent schema without needing
to manage the underlying complexity.
Another option is leveraging a custom
parr, which is a source specific
parr, which uses KQL functions.
To do something very similar.
In the slide, we can see an
example of data which has been
ingested via data collection rules.
We can see that the custom table still has
a suffix of under underscore cl, right?
We have the same data type support, so
things like string into long, we were able
to transform the ingested data, adding a
time generated field, which is required.
And it's important to note that billing
is based on the volume of data analyzed,
and of course the storage of that data.
So as we saw, data collection
rules allow us to define the
ingestion pipeline upfront.
We can define the table schema,
we can apply transformations
to the ingested data.
For example, filtering.
Adding fields, removing fields, and we can
also send data to multiple destinations.
Once you ingested your data, you
can use custom query language to
perform advanced analytics across the
entire data set as well as produce.
Visualizations of these results.
In the next slide, we'll see how you
can also leverage KQL For runtime
analytics, we can reduce human error
and increase accuracy by automating
threat detection in Sentinel.
We can do this by using analytics rules.
We can schedule KQL queries to
be evaluated continuously and
trigger creation of alerts.
We can also automatically create
incidents to be triaged and
remediated by operations teams.
Sentinel Connects.
Raw telemetry from various sources
such as logs, network activity,
and user authentication events.
We could, for example, query failed
login attempts across systems to
identify potential brute force attacks.
We would create a scheduled
analytics rule using our KQL query.
In this example, a rule is configured
to detect 10 failed login attempts
within a five minute window.
These rules are run at regular intervals.
Analyzing raw data from a
defined lookback period.
If the query results exceed a defined
threshold, the rule generates an alert.
When the rule detects suspicious activity,
such as a repeated fail login from
the same IP address alert is created.
These alerts can be aggregated
into an incident that SOC
teams can investigate further.
There are some additional rule
types, which you could, which are
available the near realtime rules.
These are prior faster detection
by running queries every minute.
These are ideal for time
sensitive threats, anomaly rules.
These use advanced machine learning
to identify unusual patterns in the
data and Microsoft security rules.
These automatically create incidents
in Sentinel based on alerts from
other Microsoft security solutions
such as Microsoft Defense.
So Sentinel enables organizations
to monitor the health of their data
ingestion processes using tools
like the Data Collection, health
Monitoring workbook, and the sen
the Sentinel Health Data Table.
The Health Monitoring workbook is
basically an out of box workbook,
provides comprehensive view
of the data ingestion process.
It allows teams to monitor
ingestion, size, latency, and
the number of logs per source.
The workbook includes three key
tabs, the overview tab, which
displays overall ingestion status.
The data collection anomalies
tab highlights, irregularities or
interruptions in data ingestion,
and the agent's information tab
monitors the health and connectivity
of logger analytics agents, ensuring
that is being collected as expected.
The Sentinel Health Data table
provides granular insights into
the status of the data connectors.
Ingestion health.
It tracks success and failure events
for each connector, enabling teams to
identify and resolve issues quickly.
The table supports querying for specific
health drifts, such as connectors
transitioning from success to failure,
or identifying the latest failure events.
Okay.
Let's take a look at how you
would build your first connector.
As I mentioned previously in, in
the session, Microsoft maintains
a GitHub repository where all the.
Sentinel Solutions are,
source code is available.
So you can see here all the
instructions basically for
contributing to this repo are here.
If we look, there's a solutions folder.
This is where we will
primarily be working.
Today in this demo, I will, yeah,
I'll show you exactly what you,
what steps you need to execute.
To create a new solution which
will be available in Sentinel.
Okay, so let's open up
this repository locally.
Alright.
If we're go into the solutions folder,
we go and look for an existing solution,
which I created, which is Dynatrace.
So we have to follow the convention.
Of basically the vendor name in the
solution folder, and then within
that vendor's folder, analytics
rules data connectors package.
This is produced when you actually
when you compile your solution
pauses, playbooks, and workbooks.
Okay.
So an important thing that you need
to create is the metadata file.
So the metadata file describes all the
artifacts which are part of your solution.
It also describes, how your
solution is supported and you're
able to provide description,
logo, et cetera for your solution.
Okay.
What we saw in the presentation is that
the very first thing you know, how you get
data into Sentinel is via data connectors,
or one of the ways is via data connectors.
And in this demo we're gonna look
at how you would create a data
collection, rule based data connector.
Okay.
There are a number of files
that we need to create, right?
We can see here we need to
define essentially the data
collection rule itself, right?
And so this basically we need to
define the schema for the table, right?
When we ingesting this data, we need to
define the destinations where we want
to actually send the incoming telemetry.
And then another very important
step is we need to define the
transformation query, which we'll use.
So the custom query, which we use to
transform the data as it, it's ingested.
Okay?
So another very important
file, which we need to.
We need to create, is we need to actually
set up the polling configuration, right?
So we are gonna build a
codeless a CCF connector, right?
So we don't want the customer
to have to manage any sort
of infrastructure in Azure.
We want Microsoft to basically manage
the polling and the the running of the
connector within their infrastructure.
Okay, so of course we need
to give it a a useful name.
And basically in this file, what
you can do is we can say we can
define things like what specific.
Parameters are required right
when polling the rest endpoint.
So of course we need to know
the address of the endpoint, and
this can be parameterized, right?
So we will see in the UI how we actually
provide the Dynatrace environment, URL.
But basically we concatenate that
with the actual rest endpoint,
which we are gonna connect to.
We can define, the HTT P method.
We can define also how retries happen.
We can define time format.
So this is for basically
for the query string, right?
We ask the API to return, attacks
in this case between two different
two a start time and an end time.
We can also define some HTP headers.
And any additional query parameters
which we would have to which
are needed by the rest API.
In the response we can actually tell
the connector where to look for the
data that's important to us, right?
In the json.
In this case, we're
looking at their tax array.
Finally, we can actually
specify which DCR to use.
And so this was the file
that we saw previously.
We referenced this from
the polling config.
And of course very important
is how paging happens, right?
In this case we're looking to
use next page token paging type.
And we're looking at basically
we we specify, what, where the
page token is in the response.
So in this case it's called next page key.
And we can also, it's redundant in
this case, but we can also rename,
the next page query string parameter.
Okay.
So another file we need to
define is the table file.
So workspace table.
So in this case we define the schema
for this table which is used in the DCR.
As I mentioned time generators
is a required field.
Here we can, we define what the schema
will look like after transformation.
So you can see there's no suffixes
on, on field names, which indicate
types on an underscore s in this case,
we also define then the type of each
of those fields right in the table.
Okay, now once we have those three
other files, we can now tie 'em
together with the definition file.
So here what we need to do is we
basically, we can define the connector ui.
I can show you in a little bit what
that looks like, but basically we
can we can define, what the publisher
name, description, all those things
that, will need to be displayed in
the Azure portal to the end user.
We can also define some example
queries as well as graph
queries for example, for the.
How much data has been received over,
over time, and which table to look at.
We can, this availability section
basically we use that to mark
a connector as preview in this
case, I'm using it in the demo.
And you would set this to false, right?
When it a connector would
be generally available.
Generally available.
We can define what permissions are
required, right on the workspace itself.
So we need to, of course right
permissions are required on
the workspace to ingest data.
And then we can define some custom
elements which which are displayed, right?
So in this case, I specify, the
requirements on the vendor side.
So in this case, we need a Dynatrace
tenant with a specific feature activated.
And of course we need an access
token which allows us to read attacks
from, the best endpoint in this case.
An access token is used for
authentication, but obviously
the connector framework supports
multiple types of authentication.
We also need to define instructions
for the end user, right?
In this case, the customer has the
su supplier, us with the URL right?
For their tenant, which they want, or the
environment that they want to connect to.
Then, as I mentioned before,
an access token is required.
So this is something that the the
end user has to provide us as well.
Finally we set up a connection,
connect toggle button which
you'll see later in the ui.
Okay, so that's the data connector itself.
I'll show you in a little bit
how we actually what that looks
like right in the Azure portal.
So some other interesting
things to show you, I think in
this demo are analytics rules.
So we can define analytics rules
for our solution as well, so we
can, this essentially creates a
analytics rule template right in
your Sentel workspace, which you
can then create instances of that.
You can create an instance of that.
And run it, to raise alerts, right?
As I mentioned in, in the presentation.
So in this case, what we're doing
is we're, it's defined in yaml, in
this, in, in my demo, but we give
it a name description status which
connector it's actually, dependent on,
as well as, the query frequency, the
query period and basically tactics.
So the matter framework tactics and
techniques, how we group the alerts.
And then very important, of course,
is the query that we want to run.
In this case, we, we're looking for
attacks which are not allowed listed.
Okay.
And we're giving it a custom name.
So based on basically a format, so
we're looking to call it Dynatrace
attack with this current state display
id, which is from Dynatrace, and
then the display name from Dynatrace.
From the Dynatrace attack.
Okay.
We are also configuring that we should
create incidents based on these at alerts.
And we group the alerts over the
last seven days and we have to match.
So we're doing entity mapping here.
We need to match, all entities within
the alert for that to be grouped.
Okay, I won't go into a lot of detail.
But we also have some pauses included
in the solution as well as playbooks
which essentially, are automation allow
you to automate processes based on
like alerts or events sorry, incidents.
And we can also include
workbooks in our solution.
So workbooks, like
dashboards, essentially.
Okay, so what does that look
like in the Azure portal?
So we can see, we can come to Content Hub
in this case I have we can see Dynatrace
has a solution published to Content Hub.
We can see all the content, which
is included in the solution, right?
So things like analytics, rule templates
data connectors, workbooks pauses,
that's all available in this solution.
So in this case, I've already installed
the connector, but basically if
it was not installed, you'd have
the option to install it here.
Okay.
So once it's installed once it's
installed, you will see that
there'll be a number of, data
Connect is available to you.
So for the purposes of our
demo, we're looking at attacks.
So in this case, I've created
a V two, which is a preview
version of the connector which is
leverages data collection rules.
And the V one was basically
the prior version, right?
Which used prior technology from CCF.
Okay.
So if we open that V two connector page.
We will see it's already connected, right?
So right now attacks are being
ingested into te into sentinel.
We can see over time, how many attacks
have or events have been received.
Could, we can see here what we
defined in the JSON files, right?
In the UI config, we can see the the.
The customer or the end user
needs a Dynatrace tenant with
specific feature enabled.
We can see that an access token
is required and we can provide,
documentation to the end user on how to.
Just hit those things up.
We also need to get, of course the URL of
the environment that the end user wants
to monitor and access token, in this case,
on, to authenticate those risk calls.
Okay.
So the other thing which
we can do is we can create.
So we can come in and look at the
rule templates, which were provided.
So in, in this case, there are
a number of different templates
provided out the box by the solution.
In our case, we're interested
in attack detection.
So here we can say, okay, create
a new rule based on this template.
By default the arguments or the
parameters that you see the inputs
are set to default values, right?
Which we defined in the solution
in the YAML that you saw earlier.
We can change this if we like, we
can change, alter the severity, we
can alter the Mitre characteristics.
We can also come through and say, okay we
wish to alter the KQL query, which is run.
Which is scheduled.
We can define different entity mapping.
In this case, we're
mapping ips and host names.
We can also change the query scheduling.
So currently it's run every one
day and we look back one day.
We can change the threshold
right where alert is generated in
our case, if there's more than.
Zero items in a return, then
we want to generate an alert.
In our case we also trigger an alert
for each event, but you could also
group these into a single alert.
Okay.
We can configure incident creation,
so in this case we are by default.
And then we are also
configuring alert grouping.
So we are grouping alerts, from
the last seven days into a single
incident if the entities match.
It's possible also to trigger
automation rules or playbooks, right?
Using a, analytics rule.
In this case, we'll leave it like it is.
Click save.
Okay.
So now what we'll see is that alerts
will start to be generated based
on this new rule that we've set up.
Okay.
We've seen what what our solution
looks like in the Azure portal.
Now something I haven't shown you yet is
how you actually package your solution.
Your, the content for your solution
into a package, which you can then,
submit to the partner, Microsoft Partner
Center and publish right publicly.
So let's take a look at how we do that.
So what we need is basically to copy the
path to the data folder in your solution.
We go into the tools folder
within the repository, right?
So if we look at, I'm here currently
at that path within the repo I
run sorry, I run the PowerShell
script, create solution V three.
I paste in my solution
data folder path, right?
This goes through a number of steps,
preparing basically the new package
which we'll be able to publish.
Okay?
Once that's completed it produces a
number of output files, number of output.
And also a package file, right?
So if we go and look at that, so we
go into our package folder, right?
You'll see there's a
new version, a zip file.
So 3.0 0.2 which we would use to
publish our solution publicly.
But what is also interesting is
that we have, the UI definition
file as well as the arm template.
So the Azure Resource Manager
template, which we could.
Potentially use.
So you can actually go into the
Azure portal and you can just,
you can say deploy custom template
and we can say, build our own template.
We can load the file.
So in this case let's get
the path to that fall.
Okay, we click save.
We then can provide in this case,
we can create a new resource group.
We provide all the parameters, right?
In this case, the analytics workspace.
Resource group, the location for the
workspace, the name of the workbook that
we wanna create, resource group name.
You can leave these values as
they are, they'll take whatever's
set at the deployment level.
And once you've entered in all
these parameters, you click next.
And this will essentially deploy
the solu, the side load the solution
right into your subscription.
So you won't have to publish it
by a partner center, for example.
You can actually deploy this way to
test your solution and the content that
you're deploying with your solution.
This is what I did for this demo.
Our goal as an enterprise should be
to limit threat impact by triggering
immediate response on threat detection.
Manual triage and remediation
is often slow prone to human
error and resource intensive.
Security teams face challenges such
as delayed responses to threats,
high operational costs due to 24 7.
Staffing needs fatigue and
burnout from handling repetitive
tasks and high alert volume.
Automated triage and remediation Sentinel
replaces manual workflows with automated
triage and remediation processes, ensuring
threats are addressed in real time.
Automation rules and playbooks are
used to evaluate alerts continuously,
trigger immediate responses, and
reduce the cost of operations.
Thank you so much for
watching my session today.
I hope to see you again really soon.