Speaker 48: Hello everyone.
I hope you're enjoying
the conference so far.
My name is Vishnu Kumar and I'm a supply
chain management solution architect,
primarily focusing on warehouse
management, optimization and automation.
Today I would like to talk to you
about site level engineering for
supply chain management which can be
used to build reliable warehouses for.
Making use of the human and AI
factors, combining them and then
making the warehouses more reliable
to meet the growing demands of today.
Let's get into it during this session.
Whenever you're watching the session,
if you have any questions, please
feel free to reach out to me.
You can connect with me on LinkedIn.
I'm always open to answering questions.
All right, so now let's talk
about supply chain in general.
Now supply chain to simply put
it, is to transport goods from
point A to point B, right?
That's the most simplest of
explanations anyone can give for
supply chain management to take
items from point A to point B.
Now what people.
Outside of supply chain do not understand
is how difficult it is to get items from
point A to point B is, and what happens
in those huge buildings trying to take
items from point A to point B, right?
That's what supply chain is all about.
And that is my area of work where
we try to optimize the systems,
optimize the processes make efficient.
Business practices within the warehouses
so that the 0.8 point B transfer can be
done effectively economically and quickly.
So in today's world with e-commerce,
the boom in e-commerce, right?
People are purchasing stuff online
all the time, and the demand for.
Fast warehouses, fast shipping, fast
order processing has grown multifold.
So that has resulted in
unprecedented in an unprecedented
growth in the supply chain space.
Now, when we talk about.
The recent advancements in supply chain.
We talk about integrations
with iot sensors.
We talk about integrations with
ai, we talk about disturb twins,
we talk about all that, right?
But what we don't gently talk about
is how supply chain management and how
warehouse management is not getting
the attention that other areas get.
Say like cloud systems, right?
It's something that many companies or
many organizations neglect or do not
pay much attention to and then end up,
trying to optimize it at a later stage.
So that is something I would
like to talk about today.
Now, production grade reliability
practices is something that we
are focusing on, where I'm going
to talk about how these systems.
Need monitoring and optimizing early
on, even when these systems are being
designed and put in place, even during
the implementation phase of these systems,
if you can I incorporate these components
into it and how it can turn the system
and the overall warehouse efficient,
the overall supply chain efficient.
And we'll also be talking about how,
the system can incorporate both the
human and the AI elements, combine
it, and then use it to give much
faster, much efficient throughputs.
Right now, what's the challenge
in modern day warehouses?
Now, one of the most critical areas of
it is the number of layers involved.
In today's warehouse, we have a system
that takes care of the inventory
management, it takes care of all
the stock monitoring and all that.
We have a system that takes care
of transportation management.
We have a system.
If there is a three PL involved,
we have a system that takes care
of three pl. We have system that
takes care of procurement, sales.
There are all these different systems
and maintenance production, all these
different systems that work together.
They're all integrated to the warehouse
and they're all integrated and are part
of the overall supply chain process.
Now, when it comes to it, regular
proven methods that we have been
using so far where we have been doing
manual interventions to do picking
optimizations, to do route planning, to
do demand forecasting, all of these have.
Proven to fall short to cater to the
growing demand of today's consumers.
So that's why where we are trying to
include AI driven optimizations, we are
trying to bring in autonomous systems
robots that can pick we have automated
storage and retrieval systems that can
go up and down, high racks reducing work.
Work site incidents increasing safety
for workers who doesn't, who they don't
have to go up all the way up to the
high rack area and pick it themselves.
We have automated systems
for it these days.
Many companies are using it now.
Some of the areas where we can
improve it is AI driven optimization.
Where we can talk about how picking
algorithms can be optimized and
made efficient, how route planning
can be done so that maximum
efficiency is obtained when planning
an order that is being shipped.
How demand forecasting can be done using
AI models where based on seasonal demand
or based on any other types of demand
or low demand, how the procurement can
be done, or how production practices
can be adjusted based on the demand and.
We obviously talked about the autonomous
systems, robots and retrieval systems,
automated systems within the warehouse.
And of course we still need the human
touch within the warehouse where there'll
have to go through quality, we'll have
to go through exception handling or
that needs, still needs the human touch.
And also any task that requests judgment
still needs to go through the human touch.
And then we also have predictive
maintenance where a lot of these sites
do run 24 7 and we cannot always go into.
A breakdown maintenance rather than, we
should always plan ahead, see what type
of maintenance these equipments might need
so that before something breaks down and
causes a production loss, we are always
ready to, do predictive maintenance,
preventive maintenance, and then make
sure that we are not having the downtime.
So that is also something
that can be achieved with
the sensors and integrations.
Now again, I did talk about
how traditional monitoring
falls short because.
When we talk about traditional models,
it always involves a manual input.
It always involves someone going into the
warehouse or someone going into one of
these production facilities or maintenance
facilities, and then seeing how the
machines are doing, how the components are
doing, how the equipments are doing, and
then deciding if it requires a maintenance
or if one of these items needs more stock,
or if one of these items needs, less
stock because the demand is not that much.
It is all based on annual judgment and.
In high volume warehouses.
It is just a lot of data to go through.
And also all of this is based on
just like I said, human judgment.
So we do tend to miss subtle
changes that can happen, which.
At that time might not be huge,
but then down the line, it can
have a big impact in how we manage
and run the warehouse, right?
So these models, if we train them and if
we have algorithms in place, it can catch
hold of these subtle changes early on.
And then let us know if we have to make
those adjustments in our process so
that we are ready when those changes
in the demand comes, or when that
change in the overall supply chain.
Process comes in and when we have to
talk about, or when we have to go into
the maintenance mode, when a certain
item requires a fix if these models
and sensors are able to give us that
information beforehand, we would be
able to have that predictive maintenance
and reduce the overall downtime
and increase production throughput.
So that's where the traditional
models fall short, and that's where
we'll be talking about using all
of these sensors and algorithms.
Which can help us run our Vs.
A much in a much more efficient manner.
That's what I'm talking about.
Okay.
Now some of the core elements when you
want to implement such a model in the
warehouse is first you need to identify
your service level indicator, right?
You need to understand what you're
trying to achieve with this model.
Do you want to do increase
your picking accuracy?
Do you want to increase
your inventory accuracy?
Do you want to increase or,
decrease the number of times you go?
Go to pick an item and then find
out that the item is not there.
So that is something that
falls under inventory accuracy.
Do you want to reduce the number
of such occurrences, right?
What is your service level indicator?
What is something that you're
trying to achieve with the system?
And then you need to have error budgets.
You need to have tolerances on how
much of certain thing is tolerable.
You need to tell the system that.
I can have up to 10% variance
or I can have up to 5% variance.
And then you need to also talk
about automated remediation.
Where if say for example, you go to a
certain win in a warehouse, you try to
pick an item, and then you go there and
then realize the item is not there, but
the system tells you that the item is
there, but physically it's not there.
Now what happens?
You need to block the pen.
You need to tell the system
that something's going on.
The item is not there, but the system
keeps telling you that the item
is there, and then you need to go
into that exception handling mode.
And then what happens after the exception
is raised, how it is handled, what kind
of investigation's done and all that.
So we need to have that automated
remediation also built in.
And then we need to also talk
about, observe the pipelines, right?
How we can observe the components
and machines and equipments
that are working in these sites.
How we can gather information from
those sensors and how we can make use
of that information to make sure we are
doing predictive maintenance right now.
Let's talk about the sensors for a bit.
Now we're talking about
IOT sensors, right?
Internet of Things.
We have various types of
sensors like mentioned here.
We have temperature, motion, weight which.
Monitors keeps monitoring these systems.
These, equipments these machines 24 7.
And it has various aspects of monitoring
that it does and various indicators
that it keeps giving us as an output.
And if something changes based on
the change in the indicator, we
would be able to determine if that
specific machine or piece of machine.
Needs to go through any sort of
adjustment, needs to go through any sort
of maintenance, any sort of replacement.
So by using this information beforehand,
and by having this update beforehand, you
would be able to fix it before it breaks.
So that's what we call
predictive maintenance, right?
And also preventive maintenance.
So if something breaks.
And then you try to go fix it.
You need parts for it, right?
You need to order parts for it.
You might not always have it in stock
to fix something, and then you need
to wait for the parts to come to you.
So that's gonna take time.
So that's why we talk about
predictive maintenance.
We are like, okay, I'm just going
to fix things before it breaks.
I'm just going to constantly monitor
it and then fix it before it breaks so
that I can avoid production downtime.
Because when a machine goes down,
when one of these components
go down these sites, which.
Sorry, which usually run 24 7.
One of these machines, you have to shut
it down until you get a replacement
component and until you can fix it,
the machine is going to be shut down.
That causes production loss and
based on what kind of industry you're
in, it can be a huge loss, right?
You cannot predict how long it
might take a component to be fixed.
There could be supply chain
disruption, so that's why.
Predictive maintenance is an
important component of these
high velocity sites, right?
And based on the information
from these sensors, you can
always train the algorithms.
You can have.
Vast amounts of sensor data analyzed,
and it can keep telling you if
something needs to be changed.
And then we can talk about the basic
KPIs that needs to be monitored.
How soon you're fulfilling your
orders, how soon you're picking, how
soon you're sending stuff outside
your warehouse from the time you got.
You received a customer order, by the
time somebody goes to your warehouse
and picks it, and then by the time it
leaves your site, it's issued out and
then it's on the way to its customer.
You can track these times to make sure
that you identify any bottlenecks in
this process, and then make sure that
you're also optimizing the process so
that the overall customer satisfaction
is also improved and you don't have any.
Holdups in your overall process
because something is not working
the way it is supposed to.
Alright.
And then digital twin.
So that's something that has been
that's being used widely in the supply
chain area simply because when it
comes to supply chain management and
warehouse management we have various
softwares that are being used to handle.
Activities, data, activities
within the warehouse.
Again, just like I mentioned, we
talk about inventory handling,
where all the inventory is stored.
We talk about picking where you
pick stuff from your warehouse,
shoot it to a customer order.
You do put away, you receive
stock from the vendor and you
sort it into the warehouse.
You do internal movements within
the warehouse, and then you talk
about inventory accuracy, where
you do go do cycle counts, right?
You count and make sure that your entire
warehouse, the stock levels are good.
It is as per what is there at
physically in the s is what is
being reported in the system, right?
You do all that now.
If you take a high velocity warehouse
where a lot of these activities are
happening on a day-to-day basis,
any implementation, any change that
you do, any new system that you try
to implement is going to cause a
disruption because it's just brand
new and the volume is too high, right?
And even when something changes
a pattern emerges, right?
Say for example.
There is a high demand for a specific
material, and then you certainly get a lot
of orders for it, or there is low demand.
Certainly the demand drops because
of, it could be various reasons.
It could be natural calamities,
or it could be a geopolitical
reasons, it could be anything.
So demand can raise or go down
and during those situations,
how your warehouse handles.
Those situations, how your
warehouse handles the volume is
something that you can only say
when you go through it, right?
So that's when digital twin helps,
where you can create a digital twin,
a copy of your warehouse, and then
simulate these variations in the
business process and then see how
your current process is holding up.
Say for example, you can test just
like I said, you can test a high.
Demand scenario and see how your
warehouse, or how your current warehouse
set up, how your current system set
up is built, sorry, is able to cope
up with that kind of a demand, right?
So that is when stillton helps
in the overall simulation.
And then you can review the
results and then you can decide.
Which areas in your process, which
areas in your system needs refinement to
handle those changes Right now, that's a
replica, that's what I'm talking about.
Now let's talk about analytics
and predictive maintenance
a little bit, right?
So the first step is that
you need information.
You need a lot of data to do the analysis
and then come up with predictive and
predictive maintenance schedules.
So the first step is data collection.
You need seasonal patterns to identify
when a material can be in demand and
when a material can go out of demand.
You need to think about the trends,
the growth trends and then you need
to go to predictive models where
machine learning models will identify.
Identify these capacity that in
which your warehouse is operating.
Incorporate the data collected, run
simulations, and then tell you, this
is when you might go through a high
demand phase, and this is how your
warehouse is acute to handle the volume.
High volume or less volume, right?
How your warehouse is equipped to do that.
And then you can also talk about automated
alerts and recommendations on how your
infrastructure is currently holding up and
how your infrastructure might need some
kind of a change to accommodate say an up
upcoming change that can be really big.
And if your virus is not ready.
For that kind of a scenario, then
these models can let you know, and
then you can make those changes.
Now talking about these automated
systems, we need it, it goes through
several steps through the process, right?
So the first is detection.
We need to know what, when, right?
And then the diagnosis, why the
remediation, what happens next?
And then the verification.
What was done to fix it?
Did it really solve the problem?
So the first step in the
process is detection.
Now, in that step is when you monitor
the system and then you try to identify
if there is a failure or if there is.
Degradation in the performance, right?
That's when you get into that
predictive maintenance mode.
If it is a failure, it goes
to breakdown maintenance.
If it is a performance degradation, then
we go into the predictive maintenance
model, and then we go to the diagnosis.
Now, based on the information detected,
we go and check and analyze the
data and then decide if it's going
to be a breakdown maintenance, or
if it's going to be a productive.
Preventive maintenance makes it that
the production is not interrupted.
And then we see what
kind of an issue it is.
Is it a component health issue?
Is it a connectivity issue?
Is it data inconsistency?
Is it a volume issue?
Is it a process issue and all that.
And then we talk about remediation.
We talk about.
Steps that we can take to make sure that
whatever anomaly that was just detected,
whatever issue that was just detected, is
not going to cause harm for the business.
Not going to cause production
outages and cause revenue loss.
Now we can talk about a bunch of
self-healing or automated responses
to these anomalies now in here.
Sorry.
Now in here when these items, or
when these anomalies occur, there
are certain steps that the system
itself can take just to make sure
that, that situation is averted,
but that can not always be the case.
So we should also build that human
factor into it so that there is
someone who is always overseeing these
actions and making sure that, there
is a human judgment factor to it.
Just to ensure that whatever action
is being taken is the right course
of action for that situation, right?
So that comes into the verification model.
Just because you throw a bunch of
resources at a problem doesn't mean that
the problem is getting resolved, right?
You need to make sure that you throw the
right resources at the problem so that
the problem is resolved, and then that it
is also a permanent fix to the solution
and it's not ha going to happen again.
And then we also have some best practices
that we can follow when you're going
to implement a new system or when
you're going to implement a change
in one of these high volume sites.
So what you can do is always
make sure that any change
that you do version control.
So if something is breaking.
Something is not working right.
With the new version, you can always
revert back to the older version.
And then you should always do
multiple rounds of testing, be
it unit tests, integration tests,
user acceptance tests, right?
Load test, performance test.
All sorts of testing needs
to be performed when you're
implementing a new warehouse system.
And then the type of implementation
that is being done is also.
An important factor.
You don't do a massive implementation
of a big scale all in one go.
You do incremental implementations.
You do incremental rollouts, making
sure that you do the first phase
of it, you observe, see that it's
successful, and then you go to the next
phase of it, implement it, observe,
see that it is successful, and then
you go to the next phase, right?
You don't do all at once.
If something fails, you don't want
the entire network within your
organization to fail because your
implementation did not work out.
And then you also don't want a lot of
downtime for your warehouses during
these system implementations and
during the system changes, right?
Because just like I said, all of
these high volume and high velocity
warehouses, a downturn means.
It could mean millions
in lost revenue, right?
So you cannot have, you cannot
afford to have that kind of downtime.
So whenever you do that, you need
to make sure that you're minimizing
your downtime to the maximum extent
possible, and then making sure that
you're not disrupting live activities
within the warehouse and you're not
disrupting the supply chain activities.
Now you need to, when we talk about
these automated systems where it can have
human ai collaboration and, these systems
suggesting changes, suggesting fixes.
You should also talk about how if
something did not work, something
that the system suggested, something
that these models suggested did not
work, how do you make sure that it.
Is fixed.
How do you make sure that, sorry, how
do you make sure that it is refined?
How do you make sure that it is
working in the next instance that
something like this happens, right?
You need to do an initial assessment on
what happened, why it failed, and what
was the impact of the failure, right?
That is the first thing
that you need to understand.
The second is you need to have a
manual workflow where somebody.
From the warehouse or somebody from
the supply chain organization is
able to go look at it and then see,
okay, some of our systems failed.
That should be a fail safe mechanism
that needs to be triggered.
Now I need someone to go look at the
problem and then come up with a solution
for it because the system was not able
to come up with a solution for it, right?
And the root cause analysis.
We need to find out from
where the problem was.
Was it a problem in these models running
the analysis and giving us outputs?
Was it a problem connecting these systems
to the warehouse management system?
Or was it someone.
Or in the warehouse or in the overall
supply chain model that, we have training
gaps, is not able to do their job the
way that they're supposed to do, right?
So we need to find out where this
problem is coming from, and then we
need to talk about system restoration.
How if such a failure happens, the
system can be restored and brought back
to an extent that it is functioning at
the same level as it was just before.
The breakdown, right?
So we need to make sure we validate
the fix that was being applied.
We need to make sure that we validate
the performance right after the fix.
And then we monitor the situation.
And then after we fix the identified
gaps, we gradually transition back into
the automated operations model, right?
And then we do a post incident
review where we try to understand.
The entirety of what happened,
why something did not work, what
can be done to fix the scenario
if it happens again in the future.
A lessons learned review that we
need to do so that we can prevent a
future recurrence of the same issue.
Now let's talk a little bit
about actionable frameworks for
these platform teams right now.
We have just like I said supply
chain management needs production
grade frameworks, right?
That can help them have reliable
warehouses, scalable warehouses, and
scalable warehouse systems, right?
So one of those items is SLO templates.
So we need to have ready to use service
level objectives so that I know it
is tailored for the s operations.
Observability architecture,
integrating IOT sensors integrating.
Temperature sensors, integrating weight
sensors, integrating it could be RPM
sensors and getting back all their
information, analyzing that information,
and then coming up with suggestions on
if everything is good or if something
needs maintenance and all that.
And then we have automation patterns that
we can talk about where we have workflows.
If something happens,
what the system has to do.
If something is still not right, if
it has to go through a man lower ride,
if it has to go through an exception
handling process, if it needs to get
somebody involved, and all of that control
mechanism that is built into the process.
And then let's, it's to talk about
how to build a production grade
supply chain infrastructure right now.
Like I said, supply chain is a critical
component of any business that is involved
in sending and receiving goods right now.
By applying these site level engineering
principles to warehouse operations, these
platform teams can create predictable.
Self-healing automated fulfillment systems
that can scale with business demands.
Because again, it has all that
information to look at the forecast,
look at the demand forecast, and
make all those decisions, and
then we can ma make use of these
integrations to make sure that we have.
We maintain high service levels, we adapt
and change to growing business needs.
We always maintain higher customer
satisfaction, higher customer
retainment, and make the overall
supply chain process efficient, right?
So that's where these practices come
into picture, and that's where the,
these practices can help any supply
chain organization succeed and keep
succeeding in what they're doing.
That is everything that I
wanted to talk about today.
Thank you so much for listening in.
Again, if you have any questions, please
feel free to reach out to me on LinkedIn.
My name is Vishner Psad Krishna Kumar.
I hope you have a
wonderful rest of your day.
Thank you.