Speaker: Hey everyone.
Welcome to today's talk on
building Enterprise Ready,
CICD pipelines using Agent ai.
My name is Chen Mike Aqua, and I'm
responsible for the technical marketing
of all of the AI products at Harness.
Previously, I've worked for
companies in the DevOps Kubernetes
apps, I observability spaces.
So let's get into the topic.
The agenda for today looks very simple.
It's the what's and whys of
enterprise readiness, the role of
agentic AI and knowledge craft.
And last, but not the least, one of the
most important topics of governance.
Let's start with enterprise readiness.
Before we get into what an enterprise
ready pipeline looks like, let's take
a broader view of the problems in
the CICD space or the DevOps space.
So software delivery workflows today
are very manual and involve a lot
of toil, which means that a lot of
companies still use homegrown scripts.
And point solutions to
manage these pipelines.
And because of this, the velocity at
which the customer gets product updates or
feature updates goes down by quite a bit.
The efficiency of the engineering
team, the security of the code being
delivered to the customers as well
as the resiliency go down as well.
With AI generated code, this problem is
multiplied or it grows exponentially.
As you can see, the bottleneck is
still the software delivery pipeline,
which means that testing, securing,
deploying, and optimizing need to
expand to match the AI generated code.
We've seen a lot of organizations using AI
prototypes to figure out how to use AI to
expand their software delivery pipelines.
AI prototypes take less time to build.
Used to solve the initial capacity problem
and they stop at prompt engineering.
However, with enterprise ai,
you need a robust architecture.
You need something that demands
consistency and reliability, and you
also need something that masters context
engineering We'll get into what is the
difference between prompt engineering
and context engineering a bit later in
the session, but because of this, these
differences, majority of the prototypes
fail to scale at enterprise level.
So the need for enterprise readiness
basically comes from the fact that
almost 80% of the SDLC failures
don't happen during code generation.
They happen after the code is written.
The tools sprawl doesn't
help this problem.
It basically amplifies it.
So with tools sprawl, you have a lot
of unshared context, which basically
means that you create fragile
pipelines, which basically means that.
The code is not being delivered to the
customers in a secure and reliable way.
Manual policy enforcement is another
blocker to this, which basically means
that you have a lot of bottlenecks in the
governance and security aspect of things.
All of this basically means that teams are
stuck balancing between speed and safety.
So enterprise pipelines need to solve
the velocity and the control problem
simultaneously, and which is where.
Agent AI can be really effective.
Let's define what an
enterprise pipeline means.
Here's a simple layout of a pipeline.
I know enterprise pipelines can
get really complex, but developer
commits a code into code repository.
The code is built, tested, and deployed.
So that's like a very simple pipeline.
What makes this pipeline
enterprise ready is it is scalable.
It's secure and it is compliant.
What do these things mean though?
So by scalable we mean that the pipeline
should be able to support multiple
environments through natural language.
The pipeline should be able to
automatically figure out resource
requirements based on workload patterns.
It should be able to provision
infrastructure based on deployment demand.
And it should also do intelligent
caching and artifact management
across different teams.
From a security perspective, there should
be real time vulnerability scanning.
So SaaS and das scanning across the board.
And this is done during code
generation, during build.
At each stage of SDLC.
Supply chain integrity is becoming
really critical these days, so tracking
the provenance of every artifact and
dependency has become extremely important.
And secret management.
Basically rotating the secrets as well
as giving the least privileged model.
Access has also become very important
on the compliance side of things.
The compliance should be a
default, not a reactive measure.
Audit trails for everything that is
generated right from code to bills to
artifacts should be a mandated thing.
There should be regulatory requirement
mapping such as HIPAA or SOC two.
And finally, there should be
documentation for each and
everything that's being generated.
So let's look at how Agentic AI helps you
to achieve enterprise ready pipelines.
With the help of knowledge graphs,
the role of agentic AI basically
is to make sure that there is
autonomous problem solving.
So the agents can actually be proactive
in perce perceiving failures and
reasoning, the root cause, et cetera.
There should be specialized
agents, for example, DevOps agent,
SRE agent, across the board.
And it should not be orchestrated
by humans, it should be
orchestrated by an agent.
Take ai.
It should also be a
continuous learning pattern.
So AI is really great at learning
about different patterns.
And then the, that feedback loop should
be fed back into it so that next time,
whenever it comes across a similar
pattern, it can action accordingly.
And policy as an intent should be the
fundamental for TKI, which basically
means that AI should understand what
are the enterprises policies and
best practices and implement them.
Let's look at context engineering
versus prompt engineering.
Andre Card Party said, plus
one for context engineering
versus prompt engineering.
And I completely agree with that.
And let's see why.
Prompt engineering is basically
dependent on the user's skill and
specificity, whereas context engineering
is actually dependent on your systems'
knowledge, so your enterprises
policies, templates, and infrastructure.
So it's way more comprehensive
than prompt engineering.
Let's look at an example.
Enterprise, CICD.
When the user says, build me a pipeline,
the AI has, which has access to rich
context, will figure out your governance,
your templates, your infrastructure,
and your team standards to build
pipelines that are secure and compliant.
This is by design and not by
luck, so that's why this reframes
why knowledge graph and strong
governance matters and your context
essentially makes AI really reliable.
At an enterprise scale.
So put this, to put this in a
diagrammatic view, whenever a user
prompt comes into ai, AI uses the
context which it has access to, to
create enterprise ready pipelines that
are scalable, secure, and compliant.
So that brings the entire picture
that we discussed together.
Let's look at how exactly.
We'd be build knowledge graphs.
So first of all, let's get into
what a rag and a knowledge graph is.
A knowledge graph is basically structured
data that is organized as nodes and
the relationships between those nodes.
We'll look at an example a bit later.
Rag essentially is unstructured
data from external sources.
So if you have like playbooks in
Google Docs or Word, that would be a
good example of unstructured content.
And then the hybrid approach is making
these knowledge graphs rich using drag
as an input to these knowledge graphs.
So for DevOps, in a DevOps world,
everything is relationship based.
So for example, let's say an e-commerce
business has hundreds of microservices.
And let's say if I update service
A, I need to figure out which
downstream services are affected.
And that basically.
I need to figure out the relationship
between different services and basically
points to creating a rich knowledge graph.
What we recommend for DevOps use
cases is using a hybrid approach,
which is enrich knowledge graph,
which is ingested with rack.
So let's see how we can
build such a knowledge graph.
So first, you need to extract entities
such as services, users, and incidents
then need to enrich with metadata.
So you need to figure out the
owner's versions and the policies.
Then you need to connect these together
so you have a relationship between who
owns what and what depends on what, and
then finally expose this to the AI agent
so that they can make use of this data.
A fellow engineer said
this pretty accurately.
If context is a new code,
knowledge graph is its compiler.
I really love that code.
So again, in a diagrammatic way,
this is this very simplistic
view of knowledge craft.
So you have entities, events, and third
party data, and they are all connected.
So you know what the relationship
between different entities,
events and third party data is,
let's talk about governance.
Now.
For governance, we need to figure
out who, what, how, and why.
Basically who has access to what, and
RAC is a great example of figuring that
out or giving access to specific users.
What access does AI have to your data?
So what data is being used to train
where the data flows from, et cetera.
These days, a lot of LLMs have
zero data retention policies, so
your data is not used for training.
This is a great example of
data and privacy card rails.
The how focus is on policy
enforcement and guardrails.
So essentially how AI behaves
can set guardrails so that the AI
doesn't break those guardrails and
operates within a safe environment.
And the why is basically auditability.
So for everything that AI does, we
need to audit it, need to tag it.
So for example, if an AI creates
a pipeline, you should tag it as
AI generated pipeline so that your
compliance team can figure out what was AI
generated and what was not AI generated.
So again, a different code.
This time context is a new code,
and governance is, its new runtime.
Let's talk about RAC
for a second with RAC.
It's very interesting.
The question always is, should
AI have its own RAC or is there a
different mechanism for RAC for ai?
Our view on this is that the
AI is an extension of the user.
Whatever RAC is assigned to a user
should be applicable to the AI as well.
An example is given here, example,
if a user cannot deploy to
production, that the AI should not
be able to deploy to production.
And the example is modifying policies.
Only admins in organizations
are supposed to modify policies.
And as far as AI is concerned, the admin
AI can modify policies, not a user.
So essentially AI becomes an
extension of the user, and thus
the RPAC is also tied in that way.
So the enterprise adoption framework
that we have seen a lot of customers use
and be successful is there is a prompt.
AI generates the pipeline, the
audit trail is updated, the user
saves or executes the pipeline.
In this case, the RAC is checked unsafe.
The policies kick in.
Depending on the RAC permissions and
the policies, the pipeline is either
executed or it fails, and then a real
time feedback is given back to the user
so that they can modify the pipeline
or involve the necessary people to
make sure that this pipeline executes.
It's a very simplistic F frame
framework that we have seen a lot of
our customers use and scale their ai.
Let's look at an example of how
we have implemented enterprise
Ready CI ICD, pipeline creation.
Just to give you a brief
overview of Harness platform
for those unfamiliar with it.
So we have a lot of products
around 18 products and everything
is powered by harness ai.
So essentially we make sure that
you create CI ICD policies or
infrastructure using harness ai
and they are enterprise ready.
So what we do is whenever a user gives a
prompt, a unified agent takes a prompt and
divides it into different specific agents
that are specialized in specific domains.
For example, the DevOps agent
can take care of CICD pipelines.
The release agent can take care of feature
management, pipe feature management
work, the reliability agent can take
care of chaos, engineering, et cetera.
And then once the agent takes care
of that work, the output of this.
Either pull requests or
pipelines or dashboards.
But what powers all of
this is the context.
The context basically is as you can
see from top down knowledge graph.
So whatever the knowledge graph is
created based on harness actions,
so building, deploying, et cetera,
and as well as external data.
So if you have a Jira ticket
somewhere, so getting context
from that Jira ticket example.
The other layer of context is essentially
your enterprise rules and policies.
This is the governance aspect
of things that we discussed.
So this creates a, for the AI to
take action on, and memory is also
critically important because then
the user doesn't have to restart
from scratch every time they log in.
There is memory and there is context
saved in that memory, but the user can
reuse for the AI to be more effective.
So that's an a very practical example of
how we have implemented all the things
that we discussed in this talk today.
And I le leave you with
this practical example.
I hope you had a good understanding
of how to create CI ICD pipelines
using tic ai that are enterprise
ready and can be done at scale.
Again, thank you for
listening to this talk.
If you have any questions, please feel
free to reach out to me on LinkedIn.
My LinkedIn is shown here
and again, have a great day.
Thank you.