Hello, my name is Mesut Erkal.
I'm a software quality assurance engineer.
And as most of my colleagues test
automation is a very important part
of my daily tasks because nowadays
we are not having big releases
or seasonal releases anymore.
But almost every day we are pushing
some new commits and we are implementing
some new features to the working
product in the production environment.
But even if not implementing new features,
sometimes we are changing or updating
the behaviors on the existing features,
which means we are doing the continuous
delivery and continuous integration.
And accordingly, of course, this means
we have to do the continuous testing
as well, because we have to ensure
that these frequent updates or frequent
development activities do not break,
do not break the working functionality.
So we have to do continuously
the testing and verification
and validation activities.
And in this way, we can continuously
ensure the quality and improve the
confidence in our team to deliver
the best product to our customers.
So, in these terms.
Test automation is very important
because if we have only manual testing
activities, of course, with solely
manual testing efforts, it is not
possible to catch up all the verification
activities because there is a huge
and comprehensive verification scope.
So doing this frequently, almost
every day with manual efforts.
It, it will be not possible to catch
up with, to cover all the scope with
limited resources in a limited time.
So if we have already some implemented
test code or the automated test
executions, it will be much more
easy to cover with a, much more fast.
And, reliable, test execution activities.
But in these terms, reliability
and robustness, or even
stability is very important.
So even if we implement test
cases, are we having reliable
results from these test cases?
Or, even if we automate all the
test cases we already designed,
it means, does it mean that we are
already catching all the possible or
potential vulnerabilities or bugs?
So in this session, we will talk about
the potential risks or difficulties or
drawbacks or test automation challenges.
And of course, if we are talking about
challenges or problems, of course,
we will talk about the solutions
and some proposals to cope with
this kind of challenges as well.
So, let's get started.
As we briefly discussed, test automation
has great advantages and benefits.
First of all, it saves time, because
while we are doing the test automation
or executing the test cases manually,
sometimes it may take hours or even days.
But while doing the same thing with an
automated run, we can execute several
scripts to fasten the execution or even we
can create some virtual machines to divide
the whole suite into different subsets and
we can already utilize the parallel runs
to reduce the total execution duration.
And not only the execution duration,
but also we can improve the coverage.
For example, we can perform
the same test scenario.
by providing different data inputs.
So we can perform the data driven
testing to apply not only the positive
scenarios, but also the negative
test cases by providing or inputting
some different negative data values
or with some different data formats.
So all this means we can already eliminate
So, we can reduce the manual effort.
But beyond that, there are some
scenarios in which we cannot
do with only manual testing.
For example, when we try to do
the load testing or performance
testing, we have to send lots of
different concurrent requests.
So we have to create several requests
which will be sent to the servers and
we will be checking the responses or
the responsiveness of the servers.
So for this purpose, of course, we cannot.
Collect a lot of people who will try to
send different requests at the same time.
But instead, we can just create those
requests on our machines and resources.
And then we can do these kind
of load testing activities.
So all these different aspects are great
benefits and advantages, which we can
utilize by performing the test automation.
But.
Of course, there is a bad side
of all these advantages, and of
course there are some difficulties
that we have to cope with.
So, let's start to
discuss them one by one.
The first difficulty that we have to
cope with is the frequent updates or
changes, because Since we are working
in Agile environments, it is very
likely to see some updated behaviors.
Initially, we design our features in a
way, but after going to the customers
or the end users, after getting
some feedback from them, sometimes
we update some, changes or updates.
And we try to improve the usability or the
even the functionality of some features.
So it means that even if we implement the
test scenarios to cover these use cases
once, it doesn't mean that we can execute
them forever without any maintenance.
So sometimes we have to
continuously maintain and pay
attention to these test cases.
Because otherwise, as we can see
in the famous cartoon on this
slide, sometimes the customer
expectation is totally different.
Then what we do or design or provide
to the customers or the end users.
So this is the importance or
the proposal to cope with the
frequent updates or challenges.
In addition to those changes or updates
to the working functionalities or
the features, sometimes even within
the specific feature or use case.
we may have some instabilities.
For example, if we have A B testing
activities, we deploy different instances.
This is why I have a
cute canary in the slide.
So we may have canary deployments,
including different instances,
returning different results.
So sometimes the results coming from
different instances will not match
to our expected conditions because in
these cases we won't be able to know,
Which instance or which version we will
hit during our execution in advance.
And there may be some different
difficulties, namely testability.
Some of the features are not easy to test
because if we are, especially if we are
testing a subsystem in the whole system,
and there are some different interactions
and integrations to the other subsystems,
and sometimes we don't have access to
those other parts of the whole system.
For example, let's assume a feature.
Which is syncing our subsystem which
is under test after a data is created
on the other part of a system.
So when a data or an instance is
created in the other subsystem,
our subsystem which is under test
should sync itself by pulling.
The newly created object.
But in this case, if we don't
have access to create an object
in the other subsystems, then
how can we test this scenario?
So we have to simulate or trigger
this scenario to be able to check
if the communication is done or the
whole interaction is done properly.
First of all, we have to create the data.
But if we don't have access or
right to do that, then we will be
having some testability issues.
We will not be able to trigger this
condition because, we will not be able to
create the relative or relevant condition.
instances on the other subsystems.
So what we can do is, of course, we
can utilize some mocks, or we can
develop some other subsystems, which
is faking as the modules which our
system under test is communicating with.
But what one initiative we can
do in this, in that regard is.
We can communicate to the development
teams and we can try to find
ways to improve the testability.
For example, if we need some public APIs
or other interfaces by which we can create
some instances just for testing purposes,
because we know that they will not be
used in the real production environment,
but just for testing purposes to be able
to trigger the condition that we need.
To perform this scenario, we can
request some additional interfaces from
them, and then after with the help of
development teams, if we have those
interfaces through which we can trigger
our expected conditions, we will be
able to cover these testability issues.
And one more thing which may little
bit make Things difficult for us is
the hardware modules because sometimes
to perform or verify and validate
the interactions, which is done with
the hardware modules, we have to
simulate those kind of messages or
the protocols, which is communicating
the hardware modules with the software
algorithms that we have in our system.
Not only the hardware modules, but
also the AI components is very likely
to be seen in our products nowadays,
because we know that today AI or the
machine learning algorithms is a very
important part of our daily life.
So which means when we are developing
some products or the features or the
functionalities to our customers,
it is very likely to include some
machine learning algorithms to provide
them the best user experiences.
So when we are deploying.
or delivering our products, how can we
ensure the performance of these kind of ML
or AI components involved in our products?
So, of course, there are lots of
different ways to improve the performance
by developing the algorithm itself.
But speaking in terms of the functional
test automation point of view, how
can we ensure the best performance
coming from these AI modules?
So it is a little bit tricky.
And what we can do is maybe we can
perform several experiments and we
can do lots of different benchmark
studies, but just from functional test
automation point of view, it is almost
impossible to perform or ensure the
best performance of this AI components.
And a little bit related to this issue,
there is a non functional aspect of
the quality in our product that we are
delivering or providing to our customers.
It's not on the functionality, but
there are lots of different aspects of
the quality, for example, performance,
how responsive our services are,
even when under load, the how is
the performance of our services.
Or even the usability, how easily
the end users can use our services.
This is just the user experience and
the, usability aspect of quality.
And of course, these, these, all these
aspects and dimensions are very important.
Not only the functionality, but
also all these other aspects of
the quality are very important.
So how can we ensure with
the, test automation?
Of course, it is not, possible
to cover all these aspects, but.
We can support, on top of all our
test automation activities, we
can do several studies, sometimes
manual testing activities, sometimes
exploratory testing activities.
Which means test automation will
never enable us to provide a bug free
software, or even the manual testing
activities will never enable us to
deliver a bug free software, because
bug free software is not possible,
and infinite testing is not possible.
So we will always have some issues
or always have some bugs, but
of course the priority of the
severity of them are very important.
So the important thing is Try to minimize
those kind of issues as much as possible.
Try to reduce the escape
bugs as much as possible.
So, on top of the test
automation activities, the
manual testing is very important.
But, without test automation,
we cannot cover the scope
which is sufficient to deliver.
our products with a certain quality.
So test automation is very
important as the baseline.
But on top of that, we should never
ignore the manual testing activities.
Recently, as an initiative in our team,
we performed a bug bash in which everyone
in the team tried to use the products.
So it was a kind of dog fooding activity.
And we tried to find the issues, all kind
of the functionality and usability issues.
And we found several issues.
So we were questioning in the team,
if so, if this is the case, what are
the automated test case are covering?
What are they finding?
But it doesn't mean that
they don't find any issues.
So we already found several issues
reported by the automated test cases.
But those were the issues
already remaining from the
test automation activities.
They were, they were still.
A lot of issues which can
be fixed or even improved.
in the product.
So both the test automation and
the manual testing activities,
are very important in these terms.
And there will be still a lot
of issues which can be improved.
So what we can do is maybe we can
do some chaos testing activities
to test if something unexpected
happens in some parts of the system.
If some parts are going down.
What will be the other parts or
the other systems will be reacting
to this unexpected situation?
So after these kind of difficulties
stemming from the product or the
way of working off the features or
the functionalities, of course, we
can talk about some difficulties
regarding the implementation itself.
On this slide, I have an example
showing a setup to test the
account or tenant creation feature.
And one requirement of the
feature was After a tenant was
created, The user of this tenant
should be notified by an email.
And the difficulty in this scenario
was, after each time we execute this
test scenario, we should go to the
email account, and we should log in with
the correct credentials, and we should
verify that the email was there with the
relevant subject and the correct context.
Creating unique email IDs after
each run, and managing all the
credentials was super difficult.
So what if we did this?
We set up an email relay, which
was capturing the email to be
sent to an email address, which
is sort of format and forwarding
them to one other email address.
So in this way, whenever an email is
prepared to be sent to an email address,
which is fitting to a certain format, it
was capturing this and forwarding to an
other email address, which managed by us.
But of course, preparing this environment
and utilizing these servers to prepare
the email relay itself was very difficult.
So of course we had to put some effort
and we of course should spend some
time to prepare this environment.
test environment, but not only the
test environment, sometimes the test
code itself is difficult to maintain
or difficult to implement because
we, as we already discussed about
the front end automation, sometimes
the element locators are tricky to
figure out, but even sometimes the
normal algorithms to test the backend
services like sending the responses,
preparing the, correct, format request.
Or even parsing the responses.
Sometimes implementing the
test code is challenging.
So we have to cope with
this kind of difficulties.
And we have to improve the ease of
coding in our test automation framework.
And not only the implementation, but
also the maintenance is very important.
And one aspect of the maintenance
is the execution durations.
So if our test executions are taking
too much time, it means sometimes The
features to be deployed are waiting
for the test results because, as we
discussed in the beginning, normally we
want to integrate our test executions
into our pipelines to ensure that
the frequent updates or changes do
not break the working functionality.
But each time, after each commit,
after each merge request, if we are
running test cases and if they are
waiting, or taking too much time.
Then after some time, the team
members will start to complain.
I'm raising an MRI and I'm waiting for
hours to comment or to march my comments
to my updates and Test cases are really
blocking our development activities.
To avoid these kind of situations,
we can try to reduce the execution
time as much as possible.
As we already discussed previously, we
can, introduce the parallel executions,
but even within the certain test
scenarios, we can, analyze, Which steps
or which operations are taking too
much time and we can try to find out
the root causes and if there are some
dummy ways or there are any other steps,
redundant steps which can be eliminated
to cover the same scope, then we can
already reduce them, eliminate them and
reduce the total execution durations.
And one more aspect which will help
us to improve the maintainability
of test code to implement.
The next test cases in a way faster or
easier way is removing the duplications.
If we already introduced some helper
classes which are providing some methods
duplicated, in lots of different test
scenarios, then whenever we need to
implement, such a scenario, we will be
already having the chance to call these
methods implemented in the, Those helper
classes, and it will already help us to
improve the ease of coding and not only
the ease of coding, but it will help us
to remove the duplication because instead
of having this kind of helper classes in
which the repeated steps are implemented.
If we implement these steps in each
test case separately, then what
will we do when a fix is updated?
We have to update one step.
Repeatedly used in lots of different
test cases or test spec files.
We will go to each spec file
and we will fix this problem.
in each of them separately, but instead,
if we already have the unique point
of source, then we will be, having the
chance to apply our fix to a single point.
Another important aspect of the
maintenance stage of the software
testing lifecycle is managing the bugs.
So of course, when we are doing the
test automation or the automated test
executions, some test tests may fail.
And we have to understand the root causes.
Sometimes they may be false alarms,
but sometimes they may be the real
bugs stemming from the product.
So we should find the root cause
and we have to report our bugs.
But of course, in these cases, the
evidence collection is very important
because we have to provide as much as
possible information to our reports.
So let's a little bit wrap up what we
have discussed in terms of the test
automation challenges and the proposals.
to cope with this kind of challenges.
So we discussed first of all, we have
to cope with this frequent updates
because once the tests are implemented,
it doesn't mean that we can execute
them forever without paying them
paying attention to them anymore.
So what we should do is to cope with the
agile limited time and limited resources.
To have the minimum viable product
in a very limited time, we have to
encourage the early QA involvement.
And to cope with frequent updates, to
be able to cover the correct scope, we
have to continuously maintain our test
cases and do the continuous maintenance.
The next thing was the instabilities,
sometimes stemming from A B
testing activities or sometimes
stemming from some scripts or the
nature of working in our product.
So we have to improve the test
robustness in lots of different ways.
We have to improve to be ready for
a different actual results and to
be able to cover them properly.
And the next thing was
different testability issues.
What we can do is we can collaborate
with the development teams.
And we can try to find different
ways to improve the testability.
And we may have hardware dependencies, or
similarly we may have some AI components
in the products that we are developing.
So what we can do is we can prepare
several simulation environments.
And it's not only the test
automation, but also we can do
the manual testing activities.
Maybe some experiments or exploratory
testing activities to understand.
They are performing with a good
performance and of course, functionality
is not the only aspect of the quality
that we are trying to ensure, but also
the usability, performance, responsiveness
and maintainability, recoverability,
all this kind of non functional
aspects are also very important.
So we can do a lot of different
non functional tests as well.
Especially chaos testing
will help us to ensure.
The responsiveness of the product,
even in the worst cases, when some
parts of the product are down.
And one more aspect or the
difficulty we have to cope with
was the implementation itself.
Sometimes we have to set up some test
harness or test environment and sometimes
the implementation itself can be tricky.
And, in addition to implementation,
the maintenance, the reproduction
of the bugs or the test execution
durations are all related difficulties
or the challenges that we can improve.
So what we can do is we can try
to reduce duplication, eliminate
the duplication, and we can
improve or encourage reusability
in our test automation frameworks.
So we can categorize these
kinds of difficulties.
first of all, The frequent updates,
and the instabilities are the
reasons stemming from the nature of
the product or our implementation
methods like, agile methodologies
or, other, working principles.
And the second category
can be, considered as.
The testability or the
components of the product.
And thirdly, we can talk about
the non-functional aspects
and then we can talk about the
implementation, maintenance, or
execution related difficulties.
So, we talked about lots of different
difficulties, but of course when there
is a difficulty or there is a problem,
of course it means there should be
some solutions which will help us to
ease or, solve these kind of problems.
So, the.
A call for action should be you should
list your problems or the difficulties
in the test automation framework because
there is always something to improve.
There should be always some improvement
rooms and please try to fix them
or try a lot of things to improve
them and solve them as much as
possible and adapt your solutions
in the test automation frameworks.
Thanks for listening and enjoy
the rest of the conference.