Speaker 24: Good morning everyone.
It's an honor to be here at
the DevOps Conference 2026.
My name is Hil Coker.
Throughout my career at
Google, Salesforce, and Disney.
I've had unique opportunity to build
and manage systems that don't just
serve millions but billions of users.
At Disney, I've seen our ad
platforms handle over 200 billion
annual impressions, maintaining
low latencies, even during
massive spikes like sport events.
Today our wanna move beyond the
theory of high availability.
We are gonna talk about
extreme scaler reliability.
We will discuss what happens when
traditional scaling hits a wall and
specific architectures and algorithms.
You need to stay online when the
world is knocking at your door.
We are currently in a transition
from large scale to extreme scale.
APIs are no longer just
external interfaces.
They are the nervous system of a
global infrastructure, whether it's IOT
sensors, streaming telemetry, social
media platforms, managing viral burst.
Or even ad tech processing
real time auctions.
The demand for a fine nines
availability is no longer a
luxury, but it's a requirement.
The engineering reality we face is
that traditional scaling hits a wall.
You cannot simply buy a bigger server.
Vertical scaling has physical
limits and diminishing returns.
Even horizontal scaling if done,
enabling introduces coordinated overhead.
As you add more nodes, the time
system spends for self checks, service
discovery, state synchronization,
all these things starts to exceed the
time spent to doing the actual work.
In this doc, we aren't looking for hacks.
We are looking for a systematic framework
that aligns your architecture with
algorithmic efficiency to ensure your
API remains fast and cost effective as
you cross that billion request threshold.
Before we look at the how, let's look
at the who we are standing on the
shoulders of giants who have solved
these complex problems at scale.
Netflix is a good example for this.
With over two 50 million subscribers,
they don't just serve video.
They manage a complex
web of microservices.
They have pioneered the use of edge
caching and adaptive streaming algorithms
that adjust the quality in real time
based on network congestion, ensuring
the user experience never status.
Uber handles billion of
real time location updates.
To manage this, they utilize
something called S Geo Sharding.
By partitioning the data and processing
based on geographic cells, they ensure
that traffic surge in a one city does
not create a noisy neighbor effect on
any other city and any other service.
And then look at revenue Cat.
They provide a masterclass in
request coalescing by identifying
when multiple clients are asking
for the exact same piece of data at
the same time, they collapse those
requests into a single backend call.
The simple algorithm change can reduce
backend load by the order of magnitudes.
Let's look at the four
layer scaling framework now.
To manage extreme scale without
getting lost in the weeds, I recommend
this four layer scaling framework.
You should view this as series of
defendants defensive parameters.
First is the edge layer.
This is your first line of defense.
It is about being close to the user
using CDN caching, geo routing.
To reduce the physical distance, your
data has to travel to reach the user.
Second is a gateway layer.
This is your traffic cop.
It handles authentication and crucially
distributed rate limiting to provide
to protect your internal services.
Next is the microservices layer.
Here we focus on the resilience.
We ensure that service meshes that we
create and circuit breakers to ensure
that if one service fails, it does
not take down an entire ecosystem.
Last, but not the least, the data layer.
Here we address the concern
for ultimate bottleneck.
We use sharding and distributed
caching to ensure that databases
can scale as fast as the compute.
By looking at your system through these
four lenses, you can identify exactly
where your current bottleneck six, and
which tool is best suited to fix it.
The first layer is the edge in 2026.
A CDN isn't just for static images,
it's for dynamic API responses.
The key to extreme scale caching
is strategic cache key design.
If your cash key is too specific,
your head rate drops and traffic
flows through the origin.
And if it's too broad,
you serve stale data.
You can solve this by segmenting
keys, by user class, geographic
location, or even device type.
You can use the stale
white revalidate pattern.
Imagine a entry expires
in traditional system.
The next request missions the
cash and goes to the backend.
Causing a latency spike for that user
In this architecture, the ad service
serves the stale data immediately, but in
turn triggers an asynchronous background
process to fetch the fresh data.
This guarantees that your user
always sees sub 50 milliseconds
responses even during a cache refresh.
Furthermore, you can
also use adaptive DTLs.
If your backend is under a heavy
load, your edge should automatically
extends at its TTM and practice.
A combination of these can
reduce origin traffic by 95%.
Now, let's look at the
request coalescing patterns.
What happens when your cache
is empty and let's say about.
10,000 requests for the same
item hits you all at once.
This is known as thundering herd.
We saw this with request coalescing.
This is often implemented using
the single flight algorithm.
When the first request
arrives, it misses the cash.
The subsystem marks that
request as in flight.
Any subsequent request for the same id.
I put in the wait queue.
Once the first request returns from
the database, the result is broadcasted
to everyone waiting in the client.
Think about the math.
Instead of sending out 10,000
database queries, you perform one.
This isn't just performance optimization.
It's a reliability insurance policy.
It prevents your database
from melting down.
The moment a piece of content goes viral.
You cannot build a reliable
system if you don't understand
the shape of your traffic.
At scale, we see three primary patterns.
Okay.
Diurnal searches are predictable.
Waves of the sun moves across the globe.
You can use historical modeling to prewarm
your clusters before these peaks arrive.
Burst traffic is the new breaking
news or live event scenario.
Traffic might jump 10 times or a
hundred times in under a minute.
Here.
The goal isn't to scale.
It is to prevent cascading failures
where one overwhelm system service starts
timing out, causing its callers to retry
with further barriers, the service.
So we need to handle,
how do we prevent that?
The adversarial loads are the bottlenecks
or the DDoS attacks on your systems.
At extreme Scale, your system must
be able to distinguish between a
loyal user and a malicious script in
milliseconds understanding which of
these are your design for changes, how
you need to configure your auto-scaling
and protect your layers of your system.
The distributed LA rate limiting
is your API's immune system, but
in a distributed environment,
it's actually a difficult problem.
Here we primarily use to two algorithms.
The first one is called token bucket.
It allows for the burst
bursts nature of the traffic.
A user can send flurry of requests as
long as they have tokens in their bucket.
This is great for modern web apps
that might load 20 resources at once.
The leaky bucket and algorithm enforces
a strict smooth flow of traffic.
It's what you can use to protect
fragile downstreams legacy systems
that can only handle specific
requests per second exit rate.
But the real engineering
challenge is global coordination.
Let's say for example, if a user
has a limit of thousand requests
per minute and you have 50 data
centers, how do you keep track?
You can use a local first
approach, nodes track.
It limits locally and sync with
a central Redis or a similar
cache clustered up periodically.
This gives you the speed of local checks
with the accuracy of global enforcements.
Next is multi-region active architecture.
So when your request reads,
reaches a billion requests.
High availability means multi-region,
but usually active passive,
where one region sits idle is
wasteful and slow to fail over.
Hence, we should always
try for an active solution.
And this model, the traffic is routed
via a geo DNS to nearest healthy region.
If US East one experiences a power outage.
Traffic naturally flows to us to West two.
The complexity here is data consistency.
You can utilize regional autonomy.
Each region should have enough
data locally to serve a request,
even if cross region fiber is cut.
You can use asynchronous
replication for noncritical data.
And conflict free replicated data
types CDTs to ensure that if two users
update their profile in different
regions simultaneously, the data merges
correctly without any human intervention.
Next, look, let's look at
the sharding techniques.
Eventually your database
becomes a bottleneck.
When a single cluster can't hold
data, we shard, you can use something
called a consistent hashing.
So unlike traditional hashing, the mod
N hashing that is consistent hashing
allows you to add or remove database
nodes without remapping the entire
data set by using virtual nodes.
We ensure that data is distributed evenly
across the cluster, preventing hot shards.
You can also use geographic sharding
to keep user data in their home region,
which isn't just a performance win.
It's often a legal requirement
for data residency.
A hybrid approach combines the user
ID and geographic usually provides the
best balance of performance and scale.
As we move into the microservice layer,
managing communication between 500 plus
services becomes impossible manually.
Here we use a service
mesh like NY or Istio.
The mesh acts as a transparent
sidecar to every service.
It handles heavy lifting.
Of DevOps mutual TLS for security,
automatic retries with exponential
back off and even circuit breaking.
A circuit breaker is actually critical.
If service A sees that service B is
failing, it trips the circuit and stops
sending request for a cooling off period.
This prevents the death spiral
situation where a failing service
is hit with more and more retries
until it can never recover.
The separation of business logic and
network logic is what allows developers to
move fast without breaking the platform.
Let's talk about observative
observability a bit.
So at billions of requests, you
cannot literally log everything.
If you did.
Your logging bill would be
higher than your compute bill.
You can actually use something
called a tail based tracing.
In traditional ting, you might sample
1% of the request, but if your error
rate is 0.1%, you might miss the
very errors that you're looking for.
With tail based tracing, what you do is
you keep the trace in a temporary buffer
if the request is successful and fast.
You can discard it.
If it returns 500 error or
takes longer than, let's say 200
milliseconds, you save the full trace.
This gives you a hundred percent
visibility into failures, while only
storing a tiny fraction of total data.
High cardinality metrics and cost aware
logging samples are some of the other ways
also to achieve observability at scale.
Predictive autoscaling
is another technique.
Reactive autoscaling, for
example, scales when CPU hits 70%.
It's too slow for extreme scale.
By the time a new Kubernetes cluster
node is ready, the traffic has
already spiked and cost time out.
You can use predict model pre predictive
models here by feeding historical
data of how traffic works in your
system into machine learning models.
You can predict with the high
accuracy, what the traffic will
look like in the next 30 minutes.
You can use this pre.
To pre-provision the capacity
for major events where you
expect traffic to be higher.
This allows you to maintain a trite
headroom, which saves millions in
infrastructure costs while ensuring your
service is scaled up enough to handle the
uptick in the traffic, and you're never
caught off guard by predictable surges.
As we look forward to 2027, the challenges
are evolving In this space, one major
focus is energy aware elasticity.
We are be beginning to see the green
DevOps, where we shift heavy background
processing workloads like data indexing or
ML training, two regions where renewable
energy is currently at a peak production.
We are also attacking extreme tail
latency where we are moving past the P
99 metric and focusing on the P 99.99.
Eliminating those microsecond level
jitters caused by garbage collection
or even kernel interrupts requiring
a level of full stack observability
that reaches down to hardware itself.
Finally.
Cross region rate coordination remains an
active area of research, finding ways to
enforce global limits with zero latency
penalty using edge computing platforms.
So your billion dollar
request bill of rent.
To summarize, scaling at Billions
is a marathon, not a sprint Layer.
Your defenses don't expect
One tool to solve everything.
Optimize this edge.
The fastest request is the one
that never hits your backend.
It.
B algorithmic request coalescing and
smart sharding to reduce work per request.
Bpo, be also proactive.
Move from reactive monitoring
to predictive operations.
These are the patterns that
you can use every day to keep
your platform running smoothly.
Start with your most critical bottleneck.
Apply these patterns systematically, and
you'll find that extreme scale is not
only achievable, but also manageable.
Thank you all for joining me today.
Building at this scale is a
collaborative effort, and I'm
excited to see how you apply these
patterns into your own systems.
Again, I am Hil Koko.
You can find me on LinkedIn or reach out
to me if you have any questions regarding
the architectures we discussed today.
Thank you.
I.