Speaker 17: Hello everyone.
My name is Kika Gupta and I'm
a software engineer at Amazon.
Today we are going to deep dive
into a critical intersection of
modern engineering where high
scale machine learning meets the
operational rigor of CICD and DevOps.
CICD stands for continuous integration
and continuous delivery pipeline.
We will discuss how we build a system
for ML driven intellectual property
detection that operates at massive scale,
focusing not just on model accuracy,
but also on the cloud native enforcement
mechanisms that make these models
viable in a production environment.
So let's dive right in.
The challenge IP violations At
Unprecedented Scale, the scale
we are dealing with is immense.
Digital marketplaces are seeing
explosive growth in IP violations.
We aren't just processing a few items.
We are handling millions of
new listings every single day.
Every one of these require a
decision in near real time.
These decisions.
Our high stakes, they directly impact
our seller's livelihoods, our brand
partner's rights, and the trust
our customers have placed in us.
Let's deep dive into this a bit.
We face a fourfold challenge.
First volume, millions of daily listings.
Second, high stake decisions and
enforcement action is not just a
data point, it's a business action.
Third, precision imperative.
A false positive harms a
legitimate seller, whereas a false
negative enables a bad actor.
Finally, trust and compliance.
We operate within a complex web of
legal and regulatory requirements
that demand extreme accuracy.
Why traditional approaches can't keep up.
Traditional systems are breaking
because their limitations are
architectural, not just technical.
Let's look at five specific failure modes.
First, manual review.
Human oversight is essential for
quality, but it's impossible for volume.
You cannot hire enough people
to review millions of listings
per day with consistent speed
and accuracy at the same time.
Second rule-based systems.
These are brittle adversaries are smart.
They see a static rule and immediately
pivot their tactics to evade it.
Every day, we are seeing multiple mos
being popped up by the bad actors.
Third ML only focus.
This is a common pitfall.
If your team only cares about F1 scores
and ignores deployment, monitoring,
and incident response, the system will
fail in the wild static models, dec.
Adversarial behavior evolves and
without a continuous retraining loop,
your model becomes a legal liability.
Within weeks five siloed teams, when
the ML researchers are separated
from the infrastructure engineers,
you get massive blind spots and
this low incident escalation.
Core Insight production.
ML is a systems problem.
This brings us to our core
philosophy production.
ML is a systems problem,
not a modeling problem.
Detection accuracy is necessary,
but it is insufficient.
Even a 99.9% accurate model is a
failure if you cannot roll it back
instantly when it hits a new med case.
So here are the key pillars.
Real world enforcement
requires operational rigor.
We must maintain visibility, handle
rollbacks gracefully, and earn
business trust through reliability.
This is a full stack engineering
challenge that requires us to prioritize
reliability over raw accuracy and
use observability to detect drift
before it becomes an incident.
High level system architecture.
Our architecture treats the entire
pipeline as a unified observable system.
It is designed to separate concerns while
maintaining end-to-end traceability.
Here are the components
within our pipeline.
Real time ingestion.
We use a streaming pipeline.
To ingest millions of events.
Number two, multimodal detection.
We do not rely on one signal.
We analyze images, text and
seller behavior in conjunction to
make the best possible decision.
Number three, event driven orchestration,
intelligent routing based on.
Humans based on models confidence, human
plus LLM verification, A hybrid approach
for edge cases that we take observability
and feedback a loop where monitoring
directly drives model improvement.
Online and offline separation.
This allows us to run inference in
real time while retraining models
independently in the background.
Multimodal detection engine.
So different signals capture
different evasion tactics.
Bad actors might obfuscate text or
manipulate images, but it's much harder
to hide when you combine the modalities.
So here's our technical stack.
We use a weighted ensemble
approach for images.
We use a fine tuned YOLO V seven model.
Or Roberta for object detection for text.
We utilize domain adapted bird
models to understand semantic context
rather than just keyword matching.
We also integrate behavior signals
like seller history, seller enforcement
actions other platforms on which
the seller is selling, et cetera.
The key advantage is that this modality
independence is crucial for CICD.
We can upgrade the image detection
model without touching the text model.
This reduces regression risk and allows
for a much faster deployment cycle.
Vector similarity, surge at scale.
So the engine behind our detection
is embedding based similarity.
Let me explain the workflow here a bit.
We convert both images and text
into dense vector representations.
After that, we pre-compute a
reference index of known violations
when a new listing comes in.
We perform A KNN, which stands for
KN nearest neighbor search, using
cosign similarity to handle the scale
we use approximate nearest neighbor,
a NN search via AWS open search.
This allows us to trade a. Tiny fraction
of recall for massive gains in latency,
specifically subsecond P 99 latency.
Even at millions of queries per
second, we use index versioning.
Every index is immutable.
If a new deployment degrades
quality, we can perform an instant
rollback to the previous version.
Event driven orchestration.
Our backbone is an event
driven orchestration.
Our architecture designed for failure.
We use Amazon Kinesis for real-time
ingestion, and here's how we
handle all these ingestion events.
Listings are routed via S-N-S-S-Q-S based
on the confidence score of the ML model.
Complex workflows are handled by AWS
step functions, which provide built-in
retrial, logic and error handling.
We focus heavily on reliability.
Every component is designed with
circuit breakers and back pressure.
If a downstream service is struggling.
We rate limited to prevent
cascading failures.
Perhaps most importantly, we
use immutable event streams.
This allows us to replay a sequence
of events to debug exactly where a
specific decision to debug exactly
why a specific decision was made.
Confidence based enforcement strategy.
Not all enforcement actions are equal.
Our system maps ML confidence scores
directly to business policies.
These are the different
tiers that we operate in.
High confidence triggers
immediate listing removal, or in
some cases, account suspension.
These require more than 99% position.
Medium confidence triggers a seller
warning or educational intervention,
or in some cases listing removal as
well, depending on the seller history.
Low to medium confidence listings are sent
to a manual review queue, the governance.
Finally, this makes the system auditable.
Legal, and trust teams can
modify these thresholds in.
In an app config without
needing a developer to retrain
or redeploy the ML models.
LLM assisted verification.
For those medium confidence cases,
we use large language models,
LLMs to augment human judgment.
The LLM acts as a reasoning engine.
It aggregates similarity scores, seller
history, sellers enforcement actions,
and metadata to generate a structured
decision with a supporting rationale.
What has been the impact?
It has been transformative.
We have seen a 78% auto verification
rate for medium confidence cases and a
68% reduction in manual review workload.
Because the LLM provides an
explanation, the appeal win rate
has improved significantly as we
can provide sellers with clear
defensible reasons for enforcement.
CICD and model governance.
We treat models as first class
software artifact artifacts.
This means strict versioning
in a model registry with full
lineage and approval workflows.
So the model pipeline is as follows.
Every model candidate undergoes
automated evaluation against
holdout sets before it goes live.
It runs in shadow mode.
It produces production traffic
and generates decisions, but
those decisions are not enforced.
We compare these results to
the current production model.
And decide the next steps accordingly.
We use gradual rollouts with
automated quality gates.
If the system detects any degradation,
it triggers an auto rollback.
This cultural shift, knowing that the
system will protect itself, has allowed
us to double our release velocity.
Observability and monitoring.
We monitor three distinct layers.
Business metrics like false
positive rates, true positive rates,
false negative rates, et cetera.
System metrics like API latency,
API, throughputs error rates
failure rates, et cetera, and
model metrics like feature drift.
We have early warning systems in place.
We do not just wait for accuracy to drop.
We monitor the distribution
of confidence scores.
If we see a shift in that
distribution, it's an early warning
of model decay or an adversarial
pivot often detected within hours.
This unified view ensures the ML engineers
and support engineers that all of them
are looking at the same source of truth.
Incident response and debugging.
Production insights are inevitable at our
scale, so we have architected our system
to make them manageable through rigorous
engineering rather than guesswork.
Our goal was to turn debugging from
an art into a repeatable science.
So what is in our arsenal?
Trace IDs we use end-to-end trace IDs to
follow a listings journey across every
service, hop to the final destination.
Event replay immutable streams allow
us to determine ally reproduce and
investigate incidents by replaying the
exact event sequences, structured logs.
We query logs by listing seller or model
version to isolate root causes instantly.
We have couple of response scenarios, like
latency spikes, if the downstream service
degrades, the circuit breakers, activate
and shift traffic to backup regions.
False positive waves.
If feature drift causes a wave of
errors, auto rollback triggers and
affected decisions are reversed.
Data corruption, schema changes or
passing errors are caught at the
ingestion and routed to dead letter
queues to prevent pipeline poison.
What has been the result?
By using all the run books and error
budgets, we have dropped our meantime
to resolution from hours to minutes.
The results and operational
impact, the results have been
incredible and impact is clear.
We have doubled our throughput
and we have halved RP 99 latency.
We have reduced manual review by 68%
while doubling our release velocity.
But why?
Here's the answer.
These metrics are great, but the
real win is trust by making the
system reliable and observable.
We have moved from a world where ML
was a black box to a world where it
is a trustworthy, fundamental part
of our enforcement infrastructure.
To conclude production ML is
about the convergence of ML
expertise and DevOps discipline.
The systems that win aren't
just the most accurate.
They are the most observable
and the most resilient systems.
Remember, engineer for failure,
prioritize deployment over
training and use automation to
create velocity through safety.
Thank you.