Speaker 45: Hi everyone.
Today we are getting into the
real time finops intelligence.
We all know that AI space is being rogue
in terms of innovations in the latest
years and financial services is no,
different from any other industries,
from being impacted in a positive way
and enhancing the capabilities especially
the ops part and all as same as the
developer productivity side of it.
So today, so I'm Tina.
I work for Microsoft and I work in a team
where we, drive the financial engine, the
trillion dollar platform for Microsoft.
So without further you, let's
jump into the topic and.
Let's talk about the challenges first.
So what happens in the financial platform?
So we're in the realm
of a revolution, right?
And what was the previous one?
It was the cloud services.
So most of the financial platforms
which are risk award, wherein
on-premise servers, which were
moved to cloud services and
most of the companies that as.
That has happened and still there
are like some places here and there,
which is, which are still catching up.
But how for being in cloud services
and in distributed world, brings
its own advantages and challenges.
So what do we do here?
So we have millions of events
coming and we have a high
throughput streaming system.
So most of the systems are either
microservices spark engines,
and they're being like store.
There are storages, like cosmos or reds
in between, storages in Azure or AWS,
which are cloud platforms, which we
have today, and we drive observability
on top of it, which is very critical.
Monitoring and observability are
very critical to her running the
financial systems without outages.
And what do we have here?
So we have transactions.
Which are high throughput.
We have logs coming in.
We track some metrics and there are.
Schema.
So when you say schemas, those are
like very domain dependent, right?
So if, suppose if I am a team which
browses the revenue or recognizes
the revenue of the company, then I.
As a team would be interested in few
fields, whereas the finance or the
marketing would have would be looking
into some other fields as well,
together with some of the consolidated
fields are populated from one team.
So those differ, but what remains the same
as the challenges of less outages high
availability and having minimum latency.
And also the auditability when it
comes to the tools we implement.
So right now we have
automations, we have tools.
So we are at a juncture of finding,
okay, what AI can do, how can we leverage
AI more yeah, this is what sort of, we
talked about, like what we are processing.
So what do we have in hand?
So today, all these systems, whether
the transactions the metrics and
the application locks all are
in different tooling systems.
So we don't have a consolidated
place at DAB or an SRE should go.
To each individual systems and trace the
path of a particular transaction when
it comes to an outages or an error or
why didn't process some transactions.
That's the most common
questions we question we get.
So these are the challenges and.
Yes, we do have ai, we do have co-pilots.
We have authenticated co-pilots integrated
to our systems with some exceptions
like, high risk financial platforms.
Still, we are not fully not every fully
enabling the AI access, but, with with
our own guardrails, Microsoft has AI
systems enabled and if we fully run on AI
platforms with adequate security keeping
security out of the context for a while.
So given that you know we are working
in a secure environment, what are
why the ad hoc prompting fails?
The most important or something as
important a as prompt is the context.
So context engineering is an enter, is
a field by itself and which wouldn't
suffice the stock to cover even.
So we can't even scratch the surface.
Prompt engineering, context
engineering or the mix of both.
But what we carry with us, or what we
keep in mind is that prompt engineering
and context engineering go hand in hand.
One is not a substitute of
other, so I could be a master
of writing the best prompts.
I would've learned everything, what a
clouds on it system or a Gemini system.
Gemini model can work through the
prompts and give a adequate maybe
I can even fine tune my model.
But then if we miss the context,
then it is the prompts are failing.
And why why do you think ad
hoc prompting doesn't suffice?
It's because I'll be a dev one.
I. Write certain type of certain
prompt, and I may not have all the
context on how I should troubleshoot
it or how what I am really looking at.
So maybe I am dev working in a
different team or sister team
or my expertise somewhere else.
And Dev too comes in and writes
the same prompt, but they give
all the necessary context and the
moral give as the right output.
This is more of a
standardization, I would say.
So that calls for the standardization of
using the AI models across not only in
observability space or the DevOps space.
It is everywhere.
So suppose I'm working in a mi in a
microservice and I'm developing those,
i'm developing some logic around like how
I process this process, a set of records,
a set of transactions, or what is the
input how the output should look like.
I would be working and then, moving
forward to another another one and
the one and keep going, but whoever.
Comes in later and makes changes
to that system, which still have to
adhere to the fundamental design of it.
So some of those just just tangent,
tangential to this is, would be like
in developer productivity at GitHub's
SPECT as being phenomenal in setting
up the guard release for the project
and not letting the developers
violate from the design requirements.
And coming back to our topic, so
missing the context when we get an Inca.
So we know that all these AI models
are probabilistic with the same prompt.
There are times where you
get different outputs.
That could be the context window,
that could be how we write the prompt
or like how we write the prompt.
In the sense that, what is the order in
which like we analyze a certain scenario.
With probabilistic model, inconsistent
output is something which should be,
expected at this point, and I know
many of us have gone through the paper
paper published recently about the
hallucinations of the model and how we
can, how that is something unavoidable.
Yeah.
Again, that was something tangential
to our topic, but I think with
the advent of ai, we all have.
Been experiencing, consuming huge
amount of knowledge and catching up
with development every single day.
So we are, should be used to it.
I know all of you are, so I. Yeah,
so this will so moving on to third
and fourth, like this will result
in a poor level of auditability.
So how I'm going to say or
determine the efficiency of that
platform, which I implemented.
So when ad hoc prompting does all of this
will risk cause poor auditability as well,
and in it'll cause a latency overhead.
Now, what is the solution we should do?
Template driven, prompt engineering.
Like I said, this is very similar
to what GitHub's Spec Kit does in
terms of developer productivity,
in terms of software development.
Why then we do have, we are having this
talk here on template driven prompt
engineering for DevOps as assets.
That is because of the
complexity which we spoke about.
Like I have microservices, I have
spark engines running, I have logs
and sto I have data and Cosmos.
How do I integrate all this?
So in case of a software development,
that's not the environment which a
software development happens, but
DevOps happens like this, right?
So we should have the.
The models should be validated, the
designs, the sequence diagrams, the
umls, everything should be integrated
in case of a software deployment.
But in case of, an infrastructure
and full blown application.
We have several components, like
what I stated comes into play.
That is where there
should be more templates.
That's a concept where we can
use LLM into real automation
of financial event streams.
High throughput, high
viability, minimum latency.
All of this could be insured
by moder templates where we.
As engineers, we work on the templates
on what needs to be done and what
sort of prompts and what context are
relevant in a particular scenario.
And.
We also implement the policy constraints,
like what the model should not do.
These become very critical in case
of like production data, especially
you know, when you are dealing with
financial data and machine actionable.
So this is what something going
into the multi-agent system where
the output of one system should
be actionable to actionable and.
Would, should be in a format which
is Fable as input to the next
system for another agent to work on.
Now there are the core framework, so
like we can create template libraries.
And another advantage of doing all
this is that we can use source control
and have it standardized right?
Then any change would go through
reviewers and approvers, which
would help the entire team or the
organization to standardize the process.
And the benefit data layer, which
have all this schema registry.
So this comes into play when we
have to handle the, like anomaly
detection in a financial data
or like any type of transaction.
So that is where the metadata IRK
comes in and the policy engine.
So where you can write rules and
you will have, we have the output
validator to validate the output.
And also this is where the
output validator stage is where
the dashboarding comes to play.
Why won't XX allow a dashboard?
Where the the model efficiency
is being visualized, right?
So the template anatomy what
happens in the template?
What do we have in the template?
We should have the let me touch upon
the operational knowledge first.
Operational knowledge and
the policy constraints first
before coming to the event.
Context and schema reference though, what
constitutes the operational knowledge.
So when do we see an A log?
A log message?
What should be the next action?
So from the log message, what feels a
relevant for the agent for AI system to.
Take the next step or what feels
determined, the next action.
So this operational knowledge lie lies in
the head of many engineers or SRE today.
So this is AI platforms and prompt
engineering especially is a great
way to democratize the knowledge
between within an organization.
So once it is written out there by an SME.
Anyone can use.
So if, I suppose if I'm a junior
engineer going into a troubleshooting
how I do or I, what steps I take for
the troubleshooting, except for the
base basics, it could be way different
than how a senior engineer would
troubleshoot it and get to their results.
So what constitutes
the difference is that.
Subject matter expertise,
their experience and such.
So this is a great equalizer,
great leveler platform.
So the operational knowledge that, and
this is somewhere like the executives
of the ARC comes to play and what the
leadership thinks about AI platform and
how do we enable everyone to be to be
most productive and do more with less.
And the policy constraints, and
we should have an output format
where we determine what should be
or how the output should look like.
So from the templates to the
decision, so when the event.
Ingestion happens.
So we ingest events, which are like
financial events coming into our system.
That is where the
templates come into play.
We can route it using semantic kernel,
which could be a Microsoft agent
framework where, and we can write plugins
where plugins and the agent can route.
The request to several plugins, so
that is the software part of it, the
middleware part, and the templates.
Are the prompts and what do they act upon?
They act upon the logs.
And what is the corpus?
The corpus will have all the docs
that designs the code, everything
embedded and vectorized and
stored in a vector database.
So that, and then we can deploy an
LLM model to process the process the
request or to process the logs, right?
In between it happens.
The that it, what happens
is the context injection.
So the context injection to
a great part would be a part
of the agent framework too.
And we can write the software
to route route on the context
selection of the model.
Of the end framework, I would say.
And then we do a, we can do
necessary validations and
come up with an action item.
So what would be the action item?
The process doesn't end here, right?
The action item could be like, okay, I
have to replay these orders, or I have
to, I have to delete some duplicates.
So there should be an action or which
can be automated enough or enough to,
enough for the agent to perform by
itself or go through an approval process.
So what do we gain here?
So these are production scale, like
we know with the advent of cloud
itself, millions of transactions or
millions processing has been like
like a very common phenomenon with the
capabilities of distributed computing.
So we get the same benefits here
and we get reduced latencies.
And once you build a framework, all
you do always is to build on top of it.
And, what we need to do is only
to update the models when the
new models are in the market.
And by delivering, by using a well
balanced combination of context
engineering and prompt engineering.
We are not, the org organization
is not investing in LS two.
That would be just reinventing the wheels.
We have best performing LLMs right
out in the market and they are all.
We have them out of box.
So all we do is to tweak
it to our own requirements.
So this, for the platform teams,
the most critical component are
critical function of platform
teams is to maintain the systems at
high availability, which AI comes.
Pretty handy.
These tools comes pretty handy and they
have proved to be phenomenal invoices.
And we can automate.
So adding the context and having
the prompts, creating this
automation workflows will give
us more control on what we do.
Not let the model just go hair
and do whatever it wants to,
or whatever it thinks is right.
Rather that the SREs and the platform
teams have a better grasp or better grip,
better control of what these systems do.
What are the considerations?
So where do we start here?
So we can start with a
most common problem, right?
So this is where we go
with the 80 20 rule.
Like 20% of the problems we
solve, we gave an 80% gain, right?
We pick some use cases which are like
very frequent and are at the same
time causing a lot of tile to the DRIs
and integrated through the system.
We connected to the Observative
platforms and at the same time
implement back mechanisms until we know.
The performance and the performance
evaluation is fully done, and we
need to, it's best to have, establish
a feedback loop for improvement.
That could be like ad hoc also, right?
That need not be integrated
at the very beginning.
We can, get the feedbacks, validate get
the results, validate, take the feedback.
And that could be like
one time processing.
So in case of the vector databases, like
people like engineers, the teams are
continuously adding more documentation.
So how do we, how do the model
becomes stale if it works on
the previous data and some of.
Changes could be like critical, right?
So how do we change that?
So there should be a pipeline,
a separate pipeline to populate
and, do the vectorization and
store it and update the database.
So those are the those will be
like a feedback loops which can
sustain the sustainably improve
the performance of the model.
Like we said, we should have version MA
to maximize the template effectiveness.
We are like teams with 40 or 45
engineers working and in an application.
So version control comes, becomes
very important and we should have a
modular composition of the templates
rather than, write in our one big file.
Everything.
So the advantage of prompts is that like
that, again, that's like a separate, that
could be a separate session in itself.
We modularize the prompts and at
the same time and later we can
refer the prompt files so that
the module can check for the file.
So that is something which we touch.
Bay touch touched up on a bit on the agent
while talking about the agentic framework.
Now extending the framework.
So we have lot of cost gains,
especially lot of man hours would
be saved by automating these
workflows and we can implement the
risk evaluations for our platforms.
I'm sure you all would have heard about
architected frameworks, AWS and Azure have
their well architected frameworks and we.
Many teams leverage the, those frameworks
and have agent model evaluate their
applications to for the agent to
validate the security requirements,
the performance efficiency, and
cost effectiveness of those systems,
and it just churns out the results.
So those automations have like huge value
monetarily as well as efficiency wise.
So yeah, that's what the compliance,
something which we attached upon.
And security capacity planning, so the
resource forecasting and scaling recomme.
Also, this model can turn out.
So incident triage is one of the
main areas where many teams have,
are highly leveraging DevOps for ai.
So what are the key takeaways?
Use your templates, modelize your
templates, and put the context in
the right place and make sure you
audit the performance of the model.
With that, I'll end talk here.
It was great to have the
opportunity to interact with.
Everyone of you and we all
look forward to what's next?
What's the next major wave in the ai.
I am also like braising for that.
Thank you everyone.
Bye.