Speaker 28: Hello all under
the track of sustainability.
Today I'll be discussing generative
AI workflows for climate risk
modeling in food systems.
2024 was likely the first calendar
year recorded 1.5 degrees ingrade
above the pre industrial baseline
with cascading extremes affecting
agriculture and logistics.
This is now the operational
backdrop for our DevOps decision.
Today I'll show how to embed, generate
new climate intelligence into c cd and
so that the risk modeling downscaling and
stakeholder briefings, reliable software.
I'm Phan a data a, an analytics architect.
Working at the intersection of enterprise
platform and climate resilience focus
today from to maintainable systems
ml, that is DevOps m the challenge.
Climate volatility and that
threatens food systems, food
insecurity remains stubbornly high.
Sophie
Hunger.
2.3 billion experienced, moderate,
or severe food insecurity.
Affordability of healthy dates
remains a critical constraint.
2024 shattered climate shows that
compoundings floods and heat stress.
That heat production storage transport.
WO emphasizes early warning on climate
services as vital for protection.
The engineering takeaway is that
our data ML systems must anticipate
extremes, quantify uncertainty,
and continuously adapt them.
The convergence opportunity to start with
climate data availability, year five.
Provides howly globally analysis
since 1940 at around 31 kilometer
with uncertainty estimates.
A near realtime updates ideal for
historical baseline and features.
Sentinel two offers 10 to 20
multi-spectral L surface reflectance
with frequent revisit greater for
vegetation stress signal on soil moisture.
CIP six scenarios define futures
for emissions, socioeconomics for
forward looking stress testing.
The second, the generative and
ML weather climate graph CAST GNN
delivers 10 day global forecast.
Outperform.
E cm. Greater than 90% of targets
under running and minutes weather
transformer achieve nature.
Published accuracy orders
for magnitude speed.
Neural GCMA hybrid physics ml runs
weather and climate stably for multi
decade metrics with big efficiency gains.
Quad drift for kilometer
scaling down scaling.
For precipitation and near surface
fields critical for form level risk.
Finally, The DevOps maturity.
The gits ization and policy as a code.
Let's treat models like software
with tests, rollouts, and rollbacks.
We all use I workflows for
Q Flow case of so being said
that the core capability one.
The climate scenario build synthetic
extreme event tender symbols by
conditioning on CISP trajectories
and back testing against e use
to down scale global fields from
local ation temperature extremes.
Use graph to generate rolling 10
day ation sets for operational
planning for mid-century
stress test sample PS and bias.
How do we validate?
Compare synthetic extremes to historical
analogs from E five and even archives.
Quantify distribu with a high frequency
long regard helps here from technical
output to field ready intelligence.
Inges use CD APAs for ELI Copper
Data Space Sentinel Hub for Sentinel
two plus soil water rack databases,
generate scenarios, produce
drought, food, heat, and assembles
where cord ripped on scaling.
And graph cast, no cast.
Both are traceable in
CI because they're ized.
Model crop response link
weather stress indices.
Example, hot degrees, days, SPI
to yield models or agronomic Rules
translate into management actions,
translate produce form friendly
maps, sentinel, two LGA based layers.
Policymaker Brief summarizing
risk and R OI for interventions.
Core capability two.
Adapt to strategy generation.
Localized interventions
synthesized by LLM.
Agent workflows, cooperation,
irrigation timing, heat tolerant.
Risk sharing instruments conditioned
on hydrology, soils and economics FO
O 2025 disaster assessment underscores
raising shock across crops, livestock
and act culture strategy engines show
explicitly reason or multi hazar context,
localized intervention recommendations.
Crop rotation MA to soil via
pressures, irrigation tied to
seasons and soil moisture seed
selection aligned to phenology
under high drought and financials.
Ed by.
Vulnerability aligns again with WOAO,
emphasis on early warnings and climate
service for agri food resilience.
Core capability.
Three.
Automated brief generation use LLM to
gen compose stakeholder specific briefs.
Farmers what?
When.
Like sourcing risk, like budget
investments, NGOs, right include
uncertainty bans, references to
scenario IDs and data provenance
to satisfy governance and trail.
So DevOps integration
architecture, ization.
I grow workflows for CONT container
NA two Ds like ingest, generate
downscale, evaluate brief.
It's a CNC of graduated Kubernetes.
NAT and battle tested Cuba.
Flow pipelines V two.
Where you want to reusable
ML components and experiment
tracking serving case server for
standardized autoscale interference.
Supports both predictive ML and
LM two Endpoint with can rollouts.
Anders gis cd.
Cluster state with Kit Pipeline
services, confi, drift detection
and self model registries.
Azure ML Registry Model.
Registry for promotion and
lineage like Dev a w SageMaker.
Approval and CI CD integration.
Practical implementation considerations
like model, version and promotion.
Azure ml resist models as by our
registry across workspace with lineage.
Stage maker use model registry with
staging constructs and approval
Gates integrates with event breach
for approvals, scalable serving.
Case of inferior services for graph
cast, pango cord, and policy alums,
request based auto-scaling and can lots
continuous testing and data quality.
Run drift checks on features
and predictions using
identify, fail the pipeline.
Significant observability, use agro
metrics, surface dataset models, version
ID in metadata track extreme explicit
real world impact across ecosystem.
Tie outcomes to stakeholders.
Planting windows, variable
rated irrigations.
Seed selection insurance
triggers supply chain routing.
Align messaging with WMO data.
Four framing.
Invest in early warning plus climate
services and deliver actionable,
localized guidance via our of platform.
The path forward governance
and safe safety built in.
Operational trust using NI a RMF
four GO map, measure, manage, and
the 2024 generative VA profile
For LLM specific risks, map these
controls to your pipeline stages.
Publish model cars for each climate.
LLM component intended
Use data metrics and.
A P metadata.
Key takeaways integrate AI into pipelines.
Treat climate LLM artifacts
like software version tested.
Promote via GitHub's.
Agro CD ensures design states stay
in focus on practical outputs.
Farmer ready visuals Sentinel two.
Policy briefs with uncertainty and
R enable continuous adoption data
and concept as needed and registries
to conclude, generate AI foresight.
DevOps gives us.