Hello.
Welcome, everybody.
My name is Clara, and I want
to welcome you all to this new
edition off DevOps Conference 2025.
In the following 30 minutes, we
will review and navigate through
different test plans and test
strategies for the DevOps framework.
So let's start.
Welcome back to our session
DevOps test management.
strategies.
Let's start by introducing myself.
Who am I?
My name is Clara.
As I said, I'm from Argentina,
but I'm currently living in Spain.
I'm a passionate QA manager.
I have been in the QA industry
for over 14 years, and I have
enjoyed each one of those years.
I love our field of action.
I love our quality assurance work
and I'm very passionate about it.
There is a say in the QA industry and
we say for every development activity,
there is a corresponding testing activity
and I always want to honor that saying.
I'm also a lifelong learner.
I love to study, I love to train
myself, I love to develop and
acquire new skills, and I'm always
trying to achieve new goals.
I think, I honestly think I can
learn from anybody around me.
And I'm also a yoga teacher
and an assiduous meditator.
And I like to combine that
with my work activities.
I think the skills that I have
accomplished during my years meditating
are very useful for me during my work.
Okay, but enough about me.
Why are we here?
Today we are going to learn a little
bit about testing in a DevOps framework.
So we will start in Talking about
the generalities of our DevOps
framework, then the QA role within it.
And then we will deeply navigate
into the construction of a
proper test plan for DevOps.
And we will review a dual testing
strategy that encompass that test plan.
So I hope you enjoyed this
session as much as I did.
And let's start.
What is DevOps is a combination of
cultural philosophies, practices, and
tools that increase the organization's
ability to deliver applications
and services at a high velocity.
DevOps is all about fostering
collaboration, efficiency, and efficiency.
quality in DevOps framework, and we have
seven C's seven continuous activities
that we need to accomplish and ensure
those are continuous operation, continuous
development, continuous integration,
continuous testing, continuous deployment,
or deliver continuous feedback and
improvement and continuous development.
Monitoring.
This is, in a few words, in a nutshell,
the essence and the life of the DevOps
framework is not only a work framework,
it's also a cultural philosophy, a
mindset, and a way of we in the team
to work and collaborate together.
Together, evolving and improvement
products at a faster pace so we are able
to deliver to our clients in a velocity
way within this DevOps framework.
Which one is the QA role?
So we have been spoken
about continuous testing.
So what is the role of a QA in
a continuous testing framework?
DevOp DevOps, it's all about fostering
collaboration, efficiency, and quality.
In this continuous delivery model, QA
plays a crucial role by ensuring the end
to end testing integrates seamlessly.
Into the DevOps pipeline in DevOps, we
need to construct, maintain, sustain
a set off unit test cases to automate
and to execute within each deliver.
So continuous testing automates
and validates code changes
continuously, enabling rapid
feedbacks and risks reduction.
Enhancing, enhancing product reliability
and accelerating the release cycle
with a robust product ensuring quality.
So to start talking about a test
plan, we need to know what is a
test plan and which are the parts
that compose a good test plan.
There are a lot of things to
have in mind when you are working
and constructing a test plan.
I'm sure everybody here
is aware of those parts.
So we will quickly review the life and
the foundations of a test plan to go
deeply and navigate into the test plan
strategies and the test plan construction.
So the parts are the objective
is the first thing you need to
establish what is what are the
objectives for this testing endeavor.
Then the scope test methodologies.
Approach, the assumptions you
need to do, the risk assessment,
the risk identification, then a
mitigation plan or contingency plan.
You need to establish within your test
plan every role and responsibility.
You need to do the proper schedule
to have a proper timeframe
established for your test plan.
Then, we need to
establish a proper defect.
Tracking process tools
and people involved.
We need to establish the test
environments that this testing this
test plan is going to be conducted
on our entry and exit criteria.
Those must be written
within the test plan.
I know DevOps and agile.
Are not that deeply
into the documentation.
We are trying to deliver faster.
So documentation is relegated to a
second plan to a second part, but
it's not that we don't have any
is minimal documentation approach.
But we need to have the
necessary documentation in
the test plan is one of those.
So you need to write into your test
plan, your entry and exit criteria,
then the test automation part.
They want that we execute continuously
and also the ones that will be
added to that continuous test
suite within this test project.
Then our effort and estimation how long.
It's going to take us and what we need,
we need to do a resource allocation
here for environments, tools and people.
And then the test deliverables and temp.
So these are the 16 steps,
tasks or modules that forms.
A test plan.
So we will, explore the test plan
itself and the test strategies.
Let's just start regarding our test plan.
I want to introduce you guys and
girls in this opportunity to the
different levels that a test plan can
have in my organization, in my team.
I like to create a test plan
for organizational level.
Project level and software
development life cycle level
regarding the organizational level.
I always start by analyzing the
organization itself, its generalities,
the industry our organization is
in, the legal compliance that we
need to have in mind, the tools
that are used organizational wise.
So you need to have those in
mind regarding the project level.
That's regarding.
That's reflecting the current project,
so includes the test script, the test
suites, the people itself, and about the
software development life cycle level,
we need to make sure we accomplish
the delivery fast piece progress.
And cadence.
So by creating these three levels of test
plans, Yay Manager, as myself, ensures
that the testing activities are consistent
with organizational goals, flexible to
the individual project requirements,
and adaptive to the specific development
practices like DevOps, leading to a robust
and efficient quality assurance process.
We will review each one of
these test plans levels.
Let's start by the organizational level.
When you have a test plan at
organizational level, the purpose for this
test plan is to establish the overreaching
goals and standards for quality
assurance across the entire organization.
If the test plan, the organizational
test plan, has never been created,
This is a great opportunity for you to
start this practice as this test plan
will serve as foundation and baseline
for every other project test plan.
So in this organizational test plan, we
need to point out the tools for testing
that are used at organizational level.
the organizational industry requirements
that we need to comply and the
organizational goals for quality that
our complete company wants to achieve.
It ensures consistency in testing
practices and align the testing
strategy with the organization
mission and the quality objectives.
What will you add into
this test plan content?
It includes a guideline for testing
methodologies that we can use in our
organization that are recommended
and encourage the tools, as we said,
that we can use for each project.
Depending on the project, you will use,
utilize more or less of those tools.
If, for example, your project Is regarding
the non functional aspects, you will need
to use the tools for performance testing.
For example, Jmeter, if your project
includes user acceptance testing part
only, then you will focus on manual
testing, functional testing, and we
need also to address in this test plan,
in the organizational test plan, the
resources Allocation, including the
environments, servers, capability, the
third party vendors, if any, and the
resources within our organization, it
serves as a framework for all the project
specifics test that we will review now.
For a project level test plan, the purpose
of this, this is the most common test
plan that everybody designs and develops.
When you design your test plan is
commonly mostly at project level because
address the needs of the current project.
So it will include all of the actions
and steps that we review before.
But our project level, it focused
on the specific needs and goals
for this particular project, and it
includes the time map, the scope,
the objectives, technologies, and all
the aspects related to our project.
The content will be the testing approach,
the entry and exit criteria, the
resources, The timeline, the estimation,
of course, the specific test cases
and test suite or use cases are the
life of this test plan project level.
Here we will include the risk
analysis and the roles and
responsibilities for the project.
This is more detailed, is the longest
of our test plans and contextualize
that the organizational test plan
and use the organizational standards.
As a foundation, so the project level
test plan is unique per project, but the
organizational level test plan is the
same for every push now to review the
software development life cycle test plan.
This will also be reutilized and can be
shared within all the projects in the
company if we are all user using the
same software development life cycle
is a guideline baseline to utilize when
we are executing our project test plan.
The purpose of this project, the software
development life cycle test plan.
It's to address the specifics of the
development life cycle being used, such
as Agile, Scrum, or in this case, DevOps.
It ensures that testing is
effectively integrated with the
development process and aligned with
its iterative and collaborative.
Nature for this software
development life cycle test plan.
We will involve our project managers
are developers to validate that we are
planning the corresponding test activities
for every each development each deploy.
The content of this test plan, it's
specified the testing activities
tied to each phase of the software
development life cycle, such as in
continuous integration and continuous
deployment, the automation strategies.
The acceptance criteria for each
iteration, the performance testing and
non functional testing and monitoring
practices that we are going to put
in place and this helps ensures the
testing is an ongoing and adaptive to
changes during the development phase.
process.
So again, this can be reutilized in
different projects is not specific
to the project, but it is specific to
the software development life cycle
that we are using at company level.
That's regarding our
test plan development.
We have learned how to develop a
test plan in organizational level.
At project level, which is the
most common one and at software
development life cycle level.
Now that we have our test plan
developed, analyzed and tailored
to our needs and our project, we
can decide our testing strategy.
To construct a testing strategy.
In this case, I, myself, will use
three different testing strategies
coexisting for a DevOps project.
First of all, it will be
our continuous testing.
So this will include our automatic test
run that executes every time a code is
committed, allowing quick feedback and
rapid interactions as DevOps baseline.
But that will be general to any DevOps
project, the life of a DevOps project.
It's the continuous testing
and it's the robust set of unit
testing that is executed and run
every time a code is committed.
But for each project, we will need
to have our own testing strategy.
In this case, I would like to address a
shift left testing strategy as a first,
practice as a number one testing strategy
within, combined within a risk based
testing strategy as a secondary testing
strategy.
Let's review.
Shift left testing as it is on the name.
It stands for going to the
shift, shifting, shifting to
the left as much as you can.
You need, you need to start your
QA or testing activities as early
as possible within your software,
the development life cycle.
It's a day identify and fix defects early
in the development process by starting
test activities as soon as possible.
This is.
Very, very important.
The cheapest way to fix a defect is
to find this defect within the same
phase of the software development
lifecycle that was introduced.
That's the cheapest way to fix it.
And if we can mention some
industry standards, it's 15 times
cheaper to fix a defect within the
development phase that in production.
So that number is a lot.
If we reach our pre production
status or stage with a lot of
defects, we may consume our budget.
And there are a lot of projects that
never reach production because of this.
because of budget running out.
So shift left strategy involves
QAs as early as possible.
And what is the earliest possible?
Static testing.
So we will try to start our testing with
a static testing, Practices, the static
testing of the code, we can use tools
for the static analysis as SonarQube or
any other tools that your organization
is maybe using, or you can introduce to
the organization and the manual static,
testing, which is the reviews, the
reviews of the work products, reviews
of the user stories you can conduct.
And informal reviews, or if you
can go more formal and conduct
formal reviews or retrospectives.
For informal reviews, and the
most common practice that I will
recommend is the peer review.
So you can go doing peer review and review
the requirements, the test scripts, the
code, everything can be reviewed at its
early stage to try to identify and fix the
defects as soon and as cheap as possible.
So engage testers early in the sprint
or iteration, incorporate testing
into the design and decoding phases.
and carry out early non functional testing
such as performance and security testing.
Our second test strategy
will be risk based testing.
Risk based testing can coexist with
any other Testing strategy because
risk-based testing, BA is based on
the execution of the test script,
the execution of the use cases.
So let's review a little bit for a
risk-based test strategy, we prioritize
the testing activities based on the risk.
And the impact of different components and
features by focusing on areas that present
the higher risk, you can ensure critical
functionalities are thoroughly tested,
which is essential in DevOps environments
where rapid delivery is important.
So for a risk based testing
strategy, we need to perform.
two important actions.
One is the risk analysis and
the second is risk monitoring.
Let's review our first activity
for a risk based testing strategy.
The risk analysis.
The risk analysis includes two parts.
The first is risk identification.
You need to identify properly which
are the risks within your project.
How do you do that?
You involve in the risk identification
the correct Everybody that is a relevant
stakeholder needs to be involved in
a risk identification assessment.
You can do it by performing interviews,
retrospectives, risk workshops,
which are my favorite, actually,
because it's a very dynamic and
collaborative way to identify the risks.
Or you can use training.
checklist.
That can also be an offline activity and
you can send those to the stakeholders
by email and track the answers.
But within this activity, you should
end up with a proper list of risks,
properly identified by every stakeholder.
I cannot repeat Enough.
How important is to involve
the proper stakeholders in the
risk identification process?
Because if you don't identify the
risk properly, if you, oversee a
risk, or if you highlight as a risk
something that is not, it will result
in the complete risk based strategy.
being unused.
So after you conclude your risk
identification process, you
should end up with a list of risk.
Let's say, let's say risk
A, risk B and risk C.
Then it's time to do your risk assessment.
In this qualification of your risk,
You will assign a risk level for
each one of those identified risk.
What is your risk level?
A risk level is the combination
between the risk likelihood
and the risk probability.
impact upon occurrence.
So, for example, if risk a is very
likely to occur, but the impact upon
occurrence is very low, you will
identify this risk in a medium level
because it's very likely to happen.
You want to cover that to mitigate
that, but because its impact is very
low, you will assign it a medium level.
For risk B, for example, if the likelihood
of appearance is low, but the impact
upon appearance is critical, you will
anyway assign a high level to this
risk because you want to make sure that
This will not happen in production as
soon as possible and for risk C, if
they have a likelihood of appearance,
it's made, but the impact it's high.
You will also assign it as a
high risk level feature or this.
Then this will be the first
part of our risk based testing
strategy, the risk analysis.
After we have identified a risk and
assigned a risk level to each one of
those, we will continue to the second
part, which is the risk analysis.
Within the risk control, we continue
perform the risk monitoring.
This is a continuous activity.
This never stop.
Risk monitoring is part of our
strategy and our testing process.
This allow us to report on
testing progress in terms
already of residual risk level.
At any point, which is very important
for the stakeholders to make informed
and appropriate decisions regarding going
or not going to production, for example.
And also the risk control part includes.
The risk mitigation.
Our essential mitigation action
when we execute a risk based
testing strategy is to execute our
test scripts in a prioritized way.
We prioritize According to the risk
level, so the test scripts are assigned
from highest to lowest to a different
risk level regarding the feature of
functionality, having in mind the
risk assessment and identification we
just did during risk analysis part.
Regarding this test execution, there
are two ways in the industry that we can
choose to execute, a risk-based strategy
to mitigate risk as soon as possible.
The first execution will be a deep
first approach that execute all the
scripts in a strict descending order.
For the level of risk from the
highest to the lowest, so no matter
the feature or the part of the
system that we are executing the test
script, we will execute all the high
priority regarding the risk first and
then go down into until the lowest.
So that's one way to go.
It's very robust.
But it's time consuming
and it's very structured.
If we need to be more flexible or if we
need to make faster decisions, we will
choose a breathe first test approach.
In this test approach, Each test script
will be assigned to with the highest risk
priority, we will assign one test script
per feature or per product to the highest
test priority, and we will execute those
highest one per product or one per feature
as soon as possible in the first round
of execution, and then we will continue.
In this way, we will be able to
provide information regarding
the sanity of our project to the
stakeholders in a faster way.
So we will be able to assess and evaluate
the current quality if we execute
breathe first approach one test script
with the highest risk per feature.
Normally in our projects, we start with
a deep first testing approach because
it is more robust, more organized, but
as soon as we are starting consuming our
time and our budget, we move to a brief
first approach trying to provide it.
Thank you.
more information and to assess
the quality of our project in a
general way as soon as possible.
So this is regarding our risk control.
Let's review our key takeaways.
That has been our analysis regarding the
test strategies that we want to choose
and a compass for our three level test
plans within our DevOps framework project.
Why we will choose A mixed test strategy.
First, it allows you early detection
of the highest important defects.
It ensures efficient resource allocation.
You will allocate your resources
as soon as possible to the
highest risk part of your project.
It enhance collaboration.
You will involve all the stakeholders,
developers, project managers,
product owners, final users.
You will involve all of the stakeholders
within your development of your risk
strategy, and this will foster a
collaboration spirit in your organization.
It improves quality and speed because
you will isolate the defects faster
and you will have a robust test
strategy with three different test
plan levels and with three different
test strategies, the continuous testing
strategies from DevOps, a shift left
test strategy and a risk based approach
sustaining your other strategy.
And this will enable informed
decision making for your stake
holders and your managers.
So that's why we should always
consider this mixed test strategies
as a driven for our projects.
So that will be all.
And I just want to remember you guys,
girls, team, all the, this phrase that I
love from RQA environment and RQA world.
The product quality is highly
influenced by the quality of the
process being used and applied.
So if you, your process has a
high quality, it will influence
highly the quality of your product.
So remember to invest time
developing a tailored process
for each of your projects.
Thank you very much.
And I hope you, we can stay in touch.
So please add me to your LinkedIn accounts
and let's continue talking about quality.
I hope you have enjoyed this time.
So thank you.
Okay.
So that was all for today's session.
Thank you very much for staying
with me for this 30 minutes.
I hope you find this information
very useful and let's keep in touch.
Thank you.