Speaker 21: Hello everyone.
My name is Mohi Gupta.
I'm a staff GP performance
verification engineer at Intel.
Today I will talk about how we can
make these GP performance a first
class citizen in the CICD pipelines,
especially for the modern AI
infrastructure where GPUs are expensive,
shared and performance sensitive.
When I say CACD, that stands
for this continuous integration
and continuous deployment.
The key challenges with the GP performance
to scale is often discovered when
you're, when you do after deployment.
So at that point, the feedback
loops are slow and costly and the
traditional post-deployment testing.
Doesn't work well when GPUs are shared
across many workloads and teams.
So when we say widely, the
performance validation matters.
There are three main reasons this matters.
The first one is the cost.
So GPUs are major infrastructure
investments and regression,
actually waste compute resources.
The second one is the reliability.
So AI workloads needs predictable
trainings and inference performances.
And the third one is the early detection.
So when you're catching issues in
the CACD, it prevents production
incidents and keep teams moving fast.
Going with this framework overview,
the solution we proposed is
embedding GPU performance validation.
Directly into the CICD.
So when the framework focuses on GPU
micro architectural behaviors, and
it reduces quantitative metrices,
automated performance gains, and all
these observable signals that actually
persist throughout the deployment cycle.
So understanding these workloads
characteristics, not all GP
workloads behave the same.
So there are two major ones.
One is the compute bound
and then the memory bound.
So if we talk about compute bound
workloads, they're dominated by
math operations and expect high A LU
utilizations with low memory stalls.
But when it comes to memory bound
workloads, they're limited to data
movements such as cache misses, bandwidth
saturations access pattern, where it
matters more than the actual raw compute.
So the classification criteria for these
quantitative metrices, so we classify
workloads using measurable GPU counters,
things like a LU utilization, cash hit
rates, memory stall cycles, bandwidth,
the usage and coalescing efficiencies.
So these gives us objective
signals instead of relying on
subjective performance debugging.
So the validation methodology uses
three categories of benchmarks.
The first one is the dense linear
algebra for compute heavy AI workloads.
The second one is irregular
memory access patterns such as
graphs and spars operations.
And the third most important one is
the hybrid workloads that combine both
the compute and the memory behavior.
To reflect real production systems.
So let's go with compute
bound work workloads.
So we have seen that, we can see that
the sustained A LU utilizations around
85% in the compute bound workload.
We have strong L one cash localities
and memory minimal memory stall cycles.
So these results confirm that
are benchmark effectively.
Stress compute pipelines without being
memory limited, but when we talk about
memory bound results, the bandwidth
utilization reaches about 75, 70 5%, and
we all see a clear difference between
structured and the irregular access
patents, especially high coalescing
efficiencies for all the structure
accesses, and much lower efficiencies
for irregular ones highlighting.
The optimization opportunities
for these workloads.
So the critical discovery is this
mixed workload interaction in which,
when compute bound and memory bound
workloads run concurrently, so the
performance degradation appears that
isolated testing completely misses.
So cash, contentions, and
resource interference.
Change performance behavior, which is why
mixed workload validation is essential.
So implementing this automated
practice, this means we are defining
performance gates in CICD, automating
benchmark executions in a control
environment, and actually capturing
GPU Metricses as a part of every build.
So the performance become code.
Version, repeatable and enforceable.
Some of the platform engineering
capabilities approach, if we talk
about it, helps actually to prevent
regressions, gain continuous
visibility into performance trends,
and actually shifts optimization
earlier in the deployment cycle.
So when the fixes are
cheaper and actually faster.
The same metrics used for validation
feed directly into the observability.
The GPU utilization trends, the bandwidth
saturations, the cash degradation alerts,
and the workload mix actually give the
SRE teams the data they need to manage
reliability and capacity proactively.
So some of the key takeaways from
these for the platform teams, if
I have to summarize, is the first
one is the embedded performance
validation into the CICD.
The second would be use quantitative
metricses to classify workloads.
The most important that to test
mixed workloads, especially
not just isolated benchmarks.
And the fourth one is the to
build observable systems so
that the GPU performance remains
predictable as AI platform scales.
At last, I would like to
thank you for your time.
I'm happy to take questions or discuss
how this approach can be adapted
to our CACD and AI infrastructure.
So thank you so much.