Hello, hello, hello to all the brilliant
souls on the another side of the screen.
I hope you're doing great.
At first, let me introduce myself.
My name is Denis.
So, as you can see, I've been
in this field for quite a while.
Long enough to have caught
HTML for an escape navigator.
I imagine some of you might
not even know what this is.
And it's perfectly fine.
no worries here.
there have been many interesting
developments in those days.
I've worked in numerous roles
here and there, but always
within the tech industry.
Along the way, I earned some badges
I found really handy and fancy, like
Associate Coach from the International
Coaching Federation and Professional
Scrum from Ken Schwaber's Scrum.
org.
And, long story short, I'm currently a
contributing engineer at a tech startup.
We're developing project portfolio
and program management software.
So, yeah.
for the banking industry.
And, today I'm going to bring
out some insights I found
available to share with you.
when considering sustainable
software development.
So, let's go ahead.
You know, whatever is suffering,
as Buddha said, but, I suspect
software engi software development
is the real cause of the problem.
I see that, coding is actually a
relentless choice between bad and worse.
you know, many of these delays,
microservices, or monolith service side
render, or client side render, space
complexity, or time complexity, making
a call, or sending an email, and so on
and so on, thousands of them every day.
Let me simplify here.
Imagine the code you write every day
is just a set of words translating
business requirements into machine code.
So, here I suppose coding
is simply communication.
Communication causes a lot of issues.
I didn't get it.
I forgot it.
I didn't hear it.
maybe I don't like it.
Familiar situation, innit?
If we agree on the idea that coding
is communication, then corollary
one is the best code is no code.
And I would like to show you how
complexity arises from absolutely nothing.
So, have a look at this.
It's quite an ordinary situation.
We have a page with a footer.
It's here.
Footer.
And, we want to add some copyrights,
some copyright block here.
With dates.
Let's do it.
Like, 2024.
Denis
Ermakov.
All rights reserved.
Let's check in the browser.
Refresh.
Something goes wrong.
Perfect.
it's here.
We, we can see a photo.
We can see a photo here.
but, what if the new year comes?
May wonder a newbie engineer.
we need some automation here.
So, let's do it.
New Year comes, like that.
Let's say New Year is current year.
New Year is current year.
Let's define the current year.
Let's check.
Yeah, it works.
It works.
So, that looks great.
But, wait, what if someone else,
will use our great solution?
and it might happen another
year and we don't know.
What's here exactly?
So let's help them.
let's say they started it.
Started using it at the start year.
Let's define start year.
Let's say it started the same year.
Let's check.
Oh, something goes wrong.
we can see 2025 twice.
That's a problem.
we must fix it.
Let's check.
I did it before to save our time.
There is solution.
Let's check in the browser.
Perfectly, it works.
Let's check another case.
Let's start with 2023, fresh.
Yeah, it looks great.
We fixed the problem.
But wait, there was no
problem to begin with.
We add some code, conserved a
problem, and then we fix it.
That's absolutely,
absolutely no, no sense.
Imagine, nobody dies if
there is no code at all.
Nobody loses their fortune
if there is no code at all.
Absolutely nothing happens.
No code, no problem guys.
Let's fix it.
Yeah, we did it great again.
Fantastic.
Let's go back to the slides.
Go back to the slides.
so, here is another example.
there is a simple GitHub flow.
Someone pushes to a repository.
which triggers a linter to
run, and then build runs, and
finally the deployment happens.
So, let's, let's see, let's
see, what do we have here?
That's, that's a GitHub action
described in YAML format.
So, we have, push to stage,
and then we run some lints.
When we run build, if everything
okay, if everything okay.
here, everything okay on success,
we'll send message to Telegram channel,
and if something goes wrong, if
something fails, we'll send a warning
message to the Telegram channel.
Looks fine, good enough, not really
a newbie engineer might reply,
they don't want broken code in the
staging branch, they want to revert
the broken code, hmm, let's check.
There is, adjusted GitHub action.
It, does the same thing, but there
is a reversion, a reversion on fail.
So we added one step to robot
comment, and then if everything
okay, we'll send message to telegram.
Fine.
We fix the problem.
Yeah, we fix the problem.
But wait, what?
The previous committee is also broken.
Let's, run linter and run build one
more time to check if it's okay.
So, the same extended or adjusted action.
So, we revert last commit.
And then we run, we run lint and build.
So, and then we send telegram message.
Fine.
Hmm.
Wait, but, What is, the
comet before that comet?
Is it also broken?
We need to find the last healthy comet.
We'll say in UBIngineer.
Let's do it.
It's easy.
So, so here we are.
There is a recursive revert and rebuild.
So, we have, the cycle whileJune, where
we, run reversion, and then we run lint
build, and if everything is okay, we'll
exit from the loop, and it looks perfectly
fine, but, but, guys, are you ready to
bet against GitHub, and, are you ready to
bet against, possibly an infinite loop?
You know, I've played this game
before, and I lost, so I can't advise.
the idea that we really don't
need to cover each cases here.
bro, just go and fix the
problem in the comment.
It's easy.
So, let's get back to slides.
What is going here and here
we have the corollary to The
best library is no library.
So let's have a look.
Let's have a look Best
library is no library.
So, you know, take a look on this
piece of code Here imagine we have
a duration in milliseconds Like the
time a ticket has been in progress.
We want to format the duration
in a human readable style.
So, if it's too long,
we'll print out days.
Otherwise, we'll show hours,
minutes, or even seconds.
So, what will the newbie engineers say?
they could say that date
objects are really awkward.
Wait milliseconds that normal
people never deal with.
The 29th of February only
happens once every four years.
The 2038 problem is looming,
endless division by 60 and 24.
Let's use a handy library like moment
to handle days like normal people made.
Bro.
It's a trap.
Let's see.
So we have, what we have
here, we have milliseconds.
We have, function for duration.
We have.
milliseconds as a, an argument.
So we are, we're going to use moment
here to convert, in human readable format
using human readable methods as second.
We, we get milliseconds and,
apply the method eight seconds.
And we then we took milliseconds
and, converted to minutes.
We took milliseconds
and, converted to hours.
And so on, and so on, milliseconds,
two days, great, great enough,
but, let's have a look, let's have
a look, the next piece of code.
So, let me, let me do this one.
Oh, something goes
wrong, let me check, huh.
Okay, what's going here?
we can achieve the same result, same
result, the same function, yeah?
Okay.
Formal duration.
We can achieve the same
result with proper naming.
We don't need to use
library with proper naming.
We can just use proper
naming in our variables.
So we took milliseconds
and divided first on 1000.
So we got seconds.
Next, we divide seconds.
And, got means, and so on.
Hours, days, the same number
of, the same number of lines.
The same result.
And we have saved 145
kilobytes of collateral code.
Amazing.
How does it work?
I didn't show you.
Yeah, here it is.
Duration, days, like that.
Yeah, so, let's back to, let's
back to deck with lights.
What's here?
Corollary 3.
Well, if you still need words
to communicate, then code them.
There is no need to write
long stories in your readme.
md or in your wiki or
Confluence or whenever.
do you have your own unique
code style in agreements?
Yes.
Good, code them into linters and let
them run on every command s after saving.
let's have a look.
So, what's here?
Yeah, what, what, what's here?
Yeah, there is printer,
and there is this lint.
So, it's quite easy.
what actually happens?
you actually don't need to write
the number of spaces for your tabs.
In Confluence, it's described here in
Pre TRC, so you, you can just put them
in, in your repository, let them be
part of your repository, and, relax.
So, it's quite easy, you
don't need any words.
Add some code and put
it in your repository.
That's great.
So, back to slides again.
Corollary 4 is foster
your team's dictionary.
So, what does it mean?
foster your team's dictionary
and keep it in your readme.
ind.
and I suggest to start with done.
What does that mean to the team?
do you know I sure everyone is
aligned on what does, what done means.
Let's write it down to make sure
what's what, what does done means.
What does done mean?
So, let's write it.
Yeah, readme.
What does done mean?
So, here is readme.
And I want to start with dictionary.
Dictionary or glossary.
Okay, let's start with
done, as I suggested.
Done.
So, I suppose there are a
lot of work items you deal
with every day, like rechart.
Like, maybe a user story,
or maybe task, or even bug.
So, let's define, let's
define dan for user story.
When I said, When I say, then I say
a done for user storage, that's mean.
for example, the re the Ram Unit tests,
unit tests and the coverage, I say 70%.
So when I say done, that means there, that
means, there, Integration, integration
tests and coverage say, I don't know, 50%.
When I say user story done,
that means there are end to
end tests, end to end tests.
And say coverage, I don't know, 30%.
Okay, what else?
When I say done That mean,
product, documentation.
Done.
Yeah, documentation.
If I say, if I say done,
that means, there is
documentation.
If I say done, that mean
product owner got a video link.
With end to end test.
And if I say done for user story, that
mean that Pure said amazing, guys.
So, if Pure said amazing, we are
ready to ship the user story.
So, we did it.
Now everyone knows what does done mean.
Means.
So, let's, go ahead.
let's go ahead two slides.
yeah.
Remember corollary three,
it said, code, code.
If you have words, it's
better to code them.
So let's let, let's, let's do it.
Let's code the words.
There are a lot of words.
something about unit tests.
So, let's imagine we
already have unit tests.
And, we want to run it.
And see the coverage.
Let's run.
Something goes on.
Going on.
Yeah.
Look at that.
Come on.
Yeah.
Great.
We are green.
We are totally green.
At first.
We have coverage.
So, fantastic.
We can, we can, we can
check that it's done.
So, next, imagine we are done with
integration and end to end tests.
So, what about documentation?
Yeah?
what about documentation here?
I need a code.
Let's make some documentation.
So, I would use I will use robot for that,
let's ironman walk, works, give me a type
doc, I use type doc, comment, for function
format duration, yeah ironman is walking,
yeah we have some description, let's
save it, and next we need to generate
some documents, I use tab doc,
The generation is in progress.
Yeah.
Generation is in progress.
Something goes wrong.
What?
Yeah.
Everything is done.
Let's check.
Let's check here.
Yeah.
Here is a documentation for our
function with comments from Copilot.
So, We are done with this function, this
item, this item of done, we are done.
So, and and so on and so on.
there are, there could be any items,
any items in your done definition.
So, it's your choice.
But, what is important about here,
now you can easily make this choice a
part of your GitHub action, you know.
And to save time, I'm
going to skip this part.
And, what's important here, by the
way, speaking of testing, there, you
know, there is a mass load pyramid
for normal people, and there is
a testing pyramid for engineers.
And, the Pyramid suggests
writing a lot of unit tests,
and just a few end to end tests.
But, I'm afraid, I'm, I'm
afraid we are mistaken.
I suspect, it's really telling
us, one end to end test is worth
a billion unit tests and mocks.
So, I prefer one end to
end, one end to end test.
and, that, is what I Can advise
so let's go father We called it.
We called it.
We called it some words.
Yeah, we are here.
So We still talking about communication.
And if you still have to communicate
then Just short shorten the feedback
loops you have I Suppose there is the
smartest guy in the room Who reviews
your pull request once a day And,
well, that's good enough, but, what's,
about an hour of peer coding session
or an hour of mob coding session each
day with ongoing peer to peer reviews?
that shortens feedback loops and
forced sharing of knowledge, you know?
So, try to shorten your feedback
loops, any, any feedback
loops you have in your team.
And, you will be wondered.
So, about communication, most people
feel uncomfortable in uncertainty.
Feeling uncomfortable
leads to wrong decision.
And wrong decision lead to messy codebase.
So, how can, how do we handle it?
Let's see.
As a software engineer, you spend
most of time, most of your time
operating within this triangle.
I call it the Manager Sensara Triangle.
So, that's a, that's a triangle
about money, time, and requirements.
So, your decisions are restricted
by boundaries of this triangle.
But, say me, does it make sense?
Make you feel any better?
I bet not, very much actually.
So how can you, how, how, how
can we empower our re resilience?
It's, simple.
Follow your principles,
share them with your team.
Enjoy.
Sounds simple because that's simple.
Principles are something you
always carry in your pocket.
So, they are always with you.
And you can say, what
even are principles, dude?
What's it, what are you talking about?
There are plenty to choose from, and
you can pick something from above.
You can take some from
Scrum, or Java, or Kanban.
Or you can ever take something from
Prince, if you are a votes for guy.
So, just go with the 10 commandments,
I've heard they work pretty well, indeed.
So, you can pick any system of
principles and values, but you
should embrace them entirely.
That's the key.
You cannot deliver 10 times a day and only
meet business people once a fortnight.
Yeah, that's agile principles,
if you're familiar with.
Yeah.
So, what else?
Build your daily routine step by step.
Have you ever heard that small,
small kids tend to develop attention
deficit hyperactivity disorder?
If they are, if they
aren't properly routinized.
That's exactly what you would
expect as a software engineer.
So, I suggest, fill your day
or week with simple routines.
Every short day, briefing,
paid programming session, maybe
mobbing session, refactoring
session, whatever works for you.
Maybe retrospective or
sprint reviews, whatever.
And just stick to them.
So, few words about bad news, you've
already been out if you choose comfortable
task or those that truly matter, you
spend time trying to figure out the best
solution instead of focusing on workable
one, or you are simply tired, so I suggest
next best action for you, remove one
library from your app today, eliminate
one item from your backlog next sprint.
And, define you're done
and automate it, please.
So, at least get some
rest if you're tired.
but, That's the end actually, around
the end, don't hesitate to reach me,
to reach out to me, all my contact
details are on my website, which you
can find on the second slide above.
And, guys, always remember, syntactic
sugar causes cancer of semicolons.
Bye bye here.