Hello everyone.
I'm Alex.
Very honored to be here.
once again, I can say, so I am
going to talk a little bit about,
AI, you know, AI is everywhere.
Nowadays you can find it in, I can see
in every single aspect of our life.
So.
as a DevOps engineer.
I'm going to talk about a little
bit about the impact of artificial
intelligence in our daily activities.
So this is leveraging AI in DevOps, next
generation strategies for enhance and
efficiency, efficiency and innovation.
So a little bit about, about me.
I'm Alejandro Mercado
Rice and born in Mexico.
I, I do the bobs as I said,
technical writer and speaker.
Sometimes I speak.
So there is, if you want to reach
me, there is my, you can see my
information right on the slide.
So.
Talking about some predictions, I don't,
I don't like to talk about predictions.
I can say, I will rather say perspective
because I mean, I don't have a crystal
ball, but for sure we are going to
see this, this trendings, in this year
and the following a couple of years.
in the following years.
So, so we are going to keep seeing,
of course, a lot of artificial
intelligence, quantum computing,
computing, 5G connections.
H computing block, more blockchain,
more blockchains, cyber security is a
major factor in, in all the industry.
The software development industry,
augmented reality, sustainable
technologies, remote work and
collaboration tools, human.
Human computer interaction is
something that we are evolving at.
We, for sure, we are going
to see more about that.
More experiments, more
projects, more technologies.
And I can say a lot of these
technologies and trending technologies
are going to overlap for sure.
I mean, you can do human
computer interaction based on AI.
and I mean, overlapping is
going to be pretty common.
So Why the bobs and why and where
is relevant artificial intelligence
that the bobs, practices, we have
been doing the bobs a lot of time.
You know, you can see
this, this, timeline.
so right now we can see in the, in the
last, Bullet or milestone that DevOps
is like a present or regular practice.
I can say right now in a lot of
companies adopted DevOps because
they are seeing the advantages.
So what we are doing now is to
increase the maturity and the
productivity while doing DevOps.
So, so, well, this is a, the traditional,
I can say, So you can see each one of the
software development like cycle phases.
So, you know, it's, it's your plan,
code, build, test, release, deploy,
operate, monitor, and repeat.
And this is like an infinite loop.
So I bring this to the
conversation because in each phase.
We can use artificial intelligence.
So of course, as a engineer,
we are doing more with less.
I mean, we can code, we
can test, we can plan.
We can, and have like this secretary
or assistant to help us to, to increase
our productivity and be more efficient.
Spend the better the time.
I mean, you can spend more
time in important things.
So for sure, this is one
of the main advantage.
I am not saying that artificial
for, for, for, for sure.
I'm not saying that artificial
intelligence is going to replace
humans, but we need this kind of, AI
to be more efficient and they are here.
So the idea is if you take a look of each
one of these phases, there is a tool on
the market, open source or proprietary to
help us to accomplish these activities.
So I just want to, to mention
a couple of these, because we
have, In, in every single aspect.
If, if you consider the, the whole
DevOp cycle we have in, in deployment
and incident management and, and code
testing and quality analysis, and
in the monitoring and observability
field, we have a lot of tools helping
us to improve our, well every aspect.
We, we, at them, we are going
to have more secure software.
box, decrease the, the, the time to
repair or even to, to acknowledge the,
the Abu on, on production environments.
So definitely because systems are
getting more and more complex.
The landscape are.
Cloud, on premise, hybrid, multi
cloud, different databases.
I mean, there is a lot of
considerations, a lot of components,
microservices, mono, monolithics,
containers, et cetera, et cetera.
So there is no.
enough human power to attend all of these
aspects and to take care about everything.
So we need this, this, this tools
to, to help us to in our activities.
So.
One aspect that we are talking,
the, the last, it is not new.
I, we can say that last couple of
years is, is an operation side.
You know, having this code, this piece
of code on, on production, it means that
there is going to be a lot of activity
attending users, request, latency.
So.
We talk now about AI ops.
I mean, the operation assisted by, by
artificial intelligence, to detect to
early detect some problem, even, even,
we talk now about observability
versus monitoring, meaning that
we can be proactive in what
is going on with our software.
I mean, we can detect if we
have a pattern that I mean, is.
By correlation, we can know if something
is going to fail, it's going to fail
because it's taking a lot of resources
or latency or it's taking a lot of time.
I don't know.
It depends on the day.
So we can find a root cause, before even
it fails, even the, the user, notice.
So this is, this is pretty important.
Because of course we can,
we can save a lot of money.
So new frontiers.
Yeah, for sure.
Well, we are seeing new frontiers
in each aspect of the, the, the,
the, the, the, the DevOps cycle,
like in the project management.
we can see a lot of open
source or commercial tools.
Like I can say, just to name a few,
Jira, Asana, Notion, et cetera.
They are all based on artificial
intelligence, but they are adding some
features based on intelligent AI to,
to be so, so we can be more productive.
This is like an experiment, something
that I have been working on.
It's, it's, you know, we have these
boys skills assistants, in, at home.
So, so we are going to
see these new frontiers.
And one of these frontier
is the, the boys assistants.
So I started to think, and why, why not?
I can handle my daily activities
with, with just my voice because
I can handle some difference.
I don't know, pipelines, clusters,
health, et cetera, et cetera.
Many related activities to DevOps.
Well, I want, I am driving or I
don't know, I mean, hands free.
So I started this experiment is, is, is
at this moment is just running on Alexa.
Because I, there's no, no other
reason than, than I have an Alexa.
so my experiment is about this
integration of voice control
technology with Kubernetes management.
So, so I can same, I can, trigger an Alexa
skill just to manage my cluster so I can
monitor, I mean, if, if there is an error
or the systems goes down, I can notice.
with, with an alarm in my Alexa, or
I can do some, administrative tasks.
So, well, this is a work in progress,
but it's, it's something like that.
so I can, there is a, an activate
voice command, open Kubernetes manager,
so I can create a cluster, destroy
the cluster to ask for the help.
It's some, some, some node is failing.
I just want to know about it.
So, well, this is something that, if I
think about it, I can monitor or I can
handle manage every aspect of my daily
activities, but of course it's requires
a lot of, I mean, instead of using the
regular input, that is the keyboard.
Well, maybe some tasks can be
done through the, to the boys.
So, so I think this is.
Like the things that I, I want to see
that we are going to see in, in a couple
of years that we are evolving for sure.
So why, because we can have this increases
efficiency, we can reduce error in his
collaboration, improve accessibility.
That is a very important aspect of
using voice assistance technologies
so we can have streamline
workflows and contextual awareness.
So yeah, for sure we are going to see
this kind of trending, this kind of new
technology or some not so new technologies
helping us in our daily activities.
Project manager, we already talked
about a little bit of a project
management powered AI tools.
in the side of code generation, I
mean, when I'm writing code, I can
get a lot of help from Any of these
ones, choose your favorite one,
GitHub, Coursera are pretty famous one.
so, so we can be more productive because,
well, this is something that we do a lot.
I mean, some, some, sometimes we don't
know about a method or, or a property.
So we come to, to Google it or to,
to ask in a stack overflow or other.
other sites to get some help.
And this is something that we do a lot of.
So instead of going to through these
portals or forums, we can just write
what we need and it's going to help us.
I mean, it's not going to replace us.
We, we, we have the, the, the wheel, but
the steering wheel But definitely it's
going to, it's, it's, it's like having a,
an assistant, like doing pair programming.
So this is in the, in the generative
code side, even in the testing, in the
testing side, we have a lot of options.
So we can conduct any, any type of, or
almost any type of, of testing, like
continuous, static units, testing,
code coverage, mutation testing.
Using these tools like JetBrains,
Snyk, SonarQube, et cetera, et cetera.
So in general terms, we are going
to find, we currently find a lot
of AA based DevOps tools, like for
automated infra provisioning, like,
Ansible or in the other side for.
For incident response like Splunk,
Datadog, ServiceNow, et cetera, et cetera.
There is a, a, a, a huge
explosion of these kind of tools.
So, In the, in the site of infrastructure
of ASCOTE, we are seeing right now a lot
of traditional Tools like Terraform that
they are using now, they are powered
by, AI to help us to create a more
robust code and to, it can detect if
there is not consistency in our, at the
moment of provisioning the resources.
So, yeah, of course it's, it's in every,
in every single aspect of our project.
So we're developing like sample.
So, so you can take a look of any,
any, so if, if you are more on the site
reliability engineer side, you have
this, service level object at the DNA,
so of course you are going to improve
the, the service level on your teeth.
With this kind of tools.
So in summary, server ledged objectives
are essential in DevOps cycle, as
they provide clear and measureable
way to define, monitor, and improve
the quality of services, ultimately
driving better outcomes for the
business and its customers, for sure.
So.
Well, I, I would like to quote this,
AI is not the future, it's the present.
So take that in, if you, when
I take away, this can be one.
a lot of these, tools, are based on logs.
You know, logs can say a lot of things and
we can find through the logs, root cows.
So CloudWatch is one of many, many
of the monitoring and observability
services that we can find.
Well, this is, of course,
running in AWS, but any other
cloud provider have, have logs.
So the importance of having logs
is that we can have these AI
power tools to get the root cause.
So, yeah, that's why I bring
it into the conversation.
So I drive in the Bob's causes, besides
the single Presti practice of AIOps is
automated infrastructure provisioning,
predictive maintenance, code quality
analysis, intelligent incident
responses, and automated density.
So you can be.
Way, way more productive with, with these
tools than, I mean, like an attrition
now, team that is doing this manual,
it's, it's, it's tough to, to measure the
impact of, AI in, in DevOps, because, I
mean, sometimes we don't even notice that
the, the, this kind of tools are using.
The, the, these technologies, or
we don't have like a metric to say,
well, I started to, to use copilot.
So I commit, in shorter time.
So, well, I mean, it's difficult,
but according to some studies,
some studies by Garner, we, we, the
impact, for instance, in the meantime,
to recovery is reduced by 25%.
Well, in terms of, you know,
this is related to money.
So, so we are saving 25%, because
the system is, is, is not down.
deployment frequency, you know,
you are going to have more value
because You are streaming the
value because you are increasing
the deployment frequency by 30%.
So, so, well, these are just,
to be honest, I don't know how
these guys, calculate the, these
metrics, but I mean, it's something
that we are going to talk more.
And it's, it's going to be in our daily
dialogues and conversations at the office.
So of course there are, challenges,
you know, the whole DevOps theory
is, is more cultural than practices.
It's, it's a long journey and there
is a lot of implementation challenges.
Yes, I can say.
So like, you know, the, the hallucination,
sometimes you don't, you don't get
the, or the responses or answers
that you get are just misleading.
It's happened a lot at this point,
but that's the idea to train the
model to, to get better results.
So it's, it's going to, I mean,
under the hood is, is a, is a
model that we need to train.
So, so the data quality
is, is, is important.
So, so it's, it's, that's where
I say that it's a long journey.
We are going to train these,
these models to get better
information, better insights.
So yeah, the integration
takes, takes time.
So you have to, you know, to, to
play, to experiment and to spend some
time to get this, this advantage.
But at the end, and this is for
sure, you are going to see the, the,
the results of, of these practices
based on, or powered by AI, you know,
like the increased deploy frequency,
reduced mean time to response, customer
satisfaction, change failure rate.
So, as I said, it's a long journey.
The maturity in DevOps, I mean, it's not
like the automation is not the purpose.
I mean, it's like a consequence of
implementing DevOps and DevOps with AI,
but achieving DevOps maturity is ongoing.
It's an ongoing journey that
requires commitment, patience and
willingness to adapt to the ever
evolving software delivery landscape.
So be patient.
and that's it.
I am going to be around here.
If you have any question or
you can contact me, there
is my LinkedIn information.
So yeah.
Thank you very much.
Bye.