Speaker 32: Hello everyone.
I'm Pran ami.
I am excited to be presenting at
DevOps 2026 organized by Con 42.
I'm thankful for the opportunity,
and today I will be speaking about
from Signal to Insight, how I've
built a Queryable observability
dashboard and a tool chain using MCP,
which is the model context protocol.
So let's get into it.
About me.
So I am currently a software engineer
at Workday, and previously I've had
stints at McKinsey, Microsoft, PayPal.
I am experienced with distributed
systems, AI and cloud infrastructure,
and my work focuses primarily on ai
ML infrastructure and observability.
I often write about my findings and.
My learnings in my blog on LinkedIn
called Distributed Bys with
Prone, and these are my socials.
So I'm excited to be sharing this
con this presentation with you.
So now let's get into the weed of things.
Why should you actually care?
And what's in it for you guys
who's attending the conferences?
So let's imagine a scenario like we have
all been there as on-call engineers,
that we get a 2:00 AM page and whenever
we get on that, we start looking into.
The data avalanche, like tens of terabytes
of blogs daily are being ingested in
that pla in a platform or services,
millions of metrics and data points,
millions of distributed traces and
thousands of correlation ID per minute.
And what we struggle with most is manual
correlation across systems, tribal
knowledge, dependency, alert fatigue,
and delayed root cause analysis.
So from what we have seen.
So far in our careers is that we don't
have a data shortage problem because data
today is not the scarce commodity, but we
have a data context or meaning problem,
and that's what I'm going to solve with my
proposed new architecture from converting
observability from a reactive standpoint
to a more proactive and measured approach.
So let's look at why
modern observability fails.
So we all know that observability,
there are three key pillars in
observability, which is metrics, which
tells us essentially what is happening.
Logs tell us why it happened,
and traces where it happened.
And the core problem is that
without the consistent thread
of context, debugging and manual
correlation it becomes really hard.
And this has been actually backed by data.
So 50% of the organizations report siloed
telemetry, and only 33% achieved unified
views across metrics, logs, and traces.
According to the 2023 Observability
for Forecast report by New Relic,
which has been cited let's look at the
paradigm shift that we are observing
and that we have leaned into it.
Leaned into to solve the problem.
So traditional observability
correlation at incident time.
So whenever we get an incident, we
correlate and draw the path of the
whole incident, how it happened, why it
happened, and understand the context.
The minimum time to detect
resolve becomes slower.
However, in the new approach, the minimum
time to detect resolve becomes faster.
There is higher alert fatigue.
On the on-call engineers or an SRE
and reduce developer productivity.
However, on crown contrast this, by
this approach, we feel that there
would be lower alert fatigue, increased
developer productivity, and so on.
So let's look at model context protocol,
which lies at the heart of this whole data
pipeline for the AI enhanced telemetry.
So MCP is an is I think we all have.
Might have worked with it or
heard about it, but MCP is an open
standard that allows developer to
create a secure two-way connection
between data sources and AI tools.
So if we look at the image here, MCP,
there is an MCP server that connects
with different large language models
like Anthropics Cloud, Opus Open, ai,
OSS and then there are different tools
or services that get integrated and.
There are three key components here.
So one is the contextual ETL for ai.
So for any AI model, I think the
most important part is like how do
we provide them the right context and
data so it standardizes the context.
Extraction for multiple data resources
basically defines a schema of what
our data should look like across
different services and resources.
A structured query interface, so that.
The AI can interpret, the AI models
can interpret and trans get transparent
access to these enriched data layers.
The semantic data enrichment embeds
meaningful context directly into the
telemetry signal that we have received for
whether it be metrics, logs, or traces.
So let's deep dive into
the proposed architecture.
This essentially can be called
as a three layer architecture.
Here I have shown a payments
processing microservice.
It could be any microservice or also a
monolith, but essentially it's just here.
It's here for more
easiness of understanding.
So we have an open telemetry exporter
that emits raw metrics, logs, and traces.
Then it goes into the service that does
the hotel instrumentation and the context
enrichment, which is the second box.
And then the enrich telemetry is stored
into, say, a telemetry storage like
influx TB or Prometheus or something.
Then there is an MCP server
and an MCB query layer.
The MCP server acts as an interface
between the influx tvb and the actual AI
analysis engine, which is essentially the.
Large language models, fine tune
for specific observability, and
then there are dashboards on top
of that based on, again, APIs.
I think today Grafana we'll see for
in the coming slides that Grafana
and other have good integration
with any of the large language
models and the API interface layers.
So the goal here, and the key insight here
is to shift observability from a reactive
problem solving to proactive insights.
Let's do an implementation deep type
without further a so the layer one as
we spoke about is context enrichment.
So I have here shown a code example
where again, this has been simplifying
and obfuscated for understanding.
So for example, at step one
we generate the correlation
IDs for context propagation.
So here we look at the process
checkout for a payment.
Gateway, like PayPal or Stripe.
And then we generate here the order ID and
the request id, and then we initialize a
context dictionary to enrich the spans.
Another interesting thing here is that I
am going to give you a walkthrough on how.
Traces for distributed tracing are being
enriched, and how we have used this to
reduce MTTR and con and basically adopt
this and lean into this AI enriched
data pipeline for observability.
So the key idea here is that the ev
every telemetry signals contains the same
core contextual data, which we can see
here, and it can depend, vary from you.
Case case by case.
So user id order, id request id,
card item count, payment method,
service name, and the service version.
So tomorrow if something breaks
or some there, we see some high
latency in the fulfillment service.
Like after or after the payment is
done, there is a fulfillment service.
Then there's a W warehouse
service that actually dispatches.
So we know where actually the
delay is happening or where
the incident has happened.
Now let's see a very simple
example of context enrichment.
So this is a simple, very simple
debugging scenario and we, I've done
a comparative analysis on how traces
how we see error messages without
trace context and vic trace context.
So without trace context, we see something
like payment failed and we get some
error, and then the and it fires an
alert, and then the on-call engineer or
the subject matter experts goes into and
starts looking into logs for that event.
And it takes a lot of time.
It requires background knowledge.
However, in the enriched case, we see
that okay, there is an error at the same
time, but we see that the request IDs,
their order IDs, their user ID service.
So even in the first layer as
different dimensions, we see that
these traces have been enriched.
So what?
What it does immediately is that
instant correlation via the request id.
We can backtrack this request ID
and figure out where we went wrong.
Service identification, the
user assessment, and automatic
trace assembly, essentially.
So we can see here how context enrichment
helps with debugging scenarios with a
very simple example, and this is very
simple and you can adopt it and make it
more versatile for different use cases.
Layer two is the MCP server, which
is the structured query interface,
which acts like an interface between
the, as I said in the diagram,
the influx TB or the telemetry
storage database and the AI models.
So here we do three things essentially
and step by step, we index we index
the telemetry spans based off our
efficient lookups via context field.
We do filtering, based on precise
data segregation so that like we
apply different time-based filters.
There could be different other
filters based on different dimensions.
Like for example, we know that during
Black Friday there are some deals
that are happening on amazon.com.
So we might know that, okay, these
are Black Friday lightning deals and
we want to track what's if something
goes wrong, how do we solve it?
So there is filter filtering.
And then at the last step
there is aggregation.
So this is very simple the
results for login results.
If log context and this and request
ID is equal to the given request id.
We do a bunch of things and then
we apply a time-based filter.
Then this is the heart of the
whole architecture here is
the AI driven analysis engine.
So it defines the analysis
time window in step one.
Basically when we want to analyze,
and this is exposed via an API on
the Grafana dashboard or wherever
you are viewing your telemetry.
Like it could be for tracers, it could be
Zipkin or Yeager, but again, this is just
the internal heart of what the API does.
So we define an analysis
window which the user provides.
We extract the relevant telemetry based
on the context current one context.
So we extract here metric names by values.
We extract here traces and
whatnot, and logs as well.
And then we calculate statistical pro
properties to capture anomalies and AI
recommendations, which is this part,
which is essentially we are using Z-score
and checking the standard deviation.
To calculate and see if there is any
anomaly in the current traces and
the telemetry that we are seeing.
So here, context enables
automatic cross signal analysis
without manual intervention.
So the from, so for from the user
perspective, it would just be that you
enter the timestamp just like you do
for looking into traces or logs and we,
and basically the whole model and this
whole infrastructure that is there,
pipeline is there, would give you.
Insights that, okay, this is what
has happened in the past seven days.
Rani, right now we are seeing it as
an anomaly or not and what, or whether
it's the right whether it's right
and everything looks good essentially
from latency wise or error wise.
So what is the impact
that we have observed?
So a real world impact from our,
we've seen like the time that has
been reduced from ours, two minutes.
So before adopting this and leaning
into this pipeline, we saw that
approximately 45 minutes times were
spent in average and resolution.
We had to do manual law correlation,
multiple context switches between tools,
tribal knowledge required for developers,
and a lot of high cognitive load.
However, after this, we've seen
approximately average our MTTR
being reduced to eight minutes.
Automatic and because, and it's
been reduced because of automatic
correlation, a single pane of glass
unified view in observability.
There is a silver bullet term called
single pane of glass view or unified
observability, and this allows
us to do unified observability.
We also get context of insights and
AI suggested and enhanced rc, so
you just get a boilerplate RC and
you can work on top of that based
on the AI model's understanding of
your context and how well you have.
Propagated your context and
given basically populated
the enrichment dictionary.
So we saw how we have seen 82% reduction
in the MTTR 65% reduction in alert
fatigue and 3.2 x faster duction.
Again, this has been right
now in more of a data phase
within for the implementation.
But again, we see massive
potential here for.
Adopting it.
And recently a lot of companies like open
source companies like Elastic Search,
have been using Elastic Stream that allows
the same thing to happen, like for logs.
They can do context propagation and
context enrichment in the L Clear.
But it is again, a vendor
specific, however, by this
way, which is open source.
You can be vendor agnostic and
do a lot of enrichment and AI
driven analysis on your end.
And of course, use Elasticsearch
for specific problem solving
because again, that's also paper.
API pay pay as you go.
So the cost also adds
up given observability.
Anyways, a very costly business.
So I think the question that was raised
was, this seems like a lot of overhead.
I think that would come through your mind
as well, but it came to our mind as well
when we were doing the decision making.
Is the complexity worth the
effort that we are spending?
So what's, what are, so
let's compare to scenarios.
What are the hidden costs
that you're already paying?
So usually we, like, whenever we do
capacity planning, we do put like around
20% of an engineer's time on, on-call
workload or like engineering efficiencies,
so which is around 15 to 20 hours per
week, 60 to 70% of alerts are unactionable
or get auto resolved context switching.
So there is a massive amount of
study done here that 23 minutes, it
takes 23 minutes to refocus after
an interruption, whether it be just
be chatting with a colleague or.
Something else for you to get in the zone.
And we all have been heard
by this multiple times.
I have been over my span
of career of 10 years.
I've been heard by it multiple times.
And then tribal knowledge, like
critical dependencies on certain
individuals, and you become the
bottleneck in the whole process.
However, if we invest in this, so the,
if this is again, a one time setup and
it could just be, iterative increments.
You don't have to boil the ocean at once.
You can just implement one service and
focus on that, which is your most critical
service, and then later evolve your
learning from it and implement it across.
So initially you might have to spend
two to three weeks, I would say
even four weeks if starting out new.
Incremental adoption.
Start with critical services, permanent
against, replicate to every service.
Once you implement it, it's easily
replica, replicable to any other service.
And the break even time is around six to
eight weeks because given like everybody's
spending 15 to 20 hours, that time would
drastically reduced to five, four to
five hours, right around 80% reduction.
So in six to eight weeks or maybe.
10 weeks you get your ROI or the
time spent in resource allocation
and engineer time spent in
designing this whole infrastructure.
So the key insight here is
that the complexity you add
at generation time eliminates.
Exponentially more
complexity at analysis time.
So yeah, you are doing laying up
the foundation, but later on when
the incidents really happen the
complexity and the time spent and
alert fatigue gets reduced drastically.
So what are the key takeaways?
So we now get into what have been
the key takeaways for us when we have
implemented it and others have adopted it.
So first insight is that
start with context enrichment.
Again, as I said previously,
big begin small and think big.
Don't implement the full three
layer architecture at once.
Just start by enriching
one critical service.
So minimum viable context,
like essentially says,
what are your crucial tags?
It could just be for cost tracking
that you are track tracking a team's
id, for example, an owner, team
owner tag, or like a service id,
and you know that this service.
Really heavy load.
So just start with the minimum
viable context and also the
minimum viable implementation.
So for that, we do we add dictionary
context dictionary to your logging
setup, propagate context through
service calls, include context in oal
spans, validate context appears in all
signals, and expand to other server.
So the first insight is that for
one, your week one goal is that pick
one high traffic service and add
basic context enrichment on that.
You don't even have to add the, the
analysis engine layer, the AI layer.
The second insight is that
it's very essential for us to.
Make sure that our data is variable and
it can, we can draw insights from that.
So make the data AI ready even without
the full implementation, create
structured APIs over all of a telemetry.
The thing that we saw previously,
based on request ID, is based
on timestamp filtering create
the APIs and integrated with.
Dashboards, wherever you view your
telemetry, whether it be Grafana,
zip gain, Kibana, anything.
So the what are the benefits?
So programmatic access, consistent
interfaces and AI friendly formats.
And here I've provided some simple
rest API patterns for the payment
service, which we used as an.
So the quick, the second insight
is, and the quick win from here is
that wrap existing observability
tools with simple query APIs as we
spoke about, so that filtering and
querying that data becomes easier.
So insight three, I think this is a
very, very well known fact and software
engineering and also product development
is that we always iterate with feedback
from either customers or from within.
So from within we say
like operational feedback.
So context is a living system and
because context changes is every
day the best schema emerges from
real world incident patterns.
So I would say like what we have
basically lean into is that we measure.
Refine and expand.
And what I mean by that is that we
track which context field engineers
actually use during incidents.
And if those fields are missing, we add
those and remove the unused fields so
that we are not adding essentially like
raw data, which is not very actionable.
Fraud, fraud, even the AI models.
And then expand that learning to
different services incrementally.
So the anti-patent to avoid here
is that don't try to design the
perfect contact schema upfront.
Let on-call incident and operational
load guide really guide you into
designing the contact schema.
What's next?
So let's see, like what are we planning
for the future and then what are
the enhancements that we want to do?
So industry adoption and scalability.
Here we talk about like the different
phases in which like somebody wants
to implement this, how would they
implement it and how have we thought
about implementing it and also
getting returns from our investment.
So firstly, the solution scales
from startups to enterprises.
There is no one size fits all but
essentially here, like anybody
who uses this solution can.
More fit to their specific needs.
So it's ideal for organizations
with microservice architectures,
cloud native deployments, systems
at scale, having a very cluttered
non-uniform observability stack, alert
fatigue problems and long mean time
to detect and resolve essentially.
So phase one, as I said, is like context
enrichment, which is the key part Then.
Query layer, which is phase two, the basic
APIs that you have, and then AI analysis,
anomaly direction layer basically, which
and then scale for scale across services,
and then do a full MCP implementation.
So till here, I think a lot of folks like
till phase four, a lot of folks and we
all have understanding of how things work
and this we can move fast even before
into getting, before getting into the
complexity of the full MCP implementation.
So what's the future of observability?
And what we are seeing today is that
observability is shifting massively from,
error prone like fatigued, reactive to
a more optimized, proactive approach.
So traditional observability, we wait
for alerts to happen, hunt root for
root causes, and do manual correlations.
We do reactive firefighting and.
Fatigued on-call engineers, like
on-call becomes usually a nightmare.
However, in this new paradigm where we
have AI powered observability which is
full of context enriched context, so we
predict issues before impact, even if we
could solve like around 20% of the issues
and that is happening again and again,
and we can predict them, it becomes very
easy for us for engineers to scale it.
If the load is predicted
to increase, like you can.
Hyperactively scale it.
You can also automate it, if you
have an MCP server, like it can scale
on your behalf but again, it can
be manual or it can be automated.
So AI suggested root causes.
So if you get a boilerplate of the
root cause, you at least get what
is the hypothesis and deep dive into
that For creating the public, facing
RCS usually automatic correlation.
Of course proactive optimization.
You get and the on-call engineers are.
Empower and they can focus on
better things rather than solving
the same problem repetitively.
So from what we've see, from what we
are seeing is that observability problem
is fundamentally a data problem, and it
should be solved at the data layer, not at
the insights layer or the inference layer.
So we should try to solve
that at the data layer itself.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Hope, hope you find this
presentation insightful.
Feel free to follow me
on LinkedIn and Twitter.
And these are my socials.
I have just.
Put the sample code and references,
and I've made it open source on
my GitHub, so feel free to start
it or use it and raise issues.
If you want to reach out to
me there, here's my email.
But yeah, it was really glad presenting
this in front of you folks and I hope.
You all have a great DevOps 2026,
and I thank Con 42 and Mark for the
opportunity to present, and I hope
you guys liked it, so signing off.
Thank you everyone.
I.