Speaker 47: Hello everyone.
Welcome to Zero Trust Security in DevOps.
Automating test verification
across 5G Pipeline.
I'm VI Marvin Genti.
And today we'll explore how zero
trust transforms security in
fast moving 5G DevOps environment
with 5G connections
exceeding projections and.
Cybersecurity threats evolving very
rapidly, including AA driven attacks.
Traditional perimeter
security is obsolete.
Zero trust is now the baseline with
over 60% of organizations adopting
it and plans for 81% by year end.
According to recent surveys, this approach
enables secure high velocity deployments
without compromising project protection.
Now I will cover the security imperative,
the core paradox, why legacy models fail,
zero trust fundamentals, embedding in
pipelines, the four layer architecture,
CICD implementation, 5G integration
challenges, and finally, real world
insights and future directions.
Let's begin.
In the world where we live in security
is no more a check, just a checkbox.
It's enabler of innovation
in a high connected world.
The rapid adoption of DevOps in 5G has
transformed security industry, software
delivery, but it introduces massive risks.
Organizations now deploy
code multiple times a day.
Compressing security reviews.
Key issues are these
development velocity pressures.
Team expands, attack
surfaces with each push.
Hence, continuous verification
is very essential.
Perimeter security assumes threats
stay outside, but in cloud native
architecture, that boundary has dissolved.
Recent study highlights that 70% of 5G
networks still face misconfiguration
vulnerabilities often from
unverified access in dynamic steps.
5G distributed nature with edge
computing, network slicing and
massive iot demands a paradigm shift.
No more relying on perimeter.
DevOps team faced A paradox rapid
cycles conflict with thorough
validation with expanded attack surface.
This is even intensified in five G's
complex and foster infrastructure
where infrastructure completely
multiplies exponentially.
Why traditional models fail?
Because legacy assumptions break down
traditional perimeter based fails.
As it assumes threats are coming from
outside, but this perimeter trust becomes
invalid in multi-cloud 5G for instance,
Ericson notes that zero trust matches 5G.
By eliminating implicit trust,
reducing lateral movement by
up to 80% in enterprise setups.
Static rule-based access control
can't adapt to constantly
changing infrastructure.
One time authentication leaves
unverified windows and lateral
movement goes undetected.
Once inside a private 5G penetration test
case study revealed that without zero
trust, industrial networks were vulnerable
to insider threats in under 30 minutes.
Zero Trust is a security model
built on simple but powerful idea.
Never trust, always verify Key
principles of zero Trust are every
user, device, and service must
be continuously authenticated,
authorized, continuously validated.
It assumes attackers are
inside the system already.
So you design your system
to limit blast radius.
Detect anonymous quickly,
and respond instantly.
This philosophy designs systems to
contain compromises immediately as per
NIST and CISA guidelines of 5G clouds.
Zero Trust reduces breach impact
by focusing on data and apps.
Integrate zero trust into CI CD pipelines
by automating verification at every stage.
No manual bottlenecks.
That means at code level
that is sign every commit.
Run static analysis, scan
dependencies, and at container level
image scanning, verify provenance.
Apply runtime policy and at
the infrastructure level,
validate infrastructure as
a code, detect configuration
drift, and enforce immutability.
And finally, at the network
level service mesh with mutual
TLS enforce MIS segmentation.
The key is automation manual review
won't work anymore at this scale.
We need automated consistent checks
that execute at mission speed.
Propose this four layer approach,
which addresses challenges of securing
DevOps workflows in 5G environments,
the access layer, transport layer,
policy intelligence layer, and
control, and orchestration layer.
The access layer start with
continuous identity verifications
with multi-factor authentication.
Mutual TLS container attestation.
Run time monitoring, behavioral
analysis, detect anomalies.
Recent a advances a integrates device.
Posture for decision, as
in Palo Alto Networks.
Nvidia.
A factory integration for
zero Trust in edge ai.
The next layer is transport and
segmentation layer prevents lateral
movement via 5G slicing policies,
zero trust gateways, ai analyze
traffic, auto blocks, anomalies.
Best of practice, microsegmentation,
isolates, workloads.
The next layer is policy
and inte intelligence layer.
AI driven decisions making uses
AI baselines and alarm detection,
dynamic policies, auto containment.
It uses adaptive security
ecosystem to continuously learn
normal behavioral patterns.
For users, services and infrastructure,
any deviation from these baselines
will be detected as potential threats.
Once threats are detected, it adapts
policies in real time, a powered zero
trust for 5G slices, managers, dynamic
security without performance hit the loss
layer, control and orchestration layer.
This layer governs centralized
policy with distributed environment.
Central government is like a centralized
zero trust controller, which is AI
powered identity and access management
with policy as a code immutable
audits for every run by providing a
feedback loop so that a risk insights
directly update the security posture.
This overall four layer approach ensures
distributed enforcement for resilience.
You can't trust what you can't see.
This layer gives you total visibility,
zero trust implementation in CICD
workflows, embedded every stage.
Signed commits, secret
scanning, container analysis.
A SC validation, air and
AMI detection, practical.
Remove static credentials and
automate checks for every deployment.
Create an immutable chain of custody.
Each step creates cryptographic attention.
Attention.
Forming a trusted chain from
developer to production.
Zero trust integration with 5G networks.
Leverage 5G slicing for pipeline
isolation, edge intelligence for
low latency detection, continuous
device authentication and isolation.
C. SG recommends zero trust
for CSPs to master 5G.
Security
implementation challenges and limitations.
Some of the challenges are
operational complexity, ai attack
surfaces, performance, overhead
skills, gap and cultural shift.
Address these with the
training and phase adoption.
It's not just about the tools, it's
about mindset, skillset, and discip.
To wrap up, zero.
Trust is no longer an optional.
It's a foundational for 5G
and cloud-native DevOps.
It enables fast, safe deployments.
It minimizes blast radius.
It accelerate accelerates
automated response.
The future is self-healing systems.
Quantum safe, crypto verified
policy correctness zero.
Trust is not in a destination.
It's a mindset, a continuous
process, and it's your best defense.
With this conclusion, I'll end my session.
Please reach out to me if
you have any questions.
I can be reached out via LinkedIn.
Or email.
Thank you so much for joining with me.
Thank you.