Hello everyone.
How's it going today?
This is Con 42 and my name
is Muhammad Ahsan Ayaz.
I'm a Google developer expert
in Angular and a software
architect working at Scania.
I'm also an author of two
worldwide published books,
namely The Angular Cookbook, and
you can find me on my socials.
Now today I'm going to actually
talk about something special,
something that's close to my heart.
The topic is from Patchwork to Picasso,
managing or refactoring 150 plus
web projects and what we went wrong.
You're gonna hear some stories.
You're gonna also learn
quite a lot of things.
So if you want to follow on my socials,
you can see them at the bottom.
And I want you to take just a second
to take this picture from your camera.
This allows you to give feedback
directly to me about the talk
and anything that I can improve.
So thank you in advance.
Now, I want to ask you to UI question.
A very existential question,
if I may dare to say that.
What if you had cats, about 150 of
them, and you tried to walk them at
the same time around your street?
What would happen?
Can you imagine what that would feel like?
And this picture actually is a
depiction of what it could feel like.
And that is exactly how I felt when
I was working on my second edition
of the angular cookbook, because
I had more than 150 projects.
to work with.
And that's what we are going to talk
about in the next about half an hour.
Who am I?
I already introduced myself a bit.
I'm an author of two
worldwide published books.
I'm also working as a software architect
at Scania and I'm a GDE in Angular.
I'm also maintainer of a lot of
open source projects as well.
But one of the most famous ones is NGX
device detector, which is being used
by more than 5, 000 projects on GitHub.
I'm also someone who's recognized in
the developers community as an educator.
And this is one of the awards
that I got recently at JS Pullin.
And I've also been featured by Google
when I was working with them on
this AI campaign for Google Gemini.
Let me take you back to 2019.
That's when Pact, which is one of
the publishers out there for books,
reached out to me and they wanted
me to work on a video course.
And that was on Ionic.
So I hope A few of you know what Ionic is.
And at first I was really happy.
I was like, okay, this is super
cool because I was fascinated by
all these, you know, thought leaders
and course creators out there.
And I wanted to do that myself as well.
But there were some challenges.
I used to live in Pakistan back then
with my family and Even though it is
a preferred way of living there, it
comes with some challenges when you're
living with your family, which means
that each couple has one room to it.
When I used to record, it was usually
at night when everyone was sleeping and
that actually came with some challenges.
So the first challenge was I was newly
married and I had very less furniture
in my room, which means that whenever
I was trying to record something and
even if there was a slight echo, that
would be recorded in the microphone and
I would have to eventually re record it.
So even the slightest sound of my
wife sort of moving on the bed would
just make me angry and I was like,
ah, can you please not breathe?
And then I would basically go out
in the living room and I would
try to record there, but that
also came with some challenges.
For example, or so I would hear all
these sounds and that would make me.
Yeah, as you can imagine.
Fortunately, I moved to Sweden
and you can see how happy I was.
But once I published the video course,
I thought I would earn a lot of money
and I started dreaming about it.
But that was exactly the same time
when React Native came out and
that basically kicked Ionic away.
So the course actually did
not perform really well.
Then in 2020, PAC reached out
to me again and they were like,
can you write a book for us?
And I was like, okay, I can do that.
So long story short, I took over
10 months and wrote this Angular
cookbook with over 80 plus projects
and we sold over 2000 copies of this.
So this was really a success.
After that in late 2022, PAG reached
out again and they were like, can you
work on the second edition of the book?
And I was like, okay.
We can do that.
And at first I thought it would be super
easy because I just had to migrate or
update what has happened in Angular.
And this is just a second edition, right?
But when I looked at the code base, I
knew I was in trouble because there were
more than 150 projects all staring at me
and they were waiting to be updated from
Angular version 12 to Angular version 16.
Now you may ask why, and
that is because Angular has a
predictable release frequency.
So every six months there is a
major release and there are about
one to three minor patches as
well during the six months time.
So for me, updating 150 projects
basically seemed like this.
I knew it was going to
be super, super slow.
So what did I do then?
I basically found out this really
cool tool called NX, which is the new
cool way of managing monorepositories
for your particular projects,
especially if you have a lot of
applications and or libraries.
So looking at that, I decided to have one
monorepository with two NX workspaces.
So I had one GitHub repo that had two
NX workspaces in that one for start
and one for final because my book is
basically in the form of a cookbook.
So you have a Problem statement,
you follow the recipe and then
you have the solution for it.
This is how the architecture looked like.
So if you look at here, we have
the GitHub repository that has
two folders, start and final.
And then in both of them, we have
these chapter folders and inside we
have a folder for each particular
project or what we call a recipe.
Let me ask you a question.
Do you like ui ux or do you love ui ux?
I think a few of you say yes.
Then how many of you
really advocate for ui ux?
That means you go to designers, talk about
that, or your product managers, et cetera.
And then I want to ask you, how
many of you actually advocate
for a great developer experience?
Because what I wanted for
my audience or my readers.
was a great developer experience,
but not just for them, but for
also myself as well, because I was
about to migrate 150 plus projects.
So with the current NX structure,
this is what I would get.
I would get a GitHub repository with these
folders and I had to proceed with this.
Now, by default, when I was
designing this, any recipe
would have to work this way.
The reader would have to
first go and do CD start.
Then they would have to run NX.
And then this whole name.
Now, remember, whenever we are structuring
our folders or our applications in
Angular or in NX, whenever we try to
give them a hierarchy of folder, that
becomes the name of the project itself.
So if I wanted something like CC
on changes, inside the chapter
one folder, then the name of that
project becomes this, which is huge.
And I think that's not
really easy to remember.
So for running a recipe in the start
folder, they would have to run this.
Similarly, they could also run
other recipes like this as well.
Now, as you know, as developers, we
want to be dry, not exactly this,
but I think you'll get my point.
But also remember, we
need a really good DX.
I'm going to actually come back to this
term again, which is developer experience.
So my first goal was how do
I make it so that the name of
the project is not as long.
So the first goal was actually to run
this npm run serve and this command,
which means that I don't want to cd.
into the start or the final folder.
I could just run either this or
run the same command, but with
additional parameter called
final from the project's root.
So nobody has to cd into it.
And this was pretty simple.
But the second goal was to avoid
even having the chapter name
when I'm running this command.
And you may ask why that's
because each recipe is unique.
So in my entire code repository
in the start folder, there
is no duplicate recipe.
Similarly in the final folder,
All the recipes are unique.
So I should be able to just use the recipe
name instead of specifying the chapter.
Now, the first goal was really simple.
As I mentioned, I just moved to the CD
step and the command into a script file.
And I moved that script or use
that script in my packages.
And with this change, I could actually
run this command pretty easily.
So I could run this for the start
folder and this one for the final
folder, just by using npm run surf.
Now I had to focus on the second task,
which was how do I remove this change?
chapter name from running the command and
can just use the recipe name in general.
Now I want to emphasize that
at this point, I'm actually
migrating these projects.
So I'm actually creating those projects
one by one, and I'm migrating them
from separate 150 plus projects to
two monorepositories start and final.
Now, when I was doing
that, I had three options.
One, when I'm actually creating a project,
I could exclude the chapter name from it.
before the project is created.
The second option was I create the project
and then rename after it has been created.
So just going into the files automatically
somehow, and then renaming it, and
the third option was just give up and
start writing a PHP book, maybe that's
easier, but I did not go for this.
I choose the second approach, which means
creating the project and then renaming it.
Why?
I actually don't know.
At that particular time, I
had no idea what I was doing
and that's perfectly fine.
You get into these issues as
developers always when you don't
know something and you know that.
later on.
Now, coming back to the problem at hand,
I wanted to use this particular command
npm run serve and just the recipe name.
So keep that in mind.
So for this particular situation,
I created my own plugin using
the narwhal NX plugin package.
It's quite possible that the package
name has changed now since everything
moved to at NX now, but I used NX's
plugin package to create my own plugin.
Again, the question is why?
Because I wanted to do.
this in the steps.
So let's have a look at how I was
creating the application for my book.
Back then I was actually
trying to do this.
I would actually go to a start folder
and I would create a new project.
Since I'm migrating them one by one, I
would actually go and do NPM NX generate,
create an Angular application for me,
and then I would give that the path.
So the chapter name or the chapter
folder, and then the recipe folder,
just like this, this basically
generates with the app name.
this one.
And as we discussed, that
is too much to remember.
The chapter name and the
recipe name, not super easy.
Now, the plugin I created
actually had two counterparts.
One is the NX generators and
the second is the NX executors.
And that is what I'm trying to focus
on this talk to actually tell you.
So, the first part, that is the generator,
actually creates the application.
So instead of me going into the folder
and running the command, it actually uses
a generator to generate the application.
And during the generation process, it
adds the executor into the project JSON.
So take it like two steps.
So in the first step, we create the app.
In the second step, we rename the project.
That's the idea.
So for that, the code
looks something like this.
When I generate my project, there's
a function that I call and that
essentially looks like this.
It takes the package JSON of the
project and then adds this rename
executor inside that from my plugin.
Then it basically becomes
something like this.
So let's say the recipe was This
NG on changes, then I actually
have these parameters like chapter
number and then the app name.
Since the actual name that we are
targeting right now contains both the
chapter number or the chapter folder
and the recipe name, I can actually use
this to use some regex to rename easily.
Now, the second step.
is to run the executor.
So first step, we created the
generator that creates the application.
Second step, the executor actually
goes into the project, JSON, and
then it fetches out this information.
What is the chapter number?
And what is the recipe name?
When it looks at that particular
situation, it actually then renames
this right here in this function.
So we're not going to go too deep
into this, but the idea is actually to
rename using the executor's information.
So if I Summarize this.
This is my whole process.
I had to just run this command to create
a new project, which is super easy for me.
I just run npm run create.
I give the number of the chapter.
I give the recipes name and the
title I want to show in the header.
So that means that runs
a couple of things.
First, it starts with a batch script.
It runs the generator, which
generates the application.
Then it runs the executor that
goes and renames the application.
That's easy peasy.
So.
This is what happens when we run
npm run create, this runs the
packages in the script, which
in turn runs the bash script.
This is the chapter number.
As I mentioned, this is the app name, and
this is the title to show in the header.
So this is pretty simplified
version of what happens.
So it takes out the app name, the app
title, and all of these things as the
argument or the positional arguments.
And then it runs all of this.
So here you can see that it runs the
rename executor before that it runs the
generation of the application for me.
Awesome.
Which means that if I was able.
To run this correctly, all I had to do
was run this NPM run serve CC engine on
changes because the name already has been
changed and the app has been renamed now.
Great.
Now, do you remember what our goal was?
It was actually a great
developer experience.
And this was the time when I
actually felt like I was over
the moon because I actually
conquered one of my biggest fears.
And that was working with Angular
schematics, which is what we use.
to work with, NX generators and executors
because it scripts everything and then
does it automatically on the file system.
As I felt enlightened, actually
a new problem knocked my
door and that was not great.
Have you heard this
term called consistency?
Well, I actually wanted my entire project
to be consistent in terms of UI UX and
I wanted the same structure and user
experience for all of my applications.
So the idea was to have the same header
across all the projects, which means.
It could look something like this.
So we would have the header at the top.
So if we dissect it, it's the header
having the title of the application,
the Angular logo and information burden.
And then this content is the
dynamic content, which is
different for every application.
Now, I thought I could do the
following using my generator.
So my generator is already creating new
applications, which means that if I went
inside my generator and I look at the
template, so one of them was index HTML.
And the other one was app component HTML.
So for all the things related to the
consistent fonts across all applications
and the icons, which is like material
icons, which I can basically load from the
CDN, I could actually work on index HTML.
And for the applications architecture, I
could actually use the app component HTML.
To have the header and then
the placeholder for dynamic
content of the applications.
So this is what I did.
I actually modified the index HTML to
include material icons, the font that
I basically use, which is Nonito and
everything that I needed on the index HTML
level, then in the app component HTML,
I actually had the toolbar and then this
main element, which would have the dynamic
content different for every application.
And here you can see that
we do have the info button.
We also have the title here.
And we also have the
Angular logo as an SVG.
Now we have discussed only the
HTML part or the templates.
But what about the biggest fear
of web developers, which is CSS?
How do I ensure that the styles
across the applications are consistent
and they're easy to update as well?
That's actually when I created my own
NX library within the NX workspace.
So I created a library named NGCB UI.
And this is actually within my plugins
package repository or monorepository.
So now I have this global SCSS,
which contains all of my styles.
I package it so I can use that.
in my other workspaces
like start and final.
And I also ensure that this is included.
So that means that now when I'm creating
a new application, not only I'm creating
an app with this consistent, structure
with HTML for index HTML and app component
HTML, but I'm also including this global
SCSS sneakily into both those projects.
And the beauty of this is that I'm not
doing this for one 50 plus projects.
I only have to do this for two projects.
two workspaces.
The start workspace and
the final workspace.
I don't have to do it for every project
because I only have two NX workspaces.
This is the beauty of automation so far.
So when we looked at the
result, It was beautiful.
We had a header, we had the logo right
here, we had the info button, and this
was consistent for all of my applications.
Having this dynamic container here, which
can have different content, of course.
And just as I thought everything
was sunshine and butterflies,
something big happened.
Something crazy.
Can you guess?
I'm going to give you
some seconds to think.
All right, maybe you guessed it.
Maybe you didn't.
Angular actually changed their
logo and they went from a
red logo to this cool logo.
And while this is so pleasing
to the eye, this is so modern,
I actually really liked it.
But this caused And that was, I was
left with 150 plus Angular projects
still now, even with NX workspaces with
hard coded SVGs that I had in my, App
component html and that was not super
cool So if you remember we had this app
component html which had a toolbar the
dynamic content But this hard coded image
now, I have 150 projects having this in
their code base And that was not good.
First of all I compose
myself like a good developer.
I thought of analyzing what's
happening right now and
started thinking of a solution.
So the first thing that came to
my mind was to go from this, which
is the current state of the app
component HTML to something like this.
Instead of having a hard coded logo, I
could create a component in my NX library
and I could use the same component
throughout all of my application.
And this file right now, which is app
component HTML is part of the So if
you think that sounds good and this
could solve the issue, You're wrong.
And that is because we are talking
about the code of a generator.
The generator only works when we
are creating the applications.
I already have my 150 plus projects
already, which have that code.
So having changed the generator's
code or the template doesn't
really work right now.
I need something else.
Because I have 150 projects,
my 150 plus cats having the old
logo, which nobody likes anymore.
So I started thinking about the
solution and I had some questions.
My main questions were, how do geniuses
at Angular and NX solve such issues of
a workspace wide, Migration or change.
How can I have a graceful fallback if
I'm trying to do this automatically
across my GitHub repository, how do
I know if something breaks and, you
know, revert my changes and not, you
know, come in middle of a situation,
which is half baked, so to say.
And then how do I ensure that
I don't have to think about the
same problem again in the future?
So first I created this header
component inside my library is still,
because still it's a good idea.
Do not have the hard
coded, header everywhere.
And we could have this from a library.
So if we needed to change anything
in the header, we could just
update the library and then all
the projects start using that.
So that's what I did first.
Secondly, I use something
called NX migrations.
And trust me, this is really, really cool.
Beauty of migration is that it
allows us to run generators after
the applications have been created.
And this can run to the whole workspace.
So to say, the beauty of this is that
I can also specify which version of my
plugin that I'm using right now in a start
and final will trigger this migration.
So I can also, versionize it.
So to say, and that is.
Really, really nice.
So the goal for my migration was to
have this replace app toolbar run
in both the start and final folder.
So that means two steps.
And when I do these two steps,
I should have migrated my whole
code base, all the projects.
And this is what the migration looks like.
So if I show you the code base, it
basically goes inside my application
and looks at all the projects.
Now, some of the Angular projects are
module based, some are standalone.
So essentially it goes, it finds
the header or the title, it
extracts it, and then it replaces
it right here with the new toolbar.
And if you look at the new toolbar,
it is essentially this, the ngcbui
header, just like we discussed before.
And once that does it, it also makes sure
that this particular component is also
imported in the TypeScript file as well.
Because you need that.
For the standalone components.
And if you're using a module based
application, then you need to import
this or declare this in the ng
module of your application as well.
So that was pretty nice.
And if we actually look at what happened
after I ran these migration, let me
show you, this is the commit that
actually was done after the migration.
So this is replacing all the headers.
in the start folder.
And if I close the migration
files, I also want to show you
what happened in each project.
So here you can see that this whole
toolbar was replaced by API UI header.
Then in the TypeScript file, we
go and import this automatically
and add that to the imports.
And this is the same for all the recipes.
So this toolbar had the same
result, just like this, this one.
And this one, and this one, you'll see the
repeating sort of pattern for all of this.
So this basically ran across all of
my projects within the start folder.
And then I did the same for
the final folder as well.
And once I ran the migration on
both the folders, things were
like muska as we say in Pakistan,
which means like buttery smooth.
And I want to show you
the final result now.
So if I.
show you the demo.
This is what it looks like.
You can see that all the applications
have a header right now, have this
logo, and then this content is dynamic.
So I can show you this really
nice example in which I have, for
example, folders moving right here.
And this example actually shows
how to lazily load different
components, even on a single page.
So here you can see that a lot of
these projects or a lot of these
components are lazily being loaded.
So all of my recipes in my
Angular cookbook, right now
have the same consistent layout
across all of the projects.
And when I was actually able to
achieve all of that, I felt like
a self proclaimed NX expert.
So if I summarize, what we have talked
about is cats are possum, managing 150
plus projects is completely possible
and no solution is perfect because
I started with something, I failed,
I found out the issue with that,
and then I re evaluated and improved
the solution and we as developers.
should be easy or should be,
you know, not hesitant to do so.
And it's also never too
late to learn something new.
As soon as the opportunity presents
itself, I think we should just grab it.
Because when I started with migration,
I did not know about Angular schematics
or all of these things like NX
plugins, generators, executors.
But by the end of all of this, I
actually know a lot that I can share now.
So that's pretty much it.
I would highly encourage if you can
provide me the feedback with that.
QR code that you can see here.
And also, if you want to take your skills
to the next level, and if you just want
to explore all these projects, cool
projects that I've built with the angular
cookbook, check out the angular cookbook,
second edition, or the latest edition,
whatever is out there at the ng cookbook.
com.
And with that said, I want to thank con
42 for having me this time as always.
Happy coding y'all.
I'm going to see you next time.