Speaker 10: Hello everyone.
I am Gober working for Amazon, and
today's topic is from demo to deployment
building, evaluating and observing
multimodal conversational agents.
And today I want to talk about
something many of us have seen, but
far fewer have successfully deployed.
We all have seen impressive
multimodal demos, right?
It could be voice, it could be
vision, it could be touch all working
beautifully in a controlled environment.
But turning those demos into production
study systems that are relatable,
observable, and cost effective
is a very different challenge.
Let's take a real example of
how we interact with the voice
enabled TV in our living room.
Let's like like asking, it's find a
comedy movie for family night and turn
this into a production system that
understand voice onscreen context,
personalization signals and realtime
content availability behind the simple
interaction with your multimodal
orchestration, you need to interact with.
Speech ui ML models and cloud
services, along with continuous
evaluation and deep observability to
ensure you are getting the accuracy,
latency, and reliability at scale.
This is a simple example of how your
multi conversational agents work in the
background to enlight and delight the
customer experience in your living room.
Today I walked you through how multimodal
conversational agents actually move
from demo to deployment and what
it tends to break along the way.
Let's go to the next slide.
Let's get an introduction on what is this
multimodal shift is all about, right?
Multimodal, conversational agents
are no longer experimental.
They're quickly becoming the default
interaction model across smart homes,
vehicles, variables, and any sort
of computing devices in your home.
In field studies across 250 households, we
saw as 30 percentage improvement in task
completion when users had access to multim
modalities instead of just voice or text.
What's more interesting is
behavior within about three weeks.
Users naturally shifted towards
multimodal commands without being taught.
You don't need a special user training
to give them, Hey, this is how you
should interact with, it just becomes
like a natural conversational activity.
Any human will be doing it.
That tells us this is inte.
It's a fundamental shift in how
in humans interact with systems.
So the question is, no
longer does multimodal work.
The real question is how we operate
at scale, which we are going to cover
as part of our today's discussion.
Today's agenda, I will
start with the disclaimer.
We are not going to get to the
low level design or low level
architecture of hows get implemented.
It's more of a framework.
This goes like a checklist.
Whenever you want to move your demo
to de demo, to production of any
of your conversational agents, what
framework you should think about
and what things you need to consider
before moving into production.
That's what we are going to cover
as part of our today's session.
It's my majorly classified
into five areas.
First one is, what does a production
grade reference architecture looks like?
Se second, we are going to talk
about the fusion strategies and
their operational trade-offs.
That might not be a situation where
one, one thing will fit for every single
use case you're going to implement.
So we are going to discuss about
the various fusion strategies
available and their operational
trade-offs in the system.
Third one, how evaluation changes
when text is no longer e enough.
The fourth one is.
Observability and incident readiness.
How are you keeping your systems
being ready for incidents?
It happens in the production systems.
And finally, what are the real world
deployment patterns across industries?
Okay, let's start with
our architecture today.
Awesome.
Let's dive into this architecture.
A production multimodal, A
multimodal pipeline typically
breaks into four stages.
We are seeing over here in this slide.
The first one is ingestion,
second one is fusion.
Then reasoning and action.
So these are the four different layers
are the four different stages of
architecture of any multimodal pipeline.
This, there is a reason for the
separation because it's very intentional.
Each stage needs to scale independently.
Fail independently and be
observable independently.
When team blurs these boundaries,
Deva game becomes nearly impossible
once you hit the real production
systems or production traffic.
So let's talk a little more
about ingestion, right?
Ingestion is where
things quietly go wrong.
What it means is you have an
audio, video, touch, or sensor.
That's where actually it gets injected
into your system, into our system.
Suppose all the sensor data, all
this data arrive at different
frequencies and latencies.
If timestamps aren't aligned
properly here, the downstream
reasoning will be incorrect.
Even if your models are perfect
in production, engine ingestion
needs strict synchronization
guarantees back pressure handling
and observability hooks for day one.
The reason is, for example, you
give a command and it takes long
and you give another command.
You get multiple results in a
different timeframe, that it entirely
messes up your experience altogether
with your interaction, right?
That's why ingestion is very
key, because every individual
interaction will be received through
different frequencies and latencies.
So that's the very beginning
of your architecture.
What type of, how are you going
to make sure your tion is tight?
The next thing we are going
to talk about is fusion.
Fusion is where multimodal systems
either shine or fall apart.
This is where signals are combined
and meaning starts to emerge.
But fusion decisions have
direct operational consequences.
For example, latency cost
resilience and failure isolation.
This bring us to FU fusion strategies.
Let's talk about how a fusion strategies
work and what are the different
type of fusion strategies as there.
So there are three major things we are
going to discuss on today's presentation.
One is early fusion, late
fusion, and hybrid fusion.
Let's talk through it.
What does early fusion means by So early
fusion combines signals immediately.
What it means is it fasts it.
It's fast when inputs are
perfectly synchronized, but
it's expensive and brittle.
One missing modality can disrupt the
entire pipeline to get processed.
The second one is late fusion.
Late fusion process modalities
independently and merges decisions later.
This improves fault isolation and
flexibility, but adds latency and
often loses cross model nuances.
The third option is third.
Third strategy is about combination of
both hybrid fusion NOS production system
end up with hybrid fusion, selectively
combining signals based on context.
It's more complex to build, but it balance
costs latency and resilience, which
makes it more practical choice at scale.
So it's not like we will be able to.
One thing will fit for every single
need of our business need based on what
you are trying to implement and based
on your system you're trying to do,
you can choose one among this fusion
strategies which can fit for it, right?
So when you when you are choosing
the operational tradeoffs, what are
the things which is considered for
operational trade off, which we'll
talk about it in the next slide.
So when you're selecting the operational
when you're selecting the fusion
strategies, what you need to trade off is.
Teams should focus on
five important factors.
The first one is latency budgets.
What is your budget?
What is your real time requirements
for voice and video streams?
Is it required that it has to be
high performing and you cannot
tolerate on any latencies?
Or is it okay to have little bit of
latency that decides your latency budget?
Where GPUs and eh compute live, where
you want to make sure you are your
compute, a compute distribution between
your cloud and devices, what you want
to have it on device, what you want to
have it on cloud that has to be decided.
Streams, streaming versus batch workflows,
whether you want to stream on live
or it can be processed on a batch.
Workflows.
Failure models and de degradation paths.
How do you want your failure
models to be handled?
It should be a graceful degradation when
mo, when something fails or how you want
to handle your failure modules, right?
Model modes and cost controls.
How are you going to utilize
your data transfer costs,
cross region costs and whatnot.
So these are the five trade offs you
need to decide when you are going to
design your strategies for fusion.
It could be everything.
Everything.
If you put into the metrics what
you can trade off accordingly,
you can choose your strategy for
your fusion fused methodology.
Okay.
In production, these constraints matters
more than theoretical model accuracy.
Yes.
Okay.
Let's dive further on
evaluation beyond text.
Now, let's talk about evaluation.
What does evaluation
means mean by text only.
Metrics completely fail
for multimodal systems.
You can't just rely only on text.
You can't measure success by scores
where the system is looking at the room.
Hearing a command and touching
a screen evaluation must
reflect real user outcomes.
That's why you have to maintain some sort
of a way to make sure, that way to ensure
that your your system is beyond text.
That's where task success rate.
So end-to-end completion of
user intents across modalities.
You make sure that you have
end-to-end completion of user
intents to give a complete,
meaningful input and output as well.
Grounding a accuracy correctness of object
recognition and spa reasoning, right?
So we focus on those four key
metrics, multimodal metrics.
Is that based on these four key areas.
What is that task success rate?
Did the user actually
get what they wanted?
End?
End completion of use
sentence across modalities.
That's what it mean by, did the
user actually get what they wanted?
Grounding accuracy, which means that
did the system correctly identifies
objects and partial context.
Does it got the right context?
Is it really getting identifiable
to identify the objects?
Next is modality agreement to voice,
vision and touch Align does all of this
line up in the way it's expected to be?
The last is the temporal
alignment or signal synchronized
correctly over the time.
That's what mean by temporal element.
These are the key metrics which
will help us to evaluate evaluate.
Evaluate whether the system which we are
designing are hardened enough and it's
going to manage the production load.
Okay, let's talk about observability.
Without observability, multimodal
systems become unmanageable.
Failures are rarely obvious.
A system might work, but with de
degraded accuracy, pricing latency,
or runaway GPU costs, it's very tough.
Let's talk about individual
tracing individual way.
How we can absorb the production
system is actually working in
the way it is expected to work.
The first one is cross model tracing.
Cross model tracing lets us follow
a single user interaction across
audio, video, and touch pipelines
using correlate correlation IDs.
This is essential for diagnosing latency
spikes, dropped signals, and subtile
failures that only occurred at the load.
So it's very tough to replicate
in a development instance or in
a non-production instance because
it, the load amount of load we are
trying to test is mere impossible to
create it in that environment, right?
That's why this is all this are
going to help us track it towards it.
The next one is computer
compute attribution.
Oh, sorry.
Drift.
Yeah, drift reduction.
Second is compute attribution,
sorry, per modality.
Per per modality.
Compute attribution tells us where
GPUs are actually being used.
Many teams discover that one modality
quietly consumes the majority of
resources without this visibility.
Cost.
Cost optimization is guest work.
Guest work.
The amount of infrastructure costs
required for any agents is very high,
so we have to be very frugal when we
are developing the systems at scale.
Last one is drift detection.
Drift happens everywhere.
Input distributions, user
behavior and model performance.
Task statistical monitoring helps.
Catches the shifts early,
but users, before users, user
experiences, any failures.
That's the use of drift reduction.
Let's get into safeguards.
Production systems must assume failure.
Like it's not possible that
it cannot go through failure.
We can have a hundred percent
Accu a hundred percent run time
on any of the production systems.
So we must assume failure,
multi-model pipeline should degrade
gracefully instead of collapsing
in case there is a failure happen.
We should find ways to gracefully
gracefully degrade our pipelines
instead of just collapsing
and then left with no choice.
So what are the ways we can do this right?
Fall back and degradation infusion fails.
Systems should automatically fall back
to a single modality like voice only.
So use still complete code tasks.
Graceful degradation, keep
system us usable during partial
outages or traffic spikes, right?
Privacy boundaries.
Audio and video data requires
strict privacy controls, encryptions
access, boundaries, retention
limits, and user contact Consent.
Privacy is not an option in the
production environment and requirement.
The reason is in production you
will be capturing most of capturing
the voice movements and whatnot.
So privacy is very key in
ensuring that you are handling
the customer data effectively.
Let's get into the next slide.
ML OPS and L-L-L-L-M ops.
So these are some of the operational
patterns which can help us to
see how we can able to operate
effectively in a production system.
The multimodal systems multiply
operational complexity.
Your version, your versioning.
This can help us in you, you are
version your audio models, vision models
and language models often together.
So there are ways.
You can maintain your models
effectively only among through
the versioning of your models.
It ensure that it's
always a version exists.
If something doesn't work, you can
always fall back to the previous version.
How do you test your ML models
through a b testing, right?
That helps you to experiment your
data, collect enough data pointers
before you roll out to production.
So you do AB testing on your
ML models, model registries.
This is, this is like a registry
with metadata for modality specific
performance characteristics, how we
see your model actually performing.
How is your characteristics of your model?
So these are the rollout rollout
strategies must understand
modality specific behavior before
you roll out to production.
The next comes the data operations, right?
How do you operate your data?
The data operations, data pipelines
must support multimodal data
sets with timestamp validation,
synthetic data generation for rare
cases, and automatic PIE detection.
Without this model
evaluation slows to a crawl.
Let's move on to next slide.
So let's talk about real
world applications, like
how it works across systems.
We see successful deployment across smart
homes with subset subsecond responses.
It could be voice, gesture,
screen interactions for lighting,
climate, and environment control
with subsecond responses, right?
The second one is automotive.
Automotive systems combining driver
mon monitoring and voice, right?
The third one is wearables, using
voice and ha haptics and AR and vr.
There are like AR and VR environments
built around spatial interactions.
Each domain pushes different constraints,
but the core principles remains the same.
Right.
Let's talk about from
production from prototype, pro
production, key success factors.
Team that succeeded in
production do five things well.
They define base metrics, early metrics.
That's your key for your success.
Success, what type of metrics you measure.
How you measure it is very crucial in
any production system, especially on
this multi, on this agent based model and
deployment and through pipelines, right?
So they define baseline metrics early.
They roll out progressively
with feature flags, right?
They deploy.
This is like differentiating between your
deployment and your release strategy.
You deploy your software either to
the device or in your cloud or in
your cloud system, but you're not
open up to all the customers, so you
control it through feature flags.
So they roll out progressively
through feature flags, and they
have an option to turn it off too.
They build feedback loops
from real usage, right?
So capture those user corrections
and then identify anything you
can able to capture from the real
usage and then course corrected.
They actively optimize cost.
Cost is very crucial in
this complete process.
So they optimize cost and they maintain
operational ance with runbooks and
on-call rotations so that anything go,
anything and everything can be supported
at any time and point of any point
of time for the system in production.
Okay, let's go to key takeaways.
So one message, if there is one message
to take away from this presentation
is the architecture is matters.
Architecture matters most,
measure real tasks, success.
Success, right?
You observe everything and
plan for failure before it
happens, not during an incident.
So these are the four takeaways
I would leave you with on
this particular presentation.
I'll repeat one more time.
It's architecture matters.
Measure real tasks success,
observe everything, and plan
for failure before it happens.
Okay.
And last but not least,
thank you for your time.
I hope this gives you a practical
framework for building multimodal
conversational agents that your
teams can deploy with confidence.
And if you have any questions, feel
free to shoot it over my LinkedIn.
I'm happy to answer it over there as well.
Thank you so much for your
time and see you soon.
Bye.