Speaker 19: What is going on everybody?
My name is Michael Lavan, and I'd like
to welcome you to Conf 42 DevOps 2026.
So in this session, what we're gonna do is
we are going to talk about all things cost
around LLMs, around AI in general, and
all the traffic that you may be sending
from an agent to an LLM or an agent to an
MCP server, or an agent to another agent.
We're gonna see how we can not only route
all that traffic through an AI gateway
using agent Gateway, but we're actually
going to see the cost, the breakdown,
what model is used and everything from
a metrics perspective within Grafana.
So let's go ahead and jump on in.
Okay, so the first thing that we want to
do is we want to make sure we have agent
Gateway installed, which I already did.
I can go ahead, run this command,
and then we can see that output here.
Now the next thing that we want to do is
we want to figure out what LLM provider
we want to use to route traffic to, right?
Again, whether it's via an agent, whether
we're just going directly through the
gateway, however we want to do it.
We need an LLM provider.
So in this case I'm gonna use Anthropic
just 'cause that's where I have a
subscription, but any LLM provider
will work just fine in this case.
Now I've already set my anthropic
key, so what I can do is I can
create a Kubernetes secret that's
pointing to the Anthropic API Key.
All right, so now what we're gonna do
is we're gonna create three gateways,
and it doesn't matter if you create one
or two or 10 or 20, it doesn't matter.
I'm just using three because I feel like
it's a good number to showcase all the
costs and how we can put it all together.
But again, if you're using one.
20 doesn't matter.
Alright, so to break this down,
I'm gonna create a gateway object.
And this is of course coming from the
Kubernetes gateway, API CRDs, right?
And I'm gonna name it agent gateway one,
and then I'm gonna have three gateways.
So there's gonna be agent
gateway one, two, and three.
Alright?
I'm gonna use the agent gateway class,
and then I'm just gonna allow traffic
from all name spaces for testing purposes.
Next what we're gonna do is we're
gonna create an agent gateway.
Backend.
And this backend is how the gateway
itself knows what to route to.
So in this case, I'm routing to a
clawed model, but I could also be
routing to an MCP server, for example.
Alright, and then last, but certainly
not least, is the HTP route.
That way we have an endpoint that
we can actually route to, right?
And as you can see here, I'm
referencing the gateway and then I'm
referencing the agent gateway backend.
Now the other thing that
I'm doing is I'm replacing.
The slash V one slash chat slash
completions path with slash anthropic.
Why?
Just because slash anthropic is
a lot easier to type than slash v
one slash chat slash completions.
Okay.
Now one thing I will say is if you're
wondering hey Mike, I thought you
were routing to Claude, so shouldn't
it be slash V one slash messages?
This path here would be considered
part of the OpenAI API format
spec, which Claude supports.
So it's totally fine.
This will work as expected.
That way we can route to it and we
can even curl it to see that it works.
So I'm gonna go ahead.
I'm gonna create this gateway here.
Alright, and then I'm going to
create the gateway for the second
gateway and the third gateway.
And again, this is the, it's
literally the same configuration
pointing to the same LLM, all that.
I'm just using three gateways so
we can see the cost breakdown and
how the cost can come together.
Okay.
Now the next thing that we want to
do is we want to send some traffic
to our gateways and we want to see
that they actually work as expected.
Alright, so I'm gonna export the
IP addresses and put them into
environment variables of all of
the A LB ips for the gateways.
All right, so we have Aging
gateway one, aging gateway
two, and Aging gateway three.
All right.
And we can see those three
IP addresses pop up there.
Again, those are the a LB
public IPS for the gateway.
Alright, so now let's actually test
the gateway configuration here.
All right.
And what we'll do is we will
curl each ingress gateway.
That way we can also send some
traffic to it as well, right?
So I'm gonna curl the first one here.
Then I'll go ahead and
curl the second one.
All right, and then I'll go
ahead and curl the third one.
And this will allow us to actually
generate some metrics, right?
So like when we curl to the
gateways, we can generate metrics.
That way we can actually see those
metrics within the Grafana dashboard.
Alright, now the next piece of the
puzzle is to install Q Prometheus.
And if you're not familiar with Q
Prometheus, it's a pretty cool project.
It's as the name sounds
like Prometheus and Grafana.
But the cool thing is you get a lot
of dashboards out of the box for
Kubernetes, whereas if you were just
installing Grafana and Prometheus,
you wouldn't have any dashboards.
So I do like typically to install.
Q Prometheus.
All right, so I'm gonna go ahead.
I'm going to install it on my cluster, and
now that it's installed, what I'm gonna
do is I have two new terminals open here.
I'm gonna go ahead and pour forward
to Prometheus, and then I am also
going to port forward to Grafana.
All right?
And then what we can do
is we can open up Grafana.
That way we can just get logged in.
Speaker 20: All
Speaker 19: right.
And then admin, and we just
gotta pull the secret here.
So I'm gonna go ahead, run this
command to get the secret right.
Copy that.
Paste this in.
Okay, cool.
So now we are in Grafana.
Let me zoom in a little bit, and
if I go to the dashboards here, we
can see all the dashboards that are
already available out of the box.
But we're gonna need to do two things.
We're gonna have to set up some
monitors, and then we're gonna
have to set up our dashboard.
Okay, so as you can see here, I
have a couple of different monitors
and they are all the pod monitors
for the gateways that we deploy.
Okay?
So as you can see, the name is Agent
Gateway one Pod monitor, right?
And then you can see that it's
listening for Agent Gateway one.
And that's our gateway
that was deployed, right?
So if I run Cube, CTL,
get Gateway, namespace.
Aging gateway system, right?
We can see aging gateway
one, two, and three.
Actually have to do a quick update
here, and that's because we used
to deploy to K gateway system.
Now we deploy to aging gateway
system, and then you can see that it's
listening on slash metrics and it's
pulling the metrics every 30 seconds.
And then again, we do this
for Agent Gateway one.
Agent gateway two, and
Agent gateway three.
All right, so I'm gonna run QCTL
apply minus F agent gateway,
O-S-S-K-S, cost and monitoring dl.
All right, so those are deployed here.
And then now what I'm gonna do is I'm
just gonna go and send a little bit
more traffic through my gateways, right?
Some traffic is sent.
Now what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go
into Grafana and I'm going to implement
this dashboard that I created, and
this is a custom dashboard for all
the costs and the metrics and such.
But if you want, you just
need to go to my GitHub.
Go to this path here, and then
you can import the dashboard
yourself as well, if you'd like
to use it in your own environment.
Okay, so I'm gonna go
back over to Grafana.
I'm gonna say new import.
Oops, sorry.
New import.
Okay.
And then I'm going to specify
my path to my dashboard.
Okay, perfect.
So now I'm gonna say import and we
can now officially see the cost.
Per gateway and for all of our gateways
together, and luckily I haven't spent
too much money, so I am still in budget.
And if you want, what you can do is you
can actually go to Prometheus as well.
And if you type Agent Gateway, you'll
see all the different metrics available.
So if I wanted to see, token usage, for
example, I can see token usage based
on what gateway I sent the request to
the model and where it originated from.
And that's how you can begin to
track your costs for any AG agentic
traffic using Agent Gateway.
Thank you so much for watching.