Hello, and welcome to this talk on
the future of observability and what
you can expect over the next 10 years.
I'm Shamshree Wilson,
and I work at NetData.
NetData is a real time observability
platform with a unique distributed
architecture and an open source core.
This talk isn't really
about NetData, the product.
though I might, talk about a few of the
decisions we've made along the way and
some of the principles that we follow.
If you'd like to find out
more about NetData, you can
check out our website at www.
netdata.
cloud.
Now let's get started with the talk.
Let's start by discussing a
little bit about the evolving
definition of observability.
What is observability
and what does it mean?
and has this meaning
transformed over time.
Now the traditional definition of
observability is that it is the
ability to observe and understand
the internal state of a system by
examining its external outputs.
And when we talk about external
outputs, we usually mean
metrics, logs, and traces today.
In other words, observability
is to understand what is
happening with the system.
Now, this traditional definition
came out of control systems, and
that explains some of the terminology
that you see here, when we talk about
internal state, external outputs.
But today, observability has,
has evolved over all these years.
And it's a term that's primarily
used for people who are managing
IT infrastructure these days.
And IT infrastructure, as we all
know, has been growing ever complex.
and it's, deployed across multiple
kinds of environments, and it
scales up, it scales down, and
there's hundreds, thousands of
services talking to each other.
So it's, it is a very complex environment.
So the current reality of observability
is that it's really the digital
nervous system of modern enterprises.
Thank you.
So it's no longer just about logs,
metrics, and traces, but what we're
trying to get out of observability is
to achieve real time comprehension, real
time understanding of the complex digital
ecosystems through the lens of causality.
And causality is an important term
here because what we expect out
of observability today is not just
to understand what is happening,
but also why it is happening.
what to do about it, and
all of this in real time.
So this is now the new evolved
definition of observability, if you may.
So now that we've talked about
what observability is, let's just
pause and think about what is the
current state of observability?
What are the problems
with observability today?
So, You can see that there's, there's
some problems that are called out
here, and it's, it's been classified
into three different categories.
Too little observability, too
complex observability, and
too expensive observability.
And as you can see by that interconnected
graph here, it, it's actually a mix
of all of these things, and it kind of
bleeds into each different category.
So let's, let's start by talking
about too little observability.
What does this mean?
So what this means is that the,
the, the system either doesn't
have any observability at all.
So there's nobody really
looking at what's going on.
or there's very limited visibility,
which means that there's some
monitoring of a few metrics.
There might be a dashboard here or
there, but it's not really capturing
the full state of the system.
And this is a very dangerous situation
to be in because, you might have
a false sense of security that
I have monitoring for my system.
But you just have a very partial view, and
that partial view might be telling you a
very different story from, from reality.
So limited visibility is a problem.
And, the other problem is late detection.
So when we talk about too little,
observability, it also means that Maybe
you have the metrics that you need, but
you don't have the sampling intervals
that you need, which means that you're
collecting the data, but it's too late.
So you're missing out on these short micro
spikes or bursts, or, you know, you're
finding out about the issue too late.
So late detection becomes
a big problem as well.
performance bottlenecks either
directly due to the kind of
observability that you've implemented.
Or the fact that you're missing
out on identifying the performance
bottlenecks becomes a problem too.
and all of these things kind of
contribute to delayed troubleshooting.
So you don't have the right tool
set to be able to understand and
troubleshoot an issue in real time.
And when this happens, somewhere down
the line, you're going to have outages.
And outages are very, very expensive.
And they're getting more
expensive, with each passing year.
And all of these things, of course,
contribute to reduced engineering
efficiency and, overheads when it
comes to maintenance and operations.
So, clearly, too little
observability is not a situation
that anybody really wants to be in.
What's the second category here?
So, now we're talking about when you
have observability, but it's too complex.
and this is again, you know,
complex observability leads to
many of the same sort of issues.
Such as delayed troubleshooting,
the fact that you're not able to
identify outages on time, reduced
engineering efficiency, and so on.
it also has, different aspects that makes
it hard to scale, when you're, as your,
as your system and as your team scales.
And especially hard when you're
dealing with hybrid infrastructure
and dynamic environments.
let me give a little bit of an example
about what I mean when I say too
complex observability, just so that
it's easier for you to understand.
think about a case where, you're starting
off with, with a system, and it's,
it's initially the MVP version of the
product, and you set up, observability.
So maybe you start off with a
Prometheus and Grafana stack,
and it's not complex, right?
It was pretty easy for you to set it up.
You're experienced in Prometheus
and Grafana, and you put
everything up, it's fine.
The problem happens when, as time
passes, you add more features, more
services to your stack, there's
no different kinds of applications
running in tandem, there's messaging
between them, Maybe your environment
scales, you're not on prem anymore.
You're hosted as part
of your system on AWS.
there's some services on prem.
Maybe there's other services
running on other clouds.
And now you have a
complex system in place.
And the question then arises,
were you able to keep up with your
observability that you set up on
Prometheus and Grafana over time?
and that's, that's becomes a
very interesting challenge.
Because what started off as
simple may no longer be simple.
because as you scale, there's more
things that you want to monitor.
So every time you need to take
the decision, do I have the
right, Prometheus exporters?
am I getting all the right metrics?
how should I visualize this?
because spending a lot of time creating
custom dashboards is, not going to be a
fun thing to do as your services scale.
So you might have to rely on community
dashboards, but then you're not 100
percent sure if the community dashboard
is capturing everything that you need.
So it, it adds up over time into one
cognitive overload for you, and then
there's, of course, going to be other
business related tasks that, that
your team, need to spend time on.
So they don't really have that
time to dedicate building custom
dashboards and writing custom
queries on PromQL, or wherever.
And over time, it becomes
really, really complex.
So it starts off simple, but then
it becomes complex over time.
And now finally, let's look at the
third category, which is too expensive.
And this really kind of touches upon
all of these different issues, right?
So we have these modern observability
platforms, whether we're talking
about tools like Datadog, Dynatrace,
which are really powerful, right?
They have all the features that you need.
They're gathering all the right
metrics and logs and traces and
have really neat visualizations
to kind of present them to you.
But they're also really expensive.
and while that might not be a problem for
large enterprises who have money to spare.
it becomes problematic for smaller
enterprises and startups and companies
that are starting out because they
don't have, that amount of, capital
to invest into observability.
And what do they do at that point, right?
So what are the choices
that they're left with?
Either they say that, you know, we're
not going to invest that much in
observability, and, you know, we'll
see about it when it comes to it.
And that, which means that they fall
back to too little observability.
Which is a problematic scenario to be in.
or they try to say, we'll do it ourselves.
And that takes them to the second
category of too complex observability.
So this, this becomes a
problem when we think about how
observability can be democratized.
And it also becomes a problem
when we think about the kind
of architectures in place.
So, later in this talk I'll, I'll
be speaking about centralized versus
distributed or decentralized architectures
when it comes to observability.
And why this is the, the crux
when it comes to why observability
becomes too expensive.
So this is a little bit about the
current state of observability.
And now let's look at, let's
look at the future, right?
Because that's what this talk is about.
Let's look at what's headed
our way over the next decade.
So I like to term the next 10 years, the
great infrastructure explosion, because
that's, that's absolutely what we're going
to be able, what we're going to be seeing.
there's, there is already, and there
will be an even bigger data center boom.
so the global data center market,
which is around 500 billion, worth
today in 2025 will grow to nearly 2
trillion by the end of the decade.
and that, so that's, that's
a huge amount of growth.
And considering what's happening with
AI and the AI arms race that we are
in, with all the major, tech companies
really locked into, you know, the
race towards, super intelligence, we,
you know, we might be underestimating
it when we say 2 trillion.
the data center market might
actually be much larger.
And a different way to look at this is
that the energy consumption that data
centers globally would be consuming,
even at a conservative estimate by
2035 would be 8 percent of the world's
total electricity, which means that a
large part of human existence and our
world in general is going to be built
around supporting, these data centers
where we are cultivating intelligence.
Compute capacity has been growing
at two and a half times faster
than Moore's Law recently.
And all of this means that there's going
to be A lot more data centers running a
lot more different kinds of workloads.
there's going to be a lot more IT
infrastructure which needs to underpin
all of this and Eventually, it means
that we would need better and more
observability So that the teams
who are maintaining and managing
all of this and can keep it running
That brings us to the human
factor So DevOps and SRE jobs are
actually growing, multiple times
faster than traditional IT jobs.
Now I know that, you know, there's been a
lot of talk about what's going to happen
with AI and people's jobs in general.
And of course, AI will
affect the jobs market.
There are certain jobs or certain
roles that people are doing today
that will get automated away.
Or at least parts of that
job will get automated away.
but at least what, what I believe
is going to happen is that the,
the amount of work will increase.
So the average organization is going to
be managing five times more services.
by 2030, that's, that's in five years.
which means that there's going to be a
multiple fold increase in infrastructure
teams needed overall, which means that the
amount of total jobs available is going to
increase, especially for DevOps and SRE.
And this is directly related
to the data center boom.
You're going to have huge number
of data centers, with, you know,
increasing complexity of workloads.
And you're going to have, you're
going to need teams to manage this.
Now, of course.
You know, AI is going to be a factor here.
so the, the kind of work, that your
average SRE does is going to be different.
But you're still going to
need a lot more of them.
And a combination of these
things means that observability
is mission critical now.
The average cost of downtime
is more than 9, 000 a minute.
And you know this number is from a few
years ago I'm sure that it's grown to
even higher now by now and it keeps
growing up every year so Downtime is
something that you want to minimize
to the most infinitesimal possible
value as much as you can Unobserved
or, you know, partially understood or
misunderstood failures can cascade today
across thousands of different services,
distributed systems, nodes, multiple
clouds, which makes it a lot harder
when you don't have the visibility to
understand what really happened, right?
Because you need to understand
what happened so that you can
prevent it from happening again.
And all of this means that good
observability is survival critical and
it's not just a nice to have anymore.
So now that we've talked a little
bit about what's headed our way
in the next 10 years, and here
are some references as well.
I know that the text is kind of
small, but, you can download the
slides afterwards and you can look
at where these numbers come from
that I was quoting in the stats here.
So let's, let's talk about the stats.
what the observability
equation really is, right?
And, and this is the, the
traditional observability equation.
You might have seen it, heard it
in other, in other talks and other
sessions and books and so on.
That observability is made up
of metrics, logs, and traces.
Now, I think where we are today and
where we're headed in the next ten years,
we need a new observability equation.
And it's not just about
metrics, logs, and traces.
So the way that I see this is the new
observability equation is made up of
three things, but those three things
are data, context, and intelligence.
So data is all of the data,
including metrics, logs, traces,
any, any sort of raw system output.
And they form the foundational
layer of observability.
But observability is
just not limited to data.
Observability isn't just
metrics, logs, and traces, right?
It just forms a foundational
layer on which the new
observability equation is built.
The second part of this
equation is context.
So context is really important.
Without context, your data,
even though you have it, might
be telling you a wrong story.
It might not be telling
you a story at all.
So it's not really providing the
value that it should without context.
So, what do I mean by context?
Context really is a rich metadata.
So it's, it's information about
the data that explains the data.
For example, it might be an anomaly
pattern which says, you know, here's
your, the value for your, CPU percentage.
but here's additional metadata which
tells if this is normal or not for
this system, for this particular
component within this system.
So that piece of extra metadata
now tells you that, you know, it
tells you a better story, right?
So you have a value, CPU is at 90%,
but maybe the, the anomaly pattern
tells you that CPU for this component
on this system is always at 90%.
So that's a very different thing from
just telling you that the CPU is 90%.
you can, you know, anomaly
patterns is just one example.
You could have, correlation information.
So when you have information about a
single metric, you also have correlation,
which says that here's what happened
with other metrics or other logs, while
this metric was exhibiting this value.
So this is You know, at NADATA,
we really believe that context is
important, and, and we try to make
our, our tool, our product, more
opinionated, so that it's bringing you
these opinions about what you're seeing.
It's not just showing you data,
but it's also trying to tell
you a story about the data.
I'm not saying that, you know,
we're, we've solved, the, the
equation when it comes to context,
there's a lot more that we can do.
And there's a lot more that the industry
in general should be doing, about making,
metadata a first class citizen, because
there's, there's a lot of, important
information when it comes to, you
know, what, what the business KPIs are
that your system is trying to achieve.
what's the real world events that are
happening that are related to what your
observability data is trying to tell you.
And bringing those things together, will
provide, you know, exponential value.
Now, the, the third component to the new
observability equation, is intelligence.
And yes, I'm talking about AI.
because up until now, intelligence
was solely provided by humans.
And we were limited by, the amount
of time, the amount of people
that, you know, could be working
on this at one point in time.
but, With the, the capability
increases in AI that we've been seeing
recently, it means that we have this
layer of intelligence that we can
start applying to data and context.
And context becomes ever more
important because, humans, And the
human teams had experience to rely on.
They had a better inherent understanding
of context when it came to the data.
For example, you know, a team of SREs
or, or DevOps engineers would already
know if, if they were working on an
e commerce platform, that there would
be certain trends when it came to.
a particular sale that the
company was running, right?
It might be a Black Friday
sale, it might be something else
which is region specific, but
they would already know that.
whereas if you're, if you're relying
on an AI, platform or an AI agent
to do this, maybe the AI agent knows
this as well, but maybe it doesn't.
maybe it's, been biased based
on the training data, so it's
not really expecting that this.
this context, exists
for, for your use case.
So to be able to provide that context
as metadata means that, the, the, the
AI intelligence that you're relying
on becomes a lot more capable as well.
And we are going to be, seeing a lot
more, from autonomous agents, and
predictive modeling when it comes to AI.
you know, we'll, we'll speak
more about this as well.
But this new equation, what this
does is that, you know, you, you, you
have data as your foundational layer.
You add a rich metadata in the form of
context on top, and then you have this
intelligence layer that can try to kind
of combine this, stir the stew, if you
will, and really bring out of it insights.
And that's, that's the ideal, if you will.
end product or output of the
observability equation is the
fact that you get true insights.
So you're getting true insights into your
infrastructure, into your system about
what's, you know, what's going on, why
is it going on, what, what you need to
do about it if you need to do about it.
And you, all of this is
happening in real time.
So this is the ideal new
observability equation that I
think, both companies and teams use.
should be talking about.
Now let's dive a little bit
deeper into each of these three
different parts of the equation.
Starting with data, right?
So starting with the foundation.
And I really want to stress on the
importance of high fidelity data.
So what does high fidelity mean?
High fidelity means that you,
you have all of the data.
So you're getting all of
the different metrics.
You're not missing out on any of the
metrics, but you're also getting as
many samples per metric that you can.
And more is better in this case,
because higher resolution, which
means that you're, for example,
if you're capturing data for a
particular metric every single second,
that's high resolution compared to.
capturing data every 10 seconds
or every 60 seconds, or in some
cases, you know, there are tools
out there which only capture data
every five minutes, every 10 minutes.
and that, you know, it does
give you, you know, you could
still plot a chart out of it.
You can put it on a dashboard, but that
number, if you're gathering it every,
every minute or every five minutes is
very different from, you know, the, the
story that you can tell if you're getting.
per second information
for that same metric.
You get way better insights into
what's really happening with
that metric, with your system,
when you get a high resolution.
So, you know, every time that you increase
your sampling intervals, you're, you're
missing out on unknown unknowns, right?
And this, this is a, this is
a really hidden issue because
you don't see what's going on.
So you don't know if
it's a problem or not.
So it, this is why we call
it an unknown unknown.
so if you really want to future proof
your troubleshooting and, future proof
your observability stack overall, then
you should be waiting towards, you know,
leaning towards higher resolution data.
The more data that you can have,
you know, the, the lower sampling
intervals that you have, the better.
And of course, a side effect of
this is that if you're relying on
machine learning, if you're relying
on artificial intelligence, then,
you know, a higher data density is
always better because it allows the AI
systems to learn the right patterns.
If you provide a machine learning
algorithm or an AI model with sparse
data, then, you it finds it harder to
learn the right patterns, or sometimes
it might arrive at the wrong patterns.
Give it the, you know, the more
data that you give it and the more
context that you give it, it can
arrive at the right conclusions.
So what are the new rules of data?
Rule number one is collect everything.
You can filter out the stuff
that you don't need later.
Rule number two, you know, the
better the sampling frequency,
the better the outcome.
Okay.
Rule number three is don't
have artificial limits.
So don't have a limit which says
that you can only collect x number
of samples per y interval and you can
only store it for, you know, x days.
If that limit is artificial, if that
limit is something that, you know,
a tool is introducing but it's not
natural to your system, to your
workflow, don't settle for that limit.
And finally, In an ideal world, you want
to store everything indefinitely, right?
Maybe you need to archive it,
maybe you need to digest the data.
But still, it's available there
if you want to go back in time.
Because very often what happens
when you're troubleshooting an
issue is that you want to know
what happened when similar issues
like this happened in the past.
And you need to be able to
go back and look at data.
which means that you want to
have, you know, some form of
that data available to you.
So if, if you're designing your
observability stack today, you know, I
would play very, I would pay very close
attention to these new rules of data
because the real impact that it can have,
on your team and on the work that you
do is that you can have significantly
faster mean timed resolution.
when you have access
to high fidelity data.
it allows you to catch micro
anomalies before they cascade
and start creating problems in
different parts of your system.
And, the, the high fidelity data also
makes, learning historical patterns to
reveal future issues, a much more exact
science, than it otherwise would be.
So, to sum up, you know, the difference
between low fidelity and high fidelity
is that You know, you're dealing with,
real time, one second samples versus
dealing with ten seconds to sixty seconds
or even worse, sampling intervals.
you're, you know, you have the
option to gather any number
of metrics that you want to.
So, you know, in, in
theory, it's unlimited.
You can get anything and
everything that you need.
So you shouldn't be metered by how
many metrics you're collecting, because
anytime, any of these things, have a
metering in terms of the price, then it
becomes a decision for the team to take
that, you know, we can't get everything
that we need, we're going to get charged
by the number of metrics or the amount
or the usage of metrics or logs, for
example, then you have to decide, okay,
you know, I need to take a decision.
I'm opting in for only
this subset of metrics.
so you, you, you become, you get
stuck in a partial metric situation.
You don't want to be there.
you, you want to have full freedom on
getting all the data that you need.
And a similar situation
with retention as well.
So in, in an ideal world, you
want to be able to retain.
the data up to what is
naturally, meaningful for your
workload, for your system.
You don't want an artificial
limitation that's being decided
by, by a vendor or a tool, that is
not natural to what you're doing.
So we talked about data, high fidelity
data, which, which is the foundation
of the new observability equation.
let's talk about, metadata.
Rich metadata.
can be thought of as
context at scale, right?
So you're getting context from
different parts of your system
for different kinds of metrics,
and you're getting it at scale.
And, and this really, you know,
is where the magic happens.
So this, this could be all kinds
of different information, right?
So you could have business context in
here, which, which talks about, you know,
what, what is the revenue impact to you?
what are the, the touch points in the
customer journey or the user journey
while the user is using the system?
you can have context around the
business transaction flow and also
SLA, SLO implications because that
matters a lot for, for certain
products and certain teams.
Then there's the operational context.
so service dependencies, changes in the
infrastructure that are being rolled out.
deployment events.
So when, when a new build is being
deployed, you need all of that information
to, again, tell a better story, right?
and it's not even if, you know, every
time it doesn't have to be about a
major change in the infrastructure
or, or a new build being deployed.
It could be a minor
configuration update as well.
But that information is still critical
because without it, some of the other
data might not tell you the full story.
And then you have environmental
context, which is, real world events.
So what's happening in the world
today that might be influencing
what your system is experiencing.
There could be regional impacts
due to outages that are not related
to your product, but maybe AWS
is down and that impacts you.
Or maybe there's another third
party service, that does that.
You know, that, that's announcing
its status on their status page,
which is accessible publicly.
But that story isn't being told as
part of your observability story.
And it just adds extra work
for, for somebody to go and
manually connect the dots.
In an ideal world, those things
would happen automatically.
So there's all of these different
various market conditions which
can, which can influence what
your system is experiencing.
And all of that, could become context that
your observability, equation could use.
And then there's the opinionated insights
that I was talking about earlier.
so this is an area where we've,
started, trying to, get some of
this done as part of the NetData
product, including, anomaly detection.
So when, when we do anomaly
detection at NetData, we don't
do it as an optional thing.
We do it for.
every single metric that we collect.
It means that every metric comes
with this extra piece of metadata
that tells, you know, is what
you're seeing anomalous or not.
Similarly, there's the ability to, we ha
NetData has a scoring engine, which allows
you to do, correlation of what's happening
at any time interval of your choice.
So you understand which metrics are
behaving in a correlated fashion
at that point in time or not.
But of course, there's a lot more that
we could do in terms of, you know,
root cost ranking and things like that.
So what all of this means is that
when you have rich metadata, when
you have the right context, you
can tell a much more meaningful,
interesting, and useful story, right?
So instead of just saying that
triggering a raw alert, saying that
you have, you know, CPU has hit 90
percent because it's hit some threshold.
When you have the right context, you
could actually tell a story which
says, you know, this particular revenue
critical service is experiencing
never before seen slowdown, right?
So it's, it's an anomalous slowdown
during peak shopping hour because
we have that context as well.
And we can have the context which says
that this is likely happening due to
a recent deployment because you have
the time when the deployment happened.
And you can see when
the slowdown occurred.
started after that, right?
So just, just look at the difference
between these two things, and you
will understand, you know, where
observability needs to be for you.
And now, you know, the third, spoke in the
wheel, of the new observability equation,
the giant pink elephant in the room, AI.
So, I like to think of AI as
the, the force multiplier.
And What's going to happen with
AI in the next 10 years is, it's
really anybody's guess almost.
because the, the, the capabilities of
the models that are available today,
especially with the success of the
transformer architecture and, the
takeoff of large language models.
that that has happened after Chad GPT was
launched and the world really got their
taste of, you know, what these models are
capable of, has been really something.
The models are almost doubling
in capability every six months.
So it's very hard to predict what
exactly will happen, but there are trends
that we can see and there's, there's,
there's things that we can expect that
will happen over the next 10 years.
Specialized AI agents is something
that it's already starting to happen.
And I, I see this as one area
where we're going to see a lot more
traction over the next few years.
And there will be, agents that
are optimized for certain things.
we are already seeing models that are
optimized for reasoning, so that they
take some time to think through the
answer before giving you a response.
So reasoning agents will become very,
key for, for causal analysis across,
services and across a large system.
we will also have memory augmented
agents for historical pattern matching
because the, you know, when we're
dealing with observability data.
And all of you know this,
there's a huge amount of data.
so it's not like you can take all
of the data and fill it into the
context of a large language model.
In most cases, it's either not possible
or it's prohibitively expensive today.
Of course, the cost is going
to come down in the future.
but there will be different, different
models of how, memory will be
handled by, by models in the future.
This is, this is one area, memory is one
area where today's models are lacking.
There will also be planning agents,
that, that will, You know, sit or embed
in your observability stack and, and
are looking at, you know, achieving
specific goals or targets, whether
it's capacity optimization, capacity
planning, or cost management, the
planning agents should be, you know,
will be able to run independently.
And they're always there.
They're always looking through the
data, always looking for ways in
which you can optimize your costs
or, or plan your capacity better.
And, and they're, they're going through
the data, they're going through the
context and they're bringing back
insights to you that, you know, here's
something that, that could be done.
And maybe there's things that can be
automated as well when it comes to,
automatic scaling and things like that.
and, and the final point here, is
about autonomous, RAG enabled agents.
RAG stands for retrieval augmented
generation, which means that you can
provide, for example, documentation
information, you can provide access
to your JIRA, or to your incident
management system, and the agent,
the AI agent, would then be able
to look at all this information
based on a search for relevancy.
And You know, based on that, it can
provide you either here's the steps that
you need to do, or in some cases, you
can automate it so that certain runbooks
or playbooks get executed automatically.
I'm already seeing, a lot of startups out
there who are experimenting in this space,
and I expect that we're going to see a
lot more of this, in the next few years.
So the technical capabilities, of
these models, are, are an area that
it's, it's worth spending time on.
there, there's a lot that can be
done here and we're, we're barely
scratching the surface with the things
that I'm talking about on the slide.
but for exam, I'm just
giving you a few examples.
There's a lot more that
could be done, of course.
So when it comes to parsing large
amounts of logs at scale, trying to
understand complex error patterns, you
can really use LLMs to transform the
way that this is being done currently.
You can do multi hop reasoning.
So you can try to connect the dots
between, you know, what you see on
service A with what you see on service B.
You can do vector similarity searches
across incidents and try to understand.
Is what I'm seeing right now unique?
Is it related to incidents
that have happened in the past?
You know, what were the playbooks or
runbooks that were executed when this
kind of issue happened in the past?
does it make sense to re
execute those things now?
Sorry.
And the other thing that, you know,
will happen and is already starting
to happen is a real time prompt
engineering based on the system state.
So prompt engineering is just a
fancy term for, tweaking how you're
interacting with a large language model.
So what are you asking it to do?
Because the, the, the way in which
you ask it to do something is
determining, you know, the quality of
the output that you get in response.
So, you know, if, if you don't, if
you just have a static prompt and
that's what the large language model
you're interfacing with all the
time, then you get a very similar,
same ish response all the time.
But when it comes to something
as dynamic as, you know, your, a
complex IT infrastructure and the
observability system that you're
trying to build on top of it, the,
the prompting needs to be, adaptable
and dynamic in real time as well.
And really where we're going to see
a lot of the lift off or a lot of
the, the impetus over the next few
years is from agents, AI agents that
can operate autonomously, right?
So you give it a policy, you give it a
set of directions, and then it can take
that and then operate autonomously.
It can modify alert thresholds.
It can, scale your system up and down.
It can, enable traces when it
thinks it's important to do.
It can, it can create service
dependency mapping on its own.
So some of these things might sound a
little bit scary to you that, you know,
if you're, if you're handing off this
to, a non human, what's going to happen?
And, and it's a fair fear
and I understand that.
but as the capability of these models
grow and grow, And of course the models
can do things that humans cannot.
They can, you know, be working on the
problem 24 hours a day, looking through
vaster amounts of data than a human could.
You will start to see that you're
better off with the tools than without.
And we're, we're already
approaching that territory.
Some of you might have already
started using some of these,
automated and autonomous tools
and self healing and so on.
but it's just going to become much
more prevalent, in the future.
And what all of this again means is that
we're, we're living in a new reality.
potential workflows that did
not exist before exist today.
So, you could have a scenario
like this example here, where you
detect a memory leak, the agent
then does a git blame analysis and
understands the, the particular
commit which created the memory leak.
The agent automatically deploys a
rollback decision, and then it, it has
to do an auto scaling adjustment to,
to get the system into the right state.
And all of this could happen
in an automated fashion.
Transcribed And you would just get
a report that this happened, and
this is a very possible workflow.
And you can also see new
KPIs coming out of this.
So X percent of routine incidents
resolved without human intervention
could become a new KPI for,
for SRE teams and DevOps teams.
So it's, it is a new reality.
it's a very interesting
world that, that we live in.
So now that we talked about
this new observability equation.
About data and context and intelligence.
I just want to touch a little bit
about the, the underlying architecture
of the observability stack and why.
you know, at Net Data, we believe
that decentralization is the way
forward, and it's, you know, it's,
it's really not very complicated.
Modern systems are distributed by nature.
Why should we force their
observability to be centralized?
That feels like an artificial limitation
that we're forcing on to a natural system.
There's a lot of different reasons in
which and why centralization fails.
So the minute you bring in centralization,
and by centralization what I mean is,
when you think of your usual observability
platforms, what happens is that you're
collecting logs and metrics and traces
and you're forwarding all of this into
the central data lake or repository.
It might be in somebody's cloud.
You know, you might be self hosting
it yourself, but there's this giant
central repository where everything sits.
Right?
And this creates all kinds of problems.
Now, of course, it becomes a single point
of failure for the entire observability
stack, because if your central store
goes down, you have zero observability.
There's also exponential cost,
that comes from all of this
data movement and storage.
Especially if you're using, you
know, a cloud based provider where
everything is stored on their cloud.
It means that you're not just
paying for their service, but
you're also paying for the egress.
So all of the data leaving your, system
and, you know, getting transmitted to
their cloud is stored on their cloud.
And of course, you're paying
the downstream costs for the
amount of storage that it takes.
Because as systems get complex and
larger, and we're talking about
thousands of services, hundreds of
thousands of nodes, and millions of
metrics, to actually store all of this
centrally is, is a gargantuan task.
And it costs, so it costs
the vendor who is doing it.
It costs you, to pay the vendor
or to self host it yourself.
And it, it quickly becomes a bottleneck.
You also have, cross team
bottlenecks, access control issues
when it comes to centralization.
You know, you know, who do you provide
access to, to this giant central repo?
How, how, how carefully do
you control that access?
you can, you can run into data
sovereignty issues, compliance
headaches, especially if you have multi
region, multi continent operations.
And, Another thing that you will, of
course, see is that your, your query
performance starts to degrade at scale.
And again, this would mean that you
need to make these decisions, right?
Do I need all of this data?
Maybe I need to get rid
of some of the data.
Maybe I need to filter out some
of the data so that I can query
it at a reasonable timeframe
and use it, make it usable.
So decentralization, so if your
architecture is decentralized or
distributed, which means that instead
of storing everything in one single
place, you're storing it all over the
place, and your, your querying is then
intelligent enough to fetch all of it in
real time, solves a lot of these problems.
So this is the way that NetData
has been architected from day one.
And this is one of the reasons
that it allows us to do some of
the things that your traditional
observability platform cannot do.
things like unlimited metrics, per second
granularity, so real time for everything,
and only detection for everything,
while keeping the costs really down.
So, the real world impact of going
distributed, would mean that you can, you
can reduce data transfer costs by up to
90%, you get 65 percent faster mean time
to detection, and, you know, this is,
you know, indirectly happening because
of the distributed architecture, right?
Because, because of the
distributed architecture, you
can have high fidelity data.
And because of the high fidelity
data, you're able to capture the,
you know, the, the right patterns,
tell the right stories with the data.
And that leads to faster mean time to
detection and mean time to resolution.
And of course, this means that,
you know, teams can operate
a lot more independently.
You don't have a single point of failure.
So even if your centralization points
fail, you still have direct access to
the systems and the observability data
originating from those individual nodes.
And you can vastly reduce the
amount of money that you're
spending on network and storage.
And, you know, downstream
the licensing costs as well.
And, you know, you're able to process
the metrics where they originate.
And this becomes important as well,
because As an example, if you're
trying to do anomaly detection, you
know, where are you doing the anomaly
detection becomes important because
you're processing the data, right?
If you're processing it centrally,
you're losing out a little bit on
the context that you had, about
where this metric came from.
Because this, you know, a CPU of 90
percent on one node and CPU on 90
percent on another node could mean two
entirely different things based on the
workloads that are running on them.
So now that we've talked about the
new observability equation and the
underlying architecture, you know, are
you as an organization, as an engineer,
are you ready for the next 10 years?
Right?
So this, this is what's,
what's really important to us.
So for organizations, I, you
know, here are some of the touch
points that I think you should be
thinking about, when it comes to
observability and, the next few years.
You should really focus on
reducing the sampling intervals.
High fidelity data is
super, super important.
So if you can get per second granularity
at scale, you're going to be able to
do so much more with your observability
data that you are doing today.
And this is related, of course.
You should really focus on real time.
So it's, you know, observability
isn't just about historical analysis.
You're not just looking at, you
know, the last X hours or weeks
of data, in a historical fashion,
the data needs to be real time.
You need to be able to see the issues
as they're happening so that you
can take action before it becomes
a problem, not just afterwards.
And ideally you want to democratize
observability across the teams.
You don't want to silo the
observability into just one team, right?
It shouldn't just be, you know,
this is the SRE team and they're
in charge of all observability.
Nobody else needs to look at this data.
Ideally, You know, you should be able
to share that with the developers and
whoever else, you know, management,
whoever needs to see this data, should
have some form of access to the data.
And the, the platform or the tool
that you're using should be usable by
all of these different stakeholders.
You should, As an organization,
invest in AI driven anomaly detection
and automated root cause analysis.
So, really look at if the platform that
you're using today, if you are using
one, offers you these capabilities.
If it doesn't, then it's time to evaluate,
a few tools and platforms that do.
And finally, you know, I would
really recommend implementing a
decentralized observability architecture.
And really think about, how you
can minimize the centralization, in
your, in your system overall going
forward due to, you know, for all
of the reasons that we talked about.
So this was for organizations.
Now let's talk a little bit
about the individuals, right?
For, for the SRE DevOps
professionals of today.
What are the things that
you should be doing?
So of course you should be mastering
cloud native observability and AI ops.
I don't think I need to tell anybody this.
People are already
doing this on their own.
I think you should start thinking
beyond, basic infrastructure as
code to, to policy as code, to
security as code practices as well.
it would be really good if you can develop
expertise in causal analysis and real
time analytics, because this allows you
to tell those better stories, right?
So you can actually.
this is a skill that you can develop.
You can, you can try to tell
better cause and effect stories.
So here's what you see, here's,
you know, what could have cost it.
And then being able to present that
either through a dashboard, through a
report, through, through a tool, you
know, it, it gives you a lot of power
when, when you can tell the right stories.
you should develop multi cloud and
edge computing skills, because like we
discussed, as, as the workloads become
more complex, as the data center explosion
happens, you're, you're not going to
have your entire workload running on a
single system, on, on a single cloud.
It, it's going to be spread out, and
you need to be able to, understand
different systems and different scales.
And finally, I think it would be, very
useful for you, for your career in
general, if you can gain expertise working
with and orchestrating AI agents, right?
So, get, get familiar with with
AI in general, with AI agents, get
comfortable with them, understand
their intricacies, understand what
they're good at, what they're bad at,
understand the scenarios where they fail.
And doing that will give you a big
head start, in, in the next decade.
So I hope that, this is, useful
advice for both organizations and for
individuals, and that, you'll be able to
do great things, with this information.
So that's, you know, that's about the,
the, the guidance that, that I would
provide for the next 10 years and, and
to leave you with, with a quote, that I
made up just now, I think that future SREs
will manage a hundred times more services.
But they'll be doing it, with 10
times less manual intervention.
So there will be a lot more work
for SREs, but that work, will be,
less manual burdens involved, right?
So finally to wrap up, it's
time to go back to the future.
there's, there's this quote that I really
like, I really enjoy, from William Gibson.
It says, the future is already here.
It's just not evenly distributed yet.
And I think this is really true, about a
lot of the things that we talked about.
That some of these capabilities, some
of these tools are already here, but
everybody is not aware about them.
Everybody is not using them.
So there's, there's pockets of space,
in the industry where, where, you know,
people are aware they are using them and
they're miles ahead because of this fact.
So, as, as my final, statement as part
of the talk, I would, I would like to
tell that you should not wait until
your monitoring tools are obsolete.
You should not wait until your
dashboards are, you know, either
peddling lies or half truths.
You should not wait until your
teams are drowning in alerts.
And you definitely don't want to wait
until your systems are too complex
for humans to manage them alone.
The tools of tomorrow are here today.
Use them.
So embrace high fidelity, real time data.
Don't settle for less.
Use AI agents.
Get comfortable with them.
Let the machines do what humans cannot
or don't want or should not be doing.
Go distributed.
True fidelity in your data demands
decentralized architecture.
And then finally, demand insights from
your observability stack, from your
observability platform, not just more
charge, more dashboards, and more noise.
Don't settle.
Thank you.
thanks for listening to the talk.
like I said at the start, if
you'd like to find out more about
NetData to the company, you can
visit our website at netdata.
cloud.
You can also check out our GitHub You
can just search for NetData on GitHub.
And if you have any questions
about the talk, I'd be more than
happy to discuss it with you.
Here's my email.
You can find me on LinkedIn.
And you can also find me on Substack,
where again, I talk a little bit about
the future, what's in store for us.
Thank you.
Thanks again.
Bye.