Generative AI is like a groundbreaking
technology, capable of like creating
new content, solving problems,
and also automating the processes.
So today, like, we'll focus on its
application in cloud native DevOps, a
methodology combining the scalability
of cloud native principles with the
agility of like DevOps practices.
So to set the expectations
throughout this talk, I'll
highlight like real world use cases.
Key benefits and challenges along with
like practical advice for integrating
AI into your DevOps pipeline.
And also, but first like, let's
define like what a Gen AI really is.
So what is like Gen AI?
Like Gen AI refers to models like GPT
and DAL E that can create new outputs,
such as text, images, and even code by
learning the patterns from existing data.
Okay.
So to give like real
life, examples, right?
So chat GPT assets with the NLP tasks,
like natural language for tasks and with
also with the GitHub, Copilot generates
code and Dali creates like images.
So these tools are not just, tools.
They are like enablers of great
productivity and creativity
in the tech workflows.
So to highlight like relevance to
the topic on the DevOps, right,
like in depth, like in DevOps,
generally, so Genii can streamline
workflows, improving the collaboration
and reducing the manual effort.
which leads us to why it's gaining
traction in modern development.
And when it comes to the transition
before, like we deep dive into the
applications, let's explore the challenges
in the modern, software development that
generates like AI that helps to address.
So let me go to the next slide and
let's talk about the challenges.
So like what, what are the
challenges in like DevOps, you
know, software development, right?
So let's go deep dive into this.
So.
So firstly, like let's say rapidly
evolving technologies make it difficult
for developers to stay up to date, right?
So Genii can help bridge that gap
by offering context, you know,
assistance and also recommendations.
And, also like secondly, let's talk
about like increasing complexity
of applications requires more
sophisticated tools to manage code
and infrastructure effectively.
AI provides automation and error reduction
and, on the next, let's talk about like
shorter development cycles, place pressure
on the teams to deliver faster pace.
So, so AI can accelerate testing
and deployment giving teams
like the breaking room, right?
So, and like finally security
and compliance concerns
are growing as we all know.
Gen AI can proactively identify
the vulnerabilities and ensure
adherence to evolving regulations.
So how do we integrate like,
Gen AI into DevOps effectively?
So let's, let's define a foundation
of like how, native DevOps.
So if I go to next slide.
Okay.
So let's go to the, like defining
cloud native DevOps, right?
So.
Cloud native DevOps emphasizes
applications designed for the cloud,
scalable, resilient, and leveraging
the microservices architecture.
So if we talk about the DevOps practices,
DevOps integrates It's planning, coding,
deploying, testing, and also monitoring
into the unified automated pipeline,
fostering, the collaboration across teams.
So to highlight, like, the synergy, right?
So combining these principles
with AI creates like an ecosystem.
where applications are not
only effective but also like
adaptive to evolving demands.
So now let's see like how AI bridges
the gap into the ecosystem, right?
So, okay, So let's go and talk about
like see how AI can bridge the gap
like integrating with DevOps, so
let's break down the benefits, right?
The first, firstly, AI automate the
repetitive tasks, as you all know,
like freeing up the developers to focus
on strategic and high value content.
Like, let's say if developers are, you
know, writing code for the business
development, they can actually focus.
on, the business logic instead of,
like, you know, trying to figure
anything out, like DevOps stuff,
like, deploying, you know, the CI CD
pipelines and configuring and et cetera.
And also it improves the, you know,
efficiency and also by reducing errors
and accepting, accelerating the workflows.
And accepting like the
income of, of that, right?
So, and also AI provides insights
from data, enhancing the application,
performance, and also the security.
So most importantly, it helps
organizations adapt to changing technology
landscapes seamlessly without no issues.
And also to talk about the real world
impact, many organizations already report,
you know, shorter development cycles and
better scalability with AI driven DevOps.
DevOps.
And let's dig deeper into like specific
AI capabilities into DevOps cycle and,
starting with like code generation.
So let's talk about like how, AI
can, you know, generate or help
the automating the code generation.
So AI powered tools, like
we all know, Copilot, right?
So GitHub Copilot assist.
with code complexion saving developers
hours of manual work and AI can
generate entire code blocks or
functions from simple prompts to
reducing repetitive tasks over and
over and code factoring tools like,
analyze existing code to suggest the
improvements, ensuring the better
readability and also the performance.
So to talk about, like, the impact,
these features help, like, reduce
the technical depth and also
accelerate the delivery timelines.
And also, let's talk about the transition.
So beyond coding, AI can optimize
this continuous integration and also
the continuous, delivery pipelines.
So let's talk about, like,
how, AI can actually help in
like enhancing CICD, pipelines.
So the key improvements
in this area, right?
So automated testing generates by
AI ensures broader test coverage
and also the faster bug detection.
This is one of the key improvements
that AI can help within the CICD world.
And also like AI powered deployments
tools like Analyze, right?
Performance data to recommend optimal
like strategies for scaling and deployment
and predictive maintenance is also like
one of another area that we can improve
with AI, like predictive maintenance,
monitor systems to identify and address
issues before it actually happens and to
also like, let's, let's also in explore
how AI role in like enhancing security.
Because as we all know, like
security is the key and also, for
any development like nowadays, right?
So let's talk about how we can improve
security and vulnerability detection.
So let's say, let's discuss about the,
security enhancements, for example.
So AI detects unusual patterns
in network trafficking, right?
And, enables faster responses
to potential threats.
So vulnerability assessment tools
scan code and suggest patches,
reducing the risk of breaches.
And other example is like security
policy, you know, and enforcement
ensures compliance by automating and
mitigating the risky configurations.
So now let's take a look up
like how AI can optimizes
resource allocation and scaling.
So to talk about that, let me go.
Yeah.
To talk about like how AI
can really help in optimizing
resource allocation and scaling.
So one of the key areas here is the AI
can predict resources based upon the
historical data of the application and
also optimizing cost and performance.
It enables, like, dynamic scaling
and also ensures applications
respond to real time demands.
And cost management, insights
help organizations minimize
the cost expenditure while
maintaining the efficiency.
And, also, like, like we discussed,
like, AI can also help in enhancing,
the observability and monitor.
Let's deep dive into how AI can
help in, in the monitoring, and
also the observability world.
So one of the couple of common
features that AI monitors application
performance, detecting the bottlenecks
and suggesting improvements.
It identifies the anomalies, alerting
teams to issues like early on,
like before it actually occurs,
and also it can help, giving like
a RCA, that root cause analysis.
Speeds up the troubleshooting
that using the downtime.
And also one other example is like, if
you want to have like an RCA for your
application, like if you had like a
production outage and you don't have to
sit and write the whole RCA, and if you
have like a tools, like AI, where it has
the ability to monitor your application.
It can actually provide you like
insights based upon the outage.
And also like lastly, not lastly,
I think let's discuss about, how AI
can help like, streamlining testing
and also, quality insurance, right?
So AI generates like test cases for
ensuring comprehensive coverage.
It also automates test
execution, providing faster
feedback and also saving time.
Predictive, quality analysis,
identifies potential issues
before they affect production.
And, and also let's talk about, like, how,
like, you know, we can collaborate and
also ethical consideration in AI adoption.
So, overall, like, ethical and
governance considerations, like,
these are the key areas, right?
Because the data privacy and also the
fairness and the transparency is one
of the key areas we have to maintain
for the governance considerations.
So, in talking about the data
privacy, ensuring data is responsibly
handled to comply with regulations.
And also, we have to mitigate the AI
basis to avoid discriminatory practices.
And also, we have to build
the AI models to foster trust
and also the accountability.
And also, let's talk about
like, how the future of the AI
powered cloud native DevOps.
So, AI will continue to drive
greater automation, efficiency,
and innovation in DevOps.
Thanks.
So organizations that adopt these
technologies will gain a comprehensive
edge in the rapidly evolving landscape.
So, and I would like to, thank you
all for your attention and I'm happy
to answer any questions or deep dive
into like any of the topics we covered.
Thank you all.