Speaker 15: Hello everyone.
My name is even Sen and today I wanted
to talk to you about designing a r
intensive architecture for systems
with high data throughout output.
Let's think about terminology first.
What you see here is a golden standard
for modern lead intensive architecture.
It's what you'll find in almost any
big tech stacks Kubernetes, where ports
are moving constantly and microservices
where logic is the coate into domains.
It's great for developer but it
puts a heavy tax on the network and
charted and replicated storages.
Caches and persistent license.
Design it for fault tolerance.
In theory, this scales linearly.
If you need more just throw more
pots or knots at the cluster
and allow to medium load.
This works like a charm.
But the magic disappears.
One, you cross the thousand
North, north threshold.
That beautiful architecture
diagram turns into source of pain.
We hit a wall of system issues like.
Tail latencies or protocol entropy,
high contention and topology drifts.
Let's discuss them.
On large scale mean latency
does matter and fight a tail.
Look at the fanau pattern on the ride.
To solve single query search your
service might pull 50 database charts.
This is where slowest link rule kicks in.
Your total response time is dedicated by
the slowest chart in a bunch at scale.
Those rare anomalies become
your daily statistical reality.
Scalability isn't free.
There is a tax you paid.
Just keeps the light on.
Orchestration.
A counter plane and serial
discovery generate a massive event.
Term.
CPU Overhead of every note must track
in neighbors protocols like gossip.
Starts eating significant apart
of CPU cycles, network noise
and management traffic checks
lead directions gross non-line.
It eventually start competing
with actual user traffic.
You might add 20% more hardware
and get only five percent.
Of performance boost
this attacks in action.
Let's look at the math of resort death.
Imagine an application pots and m
and cash pos in starting set type.
Every port opens connection
pool to every cash.
No, with 1000 application ports and 100.
Cash notes.
You suddenly have 100
thousands open connections.
This exhausts a file descriptor and create
massive connection for top of rack switch.
This system literally shocks itself.
This is the most critical chart for SRE.
The latency was throughout procure.
There are three zone, A linear zone.
When load is low.
Latency is stable.
A point of inflation where queue
queues start form latency shift
from Lanier to exponential.
And a saturation zone.
This is a blessed zone where
we heat the throughout ceiling.
Any tiny increase of flood
Causes a catastrophical latency spikes.
Our job is to keep the system in
a linear zone with enough safety
margin to absorb traffic spikes.
When throwing hardware to the
problem stops working, we use
architectural painkillers like graceful
degradation circuit breakers, soft
amounts, and reading stale data.
Yes, we just don't wait for
our throttle resources forever.
If the database.
Doesn't respond within 20 milliseconds,
just kills the connection.
It's better to serve a partial
response than a full response.
Never.
Once the painkillers are in the
place, we move to a physical
segmentation multi AZ or Zal isation.
The concept is simple.
We duplicate the entire.
Stack across individual
availability zones.
Each zone gets its own microservices
load balance, cash layers, and databases.
The goal is a total fault is a lesion.
If one zone goes down, the others don't.
And the price is infrastructure overhead.
You're paying for triple set of resources
and a complex data synchronization.
At this point, your
dashboard might look great.
Multi disease rion, circuit
breakers are turned.
The system seems stable.
But don't default.
This is illusion of stability.
We have mask the symptoms, but
we haven't cured the disease.
Our painkillers helped us survive
the day, but they didn't affect the
underlying inefficient to truly scale.
We need to stop fighting side effects
and start rethinking our services.
Our how our service handle
data at the lowest level.
To move the needle on performance, we
need to look inside the black boxes.
In typical grid intensive
systems resources leak in
a three zones protection.
We burn CPU cycle processing in official.
Format months.
The runtime spent more time digitalizing
objects than executing a business.
Logic.
A transfer a network is
our toughest bottleneck.
We, we waste bandwidth on redundant key
and metadata repeated in every single.
Request and the storage how data
sits in, in, in memory dedicates
its IO and RAM consumption.
Reading an entire row just
to get one column is luxury.
We can't afford.
We need to make our data smarter and
more efficient in all three states.
In highlights data formats aren't
a matter of developer convenience.
They are resources entry ticket for
your CPU and ram, how you pick your
bytes data minds, how much actual
work your processes can handle.
Core.
Our core optimizing
levels are bin over text.
Moving your data from human readable
formats eliminate overhead of par systems
syntax, and drastically shrinks payload.
Zero copy access utilizing the structures
that doesn't require sterilization.
By mapping data directly to memory,
we bypass the CPU tax of creation and
eliminate a garbage collection pressure
physically skipping unnecessary bite.
If you only need three fields
out of 100, the system should.
Mon sorry.
Saving this KO Network, bandwidth
and memory stripping s schemas
and field needs from message body.
By using Center Central Registry,
the Y occurs only the data,
Optimizing data isn't just about saving
space, is about reclaiming CPU cycles
from infrastructure to power your
logic, to power your business logic.
Clean code and elegant.
Abstractions are great but the hardware
doesn't see them at higher scale.
Your CPU only cares about
data collect and cache.
Efficiency grouping data into ETF
object is develop friendly, but it often
result in polluted cache lines forcing
the CPU and load unnecessary bytes.
Mal Lightning.
That layout with the CPU physical
architecture can eliminate caius and
unlock hardware through processing speed.
There's not a silver bullet.
One pattern might excel
and a random as well.
Another dominates in a stream procession
don't default toward standard.
Profile measure and choose layout
that fits your specific max pattern.
We are shifting from bite level
optimization to high level architecture.
When your rate load hits a
wall, stop using the same
data models in every process.
It's time for CQS.
The principle simple prepare
data for task in advance.
We take a single source of
truth and generate a projection
tailored for specific processes.
Each projection contains only the
field and format require by customer,
no blood, no overhead, so the format.
A set the structures ready.
Now we must move the data as
close to the customer as possible.
We are shifting from an external cache
to cache directly within the memory.
So the benefits are zero network
latency in process memory.
Access is measured in
nanoseconds, not in milliseconds.
And resource efficiency, we
flowed a shattered cached cluster.
The but the challenge is if your
cash everything, the port will
run out of memory instantly.
So that type of question is useless.
Without Smart r we transform
our ports into from identical
copies into specialized data.
Shark, we achieve this.
We are three mechanism, a service
discovery, a real time tracking of exact.
Clustered topology.
A clean side balancing is a clean
celiac is the target node eliminated.
Unnecessary network hubs
and a consistent mechanism.
A consistent hash to choose a right
po it guarantees that a request
of specific my D always lands.
On the same note, this
create data locality.
Each pot stores only its
unique slice of the global data
and a final touch.
The different formats in
different storage tires.
What work on a disc.
Is often poison In A CPU we prioritize
storage based on the environment.
External storage is like
noise scale or L 2K.
The priority are compactness
and backward compatibility.
We optimize for transfer
sites and storage volume.
In process ces here we
fight for every C cycle.
We use large, specific language formats
native to your machine and runtime.
We use structures at all
that I'm allowed direct.
Field access without passing.
For example use flood buffers for
transport but transforms them into
native object upon internal support.
For instance, zero decoder access.
It is the bottom line of this architecture
marathon economics versus risk.
When classic set up, 100% of
request hit the external caches.
In our target architecture, 85%
is settled in the local cache, and
only 1% ever reaches the databases.
This delivers massive resource efficiency.
You need.
A significantly fewer service and
drastically cut your AZ traffic costs.
But on the other hand, there is
there is a com very complex system
with trading simplicity for density.
The system is harder
to maintain and impact.
Unpacking the hardware and reduces
your safety margin and urine
anomalies out scale and monitoring
now requires surgical precision.
Yes, the system is complex.
Every layer we discuss introduces
new protocols and design risks.
But this complexity unlock the data
density and performance that are simply
impossible in a standard hardware.
So this architecture is a balance
between survival and complex.
Before implementing this solution ensure
you're fighting the physical limits of
hardware and not just suboptimal code.
Thank you.
I.