Hello everyone.
My name is Oriaki Victor Nsakai.
I'm a design engineer by profession.
today I'll be talking about,
securing embedded systems in
IoT, a practical DevOps approach.
Now let's dive right into it.
firstly, I'm going to talk
about, I'm going to talk about
what is IoT on embedded systems.
then I'm going to talk about
security challenges with them.
Then we'll move on to the role of
DevOps in securing embedded systems.
And we'll talk about securing
the development, life cycle.
And so we'll talk about, securing
post deployment IoT devices,
balancing innovation, securely.
And lastly, we'll talk about the best
practices for securing these, embedded
devices, practical take home, take homes.
Now, what are these embedded, devices?
Now, these embedded devices, they
are like the brain behind what modern
robotics and IoT applications do.
they work silently to perform
specific tasks within larger systems.
they are like the brain, behind this, this
modern technology, these smart systems.
Yeah, they find applications
in, in headscale sector, in the
manufacturing sector, even critical
infrastructures like the railway
systems, power grids, smart grids.
this IoT, device is expected to grow to
over 25 billion users by the year 2020.
Now, we've talked about embedded,
so now let's talk about IoT.
IoT refers to a network of interconnected
physical devices embedded with sensors,
software, and other technologies that
enable them to collect, exchange,
and add on data over the internet.
basically, this is IOT, system, they
collect data, they exchange the data, and
they add on this data over the Internet.
for example, in the healthcare sector,
these IOT, embedded devices could be used
to, monitor and track a patient's health.
in my patient sector, it could be used to,
to manipulate robots, to be used for the
supply chain to check the movement of, the
movement of, goods from one, production
cycle or production, desk to nest.
because we use, it can be applied, be
used in our homes to control thermostats.
control some devices in our home.
So these devices are widely
used in various industries.
Now, what are the security
challenges with these devices?
we have, different levels, from the
hardware level risk we have, where
attackers can be exploited, by trying
to physically tamper with these devices.
for example, an IOT embedded
camera can be, an IOT embedded
camera can be, tampered with.
a circuit could be plugged into
it and, sensitive data could be
exploited or gained from this, device.
Also, we have the firmware
and software vulnerabilities,
things like updated firmware.
software, weak encryption, if not
properly, secured, or if not properly,
if not regularly updated, it's going to
be exploited by these cyber attackers.
also we have the communication
protocol weaknesses.
These IoT embedded devices, they rely
heavily on, communication protocols
like the Wi Fi and Bluetooth.
So if not properly secured.
It could be, intercepted
by this cyber attackers.
Now, what's the role from DevOps
in security and business systems?
Now we're talking about security
and we want to talk about how
DevOps could be used to secure
these devices on these systems.
So DevOps is, a combination of,
a combination of development and
operations through automation.
so with DevOps, we can ensure
software is prepared and,
deliver efficiently and securely.
Also applying these DevOps principles
to embedded systems can help improve
security, agility, and automation.
Now let's talk about benefits.
So some of the benefits include
the real time detection of
security vulnerabilities.
So with DevOps, we could
continuously monitor these systems.
So vulnerabilities have been exploited.
Also, we have automated security
testing to ensure security validation
is part of the CICD pipeline.
so an example could be, we could
use automated testing tools to,
automated testing tools in DevOps.
Pipelines to simulate, attacks
on these IOT devices to find
vulnerabilities even before deployment.
So, lastly, the another benefit
of this, this another benefit of
DevOps in, in securing embedded
systems is faster issue resolution.
So this, because it's an automated
process, it's, it responds
fast and it detects, this.
vulnerability flows, on time
through this automated processes.
Now securing the development life cycle.
Now we need to, we need to secure these
devices from the design stage, not
after deployment or during maintenance.
So we could use, We could
use, communications that are
encrypted, like the TLS protocol.
We could also use, secure booting
methods, to ensure that, only trusted
software, ensure these devices
start with only trusted, software.
Also, we could use, the trusted platform
modules to protect hardware integrity.
All right.
We could secure this, design to get
the design of this embedded systems
during the development lifecycle is
by ensuring security is validated
at every stage of the process.
So from the design to the deployments
to demand, you want your methodology.
Maintainers, excuse me, even during
maintainers we could, we could secure
this, the design of these systems.
Now, even after, after the design
phase of this embedded system, we
also need to continuously monitor
them for unusual activities.
So we could use, things like the
log and alert systems, thereby,
permitted, automated alerts for
potential security breaches.
So whenever there is a
breach we are alerted.
Also we could use a patch management
method whereby we are whereby there's
regular firmware software updates
to patch these vulnerabilities.
Also this can be done remotely.
It doesn't necessarily need
to be to involve a human or
have a physical intervention.
I want to talk about, balancing
the vision of security.
So while there's an increase in the
use of these devices, like I said, they
are applied in various industries from
the healthcare sector to manufacturing
sector to critical infrastructures.
we need to also increase the
security of these devices.
like I said, there's an estimated growth
of these devices to, to increase to
over 25 billion users by the year 2030.
So ensuring these devices
are safe is very important.
So why is it important
we secure these devices?
So firstly, when we, when we, put, when
we include security features in the design
of this, Embedded IoT devices from the
design phase to the deployment phase.
Even during maintenance, we
want to continuously ensure
these devices are safe.
They tend to be more trusted
and adopted by the users.
nobody wants to be exploited.
So when these devices are safe, we have
more people wanting to use them, wanting
to buy them, wanting to adopt them.
This also further, leads to,
open opportunities to new
applications and markets.
So there's an increase in marketability
of these, devices because they
are safe and they're trusted.
They are not easily
exploited by cyber attackers.
So by this, we've also increased
the scalability of these, devices.
Now, what are the best practices for
securing these embedded IoT systems?
firstly, we need to ensure this,
security is, embedded at each stage
of this development life cycle from
the design phase to the deployment to
post deployment to maintenance stage.
So we need to continuously conduct
regular threat modeling and risk
assessments at every given time of this
development stage, the development cycle.
Also, we should ensure we use, secure
communication protocols the HTTPS
and TLS, other secure protocols.
Then, we should try and integrate
security testing into our CI CD pipeline
for faster vulnerability detection.
like we said, DevOps responds fast.
It detects, Threats and vulnerabilities
early, so we should try and, while
implementing this DevOps approach to
securing this embedded IoT system,
we should try and integrate security
testing into our CID pipelines for
faster vulnerability detection.
lastly, we should develop clear
actionable protocols for responding
to this, to security incidents.
So by also doing this, practice, we
could secure our embedded IoT systems.
Now, what are the key takeaways
for designers, for systems
engineers, for, DevOps, engineers
as well, or professionals?
So the first one is we
should embed security early.
So from the design phase to development
phase, we should Try and embed the
security early to mitigate this risk.
Also, we should implement continuous
integration and continuous delivery,
practices for hardware security.
Then we could use, the regular
monitor and patch devices, after
deployment to maintain security.
So even after we've done that.
After the deployment, we should
also regularly monitor our partial
devices for vulnerabilities.
Then, lastly, we should continuously
adopt these, security, strategies,
continuously try and, come up with
ideas, innovative ideas to drive
greater use, user trust of this event.
Like I said, while there's an increase
in the use of these devices, we
need to, increase the, We need to
increase the trust of you to increase
security, thereby gaining greater
user trust and diverse scalability.
So as I conclude today, why there
is an increase in the use of
this IoT and embedded systems.
We need to, try and use the DevOps
approach to, increase our security
as DevOps tends to, tends to
automate its response to attacks.
I've also run over this early.
It's something with a response fast, by
applying this DevOps approach, we thereby,
prioritize security and build trust.
We also drive scalability and
ensure a safer future for everyone.
Thank you.