Speaker 40: Hi everyone, and
welcome to this presentation.
I'm gonna talk about how AI is
redefining SRE and customer experience.
And this talk isn't about replacing SREs
or changing, the next AI hype cycle.
It's about how reliability work
is changing and why customer
experience is now tightly
connected to how we run production.
Everything else here today comes
from being on call and running real
production systems and building no
fire while Watson AI dramatically
increased the pace of a change.
And lastly, this presentations,
I'm pretty sure that is gonna be
totally different in a year from now.
I spent over a decade building and
operating production systems that
changed faster than their documentation.
I've been the person that people DM
at 3:00 AM because you know how this
really works when you're on call.
And that experience led me here,
not because tooling was bad, but
because context kept disappearing.
So let's start with reality, not
with just an architecture diagram.
We wish we were through, let's see, the
world engineers actually living today.
And this is not a critique,
it's a recognition.
Most of our work doesn't
happen in clean abstractions.
It happens in exceptions edge
kcs and half known systems.
And that reality has shifted
dramatically in the last, two years.
This used to be hard.
It's not something new.
I think now it's something totally
different, especially with all this
AI generated code and vibe coding.
We fish, we, we seep faster than ever.
So the production changes constantly.
Reliability didn't get harder
because teams got worse.
It got harder because teams grow system
now change faster than the humans can
really build up a stable mental model.
It's not that AI created this, right?
It just accelerated this because
right now, as I mentioned, we
see faster than ever and when the
systems outpace, understanding the
first thing that breaks isn't only
the uptime, it's also the clarity.
If you see this diagram, this is what
a production actually looks like today
and most of the years in the past.
At the bottom we have a couple of
services and systems, which is,
mostly our production environment.
Code infrastructure, telemetry
tools knowledge, different
kind of various places.
On top of this, there is a couple of
workflows like releases, incidents,
security, cost, and we have also the teams
each of them owning a piece of, of of a
slice, but not knowing the whole, right?
Not nobody understands the
full production system.
So no single person really sees
and understands all this at once.
Yeah, every incident, cut across
boundaries that were designed to work
together, and each handoff loses context.
This is where most reliability,
pain actually lives between underst
lives, not in one service, not
in one dashboard, in the gaps.
And it's obvious that we don't
like data, we don't like tools.
If you see the diagram, we lack a common
and a certain understanding and meaning.
Of how these changes turned into outcomes.
The systems are connected teams
are divided and production
live somewhere in between.
And when engineers struggle to navigate
this customers fill this immediately.
Engineers, engineers struggle and because
of that, incidents take hours or days.
Customers wait and stand wondering if
they can really rely on us next time.
It impacts revenue and our reputation.
Customer report these issues first, right?
We learn something is broken
from a support ticket, not
from our systems or to link.
Engineers become single points of failure.
A few people carry, the full
knowledge of a production environment.
They're burned out.
Or they leave and not only
when they leave, they get this
knowledge together, right?
So lots of people, they have
no idea what's happening.
Customer experience is no longer
separate from reliability.
What customers feel is the external
result of an internal confusion.
And the problem isn't that engineers
don't care is that systems don't
really remember, even when people do
every investigation starts from zero.
Because contact doesn't survive
change, which led to the
fixes we've all tried, right?
More processes, more tooling than others.
We'll discuss this.
So we try to fix that, right?
What we, and we're trying
to do the ob obvious things.
The first instinct is visibility.
So what we do, we add more dashboards,
more metrics, more alerts, but
visibility without structure
just increases the mental load.
We didn't reduce uncertainty, we
multiplied, so we moved from more
data to smarter looking data.
And we taught systems because of
this, to find patterns, right?
But patterns without the real cause.
Don't tell you what changed.
Correlation helps you react fast, right?
That's a correlation trap.
It doesn't help you understand why this
bloke, this incident, happened this time.
And when that, that still didn't
work, we did a, another trap, right?
It's what I call the tooling trap.
We added more tools.
Every new problem, got a new
tool or a new workflow or a
new processes or a new policy.
So now we have also AI tools.
You have more AI tools to do a
couple of other things, and each tool
sold a slice, but added handoffs.
Ownership gaps and context loss,
the system became operatable,
but not understandable.
So the question isn't
how do we react faster?
It's how we keep up, in a constant change
of a production, which is happening
in a tremendous speed at this moment.
And today.
AI didn't just help us, to do
the same work faster, right?
So things has changed for many ways.
It changed what system
can do at all, right?
Until recently, systems mostly
emitted, row signals, numbers of
logs, traces, commits, deployments.
There's a lot of fragments here, right?
With modern ai.
There's a shift.
Understanding doesn't have to
be reconstructed later, right?
It can exist earlier, it can be
persist right close to where the
production is actually operating.
So this is a move from raw signals
to certain meaning from isolated
metrics to system awareness, and
from reconstruction after the
fact to recognition in the moment.
It, it changed, where and how
understanding lives in what form.
And once understanding moves
closers to the production and
to your systems, it completely
changes how we respond for years.
The main question we've asked
during incidence symbol, what broke?
Is it disservice?
Is it the node?
What is it?
That question assumes failures
is a starting point, but when
you can track systems over time,
you can ask a better question.
Not just what broke, but what change
and what did that change affect.
This is the difference between reacting
symptoms and understanding code.
To do that, we need to follow systems.
That way they actually evolve, right?
How your production is operating
consistently and continuously.
So production doesn't fail in
isolation, production is changing.
There's configs code, service
dependencies, new infrastructure, traffic
changes, and those changes can rip.
So the view you see here is.
How connects these three things
continuously from what changed,
where it landed, what is the
current state of the behavior.
So instead of treating every incident
as a one off, the system keeps
our running, understanding every
incident adds knowledge instead of
wiping the slate clean and that.
Mother matters a lot before
something breaks, right?
So there is a persistent
understanding across time.
Antifa system continuously
understands what changed, where it
landed, and how behavior shifted.
The reliability doesn't
start at the alert.
It starts before the
incident even exists, right?
The ability decisions happen before
anything breaks while I'm coding.
So history stops being something
we look back on or we are
just have a few people, right?
It becomes something you used
to decide what to do next.
This isn't about, predicting
the future perfectly.
It's about not being blind to risk.
We've already seen before,
and this is foresight.
Grounded in how production
actually behaves over time.
And once you have that reliability
moves to a very different place.
This is reliability embedded directly into
the workflow of how we work every day.
Before code sips, the system already
understands what changed, what
depends on it, what is going to
change and what's already unstable.
So engineers don't need
to remember everything.
The system brings the context to them
and, automatically a deployment happens,
triggers a deployment analysis on every
PR because incidents don't be keen.
The deploy time, they definitely
don't be begin at the alert time.
So you have reliability, not
after users feel the pain.
And this isn't just incident data,
it's how the service normally behaves.
It's how often it change what actually
goes wrong after those changes?
It's like a validation based on
the change we're gonna, we're gonna
apply and that history is always
there, even when the team changes.
And once you have that memory
availability, steps being
stops, being a moment in time.
And reliability, traditionally
used to live in best, right?
We were deploying, there was an
incident, we had a postmortem,
we had, tasks after that.
We have already forgotten, after
a few months what happened.
But now with, all these context graphs
and the advancements of ai, you can
spot risky changes when you code so you
can understand the impact of attains.
Early on when you really actually doing
coding in your ID find the real cause when
there is an incident and now it starts
becoming also a continuous loop, right?
Every change, every incident,
every outcome adds to understanding
as a continuous feedback loop.
And this is where, where we call
this a full context embedded des
and this is where the things are
moving the next couple of years.
Everything I described so far might,
sound familiar to most of you.
And we have all of us tried,
better dashboards, better
alerts, better runbooks.
So what's actually different this time?
The system right now can drag
change and this change, as I
mentioned, can have, right?
Can have a certain meaning.
Can have, can present the system.
Awareness can also not only present
the system awareness, but also,
reconstruct it later from the
context you have already captured.
And these are not snapshots on, not point
in time metrics, but how code config,
dependencies, deployments, signals
telemetry evolve through the time.
Second.
Right now we can inter, we can connect
these to a cause and effect relationships.
So not just these things move together,
but these change led to that outcome.
And third, as we discussed earlier,
we can keep learning between
different kind of incidents, between
different kind of architectural
documents, between our collaboration
in different kinds of places.
How work in communication platforms.
So there's no reset
button after a postmortem.
Now what The system learn sticks.
There's no hero X, no, starting from
zero 3:00 AM there's no reset button.
And when systems stop forgetting the
impact isn't just internal for customers.
This shows up in various ways, right?
Few surprises because right now, so
there's a lot of benefits, right?
There is a few surprises to the customer.
Because risky changes are caught earlier.
Faster recovery right now because
engineers aren't guessing.
They're acting in a full context
and in a behavior over time.
More confidence, in more predictable
changes and releases and deployments
because reliability isn't like anymore.
It's informed decision making and
where reliability improves, right?
Customer experience follows and
not as a downstream metric, right?
But as a direct result and
impact to our business.
And that shift also changes what
it means to be an engineer anymore.
With all these a advancements
of ai, this is where the human
impact really shows up, right?
Engineers right now,
stop chasing symptoms.
And start shaping out outcomes
because they stop paying, WAC
playing guacamole with alerts.
Instead, they start shaping outcomes,
as I mentioned, deciding when to see,
deciding when to wait, decide how risks
should be managed before users fill it
and the system can carry this memory.
So engineers can focus on
adjustment, not just recall.
And this leads to very different future
for SRE and for everyone in the industry.
And for observability in general.
For a long time, we've optimized SRE
for speed, faster detection, faster
response, faster root cause analysis, but
speed alone doesn't reduce risk, right?
Understanding does.
The future of SRE isn't
just faster reaction.
It's be better decision much more
early in the process before we
deploy, before there is an escalation
before customers feel the pain.
And that's a shift we are building toward.
I leave you with this idea.
Reliability doesn't live
in alerts, that's for sure.
It lives in understanding how
production change over time and when
systems, especially with ai, remember.
Teams move faster with less fear and
customers really feel the difference.
Thank you.