Speaker 22: Hello Con 42 attendees.
Welcome to my talk on Guardrails.
First, a framework for designing
safe, scalable, and accountable
AI agents for security operations.
Let's dive right in.
The first thing you may be wondering
is why do I care about security
operations as a DevOps person?
And let me assure you, and I'm willing
to bet money on this, is that your
security operations colleagues will
come to you seeking your help to build,
deploy AI agents literally this year.
And when that happens, my hope
is by spending the next 30 or so
minutes with me, you'll find yourself
much better equipped to help them
and your organization succeed
with AI in security operations.
What qualifies me as a
presenter on this topic.
First off, I have over five years
of experience across the leading
security operations companies, building
solutions for practitioners Proofpoint,
Zscaler, Splunk, and Cisco are just
some of the names that I've worked at.
Secondly, I talk to over 150 security
operations teams every single year
of all shapes and sizes, including
large Fortune 500 organizations
with mature practices, as well as
organizations that are literally
building a SOC for the first time.
I know a thing or two
about security operations.
Now, the thing with security operations
is even before Gen AI happened,
there were massive challenges.
Teams were faced with alert, fatigue,
tools, sprawl, and there was a widening
skill shortage where there were so
many jobs with not enough skilled
people to be able to man these posts
needed to keep organizations secure.
And then gen AI happened
in 2022, making this all.
Even worse because AI made it easy for
attackers to launch attacks faster, scale
them better, and also lowered the skill
required to be able to make to be able
to launch really massive attacks, right?
And that, that basically made the
challenge for security operations terms,
which was already a very bad situation.
Even more worse.
The good news though, or the slight silver
lining is ai and AI agents in particular
also present a possible solution, and
in my mind, are an absolute necessity
for SOC teams to be able to keep up
with the increased demands off of them.
So AI presents a massive opportunity.
But the challenge with security operations
or just security in general is you are
paid to be right every single time.
And LLMs that are non-deterministic have
high amounts of variability and could be
wrong at times are really not a recipe
for success in security operations.
So how do we actually realize this
opportunity despite all of the
difficulties and challenges and.
There are two, two broad set of
options but really it's buy or build.
I don't think I, I don't think the
decision of whether you choose to buy
or whether you choose to build your own
is really the most fundamental decision.
That said, there are.
A plenty of options out there from
both perspectives where, there are many
startups that have spun up and are trying
to build AI SOC platforms as evidenced
on my slide there, there's typically also
going to be good ics in your organization.
It could be a security engineer, it
could be a SOC analyst who is, built
a prototype that, tries to use AI
agents or deploy AI agents to help.
Alleviate some of the pressure
that SOC teams are feeling.
However, the challenge that you're gonna
find is all of these solutions demo
very similarly and demo really well.
However, when it comes to building
trust to be able to productionize
these solutions, that's where you're
gonna have a really hard time.
And the goal behind this
talk and introducing the
guardrails first framework.
Is to give you a methodology for how
you may go about, deploying these
agents in production so that you're
successful in your endeavors, right?
And there are four
pillars to this approach.
Firstly, making sure that context
about your organization is
front and center in the design.
Appropriate policy controls are
in place so that you don't, you're
not looking at adverse outcomes
if you get suboptimal results.
Solution needs to be designed with
trust and auditability in mind.
And then lastly, it needs to be human
in the loop for critical actions
that it may take, which may pose
a more pose potential harm to your
organization if done incorrectly.
Let's double click into this
framework and see it in action.
Let's talk about the first pillar,
which is organizational context.
Now, I'll tell you this, from my years
of experience working with security
operations teams, the process for triaging
or investigating and identical alert.
Is never the same or
never exactly the same.
Across two different organizations,
depending on the security tools that they
own, how their data is structured and what
their standard operating procedures looks
like you will have a very different set
of standards that need to be followed.
Two, two triage and investigate
literally the exact same alert across
two, two different organizations.
And that's where AI really needs to begin.
So as you think about building AI
agents in your own organization,
you need to leverage all of the
context about your organization in
training data for your AI agents.
And what do I mean by that?
The first part of this is you
need to leverage all of the human
knowledge in your environment.
For things that have already
been triaged or investigated.
So what I mean by that is you probably
have a plethora of case notes that
indicate processes currently being
followed to triage and investigate various
types of alerts in your organization.
Secondly, you probably have lead
SOC analysts who are able to write
pretty detailed SOPs or standard
operating procedures for how they go
about investigating specific types
of alerts that originate from various
detections in your environment.
And both of those serve as a key
training material to help your AI agents.
Both from a rag or prompting context,
succeed in your own environment
and understand the nuances of
what investigation or evidence is
really required to be successful.
One thing I will warn you from
talking to all of these teams.
That you may already have a standard
set of SOPs that are written, but
you, as you discover as you start
building AI agents, you're likely to
discover that there are gaps in those
SOPs, not just from a perspective of
not just from the perspective that
some steps are being missed, but also
from the standpoint of hey if an AI
agent is really to understand these.
Some of the steps may need to be
rewritten without, corporate jargon
that, AI may have no path to succeed.
And the third thing I will say is
anytime you are going to go ahead
and deploy this agent, and this may
sound really basic, but anytime you're
deploying an increment, make sure you
have a very robust back testing pipeline
where this AI agent can disposition.
Alerts or analyze alerts that have
already been labeled by your security
operations team from a manual
investigation and triage process.
So a back testing pipeline
is an absolute must.
Third element, this is how organizational
context can really be at the center of the
AI learning curriculum and help AI agents.
Actually be practically useful
in your production environment.
The second pillar that I want to
talk about is policy constraints.
You do know that AI at times can
produce less than ideal unpredictable
outcomes, and that's where policy can
really be a CYA with capability, scope,
tools, policy driven gating, human
oversight and decision pro provenance.
Being built into sort of the design of
your AI agents or one that you procure.
Now, what do I mean by
capability, scope tools?
The first thing is, decide
what the boundary really is.
Is this a tool that is trying to
perform enrichment or is this an agent
that's, trying to go update tickets?
Is it one that's gonna go take
response actions in your environment?
If it is one that is.
Purely going to do enrichment.
Make sure that it is scoped down
to only have access to tools
that allow it to do enrichment.
That way you are able to limit
your blast radius in, in case it
ever reaches the wrong conclusion.
Where you may not want it to go
take a response action locking out
a user account or locking out a
domain controller, which makes your.
Entire organization go dark.
Things like that could happen.
And, you wanna make sure that you are
building in controls in your architecture
to prevent that from happening.
So all of these AI agents need to
be scoped or need to be exposed
to tools that are scoped down to
specific purposes in terms of what
they, are permitted to achieve.
Next.
You should have.
Some level of policy driven gating where
AI is able to come up with a proposal.
It is evaluated against various
policies that you have in place.
And a decision in made is made on whether
this is ex supposed to be escalated
for human review, whether this is
supposed to be automatically executed
or even if it is automatically executed
that it actually had the right in.
Outcome of that execution.
So policy constraints or
policy driven gating is an
important part of that design.
Now, all of this, organizational
context and policy is great,
but how do you build trust?
And this is one of those areas where
over time I think you will have
to do less because AI will just.
The tooling should just get
better and better over time.
And people as they embrace this new
technology will be more trusting
of it than they are at the moment.
The things that, that I would
advocate for is when you're looking
at either buying or building your own
AI agents for security operations.
Make sure that you have
access to a full audit trail.
This includes an entire timeline of every
step the AI agent took right from, what
data it used to arrive at its conclusions.
How did it reason past that data?
What are all the actions that
it took, and then what was the
final outcome that it suggested?
A hundred percent traceability and
auditability is a must have when it
comes to succeeding with AI agents
in production, in your environment.
Make sure you hold that bar off
any solution that is either being
built internally or being procured.
If you want to be able to succeed
in a manner where you're truly able
to augment, your SOC analyst with AI
agents to help investigate and triage.
And lastly, from a adoption
roadmap standpoint.
I would advocate for taking a very human
in the loop oriented approach and a
practical way of achieving that is any
solution you deploy, I would advocate to
begin it pretty much in shadow mode where
it is accessible to a subset of security
operations leads in your environment.
Not even the entire security operations
team where AI is silently making
recommendations on what it would have.
Dispositioned a particular alert or
finding as and that is just evaluated
by some of your best SOC analysts or
SOC leads to find if the reasoning
and the conclusions actually hold up.
The second phase I would
advocate for is to go ahead
and allow AI to make proposals.
Pretty much on your, ui where
your analysts sit, where you know,
they, it, it is able to go suggest
potential things to do, or based on
its investigation outcomes to all of
your security operations analysts.
However, there's by no means a mandatory,
like it, it's no, by no means mandatory
to accept the suggestions provided by ai.
In fact it is they're
encouraged to audit these.
And then decide which ones they
would actually want to go and apply.
Now, once you've gone past this point
where you've built a fair amount of
trust and you think AI is pretty much
reaching the right conclusions and
your team knows how to leverage some of
those conclusions to accelerate their
workflows, I would consider giving it a
little bit more bounded autonomy where
it's able to, autonomously perform.
Low risk actions that would not,
lock out people in your organization
or cause severe detriment.
And that sort of boundary
autonomy is provided to it.
And then lastly, I do
not see a world where.
You would fully let AI go and, execute
a large detrimental action with
the technology as it exists today.
So providing continuous feedback
and making sure that it is able to
grow in trust and reach that point
is the fourth phase where I would
love to keep pushing in terms of
expanding the scope of that bounded
autonomy to be, more wider with time.
So those are the four pillars,
organizational context for training
policy con constraints to limit downside.
Auditability to build trust and a roadmap
that begins pretty much with your SOC
leads then graduates to your entire SOC
team and is bounded in terms of scope
of autonomy that it has while that scope
continues to expand and grow over time,
where you're able to just take things off
your plate and put it on the AI agents.
Alright, so that's the framework.
How do you know if you implemented that
framework correctly and have an AI agent
that actually works well in production,
delivering the outcomes you want?
So first off, you obviously wanna
check, Hey, were you able to
eliminate a lot of the false positives
that your team is looking at?
Reduce your MTTR mean
team, mean time to analyze.
With all of the AI provided output
did that provide or manifest as
an analyst productivity gain?
Pick your favorite metric for how
you measure analyst productivity.
It could be tickets that they triage
in the shift whatever they did.
And then at a very base level, obviously
you wanna look at how accurate were
the recommendations as well as the
reasoning of what the AI produced, right?
And then from a actual blueprint
standpoint, I would recommend you take
these six phases or six stages, right?
First off, assess the current
state of your knowledge
base and your documentation.
Like I said, the first pillar
is organizational context.
Hey, do you even have your existing
SOC workflows documented really well?
The next phase I would recommend
is find a narrow scope.
Like in fact start really small.
Hey, here's an area where we
are feeling some amount of pain.
It's relatively low risk.
It would be great to go and let
the AI agent lose on this, right?
Particularly in talking to some of
the security operations teams, I've
heard areas like employee reported
phishing emails be considered
relatively low risk for things that
people would consider automating.
And, having some level
of automation around.
The third thing would be to see, what
kind of guardrails do you need in place?
What kind of capability
scoped tools do you need?
What kind of policies do you need to
make sure that, hey, even if AI reaches
the wrong conclusion, the the impact to
your organization is not catastrophic.
With that, you'd go ahead and develop your
AI models or AI agents and then deploy
them in some sort of shadow mode with your
lead SOC analysts where there is no impact
on any of your UI or work surface where
your where your analysts operate today.
Fifth phase would be to deploy
them in a manner where it's able
to make suggestions to analysts
in the UI that they operate in.
And over time expand its autonomy
so that it's able to achieve
better automation outcomes for you.
So these would be the six phases in
which how I would approach a build
project or even if it's a by project
implementation of a project like that.
Hopefully that was helpful.
I do think the key takeaway from
this conversation, hopefully is
that while AI agents have a lot of
promise there is a path where these
AI agents can be deployed in a safe,
scalable manner, but human centricity
is still at the forefront, right?
So as long as you start
with a small scope.
Which, which can be expanded over
time, you're gonna be able to succeed
and get off the ground a lot faster.
You need to be able to measure
whether you're actually hitting
the outcomes you're after.
What is the accuracy of the
recommendations that the AI is
making how much efficiency is
it able to add to your workflow?
You wanna make sure that humans
are in the loop in terms of
making all of the key decisions
while you expand the scope of ai.
And then as you build this trust,
you need to be on a journey where
you're constantly expanding the
scope of what autonomy means for AI
agents deployed in your environment.
Hopefully that was helpful.
So you as a DevOps person,
when you do get your security
operations teams coming to you.
Pretty much as I promised
this year, asking you to help
build and deploy AI agents.
You're able to help them succeed
and help your organization
succeed at this endeavor.
Thank you so much for the time.