Hey everyone.
Thanks for participating of
this conference to DevSecOps.
2024 from, confi 42.
And today I'm going to talk a
little bit about the improvement of,
DevOps workflows with generative AA.
So a little bit about me.
I am Tulio Arruda, AI Impact Lead at
GFT Technologies, leading a global
product, focused in a developer
productivity using generative AA.
I am an 18 years Microsoft MVP
focused on DevOps areas, talking
about Azure DevOps, talking about
GitHub, Kubernetes, productivity,
career, and other contents like that.
I'm a part of the GitHub Start Program
too, and I'm the first one from Brazil.
And I'm more recently, I'm a part of the
Docker captain program as well, okay.
I'm a speaker in technical
conference like that.
I'm a YouTuber about DevOps, about career,
about productivity, about JNA, okay.
you can find here the link
for my YouTube channel.
Youtube.
com slash at Julia Arruda.
You can find here my
LinkedIn as well and my mail.
If you need to talk about some content
about this presentation or about
something else about my contents.
Okay.
So to start this talk, I think
that's an important point that
we can explain our, your define
here is what is the generative AA?
Basically, this is an approach
that you can use to generate a
new content, such as tests, such a
text, images, music, or in our case,
source codes, code documentations
or, unit testing, for example.
I'm talking that it's an.
Because we already have a lot of
contents and materials and usable, AI
tools, AI, frameworks, AI algorithms
to, to provide us, many different tasks.
And we, already using, artificial
intelligence for many years, for different
tasks is like a classification information
or training, to support us to providing,
Data classification to provide us,
tools like a chat, chat bots as well.
We can do.
A lot of things with artificial
intelligence from years ago, but, the
general TVA provide this, easier way to
interact with the artificial intelligence
at, before the general TVA to work with
artificial intelligence was, very hard
and complex to do because we need to know.
too much about the complex algorithms,
about data classifications, about
we need to have a, so many hard
skills to work with, to work
with artificial intelligence.
But with gender TVA, all of us can
interact and use the artificial
intelligence, the to transform it.
The scenario with, the
easy way to interact.
Basically, I can ask something
and generate TVA will be answer
to generate a good answer to me.
Basically, this new
approach changed everything.
It's not only for software
development life cycle, but for all
areas, that you can imagine here.
Okay.
And to work in with, this general TVA.
A new thing appeared that it's a prompt
engineering to what is this properly?
Basically, this is an art of
crafting effective instruction to
get best response from AA models.
I'm talking here.
That's an art because we don't
have, exactly point or, exactly,
exactly tutorial about how can
you create your best problem.
We have techniques.
We have a lot of techniques of that.
But, imagine that if I tell you to
create a new prompting, for example,
answer to me about, the vulnerability
in the code and show me the SQL
injection or other points in the code.
You probably have one specific result.
And if I try to do the same,
the result will be so different,
will be big different.
Basically, the prompt engineering
is an art because, you need to
improve your prompt to create
your prompt with your own ideas.
I cannot tell you using
this specific word.
Using this, using that, you need to try
to create something, to imagine, the
results to test and test again, improve
and improve it again, because it's not a
fixed point, about the creation of this.
If you change one thing, one small
thing, if you include a comma in
your prompt, your answer can be
changed, entirely changed, okay?
Basically, you need to think
about that, to study about that.
We have a lot of techniques.
We have a different kind of
promptings like a chain of
thoughts, or one shot promptings.
We have a different kind of
this, but, the creation of this
prompt is not a exacting point.
It's a, basically an art to creating this.
And, we can see here the
different of these prompts.
I put this in a PPT, but I can show
you directly in, in my VS code.
Let me open here.
For example, let me try my first
prompting that I'm using, in this demo,
basically I'm requesting for GitHub co
pilot, that building an application to
display electrical vehicle, vehicle data
and I'm request to give some options
for how can I structure this app?
Okay, I will send this for copilot
and I will be, I will be received
from this a good information.
I will be receiving here, different
options about, what I can do this,
for example, an MVC, architecture.
NMVVM, Microservices Architecture,
Component Based Architecture, Serverless
Architecture, Monolithic Architecture.
And here I have one example.
It's a good result.
Yes, but, it's not properly that I
need because I have a lot of options
here, but imagine that if I provide
more information, more context
for, the co pilot, let me clear
my, shed here and let me using my.
Second version off the same prompting
here in this version off this prompt.
I request the same thing.
I'm building an application to
display electric vehicle data, but
I'm including more information here.
For example, I went to use
express and typescript.
Give me some options for
how to structure this app.
I'm informed that's a large scale
project with more than 1000 users online.
For authentication, I'm using
Key Cloak for front end.
we'll be creating TypeScript and the
application will be deployed on Azure
Kubernetes Services, for example.
let me send this for my GitHub Copilot.
And now, we can see that the
information is, a little different.
For example, I have here a project
structure, a key components, information
about key cloak integration, and
for example here, source codes, to
implement my key cloak integration, to
implement my, route for vehicle data.
Basically, I have more detailed, more
examples about what I can do here.
and for example, the container code to
generate my, Kubernetes implementation,
basically the point here is, if you
provide more information, more details
about, your request, if you provide more
context or how many that they use, you
provide in these, you will be received.
best information.
as possible.
all the time when you need to use,
generate two, like a chat, TPT,
Google Gemini, or get hub copilot.
In this case, the important point
is providing more context, be
clear about your request to prove
to receive the good Answers.
Basically, good things in the prompting,
good things out in the answer.
Okay.
Basically, is that what happened here?
And it's basically what happened
in all tools that you are using.
All General TVA tools that you are using.
Or in the tool, GNA tool that
you can develop in the future.
Basically, the idea is the same.
Context is important.
The prompt is important and how many
details you provide is very important.
Okay?
And Only to understand how this
prompting, works on GitHub Copilot,
but not only on GitHub Copilot.
The idea, of this will be the
same, in other JNAA tools like
a JDPT or in the tool that you
can be developing, using JNAA.
Okay, the structure will be
Something like that, with the
change, the necessary changes.
Like you are using, other
techniques to interact with
GenerateVA, but the core is that.
The user will be making a request
for your tool, in this case
GitHub Copilot, for example, to
create a web server in TypeScript.
The GitHub Copilot will be understanding
this, and Append a system prompting.
What is this?
The idea of the system prompting basically
is a set of rules that you, provide
for your system, for your, GNAA tool.
In this case, for example,
the GitHub CodePilot have, two
lines in the beginning here.
You are a friendly code assistant
and probably have something
like, you need to answer the
question about source code only.
you need to guarantee that you are not
implementing vulnerabilities in the code.
and you need to talk only about the code,
without for, and you do not have answers.
I don't know for polyfix or other
contents without source code development.
using the system tag with this
set of rules, your DNA will be,
Follow these rules to answer
only the necessary information.
For example, if I try to work to ask
about, for copilot, about politics,
for example, to get help copilot to
be answered for me, something like,
I was not able to answer about that.
Okay.
The idea is that of the system.
area in the prompting.
Basically now, I'm sending to GNA
the user section, create a web server
script, and assist an area with the
set of rules from GitHub Compilator
or from ChatPT or from your tool.
Okay?
And I send the both information
for GNA like, GPT 4 or cloudy 3.
5 sonnet or Google Gemini pro.
it's don't matter.
I send this for my GNA and
GNA will be understanding.
Okay.
I have these rules.
I have this answer.
And now, I have this rule.
I read this question and now I
need to answer this question.
Basically now I have new, a new section
called assistant with the answer from GNA.
Okay.
that response for your tool and
your tool response for a user.
Basically, it's that the workflow
about the prompting on GitHub
Compilator and other GNA tool.
Okay.
I'm talking about this, but you
probably, asking for why we use Gene a
in the SDLC, and I have here these four
key points, but we can include other
because we have a lot of benefits to
using, JA in a DevOps workflow, but.
These four key points are the most
important for now for me, okay?
The first one is the enhanced developer
experience because, when I started to work
as a software developer, I learned that
the user experience is the most important
part of software development because
if the user don't like the experience,
about don't like the user experience.
The users will not use
your application anymore.
but yes, it's important.
But the other part is important as well.
The developer part, it's very important
because if the developer have a good
experience in the source code creation,
the product creation, we will have
best results for product creation.
The final user, not only in the user
experience, but we have a good back
end, a good source code, improvement, in
the usability, in the higher viability
of the application, we can have.
a lot of benefits if you're focused
in a developer experience, okay?
GNAA will be solving all points
of the developer experience.
No, it's not the idea, but it's a
interesting point to start in this if
you don't have, a developer experience
implemented in your process yet.
Okay, only about developer experience,
you can have, One, another talk
about that because we have a lot
of contents for this, but for now,
keep in mind that, a GNA can be
support you on this to starting, To
start to improve in this, but why?
Because going to the second point,
it's increased the productivity because
the DNA tools enables the developers
to work more smarter because we have,
for example, GitHub Copilot, a code
assistant directly in my IDE, in this
case, I do not need to go anymore for
forums on the internet or to Google to,
understand how can I solve a problem.
I remember in the past, before
GitHub for Pilot, I spent more time,
looking in the internet, looking in
the forums, how to solve, specific
problems in my source code, in my tasks.
because, some, some errors
happens and I have no idea why.
Or I need to specific implementation
that I have no idea how can I do and I
need to made a lot of researches this
and this spend time, a precious time
that you have, in the projects and now
with GitHub Copilot I can use this to
support me on this part because GitHub
Copilot already suggests, implementation
to me based, in, in what I'm writing.
In my code, for example, if I'm
writing here a switch case, the
GitHub copilot already suggests
me, how can I complete the section?
I can use the copilot to suggest
to me improvements in this code.
Or for example, if I don't remember, I
don't know, how can I do a SQL insert, in
a SQL language on Oracle database, because
I don't use Oracle database so much here.
I don't need to go to Google anymore.
I can only ask for my chatbot in my IDE.
And in a second, I have now an
implementation, an explanation if
necessary, and the implementation
will follow my code standards
that I'm already creating for.
It's a very interesting point.
Okay?
And it's providing, so
many productivity for us.
and going for the 13 point, it's,
providing us, increased learning because
it's supporting me to understanding
more about my projects and not only
about that, but imagine if you are
starting in a new project that you have
no idea what this project does, you
need to see the documentation, right?
Yeah, but we have a point here.
It's very common that projects
don't have documentations, right?
Or if have documentations, the
documentation is very outdated.
And basically you need to check with
other teammates, how this project works,
what this project does, to understand,
to understand what happened here.
And you need to spend time for
other team members for this.
Using Jinner TVAA like GitHub Copilot
or other tools like ChiefTAI Impact that
I'm working for, you can increase this
because we can, for example, generate the
documentation, about the project using
Jinner TVAA, having this documentation
alive day by day, for example, or week
by week, it doesn't matter for now.
You can have a live documentation
properly, or you can use a github
compiler, for example, to explain,
in a real time for you what the
project does, what class does, and
it will be, increase your learning.
But it's.
The increased learning is not only about
your project, but you can, increase
the learning about other points,
about a new language, for example.
If you have no idea what another
language does or how can you start
programming in another language, you can
use IdentityVA to support you on this.
For this specific point,
I have a personal example.
a few months back.
One month ago, I needed to create
here in my project, a new VS
code extension, and TypeScript.
But I never wrote a code
in TypeScript before.
This is, this was my first
contact with, TypeScript.
And then use it, a GitHub copilot
to support in me, to explain.
more about TypeScript to support me
to create a hello world project on
TypeScript to try to understand a little
bit more, to create more complex process.
And I'm using GitHub Copilot to support
me to create this extension as well.
And I have, I had a very good experience
on that because I created this extension.
So there is that.
It's not so complex extension,
but have a good complexity.
but they created this in two days,
a new functional VS code extension.
And I had no knowledge before.
Now, I'm not a specialist on TypeScript,
but I have more knowledge on TypeScript.
I know how can I write a code,
understand the problems, improve the
code, but I had no knowledge before.
I'm using only GitHub
compiled to teaching me.
How can I do that?
Supporting me in the
implementation and in two days.
I implemented a new feature
with the things that I have
no, I had no knowledge before.
It's a very important and it's a very
interesting about the powers of the
GNAA tools into developers productivity.
And going then of these key points,
we can focus on the business
properly because we don't have to,
to looking for, about, common things.
FNL, switch and case or other simple
parts, of the software development
that you cannot remember day by day
and you need to go to Google to search,
about this because This will provide us
this information and you can focus to
improve the application to understand
the business rules to improve the best
ways of this business rules to create
the best implementation for all to have
the best application for our users.
Okay, basically, this is four key
points that you can, understand
about why you can use GNA on SDLC.
Okay.
And how can GNA tools improve the
developer, the DevOps workflows for us?
we can have here a lot of points.
I sat in here, six, The first
one is the code creation.
It's the most common, for all of you.
Probably you are already using
a GitHub Copilot or Amazon Q or
other, code, assistant in your IDE.
And, it's can provide us, as
I mentioned before, a lot of
suggestion, a lot of improvement
support us in so many tasks here.
It's a very interesting and I'm
using this a lot and it's amazing.
The second one is the code
reviewer process because we know
that, the developers was not
providing information for us.
But if you don't know what I'm
talking here, the code review
and process basically is when a
developer made a new change in the
source code and need to request.
That this change is merged in a
production version of the application.
Basically, the developer had a
new task, worked on this, created
a new source code implementation
and needed to merge this code.
The idea of this process is that the
developer creates a good description
about the changes that he made to support
the approval to understand everything.
happened here and decide if this
change can be approved or nothing,
or if this change can be, need to be
improved before this merge happens.
But we know that the developers do
not wrote this explanation properly
in general, or developers wrote no
information or put update the code.
And it's.
Provide no information for us.
Okay?
And following this, the approval
need to go to the source code, read
line by line to understand what's
good happening, or call for the
developer, to request developers
to, to, to, explain the changes.
And it's, spend a lot of time to,
to do this using generative a tools.
like a GFG AI impact, for example, or
GitHub Compilator or other, tool for that.
The GNA is supporting you to understanding
the change and explain everything for you.
Basically, it can generate a good
description with a lot of details.
Details, change by change,
implementation suggestion.
We can do much more.
with GNA2 in a code review,
making the approval job easier.
Okay?
The next one here is documentation.
I already mentioned before because, in
general, the projects have two scenarios.
It's the most common.
Or the project don't have documentation,
and it's a problem that we know that.
because no one have any idea about
what's project does, if the creators,
go out of the company, no one,
will have a knowledge about that.
Or, in general, we have a documentation,
but this documentation was created
in the first version of the
application, the first implementation.
And it's very outdated.
In both case, we basically have
no documentation for the persons.
Yeah.
But using Jenny eight to
you have to impact as well.
you can, Have an alive documentation
because we can use a GNA2 to scan
your source codes automatically,
understanding the source code and
creating a new markdown documentation.
For example, a new PDF documentation or
in another format documentation and, store
this in your documentation repository.
To support your developers to
understand what happened here.
To support your future developers
to understand what happened here.
And, you can use this to generate
documentation change by change.
If the code changes, the
documentation, changes too.
And maintain real life.
it's a great, improvement in our process.
Another point that we can do
here is a test generation.
For example, we can use a unit
test to support us in a unit
test creation following your
standards, your company standards.
you can use this to, to
generate functional testing, for
example, using natural language.
in general, you need to create a
functional test in mapping, HTML fields.
Pass some information, making this process
a little bit difficult because if, the
front end developers change everything,
change a component, your test will be
broken, but you can use here, tools with
generative VA to write your tests in
natural language, for example, requesting
only to make a login in a specific page,
with specific username and password
and the DNA to will be identifying it.
For example, your fields and components on
your screen, and you don't need to care,
with how the field is called, is named
for, because it will be identified this
for you and create this automatically.
The other point that, I can mention
here is the code correction because we
can use to understanding, what's wrong.
With your source code or vulnerability
in your source code or bugs in your
source code and request for GNI to
support us to improve, to correct, this
implementation and we can do manually,
with chatbot tools or automatically
with, batch tools like a GitHub code,
correct, GFTI impact code fixer as well.
But we can do much more on this.
I put these only five points here,
but you can, improve in this to
creating, to support your creation,
DevOps workflows properly to support
you to create a Kubernetes, scripts
properly, for example, or supporting
you in a modernization process.
For example, for, from an ODS language
for a newest one, from, I don't
know, from CoWolf to Java or to Java
8 to Java 21 for, from C sharp 3.
5 to C sharp 8, for example, you
can use this for a lot of tasks.
And day by day, new tools
and new ideas, is appearing.
to support us on this, improvements.
And it's very interesting.
If you're very amazing for us.
And today I'm using this two tools.
The first one It's the GitHub Copilot,
in general I'm using GitHub Copilot
to support my things, to write code,
the VS Code extension and here with
the chatbot experience, but I'm using
the other parts of the GitHub Copilot
because GitHub Copilot today have So
many implementations like, another
one that I like to like them what too
much is, GitHub co pilot to workspace.
It's a very interesting implementation.
And the next one that I'm
using is the GFTI impact.
I'm working for in this tool.
I'm, I'm one of the creators
of, this tool on GFTI and.
The focus here is improve the software
development life cycle with generative
VA focused on productivity again,
integrating this in a pipeline if, if
it's possible, but have a user experience
to support other tasks like a user
story creation, documentation creation,
create a unit testing, reviewing,
code review and code correction test.
We have so many tasks here
and I'd like to show a little
bit about Both of them today.
Okay.
To support you to understand how
can GNA, can be supporting us in a
software development life cycle in
a develop, devops workflows process.
Okay.
I have here two demos.
The first one, it's more simple, because
it will be executed directly in my IDE.
Okay.
And what I will be do here.
Basically, I received here this
scenario, I'm working in a new project
that I have no much information
and I need to solve a vulnerability
reported, by my SAS tool, document
the code and create, a unit test here.
Okay.
Basically, I received this
information from my SAS tool
that I have a SQL injection.
What I can do here.
Let me open my, My VS
code here in this project.
Let me check only.
I'm still connected on my
okay.
I have connection with my JFJ.
Impact.
And here, I'm have my GitHub copilot
XC assistant here and the file with
the vulnerability mentioned in my PPT.
For example, here, if I'm back
If I'm back here on my PPT, I have
here the information is the user.
java and I have here this SQL injection.
And what I can do here?
Basically, I can request to GitHub
Copilot to explain me the code.
And the GitHub Copilot is explaining
about this class, what class does.
And supporting me to
understanding this easier.
But I need to solve this SQL
injection and what I can do here.
I will be request, for example, for
my github compiler to refactor this
code and correct SQL injection.
Let me see what happened here.
Now, The GitHub Copilot will be
understanding here my request and
basically it's generating to me a
refactored code and if you see here
the SQL injection solved it for me.
And this is explaining for us what the
change was made here, basically replaced
the statement with prepared statement,
added a final here, moved the return.
And I can copy this, for
example, and based on this to
have a new, implementation.
And I have here a correct
version of, the source code.
an interesting point that we can
do here is using a different LLMs.
I have here Cloud 3.
5 Sonnet 01.
Mini 01 preview as well, and we
can use all of them to generate
our answers if it's necessary.
But I already generate here with
Copilot, my new implementation.
And now my request is generate
documentation and generate unit tests.
How can I do that?
Basically, if I'm going here in my
file explorer now, I already have
my GFT AI Impact extension installed
here and I can click in the file and
request to create the documentation.
And here I can choose the prompts because
I have a different prompts on AI Impact.
I need to choose the source code
language to have the standards.
and the LLM that my GFTI
Impact is supporting today.
We support the three principal
clods with AWS with clod 3.
5, Sonnet, GMI and GPT 4.
0.
Okay, I will be using AWS clod.
And we need to wait now,
the documentation process.
But, for now, the AI Impact
is understanding the codes And
applying a lot of, convention and
standards to generate a very good
and detailed documentation for us.
Okay, and the process generate a new
Markdown document for us like that.
I will be open my Markdown
preview to see better here.
And, okay, now I have here a documentation
with overview, process flow, insights,
dependencies, data manipulation.
We have here important information
about this person, but yes, we
already have a new document here.
Now to finish, you need
to create a unit tests.
Let me right click again, create
unit tests for this class.
And again, I need to choose my prompting.
I need to choose my frameworks,
the source code language, the LLM.
And here, The impact is asking to me if
I'd like to include existing test file.
For example, if I try to create
a new test for a new class.
Like that, I cannot include, I do not
include, existing test files, but if I
already have unit tests for this, I can
put yes and point in this file to use
extra context and the impact will be,
improve or correct the unit test for us.
Okay.
Basically now the process is working
for and the impact to be understanding
the source code class for you.
And, we are applying internally a
lot of standards, best practices
to create the unit test for us.
and we already have here the unit
tests we have here, the imports,
the user test class with mock you
and a lot of unit tests to support
this current implementation for us.
Okay.
Now, following this idea, we already
have the demo one implemented.
Great!
We used GitHub Copilot and AI
Impact inside the developer IDE to
increase the productivity, explain
the project, support the code, in
the code correction, documenting
the code, and creating a unit test.
Okay?
Let me open the presentation module.
It's changed.
Bye.
And in the second demo, we have a
lot of, a little different process.
I need to hear, the same, scenario,
but we need to run this directly in
a pull request because the idea of
this, let me copy the corrected file.
The idea of this project is
this process now is, Do the same
job that the developer does.
I will be creating a new change, submit
this change and waiting for approval.
And basically I will be open my source
code file here in my repository.
I'll be open the user.
java, edit this file, and I will be
paste my corrected version of the code.
Commit this, create a new branch.
Okay.
and create a new, pull request here.
When I create the pull request, I'm using
here a GitHub in this case, but you can
use Bitbucket, your other DevOps tool.
It's not important.
It is important that this DevOps tool
can be triggered a new pipeline when
this pull request is created like that.
Basically, if you see here, The
GitHub, actions, was triggered a
new pipeline and this pipeline,
is triggering the GFTI impact.
And what will be happening here,
basically, I'm creating a smart
request process that I'm calling,
internally because I'm using
different tools from AI impact.
Okay.
To support the pull request,
to improve the pull request.
For example, we saw in the IDE that I
can create a documentation and create
a unit test with, the, with the IMPACT.
And I mentioned for you before that
you can use JNA to analyze, the
changes to generate a code review.
What I'm doing here, when the developer
create a new change, submit a new change,
We know that, the documentation will be
outdated and in general, the developers
do not create Unity tests properly or
forget to create a part of the Unity
test, do not create implementation,
all implementation as possible.
In this smart pull request, included, in
my action process, a calling from, for
AI impact to run the Unity test creation.
To create a unit test for this, a document
creation to create a new documentation.
And after that, review this pull request.
If you can see here, I already have this
test generated, documents generated.
And if I click on files, change it, I
can see here in the first file, the user.
java, the file that I changed.
Okay.
My chains, have here,
the user test dot Java.
The red section is the existing tests
and the red is to change its tests
because I changed the implementation.
The impact understood that I
need to change the test class and
you can see here what happens.
some tests was removed.
Other tests was be included or improved.
Okay.
And.
In the final of that, I included
a new documentation in Markdown.
Let me open in a display rich
GIF, it's be easier to see.
But I have here a new documentation
with an overview, process flow, like
we saw in TVS Code IDE, with insights,
dependencies, data manipulation, and here
a vulnerability section, because we have a
lot of vulnerabilities in the source code.
I do not solve all of them.
I can do, but I didn't this.
But, I can see here password
storage, exception handling,
providing new information about that.
And if I'm back in here to my
pull request description, I have
now the revision created by, GFTI
Impact Bots, providing us a general
description about the changes here.
For example, to, this implementation,
improve the security and
code quality include changes.
And here I have summary file by
file explaining the changes in
the class that I manually does.
And in the usertest.
java that AI impact does.
And user.
java.
md that is documented, included.
AI impact in the process.
here we have recommendations for this
pull request related with this change.
Okay.
It's not a generic recommendation.
It's a specific recommendation.
And we have here explanation of
vulnerabilities if necessary.
Okay.
With examples, if necessary.
Basically we are using the generative
AI to improve Our process to, improve
our productivity day by day here
to improve the developer experience
because, now, I can, support developers
to do the task is more easier.
For example, with the reviewing
processing, supporting the description
generation with a lot of details to
support the best creation automatically
to create documentation automatically,
or using the ID to creating this
directly in your, developer environment,
we can do a lot of different tasks
in a different places here, but It's
provide us so many productivity here.
I'm using this both to get hub
copilot and AI impact in my days.
And it's very interesting to me.
I'm getting a lot of productivity.
I was talking with my boss recently
that, I'm using a lot the GNA tools
like a GitHub copilot and Microsoft
probably is boring with me because I
spent more money, than a GitHub copilot.
Then the license provided in general
for GitHub code, but because I use
it really a lot, Again, a lot of
productivity using this JNA tools.
Okay?
Thanks for participating for this talk.
I think that Can be help you to have more
ideas, to have more insights about that.
If you need to discuss About the GitHub
compiler to our impact, please send me
an email or, look about me in, in, in
linkaginess and, me, a message, if you
need to know more about, DevOps, Azure
DevOps, Career, GNA, Productivity.
Follow me on my YouTube channel.
Okay.
most part of my content is in
Brazilian Portuguese, but, I have
so many videos in English, as well.
Okay.
Again, thanks for participating.
Don't forget to follow
me in my social networks.
I hope to see you again in next,
sessions in next conference.
Thank you.
And bye bye.