AI is reshaping how we build
and shape software, not
gradually, but in giant leaps.
It's writing code, generating
infrastructure, fixing tests, reviewing
pull requests, and making decisions
inside our pipelines that used to
require a human for the first time.
The pace of delivery isn't set by
developers or release managers.
It's said by automation and
specifically AI driven automation.
That means something
fundamental has shifted.
We're delivering faster than
ever, but the guardrails we have
relied on for the past decade.
Were not designed for systems that think,
respond and adapt, and that gap between
how fast AI can move and how slowly.
Traditional security evolves is exactly
what we need to talk about, because if
we don't redesign our security for the AI
era, AI won't just accelerate delivery.
It will accelerate risk.
So today's session is about one idea.
How do we make AI driven delivery
secure by default, not by policy, not
by hope, not by heroics, but by design.
So before we dive into the technical
depth of the talk, let me give
you a quick sense of who I am and
where my perspective come from.
I'm Don Hammed.
I serve as the principal developer
advocate at Harness a company with a
simple but ambitious mission to help
every software engineering team deliver
code quickly, reliably, and efficiently.
If your team is trying to ship fast,
but not break production in the process.
Harness exists for exactly that reason.
Before this role, I spent over 15 years
working across the software delivery
lifecycle as a Java backend developer, QA
lead consultant, and later in advocacy.
I have worked for both small
companies, large enterprise, and on
government projects with one goal.
I wanted to help teams ship software.
With confidence and security baked in.
I live on the East coast and
outside of work I spend a lot of
time giving back to the community
by free resume reviews on LinkedIn.
Alright, enough about me.
Now let's dive into the perspective
of secure Pipeline in the AI era.
Now, here's the dream.
A pipeline that flows in this
beautifully simple, linear way.
You write code, you build it,
you run security, you deploy,
and then you monitor and audit.
Just like the textbooks say.
It's so clean and so orderly
that you could imagine it on a
DevSecOps brochure or a pamphlet.
If you're in the Europe, everything
behaves exactly the way you think it will.
Nothing surprising, nothing out of place.
You push changes and the pipeline gently
moves them through, through production,
like a well-behaved assembly line.
This is the image we all have in our
heads when we think about our DevSecOps
done right is the idealized version, the
Instagram version of software delivery.
But here's a problem.
This is not how real pipelines work.
Real pipelines are messy, real
pipelines are unpredictable, and
most importantly, real pipelines
have layers of hidden complexity.
That this simple diagram doesn't show.
So let's move Zoom in because the moment
you inspect the details, this perfect
pipeline start to look very different.
So now this, and this is closer
to reality, let's break it down
because each stage here represents a
failure mode we have all encountered.
So we start with a base
image or dependency set that
hasn't been touched in years.
It's packed with vulnerabilities,
not because anyone is negligent,
but because teams are juggling so
many priorities that updating the
foundation gets deprioritized.
So right from the first step, we're
injecting risk directly into the pipeline.
Next, the build stretch proudly
announces all test passed,
but when you look closely.
You found out that only a tiny silver
of a code base is actually tested.
This is like checking only
the headlights on a car and
declaring it road trips ready.
It's technically true,
but practically useless.
Next comes security.
So SaaS and das are there
in theory, but in practiced.
They're often skipped.
Maybe scans take too long.
Maybe someone's under pressure to
meet a deadline, and because the
system isn't enforcing anything, the
pipeline just shrugs and moves on.
Then we deploy everything all at once.
No calories, no blue, green,
no gradual rollout, just.
Ship it and hope nothing explodes.
Monitoring fires, alerts only after
the application is already throwing.
HTPs five hundreds.
There's no early warnings, no behavioral
signal, only catastrophic detection.
And finally, audit becomes
a manual guessing game.
No continuous compliance, no real
traceability, just someone asking.
So is production on fire?
The point of this slide is simple.
The ideal pipeline fails because
it ignores reality, and AI is about
to amplify all of these weakness,
which brings us to our next slide.
So over the last decade, we became
experts at automating delivery.
We built modern CICD pipelines, shifted,
left, shifted everywhere, and for the
first time in the industry's history.
We actually had a clear, well
established path from code to production.
Think of that pipeline as a set
of carefully laid train tracks.
A lot of hard work went into getting
them stable, predictable, and safe
enough to run at reasonable speed.
And then we added ai.
That's the bullet train
you see on the slide.
AI writes code.
It generates configuration.
It proposes infrastructure.
It drafts remediation, automatic
decisions, and accelerates
everything we feed into the pipeline.
But here's the critical problem.
We added the bullet train before
checking whether the tracks could
handle it, the rails, our processes,
our guard rails, our security models.
We're built for a slower world, and
the moment you increase speed without
increasing safety, the consequences
aren't just faster delivery.
They're faster failures.
This is the core tension
of modern DevSecOps.
AI doesn't fix broken process.
AI amplifies them and that leads
directly into our next problem, the
real world impact we are already seeing.
Here's the first data point.
76% of enterprises, not startups,
experiment experimenting, not
hobby projects, but established
enterprises have already experienced
a prompt injection incident.
Prompt injection is one of the
simplest attacks against AI systems,
and yet it's incredibly powerful.
An attacker doesn't exploit code.
They exploit behavior.
They manipulate the model's, instructions,
override guardrails, or change
the intent behind the interaction.
All through crafted input.
In traditional security, this is
like someone whispering the right
sequence of words to get root access.
It feels absurd until you realize
how easy it is to pull off.
And this isn't niche.
This is an oh that only
happens in the research labs.
This is happening in
production environment today.
Prompt injection is the warning
sign, the indicator that we are not
adequately prepared for behavior
level attacks that AI enables, and
it doesn't stop at prompt injection.
66% of organizations have shipped
code that contained vulnerabilities
introduced by AI generated suggestions.
This is the part that's our price.
People LLMs are excellent at
generating syntactically correct
code, but they are not inherently
good at generating secure code.
They don't understand memory safety.
They don't have built-in threat modeling.
They don't know your
architectural constraints.
They don't reason about.
Authentication boundaries
or or privilege escalation.
They simply produce what looks right
based on patterns in training data.
Okay, so developers accept a suggestion
pushes a commit and test pass because
tests often cover too little and our
vulnerability quietly enters the system.
In other words, AI accelerates
delivery, but unless we guide it
carefully, it also accelerates
the spread of insecure patterns.
And when you combine that with
increasing speed, limited review
windows and pressure to ship.
A vulnerable code becomes an
automated problem at scale.
Uh, let's look at one more number
and this one reinforces the trend.
66% of enterprises have already
experienced some sort of LMG breaking,
which means someone managed to push
the model into doing something it
was explicitly instructed not to do.
This is different from prompt injection.
Prompted Injection manipulates the
model within its allowed structure.
Jailbreaking convinces the model
to break its own rules entirely.
It's like having a safety system
that says, I'll never disable
breaking, and then someone gets it
to say, well, unless you ask nicely.
The scary part is that jailbreaking
doesn't require advanced hacking skills.
It just requires creativity
and enough persistence.
Once a model breaks its own boundaries,
every downstream workflow that
relies on it become vulnerable.
If the model helps generate configs,
those configs can become unsafe.
If it influences deployment decisions,
those decisions can become risky.
If it shapes, uh, access policies, uh,
permissions can be escalated or weakened.
And if it interacts with user
data, the guard rails around
sensitive content can evaporate.
Jailbreaking is a symptom
of a deeper truth.
AI systems are not purely deterministic.
They behave, they interpret, and
they adapt, and that creates an
entirely new category of threats.
Now let's connect that shift to the
broader picture of software delivery.
So AI has dramatically improved
how we deliver software.
It accelerates development, simplifies
infrastructure, automat decisions, and
turns complex tasks into simple prompts.
In many ways, delivery has never been
more efficient, but the threat landscape
didn't just evolve alongside ai.
It evolved faster.
So traditional security models
were built for static systems.
We scanned for, uh, SQL injection.
We look for, uh, cross edge scripting.
We hardened servers.
We watch dependencies, but AI native
systems don't break the weight.
Traditional systems break.
Their vulnerabilities don't
live in, uh, code lines.
They live in model behavior, uh,
contextual interpretation, uh,
reasoning pathways, uh, decision
making, logic, uh, emergent responses.
The visual on this slide captures
the difference perfectly.
On the left, you have the old
world structured static governed
by predict predictable code paths.
On the right, you have
the AI native world.
Fluid, contextual, adaptive, and
therefore susceptible to entirely
new classes of manipulation.
This is why we are seeing prompt
injection, jailbreaks, data
leakage, and behavioral drift.
They're not bugs, they're consequences
of how AI systems function.
So what happens when we put AI inside
our delivery workforce, inside our
pipelines and inside our automation?
That brings us to the next critical idea.
This is one of the most important
truths in modern DevOps.
Pipelines don't have opinions.
They automate whatever we
put into them, good or bad.
If you give them secure, well tested, well
reviewed code, they automate excellence.
If you give them misconfiguration outdated
images or vulnerable AI generated code.
They automate those mistakes
with the exact same enthusiasm.
Now introduce AI into the equation
and everything accelerates.
AI writes code faster.
AI proposes convic faster, generates
infrastructure faster, approves
changes faster, makes decision faster.
So if there's a crack in the system,
um, we control or an outdated
pattern, uh, permissive policy.
AI doesn't fix it.
AI amplifies it.
So the image on this slide shows this
perfectly, a clean green flow until
one flow enters, and suddenly the
entire system becomes a high speed
distribution mechanism for risk.
This is why the idea of secure by default
is not a slogan in an AI driven pipeline.
Security cannot be optional.
It cannot depend on developers
remembering something or
waiting for a late stage scan.
Security has to be embedded at every
layer because the pipeline will
run and it'll run fast, whether
the safety rails are there or not.
With that in mind, let's talk about how
organizations are currently adopting AI
and why the patterns aren't keeping up.
So across industries, teams
are doing something very
exciting and very dangerous.
At the same time, they're shipping
AI integrated systems into
production, not prototypes, not,
uh, side experiments, real customer
facing business critical systems.
Um, AI is generating code generating yaml,
um, suggesting infrastructure changes.
AI is, uh, triaging incidents.
AI is shaping the
behavior of our pipelines.
And teams are adopting these
capabilities incredibly quickly
because they're powerful and because
they re um, they reduce friction.
But here's the part we're
not talking about enough.
We're not updating our security
patterns at the same speed.
We're still relying on AppSec models
built for deterministic systems.
Still treat security
as a separate workflow.
We still focus on code level flaws
while the risks have moved to be
moved to behavior and context.
This creates a mismatch.
Modern delivery is dynamic, but our
security tools and process are static.
So teams are moving fast with ai, but
without AI aware guard rails policies
or verification, and that mismatch
is exactly where incidents happen.
To understand this gap more clearly,
we need to step back and look at
how delivery itself has changed.
Okay,
so for the last decade, delivery
cycles have been compressing Quarterly
release became monthly release.
Monthly became weekly.
Weekly became daily, and in many teams
now deploy multiple times per day.
Then AI entered the picture
and compressed everything.
Again, work that used to take hours.
Now happening in minutes, work that
took minutes, now happening in seconds.
The velocity of software creation
has fundamentally changed, but
security practices didn't evolve.
Alongside this shift, we're still
depending on manual reviews, periodic
scans, point in time approvals, human
driven decision making, security teams
already overloaded with requests.
In a world where code is generated
instantly and configurations
are modified automatically.
Security that operates on human time
cycles simply cannot keep up even worse.
Misconfigurations are
no longer just mistakes.
They have become automated hazards.
A bad configuration generated by AI
doesn't sit quietly in one environment.
It gets replicated, it gets
de deployed and redeployed.
It becomes infrastructure as as a risk.
This widening gap, fast delivery,
slow security is the core
reason we need a new approach.
And that new approach starts
with understanding that AI
native delivery lifecycle.
Now this slide captures the fundamental
shift in how delivery works in the AI era.
Traditionally, our pipeline was linear.
You code, build, test, deploy, monitor,
changes, move forward step by step.
But AI has changed that model entirely.
Today's delivery lifecycle
looks more like this.
AI influences every layer.
It helps generate code, is suggest,
uh, or modifies configurations.
It influences infrastructure definitions.
And it affects runtime decisions
through automated remediation.
And importantly, this is
no longer a one-way flow.
Issues don't just move downstream.
They move in both directions.
Here's what that means.
A config change can trigger AI to adjust
infrastructure and infrastructure.
Drift can cause AI to regenerate code.
A runtime anomaly can cause automated
remediation that shifts your system
away from its source of truth.
And AI generated fix can
accidentally introduce new
misconfigurations backup upstream.
This creates a closed loop
system, not a linear one.
And in closed loop, a small
mistake doesn't stay small.
It gets amplified, it
propagates, it becomes a pattern.
That's why AI driven delivery
demands new controls, new
guardrails, and a new security model.
One that understands behavior,
context, and system wide effects.
With this lifecycle in mind,
let's talk about what it means
for security, because the attack
surface has fundamentally changed.
So when we think about securing AI native
delivery, it's important to recognize that
the attack surface has expanded far beyond
traditional application vulnerabilities.
In the pre AI world, our
threats mostly lived in code.
SQL injection, uh, cross site
scripting, uh, dependency
vulnerabilities, configuration
mistakes, um, author and access issues.
But, uh, with AI embedded across
the delivery lifecycle, we now face
entirely new categories of risk.
First prompt injection.
Now, this is the most common attack today.
Instead of attacking your code,
attackers manipulate the model's
behavior by injecting crafted prompts.
The model is tricked into revealing
data, altering its reasoning, or
taking actions you never intended.
Second is the AI supply chain.
We're not just depending
on packages anymore.
We rely on model weights, fine tuning
data, prompt libraries, uh, embedding
stores, third party inference, APIs.
Each of these become an attack factor.
Um, if any component is compromised,
it enters your delivery pipeline
just like a toxic dependency.
Third is the automated misconfiguration.
So in the past, misconfigurations
happen manually now AI can generate or
modify configurations at machine speed.
If there's a mistake, a bad IM roll or an
insecure default, a faulty YAML pattern.
That mistake is propagated
instantly across environments.
And last but not the
least, the model exploits.
These include jailbreaking, model
poisoning, output manipulation,
data extraction, uh, via embeddings,
uh, or inference attacks.
These aren't weakness in your code,
their weakness in how the model behaves.
And this is why traditional
AppSec tools fall short.
The design to secure code not behavior.
The threat surface has moved.
Our security model needs to move with
it, and yet the teams responsible
for securing all of this, they're
not being, uh, set up to succeed.
When you look at how organizations are
adopting ai, there's a clear disconnect.
Only 43% of developers say
they're building security
into AI native applications.
Not because they don't care.
Developers always want to build
things correctly, but because they
haven't been trained or equipped
for this new threat landscape,
74% of teams say security is
still viewed as a blocker.
This is the old DevSecOps
friction returning in a new form.
When delivery accelerates,
but security can't keep up.
Teams don't slow down.
They bypass controls.
And 62% of developers report having
no AI security training at all zero.
Yet we are asking them to defend against
prompt injection model manipulation, LLM
data leakage, AI driven misconfiguration.
Embedding level exploits behavioral
automated decision making gone wrong.
This is like asking someone
to secure a distributed system
they've never seen before.
Developers want to ship safely, but the
industry hasn't given them the guardrails.
That gap leads us to central top,
to the central concept of the
stock, secure by default delivery, a
system where safety isn't dependent
on heroics or expertise or luck.
So what does secure by
default actually mean?
It means designing delivery systems in
a way where the safest possible option
is the default option, not an optional
configuration, not a best practice,
not something someone has to remember.
Secure by default means the pipeline
starts in a secure posture without
needing manual intervention.
Developers don't have to constantly
think about security edge cases, risky
changes are caught automatically.
Not through late stage reviews,
AI generated output is evaluated
for safety as it's created.
Unsafe defaults don't exist because
the system won't allow them.
This isn't just philosophy, it's a
practical engineering goal because in an
AI driven world where delivery happens
faster than humans can meaningfully react.
Security has to be
built in, not bolted on.
And the way we achieve this is
by embracing the intelligence
that AI provides, not just for
generating code or configs, but
for securing the pipeline itself.
So the next question is,
how can AI actually help fix
the problems AI introduced?
That's where we go next.
So we have talked a lot about how AI can
introduce new risks, but here's the twist.
AI can also help solve the
very problems it creates.
The key is shifting our mindset
from AI generates code and
configurations to ai, observes,
interprets, and protects the pipeline.
So what does this look like first?
We need pipelines that know when
something simply looks wrong, not
because there's a specific rule or
signature, but because the pattern doesn't
match the system's historic behavior.
AI's great at spotting these anomalies.
Weird output.
Suspicious config changes, unexpected
infra calls, things humans might miss.
Second, the system needs
to understand provenance.
Where did this artifact come from?
Was it written by a developer
generated by an LLM imported from
a third party model or data set?
Without provenance, there is no trust.
AI can track lineage
deeply and automatically.
Third, the pipeline
needs context awareness.
A risky action might be safe in
staging, but catastrophic in production.
A permissive policy might be fine
for r and d, but unacceptable
for a customer facing workflow.
Security shouldn't block everything.
It should understand the
intent and environment.
Finally, the system needs to
understand the behavioral gift.
AI systems change over time.
Their outputs evolve, their
interpretations shift.
If a model that used to produce safe
output suddenly starts acting differently,
that drift needs to be caught early.
So the big idea is this.
AI shouldn't just accelerate delivery.
It should accelerate security by giving
our pipelines, eyes, ears, and judgment.
And this leads us directly to the
framework that ties all of this together.
To build secure by default systems,
we need more than good intentions.
We need structure, a way to operationalize
everything we have talked about so far.
This bring us to the four pillars of
Secure by Default DevSecOps, A framework
designed for AI native delivery.
These four pillars work together
to transform pipelines from
passive automation into intelligent
self-protecting systems.
They are contextual intelligence,
automatic verification, behavior
based, anomaly detection,
and continuous learning.
And here's the important part.
You don't need all four pillars to start.
But eventually a mature AI native
delivery system needs every one of them.
Each pillar solves a specific
part of the risk equation.
Each builds on the others, and together
they create a pipeline that stays
secure even as the delivery speeds up.
So let's walk through each pillar
one by one, starting with the
foundation, contextual intelligence.
This is what separates traditional
DevSecOps from ai, native
World traditional pipelines.
Detect that something changed.
Contextual intelligence, understand
what changed, why it changed, and
how that change affects the system.
So let me break down what it means.
So a regular diff just shows
lines of code contextual
intelligence interprets meaning.
Is this change altering security posture?
Is it affecting permissions?
Uh, is it something AI generated that
doesn't align with the developer's intent?
Then in AI native delivery, these
layers influence each other.
A config tweak may alter infrastructure
and infrastructure drift may
cause AI to regenerate code.
Contextual intelligence ties
this relationship together.
Every team has a typical
pattern deployment, size,
frequency, rollback rates.
When something deviates from the
pattern, it might be a risk signal.
And then the last one, this is huge.
Developers often intend
one thing, but the outcome.
Ends up being something else.
Especially with AI generated
changes, contextual intelligence
catches this inconsistencies early.
This pillar is the foundation because
it gives your pipeline awareness.
Without context, everything
else is guesswork.
With it, your pipeline becomes a system
that understand what's happening,
not just executing steps blindly.
Now that we understand context, the
next step is to verify trust, which
leads us in into pillar number two.
So once we have contextual intelligence,
once the pipeline understand what's
happening, this is the next pillar,
which is automatic verification.
So this is why we shift from trusted
by default, to verify by default.
In the AI era, artifacts
come from everywhere.
Developer written code, AI generated
code, external model outputs, downloaded
containers, uh, infor configurations,
automated re, re, uh, remediation.
And because these sources vary, we
need pipelines that automatically from
trust before anything gets deployed.
Now, here's what automatic
verification include.
The first one is provenance
and integrated checks.
Where did this artifact come from?
Did it come from a trusted bill
system or was it generated by ai?
Has it been tampered with?
If the pipeline can't prove the origin
and integrity, it shouldn't ship.
The second one is the config
environment and infra alignment
with the source of truth.
AI often generates changes
that unintentionally drift
from what's defined in Git.
A verification ensures that
actual environment matches
the declared configuration.
No surprise, no hidden divergence.
The third one is that every pipeline step
is signed, trusted, and re reproducible.
If a bill can be reproduced, it can
be trusted signatures ensure every
piece of software has a verifiable
chain of custody, and the final
one is enforced safety conditions.
If a deployment doesn't meet predefined
safety criteria, wrong version, missing
signature, drifted config, or un
untrusted model, then those enforced,
uh, safety conditions are not met.
So this blocks your pipeline on
worms when the pipelines don't meet
these predefined safety conditions.
Now this leads us to the third pillar,
which is a behavior based anomaly
detection, and this is where traditional
security models completely fall short.
Traditional security looks at code
dependencies, configs, static rules, but
AI native systems break in dynamic way.
This through unexpected behavior, a
reasoning drift or contextual anomalies.
So what does a behavioral
based detection let let us do?
Uh, first one is it detect
abnormal behavior across code
config, infra, and model outputs.
So this means the pipeline actively
watches for things like unusual model
responses, unexpected API calls or
infrastructure activity changes that
don't align with past deployments.
The second one is risky.
Configurations rarely blow up.
Immediately.
They degrade slowly.
So behavioral signals catch these
problems early before the cascade.
Next.
These attacks don't show up in
code, they show up in behavior.
The model suddenly becomes
more permissive, more
confident, or more consistent.
So.
This is important.
Every engineering team has its
own rhythm, deployment sizes,
frequency, rollback rates.
So when something deviates, we need
to understand you need to learn
the normal delivery patterns and
flag the deviations in real time.
And the final pillar, the, and
arguably the most transformative
one, is continuous learning groups.
This is where the pipeline
evolves over time.
It just doesn't detect issues.
It learns from them, adapts and
becomes safer with every execution.
So what it means in practice
is you improve security posture
automatically using real pipeline data.
So the system uses the signal.
That from every build, every deploy, every
rollback, every failure, the generative
signal you get, the system uses that
signal to refine its understanding of
what is normal versus what is risky.
Next teams change tools.
Team set up new frameworks.
They restructure services.
Static rules become outdated quickly.
Continuous learning ensures that
guard rails evolve with the team
instead of blocking valid changes.
Now failures aren't just fires to put out.
They become lessons.
The system absorbs, not just humans.
This turns incident response into
future prevention and finally
turn failures into system level
improvements, not human rework.
With these four pillars, contextual
intelligence, automatic verification,
behavior based detection, and
continuous learning, we now have the
blueprint for Secure by delivery.
Secure by default delivery.
So let's talk about how this actually
shows up in real world through harness.
So now that we have identified
the four, uh, pillars of secure
by default DevSecOps, let's look
at how these ideas can come to
a, a life inside a real platform.
So harness was built on a simple belief
delivery should be fast, safe, and as
automated as possible without recurring
teams to become pipeline expert.
Now, when a pipeline fails, most
systems throw you into a log avalanche.
You are left digging through stack traces,
clicking to artifacts, jumping between
dashboards, and trying to reconstruct
what happened, harness that process.
This approaches this differently.
The system analyzes the pipeline
execution, understands what failed.
So here, harness ai, uh, it,
uh, understand what failed and
automatically explains why.
This is contextual intelligence in action.
The pipeline understand the story behind
the failure, not just the raw output.
And it has two huge benefits.
First, developers get clarity instantly,
no time wasted, uh uh, going through logs
or trying to reproduce flaky behaviors.
Second.
The recovery is faster and safer.
This is the first layer of secure
by default delivery, an intelligent
CICD engine that interprets, explains
and assists, not just executes.
Now one of the biggest historical
problems in DevSecOps is that security
is often bolted on a separate workflow, A
separate tool, a separate responsibility
harness takes a different approach.
Security is not something you
add on top of the pipeline.
It's woven directly
into the delivery path.
Let's look at wha what, what that means.
So on the left side of the screen,
you see continuous compliance.
Cross pipelines, repositories,
services, and environments.
Instead of re-running security scans
once per sprint or only on pull request,
harness, continuous labels, everything
using the CIS benchmarks, WASP standards,
custom policies and environment.
Environment rules.
This gives you a breakdown of passes
versus failures, the severity of risks,
where violations are trending, and
which services are repeatedly failing.
Security checks.
This transforms security from
a reactive process into a
real time posture dashboard.
On the right side, you see a deeper
example harness detecting a command
injection vulnerability inside
a pipeline, and providing a full
contextual explanation what the
vulnerability, what matters, what
it would impact, and how to fix it.
This is not just a scanner
returning a red cross.
This is a system that understand
the risk well enough to teach
you how to remediate it,
and this final piece
ties everything together.
Harness isn't just adding
AI feature to CICD.
It's becoming an AI native software
delivery platform where intelligence is
part of the foundation, not an extension.
Now the gif or gif you see
here is a good example.
This isn't a chatbot sitting beside
your pipeline scoring through logs.
This is AI inside the pipeline
execution, observing the behavior,
interpreting the failure, and
generating precise actionable guidance.
So let me highlight
the key advantage here.
AI that understands delivery, not
just text it, understand deployments,
manifest infrastructure, rollbacks
and traffic routing, the actual
mechanics of software delivery.
You have governance and verification
built into the intelligence layer.
Every incident rollback, successful
redeploy and policy violation
become training data for the system.
So it's continuously learning.
So this is what secure by default
delivery looks like in practice,
a platform that understand
context, verifies trust, monitors
behavior, and learns continuously.
And with that, we have
covered the full journey.
From the risks of AI native delivery
to the framework and the real
world platform implementing it.
So as we wrap up, I want to
bring the entire story together
in a few clear takeaways.
First, AI native delivery has
expanded the attack surface far
beyond traditional code vulnerability.
Second, our old security patterns
can't keep up with this New world.
Manual reviews, pointing time
scans, rule-based checks.
They were already struggling
before AI arrived.
And third, the future of DevSecOps
is secure by default systems.
Pipelines that can detect anomalies,
verify provenance, understand context, and
continuously learn from every deployment.
It is not about slowing teams down.
It's not about adding more
friction or more gates.
It's about building delivery
systems that are smart enough to
keep you safe as you move fast.
Systems that make the secure
choice the default choice, this
is the path forward for DevSecOps.
That is how we build confidence
in AI driven delivery.
Now before we fully wrap up,
I'd love to hear your feedback.
If you scan the QR code on the screen,
it'll take you to a very short form
where you can share what resonated
with you, what you'd like to.
Learn more about your feedback,
genuinely helps me improve and as thank
you, if you fill out this form, I'll
share the resources from this talk
with you, the slides, relevant links,
reference materials, and any deep
dive content that can help you take
these ideas back to your own teams.
Thank you again for spending your time
with me today and for being part of the
future of secure AI driven delivery.