Hello everyone.
This is Ma Car Busa.
I am a BN data specialist
with 18 years of experience.
Today I want to talk about something
every company struggles with.
How do we let people use data
easily while still keeping everyone,
everything, everything's secure.
We are living in a world
where data is everywhere.
And everyone want answers fast.
So let's walk through how self-serve
BI and DevSecOps can work together
in a simple practical way.
So here's our plan for today.
The huge growth of data, why
self-serve BI is becoming essential,
why security must be built into
everything, how AI is changing analytics
with some real time examples and.
Simple roadmap you can follow.
Let's get into it.
We are surrounded by more
data than ever before.
The world is hitting 1
75 terabytes of data.
That's a number.
So huge.
It's almost silly, but here's the problem.
Even though we have all this
data, companies still struggles
to answer simple questions.
Why?
Too much data?
Too many systems.
Reports take too long, and
everything is struck in silos.
So the business waits and waits.
This is where self-serve BI comes in.
Self-serve BI is simple, lets people get
their own answers without waiting for it.
Imagine if marketing,
hr, finance, operations.
Everyone could open a dashboard
and get insights instantly.
It saves time.
It speeds up decisions.
It removes body lengths, and instead
of waiting a week for a port,
people get answers in minutes.
That's the power of self serve.
But here's the catch.
When you give more people access
to data, you must also be careful.
That's where DevSecOps comes in.
It basically means build security
into every step from development
to deployment to daily operations.
Don't think about security at the end.
Think about it from the beginning,
just like you put on a seatbelt
before driving, not after.
This slide is important because
studies show 70% of BI projects fail.
Not because the technology is bad, but
because there is no governance, people
aren't trained, access is too open and
too restricted, or the system is too
complicated, so only 30% succeed, and they
do so because they balance two things.
Security and easy access.
Not too tight, not too loose, just right.
Ai, AI has changed the game completely.
Now, you don't need to write code our sql.
You can simply ask the system,
show me this month revenue.
What are the top reasons
for customer churn?
And the system answers.
AI can find patterns, predict
outcomes, and guide users.
It's like having a mini data analytic.
Analyst sitting on your shoulder.
But again, the more powerful the
tool, the more important the security.
This is the perfect mix.
Faster insights, more accurate
predictions, strong security,
working quietly in the background.
Users shouldn't have to fight the system.
The security shouldn't show
slow down and business.
When done right, you get
speed and safety together.
Here's a simple example.
A marketing team used AI powered BI to
check how their campaign campaigns were
performing before reports took hours.
After insights came in minutes, they
cut costs improved ROI and still
stayed compliant with privacy loss.
That's the goal.
Fast answers with zero risk.
One more example this time from hr, A
company used predictive analytics to
understand which employees might leave.
Not to punish everyone,
but to offer help early.
This only worked because
sensitive data has protected.
Only HR could see the details.
Every access was audited.
This is responsible analytics.
Good security starts with simple
things, give people access only what
they need, hide sensitive data for
people who shouldn't see it, and use
multiple multifactor authentication.
Make sure sessions automatically time out.
These control prevent, prevents accidental
mistakes and protect the organization.
Lineage is basically the story
of your data, where it come from,
what transforms happened, who
touched it, how it be being used.
This builds trust.
When leaders ask, where
did this number came from?
You have the answer, right?
It also keeps auditors happy.
Tools don't create success.
People do to make BI and security work.
Leaders must support it.
Users must be trained.
Policies must be clear and
continuous improvements must
happen when people understand the
why they follow them, and how out
here is an easy roadmap,
access your current state.
What data do you have and what gaps exist?
So design your architecture, build
the security and automation in mind,
and how do we enable users, train
them, support them, make tools simple.
And finally, monitor and option optimize.
So improve based on usage and
feedback and security needs.
This roadmap works for small teams
and large enterprises as well.
And finally the key takeaways,
let's, let me summarize the
whole talk in four points.
Security and accessibility should
work together, not against each other.
AI is speeding up analytics tremendously.
Culture matters more than tools and
DevSecOps ensures BI is scalable and safe.
If we get this right, we build a truly.
Data driven organization.
Thanks for thanks everyone for listening.
I'm happy to answer any questions and
talk through any of the challenges
that you're facing right now with
the within BI and data space.
You guys can reach out to me in LinkedIn.
Thank you.