Welcome to COM 42 DevSecOps 2024.
This is Praveen Kumar Vallabhoju.
I'm a Landovering.
And in this session, I'll be talking
about integrating cloud technologies
for enhanced healthcare system.
A comprehensive approach to
revolutionizing healthcare
efficiency and patient care.
Whenever I say cloud technologies, I
like to give some examples like AWS,
Azure, Google Cloud, and Autoclick Cloud.
I'll start with my table of content.
It has introduction, challenges in
healthcare, proposed solutions, AI seed
automation, Kubernetes for scalability,
containment with documentum, neural
network for AI driven insight, innovate
platform benefit, finally, conclusion.
Introduction, the need for digital
transformation in healthcare,
why now healthcare is facing
unprecedented challenges in
managing massive data volume.
The need for timely care and compliance
with evolving regulation is growing.
Solution.
Cloud technologies address these
challenges by enabling secure,
scalable, and efficient system.
Key insight.
A unified cloud platform can bridge
the gap between technological
limitation and healthcare demand.
Challenge in healthcare.
Current challenges in healthcare system.
Key challenges.
Data overload.
Lack of structure.
System for storing and
retrieving patient information.
System downtime.
Even a few minutes of system
downtime can jeopardize patient care.
Regulatory compliance.
Keeping up with HIPAA and other
global healthcare standards
is resource intensive.
Workflow inefficiency.
Manual process increases errors
and delay critical decision impact.
Without modernizing these challenges
will escalate as healthcare demand rises.
Proposal solution integrating
advanced cloud technologies.
CACD automation reduces
manual intervention and
ensures seamless deployment.
Whenever I say CACD, it's like
tools like GitHub and GitLab.
And Kubernetes handles dynamic
scaling to meet fluctuating demands.
So when I say Kubernetes, it's
like EKS, AKS, and other Kubernetes
platforms available in the market.
very much.
organizes structured and
unstructured medical data efficiency.
in other words, a documentum is an open
text product available in the market.
It's enterprise level management.
Neural network drives insights for
diagnostic, imaging, and decision
making, which can be achieved using
Python libraries like TensorFlow.
And other neural network
libraries like Keras.
Those libraries can help in
making the neural network work.
Outcome.
A unified platform that lowers
costs, ensures compliance,
and improves patient outcomes.
CSED.
Automation automating healthcare
application deployment.
Why does CSED matter?
Fast, reliable updates are crucial for
mission critical healthcare applications.
Automation reduces human errors.
and ensure constant deployment.
So when I say CRCD, it's like
a code commit, manual testing.
All these things can be automated in
the CRCD platform so that, deliverable
will be faster and reliable and secure.
And, with the key benefit, 30 percent
priority gain, teams can focus on
inline automation instead of manual
deployment, faster responses,
bug fixes, and feature updates,
rollouts, in hours instead of days.
Thank you.
Kubernetes for Scalability Dynamic
Resource Management Kubernetes How
Kubernetes helps Automatically scales
resources based upon their real time
demand Ensure critical systems remain
operational even during peak usage.
So it's like you have a hospital
website and it might be need like
more resources during the peak time.
Kubernetes will help in making autoscale
and which brings up the based upon the
traffic and CPU configuration we can
bring up the application to support with
the more parts and when there is low
traffic and low usage and based upon the
CPU you can bring down the parts usage.
So with this we can reduce the.
resource, management, which is equal
to a benefit, like 40 percent cost
reduction only uses resources when
needed, optimizing cloud expenses.
And it supports zero downtime
reliable service for the healthcare
professional and patients.
which means if we have a new feature,
we can just bring up the new feature.
Like we thought bringing up with the
current application going down totally.
We can just bring it up, do
the blueprint deployment.
which means we can just bring up the
newly featured application up and
just bring down the old feature down
using the pod reduction and bring up
the new feature up with more pods.
which means We can achieve the zero
downtime and without a patient even or
persons who are using this application may
not even know there is an application went
down for the significant amount of time.
Example, a hospital can scale
its systems during health crisis
without overhauling infrastructure.
Content management with Documentum.
Managing healthcare with Documentum.
One Documentum solves.
Organizers.
Structured and unstructured data
allows secure and quick access
to critical patient record.
So when I say organized structure
like lab results, we can just store
these lab results and document them
using metadata and all other fields.
And whenever we enter this data and
which is finally helpful for us to
return the document quicker than the
normal process of finding the document.
So with these, the benefit includes
like HIPAA compliance document handling
ensures data security since it is stored
in the enterprise content management.
So content management is designed for the
providing the security of the document.
So it provides the, as for
the complexity, provide the
security standard and efficiency.
Since we have the metadata on this
document, we can, it is, helps like
finding the document very faster
as compared to The normal process.
And with this example, document reduces
patient record retrieval times by up to
60 percent enabling quicker diagnosis.
Neural network for AI driven.
So transforming healthcare
with neural network.
Applications in healthcare.
Medical images detect anomalies in x
ray and MRI with a human level accuracy.
Predictive analysis
identify potential outcome.
Complications early.
Personalized treatment.
Suggest treatment plan
tailored to individual patient.
Impact.
Reduces diagnostic errors and support
evidence based decision making.
Surpasses human performance like
tasks like detecting cancer itself.
I just want to give some example.
So basically where we use neural network.
So example of patient A
goes to the patient B.
perform the CT scan and it may be any
way, it is due to, it may be due to
the device malfunction or the person
who is operating who need more, higher
accuracy of the image due to the
chance, high chance of, exposing the
radiation to the particular patient.
So with this neural network, we can
easily, you know, detect, is the person
exposed to higher radiation and, if it is
go, if it goes for the higher radiation,
we can start working on the, treatment
before it makes go to the cancerous cell.
With this slide, I'd like to give
the benefit of this platform, unified
cloud platform for healthcare.
Integrating solutions like CI, CD,
Kubernetes, Documentum, and AI for
seamless operation benefits workflow
automation eliminates redundancies and
improves collaboration, cost reduction,
pooling resources, lower operational
expenses, patient outcome, faster,
more accurate diagnosis and treatment,
scalable and feature ready, easily adopts
new technologies and growing demand.
example, hospital adapting unified
cloud platform reported 25 percent
improvement in patient care efficiency.
Conclusion.
The integration of advanced
cloud technologies into health
care system is non step.
It's not just a technological shift, but
a transformative approach to addressing
critical challenges in the industry.
By leveraging CI SEED Automation,
Kubernetes Documentum, and neural network,
SDK organizations can create a unified,
scalable, and intelligent infrastructure.
This integration optimized workflow
ensures compliance with stringent
regulations, reduces operational
costs, and most importantly,
improves patient care outcomes.
The unified platform fosters collaboration
among healthcare professionals, enhances
diagnostic accuracy, and enables timely
treatment, laying the foundation for a
data driven, patient centric healthcare
system as the healthcare landscape
continues to evolve with trends like
precision medicine and remote monitoring.
This integrated approach
provides the adaptability and
scalability needed to incorporate
emerging technology seamlessly.
So with this, I would like to thank
everyone who gave this opportunity to
speak up on these cloud technologies.
Thank you and have a great day ahead.
Bye.