Hello, good day.
My name is Victor Yonagibon and
I'm pleased to be speaking at
the conference to DevSecOps 2024.
And today I'll be talking about
people power security, the role of
sub skills in a DevSecOps culture.
There's a lot of focus today around
technical skills and, but not a lot of,
there's not a lot of discussion around the
role that sub skills could play to improve
the security culture of an organization.
So looking at how sub skills like
communication, like empathy, like
collaboration, like relationship
building can actually improve security
awareness within an organization.
And this has to do with people.
Thank you.
So First of all, we need to
understand that, there's a gap
in the cyber security landscape.
every day there are increase in
the type of cyber security threats.
the threats are evolving and
organizations need to stay vigilant.
Okay.
And since these threats are becoming
more and more complex, it's important
for organizations to rethink
the way they see cyber threats.
And in terms of in that interdisciplinary
approach, there needs to be a mix of.
Technical sub skills in solving
these challenges, right?
We've seen the rise of social
engineering attacks that does
not just rely on technical
expertise, but also people, right?
To hack somebody, right?
To hack people based on their
emotions and take advantage of them.
So there needs to be like, A combined
approach as regards solving cybersecurity
issues in the world we live in today.
So, how can we empower human element?
What are the importance of soft skills?
Why am I even talking about soft skills?
Is it important?
Why not?
Why should we not just focus on
the technical skills after all?
That is, isn't that what is always needed?
But we would see that soft
skills are like very important.
For instance, effective communication
is very crucial to the world.
Because if you are a cyber security
analyst, for instance, and you have to
give a presentation to the C level, maybe
to the CFO, to the CIO, to the CEO, they
may not be very technical people, and
you need to have effective communication
skills to explain to them why you are
doing what you are doing, why you need
to take certain decisions, to boost the
security posture of the organization.
And there needs to be a
collaborative approach.
See you.
aspect of things, collaborative problem
solving individuals who are security
consultants, whether it's in cloud
security on any type of security,
there needs to be, a voluntary or an
intentional, effort to collaborate, in
solving problems because some problems
would need, One or more departments in the
organizations for it to be solved, right?
So for instance, if the accounting
department of a of an organization is
hacked and the security team comes in
to solve that problem, the security team
needs to work in a collaborative manner.
With the accountant with the members
of the accounting department to ensure
that the root of the matter is found.
It doesn't need to be adaptability
because I'm cyber security is
a few that changes very fast.
People who want to walk in this line
who wants to be into cloud security and
in any other area of cyber security,
they need to be adaptable and they
need to be continuously learning.
You cannot just depend on
what you learned yesterday.
You need to depend.
You need to keep on learning.
and Lenny, right?
See, there's a lot of, issues.
They even around generating.
I aren't a I did fix, so it is
continually changing the attack surface
for many organizations keep increasing.
So therefore, the cyber security,
workforce needs to also keep learning and
keep staying at the top of their game.
So effective communication,
why is it important, right?
Effective communication is important
because it is important for you
as a cybersecurity consultant to
be able to translate technical
concept into non technical bits.
that a layman can understand.
In that way, you are able
to drive across your point.
If you are a cybersecurity awareness
lead, for instance, in your organization,
and you are in charge of security
awareness in your organization.
Remember that not everybody in your
organization understands things around
cybersecurity or technical bits.
They may have some idea of IT, but
they might not understand why they need
to change their passwords regularly.
They might not understand Why did
they need to check emails properly
so that they don't fall victim to
phishing emails and things like that.
So you need to simplify it
into contextualize this.
You need to break it down with
storytelling to ensure that you
the idea or whatever is the aim
of the training you're conducting.
Is, passed across to
them and it's possible.
Some people learn better when
you show them a picture of what
you're trying to talk about.
they are visual learners, right?
So that if you have a picture of
adding diagrams, your presentations
would actually really help.
maybe dashboards, that might actually
really help in terms of storytelling.
So even though you're a cyber
security consultant, Having that
skill of storytelling is like very
important for you to actually have.
Then collaboration and empathy.
We're looking at
collaboration and empathy.
Relationship building is actually key.
Being able to form relationships with
people who are not in your department.
Like I mentioned the example
of the accounting department
and the security team.
Being able to work in tandem with
members that are not in your department.
People who are not of the same
background from you, people who are of
different races or different cultures
or different religions, and that talks
about in relationship building here,
it is essential to understand that what
is important is for you to understand
diversity and inclusion, okay, diversity
and inclusion, you need to be able to
work in a diverse environment, you need
to be able to build relationships with
people of diverse races and religion,
very important, and you need to have
emotional intelligence, You need to
know what to say, when to say it, and
in what manner to actually say it.
Sometimes it's not really about
what you say, but how you say it,
mannerisms actually matter and body
language actually also matters.
Okay.
So collaborative problem
solving, I'm talking about that.
The fact that if you're able
to build a relationship with
people, I'm able to have empathy.
Collaborative problem
solving comes naturally.
Okay, comes naturally.
That sort of skill comes naturally.
So you're able to work with, people,
in a team, if you have that, if you're
able to build a relationship easily,
very important people skills to have.
Okay.
in terms of navigating complexity.
It is important that you
are not resistant to change.
Change is constant.
And you must, like I said,
you must keep yourself abreast
with changes in your field.
Okay.
You must embrace change and
you must not resist change.
Okay.
So you need to anticipate change
because cybersecurity is a field that is
constantly changing, constantly evolving.
there are, there's always something
new to learn, so in whatever
line of cybersecurity, there's
always something new to learn.
It's always something, a new train,
so it's very important and critical
thinking is also like very important.
if you're into cyber security, you
definitely have to have critical thinking.
How do you approach the situation?
How do you communicate properly?
How do you, when there's an incident,
when an incident happens, how do
you, how do navigate this instant.
How do you communicate to the public in?
How do you organize your team?
How do you respond effectively?
How do you make sure that okay,
your data backups are restored?
How do you ensure that okay, your business
continuity plan is you stick to it and
there's little minimal disruption to
your business when an incident occurs.
All this would take critical thinking.
Okay.
And there's also the
case of agile responses.
Okay, so being able to adapt Okay.
being able to tips of agile.
We're talking about the fact
that you can always make changes.
You can always go back and say, okay,
we didn't, I've gone through this
process, but I didn't see that we are
going to have this kind of circumstance.
Okay, let's go back and change something.
Okay.
So it's more like having a growth mindset.
Very important to have a growth mindset.
Been very important to talk about agile.
Look at by you being able to be
flexible in your approach to make
sure that you're able to solve
problems and navigate complexity.
So it is important for you as a
cybersecurity, workforce member
or a cybersecurity consultant,
or maybe a security analyst or a
cybersecurity engineer to understand
that you need to continuously learn.
I've said, I've spoken about this.
You need to embrace the fact that
if you're in cybersecurity, you
must be a lifelong learner and you
must cultivate a growth mindset.
I've spoken about that.
This closely relates to the Agile.
responses I spoke about, then it's also
important for you to be able to share
your knowledge and for you to be able
to share your knowledge, you need to
have effective communication skills.
So you see that all these soft
skills, they are like a chain,
they connect to each other.
Okay.
So you need to be able, if you are able
to have good relationship building skills.
You have good collaboration skills.
You have empathy.
Okay.
And you are willing to share you,
to be easy for you to, collaborate
and share knowledge in your team.
It's easy for you to mentor people.
Okay.
And it's easy for you to mentor people.
And it's also easy for you to be mentored.
Okay.
by people ahead of you.
Because if you have empathy, you have
emotional intelligence and you can
communicate effectively to say, Okay,
I think I'm lacking in this area.
I need to be.
I need directions on
how I can navigate this.
My learning journey and things like that.
your superiors can actually help
you and maybe place you on a
certification or something like that.
So you need to understand that.
Soft skills are not just,
something that is optional.
There are things that are, very like
important to have, it's important to
be able to have the soft skills and
so that to improve, your productivity.
Okay, in conclusion, I would just
say it's important for you to
cultivate a people centric mindset.
Okay.
Understand that you cannot
do cyber security alone.
You need people and the members of
your team are there to support you.
Okay.
So it's important you place, cyber
security, understand, embrace
the power of soft skills and
understand the human element.
is the center of, cyber security.
And of course, if an organization wants
to, build a resident, a resilient,
culture, they need to put people at
the center of that particular culture.
Whether it is for their security
awareness training, whether it is for
their incident response planning, the
future of cyber security lies in that.
in empowering the people who drive it,
and we empower these people by giving them
technical skills and also soft skills.
Thank you very much for listening.
Have a great day.
All right, I'm glad soft spoken
in this event, and, I hope
you enjoyed the presentation.
Thank you very much.