Hey everyone, Peter De Tender here,
more than happy to have you here, for
attending my session, discovering and
talking about DevSecOps as an approach,
I know it's a long title, DevSecOps as an
approach to building and deploying secure
applications by using shifting left.
So my name is Peter.
I'm a Microsoft technical
trainer at Microsoft.
Which means I'm actually helping our
enterprise customers across the globe
every single day, every single week.
Delivering, workshops where, no surprise,
Microsoft DevOps solutions, both Azure
DevOps and GitHub, are my prime, topics.
If you should have any questions
during the conference or you're
watching this later on as a
virtual recording, don't hesitate
reaching out on LinkedIn, Twitter.
I'm on BlueSky in the meantime as
well, where my handle is PDTIT.
Now, what we're going to cover in
the next 45 ish minutes is, the
baseline of DevOps from there.
Obviously I need to talk a bit
about shifting left because it's
part of the title of my session.
And then mapping the concept, the
culture of DevOps with some DevSecOps
tooling, where I'm primarily focusing
on Azure DevOps and GitHub within
our Microsoft DevOps product family.
And as you can figure out, I'm
going to have quite some demos.
Q& A is a little bit challenging,
although we're live during the
conference on the Discord channel.
But again, if you have any questions
afterwards, don't hesitate reaching out.
You already know a little bit
about me, and it's obviously more
important to know about the session.
But within the Microsoft role, I've
been a trainer for close to six
years now, before I joined Microsoft,
initially out of Belgium, supporting
the West European customers.
But about three years ago, managed
to move to the Redmond area.
And in the meantime, because it's
all virtual, workshops supporting
customers all over the globe.
And a little bit of free time that
I have, I somehow still like to,
share knowledge with communities
like presenting at conferences like
this one, writing technical posts.
Although on my blog, it's been
a little bit slow last couple of
months, but then also supporting,
publishers, writers, giving them
some ideas about writing content.
If I did not publish a book myself.
So with that, we're going to jump
into the actual topic of the session.
And starting with the concept of DevOps.
Now I'm pretty sure this is not the
first time you hear why we do have
the whole day wrapped around DevOps.
So I'm pretty sure this is
not, surprising if you've been
watching all the other sessions.
Now, my definition here, I would
say the Microsoft definition
is the union of people.
Processes and products to
enable continuous delivery
of value to an end user.
And you can think about this in
almost each and every concept.
Union of people that's really
bringing the teams together.
We have the developer teams, we
have the ops teams, and we're going
to try and break down that wall,
trying to create a bridge, you could
say, to bring those teams together.
Now, in my DevOps classes,
I always explain that it's
a lot more than just DevOps.
Why?
Because we also have product managers,
we have the business stakeholders,
we have, C level, we have marketing,
and obviously we also have the user
and the customer, depending a bit
on the scenario we're looking at.
But that's in short what
we're talking about.
Next to that, the process is the
automation piece, where I'll talk about
it a little bit more later on, and then
the product can be releasing a piece of
application, to your internal users and
obviously towards customers as well.
Now, I also have a Peter definition.
I think if, you're taking DevOps a
little bit serious and I've been training
and implementing DevOps at customers
all over the globe for the last couple
of years, so at some point in time,
I came up with my own definition.
So Peter's definition about
DevOps is integrating the culture.
delivering value to the end user,
relying on team collaboration
and workload automation.
Why is that important?
Because honestly, DevOps is 60
percent related to the culture.
Like again, thinking about the concepts,
breaking down the barriers, and only I
would say 40% Focusing on the tooling.
Now I'm not going to break down the
importance of tooling, but as in a lot of
scenarios, if you focus too much on the
tooling, like implementing all the tools,
but the teams are not collaborating,
there's no focus on automating anything.
Then in the end, you're
not really doing DevOps.
So that's my little twist on the DevOps
definition and focusing on the culture.
Now with that a little bit specific within
DevOps, like why should we do DevOps?
I would say it's really to
automate, not only yourself.
That's actually what I always talk about
in my DevOps workshops at the first couple
of minutes when starting, it's always
about, you're going to love DevOps because
it's really about automating yourself,
automating your job, as much as possible.
So wrapping this in a couple of,
slides, it means automating yourself
and even more so automating everything.
So the starting point is
the development cycle.
The developer is the team or the
individual, but preferably the
team, I would say, responsible for
building, writing the code, testing
it, thinking about the language,
NET, C sharp could be, like a Java
app, could be Node, could be Python.
So that's the flexibility we have.
Once the developer creates code, like
diving into Visual Studio, VS Code,
Eclipse, IntelliJ, so many other examples.
We're ready for the next step,
and that's validating code.
The validation means that we're not
only trusting the developer work by
checking the code, but we're also going
to integrate some other capabilities,
checking the syntax later on for security,
checking for vulnerabilities, for example.
To validate if the work that the
developer created is actually
working fine, that's where we're
going to move it into a package.
Now the package, you could say, in
a web application example, could
be like a web deploy zip package
in like the NET framework or
anything similar in other languages.
The package also allows us to actually
release it to deploy it right away.
And that's where we move
it into a running state.
The running state, don't
get fooled too much here.
Doesn't mean moving in production.
Running could be moving on your
local machine, going through a
bunch of validation steps, and then
running it in a test environment.
Running it in a test environment to do
functional testing, smoke testing, And
then maybe moving it into a staging
environment, where now you're going to
run against performance testing, maybe
against security validation testing.
And then ultimately, you want
to move it into production.
So the, the traditional way of
deploying releasing Dev and test
staging production is totally fine.
You could also look into,
canary early adopter.
Maybe you're more familiar with blue
green deployment, like a typical
scenario in containers, but in the
end, it's all doing DevOps in some way.
or the other.
And then last we have the operations,
which means that we're going to manage,
we're going to maintain it, we're going to
operate it, and then we technically, you
could say, go back to the starting point.
So that's the overview of my DevOps cycle.
From here, we're going to expand
on it a little bit more and
touching on the security of
each and every of those cycles.
So the cycles are not changing.
The cool thing here is that obviously
we're now moving into DevSecOps, where
we're still doing the same thing.
We're still automating ourselves.
We're still.
automating as much as possible,
but now we're going to squeeze
in security wherever possible.
Now, what does it mean?
Just a couple of highlights
in the development stage.
We're going to rely on, for
example, threat modeling.
I'll show you in a demo
later on what it means.
We're going to integrate
security code scanning.
linting and like a PowerShell script,
for example, or we're going to integrate,
built in security code scanning tools,
maybe relying on third party tools
to bring in other capabilities, maybe
because you're standardized across
different languages, which might
not be part of the core DevOps tool
that you're using to recognize code.
We're going to make sure that we're
storing credentials outside of the
source code, where I'll show you a little
bit of what Key Vault could look like.
And then the peer reviewing, it's not
really about the technology, it's not
about the tooling, but that brings
me back into the cultural piece.
where you could rely on colleagues to do
code reviews, to rely on them to actually,
I don't know, get advice on what it means
to actually write secure code, and so on.
In the validation stage, a lot
of it is quite similar to the
actual developing piece, right?
But that's where, again, we're going
to run code analysis, still validating
that we don't have credentials, that
we integrate, secret security, secret
management in again, Key Vault secret
store, or using the local secret options
like in a Visual Studio NET scenario.
In the end, no longer storing code,
secrets in the app settings JSON file.
That's the main message.
We can integrate approvals,
which means that we're going
to use, source code branching.
We're going to use pull requests and
it actually allows us to validate
code submissions before they actually
get merged into our source control.
Integrating unit testing.
And then if you want another example,
if you're building, containerizing
applications, then we can also integrate
container vulnerability scanning, which
is obviously the same concept as code
scanning, but not only scanning code,
but also the container wrapper around it.
Then once we move into the next cycle,
that's closer to the running state, right?
We're going to secure
infrastructure as code.
Because up till now, in my examples
only touched on writing code, being
the developer, but it's Relevant in
DevOps if we also start embracing
automation for the operations team.
So if you're using public cloud, you
could look into Azure templates, bicep
arm, terraform in different clouds.
Terraform could, again, be a good
option or, cloud formation in AWS where
again, we rely on infrastructure as
code writing template syntax to deploy
something in a cloud environment.
Integrating container scanning,
integrating quality gates, allowing
you to run your release pipelines,
but following certain conditions.
If the conditions are not met, then
we're not even releasing the pipeline
or not running the release pipeline.
And then obviously everything you should
know about managing, securing your cloud
environment, integrating Azure network
security, integrating Microsoft Defender
products could be a good option if you're
using cloud on the Microsoft side at
least, and then a little bit more on the.
infrastructure security, integrating
overall network security,
maybe pen testing, totally
away from developing and code.
And then we're going to run it.
So that's again, where we
have the security capabilities
from the target platform.
Again, using Azure as an example,
would be RBAC role based access, and
again, still validating credentials.
They're not part of code, but we
still need to start them somewhere.
So you could use like app settings,
variables or environment variables,
app configuration, and again,
preferably using Key Vault.
And then once everything is
up and running, you could look
into something, like a Azure.
Defender for cloud, where it's our
security posture tool, allowing you
to get a view on your security state,
looking into threat detection and
mitigation, like the actual operational
piece, how to not only detect issues,
but how to prevent them, but also do
some investigation, creating incidents
where out of the Microsoft world, it
could, for example, be a tool like
Sentinel or any other SIEM solution.
If you want to use and look into that.
Now, what we see in the field over the
last, I don't know, 20 something years,
that's where I started my career in 96.
So I've been around for a while and this
is basically what we did on prem cloud
hybrid Where the security focus was
always happening all the way at the end
why because that's where the runtime is
running That's also the environment which
is typically under attack now nowadays.
We actually find out and not only
nowadays I mean we've been like made aware
about this for multiple years already.
When an attack happens, it's typically way
too late, which means it's hard to detect.
It's hard to fix.
It's probably cost,
costly to try and fix it.
And every now and then, like a ransomware
attack, there's a lot of information
available from companies in the news
who actually didn't even manage to
recover from ransomware attacks.
So all this to say that instead of waiting
all the way to the end of the cycle.
once it's only running in
production, that's where we're
going to validate security.
The mindset now is we're
going to shift left.
And that's the clarification I
would say of the session title.
And even more I would say, don't
just think about it in the, all the
way at the left, like the planning
phase, the developing phase, but also
make sure that security comes back in
each and every step of the scenario.
That's pretty much it from
the presentation perspective.
So from here, it's going to shift, quite
fast to a couple of different demos.
I just have a few slides as a
placeholder for the actual demos to
know what I'm, supposed to show you.
So I'm going to start with, the first one,
and again, I'm mixing some of Azure DevOps
with GitHub to show you that, again, it's
not, Always about the tooling, it's a
lot more about understanding the culture,
the concept, and knowing what it's about.
assuming that we are a developer,
or a DevOps member, I'm gonna open
up my DevOps portal, there we go.
This is my, DevOps world, so I'm
using Azure DevOps Cloud Service.
And one of the first scenarios we
have is the project abstraction.
So the way we organize this
is obviously permission based.
We're going to create projects,
and within each and every project,
we have, the permission model.
So in this case, let's say Peter
is working as a DevOps team
member on, my retail application.
I'm going to give Peter specific
permissions, can be owner, maybe
not even required to be an owner,
creating contributor permissions or
so many other different levels, and
I'm working on another project where
maybe I'm just a project manager.
I don't need any technical permissions
to create code, to upload code, to run
pipelines, and I have that flexibility.
If you do not have the permissions.
to see the project or to
participate in the project team.
You're not even seeing
any of those details.
And then within we can use the different
Azure DevOps features where for now, since
I was talking about, source control, which
would be step number one, integrating
your code in a source control scenario,
which would be get based source control.
using Azure DevOps repos or using
GitHub and I'll show you that
in the next couple of minutes.
So I'm running my application and
one of the scenarios I have here is
a repository where I'm storing code.
So this level here comes back
here and I'm storing some code.
I got my Azure pipelines and down here in
my source folder, that's where I actually
have my web application using NET code.
I'm mixing my Azure deployment, like
infrastructure as code, you could say with
Azure Bicep, and I'm running some images
and whatnot in one single repository.
Works totally fine, but there
might be a better option.
The better option is what I have in
another project, where I'm using a
scenario that's now called multi repo.
So in this example, the
logic is roughly the same.
I still have my eShopOnWeb,
that's my actual application
code for my retail website.
But now I got some ARM templates
for Infrastructure as Code.
I'm migrating my ARM templates into
Bicep, so I'm going to store them
in yet, a different repository.
And the mindset behind it is that I can
integrate my source control permissions.
into my repo as well.
If my developer who's writing code
working on the retail website, I
only need to give them permissions to
interact with my application code repo.
They don't see anything else
from the infrastructure side and
obviously the other way around.
So that's an easy solution
multi repo model to split up
where am I storing my code.
From here, let's say we're
moving on in the stack, and
I'm going to make some changes.
So I'm in my application.
I'm just going to use an Azure container
example, and I'm in the main repo.
Inside, I'm going to make some changes.
I'm going to use the Azure DevOps
portal to show you how easy it is to
edit code, but in a real life scenario,
you would do this from your local
machine, your development environment,
making changes, committing the changes,
synchronizing to the repo backend.
But I'm going to save you all that
to speed up my demo a little bit.
So I'm going to make a change here.
I'm just going to add, comment, Peter
update software or something similar.
Not too important.
I'm going to commit.
I'm going to confirm, and
that's pretty much it.
Now what happens here is okay,
but it's also quite tricky.
Why?
Because now I'm overwriting code, and
this could potentially break my code.
So what we need is a mechanism.
that I'm going to protect my main code.
And that's where branching and pull
requests and approvals will come in.
So what we're going to
do is back in our repos.
And from there we go into branching.
And as you can see, I already have
multiple branches and behind the branch,
I can interact my branch policies.
So what I would recommend
here is for example.
forcing reviewers, remember I talked
about the peer reviewing, which
means that if I enable this, I can
specify how many reviewers, and I
could actually specify who is part
of the reviewing permission team.
And if, some code submission, a
new update or update in the code,
is getting submitted, that's
going to trigger a pull request.
And I'm not even allowed to
merge if there's no approval.
So that's, a good option there.
There's a few other settings, but I guess
the baseline, should be okay enough.
So if I take one step back, I go
back into, whoops, my branches.
Let me go back to my
repo, back to my branch.
I'm gonna, Open up the other branch.
So I got the main, I got a second one.
And whenever we make a change
in another branch besides main,
it means that now we cannot even
directly update the main branch.
So we need to offer a pull request.
now a pull request is actually a
suggestion, you could say, where
my colleague Jason here, made some
updates in code and now suggesting
them for me to merge them into main.
We can still provide a title,
we define a description and
again, defining the reviewers.
And that's, I would say bringing in
again, the culture, like we're not
just, allowing any developer, any DevOps
team member to do whatever they want,
but we actually want to stimulate that
team collaboration and evaluating that.
The
next step in our shifting left cycle
was after we have code being uploaded
into our repos, which by the way,
and GitHub is the same thing, we can
shift to code scanning, code security
scanning, and credential management.
So I'm going to shift back to my
DevOps environment where I'm going
to switch back to my other project.
I have my code.
I'm going to run my pipeline.
And as you can see, my
pipeline has been running.
And it's detecting
security vulnerabilities.
Some outdated packages,
known vulnerabilities.
How does this work?
What I did is injecting
a code scanning tool.
How do you inject a code scanning tool?
It's technically doing the
same thing in your pipelines.
Just running NET build, NET run,
NET publish, for example, but
now also integrating scanning.
Next to that, What I have here in
my environment is overall DevOps
code coverage, and I could also
integrate with third party tools.
Now, how do you decide
which tool you want to use?
it's quite easy.
You go into marketplace.
visualstudio.
com and you can look for
extensions for integrations.
You can install security
tools in Visual Studio Code.
Or you can switch to Average DevOps,
searching for security, and it's going to
give you a pretty extensive list of tools.
Some of them are specific to, containers.
Aqua here is a pretty good option.
Snyk is a pretty good option.
The built in Azure DevOps
Security Scanner is a good option.
And probably so many other ones as well,
but I don't really know all of them.
And it also depends a bit on the language,
the development language you're using,
like PowerShell code, NET code, Java
code, where some scanners might be better
than others for that specific language.
Another option is not using Azure DevOps.
Obviously nothing wrong with it,
but what we can do is using GitHub.
GitHub.
The baseline of GitHub is about the same.
Now, what we can do with GitHub
is, again, creating repositories,
using source code, using branching,
using, reviewing everything I
talked about on the DevOps side.
So that's all quite similar.
The look and feel is obviously slightly
different, but apart from that,
it's actually doing the same thing.
We're now inside a repo.
I'm just going to grab one of these.
I got a pretty outdated one with a
sample React app from years back.
now I'm going to dive in security and
the beauty of GitHub code scanning
is that it's available by design.
So you don't have to go out and search
for your own tools on the marketplace.
It's already part of the platform
for public and private repos.
Only thing you need to do is
deciding if you want to use it.
Yes or no.
So you just enable or disable.
And then from there you get,
Dependabot, which is like a
scanning, scheduled scanning tool.
And it's going to report back about
your potential vulnerabilities.
And if you allow it to, it can
actually help you fixing the problem
by moving up a vulnerability package
versioning into a newer version
that's actually fixing the problem.
Something like that.
The other part here is
credentials and secret management.
Now, why is that important?
Because something like this could happen.
This was literally a
screenshot, in already some
years back, like January 2021.
So four, almost five years ago,
four years ago, where my personal
access token, like a secret, a
secured key, got published to GitHub.
Now, if you know a little bit about
Peter, in the meantime, there's one
thing and it's Peter not sharing
personal access tokens on GitHub.
So what happened here, I was delivering
a workshop on DevOps, interesting
enough, showing how to create a DevOps
personal access token, obviously
sharing my screen during the whole
day, and one of my learners was
actually screen capturing recording.
And then finding the personal access
token in the recording, which obviously
was not allowed and then storing it
in one of their own GitHub repos.
The cool thing was that GitHub
detected this right away.
And within just a couple of minutes
already sending me a notification,
because obviously they recognize
the personal access token linked
to an Azure DevOps organization.
And even more interesting, you
could go okay, makes sense.
You're working for Microsoft.
So it's probably Microsoft helping here.
but it was not even related
to the Microsoft relationship.
It's just a core functionality
of GitHub built in security.
If you have Azure resources, storage
account keys, SQL connection strings,
AWS relational databases, personal
access tokens, and whatnot, GitHub
security documentation allowing
you to validate which of your tools
And the corresponding secrets can
already be recognized out of DevOps.
Sorry, out of GitHub security.
The other piece in the demo was Key Vault.
So how does that work?
Imagine I have my pipeline, and in my
pipeline I want to run some variables.
So you could create a variable group Where
you're going to store some variable names.
So I'm using this for my demo deployments.
If I want to deploy like Azure
containers, I need a container name.
I'm going to use a variable, but
then I also need, some specific
secrets, like in this case here,
Azure Communication Connection String
to interact with some AI services.
And I'm going to store
them as a secret key.
How do you get into a traditional text
string and turning it into a secret?
That's what this little
icon here is doing.
It's going to encrypt it within
your library and then transforming
them into an asterisk next to
that, you can define permissions.
So this is another security model,
which of my pipelines in my project
can connect to this library.
Instead of repeating the same,
variables in each and every pipeline,
you could move them into the library.
The other nice thing is that instead
of storing them encrypted here,
we can now integrate The variable
list in DevOps with Key Vault.
There is a small catch, I would say.
If I enable this link secrets
to Key Vault, it's going to
clear all my variables here.
So it's like forcing you to
have a dedicated, library of
variables for Key Vault and, for
anything that's not Key Vault.
What is Key Vault itself?
So in the Azure platform, You
have Key Vault as a service.
And what you're going to do
here is defining keys, secrets,
and if you want, certificates.
Now, I told you at the start, as a
developer, it is recommended to not
store your connection strings, API
keys, and so many other examples
hard coded in your application.
what we've seen in the field is that a
lot of customers are, Indeed, not storing
these in application code anymore,
but storing it in Azure settings.
So what it means is if I go into
functions or web apps or databases,
it's all based on the same concept.
I can.
Pull up my variables, so I
go into my Azure functions.
I open up my.
Settings an inside my
environment variables.
I'm going to play with my variables.
The old way is again, no longer in
code, but storing them inside Azure.
What's the benefit if it's not
in code, but it is in Azure?
Because you have Azure role based, sorry.
You have Azure role based access
to define who gets access to the
Azure platform and actually manage,
interact with our environments.
So I got my App Insights,
instrumentation key, just as an example.
And it's connecting to.
value.
So even App Insights, like a monitoring
tool for applications, requires a key.
And that's what you see here.
There we go.
I might have a connection
to a storage account.
So I create a variable in my application,
in my web app, in my function,
and I need a connection string.
So that's what I'm showing here.
This connection string, again,
should be treated confidential.
And that's where now Key Vault comes in.
So in my third example here, I'm
connecting my app, my function into Azure
AI services, and it needs an API key.
To do that, we need the API key
as the variable, but now this
time the value is no longer
pointing to the connection string.
It's not having the actual content.
It's not having the keys, the
connection strings, but it's
now pointing to Key Vault.
The cool thing here is that for the
look and feel, the experience of your
app, you're not changing anything.
The only thing you need to do in the
app code is adding the Key Vault package
for your development language, allowing
the product to recognize what is,
that add Microsoft Key Vault string.
From here, it's pointing to Key Vault.
Microsoft Key Vault connecting to a Key
Vault URI, inside Key Vault connecting
to the secret, and from there pulling
up the computer vision API key variable.
So how does this work inside my Key Vault?
This is my Key Vault object
inside keys and secrets.
I'm going to define my actual variables.
And from there, I'm going
to store the actual key.
Now, this, by the way, is not the key.
This is just, a unique object ID.
The key itself is hidden.
It's secretly valued.
It's encrypted.
And in my variable settings, this
is the only thing I need to specify.
Allowing you to really integrate
security, moving all secrets away
from code, storing it into Key Vault.
And on top of that's the other
piece in the security story.
We're going to define explicit
permissions that not everyone
can connect to Key Vault.
So what we do here is, after adding
the keys, We're going to move into
access policies or using Azure role
based access would be another option.
That's the newer way of managing
permissions where I'm specifying, hey, my
dear function, you get, get permissions
because you only need to get the keys.
You don't need to change them.
And for example, in the same way, Peter,
the admin account can do get and list.
Now there's a little bit of a
chicken and egg scenario here.
Why?
Because someone, like being Peter
in this case, my admin, my DevOps
team member, still needs to add the
original initial key into the story.
now you could go what's the point
in storing all that encrypted if
Peter actually And that's where
key vault key rotation comes in.
In our Microsoft documentation
you'll find guidance what it
means to actually rotate keys.
What it means is, for example,
if I go into a storage account,
imagine I have my access keys,
Manually, I'm going to
run the key rotation.
It's going to change key
one and key two over here.
I'm going to copy paste them.
I'm stored the connection string
or the key in Keyval, and I'm done.
You can automate this process like
set rotation reminder, and you can
interact with Azure Automation running
a Cloud Shell script, running PowerShell
script, running Azure Automation script
to run that key rotation for you.
Technically, it's updating key one,
storing it in Key Vault, updating
key two, storing it in Key Vault,
but from an app perspective, your app
is pointing to the Key Vault object.
It's not pointing to the
Key Vault object content.
So that's, in short, how that part works.
So that was pretty much it on
storing secrets not in code.
And if you have the, I would say the
correct code scanning tool, it will
actually detect that you do have keys.
And then the solution is moving
them out into a key vault scenario.
Next option we touched on in our shifting
left overview is what about containers?
So what I'm doing here on
the slide is just a listing
of container scanning tools.
There's again so many different ones.
I mentioned Aqua without
doing any marketing for them.
It's just one of the so many tools.
I have Qualys here.
Why Qualys?
Because we have it as an integrated
security scanning feature inside, for
example, Azure Container Registry.
So that's going to be my next demo.
How to integrate container scanning
as part of our DevOps process.
There's a couple of
different options to do that.
I'm going to switch back
to my DevOps environment.
I don't need this anymore.
I'm getting a bit lost in my
DevOps and browser portals.
Okay, but we're back in business.
Cool.
So one option is using Sonar.
Sonar is one of the so many
third party code scanning tools,
also valid for containers.
The way it works, you have your build
pipeline, like scanning code, validating
code, or compiling code, where now
we're gonna integrate a scanning task.
If I open up the pipeline syntax,
I'm installing NuGet package.
Yes, I know this is an updated version.
It's an old sample, but
that's totally fine.
We're going to run NET, restore.
Later on, we're going to
run NET test and so on.
And what we're doing now is
integrating a third party scanning
tool as part of the pipeline.
What this is going to do is, again,
doing the same thing, looping through
the code, running the build pipeline,
but as part of the build process.
It's now importing the latest updated
patron files from this third party
scanning tool, and it's going to
run it and providing the details.
So the outcome of this, if I look
into the actual pipeline run,
it's going to do NuGet, restore.
net, import, export, all that
cool fun, preparing the analysis,
building the solution, running some
functional testing, smoke testing,
anything like traditional DevOps.
And from there it's
integrating the scanning.
Oops, sorry, that was a bit
too fast running the scanning.
I wanted to move this little guy out
of the way, but I couldn't get there.
There we go.
So in my scanning task here, it's now
downloading this third party vendor
sonar pattern files and running a
scanning and then looping through all
the scanning detection mechanisms.
And then eventually, depending on
the outcome, depending on how many
vulnerabilities, depending on what kind
of criticality, depending on so many
parameters you can define, it's gonna flag
the pipeline as a successful build or not.
You can reuse this information
once you move into release.
So what we can do here is now going back
into our pipelines Go into a new pipeline.
I'll show you the classic interface
like the more graphical interface,
but the concept is the same.
Imagine we're going to publish
to our Azure app service.
Where now I can enable my,
pipeline quality gates.
Now, before I can do that, I
need to define some settings,
which I wasn't planning on doing.
I can do pre.
deployment.
I can integrate quality gates and
I can validate My third party sonar
cloud in this example, or running
rest API calls, checking with Azure
policy, is the environment I'm
publishing to actually compliant
with PCI with hyper with ISO 27 one.
And if not, then I'm not
allowing the pipeline release.
So I'm not publishing my code,
something like that, or here with a
sonar example that I was using before.
It's going to allow me to run the
sonar scanning during the build, and
then during the release, I can go
back to it, Hey, can you check with
the results of my build from a sonar
cloud perspective and yes, for any
other third party tool for that matter.
And based on that, we're going to give you
green light or not to literally move into
that CICD end to end automation concept.
Last little piece here, and
then I think we're going to wrap
it up, is Defender for Cloud.
So I talked about Defender a little
bit in the introduction, like setting
the scene on DevOps and integrating
security, where one of the pillars
was all the way at the end, runtime.
Your workload is running in Azure.
I showed you functions, showed you
web apps, showed you Key Vault.
We're now out of Defender for
Cloud, It's going to create
a security posture overview.
So it's not a security slash
protection mechanism as such,
although it actually comes with
those features for specific Azure
scenarios, but that's the paid version.
But even in the free edition that
you can just enable in your Azure
subscriptions, it's going to
list up security recommendations.
You have secure score, so a ranking
some, Like a set of points, you
could say, the more points, the
more secure your environment runs.
And based on that, it's also giving
you, an overview of your resources,
a potential security risk, any
alerts, attack path, and whatnot.
If I drill down on my security score
within my subscription, I open up
my recommendations and it's going
to list up anything that I should
try and fix in my environment.
So from here, I could, for example,
filter on containers because that was
the last piece I was talking about.
And it's going to show me you, Peter, are
running a repo, like a container registry.
Inside there's a container image, and
you should run a vulnerability scan.
If I have something else in another
Azure resource, like here, a storage
account, it's going to show me
public access to that storage account
should be disabled, and so on.
Since we're talking about DevOps,
inside my Defender for Cloud
is now also DevOps security.
What it's doing here is allowing you
to read out your repo state from Azure
DevOps, from GitHub, and bringing
in that security view into your, or
the DevOps security view into your
security team's overall management.
I just need to refresh.
Because it looks like
it's not coming through.
There we go.
So I showed you my DevOps, I showed you
my GitHub, and these are all my repos.
So my React example here that I
used in one of my demos to show
you the built in GitHub Dependabot
CodeQL security scanning tool is now
also moved into my security view.
I can open it up and I can see
what is the security state?
As no secrets.
GitHub was reporting some security
issues, and they're now nicely
reported in my security environment.
To again, once more focus on the
culture, bringing down the walls between
DevOps teams, operations team, DevOps
security teams, and allowing everyone
to get a view on the security state.
Cool.
So with that, I'm going
to wrap it up from here.
I started with the
Peters DevOps definition.
I'm pretty sure no one remembers, but you
can move all the way back to the start.
What I'm doing now is
updating my definition.
It's no longer just developing
a culture of delivering value
to end users, relying on team
collaboration, workload automation.
That's just doing DevOps.
But now we're also integrating
end to end security.
And that's the baseline of the story.
So with that, what did I cover?
I started my session 43 minutes ago with
setting the scene on DevOps, talked about
the concept of shifting left, and then
the majority of the session was touching
on the tooling, Azure DevOps, GitHub
as the Microsoft DevOps solutions, and
then the second half of the session,
or three quarters of the session, was
jumping around across different demos.
I hope you enjoyed.
I hope you learned something new
around DevOps, around DevSecOps, a
little bit on the Microsoft story.
There's obviously a lot more
that we need to cover, but I
only got 45 minutes to do that.
I hope it gave you a little
bit, of, awakening, a little
bit teasing your brain.
If you're part of DevOps and you're
like, I had no idea how to integrate
security, why it's important.
Then I hope I helped you a bit
understanding that message.
With that, I'm going to close out.
Thank you for watching my session.
Thank you for being here.
Have Don't hesitate, please,
don't hesitate reaching out if
you should have any questions.
Petender at Microsoft.
com, PDTIT on LinkedIn, on
BlueSky on Twitter, but I'm
not that active there anymore.
And overall, if you forget
anything else, I would say aka.
ms slash PDTIT is going to send you to my
blog where you find all the other details.
Thank you for now.
Enjoy the rest of COM 42 DevSecOps
and hope to see you again in
any of our other sessions.