Hello all.
I'm going to talk about how do we
leverage sales data analytics to optimize
the pharmaceutical drug launches.
We'll do a deep dive on the technical
analysis of using predictive modeling
and real time market insights.
I think we'll cover a few topics.
I think we'll talk about,
Standard, challenges in the,
in, in the drug launches.
Also, how the data analytics,
can be used as a solution.
what are some of the
important KPIs do we use?
also talk about predictive
modeling and s impact.
on, on those launches, we look at
one of the case study, also we'll
talk about, the real time analytics,
and also some of the best practices.
And the recommendation and then we'll
look at the some of the key results and
impact, starting with just giving us more
background and challenges like why is such
an important, issue to talk about, right?
So to develop a drug, in the, in the
highly regulated environment, it takes.
On an average 2.
6 billion to develop one, drug and then
60 70 percent of the revenue Produced by
this drug is achieved in first six months.
So Think about the first few months
of the launches are very critical a
lot of products a lot of drug at their
initial phase, they fail to meet Their
sales goals and protection, and then
typically around like you would see 30 40
percent, Below on the expected revenue.
Also, you can see our development
costs are also going, high every year
so with that I think it's an important
problem to solve and then We are talking
about like how the data analytics
how the sales data can be used as a
solution So I think the very first
case is, predictive models, right?
So right now You When you think
about pharma industry, we have
very good models with more than 85
percent accuracy in forecasting.
Also we do have a lot of real time
data, millions and millions of data
points for the patients, for the
doctors, for the hospitals, which
can be used for the decision making.
Also when we are deploying the
field force, a lot of AI model can
be used to increase the efficiency.
And then I think we have seen, when there
are the launches which are more analytics
driven, they have a higher penetration
as compared to your traditional, methods.
Also, we see, an improvement on
the launch trajectory in the first
12 to 18 months of the launches.
I think once you apply these predictive
models, and real time insights, the
KPIs play a crucial role, right?
So that you know that, are you
on track on the launch, right?
Are you on track to get to your goals?
As we talk about, I think the first
six months are very critical, like
60 percent of the lifetime revenue
is achieved in the first six months.
so in that time, I think the prediction
accuracy is definitely an important piece.
We need to have 85 90 percent
prediction accuracy, using all
the advanced analytics methods.
A market penetration or
adoption by the early doctors.
That's also an important KPIs
to measure, by different teams.
also if you want to make sure we're
reducing the forecasting variance,
based on the machine learning models.
I think now maybe let's talk more about
the, how the predictive models are using,
what kind of models do we make and like
what kind of framework do we utilize?
So I think that the very important
one is, the doctor adoption
or the physician adoption.
one of the very, popular models
are doing segmentation based
on these doctor behavior.
And then there's a lot
of data coming, right?
There's like thousands and
thousands of data based on these
doctors, their prescription, their
demography, their sales information.
So these all can be used
to segment these doctors.
into different bucket, right?
And then we can have a different
tactics for each of the segment.
Also, when we think about the
real time engagement, that also
are doing a very good accuracy.
the use of these ML models, we are
reducing a lot of variance when we think
about the forecasting of this launches.
there's a lot of different machine
learning algorithm, used to
analyze, and prescribe, patterns.
you look at the engagement metrics.
we look at a lot of patient level data.
which is your transactional level,
medical gains, pharmacy claims.
we also use a lot of ensembled model,
like random tree to make sure, there's
a stability right in the prediction, and
we are making sure that we are baking in
all the market condition in these models.
I think maybe, a case study, and this
is not a real data, but, think about,
there's a pharma company, they're trying
to launch a product in type 2 diabetes,
disease area, which is a very big area.
Yeah.
when you think about the market, like
you're talking about, maybe 20 to
30 billion dollars of market value.
And there are already a lot of
competitors, there are already
8 to 10 market competitors,
with very high market share.
So when we apply these methods, when
you apply the segmentation, you do a
lot of real time insights, have the
analytics KPIs in use, definitely you,
you achieve a very high 72 percent
prescriber reach in, in first three
months, which is very important.
Also the new patients who are
starting on therapy that also
exceed your target, right?
So for example, in this scenario, we said,
Oh, we want to reach to 12, 000 patients
in first three months, but because
of the use of all of these analytics
tool, we are reaching to 14, 500.
Okay.
also, we are able to do a lot well
in different payor channels, like if
you think about commercial, Medicare,
Medicaid, so these, and then I think
that the other element is when you
think about the territories, so you
can do also a lot of AI based territory
optimization, and then look at a lot of
patient journey, like how patients first
diagnose when they get treated, what is
this whole adoption funnel looks like,
and then because of the real time data
processing, we are able to process a lot
of thousands and thousands of data points
across these doctors and the patients.
Now, maybe let's pivot more on the
real time, analytics infrastructure.
as we talk about now, we have a lot
of data elements across doctors.
patients, payer, hospitals, right?
And then to process these data
elements, we also have, most of the
pharma companies are investing a lot
on having, big data warehouses where we
have a lot of processing capacity which
can, where you can have your analytics
tools sit on top of that, right?
We're talking about like processing
capacity in, in, in petabyte, right?
So a lot of real time
data, very fast processing.
and then with that, also all of
these, I think the data nowadays
have very good capture rate.
So capture rate means how much of
the actual data is captured, right?
So when we get like a third party
data, We can see that it covers 94
95 percent in the pharmacy side, and
then these Claims or these transaction
also have different layers of quality
checks right to make sure That these
are highly accurate when we are trying
to use in the predictive models, right?
It's garbage in garbage out So the data
quality is very important So that's where
there's a lot of data stewardship and
data quality checks are in place When we
are processing all of these big data sets
And then with that, because of the real
time market insights, it also allows us
to respond in a very faster way, right?
So we can have a market response
as soon as like three days, right?
When we see something and important
insights out of data, we can, we can have
a change in tactics in, in, in three days.
Also the data validation, like
the data you get is like 99.
8 percent accurate.
So with the having a right infrastructure
in place, you can process of tons
of data also having a proper quality
checks can give you a higher accuracy
and that eventually allow us allow
companies to react in a very fast time.
Also, Thinking about the best practice
and recommendation in the context
of the product launches or drug
launches in the pharma industry.
We talked about that the data
integration is important, right?
Because you're getting data from
different data sources, right?
So you have like sales data, you have
demographic, maybe you have the social
feed like this, like tax mining.
So all of these data has to
be integrated together, right?
So there's a lot of De identified or
encryption decryption happening with
which is done by a dedicated companies
right to make sure there's this compliance
and privacy when we are looking into the
data for the doctors and the patients.
there's definitely a very high
compliance standards across
pharmaceutical industry, right?
it has to go through a standard,
encryption decryption model where
we cannot identify a certain
doctor or certain, patient.
And then also a lot of time when
the data is not available, we also
do a lot of data amputation, right?
To make sure.
That even for the missing
data, can we predict what can
be a possible data outcome?
data integration is an important
piece, when you're trying to
combine all of this data together.
Also, I think when you're trying
to do, analytics deployment,
either you talk about predictive
models, or an AI model, right?
I think a lot of times these models
are expensive to implement, right?
It requires a lot of infrastructure
from the IT side, and a lot of
investment from the business side.
I think the best, I think a good practice
when you're trying to do any new model,
you can start with a pilot, right?
You can start with, one smaller area.
for example, you can start a pilot
just for the California state and
try to see, based on that, are you
able to get, a higher response from
the doctor or for the patient, right?
And if you see, a good successful
model and then the same thing can be
applied for the whole nation, right?
so this pilot implementation is
very popular, in the industry.
and then you can also always
make finer tune based on what
we see on the pilot side.
I think the other important thing is
we talk about the KPIs, but then, we
need to have a lot of dashboards, for
different teams, like sales may want
to see a different KPIs, marketing
may want to see a different KPI.
So having a dashboard, which
is updated more on the frequent
manner, like weekly or daily, right?
and then having an important KPIs,
is an important thing, right?
And then I think the.
The other layer on top of that you can
also we can also create a lot of alerts
which are automated So we I don't have
to look at the dashboards every day But
it does create an alert right when it
try when it identify an important pattern
in the data also based on that, the
kpi dashboard there should be a proper,
resource allocation and optimization.
So these are like some of the
best practice and recommendations,
especially from the analytics side
and the infrastructure side when
you're trying to launch a product.
I think we talk about, and these are some
very high benchmarking number, right?
When you think about, When you apply
these best practice, when you apply these
analytics model and AI, you see almost 45
percent higher market penetration, right?
Compared to the traditional model,
your launch trajectory also improves
a lot, based on the insight.
And then real time data analytics
allow you to response in a few
days if there's any market event.
Also, we have seen, an increase
in the prescriber engagement, we
increase in the patient engagement
on these AI driven models.
so I think, now I think I want to maybe
conclude and I think what are the key
takeaways from all of these things, right?
a sales data analytics is definitely,
and key piece, when you're launching
a product in the pharma industry, it
definitely have a measurable improvement.
it gives you a higher market penetration.
It gives you a higher Doctor engagement.
It also give you an operational efficiency
real time analytics Enable you to make
like agile decision making and you can
navigate through a complex Market tool
like where you have so many competitors
and so many market events happening at
the same time Also, I think the advanced
predictive models also provide like very
high accuracy in the forecasting which
Eventually help you to do a resource
optimization Integration of these, the AI
models, and I think, it definitely going
to improve the model accuracy and the
new AI tool will definitely help that,
and real time monitoring, enhance the
global survey across the market insights.
Thank you.