Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining me
at Con 42, DOOPS 2025.
Today we'll discuss about and
open source static analysis tool.
My name is, I'm an SRE for more
than 20 years, more than 20 years of
experience, and I have reliability,
infrastructure and platform engineering.
I'm another analyst speaker
and I'm currently working as
a principal engineer language.
So what is sast?
So it is static application security
testing, also known as static analysis.
What it does is discover
vulnerabilities in your source code
before it's research production.
SaaS can scan an application before
the code is coupled or built.
It's also non white box testing
because the tool has access
to that or little source code.
So what is that done of using sast?
See manual security review of
every code change is impossible.
Nobody's gonna scale at the
volume your code is generated.
Alright?
So shifting security left is the only way,
and since Saasta has access to your source
code, it can do a hundred percent code
coverage for all security vulnerabilities.
You can also scale across large
code base and can for every change
you recommend that you make.
So it can also identify certain
wellknown vulnerabilities, like
SQ injection, secret key exposure,
buffer workflows and things like that.
But it is not limited to that.
There are like, large number of
vulnerabilities and so it can bubble.
So the initial SaaS tools, otherwise
known as first generation SaaS tools.
Had its phone issues they were clumsy.
Their scans took covers, and the
setup was very complex and the result
in itself was not very testable.
And many developers because of
this, had security atic fatigue
and felt that, the tool is tools.
SA scan of tools are useless right now.
The difference here is that, in second
generation SaaS tools, it also has issues.
It also brought in some improvements,
but some of the issues still are
higher number of, false positives.
It is also difficult for SaaS to
detect advanced security issues like
authentication, access control, and
authorization and things like that.
It cannot dated weak cryptography or
any other kind of security issues.
It also cannot find out issues
with the configurations because
it only looks at the source code.
So how does SaaS work?
So the source code is broken
down into tokens keywords,
identifiers, operators, and whatnot.
It's in the, programming language.
Then this tokens are analyzed according
to the grammar rules of the language to
create a hierarchical set of know code.
Typically, this is abstracts industry.
And this still determines
how the program execute.
And, in the case of, control for
analysis it determines like, how the
control from of the program falls
from one part of the code to another.
And then there is data for analysis,
which tracks how data is manipulated
and, traveling through the code.
And once the code structure on the floors
are identified the pre different rules
or pattern are applied to this structure.
And then it can detect common coding,
reverse inside of practices or
indicators of potential vulnerabilities.
And that is the way SaaS operates.
Now we talked about ASTs
briefly in the previous slide.
So what is an A SD asds Abstracts
Industry, which is a three shared
representation of your code
that captures its tructure and
not its raw text or formatting.
You can think of it like you know
how we compiler operator that
understands your code internally?
Now, why is it put abstract?
It is because it ignores details
that doesn't matter for the
meaning or the purpose of the code.
No comments, no white tion
no exact formatting or
beautification, things like that.
As you can see on the exam at the
bottom, all of these essentially,
if you look at from a pure text or
pattern perspective, these four.
Print head over statements are
totally different, but when an as
is generated out of these 2, 3, 4,
sorry, four statements, they are, go
do that is the beauty of using ASCs.
It gives you a deterministic
program aware structure.
Now let's look at, a simple
example of how a Python program
is converted into an A SC.
So Python provides an a ST library,
which takes a source code as an input,
and then returns an A ST. And as you
can see at the bottom output, the A ST
proves a relay structure for the code.
So to make the concept a little
bit more clear, let us look at the
graphical ation of the ceiling.
As you can see, the core
only has one expression.
And the function name and the
arguments as will test tokens and
are the same note within the two.
So let's look at a slightly different
example to clear the concept here.
So here we are using a variable
assignment and then printing the
variable rather than directly
using a scaler or string to print.
This has two soft, one for the same,
and then another for the functional
n. If you have a large number of lines
of code, you can see how this will,
expand into a huge three already.
So let's talk about similar now.
So Send RA basically is
a tool and a platform.
It's available at, similar about Dev.
The core of the is an open source.
Engine for Vulner, the evaluation, and
that is called C or Community Edition.
Now, if so, it also has a central
pro and commercial SaaS platform,
which adds additional features,
reporting central ruling, et cetera.
So what is the name mean?
Sam.
Sam essentially is.
Semantic.
Grap semantic essentially means
that se grip as a tool understands
your programming language, semantic,
and then uses grap or not Israeli
graph, but grap means patterns graph
like patterns that you can use to
apply on the your code basically.
So the commercial platform also while
we are covering C here, the commercial
platform in itself, not just the sas,
it can also software com analysis,
supply chain, security, et cetera.
So how does SIM work exactly?
So BR doesn't need compelled artifacts.
It works directly on the source.
So it'll answer the,
according to an EST, and then.
There are rules which are patterns
that match against this a ST to
detect in code or buggy code shape.
The thing with sum up is that, it
is not just code, but the rules
are also converted into ASTs so
that the matching becomes much
more return mistaken and easy.
So this rules essentially are yamal
structured documents that can be the
stored locally or centrally in a registry.
And you can also add your own rules
and run them against your code
locally and the output of the, scan
or the assembly of scan of your.
It can either be a simple text for,
that you will see in CLI or you can
audit them or a security specific
form called, which helps you in
integrating this with CI systems or
other security tools for reporting.
So the core of graph is the
patterns or the rules, right?
So the sum patterns looks
pretty much like a real code.
You write a snippet with the
placeholders for the parts that you
want to, vary or apply specific rules.
Things kind like that, right?
So let's say, for example, you know you
want to match a Python function, call
that directly with the library code.
You can just, put request order.
I said no.
Pure statement, but let us say you
won't use within request order, get your
passing a URL and you want parameters
that URL and do some checks on that URL.
Then you can make it's, you can create
some, or there is something called meta
variables within some grid, which is
essentially parameterizing and variable,
creating variable out of that pattern.
And then you can apply
rules on that variable.
No.
In addition to that, a single
rule has multiple things.
It also has metadata like messages,
severity, language, et cetera.
And the good thing about the pattern
rules is that since this patterns are
code alike, developers can really review
direct without needing to a complex DSL.
So what is the structure
of a specific rule?
The first thing is a unique rule Id it
could be it just has to be a stream.
Could be in any format.
What you're seeing here is, something
that is structured like a company
then type of vulnerable di but
in reality it could be anything.
So the pattern is what define
your actual match criteria.
The code snippets that, you
have to scan and message.
Message is what, a developer will find
when you scan against a vulnerability
and it takes a vulnerability.
The message is sent as an output and there
is a variable that pins a rule to one or
more specific languages, which makes it
easier to filter out words from a large
number of words for multiple languages.
And metadata for message know, or a
rule can store, CV links, documentation,
internal if you're writing a local
rule, things like that, right?
So this overall structure allows you
to build an internal router that can
affect your organization's coding,
standards, security practices,
and also educate your developers.
By using the metadata effectively into
reporting into specific sacred code
deadlines, documentations, et cetera.
Alright, so let's look at Hello
program in some so our code here
in question is a simple print.
Hello.
That's a simple python, one
manner, and the rule is essentially
going to match it exactly.
Footprint.
Hello?
'cause we are looking
for the pattern print.
Hello.
In any program, any Python program.
And here we will get an excitement
because the rule and the content
of the program remains same.
We'll just run that now rule using
some group CLI against the court.
Now what you're seeing here is CLI
and all this the no verification
output, but it found one issue.
If you see here, it outputs what is
the file on which state form the issue.
It outputs the rule.
It also does a output, your message.
What was the exact error about?
So this is where like your met
message is what comes into picture
and gives that a context, right?
And it also finally, it also outputs
line number of the program and
the program impact that it itself.
All right, now that we are on
our, hello program, let's move on.
So we talked about patterns, right?
Pattern is the core of
your rules, similar rules.
So there are different ways to
indicate and define your patterns.
So if you just give pattern
in the know Yael file, it is
a single pattern that it is.
You can have multiple patterns by
stacking the mass in a using pattern.
Either you could have a list of patterns
and any of them could be matching.
Then you can have patterns, which
essentially says like you can have
multiple patterns, but all of them
are considered, it is like an ant.
And then there's pattern which allows
you to match against, again, it is
like pattern, a single pattern, but
the it match against the profile.
Pure text, right?
And then there are
nestable pattern operators.
So let's say you define a top
level 11 called pattern or pattern
angle, which is stand or core.
And then you can have one or more
of this sub pattern operators, which
could be pattern inside, which says
it'll look inside, know the code
or pattern note, it's an negation.
Pattern, not insert if this code
is not inside the particular block
or, it doesn't match the specific
projects, things like that.
Then of course there is meta variables
that we already, talked about.
Meta variable is essentially, I think,
but placeholder for some part of your
code, which you want to process later in
the pattern matching right now, for that
matter variable, let's say, you have,
you are as I mentioned earlier, right?
Python request is basically for URL.
So let's say you are passing a UR
and you want to variable that ur,
you can use meta variable, and then
in the next line you can probably
use select meta variable pattern to
look for a pattern within that URL.
You can do a comparison, you can
run, reject anything that you
want for more fine grain control.
So these are a few examples of patterns,
as I said pattern essentially is you
could have a bunch of patterns in there.
The first pattern, if you see patterns,
defense, you can have all more patterns.
So you can list additional
patterns in here.
And as you can see, this is a multi-line
pattern, not a single line pattern.
Pattern two, also multiline
pattern, but it's negation of
pattern, which says patterns now.
And the third one is basically
patterns, either which means
this is actually a pattern for SQ
injection finding SQ injection.
And there are three patterns.
If any of them matches the rule
will say no rule will alert that
is, there's an SQ injection.
So structural matches versus
structural process in are basically
a rule that matches snapshot
of a code shape in one place.
Then there is data for rules.
Consider how your data moves from, one
place to another within your program.
And then there is change analysis,
which tracks untrusted input
flowing through your dangerous APIs.
The community edition essentially
only looks at rule-based engine
and a simplifi single file code.
Pro engine on the other hand,
gives you advanced in file
scanning 10 support, et cetera.
No, several.
I'm talking about some community
rules registries, essentially
3000 plus open source rules
available in in central place.
So if you are just starting off,
you can just start by running your
code against central registry with
all the, de default rules that is
want to build with the community.
So most of the rules covers like
industry best practice, like our top 10
common cws and flavor specific issues.
Alright?
And some groups is of for a CLI
and the confi equal to auto option
allows you to just talk to not
central registry and pick whatever is
applicable or relevant to your code.
You don't have to do anything
specifically, it will just
automatically determine what is the
log language, and based on that,
you'll go to the registry and pull
the local language and the framework
specific rules from the registry.
Now, we can always for and
tweak some of these rules,
make it your own COVID locally.
And this helps you in building
like, rules from accession.
You don't have to, start
off from the scratch.
Rather, you can start from the open
source rules, then make it your own.
Collaborate locally,
keep the, rules locally.
And as your code and your
organization needs role.
Now if you're install, it's of course it's
CRA and options like, Docker, depending
on where you want, install this CRA.
And as I mentioned, like auto
rule configuration is the easiest
one way to, get started off.
But of course know you can point your
configuration local or to, multiple,
locations and it'll accumulate
rules from all these locations
and run it against your court.
So result of course, is the by default,
you'll see it from the console as you
saw earlier, but we can also convert them
into just format or salary format so that,
it can be negative with dashboards, code
scanning, or any other security tool.
So now let's look at where we can
integrate now to set up, and get the
comfort with the, where we can integrate.
Similar right in the NSTC.
So the earliest you can integrate
any tooling in the T Cs in the id.
And software is actually getting developed
similar, has plugins for most popular IDs.
And this means that you are shifting it
to the no atmos left the security right,
and you can, cash in patterns before they
even committed into the local problem.
Alright.
And developers can immediately get,
hints and fixed patterns they might
otherwise repeat somewhere else.
And this also makes it easier, change
similar stance from a gatekeeper
or an entry point to a teaching
tool that continuously educates
developers about security issues.
Nope.
The next option is, of course, we
are moving towards the, right now, we
were extra alert with the ID plugins.
Now we are looking at pre-com rules.
So pre-commit rules also creates a
natural, low friction checkpoint.
It's a checkpoint.
It has a bit of friction, but it is still
low friction because when you make the
commit itself, you can use to scan the
changes that you know you have committed.
And that makes it easy to like,
integrate into your precum books
because only the changes are looking
into, and the when find something
critical, it can block the commit with
a or more like clear messages, right?
And that helps in catching,
before this is committed
no CHCD.
And that is you can have
just pre, you can have.
Automatic scans for every
committed code, right?
And again, on all these steps, the rules
might change you, in the id the developer
might have, personal specific, more
specific rules that he he or she catches
in the pre, probably there's the team,
the rapport owners are maintaining a set
of rules that they only know about or
spec very specific to their code base.
And CSCD, where like you can
implement community roles, organize
specific rules that run your
infrastructure or the implements.
So that is how you know the
the scanning progresses, right?
So when you are adopting it initially, you
should start with some soft fields, right?
Rather than first just give a warning, put
a warning in, unless it's a very critical
security issue, just put a warning in the
logs in CI and you don't move on with it.
Also use the salary for just based output.
Put it into, GitHub or some other
reporting tool that supports format.
Now if this is an example of data actions,
file, if you want to integrate graph into
your ca or process ca process, actually
this is a sample that you can use.
Now, you can also use
graph in, quarter pr.
What it could do is it can
make security review a part
of your review culture, right?
And instead of reverse manually
looking at common patterns
rules can automatically do that.
And also comment on the PR and over
period of time, teams can find,
okay, what, what are the issues?
Then add more rules in the, rule base and
the tribal knowledge get translated from
people's mind into, some rules, right?
So noise, right?
So of course, as I mentioned earlier
sas, the biggest problem for SAS
is or the noises we can call it.
So to avoid that from early on and
not to avoid hindering of adoption
because once ERs find that, and
it's even too much noise, they don't
look at the tool for their right.
So to avoid that.
Start with the non baseline scan and
focus on some of the new issues similar.
Gives you options like, exclude
during runtime or send up as a
file within the report so that you
can ignore certain pattern or in
certain parts of the code base.
Alright?
And slowly iterate on the rules,
and the patterns and combinations
to reduce, force positives.
Realistically on a daily floor, a
developer can implement the feature
warnings in the id, fix them and
then know get come passes, which
manage everything is well and good.
And then same know in CH stage,
some block manager check for all
they know, full change it and come
on any issues, reviews can happen.
And during the remote, engineers
can review suggestions.
They can add additional violations
to the rules, things like
that over a period of time.
There will be fewer issues that is
getting through your, code because your,
all your baseline thing, security stuff,
taking care of what, flying by system, it
gives like a much faster, feedback loop.
So that's quite useful in terms
of, shifting your security left.
So when you're adopting assembly.
Don't turn on every rule reports.
It adds you phatic and for the right.
So start smart.
A few reports, limited rule set.
Focus on the developer's experience first.
'cause they need to get used
to running some rules locally.
And then only you should,
no more rules, more.
And even there is, success stories,
this particular application so on.
So which, start adopting some, right?
And you can of course work with security
engineers side by side, fine tune the, and
also you can document local conventions.
Local rules and, and additional rules
do things like that so that you know
you have much better security also.
And let's look at a very quick demo
and see a few rules and know code.
So as you can see here we are
looking at three type of rules here.
And so you are already seen
our, hello and program.
So other than that, we have three more
now set of rules that programs here.
So let's start with the first
one, which is sq e rejection.
So let's just look at the file first.
So as you can see this is the rule
for sq e rejection, and what you're
seeing here is three patterns.
It's an either pattern, any of this
pattern matches, it's an SQ induction.
So if you see here if you remember
on Python, there are cursors that
you can use to execute SQ queries.
And the first argument is, of
course, you know the query.
So now this pattern essentially
says any pattern plus you are
conga, connating a variable,
then that is an integral pattern.
Second one, user and upstream,
and then use variable within that.
That's also an integral pattern.
But you could also use the
percentages for replacing variables
within the query that's there.
Also, if you're using a variable
and a text together, then that is
again another, chance of injection.
And of course you can add metadata about
you, what kind of vulnerability this is,
what kind of categories is what technology
or language supports, languages.
You here.
Technology is more like metadata.
All right.
And as you can see, the ID here
is again, something unique and
you can pick interest, know
what this ID should be, right?
And again, severity error.
You have a very post message that this is
an injection and how you should, fix that.
Let's look at the sample program.
Sample program is quite simple.
It has around two functions.
And, both of the Mexicos one as pure code.
As you can see in the first
one, there's a pattern where the
variable is conga, they variable.
And the second one it use an upstream.
But again it replaces, it
inserts a variable here.
So both are in circuit patterns.
Let run this, pattern against
the file and see what happens.
Cool.
So as we expected, it formed two issues.
As you can see, the file will scanned.
Is this one?
The rule ID is this one, and
as you can see, there is.
Two no issues that you know
it or it rather tells you like
this is possible skill ejection.
And these are the two patterns out of
the three C, three patterns we give.
Two of them were detected.
Here.
There's more.
And look at, the next type of
program, which is input validation.
So just say in your organization,
you want to implement a standard.
Function, which will do, or
validate all sort of input.
Right now we have doing the function,
it can be improved as a library and
function in your code, but we need to
check whether the reps are actually
using it during a program right now to
do that, we again, define again, there's
an ID and another whole things, and
then you have a pattern which differ.
It's a multi-line function.
Which defense a function.
Then there's an argument
passed to the body, right?
So that is a, and this
is the next one, right?
Where if you see what is the difference
here, both are same function definition,
but in the first one it just, it
could be another, could be anything.
But in the second one, there is
actually a function called validated.
And this is the right way to do it,
because validated input is a function
that you give to your organization.
So that everybody in the company
uses this validate input.
Now let's look at the quote.
So there are two functions here.
The first function, just,
process, the input as it is.
And the second one actually
validates input first and
then only process that I know.
Data again, run this group.
Again, we found one issue because
the second one, actually not
second part of the code actually
used the well data input function.
The first one didn't.
So that was code.
And as you can see, this is a
multiline pattern and it found on
all the lines that matches the.
Now let's look at the third
and the final pattern.
This is quite common nowadays that
people commit their AWS credentials,
which includes access key and a private
secret key into the code, right?
So let's look at the rule first.
It's a little lengthier and
reduces specific, pattern Then.
So if you see the pattern here, right?
Essentially most of the time if you
are using access security, it'll be
in a variable assignment formatted.
And that is exactly what it's
a simple variable assignment.
Whereas know there's a,
then there's a value.
Right now here we are making
use of ware 'cause we defend
the dollar a dollar value.
Right now you can apply pattern, any
of these things, no meta variables.
So here we are seen meta variables.
Within the pattern.
And what it says is the
meta variable to be used, no
evaluated it, value, lower value.
And that rejects is this one.
So this is a common pattern
for, this one, what you say.
This is a common pattern for access
keys, not secret keys for access keys.
Alright?
So it is going to have first a
specified, bunch of defined patterns.
But there'll be four characters
and then there will be additional
section characters altogether,
making it a 20 character Id.
Now you look at the second one,
we are looking at The Secret.
I know a w Secret right now in here.
It is pretty much like a Basic 60 for
Know The Secret is pretty much now
looking like a base 64 recorded online.
You have, alpha characters
plus slash plus and them.
Equal to.
And the total size of
the key is 40 characters.
And let us look at the
program that used it.
It is a quite simple program.
There are two factors.
One of them just, have demy credit here.
Whereas this function here has a
code AWS access key and secret key.
Embedded in the code.
Alright, so let's see what happens when
you run some grid against this rule.
Cool.
We did two code findings.
The first one is finding the
secret, sorry, access key Id
and second er, secret key id.
That brings us to the end of our demo.
I hope you got an idea about how, what
similar is, how similar can be used,
and I would argue to not start using
or any other SaaS tool in your SU.
Thank you.