Hello everyone.
My name is Shilpa and I'm a staff software
engineer With our 20 years of experience
in software development and more than a
decade of specialization in the payments
industry today I'll be talking about a
transformation that's reh reshaping the
financial technology world, how DevSecOps
plays a central role in securing payment
gateways during the migration from
monolithic architectures to microservice.
This shift touches not just
technology, but also culture,
process, and risk management.
So with that, let's begin.
To start, let's take a step back
and understand what's happening
in the payment gateway landscape.
For many years, payment systems were
built as large monolithics stable,
predictable, but extremely slow to change.
And because they handle sensitive
transactions, modifying them was
risky and involved long development
cycles, but the world changed.
We now have real-time payments, internal
international commerce, mobile first
users, and 24 by seven consumer demand.
As a result, payment process began
shifting towards microservices
because microservices offer
agility, independent scaling, faster
updates, better fault isolation.
However, and this is important,
microservices also introduce
new complexities, especially
for security and compliance.
So this modernization is not just a
technical upgrade, it's a complete
reimagining of how security fits
into the software lifecycle.
With that foundation set,
let's talk about DevSecOps.
Traditionally, security happened at
the very end of the development cycle.
Developers wrote code.
QA tested it and only then
security reviewed everything.
This cause delays,
friction and bottlenecks.
And in the microservices world where
deployments happen multiple times a
day, this model simply doesn't scale.
That's where DevSecOps come.
DevSecOps integrates security
from the beginning, embedding in,
embedding it into design development,
built deployment operations.
It shifts security left, meaning
security moves earlier in the life cycle.
This ensures that security becomes
a continuous collaborative and
automated part of development
rather than a final checkpoint.
Now let's start transitioning to a
topic that is unavoidable in payments.
PCID S'S Compliance.
PCID.
S'S define strict rules for
protecting call holder data, access
control, network segmentation,
encryption, logging, and monitoring.
In traditional monolithic systems,
organization relies, relied
heavily on perimeter security,
isolated networks, firewalls, DMZs.
But in microservices,
workflows are distributed.
Data moves across many services.
Perimeter became less clear,
the attacks surface grows.
So complaints must evolve from being
network based to being service based.
And failure to comply could
result in heavy fines.
Loss of processing privileges,
significant reputation damage.
In short complaints becomes a constant
priority, not something done once a year
with complaints in mind.
Let's shift into what changes
when you move to microservices.
There are three major paradigm
shifts, expanded attack surface.
Instead of one app, you now
have dozens of services, each
one, a potential entry point.
Dynamic infrastructure, containers and
services scale up and down constantly.
Security controls must handle
rapid change, integrated
security responsibility.
Security is no longer
owned by just one team.
Every team and every service
carries shared responsibility.
This shift requires new tools, new
thinking, and new design patterns.
Now that we understand the
challenges, let's move into the
architectural solutions that help
secure microservices service mesh.
A service mesh provides mutual
TLS encryption, authorization
traffic policies all automatically,
meaning developers don't need
to manually code these features.
Next is API Gateways.
An API Gateway becomes
the secure front door.
It handles authentication rate, limiting
threat detection and input validation.
Lastly, zero trust.
Zero Trust essentially means
trust, nothing, verify everything.
Every service must authenticate
and authorized every
request, even internal ones.
Now let's talk about
protecting the data itself.
We use a layered approach.
Tokenization actual card
data is replaced with tokens
reducing PCI risk dramatically.
Encryption address stored data is
encrypted using strong keys and
managed through secure keywords.
Encryption in transit.
All network communication is
encrypted with TLS Secrets Management.
Secret Secrets must be stored
in secure walls, not in code
and environment files or repos.
With these combined, we
build defense in depth.
At this point, you might be thinking.
With so many security
checks, won't they slow us?
Slow us down, not if we automate.
Automation enables security to
keep pace with rapid deployments.
We automate static analysis checks code
for vulnerabilities early, and we automate
dynamic testing attacks the running
application to find runtime issues.
Name container scanning ensures images
and libraries are secure and up to date.
Automation turns security from
a body like into an enabler.
Now let's build on automation by
talking about infrastructure as code.
Infrastructure as code allows us to
define networks, servers, configurations,
security settings, all as code.
This provides consistency, version
control, and automated guardrails.
Similarly, there is compliance
as code, which converts PCR
requirements into automated checks.
The sensor's complaints becomes
continuous, real time auditable.
Instead of waiting for a quarterly
or an annual audit, we validate
complaints on every deployment.
Now let's move into what
happens after the deployment.
Even with strong prevention,
incident will still happen.
So detection and response
become essential.
We rely on SIM systems, which collect
logs EV from everywhere to spot suspicious
patterns, fraud detection models, analyze
transactions and behaviors in real time.
Distributed tracing allows us to
trace individual transactions across
potentially dozens of microservices.
Anomaly detection alerts when something
deviates from normal behavior.
These capabilities give security teams
visibility and actionable insights.
Now let's turn our attention
to the CICD pipelines, which is
often the first line of defense.
Source control, security.
This prevents secrets from being
committed, prevents secrets from
being committed, requires code
reviews, and then coming to bill
process, analyzes dependencies and
libraries for vulnerabilities and
vulnerability issues, artifact signing.
Ensures all images and binaries are
trusted and unmodified deployment
gates block insecure builds
automatically, and then rollbacks
allow quick recovery during incidents.
Microservices rely heavily
on this pipeline discipline.
Next, let's talk about the cloud.
Since microservices often live there,
cloud platforms provide fine grained
identity access management network,
microsegmentation managed security
services, automated encryption.
However, the shared responsibility
model means organizations must still
secure application code configurations,
access permissions, cloud can strengthen
security, but only when used properly.
How do organizations actually succeed?
Here are the proven
strategies phased migration.
Start small, learn and iterate.
Security champions empower individuals
on each team to be security advocates.
Threat modeling, identify
risk early before writing code
realistic test environments.
Mirror production closely to
catch real vulnerabilities.
These approaches reduce risk
and increase predictability
when implemented well.
DevSecOps offers clear benefits,
stronger security posture, faster
and more reliable releases.
Easier compliance, better cross
team collaboration, a culture where
security is shared, not siloed.
Ultimately, DevSecOps aligns
both innovation and protection.
As we wrap up, let's take a
forward looking perspective.
Okay.
The shift from monolithic payment systems
to microservices is one of the most
significant transformations in FinTech,
but to succeed, organizations must commit
to new architectures, robust automation,
continuous monitoring, a culture change.
Security is not a one-time achievement.
It's an ongoing journey.
Those who build security first cultures
will be the ones best positioned to handle
future threats and industry expectations.
Thank you so much for
your time and attention.