Hello and welcome to this conference.
Thank you very much for
attending this presentation.
Today we are going to introduce
you to a very innovative
Solution for cyber security.
We are going to, start with the
first slide and introduce some of the
concepts and I will deliberately, go
slow so all these concepts can be well
digested because some of them may be
relatively new or relatively not very
common in the world of cyber security.
So first thing first.
Internet2.
ai, so number two is because This is
the evolution of internet in a more
secure internet and AI because we do
use AI in most or all of our processes.
And in particular, we use that
in a very key process in this
solution that we will explain later.
We are, as long as we are
aware, The first company in the
world for doing ISP reputation.
So basically ISP reputation
is to put a rating to the ISP.
Originating the traffic.
So when we receive traffic from internet,
from a specific network that belongs to an
ISP, we know how good or bad this specific
ISP and network has behaved in internet.
And for this purpose,
we use multiple ways.
We will go in detail in
the other slides, but.
It is good that you start understanding
that this solution or this approach
is different from what you are used
to see, in the cybersecurity space.
This time, we are going to start the
controls in the ISP originating the
traffic, not on the destination of
the traffic where your company is.
We are going to take one step forward
and enhance the security perimeter.
Basically, this is all about.
If you understand this concept, the
enhancement of the security perimeter,
this is what it is all about.
Based on a specific technology related to
the rating, to the reputation of the ISP.
But the concept is this enhancement of the
security perimeter, which by the way, is
a concept that in other areas of defense,
like the military, it is a very well
understood, technique or strategy to use.
When we say AI being used in
our processes, there is one key
process, which is the, the rating.
So what rating we apply to
different scenarios of the ISPs,
networks delivering traffic.
this policy is dictated by AI
with very minimal human oversight.
So let's go slide by slide,
introducing the concept in more depth.
So the security challenge,
the current landscape.
is terrible.
The threats are evolving, we get more
threats, defending an organization is
really difficult these days because
they attack from multiple places,
they are dedicated, dedicated,
targeting, there are different types
of attackers, so it's really difficult.
And unfortunately, I have to say that
if that was a race, we are not winning.
At least, what we hear from the
media is that large organizations
with many resources, they
are also victims of attacks.
Which make us think that there
is something that needs to
change, but something at the
base, something different.
We need to do something different if we
want to change the direction of the race.
So basically, the speed this is going,
we do need to take action on it.
As soon as possible.
Okay, so at the moment, in cyber
security, the main idea, different
colors, good, but the idea is to
do the defense at destination.
You put firewalls, you put all type of
defenses when you receive the traffic
from internet, the offending traffic.
And this is basically what you
are doing, for your defense.
This is good.
It's really very good,
but it has some issues.
Or maybe to say that in a
different way, it is not enough.
There is something missing here.
Otherwise, we wouldn't be
in the situation we are.
So we are getting millions of attacks
every day from different angles.
It's if we were to make an analogy
with the real world, it's like having
millions of people hitting your
doors And your windows in your house,
which is something that obviously
is not something you want to have.
And probably because some of them may
be also to get into your house at some
point, because there are millions.
And they are doing that
every day in every second.
Even when you are at home, when you are
not, in the morning, in the afternoon,
in the evening, and when you're sleeping.
So basically the breach is warranted.
We all in cybersecurity say that is not
the question of when, but sorry, not
but if, but when it's going to happen,
we all know it's going to happen.
I have an anecdote related to this is
one CIO of a very large organization.
One of the statements, last statement
I read a few weeks ago was, We have
the enemy already inside, so we need
to make our defenses based on the
idea that they are already inside.
what they were saying here is that
we don't have this perimeter anyway,
so we need to start defending
ourselves inside the house.
Which really sounds a little bit Too much.
And legal complexities.
Due to the nature of Internet, which
is, international, you can be attacked
from many multiple different countries
and the legal enforcement there is very
difficult because by the time you raise
a complaint really it is very difficult
that you hit the attackers in, in, in
the final country, in the country where
they are originating these attacks.
It's almost impossible.
That's why we sometimes do see in the
news that the FBI has captured, some,
malicious attackers somewhere and they
have deactivated, thousands of boats
and stuff like that for ransomware,
for phishing, for all these attacks.
But the thing is still continues.
it's Something really is not
working because this is not.
Only continuing, this is growing.
So we are in a worse situation
than we were yesterday.
So the trend is not good.
We need something else to stop this trend.
So our suggestion is that we change
something at the strategic level.
A big change in cyber security.
So this big change is related to the
issues related to the root cause.
We think it is the cyber impunity.
We think that the lack of, there is no
deterrent at the moment for attackers.
They basically can attack at zero cost.
they are anonymous.
They can attack pretty much from anywhere
and they don't have any consequences.
So it is for free.
For example, it is a term that
is not being used that often
these days, but in the past we
had, we had this script kiddies.
And how is that possible that large
organizations with multiple millions
or miles of employees, millions of
revenue, there are script kiddies
that These large organizations and
sometimes they even penetrate these
companies and they commit fraud.
So why is this happening?
Because really these attackers
are very difficult to catch.
So it is basically, in
summary, attacking is for free.
So the return of the
investment is very high.
So as we say, the solution, we
think that we need a change.
We need to think out of the box.
The change requires A different type of
change, not only making your doors and
windows stronger, which is very good.
It's something you need to do,
but we need something else, and we
suggest Taking a strategic approach
and make our doors strong, make our
windows strong, but also enhance
the perimeter and put some distance
between the attackers and our house.
So then we can control them
from far away from where they
are and not from where we are.
some of them probably, obviously,
will penetrate this first perimeter,
but many of them may be filtered
because you are already, by default,
you're doubling the control.
So you have two controls instead
of one, and one of the controls
is not anymore at your doors.
It's at their doors.
It's where they are.
You get close to them, you are
moving the defenses, or doubling
the defenses, next to them.
And then the things change, because I'm
sure that all these script kiddies we have
mentioned before, they will think it twice
before attacking a large organization.
If they know that the ISP to where
they are connecting and which is
where the attack is going to be
originated is controlling them and
may raise a complaint and they could
be prosecuted because the ISP is in
the same country they are and then can
do the prosecution of the malicious
attacker, which is something that at
the moment is not happening because of
the complexity in the international law.
So we have two defenses, and one of the
questions that sometimes arises when
I do this presentation is that, yeah,
okay, but We all know that the attackers
are, chaining through multiple, country
servers, before launching the attacks.
That's true.
But the same way that they chain,
we can chain it back as well.
And I'm going to explain
that in the next slide.
Once that we have introduced
what the specific technique we
suggest to enhance this perimeter.
So the tech we suggest is the rating.
The rating is very,
extremely powerful tool.
Large organizations like Amazon,
eBay is an excellent example.
it wouldn't exist if that
wasn't for the rating.
Who of us would buy something in internet
without knowing who is selling that?
Thanks to the rating, we can buy goods,
that, and we are safe that these goods,
will, we will receive them and they
will be in relative good conditions.
So the rating is, is an powerful,
very useful technique to use.
So then the question is why we are not
using the rating of the ISPs, that are
launching or sending this traffic of
the malicious attackers to internet.
Because if we had.
A rating of these ISP networks,
we could say, okay, the traffic
coming from this network is usually
malicious and the traffic coming
from this network is usually is good.
So this would strongly support and help
the security analyst in our organizations.
And yeah, the rating is something that
is an extremely good candidate to be
introduced in the cyber security because
the power it has may help us, doing the
things better in our particular case.
We do have, some intelligence of the
malicious traffic because we do have
some probes worldwide, distributed
through geographically around the world.
And we do also take some reports
from third parties on the IP
addresses, and then we assign this,
this rating to the ISP to which.
this IP address to the ISP to
which this IP address belongs.
And we also do have
proprietary algorithms.
This collection of data is done
in real time and the good thing
here is, many people, also another
key question is that, okay, yeah,
but we already do have IP rating.
Yeah, but the IP rating, the problem
is that there are billions of IP
addresses and they don't have a history.
ones that, for example, a server
with malicious, I don't know,
phishing or whatever, or some
malware, Once that this has been
clear, this IP address is disappears.
we remove that from our filter list
and it is again a good IP address.
It doesn't keep a history, while in
the ISP rating we do keep this history.
We know that today this ISP
network was behaving well.
But we also know that yesterday,
this ISP network was launching an
attack to our, and that was detected
by our probes or by any other means.
And so we know how many times we
have rated this network and what the
ratings were for the different, times.
So we keep a history of that.
And this history is like when you go
to the restaurant, there are like, it
is not the same to have a rating of, of
five or four to five for a restaurant.
if there are two people that are
doing the rating for this restaurant,
when you see a restaurant that has 1,
542 ratings and this one has a fault
of three, it's probably a very good
rating and patent pending application.
Yeah.
We are about to make this
application in the next few days.
we have this coverage
geographically, through worldwide.
And we get this rating
is continuously updated.
One of the key things again that I want
to mention here is that this policy
of the rating is dictated by the AI.
We do have a little bit human
oversight, but the policy of the
rating is dictated by the AI.
And you will be surprised, with the
evolution of the AIs these days,
rational data statements look when
asking for a specific, scenarios.
So they really, really logical and
really, explained why this, rating
should be applied based on the
scenarios we have, suggested to the AI.
That is awesome.
Some use cases, very typical is
that you use the sim here to ingest
this cyber intelligence, into the
sim, which at the moment, we have
a straightforward integration with
Microsoft Sentinel for which you don't
need to change your ingestion layer.
so this is the most typical scenario,
monitoring the traffic, but there
are some other customers that
they do, have, more sophisticated
or they do have, a different,
sorry, a different risk appetite.
And they do, for example,
financial entities, they can
do, limit the operations.
For example, they may only allow you to
see the balance of your account if you are
connecting from an ISP with a poor rating,
or they may just limit the transfer of
the money, if that is, this connection is
coming from one of those, ISP networks.
and the risk assessment, for example,
when you get, Customers or employees
connecting to your network, you can
make a profile and look at, how many
of them are connecting from, from ISPs
with a good rating or a poor rating,
and then you can make a profile on them.
Yeah.
What risk is your organization having
based on allowing some poor ISPs
and make decisions based on that.
So this is what basically the
intelligence obviously allows you,
the intelligence we provide to you.
One of the things also to maybe
mention here before going to the next
slide is that we do rate the origin
ISPs, we are in touch with them, we
have a strong relationship with them,
contact and a community with the ISPs.
So we do not only do the
rating in a cold way.
We do support the ISPs and try to
all these ISPs that don't have,
very good or these networks that
they don't have very good rating, we
support them improving the rating.
And this is very important because
we are here to, our mission is to
make Internet more secure, make
this second Internet, the evolution
of Internet, where we can be safe.
And the reason, and again, sorry for
extending a little bit, but the reason
is that sometimes we are not Aware of
how far internet is getting into our
lives and I have a little bit of a
dramatic anecdote regarding to this.
I'm living in the UK and a few months ago,
I am a blood donor and receive, An email
from NHS asking for blood, additional
blood, because they were running out of
stock due to a kind of a perfect storm.
And one of the, one of the key
components of this perfect storm
was that the NHS was under attack.
They were being cyber attacked.
So what I'm saying is that this is not
anymore about computers, about electrons,
about circuits, about electricity,
about all these things that we do love.
it is going much deeper is, the
impact in our lives of cyber
attacks is getting bigger.
And the way the digital, obviously
the world is going to the digital
direction, it's gonna get worse if
we don't take strategic measures.
As soon as possible, that's
why we are in our mission.
We are presenting this strategic
approach here, some real world analogies.
Okay.
I have mentioned already the
restaurant one, which is the one
that I do the most, because I
think it's very easy to understand.
We all go to restaurants and
we buy goods or we go dining.
we look at the rating and I'm a big
fan of looking at the restaurant and
which one has the best rating and the
comments of the people and all this stuff.
the football defense is another one.
we all like, many of us do like
football, not necessarily and not a
super big fan, but I do like to see my
team playing and doing a good defense.
And I couldn't imagine my team, like with
all the 11 players, like in the goal.
Score, they all waiting for the attackers
to just, to wait until they score.
It doesn't make sense.
So we all will be asking, that, for
example, we use a 4 4 2 strategy or
something, some layered security, in
place, not all the players in the score.
So basically that's what we are doing
in our organizations at the moment.
We are allowing, ISP networks
to send traffic to us.
and with a very poor rating and that
is the same as football or it is in
the restaurant and the home security.
I have already mentioned that.
all the solutions which are very good.
Don't get me wrong.
They are very good.
These old tactical security
cyber security solutions.
But we need to go one step further.
We need to do a strategic change.
We need to think out of the box for
cybersecurity solutions, or this race,
we are not going to win it at the
trend, at the speed direction is taking.
Okay.
So let's make our windows and doors
strong, but also let's put some space
between the attackers and ourselves
and let's get us into their territory.
to be next to them and protect ourselves
better before they hit our house.
I know that you cannot make any
questions here, so this slide
probably doesn't make much sense.
but just to let you know that if, even
if you cannot do the questions now, we
are happy to answer you any questions.
So for that, you just need
to contact us in internet2.
ai, easy to find in the website.
you have the contact details.
we are in Twitter, in, in
email, obviously, and we
have the website as well.
And we do have a tool that you can
check in our website to, to look at
the rating of the different networks.
And it is for free.
We also do have free plans and blah, blah.
We haven't discussed the commercials here.
But if you're interested, we are happy to.
Here is what was more the introduction
of a new strategic approach
in order to make internet more
secure for the best of all of us.
So thank you very much for
attending the presentation.
That was for me a pleasure.
Thank you very much also
conference 42 for letting me
presenting this innovation here.
And yeah, have a good day.
Thank you.