Hi everyone.
Good morning.
Good evening.
This is Rajkumar Supermar.
I have close to 21 years
of industry experience.
I'm currently working as a lead data and
AI engineering for at t services, right?
Today I want to talk about, the
critical or origin challenges that every
organization facing every day, right?
While building.
The AI are implementing AI under
machine learning pipelines.
So before I get into, my topic, I
would like to thank Dev SecOps for
providing me opportunity to speak
in this conference in front of you.
Okay.
Okay, let me begin my topic with
the simple the recent example.
Alright.
Couple of months before, right?
You're a large retail
company in the US right?
They deployed an automated visual
quality inspection model, right?
And once after the deployment, right?
Everything works fine and
whatever they expect at, right?
They got the outcome,
everything works fine.
People are happy.
But after several weeks, right?
The product defects are
skyrocketing, right?
The customers are not Hannah.
The customers are, complaining.
Lot of defects, right?
The business leaders are
getting investigation.
They start the investigation into that,
and then the team discovered, right?
Someone has intentionally
uploaded you, manipulated images
into the training data, right?
It's a very small poisoning, right?
I can say very small poisoning into the
training data, but that compromised, yeah.
Multimillionaire dollar system.
But the problem is nobody
noticed that is a worst part.
Nobody noticed this, once, once
they, deployed this model into
the C-D-C-C-A-C-D pipeline, right?
Because the pipeline doesn't have any
control over the, a security, right?
And this story is not
only for retail, right?
It's for everywhere, right?
It's, it starts from telecom, it starts
from insurance, or, it starts from.
Banking, right?
The DevOps pipeline have no
control over the security, right?
We need to have some kind
of strong DevOps, right?
That's what we're going to discuss.
Okay.
Let me move to the next slide.
Nowadays deploying EA systems
into the production is very fast.
It's not even taking
weeks or month, right?
It's days, right?
They plant, they implement
in a days, right?
But the speed comes
with a couple of issues.
One is data poisoning.
That's what we discussed
in the previous slide.
And then, we have and very still attacks.
We have a prompt injection.
We have ethical risk,
we have privacy leak.
So these are, some of the issues
it's come bundled with the first
deployment of the ai, okay?
So in 2023, right?
You have big financial institution
right past its loan approval system.
They implemented they
deployed using ai right?
For the loan approval.
But they stopped within few
weeks or within few weeks, right?
Because, it is not a it is, it's keep
on, rejecting the loan application for
a different sector of people, right?
When they tried to investigate the
issue they found, there was no issues.
But the problem is the model was trained
with a particular set of people, right?
So it is not able to recognize the
different set of peoples, right?
So that's what it's like a bias, right?
That's the issue, right?
So again, that's a need,
we need to build, yeah.
EA native dev SecOps framework.
Okay let me talk about, the EA
native dev SecOps framework, right?
It's, it comes with the,
different layers, right?
We have data injection we have
privacy preserving training.
We have automated security testing,
we have governance, ethical governance
case, we have producted interference.
And finally, we have to do
continuous monitoring, right?
We should not we should not
lift off the deployment.
We should monitor completely, right?
Why it's, for example, why it's
approval, why it's denying the loan.
For example, loan application, right?
We need to do monitoring for
several months at least, right?
Until.
The product become very stable.
Okay, so let me break into this, into let
me break this layer into small chunks.
Okay.
Secure data injection, right?
How do we implement this, right?
The data, and the trust starts
with the data injection, right?
We should properly inject the
the data, whichever we trusted.
And then we need to implement
the cryptographic verification
of the data sources.
And then we need to detect the real
time anomaly and the automatic p
P two i detection and redaction.
If it is having any, P two I P two
I values, for example, email id,
personal information that that we need
to redact, that we need to mask that.
We need to enable our a or in
audit audit logs we need to
track the lineage, data lineage.
Again, just wanted to underline,
the what is data lineage, one of the
enterprise again happened in us, right?
They traced a model failure back to
a single character CSV file, right?
The issue is right.
Because of the lineage.
Lineage, right?
Nobody knows.
Where exactly the CS
file comes from, right?
So it should come from a trusted source,
but because of the corrupt corrupted
file, they had a model failure.
Okay, so let me go to the next one.
That's privacy preserving training.
So nowadays companies, social
media companies are, telecom
or financial companies, right?
They're dealing with
sensitive data, right?
So in, in terms of in terms of
adding the privacy we need to
apply multiple privacy techniques.
For example, we need to apply differential
privacy which is something like, adding a
nice during the training so that the model
cannot memorize the individuals, right?
It's like a collaboration, not
individual kind of training.
Then it's like a, and
then second, second level.
Second level will be like federated
training, federated learning.
So the data stays at the source.
Only the model updates the travel, right?
So for example, think of it as a
learning from 10 hospitals, without
ever moving patient data, right?
And then third one will be
like, homomorphic, encryption
training and encrypted data.
Nobody sees.
That's a plain text, right?
So for example I can say,
usually the banks, right?
They used to do the fraud detection.
When once they do the fraud detection,
they cannot share the real data, right?
They also encrypted data and
then they help each other to
do the fraud detection, right?
Only they need to share the,
the patents right in, in stuff.
Sharing the real or the
raw customer data, right?
So that's the power of privacy.
Privacy of the preserving ai.
Okay, let me move to the next one.
Okay.
And in terms of security testing,
the machine learning pipelines we
will we bring CACD automation, right?
With multiple layers of testing.
For example, advers testing that
will generate the host inputs.
After that, it'll do the
static code analysis and then
the model hardening, right?
If there was any differential
things it'll validate the, it'll
do the input validation, right?
And further it'll do we have implement
dependency scanning for the ML frameworks.
So this these stages ensures the the
issues and if there was any issues.
That will be caught before
the deployment, right?
We can able to cut the issues,
we can able to fix it, right?
So we cannot able, we, so we
will avoid those breaches, right?
Or the customer complaints.
Move to the next one.
Okay, next one is, producting
interference inference endpoints, right?
Defense against real time threats.
So once after we apply the model, right?
We should secure by, by the
model extraction or the, bots in
inference or the prompt injection.
And, there are multiple ways.
One of the common ways is, setting
up the valve security protocol
valves can be used to call us.
And security protocol, right?
So that will detect the bots that detect
the injection like that some of which
like, it'll it'll it'll pass each request
coming from the outside and then it'll
pass the request and understand, you
said, coming from the trust source.
It's not from the, it should not
be coming from, the bars, right?
And then it'll filter those
requests, try to understand
what is a request header, right?
It should not be any SQ injection or
there should not be any bad request.
Yeah.
So that's, that's how we'll
product the the endpoints.
Okay.
Let go to the next one.
Alright, so next one is
governance by design, right?
Ethical AI checkpoints.
So now, security is not, now, not only
security is enough, we must ethics and
accountability into the pipelines, right?
We need to add the governance gets
the pre-training ethical review
and we should do the bias testing.
Across demographic groups, right?
We should not do the testing in a in
a, in a isolated group of demographics.
We should group across
demographics, right?
And then for sometimes at
least we should have the human
in the loop approval, right?
Yeah, again, I can tell, one of
the one of the example in one
of the recent deployment, right?
The bias test revealed
the model performed.
20 percentage was for
minority group, right?
The data scientist who developed
the model does it, did not
know why it was went wrong.
The business doesn't know.
But the problem is, it's all
about the training data, right?
The reason is they did not provide
the enough training data for
those minority, minority groups.
That's the issue.
Okay.
Now, we can have policy as a code
or we can have the blockchain
audit trials to scale governance.
We can qualify policies, we can have
version control rules, and then we should
implement automated compliance validation.
Like enforcement across
every EML pipeline.
And once we implement the blockchain it'll
it'll extend the immutable audit logs.
No one can able to temper that and
it's other transparent lineage, right?
So some where exactly the source that
you know it's coming from, right?
It's another transparent lineage
and then regulator ready evidence
without the proper evidence, right?
So that's what we build the
trust across the company.
We know from where exactly
the data is coming.
The the training data is coming and
we should have, the strong nobody
can able to temper the audit logs.
Who is going to modify
everything will be recorded.
And then regulator ready evidence.
Whenever there was a question from
the federal, we know how to answer.
We should have the the answer is
ready, okay what the next one?
Okay because of this recently
healthcare, a healthcare company
implemented the, the above strategy.
And after that so the implement
is DevOps framework, what we
discussed the previous slide, right?
So now the results, they don't have they
have zero security incidents and they
have much faster deployments, right?
Through automated CSCD or
automated compliance pipelines.
And then they can successfully
complete the audits, like in
a HIPAA or SOC the process.
And then they do have a trust, higher
trust in among the healthcare systems.
This explains once we deploy on the
dev sec of ea AI innovation, right?
With the multiple safeguard so
we can able to achieve the fruit.
Okay, next one.
So now, what are the strategies we can
do for every organization based on, the
couple of the real time success stories?
We should start with
the, yay risk assessment.
And then we should integrate
address and bias testing into CSCD.
And we should have human in the loop for
at least the model became very stable.
And we need to implement policy
as a code enable cross-functional
collaboration deploy runtime
monitoring for inference for, and then
maintain immutable audit trials so
nobody can tamper the audit trials.
Okay, go to the next one.
Okay, so what are the key takeaways?
Right?
This security and ethics cannot
be bolted onto the AI systems.
They must be embedded, right?
They must be extended right.
This is how we build the ai that
is, it should be secure, should
be private, should be fair,
trustworthy, transparency, and then
ready for the production at scale.
Okay.
I think that's all I have.
Thank you so much for, joining me today.
If you have any questions,
you can let me know.
Thank you.