Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the conference
42 DevOps Cops 2024.
I'm Spandana Saigam.
I'm excited to be here to discuss the
future of transportation navigating
through automated and autonomous vehicles.
With my background in autonomous
vehicle technology, I worked
excessively on advancements of AI,
sensor fusions, and mobility solutions.
Throughout my career, I'm fortunate
enough to contribute for the development
of these systems that will redefine the
future of transportation, focusing on
safety, efficiency, and urban mobility.
The topics we are going to discuss on
this presentation is Autonomous vehicles,
their safety, how they are impacting our
urban and logistics at the same time.
What are the challenges we
face ethically and socially?
Autonomous vehicles.
Autonomous vehicles are powered by
a variety of autonomous advanced
technologies, including AI,
machine learning and sensor fusion.
These technologies Take the real
time decisions by preserving their,
360 degrees view of the surroundings
and reduce the human errors.
AVs are, AVs has been differentiated
by the level of automation.
They differ from level 0 to level 5.
How AVs are good for the safety.
One of the most significant
benefits of AV is their potential
to reduce the traffic accidents.
Human errors accounts up to 93%, 94
percent of serious traffic crashes,
but AV can respond 25 percent
faster than humans because of the
combination of advanced sensors and
real time decision making algorithms.
That means AV can make decisions
such as braking, avoiding
obstacles in milliseconds,
enhancing in the road safety.
Urban mobility transportation.
AVs will also significantly
transport urban mobility by
reducing the vehicle ownerships.
AV can be used as a shared fleet,
reducing the number of cars on the roads.
Because of this, it reduces the
parking areas for green spaces
and pedestrian zones, potential
redemption in parking areas.
usage from 14 percent to 5
percent of the urban land.
What are the benefits of this?
The most important benefit of this
is it reduces the traffic congestion
and increases the public transport.
It also helps the elderly
and disabled people.
Logistics.
These AV vehicles can be used 24 by
7, whereas human drivers, whereas the
vehicles used by the human drivers
are limited by the regulations.
The key advantage of this AVs
are it reduces the human error,
enhances the fuel efficiency and
it predicts the delivery schedules
based on the AI powered optimization.
It also helps in the last minute
deliveries using the AI drones.
The next, the most important aspect
of the AVs are the challenges
we face in the AV vehicles.
Those topics will be
covered by my colleague.
Thank you, Spandana.
I'm Govardhan Reddy Kothinti.
I'm currently, currently
serving as a Functional Safety
Manager, at Aptiv LLC, PLC.
I have over 18 years of experience
in the developing of the critical
systems, embedded systems, as well
as avionics and autonomous systems.
I had a, I had an opportunity and
privilege working on the safety
critical systems and adaptation of
AB into these, autonomous vehicles.
I'll be covering the challenges related
to the cybersecurity infrastructure
needs and societal implications of
the autonomous technologies coming to
the challenges of the a VA adaption.
While the AV, benefits of the AV are
clear, widespread, adaptation of these
vehicles face significant challenges.
One of the primary obstacle
is with the regulations.
there are the regulatory,
things are like uncertainty.
We currently have state specific
regulation for testing of the AVs.
but global regulatory frameworks needs to
be established to ensure safety, reliable,
liability issues as well as provide clear
guidelines for the insurance of the AVs.
These regulations needs to be
evolved alongside advancements
in the AV technology.
Coming to the cyber security is
a critical concern of the AVs.
These vehicles are interconnected with
cloud based systems and communicate
with the surrounding infrastructure.
This connectivity opens up
multiple vulnerabilities, making
AVs suspectable to cyber attacks.
Strong encryption and intrusion detection
systems are essential to protect
these vehicles from potential threats.
Furthermore, the infrastructure
needs to support AVs.
such as, smart roads, 5Get work
requires significant investments
to ensure that a safe and efficient
operation to the environmental impact.
particular electronics, Electric
Autonomous Vehicles which are
called EAVs, they can offer
substantial environmental benefits.
By optimizing driving patterns,
reducing congestion, EVs can
reduce fuel consumption by 60%.
Additionally, EAVs contributes to
cleaner air by eliminating, tailpipe
emissions, making them a key component
in the fight against urban population.
Coming to the ethical and
social considerations.
Ethical concerns around AVs are
significant, especially in avoiding
unavoidable accident scenarios.
How should an AV decide who
to prioritize in an emergency?
This trolley problem is a key
challenge in the AV development.
And another important issue is the privacy
of the data generated by these AVs.
These vehicles collect a vast amount
of data, including location, behavior,
and environmental information.
And it is vital that this data is
protected and used responsibility
to ensure the public trust.
Coming to the social equity and public
trust, as AV technologies become more
prevalent, it is essential to ensure the
benefits of AVs reach all communities.
Especially undeserved or
the vulnerable groups.
AVIS holds the promise of increasing
accessibility particularly for
the individuals who face mobility
challenges such as elderly and disabled.
These groups stand to benefit
from the reduced transportation
costs and the availability of on
demand shared mobility services.
However, we must also be cautious
how AVs impact employment in
sectors that rely on human drivers.
The potential for the job displacement
is a real concern and it is Crucial to
invest in retaining programs to help
the workers transition to a new roles
in the AV ecosystem At the same time
we must ensure that the AV benefits
such as enhanced mobility Improved air
quality and safe roads are Equitably
distributed, particularly in rural
or economically disadvantaged areas.
To conclude, while autonomous vehicles
offer transformative potential, enhanced
safety, reducing congestion, and promoting
environmental sustainability, we must
address the challenges that lie ahead.
Key areas such as regulatory
adaption, technological infrastructure
development, and public education
and acceptance will be critical
to realize the benefits of these.
AVs on the Global scale.
Governments, industries and researchers
must work together to create a
seamless integration of AVs into this
existing transportation ecosystem.
Looking forward, the success
of the AVs will depend on the
collaboration among the governments,
industry leaders, and researchers.
By working together to adhere to the
challenges, we can ensure that the
AV technology will benefit everyone
from reducing the traffic congestion
and lowering emissions to improve the
safety and increasing accessibility.
The future of the AVC is bright, but it
will be required to continue effort and
innovation from all the sections involved.
I would like to thank everyone,
for providing this opportunity to
be, to speak in this conference.
and we are open to questions and if
you have any clarifications or more
details on this topic, you can reach
out on our LinkedIn profiles and, thanks
everyone for giving this opportunity.