Hello everyone.
My name is Alex.
Welcome to my talk about MCP.
We will talk about what it is, how
it can help supercharge your DevOps
process and how you can do it safely
without opening a security hole.
Now I am head of Myop in DevOps
at a company called Koder.
I also work as devel there as well.
Synder is an AI coordin assistant
which I will show briefly when
we will get to that stage.
But for now.
A few fun facts about me.
So I've been in it for
more than 10 years now.
Mostly in machine learning.
I did of course also lops
and the ops and backend.
I've been building code since they
since the first day pretty much.
So I'm one of the founders
members for the last year.
I mostly been working as deral.
This is my win number 52.
And this also resulted
in a lot of flights.
And I also have four main couns,
which I occasionally, between
flights I have a chance to see
back home on Madeira Portugal.
Now, MCP is something that everybody's
talking this year like everybody is
trying to create their own MCP server.
But what is MC.
To answer the question and also
why we need MCP, we need to take
a step back and talk briefly about
AI or specifically about lms.
Everybody nowadays, when they talk
about ai, they mean LMS and lms.
As you might know, they are trained
to predict the most probable
token or symbol, and sometimes
it still can lead to mistakes.
They are great at detecting patterns,
but they don't still understand
what is behind those patterns.
And of course sometimes this can lead
to some mistakes, some errors, which
for us, for humans doesn't make sense.
But then, as I mentioned, LMS
are great detecting patterns.
So this is what we did in this case,
but we all know how AI is with hands,
so that's not really surprising.
But yeah, jokes inside, joke aside we can.
From this sort, for example, we
can de deduce that LMS actually
lack ground in the physical world.
So what this means is they
sit the models themselves.
They sit somewhere in the cloud and
they don't have actual access to,
to physical world, to your local
machine, to your servers and so on.
And of course if you ask, let's
say, charge GPT about what's
the response time for Google, it
wouldn't be able to answer you.
It'll provide some
helpful comments for that.
So it might say you can use Ping or
whatever, but of course that's not the
actual answer to our question, right?
So if we were to ask something
more specific to our systems.
JGPT or any other LLM wouldn't be able
to help them, who to help us because
it it sits somewhere in the cloud and
again, doesn't have access to our servers
or to any servers for that matter.
And of course it becomes even worse Again,
if you want, to use your own framework.
Few maybe want to use your own
systems like infrastructure and so on.
LMS have usually no knowledge about
those, especially if you are developing
some in-house company framework.
Lms most likely do not know, do
not have any knowledge about those
frameworks, and they would just
fall back to those frameworks which
they seen in the open source data.
Technically, we can then replace this
phrase, this version that lms like
ground in the physical world into
lms, can't collect extra context.
And again, by extra context things
like you've seen an example with Bink.
Getting response time is
essentially getting context right?
Extra context.
So actual response time would
be those milliseconds would be
extra context for LLM to give
us more contextualized answers.
Or access to your sys, to your systems,
to your servers, to your login systems
and so on also allows, would allow
LLM to get extra context to give
you much more personalized answers.
Now the solution to that is let's
allow LLM to use tools, right?
To get to get this extra context
and what could go wrong, right?
So we can allow LM. To push code to
production, maybe like some companies
already apparently do this up to
them up to 75% or we can give a lamb
access to the database maybe, right?
Maybe not right date, maybe not right.
Access to the database.
'cause it might, for whatever
reason, decide to wipe it.
But still be, would be useful
for RLM to get this knowledge.
Now, JUX aide the most common, the
most popular way to give LM access to
tools is MCP or model context Protocol.
And it was introduced by Anthropic roughly
a year ago, I think, in December, 2024.
But since then, it became the
factor standard across the industry.
And just to give you an example
OpenAI, the main rival of Atropic
actually also adopted MCP.
The latest GBT five, GT 5.1 they can also
work with MCP, but MCP essentially is a
protocol for LLMs to gather extra context.
It is based on recent RPC 2.0, and
essentially it is just a set of structured
inputs and outputs, but the main two,
entities, the mental concepts inside MCP
would be MCP host first of all, right?
So MCP host is essentially your
LLM your id, which is essentially
the proxy between the LLM.
And the MCP server and then
MCP server the second entity is
responsible for two main things.
First, it is responsible for advertising
the list of capabilities, the list of
tools available to MCP, host to LLM.
And second, it is responsible for actually
executing those tools and those tools
can access pretty much anything, right?
So anything you need to
gather extra context.
And provide it to LLM.
You can convert to MCP server
and it can access, let's say,
local resources, maybe your file
system, maybe trans batch commands.
It can also access remote resources, of
course so it can access, for example,
GitHub or Jira or whatever system you use.
So again, essentially whatever,
anything you can convert to, the code,
anything you can access through code
can be converted to MCP server and
then used to feed more context to LLM.
There are actually several features of
MCP inside the model context protocol.
However, the most known is tools, and this
will be the main focus of our today stock.
But I also would recommend to
check out all the other features
like resources, prompts, sampling,
'cause they do provide some useful
capabilities on top of MCP tools.
But here's an example of the tool.
So on the right over here you
can see the actual implementation
of the tool for creating branch.
This is taken from GitHub, MCP server,
and this is actually not the full code.
This is just the
beginning of the function.
So we hear that they define
essentially the description the
annotation of the tool and which kind
of parameters it takes as inputs.
You can actually see a more compact
description on the left, which is
what is actually included into the
prompt and then later fed into LLM.
So as you can see there's
a description, right?
So it creates a new branch in GI
repository, GitHub repository.
It takes as input four parameters,
although only three of them are required.
And essentially this helps
LLM to decide which tool it
needs to use and how to use it.
And this is how the actual flow would
look like between the user us LLM CCP
client server, and some external system.
So first, as I mentioned the
MCP server is responsible for
adver advertising capabilities.
So this is essentially just
a handshake stage between MCP
client and MCP server over here.
So whenever.
MCV.
Whenever MCP client initialize connection
to MCV server, the server returns the
list of its available capabilities,
which are then later, as I mentioned,
attached to the prompt of, input to LLM.
Now, whenever we as user ask
something from LLM, so let's say
again we ask for the response time
for Google, LLM recognizes the
need functional external data.
So in this case, it needs to
perform maybe pin command, right?
Whenever a lamb.
The decide that it needs access
for to more data, that it
needs to gather more context.
It can request the use of MCP capabilities
and then well, there is of course
also optional permission request.
Although most of m, most of
MCP servers do not do this.
Or MCP clients.
Then MCP client, it provides to MCB server
which cap, which kind of capability.
It wants the server to execute along
with some inputs if they are required.
And then MCB server is actually
responsible for executing that tool call.
Gathers the data and then this data is
returned in a formative way in a start,
in a standardized way back to LLM.
And then LLM hopefully can give us the
answer already right away, or maybe
it can, decides to gather more context
through different tool and so on,
all the way until it gathers enough
information to give us contextualized
answer to our initial query.
And there are already quite a
lot of different MCP servers
available for you to use.
So on the left this not, probably not
even the 1% of all the servers available.
As you can see, they they're not only
about software systems, although you can
see for example, there, there is Grafana
there is Click House or CloudFlare.
So those MCP servers would allow
LLM to access those systems.
But there are also, cPS for
tools outside of IT space?
There is, for example, the one Thea,
which it is a search engine, but of
course you can find MCP servers pretty
much for I would say almost anything.
And there are a few marketplaces
or registries for MCP servers.
The first one, the initial one sort of
from Tropic contains quite a lot of,
mCP servers for example, MCP servers,
as well as those which are in which
were initially implemented by tropic.
We at Quar also have our own
marketplace, and there are of course,
also a lot of third party marketplaces
available for you to search for MCP.
And here's an example of a few probably
the most helpful cps, which you might
find useful in your everyday life.
Of course there is MCP to access
database to access databases.
So here's an example for Postgres.
But depending on what kind of
database you use internally,
you might prefer different.
Different MCP.
There is, there are of course servers, MCP
servers to access login systems, right?
So monitoring systems like Grafana,
for example, or sentri there is
tools or servers to access messaging
tools like Slack, for example.
Context seven is another helpful
MCP, which essentially allows LLM
to search for UpToDate documentation
for any library, for any framework.
And there is also playwright, MCB, not
to be confused with playwright testing
framework playwright, MCB server allows
LLM to essentially use the browser.
So it allows LLM to open the browser,
navigate to pages, click around
fill fulfilling forms, and so on.
And then LLM can later use that to
write, for example, end-to-end tests.
Now if you don't find, the server,
which fits your needs you can of course
quite easily create your own MCP server.
And they there are SDKs available in
quite a lot of different languages.
I think there is now even
probably around 11 or 12.
Sdk.
So languages available for SDKs, and as
you can see, of course it is available
in the most popular languages like
Python tab script, Java, and so on.
And you've seen an example
for MCP server, right?
For the creative branch.
It was actually in Go.
So you are not limited to
some specific language.
You can create MCP servers in pretty much,
any language you are comfortable with.
But here's an example on Python.
So in order to convert any code
to MCP server in Python, you
need essentially just those
three lines I circled in orange.
So of course we need to first
import library called Fast, MCP.
Then we need to instantiate
the faster MCP server.
And then we just need to label
our function in this case for
execution batch commands with
this, the curator m CCP tool.
And that's pretty much it, that.
So with just those three lines, we
converted our initial code for running
batch commands into MCP server.
And now any LLM compatible with MCP
can use this server to execute batch
commands on our local system now.
Let's actually see this in action.
I have a few practical examples to show
how it looks like in, in real life and
how MCP can extend the capabilities of LMS
beyond just output in the text for you.
So first one the most, probably
obvious one, is a combination
of Jira and Git and GitHub, MCP.
So through this combination.
You can essentially ask Lamb to
pull the contact from Jira Ticket,
solve it for you commit changes,
and then create a pull request.
And of course, if you are using not
Jira, but maybe linear or maybe not
GitHub, by GitLab, you can replace
the, those MC, those respective
MCP servers with something else.
But in my case, I will be shown
an example in this combination.
So let me switch my screen
over here to this code.
And over here I'll actually
already pre executed an example.
So inside encoder we have a native
integration of Jira, which essentially
allows you to just tag the ticket.
However, of course you can achieve
pretty much the same through JMCP,
although it wouldn't be as user friendly.
As native integration.
But basically here I'm taking the
ticket, asking the agent, let me zoom in
asking the agent to solve it, create a
branch push and create a pull request.
And it took the agent a bit of
time so it, navigated through the
repository, again, through different
tools, through different CP tools.
It has access not just to Jira,
Git and GitHub, but also it is,
provided with tools we serve as
part of encoder, so tools like grab
or maybe reading files and so on.
So it did a few, a bit of
exploration of the repository.
It found all the next three
files, which needs to be modified.
And it starts modifications.
So modifying the code, it, it ran some
batch commands to generate the open.
I open API schema.
And in the end let me
scroll all the way down.
So somewhere in the end, it
created the branch for us.
Let's see.
I don't see the, yeah, the
branch was created somewhere.
I think I missed it.
But basically it created a branch.
It created a commit, it pushed everything,
and then it used GitHub, MCP tools.
To create a pull request
for us over here and let me
actually show how it looks like.
So this is our pull request and
I would say it this probably.
One of the nicest looking
pull requests I've ever done.
It was used my token, so it is authored
by me, but it basically made also
changes in this case, quite a lot of
files 110 files it committed them.
Created a nice description.
Again all the changes, how it
works pretty much everything.
And yeah, again, I would say with
probably one pull request I've ever done.
And I guess it is nowadays the
sign of AI because, in this
day and age document PR, is.
Apparently by thing because it
is most likely generated by ai.
But jokes aside, asking LLM
to solve a ticket for you is a
rather obvious example, right?
So let's go to the second one, which is a
bit more more not advanced, but a bit more
going beyond just, solving the ticket.
So we can actually give LLM access
to Kubernetes, so we can give it
access to our Kubernetes cluster,
and then we can for example, ask
it if there are any issues with the
pods with the deployments and so on.
So let me actually switch
to my vs code over here.
And again, I pre executed one example.
Let's see this one.
So essentially here I'm asking are
there any pods in the specific name
space which are in non-healthy state?
So you can see LLM used the, that.
Specific tool for listing pods in name in
namespace from the Kubernetes MCP server.
And in this case the, there are apparently
no pods in unhealthy state, but of course
if there would be any you could then, for
example, ask LLM to fix the issue for you.
Maybe there is an issue in the code.
Maybe there is an issue in the deployment,
but essentially given access to the
Kubernetes to the Kubernetes cluster,
LLM can then help you either Deb back
something without you needing to copy,
paste the errors or anything else.
Essentially, LLM can adjust.
Do that for you.
It can just go to the cluster, check
the logs, check the events see what
are the states of the posts and so on.
Then use that information to give
you better better answers, more
relevant answers, and help you
further improve your productivity.
But of course, now with a great
power comes great responsibility.
And while MCP is great for extending
capabilities of our lambs beyond
just output and text MCP servers
also do make with a lot of issues,
security issues and backdoors and
you be doors and no authentication
is just scratching the surface here.
But I prefer to split those security
issues into two kinda main categories.
First of all, of course, as I was
shown previously, MCP servers are
essentially code which you run on
your server or on your local machine.
Which means that whenever you are using.
Any third party third party MCP
server, it is essentially you
running any third party code.
And of course the usual suspects when
it comes to executing third party code
on your machine, on your server are,
the typical stuff which you might,
already be protecting from, right?
So it can be packaged and hijacking,
it can be executing malicious
code because you are essentially
executing the code that could be
supply chain attacks and so on.
So in this category of attacks, there is
no really specificity to MCP or to ai.
It is essentially general attacks based
on execution, third party libraries
and all the tools which you might
already use to protect from that.
So maybe some study static code
analysis or something similar.
They are already helpful.
When it comes to MCP, however
with MCP, there is another
player which is essentially ai.
And there are of course a lot of
attacks or which are based on sort
of social engineering for ai and.
All of those attacks, in a sense, can
be classified as prompt injection.
But they have their own sort
of twist when it comes to MCP.
But of course, still prompt injection
itself is one of the most prominent
way ways to attack AI systems.
And prompt rejection means that
essentially, the perpetrator injects
a special string into the prompt,
into your initial prompt as a user.
And then this prompt is is
essentially hijacking the LLM
and making it do something else.
So let's say you as a user ask LLM about
the weather somewhere but then attacker.
Adds some specific lines of, specific
line of lines of text and it makes
LLM instead of answering you about the
weather, it makes LLM do something else.
Maybe create a file on your
system or maybe just output
some text about something else.
So that's prompt rejection.
And of course through MCP you can inject
it in different ways, but there are
also attacks which are MCP specific.
So of course you can potential the
attacker potentially can poison
the tool, meaning that the code,
which is being executed whenever
the tool is called can be malicious.
It may, it might be doing something
else, not what advertised by the tool.
There are also attacks
based on tool shadowing.
So essentially let's say a malicious
MCP server creates a tool which
is called the same as, or maybe
similar to to the benign server.
And then.
AI might decide or speak, client
might decide to use this shadowed
malicious tool just because the name
is similar or the same and hence goes
unnecessary execution of malicious code.
Then of course MCP through MCP source,
you can actually execute code as well.
There is a way to essentially ask AI.
To just simply execute the malicious code.
You don't even need to modify the
MCP server CP, the code MCP server.
Somehow AI can essentially execute
malicious code for you through MCP.
Now let me show a quick example
of how the prompt objection can
hijack your LLM through the use
of a few cps, a few simple cps.
So let me switch to my notebook over here.
Let me remove all this.
And what I have here is a simple
MCP client which is, in this
case using a closed, so 4.5.
And execute this.
It is simple MCP client.
It gets a few tools at this disposal.
So there are 3M CP servers.
First one is for accessing a file
system so it can read files, it can
write files, move files, and so on.
There is a MCP server for fetching
web pages, and then there is MCP
server for executing batch commands.
So on top of that, I also have
right now locally a simple web
server, which looks pretty much
safe for us for human eye, right?
And as a name suggest it is actually safe.
I have another page, which is called
Not Oops, which again looks the same.
And I have a third page
called Oops, which is.
Again, looks the same for humans,
but let's ask our LLM to fe the
content of those three pages and
observe how it look, how it behaves.
So every time I ask to our LLM,
our son is 4.5 to fe the content
of the page and then say hi to us.
So let's see what happens
with our regular page?
As expected, it fetched the content.
The content looks pretty
much like what we saw, right?
And then well the LLM says
hi to us as instructed.
Now the second page, not
oops, is a bit tricky.
Because even though of course LLM
providers, they try to protect
from interjections still, not all
attacks can be successfully detected.
Actually, I think on Tropic several months
ago reported that they detect up to 88% of
prompt injection attacks, but this still
leaves 12% of attacks and not detected.
So this page not, oops.
Sometimes it's actually hijacks LLM.
Sometimes it doesn't.
So let's see if it will hijack
the LLM in this case, in this run.
But essentially, as you can see, the.
In addition to what we've
seen on the page, right?
So the hello world this
is my simple webpage text.
It actually also had an extra instruction,
which was hidden from human eye, but
it was fetched through fetch MCP tool.
Now in this case the agents hi to us.
It also noticed that the code block but it
decided not to follow instructions because
it appears to be potentially malicious.
There could be like security vulnerability
and so on, similar to prompt injection.
So in this case the prompt injection
detection worked on the tropic side.
And LLM actually refused
to do anything else.
And in this case, we asked the LLM to also
create a file called, oops six, oops, 60.
Now let's try our third page and see
how our LLM will behave In this case
as you remember, it was for human eye.
It was the same context.
However, there is actually extra
data added to the page and as
you can see in this case, okay,
let's see what's going on there.
Okay.
It looks like there is
some issue with Tropic.
Let's, let me try to run this.
Hopefully tropic will be back up.
Okay.
But yeah, wireless execution, basically,
as you can see in this case it is
a bit more elaborate instructions.
So we are asking LLM to list
every function it has access to,
which in sa in itself it is not
really a malicious intent, right?
But then on top of that, we actually also.
Telling LM that we have a new
function, which is basically writing
a phrase into the file and then we
asking it to test it by cus this
function and simulate the output.
As if it was a real function.
Now, as you can see, it took quite
a long time for LLM to respond,
and surely enough, first of all,
it set high as instructed, but then
on top of that it actually started
listing all the available functions.
It's actually quite a lot
of functions, 17 functions.
But then what is more, when we
asked to test mock function,
it actually didn't just.
Simulate the output.
It actually ran a right file
tool and created a tech txt
file on our local machine.
Let me actually show it.
So it was created 49 seconds ago,
and surely enough, essentially LLM
was hijacked and potentially this
could lead to LM either executing
some malicious code or maybe.
Still in some files, still
in some data, and so on.
As you can see it was still quite
easy to attack an LLM, but again,
for the human eye, the page
looked pretty much safe, right?
So it only for human eye only
had these these two lines
of code written on the page.
Now, if you want to play
with this notebook, here's a.
Sorry.
Here's the cure code, where you can find
that code, that notebook, and you can
play around with it on your own free time.
That as you've seen technically the
MCP itself in my example, was not
responsible for the actual attack, right?
So it just fetched the page and
the actual attack was, execute
through the context of the page.
MCP itself didn't do anything wrong.
It did exactly what it was created to do.
And this is actually how one of the recent
attacks on GitHub MCP, it was executed.
So you might have heard about this
essentially again, in this case.
MCP on its own was not
responsible for this exploit.
Okay.
What they did in this case is they
essentially just created a issue in
the public repository saying that
the author is not widely recognized.
And then they just asked LLM to go
through all the private repositories,
collect information, and then add this
information to this public repository.
And then LLM give.
Being given access to GitHub MCP,
it did pretty much what it was
asked to do because 'cause why not?
It was asked to gather information.
It did this because it was given the
tools to do this, and then it essentially
just leaked, private information into
the public space, and again, technically
MCP itself, I have MCP itself is.
Is not the tool at fault here it
is the way AI is behaving or the
way AI agents are behaving that is
responsible for this exploit Now.
What are the ways to
protect your organization?
First of all, of course you
might want to wide list cps.
So you might want to define
which MCPS you actually want.
To allow your developers to use, or, your
LLM to use, you might want to consider
organization wide MCB Confis which
means that you can control permissions.
So it could be some redundant flags,
it could be some specific set of
tools which are allowed to be used
of from this MCP server and so on.
And of course, some MCP
servers require tokens.
So let's say GitHub, MCP,
of course, requires GitHub.
Personal access token to be able to
access GitHub, and you might want
to, somehow safely and securely
store them in your preferred system.
You might also want to limit access to
sensitive systems, which means maybe
not give access to production databases.
To LLM or maybe at least not
access to those databases.
And you might also want to limit
server or tool permissions.
Again, readonly is one example,
but actually in Kubernetes,
CCP is a good example of that.
So they provide two flex as
part of their MCP server.
One is to enable return the tools.
And then the second one is to
disable destructive so that LLM will
not accidentally or not delete the
cluster or do some modifications
to the cluster and so on.
And then specifically for the prompt
ejection detection prevention, as
I mentioned most of, all of the,
large labs which provide LLMs like
open air and tropic and so on.
They, of course work on securing and
preventing from injection attacks.
Although again, of course you
can't protect from anything.
If you are worried about.
L lamps ingesting some harmful data
you might want to consider to use
some sort of intermediary tool.
So again, in case of ingesting webpages,
for example, specifically like I've
shown before, you might want to consider
using some proxy that doesn't just
ingest webpage and pass it as is to LLM.
You might want to use some
sort of ai, web search, right?
SOA or perplexity for example.
'cause they on top of just
ingesting the web pages.
They also do some summarization.
They also do some protection and so on.
So you might want to essentially use
these sort of proxy tools before actually
dumping the data into the LLM leading
to potentially harmful consequences.
And with that that's all for me.
So if you want to try out Sun Code,
you can use this secure code over
here on the, I guess on your left.
And then if you want to
connect with me over here.
You'll find all my socials
LinkedIn and so on.
And thank you all for attention and I
hope you have a good day ahead of you.