Good morning.
Good afternoon everyone.
My name is Rajni k I'm a senior support
communications manager at Snowflake.
Welcome to this talk.
This talk is about AI driven
customer experience, how to start
scale and succeed in the enterprise.
Let's get started.
Okay.
So customer experience
is rapidly changing.
Like all these companies and enterprises
were able to serve customers in a reactive
mode until yesterday, meaning customers
if run into any problem, they'll come to.
The enterprise support portal, or
they'll call the customer service,
they'll open up a technical ticket
or support case with the company, and
then somebody will be looking into the
problem after they happen and then they
try to solve and help the customer.
So that was the yesterday scenario,
how the customer's experience was.
And coming to today, in this, today's
years and world of ai practically
anticipating customer needs even
before the customer asks, right?
It's becoming increasingly
common by, by leveraging AI
tooling and the technologies.
So yet these AI tools are delivering.
Delivering, sorry, personalized
experiences to millions of
people simultaneously in
real time across the globe.
You take an example of retail
or healthcare or banking and
finance, whatever industry it
is, they are using AI to deliver
personalized experience at scale.
So I'll talk about that in the
upcoming slides and I'll show you some
examples from different industries.
And also, yeah, mixing AI with the
human expertise is very important
not to replace the humans.
One has to leverage AI to amplify
that kind of an expertise from
the human side of the things.
So that's that, that's how
like the customer experience
is changing in today's world.
So here are the three pillars
of like artificial intelligence
driven customer experience.
The first pillar is hyper
hyper personalization.
Like tailoring experiences
to individuals based on their
preferences, behaviors, or context.
For example, if you take any
e-commerce business so like Amazon or.
Any other e-commerce retail,
so they know like what the
customer's browsing history was.
They know what the customers
purchased during what time, what
they bought in the last winter, or
like what kind of a colors they like,
what kind of a models they like.
So they know everything, right?
They know everything about their customer.
So by leveraging AI on top of
the data, whatever they have.
They can personalize
everything to the customer.
That particular customer, not 10 thousands
or a hundred thousands of customers.
It's personalized to that particular
individual who is browsing during
that moment, during that day,
during that festival season or
holiday season, whatever it is.
And the second pillar
is like intelligent ent.
These AI powered reagents, like
they, they are very capable enough
to try solving complex problems.
They understand the patterns.
Even if you have.
Mountains of data, they know how to,
dig through the data and come up with
like solutions with, for those complex
issues with mixing up with human empathy.
So these are going to be very
powerful agents, these AI agents.
And the last one is
predictive insights, right?
Anticipating needs and resolving any
issues that may happen even before
customers notices them, right?
For example, in the, i in the
telecom industry if the company
companies are using AI to
proactively monitor the signal drops.
Or if it is in fiber internet
or something, they even.
Getting to know if there are any
pockets, drops or something like that.
And then they are proactively
fixing those issues even before
the customer noticing them.
So that's pretty solid pillar.
For the, aI driven customer experience.
Alright, let's go to the next one.
And the next one is an example
from the retail industry.
I talked about this a little bit in
the previous one as I said if you
take a real world scenario as soon
as a customer walks into your store
or they started browsing online.
Shopping online.
So AI recognizes who that customer
is and what their browsing history
and what kind of purchase patterns
the customer had in the past.
And then they'll there, and then
they'll provide those recommendations
based on all these points.
And the second one is the AI will enable
dynamic pricing for the customer based on
their individual preference and demand.
It's not like a. Generic solution
or 20% off across all the
customers or something like that.
But it's basically pointing or
categor like delivering the pricing
strategy exclusively designed
for that particularly individual
during that day, during that time.
During that holiday season.
So that's the hyper
personalization in retail.
And the third one again, as I said
showing product recommendations
based on the weather.
Hey, this customer has purchased a winter
jacket during last year, during November.
And if the customer is browsing during
November, but this year around the
same time, probably let's show him
like some different winter jackets
based on his color references, based on
his choices that he made in the past.
So that's hyper-personalization that
we are talking about, and this is
all made possible because of, like
using AI into the regular workflows.
So that's the power of AI and
coming to the hyper-personalization.
And if you take finance
or healthcare, right?
So finance financial services
are like companies who
offers like investment plans.
They are basically using AI to tailor.
Tyler to provide a tailored approach
based on the risk tolerance of the
individual based on their personal goals.
Based on the, based on like
their age, where they are in
their life during wall stage.
And, like it's a powered personal
financial advisor for that particular
design, exclusively for that individual.
Based on these, all these factors,
a 25 year world startup founder.
Maybe looking at the different
options compared to a 55-year-old
person who is nearing retirement.
So the system understands using the ai
about the, about all these like data
points, and then comes up with the,
like financial plan, investment plan
exclusively designed for that particular
customer based on all these factors.
That's about finance.
And if you come to healthcare,
again, the same thing.
AI is powering, delivering care at
speed based on the medical history,
previous, past episodes of the
customer their references, their
demographics, or if they, based on,
even based on their literacy level.
Because some of the educational
materials they are very important
for the patients, let's say.
If your patient knows that, if they're
the first time diabetic patient, they
wanted to understand what are the,
some of the things that they have to
take care and what are the dietary
plans and all this kind of stuff.
If you just hand out your education.
Educational papers or something like
that, that they have to go through, it
would be difficult for them to understand.
So that's where the AI can help you.
Like based on all this information
to serve patients better based
on all these, like inputs it's
exclusively like patient-centric.
I, as we know it's not like
one size fits all, right?
It has to be.
Category.
It has to be specially designed for
that particular patient based on all
these factors that we talked about.
So that's another example.
In the healthcare we talked about
retail, finance, and healthcare.
So in the next slide, probably I'll
talk through the case study that
we work at Snowflake for processing
thousands of customer satisfaction
feedbacks that are coming in.
So the part one in this particular
slide I'll explain the challenge
that we have faced, and in the
next slide I'll talk about the
solution that we have put together.
Okay.
The challenge was, as I said as soon as.
Like a support ticket is closed.
We ask, or we send a survey link
to our customers, ask them to
provide their feedback, right?
Based on the service
that they have received.
And as part of the survey, we are
providing a open text form, open text
box, asking them to provide their response
whatever they're thinking about the
survey, and if they would like to see
any improvements or if they wanted to
understand why certain feature is designed
in such a way or something like that.
Or even if they wanted to say
thank you to the customer engineer,
whoever helped them to fix the issue.
So that's the kind of open text box
that we are putting in the survey form
and asking our customers to fill the
form as soon as they have some time.
So we are receiving definitely
responses thousands of responses
are coming in every week.
And we are a we have a team of
three and manually going through
each of those responses and
categorizing them by sentiment like
positive, negative, or neutral.
And also mapping them to issue type.
Like this is a product feature issue.
This is a service quality issue.
Or this is a technical issue,
something like that, right?
So we need to bucket those feedbacks
into various issue types so that we can
have some kind of a closed loop process
so that we can fix those issues and
improve our overall customer satisfaction.
So manually categorizing those thousands
of feedbacks that are coming in and
putting them into various sentiments
and issue types is a very tedious tasks.
Literally it takes weeks.
If we are receiving thousands of
feedbacks this week to process those
thousands of feedback manually, it takes
weeks for a team of three or team of
anybody to to, do that kind of a work.
So of course, like the teams were
burned out doing a repetitive heavy
manual data entry kind of a work.
It's not going to scale out, and
it's by the time the feedback
reached to the particular team
it's already scaled out, right?
We cannot really make use of the feedback.
So that's the problem that we, we dealt
with in my company where I work right now.
And let me show you the solution, right?
What's the solution that we came up?
Of course we used the ai but what we
did was like, we plugged the AI into
the whole workflow, as I said, like we
have a platform survey platform that is
getting all the survey responses and we
are feeding the survey responses into
your snowflake table, capturing that
information into your snowflake table.
And then we have plugged in
the AI deployed AI model.
To read all those, like feedbacks and at
scale and classify them into sentiments,
into issue types and everything right.
At scale.
We don't need to manually do this.
Yeah.
The workflow will automatically.
Call the ai model a AI function, and
then it'll process all those feedbacks
we, which were came in the last
week and automatically process them.
So what's the result?
Earlier it used to take weeks,
as I said, like to process
those thousands of feedbacks.
Now it is, AI is doing it in overnight,
maybe within hour, within few hours.
So that's a tremendous change from
the effort standpoint, and then it's,
it is definitely saving millions of
dollars by, like eliminating that kind
of manual work and freeing up the teams
so that the teams can free up from
that kind of a robot type of work.
And better utilize that time in strategic
problem solving, building relationships,
and working with cross-functional teams
to actually implement the feedback that
we are receiving from our customers.
So what's the end result here?
Of course, we have an improved
csat customer satisfaction.
And also pretty faster
response times, right?
We don't need to wait for weeks and
we can solve those issues pretty fast.
And also happier teams, right?
So even like the internal teams are pretty
happy because they get to see the customer
responses, customer feedback in any
faster time so that they can act on it.
Then they can close the loop.
That's this kind of a solution.
So again, like we didn't
build it from the scratch.
We used our existing workflow and instead
of doing a manual categorization, we
have we have plugged in an AI model a
classification model into the existing
workflow, which is like reading,
feeding sorry, reading the data from
a snowflake table and processing it
and putting it into another table.
And then that table is of course having
all the information, the sentiment and the
issue type, categorization, everything.
And so this entire workflow is
scheduled to run every week.
We don't need to do anything every week.
Midnight Sunday night, it kicks off and
it starts processing all that information
by Monday morning as soon as the teams are
in, and they will be able to see all the
information and start working on those.
Yeah, this is very useful.
Our teams are happy, as I
said, like we are using it.
In our company right now,
and it's pretty good.
It's going pretty good.
And like even when it comes
to in this slide, right?
Even it comes to we, we all, at
some point in time in interacted
with chatbots for sure, right?
These chat bots, right?
The traditional chat bots,
more or less are designed to.
Answer frequently asked questions
based off of script based responses.
Something like, what are your store hours?
Or what's your written policy?
Or something like that, right?
So immediately there will be.
There will be an answer
available based on a script.
So it's a traditional chat bot
that we have that we are we have
all seen, and interacted with.
But AI has changed that
game as well, right?
So the modern AI agents are
so powerful and they're pretty
good at solving complex issues.
And, like understanding the context,
the full context, what the customer
is talking about, and they can also
signal the customer frustration and
like they, they try to, empathetically
respond back to the customer based on the
questions that the customers are asking.
And even it can pull in a human, right?
If it cannot solve.
The problem there and itself.
And it'll provide the full context
to human and then the human can pick
it up there and there itself, right?
Without needing to go back, start
over everything from the beginning.
So that's the power of modern AI agents.
So just to give you an example, right?
If you.
Look at any airline if you missed
your flight, and then you are
looking to rebook your flight, right?
So if you imagine you have
a ai chat bot or a agent.
Available within your flight provider
app, which will automatically understand
your situation, compares prices and
everything rules and everything.
And it comes up with your
new new flight booking.
All.
You just need to do an accept, click
on accept, and then you're good to go.
You are new boarding pass
will be ready and you're ready
to board your next flight.
So that's a kind of an, a good realistic
example that I can talk about other than
what we have implemented at Snowflake.
With the modern AA agents,
you don't need to do anything.
You don't need to talk to any
person, any human, so everything
will be taken care automatically.
So I think that's where like the,
a AI agent, short signing the agent
AI is becoming so popular especially
for these type of use cases.
Let's go to the next slide.
So this is where like I just wanted
to touch upon various industries
where they can start, where, how they
can scale and succeed with the ai.
For example, as I talk a little bit about,
like the telecom or the internet companie.
They can predict predict so churn
even before customers leave, right?
Let's say the usage is going down or, if
the customer is not using their service
pretty much any much pretty much, then
probably, like it can practically.
Send out personal retention offers
through their, to their emails based
on the behavior or something like that.
So that, that is one thing.
And also, if the, as I said, if the
network is not working as expected
let's say a customer has signed up for,
like a hundred megabits per second.
But they are end up receiving only 20
s. But they're not noticing anything.
Major difference.
Like the, these systems can predict
and then they can fix everything
back in the backend automatically,
even before customer notices it.
And also in the SaaS side of the things
we know, like the SaaS is a very popular,
like a lot of product, a lot of companies
are spliting up their SaaS products.
The AI can help you.
Identify feature adoption gaps.
And also, let's say O one SaaS
company have 10 different features,
the customer is only using one
or two probably, like the AI can
automatically send a personalized
tutorial based on the customer use
case or the customer environment.
And then they can explain like
how they can use other eight
or nine features, which the
customer is not using as of today.
And also it can help respond to customer
proactively even before they come and
open a support case with us, right?
Support ticket with us.
And when you take a look
at the manufacturing, the
predictive analytics kind of a.
Use case for the manufacturing industry is
basically anticipating equipment failures.
Scheduling, maintenance even before.
And they go down IOT sensors by using
IOT sensors and like the systems will
predict and then they'll send in alert.
To the technician, and the technician
will automatically take care of
the, of those, missions missionary
before, before they go down.
And also as we all know ai is
helping financial and all companies,
maybe mostly this is applicable
for all industries, right?
Where payment is payment processes
involved, so it can automatically
detect payment issues and issue
auto refund in case of any
failures or something like that.
And even communicate before the
customers can complain, saying that,
Hey, your transaction is failed.
We have automatically refunded every
amount back to the original payment
method or something like that.
So that's the power of predictive
analytics, and that's where the
companies can start scale and succeed
without, needing to put too much of
manual effort just by tapping on the
AI and including AI into their regular
workflows and adding human in the loop.
All right.
Let's so what are the, some of the ethical
challenges or what are the, some of the
challenges that, that anybody or everybody
can face during this whole journey?
Number one is and also I'll touch base
a little bit about how to navigate them.
Number one is like the data
is always residing in silos.
So that is the biggest challenge that
they all these enterprise companies
have, like they have their CRM systems,
they have their customer transaction
systems, they have their royal TP systems.
Maybe they have their like data
warehouses, data lakes, so that
the data is everywhere, right?
So we need to invest in, how to
overcome the challenge is simple, right?
We have to.
Invest in, in data integration
and a good data governance before
plugging in yay AI on top of the data.
So that's the number one challenge.
And and how to overcome that is
is having a good data governance
and data integration in place.
And the second one is by
us in training, right?
So if you train your model
only on some type of data.
It'll always try to, bias
us towards that, right?
So you have to ensure that your
training data is well diversified
and also you need to audit data for
the training data for data quality.
Are there any issues or is
the data, is the good data
or does it have any bad data?
Missing emails or missing missing,
like some other information,
which is very key for the AI
model to predict and take action.
And also how to test models for
fairness across, different segments
of people, different segments of, like
geographies or something like that.
So that's one thing that
we have to be very careful.
And the second one is and the third
one is like our personalization
is sometimes it causes.
Too much of a problem for customers.
We have to be always transparent
and we have to tell our customers
that saying that, Hey, we are using
AI to provide you a better service.
If you are not into it please opt out.
From that, something like that, right?
So we have to provide better
controls to, to our customers.
And also adding humans in the loop for
any critical decisions is always best.
Even though AI is doing a lot
of heavy lifting, that shows
some accountability on our side.
Which is very important in this slide.
So these are the five best
practices that, that I can, and
that I can share with you all.
The number one is of course data is first.
I always put data at the first
because, like quality data foundation
even before building your EA models,
training your EA models or testing them.
So you have to always have your
data, quality of data available
in a commonplace and also.
You need to integrate AI
into your existing workflows.
You don't need to, create or
rebuild everything from the scratch.
Just identify areas where your
teams are putting a lot of manual
effort and see naturally v AI
can be a best fit in that area.
And then start including ai there, right?
So you just build a AI model or try to
plug in your s and then input your, data
into the LLM and it'll automatically,
start taking care of that heavy
process lifting or something like that.
And of course, you have to
the third best practice.
You have to always.
Add a human in the loop.
As we know, AI tends to make
some mistakes, so it's always
good to have some human oversight
and feedback into the model.
The fourth one is, like
measure continuously.
In our previous example that
I have shown you, like csat.
So we have before and after, and also
we try to see like how the CSAT scores
before and after, how the resolution
times are looking, like, how the
retention rates are looking like,
so you have to track and iterate on
the same thing every now and then.
And the last point here is the,
transparency, as I talked about it
in the earlier slide, you have to be
very transparent with the use of ai.
So you have to tell your customers
that you're using AI to improve
their overall experience.
It, it definitely builds trust and you
have to provide them options, right?
If they don't want to use ai, they can
they should be able to opt out of that.
So that's the fifth to best practice.
These five best practices are a very
important, and we have used these five
best practices in our day-to-day regular
work at Snowflake building the, especially
the examples that I have talked about.
So what is the path forward?
So the path forward is
pretty simple, right?
So these companies are, that the leading
tech companies are using ai for serving
better providing best customer experience.
Come up with like the features that
the customers are asking for, improving
their overall products and services.
So those are the winners.
These winners aren't
replacing humans for sure.
With the AI automation or A TKA are
using AA in regular day-to-day life.
But instead they are enhancing the overall
experience by adding AI into the regular
workflows and having human connection
with with all these intelligent systems.
One, one small thing that I can suggest
definitely to everybody, whoever
is listening to this conversation
this talk you have to start small.
You don't need to build everything
from the scratch, as I said, see
observe your existing workflows
and see where you can include ai.
So that's where like you have to
measure your impact and, and also
see that if the scaling also works
from if AI can best serve that kind
of a scale always keep the human in
the loop and feedback to the model.
Thank you all so much for.
Like joining in if you have any questions,
feel free to reach out to me and you
can find me on LinkedIn by my name
Rajni K, and you can connect with me.
Thank you so very much, and you happy?
You have a great conference.
Thank you.
Bye-bye.