Good day everyone.
My name is Victor Abola, and today
I'll be speaking on a very important
topic in the field of cybersecurity
and digital investigations, how IC
or improved digital forensic analysis
and evidence collection processes.
In this section, we explore how
digital currency works with active
intelligence, what this means for
investigators, how modern tools are
evolving, and the future trends we
should be preparing for in the industry.
Digital forensics has expanded far
beyond computers with our evidence
for mobile devices, cloud environment,
vehicles, IOT devices, and more.
With this expansion comes massive
volume, complexity, and urgency.
Yet we also have ai, which provides
powerful waste to speed up investigations,
surface eating evidence, and reduce
overwhelming forensic backlogs.
It meets ai.
Today's evidence landscape is
complex investigative deal with
three to four week backlogs.
Because of huge data volumes,
AI helps it to automate routine
task, detect aiding patterns, and
highlight high value evidence.
AI augmenting investigative workflows
by automated repetitive tasks.
It helps in identifying
patterns humans may miss.
Highlighting priority evidence,
improving consistency and defensibility.
Machine learning detects anomalies
in backlogs where machine
learnings and understanding system
behavior and network traffic.
Machine learning also clusters, active
apps to refill at that campaign.
Machining.
Then it also classifies
more aware of families.
Deep learning performs image
and video analysis, facial
recognition and object detection.
It helps to detect medial taming.
It helps to analyze more aware behavior.
And we are NLP Natural Language
Processing that helps to extract entities
from emails, charts, and documents.
It helps to perform sentiments
and context analysis.
Summarizes long communication trait.
We have an understanding of what
this machine learning and deep
learning and natural language
processing does in our investigation.
So we'll be moving on to key applications
and use cases, automated evidence,
trial ai, prioritize relevant evidence.
AI helps to like have an
understanding of how to help
arrange our evidences in terms of.
Their priority in terms of putting
them together in terms of also
maximizing the full potential of
our investigation and our evidence.
We have pattern recognition
where it helps to reveal
reoccurring cyber crime patterns.
Has this been happening?
What is the duration of period
that has been happening?
What are the cases that has happened
that has helped us understand that
these cases is is similar media
analysis, categorizes images and ly.
Behavior and disease.
It helps to flag insider
traits and abnormal activities.
We have network analysis.
It helps to dictate exfoliation
and brute force activity.
Data recovery models like CAR dl.
It helps to construct fragmented
files with up to 85% of accuracy.
Moving on to AI power tools and platforms.
We have several platforms and several
AI investigation tools right now.
And one of them, one of the
leading is Celebrate Pathfinder
and AI driven evidence.
Correlation.
We have magnetism, we have Magnet
J, we have Microsoft with GPT,
and we are magnet copilot also.
The we'll be moving on to the benefits
and industry impact of these tools.
AI reduces backlogs, it improve
consistency skills, investigator
capacity, and strengthens differe
defensible evidence processes.
According to Celebrate 2025
survey, 19% cais positive impact.
It is insufficiency,
it's speed up analysis.
82% say it automates repetitive tasks.
61% sees AI as evaluated to as
much as potential of AI being
the risk, AI being the trade.
It owes a lot of important impact
in our industry, in our day-to-day
activities in whatever we do.
AI owes an a very, a large
impact of positive impact.
Also, we'll be discussing more about real
world implementations, how we've seen.
Where we've seen AI work.
Let's take for let's take and a look
into automated data with evidence
trials In many law enforcement
agencies, investigators routinely
receive multiple CI devices.
We have phones, we have several
gadgets, laptops, tablets, SB
devices naming, so creating a lot of
backlogs that can stress for weeks.
AI driven trial system
automatically scan these devices
the moment they are ingested.
Identifying priority items or sustain
deleted messages, suspicious media
on usual communication patterns or
recently access files instead of an
investigator manually combi through
thousands of artifact, the this AI
helps to organize the data by relevance,
drastically reviewing, reducing the
review time for the investigators.
These tools also highlight
anomalies such as rare file types.
Encrypt containers or apps
frequently used by no offenders.
By automatically producing a structured
preview, investigators can determine
which devices require full examination
and which do not, which reduces the
maximum of going through different each
one of the devices and gadget one after
the on this approach automatically
reduce wasted efforts, allowing teams
to focus on the highest value evidence.
In some agencies, this shift has reduced
turnaround time for three to four
weeks, to just a few days improving
case outcomes and speeding of justice.
AI also has helped a lot in
investigating C-A-C-S-A-M cases.
Child sexual abuse material is it
helps in the air system with deep
learning models can automatically
identify probable abuse content.
Without human exposure.
During the initial review, the
system analyzed image, visual pixel,
excel patterns, and contextual
cues to classify unfold media
with accuracy rates as higher 95%.
They also duplicates across global
databases, helping agency connect
vendors to known victims more rapidly.
Because the AI handles the first
layer of screening investigators see.
Only content that has been tried as
relevant, reducing emotional trauma.
The automated, the AI automated
workflow also speeds up reporting
to Child Protection Organization.
Ultimately, AI allows investigators to
focus on the legal and contextual aspect
of cases rather than manually reviewing
large volumes of disturbing content.
We, we've seen our AI has improved
a lot of real world cases.
It has helped us have an
understanding of what it takes to
induct AI in our investigation.
Let us also take another look at
at another real world case study c
dl and similar motives in terms of
deep learning based file recovery.
It helps it has shown how traditional
five carbon relies on pattern machine,
which struggles when files are fragmented.
Overwritten or partially corrupted
the deploy approaches social as.
CD uses neural networks trained
on thousands of file fragments
to construc data, even when
traditional methods failed.
Looking into a fraud investigation,
suspect or communicate across multiple
channels, SMS, name it, WhatsApp, email,
social media, and lots, like several apps.
Which creates a massive text
boarding for analyst NLP.
Tools automatically extract key
entities such as names, locations,
transaction details, or repeated keyword.
They can also map relationships
between individuals revealing
e network of collaborators.
In many cases, AI identified
pattern of deception, social
as sudden change in sentiment.
Repeated linguistic structure
used by scammers or put language.
This insight help investigators
quickly establish timelines,
communication, hierarchies, and motives.
The AI also surfaces messages that Devi
is from normal behavior, enabling ANA
analysis to support critical clues faster.
This has shown how important AI has
been, especially in important cases
that, helps to show how much we are able
to fish out and attack to understand
how we can comb through our evidences
real fast and real quick to make us to
make our investigation more fast and
better, we'll be discussing about the
challenges and ethical considerations.
AI system.
We have the bias and fairness in models.
AI system can unintentionally
irritated biases.
From the dataset they are trained
on, which may lead to on unfair
outcomes during investigation.
Let's take for example, even AI model
has been trained primarily on data
from a specific demographic group.
It may falsely classify
or over prioritized data
belonging to those population.
This can lead to unequal treatment and
investigation or misinterpretation of
digital evidence, forensic outcome, most.
Be consistent across all individuals
regardless of age, ethnicity,
gender, or socioeconomic background.
We have the privacy and legal constraints.
We it's resists a lot of complexity
when people are being where like when
we don't take need and real clear of
what it takes to have a privacy and
legacy constraint in our AI system.
AI analysis often involve processing
massive amounts of personal
information, auto messages, location,
history, and a lot of metadatas.
It raises a lot of complex privacy issues.
Investigators must follow sheets, legal
frameworks, including warrants, data
minimization laws, and restriction
on access cloud across data.
Cross-border datas
mismanaging data privacy.
Can compromise an entire investigation
or expose agency to legal liabilities
and definitely no agency or no.
Standard wants to go through social
and also the explainability and
code admissibility is the third one.
Many AI models, especially deep
planning systems, operate as black
boxes, making it difficult to clearly
describe their internal workflows.
Their processes, and most of the time
it's often invalidate a lot of things.
Courts often require transparent,
reproducible, and auditable
workflows to validate their
evidence was processed correctly.
If investigators cannot explain as
an AI output, a defense autonomy,
or really challenge its credibility.
Fourth on this list, we have
reliability and hallucination.
Although AI is very powerful, yeah,
understandably, it is not perfect and
can occasionally miss some upgrade data
or generate incorrect conclusions known
as hallucination In data forensics,
relying on hallucinated output can
lead to false leads, which identified
suspect or misclassified evidence.
Investigators must always validate
AI findings against raw, verifiable
data before, during conclusions.
Reliability testing is
essential, especially when
models are updated or retrain.
Systems should have safeguards to alert
users when confidence scores are low,
or evidence requires human review and.
Fifth on this list, which is one
of the most important governance,
oversight and accountability.
Successful AI deployment requires clear
governance frameworks that define how
tools are used, monitored, and audited.
Agencies must establish policy
detailing who is authorized to run
AI processes, how output should be
interpreted, and what documentation
did you require for every case.
Regular audit helps.
It helps to ensure that AI to
remain compliant with evolving
laws and ethical standards.
Oversight teams must also evaluate
model performance, DIC drift, and
ensure tools are not misused or
applied outside their intended scope.
And woman number six, woman
exported remains irreplaceable.
Even with advanced AI capabilities,
Oman investigators bring contextual,
understanding, intuition, and critical
reasoning that machines cannot replicate.
AI may alight patterns or
anomalies, but women must interpret
their significance within the
broader investigative narrative.
Complex cases involving emotional, social,
or behavioral element require non-judgment
that no model can actually fully capture.
This is like a great understanding
of the challenges and the ethical
consideration that we might have using ai.
And actually it helps us understand of
the kind of steps and processes of things
we should follow that would improve and
help our efficiency also in investigation.
Looking into the future trends,
what to expect, things we
should focus on going forward.
We have the LLM forensic copilot
that has been integrated across
a lot of DFIR work workflows.
It represents one of the most significant
advancement in digital investigation.
This AI assistant can summarize
case artifacts, interpret logs,
explain technical findings, and even
generate preliminary forensic reports.
Unlike traditional tools.
They provide contextual reasoning,
helping investigators quickly
understand conversions of events.
Co-pilot are also cross reference
multiple types of evidence messages,
metadata, images and timeline to
highlight patterns, human MI value.
And number two, under list,
we have the automated cloud
forensics cloud platform store.
Enormous amount of evidence.
But they are distributed and encrypted.
Nature makes investigation difficult.
Future forensic tools will integrate
automated cloud evidence capture,
allowing AI to collect logs, reconstruct
timelines, detected suspicious
activity across AWS Azure, Google
Cloud, and hybrid to architectures.
These systems will track
authentication events.
API calls.
By movement and access attempt
to create a full picture of
what happened during the breach.
And number three, on the list, we have
the IOT and vehicle forensic inspection.
The growth, the growth of IO OT has
connected vehicles, has created new
forensic data sources from smart home
sensors to automotive telematics.
Visual tools.
We incorporate AI models capable of
interpreting diverse iot metadata, social
device activity log, location based
triggers and environmental interactions.
This trend marks a significant expansion
of what is considered digital evidence.
We have advanced counter
anti forensic capabilities.
Criminals are increasingly using
anti forensic techniques like data
wiping, stick iconography, timestamp
manipulation, or encrypted containers
to I. Their tracks Visual AI system
will be designed to dictate these
techniques with far greater accuracy.
Deep lining models will identify so
to inconsistency in metadata residue
patterns left after wiping or pixel
level up anomaly that suggest tampering.
AI will become a critical defense
defense against increasingly
sophisticated digital cover.
We should have an understanding of that.
And the fifth on this
list is standardized.
Automating pipelines for investigation.
As AI becomes more embedded in the digital
forensics organization will move forward,
standardize repeated workflows that
reduce error and increase consistency.
Automation pipelines.
We are the tasks such as
evidence in the ingestion, ashin,
triad, artifact, destruction,
correlation, and initial reporting.
In the long term, automated forensic
pipelines will become the industry
north rather than an advanced feature.
We should know that.
And most importantly, number six, AI
power training and upskilling at scale.
The shortage of forensic investigators
is like a global challenge, like
a global thing, especially as
cyber camp concerns to grow.
These systems can generate customized
exercises based on a learning skills
level and provide immediate feedback.
LLM based tutor thought
will explain concept.
Guide trainings through complex
findings and answer technical
questions in real time.
Most importantly, we just have to keep
improving our language, learn more,
and as a result, workforce readiness
improves and the overall quality
of digital investigation increases.
Most importantly, one thing I want us to
focus on is the central insights from the.
Integration of AI into digital is
that the most effective investigative
outcomes emerge from combining machine
efficiency with Oman expertise.
In conclusion, the future of digital
forensics will be defined by a
balanced partnership between advanced
automation and skilled Oman analysis.
AI will become, it would always
continue to enhance capacity.
Reduce backlogs and uncover ING patterns.
While investigators maintain
responsibility for interpretation,
validation, and adherence to legal,
an ethical standards as forensic
technology, enforce organization
that successfully integrate both
human and artificial intelligence
will achieve the strongest and most
trustworthy investigative outcomes.
Thank you very much for listening
and I would be open to any questions.
Thank you very much.