Hello everyone.
Uh, this is Nhan nda, senior I
three B, member and, uh, cloud
architect to be talking about the
building unbreakable systems, the
risk driven DevSecOps and actions.
So the practical, the best practices.
Securing a distributed system is
complex, but true resilience comes from.
Robust practices, not just tools.
Alright.
The evolving challenges of
modern enterprise systems.
You know, the dynamic,
interconnected, and rapidly evolving.
Whereas coming to the complex systems,
you know, the modern enterprise
systems are complex way above the
cloud infrastructure like, you know,
SaaS, APIs and third party integration.
The forming a, the vast digital fabric.
Hidden vulnerabilities like you
know, vulnerabilities, luck and
misconfigurations, identity sprawl
and supply chain weakness, often
unseen by traditional security.
The proactive resilience.
You know, the true resilience requires
shifting from a reactive firefighting to
proactive foresightful security assurance.
Right.
Why traditional devs SEC
apps is not enough, right?
Limited scope, the pipeline focus.
DevSecOps leaves the critical grabs,
you know, across SaaS platforms,
identity and access management
and integration layer that exist
outside traditional ci cd workflows.
Reactive push security becomes a
downstream checkpoint focused on
scanning and gating releases rather
than an upstream design principle that
prevents issue before they manifest.
Scattered dispute without centralized
risk visibility, organization struggles
to prioritize, uh, remediation efforts
or understand the true security
posture across distributed systems.
We must expand dev apps behind
infrastructure and pipelines to
encompass the full ecosystem, the
shift to risk driven dev apps.
The first thing, identify critical assets.
You know, understand the
key business value and the
potential impact of the failure.
The second, prioritize by impact,
you know, allocate security
resources based on business impact.
Anchor decision and risk.
Use risk to guide engineering
priorities, automation and architecture.
You know, the risk driven dev sec apps.
The build Reside by focusing efforts on
protecting critical systems and data.
Seeing the wild risk landscape.
Map the ecosystem, not just the pipeline.
Okay, the cloud misconfiguration
storage buckets, network rules.
Encryption settings and
resource permissions across
multi-cloud environments.
Such third party risk, external
integrations, you know, a PA connections,
the vendor access and data sharing
relationships, identity surfaces, user
permissions, service accounts, or the
grants and privilege escalation parts.
The data flows, cross system dependencies.
The data movement patterns
and integrations, touch point,
comprehensive visibility across
your entire technology ecosystem
is the foundation of the residence.
You cannot protect what you cannot see.
Continuous monitoring complaints
as a practice detect issues
before they become incidents.
Right.
Rule number one, establish baselines,
define guardrails for common
failure points across cloud SaaS
identity and a PA configurations.
The next thing, continuency
policy checks audit.
Automated validation runs constantly
catching a drift and violations
in real time rather than during
periodic audits, always on feedback.
Treat compliance as continuous feedback
mechanism that informs engineering
decisions and improve system design.
Okay.
Alright.
What's the key insight?
The monitoring is not about deploying
more tools, it's about establishing
disciplined continuous validations
as a core operational practice.
I'm reading Zalen in CICD development.
The build systems that
can bend without breaking.
Automate early checks.
Okay.
Integrate security validations
directly into development workflows to
proactively identify and fix issues.
Dependency hygiene.
Ensure supply chain integrity,
buy consistently auditing and
updating all third party components.
Strengthen extension.
Fortify the custom scripts and integration
points with strict security standards
to eliminate common vulnerabilities.
You know, the pipelines became
resilience engines when practices
enforce consistency and predictability
across every deployment.
Access governance and audit as
a risk controls, reduce exposure
through good operational hygiene hub.
The role-based access
control design, RBAC.
Roles that map to a real job.
Responsibilities, not generic templates.
Regular reviews.
Ensure permissions remind
aligned permissions.
With current duties and follow least
privileged principles, conditional
access standards, implement contextual
access policies as a default
considering device health, location,
risk signals, and user behavior,
not as a special case exceptions.
Reliable audit trials?
Yes.
Maintaining comprehensive tamper evidence
logs that support both accountability.
Organizational learning.
Audit data becomes a strategic asset
for improving security portion.
Governance and identity disciplines are
quite superpowers and resilient systems.
Alright, but essential foundations
for security as a scale.
Connecting DSEC apps to your business
risk speak the language of impact, right?
Translate technical into business
risks, frame vulnerabilities and
exposures into terms of potential
business impact, revenue loss,
complaints, violations, reputation
damage, not just the technical T codes
aligned with enterprise frameworks.
Right.
Integrate Dev Ssec apps with
existing risk management frameworks.
The board reporting on strategic
planning cycles show progress
through risk metrics report using
risk deduction metrics that resonate
with executive leadership meantime
to remediate the critical exposures.
Attacks, surface face reduction.
Control effectiveness,
making system hard to break.
Actionable resilience.
Resilience is built through
a practice, not tools.
Look behind your code
quarterly SA security reviews.
FMA, enforce access.
Annual API Penetration Test what
new pattern within two weeks
and focus on business impact.
Mag technical issues to business impact.
Remediate critical risk within seven days.
Automate security steps.
Integrate S-C-A-T-S-C-A into
CICD, halt critical flaws.
Policy as a code for 98% complaints,
configuration as a code for
auto fixes within 24 hours.
Connect to company goals,
monthly risky meetings.
Leadership dashboards to show
reduction attack, surface shrinkage,
automating, measuring and collaborating.
Build resilient systems,
aligning with business goals.
Thank you.
Thank you for engagement.
Um, we appreciate your time and attention.
These presentation aim to
provide a valuable insights into
building design system through
a risk driven EC app approach.
Building resilient system by prioritizing
business impact, automating security and
aligned efforts with company goals before
systems that are truly hard to break this
strategy drives continuous implement,
and a proactive security portion.
Uh, you're welcome to
take any questions now.
We are now engaged to hear your
thoughts and questions and look
forward to simulation discussions
and making system hard to break.