Okay.
Hello everyone.
My name is Khali Dewa.
I am director of engineering at
Proofpoint, and I'll be talking about
developer productivity and the common
pitfalls with this presentation.
Now, developers, the most
important asset for any company
delivering software as product.
Making sure that they're set
up for success is the key
to ensuring overall success.
Now, we can't lean into this discussion
without knowing that what is it
that the developers really value?
Studies after studies have revealed
that developers crave meaningful impact.
They like to understand big
picture and how their contributions
help drive long-term outcomes.
Now with that context in mind, let's
lean into the most common pitfalls
of driving their productivity.
Let's start with the ones we stumble
on as managers on this front.
Now, some of the managers like to dig deep
and want to be involved in every detail.
Various studies have proven that
this is a massive anti-pattern
for that productivity.
In addition to that, obsessing
our metrics has been the trend of
our times, but like all trends,
it has some pros and cons to it.
Looking at the metrics such as prs,
commits, deploys, lines of code velocity,
all of these numbers without context
can drive a lot of unintended behavior.
Next, let's look at things
from tooling point of view.
Given how the role of developer
has evolved over the years.
With the DevOps DevSecOps observability
movement, it has left a lot on
an average developer's plate.
Now, all of this means that devs have to
do a lot of context switching throughout
the day while dealing with a lot of tools.
This can be the biggest drain.
On an asset for dev productivity,
depending on how the tooling is
set up and if the culture and
tooling is set up with empathy and
respect for developer workflow.
Next is prioritization
related related pitfalls.
Now setting a processes and automation to
shift left security concerns is critical.
Otherwise, developers are
always playing catch up.
Now, given the range of tooling, types of
vulnerabilities, threats, surface area,
if this is not set up correctly, this can
significantly drag down dev productivity.
In addition to that, this is well known
that tech debt, if not addressed in time,
can snowball and become a major roadblock,
severely impacting the depth productivity.
Huh.
After all, we all know that it
takes a lot longer to make any
changes to those legacy apps.
Okay, next one touches on things
from arcs at a point of view.
Now, with the kind of speed tech
landscape evolves, it is very natural
for learning gaps and organizational
silos to show up now to deal with that.
It is important to proactively set
up processes and forums that can
help drive collaboration and help
devs keep up with evolving tooling.
A more recent example on this
front is AI based code gen tools.
The tools in this space are evolving and
getting better every day, leaving depths
to play catch up almost all the time.
Now, while we are busy breaking silos.
In catching up, it is also critical
to make sure that the teams and
organizations are set up with
the developer wellbeing in mind.
All right, now that we have examined the
pitfalls, let's discuss the four pillars
of sustainable dev productivity activity.
Now, metrics are still the key,
but here we need to make sure that.
We are tying up activity based
metrics with the outcomes.
In addition to that, developer
is a creative endeavor.
Autonomy and trust are at
the heart of development.
Now, none of that will work unless
the goals and the respective
business outcomes that the company
is trying to chase are spelled out.
Clarity.
While we have clarity, trust, and
context-based measures, we still
need to keep up with the trends of
the time with continuous learning.
Okay?
Easier said than done.
What's needed to execute
sustainable productivity?
Now, for practical execution,
we need to make sure that we
have context based picture.
Of the productivity metrics.
Now we can ensure that by
collecting qualitative metrics
with quantitative metrics.
In addition to that, we study the
variety of reasons across organization
that lead to context switching, and
that rather trigger triggers, context
switching and then take action or
diagnose appropriately at the same time.
We set a platform, tooling and
automation in a way that it creates
minimal cognitive load on the devs
trying to deliver customer features.
Now, to build a sustainable flow with
the four pillars at the beginning, we
need clarity of goals, then autonomy
of execution, next, measurable
outcomes to track the progress.
And while all of that's going on,
we need to continuously invest
in the growth of our depths.
All right, we are at the
tail end of the presentation.
So finally, I'd like to conclude by saying
that for any engineering organization to
be successful, empathy and respect for
developers and developer workflow should
be front and center of the culture or
planning and customer value delivery.
Thank you everyone.