Hello everyone.
A warm welcome at CON42
DevSecOps 2024 conference.
APIs are like teenagers.
They need constant supervision
or they will break the rules
in ways you never imagined.
That makes API security
sound more like parenting.
It's challenging, it's hard,
and there are no guarantees.
Welcome again to the talk on
API security in DevSecOps.
A brief background about myself.
I am Anirudh Karandikar, Principal
Software Engineer at Fortune 500 company.
I am a full stack engineer with a niche
skill set in API management and have
around 18 years of industry experience.
As part of my work profile, I deal
with all phases of APIs, right
from inception to governance.
All the views and opinions expressed here
are based solely on my observation and
in general industry research, and as such
have no binding on any of my employers.
Having said that, let's
jump right into the agenda.
So first and foremost, we'll see why
do we even need API security or why
do we even care for API security.
Then we'll take a look off about
what do we mean by security mindset.
Then we'll gloss over some of
the security best practices in
API design, development, testing,
release, operations, and monitoring.
Basically, we'll walk through the
SDLC lifecycle of API management.
So why API security?
Let's take a look at a few of the stats.
Rapid API growth.
By 2025, over 80 percent of all
web traffic is expected to pass
through APIs, making them a
vulnerable target for attackers.
About 91 percent of organizations
have experienced some sort of an
API security incident in last year.
Underscoring the critical need
for proactive security measures.
Cost of security flaws.
It costs astonishingly 30 times more
to fix a security vulnerability in
production than during design phase.
Highlighting the importance
of early security integration.
The underlying messages catch
them early, catch them often.
Human errors in API security.
This is a very important stat.
Nearly 80 percent of API
vulnerabilities are caused either by
misconfigurations or by coding mistakes.
Proactive security majors are
needed in API development lifecycle.
And we will take a look at a few
of these majors later in the talk.
Rising API threats.
APIs are becoming the most
targeted attack vector, exceeding
web applications in frequency.
Web applications held this crown for a
long time, but today APIs are numero uno.
Security testing gaps.
Despite the high risk, only 40 percent
of organizations test their APIs for
vulnerabilities during development.
Many systems remain exposed
to attacks post deployment.
This underscores the need of
having security testing as part
of the overall testing strategy.
So now let's take a look at what
do we mean by security mindset.
But before that, let's see
what DevSecOps advocates.
So traditionally development, security
and operations have been its own silos.
DevSecOps advocates a cultural
shift in which there is a need
to break these silos and draw
synergies and collaboration between
development, security and operations.
Now, once you have this practice
established, What security mindset
or security first principle means
it is it emphasizes embedding
security at every stage of software
development lifecycle, ensuring that
security is a shared responsibility.
So the underlying fundamental tenet
is security cannot be an afterthought.
It needs to be ingrained right from
its inception during planning and
design and then carried through all
the subsequent stages be development,
testing operations and monitoring with
the objective to proactively identify
and mitigate the vulnerabilities
early in development, because as
we saw earlier, the cost of fixing
security in production is very high.
So let's take a look at a few of
the API design best practices.
This is not an exhaustive list, but it
highlights some of the key security areas.
So first and foremost is
authentication and authorization.
Now it's a big topic in itself, but at
a very basic level, All the APIs need
to solve for a need to validate their
API consumers and identify who they
are and whether they have the right
privileges to access this particular
endpoint and the data exposed by the API.
Now, there is an OAuth specification that
explains quite in detail how to do this.
As to how an authentication and
authorization should be implemented.
And then there are identity providers
like Okta or Azure that have already
implemented parts of this specification.
So enterprises today can leverage any of
these IDPs to realize their authentication
and authorization requirements.
Data encryption, in the Veeam, in the
same Veeam of Authn and Authz, the next
important step is to classify your APIs
based on the data that they are exposing.
Now it could be restricted,
confidential, public, or internal API.
Depending on that, the data
encryption needs need to be designed.
Most of the enterprises today
are doing decent when it
comes to encryption at rest.
However, it's equally important to
encrypt the data during transit.
If I were to take a case of rest APIs,
then H three t ps with DLS 1.2 is a given.
But I would advocate even one step
further, and I would say that it
needs to be explicitly encrypted.
If you could use hybrid
encryption and good.
If not, you can use a single
encryption, algorithm like a ES.
What, is, an important nuance is
due to performance reason you may
or may not be able to encrypt the
whole payload, in case of latter.
It is imperative that you at least
encrypt the sensitive attributes, in
the request and response payloads.
Limit sensitive data.
The underlying principle is,
reduce the attack surface.
So design APS to return only
necessary data to users, minimizing
exposure of sensitive information.
Configuration management.
We saw a stat earlier that about
80 percent of the incidents
are caused by human errors.
And configuration management is
one of the key reasons out of it.
So during design, it is,
Very imperative to design.
How are we going to
manage our configurations?
And it's not only related to your APIs,
but configuration related to all the
components that APIs interact with.
Those could be your API
servers, databases, caches.
Another good strategy to think about at
design time is how are you planning to
propagate these configurations across
environments and up to production.
Logging and observability.
They say you can only protect or
secure what you can see and measure.
So that makes logging and observability
a critical component of design.
You absolutely need to have logging
frameworks and observability in place
so as to monitor API usage, detect
anomalies, and enable forensics.
However, it's a double edged sword.
When it comes to logging, you
have to be careful that you
are not logging sensitive data.
If there is absolute need to log
sensitive data, then at the very
least, that data needs to be masked and
then it needs to be stored securely.
so that only the people who need to
have access to that data have access
to that particular piece of data.
Error handling.
This is more for your presentation there.
So use generic error messages to
avoid revealing implementation details
while locking specifics securely.
many attacks have been happened
because the error messages were too
descriptive and hackers could find a
way to bypass those particular errors.
So you have to be very careful,
especially if these error
messages are getting exposed.
Access control.
Clearly define what are your
public APIs and internal APIs.
Have this classification done
at the design time based on
the very purpose of that API.
Again, many attacks have been happened
because The APIs that were supposed to be
internal were exposed on the internet and
by the very nature of it, they had less
security guardrails around it and that was
exploited to gain access to the system.
Rate limiting and throttling.
This is a industry practice and
there are products that will help you
achieve rate limiting and throttling.
So implement rate limiting and
throttling to control request
frequency and prevent abuse.
This is basically to avoid the
risk of DDoS and DDoS attacks.
Input validation and data sanitization.
Yeah, this is again a well
established industry practice.
Validate and sanitize all incoming
data to prevent injection attacks
like SQL injection, XXS, and so on.
Token expiry and refresh policies.
This is a key call out.
Set expiration times for tokens
and establish secure token
refresh mechanism to limit misuse.
Many attacks have happened
due to the long lived tokens.
Tokens usually have access to
parts of the system and as long
as they are not expired, they
have the risk of being exploited.
API versioning.
It is a good practice to have your
APIs versioned and to maintain
a list of which consumers are
accessing which version of APIs.
This is especially important if
you are releasing security fixes
as part of your versioned APIs.
And it is also a good practice to have
your API consumers move to your latest
APIs and then deprecate the outdated APIs.
Again, a lot of attacks have been happened
because the outdated APIs were running
into production and those APIs were used
as a backdoor entry into the system.
Secure API documentation.
Restrict access to API documentation,
especially for private APIs.
Limiting it to authenticated users.
Again, it has been a finding that many
attacks have been happened due to the API
documentation being exposed on the net.
And that same documentation was used
to design well crafted attacks to
bypass the security of those APIs.
Minimum privilege principle.
I think this is a general good
practice, not only for APIs.
Design APIs to grant only the
necessary permissions based on
user roles or scopes or privileges.
And lastly, request and response
payload site restriction.
This is again, one of a good strategy
to prevent resource exertion attacks.
The modulus operandi of these kind
of attacks is, you would have a valid
request with valid request headers,
but they would stub garbage data inside
your request or response payloads
so as to overwhelm your system.
So one of the ways to prevent these
or to put such kind of requests in
check is to have a check on the request
and response size payloads and then
reject all the payloads which are not
adhering to that particular restriction.
So after design is done, let's take
a look at a few of the best security
practices in API development.
First is software version.
Regularly update software
libraries and frameworks to
eliminate known vulnerabilities.
It is a good practice to have a
certain amount of bandwidth reserved.
if you're falling agile, reserve a
certain bandwidth of your effort for
software upgrades or technical upgrades.
This helps you get out of tech debt
and it also limits your attack surface.
In the same vein is dependency management.
Software today's rely on a lot of third
party libraries or third party softwares,
and your code specifically may not have
any vulnerability, but the dependency
that you are using might have that.
A good example would be a
logging library like Log4j.
There are tools in the market
like Renovate that help
automate dependency updates.
ensuring that your
software is always secure.
Secrets management.
Use tools like HashiCorp Vault or
AWS Secret Manager or others that
are designed specifically to store
secrets or sensitive information.
There are also tools available
such as ggShield that detect and
prevent accidental commits of
sensitive information in source code.
This ties back to that stat
earlier which we looked about human
mistakes like accidentally leaking
secrets into your Git repositories.
Tools like ggshield help arrest
these security reviews and scans.
Most enterprises today employ
some form of CICD pipeline.
So it is a good practice to integrate
your static and dynamic analysis
tools into your CICD pipelines.
to continuously access
for vulnerabilities.
Another key call out is your peer reviews.
So peer review should not only
focus on your functional reviews,
but they should also take a look
on the security of that code.
is the code following some of the
best practices and, is the exposure,
limited, Is it classified correctly,
like we saw earlier, whether this
is an internal API or external API
or the data classification thereof.
It would be even nice if there is some
sort of a checklist, which is custom
or tailor made, depending upon the
code you have, infrastructure as code.
This is a good SRE practice, which
also helps drive security in terms
of consistency and having the version
control and security checks in place.
So what do I mean by that?
So let's take an example.
For example, I have to set up an
AWS resource like say S3 bucket,
and I'm doing it manually.
if I have to do this across, let's say,
10 environments and also on production,
there is a chance that while setting
this up manually, I might miss a certain
access control policy or a security
check in one of the environments.
Doing it as infrastructure as code,
allows for those version controls and
checks to be in place every single
time, knowing that each environment,
in each environment, it would be
set up in exactly the same way.
Automated code quality checks.
There are tools like Sonar Cube, to
evaluate your code quality alongside your
security, ensuring code is maintainable
and adheres to best practices,
which indirectly improves security.
you can even shift left, like there
are tools that can integrate with your
IDs, like Sonar Lint or check marks
that provide instant feedback to the
developers while they are coding.
And they highlight the best
security, Practices as well as if
their code has any vulnerabilities.
Moving ahead.
Let's take a look at security
practices in API testing.
The first is static
application security testing.
Analyze source code early in
the development cycle to catch
vulnerabilities before deployment.
Yes, we saw like typically enterprises
today employ some sort of CSAD,
so it's a good place to integrate.
SAST testing, dynamic application
security testing, or DAST.
Test running applications to
identify security weakness
through simulated attacks.
So the well formed simulation attacks
are formed and those are tested against
running applications to discover runtime
security discrepancies or anomalies.
Container scanning.
Most of the APIs today employ
use containers and some sort of
container orchestration tool.
The most popular ones are
Docker and Kubernetes.
However, the base images that are
used for building these containers
might have vulnerabilities.
So it's absolutely imperative
to scan container images for
vulnerabilities to ensure secure
deployments performance testing.
This is a good strategy.
always have both tests set up,
in one of your environments
to evaluate API performance.
Under various conditions adjusting
parameters like rate limiting to prevent
abuse So they not only help uncover the
benchmarks, but they also help Discover
any security anomalies, especially when
under load like what happens if your
timeout Increases what happens if your
backend systems are not responding?
In time, does it accidentally
expose any security vulnerabilities?
So these are very good tests to have.
And lastly, security testing.
Conduct negative tests, negative
access testing and penetration
testing to discover and remediate
security gaps effectively.
A major chunk of your testing strategy
should focus on security testing,
not only your functional testing.
And this is like explicitly conducting
negative testing to break your systems.
Because as we saw, the cost of fixing
this in production is very high.
Moving ahead, let's take a few,
take a look at a few of the security
best practices in API release.
so the first and foremost
is canary deployment.
again, this is a good SRE practice
and also it helps security as well.
So what do we mean by canary deployment?
This is a practice in which we gradually
release updates To a subset of users
allow allowing for monitoring and
rollback if issues arise So imagine if
your latest deployment has some security
issues then as part of canary you will
only release this to a subset of users
thereby reducing the attack surface And
once you identify it's easy to roll back.
So the basic fundamental principle behind
this is limiting your attack surface.
The next is automated sanity testing,
integrate security test cases in
CICD pipelines to ensure every
deployment meets security standards.
the keywords here are automated,
so that it becomes part of
each and every deployment.
You run those negative access
testing and penetration testing,
and you test those against some of
your key flows to make sure that
deployment meets security standards.
Your standards, security, your
standards, security standards.
Moving ahead, let's take a look at some
of the operational security practices.
Now, most of these, are curated for
if your APIs are exposed in public.
But nevertheless, it's good
practice to have these components
as part of your API infrastructure.
So the first one is Web
Application Firewall or WAF.
There are many COTS
products available for WAF.
So use WAFs to shield APIs
from common threats such as SQL
injection and cross site scripting.
Next is bot detection.
There are tools like sequence that
identify and block malicious bot traffic
protecting api resources These are usually
policy based and configuration based
so you can determine how your normal
user traffic looks like you can also
Distinguish between good bots meaning the
bots that you specifically have returned
versus the general api crawlers api
gateway api gateways Can do four
or five important functions.
So let's take a look at that.
This is your first line of defense.
where in you can implement
your access restrictions.
So you need to have your auth and analogy
policies configured in API Gateway.
Next is translation.
they can do your request translation,
wherein they can enhance your request
headers based on, some of the origin,
It is coming from and other different
parameters third is routing They
help isolate your front end from your
different backends like they can do the
necessary routing based on the endpoint
and other Configurations fourthly they
can do rate limiting and throttling.
So this would be the best place
to configure your rate limiting
and throttling policies to
prevent DOS and DDoS attacks.
And fifth is security
compliance, schema compliance.
Sorry.
What do I mean by schema
compliance is earlier we saw
resource exhaustion attacks.
And one way to address that was your
request and response size restriction.
Schema compliance is another
strategy to address that.
And what do I mean by that is
every request is check whether
it is adhering to a schema.
Like you can define how your
API request should look like.
And if those requests are not adhering
to those schemas, then those requests
are rejected right there at the API
gateway layer, protecting your back end
API resources from getting overwhelmed.
SIEM solution.
SIEM stands for security information
and event management systems.
And these are the systems that
are designed to gain real time
insights into security events.
If I were to give some of the examples,
it would be Splunk, IBM QRadar or
Microsoft Sentinel for Office 365
and other Microsoft offerings.
The key fundamental principle of this
is in today's day and age APIs are a
lot of complex, like it's not simple.
If you were to, if you were to look at the
APIs, it looks more like a mesh structure.
and in, in such a complicated mesh
of webs, mesh of APIs, it's not
easy, to troubleshoot if you are only
focusing on one single component.
So what same stands are?
The underlying principle is it can take
a look at different systems and try
to establish correlation between them.
So it can take a look at logs
between different system.
It can take a look at
the log forensic results.
It can take a look at your real time
threads, your user monitoring dashboards,
your reporting dashboards, device
monitoring dashboards, and other stuff.
So the idea is one system in isolation
may or may not able to determine
all the security vulnerabilities.
However, if you take a look at all the
different components and try to correlate
them, you can uncover a lot of security
anomalies, and thereby proactively.
proactively address those anomalies.
Moving on, API monitoring
security practices.
First and foremost, you
need to monitor metrics.
At the very least, you need
to have your red metrics.
So your red stands for
rate, error, duration.
These metrics, help to track API
performance and availability continuously.
Next, security control testing.
Regularly validate security headers
and access controls to ensure
compliance with security policies.
The best way to do this would be
your API gateway, because that's
your first line of defense.
Third sample tracing.
there are tools like Yeager and
AppDynamics that h that imp, that
help track, your API requests.
and these are configuration
based, like you typically have
something called a sampling rate.
Let's say you.
1, 000 requests per hour, then a
sampling rate of 1 percent means
you can sample 10 API requests.
and what do these sampling help is you
can basically trace these APIs, from
point to point communication and see what
payload is being passed across these APIs.
It's like taking an x ray of the
system so that you know how your
system is working under the hood.
And the third is access to
tools and this goes back to
the DevSecOps, cultural shift.
So earlier, as I said, there were
silos like development and operations
and only the operations team used
to have access to monitoring.
but it's, It would be a great shift to
have that monitoring dashboards access
to all the non operations people,
because that way you can facilitate
proactive security management and
uncover security anomalies faster.
so far we have seen why we need API
security, what do we mean by security
mindset and walk through some of the.
best practices across
all the SDLC life cycles.
Now it's time to bring all of
this together and conclude.
So in today's digital landscape,
securing APIs is not just an option.
It's a necessity.
The security first principle in
DevSecOps emphasizes the importance
of integrating security at every stage
of software development life cycle.
By embedding security practices
in design, development, testing,
release, and operations.
Organizations can proactively
identify and mitigate vulnerabilities
before they reach production.
This approach not only enhances the
security posture of applications,
but also fosters a culture of shared
responsibility among development,
security, and operation teams.
The TLDR version of this is security
is a shared continuous responsibility.
And the essence of the hour is to
shift security left so that we build
trust and resilience from ground up.
Thank you all if you
have made it thus far.
I hope you learned a thing or
two from this talk which you can
employ in your day to day work.
Enjoy the rest of the conference.