And thank you for
joining my session today.
I'm Nina Emran, a program
manager at Three Code Solution.
Over the last several years, I've been
leading the enterprise scale migration
initiative, which is modernizing
the data platform, automating
the transformation pipelines, and
enabling the DevOps principle into
a large transformation program.
So in today's talk, I'll walk you through
on how secured, automated, and scalable
migration frameworks are redefining
the modernization for enterprises.
So now we are going to see about the
evolution of enterprise migration.
In the past, migrations were
simply a lift and shift.
These were mostly physical to virtual
transitions which is like quick minimal
transformations and not very strategical.
But today, migration involves complex
multiple platform registration.
We deal with hybrid ecosystems and
compliance constraints, and also the
need for continuous security, which
also requires alignment across team.
So going forward, the migration will
be fully automated and also becoming a
repeatable and a strategical process.
So it has to be driven by a
DevOps framework that delivers
predictable outcomes at scale.
So now we will see what are the
critical challenges that are currently
in place for the manual approaches
and how the automation overcomes it.
So traditional manual approaches have
lot of risk and inefficiencies, like long
timeline coordination, failures, security
gaps and challenges in compliance.
But in automation, the first strategy
itself is to change a game completely.
It accelerate the delivery, reduces human
error, validate the security early in the
cycle, and drives continuous compliance.
So the key message here is the manual
migration methods simply can't keep up
with the complexity of the modern systems.
See what are the migration
scope across the platforms.
So when we talk about enterprise
migration, the scope spams
across multiple platforms.
For example, the legacy system
like mainframe still carry the
mission critical workloads and other
example is the AWS cloud migration.
Which introduce multiple account
governance, containerization,
and modernization.
And the other two example highlighted here
are the Hadoop ecosystem, which requires
replatforming towards cloud native system.
And snowflake drives consolidation
and modern data warehousing.
So this diversity is exactly
why automation and DevOps
principles are essential.
They bring consistency across all
these heterogeneous platform and make.
Use of it in an efficient way.
Now to make a migration
predictable and scalable.
The enterprise depend on four
key automation components.
Number one is the discovery tool.
These reveals hidden dependencies
and architectural gaps.
Number two is the data
transformation engine.
These automate schema, mapping,
cleansing, and conversion.
Number three is the
workflow orchestration.
This manages the sequencing
dependencies and coordination.
At last is the automated testing,
which ensures accuracy and
integrity across all the stages.
This modeler set of capabilities
forms the backbone of any
mature migration framework.
So now we will see few of the
components in a more detailed manner.
Number one is the discovery.
So discovery is there.
Automation creates the biggest
early impact because the modern
discovery tools automatically map your
entire ecosystem, like application
data flows migrations, security
policies and performance baseline.
So this is essential because
unknown dependencies are the
biggest cause of migration setbacks.
So by bringing complete disability
upfront, we eliminate surprises
and also we can plan far more
accurately on the migration.
The next one is the
transformation at scale.
The transformation pipeline, we
can summarize into four stages.
Number one, extract.
We can do parallel extraction with
minimal impact on the source system.
Number two is the transformation like
automated schema, conversion cleansing,
and business rule transformation.
Number three is the validation, like real
time reconciliation to prevent data drift.
And number fourth one is the load,
like optimize loading strategies
with rollback capabilities.
So when we do all these
things within an automated.
Fashion.
These steps allow migrations to run in a
really reliable and repeatable fashion.
And these are all can be done
regardless of the complexity.
So the next component is
the workflow orchestration.
So orchestration is an engine that
keeps the migration moving smoothly.
The workflow automation manages
dependencies, execute task in parallel,
and also handles executions, and provides
a real time visibility into progress.
Most importantly, it reduces
human errors and eliminates manual
hands-off, which are the two biggest
contributors to migration delays.
So the next component is the security
and the compliance integration.
So in modern migration, security
must be built in not blotted on.
So security by design means
embedding, encryption, access
control, and vulnerability scanning
directly into the pipeline.
Number two is the continuous
compliance, which provides real
time monitoring against standards
like SOC two, hipaa and GDPR.
And number three is the validation
gates, which enforces security and
compliance criteria at every stages
before the process can move forward.
So this DevOps driven approach eliminates
last minute surprises and ensures that
the migration is secure end to end.
Now we are done with all
the automation components.
Now we are going to discuss
about the forward looking trends.
Here's where the future of
migration automation is heading.
Number one is the AI driven planning,
where the mission learning will
analyze the historical data to
predict risk and optimize the plants.
Number two is the adaptive orchestration,
which is like the pipeline will auto
adjust based on the performance and
the live system behavior number.
Three is the zero downtime cutovers.
Like more organizations will adopt
techniques like traffic routing
and real-time replication to
eliminate business disruption.
So these innovation will transform
migration from a risky initiative
into a seamless background operation.
Now we are going to see the real
world impacts, so enterprise
that adopt automation experience.
Major advantages number one, is the
faster completion, up to three times
faster than the manual migration.
Number two, lower risk, fewer data
integrity issues, and significantly
reduced security vulnerabilities.
Number three is the higher success rate
automation improves consistencies and
reduce the risk of mid migration failures.
These outcomes are why more
organization are moving towards
an automated migration model.
So overall, the main motor risk.
Building a migration asset capabilities.
The shift we see today is moving
from project-based migrations
to platform-based migration.
So by embedding automation into DevOps
pipeline, we built a reusable framework.
We capture knowledge and create playbooks.
We shorten the time to value for future
migration, and at last we create a
culture of continuous modernization.
So this transform migration from
a costly cyclical event into a
scalable business capabilities.
So overall, the key takeaways
on the automated migrations are,
number one, speed and scale.
Automation, accelerate migration
even on the most complex ecosystem.
Number two, the security first.
The DevOps integration ensures security
and compliance throughout the lifecycle.
Number three is the
strategical capabilities.
Migration becomes a repeatable and a
competitive advantage, so organization
that embrace automation today are the
ones who are going to get ENT for a
continuous modernization tomorrow.
Thank you for your time and I'm
happy to take any questions or
discuss further on any other aspects
on migration automation offline.
Thank you.