Hi, my name is Daniel and I'm glad
to introduce you my talk on how to
migrate from monolith to microservices,
a guide to seamless transitions.
Today we're going to
talk through five parts.
The first one is the
architecture of the overview.
We're going to briefly describe,
the benefits, of microservices
architecture and disadvantages
of the monolith architecture.
We will talk on how to choose
the best architecture for
your system, for your case.
Then we're going to discuss on how
it is related to high loads and how
to connect microservices and high
loads and how to split a large system
into separate smaller microservices.
Then, when we know how it is related
to high loads and, we will going to
design to talk about design for failure.
we're going to discuss what it is
and how it's useful for our purpose.
After that, we will go through main
challenges and we'll also talk about the
solution for this, for these challenges.
We'll describe the problems that can
occur during your transition and what
are the main approaches for them.
to handle them.
And in the end, we will take everything
all together and, see how we can apply
our knowledge on real practical examples.
the first thing is, what
is a software architecture?
you can go through many books and
websites and find many different
definitions for software architecture.
But the one that I'd like to, share
with others and stick with me is,
It is a method for documenting
decisions made for the implementation
of an information system.
decisions are presented as a
connection between several components.
And one of the most important thing
is that architecture is always
considered from different perspectives.
You can, come up with different
frameworks, for example, UML, when
you can, look or describe software
architecture from different perspective.
For example, you can create sequence
diagrams to describe the behavior of
your system, or you can create use case
diagrams to show which, in which way
your system can be used and et cetera.
as a separate type of architecture,
we can, name monolithic architecture.
And of course, there are many other
types, but we're not going to, look
at them today because it's a very,
large topic and, we're not going
to cover In our talk and, okay.
Talking about monolithic architecture.
as many of you already know,
monolithic architecture is when
you have a large piece of software.
And of course, it's simpler
for your development.
It's very easy to deploy on servers.
And usually it has great performance.
And, it's easy to manage
from all perspectives.
But when I was working at the world's
largest social network, my domain,
my main domain was the authentication
and the authorization systems.
And when the, amount and when We
have more than 500 developers.
Then it was almost impossible to,
deploy some fixes, new code, and you
have, I had to wait for more than
several days to have my code deployed.
So of course it presents
different scalability issues.
You cannot like simply copy,
one, large piece of software,
because if one component fails,
then the whole system fails.
So it is tightly related to
coupling between your components.
of course, deployment risks, as I've
mentioned before, we had more than
500 developers and when one of them,
had an error or some bug in, in his
code, then, the whole, we call them
so called trains, with comets, the
whole train was a total failure.
So we had to roll back it.
Okay.
I'm going to a much better approach
microservices architecture.
It divides your large piece
of software into smaller and
loosely coupled microservices
that are deployed independently.
And of course, when you talk about its
benefits, you don't have such problem as,
complex deployment or, tightly
coupled components, you have
other problems that come up when
you use Microsoft's architecture.
For example, the whole
system costs more for you.
It's, it is more complex.
So you have to find, more SRE engineers
for your company, for your team to handle
the infrastructure for your microservices.
The software you use is more complex.
For example, in almost every
microservices architecture that
I've worked with, we had Kubernetes.
And, it's if team is not ready for
to work with such tools, it will be
a bit painful for you to migrate.
So we know the benefits and disadvantages
of both types of architecture.
so let's.
describe the use cases when microservices
architecture might be a better choice.
So when you have to scale your
system, when your system is becoming
more complex and always evolving,
as an example, a social network, it
is all, it always receives updates.
when you have to deploy and develop,
some applications independently,
microservices is a great choice.
Also, it is tightly connected
with the team structure and
ownership in monolith applications.
It is usually hard to, separate one
component from another and to divide it.
for different teams to use the other
use cases when you have a, when you
have technology diversity, for example,
you have one microservices written
in Golang and the other in Java.
So microservices.
architecture handles this case great.
the other thing is the full
tolerance and isolation.
when you want one part of the
system to fail and not have
other part of the system to fail.
The other use cases when you have your
application distributed across different
countries or different parts of the world.
the other use case is integration
with third party services.
And when you have to speed up
the development process or the
simplest case, when you just want
to modernize your legacy system.
we also have to mention.
Use cases when microservices will not
suit well for example when your rps is
are Not too big for example down two
to four rps or When your application is
very small Or team expertise is limited
Or maybe you have limited resources this
is a use case when you don't want to
use microservices and better stick to
your old technologies and architecture.
Uh, as I mentioned in the beginning,
we'll briefly discuss on how
microservices are related to high loads.
I would say that high load is almost
impossible when you are creating, It's
using monolithic architecture, but I
would not be 100 percent sincere with
you because the world's largest social
networks, such as Facebook or pk.
com, they are, they, historically were
built using monolithic architecture
and developers had to invent
different solutions to handle this.
For example, to create transpilers
to translate PHP code into C code or
developers had to create more, more
performant perform the software, like
databases, with much better performance.
Because high load is where the
bottleneck is the CPU, and the main
challenges are the volume of data,
the quality of data, the high rate of
change, and high level of complexity.
There is no clear definition of high load.
We can only name some signs of it.
For example, the system can no
longer handle the current load or
common approaches are insufficient or
there's an urgent need to scale the
infrastructure or a single server is
not enough to serve your customers.
Thank you.
And also when hardware can't cope
with increased loads and existing
tools are, cannot solve your problems.
And when you are in such situation,
when you have a very high RPSs, the
main questions that you should consider
are reliability, two, scalability,
and three, ease of maintenance.
Thank you.
I want you, from the all, points that I
will mention today, these three are the
key ones, so I want you to remember them.
Designed for failure.
Some of you may know such
person as Edward Murphy.
And he said that anything that
can go wrong will go wrong.
And this is the principle that you should
keep in mind when developing microservice
architecture and high load systems.
Let's see a small example of it.
For example, you have an order service
which stores its orders in a database.
and sends an email when it
receives a creation request.
So everything is pretty simple, right?
Then let's say that your email provider
unexpectedly fails, but you still have to
deliver your messages to the customers.
So the great choice for you would be to
add a fallback email service that you're
going to use in case your main one fails.
In the case of a service failure,
external or internal to the system,
it must be properly handled.
And another good option for handling
degradation is to use a cache
service for your data storage.
For example, your database cannot
handle the load and, Sorry.
But you still have to serve your
customers with, many pages that
they can watch your, their orders.
And, of course, the, they're
going to face some problems when
they want to create a new order.
But, for example, just to watch them or
just to, list them, the cache is enough.
The other thing is, that's
slightly patches microservices
patterns is transactional outbox.
when you have some messages in your
system, when you have messages queue,
you want to implement delivery,
grant some guaranteed deliveries.
And for that purpose, the
transactional box pattern is the best.
And if you're working with very important
data, maybe with finances or personal
infos, personal data, this is the kind of
pattern that must be used, otherwise you
will face some unpleasant consequences.
And we are moving to challenges
that you are going to face when
you are migrating your system
from monolith to microservices.
And the first one is code complexity.
As you see on the screenshot, This
is a real screenshot that I was
taking, when I was working on the
code base of the social network.
And I've just clicked the button
to find the usages of ID function.
And as you can see, we have more than
30, 000 results, which is mind blowing.
And apart from it, the
code is tightly coupled.
It's usually hard to understand and you
spend days to understand how one component
work And of course The development
is slow and you're you cannot deploy
your code very fast when you have Many
developers working on the same parts Of
course, it's limited in its flexibility.
It has high risks of bugs.
It's almost impossible to cover with
tests, unit tests or integration tests,
because you have the problem when you
do not have interfaces and basically
your test environment cannot use this.
production databases, so you cannot
write your test code in such cases.
You have, firstly, you have to
disconnect the data that is used
in production from the code.
The other thing that I think is the most
important, it is a high entry barrier.
It is very hard to find new
developers, especially if you use
some old technologies like PHP and
maybe Perl or other stuff like this.
But what's more importantly is
that even if you find one, it will
take more than a year, two years
for them to adapt to the code, but
code base to understand processes.
And then developer works more
than two years on such project.
it is very hard to, not lose him
because, usually developer gets tired
working on such, bad quality code.
So that introduces recruitment challenges.
for listening.
The second thing is data
management and decoupling.
we've mentioned this thing before,
so we'll go through solutions.
first one is database per service
pattern, when you use one, exactly
one database for your microservice.
And, You use event sourcing or change data
capture to, let the other microservices
know that some data has changed.
You may also use data replication and
shared databases as temporary solutions.
For example, you have module one,
module two, and et cetera that, that
are working with the users table.
And the first module was
working with username field.
The second module is working
with a password field.
so how do we handle such situations?
We can create, let's say, two
microservices and divide our
data into two separate tables.
The first one is for users and
the second one is for addresses.
And if our personal data service
needs some user info, any user
info, then it can just, Make a
get request to the ALF service
The next thing is the multi layered
caches It is a on the slide.
You can see a real example of how
the caching Could be implemented.
I Would not say that it is a great
approach, but it's how it is in big
systems that Handle a lot of requests.
You have your app, usually monolithic
app, and you have your local caches,
maybe memory caches, and then you have
a chain of caches, multi layered caches,
and one question could come to your
mind, You can pause and try to answer
it by yourself, but the answer is, when
you want to, simplify such systems, you
have to, go through all the complexity
of the code that works with this
chain, and usually it's mind blowing.
microservices rely on communication
between services, and it
introduces latency, failure
points, and complex dependencies.
For such cases, you better use
message queues, service discovery
tools, and circuit breakers,
to not allow cascade failures.
And usually for this, you have different
libraries in your programming languages.
we're going to talk about security.
Microservices, of course,
they increase the numbers.
of communication endpoints exposing,
the system to vulner vulnerabilities.
And, to handle this, you can use API
gateways to centralize authentication,
authorization, and request validation.
for example, you can use Istio Gateway if
you're using Kubernetes, or you can use.
Many proxies like NGINX
or Envoy or Help Proxy.
The other thing that you can use is of two
protocol and token based authentication
like JVTs for secure access control.
And if you have a separate team or
specialist, which is, Which responsi
Which responsibilities are connected with
information security, you can implement
penetration testing, and all that.
Of course, it is very hard to
deploy decentralized systems.
Distributed systems, sorry.
So usually, you want to
have a separate server.
team member, maybe DevOps engineer
that will handle all these tasks.
and usually in his responsibilities,
you can expect counterization and
orchestration tools, CI CD pipelines
in GitLab or GitHub actions.
And of course, GitOps for infrastructure
as a code, maybe, such things as, Argo
CD and other stuff, maybe Ansible.
To monitor a monolithic system,
you can use maybe the things like,
Sentry or, things like that, but
to monitor many small applications.
You'll have to use more complex
approaches like logging, tools like ALK
stack, distributing tracing solutions.
You can also implement distribution
tracing by yourself, but if you
are limited in your resources
or doesn't want to, you can use
um, ready solutions like Zipkin.
Also, it's a great choice to
use service meshes like Istio.
It's great for Kubernetes.
And it also helps to, for, to increase
the observability of your system.
I've mentioned before that microservices
introduce some, HR problems.
So teams.
and organizational
resistance and skill gaps.
teams may resist, change due to lack
of familiarity with microservices
or fear of increased workload.
And you probably will have to organize
training programs and workshops and maybe
transition your responsibilities between
team members and groups of developers.
And to demonstrate that microservices
approach can work with your system,
you can create, let's go, an MVP for
your system, for your microservice,
and then the team will understand
the benefits, and you'll more likely
continue to migrate to microservices
your other components of your system.
of course, working with
legacy monoliths is hard.
and the parts that are going to help
you are strangler, facets, adapters,
bridges, and, different others.
Also, you'll have to maintain
some compatibility layers.
The main concern that I have faced with
when I was working with the, when I was
migrating authentication part of the
social network to microservices is that
authentication is under a very high
load, hundreds of thousands of RPSs.
And, It was unacceptable to, increase
latency even by one or two microseconds.
So I had to think about how to, increase
performance of my microservices or of
my, networking of my infrastructure.
for example, I've used, for
interconnection, I've used
gRPC protocol made by Google.
we've also used Kubernetes to
scale horizontally our system.
And to measure the impact of the
migration, we've used performance testing.
It was very hard in the beginning to
manage dependencies, but, there are
great solutions for such problems,
such as event driven architectures.
or API versioning with service contracts,
a great tool Swagger and OpenAI are
a great choice for you to document
your APIs and share it between teams.
So we've covered almost every significant
problem, and we've mentioned the
solutions that can solve these problems.
So let's go to the practical example,
and we will try to create a token
management service by moving, code parts
from one monolithic data, code base.
And the system itself just
generates and checks APIX tokens.
So we have our user, which provides
session token like any string.
And we have our legacy monolith system.
We have our web server, where
our users send requests to.
And our web server just sends.
user's token to parse session
function, which returns ID, IP and
expires date, taken from database.
Everything is simple.
We want to migrate gradually.
So the first thing we do is we take, we
create new microservices, let's call it.
token microservice and we just copy our
parse function and we send two requests
simultaneously one to the monolith
version of this function and the other two
microservice version of this function both
of them are temporarily using sessions
database so they're sharing it and if
we compare our ID and IP and other data.
And if it's equal, then we can gradually
decrease the traffic from the monolithic
function to microservice function.
And we'll have something like this,
where parse function is transferred
to token microservice But what if some
other module uses Session's database?
We have to migrate it as well.
How do we do it?
And the problem could be even
worse if we have different caches
between database and monolith.
here's A solution for this problem,
we add a consumer to the monolith
and we add a producer to the
microservice and use patterns that we
have mentioned earlier, CDC pattern.
So when our sessions database
changes, then we capture changes and
we're producing message patterns.
into the message queue.
the consumer will take the message
from the message queue and update
its local state in some other DB.
And our other module will use
data for not from sessions
database, but from other database.
So we have decoupled two
modules, one from another.
And to make everything more, more
concise, to keep it simpler, to make
everything beautiful, we can transfer
the logic from monolith to the second
microservice and let everything
other, everything else untouched.
That was it for today.
In the end, I want to recommendate, give
you some recommendations on books that you
can read and take useful information from.
So the first one is Designing Data
Intensive Applications by Martin Klapman.
And the second one is the
website called microsoft.
io These two will probably be enough to
cover the main aspects of microservices.
But if you want to go deeper,
you can use distributed systems.
It's free and could be found
on the URL that I provided.
And if you are familiar
with Go, you can go there.
take a look at the book by Nick Jackson.
So thank you for your attention and
I'm looking forward for your feedback.
You can send me questions if you have,
in telegram or you can write me an email.
So thank you once again
and have a nice day.
Goodbye.