Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining today.
We are going to explore something
absolutely foundational to the rapid
expansion of ai, the network fabric.
Before we dive in, let me
quickly introduce myself.
My name is Nam Khan and I'm a solutions
engineer at Cisco on the data center
and the AI infrastructure team.
My job is to make sure the
solutions we build align with our
customer's real business needs.
I've been in the industry for over
23 years working with companies like
Motorola, quest Communications and Cisco.
I hold a dual CCIE certification and
have delivered multiple sessions at
Cisco Life across the US and Europe.
Now, why are we here today?
Because we are living through
one of the biggest infrastructure
shifts in the history of computing.
Every organization is racing
to build or consume AI models.
And the interesting part is
this, the bottleneck in AI isn't
just the GPU speed anymore.
It's how fast those GPUs
can talk to each of them.
You can buy the fastest GPU in the
world, but if they're connected through
a slow or congested network, it's like
driving a Ferrari in a traffic jam.
All that horsepower completely wasted.
So in the session we'll look at
how ethernet, the same technology
that powers the internet.
Has evolved into high performance
fabric for scalable secure
AI training and inference.
Here's a roadmap for our session.
We'll start with the silicon building
blocks, the C-P-U-G-P-U and DPU.
Then we'll look at the different
types of AI clusters and the specific
network requirements for each.
The core of a discussion will
be on network architecture.
Focusing on RDMA, Rocky V two
and Congestion Management.
Finally, we look at the
future with the Ultra Ethernet
Consortium and discuss security.
Let's start by breaking down on what
actually sits in a modern AI server.
It typically contains three
MA major processing units.
The CPU or the Center Processing
Unit, which is the brain of the AI
system, it manages the operating
system, orchestrates data loading
and handles all journal purpose task.
Think of it as a conductor of an
orchestra, making sure everything
stays in sync in harmony.
Next is the GPU or the graphics
processing unit, which can be turned
as the muscle of the AI system.
This is where the heavy lifting happens.
GPUs Excel at massive
parallelism, performing thousands
of metrics multiplication.
One in AI clusters.
GPUs are the most expensive
resources, and everything about the
network is designed for one purpose.
Keep the GPUs busy.
If a GPU is waiting for data,
you're literally burning money.
Finally, the DPU or the data processing
unit is the traffic controller of the
AI system as network scales to 400
gig and 800 gig processing packets.
Eats up CPU cycles, what we call the
infrastructure tax, the DPU offloads
set, tax handling, encryption,
packet inspection and routing.
So the GPU and GPU stay
focused on their workload.
Thinking of DPU as a personal assistant,
making sure the main performance can shine
these three components together form the
backbone of modern AI infrastructure.
So what is an AI cluster?
Isn't it just a rack of servers?
Essentially, it is an interconnected
network of high performance GPUs,
acting as a single supercomputer.
The network here is not just the plumbing.
It is part of the compute fabric.
If the network slows down
the entire cluster stalls.
This brings us two
collective communication.
In standard networking, aox to B. In ai,
a whole group of GPUs need to exchange
data simultaneously to function as a unit.
During training, every
GPU calculates a gradient.
And they must all share that
data to update the model.
We use topology aware algorithms
like rings or trees to ensure
this happens instantly.
If this synchronization lags
training, time explodes.
Now let's distribute between the workload.
Training is where the model learns.
It uses massive data sets.
To teach the model patterns.
It's like teaching a robot to read, walk,
dance, whatever the robot was built for.
Inference is the application phase.
This is when you use the train model
to make predictions or generate text.
It's like asking that robot a
question and getting an answer.
Let's look at the specific
requirement for each of these
clusters as shown in the table.
The bandwidth.
Training requires a high no to node
bandwidth because of that gradient
synchronization, which we talked
about in inference, it's the bandwidth
requirement is relatively lower.
The key metric for the training and
the inferences for the training,
the key metric is how much time
it takes to train the model.
For inference, it is about
latency and higher liability.
So basically, if you think
that you're building a robot.
How much time it takes to build a robot
and how much time it takes to train
the robot so that it can perform the
task, which is, which it's intended for.
Inferencing is just like
executing the robot.
So basically the the end user commands
the robot to walk, dance, or whatever
the purpose it is built for to
execute the purpose it is built for.
Training happens offline, like
when the robot is being built.
It is trained.
It is not available for the user.
It's still being manufactured
by the company or the system,
which is developing it.
Inference is online, right?
The robot is available for
service whenever it's required.
From an infrastructure requirement,
training clusters are massive.
They're like centralized networks because
they require a lot of bandwidth and the
more resources they have, the lesser time
it takes to train a particular model,
influencing clusters, often small and
distributed, something similar to what
we have been using in our data centers,
the regular networks, what we have
been using in the data centers, those
could be used as intrinsic clusters.
So with those differences in mind, let's
talk about what it takes to build a
network that supports these workloads,
specifically a lossless network fabric.
This is where technologies like RDMA,
condition control and specialized
architectures come into play To get the
performance we need for training, we
use RDMA or remote direct memory access.
Standard networking is too slow
because data has to pass through.
The C-P-U-R-D-M-A allows the NIC to
transfer data directly into G p's
memory by passing the CPU entirely.
This gives us the low latency
required for a loss risk fabric.
I often joke that if humans had
RDMA, you could just sit in the room
and by the end of the session, all
my AI networking knowledge would be
copied into your brain instantly.
But for RDMA to work, the network
must act losslessly, meaning no packet
drops even during spikes or congestion.
This requires careful planning around
buffers, queues, and traffic engineering.
Now, we may say we are
using RDMA as a technology.
How about the physical network for ai?
Here is a high level topology.
We typically split the network
into two, which is the front end
network and the backend network.
The front end network is your standard
ethernet network, which you use for your
storage, out of management, user access.
Just the regular data center
which you have been using.
The bank end network is a
place where the magic happens.
This is a dedicated high
speed GPU to GPU fabric.
So any model you're training here,
any robots you're training here, it
has to happen in the backend network.
It is purpose built and it
carries only compute traffic.
The GPU gradients, which you talked about,
the activation, the model TERs, all of
that happens in the backend network.
And of course, since the backend network
uses RDMA because it involves G pt, GP
communication, so it has to be lossless.
Because if any packet drops the
entire collective operation on
the collective communication.
Communication we talked about between
the GPUs will stall or hash to restart.
For the backend network, which runs RDMA,
we have two choices in terms of technology
or in terms of system infrastructure.
Either we could use Infinity Band or we
could use Ethernet Infinity Band have has
been used in high performance computing.
It's a traditional, it's a standard,
but infinity band is propriety.
It is fast, it has better latency
as compared to ethernet, but it is
propriety and all its component, all its
element, the infrastructure to build up.
And InfiniBand, a cluster.
It's expensive.
RDMA is natively supported
on Infiniti Bank.
Like it does not require any tweaks or
adjustments to run RDMA or Infiniti Bank.
You can just directly run
RDMA or Infiniti Band as is.
However, when you talk about ethernet, so
ethernet as we know is our best effort.
Technology, basically.
It's not lossless.
RDME requires lost us.
What we have been talking about and what
we have done to run RDMA or ethernet
is we have developed some industry
standard a particular protocol, which
we're going to talk about in the upcoming
slide, and then we also have to kind
of configure or make the ethernet with
certain condition mechanism to make it.
At on par within InfiniBand without
compromising on its features.
So ethernet as such,
we know is a standard.
Being used widely, very popular.
Most of the folks out there know how to
operate ether, ethernet, the switches, the
infra, the optics, all the infrastructures
are quite standard, and we can run the
entire backend network or e ethernet.
We don't have to change anything except.
For the part where we have to tweak
the RDMA to how to use ethernet.
So we have to customize ethernet for
RDMA and nothing is non-standard.
Everything is quite a standard procedure.
So the big question here, what it takes
to get ethernet on par with Infin Bank.
So the answer is rocky, which is
nothing but RDMA or converge ethernet.
What we do here is we encapsulate
RDMA inside an ethernet frame.
We started with Rocky version one, which
was only limited to layer two domains
because it did not have a UDP IP header.
Then that was slowly upgraded to
Rocky version two, which where
we added the UDP IP headers.
RDMA would be able to route
across layer three networks.
So this is what allows ethernet
to scale AI clusters across racks,
row and entire data center halls.
So let's talk about
more about Rocky V two.
With RO UE two GPU still use RDMA, but
now the RDMA packets ride over ethernet.
The NIC can place data directly into
the GPU memory without involving
the CPU kernel, which cuts latency
from microseconds to nanoseconds.
This is a magic that makes ethernet a
serious contender for AI networking.
Of course, using ethernet
introduces one challenge.
RDA assumes a loss alert
network, which you talked about.
And ethernet is best referred if the
buffer fills up ethernet drop packets.
But RDA cannot tolerate drops.
So introduce two mechanisms here,
starting with the ECN, which is the
explicit condition notification.
ECN does not drop packet insert.
It marks them.
When the switch starts to build
queue pressure, the endpoints then
slow down based on those marks.
This keeps the network stable
and predictable exactly
what AI workloads need.
The second mechanism is PFC
or priority flow control, PFC,
pauses traffic, its specific
priorities when congestion occurs.
This gives us.
Per prietary lossless behavior, even
when multiple traffic types share the
same links, proper tuning of PFC, the
headroom, the pause thresholds, and
the queue management is critical to
deploying Rocky QV two successfully.
Looking ahead, the UAC or the Ultra
Ethernet Consortium Initiative
is an industry group optimizing
ethernet specifically for ai.
They're developing standards for better
congestion control, lower latency, and
brought interoperability to replace
proprietary solutions completely.
So what we are seeing here is UAC
because we know that ethernet in
its own form cannot be used for.
The backend network, what we discussed
about how we use Rocky V two and how
we are using congestion mechanism.
So the goal of the alter Ethernet
consortium team is to ensure that
we develop a standard ethernet or a
modern ethernet, what we call it, or
what they call it as ultra ethernet.
Which will work flawlessly for
building AI backend networks.
Performance is critical,
but so is security.
AI introduces new attack surfaces that
traditions, tools don't always cover.
Some key risk included here,
like I've put it on the slide, is
data poisoning, model extraction,
privacy violations, insider threats.
As AI systems handle more sensitive
and proprietary data, securing
the pipeline just becomes an
important as a accelerating it.
To address these race, we rely
on we many core strategies, which
is like encryption of data and
transit and rest secure designs.
Continuous monitoring.
We monitor the AI network
continuously to di discover any
anomalies in traffic flows or any
anomalies in behaviors of the users.
And then access control,
which is all very important in
aspects of securing our network.
So these guardrails ensure AI
workloads remain secure even
as they scale dramatically.
Talking about dpu, DPU play a huge role
in they enforce these security policies
like encryption and isolation right at
the server edge, operating the work.
So the GPU can focus a
hundred percent on training.
They also help with model partnering
by managing data moment efficiently.
Let's bring everything together.
What we discussed so far
is scalability aspect.
How we are making AI
networks more scalable.
So AI is moving from a single server
to massive clusters like we talked
about, how we require massive amounts
of GPU to cater to the AI demand.
What we have.
So the network must also scale with it.
We discussed about performance, how
ethernet with the Rocky V two can
provide the high throughput, low
latency fabric AI workloads required.
Also, we talked about the UEC or the
Ultra Ethernet consortium initiatives
where they're trying to develop
ultra ethernet, which would work
flawlessly with the AI backend network.
And if you get the network architecture
right, you can build a system that's far
secure and ready for the future of ai.
Thank you for your time.
I hope this was informative, and
I wish you a great confidence.