Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining me
today at DevSecOps 2025.
It's an honor to present my
talk on the intersection of
pedagogy and technology today.
So we are going to cover the careers
in educational AI and digitalization.
I'm Santosh Kumar Pulijala, a senior
NET developer at HCL Global Systems.
Today, I'm very excited to share how
AI And digital tools are reshaping
education and career opportunities
that arise from this transformation.
So let's look into what we are going
to dive deep into this topic today.
We are going to look into
the introduction, which will
cover the exploring of digital
revolution in education.
then we are going to look into
the landscape, which covers the
understanding how AI and digital
tools are transforming education.
Then we are going to look
into key competencies.
which covers skills needed
for careers in edtech.
Career pathways will cover opportunities
that are available in educational
technology and challenges, the key
challenges and how we can address
those barriers to success in edtech.
future directions, which will cover the
trends and innovations shaping the future.
And we'll look into the
professional development.
Which helps us in building the skills
and network in edtech impact and
opportunities will cover How edtech
transforms education globally call to
action will have the steps to join and
contribute to this digital revolution
And we are going to conclude the topic
in how this digitalization helps in
shaping the future of education together.
Now, let's look into the
introduction of our today's topic.
As we dive Into this session, let's take
a moment to reflect on the unprecedented
changes happening in education.
The digital revolution is
shaping classrooms, schools,
and learning systems worldwide.
AI driven adaptive platforms, virtual
classrooms, and data analytics
tools are no longer futuristic.
They are here.
They are revolutionizing how students
learn, How teachers teach and how
administrators manage education systems.
This is not just about technology.
It's about creating more
personalized, efficient, and data
driven approaches in education.
But it's also about tackling challenges,
ensuring equity for undeserved students,
preparing teachers for these changes,
and making these innovations sustainable.
Why does this matter?
Because education is the
foundation of progress.
By embracing these tools, we are not
just creating smarter classes, but
building a smarter society, empowering
students with tools for lifelong success.
And the best part?
Each of you here has a role to
play in this transformation.
Let's explore how.
So the landscape.
Education today stands at the
crossroads of tradition and innovation
and technology is leading the way.
Let's talk about some of the digital
tools driving this transformation.
First, we have e learning platforms
like Moodle, Canvas, and Blackboard,
which enables flexible and accessible
online learning environments.
Then there are student information
systems, tools like PowerSchool
and Infinite Campus that simplify
attendance, grading, and data tracking.
these are like the collaboration
management systems, like Google Classroom,
And Microsoft teams have become staples
in fostering teamwork and resource
sharing among educators and students.
But the game changer is AI.
We all know that AI is currently
transforming the digitalization
and it is also entering the
digitalization of education as well.
Adaptive learning systems now personalize
content for each student's unique needs.
Automated grading tools are reducing
administrative burdens on teachers,
giving them more time to focus on
what they do best, which is teaching.
Yet, as promising as these technologies
are, their effectiveness depends on how
well they are designed, implemented, and
integrated into our educational systems.
This is where your expertise in
DevSecOps, AI, and innovation
can make a profound impact.
Let's look into the key competencies.
To excel the educational technology
space, professionals need a unique
blend of technical expertise
and pedagogical understanding.
On the technical side, skills in
programming languages like Python,
Java, NET, and JavaScript are crucial
for building sophisticated tools.
Data science and machine learning
open doors to analyzing educational
trends, enabling predictive insights.
Cloud computing platforms like AWS and
Google Cloud are essential for scalable
solutions and AI ML techniques like
natural language processing, which is NLP
and neural networks, power personalized
and adaptive learning systems.
But let's not forget the pedagogical side.
That's the main thing, right?
We are used to the pedagogical
side of the education.
So understanding learning theories
like constructivism, or behaviorism is
vital to ensure these tools actually
enhance the learning experience.
Curriculum design and assessment
techniques tailored for digital platforms
are key to creating effective systems.
This combination of technical know
how and pedagogical expertise will
set you apart as you contribute to the
future of educational technologies.
Now, let's look into the career pathways.
The intersection of education
and technology offers a wide
range of career opportunities.
Let's explore these three key roles.
Educational technologist.
These professional bridge the gap
between technology and pedagogy.
They design digital learning materials,
train educators and work directly
with schools to integrate technology.
Thank you.
The salary for this role ranges from
50, 000 to over 100, 000 annually.
AI and ML engineer.
AI and machine learning engineers develop
Algorithms for adaptive learning tools,
chatbots, and automated grading systems.
They play a vital role in creating
intelligent, scalable solutions.
This role typically offers
salaries between 80, 000 and
150, 000 or even more than that.
So next will be the data analysts.
Data analysts turn raw educational
data into actionable insights.
They design dashboards that track
trends like student performance
or teacher effectiveness.
The salary range for this role
is like sixty thousand dollars
to like more than hundred and
twenty thousand dollars easily.
The demand for these roles is only
growing as schools and educational
organizations recognize the value
of technology driven solutions.
Now let's look into the challenges.
Like any transformation, the integration
of AI and digital tools in education
comes with its own set of challenges.
Equity issues.
Equity issues are among the most pressing.
Many students around the
globe lack reliable access
to devices and the internet.
Digital literacy is another barrier
with varying levels of comfort and
expertise among different populations.
Next will be the Teacher training.
Teacher training is equally critical.
Technology is only as
effective as people using it.
Teachers must be empowered with skills
and resources to seamlessly integrate
these tools into their classrooms.
Lastly, there's the
question of sustainability.
Ensuring that these Initiatives
remain impactful over time and can
be scaled to meet the diverse needs
of the students across regions.
Addressing these challenges requires
collaboration across disciplines,
developers, educators, and policymakers
working together to create equitable,
scalable, and long lasting solutions.
Now let's look into the future directions.
The future of educational
technology holds immense potential
to revolutionize learning.
AI is leading the charge in creating
high personalized education.
Adaptive learning tools powered by machine
learning can adjust content delivery in
real time to suit individual students
needs, abilities, and learning speeds.
This approach enhances engagement
and retention making learning
more effective and tailored.
One major trend is the development
of equitable technologies.
For instance, offline capable solutions
and low cost devices are being designed
to bring quality education to underserved
communities, bridging the digital divide.
This focus on inclusion ensures
that technological advances
benefit all, regardless of
geography or socioeconomic status.
Frameworks like TPAC, Technological
Pedagogical Content Knowledge, are gaining
traction to help educators seamlessly
integrate technology into their teaching.
These frameworks address the
synergy between technology, pedagogy
and subject matter, empowering
teachers to innovate effectively.
Long term studies are another
critical aspect of the future.
These studies aim to qualify how
technology Impacts learning outcomes
over time, providing insights
into what works and what doesn't.
Such data driven evaluations
will help refine tools and
strategies for maximum impact.
The emphasis moving forward is
on context sensitive solutions.
No two regions or schools are the
same, and innovations must cater to
local needs, cultures, and resources.
Expanding digital literacy programs and
fostering international collaborations
will also play a pivotal role in
scaling these technologies and
ensuring their global relevance.
The future of education is undoubtedly
exciting, but it's also a call for
action for all of us to innovate
responsibly and inclusively.
Now let's look into the
professional development.
In the rapidly evolving world of
educational technology, staying
relevant requires a commitment to
continuous learning and skill building.
Professional development is
not just a career enhancer.
It's an essential pathway to
contributing meaningfully in this field.
The first step is embracing
continuous learning.
Online platforms like Coursera,
edX, and Udemy offers a wealth of
courses in areas like AI machine
learning and digital pedagogy.
Specialized certifications such as
Google Certified Educator and ISTE
certification add credibility to your
skills and help you stay competitive.
These certifications are not only valuable
credentials but also gateways to gain
deeper insights into the practical
application of technology and education.
Equally important is building
a strong professional network.
Joining associations like ISTE, which
is International Society for Technology
and Education, or participating in
edtech meetups that happens around
fosters connections like minded people.
Conferences and forums provide platforms
to share ideas, discuss challenges,
and learn from leaders in the field.
Engaging in collaborative projects with
other professionals can also broaden
your perspective and expose you to
diverse approaches to solving problems.
Collaborative learning opportunities,
which is also, hackathons are
invaluable for hands on experience.
They provide a chance to tackle real
world challenges, brainstorm innovative
solutions, and work across disciplines.
Cross institutional research institute
initiatives are another excellent
way to contribute to impactful
projects while honoring Your skills.
Ultimately, professional development
is about blending technical knowledge,
collaboration, and creativity
to lead the way in transforming
education on these technologies.
Staying proactive ensures your
career thrives in this dynamic field.
Now let's look into the
impact and opportunities.
The impact of educational AI and
digitalization is transformative,
creative opportunities that ripple
across all stakeholders in education,
students, educators, administrators,
and even global communities.
For students, the introduction of AI
driven tools offers personalized learning
experiences, adaptive system tailored
lessons, activities, and assessments to
individual learning styles and places,
ensuring that no student is left behind.
Furthermore, inclusivity is amplified
as digital tools provide solutions for
learners with special needs, offering
accessibility features like speech
to text or audio to visual aids.
Educators too benefit
from this revolution.
Automation tools such as grading
system and administrative software
significantly reduce routine tasks,
freeing up valuable time for teachers
to focus on engaging with students and
refining their instructional strategies.
These tools empower teachers to
become facilitators of knowledge
rather than just content deliveries.
For administrators, the data
driven insights provided by
educational technology revolutionize
decision making processes.
Dashboards and analytics enable
them to track trends, measure
outcomes, and make informed policy
decisions that improve institutional
efficiency and student success rates.
On a global scale, the opportunities
are even more profound.
Digital tools can bridge
educational disparities by bringing
quality learning resources to
remote and underserved regions.
With equitable tech solutions, we can
ensure that every child, regardless
of background, has access to the
education they really deserve.
The innovations in this space are
not just technical achievements.
They are enablers of societal progress.
By fostering collaboration,
lifelong learning, and inclusivity,
careers in educational technology
have the power to shape a better,
more equitable future for all.
Now let's look into the call for action.
As we wrap up, I urge you to
take part in this transformation.
I really urge you to take
part of this transformation.
Transformation.
The edtech revolution needs your skills,
your vision, and your commitment.
Pursue continuous learning to
stay ahead of emerging trends.
Collaborate to create inclusive and
effective learning environments.
And most importantly, Let's
work together to redefine
education for future generations.
now let me conclude the topic.
As we reach the conclusion of this
session, let's take a moment to reflect on
the incredible journey we have explored.
The integration of AI and digital
tools in education is not just a trend.
It's a paradigm shift.
It's transforming how we
teach, how we learn, and how
we manage education systems.
From personalized learning experiences
for students to efficient data driven
decision making for administrators.
These innovations are reshaping
the very fabric of education.
But with great power comes
very great responsibility.
As professionals in this space, we
must ensure these technologies are
Inclusive, equitable, and sustainable,
but with great power comes
great responsibility.
This field is filled with opportunities to
innovate, inspire, and make a meaningful
impact, whether you are designing
adaptive algorithms, training educators,
or analyzing data to improve outcomes.
Your contributions have the
potential to shape the future of
education for generations to come.
Together, let's build a future
where education is accessible,
adaptive, and impactful.
A future where every learner has the
tools and opportunities to thrive.
So I really want to thank you for
your time and attention today.
If you have any questions or concerns,
you LinkedIn at santoshkumarspacepulijala.
Let's innovate, inspire, and
transform education together.