Hello everyone.
I'm Rag Ola, senior Cloud architect
at Miracle Software Systems.
While my core work has been in pharmacy,
retail, and food industries today I'm
excited to share how those relationship
play breakthrough in cloud banking through
ours cloud banking algorithm or ECBA.
Let's begin with the challenge
that inspired ECBA and why secure
scalable transactions are more.
Critical the digital banking challenge.
Growing demands, digital banking
has transformed financial
services, creating unprecedented
pressure on transaction systems.
Cloud environments must deliver high
performance processing, uncompromising
security regularity, comprehensive
continuous availability, traditional
load balancing falls short round robin.
Distributes requests sequentially
without considering server
capacity or current workload.
So leading to uneven utilization, leased
connection routes to servers with fewest
connections, but ignores processing
power and response times common problems.
So dynamic workloads cause bottlenecks,
uneven resource utilization, and degraded
service quality in banking system.
Introducing E-C-B-A-E-C-B-A.
The Ansible Cloud banking algorithm
is a hybrid approach combining weight
round robin and adaptive load balancing.
It's designed to intelligently
manage cloud banking transactions.
Let's look at how ECBA works
and how it adapts in real time.
ECBA monitors, server capacity,
transaction types, latency.
And throughput.
It routes request based on real-time
metrics and predictive analytics with AI
forecasting and reinforcement learning.
ECBA evolves continuously anticipating
spikes before they happen.
A spotlight is behind ECBA intelligence.
It enables fraud detection, predictor
routing, conce monitoring, and.
Even self-healing in DevSecOps, these
capabilities make ECBA, not just
a scalable but smart and secure.
Let's look at how we validated
this research methodology.
Python based simulations, we
conducted comprehensive testing
across various workloads to benchmark
performance workload ranges.
We tested from thousand two,
10,000 transactions compared agist.
Round Robin leased connection and
standalone A LB measured response time
and throughput and utilization, real world
banking transaction patterns, integrated
power ly detection to validate system
behavior under unexpected load conditions.
Future simulations will integrate a
models to predict workload spikes and
based on historical transaction data.
Performance.
8,000 transactions.
ECBA achieved the lowest response
time, just 15 point milliseconds.
That significant efficiency gain,
let's see how it performs under heavier
load scaling to 5,000 transactions
as we scale to 5,000 transactions.
ECBA maintained its age.
With 36.9 requests per
second and 83.3% utilization.
This consistency under pressure is
what makes ECPA enterprise ready.
Let's summarize the key advantages.
ECPA ensures fairness, prevents overload,
and maintains performance, consistency,
even under fluctuating workloads.
These strengths are especially
critical in secure environment.
Let's talk about DevSecOps integration.
DevSecOps Integration, ECB operates
within DevOps SecOps frameworks to
ensure end-to-end encryption for
transactions regularity, compliance
monitoring, AI power compliance
in monitoring, continuously scans
for anomalously and regular risks.
Audit trial generation a driven.
Threat detection identifies
suspicious traffic patterns in
real time using behavior, analyze,
analyzing, and automated risk scoring.
So resilience features, so built in
capabilities for security operations.
So ECB operates within dec DevSecOps
Frameworks supports encryption,
ly detection, audit trials,
and zero trust architecture.
It's built for resilience
and regularity alignment.
Now let's talk about the implementation.
Deploying ECBA starts with
infrastructure assessment, metric
configuration, and rigorous testing.
It's designed for continuous optimization.
Let's explore how ECBA applies
across real world banking patterns.
So real world banking patterns.
So from payment processing to
fraud detection, ECBA, adapt.
Across platforms, ensuring
seamlessly customer experiences
and real time analysis.
These use cases show ECBA Ality.
Let's wrap up with key
advantages and key takeaways.
So key takeaways from here.
Here is what we learn.
Hybrid algorithm, alpha
form legacy methods.
Adaptability is essential, and
AI transforms load balancing.
ECPA isn't just a technique upgrade.
Technical upgrade.
It's a strategic leap
forward for cloud banking.
Thank you.
Thank you for your attention.
I hope ECBS sparks ideas for
your one in cloud strategies.
I would like to continue the conversation.
Just search Ana on our LinkedIn.
Let's connect and collaborate.
Thank you.