Hi there.
My name is Nick Manoogian and I'm
the head of engineering at Doppler.
Today, we're going to be talking about
secret ops, but before we talk about
that, I want to talk about software.
Every app has three components, the
code, which is the logic of the app, the
compute, which is what runs the code,
virtual machines, Kubernetes clusters,
serverless functions, things like that.
And then there's secrets, which are the.
Configuration for the app, these
could be sensitive values like API
tokens, encryption keys, or they
could be non sensitive values like
database hosts and port numbers.
I want you to think about the automation
that your org has for each of these three.
For code, we have things like Git
and GitHub and CI for managing the
lifecycle of our applications and
deploying them to where they need to go.
We've got compute like Kubernetes, IAC,
Terraform, and Pulumi that are responsible
for managing how we deploy our code.
And then we've got secrets.
What do we have there, right?
There's usually a native store in
our compute systems for being able to
inject these values, but where is the
Git like maintenance of these values?
Where, how do we, how are we
tracking changes over time?
Every organization has some processes
for managing their secrets, and
we're calling this secret ops.
Every organization is already
doing these things to some extent.
And I'm trying to propose a framework here
for thinking about how you are managing
your secrets on a day to day basis.
I want to make a small disclaimer that
as a Secret Ops tool, we do I don't
have a product in this space and I'm
going to be showing it throughout,
throughout this, this talk, but I am
not trying to sell you on the product.
I want to sell you on the framework.
So this is a layered approach
and these layers don't really
correspond with particular features.
They're more broad categories.
And I think it's useful to think about
these as abstractions for the processes
that you already use today and where
you can improve as an organization.
So let's start at the top with.
I like to tell a story about, my first
job out of school, I was working, at a
shop that was developing an app in Python.
So I cloned the repo, I ran app.
py and I got an error about a missing
API key, the Google Maps API key.
So I went to my manager and he told
me that I should go to Steve for
the ENV file for this, project.
So I went to Steve and he got back to
me after a few minutes over Slack, or I
think maybe it was HipChat at the time.
And, he gave me his ENV file.
I was wondering, do I need
to change any of these?
Are they unique to Steve?
Do I need to update, my,
any of the values in here?
And, how do I add values
to this going forward?
I'm getting, was planning on
integrating with an email service.
And do I just add the
SendGrid API key in here?
How does it make it to
the other developers?
like they absolutely don't know how
to add it for staging and production.
And the point of this is storage
is more than just keeping
secrets in a secure place.
It's about centralizing them to make
sure that everyone knows where to
find them and where to put them.
And this kind of ties to this idea of
sprawl, which is a problem that happens
when there are many secret stores.
And it becomes a little challenging
to know where everything is.
So if you're running your monolith,
you've got secrets for that
stored in AWS Secrets Manager.
But then there's also secrets for
CI that are in GitHub Actions.
And there might be some overlap, right?
There's like a service
that's used in both.
They're both posting messages to Slack.
And pretty quickly you lose confidence
that you understand where all
of your secrets are being used.
And if you find one in the wild,
or if you're trying to rotate
something, you're not quite sure
what's going to happen next.
and that's really the core
problem at this layer is how do
we get a single source of truth.
For where secrets are stored and make sure
that everyone knows where that place is.
So I promise to not sell you on Doppler.
I'm going to try not to, but I do want
to point out how we're thinking about
the problems at each of these layers.
So for the storage layer, this
is how we're thinking about it.
When we're talking about secrets,
we're talking about secrets
for a particular environment.
So I've got a list of secrets
here that are all used to run
the backend project, right?
The app.
py example.
And some of these values are sensitive.
Some of them are not.
And addressing that being
forthright about that is useful.
If I'm a developer and I want to add a
new API key, I know where to put that.
I'm want to make an edit to
the development environment.
So I go to dev and I
add my SendGrid API key.
I like to call out that
this is just a random value.
It's not actually a SendGrid API
key, but you're welcome to try it.
I add that API key, and when I
go back to the project level, I'm
getting warnings in staging and
production that secret is missing.
Because presumably I'm going to commit
some code that requires that secret, and
I don't want to take down these, these
other environments that might need it.
So these are the kind of benefits
that you get from centralized,
from a centralized secret store.
You get this sort of cross sectional
view across environments and projects
as a whole to be able to get this
visibility around the parity that should
exist in these different environments.
Okay, centralization is good.
We've got one store where
everyone is working out of
the next layer is governance.
So it's really up to teams to determine
who should have access to what at Doppler.
No developers have access to the
secrets in any production environment,
but not every org works this way.
There are disadvantages to doing that.
No matter what your policy is, though,
you should be able to set up rules and
your secrets manager to make sure that
you can get access to your values.
And this is particularly important
in onboarding and offboarding.
When a dev joins the team, they
shouldn't need to go find Steve, right?
It shouldn't be a whole thing.
They should get access immediately
to what they need to do their job.
When they leave a team, they should
be able to lose access immediately
without having to, try to claw out
an EMV file from them or having to
track down who has access to what.
it's a, it's an important thing to
be able to grant and revoke access
whenever, you of the handler as well as
other variables or context, assigned,
by user whenever it's required.
And another section of this is, tracking
secrets, just like Git, you wouldn't
ever want to try and develop an app
without being able to see how your
application is changing the context.
Over time, the same is true for secrets.
If you've got a static secret store
and you aren't able to see how changes
are happening over time, there are huge
risks overwriting data could result in
loss that you can't get back that data.
And you're also missing a lot of
auditing information around what's
changed, who changed it, it can make it
very hard to determine what happened.
So I won't show, how we handle
roles and groups in Doppler.
Cause it looks pretty similar to
other tools, but I will show our
audit logs, particularly for writing.
So when you're evaluating, your posture,
in storage and governance, it's useful to
see exactly what's been modified, what it
looked like before and after the change.
And it's also useful to be able to
easily roll back to earlier versions.
So I'm looking at this red green line
diff here for what's been modified.
I can see I've modified, the password
for the database, for example.
And if there was a typo in that,
or I need to roll back to that
earlier version or see what it was.
I can click a rollback button immediately
and jump back to that earlier version.
really useful kind of table stakes.
I'll, if I'm honest, this is
something that everyone should have.
So once you've got, access control
and, you have the ability to roll
back, the last bit of this is being
able to gate that access control.
The ephemeral access that people need.
as I mentioned, nobody at Doppler has
access to the production environment,
but that doesn't mean that they aren't,
that it isn't important to them or,
that it isn't a part of their job to
introduce a change to that environment.
So the way that, this is handled at a
lot of orgs is file a ticket with the
ops team and they'll take care of it.
And one of the things we're
seeing in this space is.
Tools allowing teams to self
serve these sorts of operations.
So instead of just.
I'm just handing this off and hoping
that it gets done, giving developers and,
and folks on these teams, the ability
to submit changes for review, and then
still maintaining control over the
approval and application of these secrets.
So what this looks like in Doppler.
Is a change request.
So instead of making a change
directly to an environment, for this
centigrade API key, for example, as
a developer, I can propose a change.
So I've got three values in each
of these environments that I want
to merge into the backend project.
I can review how this is going
to impact those environments.
I have access to the development and
staging environments, so I can see
exactly what's being changed, but in
production, that's not visible to me.
So all I know is that
there's a new value going in.
Then the team members with approval
access are going to get notified
and they can improve, they're able
to approve individual updates.
So dev and staging, they've
gone ahead and approved that.
And the one for production is
still waiting to be approved.
Once it's approved, either the
author or the approver is able to
apply that into the environment.
So providing a.
You can call it ephemeral access or,
workflows from making modifications
in a more controlled way.
So we've got storage and governance down.
Orchestration is really, where things
start to get interesting because all
the earlier layers are useful, but we're
not really doing much more than storing
secrets in a password manager, right?
Which is exactly what
Steve and I were doing.
At the company that we worked for, so
one password was our source of truth.
And, the orchestration layer
is like the CICD bit, right?
How do you actually deliver these
secrets to where they need to go?
And Steve was responsible for this.
he needed to be super diligent
about making sure that a secret
for staging or production.
Ended up in one password and
he needed to SSH into the
servers and update the secrets.
json file.
And we've absolutely had downtime
because of a copy pasta error or
forgetting to copy it over entirely.
He just added it to one password
and it's been many years since
Steve and I worked together and
their processes have improved.
but this is a real problem
for a lot of businesses.
So how do we solve it?
there are a couple ways to go about
it, but at Doppler, our approach
is to meet you where you are.
So we have a hub and spoke style model,
where we see Doppler as the source of
truth and it's responsible for sinking
secrets to wherever they are consumed.
So let's look at what that looks
like in a couple of different spots.
It's just like the hub and spoke
visualization here, but for
a developer running locally.
And the CLI might be the easiest
spot to consume secrets, right?
they're going to be working in, app.
py, right?
So the CLI is the easy
place to use those things.
In a Kubernetes environment, using
an operator to sync those secrets
into native cluster secrets might
be the easiest way to, to use those.
In an AWS Lambda environment,
Parameter store or secrets
manager might be the right spot.
So treat Doppler as the source
of truth and then be able to sync
secrets to wherever you need them.
And the last bit of this, it's interesting
to talk about is automatic redeployment.
So this is optional, but there
are some really cool benefits
to being able to layer in.
automatic updates.
So the idea here is that you wire up
Doppler with either the Kubernetes
operator or with webhooks to trigger
your builds or redeploy, redeploy your
workloads whenever a secret is modified.
and this is particularly nice in
conjunction with CRs because you're
empowering teams to propose a change,
you approve them, and then they
deploy them when they're ready.
And with this orchestration set up,
there's a, you have a lot more knowledge
around how secrets are being used.
You have confidence that the services
that are relying on these secrets are
actually going to consume the new values
that you are adding to the system.
Move through here.
Great.
So this is definitely where Steve
and I, Could not go further.
We did not have the orchestration layer
and we wanted to rotate secrets and we
talked about doing it, but it just seemed
too risky because there was certainly
some service somewhere that had the key
that we wanted to rotate in secrets.
json and we didn't have the confidence
that we knew where all these things were.
This is the ugly end for
secret sprawl, right?
you really don't want to be in a
position where you're choosing between
security posture and risking your uptime.
So orchestration is the solution to this.
Once orchestration is set up, you
have the confidence that you're able
to rotate a secret whenever you want.
You can just go to SendGrid,
issue a new API key and save it
right back into the application.
They're going to restart either on
the next deploy or automatically,
if you have that set up and.
You can actually take this a step further.
If you have the confidence in your
orchestration, you can actually
go forward and automate this.
So we do have an
integration with SendGrid.
I'm showing here Twilio.
And in this example, we have Doppler
hooked up with Twilio directly, and
it's responsible for issuing and
revoking Twilio API keys that are
going to be consumed in the app.
So I've got a policy here set up.
It's a little.
Small and hard to see here, maybe, but,
policy to rotate every 30 days, or you
can manually rotate in an emergency.
And what's really neat about this is when
you have automatic rotation set up, no
human has ever handled or seen that value.
And I'll talk a little bit more
later around why this is so useful.
But at this stage, you've
got automation set up.
That's coming from the confidence that you
have in your applications, being able to
consume the secrets that they need to run.
That's really the key here.
So every time a secret comes
across the wire, it increases
the chance of a leak, right?
A secret is basically just
a vulnerability, right?
That's like another way to think of it.
It's a portable identity.
And when viewed this way, a
secret read is just as important
as a secret write, right?
We should be tracking these events.
we should be able to audit these things.
And when you're looking at this
data, historically, you can answer
questions like a person left the team.
I need to know every
secret that they've seen.
Are there any services
that are using this key?
Can I revoke this?
Is it safe to do And it can also help
you track down leaks if they do happen.
So you can imagine that secret
that's being rotated every 30 days.
If you find a API key hanging out
somewhere, it should be a pretty
short list of human and non human
identities who had access to that
particular version of the secret.
So let's play through that.
we find this key.
somewhere we know it's like the
password for the database and
it's leaked in the wild, right?
You can do a global search in
Doppler, find where it's being stored.
Okay.
It's being used in the backend
environment, in, in the backend
project in, in production.
So then we can look at the
access logs for that secret.
And for the current version, we
can conclude that only me, Nick,
and these sync bots that are
responsible for syncing this value.
Into Azure vault and, and AWS
secrets manager have seen this value.
So I can conclude it was either Nick
or it was one of these identities.
I should go look at
how they're being used.
I should look at the audit
logs in these services and
track down what happened here.
Super powerful stuff.
So what is secret ops?
It's an automation framework for secrets.
That's really what it is.
You've got Git and GitHub, which
are 15 years old at this point.
You've got Kubernetes and Docker
that are 10 years old at this point.
Where are the tools
for automating secrets?
I'm hopeful that I've convinced you to
take a closer look at this framework
and to look at these layers and
really see where your org stacks up.
Do developers know how and
where to store secrets?
Is access configured in
the way that you want it?
Are secrets delivered to
where they need to go?
And are you able to effectively rotate
secrets and quickly adapt to leaks?
It's worth thinking about and
you've made it to the end.
we're really excited about secrets.
And if you are too, please
feel free to drop us a line.
My email is nickatdoppler.
com.
We would love to hear your feedback.
Thanks again for watching
and hope to see you all soon.