Hello, everybody.
My name is Shraddha Kohli, and today
I will be talking about building user
trust in conversational AI, the role of
explainable AI in chatbot transparency.
The agenda for today's talk is, I will
be introducing what is explainable AI,
the evolution of chatbots, what are
the key technologies in the explainable
AI domain, what is the methodology
that I used in my research, What was
the result of my research, the user
impact, some of the challenges, and
lastly, what is the future research
directions that can be taken in this area?
Starting with introduction
to explainable AI.
Explainable AI tackles the black box
challenge in complex AI systems by
making decision processes understandable.
It helps, it's essentially for
systems that interact directly
with users, such as chatbots.
Without transparency, it's impossible.
Users often feel unsure about how
chatbots arrive at responses, especially
in areas such as healthcare or finance.
This leads to a lot of mistrust
and hesitation for users
to use these technologies.
There are many explainable AI methods
like LIME, SHAP, and Counterfactuals
that can actually help chatbots
provide insights into their reasoning,
fostering user trust, and enabling
developers to fine tune their tools.
How do chatbots actually evolve?
Chatbots have been here for a long
time, since the 1960s, and previously
they were rule based on pattern
matching and scripted responses.
But now with the advancement in the
field of AI, a lot of them use very
deep neural networks as well as very
advanced AI and machine learning
technology to allow for more natural
and conversational interactions.
But today's modern chatbots Though
they are very powerful, they do not
provide us the transparency in their
decision making, which tends to create
a sense of doubt in the user's mind.
In order to solve this, there
are a few key techniques
that we can use for chatbots.
The first one is called LIME,
which is Local Interpretable
Model Agnostic Explanations.
This tool necessarily generates
explanations by creating a simplified
interpretable model of chatbot
behavior for a single response.
Users can see which input features
example words most influenced
the chatbot's responses.
The second one stands for SHAMP, which
is Shapely Additive Explanations.
This uses values from game theory to
assign importance to input features, such
as adding weights to the different words.
Which helps to offer a clearer picture of
how each input or how each word has been
contributing to the chatbot's response at
both the local as well as global levels.
Lastly, the counterfactual explanations
provide how slight changes in the user's
input can actually lead to different
outputs, helping users understand the
decision boundary and the sensitivity of
the chatbot to different input variations.
For our study, we actually interviewed
around 150 users in different
demographics, and we selected three
different types of chatbot models,
ranging from retrieval based,
generative, as well as hybrid models.
These represent the diversity of different
modern chatbots that we have, ranging from
simple FAQ based to highly conversational
systems that we see nowadays.
The explainable AI application process,
we basically use the three models that are
described above to, to use, on our users.
Starting with the LIME one, this one
helped us analyze specific chatbot
responses by approximating them
with simple interpretable models.
The SHAP1 helped us to calculate feature
importance scores to understand which
parts of the input influence responses.
And lastly, the counterfactuals identified
minor changes in input that would actually
yield a different output, showcasing
the sensitivity of the response.
In order to evaluate this, we
had three different metrics.
The first one was faithfulness.
What was the accuracy of the response?
The second one was stability.
What is the consistency of the
explanations across the different users?
And lastly, the comprehensibility.
How easy was it for non technical users
as well to understand the responses?
The results were pretty good.
What we found was that LIME worked
well for individual, for explaining
individual responses, but it struggled
at global level, meaning that the
explanations may vary for similar inputs.
The SHAP provided detailed
insights into feature importance
across multiple interactions.
However, due to high processing
and computational need, LIME did
not meet the initial need This is
not, this was not feasible and also
confusing for non technical users.
The counterfactual explanations were
very intuitive for users, but this
was also challenging due to real
time demands that the users have.
The main insight is that each technique
brings its own pros and cons to
the chatbot transparency, though
real time interaction and latency
and ease of comprehension are still
some areas that need to be explored.
Some of the key data points and the
user impact was after trying this
with, trying these techniques with
some of the users, we found that their
trust in their users trust in the
chatbot technology improved by 35%.
They also understood that 48% What
of users understood what is the, what
is the reasoning behind the chatbot
behavior complex task engagement.
This was the willingness to
engage with complex chatbot
tasks was also increased by 27%.
The error tolerance for users.
Basically, in forgiving the chatbot
for the responses or the errors was
also increased to a stunning 40%.
And the overall engagement and the removal
of hesitation increased by 30, 31%.
So pretty promising results.
Some of the challenges that we
experienced in implementing the
explainable AI for chatbots is number
one, as I said, real time constraints.
There is a, the generate, generating
explanations in real time without
actually providing a noticeable
delay and latency is still difficult.
How do we balance detail with
comprehension to make sure that the
explanations have the correct amount
of detail, but they are also easy to
be understood by non technical users.
Then each of the model, as I said,
has its own limitation and not
everything will be suitable for
complex architectures in state of the
art chatbots that we have nowadays.
Lastly, ethical concerns.
When our chatbots are providing us with
this information, there is also a chance
that some sensitive information could
be exposed or there could be some bias.
This requires careful ethical
handling of explanation techniques.
There are a lot of future research
directions that are, that we can take
in this area, starting with advancing
the explainable AI for complex models.
How do we develop new explainable
AI methods suited to complex
architectures like transformers,
which are common in chatbots?
Lastly, real time adaptive explanations.
How do we make sure that the research
adaptive systems that adjust with the
right level of detail that is needed?
And that's Third, self
explaining chatbots.
Investigate how chatbots can learn
to explain themselves as they evolve,
leading to a truly self explanatory
AI that users understand intuitively.
Lastly, I would like to conclude,
as chatbots became an integral
part of customer service and user
interaction across sectors, building
trust in these sectors is critical.
Explainable AI offers a pathway to
address the black box nature of AI
by making chatbot decision making
processes transparent and interpretable.
By leveraging methods like LIME, SHAP,
and counterfactual explanations, we enable
chatbots to provide insights into their
responses, which helps to foster a more
reliable and user centered experience.
This transparency not only enhances user
trust and confidence in the chatbot, but
also equips developers with powerful tools
for refining and improving these systems.
Our research demonstrated that
integrating XAI with chatbot technology
yields significant benefits in user
trust, comprehension, and engagement.
However, this journey is still a long
one and there is a lot of research that
still needs to be done in this area.
The advancements in XAI techniques
have provided a promising foundation
for more accountable, transparent,
and trustworthy AI applications.
Thank you.