Hello everyone.
My name is I'm from Meta.
Today, I'm excited to talk about like
how we can bring together AI DevSecOps
ethics and accessibility to create
personalized learning pathways that
truly like supports every student,
especially those with learning needs.
So this talk is built
around like one core belief.
AI and education must be secure,
transparent, and equitable if
we wanted to like change lives.
So currently, like where do we
stand the landscape, especially
like the challenge in general.
So we have like over 7.5 million US
students that receive services under idea.
Which is nothing but the individuals
with Disabilities Education Act.
So these students like still
experience persistent achievement
gaps and the traditional instruction
just wasn't like built to adapt
dynamically to like cognitive
sensory communication differences.
So the opportunity is that here, like
how can we like adapt AI where we
can personalize learning in general.
And also in real time which can
like significantly improve reading
outcomes for like students,
especially with like disabilities.
So this is basically like
adapting AI for these students.
And before jumping into like
how can we like, use AI in
general for the, in the ed tech.
So we also wanted to bake few things.
How can we like, protect the user data in
general as we are like dealing sensitive
data, especially related to like students.
So dev, DevSecOps, like embeds like Ed at
each and every stage enables like scalable
deployment and forces like compliance.
With ferpa, GDPR and like the
accessibility laws in general and provides
like transparency through audit trails.
So in education, like trust isn't
optional, so it's essential.
So these are the things that we
wanted to make sure the DevSecOps
like can needs to be like baked
into the AI ed tech services.
So this is like the overall picture on
a DevSecOps how we wanted to do it, but
also measuring the impact in net tech.
So using ai, the skills have been
like accelerated by 41%, like
acquisition and the engagement has
been like significantly grown by 35%.
And reading challenges can be like
detected as early as seven months.
So using ai, like these are
like the things that were like
achievable in like recent days.
Which can like, actually impact the
long term economic for these students.
And basically like how, how these
AI enabled ethics system have
like threat modeling as well.
So essentially like the
AI driven education like
comes with some unique risk.
So these include like exposure of like
sense to student data model inversion
attacks, bias outcomes, and some spoofing
of assistive tech interface interfaces.
And also like some insider threats.
So these risks define the guardrails we
must build into the system from day one.
I meant to say so these
are like some risks.
And we wanted build some guardrails
around it and we build a system for
the for the students in general who are
like using ai in their tech systems.
So before before that, like.
How can we use AI in general?
This is just like an overall picture
that I want to like, talk about,
like how these adapt algorithms
can, like personalize learning.
There are like three major
ways we can make sure the
adapt systems can personalize.
One is like the modality adoption.
The system identifies whether
the student can learn through
like best visually auditorally.
Can especially and improving the
engagement improving the engagement
of the students in general.
So one is the other the other one
is the difficulty calibration.
So the task continuously can adjust
to keep the student in their optimal
learning zones, resulting in like
more faster skills acquisition.
This is one of the important thing
like to make it like optimal zone
for the students in general so that
they can learn as soon as possible
and the scaffolding intelligence.
So what does this mean?
So the system actually like, provides
the right level of support at the right
time by providing hints, examples, and
some explanations where they can like
gradually feel that support is not needed.
And and so that they can like mastery
those skills as soon as possible.
So as soon as like the, these
things like gradually fades
away so the mastery increases.
So this reduces the learning helplessness.
And also and boost the
confidence in students.
So this is how generally the, you
can have some adapter algorithms
for personalized learning.
Okay, so now coming to the security
privacy of designing these systems.
So the systems have to
be like built securely.
We must ensure that there are
like, all the compliances are met,
like for example, the ferpa, GDPR.
And we also need to like encrypt
the data, use zero trust security
models and continuously like monitor
access and model behavior so that the
student shouldn't have to like trade
privacy for like personalization.
So this is like the overall design that
we wanted to have for the students.
Basically not for the students,
but for the the system itself.
And so that is like the overall picture
of the security and privacy and coming
to the, how can we in general, like you
also need some message to technology along
the way for building these technologies.
So we are not leaving some of the core
essential parts like accessibility.
Especially we need some seamless
screen data support, like text to
speech input and like natural text
tope our ascension for, so that
the students can easily understand.
So with these things like set up the
students can see like nearly like 50%
increase in independent task completion
and like even 40% increase in engagement.
So accessibility is like the
core component and also like
the performance amplifier.
So you wanted to have like bridge these
gaps as well with AI and like the assist
techno assist to technology integration.
So coming into like the, yeah, this
is what I was like talking about, like
increases the engagement in general.
So when students can access their
content in their preferred modality,
which we like spoke about previously
having having them to navigate smoothly
which frustrat which kind of like
decreases the frustration and also the
ta and also we can see like the reduce
in the task abandonments in general.
So the more the intuitive the experience
is, the deeper the learning is.
So that is what we have to like, make
sure we have all the systems in place
like the accessibility engagement like
ski like this like the screen readers,
like this speech to tech text or vice
versa so that they have like much
more intuitive experience and they
have the deeper learning in general.
So that is how we wanted to
define ai in the ed tech systems.
Like a overall core goal.
We wanted to make sure that the
students doesn't feel demotivated
and have like more stronger focus
and more improved retention rate.
And yeah, and coming to making the, how
the algorithm should behave as well.
So in order to be like trusted
the AI must be like explainable.
So we should use interpretable models
and we should like audit and like
providing dashboards for the teachers and
providing clear explanation for families.
So the transparency has to be
there so that the no addition
feels like a black box in general.
Because as we are like dealing
with student data especially,
and and the other things like coming
to the transparency the one of the
other things we need to take care
is like the mitigating the bias.
So bias in like educational
AI has like real consequences.
Where the thing is like we need to
like combat this using like diverse
training data, like fairness metrics
and routine audits and inclusive,
like design practices in general.
So the solution is to have like
proactive bias detection and
mitigation which must be like, embedded
into the development life cycle.
So it's not like a checkbox, it's a
continuous responsibility so that we like.
Mitigate the bias in
general in these systems.
So the tech, the now we are actually
even like looking at these systems like
making what they call it this technology
is done meant replace the educators
or like the teachers in general.
So it has to it's ma it's basically
like helping the teachers in a way.
Over here, I meant to say it deliver
relieves from a few of the things
like automatic grade using the ai
you can do, like automatic grading
adapting the content in general.
And so that the, it's,
it frees the teachers.
To focus mostly on having an emotional
connect and providing like context
and providing like individual
support to the students so that the
AI can really help in other ways.
And also like making the teachers to have
that special connection with the students.
So it like arguments together in a
best way not to replace everyone.
That is like the main motivation
that we need to like, take
into the account as well.
This is like how the ai has to be like
baked into for the EdTech systems.
Now it comes to the picture of
like how we can set up a blueprint
in like implementing this.
So we respond like how, like
the DevSecOps can help us.
Operationalize these things.
So we need to like look into like few
things like infrastructure as a core,
automated like security and accessibility,
like testing through each and every
scenario and need to see checking that
like model signing and like tamper
detection is in place like continuous
monitoring and iterative, like fast back.
It to like iterative feedback
driven improvement so that the.
You have if anything like goes out
of picture so we need to make sure
the platform like evolves better
for like students and educators.
That is like the core blueprint
in this AI tech related.
And how do we like, see like pipeline,
these adapt to like learning models.
So the things that we need to like
look into is like some of the data sets
and models and like making sure every
scanning like takes place like secretary
scanning at each and every step and
ensuring like you have the fair pan
GDPR checks and mitigating like bias and
like drift through some like fairness
tests to make sure there is less bias.
And and continuous like
monitoring of the model behavior.
That is what we wanted to like look into
some learning like the adapt learning
models in this like DevSecOps pipeline
and during this the same pipeline.
The thing is like we wanted to
look is like how can we like secure
the the student data lifecycle?
The thing is like we need
to make sure collect like
minimally, like minimal encrypt.
We collect like minimally and like encrypt
thoroughly to make sure like the data is
like secure and and also like we need to
make sure the student has the consent has.
Taken and delete any logs in
general for only like storing it
for like certain period of time.
And also like taking the pay
and consent and revoking if
needed if they don't need it.
So the privacy is like
non-negotiable in this in this case.
So we may, we need to make sure
that the student data has like
a strict life cycle in general.
Along this process it comes into
the picture of each region has
their own compliances as well.
For example, like the compliance score.
We need to embed like multiple
compliances like ferpa, GDPR A-D-A-A-D-A
is nothing but like the Americans
with Disabilities Act and V sag.
It's nothing but like the web content.
Accessibility guidelines, so me
ensuring like these are in place and
and checks which checks di directly
into the continuous integration and
like continuous deployment pipelines.
And making sure we are like auditing
the each and everything in place.
So if anything comes up you are like
protecting the user data in general.
So this makes like the compliance, like
proactive rather than like reactive.
So yeah.
So the compliance must be
like continuous in general.
But so this is what I was saying so
it has to be like the compliance has
to like balance with the innovation.
So you have to like, follow some
the DevSecOps transforms the
tension between the innovation
and regulation into strength.
So you need to have automated,
like guardrails, allowing teams
to like, innovate quickly while
ensuring like trust and safety.
So the balance has to be there in
between these two things and making
sure that we are in compliance.
And so these are like some of the lessons
for AI and like regulator sectors.
The thing is like key lessons,
which include security first, like
design which prevents like rework.
So accessibility issues must
be treated as a severity one.
Because without these especially we
as we are like dealing with diversify
students with di diversifying needs.
So the accessibility is a core
issue which I spoke earlier as well
which has the performance one mark.
And and auditing the bias runs in
production and having like privacy tools,
friendly making sure that everyone has
the access to these data, especially
the students and their parents.
So these are like some things we need
to like, keep in mind because these are
like the crucial stakeholders and, we
wanted to make sure like everyone is
safe using the AI and ed tech and there,
and we are not doing any privacy leaks.
Yeah.
So that is what, like the trust, like
building transparency, inclusion, ethical
thinking and like secure engineering.
So when DevSecOps, like guides adaptive
learning, the result in systems.
Like safe, scalable,
and like human centered.
So we need to build that trust
using this AI enabled education.
So that comes to like closing.
So the key takeaways from these, like the
prac basically the practical path forward.
So we need to like, start
with security and ethics.
Basically like design for
like diverse learners.
Keep educators at at core and commit
to like continuous improvement.
The current presentation
provides like a blueprint.
So the tools are here and
it's now the time to build
AI and education responsibly.
So embrace the, like the
continuous implement in general.
So the DevSecOps kind of like
rapidly, like enables like
rapid learning and refinement.
So yeah.
Now it's like time to build AI and
education responsibility using some of
these core blueprint ideas in general.
Thank you.
Yeah, I would like to hear like
some some of the questions feel free
to drop me a message or email me.
I'll try to respond as soon as possible.
Thank you.