Hello, everyone.
It's an honor to be in Con 42, and
I'm here to discuss a topic that is
shaping the future of technology,
multi cloud and hybrid cloud
architectures in data management.
in this presentation, we will explore
the benefits, market growth, challenges,
and best practices, and understand why
they matter in today's digital age.
according to Gartner, by 2025,
95 percent of the digital
workloads will be cloud native.
So IDC predicts the global data
sphere will reach a staggering
175 zettabytes by then.
So these figures emphasize the growing
importance of scalable cloud solutions
to handle the immense data demands.
So we'll see what are the multi
cloud and hybrid cloud architectures.
So multi cloud refers to using two
or more cloud providers, public or
private, to distribute workloads.
it helps to avoid the vendor lock
in and enhances the redundancy.
on the other hand, whereas, hybrid
cloud integrates private or public
clouds with on prem infrastructures,
offering the flexibility in data storage
and processing, these strategies,
which are vital for optimizing the
performance, reliability, and compliance
key for pillars for modern businesses.
So we'll see the benefits of
multi cloud architectures.
So multi cloud strategies
bring four key advantages.
So one, one is the redundancy.
So the redundancy is nothing but
distributing of workloads across
providers, ensures a business continuity.
even if one provider faces the
downtime, let's say in effect, 63
percent of the organization reports Oh!
Improved business continuity.
And the second one would
be the vendor flexibility.
So this approach allows choosing the
best services based on the work needs.
For example, AWS for scalability,
Google cloud for AI and Azure
for the enterprise applications.
the third advantage is
the cost optimization.
Competition between the providers
can lead to a significant savings.
45 percent of businesses, leveraging
multi cloud report cost reductions.
the fourth one will be,
performance enhancements.
workload distribution across, providers,
which ensures the optimal performance.
So coming to the growth of multicloud
market, the multicloud market is booming.
So valued, I would say probably 15
plus billion dollars in 2020, it's
projected to reach 44 billion, maybe
by 2027 growing at a robust at 18%.
So this growth is.
Driven by increasing I.
T.
Complexity and the demand of
resilient infrastructure, providing
the relevance of multi cloud
strategies and across the industries.
So the hybrid cloud architecture
overview, the hybrid cloud combines
on prem data centers, private clouds
and public clouds into one system.
So it serves as a bridge for a base
businesses, transitioning legacy
systems to cloud environments while
keeping critical data on prem or
a private like with the 87 percent
of it leaders favoring this model.
It's no wonder hybrid cloud
adoption is expected to grow by
39 percent in the next few years.
we'll see the advantages of the
hybrid cloud for data management.
I would say three standout benefits
of hybrid cloud includes, the first
one will be the data sovereignty.
Sensitive data can remain on prem
or the private clouds to meet the
compliance needs like GDPR or any
HIPAA while non sensitive data
leverages public cloud resources.
So coming to the second advantage,
I would say scalability with on
demand public cloud resources.
Scaling operation becomes like
four and a half times faster
compared to the traditional setups.
The third point would be the
legacy system integration.
It allows businesses to modernize
gradually integrating legacy
systems with cloud environments.
next one will be the growth
of the hybrid cloud market.
the hybrid cloud market is
expanding significantly.
I would say expected to grow
from, 73 billion dollars in 2020
to 171 billion dollars by 2025.
cost efficiency,
scalability, and compliance.
Needs are major drivers of this growth.
Additionally, SMBs are adopting hybrid
cloud solution to access advanced
technologies without any upfront cost.
we'll see the next one, next slide is
coming to the multicloud and hybrid cloud.
So despite of all these benefits,
there are a couple of challenges
I would like to present.
So first one is a data integration
differences in architecture,
making integrating data complex.
The second one would be the security
risk in the sense like when, with the
data spreads across the environments,
ensuring robust security is critical.
The third challenges
would be the skill gaps.
So finding skilled professionals.
remains a hurdle for many organizations.
So we'll see another, a couple more
challenges in a cloud strategies.
So compliance and the cost
management, add to the list.
For example, like 53 percent of the
organizations struggle with evolving
compliance policies across multiple
environments without proper governance.
Cloud costs can spiral out of control.
So interestingly, the global data privacy
market is projected to reach 83 billion
by 2027, reflecting RISE compliance needs.
So I would like to present a
best practice of implementation
to overcome these challenges.
Business should adopt best practices
such as like implementing Strong
data governance policies to ensure
data integrity and security.
using, data integration tools like ETL
and virtualization to streamline these
operations, and adopting cloud agnostic
technologies to avoid vendor lock in.
practicing continuous monitoring to
optimize cloud performance, cost, or
any such kind of potential savings
of which, which are up to 30%.
to sum up the multi cloud and
hybrid cloud architectures, Provide
businesses with the unmatched
flexibility, scalability, and security.
while challenges like integration security
and compliance exist, the advantages
would be, which will outweigh the hurdles.
by leveraging the governance,
cloud, agnostic tools, and
continuous optimizations,
organizations can fully realize the
potential of these architectures.
As we move on, into a data driven era.
those who master these strategies will
undoubtedly lead in innovation and growth.
thank you for your time and attention.
Let's embrace the opportunities,
from multi cloud and hybrid cloud
architectures, and bring and unlock any
new possibilities for the data management.
Thank you.