Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 DevSecOps 2024 event.
Today I am presenting you one of
the exciting topic about securing
the Kubernetes ecosystem, a
comprehensive multi level framework.
Here is the agenda.
I will cover key points of securing
Kubernetes ecosystem, including about
me, a statistical report from Red
Hat, With allowing security facts.
I will cover the goal of this presentation
with a multi level security approach and
architecture followed by a final touch.
Let's begin.
My name is Thyagarajan Aramudan.
I am a cloud services manager
with extensive experience
in Kubernetes security.
You can connect with me in LinkedIn.
The recent Kubernetes security statistics
report from Red Hat alarming trends.
If you notice, about 67 percent
of organizations delayed their
deployment due to Kubernetes security
concerns and about 46 percentage of
organization lost their revenue due
to Kubernetes security incident.
Wait, no need to be panic.
Let's stay alert.
Our goal is to provide a
multi level approach to secure
the Kubernetes ecosystem.
ensuring robust security at every level.
We will explore multi levels of security.
It is like an onion layers,
applying security at each level.
So let's say level one with infrastructure
and then level two at cluster and
then applying security at container
level, applying security on the
application layer and finally followed
by applying security at code level.
This architecture diagram shows a typical
API and web application highlighting
the areas that are not fully secured.
Here, traffic from UI, front end goes
to API management and the service A
and service B deployed to Kubernetes.
If you notice, the service A communicates
to database and service bus, whereas
service B communicates to all the
systems like database, service bus,
key vault and external services.
And the service A also
communicates to service B.
In this architecture.
The request from UI goes directly
to API management with no controls.
Here, no RBAC applied,
no pod security as well.
Pod have absolutely no controls.
So it can communicate to
any system by default.
So system is at very high security risk.
So let's start our multi level
security approach and see how our
clean slate with fully secured
architecture going to be look at.
Let's dive in level one
infrastructure level security
laying and securing the foundation.
So securing the infrastructure layer
involves implementing firewalls Applying
the security patches and leverage cloud
provided security features like Azure
security features in azure Whereas in
amazon, they have aws security groups
and network acls I come up with a matrix
table with security tool options for cloud
and open source in case of azure We have
azure security center nsgs and firewall
which can be You Utilized for AWS they
have security hub security groups and WAF
which can be utilized And then for the
open source, we can have firewall and OS
ordaining, which can be used for applying
the infrastructure level security.
In this architecture, I have added
firewall just before the API management
and added the subnets and NSGs to
protect all the incoming requests.
This would safeguard the request.
Securing the infrastructure is only
20 percentage of the overall security,
but it is a critical foundation.
Next level is cluster level security,
protecting our Kubernetes core.
We need to implement RAC and then
enforcing a network policies like
Calico, and then adding the encryption
and the con in the communication layer
where we can use the STO as a tool
for encrypting the communication.
So in case of Azure, we can have
Azure R back and Azure policy.
We can apply for the cluster
level security for AWS.
They have an a m roles and security hub.
Whereas in open source we have the tools
like calico and istio So in azure, aks,
it comes with an add on an istio add on
which can be utilized And calico also
can be added to an azure aks so that the
cluster level security can be enhanced.
In this architecture, I have added
Calico STO, which comes with Sidecar.
Calico controls the power communication.
The first step is to set global
policy as default, deny all, to
block all the incoming traffic.
Then add network policy to enable the pod
communication to corresponding services.
Next, the STO encrypts the communication.
Here, pod communications are
managed, controlled, and encrypted.
securing the cluster brings
the security level up.
to 40 percent showing
the significant progress.
Next is the level 3.
Using, sorry, next is the level 3
which is container level security.
Using the minimal base image and scanning
for vulnerabilities are essential for
securing the container images and runtime.
In case of Azure we have AZR
and AKS vulnerability scanning.
And then for AWS, they
have ECR and Inspector.
For the open source, we have the
image scanning tools such as Trivia,
sorry, Trivi and Clare, along with the
security contacts which can be utilized
for the container level security.
In this architecture, I have
added scanning tool, real time
monitoring tools, and signed images.
This would very well
safeguard the container.
All right.
Securing the container level increases
the security to 60 percent demonstrating
the importance of this layer.
Next is level 4, which is
application level security.
In this layer, we need to focus on
implementing secure coding practice
and manage the secrets properly.
In case of Azure, they
have Azure Key Vault.
AWS, they have Secrets
Manager and IAM roles.
And for the open source, there are
tools like Vault and Sealed Secrets.
And then we can also have secure coding
practices applied at the code, at the IAM.
application level.
In this architecture I have
added code repo and showing
secrets stored in keyword.
Securing the application level
increases security to 80 percentage
Showing substantial progress.
This is the final level
which is code level security.
We need to conduct thorough code
reviews, utilize the static and
dynamic analysis tool and implement the
policies for automated compliance check.
In case of Azure, we have security
features, DevOps security features
and static code analysis tool and
AWS as code pipeline security.
And static code analysis tool and
followed by in an open source.
We have an open source sonar cube versions
and opa so we also have the sonar cube,
Licensed version which can be utilized
in case of having More features comes
with the SonarQube licensed version.
So in this architecture, I have added
DevOps pipeline, code reviews, policy
enforcement, and code scanning tool.
So securing the code, sorry, so securing
the code level achieves 100 percent of
security, 100 percent of the security,
completing our multi level, approach.
This is the ultimate secured architecture.
So we can choose the tool based on
cloud provider or any open source.
The goal here is to apply
the security at every level.
We can use any tools like an observability
tools like Grafana or any tools for
real time monitoring of Kubernetes.
vulnerability alerts.
If you notice here, starting
from infrastructure level to code
level, Our code, our application
is secured in all the levels.
So this shows the 100 percent
of secured applications.
We can also leverage AOPS for proactive
threat detection and self healing process.
One more last thing is
zero trust security model.
it is a principle to follow,
never trust, but always verify.
One example is to apply it
for granular access control.
Here is the a hundred percentage secure
protect, secure protected product
introduced to buy multi-level of security.
You can see, the secure product
within the multi-layers of.
multilayers of security
conclusion.
So securing the Kubernetes is
not one size fits all solution.
I'm going to repeat, securing Kubernetes
is not a one size fits all solution.
It requires a multi tiered approach
that addresses security at every level.
from infrastructure to code.
With that, I complete my presentation.
Once again, thank you all for listening
and let's maintain our application safe.
Thank you.