Hello, everyone.
thank you for joining me
at DevSecOps 2024 by CON42.
In this talk, we will be discussing about
Software Bill of Materials, aka SBOMs.
But before we dive into the topic, let
us get the introductions out of the way.
My name is Safeer.
I have been in the SRE
and DevOps 19 years.
I'm an author, speaker, and an ambassador
for the Companies Delivery Foundation.
All right.
So let us set the stage by recapping
our understanding of DevSecOps.
The DevSecOps framework improves SDLC by
detecting vulnerabilities throughout the
software development and delivery process.
It merges the security into DevOps
practices and shifts the security left.
So what are the benefits of DevSecOps?
You can catch the software vulnerabilities
early, ensure that you have regulatory
compliances, and improve performance.
So what are the benefits of DevSecOps?
build a security aware
engineering culture, and
develop new features securely.
When we are talking about security
in SDLC, a key concept we should
learn about is software supply chain.
Now the term supply chain refers
to people and process for making
and distributing a product,
typically applied to manufacturing.
In the context of software supply
chain, It includes people, processes,
and software components that touch
your software development lifecycle,
starting from the source code, all the
way up to your software deployment.
Now, what makes software
supply chain special?
Almost no modern software products
are built from the ground.
They are always built on
top of existing software,
predominantly open source software.
Now, it is this that Dependence
on open source software that
makes it both powerful and work.
software supply chain is a complex
mix of technology, people, process.
And that introduces a large
number of touch points.
And for threat actors, these touch
points become the attack surfaces to
infiltrate the software supply chain.
Now, a crucial issue with supply
chain is that, this chain of open
source dependencies are outside
the control of the software
developers and the organizations
that build the final product.
Now, this limits their ability
to improve the security of these
dependencies and the infrastructure
that holds these dependencies up to us.
The reason why, supply chain security is
very critical is that Compromising, even
a small component in this ecosystem can
have a wider and catastrophic impact.
To drive this point home, let us look at
a few attacks on software supply chain.
So there are some, surface, so these
are some software supply chain attacks.
there are actually a lot more,
I just checked a few of them to
show you the variety of attacks.
So first one is even stream.
In 2018, so an attacker published
a new NPM package called
FlatMapStream with no malicious code.
A month later, it was added as a
dependency of the EventStream package.
And another month later, a malicious
version of the FlatMapStream, which
was a dependency, was published.
And the issue was detected only
after 8 million downloads of the
affected software happened, and it
infected a large number of systems.
in 2020, SolarWinds attacked.
what happened was, attackers
injected a backdoor into the
software update of SolarWinds.
Now, SolarWinds is a networking
software, that is used by, big companies,
as well as government agencies.
Now this backdoor allowed attackers
remote access to thousands of systems
across the world from every client who
would have used the SolarWinds software.
So the affected organizations
included Intel, Microsoft,
Cisco, and even a number of U.
S.
government agencies.
The third one is Kaseya.
So attackers compromised this
platform, infecting with ransomware,
which then deployed together
with an update of the software.
Now this ransomware spread to thousands
of customer environments, and, attackers
were able to extort more than 70
million from the effect customers code.
Code.
So an attacker infected the code
bash up letter, which is, part of
a code coverage testing tool that.
automatically sends customer reports.
By injecting malicious code into
this grid, the attacker was able
to eavesdrop on the quad core
servers and steal customer data.
And the most recent one
is exit utils backdoor.
So malicious backdoor in the exit
linux utility was created, which is
giving backdoor access to And that
backward actually, gave remote,
execution privileges over some versions
of OpenACCESS on the target systems.
Now, these are like, again, very
few number of attacks that I have
quoted here, but this should give
you, an idea about the variety
and the impact of such attacks.
So, test points are, these are the test
points where the attackers can exploit
vulnerable parts of the supply chains.
And as you can see, from the
list of the left side, it covers
the entirety of your SDLC.
Now on the right side, what you're
seeing the attack vectors and you
know how an attacker can exploit
some of the vulnerabilities.
for example, third party
components, so malicious actors can.
Target third party components like
libraries or frameworks and search for
opportunities to insert malware into them.
Compromise development tools.
Again, tools like compilers, build
systems or other development tools.
Again, try to, inject malware.
Developer accounts.
This is quite common.
Many users can try to exploit
vulnerabilities within developer accounts.
Could be in, hosted core platforms
like GitHub or GitLab Compromise
Software, updating processor.
Now, again, actors frequent target,
this kind of in, software updating
processors to, compromise and insert
malware and into software updates.
Social engineering, again, attackers
can try to, contact employees and, make
them in order to, Give up their security
credentials using social engineering.
So how do we prevent and
mitigate this kind of attacks?
four phases of it.
One is protecting the source
code integrity, because that's
where everything starts.
code signing can protect
source code integrity.
there are a number of standards
for signing and attestation
of code and artifacts.
Now, mitigating dependencies, requires
that you know about the dependencies
of your software and continuously
monitor for the vulnerabilities.
And for, your build and deployment
infrastructure, again, improve the
security in terms of, whether it's exposed
to the internet or is there any opening
points which, attackers can exploit.
Things like that, securing the
entire infrastructure is important.
It should always be a high
priority for DevSecOps and DevOps.
So far from whatever we discussed so
far, one key takeaway is that a number
of DevOps and DevSecOps responsibilities
revolve around the software supply chain.
And protecting the supply chain will be
a major part of DevSecOps responsibility.
And one of the most important steps
in protecting supply chain is to
understand What is in your software?
Because if you don't know
what is in your software, you
cannot protect your software.
So figuring out what are the
dependencies that goes into
your software is very important.
And this is where software bill
of material comes into play.
So bill of materials is a common thing.
it's mostly used, it's used in many
industries, even in constructions,
manufacturing, and a lot more.
Okay.
So Bill of Materials is an
extensive list of raw materials,
components, and even instructions
required to construct, manufacture,
or repair a protected service.
So there are manufacturing BOMs,
engineering Bill of Materials, etc.
But in the context of software, an
SBOM, or a Software Bill of Material,
includes all software components that are
used to make a final software product.
The SBAR will introduce, details of the
software version, patches, dependencies,
vulnerabilities, licenses, etc.
Some of the key, benefits of
software build of materials,
one is component transparency.
once you have an SBAR software, it
offers complete transparency into the
components used in that application.
which helps identify potential security
vulnerabilities or licensing issues
related to third party dependencies.
Vulnerability management.
once we know all the components and their
versions, and, organizers can quickly
identify if any part of the software
is affected by non vulnerabilities and
take appropriate remediation measures.
Think of the log for Shell vulnerability.
Any organization that had SBOM at that
point in time would have been able to
quickly protect them because they would
know which all components in their
software infrastructure would be impacted
by the law of forced vulnerability.
Compliance and risk assessment.
S1 means in, complying with
industrial regulations and standards
that mandate transparency and
disclosure of third party companies.
It also helps in evaluating potential
security and legal risks associated
with the And again, general supply
chain security, it enables organizations
to better understand and manage
their software supply chain, reduce
the risk of, supply chain attacks
and ensuring that components and,
are sourced from, trusted sources.
Again, You don't just manufacture
one software, you will have a number
of software that are deployed.
Some might be open source tools,
some might be infrastructure tools.
Any company would have a number
of softwares and managing all
of them And processing them.
Obviously, you cannot process
them in a using humans.
So which means It requires
automations, right?
So it is imperative that you should have
standards for SBOPs And as you can see it
helps you with interoperability automation
and adopt industry based practices.
let us look at some of
the standards in S4.
So the current industry standards
are Cyclone DX and SPDX.
we will look into them in a bit
more detail in the next slides.
so in addition to the this to
explore, standards, there are also
a few other standards that help in
naming and describing softwares.
So they are, software IDs.
it defines a structural metadata format
for describing a software product.
Common Platform Enumeration or CPE.
There's a standardized method for,
for describing and identifying.
Class of applications, operating systems,
and even hardware devices present
in an interface's computing assets.
Package your, PURL is, it's a URL
string used to identify and locate
a software package in a, universal,
way across programming languages,
package managers, packaging
conventions towards a p and database.
So, let's say know you have a machine,
water softwares are installed on it,
whether they are, RPMs, DN packages.
For java packages, and anything
of the sort, everything can be,
represented using a package URL.
So let us, come to one of the,
SBOM standards, that's SPDX.
So SPDX is essentially a
software package data exchange.
And it was, Linux software,
Linux foundation that, developed
this in the early 2010s.
So it's focused mostly on
compliance and licensing.
And it's, the latest version is, 3.
0.
1.
one thing about SPDX that
is very comprehensive.
It not only lists packages, or
its licenses, it also, lists files
used and code snippets sometimes.
So this actually helps in, getting a
well rounded view of what our components
are there in your software ecosystem.
And it has been around for
a long time, from 2010.
And it's already used by many industries
and products, including automotive
and the healthcare industries.
Cyclone DX came from OWASP.
Anyone who is into security would
know about the OWASP Foundation.
And actually their core focus is
on vulnerability and security.
And it is used quite widely in
a lot of software organizations.
And the latest version is 1.
6.
So SBOM classification, so SBOM can
be generated at various stages of
your software development lifecycle.
And it has different
classifications and purposes.
CISA, the U.
S.
Cyber Security Agency, classifies the
SBOMs into six categories, as you can see.
there's design, source, build,
analyze, deployed, and runtime.
And, you can see the, description
here, it's quite self explanatory.
. So again, the software bill of
material can be generated all these
stages depending on it, whether we are
building a software or you just bought
a software and, things like that.
But there are also other types
of classifications for bombs like
SaaS, bill of materials, machine
learning of materials, hardware,
build of materials, et cetera.
let's go into a short demo of generating
an S om in Cyclone DS format, and
then look into the data in sbo.
All right.
so there are a number of tools
which you can use for generating
software bill of materials.
We are, using a utility called
SIFT, which is from the company
Anchor, which is a security company.
And what we're going to, so there are,
again, S1 can be generated from any
sort of packages, software, even, just
a directory within your patch system.
In this particular case, we are going
to Directly fetch the alpine docker
image and scan it and generate a
software build of material out of it.
There is no additional software installed.
This is the plain vanilla alpine image.
And again, if you see the CLI options, we
are giving it, the cyclone DX JSON format
and save it into a file called alpine.
cyclone.
json.
As you can see, it fetches the
image, doing some cataloging
of all the softwares.
Looking at, file metadata,
file digest, et cetera.
It looks like it is finished.
So let us, start examining the json file.
We'll start with the top
elements that, this file has.
All right, you can see schema,
bomb format, components,
dependencies, metadata, serial
numbers, spec version, version.
So if you go to the, actual,
cycle only specification, that I
had given in the previous slide.
There's a lot more, elements
within the Cyclone DX format,
but, a lot of them are optional.
if I remember right, there are
only serial number and spec
version which are compulsory,
and everything else is optional.
So this gives a lot of freedom for, people
to generate S forms as, as they require.
But, again, if you want to know
more details about what each of
these components mean, you can
actually visit the specification.
Now, let us look at some
of the basic information.
schema again, points to
the actual schema website.
The BOM format, obviously, is cyclone dx.
And the spec version is 1.
6.
Now, the other things are
serial number and version.
So, the standard, SBOM standard mandates
that there should be a serial number.
Which can uniquely identify a particular
sbomb file and whenever So let's say, you
are right now, we have targeted alpine
docker image right now Let's say after
where the docker alpine docker image
changed And you have the again generation
sbomb then it should have a different
version It could be you know, it will
start from version one and version two
and progress like that So you are most
important things to remember you have a
cl number and a version Now there is a
metadata dictionary within the Cyclone DX.
If you see here, it, talks about the
software itself and how it was generated.
So the timestamp is the time at
which the S Bomb was generated.
And the tools used for generating it.
Again, I don't know who's the authors.
It's from Anchor.
The utility name is SIFT
and uses the version 1.
170.
And there's a component here.
So this component actually
displays, what is the software
for which this S BOM is generated.
And this obviously is Alpine
and it's a type container.
And what you see here,
BOM reference as a string.
So in the, in, Cyclone DX, format, a
BOM reference is like a unique key or a
primary key for any software component
within that particular document.
Okay.
Now, you could use this reference ID
to refer to this particular component
in any other part of the same document.
That is the whole idea of BOM references.
You will see more BOM references
in the upcoming portions.
let us look at components.
Components are nothing but these
are the actual software components
that the SBOM utility detected
and added into the SBOM file.
So what you can see, sir, now, it
actually generated 15 components.
remember that is a very lightweight
image and it has a very limited
number of software changes, and
that is you are only seeing 15.
If it was a, large, Docker, image
with the bunch of files for, code,
this would've be totally different.
So let us, we know that there
are only 15 components, so
let us, look at what are the.
Components that, this file has.
So as you can see, there
are again 15 packages.
And what I have listed is the package
name and the type of the package.
So for S BOM, most of the packages are
considered as libraries or dependencies.
and it also detected Alpine
as an operating system.
So these are the 15
components within this S BOM.
Now we'll take a look at one of
the packages called s SR client.
So for this package, so there's a lot of
information for per package in an S one.
So properties is one,
element, which is quite long.
We will see that in the next session.
before that I want to show the
rest of the components here.
So if you see here, again, there's a bone
reference, which is the unique key for
this particular package called SSL client.
Within this document.
So that is what bomb reference is and
you can see that it has a particular
format The type is library obviously
and the publisher is the author of the
software and the name version description
everything is Gathered here and one of the
important thing is it also lists licenses
and it is a gpl2 version one thing you
have to Know about this structure is that
it says licenses not license The reason
is for open source software, it might
be built from a bunch of other softwares
and they might have varying, licenses.
And that is why the provision is there
for adding a bunch of additional licenses
that might be applicable to the software.
And if you remember, we had discussed,
known SBOM standards, CPE, BURL,
et cetera, SWDID, all of them.
this system actually uses CPNP URL for,
referencing to some of these components.
External references, whenever a tool
can find some information about where
this software came from or, where the
documentation site is or whatnot, it
will be added as an external reference.
Let's look at the properties, property
of the, this, particular package.
So there's a long list of, items.
we will look at a few.
So again.
How did, how was this package discovered?
APK DB cataloger is a
component of the SIFTS utility.
Nesmo utility will have a
bunch of catalogers, for
different type of softwares.
And this actually found
out that, it's an APK.
And the package type is APK.
And, some of the other important
things are, the size of the package,
some of the dependency lists,
and what it provides, et cetera.
And the version, things like that.
Moving on, I talked about
multiple licenses, right?
And, there is, the package that
we saw had only one license.
Let us see another package.
This is special.
And I took it from, another S bomb
that I, generated earlier for Kubuntu
image, the basic Kubuntu image.
And the license we are looking
for is for the package bash.
You see here, bash has a whole
bunch of licenses attached to it.
PSD, GFDL, GPL, Latex2V, MIT Lite.
All of them.
So that's why I was talking that is,
why, when you are looking at license
compliances, not just security, SVM
also helps you with license compliances
to see whether, you have possible
legal issues in terms of license
violations or anything like that.
So that is why this licensing
part is very important.
Again, let us, so we looked at
components as a top level element
now, and there is another top level
element, which is dependencies.
Dependencies as the name suggests
is the dependency between the
components that we saw already.
Now there are 10 entries
for dependencies here.
And what we are going to do is pick
just one package for the time being
and see what are its dependencies.
You see here again, there's a reference.
So basically we picked the dependencies
of the SSL client package and what you can
see is it depends on three other packages.
And if you see here, all of them are
bone references, which means you can
find these packages within this SBO file.
Now, since you know what packages
are in your SBO and what is avers,
it's always possible to look up into
external vulnerability database and
figure out whether this package has
well , and that is one of the, of
having an . And to do that, we are
using under CLA from the ancor com.
it's another CLI to which you can feed
this, S BOM file and Accur will go online,
sorry, GRIBE will go online, talk to a
few vulnerability databases and figure
out is there any, vulnerability in this
S BOM, packages listed in this S BOM.
So let us do that.
All right.
Created a report called alchemy.
gribe.
json.
So all the autoresponse it gave is here.
And what we're going to do is, I know
that, it has formed a few matches,
so I'm just picking one of the
matches and some of the information
about that vulnerability here.
Give me a second.
Sorry for that.
it looks like there is a slight problem.
Give me a second.
All right.
it looks it didn't work out as I expected.
Let me just try to
troubleshoot the slide.
All right.
My bad.
I think there was some system was hanging
for a bit, but you can see the result now.
all the vulnerability we picked
is for the package libcrypto3.
the vulnerable version is.
3.
2 R0 and the vulnerability
is CVE 2024 9143.
It has a medium vulnerability category.
And this version is basically
showing that, This is the fixed
version of this particular package
without this vulnerability.
as you can see, this is
only limited information.
If you look at this file, actually,
if you generate this file, you will
see there's detailed information about
what is vulnerability, what are the
artifacts impacted, et cetera, et cetera.
I just, some information
to show you what it can do.
All right.
And again, you could use any tools.
You will get, similar results.
And this helps you in finding out
what packages in your system has what
vulnerabilities and mitigate them
Now just to show you about the
dependency, we'll do one more thing.
I am Picking up all the dependencies from
this sbomb and plotting it as a graph
All right
As you can see There's a lot of
dependencies, as you can see.
If you see, PK2 has a bunch of
dependencies, Alpine based layout
has two dependencies, SSL client
has three dependencies, like that.
And the dependencies might be depending
on some other different software.
So there is going to be a
multilevel dependency here.
And just to show you that, let me
actually pick a package called Alpine
based layout from this SBOM and
show its dependencies as a graph.
All right.
So as you can see,
Alpine base layout is the package.
And it has two dependencies.
One is alpine based layout data.
sorry that it's not showing the
entire package name here, but
that is one of the dependencies.
And the second dependency is bcbox
bin assets, which in turn is a
bcbox dependency, which in turn
depends on the muscle library.
As you can see, this is just to show
you that, when you have a package,
the dependency is multi legged.
And with this dependency information, You
can actually put the entire dependency
and figure out if your software
has some upstream dependency or, in
some, by, at the level dependency,
which could have vulnerability
or other legal issues, right?
So that is the power of having an SBOM.
Now with this, let me wind up this
demo and get back to the presentation.
All right.
So with this knowledge
of SBOMs, what should the
DevSecOps do to adopt them?
See, SBAP is a new topic
for most of the engineering.
understand them first and then
assess and document the use
cases within the organization.
And if necessary, evangelize this
to the rest of the organization.
And to do that, evaluate the tools,
for, creating and managing SBAPs.
There are a lot of open source
as well as vendor tools.
Many of them are SaaS products.
so once you pick the tools, integrate
them into your, software development
lifecycle and automate SBOM generation.
You should have tools that will help
you, save the SBOM data and analyze them.
And also remember that this is not a
one time task and should be part of
your SDLC and the continuous process.
So to analyze the data, make reports and
share it with the right stakeholders,
might be your engineering counterparts,
leadership, or security team.
And also set alerts and reports
on vulnerabilities, license
components, et cetera, so that
your security posture improves.
With that, we are coming to
the end of this presentation.
If you would like to know more about
SBOM, these resources will help you.
So the OWASP authority to get
SBOMs is extensive and it will
give you a good idea of what to do.
Cyclone DX format as well as the
general information about Sbomb,
how to go about that option, etc.
And if you want to know about Sbomb
tools, Cyclone DX tool center is
actually a good starting point.
Of course, it is, it doesn't cover
all the tools that is out there, but
it gives you a good starting point.
I hope you were able to get some value
out of this and thanks for listening.