Hello, everyone, and welcome to this
session on Kubernetes networking 101.
In this session, we'll dive
into the fascinating world
of Kubernetes networking.
Now, I know networking can sometimes
feel like a black box, especially when
Kubernetes has its own complexities on top
of it, whether you are a developer or a
DevOps engineer or somewhere in between.
My goal today is to make this topic
approachable and practical for you.
Networking in Kubernetes is a vast topic.
And it's impossible to cover
everything in just 30 minutes.
So in this session, we'll focus
on the foundational concepts and
key areas that you can build on.
So before we start, a quick introduction.
My name is Abdul Kareem.
I'm the founder and principal
architect at V Lambda.
And I've been in DevOps SRE
space for more than a decade now.
You can feel free to ask questions
during the Q& A at the end.
Or you can also reach out over email
or Twitter using these coordinates.
So here's the agenda.
We'll start with a brief
introduction to Kubernetes to
ensure we are all on the same page.
Then we'll dive into the core topic.
That is Kubernetes networking.
First, we'll explore how pods communicate,
starting with communication within
the same node, and then moving on to
communication across multiple nodes.
Next, we'll talk about the
overlay networks and how they
handle cross node communication.
From there, we focus on services,
which are a key to abstracting and
simplifying, port communication.
We'll also briefly touch upon IP
tables and its role in routing the
traffic within a Kubernetes cluster.
So Kubernetes is the most popular
open source container orchestrator
platform available in the market.
It simplifies the deployment, scaling,
and management of containerized workloads.
Making it a crucial tool
for modern infra developers.
It was originally developed by Google and
they released it as open source in 2014.
So it's been almost 10 years now that
Kubernetes is available in the market.
One of the reasons Kubernetes has
become so popular is its ability
to handle dynamic environments.
Imagine running hundreds of
thousands of containers manually.
It is just not feasible to automate
much of this complexity for you.
It also stands out because it adapts
to changing demands effortlessly.
For example, you can scale your
application as well as infrastructure up
or down automatically, ensuring you always
have just the right amount of resources.
Never too much and never too little.
When something goes wrong, Kubernetes
acts like a safe healing system as well.
detecting and replacing any
field containers to keep your
applications running smoothly.
All of this is made possible by Kubernetes
networking, of course, which acts as
the highways connecting every container,
pod, and service within your cluster.
Without a well maintained network,
traffic would slow down, applications
would crash, and the entire
system could grind to a halt.
So networking is a foundation
that allows Kubernetes to
orchestrate applications at scale.
And that's what we'll be
explaining in the session.
Now let's talk about pods.
Pods are the basic building
blocks of Kubernetes.
In Kubernetes, you don't work
directly with containers.
Instead, containers are grouped into pods.
Think of pod as the smallest
deployable unit in Kubernetes.
a logical wrapper around one or more
containers that need to work together.
All containers within a pod share the
same network and storage namespace.
which means they can communicate
with each other using localhost.
This design simplifies, the way
containers interact within the same pod.
For example, if you have an application
split into multiple components,
like a web server and a monitoring
agent, they can reside in the same
pod and communicate seamlessly.
Pods are also designed to
be atomic and ephemeral.
Atomic means they're
treated as a single unit.
If something goes wrong in a pod, The
entire pod is replaced and ephemeral means
they can be destroyed and recreated at
any time, which introduces an important
consideration, the pods IP address.
It's never permanent.
It can keep on changing.
Every new pod will have a new IP address.
So in short, pods encapsulate containers.
Provide them with a unique environment
and act as a foundation for all high level
Kubernetes abstractions, like deployments,
replica sets, stateful sets, and so on.
Next, we'll talk about the
Kubernetes networking model.
Now that we understand what a
pod is, let's dive deep into
how networking works for pods.
Kubernetes operates on a
model called IP per pod.
This means that every pod in the
cluster gets its own unique IP address.
This is a fundamental part of
Kubernetes design and a key reason why
its networking model is so powerful.
With each pod having a unique IP,
Kubernetes can treat them like
independent entities on a network, right?
much like a device on a local network.
This simplifies communication because
one pod can reach another directly
without requiring NAT or any network
address translation within the cluster.
Another key aspect of the networking
model is that all containers in a
pod share the same network namespace.
This means that they share
the same IP address, network
interfaces, and boot space.
So by sharing the network
namespace, Containers inside
a pod can communicate directly
without using pod level networking.
For example, if one container is running
a web server and another is running a
monitoring agent, the agent can collect
metrics using localhost without any
external networking configurations.
This shared namespace is what
makes pods so efficient, for
running tightly coupled workloads.
While containers within a pod work
as a cohesive unit, communication
between pods continues to rely on
Kubernetes broader networking model,
where each pod has its unique IP.
So this inter pod communication model
is a foundation, to how Kubernetes
simplifies application design.
Cool.
Let's bring everything we've
discussed so far into this example.
to visualize the concepts of IP per
pod and shared network instances.
So in this diagram, we have a
virtual machine, VM1 with an 2.
3.
Inside this VM, there are two pods,
each with its own unique IP address.
Pod A has address 0.
10 and is running a Python application
on port 3000, while pod C has IP of 0.
11 and contains two containers, one
running a Java application on port 3000.
And the other running a data docketed.
Now, if you have run traditional
workloads, you would realize that on a
single VM, it is not possible to run, an
application on the same port, multiple
applications using the same port.
But since, we are running in
this isolation provided, using
containers and Kubernetes, you
can have a number of applications
all listening on the same port.
So in this case, Python and Java, both
applications are running on the same VM.
And I'm listening on port 3000.
All right.
The setup illustrates
the IP per port model.
So each port is assigned a unique IP
address, allowing them to communicate
directly with each other, without
requiring any translations, right?
So for instance, port A, if port A wants
to send data to port C, it can do so by
addressing port C's unique IP address 192.
168.
0.
11.
And within port C, the two containers
are sharing the same network namespace.
This means, they both have
access to the same IP address.
and can communicate with
each other using localhost.
For example, the Datadog agent
can collect metrics from Java
application by connecting to
localhost colon 3000 slash metrics.
This shared namespace simplifies
the way containers within a pod
interact, making them feel like they
are running on the same machine.
All right, so now that we've discussed the
IP per pod model and how pods communicate,
you might wonder how does Kubernetes
assign IP So the answer is it does not.
Kubernetes doesn't itself get involved
in the IP address management, but
rather it leaves it to the CNI.
that is the Container
Networking Interface target.
Let's look at the pod creation
lifecycle in the next slide.
So the process of IP address
allocation for a pod involves
several components working together.
But I'll break it down step
by step to make it simple.
It all starts when, the Kubernetes
schedules a pod on a specific node.
The kubelet on that node takes over
and instructs the container runtime
interface plugin to create the board.
In this example, the CRI
plugin is container D.
Container D creates a sandbox ID and
sets up the Paul's network namespace.
Container D then hands off the
job of setting up the networking
to, a CNI plugin, right?
Or the Container Network Interface plugin.
The CNI plugin works with your chosen
networking solutions such as Flannel or
Calico or, AWS VPC CLI to assign the pod a
unique IP address from the available pool.
Once the networking is ready, the
CRI creates something called as a
pause container, which holds the
network setup and acts as the base
for all containers in the pod.
Finally, the application containers
are started sharing the same
network setup and IP address
established by the pause container.
Now what's key here is that
Kubernetes itself doesn't directly
manage the networking details.
It delegates that responsibility
to the CNI plugin.
This allows Kubernetes to support a
wide variety of networking solutions.
Now that we understand how pods get
their IP addresses, the next question
is, How does one pod communicate
with another pod using these IPs?
Kubernetes provides a flat networking
model that ensures every pod can
communicate directly with every other
pod in the cluster as long as it knows
the IP address of the target pod.
So let's take a closer look at
how this communication happens.
Starting with pods
located in the same node.
So this example, we have two pods, pod
A and pod B running on the same node.
Each pod has its own unique IP.
Now, pod A wants to
communicate with pod B, right?
We know that when Kubernetes creates
a pod, it sets up a dedicated
network namespace for that pod.
Each pod also has its own,
namespace, which includes its
IP address and network stack.
Both the pods have been assigned
their unique IP addresses.
Now, all of these namespaces
are isolated from each other.
But they can communicate through the root
network namespace of the node, right?
So the root namespace acts as a bridge,
enabling traffic to flow between the pods.
To connect the pods to the root
namespace, Kubernetes uses virtual
Ethernet pairs, or V8 pairs.
Each pod is connected to the root
namespace with its own V8 pair.
So pod A, connects to V if X and pod B
connects to V if Y, these V pairs can
act as virtual cables, bridging the
pause network namespace of the node.
This ensures that the pods can send and
receive packets within the node, right?
And V pairs are always
created in pairs, right?
imagine.
It will be a pipe.
A pipe always has two ends, right?
A pipe cannot have one end.
So the virtual Ethernet pairs
are like pipes connecting your
virtual namespaces, virtual
network namespaces within the node.
So the journey of the packet begins
in the pod A's network namespace.
From there, the packet exits to
the, with the interface, virtual
ethernet interface, which connects
the port to its corresponding
virtual ethernet pair right with xx.
And once a packet reaches this
virtual ethernet pair, it's passed
to the root network, namespace of
the load within the root namespace.
The container bridge interface
plays a crucial role.
the CBR zero acts like a virtual
switch, which connects all the
virtual Ethernet pairs on the node.
It looks at the destination
of the packet and knows that
it has a routable interface.
VETHYY available on the same
node for the destination IP.
Once the packet reaches the VETHYY, VETH
pair, it travels into port B's namespace
and arrives at its destination interface.
No, it's zero for me.
Processes the packet as it as
if it directly came from party
without any modifications to
the source or destination.
Right?
that was easy.
Now let's look at an example where
we have multiple nodes in one, right?
we have called a and
B running on node one.
while we have pod, C and
pod B running on node two.
and in this case, pod A
wants to send data to pod C.
Okay.
pod A generates a packet
with its source IP set to 10.
0.
1.
10, which is its own IP
address, and destination IP 10.
0.
3.
10, which is the IP of pod C.
This packet exits pod A
via its zero interface.
it travels to the virtual
Ethernet pair, VEtec sets into
node's root network namespace.
Within node 1, the bridge device
recognizes the destination IP.
and figures out that it is
not local to node one and
needs to be routed externally.
The packet is now out of the
host and on the network, right?
And it reaches node 2.
In this example, we are seeing only
two nodes, but in reality there could
be hundreds of nodes in your cluster.
It is the responsibility of the CNI plugin
to ensure that the packet reaches the
correct node based on the destination IP.
So if you have ever used Amazon
EKS, you must be familiar with.
This dashboard, right?
this is a worker node of an ES cluster.
We can see that AWS keeps a notebook
of all the IP addresses assigned
to the pos running on each node.
Now a WS deploys V-V-P-C-C-N-I plugin
add-on with every EESS cluster, and it
is the only supported CNI plugin on EKS.
You can use other plugins like
Calico or Celium, but they
are not officially supported.
Coming back to our example, the packet
now reaches Node 2's network interface 8.
0.
From there, the bridge inspects
the destination IP, 10.
0.
3.
10, and forwards the packet to
the correct virtual Ethernet
pair, connected to port C.
And the packet finally reaches port C.
All right.
In the earlier slides, we saw how
Kubernetes uses a flat networking model
where every pod gets its own unique
IP address, but what happens when your
cluster grows and the IP range available
for your pods starts to run out?
This is where overlay
networks come into play.
An overlay network is a virtual
network built on top of an
existing physical network.
Think of it as a way to create
a larger logical network that
spans multiple physical machines.
Overlay networks are particularly
useful in Kubernetes when your IP
ranges, your IP address ranges for
pods is limited, but you need to
scale a cluster beyond those limits.
or if you need to isolate traffic for
security or multi tenancy purposes,
or the underlying physical network
doesn't natively support pod to pod
communication across nodes, right?
So the overlay network
encapsulates pod traffic, right?
Allowing you to traverse the physical
network as if, it were part, it were
all part of a single logical network.
Now this abstraction solves the problem
of limited IP space while enabling
communication between your pods.
the common examples of, overlay
networks, CNA plugins that support
overlay networks are flannel,
We've, Calico, Cillian, and so on.
So let's try to understand how all
the networks work through an example.
Now, in this example, again, we have two
nodes, both running two parts each and
called a wants to talk to part B or C.
Now there's, you need to notice that
there's a flannel device created in the
root namespace of every node, right?
We've, shown it through flannel zero.
So it does flannel zero.
So the packet A leaves
pod A through Vth pep.
the packet reaches the root namespace
of the node, and it hits the bridge,
the bridge device, and it realizes
that the destination IP address does
not belong to this particular node.
In this case, something
interesting happens here.
The packet is intercepted
by flannel device.
Flannel maintains a mapping of all
the pod IPs and the corresponding
nodes in the user space.
So when Flannel device sees the
destination IP, it can easily
look up in the map and realize
that pod C is running on node 2.
So with this information, what it does
is it encapsulates the packet, which
means it puts a header on top of the
packet with node 2 as the destination
address and node 1 as the source address.
So your entire original packet
is now encapsulated inside a new
packet which is created by flannel.
So flannel has now encapsulated the packet
and it is ready to leave node 1, leave
node 1 and it eventually reaches node 2.
When this packet reaches node two, it is
again intercepted by the flannel device.
The magic of encapsulation is undone here.
flannel will again look up, uh, in
this map and change the source and
destination addresses of this packet.
So the source becomes IP of pod A
and destination becomes IP of pod C.
And the packet will follow
the same path in Tilt to Perth
and eventually reach pod C.
So this is how an overlay network would
function, in a Kubernetes cluster.
In Kubernetes, we've seen that pods are
ephemeral, meaning they can change the,
they can change when pods are, pod IPs are
ephemeral, which means the IPs can change
when pods are recreated or rescheduled.
This possesses a challenge, this poses
a challenge because communication
between components using ephemeral
IPs for pods is not practical.
So Kubernetes addresses this issue of
dynamic pod IPs by introducing services.
A service acts as a stable endpoint
that abstracts and routes traffic to a
group of pods instead of a single pod.
So this ensures that the application
can communicate reliably even
when the pod IPs keep on changing.
Okay.
This slide shows a typical YAML
configuration for a Kubernetes service.
So let's break it down.
There are two important
sections to notice here.
The name in metadata is
the service identifier.
And it is used for the service discovery.
if your pod wants to talk to this
particular application, it can just
say, make a gate request to Hello
Kubernetes and Kubernetes will resolve
this name, this domain name to the
service IP address using kubernetes.
The other thing is the
selector section in inspect.
It is a list of labels that
are used to group pods.
So all pods with the label Hello
Kubernetes will be part of the service.
So how does a pod actually talk
to another pod using service IP?
Let's look at an example.
So just like before, pod A
creates a TCP packet and places
it on the virtual Ethernet there.
This time the destination is
not a pod, it is a service.
The bridge device doesn't recognize
this destination IP and the packet is
about to be sent to the default gateway.
But before it leaves the node, it
gets intercepted, but before it
leaves the node, it gets intercepted
by the IP table of the host.
So IP table is a firewall program, and
every packet that goes in or out of
your node has to go through IP tables.
of course, if you have
it installed and enabled.
Kubernetes uses IP tables to perform
something called as DNAP or destination
network address translation.
Which means that we are going to,
modify or alter the destination network
address, the destination network address.
So the destination IP in the packet
is rewritten from service IP to the
IP address of one of the backend
pods behind the service, right?
So there could be multiple pods
running, in service C, it would
pick one of them at random, right?
It does a round robin of sorts by default.
So this translation is
managed by a contract.
which tracks the connection and ensures
that the response packets from pod C
are correctly routed back to pod A.
So to pod A, it appears as though it
is communicating directly with service
IP, while in reality, Kubernetes
is, transparently redirecting the
traffic to one of the backend pods.
This abstraction allows Kubernetes to
provide load balancing while hiding
the complexity of individual pod IPs.
So with this new information, the
packet lands on eight zero and finally
moves out of node one on its way back.
it again hits the IP tables, on the
node, and you can see that the source
and destination are flipped, right?
So now the source is called C and
destination is called A, and the IP tables
is going to use contract information to
rewrite the source IP address, right?
Because the original
source, of this packet.
Is the original destination was service C.
So the packet has to
come back from service C.
This is known as SNAP, right?
Source network address translation.
So earlier, when it was going
out, we did DNAT and when it
came back, it, it did, SNAP.
finally reaches port A and
the journey is complete.
So thank you so much guys.
that was it from my end.
And if you're interested in
reading and learning more about the
networking concepts of Kubernetes,
here are some resources that I've
collected, which you can refer later.
Thank you.