Hello everyone.
I welcome you all for the
conference 42 DevSecOps 2024.
My name is Kiran Nagubandi.
I'm glad to be here to discuss
with you all about navigating
security in subscription economy.
I'll be discussing about
strategies, metrics, and
compliance for sustainable growth.
My background and experience as an
enterprise and or a solution architect
in this area really helped me to
contribute this knowledge to the industry.
This session dwells into actionable
strategies for subscription based
businesses to navigate the related
challenges effectively while
fostering innovation and growth.
Join me to explore how to stay
ahead in security and compliance.
While capitalizing on the subscription
boom, I hope to see you all enjoy the
session and walk away with some good
knowledge after this talk, some key
topics, which I'm going to be covering
or discussing in today's session are,
which are related to, an introduction
to the subscription economy while,
why security and compliance matters.
What are the regulatory
compliance essentials?
strengthening cyber security payment,
enhancing customer trust, educating
customers or consumers on the security.
And then we'll be discussing
some key takeaways at the last
and also we'll do, we'll end the
session with a small conclusion.
Let's talk about the next slide,
which is about introduction
to the subscription economy.
In the age of digitalization, many
companies are under increased pressure
to change due to product complexity,
growing customer requirements,
and digital business models.
The increasing digitalization of
processes and the products has opened
up numerous opportunities for the
companies to exploit the resulting
potential for value creation.
And the resultant is the
subscription based businesses.
Now to understand on a high level,
what is a subscription based business?
Subscription business is a new
form of business model in many
industries, which is like a, this is
a business model where customers pay
a recurring fee to access a product
or a service for a specific period.
So organizations aims to continuously
increase customer benefit.
to align the interests of
both companies and customers.
This can only be achieved by a
permanent data exchange or a database
learning about the customer behavior
and the transfer into, into continuous
innovations to increase customer value.
And all these efforts, are very
much needed and will be done, in the
subscription based business models.
And due to this fact, subscription
based businesses, helps to make
industry four times profitable what
they are making in a non traditional
model or a traditional model.
Now, if you look at the statistics.
Due to this, because of these initiatives
that companies are driving towards moving
to the subscription based businesses,
the subscription economy has grown
over by 435 percent in the last decade.
And and these are driven by shifts towards
convenient and personalized services.
If you look at the market potential,
it is expected to reach 1.
5 trillion by 2025.
Spanning industries like a SaaS or
e commerce, media and healthcare.
So it can be like a SaaS can be
like a industry like a software
as a service or e commerce.
e commerce can be like a, any subscription
based models can be included there.
But in order to, for the
companies in order to achieve
this, there are challenges too.
These are the emerging challenges.
which includes, increasing cost
consumer expectations for the data
privacy because they'll be keep on,
there will be a constant exchange of
information between the consumer and
the systems of the company who is
doing the subscription based models.
you're growing complexity in the
global regulatory compliance.
And then you're raising cybersecurity
threats with subscription platforms,
which are handing more sensitive data.
these are very much, need to be addressed
by all the companies who are moving
towards subscription based model.
so we will be going, discussing
more in detail, next slides.
Let's look at the next slide,
why, let's look at why security
and compliance matters.
Security and compliance are the pillars
of a successful subscription business.
Nowadays, the machines and plans
are connected to the internet
and they exchange large amounts
of data, which has resulted in a
critical information security risk.
Whenever there is a loss of knowledge
and control, or whenever there is a data
misuse or any kind of a manipulation of
the transactions of the production data
in the context of subscription, in the, in
the context of subscription transactions.
They are really particularly at a high
risk and complimentary to direct and
obvious consequences such as loss of
production, the attacks are increasingly
shifting to non transparents and creeping
impairments of production or product
quality, which are only apparent at a late
stage or the influencing of payment flows.
A transparent presentation of possible
risks and their scope as well as their
interrelationship does not exist.
Nowadays, on an average, approximately
62 percent of customers express privacy
concerns, and 54 percent are likely to
cancel subscriptions after a data breach.
Regulatory noncompliance has
resulted in fines exceeding 1 billion
globally in the past two years.
Benefits of prioritizing security and
compliance includes, will certainly
win the customer trust and loyalty.
And it enhances if it's already
there and then reduces the risk
of fines and reputational damages.
If you go to the next one, which is
a regulatory compliance essentials.
Regulatory compliance is the
cornerstone of subscription security.
With laws like General Data Protection
and Regulation, which is nothing
but GDPR, which is based out of
the European Union, and California
Consumer Protection Act, CCPA in the U.
S., these are basically
governing the data protection.
With 62 percent of consumers.
Expressing privacy concerns, companies
aligning with these frameworks and
the industry standards such as payment
card industry data security standards,
which is PCI DSS, is essential to
mitigate risks and build trust.
If you want to understand on a high
level, what is GDPR does, they do a,
like a data protection principles,
they deal with consent management
and then breach, notification rules.
And if you look at the CCPA, that they
are into, they deal with the transference
in the data handling, deletion
requests, and opt out rights, PCI DSS.
They are for securing handling,
secure handling of the payment
data to protect against fraud.
So the practical tips for compliance
includes regular audits and updates
to align with changing laws,
appointing a data protection officer.
Transparent privacy policies and the
consent forms will certainly mitigate
the risk of this particular, global,
regulatory compliance and essentials.
Let's talk about strengthening
the cybersecurity.
The subscription business's success
hinges on addressing critical,
security and compliance challenges.
to maintain customer trust
and protect sensitive data.
The structure of subscription
models and their different
manifestations based on their risk
vulnerabilities are characterized.
This allows, suitable cyber security
measure to be taken at every early stage.
From this basis, companies can secure
existing or planned subscription business
models, and thus strengthen the trust
of business partners and customers.
Now, how do you build
robust cyber defenses?
Now, the key cybersecurity measures
include encryption of the customer data at
rest and in transit, regular penetration
testing to identify vulnerabilities,
Use of AI driven threat detection
systems to preempt cyber attacks.
Now these data points could help
companies to consider the needed
measures like 30 percent of the reduction
in security incidents for companies
adopting AI powered defenses in 2023.
The average cost of data breach is 4.
45 million in 2023, making a
prevention as a critical investment.
these data points are not sufficient
for the companies to consider
that these are, these costs
compared to, the implementation
costs are pretty, pretty low.
So companies can really go for
it to save themselves from the
potential attacks and also improve
their goodwill among the customers.
The pro, some of the proactive steps
also include employee training to
recognize phishing and other threats.
And then also some of the things
like implementing multi factor
authentication for all access points.
Now, if you look at the securing
payments, securing payment solutions
also, they also play a pivotal role
as over 50 percent of the subscription
payments are now automated.
Supporting authentication methods
like 3d secure and adhering to the
payment card industry Data security
standards, which is PCI DSS, which I
have already discussed in my earlier
slide You know these standards ensure
both fraud prevention and a seamless
user experience Additionally providing
transparent and easy cancellation
mechanisms is not only a regulatory
necessity, but also a driver for customer
loyalty with 32 percent of subscribers
valuing hazard free cancellations.
Companies has to ensure safe
and seamless payment processing.
Key challenges in payment security
include handling auto payments
across multiple geographies,
payment preventing fraud while
maintaining a seamless user interface.
experiences.
now there are solutions where, which can
be implemented to prevent these challenges
or overcome these challenges, which is
complying with the PCI DSS to prevent
sensitive cardholder data or implement 3d
secure protocols, which add an additional
authentication layer for online payments.
You can also partner with secure payment
gateways that support fraud detection.
And also, some of the key data points
to support these solutions, which
could motivate the companies to go
with these solutions is like security
companies who are following security
payment system process or, you know,
process they, these secure systems
in today's world process over 50
percent of subscription transactions,
ensuring compliance and consumer trust.
Now, the key insight is that, in the past,
the government has been promoting the
Businesses using fraud detection reported
40 percent fewer chargebacks in 2023.
Now, if you look at the enhancing the
customer trust, they basically empower
customers with the transparency.
Now, having this will certainly,
by following these key insights,
companies can really increase
or enhance the customer trust.
suppose providing the easy cancellation
policies, improve brand, their
trust, and the compliance with the
regulatory, like CCPAs or GDPRs.
If you look at it, 72 percent of the
customers say transparent practices
influence their decisions to continue
a subscription, which itself says that
company should have their transparent
practices and processes and policies,
which will make, which will be a key
factor for retaining their customers.
Now, if you look at the transparency
in practice, they've clearly defined
terms of service and data usage
policies, provide real time updates on
subscriptions, statuses and payments.
Now, if you look at the educating
consumers are on the security now.
if you, if the companies consider
educating customers on the security
best practices such as creating strong
passwords or and then significantly
enhance overall safety, companies that
prioritize proactive customer or consumer
education have reported a 20 percent
reduction in account takeover incidents.
So you companies can empower
consumers through education, like
why we need to educate customers.
Because stronger security
factors reduce, account takeovers
and then fraud incidents.
Whoever are the empowered customer, they
are more likely to trust and stick with
the service and with the company, which
in turn increases the company's revenue.
The only steps to educate, you can follow
the things like regular email campaigns.
Or, on, on, on best security practices
like creating strong passwords or
the ways to create a strong password.
and then you have in app reminders to
enable multi factor authentications
or update payment methods securely.
All these are some of the steps to
educate the customers so that they all
will be in sync with the company's,
effort to create a secure environment.
if you look at on the high level, the,
some of the key takeaways of, of this
session includes, so companies thriving
in the subscription economy, this
session offers data driven insights
and innovative frameworks to help
businesses build secure compliant and
customer centric subscription models
that thrive in the digital economy.
Security and compliance are critical
drivers of success and consumer trust.
Adhering to regulations like GDPR,
CCPA, and PCI DSS prevents costly
fines and reputational risks.
Robust cybersecurity measures
safeguard sensitive customer
data and reduce breach incidents.
Transparent policies and easy cancellation
build long term customer loyalty.
educating customers on security creates
a safer and more trusting user database.
So on a, to conclude on this session, I
would like to say that the subscription
economy, the transforming industries,
offering convenience and value to
both consumers as well as businesses.
However, it's rapid growth brings
unique challenges in ensuring.
Data security, maintaining regulatory
compliance and fostering customer
trust by prioritizing robust cyber
security measures, adhering to global
regulations like GDPR or PCI DSS and
implementing secure payment system.
Businesses can protect sensitive
customer information while
enabling seamless user experiences.
transparency in practices such
as easy cancellation policies.
are clear data usage terms.
It's critical to build
long term customer loyalty.
Moreover, educating customers about
security, best practices empowers them
to protect their accounts, further
enhancing overall safety and trust.
Successful subscription business
not only meet these challenges, but
leverage them as opportunities to
stand out in the competitive market.
That's all I want to convey to
this group and thank you all for
attending this session today.
I hope I will, I was able to
communicate what I was, mentioning
before, and thank you all for this
opportunity and thanks to Deb Sikopsti.