Hey everyone.
Welcome to the com 42
DevSecOps 2025 conference.
Thank you for joining my session
on GitHub Advanced Security.
A lap around GitHub depend upon code,
QL and other built-in security features.
I'll start the session with a quick
introduction to DevSecOps, followed
by different GitHub security features,
starting from sharing several
repositories, security best practices.
You'll learn about secret
scanning, vulnerability scanning,
and advanced code scanning.
All available within GitHub today.
Each topic, we'll have several live
demos to illustrate how this all works.
So my name is Peter Deten, originally
from Belgium, but managed to move
to the red area, close to the
Microsoft campus almost four years
ago to continue my role as a lead
technical trainer in the West US team.
What we're doing out of the role is
helping our top larger customers across
the globe in virtual workshops learning
about Azure and in meantime, a lot
of DevOps as well as AI and co-pilot.
You got my contact details here on the
slide, and I would say don't hesitate
reaching out if you have any questions
related to the session or maybe
broader GitHub DevOps or psych DevOps.
So I think with that, let's get
started with the first section,
the what and Why of DevSecOps.
While DevOps is primarily focusing on the
collaborative culture between developers
and operations teams, the ultimate
goal is really automating everything.
Automating yourself.
Now the flow looks a bit like this.
Developers write code.
Where the code gets validated and
from there gets packaged during
what we call the build stage.
And if you automate this a bit more,
it's what we call the ci continuous
integration part of the pipelines.
From there, the application
code gets moved into what I
describe as a running state.
This could be across different
environments, dev and tests, staging,
production to ultimately get taken
over, managed by the operations team.
And again, trying to automate as much
as possible now if we follow this
stream, but now integrating security,
that's DevSecOps now where it means
that we will try and integrate as many
security capabilities as possible in
each and every stage of the cycle.
The list is getting pretty long and
obviously I'm gonna talk about some of
these features throughout my session.
Now talking about security features,
let's have a look at GitHub
repositories, security best practices.
Building applications usually starts
with source control or version control,
using, in this case, GitHub repositories.
Even on repo level, there's
already quite some security
best practices that I can share.
For example, use security policies
to guide collaborators on maintaining
code set security policies on branches,
protecting Maine as we call it.
And you can add security features on
organization and enterprise level.
Another recommendation is
using secret variables instead
of storing secrets in code.
But if you do, I got a
solution for that later on.
While not immediately security related
from a secure your code perspective,
it is recommended to provide security
documentation inside your repos.
Now, what this means is that you're
gonna add details, for example, in
the Read me Markdown, adding a code of
contact markdown, and overall adding
the contributing markdown files,
especially for open source projects.
But I could also recommend this.
For private repos if you are using
that inner sourcing concept as well.
And maybe another recommendation
here is creating that security
markdown file containing how your
project handles security overall.
It'll also show up in that navigator
menu to the right of each and every repo.
That's pretty much it for best practices.
I hope I teased your interest.
From here, I'm gonna jump into
my demo environment and walk you
through a couple of those features.
So for this first demo, I'm gonna
walk you through some of those
repository security best practices.
Now I created a sample repo that is
publicly available, so you can go in
and maybe validate some settings or copy
the code and then maybe replicating it.
In your own environment.
So I call this super original,
the com 42 DevSecOps demo repo.
Now, one of the first things that we
talked about in, in like security best
practices is probably permissions.
Now the first level is
a public people pre.
A public repo or a private repo.
So from there, I assume
that's pretty clear, but then
next we go in our settings.
And over here, since this is a public
repo, we might define who can collaborate,
who we're gonna invite, and what are
some of the other moderation options.
So if we move to collaborators,
you can see over here that it
expects like direct access.
It's a public repo, as
you can see over here.
And down here, I could explicitly
invite people who could now collaborate.
Now you could think wait a
minute, Peter, it's a public repo.
Doesn't it mean that
everyone can just contribute?
Contributing is not exactly
the same as collaborating.
So this means, for example,
they can manage repost, they can
manage permissions depending what
permissions you're gonna give them.
And then underneath
the moderation options.
I think another interesting one is
defining who can perform some code
reviews, where maybe limiting users to
read or higher access could be a good one.
So that's just mainly
the user permissions.
Another interesting one is, if I
go back to my code level, is that
as mentioned in the presentation.
GitHub is now detecting that
the branch is not protected.
So what that means is that basically
anyone with the correct permissions
obviously could now move in and not
taking security into consideration
and maybe forcing a push overriding
code, which I don't want.
Maybe deleting the repo or
changing anything else that,
again, we are not really seeing
as a good security, best practice.
So what we can do is go into
protecting the branch, and then from
there we're bumping into that rule
sets or what I call branch policies.
I got an extensive multi-year Azure DevOps
platform background, still using it.
Mainly training now on the two
platforms and somehow I still
call this branch policies.
So what we can do here is obviously,
for example, what I would recommend
is protect main, and that means
we're gonna protect the main branch.
We're not allowing any bypass, and
we're gonna identify the target branch.
Now, just a little piece
of advice here is, whoops.
You would typically do protect the
default branch, but there might
be scenarios where if you have
multiple branches, that although
the main branch should be considered
default, that's not always the case.
So that's where I would recommend
using both default branch and
including by pattern where then I
would add the main branch into it.
So from here, just adding like main
into it would be good enough if
you're wondering what the difference
is with the default branch.
Since I do have a few
here, if I go into branches
and actually from here, I go into my
branch view, this is what we need.
For any of my branches, you can
see that we can change the default.
So right now my default is up here and
it's the main branch, but nothing would
stop me to go in any of my other branches.
And then from here flagging it
and defining it as the default.
So that's where in the rule set, I
actually like the two options to not only
protect the default, but also protect,
any other branch based on the naming.
Now let me go back to those
rules and show you a few of, I
would say the common settings.
So we create a new branch rule set.
You could add tagging as well, where the
difference is that not every tag is linked
to a branch or the other way around.
So once we define the setting.
As you can see here, by default, we
have restrict deletions and block force
push, but obviously there are a whole
bunch of other options and it's not
up to me to tell you which ones you
should enable or not, because I think.
It's pretty specific, but for example
a few ones that I usually enable is
restricting creations, which means
that not just everyone can create a
new branch, which might not be exactly
following the open source mindset,
but there might be valid scenario.
And then the other one I like that
I'll talk about a little bit later
on is requiring code scanning
results and code quality results.
And another pretty cool one.
If you are already using GitHub,
copilot generative FAI is automatically
requesting a code review, and I'll
show you some outcome of that later on.
Which, by the way, if you do not use
GitHub copilot yet, it's one of those
magical tools I call them in meantime.
So I could definitely recommend
you to start looking into it.
If you have a personal GitHub account,
you can enable copilot for free.
If you have an enterprise account,
you need to talk to your business
and trying to convince them
to invest in GitHub copilot.
I would say
another option that could be pretty
useful is back in the settings,
moving into the security section
over here and selecting actions.
Inside actions, you can now create secret.
You can now create secret
environment variables.
So pretty cool.
Again, we try to avoid having any secrets
or any other strings if you want, inside
our code where you could use traditional
variables, which means they're not
protected, they're not encrypted.
But if you move them into the secret
tab here, they will be encrypted.
We're almost there with secret
recommendations, but the last one I
would recommend is creating any of
those additional files where one of the
files we would add here is the security,
and the way it works is you define it,
security MD. In here you provide best
practices for security, which probably
should be a little bit more extensive.
You commit your changes
and from here, the nice thing is that now
everyone moving just to the repo gets this
little link here to your security policy.
It's the same for the code of the conduct
and some of the other system files.
And then down here you also, whoops.
You also have the,
sorry for that.
You also have the security placeholder
over here, and again, in open source,
but inner source projects I think
it's pretty useful to have those.
So that's I would say hopefully a
pretty cool demo for over all of you.
Quick introduction to some
security best practices.
Permissions using collaborators, the
rule sets or branch policies, secret
variables, and security markdown file.
With that, I'm gonna move
on with the presentation.
Now, as mentioned earlier, a
pretty, pretty powerful feature
GitHub provides is secret scanning.
So I would say, let's have
a look what that actually is
about in this next section.
Now, as you can imagine from the title,
this feature allows you to scan your
repositories for secret strengths.
There's a pretty long list
in the GitHub documentation,
listing up all the supported.
Partners and platforms of which
secret strings are getting detected.
So you can think of AWS S3 storage
keys, Azure Access Keys, API, keys
Connection Strings, but also Broader
Secrets using SSH Keys and the like.
The GitHub documentation,
again, has a pretty long list.
I don't memorize any of them,
but I typically check them out.
And they're partly embedded
in the setup as well.
So by default, the secret
protection scans the repo.
So basically when your secret's already
in the repo, now there is an additional
setting, and I'll show you in the demo
that we call push protection, which
can be prevented uploading secrets as
part of your synchronization tasks.
And obviously avoiding that any secrets
arrive in the repo, which means you don't
really have to scan for them anymore.
And I've talked about it.
Let's say, I'm gonna jump to my next
demo here and it just because I wanna
show you actually how this works.
So for the secret scanning here,
were backend, the repo, still
in the same repo as before.
MyCom 42 DevSecOps demo.
And we're gonna enable secret scanning.
So how does it work?
We move to the security tab and down here.
Although it's the last one in the list,
I always like to start with this one,
where now we have secret scanning enabled.
You could go into
secrets and then from
here you would enable it.
Now, when you enable it, it's
gonna offer you the setting to
use the push protection as well.
And I'll show you in another
part what that means.
Now.
If I move into my code
and let me add something, little web app,
I go in my index and all the way down.
I already have a little string, but
it's not a hundred percent secret.
This is GitHub token, where if
you do anything with GitHub tokens
they have the GitHub Pat Personal
Access Token as the syntax.
Where now, if I
commit my changes.
As you can see, I'm using
copilot pretty frequently.
It's pretty convenient here
because it's already helping
me with my commit messages.
I tried to commit and now here you
can see that my secret scanning
found is GitHub personal access
token on line 35 in my code.
Now from here, we could move on with
a couple of different settings, which
I guess are pretty straightforward.
You can flag like it's a false positive.
I'm using it in a test or why
not in a demo, or it's fine.
I know that I shouldn't do this, but I'll
fix it later, which is an interesting one
to me because it's bypassing the baseline.
Of having security protection
in the first place.
So I wouldn't recommend that one, but
I can still see like maybe some of you
might look into it and even then, if you
do this, I'll fix it later, which means
the secret string will go into the repo.
I'll talk about some other
scanning mechanism later on that
allows you to still detect it.
I'm not gonna save it for now,
but I hope that makes sense.
Now you might think, okay, Peter,
you are editing files from within.
GitHub directly.
Who's actually developing
code from this view?
Maybe you might use code spaces.
Maybe you do vs code.
Maybe you do something
else on your local machine.
So what we can do, and
that's the push protection.
If I shift to my exact same view, this
is the same code, nothing's changing.
I could now try and inject.
Again, that secret string.
So I'm gonna grab it.
I have it here on the site.
I move into my index file.
I add it in my code somewhere in
any possible file, doesn't matter.
And then go in my source control.
I'm gonna sync my changes.
And as you can see here, it tells me
like, whoops, something is not working.
But now if we check the comment
output, it's telling me here whoops.
The push feature cannot contain secrets.
So instead of trying to update your
code from the repo perspective, this is
now happening before you try to push,
which I think is definitely convenient.
So that's, I would say, pretty
much it on secret scanning.
So showed you the secret
scanning, how to enable it.
Showed you the impact from the GitHub
view, little popup message, warning
you with a couple of options, and
then showing you the same from the
code view in my VS code as well.
So with that, let's move
on with the presentation.
So with that, let me move to the
next section, covering dependency and
vulnerability scanning using GitHub.
Depend Bott.
So GitHub Depend.
Bot is a built-in service for any
repost public private, which allows
for scanning repo package dependencies
and corresponding vulnerabilities.
Now, by default, it's using the cve.org
public database of already publicly known
vulnerabilities, together with obviously
GitHub advanced security patterns itself.
You can enable Pena Bot from the security
settings, and I'll show you in a demo
of that repo in basically just a couple
of seconds and after a few minutes it
starts running GitHub actions pipeline,
providing you detailed overview of any
detected vulnerabilities, listing up
the criticality, and even including a
possible fix to mitigate the problem.
And as obviously another
demo is coming up for it.
So this next one is the
depend bot code scanning.
So we move again once more to
the security tab over here and
we move to depend bot.
As you can see, once we move
into the security options, I
would enable depend about here.
And then maybe some other options
if you want to use them, is the
private vulnerability reporting.
It's not the scanning, it's
pretty obvious out of the naming,
it's the reporting itself.
So we would move in, enable,
depend bot, and from here again,
we have a whole bunch of options.
The ones that I recommend most,
and I'll show you a little bit
of that, is the dependency graph.
Then obviously within depend bot.
It's not just enabling all or nothing.
You have a lot of flexibility here.
So we would enable the depend
bot alerts, and then it tells
me like, oh, pretty cool.
We also need to enable the dependency
graphs so I don't have to worry about it.
We can define specific depend bot
rules, meaning if you don't like to
use just the ones you get from the
built in GitHub, advanced security.
You could now add your own rules.
You could focus on specific security
updates, like as part of pull requests,
you can do version updates, and then
it's gonna integrate some little
task that's called depend Bot inside
your github.com system folder.
So again, pretty flexible.
I'm not gonna walk you through
all options because we don't
really have the time for that.
But what happens from here if.
You enable, it's gonna trigger a
scanning where for now we don't see
the outcome yet, but that's where
I can switch to another demo repo.
And again, it's a public one, so
feel free to have a look into it.
It's called the bot demo.
I enabled just the exact same settings
couple of days ago, as you can see.
Where now if I move back to
security, I select the pan bot.
This task was already completed where
now it's telling me like, whoops,
Peter, in your sample code here,
you have a few security issues.
The security issue, I'm just gonna
grab one of these, is again, based
on those public CVEs together with
GitHub advisory database as well.
It usually looks into
your development package.
It is aware about any versioning
challenges or versioning issues, and in
this case, it also tells me that there
is a potential solution to move up my
package version to a later one, and that
should fix the problem here on the site.
Pretty relevant information.
What is the attack vector?
What is the complexity?
What is the severity?
And if we move down a little bit
more, we can see the C-V-E-I-D.
I'll talk about that in a second.
And down here we could also pick up the
GitHub advisory database information.
So this specific example, and
again, it's just a demo, right?
But it's related to comment, injection
in low dash, which is like a specific
package that we used for the demo.
And we can list up all the references
from different security and non-security
vendors I talked about@cve.org.
And if you've never seen that
before, let me grab this CVE number.
You can do c v.org.
In this example, which I used in
another demo couple of days ago to test.
Was searching for SQL injection,
and as you can see, it's listing
up all the 2025 security problems.
And obviously it goes all the way back
since my previous example was 2021 and
a specific number here in the sequence.
You can also find all details here,
so it's partly coming from that public
CVE database, and then maybe additional
information from the GitHub advisory.
Last part, if I switch back to my
code view and I go into insights and I
navigate to the pendency graph over here.
Since we enabled the pan bot,
remember, it tells me it'll
also enable dependency graph.
It's now not only showing me the
individual problematic package, but
it's also showing any other dependencies
where for some of you it might also
be relevant to export the sbo, and
that's gonna give you a JSO file with
all details from all your packages.
Looks a little bit weird here, but.
You can say that it's a pretty
extensive, detailed JSO file.
So pretty useful, pretty cool I would say.
And that's in short what Pena Bot was
about, at least the part that I wanted
to show you in just a couple of minutes.
So with that, let's move on
with the last part of the
presentation, talking about code ql.
Awesome.
This brings me to the last section
for this presentation detailing GitHub
code QL proprietary code security
scanning tool from GitHub itself.
Code QL tries to treat your repository
code like data, starting from creating a
database and using what I call queryable
data that you extract from your code base.
You can create your own custom queries
or rely on a set of standard queries
provided by GitHub research teams, as
well as community contributions for any
common possible development language.
Using Code ql, you can detect security
issues, coding errors, and overall
using custom que. Another cool feature
is using code QL comment line on your
development workstation, or what I'll
show you in the demo is integrating
code QL as a visual studio code
extension, which means that now your
developers, or maybe you, yourself as
a developer, can perform scanning tasks
before even merging code into the repo.
Which brings me to my last demo for
the presentation, showing you how to
set up code QL in GitHub, first of all.
And then from there I'm gonna
jump into some vs code extension
configuration settings.
And what I did here is once more
go into security, selecting code
scanning, and then here also
obviously enabling code scanning.
Now what that's doing is
actually building an actions
pipeline so we can go into code.
If you know a bit about GitHub actions
pipelines, you should know that they're
stored in the dot GitHub workflows
folder, and inside we have a code ql.
You can modify this because it's
following obviously a lot of
the traditional common pipeline.
Syntax and use cases.
So we have the on keyword, which means
it's a trigger, automatic trigger
whenever we have any of these operations.
And you can make this a lot more filtered,
not just the main branch, but any branch.
Or you could also use a schedule
task or use the workflow dispatch.
And that means it's a manual trigger.
Now in this case, again, it's
based on the built-in capability.
So it means whenever we have some PR
push-pull operations against the main
branch, we gonna run the code scanning.
Then the code scanning itself.
If it's the first time you use
it, I would heavily recommend you
to look into those details where
it's becoming part of a pipeline.
This is a separate pipeline, but in a
real world scenario, I could imagine.
That you're integrating the
syntax into your build pipeline.
When someone is committing code
out of a pr, out of the PR review,
you would run a CI built pipeline.
And part of that is obviously
validating code, like a dotnet
run.net dotnet restore.net
publish to create the artifact.
And then maybe from there, integrating
the code scanning or like in this
example, running it as a scheduled
task would also be beneficial.
Since we talked about some security
best practices, one of the things
I didn't mention, but inside your
pipeline you could actually also
define permission limitations.
So in this case, the read action
items here means that the pipeline
runs cannot change anything in code.
The actual scanning is happening a
little bit more below where Over here
we identify what is the language.
And again, code QL supports
most common languages.
So you can read through the, read me here
to identify which language you wanna scan.
And then a little bit more down,
we have the actual code actions.
So it starts with code, ql,
action, initializing it.
So that's basically recognizing the
language, the build mode, and then
a little bit further, it's running.
I'm challenged a bit with my view.
I'm gonna try and zoom in again.
Where then after the initialization,
it's running the actual code
scanning, so that's the analysis.
So nothing really different from any
other pipeline syntax, I would say.
Where then if we look into the actions
view itself, we have code QL advanced,
and then here you can see based on my
operations, like adding my security
file, it's triggering and scanning code.
If you look inside the code
itself, then there's two tasks.
Why?
Because this sample has two different
code frameworks, one for net C sharp,
another one for JavaScript, and
it's obviously looping through them.
And then inside we can see the code QL
initialized, and then performing the
analysis and then basically wrapping up.
If we look inside the code analysis,
it's gonna show you the details.
And that brings us back into
the security tab, code scanning.
And then here you can see for the
different languages what got detected.
And I just like a, I would say a clean
or a green view, which means there are
no security issues detected, but I was
assuming that it's pretty straightforward.
So you can look into the scanning results.
You can open up the.
More detailed view for any
of these running the queries.
And this is where you can see like
what code is actually getting scanned.
Now what you see here is those QLX files.
So those are the query language,
code, query code, QL query language.
And the nice thing is that although
this is all running from within the
GitHub backend, what if we wanna
move this a little bit more to
the left in the DevSecOps story.
What I'm leaning into is what
if we can move code QL to
our development workstation?
And that's exactly what we can do.
Where if I switch back to my code
application here, this is still from our
secrets, so not gonna use that anymore.
But now I can go into VS code and
installing the code QL extension.
There's also code QL command line if.
You don't have yes code or you
don't use the extensions that much.
You could do similar
tasks using command line.
So after installing the extension
and navigating to it, it's
gonna give you a few options.
Like what development
language you already know.
I'm using T net C sharp.
I'm gonna download a cloud-based, GitHub
based database, which is called the
Rest Sharp, at least for C Sharp code.
And it comes with a sample query
and I can pull up some other top 10
repositories if I would like to use that.
What I did is navigating to my
example query, and then, as you can
see here, I'm searching for a secret.
Not really, I would say
necessary, but just an example.
Where we already know
that we have that secret.
But if you don't have that secret
scanning enabled or you don't have the
push enabled, or you flag it as, I'll
fix it later, which I did in one of my
demos, you could now go I'm gonna rely
on code QL to actually detect it for me.
So from here, we're gonna run the query.
It's probably not gonna
take all that long,
and I could actually navigate to.
My previous scan in prep for the
demo, and you can see that out
of the code QL database, it's not
finding that text string 115 times.
It's detected by 115 different
prebuilt C sharp queries where all
of them recognize the secret string.
That's the main thing.
Where the cool thing is that it's
not just scanning for secrets, it's
scanning for pretty much anything.
So you could obviously do a lot
more with the code QL language.
Just wanted to bring an easy
example that's probably relatable
to any kind of scenario.
But with that, I think I'm gonna
wrap it up to make sure I'm not
running out of time too much.
But let's switch back to the presentation.
Whew.
I'm quite happy with all this, especially
because all my demos worked as expected.
Now we're close to the end of my
session where I shared information about
DevSecOps give you a set of repository
security best practices, followed by
more detailed insights on GitHub's.
Security features like secret scanning
depend about vulnerability scanning and
advanced code scanning using code ql.
All those features are part of GitHub
Advanced Security capabilities.
I hope you enjoyed learning
about GitHub security features.
As much as I enjoyed presenting on
the topic, I would like to thank
you for having joined the com 42
conference on DevSecOps and even more
so thanks for joining my session today.
Enjoy the rest of the conference
and again, don't hesitate reaching
out by email Connect on LinkedIn.
If you should have any further questions
on anything I presented on broader
DevSecOps in GitHub, in Azure DevOps,
and apart from that, I would say enjoy
the conference and have a great day.
Thank you so much.
Okay.