Hello, my name is Chandler Mayo, and
I'm a developer advocate at Doppler.
Today, I'm going to talk a little
bit about how AI is potentially
coming for your secrets.
At Doppler, we're a developer
first secrets management platform.
Usually when we think about secrets,
we're thinking about things like API
keys and certificates, and that's what we
protect for developers with our platform.
As such, we're constantly thinking
about developers needs, and AI is
one of those things that has come up
quite a bit recently, with all the
different advancements and things
that you can do with generative AI.
there's definitely a risk to
security, risking your secrets
actually being exposed, or the wrong
person, tricking an AI into revealing
something that it shouldn't do.
In tech, we usually want to
move fast and break things.
if you're too slow, your
competitor will beat you to market.
And generative AI is making that even
more complicated, because with generative
AI, companies can also iterate faster
and create things potentially faster.
but there's a risk to security when it
comes to that's often underthought out.
you want to move fast and break things,
But also it doesn't really matter if
you leak all of your customer data
because you improperly use generative AI.
Generative AI is also being used
to do things like create more
sophisticated phishing attacks.
Phishing attacks are the bane of every
security team and chances are you
probably had to go through training
and have to go through it every year
to learn how to avoid phishing attacks.
A lot of us think phishing
attacks are just something that,
your grandma would fall for.
And that's because traditionally
they've worked by just sending out
millions of emails to millions of
users and trying to get just a small
percentage of them to respond back.
But with generative AI, things are
getting a lot more complicated.
With generative AI, you could
scrape someone's profile, create a
customized email, and target them
directly and automate that across
millions of users, so your response
rate could go up significantly.
You can also automate responses
to them and make it sound
really authentic and real.
In the same space, deepfakes are
also becoming extremely concerning.
If you're able to replicate someone's
image and their voice, you can
create a really convincing story for
someone who's not suspecting that.
Like phishing attacks, ransomware
attacks are also getting more
sophisticated, thanks to generative AI.
Now, ransomware attacks can be almost
entirely automated, which means you
can do more of them at the same time.
You can also customize them to go
after individual targets better,
because different companies are
going to have different concerns,
and you can exploit that.
Another way that generative AI is leaking
information is through jailbreaking it.
A lot of companies are using AI to power
different features of their platform
unaware that those AIs can be exploited
to basically derail from their safeguards
and expose things that they shouldn't.
According to the state of security,
2020 full report from Splunk.
Generative AI adoption is
absolutely outpacing policy.
And that's not really surprising
because the technology is evolving
faster than anyone can really
think about how to use it.
But that doesn't mean that companies
shouldn't be identifying their
potential use cases, establishing
some sort of framework with ethical
principles, outlining how they want to
safeguard privacy, as well as educating
their employees on how to use AI
properly and designate accountability
for who's responsible for AI.
And then of course.
update and review the
legal side of things.
With all of these things to
consider, overreactions are often
a concern with generative AI.
Some companies have decided that
the best approach is to just not
use it at all, and as a result,
their engineering teams move slower.
They can't create tests as fast, they
can't create code as fast, but it might
be necessary depending on their industry.
But you have to face the
consequences of that.
When your competitor is using generative
AI to create stuff faster than you are.
In most countries, AI regulation is
still a patchwork because we're not
totally sure what to pay attention
to and what not to pay attention to.
But we do know that AI needs to be very
carefully used in critical systems.
The European.
Union recently passed
the European Artificial
Intelligence Act, or the AI Act.
The idea of this is to basically
leave simple uses of AI almost
completely unregulated and only
regulate it in high risk environments
and in high risk software.
This is a pretty common sense
approach, but unfortunately, it'll
have to continue to be adapted as
AI evolves and as we continue to
have other AI security concerns.
Most of the time, the government
being slow to implement it.
Embrace technology can work to
different companies advantages
by giving them time to innovate
before regulations are imposed.
But in this case, AI can
be extremely dangerous.
It could expose user information in
ways that we've never considered before.
And so it's up to individual
developers to make sure they're
implementing it responsibly
while the government catches up.
Of course, it's not just
developers who have access to
API keys and secrets and data.
So I'm going to leverage my team at
Doppler to take a look at how different
departments are leveraging AI and how
they're thinking about the security
of the AI features that they use.
Would you please introduce
yourself and your role at Doppler?
Yeah.
so I'm Amber Britton.
I'm head of go to market at Doppler.
I oversee all of marketing,
dev rel, and product growth.
I have a team of five, so a small
little team, but we're responsible
for generating traffic to Doppler, the
product at our marketing site, and then
generating signups and leads to our sales
team as well as self service customers.
How is your team using AI and how
are you as an individual using AI?
Yeah, for the team we are We're
definitely using AI to be more efficient.
Every marketer I know pretty much
is using AI in some way, so to help
get you, 70, 80 percent of the way
there for some new project, in terms,
like mostly it's pretty superficial.
Like we're using it for copy help, help in
generating copy for social or copy ideas.
But from a security standpoint,
in terms of the data it ingests.
We're very careful about what
to give it, especially being
at a company like Doppler.
We do give it, I found the most
benefit for the team is to give it data
from different sources and help with
analysis and synthesis of that data.
Things that could take days or
weeks can now be done in seconds.
So thinking of there was an example where
I took a bunch of our reviews from some
third party review sites, no identifiable
information about who gave that
review, but just the copy of it itself.
put that into GPT to look for different
themes among, among that data about
like pain points or benefits about
our product that we could then use
to distill both for the organization
to know, and then for future plans.
so that, that's the kind of data.
Occasionally, it might also give
it some metrics data on here's some
analysis on how many page views we
had or clicks we had on something
on our marketing site and over this
period of time versus this period of
time and look for these differences
or look for trends or themes or ideas.
Again, not giving it any personally
identifiable information about who did
those visits or who the users were that
contributed to those visits, but just
the data itself and help with reducing
the time it would take to do that
synthesis and analysis on your own.
It's almost like having another
team member who's Instead of having
to necessarily hire a data analyst
right now, we're getting that, the
benefit of that help or brainstorming
with a virtual team member.
In the interest of data security, what
rules do you think are most important
for your team when using generative AI?
So it's definitely important to be on
the same page about what data is allowed
to go into an AI tool and what is not.
for my team, we're very clear on
what's personally identifiable.
That's very important to us as a company.
So making sure we're not putting in,
names of organizations that use us or,
Information that could ever be traced back
to a user, not doing anything like that.
That's why when I mentioned, we'll
use high level metric data about
performance of something, but not
who contributed to that performance.
In addition to that, you also, I would
also consider something sensitive to
be about how the company is performing.
We're a private startup.
A lot of our customers
are private startups.
A lot of marketers I know
are at private startups.
your financial information about
how your company is performing
is not public knowledge.
And so anything that you don't want
basically read aloud in a courtroom,
you should not put into an AI
tool, unless you are the owner and
creator of that AI tool potentially.
so not putting in any, information about
how our company is doing financially
or, that would be essentially personally
identifiable to us and could be
something that we didn't want public
at this moment on any other small
startup would be in the same boat.
So knowing that is maybe not the same
level of what you think about it.
Like we're not putting API keys in.
That's not something that's
really relevant to my team.
Most of the time, especially not with a I.
But that other kind of data
is still a security risk.
You don't want that data getting out
where it could be used against you in
some sort of social engineering attack.
thinking about it like that, we're
constantly trying to think ahead of
those kinds of risks and make sure that
we're not putting that data in place.
and that extends to really any AI tool,
which is difficult because every tool is
now have some, now has some AI component.
so making sure that those
are properly vetted.
by whatever security team
you may have, which we have a
service that does that for us.
Great responses, Amber.
Thank you.
All right, now let's
hear from our sales team.
Would you please introduce
yourself and your role at Doppler?
Yeah, my name is Adam.
I'm the head of sales at Doppler.
We work on both pre sale and post
sale work with the customers.
So we help new prospects engage with
Doppler, evaluate if it makes sense for
their organization, and pending them
moving forward with us, we also maintain
the relationship long term, ensuring
that we help with their implementation
and their long term expansion with
us to drive revenue for the company.
How is your team using AI and how
are you as an individual using AI?
pretty narrowly.
really we do our handful, a handful of
work with, with chat, GPT, ghost writing,
copy, and then adjusting it ourselves.
But for the sake of mass, mass writing,
or trying to write in bulk, we'll
usually use chat for a handful of
drafts and then iterate from there.
another place we use it
is in our note taker.
We use a generative AI for
transcriptions, to easily write up
the, not only the summary, but also
the full transcription of the call.
And then use those recordings for faster
note taking to then post those notes
internally for company visibility.
And then personally, I use it on
a service called perplexity, which
is like chat GPT meets Google, to
allow for getting the information I'm
looking for and abstracting insights
faster through a search engine
in the interest of data security.
What rules do you think are most important
for your team when using generative AI?
Yeah, again, knowing that our team only
really works with customer data and not
anything on the back end, it's really
like how we use, how we prompt rather.
So when I talk to my team about this
is our general practice of not being
too specific to a customer when it
comes to like how we're ghostwriting
a message or something like that.
so we're not going to use like first
names or emails or anything like that
when we're writing out the customer name,
we might use the company name, just to
make sure that the prompt that we're
using has the context of the business.
But we won't, reference the
customer specifically, we
won't reference their email.
it's more so just to reference the
high level themes of their organization
and why Doppler might make sense for
them when it comes to, writing an
email or writing a draft with ChatGPT.
The goal really is just to
keep it narrow in scope.
like, when in doubt, we try and use it
for very specific niche things instead of,
having the default be to AI everything.
just with the sense of trying to keep
it easy to manage and also reduce
the potential vulnerability there.
Awesome responses, Adam.
Thank you for your time.
Now let's look into our engineering
team and see how they're using AI
and how they're doing it securely.
Would you please introduce
yourself and your role at Doppler?
I'm Nick Mnookian.
I'm the head of engineering at
Doppler and our team builds Doppler.
How is your team using AI and how
are you as an individual using AI?
Doppler is in a unique position of being
a very highly trusted security tool.
So we are very risk averse when it
comes to any security related decisions.
So one of the first things that we do
when we're proposing any addition of new
technology into our stack, generative AI
included, is Consulting our security team.
so when we engage them, they've worked
with a couple of other folks in the
security space and have recommended
against using any generative AI for
any application logic within Doppler.
And.
the engineering team has
mixed feelings on this.
this is a security recommendation
from our consultants, not a like,
official, not an official ruling,
So that's the recommendation.
We have our choice of whether
or not we want to comply.
but they make some compelling arguments
around not fully understanding the
code that you're deploying, because
there's a lot of ways a secret can leak.
One of the ways that it can leak
very easily is by accidentally
logging or otherwise disseminating
that secret from the application
that is handling it, right?
There is certainly one identity that
absolutely needs the secret, and
that's the service that's running
your production applications.
So it's really easy to accidentally log.
A network request containing
the API key that you're using.
It's really easy to accidentally
log all of the configuration values,
which would include secrets when
your application starts up and when
you're writing code by hand, you are
thinking about what that code should
be doing before you are reviewing it
to make sure that it's correct, right?
Like the process is, what do
I want the computer to do?
What do I want?
How do I want the service to behave?
Then I write the code that matches that
generative AI kind of flips the script
there when you ask it to, start, to
write a service that handles network
applications with three endpoints.
For example, it's going to thumb
all that out for you and it
determines how the service behaves,
you go back and correct it, right?
So you can imagine if you were writing
a service and you were looking at, the
startup lines, for, The examples, you
could make a decision on, Oh, do I want to
print out my environment variables or not?
And you might at that stage be like,
Oh gosh, like the environment variables
that I'm using here are sensitive, right?
I should not print those to console.
Cause they'll end up in
my logs in AWS or GCP.
But if you see the code, that's
Oh, it just says it's starting up.
And then it prints out like
some configuration values.
If you're not really thinking about what
that's doing, it's it seems correct.
And that's like a lot
of what generated AI.
I think is like Really bad at is the
things that it's, or I guess a risk of
generative AI, the things that it can't
really do still look correct somehow,
like they sound right, or they seem right.
But once you start scratching at
it a little bit, you're like, wait
a minute, this isn't, this is bad.
This doesn't work.
Or that's not actually accurate.
It just.
It just seems like it, it's
like, maybe not useful, but it's
really good at bullshitting.
like that's, that's really, that's
what it really, truly excels at.
Sounding right is like the
hallmark of generative AI.
Looking right is the
So, for that reason, our team
does not use any generative
AI for any application logic.
This includes, our core backend
services that handle secrets.
It includes, any of the like
intermediary layers, like our API routes.
and it also includes like our
front end code because those things
are actually handling secrets.
When you type a secret into the Doppler
UI, that's probably one of the most.
sensitive spots where we could
accidentally leak a value, out of
the Dom because it's so easy to make
network requests from that environment.
So we do not use it at all
in any application logic.
and I think for that reason, our
team gets less value out of it than
maybe other engineering orgs would.
The places where we do use it
occasionally is for writing tests,
boilerplate, things like that.
I do.
Use it quite frequently personally.
I think my team does as well, for
writing like one off code scripts.
Like I really don't like writing bash and
I don't know how many people really do.
but it's pretty painful to like,
look up the syntax for all the
specific things you need to do.
Like I wrote a script the other day.
That was querying a DNS
record on 15 domains.
And I was like, I want the script to
take in, a file, read it line by line.
I'm like, I know it's like an IFS
separator thing I was supposed to do.
It was so much easier to just write,
a prompt that was like, write me
a script that does this thing.
And then it writes,
it's very good at that.
And it's also really easy to review
that code and make sure that it's
doing what you expect it to do.
Because it's usually for
very simple applications.
and it's really good at that.
And then if you know the language, you can
make little adjustments and tune it up.
In the interest of data security, what
rules do you think are most important
for your team when using generative AI?
I think, somewhat obviously
the number one thing is.
Just really make sure that the code is
doing what you expect it to be doing.
it's really easier said than done.
be thoughtful around what patterns
you're introducing, like there are
practical security implications to
this, make sure the code isn't logging
secrets someplace, or make sure that
it isn't repeating a pattern that
actually has a vulnerability, right?
Something that it found on stack overflow
or has been done over and is problematic.
Yeah.
Easier said than done.
there are also practical, non security
related, but like performance things.
There, there might be a very common way
to implement something that has less than
favorable performance characteristics.
And you, it's something that you might've
known if you were writing the code,
you would have said, Oh, wow, this is
actually a lot of iterations over this
array, but if you're just accepting
it and checking it for correctness,
it's Then, yeah, it looks pretty good.
It works.
It, all the tests pass.
So I think just being very thoughtful
around the uses of generative AI in your
application logic, making sure that it
behaves how you expect it to behave in
addition to, is it correct behavior?
Also be asking, how
could this be exploited?
really put the code through
the ringer like you would for
a new developer on your team.
So as you can see, different departments
use generative AI in different
ways, but a lot of their security
concerns are similar or the same.
Considering this, it's important to
make sure that you have a company
wide AI policy that reflects the
needs of your organization at a level
that's most appropriate for you.
I hope you found this presentation
helpful and got some insights
into things you should think about
regarding AI and data security.
If you'd like to reach out to me,
please send me an email at chandler.
mayo.
edu.