Hello everyone.
Before we dive into today's
topic, let me introduce myself.
My name is Karthik Vallamsetla
and I'm a senior software engineer
with over a decade of experience in
building cutting edge web applications
and optimizing user experiences.
Throughout my career, I have specialized
in leveraging modern technologies
to solve real world problems.
particularly in the e commerce domain.
Currently, I'm working at Cisco where I
focus on creating innovative solutions
in network management technology.
In the past, I've contributed
to various impactful projects,
including enhancing user interfaces
for global e commerce platforms
and optimizing system performance
to meet dynamic consumer demand.
What excites me most about my
work is the intersection of
technology and user experience.
How the right tools and strategies
can transform a simple web
application into a seamless,
engaging experience that users love.
I'm also an active member of the tech
community, contributing to scholarly
research and sharing insights on
emerging trends in web development.
Here are the key topics
for today's presentation.
This roadmap will guide us as we dive
into each topic with plenty of examples
and actionable insights along the way.
Let's get started.
In today's session, I'm thrilled
to share insights on how modern web
APIs are transforming the way we
build and enhance web applications.
This presentation is inspired by my
experiences in the e commerce industry.
where I have witnessed firsthand
how APIs like Geolocation, Web
Notifications, and Intersection Observer
can elevate user experiences, increase
conversions, even boost revenue.
Together, we will explore how these
APIs work, why they are valuable, and
how you can leverage them to create
dynamic, interactive web applications.
By the end of this talk, You will
see how using these APIs thoughtfully
can help you bridge the gap between
web and native app functionalities
while delivering meaningful, impactful
results for businesses and users alike.
Let's begin by understanding
how web APIs have evolved.
In the early days, APIs were
simple tools used for basic
tasks like DOM manipulation.
Things like dynamically updating text.
or hiding elements.
But as web development grew more
complex, so did the capabilities of APIs.
Today, they allow us to access
advanced features like device hardware,
geolocation data, and even offline
functionality, bringing web applications
closer to native app experiences.
In a project I worked on for a
major retailer, We used modern web
APIs to provide real time inventory
updates for online shoppers.
This ensured that users always saw
accurate availability even during high
traffic sale events like Black Friday.
The results, a 15 percent
reduction in car abandonment and
a 10 percent boost in revenue.
These advancements also paved the
way for progressive web apps, also
known as PWAs, which combine the
best of web and mobile experiences.
PWAs are reliable, installable, and
incredibly engaging, making them a
key trend in modern web development.
Now let's dive into our first
API, the geolocation API.
Geolocation API allows web
applications to access a user's
location, provided they give consent.
This opens up a world of possibilities
for creating personalized,
location based experiences
that feel intuitive and useful.
Let's explore some use cases to
see their practical applications.
Helping users find nearby
stores with in stock products.
Offering location-based promotions like
discounts for in-store visits, providing
tailored recommendations such as local
event tickets or region specific products.
For an outdoor care retailer, we use the
GL location API, to provide users with
hiking care recommendations based on their
current location and the local weather.
This not only boosted engagement.
But also increased conversion rate by 20
percent as users felt the recommendations
were highly relevant to their needs.
This API is not just about
functionality, it's about creating a
connection between the user and the
experience by making it more relevant.
While the Geolocation API offers
incredible benefits, it also
comes with responsibilities.
Best practices to consider.
Always explain why you
need the user's location.
For instance, a simple message like,
We use your location to show nearby
store inventory can help opt ins by 30%.
Use encrypted connections to protect user
data and avoid storing it unnecessarily.
Provide alternatives.
like allowing users to enter
their zip code manually.
In one project, this simple addition
retained 15 percent of users who
initially denied location access.
By adhering to these practices, you
can ensure that your implementation
not only delivers value, but
also respects users trust.
Next up, in API, which is all about re
engaging users, you'll This API lets you
send notifications to users even when
they are not actually browsing your site.
It's a powerful tool for
boosting engagement and driving
traffic back to your platform.
Some e commerce use cases are sending
price drop alerts for wishlist items,
notifying users about flash sales,
Our limited time offers reminding
customers about items left in their
cart for a holiday sale campaign.
We use this API to notify users when
items on their wishlist went on sale.
The personalized approach led to a 25%
click through rate and contributed towards
incremental revenue during the season.
Notifications like these
are highly effective.
because they tap into user intent
and drive immediate action.
While notifications are effective,
they can become intrusive if overused.
Here are a few strategies for success.
Let users set preferences for the type
and frequency of notifications they
want to receive through customization.
Use analytics to send notifications
at times when users are most likely to
engage, such as lunch breaks or evenings.
Limit notifications to three
per day to prevent fatigue.
In one project, implementing frequency
caps Reduced opt out rates by 15%.
An abandoned cart notification sent
24 hours after browsing recovered
18 percent of carts, contributing
to an additional revenue in sales.
Timing and relevance are critical for
maintaining a positive user experience.
The Intersection Observer API is
all about optimizing performance
and enhancing interactivity.
Thank you.
This API tracks when elements enter
or leave the viewport, allowing
developers to trigger actions like lazy
loading images or starting animations.
For instance, we can lazy load
images for faster page load times.
Also, trigger animations as users
scroll through product categories.
For a fashion retailer, we implemented
lazy loading using this API.
It reduced page load times by 35
percent, which directly increased
mobile conversion rate by 12 percent.
Improving performance not only
enhances the user experience, but
also drives tangible business outcome.
The real power of APIs
lies in combining them.
In one project, We combined Geolocation
API to identify users near physical
stores, Web Notifications API to
alert them about in store promotions,
Intersection Observer API to animate
banners highlighting these deals.
This integration drove a 30 percent
increase in foot traffic and a
20 percent rise in local sales.
The synergy between APIs
creates experiences.
That are both functional and delightful
some challenges and their solutions
Integrating multiple apis can be
challenging browser compatibility Is a
huge consideration Use feature detection
to gracefully handle unsupported features
provide clear fallback options to
maintain usability Optimize API calls
and caching strategies should help you
with overcoming performance overhead.
By adopting modular architecture
and efficient caching, we resolved
these challenges in a global e
commerce project, ensuring consistent
performance across platforms.
Future trends.
Looking ahead, emerging APIs
will reshape e commerce.
WebXR API enable virtual showrooms
or AR based furniture placement.
Web Neural Network API
provide hyper personalized
recommendations using in browser AI.
Web USB API facilitates direct
hardware integration like label
printing for small businesses.
The future of web applications
is about seamless, intelligent,
and immersive user experience.
In conclusion, modern web APIs are
transforming the e commerce landscape
by enabling personalized, real time,
and efficient user experiences.
By implementing APIs like geolocation,
notifications, and intersection observer
thoughtfully, we can increase conversions
through targeted interactions, enhance
engagements with timely notifications,
boost revenue by optimizing performance.
Thank you for listening.
I would love to discuss any questions or
hear your thoughts on these innovations.