Hi everyone, and thank you for
joining this session today.
My name is Baskar Savan.
I work as a team lead and
full stack software engineer.
I'm also an I Triple E senior member
with the Southeastern Michigan section.
I have spent around 15 years building
and improving the develop pipelines,
automating the workflows, and
strengthening the delivery systems.
Over the last few years, my focus has been
on supply chain security and AI driven
automation, helping teams adopt SBOs
Provenance and SLSA so they can deliver
the software that is both fast and secure.
Today we are talking about the
supply chain defense by default,
SBOs, SLSA, and provenance in CICD.
This talk is focused on the practical
security, not the theoretical
framework, not the security
checklist that sit in the document.
No one really read, and
definitely not the heroic.
That depends on the individuals
remembering to do something manually.
Instead, we will look to how to build
supply chain security directly into the
pipeline so that the secure path becomes
a default path, and the developers are
not slowed down by the security controls.
Security becomes a natural
outcome of the way system works.
The landscape of the software security
has shifted dramatically 10 years ago.
Attackers focus mainly on the application
level issues, SQ injection, cross
script scripting con misconfiguration,
but today they are going upstream and
attacking the software supply chain.
They're targeting open
source dependencies.
Package managers, CICD building
systems, artifact repositories.
And the automation that ships
code into the production.
Modern day pipelines move fast, which
is good, but fast pipeline that lacks
transparency or verification can become
the blind spot, and attackers loves
blind spots in many organizations.
CICD becomes the most trusted system,
but ironically, least verified.
Recent incident shows us why the
supply security chain is urgent.
Solar Wind scale wasn't an application.
It was the build system
itself being compromised.
Log four J wasn't a failure
of application code.
It was a failure of visibility
into the dependencies.
And the XZ backdoor showed us
that even a long term open source
maintainers can become attack vectors.
These are not isolated cases.
They are part of the pattern.
All of them teach the same lesson.
If you can't see what your software
supply chain, you can't secure it.
Security teams were blind spot blindsided,
not because the vulnerabilities were
impossible to address, but because they
lacked visibility, traceability, and the
proof of where the software came from.
So what does defense by default means?
It means building security into the
pipeline so deeply that developers
don't have to think about it.
Security is not a separate process, not
a afterthought, not a manual approval.
It's simply how the pipeline operates.
Every bill automatically
generates the evidence which
needed every artifact carried.
The metadata that proves is trustworthy.
Even a deployment is verified by the
platform itself, not by the person.
When the security is by default, it
becomes the consistent, predictable,
and scalable, and the developers can
stay focused on building not policy.
ASBOs software build off materials
are one of the most effective
tool in the supply chain defense.
They are basically ingredient list
for your application that tells you
exactly what's inside your core base.
But here is the important
part, and ASBOs only works if
it's generated automatically.
On every build and stored with the
artifact when vulnerability hits log
four J, you shouldn't have to scramble.
You should be able to instantly
answer are we affected?
Where are we affected?
Which versions are impacted?
Organizations that had the s om
generally generator automatically
handles the four J law, four J in our
organization without SBOs pen dates.
Even some weeks just
figuring out where to start.
This is why the SBO M aren't
just paperwork, they're
operationally lifesaving.
Provenance answered the critical question.
Can we prove how the software was built?
It's a full chain of
custody of an artifact.
Who builds it when it was built?
What source code is used,
what pipeline executed it, and
what environment it ran on.
Attestation are simply the
sign proof of this information.
This stops attacks.
Someone insert inserting a
malicious image into the registry.
A developer pushing a local bill
by accident, or the compromised ci
runner injecting something harmful.
If provenance is missing or incorrect,
the artifact should not be deployable.
And that's not something
human should decide.
It should be automated and
enforced by the system.
The SLSA framework
gives us a path forward.
You don't need to start
at the highest level.
You start where you are
and match your over time.
You begin by ensuring
the bli bills are logged.
Then you ensure bills run from
the version control scripts.
Then you add provenance, sign
signing, and eventually you
reach the ame reproducible bill.
SLSA is not about perfection.
It's about making each link
in a supply chain stronger.
Even small improvements
make a big difference.
Once we begin strengthening the pipeline,
several important controls comes
into play first, keyless assigning CI
pipeline, gender temporarily identities.
Instead of re relying, replying,
relying on a stored private keys.
Imperial Runners built environments
are de destroyed after each run to
reduce the long term compromise.
Immutable artifacts once published
artifacts cannot be si silently, swt,
or replaced deployment and verification.
The platform checks signatures and
prominence before allowing the deployment.
This means the system, not the
humans validates trust, and that's
the only scalable way to secure
the modern delivery pipeline.
Run in isolation with no network
access and no ability to face the
unknown dependencies during the build.
They rely on a pre-approved
PIN components.
Reproduceable Bills ensures that the same
input always produce the same output.
This lets us detect the
tampering instantly.
Together.
This approach transform your
pipeline from open work shop into
the control environment where every
input and output can be verified.
Dependency hygiene might sound
simple, but is one of the most
impactful thing you can do.
It means pinning versions, reviewing
all new libraries, avoiding
floating dependency versions,
and preventing automated updates
from bypassing security review.
This keeps the unverified code
from sneaking in silently.
One of the most common way attackers
get into the supply chain code
dependency hygiene creates the
stability and predictability.
Let me share the practical example.
That shows how powerful
these practices can be.
Before implementing the supply chain
defense, one team was deploying the
microservices to the Kubernetes.
Their pipeline was fast, but not verified.
Deployers could push local
images into the registry.
ASBOs were inconsistent, and
Providence wasn't enforced.
When the log four J Crisis hits,
it took almost a full week just
to locate the affected services.
Now let's look at the after.
Once they adopted the supply
chain defense, by default, every
bill was signed automatically.
Every artifact produced the
SBOs Bernet enforced signature
verification and dependency.
Metadata was centralized.
Later during the simul simulated
vulnerabilities event, they identify
all the impacted services in a minute.
What's beautiful about this
is that security improved,
but velocity didn't drop.
Pipeline becomes safer
without becoming slower.
That's the ideal balance.
Deployment is a movement
where the risk become real.
Everything before deployment
is a hypothetical.
Risk deployment is the point of no return.
This is why the deployment,
time enforcement is.
If the artifact lacks the valid
signature or provenance deployment
should simply fail, not with
an email, not with a warning.
Just hard stop.
This prevents the accidental deployments,
malicious insert, and unapproved builds.
Think of it as a last checkpoint, the
final quality gate before the production.
One.
One of the biggest misconception is
that the supply chain defense requires
a massive all at once transformation.
It isn't.
You start small, begin by
generating SPO automatically.
Then add signing and provenance in ci.
Verification in staging, and
once the process is stable,
enforce it in the production.
This phased approach, the delivery
smooth and builds organizational.
Let me add one more important
piece that often gets overlooked.
The cultural shift.
Supply chain security is not just about
tooling problem, it's a mindset shift.
Teams need to move from, we trust
our pipeline to our pipeline.
Pers it can be trusted.
They need to move from.
We hope our dependencies are safe
to, we know exactly what we are
shipping and they need to move.
Move on from security
slows us down to security.
Done right, speed up.
By preventing the emergencies, the real
transformation happens when developers
develop engineers and the security
team all see supply chain defense as
a shared advantage, not an optical.
When the shift happens, adoption
becomes smooth and natural.
Here are the few key
takeaways from our discussion.
First, the software supply chain
has be, become one of the most
active cybersecurity battle work.
Battlegrounds attackers are targeting
dependencies, build systems, and
automation, not just the production apps.
So if we don't secure the pipeline,
we can't secure words comes out of it.
Second, the strongest defense
is the shifting security
into the CICD process system.
Ev when every artifact is signed,
stress able and verified automatically,
we reduce this risk without
slowing down the delivery pipeline.
Trust become the application trust.
Third, the tools and the practices
were dis, were discussed.
As bombs, ance attestation, SLS,
AMIC bills and the deploy time
verification are not theoretical.
They are practical adopt steps,
adoptable steps that any organization
can start implementing in phases.
And finally, remember this security
should not depend on a late
night heroics or manual checks.
It should be the default outcome
of how we build the software
when we design the pipeline that
enforce the security automatically.
We protect our systems and empower our
teams to innovate with the confidence.
Before I close, I want
you to leave with this.
Security shouldn't depend on the
people remembering the steps.
It should be the build into the pipeline.
So every release is trusted by default.
If we can make supply chain
security automatic, we make our
team faster, safer, and more
resilient without slowing innovation.
Thank you all for your
time and attention today.
If you have any question, you
can reach me on my LinkedIn id.
Thank you.