Hello everyone.
I'm Nagarjuna Malladi.
Today, I'm going to talk about the
multi faceted landscaping of Site
Reliability Engineering, SRE, a deep
dive into expertise specific concepts.
We'll discuss about
these, table of contents.
You can review them once.
Let's go into, introduction to SRE.
So Site Reliability Engineering SRE
is a discipline that merges software
engineering with IT operations.
It emphasizes the primary goal
of ensuring system reliability,
performance, and scalability, especially
as system grows in complexity.
SRE originated at Google and
integrates engineering practices
with operational responsibilities.
SRE is a relatively new field
that has gained prominence,
especially in the tech industry.
It recognizes the need to address
the challenges of managing complex
systems in modern dynamic environments.
SRE, I can tell key goals of the SRE.
Enhancing system
availability and reliability.
Thank you.
Ensuring that services function
reliably and are available to users
and automatic operational tasks
just to reduce the manual errors
and make things more reliable.
Efficiently managing system failures.
By reducing recovery time, thereby
minimizing service disruptions.
So these goals showcase the
proactive nature of SRE.
It's not just about reacting
to the failures, but also about
preventing them and ensuring
systems are robust and resilient.
So cloud native infrastructure platforms.
It's introduced the concept of cloud
native infrastructure, highlighting
industry leading cloud services providers,
such as AWS, Azure, GCP, and OCI.
These platforms offer scalable
and flexible computing resources.
Cloud computing has revolutionized
how organizations manage
infrastructure, providing on demand
resources and scaling capabilities.
Code technologies in SRE.
Infrastructure as a code.
Tools like Terraform allow for
a consistent infrastructure
provisioning and management.
Serverless computing platforms,
AWS, Lambda, Azure Functions, GCP,
Cloud Functions, enable running
code without managing servers.
Containers orchestration systems like
Kubernetes, ECS, AKS, manage and scale
containerized applications efficiently.
Cloud native security solutions
ensure secure access and data
production in the cloud environment.
These technologies are pivotal in
modern software architecture, enabling
dynamic and scalable infrastructure
with enhanced security measures.
Let's discuss about networking in SRE.
Designing resilient network topologies
with redundant and low latency.
Performance monitoring, like
tracking metrics like latency,
throughput, and jitter using machine
learning for anomaly detection.
Network security, employing firewalls,
IDS, IPS, VPNs, and zero trust
architectures to safeguard the network.
DNS and CDNS, optimizing domain
name resolution and content
delivery to reduce latency.
Networking is the backbone
of any distributed system.
Efficient network design and performance
monitoring are crucial for ensuring
reliable and responsive applications.
Let's go to database.
Database management and reliability.
High availability through replication
ensures continuous access.
Disaster recovery mechanism, including
backups, geographic distribution,
safeguard against data loss.
Think about, some natural disaster
happening in any area, and, having a
disaster recovery, for those data centers.
How important is for the, clients,
customers, and everyone like company,
having this disaster recovery of data.
performance optimization, techniques,
that improve query efficiency and
implement caching, mechanisms.
Security measures, product data,
employing encryption, access
control, and data masking.
Comparison of NoSQL and
relational databases highlights
their respective advantages.
Thank you.
Databases are critical
assets for any application.
Ensuring their reliability,
performance, and security is essential
to maintain system integrity.
I can spend a lot of time,
explaining only on this slide.
It has so much data there.
in the event of time, I'm
going for other slide.
Observability and monitoring.
Metric collections.
Capture resource utilization,
latency, and error rates.
Centralized logging tools like
Elkstack, Splunk, Aggregate
logs for in depth analysis.
And now clouds are doing
their own open search.
and that's for the same reason.
Distributed tracing assets in
tracking request flow using
tools such as Jagger and Zipkin.
Electing systems leverage dynamic
thresholds and anomaly detection
to trigger notifications.
And then by using of machine learning and
AI, this can Find the pattern also, at
what time the system is going high CPU,
at what time the system having more load,
that kind of good information we can get.
And Matrix framework establishes
SLIs, SLOs, and SLAs for quantifying
and managing reliability.
Observability tools enable SRE teams
to detect and resolve issues promptly,
ensuring efficient system management.
Let's go to automation and DevOps.
It's one of my favorite topic, CI,
CD pipelines for automated testing
and deployment using Jenkins,
GitLab, CI, and GitHub actions.
Configuration management tools
like Ansible, Puppet, Chef,
ensure consistent environment.
Scripting languages like Python,
Bash, PowerShell automate
repetitive tasks and checks.
Incident response automation
focuses on self healing systems
to minimize mean time to recover.
Chavos engineering introduced controlled
failures to test system robustness.
Service level management sets
targets SLOs and agreements SLAs
for reliability measurement.
Capacity planning utilizes ML and trend
analysis to predict resource requirements.
Automation streamlines processes
allowing SRE teams to manage
complex systems efficiently.
Chavos engineering might seem
counterintuitive, but it's a
proactive way to test system
limits and enhance resilience.
Let's see some advanced topics.
Chavos engineering
It's a practice of introducing
controlled failures is further
emphasized with tools like Chavos Monkey.
Error budgets allows team to allocate risk
and balance stability with innovation.
Capacity planning techniques
employ machine learning to
forecast resource needs accurately.
These advanced concepts showcase the
strategic thinking involved in SRE.
It's about staying ahead of potential
issues and optimizing system capabilities.
Industry specific SRE considerations,
financial services, emphasize
security, regulatory, compliance,
and handling with the High frequency
transactions, e commerce, focus on
massive scalability demands, especially
during peak times and fraud prevention.
Healthcare, prioritize data
privacy, ensure interoperability and
manage life critical applications.
SRE adaptability allows teams to tailor
strategies to introduce strategies
to industry specific needs, ensuring
systems are reliable and compellent.
Think about financial services,
financial companies, JP Morgan, and a
lot of banks, Capital One, Citibank.
See, how important, for them, the
security and, having, high frequent,
transactions, how important to make
their system always up and, running.
And think about, e commerce,
in the black Friday, the load
on the, e commerce, systems.
Amazon, Walmart, like you think
about anything like Apple's,
Samsung's, like mobile phones.
So there's so much load on these systems.
And then, if they're down for some
time, the companies, have a huge loss.
And then, a lot of, Folks try to do fraud
also at this time and then we need to
prevent those transactions as SREs and
then Think about data health care and
how critical it is with a lot of viruses
and all you know, how critical the Trials
are, the companies that do Lily, Leap,
Pfizer and a lot of healthcare, Merck's.
they are like very important
and then, trials and keeping
patient's data, secured.
Yeah, other than regular information,
doctors also cannot see all the patient
information, because of this HIPAA rules.
So that's important.
That's how it's very important
in the healthcare industry.
Let's, conclude.
So in conclusion, this, encapsulates
the essence of SRE emphasizing its
value in achieving reliable, scalable,
and efficient systems by harnessing
automation, observability, and
robust incident response practices.
Organizations can manage
complex infrastructure.
The adoption of cloud native
technologies and CICD pipelines
enhances SRE effectiveness.
SRE has become an indispensable aspect
of managing modern software systems.
It integrates engineering
principles with operational best
practices, ensuring organizations
can scale their services reliably.
if you have any questions, if you need
any suggestions, you can reach out to me.
You can search my name on the LinkedIn,
Nagarjuna Malladi, and you can find me.
And, you can send me a note.
I can be able to answer if you
have any questions or if you need
any recommendations in terms of
site reliability engineering.
Thank you very much.