Hello everyone.
Pratish and I are excited to welcome
you to our talk on healthcare
chatbots and explainable AI.
Today we'll delve into the evolving role
of healthcare chatbots, the integration
of generative AI capabilities, and the
critical importance of explainable AI.
We'll explore their current impact,
future potential, and how they are
transforming the healthcare landscape.
Towards the end.
We'll also discuss the challenges
these technologies face and potential
strategies for their broader adoption.
Today's agenda is as
displayed on the screen.
We hope you'll enjoy this talk.
Over to Radhesh.
Thanks, Abhishek.
Let's begin with how AI powered
chatbots are transforming healthcare
by addressing accessibility, cost,
and personalization challenges.
AI chatbots alleviate geographical
and scheduling barriers, ensuring
24 7 support for patients.
They provide personalized care
by adapting to individual patient
data, enhancing engagement.
And they also streamline
processes like symptom checking
and chronic disease management,
making healthcare more efficient.
These capabilities set
the stage for how chatbots
revolutionize healthcare delivery.
Expanding on the need for 24X's
ability, one of the primary benefits
of AI chatbots is their ability to
provide round the clock support.
Unlike traditional systems, limited
by office hours, chatbots are
always available to guide patients
or escalate care when necessary.
They also support chronic condition
management through continuous
monitoring and reminders.
Triage ing symptoms quickly saves time
and provides healthcare providers with
tools they can use to identify care.
A great example could be, imagine a
diabetic patient receiving a reminder
to check their blood sugar if there
is a glucose spike or a drop, so that
the chatbot can ensure the signal can
be captured for appropriate treatment.
This brings us to how Genitive AI
is changing healthcare chatbots.
Genitive AI takes healthcare chatbots
to the next level by making interactions
more dynamic and patient specific.
These chatbots deliver contextual
responses, enhancing the user experience.
They simplify medical jargon
into patient friendly language,
improving clarity and engagement.
This personalization builds trust
and ensures patients feel understood.
One of the key elements in chatbots
is their ability to retain what
has been already discussed.
Has it happened many times to us that
repeating ourselves to different doctors
tend to frustrate us over and over again?
AI chatbots, due to their vast context
retention, aim to eliminate that and
have a coherent patient history while
talking to them, remembering most of the
things that they have asked the chatbots
to remember or stress the importance on.
Context retention ensures
chatbots remember past interaction
and provide continuity.
This enhances trust, reduces
frustrations, and also speeds up support.
Another key element.
In chatbots is the amount of
memory the chatbots can retain.
AI chatbots don't just assist
patients, they also evolve over time.
Using deep learning and reinforcement
learning, they refine their
interactions for better accuracy.
Technologies like Knowledge
Graph help them contextualize
medical data effectively.
This continuous learning ensures the
chatbot improves with every interaction.
This brings us to one of the
core topics of our discussion
today, which is explainable AI.
In healthcare, blind
trust in AI isn't enough.
Patients need to understand
why and how decisions about
their health are being made.
While the benefits are immense, we
must also acknowledge that we need
to address the ethical challenges.
Explainable AI intends to
transform the black box into
transparent medical assistance.
Transparency ensures patients know
that they are interacting with AI.
Healthcare professionals also need to
verify the logic used for the decision.
or the recommendations made
by the healthcare jackpot.
Healthcare AI can also get help from
explainable AI to meet regulatory
and compliance standards set by
governments and institutions.
To the patients, it's also beneficial
because it can, again, just like
explaining it to the healthcare
providers, give tools to validate the
logic while remaining in compliance.
Let us now look at how we can actually
achieve this transparency through some
of the specific explainable AI methods.
Explainable AI methods broadly fall
into two categories, the model agnostic
ones and the model specific ones.
Some of the model agnostic ones are
discussed here, such as line, Okay.
which tries to explain responses
through approximations useful for
explaining complex decision making.
SHAP, where each input feature gets an
importance value, or the counterfactual
method, which is a classic way of
assessing the what if scenarios.
All of these methods have been widely used
across machine learning and AI systems
to interpret and explain ML models.
Let's now look at some of the
more model specific methods.
Some of these methods might seem familiar
to those who come from a machine learning
background, such as decision trees.
or feature importance analysis.
They have a lot of things in common where
decision trees, just like in traditional
methods, can create feature importances
that can be interpreted for future use.
Model specific methods can help
understand how each feature
contributes to the outcome and can
be communicated to the healthcare
professionals providing that care.
Feature analysis uses each input feature
and assigns an importance value to it.
Whereas layer wise propagations,
such as used in clinical trials,
The convolution neural networks
or traditional neural networks can
help give the same information.
I'll hand it over to Abhishek
now to talk about more on the
data engineering side of things.
Thank you, Rathesh.
Behind every effective AI chatbot is
a solid data engineering framework.
Robust data engineering ensures clean,
reliable, and scalable pipelines
that drive chatbot algorithms.
These pipelines enable real time
data ingestion, storage, and
processing, which is critical for
immediate and accurate responses.
Seamless integration of diverse
data sources to support personalized
and context aware interactions.
The key components include ETL
pipelines, data lakes to store
diverse data sets, both structured and
unstructured, such as medical images,
patient notes, and device readings.
Also, data warehouses enable fast
querying and reporting, helping
healthcare providers quickly retrieve
insights for decision making.
Now let's dive into the architecture
that powers these chatbots.
The workflow consists of several
interconnected components, starting
with data sources, which store patient
records, IoT devices like wearables,
and medical knowledge graphs from
the backbone of the data feeding into
chatbots, batch processing, such as
daily updates, ensuring data consistency,
while real time streaming also allows
chatbots to respond instantly to events
like a patient's abnormal heart rate.
After data pipeline is set up, we use
the data for AI model training, enabling
chatbots to deliver personalized and
mathematically sound interactions.
Finally, chatbots integrate with
mobile apps or web platforms, offering
patients easy access anytime, anywhere.
While these technologies offer
incredible potential, they also
raise important ethical questions.
Given the sensitivity of Healthcare data,
secure storage and secure transmission are
paramount to maintaining patient trust.
Patients must know they're interacting
with AI and give informed consent
for how their data is used.
AI models must be trained on diverse data
sets to avoid biases that could lead to
inaccurate or unsafe recommendations.
AI should complement, not replace,
human healthcare providers.
The goal is to enhance care
while retaining the human touch.
Now, I will hand it back to
Ratesh for closing comments.
Thanks, Abhishek.
Of course, no technology
is without its challenges.
Running AI systems is already a complex
task, and add to it explainable AI
and the requirement goes even higher.
We need to address technical
reliability, operational training,
and ethical guidelines likewise.
Clear regulations on privacy and consent
are essential for widespread adoption.
Guidelines like HIPAA needs to
be followed strictly, as well as
clinical validation and integration
is needed for a widespread adoption.
Thank you so much for listening
to our talk and I hope you
have a great rest of your day.