Hello, friends.
thanks for joining my talk.
let's see how we can master
Kubernetes, security.
I'm Deepu K.
Shashidharan.
I'm a staff developer advocate at Okta.
I'm also an open source, enthusiast
and a polycloud developer.
I co lead the Jhipster project.
I have built a Kubernetes
dashboard called Kdash.
you can, find out more about
me on my website, deepu.
tech, or you can find me
on BlueSky at, deepu105.
So let's, get into the talk.
So before we talk about, security best
practices in Kubernetes, I think it
is important for us to have a basic
understanding of Kubernetes security.
Like any other complex piece of software,
security in Kubernetes is multifold.
So it can be broadly
categorized into four layers.
so first we have, the transport layer
security, which is insured using, TLS.
So all a p communication is done via
TLS using valid certificates that
forms the base layer of security.
Then we have the authentication layer,
and there is a flexible authentication
layer with multiple supported mechanisms,
including open id, connect, token
based authentication, and so on.
So all a PA requests are
authenticated with one of these,
several authentication mechanism.
Then we have the authorization layer.
And, again, all authenticated requests
are authorized using one or more of
the supported, authorization models.
We'll talk a little bit
more about this, later on.
And finally, we also have a possibility
of adding custom admission control
modules to further lockdown access.
which means all authorized requests,
except read and get requests, are also
validated by admission control modules.
So Kubernetes comes with many security
options out of the box, but to bulletproof
your infrastructure, you need to consider
many more security best practices.
Today, we look into some of the
vital security best practices.
You can also find a blog post
from me, with this content
on the link provided here.
Most of the security best practices,
are not enabled by default.
So you would have to do this yourself.
And, most of these, are
extremely important.
So let's, get in and see what they are.
first and foremost would be using RBAC.
Kubernetes supports multiple,
authorization models for its, API server.
so we have, ABAC or Attribute
Based Access Control.
We have RBAC or Role Based Access Control.
We have Node Authorization and Web Mode.
out of all these, RBAC, I would
say, is the, most, secure option.
It's also the most widely used, option
and it is ideal for enterprises and
large to, medium to large organizations.
So with the role based access
control, you can define, a control
structure that closely resembles
your organization's business rules
or access structure that you have.
based on business, rules.
So RBAC also works great with, OIDC
authentication, and it is easier to
manage if you have, an OIDC provider.
RBAC makes it easier as well.
using RBAC would be the number
one, security best practice.
So most Kubernetes distributions
have RBAC enabled by default.
So you can check this by running
the kubectl command, kubectl cluster
info dump, and then look for the
authorization mode, in the output.
ideally, it should show
authorization mode equals RBAC.
if not, you can enable it
using the, authorization mode
flag for the API server, while
creating or patching the cluster.
For example, setting the authorization
mode, flag to RBAC comma node
will enable both RBAC and node
authorization on the cluster.
Once RBAC is enabled, you can
create, roles, and, role bindings
for either, role or cluster role, or
role binding or cluster role binding
to control access to your resources.
Here's an example of a role
and role binding that lets
users view ports and services.
I would recommend checking out
the Kubernetes documentation on
our back for, for the learning.
this is a very simple ex, example.
You can do much more with,
role and, role bindings.
you can, control, who has access
to what, on a namespace, level or
at the resource level, for example.
So next security best practice would be
to use OpenID Connect for authentication.
So Kubernetes supports many
authentication mechanisms.
Some of the most common ones are
like client certificate based
authentication, basic authentication,
token based like service account
tokens, bearer tokens, and so on,
proxy based authentication, and finally
OpenID Connect based authentication.
So out of all these authentication
mechanisms, OpenID Connect or OIDC is
the most secure and scalable solution.
So it is ideal for clusters accessed
by large teams as it provides a single
sign on solution for all users and makes
it easy to onboard and offboard users.
It is also way more secure than
other mechanisms as you don't
have to store any sensitive
information on a user's computer,
like client secrets and passwords.
You can also use, advanced features like
multifactor authentication, pass keys,
hardware, tokens, like UB keys, et cetera,
as most of IDC providers would be, might
be supporting, these features as well.
and YDC with R Bag gives you powerful
access control that can be managed in,
Identity systems like Auth0 or Okta.
for example, if you are using,
OpenID Connect along with, Okta, or
Auth0, for your Kubernetes cluster,
you might, you will be able to use
all the advanced security features
provided by these platforms.
You would be able to configure, and
manage users in these systems instead of,
meddling with the Kubernetes installation.
You'll be able to manage your
RBAC setup, with these platforms.
So it gives you a lot more flexibility
and it is ideal for larger teams.
Here is how UIDC works with communities.
When you run a command with, cube, CTL, it
uses, cube login, and opens a browser to
authenticate you with your OIDC provider.
once, you authenticate, with your YDC
provider, let's say, or zero in this case,
you will get, authentication response, and
the odd response, the, the cube login will
get no author response, from the browser.
It'll then use that, response to make
a token request to your application
server to get a access token.
And then it'll use that, it'll
pass that access token to Cube CTL,
which can use that token to make,
a PA requests here Banes cluster.
This makes the entire, setup extremely
secure and, easy to, control.
If you are interested in setting
this up, you can check out this blog
post that I wrote some while ago.
It shows how to set up OpenID
Connect on a Kubernetes cluster
and how to use Okta to manage this.
one of the most often overlooked aspects
of security in Kubernetes is secrets.
And that's why, next best practice
would be to use secure secrets.
So many don't set up proper
secret management and end up
using stock Kubernetes secrets,
which are not technically secrets.
because, the default Kubernetes
secret is nothing but, plain text,
resource, with, base64 encoded strings.
And base64 encoded is
not same as encrypted.
So your secrets are in plain text
and anyone, can, decode base64.
And you don't need any, private
keys or anything to decode base64,
because it's not encrypted.
which means you can't store them in your
version control, making GitOps difficult.
And you will end up resorting
to environmental variables and
stuff like that, unnecessarily
complicating your setup.
Even worse would be accidental commit
of secret definitions, along with
Kubernetes manifest to public Git
repos in case of open source software
or source available, projects.
And other disadvantages are that
Kubernetes secrets does not work
with external secret managers.
we have, multiple options,
here, to work around this issue.
one of the option would be
to use a sealed secrets.
sealed secrets are simplest to use as
it, encrypts, the secrets on developer
machine, which can be decrypted only
by the cluster when it, will be used.
This makes it possible to store, the
secrets along with other data in your
version control as they are encrypted.
This is ideal for smaller
setups and smaller teams.
Here is how it will work.
So you deploy a seal secret, controller.
In your, cluster, the controller
generates a private public key pair.
the developer, has access to,
developer can get the public key out
of, this, generally extracted out.
the private key is kept,
secret and, you should, have
proper RBAC on this, resources.
So that's not exposed.
the developer then uses
the public key extracted.
from the cluster to encrypt
any sensitive, data, in their
machine using the kubeseal CLI.
for example, if you have a secret YAML,
you can, encrypt that using this public
key and make it into seal secret, YAML.
the encrypted sealed secret
resource can now be committed
and deployed to the server.
to the cluster.
the sealed secret controller.
so when you, this is where you
will put it in the git repository.
It is safe because it is encrypted now.
when you apply or deploy
this to your cluster.
the sealed secret controller will,
scan for any sealed secrets and when it
detects one, it will use the private key,
stored on the sealed secret controller
to decrypt the sealed secret and it
will create a normal Kubernetes secret
with the, basics differ encoded, secret.
It's simple and effective mechanism.
Of course, you would still need RBAC to
restrict access to the created Kubernetes
secrets on the cluster and so on.
But at least this solves the
issue of not being able to
commit your Git repo and so on.
So at least until it reaches the
cluster, everything is encrypted.
So this is simpler to set up and
this will work fine for smaller
teams and for smaller projects.
for bigger teams and projects, a better
solution is to use external secret
operator, secrets operator, or ESO.
So ESO lets you use external secret
managers like Hershey Cobb Vault, Google
or AWS secret managers, Azure so on.
So it can keep secrets synced with
the external manager and provide
support for most of the well
known external secret managers.
It's a bit more tedious to set up than
seal secrets, but it is worth for it, for
the security and flexibility it offers.
And this is also ideal for, bigger teams
as, seal secret requires individual
developers to use the CLI to, create
the encrypted, seal secret and so on.
and, yeah, and it's not that
scalable, whereas, external secret
operator, have more flexibility.
Let's see how it works.
you deploy the, external secrets operator
on the cluster and, you, will generally
create a secret store to define external
secret managers, connection details,
like how you can connect to this and so
on, or what mechanism you will connect
to the external secret store and so on.
Stuff like that.
you will, you can now create your
secrets in, in the external service,
like for example, Vault, for example.
now you create an external secret
resource, yaml file basically that
defines what secrets to fetch from Vault.
You won't define any sensitive data
here, you'll only define which data to
fetch from your external secret manager.
this can, so this files can be
committed to git as it does not
have any sensitive information.
So you can commit them
freely in git repose.
and when you deploy this to the
cluster, the external secrets, so
when you deploy this, the external
secret operator will be watching for
any external secrets on the cluster.
And it will, once it gets that, it will
use the secret source information and it
will fetch the appropriate, sensitive data
from your external, secret manager vault.
And it will create a normal
Kubernetes secret on the,
cluster for the pods to access.
again, you would have to define
RBAC and, so on to secure this.
Because in the end, both these options
still use kubernetes secret and it
has the same issues as kubernetes
secret being, base64 encoded string.
But at least this is quite secure on
the, secure outside the cluster, like
putting it in a git repository and so on.
this is a good option for bigger
teams, and it's easier to manage
secrets in a vault, setup like
an external secret manager, so it
gives you much more flexibility.
Of course, you would still, you have to
use RBAC and all other best practices
here, but it's a better option compared
to sealed secrets or regular secrets.
Another option is to use,
secret Store CSI driver.
It's a native Kubernetes driver
and it lets you use, external
secret managers, similar to ESO.
so you can use Hashi wall, Google, AWS,
secret managers keywords and so on.
so it uses a platform
authentication mechanism.
it can also keep secret synced
with external manager and
supports rotation and so on.
it has providers for most of the
well known external secret managers
and the CSI driver is the most
secure solution, and also the, but
also the most tedious to set up.
let's see how it works.
you deploy the, the driver and external
secrets provider on the cluster.
so generally, depending on the provider
you use, you would have to, deploy
the specific provider, driver for the
specific provider as well on the cluster.
this works at the APA server level.
hence, this is not going to
create any actual issues.
Kubernetes secrets here.
So this is a slightly more secure option.
so you can create a secret provider class,
CRD to define the details of the secret
to be fetched from the secret manager.
next you will create your
normal, deployments and
pod definitions, et cetera.
And here you will define, you
will, reference the SecretProvider
class in the pods volume spec.
when you deploy this, when you deploy
this, the driver will watch, for this.
And when it finds the SecretProvider
class, it will fetch the actual
secret from the external secret
manager and it will mount that,
into the pod tempfs volume.
So only the particular pod, which
references the secret provider
class will have access to that
particular secret in the pod.
and this volume will be removed when
the pod is scheduled for deletion.
So this is nicer as nothing is
exposed as, Kubernetes secrets.
So that even people who have access
to read KU Secrets, will not be
able to, decode the sensitive data.
So this is a much, secure option and
ideal for, large projects, enterprises,
and, very, security savvy, tips.
if you're, If you are interested,
you can also find a blog post
where I, detail these options
and, provide, examples and so on.
I'll also, I also talk about all
the pros and cons of these different
options in more details here.
So please do check it out.
So next, best practice would be to
keep Kubernetes version up to date.
Of course, this should be obvious
because like any other software, like
any software, it is important to keep the
Kubernetes version up to date as well.
and like any other software, Kubernetes
also has bugs and issues and from
time to time, there might be high
severity bug that calls for a CV.
Hence, it is important to keep the
Kubernetes version up to date for,
the server and for the CLI client.
you can check the Kubernetes security
and disclosure information website
to see if there are known security
bugs for your Kubernetes version.
And if you are using a managed
pass, GKE or, AKS, it should
be pretty easy to upgrade.
And, for on prem installations, there are
tools like COPS, KubeAdmin, and so on.
So that makes it easy
to upgrade, clusters.
So use any of these available options
to keep your cluster up to date.
next is, restricting admin access.
So kubelet is the primary node
agent running on each node.
And by default, a kubelet's
HTTP endpoints are not secure.
we need to restrict access to kubelet,
the API, and, restrict SSH access.
this could allow unintended
access if it is not, secure.
And hence, definitely should
be, number one, on the priority.
furthermore, when someone access to
a Kubernetes cluster, they can access
the k, Kubernetes API server and SSH.
So this should not be allowed.
all non admin users should
not have API and SSH access.
So all this should be locked up.
to limit node access, to limit
node access, cluster access should
be limited as much as possible.
So disable SSH access for non admin users,
secure the API using OIDC and RBAC, have
proper, role based access control, set
up for AROIDC setup, as we saw earlier.
So that only authenticated
users with sufficient roles have
access to the Kubernetes API.
Next on our list would be to control
traffic between pods and clusters.
So generally, pods within the
same cluster will be able to
communicate with each other.
And if you have multiple clusters
in the same network, there may
be traffic between them as well.
do not leave this all open.
in most cases, you don't want different
clusters to be talking to each other.
And in most cases, You don't want
pods to be talking to each other
unless you have a microservice setup.
Even in that case, you would probably
have, proper ways for the pods to
communicate with each other like service
registries and load balancers and so on.
So you don't want them just
directly talking to each other.
so do not leave this all open as it
could lead to a compromised cluster.
and, when a particular pod, has a
vulnerability, this, open communication
could lead to a bigger attack surface.
So it is important to, reduce
the attack surface as much as
possible in case of a breach.
and it's important to isolate, as a attack
surface as much as possible as well.
lock all this stuff.
So you can use Kubernetes security
policies to control traffic
between ports and clusters and
you only allow necessary traffic.
So again, follow the principle
of least privileges, just
allow exactly what is required.
don't allow wider access.
Next on the list would be to use
namespace to isolate workloads.
This is often overlooked.
Do not run all your workloads
in a single namespace.
Isolating workloads in different
namespaces based on business needs is
more secure and easier to manage with
RBAC so that you can control access
to namespace based on requirements
and not have everything in the open.
This way you can fine tune RBAC
even further to let users access
only what they need to see.
You can also use Kubernetes network
policies to isolate traffic between
namespaces where applicable.
So use all these tools at
your disposal and lock access
between namespaces as well.
Next will be to limit resource usage.
So as with securing APIs and cluster
itself, it is also essential to
set resource limits on how much
CPU, memory, and disk space can be
used by resources and namespaces.
this secures your cluster from denial
of service attacks when a particular
container uses up all the resources.
You don't want a single container in your
setup to use all the resources at once.
This is often overlooked and it can easily
happen if you have a rogue application, if
you have a rogue library in a particular
application, which might suddenly,
you know, hog up all the resources.
you can use resource quotas
and limit ranges, to set
limits at the namespace level.
you can use requests and
limits, to set resource limits
at container level as well.
So use all these and define,
resource quotas and limits.
Next on our list would be
to use monitoring tools and
to enable audit logging.
it is extremely important to
monitor and audit our clusters.
this way, we may be able to catch a
break in attempt before it happens.
it can, it can help you to keep
an eye on the traffic, detect
unauthorized access attempts.
So enable audit logging for the
cluster and use monitoring tools to
keep an eye on the network traffic.
to and from within the cluster,
the egress and ingress traffic.
Monitoring can be done using open
source tools like Prometheus,
Grafana, or proprietary tools.
So enable alerts for suspicious
activities, alerts for access,
unknown access attempts
from unknown IPs and so on.
So have an alert for all these
general, suspicious activities
and irregular activities.
Now that we, saw what can be done for
cluster security, we also have to consider
the infrastructure best practices because
keeping the infrastructure, secure is also
part of securing a Kubernetes cluster.
So first and foremost, ensure that
all communication is done via TLS,
Then protect ETCD with TLS, firewall
and encryption and restrict access
to, ETCD using strong credentials.
Set up IAM access policies in a supported,
PaaS environment like, EKS or GKE and AKS.
Secure the Kubernetes control plane,
rotate infrastructure credentials
frequently, restrict cloud, metadata,
API access when running in a pass
like AWS, Azure, or GCP, as it
could expose sensitive metadata.
And in, often it is the case that
these metadata APIs are not secured.
So look into those.
we also need to secure
our containers, right?
It's not just, enough to secure
the cluster and the infrastructure.
We also have to.
go granular and secure
the containers as well.
And securing the containers are as
important as securing the cluster itself.
Let's look at some of the
best practices in that area.
Number one would be to not
run containers as root.
This is extremely overlooked.
And it's very important, do not run
containers as root as this would give the
container unlimited access to the host.
So and in case of a compromised
container or, vulnerability in a
particular container, this would
give, the attacker a wider, attack
surface and root access to the host.
So do not let this happen.
avoid container escape
and privilege escalations.
always run the containers using
a non root user to limit access.
Use chown user, when using docker
copy commands, for example.
Always set up a, least privilege
user for the container and use that.
another often overlooked aspect,
is, Using minimal up to date
official base images, right?
So especially during development since
it's not very convenient, mostly Often
you will just go with a standard os image
and just focus on the application But for
production always consider starting with
a slim base image and adding what exactly
you require there instead of going for a
fat, full fledged operating system image.
use the minimal and up to date
official images as I mentioned.
Don't use generic images.
Go for slim or light versions.
Maybe even start with the
bare bone version and add the
required dependencies yourself.
This will give you much more control.
This will give you much more
control, if you want to replace
a particular dependency or if you
want to upgrade a specific, library
with vulnerability and so on.
This will also make the overall
image lightweight, gives you latest
bug fixes and security patches
and overall is much more secure.
for example, use deterministic image tags.
Don't go for generic ones.
Use the exact specific
version that you want.
don't give, ranges, et cetera.
Remove all unwanted dependencies,
packages, and debugging tools from
the images, to make the image lighter
as well as to reduce the attack
surface in case of a vulnerability.
only install production
dependencies, don't go for beta
or, test dependencies and so on.
use official verified images from
popular software for popular software,
prefer LTS version when available, use a
trusted registry for non official images
and always double check non official
images, look into the images that you
are using and verify the image publisher.
these are all extremely important.
Next would be to prevent
loading unwanted kernel modules.
This is similar to the previous one.
If you're using a FAT, a full fledged
operating system, it might be loading
a lot of unwanted kernel modules
that will unnecessarily use up your
resources, reduce your performance,
increase the image size, increase
the attack surface, and so on.
use only the kernel modules that you
absolutely require for the application.
This will reduce the attack surface
and give better performance.
this can be restricted using rules in
the, Kubernetes blacklist conf, at the
node level or by uninstalling unwanted
modules from the node, directly.
this can also be done by using a
very bare minimum base image and
controlling exactly what loads and,
what dependencies and modules are there.
Next would be to enable container
image scanning in your CACD phase.
If you haven't already add container
image scanning into your build
pipelines, you would thank me later.
This is extremely important.
this can be helpful to detect known
vulnerabilities before they are exploited.
So enable, container image scanning
in your CICD, to catch vulnerabilities
before they become an attack vector.
use OSS tools like Clayer or
Anchor or commercial tools
like Snyk, it's up to you.
But use one of these tools, to
enable, container image scanning.
And, have, have your CICD
pipeline fail if, There is a
vulnerability in your container.
these are quite easy to set up and
they support most CACD, solutions.
So there is no excuse to not do this.
Next would be to audit the images.
It is extremely important to monitor and
audit the container images periodically.
check for security best practices.
If possible, make this auditing
part of your CI CD pipeline.
use Docker Bench for security
to audit your container images
for security best practices.
It's a great tool to ensure that
custom images you build for production
are following best practices.
Finally, use port security
policies for containers.
So this will help reduce attack surface
and prevent privilege escalation.
you can use the pod security admission to
limit the container's access to the host.
This is the successor to pod
security policies from version 1.
2 and onwards.
This will help reduce attack surface
and prevent privilege escalations in
case the container image is compromised.
And this is more common than you think.
More than a million Docker
images were found to be affected
by malware at different times.
this is nothing to be, nothing to, ignore.
set this up.
And, with that, we conclude all
the security best practice tips.
thank you for joining.
Hope you, had, some useful
information from here.
Hope you follow some of these
and secure your clusters, better.
thank you.
You can reach me on, BlueSky,
Mastodon, and LinkedIn.
Thank you for your time.