Hey all, this is Nikhil Ramasastry.
I work as a staff
software engineer at Turo.
I'm going to present my learnings
of API first development.
Embracing it has enhanced
scalability and integration for Turo.
To go over the agenda items, I
will first introduce the concept
and explain its core principles,
specification formats, tools used for
design, documentation, and testing.
Then, we'll present you with use cases,
later go over the benefits, challenges,
mitigation strategies, and best practices.
Eventually, we'll conclude.
To start with the introduction, according
to 2023 survey conducted by Postman,
67 percent of the developers expect
to spend more time on the software.
on developing an API
or API work in general.
At Turo, we often struggle with explicit
versus implicit scope of an API without
understanding the third party clients or
front end developers or mobile developers.
Over time, we have learned development
of an API with respect to stakeholders
who are using it defines its scope.
Hence, API first development
prioritizes designing APIs as a
foundation of application development.
At 2.
0, the backend development team has
started involving stakeholders during
the brainstorming sessions of API design.
this help does close a lot of loose ends.
Hence.
We followed the pattern of
define API contract, implement
it, and test and apply.
In application development, there is
always a producer and consumer lifecycle.
As a producer, we started
defining the API endpoints and
its request or response structure.
With stakeholders in some cases we have
mocked the data with loose coupling
that enables scalability and flexibility
Three these principles has enabled
consumer to not worry the underlying
complexity of an api in turn provided The
abstraction and encapsulation as well.
To give an overview on specification
formats, we have used OpenAPI 3.
0.
There are other formats like RESTful
API Modeling Language and Markdown based
API Blueprints for different use cases.
Among these, OpenAPI stands out
clearly as it supports JSON and YAML
and generates codes extensively.
As part of OpenAPI 1st development
to establish smooth collaboration,
we used design tools like Stoplight,
Swagger, and Postman for testing
and marking requests or responses.
Swagger UI is very handy with
respect to documentation, where we
have explicitly collaborated about
things like HTTP error codes and etc.
API first development can be applied
in use cases like independent scaling
microservices, content management
systems, mobile applications, and
Internet of Things ecosystems.
After practicing API first development
for a few projects, our developers are
never going back to code first approach.
As API first development
provides scalability, flexibility
with better integration.
It enhanced developer experience
by 29 percent and API adoption
rate by 35 percent for our teams.
The challenges to implement
API first development started
with huge learning curve.
With key challenges around versioning
and security concerns manage to handle
these challenges with Few breakout
sessions from time to time and training
around tools like swagger and open api 3.
0 adoption Started to follow versioning
policies strictly and API gateways
and doing regular audits have
helped us from security standpoint.
Here are the few best practices for
implementation of API first development.
Brainstorm design of an API with
intention to future proof it.
Implement robust error
handling and validation.
Update outdated documentation
from time to time.
Involve stakeholders
early and gather feedback.
That helps a lot and effectively
versioning the APIs for
smooth transitions also helps.
In conclusion, API first development
is revolutionizing the modern
software architecture by emphasizing
scalability, flexibility, and
superior integrations capabilities.
By designing APIs as foundation
layer, organization organizations
can foster parallel development.
enhance collaboration between the
teams, ultimately accelerating the
time to market for their products.
Two row experience with technology
leaders such as Uber, GitHub and Stripe
have demonstrated the significant
advantages of adopting an API for
strategy from improved system modularity
to seamless third party integrations.
Thank you for your time.
Have a nice day.
Bye.