Hello, my fellow tech enthusiasts.
I am Clifton Reddy, and by profession,
I am a software development manager.
Today, I'm going to talk about green
code, a possible process to reduce your
carbon footprint in the dev and ops arena.
So what is green code and how can
it be integrated into operations to
reduce the overall carbon intensity?
Just as code red signals a security
issue, should code green signify?
The need to prioritize carbon emissions
and sustainable software practices.
This picture shows the carbon intensity of
electricity consumption around the world.
So what is carbon intensity?
carbon intensity is a metric that measures
the amount of carbon dioxide and other
greenhouse gases per unit of activity.
The map is a carbon intensity map
of the power grids across the world.
Obviously, the greener it is, the
greener the operational carbon created
in the power generation spaces, and
the redder it is, the more of that
energy is derived from fossil fuels.
No data was found for
the gray color regions.
Real time data of the carbon intensity
can be derived from electricity maps.
And also from other
providers such as wartime.
If you are the curious type, I would
strongly recommend working on a personal
pet project to check and validate the
carbon emission across regions and times
to verify the carbon intensity, especially
if you have access to multi cloud data.
and run processes across the globe.
So what are we trying to
accomplish in this presentation?
As IT personnel, we are often oblivious
to our contribution to greenhouse
gases via the programs we write and
processes and methodologies we follow.
So it is my intent to try and highlight
some practices to reduce and minimize our
carbon footprint via sustainable software
development and operational practices.
Like any other architectural principles,
such as performance improvement,
scalability, security, cost, availability,
et cetera, that are commonly known to us.
We've seen other industries, such as
the airline, that disclose their carbon
emissions, and many of them offer
carbon offset options, where you can
contribute to environmental projects to
compensate for your flight's emissions.
However, we have not seen
a similar initiative.
and wider option in the software
development industry, especially by IT
management and others in the IT workspace.
In this presentation, we will delve
into some important concepts and ways
to control, reduce carbon emissions
by bringing changes to our day to
day software development habits.
All of what we've talked about so far
makes sense, but the real big question is,
how can you and I as software developers
DevOps personal solution architects, be
responsible and curb carbon emissions.
What tools, techniques, and methodologies
do we have at our disposal to reduce
our carbon footprint and measure the
carbon intensity in the software?
thankfully, several organizations have
built and are continually enhancing
tools and frameworks to measure software
carbon emissions, the list of which are
provided at the bottom of this slide.
In this presentation, we will talk briefly
about Green Software Foundation or GSF.
GSF is an organization that came up with
a way to measure carbon intensity in your
software via Software Carbon Intensity,
SCI, which is a specification, which
is also by the way, an ISO standard.
You can find more information at sci.
greensoftware.
foundation.
Software carbon intensity is
the amount of soft, of carbon
emitted per functional unit.
A functional unit is any work,
for example, a batch job, or it
could also be invoking an API.
So how is SCI calculated?
it is calculated by taking into
consideration the carbon per functional
unit, where E represents the energy
consumed by the software system, L is the
location based marginal carbon intensity.
M denotes the embodied emissions
of the hardware needed to
operate the software system.
And R stands for the functional
unit, such as calling an API.
This comprehensive approach
underscores the importance of
considering both the direct energy
usage and the indirect emissions.
from hardware in assessing the overall
carbon intensity of software programs.
Some of the steering members
of GSF include Microsoft,
Accenture, Intel, and UBS.
The slide on the right is
the carbon footprint based on
regions and cloud providers.
This information could be
used to calculate your SCI
score, which is important.
By the way, on a side note, at the
GSF USIN chapter, I am a member
of the leadership group and the
organizer for that meetup group.
It Is the fastest programming program
the best and the most energy efficient,
or is it a misconception continuing from
some of the architectural principles
I mentioned in my previous slide,
what I have here is a research paper
that compares energy, time, and memory
consumption between various programming
languages that we use to run the exact
same algorithm on the same hardware.
Configure configuration, by the way.
To measure the energy consumption,
they used Intel's RAPL tool, which
is the Running Average Power Limit.
And RAPL is capable of providing
accurate energy estimates at
a very fine grained level.
While there were several other algorithmic
benchmarks that were performed across
various programming languages, for the
sake of this presentation, I narrowed
it down just to two to prove the point.
The benchmarks I chose here are The
regex redux and the binary trees
algorithm, the figures below denote
the energy and memory consumed by each
algorithm based on the different type
of language, out of which some are
compiled, interpreted, and VM based.
While C consumed the least energy in
the binary trees algorithm execution,
TypeScript consumed the least energy when
the regex redux algorithm was executed.
Where are we going with this?
In the previous slide now, we discussed
performance programming languages.
does improving performance
alone solve our issue?
What if servers and their
resources complete tasks rapidly?
Does that solve our CO2 emissions problem?
Unfortunately, this would
lead to underutilized CPUs and
resources causing idle states.
The research article PowerNAP Eliminating
server idle power highlights that in
typical deployments, server utilization
is below 30%, yet idle servers consume
60 percent of their peak power drop.
Should we then consider
containerizing applications
to maximize their performance?
Resource efficiency?
that seems like a viable option.
However, according to a, according
to CAST AI study, only provisioned
CPUs and 20 percent of memory are
actually utilized in cloud computing.
So it's back to the
drawing board then, huh?
We might consider implementing
some techniques derived from the
research in the previous slide.
Let's take a look.
Table 1 lists the various
benchmarks performed.
The table beside it presents the data
and their rankings based on energy,
time, and memory consumption, while
the table on the right offers a visual
representation of different combinations.
Based on the optimal sets for different
combinations of objectives shown on
the right, we can select our languages.
This approach may help utilize
resources to their fullest potential
at certain times, but not consistently.
Thus the question, is the fastest, the
most energy efficient, that still remains?
And the answer is no.
The fastest language is not
always the most energy efficient.
Server utilization varies significantly
based on workload and the level of
virtualization, typically ranging from
30, from 5 to 30 percent in enterprise
environments, while cloud service
products often achieve higher utilization.
You might wonder why we're delving into
these details in a DevOps presentation.
Remember, our focus is on green code.
within DevOps, aiming to identify
coding practices that will
lead to more sustainable and
efficient software solutions.
Understanding these utilization metrics
helps us see the impact of our code on
resource usage and efficiency, guiding
us toward achieving green code outcomes.
So what can you do to
minimize carbon footprint?
To improve server utilization,
one strategy is resource density.
which refers to the amount of computing
power and storage capacity packed into a
given physical space within a data center.
High resource density means more efficient
use of space, power, and cooling, leading
to better performance and for the C
suite folks, lower operational costs.
And some possible ways to alleviate
these problems are by going serverless.
Serverless functions can contribute
to high resource density Efficient
resource utilization through dynamic
scaling where serverless functions
dynamically scale in response to
demand, ensuring that resources are
utilized efficiently without needing
dedicated servers running at all times.
Serverless functions execute
in response to specific events
and terminate once the task is
completed, minimizing idle resource
usage, thereby reducing idle time.
Serverless functions often run in micro
VMs or containers or custom runtime
environments, which are lightweight
and can be densely packed on physical
servers, optimizing space and power usage.
Cloud providers manage the underlying
infrastructure, ensuring optimal resource
distribution and reducing wasted capacity.
By maximizing resource density and
minimizing idle time, serverless functions
help reduce the overall energy consumption
and carbon footprint of data centers,
thereby making your infrastructure
more efficient and sustainable.
While serverless functions scale actively
based on demand, thereby reducing idle
time to an extent, it still suffers from
the concept of cold starts, where the
environment needs to be initialized.
Also, according to our research, many
Azure functions are infrequently invoked,
yet they stay running constantly,
leading to high costs and inefficiency.
Additionally, Serverless solutions
often suffer from vendor lock in
and inadequate support for local
development and CI CD practices.
WASM, WASI.
Before that, Solomon Hikes, the founder
of Docker, once said, and I quote,
if WASM and WASI existed in 2008, we
wouldn't have needed to create Docker.
That's how important it is.
Web assembly on the server
is the future of computing.
A standardized system
interface was a missing link.
Let's hope YAC is up to the task.
End quote.
WebAssembly, or WASM, is a portable binary
code format that allows developers to
run code written in multiple languages
on the web at near native speed.
It's designed to be efficient
and fast, making it ideal for
performance intensive applications.
Look at the start speed of a
Wasm application compared to
an AWS serverless function.
52 milliseconds versus 250 milliseconds.
Now we've seen some great advantages
of serverless, but we also saw
that serverless functions require
a cold start from time to time.
This is where Wasm comes to the rescue.
Wasm does not have a
concept of a cold start.
WebAssembly system interface.
WASI is a modular system
interface for WebAssembly.
It provides a standardized set of
APIs that WebAssembly modules can
use to access system resources like
the file system, network, and time.
This means you can run WebAssembly
code outside of a browser on
any platform that supports WASI.
In a sense, WASM is about running
high performance code on the web, and
WASI is about making the code portable
and able to interact with system
resources across different environments.
Wasm also provides a stringent
security environment by running
code in a sandboxed environment.
Wasm implementation can thrive on edge
devices such as smart thermostats,
security cameras, wearable health
monitors, smartphones, and tablets that
run apps and processes data locally.
So what's next?
Coming up now is GraalVM, which
has several similarities to Wasm,
except that GraalVM uses JVM.
Whereas WASM uses the WASM runtime.
Grand
VM is a high performance runtime
supporting multiple languages and
execution modes designed to enhance
application performance through advanced
optimization techniques by compiling Java
applications into native executables using
the ahead of time compilation strategy.
Grand VM ensures instant startup
and reduced compute resource usage.
It minimizes CPU and memory consumption
leading to lower power consumption
and reduced carbon emissions.
Additionally, GraalVM's native
images eliminate the need for JIT,
just in time compilation, allowing
applications to run efficiently from
the start without the warm up overhead.
Moving on, we have looked at some
possible application development
and programming strategies.
Here in this slide, we will
discuss some of the practices
from an operations standpoint.
DevOps can play a significant role in
reducing carbon emissions by promoting
efficient and sustainable practices in
software development and operations.
Here are some ways DevOps can help.
While there are many strategies that are
helpful, constant monitoring of resources,
tweaking the build and deploy via CI CD
pipelines to be scheduled at the time when
the cloud providers consume energy from
greener sources would definitely help.
Using tools to track and report carbon
emissions through automated solutions.
efficient resource utilization
by automated scaling and load
balancing, thereby preventing
over provisioning and waste.
Also, cloud selection
plays an important role.
Maybe consider shifting to a cloud
provider that uses renewable energy
and have energy efficient data centers.
By incorporating green software
practices, where we follow principles
to minimize carbon emissions and energy.
Use for example, as an example,
checking the SCI score during the
build and deploy and suggesting
changes to better reduce the SCI score.
It could also be collaboration
and innovation where collaborating
with suppliers and customers on
joint initiatives and continuously
seeking innovative ways to
improve energy efficiency and
reduce environmental impact.
By integrating these practices,
DevOps can help organizations reduce
their carbon footprint and contribute
to a more sustainable future.
In conclusion, I would like to say that
while not a single language or approach or
operational style will render a complete
100 percent carbon free footprint, a
combination of what we've discussed in
this presentation will surely reduce
the carbon emission and our footprint.
With that, I conclude
and thanks for your time.