Hi, I'm Elon Finkelstein.
I'm Peter Van Eyfren.
And today we're going to
talk about the CISO is dead.
Now what?
Building quality DR, IR, and
BCP exercises and simulations.
Very quickly, as mentioned,
I'm Elon Finkelstein.
I'm a principal security architect
on the security development
team at OWN by Salesforce.
I can be reached at elon.
finkelstein at owndata.
com.
I'm also available on LinkedIn.
I currently have a master's in
cybersecurity from NYU, a bachelor's
of science in computer science from
John Jay, and I'm multiple times AWS
certified and a member of ISC squared.
Hi, I'm Peter Van Iperen.
As I mentioned, I am the chief
information I'm a former Deputy
CISO at Clear, Fox, and Disney.
I also have a Master's in Cybersecurity.
I'm a former Deputy CISO
at Clear, Fox, and Disney.
I also have a Master's in Cybersecurity.
And I have, 25, more than
25 cyber certifications.
I also, teach some cybersecurity courses.
Okay, so very quickly, we're
going to just talk about our
overall topics for today's talk.
we're going to walk through an
introduction, a quick review of the
terminology, developing real world
possibilities, introducing randomness
into exercises, conceptualizing
Black Swan events, gaining
management buy in, including others.
And then some follow up
and conclusion points.
So very quickly into the terminology,
in order to build a common body of
knowledge, disaster recovery or DR is an
organization's ability to restore access
and functionality to IT infrastructure
after a disaster event, whether
natural or caused by human action.
I think what's more important here
is not what this definition says, but
what it doesn't say, which is, it's
restore access and functionality to
IT infrastructure, but really it's.
What keeps you operating?
Second would be incident response.
Incident response is the actions that an
organization takes when it believes IT
systems or data may have been breached.
security, for instance, security
professionals will act if they see
evidence of an unauthorized user,
malware, or failure of security measures.
That's from Microsoft.
BCP, or business continuity
planning, that's documentation of
a predetermined set of instructions
or procedures that describe how an
organization's mission slash business
principles will be sustained during
and after a significant disruption.
That's from NIST.
And finally, a black swan event.
A black swan event is an event
that defies expectations.
They carry extreme consequences and
are only understood in hindsight.
That Forbes.
I think a good example is.
COVID.
COVID was the black swan event
of the last 10 years, right?
No one saw it coming, totally
unexpected, shut down almost everything.
And I, I think another type of black
swan that we have to look at here
very seriously in this is, not throw
anyone under the bus, but CrowdStrike.
CrowdStrike, what happened
inside CrowdStrike, probably
preventable, predictable.
the effects that occurred
to the rest of the world.
Not so much.
and I think that we need to really look
at, true code, black, and then, and events
that, start out as something predictable,
small problems that, aren't taken care of
in places, and they build into something
that has truly unpredictable consequences.
Yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
So in developing exercises, we want
to build quality simulations that rely
on a whole bunch of different factors.
some of the ones that we want to talk
about are clear purpose, well defined,
authentic, interesting, exciting,
unpredictable, inclusive, and automated.
clear purpose, successful exercises
begin with a straightforward and
simple explanation of the goals.
That's really just basically
laying out exactly what the idea
is, what our plan to do here is
and what the end result will be.
and the more clarity we can provide
our participants, the easier and much
more fun that these exercises will be.
And I think we should note here that
when we say Expectation of the end goals.
It's what is the outcome?
What are we more prepared for?
What have we learned from this?
Not this is how the beginning and end
of this simulation occur, everyone.
I think that's precisely what
we're here to talk about not doing.
So I just want to make
sure we clarify that.
Next up is well defined, right?
We really want to have a good explanation
of what is fair game, what's out
of bounds, and what the parameters
and boundaries of our exercise
include, and also don't include.
Generally speaking,
don't include production.
Don't include production.
I'm going to say it one more time.
Next, we want to make sure that
our exercises are authentic.
So they need to be built on real
world possibilities and true
potentialities for the organization.
I would just add to that, that, true
possibilities, true potentialities,
flexible, and you're thinking of that.
Precisely to the point of what
we'll talk about later in this
talk, black swans are unpredictable.
there is a reason that the U.
S.
military has plans for,
a zombie, apocalypse.
It's not because they think a zombie
apocalypse is going to happen, but
it's because it illuminates all the
different problems that, rear their heads
when dealing with an issue like that.
So I think, be flexible in the thinking
of what is, included in your exercises.
Better to be more prepared, for
things that might be somewhat unreal.
Then, not prepared for things that
could be very real, a la COVID.
Absolutely.
Next thing we want to do is make
our exercises interesting, right?
We need to capture the audience, right?
We need to make sure that our
participants, are invested in the game.
And we need to do that by developing
enough of a challenge, right?
But still something.
Solvable, that folks are interested
for long periods of time and don't
give up in frustration, right?
We don't want them slamming
their hands down and saying, I'm
done, but we also don't want them
finishing in 35 minutes, right?
And I also think that, solvable,
achievable graspable is important.
always ends in success.
It is not important, and as a matter
of fact, not ending in success is
often more important than being
successful in all of these exercises.
I think the next part we want to talk
about is the unpredictability, right?
Exercises need to have enough
randomness of events and outcomes,
that keep the participants
interested but also on their toes.
So there is no expected outcome,
just to what Peter was saying.
We also want to make sure that
our exercises and simulations
are inclusive, right?
We want to remove the typical
cast of characters, right?
Those who are constantly or regularly
involved in incident response, disaster
recovery, or BCP planning, right?
We want to substitute in the folks who
may have less experience, the people
who potentially are the juniors on
the team who have never been involved
Incident Response, or BCP, or DR, right?
That's what's really going to both cross
functionality train our team, but also
help to teach folks who haven't had a
chance to lead an incident or an incident
response how to do so effectively.
They used to have a hard and fast
rule, if you wrote the BCP or the
DR plan, you're not in the exercise.
And I think the final
one is automation, right?
So we want to use scripting and automation
to develop scenarios that unfold
without organizer interaction, right?
You don't want to be leading one of
these exercises and Be stuck behind
a keyboard trying to manually trigger
events Trying to generate some sort
of lock that can be used for an alert
creation or anything else, right?
We want to be involved with the players
themselves And we want to leave all
of the preparation to an automated
And I just want to be clear here, if
anyone leaves this talk thinking, I
need to go, to write simulated triggers
through an AWS environment to do what
we're talking about, that'd be fantastic.
and I've seen it done and
I've seen it done really well.
Simply numbered and rolling base or,
decisions that are made, sufficiently
would bring in enough randomness that
is out of your control and also leaves
you from, disengaging with the exercise.
Okay, so introducing randomness.
when we develop these exercises, we
want to make sure that we include
a lacking or definite plan, right?
to introduce exercise, to introduce
randomness into our exercises, it
serves really two purposes, right?
We help to maintain the
participant interest.
It also makes our exercises
really authentic, right?
Because nothing that in
a true BCP, DR, or IR.
Our situation is going
to be predictable, right?
Everything is going to go haywire.
Everything, might go out the window
and you need to be prepared for that.
And I think when we introduce randomness,
we can do it in a lot of different
ways, including rolling dice, including
picking envelopes, including simulated
random number generators and options.
I think also something interesting to do
is treat it like it's a real disaster.
Take shifts.
Make people step away to take
food breaks, to take, go to the
bathroom, be a human, get tired.
That's what's going to happen
in a real world scenario.
We're not all going to have a neat
hour and a half break where we all
get to have a nice conversation
in the middle of a disaster.
so treat it like a real disaster.
I think the second part, when it
comes to introducing randomness, is
it helps to maintain interest, right?
when we're able to limit distractions
and develop something that is really
engaging and really interesting
in, to our participants, right?
We can keep them involved and we can also
make sure that there's no predictability.
We're able to remove any expected
outcome and make the game very
interesting and unpredictable.
And I think it's important to
dedicate the team to doing that
and taking away distractions.
And I think it's really important too
that whoever is running the simulation
doesn't know when the simulation
is ending or how it's going to end.
That is.
That is a disaster or a business
continuity recovery, right?
You don't know when it's going to be over.
And I think that helps keep people engaged
because if you tell people, Hey, we could
be in this room, it could be an hour, it
could be 8 hours, it could be 12 hours.
We're all going to dedicate
ourselves to really simulating this.
You really start to understand what
will occur in a disaster in your teams.
And, it also focuses people, right?
just generally speaking.
in the first half hour, people
want to check slack after
they've been at it for a while.
If they want to avoid the game
and they want to get out, I think
distractions will go away very quickly.
Very good point.
Very good point, Peter.
And next up, we'll talk about
some Black Swan events, right?
So it's really hard to figure out the
one in a million possibilities, right?
If they were well known, they
wouldn't be Black Swan events, right?
I think a lot of what goes into this
is the creativity and understanding
of your actual environment and
what would really derail it.
I think that, how do you stimulate
a black swan event, right?
How do you simulate the unknowable?
I think if you, research and look
at people who study black swan
events, one of the characteristics
is that they're always.
I don't want to say predictable,
but knowable in hindsight.
The reason they're knowable in hindsight
is you can see the seven or eight
factors that interacted with each
other to create that black swan event.
so if you want to simulate
black swan events, create
seven or eight random factors.
Let them interact with each
other and see where things lead.
You may not end up in
a black swan scenario.
You may end up in a very
vanilla scenario that, that is.
a typical, DR scenario, someone
kicked the court out, right?
but you also may end up with a truly
unique scenario to you that really
starts to highlight how you would
have to act during a black swan event.
definitely.
Now.
Okay.
Gaining management buy in.
So convincing management that half
the ops team, three quarters of our
security resources and legal finance
and product all need to be in the same
room for the next eight hours and not
at their desks is not easy, right?
it's only a few people from the company.
who needs three quarters
of the company working?
It's going to be an uphill battle.
I don't have a lot to add here.
I, in security, we're often.
What is the ROI of
something not happening?
What is the ROI of things
being proven negative?
Ah, what's the ROI of
something that not happening?
and preventing the bad
thing from happening.
but I do think, Ilan, you have some
good points, pointers here on how
we can help people make a case.
So absolutely.
So really quickly, we need to
have a good understanding of
what motivates business, right?
Typically, business is motivated by So
I think in this case, I think it's just
about the ability to supply the ability
to continue to be in business, right?
Our ability to be successful.
and some of that comes down to
our ability to make sure that
our systems are continuous, that
we're, our data is not leaked.
in addition to being able
to make money, right?
So I think if we're able to show
the value add that a lot of DR, BCP
or IR exercises can bring to the
organization, we're able to see much
more buy in from our leadership.
to really help make this point, we
have some really good stats here that
hopefully can help as you translate
them to your business leaders.
So very quickly in terms of BCP,
continuity breaks cost somewhere between
137 to 16, 000 per minute, right?
Nine out of 10 businesses
experience one or more continuity
breaks in a quarter, right?
And I think this is just a really
important thing to hit home on here.
I think often when people try to make
these cases, they try to say, the
average cost of a server going out.
we have that here, but really
the most important thing in this
slide is 9 businesses experience
one or more outages per quarter.
Go find that last outage, go
talk to the product people,
go talk to the sales people.
Go find out how much that
outage cost for your business.
And look at the time that it was out
and then go make that multiplication.
It's the multiplication.
That loss of revenue or that refund
to a customer, et cetera, is a much
healthier and more significant argument
than how much it costs to fix a server.
Absolutely.
So some really quick DR stats, right?
Corporations lose 40 percent of employee
productivity during outages, right?
30 percent of organizations
permanently lose data and more than
two Thirds of how do I do that?
Where you see all these big companies that
have large outages cost companies over
a hundred thousand dollars in revenue.
Sorry, go ahead.
No.
taking this all back to your
leadership helps to make that case.
And I think just again, focusing
in this slide here on people know
what it means if 40 percent of
people can't work, especially
recently people live through COVID.
They understand that.
I think the other really important
one on here is 30 percent of
organizations permanently lose data.
In your scenario, I am.
Encourage everyone in your scenario,
somehow lose data, somehow have
data inaccessible, even if it's
through randomness and it's how
much of the data or et cetera, but
have them feel the effect of not
having data at their fingertips.
Businesses operate on data and the only
thing scarier to lose in revenue is data.
'cause data loss always leads to
revenue loss 100% of the time.
It leads to revenue loss
in one way or another.
Really good point.
And I think the third one is probably
one of the easiest cases to make,
and that's the IR stats, right?
IR is probably the most well known of
all the things we're talking about today.
But again, these stats are overwhelming
when we present them to leadership, right?
Ransomware gangs collected 1.
1 billion in 2023 from
their victims, right?
72.
7 percent of organizations worldwide
have experienced ransomware
attacks in 2023 alone, right?
And cyber Cyberattacks exposed health
records of 25%, 1 in 4 people, in
the first 9 months alone in 2023.
So the idea that you're not going
to start to prepare for these
basically eventualities seems silly.
And I think just adding to that
too, the ransomware and attack
landscape is shifting significantly.
You're seeing more places where
data will just be exposed,
data will not be returned.
I, Brandon.
It's where gangs don't want to negotiate,
insurance companies don't want to pay.
So again, adding that randomness, adding
that fluidity into your simulations
is more important than ever, because
when you are faced with something
like this, which 73 percent of us were
faced with in one year alone, you don't
know what you're going to be facing.
and it's something at,
in the security industry.
community we talk about all the time,
but other business leaders don't realize
that and assume that there's one or two
really easy ways out of these scenarios.
And I think it's really important for them
to understand that's not often the case.
absolutely.
Okay, I think we're coming into another
really important part of a successful
exercise, and that's including others.
So when we talk about including others,
once we have management buy in, right?
We want other teams to participate, right?
When we operate in, let's say,
DR, BCP, or IR world, right?
We're not operating with
only technical folks, right?
We need to make sure that all of the
teams involved in an incident, right?
Any of those types of incidents
will be prepared, right?
And by doing so, We can ensure that,
again, we have a better incident
response or IR or DR or BCP.
So I think if you're performing a
simulation and a lot, we're looking at
the list of teams here, and I want you
to tell us why it's important, but I just
want to say to everyone, if you're doing a
simulation and it doesn't involve at least
two of these other groups on here, you
shouldn't be doing the simulation because
you're not simulating something serious.
You can have a big enough that it
actually matters to simulate it.
You're not rehearsing something
that is actually, significantly
damaging to the company and that's
what we need to prepare for.
many of the little things we can
handle, it's the big things where we
need cooperation and we need to know
that things will continue operating.
Go ahead.
Absolutely.
And I think some of those teams
that operate during, whether it's a
DR, RBCP or IR in real life world.
include finance, legal, our C suites,
our physical security teams, and
our marketing and PR teams, right?
Because as technologists, we are only
privy to a small scope of the business.
These folks handle the other
important pieces of the business.
And I think that, going back to the cogent
title of this talk, the CISO is dead.
which is something we talk
about internally here.
I like to think I won the lottery,
but I'm fairly certain a lawn
kills me in a plane crash.
regardless, I think it's
important, especially across
the C suite, to do that, right?
Often in these plans you have that legal,
or privacy, or your chief legal counsel
or someone like that will sign off on
the language that's released, or, your
internal comms, or something like that.
we often don't look at who the
backups are for these people.
And we They often take for granted
that these people will be available,
and the first thing that will occur
in a real world scenario, in a real
disaster, especially a large scale
black swan event, is some of these
people are just not going to be there.
They're not going to be available.
And the last thing you
want to do is not know who.
If you don't know who, you're paralyzed.
And that is literally
the number one thing.
People can do things.
If people, but what's the point?
It's the old saying a long, a
person is smart, people are dumb,
a crowd is dangerous, right?
People in a group, a crowd of
people getting on a phone, no
one knows who's supposed to be
doing what, who's in control.
Things are going to go sideways really
quickly, so I think that's really
important to bring into your scenarios.
And you get to kill me in a plane
crash, so who doesn't want to,
take their boss out for a day?
I guess now we can get
into our conclusion.
I guess the first conclusion
The final conclusion from this
talk is the CISO is not dead.
He's very much alive and here with us.
So that's a plus.
but also, it's developing really
interesting and seemingly random exercises
requires time and attention to detail.
it requires management buy in and
also a level of authenticity, while
being anything but average, right?
So like we talked about,
you want to include some of
those black swan type events.
You want We want to make sure
that you're not utilizing the same
resources that are utilized every
time a real incident occurs, right?
We want to make sure that none of
the incidents or simulations that
we're developing fit into any of our
established playbooks, and we want to
make sure that we really keep things
interesting for our participants.
And inclusivity helps a lot with that.
I just to take the temperature really
quick here too, I would just say that
if you run simulations once or twice a
year, and When everyone walks away from
that simulation feeling really good
about themselves, you've done it wrong.
Just hands down, you've done it wrong.
I don't care if you do it twice a
year, every year for the past ten
years, if you walk away feeling
good, you're not doing it right.
The whole point of doing these
simulations is to be over prepared.
You should be losing, you should
be noticing things that are wrong,
and you should be walking away
with kind of an ick in your gut.
oh, this isn't, this is,
we didn't account for this.
If you're not doing that, and that's
at least not happening at least the C
suite level, you're not doing something
right, and you need to reevaluate
how you're handling your simulations.
Absolutely.
I guess the next piece to just follow up
on once more is that when we're developing
these exercises, including members of
departments that are peripheral and
not necessarily technologists, right?
Enhancing.
It extends our overall unity.
It helps to prepare us for when we are
on calls with these folks, during real
incidents or during real responses.
And it also builds some sort of
cohesion, That exists going into the
next real live disaster recovery event.
Or business continuity event
or a real incident response.
Oh, I, can I ask you a question?
Sure.
If we, if we kill a
computer, does it complain?
No.
We talk about shooting
computers like cattle, right?
Yes.
I'm fairly certain that computers are
not what matters when something breaks.
The customers matter.
The clients matter.
The workers matter.
And I'm fairly certain that last
time I checked, InfoSecurity doesn't
manage all those departments, right?
No.
you're not having a real
disaster if only InfoSecurity
is involved in your simulation.
Absolutely.
And I guess the last couple of things is
just to make sure that these exercises
are fun and interesting, right?
but also making sure that you have
the organizational support, and
getting an executive sponsor, along
with providing that sponsor and your
management clarity about what the
exercise entails and what they can
help to do to ensure success, right?
Like we talked about in the management
buy in really makes a big difference.
Because at the end of the day we
want to do this multiple times.
We want to continue to practice,
continue to build, continue to
grow, and continue to improve.
And the only way we can do that
is by continuing to practice.
And I think continuing to practice
means that we need to take what
we did wrong and evaluate it.
In a way that isn't repercussion based,
isn't consequence based, but is instead
improvement based and say, okay, next time
we're going to do this better and we're
going to evaluate ourselves to make sure
that we're going in the right direction.
And I think that if we can show
market improvement every time, it,
you will gain that executive buy
in and that sponsorship, right?
There is
at a certain level, everyone's
job becomes basically care.
That's what you do for a living.
And, what keeps you up at night
is the inability to take a problem
that's gonna come along and solve it.
having the confidence in the fact that
You can have an outright disaster come
along and you will at least be given the
time and opportunity to figure out how to
solve that through your disaster recovery,
through your business continuity,
through your incident response, and
know that it will work when the big
one comes and that you will not be S.
O.
L.
Pardon my French.
is something that most executives, when
they understand the value of that, will
110 percent support, building out a
program that does these simulations, and
most importantly, building them out in
a way that's random, and building them
out in a way that one day, they will
be the C suite officer and they Who is
dead, and volunteering to do that, to
see how their team responds and react.
so a lot of final words.
no, just to go out there and have
fun and thank everyone so much.
really appreciate you joining our talk.
Peter's not dead, so if anyone comes
and knocks on my door, I didn't
kill him, it was someone else.
However, do know, I do turn up dead.
There is a gentleman we're watching
right now, who we should talk
to first, before anyone else.
But seriously.
It was great doing Elon, and I
think that, This is something that
is so overlooked in our arena.
it's often a compliance checkbox and
yet, it proves time and time again
to be the most important thing,
that we do, and, really appreciate
you including me in this, even
if, you had the threat to kill me.
So thank you so much.
And thank you guys for joining.
I thank you.
Bye.