Hi everyone, and thank you for joining me.
My name is Sanny and I work at Salesforce
as a director of product management,
and today I am thrilled to share a
transformative framework for understanding
DevSecOps Health, the one that moves
beyond individual tools or isolated
metrics into a more holistic, actionable
engineering first way of driving.
Security and operational excellence.
This framework responds to a challenge
nearly every organization faces.
You are investing heavily in DevSecOps,
automation, scanners, compliant
workflows and whatnot, right?
And yet, leadership still struggles.
To answer this simple question, is
our pipeline actually healthy today?
I'll show you how to answer
that question with clarity.
Precision and confidence.
Let's talk a little bit about
the DevSecOps Health Paradox
that we currently face.
This is at the heart of the
modern, uh, organizations today.
Organizations never had more
tools than we have today.
Um, more scans than ever, more dashboards
than ever, but somehow the actual security
posture is less clearer than ever.
Strange, right?
Security teams are checking boxes.
They are, their development teams are
pushing code and operations team are
maintaining uptime, but they're not
speaking a shared language of health.
When everything gets measured
independently, nothing gets understood
collectively and the result, you might
have pipelines that technically pass every
scan, but they're fundamentally brittle.
You might have deployments
happening rapidly.
Yet the observability debt is
masking early signs of incidents,
and the more tools we add, the
more artifacts we generate, like
logs, alerts, reports without
necessarily improving decision making.
This is called the DevSecOps Health Para.
So basically the bottom, the bottom line
is more tooling does not really equal
more clarity in many cases, less is more.
So what are some of these, um, gaps
in our current practices today?
So we studied organizations across
various industries, and there are
these three systemic gaps that surface
again and again across all of them.
The first one being.
Lack of standardization.
Everyone collects data, but nobody
translates it in the same way.
What I mean by that is there is
no consistent methodology for
turning raw scan output into
health signals, which means no two
teams measure things the same way.
The second one is inconsistent threshold.
Teams are defining their own
acceptable limits, their own threshold.
So one group might consider
a 32nd bill delay acceptable
versus while other would not.
Security exceptions may be strict in
one unit, but relax in another unit.
This inconsistency, undermines
benchmarking and meaningful
improvement systemically.
The third one is missing
remediation guidance.
Even when a problem is identified,
teams don't know what to do next.
What is the next best action to take?
Is this a configuration fix?
Is this a redesign?
Is this a backlog item?
How do I actually move forward?
So our framework addresses all of these
three gaps by grounding these thresholds,
maturity levels, and remediation
pathways across the research that we did.
So let's talk about this framework and
the four dimensions associated with it.
So instead of drowning in dozens
of disconnected metrics, these are
the four dimensions that we have
distilled DevSecOps health into
these act as pillars of a secure,
sustainable, and scalable ecosystem.
The first one being platform
efficiency, meaning how effective and
stable your underlying platforms are.
The second one, customization.
Resilience, meaning how safely you
diverge from vendor or community defaults.
The third one, observability meaning
how deeply you understand your
application and system behavior.
And the fourth one, security guardrail
adherence, meaning how consistently
teams follow automated, preventative
detective and corrective controls when
assessed together these dimensions.
Give you a 360 view of your
security posture, not only
in theory, but in reality.
Now, let's deep dive into each one
of these dimensions and understand a
little bit more about what they mean.
So the first one is platform efficiency.
We start with platform efficiency
because nothing else matters if the
foundation itself is shaky, right?
Security cannot just be bolted on.
It cannot be something you add
once everything else is finished.
It must be embedded inside
a performant and scalable,
stable and resilient platform.
Here's why, right?
If builds are slow, developers
are gonna bypass the gates.
If infrastructure provisioning is
sluggish, incident response slows.
If reliability is low, teams
constantly are in that firefight
mode, and when you're firefighting,
you're not proactively securing.
So what are some of these key
indicators of platform efficiency?
The top four are pipeline performance.
We all no long builds in white shortcuts,
so pipeline performance is key.
Second one is provisioning speed,
'cause that impacts your blast
radius and response window.
The third one is resource utilization.
Shows whether systems are tuned correctly
or accumulating silent technical debt
and reliability.
Frequent outages, degrade
trust in security processes.
So a secure organization is first
and foremost an efficient one.
Hence platform efficiency is
one of the key dimensions here.
Alright, let's talk about
the second dimension.
Customization, resilience.
This is one of the most underestimated
sources of incidents, customization.
They involve, they evolve, they
drift, they become outdated.
Customizations get orphaned.
Uh, and that accumulates tech debt, right?
And many of them inadvertently
introduce vulnerabilities.
We classify maturity
in these three levels.
Low maturity, meaning everything
is customized, nothing is tracked.
The security implications in this
case are wild and unknown, right?
And teams inherit this fragmented,
inconsistent ecosystem,
which is not sustainable.
The next level is the developing
maturity where teams maintain
a customization registry.
At least basic reviews are happening,
but still like the long-term governance
is missing from the picture, which
is where the high maturity comes in.
This is where the magic happens, right?
Customizations have clear owners,
lifecycle management exists.
Deprecation is intentional.
It is regular.
Testing coverage is deep and wide, and the
security reviews aren't just ceremonial.
They are meaningful.
This dimension, as you can
see, helps organization balance
between what they must customize
and with what they cannot break.
Security hardening by over customizing.
Alright, the third dimension
talks about observability.
Right.
Observability is one of the most powerful
predictors of incident reduction, right?
It tells you what happened,
why it happened, where it
happened, and what it touched.
So observability spans
across these four layers.
Application instrumentation, which is
all about, you know, code level behavior
and application logic, execution,
infrastructure, telemetry that talks
about system level patterns, revealing
source usage and performance indicator.
Security event aggregation, that all
these logs that come from scanners
identity system and the correlation
across these distributed systems.
And the last one is trace propagation,
which is all about understanding attack
paths across these microservices.
But what are the security benefits
behind, you know, implementing
a robust observability platform?
Well, it gives you earlier detection.
You can catch these anomalies
before they become breaches, and
everyone wants to do that, right?
The second one is faster investigation.
It's all about, you know, reducing
your mean time to detect your mean time
to remediate, and these containment
time so that you are investigating as
fast as possible and you're reducing
your SLA or you do reducing your
turnaround time because that all.
Has a business impact.
The third one is control validation.
You empirically see what guardrails
are walking, validating those
security control effectiveness through
empirical measure measurements.
And the last one is continuous learning.
Learning from the past incidents
through post mortem analysis.
'cause every incident becomes a source
of this pattern based improvement.
So strong observability isn't optional.
It's foundational.
So the first dimension that I
talked about in the previous slide
is security guardrail, adherence.
Guardrails generally fall into
these three categories, preventative
detective and corrective.
But the real differentiator
here is the maturity.
High performing organizations
don't just create cartridge.
They are operationalizing it so that
leadership enforces them consistently.
These the exceptions are
clear and controlled.
The signals are continuously
refined and the feedback loops are
integrated into development workflows.
When guardrail adherence is high, security
becomes the fastest path, not the slowest.
So now that we have talked about all
these four dimensions of the framework,
let's talk about the methodology and
you know, measuring what matters.
So our measurement approach uses a
layered data collection architecture.
Why layers?
Because each dimension needs
a different data source.
Monitoring tools, repost,
storing configuration.
Logging and tracing platforms, scanning
engines, and policy frameworks.
All these have different data sources,
so automation is non-negotiable.
Manual processes create
inconsistency and they don't scale.
So we also incorporate data quality
validation because missing or incomplete
data often reveals infrastructure
issues that we didn't know we had.
Right.
So automated collection priority and
data quality validation are the two
main concepts to prioritize here.
Now, when we talk about establishing
thresholds, what we want to avoid is
one site, one size fits all number.
Instead, we created three
performance tiers, baseline
meaning foundational health target.
Meaning competitive performance
and excellence, meaning industry
leading outcomes, which is where
industry leader performance achieved
by top performing organizations.
So the key principle here is
thresholds must remain stable over time.
Only then can an organization truly
understand improvement versus fluctuation.
Let's talk about some of the different
industries that adapted these, this
framework to their unique constraints.
Healthcare where security intersects
with patient safety, custom
guardrails for medical device and
data needed, and there's a significant
compliance lift as well in retail.
There's elastic infrastructure that
is needed with high seasonal velocity.
Payment systems are required
with restricted thresholds.
Now, when you, when it comes to financial
services, that's where like the most
advanced customization governance
lives, and there's a heavy emphasis on
resilience and regulatory stability.
Last but not the least, we also looked
at manufacturing industry where.
IT Convergence creates special
safety critical requirements and
guardrails had to account for legacy
systems and long deployment cycles.
This cross-industry validation
demonstrates the framework's
flexibility and robustness.
So what were some of
these measurable results?
Uh, when we wanted to quantify our impact?
Right.
The organizations that implemented
all four dimensions saw very
powerful and tangible outcomes.
Actually, there was a major
reduction in successful attacks.
There's a stronger operational resilience
across the board, faster and cleaner
incident responses with shorter release
cycles, and there's fewer production
defects that coupled with optimized
resource optimization utilization.
And increased developer trust, right?
These were not just theoretical results,
they were real measurable improvements
based on using this framework.
Now, how do you get started on this, uh,
on, you know, implementing this framework?
Right?
The first thing to do here is
doing a baseline assessment.
Understand your starting point, right?
Conduct a comprehensive assessment of all
these four dimensions and establishing
starting points in each of these areas.
The second one is stakeholder engagement.
Align your stakeholders from various,
um, cross-functional teams, including
security development, operations, product,
and establishing those regular health
review forums for cross-functional
collaboration and strategic planning.
Capacity development, build that
statistical literacy, those RCA, the
root cause analysis skills, right?
And develop these specialized
DevSecOps health roles and
champions across the company.
Then you get into the phased
implementation aspect of it.
Begin with platform efficiency and
security guardrails for quick wins.
Those are essential and you
need to build upon them.
Then progress to customization,
resilience, and observability,
which require a little bit
more of instrumentation.
In terms of tool
integration, keep it simple.
Leverage existing tools
that you currently have.
Start by what you already
have, and less is more.
In this case, continuous improvement.
That's all about establishing
your regular review cycles.
Uh, to assess the
framework's effectiveness.
If you need to tweak something, maintain
that governance process, ensuring
regular evolution of version control.
Ultimately, the DevSecOps Health
Framework represents a paradigm shift,
the shift conversion, the, the shift con.
This shifts conversations
from opinions to data.
From reactive firefighting to
proactive prevention and from
siloed metrics to holistic health.
Looking ahead, this framework will
also start to incorporate AI driven
operations, confidential computing,
third party risks, supply chain
security, and other things like that.
So this journey towards DevSecOps
Health Excellence begins with honesty,
gains momentum through discipline,
and sustains itself through evolution.
The question is in whether
to pursue this or not.
It's how fast your organizations
can start with this.
So thank you.
Thank you for your time and attention.
I hope this session empowers
you to rethink DevSecOps Health
holistically and strategically.
I.