Hi.
Hello everyone.
Myself, Hamdi.
I'm a senior mobile developer
slash like a mobile architect.
Today's my topic is securing
healthcare at scale dev DevOps
for critical patient platforms.
So as a mobile architect overeducated
in health technology have navigated
the complex intersections of security.
Complaints and patient safety while
building platforms that solves like
millions of patients across cancer
centers and different organizations,
health organizations nationwide.
This presentation says how we
implemented DevSecOps for my story.
So this application is a award-winning
trademark mobile health and cancer.
Cancer patients like a
symptom tracking application.
So this platform supporting active
clinical trials at institutions.
So the stakes of healthcare security.
So generally in the health technology,
the stakes are immensely high.
The security failures aren't
merely embarrassing incidents.
So if you take any examples, there
are lot of security failures.
So they are direct threats to
patient lives and public trust.
So whenever there is something
happened in the healthcare industry
that might affect a lot of patients.
So consider this critical
chain a patient's.
Chemotherapy remain relies impact fully
implicitly precise data transmission.
So the integrity of lifesaving clinical
trials results in based on the data,
what we data, what kind of data we
selected, what kind of data we got, and
deeply personal information there in
the healthcare applications as we know.
So in this landscape, very in the
landscape, the very concept of
margin for error is eradicated.
So the small error like affect a
lot of patients information the
PA data leakage, those things.
So we have to take care of all the
security things considerable rely on
that traditional security para paradigms.
Where the safeguards are related to
the final predeployment checkpoint.
It's not just a it is not
just in the intake industry.
It's it is dangerously absolute
for a security is not a future.
It's like foundation upon which
digital health solution must be built.
Like when we like building the application
we considered all these security concerns.
What kind of PI data is there?
What kind of information?
We have to be secure while
releasing the stores.
DevSecOps represent a paradigm script.
So basically it's it's not just a process.
It's like a profound culture
and operational transformation.
So strategically integrating
security into every facet of
healthcare technology lifecycle.
So this means proactively emit a
robust security measures directly
into the development phase for example
modeling, securing design principles
throughout the con continuous,
static and dynamic code analysis.
With automated CSD pipelines catching
vulnerabilities, long before deployment.
So basically when we like deploy the
applications in the DevSecOps, we are
like putting like a security scans
using Soner, Google or some other tools.
So we scan all the application we'll
try to find like a, before releasing
the application, we'll try to find
where are the loopholes, where are the.
Security security gaps are there.
We identify by using these gaps, like
operations are deeply infused in security
places like involving cons, constant
monitoring, automated compliance checks,
proactive vulnerability management, and
redefined incident response strategies.
So ensure all unparalleled
systems readability ultimately.
District Cups cultivates a shared
responsible across all teams.
So generally, like when we develop, like
we have a frontend team, backend team
all the other teams are there so we have
to consider like each place where all
the teams are working what are the gaps
what kind of security, what kind of like
sensitive patient data we have to be.
Critical care to be considerable, we
have to take care of all those things.
So this day, historical approach ensures
resilience, trust, and is standards
of patient safety in a constant
evolving threat landscape generally.
The scammers are there, lot of scammers.
Everybody's trying to steal the data.
With the data like whatever data,
like for example, if we use any
patient information those things
like might affect in the industry.
So we have to take care exactly
what data we are collecting.
We have to give security for
the trust purpose for this.
Patients also need to be like very
confident on the application before using.
So this is healthcare security landscape.
So first one is like a
regulatory complexity.
So when we EPA establish the EPA
establishes baseline requirements,
but clinical trade introduce
FDA oversight state level
regulations, add another layer.
So basically on top of hip, we
are adding another layer for
international institutions.
Introduce, gDP are considerations also,
like for the international use, we are
using the other considerations also.
So our attack surface also data is
uniquely vulnerable to attackers.
Medical records sell for far more than
credit card numbers because they contain
information that can't be changed.
So because of this we have to be careful.
So the third one is patient safety.
Like when we build anything.
So we have to take care of,
security failures can directly
harm patients incorrect medication
diagnosis missed appointments or
delayed treatment represent security
failures with physical consequences.
So these are the three things we have to
be consider while we develop anything.
So this is like a mobile health
expands the attack service.
So data moves between patient
devices and cloud infrastructure.
Generally like a patient
enter the information by
using like a TPS or anything.
We just exchange the data between
that whatever database cloud
architecture we use those things
we do generally does, right?
So those things like a patient data should
be like, very we have to like encrypt
all the patient data, whatever we use,
so they connect unru networks that may
have another application with permissions
that could access sensitive data.
So we have to be careful whenever
we access, like Unru networks, the
offline requirements of healthcare
applications add complexity.
Patients need to access their health
information even without connectivity.
Hospitals with poor
representation reception.
During travel or rural areas.
So the mobile offline is
one of the other challenge.
So basically we, for this we
can come up with zero zero trust
architecture t as a parameter.
So first we choose like a multi-pack,
multi-factor authentication.
So in initial patient development
requires MF aide with the verified
health system credentials, patient
don't reply simply create accounts.
They have provision through
secure enrollment process.
For example when you create account we.
We have all this authentication
to some other things we develop.
So device binding after authentication,
we crypto ly bind patient's identity to
their specific device, prevent credentials
trip from immediate compromising access.
So this is like device binding is one
of the other security, we can build
on top of multifactor authentication.
And the third one is like
a biometric authentication.
So by using fingerprints or face id by
these two things, we will add another
authentication for the enrolled devices.
Fourth one is like
continuous verification.
So generally by using tokens,
every 15 minutes, 10 minutes,
the token will refresh.
So if the application aid is
ideal, the lifetime of the
application will automatically
kill that particular session.
If they want, again, they have to log in.
So these four things we'll
consider for the security.
So this is end-to-end
encryption architecture.
So the data centric security.
So first one is device encryption.
So as I told device encryption before,
leaving a patient device data encrypted,
so that transit protection, encrypted
transmission with certificate pending.
So the certificate winning is another
concept for the data data encryption.
So storage, security encrypted address
with the hierarchical key management.
The fourth one is authorized access.
So decryption only
authorized devices can do.
So this way, the before sending
the data this way, this is the
encryption decryption method we use
to secure the patient information.
So the key DevSecOps implementation,
so first one is end-to-end encryption.
So the zero trust architecture
with Oracle Key management and
device planning is the first thing.
Second thing is automated
security testing.
So CIDC, CICD pipelines with
static analysis, dependency
scanning, and dynamic testing.
So these are three things we can do
and do automative security testing.
So offline fast design.
So secure local storage with the conflict
resolution and data integrity controls.
So this is the third step.
The fourth step is compliance as a code.
So automated validations of IPA MDA
are other regulatory requirements
that we have to be considered.
So fourth one is real time monitoring.
So continuous security monitoring
with automated instance response
we have to be considered.
So these are the five key
implementations we have d we consider.
So the other one is automate.
So the automating compliance
infrastructure as a code.
So healthcare regulations feel
like immovable constraints,
so they dev a cup inwards.
This relationship treating complaints
as a dynamic requirements that
automation can continuously verify.
So the IPA requirements as a IPA requires
a encryption that rest in translate.
Our infrastructure code
enforces this by refusing.
To proven storage of network without
appropriate encryption configurations.
So generally as a policy, as a core
tools validate infrastructure, agonistic
complaints, requirements before the
application deployment, attempting
to deploy database without encryption
triggers immediate rejection with
clear explanation of which complaints
requirement would be violated.
So these things we will
do as part of the process.
So this is the layers of the CICD.
So first one is we'll do
like a static analysis.
The static analysis.
We analyze the code the catches,
like a hard coded credentials
and also the skill injection.
Any crypto insecure
implementation we will find.
Second one is dependency scanning.
So in the dependency scanning, we
will check like every third party.
Library for known vulnerabilities.
If there is any vulnerabilities,
we will block the deployment.
Third one is dynamic testing.
So dynamic testing, stimulus
attacks, organized running
applications, so authentication,
bypass, and authentication.
Failures will test.
Fourth one is container scanning.
So we'll scan the containers
based on the images.
Verified security best practices.
And fifth one is a p security.
So part of the backend APIs, we will test
the unauthorized access and rate limit.
So we will check all those things.
Offline first, architecture challenges.
So these are the, some challenges
for the offline first mobile
development architecture.
So secure local storage.
So full device encryption as
a base baseline production.
So this is the one, first one.
So application level encryption
required for with the keys
derived from patient credentials.
So secure element integration
and hard hardware protected keys.
Also, we have to implement, so
biometric authentication, the other one.
So conflict resolution vector clocks
track modification history, operational
transplant, maintain eventual consistency.
Complete audit trails
for all offline changes.
So these are the conflict resolution
things we have to be take care.
So continuous security monitoring.
For the this application, so
we have to be secure comp.
These are the four steps.
So application monitoring.
And so we have to be always
monitor the application.
So the second one is
infrastructure monitoring.
So observe like a system behavior and
is any potential attacks we have to be.
And also all the authentication
attempts any in the network.
Unusual traffic generates any secural.
These are the things we have to take care.
The other one is audit log analysis.
We have to be.
Detailed records of all security relevant
events, automate analysis, identifies
suspicious pattern authentication,
data access and configuration changes.
So anything happen, we
have to check this Also.
The other one is behavior
analytics submission, learning
models learn typical patterns for
individual patients and clinicals.
So is any like those kind of things
models or anything he's doing?
So we have to be, take care and
continuous monitoring all this process.
So platform success metrics.
So these are the platform success metrics.
So first one is like enhance
the patient engagement.
Second one is a compliance.
Third one is the data breaches.
Fourth one is un
uninterrupted availability.
So the platform country
consistently achieves significantly
higher patient engagement.
So this is one thing for the
enhance the patient engagement.
Second one is like we have to
check like HIPAA validations,
unwrapping ONM commitment.
Un underwing.
A commitment builds profound trust in
both patients and healthcare providers.
So these things, we have to be
checked, zero data breaches.
So we have to be, take care,
like what kind of data and also
every time we have to be careful
with the patient information.
Fourth one is power, the
continuous monitoring and
automated incident response.
This is the one thing we have to care for.
We have to be, do every 20, 24
hours and seven days a week.
So response framework.
So detection analysis is the first thing.
So we have to be like,
check any detections.
So this thing we have to check.
The containment is a second thing.
So any limit impact, isolate by systems,
revoking, compromise, credentials.
So those things we have to check.
So eradication, it's the third thing.
Remote rates from systems by fixing
vulnerabilities, improving security
controls and updating configurations.
So recovery, the fourth thing,
validate rates are eliminated.
The restore systems can secure
state and gradually store service
while monitoring recurrence.
So the last one is post instant analysis.
So security as a foundation.
DevSecOps in healthcare represents
more than implementing security
tools for following complaints.
At least It reflects a fundamental
philosophy that the security,
privacy and patient safety are
the foundational requirements
rather than futures to be added.
So the My Story platform
demonstrates that robust security
flood practices and excellent user
experience aren't opposing goals.
Success requires cultural change.
Alongside technical
implementation, security becomes
everyone's responsibility.
So the patient trust depends on security.
When patients here intimate health
information, so when they rely on
application during vulnerable moments,
when they trust systems with data
that could literally save their
lives, robust security isn't optional.
Thank you.
Thank you for giving me this opportunity.
Yeah.
If you have any questions,
please send an email.