My name is Åukasz.
I'm a security solution
architect at G Core.
Firstly, thank you for organizing
this conference, CON42.
I'm excited to talk to you
about our comprehensive approach
here at G Core to protect
infrastructure from Adidas attacks.
Also, why connecting web application
protection with protecting infrastructure
is crucial in current times.
During my talk, feel free
to ping me over Slack.
If you have any questions or comments,
I will do my best to answer all of them.
Firstly, I want to, in my speech, talk
about the G Core infrastructure, what the
cyber security means in current times.
also about the DDoS attack, what
the DDoS attack means, protecting
your infrastructure with the G Core.
firstly, let's go to the
G Core infrastructure.
G Core, so we are a global
company, It means that we are
located across the whole world.
You can find our point of
presence across the whole world.
We have more than 180 points of
Also, we have more than
50 cloud locations.
We are located in Luxembourg.
There we have the headquarter.
But also, like I said, we
have the global presence.
At the core of our industry, this
is the low latency secure network.
It means that we are focusing
to provide a low latency network
for all of our customers.
Also, what we can say that due to that
our network capabilities, we are more than
sure we are able to handle everything,
all the traffic that is coming to us.
Also, the biggest DDoS attacks, but about
that, I will tell you a bit later on.
what the cyber security means.
so cyber security, okay.
Cyber security is very, very large topic.
So what that means that protecting
and monitoring, we need to
protect and monitor everything.
Yeah.
Why not everything?
It's impossible.
But let's split it.
So we need to protect the
Network, of course network.
This is the core thing for most
of us, most of our businesses.
Endpoints.
physical endpoint, physical end
devices in each of the company.
This is crucial that we need to protect
them and monitor what users are, what
users of our, in our company are doing.
What, our, workers are
doing on the devices.
This is crucial from the security
point of view, from the cybersecurity.
Later on, applications.
Also web applications.
Yeah.
And also the applications
that we have on our endpoints.
Yeah.
Web applications.
We need to monitor them and
we need to protect them.
Web applications, crucial for
our business, for most of us.
later on access.
I am so connect.
So privileges and the,
what the users can perform.
This is crucial to protect
and monitor what the users
can do and what they can do.
Provide the lowest privileges
that they should have.
To just be sure that we are not providing
something access to something someone
shouldn't have access for so All of
this, we are going to the cyber threats.
Cyber threats are escalating.
Yeah, everyone will agree.
I don't think so that we'll have
here someone who will say that
cyber threats are not escalating
and they are decreasing.
No, cyber threats are increasing a lot.
We received, a lot of reports
that this, this rise in the cyber
threats is parabolic currently.
Maybe later on in the coming years, it
will, just be increased step by step.
Maybe due to AI, due to maybe
machine learning, we'll be able to
like, reduce the, the rise of the
cyber threats at least by something.
But currently, I don't think so.
cyber threats are rising.
It means that the crimes, the
number of the crimes, cyber
crimes, will be more and more.
For us, it means that we have
more and more DDoS attacks.
So we have more applications to protect,
more infrastructure to protect, more
servers that we need to protect.
So more things that we need to protect,
number of the attacks are increasing,
so we have like more servers, more
attacks, more different types of attack.
So we have disaster from
security point of view.
Yeah, and here we have G Core
to protect you from everything.
Okay, from near everything.
Okay.
like I said, number of the trees
is increasing and the scale of
this increasing also the scale
or the DDoS attack is increasing.
So this is the, this is with
what the people need to face.
in case that's okay, our
security, protocols, everything
that we have from security point
of view is fine here and now.
Here and now our network capabilities for,
dealing with the DDoS attack are fine.
But what about in five years?
What about in 10 years?
Are we sure that without doing
anything that will increase our
capabilities to deal with the cyber
threats, we'll stay on this business.
We'll stay on the network.
We'll be visible.
We'll be able to provide the
services to our customer.
I don't think so.
To be honest, you need to,
increase your security level.
Constantly, you need
to increase, increase.
You need to build better services.
You need to build more services.
You need to build everything, better,
more and bigger infrastructure.
going further, what about the DDoS attack?
DDoS attacks?
We can have one attack.
Maybe we have more attacks.
Yeah.
So we have, mostly three different
types of the DDoS attack.
The first, the three, the most common
one, to be honest, Volumetric attack.
It means that, we have an attacker
that is sending tons of the request,
like we can imagine millions, the whole
ocean of the request of the traffic
that is coming to our, backend server.
And our server won't be
able to deal with it.
I'm more than sure that in case of DDoS
attack without any protection, 99 slash 9.
9999 percent of the
servers will be taken down.
Of course, in case that there
will be small DDoS attack.
In such case, maybe server will
survive and we'll have super,
server from, from future.
So volumetric attacks.
So here we have the tons of the
requests, a lot of requests.
Mostly it means that
there is like this attack.
We'll try to use all the bandwidth, all
the resources that we have on the server,
on the bandwidth that we have available.
Mostly here, attackers are
using EDP flat, ECMP flats.
So.
IPsec flat.
So a lot of, packets that they
are just spamming with it.
Spamming, there is totally
spam on this request.
And there is like near zero
of the good requests here.
So this is a typical volumetric attack.
Later on, we have, connection attacks.
So here we have the attacks that
they are just, creating attacker
is creating here the connection
and never ending this connection.
It means that we have the one user
that is logging into the shop.
For example, the webshop, adding
something to the cart and doing nothing.
And we have 10, 000 such, clients.
Okay.
That will just over That will
just use all of our resources
that the server does we have.
Later on, what in case that
we have the game server?
And we have the, attacker
that is establishing 20.
Thousand or twenty millions connections
to the server from the one user.
That's possible.
And in such case, without a
DDoS protection, this user, this
attacker, being Tritos a normal
user, will just use all the resources
that we'll have on our server.
So here attackers mostly use the,
like previously UDP TCP protocol,
but mostly this part that is
responsible for keeping the connection.
So the connection is still kept open.
So the connection is keep open
forever until we from the server
side, we will close this connection.
So it means that if the
connection is never closed.
So we have problem because our server
soon will be out of the resources.
And if we don't have the
resources for attacker, great.
But in the same time, we have normal
user who want to perform some actions.
In such case, he won't be able to do that.
Due to that, Without, that the user won't
be able to perform normal actions due to
the older resources are reserved for the
non existing user, for the connections
that there are opened by the attacker.
It means we are just, we have the problem.
We have the problem because normal user is
not able to perform any actions later on.
So these two, types of the attack, they
are mostly on the layer three, layer four.
So on the layer seven, we
have the application attacks.
Application attacks, they are mostly
focusing on the complexity of the attack.
They are trying to use some kind of
the vulnerabilities on the server,
vulnerabilities on the web application.
So it means that we'll try
to use some kind of the small
part of the volume that we can.
to just use the server in a way
that he will, for example, do some
recurrences, do some loop inside the,
some, some processes on the server.
And in this way, we'll just use all the
resources on the machine, on the server,
and that server will won't be able to
response for the normal user activities.
So that's the issue.
That's the problem that
we are facing here.
The application attacks.
Okay.
What's further?
So we have the attacks, we have the
attacks, and we have challenges.
Yeah, because we have attacks
and we have challenges.
What the good DDoS protection
will be able to handle?
What good DDoS protection
will be able to do?
Firstly, real time protection.
Real time protection is
crucial in current times.
Can you imagine that?
Okay, we have two scenarios.
We have a DDoS protection that
is providing the protection
since beginning, always on.
Full traffic is filtered and second
protection that is filtering 100
percent of the DDoS attack, but after
one minute, you have 100 percent
fully mitigating all the DDoS attack.
You know what?
the first DDoS protection will be
better if we protect from the, even
for example, it will be cheaper.
80 percent 90 percent and he will do
the same because he will first clean all
the traffic and the second protection
will be much cheaper But it will clean
the traffic from the first after first
minute in the one minutes Attacker will
be able to for example sent to you one
terabit per second over 60 seconds.
I Don't think so that we have the server
in the world that will be able to handle
one terabit per second over Constantly
one minute I don't think so that we
have server like that on the world.
The issue that we are facing
with the DDoS protection, this
is the real time protection.
It means that all the traffic
that is delivered to the server,
it must be already clean.
And this is the approach that, for
example, we at GCON, we are doing.
So we are, be sure that the
traffic that is sent to our
customers is already cleaned.
If you are not cleaning, firstly, the
whole incoming traffic, that's the issue.
That's the big issue, because you
are allowing the attacker to send
the malicious request, malicious
payload, malicious amount of the huge
amount of the traffic to the server.
Even after one minute,
you will clean everything.
The server will be already down
after this one minute, or maybe
not responsible for, I don't know,
a few hours without resetting.
So that's the issue.
That's why the real protection is needed.
Also, okay, we have two
different scenarios, the web
application and the game server.
For the web application Okay, after
one minute, maybe we restart the
server, everything that will be fine
because we have this protection.
Okay, maybe someone want to make this
approach, but what about the game server?
Okay, about the game server, if we have
the game server, we need protection
here, now, in real time, always.
I can't imagine that someone who is
hosting, for example, the game and have
thousands of the servers will allow to
restart all of the servers After one
minute, because the DDoS attack happened,
I think he will have tons of the angry
players that will stop playing his game.
They will leave the game, they
will leave the server, they will
stop buying something in the
shop, for example, from this game.
So that's the huge problem.
Going further, network code design.
This is a challenge for
Intuitus Protection.
Because, for example, if we take the
game servers, the netcode of the games.
Games, different games
using different netcode.
It means that different netcode.
it's used by different games.
So we have.
We can have thousands of the different
type of the, we can have thousands of
the different and network code design
are more than sure in at least even
1 percent of this code is vulnerable.
We have problem for this game
that there is in this protocol
because, attackers will more than
sure use this vulnerabilities.
So here we need a DDoS attack that will
be preventing from exploiting such things.
In case that, okay, there will be
vulnerable, vulnerability that will
allow attackers to use something.
But in front of it, we have the DDoS
protection that is blocking all of the
malicious requests based on some rules.
Yeah, with this approach, we can
leave the DDoS protection part.
from the network code design.
Of course, code should be good, but we
can left this network code design part
to the DDoS protection solution to be
sure that the DDoS protection solution
will prevent everything from that.
It will prevent the attackers
from using these vulnerabilities.
Later on, we have the evolving threats.
Like I said at the beginning,
threats are evolving.
Okay.
I will tell a bit later on, but also
Evolving threats, what we are facing
currently, what scenarios we are, this
is scenarios from the real cases, like
attackers are doing a lot of work,
they are spending a lot of money to
just realize that the user, that the
customer is, for example, hosting
the web server, the web application
on the same machine, on the same
network, that also the infrastructure,
for example, the game servers.
We have the case that the someone is using
the, someone's hosting the game server,
for example, I don't know, Minecraft.
We have the Minecraft server,
and we have also the, some shop
inside the Minecraft server.
And maybe this shop is on
the same machine, on the same
network that is the game server.
So maybe we can use the web
application that is not using the
web application firewall to take down
the infrastructure, to take down the
server, the game server, and vice versa.
Maybe we'll be able to take down the
web application taking down the whole
infrastructure by taking down the game
server if we don't use here, if we don't
use here the full comprehensive approach.
Also, using bot, botnets, this
is also a huge problem for future
and also for current times.
Going further, high performance
infrastructure, crucial point because I
can't imagine that someone will be able
to handle a huge DDoS attacks without
the good infrastructure, good performance
on this infrastructure, and good quality
of the service that he is providing.
Without the good infrastructure, you are
not able to provide the good service.
So we need high performance, super
fast servers, and super good fast DDoS
protection with the lowest latency.
Because of great.
All kinds of the, all kinds of the
protections, adding some latency.
Here at G Core, we are providing the
lowest latency that is possible for
our customers, because we are the
closest, and the closest source, we
are the closest on the source attack
that's possible to reduce the latency,
to reduce the risk for our customers.
Going further.
we have Nudinus protection and
we have the web application.
Okay, so we have the web application.
When we have the web application, we
need also, we need to protect it from the
latest attacks, layer three, layer four,
mostly, for example, the infrastructure
and also the web application.
For protecting the web application,
the typical web application firewall.
Yeah, because we need it.
This is I can't imagine going live
with even a library with a non profit
sample, non profit service, non profit
application without the simplest, at
least the simple web application firewall.
This is totally no go from
security point of view.
Later on, bot management.
We have good bots and bad bots.
Good bots, they are bots that they are,
for example, they are the web search bots.
Indexing bots and other bots like that.
They are good one.
We want to allow them to flourish
our application but in the same
time we don't want to allow bad bots
like Scrapping bots, some bots that
they are doing some autonomous test,
penetration test on our website.
We don't want such bots
and we need to block them.
We need to block them on
the application layer.
Later on, we have a DDoS protection.
We have the layer 3, layer
4 DDoS protection, but also
unvolumetric attacks there.
And also we have the volumetric
attacks on the layer 7.
Yeah, it happens.
Why not?
We have, you can have tons of the
middle, have tons of their, DDoS attack
that they're on the layer seven and
they are, for example, the HTTP floats.
Yeah, why not?
Attackers can do that, can send that.
So we need also the DDoS protection, also
the volumetric one on the layer seven.
For that, you need the huge
infrastructure, you need
huge network capabilities.
API security.
This is like also very important thing.
I can't imagine that you, just, running
application, running some services.
We want API protection in the
current times with the current
solutions with the current threats
that they're arising This is crucial
points and everything like that.
You have for example in our solution in
our web solution Going further we have
a we discussed the two layers of the
DDoS protection to be honest This is
the free layer from the technical point
of view Layer 3, Layer 4, and Layer 7.
But let's split it here as two layers.
Layer 3 and 4, protecting the
infrastructure, and Layer 7,
protecting the web application.
For the protecting the infrastructure,
so our main objective is to
protect the infrastructure, the
servers, the network, the heart,
the inside, the core of everything.
Here on the web application side, we
are like protecting the infrastructure.
the web application, it can be, we
can say that this is the front end,
front to the front end for the, for our
customers, for our clients that they
will use, for example, some e commerce
shops, some shops, they will try to,
for example, make some, actions on the
bank accounts, other things like that
on the layer three, layer four, we are
focusing against, to protect against
the, attacks that will exhaust network
bandwidth, and they will just overhaul
our resources that we have on our servers.
On the web application
side, we have same risks.
And also, additionally, we need to figure
out that if the attacks want to use
vulnerabilities on our web application.
I can't imagine that we're running
web application without the WAF,
and we have vulnerability that will
allow, for example, have negative
balance on the bank account.
You know what?
I don't think so.
That's, that will be good from
the reputation point of view.
Speaking about the reputation, we'll
tell, we'll speak about it later on.
Going further.
So we have the DDoS attack.
And what in case that we have a
typical small customer that is
using, for example, a few servers.
Oh, maybe some tools like some
small WAF, maybe some, let's say,
manual DDoS protection rules.
In case of the DDoS attack, his chances
to survive are near zero, because
this is like he's trying to build the
protection without having enough tools.
For example, I can imagine that it would
be similar situation like we are trying
to build a wall without the tools,
wall for example from the bricks, but
we can't make bricks, because we don't
have enough tools, or we can't cut the
tree to build some polysate, because
we don't have also the tools to that.
In such case, here, the user, the
person that is trying to protect
himself and his infrastructure from
this attack, without the tools, his
chances to survive are near zero.
But when he will start using some tools,
he recognize that, okay, I have more
tools, I have more options, I have more
capabilities to deal with the attacker.
Maybe I will be able to survive and
my business will be on the Good road.
Yeah.
But you to that, to do that,
you need the D protection.
You need some tools.
Tools can bring, you are bring by the
D protection or the web application
protection, by the, by the solutions.
like our, when we are able to provide
the tools for our customers to
survive the DS attack, to survive the
attacks from the attackers survive
on the current of the current risks.
But when we have a DS attack.
Okay, we have a news attack.
Let's say we blocked 50 percent of
the traffic with our manual tools.
We didn't use any advanced provider.
And okay, we survived somehow,
but we had a few hours of
interruption of our services.
Our database is somewhere in the dark web.
Okay, and what's now?
Okay, we have problem.
Yeah.
In such cases, we have problem.
So going this direction, such user,
such typical small company will have
issues from the financial point of view.
Yeah.
Because first of all, for example,
that was the webshop and they were
not able to, users are not able to,
make some transactions on the website.
Yeah.
Okay.
We are, we lost revenue, but what in case
that We had also some legal consequences
from that point of view, because we had
some agreement with other companies that
in case that, we won't be able to sell
some kind of the shoes or something.
Let's say shoes, let's take the shoes.
in the same time, we need to pay the fee
because we, our shop was unable to sell.
We are unable to sell the shoes for 10
percent of the time during, for example,
one week or one month or one day.
And due to that, we need to pay the fee
because we agree on such agreements.
Thanks.
So we have second time we have
the financial use first one users
Customers didn't buy something
in a web shop second one.
We need to pay the fee So combining
these two things we have we are
losing reputation This is we are
losing the trust in our business.
this is very good.
This is very important point
of view going further comparing
everything, we have disruption on
the operations that we are performing
and our users are able to perform.
Can you imagine that you are hosting
bank, international bank, and
your users are unable to perform
international bank transfer, or
maybe you are not able to send a bank
transfer between different banks.
, that's issue because for example,
what in case that you want, you
are not able to pay the law.
If you are a bank and you need to pay
the law or something like that, we are
backing to the legal sequence and this
is why, because there was a attack
and you didn't realize that maybe you
need some protection going further.
Customer impact, this is the issue that's.
Many, I'm still facing this
and, that people don't recognize
that the customer is a king.
Customer is the king.
This is the truth.
And we need to agree on that.
Customer impact from the attack is huge.
What in case that we have the group of
friends, like 10 people, 10 friends, that
they want to play some game, they buy the
server from some hosting provider, let's
say they want to play Minecraft, they want
to build some houses on the Minecraft.
Okay, great.
What in such case they buy the
server, they pay for the server on
the hosting that is under DDoS attack.
And the server is constantly down.
Okay, maybe they will survive somehow and
maybe they will play on this server when
there is outside of the DDoS attack hours.
But I'm more than sure later on they will
never ever back to this hosting company.
And also they will tell their friends
that don't go to this hosting company.
They are constantly under DDoS attack
because we didn't were able to play on the
Minecraft server that we paid the money.
So can you see that this
is like the spider web?
This is increasing, like the customers
are spreading the news, spreading
the truth that this hosting company
was not using the DDoS protection
at all, or maybe some pure one.
And we will pay for the server, but
we are unable to use the services.
And going further, we have
the competitive disadvantage.
With all these points, we have the
issue that these customers, they
will come to a different provider.
different hosting company,
we are losing the clients.
So we have minus one point and our
competitors are plus one point.
So the distance between us
and our competitors are two
points, everything due to that.
You didn't think about the use protection.
that's a problem that the people
are still not thinking about the
use protection and that's crucial.
So what to do, how to
survive in this cruel world?
Stay with the G core , protecting
infrastructure with the G Core.
So how, what we are using in
the G core, what's our, what's
our, approach at the G core?
So firstly, I want to show you
a quick video from the game,
from the inside the game.
On the left side, you will
see the, the video on the game
server that is unprotected.
And on the right side, the
server that is under the DDoS
protection from the G core side.
Game Counter Strike.
I think everyone played this
game or at least know this game.
So just please watch with me
As you can see on the left
side On the left side, we saw
that the screen was shaking.
The player was just constantly lagging.
There was literally unable to
play What will be your experience
from playing on the laggy server?
I think negative So you will just
let the server, let the game go
to a different server Provider.
Yeah, on the right side, smooth game,
no lags, everything was excellent.
So on the left side, okay,
what this person will think?
Okay, I don't want to play on the server.
I will go to a different server provider.
What about that?
That will be totally two
different games maybe?
And what in case that from the first
one, that next game that is not under
the users protection, the user will
decide to just leave the game, go
to a different game, and , he will
spend money on the different, on the
different game, on the different server.
So we always in clients due to that,
even if the server was still done up,
server was still up, it was working,
it was partially responding, but
it was lagging, extremely lagging.
That's the issue going further.
combining the web application protection
and the, and also the protecting
the infrastructure is crucial.
Why?
Because, okay, we have the
Layer 3, Layer 4 and Layer 7.
Protecting the infrastructure on the,
protecting the infrastructure on the
Layer 3, Layer 4 is different than
protecting the web application layer.
When you have here, for example, on this
slide, we have the , HTP flood attack.
We have excellent web application.
Firewall is blocking everything great.
We allow only valid HTP requests that will
come to our end point endpoint server.
Excellent.
And in the same time, attacker recognize
that, okay, we are in this network.
We have in this day, we
are in the data center.
This is our server, and he's
attacking our infrastructure
on the layer free layer four.
Our server will survive?
I don't think so.
We can have the best web
application firewall.
We have, we can have 20 different
web applications from a firewall,
each one behind each one.
But when we don't have the, any
protection for the infrastructure,
our server will be down.
Everything will be down.
Because, the server will be down
late on the, due to the attacks
of the layer three, layer four.
layer seven will have nothing to do with
it because there will be no server to,
to proceed the layer seven requests.
So this is why you need the,
protecting, you need to protect also
the infrastructure protection on the
layer three, layer four, in the same
time, protecting the web application.
So we need to protect
layer three, layer four.
Also, layer seven, what in case that you
have the game server, this is example from
the slide, what in case that you have the
game server and also the web shop that is
associated with this game server on the
same machine, you need to protect both.
You can't protect only the web server.
And.
will leave the game server
without the protection and
protect only the web application.
You can't do that because the attacker,
I'm more than sure they will check and
they will attack both in the same time.
And they will check which one
is down due to the attack.
And later on they will constantly
attack that one part that is
vulnerable without the protection.
So that's the problem and this is why
you need to protect the web application
and also the infrastructure G Corp,
provides the comprehensive solution.
You have the multi layer defense,
so we can protect against everything
we can protect against layer
three, layer four, we can protect
against the layer seven attacks.
We have everything that is available.
I think what we don't have, maybe
it's only some future technologies,
but to be honest, we have the
AI and I think soon maybe.
We have, we are working, constantly
on the good AI and I think, even
we'll have technologies from the
future that no one ever will have.
first, let's take a look
on the access control.
What in case that we have the two
different, two different servers,
game servers, one server in the US
and second one server in the Europe.
Firstly, on the server in the US, we want
this server to the users to play on the
from the US like the players from the
US and play on the servers in the US.
And for this server, we are
blocking access to the traffic
from the outside the US.
Great, because from the data, from
the security point of view, we are
just blocking most of the work.
So most of the attacks from the other
countries won't be able to, reach our
server because on the DDoS site we'll just
block this, we'll make it go blocking.
And the same for the Europe.
Traffic from the Europe stay in Europe,
traffic from the US stay in the US.
Right on, we have the right meaning.
Let's say that we need some limitations.
Let's say we have the Minecraft server.
Minecraft server, normal user,
let's say, can create maximum
5 connections in the same time.
So let's make a hard cap,
6 connections per user.
on our server.
Okay, great, because we are limiting
the number of the requests that
one user will be able to perform.
Backing to the previous slide,
we had the connection attacks.
From this part, we are complete, we are
safe because we are protecting against
such type of the attacks because we are
blocking the number of the requests,
number of the connections that the
attacker will be able to perform, reducing
the, the power of the attack in case
that we'll have something like that.
Later on, we have, let's
say, the packet validation.
In what in case that we don't want
to, proceed by our server, some of the
packets that they are like corrupted.
Let's say the network.
On the network side, there
was some malfunctions.
So there, there was like some device,
network device was not working correctly.
Some H route was not working
correctly on one of the ISP.
Okay.
We don't want to provide such packets
because we are not sure that if this
is the normal packet or maybe this
is the packet that they are sent by
attacker and they are just looking
like they are, not fully good.
there is something wrong in this
packet, so let's block them.
Yeah, why not?
The game will work, players will
be able to play, because we'll just
proceed only with the valid packet.
Later on, we have the machine
learning, behavior analyze.
Okay, what in case that we have in
this game, we have the web shop.
We have the web shop that
will be inside this game.
Like inside the pop up, the
screen, the web browser that
will be open inside the game.
It's possible.
let's say, And in this web, in
this web, in this webshop, players
can buy some, let's say, some
skins, some items in the game.
Everything is connected with the account.
Maybe you can add the credit card there.
this is a huge machine.
Everything is there.
Everything is inside the game.
And we have the connection, everything.
Our infrastructure, web application, and
also, players were able to pay there.
Okay.
And here we have someone that is adding
constantly 10, 000 things to the cart.
Okay, that's not normal.
And here we have the behavior analyze.
So we can check if this is normal
user or maybe this is not normal user.
I don't think so that normal
user will add 10, 000 different
items to the cart constantly.
This is not normal.
And here we have the behavior analyze
and our web can just block it based on
the behavior analyze because this is
not normal behavior for the normal user.
So this is like a huge.
With this approach that we have
in the G Core, you are able, we
are protected against the layer
3, layer 4 attacks because the
infrastructure is fully protected.
We are protecting against some,
against the other attacks based
on the signature analyzing.
We are protecting against the attacks.
And for example, the behavior,
use behavior analyze.
So this is huge.
So we are fully protected.
Everything in one place,
everything is global.
You can do it everywhere,
every, on each server.
So everything is fully automated.
You can use everything from the
set up everything from the home.
Excellent.
So later on we have the DDoS protection.
We have the WAP.
And also we have the CDN.
When can you have this?
let's say the example from the
previous slide, this webshop
that is inside the game.
Okay, maybe we have the servers
across the whole world and we want
to just reduce the latency that the
users are expecting, that they are
having in this webshop to minimum.
So we can use the CDN.
We don't use the CDN from the provider
that we are already using the WAF
and this, and the DDoS protection.
Everything is working correctly.
Everything in one place.
And also.
We have the DDoS protection
and the web also for the CDN.
Wow, looks good.
I don't think so that someone, some
attackers when they will see that
they can't break the layer freely for
protection on the infrastructure level.
They can break the web application and
they see right now, okay, the customer,
this person is also using the CDN.
Let's just leave and try to
find another person to attack.
Our CDN is also fully protected
against the DDoS attacks.
So it means that we are protecting
against the DDoS attack with the CDN
with the content that you never network.
We are also able to deliver everything
to our customers with the lowest latency.
So it means that if normally, let's say
the web shop will be loading in five
minutes, five minutes, three minutes,
maybe two minutes, because there will
be a lot of pictures, videos, maybe on
the website or something like that with
the CDN, it will load in 10 seconds.
Why?
This is huge.
This is huge reducing, let's say.
I don't think so that, users will say that
the loading as loading time three minutes
is better than 10 seconds, or maybe
one, maybe 30 seconds, even 20 seconds.
So this is everything.
That's everything that we
are providing in the G Core.
So we have the DDoS protection WAF, and
also we can combine the WAF and DDoS.
Inside the CDN, so we have we can
protect you against everything.
We can protect the infrastructure.
We can protect the web application layer.
That's looks good to be honest.
We have many companies, that trust us.
We have many companies,
many hosting providers.
We have many games that we are protecting.
Everyone is like happy from using us.
I'm more than sure that at least a few
websites that you visited, last time and
few games servers that you played and few
games that you played are protected by us.
And I'm more than sure you
expect you had there zero lags,
zero issues with everything.
I hope you enjoy the talk.
Thank you for joining me today.
Please reach out to me if you have any
questions or you want to discuss any
part of the solutions I presented today.
Have a great conference.
Stay safe with the G Core.
Bye.