Hello everyone, I will be talking about
identity federation This concept deals
with a single sign on a specific across
industries Here is an overview of what
I would like to present today coming to
the problem statement Looking at the key
challenges in digital identity management
A user, on an average, has to manage
100 passwords across online accounts.
What are the key issues here?
Password fatigue.
66 percent of individuals reuse passwords,
increasing vulnerability to breaches.
Then comes security risk.
60 per, 61 percent of the data breaches
involve compromised credentials.
And also human error, including
phishing attacks, is a significant
contribution for breaches.
Another issue is poor user
experience because 55 percent of
consumers have abandoned online
purchase due to forgotten passwords.
Then insufficient onboarding.
Financial institutions especially could
save up to 1 billion annually through a
streamlined identity verification process.
So this is where identity federation
comes into picture by definition identity
federation means a shared identity
model enabling a single identity to
be used across multiple institutions
Such as banks or health care providers
the key benefits are seamless single
sign on accessing multiple surveys with
one login improves a lot of convenience
for the user then enhanced security
this basically Because we are using
one single, uh user sso kind of feel
it reduces the password fatigue and
associated risk by then It strengthens
the cyber security Next it improves
user experience streamlines access
Leading to a higher user satisfaction
and engagement So what are the key
concepts of this identity federation?
First one is single sign on next
standardized identity attributes
Then come consent management And then
industry specific trust framework You
In a single sign on experience, user
authenticates once and gain access to
multiple services, reducing friction.
In a standardized identity attributes,
basically we define essential
attributes for key different industries.
For example, for banking, uh, we
can talk about name, financial
history, financial name.
Similarly, for healthcare, we can
talk about medical history, user
SSN, all these kind of fields.
Then come consent management.
Basically this empowers users to
control over data sharing ensuring
compliance and forecasting the trust
next industry specific trust framework
basically, this establishes rules
and standards for participation
ensuring security and privacy And
interoperability across entities.
Looking at the economic impact, uh,
the potential GDP growth could be
up to three to 13% by 2013 countries
implementing the Identity Federation
cost reductions are significant.
For example, organization reports a 50
percent reduction in these incidents that
are password related support incidents.
Then onboarding time in banking,
uh, got 80 percent reduction
saving significant resources.
Next come healthcare savings,
interoperable systems could yield
30 billion in annual savings,
improving overall efficiency.
Um, and how do we implement,
uh, in a technical perspective?
So first we have to, uh, set a
standard that needs to be utilized.
So we should extend the OAuth 2.
0 and OpenID Connect to
create a robust framework.
And what are the components here?
So, uh, Extended OAuth 2 scopes allow
for specific access permissions relevant
to each industry, enhancing security.
Then, federated identity providers.
Each institution acts as both a federated
identity and a service provider.
Enabling seamless user experience.
Then comes Attribute Exchange
Protocol, which enables secure
sharing of user attributes, which
encryption and digital signatures.
Next, Federation Registry,
a central repository for all
participating institutions.
And, uh, should maintain a
federated registry to ensure
transparency and security.
What are the industry
specific applications?
For example, if we look at, uh,
banking, the onboarding efficiency
increases, uh, with 80 percent
reduction in onboarding time.
Saving significant banking resources
Then comes service integration this
basically enhances customer retention
by providing seamless access to various
services Next come fraud reduction Shared
identity verification could lead to a 90
percent decrease in identity fraud Saving
the industry approximately 7 billion
dollars If you look at it similarly in
a health care industry, it could save
up to 30 billion in annual savings from
a streamlined patient record access.
It also improves care for patients
with complex histories, reducing
hospital readmission by 20%.
If you look at education, Uh credential
portability a federated system
could reduce transcript verification
Time by at least 90 percent easing
student transaction transitions Uh,
and and then come enrollment growth
simplified process could increase
adult learner learner enrollment by 25
Uh, however with a lot of advantages there
are a lot of challenges to adapt this Uh,
first of all, uh, regulatory compliance.
We must adhere to industry
specific standards as noncompliance
can lead to severe penalties.
Then centralized systems
may attract cyber threats.
Robust security measures are
essential to mitigate risks.
Protecting user data and ensuring
transparency in how data is
shared is crucial for trust.
Then come Uh, adoption and
interoperability collaboration
among industry players is necessary
to create interoperable standards
and drive widespread adoption.
If we can look at some kind of
strategic approach here, so regulatory
alignment, uh, basically designing
this identity federation framework
that inherently align with the key
regulation to streamline compliance.
Then we have to use
advanced security protocols.
It could be biometric
authentication, multi factor
authentication to protect user data.
And we should incorporate technologies
that enhance privacy and give
user control over their data.
Then come we have to foster the
participations to develop and promote
interoperable standards across sectors.
And then initiatives to inform
the organizations in that specific
industry and users about Identity
Federation benefits and best practices.
In conclusion, Identity Federation
represents a transformative approach
to digital identity management that
addresses the critical challenges
faced by users and organizations.
By enabling a seamless SSO experience
across multiple service providers,
Identity Federation enhances
user convenience and security
while significantly improving
the overall user experience.
As industries increase, digitalize,
and integrate, the ability to
manage identities efficiently
and securely will be paramount.
The economic impact of adapting identity
federation is substantial with potential
GDP growth of 3 to 13 percent by 2030 for
countries that implement these systems.
Additionally, sectors such as
banking, healthcare, and education
stand to save billions in operational
costs and improve service delivery.
By establishing standardized identity
attributes under a robust consent
management framework, Organizations
can foster greater trust and
interoperability among users.
Thank you very much.