Hello everyone and welcome to my session.
Today we will talk about Polisys
code and how to use this approach
to build RBAC and OpenPolicyAgent.
Let me introduce myself.
My name is Graziano Casto and I'm a
Developer Relations Engineer at MIA
Platform, an Italian company that,
among other things, is the creator of
the tool we will be discussing today.
Feel free to check out my website
and follow me on LinkedIn.
Before diving in, let's start
with the basics and understand
what we mean by policies.
When we think about policies,
we often immediately associate
them with roles and users.
And this is correct.
A rule that governs a specific
role access to a particular
resource is in fact a policy.
However, even an instruction that
defines the behavior of a system based
on the value of a certain property
can also be considered a policy.
And applying this to real life, even rules
like the age limit for purchasing alcohol
can, in a way, be considered a policy.
In general, a policy is simple.
simply a set of rules that govern the
behavior of a system by describing the
invariance that must hold will in it.
Policies are not necessarily limited
to the world of authorization.
Authorization policies are just a subset
of a broader category and they specify
which users or machine of course are
allowed to perform certain actions or
on specific resource within a system.
The first thing we need to
think about when considering API
authorization is which strategy to use.
There are different strategies to
define the access control on our system.
Let's take a look at a couple of them.
Let's take the example of an
internal developer platform.
In this context, we may have
senior developers who are allowed
to access project configurations,
commit changes and deploy them.
Then we have a group of junior
developers who are allowed to access
the project configurations and
commit changes, but not deploy them.
And finally, we have the platform
administrator with full permissions.
They can do everything senior
developers can do, but in addition,
they can also create new projects.
In this situation, even if we
used a simple example, scaling by
directly assigning each user the
specific set of actions they are
allowed to do becomes really complex.
One way to simplify this process is
by categorizing users into roles.
This way, we only We will only assign
the user to a role and the permission
will be inherited directly from the role.
This means that whenever we need to add
a new user to the platform, for example,
we just need to identify its role.
And if we need to add the new features
that require new permissions, the
only thing we need is to assign this
permission to the roles that require it.
In this way, all the users associated with
that role will inherit the permission.
This strategy is known as Role Based
Access Control, RBAC, and it is useful
for abstracting out the complexity of
assigning permission to users by using
an intermediate level of assignment.
Another popular strategy is called
Attribute Based Access Control,
ABAC, which focuses on the use
of attributes instead of roles.
In this access management strategy,
each user is directly assigned to
attributes, which are used to determine
whether the specific user's methods
certain conditions for accessing a
resource or performing an action.
Both strategies have their pros and cons.
On one hand, the airbag strategy is
certainly simple, but compared to an
ABAC approach, it lacks of granularity.
On the other hand, using
attributes allow for more granular
definition of access points.
specific access, but implementing
such a strategies requires more
time and expertise to define
correctly the attributes you need.
The ideal solution could be to use
a hybrid approach, using roles for
a high level access control and then
using attributes for more granular
management of access to specific access.
Let's look at some example
of this hybrid strategy.
Suppose our users have roles
and corresponding permissions as
described in the previous example.
And we have also assigned them attributes
like the environments, which describe
the environments they are allowed to
work on, and the project, which is
the list of projects they work on.
In this case, a senior developer
having the permission to deploy
as part of their role will be able
to deploy to any environment for
the project they are assigned to.
On the other hand, the same
senior developer will not be able
to deploy anything to projects
they are not assigned to.
In other words, even If they inherit the
deploy permission from their role, if
they don't have the project attribute
associated, they will not be able to
deploy any changes to that project.
Now let's analyze the case
of a junior developer.
They don't have the permission to
deploy, so it doesn't matter which
projects they are assigned to.
They will not be able to deploy
any changes to those projects.
In this case, if we want to give a
specific junior developer the ability
to deploy changes, but only to the dev
environment, for example, for the project
they are assigned to, a poorly error back
approach wouldn't allow us to do that.
However, with this hybrid
approach, we can assign the
environment attribute to the user.
Even if the junior developer doesn't
have the deploy permission in their
role, by assigning them the development
environment attribute, we can make an
exception that allows them to deploy
only the development environment for
the projects they are assigned to.
This provides a more flexible and granular
way to manage access to specific, specific
assets like the environment and the
projects now that we know the strategies
available to us and all that's left
to figure out how to implement them.
The old approach of keeping everything
inside the code base works well and
that's why it is always being used.
This approach involves having the
code responsible for enforcing the
authorization policy co exist within
the same code base and the same
code base as the business logic.
Handling authorization this
way has its pros and cons.
On one hand, it's convenient
because it is the simplest and
quickest solution to start with.
Start developing our system.
On the other end, it exposes to several
problems such as the repetition, for
example, if the same policies need to
be used in other services, especially
in a distributed application, it
has to be repeated and this lead
to difficult code maintainability
in the larger scale application.
A better way to manage our
policies is to decouple them from
the code base that contain the
business logic of our services.
The way to do this is by adopting
a policies code approach.
this is involved, this involves,
extracting the policies definition code
into a separate repository from our
application code and using an agent that
sits between our APIs and the users to
handle the enforcement of these policies.
The tool that allow us to do this is
Open Policy Agent, OPA, an open source
tool graduated by the Cloud Native
Computing Foundation, the CNCF, and
it provides an high level language
called RIGO for defining policies
and an agent for the enforcement.
What you are seeing on the screen
right now is a snippet of a simple
regopolicy that only authorizes post
requests on the slash order route,
where the value of the store property
inside the body matches the store
assigned to the user making the request.
Returning to the previous example and
implementing it to using Rigo for policies
definition, what we would have is that
all the code in our code base responsible
for enforcing policies is managed through
Rigo code, outside our code base, okay?
This way the policy enforcement
logic is decoupled from the business
logic of our services and managed
independently, making the system
easier to maintain and more flexible.
By analyzing the Rego policy code,
we have these two allows blocks,
which are the actual entry point
for the authorization logic.
With each request, if one of
these two blocks returns true,
then the request is authorized.
These blocks use functions defined
above to evaluate, for example, the
role of the user making the request.
To retrieve the user's role,
the JWT token is decoded.
Which is retrieved from the
editor of the request itself.
This approach does indeed add
a first level of decoupling of
decoupling, of the policies from
our code base, of our code base.
However, the problem is that hope
can be deployed as arrest service,
which means that our application with.
We still need to communicate with
the services, with the service, and
therefore a minimal level of coupling
remains in our application doing so.
So we want more, we want to
do better, to do it better.
And to further the couple, the policy
from our code base, what we can do is
using R Round is an open source project,
is a lightweight side car container for
API protection that used OPA and Rigo
for authorization policy validation.
natively allows building airbag
solutions by defining the concept
like roles, permissions, user groups
as binding blocks inside the project.
For its configuration, ROND uses open
policy, open API compliant files.
Therefore, to add RON to our project,
all we need to do is modify these
files to add the XRON property to
the routes that we want to protect.
Inside this property, we will declare the
name of the regopolicies that we intend
to use to protect the specific route.
We just need to do In addition
to protecting routes with
authentication rules, ROND offers
two other powerful features.
The first one is query generation,
which allows us to filter the results.
response of our APIs before
returning it to the client.
In this case, we can define a policy
that will be executed before returning
the result to the client, allowing
us to filter the response dataset
we will return to the client itself.
The second feature is the ability
to define a policy that modify
the structure, the response schema
before returning it to the client.
In this case, let's suppose, I
don't know, we have the response
payload for our request to fetch
the customers of our application.
Using the same endpoint, for example,
the get slash users, we can use run to
ensure that, Power users, so the user
with more privileges, can access the full
payload, while users with fewer privileges
receive just a filtered payload, without,
for example, sensitive information.
Now, we get to the point.
Let's start, let's talk about
why ROND was created and how
it is used at large scales.
At MIA Platform, we created ROND to manage
the entire authorization flow of our EDP.
And it is also provided as an
authorization mechanism for the
workloads managed by our platform.
From our clients.
For the ADP alone, ROND is currently
running on more than 30 microservices,
managing over 5, 000 policies
across more than 300, 300 routes.
ROND is a project designed to be
integrated into existing distributed
application without the need to modify
the existing services thanks to the use
of the sidecar pattern and the open ABI
specification compliant configurations.
This design make it easy to integrate
into existing system by design.
ROND also exposes various metrics to
track the usage of policies, such as the
number of time each policy is used and
the average evaluation time from them.
additionally it provides metrics to
monitor the resource usage of the
sidecar container, including resource
utilization at the container level.
We have reached the end of the
presentation and thank you for following
me this far and I invite you to connect
with me on LinkedIn and start using Roam.
Thank you all and see you next time.