All right, let's get started.
And first of all, hello everyone.
Welcome to my talk today.
And this talk was brought by the
Qtion stack with the open source
project that I'm working on.
And today I will go into the simple talk.
I will address the crucial issue we
encounter in software development.
Understanding the challenge is essential
for creating an effective solution.
And driving processes in our bills.
And we were going to
talk about the kitchen.
and how to integrate the kitchen
with your developer platform.
to optimize the software
development project.
the first quick, introduction.
Allow me.
Presenter.
I am.
I work as cloud engineer at the.
are responsible for working on platform
services like Kuber, engine Cloud, cloud
Observability, and also, designing and
building the IDP that serve a large
number of developer, on the daily basis.
And I'm also working on the
Open source project,
as is, a part of the CNCF sandbox
and platform swimming landscape.
And this is also the tool
we're going to talk today.
about the agenda today.
And I will cover the background before
jumping in the Qsend and IDP itself.
Mostly so that we have enough context
for the solution to make sense.
And we will talk about
the challenge thing.
We're placing, specifically.
the unique one that's contributed
to the birth of this project.
And I will explain some of the basic
concepts of the Qtion, with the platform
of Hadoop tool in the Qtion stack.
And then we will go into the powerful
capability of the Qtion, and demonstrate
how integrating it in our developer
platform that can enhance the Qtion.
our project and driving the chat.
the term DevOps, was officially introduced
in 2009, The foundation of DevOps was
envisioned as a cultural shift, an
enhancing collaboration between the
development and the operation team.
However, at the concept that involved
some, Organizations have veered
away from it of an original intent,
rather than fostering teamwork.
There has been a tendency for some
companies to place an excessive burden
on developers that reallocate various
operational responsibilities to them,
which detracts from the foundational while
the DevOps are fantastic in theory, but
put it in the practice can be his or miss.
Along with the ship to the DevOp,
a few chains are making a bit
charter for the developers.
we are dealing with a huge variety
of tune popping up everywhere.
more people adopting cloud services.
And some pretty complex tools become
more popular like Kubernetes, Terraform,
Istio, CloudFrame, or Qtion, maybe?
After when developers suddenly have
to, What they had around complicate,
complicated tool, cloud native
tool, and just do a single stop like
chaining an environment variable
or fixing basic database setup.
this has, this has led,
crazy amount of mental train.
Totally messing up with the
developer experience and dropping
the productivity to the floor.
Just take a look at how bad things
have gotten over the past 20 years and
honestly, it has been any size that's
going to slow down or change anytime soon.
We use the Chinese platform
as a service set up.
Almost 10 years, but we found
that it's start to hold us
back due to some major issue.
The main problem is about, infrastructure
has gotten super complex all time.
People are swamped with all this
infrastructure knowledge and they
have to, they need to have and the
platform itself has become bottleneck.
When it comes to making infrastructure
capability available, and they often
have many teams involved, which makes the
teamwork and coordination pretty tough.
On the top of that, on the top of that,
configuring our security parameters
and the privacy is harder than ever.
Thanks a lot.
the platform engineering here is
to make it easier for developers.
Many top tech, top tech companies have
set up platform teams, dedicated to
build the making internal developer
platform, the team approach that
works like a product focusing on,
simplifying and the developer journey.
With, with this platform, the
developer no longer have to,
juggle complexing toolchain.
They can focus on what,
focus on what they love most.
Coding, creating amazing application
with a friendly approach, reduce
stress and boost productivity.
Allow team to work quickly and
efficiently without compromise.
On quality, so we are the platform
team defy that we refer as the
voting path for the developer.
This look really do look, complex,
but, I will take a check in the main
point so you can understand it easily.
we believe that the application
team on the top left of your screen.
should focus on the aspect that
are not stick to the environment.
Typically this is intent about that,
the application team want to define
what the application will have, like
the workload of the application.
the ascensor, the other ascensor
Infrastructure like the database
that application use without
worrying about the specific database
specification for given environment.
on the bottom left of the figure, we
involve that the platform team should
be responsible for the certain task.
They need to handle a
standard workload profile.
We're choosing the community
deployment on the customer workload
along with define the behavior line.
In this point, Percy, father, more
platform team, also set a standard.
For the variable dependency line,
that way, networking behavior.
Which, that needs to be consistent.
this is some, this is system time
require different complication
to speak to the each environment.
For example, having the lack of
larger database in the production
and smaller one in the development.
And we believe application developer
should need to handle and worry
about the, the whole approach.
Consider two component, one
being, standard capability,
which we call the, QC model.
and the other being the environment,
specific configuration should,
such as, writing database by
different in different environment.
The fusion platform orchestrator,
which is the term we currently
use and, take into take, in taking
two input one from the, platform.
Team one from the application team
and, we refer and is efficiently merge.
the two aspect allow them with
the approach deployment contact,
we refer as the workspace.
you can think, workspace as a general
concept of the, application environment.
And, this come together, we call, deep
facing and specification, which we hope
that makes straightforward and agnostic
to both environment and platform.
The platform engineer will define element,
elements such as model along with the
environment specific configuration.
And this will, match together to
produce what we refer to as spec,
resources facing data format.
This spec will stop a uniform
format, uniform format, AP cable,
to both kuber the resources and
cloud provider resources in infras.
Ultimately, this spec acts
as a single source of truth
corresponding to one, one to one the
environment's actual infrastructure.
So we will have, going through the
app configuration, in the
contact of Cuon app configuration,
give developer will play a crucial role
to define the application component.
They just focus on the spec specific?
Yeah.
Key elements such as the ER
configuration, the monitoring system.
The monitoring component and the database,
cloud based database, like using a cloud
and the version of database, for example,
in here, and they don't need to worry
about, without needing to address the
infrastructure concept or the deployment.
Of the required services
and application itself.
this stream, of course allows them
to enhance their productivity,
and especially in the open process
and about the Cuon workspace.
you can understand the workflow
as the, environment, like
production environment, and.
Staging environment, development
environment, the workspace is a
concept that corresponds to a specific
target environment used to deploy
applications in a contemporary use.
This typical refers to the Kubernetes
cluster that hosts the application
workload along with an optional cloud.
provider, and, to provisioning necessary
infrastructure resource such as database.
And, in additional serving as the
deployment works by, to link with,
set up, platform configuration
that apply to all application
deployed within that, workspace.
Thank you.
They can, define, platform, team
can define any resources on the,
environment, the secret store from any
provider, cloud provider, and the code
that application will be deployed on.
So we will go in deeper in the Qt model.
This model, this job really,
this, will, This is our view.
We'll provide a deeper understanding
of the functional objection model.
We, the execution model effectively
manage board C with the resources and
from the, from the app com app developer
and the platform publication, and
translating them into the ation that
show as the middle layer data format.
And calculating both, resource
type and the platform team.
task with the managing the
configuration, refer at the workspace,
configuration with team, the
contact execution, and typically the
configuration set of the default value.
For example, here, they will follow the.
the platform team will define the
model in the workspace that, that,
the application can be used, like the
database we will use, ware database
with the 20 nearby upside and the
instant class of the TBT three micro.
And another profile is the
small class with the size of 50.
And the instant class is the dbt3 small.
And the large class is
using the dbt2 large.
for more specific sector of the
application required customer
testing, it is possible to define
a variety in the configuration.
And, however, this spec will
be for more advanced to use K.
So it is not cover in this, top, you can
learn more in the future website provided
from the perspective of the application.
Developer, the process begin to select
the model and the subsequent created.
created, creating, configuration file.
This file will serve, as a declare
model that will totally describe
application configuration that I
described in the, previous slide.
Furthermore, detail is going first.
We will design in the next slide.
Let go into the next slide.
Okay.
This is the workflow.
This look a little bit complex,
but we will just focus on, three
part of it below here is the
write, generate, and application.
So with the write process, first of
all, platform orchestrator, platform
team will define the model of the
QC model, like database model.
And monitoring model, storage model,
anything, and it will, after defining the
model, it will, the platform team will
define the workspace configuration, like
the environment of the application, like
dev environment and product environment,
that each environment, the platform
engineer will provide the resources.
That's what Spike can use and,
Kubernetes cluster of that environment
and cloud provider of that environment.
And about the application
developer, they will just care
about the app configuration.
conflict about the app workload and
the database that, the database I,
that application use the monitoring,
that application, use the story, that
application use and enter this process.
The configuration are merged
into what is a referral.
To the, as the intent workshop at a
single shot of truth, a single shot of
truth, for all resources and scheduled
for the point in your environment.
One intent is a tab listed.
The next phase is applying that
during which, specific resource,
at a creative or updated.
Importantly, before reaching
the upline step, there is a
crucial step called preview.
This step allows a user to review and
leave different of the resources that's
about to change, ensure that expectations
are set for upcoming modification.
Just a simple, workflow of the Qtion.
And now we're going to provide
some, methods to integrate
the Qtion with, your IDP.
And Qtion will work as the
platform orchestrator in your IDP.
Then the application, application
developer just care about the
developer control plane here.
About the git repository have
the app configuration file.
And then the Qtion will add the
CI pipeline, like building images,
testing, and verifying some spot
of the application workflow.
the next step is the CD pipeline.
It either is we'll get the application
configuration, app configuration
from the SoCo and the Cuon model,
that platform engineering device
before is we're going to, deploy the
application and, Provisioning, require
infrastructure for the application.
This workflow will have
continual delivery, everything
that, application developer.
Don't need to worry about the below
layer, like provisioning database.
how to deploy the application in each
environment, the application global.
Just define everything in the
app configuration, and then
the workflow of the pipeline.
We will do it for them.
The platform team will, define the
Qtion model, define the, workflow of
the CI pipeline or CD pipeline, define
everything, set up the Qtion stack, so
that, AppDeveloper just puts the code to
the version control like GitHub or GitLab,
Watch, watch, CI flow and CD workflow.
And then after that, the application
will be delivered to the something
like committee engine or every
infrastructure will be for business.
If you have any change in the app
configuration, the Qtion tech will
handle that task and change like
they can change the database size,
they can remove the database, or
add more database, for example.
The Qtion currently operates as a
command line interface tool that's
functional as the event driven interface.
Platform orchestrator is, introduced
a protocol driven collaboration
paradigm that allows platform owner
and application developer can to
execute their own independently.
The Qsync then orchestrator orchestrate
their contribution dynamically matching
and generating the final output.
Infrastructure pacing specification
refer at, spec, subsequent apply by tion.
However, the existing version tion with
the limitation in providing the scale.
Both of this, user can user have to
encounter challenge related to the
credential management resources.
Visibility from flexibility in managing
permission and the effort, required
to integrate with other systems.
in the response to the challenge, we
are posting a Qtion server, and this
will be by the version of the Qtion will
operate as the long run main service.
Okay.
and this will expose the REST
service endpoint, thereby enhance its
functionality and user experience.
And it can easily integrate with the
internal developer portal like Backstair.
We'll have more about the
backstage plugin and you guys
can easily integrate it in on it.
about integrate on it, like fusion,
presently, currently can integrate it in
your CI pipeline work as the, common line.
And, but in the future, using server will
release and you can have your centralized
platform orchestrator by every project.
You can call to the platform orchestrator
to handle the tasks, like deploying
application provisioning infrastructure,
just, wait for the fusion server.
in the future in this will really show.
And it's also the last slide of this talk.
Thank you for attend my talk today and
here is my in some information about me.
You can, contact me to learn
more about the Q or going through
the Houston Q website here, to
learn more about the project and.
I'm waiting for the release
of the Qt 79 server.
thank you, again, for attending this talk.
And, hope you guys have a
nice day with the conference.
Goodbye.