Hello everyone.
I'm GR Malu.
I'm a cybersecurity risk
consultant at Chevron.
Over 11 years I spent across in
working with investment banking,
oil and gas, energy and consulting.
Majorly focusing on CICD pipelines,
DevSecOps, third party risk
management, and AI security.
Across the industries I have seen,
one thing in common is it's not just
your code gets you into trouble.
It's about the dependencies,
the CICD pipelines and the
third parties wrapped around it.
Today I talk about software,
supply chain attacks and attacks.
Just don't hit your application
directly, but instead target the
tools, dependencies, and the pipelines.
You re, you rely on.
These attacks have go grown by 700%,
which is a significant amount in recent
years, and now one of the biggest
risk to the modern organizations.
My goal in this session is to share
practical, real world strategies you can
apply to your own DevSecOps pipeline so
that they become proactive and resilient.
Let's move on to the next slide where
we talk about critical threat landscape
and supply chain attacks, and why
supply chain attacks are so dangerous.
A modern application is
no longer just your code.
It's built from open source library,
third party software development kits
and cloud services, and CAC retooling.
Attackers have learned that it's
they, if they compromise a trusted
software, a delivery channel, for
example, a built pipeline, a popular
open source package, or an update
mechanism that they can impact hundreds
or thousands of organizations at once.
Most enterprise applications today depend
on hundreds of open source sub components,
and many of those are transitive
dependencies, and the teams don't
even realize that they are using them.
The lack, that lack of visibility
creates perfect hiding places
for the attack vectors.
We have also shifted from monoliths to
microservices and from OnPrem to hybrid
or multi-cloud, and from manual releases
to high velocity CI I CT pipelines.
The great shift.
That's a great shift of innovation.
But that also means like attackers
now have dozens of places to slip in.
For example, package ies, build systems,
pipeline plugins, and vendor APIs.
Oas reflect the shift clearly
and in OVAs top 10 for web.
You see the items like vulnerable
and outdated components and
software and data integrity failure.
In the O-S-C-I-C-D top 10, risks
like dependency chain abuse,
poisoned pipeline execution, and
inadequate identity access management.
That's literally a description of
the modern supply chain problem.
We know from data that organizations
who implemented formal third
party risk management programs and
strong DevSecOps practices have
significantly fewer incidents.
So the message is clear.
This is no longer a, just
a checkbox or an edge case.
Supply chain now has become a
critical to application security and
let's move on to those slide three.
Aware we'll learn about will
modern divesting real world
examples and what their impact are.
Let's first talk about SolarWinds,
which is a classic example
of build system compromise.
Nations tech attackers infiltrated
the vendors built up environment
and injected malicious code into
the trusted software update.
That single update went out around
18,000 customers, including government
organizations and large enterprises.
The attack then started the customer.
It started at the
upstream in the pipeline.
Let's talk about Log four J. We saw
how one widely used open source logging
library could become a global emergency.
Most organizations didn't even
know where Log four J was running
because it was buried deep inside.
Other components.
This is the risk of vulnerable and
outdated components, which are exactly
OSP has mentioned in mid Stockton.
In 2024, the CrowdStrike Falcon Update
Falcon content update caused a massive
outage when faulty security update crashed
millions of windows systems worldwide.
This wasn't a malicious attack,
but from resilient perspective, it
behaved like a supply chain failure.
One update pipeline, global Impact.
And with platforms like Snowflake, we
have seen how attackers can abuse stolen
credentials, or we can access controls
in third party cloud data service to
access many different organizational data.
The common pattern is simple.
The adversary writes on something we
are already trust and update an agent,
a library, or a vendor platform.
Let's move on to next slide here.
Let in response to these incidents, I
have worked on defense framework that
combines lessons learned and research
industry standards and real implications
across sectors like energy and banking.
At high level, the framework has several
pillars, and if you see shit left in
DevSecOps, it brings security into
planning, coding, and build stages.
That means all the stages of
software development Lifecycle L, and
secure the CACD pipelines, lockdown
identities, secrets and infrastructure
for your build and deploy systems.
Advanced detection use behavioral
analytics to spot unusual activity
and runtime application self
protection to detect and block
attacks from inside the application.
Vendor risk management, continuously
evaluate, monitor, and third
party tools and the platforms.
Zero.
Trust architecture, never trust,
always verify for every component, even
internal ones in production environments.
When we have applied this framework,
we have seen faster detection of
vulnerability, dependencies, and of
measurable detection in tampering
incidents and better containment
during the potential compromises.
I'll walk you through each of these
pillars in the next upcoming chapters.
Let's move on to the next slide with the.
In this chapter one, I'll focus on
how supply chain attacks have evolved
and what it looks like today in our
software development ecosystem, we have
more from mostly proprietary monolithic
application to highly con componentized
systems that depend on open source
managed services and cloud native coding.
That shift has increased.
Speed in innovation, but it has
also multiplied trust relationships.
Let's see some modern threat vectors.
Let's first talk about
dependency confusion.
You think you are pulling, if you
think you are pulling the company
internal logging from your private
registry, but your ci misprioritized
the public registry and an attacker
uploads the package with the same name.
The build passes the test, even
pass, and you have just to ship
the attacker control score.
And let's talk about hypo squatting.
Hypo squatting.
Attackers publish packages with the
file names, with the small changes,
or just deferred by one character.
So that means like late night, the
dev, the tire developer mistypes
a name installs the wrong one.
And the malicious payload isn't,
it's simple, but still works and.
Let's talk about the CICD compromise.
What's worse than a compromised repo?
A clean repo with a
compromised build runner.
The source looks perfect.
The malicious payload gets
in injector only at build or
packaged package packaging time.
The key idea in is that modern
supply chain attacks are not random.
The, they systematically exploit the
way we develop and ship software.
Understanding these patterns is the
first step to defending against them.
Let's move on to the next slide.
Let's talk about why traditional
security fails in this slide.
Traditional security models struggle with
the these attacks for a few re reasons.
First, like first, older models
are based upon stronger perimeter.
We assume inside the network is
trusted and outside is untrusted.
Distributed pipelines, cloud
services, and remote teams, that
assumption breaks down completely.
Second, many security processes
are still focused on static checks
at the end of the lifecycle.
A final penetration test, a
yearly audit, or occasional.
Manual reviews, supply chain attacks,
especially those targeting on CACD
often happens in the middle of pipeline
during the bills, packaging, or
updates where checks don't see them.
The third, when we fully trust code
because it is slight signed or delivered
by a well-known vendor, we forgot that
signing only proves origin, not safety.
If the bill system or maintainer
is compromised, the signed
artifact can still be malicious.
This is why we need to change our
mindset from inside is safe to
continuous verification and defense in
depth across the enterprise pipeline.
Let's move on the next slide.
In this, let's talk about the cascade.
This is one of the most aspects
of supply chain attacks is.
Supply chain effect attacks these days.
Imagine a single popular
open source component.
That component is used in dungeons
of libraries, which then get used
into hundreds of applications when
vulnerability or back door appears in
that one of the component, the impact
cascades through entire system ecosystem.
We saw this with a log four j. A single
component far down in the dependency tree
created crisis for many organizations that
didn't even know that they were using,
that the same Cascade Direct applies
to ci, cd platforms and security tools.
If a widely used build agent or
endpoint agent, which out bad update
like in the CrowdStrike incident,
the consequences are global.
Very huge.
This is why we must treat software supply
chains as a complex interconnector systems
and not just individual applications.
Let's move on to next slide where
this is a chapter two, we talk
about resilience, DevSecOps.
In this chapter, let's talk about how to
build resilience in your devs practices
so that you can handle this cascade risk.
The goal is not to slow the teams, but to
secure, but to bake security into daily
workflows, from planning, to coding,
to testing, releasing and operating.
We'll look at practical
ideas like shifting security
left into design and coding.
Integrate security checks into
integrate integrated development
environments and pre-committed hooks.
Continuously scanning dependencies
and generating software, bills of
materials and software builds of
materials is a structured list of
all components inside your software.
I in.
These are found foundations that make
later more advanced control effective.
Let's move on to next slide.
Let's talk now.
Let's talk specifically about securing the
CICD pipeline because this is a heart of
your software factory As a reminder, c.
It's a, as it is continuous integration
and continuous delivery or deployment.
It's the automated systems that spool
score runs, test to build artifacts
and ships from them to production.
If an attacker controls
your CICD pipeline, they
essentially control what you.
The key controls include a majorly
identity access management, ensuring
that build agents, service accounts,
and human users will all have least
privilege only the permissions
they absolutely needed based upon
their role and secret management.
Using the secure walls instead
of hard coding credentials
and configuration or code.
Secret Ma. Isolated runners
treating build agents as ephemeral
shortlived mechanism that are
destroyed after each job, reducing
the chance of persistent compromise.
Network segmentation.
Make sure CICD components cannot freely.
Every internal system, especially
production databases, it's also
crucial to manage third party plugins
and actions used by CICD tools, each
plugin in efficient, effectively
code that runs in your pipeline so
that there should be a review and
approval process for what you allow.
These measures align directly with ova top
10, CACD risks such as inadequate identity
access management, dependency chain
abuse, and poisoned pipeline executions.
Let's move on to next slide
where we talk the chapter three.
Where we talk about advanced
threat detection, even with the
strong preventive controls, we
have to ensure that something.
Someday we'll slip through.
Here we move beyond basic signature
based detection into techniques that
understand behavior and context.
For example, monitoring CCD, unusual
behaviors like a pipeline suddenly
pulling a large number of new
dependencies from unfamiliar sources.
Watching for abnormal network
connections from build agents
or application containers.
This is where security information
and event management, CM tools
and user and entity be behavior
analytics can play an important role
correlating events and highlighting
anomalies that deserve investigations.
The idea is to quickly answer
the question, is the behavior
normal for this system?
If not, we have, we want to
detect and respond before it
turns into full down incident.
Let's move on to next section slide.
In this slide we talk about runtime
application, self-protection,
a key component of advanced
detection in the ecosystem.
Runtime application, self-protection
technology that runs inside
your application monitors
its behavior in real time.
Unlike a traditional web
application firewall that
send sits in your application.
And this runtime application, self
protection can see how inputs are
being processed internally and can
block malicious actions even if
it play even if the play load has
already reached the application.
For example, if you have compromised
dependency, tries to execute a
suspicious command or attempts
unexpected file or network accesses.
REAP can detect that pattern and stop
the request or terminate the session.
So that would really help
when I combine, when combined
with these techniques like us.
SaaS static application security testing,
and the dynamic application security
testing test earlier in the lifecycle.
RASP provides laced last line of
defense in the production line.
In practice, we have seen that
organizations use using R-E-C-A-R-E-S-P,
especially for their most
critical external facing services.
Have much better chances of preventing
vulnerability from turning into a
breach, even when a supply chain
flaw surfaces after deployment.
Let's move on to next slide with
the chapter four vendor risk
management, which is very important.
The, this will focus on how to manage
vendor or third party risk management,
which is absolutely center to the
key to the supply chain security.
Most of the organizations rely heavily
on software as service, SaaS platform
as service pass and infrastructure.
As service as IAS provides
providers as well as we specialize
security and analytics tools.
Each of these vendors become an
extensive for your attack surface.
Strong third party risk management
programs looks at security certifications
like usually reviewing the SOC two type
two reports IS four 27,001 deficiency
reports or PCI DSS where it is based
upon the relevancy of the industry.
The vendor own CICD and supply
chain practices, do they use
S-P-O-M-S Code Signing and Strong?
I do.
They have strong I identity and
access management practices and
there how their incident response
system looks like process looks like.
How quickly do they notify
customers when something goes wrong?
And ongoing continuous monitoring, not
just a questionnaire at onboarding.
It's like how they are doing the
continuous monitoring and how we are
monitoring our third parties continuously.
Incidents like this, like snowflake
breaches, highlight that it's not
enough for a platform to be powerful.
It must also be operated securely by both
the vendor and the customers and vendor
risk is shared responsibility and our.
Detentions must reflect that.
Let's move on to next slide, the
chapter five zero trust Architecture.
Finally, in this chapter, we we
talk about zero trust architecture,
which is never trust, always verify.
Instead of assuming that anything
inside our network is safe zero trust,
assume that threats can exist both
sides inside and outside as well.
Organization In a zero trust model
for supply chain and DevSecOps, we
require strong authentication and
authorization everywhere, often
using multifactor authentications.
Role-based access controls, treat
every component, repositories,
build agents services as needing to
prevent its identity and registry.
Cut.
Continuously, not just once.
Use code signing hardware, security
modules, and sometimes trusted
platform modules to anchor trust
in hardware where possible apply
microsegmentation so even one part
of the environment is compromised.
Lateral movement is limited.
Zero Trust is not a just a
product, it's a design philosophy.
Applied if this is applied correctly,
it significantly reduced the impact
of compromised dependency tool or
supplier because nothing nothing
and no one is implicitly trusted.
Let's move on to the next slide.
To make this all actionable, I like
to think terms of paced roadmap,
foundation enhancement and optimization
foundation in this foundation phase.
And coming next three to six months,
you can enable automated dependency
scanning systems and start generating.
O software builds and of
materials for key applications.
Begin code assigning
for critical artifacts.
Establish basic vendor
assessment and T-P-C-R-M process.
Enforce multifactor authentication and
list platforms and critical SaaS tools.
Enhancement phase in coming
next six to 12 months.
Deploy RASP runtime
application self protection.
For your most critical external
facing applications, implement
behavioral monitoring for CICD
pipelines and production workloads.
Integrate automated security
tests, testing like SaaS and
DA scans and container scanning
throughout your pipelines Rollout.
Continuous vendor monitoring
instead of one-time reviews
optimi at the optimization phase.
It's cons.
It should be considered as ongoing.
Tune detection rules to reduce noise
and focus on high risk anomalies.
Optimize governance, so security control
support, not block development velocity.
Implement advanced capabilities
like software at the station and
a province tracking, for example,
inspired by frameworks like supply
chain levels of for software artifacts.
This idea is to build progressively rather
than trying to do everything at once.
Let's move on to next slide.
Let's wrap up the content.
I want to written to key mindset
shift, moving from reactive
security to proactive defense.
Reactive security waits for an
incident breach, an outa outage,
or a critical vulnerability,
and then scrambles to respond.
Proactive supply chain defense
assumes that vulnerabilities
and attacks are inva and designs
resilience into the entire lifecycle.
That means treating your DevSecOps
pipeline itself as a primary asset
to secure investing in visibility
so you know what components
you run and how they behave.
Building layers of defense from
design and development to build
deployment and runtime monitoring.
Organizations that embrace this
approach are able to maintain
development speed while drastic,
drastically reducing the risk.
You don't have to choose
between agility and security.
You just have to design
both intentionally.
And I would like to thank you so
much for your time and attention.
I would like to continue the conversation
about DevSecOps and CICD pipeline
security and our supply chain risk.
Risk.
So feel free to catch me upon LinkedIn.
I'm always happy to exchange the
ideas and real world experiences.
I hope this talk gives you a clear
starting point to strengthen your own
pipelines and supply chain supply chains.
Thank you so much.