Hello everyone.
Thank you so much for joining today.
My name is Bar Ndira.
I'm a senior software engineer at
Ascension Health, and today I'm excited to
talk about how AI and generative machine
learning are transforming DevSecOps into
foster, smarter and more secure discip.
In the organization I have worked with,
we have seen firsthand how traditional QA
and security practices struggles to keep
up with the modern delivery velocity.
So this session is focused on one idea.
How do we evolve devs SecOps
into an intelligent, productive,
autonomous system through ai?
Let's dive in.
The challenge by traditional
dev SecOps is falling behind.
Today's software delivery environment
is fundamentally different from
DevSecOps was originally built for.
We are dealing with extremely
high deployment velocity, daily
and continuous deployments.
Microservices are distributed cloud native
architectures, right, dynamic attack
surfaces, and unpredictable interactions.
But our QA cycles, security
reviews, unscripted automation
are still largely static.
The result, a widening gap between
deployment, speed and assurance.
Traditional pipelines simply cannot
safeguards today's complexity because
they rely on rigid tests and predefined
security rules while real world systems
behaves in fluid, unpredictable ways.
This is why we need significant evolution.
Evolution required for reactive
to intelligent DevSecOps.
DevSecOps has to move from reactive to
predictive manual to automated static
context error, gatekeeping acceleration.
We are no longer talk, talking
about adding more checks.
We are talk, talking about
self-learning systems.
That enhance QA and
security automatically.
So think about like this.
AI becomes the engine that drive
this transformation, right?
AI is going to be feature that's
going to drive this transformation.
Let's move on to this next slide.
Generate you AI accelerating test
and security script creation.
One of the biggest.
Breakthrough is generative AI for
tests and security automation.
AI tools like copilot can do everything
right, but I just shot it into a
little bit of what are I am seeing
it day to day read usage storage.
It was able to re it stories,
understand code context,
generate complete test suits.
Create security validation
scripts built end-to-end scenarios
aligned with real business logic.
These are automated these are excellent.
So read user stories.
It was able to read the user
stories and add stories to our
Jira as well using cps, right?
JIRA plugins.
So these are all something which
GitHub copilot can do right now.
This drastically reduces manual
scripting efforts and ensures.
Coverages of scenarios
humans often overlook.
In short, yay becomes your
automation engineer working 24 7.
Moving on to next slide, machine
learning, predictive quality engineering.
This is an interesting topic,
which we are like using.
Most of the companies started
using day-to-day, so machine
learning takes this step further by
making your pipeline intelligent.
Machine learning models can
analyze it, analyze production
logs, historical defects.
What else?
Code changes.
Any threats, intelligence system,
behavior patterns, and then they can
make predictions, which models are risky.
Why is that risky?
Which tests should run fast?
Why is it running fast, slow now?
Which areas are likely to break?
What is the, what are the chances that
data can break in future code changes
where new vulnerabilities might emerge?
That's again, key, right?
We are all into security where I'm seeing
like the security testing is rapidly going
fast and machine learning can, using,
use that this create risk-based testing
strategy that reduces execution time.
While improving the
accuracy, that's the key.
QA is more crucial for accuracy.
So here we are increasing the execution
time and increasing the speed of the
testing and while improving accuracy.
Think of this as your pipeline,
learning from every release and
getting smarter over time, that's
like excellent feature, right?
Machine learning was able to help us,
that our pipeline itself learning,
okay, these are the things going on.
Okay, this needs to be improved.
If you receive a email with all
the issues, what are the things we
changed from the previous things
that's going to make a real impact.
Let's move on to.
The key thing, the real world impact.
When teams adopt a driven
SecOps, the impact is dramatic.
Major reduction in text
test, execution time, foster
identification of vulnerabilities,
huge drop in manual scripting.
Better coverage of edge cases is
early detection of system anon.
You in this way, what will happen,
what is the real world impact here?
You deliver faster, safer,
and with higher confidence.
That's the key.
We need to be confident when
we are delivering something.
Let's move on to a case study here.
A driven test data generation.
Let me share a real world example
in microservices environment.
Generating realistic, interconnected test
data is extremely dissolve difficult.
Yay.
Solve this by how can yay help us?
Yay, can solve this by understanding the
schemas, what kind of schemas we have.
Analyze the production data patterns,
what kind of data we are getting
in production, what kind of data we
should use to recreate these issues,
or what kind of data if we use, we can
eliminate some of these issues to do.
That's something we can use the AI
for Synthesize realistic data sets.
That bunch of data sets can be there.
It can help us to synthesize
the realistic data sets.
Auto generating boundary
and edge case data.
So that's something
which is always tricky.
There are multiple edge
cases can be there.
We can use here.
Help to understand some of the
edge cases, the outcome of this
case study, test data generation.
Test data preparation time drops massively
while coverage significantly increases.
That's the key.
Dramatically reduces the test data
preparation time with significantly
improved coverage across service
boundaries and data sets.
That's key.
Let's move on to another case study where
machine learning based anomaly detection.
Another powerful use case
is anomaly detection.
Machine learning can learn what
normal looks like across distributor
services, and then monitor for
deviation in the real time.
That's very key, right?
Performance drifts, suspicious
access patterns, latency spikes.
Unusual resource conception.
This are something where which we
can use the machine learning set.
When ano an anomaly occur, the system
can trigger automated workflows, alert,
security systems, or even mitigate.
We stage attacks where in my case,
we are triggering a Slack alert.
Hey, there is some kind of spy
thing, suspicious pattern going on,
which is not happening day to day.
We can, we are seeing like there
is a slowness when a user try to
submit a prob, this is taking this
long, this was not the case in past.
So un importantly, unusual unusual
resource conception like memories.
It, we can also see memory
conception might be too high.
This was never happened in the past.
We can request, we can.
We will receive a Slack notification.
If it's way bad, we will
also receive a call.
This brings us closer to
autonomous operation in pipeline.
Okay, let's move on to next slide.
Integration strategy.
How to bring a into your pipeline.
You don't need to rebuild your digs.
DevSecOps pipeline.
Your adaption happens in phases.
Phase one, assess and pilot.
Start small.
It's always important.
Don't rush into the things.
Start small.
Usually with AI based generation
and vulnerabilities planning, that's
where you, you should start phase two.
Integrate and train.
Connect AI tools into your ci cd pipeline.
Train machine learning models
using historical locks.
Incidents.
How the, how, what are
the errors were happening?
Give enough access to the
machine learning models.
What are the things it should rate?
Okay, on phase three, the key
thing, skull and optimize.
Expand to more service.
Refine your models with feedback loop.
The model service, you gi give the machine
learning models, it can get more data
and understand how the system works here.
And phase four is again
another important one.
Autonomous operation enable
AI to make real time decisions
such as test prioritization
and automated security export.
So those are some key things.
Okay, to move on to next slide.
No complete overhaul required.
This is important.
Yay augments.
It does not, doesn't replace
your existing framework space.
It would, it won't.
It's not going to change your
existing automation framework.
It's just going to improve it.
Okay.
That's the key thing again how
efficient it's going to be,
how important it's going to be.
That's the key thing.
Your security policy, stay your
security policy means your company
security policies is going to stay.
That's again, a key thing.
Okay?
Alright, next one.
Your CACD pipeline stay.
Your CACD pipeline is going
to not going to change.
It's going to still stay
same as it was before.
Focus.
Yay.
On the areas where manual
efforts is highest and risk
is greatest for maximum R way.
Yay.
Simply takes over the most
repetitive, complex and high risk
tasks to boost speed and quality.
Let's move on to this
next slide number 10.
Risk-based testing Focus, vari matters.
Yay enables intelligent
prioritization there.
In my opinion, it's a pyramid.
There are five important things,
which A, is AI prioritize.
Okay.
Critical parts, high risk models
recently change code, change
components in integration boundaries,
low risk, stable code, and I like
to tell a stable low risk areas.
This cuts execution time and
improves precision by validating.
What truly impacts business critical
functionality, so that's important, right?
Validating the what truly impacts
our business Critical functionality.
MI models analyze the code, changes
historical defect rates, and
business impact to automatically
prioritize testing effort.
This intelligent allocation ensures
critical functionality issues maximum
validation while reducing wasted
efforts on stable low risk areas.
Let's move on to the next slide.
Slide number 11, automated
vulnerability detection.
There are three key things,
statistic analysis, runtime
protection, and dependence.
Intelligence.
AI improves security through
context of our statistic analysis.
Also, realtime behavioral
monitoring supply chain intelligence
prioritized patching this
transform security from reactive
patching to predictive protection.
And if you see dependency intelligence,
yea continuously tracks supply chain
risk, automatically prioritizing patches
based on exploitability and impact.
That's important.
Okay, let's move to next slide.
Benefits, speed, cost, and confidence
when YEA becomes part of DevSecOps.
Organization experience poster releases.
Reduce the test maintenance,
proactive security postures, lower
operational cost, higher customer
trust, resilient systems quality and
security no longer slows you down.
They become business accelerator.
So let's move on to the key slide.
Actionable stake takeaways for your
team to wrap up with practical aspects.
Start with one pilot.
Start with one pilot use case,
improve your data quality, build your
work, build cross-functional teams.
Create feedback loops.
That's again important.
Create mechanisms for models to learn
from production incidents and fall and
continuous implement is essential focus.
Focus on enablement, not
replacement position.
A s an enabler, not a replacement.
It's not going to replace anything.
It's just going to improve
it, so it's enabler.
With these steps, you can move
towards intelligent DevSecOps
without description, conclusion.
The next slide will be conclusion.
AI driven DS DevSecOps is not the future.
It's the present.
We are not going to enter
into a, we are already in ai.
It transforms quality and
security from bottlenecks into
powerful competitive advantages.
With the predictive defect
detection, automatic security
scanning, and self-learning
pipelines, teams can deliver faster.
Safer and with the complete confidence,
the organization that adopt AI
early with lead innovation, customer
trust, and operational excellence.
Thank you for joining today.
And I am excited for any
answer any of your questions.
Please email me if there is any questions.
Thank you for opportunity.
Thank you.
Thank you for giving time to
me to speak in this conference.