Hi.
Today we are discussing about
resilience for secure and fault
tolerance enterprise systems.
First, welcome to this deep dive
into resilience engineer A three
plan for modern enterprises.
Today we are exploring how to build
systems that not only survive failures,
but actually thrive under pressure.
This is Practical Session grounded
in real world distributed systems
challenges to at enterprise scale.
By the end, you will have
actionable strategies to implement
in your own architectures.
Let me introduce myself.
My name is, I am working as quality
performance engineer at Inc. I
bring Tenness years of experience in
enterprise scale distributed systems.
My focus is mainly on performance
optimization, reliability
engineering, and DevSecOps practices.
I specialize in building
resilient architectures that
balance three competing demands.
Security fault tolerance
and operational efficiency.
I work extensively with complex
microservices environments
where one failure can castrate
across your entire platform.
I have debug systems serving 30 K request
per minute, so the challenge, modern
distributed systems under pressure.
There are three typical pressures.
One is security threats.
Second is cascading failures.
Third is performance demands.
The first related to security
threats, we are seeing evolving
attack vectors, specifically
targeting distributed architectures.
Example, attackers exploit
microservice boundaries where
security controls are inconsistent.
It's a vulnera.
Vulnerability in one service
can propagate across your entire
mesh, if not properly isolated.
Cascading failures, single point
failures, don't stay, isolate it anymore.
They cooperate across microservices,
database connection, pool exertion.
Memory leaks, independent services,
and ultimately your entire platform
cascades the do like saying service
safe rails, service speed, timeouts,
and due to this service, C tries
aggressively, which causes resource,
star, and entire system will collapse.
Third threat performance demands,
you must maintain reliability
under variable workloads.
Example, black Friday traffic
is 10 x. Your baseline security
instance create traffic spikes.
Your system must handle report gracefully.
You want to slow down to say cars,
but can compromise reliability.
What is resilience engineering?
So the core definition of resilience
engineering is about engineering
systems to maintain secure and reliable
operation under adverse conditions.
This goes beyond
traditional fault elements.
The key insight is it's not
just about surveying failures.
It's about adapting to threats, recovering
gracefully in a three part foundation.
First is proactive design.
Don't wait for failures to happen.
Designwise system as human
failures will happen.
Step two, security integration.
Combine security controls with
reliability mechanisms not after
tops, robust distribution systems.
Systems that work reliably across
complex microservices environments.
It's example for this is
for traditional approach.
It's like building a service,
moderate and react others.
But as part of resilience, engineering
approach, assume the service will fail.
How does the system handle it?
What mechanisms prevent gas?
Can we recover automatically?
So there are.
Score four tolerance mechanisms
and the three, mechanisms.
One is circuit breaker patterns, second is
logic, third is redundancy calculations.
Let's discuss one problem,
so circuit breaker patterns.
So the problem we are solving
here is when a downstream service
fails, clients keep bonding it with
requests, making recovery harder.
Resource based, slow recovery
and customer facing types.
The solutions a state-based model
that detects failures and prevents
cascading errors by temporarily
halting request to failing surfaces.
Think of it like an
electrical circuit breaker.
When current gets to
pipe, it trips and stops.
There are three states.
Closed state, open state, half
open state, enclosed state normal
operations request flow through in
open state failure threshold exceeded
then circuit clicks has stopped
sending the request half open state.
In this, we test recovery with
the limited requests, like sending
one or two requests and checking
whether the service is up or not.
Let's take an example.
Your microservice handles thousand
requests per second normally.
Database crashed.
So response times spike two, 300 seconds
or 30 seconds After five consecutive
failures, circuit opens, so normal
requests sent to failing service.
After 30 seconds of open, we'll send one
or two requests to DB to check if the full
circuit closes and traffic will ratio.
They open and they'll try again.
Up 30 seconds coming to, we try logically.
So the problem here is transit
failures are common in distributed
systems like network, temporary
resource ET can create thundering hub.
All clients retrain simultaneously
or wellbeing the system.
So the solution is exponential
back of strategies that
intelligently fe the operations
without overwhelming the systems.
Each.
We 12 wait longer than the
previous one in exponential.
Like one second, two seconds, four
seconds, eight seconds, 16 seconds In
that time, so jitter will add randomness.
So all the clients don't replay the exer.
Same moment example form our system.
Six a p. A call failed
trans due to network error.
So the first feature happened
at a hundred milliseconds.
It'll wake.
Then next will happen at 200
milliseconds, and then third
will happen at 400 milliseconds.
So by the time you get to the
ry, you are waiting 1.6 seconds,
giving the system time to recover.
Progressive delay interval,
prevent cascading tress.
The key benefit of this
is transient failure.
70% succeed on first retirement.
Exponential.
Back off.
Recover from temperature failures without
adding already struggling systems.
Next is redundancy calculations.
So the concept of this is active,
passive and active deployments ensuring
continuous available, no single mission,
pulse, the entire load, spread the risk.
So there are two deployment patterns.
I two passive.
In Active U Primary server
handles all traffic.
Secondary server status one standard
example, master slave database setup.
No primary failure or on primary
failure to secondary intent to 32nd.
Recovery.
Active multiple service, actively
handled traffic submitted easily.
Load balancer distributor requests.
So example, three
identical payment process.
Each handling one third of a
traffic one, fail the remaining
to observe the traffic with grace.
Perhaps with 50% slower, not complete
outage, geographic distribution.
This is a real example.
So recently, or if we take an AWS, we
can see that there are data centers
that are present in different regions.
Like USE is west eu China everywhere.
So if a Ws USC has an auto US west
and EU keeps serving customers.
So rt, recovery time
objective, it's near zero.
Users don't notice.
RP recovery point of ticking.
Minimal data loss volume, replication,
load balancing across replicas.
Three identical services just
to traffic will be 33% to each.
Healthy checks ensures failed instances
get removed from road balance.
Automated scaling as load increases,
it'll speed up more instances.
Let's go in depth between circle
breaker pattern and action.
Okay, so first State, ERBC.
Normal operations requests
are flowing through.
Normal system is healthy.
Metrics are green.
Customers are ahead.
This is 99% of the terminal healthy system
stays to open state failure detected.
So failure threshold, exited circuit
tricks, five consecutive failures
happened and circuit got okay.
No request will be sent to the
failing service written return,
faster response to class saying
service temporarily and available.
This is crucial.
Stop wasting time from stage
three half ated testing recovery.
We are testing recovery with limited
requests like sending one or two request.
Proceed with the service if both succeed.
Recess circuit two, closed.
Full recovery.
If circuit stays open,
we'll try again later.
Stage four, recovery return to
normal so the now the service has
covered and is successfully restored.
Normal flow.
Once service healthy, circuit complete,
full traffic will be resumed and
customer see normal service levels.
Business impact due to thesis
without circuit breaker.
Outage last five minutes plus 15
minutes recovery, it'll be totally
20 minutes Pain with circuit breaker
outage recognized in 10 seconds.
Fast fail responses.
Recovery happens automatically.
User experience impact is minimum.
Next is chaos engineering testing,
resilience through control feature.
So the philosophy is chaos
engineering is disciplined approach
to discovering system weakness.
Con counter idea intentionally break
your system before real failures happen.
This is not randomly breaking
points, it's hypothesis.
The definition is chaos.
Engineering proactively injects
failures into production like anyons.
To validate resilience
mechanisms and security posture
before real insurance occur.
Example, instead of discovering
your disaster recovery doesn't
work during an actual disaster.
Test it.
Intentional key practices control
failure induction example.
Turn off one database replica.
You are simulating here.
Hardware failure.
Run the experiment for finance.
Observe system behavior.
The system should automatically
fail our two remaining requests.
Two hypothesis driven experiments.
Start with the hypothesis.
If the cash cluster goes down, our a
PA should still serve requests from
the database slower, but flex down.
Kill the cache to install.
Observe.
Does the hypothesis hold?
Can we handle it for how long?
Gradual blast radius expansion.
So we test in terms like in week
one, test a single no failure.
Week two, test network
partition between two regions.
Failure of multiple critical
services, week four, similar security.
Instead detect and
block malicious traffic.
Continuous learning and improvement.
Every chaos experiment reveals gaps.
Example, when cash failed database
was, we need better fix the
gap, then rerun the experiment.
Netflix runs chaos and they didn't
constantly, they pioneered this.
They intentionally kill services in
production using chaos and chaos.
Experiments and tools.
Because of this, they're ultra resilient
and competitors who let discuss a four
CAP Thera CP is means consistency,
availability, addition, tolerance.
So the fundamental transcr
distributed systems must
choose two or three properties.
This is a hard law of distributor systems.
You cannot have all three.
Let's explain each product consistence.
All nodes see the same data.
Some example, you transfer
hundred from account to company.
Consistency means before the transfer
A has thousand dollars and B has $400.
After that.
A has $900 and B has
$600 never in between.
Every query returns the
most recent point available.
Every request receives a response.
Your system always
response, never returns.
I don't know.
Availability goes to.
Example, 99.99% availability
is equal to max.
43 seconds down one year.
Partition tolerance system continues.
Disparate network failures.
Example, your data center
are split across continents.
A fiber cuts, some operating, even
though the two hos contacting each other.
The trade off in this practice.
CA systems, it's very rare.
It's like consistent place available,
but failure if there is a portion
example, traditional single data center,
relational database, not fault to.
So one failure is complete
locked each CP systems.
Consistent place, partition
tolerance, but may not be available.
Example, some financial systems
priorit test consistency.
Money must never be wrong, so the
trade off is if a partition happens,
stop serving request are rather than
serve inconsistent data, AP systems.
Available plus partition tolerant,
but may not be consistent.
Example, most modern web services like
Twitter straight up, is on partition.
You might solve slightly scale
data, but service keeps funnel.
So the enterprise guidances,
enterprise architecture typically
prioritize partition orders.
It's non negotiable.
They balance consistency and availability
based on businesses for money.
Choose CP Sacrifice, availability
for consistency for social.
First choose AP availability.
More important than consistency.
So next is Observability, unified
Security and Performance Manual.
So the core concept is you can't
manage what you can in your
systems behavior through data.
Four pillars of observability
methods S collection.
So performance counts,
latency measurements.
So example of these metrics
is CPU is costed 45%.
Memory is 72%.
Request C, like P 99 is goes to 200
milliseconds, which is 99% of requests
completing to 50 milliseconds.
Error rate is 0.02 percentage.
That is one error top 5,000 request.
This metrics are collect two seconds
using data tools like Prometheus,
Datadog, new Relic Plot, et cetera.
Second is centralized logging.
Aggregated logs with
security event correlation.
Every service generates logs.
You collect them in one place.
Security correlation.
Did we see suspicious patterns?
Multiple failed logins from
CNIP, et cetera, like that.
Distributed across
microservices parameters.
One customer, click Buy now request
goes through seven microservices.
Okay.
Shows order service to payment,
service to inventory service to
fulfillment service, and each lecture
timing like order is 50 milliseconds.
Payment is to 200 milliseconds.
Inventory is goes two 30 milliseconds.
Find bottlenecks while payment,
taking 200 milliseconds when
it should be 50 milliseconds.
Intelligent alert, anomaly
detection, combining security
and reliability signals.
Not just threshold, almost
like CPU greater than 80%.
I it's not that like that.
So detecting anomaly error rate should
only jump from 0.02% to file loss.
So it can be an attack or attack.
Then latency increase gradually
unusual geographic pattern.
So it can be DDS from new country.
So why this matters for resilience.
When failure happens, observability,
let us detect 18 seconds.
Not ours.
Not just what happened.
Volume first of maintain less customer
impact, data driven resilience analysis.
So we can use mathematics to
predict and proven failures.
Move from to data foundation model.
There are two mathematical models.
First one is mark change.
Model system states and transition
positive bilities to predict failure
scenarios and recovery parts.
Example, the service status
will be status is healthy, where
94% chance is L 5% chance face.
State B, it's degraded here,
60% chance recovers, 40% chance
where it fails comfortable.
And stage C, it's a first level, a
hundred percent chance must recover.
Use probable math to predict
if one service has 5% failure
probability, that's the probability.
Three.
Services all fail simul, the
answer will be 0.01 to 5%.
It's very extremely clear.
Helps you understand where
whether non helps must.
The second mathematical
model is ING theory.
Request patterns, service
rates, and resource to optimize.
Example, we have a current request
thousand per second, and the service
capacity is 400 per second average rate
than is four millisecond calculated duty.
Q not, but if it goes where it's,
so then Q will be built up and the.
Hundred Medicinals and customer.
So human theory per cells, you do at
least 1400 capacity to stay below 50
millisecond Ancy, real example from
the metrics is, let's say system can
handle 25,000 request for minimum.
That's four because possible.
Approximately.
If traffic spikes at thousand requests
per second, you need to scale up
queuing three models, request rate,
service media business model is
these quality operations enable
objective co of resilience strategies.
Example, she will spend 50 K dollars on
active readiness, or 30 K dollars on.
Map will show like active, reduce downtime
by eight 15 plus hours per year and
care delivery 30 hours per year there.
So we reduce chaos, delivery, integration,
challenges in network elements.
So the first challenge is
technology stack diversity.
We have multiple languages
about some platforms requiring
unified resilience supports.
In the real scenario, the new application
will help different frameworks, like
a payment service can be a Java Spring
Boot framework service will have Python
or first A p. A mostly will be or not.
Database will be posted to non et cetera.
Message will be each has different
failure modes, modern tools,
recovery problems, the trial.
How do you implement unified
pattern opposed to all this.
And the solution will be like
used boxes slash pattern.
Example is service me.
It had a circuit in the past.
Challenge, legacy system constraints.
All the components we
limited for capabilities.
Ready, protective block example, you
have 20-year-old main front thermal
pass contacts are rator logic.
Contact distributed person.
We can't do not auto.
The solution will be wrapping gateway with
modern resilience layer like a PA gateway,
replace sets of problem, challenge
three, security policy and forecast.
And first, all consistent security
controls across desk, correct
systems, boundaries, and trust.
Challenge is how do we ensure
all services enforce encryption,
authentication, audit log.
So parent service might be work.
I take service, might be API.
Keys legacy system might have no help.
The solution is implement security pulse.
A P Gateway service Challenge
will be operational contracts,
managing resilience mechanisms.
We thought engineering teams,
when we implement secure circuit
breakers, timeouts, redundancy.
And chaos testing.
Each team needs to
understand these concept.
Each service needs configuration
treatment, and the problem is
configuration will be sprawled,
inconsistency, and team will partner.
The solution will be its standardized
platform service mesh managed government
is will handle common credits.
Resource optimization
without compromising related.
So the, you need to scale for peak
profit example, 50,000 request per
on platform, but you can't afford to
run a peak team 365 days per year.
So solution will be optimized.
Resource without optimizing related.
First it's baseline measurement.
Establish performance and cost benchmarks.
So run for a non from collect below, like
average traffic, 2000 equals per second.
Peak traffic, 8,000 equal per second, and
the cost will be 50,000 bucks per month.
Available is 99.94%, and
that run rate is 0.0 people.
This will be your best address.
Second, identify inefficiencies.
Look at all profit from or
under replace resources.
Example in efficiencies will
be database has 16 CPU course,
but it feeds a 30% utilization.
This work provision, KPI, gateway,
has expensive certificates, but
traffic only needs 20% records.
Capacity caching layer of
its data too aggressive.
Should use bigger cash opportunity.
Reduce database to eight
course still handle three.
Circuit data rightsizing possible
applying out safety at 60% CP utilization.
Add one, use user server utilization.
Remove one server.
Example, three servers.
Black Friday can scale up
to eight server on January.
Again, you can scale it
back to three server.
Safety scale to exact amount, right?
Keep 20% metro four.
Step four, continuous violation.
Ensure optimizations maintain
s. S after optimizing measures
is available still 99.94% if you
drop to maintenance for eight.
Four of the optimization went too far to
reduce the optimization of is latency.
P 99 still below two 50 Millis.
Increase we find NCE is no capacity,
is error rate still 0.0 0.03%.
IT 50 increase time.
Progressive example, new conflict and
they maintains SLS and cut cost from
50 gig dollars, 38 K dollars per month.
This will be like 1 44, $3
per year will be served.
So actionable resilience strategies.
So we have five strategies and
we can try in depth strategy.
So first strategies defense, and
layer multiple security and form.
Others don't rely on single control.
Example, layer one, network failure.
It'll blocks weight limiting and
a layer three circuit breaker
blocks, cascading failures.
Layer four, re try with backup.
So here we handle transient
failure, ance layer six, automatic
filler so it can check our health
checks layer seven kio system.
So this will validate all the
layers one to six in scenario
if one other still theia.
So start regular chaos.
Example, we Q1 data system.
Should we two similar network partition
regions system should operate and
take to tenant now system should
and then similar security breach.
Monthly incident postmortem
to learn from the RC strategy.
Three.
Automated recovery implement
self-healing patterns and balance.
Self healing patterns.
Examples are hard pressure
ES automatically restarted.
Database slip, memory leak causes service.
Restart automatically drain
all the connections around.
Book examples if latency exists.
One second.
First, check.
Cing.
Second, scale up, part clear cash.
Four trigger logs if error rate exceed 1%.
First rollback, deploy, check locks.
Then incident deploy strategy
for unified observability, common
security and performance development.
Example, we'll have dashboards where
for performance latency error, red
through and for security log failures
are not raised by accessories.
Malicious traffic s. For correlation
will be like error rates.
Spike correlates with traffic.
Spike for it can be videos unified.
Alert, trigger alert or
combine signal security.
Press related strategy.
Five.
Continuous improvement.
Learn from incidents and media
basis after everyone's dead.
Blameless post product
should be done like that.
Not who failed, but why
failed and what failed.
We need to check Example breaker.
Didn't open fast enough.
Let's registration and chaos
test will build security.
Incident show we are missing buffer.
Let's add it so that time to detect.
Time to respond, time to recover.
Improve each quarter.
The key takeaway is take
resilience, engineering, integrate
security and reliability.
Fault tolerance mechanisms must work
in harmony with security controls.
Don't build resilience and security.
Security must work with
issue, can be exploited as DDO.
So keep opening and it'll keep
on opting since the survey.
Monitor if circuit optic
pattern was suspicious.
This bottom take observable enables
faster detection and response.
Front.
Monitoring of security and
performance signals accelerates
incident solution with observable
data proper and 10 seconds 1230.
Faster production is equal to faster
response equals to plus customer impact.
Example without observability it.
Lets start minutes.
Exclude S renal surface down, and
with the 30 seconds, take three.
Chaos ing, while its assumptions
before production and failure,
injection levels, weaknesses, system.
Then discover by months real.
Discover them.
Us.
Every chaos experiment.
A real incident example.
Will data backup start
fix before it is matter?
Don't wait till it becomes a real issue.
Data driven models provide
objective, benchmark mathematical
approaches enabled quantitative
comparison of resilience strategies.
Use smart chains and QIC data to make
objective decisions instead of, I
think we should scale to 10 servers.
You can say MAP shows.
We need eight to 10 servers
for this traffic pattern.
Enable fact-based conversation
Will stakeholders.