Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining.
Today we're going to talk about
Codeia Cloud Infrastructure as
Code best practices with Terraform.
My name is Madhu Kumayaluri.
In this presentation, we will discuss
how Terraform as an Infrastructure
as Code tool helps manage your
cloud resources effectively.
We will cover some best practices
for creating scalable, secure and
maintainable cloud infrastructure.
That's my company I use for consulting
projects with various customers,
Fortune Technologies Limited.
A little bit more about me.
I'm a principal cloud architect and
DevSecOps consultant, helping many
customers to migrate to cloud and help
them with DevOps processes, helping
with architecture designs, end to
end automation, security, et cetera.
I'm also an AWS hero and lead many
global dev communities like AWS User
Group, HashiCorp, DevSecCon, Snyk,
and DevOps Institute PeopleSet as a
chapter leader and brand ambassador.
If you want to learn more about
me, please scan the QR code
and connect me on LinkedIn.
Infrastructure as a Code is a
powerful way to manage cloud
resources by writing code rather than
manually configuring each resource.
like going to the console, click,
and just creating the resources.
And that's not a good way.
IAC provides consistency, allows you to
version control your changes, and makes it
much easier to scale your infrastructure.
So today we'll focus on how
using infrastructure as a code,
specifically with Terraform, can
enhance your cloud deployments.
So let's begin by defining ISE.
So infrastructure as a code
means describing your cloud
infrastructure using code, like
we learned in the previous slide.
This approach enables consistency in
configurations, allowing us to track your
changes, makes deployments repeatable.
By coding infrastructure, we
can avoid errors, reduce manual
configuration, and deploy much faster.
So why Terraform?
Why Terraform?
So first, Terraform is Provider
Diagnostic, meaning it can work across
multiple cloud platforms like AWS,
Azure, GCP, multiple hyperscalers.
It doesn't mean that you use the
same code in every hyperscaler.
It means that you have to create
separate modules for each of them.
But it's possible to create
for, yeah, various hyperscalers.
It uses a declarative language called
HCL, HashiCorp Configuration Language.
So where you define the desired end
state rather than the exact steps.
Terraform also has a strong community and
ecosystem with reusable modules, making it
more ideal for infrastructure as a code.
So in this session, I'll try to cover
some best practices for Terraform,
including organizing code, modules for
reusability, how you manage your state
files, handling environments, implementing
security, testing and automating
deployments, on a very high level.
So these practices are essential
for creating efficient and scalable
and, secure your environment.
So organizing code structure to
keep telephone code organized,
it's important to structure it
by a service or a component.
like you see on the right hand side of
the picture, so such as like network
layer, database layer, application layers.
So use a consistent file naming
convention as well, like main.
tf for main configurations, variable.
tf for input variables, and output.
tf for outputs.
A clean structure makes it
easier for the teams to find and
manage specific configurations.
Modules for reusability.
So modules are key to write
the reusable code in Terraform.
By using modules, you can create reusable
standalone pieces of code for common
infrastructure patterns like landing zone,
SHL, like VPC, virtual private cloud.
It's best to design
modules with clear inputs.
and outputs and to keep them focused on a
single purpose for better maintainability.
State management, terraform, state
files track, every single thing you
create on your cloud and tracks the
current state of your infrastructure.
To avoid conflicts and enable team
collaboration, store files remotely, such
as in an Amazon S3 bucket and use database
like DynamoDB for state locking, securing
and versioning your state file is very
critical to prevent sensitive data leaks.
Environment segmentation, when working
with multiple environments like
downstaging production, it's important
to isolate each environment using
telephone workspaces or directories.
It's more of common sense, The
isolation like you see on the right
hand side of the picture it's it makes
more sense for you to isolate your
dev environment because Where you
play around it's more like a sandbox.
You don't want to do Yeah, you can
do anything you want and production
is more like, you don't want to touch
It's live it impacts the customer
it impacts It causes a huge impact.
So It makes sense to isolate this to
ensure that changes from one environment
won't impact others and makes deployments
more predictable and manageable.
Some of the security practices, security
is very ground zero in cloud and
crucially infrastructure as a cloud.
Avoid hard coding secrets.
Instead, use secret management
tools like AWS Secrets Manager,
Parameter Store, or HashiCorp World.
Grant the least privilege access
necessary to developers, and enable
auditing to track those changes.
this approach basically safeguards
sensitive data, and keeps your
infrastructure more secure.
The most common security pathway,
like I've seen, is more like,
this, Yeah, secrets, API keys.
So they're basically hard coded in some
of the things, which is not a good habit.
So I would definitely recommend
putting them in a parameter
store or a Haskell world.
Automation and testing.
So automation is essential for
consistent infrastructure deployment.
By integrating Terraform into your
CI CD pipelines, either you use a
GitLab or Jenkins or Code pipeline
on AWS, you can automate testing and
validation and deployment of your
infrastructure in your pipelines Use
tools like TerraTest or Check how For
testing to ensure configurations are
secure and correct Managing drift.
like I mentioned, in the past, the most
common thing I've noticed is the manual
changes that are made outside Terraform.
some developers go on a, console,
just click, change some things
because to fix something.
to develop some things that's, in the
long run creates a drift and, and it's
painful to track those changes as well.
So regularly run Terraform plan to
detect these changes and consider
adding those in an automated drift
checks in your DevOps pipeline.
Detecting this drift early in the stages
helps you to keep your infrastructure
more consistent and avoid nasty surprises.
Let's look at an example workflow
deploying a landing zone example,
AWS VPC with multiple subnets by
following best practices, like reusing
modules for VPC, storing state file
remotely, using CI CD automation, you
can create a scalable and maintainable
and consistent cloud environment.
So this is very useful when you also have
multiple account, multiple environment.
So this code basically is just one click
on, but you change your input parameters
to create multiple environments.
So it's very useful.
Sorry.
Common challenges, the most
common challenges in the
infrastructures I've noticed
personally are like state conflicts.
Sometimes the street file might corrupt
or sometimes, they go and mess around
with the console and it creates a drift
and yeah, changes like that also sends to
data, which they keep some passports in
your telephone call, which is not good.
So solutions include using Terraform
workspaces like we discussed earlier
and isolate your environments.
manage your state file
securely on outside.
S3 bucket and all secure there.
Integrating your CI, CD
pipeline for automated testing.
we discussed about that.
So by addressing these challenges,
you can also deploy infrastructure
more securely and reliably.
Additional tools I would suggest
to improve your Terraform workflow.
Telephone cloud or enterprise
provide better collaborative
features and policy management.
It's a paid version, but it's definitely
worth it for large enterprises especially.
Or you can use Teragrunt.
Which can simplify your workflows
for larger teams Finally explore some
community resources such as terraform
registry or github Repositories or ready
made modules and examples, but don't just
blindly copy them and just directly use in
your production Just make sure do a sense
check Avoid all the sensitive information
is not there, whatever customize it for
your requirements Just to summarize,
remember the key best practices for
Terraform, structured code consistently,
use modules, prioritize security.
Security, security is ground zero,
so definitely prioritize security.
Automate with CI, CD pipelines.
So follow these best practices.
it will help you to create scalable,
secure, and more maintainable
infrastructure with Terraform.
So if you're interested in HashiCorp
tools or in the process of taking any
HashiCorp exams, feel free to join my
HashiCorp user group to learn more about
HashiCorp tools and win free HashiCorp
Terraform world console exam vouchers
by attending one of our meetup events.
With that I would say thank you for
attending Let's open the floor for
any questions or specific challenges.
You might face And thanks mark
and his brother for bringing
communities together like this 42
team you guys are doing a great job.
Thanks for giving me the opportunity