Hello everyone.
My name is Jonathan Chela.
And in this talk I'm gonna talk about
high frequency trading, where speed
is everything, we are tackling a big
problem, how do you keep things secure
when you have to be faster than lightning?
And if we add security tools, they
basically, slow down the trading.
We need a new way to be, both
fast and at the same time.
Safe.
Think of three main goals in trading.
One is, speed scale where you have to,
process millions of orders per second.
And at the same time, you cannot
compromise, security usually, when
you focus on one thing it could turn
into sacrificing the other thing.
The main issue is that, the latency
tax, every security check adds a delay.
If a traditional firewall adds,
let's say, 50 microseconds, we
are gonna lose some money, right?
We have to design systems that handle
huge volume without getting slow.
So that's the objective.
So here comes the, even driven and
cloud native, architecture where you can
design the systems, without compromising
the points that we just talked about.
So let's talk about the latency killer.
Why is the standard
competitor is too slow?
Because the operating systems, for
example, you look at Linx or Windows
gets in the way of the network card.
We use a specialized tools DPDK
or RDME to skip the voice entirely
and talk right to the network card.
So this gives us the pure speed,
but it also means we bypass
some of the, security measures.
We must move securely
to the hardware itself.
We use this, the concept of Aaron.
Which will give a sub microsecond latency.
So for the absolute fastest part
of the system, that, which is the,
the order matching system we use,
the messaging system called Aaron.
Aaron is like extremely reliable,
encrypted, instant messaging for machines.
It's built for speed.
And uses a method called raft
consensus to ensure all our trading
computers agree on the order of the
trade, even if one computer breaks.
So let's talk about, cloud native,
even bus and orchestration for
slower and high volume tasks
like analyzing market data are.
Settling trades.
We use tools like, Kafka.
This allows us, to handle huge
systems of information without
slowing down the trading engine.
We separate the tasks one part handles the
trade, which is which has to be very fast.
And another handles, record keeping,
for example, which could be.
High volume, it not necessarily
to be like, ultra fast, it
still should handle huge volume.
So the latency tax, let's look at
some of these security patterns and
how each of them, will add security
latency in terms of like microseconds.
So this chart will show how much
delay, common security tools will add.
A common security pattern called, a
sidecar used in modern microservices
adds about 150 microseconds.
That's too much for
high frequency trading.
We must bake security directly
into the application code using, in
process library to keep the delay
to, five microseconds or even less.
So at the same time, when we talk
about all these high frequency ratings
and a bunch of other applications,
connected to that observability is also,
one of the key aspect of the system.
And at the same time, we have
to achieve this observability
without, much penalty if you can't
use the standard security tools.
So how do you watch, what's happening?
We use a, a tool called EBPF,
which lets us hook directly into
the kennel without adding a delay.
It lets us observe every packet and every
action of the system that it takes for,
for compliance, all while maintaining,
zero latency goal it's observation
without the performance penalty.
So that is the goal, basically.
Determination itself is
the, is know security.
Even sourcing.
So anything that is happening in
the system, we, we need to capture
that as a, as an immutable event.
If you can't replay basically if
you have to replace a scenario,
something happened in the system.
These immutable events are very helpful.
You can basically replay the event,
what happened in the past, and
if you can't replay it, you can't
prove it, what happened, right?
That's the key.
Okay.
And four and six, like for example,
if something happened in the system
or something went wrong, you should be
able to do the, post-mortem analysis.
Where you need to replay, the trading
sequence, what exactly happened,
at a certain, time interval.
And compliance is, another aspect.
So nowadays, regulators are
demanding, proof of best execution.
And deterministic logs provide, the
evidence of the, system behavior.
So you know, com, let's talk about,
compliance as a code and real world
scale by building security and
resilience into the architecture.
We are calling it as a,
compliance as a code.
We get some amazing results.
For example, if you do, if
you look at some of these real
world, real world examples.
The London Ex Stock Exchange, can
handle, almost like close to, 15 million
messages per second, and they cut out
the systems downtime from, 40 hours to,
just about 2.5 years in the whole year.
This shows that the speed and
reliability, goes hand in hand.
And in short, when you talk about,
resilience and chaos engineering basically
in a high frequency trading system a
system that cannot recover in milliseconds
is a system that already failed.
It's you can think of it as a quote,
but, so that's the core principle of
the, high frequency trading system.
And not only, what we talked, in this
talk, there is also, a future aspect
of the high frequency trading systems.
There is still a lot need to be improved.
The next frontier is moving security
logic directly into the hardware and,
we need to achieve, zero CPU overhead.
We need to implement the firewalls, risk
checks and encryption, directly into the,
FPGA gates and bump it, bump in the wire.
Bad packets are dropped at the,
core level ensuring that they
never consume the whole CPU.
And of course we need to implement
all these things with the aspect of,
public clouds and not only private
clouds, public clouds as well.
That's the end of this talk.
Thank you for attending.