Welcome to Azure Virtual Desktop
with Terraform Infrastructures as
a Code for a Secure Experience.
This presentation appeared
because I had this question.
Is there a way to implement a
secure and replicable infrastructure
that meets specific standards?
And this presentation, I hope
I answered that question.
First, a lot of things are coming
again, like clothes, shoes,
glasses, the vintage experience.
The terminal also came back again.
Those that have a little bit
more experience know what I'm
talking about, the terminal.
server.
First, I would like to talk about me.
I am Carlos Elizalazar.
I am one of the leaders in
Comunidad Dojo in Panama.
We help people, we transform life through
cyber security, teach them, or help
them to find even a new career path.
also have a lot of certification
related to Azure and Microsoft 365.
I am Microsoft Certified Trainer and
also Terraform Certified Associated.
I have, some reconnection in some
Microsoft internal communities.
also I am a Microsoft MVP in Azure area.
I currently work in Aus Digital
Consulting as a senior, Cloud
architect or senior cloud solution
architect and a fun fact about me.
I know seven ways to prepare black coffee.
So if you like coffee, you can
ping me and I help you with that.
Also, don't look for me as a Carlos
Solis because this is will be the result.
That is a fictional character.
So please don't.
Use Carlos or Lisa to try
to find me on Internet.
We'll be talking about what is Azure
virtual desktop, of course, and we'll
be talking about the infrastructure and
architecture around Azure virtual desktop.
What is and how we will
secure Azure virtual desktop?
What is.
Terraform, what is a infrastructure
as a code with Terraform?
we will talking about, Terraform
lifecycle, and, we will see,
talk about how Terraform works.
And at the end, we will explore
the code for this demonstration.
First, I would like to show you that still
we don't have create any Azure In fact, if
you see here, this is my Terraform code.
So I first, I would like
to show you my environment.
I don't have create
any new resource group.
So first we need to create our
environment or init our environment.
I will explain any of these commands in a
couple of minutes during the presentation.
So first we init the environment.
And then we will apply our configuration,
then we'll start reading our file, our
configuration files, and it's asking
me to create a lot of resources.
Let's say yes, then we will explain
about any of these environments.
Let's go back to the presentation
and in a few minutes we will
come back to our environment.
So first, what is Azure Virtual Desktop?
And Azure Virtual Desktop, it's
a VDI infrastructure, virtual
desktop infrastructure To
virtualize service and workstation.
When to use it?
For example, when you have some
geographical limitation, you can
force your user use those, that
environment in a secure way.
Also, when you have IoT environments and
you need to access to that environment
with a terminal, you can use this
environment or Use a BD to access
to that environment in a secure way.
And also when you have a lot of
people working around the world
and need access to a secure
environment, this is a good option.
So I should be to a desktop.
One part on one big part is
administrated by Microsoft.
We don't administrate.
The gateway, the web access,
the connection broker, the some
diagnostic is tools, even the
license related to that environment.
All those resources will be
administrated by Microsoft.
What are we going to administrate?
The session host, for example,
the regular, windows or
linux, windows environment.
And, also the image of those custom,
custom OS could be possible, the
applications related to that session
host, and also the users through
our domain controller or Enter ID.
One good aspect related to
Azure Virtual Desktop is that
you can use it in your browser.
In fact, you can use
it in any environment.
for your time.
or any device that support HTML5.
So you can connect to your environment
through the browser or even if in Windows
or Mac you can use the application.
So to understand a little bit
how Azure Virtual Desktop network
connectivity works, let's say our user
is in a laptop table, or a computer.
Tablet or even a phone.
He first authenticate in our entry did.
During that authentication, they
will use the web access, the portal.
And if we have the authorization,
also we are connected to the gateway.
And it's the ends ID that will
allow us to connect to our session
host, our desktop application.
And all that is through HTTPS.
We don't have to create this
firewall or this other firewall.
Those resource are administrated
by Microsoft, so we don't have
to open the Port TT eight nine.
We just use our browser authentic
k with our ID credentials, and then
we can enter in the environment.
A good security layer
related to Azure Desktop is.
We will use our Entry ID Authentication.
So using Entry ID Authentication,
we can use our process of
multifactor authentication.
We start, evaluating the
user, the location of the
user, The device is a phone.
A computer is a computer.
A trusted computer is a new computer,
which application the user is
connecting and the real time risk.
Those are some evaluation
related, different variables.
All those values can allow us
to connect or will ask you for,
we will require multi factor
authentication to enter or even block.
And when we pass this, we can
access to our environment.
So we have the first layer is
related to the authentication.
If the user cannot authenticate
in Azure Virtual Desktop, cannot
access to the environment.
Then we can, in all
session hosts, we can use.
Microsoft Defender for endpoint.
So we can have our malware protection
layer covered with this solution, and
also we can monitor all the behavior
of the OS in our environment and to
administrate all those machines in
Azure Virtual Desktop, we can use, for
example, the Active Directory domain
service to apply some GPOs in the OS, but
also we can implement Microsoft Intune.
That is a service, a fast service of
administration of a mobile device.
So we can apply controls to our
host from, Microsoft Intune and
the Microsoft infrastructure.
Another good thing related to Azure
Virtual Desktop is we can apply a disaster
recovery infrastructure really cheap.
And really fast in our environment.
When we have a disaster, let's say in a
point we have a disaster in the region
can be in the region, the Microsoft
region and the Azure region and we
can replicate or we have activated a
replication of our OS on session host.
For the user will be really
transparent, connect to another region.
Maybe they will have some latency,
but can access to the environment.
And they not necessarily
lost a lot of information.
Maybe it's a little bit information.
In Azure Virtual Desktop, you have
a lot of way to set and save the
data of the user in real time.
Let's talk about Terraform.
First, let's talk about
infrastructure as a code.
It's a practice of managing and
provisioning compute infrastructure
like servers, networking, database,
and even a lot of more resources
through machine, machine readable file.
we can control our, Resources
and change all the resources.
But what is a infrastructure as a code?
with Terraform is from HashiCorp.
company is an infrastructure as a code
tool and will let you define, and an
infrastructure in a human readable
dec declarative configuration file.
We receive the file, don't worry and
manage the infrastructure lifecycle.
And using Terra phone you have.
Several advantage and I would like to
talk why I start using Terraform in my
case, I was working with some developers.
We implement Azure DevOps
in the deployment of the
code, but usually we have.
Some issues, some communication issues
related and the deployment of the
infrastructure in production in QA
and in the in development environment.
So I started learning Terraform
to deploy the environment.
This allow us to Manage the infrastructure
and have control of the infrastructure.
So in a point I when I had conversation
with them and they told me the developer
I don't have access, the configuration
for QA is not the same from production.
I start from the beginning
telling that it's not possible.
It is the same code.
So when it's the same code, Code you
there is no a way that the configuration
is not the same in any environment.
So we first can't manage
any infrastructure.
We can manage a lot of
infrastructure related to, for
example, Azure, AWS, Google cloud,
even, being where environment we
can manage that infrastructure.
We can standardize, deployments.
And, eh, the deployment workflow.
When we have this big workflow that we
need, eh, we won't have any issue, any
problems because, eh, the code that we
already test in one moment, we can know
that, eh, that code will be deployed
in any environment, each environment,
which you can track the infrastructure.
One thing that I really like it because
in the projects usually somebody edit
or modify the infrastructure directly
in Azure, for example, directly edit
and modify the environment so telephone.
I can know where.
they change and what is
the value that they change.
For example, in my case, when I have the
issues with the developers, they make a
change in the developer environment, I
can see it and apply that modification
in QA and production to allow the
functioning of the application, the
correct functioning of the application.
Also, when you have a GitHub, You can
use the environment, for example, that
is an example in a current project that
I have, we have some architect working,
developing the Terraform code, everyone
is working a piece of the environment,
and we are updating the environment.
Same repository, and we have one code
for all the components that we need
infrastructure, and I just need to use git
and make a git pull, git push, and merge
a branch, but I can't Work on a lot of
the team can work in the same code with
the correct planification coordination.
What is the life cycle of telephone?
I started the presentation
doing some comments.
Let's explain those comments.
First is the telephone in it.
Telephone in it will read your main file,
will read which modules, which providers.
Are you using, for example, in my case,
I am using a module that I developed
and using the Azure Rm provider.
using those, values in the environment,
if they, Terraform will download the, all
the information that they to run locally.
There is a command.
We didn't run it, but we
can run a Terraform plan.
Terraform plan will help us to identify
what a what is the modification?
What are the code that
we are implementing?
And if they change that we want
to apply, is the correct one.
Just will show you, show us
what is the plan that we have.
The code that we just run
is the Terraform apply.
Terraform apply, we read our
configuration and then when they read
the configuration, they will Execute
and create the resources that they have.
They first run the Terraform
Apply, will run a Terraform plan.
And when they run that Terraform plan,
will ask a question, I have to answer yes.
And that is the only possible answer.
If you respond, anything else
will be canceled the application.
So they, after we answered yes, they
started creating the environment.
And at the end, the final of the
life cycle is Terraform Destroy.
I can destroy a complete
and complex environment.
Within minutes, just applying this
command, they'll also will read all the
information and tell me if I have agree
of the destruction of the environment.
So we have to be really sure about it,
but we just need to run this comment.
I can run all this and in less than
an hour, I can create a complex
environment, make my test, do all the.
Test that I need to do the
demo that I need to do.
And then I destroy the environment.
That is a cheaper way to, to
have a complex environment.
make my test, any time that
I want, how Terraform works.
I have.
A file in Windows is Terraform
do access file in Linux.
We just install the epi
installed Terraform.
We will install the
executable of that comment.
So that's executable.
When we run these comments
that I show previously, they
read the files that I create.
They read the files, they
create and update constantly
A file called telephone dot.
TF State, this show the state of
the environment, in, in, in a file.
And we will connect to a multiple
providers, like I said, AWS Azure,
Google Cloud, even digital Ocean.
So if I make a change in the,
in the environment and run
the Terra code, they will.
Evaluate what I have in Terraform
state, what I have in the environment
and what I have in the file.
And if something has changed in
the environment, then show me
in the code and in the prompt, I
will see what is the difference.
Related to my file, my Terraform
state file and the environment.
So with that, I can know somebody modified
something that didn't, I didn't provide,
didn't authorize, or that wasn't the
plan, or if it is, if the plan, I can
update my Terraform code and run again
the command and we say that everything is.
It's okay.
So enough talking, let's show you
a little bit about the environment
and the code that we deploy.
So as you can see, we
find, we run our command.
A lot of resources were created,
25 blocks, but not the resources.
So a lot of thing was creating.
I will explain to you the code.
But let's see how, that is in
the end user point of view.
We, we need to update this
usually take a couple of minutes
or seconds to update.
So I have my session host
and my connection to a
computer in the environment.
Let's say I allow these are RDP
configuration, so I can, by default,
for example, block, copy and paste,
they use the clipboard, so I cannot use
the clipboard on the environment or my
personal clipboard in the environment.
And while this is happening, because it's
the first start, take a couple of seconds,
let's see the first part of the code.
the first part of the code, I
define where I will storage my,
my, my Terraform state file.
I store it locally, and we have it here.
This is our file, our Terraform
state file is here, as you
can see, and we can, we know.
All day.
And if we see the file will
tell us what they create and
what we have in the environment.
So in our main file, we have first,
I have a comment to remember, work on
how to connect to the Terraform file.
I create a module, and this
module is, using my source call,
my, my provider that I create.
What is the version I define the
users that will use the terra.
The visual, virtual Dexel environment.
I define some variables to make
it more related to the event.
I define how many
computers I want to create.
I create two computers in
this Terraform environment.
And what is the tenant ID and what
is the subscription ID that I'm using
because my user have two computers.
A lot of secretion, and then I
hope I use a lot of them and I need
to create a registration token.
I need to create this value and
one requirement shouldn't be more
than one month and less than a day.
It's the period of time that
I can create the registration
token and those variables.
I define the variables, the my
tenant ID and my subscription id.
This is all that I need locally and when
I run telephone in it, Terraform will read
this and will download all the information
that I need to create my environment.
So I have here, this is the
module that I use, to run.
The creation of the Terraform, I will
show you the configuration of the files.
Before that, I would like to show you
our Windows environment already created.
And I, in one of the
hosts, let me show you.
In which hole I am connected.
So I am connected in the first hole.
What is that first hole?
Let's see it in the first graphically
or in the dashboard portal.
What I have.
So I update my resource group.
I have my new resource group
created with the resources.
And I have two computers.
One is called Con 42, 20 24,
2, and the other one is con 22.
con 42, 20 24 1.
I create two virtual machine.
I just need to change the number,
update the number, reduce the
number, the quantity of number,
and they will automatically.
Increase or decrease the resources.
I need to create a virtual
network, a network security group.
As you can see, I don't have public IP
in this environment, so I don't use any
direct connection to the virtual machine.
All they manage is through
the Azure Virtual Desktop.
I have the host pool.
Here I manage all the resources.
I can even define a scaling
plan, that is, I decide shut
down or, turn off the computer.
Here I have the different,
RDP configurations.
I can define, for example, if I want
to use the Microsoft, the micro,
the microphone, the camera, and.
Also, the clipboard or the drivers of
the printer, or I can do it through
different variables to create this result.
And here I can see the state of my
computers or my session host connecting
to the Azure Virtual Desktop environment.
and here I have a user
connected, in fact, two users.
In the test, I can see which users
are connected in the environment.
This is a validation of what
is the state of that computer.
let's see the telephone code.
And first we create a, as I said, the
first we have to create a resource group.
So this is the value or this is the block
to create a resource group with Terraform.
They, we will create, um.
network and this is one phone value I
by default define that when I create the
virtual network will have the suffix PNET.
I define the prefix.
This is my prefix defined here.
But all the Sufi always will be have
and always the network acuity group.
The Sufi will be an SG, and
those are the default values.
So I always will have that, a
convention name in my infrastructure.
So we created the
networking part and then.
After that, we need to create the
azure virtual desktop environment.
creating the azure virtual desktop
environment, I create the Workplace,
the host pool, as you remember,
we, we had, the same configuration.
These are the custom RDP properties.
I define it here by default in
the environment and also define
how we call the host pool.
They always Terraform host pool and
then, something here, always I can.
Customize the prefix.
Create the registration info that
I need for the other resources
and creating application group and
automatically I create everything
related to the Azure Virtual Desktop.
So after I create that, I
will create the session host.
I take the registration token, but
I create the network interface.
Because I decide create two
machine, they will use, a loop here.
So we're creating two network interface,
and then we're creating two VMs and
also with their OS disk, and this
is the fun part first, I need to.
Make that those computers authenticated
with enter ID authentication.
So I, this is the
configuration to achieve that.
And why is that?
Because Azure, Beto only will work
if we have a active director, domain
service authentication, the computer.
So we have to join to the domain,
those computer, or if we are
using, enter the authentication
for my demo purpose, I will.
Don't create a directory domain service,
but I use the Enter ID authentication.
So first, I force the compute that
those session hosts, I force them to
use a Enter ID as an authentication,
as a domain controller, quote unquote.
And then I will register those computers,
those virtual machines in the environment.
As you can see, also, always I have the
count, so if I define two computers,
they will create this block two times.
And they will use in the computer
because this is the structure
of the idea of the computers.
And with this script, I add the
computer to the environment.
And because the security is important.
I extract the information of the user,
I create a security group and I add
the minimum roles that those users
need to use Azure Virtual Desktop.
I don't give them any other roles.
I don't have to be always asking
which role need the user to connect.
I know they need desktop
user virtualization.
and in the application group.
And they will need a virtual machine
user login in the session host.
Always I will be complying
that configuration.
Ow!
If you remember, we already are in
the environment, but I will show you
what happens when we have an incident.
Let's say, for any reason,
the computer fails.
I stop, let's say, the computer fails.
we come back to our
environment, and we will wait.
A few seconds, and we have an error.
We disconnected to the computer.
For some reason, we lose
the connection to that host.
I just refresh the screen
and try to connect again.
Let's see if we can.
We already lost one host, but
we have a second host running.
We log in.
And because this host is new, it will
be making the login process again,
but as you can see, I have access
again to my virtual environment, even
if I lose a computer for any reason.
The computer failed, crashed, any reason,
I automatically have a secondary host
where I can work and continue doing
my process or my daily activities.
if we come back here, we can
see, let's enter in the computer.
This is the virtual machine
that we just shut down.
As you can see, the computer is shut down.
And if we go to the Azure virtual desktop
environment and refresh the screen, we see
that we have one host that has a screen.
We don't know what it was, but we
know that we have a host with a
problem, but our user could connect
to the new host without any problem.
Let's prove that we have
in the secondary host.
As you can see, I am the host number two.
So what's relative fast,
transparent to the user.
And we can continue doing
our daily activities.
Let me run again the VM.
This will take a couple of minutes.
Start the VM and then in a
few minutes, we'll be seeing
everything is running okay.
As you can see, Azure Virtual Desktop
can help us in our deployments, in our
tests, I just show you a way to create
Azure Virtual Desktop environment,
can help the developers, can help the
teams, but we can do it also for Azure.
Other resources are using telephone.
We can deploy environments,
complete environments with a code.
And also we will have a, the security
layer that we need in our environment.
One final thought, there is
a complete certification.
Related to Azure Virtual
Desktop is the Exang AC 140.
It's all related to Azure Virtual Desktop.
Also, there is the Terraform
certification that you can execute it.
And, of course, Use the Microsoft
MVP Forum Stack Overflow to ask
questions if you have any issue.
I asked a lot of questions
to complete this code.
in those forums a while ago.
you can find me in LinkedIn.
I'm Solis Carlos.
Please, if you will look for my
complete name, use Carlos Solis Salazar.
to finish or close our.
our life cycle of Terraform.
Let's see, for example, let's see
again, if we recover our host, I
don't see it anymore as a failed host.
I see, okay, here, maybe I have to wait.
Ah, as you can see, we
already have the host.
So let's now the final step is
Terraform destroyed environment.
This will take again.
We'll read everything that we have
in our Terraform state file in our
environment and in our configuration,
and we'll define what we have to
do to destroy the environment.
As you can see, we'll destroy
everything that we created, computers,
and, The different computers and
network interface and this, and the
extension that we use to, to, you,
to join the computer to enter ID.
and, It will destroy practically
everything we created, and we just have
to approve the destruction, and that's it.
That's it.
The process will take a couple
of minutes, but at the end, you
can be sure that everything will
be destroyed, and that's it.
We just use a little
bit our Azure created.
I hope everything, was nice.
And if you have any question, please don't
hesitate ask me in any social network.