Good morning, afternoon,
evening, everyone.
my name is Paul Edward and, I have
over 12 years of experience in
enterprise software development.
I love the open source community.
I contribute to the open source community.
I love writing.
I speak, I build, and most
importantly, I'm a boxing advocate.
It's I'll be talking to you about.
A topic that is very dear to me,
the risk you don't want to win.
I've been fortunate to work on systems
that undo sensitive transactions, which
means security is always a top priority.
Today, we share a story about a breach we
faced, a flaw very subtle yet devastating
that shook our system and our confidence.
This is the race you don't want to win.
So let's, dive in.
So imagine two kids running
to grab a cookie from a jar.
The jar is supposed to hold just
one cookie, but if the kids grab at
this exact same time, the jar might
magically let both of them win.
That is a race condition.
Two processes competing to access
the same resources and most of the
time the system gets very confused.
So in, software development, this Apple
went to process, try to assess or modify
the same database record at the same time.
Imagine your system is updating the
user wallet balance and to withdraw
request, it's the database simultaneously
and there are no checks in place.
In that case, the database might end
up processing both of them, even though
there was only enough money for one.
So it is like your code is running
just too fast for his own good.
And here is the kicker.
It doesn't matter what programming
language you're using, Java, Python,
even SQL database aren't immune.
Condition doesn't discriminate
the mess of any system.
And that is if you're not careful.
So this condition has cost
the world a lot of money.
Companies like, night capital has lost
over 440 million, Dollars even this year
gt bank has had the same issue according
to the news report online And they
were like, I think they had two weeks
of transactional failures and so The
smallest oversights most of the time.
I think all the time they are very
catastrophic consequence So That
is why we are talking about it so
here's what I put in our system, our
app possesses wallet transaction.
Let's say a user has 1,
000 in their wallets.
Then a clever attacker discovered
he could send two withdrawal
requests at the exact same time.
The system, thinking it is handling
things one by one, approved both requests.
The same 1, 000 was withdrawn twice.
So it was like the system was just too
polite to say, hey, wait your turn.
Now, multiply this by hundreds
of transactions and you are going
to be staring at a massive loss.
A financial loss of over 70 million
and a loss of sleepless nights.
how did we, tackle this?
We immediately launched an investigation.
Step one was to, identify
the breach entry points.
We come through the logs, replicated
that issue in a controlled environment.
We use, tools analyzers and
debugging frameworks were our
best friend at that point in time.
It wasn't just about fixing the problem.
We needed to understand.
fully What really happened to be able to
prevent future exploits and I will really
advise you to do so as well So what are
the countermeasures that we also did?
Our first move was damage control.
And we disabled the affected feature
first of all and implemented a
temporary fix just to stop that exploit.
And long term, we redesigned the
transaction flow to be able to undo
we also added some very stricter
monitoring and, monitoring and anomaly
detection, ensuring that subtree
regularities will just trigger an alert.
And we also implemented an accounting
feature, the principle of double
entry, just to make sure that for
every credit, there's a debit.
For every debit, there's an
equivalent, credit as well.
The preventive measure that we
took, we make sure we test for
edge cases, this weird scenario
where your code might break.
You have to always test for edge cases and
probably under a controlled environment,
simulate a very high traffic, stress test
your application to see if it holds up.
You have to always think like an attacker.
Yeah.
If you were trying to break
your system, how will you do it?
Ask yourself that question and review
your code with concurrency in mind.
Ask yourself, what happens if two people
click the same button at the same time?
Secure coding is all about
asking the right question.
Regularly test for vulnerabilities,
anticipate edge cases,
test concurrency on that.
Eye loads as well.
So I'm just going to be walking you
through a very live demo to explain to you
in real term how, this condition works.
So I spinned up a PHP application, this
wallet controller as a withdraw method.
And this withdrawal method is taken
into payload, the user ID and amounts.
The user ID to be able to
identify the wallet that we
intend to make a withdrawal from.
And here is where we're trying
to get the, withdraw, the wallet
that belongs to that user.
And if that wallet is not found,
we immediately throw an error
that the wallet cannot be found.
And if the wallet is found, we
check if there's sufficient, if
the balance is sufficient enough
to be able to make a withdrawal.
And if it, if there is no enough fund, we
trigger insufficient balance straight up.
This code looks very cool because
you're doing all the right checks,
all the things are rightly done here.
And immediately after that, we deduct
the money from the user, from the
user's wallet balance and immediately
updates our database record.
And we.
Is that instant?
We also notified you that
it would rise successful.
As well.
And if anything goes wrong, we
throw an error telling the user that
probably, okay, something went wrong.
If you're looking at this code, we are
doing all the right checks in place.
Everything is done in the way
that is expected to be done.
And I'm sure if you try this, you probably
throw a request at these, this to walk.
very smoothly.
The right amount of money that
you're throwing at it is going
to be, deducted accordingly.
if we are going to be attacking these
probably with this condition in mind,
let's see what is going to happen.
So here I spinned up a Python
code base and, I'm calling, I'm
making, A call to that endpoint.
And then we have a user idea of one.
And because I think I need to show you
what is happening in the database here.
So let's look at the wallet table.
if you look at this, we have a user idea
of one and the wallet balance is there.
So I think let's make this, 600,
and let's save this quickly.
So really, so yeah, is the Python
request, and, just a very busy Python
script that sends, concurrent, multiple
concurrent requests to these endpoints.
And I think we're just going to be
sending 10, simultaneous requests
to these endpoints instead of one.
I think, let me try to just,
probably simulate just one request.
And, and see, let's see what happens.
We're going to be deducting 100 from
the 600 box we have in our database.
And if I'm calling this, probably only
this Python scripts, what do we get?
as you can see, your new
wallet balance is 500 now, 500.
And if we are to refresh
this, you will see that.
I think, balance has been updated to 500.
Everything works very smoothly.
So what about if we
decide to make this, 10?
Simultaneous request, like we are
trying to call a end point 10 times.
And, those 10 that we're trying to deduct
a hundred, a hundred bucks, we should
not be able to deduct the piece because
a hundred multipli by 10, I think that
will give us, 1000 and we just have 500
bucks in our, in our wallet balance.
So let's see what happens.
So I'm going to be initiating this end.
If you can see, I was able
to make this call 10 times 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
And he's still telling me here that
I have a hundred bucks as my balance.
I was able to, make a withdrawal
of, 1, 000 bucks, 10 on red box.
It's telling me, yeah, that if
I'm to refresh this, we have,
a balance of a hundred bucks.
What does this mean?
I have cheated the system.
Yeah.
So just in case you have this, I
would advise you to run this script
against probably your code base
and see, and probably the results
might be very shocking to you.
So one of the lessons that's, we learned
from this is this, I'm coming back
to explain how you able to fix things
like this is, we, you need to know that
small flaws have very big consequences.
If single book, almost true brought
down our system and prevention
is better than cure tests.
tests, proactively test
and test repeatedly.
Monitoring could have also caught this
earlier, but I don't think we implemented
all of this at the earlier stage.
And also security is a team sport.
It's a collective effort.
Developers, testers, even users have
roles to play in keeping systems safe.
But the real tiki we here is this.
Treat every bug like it could
be your next big breach.
I think let me repeat this again.
Treat every bug like it
could be the next big breach.
Because sometimes it will be.
Yes, it could be sometimes.
So I really emphasize on also
secure design and testing
that Every stage as well.
So before I would go back to the
conclusion, let me quickly go back
to the live demonstration and okay.
How did we fix this?
So one of the things that
we did, let me go back.
Yeah.
Is one of the ways we can to prevents
a race condition is to use things
that we call disable deadlocks.
So be able to control.
resource access.
Usual transaction logs and rollback
mechanism like probably your DB
transactions to, to make sure that
when probably there is, a bridge
at any point or there's a failure
at any point, it can roll back the
previous record as it has entered.
And like I said earlier, introduce
rigorous testing and probably in a
controlled environment simulate high
concurrent scenarios to be able to show
that your code is running very smoothly.
So let's go back to, the code base.
And I think that will add more
light to what I've just said.
and that is, it's, so now
we have a hundred books.
I think I'm going to make this, 500.
Now, and, let's save this.
So I implemented another method here,
where we call this, the withdraw fix.
So we are taking in the same,
payload, the user ID and the
amount, but what did we do here?
We, just like I mentioned in, my
previous, on the slide that we should you
should watch, use this, use, she used,
transaction logs and go back mechanism.
And that was what we did here.
Laravel has a feature like this.
I think this is for Laravel.
other frameworks as their, other language
as their own, method in also making sure
for you to be able to, do your transaction
log and your go back mechanism as well.
But this is strictly for Laravel.
So We started the transaction here
that anything between this transaction
when there is an issue here, it's
When there's an issue here, it should
immediately Roll back anything that it
has done previously, so let's, sorry,
I was not showing you the code base.
so yeah, we started the, transaction.
Yeah.
I think, like I said, this
is strictly for larval.
So now I think let me close this.
So we can have a full screen.
And another thing we did while
we were checking for the user
that owns the wallet, we did
what we call log for updates.
So we're saying that the pending, when.
This query is being run on the
database, lock that, rule for any
further updates till I'm done checking
what is, what I need to do here.
See when this query is successful,
lock this for further updates.
So and I think this is one of the first
place we need to, we are, we actually
started solving the issue of the risk
condition and if the wallet is not
found, you need to do the same thing.
Thank you very much.
If the wallet is not found, you notify
the user that the wallet is not found.
And yeah, we do what we call, we check
in the database is, if you have, enough,
funds in your DB and we do a row back
here, just when, your wallet balance
is less than, the amounts, we do that.
And if not, just in case anything,
any edit has been made to the
database within these points.
So we want it to be rollback.
So here at this point, then we make
the wallet deduction on the database
and we commit the transaction.
And if everything is successful, we return
that successful message to the user.
and in case of any error,
we can also roll back here.
I think I can also take these out, we
go back here and just probably had one.
this is just to be able to prove a
point on how we can solve this as well.
So now we are going to
call the second endpoints.
And I think what I call these is,
I think, let me see, we draw fixed.
And don't forget, we have
all we are, we just have, 500
bucks in our wallet balance.
So I'm going to call this again,
I'm going to run this again.
So we're going to still
simulate 10 concurrent requests
and let's see what happens.
So I think 10 concurrent requests,
that would still be 1000.
I should not be able to withdraw more than
500 because that is what I have in mind.
So we'll try it again.
Good.
Now, as you can see, something went wrong.
Okay, we started.
I hear something went wrong.
Something went wrong.
Yeah.
Our first, but I would
meet the first, 100 books.
we draw a quest 400.
300, 200, 100, 100, zero, and
it may start saying insufficient
balance, as you can see.
So we could not make that same withdrawal
of 1, 000, box like we did earlier.
So and if we are to check the
database record, yeah, I think
it should be zero right now.
So we've prevented the
issue of race condition.
I really hope this is clear.
I believe it's clear.
So let's, and, let's go back
to, the conclusion and yeah.
Yeah.
So
security is in this point is a marathon.
it is not just a checkbox.
It is a mindset.
We need to have security as a mindset.
The reason you don't want to
win is, is the race to fix
your system after an exploits.
So let's stay vigilant, test
everything, and remember it is better
to prevent the fire than to put it out.
Thank you.