Hello and welcome to an existing
edition of our podcast, bridging
Science and Spirituality, the future
of mobile and digital knowledge
management, where we explore what
happens when technology, science
and spiritually spirituality needs.
I am xla.
I'm thrilled to be joined by 2 billion
HE, Dr. Ranita kli and Priam kli.
Together we have been working
on an innovative mobile
platform called Neo Light.
Designed to make learning across
spiritual and scientific domains.
the app right now is in the alpha
testing phase and it is very
powerful, in and personal from a
deep, from a developer point of view.
I have spent months architecting
and deploying Neo light
on the Android platform.
It's been a deeply technical journey.
Configuring, get compost, firebase, file
store, optimize offline support for the.
The purpose behind it has been
equally profound, building a digital
sanctuary for seekers of all kinds.
Thank you, sva.
Yeah, thanks a lot, sva.
this has been a collaborative labor
of love and I'm delighted to be here.
While Shva focused on the foundation
I worked on curating and testing
the spiritual content to ensure it
resonates emotionally and energetically.
with the users, my role focused on
tuning, the ancient wisdom and turning
it to daily practice through the
app, which required a lot of user
empathy and cultural sensitivity.
Hi everyone.
My name is Priam and
I'm the content analyst.
And, from my side, I helped,
bridging the scientific concepts,
with cognitive, learning strategies.
Neo light is just not
a information platform.
I would say it's a form of
living, breathing tool as well,
and that evolves with the user.
I, currently worked on, validating
and testing the pathways using neuro
neuroscience principles and making
sure we are aligned, learning with the
learning with how our brain works too.
The synergy we have built between
spirit science and code mix.
This one of the most unique
digital platforms I have had
the pleasure on working on.
Thank you Ranita.
And.
So near light began as a simple idea
to the billion app that doesn't just
deliver information, but nurtures the
consciousness from a technical standpoint.
This meant building a scalable, modular
system that could support structured
learning paths, micro learning modules
and spiritual practices without
needing constant internet access.
The app.
The app runs on preferred content
right now, meaning all resources
are bundled securely within the app,
making it usable in, in the remote
and rural regions with the limited
data access for, yeah, actually, I
remember testing those early bills.
Simplicity was the key.
A verse in the morning, a
meditation prompt in the evening.
When consistently practiced these
small rituals transformed how
users related to their inner cells.
We wanted to make that a spiritual
process, not just, accessible,
to everybody, but as a natural
and as much as possible, like
sipping tea or going for a walk.
And when it comes to about that
app, we have backed it with data.
We observed that the users felt calmer
and pacified, and much more focused
when the content rhythm matched their
psychological state of mind as well.
Our models weren't just
spiritually meaningful.
But we actually, they were
placed in a scientific manner.
One of my favorite test runs showed a user
sleep score particularly improved using
our guided breath model for just one week.
Yes, exactly.
Priam.
So scientific spiritualism is a term we
often use, but it deserves deep unpacking.
It's not just about using science
to prove spirituality, not using
spirituality to, mystify science.
It's about treating both as complimentary
paths to understand the human condition.
One observes from the outside in
and the other from the inside out.
Exactly when we build the
pathways in your light, we were
intentional about our journey.
You might start with neuroscience.
Explainer or emotion regulation over here.
But then we eventually, we
moved into guided practice from
Budhist philosophy as well.
We built this bridges between content
that seemed unrelated, but actually
completes a full circle of understanding.
Thank you.
my response will be was to make sure
this journey was technically possible.
Our content management system built to
tag content semantically by emotion.
Topic, tradition, and even energy level.
So if you want to explore balance, the
app can surface resources from multiple
disciplines and help you see that.
Science and spirituality are really just
different languages of the same truth.
And we often call neo late as a digital
tempo and they truly believe that.
Every screen color transition and
font was selected with intention.
The tech stack jet pack, composed fire
base and room database for offline
learning allowed us to construct a
robust backend and elegant front end.
But more than that, we
treated every design decision.
Like a spiritual choice.
Exactly.
It's univa.
So the results showed during testing.
Because when we were testing it,
users say that the app felt safe,
and that was a powerful word.
Indeed.
One said it felt like opening
a sacred book, and another
described it as a mirror.
We are often used to noisy, chaotic
apps, but neo light was built to
feel like a white walk in the forest.
And Ranita, as you have rightly
mentioned, we have also validated
this using UX psychology principles.
We have reduced the visual clutter, muted
tones and strategic micro interactions,
lower cognitive loads as well.
When users experience less friction
there, they engage more deeply and the
digital becomes devotional as well.
Yes.
So what is the science of microlearning?
Spirituality doesn't always
come in grand gestures.
It often whispers.
That's where microlearning comes in.
Users may not have time for a full hour of
study, but they can engage with a verse,
a question or a three minute reflection.
So we tested this and with a daily
rhythm and it really works well.
We use learning science models like,
spaced reputation and contextual
queuing to design content.
So suppose when someone reads about
gratitude in the morning, they might
be nudged later to reflect our journal.
And also this reinforces
their memory and emotions.
Creating a loop of learning
and transformations.
Yeah, exactly.
So implementing this was a technical joy.
We engineered the app to send
notifications based on based on
user preference, not just time,
but mood, content, affinity.
And since it's all stored on device for
now, it's a fast, private, and stable.
And even during travel are low
connectivity periods when the people are
traveling to remote locations and even
when they're like hiking and if they want
to rest in a kind of, like outing, right?
Anywhere you can access the
app because the data sitting
on your local devices, right?
So what we can summarize, like this app
can be a companion that understands you.
So new light is not just a mobile
application, it's a companion, it's
a friend, it's sentiment aware,
interfaces and voice recognition
tools, helps in development.
And we also, want the platform to
respond just more above than the clicks.
It should respond to energy as well.
Exactly, yes.
I do remember when we tested the
voice queries with different tones.
The users asking, I feel
lost, or Show me peace.
The app responded with curated
modules like chance, poems,
songs, and reflections.
It became more than smart and
it became just compassionate.
Thank you, Anita, for your kind
words, but we are still early
in that process right now.
the app doesn't use real
time data, but works with
carefully curated prepaid files.
That gives us control and consistency
during our alpha testing phase,
but once we go public, AI will
help it to grow into something even
more interactive and personalized.
And we are currently in alpha testing,
phase gathering feedback, refining ui,
ux, and finalizing multi-language support.
The content is preloaded and there
is no real time data sync yet.
But soon we will begin rolling out
our beta with guided meditation
series, a HR support and.
I'm specially excited about
the collaboration tools.
We are working on community led
journeys where groups can follow
the same path, reflect together,
and build wisdom collectively.
It's called as a spiritual mentorship
reimagined for the mobile age, and
scientifically, we want to integrate
passive biometrics, measuring focus.
Heart rate and even voice stress levels
as well to adjust the contact, the,
to adjust the content dynamically.
The long-term goal, an app that
evolves with you emotionally,
cognitively, morally, logically,
sure, and spiritually as well.
So your light isn't just a software.
So it's quite kind of a soul where
you can see a space where seekers
can pause, breathe, and begin again.
I would say it's a bridge
connecting heart, mind, and machine.
And it's built with care,
science and devotion as well.
Yeah, you guys very well in our, set about
the app, but as the new light is still in
alpha, but the light is already spreading.
We can't wait to share it with the world.
Stay tuned.
Your journey awaits.
Thank you folks.