Hi everyone, and welcome
to this session at Con 42.
I'm thena and I'm thrilled to be
a part of this incredible event.
A big thank you to Con 42 for organizing
this and to all of you for tuning in,
even though we are not in the same do.
I'm excited to share some
valuable insights with you today.
So I'm an open source
contributor at Gopher.
Gopher is a Golang framework for
accelerated microservice development.
In Golan, we focus on building resilient.
Scalable and secure microservices.
Over the years, we have faced numerous
challenges, building and scaling
distributed systems, and Boer is the
result of all those hard earned lessons.
Boer is designed for efficient
interservice communication.
Observability and scalability By building
microservices, it removes the boilerplate
code for you so you can focus on your
business logic with minimal lines of code.
In this session, we'll explore the
challenges of interservice SGTP
communication in microservices.
Then I'll go on to introduce you to
gofer, which simplifies these challenges.
We'll dive into the key features
of gofer that help you build
efficient interservice, SGTP
communication architectures like
circuit breakers and retry confis.
Authentication observability
and health monitoring.
Finally, we'll see a live demo to show
you how easy it is to set up Interservice
SGTP communication architectures in Gofer.
So let's not waste any more time
and let's get going with Gofer.
Now, imagine you are building a
microservice based e-commerce store.
So when a user places an order,
the user service calls the payment
service to complete the payment.
But what if the payment
service is unresponsive?
Sounds familiar, right?
This is one of the many challenges
that can arise while interservice
communications in microservices.
In today's world of distributed
systems, microservices are the
backbone of modern applications because
they allow us to build scalable,
modular, and maintainable systems.
But one of the most critical
aspect of microservices is how
they communicate with each other.
SGDP is the defacto protocol for
this communication, but it is
not without its own challenges.
For example, every time one service
reaches out to another, it can face
potential hurdles like latency issues,
security breaches, or unexpected failures.
So let's break down these challenges
and discuss about them in detail.
We talk about latency when
services communicate over HGTP.
Every call adds latency, so if one
service is slow, it can create a
domino effect slowing down the entire
system, even a minor delay in one
service can ripple through the system.
Needing to significant performance
bottlenecks by when we talk about
failures in microservices, when no
system is immune to failures, be it
hardware issues, unexpected spikes in
traffics, or simple misconfigurations
failures are inevitable when one
service fail to respond as expected.
It doesn't just affect that one component,
but has the potential to have a cascading
effect into broader system-wide issues.
When we talk about security,
with interservice communications
actually happening over
potentially unsecured networks.
Each SGTP call becomes a
point of vulnerability.
Ensuring robust authentication and
secure data transmission is paramount.
If a service security is compromised, it
could lead to unauthorized access data
breaches or even further exploitation.
Of other services in the network.
Last but not the least, it is also very
important to tackle observability as
without proper monitoring, diagnosing
issues becomes a guessing game,
delaying resolution at increasing
the downtime of your services.
So these challenges aren't just
technical, they are business critical.
A single outage can cost millions
and a security breach can
damage your entire reputation.
That's why it's not enough to
just write code that works.
We need to build systems that
are efficient, resilient,
secure, and observable.
And that's where Go For comes in
a framework that is designed to
tackle these challenges Head on
making in the service communication
not just manageable but effortless.
'cause with Go For You don't just get a
framework, but you get an entire toolkit.
Empowers you to focus on building
features and not start again with
writing the whole boilerplate.
Whether it is preventing cascading
failures with smart circuit breakers,
securing every call with robust
authentication, or ensuring that your
services stay healthy and monitored.
Gopher does it all under one roof.
And because it is modular, you
only use what you actually need.
And since Gopher is open source, it has
evolved with its community to stay at its
cutting edge with resilient system design.
So let's dive deeper into its
key features that make it an
efficient choice for Interservice
communications in microservices.
In this section we'll be discussing few
of the gophers features like circuit
breakers and retry configs in build
authentication observability, as well
as health monitoring, which form the
pillars of resilient microservices.
When we talk about retry confis.
BofA allows you to add the number of
kind the framework must attempt or retry
before actually returning your error in
case any downstream SGTP service fails.
However, cost to remote resources and
services can fail due to temporary issues
like slow network connections or timeouts.
Service, UN availability, et cetera,
while transient falls can be mitigated
using the RY pattern, there are cases
where continual ries are futile,
such as severe service failures.
In such scenarios, it is crucial for
applications to recognize where an
operation is unlikely to succeed and
hand in the failure appropriately
rather than persistently retrying.
When we are talking about circuit
breakers are a design pattern
inspired by electrical systems.
Just like a circuit breaker stops the
flow of electricity during a fault.
A software circuit breaker stops the
flow of requests to a failing service.
This prevents cascading failures and
gives the system time to recover.
Go makes implementing
circuit breakers effortless.
With just a few lines of configuration,
you can set up the threshold
and intervals for failing calls.
For example, if a service fails
more than a specified number of
times within a time window, gofer
automatically trips the circuit breaker.
Once the service recovers, gofer
resets the breaker, allowing
the request to flow again.
Next, let's talk about authentication.
In a microservices architecture, every
SGTP call is a potential security risk.
Without proper authentication,
unauthorized access can lead to data
breaches or even systemwide exploitation.
Securing inter-service communication
here is non-negotiable.
Gofer simplifies authentication with
built in support from multiple methods.
Whether it is API, keys, basic
auth, or O gofer integrates these
seamless into your services.
You can configure authentication
globally or per service, ensuring
that every call is secured by default.
Now we encourage best practice like token
based authentication at award for secure
and scale systems, and we also support
custom headers so we can pro, so you can
propagate authentication tokens or other
metadata across services effortlessly.
Next, let's talk about observability.
Observability is a de
facto in a framework.
It is one of the most unique
points that goer has to offer.
Observability comprises of logs,
traces, and metrics, which comes by
defaulting everything that GOER provides.
And similar is the case for
Interservice, SGTP communication.
All the outbound requests are actually
properly logged and the UN traces and
metrics are exported to the specified
port as well as the tracer URL.
We will dive deeper into this in the next
section where see a live demo of actually
setting up STTP services in gofer.
Moving on.
If we discuss about health monitoring
in distributed systems, we need to know
the health of the services all the time.
And without proper monitoring,
issues can go unnoticed until
they escalate into major outages.
Gofer provides robust health monitoring
out of the box where we can configure
the health endpoints for each services.
And Gofo performs regular
health checks on them.
It also collects the metrics
and logs giving us the realtime
insights into our systems health.
Many organizations usually pair
these health checks with alerting
and dashboards, turning raw
data into actionable insights.
For example, imagine a service that
starts responding slowly, go first's.
Health monitoring can help you
detect this early, log the issue,
and can even trigger alerts.
This proactive approach can help
you resolve issues before they
actually start impacting users.
So all these features that is circuit
breakers authentication, observability,
and health monitoring are just
the beginning of what GOER offers.
In the next section, we see them in
action with a live demo, and you'll get
to see how easy it is to build resilient,
secure, and observable systems with gofer.
Let's not waste any more time,
and let's get coding with gofer.
Gofer allows you to register SGTP
services at the application level
using ADD SGTP service method.
This means you can easily configure
interservice communication while
keeping things clean and modular.
So in our main function, we
can write app at sgtp service.
We then give the service name with
which we would like to register
as well as the service address.
Services registered this way are managed
automatically by the gophers container.
Once registered services can be accessed
anywhere using the method on gophers
context as c PX dot get sgtp service.
So let's define two routes in two
different projects in one of our projects.
Let's set the STTP port and metrics
port as 80, 81 and 2020 respectively.
And for the other.
Let's keep it at 80, 80 and two.
1 2 1. After setting up our
projects, let's define the
routes in both of the projects.
As for our applications workflow, for
simplicity purpose, we'll still be having
just a Hello Handler, but the name that
we send in the response, we'll actually
be fetched from the other service
that we call inside a Hello Handler.
So for the other service, let's
go and define the name handler.
And return a hardcoded name.
Let's say my name, the we over there.
So we write return the
We and Nel for the error.
Then we go back to our existing project
and now add this SGTP service as we will
be running the service at STTP Port 80 81.
So the service address will be
SGTP, local host 80 81, and we
then give the service name with
which we would like to register it.
Moving on, we define a Hello Handler
inside, which we then get the registered
SGTP service using GET SGTP Service
Method on the go first context.
Then we call the GET method on that
service, specifying the get endpoint
that we have registered on our other
service, and then give the argument
as name that is the endpoint that
must be hit on our registered service.
We then return the response
received if we encounter no error.
Now let's run both of our services.
And go to Postman and hit a URL that
is local host 80 80 slash hello.
We can see that we get hello the is
actually Freshed from the other server.
If we also look at the logs in our
terminal, we can see that go for
also logs Be call to any external
S TT P services that you called
inside your running applications.
Having the same correlation id.
As the parent span where it is called,
we can also go and check the traces and
see that the traces are in a hierarchy.
One of go first's strength is
its flexibility in configuring
interservice communication, making
it both powerful and simple to use.
Let's start with authentication
methods and then move on to the other
configurable options like circuit
breakers, retries, and health checks
in gopher, authentication in Gopher.
When services communicate,
they must be secure.
Goer provides multiple authentication
options to ensure only authorized
services can interact like API.
Key authentication, basic authentication,
and OAuth basic authentication.
Uses a username and password to verify
identity before processing the request.
API Key authentication is
a straightforward method.
Where request must include a predefined
secret, API Key and OAuth authentication
is ideal for external API access
requiring a client ID client, secret
token, URL, et cetera, to fetch
authentication tokens dynamically.
Each method serves a different
security need, allowing you
to choose what fits best.
Now, while making API requests,
we often include headers like.
User agent, content type, et cetera.
Some of these headers stay the
same for all requests, while others
change dynamically depending upon
the request context, the header, for
example, content type application.
JSON always remains the same.
Most of the times for the API request, so
to avoid adding them manually every time.
COFA lets you define default headers once,
and they're automatically added to all of
your requests sent to that SGTP service.
Also, when working with multiple services.
We must ensure they're available
before sending the request.
Gofer lets you configure custom
health checks that pings a services
health endpoint at regular intervals.
If the health check fails, gofer
marks the service as unavailable
and stop sending request.
The Health Check.
Timeout ensures that if a service
doesn't respond within a given
time, go for treats it as down.
This prevents long waits.
And help protect failures faster.
Now, these failures happen due
to network delays, temporary
outages, or high server load.
So instead of failing immediately,
we can also configure our SGTP
services to automatically retry the.
Request for a specified number of time.
For example, if a payment service
times out gofer allows you to set
up a retry config that helps you
to retry, for example, up to five
times before marking it as a failure.
This improves reliability by
handling temporary issues gracefully.
While these retries help with temporary
failures, they aren't always the
solution because cost to external
services can fail repeatedly due to
a. Service being completely down high
traffic, causing extreme delays and
misconfiguration or deployment issues.
Rying indefinitely in such cases, can
base resources and can overload the
failing service, making things even worse.
If multiple clients keep retrying,
this could even lead to an accidental
denial of service attack on your system.
So instead of blindly retrying,
gofo introduces a circuit breaker
pattern that can protect your system
by detecting the repetitive failures
and stopping request to that service.
Changing its state to open when
failures exceed the threshold, making
periodic requests to the health check
endpoint that is by default slash
wellknown slash alive at the interval
set in the config and automatically
resuming this request being sent to the
service once the service recovers by.
Using this gopher ensures your
system stays stable without
overwhelming failing services.
With this, we come to
the end of this video.
Let's take a moment to recap
what we have covered today.
We started by exploring the
challenges that you usually face
in interservice SG communication.
That is latency, failures, and security.
We then explored BofA, which is
a framework that is designed to
tackle these challenges head on and
deep dived into its features that
is circuit breaker for resilience.
Authentication for security
observability and health monitoring.
And finally, we saw these
features in action in a live demo.
So if you are as excited about
goer as I am, I encourage you
to try goer in your own project.
Whether you are building a new
microservice or enhancing an
existing one, goer can help you
focus on what matters the most.
That is delivering value to your users.
For more info checkout or documentation
at goer, you can also join our Discord
channel for any feedback or design
discussions regarding the same.
Thank you so much for joining me today.
I hope this session can give
you a clear understanding of how
GOER can simplify interservice
communication and microservices.
If you have any questions
or want to learn more.
Please feel free to visit our website
and reach out to our community.
Let's continue building resilient,
secure, and observable systems together.
Thanks for watching and enjoy the rest of.