Speaker 10: Hello, everyone, and welcome
to CON forty-two Golang twenty twenty-six.
My name is Rajnesh Kiran.
I'm a QA engineering manager with Citizens
Property Insurance Corporation in Florida.
Today, I will discuss AI-assisted test
execution and how AI agents can improve
scalability, resilience, and governance
within Go quality engineering ecosystems.
Let us begin with the core capabilities.
AI test agents extend beyond
traditional scripted automation.
They can interpret requirements written
in plain language and convert business
intent into executable validation steps.
They also navigate interfaces
adaptively, making them more
resilient when application
structures or attributes changes.
And importantly, they validate
expected behavior even when
underlying implementations evolve.
So what does current research actually
tell us about these approaches?
Research across enterprise web
systems shows promising results
for AI-assisted testing approaches.
Context-aware locator techniques have
demonstrated better resilience when
DOM structures and identifiers change.
Maintenance effort also shifts away
from fixing locator drift and towards
validating genuine behavioral changes.
At the same time, large-scale
enterprise validation remains limited,
especially in regulated industries like
insurance and banking, so adoption must
remain careful and evidence-driven.
This leads to an important principle:
augmentation rather than replacement.
The goal is not replacing go-testing
ecosystems, but existing Go framework
table-driven tests, benchmark
suites, integration harnesses
remain the core execution layer.
AI operates as an augmentation layer
above those systems, introducing
adaptability where it delivers
the highest value, especially in
system and acceptance testing.
However, introducing AI also introduces
new governance requirements, especially
in regulated environments like ours.
Traditional automation is deterministic.
You give an input, you get an output,
there is nothing unpredictable.
AI-assisted systems are
probabilistic, meaning outcomes
may carry varying confidence levels
That makes governance essential.
Organizations must define confidence
thresholds, escalation policies,
and human oversight mechanisms
before deploying AI-driven execution
into regulated environments.
One practical approach is
confidence-based escalation.
A matured AI-assisted testing model
should not produce only binary outcomes.
Instead, confidence level
drives the downstream actions.
High confidence outcomes
may proceed automatically.
Medium confidence cases
triggers engineer review.
Low confidence scenarios escalates
to humans or block releases entirely.
And if the classification
fails, deterministic fallback
execution remains available.
Beyond escalation,
explainability becomes critical.
In regulated industries, test execution
artifacts are compliance evidence as well.
Every AI action should remain explainable,
attributable, and reproducible.
That includes maintaining decision logs,
traceability chains from requirements
through execution, and replayable sessions
for investigation and audit review.
Closely related to this
is safe failure handling.
AI-assisted systems mu-must fail safely.
When confidence drops, the system
should transition through clearly
defined fallback paths rather
than entering undefined states.
That may include pausing for human
input, falling back to deterministic
Go scripts, or generating
escalation tickets automatically.
Now let us connect these concepts
specifically to Go ecosystems.
AI agents integrate naturally into Go
ecosystems because Go already emphasizes
structured testing and observability.
The Go test remains the
source of the truth.
AI layers contribute orchestration,
telemetry, confidence scoring, and
escalation workflows while integrating
cleanly into CI/CD pipelines such as
GitHub Actions, GitLab, or Jenkins.
Another promising area is
learning-based defect prediction.
Learning-based models can analyze
historical execution patterns to predict
where defects are more likely to emerge.
This enables risk-based prioritization,
allowing high-risk test to execute
earlier in the CI pipelines and
reducing time to first failures.
So how should organizations adopt
these capabilities responsibly?
A responsible adoption strategy
should remain phased and incremental.
Organizations can begin in observation
mode, then gradually introduce
augmentation capabilities before
scaling AI-assisted execution
across broader test portfolios.
Governance and evidence collection should
mature alongside technical adoption.
Let me close with a few
take-- key takeaways.
First, AI should augment existing testing
frameworks rather than replacing them.
Second, probablic sy-- prob-probabilistic
systems require explicit governance
through threshold, escalation
paths, and fallback strategies.
Third, explainability and auditability
are essential in regulated industries.
And finally, adoption should
remain incremental and
evidence-dri- evidence-driven.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for attending this session at
CON forty-two Golang twenty twenty-six.
I appreciate your time and interest
in AI-assisted quality engineering.
I would be happy to continue
any conversations further
through LinkedIn or email.
Thank you.