Hi, my name is Heman and I'm a
software developer@amazon.com.
I specialize in building machine learning
solutions for identifying and detecting
intellectual property infringement.
So today I'm here to give a talk
on machine learning approaches.
YP protections and cloud environments.
Let's go over the agenda
for the presentation.
We'll start off with discussing what
are the key challenges or problems
that when it comes to IP protection.
Then we'll go over some of the techniques
and methodologies to identify use of ip.
Then we'll go over some of the ML models
and techniques that you can use to
detect illegal or violation of IP use.
then we'll talk about how to
make these systems more scalable
by deploying them in cloud.
And finally, we'll go over how we
can use Colan to improve performance
of these similar pipelines.
Intellectual property theft
is a huge issue to companies.
it's estimated that globally companies
spend almost $600 billion every year.
Fighting IP theft and 60% of
these cases are all digital.
Predominantly this industry of,
intellectual property protections has
been very manual, but the advent of
machine learning systems, we've been
able to automate a lot of the processes.
and improve detection.
ML systems are just as good as humans
when it comes to identifying patterns
or repetitive patterns, and that's
one of the major reasons why we've
been able to automate a lot of these.
So what are some of the critical
challenges in IP protection and how
can ML help solve these challenges?
As I just mentioned, automation
was one of the key cha, key issues.
this industry was predominantly manual
and a human could take, only a hundred to
200 cases in an R, but with ML systems,
we can process and identify almost.
A hundred thousand occurrences of
IP infringements within an R. one of
the key problems for this industry
is pattern recognition, because
when it comes to IP protection, you
need to be able to identify use of,
logos, copyrights, and such product
protected assets in different places.
So machine learning is, this is a really
good use case for machine learning.
with the advent of convolutional neural
networks, pattern recognition become,
became very easy for, ML systems.
And with the recent advancement of the
transformer architecture, of identifying
nuances or identifying edge cases where
it comes to pattern recognition has just
become even more easier for machines.
The other problem is how to
make it more scalable, right?
this is where cloud comes in.
Cloud-based ML systems can handle almost.
Like huge volume.
it can easily handle
traffic spikes and whatnot.
And with the recent advancements
that we are seeing, that it comes to
training and inferences, inference of,
a lot of, GPU based chips being built,
which are very efficient, it can help.
Train ML models in shorter time,
it can handle very high throughput
inference, inference volumes.
so with that, we're seeing the costs
almost reduce 20 to 30% year over year,
when it comes to deploying ML pipelines.
So let's get into the
process of IP protection.
I would say IP protection
is a two step process.
Step one is discovery,
and step two is detection.
Discovery is basically searching
or finding the use of your ip.
Step two is detecting if this
use is indeed, fraudulent or not.
let's focus on the search part first.
There are two foundational
search methodologies.
One is keyword based search, and
the other is embedding based search.
Keyword based search is basically
searching for use of keywords.
It's predominantly a text-based
search mechanism where you try
to search if certain keywords.
Are present in a subset
of your search base.
so say you have a hundred million
products, or a hundred million web
pages, or a hundred million books,
and you're trying to search for the
trademark, Nike being used in, which
of these web pages, does mention Nike?
you could employ keyword based
search mechanisms to identify the
pages, which use the term Nike.
F the plus point of keyword based, systems
is that, they offer high throughput.
The compute that it uses is min,
minimal or lesser compared to embedding
based searches, and that's why you can
search across hundreds of millions of,
documents within a fraction of a second.
on the contrary, the drawback is
that it lacks context awareness.
It would, given that it is very
rudimentary and string based search
operation, it does not actually
understand the context or the meaning
behind the search query and the meaning
behind the use of the search term in
the documents that it's searching.
so that's where embedding
based search comes handy.
embedding based search is a lot more
context aware search where you employ
different machine learning models.
To convert your search query or your
document into embeddings and these
ML models to the job of extracting
context from your text, or image.
And store these context in the
form of vector representations
or numeric representations.
So because of such, mechanisms, it is
able to gather context out of your query
and do a much more targeted search.
but the drawback of embedding based
search is that, it uses a lot of compute,
so it's hard to, make it very scalable.
If you want to use embedding based
search mechanisms on a billion scale,
your queries tend to perform much more
slower than keyboard based search.
The gold standard generally is
to use a hybrid solution so that
you get the best of both worlds.
You get the high throughput, advantages
from keyboard based search, and
you get high precision, related
advantages from embedding based search.
what we generally do is first employee.
Keyword based search to
narrow down your search base.
And then when you have a base, you
use embedding based search to just
give you results that are highly
accurate to your search query.
if I were to give an example, say you
have 500 million web pages and from these
500 million web pages, you only want.
Web pages that use, which have images
of Nike Air Jordans, the shoes,
what you can first do is first use
keyword based search to find all the
web pages that have mentioned of the
term shoes or any of its synonyms.
And by doing this, you might come,
you might reduce your space from.
500 million to just 10 million web pages,
which have mention of the term shoes.
And then you do a embedding based
search, where you generate embeddings
for the images of Nike Air Jordans.
And you then, generate embeddings of,
these 10 million web pages and see which.
do a sort of a similarity search.
K and then similarity search to identify
which webpages from these 10 million
actually have the use of a shoe, which is
very similar, looking to Nike Air Jordans.
So with this, you might be just
left behind with two, 2000 or 3000,
webpages that have use of images
of a shoe that are very similar.
Looking to a Nike Air Journal.
Now that we've seen some of the search
techniques on how to, shrink your
search space or just find relevant
documents, from your search space,
let's look at some of the techniques
on how to detect IP infringement.
we'll look at two, two domains, broadly.
One is.
image-based IP detection, and
one is text-based IP detection.
let's look at image-based
IP detection first.
There are three main, use cases or
problem statements in this category.
one is the identifying
use of logos in images.
The other could be identifying use
of visual trademarks or copyrights.
And the third is.
detecting manipulation of a
copyright to a certain degree.
so logo detection is basically identifying
use of brands, logos in, images.
there are a few ML models that are
doing really good job in this space.
one of the, one of the state of the art
models is the YOLO family of models.
YOLO stands for you only look once.
These are predominantly object detection
models, but it's really easy to pick a,
one of the, pre-trained yellow model and
fine tune it for, for a data set that
only contains, annotated logos, in images.
And the output model that
you get after fine tuning is.
A model that easily detects, a logo in
an image when you pass an image to it.
And these are very lightweight models,
so you can blast it up at, 20, 30,000
transactions per second and you can
really get good, good throughput out
of these models for lesser costs.
these models generally have a high
accuracy upwards of 96, 90 7%, and
they allow for high throughput as well
when it comes to identifying use of,
a brand's or an artist's copyright.
the.
VIT, which stands for Vision Transformer
Models or the VLM Visual Language Models
has been really useful, in these domains.
These are.
Predominantly multimodal models where
they take an image, gather as much as
information as possible from this image.
they also convert this, the image
into textual format and then try to
understand what is there in this image.
so these models really help
identify, use of, copyrights such
as, Fictional characters being
present, present in content.
And they, these models are much
more larger than some of the logo
detection models such as yellow models.
but, and therefore they take much more
time for, inference than the logo models.
But these, these have really
high precision and low FB rates.
The third problem, image manipulation is
a much more simpler problem than the other
two because this is, the, the solution
that you could employ is very simple.
You just use, some
image-based embedding models.
To generate embeddings of your artwork or
your asset, and then, generate embeddings
of other images that are there on the
internet and see how similar are these
two vectors, if the cosign similarity
between, these, these two vectors.
your vector and the vector of, image that
you fetch from the internet are very high.
Then it means that it's a very similar
looking image or very similar looking
artwork with just a few nuances.
You don't even need a multimodal
model for such use cases.
just a pure image based
embedding model, does the job.
next comes text-based IP protection.
so let's talk about text
similarity detection first.
just like.
Image-based embedding models.
There are a lot of text-based embedding
models, which, have, been j been trained
on the entirety of the dictionary.
And, the probability of occurrence
of every word in the dictionary
to rank, different words in the
dictionary and generate embeddings
for any given, text phrase.
these models can be pretty useful
in, generating embeddings of.
a text phrase and seeing,
if you if, another phrase.
out there in the search space is
very similar to your trademark text.
some of the use cases where this
comes in very handy, we see in
the industry is for plagiarism.
Check, for checking if research papers
are very similar to, very similar
of a research paper in the past,
or, Or text-based original content.
For example, books, books of authors,
if they're being infringed on, text
of another book that has been, you
know, launched or released in the past.
the other use case is
brand misrepresentation.
So what in the, in the retail
industry, what we see is that.
Once a brand becomes famous, there
are a lot of knock knockoffs that
come, come into the market, which,
sound very similar to this brand.
some of the famous examples are Adidas
and, ABAs, where the second D is
converted to a B. just to, just to,
Have a difference in the name, but
have the design language and everything
that's very similar to, Aidas and,
some of these NLP techniques where
you can, normalize, text using a lot
of different tokenizes and a lot of
different packages that are given out.
A lot of Python packages that are
available to normalize your text
and then perform a similarity search
is helpful for such use cases.
And then comes, the l LMS that
we've seen in the recent, past
where these are multilingual.
it can perform similarity
search across languages.
so it has a machine translation layer,
which normalizes, text before generating,
embedding into a single language.
u using, using the same ip, or the same
trademarks, but in a different language,
can also be now identified using, such
models, deploying ML pipelines in cloud.
Helps reduce costs by a large percentage
because, cloud is generally a multi-tenant
environment where multiple organizations
or multiple clients deploy their
workloads and you only pay as you need.
You only pay for the services or for
the duration that you actually use.
an instance or a cloud resource,
given that these are huge data
centers, they high, they offer
really high availability, with.
a lot of replication factor in place
such that, your instances are deployed
and replicated in different, zones in
multiple, data centers across the world
to offer high system availability.
the use of GPUs is a lot more
efficient when it comes to cloud.
Also, having our own GPUs, on an
on-premise system is a very expensive, is
an, is a very expensive affair, especially
if you are underutilizing the GPU.
If your workloads aren't, continuous,
continuously high or maxing out the
GPU, then you're paying a lot of money
for the GPUs when utilizing very less,
with cloud, this becomes cheaper because
there are multiple tenants and everyone
reuses the same GPU when required.
Let's look at some of the techniques
that, one can use to optimize or improve
performance of ML systems or ML models.
there are four main things, main
approaches that we look at, model
parallelism, data parallelism,
model, shing, and quantization.
So model parallelism is something
that you can use when your models
are very large, where, model might
not fit on a single GPU instance.
So what you do is you split the model,
where certain layers you, split the
model horizontally across layers.
And deploy the chunk of the model on
different, GPO instances and invoke
each model, each instance one of the
other, where the output of the first
instance goes as the input of the other
instance, and then you can reuse the
first instance once the it has finished
processing for the next request.
So this is where you can split
your model across multiple GPUs.
and this is generally useful when your
models are very large and you want
to use smaller GPO instance sizes.
And of course, when the model is built
in such a way that it allows for,
splitting up the layers of the model.
then comes data parallelism.
So this is useful when you
are underutilizing A GPU.
it is pos you can deploy multiple
instances of a very small model
on the same GPU and or across
different GPUs as well, and.
and batch your data and invoke
it across all the different
instances, for inferences.
this helps, boost the throughput as
well because now you are utilizing your
memory and compute more efficiently.
Third comes model shouting.
So model shouting is.
A little similar to model parallelism,
but works a bit differently.
In Model Sharding, you vertically split
the model into a number of pieces when
it's hard to deploy, the model on a
single instance because it's too large.
So you shard the model, in such a way
that your input data also can be shorted.
when you want to invoke the model for
inference, so the model which is now
charted into four or five different pieces
are, deployed on different instances.
And when you invoke the model, your
input tensor also can be broken down into
corresponding pieces and sent to the,
Respective shot and the output can then
be concatenated to generate the response.
the last one is quantization, so this
helps lower the size of the model by
compressing the weights of the model.
So say you, compress or convert
the weights of the model from
a floating point, a 32 bit
to a 16 bit floating point.
You reduce, the size of the model
and also the memory required
for inference of the model.
So let's talk about how Golan
can be helpful in, ML pipelines.
So before we get into that,
some overview about Go.
it's an open source programming
language developed by Google,
and, the best part about it is.
It's, speed, because it compiles
to, machine code, its performance,
similar on the likes of, CCC plus.
it's really fast, compared to
programming languages like Java,
which have a lot of overhead because
of JVM or Java Virtual machines.
it's.
very cloud native and designed
because it seamlessly integrates
with, Docker, Kubernetes.
it's really useful to build
containerized, APIs, or services,
basically microservices.
And, it offers high concurrency with,
built in go routines and channels,
which enable multitasking and
help build high through pipelines.
so specifically when it comes to ML
pipelines, the biggest use case or biggest
place where go could be useful is building
streaming, high throughput streaming
pipeline, where, you have, incoming, data
in a streaming fashion, where millions of.
records are coming in
every minute or every hour.
you use, a sort of a Kafka plus co
consumer set up to react to these
incoming reactions or incoming signals
and, invoke machine learning models.
so you could use, A GRP, GRPC client,
to invoke remote procedure calls, and
go to a PyTorch or a TensorFlow backend.
it really helps, convert a lot
of asynchronous applications into
synchronous or real time processing
applications, because of its throughput
and low latency capabilities.
And it's really easy to deploy these
services on cloud because of it's,
it's, integration with Docker and
how we can containerize these web
services and deploy, in containerize
web, services platforms such as.
ECS provided by AWS and so on.
Looking ahead, there's a lot more to be
achieved in this space of IP protection.
there's a lot more automation that is
required and for which there is scope for.
where, AI is, or machine learning is able
to identify most of the patterns, but
the novel approaches taken by bad actors
are still being identified by humans.
there's research being done on how
to use blockchain and blockchain
based ledgers for verification and,
determining ownership of IP assets.
And there's.
With the time we are seeing adaptive
AI systems, where we use a lot of
these lms, to make themself learn and
help them identify the new patterns,
that bad actors can develop over time
without a human having to tell them
what to do or pass training information.
Thank you so much for your time.
Hope this was a informative session.