Hi, I'm Manuel de Rap Pena.
I am a staff software engineer at Docker.
I'm the test container, go
maintainer, which is the library
I'm going to present today.
Argo applications usually consume external
resources such as SQL or no SQL databases.
Message queues for sending US SQL
messages, L up, or mail servers,
cloud services such as S3 or a w.
S Landas and more recently, vector
databases for AI applications.
How do you make sure the
application code interacting
with those services is correct?
When you are writing it, you have the
right tools to test your application
while developing it so that you have
confidence in creating the core behaviors.
One of the most adopted techniques is
using a continuous integration server
such as Jenkins, GitLab runners, or
GI actions in which you or a platform
team configures the servers to run all
your dependencies in the CI pipelines.
At some point, you must make sure that
those dependencies, databases, queues,
code, tors, et cetera, are in exactly
the same version as in production with
the same configuration if possible.
Also, the CA workers must be big
enough to start and run those
dependencies at the same time your
test codes executed in the test.
My question is this kind of setup
convenient for making progress?
Every time you need to update
the dependencies, you need
to update the CI confi.
And many times as a developer,
you don't own the CI service.
On the same hand, when your application
grows and you depend on more services,
you have to start them on the
ci, increasing the probability of
overloading the CI server with concurrent
execution of different CI pipelines.
Finally, how can you reproduce a
failing test in your local machine?
In that scenario, do you need to
start the full blown application
to run just one failing test.
Enter test containers for Go test
containers is a set of open source
libraries that are present in the
most popular programming languages.
I am the official maintainer for
the GO implementation and I'm
going to show you how to use the
library to resolve the issues.
I described it before.
First test containers for Go gives
you programmatic access to the
Docker engine, so you are not able
to create, start, stop, and terminate
containers that in your code.
Instead of configuring the ci, you'll
be adding the containers to the place
they're using in your test code.
Imagine you're working in the persistent
layer instead of spinning up the
entire application to run this layers
test, you just add an instance of your
database where you really need it, so
your test will interact with just a
container representing database test
give you a random port for the well
known port for a given technology.
For Postgres, it is the 5, 4, 3 2 port.
For MySQL, the 3 3 3 0 6 port.
This allows you to run multiple containers
in parallel with three major benefits.
Consistency, test that isolation
and bill speed consistency.
Thanks to docker containers, the
dependency will be isolated in a
container, so you don't need to mess
up your system installing different
technologies with multiple configurations
and apply only to your host instead
of creating an onboarding document
with lot of instruction to set up
the development or test environment.
Do as install docker and run the test.
We call it the clone and Run
experience about that installation.
Each container will have its own
set of data, so depending on how
you start them, by test function, by
test suite, or by test package, you
have more or less containers running
in your system at a given time.
But with no test data pollution,
and for biller speed, thanks to the
containers, spin up technologies as
docker images is a piece of cake.
Of course, depending on the size of
the image, you must pull it first and
it could be js, but talk is cheap.
Let's show the code.
We are gonna present here
a simpler microservice app
for rating conference talks.
It probes an API to track the
ratings of the tax in real time.
Stir the resource in a postgre database.
Also using, already discuss a red pan
as a broker for evidence streaming.
Finally it will use an AWS Lambda
function to calculate some aesthetics
about the ratings of the talk,
we have an ster layer here with
PostgreSQL in the to report GO file.
So if we go to the tax report,
go file, we'll see the repository
pattern holding the PEX connection.
We build a new repository
from the connection stream.
And with that we perform
the crude operations.
Create insert into sql exist.
With this sql, et cetera, for the already
discuss, we follow the same pattern.
We have a repository here, and this
repository has a new repository
receiving a connection stream.
We create the client, we ping
the client and we add find all.
We convert to a key here
about the streaming.
We have here a broker and this
broker with a friend client using
the Kafka, France Go package.
We create a new stream from the connection
stream to the queue, and finally we do
a ping here to verify the queue with
app and we're able to send rating to.
To interact with the AWS Lambda, we
have this Lambda client, which is
basically doing HTP requests to our URL.
So we create the new Lambda client,
basically HTP client with the
Lambda URL as URL of the client.
We're gonna perform a post request
to the URL of the Lambda with this is
the Specter response, and this is the
payload that the Lambda will receive.
Finally, we return the response
so the application can consume
the result from the AWS Lambda.
How do we verify that those
interactions work properly?
The simplest way is to create interaction
test with test container score.
We're gonna see them in
action for the database.
We have a new repository test here,
and we'll consume the progress
module of test container score.
We are gonna create a container with all
the options that we want to customize.
The Postgres instance, the SQL database
that will populate the database, the
name of the database, the credentials,
and we are gonna wait for the
Postgres container until this log
entry appear two times in the lock.
We are gonna make sure the container
is disposed at the end of the test,
we're gonna get the connection stream
to the Postgres instance, which is part
of the API with the Postgres module.
And finally we're gonna create our new
repository, which is the persistent
layer that talks to the database.
If you recall this repository,
received the connection stream
and perform the connections.
Once we have the to repository
here, we are able to perform any
crude operation like creating,
retrieving a talk or checking.
It doesn't exist.
We're gonna execute this.
We run the file test.
See the logs here, we're
gonna see the test containers.
We'll run the test and
create the containers for us
a using in the post 15 Alpine image.
And in just 10 seconds, everything
passes exactly the same.
For the red cast, we consume
the module for Redis.
And create a container
with the run function.
We don't need to customize it here.
We just consume the plain module again,
we clean up the container, we get
the connection stream, we create the
repository from the connection stream.
If you recall, it receives
the connection stream.
And once we have the repository
ready, and once we have the repository
ready, we are able to perform
operations like adding on getting
the results if we run the test here.
Redis, we're gonna see test containers
running the Redis container and
executing the test in just seven seconds.
We are confident that the word
production can work as expected
because it talks to Redis instance.
And finally, for that queue, we
have this test In our application.
We are using Red Panda.
For that reason, we are
gonna use the module for Rand
and Discon continuous goal.
We call the run function from the
red pan module with this image, and
we configured the red pan container
to auto to create the topics.
We calculate the sheet broke
everywhere, L for the red pan container,
and we create our near stream.
If you recall, this stream received the
connection stream and created the Kaf
client, and we are able to execute our
tests against that red panda instance.
We're gonna run them.
Probably takes longer because he's
gonna pull the image and finally in
14 seconds it's able to run the test
against a real red panda instance.
If we run the test again, we're
gonna see that it takes shorter
time because the red panda image is
already pulled just five seconds.
Amazing.
Let's see the code for the AWS Lambda.
It is basically using the AWS Lambda
Go package to create the Lambda and
it will receive this payload and
we'll respond with this response.
here is scanning the request.
Calculate the maths here.
Very simple.
And finally, we have a main function,
which is the start from the Lambda.
Let's see how to test it.
Here we are running make to see
the Lambda, which is basically.
Packaging the Lambda into the
artifact that AWS needs to create.
The Lambda is very basic.
We see here that we're building
the Lambda and creating a thi file
for that name function of thi.
And for the test, we are
gonna use local stack.
Local Stack is emulating all
the AWS services specifically.
Lambda and we're gonna copy the
C file created by the Meg file
into the local stack container.
And we are gonna execute our custom
code in the container after itta.
In this case, we need to create
the Lambda and get its URL.
So for that reason, we are
gonna get the file here.
Create this Lambda
command, which is Lambda.
Create function config.
Wait for the Lambda to be ready, executing
these commands inside the container,
which is provided by test container to
execute commands in the running container.
Finally, we're gonna get the
function, rural configs, and for
that we are gonna pass the response.
And we need the function
URL here for the Lambda.
This URL is the one needed to
perform HDP requests against
the Lambda provided by localist.
So if we continue, we
have another container.
We have the MapIT port.
We're gonna replace this
in the URL of the Lambda.
This is needed because test container
give you a random port for the
running container, for the well
known port for the running container.
So we need to calculate that
and replace it in the URL.
We are gonna pass this
payload in our test.
We calculate the histogram here.
We perform a post request, and
finally we, this is the expected
response from the lambda.
Pretty amazing, right?
We're gonna execute AWS
Lambdas in our local machine.
So we're gonna run the test here
and are gonna see the local stack
container running where the code is
calculating the UL of the Lambda.
And finally we'll execute the
HTP request against that Euro
on the test pass.
We are gonna make it fail,
for example, here, instead of
calculating the average properly,
we are gonna introduce a back here.
And if we run the test, we are able to
detect that back in just a few seconds.
We are able to run locally AWS Landas.
And verify that our code
is working as suspect.
Cool.
We detected it.
Total count is correct, but
the average is incorrect.
We're gonna find more information
about test containers for go.
If you visit the test container.com
website, you can find all the modules that
we support for test continuous Go here.
You can find for.
Databases, retinal databases,
no SQL databases, vector
databases, major brokers, web
ventilators, cloud, et cetera.
Lot of them, all the modules are based
on the container request striped.
With either strip, you're
able to configure your
container are the way you want.
For example, defend the image,
defining the exposure sport.
Defining the network.
This container belongs to
defining the conditions to wait
for this container to be ready.
And more.
For example, one advanced
capability are the like cycle hooks.
You can execute your own code directly
into the container lifecycle, for
example, before the container creates bef.
After the container creates, before the
container starts and after it starts.
Before the container and after the
container stops, before the container
is ready, checking the health checks
and also before and after the container
terminates, you can inject your own
code and execute it in your test code.
You can also create data into the
container, for example, mounting volumes
or copy files into the container.
It's interesting that the files
attributes allow you to copy container
before the container is started.
They are copied after
the container is created.
So when the container starts the data, the
state of the container is already there.
This is really useful for containers
with, depends on an state.
For example, databases you can pass here,
a file to a SQL file to load the database.
So the tests start with
a well known state.
One interesting capability
of test containers is real.
You have probably seen the name
real in the list of containers
that are running in your system.
This real container ISR responsible
for removing containers,
networks, volumes, and images
created by test container for go.
So you don't need to clean up the
containers you create in your test.
Regarding the weather strategies, which
I mentioned before, there are situations
where you have to wait for a, the
container to be in a well-known state.
Instead of adding timeless slips to
your CI pipeline or your or to your tax
execution, you rely on waiter strategies.
You wait for a command to
be executed, a container.
For example like this here,
let's wait for this command to
be executed in the container.
Or for example, we can wait
for a container to exit.
At the same time.
We can wait for a file to be present in a
container and the test will continue after
this file is present in the container.
Also, you can wait for a
health check waiting for the
health check of the container.
You can wait for a port to be
already listening in your container.
For an HDP request, and you can configure
the port you want to wait for, or even
the path, the credential with pathic
out or even expecting as response
code to be present in the response.
You can also configure the
response headers and wait for them
to be present in the response.
Another wave condition that is very
handy is waiting for a lock to be
present in the log of the container.
You can configure it to inspect
a string or a regular expression.
Using Azure records.
You can also combine multiple of
them with wait for all and all of
them will be applied at the same
time and you can wait for a SQL
query to be executed on a database.
It's also possible to use this container.
Go for building docker
images from a Docker file.
If you define this stroke inside the
container, request struck, you will
be able to build this Echo file in
this path and with this repository.
Name and name.
You can also pass arguments to the
build and at the end the container
will be running after the build.
This is what I have here.
I'm sharing with you the CURE
calls to ago where we demonstrated
power of this containers for goal
and also the website with all the
information about the project.
I hope you enjoyed my talk.
Thank you very much.