Speaker 7: Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining my session.
My name is Himabindu Yanalla, and
I am a senior full-stack Java and a
mobile hybrid application developer.
I bring ten-plus years of experience in
designing, developing, and supporting
enterprise-scale applications
across web, mobile, cloud, APIs,
microservices, and distributed systems.
Today, I will be speaking about designing
resilient self-service search in Go.
How self-service systems fail and why
silent degradation matters, and how
intelligent fallback architectures
can keep users moving even when
the primary system is under stress.
We will see the role
of self-service search.
So the self-service search is often
the first line of customer support.
When users search for help, products,
documents or answers, they are usually
trying to solve a problem by themselves.
If search works well, it
reduces sup-support effort
and also improves confidence.
But when search fails, users do not think
of it as a technical research issue.
They simply feel that the
platform did not help them.
So that is why search reliability has
direct impact business-- on business.
So every degraded query can
become a support ticket, a lost
sale, or a frustrated user.
So the more dangerous failure
is not always an error page.
Sometimes the system returns two
hundred status code, but the results
are empty, incomplete, or not useful.
For the infrastructure side, the request
may look successful, but from the
user side, the experience has failed.
So the key here is empty does
not always means correct.
So we will see what can go wrong.
What can go wrong?
In distributed search, many
failures can happen quietly.
A traffic spike can overwhelm
shards, and some shards may return
incomplete or degraded results.
One slow node can delay the
entire response, and sometimes
the system returns empty results
without raising a clear error.
These failures are very dangerous because
they may not appear as obvious outages
In sometimes building infrastructure
dashboards may show that the system is
technically alive while users are still
experiencing the poor search quality.
That is why we need to monitor not
only errors and latency, but also users
facing signals like zero result queries,
query reformulations, and abandonment.
I would say the real goal is not
only to prevent system failure, but
the goal is to prevent a bad user
experience before user escalates.
Now we will see the problems
with reactive fallback.
So in many systems, fallback is
often only after an incident.
A production issue happens
and a team adds a patch.
Another issue happens and
another rule is added.
So over the time, fallback becomes a
collection of reactive fixes instead
of designing a reliability layer.
But high traffic distributor systems
that we have expose new failure modes.
They expose faster than the
reactive patches and keep up.
But fallback should be treated as
a first-class architecture pattern.
It should be designed from the beginning,
including capacity, routing, freshness,
monitoring, and user experience.
And we can leverage AI and data-driven
analysis can also help us by identifying
a repeated zero results, traffic
anomalies, and failure patterns.
The main point that I wanted to
emphasize here is fallback should
be engineered, not improvised.
Now we will see the fan-out amplification
and a hidden threat in this slide.
Fan-out is one of the hidden
risks in distributed system.
A single query may be sent
to multiple shards at a time.
So this improves speed through
parallelism, but it also
increases the failure surface.
If most shards respond quickly,
but one shard is slow, so the whole
query can be delayed in this case.
That is why the tail latency
is very important here.
Users do not experience average latency.
They experience the specific
request they are waiting for.
So that's gonna that will make fan-out
efficiency through Go routines.
But concurrency must be controlled.
So without having these limits, the same
concurrency that improves throughput
can also increase blast radius.
So for this one, we can have
resilient Go systems that need
context deadlines, timeout budgets,
cancellations, worker limits, and
clear rules for partial results.
Now we will see one of the important
slide, which is the architecture overview.
So in the architecture is basically
is built around layered resilience.
The distributed re-retrieval layer
sends queries to primary shards.
Circuit breaker is there to monitor
system health and decide-- it
will decide when traffic should
move away from the primary path.
The fallback index provides like a
lightweight, it is always available for
results, and we have bulkheads to protect
fallback capacity anyways from being
consumed by primary system failures.
So each layer is basically defining
a clear responsibility, and the
retrieval hands handles the fan-outs.
So the circuit breaker controls routing,
the fallback index supports gracefully
degradation, bulkheads isolate resources.
So this is the defense in depth.
We do not depend on one
component to save the system.
Instead, multiple layers work together
to protect the user experience.
Now we will see the fallback index.
So a fallback index should
always-- should not just be a
small copy of the main index.
It should be designed specifically
for failure scenarios.
That means it should be lightweight,
fast, predictable, and isolated
from the primary system.
It does not need every ranking
feature or every document.
It needs enough high-confidence
data to keep the user when the
primary system is degraded.
This can include pop-popular
queries, common help articles,
recent successful results, curated
mappings, or simplified data.
We can leverage AI and query log analysis
that can help decide what belongs in
fallback by identifying frequently used
content and also the most common failures.
The goal here is not perfection.
The goal here is to keep
the user moving forward.
In the next slide, we will s-- we will see
about the circuit breaker-driven routing.
So the circuit breaker helps the
system fail in a controlled way.
In the closed state, where the traffic
flows normally to the primary index,
the system basically monitors latencies,
errors, timeouts, and irregular quantity.
If failures cross a
threshold, the circuit opens.
At that point, traffic
moves to a fallback index.
So instead of continuing to overload
the unhealthy primary system, later--
the later happens, the circuit moves
to half-open state, where limited
probe requests check whether the
primary system has recovered or not.
If the probes succeed, traffic
gradually returns, and if they
fail, the circuit opens again.
So the key idea h-here is that
the fallback routing should be
automatic, fast, and measurable.
We should not wait for the
manual intervention while users
are already seeing failure.
In the next s-slide, we will see about
bulkhead-based res-resource isolation.
So the bulkhead pattern that that
comes basically from ship design.
So if one compartment floods,
the other ship should not sink.
So the whole other ship should not sink.
That is the main idea
behind the bulkhead pattern.
So in software, the bulkhead
isolate failures domain so that
the overload is in one area.
If it is in one area, it does not
consume to all shared resources.
In Go, this can be implemented through
separate goroutine pools, connection
pools, and we can use semaphore
limits and context cancellations.
This is very important for fallback
because if the primary search path
consumes all CPU, memory, connections, or
goroutines, then the fallback cannot help.
In-- if it exists in
design but not in reality.
But they-- but we have bulkheads
to ensure that the fallback has
protected capacity, so even when
the primary path is under stress.
So the main point that I would like to
emphasize about this one is fallback
must be isolated from the failure.
It is desi-- it is designed to survive.
So now we will see about
avoiding zero-result queries.
So avoiding zero-result queries
are one of the worst search
outcomes that I would say.
They may return two hundred
status code, but for the user,
they feel like complete dead-end.
To reduce this, we need layered defense.
First of all, the primary index should
perform full search with normal ranking.
If that does not produce useful
results, then query relaxation can
help by loosening strict filters,
correcting spellings, expanding
terms, or applying synonyms.
If a primary path is failing or still
produces poor results, the fallback index
should provide meaningful alternatives.
AI can help through semantic matching,
intent dis-detection, spelling correction,
and intelligent query expansion.
The goal is not to pretend
nothing has failed.
The goal is to avoid giving the
user a blank result when when
useful alternatives still exist.
So we wanted to avoid this thing.
The next slide we will see about
query log-driven synonym optimization.
So search quality improves
when we learn about query logs.
Static synonyms are always there or
like dictionaries will become outdated
because user language keeps changing.
Users may search with abbreviations,
misspellings, brand names, or
even poor description that do not
exactly match indexed content.
So the query logs reveal these gaps.
So if a query often results a
zero results, it may need synonym
expansion, content improvement, ranking
adjustment, or fallback support.
So the reformulation is
always is also valuable here.
In terms of when user searches once,
gets no results, and then changes
the query, the second query starts.
Then the second query, which
shows the system failed to
understand the first time.
So we can leverage AI by clustering
similar queries, detecting
intent pla-- patterns, and
suggesting synonym candidates.
But tuning must be very... We have to
do the tuning very carefully because
broad synonyms can reduce precision.
Next, we will see about connecting
infrastructure signals to user impact.
So infrastructure metrics and user
metrics tell different parts of a story.
So the infrastructure metrics are nothing
but the P ninety-nine latency, timeout
rates, shard failures, circuit breaker
tilts, CPU memory, and a connection usage.
But the user metrics include zero
result frequency, query reformulation
rate, abandonment, support
escalation, and click behavior.
Both are needed.
A system can have good average latency
and still fails user at a tail.
It can also return no technical
errors, but still provide poor results
We can have AI-assisted monitoring
that can help us in connecting these
signals by identifying patterns across
telemetry and even user behavior.
So for search, the uptime
alone is not enough here.
The system should not re-- only respond,
it should respond with something useful.
That is important here.
In the next slide, we will see about
early detection be-before user feels it.
Support escalations
are lagging indicators.
So by the time the user opens the
ticket, abandon sessions, and give
negative feedback, the damage has
already happened, so we cannot do
anything about the damage at this point.
So a better approach is to
detect leading indicators early.
These includes raising tail latencies
more circuit breaker trips, shard
timeouts, higher zero result rates, and
unusual query reformulation patterns.
So these signals show degradation before
it becomes visible as business impact.
So when leading the indicators across
these thresholds indicators that acro--
that cross these thresholds and also
the system that can trigger fallback
routing, relax queries, protect
resources, and alert engineering teams.
The u- the ideal outcome
is very simple here.
Users should not notice the
incident before the system
already responded safely.
Now we will talk about one of
the important things which are
like the key design principles.
Let's summarize the main design
principles that we spoke about.
The first one is fallback
must be first class.
It should be designed from day one,
not added after the first major
incident or something like that.
And the second would be
design against fan-out.
So Go makes concurrency easy, but
e-every fan-out boundaries that
we have needs timeout budgets,
cancellations, and concurrency limits.
So the third I would say
is use a defense in depth.
Circuit breakers control logic, and
bulkheads protect fallback capacity.
And fourth, I would think
of is measure user outcomes.
Uptime is very important here when
it comes to measuring user outcomes.
So but search quality also depends on
zero, zero result frequency, reformulation
rate, and support escalation.
And fifth, I would think about
is treat query logs as continuous
feedback, and don't take it lightly.
So they reveal the vocabulary
gaps, synonym opportunities,
and silent failures.
And finally, use UI practically.
AI should improve ca- Query understanding,
anomaly detection, sy- synonym
discovery, and fallback decisions.
Not just being added just as a buzzword.
Thank you so much for
giving me this opportunity.
And to close on resilient self-search,
this is all about giving users a
useful path forward even when parts
of the systems are under stress.
So failures are, like, normal in
distributed system world, but what
matters is whether we design the system
to fail safely, recover quickly, and
protect the u- user experience or not.
Thank you so much for your time.
I truly appreciate the opportunity
to share this topic with you.
Thank you.