Speaker 15: Hello.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Sridhar Rao Mutheneni,
and I am a product lead at Capgemini.
Today, I want to talk about something
that touches almost every one of
us, our money, our banking apps, and
how they stay both safe and smart.
Especially how we use artificial
intelligence to catch fraud the moment
it happens, while also making our
financial apps feel more personal.
How a programming language called
Go quietly making all of this
possible behind the scenes.
Let us dive in.
So Fintech is growing super fast.
At the same time, the threats
are also going super fast.
So there are four big problems what we can
see on every-- almost like a day-to-day
basis for the millions of customers.
One of the challenge is the
account takeovers, where someone
steals your password and logs
in as you, and it happens to the
millions of users on a daily basis.
The second problem what we can think
of, like a synthetic identities.
Imagine a fake person building from
real pieces, a real Social Security
number, but a fake name, fake address.
And these ghost identities open accounts,
take loans, and disappear after some time.
And the third one is money laundering,
where criminals move dirty money
through dozens of tiny transactions
into hidden account to look--
make it more clean transactions.
So that is one of the
money laundering challenge.
And the last one is the biggest
one, like customers expects
Netflix or Amazon-like experience
for the-- from their banking app.
So this is they want it more
secure, as well as they want it
to be more personal and instant So
we have to do two things at once.
That is catch criminals and
delight our customers with
their personalized experience.
Historically, now we have two goals.
One is the security and the
second one is the personalization.
And these both are handled by completely
different teams and separate tools.
That is a very slow in general.
So what I'm going to show you
today is a single framework that
does the three things together:
detect, personalize, and govern.
So the aspect of detect is to spot
a fraud as a transaction happens
in a real time, so that we can
immediately stop the transaction.
And personalize is recommending the
right product, give the right ad
financial advice at the right moment.
Governing make sure is fair
and explainable, and it
respects the user's privacy.
Think of it like one engine
doing all three jobs at once.
Now let us look at the different ML
architectures used for a fraud detection.
So in context of a fraud detection,
the next few slides will look at
the-- what are the different AI
models we use to catch the fraud
and trade-offs between all of them.
So there is no single best model
which... The right choice really depends
on the how accurate you w-want it to be.
And the second aspect is how fast it
has to respond, and whether a human
can understand why the AI made its
decision and how much it costs to run.
Let us look at these ML models, and
we'll l- also look at the different
trade-offs between the different models.
So there are m- mainly four families
of AI models we use in nowadays
for a financial transactions.
That is the Gradient-boosted
decision trees.
Don't worry about the name.
This name looks more complicated,
but think of them as a, like a very
fast pattern matchers for structured
data, like rows in a spreadsheet.
They are great at a quick yes/no
fraud decisions so that we can
avoid the-- we can spot the fraud
then and there and save the users'
transaction from the fraudsters.
The second type of ML model is a RNN.
So this is very good at
looking at sequences.
If user is spending a pattern over
the last 10 transactions is not
looking good, then RNN will notice
and trigger a fraud event, which will
help the financial institution to
stop the transaction then and there.
The third type of ML model
is the graph neural networks.
So think of these as like a detectives.
They look at the relationships
between the accounts.
If five seemingly unrelated accounts
all send money to some hidden account,
then the graph model can uncover it as
a fraud and detec-detects the fraud and
alarm the the financial institutions.
The last type of the model
is the transformers model.
Maybe many users will be familiar
with this model because-- So this
is the same technology behind our--
one of the commonly used ChatGPT.
So they are powerful at
understanding long-term context,
like a person's behavior over
months, and detect the fraud.
So if you look at all these models are
like a-- used to identify different
patterns and identify different type of
criminals using these different tools.
Now let us look at
why Go.
Why Go as the programming language?
Why not the other languages,
some other languages
So why do major like financial
institutions and banks use a reliably
u-use Go for a part of their system that
runs on the AI predictions in a real time?
So three primary reasons behind this.
The number one is the speed, concurrency,
and memory efficiency with the Go.
S-so when you tap a card at a coffee
shop, the bank has a millisecond
to decide if it is a really fraud
or a l-legitimate transaction.
Go is a a compiled language.
It runs super fast and like a
sports car in a curve in the line.
The Go by default supports concurrency.
Go can handle thousands of transaction
at the same time without breaking
a sweat, thanks to its built-in
feature called Go routines.
So think of them as a tiny
lightweight workers that can run in
parallel to achieve the concurrency.
The third reason, third...
One of the best reason is the
memory efficiency with the Go.
Other programming languages
sometimes pause to clean up a
memory at the worst moments.
Go keeps those pauses tiny as predictable,
which matters when every millisecond
counts in the financial industry.
Now let us look at the architecture
deep dive when we were streaming
the inference pipeline in the Go.
So when a customer taps a
card at a coffee shop, the,
the actual flow of a transaction hits
our system with a, on a high level, like
a three-step approach, so which is a
ingestion, pre-processing, and infer.
So ingestion process, when the
transaction comes in, it often throw
it to like Kafka, which is basically
a high-speed conveyor belt for data.
It goes through the Kafka and
Make it ready for the pre-process.
During the pre-process step, we
clean up the data, format it,
and add a context like a user is
swiping this card from a New York.
This is his maybe third or fourth
transaction in the day context.
It adds to the pre-processing step.
The infer process-- The infer step of
this process will run the AI model and
gets the score the-- which is used to
identify whether this is a fraud or not.
All of this happens under a second,
and Go has excellent libraries
to every step of this process.
So engineers can build these
pipelines quickly and reliably.
So to identify whether our model
is good at identifying that is
fraud, we'll use the following
three metrics, like a detecting--
detection of accuracy, false
positive rate, and latency.
Detection of accuracy is how often
we correctly catch the real fraud,
so that this is one of the scores
we use for the-- as a metric.
And the second one is false positive
rate, like how of-often we wrongly
flag le-legitimate transaction.
So we all-- we have all had this happen
when you try try to buy something
at a shopping center and card gets
declined message for without any reason.
That's like a false positive,
and it is a painful for some
people, like painful sometimes.
The third one is a latency, how long the
system takes to make this decis-decision.
If it is too long, then the payment
will be timed out, and it fails.
So we use generally these three metrics
to use metrics to identify whether
our ML model is performing well.
Next, we'll look at the second part
of the problem called personalization.
So When you are making a-- your financial
app, when you are thinking about like
a financial app, if it is knows you
without crossing the line into creepy.
So there are three technologies that does
the heavy lifting for a personalization.
One is the recommendation
system, reinforcement learning,
and LLM conversational agents.
The recommendation system
is like a Netflix or Amazon.
Instead of suggesting a movies,
they suggest a financial actions.
Hey, you might want to move this money
into savings or suggesting a credit card
based on its spending pattern, based off
user's spending pattern can be a good
examples for a recommendation system.
The reinforcement learning, okay,
AI learns from the feedback.
If user is ignoring a certain type
of alert, it learns and stops sending
this similar alerts in the future.
So this is the learning pattern the
AI adopts over time and, The next
one is a LLM conversational agents.
These are like a chatbots powered by LLMs.
Imagine you're asking your bank app,
"Can I afford a vacation next month?"
And getting a real helpful answer by
looking at your financial information.
Now let us look at a couple
of examples for a each.
If you take a recommendation system
that might notice you are saving
cons-consistently good amount of
money into your checking account, and
then it can suggest like a high yield
saving product, which can give you
more interest, and that, that will
add up more money for the end user.
If you take an recom-- reinforcement
learning agent, it might adjust the
timing and size of a credit offers based
on what's worked for a similar users.
So these agents are getting smarter
every week so that it can suggest,
The better offers for a users.
The LLM-powered advisors If you ask
your LLM advisors with a w-why my last
transaction got flagged as a fraud,
then it can explain the the real
challenge in a real English with-without
giving a more of a legal text.
So that is how I think we
can-- personalization help
the end users for a goods.
Now let us look at the
adaptive credit scorings.
So this is one of my favorite
slide because it shows how
AI can gener-genuinely fair
with the credit scoring.
For decades, you-- our credit scores
are in like a snapshot based on what
is on the file at a specific date.
It is very slow to update,
often unfair, and often not
transparent with the overall.
So AI-driven credit scoring
is completely different.
It looks at your behaviors over time.
Are you paying the bills on a time?
Are your income is stabilized?
Or is your spending habits
in a responsible way?
This means your score
adjusts in a near real time.
You get product offer that
actually fits your situation.
The system can warn you before
you overspend instead of
punishing you after spending.
So it is the difference between security
camera and a, like a helpful advisor.
The helpful advisor will give
you advice ahead of the time,
whereas the security camera will
show you the event after
the event happens, right?
Now let us look at the how
can we safeguard the AI.
This is one of the third pillar, and
arguably it is the most important one.
AI in the finance is powerful,
but it can also go very wrong
So we have to bake in safeguards
so that AI can be more powerful.
The AI-- every AI product or
every AI decision follows the
responsible AI principles.
The key principle behind the
responsible AI are explainability,
fairness, and privacy.
The principle explainability guides
every system should be... If AI denies
a loan, you and your regulator deserves
the right to know why it has denied
your loan with the actual reasons.
And the second principle, if you look at
the fairness, AI cannot discriminate by
your race, gender, age, or a zip code.
So we audit these decisions constantly to
make sure AI is following the fairness.
And when we look at the privacy,
so your data must stay in your,
Y-your data must stay yours.
You-- We use that generally
techniques to learn from it
without exposing the real data.
So all of these principles
are like not optional ones.
So these are the price of being
trusted with the people's money.
Now let us look at the various regulatory
and ethical constraints for the fintech.
And this is the most important
part many engineers miss.
Compliance isn't checkbox at the end.
It shapes the entire system from day
one so that the system is more safe.
For example, under European law,
especially GDPR Article twenty-two,
if an AI makes a decision about you,
you have the right to an explanation.
So we use tools like a
SHAP values and a LIME.
So these are the technique that translate
AI decisions into human-readable reasons.
For lending, every model we deploy
is tested for a bias across the
different demographic groups.
If it gives a different results for
similar people from different backgrounds
That is the stop line problem.
We have to fix those biasing issues.
So generally, we'll build this in early.
Retrofitting it later is enormously
expensive and sometimes impossible.
So now let us look at the
privacy-preserving techniques
in the Go deployments.
So there are three powerful ideas
for keeping the data private.
One is the federated learning and
differential privacy on-device inference.
So federated learning, instead of
pulling all of your data into a
big central computer, the AI model
travels to your phone, learns a little
there, and only shares the learning
not your complete data, so the
transaction never leaves your device.
The differential privacy principle
shows like we add a tiny bit of
mathematical noise to the data, so no
one can identify any individual person,
but the overall pattern still hold.
Apple and Google use this
for a similar reasons.
If you look at the on-device inference,
small AI models compiled with the Go
can run directly on your phone, scoring
transactions for a fraud without even
ever sending the details to the cloud.
So it will be processed at the on-device.
So all of these techniques let
us be like a smart and respectful
so that it will be more safe.
Now let us look at the various emerging
challenges and the frontier problems.
Where is this all going?
The three main problems
to keep us at night.
Adversarial robustness.
Even fraudsters are using the AI too.
They probe our systems, learn
from our defenses, and adapt.
It's a, it's like a, an arm race, and
we have to keep it evolving on a day
to day The real-time graph analytics.
Fraud rings are live in networks.
Watching those networks update in
a real time is a computationally
enormous, and the tools to do it well
in the Go are still being invented.
Responsible at AI at scale.
As we deploy more and more AI into
high-stakes financial decisions, we
need a stronger governance, better
audits, better oversight, and better
accountability so that all the
systems are safe and more responsible
at the end.
The key takeaways from
the this topic today is...
There are four key takeaways
from the today's topic.
One is Go isn't just a language
for a backend microservice.
It's a serious option for
production ML infrastructures.
It i- its speed and concurrency make it
perfect for a real-time AI solutions.
The second is a fraud detection and
personalization look different problems,
but them-- they both share the same
data and same plumbing and same models.
Build them together.
The third one is regulation
is not a final stage checkbox.
It is an architectural choice.
It bakes a fairness, explainability, and
privacy into AI models from the day one
so that the models are more safer and
follow the responsible AI regulations.
The last one is the once AI
is live, watch it like a hawk.
Models quietly degrade over
a time as the world changes.
Monitoring is not a just a important--
Monitoring is just important as
a building so that all of our
models will work effectively.
Thank you so much for your time.
I would love to Take your questions
if whether you are an engineer
building the systems or a leader
trying to navigate the trade-offs, or
just curious about how your banking
app really works behind the scenes.
You can find me after the session.
You can contact me in LinkedIn.
Thank you, Golang, for this
opportunity to s-speak.
Thank you