Everyone, welcome to
Conference 42 Golan 2025.
I'm Kumar Borum.
I have 22 years of consulting
experience and I'm currently working
with Consult as a specialist Leader.
As part of my role, I'm associated
with big, large scale industries
where I do digital transformation,
financial transformation, and
as part of today's conference.
I like that on Golan and how it is
impacting, transformation in healthcare
education and sustainability.
Now, golans versatility and performance
enable impactful technological
solutions at critical sectors when paid
with consulting expertise solutions
accelerate digital transformation
and enhance social outcomes.
Now as part of today's agenda, I would
like to touch upon the Ang social impact
landscape, especially in association with
healthcare, in association with education,
in association with sustainability,
and in association with implementation
of best practices across industries.
Now, from a healthcare standpoint,
Golan has been revolutionizing
patient care through robust systems
and expanding telemedicine access to.
Underserved communities from
an education advancement.
It has been building responsive
learning platforms and optimizing
institutional operations for
equitable educational opportunities.
And from an sustainability solutions, it
has been developing resource efficient.
Energy management systems and
creating transparent, ethical
supply and monitoring tools.
And from an overall implementation,
best practices, Golang has been,
specialized in implementing
strategic deployment frameworks,
cross sector collaboration models.
And social impact measurement methods.
If you look into the healthcare sector,
it has been enhancing the patient care.
One of the major factor is
staff mentioned there has been a
significant reduction in healthcare,
professional burnout and turnover.
Following Goalline powered EHR
implementation, there has been a care
coordination there has been enhanced.
Patient outcomes through seamless
ation of care processes and real
time clinical data exchange.
And there has been a huge, huge
growth in tele telemedicine.
There has been unprecedented such in
virtual healthcare delivery, making
critical services accessible to
previously underserved populations.
How it is making an
impact in telemedicine?
What are, what is that is
doing to break the barriers?
Now, if you look into the pre
pandemic era, there was minimal
telemedicine integration with
only 8% eruption rate with Golang
solutions ran largely unexplored In
healthcare, significant urban rural
access dispatch is persisted, but.
With pandemic with Covid, there has
been a response to this and it has
expedited implementation of going forward.
telemedicine platforms there has been
unprecedented, about 44 percentage
scaling capacity achieved within weeks.
Virtual care become essential
for continuing of services.
Currently the current landscape is
where, telemedicine infrastructure
has reached a 90 per 92 percentage
of previously unserved communities.
Rural adapt adaptation rates match urban
metrics for the first time, go Lang
solutions maintain 99.8 up time while
handling three x pre pandemic, patient
volumes from an education standpoint.
Golan has been, part of the
digital learning, revolution.
The integration of golan based
solutions has dramatically transformed
educational technology platforms
as evident by key performance
indicators across multiple dimensions.
The data reveals substantial improvements
flying Golan implementation with
student and educator adaption rates
increased by 76% platform efficiency.
Improving by 49 per percentage
and overall user satisfaction
raising by 50 percentage.
This me metrics demonstrate how
Golans performance capabilities
directly translate to enhanced
educational experiences and outcomes.
How Golan is making an impact.
Let's do a deep dive on it.
it has impacted the learning management
system now, Ang powered platforms
have driven a remarkable 34 percentage
increase in student at action rates.
Students now access educational resources
with 99.7 percentage uptime reliability
even during peak usage periods.
Teach report, 42 percentage
more efficient workflows.
Allowing them to focus on instruction
rather than technology management.
And from an operational deficiency,
administrative processes have improved
by 30 percentage through streamlined
automation eliminating tasks.
Educational institutions have reduced
paperwork requirements by 65 percentage,
saving thousands of staffers annually.
Automated assessment tools.
Have accelerated grading cycles by
28 percentage, providing students
with timely actionable feedback.
And there are accessibility features
as well, which are cutting edge.
Goal line implementations enable
real time translation across 47
languages, breaking down communication
barriers in diverse classrooms.
Native integration with screen
readers and other technologies
has increased participation among
students with disabilities by
58 percentage, which is huge.
Even personalized learning path
adapt to individual student progress
that resulting in 20 percentage
implement in learning outcomes.
All this done in the recent times,
with Golan and Golan is playing.
A major role in sustainability
and energy optimization.
what it is doing it is monitoring
concurrent energy, consumption tracking
with the millisecond per position.
There, there has been constant analysis.
Machine learning algorithms, identifying
inefficiency patterns, and at the same
time, it is reporting on optimization,
intelligent resources, allocation with
automated load balancing and reporting,
interactive data visualization with
predictive modeling goal lines.
Concurrency model enables energy
management systems to detect
inefficiencies with remarkable precision.
Identifying 15 to 20% of
previously undetected energy waste
post-implementation metrics consistently
show 20 percentage reduction in
energy consumptions while maintaining
or improving operational output.
These systems demonstrate.
Linear scalability across
enterprises, facilities from small
operations to industry complex
complexities with minimal overhead.
Golan has been impacting with
supply chain sustainability as well.
you take into transparency,
end-to-end visibility.
There is verification.
Blockchain, secure data.
There is integration.
Connected supplier networks and there
is reporting animated compliance.
Leading consulting firms have implemented
Golang based supply chain platforms,
that increased end-to-end visibility
by 43 percentage, enabling real time
tracking of materials and products.
The blockchain integration ensures.
Immutable data integrity while preventing
fraud and unauthorized modifications.
Orination adapting.
These solutions have achieved substantial
efficiency improvements, including 37
percentage faster supplier onboarding,
and 29 percentage reduction in
compliance related administrative costs.
Now, key success factors for Gula is.
It's agile implementation.
Golans concurrency model facilitates
rapid prototyping and iteration.
This shortened feedback loop enable
teams to validate assumptions quickly
and adapt to changing requirements,
ultimately accelerating the value
delivery by up to 40 percentage.
And Golan has a user
centered design solutions.
Architected around core user
needs, yield higher adoption rates.
Comprehensive field testing with
actual beneficiaries provide critical
insights driving continuous improvement
cycles that measurably enhance user
satisfaction and impact metrics.
And there has been a
cross-functional teams.
with Gox now integration of technical
developers with domain experts,
like healthcare professionals,
educators, sustainability specialists,
create knowledge, synergies.
This collaborative approach fosters
sharp ownership resulting in solutions
that address both technical elegance
and real world practicability.
And of course there is an aspect
of data governance as well.
Robust governance frameworks
safeguard sensitive information and
ensure with international privacy
standards, these protocols guarantee
ethical data utilization while
maintaining data integrity and quality
throughout the solution lifecycle.
At the same time, Golan has its
own challenges, the implementation
challenges and solutions.
Now, one of the thing is one of
the major challenges, legacy system
integration, golans exceptional.
Interoperability eliminates
compatibility barriers.
Our A first approach seamlessly.
Bridges legacy and modern systems.
Strategic phased migration minimizes
business disruption and security risks.
Organizational change expert
change management, accelerate
accelerates transformation.
Comprehensive training program build
technical confidence and expertise.
Transparent communication and stakeholder
engagement drive sustainable adaption.
Technology tech, technical complexity,
specialized consulting expertise,
transformation, complex challenges
into manageable components.
Our model services are
architecture, enables unprecedented
flexibility and scalability.
Comprehensive documentation
ensures long-term maintainability,
knowledge transfer.
And how we are, how it is measuring
the impact, custom metrics, frameworks,
capture, growth, technical and
business value integration of.
Qualitative feedback with
quantitative performance data
provides complete insights.
Data driven continuous improvement
cycles maximize return on
investment at the same time.
where we see the future of GoLine
expanding GoLine social impact, wider
adoption organizations increasingly
leverage golans performance.
For mission critical social initiatives,
cross sector knowledge sharing,
accelerators implementation, and amplifies
collective impact enhanced integration.
ANGs elegant concurrency model
enables powerful synergies with ai,
blockchain, and IOT technologies.
These integrated ecosystems deliver
unprecedented capabilities for
addressing complex social challenges.
Community growth.
A flourishing developer community
dedicated to social impact creates a,
cycle of innovation, growing, pository
of open source tools, dramatically
lower barriers to entry for resources,
constraint, organizations, measurable
outcomes, advanced analysis frameworks
quantify ANGs contribution to social
change with increasing position.
Data driven Insights guide, s
investments and policy decisions
for maximum sustainable impact.
This is what I would
like to cover on Golan.
If you have any questions,
please reach out to me.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.