Hi all.
This is today I'm going talk about
the topic revolutionizing industry
with AI and the collaborative
workflow intelligence framework.
Today we'll be seeing how the Golan
and the artificial intelligence are
resetting the automation heavy industries.
we'll examine various, like industries,
like finance, manufacturing, and see how
the collaborative workflow, is working.
Basically, it is the bridge
between the, human expertise
and the, machine intelligence.
Our framework offers a very structured
approach, solutions, Characteristics,
there are like a different, a good
number of resource, oriented values.
we can see from, different,
domains such as manufacturing,
logistics, and financial services.
we'll, slowly, discovering
the coming slides, how, these,
collaborative, workflow framework
enhances, the performance.
And cost reduction.
Let's go to the next slide.
Welcome, the challenges
of the modern automation.
in this slide, there are like
a four, points I have tried
to mention here in this slide.
One is the balancing automation
with human oversight.
another is the, real
time processing demands.
Integration complexity and, workforce,
automation, with human oversight.
there are organizations
which trying to, of.
they are trying to, maintain the proper
industry standards and, safety standards.
that is one of the major challenges
the modern industry is facing.
So our, framework, will,
definitely, take this into account
for the, for balancing the.
then the, as for the real time
processing, so modern industry is
dealing with a huge data volumes.
So it needs, immediate analysis and
response, for the, massive data.
it, Then there comes the,
integration complexity.
we're dealing about,
complex, technologies.
so we need various, like a flexible
solutions to cope up with that.
And then there comes
the, workforce, adapt.
in, in our current days, employees
need clear frameworks to, collaborate
effectively with the AI systems,
rather than the, competing with them.
There needs to be exact, balance
between the AI and the humans.
we can, get the desire.
what is, collaborative workflow
intelligence framework?
Basically, it's a human ai,
partnership and it'll take, the
ethical oversights and, context,
sensitive decisions, in this, in this
bidirectional information flow model.
And it, used to learn from the
continuous, learning and adapt to the,
for, adapt to the, just performance,
feedback, to get it more accurate.
the framework also, has a, like
very high performance concurrent,
processing architecture.
Are like, the collaborative workflow
intelligence framework, establishes
clear boundaries between the AI and the
human decision authorities, creating
a symbiotic relationships, that,
leverages the strength of the both.
It is very high, concurrency model,
performance and it be used in the
real processing for large, data.
This is not just a theoretical concept.
it can be, used, practically in
different, industries like finance,
manufacturing, and it can be used in
complex scenarios and where there are
like, lot of technical complexity.
this framework, definitely
benefits from that.
So there different, advantages.
we can select, like from the other
framework, we, we can say of the
exceptional performance of, framework.
And, there are like a different, garbage
collection efficiency, modules, which can
enable the microsecond response times,
essential for industry automations.
it helps seen improving the
performance and we have given
some benchmark of around, 40 to
60% improvements we are seeing.
Language, implementations.
Then there comes the,
built-in concurrency.
it gives, multi, multi-threading,
capabilities, perfect for, managing
a large amount of data streams.
Currently, our industry is
dealing with a large amount
of data and complex technical.
Scenario.
And it helps in, just, building, with
con on top of any technical complexity.
And this is by far, justing the,
traditional, threading models.
And then there comes
the strong type safety.
So colon static typing prevents common
runtime, errors, crucial for mission
sensitive, industry applications
where system failures, can have
significant consequences in terms of
revenue and production continuity.
here the, our framework, helps in,
So we are talking about the technical
strengths here, but also apart from
the technical strengths, goal and
simplicity and readability also make
it, for the, cross-functional teams
where the engineers and the data
scientists, can collaborate closely.
it is also using the standard,
library, which dependencies and.
To the next slide.
We have went through
a number of use cases.
one is the, manufacturing,
sector implementation.
so in this, we have went through a
few, module like, sensor integration,
predictive analytics, intelligent
and human direction resolution.
in sensor integration, Golan
microservices, collect and
normalize data from, heterogeneous
sensor networks across, factory
floors and predictive analysis.
it, analysis the pattern, to,
predictive the maintenance needs.
And then comes the intelligent,
so intelligent alerting,
the notifications issues.
Then, we also, go through the
human director resolution.
So it makes in the final decision
making on the complex and
maintenance, and quality issues.
so ai, requirements, those
complex financial decisions.
And it, we have owned to a, like a,
successful, like a metrics for these
17% reduction in the, like a production
delays, around 23% in unplanned downtime.
The, systems ability to integrate,
with the existing systems.
We are seeing investment
in.
We are also going to the, logistics,
optimization case study where we're
doing the route planning, load
balancing, exception handling,
and performance analysis.
So in route planning, we s the optimal,
delivery sequences, accounting for.
And, load balancing it, helps
in allocating in the dynamically
allocating the resources.
therefore, making the, cost optimization
and, exception handling, human
dispatchers, review the AI recommendations
in critical unusual situations, which.
Performance analysis.
So here, we going through improvement
information and we can
get the recognition.
And for the performance analysis
and, we're getting here, almost
80, 30, 12%, cost reduction in the
regional logistic, provider for this
kind of, architecture, this kind of
framework implementation and on time
delivery rates also improved by 14%.
And, real time adjustments also.
Now coming to the, financial,
services application.
So we have discovered like a
few modules in this, under this
financial services application.
One is the, document processing.
in this state, AI extracts and,
the data from the loan applications
and the supporting documents.
then the risk assessment goal length
services from complex risk calculations
with, subsecond, millisecond latency and
continuous learning system goes through
the, feedback on decisions and outcomes.
And this will help in making
the, optimized solutions.
Underwriter focus on complex
cases flagged by the system.
A mid-size regional bank, implemented
this framework for their loan processing
operations, which in fact helped in 25%
implemented the loan approval efficiency
while maintaining their risk profile.
So it's evaluating all the complex
case scenario applications.
And it has particularly good features,
environment and making it more,
performance has more performance.
And, we have gained significant
business impact for this framework.
And, from the manufacturing production
efficiency improvement standpoint,
there were, percent, reduced delays.
And, 25%, processing efficiency.
Also, we can get, when we're just going
through the use case of the financial
services applications throughput
increase, and, for the logistic
delivery optimization savings, we are
getting eight to 12%, cost reductions.
And, 32% for the, like employee
satisfaction, when we're just worker
engagements across implementations.
there.
A good number of metrics we can solve
for this, f framework, which can
use to drivers range of industries.
the combination of the LANs,
performance characteristics and along
with the ai, human collaboration
definitely, makes a competitive
advantage over the traditional, models.
We.
Then organizations also report,
significant, improvements in the
ability to extract and retain the
technical talent as the framework,
the engaging roles that emphasize
the human judgment and creativity
rather than the routine processing.
So implementation methodology,
we can, four, the,
the map, the current processes
and the decision boundaries.
This comes the advisory pilot where we
deploy AI in the recommendation only mode.
That is the supervised automation.
gradually increase automation
with the oversight.
Fourth is the continuous
optimization refined based on the
performance data and the feedback.
Our implementation approach, emphasizes
gradual adoption, starting with
systems that provide recommendations
but lead decisions to humans.
goal's, modularity support this
incremental approach through,
clear service boundaries.
And, change management is also
integrated through the process, with
education programs that helps, workers
understand how the AI will be complement
their roles rather than just them.
Technical architectural overview.
so this C architecture,
there are three layers.
One is the data collection
microservices, and AI processing core
and the, human interface components.
goal powers the critical performance
path, particularly in the data collection
and transformation layers where the
concurrency demands at the highest.
So we have going through various
benchmark competition here.
So we have just on the previous,
systems, and then we have going through
the processing times and the memory
usage of the previous systems, and also
in the Python implementations, Java
implementations and goal implementations.
These.
real time processing much more faster than
almost like three to 11 times, processing
faster, than the, traditional models.
And also it helps, in taking
the, less memory, compared
to the traditional models.
it, allocation of the resources
in all the environments.
So what will be our next
steps in the future research?
we definitely need to focus on
the, adaptive, learning models.
then, we have to define on the
systems, where the, they're making
the continuous, decision boundaries
based on the human feedback.
The outcomes, reducing the
need for manual retraining.
Then, we're using these models in
the, already in the cross-functional,
industry, be healthcare, energy finance.
So all are now tied up into the safety
requirements and the unique regulatory,
then the workforce evaluation.
researching long-term impacts on
skill development and the job roles
to guide the educational and training
programs for the a augmented workspace.
It helps, in benefits, lot of
benefits in the workforce, evolution.
And, then there is the goal
line ecosystem expansion.
So developing, specialized libraries
and frameworks, optimizes further the
goal line for ai, human collaborative
systems in industrial context.
we're dealing with various organizations
and ask them to, do their CWIF journey,
with a workflow assessment workshop.
we can, gain the maximal, amount
of the benefits our team provides.
Implementation roadmap, tailor to
your, industry context and technical
maturity, whether it a complex
problem, definitely our model can,
Yeah, that's all my, like in and.