Speaker 3: Hello.
My name is Amol Lele, and
today I'm presenting real time
ML training profiling in Go.
How a multilayer observability platform
cut infrastructure costs by fifty
percent by making bottlenecks visible
while workloads are still running.
This is built on Go's concurrency model,
Go routines, channels, and lightweight
scheduling to deliver sub minus one
percent overhead at a production rate.
What is the core problem
that we want to solve?
It is a lack of visibility.
Organization often deploys sophisticated
GPU clusters expecting maximum efficiency,
yet the production environments
routinely suffer from invisible
bottlenecks across software, hardware,
and distributed communication layers.
Why is it reason one,
it's a reactive debugging.
Failures discovered only after
expensive runs are completed.
That causes wastage in compute resources.
Budgets are consumed even before
root causes are identified.
It results in slow experimentation
because each failed run becomes
an increasingly expensive.
Why existing profiling
approaches fail today?
One, pro-- framework profilers.
These are high memory overhead, large
trace files, and ha-- often have
poor scalability, which is useful
for shorter sess- shorter sessions
and not continuous production usage.
Then the infrastructure dashboards.
These typically are for cluster-wide
metrics, but causality remains invisible.
Low GPU utilization does not explain
the reason why that is the case.
More often, these profiling approaches
are log-based analysis, and that
generates an excessive overhead.
It is inconsistent instrumentation,
delayed analysis by the time team
investigate, the run is actually over.
What are the design goals
in this runtime profiling?
First, low overhead.
We want minimum allocation
of resources, asynchronous
processing, and adaptive sampling.
We want multilayer visibility.
All the layers, including the
application layer, system layer, and the
infrastructure layers simultaneously.
We want real-time analysis
Immediate anomaly detection
during the execution phase itself.
Distributed scale.
We want to-- horizontal
aggregation across large clusters.
Also extensibility.
We want modular support for new
hardwares, frameworks, and metrics.
Why Go was the right choice?
Number one, Go routines.
These are lightweight
concurrent collectors.
Each subsystem runs independently,
sharing centralized aggregation channels.
Channels.
Structured telemetry transport with
backpressure management that reduces
lock contention and clear ownership.
Networking.
Efficient gRPC, streaming
telemetry, and connection pooling
without low-level optimization.
And the last one is
operational simplicity.
It is very easy to deploy.
The solutions are-- can be easily
containerized, can cross-compile
and upgrade, reducing operational
complexity significantly.
The platform architecture starts
with edge collectors, which is very
close to the model, which is under
training, then the recommendation
engine and the local aggregation.
Often, data pipelines are
themselves are bottlenecks.
The most common and expensive inefficiency
is the GPUs that are waiting for data
to arrive at them rather than executing
the training workloads, and that is
caused by the data pipeline bottlenecks.
Fine-grained profiling has revealed
repeatedly that the idle gaps
hidden beneath these acceptable
average utilizations are due to
these data pipeline bottlenecks.
And why these bottlenecks occurs?
Those are because of intermittent storage
latency spikes, CPU saturations during the
augmentation, garbage collection pauses,
which are inherent in Python workers,
and excessive serialization of overhead.
How do we fix these data pi--
data pipeline bottlenecks?
One, asynchronous prefetching.
Batches are prepared ahead of GPU demand.
That eliminates the
synchronous stalls in GPU.
Adaptive worker scaling.
Processing workers expand or contract
dynamically based on the queue pressure.
Storage-aware scheduling.
Locality-aware scheduling that reduces
remote fetch dependency and latency
variance Pipeline dis-dashboards,
queue depth, pre-processing latencies,
and GPU idle time is visualized
all together for rapid diagnosis.
What are the communication
overhead in distributed training?
As the cluster size grows,
the synchronization overhead
becomes a dominant player.
Even a smaller delay cascades
into a cluster-wide stalls.
These are in typically that
happens in network contention
and congestion amplification.
There is a topology imbalance
between the rack placement.
A minor jitter triggering
the substantial idle periods.
What are the effective
optimizations that we can do?
We can do a gradient compression,
hierarchical synchronization,
topology-aware scheduling, and
overlapping communication with
forward computation phases.
The bigger problem is
the straggler workers.
What are straggler workers?
In any distributed system, the speed
the w-- at which the distributed
system moves is at the speed of
the slow, slowest participant.
The challenge is not just detecting
the slow worker, it's identifying
the root cause, why they become slow.
The typical reasons for the straggler
workers are thermal throttling, which
is gradually increases the latency
signature, network instability,
data imbalance, resource contention.
The most important part of this
profiler is the recommendation engine.
Just collecting the telemetry
is not... is the first step.
That does not eliminate the problem.
Engineers often want answers,
not just the dashboard.
The recommendation engine
caters to that use case.
This engine combines deterministic rules,
statistical thresholds, time series
analysis, and historical comparisons.
A hybrid approach for
reliability and interpretability.
Typical examples for the recommendations
that are generated are increase the
pre-processing worker count, enable
the gradient compression, investigate
why the thermal instability on specific
nodes, rebalance the data set shards.
Runtime overhead engineering.
Any profiler comes with a cost, but that
cost should not defeat its own purpose.
We want to control that
overhead How do we control that?
One, the memory efficiency.
That is achieved by object
pooling, reusable buffers, compact
serialization, and that reduces
the GC pressure aggressively.
Adaptive sampling.
The sampling frequency is adjusted
dynamically based on the workload
state, anomalies, or the cluster scale.
Asynchronous pipelines.
Collectors never block
a training execution.
Telemetry emitted through these
buffered non-blocking channels
reduces the profiler over-overhead.
Graceful degradation.
Under a very heavy load, a lower
priority telemetry is sampled,
aggregated or selectively dropped.
What are the production
challenges and energy impact?
The first one is the deployment challenge.
Often, the infrastructure on which
these activities are happening, the
ML training activities are happening,
they're heterogeneous in nature.
The GPU generations vary, drivers,
topology required for these ones vary.
So we want to have these
instrumentation portable.
Clock synchronization.
As we need to detect the drift
between these events so that we can
easily correlate those events and
reach a me-- reach the conclusion
or give the right recommendation.
It can be achieved by monotonically
increasing timestamps, and we want
to introduce the correction layers
so that the clocks are synchronized.
And the third one is organizational
adoption or the inertia.
A trust in automated recommendation
only grows gradually through
repeated accurate diagnosis.
How does it impact the energy consumption?
It is a sustainability impact.
An idle GPU consumes a substantial energy,
even if it is not training or even if
it is not doing any useful computation.
Real-life real-time profiling exposes
this waste, and it improves the
energy efficiency by reducing the
idle accelerator periods, shortening
the training duration, lowering
the cooling demands, reducing the
unnecessary experimentation cycle.
Operational efficiency and
sustainability increasingly align.
What lessons have we learned and
what are the future directions?
The key lessons.
Visibility often changes the
culture Real-time observability
makes optimizations proactive.
Engineers experiment more confidently.
Multilayer thinking.
It is not limited to a single metric,
explains the distributed performance.
Application, system, and
infrastructures must all be correlated.
Automation amplifies the expertise.
Recommendations scale engineering
knowledge across larger
organizations as ML complexity grows.
What are the future directions?
Number one, predictive optimization.
We proactively prevent bottlenecks
before even they occur.
Autonomous tuning.
Dynamically topology adjustment
and workload migration
without manual intervention.
Unified observability.
End-to-end visibility across
training and inference pipelines.
The future of efficient ML is intelligent
visibility, which often require results
into a cost reduction, failure modes,
platform layers, where we get all-- where
we address all the platforms, connectors,
aggregations, stream processing,
all those recommendations together.
The future of efficient machine
learning is not simply faster hardware.
It is intelligent visibility into
how that hardware is actually used.
With this, I'm ending my presentation.
Thank you very much for attending that.