Hello everyone.
Welcome to Convert two I am.
Today we'll explore how go and
cloud native technologies are
transforming the retail distribution.
These innovations are not only
improving efficiency, but also
making operations more sustainable.
We'll.
And how retailers worldwide are
using go based microservices to
optimize supply chains, reduce carbon
footprints, and boost the performance.
I'll also share proven strategies and
real world examples that have delivered
measurable results in inventory
management and resource allocation.
Let's dive in and see a. How technology
is shaping the future of retail,
the rise of go in retail technology.
We are seeing a big shift in retail
technology and GO is playing a
major role in this transformation,
growing adoption, and growing such.
More and more retailers are using,
go for their backend systems because
it's fast, reliable, and efficient.
Modern infrastructure companies are moving
away from traditional monolithic systems
and adapting microservices, making their
operations more flexible and scalable.
Cloud integration retailers are
leveraging cloud native technologies
to improve efficiency, reduce cost,
and scale their business seamlessly.
Sustainability focus.
With smarter resource utilization go
helps retailers lower their carbon
footprint and operate more sustainability.
Go simplicity, speed, and ability to
add in multiple processes at once.
Make it an excellent charge for
today's retail distribution needs next.
Let's look at some real world
success stories that highlight
the impact of goin global retail
global success stories with go.
Let's see how companies worldwide are
using go to improve their businesses.
European grocery Chain, this
company wanted faster and
more efficient deliveries.
By using Go microservices, they
improved logistics cut fuel used by
28% and speed up deliveries by 32%.
This also reduced carbon emission
by 5,400 tons of a year, good
for business and the environment.
As a result, they achieved
record ontime deliveries.
Not American retailer.
They struggle with inventory management.
After switching to a goal-based
system, they reached out
45% faster and had 15% fear.
Stockouts plus software updates that
used to take days now happen in minutes.
Helping them react
quickly to market changes.
Asia Pacific Passion Distributor, they
needed better demand forecasting by
using AI with go based cloud apps.
They improved accuracy by 37% and
cut extra inventory cash by 22%.
Better coordination.
With manufacturers also reduce waste by
18%, helping their sustainability goals.
Key takeaways.
These stories show how go is making
retail smarter, faster, and more
sustainable, whether it's logistics,
inventory, or a, or decisions.
For performance metrics that matter.
Let's talk about the real impact of Go
in Retail measured by key performance
implements, 68% faster response time
retailers using Go have seen their
backend system respond much faster,
improving customer experience.
42% more inventory, tons.
With better inventory management,
businesses are restocking
and selling products faster.
31% less code goes.
Simplicity means fewer lines of code
while maintaining the same functionality,
making development more efficiency,
24% lower carbon emissions, optimizing.
Resource use is helping companies
reduce their environmental footprint.
Our research across multiple
retailers shows that go
delivery is real business value.
It's not just about
speed of the efficiency.
It is also about sustainability with
low energy used and smaller logistics.
Microservices architecture for retail
microservices allow retailers to create
flexible and scalable systems by breaking
them into smaller, independent services
that can grow as shrink based around the
demand go is perfect for this business.
It's lightweight and can handle
multiple tasks at the same time.
Making it ideal for these distributed
systems, key areas in retailing, order
processing services that handle customer
transactions, payment processing,
fraud detection, and order validation,
inventory management, real time
tracking of stock across the network,
stock allocation and smart figures.
For replenishment and predictive stocking,
logistics optimization, planning routes,
coordinating deliveries, reducing
carbon emissions through efficient
routing and optimizing load and delivery
schedules, analytics in general.
This includes data processing
for business intelligence, demand
forecasting, performance monitoring,
and tracking sustainability metrics
go ability to power the systems,
choose retailers can run efficiency
while adapting to customer need
quickly to make project successful.
There are a few key
things that really matter.
Strong teamwork across different areas.
Uni B, a mix of retail experts
and skilled go engineers.
Working together,
clear service boundaries.
Microservices should be well
defined with clear roles and
connections, standardized tools.
Everyone should follow the same
development and deployment practices.
Good performance tracking.
Keeping an eye on system performance
with proper monitoring and
data collection is essential.
Our research shows that companies that
get these things right, see big benefits.
Projects move 3.2 times faster, and
teams are 68% more satisfied with
their goal based retail systems.
Then with older methods, one of
the big success factors, smooth
knowledge sharing between business
and tech teams, especially when
moving to cloud-based systems.
How Ghost Concurrency helps in retail.
Imagine running a retail business
where thousands of customers
are shopping at the same time.
Keeping inventory updated, processing
order smoothly, and handling
request efficiently, all without
slowing down can be a big challenge.
That's where Goes
concurrency model comes in.
Real time inventory
updates with Go routines.
Go uses something called Go Routines,
which are like super lightweight threats.
This means your system can
update inventory across thousands
of products and the same time
without using too many resources.
Even during use sales event, staff
levels stay accurate in real time.
A single go service can handle over
10,000 inventory updates at once, way more
efficiently than older technologies is
smoother.
Order processing with channels goes.
Channels help different parts of the
system talk to each other safely,
so there are no mix ups or lost
orders when a customer checks out.
There are other flows smoothly
from payment to shipping without
any errors or data corruption.
Thanks to this retailers see
87% fewer failed transaction
even when things get busy.
Better request handling with context.
Ghost context package.
Make sure request don't get stuck.
If system is slow, are unresponsive,
go can cancel those request
and pre-op resources instead
of letting them hang over.
This has reduced manuals for
stuck transactions by 94%.
Saving time and keeping
things running smoothly.
With these smart concurrency features,
retailers don't have to overspend an
extra servers to handle peak traffic.
They can run a fast, efficient,
and reliable systems that
can scale when needed.
Helping both their
business and environment.
Open source go.
Tools for retail analytics,
predictive inventory management.
Retailers needs to keep the right
amount of stock at all times.
Open source, go libraries like temporal.
Go and go.
Help predict demand by
analyzing fast sales, weather
patterns, and social trends.
This means fewer empty shells
and, less wasted inventory, all
without needing expensive systems.
Geo distribution, optimization, delivering
products efficiently is key for retailers.
So go based tools like Geo S two and
YSRM helps businesses plan the best
delivery rules and where of the locations.
This reduces free use, saves
money, and makes, delivers faster
sustainability metrics.
Processing, tracking, environmental
impact is becoming more important.
Specialized Go framework help
retailers measure their carbon
footprint across supply chains
and find ways to reduce emissions.
This helps businesses be more a
corporately while staying efficient.
The use of these open source tools has
grown by 12 215% in just 18 months.
Okay, and 78% of retailers report
better decision making and operations.
A more businesses adopt these tools.
Retail is becoming smarter,
faster, and a small, sustainable
cloud native.
Integration challenges, solution testing.
Retail systems are complex, so
it's important to test thoroughly
across different scenarios.
This helps make sure everything runs
smoothly, no matter the situation.
Data synchronization.
With so many systems working together,
keeping data consistent across
all the platform is a challenge.
Businesses need strong
synchronization methods to our error.
Security implementation,
protecting customers and
business data is a top priority.
Strong security measures help
prevent breaches and keep
sensitive information safe.
Legacy integration.
Many retailers still use older
systems, so connecting them with
modern cloud native applications.
Can be tricky.
Yeah.
Smooth integration processes
keep key to the success.
Go brings big benefits to cloud
native retail applications, but these
challenges need to be tackled early.
Companies that plan ahead and theft
thoroughly can launch 47% faster
than those that wait to fix issues.
Ladder setting clear integration patterns.
I understand error handling strategies
is especially helpful when linking go
microservices with older retailer systems,
building resell supply
chains, disruption detection.
Retailers need to spark problems
before they cause major delays.
With go forward monitoring
businesses can detect supply chain
issues in real time using smart
sensors and an enemy detection.
Alternative routing.
When transportation routes are suppliers
run into travel dynamic, rerun, rerouting,
kicks in, go based systems quickly
calculate the best alternative plans.
Are parts keeping products
moving without major delays?
Inventory reallocation
if disruption happen.
Intelligent algorithm redistribute
inventory across the network, making
sure the most critical needs are covered.
First and service levels stay high.
Normal operation presumption.
Once the issue is resolved, automated
recovery process brings operations
back to normal, reducing the need for
manual fixes and saving time goals.
Speed and reliability make it a perfect
fit for handling supply chain changes,
challenges retailers using the strategies
see 76% faster recovery from destructions.
And 23% lower financial impact
from unexpected problems.
Building resilience, supply
chains, disruption detection.
Retailers need to spot problems
before they cause major delays.
With go forward monitoring, businesses can
detect supply chain issues in real time.
Using smart sensors and anomaly
detection, alternative routing.
When transportation route or supplies run
into trouble, dynamic rerouting kicks in.
Go based system quickly.
The best alternate paths keeping
products moving without major delays.
Inventory allocation.
If your distraction happen, intelligent
algorithm tribute inventory across
a network, making sure the most
critical needs to be are covered.
First and service levels stay high.
Normal operations resumption once the
issue is resolved, automated recovery
processes bring operations back to normal.
Reducing the need for manual
fixes and saving time, go speed.
The real reliability make it perfect fit
for handling supply chain challenges.
Retailers using these strategies see
76% faster recovery from disruption
and 23% lower financial impact.
From unexpected problems,
implementation roadmap, and
next steps assessment page.
Start by evaluating your current system
to see where go can bring the most value.
Key steps include reviewing
your technical architecture.
Analyzing sustainability impact assessing
your team's skills to ensure they are
ready for go pilot implementation.
Next, begin with the small project
focusing on microservices that will
deliver tick, measurable results.
These could include inventory
optimization, services, distribution,
routing, service engines,
real time analytics pipelines.
Scale and integration.
Once the Pilot Pro works
expands the successful patterns
across your organization.
This involves automating deployment with
the DevOps, integrating with the legacy
system, building team capabilities to
scale further continuous optimization.
Use metrics to keep improving
your system over time.
Focus on for farmers tuning,
reducing their carbon footprint.
Testing supply chain reseller.
Start by choosing the one retail
function, which clear goals around
sustainability and operations.
Thanks to open source framework, you
will type currently see measurable
results within 90 days of deployment.
Thank you for this great opportunity.
I have a great day.
Thank you.