Speaker 2: Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining my session.
My name is Devi Manoharan, and I work
in healthcare quality engineering,
focusing on healthcare claim systems,
EDI processing, automation, APIs,
and scalable backend platforms.
Today I will discuss how AI and
scalable EDI pipelines can improve
healthcare claims processing systems
and help organizations process
claims faster and more efficiently.
Let's get started.
In this session, I'll talk about
the challenges in healthcare claims
processing, how machine learning
improves decision-making, how EDI
pipelines work work at scale, and
how modern backend systems support
high volume claim processing.
Healthcare claim systems are becoming
more complex because of growing claims
volumes coding standards and pay, payer
rules and compliance requirements.
So manual processing alone is no longer
enough to handle this scale efficiently.
So organizations today need systems
that can process claims faster while
maintaining accuracy and compliance.
Traditional rule-based systems work
for basic validations, but they become
difficult to maintain at large scale.
Large organizations often manage thousands
of business rules, and even small
changes can impact multiple systems.
So they also can't understand
patterns or detect anomalies
like machine learning models can.
Machine learning helps automate the
claims classification, anomaly detection,
risk scoring, and intelligent routing.
For example, the system can identify
duplicate claims unusual billing
patterns or high-risk claims
before they reach adjudication.
This reduces manual work and
improves processing efficiency.
One major advantage of
AI is early detection.
So the system can identify issues
during claim ingestion itself,
reducing downstream rework and and
also the manual analyst review effort.
So high confidence claims can
move directly through automation
and while only complex cases are
sent for manual analyst reviews
And finding issues.
The-- why it matters.
The reason is finding issues earlier
saves time and operational cost.
So the AI-driven systems helps reduce
denials, denied claims, improve
turnaround time, and also support
large-scale claims processing.
Even small efficiency improvements
can create major business impact
when millions of claims are
processed in a large-scale system.
And EDI transactions like eight
thirty-seven claims for dental,
professional, institutional
claims, and eight thirty-five
remittance files are the foundation
of healthcare claims processing.
The pipelines, the pipeline parses and it
validates and enriches and prepares these
transactions for downstream systems like
adjudication, analytics, and reporting,
and further for payment processing.
The EDI workflow includes parsing,
enrichment, schema mapping,
and compliance validation.
For example, eligibility and
provider information can be added
during enrichment before the claim
moves for further into processing.
So the-- breaking the overflow,
w-sorry, breaking the workflow into
smaller stages, it really improves
the scalability and reliability.
The important EDI capabilities
include segment parsing, eligibility
enrichment, schema mapping, and
HIPAA compliance validation.
It is very important based
on the CMS guidelines.
These validations helps ensure claims are
accurate before before even entering into
the adjudication systems and also further
moving into the payment processing.
Because, for example, if the claim is
by mistake, if the claim is denied or
voided, then the company, the healthcare
companies have to pay the denial.
They ought to pay the cost of the claims,
even though the members have to do some
adjustments to this-- those claims.
So this creates lot of overpayment
issues in the same claim
And modern claim systems it needs
high accur-- high concurrency
and scalable architectures.
Technologies like Go and Kafka help to
process large claim volumes efficiently.
It is a kind of event-dri-- it is
a event-driven architecture, and
it also helps for organizations to
handle traffic spikes and traffic
traffic spikes more reliably.
Our AI models should work directly
inside the claims pipeline using
real-time scoring services.
So this allows claims to be evaluated
immediately during processing.
Model versioning and feature
consistency are also important
for reliable predictions.
These architecture patterns it
really improves the throughput,
reduces manual reviews, and supports
real-time processing requirements.
The concurrent processing also helps
systems to scale more efficiently compared
to the traditional sequential workflows.
The healthcare systems
requires strong reliability.
Features like circuit breakers,
retries, distributed tracing,
and audit logging helps to
maintain stability and compliance.
So these capabilities are very important
in regulated healthcare environments.
And this slide shows the modular
architecture where independent services
communicate through Kafka topics for
scalability and fal-fault isolation.
So each service can scale independently
based on the input over workload.
This solution uses Go for backend
services, Kafka for messaging
Python and TensorFlow for machine
learning, and PostgreSQL with the
Redis for storage and caching.
The key takeaways are move intelligent
intelligence earlier into the workflow.
So to treat EDA as a scalable pipeline and
it-- and design systems for concurrency
and build reliability into every layer.
Thank you everyone for
attending this session.
I hope this presentation provided useful
insights into building scalable AI-driven
healthcare claim systems using modern
EDA pipelines and backend architectures.
Please let me know if
you have any questions.
Thank you