Hello everyone.
thank you for joining me
today in this conference.
My name is S University di
and I'm a senior consultant
systems engineer at Visa.
Today I'm going to discuss on
an important topic on how to
scale FinTech infrastructure that
never experiences the downtime.
As you all know, FinTech operates in
a fast-paced, high stakes environment
where downtime is simply not an option.
Even a few seconds of an unavailability
can lead to a massive financial
losses, regulatory scrutiny,
and more importantly, a dent in
customer trust on the organization.
Okay.
Before, we dive into the, details,
let's go over today's agenda.
In this session, we will explore
best practices, technologies, and
strategies that can help us achieve
zero downtime in FinTech industries.
I. We will start by discussing the
foundations of high availability
and architecture and how it ensures
uninterrupted financial services.
Then we will explore real time
scalability, strategies to
handle peak loads efficiently.
we will then look at disaster
recovery mechanisms and failover
strategies to prevent downtime
during any unexpected failures.
We will then go through security
compliance, which are critical
for any FinTech organization.
So we will discuss how to
maintain both, without sacrificing
on speed and availability.
we will then look into the observability
and instant response, which are
crucial part of any proactive
management of infrastructure.
And we will also cover best
practices in that particular area.
Then we will explore container and cloud
strategies in managing FinTech, workloads.
And finally, we will wrap up this
discussion by, by discussing on the
maintenance strategies, that minimizes the
impact and how to achieve the overall zero
downtime as a core FinTech, objective.
Okay, so the high availability,
is a fundamental requirement
for FinTech companies.
So it ensures that financial,
services remain operational, even
in the face of unexpected failures.
So there are like two main approaches,
to achieving high availability.
One is to have this active setup.
And then the other one is an
active passive architecture.
So coming to an active setup, multiple
systems, like hand request simultaneously
allowing seamless failover in case of an
issue and in an active passive, setup.
One system is kept on standby, which
is more cost effective, but it may
introduce, a small delay during failover.
So the multi-region deployment
ensures like redundancy, or
preventing, localized failures from
affecting the service availability.
we can also use load balancing at
different layers, of the infrastructure
to ensure like the equal distribution
of traffic, is happening and which
will also prevent the overload
on any particular single system.
additionally, We can also configure object
storage applications, which prevents
the data loss and ensures that users can
always, access their financial information
even if there is an event of a failure.
Moving on.
So this slide, discusses the
real time scalability in FinTech.
particularly handles the peak loads during
high traffic events like, stock market
opening, payment processing, spikes,
which happen during your holiday season.
So to, to manage these
searches effectively.
AI driven, predictive, scaling can be
used to analyze, a usage pattern and
then the, and then adjust, resources
proactively before the demand peaks.
There are like two primary scaling
approaches, which access in this
particular infrastructure level.
One is a horizontal scaling,
which involves adding more
service to distribute the load.
the sensors like the systems can
handle increased traffic without,
any performance degradation.
So then we have something called
a vertical scaling, which ensures
that the processing power of an
existing servers is increased.
this increase.
This increases the CPU
and the memory, resources.
Both these approaches are
essential for maintaining the
high availability and performance.
So additionally, we can also deploy
a serverless computing strategy,
which can offer, a cost-effective
solution by dynamically allocating
the resources based on the demand.
So this also eliminates
the, need for, provisioning.
provisioning infrastructure and this
approaches also optimizes the efficiency
and minimizes operational costs.
So there is another approach,
is like implementing the caching
mechanism, such as using a red or a
content delivery networks, which can
primarily improve the response times,
while reducing the backend load.
So these strategies help with
seamless user experiences
during the peak traffic hours.
Okay, moving on.
this slide focuses on the disaster
recovery and the failover mechanisms.
these are the crucial, for
any, for ensuring that the fin
FinTech systems remain resilient
against any unexpected failures.
no system is completely immune to failure.
So making a robust, a disaster
recovery plan is essential to minimize.
minimize the downtime and the data laws.
So one key strategy, is cross
region replication, where backup.
Are stored in multiple, geographical
locations to safeguard any, against any
regional outages and the data, corruption.
So additionally, a multi-master database
architecture, can be deployed, which
can enhance the system reliability by
allow, by allowing the seamless failover.
So in database, node failures, if
any of the database node failures.
Happen, Arthur takes over instantly
and ensuring that uninterrupted,
transaction happen for the customers
to further enhance the resiliency.
Chaos engineering, can be
implemented as a proactive strategy.
So this involves deliberately
like simulating the failures
in a controlled environment, to
identify any vulnerabilities before.
The real incident occurs.
So another critical, measure we
can, deploy is, or, use is to have
the automated, rollback pipelines.
So these, the, so this enables the quick
reversion to the system, state, in case of
failure, reducing the overall d downtime
and maintaining the business continuity.
Now let's go through the
security and the compliance.
security and compliance are
fundamental pillars of FinTech.
So where a breach can be more damaging
than the actual system downtime itself.
So while man, while maintaining the
availability is critical, I. ensuring
the Rob robust security measures is
equally essential to protect the financial
transactions and the customer data.
A zero trust, security, model is
like one of the key approaches
in modern FinTech infrastructure.
So operating under the
principle that no entity.
Internal or external should
be automatically trusted.
So this minimizes the overall
attacks, and enforces, continuous
authentication and verification.
So additionally, encryption, plays
a crucial role in, safeguarding
the overall sensitive financial
data, both at rest and in transit.
Ensuring, information, remains
protected against cyber threats.
So regulatory compliance
with the frameworks like,
G-D-P-R-P-C-I-D-S-S-O-C two is mandatory.
but meeting this requirement should
not come at the cost of performance.
going forward, Advanced security
solutions, must be optimized to ensure
like the regulatory adherence, while
maintaining the high speed transaction
processing to further enhance your
security posture, without showing any down
operations, AI driven fraud detections.
Is an effective way, to deploy.
by analyzing transaction patterns
in real time, AI can detect and
prevent fraudulent, activities,
which allows FinTech platforms
to protect users while ensuring,
like seamless, transaction speeds.
By integrating these, security
and compliance strategies,
FinTech of course, can maintain
a strong security posture without
compromising on security efficiency.
And of course, a user, experience.
Moving on to observability,
observability is a key aspect,
of modern FinTech infrastructure.
So going beyond traditional
monitoring to provide like deep
insights into system performance
and, potential failures unlike, any
conventional approaches that rely.
Only on reactive, troubleshooting
observability enables proactive
issues, detection and resolution.
The foundation of observability is
built on three key pillars, right?
you can have, logs, you have a
metrics, and you have your traces.
So logs will capture the real
time, system, events, metrics,
quantify the performance indicators.
And the trace map, traces map
out the journey of the request
across the distributed systems.
So to, so together these elements
offer a comprehensive view of
system health, making it easier
to pinpoint, any kind of issues.
So leveraging, ai, driven
anomaly detection techniques.
FinTech platforms can identify
performance degradations before
they can impact the actual users.
this also allows like teams to address
any of the concerns proactively.
additionally, predictive analytics can
forecast the potential infrastructure
issues, by analyzing the historical
patterns and then helping to help
to prevent the future occurrences To
further enhance the reliability, ling
mechanisms can be integrated, which
allows like the systems to automatically
resolve minor failures without.
any human interventions.
So during these, manual efforts,
speed, this reduces the manual
effort and then speeds up the,
overall, service availability.
by embracing this availability, like
FinTech companies can strengthen
their instant response strategies,
mitigate risk, before they get
escalated, and then provide
uninterrupted services to the customers.
Okay.
Ization has a, has revolution,
revolutionized the workload
management in FinTech.
So with the, humanities imaging as,
industry standard, due to its and
parallel, scalability, resilience, and
automation, many industries are now
focusing on containerization as a go-to.
strategy.
So by orchestrating the containerized
applications efficiently, so Kubernetes,
like enables, like FinTech platforms
to handle fluctuating demands, while
ensuring like high availability
and security, poster is maintained.
a key advantage of ha
of, deploying Kubernetes.
it has an horizontal pod autoscaling
mechanism, which dynamically adjusts
the resources based on the demand.
this also ensures like the application
scales automatically during
high trans, transaction volumes.
such as Again, market openings or
any kind of, a holiday season, right?
During that time, you can, you can
enable this, HP or the horizontal
port auto scaling feature, that can
ba basically dynamically adjust your.
resources.
Then Kubernetes also offers
a built-in to fall tolerant
and self-healing capabilities.
So if any node, fails workloads or
the parts that are scheduled on that
particular node will automatically
get rescheduled to a healthy node,
which minimizes the downtime without
having a manual intervention.
additionally, you can, have a
role-based, access controls the RAC
policies and network policies, which
enhances the security by limiting
the sensitive financial data.
And then, and critical services
information to unauthorized
users, while stateful, workloads.
such as databases and financial
transactions, present unique challenges
in the Kubernetes, proper configuration
such as stateful sets and persistent
storage solutions ensures like the
stability and the reliability is
achieved within the environment.
So optimizing these Kubernetes techniques,
for FinTech use cases, organizations
can, achieve operational efficiency,
security, and like seamless scalability.
Okay.
Now let's discuss on maintenance
activity and the best practices.
how to use, use to minimize the overall
impact in this particular situations.
So in FinTech industry, maintaining the
system reliability, while minimizing
the impact is critical for ensuring
the seamless financial transactions,
regulatory compliance, and customer trust.
a proactive maintenance strategy is
important, which leverages automated
monitoring tools and, AI driven predict.
analytics to detect and dissolve
potential failures before they affect
the operations so teams can perform,
regular health checks, security
audits, and load testing to further
strengthen their security posture.
to ensure like zero, downtime
deployments, FinTech companies should
adopt like blue green deployments,
cannery releases and feature flagging
techniques, which allows, seamless updates
without even disrupting the services.
and then high availability
is also crucial.
So achieving, through multi-region
deployments, self-healing, infrastructure
and robust, database replication
strategies that provide like automated.
Automated, a failover, in
case of failures, right?
So this can be implemented, to make sure
like how we high availability is achieved.
Then, security and compliance
must be a top priority.
we, with continuous vulnerabilities
scanning, Automated patch management
and strict adherence to the industry
regulations, we can still maintain
that security posture, coming to
the data encryption organization.
further protect, which will
protect the sensitive financial
information from cyber threats.
Database schema versioning is one.
the 10 shows like the
backward compatibility and
preventing the disruptions when
database structures, change.
So equally important is, effective
communication and instant management.
So customers and stakeholders should
receive timely maintenance notifications
while, instant response frameworks such
as, SRE principles or the playbooks.
help teams quickly identify the, the
issue and then mitigate and learn
from those, system disruptions.
So conducting the postmortem
analysis, is very important after
your, after the instance, ensure.
After the incident, which ensures like
the continuous improvements and long-term
stability, by integrating these best
practices, fin FinTech can, achieve a
balanced approach between the continuous
innovation and system reliability,
fostering, customer confidence while
maintaining the regulatory complaints.
Okay, moving on to the next slide.
the goal of the overall goal of
the FinTech is to achieve, the 99
point, however nines, uptime, right?
So which translate to just few minutes of,
downtime by per year, downtime leads to
a financial losses regulatory ities, and
of course, decline in the customer trust.
achieving the zero downtime,
requires a holistic approach.
that includes scalable, architecture,
automated failover, security
compliance, continuous observability
and AI driven automation.
So companies that prioritize
reliability have a competitive edge,
as customers and partners trust them
to, provide uninterrupted services.
So always make sure like
reliability should be.
it should not be just a technical goal.
It is a fundamental pillar
of a FinTech success.
Just to summarize, I think we
have, explored like strategies for
building and, resilient, FinTech
infrastructure, including scalability,
security observability and automation.
we have gone through a security
and compliance, posture, which
must be integrated into every
aspect of infrastructure design.
So finally, I want to thank everyone for
joining me in this particular session.
So I hope you like this session.
Thank you.