Hello everyone.
I'm Andre and I'm here to present,
the Rabbit Hole of Dependency in
Goal and let's slowly get started.
First of all, again, I am Andre.
I am a principles of twin
engineer at Delivery here.
We are using Goal a lot in all of our
services, and I have a lot of examples.
Good and bad, how to work with,
dependencies, and that's why
today I want to show you, some
problems we had in our code base.
So if you want to, contact me and
discuss some of the topics, you can
easily, contact me by any of this.
LinkedIn or, Twitter or Medium, whatever.
Please feel free to reach me out there.
yeah, let's slowly get started.
And first of all, I want to ask
you, can you clearly name couple of
dependencies in your current goal
and project and why do you need them?
Just take your time, think a bit
about this and, the next question
I would like to ask you, can you
clearly the name, couple of indirect
dependencies in your goal and
project, and why do you need them?
Again, take maybe, press some, pause
on the video and think about, but
during the presentation, I would,
ask you now to think about this.
and yeah, but we are going through.
first of all, I prepare a very
simple goal program for you
and yeah, you see it almost.
It doesn't have any dependency.
It doesn't have any glue in the program.
It uses very default print
end and it prints volt.
So if we just take this and compile
our Compile it file will be, or
almost one and a half megabytes.
this sounds decent, is a
B. We in my presentation.
Let's just to use some imports.
Let's import very another very
standard library from their goal.
And it's FMT.
Everyone is using it.
It, I can't imagine any goal and
projects where this is not being used.
So we are using FMT to do the same.
Just to print Hello Vault, and
check how cha how the size of our
application is going to change.
Surprising, surprising.
It's actually changed it, and it is two
more, one more megabyte in the project.
So if you compare, the size of
our application, it's actually
changed it almost in half.
It's plus 50% of compared
to the previous result.
And, why this happens, I will explain a
bit more in the, And let's look, if we
add more dependencies into your code.
So we added in o why we agent, because
we want to read some, we provide in
when we on the program, and maybe I put
them, for example, just put my name.
Hello.
and, if you go into compile this, the
compile it, size of the competitive
program almost doesn't change.
And this is something which,
already should, rings a bell.
What is going on?
Actually, I just edit maybe huge, another
dependency to the code, but actually
it's not reflected in the, application.
Yeah.
And here you can see, if
you compare it was 51%.
Right now it's 53.
But yeah, not the big change, but
the answer, to this, not, this is
not a problem, but answer to this,
puzzle, lies in the FMT library.
If you check FMT Library, you will
find out that, in print go and.
Some other of them you actually
already include in IO and o Libraries.
So this is a hidden dependency
coming this FMT, when you include
it, all of this is actually used.
for example, reflect io.
We are using, I don't know, for output
in your prints to some re writers.
It's very common in GoLink reflect you
might use if you, for example, when
you format it, you want to output the
type of your, variable you providing.
Or if you want to print, some information
about the content of the object, SST Con
we're using to convert integer, or not
only integer, but numbers and into strings
sync is puzzle me why we need sync.
But most probably, it has
some usages in the packages.
And yeah, for sure you have Unicode
because you made play around with Unicode.
So when you include fmt, you also include
a bunch of other dependencies among this.
This is something you need to understand
when you are working this, your program.
So yeah, this is what I already mentioned.
Agent FMT, you bring a lot of hidden
dependencies and this hidden dependencies,
they may have another hidden dependencies.
and we can go into this
rabbit hole very deep.
Maybe I don't recommend, but
yeah, we can do this actually.
So if we, try to do something more
sophisticated or what I wanted
to experiment, I, okay, if I move
my coat to some external library,
how this is going to affect the
size of my package at the end.
So I created external library.
This is.
Of this library and, yeah,
I format it as a library.
I upload to the GitHub and
I imported it in my program.
So it's a simple function,
message, print, and when I compile
it and when I check the size.
The size almost didn't change.
So moving your dependency to a external
library doesn't, bring something
new actually, because you already
have all of this in your program.
So yeah, if you compare
size almost didn't change.
Absolutely the same.
So then the need to ask ourselves a
couple of questions, what if we try
to do something more interesting?
And like we were playing around
with pretty simple quote before
we were just, printing some out.
What if I need to, print out the list
of, S3 buckets I have in my account?
And the quote for this program
will be also very simple,
compared to the previous one.
So we have some external dependencies we
introducing, Some generic library for AWS.
We have sessions because
we need to authenticate.
We have S3 itself, and then we create
in session, we create, a new service.
And the call please lead the packets
and then go in, in the, in the
loop to print all of these buckets.
Very simple quote.
What can go wrong?
nothing can go wrong,
but what will the result?
Let's check what this is a result.
So when we compile our
application, actually the size
of the application jumps a lot.
And this is interesting, thing I
would say because if you compare
like our size of application,
actually increase it by almost 900%.
So these goers here exactly for
completion to show how the size of the
application increasing, so you really
can see it jumped to a bigger number.
So why this happened, if you
ask ourselves, yeah, maybe
this is a huge package.
It has a lot of APIs, it has
a lot of, different objects.
So maybe all of this together
creates a huge, dependency.
Hidden dependency, injecting,
and what I thought.
Okay.
AWS states, for web services, this is
Amazon Web Services, so it means it
has some API and we can call this API
directly, and just get the same result.
For sure.
It has some, complications
about authentication.
We need to sign our request,
but we can figure out this.
So what I did, I just asked
Chad GPT to generate the code.
This code actually work and the
code itself doesn't, that is
not interesting for us at all.
It works.
You can believe.
What is more interested for us
as this list of, dependencies, we
have, so we have a working court,
which can call list of buckets.
without all of these, AWS dependencies,
this is clearly only from the,
default, goal length packages.
So when we compile it, our
size is, has decreased.
It's less, six megabytes less right now.
but still it's eight megabytes.
And the program I was showing before,
it's actually, like hundred lines of code.
It's not something huge.
amount of, dependencies.
We important is also not that huge.
why do we have these, problem these.
Still, I would say inflated
size of the application.
And yeah, you can see
it decrease it a lot.
It decrease it almost 400% compared to
the previous one, but still it's big.
What can we do to solve this problem with
our application or why this happened?
and again, we implemented
only one EPA call.
In our program, and this S3 has multiple
calls, to list object, to add object,
remove object update to get versions.
It's huge amount of API calls.
So maybe the six megabytes we
just, removed from our application.
The six megabytes is, exactly
implementation of this code, but still.
Our application is still big.
It's still big.
if we compare to the previous
one, it was two mega pies.
Right now it's eight.
So these six more megas of the program.
So which of this dependency take, all the.
Credits for being, for abusing,
the size of our application.
So I did another experiment.
I started to remove one by one.
This crypto sounds a
good candidate to remove.
So what I did, I commented code
to still keep, the program they
were can and try to compile.
I did it.
so yeah, I remove it.
Crypto, there is no crypto
independencies anymore and I compile it.
I compiled it, but size of
application didn't change much.
You can see the again,
on the four kilobytes.
okay.
my thought was let's proceed
removing more and let's find out
which one actually is the reason for
this inflated size of application.
So we also remove it, Yeah, there is no
encoding in, our application and run and.
This is not the mistake, actually.
this is two different screenshots,
but unfortunately, there is no effect.
Nothing has changed in our program.
So most probably this accordion comes with
another dependencies, as a hidden one.
So yeah, we need to build the three
of dependencies to understand,
what could be abuser of our size.
yeah, still we have eight megabytes.
Nothing has changed that much, so I
decided to proceed to removing stuff.
So I remove it time library,
and nothing has changed.
Almost.
I remove IO and the same, we
know I already included in fmt.
You not bring anything.
But we have on the FMT Os,
which is also included in the
FMT as a hidden dependency.
And we have net fm, net HT TP.
And what I did next, I created
a simple program using only, net
htt p just to call, random URL.
And yeah, if we compile
it, actually it bring it.
Our application becomes
like five megabytes.
So yeah.
And net HT TP is another very
common library we have in Golan.
maybe 99% of application using it
because we need to communicate our
application with other applications.
So we are using it so it brings
another batch of dependencies and yeah.
And why I'm bringing this, I am for
sure not encourage you to remove all
your dependencies from Sakoda base,
and I'm not encourage you to remove or
implement nett TP on your own to have
zero dependency and very light code.
And, but what I'm trying to say, most
probably you would never, bother yourself
to, Look into size of your application
when you remove something or add
something, and you didn't know that how
many dependencies it brings when you
add a small lever to your application.
And yeah.
And maybe net CDP is not the
biggest one, but this is common one.
And when you add it, you really
don't understand what it brings
to your application amongst
this, what the dependencies of
dependencies go to your application.
And what I want to bring into the
table that when you work with,
in the beef company, for example,
like delivery here or even smaller.
You need some, culture
of dependency management.
If you don't have it,
you can face some issues.
And the second part of my talk will
be, again, exactly about these issues.
We face it in our quarter
basis, couple of times.
And, I mentioned in this slide, yeah, it's
you risk to have very poor code quality.
It doesn't really, go to these bad
things, poor code quality, but it
leads to a lot of technical depth,
which you can remove forever.
Okay, and proceed with my presentation.
I want to give you some small example.
So just imagine you have a
service, some global service.
I call it the STS because this
is common name, around the world.
And, it stays for, service to service
tokens and this service commonly used
in different, ecosystems, to create a
token to, communicate between services.
So let's imagine we have
this global service.
Since this is a global service and
everyone need to adopt it, we also want
to support our teams to not implement the
well every time, but reuse, as something.
So we create some library.
So in different languages,
Java, python, Ruby Rolling.
We implementing some help levers, which
abstract communication or abstract some.
This a P layer for your application.
So some teams just need to plug
and play and use this library.
sounds easy and sounds
like a common sense.
And this is what we're using
in on daily basis all the time.
So we have this service, we have this
library, and we have, service a, this
is just some business, service, which
executes some business and it needs
to use this, service to service token.
So we use this library and yeah,
what I forgot to mention, the
library has version and version one.
This is important, for future.
And yeah, we're using everything works and
then team decides to implement version two
and what they actually do, unfortunately,
and this happens, this happened in my
career couple of times, and in Delivery
Hero as well, guys, implementing new
features and changing the contract.
The change in interfaces.
And this leads to inconsistency and low
record compatibility between version one
and version two, and what happens next?
even if team, of service a, if they want
to migrate to a new version, they would
need to, do some extra effort to do this
migration because interfaces change it.
they need to rewrite some code.
And maybe not in one place,
but in multiple places.
This leads to the case when team
decides to stay with version
one because it works for them.
And in software engineering they have
this proverb, if it works, don't touch it.
So the team is not going to touch it.
It'll stay and they'll not
going to use version two.
And here another problem because,
like teams who create in, these global
services who maintaining the libraries
for these, global services, they
also don't have a lot of capacity.
So they can maintain both versions
simultaneously and usually they
say, okay, this is deprecated.
We are not supporting it.
We'll not implement new features.
We'll not implement security updates.
You all of you should use this
new amazing, shiny version tool.
Okay?
So team of service A stays with this
technical depth almost forever, I would
say, and then happens what happened
in my experience multiple times.
We have another global service.
And, it's a global service doing some
stuff, but, and also another team
decided, okay, to help team needs to
implement this library, to support, easy.
Plug and play, for
other, for our consumers.
Okay.
They did, but they also use
this, service to service token.
And for sure, since they
creating a new service, they're
not going to use old version.
They're going directly with version too.
Which has different interfaces
compared to the version one, and
they starts to create a problem.
If service a wants to use, this service
and they use this library, it may
have some dependency and, dependency
on what is implemented in SDS.
And in this case, when you try
to install the library from the.
another global service.
It won't work.
What it'll tell you.
It'll tell you that, oh, I see,
different implementation or of some
functionality, which has the same name
and it stays for the same, library.
Actually, it'll fail.
And this something what happened,
in my company couple of times.
And this is something,
really huge problem for us.
and if you look what the problems, yeah,
it's hard to maintain multiple versions.
As I mentioned, the team, which created,
this library, they may not have capacity
to maintain version one and version
two and keep different interfaces.
These are hard to push as a
teams to migrate to new version.
As I said, they also don't have
capacity and for them to, assure
their product people that technical
debt is something bad and we need to
migrate, it's usually very complicated.
At some point, the loop will be closed
and you will end up with some services
are not able to use your libraries.
As I mentioned in the, example, Above.
It actually takes a lot of time
to end up to the situation.
This is a problem because
what he described, it didn't
happen in day or week.
It happened during like
year or couple of year.
And then this situation
evolve with evolve.
But you may develop more code
in service A where with this
old dependency to, old library.
And at some point it's.
Super complicated to avoid this
technical debt or get out of it.
You have years of development of on
top of this and it's more and more
complicated to change or write your
pot and it's really requires a huge
investments to fix the problem.
And sometimes people even say, okay, it's
really easy to start a greenfield project
rather than trying to solve it in place.
and yeah, what is the biggest problem,
was in this case I need to mention
because also the team who is maintaining
the library, they did the mistake.
they need to, acknowledge
this and understand, when they
were, create a new version.
What they did, they just said,
okay, we have version two, and
they changed it in version.
So in the same version, it shouldn't be
changes in the contract actually, but
unfortunately the guys did this and, it
created all of these, following, problems.
What they had to do, and usually most
probably working with core programs,
you notice this multiple times.
They had to create kind of separate
folder in their project and call it.
Should have a separate goal mode actually,
then it'll be, use it as a separate
package, and it'll solve the problem.
I described it previously because
if you look at your, go some,
and this is go some from the Real
project, for example, Google, Google.
Has this amount of different,
hidden or indirect dependencies.
Why?
Because, we have dependency, then
we have another dependencies and
we have another hidden dependency.
And it could be different or like
huge amount of layers or dependencies.
And each of them may have their own
go model these, specified versions.
And this can end up, so in this case,
guys was keeping, the contract the
same, maybe adding new features, some,
fixes, but the contract was the same
and did, this didn't break anything.
In our case, the break happened on
the hand then yeah, we can proceed
without code modifications, beef
code, modifications, I would say.
So unfortunately this is very common
example and in my years in the company
I have seen this multiple times
so far for in different projects,
and this happens over and over.
If you go to the next example, I
have these I called helper packages.
This is also very common at some point,
like when our project evolve, we, write
and write in cotton and we find out
we have some common parts we can reuse
and move to the some, common library.
First of all, inside the project for
sure, and we create this helper packages
or it, called, or whatever it may have
different names, but idea the same.
We applying the dry principle and
we, remove duplications of the code.
And in this example, I have package goer.
And I have some helper.
Helper has some random function,
just for this, just example.
and what we decided, okay, we are
going to create another function inside
our go, inside our helper package.
And this, function is going to print
some information about our goer.
So it was going to, just.
Print informatic the name with the
age and position and then, yeah,
we can call it in our main project.
Oops.
Ah, yeah.
we can call it in our main
project and we call it India.
This is how it works.
Unfortunately, place its
slides in the wrong position.
Yeah.
What is the wrong, wrong in this example?
So we have helpers and we have
dependency to the goer object or
another library in our project.
And at some point it can lead
to the situation when, we would
need some helpers from the goer.
Package and then what happens?
We will create a link to their helper
functions here and it'll create
circle dependency infinity loop.
I would say to avoid this, what we
would need to create another helpers.
Let's call it ER helpers, and this
again, duplication of the code.
So we are not solving situation,
we are making it worse.
Oh yeah, this is what I already mentioned.
because when you create the helper,
it's, and when you use a helper from
one library, you, automatically adding
this dependency to the goer package to
all packages where you use it helper.
And this creates some dependency tree,
which at the end could lead you to
the, Dependence, circle or dependency.
Yeah.
In my example, it's like very short pass
to do this, but usually again, it takes
a month, years until you at some point
need touse something from the helper
when you are inside the goer package
and you can't because it doesn't work.
So how to solve it, this is a easy
example and I see such examples.
Everywhere in the code.
this info function should
be part of our object.
It should be met inside our
object, so we can easily access
information from the object.
We even don't need to make this
information public, so it could
be these lowercase name or case
age, and then we can print this
information and this is how it used.
This is better, I would say.
You can argue with me, but
this is better actually.
and as I already mentioned,
this is another problem I
see in our code base a lot.
So people are misconceptions, people
not really thinking in advance and
not applying common sense when they're
moving some parts to the helpers and.
Sometimes they don't see, this
pattern, that these should
be a method of the object.
This shouldn't be
separate helper function.
There is no any reason to have
it as a separate function,
create all of these dependencies.
So going back, I have, no,
not going back, going user.
I have another very common example
related to the helpers because
when you try to apply this.
Right principle.
You try to apply it almost everywhere.
So you start to know, first
of all, you try to remote
applications inside your services.
Then you see that another service, also
has dependency, and you move in already
some applications from different services.
And so on and so forth.
So this is example, we have a service,
a and yeah, at some point we decided
we need to create a helper package
because we have some dependency,
duplications in our code base.
We created helpers.
It work for us perfectly.
but then, We have very similar service, b
with very similar helpers, labor insight.
And then we think, okay, there is no
reason to do modifications in two places.
Let's move out this, package
to some, external one, and
then they're going to reuse.
But here again, we have the
same problem with capacity.
Maybe one team has enough time to
work on the technical debris, removing
these helpers from here or here.
Maybe another team doesn't have
the pen, capacity to do this.
And we end up in situations like
this one service using this helpers.
Another service doesn't do this.
Helpers.
Or maybe even worse.
And this I dislike more, that this
service still has a library with helpers
and some part of the code still use it,
but also we already trying to know to
migrate to the new solution and some
of our, parts of our code using the new
implementation from the external library.
This is a huge problem and because
implementations here may go into
different directions, they may
have similar name of the function
with different implementations and
different behavior, and also with
different vulnerabilities Actually.
But unfortunately this is not the
worst case I have seen in Codebase.
Actually, the worst one is this one.
in this situation we have another
service also implementing this library.
And, for some reason, for example, we
have another, library we are using from
this service, or I don't know, some.
Batch of services.
And then it opens us the door to, use,
helpers from this service as well.
If we embedded it as a, not embedded,
if we use it as a dependency in
service a and then we have, three
dependency with absolutely similar code.
So our principle just fail it.
Drastically failed.
And I want to emphasize
this is the real case.
This is the real case I have
seen on code base couple of
times, which, made me very sad.
Yeah.
And yeah, I. About conclusions.
your team acquires strong
dependency management culture.
Not only your team, it should be
enforce it on the company level.
It should be enforce it on the team level.
You need to work with your product
people to prioritize technical depth
and remove, unnecessary dependencies.
As you remember, I asked you at
the beginning, can you name a
couple of dependencies you have
in your current project, and then
can you name a couple of indirect
dependencies you have in your project?
Hope you can name some of
them actually, but let's go.
you need to commend dependency
policies, so it should be written,
it should be followed by the people.
You should use this guidance to minimize.
And the define what dependencies
are, how they should be used.
You should do regular dependency audit.
you need to update versions.
You need to detect and
fix vulnerabilities.
This is actually a super serious stuff
because you may, use some library in your
code base, which is, indirectly using
another library, having, Vulnerability
and you already expose it to the problem,
because your application could be attacked
and you even don't know why actually.
So please update your versions,
check your vulnerabilities.
There are some tools to do this,
so please follow the best practice
and follow the common sense.
don't skip imports.
During PR review, this is a problem
I, noticed multiple times with guys.
so I mentioned this let go quickly back.
Yeah, the, this slide, this happened
because actually guys were ignoring these
first sections of imports in the program.
They was keeping on what could go
wrong in the imports, but imports was
saying, okay, the new library is going
to be added to your project, and this
library is very different from what you
should use actually, if this won't be.
it'll be solved way before when we face
it, some circle dependencies in our code
base or when, different parts of the
code using look similar, implementation,
but actually implementations
are super different in them.
And yeah, that's all from my site.
I have a couple of slides, so yeah.
we are hiring and if you want
to help me to build, this good,
dependency management culture in
delivery Europe, please join us.
We have couple of, positions in the
company and yeah, if you have any
questions or you want to discuss, this
topic or any other topic, please don't
hesitate to contact me, using any of this.
Or websites and thank you guys.
Have a nice day.
Bye-bye.