Speaker 21: Welcome to my talk on
modularizing a 10-year monolith.
My name is Victor Luboslavsky.
I've been in tech for over 25 years,
and I'm currently a principal software
engineer at Fleet Device Management.
At Fleet, we make endpoint telemetry
for corporate security teams and device
management for corporate IT teams.
In my current job, it took me roughly
a year to figure out the code base, get
familiar with the programming language,
and understand our business domain.
So around that time, I started to
notice a consistent issue whenever
working on our service package.
A package in Go is a compile unit.
This service package was the
biggest one in our code base,
and every time I recompiled its
tests, it took about 30 seconds.
Even changing one character in
a string meant waiting again.
That is a very specific kind of delay.
It's not long enough to switch tasks,
and it's not short enough to ignore.
It just interrupts your thinking.
You wait, your attention drifts,
and then you have to load the
problem in your head again.
And that happens over and over.
When your thinking loop breaks,
you lose context, and getting that
context back is the expensive part.
The wait is not the real problem.
The problem is the
broken train of thought.
So I did a little digging.
The Go programming language is
known for fast compile times.
However, the linking phase of the
compile still occurs largely in series.
In my experiments tracing the build
process, most of that recompile was
stuck waiting for a single thread.
This means if we have a large number of
packages to link together, the linking
phase will dominate the compile time.
From this analysis, the issue was obvious.
Our service package was too big
and had too many dependencies.
So I asked myself a simple question.
What am I actually trying to do here?
I'm not trying to fight a build system
or wrestle with a giant package.
I'm just trying to write good software.
And it shouldn't take 30 seconds
of self-therapy every time
I change a string literal.
What about AI agents?
They aren't as concerned about
waiting 30 seconds for the
code and compile loop, right?
So if I'm using an AI agent, I
can let it handle the coding while
I switch to another task, right?
That doesn't fully solve the problem.
If I need to do a small code change, I
can do it faster than an agent right now.
This means using an AI agent
for some tasks will actually
slow me down even more.
Second, if an AI agent-- second, an
AI agent often runs the test cycle
way more times than a human developer.
And in our case, the
tests are the bottleneck.
So it's arguably even more
important to reduce the compile
time to speed up our AI friends.
So if I just wanna write good
software, what needs to change?
I want a code base that feels light,
understandable, and fast, one that helps
me think instead of slowing me down.
And I realized the only way to get there
was to make the code base itself smaller.
So we tried modularizing.
Next, let's discuss our first
attempt at modularization, where,
as you might guess, things didn't
quite go as smooth as we hoped.
Let's talk about our code base.
Fleet Device Management is
primarily MIT licensed open source.
We also maintain a small set of
advanced features in a clearly separated
directory under a different license.
Our code base is roughly ten years
old with about eight hundred thousand
lines of Go code and growing.
This is a much simplified picture
of the core of our service layer.
We have a su- single huge Go
package for the API layer.
It's our service package.
It includes controllers and the
service containing our business logic.
This API layer calls
the persistence layer.
The persistence layer is
another huge Go package.
It constructs the SQL queries and
executes them against our MySQL database.
We also have an in-memory cache, a React
front end, a CLI, and a bunch of smaller
components which are not pictured here.
So at one of our engineering all hand-
hands meetings, I gave a presentation.
I described how we could scale our code
base to a more modular architecture.
The core idea of my presentation
was that when working on a major
new feature, we could create a
new module, a vertical slice.
This new vertical slice would mirror
the structure of the legacy code.
We would organize it exactly
like the legacy code.
That way, engineers would still
roughly know where things are.
This actually looks exactly
like a microservice, but still
within a single compiled binary.
The presentation seems to land,
and I felt confident enough
to try it on a real feature.
We have some smart engineers
on the team, so I felt like I
was going down the right path.
I did get one question
that I wanna mention.
The question was, "If the team
structure changes, do we have to
redo the architecture?" Maybe.
The boundaries still need to make
sense in the product and the domain,
but they don't need to have a
one-to-one match with the org chart.
A single team can own several slices,
and if that team later splits,
those splice slices can split too.
Shortly afterwards, we started working
on a new feature, and this new feature
seemed like the ideal candidate to
try this new modularization approach.
The feature was Android MDM,
Mobile Device Management.
It meant a new hardware platform for us to
support using a new, for us, Google API.
I created the new structure
for the Android support.
I created new packages
in a dedicated directory.
Most of the work was actually untangling
some common por- parts so they
could be reused between the legacy
code and this new Android feature.
I put up the PR, the pull
request, and it just sat there.
Our guidance is to review and merge
PRs within twenty-four hours, but
no one wanted to touch this one.
In retrospect, I should have done a
better job communicating to the team
that I was actually going to do what
I proposed in my earlier presentation.
Some engineers felt
surprised by the changes.
They didn't feel like they
had a voice in this approach.
They didn't have an
opportunity to speak up.
So facing this resistance, I backtracked.
Let's take a look at these
two MySQL databases down here.
Having two MySQL schemas made
our migrations more complicated.
It also made it impossible to
join tables across schemas.
Even if we put both schemas into the same
physical database, it still would have
made our deployments more complicated.
We'll talk about this later in the
presentation, but at this point in the
story, I decided to take a step back
and unsplit, unsplit the MySQL layer.
So all requests would still
go to the same MySQL schema.
Then I had several lengthy conversations
with my PR reviewer regarding the
overall approach, and after a few more
minor adjustments, we merged the PR.
A few weeks later, we also instituted an
ADR, architecture decision record process.
This mens- this meant I needed to
create ADRs and retroactively get
approval for these architecture changes.
I wrote two ADRs, one to split the API
layer and one to split the persistence
layer of the Android feature.
The ADR to s- to split the API layer
was approved, but the ADR to split
the persistence layer was rejected.
Engineers voiced their concerns, which
included, " We've had this structure for
a while, and people know how it works.
Why do we need this change?
It might confuse and slow people down."
" With separate persistence layers,
it'll be much harder to do database
transactions across two separate modules."
And, "This change is just too big.
Let's try something incremental,
like splitting the API layer only.
We can split the persistence layer
later." Their feedback was consistent.
This felt risky, confusing,
and too big to do all at once.
So I reverted the
persistence layer changes.
The new API layer now talk to the
same large persistence package
as the rest of the code base.
And at this point, I actually
moved off this feature.
I moved to help another product team.
I worked on other parts of the code base,
and other engineers continued to work on
this Android part of the code base We as a
company had a lot of features promised to
our customers, so we were all moving very
quickly trying to get these features out.
But this took a toll on our architecture.
Without architectural oversight,
without a strong commitment from
the engineering team, this Android
feature seeped into the legacy code.
So what do we have now?
The picture shows roughly what we have.
Certainly, at a high level, the code
base doesn't appear to be very modular.
Arguably, it's even more complex and
harder to maintain than it was before.
In practice, there's really no
clear separation between the legacy
code and the Android feature.
But it's not all bad news.
Some positives do remain.
Most Android-specific controllers are
in a separate package, which makes
it easier to change and reason about.
Some Android-specific code is
now isolated, which accelerates
development and testing within
that Android service package.
And not shown here, we did break apart
some common code out of the legacy
service package, which makes it easier
to create new API layers in the future.
Next, let's discuss what we've
learned from our first attempt.
I keep rediscovering that
talking to people takes time,
and there's no shortcut.
Real time.
Meetings, follow-ups, side
conversations, and the bigger the
organization, the slower that loop gets.
We also can't rely on who speaks up first.
Early voices are often smart
and well-intentioned, but
they don't represent everyone.
To build real consensus, we have to
actively solicit feedback, especially
in one-on-ones and smaller forums.
To succeed, we need strong commitment,
both from the engineers and managers,
to the architecture and to the
specific boundaries we are proposing.
Without that commitment, engineers
naturally revert to old patterns and
architectural compromises creep back in.
And without management support,
short-term delivery pressure
wins over long-term structure.
Let's give a small example
of misunderstanding.
In one case, people were
confused about the words.
I was using the term modules.
I was using it in an architectural
sense to mean a cohesive group
of code with a clear boundary.
However, some people thought I was
talking about Go modules, which
is a way to distribute packages
in the Go programming language.
Nobody was wrong.
We just weren't talking about
the same thing, and it took a
face-to-face meeting to sort this out.
We thought the hard part
was the architecture.
It turned out the hard part
were the conversations.
Let's move on to the second lesson.
What is an architectural change anyway?
That sounds like a straightforward
question, but in practice, it
turns out to be one of the most
political questions in engineering.
Here's what we saw in reality.
Architectur- architectural
changes in our code base rarely
showed up as architecture work.
Instead, they went in
as part of feature work.
If you framed your change as part of
feature work and included it in a PR with
other feature changes, it moved, even if
it broke existing architectural patterns.
After all, we needed to get all
the feature changes in quickly.
Features are what make
money for the company.
But if you framed your change
as a standalone architectural
improvement, it stalled.
It stalled because it was
prioritized behind feature work.
It stalled because engineers wanted
to have bigger discussions around it.
It stalled because it wasn't providing
immediate value to the company.
So what's the main lesson here
about architectural changes?
If you don't define how your architecture
is allowed to change, it changes anyway,
and often it changes behind your back.
Let's move on to the third lesson.
One thing we were missing
was clear ownership.
In a modular system, not
every API endpoint belongs
cleanly to a single service.
Some endpoint mostly orchestrate
work across multiple services.
That was true for us because this
new Android function- functionality
still needed to talk to legacy code.
The mistake was leaving
this orchestration unowned.
Every API endpoint still needs a
clear home, a specific module, and a
specific team that's responsible for it.
Even if the endpoint is just glue,
someone has to own that glue.
So where are we at this point?
The first attempt didn't quite succeed.
We still have the pain points of a
large, tightly coupled code base.
But hopefully, we learned a few things.
We now have experience.
So where do we go from here?
At this point, I realized the
importance of the people part in
architecture, and I felt like I
couldn't convince the company on my own.
I still didn't feel like
an architecture expert.
The first attempt was a mess, so
why would other engineers take my
next proposal seriously and not
see it as just another crazy idea?
I needed someone else's help.
I needed something like
an appeal to authority.
I needed to find someone else that had
already done this transition, and I needed
to analyze the way they approached it.
Unfortunately, I did not find any
large open source Go projects making
a transition to a modular monolith.
As far as I know, we're the first large
open source Go project doing this.
Yay us.
The next best reference was GitLab.
GitLab runs a Ruby on Rails
monolith with over two million
lines of code maintained by a large
distributed engineering organization.
They faced the same decision we
were facing, whether to break
everything into microservices
or find another way to scale.
They deliberately chose
a modular monolith.
GitLab publicly documented this decision,
and their motivation was practical.
They wanted to avoid the operational
complexity of microservices,
and they wanted to keep the code
base approachable for engineers.
And they wanted to use clear domain
boundaries to scale development safely.
Their example showed that modularity
and scale don't require microservices.
And to us, it showed that
a large successful team had
already walked this same path.
And it turned my proposal from a
crazy idea into a proven pattern.
We weren't trying to invent something new.
We were trying to follow a
trail that was already there.
Internally, that changed the conversation.
Before that, the conversation
kept circling about whether this
was too unusual, too risky, or
too academic for our code base.
GitLab gave us a reference point
that was concrete, public, and
large enough to be taken seriously.
It didn't answer all of our questions,
but it changed the burden of proof.
I no longer had to argue that
modularization was some novel idea or
personal preference we should gamble on.
I could point to a real company with a
larger monolith than ours that had already
made this same bet for practical reasons.
Next, we had to decide where to start.
This time, there was no obvious
feature to use as an anchor.
So we had a series of discussions
with the engineering team.
We aligned on bounded context and
domain-driven design in principle.
The hard part was choosing
that first boundary.
I looked at our code organization
and had a few conversations with my
AI agent friend and proposed several
ways we could slice the monolith.
As you can imagine, this whole process
was a lot to get your head around,
trying to tease apart a 10-year-old
system into self-contained modules.
I felt like I was barely
scratching the surface.
I felt like I was surely missing
a lot of details and edge cases.
There were a lot of unknowns.
Starting our modularization
effort with anything beyond
the bare minimum seemed risky.
All the engineers generally agreed that
we wanted to do an incremental approach.
So we ultimately agreed on this
activity and audit over here.
This content is- context is
about recording things that
already happened in our system.
For example, recording when a new user
was created, when a new host enrolled,
when a key configuration was changed,
and a ton o- of other activities.
Next, I wrote up a detailed
architectural decision record and
put it up for review by the team.
Here's the link in case someone
can't wait to dive into the details.
Again, this ADR was framed as a pilot.
This is the first bounded context we
were creating before a bigger rollout.
The ADR was up for review for a while.
We discussed it multiple
times in multiple meetings.
For me, I just wanted to start
coding, so I felt quite uncomfortable
to be stuck in that waiting limbo.
Instead, I got another lesson regarding
the importance of interpersonal
skill in software architecture.
Most of the feedback I got was good.
We have very smart
engineers, and that showed.
What made it hard wasn't bad feedback,
it was the volume of it and the timing.
Sometimes feedback came faster I-
than I could realistically absorb.
"Have you checked in with so and
should we run an event storming
session? Can you do this other thing?"
All reasonable suggestions, all
well-intentioned, but they added weight.
Then a few times, the
feedback landed late.
Things like, "Whoa, can we step back
and think about the bigger picture?"
That's an important question, it just
would have been easier earlier in the
discussions before trying to slice up
the monolith, before the ADR went up.
At that point, we were already six
weeks in, momentum was building, and
it felt like being asked to rewind.
This ended up being a good exercise
in patience, mostly for me.
Often, my best response was, "Okay, that's
interesting. I'll think about it," then
take a break, calm down, and come back
to the feedback in a better head space.
Several times, I wondered where this
whole thing was gonna go anywhere.
Sometimes it felt like
everyone was on board.
Other times, it felt like I
kept running into a brick wall.
It felt like I kept bringing
people along with the plan, and
then they slowly drifted away.
It felt like I kept grabbing people
to get them on my side, and then
they slipped out of my hands.
I also felt I was deep in the weeds
and details of this re-architecture.
I didn't quite see the full picture
myself, and I had a suspicion
other engineers didn't either.
I actually needed to convince myself and
others why we were actually doing this.
I needed an argument, and I needed to use
it not just once, but every chance I got.
That's when I finally started to
understand that old management maxim.
By the time you're tired of saying it,
people are just starting to hear it.
This picture is from
the 1970 movie Pattern.
So here, roughly, is my
argument for the team.
Yes, this is a brief talk
I've given to the team.
It's supposed to be somewhat
motivational in nature.
All right, team.
Here's why we're doing this.
Our backend is around 800,000 lines of Go.
That number by itself is not the problem.
The problem is what it does
to day-to-day engineering.
At this size, you stop working
in clean, isolated areas of code.
More and more often, different teams end
up in the same database tables, the same
service layer, the same shared logic.
GitLab, Shopify, and others have written
about these scaling issues publicly.
We're seeing this same
pattern in our own codebase.
First, teams start
colliding with each other.
We've already had cases where two
groups changed the same tables or the
same service code without realizing
how tightly connected those areas were.
The cleanup took days.
Not because anyone was careless,
because the boundaries were
weak, the ownership was blurry.
When that happens, the cost
is not just merge conflict.
It is rework, regressions, and
time spent figuring out who is
actually responsible for what.
Second, the cost of a small
change keeps going up.
When packages depend on too much
around them, even a modest change
pulls in unrelated context.
Reviews get slower, testing gets
noisier, the chance of side effects
goes up, bugs become harder to isolate.
At some point, the system is
no longer difficult because
one part is especially complex.
It is difficult because too many
parts are connected to each other.
That is the problem
modularization is meant to solve.
Not elegance, not trend
following, containment.
Smaller areas of code, clear ownership,
fewer reasons for different teams
to touch the same lines of code.
If a team can make a change without
loading half the system into their heads,
they move faster and with less risk.
That is the outcome we want.
So this is not architecture
for its own sake.
It is a response to cost
we're already paying.
Bug escapes, long reviews, features
taking too long to land, and
fixes that need follow-up fixes.
We can keep treating those as
separate incidents, or we can
admit that the structure of the
system is part of the problem.
That is why we're doing this.
Our code base is 10 years old, and we
expect it to be around a lot longer.
This work is about making sure the code
base helps engineers build instead of
getting in their way, not by rewriting
the system, not by breaking into the
microservices, by introducing boundaries
we can actually maintain as the product
and the company continue to grow.
And end scene.
Now, let's talk about
the actual architecture.
The high-level idea is almost the same as
where we started with the first attempt.
The new feature or new bounded
context will be in its own
module with its own controller,
service, and persistence layers.
The controllers and services will
be able to call methods on other
services in other bounded contexts.
However, they will not be able
to access the persistence layer
of another bounded context.
In practical terms, that means a
bounded context can call another context
public service API, but it cannot
reach into that context data store
just because that would be convenient.
Once one context starts reading
or writing another context tables
through its internal persistence
code, the boundary is mostly gone.
At that point, the ownership looks
clean in the directory structure, but
not in the behavior of the system.
Here's the directory layout of the
bounded context, and we'll bring up
this slide a couple times later as well.
So the service and MySQL
directories over here match the
API layer and the persistence
layer from the previous diagram.
The integration test over here should
be able to fully test this bounded
context without requiring parts
from the rest of the application.
Now, testing this bounded context with
other bounded context will be done
at a higher-level integration test.
Another detail that mattered is what
the bounded context does not own.
It does not own authentication
or authorization, for example.
Those are injected from the outside.
Authentication comes in as
middleware at the HTTP layer.
Authorization comes in as a
dependency the service can call
but does not implement itself.
That separation kept the context
focused on its own domain instead
of absorbing cross-cutting concerns
just because they were already
present elsewhere in the monolith.
Now, let's talk about the decision
not to split the database schema.
When people hear modular
monolith, they often assume
that means multiple databases.
We deliberately did not do that.
We kept a single schema.
Our problems weren't database scale
or load, they were unclear ownership,
broad service layers, and code
that was too hard to reason about.
Splitting the database
wouldn't have fixed that.
It just would have made operational
complexity Added operation
complexity and new failure modes.
Splitting a database is also one of the
most expensive architectural decisions
you can make, and it freezes boundaries.
We were still learning where those
boundaries should be, so we modularized
the code first, preserved optionality,
and decided we'd only split the database
later if scaling actually required it.
Now, everywhere we turned, we heard
recommendations to use ports and adapters.
However, a lot of our business logic
lives in SQL, so pretending a database is
just an adapter didn't make sense for us.
Ports and adapters doesn't work for our
whole sys- our system as a whole, but
one idea from it fits extremely well.
That idea is that bounded contexts do
not share the main models directly.
Any cross-context communication must
go through an explicit owned contract.
In practice, that means
explicit module boundaries.
Earlier, I talked about how we
ended up with large packages.
When the shared common package is
used for cross-context communication,
it creates a specific problem.
When two bounded contexts
share the same common types,
they're no longer independent.
A change in one context silently
changes the behavior of the other.
At that point, the boundary only
exists in our heads, not in the code.
For cross-context communication,
shared packages aren't reused.
Instead, they're hidden coupling.
That's why we require explicit owned
contracts at context boundaries.
So when one bounded context
needs something from another, it
doesn't reach into the internals.
Instead, the providing context exposes
a small explicit interface along with
the types that belong to this interface.
Those interfaces and types
are owned by the provider.
They live with the bounded context,
and they evolve on its terms.
Other contexts can depend on the
contract but not on the implementation.
That is what makes the boundary
real in code, not just in our heads.
Now, sometimes, a new bounded
context still needs data or
behavior that lives in legacy code.
In those cases, we don't let the
new code talk to legacy directly.
Instead, we introduce an anti-corruption
l- corruption layer, or ACL.
The ACL is the only place
that understands both worlds.
It translates legacy concepts,
types, and quirks into something the
new context can work with safely.
Now, notice that this ACL package is
outside the new bounded context, so that
keeps the legacy semantics from leaking
into the new code, and it gives us a
clear seam we can replace or delete later.
The goal of this ACL isn't
elegance, it's containment.
Now, let's continue with the story.
Before we changed any code, we
had one big concern, buy-in.
We didn't want this to feel like another
harebrained idea Victor came up with
and everyone else has to live with.
If this were going to work, our
software engineers needed to feel
like the end result was theirs.
Not something imposed, not
something slipped in quietly,
something they actually owned.
We left this ADR open for
discussion for about four weeks.
That was longer than any
ADR we'd done before.
We wanted time for people to
read it, question it, disagree
with it, and sit with it.
The goal wasn't fast approval.
The goal was shared understanding.
Next, we made a deliberate
decision about reviews.
Every pull request related to this
ADR would be reviewed by the four
tech leads from each product group.
They did two things.
First, it made sure they were
generally on board, the tech leads.
Second, it meant their teams were
represented, not surprised later.
Surprises are great for
birthdays, not for architecture.
Architecture stopped being something
decided by one person and started being
something carried by the organization.
We also didn't want the
implementation to be rushed.
The stories tied to this ADR went
through a normal design and spec process.
And finally, we created a single
central page that tracked the
status of all of this work.
Anyone could see what was done, what was
in progress, and what was coming next.
That visibility was important
because it turned a potentially risky
architectural shift into a series
of small, understandable steps.
At this point, it might seem like we
were putting a lot of process in place.
Probably sounds like we were
saying, we need to have everything
figured out before we even start.
And to be honest, that
felt a little backwards.
This is the first bounded context,
and it was supposed to be a pilot and
not a well-engineered masterpiece.
And a pilot is supposed to discover
things, which means sometimes taking
a step forward only to backtrack
when things aren't working.
If we already had all the answers, if
we were able to lay out all the steps
in this refactoring top to bottom,
then we wouldn't need a pilot, right?
This means we needed to do a POC,
a proof of concept, to discover
things that we didn't know about.
This was great for me.
I love coding and I love POCs.
The aim of the POC was to discover
things like which packages were
coupled, which patterns to use where.
Do we use shared objects?
Do we use interfaces?
Do we use async events?
How will the communication between
bounded contexts actually look like?
In order to make a plan,
we needed to know the path.
So I started with a proof of concept.
Not a full implementation,
just a scaffold.
The idea was simple.
Create some basic shape
of a bounded context.
This means using some shared
utilities for HTTP, some middleware,
basic MySQL access, nothing fancy.
Just enough structure for
a hello world endpoint.
Then I ran a dependency analysis, and
that's where things got interesting.
That simple scaffold was
pulling in half our monolith.
Not because this domain needed it.
This hello world domain of the
scaffold didn't need anything yet.
But because all of these
utility packages did.
The glue code was the monolith.
The things we thought were
harmless helpers were actually
acting like dependency magnets.
And there's another issue
hiding in plain sight.
A god package.
Anytime someone needed a new type and
didn't know where it belonged, it went
into this fleet package at the bottom.
And over time, that large fleet package
picked up its own dependencies, which
were not shown in the previous slide.
Otherwise, that slide would blow up.
That meant everything that
imported it picked those up too.
This made circular dependencies
incredibly easy to create and
incredibly hard to understand.
That fleet package existed
to make things easier, but it
ended up doing the opposite.
At that point, it became clear.
We couldn't just extract a
bounded context right away.
We were missing a layer.
Before we could pull anything
out, we needed the platform layer.
Code that handled infrastructure
concerns, HTTP helpers, database
wiring, middleware, without dragging
domain assumptions along with it.
We needed to differentiate
between two types of code.
We needed domain code that should express
business rules and then platform code that
should make those rules possible to run.
So just to clarify, we do want
modules to reuse common code.
We don't want every bounded
context team reinventing HTTP
helpers or database plumbing.
But reuse without
boundaries creates coupling.
And coupling was the thing
we were trying to escape.
Before we could modularize the domain,
we had to modularize the foundation.
Another issue we had to solve from our
first attempt was that even with good
communication, even with ADRs, even with
documentation, even with buy-in, nothing
stops coupling from sneaking back in.
Especially in a large code base, and
especially nowadays when changes aren't
only written by humans, but also by AI
coding agents that optimize for make
it work and not preserve architecture.
Architecture that lives only in
people's heads doesn't scale,
and it doesn't survive time.
That's why we realized we needed
architectural checks, automated checks
that run continuously, checks that don't
care who wrote the code, human or AI.
Specifically, we needed checks to
enforce boundaries, which packages
can depend on which, what the platform
layer is allowed to know, what a bounded
context is not allowed to import.
Because once those rules are explicit,
they stop being simply opinions.
They become executable.
I try to read a lot of books,
and this is one of them.
This-- There's a term for this
in Building Evo-Evolutionary
Architectures by Neal Ford and others.
They call these checks
architecture fitness functions.
The idea is this: if an architectural
property matters, like modularity
or oscillation or direction of
dependencies, you should be able to test
it, not just once, but continuously.
If the test fails, the
architecture failed, even if
all other unit tests are green.
All right.
All of this tooling is important.
Next, let's talk about what
we learned from the pilot.
All right.
We completed the pilot.
Not a proposal, not a design, actual code
running in production with real usage.
A single bounded context, activity audit,
extracted from a ten-year monolith.
Great.
At that point, it stopped
being a question of intent.
We could actually look at the results.
And the answer is, it worked.
Not in a clean, predictable
way we imagined at the start.
It validated the direction, and it also
exposed a lot of things we didn't expect.
Some parts become simpler, some
parts became clearer, and some parts
became more complicated, which is
exactly what you want from a pilot.
Not confirmation, but reality.
What changed most was the discussion
stopped being theoretical.
We were no longer debating whether bounded
context could exist in this code base.
We had one.
We could look at the package boundaries,
the imports, the tests, the CI
workflow, the dependency wiring.
That shifted the conversation.
The problem was no longer
is modularization possible?
Problem became, what patterns actually
hold up when you do it for real?
One of the more interesting
outcomes was bugs.
Refactoring did not just reduce risk,
it revealed risk that we already had.
As we pulled the activity context
apart from the monolith, we
started seeing assumptions- That
had never been made explicit.
Rules that existed in our documentation,
but not consistently in code.
Edge cases that had been
hidden inside legacy flows.
In one case, we found we were violating
rollback access control rules, RBAC,
that we had publicly documented.
In another, we found an edge
case that cut against our claims
of visibility and transparency.
A canceled operation could end up
deleting past activity record, including
who requested that original operation.
And those were not new
bugs created by the pilot.
They were old bugs that became easier
to see once the boundaries were clearer.
That was one of the strongest signals that
this refactor was doing something real.
It was not just moving files around.
It was forcing the system to say more
precisely what the behavior actually was.
Another strong signal that this approach
works came from something ordinary.
This internal package, internal directory.
Code outside that bound- boundary
simply cannot import the implementation.
The boundary is this whole directory,
the se- service activity directory.
So in Go, internal is
enforced by the compiler.
If you could put code inside
it, nothing outside this part
of the code base can import it.
No conventions, no code review
rules, no "Please don't do
this," it just fails to compile.
Why I bring this up is because a
lot of architectural boundaries
are softer than they look.
They depend on engineers remembering
the rules, reviewers noticing
violations, and everyone continuing
to agree on the structure.
Internal removes that
entire class of failure.
It means another bounded context cannot
reach into your service implementation
just because it's convenient.
It cannot pull your MySQL layer directly.
It can't quietly start
depending on internals that
were supposed to stay private.
The compiler stops it, and in a large
code base, that's a big difference.
At that po- point, the boundary is
no longer just something written
in an ADR or drawn on a slide,
it is part of the program itself.
You can't cross it accidentally.
Another pattern that proved useful
was the bootstrap layer over here.
Each bounded context has a single
entry point, a bootstrap.new function.
That's the only place where
dependencies are wired together.
From the outside, you don't see the
internal structure, you don't know
about the database implementation of the
service internals, you just get a fully
constructed Bounded context service.
That sounds small, but it
simplifies a lot of things.
Testing becomes easier, integration
becomes predictable, and r- it reinforces
the idea that a bounded context is a
unit, not just a collection of packages.
It gives us one consistent way to
instantiate the bounded context
in both production and tests.
That was a bigger deal than I expected.
Without a single composition
root, dependency wiring tends to
spread across the cal- codebase.
Different entry points start assembling
slightly different versions of the same
thing, and then it becomes harder to tell
whe- whether different environments are
really exercising the same code path.
Keeping that wiring in one place
removed a lot of that ambiguity.
We introduced an anti-corruption
layer between the new context
and the legacy system.
Now, we covered this part earlier,
and this was the first time we
applied it in this codebase.
With the ACL, those calls moved
behind a single interface.
That interface listed exactly what the
new bounded context depended on, right?
We could point to methods, not
categories or concepts, actual functions.
Most of them already existed in a legacy
system, but we also had to add a couple
new methods to support this interface.
That addition was useful.
It forced us to be explicit
about a dependency that would
have otherwise stayed implicit.
At that point, the ACL became
easier to reason about.
If you want to understand how this
context interacts with the rest of the
system, you just read this interface.
And it also gives us a
simple way to track progress.
Every method in this ACL is a
dependency on the legacy system.
Fewer methods means less coupling.
More methods means the
boundary still needs some work.
That interface gave us a much
clearer definition of done.
The goal was not to build an
impressive ACL, the goal was
keep that interface narrow.
If the activity context needed five
or six methods from legacy code, fine.
If it kept growing, that was a signal.
Either the boundary was wrong or
we were still dragging too much
of the monolith through that seam.
In that sense, the ACL was not just
a bridge, it was a measurement point.
We also changed how CI, continuous
integration, works for this code.
Instead of running everything on every
change, the activity context has its
own workflow, its own CI workflow.
It only runs when files
in that context change.
That had an effect on both sides
of the system For the new bounded
context, the signal is clear.
If something fails, it is in
the activity-bounded context.
There's no ambiguity about where to look.
For the legacy code base, it also helped.
We removed activity-related tests from
the main test suite, so the remaining
tests run slightly faster, and there's
less noise from unrelated failures.
That separation is small but
noticeable, and more importantly,
it reflects the architecture.
The code is split, and now the
feedback loops are split as well.
That sounds operational,
but it changed behavior.
When the team sees a failure tied
to its own context, ownership is
clear, and when unrelated failures
stop showing up in the same workflow,
people spend less time triaging noise.
The architecture becomes visible
not just in the code layout,
but in the daily developer loop.
We also added architecture tests.
They define which packages
are allowed to import which.
Each bounded context has an allow list.
If a package pulls in something
outside that list, the test fails.
That check runs in CI
just like any other test.
So if someone or an AI agent
introduces a new dependency across
a boundary, it shows up immediately.
There's no need to catch it in
a review, and it doesn't rely
on people remembering the rules.
The constraint is in the code.
Taken together, internal, the ACL,
the bootstrap layer, the dedicated
CI workflow, and the architecture
tests did something important.
They turned the bounded context from
simply a clean directory structure
into something we could enforce,
test, and operate separately.
That is a much stronger result
than, "The code looks nicer." But
it's important to be clear about
what this pilot did not solve.
We did not modularize the system.
We modularized a small part of it.
Most of the monolith is still there.
Most boundaries are still undefined.
We still have shared concepts
that don't map cleanly to a single
context, and we still have open
questions about how these contexts
will interact as the system grows.
So this is not a finished architecture.
It is a validated direction.
Where we are now is
somewhere in the middle.
We've completed one bounded
context, and now we're figuring
out how to do the next ones.
The next likely candidates are
user management and certificate
management, and those are harder.
Activity was a good pilot because
it was more self-contained.
User management and certificate management
sit closer to the center of the system.
They touch more workflows, more
teams, and more legacy code.
So the next phase is not just repeating
what we already did, it is applying
the same ideas in parts of the
monolith where the boundaries are less
obvious and the coupling is heavier.
But the uncertainty is different now.
We're no longer asking
whether this can work.
We've seen it work.
Now the problem is scaling it carefully
without breaking what already exists.
All right.
Let's circle back to the core
problem we're trying to solve.
Looking back, the real
constraint wasn't Go.
It wasn't MySQL.
It wasn't even the monolith.
The real constraint was human attention.
How much of the system can
one people hold in their head?
How much confidently
can they make a change?
And how much unrelated context they
have to load just to get started?
Once a system grows beyond that
limit, progress slows, no matter
how good the engineers are.
We often talk about architecture
as if it's for computers.
But computers don't care
how big your code base is.
Humans do.
Architecture is really
an interface for people.
It defines what you need to understand,
what you can safely ignore, and
what you're allowed to change.
When that interface is unclear,
every change feels risky.
When it's clear, people move
faster, even in a large system.
The tricky part is that this
problem shows up after success.
The monolith works, the product
ships, customers are happy, and
slowly, almost invisibly, the
system becomes harder to change.
We're not fixing a broken system.
We're fixing a system that
worked until it didn't.
That's why these conversations are
hard, and that's why they matter.
We knew our system had grown too complex.
Not complex in an abstract
sense, complex in a human sense.
It had grown beyond what a human
brain could comfortably hold.
Every small change required
understanding too much at once.
At that point, adding rules or
documentation doesn't fix the problem.
You have to change the
shape of the system.
For a long time, I thought the hard part
was architecture, or code, or tooling.
It wasn't.
The hardest part was
alignment with other humans.
Shared language, shared
understanding, shared ownership.
Code changes fast, especially
now with AI agents.
Architecture survives only when
people agree to carry it together.
We don't have a clean ending.
The work is still moving.
Boundaries are still being uncovered.
Edge cases are still surfacing.
But something important has shifted.
The system is starting to feel smaller,
more defined, easier to follow.
And for the first time in a long
time, the code base is helping us
think instead of getting in the way.
So if there's one thing I hope you
take away from this talk, it's this.
Modularization isn't really about modules.
It's about respecting the
limits of human attention.
It's about designing systems
that people can understand,
trust, and change without fear.
Tools matter, patterns matter, but
architecture lasts only when it's
owned by more than one person.
That's it for this talk.
If this resonated with you, I'd
be interested to hear from you.
How are you approaching similar
problems in your own systems?
Details are different, but
the patterns usually aren't.
Here's a few links to Fleet, my company.
This QR code goes to our webpage.
We are hiring developers, Go developers.
And then you can, there's
links, you can find me.
Feel free to connect with me on LinkedIn.
Thank you for listening.