Hi, all greetings.
thanks for joining with
me for this session.
Artificial Intelligence for the
Life Sciences and the Salesforce
benefits for the CTMS system.
To introduce myself, I am ula a software
professional with the 17 years of
experience in the IT industry, and my
field of expertise is a cloud computing
digital transformation document management
with a focus on artificial intelligence
with generated AI capabilities.
Artificial intelligence is
revolutionizing in the life
sensors industry and generative.
A automates the creation of the
regulatory documents, reducing the
administrative burden, and ensuring
the compiling the generative.
A also enhances the workflows
efficiency by securely.
Connecting the Salesforce data
with the large language models to
create a relevant customized report.
Salesforce also emerged as a pivotable
force in this transformation, introducing
sophisticated solutions that fundamentally
reimagined that rail operations across the
patient recruitment and the supply chain
optimization and the data management.
And the, finally, the healthcare head
cp, the integration, this presentation.
Explores how the integration of
the advanced remission learning
algorithms, the natural language
processing and predictive analysis.
The predictive analysis has a
fundamentally changed how the trails has
been redesigned, executed the monitored,
addressing the critical challenges,
enhancing the patient engagement, and
reducing the operational cost, and
maintaining the quality standards.
The impact on, the impact of, AA on, CTMS
is like, enrollment pattern prediction,
error reduction, and subject MA matching
the enrollment pattern prediction.
The mission learning algorithms
have demonstrated a remarkable
accuracy in predicting the subject
enrollment patents while reducing
the site collection timelines by.
40% through the automated data analysis.
This technology advancement has proven
the, particularly the crucial as the
industry grapples with the increasing
the trail complexities and raising
the operational cost and coming
to this error, reduction traction.
The AA power, trail management
systems has achieved a major
reduction in data entry errors under
decreased protocol deviation rates.
Above 50% across the phases between
like first phase to second phase
and third phase of the trail.
The platform predictive analysis
capabilities have revolutionized the
site collection process with the machine
learning models, analyzing over thousands
of variables simultaneously, and the
subject matching the Salesforce AI driven.
Patient matching algorithms process
electronic health records above
90% specificity in identifying
the eligible trail candidates.
And this sophisticated matching
resulted in reduction of the screen
failures, rates and above percentage
improvement in the patient retentions
and the operational excellence
and operational excellence
through the Salesforce.
Yay.
In this section, we'll deal about this
instant analytic integration and workflow
optimization and patient experience.
Instance, a instance, a power analytics
have demonstrated nearly 50% of reduction
in the trail timeline deviations while
improving the outcome prediction accuracy
while across the phases of, from the
phase two, two, phase four trails.
And this platform has
also predictive, analysis.
For the trail outcomes and have
achieved high accuracy rate forecasting
the steady completion timelines
while reducing the operational in.
Inefficiencies workflow optimization.
Workflow is nothing but like the task and
how this automated task is helping the
CTMS system and the workflow Automation.
workflow optimization features have
improved the resource utilization by 50%
while reducing the manual task processing
time and the real time performance
monitoring capabilities continuously
analyze over thousands of metrics per
site, identifying the potential issues.
Patient experience enhancement.
The implementation of 24 7, yay.
Power, patient support has
increased the patient satisfaction.
Crosses for above 50% while
reducing the average query
responses from hours two minutes.
And this is a big drastic change from,
for the patient experience enhancement
as it is changing the response
time from the hours two minutes.
This intelligence support system
successfully manages the subject
inquiries automatically and
maintaining a participation participant
satisfaction rate above the 90%.
Apart from this, the Salesforce AA
also helps the, the business users in,
drafting the subjects and the sites
through the instate and the automated
AA capabilities in the CTMS system, and
as well as in the Salesforce CRM system
data management.
And.
And this data management and the compiles
are the very, the crucial steps in the, in
any industry, and particularly it's very
important in the life sensors industry.
And here in this, in this section,
we'll talk about the security
framework and the threat detection
and the natural language generation.
This, this a has the capability as we
have seen in many ways, like it enhances
the system and again, reduces the time
and how it is helping the business
users in the real time scenarios.
But however, still we, we have, we
had a thoughts of like how it'll
handle the security framework
and threat detection and through
the natural language generations.
Yaya public, data protection systems has
demonstrated about 90% of the accuracy
rate in identifying the potential.
Security vulnerabilities
while processing an average of
million data points per study.
And these studies are very important,
and this and the security of the
framework needs to be maintained
at high vulnerability date.
So this AI powered data protection
systems will help, will help in
demonstrating about 90% of the accuracy
rate and, the platform automated it.
H-I-P-A-P compiling, monitoring
systems, that has assured ac
accuracy rate in detecting the trail
violations and the threat detection.
And this place a, plays a important role
in the, data management and the compiling
section and the realtime security
threat analysis capabilities process.
Approximately hundreds of thousands
of security events per second.
This, AA has a capability and it has a
sophisticated system that successfully
prevented unauthorized access,
incidents while maintaining an average
response, time to just a milliseconds
for threat detection and mitigation.
And this is the greatest achievement,
that we can see from the AA power.
And a language natural
language generation.
The system achieves about 95% accuracy
rate in this section by in generating
the standard clinical trail reports
while reducing the documentation time
by half compared to the manual process.
And implementing of NLG, which is also
like a natural language generation
technology, which has excelled in
reg regulatory submission process.
Automating about 70% documentation task
while reducing the, preparation time
and intelligent subject
recruiting and matching.
This plays a very important
role in the life sciences.
especially for the CTMS systems
when we are working with the CTMS
systems and how this a will help us
in subject recruiting and matching.
The first one is, comes as like the
recruitment transformation, the recruit.
The second one is like a EHR integration.
The third one is the predict two analysis
will go one by one and how it is.
Helping the CTMS system and how the
Salesforce is directly impact on CTMS
system and how it is getting benefited for
the, subjects and as well as the business
users Recruitment, transformation.
The, a driven recruitment strategies
have a two, a reduction in the subject
identification time, and while maintaining
the accuracy, while maintaining the
accuracy rate in matching the patients.
Patients to appropriate trails.
The traditional recruitment, where the,
without, without aid driven approaches,
the manual approaches and the traditional
follow approaches, methods that
typically result in just a very minimal
of, eligible patients being enrolled.
And it was like really challenging
for the life census industry domain
way to match with this, recruiting
process of the transformation like this.
E with the help of this yay driven
under the Salesforce EAA and this
met, this, a preferred approaches
increases this rate to 18 to 20%.
It is just like the.
Or five times more than that of the
manual, traditional, recruitment
methods and EHR integrations.
EHR is nothing but like the electronic
health record, things and how this are
integrated with the CTMS system and
with the Salesforce, the CRM and the
document management and how the Salesforce
AI is helping this, EHR integration.
The natural language processing
algorithms have demonstrated about
90% accuracy in extracting the
relevant clinical, information from
the unstructured medical records.
It is always a challenging to, to get the
information from the unstructured medical
records, with the a, a, with the aa.
and this can be p and this can be.
A hundred percent possible and we can
achieve 90% of accuracy in extracting
the relevant, clinical information
from this unstructured medical records.
The artificial intelligence facilitates
seamless data exchange between the
different, different EEHR systems.
re it means like the breaking down
of the data sales, and enabling the.
Comprehensive patient insights
and the intelligent subjects
recruitment and matching plays.
It also plays a critical role in
the CTMS system and, the Salesforce
a is helping the business, at more
than a 90% with accuracy rate coming
to the, supply chain optimization.
This is one of this, important
area in the life sensors, industry.
And, You see the how the overall impact
and how the inventory management and
how the distribution optimization,
is helping this, yay and helping
this, supply chain, inventory.
And overall the impact is like the
yay, a power supply chain solutions.
How achieved a reduction in overall
logistic cost and while improving the.
inventory accuracy to across the
multi multicenter trail sites
and this deep learning models.
The deep learning models that were
implemented, for the supply chain
optimizations have demonstrated,
demonstrated improvement in the
resource utilization, compared to,
conventional, management systems.
And, next coming to this, inventory
management and through machine
learning algorithms and how we will
see how the inventory management, have
transformed the, inve, Have transformed
and achieving a high accuracy rate.
I can say like more than 80% of
the accuracy rate in predicting
the site specific supply needs.
the system has resulted in a significant
reduction in stockout instance while
maintaining the optimal inventory.
Inventory levels are around,
30% below the traditional.
management methods, the distribution
optimization reinforcement, reinforcement
learning algorithms have reduced, have
reduced average delivery times and
transportation costs and, across the
international rail networks that this
system and, and this system, predictive
maintenance, scheduling, and has.
99 percentage and temperature compliance
rate for the cold chain products while
reducing the, temperature, exclusions.
And the next section, we will see
how any, artificial intelligence
enhanced the HCP integration.
HS.
CP is healthcare,
professional integration.
And here, we will see the
different section like enhanced
deficiency, data model architecture.
And, clinical decision, support
and the data validation.
So when it comes to the enhanced
efficiency, the, artificial intelligence
enhanced HCP integration has demonstrated
reduction in data entry time, and, while
achieving the data accuracy rate, or nine
or 90% across diverse, clinical settings.
And it comes to the
data model architecture.
this custom objects, this custom
objects for, Trail management has,
resulted in a major reduction in
data redundancy while improving the
query responses times by double.
And coming to the clinical, decision
support, the realtime analysis
capabilities also have the, improved
the patient outcome predictions
with the decision support and the
processing complex and data with
within minimal of seconds, just like
a few seconds, we can, the clinical
decision support can be taken.
The realtime analysis capabilities
have improved the patient outcome,
predictions with the decision
support and data validation.
And automated protocols exhibit high
accuracy in real-time verification
across multiple, data sources.
By reducing the manual
validation around 70%
the development and the
development and the CTMS.
Simulation here In this section we'll
talk about the machine learning,
machine learning applications, the
protocol optimizations and the resource
allocations, the machine learning
applications, what are the machine
learning applications and how it is
going to impact this, a powered trail
simulations, how demonstrated reduction
in early phase development costs.
And while achieving the, while
achieving the above 80% accuracy rate
in predicting the trail outcomes,
the A driven, virtual trails have
achieved accuracy in, predicting the
subject responses while reducing the
required patient enrollment In early
studies around 25%, and it can be more.
These numbers are just based on the
research and the PVOs that perform
and how the, a has given the results.
And these results may.
Vary when working with the real time, and
it'll be definitely, and it'll be more
accuracy rate than of the assumptions of
the rate and the protocol optimization.
Machine learning algorithms have improved
protocol, design efficiency by above 50%,
reducing the amend, amendment compared
to traditional design methodologies,
the system's patient burden assessment
capabilities have analyzed approximately,
300 protocol specific factors around,
like near to 300, protocol specific
factors to predict, patient dropout risk
with accuracy and resource allocation.
This predictive methods achieve around
80% of accuracy in forecasting the
site specific resource requirement.
And this enhanced, precision has resulted,
has resulted, in resource wastage.
And significant in improvement
in the site productivity across
multi-center, trails, particularly
in, complex, phase three studies.
And when you come to this,
future, I'll make look this
and the future implications.
And in this future implications we can
or we can see enhance prediction accuracy
and, Reduced recruitment timelines.
This is one of the most important.
and, through AA we can achieve
this and we can reduce up to
40% acceleration in patient
identification and enrollment process.
And the thought is like
the protocol optimization.
Optimization is like a. Decrease in costly
and time consuming protocol amendments.
And within the fourth section,
we can check about the improved
subject, 30 to 35% of enhancement
in the participant rotations.
Across all the clinical trail phases, we
see the current implementation results, it
varies between 81% enhancing these things.
The integration of Salesforce a into the
CTMS systems represent a paradigm shift
for the life census information research.
which are deliverable like,
measurable impacts, across, multiple
operational, dis dimensions.
This platform also, this platform
also demonstrate a high boost, high
percentage increase in the boost in
the operational efficiency, translating
the more resource effective resource
utilization and a remarkable,
increase in the trail success rates.
And throughout the phase two.
to phase four levels of, of the CTMS
lifecycle, fundamentally, transfer
meaning how a pharmaceutical company
design and execute, clinical studies.
Coming to the conclusion.
And here in this section, all the
section we have, discussed about
how the Gen, generatively helps and
how the artificial, helps in supply
chain, optimization and CTMS systems.
And we also discuss about the data
management and the compiling, to give the
conclusion, to give the conclusion that
the integration of the sa Salesforce in.
CTMS systems represent as we are
telling the shift in life sciences
research and the development.
And it has the enhanced, enhanced
analytics and efficiency.
The AA power tools have improved,
operational efficiency by around
40%, the clinical success rate,
which will be more than 35%, using
this AI power while reducing the,
trail timelines by around 30%.
Optimize the patient engagement
through a algorithms, the
patient matching precision.
Or we can say like the subject
matching precision increased by 80%
with the significant reductions in the
protocol, deviations, creating more,
Patient, centric trail experiences,
the future ready compliance, the data
entry error, the data entry errors.
the data entry definitely,
can be reduced by 90%.
ensuring the regulatory compliance
while the platform continues to evolve
with the advanced i a capabilities
and, protocol optimization.
The real tempation support
and this platform as the
platform continues to evolve.
The future developments in the AI
capabilities to further revolutionize
the CTMS system, ultimately contributing
to more efficient and effective clinical
trails in the life census industry.
And
thank you.
Thank you for joining the session with me.
I hope you had a great
information on this.
yay.
A for the life sciences
and the Salesforce.
yay.
Tools that, how it helps the,
and how it helps and how it
benefits for the CTMS systems.
And thanks for joining with me.
If you have any questions,
please reach out to me.
I'm happy to help you.
Thank you.