Speaker 13: Hello.
Good morning, everybody.
This is Sanjay Basu the Global
Head for AI, Gen AI Products from
TCS within the Digital Software
and Solutions Business Unit.
Today we are going to cover building
cognitive commerce platforms in Go
architecture with LLM-driven intelligence
for grocery, retail, and e-commerce.
To get started, what we are looking at
is a shift from rule-based to cognitive.
So grocery, retail, e-commerce are
crossing a fundamental threshold.
Systems that once relied on deterministic
rules and handcrafted logic are
giving way to intent-aware, LLM-driven
platforms capable of reasoning,
adapting, and responding in real-time.
This is not a model swapping exercise.
It means a complete rethinking of the
backend architecture, orchestration
patterns, and obviously data pipelines.
And if you look at from the overall
perspective, Go is exceptionally
positioned to carry that weight.
Today we were going to, look
at that exactly the same thing.
Looking at architecture function,
commerce intelligence, merchandising
automation, operational
intelligence, and agentic systems.
Why Go is chosen for cognitive commerce?
For several reasons.
One definitely is concurrency at scale
predictive predictable latency, and
obviously operational simplicity.
Now, if you look at concurrency
at scale, Go routines and channels
handle thousands of simultaneous
LLM calls, so that's a big plus.
Predictable latency, we are able to, look
at sub hundred milliseconds of latency.
Operational simplicity because of the
nature of how Go operates as a single
static binary, et cetera, it's makes
it more convenient and more simplified.
Now, if you look at the architecture
backbone, which is, integrating
LLMs into the commerce stack.
Data layer which is a core layer, holding
the the vector store the POS feeds and,
all of the data data which is needed.
The second layer from there is the
LLM inference layer, which is your--
where the model call streaming
responses, et cetera, are happening.
And third, the most outmost layer is
your orchestration layer, which is
your Go services context assembly,
composable in nature, et cetera.
And if you look at the design principles
which are like, prompting the routing,
prompting routing as a gateway, routing
intent, et cetera, which are happening.
Context assembly in Go, which is
aggregating the user history the inventory
state, and then, it's creating a whole
context sensitive from that perspective.
And the third is the
streaming post responses.
So it's stream tokens directly to the
client, so there's no intermediary unit.
Concurrency patterns for LLM
pipelines when it comes to LLM.
A single concurrent or a single commerce
request may fan out to multiple LLM calls.
Inventory classification, personalization
scoring, inventory aware, et cetera.
So it goes the core architecture
or the principles, bounding bounded
worker pools, context propagation
make this absolutely trackable without
external orchestration from us.
So no external orchestration is needed.
Now, let us look at some of the
use cases that we were working on.
One is a commerce intelligence and
search discovery and personalization.
So conversational search, if you
look at from an LLM's parsing of
natural language queries, right?
If we take an example for something,
we all, every day need is some quick
high protein for tonight, for example.
And here's an example that we have
taken into a structured filter
resolving those vec-vector, indexes,
product embeddings are from Go.
Second is a real-time personalization
use case, which is, we have been
seeing personalization for a long
time, but right now I think it is
make-- made more, convenient and
im-- the more context aware, right?
And so behavioral signals from
clickstream looking at the basket
history and combining the loyalty
data of the members assembled into
Go to inject it into a prompt.
So it's grounding the prompt, right?
Multimodal product discovery, as we
have seen with respect to your videos,
images, text, all of those embeddings
can actually continue to happen.
If we look at the vector search
infrastructure within Go, okay then
running the embedding generation,
with the backend Go worker pool.
So that's a big plus.
Then from things already in process,
then, they can completely use it.
Then cache popular query embeddings
with a short detail to other search bar.
So all of these things are architecturally
helpful within the infrastructure of Go.
The second use case we're
looking at is merchandising
automation and cataloging scale.
Within the framework of taxonomy
generation, attribute extractions or
catalog enrichment, for that matter in
case of elements, classifying new SKUs
into architectural category trees or
Go services, batch process, supplier,
et cetera, which is actually helping.
Unstructured product descriptions,
images, spec sheets, et cetera, are
parsed with a multimodal model and Go
pipelines normalize and validate extracted
attributes against the catalog schema.
So that's a that's a
validation that happens, right?
And if you look at the catalog enrichment,
then missing fields for example, in
case of food items like nutrition
data missing, allergen flags, sizing.
So all of those are populated
in real time, giving the
assortment, mission datable for
downstream search and compliance.
Third is the operational
intelligence driving the demand
sensing and non-substitution.
Very important for grocery retail, right?
So single sources signal sources, right?
So Go microservices ingest the real-time
signals across all the domains, right?
Three domains, and feed them into
LLM-assisted decision services.
Substitution intelligence
is extremely important.
When a product is unavailable, then
LLM-backed substitution service ranks
alternatives by semantic similarity
and then dietary complementary
sorry, compatibility Or maybe the
price delta and margin servicing the
best option under 200 milliseconds.
So that's that's what the substitution
intelligence and online behavior,
point of sale, logistics, et cetera,
are part of that whole process.
Here you see the most simplistic
lean model of how, a fulfillment
orchestration with Go microservice.
A very simple order is received,
picking optimization happens,
then dispatch happens, and then
the last mile tracking happens.
Now, if you look at all
of this combined, right?
Intent parsing and slot
allocation, then, route planning
and real-time prioritization.
So all of those are Go's channel-based
coordination allows each stage to emit
the events consumed by the next, right?
So one is connected to the next with
with long queues, circuit breakers,
preventing cascade failures, et
cetera, across fulfillment chain.
The last is mostly the agentic
architecture, how that is
controlled in a controlled economy.
And though i-in, in that context,
we're looking at warehouse management,
like LLM agents interpret pick
exceptions or, replenishment
triggering or maybe slot conflicting.
So all of those Go services execute the
reserved actions with full audit trails
and, you'll be able to really look at
all of those audits, what has happened.
We are looking at micro-fulfillment
where the agents coordinate robot tasks
adapting to real-time inventory deltas.
Go routines manage concurrency across
hundreds of simultaneous such pick tasks.
And it is, by default, it's
the most performant system
that you can look around.
Route optimization, customer
communication, exception handling
are agent orchestrated with
Go service maintaining state,
enabling the SLA what is needed.
The last is observability and
reliability and cost governance.
Because that is also important very, in
such ca-- in such cases of architectures
that we are pursuing in the world.
Tracing every LLM call end-to-end,
with OpenTelemetry correlating,
token cost to business outcome.
So it's important, right?
Everybody's asking, we need to tag and map
the business cost to the so the business
outcome to the token cost that is needed.
And the budgeting, the governance,
et cetera, are all part and
parcel of the of framework.
Then the key caveats are if we, look at
key caveats, then we are talking about
architecture-first LLM integrations
and architectural challenges.
So design for streaming, fan-out
concurrency and, context assembly
before choosing a model are some part
of the principle of architecture-first.
Go is a natural fit, and why?
Because Go routines, low latency
runtime, static binaries make Go the
right substrate for high throughput
real-time cognitive commerce services.
So that's how, Go is also getting
some of this getting executed
with agentic versus uncontrolled.
So autonomous agents require
stronger observability, right?
And stricter circuit
breaking and not less.
And that's where, Go services are
the enforcement layer in case of when
it talk-- when we are talking about
agentic the autonomous agents per se.
Governing cost from day one is very
key and critical in the terms on,
when a lot of CIOs are coming out
and saying, "My token cost is is just
skyrocketing." How you manage it.
So token budgets, model tiering, per
intent routing are not afterthoughts.
Build them into the gateway before your
first production deployment happens.
So that's a big plus
that you need to look at.
And thank you everybody for for your
time today and pleasure talking on this.