Hello people.
My name is Vanka Cheru.
I'm a senior infrastructure
engineer in the Orange County area.
I the today, the topic I want to
present to you about, is optimizing
hybrid object-based storage for
scalability, performance, and cost
across on-premises and cloud environment
went of social media and advancements
in healthcare and financial industry.
There has been a massive increase
in unstructured, data like,
videos, images, IOT sensor data.
Which led to, a need for scalable
and cost effective storage solution.
This presentation explores,
how object-based storage
architecture seamlessly integrate.
OnPrem on premises infrastructure
with cloud environments and to
optimize enterprise data management
addresses critical challenges
faced today by IT industry.
We'll go through the various
implementation strategies, cost
advantages, and performance improvements
to help you develop and, effective
strategy for your organization.
Organizations, today, face an
unprecedented, challenge in managing
the exponential data growth.
The object-based storage, can handle,
large volumes of unstructured data more
efficiently than, a traditional file.
Or, block storage organizations facing
exponential data growth in Glo, in the, in
global data footprint, that byte, by 2025.
So organizations must embrace
and innovative storage solutions.
That balance, performance, cost, and,
compliance, regulatory requirements.
Hybrid object-based storage has emerged
as an, critical foundation for enterprises
seeking competitive advantage in
data-driven economy, saving about 40% of
annual operational and maintenance cost.
Let's talk about hybrid architecture
of the hybrid, object based storage.
Hybrid ob object based storage
architecture establishes, E
echo seal echo system where
data can rec reside on premises.
Or in multiple clouds while
presenting a single unified, strategy
stor while pro, while providing a
single unified storage repository
to the, for all the applications.
This architecture implements industry
standard APIs and protocols, ensuring
seamless interoperability and consistent
data access methods, across local
infrastructure and cloud environments.
To talk about the architecture.
the architecture typically consists
of, four layers, a management
layer, an application layer,
orchestration layer, and storage.
and storage.
so coming to the management layer, is
management layer, basically consists of.
it's a software frontend interface, helps
us access the entire infrastructure.
And, the application layer is nothing
but, user facing services and APIs
connecting backend storage and
cloud, in the orchestration layer.
it's it functions.
The orchestration layer functions as
the core of the system making data
placement, decisions, based on the
analysis of data access patterns,
performance requirements and cost
parameters, it continuously evaluates,
and automatically migrates data between.
Appropriate storage tiers,
optimizing both performance and cost,
without any manual intervention.
The storage layer, is nothing
but a physical backend
integrated hybrid storage.
Let's talk more about orchestration.
let's talk more about, the orchestration
or data tiering architecture,
the intelligent, tiering, Engine
continuously analyzes metadata, and the
access patterns and business policies
to automatically orchestrate data
placement across performance tiers.
This zero touch optimization
ensures each data set.
Resides on most economically efficient
storage layer while maintaining
compliance requirements and
performance service level agreements.
Data tier can broadly be classified in
two four tiers, hot tier, cold tier, and
archive, vomit tier and archive tier.
And my.
Hot tier is nothing but emission
critical workloads with high latency
requirements and maximum throughput.
We can leverage on-prem storage
platforms with, which has, flash
or high performance, SSD drives.
in it, coming to the Walmart tier,
the data that is not frequently
accessed, but it is quite important
enough to maintain for future use.
Cold tier is, nothing but is data,
that can be stored in cloud, like
historical data sets, reporting data.
Things like that.
And in the archive tier it's nothing.
But, it's mostly about, comes to the
data protection suite, where data,
with data that requires an infinite
or long-term retentions to encompass
companies, regulatory requirements.
Best use case examples are healthcare
and financial sectors where they got to
maintain, maintain, longer retentions.
Here are some of the strategies, to
achieve cost optimization by analyzing
data lifecycle, identifying data,
access patterns, use, tier storage
solutions to store data based on its
frequency of access, hot data on high
performance, like our expensive storage.
And coal data on cost effective,
slower storage implementing by
implementing tiering policies,
automating a data movement across
performance and slower storage.
continuously monitoring, and
analyzing the performance metrics and
refined data placement strategies.
And, optimizing cloud resources
strategically select appropriate
storage tiers and geographical regions.
based upon the organization,
location, you can choose, the local,
availability zones or something.
far from your organization, which
could be, most cost effective option.
So organizations implementing these
strategies or hybrid object storage
solutions consistently has achieved
about 30% or greater reductions in their
total cloud, cloud storage expenditures.
Through sophisticated tiering strategies.
So by conducting comprehensive analysis
of access, data access patterns and
regulatory requirements, IT departments
can establish automated governance
policies that dynamically position data
in the most cost effective location
without requiring any manual intervention.
On-premises Infrastructure investments
can also be maximized by this strategy
by allocating high performance capacity.
exclusively to latency sensitive
workloads while maintaining, simultaneous,
while simultaneously leveraging, cloud
economics for substantial majority of,
enterprise data that doesn't demand a sub.
Second response times are consistent
IOPS performance, hybrid object
storage architecture meets, industry's
regulatory compliance and data.
Sovereign with an unified API layer.
with 75 per up, up to 75% of the global
organizations are now, navigating multiple
overlapping regulatory frameworks.
Hybrid storage architectures deliver,
the essential flexibility needed
to address complex challenges.
Forward-thinking enterprises can
securely maintain sensitive workload
on premises while simultaneously
leveraging cloud economics to optimize.
cost for less regulated
information assets.
So with this unified API layer, we can
maintain data sovereignty, retention
policies, encryption, and audit
trail implementation, best practices.
it is always recommended to implement
these, solutions, these hybrid
based solutions or hybrid storage
solutions or any solutions with
industry standard best practices.
by successful, any successful hybrid
storage, implementation, approach,
organizations to start with non-critical
workloads to refine their approach.
as they go before me migrating more
sensitive applications to begin with,
you start with an initial infrastructure
or environment assessment by evaluating
the existing infrastructure data,
access patterns, and, getting
through the compliant, getting to
know the compliance requirements
of that particular organization.
And, identify, performance
sensitive workloads, and data
that could benefit from tiering.
Also to document, it's always
best practice to document all
these regulatory constraints and
the infrastructure information,
that will view, that will further
influence the architecture decisions
coming to the architecture design.
it's better to develop a
blueprint for integration between.
on premises and cloud resources, selecting
the appropriate storage technologies
for each tier, and defining the API
integration points and establishing the
performance baselines and expectations.
Policy development, is key in
creating, to create, automated data
tier policies based upon the access
patterns and, business defining the go
governance frameworks for consistent
management across the environments and
documenting all these, the security
controls and compliance measures.
Implementing and testing.
So deploying integration
components and validate
performance against the benchmarks.
So test, a failover scenarios, testing
a failover scenario and data recovery
process, and also defining R-P-O-R-T-O,
recovery point objective, recovery
time objective, and, verify the policy
enforcement and audit capabilities
are met across the environment.
And also testing the RPO.
testing the defined RP one are, are
being achieved with this solution,
with the implemented solution.
let's, now let's go through, a case study.
Where the financial services, financial
organization was meeting, having a
challenge and, where, they had five
petabytes of data increase, which
is data is, has been increasing
and their infrastructure, existing
infrastructure could not be scaled,
due to financial constraints.
with the, by the way, the global
economy is, tumbling, to meet,
the growing analytic, to meet the
growing analytics and the workloads.
While strict regulations, required certain
data to remain on premises, the solution
that they chose was, the firm implemented.
a hybrid based storage architecture
with high performance flash on,
with high performance flash discs
on premises for active trading
data and other customer records.
and all their, unstructured data
integrated that with the cloud
storage for historical analysis,
and long-term retention, to meet
the regulatory requirements.
So they also adopted
an intelligent tiering.
algorithm, which automatically moves
data based on access pattern while
unified, while a unified, interface
provided consistent policy enforce
enforcement across all storage locations.
So the result was, reduced storage
cost by about, 30% in the first year.
And improved the analytics per, improved
the performance by about 35%, and they
were, yet achieved, they yet achieved
99.9 in compliance requirements, that
was being set to their organization.
And also, and also they have decreased
the storage management overhead
by about 40%, and accelerated, new
application deployments by 60%.
So when their organization had to
invest less on implementing the storage,
implementing, storage, implementation
and their op storage operational costs.
They focused, and they leveraged
that, that financial budget towards
deploying new applications, which, which
helps their organization, big time.
So let's talk about, future
trends in the hybrid storage.
So the hybrid storage landscape
continues to evolve rapidly with the
emerging technologies, enabling more
intelligent and seamless integration
between different environments.
So organizations should prepare
for these advancements by building
a flexible architectures that
can adapt to future innovations.
So industry analysts, predict that by
2025, by end of 2025, more than 70%
of the enterprise data will be managed
through unified hybrid storage platforms.
That dynamic, that dynamically
optimizes pla that dynamically optimize
placement, based on real time data
placement based on the real time
analysis of workload requirements.
key takeaway from this presentation are.
to assess your current environment
before, you implement the solution and
developing a solid tiering strategy,
which plays a CLO crucial role.
And also implementing a unified
management, solution by deploying
a robust orchestration tools that
provide comprehensive visibility and
control across your entire storage
ecosystem and prioritizing the APIs.
implementing the standard industry
best in industry, adapted APIs
and interfaces to ensure any,
frictionless operations regardless
of data, location and storage medium.
And finally, defining a clear
success metrics, what altering of
the performance and cost efficiency.
And, making sure compliance,
regulatory compliance are met.
Leveraging these analytics to
continuously refine your hybrid storage
architecture and ensuring alignment
with evolving business objectives.
So hybrid object based storage deliver
delivers, transformative advantages for
organizations confronting exponential data
growth challenges through the strategic
implementation of these solutions.
it, teams can provide superior,
performance, unlimited scalability,
robust compliance capabilities,
while significantly optimizing cost
across the entire data lifecycle.
this sends my, talk and the presentation.
Thank you so much for, listening to me.
Thanks for your time.