Hi, this is Baskar America.
today our topic is,
revolutionizing telecom BS with go.
So in this presentation, we will
explore how go based solution have
enabled the telecom companies to
handle them millions of transaction
while achieving the significant cost
saving and performance improvement.
Join us, as we shared that practical
insight and real world implementation for
the, engineering team looking into the
build a next generation telecom, infras.
So what are the DSS.
BSS is I better been a support
system in telecom, industries.
it's a kind of pyramid architecture
like, network layer and VSS layer on
top of BSS layer on top of, customer
experience layer kind of thing.
telecom industries, they have a.
Which we have to translating to the
digital, using the GO programming
and apply the microservice
architecture and in data cloud.
the digital BSS market, landscapes, so
8.9 billion, projected, global digital
BSS market value markets size back, 2026.
So they're expecting,
almost, $9 billion, in 2026.
The compound annual growth rate is
almost 18%, 70.8%, and cost is 75%,
and 40% is operational production.
So telecommunication BSS
market is experience.
A rapid growth has provided,
transition from the legacy
system to a digital solution.
This c is, driven by the
increasing customer, demand
for the real time services.
The need for operation efficiency and,
competition, competition from the digital
need to company entering the space that
go programming is emerged as a key enabler
in this, transformation offering the
performance benefit that translates that
directly to the business value through
the, through reduce their development
cost and the operational savings.
So when we are applying the,
transformation from the legacy application
to the digital, so it's almost a percent
cost sale and 40% operational traditions.
why go, for the telecom bss.
So go programming language,
having a special features.
using these features we can, efficiently
develop the, transformation from,
legacy application to the, digital.
So high performance, concurrency
model and a memory efficiency
cross platform supports.
concurrency model means, go, go
routine for the efficient processing.
and memory efficiency to go programming,
having, language, having a special,
garbage collection, features and
class platform support means it's
compiled once and put anywhere.
So go doesn't philosophy
aligns there perfectly with
the telecom BSS requirement.
It's, compiled the natural delivery
and performance needed for the high
volume transaction processing while
maintaining the developer productivity
through the clean accessible syntax.
The language is built in the concurrency
model with the go routine, and the channel
provided a solution for the handling them.
Millions of simultaneous connections, a
common scenario in the telecom enrollment.
Additionally, gross memory management
and garbage collection minimize
the resource utilization and
making it a. But always on systems.
So that is what earlier, we discussed go
programming language, having a special
features like a congruency model.
It has to, handling the, parallel process,
concurrency programming kind things.
and, special garbage collections.
so I, because of that, utilizing
the resources, very minimal.
So when we are supposed to using the
any resources, once that, task is done,
that resources immediately are released.
So that's part
microservice architecture in the tele.
Service independence.
Each business function operates as
a standalone service with, with it
one data store and the AP interface.
This independence allows the team to
develop and apply the scales, services
without affecting other components.
So service, independence.
when we are, talking about
translating application to.
we have to, I mean that, BSS
enterprise applications, we have to
divide into the multiple services.
So each services, it has a own
data source and, multiple a PA
calls or multiple a p interfaces.
because of that, it is very easy
to develop that services and it
applied individually and, development
activity is very ly happening,
so multiple services we have to.
And the resilience and, for, to
isolation, failures in one service,
don't catch cutting into the system.
in the, in BSS side, we have a. Multiple
services, I suppose any services, is down
so it do not cascade through the system.
So we can apply some patterns like,
circuit, brake cards or time mode,
and mechanism ensure that viral
system remains operationally even
when individual component fails.
At the same time, target scaling resources
can be allocated precisely where needed.
High demand services like a
building or customer management
can scale independently during the
peak period without, our project.
Yeah, that's absolutely.
So we no need to enter system
to scale up something like that.
So what are the service, on demand?
That particular service only
we have to scale up actually.
So that is a targeted scaling.
So the transac, transition from the
monolithic, VSS to the microservices
has been, transformative to, for the
telecom approach, this architectural
approach, based on the complex systems
into the manageable, manageable and
specialized services that communicating
through the well defined a PS.
Go small memory, footprint and fast.
start, time.
Make it, practically well suited
for the microservice implementation.
Enable that rapid scaling in response
to change the demand pattern.
performance metrics and benchmarks.
So our real world implementation of core
base BSO solution have demonstrated signal
performance improvement, legacy systems.
Our benchmark shows that, go
implementation, consistently.
our performance previous, generations
of telecom software across the
critical metrics, they able to handle
the 2.5 million transaction per,
our, representative of four times
of implement our legacy systems.
While then 99.99% uptime
translate into just a minute of.
A critical requirement with telecom
operation where service interruption
to directly impact the revenue
and the customer satisfaction.
So using this, transformation, so
it has to improve the performances.
almost 2.5 million, transaction per hour.
At the same time, using this,
transformations, our downtime
means very minimal per year.
So almost 1e-05% of downtime per year.
so almost your system
is available, 99.999%.
yeah, that's the, here.
So security implementation.
whenever, we have a services,
when we are developing that, go
language with microservices and
enterprise B BSS applications.
So each services have a multiple,
a Ps and those a Ps communicating
internal a, internal a Ps or external
a Ps or third party, a Ps. Like that.
So in these cases, we have to, provide
the security for the a PA calls.
So we have to use the authentication
and author mechanism, implement the
s to, and, implementing the J token
with, GO crypto package or identity
management across the microservice.
And data production.
Data production is most crucial thing.
So that's the reason we have to apply
the encryption, A ESO 2 56 algorithms.
the data encryption where we need,
actually, we have a very, since
two customer data at the same
time, financial transaction data.
we need to provide that data
protection and correction at the,
the rest and in transit using
the AS 2 56 with the customer.
Go.
Implementation optimization for
telecom workloads, threat monetary,
a real time security event processing
with the go forward analysis in
general for the pattern detection.
Complaints adherent ITU, eight by 8
0 5 standard throughout, automated
security control on the audit capability.
So security is a paramount
in a telecom bss.
Which handled us to customer
data and financial transactions.
Our goal base security implementation,
leverage the languages performance
to process the security even at the
unprecedented scale while maintaining
the comprehensive protection.
Go Standard Library provides a robust,
cryptographic tool that we have
extended, with the telecom specific
security modules aligned with the in
state standard like itt, GT TX, 8 0
5, ensuring the both regulatory and
competence protection evolving threats.
So in, in this, security implementation,
so we have to provide the APAs
security at the same time, we have
to provide that at the protections.
DevOps integration.
DevOps integration is the most,
crucial part, while translating from
legacy application to the, digital.
DevOps, integration.
It's, providing a very fast development.
So continuous integration,
automated build, quality
assurance, deployment, and monitor.
So continuous integration is the,
about automated testing with the ghost
building there, testing framework.
Automated, build across, compilation
for multiple deployment, targets
and the quality assurance of static
analysis and security scanning,
deployment blue gate deployment with
the CAN testing, monitoring realtime
metrics and distributor, tracing.
In this, DevOps integration.
that develop, develop the code and
they, we have automated, execution
of journey integration test after
that, Build up, code actually.
And that, that, once that build is
happened, then we have to deploy
our services, into the, cloud
networks, actually cloud platforms.
At the same time, we have to, check the
quality assurance like, sonar, sonar
quality checks actually, once we applied
and services running in the production.
we have to monitor the services, whether
the services is, down or up and, the
particular services, how much, CPU time,
and how much memory it is, occupied.
These things also, we can monitoring
actually, so using that DevOps
integration, each and every services.
We can monitor it and how much, CPU and
memory it is occupied actually, that
we can monitoring it and the entire,
deployment and build and deployment
process, we can automate it actually.
So DevOps practices are essential
for realizing the full potential
of go in the telecom environments.
Our integrated pipeline enable us
to deploy the changes to production
multiple times per day with the
confidence dynamically reduce the
time to market for a new future.
So when we are developing any new
feature, it's very less time we can
deliver those things actually, and goes
to compilation speed and, comprehensive
testing capability make it, particularly
well suited for CICD workflows.
The ability to quickly build test
the plan changes has, transformed
how telecom BSS evolves enabling a
continuous improvement rather than
the, Infrequent high risk upgrades.
overall, DevOps integration is the most
crucial part in the translating from
the legacy application to the, digital.
cloud data deployment,
so containerization,
orchestration, multi-cloud
strategy, and the service mass.
So cloud network deployment model enables,
telecom b to achieve the elastic scaling
and the graphical distributions goes.
Minimal random dependency and the
small boundary size make it ideal
for the environments with typically
microservice required for, request.
1520 MB for container space.
So whenever we go with, when we are
using the GO programming language,
the, what are the dependencies?
It is very, 15 to 20 MB only
for container space occupation.
And this container
radiation is, one of the.
Crucial part.
And, it is called as a
docker containerization.
And, that container, we have to convert
as a docker, images, that images we
can, apply into the, higher involvement.
because of that, we have to award the.
enrollment basis, discrepancies, any
issues, enrollment, lower enrollment,
having, lot of issues one enrollment or
another when we are moving to our code.
So it has a lot of, discrepancies.
So to avoid those things, we can
use the docker container variations.
So yeah, our cloud native approaches
has enabling to us to the 300%
improvement in scalability with the
system automatically expanding and
contracting based on demand patterns.
This elasticity is, particularly
valuable for the telecom operators
are dealing with, unpredictable
traffic spike during the network,
events or marketing promotions.
Okay.
So yeah, this cloud NATO
deployment, mostly, we are using
the docker containerization,
open source tools and frameworks.
using this open source tools
and frameworks, so it's
obviously, reduce our cost.
It's a open source, so using
that open source tool to start
developing your activity.
So you have to spend the
only development activity.
There is no license cost for
the, or, tools or, so it is
available on open source.
Okay?
we have to, use those things and we can
develop the, our entire transformation
from the legacy application to digital.
And, we can, implement
our, BSS application.
Actually, okay.
Data access and storages, go,
for our capabilities, cockroach
for their distributor desk.
cockroach distributed means cockroach, DB
is nothing but the NoSQL kind of things.
Ready for caching with, go ready client.
these tools provide the foundation
for that data per, persistency with
the performance characteristics
required by the telecom workloads.
So a PA development, again, an
E ECHO framework for the, high
performance, rest, P-A-G-R-P-C for
the internal service communication
and open a PA for the documentation.
Our a PA handling, millions of
requests with, sub millisecond latency.
Observability, premises for the metric,
collections for the distributor.
Tracing and grafana for visualization.
Complete observability has reduced
the MTTR from, hours, two minutes
for the, production issues.
Project structure, go module for the
dependency management and, project
organization Following, domain,
domain driven, design principles,
consistent structure, has improved
the developer onboarding time base
system, the go ecosystem year rich
collection of open source tools,
that, accelerate the BSS development.
we have leveraged these tools to
create the modular maintainable and
co maintainable code basis that reduce
the service time by 50% improving.
So to, using this open
source tools and framework.
So they're telling that we are
leveraging these tools to create the
modular maintainability, code basis
that reduce the service ing 10 by 50%.
Absolutely.
So using these tools,
we can, protein 10, 50%.
A real time data process.
So yeah, real time data process,
nothing but Kafka streaming with, go
consumer processing and enrichment.
go powered streaming Processor analysis
is ML model with a go, inference engines.
Action, automat response on three
A ps. real time data processing
forms the backbone of the
modern telecom bss, enabling the
intermediate insights and actions.
Our go base, stream processing pipeline,
handle the millions of events, but second.
From network performance metrics to
customer interaction, all process with,
minimal latency, these capabilities
as, transformed how telecom operators
will respond to the customer needs
with the EA driven system, reduce the.
Shown by the 45 person through
proactive inter interventions, the
net promoter score improvement of 25
points, demonstrate that the impact
of the, technical capabilities as
customer experience of more respons
and this realtime data processing,
we obviously use that Kafka.
It's millions of transactions.
So we have local transaction
mechanisms there.
We have to apply this, kafa.
It's nothing but a event
driven architectures.
In the event driven architectures.
Obviously each event triggering.
And based on that, what
transactions we have to roll back.
What are the transactions, rollbacks
or tasks or rollbacks that we can
using, the Kafka streaming section.
This is a real time
processing data processing.
So implementing your go power
BSS transformation, start with
the clear business objectives.
when we are, implementing your go
power BSS transformation, so we
have a clear business objective
and defining services properly.
And each services, defining multiple,
aaps and, those a Ps, with, using
the, securities and, that also more
protect and modular transformation.
Begin with the bound context
that offer the high business
value, but moderate risk.
gradually expand your go, footprints.
Build, build a Go expertise, investing
in training and, pair programming
to build a solid foundation of Go
kill with your engineering team.
Yeah, this is obviously so better
to do with, pair programming, learn
the go programming language, and
understand the key features, of the
go language and, Whenever we develop
any services, we have to apply
these, go features and especially,
there is a parallel processing.
so this go parallel processing is very,
effectively, and, provide the more
performances, measure and optimizing,
establish the performance, baselines
and, continuously optimize, based on your
real world telemetry and user feedback.
As we conclude, remember that
successful BSS transformations technical
excellence with a strategic, business
alignment, your journey to go forward.
Bss, should follow the clear roadmap
that delivers the incremental
value while building towards
comprehensive organization.
By leveraging a growth performance
advantages, embracing cloud NATO
architecture, and implementing the DevOps
practices, your team can achieve the,
remarkable performance improvements and
the cost savings we have discussed today.
The features of telecom BSS
belongs to those who can deliver
the robust, scalable, and secure
systems and go provider, ideally
foundation for this next generation
of telecommunication infrastructure.
So as we discussed, on previous
slides, so go provide the, ideal
foundation of this next generation
of telecommunication project.
so far, whatever the legacy is on,
also, they are facing plenty of issues.
So any, environmental
wise or whatever it is.
and performance wise or whatever it is.
when we are using this, go programming
language and translating into the
microservice architecture, so definitely
we have to see that dramatic changes,
and a lot of, performance improvements.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.