Hello everyone.
I'm Nikita Kamath and I'm thrilled
to be here today to talk about real
time notification systems, a critical
component in today's digital world.
These systems are responsible
for delivering adults messages
or updates to users instantly.
Whether it's a push notification,
a SMS or an email, they play a huge
role in user engagement and retention.
When done right, they feel
seamless and intuitive.
When they fail, users
will notice immediately.
Today we'll explore how to architect
these systems to scale globally, stay
reliable under pressure, and deliver
messages that matter at the right time.
So let's talk about the first thing that's
most important in these large scale, real
time notification system and that scale.
Or rather, let's call it the
scale challenge, because before
we optimize, we have to survive.
Platforms like Facebook handle about
8 billion notifications every day.
That's nearly a hundred thousand
notifications per second.
And these systems are expected
to deliver with latencies of
less than 75 milliseconds.
Do you know that's less than
a, how much a human can blink?
On top of that, usage
patterns can be unpredictable.
Think major news events, celebrity live
streams, or e-commerce, flash sales.
These triggers, traffic spikes
like, like 300% over the baseline.
Architectures need to handle these,
this level of scale gracefully,
which means being both horizontally
scalable and resilient in real time.
So let's talk about the first thing
that's, architecture, which drives
these real time notification systems.
200 such scale and complexity.
We move away from monoliths and
adopt a microservice architecture.
Each service is small, focused,
and independently deployable.
One service handles user preferences.
The other manages device tokens, a
third one probably queues messages,
and a fourth one actually sends them.
This lets teams deploy and scale
just the services under stress, like
delivering service, like delivery
services during a big campaign without
impacting the rest of the system hidden.
Savings there on cogs, you
only scale where you need
to and not the whole system.
Another huge benefit is
technology diversity.
You might use no JS for low ancy delivery
services, Python for analytics, and go
for performance critical components.
This modularity also further announces
fault tolerance if one service fails.
It doesn't just bring down the
whole system, it's limited, and
just that feature, that part
functionality is what is impacted.
Moving on, the next thing we would talk
about is event driven architecture,
often tightly coupled with services.
Microsoft has shine actually when
paired with event driven architecture.
In this model, services emit events
instead of calling each other.
They're asynchronous, meaning
producers no longer wait for consumers.
For example, when a user likes a photo,
say on Facebook or Instagram, the app for
emit an event, the notification system in
the background listens to this event and
triggers the appropriate notification.
All where the user is totally believes
and the user's experience as such is
absolutely not impacted or affected.
This pattern causes natural deconflict,
so services can evolve independently.
It also introduces buffer zones that
absorb traffic spikes without passing
on back pressure to the whole system.
It's resilient, scalable
patterns that can.
10,000 to a hundred thousand
messages per second with sub
millisecond internal latency.
Isn't that fascinating?
What can event driven architecture
not really function without,
for folks who, you guessed it.
You guessed it, right?
A message broker.
Message broker is basically a glue
that holds the whole system together.
Two of the most popular options that we
have on the market are Kafka and Rabbit
mq, and they serve different purposes.
Kafka is ideal for high throughput
streaming, capable of handling
millions of events per second.
It's optimized for bulk data
fault tolerant and built to scale.
On the other hand, RabbitMQ is more
feature rich in terms of routing.
It supports conditional delivery.
Topic based routing and priority queues.
This is perfect when you need to
deliver different types of messages
to different devices or user segments.
Many real time systems use both Kafka
for ingest events and rapid MQ for
routing and personalization issue.
We discussed earlier that two distributed
systems drive on two specific Cornerstone.
One being scale, which we just discussed,
and the second being resiliency.
So in the next slide, we are gonna
be talking about resiliency patterns.
Let's take a closer look at like
resiliency, because in large scale
distributed systems failure is not just
an, it's imminent, it's a certainty
that's gonna happen someday or the other.
This system consists of dozens
or even hundreds of services.
Communicating over the network.
This means a failure can cascade
fast if not handed properly.
A small issue like a slow red,
instant can ca, can literally
snowball into a full outage.
There are different ways how we
can literally stay resilient.
Let's start off with the first one
on the slide that's circuit breakers.
A circuit breaker has nothing but
a fuse in your electrical system.
If a downtime service starts failing,
say 50% of the requests of a push
certificate provider are timing out
the circuit breaker, the circuit opens
and stops sending traffic temporarily.
This prevents your system from wasting
resources on a failed component and gives
the troubled service some time to recover
after a. The ser, your service will again
test the waters and resume only if the
downstream service is healthy back again.
Next, we are gonna talk about our Balkans.
let's think of a ship here.
It has com compartments
or Balkans if one floods.
We just hope and play that the ship
doesn't go down right or it doesn't sink.
Similarly, in the concept or in the world
of software, it primarily means isolating
components, so failures can be contained.
For example, if an SMS delivery fails
due to a third party provider, it
shouldn't affect push notifications.
Each channel operates in its own resource
pool, separate threads, separate queues.
Sometimes even separate services, so
when there is isolation, you at least
your whole system is not failing.
Catastrophically.
Let's talk about time management here.
A slow service can be more
dangerous than a failed one.
It consumes threads, memory, and
blocks the upstream components.
That's why we use strict timeouts
with exponential back off if a
downstream calls takes more than.
Say your timeout is set
to 200 milliseconds.
We just abandon it.
We don't wait endlessly, and with
exponential back off, each retry is spaced
out to reduce load and increase the chance
of recovery for the downstream system.
That brings us, we spoke about
exponential back off, but wait, how,
where does it come into a picture?
That brings us to the next
topic, which is retry policy.
Not all failures are permanent
transient failures like a network
hiccup can often be resolved by
retrying, but we must be smart.
Use exponential backup to avoid hammering
the downstream service repeatedly.
Add jitters or randomness to spread
out retrials over a period of time and
avoid synchronized spikes a problem
also known as the thundering herd.
These resiliency patterns together
reduce the blast radius of a failure
and let the system degrade gracefully
instead of catastrophically.
Is it a great thing?
No, but at least it's more contained
and handled better than the whole
system going down in like a J.
Coming to our next topic,
sharding and partitioning.
Sharding is how we scale horizontally
and keep the performance consistent.
Even as we add users,
region, and functionality.
there is not a one size
fits all solution here.
So let's take a moment and explore
the different sharding strategies.
Starting off with user based,
shared by user ID to ensure
ordering and consistency.
If all notifications for a user are
handed by the same partition, we can
guarantee that they arrive in order.
This is a critical experience,
especially for messaging,
security alerts or sequential
delivery where ordering matters.
The next thing is the geographic charter.
Be by user ID to ensure
ordering and consistency.
If all notifications for
a user are the partition.
We actually ensure that
they arrive in order.
Now, what is geographic
sharding come into picture here?
The closer your data and the
services are to the user, the
faster you can deliver sharding.
We route users in Europe to a EU based
cluster and us to a US based cluster.
This reduces round trip time,
especially important for push
notifications and mobile devices
where latency is visible to users.
So with the combination of where
we need user, where order matters,
and we also latency matters too.
It's a combination where geographic and
user based sharding comes into picture.
The next thing is time-based charting.
This separates hot data, like
recent notifications from
cold data archive messages.
It improves performance and
simplifies data lifecycle management.
For instance, messages from like
today are placed in fast access
partition, while older messages are
placed in cheaper, slower storage.
What is functional charting?
We often separate different
types of notification.
A high priority alert, like a suspicious
login, doesn't go through the same
pipeline as a promotional banner.
This allows for tailored
delivery strategies, failure,
isolation, and even different
compliance requirements prototype.
By combining these strategies like
we just discussed a little before, we
can scale to millions of users while
keeping latencies under 15 milliseconds.
That brings us to our next
topic, which is adaptive rate.
Limiting rate limiting is traffic
control for your services.
It ensures that no component is over and
that critical traffic gets through first.
But in modern systems.
Static limits just don't work.
The system needs to adapt to these
limits in real time, monitor,
load, system load, and calculate
these capacities dynamically.
So let's go through this phase,
like a brainstorming session, right?
What do we need to have
adapting rate limiting sessions?
Firstly, we need to know
and monitor the system load.
That's where the observability of
our services comes into picture.
We continuously track these health
metrics, whether it's the CPU, our
memory, our request, latencies Q Depth,
and also the downstream success rates.
This gives us a live pulse on how the
system is performing, or what we call in
software like cost, quality of service.
This enables us to calculate
the capacity dynamically.
Based on current and historical
data, we estimate safe throughputs
using predictive models.
If a service has been degrading
around 70% of CPU U historically,
we set that as our soft ceiling.
We also monitor bus patterns.
For example, say that every Friday
at 6:00 PM we see a spike or a peak.
Then we can adjust our models proactively.
This like this kind of helps us adjust
and we have the data, we have our
capacities, and now we can actually
talk about what we do or how we
adjust rate limits when loads spike.
One of the ways we can do this
is adjust in ingress rates.
How many new events can our
service except per second, we can
modulate or titrate this data.
Second, we can also work
on our prioritization.
Give more preference to urgent traffic.
For example, two FA
Codes, alerts, throttling.
Before or further the matter even drop
low priority events at a given time,
like newspaper, less letter things.
If your service is not healthy,
then you actually prioritize, and in
that low prioritize, higher priority
notifications in the load times so
that your system is actually doing
what it essentially needs do, deliver
what's highest priority at that.
This ensure survival system survival and
graceful degradation again, and not just
an abroad failure where, you might end up
delivering a new newsletter notification
and not really, delivering a notification
from the bank, which is of, speech log.
So that's where stuff like prioritization
and throttling help comes handy.
So now we have gone through a whole
cycle of how we have adjusted our rate
limits, but what's the most important
thing after all, this is feedback loop.
We implement a closed loop feedback system
that refines our rate limiting decisions
continuously based on outcome metrics.
what were our vitri rates,
what were the latencies?
Or one of the event drop counts.
This reduces overload incidents
by up to 85% and keeps the system
utilization at peak efficiency.
We have gone through a gamut of different
architectures, strategies, techniques,
which brings us to our next highly
important topic, which is caching.
So in a distributor system.
We talk about ma multilevel
caching strategy.
Caching is what allows our system
to meet performance goals of sub
millisecond latencies or deliveries.
In this case, even when we are
handling billions of events, but.
One cache is not enough when
you're talking about the scale
of billions of notifications
or message deliveries, right?
So that's where multi-level caching
hierarchy comes into picture.
So first we start off with L one, which
is application level memory cache.
This is like an inpro memory stored
directly on your service runtime.
More, you might have heard of terms
like in memory objects or LRU caches.
It provides sub microsecond access time,
perfect for extra extremely hard data.
Things like notification templates, flags,
or user personalized reference toggles.
But it's limited.
It's a limited till you don't have
unlimited storage on that and.
It's local to your service
runtime and cannot be stored
across, shared across instances.
That's where our L two cache or
distributed cache comes into picture.
Here we could use technologies
like reddish or memc.
This cache is shared
across nodes and supports.
Fast read writes in say,
one to five milliseconds.
We store data like device tokens.
Rate limiting metadata or frequently
access personalization info.
We also set that TTL broadly known as
time to live per, and it's done per key
to balance, freshness and efficiency.
TTLs can be dynamic, for example,
shorter for volatile data and
longer for templates, things
that don't train so often.
Moving on from L one and L two, we move to
L three, which is more persistent storage.
That's our database.
You could use something like a
Postgre, SQL, cosmos, DB Cassandra, and
multiple other options on the market.
Access to these systems are
generally taking between 10 to
a hundred milliseconds, so we
use them only as a fallback.
Only when the data missing is
missing in the L one and L two
cache, that's the upper layers.
The database holds the source of
truth, but our caching ensures that it.
It's, it only serves a
fraction of the traffic.
Remember that our latency and
efficiency numbers will only be
met when most of the traffic is
served from L one and L two Caius.
With this approach, we offload 95% of
the reads from the db, dramatically
improving system performance and scale it.
We've spoken about the
first part of efficiency.
How scale and how motivation systems
can actually handle those facets.
Now the second thing that we spoke
about, especially pertaining to
notification systems, is user engagement.
Or how do we actually optimize
user engagement or retention tube?
So it's not just about
sending notifications, right?
It's about sending the right
message at the right time.
So what's important here is timing.
ML models can analyze user behavior and
identify windows of high engagement.
For example, sending messages for
lunch apps during, like for food apps
during lunchtime, nothing like it.
Second thing is personalization.
We tailor the content based on user
interest, location, and recent actions.
This increases click through rates
in instantly and dramatically.
For example, you might have noticed
that sometimes if you have a NTO
gift card in your wallet and you
are around a n some store, you see
a pop popup from your Apple wallet.
That's because you ubiquitously checks
that you are in the area and goes ahead
and pops that user notification for you.
Another thing to keep in
mind is frequency management.
We dynamically adjust how
often we notify each user.
If someone isn't engaging, we
slow down to avoid fatigue.
Brings us to our next topic, which
is cross channel coordination.
If a push call unseen for a long
time, we do follow up with an email,
making sure that we don't keep
bombarding the user, of course.
So having discussed all these topics.
What are our key takeaways
from this presentation?
Let's summarize the key ideas here.
Starting off with scale.
Again.
Designed for extreme scale,
built for five to 10 times of the
expected peak using distributed
microservices, built and resilience.
Use circuit breakers, retries,
and isolation to protect
against catastrophic failures.
Optimize for latency.
Use caching and sharding to keep
delivery times under 15 milliseconds.
Lastly, maximize engagement.
Obtain delivery by timing,
content frequency, and channel
realtime notification systems
aren't just technical challenges.
They're critical to a user
experience and business success.
Thank you.
For.
So thank you so much for all your time.
I hope you had a practical look into
how we build and operate large scale,
real time notification systems.
If you are working on something
similar or just wanna geek out on
distributed systems, I'd love to connect.
Please feel free to reach out to
me after the session or online.
Thanks again and.