Speaker 20: Hi viewers, this is
Vivek Senter, Director of Engineer
at Sunland Logistics Solution.
Thanks for attending my, my session in
Conference Golang twenty twenty-six.
My topic for today is Data-Driven
Warehouse Design for Scalable
Risk Resilient 3PL RFP.
As a warehousing service provider,
it is very important to turn around
RFP, and it is very time sensitive
as well, so speed is important.
But in this process, few of the 3PL
misses an approach which is looking at
the data and making sure what data tells
rather than have putting some assumptions.
So this is where I'm-- I, I came in,
and I, I, I think this is helpful to
understand the framework to how to
approach the RFP so that we can make a,
make a solution and a cost that could
be transferred or transition to 3P...
uh, to implementation and
eventually to operation.
And this will also help the customer
to see the inputs and have, have a
traceability of all the cost, which will
build trust and long-term partnership.
So the problem with generic proposal.
So like I said, with the time, with
the crunch of time, RFPs are being,
uh, being costed based on assumption,
misaligned fulfillment strategy,
and indefensible cost structure.
What that means.
That means when the RFP comes in, rather
than looking at the, at the profile of the
business, rather than understanding the
business, team replicate some of the...
Based on the previous experience, team
replicates some assumptions from the
other businesses and make up, make up
assumption on the strategies as well
that does not align with the current
business that we are putting the RFP for.
That leads to, that leads to have a
disconnect, uh, between the pricing that
is shared versus what is the reality.
And this, uh, this, this thing, uh,
challenges, uh, c- the challenges
comes, uh, afterwards in a real-world
operation and during the startup.
A-again, risk in, uh,
partnership, uh, deterioration
In order to avoid that, th-uh, this is
the framework that companies should follow
and solution engineers should follow.
This has a s-six-layer methodal--
methodology, and it start with throughput.
Throughput converts into order
profiling and SKU profiling, and
that will yield the layout design.
Once these four stages are
done, all these inputs go, uh...
Based on these inputs, we will calculate
our, our labor and equipment and then
system tech-- uh, system, uh, workflow
so that we have a detailed solution.
Layer one, throughput analysis.
Uh, in order to understand the ca-the
capacity for the business, uh, required,
we need to understand what is the
throughput and volume that comes, uh,
for that warehouse, which means we need
to know how much inbound per day we are
getting, if there's any peak, uh, meaning
if there is any high volume or variation
in volume on a daily basis, and what are
the pallets that are being hand-handled.
In terms of outbound, we need
to understand the daily capacity
of orders we are getting.
What are the patterns of shipment?
Uh, for example, if we are getting...
If there's any seasonality of that
business, and then the order complexity,
meaning how many lines per order are
we, we are kind of, uh, working with.
This will yield or ha-have, uh, make us,
uh, give us a better understanding on
the, on the capacity of the business,
which will help us eventually to
calculate the right labor modeling.
Through, uh, throughput analysis
defines the true capacity requirement
and the foundation of every
other design decision rests on.
Layer two, order profile analysis.
What is order profile analysis?
Order profile analysis is dictating how
the customer is reacting to that business.
Uh, what that entails is, is this,
is this, uh, is this company,
uh, the, which, uh, which we are
working on RFP on, are using,
are using, uh, retails or are
they shipping to end customers?
Is the SKU breadth, which is how
many SKUs we are shipping per day,
and how that, uh, that dictates
in the complexity of pick path.
Um, for example, if, if you have hundred
SKUs for that business versus thousand
SKU per business has a different pick
strategies and zoning strategies.
Order size distribution is tells, uh,
tell-- dictates our pick type selection.
Uh, for example, single line
orders will mostly be picked ba-
uh, in batches and segregated in
the, uh, in the end staging lanes.
And multi-line orders will be more
towards zone-based or wave picking.
This will help us... Order profile will
help us to make sure we are, we are
picking the right pick type selections
and also help the operation to, to
understand the, the nitty-gritty of,
of making decisions on the floor.
Layer three, SKU and inventory profiling.
SKU profiling is nothing but we need to
understand the specs of every SKU, and
based on the velocity-based segmentation,
we need to put them or, uh, or put
those right SKUs on the right area to
decrease the walking path for the pickers.
Uh, for the, for the velocity-based
segmentation, there are three
types of mover: fast movers,
medium movers, and slow movers.
The concept is making sure the high
movers or the fast movers are closer to
the staging lane so that we can minimize
the, uh, walking distance for the picker.
The, the lesser the walking distance
is, the more efficient the pickers
will be and our-- or hence our,
uh, solution, uh, will be more
efficient and labor efficient as well.
Layer four, warehouse
layout and storage design.
Based on these three inputs: inbound,
outbound, inventory, and order
profile, there would be a material
flow that would be designed that
complement the business needs.
And, uh, we will get a dock, a dock
configuration requirements, basically
how many staging we need for inbound
and outbound, how many door counts
we need based on the number of
containers coming in, numbers of trucks
going out, and the storage system.
Uh If we have low SKU, high inventory,
uh, chances are you will be putting
those, uh, storage system will be bulk.
If it is high SKU dense, lows--
low pallet quantities, it will be
racking or drive-in or flow racking.
That depends on, uh, inventory and how
you want to pick your orders, uh, and
how you want to put away your orders.
All three contributors, uh, play a
role in designing the storage system.
Labor modeling.
After we got to know the capacity,
the complexity of picking the orders
slash order profiling, and once we
have a material flow and the layout
ready, uh, the next step is how to
use-- how to calculate the headcount.
Few tools that we use is MTM and
MOST, uh, processes, which is nothing
but telling, uh, having a, having
a standard for, for every move or
every step that will tell you how
much time it will take for that step.
In this process, it is important to
go in details and touch every function
that will happen in the business.
Few of the examples are, uh, unloading
slash receiving, put away, replenishment,
picking, packing, and shipping.
In when, uh, when labor modeling is
happening, make... It is, it is very
important to have peak into consideration
for the annual head count, uh, an-annual,
uh, hours calculation and have a, have
a good leadership on the floor, uh, and
that will be based on the supervisor
ratios and indirect labor ratios.
Outputs feed directly into cost
modeling and facility sizing.
All the labors, uh, labor that is
calculated based on, on the, on the,
uh, other four layers, uh, uh, which
we, uh, shared in the previous slides
will, will be, uh, put in cost models.
And, uh, based on their wages, there
would be a cost will-- which will be
defined and sha-- uh, eventually shared
with the cust-- with the customer slash
the business we are working o-for.
Equipment cost and customer validation.
Based on the storage design and
the, and the pick, uh, and the order
profile, equipments will be selected.
For example, uh, and throughput as
well, equipment will be selected.
For example, um, we will have,
um, for For a daily capacity, uh,
where you have more than eighteen
pickers, three shift operation,
automa-automation will make more sense.
For example, AMR
solutions, ASRS solutions.
If you have a low volume, uh, it is,
it is worthwhile to do not to put much
automation there because the ROI will
not be there, and it is worthwhile to
look for lift trucks or any MHEs that,
uh, that is re-required for the business.
The different types of MHEs, for example,
forklift, order picker, uh, s-- uh,
stand downs, and, uh, pallet riders.
Any, uh... Based on your business
needs, uh, there should be
equipment selections as well.
Transparent cost building.
The labor, equipment, and fas-- and the
storage that we, uh, we calculated based
on the data should be dictated and, and
eventually should be explained by cost.
Inputs defines output.
For this, uh, this, uh, this one,
input is your throughput, your how
much square footage of space you
need, what type of infrastructure
and e-- uh, equipment you need in...
for this business, and
that will dictate the cost.
This should be traceable enough, uh,
for the customer so that, so that they
can get, uh, they can have a confidence
in the solution and also the costing.
Customer validation.
This is an important part.
Once the solution is made, uh, once the
throughput, order profile, the layout, and
labor is calculated, it is important to
validate those numbers with the customer
before costing them out so that you have
a buy-off from the customer as well.
In the quick turnaround of RFPs, uh,
it is, it is ve-- it-- this is crucial
to, to understand that customer knows
their business, and it is important
to get their insights for every step.
Data continuity.
Once, once you have the costing and
you have the, uh, the whole proposal
ready for the RFP to select, make sure,
think about the future, how it
will entails in implementation
planning and smooth transition
from the award to go live.
These data points that we have discussed
earlier and then work that we have
done, this should be documented in
a way where it could be transitioned
easily to the next department
for them to execute this project
What we learned from all of this.
RFPs are crucial, and it is, uh, it is
the very first step for the partnership.
What we need to do is projects
are being defined in a detailed
data, uh, with the data, uh,
summarized or analytical approach.
Every des- design, decision
storage, there should be a, uh,
labor and, uh, and cost flows for
actual customer operational data.
Attention to detail is, is needed.
Credibility reduces risk.
If we have explanation or traceability
for all the cost structure and ex-- uh,
that will build the trust to the-- for the
customer on the solution plus the costing.
Continuity accelerates go live.
Once we, once we win the, win the
business, this data, the propo-- uh,
the solution design should be detailed
enough that it can be transitioned to
implementation and, uh, and that will
help us to transition, uh, for a faster,
smoother, and lower risk, uh, projects.
Thank you.
Again, this was Vivek Sinder sharing how
to approach data-driven approach for RFPs.