Hi everyone, my name is Punit, and
today I'm going to discuss and share
some of the innovative methodologies
for timing ECO implementation
during chip physical design phase.
We can call it optimizing to timing
ECO implementation through Slack aware
post routing cell legalization and why.
this is an important aspect of PNR.
The reason behind it when we apply any
ECU during the chip timing closure or any
other phages tool, does legalization based
on the net length tool, does not consider
any requirement of looking at Slack or
any other aspect of the design in such
a scenario when tool through these cells
or anytime in critical cell far away.
It loops or looms into a new timing
violation, which creates a necessity to
discuss these kind of, things in a regular
day to day EC implementation approach.
overall, if we look at this approach,
what we can do, we can divide the
legalization process into multiple
steps and can control the legalize
in a very sophisticated way.
this methodology helps, prioritizing
some of the, negative slack cell.
Strategically, we can legalize some of the
cells and we can optimize the design in a
step by step, and we can maintain the QOR.
so to do that, we first need to understand
from where the ECO requirement comes.
ECO requirements can arise from
many places generally during
the physical design phase.
What we do, we run the p and r in
some of the dominant scenario, whereas
there can be multiple scenarios for
the timing closure need to be utilized.
If we are running our p and r,
in some scenarios, we may be
having little bit timing closure
requirement in different scenarios.
So at the end of the p and r, we
will be applying these timing, ECO,
or let us say, when we started the
design, we had some functionality
and during the design verification.
The team finds out that there is
an issue with the design and there
is a need of a logical CO to apply.
such kind of scenario can
occur and we need to apply the
CO and we need to do further,
optimization with respect to the CH.
Also, at the same time, during the
D-R-C-L-V disclosure, we need to move
sometimes cell here and there in the
design and these, requirements occur.
So let's look at the details
of this presentation.
And these, reaches to the
first of the, challenges of
the timing EC implementation.
So when we start, applying the
ECO and if in certain areas there
are so many, cells, which are
densely sitting next to each other.
And we need to insert some of the cells or
we need to upsize or downsize of the cell.
In that scenario, there is a necessity
of, moving these cells, and if these cells
moves from original location, these can
create some of the new timing violation.
So in that scenario, if we can preserve
or fix those cells and move only other
cells, we can reduce this challenge.
The second thing, this comes from in a
conventional, pla placement algorithm.
What we have noticed, generally, that
tool does not consider timing and it
keep adding, the new violations when it
moves the cells here and there where it
can find a place to move those cells.
the third scenario can be where we
see that there are congested areas.
Let us say to fix the whole timing
violation tool, need to insert one more
buffer and tool cannot find it, and it
puts that cell pretty much far away.
In that scenario, what can happen, the
net routed from that newly inserted
cell can cause additional violation.
It may be the set setup, or
either the whole violation.
Sometimes you have seen
because of the crosstalk.
So what are the ECO corrective
actions we take in that scenario?
as I mentioned, we do sell up saging,
based on the setup requirement,
to improve the timing margins.
We do insert new cells based on,
if we need to insert the buffer or
during the logical ECO, let us say,
we can introduce some logical gates.
And we need to do very careful placement
if it is a congested region, even.
In other case, we need to place next
to each other so that we can reduce
the time enclosure requirement.
And the third thing is, like we have seen
that there are cells sitting far away, and
that path is creating a timing violation.
Can we bring that cell
next to the driver cell?
And can reduce the timing,
parasitics requirements so
that we can improve that path.
So these are the some ECO
corrective actions we take
during our, p p and r phage.
Now, what is different in this approach,
what I'm explaining here, the first
thing is when tool sees, okay, there
is a buffer inserted or cell upsized.
It looks for the narrowing empty spaces
and then place the cells in those areas.
But if, let us say, if those species are
not available, what tool is going to do,
tool can throw this cell very far away
where it can create some new violation.
So how we can reduce that?
So the approach here is, run a complete,
full timing analysis on that design.
C in which area we are applying.
The ECO cells nearby, areas
can be identified where the
ECO cells will be placed.
Tag the cells with all the slacks,
do the slack filtering based on that
slack filtering, fix the critical
cells and now whatever the cells which
are unfixed and need legalization.
Move it by extreme algorithm.
And extreme algorithm means if we need
to move cell by two track, move first
cell, which is sitting nearby to the
next track, and then move this cell.
So we are displacing all the
cells by relative placement.
And then once this is done, we can go
with the IT refinement where we can.
Take some loops and can legalize
you these cells by repositioning
it again and again until less.
We do not see that timing is completely
fixed, and here we are not creating
new violations because we are
fixing most critical cells first.
Then, we are moving the least
timing critical cells, then next
level of cell, and then finally.
When everything is legalized,
we are trying to legalize the
critical cells, which were fixed.
So in this approach, we are not
creating any new violations.
Also, at the same time, we are taking care
of everything altogether without giving
any cost function to any other function.
So select based, self prioritization,
we can create, in four different
categories, as I mentioned.
The most critical slack, which are
the highest priority cells, like
generally, we keep our flops fixed.
And then moderate, critical, slack cells,
let us say if there are an end gate,
which is a three input end gate, and have
a critical connection to multiple cells.
So those can be, considered as a
secondary, critical slack cells.
Then minor, negative, select cells
and noncritical select cells.
So in this scenario, what we
can do, the category first
one cell will be hard fixed.
Second will be hard fixed.
Third will be soft fixed.
Fourth will be, unfixed.
So we'll move first the noncritical
cell legalize it, then unfix the
category, third cells legalize
it, then move the second.
Category cells and I think,
first one, we should not move.
We just can, change some of the tracks
here and there to make sure that there are
no DRC violation because of those cells.
So in such a methodology, what we can
bring that this progressive or looped
enhancement can give us a very good,
placement of these critical cells.
And we are not creating anything new
or any new violation in terms of DRC
or timing, and we are maintaining
the performance of the design.
In recent, experience, I have seen that
CPU designs or GPU designs where we are
trying to post as much edge density.
These algorithms are very useful.
The iterative legalization process,
again, as I mentioned, that we can
go fix the, all the hike, negative
slack or the critical slack cells.
Legalize the moveable cells.
Then again, we can go back,
evaluate timing, and we don't need
to run the full update timing.
We can run just some of the update cells,
which, based on the ECO cells we can run.
And, unfixed less critical cells and
then move those and then we can, ably
fix in three poor cycles, all these
timing violations and can move on.
So this methodology is not only
taking care of the timing as
well as what we can do, we can.
create a such kind of grouping where we
are maintaining the critical part timing,
as well as not creating any new DRC.
let's see, what is stream
algorithm implementation age?
We are sorting the cell based
on the priority and then
creating the order queue.
So this can be done.
we can report the max
rise slack in any tool.
Can tag it accordingly and
create a list of those cells.
We can, look into the placement
analysis, can unfix and place
the cells which are less critical
in the available ing empty area.
Then we can go for the optimal, location
selection for the rest of the cells, which
are critical so that we can other the
minimum wire length, algorithm as well.
And then we can do the
incremental timing updates.
In that scenario, we are taking care of
each and everything at the same time.
So some of the quality results, what
I have seen in the designs, based
on this approach, so WNS, which
is we call was negative slack, had
improved by 15% by utilizing this,
approach for the legalization.
So initially when, let's say design was
70% utilization, utilized and tool through
the cell somewhere far away, created a
new slack to fix that slack, inserted
some new cell, created a new slack.
So that kind of it, process took very
long, time to close because of news slack.
In this scenario, when we are
doing it very control and.
Observing all the things at the same time.
Thus, WNS improvement observed by
15% during the ECU application.
And when we are seeing good,
TNS improvement, TNS will
automatically will help improve.
And these are the things we noticed.
At the same time, when I'm taking
care of my ECO in one single sort.
And not, looking for the new ECO,
which can arise from different
kind of ECO, requirement.
So I'm reducing the whole ECO
cycle to fewer iterations.
So let us say I fixed one ECO, created
some new timing violation, fixed those,
created some new timing violation.
That process is not happening now.
So I can reduce my ECO cycle
time by say 40 to 50%, and
I'm applying fewer ecos now.
Now the runtime overhead comes
from when I'm looking at only
legalizing, only some cells.
the placer can go and legalize those
cells very fast and can come back also.
excuse me, not doing, the
complete, set of, update timing.
So that is also giving me some of
the advantage when I'm doing the
legalization or timing updates.
So these are some of the QR checks, in
seven nanometer mobile SOC implementation.
what I noticed that.
When during the EC implementation,
these things are happening.
I'm not stuffing new cells, not
putting, there is an, less need
of, putting more buffers and other
things wide drafting this algorithm.
So in those areas where ECO need
to apply, there is a huge amount
of congestion reduction happening.
By adopting these methodologies, the
violations are not ha as I mentioned that.
If we will do it very carefully,
new violation will not come.
So EC requirement also will reduce.
In that scenario, I have seen
that I'm applying only half
of the ECOS or less than that.
Also, when I'm applying very fewer
ecos, my closure timing is much faster.
So this kind of scenario I have seen,
like in CPU design, GPU design, I've
worked on neural network accelerator.
The designs were really, really congested.
And these requirements must have been
adopted and implemented in such a way.
So these are some of the advantages I
have seen in the designs, which definitely
helped me to get the chip out on time.
Yields were really nice.
when the Sleen came back, we did not see
much of the problems since we have taken
care of all these things at the same time.
So some of the implementation
consideration for these kind of
methodologies, what we can see that
when we are going, in partial EC
implementation and doing step by
step partial implementation of,
legalization and timing closure.
And then, again, running
routing and looking it back.
We have a runtime optimization, scenario
where we can, look at very specific
area, target those for implementation,
and can definitely improve the accuracy.
These, flows can be, or methodologies can
be, integrate in the flows very easily.
So I have written some, tick script,
which tool can read and can write also.
And then based on that we can write CSV
file to list the cells, slacks, and keep.
We can do some kind of sorting
based on and tool can read it
back and can apply the algorithm.
So very easy to use.
From the integration perspective or we
can apply in an existing flows as well
as we can develop some new methodologies.
Parameter tuning is another thing, like
lot of things, can be guided by the tool
also, like some of the stream commands,
tool already hedged int inside, so we
can call those commands and can utilize.
To do these kind of ECO.
conclusion here is, so in this scenario,
when we are doing this time enclosure, it
significantly improves the predictivity.
It definitely reduces a lot of
ECO attrition and that when we are
looking at very high frequency,
highly congested designs.
This is the only way to go
for any ECU application.
in the industry.
I have worked on seven nanometer
design, five nanometer design, and
lower node of high performance designs.
This is really, important and,
lot of industry applications are
there in other designs as well.
in future there can be, Lot of things
added on these, top of, this algorithm.
so some of the things like if we are
looking at power, if we are looking
at area, so these legalization schemes
can help in those aspects as well.
So this methodology, overall
I'll say, presents a new era
of legalization for ECO cells.
Also helps in all kind of, PP aspect
of the designs and can be easily
integrated and connected to any flow in
any technology based on the requirement.
this is all, from my side for today and
thank you very much for listening to me.
Please, feel free to reach out
to me if you have any question.
Thanks.
Have a great day.
Bye.