Hello everyone.
this is Mohi with 17 years
of experience in IT industry.
today I'm gonna talk about
OCR technology and how it is
considered as the cornerstone of
modern intelligent automation.
let's start with what is O-C-R-O-C-R, also
known as optical character recognition.
Is a technology that converts
images of texts, like scan documents
or photos into machine learning,
machine readable editable text.
What it does it allow you to search, copy
and edit text from images, making them
more, readable, accessible, and usable.
OCR enables intelligent automation
by digitizing and processing
document based information.
OCR was valued as at a massive 9.3 billion
in 2022 with strong growth expected
by 2030 due to increased demand of
automation and digital transformation.
So that, coming to the topics that I'll
be covering today, I'll be covering today
the technical foundation, which, in turns
cover how the OCR system actually work.
we'll also be talking about the framework
of using OCR in different industries,
and the practical industry application
in, healthcare, finance, legal, and also
we'll talk about education sector as well.
finally we'll discuss how OCR enhances
efficiency and digital transformation
across these various sectors.
coming to the slide, two.
this shows, the, graph shows additional
adoption, rate across various, continents.
as it shows, the North America has the
highest adoption rate, of 82%, followed by
Europe, which is 78, and then followed by
Asia Pacific around 65, person, which is
the most emerging potential, that OCR has.
news research has shown that AI and
machine learning integrate, integration
boost OCR growth, and it's gonna be,
gonna do it in the coming years as well.
deep learning based OCR
solution shows high potential.
and it's also being discovered that
banking, and financial service,
which is BFSI domain, has the
largest market share in 2022.
coming to, how this OCR technical
architecture, works and what
are the stages involved in it?
coming to the first stage, which is known
as image pre-processing, this stage also,
can be subdivided into further sub stages.
let's talk about that first.
the first, sub stages ization.
Which convert the gray scale image
to binary using adaptive thresholding
to handle the, lighting variations.
The second sub stage is orientation
correction, which detects and, correct
the SKUs using, HOF transformation
and, projection profile analysis.
The third sub stage is noise reduction,
which is a very important stage.
in pre-processing.
It removes artifacts
using, median filtering.
Gaussian smoothing and,
more follicle operation.
I've used some heavy terms here.
I understand that.
so let's, take a small
deep dive in into it.
What is like gian smoothing?
it's a technique, that
blurs the images or data.
By applying, Gaussian function
effectively, it reduces
the noise and detail while
preserving the overall structure.
I also talked about,
more follicle operation.
What exactly it is?
It is again, a set of, the non-linear
filters, that analyze and modify
shapes with operation, including
erosion dilation, opening and
closing, coming to the fourth,
substrate, which is a resolution
enhancement, which is self-explanatory.
That is, it improves a low resolution
images using super resolution
and sampling and interpolation.
Now, what is the impact of pre-processing?
Alright, so it enhances the OCR
accuracy by up, by almost like 35%.
It also reduces the
error rate by 40 to 60%.
Especially for the degraded or low
quality document, and that is why
it's a very important stage of, OCR
coming, to the second, stage, which is
feature, extraction and recognition.
coming to this, what it does, it,
it just converts the, raw image
into the recognizable features.
It uses, again, uses, geometrical
features like shapes, angles,
strokes, and, topological features
like whole endpoint junctions, to
effectively, scan the document, right?
it also uses some complex scripts
and, what it also, the second, stage
of this, is character segmentation.
What it does is it identifies the
characters using connected component
analysis and clustering algorithm.
yeah, let me just, go through it.
what it means.
clustering, clustering algorithm, it is
again a method, used in unsupervised,
machine learning to group, similar,
data points into clusters or groups,
based on their characteristics without
any prior knowledge of the group.
and also it also improves handling
of vertical and horizontal text
coming to pattern recognition.
it uses some, some, again, some
algorithms, template matching and
adaptive algorithms to do that.
it, neural networks also improves,
recognition across various character sets.
And multiple classifier approach
approaches enhance, accuracy,
coming to the third, and the, the
stage which is post, processing.
again, a very important stage of OCR.
it represents a final critical
refinement, layer in modern OCR.
Again, it refines raw
O-C-R-O-T, OCR output into high
confidence and accurate text.
what are the techniques which are used?
It uses contextual understanding and
probability stick analysis to correct
the errors and what's the impact of it?
it, it is used to, make the
document or the OSHA technology.
Accurate, which is almost
like 95.8% accuracy.
It reduces the errors by almost 82%.
And it outperforms image
pre-processing, which is 92.5% in
feature extraction, 88 point, 7%.
key role of, post-processing is,
it elevates OCR from functional
to exceptional, performance.
now since we've gone through all
the stages of OCR, let's see, what's
a practical, implementation, which
is used in various industries?
let's first talk about, healthcare,
which is my favorite one.
how is used, what it is used for?
the very first thing that it's used for
is medical, record management, which,
where it reduces the manual entry errors.
It digitizes the patient records,
prescription insurance form and whatnot.
another thing is it provides,
clinical decision support.
It helps the doctors and access the
historical patient, data very easily.
It also provides the cr, it's very
crucial for the emergency care to provide
very quick treatment, to the patients.
the third implementation, use is
the laboratory result management,
which enables, fast and accurate,
access to the test results.
It ensures, HIPAA compliance
and reduces delays.
We all are aware how much,
importance, HIPAA compliant
has in the healthcare sector.
so it, it takes care of that.
It improves, the patient outcomes as well.
So this is all about the healthcare
sector, coming to the financial, sector.
let's first see the key,
highlights about it.
we have seen that in financial
sector, what it does, it, it
provides, 92.7% processing efficiency.
what I mean by that?
It is, it paper-based, paper-based,
processes are not, converted to digital,
reducing the bottleneck and resource use.
It also gives 99.1%, document accuracy.
so OCR technology ensures nearly
perfect accuracy in this case,
in document processing, reducing
errors, compliant risk, and whatnot.
it also, has, 76.8%, time reduction.
processing times have drastically
dis, decreased, enabling the
same day service for transaction.
That one stop days.
third key highlight is
90.3% user satisfaction.
financial professionals, report
high satisfaction with the OCR
system, praising improved workflow
and less, administrative work.
key impact of OCR in financial sector.
coming to that.
from the audit perspective, what
it does for them is OCR reduces
the audit preparation time, up
to 70, 70%, from the client.
compliance perspective,
intelligence system flags,
regulatory issues in real time.
in banking, it's been seen
that oia speed up the customer
identification verification.
cutting.
it also cut down the onboarding times
and improves our fraud detection
and customer experience as well.
coming to the third, sector, which
is a lock, legal document management.
so what it does is OCR does, document
digitization, which is OCR technology,
speed up their digitization, and analysis
of legal document like contracts.
code filing and the case papers.
It also helps in a litigation support,
which is a good, very good, nice feature,
which OCR enables a faster document,
discovery by allowing, quick searches
and analysis of, large document set,
cutting down again on the manual effort.
It, it also performs some
regulatory compliance.
it automated document analysis, ensuring
compliance with legal, requirement and
deadline, while, maintaining the accuracy.
It also does improves,
their legal research.
OCR again improves legal research by
making historical case documents and
legal reference easier to find and
access, which again improves a lot
of time for, The fourth sector, which
is our education technology, right?
And, what it does there is the very nice
feature that, OCI provides, to them is
converting, speech, text to speech, right?
And it, what it does for,
the visual impairments.
Impaired people.
it's a boom to them, right?
it gives them high, accurate and,
whatever they, because they can't go
through the documents, provides the
speech, whatever they want to go through.
Another use case, also is
listening to books while driving.
So OCF plays very important role
in, in those sort of technologies.
and the second, key factor is
digital research, repository.
OCR helps convert archive documents
into searchable digital formats.
it may making the educational
resources easily available to
the students and researchers.
the third, important point here is the,
it also auto automate the assessment.
So OCR, that's it, streamlined the grading
of the handwritten assignments, reducing
administrative work for educators,
and speeding up feedback for students.
they can easily, the, the time that
is, needed for an as assessment
to be done is greatly reduced.
which is very beneficial for all the,
students and the researchers, coming
to the cross sector analysis, right?
We have gone through all the four
sectors, healthcare, financial services.
We've gone through the
legal and the education.
I. As you see in this
particular table, right?
all the sectors are broken down into
what is the percentage of profic,
processing efficiency, the document
accuracy, what's the, percentage and
time reduction, digital conversion
rate, and the user satisfaction.
So let's, let's go through
what this table, states, right?
And then we'll follow by what
insights we can derive from it, right?
now if you see the first one, which is
a healthcare one, healthcare sector, it
has a very strong, document accuracy of
98.2% and solid, pro, what you call as,
processing efficiency, which is only
85% with a time reduction of 72.5%.
coming to our second
sector, which was financial.
It leads in performing with the
highest document accuracy, which
is a nine, which is 99.1%, and pro
processing efficiency of 92 7, along
with the, time reduction off, 76.8%.
coming to the legal one, it has
a good performance where's 97.8%
document accuracy with, and,
88.4% processing efficiency.
It has some, little lower, time reduction,
which is 70.2%, but very much acceptable.
coming to education, it has lower
processing efficiency of 82.6%,
but very high user satisfaction.
If you see there, it's an
89%, and, 65%, time reduction.
So what we can derive from this particular
table right across various sectors.
financial services excel
in most categories.
That's the second rule that we can see.
we also see that healthcare, shows
strong document accuracy, which
is used to diagnose, diagnose
a prescription and whatnot.
coming to education, it has
very high satis, satisfaction
despite low efficiency.
which works in favors of edu, favor
of education sector and all the
sector experience, significant time
saving compared to manual process.
going to the next page, which is, what
is the future development and integration
challenges that OCR, has, right?
So it's been shown, like the
deep learning integration.
it's currently deep
learning machine learning.
It's, it's in demand.
it's going on.
There's a strong acceptance rate and
it's also with, in combination with OCR.
It is it's gonna improve the
feature extraction and pattern
recognition, which will again enhance.
everything in OCR, in all the all sectors.
and regarding the second future
development that we see is a multilingual
recognition, handling diverse
character sets and writing system.
Third one is a edge computing
deployment, which is optimizing models
for devices and limited resources,
regarding, data quality management.
It has better, it'll be better
people processing for handling
that document variation.
the fifth one is a security
framework protected how
important it is in all sector.
We are, we, everyone is aware of,
so it pro provide the protecting,
sensitive information, right?
So what we derive from it, right?
What are the key insights,
regarding the future?
as we see here, right?
OCR technology advancing, quickly,
driven by AI and, deep learning
challenges include, know, balancing,
security, accuracy and scalability.
which, along with ai,
it's gonna improve a lot.
Future, OCS system will go
beyond character recognition to
include contextual understanding.
Multi-format processing
and real time analytics.
how important is analytics
in all the industries?
I don't think I have to explain, to
anyone, but, so it's gonna be a really
great combination of OCR with, there
are deep learning, multilingual and
machine, machine learning in the future.
And these advances will revolutionize, in
our digital sector, operations in sectors
like healthcare, again, finance, legal and
education, which again, which reducing the
manual work and unlocking new insights.
here I come to an end of
the, this, my presentation.
thank you for listening in.
hope you gain some insight
about OCR, and happy learning.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.