Hey everyone, and welcome
to Con 42 Golang 2025.
I'm Banini, and today I want to take
you on a journey through one of the
most promising areas in cloud security
called confidential computing.
We'll see how it's not just a buzzword,
but a practical production ready
approach to running secure workloads.
And how Go happens to be an incredible
tool for building in this space.
Just to set the context, I am
currently a senior software engineer
at Walmart Global Tech, where I work on
scaling secure distributed platforms.
Most of my work sits at the intersection
of cloud native infrastructure.
Security and performance.
I work with tools like Go Kubernetes
and various encryption frameworks on a
daily basis, and that's why confidential
computing caught my attention because, it
allows us to design systems where trust
is built in and not just assumed and
go is a surprisingly good fit for that.
So let's begin by talking
about why, this even matters.
So over the past decade, our systems have
exploded in complexity, microservices,
APIs, cloud Edge, et cetera, right?
That came into, popularity and
there has been a wide usage of
those in the enterprise industry.
But, with that growth, our attack
surface has also, grown, massively.
So today the average enterprise sees a 2.5
x annual increase in attack entry points.
And here's the kicker.
Nearly 80% of data breaches
involve privileged access misuse.
This means, attackers aren't always
breaking in from the outside.
They're just misusing
what's already trusted.
So with that in mind, traditional
perimeter security like firewalls,
VPNs, IM, which is, which are widely
used, today in all the enterprises.
enterprise orgs, it's no longer enough.
What we need is a way to protect data even
when the infrastructure is compromised.
That's exactly where confidential
computing enters a picture.
So foundations of these at the core
of confidential computing are trusted
execution environments are simply.
Dees, think of them as a lockbox
inside your CPUA place where
sensitive code and data can execute
isolated from the rest of the system.
Three things make Dees powerful.
They are isolation,
attestation, and encryption.
Sorry about that.
Let's talk about, each of them isolation.
Even if someone has, due taxes,
they can't peek into the enclave
and coming to the attestation, you
can prove that only trusted verified
code is running inside the enclave.
And lastly, encryption data remains
protected at all stages, addressed
in memory and during execution.
So with all these.
It's zero trust implemented
at the hardware level.
Now here's the interesting,
interesting twist.
Why should we use go in this space?
There are many languages, available
Java, scaler or any other languages
like Python, low level languages
like c. C plus rust, et cetera.
So Dees are typically
associated with C or rust.
that is, low level system languages.
But go is quietly carving an issue.
Y first go has a tiny runtime footprint.
This makes it ideal for running
inside resource constraint
environments like Cleves Second.
Goals type, safety and simple
syntax reduce the chances of memory,
corruption, or security bugs.
These are huge ones when
working in trusted environments.
And goes concurrency
model with go routines.
Let us write parallel workloads that are
still lightweight enough to run securely.
So with all these, the balance go
strikes between developer simplicity
and system level efficiency makes
it a great fit for the domain.
So now coming to the performance
breakthroughs, right?
One of the common criticisms of Dees
used to be performance, and rightly
early implementations were slow back
in 2018, as you see in the graph,
running code inside an ink leaf could
add up to 35% performance overhead.
That's a lot, but just five years later.
We are down to around 4%
overhead on modern hardware.
That's a game changer, right?
Combined with course efficient memory
handling and over, low overhead.
It, finally makes sense, to
that the confidential computing,
is practical for production
workloads, not just any prototypes.
Coding inside ENC Cleaves.
So let's talk implementation.
How does this actually work in practice
when you're writing Go code for Es, right?
The basic flow usually looks like this.
You initialize the enclave, which sets
up a isolated memory space and generates
secure keys, and then comes attestation.
You prove cryptographically that the
code inside is what it's supposed to be.
And once verified, you run your sensitive
logic, maybe decrypting your data,
processing it or applying analytics.
And finally you seal the results, meaning,
they're encrypted before leaving the ncl.
So ghost structure
actually helps a lot here.
It's easy to build.
Clean state machines, modularize logic,
and right secure test around these stages.
So enclaves and microservice architecture.
Now, not everything needs to
be run in an enclave, right?
And that's the key.
So let's take for example.
In a microservice architecture,
there might be many services, And
some might be, very sensitive data,
which needs to be part of the Cleve.
And some should be fine.
even if it is, running outside and
even if it is compromised, there is
nothing much that we would lose, right?
So keeping that in mind, in a
microservice architecture, we
take our targeted approach.
For secure data ingestion,
we encrypt data at entry.
And for sensitive logic, like working
with PII, personal information,
we run it inside the enclave.
And supporting services can
handle buying, blind processing
on enc, encrypted payloads.
And finally, the authorized
delivery phase, decrypts results
only for verified consumers.
This modular security lets you
protect only what's critical,
minimizing the performance hit
while maximizing data protection.
Perfect.
So one question I've heard a
lot, I've seen a lot in different
discussion channels around this
topic is, can we actually integrate
this into DevOps pipelines?
And the answer is yes, and the
tooling is maturing really fast.
You can enforce attestation checks
before workloads are deployed, and
Kubernetes operators can now orchestrate
NLA workloads using extended CRDs and
tools like HashiCorp Vault support,
enclave packed secret distribution.
And with hardware support, secure
boot tpms and remote attestation,
it's becoming feasible to run
trusted workloads at scale.
So with all these, it opens up
confidential computing to cloud native
workflows, and that's a major win.
And, not just tightly
controlled environments.
So that gives us, the advantage
over the cloud native workflows in
setting up seamless integrations.
And then let's look at a real
world scenario now, right?
like analytics on encrypted data.
So the flow would look like,
we ingest encrypted data, say
from users or edge devices.
The data flows into a TEE based
analytics engine, and inside the
enclave data is decrypted analyzed
and the results are sealed.
Again, only end points with
proper identity and attestation
can read the final output.
What does this do?
So with this proper flow that
we discussed here, it creates a
zero trust analytics pipeline.
Perfect for industries like healthcare,
finance, or multi-tenant SaaS where data
separation and privacy are critical.
Alright, now, engineering challenges,
of course, this, isn't a silver bullet.
There are challenges and those
would be side, channel attacks.
So these are still a risk.
They require careful engineering
and mitigation at both
hardware and software layers.
Then comes the remote attestation
where it becomes complex across large
clusters or hybrid environments.
And then key distribution is especially
hard when dealing with isolated nodes.
And secure channels must be
established without exposing secrets
and designing minimal APIs between
enclave and non enclave code is
critical to reduce data leakage risks.
So these, all, these are Aren
easy problems, but the open source
community is making real progress
and projects like, NA and grammar.
And secure key orchestration layers
are paving the way for all this.
All right, so with all that,
the next question, next question
comes where are we headed?
So the future is shaping up
to be even more powerful.
So we are seeing multi-party computation
that will let us analyze joint data sets.
Without ever exposing raw data.
And then we have confidential containers,
which will allow us to deploy secure
workloads with minimal friction, and then
specialized chips and TEE acceleration
will bring near native performance.
And all in all, zero knowledge proofs will
let us verify correctness of computations.
Without revealing any inputs, and with all
these go as a language is evolving right
along with it, it has the simplicity,
speed, and structure to be at the heart
of trusted systems in this new era.
Great.
And with that, thank you.
I hope this session gave you a clear
view into why confidential computing
matters and how go can be a key
enabler of building secure systems
that are cloud native and future ready.
If you are curious, experimenting,
or building something in the space.
I would love to hear from you,
and you can find me on LinkedIn
at linkedin.com/in/banini.
Or you can scan the QR code,
present here and you'll land
directly into my LinkedIn profile.
Thanks for listening and enjoy
the rest of, con 42 Golan, 2025.