Hey everybody, welcome to this session.
we are going to talk about
cloud computing, edge
computing and web assembly.
I am Alex.
great to join the conference today.
what are we going to talk about?
we'll go through.
Some quick history just to make
sure we are on the same page about
cloud and edge and what is web
assembly and all of that fun stuff.
And then we dive into the Wasm Plus
Edge, and I'm going to also share,
prac practical, real world use case
about, doing Wasm at the edge at.
Edgy, which is the company I work for.
I'm Alex.
I'm a software engineer from Italy.
I've joined a few different
companies in the last 10 years
from the eCommerce world at Cloud
Academy to AWS, for about six years.
And today I'm a developer
advocate at edgy.
I'll tell you more about what Edge
is in a, in a few minutes, but
let's start from the fundamentals.
what do we actually mean?
When we say edge computing because,
in my opinion it's quite a large
umbrella, term that can mean different
things in different contexts.
So what I want to focus on is the
web development, the web world.
if you're a web developer, if
you build websites or APIs, edge
computing problem means to you.
code that can run in a almost serverless
fashion on top of, global networks
or content delivery networks, the
Fastly or the CloudFlare of the world.
there are a lot of other
meetings for the term.
you probably have heard about edge
computing in the context of IOT.
devices or other, subcategories of that
world, like telecom 5G gaming, virtual
reality, smart retail, smart vehicles.
there are a lot of smart things
where you take some computation that
traditionally happens in a centralized
data center and you try to move it.
Somewhere else to the edge of the
network on a or on a iot device,
for example, or a smart device.
We are not talking so much about that
today, although some of the things
that we see do apply now to understand.
How we got where we are, where we
are today about edge computing and
all the things we all talk about.
It's important, in my opinion,
to look at the cloud history.
Now, this is very ancient history.
If you're curious about that,
pause the video, have a quick look.
There are some interesting milestones
in the last 50, 60, 70 years.
I'm not going through all of that.
Let's look together at
some more recent history.
in the last.
15, 20 years.
The cloud, started existing, around
2 0 0 6 AWS came up, and then all the
other vendors followed up from Google
to Azure to the open source, world.
And then Docker came.
And if you look at the pattern, we
went from barebone virtualization to.
virtual machines that could start
up in minutes on the, in the cloud.
And then we went from that, from
the virtual machines to containers,
the Kubernetes and all the different
managed container services out there.
And about 10 years ago, in 20 14,
20 15, we went from containers
to serverless functions.
they coexisted, the two communities
are now re converging back together.
luckily.
but this idea of running functions.
In a serverless fashion where your code
just pins up runs for, I don't know, a
hundred milliseconds and then shuts down.
And so this different computing model
came up about, in the last 10 years
and they've been evolving together.
now most of these vendors are
just trying to sell you ai.
But until a few years ago,
they deeply cared about compute
models and compute obstructions.
And what is the next thing and another
interesting evolution that happened.
A kind of, in parallel, but for
some people, including myself,
it happened behind the scenes
without a lot of people noticing.
A trend is the evolution of
content delivery networks too.
most of these were born to provide
simple content delivery or security
DDoS production, for example.
and some of these companies are as
old as Google, from 19 88, 19 89.
Akamai, for example, was born, the
same year as Google, so they've
been around for a lot of time.
and there used to be various ways
to implement custom logic on top
of these global delivery networks.
They were optimized for, again,
delivering content, caching
content, helping you with streaming,
especially, in the last few years.
that grew a lot.
maybe you've heard of things like
the varnish configuration language
that allow you to do, more dynamic
logic directly at the edge.
But, so this was the edge until, say,
10 years ago people used CDNs for
caching, but then something happened.
And look at the years, it's
all about, 2016 to 2019.
This idea of running, the edge workers
or the CloudFlare workers, or the Lambda
Edge or CloudFront functions in the AWS
world or the Fastly Compute platform, the
idea of running code directly on top of
the hundreds and hundreds of points of
presence became more and more popular.
and this all kind of aligned to the
revolution of the serverless, mindset
where you could just spin up a function,
run it, take care of some business logic
in a few milliseconds, and then shut down.
So it aligned to that, change, after
20 14, 20 15, Now there are many
different technologies behind the hood.
And another interesting fact is that
when you finally have compute somewhere,
it's not long until you have additional
services, like key value store databases,
AOC domain specific services like image.
optimization and compression.
You have databases, queues,
object storage, configuration
management, services and so on.
So if you look at this from the
perspective of the cloud computing
world, it's almost as if, and some
people will tell you it's exactly
as if, many c DM providers became.
Cloud computing providers themselves.
'cause now they offer you not just caching
and CDN and content delivery, they offer
you everything from compute to databases,
queues, object storage, and so on.
So the difference between edge computing
and cloud computing is blurring.
if you see the pattern that
happened in the last few years.
Now, another interesting.
A pillar of this talk is web
assembly, where if you have
never heard of it, don't worry.
I'm going to try and cover the basics
and make sure everybody's on the same
page if you have never heard of it, I
believe it's possibly one of the most
interesting development in the web space
of the last few years, as we'll see later.
Some cloud and edge providers
already allow you to deploy.
Was.
Applications to their computer platforms.
to recap its evolution, it was announced
in 2015 and then released in 2017.
So it's been around for a while.
It became a W three C
recommendation in 2019.
That's a bit more recent and
there is still a lot happening.
So it's not, it's still
evolving, it's still changing,
and adoption is still, growing.
So a lot of people talk about web assembly
in the context of running binary files
in the browser, and that's amazing.
You can do incredible things
where you compile, super
efficient, see or rust or go.
Library or algorithm into a binary file,
web assembly file that then you can take
and run anywhere else 'cause you have full
portability and one of the places where
you can run this is in the browser, but
that's not what we're talking about today.
We are talking about servers, li,
service side, execution of web assembly,
which also has a lot of potential.
Including at the Edge, of course,
now you may already know the
Wasm support a lot of different
languages, from Java to TypeScript,
PHPC, sharp, go Rust, and so on.
It's probably the most interesting and
more common pattern is where you implement
something complex or competitionally.
Complex in a compiled language like
CC plus rust or go, and then you use
that web assembly component or web
assembly module, into another language
since you have full portability now.
Some mandatory quote here in 2019, when it
reached, W three CA recommendation status.
The founder of Docker, wrote
that if was and Wze, and we'll
see what Wze is in a second.
If they existed back in 2018,
they wouldn't have had to create
Docker in the first place.
So this is just to give you some
perspective of how much potential
there is and how much the industry.
It is trying to, adopt it and
see what's possible with it.
now, there is a lot of
online documentation.
Most things in the web assembly,
if not all things are open source.
So you find, design decisions on
GI and a lot of documentation.
the second interesting part of the full
picture, in addition to WebAssembly, is.
Azi, which is the web
assembly system interface.
It's basically a collection of APIs
that allow a, was and run time to
interact with the operating system.
So you get all the benefits of interacting
with the file system, with the network,
with the, threading APIs, sockets, all
the operating system calls that you would
not normally not have in wasn't now.
the vision for some people here is
that was and will become the defacto
standard for backend development.
And that's a bold vision, right?
It start to replace the Docker or
the Kubernetes, but they're actually
already coexisting if you look at
some of the registries and, and
services up there already support.
wasm, containers, for example.
there is also the wasm component
model, which is a more recent way
to build, not modules or entire
applications, but component that
are meant to be, composed and reused
across, applications and modules.
Now some of the benefits that you may
have heard, but let's dive a bit deeper.
You have full portability
when I compile into Asom.
I can take that binary file and use it
literally anywhere in other operating
systems, in other architectures and so on.
So this kind of the dream, you probably
saw it decades ago, with the Java
world as well, differences, here the.
The kind of layer of the operating
system is much smaller and the
startup time is super, super fast
and you get near native performance.
So some of these benefits are
super useful for cloud and edge
deployments as we'll see later.
And another, and probably my favorite.
Another interesting feature of Wasm
is that you have secure sandboxing
by default, meaning your code doesn't
have access to anything by default.
So you can't just do an H TT
P call or a file system call.
You have to explicitly provide access
to those APIs, and that's incredibly
useful, especially if your final goal as
a vendor, as a provider, as a platform
is to be able to run untrusted code.
And we'll, look into that later.
Now, let's look into the Go Support.
wasm has been supported as a target
since 2018, since version one point 11.
the official tool chain here,
I. Also provides, JavaScript
utilities to facilitate.
running was modules in the browser
if that's what you want to do.
for many people like us at Edgy,
we are doing only server side,
so that's not, super useful.
I'm also sharing some links, feel
free to check them out, to dive a
bit deeper into some of these topics.
now the component model and
the WZ support is a bit behind.
It's been.
In experimental status, since,
2023 in version one, point 21.
So there was the preview one.
There are currently two was
the P one and the P two.
but.
There is support for Wasi P two.
So the preview two of Wasi in Tiny Go.
So typically you want to do
a tiny Go application or you
want to use Tiny Go to Compile.
And an additional thing you probably
need, if you are using your own interfaces
or even the default ones, is that you
want to use Wi Bind Gen Go to generate.
the kind of the bindings for the
interfaces and so there is a lot
of co-generation involved as well.
wit.
Is the way that you define
interfaces in the azi world.
So you pretty much have some standard
interfaces that interface with the
operating system, like file system
sockets, HTTP, network calls.
Clocks random randomness.
And so you can also define your own
width interfaces because this is a, an
actual interface definition language.
so for example, that's something
we are doing at Edge as well.
We are defining our own domain
specific interfaces so that.
we can then allow developers to build
their own components that implement the
interface that we defined, and we can,
run those components, in our platform.
another interesting development from
I think a couple months ago, yeah, a
few weeks ago, is that Google announced
expanded support in version 1 24 of Go.
So there are better ways
to explore functions to, go
functions to web assembly.
And so that allows you a deeper
integration with a web assembly
host that's super useful if you
are building modules or components.
in the same article, and this
is something I initially missed
myself, they also announced that.
Wasm at the Edge is supported in the
Google pla, Google Cloud platform.
This is super interesting 'cause
they now allow you to use service
extensions implemented in web assembly,
in their application load balancer.
So you can add, custom code
and custom logic in the path of
the, in the request response.
Path.
I think that's an incredibly cool
example of what is possible with
WebAssembly and also how cloud providers
or platforms in general can use it
to extend the service capabilities.
Now, of course, you also find
official was wasm run times,
for example, wasm time here.
and these run times are, Explicitly
designed for, speed and security
and easy of configuration, and was
it support So you don't have to
re-implement the wheel every time, just
add a little layer of, was on time.
And that simplifies a lot of things.
so for example, here was on
time is designed and developed
by the, bio Code Alliance.
If you've never heard of the Bike
Alliance, they are nonprofit.
They're working on a lot of
different toolings like called RS
and runtime and additional language
specific tooling for web assembly.
It.
they are supported by a lot
of tech companies out there.
You probably recognize some of the logos.
many of these are cloud providers,
edge CDM providers or even
Wasm, native, wasm platforms.
So there is a lot of.
work happening in this space.
feel free to check it out
on the website as well.
now we have the basics.
We know everything about edge computing
and how we got here with the compute
platforms and with all the additional
services we know about, web assembly
and where it's going, and how is the Go
community integrating it more deeply.
Now, what I find super interesting
about this combination of.
edge and web assembly is that
with edge computing, you have an
incredible advantage that your
code is, or your application is
globally distributed by design.
So by default.
When you push code to the edge, it will
run on hundreds and hundreds of edge
locations or pops points of presence.
and that's a big difference
compared to the cloud.
That's interesting to be aware of.
'cause usually an architecture starts as
a centralized or monolithic application
that runs in a single data center or
maybe in a two or three availability
zones, within a cloud region.
And that's super convenient.
you probably don't need
more than that, but.
especially if you are building a
website or a product with a global
audience, you quickly, very quickly
end up, using or involving some kind
of CDN for caching and distributing.
That's like a architectural best practice.
And so you want to, distribute and
cash and even run code as close as
possible to your final, visitors to
your final, users and customers and.
I find it very fascinating
that with edge computing, all
of that happens automatically.
And so your edge applications are globally
distributed, with a couple of clicks.
If you compare that to the cloud,
it's been increasingly easier to
do in the last few years, it's
still not the same, in my opinion.
Now, another interesting.
Technical trade off to be aware of
is that usually at the edge you have
less compute power and you have less
resources in general, compared to a
virtual machine where you can have,
gigabytes and gigabytes of ram or a
container or even a serverless function.
also.
Things really need to happen
quickly because often your edge
compute logic runs before and
after, every single HTTP request.
So if you are adding, if it takes you 20
or 50 or a hundred milliseconds to run,
it means that you're probably adding.
Additional latency to
every single, HCDP request.
And that's not great, right?
You want to run as fast as possible.
So normally you want to run
your AT Logic in five to 10
milliseconds, and that's really fast.
If you think about it.
If you have to talk to a Qing system
or a database or a key value store,
you know you really need to be quick.
Now, while it's true that some Edge
and CDN providers are making this.
Less of a problem.
most edge deployments need to be aware
of, this kind of technical constraints or
limitations or, trade offs, for example.
bunny.net recently announced their
magic containers, just a few weeks ago.
And also Akamai seems to be pushing
a lot their managed container
service in their cloud, which is
actually, distributed like the edge.
So there is a lot happening
also in this space and being
aware of the trade offs and the.
Pricing limitations on or differences is
really useful in my opinion, especially
if you come from the more traditional
cloud world and you're used to, Ty,
traditional visual machines, for example.
Now, if you remember the was key
benefits that we saw earlier.
There are two or three of these that
are really important for the edge,
especially the neo native performance.
Again, we need to run as quickly as
possible within just a few milliseconds.
Ideally, 2, 3, 4, 5 is great.
If you go above.
10, 20 or 50 becomes a problem.
we also have that very small size
and very fast initialization, because
we cannot afford seconds and seconds
of startup time or cold starts like
you typically have with containers.
It could take tens of seconds to
spin up a container, or it could
take hundreds of milliseconds to
spin up a serverless function.
Typically at the edge, we can't afford
that, so we need to be even faster.
and then we love the security sandboxing
for the edge, especially if you are
running, again, untrusted code and you
want to limit network access because
you know it might become problematic
if you need to fetch an external API
call and it takes two seconds or half
a second, even half a second is a lot.
Now.
That's why we chose.
This interesting match of web
assembly and edge computing at edgy.
And as you can guess from the name, we
are doing a lot of, stuff at the edge.
in a nutshell, we are building a platform
for application level services powered
by edge computing and web assembly.
lemme tell you a bit more, the core
service that we are, that we've been
working on so far is really focused on.
data collection and web analytics,
but that's just the starting point.
the final goal, for data collection
and web analytics is to allow our
customers to transfer those typical,
heavy client side SDKs, like for the
Google analytics or segment or amplitude.
things that you have to do traditionally,
have to do on the client, somewhere else.
So we want to.
Take advantage of the edge and
transform those SDKs into web assembly
components that can run even before
the page is sent back to the browser.
So this allows.
Zero latency, very secure and
unblockable data connection, collection.
So it is solving an
actual business problem.
if you're a website owner, you want
to take decisions based on, how people
use your product or what content
they are consuming on your platform.
this is important to make
sure you can make data-driven
decisions that make sense.
and again, this is just a starting point.
We're working on new types of
components in the future to
support additional use cases.
data collection is, the core, but
we are adding AB testing, feature
flags, AI inference, and a lot
more use cases in the future.
we also created what we call the
edgy component registry and this is
basically a registry for wasm components.
Running at the edge, so this is just
very new from a few weeks ago as a
developer, now you can build, push,
and share A was component and then.
Allow anybody to use them
directly on the edgy platform.
And, this is super cool.
I think, all of these
components are open source.
Even the, proxy of the edgy
proxy itself is open source.
And so what we're trying to do here is
create a nice community of, contributors
and component developers that can
build and share these components.
So you can think of this
as a domain specific.
Registry, for web assembly components
where you can discover and push
either private or public components
for yourself, for your customers,
for the whole community, to use.
Now we also invested a
lot in developer tools.
it is just uploading files in a
website or, or, invoking APIs manually.
We wanted to make the
developer experience as.
easy modes and pleasant as possible.
So we built some developer tools
like the ed, GCLI to allow you to
support all the different languages.
of course, GO is supported.
We also support, rust and Python and
C Sharp and type script and so on.
The goal of the CLI really is to allow
you to build and test locally whatever
language you're using, and then easily
push your component to the registry.
it's is also open source.
and I also wanted to show you.
What this actually looks like.
so you can very easily, install it.
There are different ways to do it.
And then you create a new component.
So for example, let's choose
go, it will auto initialize all
the width dependencies, and then
you implement a business logic
and compile to web assembly.
It's all one comment add component
build, and it magically does.
They work for you of generating
the width, bindings and running.
They compile into wasm, and then you
can finally test locally and make sure
that your code is behaving properly.
And when everything's ready, you
add your component, push into
the registry and your component.
If public becomes available to everyone
out there, or even, maybe you push it as
a private one and it becomes available
to your organization or your customers.
So this is really cool.
I also wanted to share with you
a little bit of the high level
architecture, what this all looks like.
I already showed you what the
super high level looks like.
So you have the client
devices, you have the.
edge Proxy running, on Fastly today.
We are expanding soon to run on
other CDNs like CloudFlare and so
on, and then the proxy is there
in between the client devices and
the website, the final website.
And so there is a lot happening behind the
scenes because not a hundred percent of
the logic can happen directly at the edge.
We have some kind of backend
services and managed.
consoles and APIs and so on.
for example, the Edge proxy is
talking to an event API, which
take cares of actually running.
The web assembly component and
integrating with third party
APIs and third party platforms.
And then you have the public
website, you have the Edge GCLI
and potentially other API consumers
who talk to the edgy API as well.
and as you can imagine, the edge
behavior needs to be customizable.
So the edgy API itself needs to
be able to interact with the proxy
and provide, customizations and
configurations directly at the edge.
There is a lot going on.
our long-term vision here is to be
able to run even more of the web
assembly things directly on top of,
the edge proxy on top of, CDNs, there
are some technical limitations today
as far as the component model support.
So we are ending up creating our own.
Distributed network across multiple
clouds, across multiples, compute models.
For now, we are focusing on AWS
Lambda because it's helping us
go, fast and scale when needed.
and so that's what I had for you today.
I wanted to remember that.
CDNs, are not just for caching
and data protection anymore.
There is a lot more, compute capacity
and application level services like
databases, object storage, and so on.
The edge is providing a new
way for building application,
especially globally distributed
applications and functionalities.
web assembly and yz have a very
bright future in my opinion, and
we are investing a lot on it.
There is a big community, focusing on
tooling and improving experience and
adding support for even more languages.
if you're interested into the idea of
a component registry and you want to
contribute and create your components,
feel free to join our community.
You can push for free.
there is a free tier that allow you to
do a lot and experiment as a developer.
Then we can talk business as well.
thank you for joining this session.
I am Alex from edgy.
You can find me on LinkedIn
or on other social media.
Feel free to reach out.
I hope you learned something
new today and, have fun with
wet assembly and the edge.
Bye-bye.