Hello everyone.
My name is Simon.
Welcome to conference 42, goal line 2025.
Today we'll be discussing about the
topic transforming payer operations
with realtime data integration.
How.
Healthcare payer landscape is undergoing
the performed transformation and how
that can be used to transform payer
operations with realtime data integration.
So in today's world, the healthcare
payer landscape is undergoing a
performed transformation through the
integration of real time data processing.
And middleware solutions.
So these solutions are dramatically
improving the claims processing,
eligibility verification, and statistics,
while ensuring the regulatory complaints.
So organizations which are
implementing these technologies
have seen remarkable results.
Like example, 40% faster claim processing,
60% fewer denials and reduction in
integration development time with, 50%.
And also the data accuracy.
Maintaining the data accuracy
in today's world is a big
challenge for every industry.
So 99.9% data accuracy can be
achieved using this transformation.
Advanced solutions like cloud-based
message brokers can process over 10,000
messages per second, enabling faster claim
resolution and improved fraud deduction.
So let's get into the
challenges of payer operations.
Current challenges in payer operations,
like one is manual processing bottlenecks.
Traditional claim processing relies
on manual intervention, creating
bottlenecks that slow down the
operation and increase administrative
cost, which is like studies shows that
manual crime processing can take up
to 30 days to complete the processing.
and the second challenge, what we
have today is data S and fragmentation
healthcare data exist in disparate
systems, making it difficult to
access complete page and information.
This fragmentation leads to eligibility
errors and delayed claim resolutions.
And the third challenge that what we
see is regulatory compliance burden.
So payers face increasingly complex.
Compliance requirements like
hipaa, a CA, and interoperability
mandates without integrated systems.
Maintaining the compliance becomes
resource intensity and error problem.
So these are the challenges like, current
payer industries, healthcare industry,
and bay operations are undergoing.
So let's get into your topic.
Like what is the power of
realtime data integration?
How can it bring down or bring value
to the processing claims processing
like 40% of faster claims processing
can be achieved using realtime data
integration, accelerate claim processing,
and reducing resolution times and
improving your payer efficiency.
and also.
reduce claim denials, so which reduces
60% claim denials using the enhanced
data security and realtime verification.
Significantly decrease the costly claim,
rejections and rework, and it also
increases 50% integration efficiency.
Middleware solutions like Del
Boomi cut the development time in
half, which is 50% as we discussed.
Speeding implementation
and return of investment.
And the last but not least, it's very
important, which is data integrity.
99.9% data integrity can be achieved
using modern integration platform.
Ensure near perfect data
accuracy, minimizing the
error and comprehensive risk.
So these are the, things
that we can achieve using the
real time data integration.
This is the power of, real time data
integration in the middleware sector.
So when it comes to how it can be
a backbone of modern payer system,
so today business applications
like claim processing engines,
eligibility verification system.
And interactive member quotas.
And when it comes to a p, a management
layer, so second, restful a PA
services, secure restful services,
which can be achieved using and
comprehensive, a PA governance.
And the third one is like
middleware integration layer,
real time data transformation,
intelligent message routing, complex
data, workflow orchestration.
So this is going to be a pivotal role
that is going to play in the middle
middleware integration layer and
data storage and processing, right?
So distributed databases, cloud-based
data warehouses and predictive
analysis and engines, infrastructure
that is going to be elastic cloud
resources, legacy on-premises system,
and scalable hybrid architecture.
All these things combined can be
a backbone of modern payer system.
Enterprise middleware system
solution function as a critical and
connectivity issue between connectivity
issue between the heterogeneous
systems in the healthcare ecosystem.
These integrations right platforms
enable seamless bidirectional and
data flow while enforcing the robust.
Security protocol and regulatory
compliance requirements.
So this all, not only doing the seamless
bidirectional data flow, but also,
protects the security protocol, regulatory
compliance requirements, which is very
important for the payer industry by
creating a unified architecture, a
middleware, bridges legacy systems with
a cutting edge applications providing
the technical foundation necessary.
For realtime healthcare
operating and, innovations.
And, when it comes to revolutionizing
the claim processing, this is a very
good concept that, I want to bring.
So how the claims processing can be
happened while from the submission
to the status communication.
So one is like submission status
when the claims are submitted
electronically, immediately
validated against the member data.
And also provider contracts.
How the provider's
contracts are established.
Real time data integration allows
the instant format verification
and initial error detection format
Verification is very important in the
payer industry, so they maintain the
different formats for each sector.
So like that, so payer
industry has its own format.
That format verification is very
important, which is going to.
have the initial error detection
also, and adjudication, right?
When you, when it comes to the
second part is adjudication.
Middleware ate the complex adjudication
process, applying business rules,
benefit calculations, provider
contract terms in real time, reducing
the paper, reducing the processing
time in from days to minutes.
and the third payment determination.
Integrated system calculate accurate
payment amounts based on the
realtime contract and benefit data
drastically, dramatically reducing the
overpayments and underpayments status.
Communication, providing the
provide, providing the members and
providers, in, with the status.
Communication is going to help a lot.
Like providers and members receive
instant status updates through the
integrated protocols and messaging
systems, improving satisfaction and
reducing the inquiry volume, real
time eligibility verification, which
is very important and very useful
for all the members and providers.
Member data access, seamless
verification of coverage status, whether
the particular member is eligible.
Can be done instantaneously.
Benefit validation.
Immediate service authorization,
provider confirmation.
Instantaneous results.
Delivery.
Financial responsibility, precise cost
Sharing determination that can happen.
Using this real time
eligibility verification.
Revolutionizes both provider workflow
and the member experiences by eliminating
uncertainty, reducing administrative
burden, and preventing the delays.
When integrated directly with the
practice management system, it enables
instant benefit verification during
the appointment scheduling at the point
of service sustainability, reducing
the climate, and also optimizing the
entire revenue cycle management process.
So it is going to help in all
aspects like service eligibility,
revenue management process.
And also state of the art
verification system, process
eligibility request in millisecond
instead of the minutes or hours.
So seamlessly handling the event,
even most of the volume, extreme
volumes are going to happen
during the open enrollment.
So at that point of time, also, the system
will not be degraded and in the perform
in the aspect of performance or accuracy.
When it comes to event driven
architecture for claim statistics,
so checking a claim status is a
very important aspect of, real time.
This thing, real time
publishing and notification.
When a claim status changes, the
system instantaneously publish an
event that triggers notification
and updates across all the connected
systems, reducing the eligibility check
processing time from 1.5 hours to.
Just 0.3 seconds.
Similarly, message brokers and scaling
advanced message broker process over
10,000 messages per second during the
peak periods will help maintaining
the system responsiveness and data
integrity, handling the claim status
updates in just 0.5 seconds versus
three to four hours traditionally
prior authorization efficiency.
Event driven systems reduce
preauthorization process time generally
takes 48 hours from to just five seconds.
Enabling immediate clinical decision
and which supports dramatically
improving provider workflow as well
as member it, it helps members to get
the immediate clinical decision and
also accelerated claims adjudication.
The complete claim adjudication
process is transformed from a.
72 hour way to just 30 seconds.
Maintaining the data integrity while
enabling the realtime updates for all
stakeholders is not easy thing that
can be achieved using the event driven
architecture claim status, checks.
So finally, event driven
architecture enables realtime.
Claim statistics tracking through a
system of publishers, subscribers,
and message broker dramatically
reducing the lag between the status
change and stakeholder notification.
So cloud-based message brokers enabling
scalability, so scalability, security
integration, seamless integration
are the wonderful features that can
be, achieved using this concept.
So cloud-based message brokers
automatically scale to handle
very transaction volumes.
So from routine daily processing to
month end surges, this eliminates
the need for over provisioning
on-premises infrastructure,
while ensuring the consistent
performance as well and security.
So enhanced security.
Modern cloud brokers implement
advanced encryption, access
control compliance features.
That meet or exceed HIPA requirement.
This feature protects sensitive
patient data through the messaging
process from origin to the destination.
So security is a matter.
So seamless integration, prebuilt
connectors, and standardized APAs
enable rapid integration with both
legacy systems and modern application.
This reduces implementation
from months to weeks.
Which is very important.
Drastic red use of the time processing
from months to week while maintaining
the data integrity across the platform.
Okay.
AI and machine learning.
The next front are how a and machine
learning can be useful, using this
middleware technologies, real time data
so we can predict the claim processing.
Our AI algorithms analyze the historical
claims data, predict outcomes, identify
potential issues before they occur,
and suggest optimal processing path.
How, which way, which
path that it has to take?
This proactive approach reduces the
manual view requirements up to by 30%.
So we are going to, with the predictive
claim processing, the manual effort
is going to be reduced by 35%,
30% intelligent fraud detection.
Machine learning models continuously
analyzes the claims patent
to identify the anomalies and
potential fraud in real time.
So machine learning can eliminate the
frauds in the real time scenarios.
This system can detect the
sophisticated fraud schemes that
could in be invisible to system.
We can avoid the fraud detect,
fraud transactions, fraud claims.
And when it comes to natural language
processing, NLP extracts meaningful
data from unstructured clinical
notes and documentation, enhancing
the claim adjudication process with
relevant clinical content that would
otherwise require a manual review.
So here also, it is going
to save the manual time.
And autonomous resolution.
Advanced AI systems can autonomously
resolve routine claim issues without
human intervention, allowing staff to
focus on the complex cases that require
clinical expertise and also advertisement.
So edge computing.
So the most training technology,
which is the edge computing
processing at the point of care.
So distributed processing reduces
the bandwidth requirements.
Continuous operation, real
time clinical integration.
So how edge computing is going to help us.
So dis distributed processing edge
computing moves data processing closer
to the source of data generation,
such as a hospital's clinics.
The distributed approach reduces the
latency by processing the eligibility
at simple eligibility and simple claims
directly at the healthcare facility.
Before even submission, or transforming
to the transmission, to the central
systems so we don't have to process
the data to the transmission, to the
central system to identify whether this
particular processing is really required.
The central system.
So this distributed processing can
take care of that at the source
level itself by saving so much.
Time and processing,
eligibility and latency also.
So reduced bandwidth requirement.
So it is going to save the, bandwidth,
which is in process, like by processing
the filtering and locally data.
Locally it's competing, reduces the
amount of information that must be
transmitted to the central system.
These particularly valuables for
rural and are undeserved areas.
So where the limited
connectivity is there.
There, the reduced bandwidth
requirement is going to help a lot.
Continuous Operation Edge systems can
continue to function during the network.
Outages are central system maintenance,
storing the transactions locally
until the connectivity is stored.
This ensures that patient care continues
uninterrupted, even though even
during the technical disruptions also.
Real time clinical integration edge
processing enables real time integration
between clinical system and payer system,
supporting value based care models
that require immediate feedback on care
decision and their financial implications.
So let's see how the roadmap
looks like, for a future outlook.
Short term actions like
zero to six months.
Access to current integration
architecture and identify local gaps.
Implement middleware connectors
for high volume transactions.
Deploy cloud-based message brokers
for eligibility verification.
So train the staff on new real
time capabilities and workflows.
So this is the short term goal,
like from zero to six months how
we can access the integration.
Architecture and, critical gaps
and how we can, use the middleware
connector for high volume transactions.
How can we deploy the cloud-based message
brokers for eligibility verification?
So whether the person is eligible at or
not instantaneously get the eligibility
verification when it comes to medium
term goals, which is six to 18 months.
Transition to fully event driven
architecture from claim processing.
Implement AI assisted claims
adjudication for routine claims.
Develop, provide provider facing
APAs for direct system integrations.
So provider facing integrations
are going to be very helpful and
implementing the AI assisted claim
Education also at the facility is
going to be very helpful and it's going
to give the instantaneous decisions.
And establish the edge computing pilots
at major provider partners, which
is going to save, longer, processing
time for instantaneous decisions.
So long term vision, 18 placements achieve
near instantaneous claim processing.
For standard claims, instantaneous
claim processing can be achieved.
In the long term vision, implement
predictive analytics for proactive
intervention, and this can be
achieved using the edge computing
implementation of predictive analysis
for proactive intervention, deploy
auto autonomous exception handling for
common issues, transition to blockchain
for select high value transactions.
So these are the long-term visions
that what we are going to achieve.
Using the payer transformation healthcare,
using the realtime data integration.
Thank you.
Thanks, Sue.
Thank you for your.