Hi everyone.
today I'm going to discuss about how the
back cell power delivery is helping in
the chip design, to reduce the IR drop.
That means power ation in the chip and
improve the performance and even improve
the signal integrity, between the.
Signals in the design or in the chip,
like how it is helping, through the chip.
I'm going to discuss on this
more in my coming slides.
So coming to that backside
power delivery network.
Now, we'll call it as A-B-S-P-D-N.
It's a technology currently,
or opting, like in the.
Two m below that, two nanometer
below that technologies.
So it's a revolutionary because earlier
visit to have that, whole, the power
delivery on the front side of the design.
Along with the signals.
So suppose like if you have the metal
layers of 15, then the top metal layers
will go for power and the next metal
layers will go for the clock, and
the remaining metal layers is go for.
Signal.
So because of that, we can't use all
the metal layers but signals and there
is no availability of the, for the
routing resources, for the signals.
Because of that, we move that most of
the backside, most of the power routes
in the backside through nano silicone.
Through Silicon vs.
We are making like a reducing the
stop state of the chip and we are
putting like a sending the VS through
that to connect that backside power.
So it's a revolution in the chip design
currently opting like, many of the lower
level node like Intel, TSMC and Samsung.
This actually earlier as I mentioned,
the power and signal are in the, of the
design, but here we are moving that entire
power into the backside of the design.
And, we are using like,
continue this one to the.
DS V. This is helping like a
significant improvement in the
performance, efficiency and power.
So this incorporat like silicon.
We, for that power delivery
through Silicon Subrate, we are
attending like a silicon subrate.
substrates.
SUBRATE means it's a CMOs device.
There's a substrate in the CMOs device.
So we are making like as much as, thinning
because of, to connect that backside
power with the front side of the design.
Integrating that front side of
the design with, through silicon
V is routing congestion, air
drop, improving that activity.
In Intel's power via implementation and
further developments are going in the
other manufacturers like TSMC and Samsung.
So I'm going to discuss more
about on this in my coming slides.
So if you're coming to that traditional
power delivery limitations, these are
routing congestion in advanced, the five
nanometer and below there will be like,
Most of that 40% of our routing resources
is control by the power delivery.
And, remaining goes to the clock
and signal as, metal just carrying
down in the lower technology to 24
nanometer higher drop increasing
dramatically by 45% compared with
the previously technology notes.
So it's a severely constrained in the
signal routing options because we don't
have the, routing sources for the signals.
So for this, we are moving
to that, the backside power.
And also there is a other
disadvantage, water degradation.
like the technologies are,
going down, like we are going
towards the two nanometer.
So the what is operating, what
is also will come down now,
like 0.7 volts and, it drops.
What?
It drops also significantly 20 15% across
the day during the high competition loads.
Even like in the critical corners,
it's increasing like 16.5%.
So this is like another
disadvantage, with the front side.
So there is a power supply noise.
Currently the dynamic Power
Circuit operation generates
a substantial power supply.
Noise is reaching, 85 to 95 MTSS peak
to peak, under typical workloads.
This is a regular, normal,
power turbine, supplies.
And in place fluctuations, said 22% from
nominal values, security and timing.
Predictability.
So this p report delivery, very
hard feature, how it'll be the,
as I mentioned earlier, they were
processing, we reading that, this
substrate as much as less possible
to make it like, to get high yield.
Along with that, With, battery yield
and reducing that substrate sub subrate
to 12 to 50 micron thickness with
exceptional control maintained within
45 micron, across the 300 millimeter
wave advanced TV fabrication use,
remarkable s of, 10 to one in, backside
Power delivery is a featuring like
ultra fine via diameters under to 200
nanometer and beside depth exceeding to.
2.5 microns.
So power level implementation,
specialized backside.
Metal stack utilizing advanced
copper metalization techniques.
Use low sheet resistance of, point knot
one five, m for the engineered three layer
power distribution network with optimized
4.2 micrometer thickness, delivers
substantial, 58% reduction in the.
PDN implements, compared to conventional
approaches, the system benefits
significant election in, required met
layer from conventional, like conventional
10 to 12, like 10 to 15 even, met layers.
Now it is, we are moving to 7, 2 8,
for the same, frequency, so signal.
Interconnect length decreases by 25% and
that they contributing to the dynamic
traumatic cause delay improvement
of 35% while cement signal pro stock
by 42% because of, more routing
sources available for the signals.
So it improves the performance and
it's a state and weak power as,
there are more vs for the, power.
And the more routings is available for
the signal, there will be less crosstalk.
So if you're comparing the performance
between the traditional, power delivery
network and backside power delivery
network, the sistance is, traditional.
It is like one 50% and ambassador power,
it is a hundred percent the poor concept.
What for, If you're comparing with the
WA four millimeters squared, then it
is 2.5 in the conventional and 1.75,
and a metal area says it is 35% and
15% in the backside power delivery.
Pdn, it is a hundred percent, 155% I drop
it is a hundred percent in the, if you're
comparing with a hundred percent, then
it'll be like 40% with the B-S-P-D-N.
Metal layers will be calmed down.
It is if you are getting with eight in
the traditional, and it'll be like three.
So while manufacturing, we
have to capture these things.
We tending, tending or to five
to 10 microns, with exceptional
surface integration below two
nanometer or Ness TS integration.
Hi Christian, 500 nanometer TSP
featuring industrial leading tenish.
One has aspect ratio with the near
vertical, 89.8 plus or minus 0.2,
decreased side wall profiles, and the
thermal management TSV replacement
architecture, the critical thermal grads
by 40%, enhancing the device reliability.
So these are like the helping the, we have
to catch the, this while manufacturing
for the back still power delivery.
So design methodology, observation,
so machine learning optimization, 68%
action in design cycles with, 40% I
improvement and power delivery network.
Advanced simulation dose.
If you, with the 3D Electromatic
technology achieving like it's a
94% coalition with the whatever
we get with the actual silicon.
post silicon measurements,
power ga certific like best,
TSV placement algorithms.
Will it reduce like the higher drop
voltage drop by 48% across critical path?
The most of the leading, companies
that are opting this, backside
power delivery currently.
So this will reduce like the thermal
disp and improve the current density
across, different, multiple designs.
The, even the run time.
Also with that one, the run time
will be increased by 70% improvement.
The, it'll exit the time
to market of the designs.
So these are measure players
currently opting the backside power
delivery intel power via currently
Intel is opted, the old means 7.8
er, the Intel, latest technology.
It is the current, TSMs.
Latest technology.
TSMC, not at comeback, but Intel
is working on this 1.8 nanometer.
so faster.
Updated in the intel, technologies.
Intel latest technologies, it's
actually like a 30%, power delivery,
efficiency, and, the current, improvement.
Also, it's a 2.8 amps
for millimeter square.
While maintain like a four plus or minus
4% voltage regulation across the day.
TSMC has invested like the 2.8 billion
on this backstory, power delivery.
They're working on this, demonstr,
exceptionally like 28% power efficiency
with, their predicting and with
the 15% performance improvement.
In the two M process node, Samsung
Hal up to this one, vertical
power delivery with the TSVs.
one 50 nanometer diameters with
the same finished one as aspect
of TSVs advanced Metalation
Techniques Seal 2.2 x electronic.
Aggression resistance, computation,
power delivery architectures
with this, Samsung technologies.
So feature aspects 2025 and beyond.
I said 25%.
market adoption in the.
2025. predicting for the, high
performance computing and, mobile
applications, say 25% predicting will
adopt this, backside power delivery
with the latest advance nodes.
And a market opportunity
is like 85 5 billion.
for the technology integration across
semi sectors, 40%, efficiency improvement
for efficiency gains in, next generation
sites, rising advanced, the, BSPD
and our teacher with, compared to
that conventional, front cell power
delivery, the current density entity,
it's for four ramps for millimeter
square peak current handling capacity
while maintaining precise, plus
minus 3.5%, across all regulations.
Advanced research insureds now
exit towards, breakthrough BSPD and
implementations with the unprecedented
specific teams are developing ultra mini
TSP structures, with the diameters below
hundred nanometer and, revolutionary one.
currently like we are, How the 300
nanometer and a 200 nanometer TSPs,
so the current, they're working on
to reduce that, diameters to hundred
nanometer and, expect of the list.
One, it'll improve the
width and the depth of that.
we.
And also the junction temperature, beyond
and improving that current, density.
So the work is still going on.
This.
so for metrics across manufacturers
for change, implement inte leads with
the 30% improvement followed by TS
MC 28%, and Samsung at 25% with their
backside power delivery implementations.
TSV yield rates closely intellectual,
high manufacturing patient with, 19.95
TSV rate while TSMC and, Samsung, follows
by closely by 98, 99 0.8 and 99.7.
Current density city, power via
technology enabled intel to reach
2.8 times for millimeters square.
and the Samsung and TSM just, logging on
this, Just below, temperature reduction.
All manufacture choose, significant
cooling benefits with, inate using
temperature by eight degrees ingrade
while t Samsung seven degrees.
The temperature is, performs metrics
for the back power delivery, feature.
Implications, density
improvement implement is not just
transfer density improvement.
Also, along with the performance
improvement, competition powerment,
it is like 25% improvement.
with the traditional delivery
network, the power is reduced by
35, 2 40% with the different metal
layers, performance enhancements.
Overall performance efficiency improved by
2020 5% with the dynamic power, reduction.
30% in, high performance
competing measurement, and
35% who design flexibility
separation of power and signal.
do domains enable 30 reduction
in routing complexity.
It'll reduce the routing resources with
the average violent, also will come
down to 2020 5% required, metal air
reduction from, it'll also come down to.
Metal layers right into instructed while
we are going with the less metal layers.
78, for the same functional
8%, 18% delay reduction.
Economic impact and co conclusions.
ancient cost of this,
will increase 18 to 22%.
return of vestment timelines will
be like, 15, 12, 20 months For
data center implementations, yield,
implement 80%, higher than conventional
process, then cycle at 25% reduction
design cycle enrollment, cycle time.
this is, as a advanced technology.
Currently most of the lower
technology nodes, we are, adopting
in the lower technology nodes.
in the cheap design.
So for the, to reduce the power
and improve the performance
and, reduce the ity issues.
So thank you.
Thank you for listening.
Thank you very much.