Hi everyone.
Welcome to my presentation on
Revolutionary go based security solutions
for complex enterprise environments.
Today we'll discuss how we engineered a
high performance identity orchestration
framework to enhance security,
improve performance, and reduce costs.
We will also learn on how Ghost
Concurrency model and memory management
enabled us to build a system that
deliver 300% faster policy resolution
in sub millisecond response time.
Join me as we discuss on a real world
case study and actionable strategies
you can implement in your organization.
Let's discuss some of the security
challenges in multi-cloud environments.
Modern enterprises operate across multiple
cloud providers and on-premise systems.
This creates security inconsistency in
security policies and identity management.
Organizations struggle with
various authentication mechanism
leading to performance bottlenecks,
and high resource overhead.
Traditional solutions often force
unacceptable trade-offs between security,
performance and operational efficiency.
The statistics reveal a troubling
landscape where security team
face challenges with compromising
performance or increasing costs.
We will explore these key challenges
and their impact on security teams.
Why use go for developing
security microservices?
Go is an ideal choice for security
applications due to its high
performance, lightweight concurrency
model and built-in security features.
Its compilation to native machine
code eliminates interpreter overhead
while maintaining memory safety.
The language's simplicity reduces
the potential for security bugs that
often plague more complex languages.
For DevOps Team Go provides
consistent behavior across platforms
combined to create reliable
performant security services that
can scale with enterprises demands.
We look at why go outperforms traditional
languages in identity orchestration
at our identity
orchestration architecture.
Our system is structured into four
key components, request ingestion,
policy re resolution, token
management and access enforcement.
Each of these elements play a
crucial role in enforcing secure
efficient identity handling.
Our architecture implements a zero trust
security model where every request is
fully authenticated and authorized.
The system processes access request
through multiple microservices
while maintaining high performance.
By separating concerns into discrete
components, we have created a flexible
system that makes our architecture
scalable, adaptable to security
needs and resource efficient.
Let's discuss on goals,
concurrency advantages.
Concurrency is a major advantage
of go the heart of our system's
Performance advantage comes from go's,
lightweight go routines and channels.
We have implemented sophisticated
concurrency pattern that enable our
authorization service to process
thousands of policy evaluations
simultaneously without the overhead
of traditional threading models.
Our custom scheduler manages go
routine life cycles to prevent
resource leaks and ensure consistent
performance under wearing loads.
We have also developed specialized
synchronization primitives that
minimize contention points and
eliminate common bottleneck in
high throughput security systems.
Why use identity query language for
implementation, we utilized identity
query language, a domain specific language
that enables optimized query parsing,
policy matching, and decision evaluation.
This allows for rapid paralyzed access
control decisions with minimal overhead.
The language allows security
engineers to define sophisticated
rule while maintaining sub
millisecond response times.
Let's look into integration
of this solution.
With cloud native technology, our
framework integrates seamlessly with
cloud native technologies like open
policy agent Kubernetes operators.
And service mesh solutions to
enhance security enforcement
in distributed environments.
Our go microservice expose
Prometheus metrics endpoints
for comprehensive observability
and implement graceful shutdown
procedures to maintain reliability.
During updates, I will now
highlight few of the performance
benchmarks that was groundbreaking.
Our goal-based solution achieves 300%
faster policy resolution compared
to traditional approaches, all
while reducing resource consumption.
These benchmarks highlight the real
world performance improvements achieved.
These results were validated in
production environment, handling millions
of authentication requests each day.
Even under peak loads, our system maintain
consistent sub millisecond response
time while consuming significantly
fewer resources than comparable
solution implemented in other languages.
Let's dive into a real world case study.
A global financial institution with
30 plus discrete cloud environment
was struggling with fragmented
identity controls access, their hybrid
infrastructure leading to security
gaps and performance bottlenecks.
Our go based solution replaced a complex
web off legacy system with coherent
high performance security layer.
This solution was implemented and helped
to achieve 99.9997% availability, reducing
security incidents by 72%, and cutting
identity infrastructure cost by 65%.
The implementation took 12
weeks from design to production
deployment, demonstrating the
development possibilities with go.
What were some of the implementation
best practices to consider Successful
implementation requires profiling, before
optimizing, designing for distributed
workloads, and rigorous security testing.
This separation enables independent
evolution of security rules
without requiring redeployment
of enforcement points.
When designing your concurrency model
prefer channels for coordination
between go routines rather than
traditional locking mechanisms.
Using the context package consistently
throughout your application ensures
proper cancellation, propagation, and
prevents resource leaks under error
condition, or shutdown scenarios.
Following these best practices
ensures a robust and scalable system.
Finally, let's dive into the
key takeaways and next steps.
Go is a powerful choice
for security microservices.
Its concurrency model enables
high performance policy
evaluation and its cloud native
integration simplifies deployment.
Our open source framework is
available for implementation.
We invite you to explore our open
source implementation and documentation.
The team is available for technical
discussion about how these patterns can
be applied to your specific environment.
Connect with us after the presentation
to discuss your security challenges and
how our goal-based approach might help.
Finally, thank you for your time.
I'm happy to take questions and
discuss further on how this solution
can be applied to your organization.