Hello everyone.
My name is Vishnu.
I am here with you today to discuss
about cloud security for shared
management, commonly known as CSPM.
As more organizations move their
applications to cloud, maintaining a
strong security P is crucial to protecting
sensitive data and ensuring compliance.
In this session, I will be
sharing insight into how.
CSPM can help you identify risks,
enforcing, enforce security policies,
and strengthen your cloud environment.
CSPM provides automated security
monitoring, compliance management,
and risk assessment across multiple
cloud platforms like, Amazon Web
Services AWS, Microsoft Azure and
GCP and other cloud platforms.
Yeah.
CSPM, core concepts and
growing importance to CSPM.
What is, CSPM?
CSPM, is a continuously monitoring
cloud infrastructure configurations.
And security settings to identify
potential vulnerabilities
and compliance issues.
This system establish baseline
security configurations and actively
monitored for deviations that
could indicate security risks.
CSPM critical, functionalities,
identifying, misconfiguration
in cloud service.
and continuously monitoring,
reporting and alerting.
Then, it provide comprehensive visibility
across cloud environments, market growth,
compound animal growth rate, with 12.8%.
This growth is driven by raising
frequency of cloud security
breaches and the increasing complex
complexity of multi-cloud environment
within single organization,
technical architecture components.
Mainly.
We have in c in CSPM three
components out there.
One is, continuous.
Monitoring systems, risk assessment
frameworks, compliance monitoring tools.
when coming to the continuous
monitoring systems, we can build
our own monitoring systems or.
We can, utilize the vendors, vendors
or SaaS providers like, Okta with
Ivo Rapid seven, multiple SaaS
vendors or cloud service provider.
Also providing, CSPM
solution mainly we can.
We can ingest data using a p CS
Cloud service providers APAs to get,
cloud environment metadata to, to
verify configurations and to protect,
organization or cloud service.
This one, will give you, visibility
across the cloud infrastructure.
So second, risk assessment frameworks,
is automated scanning assessment
capabilities, identifying potential
security gaps and compliance
violations across cloud, workloads,
security frameworks, like CAS
benchmarks, for industry standards.
And, NIST frameworks failed ramp.
And when the best practices frameworks, we
can utilize, as a template to start, cloud
configuration, continuous monitoring.
Third one is compliance monitoring tools.
this component, works conjunction
with, security policy engines to
enforce organizational security
standards, enabling automated policy
enforcement and continuous compliance
monitoring across cloud environments.
Yeah.
implementation strategy?
First, we need to do inventory analysis.
Across all organization cloud assets
and resource, and, we can do what
qualitative analysis and quantitative
analysis, qualitative analysis like
is, if we are using cloud service
for public facing applications.
We can give more priority and
the quantitative is based on
number of resources for that
particular cloud service.
We can give priority, we can understand,
our inventory and we can define
scope of security coverage needed.
What is in scope and what is out scope
if you are using a third party sas?
Monitor CSPM tools, you need to consider.
what, how, what services they are.
They have coverage,
they have full coverage.
there are no coverage.
Particular cloud service, that same
services are we using in our organization.
Once, inventory, analysis is
done, then next step, security
baseline establishment.
In this one, we need, we can, we
can define, we can, we need to
do cloud configuration rules and
security controls in a framework
security configuration baseline.
here, using with the help of
industry based practices and
organizational security requirements.
Yeah.
in this one, some, cloud configurations
rules provided by vendor or industry
based practices frameworks may not,
applicable to our organization.
Based on our security requirements, we
need to adjust, those, default frameworks.
based on severity and risk.
Yeah.
next we can in once, security
configuration, baseline is established
and it's ongoing security monitoring
and complete compliance assessment,
then we can integrate with our existing
tools like sim systems and IAM tools.
it'll give you, comprehensive
coverage and cons, consistent
monitoring, next alert configurations.
Once, SA cloud security.
Cloud configuration.
Baseline rule is have some findings.
We need to, alert to security teams.
we can do some alert configurations
like, we can integrate with
the Jira or creating ticket.
And, based on, our national risk
tolerance, we can change the severity.
and we can, we can ensuring effective
prior of security incidents, we can
customize, when that provided severity
for that, cloud configuration rules.
we can customize based on our,
organization security requirements.
Yeah.
integration requirements, cloud
service provider connections.
Yeah.
Establishing a PA connections with
the cloud service provider, ensures
consistent data flow, and it'll give
usability across cloud environments.
This, appropriate access, control
and secure communication channels.
Yep.
we can set up this, CSP
connections in two ways.
One is, scanning, hourly basis,
like every 12 hours or 24 hours.
Other one is near real time updates,
like cloud event, integration.
Whenever some resource.
Configuration changes immediately.
update, edge Good Cloud
configuration rules.
Update inventory and up edge good cloud
configuration rules of, identify any
misconfiguration deviation from baseline.
Next, security tool integration.
Connecting with existing
security tools and monitor.
Monitor monitoring systems enables
unified security management and
consistent policy enforcements.
This includes SIM systems, IM
tools, integrations, data connector
configurations, configuring appropriate
data connectors, and ensuring
proper data formatting for analysis.
It enables effective security monitoring
and assessment across cloud environments.
Security and compliance benefits
enhance security portion CSPM
solutions, provide continuous monitoring
and assessment cap capabilities.
it's enable organizations to identify
address security risks proactively before
they can be exploited automated security
policy enforcement as a major, as a
critical component of modern security
strategies compliance management.
automated compliance monitoring
and reporting capabilities, enables
organizations to maintain continuous
compliance with various regularity.
Frameworks like, CAS
benchmarks, niche framework.
fed Ramp and, it, this
simplifies audit process and
regulatory requirement tracking.
While ensuring accurate and timely
reporting operational efficiency,
it'll reduce manual intervention
with, automated, continuous,
cloud environment scanning and
identify any misconfiguration.
in CSPM solution implementation
best practices, so regular security
assessment, conduct, systematic
vulnerability, scannings and
pen test to proactively identify
security gaps and compliance risks.
define, robust IEM policies.
Establish a principle of least
privileged access controls with the MFA
to prevent unauthorized access to, to
send two resources like NPA data, PA
data, those, any sensitive resources.
any trans, you can secure transaction
enable MFA, continuous monitoring, mon
monitor, CSPM frameworks and deploy,
automate automated, monitoring for all
cloud environments with real time alerts.
For any suspicious activities
and configuration changes, if,
we can continuously monitor, our
security configuration baseline.
If any unauthorized person changes,
our baseline, we need to identify
incident response planning.
create a detailed, untested response
playbook with a clear, escalation
pause on recovery procedure
for various security scenarios.
staff training programs.
it's a, it's a role based specific
security training with the simulated
phishing exercises and hands-on
workshop to build security awareness,
common challenges and solutions in
CSPM, like in liquid configuration
management, leading to.
Or exploitable vulnerabilities.
for this one, we can implement real
time configuration assessment with
the automated remediation workflows.
Compliance management, is dynamic
regulatory landscape evolving
change, Whenever new cloud
service releases are utilized by
organization, we need to enhance
our security configuration baseline.
Also resource management, established
role-based security training with the
with, sandbags cloud environment scenario.
With cloud.
Yeah.
Practical cloud environment
scenarios, integrations, implement
a PA driven security architecture
with centralized management council.
Yeah.
Imagine technologists in
CSPM, artificial intelligence.
Yeah, you can, utilize, enable a
for threat, more threat detection
and automated response capabilities.
Advanced automation, we can
implement autom remediation, autom
remediation workflows or playbooks
whenever misconfiguration finds.
we can, automatically fix, automatic
without manual intervention,
automatically update configuration to,
to match with our security baseline.
Predictive analyticals, the integration
of predictive security analyticals,
enables organ organization to anticipate.
Potential security issues before,
they manifest as actual threats.
Yeah.
CSPM, industry developments
and future trends.
Autonomous security systems, AI driven
self-healing, security controls,
zero trust architecture, continuous
verification, security framework.
DevOp integrations integrate,
baseline with, DevOps pipelines.
it'll prevent, in cloud resources
closing itself, edge computing,
security, decentralized protection
for distributed, assets.
we can implement at, edge locations
endpoints, quantum computing preparation,
Crip, after, cryptographic resiliency
for first, first quantum threats.
Yeah, this strategies, plays particular,
this strategies emphasis on anticipating
emerging technology like quantum
computing and edge processing, proactively
preparing for their transformative
impact on cloud security paradigms.
Yeah.
Conclusion we have in CSPM, area,
we have 12.8% of market growth.
Based on reflecting its critical
importance in modern security
strategies, three key benefits, using
cloud security portion management.
It enhances security portion.
Automated compliance and
operational efficiency.
Yep.
the evaluation of CSPM driven
by emerging technologies such as
artificial intelligence, machine
learning, and edge computing.
Positions such as a future
of cloud security strategies.
With integration of advanced automation
capabilities and adoption of zero trust
policy policies, CSPM will continue to
play a vital role in helping organizations
protecting their digital assets.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you all.