Hello everyone, and thank
you for joining today.
Today we'll explore how government
agencies are embracing cloud
technologies to digitally transform
their operation, improve citizen
engagement, and also how to optimize
internal efficiency, especially
using Salesforce government Cloud.
So this session is filled with real
data points that we have collected, so
far with success Metrices and a forward
looking view into what's next for the
public sector digital transformation.
So why there is a need for
transformation in public agencies.
So currently, as public agencies
are under increasing pressure to
modernize their tech stack and,
also to modernize their outdated.
Systems and to meet rising citizens
expectations and also to deliver services
with greater transparency and speed.
So from 2020 to 2023, cloud adoption
in the public sector grows by 72%.
You know how much demand there
is for GCP or AWS or even, Azure.
so there is almost a 72% increase in.
From 2020 to 2023, signaling a strong,
digitalization driving the shift,
our demands for, better service,
accessibility, strong efficiency
and crisis responsiveness, legacy
systems are no longer sustainable.
And those have high costs in maintenance
and also digital push platforms like
Salesforce are helping to bridge the gaps.
So why Salesforce?
Government cloud.
So Salesforce Government Cloud is
built to meet the unique security
compliances and scalability
needs of public sector entities.
So it has federal and compliant
infrastructure to ensure strict adherence
to federal cybersecurity standards.
And also 99 per 99.95% security compliance
rate demonstrate high reliability,
and it also has a S 2 56 encryption.
For data addressed and TLS
1.3 for data in transit.
So role based access controls
and a multi-tenant architecture,
improve resource utilization by
70 per 71% and also virtually ate,
crossed and data leakage by 99%.
So what are the, real world,
impacts metrics using, Salesforce?
agencies are seeing major improvement.
That have already been using, Salesforce.
So one, one is the permit processing
time has dropped from 15 days to
just three point, 3, 2, 2 0.3 days.
by using Salesforce AI and also
administrative overhead costs
have been slashed by 67% due to
digitalization and automation.
So now agencies can also handle
three times more, service request
without increasing headcount
and still maintain a 91.
Percent, service accuracy
and also the omnichannel communications,
the emergency notifications
and AI powered self service.
All these will be, adhering, to
lower the time for self resolution
of cases, and also will, reduce.
The, low hanging cases when a citizen
opens a case, using Salesforce, when the
agencies are using the government cloud.
And also the operation Excellence,
has also been improved, a lot, by
automation, and also by using, internal
workflows and flows within Salesforce.
So every day, 18,500 transactions
are processed to automated approval
chain, so there is no manual.
Intervention of people or the
government employees, to, manually,
approve, or reject the data.
So by this, the number of cases
handled every day by the agencies
has improved a lot and the citizens
are also pretty happy on, on looking
at the results and also the smart
routing, powered by machine learning,
reduced, misdirect, requests are also.
Improved.
And, the SLM monitoring with automated
escalations, results, potential
violation within required timeframes.
intelligent resource, management,
resource allocation is now, data driven.
so staff utilization has improved by 52%.
and also AI forecasting achieves
88.5% accuracy, helping agents.
This, anticipate and, balance the
workload and also hire efficiently.
So service select bottles and
bottle service delivery bottlenecks
are also reduced by 42.5%.
So predictive maintenance saves
medium sized departments, 1.8
million annually, thanks to a 75.3
reduction in unplanned downtime.
So the crisis management,
readiness during emerging.
Salesforce provide a
coordinated, scalable response.
A unified crisis dashboard cut
average response time by 55, 54 0.2%.
system, managed 12,000 plus concurrent
incident report without data loss.
And the 81.7% improvement in resource
allocation, ensures help reaches where
it's needed the most improved message,
delivery success across vulnerable
population from 76 to 94.5 percentage.
So data driven.
Decision making.
Salesforce enables smarter
governments through analytics.
Also, advanced algorithms
and realtime data.
realtime data dashboards improve
operational efficiencies while, for
2.7 percentage departments report
average annual saying of 22.1 million.
agencies now predict citizen and
demand are ate anomaly early and
are just purchased proactively.
So how does.
All this happened.
So Salesforce have seamless
integrations, and advanced security
integration and interability.
these are pretty, critical, when you
are using advanced infrastructure.
So APIs, through APIs, there is decre,
the request latency is decreased,
and also the response variation
is also reduced by 43 point 42.3
percentage data migration is accurate.
so that no data is.
Is lost, during the transitions
from old system to new system.
And also mobile infrastructure
supports eight 50 K request, per day
at 0.9 seconds average response time.
So multilayered security data detects
99.8% of data breaches across 1.2 million
transactions daily per each, agency.
So what is, what does the, future,
outlook, capabilities, look like?
So ai, all AI models.
Now deliver 92.7 accurately in
platform recognition and prediction.
Blockchain and IOT configurations have
improvement data by 94.1 percentage and
advanced analytics improved, resource
allocation efficiency by 51.8 percentage.
And enhanced security now prevents 99.97
percentage of unauthorized systems.
So not only does every agency, can
use, AI powered, service agents.
so that whenever, a citizen or anybody
using a service, by the government
agencies, they can, when once they
create a case, or any kind of request,
the AI agents, will automatically,
solve the low hanging foods.
once this happens, the number of cases,
created, as the number of cases, creation
increases more, the response time.
Will also be decreased because
of even of AI powered services.
so once these AI powered services are
introduced, into the government cloud
by the agencies, the low hanging cases
will be resolved and the regular,
regularly, created cases by different
citizens, will be automatically
resolved by looking at the history.
So overall, the next generation
government cloud, will have more
security enhancements and more.
AI capabilities, so that even, with
many cases, created many backlog
cases that are already there.
there is a significantly, less,
turnaround time and also the resolution
is within, minutes and it does not take
days, for the already, created cases.
Thank you.