Speaker 6: Think about the last
time a minor firmware rollout
or a localized telemetry glitch
caused massive operational drag
for your engineering teams.
In massive broadband operations, dealing
with multiple chipset vendors means
managing endless unique variations
in error correction, SNR thresholds,
and dev-- and device behaviors.
Hello, everyone, I'm
Harshu Varadini Taluri.
I work for Charter Communications
as a senior network engineer.
If you're, if you've ever had your
engineering resources consumed by
debugging vendor-specific exceptions
instead of scaling platform capabilities,
this talk is exactly for you.
Over the next few minutes, we will
look at how we used Go to build a
unified platform that normalizes
fragmented metrics and isolates hardware
differences be-behind micro adapters.
This goal is simple, helping your
operations focus entirely on network
outcomes instead of hardwork works.
Let's look at how we build it.
Now, the root of this challenge stems
from what I call the multi-vendor problem.
It's a reality where running a single
chipset across an entire footprint
is virtually impossible, and that
reality creates significant friction
across four core pillars: bonding
modulation, bonding modulation,
error correction, and telemetry.
Now let's start with channel bonding.
Vendors group upstream and downstream
channels differently, causing highly
inconsistent behavior across the network.
Uh, coming to modulation handling,
different chipsets respond uniquely
to SNR and MER thresholds, generating
divergent modulation profiles
under identical signal conditions.
The next is error correction.
Forward error correction algorithms vary
widely by vendor, frequently masking
severe signal degrade-- degradation
and delaying critical diagnostics.
Telemetry da-data.
Telemetry is completely fragmented because
vendors utilize non-uni-uniform schemas,
naming conventions, and metric units.
So this fragmentation isn't just
a minor technical inconvenience.
It translates directly into compounding
operational costs every single day.
Let's look at cognitive load.
Every unnormalized chipset work becomes
an extra item engineers must remember,
document, and troubleshoot separately.
Slower triage Is troubleshooting
cycles drag out because engineers
must constantly switch between
vendor-specific diagnostic tools, log
formats, and operating assumptions.
Unpredictable performance.
Service reliability suffers because
different chipsets react differently under
heavy load or marginal signal conditions.
Slower innovation.
Rollouts slower down to a crawl
because firmware validation, provision,
provisioning workflows, and configuration
testing must be repeated for every vendor.
Engineering time gets completely
swallowed by managing exceptions.
So how do we break out of this loop?
We do it by shifting our mindset
and establishing a unified chipset
strategy where vendors... Sorry,
where vendor diversity is treated
strictly as an implementation detail.
Let's start with isolash--
isolate complexity.
We must stop exposing vendor-specific
works to higher level operational
workflows or engineering teams.
We hide these differences behind a common
abstraction layer that normalizes chipset
APIs into one vendor-agnostic interface.
We standardize telemetry configuration
and diagnostic schemas into a unified
format used across an entire fleet.
This allows provisioning
firmware management and rollout
automation to execute from a
single consistent control plane.
We contain vendor differences
inside adapters, so the rest of
our ecosystem runs uniformly.
When deciding how to build this
heavy-duty abstraction and telemetry
system, Go emerged as the clear natural
fit for infrastructure engineering.
Let's see what the Go performance does.
Go delivers low latency exec,
uh, execution, and a small memory
footprint, which is vital for high
volume data pa-- uh, pipelines.
Concurrency model.
Go routines and channels make it
incredibly simple to poll millions
of devices and process in-intensive
telemetry streams concurrently.
Deployment sim-simplicity.
Go compiles down into single
static binaries, removing runtime
dependency headaches across lab,
trial, and production networks.
Tooling ecosystem.
Its practic- Its practical standard
library provides robust native
support for HTTP, gRPC, structured
logging, and foundation instra--
infrastructure integrations.
Let's look at concrete, uh, blueprint.
We organized this Go-based platform
into three decoupled independently
deployable layers: the abstraction
services, orchestration and
automation, observability plane.
Let's look at, uh, abstraction services.
This is the bottom layer where
normalization logic and vendor-specific
adapters live, translating native
APIs into our canonical model.
Orchestration and automation.
This middle layer manages automation
provisioning, firmware rollouts,
complex workout... uh, complex workflow
sequencing, and rollback guardrails.
Observability plane.
The top layer ingests unified telemetry
pipelines, running dashboards, alerting
engines, and fleet health views.
Because these layers are fully
independent, organizations can adopt
into architecture step by step without
a risky day-one overha-overhaul.
To see this architecture in action,
let's look at how to normalize channel
processing, which is historically
one of our biggest pain points.
Different chipsets report channel state
pre-equalization and bonding behavior
using widely disparate con-conventions.
Go adapters standardize channel power,
timing offset, and MER reporting
across all chip, chipset families.
The platform normalizes OFDM and
SC-QAM profile states, RX MER per
subcarrier, and bonding group membership.
Consistent detection and alerting
regardless of vendor-specific partial
service signaling conventions.
Normalization opens the door to
intelligent automation, allow,
allowing us to build closed-loop
dynamic channel management at scale.
Now let's see at feedback loop.
The system continuously
collects telemetry, evaluates it
against threshold, and triggers
optimization actions in real time.
Massive concurrency.
Go's concurrency model a-allows
us to monitor massive cable
modem populations simultaneously
without performance degradation.
Automated profiles.
We collect per subcarrier, uh,
receiver MER data to automate OFDM
profile assignments, eliminating
manual engineering interventions.
Isolated execution.
When an optimization action is
required, the abstraction layer
translates the uniform decision into
the correct vendor-specific command.
Beyond real-time channel adjustments,
this platform entirely revolutionizes and
standardizes our provisioning pipeline.
Let's look at eliminating inconsistency.
Manual vendor-specific provisioning
is a breeding ground of co-- is a
breeding ground for configuration
drift and operational errors.
There are four steps in this.
Let's look at discovery.
At registration, the system leverages SNMP
or RESTCONF to automatically identify the
hardware's vendor and baseline firmware.
The step two is config rendering.
It... the platform generates the correct
vendor-specific configuration directly
from a single canonical template store.
Step three is push and guardrails.
The designated adapter applies
the config complete with built-in
automation retry and rollback logic.
Step four is audit.
The system validates that the design
reached... sorry, that, that the
device reached its target operational
state, logging the full transaction
for absolute trans, uh, traceability.
Firmware updates carry immense
operational risk across a mixed fleet.
We use the platform to build a
systematic validation, uh, pipeline.
Now the risk.
A single firmware change can
manifest completely different
behaviors or regressions across
separate shipping, uh, families.
Now, what automated lab, uh, lab
gating does is, uh, the Go-based
pipeline automate, au-automatically
provisions lab test devices with
known good baseline configuration.
Functional test su-test suits.
It runs rigorous automated test
suits covering channel, state
transactions, registration
success, and throughput benchmarks.
Regression testing.
It compares new telemetry directly
against historical baselines using
structured pass or fail reports
integrated into release workflows.
To fuel these automated
validations and management systems,
the platform runs a massive
high-throughput telemetry pipeline.
The scale problem.
Broadband fleets generate relentless
high-volume streams of performance
and diagnostic data every second.
Concurrent ingestion.
The ingestion layer uses Go routines
to process SNMP, RestConf, and
streaming telemetry concurrently
across various network segments.
Unified namespace.
The normalization layer immediately
maps fragmented vendor schemas into
a single unified metric namespace.
The route.
Metrics are dynamically labeled by region
vendor, firmware versions, and service
group, allowing for seamless data routing.
This high-scale telemetry pipeline
feeds directly into centralized
observate, observability plane,
completely eliminating the
need for vendor-specific tools.
Unified workspace.
Engineers operate from a single unified
view where fleet health registration
statuses and error counters live together.
Advanced captures.
The plane supports scheduled and
on-demand diagnostic captures of
pre-equalization, co-effici-efficiencies,
spectrum data, and event logs.
Actionable alerting.
Alerts are triggered based on
normalized platforms signals rather
than vendor-specific, um, terminology,
making them instantly actionable.
Engineers no longer waste time
guessing which tool or schema to use.
This architecture isn't just about
solving today's operational headaches.
It is foundation...
It is foundational for navigation the, uh,
navigating the future of next-gen DOCSIS.
High split readiness.
The high split upgrades demand
highly precise upstream, uh, spectrum
and channel management, requiring
uniform handling across all chipsets.
DOCSIS four point O evolution.
As we transition towards DOCSIS four
point O, our existing Go tools for profile
management and telemetry will carry
forward into ESD and FTX environments.
True vendor agility.
Onboarding a brand-new chipset vendor
down the line simply means writing a new
micro adapter, not rewriting the platform.
Now, what the core message here
is a Go-based unified DOCSIS
platform successfully transforms
vendor diversity into a highly
managed, uh, implementation detail.
Do not spend tr...
uh, do not spend time trying
to avoid hardware diversity.
Build the right abstraction
layers to normalize behavior.
Go is built for infrastructure.
Take advantage of Go's concurrency model,
runtime performance, and deployment
simplicity to build reliable systems.
Consistency and lock speed.
Standardized provisioning, testing,
and diagnostics drastically reduce
troubleshooting, um, overhead and
dramatically improve field readiness.
Future-proof Building this unified
model today guarantees your network
is fully prepared for high split
and next-gen evolution tomorrow.
Thank you all for s- your time today.
I hope this session illustrated
how abstraction, normalization,
and automation in GOG can
streamline multi-vendor operations.
By eliminating chipset quirks, we
free our engineering teams to spend
less time firefighting and more
time driving network performance.
Please, please reach out to me
on LinkedIn if you have more
questions about this topic.
I'll be happy to help you.
Thank you so much for your time.