Hello everyone, and welcome to my
presentation on building robust
V two X communication networks
in go scaling connected vehicle
systems for urban mobility.
My name is Otam Kumar and I'm
excited to show how Golan often
called go with its concurrency model
and cloud native microservices as
pioneering safe, intelligent, and
high throughput urban mobility.
Over the next few minutes, we'll explore
how connected vehicle systems leverage
go to enhance vehicle to everything
communication, leading to more efficient
traffic flow, improved safety, and truly
transformative results for modern cities.
Before we jump onto the technical
deep dive, here is a quick
introduction to my background.
I spent over 20 years working on
program and product management as well
as end-to-end technology solutions.
My master's in engineering comes from
technological university and I'm also
a project management professional with
advanced sales scale Agile certifications.
In my role at major enterprises like
Visa, T-Mobile, Verizon, Lenovo, and IBM,
I have seen how crucial innovation is.
For scaling global platforms, especially
in the realm of connected vehicle systems.
Recently, I've also been leveraging
generative AI to accelerate product
delivery and optimize operations.
My global experience across the us,
India, Japan, Singapore, has shaped
my approach to building robust,
scalable solutions that meet the
unique challenges of different markets.
Now let's talk about our focus
for this section focusing on
how go Powers V two X solutions.
Firstly, we'll explore ghost
concurrency model and perform suit
performance suit the high throughput
demands of connected vehicle systems.
Next, we'll discuss how pilot deployments
of go based collision provision services
have shown up to and, shown up to
reduce up to 40% in crash reduction.
We'll then examine scalable intersection
management in the cloud, processing
thousands of vehicle interactions per
second to cut conditions and emissions.
Finally, we'll discuss DevOps.
Best practice on how ghost concurrency
patterns ensure fault tolerant
continuously deploy services at scale.
Let's start by defining
V two X communication.
Now, V two X, like everyone knows,
stands for vehicle to everything.
It compasses, vehicle to vehicle to
infrastructure, vehicle to pedestrian
everything, vehicle to everything.
Communication.
Essentially, it's about creating
a unified network where vehicles,
road infrastructure, and even
pedestrians can communicate seamlessly.
Now the impact is significant.
V two X can reduce collections about
a 40 percentage, improve traffic
flow by 30 percentage and even more
in certain markets, and accelerate
emerging response times by 40
percentage, which is very crucial.
As for market growth, we
are seeing around at least.
Around 18 percentage of CAGR globally
with predictions that over half a
new half of all the new vehicles will
have V two X capabilities by 2030.
Now that's a massive opportunity
for anyone building or
adopting V two X solutions.
Now let's look at why go Language
is such a powerful choice for
V two X. Communication systems.
Now GOs concurrency model is built
around go routines, lightweight threads
that can handle thousands or even
millions of simultaneous connections
with minimal overhead channels.
Provide a safe mechanism to pass
data between these core routines,
preventing race conditions, which
is critical when multiple vehicles
share the time sensitive data.
This leads to a highly parallel
event processing perfect for reading
sensor data from numerous vehicles
in real time, whether for collision
avoidance or dynamic routing, so
on and In addition to concurrency
go brings us topnotch performance.
Oh, let me dive into a
little bit depth there.
Low latency go's runtime is optimized for
near instance startup times and minimal
latency, which is vital when dealing with
such kind of a safety related vehicle
operations, which is very important.
Now memory footprint, go routines use far
less memory than traditional OS threats.
Making them ideal for high
connection counts in edge
devices or embedded systems.
Now it's obvious why we'll need that
profiling and optimization tools,
those like PP prof and tracing healthy,
constantly fine tuned performance,
identifying bottlenecks in real time
so that you can deliver the fastest
possible response for V two X events.
And everyone understands why.
Further to that, just on my
previous, slide, let's look at some
performance benchmarks now, under
a hundred million tron a hundred
milliseconds, end-to-end latency is
critical for collision avoidance.
Now you need this because you
need a near instant reaction time.
And sustainability sustained
500,000 plus messages per second.
Throughput handles the highest volume
of data from sensors like GPS modules,
traffic signals, so on and so forth.
99.99% uptime achieved via
circuit breakers and fall tolerant
architecture and safety critical apps.
High availability is a run mandatory must.
25 percentage of personal performance
gain was achieved through iterative
tuning with goals, profiling tools showing
how continuous optimization pays off.
These figures demonstrate go's
ability to deliver on the rigorous
demands of V two X. Now, let's
go on to some more advantages.
Another key advantage that is go's robust
standard library now networking and
cryptography, inbuilt packages making
soccer programming straightforward, and
the crypto libraries handle encrypted,
authenticated directions between vehicles.
Crucial for V two security,
http, json, et cetera.
Go.
Standard library supports common web
protocols and data encoding outta the box.
This is essential for over the
air updates, telemetry, APIs, or
communication with cloud services.
Now, this out of the box supports
speeds up development timelines
and ensures consistent secure data
handling across V two X networks.
That's one of the major things in
current vehicle to vehicle communication.
Let's see what these
features mean in practice.
go's, real world capabilities,
high throughput concurrency, go's
go routines handle thousands of
vehicle interactions in real time.
Crucial for traffic optimization.
Mission critical microservices
pilot deployment show up to 40%
crash reductions in collision
prevention systems built with Go.
Cloud native scalability goes
lightweight threads and network
libraries scale horizontally on container
orchestration platforms like Kubernetes,
DevOps, and resilience goes fast.
Built-in foster continuous delivery,
ensuring quick rollouts of new safety
features, IOT and edge compatibility.
This is very crucial because minimal
overhead means core runs efficiently on
distributed edge nodes, which is critical
for real-time data processing in vehicles.
Now it's very clear why these
capabilities combine to create a powerful
foundation for any V two X installation.
Let me move on.
Here's a high level view of how go
fits into the V two X architecture.
You have key components, like for example,
you have the API Gateways for secure
vehicle telemetry, ingestion, real-time
messaging, example, NAS Kafka, MQTT
to handle data streams and specialized
analyticals and decision services for
collision detection or root optimization.
Scalability patterns
deployed on Kubernetes.
These go microservices
can scale elastically.
Automated CI ICD pipelines and Canada
releases ensure zero downtime when
rolling out updates, data flows,
vehicles send data to an H stone
running on goal-based processing, which
communicates with cloud microservices.
The system then aggregates,
analyzes, and sends back.
The instructions are used in order.
We are talking about horizontal
scaling that can handle up to
600,000 messages per second.
Delivering the real time
responsiveness demanded by modern
cities, that's pretty huge.
Moving on beyond raw performance,
developer productive results, a
major benefit, and if we can see why.
Simple syntax goes minimalistic
approach and built in GO FMT
results in uniform code style,
fewer errors and quicker onboarding.
Now that's very important.
Static typing.
Scopic collection balances type safety
with modern memory management, making
code more robust for large projects.
Fast compilation.
GoPro uses small binary quickly,
which is invaluable when deploying to
vehicles or resource country edge nodes.
Now this means fast ations, fewer
bugs, and a more efficient development
cycle overall, which is a dream for
any software development company.
Let me move on.
Security and privacy.
No security is non-negotiable
in connected vehicles.
And go.
As you covered multi-layer encryption.
Go steel LS, tax, secures,
transmissions, ephemeral key rotation,
proven replay attacks, advanced
cryptography, elliptic curve, and.
Post Quantum protocols are
actively developed in the GO
Community simplified concurrency.
Because Go concurrency is built in, you're
less likely to introduce multi-threaded
security flaws ensures go crypto libraries
and concurrency model aligned with
the high security standards required
for connected automotive ecosystems.
Another huge place is grows
growing community and ecosystem.
Now you'll find abundant open source
libraries for realtime streaming messages,
queues and IOD integration Frameworks
now accelerate that AC accelerates
your video X development process.
The active developer support means
security patches new libraries
when best practice are updated
regularly, ensuring the ecosystem
stays healthy and future proof.
Now this collaborative environment can
significantly cut down on development
time and risk, which is very important
for any B two X communication systems
just like any other high priority systems.
Now let's see some ideal vehicle to
vehicle or way two x communication
use cases where go really shines
real time data ingestion, handling
sensor streams from and GPS data
from multiple vehicle simultaneously
with no bottleneck whatsoever.
Collision prevent and safety
distributor algorithms running in
parallel to exchange situational
awareness and trigger avoidance,
manual telemetry and diagnostics.
Collect engine hardware,
software metrics, and security.
Transport them to cloud or
IT service for analysis.
Which is very crucial.
Integration with infrastructure seamlessly
connected through roadside units.
Our traffic management centers
enabling advanced traffic
optimizations and coordinated driving.
These scenarios.
Highlight goals, high concurrency,
security, and lightweight
approach exactly what you need
for a perfect V two X system.
Moving on, here are the key takeaways.
If you're considering go for
your B two X communication.
One High concurrency for realtime
data processing simplicity that leads
to rapid development and fewer bugs.
Security.
Security stands why integrated
cryptographic libraries.
Exceptional performance under heavy load.
Ideal for safety critical systems.
These four points, some Y go stands out
as a top contender for building robust,
scalable, and secure V two X networks.
Now that wraps up our journey
into building robust V two X
communication networks in Go.
Thank you so much for joining me today.
I hope this session gives you
a clear picture of how ghost
concurrency model and cloud native
approach can elevate connected
vehicle systems for urban mobility.
If you have any questions about
implementing goin V two X or you'd
like more in-depth technical resources,
please feel free to reach out.
Thank you once again for your
time and I look forward to
continuing the conversation.
Thank you very much.