Speaker 8: Hello, everyone.
My name is Ivan Balashov.
I am work as tech lead in a SoftSwiss
company, and my topic today is
engineering high performance real-time
leaderboards in our application, in
our product that where I'm working now.
I think each good story started
from production incident in software
engineering because everybody do
some mix ta-- mistakes and the
interest-- the most interesting
here is how they cope with that and
what they do to solve these issues.
As I already said that I'm working
a product that s-serves some
real-time tournament leaderboards
and back office in SoftSwiss.
We have more than 1,500 casinos operators
in our platform, and we have strictly
rules to serve our data and our API.
My ma- my main focus is to build high load
Go services if-- especially microservices
and especially microservices architecture.
I built already some billing for one
fintech company, some fi-- another one
fintech product for credits for business,
and all of them was connected with Go,
with microservices, with high load.
Right now, I'm more than 10
years work as software engineer,
as backend software engineer.
In very beginning I had experience to
write on some specific languages, for
example, Perl, C, and so on and so
forth, but more than eight years, I am
stick to the Go lang, and it's my ma-
my major language to making products.
We have some SLA that we should
provide our leaderboards to our clients
around or less than 50 milliseconds to
clients of our clients, to their users.
And in one morning at the Christmas
holidays, we faced with problem that we
don't cover this SLA because we, they
started some promo campaigns, and we just
didn't expect that these campaigns will
be-- would be so succ-successful, and
our we reached one more -- we reached
one more how to say, high- highest
level of our cu- users of our customers.
One leaderboard contained more than
half of the million participants
that really pl-- that really
compete between each other.
And it it affected us by
significantly increasing CPU load.
Kubernetes started to kill our pods, and
we are started to serve our leaderboards
much more slower than we did it before.
And we-- I-- it was first time when I
saw on metrics that CPU throttling was
around one minute, not nanoseconds,
microseconds or seconds, one minute.
As already mentioned before,
SoftSwiss is the-- one of the biggest
company in the world that serve some
i-iGaming services to our clients.
Here is some s-metrics that we already
reached, and we are continue to grow.
And of course, this grow is connected
with increasing load on our platform.
What I want to cover, I want to tell
you a story w- I want to tell you a
story about how we g-got this production
incident, tell more about exactly
production incident and what we saw on the
metrics and logs and so on and so forth.
I want to cover why we didn't choose Redis
as solution to store our leaderboards
in production, and what solution we
found to, to how to say, what solution
we found to in the code, how to solve
this problem by just code in a Golang,
not by adding one more dependency.
I will say about what impact was
on our production application, how
decreased the load on CPU, how we
s-solved this production incident,
and the lessons that we learned.
We have five requirements to
our data structure that that
we already know right now.
Before that, of course, we didn't
highlight them when we started
to build our leaderboards, first
it's high write throughput.
We should our data structure should
allow us to write a lot of data in th-
in this data structure without data
loss, without any issues with that.
We should constant run queries.
It means here players, operator,
and compliance, but of course,
the main idea here is the players.
Players should see h- their place
in the leaderboard instantly.
Identity deduplication here
is the idea that we have a
lot of options to use our API.
It depends on the client.
He could choose couple of them
and we should de- deduplicate data
from them because sometimes they
could for example, had a mistake
and send data twice or more times.
Multi-tenant isolation, it's about
that our data structure shouldn't allow
to see data, one casino to see data
from another one casino, of course.
And reads can block writes.
It mean that users should see our
leaderboard while we are writing
in it new dat- new portion of data.
Here is how our leaderboard looked before.
It was the plain array and w-
which was covered by mutex.
And here is some, for example, some
ugly piece of code, how we updated
our entity inside this array.
We just traverse the whole array from
the very beginning till the end, just
update the score for one entity and
sort it using common Go sort slice.
And you could imagine what's going
on if we, for example, have I
don't know, maybe half of million
events per maybe five seconds.
It significantly increase the CPU
load because sort is CPU-bound load,
and that's how we reach our limit.
If we talk more about incident
we reached 100 CPU that
infrastructure team provide to us.
We s- after, of course, after that, o- OOM
from Kubernetes started to kill our ports
because it is common behavior, of course.
And here is 50% traffic was enough.
Yeah, The-- by our calculation
more than fifty percent at
those p- competitions part...
Those competitions contained participants
on fifty percents more than usual.
It means that we really reached our--
we were on the edge of our limit,
and we just reached it so fast.
When I noticed it, when alerts started
to bring in our Slack channel, I,
of course, asked our infrastructure
team, can I increase just CPU
count on each pod in the device and
maybe it could solve the problem?
The small spoiler, no, it didn't.
We had in our common setup, we had
eight CPU on each pod, and we have
three pods, and we load all eight CPUs.
After that, I increased them twice.
It was sixty sixteen CPU per each
pod, and we destroyed them all too.
And of course, on the... When I k- went
to them second time, they said, "No, you
should solve this problem by rewriting
code, not by increasing the hardware."
Because Kubernetes has cap of CPU on the
whole cluster, and we could add the whole
cluster CPU and of course, it could affect
the whole system, not only one service.
When we s-- when I started to think
what what the solution of this problem,
of course, the first idea that could
appear in mind, it was the Redis.
Redis already know how to work with
this, for example, leaderboards,
that he could sort out entities
in a descending ord-order.
He could provide really fast
updates inside his inside
his special data structure.
But we didn't have Redis
before in our production.
It means that we should, we s- we should
write we should write the implementation
before that, and of course, it takes time.
Moreover, the main problem here that
our admin team should deploy this Redis
too, and they have strict restriction,
like it shouldn't be just one Redis.
It should be Sentinel Redis they,
of course, they didn't know w-in
which configuration it should be,
and it could take more time to
them to deploy Redis than we just
write the code to work with Redis.
And some concerns that we have worldwide
splitted clusters, and this Redis
should be splitted too because it could
one more round trip, for example, if
somebody from Europe want to g-give
want to get his leaderboard or and for
example, master node of our Redis was
moved, I don't know, maybe to the USA.
It one more round trip that could
broke our SLA around 50 millisecond
that I already mentioned before.
And we are started to think
about the algorithmic solution,
data structure solution instead
of adding one more dependency.
As I already said that leaderboards
has one interesting dependency that all
data in this le- in this leaderboard
should be sorted in a descending order.
It mean that on the first place should
be player with the highest score, and
on the la- on the last place should
be player with the lowest score.
And at those moment, I started to think
about linked list because the main
idea that... or double linked list.
The main idea that if you, for example
if player increase his score, we
just should put him further in a
linked list I or maybe better to say
closer to the head of linked list.
Then, m- and it allow us to stay
leaderboard in a consistent way that every
player in this competition will be sorted.
But the main problem of linked
list here is that for example,
to find somebody position yeah it
will take you not constant time.
You should traverse from the head of
linked list till the, this position.
And if we talk about for example,
positions, okay, in the middle it,
it should take O, big O from N. And
it's quite, could be quite a lot of
operations as we talk, for example,
half of million participants The
main solution here was skip list.
The main idea of this skip list that we
have a lot of linked list above of our
main linked list that store the data.
But this linked list is, They
contain not the whole bunch of data
that contain the main linked list.
And the traverse for example, finding
somebody should be from the left left
upper corner till the, on the right and
down, and it could take much more less
operation than in a linked list, and that
I will show you in the fu- in the future.
And the main trick here is how
to manage all these new levels.
Because if you want to reach N
log big O notation from log N,
you should have some math inside.
And here is a coin flip.
But the main idea that this coin flip
isn't the common coin flip because
common coin flip allow us have result
50/50, have 50% head, 50% tail.
But here is 75% should be head
and only 25% should be tail.
And right now I will explain
where is here coin flip appear.
Oh, sorry.
Before that here is how our
node w-written in a code.
We have a struct node that contain
user ID, score, timestamp because
sometimes we should for example, if
users has the same score we should
sort them out by timestamp because
the user that reach his score earlier
should be upper in the leaderboard.
And here is at one more not one more,
two more special variables like height
on which height this node and levels
on which level next it contain itself
next nodes and spans th-this array.
And index of this level is index
of the level that I re- that I you
could see on this, for example,
picture I will Two or L one.
Here is how it looks like on the paper.
We have... Here we have eight nodes
from P one to P eight and three
levels from L two to level zero.
And you could see that on level two, on
the highest level, we have only one node.
It means P one.
And on the level two, we have three
nodes, P one, P two, and P four.
And on level zero, we have
the whole our linked list that
sorted in a descending order.
And above that, it's a score of players.
It's just for example.
Spans here it is the
distance between the nodes.
If you, Y- you can see the distance
between P one and end of our list is
seven, P one or P two it's two, P two
and P four, four, P four and the ending
is four, and on the lowest level zero
all distances is equal to the one.
Here is example picture how new
levels is appearing, and here is
the main mechanism of coin flip.
We want to put in our list new node
that P one the... And with score
nine thousand eight hundred fifty.
And here is the algorithm started
to coin flip, and you could
see that here was head, tail.
And our main height that height that
this coin flip provide us is three.
That... And three is much
more than we have max level.
Max level was two.
And we add new point in all our levels.
The main the main fact here that if
we put, for example... we can't put
a node on level two and level zero.
We should put node on each level
from the from the top to bottom.
It means P one here appear in level
two, in level one, and in level zero.
It's important because it allow
us to drop down from the one lev--
from the more than one levels.
Here is example how we traverse
to find seven hund-- seven thous-
thousand five hundred player with s-
Seven thousand five hundred score.
We started from the very beginning P one.
P one more than our searchable value.
But after P one, we don't have nodes.
It mean that we should drop.
We drop on level one.
On level one, we have next node, P two.
P two is more than our searchable
value and we look for the next node.
Next node in the level one will be P four.
In P four, we have value as
six thousand one hundred, that
less than we are searching for.
That's why we are dropped down.
And on the level zero, now our
next step will be our searchable
value, our searchable, for
example, player in our in our list.
By this example, I wanted to sh- I want
to show that our, for example, search
in this lin- is in this data structure
is faster than in a common linked list.
Here we took only four
forward moves instead of five.
And of course, on the biggest on
the bigger linked list participants,
it should be much more faster than
traverse by the whole this linked list.
Let's talk about second operation with
this data structure is insert new data.
Here is how we traverse the same.
We looked for the place for our new P nine
node and we are walked ju- to the P three,
and we know-- we understand that we should
put this node between P three and P four.
On the, on this slide,
how we put this node.
We are started to making
a coin throw, coin toss.
And our coin toss said that head and tail.
It means that we should put this node
from the level one to the level zero.
And as you can see on the highest level,
we just increase the span by one because
we add one more node and we should
recalculate the spans on the level
one or, and level zero one more time.
Between P two and P
four, the span was two.
And we add one more node but the
distance didn't change, and we
are started to calcu-calculate the
arithmetic here above this scheme.
I don't want I don't want to how to say
out loud how it works because we have
not a lot of time to speak about that.
And if we talk about
deleting, all work the same.
We remove our node, and we should
recalculate all spans because the
distance be-between nodes is changed.
It means between P3 and P4 distance,
total distance was two, and it becomes
one because we removed this node.
Between... On the level one, between
P2 and P4, distance was three, and
we should remove one span because
it was three and become two.
And from P1 to end, it was eight and
becomes seven because we removed one node.
And of course, if we talk about
moving our players in the linked
list, in, in this skip list, we
can just delete this no-delete this
node and put in it in a new place.
But here is the trick: we
didn't delete it at all.
We are, in our code, we are store
previous levels that this node already
had for for don't making new coin tosses.
And it al-allow us to not, it
allow us to not how to say, change
the height of this new node.
If we talk about the deduplication,
nothing special here.
We just used a hash function.
We took couple of IDs that
our customer provide us.
It mean group user ID, email, and we
just calculate hash to distinguish which
user is, which user score is changed and
whom we should to move in our skip list.
Before implement that, we decided
to to test it in a three ways.
Of course, we wrote unit test on e-exact
on the implementation of skip list.
We wrote the integration test for our new
leaderboards that was tested like that
our leaderboards works as we expected,
that the business logic wasn't changed.
And w- of course, we had manual
plus performance tests that
everything works okay, like human
check that everything is okay.
And we tried to overload our new our new
leaderboards, but perf- performance tests
didn't show us that it was work bad.
What we got by this solution.
Right now, I suppose we increased our dur-
durability of our product significantly.
We could s- work sustain, I
think, in much more load that
we got on those we holidays.
Here is an example that
100K we should work stable.
Here is data from the,
our performance tests.
We decreased latency because we not sorted
out all of these leaderboards in real
time each time when something changed.
CPU decreased CPU load was
decreased significantly.
Really, right now I don't, I didn't
see or better to say, I hadn't seen
CPU throttling less than one not
less, more than one millisecond.
It works s- really fast, incredibly fast.
And after that, of course, we we
finished the struggle by OOM kills.
Our pod worked without restarts.
And I really proud of that,
that we implemented, delivered
this fix in two working days.
Not like day, night, day, night,
only two working days for making
this solution production ready.
And yeah, the system become boring.
System work as expected, nothing special.
And we just right now look f- look
for not look for, look over these
applications and see how it works pretty
well and nothing could change here.
If we talk about lessons that,
that I learned that, It's not
common that standard answers
is always the right answer.
Sometimes you really should look aside
and find the really interesting and
suitable solutions because we are
debated, for example, about trees.
Maybe we should use tree and so on and
so forth, but I think that this idea
of skip list is fit us pretty well.
Custom data structures yes.
I think that a lot of developers
missed that understanding that data
structure is important knowledge in
our everyday rou- e-everyday routine,
that we are just use that developer
of our language provide us and forgot
that some, for example, sometimes heap
existed, graph existed, this linked list
existed, and so on and f- and so forth.
And it's important to know and study them.
And profile before you optimize, yes, it's
really important thing if we talk about
the high load and overloaded systems.
We are implemented one more
thing that it names Pyroscope.
It allow us to see flame graph in
real time in production, and we
sometimes look on these graphs and
see all good or not because right
now, as already mentioned, right now
we don't have any problem with that.
And here is finish my speech.
If you have any question,
you could ask them.