Hey, good morning everyone.
It's an absolute pleasure
to be here today.
Today I will be discussing about
scaling financial design systems
with go by building high performance
FinTech infrastructure in the cloud.
Let's start the session.
How many of you have ever been frustrated
with slow and outdated financial systems?
It may be a via transfer.
Took long.
A repayment got stuck
without a clear reason.
We have been there.
Financial system should be
fast, secure, and frictionless.
But legacy structure and outdated
technology often makes this a challenging.
This is where go on cloud
native architecture comes in.
They enable us to build scalable.
Resilient and high performance
financial systems that can perform
millions of transactions in real time.
In today's session, I will walk you
through how we process millions of
transaction style using Go Power
Microservices by leveraging AI
and machine learning to predict
risk, detect fraud, and optimize
financial decisions, build secure.
Scalable A PS that tell us seamless
integration across banks on digital
wallets and financial applications.
Reduce infrastructure cost by 40% while
some inte increase speed and security.
Does it sound exciting?
Now, let's deep dive in.
now let's deep dive into our
microservice architecture.
Now I built a truly
scalable financial system.
We need a solid architectural foundation.
Let's imagine a highway,
let's imagine a highway.
Where cars move smoothly
without traffic jumps.
That's exactly what we have built with our
microservice architecture, cloud native
process by distributing transaction.
Processing.
We present services, overloads and exits
industry standards by 35% by using Go.
Go is built for speed and con.
While traditional languages like Java
or Python struggle with high load
processing with go goin enables us
to handle thousands of requests per
second with minimal latency coming
to resilience distributor systems.
Our architecture guarantees that
99.99% uptime by ensuring that
even if a service fails, traffic is
automatically re rerouted to backup notes.
To put this into.
Perspective, think about Black Friday
or major stock market trading days when
Dragon section volume score search.
Our system scales dynamically to handle
these spikes, ensuring a seamless
experience for millions of users.
But not only scalability, we
also need intelligence in our
systems because everywhere we see.
Artificial intelligence is growing big and
machine learning is dominating everywhere.
So let's move to mission
learning integration.
Coming to mission learning, integration
and artificial intelligence.
These are revolutionaries in
financial decision making.
So how do we bring intelligence?
Into FinTech.
That's what our question.
Over here with help of data ingestion, we
process massive amount of structured and
unstructured data, including transactions.
Under histories on real time marketing
feeds, customer spending patterns, and
also with help of AI powered analysis,
our module uncovers patterns that
human might overlook, like such as
predicting which customer are likely to
default on loans, identifying trading.
Opportunities in volatile market
security and fraud detection, our
AI reduced false positive by 78% by
ensuring that legitimate transactions
go through without unnecessary blocks.
Quick caution for you all guys here.
How many of you had.
Had credit card transaction
declined due to security concerns.
Now, imagine if instead of blocking
your legitimate transaction, AI
could accurately differentiate
between fraud and a normal purchase.
That's exactly what our system does.
But intelligence is only useful
if it can be shared efficiently.
That brings us API and backbone of modern
financial systems coming to API ecosystem.
Coming to API ecosystem, APIs are the glue
that connects modern financial systems.
Without them, banks and FinTech
platforms would be isolated.
Islands struggling to
communicate with each other.
Our API ecosystem handles over 15 million
dial requests with 99.9 uptime, supporting
both rest and graphical, offering
flexibility for different clients.
Accelerates integration, banks
and FinTech companies can go
live in weeks instead of months.
Let's take a real world example.
Imagine a startup company that wants
to offer instant credit scoring
with our a PS, they can tap into
our AI engine, analyze the user's
credit worthiness in real time,
and approve a loan within seconds.
API alone or in turnoff, we
need strong, scalable cloud
infrastructure to support them.
Let's explore that next.
Coming to cloud infrastructure revolution,
migrating to the cloud is ingested trend.
It's necessary for modern financial
systems by ensuring zero downtime
migration, be transactioned, enter
bank system to the cloud without
disturbing daily operations.
40% of cost reduction.
By leveraging serverless computing,
we pay only for what we use.
Reducing the need for expenses on
premises servers and also multi-cloud
strategy utilizing multiple cloud
providers, ensuring redundancy,
prevents outage, and helps company to
compile with regional data regulations.
For example, a tradition bank
that use it to take day two.
The settlement payments can now
process them in real time thanks
to our cloud infrastructure.
Now that we have covered scalability
and cloud efficiency, let's talk about
what really matters to customers.
Personalized financial services.
Let's move to it.
Coming to personalized
financial services, ai.
AI driven financial is.
Reshaping the way customers manage
their money in by investment strategies.
Our AI driven realtime
investment recommendations.
Customize the individual's risk profile.
Coming to depth management
clients using our platform.
Save an average of 15%
on interest payments.
Through optimized repayment strategies,
coming to financial planning, predictive
modeling helps people prepare for
life's financial uncertainties.
To support these intelligent
financial services, we need
a rock solid DevOps strategy.
Let's take a look at how we achieve that.
we all know about DevOps
coming to, for the.
we all know about DevOps, right?
DevOps excellence.
Without DevOps, no one or none of
these innovations would be possible.
95 percentage of test coverage before
deploying any code by insuring zero
downtime deployment, using blue
green deployment strategies and also
realtime monitoring allows us to.
Detect resolve issues before
customers even notice.
The result is faster and innovation,
greater reliability and happier customers.
Another key technology driving
trustees, FinTech in blockchain.
Let's see how we are integrating it.
Coming to blockchain integration,
blockchain is transforming financial
transactions by introducing
greater trust and transparency.
Smart contracts are like, it
eliminates middleman and reducing
cost by 30% on risk assessment.
Every transaction is permanently recorded,
preventing fraud and insured compliance.
Adapt to market contracts, our
system dynamically responds to
market in fluctuations in real time.
Speaking of fraud, let's take a
closer look at how we can stop
financial crimes before they happen.
let's move to.
Fraud detection systems fraud remains
one of the biggest challenging
in FinTech as all we know, and we
take it seriously, to resolve this.
Microsecond monitoring transactions
are analyzed in real time to
prevent fraud before it happens.
AI powered detections.
Our models continuously learn
from millions of past fraud
items and improve the accuracy.
The fraud ion is by 60 th 63%.
Banks using our systems help cut
fraud losses by nearly two third,
but stopping fraud isn't enough.
We also have to meet strict regulatory.
Requirements.
So let's jump into regulatory Confluence.
Compliance isn't just about following
rules, it's about protecting business
and all our customers, 99.7% accuracy.
In EML screening, we flag
suspicious transactions instantly.
KYC in 40 seconds.
Customers onboard.
In under a minute.
Instead of days, 98% less manual work.
Compliance teams save hundreds
of hours through automation.
Now coming to measurable business
outcomes, oh, 78% faster processing
transaction happened almost instantly.
63% of road reduction, greater
security, and low risk, 89%
developer productivity boost more
innovations and less maintenance.
42% cost savings by less
infrastructure waste and more
efficiency coming to conclusion.
How do we make financial systems
faster, smarter, and safer?
The all out of this we can say is
like with help of AI driven and cloud
powered and go based infrastructure.
Thank you everyone for attending
the session and I would
like to take any questions.
Thank you all.