Hello and welcome to Con 42 Golang 2025.
It's a pleasure to be
here with all of you.
My name is Misal, and today we are
going to explore a topic that's
shaping the future of IT operations,
automations, and monitoring tools.
The, the landscape of systems
management has evolved dramatically, to.
Gone are the days of manual
troubleshooting issues and
reacting after failure occurs.
Instead, modern enterprises are now
leveraging intelligent solutions to
detect, prevent, and even resolve
incidents before the impact operations.
So over the, next few minutes, we
will be, diving deep into some of the
most of powerful tools in this space.
That's how they integrate with
the enterprise environment and
the key benefits they bring in.
So let's get started.
Automation is more than
just a convenience.
It's a necessity these days by
reducing manual intervention by nearly
80% organizations free of IT teams.
To focus on innovations rather
than routing maintenance.
faster response times mean that
incidents are resolved before they
escalate and increase accuracy.
Accuracy translates to
fewer costly errors.
Studies show that automation leads
to a 40% drop in operational cost.
A significant financial
advantage for enterprises.
With these benefits in mind, let's
explore how IT operations have evolved
from a reactive to a predictive approach.
Historically, IT teams only, reacted
to incidents after they occurred.
This meant extended downtimes
and increased disruptions.
Moving to a proactive model, teams
began leveraging monitoring systems to.
Catch potential failures early.
The real, breakthrough, however, is
the predictive operations with AI
powered analytics as organizations can
forecast failures with our 90% accuracy,
preventing downtime altogether and keep
critical services running smoothly.
and, To make predictive
operations successful, we need
a robust monitoring tools.
So let's take a look at the two of the
most powerful tools exist in the market.
our
Prometheus, and in our industry.
Leading monitoring solutions.
All so cells in high precision data
collection and alerting, making it
perfect for dynamic cloud environments.
Na s with its rich, plugin ecosystem and
a longstanding reputation is ideal for
comprehensive infrastructure oversight.
These organizations that integrate
these tools see, see, 94% improvement
in anomaly detection and maintain
the five nine availability.
So less, which is less, less than
five minutes of, downtime per year.
But monitoring alone isn't enough.
We also need deep observability.
and hence that's where Datadog
comes into the picture.
As enterprise shift to the multi
cloud and hybrid environments,
visibility becomes critical.
Datadog provides a unified view across
infrastructure, applications, and logs,
enabling teams to detect bottlenecks
and optimize performance in real time.
From granular quarter level, I'm
tracing to AI powered log analysis.
Datadog helps enterprises boost
system reliability by nearly 77%
while reducing meantime to solution
with cloud native monitoring in place.
Let's explore how AI is taking.
Okay.
IT operations.
Even further, AI ops or ai, our IT
operations is, it's literally, we are
transforming incident management instead
of waiting of for alerts, AI driven
tools, continuously analyze patterns,
detect anomalies, and even shared
automated remediation, these self-healing.
Billing.
These self healing capabilities help
businesses reduce unplanned downtime and
cut incident response times by over 80%.
This means fewer manual escalations
and more, reliable operations at scale.
Yes, AI just doesn't detect, data issues.
It also learns from them.
So let's d dive into how machine
learning, plays an important role in this.
The integration of, machine learning
in monitoring, systems unlocks
unprecedented efficiencies by recognizing,
patterns and predicting failures.
Ml, driven systems adapt over time,
refining that accuracy with each
incident, so advanced and detection,
and ensures that potential issues are
flagged before the impact the users
significantly reducing system disruptions.
Now to understand the full impact
of these advancements, let's take
a look at some real world numbers.
So as you can see on the screen,
organizations implementing automated
monitoring solutions report up to five
nines up times, and showing that systems
remain operational around the clock.
Manual intervention drops dramatically
with automated remediation, reducing
human effort by over 78%, quicker,
response times and AI driven
insights make it teams more effective
while cutting operational course.
So for it o. IT professionals
looking to stay ahead.
Building hands-on experience is crucial.
So let's see how Home
Labs can help in this.
for it, it, our professionals Hands-on
Learning is in valuable home labs or
provide a risk free environment to master
tools, experiment with configurations and.
Similar, the real world incidents
studies show that those who regularly
engage with home labs improve
their technical proficiency by over
80% as compared to those who rely
solely on the theory based learning.
So once we develop skills
and automation, we must also
implement strategies correctly.
Now let's discuss the, or discuss the
best approach, approach in doing that.
A successful auto commission strategy
requires a structured approach.
So first, conduct a thorough
audit to identify gaps in
existing monitoring framework.
Next, select the right tools tailored
to business needs or pilot deployments.
Allow for it.
Testing before the full-time,
full scale rollout.
Rollout
integration ensures seamless data
exchange across platforms while ongoing
optimizations refined our processes
based on performance insights with
a well, planned strategy in place.
Now, let's, let's wrap up with some.
Key takeaways, to summarize, automation
is, is the revolutionizing ID operations.
it minimizes manual workload,
improves system reliability,
and his operational efficiency.
Advance monitoring tools like Prometheus,
Nagios and Datadog enable our.
Enable predictor maintenance.
While AI will power solutions, take
automation to the next level, the key
is structured, deployment and continuous
refinement to maximize impact of finally,
or before we conclude, I would love.
Like to sh share where you
can find more of my work.
I truly appreci shared
all of your time today.
If you would like to, like to explore
more of my work for the feel free to
scan this QR code, it'll take you to my
portfolio website where I share insights.
Our projects and experiences.
I would also love to connect with you
all and, and continue on this discussion.
thank you again, all for, for joining.
Bye-bye.