Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining me today.
My name is Nas.
I'm thrilled to discuss how AI power
relationship data analysis, transforming
the fight against the financial fraud
and financial fraud is a global crisis
costing market over 3 trillion annually.
This isn't just a number, it's
a threat to economic stability,
investor confidence, and the trust
that underpin our financial system.
Traditional fraud detection matter while.
Often falls short when
it comes to identifying
sophisticated criminal networks.
Why?
Because they miss the hidden relationship
that enabled the complex fraud schema.
Today I'll show you how AI driven
relationship analysis powered by
machine learning and graph based
algorithm is revolutionizing the space.
We'll explore how these technologies.
Enable financial institution to uncover
intricate connections and interview
before significant damage occur.
Let's start by understanding
the scale of the problem.
Fraudulent activities drain
over 3 trillion from the
global economy every year.
To put that into perspective, the more
than the GDP of many countries combine.
This isn't just a problem
for bank or cooperation.
It affect consumers, small
businesses, and the entire economies.
But here are the good news, the AI power
systems, and are making a real difference.
For example, these systems can
reduce false positive by 35%,
and it means less time wasted
investigating legitimate transaction
and more focus on the actual threat.
Even more impressive AI enhanced
fraud detections rates by 60%.
This mean we are now able to identify
sophisticated fraud network and high risk
individual with far greater accuracy.
These aren't just incremental improvement.
They are game changing advancement power
by machine learning model, like random
forest gradient boosting and deep neural
network of traditional detection methods.
Now, let's talk about why the
traditional methods often fail First.
Traditional system focus on
the individual transactions.
In isolations, they look at
one transaction at a time, but
fraudster don't operate that way.
They use multiple accounts, entities,
and time period to hide their activities.
Traditional systems means
these patterns entirely.
Second, these systems rely too heavily
on the historical fraud patterns.
While history is important,
criminals are constantly innovating.
By the time traditional system catch
up, the damage is already done.
Third, traditional system only
work with the structured data.
Things like transition, record
and account is, but fraudster
leaves clues in unstructured data.
Social media, post news article, and
other external sources, traditional
system can't process this information.
Leaving critical
intelligence on the table.
These limitations create gap, that
criminal exploit, and that's where
the AI and machine learning comes in.
This is where the AI
relationship analysis, Heinz,
let me break it down for you.
First, AI deliver an 80% reduction
in false positives compared to
traditional rule-based system that
a massive improvement in efficiency.
Second AI uncovered complex
multi-layer fraud schema by
identifying non-obvious relationship.
For example, it can connect the dot
between seamlessly unrelated accounts
and entities using a graph based
machine learning models like Graph
Sage, graph Conversional network,
and the third AI seamlessly integrate
structure and unstructured data.
It can analyze the transition record.
Alongside social media, post news
article, and more using natural
language processing the techniques
like bird or transformer models.
Finally, AI enabled the
proactive risk identification.
Instead of waiting for fraud to
happen, AI identifies suspicious
pattern and emerging their threat
before financial losses occur.
In short, AI gives us a powerful
tool to stay ahead of fraudster.
To achieve this AI system, integrate
data from multiple sources.
Let's look at some example.
Public record, like government registries,
corporate filing, property records,
real complex ownership hierarchies,
and potential shell companies.
I. These are often used in fraud
schema to hide the true beneficiaries.
Transition histories are
another critical source.
By analyzing financial flow across
the multiple accounts and time
period, AI can expose sophisticated
money movement pattern and coordinate
fraudulent activities using time,
citizen analysis, anomaly detection
algorithm like isolation, forest, and.
Auto encoder.
The social connections are also key.
Digital footprints across social
platform and professional network
can illuminate hidden relationship,
affiliation, and potential conclusions
between signaling unrelated parties
using social network analysis.
We also call SNA.
Finally, the real time news and the
media monitoring provide critical context
for evaluating suspicious behavior
and emerging fraud trend Using NLP
and sentiment analysis by combining
these sources, AI paint a comprehensive
picture of fraud, potential fraud.
At the core of this technology, a
graph based machine learning model,
let me explain how they work.
First, the system ingest and
pre-process multi-source data.
This involve occurring, validating
and standardizing data from
various sources Using EDL
extract, transform load pipeline.
Next it perform entity resolution.
Unifying deduplicating identify using
fuzzy matching algorithm clustering
techniques like DB scan or kmi.
For example, it might recognize that
John Smith or J Smith are the same
person I. Then it mapped the relationship
generating a comprehensive network
graph that despite how entities are
connected, using the graph database
like Neo 4G or Amazon Neptune.
Finally, it applies algorithm
to detect and melos pattern.
For example, it might flag a network
of account that are transferring
money in a statically come in
probably way using community detection
algorithm like, label propagation.
This end-to-end process allow us to
identify fraud with unprecedented.
I could see one of the most
powerful feature of AI relationship
analysis is this ability to
detect hidden relationship.
Let's look at some example.
First, alias detection.
Frauds are often operate
under multiple identities.
AI can identify these aliases
by analyzing linguistic pattern,
behavioral fingerprints, and contextual
relationship using an LP models like
world to work vertical org glowy.
For example, it might notice that
two accounts using similar language
are having overlapping IP addresses.
Second layer ownership.
Fraudster often use nested shell
companies and complex copyright
hierarchy to hide their control.
AI can penetrate the structure to
expose the ultimate beneficial owners
using graph traversal algorithm like
breath first, search depth first search.
Indirect connections.
Fraud often use intermediate
issue to hide the relationship.
AI can uncover these hidden
connections by mapping share assets.
Common associate and other indirect
links using links prediction algorithm.
Finally, a temporal pattern.
AI can detect suspicious timing,
correlation across transaction, using
time series analysis and statistical
model like A-R-I-M-A of profit.
These capabilities make it.
Incredibly difficult for fraud to hide.
Let's look at some real world result.
AI and relationship analysis achieves
95% detection rate compared to
just 40% with traditional system.
That's more than double the effectiveness.
It also reduces false
positive from 60% to just 25%.
This means fewer unnecessary
investigation and more focus on actual
threat in terms of processing time.
AI solution can process suspicious
transition in just 15 hours compared
to 72 hours with conventional methods.
This enabled a faster
responses to potential credit.
And when it comes to complex fraud,
schema AI detect 85% of cases versus
only 30% with tradition system.
This number speaks for themselves.
AI is a game changing in fraud detection.
I. To successfully implement AI
relationship analysis, there are several
best practice to follow for establish
a robust data governance framework.
This means having a comprehensive policies
for secure data acquisition, ethical
usage, second integrated AI system
seamlessly with existing technology.
This might involve deploying the advanced
graph database like Neo 4G Tiger Graph.
The an analytics platform that
communicate flawlessly with
your current infrastructure.
The third deploying phase start
with a high impact business area.
To validate ROI refine the process
before rolling out organization-wide.
Finally, create a dynamic
learning ecosystem.
This means implementing structure feedback
loops with fraud analyst to continuously
enhance model accuracy and adapt the
emerging fraud pattern using reinforcement
learning and online learning techniques.
By following this best practice,
you can maximize the effectiveness
of AI in your organization.
Financial, regulatory Now mandate
transparent AI decision making process.
This means generate.
This means system must generate
comprehensive audit trial and clear
justification when flagging suspicious
relationship pattern using explainable
AI technique like SHAP, sharply
Adaptive Explanation or LIME, local
interpretable model agnostic explanation.
Privacy compliance is also essential.
The data acquisition and
processing must strictly adapt to
G-T-P-R-C-C-P-A and other financial.
A November organization must
implement rigorous concept mechanism
and practice data minimization
throughout analysis workflow.
Continuous testing and third party
validation of AI model is also
essential for regulatory compliance,
regular independent audit insurer.
I will call them fairness,
statistical accuracy, and freedom
from discriminatory outcome.
Finally, across border
consideration are important.
International financial investigation
of complex jurisdiction requirements
organization must establish robust
framework for compliant data sharing
across regulatory boundaries with
varying legal standard, the future
of AI in financial compliance.
Looking ahead, the future of
AI in financial compliancies,
incredibly exciting.
First, we'll see real
time fraud detection.
Instead of investigating fraud after
it happened, system will identify
as it happened using streaming data
processing framework like Apache Kafka.
Apache Flink Prevention will
replace the investigation.
Second, the cross industry collaboration
will become more, more common.
Finance institution will Moore and
patent using federated learning
technique, creating a collective defense
that strengthen all participants.
That quantum computing will take
patent detection to UDE by, by
enabling analysis of vastly large geo
dataset, quantum computing will require
patent that are currently invisible.
Finally, predictive risk
model will anticipate new
fraud type before the emerge.
Use in generative adverse serial
network and simulation based
on approach says this mean.
Adaptation will out face
the criminal innovation.
In short, AI will continue
to revolutionize the fight
against financial fraud.
To wrap up AI power, relationship
data analysis is transforming the
fight against financial fraud.
By uncovering hidden connections,
reducing false positive and enabling
proactive is identification.
It come a powerful solution
to a global problem.
The numbers speak for themself.
AI is more than doubling detection
rates, reducing the positive,
enabling faster response time.
But beyond the number, AI is giving us
a tool to stay ahead of fraud starts
in an increasingly complex world.
Thank you for your time.
I look forward to your questions.
Thank you.