Hi everyone.
Good morning.
This is Achi ma. I'm here to talk
about AI and bi, the Future of
Intelligent Healthcare Analytics.
Today we are discussing about how in
healthcare organizations are evolving
their data analytics by blending
conventional business intelligence
with sophisticated AI capabilities.
We are going from the typical structured
reports and dashboards to platform.
That uses a machine learning, natural
language processing and computer vision.
These conversions in facilitating
tremendous achievements in fraud
detection, predictive modeling
for chronic diseases management,
and automated KPI monitoring.
Let's see how these technologies
combine to build an intelligent
healthcare analytics system.
Laying the ground for more efficient
and responsive healthcare environment.
The shift from.
Conventional BI to analytics with ai.
Traditional BI has been our go-to
for building structured reports for
years, but it relies on preexisting
templates and queries that limits its
ability to detect hidden patterns.
With healthcare information now doubting
every 73 days and 80% of it is an
unstructured data, traditional methods can
no longer handle this AI driven analytics.
Turns this on its head by leveraging
machine learning to detect patterns,
natural language processing, to
extract meaning from vast quantities
of clinical documents and computer
visions, vision to read images.
This is clear.
Move away from static descriptive
reporting to a dynamic system
that provides predictive insights,
enabling us to react quickly to the
constantly evolving data landscape.
Healthcare data growth versus
analytics capabilities.
Look at the rate of change
in our data environment.
Healthcare data is doubling every 73
days, and a staggering 80% of it is
an unstructured data with 1.2 billion
clinical documents generated each year.
The traditional BI systems were built
on a yearly doubling rate of 365 days.
And that aren't completely built
to handle this kind of growth.
Furthermore, AI enhanced analytics have
been shown to have improved performance.
For example, recording over 90%
of sensitivity and specificity
in diabetic retinopathy detection
compared to 70% with traditional
methods, and by 2025, healthcare
data will reach 25,000 petabytes.
A far cry for the 5,000 petabytes that
these legacy systems were built for.
The reality says everything about
why a new AI driven approach isn't
just preferable, but is required
fraud detection or claims processing.
in healthcare, fraud is significant
problem costing the industry
billions of dollars every year.
Three to 10% of total expenditures.
Rule-based fraud detection systems are
frequently outsmarted by complex fraud
schemes, reducing false positive rates
as high as 60% system augmented with
artificial intelligence and business
intelligence features, examining billing
patterns and apply emission learning
techniques to identify statical anomalies.
Such system can achieve 70% to 90%
accuracy rates for fraud detection
while simultaneously lowering
false positives by 30 to 50%.
This flexible approach enables new
fraud patterns to be discounted
without requiring continued
continual reprogramming, thereby
allowing more efficient allocation
of investigate resources and
protection of financial systems.
Predictive modeling for managing chronic
diseases in chronic disease management.
Early identification and
intervention are paramount.
Business intelligence platforms
augmented with AI utilized sophisticated
algorithms such as deep learning
and conventional neural networks
to conduct risk satisfaction.
With predict two sensitivities above 80%.
Not only do these models forecast
treatment outcomes for individual patients
and potential side effects, but they
also forecast hospital readmissions
rates with accuracy ranging from 75
to 85% when such platform include, so
social determinants of health data.
These systems acquire a
deeper understanding of.
Patient risk and predictive
accuracy is increased by 10 to 20%.
This individualized approach
facilitates earlier intervention
and more personalized patient care.
Automated KPI monitoring ability,
manual tracking of KPIs on dozens
of metrics can be overwhelming.
A augmented business intelligence
automates this task by detecting
anomalies in real time and adjusting
sensitivity thresholds based on
historical context and contextual factors,
rather than innu, editing teams with
indistinguishable alerts the system
intellect intelligently prioritize
notifications, reducing low rate.
Alerts by 40 to 60%, thus
minimizing alert feting.
In addition, natural language generation
converts complex numerical information
into brief contextual relevant
narrative explanations, thus reducing
interpretations time by 20 to 30%.
This streamlined method allows.
Teams to focus on most critical problems,
AI impact on healthcare
analytics performance.
Here we contrast legacy systems
with those infused with ai.
The performance graph indicates
definitely advances in a range of areas.
AI not only enhances fraud detection
and decrease false positives, but
also enhance disease forecasting
and readmission prediction.
Minimizing unwanted alerts further
enhances operational effectiveness.
These performance gains
illustrate that combining AI
is greater than a tech upgrade.
It's revolutionary solution that
yields tangible benefits in patient
care and re resource utilization,
implementation challenges,
data quality and integration.
While AI powered analytics offer
significant benefits, they deployment
is not without their challenges.
For instance, even established
electronic health record system
can have up to 65% of patient
records with missing critical data.
In addition, many healthcare organizations
are use responsible for an average of 16
clinical systems and 18 administrative
systems, which often do not communicate
with each other, thus making data
integration more and more challenging.
This is also an urgent need for
standardization of medical terminologies.
Considering that coding variations
for the same clinical concepts
can be as high as 30 to 40%.
Addressing these challenges is
important to ensure the reliability
of our data to allow AI systems
to operate at their best level.
Trust building in healthcare, AI trust
is key to AI adoption in healthcare.
Over 70% of healthcare professionals
have expressed concern regarding
AI algorithm transparency.
To build conference explainable AI methods
are used to show how conclusions are
reached, rigorous validations frameworks.
Testing, sensitivity, specificity,
and calibration thus helps
ensure consistent performance.
Furthermore, thus, project
incorporating continuous clinical
input have adoption rates around three
times greater than those without.
More than 80% of respondents point
to the need of understanding the
limitations of these algorithms.
Emphasizing the importance of
transparency in AI implementation,
healthcare, ai, emerging trends.
Artificial intelligence advance
in healthcare sectors today are
facilitating additional advances.
For instance, ambient intelligence
delivers real-time analytic
support during patient encounters,
while autonomous analytic agents.
Can proactively surface
areas for improvement.
Moreover, multimodal AI models which
combine various types of data have shown
a performance gains of eight to 15% or
modules utilizing a single modality.
Furthermore, federated learning
facilities privacy, preserving analytics
by enabling algorithms to train on
decentralized data without requiring the.
Centralization of sensitive data.
These advances represent the next
generation of innovation and establish
a foundation for a more sophisticated
healthcare analytics ecosystem.
The future of intelligent
healthcare analytics.
Looking ahead, the convergence
of artificial intelligence and
classic business intelligence will
transform healthcare analytics.
In earnest, the multidisciplinary
strategy will improve patient experience
via personalized care and reduce wait
times, advance population health through
smarter predictive modeling, reduce
operational expenses through heightened
efficiencies and fraud detection,
and improve clinical satisfaction
by lessening documentation burdens.
A doesn't supplement our systems,
but arguments them delivering more
insightful insights and perpetrating
the ultimate objective of realization,
the quadruple aim in healthcare.
It is an existing data driven
future with significant
potential for all stakeholders.
In summary, our presentation
today has revealed.
How the combination of AI and
conventional business intelligence
revolutionizes healthcare analytics,
whether enhancing fraud detection or
predictive modeling, or automated KPI
ranking and undercover emerging trends.
These innovations are ushering in an era
of smarter and more efficient healthcare.
This development underpins
a data-driven echo system.
We greater insights translate to enhanced
patient care and operational excellence.
Thank you for your time and attention.
This is.