Speaker 17: Hi, I'm Sulabh Jain,
business application supervisor,
and welcome to the session at CON
forty-two Golang twenty twenty-six.
In the next few slides or so, I'm going
to walk you through a practical roadmap
of transforming a legacy insurance
platform into a cloud-native system
using Go microservices, Kubernetes,
and event-driven architecture.
Let me switch the view to presentation.
All right.
So if you're watching this,
you're probably either working in
insurance technology or you are
a Go engineer who has been handed
a modernization challenge and is
trying to figure out where to start.
Either way, you are in the right place.
All right, let's next slide.
So what is the problem?
Let me start with the problem.
So insurance carriers are being
squeezed from three direction at once.
Customer expectation, where the people has
experienced what a great digital product
feels like, and a twelve-step legacy
portal which with a PDF upload you know.
And then another one, another challenge
that the insurance carrier has is
regulatory pressure, compliance
requirements, and, they kept increasing.
And a platform that takes six
months to deploy a change, and
it cannot keep up with the pace.
And another thing is the competitive
pace, where insurtechs are sh--
are, they are like everywhere now.
They're not smarter than your engineers,
it's just that they c- they don't carry
the same architectural constraint.
The monolith system where, we
will be focusing more on monolith
system, on how to transform into the
cloud-native application using the Go.
So monolith system has predictable failure
model, quarterly release cycle that mean
features are stale before they ship.
You can, scale independently.
So either you have to scale
everything or nothing.
But a single bad deployment also can take,
a good amount of downtime into the system.
So every year over year, when we are
doing the enhancement to the legacy
system, to the monolith system, it
even makes it harder to modernize.
All right, moving to the next slide.
So the cloud-native, what is the answer?
What is the framework?
So cloud-native gets overused
to the point of losing meaning,
so let me precise what I mean.
It's a design philosophy built on four
pillars that builds on each other.
Decompose So decomposing meaning break
the monolith into independently deployable
services, each owning a specific business
capability policy like, for example,
policy management, claims intake, billing,
underwriting, and so on and so forth.
Containerize them.
The-- what it means is package
each service into a Docker so it
runs identically everywhere from a
Docker from a developer's desktop
all the way up to production.
Now, the next thing is orchestrate.
Use-- You can use Kubernetes to
manage the container fleet, scheduling
failure recovery, auto-scaling,
and governance enfor-enforcement.
And then the next one is automate.
Automate the CI/CD pipeline.
Infrastructure as a code makes
every deployment and every
environment repeatable and auditable.
So these are the four pillars of the
legacy modernization to a cloud-native
legacy monolith mi-- modernization to
a cloud-native set of microservices.
Moving to the next slide.
So now we are talking about why why
Go for core insurance system, right?
Three reason where the Go is the right
language for the insurance core system.
Number one, performance at scale, where
Go compiles into a single binary, and
it does not require any JVM or any
interpreter, minimal memory overhead, a
core engine handling tens of thousands
of concurrent requests and returning
pieces in under two hundred milliseconds.
Go is purpose-built for that.
It just runs.
And the simplicity and maintainability.
So where Go has the upper hand is Go
has a deliberately constrained syntax.
There's usually one obvious
way to write something.
For a team maintaining a financial system
across the year of personal changes, that
predictability is a genuine advantage.
The explicit error handling model.
Errors as value use check, not
the exception that you might, it's
just the validation of the values.
In the industry that we are in, where the
error means maybe a wrong pricing on the
policy, maybe, a wrong claim adjudication.
So here, basically,
the discipline matters.
So cloud-native by design what it
means is we will be using Docker,
Kubernetes, Prometheus gRPC.
The entire cloud-native
toolchain is written in Go.
First-class libraries, seamless
integration, no friction between your
application code and your infrastructure
So that combination, it basically it comes
with the compiled performance, readable
simplicity and native cloud tooling.
Next one it is the service decomposition.
So here, how do we break
the monolith system?
So what is the service decomposition?
It is a decision that determines
whether your modernization succeeds
or fails because get it right and
everything downstream is easier.
But when you're wrong, you may end
up building a distributed monolith.
All the complexity of monolith with
none of the independence, right?
So what is the core?
What are the core principle?
Core principle is it should
have the service boundaries.
What it means is its service
boundaries should reflect your business
domain, not your technical layer.
Don't split the front end, back end, and
database services like that because this
is how the typical monolith system works.
Split along the bounded context.
What it means is your policy
may have one bounded context.
Your claims may have another
bounded contex- context.
And similarly billing and
underwriting and so on, right?
Each service, m- that will own its
own data store, it's non-negotiable.
Shared database meaning, shared compiling.
Each services exposes a
various versioned API contract.
So API contract for what it owns,
and then each services can then be
evolved independently at, whenever each
service deployed in schedule, and it
can be independently deployable without
having any dependency on any other
team or any other bounded context.
So what is the best way to find
the route boundaries, right?
Basically, you have to get a team.
Team of engineers, team of business
stakeholders, subject matter expert,
and then together they will meet,
they will form the map of the
domain-driven event like policy bound.
When the policy bound happens, what
are the systems which basically wants
that event or listen to that event?
Another example is a claim intake receipt
or maybe a payment processed, right?
And then all the systems can, all the
boundaries can be loosely coupled, and
they are just listening or basically
publishing or subscribing to an event.
Next slide Yeah.
So now let me go over the
operational layer quickly, right?
So Kubernetes.
Kubernetes be the orchestration
layer which is like infrastructure
as a code and then the CI/CD because
together these three form of delivery
foundation for everything we have built.
What Kubernetes gives us, Kubernetes gives
you the automatic scaling, self-healing,
progressive delivery, and when the
catastrophe event hits, the claim spike
or maybe Horizon Pods Auto Scaler spin up
additional instances automatically, right?
Or even the pod fails, then
it restarts on their own.
Infrastructure as a code, everything
is much version controlled.
Terraform for cloud resources Helm
for Kubernetes application Argo
CD, for example, for GitOps, right?
We have-- we will-- we can also
control the, disaster recovery,
environment dis- drift that disappears.
So all those infrastructure related
concerns or, and the automation can
be handled by having the Kubernetes.
Now, CI/CD pipeline, it ties
everything all together.
Every commit runs functional test,
security scan, SAST, dependency
audit, dynamic testing, and
the performance gate checks.
And that, that will run everything until
it-- everything reaches to the production.
And then we can also handle
the compliance, that will
be backed into the pipeline.
So the next one is the
infrastructure as a code that I,
explained in my earlier slide.
The infrastructure as a code, we
can basically have it, designed for
scalability and for the disaster recovery.
And then similarly we can build a
continuous integration, continuous
deployable CI/CD pipeline to have
the code commit, automated build,
functional testing, security scanning,
and, and progressive deployment.
Now, the next thing comes into
the event-driven architecture.
What is that?
Remember in my earlier slide, I
mentioned that breaking the monolith
system into a bound- bounded context.
What it means is policy may be a
bounded con- context, claims may be
another bounded context, billing may
be another bounded context, or maybe
underwriting, could be one more.
Now, how these system will talk.
So that's where the event-driven
architecture comes into the place.
For example in the event of catastrophe,
like a major hurricane, right?
Claims volume is spiking.
The claims intake service calls
fraud detection synchronously.
It waits for a response
before it can continue.
But fraud detection is
under load, slowing down.
Every claim intake request now waits.
The queue builds.
The mobile app times out.
A cascade failure in fraud
detection becomes a platform-wide
failure for your customers.
This is the fundamental problem
with synchronous coupling.
One service is down, everything is down.
Now, with this event architecture
breaks that coupling.
Instead of calling fraud
detection and waiting, claims
intake publishes a domain event.
What it means is claims intake,
for example, claims intake received
to a durable message stream,
Kafka, EventBridge, Pub/Sub.
The technology is less
important than the pattern.
Fraud scoring, adjuster assignment,
customer notification, each consume that
event independently at their own pace.
And then fraud detection fall, falls
behind, claims intake do not care
because they already published the event.
So events are durable, right?
Nothing is lost.
Each service, whenever they
catch up, they will consume the
event, and there you go, right?
So three ex- three insurance
example I can give.
When the policy is bound, for example,
or billing setup, or document generates.
And, maybe you have to send out
a regulatory notification for
all triggers in parallel, and
no one is blocking the customer.
Similarly, when a claim is received or
fraud is scoring, adjuster assignment or
notification, these runs simultaneously.
And in, in case of when the payments
is processed, we update the ledger, we
update the partner settlement, audit
rights, all happens independently.
So this is the beauty of
event-driven architecture.
So the next thing is the API
first design and observability.
What is, what it means is on the API
first in insurance ecosystem, there
are MGAs, there are, aggregators,
there are insured tech, reinsurers.
They are your, it-- they are as
important as your internal platform.
So basically, what you have to
do, you have to write your APIs,
Before even the implementation
begins, write your contracts, write
your API specification, right?
So basically design the contract first.
Once it is published, breaking your
changes requires a version bump.
So if you make any changes to the API,
then that's a new version for you.
And, because now that you have
the contract with your consumers,
you cannot break that contract.
So any changes, if you're creating any new
endpoints, that's gonna be a new version.
And then centralize
authentication using the gateway.
For example, OAuth 2.0,
mutual TLS, rate limited.
That enforces consistently for every
partner, not re-implemented per service.
The payoff, onboarding cycle
that took months compressed to
days, even week a partner cannot
migrate to a premium, not written.
On the observability side, you
can build a beautiful distributor
system that can be completely bind
to what's happening in production.
You need three things working together.
Logs, that those should be structured
and centralized, and that should be
qu-queryable too, so that if you have
to query the logs, for example, for the
transactions, for any failures, you have
the centralized place to fetch those logs.
Now, the second thing is metrics.
What are the request rate?
What are the error rates?
What are the latency percentiles?
All those things, all those
details, the metrics will provide.
And for that maybe you can use the Grafana
or all other, metrics tool that can be
useful, in order to t-turn those metrics.
Now, what are the challenges
in practical migration?
So I'll talk a little
bit about the challenge.
So as I covered in this slide is,
centralized logging or distributed
trashing, tracing and metrics.
These three layers can be
built to basically improve your
observabilities around the APIs.
Now moving on to the next one.
What are the challenges and the--
how do you mitigate those challenges?
So distributed data consis-consistency
Without a shared database or cross-service
transactions needs a Saga pattern.
What it is it is compensating the
event if the step fails or it's out
of the box pattern, where events are
written automatically with state changes
and published by a separate process.
It avoids the distributed
locks and two-phase commits.
They introduce worse failure
modes than they solve.
Now, the another challenge
is operational complexity.
More services means more moving parts,
so basically, how we can mitigate
it, like we have to invest in the
platform engineering early enough.
So basically, a team that owns Kubernetes
and abstracts its complexity from
product teams service meshes like issues
or Linkerd standardize MTLS retires
and retries and circuit breaking,
breaking at the infrastructure layer.
So the individual teams do
not have to worry about that.
And that is again, the cultural
and organizational change because
honestly this is the hardest one.
Why I say that is because your team
is now used to make changes to that
monolith system and if your teams are
organized by a technical function,
your service will mirror the structure.
So basically, you need to organize your
team around the domains with end-to-end
ownership of, APIs, the database, and
all the, infrastructure around that.
And basically, the go enablement
will be a good practice.
And then the another challenge
is the regulatory continuity.
Leg-legacy system running the legacy
system in parallel during migration.
Use API facade to maintain the
compliance interface while the
implementation changes behind them.
And do not create a window where
you are non-compliant because
because you are mid-migration.
So basically, while you are modernizing
your applications or your legacy
monolith application, you have
to keep the legacy system alive.
You do not want to go live
without, being compliant with
those regulatory continuity.
Now, moving on to the next one.
What could be your modernization roadmap?
So first of-- first thing first is
you have to start with your domain
decomposition W- what I, as I
explained earlier, that the domain com-
decomposition is like your technical
team, your SMEs, your bus- business
stakeholder, they sit together,
they agree on the bounded context.
E-- And this happens before even
you start writing your code.
Number two is automatic delivery chain.
Setting up the, CI/CD pipeline with
security functions, performance
gate, et cetera, is a prerequisite.
Now, the third one is build
resilience with events.
So decouple your bounded
context, and they should be
communicating only through event.
Those teams, decouple those teams,
design the eventual consistency,
and then treat failure mode as a
first-class concern from the start.
Now, the next one is
instrument from day one.
What it means is open telemetry,
centralized logging, distributed traces.
Observability cannot be added
after the fact, so build it in.
The next one is, yes, because it's
a cultural shift for the team,
so invest in people and culture.
Align team ownership to service
boundaries, build Go competency
deliberately treat platform engineering
versus platform engineering as a
product, and it's not a cost center
because eventually it's gonna help
the organization and help the product.
So the technology, using the
Go is proven and, is available.
The tech-- The question is whether your
organization is willing to make that
structural commitment to architecture,
to automation, to culture, and this
is-- this transformation actually
requires because I believe it worth it
and, we have implemented that, and we
have been pretty successful with that.
At the end, thank you so much for
watching and don't forget whether
you are a large carrier or regional
insurer starting your cloud journey
or Go engineer trying to figure out
where to begin, I hope this gave you
the concrete solution to work with.
If you want to go deeper or anything
covered, Saga patterns, Kubernetes,
HPA tuning, OpenTelemetry in the Go,
or the organization side of Conway law
just I can provide more details, but,
these are the few things to talk about.
Thank you so much for
watching, and have a nice day.