Speaker 14: Hello everyone,
and welcome to CON42 Golang.
I am Sonali, creative design
director at LB Networks, and over
the next fifteen minutes or so, I
want to talk about something that
sits right at the intersection of
design and platform engineering.
How we build design systems
that actually hold up inside
high-performance analytics platforms.
If you have ever shipped UI in front
of a Go-powered backend that's slicing
through millions of rows in real
time, you already know the problem.
The backend scales beautifully.
The front end, not always.
Components drift, teams duplicate
work, and what started as a clean
design systems slowly turns into
a five slightly different ones.
So today, I want to walk you through
the architectural foundations I
think every team needs to get right.
Five measurable pillars that together
make a beautiful design system reliable,
accessible, and performant across
distributed teams and diverse interfaces.
So let's get into it.
Let's start with the problem first.
Enterprise analytics platforms have
to serve a lot of people at once.
Multiple teams, multiple surfaces,
multiple product context, all running
at the same time, all expected to
feel like one coherent product.
And without a principal system
underneath, fragmentation compounds,
and it compounds really fast.
There are three patterns
I see almost everywhere.
The first is inconsistency.
Components diverge across teams because
there's no shared source of truth.
So the button on one dashboard doesn't
quite look like the button in another
dashboard, and the chart on page A behaves
very different from the chart on page B.
Second is duplication.
Parallel implementation create
maintenance debt and version drift.
Three teams end up building the
same filter panel three different
ways, and now you're maintaining
three slightly broken version of
each one of them at the same time.
And the third is the governance gaps.
There's no clear process for contribution,
no clear standard for review, no
enforcement around accessibility.
Things get added, but
nothing ever gets retired.
So quality slips over time, and slowly.
So these three problems that
I just described are not very
Complicated or dramatic on day one.
But they do compound as you follow
the same pattern over and over.
And the bigger your platform gets, the
more expensive they actually become.
So how do we solve this in a
way that actually holds up?
I think a reliable design system
for analytics platforms resets
on five measurable interconnected
foundation, which are five pillars.
Component modularity, which is basically
decoupled UI primitives that let teams
build in parallel without colliding.
Token-driven theming, a single
source of truth for every
visual property in the system.
Cross-platform consistency,
coherence across dashboards, embedded
analytics and operational tools.
Versioning discipline, semantic
releases that evolve the system without
breaking everyone who depends on it.
And finally, governance matur-maturity,
sustainable workflows that scale
autonomy and alignment together.
So I want to walk you through
each of these pillars and show
you what makes them actually work.
Pillar one is component modularity,
and this is the core principle.
Decoupled UI primitives are the foundation
of any maintainable design system.
So the idea is very simple.
When components own their own behavior,
their own styling, and their own API
contract, teams can build independently
without stepping on each other.
The way I like to think about it
is layered model with three levels.
At the bottom, you have primitives,
the atoms, buttons, inputs,
the small decoupled UI pieces.
In the middle, you have
composite components.
These are composed elements with behavior.
For example a search input that combines
an icon, a text field, and a clear button.
A card that combines a
header, body, and actions.
And at the top, you have feature modules.
These are feature-level pieces that
orchestrate composite components into
something which is domain-specific.
A dashboard filter panel, for example.
A query result table.
So this layering matters because it
separates low-level primitives from
product-specific feature modules.
You get to reuse without tight coupling.
And when you do this
well- Three things happen.
You reduce duplication because there's
one implementation per pattern.
You improve maintenance because
changes propagate from a single
source, so it's very easy to maintain.
And you enable parallel development
because teams ship independently
against a shared contract.
Pillar two is token-driven theming.
Design tokens are the contractual layer
between design intent and implementation.
They are the single source of truth
for every visual and interaction
property in the system: color, spacing,
typography, motion, all of that.
The power of tokens is that they
let you make consistent updates
across every analytics surface
without ever touching component code.
You change a token, everything
that ref-- re-everything that
referen-references, it updates.
One change, and it propagates everywhere.
This is huge for analytics platform
because we are constantly tuning things,
adjusting density of a new dashboard
layout, updating a chart color palette
for maybe accessibility, rolling out
a new theme for an embedded view.
Without tokens, those changes mean
hunting through component code and looking
through all the code base to figure
out-- to find the right token to update.
But with tokens, they are single
update at the contract layer, and
it just propagates all over the
system, all of your dashboard.
So now the question is: How does that
token architecture actually work?
You want three levels of abstraction.
Level one is global tokens.
These are your raw design values, hex
codes, pixel scales, font weights, things
like hex color hash two five six three EB.
Just pure values, no meaning attached.
Level two is semantic tokens.
These are purpose-mapped aliases
that point at global tokens.
So instead of hash two five six
three EB, you use color primary.
Instead of sixteen pixel, you
use, say, space dash large or LG.
So instead of a ro-raw value radius,
you use radius MD. So semantic tokens
carry intent, and they make the
system describable in plain language.
Level three is component tokens.
These are scoped to a specific
component, things like button
dash PG or input dash border.
They reference semantic tokens,
which references global tokens This
three-level structure is what gives
you flexibility without the chaos.
You can rethink the global palette
without rewriting every single component.
You can override a semantic
token for a specific team
without touching anything else.
And you can tune a single
component's token without
affecting the rest of the system.
Now, that's the contract
working in your favor.
Pillar three is
cross-platform consistency.
Analytics platforms
don't live in one place.
They span multiple surfaces.
You have standalone dashboard, you
have embedded charts inside other
products, you have operational
tooling for internal teams, and
increasingly you have mobile views.
Achieving coherence across all of these
takes deliberate architectural pattern.
Hope is not a strategy here.
So let me walk you through the
three surfaces I'm thinking about.
Standalone dashboards: this is
the full expression of the design
system, complete layout, navigation,
and data visualization components.
The system gets to show up at its fullest.
Embedded analytics: this is lightweight
token-scoped components that
integrate into host applications.
The constraint here is style isolation.
You can't really bleed your styles
into someone else's product, and you
can't let theirs leak into yours.
Operational tools: these are
density-optimized variants
that share the same component
primitives and token contracts.
Same underlying pieces tuned for
information density and speed.
The key insight is that these
aren't separate design systems.
They are the same system
expressed differently.
The shared parameters and tokens
are what hold them together.
So how do you actually achieve
that coherence in practice?
A few architectural patterns
do most of the work.
At the foundation, you
have a shared token layer.
Every surface, every variant, every
platform anchors to this layer.
That's what makes the system
one thing instead of many.
Above that, you have platform adapters.
These translate the shared token
into runtime-appropriate values
without breaking the contract.
So your tokens compile to CSS variables
on the web-web, native values on
iOS, native values on Android, and
design tool variables in Figma.
Then you have component variants.
The same component expressed
differently for different surfaces.
A button in a density-optimized variant
for operational tools, the same button
full size in a dashboard And on top
of that, surface composi-composition.
How those variants come together
into actual product experiences.
There are also a few key design
decisions worth calling out.
First Shadow DOM and style encapsulation.
When you are embedding into third-party
host, you need real style isolation.
Shadow DOM gives you that.
Second responsive token overrides.
Instead of breakpoint logic
scattered across components, use
viewport-specific token values.
The component doesn't change.
Third, explicit extension points
for product-level variations.
You want pre-product customization
without forking the core
without forking the core system.
Design and extension points
are how you allow that safety.
Pillar four is versioning discipline.
A design system without a
principal versioning strategy
is basically a liability.
I want to be very clear about that.
If consumers don't know what's
going to break when they
upgrade, they stop upgrading.
And once they stop upgrading,
your system is dead in the water.
Semantic versioning paired with
controlled release channels is what
lets a system evolve confidently.
You get to keep moving forward without
silently breaking the downstream
applications that depend on you.
So let me get specific about the
strategies that protect consumers.
First, semantic versioning.
It's major for breaking changes, minor
for new features, patch for fixes.
This contract is explicit.
It's machine-readable, and it lets
dependency tooling do its job.
When a team sees a major version jump,
they know to look at the migration notes.
When they see a patch, they
know they can pull it in safely.
Second, controlled release channels.
Stable or beta releases.
This lets teams opt into
changes at their own pace.
Risk-tolerant teams can run on
surface issues early, and conservative
teams can wait for stable version.
Everyone gets to choose
their level of exposure.
And the third is deprecation workflows.
When something has to go away,
you don't just delete it.
You issue a structured deprecation notice.
You provide a migration guide,
and you give a consuming team
a safe time-bound path forward.
Deprecation is a contract too when you do
these three things well, you can evolve
the system very fast without losing the
trust of the team that depends on you.
Next up is governance maturity, and
arguably the one that determines whether
everything else holds up together.
Governance is what separates a
shared component library from
a true platform capability.
Without it, systems stagnant or fragment.
With it, they compound
in quality over time.
So mature governance has four components:
contribution workflow, where clear
pathways for teams to propose new
components, prototype them, and actually
promote them into the shared system.
People need to actually know
how to contribute and what
happens after they actually do.
Next is review standards, defined criteria
covering API design, any compliance, test
coverage, and documentation completeness.
Last sorry, third, accessibility
enforcement, and this is a non-negotiable.
Automated WCAG checks integrated
into CI pipeline, not left to
my manual audits or goodwill.
If you don't enforce accessibility
automatically, it will not
happen consistently ever.
And the last one is decision frameworks,
documented principles that balance team
autonomy with system alignment at scale.
So when there's a disagreement,
you need a written principle to
fall back on, not just opinions.
Together, these four pieces
are what turn a design system
into a really real platform.
All right, let's go a bit deeper into
the governance because I think this is
where most enterprise design systems
either succeed or they quietly fail.
The most effective governance
model I have seen at scale is what
I would call the federate model.
The idea is that you distribute ownership
while maintaining a shared core.
Platform teams own the foundation, product
teams own their extensions, and there are
clear contribution paths between them.
The platform team owns the
primitives, the tokens, the release
infrastructure, the review standards.
They make sure the core stays
coherent and very high quality.
The product teams contribute
patterns, service surface level
components, and domain extensions.
They know their users best, so they are
the ones building the specific solutions.
But they build on top of a shared
foundation, not next to it.
This federate model is what lets
you scale without bottlenecking.
The platform team can't review every
UI decision every product team makes,
but they can own the contract that
all of those decisions sit on top of.
And product teams get to move
fast inside that contract.
That's the balance, the autonomy
where it speeds people up, alignment
where it keeps the system coherent.
All right, so let me leave you with
five things to take back to your team.
First of all, build on
decoupled primitives.
Modularity is what makes parallel
dev- development and long
term maintainability possible.
If your primitives are tangled,
everything above them will be too.
Second tokens are your source of truth.
Visual and interaction properties belong
in tokens, not hard-coded in components.
The contract layer is
where consistency lives.
Third design for all
surfaces from day one.
Cross-platform coherence is an
architectural decision, not a retrofit.
Retrofitting is always more
expensive than planning ahead.
Fourth, version with intent.
Semantic versioning and
release channels protect your
consumers and your credibility.
Without them, no one trusts the
system enough to depend on it.
And the last one is invest in
governance before you need it.
Contribution workflows and
accessibility enforcement are what let
a system scale without fragmenting.
By the time you obviously need
governance, the cost of adding
it has already gone way up high.
Put these five together and you
have got a design system that
can actually keep pace with a
high-performance analytics platform.
One that holds up across teams,
across surfaces, and across time.
That's pretty amazing.
And yeah, that's it from me.
Thank you so much for spending
this time with me today.
I would genuinely love to hear how
you're thinking about this in your own
platforms, what's working, what's not,
and where you're seeing the biggest gaps.
You can find me on LinkedIn,
and here's the email address
on the presentation as well.
Feel free to reach out.
Thanks again, and enjoy the
rest of conf forty-two GoLang.
Thank you.