Hello, my name is Sli, working
as a Senior principal software
engineer at Dell Technologies.
Today we are discussing
about the evaluation of test
orchestration in ERP system.
This presentation will guide you through
the evaluation challenges and future
of test orchestration frameworks that
are ever revolutionizing the quality
assurance in ERP implementations.
As we.
I explored this critical technology.
We will uncover how organizations, can
achieve faster delivery cycles, improve
test coverage, and significant cost
savings while maintaining the highest
quality standards in their ERP systems.
Let us talk some key numbers here.
ERP market is expected to
reach $78 billion by 2029.
And, that is up from $50 billion
in 2024, almost 50% growth and 75%
of ERP projects face implementation
delays with 40% of these release
are due to testing bottlenecks.
So what are the main reason
growing complexity of ERP
systems integration challenges.
And testing requirements.
ERP systems has complexity due to
integrating the functions like finance,
hr, inventory, supply chain operations,
and some in-house applications.
So traditional testing is not sufficient
for growing complex ERP systems.
Traditional testing methods often
fall short for modern ERP deployments,
leading to missed deadlines, reduce
quality and budget overruns stress,
the urgent need for organizations to
transform their testing strategies.
So let us understand
the test orchestration.
So test coordination.
We have to closely work with the
CPLs across all modules, integration
management, and workflow automation.
So I will provide you one good
example in these both topics,
like in suppose in our ERP systems
has the 2230 different modules.
Each module has the multiple test teams.
Every team manages their own.
Style of automation testing framework
and automation testing strategies
and everything is at their own way.
and, they have their own docker to
run execute, or the grid to run the,
their automation scripts orchestration
team has to work with the business
transformation team and CPL teams.
Get the all the end to end scenario
requirements, and then we have to
orchestrate their automation test scripts.
each module test automation
scripts, we have to orchestrate it.
So based on that, the requirements
provided by the CPLs and Business
Transformation team, It'll be, and we
will maintain our own centralized test
database and the every module will be
connected with the centralized database.
And after the execution of the data
automation test script, automatically
critically puts the results into
the our centralized database.
So suppose first module will be execution.
He's completed and goes to the second.
Module and the execution starts
based on the first execution
result because both are connected
to the our centralized database.
So that is how it'll be seamlessly.
It'll be connected to the one
module, to another module.
That is how this test start castration.
So how it'll work a little bit more.
We will discuss in the
orchestration architecture place.
So here we have the, like a orchestration
engine that is a command central.
Like you can centralize your command, you
can think like that orchestration engine.
So here, this orchestration engine
will have the control, all the
GitLab pipelines and the, it'll be
triggered the each pipeline and.
And it'll be connected automatically
with the centralized database
and put the date, statuses of
the each work workflow results.
and it'll be integrated
with the integration layer.
What is the integration layer?
It has the, all the GI guitar
pipelines, information, and
the tested data information.
Each and every data will be
stored into the integration layer.
So what is the test execution framework?
So each module maintains their own test
execution so that, we don't need to worry
about the, what are the individual team
maintains the what type of framework, so
it'll be fine, whatever the framework.
They maintenance so they
maintain their bone tested data.
Everything will be, that is.
and the environment management.
So here the, in the orchestration layer
when you implement the environment
management as well, because in the
traditional ERP applications, we will
see the environment management by the.
Separate team and it has the lot
of, challenges also at the same time
because when they are copying that
data from the production to sit our
sitar, the dev environments, we'll miss
a lot of data and validation missing.
So there are so many
challenges we will face it.
and the, what are the re what are the
conditions required for the, our envi
environment, like a, validation rules?
Those are all the things
we are going to miss it.
So if it's a part of the orchestration
layer, we don't miss that part.
And the reporting analytics,
we are maintaining our own
decentralized database, so it'll
be good for the generating the
reports on our every requirement.
so orchestration, that's how it
be, the orchestration architecture.
So let us discuss about the, some
performance metrics and benefits.
So environment set up time reduced
by the 85 by percent because we are
maintaining the, everything is the
automated way, so that is the reason
it'll be reduced, will be hugely.
And the test execution time will
be reduced by the 70% of time.
Because the way of maintaining the
test execution will be there from the
beginning to end, and it'll be you, I
know it'll be, the implementation is
a little tough, but at the same time,
once the implementation is done, it'll
be, the continuous usage is there.
Very huge here.
And the business benefits faster.
EERP implementation cycles better
release quality, fewer defect, making
it to production and substantial
savings through optimized resource use.
So artificial intelligence
in the test orchestration.
So where we can utilize the
artificial intelligence many places.
But here I will cover the four important
places intelligent test planning.
So yay identifies the critical
test parts based on the user
stories and the regression defects.
If you integrated with the your
own model with Uber, JIRA, or Uber
test management tool, and it'll.
Based on the fine tuning of the ever
model, it'll be created for you.
Very intelligent test planning.
and the second part is the
automated test generation.
So you have your code repository
and, the, All the methods and the
utilities, every will, everything will
be there all already in a base, right?
So you can create your own model and
it'll be generated the automatically
based on the requirements.
So end-to-end profile requirements or the
internal requirements, model requirements
based on that one, it'll be generated
the automatically test generation.
So the third part is the
predictive analysis based on
the new code introduction.
In the GitLab code report, it'll
forecast the failure pins and
generate the new automation scripts,
self-healing, the execution.
So what is the self-healing execution?
If any scripts fails based on the
error, it'll fix the automation script
automatically and generate the automation
test script so that almost 40% of the
manual intervention will be reduced.
so we can implement our own machine
learning models in these four steps
and reduce the manual dependencies.
Let us talk about the cloud
native orchestration solutions.
the major is the scalability,
cloud-based orchestration, to handle
over 1 million test requests per
second and intelligently allocates the
resources based on the requirements.
So availability.
Enterprise grade 99 point 99%.
Availability offered by advanced
distributed cloud architecture so that
across global teams can execute test
scripts without any interruptions.
Cost efficiency, flexible pay as you go.
Models that achieve 32 40%
cost savings compared to
traditional on-premise solutions.
Business impact of test
orchestration, accelerated.
Time to market, 75% faster delivery.
Sorry.
So business impact of test
orchestration, so accelerated time
to market, 74% faster delivery of new
features and updates to end users.
Enhanced quality, 65% of the reduction in
production defects leading to better user
experience and streamlined operations.
Improved change management.
90% of improvement in change management
efficiency, cost optimization.
Substantial annual savings
through optimized resource use and
improved financial performance.
So implementation, best practices,
always the We do, whenever we start
the new projects, we will do small
POCs and the vendor success will come.
Then we will go further
bigger, the same way.
I mean start small and scale fast.
Targeted pilot launch, begin with
your focused pilot and a critical
ERP model before expanding.
This methodical approach helps build
the team's expertise in orchestration
techniques while delivering.
Immediate measurable value rapid scaling.
Successful organizations typically
evolve from pilot to enterprise
wide implementation three to within
three to six months, ensuring a
smooth and efficient transition.
And what are the standardized test sets?
Test sets establish unified testing
frameworks, precise naming conventions,
and comprehensive documentation standards.
Across all ERP components are
the modules, and, standardization
enhances asset reusability by up
to 60% streamlines maintenance
workflows, and it dramatically reduces
onboarding time for new team members.
and the continuous optimization,
structured review cycles like a institute
structured, review cycles to evaluate
orchestration performance metrics
and uncover efficiency opportunities.
Resource allocation, like a high
performer, organizations like
allocate 10 to 15% of testing
resources to optimize initiatives.
Generating three to five XRYA through
reduce execution times and improve.
So how to implement, technical design
considerations further, orchestration
layer, like a EA first architecture,
engineer your orchestration platform
with comprehensive APAs that facilitate
frictionless integration with your ERP.
Ecosystem implement, well-documented,
restful a PS with robust authentication
protocols and consistent response
structures to ensure adaptability as
testing requirements evolve and expand
the another main technical problem.
We will face it when we are developing
any product security integration, so
embed systematic security validation
within our orchestration framework.
Including automated, vulnerable
vulnerability detection
and regulatory complaints.
Verification.
Emphasize the need for continuous security
assessment through the entire development,
and testing pipeline to safeguard critical
business assets in ERP environments.
The another one challenge is that test
data management deploy sophisticated
data provisioning mechanisms that
dynamically generate and maintain and
refresh contextually appropriate data
sets for diverse testing scenarios.
I live the importance of strategic data
management for accurately simulating the
complex transactional workflows that.
Characterize modern ERP systems.
So let us go to the features
of ERP test orchestration.
So in from 2024 to 2025, so the
mainstream adoption of sophisticated
air power test, auto optimization, and
dynamic test generation capabilities.
Advanced machine learning algorithms
will analyze test results in real
time, continuously refining the
test coverage and precision without
requiring manual interventions.
So from the 2025 to 2027, I'm expecting
the predictive pa, like what is that?
predictive PA transformation.
From reactive to predictive
quality assurance methodologies,
intelligent orchestration systems
will anticipate potential defects
before code implementation so that
even the scope declared, when the
scope is defined, only you can.
Based on that one, only you can
define the Uber, test automation
scripts, everything, so that it'll
be 50% will be reduced by that time.
So from the 2027 to 2029,
autonomous testing, what is
the meaning of autonomous?
The evaluation toward fully autonomous
testing, ecosystem capable of self
configuration, self-op optimization,
and self-healing operations.
How human Q professionals will evolve into
strategic quality consultants focusing
primarily on business value alignment
rather than manual test execution.
This is end of my presentation.
If you would like to, have a discussion,
our working session on this topic,
I would like to have a conversation.
Please reach out to me.
I would like to extend my heartfelt thanks
to the Con two organization for putting
together such a fantastic event, a special
thank you to our sponsors for their
generous support and to all the attendees
for being here and the contributing
to the success of this conference.
Thank you all.