Speaker 5: Hi, all.
Myself, George Job.
I currently working as
Principal TPM in Walmart.
I got overall twenty plus years of
experience, with the last ten years of
experience in managing enterprise-level
portfolios, specialized in PMO
transformations and process improvement.
The topic that I'd like to share today
is about digital PMOs in retail with
Jira and Confluence that could help in
building governance through transparency.
So before we deep dive into this
current topic, let's identify
what are the key challenges that
we face in the traditional PMOs.
First to start is the fragmented
status recording, because typically
in a traditional PMO framework, we
use status based on the spreadsheets
and disconnected tools, but there
is no single source of truth, which
results in a late dependency discovery.
The cross-team dependencies are identified
late in the course, which makes it
difficult to mitigate them without
impacting the timeline or the cost.
Inconsistent governance, because the
controls vary by team to team, because
there is no single source of truth or
there is no standardized process across.
So what these gaps
actually cost us, right?
So it does lower the decisions because
leadership have to take reactive decisions
because they lack the real-time data
rather than proactive portfolio decision,
which could have been much faster.
Reduces the transparency
because the stakeholders are
operating on stale reports.
That also results in eroding
the trust in program management.
And it also, from a program manager
perspective, there is an operational
drag because as a TPM, they need to
focus on assembling the status in an
ad hoc manner, where they should be
focusing more on the managing risk and
driving outcomes which are more fruitful.
Now let's deep dive into the
framework, which is the current topic
for today, which is the digital PMO
framework, which basically integrates
Jira and Confluence into a unified
governance and execution environment.
So this is primarily designed considering
the scaling and complexity of portfolios
like retail tech, where it can help
in creating a single system of record
from strategy through delivery.
So this is a visualization of how
this framework looks overall, right?
It's a one system of record end to end.
If you see the strategic layer, which
involves themes, initiatives, and OKRs,
which are anchored to the execution
based on the business outcomes.
It has got a delivery layer, which is
primarily the epics and the de-telemetry,
which provides real-time progress and
health signals Governance layer is more
of risk signals that can help in executive
reporting and then surface the risk
to the leadership on a timely manner.
So now let's explore like how
are we actually distributing this
framework between Jira and Confluence.
So Jira consider it is more of an
execution intelligence where we can
define the structured workflows.
We can define those custom fields,
standardize it so that it has a common
understanding between the teams, using
which we can create dashboards that
can be updated on a real-time basis,
which can help in building portfolio
visibility without manual integration.
And Confluence, it's more treated
as more of a l-living documentation,
and this documentation will be done
based on some of these Jira updates.
As you are aware, like Jira
and Confluence comes from the
same product, means Atlassian.
So it's tightly coupled, so there are
inbuilt functionalities and capabilities
that we can leverage, which could help
in creating standardized templates or
decision records and create structures
which are persistent and searchable.
So the key things that we need
to think when you actually define
those structured workflows,
define an intake gating process.
Because any inputs, meaning any
requirements that we are going to
consider as part of the planning
execution, it should be gated so there
is a single source of truth, and we
know what is coming inside so that
we can avoid the scope creep before
it enters to the portfolio scope.
Define the status conventions.
Have common guideline defined
across the team so that we
can scale it at the org level.
Define the exit criteria, like what's our
exit criteria in terms of the quality.
On what basis we do
mention a project is done.
So we should define what is the
definition of done and basically
the quality criteria it is.
So as you see, it's a seamless,
continuous execution approach.
It starts from the intake, it extends into
the planning execution until the launch.
So throughout this, we use Jira where
we create these epics and capabilities.
We track it.
We get this updated over through
Confluence and this track.
Moving on.
So as we mentioned, this framework
that we're discussing, it helps in
creating an integrated documentation.
So this will help in reducing the
documentation overhead, how we are
making the decision and risk logs so that
we can create an auditable governance
trail And we can also leverage the space
hierarchy that provides by the confluence
mapping to the portfolio structure
which each of you have in your own org.
So the key things: standardize the
template, aud-- create auditable
decision logs, and map your space
hierarchy to your portfolio structure.
Define the templates that can be
scale-scaled across teams so that each
team doesn't have to reinvent whenever
they come up with similar projects
or key enterprise-level projects.
So define the program charter templates
constraining the various owners,
OKR alignment, RACI in a consistent
reviewable format, which is-- can
be standardized across the org.
Create templates for
risk and decision logs.
And similarly, create executive
status pages which will be primarily
based on the Jira updates so that
it can be on real-time, so we need
not spend time on creating manual
reports and ad hoc status assembling.
As we mentioned earlier have space
hierarchy aligned to the portfolio
structure so that the navigation
becomes much easier when you go
through the various documentations.
This also helps in building the
portfolio visibility, right?
So when you create delivery telemetry
using live dashboards, the leadership
is having the right informations
on a real-time manner so that they
can proactively take decisions.
And we can also create automations
around the risk signals.
The reason being now
there is a single record.
It's also real-time data.
So we can define thresholds in terms
of how many progress are at risk,
how many pro-projects are at blocked.
Does a specific projects take
more time in the discovery?
So these various things we can
actually define the thresholds
and can create automated signals
in terms of the risk call-outs.
And also it helps in mapping those
OKR alignment as part of the themes
that we define as part of the business
requirement and the strategic leaderships.
What is the OKR that they're aligned?
All this can be tracked through
this integrated approach.
So from a leadership perspective, as
we discussed in the previous slides,
it helps in getting the progress
tracking, which is aligned to the OKRs.
So one The key thing, it always keeps that
execution is aligned to the strategies
and the OKRs at the leadership level.
This helps in visualizing the
dependency heat maps because we can
call out the cross-team dependencies
as part of this Jira components.
We define what are the impacted teams.
We can identify what is the progress
on each of these teams as we track
it through this epics and stories.
And this, we can also create JQLs
based on the Jiras so that we can be
automated and put it in Confluence
based on this JQL that we create.
So what are the key outcomes?
What this framework really delivers?
So it definitely helps in
reducing the PMO effort because
operational overhead can be reduced.
And as part of one of the project,
one of the portfolio, which is like
automotive care center, it's a key
portfolio within the e-com space,
where we adopted this framework.
We piloted it initially for six months,
and then we continued for an year.
And the numbers really talks
about the benefits, right?
So in the last-- in the initial six
months of framework adoption, we
could reduce the percentage of manual
ad hoc effort to thirty percentage.
And by the end of twelfth month,
from an headcount-wise, we started
this framework adoption with eight
TPMs in that particular portfolio.
And when we completed this framework
adoption in that particular
portfolio, in an year, we could
reduce it from eight to three.
It doesn't... The key call-out is not
really about reducing the headcount,
it is more of we could channelize
those PMO effort into more strategic
and tactical efforts rather than
working on manual ad hoc mundane task.
With the same, even though there was a
reduction in the TPMs headcount, we could
still maintain the same velocity in terms
of the number of initiatives we deliver,
the number of cross-team dependencies.
Because in this particular portfolio that
I just called out, we typically deliver
thirty-plus initiatives, and many of those
initiatives involve more than twenty,
twenty-five plus teams in each initiative.
So we could still maintain the same
velocity rate even after this reduction
in the overall headcount, and we are
still able to maintain the same quality.
So key takeaways.
What are the tools that you use?
We discussed here it's more of Jira and
Confluence, but what are the tools that
you are using in your organization?
Try to unify so that we can leverage
the their capabilities to create
a single source of record and
standardize before you try to scale.
So whatever the process you
define, standardize the template,
standardize the process, define
the ways of working so that you can
actually scale it at even though it
is complex and various or global.
And make this governance continuous
because having this real-time telemetry
helps in making these decisions,
informed decisions in a much faster
pace and builds the trust and confidence
within this PMO group as well.
So make that governance continuous.
So to summarize, unify your tooling,
standardize before you scale,
and make governance continuous.
Thank you