Hi, my name is Kar Kda.
I have overall 18 years of IT experience
specializing in, data warehousing
and, data engineering background.
Today I'm very excited to talk
about AI powered ETL, in the Golan
2025 conference without much delay.
Let's dig deep into that.
AI powered ETL transforming
data with smarter pipelines.
The traditional extract transform.
And Load Paradigm is undergoing a
revolutionary transformation through
artificial intelligence integration.
AI technologies are fundamentally
re-imagining each phase of ETL
Lifecycle, creating adaptive
and intelligent data pipelines
capable of autonomous operations.
Modern AI enhanced ETL systems transcend
conventional rule-based approaches by
implementing self-healing mechanisms
that anticipate and resolve failures
adaptive to transformation engines
that learn from historical patterns
and intelligent loading strategies that
optimize data placement based on usage
patterns and business requirements.
The data explosion challenge
India leads AI adoption.
Around 59% of Indian enterprises actively
deploy AI in their business operations
considerably higher than 42% of the
global average exponential data growth.
India's data creation will grow at
A-C-H-E-R of 29.7, percentage from 22 from
estimated three pointes by.
Operational inefficiencies.
Indian enterprises spend close to 43.8
percentage of total data analysis time
solely on data preparation activities
with 72.3 percentage of data engineers
dedicating more than half of their working
hours to troubleshooting traditional ET l
systems originally designed when gigabyte
scale data warehouses were considered.
Substantial fundamentally cannot
scale to accommodate this explosive
growth without significant AI
enhancement and re-imagination,
some quantifiable benefits.
A 76.4 percentage of processing
efficiency, 83.7, percentage of error
reduction, 2.34 millions of annual savings
for each enterprise through minimized
error handling and optimized operations.
And 87.3 percentage of prediction
accuracy, a comprehensive of 2024
study published in the prestigious
journal Decision support Systems
meticulously analyzed 2 87 enterprise
data integration implementations
across diverse industry sectors.
This landmark research provides
compelling evidence of the transformative
economic and operational advantages
delivered by AI powered ETL
solutions in enterprise environments.
The technical architecture of AI
enhanced ETL, there are four main phases.
Data ion layer is the very first phase.
It processes 17 different data formats
simultaneously, including complex
semi-structured formats like nested JSON
and industry specific EDI variance, phase
number two, machine learning subsystem.
Transformer based models achieve
90, 94 0.7 accuracy in predicting
optimal transformational path for
previously unseen data structures.
step number three, metadata
repository organizations maintaining
comprehensive metadata experienced
217 percentage higher overall pipeline
reliability to those limited metadata.
Four.
Self-healing mechanisms reduced
average downtime of 6.4 hours per ETL
in traditional systems to just 23.7
minutes in AI enhanced pipelines.
Some of the implementation
challenges and solutions, the
first one being the technical debt.
The average large organization maintains
7,842 unique transformational scripts
with 43.2 percentage containing hardcoded
business logic that has not been
reviewed in over 18 months, creating
significant migration complexity.
Number two, we have skill gaps.
67.8 percentage of organizations
site insufficient a ML expertise as
a significant barrier to adoption,
despite India's reputation as
a global technology talent hub.
Number three, data governance.
91.7 percentage of organizations
report increased regulatory scrutiny
or automated data processes with
regulatory complaints, costs increasing
by an average of 27.3 percentage in the
first year following AI implementation.
Successful implementations typically
follow methodical approaches informed by.
Empirical research focusing on metadata
enrichment, targeted use cases and
hybrid approaches that maintain
critical manual processes while
gradually expanding AI capabilities,
smarter extraction with ai, intelligent
source detection organizations,
leveraging machine learning for source
discovery catalog, and integrated
new data sources 7.3 times faster
than those using traditional methods.
With 81 percentage of surveyed enterprises
reporting capability to onboard new
structured data sources in less than
three business days, adaptive scheduling,
AI driven workload balancing, reduced
soul system performance impact by
46.3 percentage, while simultaneously
increasing extraction throughput
by 32.8 percentage with dynamic
workload adaption resulting in a 51.7
percentage reduction in computing costs.
Format recognition.
Modern deep learning approaches can
identify and pass previously unseen
data formats with 93.7 accuracy
after being trade on just 2225.
A representative examples,
transformation with machine learning.
We have three categories here.
The first one being pattern recognition.
Machine learning identifies and automates
82.3 percentage of transformations
that follow recurring patterns through
unsupervised learning techniques.
Anomaly detection, AI powered anomaly
detection has reduced data quality
issues in production environments
by 76.8 percentage dramatically
improving downstream reliability.
Number three, predictive cleansing.
Advanced in simple models.
Combining multiple ML approaches
automatically resolved 86.7%
of data quality issues that
previously required manual.
Traditional E transformation phases
rely on rigid rule-based logic
requiring constant maintenance
as business needs evolve.
Machine learning fundamentally
reimagines this approach, creating
intelligent adaptive transformations
that not only respond to changing data
characteristics, but also anticipate
and address potential issues before
they impact business operations.
Intelligent loading.
we have three phases here.
The first one being
optimal target selection.
It gives 5.3 times
better query performance.
The second one being dynamic partitioning.
it gives 67.8 improvement,
in query performance.
And the third one being realtime
optimization, where, it gives
around 81.4 percentage reduction
in loading related insurance.
The loading phase has evolved
from basic data movement into a
sophisticated decision making ecosystem
that strategically determines how,
when and where data is persisted.
Modern AI algorithms have
revolutionized these traditionally
straightforward processes, enabling
systems to make complex context aware
decisions that dramatically enhance
downstream analytical capabilities.
Organizations implementing AI and he
loading capabilities have experienced
remarkable results around 62.4 percentage
boost in query performance against loaded
data at a 47.8 percentage reduction in
storage costs through intelligent data
placement and organization strategies.
These translate directly
to faster insights and
significant operational savings.
AI powered self-healing pipelines.
it has three main, steps.
The first one being predictive monitoring,
where the neural network models strain on
telemetry data correctly predicted 91.3
percentage of data integration failures
before they impacted downstream systems.
Number two, being the
automatic correct two actions.
76.4 percentage of integration
failures followed recognizable patterns
that could be addressed through
predefined remediation strategies.
Number three, being continuous learning.
Self-healing systems showed a 42.3
percentage higher autonomous resolution
rate using reinforcement learning compared
to simpler machine learning approaches,
perhaps the most revolutionary.
Aspect of AI and he ETL is the
development of self-healing pipelines.
Traditional ETL workflows often fail
when encountering unexpected data
formats or system issues requiring
manual intervention, organizations
implementing AI powered pipeline
resilience capabilities experienced,
79.3 percentage reduction in insurance
tickets requiring human resolution,
implementation considerations.
Skills development, metadata,
foundation, high value use cases,
feedback mechanisms, balanced automation
organizations looking to implement AI
Enhanced ETL should consider several
critical factors to maximize success,
probability, and business values,
starting with high value use cases.
Builds momentum through demonstrable
business impact building.
A robust metadata foundation provides
the essential context for AI systems
to make intelligent decisions.
Implementing feedback mechanisms
enables continuous improvement.
Without explicit reprogramming balancing
automation with human oversight,
ensure appropriate governance and.
Investing in skills development
creates the organizational
capability required to leverage those
powerful technologies effectively.
future discussions in AI powered
ETL, reinforcement Learning for
Optimization by 2027, approximately 67
percentage of enterprise integration
environments will incorporate.
Reinforcement learning capabilities for
continuous optimization, representing a
8.3 fold increase from current adoption
rates, natural language interfaces.
By 2028, approximately 62 percentage
of enterprises will offer natural
language capabilities for basic
integration tasks, expanding the
population of integration creators by
7.3 times autonomous data ecosystems.
By 2030, approximately 47 percentage of
enterprises will implement substantial
ecosystem autonomy for non-critical
data domains, potentially reducing total
cost of ownership by over 70 percentage.
The integration of AI into EDL
processes continues to evolve
rapidly with several emerging trends.
Transform how organizations manage
their data integration workflows.
These develop a future where data
integration becomes substantially
more efficient, more reliable,
and more accessible to a broader
population of business users.
that's all for me and thank you so
much for giving me an opportunity
to talk about AI powered.
ETL, smarter Pipelines in GoLine 25.