Hi,  this is Ika.
I'm myself, a season profession with,  14
years of experience in analysis, design,
configuration development,  and deployment
of ERP business applications,  which is
mainly focused in revenue management, a
subscription order management, conversion
charging and conversion invoicing.
I have been working,  in different areas.
And different industries,  such as
banking, utilities, manufacturing,
finance, and insurance areas.
And currently I'm working as a,  technical
program manager role with,  and I'm
super excited,  to share my overall
experience and how,  and,  and how
securing revenue managed systems,  in
an enterprise,  how much important
it is and how it's gonna impact.
Different industries.
Revenue member systems have become the
backbone of modern enterprise operations.
And in this presentation,  how enterprise
can navigate,  daling security landscapes
through AI Cloud and a robust,  incident
framework response frameworks.
I'm able,  I will be able
to,  give some,  high level.
High level,  points.
How an our nation can
address all these things.
If you consider the RMS,  secret
threat landscape,  there is a
42.2% surge in targeted breaches.
And, there are a lot of sophist
sophisticated algorithm, exportations
three points, eight, 6 million per
breach impact in every organization.
When there is a breach with the security
threats, there are some advanced
encryption standards and awareness
in every,  location they're using.
And,  AI is one of the main power security
enhancement where you can, analyze,  an
organization security based on the threat
detection, complaints, management, and
how you can,  optimize your revenue
and how can it help you,  update in the
market analysis, advance AI and machine
learning technologies for,  revenue and
system security simultaneously driving
sustainable business performance gains.
There's one more framework called
multi-layered security framework.
There are four parts in this
framework,  like continuous monitoring,
access controls, data production,
and infrastructure security.
These four areas are very much important
for an organization to,  secure
their data, multi-layer, and at the
same time,  continuously monitoring
if there are any breaches or.
If there is a vulnerability is
happening in the organization.
And,  there's one more area which I want
to cover is cloud nato, RM Security.
In this area, if you see,  automated
disaster record, which is a very
crucial nowadays because everything
is stored in cloud, if there, there's
a, if there's any disaster, how we can
automatically recover that, recover the
data and the scalable security controls.
This is one area where an automation can
impact with automated security governance.
Insur ensuring protection
throughout the automation growth.
One more area they can work,
they can concentrate, is on
secure cloud infrastructure.
Secure cloud infrastructure.
Leading cloud providers develop.
Deliver enterprise grade security
capabilities that consist
outperform in our solutions
across all protection metrics.
And one more area I want to,  cover in
this video is dynamic pricing protection.
How an automation can dynamic, do a
dynamic pricing protection, like using
an auth,  using authentication like
multi, multi factor grade authentication
protocols, algorithm integrity.
Where we're sending
controlling anomaly detection.
And one more area I want to cover
is incident response framework,
which is very crucial for nowadays.
There are a lot of breaches happening
across all the organizations.
So how to detect it, how an
incident response framework can
we build in an organization?
Like how you can detect it, what
is the response time, automated
response time, how we can recover
it, like using the backups and.
How you can restore it and documentation,
which is very crucial,  in regards to
the complaints and in future, how to
prevent it from future,  incidents.
So overall, if you see, and one
more important area I want to
cover is a compliance management.
Every country has their
own complaints thing.
If you take uk, US Middle East,
Asia, Europe, everyone have their
own compliance thing like P-C-I-D-S.
S-G-D-P-R, Sox.
It is,  it's one of the major area
where an organization should link
into it because now it is, everything
is global and it is very much
important in,  revenue management
areas, how you can be regulatory,
covering all the complaints forever.
How you are preparing your audit,
preparing for your audit, how the data
is, data privacy is,  maintained in an
organization and satisfaction management.
These are very crucial because,
every organization have their
third party vendors and,  lot of
internal audit and external audit.
So these,  these are very much
important for doing,  day-to-day
business across the globe.
The key takeaways,  and the action
items from I want to discuss,  in
this video is how you can implement
multi-layered security, how you can
leverage AI for detection and automation,
establish robot incident response time
transition to secure cloud architects.
So overall,  these are the four
areas where I covered in this video.
And,  thank you so much for giving
me this opportunity and,  looking
forward for the confidence.
Thank you.