Good everyone.
This is Sui.
It's a pleasure to be here today to
talk about AI Power Cloud security
for Comm 42 and how Golang based
solutions are transforming security
for Microsoft Azure Cloud platform.
What is Golan?
Colan is an open source programming
language developed by Google in 2 0 9.
It is designed to be fast, efficient,
and scalable, making it ideal
for cloud computing, networking,
and realtime applications.
Some of the key features of Golang
Fast performance, it compiles directly
to machine code, making it faster
the interpreted language like Python,
optimized for low latency applications.
Example, realtime security merchant
and support uses geo routings to
handle multiple tasks simultaneously.
Perfect for throughout
applications like AI powered threat
detection, and it has a memory.
Efficience includes automatic garbage
collection for optimized memory use,
helps to process large amounts of
security data without performance issues.
The cloud security challenge.
As business continue to adopt
cloud computing, security remains
one of the biggest challenge.
The expanding attack surface means,
traditional security to struggle to
keep up with the real-time threats.
Attackers are getting more sophisticated
and the operational cost of
security incidents is skyrocketing.
This is why we need intelligent adapt
to security frameworks such as AI driven
solutions to respond instantaneously
and in mitigate risk efficiently.
Data driven security improvements.
AI powered security isn't just concept,
it's delivering real results, like
64% increase in the threat detection
accuracy, 57% reduction in response
time, 43% lower operational cost.
And 18.5 million security when sponsors
by leveraging AI security teams can detect
threats faster, respond proactivity, and
reduce manual workload while cutting the
cost advanced persistent threat, which
is called a PT detection, signature
based detection method phase to identify
advanced persistent threats because they
evolve beyond known attack patterns.
Traditional security solution rely
on static rules, which struggle to
keep up with sophisticated attacks.
Our Golan AI solution, however,
uses machine learning to identify
APTs with 96.42% accuracy.
It continuously adopts to emerging threats
and using behavioral analysis to detect
suspicious patterns in milliseconds,
allowing instant containment.
No attack pattern detection.
Security threats are always evolving.
Our AI driven security solution
continuously learns and adapt to
detect new attack vectors through
24 bar zone monitoring across
all Azure resources, pattern
recognition that detects anomalies.
Automated response that deploys
countermeasures in milliseconds
self-learning algorithm that
improve at every security event.
This is real time adaptability.
Ensure that even never before
seen threats are detected and
neutralized interest initially.
Performance at scale Secure solution
must be fast, scalable, and efficient.
Our goal and based security framework
process 12,000 security requests
per second real time parallel threat
analysis using Golan concurrency
model distributed architecture
across multiple Azure regions.
For zero downtime production, this
ensures lightning fast threat detection
without impacting system performance.
You are under heavy workloads.
Implementation architecture.
Here is how we process
security data in real time.
First one is data collection.
We ingest Azure logs telemetry
and user active data.
Second, we pre-process, we
enriched the data using threat
intelligence and parallel processing.
In Golan third process machine learning
analysis, we apply AI models like
generative models with 90%, 96% accuracy
to detect analysis and declassify threat
For process response orchestration,
we automate third containment within
milliseconds, ensuring minimal disruption.
Quantum security feature security threats
are evolving and quantum computing will
bring both challenges and opportunities.
Our next generation AI security
solutions are integrating like
quantum enhanced pattern recognition.
Which improves attack
detection by 47 percentage.
Second is predictive threat analytics.
Forecasting attacks with 63% more
accuracy and quantum resistance
cryptography, ensuring encryption remains
secure against future quantum attacks.
By adopting quantum driven AI
security, we are preparing for
the next era of cybersecurity.
Implementation roadmap to help
organization adopt AI powered security.
We follow a structured roadmap assessment,
identifying security gaps and ities.
Second pilot deployment, implementing
AI security for critical workloads.
Third, full integration, expanding
protection to all Azure resources.
Fourth, continuous optimization,
fine tuning security models
with live threat intelligence.
Key takeaways To summarize AI powered
Golan security solutions software.
Unmatched performance
processing, 18.5 million.
Security actions daily.
A dwell protection, which is 96.42%
a PT detection accuracy, and 63%
improvement in novel threat detection.
Third, significant cost savings,
43% lower operational expenses with
89% of users reporting improved
confidence in cloud security.
Final thoughts.
The future of cloud security lies in AI
driven, adaptive and scalable solution.
By integrating Golang based AI models
into Microsoft Azure Cloud platform
like security framework, we are
not just detecting with threats.
We are also satisfying ahead of.
Time to protect the
resources and the data.
Thank you.
I look forward to your questions.