Hey everyone.
I'm a senior software engineer
in the FinTech industry.
Today we are gonna talk about
revolutionizing FinTech with a WSH
maker and using go in machine learning.
The FinTech industry is undergoing
a dramatic transformations powered
by machine learning and artificial
intelligence integration with global
FinTech markets projected to reach
thousand billion dollars by 2033,
the financial institutions must
adopt to scalable ML solutions to
maintain competitive advantage.
This presentation explores how A WSH
makers simplifies the implementation
of machine learning models.
We'll examine how sage makers integrated
environment streamlines the machine
learnings lifecycle while maintaining
security and regulatory compliance.
We'll also see how Golan can be used,
for ML development and integrate,
and how we can integrate it with
AWS SageMaker for machine learning
model development and deployment.
Using SageMaker has given a boost for
model development by 40% by taking
advantage of its features, simplifying,
automating various stages in ML lifecycle.
This leads to better focus on model
development rather than focusing on
managing the lifecycle development,
deployment, experimentation of the models.
Which ultimately leads
to improved accuracy.
Financial institution face increasing
pressure to innovate while maintaining
strict compliance standards.
The adoption of our advanced machine
learning solutions like A WSH Maker
represents a critical co advantage
in this rapidly evolving marketplace.
There are some key bottlenecks in
the FinTech ML implementations.
The first one is the talent bottleneck
shortage of ML specialists with the
knowledge and requiring the engineers
to be fully knowledgeable of models and
separate infrastructure management teams.
For ML models, deployment and maintenance.
There's infrastructure complexity,
model development, training,
nest states, the use of large
and powerful computing resources.
Such as high performance GPUs,
distributed competitive systems to
handle the massive data sets and,
computational intensive algorithms
they need to be handed efficiently.
With scalability, there are compliance
requirements, data security concerns.
Protecting sensitive customer
financial data remains the highest
priority, while adhering to the
stringent regulatory frameworks
as additional layer of complexity.
There are model deployment hurdles too.
Once the development is done, there's
a gap and extensive overhead of
infrastructure management, management for
training and deployment into production
for inference and batch inferences.
Here comes where we
introduce AWS SageMaker.
So let's see how it solves these problems.
The integrated ML
workflow, it provides a in.
It provides an intuitive to environment
for building, training and deploying
the machine learning models with
minimal infrastructure management.
It has prebuilt algorithms, it gives
access to production ready algorithms
for common FinTech use cases,
including fraud detection, credit
scoring, and customer segmentation.
It also provides several
state-of-the-art foundational models
to build your own gen AI solutions.
It has framework flexibility.
It supports popular M
ML frameworks, including
TensorFlow, pipe touch and MXNet.
It also has multiple kernels, and it
also enables usage of Golan for model
development and deployment, allowing
teams to work with familiar tools
while leveraging AWS infrastructure.
It has automated
infrastructure management.
It eliminates the complexity of
provisioning and managing specialized
ML infrastructure while ensuring
optimal performance and cost efficiency.
The A-W-S-H-H-S-H Maker democratizes
machine learning by removing
infrastructure barriers and providing.
Tools that support the entire
machine learning model lifecycle.
This em empowers FinTech organizations
to focus on building sophisticated
models rather than managing complex
infrastructure and adhering to,
stringent rules and compliances.
Now let's deep dive deep into the features
of SageMaker that help in achieving these
advantages and how they are ease of use.
AWS SageMaker has something called
SageMaker Studio, and most recently
they have added Unified Studio.
It provides a platform which has a
fully managed service that enables
data scientists and developers to
seamlessly build, train, and deploy
machine learning models with Unified
Studio or advanced project management and
collaboration tools are also provided.
SageMaker Studio provides an
integrated development environment.
Through which you can perform
all machine learning development
steps and deploy at scale two.
It's a web-based interface program,
which you can access directly from
the browser or the AWS console.
The studio provides environments
like Jupiter Lab Code Editor, which
is based on Visual Studio Code,
open source, and even our studio.
It has various kernels and infra
development in ones can be spun
up quickly with just few clicks,
and they come pre-configured
with necessary machine learning
libraries and kernels and frameworks.
Users can also spec select specific
instance types to optimize performance
and cost and instance types can
all can be updated and modified at
different stages of the ML lifecycle.
They also have large selection of
models optimized for AWS through
which you can select any model, train
it, deploy it, and also evaluate
the model based on your data set.
You can also quickly fine tune
the models with hyper parameters
that it feature that it provides.
So it SageMaker provides
an end-to-end flow.
It offers the capability for model tuning,
monitoring, debugging, even experimenting
with your morals and updating them.
It provides a platform to check all the
training jobs, deployed endpoints for
inferences, build and maintain pipelines,
unifying the tools needed for machine
learning development into one interface.
This is the SageMaker UI
interface with your IM rules.
You can set up environment, select
an ID, and choose an instant
type and an image and start model
development instantaneously.
You can choose, you can change the
instance type at different, stages
of the ML life cycle, like data
prep training, and the data will
be persisted across the instance.
Start and stop.
Once the, instance has been ready,
you can just start and stop or
open the AWS SageMaker Studio.
ID by clicking on the open here.
As I was previously mentioned, we have
a wide range of kernels to choose from,
and here's a sample of the web based
UI interface, for a model development.
We can use a jumpstart feature in
SageMaker where you can select a wide
range of open source models with just
a click train the model, against your
data, deploy it, and even evaluate
your data against the train model.
SageMaker has its seamless
integration with various other, AWS
services, which is a big advantage.
For example, a we can ha use AWS S3 to
store and retrieve training data models.
data models securely leverage compute
power of EC2 instances avail available.
Use A-W-S-E-M-R and a AWS
glue for data preparations.
In case of large data sets, AWS Lambda
can be used for event driven ML pipelines.
A-W-S-I-M helps in fine grain access
management to models, data and resources.
With A-W-S-V-P-C, it enables our
users to seek securely, train and
deploy machine learning models
within a private network environment.
This isolation helps protect sensitive
data and ensures that model training
and inference process are not
exposed to external threats, thereby
hand answering the data security.
Now let's go through the different
stages in ML model development and see
how A-A-W-S-H maker helps in each stage.
The first stage would be
obviously data preparation.
Once we have the, the id, set up
using SageMaker Studio or locally.
Data.
Data provision can be
done in different ways.
The first one is Juta Lab.
This is the traditional way of data prep.
In a W SageMaker, you use your,
its provided by SageMaker.
It works for manageable data
size, and when individual
has experience with coding.
SageMaker also provides data Wrangler.
It's a visual interface
for data preparation.
We can import data from various sources
like S3 Athena, upload your own file, use,
import data from Redshift or Salesforce
Data Cloud, or even from A-W-S-E-M-R.
We can do visual data
analysis of your data.
Find duplicates, missing data, and get
a general overview of the data with
pre-built functionalities before the
data prep as well, we can perform data
per perform data transformations like
dropping columns, splitting the training
and test data, and the validation data.
It's a user friendly work environment,
which works for non coders as well.
Data Wrangler is more, a UI
based data preparation tool.
We can use, SageMaker
integration with A-W-S-E-M-R.
Elastic Map produce, we can leverage emr,
big data processing capabilities directly
from SageMaker studio or notebooks to
efficiently handle large scale data sets
in the range of terabytes and petabytes.
Eliminating the need to switch
between tools and platforms.
We can create and view EMR clusters
directly from SageMaker Studio
and connect with Autogenerated
code in Eds and studios.
We can also use AWS Glue, which is
primarily used by data engineers.
However, with integration with AWS
SageMaker, AWS Glue Interactive
Sessions provide an on demand serverless
Apache Spark run type environment that
you can initialize in seconds on a
dedicated processing unit that you can
enlist to collect, transform, clean,
and prepare the data for storage in
your data lakes and data pipelines.
Once the data prep is done, we move on
to the model development and training.
SageMaker provides various model
development, methods for all stages of
doubles from novice to expert, and you,
we can also utilize predefined models or
develop your own models with SageMaker
or bring in custom models from elsewhere.
Let's first discuss about the no code
or the low code, which is focused
on using the built-in algorithms.
It requires no or less coding.
The only inputs you need to provide
are the data, hyper parameter
tuning and the compute resources
that you would like to use.
This allows you to run, experiments
more quickly with less overhead of
tracking the results and code changes.
You can utilize wide range of models
provided from SageMaker, from fundamental
models to foundational models with Gen ai.
You provide the data to your model,
train data and deploy your model.
We'll get into the more details about
the deployment in the next slides.
Then it's a, we can go into
the next, a bit more advanced
version called the script mode.
If the algorithm required for your
model isn't available as a built-in
more option, your A and you're adapt at
coding your own solution, you might want
to use SageMaker supported frameworks.
This is often called a script mode.
In this mode, you create your
custom core or a script in a dot,
PIY, or a do R or a do spark file.
You can utilize the various machine
learning frameworks that come built in,
like the TensorFlows psyche, learn MXNet.
We can add custom parameters
and do other modifications too.
Then we can use the bi, if the
built-in algorithms and the supportive
frameworks, kernels language
should cover the most use cases.
But there are times where you
might need to use algorithms from
a package not included in any
of the supportive frameworks.
Perhaps you're not comfortable
with Python or R and you want to
use your preferred language as go.
In such cases, you can write your
own models externally and create
a custom docker image with model
code and necessary dependencies.
Containerizations on models of models
is a fundamental aspect of a WSH maker.
SageMaker relies heavily on
container images for both
model deployment and training.
This allows for efficient and scalable
management of models, ensuring
portability, scalability, and consistency
and reproducibility across environments.
Space SageMaker uses, docker images
and containers as a standard format for
packaging, training and deploying models.
These containers contain all the necessary
dependencies, libraries, and core
requirements to run the model, isolating
it from the underlying infrastructure.
In the further slides, we, I
will explain the steps to use.
Go for creating a model and train
and deploy, the data using SageMaker.
You can train your model
through Studio, ID.
Jumpstart or through SageMaker, training
job for custom model AI in images
SageMaker save the train model in, in as
an artifact in the S3 bucket specified
in your training job configuration
mentioned through the UI or through code.
This bucket can be in your own
account or in an AWS service catalog.
This is an example of, using
a built model builtin model.
As you can see in these two examples,
we are importing SageMaker URIs, from
of linear and XCG boost, and passing
in our data to train our model.
We can also use the, the using Jumpstart.
We can use the foundational models,
directly, instead of even going into
the ID and, selecting a model, train
the pass, when you click, passing
your data and you can deploy it.
Two, you can also do fine tuning,
which will again open an IDE in
SageMaker studio, and you can even
fine tune the fine foundational models.
Going back, the next, method
is using the script mode.
This is an example of a script mode
where we write our own algorithm using
libraries and framework, provided
by SageMaker to build your model.
Here we have more control.
On the model and have the ability to use
libraries like LEA and TensorFlow here.
In this case, we are using the
TensorFlow, DDNN classifier.
We mentioned the script as the entry point
and the remaining parameters are similar
to using your, using a built in, model.
This is an example of building our own
model and models and using them, in
SageMaker with the help of Docker images.
This is a mo this is the case
where a model that you have built
locally using custom LI libraries
not available in SageMaker.
For example, an ML model
written in goal language.
So assume like these are the,
go language, files, of where you
have written your, your model.
Along with the model we create,
a Docker file containing the
information about the necessary
dependencies, libraries and kernels.
We created a Dockery image
and push it into A-W-S-E-C-R
Elastic Container Registry.
Now, using the image id, we
train our model in SageMaker.
There are two ways to do it.
One is in a Jupiter Studio, lab studio,
Jupiter lab, as we see in the image here
where we are mentioning the image name.
And NCE in the models model
programmatically, or or through
the console using training job.
Here.
Also, we give the image information and
training data where we want to store
the, train model artifact After the
training is done here, in this case,
you can see we are, man, we are creating
a training job, YouTube hyphen one.
we are also, we selecting an option to
use your own algorithm container in ECR.
Here we pass in our image name, the, which
has, containerized, our model code and all
the libraries and kernels that we need.
We specify the data source and
we specify the output path where
the, machine learning model,
artifact needs to be stored.
In the code format, we spare, we
use the code to pass in the image,
and we pass in the I am role.
and again, the remaining parameters
are similar to how we use the script
mode or, or as in the built in models
now coming to deployment.
Once you've trained your model
using the IDE or through SageMaker
training jobs, you can deploy it.
You can deploy your model with
AWS SageMaker to make predictions.
Amazon SageMaker provides
several deployment options
to suit different needs.
The first use case is
realtime hosting service.
This can be used for continuous
realtime inferences against your model.
This is best in the case where
there is continuous traffic.
The play payload is of smaller site.
It's deployed in our
preferred instance type.
This is best suited for the cases where,
the machine learning model is for ad
serving, personalized recommendation
or immediate fraud detection.
The second case is of
using serverless inference.
This is, this option.
We can use it for intermittent traffic
where we see bursts of traffic maybe
during daytime or during office
hours or during end of the day.
This is ideal for workloads
that can tolerate cold starts.
It automatically launches computer
sources and scales automatically
removing the need to choose the
instant type based on the traffic.
This best works in a case where
we're doing workload tests, where we
extract, analyze data from documents,
after a certain, end of the day.
And also sometimes we see
chat bots with search traffic.
This serverless inference would
be the best for these scenarios.
There are other cases where we
can use, asynchronous inference.
Here the inferences where we
have to have large payloads,
maybe up to one gb and getting an
inference takes longer processing.
In this case, we have the
flexibility of waiting for the
inference, and we are okay with it.
There are other cases where we are not,
okay with one, one or two inferences.
We need to do a batch of them and
usually this is the case for offline.
The so here where we
can use batch transform.
This is for large amounts of data sets.
It has higher throughput.
it can support large data sets in
the gigabit size, and processing
times can go up to days.
So this works for the specific case,
like churn prediction, predictive
maintenance, and historical analysis of
customers to identify any, scope of risk.
These are the cases.
we, these are the two examples
that we have where we are
making real time inferences,
calling the endpoint to predict.
So we are passing in a sentence which
we want to do a prediction on, we
call, a classifier, which has, which
we've used previously to deploy.
And we call the predict function
with our input, and we get back
a response with the, probability
of saying like this is 99%.
correct or wrong, this, however, is
an example of batch transform where
we have created hugging face model,
and we are, passing a job, a bad job
transformer to do inferences on a
bunch of data from an NS three file.
This is the overview of SageMaker and how
it can be used in entire ML lifecycle.
Financial institutions benefit from
the streamlined data labeling with
SageMaker ground truth, comprehensive
exploit analysis through SageMaker
studio notebooks, and sophisticated hyper
parameter optimization that eliminates the
guesswork, framework in model refinement.
Model operation directly translates to
financial outcomes and risk management.
SageMaker has advanced monitoring
capabilities by integration with AWS.
CloudWatch provide essential safeguards.
SageMaker is continuously
evolving with new features.
These are some of them
SageMaker experiments.
It's used to run experiments
during model building.
Monitoring the inputs and outputs
enhance the repeatability and tracking.
It helps you keep track of your metrics
and collaborate your, with your teams
in these experiments, it also provides a
new feature called SageMaker Pipelines.
It provides a fully managed C-S-E-R-D
service for machine learning workflows.
Enabling automated, scalable, and
reproduce ML model development.
It helps to define end-to-end ML
workflows with a UI based with drag drop
connect directed cycle graph structure.
This is a UI interface where you
can just drag and drop pipelines.
And AI handle the ML lifecycle from,
data preparation to model deployment.
It also has SageMaker model monitor.
It helps in oversee the quality of AI
machine learning models in production.
It continuously monitors across various
deployment methods and also alerts
any deviations in model quality.
That could compromise the accuracy in
mission critical operations such as
fraud prevention, credit assessment,
and algorithmic trading conditions.
Fa this facilitates an early direction
of wrong predicts and take early
action With Amazon Bedrock, and
Sage and Unified Studio and AWS
SageMaker, cap, capabilities, it helps
us to quickly build and customize
your generative AI applications.
It lets you work with high
performing foundational models,
customize the Foundation.
Foundational models to match your
requirements, data workflows, and
also meet responsible AI standards.
It gives an access to wide range of
foundational models from leading AI
companies through the Gen I Playground.
You can compare different
models and configurations to
evaluate their performances Easy.
Now coming to the usage of go for
ML model development while go might
not be the first language that
comes to mind for machine learning,
it offers several advantages for
specific tasks and situation.
It has the benefits of performance
efficiency, critical for real time
applications and large data sets.
We can take advantage of ghost
concurrency and parallelism to
improve training and inference.
It has the advantage of
performance and concurrency.
Goal line is a compiled language,
which means it generally runs faster
than interpreted language like Python.
This can be significant and advantage when
working with large data sets or complex
models with concurrency in goal language,
it has a built in support of go routines,
making it easier to paralyze tasks, which
can be beneficial in training large models
or handling real-time data processing.
Go Bindings are available for many popular
machine learning libraries like TENS
four Pipe Touch and Sky Psychic Learn.
This enables leveraging existing
code and algorithms with GO Projects.
Golan also has the ease of deployment.
Golang Static Library libraries simplify,
deployment, especially in environments
where containerization, it is used.
This can be particularly useful when
deploying ML models in production.
Also go language has strong
typing, which helps catch errors in
development process, reducing the
risk of runtime in ML applications.
There are also going number of, libraries
for machine learning development.
Go facilitating data transformations
and using ML capabilities
in go programming language.
we have gunna, which is like
a numerical computing library,
similar to mpi, we have goia.
It's a modern, high performance
deep learning library, specifically
designed for go programming language.
It provides a clean and expressive API
for building and training neural networks,
making a suitable choice for ML tasks.
We have also have Go Learn and Go ml,
which are versatile and comprehensive
machine learning libraries.
Again, specifically built
for go programming language.
They provide a wide range of
algorithms and tools for tasks, making
it as a valuable resource for ML
practitioners, who work with Go Language.
We also have Go cv, which is a
computer vision library, specifically
designed, to provide a comprehensive
set of tools and algorithms for image,
video, image and video processing
and analysis and manipulation.
This is the ML part of it.
There are some scenarios where we can
use, go along with SageMaker as well.
the first case is the data handling
and the pre and the post processing.
Although the act, we can go ahead
with an approach of, actually
building the machine learning models.
In the more, wide approached
languages like Python Go can be
used for other tasks that involve
data gathering, pre-processing,
or post processing results.
Go efficiency and speed makes it a
great choice For these tasks that
require high performance, such as
processing large volumes of data or
streaming data, we can use, libraries
like A-W-S-S-D-K Go SageMaker, go.
To interact with SageMaker, APIs
and services from your GO code to
interact with SageMaker to automate
workflow jobs and life cycles.
We can deploy a go based Lambda function
to build an event driven ML life cycle
events, like a new training data,
a new inference data, a new docker
image of the machine learning model.
And once these events
get triggered, we could.
Automate of the training
and deploying the models.
Finally, from our previous
slides, utilize ML libraries or go
bindings with Python ML libraries.
In Go.
We can write your own model container.
I containerize it and create an image.
Use this image in SageMaker to
train and deploy your model.
written and go.
SageMaker enables to overcome the
barrier of language by using no code or
low code solutions, providing a large
range of models, intuitive interfaces to
handle various stages in ML lifecycle.
It also provides ML model Docker image
solution to go beyond and use tools
and languages provided by SageMaker.
For example, we can use GO.
Here are some of the use cases where
ML is used in the FinTech world.
For fraud detection.
We can use XG Boost for
credit risk assessment.
Linear and neural networks can be used
to evaluate real borrower's risk profile.
For customer intelligence, we can use
clustering algorithms to identify customer
categories and tailor financial products.
We can also do portfolio management using,
algorithmic trading using reinforcement
learning and time series forecasting.
As you can see, all these models are
provided and can be built and fine tuned.
Using SageMaker architecture ensures
scalability to handle transactions, of
volumes from millions of customers while
maintaining low latency response necessary
for critical financial operations.
We can achieve this level of performance
with data encryption in transit or at
rest meeting stringent requirements for
FinTech data using A-W-S-V-P-C, we never
have to process sensitive financial
data in public internet and provide
isolation for all the ML workloads.
Again, using AWS I, we can find grain,
have fine grain access to data and models
in aligned with regulatory requirements.
Now, let's discuss about a case where
the Fortune 500 bank utilized SageMaker
for fraud detection, which led to a
false positive redu false positive
rates, reduced by 69% detection
rates, improved by 94%, and with the
leveraging A WSH Makers various features.
The model development improved by 60%
and also, you, a better alert processing
time was reduced, by making it, faster
processing speeds by five times.
So going out of this, presentations,
what are the steps ahead to begin
your journey of using SageMaker
or into machine learning?
First try.
first identify your problem
you're looking to solve with
defined KPIs and success metrics.
Start off leveraging the prebuilt models
and advanced, and advanced forward to use
foundational models and develop your own
models for more fine tuning and control.
Utilize AWS Lambda SageMaker pipelines to
create automated workflow, workflows for
model training, evaluation and deployment.
This ensures consistent quality and
enables rapid interaction attritions
on financial models, SageMaker model
monitor, and CloudWatch logs to
continuously track the model performance
and identify any drifts causing
customer impact or compliance issue.
I had mentioned previously start
with assessment phase, move to
proof of concept and production
implementation later, and then further
move across to cross-functional
implementation across organizations.
There are many resources for
understanding A WSH maker and how
it can be used in various use cases.
In this presentation, we have
seen the case of FinTech.
We can explore the different ML
libraries that are available for grow.
And explore more into the
presentation that I've just made.
one more final conclusion.
Let's make it short.
There are two main points to all this.
If you're new to ml, start
with Python and SageMaker.
It's easier to learn as a
bigger community and all of the
features implemented for you.
If you're more comfortable with Go and as
you advance and you, as you become a pro.
there are more efficient ways and
you want to have a more efficient
way to improve your model.
Welcome to Goal Language.
Here you can write an optimal model
by your own hands, of your knowledge,
and utilize features of SageMaker
for better ML lifecycle management.
Thank you.