Hey everyone.
Have a good day.
I'm, and I bring over 21 years of
experience in I series development,
project management, and enterprise
software solutions with a deep focus
on banking, retail, and ERP systems.
It's a pleasure to be here today to
discuss a critical transformation
happening in the financial industry,
modern engineer, legacy banking
systems who meet with the demands of.
So in this session, the
bridging banking generations
go Power iSeries Modernization.
We'll explore how Golang is playing
a pivotal role in revitalizing
decades old iSeries platforms as
a financial institutions, face,
increasing pressure to enhance agility.
Scalability and responsiveness.
Leveraging modern programming languages
like Book can bring the gap between the
traditional core banking systems and the
evolving the needs of digital finance.
Join me today as we dive into
the strategies, challenges,
and solutions seamlessly.
Integration modern technologies
into legacy banking
infrastructure, ensuring system.
Secure and future Ready.
Let's see, in this one, the next
slide, the banking technology gap.
as we all know, legacy banking,
system remain the backbone of
financial operations worldwide.
Many institutions still
rely on I series, a four.
Mainframes that have been running
uninterrupted over many years.
These platforms process millions of
transactions daily, but they operate
on aging COBOL and RPG core basis,
making it necessarily difficult to
adopt to the modern FinTech needs.
So what is.
Built on realtime processing,
seamless customer facing APIs,
omnichannel experiences, and
cloud narrative architecture.
So banks and financial insurance
institutions must meet these
evolving expectations, but legacy
systems often struggle to keep it up
without exponential modifications.
So this creates a technology
gap that must be addressed.
So what is the next challenge here?
the integration challenge we will
see here, the biggest challenge in
the financial institutions space is
modernizing these legacy systems without
disrupting 24 by seven operations.
So downtime is a not an option here,
and security should be, remain our top
priority and the regulatory complex
must be maintained at all times.
Finding the right approach to
modernization on these balances.
Innovation with the stability
is the key, of staying ahead in
today's financial ecosystems.
So in, in the next part of the session,
we will explore how the leveraging the
modern technologies, like Golan can help
with just this gap, enabling a smooth and
secure transition into the future banking.
So let's see why the Golang in
for the banking modernization.
So why Golan?
Let's see.
And the see the this, why the Golang here?
So go brings several advantages that
making it an ideal choice for the
modernizing the banking infrastructures.
Let's see what all.
So go lightweight.
Go ratings efficiently handle thousands of
in transactions with minimal memory usage.
How performing traditional
threading models.
And second one is a strong type system.
So go compiled time type checking
ensures transaction integrity and system
reliability, preventing costly error.
Next one is built in security.
So the gross automatic memory management
eliminates vulnerabilities like the
buffer workflows and memory leaks,
protecting sense, two financial data.
And next one is a compilation
to the single binary.
So go application replies, standalone
executables with no external dependencies,
streamlining compliance, and.
Our next slide is based on the
microservices architecture implementation.
How we implemented here.
We see here now.
First one is, So for the successful
or before that, we will see actually
for successful modernization
I series systems, we use a
microservice driven approach here.
We all know that in today's you of
FinTech era, everybody in the micro,
they are in microservice are playing the
major role in, modernizing any system.
So let's see the, what is the fire,
legacy I series here, traditional
mainframes continue running or
as one continue running in this
mission critical operations.
And the go API layer, the
lightweight microservices in the
Golan transform legacy data models
and securely route transactions.
Next one is the integration hub.
Integration hub via enterprise
grade message brokers ensure
reliable communication between
the world and the new systems.
Next one, our
a.
Expose banking functions, but the
web and the mobile applications while
maintaining the security protocols.
Let's see the word the next, you
know the case study where, the
banking transformation happens here.
Let's look at this realtime
world example here.
A tire banking transformation,
to modernize its ICD system while
ensuring that the zero downtime and
compliance, let's see, assessment.
Assessment here actually.
So we audited, 15 plus years of,
customizations identifying over two
hot team mission critical processes.
The architecture design we use here
is we build a go based processing
framework, handling 3000 plus
transactions per second with 99.999%.
Migration strategy.
We use Aries.
We developed a secure data
transformation, pipelines, migrating
millions of financial records with
the complete audit traceability.
The next one is the implementation
50 plus goal line power microservices
for deployed, reducing the transaction
processing time by 78 percentage
while ensuring the compliance.
Let's see what the next slide is.
A performance improvement.
here if you see that the results are,
really remarkable here, if you see or
what is the performance improvement here?
96 percentage faster processing
means transaction now execute in
milliseconds instead of seconds.
And, the system availability is, as
we discussed in the last, slide, 99.99
percentage of the system availability.
That is a seamless migration
with near perfect uptime
and the throughput increase.
The new system handles significantly
higher traffic, especially during
the peak financial periods.
So this is really whole improvement here.
And now if you see that the 75 percentage
of the resource reduction is happens
here, the lower infrastructure cost
while maintaining the compliance.
So let's see the next slide, the
key technical implementations, here.
Okay, the, what are the key
technical implementation we see?
We achieved these results by,
through key technical, enhancements
including, database connectors.
Optimize Go drivers for I
series DB two integration with
asset compliant transactions.
The message transformation efficient
binary processes to convert, legacy
E-B-C-D-I-C data to the modern formats
like the J XML without any data loss.
And next one is the authentication.
Securely linking legacy access
control with RIDC authentication
frameworks, and next, when the
modern monitoring, the integration.
So Unified telemetry providing
these, realtime observability across
the legacy and modern component.
So what is the I know deployment approach?
Okay.
So here is the, zero downtime
deployment approach, pattern we use.
there are, to ensuring
these continuous operations.
we implemented a zero downtime,
deployment strategy, using,
these are the four methods.
The first one is the
blue green deployment.
What is the blue green deployment
is nothing but this a parallel
production environment with
instant, instantaneous failovers.
So the power process will
always help us here actually.
And now go for the staged rollout, the
canary deployments for the progressive
traffic migration and realtime monitoring.
we use real.
And next one is the continuous validation.
So real, right?
verification ensures the continuous
across the both system, the world legacy,
as well as the new modern systems.
next one is automated rollback.
So automated rollback the circuit,
breaker, patterns, detect failures
instantly and record automatically.
So let's see.
the next slide, is, that this
is the key slide actually, the
regulatory compliance solutions.
we will see here the compliance
is critical in banking.
To keep, regulations, our, solutions are
tailored to meet these demand needs to
modern, financial landscape, particularly
focusing on the data protection
audit trails and processing Ls, SLS.
So let's begin with the data protection.
Our system leverages the
robust memory safety.
Which effectively eliminates the risk
of buffer workflow vulnerabilities.
This is crucial for the protecting
sensitive financial data and
preventing unauthorized access
with our solution so you can rest
assure that your data is secure.
Moreover, our implementation
satisfies the leading data
protection standards, including GD.
P-C-I-D-S-S and base three.
This means that not only is your
data is secure, but it also means
the strict regulatory requirements
demanded by the financial authorities.
Next one is the audit trials.
So in today's, regulatory
environment, critical to trace.
So our solutions, cryptographically
secured immutable logging system, which
captures all across system transaction
flow with nanosecond precision.
This means you can be certain that no
transaction goes unrecorded, provisioning
unbreakable chain of evidence.
These solutions guarantees.
Compliance with critical regulations
such as, so my FID two, and various,
regional financial requirements.
This gives you complete assurance that
the all transactions are traceable
and auditable at any given time.
Next, go for the processing.
left final talk.
This one about the processing s ls.
So our solution includes realtime
performance monitoring with automated
altering, ensuring that your
transaction processing constantly
meatless, strict priming thresholds.
This realtime monitoring helps you to stay
on top of performance, minimizing risk,
and improving operational efficiency.
Compliance with key payment processing
regulations like Swift, sepa, and Fed
these guarantees that all transaction
process in accordance with the
most demanding global standards.
So here in conclusion, we say our
regulatory compliance solutions
are designed to offer comprehensive
realtime protection and transparency
across your financial systems.
Robust data protection, auditable
transaction logs and stringent processing.
SLS.
We ensure that your operations
are always in compliance with
most financial regulations.
So let's see the next slide,
the code examples in the I
series integration metrics.
We'll see how the
performance metrics are here.
So here is the performance
comparison between the traditional
as well as the go based.
integrations.
So here, 96, percentage lower response
time compared, to the legacy system.
So processing time reduced from the
milliseconds, reduced from seconds to
the milliseconds year and throughput is,
has been increased high times faster,
and 65 percentage have lower CPU usage.
Also 74 percentage of the memory usage.
So this is a dramatic
efficiency improvement.
lead to of course, the cost savings here.
Let's say.
What is the future?
Next slide.
we will discuss about the future
banking integration roadmap here.
So let's, looking ahead, we
are focusing on four key areas
of banking modernization here.
This roadmap outlines our commitment
to the creating the seamless.
Scalable and innovative
banking's ecosystems.
Let's take a look at each of e pillar
that will drive, this transformation.
Let's first talk about
the cloud native banking.
So we are moving, towards the future
where the banking operations are
powered by the scalable, microservices
built with go an efficient and high
performance programming language.
So these microservices are designed,
with auto-scaling capabilities,
ensuring that your, banking systems
can easily handle, dynamic workloads
growing our shrinking as needed.
So this cloud native approach
enables us to provide, greater
flexibility, faster, deployment cycles.
And improve operational efficiency,
ultimately driving the future of banking
with the speed and the scalability.
So the next one is, API,
economy participations here.
So the banking ecosystem will
fully, leverage open banking APIs,
creating opportunities for the third
party integrations, and fostering
collaboration with innovators.
So this participation opens the door to,
world of the new in innovative financial
products offering greater choice for
the personalizations to the customers.
So these APIs will allow for seamless
integration across platforms driving the
development of modern customer centric
financial services that are built for.
Okay, next for the realtime processing,
is another key component for our, roadmap.
So we are introducing, high pu event
driven architecture that enables the
sub millisecond transaction processing.
So this ensures that the transactions
are process instantly improving customer
experience and meeting the demands
of today's financial environment.
So with real time processing, we can
offer faster payments and quicker
approval and immediate response to
the customer actions, ultimately
eliminating the entire banking experience.
So lastly, the, legacy integration layer.
so our legacy integration layer
is connectivity foundation.
Which facilitate bidirectional data
synchronization between the legacy
systems and the modern platforms.
So this ensures that the transaction
to new technologies, that doesn't
disrupt existing operations, and it
also allows for the smooth, continuous
data flow across the systems.
So by bridging this gap between the
world and the new technologies, we.
Your customization to move
forward without losing value
of your legacy infrastructure.
So here in this slide, we can conclude
that our future banking integration
roadmap represents a holistic approach
for transforming the banking systems
for the digital age, with the cloud
narrative architecture, participation
in the econ a p economy, realtime
processing capabilities, and the
seamless legacy integration layer.
We are setting a stage for the truly
next generation banking experience.
So the, the final year, the final
conclusion, we say that actually the go
along offers a powerful solution for the
modernizing I series banking systems.
It bridges the gap between the legacy
infrastructure and the modern FinTech
requirements delivering the agility,
performance, security, and compliance.
So by leveraging this, Golan infras,
financial, Golang financial institutions
can future proof, their operations
while maintaining the reliability
of their core banking systems.
So finally, I can thank you all.
Thank you all for your time.
I look forward to your questions
and discussions, how we can drive
banking modernation together.
Feel free to reach me out.
Triva alum us at gmail com.
I repeat it again, please reach me
out on triva alum us at gmail com.
Wishing you all a great day ahead.
Thank you and thank you everyone.
Bye.