Hi, my name is Kamel and I
work as software development
engineer in Amazon, Seattle.
Today I'm going to present
about building high performance
healthcare ML systems with go.
So this presentation explores how
I am able to leverage GO'S unique
capabilities to develop machine
learning healthcare solutions with
remarkable diagnostic accuracy.
Let's talk about why we use
Go For Healthcare ml. So
first thing is concurrency.
So goes lightweight, go routines.
Enable efficient parallel processing of
patient data stream, allowing systems
to handle thousands of concurrent
analysis with minimal overhead.
Second point was security.
So goes, comprehensive security libraries
and memory safe design, create robust
protection for patient data, ensuring
hyper compliance while minimizing.
Vulner expose during ML operation.
Third point is performance.
So healthcare application demand
million, millisecond level
responsiveness for critical decisions.
So goals compound nature and
compile nature and optimize garbage
collection, deliver exceptional
performance with predictable latency.
So let's talk about the
technical architecture overview.
For our system.
So on right side, I had presented the,
data diagram, like how data was flowing.
So high level things was, data ingestion.
So high performance go microservices,
efficient capture and normalized
patient data from click and clinical
devices, EHRs and variables.
So that is like 30 plus
medical data formats.
Which we need to read and we need to do
the result in near, near zero latency.
Second part was ML orchestration, so
custom go wrappers around TensorFlow,
coordinate distributed model
execution, enabling parallel feature
extraction and predictive analytic
analytics, which give us the fragmented
healthcare data sets very easily.
And prediction delivery.
So real time.
Insights are securely transmitted
to clinical work stations and
mobile devices via web sockets
with goals, encryption, libraries,
ensuring end-to-end hyper compliance.
Now let's look at the
diagnostic accuracy achievement.
So we were able to achieve
94% cardiovascular disease,
accuracy, so our algorithms are
able to detect heart diseases.
Markers with unprecedented
accuracy, enabling earlier
interventions, and significantly
improving the patient prognosis.
Then second one was the cancer detection.
So we were able to do pretty good
cancer detection and we were able to
identify cancer biomarkers in initial
stages when treatment is most effective,
substantially increasing survival rates.
Third one is the diagnosis.
We were able to achieve the time
reduction, so it was like we were
able to achieve around roughly 68%
of the time reduction, and we are
able to reduce pneumonia, diagnosis,
timelines, why 68%, allowing faster
clinical decision making and more
timely therapeutic interpretation.
Let's talk about the real time
processing in healthcare IO ot.
So what we need is, in real
time healthcare iot, we need
the continuous monitoring.
So our go microservice process,
10,000 plus vital data points
per second with 99% reliability.
The system maintains consistent
sub millisecond response time, even
under peak hospital load conditions.
Second one is the edge processing.
So lightweight, optimized go code
runs directly on medical IOT devices,
reducing network bandwidth by 78%
while enforcing end to end data
encryption and maintaining hyper
compliance at every processing stage.
Third one is the anomaly detection.
So advanced ML algorithms identify
critical patient condition charge changes.
Within, two 30 millisecond, which is
like very exceptional and it is an
outperforming traditional monitoring.
By 12 times, clinical teams
receive prioritized alerts when
contextual diagnostic recommendation
for immediate intervention.
Let's look at the privacy per
preserving implementations.
So these are differential privacy.
So advanced statistical noise algorithms
protect individual patient records while
preserving population level insights.
Then second one is the federated learning.
So distributed AML training occurs
on device aing raw patient data
transmission across network.
Then we were able to do, maintain
the encryption of secure AML
computations, execute directly
on encrypted healthcare data.
Without decryption exposure.
Then there's a GO Security library.
So cryptographically hardened Go
modules provide the foundational
security and infrastructure,
which our team is able to utilize.
Let's talk about the validation framework.
So validation framework is
based on the four stages.
One was the performance testing,
second was the accuracy validation.
Third was the clinical integration.
And fourth is the long-term monitoring.
So for performance testing, comprehensive
loss testing validates system stability
under extreme conditions successfully
processing 10,000 plus concurrent request
and accuracy validation, so other models
undergo rigorous validation against
gold standard clinical dataset achieving
97% concordance with expert diagnosis.
While continuously improving
through feedback loops, then
for the clinical integration.
So clinical workflow studies with
Frontline Healthcare provides,
providers ensure seamless adoption
with 94% of practitioner reporting
enhanced decision making efficiency.
And for long-term monitoring, we
have the sophisticated telemetric
systems, which track 27 critical
metrics in production environments,
providing a statistical confidence
interval of 99.8% for all diagnosis.
Passport let looks at the economic impact.
So before that, our operating costs
were roughly around a hundred.
A hundred, which we were
able to reduce to 75%.
Diagnostic time was also
significantly, cut down by 60%.
And treatment delays were also,
we are able to reduce by, 50%.
Let's track about the
improved patient outcomes.
So 76% decrease in the.
chronic heart conditions, with our
AML powered predictive care system,
enabling patients to proactively
manage their condition at home.
92% complaints.
So for medical thing, it is very
important to have the compliance,
so medication adherence served with
our AI driven personalized reminder
system, representing a dramatic, 39%,
improvement from pre-implementation
baseline, and we were able to redu
increase the compliance to 92%.
And after that we did the patient
satisfaction scores and we had seen
it has reached record high as our
ML system delivered faster, more
accurate diagnosis and personalized
treatment recommendations.
Let's look at the
implementation challenge.
So first thing is the
ML model integration.
So integrating TensorFlow models with GO
service required custom binding solutions.
We engineered framework specific wrappers
with the optimized memory management to
ensure seamless interper interoperability.
Then clinical workflow adapt adaptation.
So healthcare prediction required minimal
disruption to established protocols.
We develop intuitive interface that map
directly to existing clinical workflows.
Then third point is
data quality variation.
So data quality can vary
depending upon which system or
how we are processing the data.
So clinical data source
from disparate systems.
Exhibited, significant format
inconsistency, so goes robust, goes have a
robust passing capabilities, which enable
us to implement adaptive normalization,
algorithm that standardized inputs while
preserving diagnostic significance.
Then regularity compliance.
stringent healthcare regulations,
need, comprehensive audit
trails and documentation.
So our validation framework implemented,
immutable logging of all system divisions,
ensuring hyper compliance while supporting
streamlined regularity services.
Let's talk about the key
takeaways from this presentation.
So first thing is go excels at, healthcare
ml. So go exceptional performance.
Seamless concurrency and robust security
features help us to utilize, go with the
optimal foundation for critical healthcare
applications requiring unwavering
reliability and instantaneous processing.
Second one is the
meaningful clinical impact.
So our system have, quantifiably
enhanced, diagnostic precision by 87%.
Isolated treatment delivery by 56% and
substantial, improved patient outcome
across cardiovascular, oncological, and
neurological condition economic benefits.
So healthcare institutions implementing
our go based ML solution have achieved
28% operational cost reduction while
simultaneously elevating care quality
metrics, translating to a. 3.2 million.
Yeah, that's 3.2 million annual
savings for mid-size hospitals.
Future opportunities to go rapidly
expanding ecosystem position, healthcare
organization to leverage increasing
sophisticated ML applications.
Paving the way for predictive care model,
personalized medicine protocols and
revolutionary patient engagement system.
Oh, we are at the last slide.
So thank you for, listening
to this presentation.
It's really nice to
present, this talk here.
Feel free to reach out to me if
you want to have collaboration or
discussion for the related topics.
Thank you.