Hello everyone.
Welcome to the stock on large scale
data engineering in space exploration.
Now, when we think of space, we
often imagine rockets, astronauts,
or far away planets, but behind
every mission is a mountain of data
and someone needs to collect it,
process it, and make sense of it.
That's where the data engineer comes in.
We are like the pit crew for the space
science, so let's dive into how we
manage this cosmic flood of information.
First, let's talk on the data revolution
in the space exploration, space.
Missions today are generating
more than, ever before.
We are talking about hundreds
of terabytes every single day.
to put this into perspective, imagine
watching Netflix 50 year straight.
That's the kind of data some
missions produce, and with smarter
systems, we are processing this
faster and more efficiently.
which is compared to older systems, we
are processing this 47% better than that.
we are also squeezing data like magic.
advanced compression techniques reduce
the size of these huge files more than
10 times, which is like zipping it.
10 gigs file down to one gigs
before sending it across space.
Now let's talk about the
data infrastructure behind
these missions, right?
So when a spacecraft launches, it's
like flying a smart device packed
with sensors, each one, collecting
every single specific information.
Imagine your car telling you the tire
pressure, oil level, and GPS coordinates.
Now multiply that by approximately
1900 sensors working in
perfect harmony in space.
And because there is no garage in orbit,
these systems are built to survive intense
radiations and freezing temperatures.
From somewhere between minus
55 to 85 degrees Celsius.
Now let me walk you through a simple
example of how this infrastructure works.
imagine a rocket launch.
picture the rocket, like a smart
delivery van loaded with hundreds
of sensors, each one, keeping an eye
on temperature, pressure, vibration.
And much more as it
races through the space.
As a rocket lifts off, each sensor starts
collecting its own kind of information,
like how hard the engine is, how much the
rocket is shaking, or how fast it's going.
These are like real time text
messages from each sensor saying,
here's what I'm feeling right now.
All these messages are routed to
what's called a remote data acquisition
unit onboard, an central inbox that's
receiving thousands of emails per second.
This unit organizes the data, filters
out the noise and compresses it to
make it easier to send just like
zipping files before emailing them.
Then this cleansed and compressed data is
transmitted back to earth, specifically
to a ground station, which is like the
Rocket's home base or an IT department.
Once it arrives, it's stored,
decoded, and analyzed in real
time by scientists and in.
So in short, there were sensors,
acquisition unit, and then
transmission, and then ground station,
and then storage and analysis.
This entire lifecycle repeats hundreds
of times per second, ensuring we never
miss a heartbeat of the emission.
So what makes this entire
process possible is the rugged
radiation proof infrastructure.
Imagine having to keep your laptop
running during an earthquake, inside
a volcano, and with no tech support.
That's what our hardware
is built for, its space.
next we're gonna talk about the signal
crossing and how the ground support works.
Think of the sensors like a music
instruments in space, orchestra.
they're playing data notes,
vibration voltage position at
different tempos from 25 to hundred
times per second back on earth.
Our job is to make sure we
hear every single note clearly.
We use advanced filters to cut the
noise and keep the signal clean
even when the data is flying at
4.5 million times per second.
All of this is sync
perfectly to the microsecond.
That's like marching band
performing in perfect rhythm
across different continents.
So let me talk on how data
travels from Rocket to.
think of rocket as an,
texting earth from space.
It sends the data through radio
laser signals, like sending a
message through invisible waves.
Sometimes a satellite in the orbit
helps by acting as a postman who picks
up the message and hands it off to a
ground station that's ground station,
receives it using a huge antenna, decodes
the message, checks for the error, and
then stores it safely in a data center.
The system makes sure we get
every single piece of valuable
information sent from the space.
next we talk about the high
performance computing architecture.
in space, you can't afford a
system cache, literally, right?
So if something goes wrong, then
your entire mission goes down.
So we build our processors to be super
reliable and incredibly efficient.
They can run high speed data operations
using less energy than a regular phone
charger while surviving radiation
that would fry your laptop with triple
backups and automatic error fixing.
It's like having a car that
can fix a flat tire before you
even notice something is wrong.
So next we talk about the real
time processing and how the
fault management, happens.
every command sent to the spacecraft
must be executed quickly and correctly.
No delays, no mistakes.
Imagine trying to steer a remote control
tone from millions of miles away.
That's what we do with under 10
milliseconds of delay faster than
blinking, and if something goes
wrong, the system can detect and
fix the issue in less than a second.
That's the space level resilience.
Now let's look at the James
Web Space Telescope, our cosmic
photographer, it captures up to
40 gigs of space images every day.
Think of it like downloading
10,000 high resolution photos
daily from a million miles away.
And once it collects this gold mine of
data, a smart system stores organizers
and process it with surgical precision.
Producing results within eight
to 10 hours with 98% perfection.
So now let's talk about emerging
technologies in the space compute.
We are now using tools inspired by
the future edge computing, quantum
techniques, and, mission learning.
Edge computing lets us spacecraft
think onboard instead of waiting for
a, just like your phone, using face
recognition without needing the internet.
We also have AI on board processing
8.7 trillion operations per second.
Helping space instruments make
parter decisions in real time.
So usually talking to the
spacecraft isn't easy.
It's like shouting across oceans
and hoping your voice is clear.
But we now use light beams, which is,
optical communication and advanced
frequencies that lets us stock up to
1.2 gigs as fast as your home wifi.
The system adapts if signal is
weak, like your phone switching
from 5G to 4G to stay connector.
So looking ahead, we are building a case
craft that can think, feel, and adapt.
Neural networks on board can make fast
autonomous decisions with 95% accuracy.
Like an astronaut's digital brain
and quantum sensors offer 20 times
more precise measurements like
switching from an wall clock to
an automatic clock when you need
perfect timing for the deep space.
And finally, the space isn't
just for the governments anymore.
It's like booming commercially.
The global space industry is
worth over four 20 billion with
80% driven by private companies.
Think of SpaceX, blue origin, and
startups launching satellites faster
and cheaper than ever with launching
costs, dropping and innovation rising.
The space economy is
growing at over 7% a year.
And data engineering is at
the heart of this gold rush.
So with that, thank you for joining me
on this journey into the world of large
scale data engineering in space, from
powerful processes to fault tolerance
systems, and real-time intelligence.
The work we do behind the
scenes keeps missions running.
Discovery is flowing and humanity
exploring further than never before.
Thank you everyone.