Hello, my name's Brian and I'll be
speaking with you today about four
quality attributes involved in building
enterprise level distributed solutions.
Those are availability, resilience,
reliability to a lesser degree.
Scalability, do you have
a distributed system?
Will you bang if you have multiple
applications in your solution,
which operate across multiple
networked environments at once?
For example, if you have a browser on
a user's laptop, that opens up a user
experience on a remote server and that
connects to a separate SaaS, API in the
cloud, which may call other systems,
which live in other clouds or route,
may be back to a specific data center
operated by another organization.
I'll show you a few examples of how we're
going to deal with building resilient
cloud native platforms, including
our latest DevOps offering from chef.
Each of these quality attributes can
be designed into your system to meet
your specific technical goals, possibly
building up to offering a service
level agreement to your customers.
First, we'll dive into the theory, talk
a little bit about tools we have in the
open source GoLine community, and show
a couple worked examples, which should
give you a practical way to plan and
test your own distributed applications.
This talk does stay at a high level
and does not contain any proprietary
information from any of the examples.
Rest assured, they're real world
examples that are systems that
are out in production today.
I'll also show a few diagrams
as we go through this.
Some are my own, but where it's a
picture that I've borrowed from someone
else, I've cited the publicly available
source in the slide notes, let's
take a look at why this is important.
So we start with this.
This is a pretty well, versed,
Picture set of points, that talk
about distributed computing that kind
of made the rounds and everything.
And this is a set of assumptions
we might start a project with.
and we generally know from experience
that as we get out to a production
grade system, a lot of these things
tend not to hold true, right?
These reflect the lessons of systems
engineering, the engineering of
multiple systems as opposed to single
self-contained systems or maybe
even MVPs over the last few decades.
In software, we often start with
that core system, an MVP, a proof of
concept, and then if we're successful,
we grow, number of users, increased
functionality, possibly broadening
out to additional tools, to different
integrations, and then we start seeing
failure modes as that system grows, which
are both analyzable and preventable.
The key is to get design in there
at the right point in this path.
Hopefully the quality attribute aspects
are designed are considered upfront, but
the techniques we see today will certainly
be able to be added later as needed.
Just a little bit higher
cost to implement and test.
The other lesson we've learned
is that there are many levels
of quality from good enough to
supporting higher performance levels.
Maybe we phrase this as a service
level agreement or SLA, which is
effectively a more specific quality
contract with the customer, both what
the customer may see as value and
expect in the solution, and what an
engineering team has confidence in read.
We've tested it and can provide a
guarantee during normal operating
conditions, specifically to
talk to some of these points.
Distributed systems face challenges in
the fact that the network connection
between different subsystems
is fundamentally unreliable.
In timing some operations taking
longer than others to complete or
identify an error condition, other
actors may interfere with our systems.
Maybe we call this secure operations.
There may be changes to the network
topology itself, which our applications
will need know about and looking at,
number eight, the conception that
all networks are exactly the same.
Each of these aspects focuses on
the networking and integration
side between subsystems.
And this is one of three major classes
of failures which may affect our system.
The other two, apart from networking
being hardware failure, probably CPU
or some, memory or something like that.
And then the last one being
storage and persistence failures.
When we talk about writing things
to disc in persisting state, we'll
see all these as we analyze our
system for likely types of failures.
In short, there are lots of things that
can go wrong as we think about how our
subsystems work together, and we'll rely
on systems thinking to look at which are
most likely and how we mitigate the risks.
That typically mitigating risks is
reducing the impact of them if they
do occur, or reducing the likelihood
that they'll actually occur at all.
And we're gonna do this through both
design and implementation, right?
So we're gonna start from the
architecture side and we're going to
add elements to our design that help
make it more reliable, robust over time.
Now, at the end, we'll probably make
sure that we continually test for changes
in operating the system as well, right?
So we're gonna make sure that those
improvements that we've made show up again
in the system and that we cer see certain
types of failures that are either masked
we can deal with or don't occur at all.
If you're thinking this sounds a
little bit like failure modes, effects
analysis, FMEA, you'd be correct in
how we identify possible failures.
We'll show some examples of how this
process is not so daunting, and you
can apply this on your system as well.
Let's take a look at what's coming up.
We will talk about topics in this
order here, serve as a rough agenda.
We'll talk about failures
and some definitions of our
quality attributes in SLAs.
We'll dive a little bit into patterns
both on the infrastructure side and
the application development side.
It's important to note this is a shared
responsibility and that both pieces
of this puzzle of our design, of our
architecture make a successful system.
We're gonna make changes on the
infrastructure side and we're
gonna make changes inside the
software itself in the code.
That's gonna make, give us a well
designed platform and software
controls that go on top of that.
I'll show a simple example and
then we'll build up to a couple
more complex ones as we go, as we
show applying these techniques.
Then we're gonna go into Golang
specifically and take a look at some of
the tools that are available for us to
do so we don't have to write our own.
We'll follow up with a little
bit on testing and then some
final summary, summary slide.
Each slide has references on the specific
topics described, and then there's some.
Overview references on
the very last slide.
So on the slide notes for each
slide, you'll see more specifics
on what that slide covers.
Now I'll talk a little bit about
why we're actually here and why
I'm talking about this today.
And it really starts with our journey here
at Chef and we came up with the idea of
a brand new DevOps solution, which gives
fundamental capabilities of monitoring
a customer's infrastructure assets, do
some things that our previous systems
had done in terms of infrastructure,
configuration management compliance,
typical DevOps sort of work processes.
And then extending this into a general
purpose job system, which could work
across customer data centers on-prem,
multiple clouds, that they may have assets
in desktops, and which we could also
bring to market as a software as a service
offering for a large number of customers.
So multi-tenant type offering here.
This system started as an MVP over a
year ago, and we launched our first
version AWS last month of SaaS solution.
As we talk to more customers, probably
similar to your journey, we had lots of
questions about these quality attributes.
What could the individual customer
expect in terms of system performance?
How often could they do jobs?
How many assets could they
include in these jobs?
What if the system went down?
What if the network went
down between us and them?
What would happen to jobs in
flight or ones which had not been
delivered, but an outage habit?
Could chef offer a service level agreement
if these are things that your system is
trying to answer questions on as well?
This is probably the talk for you.
We've learned a lot about how our
system performs over the last year
and we realize this is really a
continuous improvement problem.
So a lot of the things we're gonna
talk about here, though, they are
analysis that we've done on our system
and we've learned from other systems
that other architects have brought us.
it shows a lot of the.
Way of thinking about these
and how to inject design into
the application as it grows.
It's easier to state goals than it
is to prove a system will not fill.
A lot of times a more approachable way
for an engineer to deal with a system
and improve quality attributes is to
plan the organic development of features.
In other words, making a
process your own right.
So you have to have kind of a checklist
or a set of tasks that you're gonna
execute probably over and over again
that fit within your development process.
These steps are just one way
that we've listed out to build
availability and reliability into
your distributed application.
This design process works for both
large systems and smaller systems
with less stringent requirements.
So fundamentally, just go through these,
start with your system diagram and what
your business process description is.
Figure out what your goals are.
We'll show how that can be expressed
as a service level agreement or
maybe quantitative measures that
you can take in your system.
And then go through a brainstorming
exercise that we'll call FMEA
to understand what failure
modes might be present.
Then you're gonna go through
looking for design changes.
We're gonna back this with particular
patterns that we know from previous
experiences that have worked, and we'll
list a few of those as we go along here.
And then finally, after you've implemented
them and deployed your solution test and
make sure that you're meeting your goals,
from an operations perspective, you're
gonna continue monitoring your solution.
You're going to automate your,
playbooks or your standard
operating procedures to recover.
That's great.
But the important thing for the
development team, and certainly an
infrastructure team supporting a
solution, is that you're gonna learn
from operations as well, right?
So when you have a root cause
analysis after an outage.
Turn that around and make sure
that turns into the design
cycle at the very beginning.
Again, the image on the right is one of
an uptime page for a set of services.
We've probably seen a lot of these,
and really this is our end goal
for our efforts is to let our
customers know if the services up
or down, hopefully minimizing the
down and we have all green here.
And if it does go down, what
can we communicate to them
about when it'll be back?
The key with large systems is really
that it's an automation game, right?
So we can't rely on manual
processes as much when we get
to larger and larger installs.
more customers, more feature sets,
more distributed type operations.
And so we're gonna have to bake this
all into the system design itself.
We can't rely on the old days of, oh,
we'll just go reboot the server and
you'll be back, we'll send an email out
to customers or something like that.
when you get to large scale solutions,
that's not as, either helpful or
promising to customers or as, easy
to do because you have large data
backups that you have to restore.
Potentially that might
take a long time, right?
Might have a sustained outage, just
due to the scale of the system.
Now, this observability and self-service
is really what we're striving for.
So you're gonna see a lot of
our techniques here rely on how
do you bake it into automation?
How do you take metrics
actively on the system?
How do you feed those back into
certain types of behaviors that
the system can adapt around?
Failures?
Next we're gonna jump into a little bit
on the common definitions of these quality
attributes and how we might describe them
to others in the business or as customers.
We've talked about SLAs.
Let's jump into a couple of these sorts
of things and talk about availability
as a first definition.
We're gonna take a look at.
One of our quality
attributes availability.
This is the ability of a service to be
able to take requests for a percentage
of a defined operating period.
Okay, so this is the front door, right?
It's open to submitting requests.
The system seems up and running to
the user for a percentage of time,
even though those results may delay by
internal errors, failure conditions.
We have the table on the left
that shows how this percentage is
determined, defined in terms of
outages as seen by the customer, right?
Just different types of systems and usage
by different customers may influence what
the system availability is built for.
Not all systems need five nines,
and many systems are not even tested
for three nines or four nines.
For example, voice software like
Zoom or something like that, may
want five or six nines, right?
It may really want to have very accurate,
packet transmission so that you don't
have a break in the signal quality,
whereas email or a non-mission critical
application, maybe your time card tool
mailing, you need three nights, right?
And maybe some days you
wish it were or less.
on the right side panel is a
description of some hypothetical
impacts of this availability.
This is from Mark Richard's, blog and
an article, which is in the slide notes.
I mentioned that before, but gives you
an idea of what do, what does, what do
different nines actually mean in real
life here right now, you could get lucky
if your system is simple enough, or you
do not actually measure the availability.
Your system may have a particular
built in high availability already.
There's a lot of cases though, this
isn't enough to give a customer
a formal service level agreement.
Or a contract, which says we're
going to hit this, or there are
some, repercussions afterwards.
There are, however, design changes we can
make to get to a desired availability,
both in terms of making sure that the
theoretical redundancy in the system
supports such a statement, and by
masking failures, maybe caching data
to make sure that a client application
doesn't notice that a backend service is
temporarily down or intermittently down.
Now, there is obviously a balancing
act that goes on here, right?
So software and infrastructure
improvements here tend have, they
may drive higher availability, but
they have an increased cost, and
not all customers may want or want
to pay for something like that.
That would be in an SLA, right?
So if an SLA is appropriate to you,
if a particular availability number
is appropriate to you, question,
what's the value statement here?
Are we building this just because we
think it needs to be this, or are we
building this because our customers.
Really have a need for it to be this
note that not all components have to
be running, and data does not have
to be consistent up to the minute
only the operations can be started.
This also talks a little bit about
how little time you actually have to
return to operations after a failure.
Manual processes can propagate you to two
nines, but you're gonna need automated
recovery and monitoring at multiple
points in the system to get to four nines.
The calculation shown at the bottom, which
can be easily implemented and calculated
in a running system through tracking
health checks and telemetry metrics.
Two additional definitions we see
a lot are a service level agreement
and a service level objective.
So typically an SLA is an overall
SaaS service availability target, and
probably has a disaster recovery plan
based on reliability and recovery.
Office 365 is listed in the
notes as a good reference for
how to build one of these.
It's typically a contractual.
Thing between the service
provider and the customer, right?
So it says what happens if
a service level is not met?
A service level objective, on
the other hand, builds up to an
SLA often is internal, right?
Where we have multiple dependent
services with different operators.
Each operator may have their own
objective, which supports the overall SLA.
For example, an IT department may
maintain data center hardware that the
SaaS product team is deployed upon.
So they would have an SLO to that
SaaS product, SLA or a security
team may operate active directory.
The IDENT identity system, which an
application may need to have a certain
uptime to meet its overall SLA.
Let's take a look at another
definition here as well.
I. Oh, sorry.
Another, example, this is one from
a sample retail store, so we'll
see this in our example here.
imagine that you can do e-commerce
orders into a store and you can
also walk into the store and order
things and get delivery of them.
And so this would be si similar
for a branch office or any
other, distributed environment.
The first statement in red text is
really a highly caveated objective,
and it's probably unreachable.
It's an availability statement, but
states a hundred percent uptime,
meaning no outer can be tolerated.
Hence the caveats for any
bad incidents or whatever.
A flood or anything like that
would invalidate the statement.
The second statement is really
a description of five nines
for a specific subsystem.
This might be more appropriate as an SLO.
And this is for the payment system which
lives on top of a platform and connects
to external banks that we're communicating
with, as one end of an integration.
We see this a lot in microservices
architecture where one API may call
another, in this case it's in a
different environment altogether.
And we have to assume then that both sides
of the integration since one is, has a
dependency on the other, are at that five
nines level or are marked explicitly out
of scope for an availability statement.
We've seen a lot at how we look
at the customer experience through
availability here, how the system can
take inputs to initiate functional flows.
Let's take a look at resilience and
reliability next, and that's gonna be
the ability of the system to correctly
process until either successful
completion or a known error condition
that can be reflected back to the
user, but to go all the way through
and mask any failures that might occur.
When we talk about resilience, we're
really talking about reliability.
The ability of the system to respond to
error conditions appropriately, reflecting
back to the user what happened, and to
continue processing subsequent requests
without a sustained outage or a failure
across the entire business process.
To do this, we need to make sure that the
system can detect failures, maybe with
error handling or infrastructure failover.
Optionally report that failure to
a person to take corrective action,
proceed to determine the type of
failure and therefore what recovery plan
gonna be put in place, what automated
recovery plans gonna be put in place.
Since failures can happen, lots
of different levels of the system,
the responses which ideally are
automated, will span both hardware
and platform reliability fixes.
And then you're also gonna have
software components as well.
You'll see these in the examples.
The last one here we're gonna talk about,
after resilience is really reliability,
which is much more quantitative.
Reliability is the percentage of time
which a system or subsystem performs
reliably and is normally applied to
a complete business process, such as
purchasing a process, purchasing a product
as an end-to-end workflow, as opposed
to availability, which is the amount
of uptime for submitting a request.
Reliability is the amount of time the
system can perform entire operations,
the ability to complete the operations.
It's usually measured by two metrics,
meantime to failure and meantime between
failure for software systems, usually we
combine this into a single measurement
because MTTF really is a fundamentally
a hardware type, measurement there.
And then you can, and you can see
there meantime between failures
is something that we can actually
measure on the software side where
we have outages and things like that.
If the system becomes unable to
process, that is it suffers an outage.
We're going to define two particular
terms related to the recovery.
We're gonna talk about a recovery point
objective and a recovery time objective.
The RPO is effectively how much data is
lost between the time when the system
goes down and when it's recovered
or declared, normally functioning.
Again, the recovery time objective is
how long that recovery takes, right?
So not how much data is lost, that's RPO,
but how long it's going to take to get
the system back up and running again.
For example, a system which is backed
up once a day and has a failure in the
middle of a Wednesday, has an RPO of
up to one day the last backup and an
RTO, we'll say maybe five minutes that
it takes to reboot the system and apply
the latest database backup, right?
So these two can differ.
We haven't talked about scalability
yet, which is really a whole nother
topic, but this is the third leg
of our stool reliability that.
Sorry.
Reliability, availability, and
scalability together form that
three-legged stool, which is usually
tested under a number of concurrent
operations or load that the system can
take on without showing failure signs.
We define this as the normal
operating range, right?
So what we want to do is build our
SLA around what we've tested to.
Now when we have complex environments,
we can look at reliability and
availability, and figure out what their
theoretical number might be, right?
And so maybe this is, for either
availability or reliability.
We have to multiply the
subsystem components which have
dependencies on each other.
in series this gets worse, right?
So a five nines in series with a
five nines is less than five nines.
if it's in parallel, then
sometimes that can get better.
So if we have redundant components
and only one of them goes down, or
if we assume that the failure mode is
that at most one of them will go down
at a time, then we may have better
availability or better reliability.
'cause we have two components
that could take up the load.
Usually we assume that software at
the top of the stack is a hundred
percent reliable and then the
things below it are less reliable.
So we're gonna use like a stack
diagram like this, show that chain
of dependencies from the software
layer at the very top on down
through, things in the physical world.
Okay.
In the diagram shown we have two
physical nodes, for instance,
side by side on the platform.
And I wish I could
point these out on here.
So you see node A and node B
that have a big 99.9 on them.
That's two elements in parallel, right?
So you have some redundancy in there.
So that's how we show that
on this kind of diagram here.
The availability of a component
may allow for some degraded mode
of operations as well, which may
count it as still available, right?
For instance, order taking may not be
affected, but backend billing is delayed.
You still may be a
hundred percent available.
If there are redundant components with
failover required, say an active passive
database, then remember that we're gonna
have an RPO and an RTO involved, right?
Which is gonna impact our uptime, right?
So if we can't recover the system
within five minutes, we can't get to
five nights, we're gonna have an outage
longer than that period would allow.
If the redundant components are
operating active, say in a load
balance service, then a partial
outage typically does not decrease the
availability unless the load is entirely
out of our normal operating range.
So if you have a side A and a side B for
instance, and side A goes down, everything
transitions over to side B. If that load
is higher than what side B is able to
take, then we may have a cascading outage.
In this diagram, the color
blue represents software.
The application green is the
infrastructure platform, and
yellow is external integrations.
And this is for, again, for the retail
scenario that we'll see in a bit.
Our sample calculation is pretty simple.
Reliability of the entire system
is gonna be the platform pieces,
the software pieces, times,
maybe some external integrations,
times, maybe some physical pieces.
The payment devices, lemme
see on the yellow side there.
database reliability that's in there
times also your container hardware.
And so dependencies in series
are multiplied together.
And so two elements at one,
at 80%, one at 85% will give
you a 68% reliability, right?
So we multiply them together.
If they're in series, meaning there's
a direct dependency one-to-one, and
elements in parallel where you have
replication or duplicate, redundant,
maybe hardware or containers, you get,
a normal parallel equation for that.
Sorry.
it's in the notes here.
but if you have five elements at 85%
availability, that might give a total
reli, total availability at 99.992%.
So you can see it gets much higher
if you have redundancy in there.
Okay.
Let's go on and we'll talk a
little bit about how we're gonna
brainstorm about failures here.
Here we're basically going
to use a technique called
failure modes effects analysis.
We're gonna go through each layer of the
stack and identify sources of failure.
We can just scattershot them and go,
what could possibly happen at this layer.
Look at our stack diagram or a
system diagram from before, and
then we can just list them out.
Now, one recommendation I would say
here is that before you get to solving
this, before you get to understanding
how you might reduce the impact
or changing design, list them out.
But we want to prioritize
them by likelihood.
Do that second.
And then also as you're going
through FMEA, you might look at it
by the OSI seven layer model, right?
What happens at the application layer,
what happens at the container layer,
virtualization layer, what happens at the
network layer, and so on and so forth.
So on the next two slides, we're
gonna see a complete result of this.
Again, for the retail example here,
I know this is a lot of stuff.
You may wanna come back to
these to look at what these are.
But basically we're going through a
tabletop, failure mode analysis, coming
up with a bunch of failures that might
happen, and then you can see we added
a couple columns to the right where
after we did the initial listing on the
left side, we're adding things that we
think might be able to avoid this type
of failure or things that we might be
able to add to the design to remediate.
Couple obvious ones that we
learned from on this one.
There's actually a good case study of
Square going down in 2017 and Chick-fil-A
in 2021 that I also put in the notes here.
This is the second slide
of our failure analysis.
This is just the, just showing
you the complete, analysis here
of what we thought could go wrong.
There are a number of solutions
for dealing with risks.
For example, when we have a dependency
on a separate cloud dependent service,
we may have an offload, offloaded
login to a third party provider.
We may exclude that from
our calculation, right?
And we may go, Hey, that provider doesn't
give us a service level agreement, or
does, and then we can include that as a
dependency in our own calculation, right?
Or we may just go, we can monitor it and
add maybe redundant paths to it and, be
able to maybe pat around it a little bit.
in the case of a database or network
link, we might add redundancy again.
or we may have a contract for a
different service provider to give us
insurance or a spare capacity to jump in.
In case of failure for long
running services, we may implement
checkpointing or store and forward
to save the request to disc before
starting a long running workflow.
If you're the primary service provider,
the one with the SLA to the customer.
Usually we can't do risk
transference to a third party.
So in our case of a login service
that someone else is maintaining,
we may have to accept that risk and
bear it within ourselves as maybe
a service level objective that we'd
like to monitor with that provider.
we may not be able to pass
that along to the customer.
Okay.
Now we're gonna take a look at how
we're going to improve our designs, what
patterns we're gonna use when we get
to looking at our top, failure modes.
What are we gonna apply
to change that, right?
Sometimes these are prior examples.
They might be codified in a common
practice or a new module that we
can adapt into our own solution.
We might use it to improve either
availability and reliability.
I. Fundamentally, the system needs
to auto automatically identify a
failure in another component and adapt
around it to stay in a healthy state.
And that healthy state is either
being able to, in the case of
availability, accept new requests,
or in the case of reliability,
continue processing a workflow while
it goes along and it encounters
something that it wasn't expected.
We may use different approaches depending
on the layer of the application we
need to, improve the performance in.
And so we're gonna see on the next
couple slides, we'll see a set of
infrastructure patterns and we'll
see a set of software patterns.
So for the infrastructure folks out
there, this is really talking about the
infrastructure patterns that we rely on.
Also, remember, it's easier
to use the providers.
Redundancy mechanisms because they'll
work well within the platform.
So for backup and restore, the same
solution can be done for redundancy.
So if you have an RDS instance, for
instance, within AWS, use that rather
than rolling in your own infrastructure
as a service implementation.
On the lower left panel, I've listed many
of the options, which an infrastructure
architect or SRE could help implement.
The only one's probably lesser
known of these is the geo pattern,
which is described in the speaker's
notes as one that Microsoft.
It came up with where services are
located in multiple regions globally,
and any one of which can serve any given
customer possibly raving to a region.
Specific backend well being
a good solution for something
as big as Office 365.
It like all infrastructure solutions,
has a cost associated with it, and
some of the infrastructure solutions
provide security benefits as well,
such as a web application firewall,
which can throttle or restrict traffic
from bad actors, as well as rates
of traffic from actual customers.
So some of these can have
two different usages in them.
Most of these are designed for
service interactions, not inside
the same cluster environment.
Since the likelihood of network failure is
low inside of something like Kubernetes,
the same cluster, it's more likely
that you're gonna see a failure between
environments where you're reaching out
from one cloud environment to another.
Let's take a look at software once step.
Reliability, resiliency,
availability and scalability is
a single pattern for scalability.
Consistent across all the services,
rarely is a good idea to mix and match
methods with some services doing one
thing and others on a different pattern.
So when we come to software ones,
we might have a set of services that
do crud operations and then we might
imagine one's doing CQRS as well.
Typically, mixing and matching these
makes it very difficult to put in the
type of scalability and availability
changes that we want because we have
to deal with two different patterns.
if you're doing database
transactions, also remember that
your backend may be constraining
your software a little bit as well.
So try and put true database transactions
in a single centralized service and
try and avoid using a transaction
broker if you're having to span a
transaction across multiple services.
Finally, think about what your
recovery should be if something
fails and microservices.
Being restarted, what actually happens?
Then we can call this item potency.
So this is the ability to of
how your service is going to
perform an operation twice in a
row with the same effect, right?
So doing a read operation is inherently
item potent, assuming the back data
doesn't change, but retrying a payment
would not be Ida potent, right?
Because if you ran it twice, the
person might be charged twice.
So you'll have to add some things
like maybe a transaction reference
IED that says the second time the
operation gets requested for the
same purchase, the processor knows
that it was submitted previously and
just says, Hey, I already did this.
I'm not going to do this a second time.
That's also why there's a spinner on a
lot of checkout buttons when you see it
in shopping carts and things like that.
It graze out the screen and takes away
the ability for you to, as a user, click
on it a couple different times, right?
For our DevOps example, as well, you're
gonna see that, we want to fail safely.
And since we're a job based system
against infrastructure, we wanna make
sure that jobs in flight, if they get
put in during the system outage, we have
deterministic behavior on how that's
going to happen and how to restart them.
And we probably are not going to
reintroduce those jobs on recovery
so that we have basically item potent
behavior, which is failing safe.
the lower left panel indicates a list in
order of common consideration from top
to bottom of software techniques that
we typically add to an implementation
to increase its reliability.
I'm not gonna go through all of these.
obviously the first ones goes
without being said, but yes,
let the user retry, right?
That's always an option unless you
have a business requirement that
says that's not available, right?
or not an okay fallback.
Just cancel it out and
then start over again.
now when you get into Software
Ones, we will go, we'll start
with error handling first because
it's the easiest to standardize.
And often one of the reasons that
Go Programs fail is really just
having an uncut panic exception.
So now there are a lot, this list
is based on a lot of the ones
that are cataloged at Awesome.
Go.
So if you're familiar with that site,
the link is again, in the slide notes.
but many of these we then go down
the list and we go, okay, if we
can't do that, can't do number
two, can we do number three?
Can we do number four?
And so we're gonna get to more and more
complicated ones as we go down the list.
Some of the ones that, we call out here,
we use a term called Store and Forward.
we don't really call this out too
often as a pattern, but basically
it's the idea that an API is gonna
write a request of immediately to
DISC before performing a long running.
Or error prone operation so that
it can restart quickly if a failure
is detected later on and it revert
back to the original request and
go, okay, if I can retry it, I at
least have all that information.
And I've kept my availability for
taking that request, even though my
reliability means I'm gonna have to take
a different path for stateless services.
Remember to invalidate the cash if
something happens to the back end.
a lot of times we think of this when
we're building microservices, but we
include it here to be complete backoff.
And retry is a strategy for intermittent
network loading issues, right?
Circuit breakers described
in a lot of places.
Microsoft, Martin Fowler,
are common references there.
circuit Breaker basically helps manage
or throttle down the requests giving.
Given to a down service until such time
as the issue is detected is cleared.
So we don't wanna, if we detect a
service is down on request number one,
we don't wanna throw a hundred more
requests at that same service 'cause
we'll probably get the same answer.
And a lot of times we'll have an
external signal that will tell us when
that down service comes back online.
Sometimes we talk about doing
asynchronous web services or
event driven services, eventing.
Maybe those tend to be a little bit
more complicated to actually tell when a
failure's occurred because we have a long
pole or some sort of socket that might be
open for a long time and you don't know
if the other end went down or if it's just
taking a long time processing something.
And then the last couple on here, bulkhead
and fallbacks, which really limit the
impact of a failure by maybe isolating
one workflow from another, or having
specific undo events and being able to.
We might call this a compensating
transaction or something like
that lets us roll back at least
partially through a workflow if we
can't roll back the entire thing.
So let's take a look at some, look at a
module that brings a lot of this together.
I'm gonna start with, probably the one
that most people would recognize is,
the Netflix one from his called Histrix.
this was a port from Java originally.
and it's a good thing that there aren't
too many Netflix sized deployments
because this is a very complex technical
implementation to add into any system.
And, so I'd say, you can
look at this as a model.
You may take parts of it, or you may
find some of the parts other people
have taken on and made standalone
that you could pick up one at a time.
This one does provide a lot of
availability, reliability, and recovery.
Techniques in it and allows you
to add it into your code base.
And also the added benefit of
providing monitoring, so when it
detects a failure has occurred in a
dependent service, it alerts, right?
It can take it to Prometheus or
it can take it out to telemetry.
Now, the techniques included here
show a wide variety of solutions
that can be used singly or in
coordination with others, right?
So you don't have to use all the things
on that previous list in the software
list to make sure that a singular
failure, single failure does not cause
other dependent services to stop working.
we may be able to get by in certain
cases with certain of those solutions.
We don't actually have to
use all of them, right?
So we might use a circuit
breaker, but only with retry.
And we don't have to use fallback and
we don't have to use bulkhead, right?
So we don't have to use
everything everywhere, right?
Just think from the architectural
perspective, where do you
wanna apply which technique?
To wrap up the patterns description,
it's important to remember that
we have to monitor for failure.
So this is something that
districts gave, gives us, it
happens at multiple levels, right?
We're gonna track hardware
performance, we're gonna track
traffic analysis for latency.
we're gonna see how the
network is performing, right?
For those.
Different lengths of service calls.
Is that within, is it normal for it to
come back after a second or is it, should
it be in the a hundred millisecond range?
And we also will have business
telemetry and metrics, right?
So open telemetry or something like that.
This goes a lot beyond logging, right?
So a lot of times our first pass at this
is just to throw out a log of all the
different things that are going on and
sequencing 'em by time of occurrence.
Realize when you get to multiple different
customers, multiple different flows
through the application, we're gonna
need things like correlation, IDs and
timestamps to start looking through
those logs to actually get the events
out of them and see causality and see
where failures are actually occurring.
It may happen on one particular customer's
job because of the way they specified that
job, or it may be because the load that
customer's putting on it is affecting.
Another customer.
So we'll have to sift through it.
And logging is often not the best
way just to, look at how we're
going to find failures here, right?
It's kinda looking for a needle
in a haystack when something goes
wrong, sometimes it goes very
wrong and we want to have metrics
to abstract that a little bit.
Now we're gonna take a look at
three systems and see if we can put
this into practice a little bit.
So our first example here is just
a simple two-step microservice,
one calling the other, right?
the two APIs may not be in the single
environment, and we have command line
activating the whole thing, maybe user on
their laptop, which calls the first API.
Okay.
Now the second API is tied to a
database, so we're gonna call it a
crud layer over there at number three.
Maybe this is a simple to-do application
or something like that, that, is
fairly self-contained right now.
AWS in this case, if that's where
we're hosting, may give us part of
an SLA as a platform, so that we can
build on top of that in each of the
two environments where the APIs live.
We may also have RDS or something like
that for the database that gives us
redundancy and maybe recoverability.
And so this is pretty helpful.
We can compose the simple case out
of pretty handy infrastructure parts.
Right now, we probably measure
availability at the first rest.
API, we're gonna put that
little yellow star on there.
That's the front door.
Remember that is our uptime.
And then we're gonna measure the overall
reliability by the ability to persist
all the way through the database.
That's the orange star
in this case, right?
So not a lot of techniques we're
probably gonna need on the software side
due to the simplicity of the system.
We probably consider the
command line outta scope.
And if the customer environment can't
reach AWS for instance, we're not
gonna include it in our uptime, right?
Uptime is, you have to be able
to get it to our front door.
Now to increase uptime, we might
have load balancing on that first.
API we might cache some results.
that might come from that
second API or something like
that over at API number one.
and then, our availability would
be based on the customer being
able to create requests and maybe
view status of their requests.
So all, everything in that rest API number
one, reliability might add a couple more.
We might add a redundant database, right?
Provided by our hoster or otherwise,
we might load balance API number two,
we might provide a circuit breaker
in API number one to store requests
locally and, back off on sending
stuff to API two if it detects that
it's, if it's going down right.
And then we might have some
way to tell the API number one.
Okay, it's okay to turn traffic
back on to API number two.
Okay.
Now we're certainly gonna probably
put in place monitoring as well
and maybe continuous testing with
something like synthetic transactions.
So we send through no
operation type transactions.
We pretend we're the user and
we send something through maybe
a read operation that goes all
the way through the database.
And returns to status doesn't
affect anything, but that's what
we'll call a synthetic transaction.
So we can actually test while the
system's running, what's going on.
Now we're gonna take a look at a
more complex scenario in retail here
that deals with e-commerce and maybe
an in-store, set of operations.
This is effectively multi-channel
sales, if you've ever heard of that.
the customer can order it either
in a brick and mortar shop or
online with maybe pickup in store.
of course nowadays we expect
delivery to home as well.
But, we'll leave that aside.
The order starts two business processes.
so when we do our online order at number
one, the starts a financial transaction,
a pre-authorization maybe against a
credit card that goes to the bank, right?
And says, Hey, does the customer
have the ability to pay for goods?
And then we're gonna send that
order down into the store.
So that's step number three there.
And then in store, the customer's
going to do what we call a
completing the transaction.
They may have to, sign that they
picked up the, goods, and then that
notice goes back to the bank to say, go
ahead and charge them $17 and 5 cents.
And then the customer walks out with
the goods in step number five there.
Now, they may short this, and
actually, instead of step number one,
they may start at step number five.
They may walk into the store.
An order right then and there, in
which case those two transactions back
to the bank probably get collapsed.
But the point here we're showing is
that bank is in a different environment.
The e-commerce is in an environment, and
the in-store system is in an environment.
So we're probably going to measure
availability at both the online
ordering site and in store, right?
So if the customer can do either
one of them, then that's good.
For this more complex set of
environments, we actually wanna
measure reliability end to end.
That is the system supports both
customer delivery of goods within a
certain amount of time after ordering
and the financial transaction is
correct, a hundred percent the time.
So obviously we used a lot of different.
Solutions from both the software
side and the infras side.
in this example here, this particular
system, so many of the techniques were
used from previous two slides there on
the patterns, but we primarily focused
on reliability over availability.
So failovers of clusters and e-commerce,
failover, data redundancy and workflow
restarts in store, are they a priority?
Next we're gonna take a look
at an example from DevOps.
So this is a simplified diagram of
a DevOps system like Chefs Cloud 360
offering that I mentioned we started about
a month ago, where one of the services is
to provide a generic job runner capable
of running scripts or specific skills for
multiple customers from the cloud hus,
cloud hoster to the customer's own data
center servers and other cloud providers.
So the customer will start a. Job
at number one, that will go into our
service environment, number two, and
then come back to their managed assets
over in number four and number five.
An end user or operator can automate
or interact with the initial rest API,
number two, to enroll their servers or
nodes in the system with a command line
that's Mark number one, or a browser
based experience as they authenticate the
API forwards the request actually to an
open ID service that we don't control the
customer's chosenness to lock them in.
These API services have internal
databases, queues, and file
storage inside the platform to
be able to perform operations.
I've shown those as basically
a Kubernetes logo and a light
blue Azure queue icon there.
In terms of ours, once the operator
enrolls the node under management, they
call it second API in AWS to submit a job.
We'll call this number two
and also the yellow star.
We're measuring availability, right?
Because this job submission is one
of the critical things that we want
to have up and running all the time.
These API services are in
Kubernetes nodes, different usage
than what the customer sees.
we're using the word node in a
couple different senses here.
in our case it is as a service provider,
we're using multiple nodes inside of
AWS in a couple availability zones.
We'll see other infrastructure
design on the next slide.
So let's continue with our flow here.
Our primary API services may call
an outpost or local set of similar
API services that live across
the bridge mark number four, in
the customer's own data center.
In order to forward a job
to maybe a local queue.
We actually call this a connector
in our architecture, but let's
consider it really a bridge right
now so that we forward that.
From the job submission from number
two, over to number four into the
customer's data center to execute.
Realize the customer may have multiple
of data centers on their side.
Now the agent and server number five,
our real target where we wanna run the
job may actually pick it up directly
from number two or number four.
Doesn't really matter.
The chef agent lives on this
server typically, or it leaves
lives where the job will run.
This is mark number five on the
diagram, and typically this is
one of the customer servers where
they want something to happen.
maybe a patch to be applied or maybe
a restart or something like that.
It may also run remotely
through to a second server
that we call this target mode.
So the agent may live on something
like number five, but it may
reach out to another server.
That for some reason we
can't put an agent on.
Maybe it's a router,
maybe it's an appliance.
The job goes then from the chef, API
service to that outpost, API service in
the customer environment to an agent or
maybe a proxy for remote targeting to
effectively where that destination of
the application or service job will run.
The final part of this workflow, which
we wanna make as reliable as possible is
the agent reporting back what happened,
the completed state back through
the same chain, through the outpost,
backup to AWS and the APIs and maybe
populating reports in a web application.
We show this as number six on here
and also where the yellow star, where
our reliability metric of successfully
completed jobs without failures.
Or if there was a failure, we can identify
what it was and have the user resubmit.
that can be measured there.
We've designed our overall reliability.
Based on a lot of AWS primitive
for infrastructure and also
application techniques.
And we do exclude from our, service
level at this point, customer responsible
items such as, how outposts are running,
how their SSO is running and their
target server reliability, right?
The actual server that's
running the job may have failure
modes and things like that.
All we can do is monitor for those.
And so when we say a service
level, we're really giving the
customer a service level objective.
Because our system is so tightly dependent
on their reliability for most of it,
we can certify our reliability in the
fact that it'll identify that an error
occurred, but that error may have occurred
in an asset that the customer controls or.
Maybe in the case of single sign-on
that they're operating on our behalf.
And so we don't have an
actual SLA at this point.
And so that makes the reliability
calculations a little bit more, manageable
when we can exclude some of those
things and say that will, that isn't
included in our reliability calculations.
So we call these customer
responsible or cr typically.
The other deployment is if a customer
deployed this system entirely on
premises, we're not really gonna
cover that here, but many of the
infrastructure parallels exist.
So if we have A-W-S-R-D-S services
there, we can have a multi-node, a
redundant database, on-prem as well.
And so we typically do infrastructure
components in a purely on-prem
deployment that doesn't use
our SaaS part of the solution.
They will have equivalent
components on the infrastructure
side as what we would have in AWS.
So we'll show in the next slide
really some of the software techniques
that we've prioritized and how we've
built up the production system.
So from a basic, MVP of sending a job
through the system, we go, there are a
lot of places that failures could occur.
So what have we done to change
the system and improve it?
go through these, in, in the order that
we present 'em here, but they're really
from the front door on through to how
do we monitor things in production.
So we're still adding changes,
improving the availability and
reliability of the applications that
make up this latest DevOps offering.
But this is just a
summary of what they are.
one thing you'll notice here is that even
our diagram, if it's, only a few different
forwards between different services,
but it does span different environments,
we're bringing a lot of different,
both software and infrastructure.
Patterns to bear on this, right?
the specifics don't really matter
too much unless you're building
exactly the same system here.
but I'll start talk you through
the process of how we brainstormed,
identified failure points and put
in place these techniques to improve
the availability and reliability.
Right now, number one is
all about availability.
It's making sure the customer, DNS
and the job submission API is highly
available, especially when combined
with number five there, right?
So we take in the request, we immediately
write it to disc, and then we start
the process of running the job, right?
So we can always fail back to,
what was the actual request if
something happens down the line
that we need to recover from.
Number two is about redundancy for the
API calls through the gateway scaling
horizontally within the cluster, and the
ability to spread load across multiple
clusters, potentially right to geo.
Diversify if you were.
Number three is about using
redundant services to the cloud
provider, making sure we're staying
on the pattern that AWS gives us.
we do have some interaction with Azure
as well, so using those primitives
that are there and then monitoring
for external service failures.
Number four is important deals with
the agent that's sitting next to, or
actually on a customer server, it has to
be zero trust, but it also needs to let
the APIs know what its status is, right?
We have to be able to monitor it.
We have to know that it's
still up and responsive.
We use multiple techniques here to make
sure the agent can reliably execute jobs.
One of the interesting ones here is
that we have a heartbeat that is on a
regular basis that tells our APIs on
the server side, Hey, I'm still here.
Hey, I'm still here.
hey, I just did that particular
job you asked me to do.
And so we have a heartbeat status that
always comes back in addition to maybe
jobs specific, artifacts and status.
And then number five is really preventing
failures by immediately writing
request to disc before executing them.
Kinda makes sense.
Number six and seven
really process items here.
So again, work with your operations
team to make sure you're monitoring
the right stuff and that you're
able to do root cause analysis
of any failures that may happen.
Let's talk next about components in Go.
And this is the language that we've picked
for building all of our services in.
So in Go, most of us will probably
know we don't have the easy solution
of something the language is already
picked for us, nor a single simple,
well-known battle tested module that,
maybe other languages might have.
and look at, in t net languages.
We have something called
Poly that's a library.
we don't really have that here
except maybe the implementation
that Netflix came up with.
What we have in Go is
really the community, right?
You can go out to the Awesome Go
website and you can get 20 different
recommendations on stuff, right?
So you'll see lots of different
options out there, some of which I've
tried to list in the most functional
to the least support and meaning.
we know some of these out.
There are single developer that may
not have the time to maintain them, but
did a good code prototype or something
like that, that we may want to take
on ourselves and maintain, right?
Going forward, at the top of
the list we have, has lots of
functionality, adds observability.
And is probably the most complex of
any of the solutions out there, right?
Maybe too big of a hammer,
but is our gold standard.
So if we were looking for somewhere
to go look for a reference,
architecture, that would probably be it.
The next few are pretty well
supported and broadly functional.
multiple patterns described on the
software slide are implemented.
We've got circuit breaker, we've
got retries, we've bulkheads.
so you could pick and choose
some of these components if you
want something lighter weight.
I tried to go with ones that had a
lot of either community forks had
UpToDate maintenance or had obviously,
a lot of people were following and
using in their own implementations.
So going with the idea that
popularity is it's usability.
Okay.
With each of these sort of
check and see how well it
integrates into your use of go.
A lot of times there's a medium or goal
or something on how to use this example.
some of them work better with
the go language, some use
goroutines more than others.
Some use go, syntax and semantics a
little bit more natively than others.
pick the one that works
best for your team, right?
Because we're probably going to be
putting these in a few different
places in our code, right?
also, as you get through looking at these
particular techniques, ask if you need
all this complexity in your application,
go back to that value statement.
Why am I building high
availability in here?
Why am I building higher
reliability to this?
Not all applications need all
the techniques applied, right?
All these techniques when applied could
probably make a really good system.
but it takes time, it takes effort,
it takes, your, cost to get this
out the door and into your system.
If your customer is demanding an SLA,
figure out what parts of that SLA are
most important and figure out which
components support that the best.
And then the code sample off to the side
is a sample, circuit breaker over there
so you can see what that looks like.
Last little note here, for distributed
systems at scale plan on having
a regular test program, right?
You can't do this automated.
You have to have people that are running
tests, new tests, different types of
tests, pick some test tools that the test
teams are familiar with, and of course,
standard guidance of don't have the
developer tests their own stuff, right?
they're only going to be looking for,
things that they conceptualize, right?
A tester's gonna find things
that a developer probably
never thought about, right?
which is what we see, when
our system faces first contact
with the, customer, right?
Run tests and pre-production of
sample data and configuration.
Run with multiple tenants,
run with different roles, run
with malformed inputs, on each
release of the application.
That's a good thing for the development
team to take on as integration test
and then run it in production as well.
If you have an operations
team, or a dedicated test tube,
you can use canary tenants.
I like this because with microservices, we
could put out there, a hundred, commercial
customers in, in there and they may have
different load profiles, but I as, as long
as I have a tenant that is mine that I can
just see all the way through the system,
kinda like those dynamic, tests that
we talked about earlier, the synthetic
ones, you can test a transaction going
all the way through to make sure all the
components are up and running and then you
can report on your availability that way.
Okay.
we use a tool called K six to do a
lot of our, testing, but I've listed
a few other ones here as well.
We do not use fail points.
That looks really promising.
I would say look at that one.
And then one of the really
interesting tools out here is Chaos
Monkey, which injects failures
into your actually running system.
Finally, I'm gonna recommend that you have
some mechanism to report on availability
and reliability of your services.
Many teams don't have a big enough
staff to have dedicated SRAs or
operations teams, but if you design in
your metrics from the very beginning,
anyone can dive in and see what's
going on and identify issues quickly.
Even if you don't have an SLA, tracking
these metrics from the very beginning
leads to being able to build fixes
into your application, which eventually
gives you better customer satisfaction,
making these measurements visible.
we use something like Grafana.
We use Prometheus, common tools that'll
help show us the business events that
are going on, show us the load on the
system, show us the performance of the
different components in there, show
us latencies and things like that,
showing that to the operations team.
And the development team then helps
both in an outage situation and then
afterwards to see how the system's
performing and you can brainstorm
collectively on improvements.
There are really four things I'd
like you to take away from this talk.
First, that availability and reliability.
Require both software and
infrastructure patterns.
You're gonna borrow from both camps,
and the combination of those two is
what's really gonna get you to the
numbers that you want as your goal.
Second, look to examples
from other systems.
There's best practice out there.
There are larger systems than the one
you're building that just shows that
the path has been paved ahead of time.
This common practice gets built
into application templates over
time and eventually becomes the kind
of the easy way to do this, right?
You don't have to build your own model
from scratch every time, and this is
certainly something I think AI is going to
help with over the years, is it'll be able
to look at all these different patterns
and then go, this is what you should
actually use until that point in time.
Use your experience or your knowledge
from other systems as a guide.
Third, do as much as you need.
Don't do anymore.
Don't do any less.
This is.
A balancing act of cost and
schedule against technical.
I call it chrome plating
or over engineering.
Use your architect's experience here
to know how far you should go with
each of these techniques, right?
You don't need all of them.
You may need only certain ones right
now, you may need other ones over time.
Finally, number four, don't overlook
testing and qu quantitative analysis.
It's the only way to be sure before
you advertise an SLA to customers.
Now we've got a wrap up slide
here that shows some of the high
level resources for this talk.
We mentioned poly for net briefly.
His, from Netflix is a good go model
to look at cast monkey for testing.
we mentioned a lot of other things.
Those will be in the slide notes as
we go, as you pull those down and look
through them on particular topics.
FMEA, Particular other testing
tools, different pattern
references and things like that.
Of course, you can look through
cloud providers best practices.
both AWS and Azure have good well
architected programs that sort of
give us a list of, these are the
prescriptive things that if we were
to give you a workshop and they
can, this is what you should look
at for a large SaaS application
that's going global or is in lots of
different, networking environments.
Uber has a really good compilation
here of notes on the SRE role.
if you're ever wonder what does
DevOps do, where did DevOps come from?
it came from SRE Site Reliability
Engineering and came a
little closer to development.
But, they talk a lot about how to
operationalize systems and how to put in
place good discipline on these practices.
And finally, if you're interested in
the latest from Chef, I put our product
documentation at the bottom here.
As a thank you.
I'll put a little bit of a pitch here.
I'd like to thank the engineers that
obviously published before on this topic.
the history goes way, way back over
multiple decades in terms of building
available and reliable systems.
obviously the teams at Poly and
Netflix who've bottled up a lot of this
into tools, modules that we can use.
Thank you, of course to the open
source engineers who maintain all
the tools that we talked about here.
A lot of teams at AWS and Microsoft
and other cloud providers that
brought us lessons learned from that.
and especially on the infrastructure
set of best practices there.
they were really the first ones to see
global scale and a lot of these things, as
organizations moved out of their own data
centers into shared hosting facilities.
We obviously learned from our mentors
and then enables each of us to take
on increasingly scalable solutions.
thank you also to you, the audience
for listening to this talk.
Without you, there wouldn't be
any next application to build.
I hope this has caused you to look at
your applications, inspires you to talk
to your teams about quality regularly.
Please reach out to me on LinkedIn if
you have any questions or feedback.
We wish you a very helpful
and valuable conference.
42 from Brian at Chef.
Goodbye.