Hey everyone.
Good morning, good afternoon, and
good evening wherever you are.
My name is Rashma.
Thanks for joining me while I talk about
application modernization, if you are
the one who is already working on any
of the legacy applications like ier,
IBMI, or IBM mainframes, or you are.
Start working on one of these
applications, then you're in the
right place because in the next
couple of minutes we'll be talking
about what are these, legacy
applications, why do we care about
modernizing these legacy applications?
What are the various approaches
or strategies and what are the
various trends to modernize
these legacy applications also?
after we, complete this presentation,
if you have any questions, you can
please feel free to shoot an email
to Arch in the new arch gmail.com.
All right, so let's dive in, to
see how we can transform really,
these legacy applications.
We'll jump into the presentation.
All right.
So application modernization.
We still, see this as a very critical
imperative for so many enterprises as
we, seek to maintain the competitive
advantage in an increasingly digital
business landscape, you do not believe,
approximately 72% of enterprises
are actively trying to modernize
their applications with 28% of
them are still in planning stages.
And today, organization implementing
successful modern initiatives have
experienced 40% increase in operation
efficiency and a 38% improvement
in customer satisfaction rates.
And definitely I would also mention
this organizations though, that are
not planning, modernization as part of
their investments, they tremendously
spend between 60 to 80% of their budget
still maintaining, their existing
applications, but not on the renovations.
Let's see the current state
of these legacy applications.
when you say current state of these
legacy applications, Sometimes we hear
that, people say legacy applications,
but we still tend to use many of
these applications for our critical
day-to-day business operations.
Though they, they claim themselves
like they're still functional.
We, we still want to continue because.
These business operations are so
critical for their existing business.
and it is.
and if I try to change any of
these things, I will have a fear
that, okay, what will happen?
Will it disrupt my today's business?
So likewise, likewise, many
companies today, they're still
continuing their legacy applications.
thinking that if I try to change
this, I may end up in some state
of disruption, but we still, try
to see some of the challenges.
For example, legacy applications still
maintain that monolithic architectures
and outdated technology stacks.
And knowingly, unknowingly, we will be
having certain challenges with these,
legacy application architectures.
64% of organizations site, they have some,
they have to improve their application.
Maintainability also, they want
to prioritize their, scalability.
This is, these are the two main challenges
we tend to hear from, corporates, in terms
of, maintaining the legacy applications
or modernizing these legacy applications.
And what are those key business
drivers, if you want to consider to,
to modernize these legacy applications?
Customer experience that is one of the
key driver people will consider to, yes.
I have this issue today and I have to try
to modernize the, my legacy application.
And security considerations is
some of these, legacy applications.
Sometimes they, they pose certain
security challenges, which again, is a key
driver for the corporates to think about
modernizing these legacy applications.
So maintenance challenges.
And business drivers.
And the third factor you should
consider when you want to modernize
these legacy applications is the
specific patterns that industry follows.
For example, if you take, health
healthcare sector, they have to strictly
follow their regulatory compliance.
certain organizations,
they still follow that.
And as part of that, you
should take care of, up keeping
your application up to date.
like I mentioned, again,
healthcare sectors, they prioritize
interoperability, improvements.
That is another factor
that you should consider.
Then API first approaches to
enable system integration.
So these are the, this is
the current state where we
have our legacy applications.
today I would like to talk about a few,
major approaches or the strategies.
many of us would try to use, if you want
to modernize these legacy application.
One such approach would be
cloud migration, and other one
would be containerizations.
So we will see what are the strategy
that we have, when we want to employ
these, cloud and containerization.
So assessment framework, yes.
Whether it is containerization or a
cloud migration strategy, you have to
thoroughly do your portfolio analysis.
Why?
There is, as per the research, it
clearly states that, you have made a
thorough portfolio analysis before.
You want to, really start your
journey with this cloud migration
or containerization strategies.
Had it been, any ad hoc approach,
then you wouldn't be really
able to realize the, written on
investment on any of the approaches.
Yeah, container architect orchestration.
I'm sure, we would've, here about,
Kubernetes, majority of the organizations
today they use is Kubernetes, in terms
of, their production operations with 64%
managing between two and five clusters.
So organization with mature T Pro
practices demonstrate a 47% reduction
in application deployment team
and 35% enhancement in resource.
whereas in terms of cloud architecture,
definitely people who, involved, in
this, cloud architectures for, as part
of their legacy application modernization
journey, they see definitely some amount
of improvement in application scalability
and decrease in operational overhead.
And definitely it is going to
boost your developer productivity.
And also must I must say that it should.
It should also show some reduction
in incident resolution times.
So when we talk about clouds to
date, it is essential that we will
be, hosting some of our applications
into a multi-cloud strategy.
So we should also consider, when
I consider these multi-cloud,
strategies, what are the various,
other factors that I should consider?
41% enhancement in disaster recovery
capabilities and 37% improvement
in vendor negotiation leverage.
And 49% implementing
geographical service delivery.
So all these things, enterprises now
operate in the multi-cloud environ.
They have to, take care of these,
parameters, so container security.
if you have chosen
containerization as your strategy.
Organizations definitely must
identify security as their top
container management concern.
So 77% have implemented comprehensive
container specific security tools, and
while 84% incorporate automated security
scanning into their security frameworks,
so data operations and storage.
So this is another consideration,
organization should take care where,
they, it is essential for database
and data-driven applications.
45%. Currently runs stateful applications
in Kubernetes with, 80% planning to
increase their stateful workloads.
So data production emerges as a primary
concern for 54% of the organizations.
So this is about, a cloud
or a continuation strategy.
And what are the various considerations
that you must be taking care of
when you are about to, introduce
this multi-cloud strategy?
Okay.
And my second approach, or the strategy
I would say is artificial intelligence.
So if I'm not still talking about
artificial intelligence, then I'm not, I'm
nowhere in this, in the competition today
who is not using artificial intelligence.
Okay?
if.
Artificial intelligence is so
popular, how artificial intelligence
is going to be, helping me in terms
of this application modernization.
Okay.
A driven code analysis, cognitive
computing and performance optimization.
So in each of these areas, AI is going
to play a vital role, to assist me in
modernizing my legacy applications.
Sir. So what, how, and what exactly these
AI tools or ML software is going to do.
So if you look at this, information
here presented, a powered code
analysis tool report, a 52% reduction
technical debt accumulation, and a
40% implement in code quality metrics.
Absolutely.
So these AI algorithms can process legacy
code bases at 15 times the speed of manual
review while maintaining 94% accuracy.
So these numbers, out of a research
paper I have, gathered this and
these numbers very much say how much,
a critical role these AI tools or
softwares will play, while you want to
plan your application modernization.
Cognitive computing today.
So if organizations wants to implement
this cognitive computing solutions.
they, they would've realized that a
63% implement in the business rule
extraction accuracy, and a 58% reduction
in system documentation effort.
NLP Natural Language Processing
capabilities show a 76% success
rate in converting unstructured
legacy documentation in the
structure knowledge basis.
So this is about cognitive
computing, performance optimization.
Okay, so AI driven performance prediction.
Models achieve 91% accuracy
in forecasting system behavior
under various load conditions.
So organization leveraging these
capabilities report a 52% implement in
resource utilization and a 47% reduction
in performance related incidents.
So not only these three areas,
either in terms of testing or data
insights, there are like several
areas where these AI plays a very
vital role, and it helps a lot in
boosting your efficiency, in reducing
the time, and the cost, et cetera.
So many ways the A is going
to play a critical role.
like I mentioned, testing
and addition support systems.
So automated testing.
So these AI softwares would really
help people to, to do the test
coverage means it really helps us
to, write enough number of testing
cases as given a set of core snippets.
so I really no need to, engage so
many people to write these test cases.
So AI is going to do the job for me.
So 78%, it does the test coverage
with 60, 65% less effort compared to
traditional approaches like I mentioned.
So it also reduces the testing cycles.
While it improves the
defect detection rates.
So much automation is in place, so why
not we see this improvement, right?
So improving defect
detection rates by 43%.
And pattern recognition.
So AI is so popular, in terms of
identifying pattern, what are the
various, stages or, situations.
My system tends to slows down or my
system shows some performance slow down.
So those areas, I can very well map
it down and I can have an algorithm in
place to see, okay, these are all the
maintenance schedule, I have to take
care in terms of, maintaining them.
System recover and et
cetera in all those aspects.
So has become, so this a powered,
pattern recognition has become so
instrumental in architecture optimization.
So like I mentioned, not only in
this maintenance schedules, like also
architecture optimization, if there is
any repetitive processes or any workflows,
this a really helps in identifying
such duplication or in redundancy.
They can very well help.
To optimize those workflows.
It also improves the decision making.
So if you have a machine learning
model, and you can very well use it to
predict the success rate of different
modernization patterns with 85% accuracy.
Data driven decision support.
So AI will also help us to, to do so
much data analytics and out of that
it'll help the, top layered, management.
Cater people to, consider these
data analytics and it'll, it really
help them to perform some data
insights and to use that further
for, next business, enhancements.
So organization implementing these AI
Power Edition support systems report a
67% improvement in modern success rates
and a 49% reduction in project risk.
These tools can effectively analyze
complex dependencies with 84% accuracy.
Okay.
in our approaches, the next
one would be low-code and
no-code development platforms.
I'm sure you guys would've already
have heard of, these low-code,
no-code development platforms.
What exactly you mean by low-code?
No, Today we all, spend so much time
in, in, gathering the requirements,
spending time in drafting the
technical requirement specifications.
And again, after that, people spending
time in, writing, a huge amount of code.
what if I'm given a chance, without,
much code or with no code, I will
be able to do all that magic.
That, that is, that, that is why
it, it is, possible through these
low-code no-code development platforms.
So as per the research, the global market
is expected to grow at a compound annual
growth rate of 28.1% through 2027 because
of the significant benefits to, you know,
through these, local no-code platforms.
Accelerated development.
organizations who are, really
thinking about these, local no core
platforms, they're going to experience
a 65% reduction in the application
development cycles compared to the
traditional approaches, cost efficiency.
People who implement these platforms.
they achieve, they're gonna achieve 47%
cost savings compared to traditional
development approaches and governance.
So in terms of governance, organizations
are going to achieve 62% higher
user adoption rates and report, 44%
fewer implementation challenges.
So training impact comprehensive training
programs result in 57% higher developer
productivity with these platforms.
Success factors include the effective
security frameworks, like 73% success
rate, robust training programs,
and integration capabilities.
So here I have put few numbers in terms
of specific industry who are adopting
these local Norco platforms, financial
services, 38% of this financial sector.
they're using this LCNC adoption
with Workflow Automation
Solutions delivering 61% year on.
Year over year growth and healthcare,
35% of these, healthcare sector.
They use these LCNC platforms for
interactive patient engagement, achieving
a 54% adoption across provider networks.
And coming to the retail sector, 27%
of the retail sector, they use these
platforms in their omnichannel customer
experience solutions and 40% in
manufacturing sector where they use these
platforms for smart operations management.
platforms.
Revolution is in production efficiency.
So enterprises implementing these
platforms or these solutions, they
have proved that you know it is going
to have a faster delivery of digital
transformation initiatives with enhanced
business responsiveness to market changes.
Also, they're going to demonstrate
a stronger cross collaboration.
Along with that, these organizations
experience a 55% decrease in IT
project backlogs and a 39% boost
in innovation capabilities through
democratized development programs.
And the next one we have in
this approach, in the strategies
is microservices architecture.
This is another popular, approach,
a strategy where we use so, so
predominantly when I want to
modernize my legacy applications.
So what exactly is a microservice?
So in, in traditional approaches,
I would be having a long services,
our workflows, our processes.
So now as the days evolve, as the
technology evolve, we realize that.
decomposing these long written
services into small, in a micro
manner so that, having constructed
all these microservices in a very,
communication manner is going to
improve the architecture and efficiency.
strategic decomposition.
So this is what I mentioned, so you
will be decomposing a long, processes
to make them much more easy for in
terms of, communication and efficiency.
So you will be dec decide
deciding a precise boundaries
for optimal service isolation.
Also, you will be talking something
about service mesh architecture, where
you'll be streamlining this, interservice
communications, like I mentioned
about, so pattern based development.
you'll be deciding or designing a
fall tolerance resilient, mechanisms.
for, as part of this pattern
based development and network
resilience, robust security controls
and traffic orchestration data
consistency, so scalable event
sourcing and transaction patterns.
So organizations implementing these
strategic decomposition methodologies
achieve a 64% implement in system
maintainability and scalability.
the demonstrate superior results, in
terms of like success rate for incremental
monolith transformation teams like
embracing domain driven design frameworks
experience a 47% reduction in cross
team boundary disputes and architecture.
So this is, so service mesh
architecture is, very popular.
Like when you implement it is gonna
deliver 58% higher reliability
in complex service interactions.
While reducing network related
incidents by 45%, organizations
report a 67 enhancement in disrupted
tracing capabilities, enabling
faster problem resolution and
comprehensive system visibility across
the microservices ecosystem, future
outlook and digital transformation.
Accelerated modernization.
84% of organizations have accelerated
their digital modernization
initiatives with 67% increasing
technology investments specifically
for legacy application transformation.
This momentum continues to build
as a digital transformation
becomes a strategic imperative
rather than an optional advantage.
Risk management.
So this is another category,
you have to consider when you.
Implementing Structural Risk
Management framework report 70%
modern disruptions success factors.
Include that proactive risk identification
on integrated adaptive response mechanism
across systems technology stack evolution.
78% of these enterprises now
prioritize flexible, scalable
architectures as foundation elements.
Those embracing modern database
technologies achieve 62% improved
application responsiveness.
57, 50 6% less data latency
and 51% enhanced systems.
Scalability, creating a more
agile technological ecosystem.
So sustainable modern practices.
But sustainable modernization practices
where, long-term sustainability, organiz
implementing sustainable modernization
frameworks achieve a 66% implement
in long-term system continuity and
59% election technical declaration.
So this focus on sustainability ensures
a system remain viable and adaptive
over time innovation capabilities.
So organization fostering innovation
driven modernization approaches
report 16% improvement in feature
delivery speed, and a 54% enhancement
in customer experience metrics.
Innovation has become a crucial
differentiator in modern in sectors,
enterprise risk considerations.
So 81% of organizations now
incorporate risk assessment into
their modernization planning phases.
So automated risk assessment tools
lead to 58% I improvement in risk
identification, accuracy, and
better alignment between technical
capabilities and business objectives.
yeah.
So this is about, our, various strategies
and trends that we would be, using
to do this legacy modernization.
one final thought I would want to,
present before I say thanks and leave
for the presentation is, I really do not
want to enforce that you have to abandon
your existing, systems legacy systems.
it is up to each one of us to
maintain a proper balance of
what are today's business needs.
And if my, today's applications or the
existing legacy applications, though they
are called outdated, are they really,
helping me to meet today's business needs.
If not, then I have to see, what
is the, what is the possible way,
what is the most profitable way?
to use the stability and the
enhancement of the existing system.
At the same time, I need to modernize in
a way that I have to make use of these
latest technologies like, cloud adoption,
microservices, containerization, I.
Importantly, artificial intelligence,
so that my application is no more called
as an outdated applications because it
has all the latest capabilities, to be
in a position to interact with the few
other peer technology platforms, for, to
meet the latest business, requirements.
So of course, another factor we
should consider is the culture of the
organization and customer experience.
people who work on these platforms, they
should all feel, comfortable when you
make a move towards this modernization,
I'm pretty sure you have learned enough,
information when you want to modernize,
these legacy applications for the most
business profitability to achieve today.
I hope you enjoy the presentation.
I just wanted to say thank you.
Thank you so much.
Thanks for listening to me.
Bye.
You have a good one.