Welcome everyone to my presentation
on, H computing and Tiny ML
Intelligence at the ferry.
Today we'll embark on a journey
exploring the frontier of this,
transformation technologies like, that
are reshaping our digital landscape.
This complementary innovations or
fun changing how intelligent systems
operate by bringing competition
power directly to where data.
For enabling real time analytics,
even in the most resource
constrained environments.
What is edge computing?
Edge computing is a proximity
focused processing approach where
computation occurs directly at
or near data generation points.
This dramatically reduces the need
to transfer information to distant,
centralized servers and back again.
It features a low latency architecture.
Enabling near, instantaneous response
times measured in milliseconds, which is
essential or time since to applications
like, autonomous vehicles, industry
safety systems, and real time analytics.
Additionally, edge computing distributes
computing power across the network
edge, ensuring operation continuity
during connectivity disruptions, and
enhancing data privacy by processing
sense to information locally.
So let's, look at the practical
applications of H computing in, autonomous
vehicles, self-driving cars process
estimates of sensor data in milliseconds.
H computing enables, critical split
second edition, making locally, ensuring
safety and, responsiveness regarding
of, regardless of the code, connectivity
in, smart factories, industrial.
Equipment leverages edge
processing for continuous real
time monitoring and analysis.
This technology identifies subtle
anomalies, predicts potential, failures,
and trigger, provincial maintenance
without relaying on distance.
Centralized systems in healthcare
monitoring advanced variable
devices analyze complex patient
vital signs directly on the device.
They intelligently process
health data locally.
Preserving privacy and battery life
while only transmitting, critical
alerts when potentially life-threatening
pattern image, And, introduction to
Tiny ml. Tiny ml. A all throw low
power, technology that consumes mirror,
micro watts, tots of power enabling
months or years of operations on small.
Batteries or energy harvesting systems.
It is ideal for long-term
deployments in, remote environments.
Tiny ML dramatically compresses,
neural networks to function within
just a kilobyte of memory through
advanced techniques like, quantization,
pruning and, knowledge legislations.
It runs on microcontrollers with,
severely constrained resources, one
device interface process data, and,
Make intelligent decisions directly at
the source without, cloud dependencies,
eliminating latency, enhancing
privacy, and ensuring functionality
even in disconnected environments.
the technical foundation
of, tiny ml, right?
So the technical foundation of ML
involves several key components.
First, modern optimization techniques
like quantization, pruning, and,
Knowledge distillations are used
to compress neural networks.
This methods, reduce numerical
ions from 32 bit to eight bit or
lower while maintaining critical
accuracy thresholds for deployment.
Second, specialized frameworks like
tensor floor light for microcontrollers.
These, frameworks enable seamless,
deployment on several cons
constrained hardware with a little at.
2 56 KB of flash memory.
Third hardware acceleration.
In latest generation microcontrollers
units integrates dedicated
ML acceleration hardware.
These purpose build silicone
employment dramatically employ
interference speed by up to 10 times
while simultaneously reducing more
conception to the micro world range.
And, tiny ML development
workflow, the tiny ML development.
Workflow consists of four main steps.
First, data collection involves
gathering representative sensor data
that captures all essential edge cases.
This meticulously labeled dataset
creates the foundation for robust,
modern, like model performance.
Second model training involves a
development in shell neural networks
using powerful computing infrastructure.
Start with full precision,
architecture before beginning the
optimization, gen third optimization.
Transform model through
strategic quantitation pruning
and knowledge distillations.
This, critical phase reduces
modern requirement like, memory
requirement, to me kilobytes while
maintaining, functional, accuracy.
the fourth deployment integrates
optimization models into target,
microcontrollers, and verify
real world performance, carefully
balanced interference, speed,
power consumption, and accurate.
C for product prediction
readiness and the synergy.
Okay.
Edge computing and tiny ml
combining edge computing and
tiny ml offers several benefits.
Enhanced privacy is achieved
since to data remains on device.
Eliminating cloud secu, security
vulnerabilities and ensuring regulatory
complaints reduced latency is another
advantage with sub millisecond re.
Once time enabling real time applications
critical for autonomous systems and
time sense to monitoring lower bandwidth
is achieved as pre-processor insights.
Reduced network traffic by up to
90%, optimizing connectivity costs
and infrastructure requirements.
Finally, energy efficiencies enhanced
through specialized hardware,
accelerations, and optimized models
extending battery life or harvest
two months for I OT deployments.
Applic.
Applications across industries.
Each computing and tiny ml have
applications across various industries.
In healthcare, intelligent monitoring
device detects, critical patient
anomalies in, real time on device
algorithms enable instantaneous,
failed detection and lifesaving,
recognition without cloud connectivity
in agriculture, precision field sensors
continuously analyze soil moisture,
nutrition levels, and Camera conditions.
Automated irrigation systems
dramatically responds to environmental
changes, optimizing water usage
and crop fields In manufacturing,
advanced equipment monitors, utilize
vibration and acoustic signatures
to identify subtle failure patterns.
Data-driven pre predictive maintenance
algorithms prevent catastrophic
breakdowns, reducing downturn by
up to 70% in the consumer sector.
Sophisticated variables recognize complex
activities and health patterns with
medical grade accuracy, energy efficient
voice interference, understand natural
language commands, and maintaining
privacy by processing all data locally.
So with this, we have implementation
challenges as well, implementing
each computing and time comes
with several challenges.
Resource constraints are significant
issue with extreme limitations in memory
and processing power and energy capacity.
Restricting model complexity and
functionality model accuracy is another
challenge as balancing performance
State ops while maintaining acceptable
interference accuracy during aggressive
optimization process can be difficult.
Development complexity
requires, specialized expertise
in embedded systems Modern.
Magician and hardware specific
implementation techniques.
Security concerns are also prevent as
v vulnerable H device devices faces
increase risk where ADV attacks and
modern theft and privacy breaches
requiring robust protection mechanism.
So let's compare the technologies.
So we have cloud computing,
edge computing, and tiny.
Cloud computing process data in remote
data centers with latency ranging from
a hundred milliseconds, two seconds.
High power requirements in kilowatts,
constant connectivity needed, and a
typical memory in gigabytes or more
each computing process, data in local
gateways or servers with latencies
ranging from 10 to hundred milliseconds.
Moderate power requirements in wats,
intermediate connectivity needed
and difficult memory in megabytes.
Tiny ML process data.
On end devices with latency ranging
from one to 10 milliseconds, low
power requirements in milliwatts,
minimal or no connectivity needed,
and typical memory in kilobytes.
And let's see the future of
the edge, intelligence here.
So it includes several exciting trends.
Federated learning is a distributed
training architecture that enable
devices to collectively improve
models while presuming data.
Privacy and sovereignty.
Neuromorphic computing involves
biologically inspired process
architectures that mimic neurostructures
for unprecedented energy efficiency.
In ML workloads, energy harvesting
involves autonomous ml. Systems
that capture ambient energy from
surroundings enable perpetual
influence without battery replacements.
Tiny transformations are radically
compressed attention based.
That bring sophisticated language
understanding to resource constraint.
Micro,
thank you.
Thank you for your attention.
I hope you found this, presentation
on each computing and tiny email
inform me too and insightful.
If you have any questions,
feel free to reach out to me.
Thank you.