Hi, welcome to the conference.
Today I will be talking about
self-healing BLE networks
powering resilient iot at scale.
Introduction to self-healing BLE networks.
Today we are exploring a
transformative approach to
internet of things, specifically
self feeling Bluetooth networks.
In an increasing connected
world, we need networks.
That can automatically detect,
diagnose, and recover from fault
without human intervention.
The core concept is simple, yet
powerful, create intelligent network
that can maintain themselves.
BLE has emerged as an ideal
protocol for iot due to its low
power consumption and scalability,
but traditional approaches have.
Struggle to make these
networks truly resilient.
So let's talk about the growth and
importance of network resilience.
Let's talk.
Talk about the market dynamics,
the self-healing iot market is.
Predicted to expand dynamically
through 2030, driven primarily
by industrial sector adoption.
This isn't just technological
trends, it's a business imperative.
Critical industries like healthcare and
infrastructures are targeting 99% uptime.
That means less than an
hour of downtime per year.
A standard that demands
extraordinary network reliability
as an as enter, enterprises
develop IOT systems at mass scale.
We are talking thousands of
interconnected sensors and devices
that meets for advanced self-healing
protocol becoming crucial.
Current challenges in IOT networks,
the obstacles are significant.
Significant.
BLE devices are in currently
resource constrained with limited
processing capabilities and memory.
This restricts the complexity of
algorithms we implement, creating a
fundamental challenge in building in
intelligent network as networks grows.
Reliability become reliability
becomes exponential and more complex.
More nodes means more potential
points of failure leading to
unpredictable propagation patterns.
Traditional fault recovery methods
suffer from unacceptable latency
between detecting a fault and recovering
the network power consumption.
Add another layer of complexity
in field development.
Continuous network monitoring can rapidly
deplete battery services, making long-term
autonomous operation, challenging
our open source framework approach.
We.
We developed a comprehensive
solution addressing these challenges
through four key innovation.
First intelligent recovery.
We have implemented machine learning
based anomaly detection with
predictive healing capabilities.
This means not just detecting failure,
but anticipating and preventing them.
Second, a distributed architecture
that enables coordination.
Between local and network level healing
mechanism devices can make intelligent
autonomous decisions while contributing
to overall network resilience.
Third memory efficient design are
algorithms are purpose built for
resource constrained iot devices,
ensuring sophisticated fault recovery
mechanisms with minimal memory footprint.
Finally, we have leveraged modern
programming patterns that enables
advanced concurrent processing with
minimal computational overhead.
Next, let's talk about power
efficiency across operational states.
Our power optimized strategies cover
every network, operational state due.
During active scanning, we have
reduced power draw by 60 to 75, 70
5% through dynamic channel hopping
and adaptive duty cycle in connected
mode, optimized packet framing and
connection intervals tuning E 40%.
Energy saving.
Energy consumption.
Our fault detection mechanism uses
intelligent, threshold based monitoring,
reduces power spikes by 83% compared to.
Periodic pooling.
In standard mode, we have achieved
sub 10 point, sub 10 micro amp powers
consumption with a vehicle latency under
3.5 milliseconds for critical events.
Let's talk about the life weight
machine learning implementation.
What we have done here's our approach.
Becoming truly innovative, our machine
learning model models consume just
four kb of memory while achieving 95%
detection accuracy for network anomalies.
Instead of relying on external
service, each device conduct
local real-time analysis.
We have implemented a distributed
intelligence model where insights
are shared across the network
through federated learning,
ensuring continuous improvement.
Without compromising data privacy,
adaptive thresholds, and automatically
calibrate based on the environment,
conditions, and network traffic
dynamically reducing the false
positives while maintaining
the subsecond detection speed.
Let's talk about the
performance benchmark.
Now.
Our frameworks dynamically
outperform traditional approaches.
We have achieved 90% faster recovery times
triple battery life and improved packet
delivery reliability by 14%, all while
using only 25% of, memory of conventional
by using conventional methods.
Next, let's talk about the
architecture for scale.
Our architecture is designed to manage
complexity at unpredictable scale.
We can orchestrate thousands of BLE
device with zero touch provisioning
and automated firmware distribution.
Advanced scheduling algorithms allow
10 to 20 concurrent BLE connections
per gateway with minimal latency.
Arm meh coordination enables transparent
roaming with sub 50 millisecond handoff.
Between coverage zones, ensuring
uninterrupted operations.
Now let's talk about code
implementation and examples.
We have created a comprehensive
open source code base that delivers
production ready implementation of
BLE, connection management, anomaly
detection, power optimization, and
memory efficient package handling.
Our goal.
Is to solve the most challenging aspect
of resilient iot development with
minimal integration efforts, empowering
developers to build more robust networks.
So now let's talk about
the real world application.
Using these methods, let me illustrate our
framework impact across diverse scenarios.
In industry automation,
we have maintained.
We are maintaining 99.9% uptime.
Our mission critical equipments
monitoring is high interference and
in high interference environment.
Some cities, can now manage vast sensor
networks with self diagnosed capabilities
that reduces maintenance visits by 78%.
Healthcare monitoring benefits from
uninterrupted patient data streams
with redundant communication pathway,
smart building scan, integrate
climate control, security and energy
management through resilient mesh
networks that maintain operations
during connect connectivity challenges.
Next, let's start off, talk about
the key, takeaways and the next
steps and the future directions.
Modern programming has fundamentally
transformed network resilience.
We have proven that resource
constraint devices can implement, can
implement sophisticated self-healing
mechanisms without compromising
performance or battery life.
Machine learning is now
practical on low power devices.
Adaptive power management
techniques allows extended device
functionality without sacrificing.
Recovery times our reliability.
I invite you to join the
open source community.
Visit our A link to access our
implementation, contribute to the
project, and help us shape the
future of resilient iot networks.
Together we can build that doesn't just
connect, but heal, adapts and times.
Thank you.