Speaker: Hey.
Hey, everybody.
Today, I wanna talk about
vulnerability detection in Golang.
My name is Akshaya.
I am a security principal specializing in
M- mergers and acquisitions at Salesforce,
and I'm really excited to talk here today.
So all of us here know about Golang.
Golang n- needs no
introduction whatsoever.
What we love about Golang is its
versatility and how easy it is to deploy,
how easy it is to literally deploy across
architectures, across OSs, et cetera.
Even though that's very comfortable
on the developer experience, on the
deployment experience, it brings a
major blind spot on the security side.
The issue in, on the security side
is that because there's a single
compiler that deploys on multiple
architectures, the same vulnerability
detection is very difficult because
the same piece of code doesn't behave
the same way across architectures.
Some of the reasons for this is that
compilers, they alter the sequences
of code, and they alter the sequences
of convention, of calling conventions.
A lot of it has to do with
processing speeds and optimization.
Similarly, depending on what opt-
optimization flag is set, it can
dramatically change the control flow.
Architecture differences, they obscure
a lot of the semantic equivalence.
And then there is a lot of efficiency
that has to be built in on the newer
architectures, et cetera, et cetera.
So the list just goes on for the number,
for the cs- sheer amount of reasons
that vulnerability detection is hard.
The... All of this makes the ha- false
positives really high, and it takes
a lot of effort on the security side
to triage and to really get some form
of, trust when issues are raised.
So talking about the very first point
of cross-architecture issues, right?
The same code can be, can look
different, can behave as completely
different binaries, even though
the logic is exactly the same.
So this brings in a lot of structural
and syn- syntactic matching
technique fails that we'll be trying
to fill through this framework.
Traditionally, the way vulnerability
detection has happened on
binaries is through signatures.
But in this case, because the binaries
themselves look very different from
architecture to architecture The
signatures are not the same either.
So it is very hard to keep track of
signatures even by OSR architecture.
The semantic equivalence, the assembly
level code that looks that, that is built
per architecture again differs completely.
The syntactic awareness is different.
So there is a lot of difference
between the same piece of code
that runs across architectures.
So to solve this problem, I'm proposing
the attention-driven multi-fusion,
multi-feature fusion technique here.
What it is trying to do is to look at
the way the code runs, look at all of the
aspects of what makes the code vulnerable
before it, it make, it makes a decision on
whether the code is actually vulnerable.
So it picks up everything for a
specific type of vulnerability that
it could, that could contribute to the
fact, to that actual vulnerability.
And if it finds all of the necessary
behaviors, that is when it's gonna
call it a specific vulnerability.
If it finds some of it, it's
probably gonna downgrade it
by in the amount of severity.
But all of that logic is built
into this fusion technique.
So what happens here is that the first
step we have three layers of architecture.
The first layer is the semantic
architecture, the semantic embedding.
So what happens here is that
the code looks different.
Like I've said many times, the code
looks different on every architecture.
So what this embedding is gonna find
is to essentially look for all types
of any type of code or any type
of instruction set that resembles
what that vulnerability could be.
So if it was if it was some form
of out of bound exceptions or
something of that sort, right?
It's gonna look at and everything that
could relate to that type of issues,
and it's gonna find every piece of code,
every... By every piece of code, I mean
in the instruction set itself, it's gonna
find every piece of code, every piece of
instruction, and it's gonna surface it.
It's gonna surface it.
It's also gonna say, "This is the
category that we think this instruction
set, it falls under. This is this other
category," and it makes it, it makes
different categories and also tags them
based on what architecture they're on.
So the next step is the
most important step.
So in the first step, we
surfaced a lot of issues, right?
In the second step, what we are gonna
do is to look at the flow of the code.
Flow of the instruction set or
flow of the code to say that in
a specific type of vulnerability,
the code will flow a certain way.
It's not enough to find the actual
instruction set that's causing the
issues, because it could be that the
way a function is called multiple times
is the issue, or the way the f-logic
flows, or the way data is sent, variables
are sent from one function to the
other function could be the problem.
Understand the flow of the program so that
we can we can add more features to the
final decision, and we are able to make
accurate non-false positive detections.
So once we have a bunch of flows, the
way we had a bunch of em- semantic
embeddings in the previous architecture
layer, here we'll have a bunch of flows.
All of those flows are found by the
GRU technique and which actually does
specialize on sequential instructions.
Like the, that's a type of neural
network layer that actually specializes
in understanding the way code flows.
So once we have... Once GRU, you get a
list of you get a list of, this the flows.
Self-attention is used to
correlate as- the type of
vulnerability to the type of flows.
So it's able to look at the, how
this vulnerability traditionally
flows and is able to weigh itself
on whether this specific flow
fol-follows that detection flow or not.
Once it does that it, it gives
weightage to the different flows.
That and so this is for a single
block of code or a small subset
of code, bl- blocks of code.
But there are long-range dependencies that
involve calling functions, calling and
where the w- the logic for the vulnera-
vulnerability is actually distributed.
So that is again brought up.
So at the end of it, we have the
semantic stream, which is essentially
the whole instruction set with GRU.
We have the control flow stream.
Again, that is also with The control flow
graph of how the logic flows, and then
you have the function level logic, right?
Like how many arguments are passed, how--
where the arguments are positioned, how
many times is the behavior called, what
is the return put of that beha- function,
stuff like that, it is also picked up.
So then you have three sets of features
that are then used to determine how
much each stream contributes to the
final vulnerability detection, right?
So we are essentially... Once we
have these three streams, we are
gonna use weights to figure out
how much of this stream actually
contributes to the vulnerability.
So th- so once we have that of... Once
we have the similarity search, all of
that, we are gonna use control flow
grow- graph matching to say that this
is the actual structure, and we can
confirm that the vulnerability actually
looks like this, and anything that
doesn't look like this or flow like
this is actually a false positive.
While like I said in the previous
slide, there are two stages here, so
I'm gonna deep dive on both stages.
So the first stage, the what
happens is everything that
I spoke to you about before.
We are gonna find the embedding vectors.
We are gonna find s- m-m, add similarity
scores between each type of embedding.
This is gonna look at
the nearest neighbors.
This is gonna look at everything that
it could possibly find that could
contribute to a specific embedding type.
So wha- how this helps is to find
everything based even if it is if it is
different on every type of architecture,
it's able to go pick up everything
that could even be remotely similar
in a sp- specific type of architecture
that this was initially tested against.
So then we have the control
flow graph matching.
The control flow graph matching
compares the structural topology
and is able to examine all of the
sequences, the patterns, the branching,
everything, and is able to confirm
confirm the actual vulnerability.
Is a... By... What I
mean by that is specific
vulnerabilities run specific ways.
It is even if the
architecture differs, right?
They are gonna run more
or less the same way.
Even if it is, if if function one might
be called before function three, et
cetera, depending on the architecture.
But for the most part,
it flows a specific way.
Here we are gonna look at that sequence,
how it branches, et cetera, to define
from whatever was found in the previous
previous embedding stage to get a la-- to
get to remove false positives and really
we get, get to accurate predictions now.
So why it reduces false
positives is because the whole
structure acts as the verifier.
It compares the actual-- it compares
the structure to being as close to
the original architecture as possible.
So that way we know that we are not we
are not gonna rise more false positives.
So step one is u- is for bringing
everything to the surface, everything and
anything that could be even remotely the
the vulnerable code or anything that could
be contributing to the vulnerability.
Step two is to really drill, dr-
find the needle in the haystack.
So once the... So talking about
efficiency, because this runs only
on-- because this whole control
graph runs on the stage one, the
previous stage candidates, and not the
entire list of en-entire code-based
behavior, we're really saving on
computational overhead and performance.
Why does AMF-- AMMF matter
for Go-based systems?
Go-based systems have single
compli-compilers that can compile
across multiple architectures, right?
GoArch and Goose.
It's a natural fit for systems
that run on diverse hard hardware.
There are also AMFF, if it's AMMF
and especially GRU is very built
for these kind of use cases.
Like I've been saying in all of the
previous slides, we are targeting
accuracy across architectures, across
compilers, and acro-across optimizers.
So you can have architectures
between Arm, MIPS, et cetera.
But it looks at the instruction
set in all of these cases.
It could be GCC or Clang, it
still looks at the binary output.
It still, e-even if you have different
types of compilers, the end result
It looks at the instruction set or
it looks at the control flow graph.
So it doesn't matter what your
architecture is, what your compiler is.
Even for optimizers from O0 to O3,
it really doesn't matter because
the control flow might differ
a bit, even a little bit more.
But we are able to map what the control
flow should look like, and depending
on what the control flow is we are
able to semantically match, which gives
us very good, very accurate results.
So what does AMMF mean
for practitioners, right?
In all of this, if you had-- if the
single defining feature is the attention,
how attention is created, how attention
is drawn and focused at every single
layer, so that we are not trying to, we
are not trying to compare like a whole
lot of use cases versus we are able
to prioritize what our flow should be.
In stage one, we brought
up all of the issues.
In stage two, we really focused on
what could be the actual issue, hence
removing a lot of false positives.
This gives a lot of weightage
and a lot of-- removes a lot of
removes a lot of fatigue from
the actual vulnerability folks.
Cross-platform languages depend-- demand
cross-architecture security, right?
For cross-- For languages that power
many architecture types, we need
something like AMMF to actually produce
accurate results, to actually to produce
the, to ga-- bridge the gap between
audits and due diligence contexts.
AMMF is available for further
discussion, et cetera, et cetera.
Thank you.