Speaker 12: Hi, everyone.
My name is Shadi Riafi.
I'm a senior software developer
at fullinfo.com, and this talk is
about building an MCP server in
Go for a real, uh, B2B workflow.
The specific case I'll use in i- is a
company intelligence platform built on
more than one million company profiles.
The goal was to let an LLM client help
the, with real workflow task, such
as searching for companies, looking
for company details, and working with
collections without turning the LLM into
unsafe bridge into production systems.
The stack behind the talk is Go,
MCP, GraphQL, and AWS AppSync.
The main point is not only
how to connect these pieces.
The more important point is how
to keep the interface narrow,
testable, observable, and safe
enough for real business data.
Um, most MCP examples stop where
a demo becomes interesting.
A demo usually proves that a model
can call a tool, get a result, and
show the result back to the user.
That is useful, but
it's only the beginning.
The harder question is what happens
when the integration touch, touches
real business data, real workflows,
and real operational constraints.
At that point, a thin API
path through is not enough.
Broad tools become hard to validate.
Prompt-level guardrails are not enough.
And if there is a little visibility,
it becomes difficult to know what
the system is actually doing.
So to read it, the MCP server as a
production interface, that means narrow
contracts, a clear read and write split.
Backend authentication preserved,
and tests and logs that make
behavior understandable.
The user-facing workflow is simple.
A user might ask a question like,
"Find a SaaS companies in Germany with
fifty to th- to one hundred employees."
But the server should not pass the
raw sentence directly into GraphQL.
Instead, the LLM client selects a tool, in
this case, search companies, for example.
The MCP server validates the inputs,
normalizes them, and shapes the request.
And only then does it call GraphQL
through AppSync behind the authentication.
The result comes back as flat
company summarize, summaries, not
as a raw nested backend response.
The separation is important.
User requests are normalized into explicit
tool calls, and the MCP server never pass
raw user input directly to the GraphQL.
This is the architecture at high level.
Like Cloud or another MCP client,
whatever, handles, handles the
user intent and tool selection.
The Go MCP server sits in the middle
and acts as a contract enforcing layer.
It uses MCP Go for dispatch,
schemas, validation, mutation,
gating, and response shaping.
Behind that, AWS AppSync
remains the GraphQL boundary
into a s- business backend.
The company intelligence platform
stays the system of record.
Cloud never talks to GraphQL directly.
This distinction matters
more than protocol itself.
MCP provides the connection model,
but the production question is how
much power each tool gets and how
precisely its behavior is defined.
Authentication is also part
of the server boundary.
The server can authenticate to
AppSync with OIDC bearer token
and app key or AWS Sigv4 signing.
Depending on the environment, AppSync
is AWS managed GraphQL gateway, so
the query body stays standard GraphQL
while the auth headers vary by mode.
For the production-oriented path, OIDC
is, is the important model because token
carries user id-- us- user identity.
The LM client is acting on behalf
of the user or of a specific user,
not as a generic service account.
That means backend authorization,
audit trails, and data scoping
work the same way they would if the
user were calling the API directly.
The MCP layer does not bypass or weaken
the existing access model, it inherits
it.
Uh, the practical rule is simple.
Keep credentials and signing inside
the MCP server boundary and let
AppSync enforce backend authorization.
The implementation defines nine
tools, and eight are exposed
in the shipped configuration.
The read-only tools cover the
company search, single company
lookup, batch lookup, AI-assisted
search, lis- listing collections,
and reading collections items.
The exposed mutation-capable
tools are added to collection
and request e- email discovery.
These are right-side actions,
so they are handled differently.
The ninth tool cre-- the ninth tool,
Create Collection was implemented
but not exposed One tool was
held back and slide 15 shows why.
It passed mocked unit level tests,
but when validated against the real
backend through MCP inspector, it
revealed a lambda null pointer failure.
The release choice was to keep
the implementation but remove
the tool from registration until
the backend issue was fixed.
This is a good example why real
system validation must remain
part of the release gate.
The separation between read and
write starts in the registry.
Read-only tools are constructed
without the mutation flag because
they have no mutation path to gate.
Mutation-capable tools receive
the explicit allow mutations flag.
This makes the design
easier to reason about.
A read-only tool is simpler to review,
simpler to test, and simpler to observe
because it expresses one kind of intent.
It cannot accidentally become
a write path because mutation
capability was never passed into it.
For mutation tools, the flag
becomes an operational switch.
Without it, the tool fails
before doing any backend work.
For the read path, the important point
is that validation, execution, and
shaping are handled by distinct layers.
The tool starts with a row
arguments from the MCP call.
Those are passed into type parameters,
validation checks required, fields.
Normalization handles things
like trimming input, resolving
country codes, and capping limits.
Then the tool builds a GraphQL variables
map and calls the AppSync client.
After the GraphQL returns, the response
is flattened into a public result type
before it goes back to the LLM client.
So the MCP server never passes raw
user input directly to GraphQL.
And it never returns raw
GraphQL responses to the client.
Scale changes the behavior
of even simple tools.
This platform has more than 1
million companies' profiles.
A broad query can produce results that
are technically valid but not useful.
So the search tool had to
be bounded from the start.
For example, if the user does not
provide a limit, default is 10.
If the user asks for more than 100
results, the server cap it at 100.
Country inputs are normalized too.
So DE becomes a backend value for
Germany and US becomes the backend
value for the United States.
Even with a hard limit of 100
results, broad requests can be too
broad to be useful and can compound
through follow-up queries that
where normalization is a production
concern, not just a convenience.
The backend GraphQL response is
naturally shaped for the backend
domain, not for the LLM client.
For example, company data can be
nested under company model, company
description, and text fields.
That might be fine inside the
service boundary, but it's not the
best shape to return to a model.
So the tool returns a consint-
consistently shaped record, ID,
name, country, employee range,
domain, and industry text.
For search and retrieval
tools, explicit conversion
functions handle the flattening.
This reduces accidental field
confusion for the LLM client.
It also makes the testing easier because
the output contract is stable and narrow.
Mutation safety uses a default deny model.
The add to collection tool checks
whether mutations are allowed before it
validates fields or class calls GraphQL.
If that flag is not enabled, it returns
a clear error, mutations are disabled.
Use the allowMutations flag.
This is a full... It is not
a full authorization model.
Backend authorization still belongs
in the backend, but it is an
effective operational control point.
It forces the team to make deliberate
decision about whether write paths
are available in a given environment.
It changes the default question.
Instead of asking, "Why not let the client
write?" The team has to answer, "What
evidence make these writes paths safe?"
The mutation gate was
developed test first.
The test constructs the add to collection
tool with mutation disabled, calls
execute, and then assert three things.
It expects an error, it expects no result,
and most importantly, it asserts that
the mock GraphQL client was never called.
The last assertion is
the real safety check.
It proves the guard happens
before any backend execution path.
This is the TDD loop in practice.
Failing test, guard
implementation, passing assertion.
The value is not just the code works, the
value is that the contract is preserved
by a test that will fail if someone later
moves the GraphQL call before the gate.
This is also where Go helped.
The MCP layer introduces its own
failure modes, weak validation,
unclear tool semantics, poor error
handling, or mismatches between tool
behavior and backend assumption.
Go's ordinary server Service
patterns made those boundaries
explicit instead of magical.
The interface shown here
is deliberately small.
Execute takes a context, a query string,
a variable map, and a result point.
That context can carry cancellation and
deadlines into the AppSync HTTP call.
The same small client interface
supports mock tool tests
and real AppSync execution.
Type parameters also matter.
The tool handler parses raw MCP arguments
before building GraphQL variables.
That gives tests a clean place to check
validation, normalization, and request
shape before the backend is touched.
Mock tests become... Mock tests
became much more valuable once
they captured the actual GraphQL
variables sent by each tool.
In this example, the mock records
the variable pa-path to execute.
After the tool runs, the test can check
the limit capping happening, the country
code resolution happened, and that
the backend variable shape is correct.
This matters because bugs in normalization
are easy to miss if the tests only
check the resu-result come back.
A mock response can make the
test pass even when the tool
send the wrong variables.
By capturing the result, a request
shape, the test checks the contract
between m-the MCP layer and, and the
AppSync, not only in the final response.
Mocked unit tests cannot substitute
for validation against the real system.
The best example was createCollection.
At the unit level, the tool behavior
looked fine, but the MCP ex-inspector
let us, let us issue tool calls over
STD before involving the LLM client.
Against the real AppSync
endpoint, they revealed a backend
Lambda null pointer failure.
The release decision was straightforward:
keep the code, but not register
the tool in the ship configuration.
That is the kind of failure that
a mock is not expected to catch.
The lesson is not that mocks are bad.
The lesson is that mock tests and real
system validation answer different
questions and are bo-and both are needed.
Rate limited-- limiting also
needed upfront design because LLM
workflows are conver-conversational.
A user might ask a question, then
ask a follow-up, then refine again.
A model may make several
tools calls in a short period.
If the tool is expensive,
the loop can become a backend
protection issue very quickly.
So AI search is limited to five
requests per minute Request email
discovery is limited to ten requests
per hour because it represents a
more expensive write set operation.
These limits are not only backend
protection, they are also LLM
loop protection because they
keep conversational follow-up
bursts from turning into
uncontrolled backend activity.
Useful error responses are not the
same thing as operational telemetry.
For version one, I kept the
operational surface small but visible.
The server records useful startup
information, such as auth mode,
mutation flag state, and tool count.
It also had type GraphQL errors
and explicit rate limit errors.
Per-tool request logs, latency,
input shape, output, and, and
error type are next layer.
I would add those before expanding
the number of write-capable workflows
because they make it easier to understand
how the MCP layer behaves over time.
This is especially important because
the MCP server is not just transport.
I-if it shapes user-facing behavior,
you need to be able to see what it does.
The recommendation from
these projects are practical.
Start by assuming the MCP layer
is a first-class interface.
Design narrow tools.
Separate read and write behavior early.
Resist optimizing first for flexibility,
because broad, flexible tools are
harder to validate and easier to misuse.
Block mutations by default.
Keep authentication inside
the server boundary.
Validate with mocks, then
validate with real backend.
And treat logging and
auditability as a baseline
requirements, not optional polish.
The main lesson is that
production-friendly MCP work is less
about exposing many capabilities
quickly and more about preserving
clear contracts as capabilities grow.
To close the path, I would
recommend this simple.
Start with one narrow read tool.
Make the input contract explicit.
Add one default deny mutation
only when the read paths are
already as understandable.
Test the actual request shape,
not only the final response.
Then validate the real backend
before connecting the LLM client.
For me, the core lesson is this.
Make the interface narrow,
observable, testable, and safe
enough for real workflows.
This is what turns an- the MCP
server for a d- from a demo wrapper
into a production interface.
Thank you.