Hello, my name is Sanjay.
I'm honored to be part of con,
so today I'm presenting
integration cloud computing.
So especially challenges,
solutions and ethical frameworks.
So the fusion of artificial
intelligence with cloud computing
is transforming industries
globally, creating unprecedented
opportunities and challenges.
So with AI cloud market growth,
reaching 11.2 billion in 23
and growing at 35.6% annually.
So organizations are rapidly
adopting these technologies.
So this presentation explores the
key challenges ordinations face when
integrating AI with cloud systems
provides evidence-based solutions to
overcome these barriers, and emphasize
the importance of ethical frameworks
in ensuring sustainable growth,
the key challenges of our secondary
challenges in AI cloud system.
The security stands as the
foremost obstacle to widespread
a adoption in cloud environments.
So, yeah.
Yeah, allowing 18% of our nations
have experienced SA security
instance while 78% struggle with
data privacy vulnerabilities,
particularly when sensory information
is processed by AI systems in cloud.
So the risk landscape is
further complicated by.
The fact that 71% of our nation lack
sufficient automated securely tools
to address these threats effectively.
So the model production emerges as
another critical vulnerability with
65% of our nations reporting concerns.
These valuable AI assets become
suspectable to theft, reverse engineering,
and sophisticated adverse attacks
when deployed in cloud environments.
Meanwhile, 42% of our
nations face complaints.
Violence is highlighting that,
regulatory challenges that the
company AA cloud integration.
So coming to.
Solution advanced production mechanisms.
So with the mplementation of homomorphic
encryption enables AI systems to process
fully encrypted data without decryption
preserving privacy toward the
entire computational pipeline.
So this breakthrough technology
has demonstrated a 92% direction
in privacy breaches violating
sensor data in ex exposure duty.
Processing cycles.
The next secure entails establishes
hardware isolated execution
environments for AI workloads,
safeguarding both proprietary
models and the data being analyzed.
So organization implementing secure
and clear architecture report.
And exceptional 99.99% effectiveness
rate in defending air models diagnos
against sophisticated adverse attacks.
So with federated learning facilitators,
distributed model training across
decentralized device without consolidating
since two data in cloud repositories.
So this innovative approach has decreased
data vulnerability exposure by 87%.
While maintaining model performance
within 3% of traditional
centralized training methodologies.
So these sophisticated security
frameworks directly addresses the
most significant vulnerabilities in AI
cloud integration ecosystem, empowering
automations to deploy advanced data
systems with enhanced confidence under
streamlined regulatory compliance.
The next challenge, operational
complexities in a cloud systems.
So, so the operate op operational
complexity, especially with
the integration challenges.
So 82% of enterprise and quantums
sustainable technical debt when
matching legacy systems with cutting
edge, a cloud zone resulting.
In extended timelines and compromise
scalability potential, the next market,
64% of organizations face significant
hurdles in tracking AI model performance
across distributed cloud environments,
so leading to diminish service quality
and undetected drift over time.
The next deployment barriers
seven 3% of DevOps teams in.
And maintaining consistent deployment
pipelines for AI workloads in
complex multi-cloud ecosystems.
So, so the operational complexities
are orchestrated AI within
cloud environments, transfer and
initial implementation hurdles.
Organizations must navigate
ongoing integration challenges,
sophisticated monitoring requirements,
and deployment complexities.
That collectively have the full
realization of as transformative
potential in business operations.
So the operational solution,
streamlining a AI cloud integration.
So implementing service mesh
just delivers a 92% implement in
service discovery, liability, and
reduces interservice communication.
LA Agency by 78.
For AI workloads.
So this sophisticated approach establishes
a dedicated infrastructure layer that top
images and secure all service to service
communications within AI cloud ecosystem.
The next monitoring automations,
leveraging AI systems to monitor
the air deployment experience.
A 43% reduction in operational cost
alongside 67% faster anomaly detection.
So this intelligent meta AI system
practically identify performance
degradation and model drift patterns
before they impact production
environments on end users.
Next.
Infrastructure As Code ISC, the
Enterprise Enterprises implementing ISC
pathologies for AI deployments achieve
1800% faster provisioning cycles and
reduce configuration errors by 64%.
So this programmatic approach enables
consistence, reproducible, and virtual
control deployments across heterogeneous
cloud environments, eliminating
manual configuration inconsistencies.
So these strategic operational
solutions directly address the
fundamental challenges of managing
AA within cloud ecosystems.
Empowering organizations, so,
uh, empowering organizations to
achieve unprecedented level of
reliability, operational efficiency,
and seamless scalability throughout
their AA deployment lifecycle.
The next ethical considerations
in EA cloud company computing,
especially there are some fairness.
The transparency.
Transparency in addition, making the
environmental impact, the privacy
of sense to get out Accountability.
So the ethical dimensions of air
deployment in cloud environments
transfer via technical considerations,
so organizations that neglect robust
ethical frameworks, risk implementing
systems that discriminate against
vulnerable populations, compromise
personal privacy or function as black.
IMP black boxes.
That meaningful scrutiny.
Addressing these ethical challenges
represents not only a moral
imperative, but increasingly a
strategic business necessity.
As regulatory landscapes evolve on
stakeholder expectations, mature
organizations that prioritize responsibly
a practices gain complicated advantages.
Through enhance trust, reduce
reduced competencies and sustain
social license to operate.
So coming to ethical Solutions
framework for responsibility.
So automation, implementing systematic
bias testing across diverse demographic
groups have achieved percent in
metrics on 56% reduction financially.
Discriminate outcomes, an extra.
The expandable ai, the implementation
of cybersecurity XIA techniques has
an enhanced model transparency by
87% and elevated user trust by 64%.
Right?
So ethical review boards, the company's
established dedicated cross-functional
a ethics committees demonstrate
net 0.8% regulatory complaints.
And experienced 70% fewer public
relations channels related to AI planets.
So a robust ethical framework seamlessly
integrates technical safeguards with
comprehensive governance structure
to ensure responsibly AI deployment
throughout the entire lifecycle.
So organizations that strategically
prioritize ethical considerations,
not only mitigate operational under.
Reputational risks, but circulate
to it, but also cultivate
enduring trust with customers,
partners, regulators, and product
case study, the financial services AI
cloud transformation with challenge.
So entire global bank struggled with a 43%
increase in sophisticated fraud attacks.
Awis average customer
response, strength on demand
regulatory, their fragmented legacy
and vouchers could not support
advanced AMLs without exposing critical
vulnerabilities in data production.
So implementation.
So the bank are, uh, zero.
Trust A cloud platform incorporated.
It's one 40 MOREOR encryption for real
time data analysis without decryption,
so it still service for service.
Secure microservices, orchestration
and and ethical a governance framework
with automated data objection across
37 demographic variables, which results
fraud detection accuracy improved by 18%
while reducing false false tools by 60%.
Customer response times drop from
to two minutes and page 19.7 bucks.
So the bank actually a validated
2 87 within three years while
maintaining technic a transparency
scores about industry benchmarks.
So this transformation creates how
financial institutions can effectively
navigate the complex challenges of.
AI Cloud integrations while
simultaneously addressing security
vulnerabilities, operational
inefficiencies and ethical considerations.
So by implementing a comprehensive
technical and governance approach, the
bank not only delivered quantifiable
performance implements, but also
strengthen the customer trust,
established a and established a leadership
position in responsible AI deployment.
Future trends in integration.
So quantum AI computing, so quantum
computing will fundamentally transform
AI capabilities by tracking complex
problems on unprecedented speeds by the
name quantum enhanced emission planning
algorithm have already demonstrated
1 94 x performance improvements
ion task critical to financial
modeling and pharmaceutical research.
Edge Cloud hybrid models.
A seamless integration between edge
and cloud AI process is creating
distributed intelligence networks
without additional borders.
So organizations implementing Edge
Cloud hybrid architecture experience 6%
latency and power conversion, augmenting
centralized management capabilities.
The next self-improving a s systems.
So the emergence of AA systems
capable of autonomously enhancing data
algorithms and that are shipped in
Comput, early prototypes have proven
their ability to optimize cloud resource
location of percent percent more
effectively than export human engineers.
So these transformative trends will
reshape the AI cloud ecosystems.
Unlocking unprecedented opportunities
while introducing sophisticated
challenges in governance, security,
and ethical implementation.
So organizations that strategically
prepare for these development will gain
competitive advantages in the next.
Digital transformation.
The final takeaway
Successfully integration
with cloud competing demands.
A strategic three tire approach
addressing critical security,
operational, and critical dimensions.
So automations must for
established a robust security
rob, robust security foundation, which
advance encryption and federated.
Build operational excellence
through modern architectural
practices, and finally implement
rigorous ethical governance to
ensure responsible AI deployment.
So this comprehensive pyramid
approach enables Orions to maximize
the transformative benefits of AI
cloud synergy driving operational
efficiency, enhancing data driven
mission making, and creating
sustainable competitive advantages.
So while effectively.
Mitigating risks and cultivated
last trust among customers,
regulators, and stakeholders.
So Ali, thank you.
Thank you all.