Hello everyone.
Today we're gonna go through some of
the cloud data engineering, aspects.
and I'm gonna walk you through
a couple of challenges.
couple of latest innovations and how
cloud data engineering is transforming,
businesses across globally, and
what are some of the benefits that
typically, businesses would see,
in terms of, moving into the cloud.
Data engineering side of things,
Mainly the cloud data engineering
is it's also driving innovation by
enabling organizations to manage data
efficiently and cost effectively.
So let's take multiple
platforms that we have today.
So we have AWS, we have
GCP, we have Azure.
we also have several platforms that are
built on top of, these different cloud
platforms like, snowflake, Databricks.
One of the very good examples
that we could also consider is
Netflix, as a, very good use case.
So the kind of, so organizations
like Netflix, they basically,
exemplify the cloud data engineering
potential by delivering, highly
personalized content experiences
to millions of users worldwide.
And they also very efficiently
manage the data streams.
by leveraging the cloud technologies.
So you would've already known that
architecture for Netflix is, it basically
runs on a. That's, that, that is
something that kind of helped Netflix
to maintain that industry leadership
by quickly adapting to the, consumer
trends, latest technology, maintaining,
a serverless kind of an architecture.
so they were able to reduce the
amount of investment that has to be
done from a physical hardware and
then just have everything to cloud.
so that is, That is one very good
example of how an organization has really
transformed, by moving away from the
on-premises, hardware and then having
the data completely, residing in cloud.
So without any delay,
let's get started with.
some of the, the challenges, what
we typically see with the data on
a day-to-day basis, what is the
whole cloud data engineering about?
And, what do we, Where do we stand today?
Right across globally.
So if you look at some of the
metrics here, that I have, so
approximately 463 million terabytes
of data generated globally.
and this data could be from
various sources like video,
text, audio, streaming content.
It could be.
various number of, sources.
As you can see, it's four 63
million terabytes and this continues
to grow exponentially, right?
So this data explosion challenges racial
data management methods, prompting
businesses to seek advanced cloud
solutions for effective data handling.
the global cloud computing market
is predicted to reach around 2.84
trillion by 2030, which is Less than
a decade, like half of a decade.
to be, to put it precisely, this
kind of highlights, this urgent
demand for robust data solutions.
we, with the recent, trend or with
the recent, increase in the usage of
social media like, Twitter, Facebook,
Instagram, TikTok, all of these
different platforms, they they widely
demonstrate this, data exposure.
They generate and process
vast amounts of data.
and it could be on a daily basis, on
an hourly basis, it would basically
go on what's basically trending.
the data would exponentially increase
within an hour or within a day.
and also, that is just one,
given use case of how, the social
media platforms react to it.
But we do also have like several.
healthcare industries, that kind of
heavily rely on the cloud technologies
to manage, the different patient
records, apply some AI on top of
it to, AI and as well as big data.
AI has recently started, but I wanted
to emphasize both on the AI and the
big data side of things where most of
the patient records are managed very
efficiently and also, there are very,
There are many predictive analytics or
predictive, applications that kind of,
help to improve the patient outcomes
and also the swim and the operations.
Now, the other business plan that
we're gonna talk about is also
on the financial institutions.
they also depend on several cloud
solutions to detect the, real
time, fraud, risk management, and
also the transaction processing.
So let's take an example for one of the
large scale organization like Capital
One, which has a huge, very huge, base or
AWS as we went through three different,
business lines, healthcare, financial,
and as well as social media, this kind
of ex extends across multiple sectors.
What I have given is only a
bunch of examples and sample.
Kind of bunch of examples, but
it extends to multiple sectors.
this would basically import
the organizations to turn
data into actionable insights.
maybe they could build some dashboards.
They could, build some analytics, or they
could, build an application such a way
that takes a preventive action against
it, Making the decision effectively
and driving the innovation as well,
in wherever, areas as applicable.
So that is the main reason why embracing
the cloud technologies becomes like really
critical for businesses that kind of
seek, sustainable growth and operation
efficiency in a data driven organization.
so most of the organizations, I
would say, In the recent times,
even if you take the large Fortune
500, most of them are data-driven.
I think that's how, most of the,
large scale enterprises are expected
to be seen, that they're data driven.
and that's.
That's where the whole operational
efficiency and everything comes into play.
Now, let's also, take, go through
in the next slide on how, we wanted
to see infrastructure aspects of it.
Like how this whole
thing had started, right?
So we.
When we go back to the old days, it was
basically when, even within mar, within
modernization, if I were to procure
a Linux server, someone has to build
a vblock for it, allocate some memory
for it, there's a human effort that is
technically involved in such a situation.
it could take anywhere from,
four weeks to eight weeks, right?
For a fiscal infrastructure to happen.
Now, when this whole cloud computing
has started, the infrastructure
as a code, can, revolutionized
how, infrastructure can be.
so it the traditional infrastructure
management by providing, automated
infrastructure provisioning.
Through programmable scripts
like Terraform for an example.
So Terraform primarily focuses on,
having the infrastructure as a code,
automating the builds and everything.
So it, the main good part or the,
the revolution that infrastructure
as a code has really brought in.
It would really transform how, businesses
manage it, resources, implementing.
ISC would also reduce the need to
physically deploy something, the amount
of time that is needed to deploy and
also minimize the number of configuration
errors or, human error from mistakes.
Now, there could be some situations where.
When someone is doing the ISE
code, basically, someone could
make a programmatic mistake, but
then that's where we, we could
basically do some peer reviews.
we can basically have some checks
against what we are trying to do
and then basically determine, detect
all of these issues beforehand.
another example is also
the A Ws cloud formation.
enabling enterprises worldwide to automate
consistent infrastructure deployments
effectively across multiple environments.
when, if we go back to the previous
slide where I was talking about Netflix.
So Netflix similarly utilizes
ISC to manage, thousands of cloud
servers globally, because it's not.
It's not truly possible when you
have a bunch of servers that are
lying across globally in different
regions, in different zones.
and, keeping a tab of them unless
it is truly automated and is truly,
code driven, which is the IAC.
Now, it also helps to significantly,
enhance the disaster, recover
capabilities, reduces the system downtime.
And fosters better collaboration
among, technical teams.
So one good example that I can
provide is, in our organization
at least, we have basically seen
a use case where, the most of the
infrastructure code is already ready.
We would just prepare a J and
submit the J to the code and it
would build out a server for us.
so that's truly the innovation of how
infrastructure as code has brought in.
That's truly a revolution that really
happened when we go back in time and look
at how traditionally things were done
versus how infrastructure as a code has
evolved over a period of time right now.
Let's talk about, modern
data pipeline architecture.
so for the Modern Data Pipeline
architecture, we know we have
like different forms of, data.
we have different forms of, data formats.
e either it could be CSV, it could be,
xml, it could be Jason, The very beginning
need, to look at the data pipeline, side
of aspects is, to consider that, we would
have to efficiently process different
types of, different types of data formats,
getting in this set on a continuous basis.
So let's go through a couple of
examples where, I can walk you through.
Excuse me, I can walk you through a very
good example of, data tion and as well
as, the processing, the transformation,
the storage, the storage optimization,
the analytics under consumption.
So let's take one single
platform as an example.
So I wanna pick Snowflake for the purpose
of our, When we start developing, a
Snowflake application, we would need
an underlying cloud, storage platform.
Let it be A-W-S-G-C-P or Azure.
It doesn't really matter.
but for our discussion, we
are gonna consider a Ws.
If I have five different, applications
that are dumping data into an SL
bucket, which are of different data
types, and I want to build something
that would technically, processes the
data in a real time format, right?
So that is where all of this
data would essentially come in,
as real time as possible from.
diverse sources, with scaling
opportunities and capabilities as well.
now, the.
the data that has coming through as
part of the data inges that has to be
processed, that has to be transformed.
so we would apply whatever, business
logic or implementation that is applicable
and we would basically go about,
running transformations accordingly.
Now, that is one very
good advantage of how.
cloud data or cloud data engineering
solutions will help us as we are
not restricted to any compute.
We would, basically have a lot of
autoscaling, autoscaling of the warehouse
size, autoscaling of the instant size.
So we are not worried truly about,
okay, I'm gonna hit about a, 50
million users within the next minute.
Now I have an on-prem infrastructure,
I don't think my on-prem
infrastructure is gonna handle.
So we would technically procure another
three or four different servers and then
just have them idle setting out there.
But in the case of cloud, the instances
would autoscale to whatever size it needs
to be scaled, like from extra small to
an extra large in the event the demand
increases and then scale back down.
So end of today, the main goal, is
to bring in business efficiency in
terms of how we are operating it
and if the scalability brings, the
bridge between, the user demand
and the business efficiency.
I think that itself, the cloud data
engineering, from Ws as an example.
It does a great job.
that's a real benefit and advantage of,
the modern data architecture pipeline.
Now we are also gonna talk
about storage optimization.
So storage optimization, technically,
there is no retention period.
There is no cleanup that
automatically happens on an on-prem.
storage systems.
So typically we would end up doing
like just store the stale data over
and over a period of time and there's
no controls or restriction around it.
So that is one big drawback of,
having an, having an on-prem
system, but then with the cloud
data engineering, with a multi-tier
architecture, we could have that
automated data movement, by looking at.
some of the patterns that
are really impacted, and.
the most important thing is the analytics
and the consumption of the data.
So we could get like different sources
of data, kind of data transform,
have, business logic applied to it.
feed the data into a Power BI dashboard
or any analytics dashboard, that we, that
whatever the enterprise, plans to use it.
And then technically
generate analytics out of it.
So this would also reduce, the need for
writing custom scripts or custom data.
So in, if I were to go back in time
and basically see, someone would have
to write a custom script to basically
see, to generate those charts and
for analytics and to run SQL queries
or, run any kind of data operations.
The data analytics is gonna really play
important and crucial role, especially
for the financial organizations.
As I mentioned, a use case earlier.
So it's gonna truly bring
out a lot of, value add.
No, elastic scalability benefits.
as I was talking about the scalability
in the previous slide as well, I'm
gonna, cover this quickly because, went
through a little bit deep previously.
resource optimization, having the
dynamic allocation, ensuring the
perfect resource to workload matching.
There is the Netflix use
case I was talking about.
the users can increase
in any minute going from.
A hundred users to a million users.
So the resource optimization is
the prime benefit of, having the
scalability within a cloud data pipeline.
and there's also a significant
reduction in cost because the
most of the instances are all.
On demand.
so technically we could scale back
to the lowest server as possible.
And for most part, all of the servers
are like very, pretty high available.
they have a very good availability,
because, most of the cloud platforms
have a dual zone, a deployment, a setup.
like for example, if I have a server in
US East, I would also have AA in West.
If the, in the US East goes down
a, that is really and readily.
To, to switch over the region
and then give that seamless
experience to the user, right?
So those are mainly the
elastic scalability benefits.
Now, we're gonna go through some of
the, mission learning, operations,
and how ML lops acceleration can be
achieved through the cloud data pipeline.
in a typical machine learning, application
or, the lifecycle, we would need to
have, a model that we would develop.
the model would be continuously,
improved upon based on user
feedbacks and user inputs.
We would also have to do some, monitoring
around it, to track if the model is
deviating from any kind of responses.
ability to do the continuous integration.
let's say, let's take a use case
where I just want to get, some data
generated through machine learning.
technically what are the,
different steps that we go through.
We need a model.
it has, the model has to be developed
and it, it has to be developed, it has
to evolve, it has to grow, and it has
to get the feedback that it needs to get
for the model to operate efficiently.
Then we would go into the
continuation, sorry, continuous
integration aspect where, it'll be
integrated into multiple sources.
And also we would also enable like
automated testing, which will basically
improve the model sufficiency and
quality and the, reproducibility Then.
The deployment of the model itself.
Now, typically, as with any other
software lifecycle, we would have a test
environment and a deploy environment.
And the deployment deploy environment or
the production environment and production
environment is something that we truly
really, roll it out to the users.
So that's, that's a deployment.
And the monitoring, of course, how
the model is behaving, how does
it act in terms of the different,
data flows that are coming in.
So how does this all tie
up to the, cloud data?
Engineering as a whole is basically
most of the cloud platforms today.
Right now, they have inbuilt
integrated, ML ops capabilities.
So ML lops is an area where it is
combining the machine learning and
the operation software together.
So it gives a great deal of,
advantage, for folks who are truly
interested with the lops, development
or, defining the morals as such.
Now, as, as much as everyone
would be interested in moving to a
serverless architecture with less
maintenance and everything, the other
main aspect that also truly really
plays a role is how secure is, are
these cloud environments, right?
because we are truly relying on, based
on the consumer versus a producer
or if something's developed inhouse
as well, we depending upon, not
in-house, which is, which could be
the case for an on-prem environment,
but we depending over the cloud,
which could be a third party provider.
Now that, that kind of brings in,
a very good, aspect of discussion,
which is about the security.
Now we could basically have, A
couple of options here, that we
could expand upon how the cloud
security can be, enforced, can be
made resilient and can be made better.
So one of them is being, is the
AI powered threat detection.
we could develop like machine learning
algorithms that basically identify and
as well as neutralize the accuracy,
reducing, the security breaches.
So typically, the model or the machine
learning algorithm gets fed of all the
different possible, scenarios around the
different threats that are really for,
the different threats that could occur.
and the model is continuously monitoring
the security, The model or the application
would continuously monitor the threats
and the application with as much
maximum accuracy as possible, thereby
reducing the security breach, right?
And the second option is we could
follow a zero trust architecture.
this is basically for a strict, very,
strict identity verification for every
user and device, regardless of network
permission or resource location.
we have, two form factor authentication,
multi-form factor authentication.
we have pink fed rate authentication
where users would get an immediate
notification whenever they're trying
to access any, any network objects
or any different application.
and every time.
Whenever user to login, it is
always, continuously authenticating
based on Based on the requirements
set by the organization.
So that is where the zero trust,
architecture comes into play.
And then the third aspect is
the compliance automation.
these are the intelligent systems
that kind of continuously monitor,
document, and also enforce regulatory,
requirements across multiple jurisdictions
with minimal human intervention.
So I'll give a classic example of how this
gets played in a financial institution.
Institutions such as, post
trade brokerages or, post
event reporting organizations.
They basically have a very huge
need to comply with the regulator
laws and the regulator requirements.
often when we are sending the data
back, to the regulators, it has to
be continuously, the, sent back in
a, continuous feedback loop and.
For most part, the regulators would
ask for, how strong the security of
the application is, how strong the
network is, and things like that.
So this also falls under that compliance
automation thing where we could
build some intelligent systems that
kind of take care, of, identifying,
the, the cloud data pipeline.
Now moving on to the next one,
we're gonna talk about the
inclusion storage management.
So with the storage management, for a
traditional storage, we would just, have
a solid state device sitting somewhere
on a rack, on a V block or something.
But, in the case of the
cloud platforms, it.
Falls under different
brackets or different ways.
So there could be auto
tiering of the data.
the data can be classified into different
deals, something that would change
frequently, something that would be
stagnant for a longer period of time.
or something that is like a hybrid.
most of the modern cloud
platforms leverage the storage
optimization techniques, that
significantly reduce the cost while
improving the performance, right?
as I was saying, if some data is prone to
change pretty frequently and we don't need
the data or a period of time, we could
set up retention policies against that.
if we need some data to be available
for a very long extended period of time,
let's say two years or three years,
like a classic example of Netflix,
that is where we could use, glaciers
Glacier type of storage, where, the
costs are significantly, low, but it
is not highly performant or anything.
that's one of the catch that
typically that we'll have to
keep in mind while dealing with,
long retention data timeframes.
Now, if you look at the whole graph
here, that I'm showing, the data
basically demonstrates how implementing
a comprehensive, optimization strategy,
combining audit, hearing compression, and
as well as intelligent data placement.
It would effectively reduce 30% of
the cost reduction when compared
rotation storage approaches.
So this would also increase the data
accessibility and the performance as
I was stating earlier, based on the
use case, what we're trying to do.
it, it is really important on, how
we structure, how we tier it and
how we, so that all comes into play.
We're gonna look at some of the
computing advancements, especially
the edge computing advancements.
Now let's look at a
couple of aspects here.
before the edge computing the
data, travel long distances to
centralized cloud infrastructure.
there used to be a very high
latency, that compromise real-time
applications, so bandwidth
constraints, limited scalability,
and transmission costs primarily.
Now after the Edge implementation, every
single data processing that is happening,
it is happening at the local network.
So let's say if my data center is
sitting in, London, which is Cent
typically if we go by the areas, world.
Now, if I have something as a data
center that is sitting in London,
my data has to transfer the network
hub from the US to over the internet
to the Londons network, which could
basically bring in a lot of latency.
But if I have a, a data center that
is located like in the same state,
in the same region as well, then
it's gonna basically, get the local
network parameter, the data accesses
faster now, in, in correlation.
And to attest to the fact it would
have an ultra response, 15 milliseconds
latency, which is like super low.
That enables the time critical operations.
So let's say, I wanna do
a trade card transaction.
Now create card transactions
cannot run for five or six seconds.
So it has to happen instantly.
So that is where, having the edge
computing, advancement will help.
And the transmission costs are reduced.
it has an optimized bandwidth
utilization that improves
network efficiency as aspect.
Yep.
Now the technology, convergence, impact.
So let's look at three
different, aspects here.
we're gonna look at the operational
excellence, the enhanced compliance,
and as well as the innovation catalyst.
So 90% of the faster data
processing through seamlessly
integrated cloud technologies.
it would enable real time decision
making capabilities, right?
So this was the data pipeline
use case I was talking about
where, you can get the data from
different sources combined together.
have a centralized data
transformation, data application,
whatever we're trying to do, and
then basically improve your business
operations and business efficiency.
Now the second part of it is the
enhanced compliance, which kind of
falls under the automated governance
and the regulatory, events, throughout
the, through the entire data cycle.
And the third one is
the innovation catalyst.
acceleration, the time to market
for data driven products, creating
sustainable, competitor advantages.
So let's take an example of,
the social media platforms.
So let's say there are two or three of
them, no, I wanna build a. There are,
we could use a mix of, machine learning.
we could use a mix of something,
as well as architecture, and have
everything deployed in no time, right?
So it accelerates what the business
really needs, in a very short span.
And also, as far as the costs are
concerned, we're not paying anything
upfront, to procure the infrastructure.
And we're also saving a
lot of time for a fact.
So let's say I need like about 20
different B blocks or, and a whole bunch
of network, routers and everything.
I would end up dealing with
a lot of infrastructure teams
waiting and paying for the cost.
Even when I'm not really using them.
so that is where the innovation
catalyst comes into play.
Where, most of the acceleration
in time to market for data driven
products are data driven applications.
It really speeds it up because it's
all, cloud driven, cloud data driven
and cloud infrastructure driven.
Now.
Someone could question back saying,
how do I really make a move, for
an application that is sitting
in a legacy environment to cloud?
So I think it is really important
to assess, do an assessment of,
A very, comprehensive analysis of
the existing data architecture.
How is the data flowing?
Is a database on-prem?
Are you using a database?
Do you need some local storage?
Do you need the cache?
how is the performance looking and what
exactly are we trying to achieve with the
current application that we really have?
That comprehensive analysis of
the data architecture underlying
performance gaps, and the high value
optimization opportunities through
the stakeholder interviews and system
audits is, is something that really
needs to happen now that serves as a
foundation as a basement to get started.
Based on that, we would go about, moving
into the strategy development aspects.
get some strategy flowing around it.
What type of cloud
platform do you want use?
do you wanna go with A-W-S-G-C-P?
do you want to go with the
cloud, driven database?
how do we deal with the data?
how do, how would your
data pipeline be built?
get that strategy going, and get
an estimate of the cost that might
incur as part of your strategy.
And also look for.
what is the net value realization
that you're getting outta the cost?
So let's say if you're spending a
million bucks today, that's, for an year.
And then if you see that, your
cost could be reduced to 150
grand, for every year, then yes.
Yeah, that, that would
be an absolute use case.
Why we would wanna move to cloud, right?
So getting the strategy development,
design a cloud, customized cloud
migration roadmap, aligned with the
business objectives, including the
technology, stakeholders, government.
Governance policies and also
the regulatory compliance
and, implementation timeline.
And with the actual implementation
itself, we would need multiple
teams, to get involved, get the
cross-functional teams leverage DevOps.
How, how do we do infrastructure as code?
How do we code deploy to AWS, how do we,
bring up, bring down the instances or,
get the regulatory, sorry, get the regular
infrastructure support aspects as well.
The DevOps methodologies and
also establishing the feedback
loops for continuous refinement
and capability building.
And as I said earlier, the value
realization, what is the cost
effectiveness that this is gonna
bring us in terms of, moving to cloud.
So that basically summarizes the,
the data transformation journey.
So that's pretty, that's
pretty much I had.
I hope you all felt interested
in what was, spoken so far.
please feel free to reach out, if you
have any questions or any clarifications.
All right.
Thank you.