Hello everyone.
Today we are diving into a topic
that sets at the intersection of
privacy and innovation, privacy,
preserving search systems.
These systems are revolutionizing
how we retrieve information while
safeguarding sensitive data.
Imagine searching for medical records,
legal documents, or financial transactions
without compromising confidentiality.
This is the promise of modern
privacy preserving technologies.
Over the next, slides, we'll explore
their evolution, core principles,
some real world applications,
and what the future holds.
Let's get started.
Okay, so if we look at the
evolution of search systems, then
early search systems were simple.
Think basic keyword matching
with no personalization.
You typed a query, you got
results, and that was it.
Fast forward to today, insert
systems are extremely sophisticated.
They analyze user behavior, they
understand context and predict what you
need, but with great power came a problem.
Privacy as data collection crews,
so it concerns regulations like
GDPR and CCPA have emerged, pushing
engineers to rethink system design.
Enter privacy by design.
A philosophy where privacy isn't
an add-on, but the foundation.
Today's systems balance
hyper-personalization with robust
protections using technologies like
data minimization and encryption.
This evolution isn't just
technical, it's ethical.
Now, what makes these systems stick?
Three core principles.
First, privacy By design.
This means building privacy
into every layer of the system
upfront, and no bandaid fixes.
Second data minimization Instead of
holding data, systems collect only
what's essential for their function.
Think of it as a lesser more approach.
Third, encryption mechanisms.
Data is encrypted at rest.
In transit and even during processing
together, these principles create
a trifecta of protection, but
it's not just about technology.
Systems also empower users
with control over their data.
Privacy becomes the
default and not an option
tying into some technical details.
So modern systems go
beyond basic encryption.
Take private information retrieval.
For example, with PIR, you can
fetch data from a server without
revealing what you searched for.
It's like checking a book out of a library
without the library knowing which one.
How do you do that?
there are lattice based cryptography
and homomophic encryptions
that make this magic happen.
Then there is secure multi-party
computation where multiple parties
collaborate on computations
without sharing raw data.
imagine something like solving a puzzle
together while keeping your pieces hidden.
And then if you add query obfuscation to
randomized searches and then distributed
trust architectures, they will help you
to eliminate single points of failure.
And then you've got a privacy fortress.
These mechanisms work together
seamlessly, proving that privacy and
functionality aren't mutually exclusive.
let's talk about machine
learning integration.
that's the secret source.
So Federated learning trains
AI models across decentralized
devices, hospitals, for instance,
can collaborate on a diagnostic
model without sharing patient data.
Differential privacy adds mathematical
noise to data sets, ensuring
individual data points stay anonymous.
Homomorphic encryption takes it further.
It allows computations on
encrypted data like doing math on
a locked safe without opening it.
It's very interesting and secure enclaves.
These are hardware isolated environments
like vault inside your computer,
protecting sensitive operations.
Together these technologies safeguard
privacy across the entire machine learning
pipeline from training to deployment.
There are trade-offs.
to be truly honest, it
does come at a cost.
These enhanced protections impact
performance of these systems.
For instance, search relevance
has seen drop as privacy.
Privacy, measures tightened.
Imagine, librarian whispering answers,
but occasionally getting them wrong.
Systems combat this with real time
monitoring to optimize accuracy.
Query latency also increases,
because now you've got multiple
systems added to your stack.
that's, adding extra heartbeats
for getting your results
from your search index.
And then computational costs,
they have skyrocketed because,
there is a resource usage.
But there is a good news, automated
resource allocations here and adaptive
tuning keeps these trade offs in check
goal being, maximizing privacy without
turning your search into a snail.
Let's shift to real world impact.
And healthcare privacy isn't
optional, it's life or death.
Systems have, you know where
insured patient confidentiality With
granular permissions, only authorized
doctors can access specific records.
Secure retrieval mechanisms comply
with HIPAA and GDPR, letting nurses
pull critical data during emergencies
without exposing sensitive details.
Audit trails, log every access
like a security camera for data.
these systems together prove that
even in a high stakes environment,
privacy and accessibility can coexist.
imagine a searcher, assessing
a patient's history instantly,
securely and without hesitation.
That's the power of privacy,
preserving search beyond healthcare.
another example is law and finance.
Legal discovery platforms handle
mountains of sensitive documents.
privacy preserving search ensures
that confidentiality during these
investigations, for example, like
fighting a needle in a haystack
without revealing the needle.
In financial systems, encrypted
transactions such as protect your bank
records, securely checking your investment
portfolio tax history without exposing it
to hackers is a very fundamental use case.
These sectors show how privacy preserving
technologies meet strict regulations
while keeping operations efficient.
Compliance then becomes built
in, and now it's not a hurdle.
Now, how successful are
these implementations?
Let's look at the numbers.
these are recorded over multiple use
cases that people have built, so I. some
examples that we've seen is healthcare
systems achieve around 90% success rates.
similar, thing for legal
platforms a little bit less.
They have around, similar adoption,
balancing confidentiality with usability.
Financial services also see
a similar rate, even with
real time processing demand.
we've seen this in hfds.
Each sector faces unique challenges like
healthcare's need for instant access
or finances, real time requirements,
but the results speak for themselves.
Privacy, preserving search
is proven and practical.
Now you're ready to implement.
What's the roadmap?
So what you can do is you can start
off with a modular architecture, embed
privacy into every layer, like building
blocks, address integration challenges,
especially with legacy systems.
You cannot just overhaul
everything overnight.
But incremental upgrades, work
deployments require structured
monitoring and incident response.
Think of it as a fire
drill for data breaches.
And then you can optimize your performance
by balancing security with speed.
It's not about technology,
it's about strategy.
A well planned rollout, ensure success.
So future directions and conclusion.
What's next?
The future is pride.
reduced computational overhead will make
privacy techniques faster and cheaper.
We are seeing it already happen.
Scalability improvements
handle massive data sets.
You can think of global financial
networks or genome databases.
And then dynamic data handling will
secure real time streams like stock
trade or, information coming out
of the sensors of your iot devices.
As regulations tighten, these
advancements will redefine how
we balance privacy and utility.
The next decade isn't just about better
search, but it's about safer search.
In conclusion, privacy preserving
search systems are no longer optional.
They are essential from all the
use cases that we have discussed.
Healthcare to finance These
technologies protect sensitive data
without sacrificing performance.
They proof that privacy isn't a trade off,
it's cornerstone of modern innovation.
thank you so much for your time.
please.
I'm happy to answer any questions.
I think they might have my email linked
so you can reach out to me in case you
have anything that you want to talk about.
Thank you so much.