Hey, hello everyone.
Thank you for joining for my talk today.
So good morning, good afternoon,
good evening, wherever you are from.
a quick disclaimer.
so the presentation includes some
research points which are purely based
on my research and is not including
any of the organizational review.
And as an attendee, you are encouraged
to conduct your own research and.
Basically, look into some of these
things before you start implementing in
any of the years, in your organization.
So let's move on to the next slide.
So this is about speaker introduction.
So my name is Santosh Bompally.
I am basically, a cybersecurity
professional with background in computer
science and master's in cybersecurity.
pretty much, since childhood,
I was basically like a hacker.
I started my journey as a hacker like
way early on in my life when I first
was trying to crack a bios password,
basically removed a battery
and basically, explored it by myself.
So I had that exploration mindset
pretty much baked us since my childhood.
So that basically gave
me opportunities to.
Think through.
And while acquiring, doing all of that, I
was able to acquire all these multi-cloud
certifications and some of these,
different certifications in cybersecurity.
So I was wearing different hats.
I worked in instant response
GRC and all the different
areas in inside cybersecurity.
that's what gave me a knowledge to
acquire some of the certifications.
And I do contributing to the.
industry too.
for example, some of the research
publications for CSAI was
able to contribute, there and
pretty much Coming back here.
So I basically like exploring cloud,
and I'm very passionate about threat
hunting because it basically gives me an
opportunity to think like a bad actor.
And as an engineer, I basically
try to build controls around
detection side and prevention side.
So it, it's really fun, playing
capture the flag even sometimes
because it gives you opportunities to.
Think a different perspective
rather than your spelling controls.
And I do participate in different home
automation projects out there, so I do
collaborate in some of those things.
and I enjoy connecting with people,
and share insights into cybersecurity.
And, if you would like to connect,
this is my LinkedIn profile, please
feel free to connect and, you can
also scan the QR code out there.
you can, if you have any questions
around the chat or any of this topic.
You can always connect.
So moving on to today's topic, right?
So today's topic is about cloud
security, posture management, and.
We are gonna be talking about what are
some of the strategies that you can
take to basically improve the per cloud
security posture and at the same time
drive innovation through shift left.
So that's the core point today on the.
Talking about some of the
strategies and how do we do it.
So by the end of the presentation,
you should be able to understand what
CSPM is, and at the same time, you
should be able to understand, what
cloud NATO technologies are out there,
which would basically help you, to get
maximum benefit, in cloud security.
So this is a quick agenda.
What we have today is we are gonna be
starting by analyzing a threat landscape.
what are the current.
Threats out there and things like search.
And then we are going to be
talking about building blocks of,
cloud security push management.
we are gonna be able to doing a deeper
dive and also a demo in this area for
the three where we are gonna be talking
about IAC and how that is incorporated.
And we are gonna talk about cloud
native security policies, what they
are and why you need to apply them.
And then we talk about even driven
architecture, p management, exception
management, and key takeaways today.
So really.
When you look into the current challenges
for cloud security industry, right?
So you all might have already
heard right from different
breaches and all these things.
These are expensive, right?
So attack service is growing.
we use see nation state actors
and all these different entities
trying to target critical
infrastructures and all those things.
So attack service keeps on changing, and
at the same time, the different status
should also enhance, and change every
day to protect for some of these attacks.
So if we do a quick, research right?
which is out there.
So if, you see my screen here?
So the report here basically says Hey.
If you basically go and check
the real world, real world
cloud security scenarios, the
impact of it is really huge.
So a study performed by CSA in 2024 says
like majority of these are because of
misconfigurations right inside the cloud.
so these min configurations are huge.
for example, think about it, right?
you might be a manufacturing company
who is like basically manufacturing cars
and all these, and basically collecting
the data from all these iot things,
and you're sending it to the cloud.
I. And you have a misconfiguration
in the cloud, and that could be
exploited by a bad actor, and that
actor can potentially expose all
the information out there, right?
Or do any kind of malicious
things if the pro service that
you're using for iot is not.
Configured in a secure way.
So there are so many use cases out
there from a attacker perspective that
an attacker could basically exploit.
So we also need to make sure like all
of those things are properly configured.
And the other report, what
you see here, is by CIO.
So what we see here is like Gartner
is also coming out and saying, Hey.
Majority of the times when you see cloud
security misconfigurations, these, would
be on the rise and at the same time
these would be the customer's fault.
because the misconfiguration happened,
because think about the cloud, right?
So it's a shared responsibility order
where a provider is responsible for
certain kind of security things.
And as a customer, protecting
some of these things is also
something that we have to do.
Either it could be with IEM
or either it could be with
some security configurations,
encryption, all these things, right?
going back to the slide, we talked
about some of the risks, which
are out there, and configuration
complexity is huge because.
Think about a confi, think about
like an organization using tens
and hundreds of services, right?
Protecting all those services would
require different configuration settings.
And this configuration settings
keeps on changing every time when
the new version comes are, so
staying updated as very important.
So compliance.
Compliance is a huge, right?
if you see my screen here, so you
might have been seeing it right?
Compliance is something that
companies would have to abide to.
And if you see the growing fines here,
it basically tells a story, right?
It basically, we can see majority
of these fines are because lack of
proper controls in place, right?
People tend to understand, and
interpret compliance and different
means and how that should be done.
all of these, what is what you see
here is because of failing to have
those proper controls in place
and, for example, GDPR, right?
we need to make sure certain kind of data
attribute data set should not leave a
specific geographical location, right?
So you have all those.
Things in play when we talk
about like compliance and when we
talk about when you're violating
with compliance or any of such.
So coming back to.
The foundational pillars, right?
So what exactly is cloud security
foundational pillar, right?
So we have four different components here.
So the first component is
infrastructure as code scanning.
So what that basically is.
When you're trying to deploy your
infrastructures, through code, it really
helps you with lot of things, which we
are gonna be doing a deeper dive shortly.
So that is, you might be having
different languages like Terraform, JCB
Deployment Manager, which you're gonna
be using for Terraform, which you're
gonna be using for, deploying resources.
And that is really a key in.
Stopping, misconfiguration so
that you can enable some of
those policies right in IAC.
So the second thing is cloud
native security validation, right?
So for example, if you have a specific
use case where your deployment is not
going through IAC, you need to have
controls in place, which are cloud native.
So think about, cloud to
cloud collaboration, right?
Maybe a third party is talking to
your cloud and you need to have
certain kind of controls in place.
So that's the second pillar.
Azure policies, GCB org policies,
AWS organization policies
would basically help you.
To build some of the cloud native policies
to ensure hey, if a resource is basically
getting provisioned, it gets provisioned
with some security settings baked in or
with a specific configuration baked in.
And the third thing, the third
pillar, what you see there is an
ontime for remediation, right?
for example, if you're trying
to deploy something, it's not
meeting the configuration.
for some reason the, the pillar
two basically didn't catch it.
The third thing is basically sees the,
what happens in the third thing is it
basically does a runtime remediation.
It sees the events in the real time and it
basically goes and starts remediating it
with any of the native functionality, like
Azure functions or GCP functions or AWS
or, config policies or things like such.
So having a complete
understanding about the.
For sure is really important.
That's where compliance, monitoring
and reporting comes into play.
So we have majority of the tools
out there, which you can do,
which you could do research.
Gartner basically ranks
them with different quads.
So you can be scared to do some
research and get some information
about, the best players out there.
So moving on to the topic of IAC, right?
So we talked about like pre-deployment
scanning, so that is really a core, right?
You need to have your infrastructure going
through the IAC that basically helps you
to basically scan those misconfigurations
and do a policy integration.
So that anytime when con, when this
conation goes through it, you basically
catch it and having an integration
with VCS, maybe GitHub, you can have or
any, any of the VVCS systems out there.
You can have integrations natively so that
whenever you check the code automatically
it scan happens and it'll basically
show you if, the proper template is.
Configured in proper way or not.
So moving on to the demo, this
is a demo of what we are gonna
be doing a deeper dive into.
So what we're gonna be doing is
we are gonna go through, we are
gonna try to deploy a misconfigured
application into the cloud.
And you're gonna see a opa, a open policy
agent, which is gonna be deployed inside
the docker and how that basically scans
it and how we are writing policies and
how the misconfiguration is stopped.
Before it moves into the cloud.
So if you see my screen here,
gimme a second.
I'm just switching the screen.
So if you see my screen here,
so this basically is what?
We have for IAC, right?
So think about it, right?
So we have a app name Insights ai.
So this app basically has
different modules in it.
So we have code in Terraform and
we have code in Bicep, right?
So if you, in Terraform
we had different modules.
For example, let's do go
inside a storage module.
Let's see a. Terraform template.
Yeah.
This is the Terraform template.
And you can see, hey, this
is a misconfiguration, right?
You really don't want to allow any of
these things, without properly configured
and see public network access is
enabled, which again, for any storage
account, you should not be doing it and.
TT PS traffic is also disabled.
So this is something, which
needs to be enabled in order
for encryption to happen, right?
And we also see a tax problems
going on inside the environment.
And some of these things are
misconfigurations, which should be
getting caught during the deployment time.
So this is a storage account.
likewise, I think we also have, Subnet,
I think this is pretty straightforward,
getting the information out, from the
variables and it's basically deploying
it, but it does not have any kind
of, elaborated security controls.
same thing here.
So this is what we have for Terraform.
let's go also see a bicep template.
So we talked about, so Terraform
is one way of deploying it.
So bicep is a secondary mechanism
of deploying the same code.
So this is a bicep code
for the similar thing.
So if you look into it, right?
So again, you see here we have
huge misconfigurations, right?
So this, these should
not be allowed, right?
So for example, for this one, where
you have it open to the world.
And you also have draw access, which is
open to the world, which basically means
like, any entity out there can reach
out to this particular storage account.
Again, if you're basically
having keys and all that, and you
basically have any of this open.
So basically with the keys, they can
basically access it from anywhere.
So some of the incidents or some of the
major, Breaches, which happened over a
period of time, did include some of those
patterns where keys were, not rotated,
and keys were saved inside a platform
which was available across, and which was
not properly authenticated, which led to
potentially data breaches and all of such.
So anyways, coming back to those, so you
can see a list of, again, you can see a
list of misconfigurations going on here.
So what we will do is we
will also do a deep dive.
into what we have from there.
CI perspective, right?
So this is what is happening
during the, build process.
So we are basically getting
an image, inside Docker.
So kicks again is a platform which
you're gonna be using, or which we
have RO Opi agent, where we basically
have all the policies written here.
And this is an image from Check Mark
and we are doing a security scan stage.
What's happening here is like
we basically, inside a query,
we are basically what we are
doing is like performing a scan.
And in the scan is basically passing out
the path where the custom policies are.
we are gonna be touching
about, these in a bit here.
And we are also doing a print screen.
And at the same time, we are exporting
all the results, onto the screen,
which you can see what's gonna
happen in that particular stage.
Okay, let's go back here.
So here is what, so you have
seen misconfiguration so far.
Right now what you're
gonna see is, Policies.
For example, we talked
about IAC policies, right?
So in order for IAC policies to
work, you need to be very specific
about which platform you would like
to have this tailored to, right?
So here what you have is, again,
inside the same repository.
I have IAC policies here
for, for the demo purposes.
And here we have Terraform.
And if you go through Terraform,
you have list of, positive
and negative, like templates.
So if you look into this one, right?
So this is something, an
expected thing, right?
So for example, if you're trying to
deploy something, this is how the
expected configuration should look like.
And this is how the expectation
con the, this is how the
misconfiguration should be.
So this will basically train the
particular, OPA agent to basically
identify what is confi misconfigured
and what is not misconfigured.
And then you come into the query.
We write queries here, in
the opa in the rego format.
what happens is, it the example for this
query is like, it's going have been.
Packed with this compliance pack,
and it is gonna be searching for
some of the misconfigurations here,
which are inside storage accounts.
and it's gonna check for these attributes.
And if any of these attributes are
missing, it's basically, or if it's
not or it's not meeting the expected
value, it's going to throw out an error.
And it's also throw out,
it's also gonna show which.
Specific storage account is having
this issue with, so that is the
reason why we use this percentile.
you might be having tens and hundreds
of resources which are getting deployed.
So only a specific set might be
having this misconfiguration.
So this will basically
help us to get that.
So I already have a build, which was run.
So let me go back here.
Let me, let's go to the build jobs.
So if you look at the recent
build, which was failed, right?
So if you look into the scan, so
you can see here, okay, now this
water basically says is okay, this,
these are the misconfigurations and
this is the reason why it failed.
I'm just highlighting it here.
So again, the risk rating and
all these would come based on.
Either how you define it inside
the configuration file or either
it might be coming from the vendor.
So whenever you scan these, so what
I did is like I included like base
policies, which are out of the box and
also I included with the custom policies.
So all, what you can see here
is like there are a list of
bunch of misconfigurations like.
Whatever you have seen here.
And it basically tells you like, okay,
these are some things that you'll have
to fix in order for this technology
or in order for this app to basically
be getting deployed inside the cloud.
So what we see here is Terraform
configuration and also what we see
here is the bicep configuration
for, whenever it goes and scans.
It basically gets everything inside.
this particular IAC scan, so inside
the stage what is happening is.
It's basically scanning for
everything, for all the built
in policies and custom policies.
And it's basically showing you the results
stating Hey, you're not complying with any
of these configurations, and that is the
reason why the pipeline is getting failed.
So this is really crucial because hey,
this is gonna give you the feedback
in the scans from the kind of,
phase itself to basically say, Hey.
These are the misconfigurations.
This is a policy violation and
this is a reason why the pipeline
is getting failed and all such.
So this is a demo of what we have.
Let's switch back, to the main thing.
So what we have seen here
is like we have seen a demo.
The configuration did not go, did
not go through the cloud because
it basically failed and we all,
we captured the misconfigurations.
We have seen custom policies.
We have seen how we need, we can
write custom policies in rego.
Again, we have seen how
we can use it with opa.
So let's move to the next one.
So again, deploying these things inside
cloud in a DevSecOps model is really
crucial, for any enterprise, right?
if you do a proper integration with
CICD, it gives you two benefits.
The benefit one is like it's gonna
give you a good developer experience.
And a good collaborator,
team, effort, right?
For example, security team knows
really what's happening before
it is an issue on the runtime.
and at the same time, developers
will get a chance to review the code.
Rather than security forcefully fixing
some of these things, on the runtime,
which is gonna be causing drift, and
sometimes to application failures.
So having a proper integration
inside the pipeline.
So as soon as the developer
writes the code, whenever he.
Basically mergers into the main,
or when, whenever a branch is
created, we can have security enabled
there itself within the pipeline.
So that, after every kind of merge
request, automatically scan happens,
and if it tries to see if a particular.
Configuration file or any kind
of, your IAC infrastructure
configuration deployment file
is meeting the configuration.
If it's not, then you basically
feel the bill there itself so that
people basically know about it.
So the second pillar, what
we are now talking about is
cloud native security policies.
So what these are, resource
specific, policy specific, for
each specific cloud environment.
If you have any cloud to
cloud integrations, right?
So you might be having an app or
something, which is sitting in the
other cloud, talking to this cloud.
Or you might be having a vendor out there
connecting you to your cloud and providing
some services by basically provisioning
infrastructure in your, so in your.
Our cloud environment.
So if you have any of that areas or
if you, for some reason you don't have
the capability to do an IAC deployment,
but rather you have a capability to
directly log into the portal and do it.
So the second, one which talks about the
cloud native security policies are really
important because you're gonna be applying
policies inside the native cloud provider.
So in this case, you're gonna be
using like tools like, AWS S, Azure
Policies on a p work policies.
So these basically restrict, what
kind of things you can deploy
and what, when you deploy those
things, how those things should be
configured in a cloud native way.
So having these.
In those environments, we'll give you
centralized policy management control.
Again, mapping back to your standards on
how you would like to get this deployed
and how you would basically mapping back
to security requirements and all those.
So compliance automation
is another portion of it.
For example, for few cloud
services, there are specifics.
Services, for example, Azure
Blueprint as a service will basically
enable you to deploy a specific
application if it only meets certain
kind of regulatory standard, right?
So you can always, have those
kind of things configured, inside
those specific cloud providers.
So that is, cloud native security policy.
Moving on to the next one.
so we are gonna talk about even
driven security automation, right?
So for instance, for some
reason I easy to not work.
Cloud data policy did not work, right?
So you have an ability to
read events in real time.
Whatever is happening in the cloud.
So what's going on happen here is You're
gonna see the event in the real time.
You're gonna perform an analysis
of each event, which hap
happens in the cloud, activity.
And then you're gonna be having a
configuration, which you can configure
inside a cloud native applications like
for example, Azure functions or Lambda
functions, or Google functions or any of
such to basically, if the configuration
is not meeting the security key.
A requirement then basically responded
and trigger an event, which is
nothing but just trigger a function
to basically go and correct it.
And after the particular thing
happens, again, it goes through the
verification loop to ensure that a
proper misconfiguration is corrected.
Maybe you turned on a storage
account to public access and
automatically an event is seen.
You trigger a function
automatically based on that event.
And that e function goes and corrects it.
And again, a verification happens.
Again, all of these are something
that we'll have to look into and we
need to understand and balance this.
for example, we need to understand
what's the, MTTR for remediation,
and things like that because
sometimes some of these solutions
get costly over a period of time.
If they're not deployed
in a proper format.
So again, when you're stitching
everything together, for example,
from a monitoring perspective,
so this is a crucial key, right?
So we have seen IAC blocking it.
We have seen if IAC is not blocking
it, at least the proactive security
blocks it, the cloud native.
The third thing even that does not
go through, you have your reactor
way of, basically correcting it.
Now the last part is
compliance monitoring, right?
So how do you tell a story?
For example, if you want to, are having
an app and you sometimes what's, you
basically gonna be more, should basically.
Benchmark that app with a specific
compliance standard, or you have
an industry wide standard that
you're complying with, how do
you check information about it?
So this particular compliance monitoring
portion of the cloud tool basically will
help you to basically create policies.
Tailored for monitoring
and also would help you to
prioritize which risks are high.
For example, if you're trying to remediate
any of these, misconfigurations gonna give
you information about what are the things
that you need to prioritize first based
on the risk, or basically it's also gonna
help you with anomaly detection, right?
For example, you can have some of these
things turned on where it's easier.
Some of these tools have visibility
into network traffic and things
like those, It's gonna help you to
paint a holistic story around the
risk when you're trying to go and
chase and fix some of these things.
So again, all of these tools, majority
one, have certain kind of AI capabilities,
which will help you to identify if
there is an act of, threat going on.
some of these things are itegrated
into IAM and those kind of
things where it sees a behavioral
analysis of a specific entity.
If it's not something, it's deviating from
certain, like baseline, it automatically
triggers a incident response,
incident to go ahead and investigate.
So some of these AI driven insights
are really gaining popularity,
with the tools out there.
So all this information, if you would
like to get information about CSPM, I
would highly suggest you to look into
the sale, the Gartner, which basically.
Checks at all the four different
coordinates to check out which
one is leading and all of such.
So again, so when you do talking
about how do you implement it, right?
So the first step really is to,
think about your approach, right?
You need to start with
discovery assessment.
So you need to understand what
are the current cloud assets
you currently have, and if the
tool currently supports all the.
For cloud all your
requirements too, right?
For example, you have Alibaba
or any of those clouds, right?
So check for any of the tools which
support those kind of environments
too, rather than just like going with
the traditional, the widely used ones.
And the same time, the policy needs
to be clearly defined from security
perspective, which basically says
okay, what are the benchmarks or
what are the things that you'll have?
To comply with no matter what.
And what are some of the things that
you are willing to do it, but you are
having some of the business requirements?
In a way, like you should be
deviating slightly from a policy
as an exception, and still you
should still be able to do it.
So again, the tool implementation comes
with different kind of strategies.
you need to ensure like proper
rpac is implemented and proper
kind of controls are in place
and you need to have automated.
Or, automation also integrated with CSPM,
the CI ICD pipelines and all of those.
So currently we have different kind of
type terminologies and means for it.
C-C-S-P-M is one, CMAP is one.
So please do your research, when
you're picking of any of these
tools, because majority of the tools
provide good kind of coverage for
some of these integrations out there.
So again, continuous optimization
is a core for any of this platform
because cloud providers keep.
Keep on changing, updating the
services as they keep on updating it.
It's, again, something that we'll have to
refine policies based on either updated
security settings or sometimes, if you
don't update it, it may lead to a failure,
which you would definitely want to avoid.
For example, if you're trying to,
if someone's trying to provision a
service and a specific category is not
supported, but your policy defines it.
And that is gonna be a block.
So again, exception management
key for everything, right?
So you will be having exceptions
that you'll have to manage.
Either it's a business trip and exception
where either you don't have the capability
supported today to ensure like it's
meeting the security requirement, or you
are willing to accept the risk, right?
Even in these two scenarios, those
exceptions should be monitored.
and should be approved by the
business and the application owner,
in coordination with security, right?
So we need to have a documented
approval pattern for it, and once we
have it, you will have to consistently
apply across all your tools, right?
Beginning with IAC.
do like proactive security.
Reactive security and monitoring.
So you need to have all of those
things clearly defined and clearly
applied across all the platforms.
key takeaways here are like, shift
left is a key as what we have seen
that really helps to prevent a lot of
sprawl in the cloud and, leverage cloud
native controls and embrace automation.
And adopt CSPM with AI Insights,
which will help you to drive
some of these conversations a
lot easier with your customers.
So in today's topic, we did a deep,
we did a deep dive into shift left.
in the future topic, we are
gonna be doing a deep dive into.
Some of the core native security controls
where we are gonna be doing a demo of it.
So this is a pattern.
So at some point of time you're gonna
be doing a part two where we are
gonna be covering topics about cloud
native security control, deep dive.
how do you embrace automation and
how do you basically look into
the AI driven security insights?
So this is what we have for today.
thank you very much for joining me
in and if you have any questions,
please reach out to me on LinkedIn.
Have a good conference.
Thank you.