Hello everyone.
Greetings to all the
listeners joining me today.
My name is Chen apa.
Today I will be talking about securing
PI data in cloud environments.
Before we jump into the topic,
let me quickly introduce myself.
I'm a technical enthusiast with 20
years of experience in IT industry.
I work with different
companies in financial sector
and health sector at tenure.
So far, I played many roles as software
engineer, full stack, job developer, data
engineer, and data architect, and so on.
And today's session is going to be
recorded one, so feel free to reach
out to me if you have any questions
on my email address RA gmail.com.
Let's move on to the first slide,
securing PI data in cloud environment.
Let's begin this with a simple question.
What is data?
Data is distinct pieces of information
which are facts and statistics collected
together for reference and for.
Doing analysis.
Every organization collects data
from different individuals and
firms whom they interact with.
And these users can be clients,
customers, vendors, and so on.
And based on the kind of relationship
they maintain with these users, they
capture different sets of information
and store it in their systems.
Let's move on to the acronym.
P-I-I-P-I-I stands for.
Personally identifiable information
that is the unique identifiers through
which we can identify a person.
And securing this PII information
is very critical for any
organization to be successful.
And now the companies like,  be it small,
medium and large, all the companies
are planning to move towards the cloud
platform because of the advantages they
provide,  along with the advantages.
There are challenges like
protecting this PII data is more
challenging in cloud environments.
So in this session today, we'll
be talking about core encryption
strategies, data obfuscation
techniques, advanced protection
methods, and implementation frameworks.
So in this slide, I will quickly
give some examples of PI data and
the different critical production
factors and regulatory landscapes.
So just before this slide, I gave
the definition of PII data, and
now I will give the few examples.
Social security number, this is a,
which I shortly call as SSN in us.
This is a unique way to identify
an individual and,  if you
talk about the other different
identifiers, like credit cards.
So credit cards of an
individual are unique and they
uniquely identify the person.
Along with that, there are
combination of fields like name,
date of birth, and address.
These fields are also
uniquely identifier person
and moving to the next, the
critical production factors.
The privacy preserving data mining
techniques have become essential
in protecting sensitive information
while maintaining data utility.
These PPTM techniques aim to
extract valuable knowledge from
data while safeguarding sensitive
information focusing on a trade
off between accuracy and privacy.
There are different regulatory agencies
like G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A-H-I-P-A-A.
These establish baseline requirements,
but most organizations go beyond
these basic requirements and
build and implement sophisticated
privacy preservation techniques.
Now let's talk about cloud
computing, security challenges,
multi-tenant environments.
Now the cloud environments introduce
additional complexity to PII production
with key concerns including data
privacy, integrity and availability,
and shared infrastructures where
multiple clients use the same resources.
Technical challenges, organizations
must address these challenges through
comprehensive security architecture
that incorporate both traditional
security measures and advanced privacy
preserving techniques specifically
designed for cloud environments.
And there are a few custom
security approaches as well.
Organizations will develop tailored
approaches that consider both technical
aspects of the cloud, security and the
requirements of privacy, preserving
data mining techniques, implementing
appropriate encryption schemes, and
securing key management systems.
Now let's talk about core encryption
strategies, and the first strategy is
when the data is addressed production.
Encryption at rest ensures data
security through application level
encryption volume and file level
encryption and database encryption,
transforming sensitive information
into cipher text using cryptographic
algorithms that make it unreadable,
which are proper decryption keys.
Next customer manager keys, the
CMEK in a so cloud environment.
Provide organizations with advanced
control over their data security
while maintaining compliance
with data residency requirements.
Bring your own key.
This is another strategy,  which
gives the organizations control
over encryption processes.
Organizations can generate and
store their keys in secure walls,
maintaining sovereignty over their
encryption materials while meeting
strict data residency requirements.
Encryption implementation considerations
at application level encryption,  that
uses advanced encryption standard
with a block size of 2 56 bids.
This provides a security impact of
direct protection of data at application
layer, volume, and file level encryption.
Implements full disc encryption
with R-S-A-R-S-A provides,
identity security solutions.
They deliver automated identity
intelligence, authentication
access, governance, and lifecycle
capabilities to defend, again, is the
highest impact cybersecurity risks.
And these provide complete
production of stored data.
For the components like database,  we
use the database encryption, which
combines both symmetric and asymmetric
key algorithms and these secure
structure data in our databases.
The key exchange protocols, RSA based
security key transmission, and this
ensures security key distribution.
And the other component is
geographic boundary controls.
Basically in cloud environments, we
can use region specific key storage
and operations, and with this we
provide the main data solidarity.
Now, let's know about data
obfuscation techniques.
These techniques talk about the
transformation of data into an unreadable
format using an algorithm and a key making
it secure unless the key is obtained.
There are three main approaches
for data obfuscation.
One is policy driven approach,
second data masking, and third
tokenization policy driven data.
Obfuscation uses predefined rules
and policies to automatically mask or
transform sensitive data, protecting
it from unauthorized access, while
still allowing its use for legitimate
purposes like testing and development.
Organizations implementing policy-driven
masking solutions, reduce data compliance
violations by approximately 85% while
maintaining data, referential integrity.
Data masking.
It is a irrevocable process that
transforms the data into meaningless text.
It operates through comprehensive
policies that define how different types
of sensitive data should be transformed.
Next tokenization.
Unlike masking, which typically
alters data values, irreversibility
tokenization preserves the ability
to reverse the process while
maintaining strong security controls.
Generally, we apply tokenization
onto data address and will de
tokenize it while retrieving it.
Recent implementation show
that tokenization can reduce
the scope of compliance audit.
Up to 70%.
Next, let's know about effectiveness
of data production techniques.
This chart illustrate the effectiveness
of various data production techniques
in enterprise environments.
Automated discovery shows the
highest effectiveness at 93%.
Followed by policy driven approach
at 80, 85%, organizations with
well-defined governance structures
achieve 78% higher success rate in
their data production initiatives.
Now let's talk about advanced
data production methods.
Anonymization involves irreversible
modifying data to prevent
identification, including removal of
direct identifiers and processing of.
CauseI identifiers that could
lead to re-identification.
Pseudonymization replaces identifiable
data with artificial identifiers,
allowing for potential re-identification
with additional information.
Risk assessment requires systematic
evaluation of both the sensitivity
of the data and the potential
for re-identification before
applying protection techniques.
It involves combination of
anonymization and pseudonymization.
Differential privacy provides
mathematical guarantees of privacy
while maintaining significant analytical
value, particularly beneficial for
media companies and organizations
handling large scale consumer data.
Now let's talk about sector specific
implementation requirements.
Different sectors have different
PII specific requirements.
Healthcare research requires very high
privacy standards with anonymization
plus differential privacy techniques.
HIPAA compliance is a key implementation
factor while maintaining high data utility
for research purposes, academic research.
This also demands high privacy standards
with differential privacy techniques.
Research validating is a key
implementation factor with high
data utility requirements to support
meaningful academic findings.
Market analysis needs medium privacy
production through pseudonymization
with business intelligence as the king
implementation factor, data utility
priority is very high to ensure valuable
insights can still be extracted.
Financial services requires very high
privacy protection through combined
pseudonymization and encryption.
Regulatory compliance is a key
implementation factor with high data,
utility needs for business operations.
Next, let's talk about
implementation guidelines.
Effective governance structures can reduce
security incidents by up to 60% through
improved oversight and coordination.
Organizations with mature change
management process experience
50% fewer security related
disruptions during implementation.
While effective performance optimization
can reduce system overhead from
security measures by up to 40%
while maintaining production levels.
Next, now move on to the conclusion slide.
Balancing security and utility successful
PIA protection in cloud environments.
Requires combining technical
expertise with strong governance
frameworks, integrating encryption
strategies, obfuscation techniques,
and advanced production methods.
Policy driven security, implementing
policy driven approaches is critical for
maintaining consistent security controls
while reducing operational overhead
across complex cloud environments.
Policy driven security approach automates
the protection of sensitive data elements,
ensuring consistent application of
security controls across the enterprise.
Continuous adaption organizations must
maintain flexible, adaptable security
architectures with continuous monitoring
and regular updates to address emerging
threats while ensuring operational
efficiency balance of production.
Effective PI security requires
balancing data, utility with privacy
requirements while maintaining
compliance with regulatory frameworks
like G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A and hipaa.
And finally, thank you
all for listening to me.
If you have any questions on
CPI data and how to secure
them, please reach out to me.