Speaker 9: Hello everyone.
My name is Manasa Uppula.
I am an enterprise web architect
based in the United States.
Welcome to my session at Con forty-two,
GoLang two thousand and twenty-six.
Today, I want to talk about something
that affects every engineer who
has ever built a customer-facing
platform in a regulated industry.
That uncomfortable moment when a regulator
asks a question or customer raises a
dispute, or you realize that your platform
was never designed to answer it cleanly.
Over time, I have started approaching
this problem in a very specific way,
treating compliance as something the
system should produce on its own,
rather than something teams have to
piece together later under pressure.
The session title is Designing
for Defensibility, and that word
defensibility is deliberate.
In financial services, every system you
should build eventually be questioned.
The question is whether your
architecture can answer.
A quick bit of background on where I'm
coming from because I think it's matter
for how you hear the rest of this talk.
I have spent nearly fourteen years
designing large-scale customer-facing
digital platform at major UI financial
institutions, Bank of America,
Citigroup, Fidelity, and BNY Mellon.
In every single one of those enrollment,
compliance was not optional, and
it was not someone else department.
Every design decision I made
had a regulatory impact.
How consent flows are built, how
disclosures are shown, how records
are stored, how audits are answered.
What I am sharing today is field
level, things I have watched work
and things I have watched break.
Let me start with the environment
because I think there is a common
misunderstanding about what regulatory
pressure actually looks like.
A lot of teams treat compliance as
something that happens at audit time.
You prepare for it.
Someone sends a checklist, you answer
it, you are done for another year.
That is not the world
financial platforms live in.
Oversight is cons-- continuous.
A regulator can ask the
questions at any time.
A customer can raise
a dispute at any time.
An investigator can start at any time.
And the expectations when it starts
happening is that you can answer right
now, clearly, completely Note that
you need three weeks and a team of
engineers to pull the evidence together.
Every regulator platform will
face a review at some time.
The architecture has to be ready
before the question arrives, not
scrambling after the letter lands.
And in the US specifically, with
regulators like CFPB, which stands for
Customer Financial Protection Bureau,
there is a growing expectation the systems
can produce clear, complete evidence of
the customer interaction on their own
without manual effort, without guesswork.
I want to focus on the digital
onboarding specifically because this
is where the stakes are highest.
Onboarding is not just a
user experience problem.
It is where the legal
relationship is created.
It is where consent
boundaries are defined.
It is where a customer is granted
access to regulated services.
Every field they fill in, every
disclosure they see, every box
they tick, these have legal weight.
They create a record that may
need to be proceed years later.
A misdisclosure is not a bug.
It is a compliance event, and this
is fundamentally different problem
to solve, which means it needs
fundamentally different design approach.
So what does it look like when a
platform was not built with this in mind?
The platform I see most often is what
I call after-the-thought problem.
Compliance gets treated as a
documentation, something you add
after the legal design work is done.
You build a feature, ship it, get
a legal review, someone writes up a
control document, and it feels handled.
Until it is not.
When an audit arise, you are manually
pulling evidence from scattered
logs, old emails, Confluence pages
written by people who may not
even at the to company anymore.
It takes a weeks, it is stressful,
and you are never fully sure if
what you have assembled is complete.
When a dispute comes in, nobody
can say with the real confidence
what the customer actually saw or
what they agreed to exactly when.
Then the specific failure pattern I want
to name this is the treating compliance
as a surface layer, as a set of UI
components, checkboxes, models, form
validation The problem with a checkbox
is that it can be changed, skipped,
broken, or deployed in a version that
does not actually record anything.
A checkbox is not a guarantee, and I
have seen this happen in a real systems.
The checkbox existed, the UI looked
correct, but when the audit question
started, there was no reliable record of
what the customer had actually agreed to.
Everything that follows is what
the shift looks like in a practice.
Here is the core idea of the talk,
and it sounds simple, but I want to be
clear about how big of the shift it is.
Compliance is not a layer.
It is a checklist.
It is not a checklist.
It is not something the legal team
owns and engineering works around.
What that means in a concrete terms,
regulatory requirement stop being you
right up after design decisions are made.
They become the constraints that shape
those decisions from the very beginning.
Before, compliance is the
documentation added after the fact.
After, compliance is architecture
built into every constraint, every
boundary, every control from day one.
That is a simple forming, but implementing
it changes everything about how you build.
Let me show you what it looks like.
This is a slide I want you to take
as a photo of if you take anything
from today because this is the
mental model that changes how you
approach building regulated platforms.
Every regulated obligations has a
direct architecture counterpart.
Not a policy, not a process,
a concrete system constraint.
Something the system
enforces, not the team.
Informed consent requirement.
The counterpart is not a policy that
says get consent before proceeding.
It is consent capture embedded
in the interaction flow, where
the system literally cannot move
to the next step without it.
Disclosure at the point of decision,
the counterpart, the API enforces the
disclosure before the action runs,
not before it should, before it can.
Those two phases sound similar.
They are completely different guarantees.
Once you start thinking this way,
regulations stop looking like external
policy document and start looking
like direct architectural requirement.
That shift in the thinking changes
everything about how you design.
To explanation, a decision trail generated
at runtime automatically Every time.
Record retention.
Not a backup, but an immutable open,
only event store per interaction.
I want to introduce the concept
that ties everything together and
that I call interaction integrity.
Interaction integrity is the property
of onboarding flows where every material
interaction is structured, versions and
evidence producing, not as a side effect,
but as a designed first-class output.
I build this on three pillars, and we are
going to walk through each one in detail.
Pillar one, consent and disclosure
as compliance artifacts.
The pillar two, identity assurance.
And pillar three, exception
handling and interaction continuity.
Pillar one, consent and disclosure
as compliance artifacts.
The way most platform handle consent today
is by capturing it as a thin UI logic.
A checkbox or a model that is
completely disconnected from
the audit system underneath.
It is legally fragile.
It can be break without
the audit record knowing.
The compliant design treats
every consent, the interactions
as a formal defined artifact.
An object that carries four things.
The version of the disclosure that
has shown, not the terms, the exact
version, the timestamp of when it
was presented, the user's explicit
response, and the state of the system
at the exact moment of the interaction.
You can see the right side of
the slide shows what that looks
like an actual data field.
This is not abstract.
It is a design contract with the
specific required properties.
Let me go one level deeper on
how you actually build this.
Disclosure content is managed as
versioned, uniquely addressable artifacts.
When a regulation changes and the
terms need updating, you don't, you
do not overwrite the old version.
You add a new changes, a new one.
Any historical interaction can always
be resolved back to the exact text
to the customer s- at the moment.
Content events are emitted as immutable
records into an append-only log.
The record is written once.
It is never modified.
The audit trail is permanently by design.
This is the difference
between a log and evidence.
A log records what happened.
Evidence produces something that
can be used to prove what happened
with the certainty under scrutiny.
The practice tools of this, Apache
Kafka for the event stream, AWS S3 with
object log for the immutable storage.
These are listed on the architecture
slide coming up shortly.
This is the most important
slide in the pillar one.
Consent is not a checkbox.
It is a system event.
The sequence has the three steps.
They must happen in order, no
skipping, no running them in parallel.
Step one, disclose.
Terms, version number, channel
context, all presented to the user
explicitly with the version tracked.
Step two, acknowledge.
The user's explicit response is
captured as a system event, not a
click tracked in analytical tool.
A platform record with its own
timestamp and reference to the
exact version of the terms they saw.
Step three, act.
The action proceeds only after
the gate is satisfied, not before,
not at the same time, after.
This is the difference between a
client and evidence, and in a regulated
environment, the difference is everything.
Pillar two, progressive
identity assurance.
Identity checking is not a
binary gate, pass or fail.
In a well-designed system,
it is a risk adjustment.
It builds up gradually.
Low-risk access first.
The customer can interact with
limited features while identity
is still being confirmed.
Verification builds incrementally.
Evidence is gathered step by
step through the onboarding flow.
Full access is unlocked only when
the stre- strong verification
evidence is in a place.
That gap between the one service thinks
the identity state is and another service
assume is exactly where the policy hide.
And this is the implementation
principles that makes progressive
identity assurance actually works
in microservices architecture.
The assurance level.
The answer to how verified is this
user has to be the first-class
part of the authentication context.
It travels explicitly
with every service call.
No service should have to
look it up No service should
assume it was checked upstream.
When verifications happen, say when
a customer uploads their ID document,
the system emits an observable event.
Downstream services pick up that event and
update what they allow to the users to do.
Each step is tracked, each
state change is a record.
For those of who building into
the code, these maps directly to
passing the assurance level as
a typed value in your context.
Propagate it explicitly, validate
it each boundary, never assume
it was handled one step earlier.
This slide title is a test I use in a
real practice, and I mean it literally.
Auditability is not about having
logs sitting on a server somewhere.
It is the ability to accurately
and confidently reconstruct the key
events on demand without pulling
an engineering team, without manual
assembly, without any guesswork.
The system answers the
question, not the people.
There are four properties
that makes this possible.
Structure records.
Not free text, but mission-readable events
with the defined structure integrity,
timestamped, ordered, and immutable.
Once written, unchangeable.
Completeness.
No gaps in the critical interaction
trail and accessibility.
Auditors can retrieve the
records themselves independently
without an engineer.
The fourth one is your
practical test right now.
Can you auditors access the evidence
they need without an engineer
doing the attraction for them?
If the answer is no, you have logs.
You don't have the auditability.
Auditability tells you
what happened at runtime.
Traceability tells you why the
system was built the way it was and
whether that reasoning still holds.
Traceability is the navigable link
between the regulatory requirement,
the design control that satisfied, and
the observable behavior of the system.
You can start at any system behavior and
trace it all the way back to the specific
obligation it was built to satisfy.
Without traceability,
compliance is claimed.
It rests on people memory, documentation
that may be out of the date, and hope.
With traceability, compliance is proven.
You can show the chain from regulation
to control To implementation, to
what the system actually does.
Two practical benefits worth naming.
First, you can scale with confidence
when you add a new product
or expand to the new region.
You know immediately which controls apply.
The second, you can predict the impact of
the change before it goes out, not after.
Pillar three, and this is the one that
gets under underestimate most time.
Production is messy.
Networks drop.
Third-party identify
verification services time out.
Users abandon flows halfway through.
These are not edge cases.
They happen every time,
every day at scale.
And here is the compliance problem.
When a flow is interrupted,
loosely connected services diverge
in their understanding of what
the state the customer is on.
One service thinks they complete
verification, another thinks they did not.
Practical computations create a
legal ambiguity, an identify state
where it is not clear what the
customer relationship actually is.
The example on the
screen make it concrete.
Identity data collected, but then
the disclosure fails to show because
a downstream service timed out.
The customer is now in a illegally
undefined onboarded state.
That is not a technical hiccup.
That is the compliance problem.
The solution pattern in
Saga-based orchestration.
The Saga coordinate multi-step
distributed workflows by including
compensating transactions, which
means if a step fails, the system has
defined way to resolve the practical
work and restore a consistent state.
The customer session is passed.
Their practical progress is preserved.
They are notified, and critically,
the cause of the interruption and
resolution taken are both logged.
The orchestration holds
the authoritative state.
Individual services do not
need to sync with each other.
They each report their
outcomes to the orchestrator.
And audit requirement is clear.
Every exception path
must produce a record.
The failure gets logged.
The compensation action gets logged.
The resolution gets logged.
Exception paths are treated with
exactly the same rigor as success paths.
Now I want to show you how all
three pillars are connect at the
architecture level in a single flow.
Customer browser.
This is where the interaction start.
Where user action that has a compliance
im- implication as captured from here.
Front UI layer.
Consent flows are enforced here.
The system cannot advance without
the consent gate being satisfied.
Consent service.
This is where the consent
event is created and emitted.
It is not an UI record,
it is a system record.
Event bus, which is typically Kafka.
The consent event is published here
as an immutable append-only record.
Immutable store, which
is S3, which object lock.
The record is persisted permanently.
It cannot be modified after it is written.
An audit API.
This is how auditors are authorized.
System query the evidence directly
without engineering involvement.
Below the flow, you can see
three compliance properties
that each layer supports.
The consent event, content,
and exception handling.
The consent event.
Versioned and immutable.
Context propagated explicitly
across all service calls.
Exception handling.
Every failure is logged and
compensated by the Saga orchestrator.
This table maps each compliance
layer to a specific technology choice
and the reason behind the choice.
Consent.
The version immutable append-only records.
Apache Kafka or AWS S3 with object lock.
The choice is driven by the
immutability requirement.
Identity.
Assurance level is the propagated
auth context, AWS, OAuth, JWT claims,
SPIFFE, and SPIRE for workload identity.
The choice is driven by the consistency
across boundaries requirement.
Orchestration.
Saga-based, exception-aware
workflow management.
AWS Step Functions and Conducto.
Temporal specifically has excellent
Go support, which makes it a strong
choice for teams on this stack.
Audit log.
That captures success and failure
and resolutions with equal details.
OpenTelemetry, Elasticsearch, CloudTrail.
The last, the disclosure count.
The versioned S3 buckets or Git ba--
backend content store chosen because
they preserve every historical version
and make any past state resolvable.
These are not arbitrary choices Each one
is selected because of the compliance
property it needs to be supported.
Let me make everything concrete by
tracing through a real scenario.
A customer opening up a saving
account in a digital bank app.
Pillar one, consent and disclosure.
The customer reviews the terms of
service and the GDPR disclosure.
Every interaction is then immediately
captured as the immutable event in
Kafka, stored in S3 with object log.
If a regulator asks tomorrow what
the customer agreed to, the answer
is already there immediately.
Complete, precise.
Pillar two, progressive
identity assurance.
If this is email verified,
low-risk access is guaranteed.
ID document uploaded.
The assurance level is
updated in the JWT claims.
Funds transfer is unlocked.
Each state change emits an event.
No service ever acts on old identity data.
Pillar three, exception handling.
The third-party KYC provider times out.
The Saga orchestrator steps in.
A compensating transactions run.
The session is passed.
The practical state is preserved.
The customer is notified.
The cause, the fix for both logged.
There is no audit gap.
So how do you actually build this?
The five steps.
I want to be clear that these are not
sequential phases you finish once.
They are ongoing practices that you
build into how your teams works.
Step one, map.
Identify your re-regulatory
obligations and map them into the
specific customer interactions where
those obligations are triggered.
Not at a general level.
At the level of at this exact
interaction point in this specific flow,
these three obligations are active.
Step two, translate.
Take each obligations and convert
it into the concrete architectural
constraint, something the system enforces.
If consent is required, the constraint is
the system cannot proceed past this point
without a consent event being recorded.
Step three, instrument.
Embedded evidence generations into your
workflow, your APIs and your system
boundaries as a first-class outputs.
This is not a logging exercise.
It is designed output built into
the flow, not added on top of it.
Step four, validate.
Test auditability and traceability
as functional requirement.
They go into the test suit.
They have acceptance criteria.
They fail the build if they are not met.
Auditability is a feature.
Treat it like one.
Step five, governor.
E-est-establish the change
control practices that protect
your compliance critical
components as the platform scales.
Not everything needs a compliance gate,
but the right things must have one.
My honest recommendation on
where to start, do not try to
do this everywhere at once.
Pick your single highest risk
customer integration, the one
that if a regulator asked about it
tomorrow would worry you the most.
Make that one flow fully
explainable, then you have the
pattern, then you have scale it.
Let me make the outcome concrete because
a compliance architecture can sound like a
lot of investment for an abstract benefit.
Audits that used to take weeks
of manual assembly get answered
in hours because the records are
already there, structured, queryable.
Disputes get resolved which verify
evidence instead of contents to memories.
No war rooms.
Regulator reviews handles
without mobilizing the entire
engineering team in emergency mode.
And the one that consistently surprise
people, engineering team actually move
faster because compliance is built-in.
They are not stopping to
retrofit it after every release.
One thought to close with.
Compliance is not a project phase.
It is a structural quality
reliability, like security.
It either holds under
pressure or it does not.
And whether it holds depends entirely on
whether it was designed into the platform
from the beginning or added on top of
the decision that were already made.
Start with your highest
risk customer interactions.
Ma-make it explainable, then scale that
principle across your entire platform.
Thank you so much.
Thank you for watching.
I am Manasa Uppala, Enterprise
Web Architect and independent
research based in the USA.
If any part of this session
con-connected with the something
you are working through, I would
love to continue the conversation.
Join the Conf forty two Discord.
I will be there during the event and
happy to dig into any of this feature.
Thank you so much.