Speaker 16: Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining me.
My name is Sudhakar Palapralu, and
I'm really glad to be part of Conf
forty-two Golic twenty twenty-six.
Over the next fifteen minutes, I want
to talk about something that sits
right at the intersection of cloud
operations and engineering discipline,
autonomous cloud infrastructure, and how
we build self-healing systems with Go.
If you run anything in production
today, you already know the truth.
System do not fail politely.
They fail three-- at 3:00 in the
morning, they fail in cascades,
and they fail faster than any
on-call engineer can respond.
So the question I want us to sit
with today is a simple one: What
would it take for our infrastructure
to detect, diagnose and repair
itself without wanting for a human?
To answer that, let us start with the
problem we're actually trying to solve.
Unplanned downtime is expensive.
Every minute our infrastructure goes
dark, you will lose revenue, customer
trust, and the engineering hours that
should have gone into building things.
In cloud-native environments, unplanned
downtime remains one of the most costly
operational failures we deal with.
Manual response is simply too slow.
With a human in the loop for every
remediation step, we are capped by
human reaction time, and distributed
systems do not wait for human
intervention for each remediation step.
So by the time someone reads
the alert and opens Runbook,
the failure has already moved.
A modern Golang-based generally
is not a single service.
It is dozens of interdependent
microservices, and a failure on one of
them spreads across all of them, the
dependency-- entire dependency graph
before even detection even occurs.
The window between an incident happening
and it is being actually resolved, that is
the self-healing system tries to address.
So that is their goal.
So how do we get there?
Let me show you the path we will take.
This is what we will cover today.
The problem.
So why traditional operations model
break under distributed and cloud-native
load, and how AOPs framework like the
ML and predictive analytics automate
the incident lifecycle management.
And we will go deeper into the
architecture layers like the
observability layer and the telemetry
that feeds the observability layer
and the actual control plane that we
need to build in Go to enable this.
And then we will go from there to
policy-driven arc-orchestration
instead of from simple provisioning
to closed-loop automation.
And then we will see what are all the
tools available currently and what we need
to enhance from there and key takeaways.
AIOps adoption has accelerated,
uh, uh, very rapidly in recent
times, enabling engineering teams
to move beyond reactive operations.
The autonomous enterprise is defined
by infrastructure that detects,
diagnoses, and repairs itself without,
uh, waiting for human intervention.
So there are three key pillars
that we need to, uh, discuss.
So first is detecting the, uh, issue.
So real-time anomaly det-detection, uh,
requires signals that we can, uh, that
the system can, uh, actually look into.
So which are logs, metrics, and
traces across the microservices
that, uh, uh, the system has.
The second pillar is
diagnosing the root cause.
So here, uh, instead of looking
at, uh, the logs, metrics, and
traces, uh, by a human at an
individual, uh, m-microservice level.
So the ML-based, uh, ML-driven root cause
analysis can look at all the data that,
uh, the observability layer, uh, which has
basically the logs, metrics, and traces
to get to the root cause of the issue
across all these, uh, signals that we get.
So this is where the main advantage lies.
And the remediate phase is where
the automated but policy-gated
responses that restore service
without, uh, human escalation.
Now, I would like to talk about,
uh, Go's advantage in the pipeline.
So as you can see, the pipeline can--
has detection, analysis, and remediation
phase along with the continuous loop of
learning from past incidents resolution.
So here, the pipeline only works if,
if the underlying pipeline can read
high volume telemetry streaming data
and can process that information
very, in a very responsive manner.
That's where Go's concurrency model,
uh, uh, and Go routines, channels,
and context propagation make it
particularly well-suited for building
this pipeline, as the Go routines
genuinely well-suited for this.
So because it lets you fan out across
thousands of concurrent signals,
and then the channels let you pass
the information between the phases
cleanly, and the context propagation,
uh, cancel the particular Pipeline--
incident of the pipeline and issues.
That is why Go is more suited
for low latency AIOps pipelines.
By saying that Go has an advantage, uh,
but it requires the, uh, foundational data
with high quality so that it can process
the information properly and identify the
issues and remediate, uh, the problems.
So the, uh, foundational data
observ-observability layer, uh, needs
few, uh, high-quality data, uh, which,
uh, you can, uh, use open telemetry with
Go services and, uh, have these three
types of, uh, in-- uh, logs or metrics
that you can, uh, feed into that pipeline.
So the first is the structured logs.
So the logs should be machine,
uh, parsable event streams
for correlation at scale.
So when a, uh, machine learning model,
uh, sees the, uh, data, it needs
to be parsable by the, uh, system.
So the second is the time series
metrics, so latency, error rates,
and then saturation signals.
So these are the ones which are driving
the, uh, alerting, uh, thresholds,
and then, uh, the distributed traces.
So if for a particular user, if you,
uh, see-- if, if, if you want to trace
a transaction of a particular user, you
will go from a microservice, uh, to the
entire dependency graph, how it flows
through, uh, where is the bottleneck.
All those details will be
through these distributed traces.
So these three key, uh, details are
required for the pipeline to have a
complete picture of, uh, what's happening
in the system, and then the anomaly
detection AI engine can, uh, really
see and, uh, do the diagnosis well.
Now that we have seen the, uh, the
foundational layer, the observability
layer, uh, where you collect the, uh,
traces, logs, and metrics, how to utilize
them and how to, uh- build a system that,
uh, prevents failures before they happen.
So here, uh, rather than reacting
to outages a-after they happen,
predictive models analyze leading
indicators such as... Some examples
are like memory pressure, connection
pool saturation, and disk I/O trends,
and, uh, trigger preventive scaling
or restarts before, uh, any visible
impact happens, uh, to the system.
You train models, uh, the machine
learning models on historical data
from Go service telemetry and use
sliding, uh, window aggregations to
surface degradation trends early.
Just to let you know that
these are degradation trends
rather than, uh, an alert.
So as you can see, the sliding
window aggregation, uh, tells
you whether the-- there is any
degradation from the previous window.
That is, uh, how you detect them early.
And then once you-- once there's a,
uh, detected, you trigger preemptive
actions like pod restarts or, uh, shift
the traffic from, uh, one site to other,
uh, one node to other node or, uh, one
site to other site or capacity scaling.
And then you continuously retrain
models as, mm, service behavior evolves.
So there might be some, uh,
developments happen to the
microservices or, uh, uh, the trends.
So these kind of scenarios, uh, will
make the predictions stagnant, uh, if you
don't continuously retrain the models.
That is why it is
important to retrain them.
Now we see, uh, that the orchestration
models have evolved from simple
resource provisioning to fully
closed-loop automation, where the, uh,
systems self-govern based on declared
intent rather than manual runbooks.
So, uh, it used to be simple
provisioning static IaC templates and
manual gates which, uh, uh, evolved
from-- to event-driven automation,
uh, where reactive triggers and,
uh, alerts and threshold used
to, uh, uh, drive the automation.
Now the shift is moving to closed-loop
orchestration, where the policy will
be continuously, uh, be, uh, evaluated
against the, uh, context, the, uh,
running, uh, operational context
at runtime and dispatch corrective
ac-actions deterministically, where
the closed-loop orchestration is
governed by AI itself and, uh,
self-correcting, uh, policy execution
will dispatch the corrective actions.
Good news is that most of the cloud--
major cloud platforms have tools that
move us towards the autonomous operations.
For example, if you take Azure Automanage.
So it automates the VM best practices,
patch management, and configuration drift
remediation across the Azure workloads.
And if you see AWS Fault Injection
Simulator, it injects the controlled
failures into the production
grade environments, which will
surface the hidden weaknesses in,
in the platform or the system.
So-- and if you look at GCP
Active Assist, uh, these delivers
ML-powered recommendations for cost
optimization, security posture,
and operational efficiency.
So if we don't-- in other words,
the control plane that you
are going to write in Golang.
So the-- you can use these cloud
platforms, uh, uh, tools into the control
plane that you are going to write, so,
and treat them as building blocks for
the system that you are going to design.
So IaC has transformed the operations
by making the infrastructure
reproducible, but next phase moves
beyond static templates entirely.
So the previous slides we have
seen the tooling that, that is
available by major cloud providers.
And the below concepts explain how those,
those can be utilized in the control
plane that you are going to architect.
So the context-aware configuration.
IaC modules consume live
operational st- signals to modify
their own execution behavior.
Drift detection and auto- correction.
So continuous re-conciliation loops,
loops written in Go enforce a declared
state, reverting unauthorized changes.
So any unauthorized changes
will be reverted through
continuous reconciliation here.
And policy as code.
So the governance is embedded in
the provisioning pipeline, so any
unauthorized deployments or any
non-compliant deployments will never
reach production automatically.
As we have come to the end of the
session, let's look at the key takeaways.
Um, build for observability first.
So for the self-healing system to work,
it needs to have high-quality telemetry
data, which is complete, structured,
and machine readable from day one Um,
so why it matters is if the system
doesn't have the complete information
that, that it needs to diagnose the
root cause, then no matter how fast
the pipeline is, it doesn't matter.
It needs to have high quality, complete
structured and machine-readable data.
So build for observability first.
Close the loop with policy.
So move from reactive alerting
to closed-loop orchestration,
and let the policy engine govern
the remediation and, mm, that...
Predict, don't just react.
Apply ML to leading indicators
so that infrastructure acts
before failures surface to users.
So the traditional way of doing
it is e-even the event-driven.
So once the alert comes or once the
system goes down, then it reacts.
So instead of that, use, uh, the AI
and ML prediction layer to look at
the data and alert or identify the
trend that is worsening over time and
then give you a signal before it leads
to an incident or a major downtime.
Let engineers focus on innovation.
So these autonomous systems help you
absorb any operational toil, freeing
the teams to build rather than being in
a firefight to fix the issues once they
happen.