Hey.
Hi.
Good evening everyone.
This is Krishna again.
I'm here to talk about my recent
implementation, elevating security
standards for my databases.
I'm an Oracle database engineer, and I
have like almost 13 years of experience
and I was, I did lot of encryption
process and I recently implemented.
These hardware security module
delivering military grade encryption
and regulatory campaigns with
maintaining the system performance.
And nowadays we are seeing lot of security
breaches and cyber threats are happening.
So encryption is more important for each
and every company and each databases.
So here are the few things which we
automated and elevated the process
and improvise the databases, with
the help of these HSM encryption.
And if we go on to my, my project, right?
the challenges which I face
solutions and the results, right?
here, we, I got an opportunity
to implement these security
standards for almost 50 databases.
So we, we started working on this for
one database, like how to safeguard
the data, like customer information,
that, and personal data and social
security, healthcare information,
which are all, everything is updated.
The personal, like home addresses,
everything is there on the databases,
the cl for the client, for the
client details and everything.
So we want to safeguard that.
We streamline the process
and the solution we deployed.
We deployed hardware security model
with at once encryption algorithm and
robust key management infrastructure.
here, if we go onto the,
like HMS encryption, right?
The hardware security module include
the stronger security compliance and
regulatory, requirements, and, secure
key management performance, scalability.
Cloud and hybrid security and
protection critical application,
which includes everything.
which results achieving comprehensive data
security, procedure and full regularities
and comprehensives, while maintaining
the optimal system performances.
So with that, like we, we improve, we
improve system performance a lot and,
We improve system performance a lot
and the, where they're trying to access
the data, it is also streamlined and
everything like the, if we jump onto
the, the how we, streamline the process
which we implement, like the process.
To install the process and the,
the project and everything, right?
we did it like everything's automate.
We automated the process, like
to involve the less downtime.
So here are that hardware security
modules, which I want to explain in
detail like temporary register hardware.
Hardware.
it is a pure physical security
application with multilayered.
defines that activi actively detect
and re respond to unauthorized physical
and electrical infrastructure attempts
like after, after this implementation.
What happens, like the unwanted users,
which they can able to access the data.
for example, if you build any
database in the company, right?
There are a default user which order,
which we, which imp Which can create
automatically in the databases, with the
sta like with the security standards.
So if any of the user, like all user
with the employee information and the
customer information are the member
of the company, if they are a current
member, the data will be stored.
And if they are all member, we will be.
Locking that account,
deactivate the account.
Like same with the employee information,
deactivating that employee information,
the old information and storing the
information in the IV database like that.
we encrypted everything and data masking
the personal, like personal credit card
information, the payment process, right?
we must the data with the
help of these encryption.
so if we tone the data from prod to a
non-pro, so the customer or the user
or developer, application developer,
they cannot see the data, like data
bridges can be halted with that.
So we mastered, all the credit card
information from the prod to non pros.
So the security key, secure key
management, so isolated and.
we, we, we isolated cryptographic
process environment that, safeguard
the entire key life cycle.
So whenever we implement, the keys,
which we stored in the, in the
cybersecurity level, we store those
keys in, in, in a cryptographic base.
So no one cannot.
It's more than we, we select more than 50,
more than 50 words to get the passwords.
So it has to be algorithm,
completely cryptographic algorithm,
which automatically change,
with the help of the, like with
the help of cybersecurity keys.
And it rotates automatically to avoid the
downtime and to get, the ballots safe.
and if we jump onto the next point,
the regulatory compliance that
facilitates, The, data protection
standards includes G-D-G-D-P-R.
It means, general data protection re,
regulations, which contains the data
collection and processing and P-C-I-D-S-S,
it's a payment card in, industry.
The data security standards,
we follow the process.
And HIPA, it's a, it's healthcare.
Healthcare.
Health insurance, poverty, health
insurance process and everything.
The health insurance information,
the HS HSA account, the PPO and
everything, the process of the
employee information, we stored the
data to, To mask that in info, to mask
and, secure those information also.
it's an internal control
for the financial report.
so it's audit, it mostly use for the
audit team, for the audit databases to
audit the audit, the databases who all
are accessing the data and everything.
So we, we follow the SOC
standards and security control
and for the audit logging.
And the performance optimization here.
specialized cryptographic process,
ac accurate, accurate, crypto
accurate encryption, decryption
encryption, decryption operations
while freeing the databases, services,
resources, maintain throughput.
even during the initiative security
operations, I. And with that, like
we, we, the performance of the
databases have been improved a lot
after implementing this encryption.
So the connections, the sessions which
are coming to the databases has been
decreased, due to un unwanted reports,
unwanted reports, pulling that, pulling
and connecting to the databases without
doing anything, they're just connecting
the databases and running something.
So we, we disconnected all
those connections with the
help of this encryption.
With the help of encryption.
If we go on to the next slide, we have
a few more topics like how we, how the
technical implementation, how we prepare,
configuration, encrypt, validate, maintain
the here, the preparation, the database
around will come, the preparation that all
the databases are not on the past level.
So initially we applied patches
to, latest elevated patches
to, for the security standard.
We have applied all the
patches for all the databases.
and we implemented those are also
like, we, what we did for initially,
we took one or two databases.
We implemented manually for the
first, and then we started doing
all the scripting process here.
the configuration, we did, we engineered
robust HMS, Oracle td. TTDE integration
channel with multi-layer authentication
protocols, encryption, deployed
strategic encryption, access table
spaces and sensitive data columns,
and minimal performance impact.
Validate, executed regular,
executed rigorous encryption.
Ation testing with third party security
experts to verify the protection.
Third party expert.
we have some expert to test that,
encryption process, like how they're
able to access the data, the maintenance
established automated key rotation.
Ation schedules and comprehensive
audit ready main management protocols.
The rotation of the
keys are very important.
We need to update the passwords,
update the current password,
current password every 90 days.
So we automated those, password
rotations, so it was very helpful
for us to do the process and.
And here are the five phases which we
implemented with most of, we went from
some minimal downtime to zero downtime
to implement this process here, we got,
we have to bonds, bond the database
multiple times, but this minimal
downtime, what we did for, we have most
of the databases are like databases.
So we did it in a no way.
Single node.
All the users, application
users can access the data even
though we are implementing
this, this encryption process.
And here are the TDE transparent
data encryption integration
challenges, which we faced.
Legacy capability.
The multiple database, instances require
critical version upgrades, patch app patch
applications before h HSM integration
would be implemented successfully.
So most of the databases
are different version.
In Oracle, we have 11, 11 I to 19 C, so we
have upgraded all the databases to latest
version 19 C. And also we are thinking
about to implement the newer version
of 23 a IE. we are working on that.
In future I'll be talking
about those things also.
So network configuration network,
establishing the security
encryption communication channel
between the Oracle databases and
HSM encryption, HSM application.
demands complex r routing rules and
certificate based authentication and
performance tuning Intel encryption
process triggered the significant io
io latency across a high transaction
system, necessary the customer buffer
and configuring in the table space
optimization and, TDE encryption and,
And the key management engineering
robust fault tolerance process for the
master key backup, restore, and disaster
recovery Required multi mul, meticulous
plans and multi-layered safeguards.
we are taking backups of the databases
every day, so if there is any need,
like the restoration points, we
are creating restoration point.
like every 15 minutes we are
creating restoration points.
Depends upon the customer interest
and also we are taking the archive
of backups so they can pinpoint
restore, they can do it anyway.
With the help of this, with the
help of this HSM encryption, we did
it a lot of changes automated, so
it'll be very helpful to restore
the databases where we want to go,
like for the testing databases.
They want to restore, like
after they are, they were,
they're testing multiple things.
They want to restore 10 minutes
before we can do easily, and
there is no issue with the keys.
And we really like, that HMH
some encryption help us a lot.
while we are doing the restoration
promotion process, it'll help
us to restore the database
very easily and fast and with.
Encryption with that encryption there.
There is no loss of data while
we are doing this, like testing
process for the testing databases.
And automate, automation.
The, we did a lot of automation during
this key, key process, like here,
custom scripts here, we use, we, we
use Python and ba dash scripting here.
What we did like initially, we did it
manual, manually, this encryption process.
Initially we need to install some
software like a Luna client for my client.
client usually use, they use
Luna client to store the keys.
So from the a Luna client, they need to
install the loan client from the server.
To the HSM encryption
valid cybersecurity team.
They use this luna kind to,
to talk from, Luna client.
it's a heartbeat.
it usually, the encryption
key issues isnt this heartbeat
from database to encryption it.
It is like it is signal.
it is.
It is a heartbeat.
it's like a, it's a human heartbeat.
similar to the HSM encryption.
It's a heartbeat and connection
between the database and the, database.
And the Valids.
So if Luna can help us to read the
data and Store, protect the data.
So we did it.
Everything is like automated,
like after the new, after
the Luna client installation.
We, we need to, we need, we, during
the manual process, we need to
get the security team, HSM Team,
CyberArk team, network team.
And me the database.
So we all need to work together to,
to, for the step-by-step process.
We streamline the process with
the help of self scripting.
So what we did with the one one execution
of the script while monitoring, we are in
front of the comer while monitoring it'll.
It'll throughput, whatever the person
need to enter the passwords and, give
access to the, access to the particular
application team or, the CyberArk team.
It'll prompt the CyberArk password there.
if it's password like HSM encryption
password, like keyword password, where
it'll come and request for the teams.
They need to just come and
enter the password with the.
Cryptographic algorithm, password,
all they need to do one click saying
that I'm granting the password.
So only that guy can control.
They need to log in from their
machine and they need to just
give that like just one click.
So we automated everything.
We no need to be like sitting in front
of the computer with everyone available
and the three, three to four hours
process, we streamline the process.
So the monitoring system.
Here, the realtime monitoring
system, while the database is up and
running like we are, we did it like
encryption process where there's
no impact for the application user.
While we are imp while we are
implementing this process, I. So we
streamline the process validation tools
after we implementation violation,
the developer comprehensive testing
framework that automatically verify
encryption integration, security
complaints, implementing potential human
over sites, documentation, regulatory.
We documented everything.
Built intelligent document system
that automatically product, Produce
audit Ready Co auditory complaints
report tailored to each databases safe
encryption parameters, and configurations.
Yeah, here are the key managed
key management workflow.
What we did and had this workflow,
it is if we go over through these
generation distribution, usage,
rotation backups, generating generation
means HSM generation, Cryptographic
key keys, which we are, we, when
we do step by step process, it'll
generate the keys in the ballot.
We need to store those creed, tamper,
restaurant hardware using NISD
certified, entropy source and true random
number generation, the distribution.
Encryption.
We securely put, propagated to Oracle
wallets through auto automated channels
while rolled database access control
and multifactor authentication.
The usage, the TD is also similar, CT,
D and HS encryption, both the same.
The TDE leverages the key keys of
seamless encryption, decryption
opt, operational while maintaining
the optimal data performing and
data leverages rotation automated.
we have automated this key rotation,
automated periodically rotation,
information hygienic and my.
Mitigates the risk of the long
term keys case and protection
compromise and the backups.
here are the backups.
we do take the backups like we automated
the key backups, which we physically
store, the store, those keys, we are
printing those keys in the valid room.
we have, like in, for my client, we,
so they have some secure, valid room.
They usually store those keys.
Keys like it.
Like a bank wallet, bank vault,
they usually store those phy, store
those keys physically every quarter.
Every quarter they store those keys.
They update the keys in the room so
no one can able to access those keys.
We, and comprehen, the backups,
which we are used like comprehensive
keys, escrow system with,
Geographically displays, encrypt
offline backups, business continuity
in the disaster recovery process.
Yeah.
Here are the performance impact.
Here are the performance impact, which
we, After implementing the, yeah, after
implementing the HSM encryption, we do
see a lot of implementing the database
performances, like the Select operations.
Select operations.
we do get almost like the 50%, like
20% increase in the efficiency and the.
like the response time and output of
the select queries has been increased
with the help of H-M-S-H-H-S-M
based encryption, like writing,
writing operation, insert update.
we have seen almost 40%
implement for these inset and
update operations and that.
All the data we just entering
the table spaces are like,
everything is encrypted a ES 2 56.
we have altered the, all the
databases with the, all the table
spaces with, a ES 2 56 encryption
after we implemented the databases.
So all the ta, all the table spaces
are like encrypted, so the insect
operations will run very fast.
Because minimal number of connections
are coming, so it'll accept the all.
Insert update.
Insert update, select queries like
the streamline, the select queries,
and we streamline the process.
there's no.
like buffer gates and the
ram speed has been increased.
the performance of the ram and everything.
The server level has been increased after
implementing this, h some encryption.
The delete operation has been
increased up to 30%, which we, which
were really re really while resort.
Full table scan while the performance,
if we see the execution plan before
and after these HMS encryption.
The execution plan of the queries
has been imp increased, the
performance has been increased a lot.
like I times buffer gates, and,
before we usually see a lot
of the s sequels are in like.
Sequences are running around.
for example, if it is running for
th 300, 3, 300, 300 buffer gates,
it is going down to 200 and few.
I and CP is going like the po
the performance of that CCPU
and I has been increased by 30%.
here, comprehensive performance testing
involve minimal overhead from HSMN
based TD implementation, operation
experience, and average latency.
Increase to 25 to 40% with
select queries, list effect, and.
Least affected and update.
Update operation shows the highest impact.
So the deployments has
been completed so far.
So application can do the testing
very fast after the completion of
their updates and delete operation
despite, despite the downtime has been
ridiculous for the weekend maintenance.
So they can like, The performance,
the performance varies.
the availability of the
database, availability of the
application has been increased.
So encryption is more important
for all the databases?
Yeah.
Compliance and benefits.
So if I already talked about these
things, the, regulatory standards and.
Corporate security audit implements.
See, the PCI, the P-P-P-P-C-I is about
these, the SE to secure cardholder
data with strong cryptography.
G-D-P-R-G-D-P-R is general
data protection Regulation.
Implement the state of the art,
the data protection measure.
HIA.
HI Security rules.
This is PHI, the personal
health insurance.
Confidential confidentiality
through encryption.
SOX control the maintain in integrity
of the financial report system.
Report security mitigating the data,
breach financials and regulations impact
establish robust inter intellectual.
Property protection layer.
Build latency client to client trust
through demonstrate the security gain
security advantage through security
excellence, the audit improvements,
the streamlined over oversight with
centralized the key management.
Enable regular security events
monitoring analysis, accelerate
the complaints, verified with
clear audit, trail, demonstrate the
security governance and stakeholders.
Here we, and if we go into the
cross team co collaboration, right?
We have collaborated with the
database team and the database
team and I have collaborated with
security team, application team,
infrastructure team and compliance team.
So we lead the TD arch architecture
design, implementing security database
level configuration changes and.
Conducted extensive
performance optimization to
minimal encryption overhead.
The security team established a
robust encryption standards developer,
comprehensive key management policies,
and perform regulars penetrate the testing
to validate the security implementation.
The, if we go to the application team.
Executed through complete
compatibility testing across all
environments, application, identify
and resolve the encryption.
Regulated keys and implemented necessary
code modification to security integration.
So here are the most important thing.
We stored all of the data, right?
Most of the data is, we are upgrading
from old version to latest version.
So application team, we work with
application team to up upgrade
their application also to access
the current version of the
data, which we are implementing.
HSM hardware procurement and
deployment configure the secure
network architecture and establish a
high availability infrastructure to
ensure uninterrupted HMS services.
So infrastructure team, they had,
they work in the middle saying
that we collaborated everything.
They helped us to build this HMS
encryption, streamline process with
the less downtime compliance team.
Mely documented.
They help us to, like we, we are, we give
all the steps to documented the process.
Implementation, again is re regulatory.
The framework, the provides complaints,
guidance, throughput throughout the
project lifecycle and prepared detailed,
elevated packages of upcoming audits.
If we go to the matrix, the implementation
of these, we, I've implemented around
more than 50 plus databases and,
comprehensive encryption deployed across
all the production development and testing
environment and up time and up time.
Maintain encrypted operation
continues sim seamlessly with.
With, negligible service integration
during these implementation.
So we, the most important thing we
worked on it is very less downtime,
which we achieved with these streamlining
automation of these processes.
And we safeguarded almost three
terabyte for each database is slow.
If we combine everything light like.
almost 150 to 200 terabyte databases,
which we, data, which we, which we
secured with this, implementation
of HSM and the 30% audit time.
Reduce the streamline.
These campaigns will verification
through automate the key management
and secured audit trials.
So we, with this implementation,
we disconnect the most of the
unwanted, unused, Read only Econs.
We eliminated all those
econs with this encryption.
So the audit team, we have
radio audit team validation.
So they were very hap happy
about this implementation.
Key takeaways and next
steps, which we are.
Elevating for these security
standards enhances security.
Deploy multi-grade HSM
encryption across 50 databases.
Established a robust shield of
mission critical customer data assets.
Scalable approach.
Leverage customer automation frameworks
to streamline encryption deployment,
reducing implementation time by
60% with assuring security control.
Complaints achievement sub process
through regulatory required in including
PCI and GDPR with maintain sub query
performance on critical system,
the future expansion in initiating
the phase encryption with and.
Quarterly cryptographic three rotation
with nine with zero downtime architecture.
And thank you so much for giving
me this opportunity to talk on my
hardware security module, which I
recently implemented for my client.
And I'm very happy to present
myself as a senior Oracle database
administrator from LGM Entry.
Thank you for giving me this chance.