Hello everyone.
This is Sunil Kumar and I
work in AI data engineering.
Today I want to talk about using go
for realtime NLP in ai, introduction
to NLP and realtime processing.
NLP is a crucial component in many time
AI applications, but it comes with its
own set of challenges in terms of latency.
Scalability and efficiency.
Understanding these challenges in first
step in leveraging the right tools,
techniques to build high performance NLP
Powered Solutions while using go for NLP
Go compile nature concurrency support,
scalability and memory efficiency, making
it a powerful choice for real time.
NLP processing in AI applications.
Key NLP libraries in Go Spago Pros,
NLP Tensor Flow Go API Go feed use
cases for realtime NLP with Go.
We have five use cases, chat bot and
AI assistance, sentiment analysis,
real time streaming, Kafka go.
Spam filtering and content moderation
was to text NLP pipelines how Go
Handles real-time NLP efficiently go.
Unique feature like goin low memory
usage and integration with streaming
platform, making it a powerful choice for
building high performance for real-time.
NLP applications.
Implementing real-time
text processing in go.
By leveraging the strength in concurrency
performance and integration with streaming
platform developers can build efficient
real-time NLP processing pipelines to
handle a wide range of text processing.
Task a sample code go
routine for parallel.
NLP.
This slide explains how goin can
be used for parallel processing of
NLP task by leveraging concurrency.
Goins allows for efficient
utilization of a system, resources,
and faster processing of text data.
Integrating go with Kafka for real time.
NLP.
Kafka Streaming provides a realtime
data processing platform that
can be leveraged to consume and
process the text data for NLP Task.
By integrating, go with Kafka,
developers can build scalable high
performance pipelines that can be
process streaming data in real time.
Go routines and channels allows for
efficient parallel processing of messages.
While low memory footprint.
The language ensures that the NLP
workloads can handle high throughput
with performance degradation.
Deploying NLP models in go
with 10 share flow APIs.
Deploying pre-trained NLP
models in GO is a made possible
through the 10 flow go API.
This allows developer to seamlessly
integrate powerful mission learning
models into their GO applications.
Enabling advanced NLP capabilities
by leveraging the 10 flow go API
go developers access wide range of.
Pre trained NLP models and
deploy them within their
realtime processing pipelines.
The future of NLP with GO looks
promising this potential for an
extended ecosystem, deeper integrations
with AI framework and increased
adoption in real time applications
as a GO community continues to.
We can expect to see more innovative
solutions and use cases for leveraging the
language unique strength in NLP domain.
The best practice for go in realtime
NLP by following these best practice.
Developer can leverage the strength
of GO programming language to build
high performance, scalable and
efficient real-time NLP solutions,
a variety of AI applications.
Performance comparison, go versus Python.
For NLP feature, speed go is faster.
Concurrency.
Python has limited ability to handle
multitask at once while go Does it better?
NLP libraries.
Python has lot of NLP libraries,
but GO has fewer options.
Memory, usage, Python use.
More memory than Go.
Scalability.
Go is better than Python
when it comes to scaling.
Challenges of using go for NLP while
go is a strength in speed, concurrency
and memory efficient, making it
promising choice for real-time NLP.
The current limitations in the
GO NLP ecosystem needs to be
addressed through continued library
development and community growth.
The Go programming language is
promising choice for NLP processing in
AI applications, offering significant
advantages in the terms of performance
scalability while NLP ecosystem in GO is
still maturing the language core strength
and integration with other tools, making
it compelling option for developers.
Perform solution.
Thank you so much for
this great opportunity.
I hope you guys enjoyed my conversation.
Thank you.