Hi everyone, this is Omar.
I'm a solution architect.
Welcome to the conference, and
today's topic is Powering AI
Enhanced Cloud Native Integrations.
This talks about the performance
statistics of AI enhanced cloud native
integration platforms, and also we
learn about the practical implementation
strategies that improve efficiency.
Security and reliability
across your enterprise systems.
I'll go to this PDF and we'll talk about
each slide in the next few minutes.
First topic would like to cover
is performance advantages,
model memory efficiency.
Fast compilation and static typing.
In con model, the goal lightweight,
enables the highly efficient parallel
processing with the minimal overhead.
This model effortlessly handles
thousands of simultaneous connections
while maintaining the consistency
of in the performance side.
Then we'll go with the memory efficiency.
This mainly focus on the
garbage collection algorithms
where it dramatically minimize,
the memory footprint without
disrupting the operations system.
Resources remain optimally allocated
even on extreme processing loads
in case of fast compilation.
It is almost like near in instant
build cycle, significantly
accelerate the development process.
Engineering teams can rapidly iterate
through complex integration challenges
with the minimal weight timings.
Static typing enables compact time error,
checking sustainably reduce unexpected
runtime values in production systems.
Mission critical enterprise
system maintains exceptionally
uptime and reliability
by having this, what is the real time
impact for your enterprise applications?
It reduces the 25% of the development
deployment period where the
microservices architecture slashed.
It deployment cycles by a quarter
percentage compared to, its own legacy
systems just by, and also it helps to
bring faster market of their application
in case of reliability improvements.
Our this goal and based approach helps.
30% fewer critical instance
with a significantly reduced
mean time to recovery.
It also supports in multi-cloud
and also reduces 23% of its time
for any concurrency model, which
is optimized to reduce resource
utilization across different
providers and infrastructure costs.
Okay, now let's go to how this, a enhanced
integration helps in different pages of
your deployment or development periods
even support as well.
First topic we call about, like
what is automated data mapping.
A go forward AI framework have slashed
manual integration efforts by 25%.
These intelligent systems analyze
complex data structures in real
time and generates optimal mapping
without human intervention.
How in the background it helps is like it.
I identify all the existing
are across the world.
Similar kind of patterns
for each data node level.
And brings down your entire efforts by 25%
by providing the existing, by leveraging
the existing, mapping structures across
the landscape or your application.
It's going to read the backend.
Okay?
Each node level identify, okay, this
is close to this one, like that.
So this gives you, reduce the time
by 25%, which is a very significant
change when it comes to mapping level.
Okay, let's go to the
intelligent error handling.
Advanced day models now anticipates
integration failures before they occur.
These proactive systems
automatically implement self-healing
protocols and dynamic adapter.
To changing operational conditions.
Next topic, accuracy improvements.
AI driven transformation engines have
delivered a remarkable 30% improvement
in data accuracy, where it has
very various sophisticated patterns
which recogni and also recognize
algorithms identify and prevent.
Potential quality issues
before they impact operations.
Let's go to the next slide.
What are the performance or this
platform benchmark comparison between
different, integration applications,
like C-P-I-S-A-P, MuleSoft?
Apache Camel and Go based solutions here.
Mainly if you see the dark color,
which is the performance score
and light color is the resources
efficiency in all these aspects.
Mainly we notice go based solutions
always, dominates our, gives
better results in both the metrics.
It always like significantly form.
There you have the traditional
integration platforms.
Our enterprise benchmarking also
revealed that our goal-based solutions
deliver up to 32% higher performance
scores and 34% better resource
efficiency compared to legacy systems.
These impressive guidance translates
directly into reduced infrastructure
cost and improves scalability.
Also enhance responsiveness by our
mission critical integration force.
Now, another key topic which
I would like to cover today
is security only four phases.
One is identifying threat detection,
analyzing the threats, responding
to your threats and the learnings.
Okay.
Threat detection.
In any security.
First, you need to have your
threats to be identified.
Our robust security libraries implemented
sophisticated patterns to recognize
the, threats using algorithms.
Ous access pattern are
identified and flagged in real
time microsecond precision.
Once you identify the
threats, then we analyze.
Okay, we have advanced
mission learning models.
Evaluate that vectors using
contextual intelligence.
This sophisticated approach has
reduced a false po alerts by 23%.
Minimize the security response recession.
Engineered counter measurements,
deploy with subsecond latency.
Compromise Systems automatically
implement isolation protocol to
prevent lateral network traverse.
What other learnings?
Every security incident enhances
future edition capabilities by 27%.
Through reinforcement learning algorithms,
the system continuously evolves its threat
intelligence database that will help.
Next identifier, next threat.
Detection pattern.
Now we go to the edge.
Computer integration.
In this integration world, you
have to have your data to be
collected from various I sensors
in a real time, field data.
Once you have the data
collection in the local itself.
You identify, local, runtime
excludes the optimized data genetics.
Once it has it enriches based on embedded,
machine learning models and understands
its contextual understanding, then
we'll go to the cloud synchronization
after having a and enrichment.
The filter data transmits security to them
securely into the cloud infrastructure
where the insightful distribution
will come, which has actionable
intelligence device generates decisions.
Whether how it takes, this
is all microservices based,
communications analysis, processing,
enrichment, syncing with cloud.
Then.
It goes to the distribution,
our lightweight runtime and
concurrent processing capabilities.
Revolutionize edge computing integration
with sophisticated AI capabilities.
Implement this implementation has
demonstrated reduced data processing
latency by 18% while decreasing
cloud bandwidth consumption
and storage overhead by 15%.
Delivering.
Substantial operational cost savings
and performance improvements,
DevOps, tooling improvements
you have mainly.
Automated pipelines we have mainly
with the go in the go, we have power
with CICD pipelines, which reduces the
deployment time by 40%, while validating
the integration points with the 99.8%
accuracy, which is, close to a hundred
percent, which has a seamless deployment
occur without human intervention
eliminating, most of the manual errors.
Intelligent testing, machine
learning algorithms identify and
prioritize critical test scenarios
with, 87% greater efficiency.
Also, these testings s strategically focus
on high risk integration points, which
reduces the overall testing time by 35%.
Once the testing is there in the
production system, you have to have
a product protective monitoring.
This advanced anomaly detection
identifies potential issues 15
minutes before, before their impact.
Our system initiates automated
resolution protocols for 73% of instance
before operational disturbance per,
we have mainly four different type of,
implementation patterns, based on APIs.
API Gateway pattern where Go Functions
has a high performance and resource.
Efficien API.
Gateways that intelligently routes
request orchestrate services and
implement robust authentication
with minimal computational overhead.
Here, this is the main thing.
The next one is event driven architecture.
Go competency model with the
channels, create sophisticated.
Event processing pipelines
enabling seamless communication
where distributed system response
dynamically, that changes the state
across your integration platforms.
And the sidecar pattern is something like,
it's like very close to legacy related
things where, you keep, word services
separate alongside your, Companion
processes and also introduced advanced
a capabilities enhanced functionalities
without requiring modifications to
your legacy data code database where
it keeps, we keep running that one
and parallelly, you go and develop, go
services, waste integration approach.
Next one is triangular
feet pattern, in this.
Go.
Implementation incrementally
replaces your legacy.
So integration components through s
interception points, facilitating non
deceptive migration while maintaining
the system in stability and integrity
throughout the transformation process.
Now it has, every pattern has its
own advantages, based on the, our
enterprise application integrations,
current, Approach and the best of the
best goal and, architecture will find
out which one is going to useful the
imple, while implementing this one.
Okay.
What are the success metrics, which saw
22% higher success rate in enterprise
integration initiatives that be completed
mostly on time and within the budget?
30% deployment efficiency.
It accelerates continuous delivery
pipelines with, fewer roadblocks, 25%
less manual work intelligence automation
eliminate repetitive integration topics,
that reduces your, manual hour by 25%.
At the same time, 30% improved accuracy,
what we observed, okay, what happens?
When you are doing this less manual
work and automation that improves the,
accuracy to reduce any errors by doing the
APIs across your system boundaries, 18%
reduce latency when it reduces, when it,
all these measurements you have improved
accuracy, deployment, efficiency, and
all response automatically it reduces.
Communication latency by 18% for all
your, mission critical transactions.
Processing our nation's implementing
goal line based integration platform
consistently achieve a measurable
improvements across all key different
indicators resulting in substantial
return on investment and competitive
advantage in their digital transformation.
Initiatives,
how we implement, just to give
you the roadmap first, we assess
that, where we conduct a thorough
analysis of our existing, system
and performance bottlenecks.
Then we map specific business processes
that would benefit go competency model.
We may not go to every point needs to be
replaced, but we can definitely suggest
what are the benefits by doing this.
Then we can implement pilot project where
we develop a targeted, go microservice
with the clearly defined boundaries.
Select a high visibility
integration pattern challenge,
and to demonstrate measurable
improvements, framework deployment,
development, and deployments in this.
Established standard, go design
patterns and reduced components.
We engineer robust connectors
for mission critical enterprise
systems and data sources.
Then we can scale up the
deployment strategically, expand go
implementations across our integration
landscape, implement comprehensive
metrics to quantify performance
gains and written on management.
These four steps, gives confidence to
customers and which is a very targeted,
approach where we can eliminate a lot
of, overhead on the customer by using,
the set security measures and approach
of the development, all the things.
Thank you, for your time.
I'm open to all the questions.
Have a nice day.