Hello everyone.
Welcome.
I'm Baba Prasad Penola and I
work as a staff technical program
manager at Walmart Global Tech.
Today I am excited to talk to
you about powered AI building
enterprise cloud platforms.
Our discussion will focus on
the intersection of AI and cloud
infrastructure with a unique lens
on how the go programming language
powers AI at enterprise scale.
Let's ground ourselves first.
AI is transforming
enterprise cloud computing.
It's enabling automation.
It is helping us to have real
time analytics and enabling us
to ha take intelligent decisions.
It enhances scalability, optimizes
resource utilization, and also improves
security posture with air driven insights.
Enterprises are now able to
streamline operations, cut
costs, and drive innovation.
Today, the unique focus would be on
how GOs performance characteristics
make it an ideal foundation for
building these AI driven platforms.
Let's know what Go is GOs compile
Nature lightweight con via go routines.
And efficient memory handling
make it perfectly suited for
scalable real time AI workloads.
It allows us to build robust fault
tolerant platforms that drive
efficiency automation, and helps us to
take intelligent decisions at scale.
Now let's do a deep drive.
Go plus ai, the perfect match.
Let's talk or let's explore why
GO and AI are a natural page
for modern cloud environments.
Go and ai.
Why are the perfect match for
building efficient, scalable,
and resilient cloud platforms?
Let's talk about the strengths
of go performance and efficiency.
Its garbage collection is optimized
and the compiled nature, it gives us a
near sea level speed concurrency model.
Core routines and channels offer
lightweight parallel processing, perfect
for training or serving AI models.
Scalability Go is bond for microservices.
Its minimal overhead.
Makes it ideal for.
Scalable modular AI services.
Now let's look at the AI requirements,
high throughput data pipelines, which
helps for processing large volumes of
streaming data, scalable microservices.
It enables and helps us to
distribute workloads across
clusters fault tolerant operations.
It helps the system to self-heal
or recover gracefully in
case of any adverse events.
So the conclusion here is very clear,
goes architecture aligns beautifully
with what modern AI platforms need.
Let's get to the next slide.
What is the enterprise impact we have now?
When you put these things into
practice, what do we actually see?
A 42% reduction in system failures.
Thanks to proactive monitoring and
AI powered health checks, a 37%
improvement in resource utilization.
AI helps balance workloads
dynamically, which is helping us to
improve the resource utilization.
A 68% success rate in AI implementation.
When organization adopt
structured governance model.
This is a super number.
These numbers aren't hypothetical.
They are real examples from
production environment.
The key takeaway from here is go powered
AI platforms are not only stable.
But also more cost effective
and easier to maintain.
Let's get into the next slide.
Technical integration.
Now, what is needed to make it all work?
Let's now talk about how we
actually implement these systems.
What are the key components we have?
There are four key components,
the Go Platform, AI libraries.
Operational tools, and most importantly,
the business value Now core platform,
which is going to be your core
engine optimized microservices.
They use containerized go services
to achieve blazing fast AI pipelines.
High performance APIs go allows us
to expose endpoints with low latency.
Critical for inference AI libraries, which
is going to be your intelligence layer.
TensorFlow and Onyx Go has strong
bindings to these frameworks for
model execution ETL pipelines.
You can build memory efficient
ingestion pipelines with native go
libraries operational tools, which is
going to be the strong control system.
Monitoring and logging real
time observability ensures
that both data pipelines and AI
models, they behave predictably.
Governance built in compliance
features help track how models
behave and how decisions are made.
So a well integrated GO AI system.
It is not only fast, but
also reliable and auditable.
The last one, which is not the
least one, the most important one.
Why it matters.
Why should enterprises care?
Because with Go powered AI systems,
we unlock tangible business value.
S meaning increased efficiency
or improved efficiency.
Faster model performance means real
time insights, reduced costs, so less
compute overhead, and smarter scaling
will lead to lower cloud builds.
Improved decision making.
AI pipelines integrated
with business logic.
It helps us enable proactive rather
than the reactive strategies.
So goal isn't just a technical
tool, it's a business accelerator.
Now what are the skills that is
required for success now to build
these platforms successfully?
Organizations need the right
blend of talent and strategy.
So three key components here.
AI governance, ethical
AI is no longer optional.
Teams need to build frameworks that
ensure transparency and fairness.
Integration patterns, architecture must
support modularity, performance and scale.
The last one, go Expertise.
We should ensure that the engineers
need to understand the go routines,
the concurrency and memory profiling
to fully unlock go's power.
It's not about just writing the
code, it's about writing the
right code at scale responsibly.
Now, what is the.
A framework that is
available for GO Native ai.
Let's talk about tooling now.
How do we actually enable all this now
inference libraries Go NAV supports high
performance bindings for tensor flow and
onyx making model deployments seamless.
There are also lightweight
go native implementations.
For Lean Edge or microservice inference
data processing with go, you can build
parallel ETL pipelines and stream
processing that auto scales with traffic.
You get specialized structures to
handle AI workloads efficiently.
AI integration GO has robust
connectors to AWS Azure and GCP.
And it also supports
multi-cloud architecture.
You can implement fallbacks,
throttling, and abstraction layers
for resilience and portability.
So these native frameworks are
what turn go from a language
into a true AI platform.
Let's get into the next slide.
Healthcare study Now.
Let's look at a real world case.
Healthcare iot devices capture
real time patient vitals.
Now, AI models running
on a go powered backend.
Analyze this data continuously.
Health practitioners, they receive
evidence-based recommendations with
probability scores for personalized care.
Over time, the platform learns from
outcomes, improving future predictions.
This isn't just a theory, it's happening
now and it's changing how we deliver care.
I, so let's get into the next slide.
What are the clinical
results that we have now?
What is the measurable impact?
Here are the results from the GO AI
implementation in the healthcare system.
A 42% reduction in readmission
rates, so people are more healthier.
21% improvement in diagnostic
accuracy, a 72% fever adverse event.
So when we get to know what's
happening, we can have strategic plans.
So that is helping us to reduce adverse
event, a 73% faster decision making.
What needs to be done?
So intelligent decision making is 73%.
These metrics show how technology
can move the needle, not just for
operations, but for human lives as well.
So AI plus Go.
Isn't just about uptime,
it's about impact.
Let's get into the next slide.
Complimentary intelligence.
Now, complimentary
intelligence, human plus ai.
I want to emphasize
something important here.
The future isn't human or ai.
It's human and ai.
Now, human expertise brings.
Intuition.
Ethical reasoning.
Contextual knowledge.
Now, AI processing brings
pattern recognition speed scale.
The best results come from collaborative
decision making and continuous learning
where human insights refine AI models.
And AI insights empower humans.
So together we make smarter,
safer, and more balanced decisions.
Now, organizational readiness,
technical infrastructure assessment.
So before we get into that.
Here's how to assess if
the A is ready or not.
Technical infrastructure, evaluate
systems, evaluate data pipelines and
skill level governance framework.
Set clear rules for ai, behavior,
compliance, and accountability.
Pilot projects.
Let's have small projects.
Let's start.
Prove the value fast.
It helps us to take the decisions,
enterprise wide deployment, rollout in
phases, monitor, optimize, and then adopt.
So successful transformation happens
at the intersection of readiness,
responsibility, and innovation.
So let's get into the next slide.
What are the key takeaways from this?
go Performance Model is ideal
for enterprise grade ai.
Native AI frameworks make
integration very seamless.
Human AI collaboration
yields the best results.
Governance is very essential for ethical.
S sustainable ai.
So powered AI isn't just a vision, it's
a framework for building smarter, faster,
and more resilient cloud platforms.
So I thank everyone for your time.
it was very helpful.
it had an insight on how.
AI powered the synergy between GO and ai.
It is not just technical
advantage, it's a strategic one.
Go offers the performance,
simplicity and scalability that
modern enterprise platforms demand.
While AI brings intelligence,
adaptability, and transf potential.
When brought together with the
right governance, architecture, and
vision, the creative foundation for
resilience, data-driven organization
that can scale with confidence.
Thank you for joining me today
at Con 40 to go along 2025.
I hope this session has sparked
new ideas and inspired you to
explore what's possible when
performance meet intelligence.
I. I'm Baba Prasad Penola.
Feel free to connect with me afterward.
I would love to continue the conversation.
Thank you so much everyone.