Hi everyone.
thanks for tuning in.
we will talk about, the architectural
evolution that has happened in distributed
training over the past decade, actually.
so today we'll explore how distributed
training has evolved to keep up with
the explosive growth in model size.
The deep learning models have grown
from millions parameters to trillions
of parameters, and as models have
scale, so have the challenges.
So memory limits, communication, resource
usage, all of these have some issues.
And there have been many things
that have been built to, get around
those issues, fix those issues.
We'll walk through some architectural
milestones, from parameter server
to ring all reduce pipeline
parallelism and zero along the way.
We'll see how these advances work
alongside optimizers, like Lars
and Lamb, to train larger models
faster and more efficiently.
let's begin.
between 2012 and 2020
model sizes skyrocketed.
A g single GPU couldn't just keep up.
we needed distributor training,
splitting work across devices,
but that created new problems.
Early systems use data parallelism.
each device persist a batch
and synced with others.
Sounds simple, but syncing meant a lot
of communication, especially for big
models as GPUs waited on each other
or the network efficiency tanked.
And the other issue was memory.
So as models grew, so did the need
to store parameters, gradients,
and optimizer states that meant
memory often became the bottleneck.
Even with multiple devices.
So then came in the parameter server
architecture, and this was done, this
came in to coordinate multiple workers.
The parameter server emerged a central
node holding the model workers who would
compute gradients and send them to the
server, which would then update the model.
it had two sync modes, synchronous
and async in the synchronous when
all workers wait and update together.
Simple but slow.
Asynchronous worker move at their own
PAs faster, but, it doesn't optimize as
good and there are some inconsistencies.
so while useful learning on the
centralized server became a choke
point, and you guessed it because
there was a centralized server, As
you scale to dozens or hundreds of
workers, the server got overloaded.
Much like everything, trying to
exit a stadium through one door.
plus it introduced a
single point of failure.
So we scaled up.
The architecture started to fall apart.
then, early optimization challenges.
Specifically stood out and, these
were, communication overhead.
The frequent, syncing of massive
tensor over tensors overwhelm the
bandwidth, the straggler effect.
So in the synchronous setup, slow
workers held everyone back, like
waiting for the last hiker in the group.
And the third one, idle resources.
So GPU spent time waiting
instead of computing, especially
in mixed hardware setups.
So we needed smart, smarter ways to
share data, memory and manage the
memory and keep the hardware busy.
then came in, ring reduced, which
was basically a better way to sing.
To get the rid of the central server
bottleneck, we turn to ring all.
Reduce and imagine arranging all GPUs in
a ring instead of syncing with a server.
Each GPU talks only to its neighbors,
so gradients are passed around the
ring gradually summed and shared.
this, reduces network
congestion and scales well.
Each node does equal work.
No bottlenecks.
It's like replacing a traffic
jam at one big intersection with
a smooth flowing roundabout.
How's that for an analogy?
So the result, better bandwidth
use and near linear scaling, add
more GPUs and training speeds up
proportionally and up to a point.
Sound good?
Next came in, pipeline parallelism.
this was basically done
to fit bigger models.
even with Ring already fitting huge
models on a single device was still tough.
That's where, pipeline parallelism helps.
we basically here in this approach,
split the model layers across devices.
So let's say GPU one
handles layers, one to 10.
GP U2 handles layers, 11 to 20 and so on.
you take the model, you divide up
the layers and, hand them off to,
different compute nodes or GPUs.
it's like an assembly line.
Data flows from one GPU to the next,
during forward and backward passes.
we use, micro batches
to keep all GPUs busy.
just like feeding the items down
the pipeline so no station is idle.
this dramatically reduced, memory
per device, memory usage per
device, letting a strain, much
larger models without hitting,
memory walls or memory constraints.
next came in the approach of, zero, this
was done to basically kill the redundancy.
so traditional data parallelism
meant each GPU would keep full
copies of the models of the model
gradients and optimizer, states.
And it was, as you can
see, it was wasteful.
I. So zero fixes this by splitting
those elements across devices.
Now each GPU only stores
a slice of model and data.
So it's like dividing a textbook
among students instead of
everyone carrying all of them.
this leads to eight x better memory
efficiency, and making trillion
parameter models more trainable.
So I would just go back to the analogy.
It's like dividing.
The textbooks for a day across students.
So History book is brought by a student.
The maths book is brought
by another student.
Instead of all students carrying
all copies of all the books.
each student copying his
or her copy of each book.
So it led to a significant memory
efficiency and models that could be
trained got significantly bigger in size.
It also didn't hurt performance.
it's smart enough to fetch or share data
as needed while keeping everything stable.
So this was a good thing to come along.
Now next what happened was, we enabled a
large scale batch, large batch training.
Not large scale, but large batch training.
So batch sizes, larger batch sizes,
increase efficiency, and faster training
is achieved through, bigger bat sizes.
but they can hurt convergence
if you're not careful.
So there are two.
Optimizers specifically designed for this,
these are larges and lamb larges are just
learning rates for each layer based on
the weight to gradient ratio, so keeping
layers balanced during training, and then
lamb builds on that with added adaptivity
for deep models like transformers.
So LAMB is specifically there to
help with transformer type models.
Now these models make training
with 32,000 plus path size,
practical without losing accuracy or
spending weeks on tuning, frankly.
So they are key to keeping
training stable at scale.
Next, communication optimization.
basically.
And less talk, more work.
So even with Google Architectures,
communication is still costly.
And so we, what, we did was compress
and quantize the gradients, gradient
compression, was done and it helps, drop
or delays, communicating tiny values.
And quantization uses fewer widths for
each number, like jpeg for gradient.
These, all these, both of these
reduce communication without
hurting accuracy if tuned properly.
And the goal is to spend less time waiting
on data and more time training the model.
Sounds good.
what did we cover?
We covered communication optimization.
Yeah.
putting it all together,
what's the impact?
so the impact is that the training
time for the same size of model I. and
the memory efficiency, the training
time has come down with each one
of these milestones that we covered
starting from parameter servers.
for this reference, the, the
model that has been used to
compare the, is the same model.
So if we just had the earlier milestone
of parameter server, and if this
model is used, is trained using that
approach, it would, The training time
would be basically 30 a month, and
the memory efficiency would be low.
And with each one of these milestones,
the training time drops and the
memory efficiency increases.
These numbers are not hypothetical
thanks to these methods.
Australian parameter models are
now a reality, and they're powering
cutting at science language,
morals, and climate simulations.
So distributor training is
no longer a limiting factor.
It's a launchpad.