Speaker 11: Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining this session.
My name is Sana Fatima.
I'm a senior software engineer
specializing in embedded systems
and vehicle dynamic software.
With over ten years of
experience in automotive software
development and system validation.
At one of the automotive industries that
I've been working, I have been working
extensively on chassis controls system,
where I focus on end-to-end testing,
behavioral validation, and integration of
complex software-defined vehicle features.
A big part of my work involves identifying
defects that does not show up in unit
testing, but emerges only at a system
or vehicle level, and that's exactly
what led to the topic of this talk.
Today, I'll be discussing how we can
move beyond just code correctness and
start validating actual system behavior
much earlier in the development cycle.
Correct code is not enough.
In embedded automotive software, a module
can be correctly written, compiled,
and actually even unit tested, and
it'll still fail at the system level.
The gap is not syntax or logic check.
It is the behavior, what the system
was expecting to do what actually
it implemented, and it is only found
when they're integrated with different
modules under real operating conditions.
Now, the stakes are rising.
Chassis and powertrain platforms
are becoming increasingly complex
and tight and interconnected.
Modern vehicles can contain over a hundred
ECUs running tens of millions of lines
of code, which module from multiple
suppliers sharing buses and dependencies.
So a single violated behavior
assumption can cascade into
a safety relevant failures.
As ADAS and electrification have further
added complexities, earlier behavioral
validation is becoming both a competitive
advantage and a regulatory necessity.
Now, where does validation fall short?
Unit testing stops at the boundary.
Behavioral intent is implicit, and
integration is tested too late.
When we say we were only testing
at the boundary, individual modules
pass all the tests in isolation, but
cross-module assumptions are never
made explicit or even verified.
Design intent lives in the
documents and tribal knowledge,
not in executable artifacts that
can be continuously checked.
System level and vehicle level
testing surfaces Defects at the
point where diagnosis and even
the rework are very expensive.
The cost curve of late defects.
Defects remediation cost grows
exponentially the later an issue is
discovered in automotive development.
Mismatch founded at vehicle validation
can cost hundreds of times more than
the same defect if it would have been
caused at the design interface or
even at the implementation interface.
Triggering full regression cycles across
supplier teams, hardware re-spins and,
different types of delays can be caused
if a defect is caused later in the cycle.
Now, what is behavioral
mismatch versus coding error?
Modern tool chains, AI are highly
effective at catching coding errors.
The emerging defect class in
software-defined vehicles is behavioral
mismatch, where individual correct modules
produces incorrect system-level outcomes.
These defect demands a functional
different validation approach.
Now let's talk about what
is shift validation to left.
Define and verify expected
system behaviors throughout
the design and implementation,
not only at integration level.
In practice, that means embedding
behavioral checks even at the design
and implementation phases instead
of waiting all the way for us to
go through the system integration.
These mismatch between modules are
caught when they are cheapest to fix
before they spread across the system.
The earlier a team can verify that
the code confirms to its behavioral
contract, the smaller the blast radius
of any defects, reducing rework,
protecting your schedules, and building
confidence in the system incrementally.
So the earlier we catch an issue,
the amount of time, the amount of
money it takes to rework and correct
that will be drastically reduced.
And this all happens if we have
correct behavior even at the
implementation and design level.
Now, what is this approach called
behavioral-driven validation?
So in behavioral-driven validation,
we have these four pillars.
Automates checks.
So it generates executable
behavioral tests from specs.
Now, if you see all these specs are
something that is gonna be a ground truth.
So that's where you will have
your specifications, and those
specifications will be divided into
modular level So that the softwares
can be implemented with those modular
specs, plus your test is even developed
using those modular level specs.
Now, the third one is
validate continuously.
Now, when we are going to create test
cases using our modular specs, we can
run those tests at every build and
integration event, so we don't have to
keep waiting at the system level in order
to check the behavior we've defined.
These can be done at a regression level
for every build for every cadence.
Now, what is defined behavior?
These test cases explicitly
map to a behavior in a design
document that is intended to
be across the vehicle platform.
Now, detect and trace.
These trace detects back to the
original behavior requirement.
So suppose a test case is failing, it's
not that we'll go and check the code.
We'll check the code as well as
the requirements if these are
matching or needs to be updated.
So there's a traceability between the test
case, the software, and the requirement.
By making these behavioral
explety- expectations explicit and
machine-checkable, teams validate
intent and execution every long step
throughout the development cycle.
So any small change, you have
these regression tests placed,
taken care of at the earlier cycle.
So it's not one time check, which
happens generally at the vehicle level.
It's gonna be a regression for every
breakthrough, every cadence, every base
comm, or every big release of software.
Now, what is the core principle behind
this behavioral intent executable?
Behavior-driven validation bridges the
gap between what the system must do
and what the code is actually doing by
turning your natural language intent
into a continuous executed artifacts.
This creates a living auditable record
of conformance, which is critical for
even our ISO safety argumentations.
So that's a win-win for the testing
and requirements and even in the
I-ISO specifications that the
automotive industry have to meet.
Behavioral specifications are typically
expressed in structural natural
language such as Gherkin style, which
is given when-then statements or s-
which can be divided into different
rules and scenarios, or informal
representation like state machines rather.
These specifications are translated
into executable test artifacts that
map directly to your system behavior,
creating a continuous feedback loop
that surface, and it immediately catches
your issues when implementing diffs
from the intent So I think when we have
these all BTSs your behavioral test
specifications created, and you have the
right test executed, any change in the
software and if it's deviating from our
requirements, then the defects can be
caught at an earlier stage rather than
going up to this vehicle level testing.
What are the three pillars of this
behavioral-driven validation approach?
The first one is explicit
behavioral specifications.
So in order for this v-validation
approach to be successful, we have
to make sure that we have a steady
behavioral specification document,
which is the ground source truth for
your requirements, for your software
implementation, and for your validation.
So for your behavior specification,
we have to make sure that we define
expected system responses, state
transitions, and timing constraints at
the first-class engineering artifact.
It's just not a document for like
just like footnotes or something,
but it's gonna be a source ground
of truth from on the top behavior
until modular level code execution.
Now, what is continuous validation?
Which is the second pillar.
It will help us integrate behavioral
test into CI/CD pipelines so that every
commit is checked against the full set
of behavioral expectations automatically.
As I've said before, any software change,
any software defect change or PR or
code change, if we have that in CI/CD
pipeline as a set stone, then we have
those regression tests, and those defects
can be caught at the earlier cycle.
And end-to-end traceability.
Since we have the behaviors, test scripts,
and software all tied to one truth, it's
very easy to trace back, "Okay, fine.
We are failing.
Where is the defect?
Is it in the requirements?
Is it in testing, or is it so we
have one source of truth, and it's
easier to defect and even triage
the root cause your defects.
Where behavioral-driven validation
catches what unit test does not.
So they... I think unit test has
its own boundary or limitations,
and then behavioral-driven has
its own limitations and boundary.
But there are certain things that
behavioral-driven validation can
catch what the unit test miss.
That's timing violations, like
latency and deadline constraints
across modular boundaries that are
invisible to the isolated unit test.
Violated interface contracts,
mismatch assumptions about signal
ranges, data ranges, or error
handling protocols between different
producers and consumer modules.
Invalid state transitions Illegal
state combination that emerges
only when multiple modules
interact under specific sequence of
inputs or fault propagation gaps.
Fault conditions that are handled locally,
but when integrated at the system levels
could actually cause a different level
of behavior because we have different
systems interacting with each other.
And if we have a system level document
tracing how e-when each module is
interacted, and we have a system level
requirement, then we can go ahead
and catch that kind of issues where
we can catch this fault propagation
gaps, invalid state transitions,
and violated interface contracts.
These all happens if we have good
requirements set in place where
we are taking into consideration
every sy- every system.
It could be your chassis, your
brakes, your steering, vehicle
dynamics, and everything.
So if we have good system requirements or
good feature level requirements, we can
tag those test cases to those requirements
and try to catch these earlier in
cycle rather than going on vehicle.
And all this happens if we have good,
steady behavioral test specifications.
Alignment with automotive
safety standards.
That's also one of the most
good advantages when we go this
behavioral-driven level approach.
Behavioral-driven validation
directly supports ISO and ASPICE
expectations for software verification.
Now that we know that vehicle is going
a lot into software-defined vehicle
approach, where most of our modules are
gonna be software developed, we need to
make sure that we match some of those
compliances for software verification.
So this bi-direction traceability from
requirement to test evidence, verification
of both functional correctness and
even the behavioral robustness.
Regression coverage, which is a very
good key point, maintain across software
releases, helps us catch defects quickly.
Auditable test records for functional
safety augmentation, which is a good handy
thing when we are getting audited to check
how our software testing is done, how
are we recording our data, and how are we
going a process, and how are we following
test validation or making these software
implementations with good source of base
that is your requirement specifications.
Okay, so let's go through benefits
at the glance and see what kind
of benefits we have with this
behavioral-driven validation approach.
First of all, it really helps you catch
your defects earlier at the stage.
And with automotive industry If you
catch a defect at the later stage,
which is at vehicle level, it gets
really expensive, as I've told you.
It costs you overhead for the cars, for
the hardware, and for doing the physical
time testing and time of an engineer
itself doing physical testing that add up,
that adds up to a lot of cost and time.
So these kind of behavioral defect
surfaces add design and integration
time, not during vehicle level testing.
So we can catch those kind of defects
earlier if you have good requirements.
Clearer design intent, exactly.
Now, when we have one source of truth,
that is your requirements, and those
are divided into modular levels,
we exactly know what are the design
intent, and it's not like everyone
is not working in silos, right?
So we have good source of truth and
we'll go through that requirements,
make the software regarding our
requirements and even our test cases.
Even the software development and the
test case development can be done in
parallel, and your design intent and
your test cases are taking the same
requirements, and that's how you can
catch your defects with clearer design
intent and greater system confidence.
So when you have system requirements
as your base and you're creating your
code and your test cases depending
upon those requirements, you have a
very, a good s- confidence in terms
of what software is delivering.
So these are the key benefits
of behavioral-driven validation.
Now, what are the key takeaways?
Unit testing is necessary
but not sufficient.
So we will need to have good behavioral
documentations in order to avoid any
defects that are not caught at unit level.
Behavioral mismatches between correct
modules are the dominant defect class
in modern software-defined vehicles.
Shift validation left with
explicit behavioral specs.
Executable specifications make
design intent continuously verifiable
throughout the implementation phase.
And continuous behavioral validations
reduces your integration risk.
It catches your behavioral defects at
early, dramatically reducing your cost and
time, and supports safety certification.
Thank you for your time, and hopefully
this session was knowledgeable.
And if you have any questions or
concerns, please get back to me.
And once again, thank you
for your time and patience.
Have a great
day.