Hello everyone.
Today we are going to discuss on
the, concept called blockchain
back at the Reconciliation System
for multi enterprise integration.
this presentation shows on the blockchain
concept, and along with that, here
we are going to use microservices
architecture to implement the
technical details, and we are going
to apply this in cloud environment.
Let's see.
dive into the presentation we'll exp here.
We'll explore how this technology
advancement transforms traditional
supply chain operations by eliminating
manual reconciliation efforts, enhancing
transparency and establishing trust
between trading partners while setting
the foundation for future enhancements.
What are the basic challenges
in the supply chain environment?
So one is unprecedented complexity.
Supply chain operations in multinational
enterprises have reached unprecedented
level levels of complexity.
Global supply chain complexity directly
influences international businesses.
Performance with multinational enterprises
processing an average of 2.3 million
orders transactions annually across
the, across their global networks.
The other challenging thing is like
critical operational challenges.
Studies revealed that 82% of com
companies experienced the supply
chain dis disruptions in 2023 due
to data synchronization issues.
Other discrepancies require an average
ation time of 48 to 72 hours with
23% of cases demanding extensive
manual intervention for resolution.
And the third challenge that we, that.
Facing is substantial financial impact.
Enterprises invest between 4 4 20
K and six 70 K dollars annually
in reconciliation efforts.
The multi multinational enterprises
with higher levels of supply chain
complexity experience a 50 15 to 20%
of increase in co coordination costs.
And those with effective
technological solutions see a 24%
improve in market performance.
So these are the challenges
that we usually face during
the supply chain environment.
And coming to the system architecture.
So here we are going to develop a system
with the base foundation, with the
Hyperledger Fabric Blockchain network.
On top of it, we are going to, Build
a framework with Hyperledger Fabric
Framework and blockchain network,
microservices and smart contracts.
API GraphQL.
All this, business Logic implementation
comes into the picture after that.
On top of it, we are integrating
APIs, even architecture, standardized
data models, all these things.
Our multi-layered approach leverages
distributed legit technology alongside
modern microservices platforms.
Patterns performance analysis.
Performance analysis demonstrates
throughput capabilities of up to
2,800 transactions per second with
an average latency of 0.5 second
cross organizational networks.
The Hyperledger Fabric Network
provides the foundational layer for
immutable transaction core recording
while Micros microservices manage
business logic and a p exposure.
Apart from that, smart contracts
automate order validation
and reconciliation process.
While the GraphQL A PA pro provides
flexible data querying capabilities, how
the core components performance will be.
If you see the core components
performance, our system achieves
remarkable performance across
all components where coming
to the Hyperledger Fabric may.
and, framework, it maintains a consistent
blockchain generation time of 0.5
seconds and achieves a validation rate
of 2,200 transactions per second with
99.98 successful transaction date.
The microservices layer effectively
processes 1500 concurrent
logistics events with average
response time of 80 milliseconds.
And coming to the middleware technology
like Apache Kafka reliably handles
75,000 events per second with
latencies below 15 milliseconds.
and coming to the smart contracts,
it complete standard Ranch
action in 180 milliseconds with
99.95 successful execution rate.
Whereas the GraphQL a PA,
consistently handles 12,000.
Sorry, 1200 queries per
second with response times
of averaging 95 milliseconds.
If you see the technical implementation
of this, idea, the blockchain
implementation, smart contract logic
and microservices and data of flow
and processing, the Hyperledger
Fabric Network deployment consists
of multiple organization representing
key supply chain participants.
System utilizes a channel based
architecture processing up to 1500
transactions per second while maintaining
data privacy between participants.
Smart contract logic.
The smart contracts develop a
chain code in Golan from the
core business logic layer.
Enterprise implementation shows that
well designed smart contracts can
automate up to 85% tough routine.
Business process, reducing
manual intervention by 70%.
Microservices architecture
is built on Spring Boot.
The microservices architecture
demonstrates significant advantages
in scalability and maintainability.
Properly containerized services
handle up to thousand transactions
per second with response times
of under a hundred milliseconds.
And coming to the database and
data processing related where
we are using Apache Kafka to
maintain all our transaction,
between the modules and the system.
Implements a comprehensive data
processing pipeline, even driven
architecture, achi archiving, achieving
event processing, latencies under 50
milliseconds for 95% transactions.
This is.
If you see the achievement, it
is very good compared to the
old latency approach, right?
And we have a better system
design architecture and good
technical implementation details.
If we have a robust environment
where we can deploy and the
performance achieves more.
That will be great.
So here we are using AWS Cloud
deployment or our deployment platform.
In this, we are using Imagine EKS,
which provides foundational for
container orchestration implementing
through cloud native architecture,
cloud native container deployments,
reduce deployment times by 65% and
improve resource utilization by 45 to
50% compared to traditional methods.
And coming to the database, platform
that we use here in Amgen, we
are using Amgen RD service for
implementation of Cloud native best
practices for data persistence.
This is available in multi available
zones so that we can reduce the
burden on the application, and
it achieves 99.99% success rate.
Even during peak operations with automated
failover completing within 60 seconds to
reduce more burden on the data, we also
use elastic catching implementation,
which utilizes a distributed catching
architecture that automatically
scales based on demand, a cloud
narrative, catching strategies improve.
The response times by 70% while reducing
database load by more than 60%, right?
We have very good deployment and
where we can maintain the software
or the implementation details.
We also need to follow
the security standards.
Coming to the security standards
that we are taking care.
That is one is network security.
Here we are using T LS 1.3, which
is a perfect forward secrecy.
The system effectively mitigates 99.9%
man in the middle attempts and can
withstand sustained attack volumes up to
300 K malicious transactions per second.
That's a gr great security in
terms of security mechanisms in
the network layer, and coming to
authentication and authorization.
Authentication mechanisms.
Lever is blockchain native identity
management, combined with the
traditional PK infrastructure.
By following this, we are reducing
unauthorized access attempts by 99.8%.
The system processes access requests.
Three, a consensus based
validation mechanism while
ensuring complete auditability.
And also we are.
Implementing multi signature operations
security here, this helps to manage
critical operations implementation
in blockchain native multi signature
protocols that require consensus
from designated validator nodes.
It prevents 99.99% of
unauthorized transactions items
while maintaining transaction.
Finality times under two
seconds and coming to the
audit and monitoring security.
The audit system creates tamper
proof security logs, supporting
throughput of 50,000 events per second.
Distributed system monitoring incorporates
both network level and application
level security metrics, processing two
terabytes of daily security events.
That is very great in terms of security
for auditing what will be the operational
benefits and the results, so we are
achieving very great operational results.
Verification time reduction up to
89% and tra traceability accuracy to
99.6% and manual process elimination.
Up to 85% visibility
improvement up to 92%.
Implementation analysis demonstrates
significant operational improvements
across multiple dimensions.
System has eliminated approximately
85% of manual documentation process
with automated smart contracts handling
verification and compliance checks,
it has strengthened this relationship
between supply chain participants.
And significantly improve consumer trust.
The blockchain solutions reduce
dispute resolution times from an
average of 45 days to just five
days while decreasing error rates
in other processing from 5% to 0.1%.
That's a great achievement.
I can say.
What will be the financial impact?
If you see the financial impact and three
major areas, which is transaction cost
reduction, blockchain implementation
reduces a transaction cost up to 65%
with the small scale farmers seeing an
average increase in profit margins of 25%
through improved market access, reduced
intermediate co intermediary costs.
And coming to work working
capital improvement.
The processing efficiency has
improved significantly, and the
study shows that the next generation
sub supply chain system reduce
working capital requirements by 30%.
Improved inventory management
and faster payment processing.
That's a very good achievement
in terms of working capital.
And coming to administrative savings
here, the report shows that average
annual savings of 0.3 0.2 million
through reduced administrative overhead
and improved operational efficiency.
Immutable audit trials have
proven particularly valuable for
regulatory compliance and reducing
compliance verification by 75%.
So these are the best implementation
details and financially it is perfect.
We are having a very good cloud deployment
environment to make this particular
idea to very good maintainable state
by reducing lot of things, right?
We can also do feature enhancements.
For this idea by implementing A ML
integration, IOT integration, cross
chain interoperability and enhanced
analytic analytics and mobile development.
By implementing these advanced features
like A-M-L-I-I-O-T integration,
it automates more process and
reducing more, burden on the system.
Inventory cost, inventory management.
In financial things, so
many things we can reduce.
It also reduces 95% of manual efforts
at, in a small scale, coming to
larger, supply chain industries.
it, it eliminates up to
90% of manual duction.
With that, I'm concluding this,
the transforming supply chain
management with the trust and
transparency, operational efficiency.
Innovation pathway and scalable
foundation, the blockchain back data
reconciliation system demonstrate
transformative potential in resolving,
in, in resolving longstanding
challenges with multi enterprise supply
chain environments, the integration
distributed technology and modern
cloud native architecture, along with
microservices environment, a robust
foundation for secure, efficient,
and automated order management.
The demonstrated improvements in
operational efficiency combined with
potential for future enhancements
through a ML iot integration Position
this solution as cornerstone for next
generation supply chain management.
This successful implementation
showcases how blockchain
technology can vol revolutionize.
Business process while providing a
clear pathway for continued innovation.
With that, I will end my presentation
here, so hope you like it and you want
to know more details on top of it.
If you are, if you want to know
more details, you can may shoot.
Always shoot an email at
Anil kumar anil@gmail.com.
Thank you.
Thank you for.
Your time.