Speaker 18: Hi, everyone.
This is Swati, and today we have
gathered to talk about beyond chatbots.
So over the last two years, I would say, I
would just call it two years, almost every
company has experimented with chatbots.
I'm just opening my eyes,
and I see chatbots all over.
Most of those systems
stop at conversation.
Like they can answer, they can
question, they can answer your
question, summarize your information,
may also generate a response.
But they usually cannot actually
complete the task which the user needs.
And the-- this talk will be about this
missing layer between the AI understanding
your task and the real business execution.
So welcome to this talk.
As I already said, everyone has a chatbot,
but few of these chatbots actually
understands or actually have a solution.
So the industry problem is
not NLP quality anymore.
It's an operational execution.
Most chatbot projects
succeeds in the demo.
So the engineers are actually
building in the development
environment, QA environment.
This is actually they have
built a very quality product.
But in the production, the expectation
with the user, it is failing because the
bot cannot-- is not telling your where
is your packages delay, your refund is
pending, or the invoice actually exists.
And this is what the user needs.
The u- it is talking to the user.
There is a continuous conversation
with the user, but is the user
getting the actual solution?
That's the gap.
And the gap between understanding
intent of the user and completing
action is where most enterprise
AI system is like breaking down.
It's just simply breaking down.
Conversational AI is something which
is easy to build, easy to demo.
But a- we are talking about we, the
user, means like the user, the we--
what we require is an action label
AI, which is really hard to engineer.
So before like diving into the
solution, I-- Let's try to understand
why these chatbots are failing.
So like the root cause is something
with without understanding this root
cause it's hard to implement a system.
So one of the biggest thing which
I understand why these bots are
failing because they are disconnected
from the operational system.
You-- They might be connected to
one system, two systems, but they
are not like six- three sixty
degree connected to all the systems.
They-- If say, the user is asking about
my-- if my order, cancel my order, it
is connected to the CRM system, but
it's not connected to authentication
system or the refund system.
So that is something which it is
failing, and I would like-- And
that is some of something which
is which should be called out.
It should be integrated to
almost all the system you have.
I'm not saying just give the
access to everything you have,
but if it requires an in-depth
integration, then that has to be done.
So even when the AI understands
the request correctly, the
system cannot execute the outcome
because it's not connected.
So the real engineering challenge
is not only the language
understanding, which is l- like NLP.
Chatbots are smart enough.
They are understanding.
It's the backend orchestration.
Now as we understood, okay, so
this is something which is related
to the deep backend integration.
Then how it should be built?
What's the gap?
So the gap is between
the NLP and the action.
The LLMs are, like, only one layer.
It's just the surface layer which
the conversational AI has been built
upon, but it has to be, like, stacked.
There has to be, like, an LLM, NLP,
then the integration, orchestration,
and lies the core system, which
is the backend integration.
Understanding alone no business
value unless the system can
integrate, interact with the
operational backbone of the company.
A production-graded AI
assistant must be able.
So a very good AI system should
be able to retrieve the live data,
validate permissions, execute
transaction coordinate multiple
services, and handle failure safely.
This-- All this requires the deep
integration into the backend system.
So listing CRM system, billing
logistic, and these instead of
just reading it mechanically is
something which the AI requires.
AI requires.
So now let's see, like, why--
go for the backend integration.
Why is this?
So I would say a Go is an
ideal orchestration problems
are concurrency problems.
The reason Go fits this
architecture so naturally is that
the modern AI orchestration is
currently heavily concurrent.
A single user may request
m- may require many things.
It can require authentication, at the same
time billing lookup, inventory validation.
So it is like a concurrency problem.
It's not just one problem.
It can require logistic, policy execution,
everything bundled up at the same time.
So we require a Go routine and
channel that makes this fan-out
pattern straightforward and efficient.
And importantly, Go gives you concurrency
without a lot of operational complexity.
So in orchestration-heavy system, so
when if you are trying to make your
conversational AI into something which
is action-able, then orchestration-heavy
system is something which is required,
and the latency compounds very quickly.
So concurrency is not an opt-optimization,
but it is-- it should be, like,
the part of your architecture.
Now we'll try to understand how the
architecture org should look like.
So if you see in this diagram, the
core orchestration is I have made it
the core orchestration should be the
nervous system, which is the core of it.
The user should-- the
audience should feel the flow.
It should be the nervous
system of the stacking.
And then from that nervous system
is something with we have built the
NLP, and we have connected the user
interface and the back-end system.
Go orchestration system sh- layer
should handle back-end coordination,
retries, caching, authentication, event
handling, and response aggregation.
So in many ways, this orchestration
service becomes the nervous
system of the platform.
And that's what we have to focus upon.
Now if the API-- How this
should the pattern look like?
So one user, if the user is
asking for just one, "Okay, do
something, cancel my order."
Understood.
So that's like a one user action
triggers, and that should trigger multiple
coordination back-end system because
it should try... if it's saying "Cancel
my order," the system should actually
perform several independent checks.
For example, is the user authenticated?
Has the order shipped already?
Like, where I fall.
Is the order refundable?
So it should check for those conditions.
Is there a billing hold?
So it's not just though the user has
executed just one step, but it has
to do a three-sixty degree check.
And these operations should happen
concurrently at the same time, not
sequentially like that, not one, two,
because that would create a lot of delay.
And this is where I was talking about
Go routine becomes extremely valuable
because the orchestration layer can fan
out requests in parallel and not in series
is something which we are not looking at.
So the user experiences one single
conversation, but behind the scene,
there's a lot of things which are
la-- Like a lot of coordination
and entire workflow is built upon.
So in between lies the cancel my order,
but the system is doing a lot of work
at the back end to get to the answer.
Now so when the AI is trying to connect
to so many systems, so many system,
multiple complex, it generates a
complex workflow exceptions, and some
workflows are, like, long-running,
involve multiple downstream systems.
For example you would say they have to
dig into the delivery exceptions, fraud
reviews, ticket escalations, and so on.
And in this, it would
increase the latency.
So just we would try to in-integrate in
such a pattern that it is an event-driven
architecture becomes very important.
Instead of blocking the user
interaction, the bot should publish
an event independent, consumes,
and reacts ex-exequiously.
So this is where the architecture
sh-shifts from like a request-response.
So this is not enough towards something
like coordinating distributed workflow.
Now, as I already said because so many
systems, now if we integrate to so
many systems often a lot of workflows
would be running at the back end,
and this would create the latency.
So we have to apply a smart
caching, which could reduce the
latency and the back-end pressure.
Because if so many things
are running at the same time,
the system will just explode.
So the AI system should often generate
repetitive lookups for same con- Next.
Without caching, the orchestration layer
can overload the downstream very quickly.
But not all the data
should be cached equally.
For example, like user profile may
tolerate longer TTLs, while the
payment states or the inventory
usually requires live reads.
Like the real design is not
should we cache it, it is what is
safe to cache and for how long.
So this is like caching strategy is
something which is really important.
Now let's try to see so when these
AIs are talking to the user is looking
for a quick response, not a static
response, because that static response
would reduce the trust of the chatbot.
User is increasingly... Because as
the systems are becoming so advanced
today users want live system response.
And if someone is asking like,
"Where is my package?" They assume
the answer reflects the current
state, not something which is like a
snapshot of what happened an hour ago.
So this type requires a, like a live
streaming architecture, which is,
which can be done by like WebSockets,
I mentioned SSE, live event ingestion,
and concurrent internal pipelines.
Go channel works especially well
here because they, the modern
streaming workflows goes naturally.
Trust in AI is dependent
heavily on freshness.
The user-- If the data is fresh, the
response is fresh, the user will trust
you, and accuracy of the operational data.
And this can be achieved by
a real-time data pipeline.
Now we have understood, like what
was the problem, how the integration
can be done, how it can be dealt.
Let's just take up like a
very small light use case.
So let's say the user in an e-commerce
background wants to just cancel the order.
So user wants to cancel
the order in between.
So like they have placed the
order, the payment has been done,
but the shipment is not done.
So it's kinda it's like in between.
So I've built an architecture like this.
So it-- In this whole thing now this is
where the pattern will come into play.
The orchestration layer
will come into play.
Now the system, the chatbot has to
validate the request Check the OMS
status where it falls right now.
Verifies the refund
eligibility in this case.
Coordinate with the billing system, handle
retry, and maintain independent potency.
And ideally, the entire issue is
resolved without a human agent.
So this is a good chatbot,
is what I would call.
Like zero human resolution is something
which we are targeted about, and
that's what we are looking into
a chatbot in this case, and that
would be like an ideal scenario.
Let's try to understand one
bit, one more use case which
is billing dispute resolution.
So this is something which
is like very common nowadays.
Failure handling matters as much
as success handling matters.
So the production systems are
defined less by happy path
and more by failure behavior.
Billing systems timeout, API fails,
downstream system become inconsistent,
so the resilient orga- orchestration
requires timeout propaganda, retries
with the back-off, circuit breaking,
and gra- graceful escalations.
These are not the edge cases, but
these are like normal operating
conditions in distributed systems.
So we talked about two, like
one is the dispute, the one
is like canceling the order.
And these are like very... I would
say these are actually very common
scenarios which we talked about.
Now, as we have understood everything,
we have gone over two examples,
the last thing which I would try to
talk about is the security concerns.
As our AI, as the chatbot becomes from
a conversation to an action level now
the operational risk is increasing.
Once this AI systems are
executing actions, security is
something which becomes like a
drama more, and very important.
A conversational mistakes are like a small
mistake is annoying for the user, and like
an au-unauthorized transaction is serious.
So the production system needs
to understand the scope of
authorization like audit logging,
rate limiting, validation, and careful
handling of the sensitive data.
This is something which is very important.
That is, the orchestration
layer becomes both an execution
layer and a security boundary.
So this has to be done.
And this is something
which is serious about it.
Now, this is something which
I was talking about today.
Some of the takeaway points where it's
like, if there is one idea, I want
people to leave with this one, that
the real value of enterprise AI is
not conversation like chit-chat, but
a system's ability to produce outcome
is something which a user is looking
forward to, and that is something
which I would call a good chatbot.
And to achieve that, it requires a deep
integration, resilient orchestration,
concurrency, and operational reliability,
and that's why Go is such a strong
fit for this category of system.
Just my last sentence, the
future of AI system is not just
answering questions better, but
it is executing business workflows
safely, reliably, and at a scale.
Thank you, everyone.