Speaker 19: Hello, good
morning, good evening, everyone.
My name is Venkata Suresh Babu Kamma, and
I represent Star Group Innovations LLC.
Today, I'll be presenting a modern
approach towards transforming financial
governance systems from reactive reporting
environments into predictive AI-embedded
governance frameworks using Go.
In many enterprises today, and
en-enterprise environments today,
especially across Oracle Cloud
PPM, grants, and capital projects,
and large-scale portfolios,
organizations still rely
heavily on financial governance.
By the time projects, risks, billing
gaps, compliance issues, or budget
overruns are discovered, the financial
impact has already been occurred.
So I'll walk through-- walk you
through the problems with the
traditional governance, the predictive
governance model, why the Go is
highly effective for this problem,
the event-driven architecture, and
the business outcomes achieved.
So the overall goal is very simple.
This presentation enables organizations
to predict and prevent financial risk
instead of reacting after damage occurs.
So moving on to the next slide.
So let us begin with the
core industry problem.
So the traditional Oracle Cloud
industry-- the traditional Oracle Cloud
PPM environments still operate primarily
in retrospective reporting model rather
than real-time financial control.
This means organizations often
discover problems only after financial
thresholds are already breached.
The first major issue is cost overruns.
In many projects, overspending
becomes visible only after budget
thresholds are exceeded, leaving
very limited recovery options.
The second issue is revenue leakage.
So missed billing opportunities
frequently go unnoticed until
financial cycle closes, making
revenue recovery extremely difficult.
The third issue is compliance violations.
Modern organizations operate under
increasingly complex regulatory
environments involving federal grants,
AC six thousand six-- six hundred
and six compliance, contract-specific
rules, and audit requirements.
Traditional post-ad hoc approaches--
audit approaches are no longer sufficient.
Organizations require proactive governance
systems capable of preventing issues
before transactions even enter the ledger.
This is the exact challenge
Predictive Governance aims to solve.
Moving on to the next slide.
What Predictive Governance looks like.
Now let's discuss the target state.
Predictive governance moves organizations
away from retrospective reporting towards
the anticipatory real-time control.
Instead of waiting for financial
reporting cycles, machine learning
interference becomes embedded directly
into the project financial workflows.
One important design principle here is
zero modifications to Oracle Cloud itself.
The intelligence layer operates extremely
through scalable Go-based services.
The framework supports four
major predictive capabilities.
The first one, as I mentioned
in the slide, is the real-time
transaction validation.
The transactions are validated
continuously as they occur.
The second one is the predictive burn
rate analysis, so which means AI models
forecast funding consumption patterns
before budget exposure materializes.
The third is intelligent
revenue recognition monitoring.
So this framework continuously
detects missed billing
opportunities and timing risks.
The fourth is forward-looking
portfolio risk assessment.
So instead of static dashboards,
executives receive predictive insights
into future project financial exposure.
This transforms governance into a
continuously learning and adaptive system.
Moving on to the next slide.
Why Go for this problem?
Now, the question becomes, why use
Go for this architecture at all?
The answer is because Go is exceptionally
well-suited for high-throughput,
event-driven financial governance systems.
So the first advantage is
the native concurrency.
Go's lightweight goroutines allow
thousands of workflows to execute
in parallel without overhead of
traditional threading models.
So this is critical when
processing large volumes of
project transactions in real time.
The second advantage is
efficient memory management.
Go's runtime supports predictable
low-latency processing, which is
extremely important for real-time
machine learning inference pipelines.
The third advantage is
the service orchestration.
Go enables highly scalable
microservice architectures with
clean service boundaries across large
enterprise project environments.
So the fourth advantage is no ERP lock-in.
So the Go service layer acts as a
clean integration seam, keeping the
framework portable and vendor-agnostic.
This means the same architecture
pattern Can be scalable
across multiple ERP systems.
It doesn't have to be just Oracle ERP.
So moving on to the next slide, the
five-layer event-driven architecture.
This slide presents the core
architecture of the framework.
The architecture is built around
an AI-driven backbone connecting
five intelligent layers.
The first layer is EPM events.
There these are the Oracle Cloud event
sources generating first, generating the
financial activity across the portfolio.
The second layer is API gateway.
The-- this Go-based ingress layer
handles routing, event intake,
orchestration, and service communication.
The third layer is validation.
The concurrent Go pipelines perform
real-time transaction checks before
downstream processing occurs.
The fourth layer is ML inference.
Machine learning models continuously
score events, detect anomalies, and
generate the predictive insights.
The fifth layer is a broader
intelligence and governance ecosystem.
The important concept here is
that Go-based APIs and concurrent
validation pipelines act as the
integration fabric across all layers
without modifying the ERP code.
This enables enterprise-scale predictive
governance with extremely high throughput.
So moving on to the next
slide, allowability engine,
allowability intelligence engine.
So this engine focuses on
pre-posting compliance environment.
Traditionally, compliance validation
happens after transaction is already
posted into the general ledger.
This framework changes
that approach entirely.
The allowability engine intercepts
the transactions before posting and
evaluates allowability rules in real time.
So the engine validates transactions
against federal grant regulations,
contract-specific cost structures,
compliance policies, and
organizational governance rules.
So concurrent Go microservices enabled
inside project financial workflows
perform these validations instantly.
So this prevents non-compliant
tasks from entering the large
the ledger in the first place.
Instead of reactive audits, organizations
achieve proactive governance enforcement.
So moving on to the next slide seven.
So forecast drift learning engine.
So the engine focuses continuously
improving the forecast accuracy.
The traditional forecasting models
degrade over time because project
conditions continuously change, and
static forecasts eventually drift
away from operational reality So the
forecast drift learning engine solves
this problem by learning from historical
behavior patterns across the portfolio.
So machine learning models continuously
analyze the spend behavior, resource
utilization, funding consumption, and
historical pro forecasting or deviations.
So these models calibrate or recalibrate
future projections before forecast drifts,
drift becomes major financial deviation.
So the engine operates directly
within Oracle Cloud PPM workflows
or the financial workflows
through Go-based microservices.
Over time, the framework produces
compounding improvements in forecast
accuracy across the enterprise portfolio.
Moving on to the next slide.
Funding to forecast intelligence.
This engine focuses on predictive
burn rate risk analysis across
complex multi-award portfolios.
Many organizations operate in environments
where multiple grants, contracts, or
funding awards overlap simultaneously.
So many organizations operate in
environments where overlap... Sorry.
Many organizations operate in
environments where multiple grants
funding awards overlap simultaneously.
So this creates high complex
funding management challenges.
The funding to forecast intelligence
engine continuously predict the burn
rate exposure across the portfolio.
It performs the predictive funding
analysis, early warning detection,
funding gap identification, and
overrun trajectory forecasting.
One important capability
is portfolio rebalancing.
So the engine can recommend funding
reallocations across awards before overrun
risks escalate into financial exposure.
So this allows companies to proactively
manage the funding rather than funding
health, I would say, rather than
reacting after the exhaustion occurs.
So moving on to the next slide,
the streaming detection of
missed billing opportunities.
So this engine addresses
one of the largest causes of
enterprise revenue leakage.
In traditional systems, missed billing
opportunities are often identified only
during the month-end reconciliation.
So this framework performs
continuous streaming transaction
analysis in real time.
So this engine detects unbilled
milestones, missed cost transfers, revenue
recognition timing violations, and ASC
six zero six compliance checks So the Go
concurrent pipelines process transaction
streams continuously as events occur.
This allows intelligent revenue
recognition monitoring to become embedded
directly within the operational workflows.
So the result is faster billing
cycles, improved revenue capture,
and reduced financial leakage.
So go on to the next slide.
So the decision intelligence layer.
This layer transforms operational
signals into executive-level
predictive learning or planning.
So instead of only displaying the
historical dashboards this framework
provides executive foresight as well.
So the first capability is
scenario modeling, so the leaders
can test assumptions and explore
multiple what-if scenarios.
The f-- the second capability
is portfolio risk assessment.
So this framework identifies
which projects require attention
before exposure escalates.
The third capability is
predictive simulations.
AI projects future outcomes across
multiple financial pathways to support
faster and more informed decision-making.
So the fourth is strategic planning.
So forecast insights become actionable
governance recommendations for
capital allocation, executive
planning, and portfolio optimization.
This layer bridges operational
intelligence with executive
governance strategy.
Move on to the next slide.
So this slide focuses on
implementation patterns used
within the runtime architecture.
So the framework is
powered by high-performance
concurrent Go microservices.
So each intel-intelligent engine
exposes the clean API boundaries,
enabling the scalable deployment.
The first pattern is concurrent
va-- validation pipelines.
So Go-based routine fan-out
enables parallel transaction
evaluation during the ingestion.
So the second pattern is scalable
inter-inference services.
Go HTTP clients is scalable and also
communicate with the machine learning
endpoints seamlessly in a stateless
horizontally scalable architectures.
So the third pattern is
event-driven integration.
So Go-based APIs consume Oracle
event cloud streams without
requiring ERP side customizations.
So these implementation patterns
Allow anyone the to use the framework,
which is a scalable efficiently across
the enterprise financial ecosystems.
So next slide.
So this is a vendor agnostic,
as I mentioned before.
So this is a vendor agnostic
integration without ERP customization.
One of the most important
design principles of this
framework is portability.
The architecture introduces no invasive
modifications to Oracle Cloud itself.
So Oracle Cloud remains unchanged
and continues operating using the
standard APIs and event streams.
So AI machine learning inference,
validation logics, and governance
intelligence exist entirely
within the goal service layer.
So because of this separation, the
frameworks remains vendor agnostic.
That means these architectural patterns
can be extended beyond Oracle Cloud
PPM into any high throughput financial
ecosystems requiring predictive
intelligence and governance automation.
It's not just for Oracle Cloud PPM.
Moving on to the next slide.
Outcomes.
So the results across
large scale portfolios.
So this slide summarizes the
measurable outcomes achieved across the
enterprise scale por-- or portfolios.
The first major outcome
is billing acceleration.
So the real-time milestone
and cost transfer detection
improved the invoice cycle time
significantly for an organization.
So the second outcome is
improved revenue capture.
So any missed billing milestones,
billing opportunities were surfaced
before financial close periods.
This reduces revenue capture.
So missed... the third outcome
is forecast accuracy improvement.
As the forecast drift engine continuously
learn from the behavioral patterns in
the past projects or the past portfolios
related to that, forecasting accuracy
improved progressively over the time.
The fourth outcome is compliant
management improvement.
So the pre-posting environment reduced
compliance incidents, audit exposure,
and financial governance risk.
Overall, the framework demonstrated
measurable operational and financial
governance improvements across
large scale project portfolios.
Moving on to the next slide
Key takeaways.
So I would like to know-- I
would like to summarize the key
takeaways from this presentation.
The first key takeaway is that Go's
concurrency model is extremely well-suited
for highly throughput financial inference
models, and Go channels or Go routines
and channels provide highly scalable,
low latency processing capabilities.
The second takeaway is that machine
learning intelligence can be embedded
into financial workflows without modifying
the Oracle Cloud ERP system itself.
The third key takeaway is
that event-driven architecture
enables anticipatory governance.
So reacting to events as they occur
fundamentally changes the financial
governance capability altogether.
The fourth key takeaway is portability.
So these architectural patterns apply
beyond Oracle Cloud PPM to virtually
any enterprise financial ecosystem
requiring real-time intelligence.
This shift from the reactive governance
toward predictive governance is
not just a technology improvement.
It is a structural transformation in
any enterprise financial operations.
So moving on to the next slide.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Questions and discussions.
So thank you so much everyone for
your time and attention today.
I hope this session provided insight
into how AI machine learning,
event-driven architecture, and Go-based
concurrent systems can transform
project financial governance into
predictive intelligence ecosystems.
This framework demonstrates
that organizations can achieve
real-time governance, predictive
intelligence, compliance automation,
and scalable financial oversight
without any ERP customization.
I truly appreciate the opportunity
to present at the Conference
forty-two, Golang twenty twenty-six.
I would now be happy to take
your questions and discussions.
Thank you so much.
If you have any questions, please
reach out to vsureshkammu@gmail.com.
So I'm happy to answer any
questions that you may have.
Thanks a lot, guys.