Speaker 4: Hello, lovely people.
How are you doing today?
Welcome to CON forty-two
Golang twenty twenty-six.
My name is Emmanuella and
I am a solution architect.
I design secure, reliable, and
scalable solutions, AI solutions,
data solutions, and CI/CD solutions
across different organizations.
And today, I'll be discussing
a very important topic, which
has to do with security.
And the topic which I'll be
discussing today is building
secure CI/CD pipeline with Go.
This topic is very important because
it has to do with security, which
is a non-negotiable, and it also
has to do with the widely adopted
CI/CD pipeline automation flow.
And for this presentation, we have
thirty minutes, so I will try as
much as I can to be detailed enough
so anyone that wants to adopt the
solution can have a vast knowledge on
how to implement the solution in the
organization or in your personal project.
With that being said, the first slide
which I'll be talking about today is
CI/CD accelerates delivery but also risky,
which is very much true, and this is why.
Before I go into details, I will
talk about what CI is and what CD is.
CI stands for continuous integration,
while CD stands for continuous
delivery or continuous deployment.
And why this particular flow
automates or it's said to accelerate
delivery, it's because is in
a-- is it-- it is an automated
workflow that enable organizations
to ship code fast to deployment.
But it is risky.
Yes, this CI/CD pipeline automation
flow is risky if the necessary
security measures are not
implemented into the pipeline.
It could lead to security vulnerability.
And in today's organization, a
lot of organizations are adopting
different solution and integrating
them into their pipeline.
While existing tools Fail is
because some of these tools are
static, give static analysis.
They look out for just a particular
vulnerability which does not really gives
a detailed policy of the organization.
Why some of these tool are AI standalone?
Yes.
AI standalone tool will fail
because AI alone doesn't know
your organization policy.
It doesn't know what to look out for.
So for it to work, it needs a dif- a
detailed policy implemented into the
pipeline, which it will then use to
analyze and check out for vulnerability.
So this is why I say a
standalone AI tool will fail.
To solve this particular solution,
to solve this particular concern,
I designed a solution, and what the
solution does is it enable developers
organization to build a secure CI/CD
pipeline and respond to incident fast.
This solution is built using the GitHub.
In your case, you might be
using a different platform or
platform collaboration or a
different platform, which is okay.
It's still the same flow
or the same process.
Whichever platform or code platform,
code management platform that
your organization might be using,
it is still the same process.
But in this case, I use the GitHub.
Now, what is GitHub?
GitHub is a platform used widely
by developers to store code,
manage code, and also collaborate.
And my solution repo contains the
workflow, which is a detailed step of what
I have inputted for my CI/CD automation.
And it also contains the
architecture of the solution.
The repo also contains a detailed policy
of what I have imputed for the agent
to scan and look out for vulnerability.
This repo also contains a detailed
README file, which gives you a
get started step-by-step process.
For anyone watching that wants to
adopt the solution, you could go to
GitHub and search for cloud cloud
architect Emma, and the name of the
repo is GoCICD Security Guardrail.
You're going to have a detailed
step-by-step repo with me where you can
actually use to implement the solution
as a project or in your organization.
This is the of architecture
of the solution.
I'm going to walk you through how
the architecture flow and for you
to know how you can adopt it, the
s-- each steps, what they do, and
why it is actually in the pipeline.
The first step, which is number one step,
is once a developer pushes a code to their
repo, for my case, in this architecture,
it is stated GitHub repo, but feel free to
use any repo that is being used by your...
for you in your personal project or is
that is being used in your organization.
It is still the same step.
And now, once it's the code is
pushed to the repo, the rep, the,
it, the repo triggers the workflow.
Now, this workflow has a detailed work
steps of what I want my pipeline to run.
And also, in this work, in this
workflow, my agent is integrated.
Now, my agent is integrated with a
detailed policy of what I want the
agent to scan and to look out for.
So in this solution, the policy
which I integrated into my workflow
is the security detection, pattern
scanning, and policy validation.
So this is the policy which
I stated in the workflow for
the agent to look out for.
And for this solution,
I use the GPT o four.
Now, if GPT o four scan the workflow and
did not detect any vulnerability based
on my input, it is going to push the code
to deployment But if it detects any of
these vulnerabilities, the pipeline fails.
It stops the pipeline.
And when the pipeline fails, it
sends a detailed analysis of why the
pipeline actually failed, and a quick
fix recommendation for developers,
cloud engineers, anyone that is
responsible for the pipeline to fix
the issues immediately and fast.
So this is why... Now you see why I say
AI standalone agents cannot work because
it needs a human input to, one, input the
policy which the AI would or the agent
would have to look out for, and also needs
a human input to respond to the incident.
And how the solution works.
First, the agent scans the code.
If the code check against rules, if it's
the code is safe, it pushes to deployment.
If the code is not safe, it stops the code
and sends a detailed analysis to the Slack
team which I integrated into the platform.
I'm going to show a demo which I
actually did for this solution, how
it stops a security vulnerability
which it detected in the platform.
Now, this is the workflow which I ran.
The first one, you could see the
first one workflow ran successfully.
And the reason why the flow ran
successfully was because the
agent did not detect any security
vulnerability based on the policy
which is stated in the pipeline.
You could see the second one failed.
The second workflow failed because the
agent detected a security vulnerability.
Here is a detailed security measure.
Here is a detailed security
analysis which it detected.
Now you could see that it stopped
because it detected a, an API
key inputted in one of the files.
And when it detected this particular
vulnerability, it stopped the
pipeline and then sent a detailed
analysis to the Slack, which I
integrated into the workflow.
And now the analysis it sends to
Slack is, one, why it failed Which
line failed and why it failed.
It stated API key failed and the
quick fix for this recommendation, it
also recommended a quick fix for the
developer to jump into and fix the code.
It said, "Remove hard coded secrets
and use environment variables."
See easy and easy for the developer or
anyone responsible for this pipeline to
fix the problem without trying to figure
out where the problem or what actually
occurred or made the pipeline to fail.
Lesson learned for this solution, which
I actually built is number one, AI
standalone needs human inputs, so human
data, human inputs, your organization
policy detailed, listed in the pipeline
so it knows what to look out for.
So it doesn't actually ignore what
your organization securities are.
And another lesson which I
learned from this solution is
that AI accelerates workflows.
In other words, it helps humans, it help
us developers, it help cloud engineers
to respond fast to issues without trying
to go analyze all of the code and figure
out where the issue is coming from.
And for future implementation you
could implement or you could put
multiple languages to support your
pipeline policies, or you could
actually implement the solution
in your cloud integration as well.
So feel free to implement these
improvements in your own projects
or when us-utilizing it in your
organization CI/CD pipeline.
And resources used in this solutions
are, I used to go some resource GitHub
And DevSecOps and also the Slack.
Slack was used into the solution.
Slack API was im-inputted or integrated
into the pipeline, which enables
the AI to send the detailed analysis
which you saw earlier into the
organization workflow, which gives
a detailed response and a detail...
and a means for developers to
respond fast to vulnerability.
So this is the solution, and I
hope this solution is going to help
someone out there with which, w- who
is trying to figure out on how to
make their CI/CD pipeline secure.
And you feel free to adopt the
solutions and feel free to chat me up
on LinkedIn or GitHub and tell me of
any solution to which you would like
me to design or also discuss in future.
And thank you for this, and bye.
See you next time.