Hello, everyone.
A warm welcome to Conf42,
Incident Management 2024.
Thank you all for joining me
today for my presentation.
My name is Prakash Oja, and the
topic of my presentation today is
AI Driven Code Review and Quality
Assurance, Revolutionizing Software
Development, A New Era in Software
Engineering, Efficiency and Quality.
AI really has taken the world by
storm over the last few years.
It has become an inescapable
part of the software development
landscape, including code review.
you cannot just avoid hearing about it.
AI offers unique opportunities
to revolutionize quality
assurance, ushering in an era of
higher efficiency and quality.
presentation today is divided
into the following sections.
About the paradigm shift that's happening
in software development due to AI.
Why do we need AI in code review?
The key benefits of AI driven code review.
How is AI transforming testing with
its presence in quality assurance?
How do we quantify the AI revolution?
What are the metrics for success?
And then we'll move on to real world
application of AI driven code review.
What are the challenges and
considerations with AI driven code review?
The future of AI driven
software development.
And finally, I'll be offering
my concluding remarks.
paradigm shift in software development
The software development landscape is
undergoing a profound, a significant
transformation due to the rapid
advancement in artificial intelligence
and machine learning technologies.
Every day, you have new AI tools
coming out and they are each
more advanced than the others.
Traditionally, developers have relied
on manual code reviews and human
driven quality assurance processes.
Which, while effective, are
slow due to their very nature.
They are prone to errors and
they are very resource intensive.
AI driven tools are now enabling
software development teams
to automate these processes.
AI tools can analyze vast
amounts of code in real time.
They can detect patterns that would
likely go unnoticed by human reviewers.
and they provide immediate feedback
during the development itself.
This shift towards AI powered
development is not only enhancing the
accuracy and speed of code reviews,
but also revolutionizing how software
is developed, tested, and maintained,
paving the way for higher productivity.
And a better quality products.
need for AI in code review.
The challenges of manual code review.
Traditional code review processes rely
on developers manually checking each
other's code for issues like bugs.
performance bottlenecks and
security vulnerabilities.
This method is effective in smaller
codebase, but as the codebase grows
larger and larger, it becomes inefficient.
AI as a solution.
There are tools such as
Amazon CodeGuru and DeepCode.
That lever is advanced algorithms to
automate this process of reviewing
the code allowing for faster
and more accurate code analysis.
These tools can scan through thousands
of lines of codes in minutes,
identifying issues such as memory leaks,
inefficient algorithms, improper error
handling, and security vulnerabilities
with a very high level of precision.
What are the impacts of
AI tools in software development?
The AI driven code reviews reduce
the time by 75%, up to 75%.
this allows for faster iteration
of development, quicker delivery
of features, new features, and
quicker delivery, for bug fixes.
And not only do these tools catch common
errors, But they can also learn from the
past reviews, improving their ability
to detect complex issues over time.
So as the time goes, they
get better and better.
They improve further.
What are the key benefits
of AI driven code review?
First of all, enhanced code quality.
AI tools continuously learn from
fast code repositories, identifying
potential problems, and with greater
accuracy than traditional methods.
They improve the development
lifecycle, making them faster.
By automating reviews, AI allows
teams to iterate faster while
maintaining a high quality without
compromising on the quality.
AI, can also offer predictive analytics.
AI uses historical data to
predict potential bottlenecks
and bugs before they can happen.
This allows developers to be proactive.
How is AI, in quality
assurance transforming testing?
AI automates test case generation,
prioritizes tests based on recent
code changes, and it enables
self healing tests that adapt to
changes in UI or code structure.
AI can also analyze historical test data
to predict areas of the code most likely
to contain bugs, allowing QA teams to
focus their effort more efficiently.
offers enhanced test code coverage.
AI driven testing tools automatically
generate diverse sets of test cases and
they ensure that edge cases and rare
scenarios are adequately covered, which
can get missed by a human reviewer.
This leads to more, more
comprehensive testing and
higher overall code reliability.
Traditional testing methods focus on
predefined cases, which means they can
miss potential bugs that can arise from,
uncommon user behaviors or interactions.
How do we quantify the AI revolution?
How do we measure the
success, the matrices?
first of all, the bug detection rate.
AI driven tools improve
bug detection rate by 35.
7%.
Identifying subtle issues that
manual reviews often miss.
Development cycle time.
AI reduces development cycles by 33.
3 by one third.
This allows teams to
shift features faster.
Code review time.
AI automates review process,
cutting review times by 75%.
Test case generation time.
Automated testing powered by
AI reduces the time spent on
test case generation by 75%.
About by three quarters of time
leading to quicker iterations
and better test coverage.
And finally, develop
developer productivity.
Developers can write up to 50 percent more
lines of code per day with AI support.
They can now focus on more complex
and more value added tasks.
What are the real world applications
of AI driven code review?
Real world applications of AI driven
tools like Amazon's CodeGuru have
significantly impacted organizations
by improving the quality of code
and reducing system downtime.
For example, Amazon CodeGuru alone
has identified, it has been found
to have identified 90 percent of
the critical issues in the code.
leading to a 50 percent
reduction in downtime.
These AI tools can scale across
large projects, helping organizations
ensure code consistency and security.
with AI tools, we also have some
challenges and some considerations,
primarily adoption barriers.
In order to adopt AI tools, teams must
invest in training and infrastructure
to effectively integrate AI driven tools
into existing development environment.
And this is not easy.
Tool integration.
The ability of AI tools to learn
from a unique code base requires
continuous improvement and maintenance.
This requires, time and effort.
Continuous learning.
AI tools need constant training
and updates as they encounter
new coding patterns, ensuring
their long term effectiveness.
The future of AI driven
software development.
As AI evolves, it will become
increasingly embedded in every aspect
of the software development lifecycle.
including CICD, productive maintenance,
and automated cost standardization.
AI driven personalized developer
environments and tools enable
faster, more creative software
development while maintaining very
high standard of quality and security.
Future advancement will continue to reduce
development cycle times, increase code
quality, and enable faster time to market.
Finally, the concluding remarks.
Artificial intelligence is not
just enhancing software development
processes, it's transforming them.
The ability of AI driven tools
to accelerate development cycles,
enhance code quality, and improve
overall productivity is already making
waves across the software industry.
AI powered code review and
quality assurance processes are
bringing unprecedented levels of
efficiency and accuracy to teams.
Allowing the developers to focus
on higher value, creative problem
solving tasks as more and more mundane
tasks is being delegated to AI.
As AI continues to evolve and
mature, it will become an essential
part of the software development
lifecycle, delivering smarter,
faster, and more reliable software.
Organizations that adopt AI driven
tools will not only improve their
development workflows, But also
gain a competitive advantage by
delivering higher quality products.
you very much for joining me today.