Today's talk is, what
can possibly go wrong?
Lessons in building resilient systems.
The motivation of this talk is
that we all know the cost of
maintenance and software is huge.
and we all know that the outage
sucks for everyone, especially the
on calls to wake up in the middle of
the night, solving sets, thinking,
what am I doing with my life?
You might be waking up your
neighbors, yourself, your spouse,
your dogs, it's not a pretty scene.
And the question I keep asking
myself is how can we prevent outage
from happening in the first place?
And this talk will talk about a few,
real life scenarios and the lessons we'll
learn and we'll put it all together on
how do we build resilient, software.
Let's first start with real
step happen and their lessons.
The first one is flood of traffic.
You get alert about CPU near 100 percent
of your host, followed by availability
drop, high client side error rate.
The background can be there is
unpredictable side wide event
with just simply more traffic.
We're sending traffic
to you, more traffic.
And then you're seeing in auto scaling,
Panel, if you're using cloud provider
that the host keep getting replaced
because they failed health check
and you're like, what's going on?
I'm just getting more host
to it, but they keep failing.
The host stays down.
and then you see that the host is down
because it failed the health check.
So when the host has 100 percent CPU,
it cannot respond pin back to the.
Out of scaling service and out of scaling,
console will think your host is done.
So you really can't spin
up any host back on.
What do you do then?
you can, you might then realize that
you just have dropped traffic for
it to do, for the host to spin back
on when host doesn't get traffic.
It doesn't go down for 200 percent
CPU, so you can draw traffic and you
can just a mass connection to the
host that instead of getting all these
connection to your host that you cannot
handle, you can set a mass connection
to handle only the connections you're
possible to have for your host.
The lesson here is that, for the long
term, you should do a load testing on max
connection a host can possibly handle.
So you don't run into issues of a host
getting too much traffic and lead to
100 percent CPU on your host, and you
cannot spin up any host because it keep
going down because of the traffic, right?
It's a Really, bad loop
of, of situation here.
The next one is a retry storm.
So this, you can get alert or something
like client bill ability below X percent.
and then if you take a little closer,
you see the traffic goes up very high
and, And the crux of the problem here
is that a lot of services like to see,
when they see error, then they retry.
So if each microservices
retries, the number of calls
to database will then multiply.
let's take this example on the right here.
So you have, let's say, a
site calls the service once.
Service 1 calls service 2, and
service 2 calls the database, and
the database says it's not available.
And then service 2 retries two
times, and it's still not available.
So you go back to service 1
saying it's not available.
Service 1 says it's not available.
Let me retry two times, so it
goes back to service two for
each of those service requests.
It retries two times again, so the
total retry now becomes six times.
And just imagine if you have
more services in between and more
retries for those services, this
can easily multiply and multiply.
And then the service at the bottom
layer will get overwhelmed, cannot
handle any possible traffic.
The mitigation here, happened along
the big shopping events that it was
to drop majority of the traffic,
significant dropping traffic to
mitigate this, and later added, retry
configuration changes and more hosts.
So the lesson here is to really
standardize retry logic, such as
exponential retry, respect to too
many requests, HTTP code, and also,
add circuit breaker for dependency.
The circuit breakers are ways to say,
hey, dependency getting too many errors.
I just stopped calling that
dependency because I don't want to.
Make matter even worse for that dependency
and being good citizens of not causing
a retry storm to, services downstream.
This one is about Plan B went poorly.
So a letter you might get as dependency
availability below X percent.
So sometimes there are more than one
dependencies to satisfy what we need.
in the case of circuit breakers, if there
is a trouble dependency, we send back.
Traffic to another dependency
now dependency be also service
on traffic in many cases.
So dependency be what you immediately
go down because it's unable to handle
this newly, send traffic and cost
problem to services using dependency be.
So it may matter worse.
Not only your service not working,
you also make other services failing.
So the mitigation here is to really focus
on fixing dependency A, and, try to fix
what's issue in there, and, A lesson here
for the long term is to not introduce
a backup dependency unless it's really
been prepared well enough, such as acting
as a lever for high velocity events.
And, in day to day operation,
focus on the plan A that will
get your service up and running.
The next one is a very common one.
It's a back commit.
An alert you might be getting is
server availability dropped 100%.
A back commit that can go out of
production is not really the fault
of the commit owner, but rather
lack of proper process to prevent it
from happening in the first place.
You think about lines of defenses, right?
So you have code review, You have
testing that covers all aspects of the
flow, such as unit testing, end to end
testing, menu testing, QA testing, right?
And the list goes on.
The testing did not catch any of this.
And there are the gatings that
people typically add to make sure
you can flip it back or flip it on
and monitor the feature releases.
And there are things like change
management, risk assessments, and
there are pipelines to get all
these changes, put it all together.
So let me ask you this.
If you have all of this and still cannot
catch the bad commit, is it really the
fault of the person writing the commit?
Especially that hasn't happened before?
No, right?
So every time there's a bad commit exposed
to something that's missing, is it?
Did this commit somehow bypass a
code review that did not catch this?
This can happen.
Did it?
Not have a proper testing or the, or
did not follow the guardrail of what's
necessary to push those changes out.
And somehow we miss all this.
So every bad commit actually carries
some positive lesson for you to reflect
what was missing in the release process
and how you, how can we catch this and
prevent it from happening in the future.
So in many ways bad commit is
actually a good way to improve your
resilience, resiliency in your services.
Now, the next one is lack
of sufficient ownerships.
This one sometimes can be comical.
You might receive an escalation of
people asking you, hey, user reported
they are able to use this feature.
And you're thinking, what is this feature?
I never heard about it.
And then after some back and forth,
You're actually the team owning this
change and feature and, you have
to fix it and also be accountable
for the, for the set of impact.
So sometimes this can happen when
there is a team changes, the, some code
don't have sufficient ownership, and
this can get to a very bad situations.
so you don't, you want to wait
that, all right, you want to
really make sure there's a process
of transferring co ownership.
You want to make sure there
is sufficient annotations.
Of co ownership, whether that's
in code, whether that's tooling,
whether that's wiki, can all help
you to avoid this, from happening.
S script is also very notorious,
some of the very best apps are
because of people running scripts
and not testing as efficiently.
Alright, you might get an alert saying
system's down at 0 percent availability,
you're wondering what's going on.
And it turned out to be a script
reference in the wrong book
that was not tested thoroughly.
And, the lesson here is to really treat
the production impacting scripts or
changes the same rigor as production
commitments, such as sufficient
testing, QAs, and proper code reviews.
because remember, production changes
are all very risky, and if you
don't test your script properly.
Something bad can happen, especially
if it's, in the wrong book, that people
are very likely to execute that script.
So make sure you have the
script tested or any production
impacting changes tested properly.
Okay, now let's talk about the
next topic, which is, prevention.
Let's put everything together.
The first thing is to have A defensive
coding practices, a lot of the, that's
can actually prevent it if you have,
a lot of defensive coding practices.
But the 1st 1 is to pay your
changes in many companies, people
typically get their changes inside.
some gating so you can use
some service side knobs to
increase allocation over time.
This is a great way to
quickly roll back and
also gradually roll out.
So you don't impact as many users.
Impact radius will be relatively small.
And remember to log any exceptions.
Corner cases and also remember to have
critical information in your login.
If you don't have critical information,
sometimes people have to actually
make that code changes right away.
And with deployment to finish,
you don't want that to happen
and do not overly rely on backup options.
Like the example I mentioned earlier, it's
better to fail fast and focus on plan A.
I've seen this many times, like
some of the steps are just because.
It doesn't have proper error handling.
This can be like no pointer exceptions.
In Java that happens a lot.
So make sure you have, no
safe, coding practices.
if you're using a more, no
safe languages like Kotlin,
you wouldn't have this problem.
A lot of modern code, programming
languages have this nowadays.
remember send a timeout.
So if you're a service calling a
dependency and you don't have a
timeout and a dependency doesn't
have a timeout either, then you got
a situation where it hanks, right?
So you want to away that from happening.
And last thing I want to remind is
having a good retry practice, use
exponential retry, and then, use it
very sparingly to avoid a retry storm.
The next session we'll
talk about is detections.
This has three parts.
The first part is alerts.
So for alerts, having an operational goal
is very important when setting alerts.
So why you're setting alerts is
to make sure, is it availability
wise, you want to meet a 99.
99 percent availability, or higher or
lower, or is it about latency, your
service is committed to, what's the
service, Level agreements, SLA you have,
and based on these operational goal,
you can set a reasonable thresholds
and you want to really find the balance
between noisy alerts and the misalerts.
If you have a very strict threshold,
you will have very noisy alerts.
If you have a relaxed one,
you will have misalerts.
And you can also use the historical
data to inform the alert threshold.
What was it before?
What do we generally need?
What's a reasonable threshold so we
don't get too many alerts or misalerts?
Alerts should have a round table
to cover common steps on what to
do and lessons from past scenarios.
when you're getting alerts, on calls,
you should not be thinking what to do.
You should have a plan.
Concrete run books with the
links and steps what to do.
It should not be thinking too much.
3am stuff shouldn't be
needing any thinking.
Neither are you capable of
doing something like that.
And dashboard offers a different,
benefits and the compliments
alerts a lot, in my opinion,
inform people about general trends.
This can be a seasonal patterns.
It can help to debug and find
correlations of what's happening.
Also, in your dashboard, you should
have a clear name, time period,
and useful references or markers.
This can be alert set criterias,
week over week changes.
And as part of your operational goal, you
should also know your system limitations.
If you don't know your system limitation,
you're awaiting a set to happen.
So you want to know what's
the maximum you can support.
If you're online shopping, you want to
know how many orders you can support.
If you're running a social media
company, you want to know how many
users you can concurrently support.
And you can know this limitation by
doing load testing and prepare yourself
for dependency failures or Other type
of failures by doing chaos testing.
So mitigation, when you get
alerts, a mitigation is like
saving life in emergency room.
Time is essence here.
You're running against time.
So follow the wrong book.
Do not have your random
thoughts to a brainstorming.
What's happening?
Follow the wrong book.
Look at your alerts and dashboard.
A few questions you can think about
is it happening at a specific time?
Does it line up with a specific
commit, aversions, or gating changes?
Is there any exceptional logs or
metrics to pinpoint specific files?
Are there related issues identified
by other teams at the same time?
Is it company wide events?
Do you need escalation?
and there are also times where
you can prepare for, you need to
prepare for high velocity events.
So what are the high velocity events?
So high velocity events
are dangerous times.
you can think about it as, you know,
of, something you want to prepare for.
So this can be an anticipated
large increase of traffic.
Let's say It's prime day, or if
it is a feature release of a major
feature release, you have a lot
of traffic going to your service.
In those cases, you will have
a risk mitigation plan based on
factors such as traffic estimations.
the risk sometimes it can be beyond just
operational, it can be about integrity,
it can be about media risk, PR risk.
in any cases, you need to set up
dashboards and learn specifically
and pay very close attention to
critical metrics to monitors and the
deltas that this advance will bring.
you should also have levers
for the worst case scenarios.
so the levers can be, hey, if
traffic is two times my expectation,
what would I do in that case?
How to, how am I able to
accommodate all that traffic?
And this is also a great
time to audit your services.
so rerun your load test, chaos
testing, reassess your levers, think
about what things can go wrong, do
a check on your, service health.
Now, when Seth is finished.
self review or sometimes in some
companies it can be called other names.
But the essence is that you
will review the self, as a
person who went for on call.
The self review is intended
to be a learning experience.
It's supposed to be blameless.
after the self, you want to,
write a report that includes
the timeline of the events.
When did it happen?
When did we detect it?
When did we start?
root causing it and, mitigate this,
and all these timelines so we can
match and find out how we can improve
on these timelines, such as quicker
time to detect and quicker time
to root cause, mitigate the set.
for the root cause 1, Useful
exercises, think in terms of why, so
for example, your service is down.
Why is your service down?
Because there's a memory
leak in your host.
Why is there a memory leak?
because there's a bad commit that
introduced a memory leak, in productions.
And why did this memory
end up in production?
Because we did not have proper load
testing to catch memory leak issues.
Why did we not have that?
the load has, and then that comes to
your action item to add the load has,
and the proper guidelines and action item
prevented from happening in the future.
in general, you want to focus on, the
next steps and action items, making
sure those action items are tracked,
making sure there's a timeline for when
those action items will be finished,
because if there's no action items, All
this learning is for nothing, right?
You need to find ways to
prevent it from happening.
very rare cases is that
this is act of God.
There is no possible
action items you can take.
And at the end of the day, self review is
really a place to foster, this continuous
improvements to make sure that people
are aware, we can build a resilient
systems and we're able to, make it
better, make our own cause like better.
yeah, that's end of the talk.
I want to thank you for
attending this talk.
And hopefully there's
some takeaways, you get.
Out of this talk, and, hopefully you
have fewer steps next time you're
going on call, following some of the,
lessons we discussed in this sessions.
yeah, thank you.