Hi, my name is Ndubuisi Obirije.
I'm the co founder and CTO of Afreex.
welcome to my session.
on discomfort to incident
management conference.
I'll be talking about AI power
detection and monitoring of social
engineering driven fraudulent
payments and remittances.
let's start with the growing
threats of remittance fintech.
social engineering, is a situation where,
there's a manipulation of individuals to
gain access to sensitive information, or
perform actions that benefit a fraudster.
in the remittance world, this could
involve, tracking someone, into,
tracking someone in their email, and
also tricking them to give access,
give the fraudulent or the fraudster
access, to, an innocent, person's
email, social media pages, et cetera.
And basically once this is done, you.
It essentially tricks, the
victim into authorizing
payments, for these fraudsters.
social engineering is
like a circle, right?
usually fraudsters start by
gathering information, right?
After gathering information, they
could, send you a phishing email.
they could buy data online,
of their potential victims.
And then once they've done that, they
now establish relationships, right?
they try to get in touch
with their victims.
and to establish like a connection, right?
So the victims don't become suspicious
at all when the exploitation starts.
So after establishing relationship,
it goes on to exploitation.
So at this stage, the victims
don't realize they are, they're
in the nets of this fraudsters.
and then the next thing is
execution, those fraudsters.
execute their plan, it could be to,
trick the customers, trick the victims
into making a payment online through
Amazon, through eBay, et cetera.
but before we start going deep into,
what these explanations are, let's
look at AI in fintech, let's look at
some key statistics, of what the impact
of AI, have right now in the sector.
basically it's transforming
the sector as it's called.
We've seen chat GPT, we've seen,
cloud, from Entropiq and the
other, LLMs out there today.
And this AI can help give us valuable
insight into the adoption of, FinTech.
And I think it's just the, it's just
the tip of the iceberg right now.
Some of the key things we've, we've
seen is, there's exploitative,
explosive growth, right?
the global fintech market is
currently worth 340 billion, with
the AI segment valued at 44 billion.
Now, the AI share in fintech is expected
to reach 50 billion over the next five
years, and then there's widespread
adaptation, 72 percent of companies that
utilize, utilizes AI, in one of their
key business functions, And others are
planning to even expand to use it and
expand on, using data technologies and
AI technologies for their businesses.
Now, also it's helps in key cost savings.
Implementing AI in businesses.
We have seen that, it saves companies,
businesses, millions of dollars.
So it's, for example, implementing
identity verification for banks
is projected to 900 million in
operational costs reduction.
this is massive, right?
Onboarding process are now digital
and onboarding process would be
close to 29 million hours, in, in, in
onboarding process for banks and most
key fintechs today, this is massive.
And this also improves the customer
service, section of these companies.
we can see charts boards, That
started years ago, we've seen
virtual assistants, from, chat GPT,
real time, voice communication.
I'm excited, and I think the
feature is exciting for real
time customer interactions.
it reduces cost of inquiries.
then there's enhanced.
Efficiency in the every time to
spend, every time spent by digital
onboarding have drastically
reduced by 30%, thanks to AI.
So these are like highlighting
some of the potential of, of AI
in our financial space, today.
now let's talk back to what's
back to what we're thinking about.
fraud stars and fraud lend transactions.
So what are financial crimes?
today.
So there's financial crime
and then there's compliance.
Now, financial crime isn't any
activity that involves financial gain.
by using illegal means, even if it
means hiding some processes from, their
victims, that is a financial crime and
then the compliance side, financial
compliance is when organizations
deploy in a strategies to prevent,
Financial crimes, strategies and reports
to prevent any illegal, activity.
Now, the, some of the shocking
statistics today is that there have
been over 800 billion to 2 trillion
worth of money laundry globally.
this is unprecedented.
And we are seeing this
number increase yearly.
And you know, the interesting
thing is this is not going to stop.
we don't have the capacity, the human
capacity to stop, financial crimes
and laundering, but we have a savior.
I know it's a heavy word to say savior,
but we have a tool that can actually
help us prevent so many types of fraud.
For example, phishing.
identity thefts, these are like one of
the two, two basic and two core, ways in
a first that can, do financial crimes.
So phishing is basically an attempt
to collect sensitive information, like
username, password, bank information, etc.
identity theft.
Identity theft involves stealing
someone's personal information, some
for starts by credit cards, debit
cards, SSNs, IDs online, on, on forums,
and pose as this, as their victims.
Now, how do we leverage
AI to, to prevent this?
One, for phishing, with advanced machine
learning and algorithms, we can analyze
patterns of communication, right?
To, identify any phishing attempts, there
could be things like, the algorithms
that could check out for emails with
suspicion subjects and contacts.
And then this.
machines, this AI could alert, either
the owners or alerts companies,
especially when, this is targeted at
employees of a particular company.
And now for identity thefts, we can
leverage AI by, using current and
improving, identity verification
solutions, today, I think there's
a lot of room for improvements.
In identity verifications and AI is
there for us to, utilizes, utilize it.
Now, I know I've already
identified about two.
There are other types of other types,
which are not, they are also important,
but the two I initially mentioned
that like the core, these are like.
The, usually the first steps, for starts
try to, get, gain access to the victims.
Now, but there are other things
like money mulling, documents
forgery, accounts take over.
And, the interesting one, which
is most recent is deepfake.
we've seen the rise of, generative
AI, how it's easy to create deepfake
even in videos and in voice.
It's scary.
It's scary feature ahead, just as AI can
be used for, but it can also be used to
checkmate this, bad and, checkmate evil,
persons that want to use it for that.
no, I want to take a
breather and, highlights.
Some of the things I've seen, we've
seen in, in Nafra is my company,
we've seen over 80 percent accuracy
in flagging social engineering
attempts, in our platform.
This is huge, in less than three months
we deployed, AI solutions, to detect,
for the event activities, especially
such engineering, we've seen, we've seen
the patterns and we've identified those
patterns and AI is just there to automate
those patterns and catch them, and we've
seen 80 percent accuracy and we have saved
over 1 million in fraudulent transactions
in a very short period of time.
And we've also seen reduction in
false positives and investigative
time because, our compliance team
leverage, the transactions have been
flagged, but the potential, activity
that was flagged by our AI system.
it has really give, reduce
the investigation time
for our compliance team.
And, I know I've already spoken about,
the processes, or some of the activities
for stats and use, but just to break down
some of the common victims we've seen,
we've encountered, 70 plus years adults,
older adults, 70, and above, we've seen.
S fraudulent activities on this age group.
We've seen from 18 to 34 years,
we've seen from 34 to 50 and so on.
So every, age group does a
specific, they're all targets.
Everyone's a targets basically,
whether you're an older adult,
younger, your adults UA targets and.
it's not going to stop, it's
not going to stop anytime.
So, there have been surveys that
showcase, there's certain types of age
group that are susceptible to, fraud,
to fraud that are especially victims.
you can check that on my slide later.
So, to reiterate, I am very, I am
super excited on how AI solution
can combat financial cramps, it's
just, it's an emerging space.
None.
It's not a new, it's not a new
space, we've seen new emerging
technologies that is exciting.
to now advance the level of which
previous AI detections, is that, we can
now detect anomaly, we can now do real
time monitoring, we can do predictive
analytics, we can do network analytics
and with natural language processing,
we can now you know, for example,
someone who posed to be an African
American, but he's speaking like an
Asian American, from identity theft.
These are some of the things that AI
can detect and from natural language
processing and combats, those that poses
as other people, these are some of the
exciting things, we've seen out there.
So to wrap up, these are my key takeaway.
no one is immune.
Everyone
is, anyone, everyone can
fall victim for fraud.
Anyone can fall victim for fraud.
because criminals are opportunistic.
they target individuals from
all across every age group.
vulnerability vary also.
but we need awareness and education.
So we need to start.
Empowering individuals with the
knowledge on common scams, but at
the same time putting, air detection
systems in place that would, allow this
individuals when something goes wrong
so they can take preemptive actions.
so these are some of the things, I
would like us to take away from this
talk and things that I You know,
I'm excited, to, improve even in my
company, for others that are here.
so thank you very much
for, listening so far.
I hope, you've learned one or
two things on, and I'm excited.
you can say I'm really excited on in
this space and I'm hoping there, we'll
see companies, emerge that would.
efficiently leverage AI to combat fraud,
especially social engineering fraud.
Thank you very much.
I remain Nwc John Umberidje.
You can reach me at my
email, johninterface.
co.
if you have any further questions or,
you want to chat or you find this doc
interesting, or you can visit my website.
My company website afriaisapp.
com, Afrais is a platform
that helps immigrants to send
money back home from the U.
S., U.
K., we're in over 20 countries now.
Please visit, and I'm
excited for the future.
Thank you very much.