Hi, I'm Ravi Kamampati.
Welcome to this talk on Mastering Network
Resilience and Scalability through
Routing and Switching Fundamentals.
In today's session, we will cover the
fundamentals of routing and switching, key
technologies, advanced concepts, and how
these concepts are applied in industries.
By the end of this session, you will
have a clear understanding of how
routing and switching work together
to build a resilient network capable
of scaling to meet modern needs.
Now let's look at the, agenda, the
table of contents that I would like
to discuss on today's, conference.
first we would like to discuss about the
introduction to routing and switching.
The second goal is the layer two
switching and its fundamentals.
and the third one goes, some of the key
technologies that are used in switching.
The fourth goes the routing
fundamentals and core protocols.
the fifth goes the comparison of
routing, protocols and list of
different types of protocols that are
used in, widely across the industry.
And then, goes the synergy between the
routing and switching, the next goes the
advanced network design concepts that we
would like to discuss on, the last but not
the least is the industry applications,
to see where all of these protocols
and switching are being widely used.
And at the end, we would like to conclude,
based on the opinion that I have that
I would like to share with you guys.
All right, so let's begin with
discussing about some introduction
about routing and switching.
So in this slide, basically I
would like to introduce two core
concepts of routing and switching.
switching operates basically at layer
two of the OSA model, which basically
handles traffic within the local
area network by using a MAC address.
This basically ensures the data
is transmitted efficiently between
devices within the same network.
On the other hand, the routing operates
at layer three and connects different
networks by using an IP addresses.
This enables data transmission between
separate networks or across vast areas.
Together, routing and switching form
the foundation of, modern networks.
Understanding these concepts is
really crucial for incident management
where quick troubleshooting and
scalability are often required.
Now let's look into, some
of the layer 2 switching
fundamentals, to discuss in detail.
let's, dive a little bit
deeper into layer 2 switching.
where, which is essential for local
area networks, switching basically
learns the MAC addresses, learns
and uses the MAC addresses to
direct traffic, ensuring efficient
communication between the same network.
we'll also discuss VLANs, which
allows network segmentation, instead
of treating all devices in, as one
large group, VLANs basically break
down into smaller grou logical groups,
improving the performance and security.
next we talk about the trunking.
Trunking allows the traffic
from multiple VLANs to travel
over a single network link.
This is significant, this is significant
because it increases the efficiency and
also boosts, the network capability,
especially in large area networks.
Finally, we would like to, discuss about
the spanning tree protocol, which is
one of the important protocols, which is
also called as STP, basically prevents
network loops in redundant technologies,
ensuring the network, doesn't experience
any downtime due to repeated data flows.
All right.
So now let's look at some of
the key technologies that are
used in, switching technologies.
here we explore some of the key
technologies that are used in switching.
the one important thing is, as
we discussed before, the VLAN is
nothing but virtual area network, as
mentioned earlier, are critical, are
basically for network segmentation.
They help reduce broadcast storms,
keeping network traffic localized.
By grouping devices into VLANs,
administrator can basically manage
network traffic more efficiently and
reduce unnecessary data broadcast.
Trunking is the next key technology.
Trunking basically eliminates the need
for additional cabling by allowing VLANs
to use a single physical connection.
This makes your network more
efficient, especially when
managing a number of VLANs.
Each of these technologies basically
play a vital role in making the network
more scalable, efficient, and secure.
Now in this slide, let's
talk, more about routing.
until now we were discussing
about row switching.
And now let's switch our gears towards
routing and understand its core protocols
and its efficiency and need for, for
its need, need to use these protocols.
Routing unlike switching operates
at layer 3 and it is concerned with,
direct data across different networks.
So there are several key routing
protocols which are used for
serving, different purposes.
let's talk about OSPF,
which is the first protocol.
before we get into it, I would like
to list the different protocols.
I would like to give an
high, high level overview.
OSPF, Open Status Path First.
The next one is EIGRP, which is
Enhanced Interior Gateway Protocol.
The third one is BGP, which
is a Border Gateway Protocol.
The fourth one is nothing but MPLS,
which is Multi Protocol Label Switching.
In OSPF, is a widely used link
state protocol, basically suitable
for large, complex networks.
It offers quick convergence
and high scalability.
In EHRP is a Cisco proprietary protocol
known for its speed and efficiency.
BGP is a backbone of the internet.
It manages routing between
autonomous systems.
Allowing data to travel from one, one
network to other network across the globe.
in MPLS, it's a multi
protocol label switching.
It isn't a routing protocol per se, but
a technique which is used by the service
providers to optimize network traffic.
So these protocols are the heart
of network routing, enabling
data to travel quickly, securely,
and efficiently across networks.
So now let's do some comparison between
the protocols that we just discussed now.
in OSPF, OSPF is basically ideal for
large enterprise networks and service
providers where it's for fast convergence
and scalability making it's a top choice.
In EIGRP, as I mentioned, it is designed
for Cisco networks offering quick
convergence and efficient bandwidth usage.
It's highly efficient in terms
of computational resources.
BGP powers the internet allowing for
the policy based routing and managing
connections across different networks.
It's highly scalable, but
requires careful configuration.
MPLS is used in service
provider networks to optimize
traffic and offer VPN services.
Understanding the strengths and
weaknesses of each protocol helps
network professionals choose the
right one for its infrastructure.
All right.
So let's talk about the synergy
between the routing and switching.
Routing and switching, are
basically, aren't basically, two
different separate processes.
They basically work in tandem to ensure,
smooth data transmission across networks.
While switching handles traffic
with the local area, routing,
connects different networks.
Together, they are, they allow
seamless communication between,
within and between LAN and WAN, WANs.
this synergy, is as crucial for,
modern networking, whether you are
working in a corporate environment or
managing a large scale data center.
The combined power of routing and
switching is what keeps everything
running smoothly and efficiently.
All right.
let's, discuss in detail about some of
the advanced network design concepts.
let's list out all the advanced concepts
that I would like to, discuss in detail.
the first one being, the route
distribution, the next one
being the quality of service,
other one being the IPSec.
so basically by integrating this advanced
technology, we can design network that
are more resilient, efficient and secure.
So what is route distribution?
Route distribution basically allows
different protocols to share information,
ensuring seamless connectivity.
Next, one being quality
of service, enables the
prioritization of network traffic.
Crucial services like voice
and video can be given a higher
priority or less important traffic.
Ensuring smooth operations
for essential services.
The next one being IPSec, the
IPSec basically adds another layer
of security by encrypting data at
the network layer, especially used
for virtual, private networks.
By integrating these advanced concepts,
we can design networks that are more
resilient, efficient and secure.
So now let's look at the, this
slide on industry applications.
We would like to discuss how these
are used in real world scenarios.
in enterprise networks, routing
and switching basically play,
enable low latency, seamless
business operations, whether it's
finance, retail, or manufacturing.
In telecommunications, advanced routing
and switching technologies power
5G networks, ensuring high speed,
reliable, and seamless connection.
in cloud computing basically relies
on seamless connectivity between on
premise cloud services and this is where
routing and switching become very crucial
for hybrid cloud models and SD WANs.
For IoT and edge computing, or allow
efficient management of connected
devices, reducing latency and ensuring
fast data transmission at edge.
these examples show how vital
these technologies are driven in
modern digital transformation.
So to conclude, we had a detailed
discussion about different
topics that we were trying to
touch base on the agenda today.
To conclude, I would like to say
routing and switching basically act
as a backbone of modern networks.
As we move into the future of
technologies like 5G, IoT, AI driven
networks, the role of routing and
switching will continue to expand.
future trends such as
software defined networking.
network function, virtual
function virtualization, NFW
nvs, and intent based networking.
IBN will automate and optimize
many network functions
as network professionals.
It's crucial to play and to be, to stay
on top of these developments, to design,
implement and manage, networks that
are, resilient, scalable, and secure.
thank you so much, for being part
of this, and thank you for joining
me today as we explore routing and
switching fundamentals and these
crucial, and their crucial role in
building scalable and resilient networks.
Stay curious and always look out for
advancement in these network technologies.
If you have any questions or concerns, or
if you'd like to deep dive into a specific
area, please feel free to reach out to me.
Thank you.