Hi, everyone.
My name is Anand Kumar, and I'm a
senior cloud engineer at SADA systems.
And what I do for my for SADA system was
to help customers in different verticals.
to leverage artificial intelligence
and machine learning language in their
business and provide solutions based
on, their, their business requirements.
one of the industry that
I work is, in retail.
during this conference, I'm going to
just talk about, how, machine learning
will impact a professional, promotional
strategies in one in the retail industry.
So this is all about, the AI powered
coupon personalization for, for
customers, in the retail industry.
so the topics that I'm going to
cover is, some introduction about
AI, which we all know, and, some
promotional strategies in and around AI.
what is AI powered coupon
personalization, types of customers for
personalization, how machine learning
algorithms drive personalization,
benefits of AI personalization, coupon
personalization, some case studies,
some real examples, that I can, I
like to share and some successful
implementation around those case studies.
And, and also some challenges and
ethical considerations, when using
AI and, ML, and, future trends
in, the AI powered promotions.
let's get into the topics.
First thing, introduction to
AI and promotional, strategies.
so to, before I start with, I'm
sure most of you, might, think
about discounts, promotions.
offers, in the real time,
world, especially in the retail.
you go to any retail store to buy
cloths or groceries or anything.
the first thing that we
noticed is about the discounts.
when you enter the store, somebody will be
standing outside the door and, welcoming
you with, the promotion newsletter or
paper, 50 percent off, 20 percent off.
so they just wanted to, welcome you
with, their offers and discounts.
but do you know that there is
a big strategy that is there?
there could be a business strategy
behind there for every of those, coupons
or, the newsletters that you receive.
What, the topic is, what the today's
topic that I'm going to do, help
you to understand is how this
AI and ML is going to help these
retail companies, retail, industry.
as well as customer, to take the full
advantage of, of the product or, or
the discounts, that, you know, that
the retail, the retail industry sales,
the retail shop sales, or, the customer
who's going to purchase, purchase that.
So quickly start with, digital
transformation, in retail.
right now everything is data driven.
in AI.
Without the data, there was nothing.
And, every, every moment, every,
thing that you do in a retail or
anywhere, it is all, the business is
all driven by the data, strategies.
So what is the AI role?
So all these days we are using some
data analytics, but now introducing the
AI into the customer's data can help
to give accurate personalization on
the offers and resonate the customer.
Individuals, individual consumers,
how that particular offer that,
that, that the retail shop gives, how
that really benefits the customers.
so we all know that, the retail,
the e commerce market or the
retail industry market is a 6.
3 trillion dollars, by end of this 2024.
And, how, yeah, AI is going to personalize
those offer, and crucial competitive,
against these retail, companies.
so let's get into the real
topic, from the next slide.
so what is AI powered coupon,
coupon personalization means?
To give you, to start with and give you
an example, say, for example, you're going
to Walmart or Amazon store or anywhere
in the world, like even in India, there
are big bazaar stores or Reliance stores,
the moment you enter, there might be a
desk or somebody would be standing and,
giving you those, coupons, or offers, or
you might get, some, letters, or you might
get some messages to your phone, email
that, hey, this is a festival offer, it's
Christmas, it's New Year, if you purchase
it can be like 20 percent offer, or if
you buy these two, there is a third one
will be an offer, and today's rate for,
if you buy two shirts, there will be a
pant, it's free, or it can be anything.
But most of the time have you
realized that, that those are
not even necessary for me at the
time that I wanted to purchase.
for example, you might be, say you go to
a retail store, There you wanted to buy
a shampoo from a different company and
a conditioner from a different company.
Say you wanted a shampoo from
L'Oreal and you wanted conditioner
from Aveeno or some other brand.
But, unless otherwise You buy both,
there might be an offer, or if you're
buying separate, there is no offer.
and sometimes I don't want a shampoo
at all, or I use something herbal,
which I buy online or something.
So you don't need that.
Or, there might be another
example where, I am, I love wine.
I wanted to drink wine.
Or some other preferences will
be, they don't want to drink
wine or, any alcohol or anything.
But in the paper, it's a very common,
collection of offers will be there.
or say a pineapple.
so some offers would say if you
buy two pineapples, there will be
another one, will be, on offer.
But I don't need pineapple
on for that particular day.
Why would I need, that on a, on a winter
time, pineapples are for summer, but
the offers that they give you will be on
winters because the retail store know that
we have to give them offer since that has
not been sold or there is an excessive
amount of, produce is already there.
Most of the time when I go, either I
don't like that offer at that point
of time, or I don't, I don't want
it that, that, that particular time.
what a, what a PowerCoupon Personalization
does is, every retail store you go, there
might be an account, they might ask your
phone number, they might ask you for, the
store, store customer number or something.
they always collect the data.
and, whenever you enter the
bill, they might ask you,
Hey, do you have the barcode?
Do you have the, your customer?
Do you want her to sign
up for that retail?
So everything is all data collected.
We collect datas.
rather than, So when I say data,
the data is collected from your
home number, your house address, or
something that whenever you go, they
know that it is you're purchasing.
So think about a year worth of data,
what all you have bought from that
particular store, shirt, or you bought
it from, from that particular retail,
say it is a Walmart for our example,
they store it in, in their database.
So they know this particular customer.
is planning to buy, or, he has bought
this many number, of products from us
and every time, or every month, he might
have bought a particular set of, product.
Say it is, it can be shampoo or it can
be onions or it can be like, like shaving
blades or creams or, or anything that.
So what we are doing is, We are
collecting all that particular data
for that particular customer throughout
the year, okay, or six months.
And we are trying to personalize
a coupon just for him.
So rather than a very generalized
discounts and offers, we want that
customer to take leverage on what
he has purchased on his history.
Say, again, going back to
the example, I love wine.
if I wanted, they know from
my every month I have bought
this particular brand of wine.
and say, okay, you're buying
that brand of wine, by this
time we are giving you an offer.
If you buy two bottles of that
wine, there might be another
bottle of wine that is free.
Or, think about another
set of brand of wine.
So if you buy that brand of
wine, you might get an offer
from this brand or another brand.
you can just, personalizing or trying
to understand the customer's behavior,
based on what he has purchased all through
these years and giving an offer would
be more valuable for the customer and
for the, and for the retail store to,
hold that customer for a longer time.
I bet that made, that
really makes sense, right?
how I achieve this is, we have to
definitely make sure the customer is
a member of that particular store.
Say, if it is a Walmart, I become
a Walmart member, and, I just make
sure I collect the reasonable data,
from different sources, from, apps
that the customer use, that the,
then the, the website the customer
has used, or, or his location,
just based on different parameters.
we, we use, machine learning
languages and models, to predict
what would customer might buy.
how can I just, be a value add?
say for example, most of the customers,
like if you, if you see the trend, if
I go and buy a wine from a store, I
have the tendency to buy a chips or a
chicken, uh, it really makes sense, right?
Hey, you buy a wine, so you get
an offer for your Lays chips or
something else or you know, there is
an offer that if you buy a wine then
there is a there's some discounts on
the chicken or some party product.
So you think about your product
personalizing your discounts only
for that particular customer and that
discount might not be available for,
the other customers, people are spending
thousands and thousands of money on
the advertisement and, and doing a
personalization would be definitely
makes sense for customers, customers.
I personally allow it.
I'm sure, everybody, if there is
a personalized discount for that
particular person, I feel like I am,
more valuable for that particular store.
And I love to go, to
that particular store.
okay, moving on, how I achieve this,
how do I know the customer's bad.
So there are various things as I mentioned
before, purchase history, six months,
a year, or the frequency, I would, I
would definitely allow to collect at
least three years of data, his age,
his gender, because, I don't want it to
give a wine to a less, an 18 year or,
or a teenager who's not turned 18 or 21.
And based on the browsing history
that he might have used, hey, is
this product available in Walmart?
I just collect that I know, and very
contextual, data, sometimes it is
mostly like that particular location.
I live in that location.
I have three walmarts around, around
my area within around 10 million years.
I usually go to any one of them.
You trying to understand your customers
better, that really makes sense.
And, think about some social
media activities as well.
because right now, when you hit enter
on any of the website, you go to a
particular website, that person really
knows that what he's, is he doing.
Say if I go to Walmart website
and I'm just searching it.
don't think that I, only I know,
Probably walmart also knows that I am I'm
searching for this particular product or
And also they would also know that How
many times I have clicked this website
what all the pages that I have visited?
So this is all is the
data collection event.
this is this is all getting into into
a database where where it is just
trying to get into a meaningful so
You so try to understand, what is that
particular customer's personalization?
What is this personality basically, Say
for example, if I am 50 years old or 60
years old and a person, if I am diabetic,
say I'm searching for diabetic or
anything, probably I won't, I won't need
a discount on a chocolate or, or a cake.
Say if an offer comes to me saying,
you buy two cakes, there is a third
one, why would I buy a cake where I
am already suffering from diabetics?
And I might ignore that, right?
Ignore that particular discount.
I might buy for another one, that is
a chance, but the chances of that is
pretty less than me having that, right?
I hope you get it.
basically trying to know their
age, gender, particular location.
This all just derives me or just puts
me into that particular, category or
a box where, okay, understand that
particular person's behavior, personality
on what he's, he may or may not buy.
And based on that, produce that,
give him that personalized offer.
Okay.
I hope you, you're getting it.
And, it's pretty interesting.
Okay.
Then comes the technical part of it.
How do I achieve this?
Okay, say, I have, I went to Walmart, I
signed up there for their membership or
I'm just taking Walmart as an example,
but really I have personally done this
project for a different retail, retail
store, and it's been an amazing success.
in future you might see this trends
going on with the most of the
retail stores throughout the world.
okay, let's talk, get in, get deeper
into the machine learning algorithms.
so these algorithms, these are some
of the algorithms that can derive you.
One is collaborative filtering.
you're collecting from, different,
users, different patterns.
Say, for example, if a person of,
of an age, age between 20 to 30, you
particularly know by now that what
his, what will be his eating patterns
will be, what he would love, I know
we all love ice creams, for example,
but the amount of ice creams you
consume in your later Between 10 to 25.
It will be more but during the period
of time you become older the ice
creams You might take a couple of
scoop but in a childhood you might
take a so basically you're just
trying to understand the pattern.
what it helps you is, okay, if I buy
two boxes of ice cream, this particular
customer is a 20 year old, probably he
might go, his parents are just sure.
It tells me that he's an ice cream lover.
So let me produce this, these offers
for the age group between, 20 and 30.
Right?
So, there will be four algorithms
that easily can help you with this.
And one is the collaborative filtering.
And the second one is the
content based filtering.
Where, the customers are
already interacted with based
on what they have, purchased.
Okay, then comes to the neural
network where I call the deep
learning side of it trying to
understand the pattern and predict
his future preferences we all know.
you know
Say if It is going to be winter
right for example What will be a
pattern of products or anything that
a person might buy during the winter?
so to just give you an example, it would
be very interesting, where a customer, he
always buys some, some pills, say for, for
cold pills, because you have the option,
you have the tendency to get sick during
the winter by cough or cold or anything.
So whoever purchased that, purchased
that in that particular store.
This store opened a pharmacy.
this retail store.
so think about like, why would
a retail store open a pharmacy?
Because the patterns are like
showing like that, right?
you buy the, based on the product.
one part of the department, you buy
the grocery based on the department,
he might have the tendency to, to
buy, the cough or cold, medicines.
so this all comes from the deep learning
analysis, based on your, behavior, right?
And again, examples like, if you go
to, right now, even if you go to a
retail store, previously, any retail
store is, come into mind, say for
Walmart, 10 or 20 years back when I,
10 years back, I was going to Walmart.
It was just, groceries.
Now, they literally expand
it to the clothing division.
Right now I can go and buy my, they
expanded to a pharmacy inside it.
Why would you buy, why, there is a
pharmacy like Walgreens and other stores
and why would Walmart get into the, but
this is all comes from the Patterns that
the customer have bought from the store.
Okay, so it literally means
like you bought something from
the store You become sick.
So rather than going to the pharmacy is
right there in the retail store, right?
Then the interesting part is now you can
see that the groceries are there Yeah, the
rest of the things have been accomplished
now you can see The restaurant the small
restaurants are inside the walmart.
they think have you ever seen like
you're going to a walmart and you
know buying pizza or Subway, you
know because people are tired.
They know that they will be hungry by
the time they pre shop so rather than
just taking their car or just going
out to subway somewhere Why don't we
just put the subway that right there?
see this is all comes from these kind of
patterns four algorithms we have used.
One is a deep learning and the last one
would be the natural language processing.
This analyzes the textual data,
reviews the feedbacks, understand the
customer's sentiments and preferences.
So these are the vital thing that we
have used, that I have personally used in
the, in driving a personalized coupons.
okay, moving on, moving on.
Why are we doing all this?
What is the benefits of
this coupon personalization?
It is pretty simple, right?
As I just informed you, one
is improves the engagement.
most of the time, keeping the
customer, engaged is so important.
As I told you, just to give you
an example, why would I have a
restaurant in a retail, store?
a fast food store in a retail store just
because, like you are having customer
engage to buy more things, right?
Say if I, I was in, in a store, right?
while printing the bill, it was, I
bought some, $50 worth off, products
and it just stays like you are worth
to buy, a pizza for free, a slice of
pizza at the food counter, but free.
I was literally thinking of after
the store, I have to go and buy
food outside to go to a restaurant
Or a fast food and i'm just I
don't know how they read my mind.
Like I was really hungry It was like 2 p.
m in the night.
So bye i'm just Okay, I love it, so
it just gives me that personalized
coupon, based on my purchase.
you go and have your free pizza because
you bought a 50 worth or a hundred
dollar worth of product, from the retail.
So this is wise, right?
So have them customers engaged.
The next one is, hyper AI driven,
AI driven personalization can drive
significant sales goals for the retail.
trust me.
I have just put it as 150.
I have we have seen the retail store
making a huge amount of profits,
and they can Decide, the based on
the customer like what all that they
need to buy, you know What all they
need to because have you ever seen?
retail store dumping their products
outside that has become less They
know What that particular store or the
people might buy they have understood
the customers better say You know most
of the time I have seen The grocery
products like potatoes or anything.
It's always You know or a pre diff time.
It just goes where they just dump it
in the yard But right now they know
that okay, this particular store only
needs this much of kilos or pounds
of potatoes So they don't over buy so
ready by reducing that they have They
have raised the bar like in they have
increased the sales and they have saved
And the most important thing that I
wanted to mention here is the customer
retention personalized coupons has become
really a built a loyalty, for those
customers, say I use target and walmart
most of the time They have their own and
differences in pieces, but I use walmart
the more because of that you know if
some store is giving me that personalized
coupon, I would love to just go back
again and again, because, they know
what I wanted and if I'm just getting
a better price out of that, why not?
and it just definitely increased my boost
because based on my purchases, they're
giving me discounts on other things.
Say, for example, I told you about a free
food that was, based on my purchases,
I got a slice of pizza that is more.
But for me, I, I like it.
I was hungry.
I know they understood my
preferences and there was a coupon
that was just popped in my screen.
okay.
Based on your purchase, you got a free,
just go and have it, what else you wanted.
Okay.
Next thing, cost effective marketing.
this is very important.
the demand and supply,
it's very cost effective.
Rather than, giving a personalized coupon,
pretty general, which has so many things,
and I don't have time to just sweep all
the coupon pages and see which of the
coupons will fit for me or fit for me.
Maybe there might be a coupon that
might fit for me, but not for that time.
Pretty simple.
Okay, moving on.
moving on to the next slide.
Okay, definitely, I cannot just
talk about without any examples.
There are case studies, and,
I have, I have made it as a
very general case studies.
Many of Amazon.
Many of Netflix.
I've just stayed at Sephora.
That is a, that's a different,
that's a big retail in U.
S.
So I will talk about that as well.
So one is Amazon.
Look at Amazon.
why they have been very successful,
right now is just because of, the
recommendations that they, they give.
based on your purchases, they have
collected all the data over the years
and giving you the right relevant product
and the discount that really makes sense.
And, I don't know.
I have been using Amazon for the past
10 years, and I have, and I don't want
to go for another one, even though the
other people have given me more offer
or the store like Walmart, but still the
Amazon gives me a little value add than
the other stores, especially in the past.
On the coupon space.
right now in U.
S.
there's a prime deal going on.
I love Amazon.
After this meeting, all day
I'm in Amazon just because of
these, because of the coupons.
though I don't want it to buy because
of the people offering me the best
coupons, I just go and buy it.
Damn.
Okay, next thing.
Netflix.
Personalized content recommendation.
Okay, I think we talked about
a lot of algorithms, right?
And, Netflix is the pioneer
in using these, algorithms.
Netflix, they were going down, and now
suddenly they just picked up, their shares
went so high just because of, they are
using, definitely they are using these,
they're giving the, they are using, the
recommendations, you know based on the
movies that you watch predictive analysis
and the deep learning and the natural
language processing they understand
that okay This person likes to watch
romantic movies or thriller movies,
such as that's something just based on
That particular Larry, how do I do it?
you see it's pretty simple, right?
I have a Netflix account, one
account, but we all as a family
shares, my wife wa watches Romantics.
I watch as Thriller.
My son watches cartoons.
So based on that recommendation
and personalization, you get
into that particular, account.
You see all these priorities.
It just personalized for
those particular, persons.
And again, the last one is a Sephora,
it's a virtual artist apps that
enables customers to buy product
virtually, imagine leading a higher
customer engagement and sales with
users trying 50 looks per session
on average, I definitely you should
use one of those it is it is great.
Okay, moving on to next.
Definitely, if there is a technology,
there is definitely, there is, there,
there is, there are high chances
there you, you have challenges.
Okay, there's nothing that, again.
one of the biggest challenges what
we have, seen, in this industry is
whenever you're collecting a large
amount of data, because, you're trying
to understand the customer's behavior.
especially I told you, if customer is
sharing an information saying that if
I am diabetic or if I have some other
disease, those customers should not be
recommended for a more sugary products.
It's just a basic understanding.
So there, you're personally
collecting those information.
You're trying to understand
okay, this customer.
So why would I, have to go and tell
the whole public of the world that I
am diabetic or I have this problem?
But, you're literally entering
that data in that app, in the
re, in the retail store app.
That has to be preserved, right?
So the, so encryptions or anything
that retail store, the data privacy.
Because once you hack, security and
hacking, I see many people talking
about security and cybersecurity.
I talk, when I say data privacy, you
know what that means is okay, algorithm
biases, AI models are premature by us.
Resulting in unread treatments
across different democratic groups.
Okay, this is so funny that, when I
ask a question, to chat GPD at the same
time, I ask, at the same question to GE
Gemini, or, the Google's version of it.
And I use prosperity of, There is
another, there are so many, every,
GPT gives me a different answer.
Some of them, it just hurts me.
Some of them I feel like, why would
you just put, put the state by a
statement rather that is not right,
so you've got to be very careful
in those using those algorithms.
say for example, you, you cannot, say
for example, you, if a kid is being
in the store and a kid, a person
of less than 18, who is a customer.
Uh, you are no willing, you
cannot recommend no matter what.
You cannot recommend, an
alcoholic beverages for that kid.
though the kid might be
searching, based on okay, or he
might be doing that, but, uh.
you're understanding that, okay, this
kid is, he's less than, seven, eighteen
years old, so I'm not going to recommend
or give him promotions on an alcoholic.
this is a basic, understanding.
I'm just giving you a high, very high
level understanding because I don't
want to get into the bias things.
I don't want to become, more religious,
and just, just telling, what the bias
means and, I don't want to get into it.
past.
Algorithmic biases are very common.
when we are using, these
algorithms, just make sure, we
put a class that we understand.
for example, recently, like my, my,
one of my friend is a professor.
pure vegan.
and when he gets an offer for,
for, meat, he gets so offended.
Like, why am I getting these
offers, to buy chicken?
I, though I am, I'm a vegan, right?
So I'm just giving a very high
level bias statement that what that
algorithm predicts, and, and just,
It just gives the results on that.
And next is the trust and transparency.
customers trust before
they put that information.
So customers find overlay
personality offers innovative, right?
ensure the transparency, and giving
user control their data is crucial.
when you're collecting some information,
just make sure that customer know that you
are, you're collecting those, information.
I think at least in U.
S.
there are many companies that
have been questioned by, by the
government, saying that, whether
Facebook tracks are, where are you?
what they do, right?
So I don't, I'm not getting into more
detail on this, but just in a very high
level, How trans, we have, we, as an
AI or whatever we are building for the
customers, we got to be very transparent
with them, with what customers, okay.
Technical recommendments.
Implementing AI is expensive.
AI systems are pretty expensive.
It requires significant inventory.
So think about, I just told you about, at
least I need a year or five years worth
of data of what customer has been doing.
Purchased in that particular store over
the years collecting the data, cleaning
off that data and make it a valuable, a
truthful or, or a very, meaningful data
to the, to the AI and ML is crucial.
And it is, it's still, you need a lot
of skills and, time infrastructure cost.
yeah, these are some of the challenges
that I have faced, when, when you're
building machine learning algorithms.
Okay.
Going on to the next, trends and
future, maybe, future, future trends.
what are we trying to deal with it?
Okay, so as I told you, this will be
your future in the retail space where
nowhere you will be getting a very broad,
a newspaper or a very broad okay, these
are the things that are in the promotional
rather than it will be a personal.
So AI is going to enable the real
time adjustments to promotions.
based on the immediate customer behavior.
I gave you an example for the pizza, okay.
Immediately I bought it for 50, 50.
You just try to understand
my personal behavior.
I, they might know because they
want me to have, have their
lunch or dinner at this time.
At that, at the retail, rather
than just going to a restaurant
or a, or, at a fast food place.
So it is gonna be dynamic, right?
why does DI dynamic?
Because I bought something and I don't
want a coupon for tomorrow to go, okay, go
back to the retail store to have a pizza.
Why would I use that?
I don't want because I go to two
weeks once you know if my coupon
just arrived on that time While I
am just going heading to the store.
How valuable is that thing?
Okay, so it is going to be real
time offers Will be producing
for customers deeper integration.
So AI will expand beyond the
promotional strategies Okay, like
customer services Automation,
Inventory Management, and Predictive
Analysis for future customer needs.
This is very important, right?
So the AI is going to, engage,
will be more, personalized.
So say for example, if I am, if I
am, going to Walmart, the app or the
AI app is Walmart app, just gives
me a, gives Tells me that, hey, if
you're about to, hey, this is Sunday,
I understand, if you're going to
Walmart, this is the offers that we are
delivering, just telling that, right?
Because I don't want to just go to
their website to understand what the
promotions are going on, rather than
AI just telling me, you go to the
store, this will be just for today.
if you're buying a laptop or
you're buying a phone, there is
an exciting promotion this Sunday.
If you go, you're the one who will
be luckiest to get that offer.
How cool is that, right?
Okay, and, A, augmented shopping.
Really, retailers will be offered an
even more interactive shopping experience
through AI, like virtual assistants.
Like AR product previews, right?
most of the time, okay?
you're always in a dilemma
to buy something, right?
You go, you pick a laptop.
you always ask the question, whether
this is the right price for me?
whether this will be useful for me?
what would be the return policy on this?
what will, what are people talk
about the reviews about this product?
And you got to be just keep searching
for all those, and just to come
to a conclusion rather than think
about you see a product Tip, tip.
These are the results that you
had, have, this many reviews
have been given all are like 4.
5 and more.
And, by geography, this is one
of the best laptops that you
can purchase from the store.
Okay, this has the best RAM.
This is the this is a jump it just
pops up in my app or application about
that product, it just really Makes
me a touch point like I don't have
to spend too much time whether to buy
that or not Right and give me what are
the advantages of and disadvantages
of buying the buying that product.
Here you go you know I don't have to call
my friends or people who have purchased
and just spend my time on a call or on
a To understand about the product rather
than it just boom pops up All right
Conclusion, good, this interactive of AI
personalization promotion strategies is
transforming the retail industry a big
time, offers businesses the ability to
deliver high category and more relevant
coupons, as I just mentioned this, right?
And, I'm just not going to technically,
I'm not going to read about that, but
just in a high level, 35 percent raise
in coupon redemination, think about
like how many people are redeeming your
coupons nowadays, you know it I don't
think you give Any attention to coupons
or anything or for if there was a sales
guy just coming to near to me I'm just
going to walk away from him rather than
just Standing with him and just talking
about the sales promotions, right?
this is going to help in 35 percent
rise in using the coupons And, we
have found that there's 22 percent
of the customers you will just retain
with that particular store, right?
However, while the potential AI
impersonalization is immense,
businessmen also address the key
challenges that I have mentioned
on data privacy, compliances, there
should be regular guardrails for
all of this, all of this, technology
behind, that works behind the AI.
so somebody is not misusing that rather
than just, it is just going to help
the real man, help the man, mankind.
some companies that are developing the
artificial intelligence, models, machine
learning models should be more cautious
to be, to understand, okay, this is
sensitive data, I'm not going to screw up
with this, just add, I'm going to add some
extra layer of protection on top of it.
Got it.
I think that's all about,
the today's presentation.
I hope you all might have enjoyed this.
And, if there are any
questions, feel free.
My contact information are, are
there with the conference, web page.
and, it was a pleasure.
to give me to, to talk to you
about this and, connecting and
meeting you or everyone on this.
thank you.
Bye.