Hey, everyone.
My name is Matthias Palmersheim, and today
I want to talk to you about how to monitor
your monitoring and why it's important.
A little bit about me.
I'm a solutions engineer at Victoria
Metrics, and Victoria Metrics
makes an amazing time series
database called Victoria Metrics.
We also make some utilities for getting
your data not only into Victoria Metrics,
but other time series databases as well.
We are also starting to make a tool
called Victoria Logs for aggregating logs.
And when I'm not working on that at my
day job, I like to take a lot of the
utilities we make as well as some others
and aggregate it together into an easy
to deploy monitoring and logging system.
So that way you don't have to have a giant
Kubernetes cluster or an expensive cloud
service to get started with observability.
So if you couldn't tell by that
intro, I'm a huge observability nerd.
And Actually, on my first
date with my wife, I wouldn't
shut up about observability.
And there was a betting pool in
the office to see if I would talk
about observability the whole time.
And the reason why I became obsessed with
observability is one of my first IT jobs.
It was a IT manager at a factory.
And when I got there, I didn't really
have any monitoring system, so to speak.
And what would happen is an application
would go down because I didn't have
a monitoring system to help me.
Prevent that from happening in the first
place and get alerts for things like,
Hey, hard drives filling up and the
hard drive would just fill up and an
application would fail and my alerting
system at the time was users coming into
my office and informing me that Hey,
this change that was made recently took
down the application and now the whole
office can't work and that's costing the
company tens of thousands of dollars an
hour and that caused a lot of stress.
So along with not having context as to why
things were broken, I had to deal with the
stress of having somebody there reminding
me how expensive this problem was.
So I could get nice automated
notifications instead of
angry users in my office.
I implemented a monitoring system
that collected the telemetry and that
telemetry could tell me that, Hey,
this resource is overused, or this
thing is being slow before it finds me.
failed and although I was angry
that now I had alerts, things
weren't going down as often.
And, when people would come into my
office after they broke, I would usually
already be working on the problem
and that helps lower stress a ton.
but I had a problem though.
A lot of the notifications I was
getting from my monitoring system
were coming through the same channels
as things like status updates or.
people, just like general
announcements, Oh, Hey, you need to
park in the other parking lot today.
And so that led to a lot of alert
fatigue because every time I got
an email, I got the like stress of,
is this just a simple update that
I needed to park somewhere else?
Or is this a tens of thousands
of dollar an hour problem?
So I looked into noisy
notification systems that were
dedicated for critical alerts.
So it was super easy to set up.
D and D override in my phone.
And the other nice things about
this is that it would make
an individual responsible.
So instead of just shouting out, Hey, the
system's broken, somebody should fix this.
It would assign somebody to the, incident.
And the way I decide if
something is an important.
notification and it should be able
to override like the notification
prefaces on my phone is that if it
costs life, liberty or property.
So if it could cause physical harm, if the
system is down, if it causes compliance
issues and the government's going to
get involved, or if it can cause loss
to property and property could just mean
that it reaches a certain cost threshold
and it's losing the company more money
than you would like for an outage.
So I was starting to feel pretty happy
about my existing observability system.
I was able to get noisy notifications when
things were breaking instead of email.
But then I had a philosophical question.
Is what happens if the
monitoring system fails?
So if my monitoring
system fell over at 2 a.
m., does anyone get paged?
So this is the problem that
I was running into where the
monitoring system would fail.
And I would think that everything's
fine, whether or not the applications
behind or that the monitoring
system was responsible for were up.
And to solve this problem, you just
deploy a second monitoring system.
So you set up a monitoring of
monitoring system that only monitors
the primary monitoring system.
And then from the perspective of
the primary monitoring system,
you It's just another application.
So it's just like the ERP system.
It sends metrics and it alerts you
when things aren't going as expected.
There's a problem with this.
The monitoring and monitoring system
is also just another application can
fail and multiple applications can fail
at the same time for whatever reason.
So this problem could be solved.
Just be solved by adding more and more
monitoring systems, but you never quite
get to 100 percent availability you
get more nines but with more nines of
Availability you also get more costs and
it's harder to maintain the knowledge
if you have all those monitoring systems
so usually the sweet spot is two But
you don't just deploy two applications
to the same region and in the same
infrastructure as code inventory You need
to make sure that the applications are
deployed in a way that they're isolated
from failures as much as possible.
And before I get into all the ways that
this can go wrong, I'm not implying that
you and your teammates aren't smart.
I'm saying that humans aren't perfect.
We make mistakes, but Usually
different groups of humans don't
make mistakes at the same time.
So you want to make a different group of
humans as responsible for your monitoring
and monitoring as much as possible.
And another thing you need to do is to
make sure that your change management
processes are aware that these two
systems shouldn't be updated at the same
time because upgrades or configuration
changes are frequent source of outages.
So if you touch both systems, if
you're allowed to touch both systems
at the same time, then there's a high
likelihood both fail at the same time.
So the different tools that we need to
make are the different technical ways that
we can prevent both systems from failing.
are to use different notification
services because again, notifications
are apps and apps fail sometimes.
you want to make sure that they're
in different infrastructure providers
because usually, different infrastructure
providers don't have simultaneous outages.
If you can't get it inside of a different
infrastructure provider or a different
cloud service, at least try to get it
inside of different regions and separate
deployments within the same cloud service.
So in summary, your monitoring and
monitoring is another monitoring
system, but it's only responsible for
the primary monitoring system because
it gets really confusing if you have
different monitoring systems available
for certain business applications.
It can be harder to test the system
too, because not only do you have to
get the okay from your boss to test and
intentionally fail a system, you have to.
Get approval for a test that could
have impacts to other teams as well.
And the monitoring and monitoring
system is just treated by the monitoring
system as another application.
So the minimum requirement is to
do the most important thing in
observability, which is make sure
that your applications are available.
This is going to be cheaper to store
and easier to configure, because in
most cases you're just configuring
a connection between two things or
feeding a list of URLs to some service
and it's performing health checks.
But the downside is that you
don't get the, you don't get a
lot of preventative alerts unless
like the applications being slow.
and so what happens if you don't get
those contextual things is that when
the application goes down, you have
a much higher mean time to resolution
because you have to figure out what went
wrong as well as fix what went wrong.
And again, this is responsible
for keeping the most important
applications in your business online.
So you really should.
treat it like another application and give
it those preventative measures, give it
really nice dashboards, have run books
and all those other things that every
other application in your business gets.
And even if you are treating it
like another application, your
applications should have health
checks that alert you if they fail.
So what are the approaches we can do this?
I'm gonna get into some like quick
and dirty approaches that if you
can't get a full blown Dedicated
monitoring of monitoring system.
It's better than nothing So the first
instance of that is gonna be a heartbeat
so Heartbeat is just one system
communicating with another and if that
communication doesn't happen for a certain
period of time You An alert will fire.
this is, again, it's the simplest up down
that you could get is just communication
between these two systems as it happened.
And the downside is that the heartbeat
is usually like a dedicated health check.
It's not like a, as accurate of a
representation as some of the other
health checks we're going to go
through a little bit in the talk.
So a good example would be
the, ANAG system with Nagios.
And that's just, if the ANAG application
hasn't contacted the server in a
certain amount of time, it will fire.
There's obviously false positive
risks with that because your phone
could be having, issues connecting
to LTE or something like that.
And the other problem is that's just
shouting into an area saying, Hey,
this is broken rather than, doing what
they do in CPR training, which is say.
Hey, somebody calling, like you point
to somebody and say, you call an
ambulance or you get a defibrillator.
Another example of this
is Grafana on call.
If you self host Grafana on call,
you can sign up for a cloud account.
And then if the self hosted
version doesn't talk to the cloud
account for a certain amount of
time, then you get a notification
that there's a missing heartbeat.
But this only covers the notification
system and not everything as a whole.
So this kind of works, but you should
probably look into something better.
if you're using a cloud vendor for your
monitoring, then usually they have a
status page, and hopefully they're not
self hosting it, because if you are
self hosting, your own status page, then
there's a higher likelihood that both
the application and the status page fail
at the same time, because there could be
overlap in the infrastructure overlap in
the humans that cause both the systems to
fail, but they're really easy to set up.
If you go, if you just like search online
for cloud vendors, status page, they'll
give you this information and give
you like point and click instructions
for getting this into email or Slack,
but the downside is those are, Those
aren't noisy notification system.
People commonly will mute, will mute
things and it's really tricky to get the
settings just right to where your status
update, or people asking for status
updates don't bother you after hours,
but, Cloud Render going down would.
And this usually doesn't work
for self hosting solutions.
A bit of a better version of this is
going to be health check services.
So if you're self hosting, you could
self host something like uptime Kuma, but
getting another team to host this inside
of your organization is going to be tricky
because you have to convince people.
that, hey, I know I'm on the observability
team, but this team that isn't the
observability team should manage the
service that does observability things.
there's also cloud options for this,
but again, if you're self hosting,
this can be really tricky because you
either have to allow access to your
monitoring application, which can be a
security risk and getting the security
team on board with this could be a
problem, or you have to, manage an
agent inside of your infrastructure.
to, beacon out information
to that service as well.
But these do hook into
noisy notifications.
and they do require a bit of
extra configuration because it's
not just subscribing to a feed
or setting up a simple heartbeat.
You do have to give a list of URLs and
if possible, you should give the correct
responses because sometimes you get a 200
HTTP code and a valid SSL certificate,
but on that, On that web page or in the
response, you say, Hey, even though I'm
serving HTTP traffic, I'm not healthy.
So if you can configure look for a string
in a response, definitely set that up.
And again, all of these are minimal
context to it's just a simple is the thing
working or not and maybe a response time.
So the first system
that I would recommend.
that I would say is an adequate monitoring
of monitoring system is to deploy
two independent monitoring systems.
this has the widest range of quality, so
you could do it the lazy way and deploy
a smaller version of the exact same
tooling with the exact same version in
the same infrastructure as code inventory
with no change management controls.
And this obviously isn't
the best solution because.
something inside of that region or inside
of that Kubernetes cluster could fail.
you could find out that there was
a regression in an update and take
out both systems at the same time.
If you use the same notification
system and that fails, you,
it's really hard to tell.
So doing all those things right
is also tricky from a bureaucratic
perspective too, because you have to
convince your boss that, hey, we need to
deploy an application in a new region.
Or.
Another thing is you have to justify
of setting up change management
processes, which can be difficult
and it can be hard to get people
to follow the instructions on that.
If you do this approach, you
should definitely test it.
So a way you could test it is
to break your monitoring of
monitoring system and then make
sure that your primary monitoring
system is sending notifications.
And when you do this, make sure
that somebody's periodically just
like refreshing dashboards or some
tests to make sure that the primary
monitoring system is working as well.
So that way you can figure out
if there's any interdependencies
between the two systems.
another thing you can do if you're self
hosting is purchase a cloud service.
And if you're approaching your cloud
service, you can either purchase a
different cloud service that monitors
the first cloud service, or you
could set up an on prem system that
monitor monitors the cloud service.
the upside of this is now you're
definitely having different humans
manage the systems, and those humans are
probably using different upstream vendors.
a lot of the time you can control
where your cloud service is deployed.
And so that way they're
geographically isolated.
and I know cloud monitoring bills have
a bad rap for being super expensive,
but because it's one application,
it's not that big of a deal.
And that application is managed
usually by the observity observability
experts in your organization.
So they're aware of things that
can lower costs like react.
relabeling rules or streaming aggregation.
And this one, you can
still misconfigure it.
but it's lower because it's a
shared responsibility model rather
than a, you're responsible model.
And the best version of this
is to purchase a dedicated
monitoring of monitoring solution.
So Victoria metrics offers this as an
part of some of our enterprise plans.
But the downside of it is it's the most
expensive because along with paying
for a separate monitoring system.
So a separate instance of Victoria metrics
to monitor your on prem Victoria metrics.
You're paying for the really smart humans
to enrich the already rich notifications.
But again, that's going to
be the best experience by far
because along with a really well
supported observability system.
You get the smart people behind
it that can help you, work
through the issues as well.
So in summary, this doesn't
have to be super expensive.
It doesn't have to be super difficult.
And if you can't get like permission
to deploy a separate monitoring and
monitoring system, there's options
that are better than nothing.
And you can mix and match the
approaches to fit your availability
requirements or fit your use case.
And the most important thing is we get to
answer the age old philosophical question.
If your monitoring system falls
over in the middle of the night,
does somebody get paged at 2 AM?
After this talk, the answer should be yes.