Hi.
Yeah, thanks for joining
the conference 42.
My name is Il Kumar Mati, working
as a product owner at Salesforce.
I did my masters from National
Institute of Technology at Warangal.
Today I'm going to present a topic
on AI driven incident resilience.
Scaling subscription systems in the $400
billion economy without losing uptime.
And as for today's endeavor, we
are discussing ERA four topics,
subscription economy, landscape, AI
driven incident detection, architectural
foundations, revenue protection
strategies, implementation roadmap.
So when it comes to subscription
economy landscape, that may go to the,
it's a $400 billion opportunity, which
has a market size of 400 billion.
The current valuation of the global
subscription economy, it's growing
at a faster rate of 18.2% per Ann and
component annual growth rate since 2018.
The main focus is on the digital services.
The percentage of growth is
driven by these digital services.
The shift represents a fundamental
change in how business delivers
value and greater revenue.
The scale of the enterprise
reliability is, harm is now directly
tied to revenue retention, so
revenue retention is important.
When considering, along with the
incident management systems, though
the cost of downtime in subscription
businesses beyond immediate revenue
loss, apart from the revenue loss, there
are other impacts that focus on the
importance of doing the AI driven system.
The average enterprise size company
lost 300 K per hour of downtime.
With this downtime, it impact of is more
and customer acquisition cost wasted
when new users and counter error and
15 to 35% higher shun rates following
significant service disruptions.
Brand reputation damage requiring
six to 12 months to fully recover.
So to recover a brand name, the
brand, the marketing, and all, it
takes around a year to fully recover.
So to avoid this, the reliability
paradox, so we can say what
factors affecting the reliability.
So growth demands innovation.
To get the growth we need A
innovation is required to excel.
So subscription business must continuously
apply new features to remind competi to
and meet evolving customer expectations.
Without the new features, you can't grow
faster and compete with other competitors.
So innovation is a must to grow.
And innovation introduces risk.
When you're innovating something.
The risk will also add
with the new innovations.
So each deployment integration and feature
adoption, it's potential failure points
in increasing complex systems is based
on the complex system, the new features.
The new integrations will increase the
failure points and comes to reliability,
require stability to get it more reliable.
The stability is a key.
Maintaining near feature uptime,
perfect uptime traditionally meant
slowing release cycles and limited
changes, so we try to reliability to
increase the reliability and stability.
We need a perfect up time and slowing
release cycles and limited changes.
So there is a tension between the
innovation and stability Created
impossible choice for engineering leaders.
Now, AI driving instant resilience
emerged as a solution that enables both
rapid evolution and robust reliability.
So this AI driven solution will help.
The robust.
So it gives the robust reliability.
That's what we are focusing
on with the AI reliability.
And comes to the second topic, the AI
drive, incident detection, the new parum.
So we going to, to the AI as a predictive
morals, so from reactor to predictive.
As of now, the traditional instant
management relies on monitoring predefined
threshold and metrics like log time, call
time durations, so detecting problems
only after they are impacted users.
We are getting the metrics or KPIs
after the users are getting impacted
that AI transforms this approach by
learning normal behavior patterns.
Yeah, we can we can understand
the behavior of millions of system
transactions by analyzing the behavior
of the patterns, detecting septal
anomalies that human operators would miss.
Yeah.
Can find those septal anomalies
where human can't find it, and
predicting potential failures.
Ai, you'll predict the failures before
it is cascaded into major incidents,
continuously improving through feedback
loops and outcome analysis, feed
feedback loops like the ai trained
systems with the feedback responses,
and it'll give a better outcome.
Let me go to the next topic.
Architectural foundations of
resilient subscription platforms.
So it main focuses on
distributed arc processing.
This architecture lines the
foundation for distributor processing.
So how region is scalable, microservices
with intelligent load balancing
and regional failure capabilities.
Intelligent load balancing through the
traffic to the different microservices
in the highly scalable environments.
And data streaming real time event
processing with buffering and
replay capabilities to prevent data
laws during incidents or outages.
So data streaming with even
crossing and a sufficient buffer.
We won't lose the downtime and we
will get the required data even
during the loss of during incidents
and multi-region resilience.
So this one Act two diplomat models
with automatic traffic shifting
during regional incidents, like one
region has an incident, it'll route
to the traffic to another region.
So it'll provide better region
resilience and stateful recovery.
Stateful recovery is transaction and
session management with automated
recovery from partial failures.
So the stateful recovery is the failures.
Some of the failures which can
be recovered without any manual
intervention or human intelligence.
CI can recover partially.
So these architectural components, these
four components work together to ensure
that even during incident response, the
customer experience reminds minimally
impacted with near continuous of time.
Continuous of time is
minimizing the downtime.
Yeah, and intelligent storage
and retrieval systems.
These storage systems will minimize
the latency even during incidents.
Latency is like the time
the response is taken.
It'll minimize the latency.
The intelligent storage systems
and retrieval systems will minimize
the latency during incident.
So the one storage and retro
systems are critical to maintain
performance during incidents.
So these systems are critical to maintain
the performance when any incident happen.
So predict to caching.
So it'll predict how much what
to be cached that pre positions
frequently access the data.
So the frequently access
data will be cached.
Based on usage patterns and
intelligent data, tiring that balances
performance needs with storage cost.
The data tiring needs, which level
of data we to store is balancing the
performance when it getting accessed,
and which will reduce the storage cost.
The foster response
requires more storage costs.
Like RAM hardware, so the intelligent
data tiring is like that, and red
replicas that scale horizontally
to handle traffic spikes.
And so the red replicas is made
commonly used with data by multiple
millions of users that can scale
HORR to handle traffic spikes, which
distributed to multiple systems.
The graceful degradation that
prioritizes core functionality
during resource constraints.
So this one is the priority goes
to the core functionality and that
during resource constraints it'll
benefit in improving the latency.
And this is the metrics, the leading
platform, 2 99 0.99% availability
for read operations, even during
significant backend incidents, ensuring
users can still access their content.
Yeah,
so the beyond detection.
Not only detect the problems
incident management, but building
revenue protection, it'll help in
building the revenue protection.
So AI stands beyond incident
management to actively protect
revenue streams without any outages.
Customer satisfaction, churn production.
So let me go to the next topic on this.
Adapt to churn models.
Retention during incidents.
So add one, subscription businesses
are implementing aid Raven Retention
Systems that specifically target risk
customers during and after incident
Windows Risk customers are like, which
are sent due to the customer experience.
And these are.
VL evaluated using impact scoring.
It'll real time assessment of how
instant effects specific user segment
based on their interaction patterns.
Proactive engagement, so how it is
automatically personalized routers to
effect users with appropriate contest
and compensation recovery monitoring.
Tracking post incident usage
patterns to identify users showing
disengagement signals so that
these three help in retention.
The customers during incidents or
like scoring how at what segments
of data users are getting impacted
and how we engage the users.
How we can monitor them back after
incident and see how the user behavior,
so the engagement signals helps in
retention during incidents, how we
can retain returning the customer
using these models that help.
To improve the user experience or user
customer satisfaction after incidents,
AI enabled personalization frameworks.
So AI is using these frameworks to better
improve the incident management and
revenue model, user behavior analysis.
So in this it's continuously monitor
of interaction patterns, content
preferences, and uses usage frequency,
how frequently they use the same data.
What is the preference of using the data?
So this user behavior analysis
is the key part in the framework
and dynamic segmentation.
So this is like on a real time basis.
Classification based on behavior.
So this is dynamically classifying
the behavior of the user, not just
static demographic attributes like
a region how the user behavior is.
It's not like static behavior.
It's dynamically based on the how user is
behaving it and personalized experience.
This is like Tyler interfaces.
Content recommendations.
AI can identify what is good
recommendation based on the user
behavior and feature highlights.
This is the key in the framework
and engagement measurement.
So we generally take the metrics,
comprehensive metrics, capturing
depth and quality of interaction.
How suppose they can, how long the video
is and how much time they watch it.
This's the easy example
of engagement measurement.
These systems maintain engagement
even during incident recovery periods
by routing users to unaffected
features and contents, minimizing
the would impact on their experience.
So during instant recovery, even the EA
enabled system will track and provide the
unaffected features and content companies
implementing advanced personalization,
C 22 to 28, higher customer lifetime
value, and significantly improved
resilience to service receptions.
So the companies who are implementing
this model Frameworks has better
advanced personalization, C 22, 20
8% higher lifetime customer lifetime.
So those who are taking a one year
subscription, they're continuing
to one year subscription, not
terminating at eight months.
This frameworks help to retain
their customer lifetime and
significantly improved their service
during, even during descriptions.
And dynamic pricing.
All dams help in improving the
revenue model during the incident.
So this is mainly focusing on
balancing value and revenue.
So the pricing system say, help
in subscription business, maximize
both acquisitions and retention.
So it considers key parts,
value-based pricing that aligns
cost with customer benefit.
So it is derived by how satisfied
the customer, how the content is
useful for them, how value based
pricing, what value the company
is providing that much pricing.
And elasticity model that produce
conversion rates at various price points.
What is the best conversion
rate that can be available?
That can predict the, a model can
predict and complete to positioning that
dynamically adjust to market changes.
The market changes like the
customer behavior is tuning
to different, experience.
So this AI helps metrics, helps these
algorithms, helps in trying to position
the company into dynamically adjustable
market changes, risk adjustment
offerings that provides appropriate
discounts to add risk segments.
Some segments are risk, so it'll provide
a better offering and it'll recommend the.
Go right, or these algorithms help
in optimization need those risks.
These systems automatically adjust
during instant recovery periods.
So if an incident happens, so
how we it, the AI will balance
out the value and the revenue.
These four models will help in balancing
out the value and revenue during.
Incident recovery periods,
the downtime, future, and
availabilities system failures.
So providing target and incentives to
users who experience service disruption.
So it helped to find the right segment of
users and provide the rise in with broadly
discounting for unaffected segment.
And what is the journey to optimize this?
How, what is aware user
journey optimization?
What is the user journey during
this incident management process?
So say the before the incident.
Pre-incident standard personalized
journeys based on engagement patterns.
And conversion optimization.
This is before an incident happened.
We have these engagement patterns,
how the customers are engaged with the
features or patterns we have, and active
incident dynamically during rerouting
to functional features, transparent
communication and expectation management.
So during an incident, this AI model
will help rerouting to functional
features, how which feature is more
feasible and how we can transparently
communicate those features to the
users and meet the user expectations.
Initial recovery.
It's like enabling of features
with prioritized access
for high value customers.
So when you recover it, who is the
right set of users has to access that?
Then we can reprioritize to a
low level of low level, low value
customers and stabilization.
Targeted re-engagement campaigns
and satisfaction monitoring
with compensatory offerings.
So to stabilize this to understand the
user behavior, understand the engagement,
how user is engaging with, and by
monitoring with compensatory offerings,
it'll offer to provide a new offers, new
feature, new free features like that.
And post recovery growth.
Post recovery growth how the growth of
the company or growth of the product.
During our, after this is mainly focusing
on after incident accelerated feature
adoption and expansion opportunities
with renewable trust emphasis.
Try to build the trust, try to
provide the right service, try
to improve the good offerings.
This AI leading subscription
business don't just manage incidents.
They transform the entire user
experience around service descriptions
to maintain engagement and
protect customer lifetime value.
Yeah.
And to implement this, what
roadmap we have in place psych
the main four categories we have.
Foundational data collection.
It'll focus on comprehensive
telemetry across all the system
components with unified logging
and standardized event formats.
The timeline it takes around
one to two months, and the
next one is baseline modeling.
So this in during this time, it'll
establish normal operation patterns and
identify key performance indicators,
what indicators are required for
specific business and correlate
with user satisfaction to understand
the user behavior, which patterns,
which indicators are required.
It'll model during that baseline modeling.
This will take around.
Two to three months.
Yeah.
And initial detection models,
so this is like a deploy first
degeneration, anomaly detection
with human verification feedbacks.
And this loops to minimize false post two
is AI system, which will be trained with
the feedbacks that's coming from human.
Verification.
So initially it starts with the
AA first generation system and
later on getting trained with human
verification feedbacks and it getting,
trying and better for future model.
It takes around three to four months
and response automation gradually
implement automated responses.
For well understood incident patterns
with clear remediation parts.
So after the initial detection models,
we'll go to response automation.
It was system is fully trained
and it was gradually implemented
the automated responses as we
captured the human responses in
the third in the previous months.
And now we are going
to automated responses.
The incident patterns with clear
remediation parts will analyze it
and continuing the advanced
capabilities with implementation
roadmap, there are two, which takes
one with the six to 12 months.
This mainly focus on
user impact correlation.
Connect systems metrics directly
to user experience indicators.
So we have, it'll follow some of the
indicators, metrics, it'll co correlate
with the user experience and predictive
modeling or predicting shift from reactive
to anticipatory incident management.
So this is a great, with predictor
modeling, it'll shift how the incident
management system will re from
reactor to predictor and retention
integration, link incident data
with customer engagement systems.
This will help in
retention of the customers.
And the second model we
have here to and beyond.
So in this phase it takes
autonomous recovery, self-healing
systems with minimal human
interventions, autonomous recovery.
It'll gain the knowledge by itself,
which is called self-healing
systems, and trained by themselves
without human intervention.
And the next topic it is cross
platform intelligence, which is shared
learning across multiple product lines.
So multiple A models or multiple
systems has common data.
It'll share the data to get and
trying the A model, continuous
architecture revolution system that
adopt based on incident patterns.
This architecture will continuously
improve and improve adaptability
based on incident patterns.
So incident patterns the first
quarter, what type of incidents
and what geography or from which
discovery, which product line.
So it's not like incident patterns.
This is continuously evolve and find
the new patterns and continuously
architecture will evolve.
Yeah.
Is the roadmap.
And the guidelines for
resource investment.
So the, we classify as team structure,
which is hybrid squared, combining SRE
data scientists and product engineers.
The ranges, it range from the project
size to five to seven members.
And executed with execute sponsorship.
And when it comes to technology stack,
the real time data processing framework is
uses machine learning, operations platform
and automated orchestration tools.
It is visualization capabilities, so
we need a visualization to see the
performance, the matrix, the output,
along with the machine learning
frameworks and real time data crossing.
With mathematical models which we covers
under technology stack and investment
returns, we can take it around.
On enterprise implementations, show
around three to five times the return
on investments within 18 months
through reduce downtime and improve
retention and decrease recovery costs.
Sees the what this AI driven system
is capable of giving three to five
x or y. The KEYT chem is with this
model it a driven, it transforms
AI transforms incident management
from reactive to predictive.
So the A model is staying
from reactor to predictor.
We are expecting the same early
detection and automated response
dramatically reduced customer impact.
We are predicting and detecting
early and providing automated
response, which reduce customer
impact and architectural resilience
in your revenue production strategy.
So how the architecture helps the
intelligent systems maintain functionality
because the intelligent system know
which functionality is more critical,
even during partial failure, it's keep
on running with critical functionality
and the user behavior preference drive
the, which functionality is critical.
And user experience continuity
require cross-functional integration.
This is like connecting
technical monitoring with
customer engagement systems.
And so it's cross-functional integration.
The technical monitoring with
the customer engagement systems.
Hey, customer can do some part of
our operations by themselves and
they can monitor by themselves.
These features in the cross-functional
integration by cross-functionally
integrate the technical monitoring
with the customer engagement systems
like CRM and back office systems.
The user experience APRO
and implementation follows
a clear maturity model.
So start with foundations and
progress build advanced capabilities.
Like auto response start with initial
detection model and then growing up to
advanced capabilities of auto response.
These helps in implementing
with more clear maturity model.
Thank you for joining this conference.