Good morning and good afternoon everybody.
My name is Ana Yata, and today
I'll be walking you through how AI
transformed the incident management.
In supply chain operations.
So from whole reactive process to
a proactive process via automated
prevention system, a lot of this thinking
builds on both academic work and my
professional experience including my time
at Amazon where we dealt largely with
a complexity of large scale operations
and the importance of minimizing the
disruptions, especially the supply chains.
The critical challenge is basically
like cast cutting a supply chain
disruptions, supply chains are
usually a fragile ecosystems, a
single failure delayed shipment.
Or a warehouse breakdown can create a
ripple effects across the whole network.
At Amazon, I saw this firsthand.
One node in the system such as a
regional fulfillment center could trigger
stockouts and missed delivery promises.
The downstream traditional approaches
usually tend to focus on fixing
the problems after they occur, but
by that point, the customer trust
and revenue are already at risk.
This is a challenge we
are trying to solve.
Next is AI revolution from reactive
approach to a proactive approach.
As I said earlier, here is a fundamental
shift instead of waiting for a
breakdown and then scrambling in the
AI enables us to predict and prevent.
At Amazon, for example, we used a
predictive analytics to forecast
ASIN level product overrides
before they disrupted the sales,
essentially intervening before
the customers felt the pain.
The same principle applies here, the
you need to automate the detection,
gain the full visibility, and then
proactively resolve the issues.
Next is a comprehensive
data stream analysis.
To do this, AI systems must
ingest multiple streams of data.
For example, supplier metrics, the
transportation timelines, inventory
flows, whether even geopolitical risks.
No single analyst can connect
all these dots fast enough,
but machine learning can.
At Amazon, we often layer clickstream.
Supply chain and vendor data to get the
whole 360 degree view of operations.
This holistic perspective is what drives
early detection and smart interventions.
Next is machine learning
pattern recognition.
Machine learning builds a
baseline of what's normal
looks like in your operations.
Once that's established anomaly
stand out immediately, whether it's
a spike in transit delays or unusual
supply lead times that you have.
At Amazon anally detection models
helped us to identify when a particular
product class was deviating from its
usual demand supply chain pattern
leading us to adjust it before
escalating into a larger problem.
The key is moving from a
hand site to a foresight.
Next is ink.
Iot enabled real time
warehouse visibility.
Warehouses are the
heartbeat of supply chains.
The iot sensors make them
smarter by tracking everything.
Like temperature, the humidity
and the vibration, and lot with
respect to equipment health as well.
This data creates a
digital nervous system.
For example, at Amazon, we tracked a
conveyor performance and environmental
conditions to spot the bottlenecks before
the disrupted The order flow iot paid
with AI enables us to prevent further
actions rather than a costly downtime.
Next is computer vision
and predictive maintenance.
Computer vision is like
giving eyes to machines.
It detects wear and tear patterns
in equipment, misaligned packages,
or early failure indicators.
Coupled with predictive maintenance
algorithms, organizations can
schedule fixes before breakdowns can
occur during mind time at Amazon.
The predictive maintenance on
sortation equipment saved us
countless hours of downtime and
directly impacted the delivery sles.
Next is reinforcement learning
for response optimization.
When incidents do occur, reinforcement
learning ensures the right response.
These systems learn from historical
responses, what worked, what
didn't, and optimize the routing
of alerts to the right teams.
Think of it as a continuously
learning playbook.
At Amazon, we often refined alert
routing logic to reduce the noise
for ops teams ensuring critical
incidents got immediate attention
while also avoiding the alert fatigue.
Next is advanced predictive
escalation systems.
These systems don't just like flag
issues, they predict escalation.
For example, models can anticipate when
an incident breach might when you know,
like when an incident might breach.
SLA thresholds and trigger
automated migration protocols.
Faster than even like human intervention.
So this is crucial in high velocity
businesses like Amazon where even
few minutes of delay in addressing
the fulfillment incidents can cascade
into thousands of missed deliveries.
Next comes to the federated learning
for collaborative intelligence.
Supply chains aren't also, they're
not isolated, so they are as
they are ecosystems of partners.
Federated learning lets companies
share threat intelligence
without exposing sensitive data.
Imagine multiple partners contributing
insights on disruptions, collectively
strengthening the network.
In finance, we call this as
consortium data in supply chain.
It's basically a collaborative resilience.
Next two comes to the blockchain
integration for audit ID trails blockchain
ensures also the trust and compliance.
It provides immutable audit
trails and also enables the
faster and smarter contracts for
automated compliance reporting.
At Amazon, while we didn't use a
blockchain directly for incident
management, we heavily invested
in immutable logging for Audible.
So similar in principle to the
blockchain, ensuring the integrity
across the large scale systems.
Next is implementation
of strategy framework.
Of course, transformation
requires a structured approach.
We need to start with
assessment around the pilots to
validate then scale gradually.
At Amazon, we followed similar playbooks
when deploying the new data science tools.
Begin small through the impact
and then expand systematically.
Continuous optimization is
also always like vital as new
risks and data patterns emerge.
Next is operational benefits and impact.
The benefits are tangible.
Like they reduced meantime to resolution.
Fewer escalations higher C higher
service reliability at Amazon, every
percentage point improvement in uptime
or delivery reliability translates
into usually like millions of dollars
saved and the customer trust gains.
The same benefits extend here.
Proactive systems save
time, money, and reputation.
Finally, the future of
supply chain operations.
The benefits are tangible here as well.
So the future is about like
residence and then adaptability.
AI will transform supply chains from
firefighting to foresight driven.
Orchestration.
Organizations that invest now will thrive
as networks get more global and complex.
My experience at Amazon showed me
that scale and complexity demand
nothing less than AI power solutions.
Next is, thank you for your time.
So if you have any questions
feel free to drop an email to me.
So my email is krishna c dot ya@gmail.com.
Thank you.