Hello, everyone.
I am Bhanu Vanendra Babu Gogula, a full
stack web engineer, and thank you for
joining my session on migrating articles
from Salesforce Before we proceed with the
discussion, I have a disclaimer to share.
The views and opinions shared in this
presentation are my own and do not
represent the views or official position
of my current and previous employers.
The content is based on
general industry knowledge and
publicly available information.
No sensitive or confidential information
will be shared in this video.
During this talk today, we'll talk
about importance of AEM guides
and how to migrate content from
crites efficiently while minimizing
downtime and ensuring data integrity.
A little bit background about me.
I'm a technical professional with more
than 10 years of experience developing
software for various industries.
I hold a master's degree in
computer science from the
University of Central Missouri, USA.
As a full stack developer, I bring
expertise in both front end and back
end development, adding value and
innovation to every project I worked on.
In this talk, let's talk about
introduction to data and importance of
AEM guides, extracting article information
from Salesforce, HTML page creation of
each article, cleaning HTML and updating
paths, HTML to data conversion, uploading
content into AEM guides, validation,
advantage of this migration approach.
In today's world, organizations
deal with a lot of content, so they
need a strong system to create,
manage, and share it easily.
While Salesforce works well for
managing customer relationships, it
does not have all the tools needed
for complex content management.
AEM Guides is a better choice
because it offers powerful features
like advanced data support.
Tools for organized content creation
and smooth content delivery.
Before we dive into migration
process, let's first discuss two
approaches for content creation,
linear documentation and component
based content management system, CCMS.
In a linear documentation
approach, content is created in the
straightforward, sequential manner.
When the same content is needed in
the other document or sections, it
has to be copied again and again.
Instead of just linking to it,
this create a lot of duplicate
content and unnecessary work.
Let's look at an example.
Imagine we have a
document A and document B.
Both documents contains the
same information about this,
specific product future.
With linear documentation, we
should have to copy this content
into both documents separately.
If there are any updates to the
product future, You need to go
to document A and document B
individually and make the changes.
These duplications can
lead to several challenges.
The main thing is reduced maintainability.
Each time you make a change, you must
ensure that the update is made in
every place where the content appears.
And, it increases workload
like a manual updating multiple
documents is time consuming and
increases the chance of errors.
as you can see in this slide,
a small update in topic 2 now
has to made in multiple places.
As the number of document grows,
this become even more time
consuming and difficult to manage.
So now coming to, component based
documents with the CCMS, this is where
actually, component, CCMS really helps.
Unlike linear documentation.
CCMS gives us a much easier way
to manage and reuse content.
With CCMS, we can break content
into smaller reusable chunks
that we can link wherever needed.
This means we don't have to copy content
over and make updates much simpler.
In this diagram, the content is broken
down into smaller pieces called topics.
A map is used to organize and combine
the needed topics into a document.
We use a built in data tool to generate
the map in the required format, which
means by using the existing topic,
the map can be generated in PDF,
eBooks, mobile, desktop, web format.
We don't need to create separately.
let's look at example.
This one.
let's say document a and document B
both have a section that describes
the same product future instead of
copying that content into each document.
CCMS allow us to create a
content pieces for the future.
Then we can just link this piece
into a document A and document
B and any other documents that
need product future information.
Now, if you need to update the product
future description, we just update
the content chunk in one place.
Thanks to the linking future,
this change is instantly reflected
in document A, document B.
And everywhere else, this
content chunk is used.
This has several advantages,
like no duplication, the content
only exists once, so there is no
need to manage multiple copies.
Easy updates, updating content
becomes much quicker, since you
only need to make the change once.
Better organization, CCMS keeps your
content organized by breaking into
smaller parts that are easy to reuse.
so with CCMS.
Updating information across documents
is no longer a repetitive task.
Instead, it is efficient and
scalable, allowing you to maintain
accuracy along all your content.
Now, coming to the actual migration
process, according to industry
guidelines, the migration process
can be completed in six steps.
The first step is extracting
article information.
The first step is to pull the
content out of Salesforce.
Imagine we have thousands of articles
stored in Salesforce, and we need to get
each article's title, article content, and
any metadata related to that particular
article, and we need to extract that into
the format that we can move over to AEM.
To do this efficiently, we use
a tool called Selenium Wire.
This tool helps us automate the
process, meaning we don't have to
manually copy and paste every article.
Selenium Wire goes to the Salesforce and
pulls out all the information we need.
efficiently with the,
minimal risk of errors.
In simple terms, Selenium wire act like
a robot collecting data for us so we can
focus on other parts of the migration.
Once this content is collected,
we are ready for the next step.
And I had provided, some,
some codes, sample snippet
for the better understanding.
It will help you more clearly.
Now, coming to the second
step, creating HTML pages.
Once we extract data from the
Salesforce, the next step is to create
individual HTML pages for each article.
The HTML pages will act as a
temporary format before we convert
the content into data, which AEM uses.
In this step, we take the title,
content, and metadata from each article
and put them into a HTML structure.
This setup organizes everything
into neat mini webpages.
Making it easy to work
in the following steps.
Each article becomes its own HTML file,
complete with the title content and
make the transition into AEM smoother.
Now coming to step number three,
cleaning HTML and, updating relative
paths, now that our content is in
HTML format, it's time to clean up
the code and make sure everything
works properly when we move to AEM.
This is where we make
sure the images links.
And other resources are linked correctly.
Updating path.
First, we check all the path
in our HTML files are correct.
For example, if an article has an
image, we want to make sure that
image will show up correctly in AEM.
We update these, path to that
they are ready to, AEM system.
We'll make sure all these related paths
are updated according to the here we use
a tool called GTD to clean up the HTML.
This tool goes through the code and
fixes any errors, make sure that HTML
files are neat and well formatted.
This step helps avoid problems later on
when we convert HTML into data XML files.
In simple words, this step like
doing a quick cleanup for our files
to make sure everything looks and
works correctly in the new system.
Now converting HTML to data.
After cleaning.
After cleaning the HTML, the
next step is to converting HTML
into data XML files, here in the
XML usually as topics and maps.
Data is a way of organizing
content by breaking into a
smaller topic based pieces.
Make it easier to manage, update,
and reuse in different documents.
Let's talk about a few important
features of AEM Guides.
In AEM Guides, we organize content
into specific types like a content,
task, reference, topic, map.
By structuring content into these
categories, we create a clear,
organized way to present information
that makes it easy to locate and reuse.
Another great advantage of data is that
it allows multiple delivery points.
This means We can publish
the same content in different
formats for various platforms.
For example, with the data open
toolkit, we can take one set
of content and easily turn into
different format, such as webpages,
PDFs, or mobile friendly versions.
The best part is that we don't
have to create the content each
time for different formats.
The data tool handles the transformation.
So the same content can be
used across multiple platforms.
This saves time, reduces effort, and
ensures that all versions stay consistent,
no matter how people view the content.
Another big advantage of data
is rebranding flexibility.
Data make it easy to update
content, to match rebranding colors.
Because the content is organized
and structured, pre user chunks,
you can quickly make changes
that apply across the documents.
For example, if a company logo
or design style changes, you
only need to update in one place.
Then data automatically
applies, applies that update.
throughout every document where the
content is used, saving time and effort
while keeping everything consistent.
Another example is like, where
the product name changes.
Let's say a product name is
rebranded and its name changes, but
its product name is mentioned in
thousands of articles with the data.
You don't have to update
every article separately.
Instead, you can change the product name.
In a central variable or a key map,
wherever the product name is used,
it will update automatically in all
the documents, making rebranding
quick, accurate, and efficient.
So once, coming to the fifth
step, this is, where we are
uploading content into AEM guides.
Once our articles are in data format, they
are ready to be uploaded into AEM guides.
This is a step where we transfer the
content from our local files to AEM.
which is a web based system.
To upload the content smoothly, we use
a tool called ACS Common Asset Importer.
This tool ensures that every piece
of content, including titles,
body, text, images, and metadata,
gets moved into AEM correctly.
Imagine we are putting our organized
content into a digital bookshelf.
AEM Guides becomes a system that
stores everything neatly, and let
us manage it all in one place.
Now, once everything is completed
here, the final step is a validation.
in this step, we double check everything
we need to make sure that all the
articles and images appear correctly in
AEM, make sure all the links works and
metadata, whatever we extracted with
respect to article is in the proper place.
In validation, we go through each article
in AEM to ensure that it looks the way it
should and everything function properly.
If any issues comes up, we can catch and
fix them before we finish the migration.
Now coming to advantages of this migration
approach, automation and efficiency by
automate automating the process from,
extraction to final validation, we
reduce the need for manual in manual
effort and save significant time data
integrity, each step of the migration
is structured to maintain the integrity
and consistency of the content.
Scalability, the, this utility is designed
to handle migration of various sizes
from a few articles to thousands and,
multiple validation points ensures that
errors and, detected early minimizing
the risk by automating the entire
process, the, by automating the entire
migration process, the solution can
potentially save substantial resources and
resulting in, Significant cost reduction.
So migrating content from Salesforce
to AEM Guides offers a more powerful
and efficient way to manage your
content by moving from linear
documentation to component based system.
So you improve the way the content
is created, maintained, and reused.
This process not only save time
and money, but also positions your
organization for long term success
in managing growing content needs.
Thank you so much for your attention,
and I hope this gives you a clear
understanding of why migrating
to AEM guides is beneficial
for your content management.
Thank you.