Hello everybody, I'm Rena.
Good morning and hope you're
having a wonderful day.
And today we are going to talk about AI
driven rate limiting for resilient and
cost efficient cloud API production.
Wow, that's a mouthful, isn't it?
And it sounds incredibly technical.
Let me rephrase it to simplify it.
It's all about keeping the dose to our
digital world open for you and other
legitimate users and closed to attackers.
Because the truth is we all use API every
single day, whether we realize it or not.
The morning coffee that
you grabbed on your way.
To office An API processed the
payment, not the coffee though.
The map that you check for
traffic details on your vacation.
The API has delivered that MAP data.
The Taylor Swift or the adult song
that you listen to in your car.
API stream the song to your.
APIs are the invisible
waiters of the tech world.
Taking our request and bringing back what
we asked for, they are the foundation of
modern business and lifestyle convenience.
And here's the problem, the more
important something becomes.
The more valuable it is.
Each one of those convenient APIs
is a potential for an attacker.
And as a reliance on the APIs has
exploded in the modern world, so has,
it's their appeal to the bad actors.
So the question is never about whether
your firm is going to get attacked.
It's about how well equipped
are you as a company.
To deal with these kind of
attackers when it happens.
Are you going to shut down your system
or shut out your estimate users?
Which brings me to a story about
a store on earth, a crowded
sales team, a very dumb door.
I tell you,
imagine you are a store owner.
Your door is like an API few years ago.
When you started it,
you had a simple rule.
Five people allowed entry
in the store per hour.
It was easy, but now your
store is the heart of the town.
Your door has, your
door is just not a door.
It's a huge business and everyone
wants to come in and shop and
probably shop listers as well here.
Old rule of five people per hour.
It's a nightmare.
I tell you on the, whenever there
is a sale, as a crowd shows up, your
rules is only five allowed at a time,
slamming the door on potential customers.
This leaves the customers who are
frustrated walking and they walk away with
potential and possible repeat business.
And if you leave the door open.
Shoplifters can sneak
in and clean you out.
U Pac Block real users
or let the thieves in.
This is exact dilemma of traditional API.
Production organizations must choose
between aggressive protection that
blocks that could block legitimate
users or lenient policies that
leave systems vulnerable to abuse.
This binary approach results in
significant revenue losses, degradate
user experiences and compromised
reliability, but AI and machine learning
presence and opportunity to fundamentally
reimagine API protection through real
time analysis and adaptive mechanisms.
Moving on.
Let me tell you about my friend Sarah.
She runs a travel app and
she lived this nightmare.
This travel app, let's say, for the
ease of understanding, has a limit
of five users per hour as well.
Practically, it'll be more, but let's keep
it five for the ease of understanding.
It happens that a famous influencer
wrote about this travel app in
her block and the, and suddenly
there are traffic spikes.
Real people excited to book their
next trip, come to her app trying
to book, and the app slams the.
For an hour, there is no revenue.
Angry users were probably in
thousands because everybody was
excited right after the article.
This is this tactic
threshold problem estimate.
Traffic from marketing campaigns
doesn't follow predictable patterns.
The next day, a bot which is interested
to steal data, comes into the app.
Oh, from probably 10 different, a
hundred different IP addresses and each
slowly trying to hack the system and
they try to ensure that they, these
logged in boards stay under the rule
of five per five people per hour rule.
Her system sees nothing wrong.
The boards get in and scrape
all of flight and hotel data.
This is a sophisticated attacker problem.
They distribute attacks across multiple
ips and varying times to stay below the
radar or below the detected thresholds.
The cost, the false positive problem.
When the estimate users are
actually blocked, they may not.
Retail requests leading to
a loss transactions and the
damaged customer relationships
significantly impacting API driven.
Revenue streams.
And the other problem is when there
is a sophisticated attack by the boats
the, this traditional rate limiting
cannot identify that there is an
attack happening at all in first place.
Forget about even mediating
it or responding to that.
Returning to a store owner.
What if we gave him a genius security
guard instead of a simple rule?
The guard doesn't just count people
he watches how they behave is
someone just slowly walking in,
looking at products, probably fine.
He's a group of people certainly shuffling
in all wearing similar clothes and bee
lining to the most expensive items.
Probably a big red flag.
That's what AI does through
behavioral feature analysis.
Instead of just counting requests,
it analyzes dozens of attributes
simultaneously, like request timing
patterns, payload characteristics,
geographic distribution, user
agent diversity and response
code sequences, et cetera.
Plus, it adds a temporal dimensions,
for example, understanding requests.
Sequences, user session patterns and
traffic over evolution over time.
It knows that the EDL users logs in,
looks for something, adds the cart,
and probably looks for something else.
But what does none of it?
It doesn't because it's not
buying, it doesn't put in the cart.
And this kind of temporal awareness
enables detection of slow burn
attacks, unsophisticated attacks that
might appear benign individually.
Talking about how does it work?
Think about it like this.
You don't you don't
hire one security guard.
You hire a committee of many experts.
One expert could be a geographic
visit, one could be a timing guru.
One could be all about browsers.
One could be about IP addresses.
So let's say we just take three of
them into concentration and a request
comes in, the committee votes.
The geographic guy says it's fine,
but the timing guru and the browser
expert says, nah, dude, that's weird.
The majority rules unblock it.
This committee is what we call.
Decision.
Pre ensembles like random forest
and gradient boosting, they excel
in handling mixed data types and are
relatively interpretable and capture
complex non-linear relationships.
Between features.
Of course, we face training challenges,
estimate traffic, typically far
outnumbers malicious requests.
We address this through
advanced sampling techniques.
And cause sensitive learning.
And here's the crucial part.
This committee never stops training.
It continuously learns from new
attacks and changes the traffic and
changes traffic patterns through online
learning algorithms and periodic.
Retraining, retraining strategies
periodically retrain strategies
to understand what kind of
attack may happen in future.
This kind of continuous learning
capability is what keeps
the system smart over time.
I.
Back to Sarah's travel app.
The influencer writes about her app again
this time with her AI in her system.
Her system sees that there are
traffic spike, but it is also sees
that requests are coming in from.
Different users,
different Instagram users.
People are browsing from different
pages using various devices, and AI
thinks this looks like a happy crowd.
The door stays wide open.
Meanwhile, those sneaky bots come back.
The AI sees they are perfectly
spaced, have DentiCal, so source of.
My source from where they come in
analytical software and hit only
the login page and they don't do
anything much apart from search.
They, I think this is suspicious,
but instead of slamming the door,
it might just slow them down.
This is progressive throttling,
moving beyond binary decision
to implement increasingly.
Restrictive measures based on
confidence level, subtle delays, rate
deduction, and only fully blocking
for clearly malicious activity.
The AI also uses dynamic user
classification, anonymously grouping
users in a behavioral cohorts
based on historical patterns.
Application users, car application,
usage characteristics, and risk profiles.
Users can move between these kind of
segments from based on the real behavior,
earning higher privilege through
legitimate users or facing restrictions
for certain suspicious activities.
Okay, how do we build this?
The beauty is the cloud
gives us the perfect tools.
Imagine you need to upgrade security
for your store coming back to the store.
You, even though we did speak about
a smart security guard, but if
you think about it, we cannot use
a single security guard like Hulk
who wouldn't be able to multitask.
You need a team, a camera, to monitor
a sec, a fast security guard who
runs around, an expert consultant
at the back end who's monitoring
things on camera and an intercom to
connect them all to be able to talk.
And it need not be just
one single security card.
It can be multiple, but that's
the whole point, having a team.
On AWS we leverage this with Full Stack.
We leverage this full stack with API,
gateway, Lambda, and SageMaker on
Azure, the API management with Azure
Machine Learning on Google Cloud.
It's API gateway with Vertex ai.
Now, what if your store
becomes so successful that
it branches on in different.
Countries, different locations.
You need to be consistent
with your security everywhere.
The challenge is making sure
that the security protocol in one
branch doesn't drift from another.
The solution, you don't let
branch make its own rules.
You have one head of
security at headquarters.
Who sends the rule to every
branch and every branch executes
it in with their local team.
Multi-cloud strategies provide
additional resilience, but con
introduce complexity in data
synchronization on model consistency.
Container orchestration.
Platforms like Kubernetes can
facilitate deployment consistency
across different cloud providers.
Now, how does AI actually distinguish less
estimate spikes from attacks in real time?
Let's get into real magic with three
specific attacks on Sarah's travel app.
Stopping credential stuffing attackers
take millions of stolen passwords and
try them on Sarah's login page, AI
analyzes the characteristics of these
traffic surges, which helps understand
the gradual onset of estimate spikes
that often contrast sharply with sudden
appearance of distributed attacks.
It sees the pattern of
rapid FA rapid failures.
From different IP addresses
and blocks, suspicious ranges.
The essentials login used by actually such
ips are also forced to reset passwords,
ensuring safety of the app data and user
data as well, preventing API scrapping.
So what happens and the competitors
uses Spike uses bot to systematically
steal Sarah's entire inventory.
Yeah.
Examines request payload
patterns and sequences.
Real users actually browse naturally
while scrappers execute perfect robotic
patterns to find data and don't do
anything with the data, like they
don't add it to the cart and all.
So that is an identifier and AI
stops those kind of attacks, catching
low and slow account takeover.
How does this happen?
And a hacker gets a valid account, say,
and slowly gathers data over weeks.
AI uses behavioral profiling and examines
user session behaviors to spot anomalies.
Like in this case, is the user
logging to just view personal data.
And payment details of the account,
then probably that's suspicious.
AI models examine request payload
patterns, response code sequences,
and user session behaviors and
statistical correlation across sources.
These capabilities are essential
for detecting distributed attacks,
credential attacks and attacks
like credential, stuffing API,
scrapping and resource exhaustion.
Attempts.
Let's talk about the best part.
The payoff.
Remember those boards that
was sneaking into Sarah's app?
Every one of them was costing her
money by stopping them at the door.
Companies see 30% lower infrastructure
costs because they are not
serving junk traffic anymore.
It teams get 40% of their time
back because they don't have to
look at bug things that are not
even getting into the system.
Plus.
25% improvement in resource
efficiency by right sizing based
on estimate traffic patterns.
This precision of AI driven blocking
reduces the need of over pro over
provisioning infrastructure to
handle potential attack traffic
deserting in substantial savings for.
High traffic applications.
This is a win for security.
This is a win for your team.
This is a huge win for
your budget and company.
And needless to say, this kind of
safeguards in place for users, data
leads to reputation of the firm,
which surges the company's evaluation.
And now
this isn't also, this isn't.
Set it and forget it system.
Remember, a committee of experts,
they never stop learning.
They are constantly learning
through continuous adapt adaptation.
Few things for them to evolve over time.
For example, data collection, traffic
patterns, user behaviors, attack
indicators are continuously gathered.
Drift detection monitoring systems.
Identify when users' behaviors
evolve to understand what is
generic user behavior and what is
an or anomaly pattern analysis.
Online learning algorithms update
models as new data arrives to
identify new patterns to new patterns.
To be aware of the attacks and estimate
user behaviors, field integration,
security team, investigations,
and user reports are incorporated.
AB testing, gradual rollout of
updates, validates improvements.
This ensures protection remains effective
as new threats emerged and legitimate
usage patterns shift over time.
The system that protected
Sarah's app last year.
Evolves to handle newer attacks.
If it happens tomorrow,
how do we know it's working?
We need to both tech.
We need both technical metrics like
detection, accuracy, performance
resource utilization, and adaptation
rates, and business impact metrics.
Remember Sarah's story.
The real success wasn't just blocking
the attacks, but the revenue impact of
blocking estimate users and improved
customer satisfaction, fewer support
tickets and reduced infrastructure costs.
Effective evaluation necessities
holistic view, combining security
outcomes with tangible business impact.
Relying solely on security
metrics provides an incomplete
picture of the system.
Systems, true performance and value.
Now let's make this concrete with
real world case study that could,
that could be Sarah's success story.
A major e-commerce platform was
experiencing credential stuffing attacks.
During peak shopping season, traditional
rate limiting blocked estimate shoppers
resulting in loss sales losses ti
estimated to be 2 million annually.
This, they deployed this because of this.
Later on, they deployed
AI driven rate limiting.
With progressive throttling and user
segmentation, the system analyzed
50 plus behavioral indicators to
distinguish between estimate shoppers.
And attackers, the results are staggering.
False positive rate reduced by 92%,
successfully blocked sophisticated
distributed attacks while hand handling
300% traffic spikes during flash sales.
Infrastructure cost reduced by
25% through elimination of attack.
Attack traffic and this ingest theory.
This is proven strategy
with dramatic results.
Looking ahead.
We see emerging technologies like deep
learning for more accurate pattern
recognition, reinforcement learning
for adaptive response strategies,
and automated feature engineering,
reducing expert requirements,
reducing expertise requirements.
Organizations that invest in
building the necessary capabilities
will gain strategic advantages.
Superior security.
PO Posture, enhanced reliability and
user experience reduced operational
overhead and competitive differentiation
to better a PF protection.
Like I told earlier, if your
protecting your data and user's
data, your reputation increases and
so does your company's evaluation.
And as a digital economy.
Continues to expand those with
most effective API protection
strategies will be best positioned
to capture the opportunities of
increasingly corrected world.
So what's the story?
It's about moving from rigid, dumb
rule that hurts your business.
To a smart adapter
system that protects it.
It's about using the cloud to build
a team of AI services that work
together as a genius security guard.
It's about keeping your doors open for
businesses, for business, not businesses.
Of course, it could be businesses as
well for everyone who brings their.
And firmly closed for those who don't.
The future is intelligent, adaptive,
and efficient, and it's available today.
So let's make use of it in your
respective systems and companies
wherever you are working.
I would like to thank all of you for
this opportunity and sticking with
me to understand this topic today.
Thank you.