Hello, everyone.
Good day.
This is Pavan Vovveti.
Welcome to Conf42
Incident Management 2024.
Today, I'm going to talk about
the role of API security in
modern enterprise platforms.
Let us explore the challenges, the
security challenges, best practices,
and future trends in securing APIs.
Before I even go there, I have a
disclaimer to say the views and opinions
expressed in this presentation are my own.
and do not represent the views
or official position of my
current and previous employers.
The content is based on
general industry knowledge and
publicly available information.
No proprietary or confidential information
will be shared during this talk.
Thank you.
A little bit background about me.
I'm a seasoned technology
professional with over 15 years
experience in application development
across diverse industries.
Academically, I hold a master's
degree in computer science from
Staffordshire University, England, UK.
My expertise lies in blending robust
security measures with cutting edge
development practices, ensuring the
seamless integration of security
into the development life cycle.
With over 10 years of focused
experience in security, particularly
in application security, platform
architecture, and API security.
What I'm going to talk about today
Introduction to API security challenges,
what are the best practices, industry
guidelines for API security, implementing
security across the API lifecycle, what
are the various tools and technologies
available in the industry to enhance the
security posture within the organization.
I have two case studies to talk about.
One is the.
a large financial organization, how
they implemented successfully the
security, by following the security
guidelines, the lessons learned from
a security breach, the future trends
in API security, and then conclusion.
Let's deep dive into the
introduction to API security.
APIs have become the backbone of
modern enterprise platforms, playing
a pivotal role in enabling seamless.
integration and communication
between the component to
component or system to system.
They allow business to connect
applications, services, platform
efficiently, supporting a range
of operations from cloud computing
to mobile app integrations.
However, this is very interconnectedness,
exposing the organizations to
a significant security risk.
Often handling sensitive data
like personal user information
or business intelligence can
become prime targets for any cyber
attacks if not adequately secured.
Saying that, as APIs become more integral
to business processes, ensuring their
security is not just a technical concern
but a critical business priority.
The APIs can be severe, ranging from
data breaches and huge financial losses.
Sometimes it even damages the reputation
of the company or organization
and even regulatory penalties.
What are the challenges
we have in the industry?
So these are the main challenges
I put just to discuss here,
within the timeframe available.
The authentication and authorization,
ensuring only authorized
users can access resources.
What does it mean?
So any user interacting with any of our
system to have the data, the user is, have
access to the data, which we are going
to provide from the company APIs or any
service we provide to retrieve the data
from our data servers or data storage.
So user allowed is, does he
have, does that person has.
Permissions are related to the groups,
belong to the groups or policies.
So how do we make sure this user is the
right user to have the, to have these
data which we are providing to the user?
And also, of course, the
authentication methods can expose
APS to unauthorized access.
Before even we authorize the user,
we need to authenticate the user.
is that person is the same person
which we have registered or which
registered with us and the second
one is the data encryption.
Data in transit must be encrypted
to prevent interception.
Weak encryption protocols can leave data
vulnerable to man in the middle attacks.
Any API to API communication at a
data encryption at rest will prevent
the man in the middle attack.
Any.
Say example, API 1 is calling API 2, a
bad actor in the middle, intercept the,
intercept over the network, the HTTP
request or response to have the data.
So if we encrypt the data, that will
be more difficult for a bad actor to,
to have the data, to process the data.
And there is one more rate
limiting preventing abuse.
a denial of service attacks by
controlling the number of API
requests made within a time frame.
Misconfigured rate limits can
either throttle legitimate traffic
or expose APIs to overload.
what is the rate limit?
So any API I have, I can configure
how many requests per second or per
minute I can have it as per my business
requirements or business, needs.
to have the, to have the interaction
with my, the lowest possible, data
storage or, any other system to
retrieve the data I can configure,
I can configure the rate limit.
My API is going to have only 50
requests per second or a hundred
seconds, a hundred requests.
So that I know when any number
increased all of a sudden,
that means that's an abuse.
That's maybe a distributed denial
of service attack so that I can
shut off my API and prevent the
security loss and the API versioning.
Managing multiple API versions
securely, especially when
older versions are deprecated.
Ensures the outdated versions don't
become security vulnerabilities.
What does it mean?
The API is over the period.
My business might be growing.
My customer's base is increasing.
So I may need to provide
the more features.
I may need to provide the more
functionality to the user to
have the best user experience.
So in that journey, I
might create more APIs.
When I create more APIs, my, my
surface attacks will be more,
my risk is going to increase.
So how do I make sure my APIs are
not vulnerable by having so many APIs
implementation in, in, in that journey?
So the API versioning is
crucial in that manner.
Say I have a feature one implemented
in V1 version of API one.
And I have feature two and feature three
implemented with the API version two.
So instead of having V1 and V2, and there
is a need of V3 again in the future.
So I deprecate my V1, I clubbed all my
feature, feature one, feature two, feature
three, and feature four in API version
three, and I have N minus one for support
to the customers and basically giving
them, giving our clients, consumers.
Some time frame to migrate to the V2
to V3 so that I always have n and n 1
in the, in basically a live API calls
provides, from, for the consumers.
So let's talk about the best
practices for API security.
So implementing OAuth2, TLS and
encryption, API gateway, regular audits.
So what does it mean?
OAuth2 is a token based authentication
protocol, enables secure access
by allowing users to authenticate
without exposing passwords.
So what does it mean?
So before I even hit any API, I hit
a token server, the token server,
the token management system gives a
token with a minimum, minimum expiry
time, say one minute or 30 seconds.
We can configure that according
to the organizational policy
or organizational, situations.
Then we can basically the token
management system provides two things.
One is.
generation of the tokens and
destroy the tokens once the
operation is completed by the user.
And the TLS encryption, the transport
layer security should be enforced for all
API traffic to protect data in transit
from interception or manipulation.
The TLS communication, a component
to component or system to system.
If there is no API or even API
involved, we can have the mutual TLS.
The one dot one dot three is the
latest but most of widely used
Dls encryption version is a one
dot two is most secure nowadays
Everyone is moving to one dot three.
It is more Enhanced version of security
and then api gateway the api gateway
provides A centralized way to provide
the policies or to enforce the policies
in between Whatever the apis or sys
services available under the api gateway.
So what does it do?
Basically, I have my api deployed in
any platform I don't need to expose the
endpoint url with where by looking at
the api endpoint url Backend service
url I can say is this deployed in aws?
Is this deployed in azure?
You is deployed in any other,
platform, or any cloud platform
or any, Pivotal cloud, platform.
without exposing the API endpoint
details, I can mask that endpoint
URL with the API gateway URL so
that it will be generic for them.
Internally, I configure
my backend service.
into the API gateway URL so that any
public user or any internet exposed
to service may not have where did
I deploy my service in the backend.
And then logging, rate limit, logging,
what data, what kind of data I'm
logging into the, any logging servers.
enterprise way.
So am I logging any sensitive data?
am I masking the data or how are we
maintaining the logging, the levels,
the info, warn, debug, errors?
how am I logging my data based on my
environments, based on my log levels?
The regular audits are nothing but
continuous monitoring and regular
security audits help identify and
resolve the vulnerabilities before
even they exploited by attackers.
Regular audits helps us to
even go further in the design.
Sometimes in the audits, we can even
think of the redesigning of any system
or within the ecosystem, any component.
Let's talk about the implementing.
security across API lifecycle,
the security by design.
So security by design means in
previous days, 10 years ago or five
years ago, the security is a part of
NFR, the non functional requirement.
But nowadays, shifting left to even
further at the design level, we think
of the security posture and we integrate
the security from the earliest stages of
development So that it ensures we build
any API which is secure and stable and,
basically we do not want to have that
afterthought after the development, we go
and see review or proactively we wanted
to move that shift left to the design
level so that we do not miss or we do
not expose our APIs after the development
code reviews and penetration testing.
Regular code reviews helps us to identify
the vulnerabilities even before by, by
having the penetration testing or scanning
like static scans or dynamic scans, or
even any manual audits or manual scans
by a security experts before even if we
deploy or even we basically move to the
higher environments within the ecosystem.
Any static code analysis on dynamic
testing in development and pre
production environments helps us
to reduce the security, to reduce
the security vulnerabilities.
DevSecOps collaboration.
Adopting a DevSecOps approach
integrates security into the
entire API development lifecycle.
By fostering collaboration between
development, security, operations
team, organizations can ensure the
continuous security improvements
throughout the lifecycle.
Thank you.
So how do we achieve the, how do we
achieve that through the CICD pipelines
in the CICD pipelines while building
the source code itself, I can integrate
so many things in the pipeline.
Say example, do I have any codes or
static codes or secrets or passwords
in, in the source code, in my code,
I can even have that through many
tools are available in the market.
I can even say, Is my dot class or
Java class or whatever the technology
you're using any of these classes
have the constants or secrets or
passwords exposing in the source code.
So that is one level we can even stop the
deployment to the development environment
or QA environment, even before we make it.
We build and jar it, make a jar
to available as a, as an API or
further products or third party
vendors or third party products.
So we can integrate the automation
test suits or security automation
test suits to see the API endpoints,
the implementation of the tokens.
How are the tokens, configurations
happened at the API properties level.
The configuration reading and the
integration testing or any testing
suits, we can run it and then move
to the further, higher environment.
Then finally, into production deployment
so that we can reduce the any vulnerable
or any threats happening at the core
level by CACD automation integration
or scans, we can avoid those.
The post deployment monitoring is
very important even after deployment.
API security requires constant
vigilance, like putting alerts
or notifications or warnings.
what is the threshold or what is the
throughput we have at the API level?
Implement real time monitoring
tools to detect suspicious activity.
Anomaly detection, we can have this so
many, we have so many tools available
to see the anomaly or bot detections.
like any potential threats before
they cause significant damage.
Let's talk about the tools and
technologies api security testing tools so
The wasp job can identify vulnerabilities
while fuzzers test the robots robustness
of api endpoints how are we going to
test I can even integrate any of the
test scanners Like like gitlab provides
a gitlab duo or we can actually put into
our source code itself You We have the
security management report, security
tools, or how are we maintaining the,
dependency managements, what are the
versions we are, what are the, patches,
available, or versions available.
So we can have those by integrating
these security testing tools so
that we will not be vulnerable.
Our code is not vulnerable
to the bad actors.
Web application firewalls tools
like AWS or Azure also provides.
The WAF protect APIs from SQL injections
cross site scripting on and many other
attacks the API management platforms
solutions like API gateway products like
Google has many API gateway or AWS Have
or new soft or congo So these kind of
API management platforms provide the
centralized security controls and we
can even enforce the So we can enforce
the common policies in consistent manner
within the ecosystem in the organization.
We can enforce these policies
like rate limit or streaming.
How are we streaming any of the
bigger data like in any, any order
management where I have 20 MB more
than 20 MB through the API gateway.
I can stream that by having a
few security policies enforced.
Threat intelligence platforms,
the real time threat intelligence
platforms help detect and block threats
specific to API vulnerabilities.
Let us touch upon the case study one,
the successful implementation, how
a large financial services company
implemented by using the OAuth2, the
authentication API gateway by, by doing
these security controls, having the
TLS and also continuous monitoring,
whatever we discussed earlier.
They resulted over two years,
the measures resulted 70 percent
reduction in API related security
incidents, significantly improving the
company's overall security posture.
The case study two does what are the
lessons we learned from a breach?
There is a API breach in
social media platform recently
on unsecured API endpoint.
So this is where it is very important
to have the API Security from
defining the API endpoint, where am I
configured in API gateway, how my API
is retrieving the data from the data
store and to whom I'm giving, are they
authorized, are they authenticated
before we give the data, is this data
belong to the same user requested,
we need to verify that before we even
pass, we even share over the network.
Lessons learned, the breach
highlighted several key issues, the
importance of strong authentication
and authorization mechanisms, such as
OAuth2 and prevent unauthorized access.
The need for regular security
audits and API endpoint reviews to
identify exposed or weakened points.
Implementing rate limiting and IP
filtering could have reduced the
scale of breach by limiting the number
of requests from ambitious actors.
The future trends in API security.
We can make use of the AI and ML.
The artificial intelligence and
machine learning can be used to
detect anomalies in real time and
predict potential vulnerabilities.
And even further, there are so many
elements available in the market.
Any cloud platform exposes an AI.
we can basically send our
source code in a string format.
Hey, give me the we can prompt the
llms Give me the security analysis
of this api As is this api Has
any potential vulnerabilities?
give us this give us the risk analysis
of authentication and authorization is my
tokens properly implemented in this class.
So I can even get the report, a
security analysis report by prompting
the LLMs having, is there any code
is vulnerable for the bad actors?
I can even say that.
So zero trust architecture, the quantum
computing, zero trust architecture.
what is zero trust architecture?
So if I have a three tier
architecture in my company.
I have a front line, I have a API
gateway, I have a backend service, and
then data store or any data centers.
So any requests come from the front
lines, any user logged into any website
or company's website, authenticating,
authorizing through the API gateway and
hitting the API, APIs behind backend
services like API 1 is calling API
2 and API 3, and maybe my API 3 is
calling multiple third party services.
Get the data, pull the data or
manipulated, massage the data to give
the response back to the API one,
which serves the frontline web page.
So in this case, layer to layer
security is very important.
How am I protecting each layer
by implementing the tokens or by
having any public private key pair?
How am I doing the token, am I doing
the tokens with my signature with the
private key so that the other system
can validate my tokens or, can see
my signature with the public key?
And then allow the request to
serve me or to serve my API request
or so API 1 to API 2 to API 3.
If I protect that I'm narrowing down
my risk by implementing the zero trust
architecture within this ecosystem.
So how do I do that?
Any bad actor comes into the network.
even if the bad actor comes to the
network, we are minimizing the risk by
having layer to layer security, layer
to layer implementation of the tokens.
The API composition security.
As APIs are chained together in
complex systems, securing these
composite APIs will be crucial.
The conclusion.
In conclusion, API security is more
than just a technical requirement.
It is a critical business imperative
that ensures the integrity,
confidentiality, and availability of
data systems powering modern enterprises.
So these case studies, whatever we
discussed so far must prioritize
within the organization to achieve
the highest level of security
at every stage of API lifecycle.
Look at to the future, staying ahead
of emerging threats like quantum
computing, using the AI technologies
or several API security testing tools.
And AI into security strategies will
be essential for maintaining secure
and scalable API infrastructures.
The balance between innovation
and security is key to driving
long term business growth.
With this, I hope you enjoyed my talk.
you listened to some of my guidelines,
make use of it in your organization.
Thank you so much for joining me.
And enjoy the rest of the
talks in CONF42 in this season.
Thank you so much.