Hello, my name is Victor
really lovely to meet you guys.
today I'll be speaking on a topic
called react and respond How to enhance
incident management with cyber awareness.
It's really important for
you to understand that cyber
awareness plays a crucial role
enhancing incident management.
Whether you're talking about incident
management for a small incident
or for a very large incident.
How cyber aware your employees or
your teammates or your colleagues are.
Plays a very big role as regards how
you are able to like bounce back and,
move on with your business continuity
plan in the case of an incident.
So looking at, this in
depth today quickly.
First of all, it's important for us to
understand that the cyber threat landscape
keeps increasing, and the tactics being
used by cyber criminals keep evolving.
They're on the, with the advent
of AI, generative AI, there's the
attack surface keeps increasing.
And of course, There's a target variety
in the sense that different, there are so
many, soft targets, so many people that
could be targeted from small businesses
to hospitals and, manufacturing,
any organization could be a target.
So hence the need to be cyber
aware, there's also financial
impact if an organization falls
victim to a cyber security attack.
Obviously it will cause downtime.
And if it's, for instance, if it's
a ransomware attack, it could also
have some financial impact where the
malicious attacker could ask for some
money before they actually give that
organization access to their data.
And sometimes even after paying
some organizations are not still
sure of getting their data.
So the cyber threat landscape
is really, evolving every day.
There's also the issue of data privacy,
with the cyber security attack, the
data you have, your sensitive data.
is compromised and data
privacy is also compromised.
So it's very important for us
to, have a cyber aware culture.
very important.
So what is important cyber awareness
for incident response, early detection.
If you have employees who are
cyber aware, they'll be more
likely to be more eagle eyed.
They'll be more likely to spot
inconsistencies, which could
actually lead to a cyber attack.
Okay.
They'll be able to spot
suspicious activities.
For instance, if you've trained your
staffs on how to identify a phishing
email, it'll be easy for them to,
identify, Efficient email some day
and let you know that okay, we're
receiving efficient email from this
particular email and stuff like
that You can actually mitigate it.
So with Cyber awareness you are
able to effectively mitigate
cyber attacks In your environment.
Also, there's also going
to be reduced risk.
because remember that we are not just
talking about technical measures because
most companies invest so much in their
technical security, spend billions of
pounds in their technical security, but
they don't do enough to make sure that
their staffs are cyber aware, right?
because your staffs are
your human firewall.
So you want to make sure that your staffs
are well trained and they are cyber aware
to understand the threats that cyber.
that malicious actor
posed to your business.
when we talk about cyber security
awareness, what comes to mind will
be employee training and continuous
education is very important for you
as part of the induction for your
staffs to give them a very good
and robust cyber security training.
Okay.
Let them have a good understanding
of common cyber security threats and
cyber security best practices, and
let them have an understanding of
the instance response procedures.
If you would fall to an attack.
Also, you also need to encourage your
staff to update your system regularly
because and open the softwares you use
because, with updates, the vendors of
those software are able to get patches
wherever these softwares are vulnerable.
The vendors are able to like those
patches with the updates, you
will get a security patch for the
software and practical exercise.
Part of your Employee training should
also involve maybe gamifying your
trainings in a way that you could
simulate real world scenarios and to
make it to be more interesting to your
employees who are participating in
this training so that they can actually
get a hands on experience as regards.
Okay.
What's the entails when there's
a cyber crime, what do I do?
What do I not do?
Okay.
It's also important that when you run
this training, you want to get feedback,
maybe survey, you want to observe, and.
Axios, trainees, what worked,
what didn't work, so that you can
actually keep improving it because,
cybersecurity awareness training
is not something that is not just
something you just do in a rigid manner.
You have to be flexible.
You have to keep changing.
You have to keep making it
better based on feedback.
So it's very good.
practice to always get feedback after
a cyber security awareness training,
then how do you also need to implement
a robust incident response plan so that
if you were to actually fall to a cyber
attack, you want to have players and
responsibilities, who's going to handle
what, who's going to call, the police.
Who's going to inform the ICO
that there's been a data breach?
Who's going to do what and all that?
who's going to speak to the, the press,
as regards the extent of the data breach,
do you have a legal team in place?
things like that.
So you want to have, you want to have, an
established procedure as regards how you
want to, handle your incident response.
And communication is really key,
for example, for you, especially
for your staff who may be working
remotely, if they find out that
they've been hacked or something, your.
Staffs are supposed to have a, a clear,
and a response, a rapid and responsive
communication channel through which they
can actually contact you as their manager
or maybe their CEO that, okay, this is
the, this is what we are going through.
We've been hacked and stuff like
that, so having a good communication
strategy can also help you in
terms of an incident management.
Then you obviously so many organizations
is already, utilizing, automation
and automation and AI tools for
fast detection endpoint security.
Basically, we have to this is like
the, the CrowdStrike Falcon go,
tools like that can be used cloud
solutions like the Falcon go.
Can be used by small businesses,
medium businesses, and, you can
use those solutions like AI driven
Sentinel one, carbon black, there's
so many solutions you can use for
trade detection and elimination.
Okay.
So you want to actually make use of those.
If you can actually afford it
and use those for Monitoring the
networks of your vulnerabilities
and keeping your system safe.
So it is very important to foster
a culture of cyber resilience.
When we talk about incident response
management, your staffs, your people
who work for you, your employees
have to be, have to need, have
needs to have security awareness.
They need to have security awareness.
And how do you do this?
You do this by communicating best
practices and also promoting.
A culture of openness where your employees
feel free to communicate with you, where
there's no barrier, they are willing to
be open with you to discuss with you.
There should also be a facilitation
of information sharing.
Each department, if there's an information
that could help one department, maybe the
accounting department should be able to
share information as regards cybersecurity
to the engineering department.
If they know that is going to help them.
Mitigate their cybersecurity challenges.
Like I said in the previous slide,
continuous learning is very important.
You should be conducting a
cybersecurity awareness training
regularly for your team.
you shouldn't just say, Oh, I'm going
to be doing this just once again.
You, the cyber attackers
are not really sleeping.
They are also innovating.
They are also improving.
So you want to also make sure that
your human firewalls, which are
your staffs, are also improving
in terms of their cyber awareness.
So continuous training is very important.
Okay.
So in conclusion and the key
takeaway, what you need to understand
is that cyber security awareness
is not just a one time thing.
It's an ongoing process as we
keep on discovering new and
new vulnerabilities every day.
Individuals need to also stay on top of
their game and keep, learning and keep
knowing, okay, these are the tricks,
these are the tips and tricks, I can
use to stay safe from cyber attacks.
And employee training and
continuous education, like I said
in this It is a non negotiable.
It is important to carry out
employee training regularly.
Also, you can also use,
endpoint security tools.
Like I spoke about Falcon.
I spoke about Sentinel 1 to protect
your technical, in terms of your
technical security, so that you
can protect your attack surface.
And you also need to foster
an atmosphere of openness.
Within your staff so that they can
always talk to you and open up to you.
If they feel something isn't right,
they can always talk to you and you can,
mitigate that challenge immediately.
with that, you don't be
proactively to handle, incidents.
So I thank you for listening to me and
thank you for listening to this talk.
I hope you actually enjoy this and I hope
you actually learn something from it.
Cyber security remains
everybody's business.
It's not just the cyber
security analyst business.
It is your own business too.
So you need to be cyber safe.
Thank you very much.