Hello everyone myself, Ika Ram.
Welcome everyone.
So today I will be walking you through
how AI and machine learning are changing
instant management in the cloud.
For over the years we have been stuck in
the reactor mode waiting for outages to
happen and then scrambling to fix them.
What I'll show you today is how
distributed AI architecture,
observability, and automation
pipeline can change that.
Focus in both strategic why and also
why this matters and the technical
and also how to build into your stack.
So next slide would be
today's agenda here.
How we will structure the session first.
We will look at how instant management
has evolved over, over the time.
Then we'll break down the core AI and
ML capabilities that driven modern
systems like things like an detection.
Root cause analysis and
auto autonomous redemptions.
Next next I'll walk you through
distributor AI architectures
where telemetry models and
automation pipeline come together.
So finally, we will wrap up with
the real world case studies with
key metrics and step by step roadmap
so you can use for implementation.
So next slide would be.
The high stakes of modern
incident management.
The stakes today are higher than ever.
In cloud environment downtown downtime
can cascade through dozens of services
and cost millions of dollar per hour.
Incidents are still caused by
human error and alert feature tube.
So where engineer get so many false
alarm that critical signal get lost.
The complexity of distributed
microservices only multiplies the problem.
The truth is manual approach
doesn't scale anymore.
So we need intelligence
system that can shift.
Through nausea, identify through
issues and guide engineers towards
the right action as a faster,
okay next slide would be the
evolution react to pro two.
So let's break down this evolution, like
in past instant management was reactive.
The Sure based.
Monitoring would trigger alarm when
metrics like CPR memory crossed
a limit and human had to dig
through, log to diagnose the issue.
Over the time we moved to more responsive
system like correlation engines automated
runbooks and structured post model.
But the real leap forward
is predictive ance.
So where a model forecast alarm
alarms before they turn into outages.
Coming to the LSTM networks and
time series forecasting can predict
failures, like casual interference
can pinpoint the dependencies and
refor reformance learning agents
can handle redemption automatically.
The shift is from reacting after
the fact to preventing issues
before they impact the users.
So next would be, yeah.
Next would be the, oh my bad.
Embarrassing.
A new era.
So this new era of intelligent
incident management changes the entire
life cycle, like metrics, logs, and
traces are streamed in real time.
Into a unified observability platform,
whereas in machine learning models
continuously analyze that data
form an patterns and correlations.
Instead of waiting for a human to review
dashboard, the system can detect the
issue and map the root cause, and in many
ca cases, apply the fixed automatically.
What this means in
practice is less downtime.
Lower co operational cost and
higher customer satisfaction.
Next slide would be core
AI or MI capabilities.
So these are four key AI
capabilities at play here.
The first is predictive validating,
whereas model trained on baseline so it
can detect early warnings signals long
before traditional threshold are breached.
The second would be is
automated Root Task Analysis.
So it's a craft-based model.
Look at service dependencies and
isolated with the fault originates.
Where coming to the third is an
autonomous redemptions where this
is reinforcement learning agents can
restart the services, reroute the
traffic or scale, cluster on their own.
And finally.
Intelligent escalation where incidents
are routed automatically to the
right engineer based on the expert
context and availability together.
So these capability reduce the noise and
cut detection and response times and.
Let human focus on the high value work.
Coming to the next slide where it
driven to the leading platform.
So there are the major cloud cover already
embedded this capability AWS SageMaker,
which integrates with the CloudWatch
so it can deploy and it detects model
and trigger the Lambda functions for.
Automated redemptions, whereas coming
to the Azure ml. Ml, so it ties
into the log analytics and log apps
where it detect can direct directly
trigger correct corrective actions.
But coming to the other cloud-based
vertex AI connects, which with
the cloud operations and cloud
functions for event driven responses.
While it's ML ops tooling keeps
model restrained on fresh telemetry.
So each provider is making AI operational
intelligence a first class service.
Coming to the next slide, like
distributed AI architecture here, how
the architecture looks in practice
Telemetry is a collector from across
your stack using open telemetry.
Friendly or native cloud agents, a unified
observability layer like elastic or
datadog which correlates metrics, logs,
and traces the a, these AI process layer.
Runs the ML model for
anomaly anomaly detection.
We are forecasting and root analysis
root cause analysis, typically
using a distributor framework like
Spark, ml or TensorFlow serving.
So in response to orchestration,
then connects to the ISTM tools
like ServiceNow or pay page duty
to trigger automated runbooks.
A feedback loop retrains models
continuously and secure data fabric
ensure governance and compliance.
This slide talks about it
and coming to the next slide,
that training intelligence.
So the effectiveness of these
systems comes down to the data.
You train them on telemetry streams,
provide metrics like latency throughout,
through output and saturation locks
can be praised with NVP techniques to
extract error codes and correlation id.
And coming to the torical incident
record like post-mortem cells as a why
training sets for root cause models.
But the most important
factor is data quality.
So model trained on noisy.
Inconsistent data will
produce false positive.
So observability pipeline must be
cleaned and normalized before training.
So coming to the next slide where it
talks about the real world impact.
So when origination adopt intelligent
incident manager management,
the numbers shift dramatically.
We consistently see 82 and
90% reductions in meantime to
detect and resolve incident.
False alerts drop significantly ly, which
reduces engineer burnout and attrition.
So auto redemption rates
climb as reinforcements.
Learning models get better
at handling repeated issues.
So let me give you one example
on the financial services side.
For example used the predictive models
to detect database saturation like
20 minutes before failure, so it
automatically scaled the cluster and
avoid a multimillion dollar outage.
So these are the kinds of outcome
that makes a business case clear.
Next slide would be the
implementation roadmap.
Whereas coming to this slide like adoption
work best in phases like first phase
is data readiness, like centralized
telemetrics, normalized logs and train
baseline anomaly detection model.
In phase two, we add augmentation
and automation where it is deployed.
AI driven alert, correlation, and run box.
So coming to the phase three we introduce
a proactive intelligence where it is a
graph driven based root cause analysis and
reinforcement learning for the redemption.
Finally the fourth phase which is focused
on the optimization predictive capacity
planning like it's maintaining and
expanding across region and the teams.
So each step builds a capability
while limiting its risk.
Whereas coming to the next slide, it
talks about the critical success factor
where technology is only after equation.
Success depends on high quality
data, pipeline, clean and label
for training, it requires a
cross-functional collaboration like.
Machine learner learning engineers,
SREs and domain expert working side
by side where it rollout should be
iterate, like start with one service,
do value, then scale and evolve.
AI should augment human, not replace them.
So exp expandability is key, like
engineer must trust AI recommendation
and or they won't adapt it.
The future.
Next slide would be the future
is intelligent relations.
The future is moving towards
adaptive self uhhe system.
ML agents will forecast failures,
autoscale infrastructure and rero traffic
before user ever notice a problem.
Engineer won't disappear.
They'll shift from firefighting to
higher level design and governance.
The organization that invest now
will defend the operational religions
standards for the next decade.
The question isn't if the DA
change is coming, it's whether
you can lead it or follow it.
That's the roadmap for, inte into
the instant management, so thank you.