Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining this session.
Today we are going to look at a challenge
that every contact center faces how to
stay resilient when incidents strike,
whether it's a sudden system outage, a
spike in call volume, or an unexpected
service disruption, these moments can
quickly spiral and damage customer trust.
Over the next few minutes, I'll
share how AI automation and modern
architectures can help us prepare
for those high pressure situations
and turn them into opportunities to
deliver consistent, reliable support.
My name is Ji Ku.
And I'm with Copart.
I'll walk you through how we can
design customer support architectures
that remain strong during pressure,
and how intelligent automation
and AI power decision making can
help us maintain excellence even
when critical incidents occur.
In the world of contact centers,
every single second matters
when a system goes down.
Or when demand suddenly surges, the
disruption doesn't stay in one place.
It cascades through the
entire customer experience.
For example, if a CRM system is
unavailable, agents can't access
order history or customer details.
That leads to repeated questions longer
hold times, and more dropped calls.
From the customer's perspective,
this feels like a lack of
empathy, a lack of care, and it
often spills onto social media.
The end result is damage,
trust and higher churn.
The message is clear, incidents are
inevitable, but how we response determines
whether customers stay with us or leave.
To handle this challenge, the
foundation has to be cloud native.
Support architecture.
This begins with microservices, which
isolate falls so that one failure
doesn't bring the whole system down.
It also means using even driven
processing, which enables real time
responsiveness to unexpected changes.
And finally, auto-scaling infrastructure
ensures that when traffic spikes, the
system can adjust resources dynamically
without sacrificing performance.
This foundation is about resilience
by design, not resilience by chance.
On top of this foundation, we
bring in ai, one of the first areas
in AI powered intent detection.
This technology uses natural language
processing and historical data to
understand what a customer is asking
from the very first interaction.
During incidents, accurate
routing is essential.
If calls are being misdirected or
misclassified, it only adds friction.
AI ensures that resources are
allocated efficiently, even
when the systems are under
multi intent and emotional intelligence.
Of course, customer
conversations are layer simple.
Many times a customer has more than
one intent in the same interaction.
Modern AI can detect both
primary and secondary objectives,
while also recognizing the
emotional state of the customer.
For instance, if someone says, I can't
log in and I'm really frustrated, the
system doesn't recognize a login issue.
It also recognizes the urgency
and the need for empathy.
This allows us to prioritize the
interaction correctly and provide
the right support in the right way.
Another major pillar in autonomous
issue resolution is conversational ai.
Conversational AI handles routine
inquiries such as account updates,
password resets, or basic troubleshooting.
By taking care of these requests
automatically, we create reserve capacity
for human agents who are then free to
handle more complex and emotionally
charged issues during an incident.
This reserve capacity can make the
difference between chaos and control.
Not all issues are equal in risk.
AI helps by applying a
risk-based escalation framework.
Algorithms, analyze patterns, account
histories and behaviors to flag
potential fraud or security concerns.
Each case is scored and the
score determines priority.
High risk situations are
escalated immediately.
While routine matters can
follow the standard workflow.
This dynamic prioritization
ensures that tedious threats
are never lost in the shuffle.
Another way AI helps is through
AI driven decision trees.
Unlike static flowcharts,
these trees adapt in real time.
They learn from the past resolutions
and adjust path automatically.
For example, if one system is degraded
during an incident, the decision
tree can automatically reroute
customers to an alternative solution.
This flexibility makes the
entire resolution process more
resilient and far more efficient.
Of course, some cases still require
a human agent, but a handoff
should never mean starting over.
Dynamic handoff systems ensure that
customer's context travels with them.
This includes the interaction,
history, intent, and emotional state.
The agent receives a briefing so they
can pick up immediately without asking
the customer to repeat everything.
This continuity becomes critical
during outages where patients
is already stretched thin.
AI doesn't just serve customers.
It also augments agents
with real time assistance.
Agents can see suggested responses,
compliance guidance, and relevant
knowledge articles right in front of them.
AI monitoring ensures that
regulatory requirements are
consistently met even under stress.
Speech analytics can even flag
potential compliance violations
in real time, allowing corrections
before they become costly mistakes.
Now, the best incident is
the one that never happens.
Predictive analytics provides
an early warning system.
Machine learning models analyze
historical patterns, system
metrics, and even external factors
to anticipate potential problems.
For example, if there's a certain
increase in support tickets for password
resets, the system can flag it as
an early sign of a broader outage.
This allows proactive communication with
customers, often solving issues even
before they ever become full incidents.
Customer support is no longer
limited to voice or text.
Multimodal AI enables
support through voice.
Text, images, and even video.
A customer can share a photo of an error
message or a video of a malfunction,
and AI can interpret it immediately.
This dramatically reduces resolution
time and during incidents.
Clarity and speed are exactly
what customers expect.
Technology resilience is critical.
We achieve this through a few mechanisms.
Circuit breakers.
Isolate degraded components
so failures don't cascade.
Intelligent load distribution balances.
Workloads across available resources in
real time and redundant systems ensure
that even if a primary system goes
down, there are still alternative parts
available to keep operations running.
To bring all this together, we use a
four phase implementation approach.
Phase one.
It is establishing a
cloud native foundation.
Phase two is integrating AI for
intent recognition and routing.
Phase three is enhancing automation
with predictive analytics
and multimodal processing.
Phase four is resilience optimization,
fine tuning, load balancing, failover, and
incident response procedures All together.
Think of this as a roadmap
rather than a one-time project.
The future of incident ready contact
centers is about convergence.
When intelligent automation, predictive
analytics, and human expertise come
together, we achieve resilience at scale.
It's not about eliminating
incidents that's impossible.
It's about being ready so that when
an incident happens, the customer
still experience excellence.
Thank you all for taking the
time to join this session.
I hope you've taken away some clear
ideas about how AI and automation
can transform the resilience of
your customer support operations.
By building incident ready systems
today, we can ensure that customer
trust is preserved tomorrow.
Thank you and have a good day.