Hi, everyone.
This is Mahesh Tautam and
welcome to conference incident
management 2024 conference.
I am here to discuss on
Azure cloud migration.
As we know, a lot of organizations are
moving from legacy on premises to a cloud.
So I want to discuss strategies, the
stack process, and the performance of your
meditation in your practice and I know
it's very emotional for a lot of people.
I came up with a lot of talk about, I
start on my, strategies, comparison of the
strategies and how could we successfully
migrate our, structures and then.
best practices and how to mitigate
them, performance optimization, and
then a case study with conclusion.
So starting with introduction.
So the rapid evolution of cloud computing
has transformed the way enterprise
manage their IT infrastructure with
Microsoft Azure emerging as one of the
leading platforms for cloud adoption.
Businesses across the
globe are increasingly.
Turning to the cloud to unlock benefits
like enhancing the scalability, cost
efficiency, and operational agility.
By migrating to Azure, organization
can reduce their reliance on
traditional on premises data centers
and capitalize on the flexibility
that cloud solution offers.
Despite many advantages of cloud
migration, the process can be complex,
And we could fought with challenges.
A recent Flexure report indicates that by
end of 2024, 83 percent of the enterprise
wire loads will be hosted in the cloud.
Yet many organization faces
difficulties during migration.
These challenges often include.
unexpected costs, performance degradation,
and technical incompatibilities between
legacy system and cloud platforms.
Addressing these obstacles require
thorough planning, a deep understanding
of migration strategies, and continuous
performance optimization post migration.
I want to bring this, and talk about,
Azure cloud migration strategies.
So what are the strategies we do have?
we have re hosting, refactoring, re
architecting, rebuilding and replacing.
So each of them, I choose depending
upon how the organization uses the data
and how they build their infrastructure
and architecture of the data.
So first one, rehosting.
So it's probably a left hand shift.
We move all the application
with minimum changes.
It's a quick, low risk approach that
help businesses exist their data centers.
And this would be mostly with the
small organizations with less data.
And for refactoring, it involves
slight modifications to applications
to make them cloud ready, improving
their performance while leveraging
cloud native services like Azure PaaS.
And re architecturing, so
significant rework on application.
This, might take much time than the
other two strategies, but, we have to go
through the process of re architecting
all the data structures and breaking
the monolithic into microservices for
better scalability and reliability.
Rebuilding, so we'll be developing
a new application from scratch.
Scratch using all the cloud native
services for full optimization
and performance replacing.
We will be substituting legacy apps
with SAS based solutions available on
Azure to reduce management overhead.
So coming to the comparison of
migration strategies, so migration
strategies, benefits and trade offs.
Each strategy has its pros and cons.
As everything, the right choice
depends on factors such as applications
complexity, business cruciality,
and organization cloud maturity.
Rehosting, it's faster approach, but
does not leverage full capability.
Cloud benefits because we are
just lifting and shifting it.
So we might be missing a lot
of pros that we get with cloud
migration or moving to cloud.
So we can't get all of
them in rehosting strategy.
Refactoring.
introduces cloud native features with
medium complexity and implementation time.
Re architecting, this is the
strategy where we start getting
to most of the cloud, advantages.
but require high time and effort because
we have to start it from architectural
stage Rebuilding it offers the greatest
clouding benefits, but again involves
significant resources and times Replacing
a suitable for non core business apps.
We are moving to sas can
be cost effective and fast.
So coming to the planning for a successful
migration, planning and assessment key to
success through planning and assessment
are essential for a smooth migration.
This includes understanding
workloads, aligning business goals and
setting clear migration priorities.
So planning and assessing then
design and Build prototype reverse
engineering migration testing and
release this would take time based
And we cannot, give a timeline for
all of this process because it's based
upon the organization and the data.
So for workload evolution, evaluation,
identify application dependencies, access,
criticality, and determine suitable
migration strategies for each workload.
Skill assessment, ensure your team
has the required cloud expertise,
identify the gaps and develop training
or consider bringing an expert
who is good in Azure technologies.
Cost analysis and ROI projection.
We need to evaluate current
infrastructure's cost, project Azure
cost and estimate ROI over time.
short and long term period.
This ensures proper budgeting
and stakeholder buy in to
see what would be the cost.
Coming to the best practices
for Azure migration, best
practices for a smooth migration.
there is no term called smooth migration.
We would be facing issues while
doing this, but we can mitigate them.
So if we followed.
These steps we could, try to mitigate
most of the issues that we come up
while doing the migration so that
those would be reducing migration
risk and ensure optimal outcomes.
One is phased migration.
So we won't do everything in one go.
So implementing a gradual approach,
migrating workloads in phases.
test and validate each stage
before proceeding to reduce
risk and limit disruptions.
Security and compliance conducted
thorough security assessment of both
on premises and cloud environments.
Use Azure Security Center to monitor and
ensure compliance with industry standards.
Then comes data integrity,
audit and validate data before,
during, and after migration.
Tools like Azure Data Box help with this.