Hello, everyone.
I'm Ram, a principal systems developer
with over 10 years of experience
in building health care products,
particularly in kidney care.
Thank you for joining me today.
I'm excited to explore artificial
intelligence in incident management for
dialysis health care, optimizing the
response and reducing the system failures.
of the dialysis health care landscape.
The prevalence.
Dialysis is a critical treatment
for millions of individuals
suffering from kidney failure.
A condition that is becoming
increasingly common due to rising
rates of chronic diseases such
as diabetes and hypertension.
The World Health Organization
estimates that over 2 million
people globally are on dialysis.
A number that is expected to
grow as these underlying health
issues become more prevalent.
This trend emphasizes the urgent
need for the effective kidney
care and management strategies.
Coming to the types of dialysis, there
are two primary types of dialysis.
The first one being hemodialysis.
This method involves filtering the
blood through a machine called dialyzer.
which acts as an, artificial kidney.
Blood is drawn from the body,
cleaned, and then returned.
Hemodialysis typically occurs in
a clinical setting, which, with
sessions lasting about three to
five hours, several times a week.
The second one, the peritoneal dialysis.
In this method, the, the abdominal
line, lining, also known, known as
peritoneum, is used as a neural filter.
A dialysis solution is introduced
into the abdominal cavity, where
it absorbs waste products from
the blood through the peritoneum.
This type can be done at home and offers
greater flexibility in terms of schedule.
The settings, the dialysis can
be performed in various settings.
some of them could be hospitals, often the
primary location for patients requiring
the acute care or those starting dialysis.
Dedicated dialysis centers,
specialized facilities that offer a
range of dialysis services typically
staffed by trained professionals.
at the home.
An increasing number of patients
are opting for the home dialysis,
which allows for more independence
and can improve the quality of life.
Home dialysis options, especially
peritoneal dialysis, enable
patients to manage their treatment
in a familiar environment.
Coming to the cost, the financial burden
of the dialysis can be significant.
Treatment can be costly with
expenses related to equipment,
supplies, and healthcare personnel.
Many patients rely on
government healthcare programs
such as Medicare in the U.
S.
or private instances to cover these costs.
However, the financial implications can
still be overwhelming, particularly for
those without the adequate coverage.
The importance of effective
incident management in patient care.
These would cover the patient safety.
Effective incident management
is crucial for maintaining
patient safety in dialysis care.
Rapidly identifying and addressing
errors or near misses helps to
prevent harm for the patients.
For example, timely interventions can
prevent complications related to dialysis
exercises or machine malfunctions.
Ensuring that patients receive
safe and effective treatment.
Quality Improvement.
Analyzing incidents that occur
during dialysis treatments is
vital for identifying systematic
issues within healthcare practices.
By examining these incidents,
healthcare providers can implement
strategies to improve process, enhance
training for staff, and establish
protocols that manage and minimize
the risk of future occurrences.
This focus on continuous improvement
ultimately leads to better
patient outcomes and increased
trust in the healthcare services.
Moving to the risk mitigation, proper
incident management not only enhances
patient safety but also reduces liability
and potential legal consequences.
For health care providers, by having
robust procedures in place for reporting
and managing incidents, facilities can
demonstrate their commitment to quality
care, which may help in mitigating the
risks associated with the malpractice
of claims or regulatory scrutiny.
Effective risk management fosters a
culture of safety and accountability,
benefiting both patients and
the health care professionals.
Understanding the incident management.
Incident management in healthcare is a
critical process designed to enhance the
patient's safety and the care quality.
It involves a systematic approach to
identifying, reporting, analyzing,
and responding to the adverse events.
The near misses are unexpected
occurrences that can impact
patients or the healthcare system.
By establishing a robust
incident management framework,
healthcare organizations can
improve outcomes, minimize risk,
and foster a culture of safety.
Coming on to the incident management
process itself, the incident
management process typically
includes several key steps.
Some of them could be the detection
and reporting of the incidents.
Talking about the detection, the
first step involves recognizing
when an incident occurs.
Or is it about to occur?
This can be achieved through
monitoring systems, the staff
observations, or patient feedback.
And then the reporting.
Once detected, incidents should be
primarily said to be promptly reported.
Many organizations utilize standardized
reporting systems or electronic
tools that allow staff to document
incidents easily and confidentially.
Encouraging a culture of transparency and
non productive, non punitive reporting is
essential to capture all relevant events.
The initial assessment and prioritization.
After an assessment is reported, it
undergoes an initial assessment to
determine its severity and impact
on patient safety and care quality.
These steps involved classifying incidents
based on their potential or actual
consequences, enabling prioritization
Investigating the root cause analysis.
A thorough investigation follows,
involving a detailed examination
of the incident to gather facts
and understand what happened.
This may include reviewing the
patient records, interviewing
staff, and analyzing the workflows.
Coming to the actual root cause analysis,
the investigation aims to identify
the underlying the underlying causes
of incident incident rather than just
addressing the surface level issues.
RCA techniques such as the five wives
or the fishbone diagram help teams to
uncover systematic factors contributing
to the event, enabling them to tackle
root cause, root causes effectively.
The implementation of corrective actions.
Based on findings from the investigation,
corrective actions are developed and
implemented to prevent recurrence.
These actions might include the
policy changes, staff training,
process redesign, or enhancements
to equipment or technology.
The goal is to create
sustainable environment in
practices and the protocols.
Monitoring and the evaluation of outcomes.
After corrective actions are
implemented, it's crucial to monitor
their effectiveness over time.
This involves the tracking of
outcomes and analyzing whether
the changes have resulted in a
reduction in similar incidents.
Ongoing evaluation ensures that the
improvements are embedded within
the organization and that any new
issues are promptly addressed.
Sharing of lessons learned.
One of the most important aspects of
incident management is the dissemination
of lessons learned from each incident.
Sharing insights across the
teams and departments fosters a
culture of continuous learning.
This can be accomplished through regular
meetings, training sessions, Newsletters,
ensuring that all staff members are
aware of findings and best practices.
The key components of incident management.
So the incident management process can
be broken into four key components.
That are the detection, reporting,
and response, and then the recovery
from what we discussed above.
The current challenges
in dialysis healthcare.
The dialysis healthcare landscape
faces several pressing challenges
that impact the patient safety, care
quality, and operational efficiency.
Among these, high patient volumes
and increasing complexity of cases
are particularly significant.
So discussing the high patient
volumes and complexity in detail,
the overcrowding, overcrowding.
So in many healthcare settings,
especially hospitals and emergency
departments, there is often an influx
of patients requiring dialysis.
This can lead to overcrowding where
facilities struggle to accommodate the
number of patients needing treatment.
Also the long, long time waits.
Overcrowding typically results in
an extended wait times for patients,
delay in treatment the existing health
issues leading to worse outcomes and
increased patient dissatisfaction.
Patients may experience anxiety and
frustration due to uncertainty over
their, over their care timelines.
Increasing complexity of cases.
Many patients undergoing dialysis
have multiple comorbid conditions,
such as diabetes, cardiovascular
disease, and other chronic illness.
This complexity requires
tailored treatment plans.
and close monitoring, straining
resources, and increasing the
likelihood of complications.
The varying needs.
Each patient situation is unique,
necessitating individualized care.
Healthcare providers must navigate
varying medical histories, medication
interactions, and lifestyle factors,
which can complicate the delivery
of consistent and effective care.
The frequent equipment failure
and patient complications.
Critical devices used in the dialysis,
such as the dialysis machines, infusion
pumps, and monitoring equipment
may be more prone to malfunction
in busy healthcare environments.
Increased usage can lead to
wear and tear, making equipment
reliability a crucial concern.
So the heavy demand placed on the
dialysis equipment can disrupt
regular maintenance schedules.
When maintenance is deferred or
inadequately performed due to high
patient volumes, the likelihood
of equipment breakdowns increases,
potentially compromising the patient care.
This could also lead to the patient
complications and increased incidences.
For example, high patient volumes can
lead to more frequent complications
such as infections, vascular access
issues, and electrolyte imbalances.
These complications may arise from rushed
procedures or insufficient monitoring
due to staff being stretched thin.
The interplay of the over covering,
equipment failures, and the complexity
of patient cases creates an environment
where patient safety is jeopardized.
Increased errors, overlooked details, and
the delayed responses can significantly
affect the care quality and outcomes.
Coming on to the impacts of the
patient safety and care quality, the
challenges stemming from high patient
volumes, equipment issues, and complex
cases have profound implications
for patient safety and care quality.
Some of them could be the diminished care
quality, increased risk of adverse event,
staff burnout, and the patient experience.
With this setting, let's talk
about the role of artificial
intelligence in the AI healthcare.
First, the definition of AI and
its relevance in healthcare.
The artificial intelligence, as we know,
is defined as the development of computer
systems capable of performing tasks that
typically require human intelligence.
This includes abilities such as visual
perception, speech recognition, decision
making, and language translation.
In the context of healthcare,
AI is increasingly recognized
as a transformative tool that
enhances the patient care.
Improves the diagnostic accuracy,
streamlines the operational process,
and advances the medical research.
By leveraging AI technologies, healthcare
providers can make more informed
decisions, reduce errors, and optimize
the resource utilization, ultimately
leading to better patient outcomes.
Moving on to the overview of
AI technologies and healthcare.
AI encompassed encompasses various
technologies each contributing
uniquely to the healthcare landscape.
One of them is, the machine learning where
a subset of AI machine learning, which is,
which is a subset of AI machine learning,
involves algorithms that enable computers
to learn from the ma, the make, learn
from, and make, the predictions based
on data without explicit programming.
Coming to the applications in healthcare,
the machine language, machine learning
can be used for predictive analytics,
identifying the patterns in patient
data to foresee potential health risks.
And the other term could be the deep
learning, where a more advanced form
of learning, deep learning, utilizes
neural networks with many layers
to analyze vast amounts of data.
And then the natural language processing.
The natural language processing is a
branch of AI that focuses on interaction
between computers and the human language.
enabling machines to understand,
interpret, and generate human language.
The computer vision.
The computer vision enables machines to
interpret and process visual information
from the world, similar to how humans
perceive and understand images.
And the last one is the data analytics.
Data analytics involves the
systematic computational analysis
of data to under, to uncover the
patterns, trends, and the insights.
AI
healthcare and overview.
So AI is revolutionizing the
healthcare by providing innovative
solutions across the various fields.
And let's look at the details on how
the current applications of AI is
helping in several key healthcare areas.
One of them is the radiology
and medical imaging.
AI algorithms, particularly those using
the deep learning, are being employed
to analyze the medical images such
as x rays, MRIs, and the CT scans.
These algorithms can identify
abnormalities such as tumors,
fractures, or other pathologies with
high accuracy, often comparable to the
exceeding set of human radiologists.
Prioritization of the urgent cases.
AI can enhance radiology workflows
by prioritizing the urgent cases.
Algorithms can flag the images that
require immediate attention based on the
specific criteria, allowing radiologists
to focus on the high risk patients first.
3D AI technologies that are capable of
reconstructing the 3D images from 2D
scans, enabling healthcare providers
to visualize complex anatomical
structures in three dimensions.
Moving on to the oncology, it helps in the
personalized treatment planning, cancer
detection and pathology slides, and also
prediction of the treatment outcomes.
Also in the cardiology, it helps in
the ECG analysis, predictive models
for the cardiovascular risk assessment,
and the AI assisted echocardiogram
let's talk about the AI applications
in the incident management.
AI is playing a pivotal role in enhancing
the incident management within the
healthcare settings by leveraging
advanced technologies, healthcare
organizations can improve patient safety,
streamlining operations and respond
more effectively to adverse events.
Here is an in depth look at three key
applications of AI in incident management.
Which are the predictive analytics,
the real time monitoring,
and the automated reporting.
Predictive analytics.
Predictive analytics in healthcare
involves the usage of historical
data, the statistical algorithms, and
machine learning techniques to forecast
potential incidents before they occur.
By analyzing the patterns from past
incidents, healthcare providers can
identify risk factors and trends that
may lead to future adverse events.
The benefits could be the proactive
safety measures by anticipating
the potential incidents.
Healthcare organizations can
implement preventive measures.
Then the resource optimization.
Predictive analytics can help
allocate resources more effectively by
identifying the times or departments.
at higher risk for incidents and then it
helps in the improved patient outcomes.
Anticipating incidents enable healthcare
providers to intervene early, reducing
the likelihood of complications and
enhancing overall patient safety.
Moving on to the real time
monitoring, it involves the continuous
collection and analysis of data
from patients and medical equipment.
This can include vital signs,
the lab results, and operational
status of medical devices.
AI algorithms analyze this data
to detect issues as they emerge.
The benefits could include
the immediate issue detection,
enhanced equipment performance,
and the data driven decisions.
And the last one, the automated reporting.
The systems leverage AI to
streamline the communication of
critical information during the
incidents in automated reporting.
These systems ensure that
relevant data reaches appropriate
stakeholders quickly and effectively.
The benefits could include the rapid
information decimation, standardization of
the reports, and enhanced collaboration.
let's dive deep into the
predictive analytics.
Predictive analytics is transforming
healthcare by leveraging data to forecast
future events or outcomes, enabling
proactive interventions and making, and
helping the, making informed decisions.
So through the use of statistical
techniques and machine learning,
predictive algorithms can analyze
historical and current data
to provide valuable insights.
Here is a detailed overview of
how these algorithms work and some
common applications in healthcare.
So some of the features could be the
data collection, the feature selection,
model training, model validation.
let's talk about some of the examples of
the predictive models used in healthcare,
which are readmission, risk prediction,
or the sepsis prediction, chronic disease
progression, medical adherence, and
the emergency department utilizations.
on to the real time monitoring
technologies in dialysis.
The integration of sensors and the
IOT, Internet of Things, devices in
dialysis has transformed the management
and delivery of this critical treatment
for patients with kidney failure.
These technologies not only enhance
the efficacy of dialysis, but also
improve patient safety and optimize
the overall treatment process.
Here is a detailed overview of three
key real time monitoring technologies
in dialysis, which are the overview
of sensors and IOT, IOT devices.
in dialysis, which helps in,
the fluid balance sensors,
bioimpedance sensors, or clinical
applications, or the weight sensors.
And then the next one could be the
dialysate, dialysate composite,
composition sensors, which helps
in, the conductivity sensors
for the clinical applications.
We could also monitor the pH and then also
the temporary or the temperature sensors.
Some of the benefits of continuous
monitoring for patient safety could
include the early detection of the
complications, which is possible by
continuously monitoring, continuous
monitoring enabled by the sensors that
allow for immediate identification
of potential complications.
And then, we could also detect the rapid
fluid shifts and the blood pressure
changes and also the electrolyte balances,
which helps in the proactive intervention.
The ability to monitor patients in real
time allows healthcare teams to intervene
proactively before complications escalate.
Early identification of issues enable
timely adjustments to treatment
plans, medication administration,
and the other interventions.
So let's.
To look at a case study for, the
predictive analytics and, action.
So let's take the example
of, the SmartCare Dialysis
Center in, AI implementation.
So let's take, SmartCare Center is
a SmartCare Dialysis Center, is a
medium sized facility equipped with 30
dialysis measures, providing efficient
treatment for approximately 120 patient.
The center faced significant
challenges due to recurring equipment
failures, which not only disrupted the
treatment schedules, but also posed
potential safety risks for patients.
To mitigate these issues, the center
decided to implement an AI powered
predictive maintenance system
aimed at enhancing the operational
efficiency and ensuring patient safety.
So here, the AI implementation could
help in the data collection, predictive
analytics model development, development
and real time, sorry, the deployment
and real time monitoring, And then from
all of this, whatever the results we
get and the benefits that could include
reduction in equipment failure, improved
treatment continuity, enhanced patient
safety and operational efficiency.
Automated incident reporting.
Automated incident reporting is a
transformative approach in healthcare
that leverages artificial intelligence
to streamline the documentation
process for adverse events, near
misses, and other clinical events.
This automation not only enhances
efficiency, but also improves
accuracy and compliance in reporting.
Here is a detailed look at how
AI can automate clinical incident
documentation through real time data
capture and intelligent form filling.
So some of them could be, the real time
data capture, which can be achieved
through continuous monitoring of the
medical devices, the patient vital
signs, and the environmental factors.
And then the automated data collection.
When an incident occurs, the AI
system automatically captures the
relevant data points at the exact
time of event, which could include
the time and date of the incident,
specific reading from the medical
devices, environmental conditions, etc.
With that, the benefits of real
time data capture could include
the immediate documentation.
where, where the, where it provides
the ability to capture the data at that
data at the moment and incident occur
ensures that, critical information is
not lost or forgotten, which improves
the readability of the reports.
And also it helps in the
comprehensive insight by collecting
the data from multiple resources.
The AI provides holistic
view of the incident, helping
to identify, contributing.
Factors and the trends.
It also helps in the reduction of
the reduced burden on the staff.
Automating the data collection process
alleviates the documentation workload
on healthcare professionals, allowing
them to focus on the patient care.
And then also we, the other key feature
could be the intelligent form filling,
where we are, we could take the advantage
of natural language processing, which
helps in the transcription of the voice
notes, The automatic for population of
the standardized forms and filling out
the required fields that are needed for
the treatment and the benefits of the
intelligent form filling could include
the enhanced accuracy and then the time
efficiency which saves a lot of time and
then the streamlined reporting process.
So basically automating, automated
reporting facilitates, quicker analysis
and review of the incidents, helping
the organizations to identify trends
and implement current, corrective
actions more, more effectively.
The benefits of AI in
Dialysis Incident Management.
The integration of AI in Dialysis,
Incident Management significantly enhances
patient safety, care quality, operational
efficiency, and resource allocation.
So here, let's explore, some of
the benefits focusing on early
detection and prevention as
well as optimized scheduling.
So enhanced patient safety
and care quality, which could
cover the early detection and
prevention through the continuous
monitoring and predictive alerts.
Let's take a look at the example.
In a personal, in a practical scenario,
an AI system detects subtle changes
in a patient's blood pressure trend.
During a dialysis session, it can
generate an alert for the healthcare team.
This proactive measure allows the staff
to intervene early, adjusting fluid
removal rates, or providing necessary
medication before a hypertensive
episode occurs, thereby preventing
complications and ensuring patient safety.
Moving on to the improved operational
efficiency and resource allocation.
It helps in optimizing scheduling based
on a dynamic schedule instead of a
static scheduling and resource matching.
We don't need to do a
manual resource matching.
AI could take take care of
doing that resource matching.
So that also helps.
So, for example, if you take an
instance, where a patient is known to
require longer treatment times due to
complications or unique medical needs, the
AI systems can dynamically schedule their
appointment to a less busy time slot.
This adjustment not only minimizes wait
times for all patients, but also improves
overall patient flow and satisfaction.
on to the implementation
considerations for AI in healthcare.
When integrating AI into healthcare
systems, particularly in sensitive
areas like dialysis management, several
critical considerations must be addressed.
Among these, data privacy and security
issues, as well as integration challenges
with existing systems are paramount.
Below is an elaboration on
these key considerations.
Some of them could be patient, like
as we talked, the data privacy and
security issues, which could cover the
patient data protection, where we need
to follow the, the HIPAA compliance.
And then, this could, include
implementing policies and procedures
that ensure the confidentiality,
integrity, and, the availability
of protected health information.
And then the data encryption, implementing
end to end, end to end encryption is
critical for predicting patient's data.
both in transit and also at rest.
This means that data is encrypted
before it is transmitted over
networks and remains encrypted
while stored on the servers.
The Access Control Establishing strict
role based access controls to the RBAC,
which is commonly known as RBAC, is
vital for limiting the data exposure.
RBAC ensures that only authorized
personnel can access the
specific data based on their
job roles and responsibilities.
Moving on to the integration challenges
with the existing systems, One of them
could be the interoperability issues
where we could, one of the significant,
the data format standardization, right?
One of the significant challenges in
implementing AI healthcare is ensuring
that the new system can effectively
interpret and utilize the data from
various existing healthcare IT systems.
Many legacy systems may use
different data formats, making it
difficult for AI applications to
process information seamlessly.
The other could be the API development.
We're, developing robust application,
programming interfaces, which are also
commonly known as APIs, is essentially
for, is essential for isolating seamless
data and hence between, exchange between,
the new AI systems and legacy platforms.
API serves as a bridge that enable
different software applications to
communicate with each other, allowing
for the faster transfer of data
without significant disruptions.
on to addressing the ethical concerns
in AI development, the development of
artificial intelligence in healthcare,
particularly in sensitive areas
like dialysis management, raises
several ethical considerations.
These concerns primarily revolve around
patient autonomy, informed consent,
access, and the potential
for bias in AI algorithms.
Addressing these issues is critical
in building trust and ensuring that AI
technologies enhance Patient care without
compromising the ethical standards.
Talking about the patient autonomy
and informed consent, this could be
achieved through the transparency
and, the opt-out options.
And then moving on to the, the
ensuring equitable actions and
avoiding bias and AI algorithms.
We, here we could, train the AI
with the diverse data sets so there
by, achieving the equitable access
and then also considering their
representative sampling the data updates.
The future trends in AI
and dialysis healthcare.
So AI continues to advance its
applications in healthcare,
particularly in dialysis management,
are becoming increasingly sophisticated.
One of the most promising areas
is natural language processing.
Which focuses on interaction
between computers and human
through the natural language.
So this could be considered as one
of the emerging technologies, which
is the natural language processing.
It is a rapidly evolving, it is a
rapidly evolving branch of AI that
allows computers to understand,
interpret and generate human language.
Its significance in healthcare lies in
enhancing the communication, improving
the documentation and processes.
The key advancements in NLP lately are
the improved semantic understanding.
The multilingual capabilities is another
big improvement in this area lately.
So, coming to the applications
in the incident management.
the natural language processing
capabilities are particularly
beneficial in incident management
within the dialysis healthcare, where
timely and accurate documentation can
significantly impact the patient outcomes.
Some of them could include the
automated documentation, clinical
load analysis, the patient complaint,
and the patient complaint processing.
Moving on to the collaborative AI systems,
the integration of AI into healthcare,
particularly in dialysis, necessitates
the formation of collaborative AI systems.
These systems leverage the expertise
of interdisciplinary teams to maximize
the effectiveness of AI technologies.
These systems leverage the expertise
of interdisciplinary teams to maximize
the effectiveness of AI technologies.
Here is some details where
the collaboration could help.
the first one being the diverse
expertise integration, where we go
with a multi faceted approach to
fully utilize the AI capabilities.
It is essential to adapt to a
multi faceted approach that draws
from the various disciplines.
The next one could be
the team composition.
Like, we've been, in a healthcare, in
a dialysis healthcare system, we would,
could have a team composition with
nephrologists, nurse, technicians, data
scientists, AI specialists, ethicists.
And then the IT professionals within
one setting, so which could also help.
But if we take an example, in developing
AI and AI driven fluid management systems,
Nephrologists can offer insights into
the clinical complications, implications
of fluid balances in dialysis patients.
Data scientists would be responsible for
designing the algorithms that predict
fluid needs based on the patient data.
While nurses provide feedback on
how the system can integrate, can be
integrated into the daily practice.
This collaboration ensures that the
final product is clinically relevant,
technically robust, and user friendly.
Enhancing the communication and
collaboration among healthcare providers.
This could be achieved through
shared understanding or the
common language development.
training sessions, et cetera.
Looking at an example, organizing
monthly AI nephrology seminars
can serve as a platform where team
members present on a range of topics.
For instance, a data scientist
might explain the basics of machine
learning while a nephrologist discuss
the clinical dialysis challenges.
Such lessons foster knowledge
sharing, enhance the team cohesion.
and encourage collaborative
problem solving.
With all that, discussed, coming
to the conclusion, as healthcare
systems increasingly adopt artificial
intelligence technologies, the potential
for transformation in, the incident
management becomes, increasingly evident.
AI's capabilities offer profound,
profound improvements in
patient safety and care quality,
particularly in areas like dialysis.
Let's take a quick recap of
the transformative potential
of AI in incident management.
The first one being enhanced predictive
capabilities, where we could, achieve
the early detection with the help
of the AI algorithms that analyze
the vast amounts of data and the
risk satisfaction stratification.
Advanced modeling techniques allow
for categorization of patients based
on their likelihood of experiences,
experiencing complications.
This risk strategy stratification
enables health care providers to
tailor monitor and treatment strategies
according to individual patient needs.
And the next one being the
real time monitoring analysis.
which could be achieved through continuous
assessment and anomaly detection.
Again, with all that, to summarize in
a final thought, the integration of AI
into incident management represents a
paradigm shift in healthcare, offering
enhanced predictive capabilities and
real time monitoring that significantly
improve patient safety and care quality.
By leveraging AI's power to detect
early warning signs and analyze data
continuously, healthcare providers can
act proactively rather than reactively,
leading to better patient outcomes and
a more efficient healthcare system.
As these technologies continue to
evolve and become more widely adapted,
the role in incident management will
likely grow, into a new era of precision
medicine and, the patient centered care.
Thank you.
Thank you for your opportunity to
share this information with you.
I hope you found it, valuable and I'm
here to answer any questions you may have.
Thank you.