Hi, everyone.
Thank you for joining in today.
I'm Kyra.
I'm a product manager with over 10
years of experience in building B2B and
B2C products, preferably in fintech.
And now I'm working as a product
lead at Neboos, a fintech service
that provides access to traditional
finance products and cryptocurrencies.
And today I want to speak about
strategies for incorporating
compliance into product development.
You may ask me, why, compliance?
Why do you focus on compliance?
Because, when you're working on a
digital product, you always work in a
cross functional, team, where all the
departments involved like marketing,
support, finance, you name it.
So why am I focusing on compliance?
That's because in highly regulated
sectors, there are a lot on the line.
So being fully compliant with all the
regulatory requirements is crucial.
compliance department, is in charge
for following industry regulation
for reducing any risks the company
faces and for building trust.
trust, of the customers.
And also trust of the, regulators
from the government and so on.
And failing compliance can lead to
fines, reputation damage, customer
loss, and as a severe consequence.
So that's why today I want to focus
on how to deal with compliance, how to
involve compliance professionals into
your product development life cycle.
And that's it.
So what is compliance in Fintech?
there's some key elements of compliance,
such like regulatory requirements, AML
and KYC, which stands for anti money
laundering and know your customer,
and sometimes data protection because
from company to company it may vary.
Sometimes compliance is in
charge of data protection.
Sometimes it is, the part of
responsibilities of the other departments.
again, why it matters, it's because,
that's a lot on the line, that
because the stakes are high in highly
regulated industries, and Compliance
Department, Helps to build and
establish trust and ensure safety and
mitigate any risks a company can face.
And the consequence of non
compliance are really severe.
So it's not only legal penalties or
reputation harm or operational disruption.
it's gonna even lead to business closure.
So there are the key components,
from the technological point of view.
So first of all, KYC and KYT, which is.
Know your customer and know your
transactions in anti money laundering.
Also it's rec tech, any kinds
of compliance management system.
And of course, AI based fraud detection
and KYT, KYC automation solutions,
because, nowadays there are a lot of
players on the market and the client wants
to, that transaction to be very fast.
And there are a lot of transactions,
so the client won't, wait for,
hours to the transaction to perform.
The client won't, wait for KYC
procedure to perform, for, days.
that's impossible without
AI based solutions.
what are the common problem of cross
functional collaboration challenges and
how it's effect to compliance relations?
first of all, it's very common to
have communication silos due to
limited interaction between teams.
But, the truth is that if you have
cis you are very likely to have a
limited interaction between teams.
And if you have a limited in, if
you have a limited interaction,
you're highly likely to have cis.
Because teams doesn't talk to each
other, teams doesn't communicate.
Teams doesn't found, like the
common things, like common
goals and common ideas.
So yeah, it's a very common, mistake.
The second is late
involvement of compliance.
So sometimes compliance
introduced when it's too late.
And there's a reason why it happens.
Because, when a product
manager and product team.
is inspired by an idea.
you just want to deploy this.
You just want to make it live.
You just want to experiment.
And sometimes compliance person
ask too many questions because
there's a lot on the line.
They're in charge of
very important things.
So they don't know what to do.
They ask challenging questions,
and sometimes the product team
is not so happy with answering.
They want to move fast,
they want time to market.
And sometimes it can look like compliance
put, the sticks through the wheels, but,
really they're just doing their work.
So if you're involving compliance
professionals, too late, It's highly
likely will lead to, late issues.
So when something important
turn out to be so very late on
the later stage of the project.
And the third one is about balancing.
Um, deploy and developing fintech or
other highly regulated, industries
product is always a balance between
innovation and regulation, which means
that you are always should be aware, how
risky is what you are trying to deploy.
For example, me as a product
manager, I think like all other,
every other product managers, I
want as many clients as we can.
So if we have a hundred clients a day,
please, I want all of them to use our
application to perform transactions.
But compliance specialists understand
that they're like some percent of those
customers are not a good customers who
will be paying bills, paying for the
coffee, paying for everyday life expenses.
But they will pay.
Perform some fraud and so on.
So that's always balancing between
what we can get and what's on the line.
So early engagement,
is the key to success.
When we talk about working
with compliance professionals.
So I would recommend to involve
compliance from ideation.
So from very early stage of your project.
So normally when I have some idea and
I understand that it's not just you,
improvement and, I am very likely
to ask compliance professionals.
I have a quick call with
one of my colleagues.
And just share this idea and sometimes
I have a very good piece of advice
of how to transform this idea in
something fully compliant, how to make
sure that we won't fail and we won't
engage in non compliance and so on.
So also, it's very important to
foster a culture of collaboration.
So that's when you, when you
are happy to interact with your
compliance professional colleagues.
on the daily basis, when you are
grateful for their questions, when
you're grateful for their comments, and
when you are really listening to them.
everybody appreciate when someone listens.
I think this culture may be
fostered in every organization.
the benefits of such an approach,
a few last minutes issues, smoothie
launches and overall better
atmosphere in your, company.
So what.
I do personally to, implement
seamlessly compliance into
product development process.
first of all, I, integrated compliance
to design of all the products we produce.
So on the early stages, a compliance
professional is a part of a cross
functional team and, We listen
to the questions, we listen to
advice and we shape our product.
in accordance with what our
compliance colleagues say.
Other thing is to clarify roles,
because you know sometimes there
are several people in charge of
other parts of compliance process.
For example, you have one person in
charge for KYC and KYB, the other person
is in charge for KYT, and the third
person is in charge of, KYC and KYT.
communication with partners,
risk appetites, and so on.
So make sure that you are
with the right person.
And if you need to involve all the
three persons, you should involve them.
And all in all, the, you should be
to have a regular meetings with,
compliance, regular compliance review.
it's not only product demo when you
like show everything you produced.
Recommend to have a separate meetings
dedicated to compliance needs.
I personally do such meetings
once every two weeks.
It's 30 minutes, just to make sure we
are on the same page with the colleagues,
make sure that nothing is missing,
that we didn't miss any news, any
upcoming audit or something like that.
let's talk about methodologies and tools
that, helps, me to deal with, compliance.
First of all, the agile product,
development is a very good, in
perspective, because that regulation,
very volatile and risk appetite
of partners, even more volatile.
So everything can change
very rapidly and agile.
A very good solution for that because
you don't need to wait for a long
cycle of development, to integrate
some new compliance ideas or tasks
you just have to you could just have
deployment every two weeks so you can.
be very rapid in addressing
compliance issues.
Also, I think it's important to use
risk assessment frameworks and make it
clear for all the team and proactively
identify the risk and address the risks.
Also, you may understand that Compliance
is not a one off action, it's a continuous
process, so everything is changing rapidly
and audit is coming like every quarter
or every year, so you should continuously
include compliance tasks in your sprints.
So let's talk about software we
use to address compliance tasks.
first of all, we automated all the tasks
and when compliance professional need
something from a product development
team, they can address the JIRA, create
a ticket, and then we can discard
this ticket, in person, being sure
that everything is track traceable.
so we use Jira, for
this, for, task tracking.
we also use Confluent for all the
documents available for every member of
the team, so we always can refer to risk
appetite for compliance rules and so on.
And we also use Slack for
day to day communication and
Trello for, for meeting notes.
And as I mentioned before, we use
AI in, for, process automation,
such like KYT, KYC, and for, in
blockchain, for data integrity.
So what else can I share with you?
Let's talk about the best
practice for building a
compliance culture in the company.
So I think everyone who works.
In highly regulated industries, our
finance and so on, knows about trainings
and those trainings are regular and
they are usually very boring and
nobody loved those trainings, but
apart from them, that's very useful.
To have some workshops with compliance
professionals because sometimes they
can share some issue they addressed
the previous week or previous
months, some use from the industry.
And this is really helpful and really fun.
Continuous monitoring and
adaptive regulatory changes.
as I mentioned, it can be 30 minutes,
meetings every two weeks or every week.
It can be, inviting a compliance
professional to your daily stand
up or anything you wish, but it
should be a continuous process.
And the third one, I highly recommend to
document everything regarding compliance.
I know that the most companies, the
most, software development is agile.
So the word of the product is
more important than documentation.
But, if we talk about compliance.
It's crucial to be very precise.
So document everything, store this
in Jira in Confluence or elsewhere
you, your company choose, but,
I, I really recommend to do that.
So let's sum up all said.
compliance is crucial for safety,
trust, and market success, and
even for company existence.
If we talk about highly regulated
industries about finance, for example,
early integration of compliance
professional into product development and
clear understanding of the roles are very
important when we talk about compliance.
Thanks.
And the third one that using
technologies and continuous
learning is a key to stay ahead.
Thank you so much for
your attention today.
let's discuss any questions
or challenges you may have.
I'll be more than happy
to answer your questions.