Hello everyone, and thank
you for joining today.
I'm Spyros Konoumakis, Director of
Product Operations at Mattermost, and
I'm leading the Infrastructure and
Customer Reliability Engineering teams.
As you can understand, there's a
lot of incident management here.
And we're going to explore today
how AI can help the SRE teams to
manage incidents better, right?
And a bit more efficient.
And as we know, every minute
of downtime matters, right?
As it can lead to SLA breaches.
Which means service gets to our customers.
So AI potentially can help us take
some control of the cows and improve
the way we respond to incidents.
If you ever been on
call, it's tough, right?
A call in the middle of the night
disrupts your sleep, messes with
your focus and adds a lot of stress.
There is you are under pressure to
solve multiple problems at once.
There is a lot of
multitasking at this time.
So these incidents don't
just stress us out, right?
There's other things which are happening.
They also slow down the innovation
because there's a constant
firefighting done building.
So let's look how the severity incidents
and why are such high pressure situations.
As we discussed.
Everything happens at once.
There's a lot of multitasking.
So you need to find the root cause,
update internal teams, provide customer
updates, and all of this while you need to
check dashboards, logs, metrics, support
issues which are coming from the support
team, customer success are complaining.
So it can be really overwhelming.
But what if AI, could help us to
manage this complexity a bit better and
empower us to make a few things faster?
Before diving into how AI can help,
let's understand what AI can really do
because it's important to understand how
exactly it's going to empower the teams.
As you can see also in this slide,
AI can work across different types of
data from text, image, audio, video.
And by connecting all of these, it
gives us a better, bigger picture.
So in practice, AI doesn't
replace our decision making.
Still, we're going to decide what
it's going to say in the end,
what will be the next action.
But instead, it can empower us
with faster, better decisions.
More informed insights based on
the data we're going to provide.
So let's see how this
works in a real incident.
Imagine this.
It's 2 a.
m.
You have the perfect REM sleep and you
get paid with a high CPU alert for X
component You know You wake up by the
scary alarming sound from PagerDuty
or Opgenie or whatever tool you are
using And I believe everyone here
actually has gone through this Wondering
it, it's, Oh my God, is this real?
What's going to break?
And, you're sleepy, you're going to your
desk and sit down, turn on the laptop
and just start checking what's going on.
And if you are lucky, you have already
a pretty fine process, and this is
actually your incident response process.
And based on this, you need
to start doing some actions.
In our case, we use modern most
playbooks feature to make sure everything
is organized right from the start.
We run the playbook and this sets
up an incident tunnel algorithm
so everyone can communicate in
one centralized place, right?
So communication is key.
In this kind of situation,
it's very crucial 'cause things
slip through the cracks, right?
And to miscommunication, delays, fixes.
So with everything organized with
a checklist and a well defined
process, you can move on to the
next step of the playbook, right?
So you have the incident sponsor.
Number one priority as you can understand
is to identify the severity so we can
communicate internally to teams like
support or customer success and eventually
to our customers the impact of the
incident, what has been, what is broken.
So AI can process multiple data
and this is where actually AI and
Mattermost Copilot can help us as part
of our incident management process.
In this example, you can see that
the compile analyzed different kinds
of data we provided, like graphs,
data from our observability tool,
specifically the dashboards, screenshots,
and classified this incident as
a severity 2, due to the severe
performance issues with the database.
And it also provided detailed summary
identifying the nature of the problem.
this triage process allows
us to communicate clearly
with our internal team.
And that's why I didn't find the severity.
We can use the same context right now.
We are ready to communicate clearly
what's happening with our internal teams.
Instead of manually crafting these
updates, AI can generate them quickly.
So as we use modern most
playbook features, right?
And we have the generated summary,
we can just with a few clicks, set a
status update internally in a channel
and we ensure everyone is aligned
from engineer to customer success.
So with communication taken
care of, it's time to dive
deeper into the investigation.
And it's just as important to keep
our customers in the loop, right?
So with AI, we can quickly
generate customer facing updates.
And as you can see also in the video, you
can even use our templates we want to have
with our customers and AI can utilize them
to generate specific, clear status updates
based on the template we want to have.
In the past, writing both in external
updates would take a lot of time.
leaving room for errors,
and now AI handles this.
So giving us time to focus More on solving
the issue versus just managing the problem
and with communication taking care of it's
time to dive deeper into the investigation
and everything said, everyone is informed.
Everyone knows exactly what's happening.
And right now we need to
gather more information, right?
So we're starting more in our
observability tools, right?
Logs.
We get more information by our
support team, more information
by customer success team.
Something doesn't work.
And AI, in providing all this
information, you can see here we
provide logs and some information
by the support and customer success.
can do a contextual analysis.
So with extra input, AI right now can
pull more information, combines with the
previous context we already gathered, and
help us clarify more what's happening.
by bringing logs, tickets, and
input from the team members.
AI with this actually, can
empower us to highlight patterns
or issues we might miss.
During the initial response, right?
Because we are on rush.
We were under stress,
we were sleepy, right?
We just woke up from our REM sleep.
this makes the investigation
process a bit faster.
And a bit more efficient, right?
Because AI is constantly adding
more pieces to the puzzle.
And helping us see the full picture.
now that, let's assume that
the issue has been resolved.
What comes next?
Right now, we need to
generate, a post mortem.
We need to have details
about what happened.
What was the evidence?
What was the events, right?
What were the next action items
based on the whole thread we have?
in this case, we just have a simple
case where we're just going through.
But imagine multiple people talking,
multiple people were discussing, so you
can summarize all these things in one
generated timeline with events, evidence,
and how the issue has been resolved.
And this was a super manual process
in the beginning as a starting point.
And you have right now just a
quick summary, which we can just
start editing and unlock with
a collaboration with a team.
And this saves hours of manual work and
ensures that we learn from the incident
and prevent it from happening again.
Of course, AI isn't perfect, right?
As we discussed, collaboration between
the different kinds of people in human
context and input is important here.
Otherwise, the post mortem is just.
A summary which has been generated by
AI, but in practice, there are a lot
of much more things which happened.
It's just a good starting point to start
using it and collaborating as a team.
So AI isn't perfect.
And it's clear, we know that, right?
So AI can make mistakes.
So this is not an artificial
SRE or someone who is going to
do all the work for you, right?
What AI can give to us and empower us
actually more is automate some repetitive
tasks during stressful incidents.
We discussed being on call is very
stressful because of all the things,
there's multitasking, multiple updates,
multiple things to, to be done.
And you will be lucky if you have a
model where you have different kinds
of roles, like an incident commander,
someone who has a communication.
most of times there's no such a thing.
So AI can give us a very good solid
base and a starting point to automate
some of the repetitive tasks, which
can drag us out from the resolving the
incident and responding to the incident
versus just managing the incident.
So this, it's up to us to engineers
to refine each suggestions and
make the final decisions, right?
AI can give us key insights for us.
So you focus on fixing the problems.
And over time, AI improves, like we see
all these breakthroughs and innovation
which is happening in the space.
So becoming a more valuable
tool for speeding up incident
management, AI can help us.
And let's see that key
takeaways, from the today's talk.
AI helps us understand the problems faster
by giving you key insights right away.
So you can get, you can combine
different kinds of data and get a
summary of it in the end and understand
what's going on and put more context.
So AI can reduce some kind of the
multitasking which is happening because
you needed before to write all the
internal updates by yourself and you
were lucky if you had a template.
All the external updates by
yourself and you were lucky you
had another template there and you
need another tool there, right?
There was a lot of multitasking,
which has been significantly decreased
right now with the use of AI.
And you just spent less time managing,
like sharing updates, discussing with
teams, sharing with the customer updates
to the customer, analyzing some of the
data or put more input to the context.
So you spent less time managing the
incident and more fixing it in the end.
And you have also the post mortems,
which can be helpful in the end for you
and your team to go to the next step.
actions and improve your reliability.
Thanks, everyone.
I hope this session gave you enough
insights into how AI can support SRE and
empower them, during incident management.
And if you are interested in
diving deeper, about the details
and how AI can be applied to
your organization about incident
management, feel free to reach out.
You can DM me, exchange contact
info, or tag me on social media.
I'd love to keep this conversation
going, sharing insights.
And hear about your experiences, too.