Hello everyone.
My name is Mihaela Guitersa.
Happy to be with you here today.
Thank you to the organizers for giving
me the opportunity to share what I love
and what I've learned into my experiences
and challenges that I had along the way.
At my core, I'm an engineer and I also
like, even though it sounds being an
engineer and someone that does some
public speaking, it's not really coming
together, but I really like to do this
and Besides my interest in software and
technology, I like to research and prepare
content that I gather from my experiences
or from things that I would have liked
to know at some point, and I didn't.
I didn't have anyone to tell me.
And I wrap this in my presentation
and, open the conversation in
events like this one today.
So thank you to the organizers
for having me again, and.
I hope that we have a beautiful
conversation or that I at least
challenge you a bit to go outside of
your, your area of looking at things.
Why I'm saying this because
today's conversation, it's
going into the area of not so much
technicalities, but the way we are looking
at the problems and challenges that we
encounter every day, the way that we
organize our work, the way we think about
ourselves as developers, I'm trying to
open the conversation about how we are,
interacting with, with our work and with
our challenges on, on a daily basis.
I want to open the conversation
with a little exercise, an
imagination exercise, basically.
Think that you're standing at the
base of a towering skyscraper and you
marvel at its intricate design, right?
Every element in the structure,
it was meticulously planned.
Each element is serving a
purpose in the overall structure.
Now let's think about the architect
who designed that, how they had to
envision all those interactions.
How their building is going to
stand, withstand the test of time
and face storms and all sorts of
challenges, serve its occupants.
How everything was so purposeful
thought of in order to have the best,
yeah, the best structure in the end.
So starting with this mindset,
we can transform the way
we are building software.
Taking this kind of concepts from another
field encourages us to think beyond the
immediate, to consider the long term
impact of our decisions, and to create
systems that are not just functional,
but resilient and scalable and enduring.
I want us to stay with
this analogy in our mind.
We are not just coding, we are building
something of a digital skyscraper.
Let's explore how we can build
them with the same level of
care, creativity, and foresight.
Because as programmers, we often
find it challenging to step back
and see our products like we are
looking at a building, right?
Most of the time we are deeply
engrossed in our tasks and unlike
physical construction, we don't have
the same boundaries, very strict,
very exact boundaries, right?
Software development does not
have the same limitations.
We have freedom and we have flexibility to
push these boundaries, actually push the
boundaries of what's possible in the end.
despite this freedom, when we discuss
perspective and way of thinking, we tend
to stick to familiar patterns, rules.
And we rarely venture outside the box and
even when we do, we may not really embrace
new ways of thinking, we feel comfortable
to stick to our existing beliefs, but by
breaking the cycle through reflection.
We can adopt the growth mindset
that leads to better decisions and
a more fulfilling work experience.
And mindset in this case refers to
attitudes and beliefs that shape the
way we approach work, the way we solve
problems, the way we tackle challenges.
It's the lens through which we view
our abilities, tasks, and potential
for work, and the way we actually
face challenges and brace for impact
when difficult situations appear.
And when we're discussing
mindset, We cannot stop,
we cannot avoid stopping actually
and looking at ourselves and if
you've ever thought Okay, I'm
just not good at algorithms.
I'll never understand this framework
instead of I don't understand
this yet But I can figure it out.
You are topping into fixed mindset
because this perspective limits
your growth It creates a mental
barrier to learning and adaptation.
Developers with a fixed mindset shy
away from challenges, fearing that
failure will expose their limitations.
In contrast, a growth mindset
is the belief that abilities and
intelligence can be developed through
dedication, learning, hard work.
People with a growth mindset
embrace challenges and view
failures as opportunities to learn.
So we need to be very honest with
ourselves and see exactly where we are.
And I'm not asking you right now to
tell me, okay, what, where are you?
Where do you find yourself more?
But more I want you to be honest
with yourself, because in the end,
the scope of this discussion is to
set a starting point for growth.
And since we're discussing about
starting point, I think it's a
good thing to bring to discussion
a story that I heard a while ago.
I think I was I don't know, doing some
volunteering and someone told me I
don't know who is the author, whoever
is, copyrights to you, credits to you.
But the story goes like this.
There were some people on a
hill that were breaking stones.
And then there is this man that
was going towards the hill and he
got curious and asked one of the
people, okay, what are you doing?
And that person was very
focused on your work.
And they were bothered by the question.
No, they didn't like to be
disturbed from their work
because they were very dedicated.
In the end, he answered and
said, I am breaking stones.
The man got very curious and he went
to another and to another until at
some point he got a different response
because this last person that he asked
told him, I am building a castle.
As developers, we grow and
we go to phases, right?
Sometimes we simply complete
tasks and we are just so focused
in that area that we complete.
The entire context.
So we are breaking stones.
On other times, we are interested in
understanding the system and going
beyond the task and trying to understand
the business, maybe very dedicated,
trying to improve and so on, which
is like building castles, right?
There are many reasons
this imbalance happens is.
Sometimes it's the organizations
where we are working.
Sometimes it's the limitation to
information, to the right information.
Lack of options, fear, burnout,
not caring about a project.
this is a reality that we
have to be honest about.
Or maybe we're just the right,
the wrong person for the job.
this happens.
But I feel that we are so
impacted by outside factors and
we are so overwhelmed with it.
Checking some sort of what is the image
of the great developer at some point,
like we have that thing with the effective
developer or efficient developer.
Should I be an effective developer,
one that takes time to ensure code
is clean and scalable and documented,
or should I be an efficient
developer that I implement, I log
box, I deploy, I, this approach
allows me a faster time to market.
And, I'll just focus on speed,
skip this part with extended
documentation and meetings and so on.
We are trying to comply with some
patterns, but sometimes we have to look
at ourselves as professional despite, the
context in which we are at some point.
add our skills.
And again, I dare you to be honest
and use the circle of competence to
understand what are your strengths,
your limits, and expertise.
Using this mental model in the end, it's
about focusing on what you know well and
recognizing where your knowledge gaps are.
And in this way, you can work
effectively with your expertise
while expanding it over time.
So we can start from the
inside circle, right?
Identifying that, seeing what are
your strengths, what technologies,
languages, patterns, you truly
understand at a deep level.
Be honest about your limits.
Stay focused on your areas of expertise
while delivering a current project
because this allows you to build
confidently and produce high quality work.
When presented with tasks outside
your circle, collaborate with others,
whose strengths complement yours.
People that inspire
and you can learn from.
While you're going, outside
in the circle, right?
Outside of your, the stuff you know.
Identify knowledge gaps or areas of
interest that you want to grow into.
Set clear goals.
practice.
Take on projects that stretch
just outside your circle but
are manageable with effort.
Of course, we're going into
this process, we're having this
process, taken into consideration.
Helps you avoid a situation of
overextending your, and having
overconfidence, because you must be
cautious about assuming you're skilled
in areas just because you've been working
at some point with something similar.
And there is this, cognitive bias,
the Dunning Kruger effect, where it
is demonstrated by this psychologist,
through a series of experiments that
People with low ability or knowledge in a
specific area tend to overestimate their
skills, while others with higher ability
often underestimate their skills, right?
So this keeps a balance for
you to know exactly where
you are and don't overextend.
I'm sure that each of you had a
situation at some point where you had
to deal with someone that was having
this bias and you were just so you
know, maybe pissed about the fact that
they are being so confident when you
know exactly how things should be.
So don't be that person.
On another part, there is this mental
barrier that we need to be careful about.
Because even if we don't realize, this
is something that is very powerful
and limiting at the same time.
Because, let's say, if you identify
as a NET developer, you are a
NET developer, you are stuck.
Right?
in your mind, you are a
NET or Java or whatever.
It doesn't matter.
You are an X developer.
But if you are identifying as a
developer who is using X, which can
be NET, Java, whatever, you suddenly
can be a programmer that knows and can
learn and can try other things too.
Just think of situations where you, maybe
someone in your company and said, okay,
we don't have a project right now that
it's using the skills that you have.
But look, there is this opening
in here, something that we think
that might be interesting to you.
technologies are going to evolve.
So try to not identify with them.
Try to keep your mindset fluid
in this area and don't block
yourself into a, a bubble.
The circle of competence isn't
just about recognizing your skill.
It's a tool for growth in the end.
When you understand where you excel
and where you need to improve,
you can make better decisions.
You can work on yourself constantly and
become not efficient or effective or, all
sorts of labels, but be a developer that
is bringing some impact in your work.
We've been discussing about the inner
circle and we've been discussing about
that circle where we know what we don't
know and we want to grow, but we also
touched the areas where we think we know
something, but we actually don't know.
But how about that outside circle?
The thing that we don't
know that we don't know.
How do we tap into that area?
that area that I think that is the
area of blind spots, It's difficult to
understand the system we're a part of
precisely because there are blind spots.
We can't see what we are looking for.
We only see them at some point where
we have, we have somebody porting from
production or something like this.
And a way to do this, I found, of course,
a lot of the conversation that we are
having today has a lot of points from the
book, that can be found also in the book.
This precisely got my attention because
these are three things that if we work
with, are going to help us see the
blind spots that we have to reveal those
blind spots and, at least minimize that
area, if not completely, reveal it.
So first would be that.
Of course, we are discussing, I was
mentioning the book, which is The
Great Mental Models by Shane Pursh.
And in the book, we have these three
factors.
Perspective, ego induced denial,
and distance from the consequences.
We need to approach problems with
different perspectives, even if it goes
on different models, mental frameworks.
We are going to discuss today some mental
models and some example of mental models.
So this is one area where we
need to expand our knowledge.
Then we need to lay low on the ego
and be honest and ask for help and
accept that we are continuous students.
And we need to face and stay close
to the consequences of our decisions.
When we are making
decisions that we are not.
assuming the consequences for we
create that broken window effect, just
as an urban environments where one
broken window left unrepaired signals
lack of care and invites more damage.
So also in our work, small
RSO issues in our code.
our mindset, our processes can accumulate,
leading to bigger problems over time.
If we don't address these issues
as early as possible, we're
just letting all sorts of poor
practices and blind spots take root.
So it becomes harder and
harder to solve problems.
And going further in the
perspective part, because this is
maybe the most powerful of them.
You know how in school we are learning.
are learning about different areas, right?
We are learning about physics
and biology and math and all
psychology, economics and so on.
And we are, we've been learning
and creating this way of
thinking in departments, right?
But in the real world, we need to
combine these departments because
problems in the real world are
not divide it so precisely, right?
So we need to work on our
multidisciplinary mindset, because
if we don't, we miss the full
picture of a problem, and our next
step is not going to be the, the
closest to the best, if not the best.
If a single worldview dominates
our thinking, we'll try to explain
every problem through that lens,
even if it's not the right fit.
the old saying with, to the man with
only hammer, everything looks like
a nail, but not It's not like this
in this, in this world, we need to
understand the complexity of the world.
And we need to understand how important
it is to draw knowledge from, from
different models and different
perspectives and different fields.
And an example, and actually the
first mental model that I would
like us to discuss today is the
Swiss army knife approach, which is
Charlie Munger's way of thinking was
Charlie Munger's way of thinking.
Basically, he believed in having
wide, a wide range of mental models,
similar to having many tools as
we have in a Swiss army knife.
And these metal models, of course,
come from different fields, from
different perspectives, and they
help us see challenges from different
approaches, approach them from different
angles, to find the best solutions.
And if we think if we're
going to a forest, real estate
agent and a yoga trainer.
Of course, each of them is going
to see, a different perspective.
Maybe the botanist is going to
be marveled by the nature, right?
Exactly.
How about details from the nature and
appreciate it and think about how we
can, we need to keep this as untouched
by human action as possible and so on.
A real estate agent maybe thinking more
from the perspective of a business, right?
How he could sell this, how, this could
well, a very good place for having, a
building, a neighborhood, and so on.
Then your veterinarian might be
thinking about the energy and
what is happening in your house.
Session would be so useful to have in
there, and to really let our bodies and
mind to, to use the energy from there
in order to have a great experience.
Each of these perspectives captures
a part, but not the whole picture.
And if we rely on a specific
discipline, we develop gaps.
Yeah, those blind spots
that we were talking about.
You can adapt, of course,
it is a confirmation bias,
which makes things even worse.
Next, a mental model that challenges to,
to look a bit at how we are, considering,
the materials that we are using or the
way that we are organizing our work is
the map is not a territory that refers to
the idea that abstractions like, diagrams
and some schemes, that we are doing, yeah.
or any representation are not
the same as the reality itself.
So any model or map that we create
to understand something is a
simplification and doesn't capture
every detail of real world system.
And this applies directly to software
development where we work with diagrams,
for example, and requirements and
models that not fully represent the
complexity of the system itself.
And we can think, for example,
Let's say we are, a very careful
developer, that follows, the project
specification, document closely.
But then when testing in production and,
having our solution in the real world, we
encounter some unexpected issues, right?
So using this model helps us
recognize that the specification.
The document, the map, yeah, it's not
the same as the actual running system,
the territory, no matter how detailed
the specification is, it will miss some
real world behaviors or edge cases.
And by acknowledging
this, we remain cautious.
We implement retesting, including those
edge cases that we were mentioning,
to ensure that the actual software
performs as intended in the real world.
The third mental model that I
want us to touch today, it's
the second order thinking.
And I would like to start by
there is this effect
called the cobra effect.
Basically, the story goes that when
the British colonial government in
Delhi wanted to reduce the number
of cobras in the city, they offered
the bounty for every dead cobra.
Initially, this seemed like a good
idea, but in time, there were some
individuals that realized that
they could breed cobras and they'll
kill them for the bounty, right?
And increasing, of course, their profits.
This was not a good idea
since the government found
out and stopped the program.
Yeah, after discovered this unintended
consequence of their program.
And in response, the cobra breeders, of
course, having no use for the snakes,
they released them, causing the cobra
population to be even worse than before.
So this unintended outcome is
recognized as the cobra effect.
And actually, this is, if we look
carefully, we see the consequence and
that the consequence of our decisions
in the consequences of our decisions.
And this is exactly what the second order,
thinking mental model, patches, because it
encourages us to look beyond the immediate
consequences to understand their long
term effects, as well as ripple effects
that might arouse from these decisions.
And let's again, take an
example in software development.
Let's say that we are part of a
team that is being assigned to
work with, e commerce platform, right?
Of course.
thing that we do, we are focusing
on delivering the, the core
functionality of the platform, maybe.
Ensuring that the basic features
like, think first, right?
Basic features like product search,
checkout, payment, work smoothly, right?
Maybe we even think about, okay, let's
prioritize performance and speed to
give users a fast browsing experience.
This is the first thing that
we are considering, right?
When we are here in e commerce, okay.
But these are the first order.
thinking.
This is an example, again,
take it with a grain of salt.
But if we go a bit more into
details, we can actually consider
those second order effects, yeah?
We can start thinking beyond the
immediate functional requirements and
think, okay, but what happens if spikes,
if traffic spikes dramatically, yeah?
What happens if part of the system fails?
For example, the payment.
component.
And if I have to add new features,
features to this, will it be easy?
Will it be, hard for
the business to evolve?
How things will be?
By asking this kind of question, so
going a bit beyond to the second order
concerns, we can see other, important
factors surface, like scalability,
the need for availability and fault
tolerance, performance under load,
security and compliance and so on.
This, this mental model helps us
exercise, considering the ripple effects
of our decisions, and help us identify
and prioritize characteristics that
will ensure long term success, right?
It prevents us from focusing on
short term functional goals and,
helps us handle future challenges and
opportunities with minimal, disruptions.
an interesting part about, about
us, and we are discussing before,
about this when talking about blind
spots is that we cannot understand
a system that we are a part of.
And relativity involves understanding
that things are not absolute and often
depend on context or perspective.
So my all time favorite example or
situation for this is when we have
to choose from or technology language
and application for an application.
Doesn't matter technology
language approach.
Doesn't matter.
I remember some years ago, we were
not sure if this dispute since
Phil is, but there is what is best.
The net or Java?
What is best?
React or Angular.
Which is the best, has the best approach?
How we are going to work with it?
things like this, like what
has the most advantages?
What, which one is the best?
Where?
instead of asking what's the best
programming language, how about, I
think, what is the best programming
language for this specific project?
The best language is relative
to the skill set of the team,
projects, requirements, timeframe.
There's no absolute best answer.
What matters is the context
in which the decision is made.
Then, instead of always striving for
brilliance or perfection, it's often more
effective to focus on avoiding mistakes.
In the context of software, for example,
this could mean focusing on common
pitfalls and making sure to avoid them.
For example,
let's say that you have a deadline.
a very aggressive deadline.
You did not expect this.
Things have changed in the
project, what we are going to do.
Instead of thinking, okay,
what are the best practices to
follow to meet this deadline?
those magazines that are giving you 10
steps to Be the best manager, 10 steps
to be a productive developer, and so on.
Instead of looking for these 10 steps
to ensure that we meet the deadline,
how about we apply inversion, right?
And ask what common mistakes
we need to avoid that could
make us miss the deadline.
What did we do the last time
when we missed the deadline?
Let's avoid doing that.
Start from that point.
Then, by deliberately avoiding
these common mistakes, you increase
the chances of success rather than
just looking for the best way to
do it without being validated.
You already validated what are the worst,
the worst things that you can do to not
beat the deadline for sure in the past.
Start from there.
Focus on ensuring that simple
errors don't derail the project.
Then moving forward, you know how we
have this tendency of Thinking that
the more complicated something, or
the problem that you're fixing, or the
more complicated the solution that we
are giving you, the more complex, the
more important we are because we don't
know the same thing as everyone else.
So we end up becoming really good at
something specific just to stand out.
And sometimes we actually find or
look for complex, resolutions for
our problems just to make sure that
others can easily understand it.
But besides that, to make
sure that we stand out.
with our complex way of looking at things.
Or Occam's Razor is a concept that
suggests that when faced with multiple
competing solutions, the best starting
point is to start with the simplest one.
If your project is not, explicitly
asking for the most complex solution,
start with the, with the simplest one.
And we have a lot of examples in software.
I'm sure that you've been thinking
about at least three since I
opened the conversation about this.
But what I can say to wrap up this is
to avoid over engineering solutions in
both development, design, architecture,
design for simplicity and usability
and focus on straightforward solution
during debugging and problem solving.
And a simple, more focused
approach is easier to use and
it's easier to build upon.
So of course, again, take it
with a grain of salt, check the
context of your situation, problem.
whatever it is, and try to build step by
step to see exactly what kind of approach
you need to do, but don't respond out of
ego, which we're mentioning a bit before.
Of course, we've touched today
some mental models, and there
are a lot of mental models.
I actually encourage you to look on
it and see, but it's not about knowing
them, knowing as many as possible.
It's about being open and learning.
Yeah, we need to move away from solving
immediate tasks and start thinking
holistically about the systems we build.
And these kind of models help us navigate
complexity and make better decisions.
And they allow us to design software that
does not only solve current problems, but
is adaptable for future growth and change.
So I'm going to leave you with this
beautiful quote from Alexander, which I
think it's the essence of a developer's
mindset, When you build a thing, you
cannot merely build a thing in isolation.
You must repair the world around it.
understanding that every piece of
software contributes to a larger system.
So just to close the
circle, build castles.
Don't just break castles.
Don't just break stones.
Think about your, your
work from this perspective.
I want to very much for staying with
me today and for listening to my talk.
I hope that I was able to.
to open some question for you or
some areas that you would like
to explore further and, yeah,
reach out and let's discuss.
Thank you very much.