Hello everyone and thank you
for joining today's session at
Con 42 on incident management.
I'm Viji Ma personally, and I bring
with me around two decades of exercise
in cloud technologies specializing
in microservices architecture.
Over the years, I have had the
privilege of working with various
organizations as a hands-on architect
and team lead, have guided teams
in building and deploying mission
critical microservices applications.
Within agile and cloud environments.
Currently I'm working as a tech leader
at Freddie Mac, and today I'll be sharing
how the same principles tie into the
evolution of modern A PA gateways and
their role in data driven reliability for
microservices and serverless environments.
Why a PA gateways matter
for the incident management?
Let's start with why.
A PA gateways have evolved from
being simple traffic routers
to becoming critical planes.
In fact, they are often the first
responders during the incidents.
They give us comprehensive visibility
across distributed services and
enabled rapid fault isolation and
allow for target recovery strategies.
Think.
Of them as the strategic checkpoints,
the place where you can apply resilience
patterns consistently without having
to change each service individually.
Let's discuss today's agenda.
Here are the things I'll
cover today in this session.
The number one, the evolution of
API gateways, and how service mesh
integration strengthens reliability.
Optimizations for serverless workloads and
edge computing as a resilient strategy.
The fifth one, AI and ML power
routing and caching techniques.
And the final one, security
and zero trust resilience.
By the end of this session, you
will see how modern gateways
are inges traffic managers.
There are incident management engines.
Let's jump onto the
evolution of API Gateways.
We'll deep dive into each
of this topic one by one.
Let's jump onto the
evolution of API gateways.
Let's trace the evolution of
this API gateways during the
different generations of first.
The generation one, the basic proxies.
These gateways just handles the simple
routing and basic authentications
and offer very limited visibility.
And the next generation API
management, it added rate limiting
analytics and developer portals.
This was the start of governance and
in the further generation, the cloud
native, which is the Kubernetes native
service, mesh integrator, and much
better at scaling with microservices.
The final generation, the reliability
engine, this is a big leap, a driven
re resilience and predictive scaling,
and even autonomous recovery.
Today, the modern gateways can process
one 80 million a p calls daily across
eight 50 plus microservices, keeping
latency under 50 milliseconds, and
uptime at 99.99 percentage even
during the incident conditions.
Let's check into the second
topic, service mesh integration.
Next, let's talk about the service
mesh integration, which I call
the relatable team multiplier.
When paid with an API Gateway service
mesh delivers a lot of great features.
Something like below, which is like
62% faster in insulin detection,
34% lower end-to-end latency.
And 57% better resource efficiency,
78% more accurate and fault isolation.
Together they form a
resilient control plane.
We get real time traffic,
shaping intelligence, circuit
braking, and observability,
all in one co one ecosystem.
Let's jump onto a real world
example, which comes from the
financial services sector.
Which coordinates eight 50
plus microservices through
a single gateway cluster.
The setup processed one 80 million daily
calls, kept LA at 47 milliseconds, and cut
MTTR from 23 minutes down to 4.3 minutes.
That's a game changer
for incident management.
Let's move on to the
serverless optimization.
Now let's move into the serverless.
Which brings unique challenges.
Some of them are something like
this, like cold start mitigation
by using pre warming strategies.
We have seen a 76% reduction in cold
strats maintaining 88 milliseconds, warm
starts even during instant recovery.
Scaling precision predictive
scaling has reached 99.995.
Percentage accuracy enables us
to handle 42 million monthly
events without over provisioning.
And finally, the request izing with
intelligent batching, we cut down 43%
of functional invocations during spikes.
The takeaways, API Gateways help
serverless workloads stay fast.
Coefficient.
And reliable.
Let's move on to edge
computing for resilience.
Under another powerful
lever is edge computing.
Deploying gateways at Edge provides 58%
reduction in global latency support for
98,000 requests per second, across 40 to
global locations, and 99.95 percentage
of time during the regional outages.
73% reduction in cross region traffic.
An example of a edge deployment
architecture looks like this, and
which has several key things which
are like regional API Edge, which are
like local gateway notes, handling
user traffic and a control plane,
which has a central configuration and
routing policies, and then an active
routing, which does load balanced.
Health aware traffic screening.
Finally, the failover paths,
which does automatic automated
fallback to healthy regions.
In practice, this multi region
architecture allowed one E-Commerce
customer survived a major US East
one outage by rerouting traffic
automatically to healthy regions,
maintaining 99.98% availability.
This is resilience in action.
Failures are contained regionally
while customers stay online.
And move on to the next topic, which is
AI and ML capabilities with API Gateways,
AI powered routing gateways make nine,
950,000 routing decisions per minute with
99.95 percentage optimal path accuracy.
This directly speeds up
incident resolution by 38%.
An ML driven caching by analyzing
request patterns, data volatility, and
traffic fix, we achieve up to 47% back
and load reduction during the incidents.
The benefit is clear here.
Instead of engineered, scrambling to
scale systems under pressure, AI and MI
allow the system itself to absorb the
stress while teams focus on the recovery.
Let's jump on to another topic,
which is zero trust security,
During the incidents, let's not
forget security re resilience.
During the peak loads, gateways can
process 1.9 million authentication
requests per minute with an average
16 milliseconds response time while
maintaining 99.99% compliance.
How.
To distributor token validation,
local policy enforcement, and graceful
degradation, even when identity providers
or restructured security remains intact.
These that during incidents, we are not
trading off availability for complaints.
We are maintaining both.
Let's discuss implementing
resilient gateway architectures.
So how do we do this altogether?
There are several key
factors to achieve this.
One, a clear ownership and
boundaries define what the
gateway forms versus the services.
And second, the multi-layer
observability, which we have to
do the tracing metrics and probes.
Failure, isolation patterns,
which are like circuit breakers,
bulk hurts, and rate limits.
And automated remediation build
self-healing with fallback behaviors.
And finally, the instant playbooks.
Clear Runbooks for
gateway specific failures.
This isn't just about the tech, it's about
the operational discipline and readiness.
So the final key takeaways from
this session, a PA gateways
are no longer just routers.
They are critical incident
management control plans, service
mesh integration cards, incidents
detection time by over 60%.
Edge deployments maintain near a hundred
percent of time during the outages.
A powered routing and ML caching deliver
fast recovery and efficiency gains.
Zero.
Trust, resilience, and
ensure security is never com
compromised during the incidents.
I hope I covered all the topics which I
intended to cover during this session.
Thank you all for listening.
I hope this gives you a clear picture of
how modern API gateways are becoming the
backbone of reliable cloud native systems.
Thank you.
I would love to connect further.
Here is my LinkedIn link
if anyone want to connect.
Thank you once again.