Hi everyone.
My name is Push.
Today I will be presenting
accelerating IR response with
distributed draft Technology.
Okay, let's begin.
So could disclaimer before
we go further and talk.
So content presented here is based on my
personal experience and publicly available
information, it has not been officially
approved and endorse by any organization.
Let's discuss the limitations
of the traditional I systems.
So I categorize the problem enough for
subcategories, the data fragmentation,
time, synchronization issues, relationship
lightness, and manual correlation
overload, so data fragmentation.
So in today's world, we have a
lot of systems producing data.
It's very hard to connect the data across
those disconnected system, which hinders
a timely aggregation and correlation.
The next is time synchronization.
So all the systems generate
events according to times
which is relevant to them.
So we don't get accurate forensic time
when we want to reconstruct everything.
Relationship planning has traditional
model failed to capture the complex
relationship between various entities.
The last one is manual correlation.
I've seen lot of SRE engineers looking at
dashboards, which is very time process to.
That happened.
The, so these inherent limitations
result in fundamental problems in the
security systems, which are leading
extended detection system, reservation
time, and incomplete investigation,
and increased operational cost.
We trying to address these issues.
So now graph technology
for incident response.
So graph can transform the all the
entities in a relationship model, which
can help us to debug the issue better.
So it can categorize the issue
among nodes, edges, and properties.
So nodes are the users.
Machine IP addresses, processes,
edges can be like relationship access
created, communicated with properties
can be contextual information like
timestamps, severity, and classifications.
So the structure enable us relationship
based investigation, which follows
the natural progression of security
incident across the system boundaries.
So in graph database, we can build
this unified sematic layer across
all silo data sources enabling
the comprehensive analysis.
For example, we can.
Put all the data from network
application endpoint, cloud
identity indexes in one big giant
dashboard and we can query across.
So now whatever problems we've discussed,
spanner graph is a natural fit for that.
There are a lot of SaaS application
available in the market, but with span
graph, we just use graph for your.
Day to day OTP workload and
also for analysis, workload,
and build a huge graph.
So SPAN graph is a globally distributed
graph, extending spans capability
for precise, reliable analysis
of massive distributed dataset.
So for incident response, paragraph
offers global consistency.
All it ensures like all the data
is consistent and immediately
available across all regions.
The.
It enables a precise globally
synchronized timelines.
Eliminate the timestamp discrepancies.
For accurate forensic P construction
relationship model, we can bring
the massive graph by edges and
connect those edges across multiple
nodes, scalability and reliability.
So Spanner inherently has horizontal
scalability for petabytes of
data with automatic charging and
replication for high availability.
By combining these attributes,
paragraph, transform the fragmented
data into cohesive, globally
consistent relationship based database,
which can accelerate investigation
and strengthen security portion.
We already discussed two specific
things, which are already interesting.
First is two, time Mother
is a relationship model.
True is a very fundamental
construct in this span, a PA, which
provides solution to as problems,
like we get globally consistent
timestamps across different system.
We get bounded uncertainty,
so we have a maximum skew.
That can happen between various
even cordial consistency.
It guarantees that events are ordered
across all regions, preventing
a true sequence of actions,
a relationship model.
So as you've discussed earlier, with
a relationship model can be defined
by your nodes, edges, and properties.
So what this get us, so this
can help us to identify a few
of the early things in the.
To the incident responders, which we
usually look for first, it'll identify
the blast radius by traversing the
connection from the breach point of the
affected asset so it can do the later
moment patterns across traverse system,
revealing the attackers path in detail.
We can also hidden discover
hidden relationships across
unrelated events, connecting the.
The dots which traditional tools miss.
We can build a comprehensive
attack timelines with perfect
sequencing, and thanks to the
temporal, consistent, and co mapping.
So the holistic view empowers the
incident responders to move beyond
fragmented, alert driven system, and
leading to fast record incident response
and minimizing the business impact.
I will briefly touch on the query
capabilities that SPAN Graph
has, so we can do path analysis,
find all the possible connections
between compromised assets.
We can do pattern matching.
We can do take centrally available
measures like critical assets
and identify the choke points.
We can do the community detection,
like group of related events
to identify the campaign scope.
So these kind of scenarios can be easily
covered by span graph capabilities.
A very brief slide on the
implementation if someone wants to
onboard, like what they need to do.
So I categorize that in four or five,
I would say five different categories.
So the first one is collection.
We need to collect the
data from all the sources.
Then we need to normalize those.
And find.
After that, we need to fit
that in those graph model.
And once we fit that in graph models,
panel storage is a natural fit for that.
And after that we can just investigate
by using those panel query model three
technical challenges, which I have listed.
If someone wants to
design the application.
So the first one is schema design.
So we need to see how we can balance
between various entities and relations
for getting the good performance.
The second is ingestion timeline.
So we need to see whether we are doing
the real time or the batch processing, how
we are handling out the quarter events,
how we are enriching the data across.
So this, we need to ensure
like all the queries are
responding within the threshold.
For that we might need some of the
tune enables in query either better
planning or some caching, or we need
to balance out the response timing
with the data that we're fetching.
Key takeaways, spanner transforms higher.
By providing few the capabilities
which are unique to the system.
The first one is it provides a
unified time synchronized view
across all security events so we
can trace the attack progression
through complex multi relations.
It provide the precise time
coordination that eliminates the
timestamp discrepancies, so it helps
us to build a relationship model that
reveals the full scope of compromise.
By implementing this approach,
organization can achieve faster.
Thank you.