Hello, everyone.
My name is Praveen Kumar, and I'm
currently working as Director of Business
and Product Readiness with a large life
insurance company here in North America.
So my topic of discussion today is how
artificial intelligence and machine
learning are creating efficiencies and
creating a transformative impact in
predicting consumer behavior analysis
and also how the claims are efficiently
processed using this New latest UpToDate
technologies like AI and machine learning.
So without further delay, let's get
onto the agenda of our discussion.
So moving on to the next slide.
As you can see here.
We have quite some agenda to cover
today during our conference topic.
I would first start with providing
you guys some background on the
industry context and challenges we have
today in the life and energy space.
And then we will discuss the power of
AI and ML in claims processing, how the
latest technologies from AI are providing
and creating efficiencies in processing
of claims, and then we will also discuss
the impact on operational efficiency.
And how A.
I.
And M.
L.
Are used in predicting the
customer behavior before or
after a policy is purchased.
We would then move on to talk
about the customer satisfaction
and some key benefits of machine
learning and artificial intelligence
in the life and energy space.
And to close the topic, we will also
discuss a few case studies and the road
map of artificial intelligence and A.
I.
Adoption for different
life and energy companies.
So without further delay, let's
start with the industry context.
So as you guys know, today,
we have three different areas
in the whole life and annuity
ecosystem, which are most critical.
One is the claims processing.
Secondly is the consumer
behavior or predictive analytics
used for consumer behavior.
The third is the cost of insurance, right?
So as you can see, claim is a
very important aspect of any
life and annuities value chain.
So the current claims process often
involves a lot of manual tasks and
there are multiple layers of review
before a claim is actually paid or,
a claim is already approved, right?
Once it is issued by the company and,
due to this lot of manual effort,
there are delays, there might be errors
because there's a lot of human, human,
factor involved in the processing
of claims, which would ultimately is
leading to customer dissatisfaction.
second topic, what we will be
discussing in detail is the
consumer behavior insights, right?
So the taste of consumer or, the choice of
consumer in selecting an insurance company
or a policy is quickly changing, right?
What they expect and what they don't
expect, what are their preferences, right?
All these are different, very
important data points for a particular
company to acquire a consumer.
And then the third topic is
the cost pressures, right?
So the cost of insurance is nothing
but the cost of a particular company
to acquire a consumer, right?
To issue a policy or to sell a policy.
to make sure that the admin costs are
in control And to make sure that all
the operation costs and overhead costs
are not, Burdening into the policy of
the consumer which is purchasing, right?
So to basically deal with these three
challenges We can, we want to use AI
and machine learning to understand
the behavior of the consumer.
In that way, we can reduce the
complexity in claims processing.
We can gather more consumer
insights and predict consumer
behavior much efficiently.
And we can also bring down
the cost of insurance.
So moving on to the next slide,
so what is the role of AI
and ML in claims processing?
So today, as you can see, most of the,
most of the claims processing work,
like documentation, getting, evidences,
Validating the information, all this is
actually done majority of the times using
a manual intervention from humans, right?
So what AI can do in
this particular process?
in this particular process, we
can actually automate the whole
process of receiving documentation,
extracting the documentation for
a particular claim, validate the
information, and route it for approval.
the whole process from claim receivable to
claim, approval can be automated using AI.
And what these, AI helps, because these
large machine learning, algorithms, right?
which actually worked behind the
scenes along with AI, they detect
different patterns, in claims data, to
see if there are any fraud cases, if
there are any inconsistencies, right?
and they would automatically flag
suspicious cases for human review.
So there is never a complete 100 percent
automation, but there is always a human
factor involved along with collaborative
AI, along with machine learning to make
sure that, we also identify and detect
fraud, predictive analytics, right?
So also the AI algorithms.
They predict claim outcomes based on the
historical data of a particular policy.
For example, if we issue a life
insurance policy for a particular
person who is in an age group
of, a senior age group, right?
So based on his historical medical
data, the AI or machine learning can
predict what kind of decision making
and improvements Can occur in the
processing of claims, once we receive
a claim with the insurance company.
So basically the AI and machine
learning are very playing a very key
important role in anomaly detection,
in predicting analytics and also
in automated document handling.
So let's move on to the next slide.
Okay.
So how does AI and machine
learning are creating impacts and
operational efficiency, right?
So they basically reduce manual
intervention, meaning wherever there
is a human factor involved, right?
Like data entry or document
classification and claim assessment.
All of this can be actually
automated using AI.
And by doing this, we actually
have benefits of getting few errors
and the processing is much faster.
And in a way, by implementation of
AI in the claims processing, the life
insurance and annuity companies can
save money, which they actually spend
on operations, which they actually
spend on different overhead cost
of, hiring people to do stuff like
document classification and data entry.
And this is actually leading to an overall
reduction in the cost of claims handling.
So basically, and it also
helps the companies to fight
against fraud mitigation, right?
Because AI's ability to detect
anomalies in real time means that
the fraud can be caught earlier.
So basically, as you can see on this
slide, we have three important key
benefits on operational processing of
any company by using AI, which is nothing
but it reduces manual intervention.
And it gives us cost savings and it
also helps us in, fighting with fraud
claims and, detect anomalies in real
time very much earlier in the process
than towards the end of the process.
Okay.
AI and ML and consumer behavior analysis.
So how do we use AI to drive
and understand the nature
of consumer behavior, right?
So basically AI actually helps us
with three important factors, what
I call as pattern recognition.
Personalization and proactive engagement.
So what is pattern recognition?
So whenever there is a change
in consumer behavior, right?
So the data, there are different data
points because the AI processes, large
volumes of data, it will be easily
able to identify trends and what
kind of buying behavior and patterns
the consumer is shifting to, right?
And what are the different payment
patterns and product differences
the consumer is actually asking for.
So all these, the AI would be able
to leverage the information, existing
information and future information, and
create data points which will help us in
creating a pattern or a trend analysis.
In that way, we can clearly see that, this
is a consumer behavior trend from, Point A
in time to point B in time how the tastes
have changed and how the preferences
have changed towards, Purchasing of a
particular policy or towards purchasing a
particular product and then with the help
of these data points What we can do is, as
life insurance companies have these data
points for review and analysis, right?
And they should be able to personalize
the products, what they built in that
way, the consumers will be easily able
to pick the right products for them.
And it also helps to bring the cost of
insurance down because now they don't have
to spend too much of money on marketing
or to acquire a consumer because most
of these products, depending on the
data insights, what we achieve from
pattern recognition, it will help us.
Customize the products for consumers in
such a way that you know, it's catering
to a mass market at the same time making
sure that you know we are taking into
account their individual preferences
and different data points proactive
engagement So this also helps us in
predicting the proactive engagement and
future needs from consumers, you know
How the consumer would predict five years
from now, how the consumer trend would
change 10 years from now So all this, you
know will be done using ai and machine
learning algorithms Which the system
will automatically be able to recognize
using different data points and trends
Based on the historical data and consumer
behavior So that is how we use AI and ML
in predicting consumer behavior analysis.
So moving on to the next
slide, which basically speaks
about customer satisfaction.
So simple thing, we have three main points
for increasing customer satisfaction.
Whenever we create a product, whenever
we create a service, it should be
customer centric and customer focused.
So by using AI and machine learning,
we make sure that we hit three main
important nodes of customer satisfaction.
One is we are creating a
tailored product, right?
Because AI will allow the companies
to design personalized policies, which
will reflect their unique preferences
and needs and financial situations.
And it will also improve the engagement
with customers because AI can offer
solutions 24 by seven with customer
support like chatbots And if in case
the customer has some sort of inquiries
to make, he doesn't have to wait
the next business day to talk to a
person, but instead, talk to a bot,
chat bot or a virtual assistant and
get responses accurately immediately.
And then we can also
improve increased retention.
So by delivering more relevant
and personalized services.
The companies can enhance customer
satisfaction Thereby leading to higher
retention rates and lower churn factor.
So moving on to the next slide So what are
the key benefits of ai and ml integration?
So the key benefits are basically,
it helps us, as I spoke earlier,
with efficiency gains, right?
Because we are automating much
of this process and claims and
underwriting and fraud detection.
Everything is more streamlined now.
the operations processes are
more streamlined and much more
faster and more efficient.
Fraud prevention.
So the real time anomaly detection
powered by AI will significantly reduce
the risk of fraud because it will help
us detect fraud much earlier in the
game than towards end of the process.
Thereby safeguarding the company's
financial interest and most of the
decision making is data driven, right?
So we use something called as predictive
analytics, which actually improves
decision making by forecasting
consumer needs, risks, and trends
based on the historical data.
So these are the three different benefits
of, using artificial intelligence
and machine learning integration.
So moving on to the next,
which is basically case studies
and success stories, right?
So one of the case studies is at
a large life insurance company.
I would not like to take names, but,
there was an AI driven claims automation
system, which was actually implemented.
And then, looking at the metrics
and looking at the tangibility
of this, implementation of
system of using AI, right?
They were able to reduce the claims
processing time by almost 40%.
Okay.
So let's say if before the AI
implementation automation system was
implemented, if the claims processing
time took like almost two days, it
was actually drastically reduced to
few days to process a claim after an
AI automation system was implemented.
Same thing at a different company, AI
was used to build personalized product
recommendations based on utilizing
the last customer historical data,
including the payment history, the
demographics and purchasing patterns.
So by doing this, they were
able to personalize and
create new product offerings.
And then the company saw a 20 percent
increase in customer retention.
So what is the road?
So this is very important for us.
So what is the roadmap
for AI and ML adoption?
Because even before we get started, we
need to understand what is the key benefit
for the need of implementing an AI in a
particular process or a company, right?
So there are different steps, as you
can see, first, we need to identify
the key areas for AI implementation.
So we have to start with something
called as claims processing and
customer analytics, where the
highest impact can be achieved.
And then we have to develop
a solid data strategy, right?
Because any AI model or ML,
machine learning model, is
as good as the data, right?
Because, and we have to make
sure that the right data is
collected and managed, right?
And it needs to follow a compliant
and ethical manner to make sure
that we are powering the, AI or ML
tools, in a compliant manner And
then the step three is creating or
building AI or ML capabilities, right?
Whether it might be in house development
or we can partner with so many vendors
outside in the market Who actually
provide us this AI services, right?
We can build the necessary AI or
automation Into a particular company.
And then the fourth step is
continuous improvement, right?
So any AI system must be monitored,
tested, and optimized regularly to make
sure that they are delivering the desired
results and adapt to changing needs.
According to the business objective
of our company, it should be
parallel and supporting the company's
business objective of implementing
an AI into a particular system.
So these are the four different steps
for four basic steps, In general, what
we need to understand before actually,
implementing an AI model in a particular
process or a company and in conclusion.
So I know we spoke a lot about, artificial
intelligence and machine learning, so
to my, to my, experience and so far
the data, what I've seen in the market,
The artificial intelligence and machine
learning, it actually represents a
very big transformative opportunity for
insurers, to streamline their operations.
And to provide a more personalized
and efficient customer experience
So by automating key processes like
claims handling and leveraging data
driven insights, we can create and
predict consumer behavior We can create
personalized products and we can reduce
operation costs, you know improve fraud
detection and overall, improve the
customer satisfaction service delivery.
So these are some of the key, benefits
of using AI and machine learning
in the life and annuity space.
thank you for giving me this
opportunity, for presenting and the
transformative impact of, artificial
intelligence and machine learning
in life Thank you, everyone.