Welcome to CONF42
Incident Management 2024.
I'm going to talk about data driven
retail, leveraging forecasting
models to enhance customer experience
and operational efficiency.
There's a lot of, jargons here, but
on a simple terms, I'm going to talk
about how various forecasting models
helps achieve, enhanced customer
experience, in this fast paced world.
Before getting into the topics,
I would like to introduce myself.
I'm, I'm Sijo Walekadmanikantan.
I'm a data scientist with,
over seven years of experience.
my specializations have been primarily,
with a huge forecasting, background.
and when I talk about forecasting,
it's forecasting at scale, dealing
with, millions of time series and,
with a lot of historical data.
I'm also, active in the researching
research space, authorship, and
as well as mentoring junior data
scientists and analytics professionals.
educationally, I have a master of
science from University of Texas at
Austin, and a bachelor of engineering
degree, in mechanical engineering.
I would like to walk you through
what I'm going to talk today.
so, At the very beginning, I'm
going to talk about the need for
forecasting, with respect to retail.
so first I will go into the nuances
of, high level retail value chain.
and then, I will introduce you to the.
Retail landscape and the necessity
of why, why advanced forecasting
models are very careful consideration
of forecasting models need to be,
considered, in the retail space.
in the next section, I will go over
forecasting challenges, specifically
regarding, Horizon Green and, the
challenges brought about by COVID 19.
I will also touch upon other,
other aspects, other challenges,
relating to these, and, and
specific forecasting challenges.
and, and once we understood the value
chain as well as, the forecasting
challenges, I will touch upon on a high
level the three different classes of,
forecasting techniques that's being
used in the industry and that has
shown, tremendous results, with respect
to performance, accuracy, and so on.
Then I will introduce you to some case
studies, that a couple of case studies on
how, certain retailers, global retailers
have managed to, use forecasting to,
to solve their supply chain issues.
and towards the end, I would discuss
where the future of forecasting
is and what are the generic trends
that's being seen in the retail space.
as of as of today and it's a it's a
very very bright future ahead as well
as filled with a lot of challenges
So without further ado, i'm gonna get
started, with why do we forecast right?
So first thing before even
understanding why we need to forecast
why need to make predictions about
anything like it could be sales.
It could be demand it could be revenues
or it could be outages and so on
any any You disruptions and so on.
we need to understand the complexity
of the retail value chain, right?
So retail value chain is on a very,
very, very high level is the chain.
It's the, series of events that
captures the flow of goods from
manufacturers to consumers.
Okay.
So talking about consumers,
we are all consumers.
I'm sure everyone is aware of Amazon,
Walmart, Kroger, and so on, right?
these are the multinational corporations.
I'm sure there are other, different sizes.
I mean, retailers come in different
sizes and scales, even, even, a
neighborhood grocery chain will
have its own retail value chain.
So, we cannot, generalize, generalize.
retail value chains, it's it's different.
according to the companies and everything
so but typically, we see these components
in like ranging from manufacturers to
consumers in in every supply chain, right?
And sometimes it could be like a different
order or different configurations, or,
or it could be, each component might
be tons, hundreds, might, it may be
one, and it might be having a different
sort of networks and so on, right?
So in here we have, the
manufacturer, right?
So manufacturer is the one
who manufactures goods.
if we take, let's say, a Walmart store,
for instance, any, or you can take any
grocery store, for instance, right?
They have tons of inventory, tons
of stocks, tons of products, right?
it's, you know, called
SKUs, stock keeping units.
each, each product is identified, each
SKU code and, and, and all other things.
Right.
So if you walk into a Walmart, any
store, you, you're, you're dealt
with like, I don't know, hundreds and
thousands of products, if not millions.
Right.
Like, a milk from a particular
brand is, is, is a SKU.
And then even if you look within a
category of something like milk, right.
There could be maybe, fifties or
hundreds of hundreds of different SKUs
comes in different sizes, different
shapes, different packaging, and so on.
Right.
So these, so if you take a simple
case of, one such product, it's
being manufactured at some facility.
let's say if you take a perishable
goods, generally, like, like milk,
for instance, it comes from the.
same country or same vicinity as, as
the places, but it's not guaranteed.
Let's say something like a plastic
product or a kitchen product
might come from as far as China.
Right.
So we all know like China is
the biggest manufacturing hub.
So a lot of products come from China
and then they need to be transported
to, how does it reach consumers?
They must be transported across the
continents to reach the consumers.
now the problem is we don't know how
many products a customer want, right?
So that's a problem.
But when you talk about transport, I
would like to go into the transport first.
So transport could be I put an image
of truck here, but it could be ship.
It could be multi modal.
It could be trains It could go
from let's say ship to a train to a
Car and then to a person in a bike
to store and then consumer so it
could be any combinations, right?
So usually the the the manufacturer
the goods move from manufacturers
to distribution centers, right?
distribution centers are warehouses
where all these products are stored
and depending on the You demand from
the stores or consumers, the products
move from distribution centers to
particular stores and then later
on consumers but there are several
questions that question marks right
like from a manufacturer to distribution
center how many products do we stock
up in the distribution center, right?
So as we talked about like we
have hundreds and thousands of
products and we need to allocate
the space in the distribution
center According to according to the
demand because the space is limited.
We don't have unlimited space.
So we should be able to Understand
how much space is required in the
distribution center and then we need to
know You How big of a transport that's
required and how frequently the transport
vehicle should go from a distribution
center to a store and how many products
should be stocked up in a store, right?
Like as a consumer, you don't
want to go into a store and then
the store associate telling you
that, Hey, we have the product,
but it's in a distribution center.
I'll get it to you in a while.
These days, people expect, deliveries
and products on the same day.
I'm sure like in the U.
S., Amazon has same day deliveries.
Most of the e commerce giants are
trying for same day delivery, two hour
delivery, three hour delivery, and so on.
And in places like India, there's
even 10 minute delivery, right?
So we expect products to arrive.
As quick as possible.
So for that if we as retailers
need to Anticipate customer
demand, and then act accordingly.
But the problem comes because when
we, when the products move from
manufacturers to consumers, these demands
need to be anticipated in advance.
For example, like, we need to know
that, let's say, six months or one
year in advance that the customers
might need, in this area might need
10, 000 units of a particular jacket
because that's a demand, right?
So Anticipation is crucial here
because the same thing if consumers
get happy unhappy They might leave
you for another retailers and and
they will look for products elsewhere.
Then they're not going to wait correct.
So in summary, There are so many
missing questions and missing, variables
that could affect, different pieces.
So, it's, it's, I would say there's
like tons of variables, right?
Like, like even, later I'll
get into the challenges, right?
Like COVID and things like those will
shut down these retail value chain,
which would cause issues, but consumers
still want, products and stuff.
Right.
So that's why we need forecasting
and forecasting at several grains,
and several horizons and make
for making, different decisions.
Correct.
So if you look at the landscape,
right, the retail landscape
and forecasting, need.
There is long manufacturing
lead times, right?
Like, imagine that you're coming
up with a new product, there is
a product design that's involved.
And then once the product is designed
and then you send it to the manufacturing
facility, let's say if it's in China,
and then, you enter a contract and
then, the products get manufactured
and then they need to be shipped.
So it takes a long time.
So it's, companies probably are, are
probably, you know, discussing about
what product might come out, let's say
one year or two years or even three
years and four years from now, right?
So you need, you need forecasting.
And another thing is consumers are
complex, especially, consumers as
in, the day to day, uses, right?
The retail users, people change, like,
especially in this world, like you're
all influenced by, social media trends
and, and advertisements and so on, right?
Like a celebrity wearing a
particular, a jacket would shoot up
the demand for a particular jacket.
But these are, these are, but
these are, unexpected demands.
but still like the point is their
behaviors and preferences change
depending on a lot of, lot of, factors.
Right.
And another thing is with with a lot
of retailers becoming omnichannel, like
blending online, in store and hybrid
experiences, it's, it's tougher, right?
Like there are so many retailers
offering order online and pick up in
store and as well as hey, go to the
store and place the order in the store.
So.
it's getting complex because, back
in those days, the retailers used
to estimate the traffic, a mall
traffic, and like, it was a traffic
based, systems and traffic used to
be a great input for the transactions
and essentially revenue and sales.
But these days that traffic could be,
could lead to no transactions and they
could go into a store and place an
order, or they could go into a store
and then look up their phone and then.
place an order from the phone and then,
then, that would, you know, throw away
the projections of the roof, right?
And retailers need a real time inventory
optimization for so and so reasons
because things change rapidly and also
right like competition is a big factor.
with let's say Amazon for instance are
are running prime day they every every
retailer has their own one or two days of
high discount high promotion events and
then that would You know, lead to, loss of
sales or maybe like, competition, taking
away market share and things like those.
So we need better decision
making tools considering the
competition in mind as well.
So forecasting is, is extremely
critical, because they can
act as so many things, right?
Like controlling costs, like we don't
want to like, let's say, build up a
lot of inventory in our, warehouse
and take up space where we could,
might as well like, Stock up on
profit maximizing products, right?
So forecasting is a very, very,
very critical competence for all
the retailers for maximizing sales,
maximizing profits, and so on.
So now let's look at, forecasting
challenges, like why it's hard and
why do we need different, scalable
and ever evolving forecasting systems.
so I'm not going to go into
all the challenges here.
I'm going to touch up on and
give a sense of two main aspects,
with respect to, the forecasting.
So
let's say, so I'm going
to look at horizon, right?
So horizon is nothing but, how long
into the future are we looking at?
let's say, if you're talking about,
I don't know, one to two, three
weeks, like what sort of decisions
are the companies making, right?
So let's say three weeks, like generally,
generally those decisions are around.
Store replenishment, sales and operations,
execution, smooth delivery, distribution
center replenishment, inventory
allocation, end of season, clearance,
seasonal promotions, and so on, right?
So these are very short term decisions
that, that the, store managers and,
Location planners or inventory specialist
or supply chain planners make to ensure
that, the products get sold, the targets
are met, inventory is sold out and so on.
And, and the other one is, is around,
like, let's say, 3 to 12 weeks.
That's, we are talking about somewhere
around, 3 weeks to, close to three
months mark a quarter, right?
So here the decisions would be mostly
around workforce optimization capacity
management And sales and operation
execution smooth delivery flows
distribution center replenishment
and inventory allocation, right?
so in these even there are a lot
of overlaps because the forecast
generally, gets more and more
accurate, as we go closer, right?
So it's easier to predict whether it
will rain three hours from now or even
tomorrow than one month from now, right?
Because a lot of things are
not in our control and it's
harder to make predictions.
especially when, like, there
are so many things driving the
demand as well as the supply.
And at a three to 24 months mark,
it's then it's a different ball game.
Like we are moving a bit about from day to
day operations to a high level strategic
planning and things like those, right?
So we talk about like, at this
this A quarter out to let's
say to up to a two year mark.
It's mostly about assortment planning like
what sort of assortments do we need to put
in a particular store as well as not just
store at a at a company level right let's
say I don't know like a Milk company,
let's say they will have not just milk.
They will have dairy
based products, right?
So What what should be the optimal
allocation of budget funds to create let's
say an assortment of 50 products so that
and as well as the units to like Maximize
profits maximize sale and also meet
the demand of all the consumers, right?
So and space optimizations like
as I talked about before You the
retailers have limited space,
at a given point in time, right?
So, they need to ensure, ensure
which products get what space.
And so they need to, or if there's a
new product development, a new product
coming, they need to make sure that they
need a lot of space and, and, and so on.
Right.
So.
And also a long lead
time purchasing, right?
So companies usually like enter
contracts with manufacturers and and
Shipping partners way in advance.
It could be as it could be long time
more than 24 months as well, but like
generally they enter into agreement
based on the price that's that's being
realized based on the future oil prices
based on transportation costs based on
manufacturing cost based on product cost
based on material planning and so on
right and also like sales and operation
planning Like do we have enough workforce?
to to function to to Drive, let's
say store operations or it could
be corporate workforce or it
could be planners and so on right?
And anything beyond 24 months Or even
up, it could be, depending on the
retailers could be like three years,
but usually most of the retailers,
99 percent of the retailers have
like a, two, two years cycle, with
respect to, long horizon planning.
so, but Anything beyond 24 months,
even that's possible, right?
Like companies are making five year, 10
year or even 20 year, strategic, planning.
So companies still want to know
what happens beyond the scale and
to make strategic decisions on which
directions to go and also to influence
product design and development.
product design and development,
decisions as well as to enter into
contractual obligations so that,
the retailers can make profit.
Like if you think some materials price
is going to go up by, let's say 50%, it's
better to lock in that contract right
now to get it at a much cheaper price.
So things like those, those are strategic
decisions, that, that could be made.
So every Decision is, is, should be
happening at a very different time.
So that means, let's say there's
something like a demand forecasting
system, and this, based on the use
case, like, based on the teams, for
instance, the, all the, use cases that
we are seeing on the screen is handled
by different departments, like, for
instance, product design and development,
versus, let's say, assortment planning.
These are all different Teams,
so these teams would need inputs
at different points in time.
So let's say, something like one to three
weeks, the teams requiring these short
term forecasts expect a very high level
of accuracy, and they might, require it
at a very, very, very small granularity.
Let's say they would get and download,
okay, this particular SKU of milk,
what is its, I don't know, sales
or demand or, or anything, right?
So there, they track a lot of,
inputs, like could be sales.
It could be transactions.
It could be, even stock outs, right?
Prediction stock outs.
So versus let's say, when we get into
like strategic planning and product
design, it could be on a high level,
like, okay, maybe the grocery chain
or, or even like a dairy, what is it?
This or milk as a whole like, okay, how
many gallons of milk or it could be at
a very high level as well Right, so it's
different every forecasting use case is
different and sometimes we are forecasting
for the same thing, but depending on
the team different, granularities are
required to ensure that the customer
experience is elevated, the the Issues
are solved at different, points in time.
So that's, that's, about horizon.
but there are so many other
challenges as well, right?
Like, as I said before, forecasting
at a SKU level or a store or a region
or a channel level, like for instance,
Walmart has both, e commerce store
and they also have physical stores.
And so these are
different, like, so maybe.
for the same product, we
need channel level sales.
It could be, let's say a
region level, forecast.
So these are all, and they
are all interconnected.
They're all hierarchical problems, right?
Like, let's say if the, the, any, retailer
has like thousands of stores and then,
Every state has let's say 50 stores
and then the sum of all these store
forecasts must align with the state level
forecast and as well as region level
forecast and then Ultimately country
level and then global level, right?
So That's challenging to make
it work, as well as, short
term versus long term, right?
Like immediate was a strategic decision.
So immediate is more around, yes,
we need to add a high granularity
and like the accuracy needs to be
precise to make that final step in the
process, as perfect as possible because
it, it, it has the highest impact.
I'm not saying the other one that
does not have an highest impact,
but still has a very high impact
making, like, some mistakes in, in
that level of the value chain can
cost, a lot for, for the retailers.
And, another thing is, since
retailers operate on both e commerce
and the store level, the data can
come from, several sources, right?
Like, POS data might come from the POS
systems involved, installed on the stores.
And these are physical systems.
So there could be issues
with the physical system.
That's a different story.
Like sometimes the store won't
work, like some PO systems won't
work and they might be faulty.
Or, so then, then the other case of, yeah,
we have POS systems and then, some people
make purchases online with credit cards.
Some people use cash So we don't have
information about cash payment, but
if you pay with a credit card you have
you get much more information about
the consumers and so on so That's
data fragmentation and then there is
an issue of Demand volatility, right?
That's that's a tougher problem to handle.
people people's intentions their purchase
behavior customer behavior changes
because of Several reasons we cannot
predict all of them, but we can kind
of look at the patterns and and Predict
their behaviors and predict the demand
based on or with some volatility and
variance, of course You on the on the
sales demand and other other metrics
that retailers care about right and also
There's a big trade off between accuracy
and operational efficiency we can always
work with High complex systems to, create
highly accurate forecast, but sometimes
training them generating forecast might
take a huge hit on operational efficiency.
one thing that I want to touch upon
has the impact of COVID 19, not just
with respect to impact of COVID 19.
the reason why I brought this
up is because, is to show
that, Such things can happen.
Unexpected things can happen in
the world of, retailers, right?
Like it's, it has been a wake up call
on being resilient on, such events.
And for instance, when COVID hit,
the retailers had to make a lot of,
a lot of, store level and like other
changes like safe shopping and six
feet distance and mask providing hand
sanitizer offering, touchless payments
and, and so free mask and like, yeah,
ensuring some people, some retailers
even like, install temperature control
systems in front of the retailer stores
to ensure safety for their customers.
Right.
And also people started working
from home a lot and they
started staying at home a lot.
So they were shopping Online a lot.
So the consumer behavior changed they
were looking for And the retailers started
facing challenges with respect to some
products might look good on a screen now
the products are our product visibility
depend is dependent on how it looks on a
particular smartphone or whether people
are shopping on a iPhone versus android
or is it on a laptop or I don't know right
like and also a lot of sharing like if you
purchase something online you tend to like
Ask somebody close to you or or you're
going to share it with a friend and so on.
So Tons of consumer behavior change
happened during, the pandemic,
as well as there was a lot of
supply chain disruptions, right?
Like when, in the pandemic started in,
in Wuhan in China, a lot of factories,
manufacturing factories were based
out of Wuhan and that caused them to
shut down these, factories and it was
affecting the inventory management.
Like, they couldn't
manufacture a lot of things.
So.
Even though there was demand
the supply was going down supply
was Just what is available in?
warehouses or whatever
is there in transit?
So there was a lot of shortages for a lot
of items and it cost the prices to shoot
up Costing inflation and so on right?
So even now, there is an influence of
COVID 19 on forecasting systems with
respect to data handling and like, like
having a different consumer behaviors.
A lot of retailers have to, you know,
rethink their forecasting systems.
And it actually, you know, thought
about, brought in a change with respect
to having, resilient and flexible
forecasting systems in the industry.
So, how do we forecast these
demand and the metrics that
are key for retailers, right?
So, on a high level, there are three
classes of, actually, three classes I'm
going to talk about, which is, these
are the most common, but there are more.
First, we have statistical models, right?
Which includes methods like,
ARIMA or exponential smoothing.
And these models work really well
for, detecting simple trends,
seasonality, and stability.
develop stable environments, but
they struggle a lot with rapid and
complex shifts in the data because
they rely a lot on historical
data and linear patterns, right?
Next, we have machine learning models.
Unlike statistical models, these are data
driven and they can capture nonlinear
relationships between variables.
we can also incorporate external
factors such as weather, promotions,
even competitive behaviors, into the
forecast, and that makes it, more robust
compared to statistical models, right?
Then we have deep learning models,
specifically neural networks
like RNN, LSTMs, and so on.
These models are particularly
effective, for time series forecasting
in complex and dynamic environments.
I mean, they can process vast
amount of data and find hidden
patterns that other, models can't.
but, one caveat here is as we go for more
complex models, like deep learning models.
We need more and more data, right?
Like, if you have only let's say
50 data points deep learning models
might not be The right approach even
a statistic statistical models or a
simple models might even naive models
could perform better than deep learning
models just something to keep in mind.
So talking about statistical
Forecasting techniques and there are
many i'm just i'm going to touch upon.
the to common and most popular ones
that's, being used in the industry,
which is the ARIMA, which stands
for autoregressive integrated moving
average for time series forecasting.
And then there are, different flavors
of exponential smoothing that is, right
for detecting trends and seasonality.
so there is the exponential
smoothing is in different kinds.
They can be a simple exponential
model to like seasonal ones
like holds winter and so on.
but they're extremely useful in
detecting trends and seasonality.
we could also be using
regression analysis to understand
relationship between variables.
just, so I've seen people using regression
analysis for forecasting as well, like.
it needs to be carefully examined
because of the assumptions
of the regression analysis.
So the, these models are simple,
interpretable, and they're really
good for relatively stable demand.
one of the problem here is, in highly
volatile or nonlinear environment,
they may not be the best choice.
then comes the data science and
machine learning techniques.
Moving beyond traditional
statistics, data science and machine
learning have transformed how we
approach forecasting in retail.
Machine learning models such as let's
say decision tree, random forest,
and gradient boosting can process
enormous amount of data and make
sense of complex non linear patterns.
So one of the key advantages of machine
learning is its ability to handle large
data sets, incorporate multiple variables,
including external factors like promotion,
weather, or even social media trends.
for instance, a machine learning
model might predict increased
demand for a product if it detects
a sudden surge in online searches
or social media mention, right?
Machine learning models are also
adaptive, unlike statistical models
that rely on predefined rules.
Machine learning models learn and
adjust as new data becomes available.
This means that they can quickly
detect shifts in consumer behaviors
and adjust forecasts accordingly.
one example is, how some retailers use
machine learning to predict the success of
a new product, product launch by analyzing
social media trends, historical sales
data, or even, influencer mentions, right?
this was an interesting case
study by one of the retailers.
However, there are trade offs.
machine learning Models, require more
data than statistical models, and also
they require greater computational
power compared to traditional methods.
And they're highly flexible, but at
the same time they're also more complex
and harder to interpret, especially
when, it comes to understanding
why the model made up data.
A specific, prediction, right?
There are explainable models as
well, but like, they're all, they're
all still considered black box.
We can, make, explain, the model,
features at a high level, but still
the, stakeholders and the business,
folks who make operational decisions,
still don't understand at the core.
And there's a trust issue when it
comes to machine learning models.
And these things need to be carefully
implemented, when productionizing.
The other class of model
is deep learning models.
I've mentioned two of them, there
are different others as well, but,
RNNs, for time series data, like if
you have sequential patterns, RNNs,
RNNs picks it up very well, same
thing, LSTM networks specifically, for
capturing long term dependencies, right?
So, like even, even, so if you.
model, like even like they can capture
like external, what do you call it?
factors as well, like events,
promotions and so on, along with
capturing the sequence based, patterns.
and they are usually really
good for long term forecasting.
and what I've seen is like a retailer
could use LSTM model to predict
for a new product category over the
next 12 months, taking into account
sales, data, competitor, competitor
actions, and even economic trends.
however, deep learning models
comes at a very high cost.
They have very high training times,
complexity, and they require significant
amount of data, computational
resources, making them more suitable
for larger retailers with big data sets.
One of the bigger drawback, according
to me, is they can be challenging to
interpret as their decision making
process is often seen as a black box
compared to more transparent methods
like regression or statistical methods.
So this is a few tips on, implementing,
time series models, in the industry
or for specifically your, use case.
this is very, extremely critical, right.
On, on trying to understand which
models to start with, right.
In the first place, I've seen like
people jumping right into, complex
models, but, they don't achieve the
results that you're looking for.
Right.
So, according to me, these findings.
Super important starting with EDA.
EDA is extremely important to
Understanding the task and exploring
your data It is crucial to first conduct
EDA to get a sense of data's patterns
trends and outliers This ensures that
you're not missing any key insights and
helps you verify that you're solving the
right problem with the correct approach.
It also solves a bunch of other
issues like, Oh, looking at the data
quality and like getting ideas for
your forecasting problems and so on.
Also check for gaps and
stationarity in the time series.
Time series models often require
stationarity and gaps in the data can
seriously disrupt forecasting accuracy.
Addressing these issues early
on will save you trouble later.
Now if you're talking about
evaluation, select the right
evaluation metrics for your problem.
Depending on your goals, you might use
MAPE, WMAPE, or any other metrics, but,
don't forget to use simple benchmarks
like Naive Forecasting set a baseline.
If your advanced models can't beat
this, there is something wrong, right?
And when it comes to models, start
simple, avoid diving straight into
deep learning or LSTM unless you have
plenty of data, simpler models can often
be more effective and interpretable,
especially when data is limited, right?
And another thing is
about interpretability.
It is extremely essential
to know your models, right?
You should be able to explain why
you selected a particular model and
understand how it works under the hood
If you can't justify your choice, it is
it's a sign that something's off, right?
there are many other aspects you need
to consider while implementing such
a system forecasting systems, but
Generally, i've seen people making
mistakes with respect to these right, so
Next, let's quickly go over some case
studies on like some practical ways.
Some retailers have
Fixed used forecasting to solve some
real world challenges The I don't
have specifics on how they on certain
aspects certain details, but like
this will give an overview about
how Companies are using it, right?
So in this case study, we are looking
at a global retailer with over 10,
000 stores across different regions.
Their primary challenge was frequent
stockouts, especially during peak seasons.
This led to lost sales, customer
dissatisfaction, and inefficiency
in managing supply chains.
The company's incident
management was largely reactive.
Whenever stock odds occurred, the
supply chain team had to rush to
make last minute replenishments
with significantly increased costs.
To address this, the retailer
implemented a machine learning
based demand forecasting system.
This model didn't just rely on historical
sales data, but also incorporated External
factors like weather, regional events,
to predict demand more accurately.
they saw, due to this, they
saw a 30 percent reduction in
stockouts during peak seasons.
And they also managed to cut down
on emergency logistics by 25%,
leading to more cost effective
replenishment of the inventory, right?
Most importantly, the incident
management process shifted from
being reactive to proactive.
instead of waiting for stockouts to
occur, the forecasting model provided
early warnings so that they could address
the issue before it impacted the store.
This not only reduced the operational
stress, but also improved customer
satisfaction as products were
consistently available when needed.
This is a great example of, of how.
proactive incident management can
lead to, extremely, well balanced
and, highly efficient, system
and how it can lead to customer,
improvement in customer experience.
Right.
the next one is around, QSR chain, QSR
stands for, Quick service restaurants
like fast food restaurants like
McDonald's and KFC and and so on right?
So their main challenge was supply
chain disruptions which led to
ingredient shortages And, and it
caused major service delays when, let's
say, certain ingredients, ran out.
Customers were unhappy because
popular menu items weren't available.
Like, imagine eating a, a
burger when, without lettuce.
I mean, they won't sell it, but
still, like, if the lettuce was,
not available, the companies or
the stores couldn't make the, such
products involving lettuce, right?
So even, same thing, their incident
management team was mostly reactive
and constantly responding to these
disruptions rather than preventing them.
This resulted in higher costs
and more importantly, a negative
impact on the customer experience.
And later the QSR chain introduced
AI driven demand forecasting models.
The model analyzed a wide range of
data, historical sales, weather, And
eventually they were able to achieve
20 percent shortage in ingredient,
in ingredient shortages, right?
And the forecasting model allowed
the chain to plan ahead, ensure
that supplies are delivered on
time in the right quantities.
and the forecasting system helped,
reduce the food wastage by 15 percent
as they could better align this,
supply with actual demand, right?
So this is a move towards achieving
sustainability goals as well.
So as a result, their incident
management became proactive with
better supplier coordination.
So this is how you can at several
companies, are using forecasting to
drive, customer experience and reduce.
become more reactive, become
more proactive, supply chain
and develop proactive incident
management systems, right?
Now what's up, about the future for,
forecasting in the retail world?
There are several key trends.
we see an increasing use of IOT
data for real time inventory
tracking and management.
Right.
So these are more data coming in at
a very high pace, which will help
us, make more, real time decisions.
And then, there's another, trend
that's being seen in the industry,
which is to incorporate social media
and external data for demand sensing.
when talking about external data, there
are data from events, like, let's say
a concert or, or sports events and so
on, as well as, with a lot of consumers
being online, we have more and more
data about their presence, their
shopping habits, their trends and so on.
So companies have started,
incorporating such things into,
into the demand sensing systems.
Then, predictive analytics
for customer personalization
and marketing optimization.
it's self explanatory.
like we see, all the e commerce
and like shopping websites giving
us personalized recommendations,
sending marketing emails, and so on.
also there's a lot of,
ethical, aspects, right?
because we Retailers, retailers collect
a lot of data, like when you enter
your, there's your payment information.
There is, yes, transactions,
your, your interest.
So over a period of time, the companies
have a huge, huge, huge, data, And
they know a lot about you, right?
They collect data and they see the
trends and they have millions of
such customers online for these
big retailers and they know what
you like and what you don't like.
And some countries, some regions,
they have their own privacy
rules and data rules and so on.
So that's, having an impact these days and
companies are getting more, taking more
actions on their ethical friends as well.
So now also.
A lot of companies have achieved this the
fully automated demand sensing forecasting
systems driven by AI there's a huge trend
right now with llms generative ai and
personally in the industry I think it
would be a great great Tool, you know to
synthesize a lot of natural language with
respect to let's say Forums social media
forums and like social media data and
text data and synthesize that As, features
into the demand sensing models to, capture
those peak peaks in the demand, right?
So,
and as I said, like, there's a lot of
uncertainty volatility, with respect
to retail and retailers must adopt, AI
powered models to remain competitive.
That's that's that's
there's no doubt about that.
The forecasting has come a long way,
but there is a need for continuous
innovation right So demand forecasting
cannot just rely on traditional
statistics with customer preferences and
marketing conditions shifting so rapidly.
the businesses need models that can
learn, adapt, predict in real time.
And Then this means that they need
to invest in scalable forecasting
systems that are capable of
processing large data sets quickly
and generating accurate predictions.
the other key point is collaboration.
retailers need to work closely with
data scientists and technology providers
to ensure their forecasting models are
not only accurate, but also flexible
enough to respond to new challenges.
The complexity of today's retail
environment, means that no single team or
department can tackle these issues alone.
One example of, continuous, innovation,
is, is, with the Retailer X.
I mean they have a I powered forecasting
system that predicts the demand for
products to individual store location by
integrating multiple sources including
store traffic weather online behavior so
they can this retailer can predict the
demand shifts in real time and adjust
their inventory accordingly like even at
a Weekly or like one week cadence, right?
So ultimately the future of retail
depends on mastering predictive
analytics for short term and long
term gains so those who can harness
the power of AI and machine learning
to forecast demand accurately, will
not only enhance their operational
efficiency, but also gain a critical
competitive advantage in this ever
changing and ever evolving market, right?
So, so, so we, we talked about how, we
talked about the retail value chain and
we talked about how there could be a
lot of incidents, in the retail value
chain that could disrupt the businesses.
so it, we, we went through how
forecasting, can, you know, help,
fix those issues and improve customer
experience and just building, smart,
resilient, robust, supply chain systems,
supply chain businesses, operations
to improve customer experience.
Right.
So there's a lot, Of topics covered
today, and some of them are very
high level, some of them, I try
to go as in depth as possible.
but if you have any questions or
a feedback, for this particular
talk, please feel free to reach
out to me on, on my email.
you can also reach out to me on
LinkedIn, if you can find me there.
but I'll try to respond as soon as
possible and I enjoyed presenting it
here, and thank you so much everyone.