Hi everyone.
I'm RA Herra, and today I'm sharing
a real world case study on building
silent cross cloud analytics
pipeline with Azure Databricks
with more than 10 TB daily scale.
You'll hear exactly how we combined
SRE discipline with Delta Lake
optimizations to keep strict SLAs
while making performance predictable
and keeping the costs sane.
For context, I think billions of
events per day, multi-region ingestion
and user facing dashboards that
must stay fresh within minutes.
So here's the flow for
the next 12 to 15 minutes.
So the first I'll discuss the architecture
and where the cross cloud seam are.
And second the reliability
engineering we enforced.
Third, the performance work,
especially Delta Lake and Sea order.
Fourth, our incident
playbook and how we shrank.
MTTR.
And finally a practical
blueprint too that you can adopt.
And I anchor each section with
the concrete thresholds and
examples so you can relate to them.
So our challenge was ad
campaign in telemetry in
double digit terabytes per day.
So with many interdependent e ETLs,
a single upstream blip could cascade.
The business expectations were blunt.
So real time dashboards, historical
trends in minutes, cross cloud consistency
without wasteful duplication and
predictable performance, even when the
load is spikey without blowing the budget.
And we set the working target of P 95,
freshness less than 15 minutes, and P 99,
less than 30 minutes with back pressure
rules when the, these numbers drift.
So we deliberately cross clouded not to
use everything but to pick the best pieces
and define hard contracts at the seams.
Three principles guided US one, data
locality and replication across regions
and providers for HADR and latency.
R-D-R-R-P-O, targeted single digit
minutes and RTO under one hand.
So two standardized APIs and oss.
So Spark or delta are lingo, franca,
and provider perks are hidden.
And the third is unified absorbability.
One place to see metrics,
logs, and traces across clouds.
So detection and response are fast.
Every alert ties to an
explicit SLI and a runbook.
Concretely, our stack looked like this.
So we had Azure Databricks for spar, for
compute paired with Delta Lake for acid
se semantics, observe schema in evolution
and time travel and Azure data factory
orchestrated dependencies, retries,
and monitoring with jitter back offs.
Amazon S3 provided durable
versioning storage, where we needed
it for landing curated zones.
Around those.
We added reliability layer this
where like the circuit breakers, bulk
heads, and the boundary isolation.
So a cloud specific issue is.
On top a performance layer which
had this z order and partitioning
aligned to access, small file,
compaction, dynamic allocation.
And finally, an operational layer run
where we had the run books, automated
remediation and blameless reviews.
Every handoff writes checkpoints, and the
stage can resume without rep reprocessing.
And we ran this like a product using SRE.
So we tracked SLIs on three things, the
freshness from the ingest to the gold
availability P 95, query latency for key
workloads and end-to-end success rate.
We set error budgets that triggered
graceful degradation for reliability
slip, for example, pausing non-critical
enrichments if the seven day rolling
P five freshness exceeded budget.
So post incident, blameless reviews,
drove sim, systematic fixes, and we
attacked toil first, like automating
the top recurring failure classes.
So humans are in babysitting pipeline.
Our goal was to keep auto
resolution above 70%.
To make failure safe, we standardized
four pipelines, patents, checkpointing, so
every stage can resume from known offsets.
Offsets are committed only after
item potent rights succeed.
Circuit breakers at integration points.
So we stop cascades when freshness
drifts and or dependency fail repeatedly.
For instance trip if error rate is
greater than 10% for five minutes,
or if the freshness breaches versus
for three cons consecutive checks.
Exponential back offs with jitters.
Retries do not create
stampedes and random jitters.
Were up to three seconds.
And item put in write offs.
Replace never corrupt state.
All mergers are key and we
avoid side effects on retry.
In short, retrials only work when
your operations are at important.
And then performance was the other half.
Before tuning we had full
scans, big shuffles and spike
latencies, and we aligned storage
to actually access patterns.
Partitioning that prunes
for example by event date.
And the ordering on high
selectivity, keys used together.
Think campaign ID region and device time.
So we kept metadata lean with
optimize and small file compaction.
So spark wasn't drowning in tiny files.
The result, drastic input, output
reduction and complex queries dropping two
minutes or even seconds with stable P 95.
And K hit rates improved and shuffle,
spill decreased meaningfully.
Practically, how did we choose C or keys?
We mined query logs to find the most
frequent multi column filters with
high cardinality and low overlap.
We validated with A or B runs and
representative workloads and revisited
keys quarterly because access patterns
shift with new features and dashboards.
And we also capsize the order frequency
to avoid consistent tree clustering.
So typically weekly for hot
tables, monthly for warm ones.
We also tackled cost without
sacrificing reliability.
We abandoned fixed clusters and
moved to workload aware auto-scaling.
Inputs included priority tire,
incoming volume q, depth SLA,
proximity utilization, and hard
costs guards like max nodes per tire.
That combination kept clusters
right sized cut, ideal burn
and preserved predictability.
The side effect far fewer capacity pages.
Engineers focused on data
quality and features.
When nearing an SLA breach, we
temporarily allele burst scaling,
then decay back to steady state.
Incidents still happen.
And our response lifecycle is five steps.
So we have detection is it is
S-L-A-S-L-I driven, freshness, drift,
and success rates not just the CPU
classification tag scope, and business
criticality and selects the runbook.
Containment trips, breakers diverse
traffic to last known good slices
and shred non-critical loads.
Reation kicks off self-healing re qing
item potent stages with jitter, retries,
compacts, small files if that's the cause.
And restart targeted tasks of whole jobs.
Recovery resumes from checkpoints and
passes a consistency validation gate like
the schema, row counts, and spot queries.
So before we lift any stale banners.
A concrete example.
So an AWS S3 cross Region Replication
Lag Freshness monitors flagged a
timestamp drift beyond budget, and
we paused drown stream joints served
the last consistent slice with a new.
Clear stale data banner and diver
diverted non critical workloads.
When replication recovered, we validated
consistency on B boundary tables
burst, scaled, or clear the backlog.
And return to steady state because
the playbook was predefined and
on call only approved steps.
Everything else was automated.
So the metrics we get about most
was MTTR, first time success
rate, P 95, query latency.
And auto resolution rate and freshness,
data quality, error rate, and overall
system uptime versus a 99.9% target.
Watching these together is
what lets you act proactively.
For example, a rising DQ error rate
pair with stable compute such as
sche drift, not capacity, a widening
P 95 with flat volume, such as.
Partitions queue or small file bloat.
So if you are adopting this
here's a practical blueprint.
So foundation that defined SLIs
and error budgets set up cost cloud
authentication, and build a unified
monitoring fabric and be explicit about
your consistency model when is slightly
stale, acceptable, and for how long?
And then for reliability, put circuit
breakers at every integration scene.
Configure auto-scaling policies with
burst windows, and add checkpoints at
all handoffs and gate promotions to
gold through validation and schemas
row counts and sampling and freshness.
For performance tuned shuffles and
partitions implements that order from
real query patents enable dynamic
allocation and targeted occasion
only where hit rates justify and
schedule small file compaction.
With the thresholds, for example,
compact, when average file size is less
than 1 28 mb. And for operational codify
the runbooks, automate the top three
remediations, hold blameless reviews
with action items and drill cross stream
on two failures modes per quarter.
So my key takeaways are one, at
this scale, SRE is not optional.
It's the backbone two, automate
recovery to slash mttr and on-call ing.
Target more than half of the
incidents to be self healed.
Three, optimize for your access patterns.
So z order and storage, lay out
choices, deliver outside spins.
Verify with query logs, not intuition.
And four cross cloud only works with
intentional contracts at the seams.
That is how you prevent cascades
and keep costs predictable.
So thank you for listening.
And in q and a I'm happy to unpack
how we picked the order keys from
query logs and extract freshness, sli
thresholds we used and why, and or
the conditions that trip or circuit
breakers, including the grace periods
and histories that prevent flapping.
Thank you.