Hello everyone, this is Vishal Khadi.
Thank you for being here today.
In this session, we will explore
transformative NLP in how
we interact with technology.
Let's dive in.
today's talk, we'll cover
five major sections.
First, an introduction to what
NLP is and why it matters.
Next, we will discuss some key
NLP techniques such as sentiment
analysis, language generation, and
name entity recognition or NER.
Following that, we will look at real
world applications where NLP has made
a significant impact as well as the
major challenges it still Finally,
we will wrap up with a look at the
future of NLP and what lies ahead.
Now, let's start with the basics.
Natural language processing lies at the
intersection of artificial intelligence,
linguistics, and cognitive psychology.
Its primary aim is to enable computers
to understand, interpret, and generate
human language in a meaningful way.
NLP compasses a variety of tasks
from speech recognition, text
analysis to sentiment analysis
and language translation.
It plays a crucial role in bridging the
communication gap between humans and
machines, allowing for more intuitive
and effective interactions across
various applications such as virtual
assistant and automated customer support.
As we go forward, I will explain
some of the key techniques
that enable NLP to work.
To function effectively, explore some
core techniques that make NLP work.
The first is sentiment analysis, which
involves detecting the emotional tone
behind a piece of text to classify
it as positive, negative, or neutral.
It's widely used in customer
service, social media
monitoring, and market research.
Next, we have language generation.
This technique enables computers
to produce human like text.
Advanced models such as GPT 3, GPT 4 are
capable of generating responses that are
contextually relevant and making them
useful for applications like chatbots.
content creation, and
even creative writing.
Lastly, name entity recognition,
or NER, identifies and categorizes
specific entities such as names,
locations, and dates within a text.
This technique is essential for
tasks like information extraction and
enhancing search engine responses.
Now let's look more closely
at each technique, starting
with the sentiment analysis.
Sentiment analysis is also known
as opinion mining, determines the
emotional tone behind a piece of text.
The process typically starts with
text preprocessing where the data
is cleaned and then standardized.
Next, features are extracted to identify
the key linguistic traits following by
classification using machine learning
or deep learning models such as BERT.
This method helps companies understand
customer sentiment in previews,
social media posts, and surveys.
It's a valuable tool for businesses
to gauge the public perception and
make the data driven decisions.
Let's move on to language generation.
Language generation allows machines
to produce human like text.
This is often achieved using models
based on transformer architectures,
such as GPD3, GPD4, which learn from
vast amount of text data to generate
meaningful and coherent responses.
Language generation has many
practical applications, including
chatbots, automated reporting,
summarizing the content.
It even extends into creative
fields, where AI assists in writing
stories, scripts, and poetry.
While generating core text is a challenge,
ongoing advancements are continuously
pushing the boundaries of what's possible.
Now let's discuss named
entity recognition.
Named entity recognition or NER focuses on
identifying entities within a text such as
people, places, organizations, and dates.
NER can be implemented using
rule based approaches, machine
learning models, or deep learning
techniques linked by LSTM networks.
It's a powerful tool for automating
the task, such as extracting relevant
information from large data sets or
improving the accuracy of search engines.
For instance, NER enables better query
understanding by identifying keywords
and categorizing them appropriately.
Now let's look at how NLP impacts
the real world applications.
NLP has made a significant
impact in various industries.
Virtual assistants like Siri and Alexa
use NLP for voice recognition and
generating context based responses.
Translation services such as
Google Translate utilize NLP for
accurate real time translations.
In healthcare, NLP helps analyze
critical notes, adding in diagnosis
and treatment recommendations.
And in finance, sentiment analysis
is used to understand market trends
and inform trading decisions.
These are just a few examples that
highlight NLP's potential to transform
industries and improve efficiency.
However, there are still significant
challenges to address, which we
will see in the coming slides.
So NLP faces several hurdles.
such as language ambiguity
is a major issue.
As the meaning of the word can
change based on the context, this
makes it difficult for machines to
accurately interpret certain phrases.
There is also the challenge of
multi lingual processing, especially
for low resource languages that
lack large data sets for training.
Moreover, ethical issues like bias
in language models and privacy
concerns must be addressed to ensure
fairness and responsible use of NLP.
Navigating these challenges is
essential for developing reliable
and transparent NLP systems.
As we look ahead, let's discuss
where the future of NLP is heading.
The future of NLP holds
many exciting prospects.
Model efficiency will be a major focus
with efforts to make models smaller and
faster while maintaining high accuracy.
This is often referred to as green AI.
NLP models are also expanding
into multilevel integration.
Combining text and visual and
audio data to create a feature
more nuanced understanding.
For instance, this could improve the
content analysis by analyzing the text
and images and the audio all together.
Common sense reasoning is another area
where NLP is evolving, aiming to make
models more capable of understanding
everyday scenarios like humans.
Additionally, there is a growing
focus on making NLP models more
explainable and transferable.
These advancements.
We'll continue to push the boundaries
of what NLP can achieve, enabling
even more seamless and intelligent
human computer interactions.
Now we come to the conclusion part of it.
In conclusion, NLP is revolutionizing
the way humans interact with the
machines, making these interactions
more natural and effective.
From sentiment analysis to language
generation and NER, we have covered
the core techniques that power
modern NLP systems, while there
are still challenges to overcome.
The future looks promising with new
advancements in model efficiency,
multi bottom capabilities, which
are paying the way for the future.
Thank you for your time and I look
forward to the questions you may have.