Hi, everyone.
I am Arun Kumar Dutta.
Currently, I'm working as an
associate director in LTI Mindtree.
Welcome to Incident Management
2024 powered by Conf42.
Today, I will be talking about
sustainability with performance
and resiliency testing.
Let me share my screen.
from agenda perspective, today I will
talk about sustainability and then I
will talk about what is carbon footprint.
Then we'll talk about Why sustainability
is so important to information
technology And then I'll talk about
sustainability with performance
and resiliency testing as I am a
performance tester by profession, right?
And then I'll talk about how
performance and resiliency testing
In with web performance optimizations
assist in sustainability.
Lastly, I will discuss on how
performance and resiliency testing
assist to improve sustainability
post digital transformation.
Before I start, let me introduce myself.
I have been into industry for
last 19 years doing performance
and resiliency testing.
I have almost 22 plus testing conferences,
12 plus of global webinars, and
72 plus of blog articles have been
published, and most of them are into
performance and resiliency testing field.
Also received many global
and organizational awards.
Let's understand what is sustainability.
Sustainability is nothing but meeting
our own needs without affecting
the future generation needs.
Yes, we all have to think
about our future generations.
Sustainability is not just
the environment, but also
it has other dimensions.
Like sustainability has three pillars.
environment, economy and society.
Sustainability assist
in many different ways.
You talked about creating a healthier
environment, you talked about
energy consumption, you talked
about employment, economy, you
talked about, good public health.
All this comes from the sustainability.
Sustainability helps in creating
a better future for all of us.
And we have all have to remember.
Sustainability is not a single person job.
It is everyone responsibility.
All of us has a role
To for sustainability.
No matter what do we do or
what background we came from.
I
will say like time has already come.
and we all need to think about if
you are not already started, right?
That about the sustainability and reducing
the carbon put free into the society.
And this will lead to a
better, sustainable environment
for our future generations.
So as I talking about reduce your
carbon footprint, let's understand
what is carbon footprint, right?
Carbon footprint is the total
amount of greenhouse gases that
are created by all of our actions.
So when I say greenhouse gases, I
was meaning mostly carbon dioxide and
Methane gases, but there are some other
gases also in terms of the greenhouse.
If you like, ozone could be one, nitrous
oxide could be one, or maybe hydro
fluorocarbons could be one or hydro
chlorofluorocarbons could be one, right?
So these all greenhouse gases are
actually not good for our society.
The more it gets emitted, the more
harmful to the society, right?
And people's products,
organizations, industry, everybody
is having a carbon footprint.
So we all have to think about it.
And your carbon footprint
includes all your daily actions.
Like how, what do you do in
your day to day life, right?
How you commute, what is the food
you take, what are the clothes that
you buy, you wear, the devices that
you use, everything you throw away.
All your daily actions.
Everything comes under
the carbon footprint.
So overall, what I'm trying to
say is that larger the carbon
footprint, the heavier it is for the
our society or environment, right?
So you all have to think about reducing
your carbon footprint and which is
better for our environment and it is
better for our future generations.
And if we all think about our daily action
in such a way that it is having a little
less carbon footprint, then eventually
it will be a huge, means it can create
a huge sustainable environment for us.
If we all start thinking about
in that direction, right?
Now sustainability is very important
to IT or our information technology
because we all people are from
belongs to the IT industry, right?
And if you closely look into the
information technology business, right?
We have Lot of servers, lot of server
forms, many devices, hundreds, thousands,
or even nowadays, like for iot cities,
like millions of devices, right?
And all these devices or servers or
server forms or whatever it is, right?
Basically it takes lot, tons,
or tons of resources, right?
And think about how much energy.
It requires to, to ensure all these
servers and devices are working, right?
And then think about the immense
greenhouse gases that are emitted
from those devices or servers.
And lastly, and most importantly, this
device generates a huge hit, especially
for the traditional data centers, right?
That they generate huge amount of heat.
So additional energy is required
to cool down those devices
or those equipments, right?
So overall it has a
massive sustainable impact.
And today, all people are
talking about it, right?
Internet is the biggest place for
the carbon footprint and it is
having the huge environmental impact.
Everybody is now connected
into the Internet, right?
And now, we are in an age where we are
not even talking about the only Internet.
We are talking about
the Internet of Things.
We are talking about AI.
We are talking about JAD GPT.
All these have a vast, sustainable impact.
And we have to think about it.
It is like a You cannot even
keep your keep silent, right?
You have to do something, right?
So what we have to do is the
organization and individual must think
about the sustainability to reduce
the carbon footprint to the society.
And we all it professionals
should work in such a way.
Think in such a way that we can make it as
sustainable or we can make it as green or
maybe like we can think about a green it.
And that's why we all
have to think about it.
If we had to think about
our future generations.
Now if you are new to this, sustainability
concept, I will recommend you guys to
go through, Two free courses, one by
Green Software Foundation and Linux
Foundation and one by Microsoft.
Green Software Foundation course is LFC
131 Green Software for Practitioners
and Microsoft course name is Principle
and Sustainable Software Engineering.
These are free courses,
but these are very good.
That means I personally went
through both the courses and it's
very, very well, um, documented.
I can say that way, right?
And still it's not the only two.
There are.
Plenty of other, free and paid courses.
You can go through that also.
There are a lot of blogs.
There are forums.
if you wanted to learn,
it is absolutely required.
you can go through those things.
Okay.
But what all we're trying to say, or
maybe what I'm trying to portray with
this particular slide is, We all I.
T.
Professionals would think about the green
ideas and we should, learn this concept.
We should play a role.
Maybe like I can say, like a active
role to reduce the carbon between to the
society and make this world a sustainable
places for our future generations.
Now let's talk about the, the,
how performance and resiliency is
actually related to sustainability.
So as I am a performance tester and
resilience tester by profession, I'm
always inclined towards seats and
knowingly or unknowingly, if you are
doing performance testing and conducting
resiliency testing, then basically
you are helping in sustainability.
Let's understand how, how, It
basically does in two ways.
First, Performance and resiliency
testing always helps in making the
applications or website faster, right?
The moment the applications of the
website is faster, it uses less
data to serve the request, right?
And eventually it generates
less Carbon to the environment.
So it actually helps
in reducing the carbon.
Okay.
On the second approach, it actually
performance and resiliency testing.
There are the other thought is
like, it always helps in optimizing
the server resources, right?
so if the server resources are
optimized, then it consume less
energy and which is better for our
sustainable perspective, right?
So both ways, performance and
resiliency testing helps in.
Right now, in a nutshell, what I'm
trying to say is like by conducting
continuous performance and resiliency
testing, carbon footprint will be reduced
and sustainability will be improved.
Now let's understand in both ways.
So yeah, either it could be your,
your data center is an on premises
or it could be in the cloud, right?
So if it is a on premises, traditional
data center does not have the
flexibility to scale up or down easily.
But it can always ensures optimal service
server resource utilization, right?
And how that will be done, that will
be done via conducting continuous
performance and resiliency testing.
In fact, there are other ways also,
you can think about optimized resource
driven, high availability concept
nowadays, application containerizations
are there, but ultimately all this
leads to reducing the carbon footprint.
That is what I'm trying to say.
Now, if you think about the cloud,
cloud itself is a sustainable.
And it is having a less carbon footprint.
It has the flexibility to
add or, not maybe reduce the
environment as and when required.
And it is shared by many teams.
and, the most important it
uses green and clean energy.
So all these are actually.
from a sustainability perspective and
what I will say like over the years,
last year, especially for the last few
years, we have seen many traditional data
centers are nowadays using green energy,
which is better for our environment.
So overall, our objective is to
minimize the wastage and optimize
the resources as much as possible
so that it can be more sustainable.
It can reduce the carbon footprint
to the And we all can do this by
doing or conducting continuous
performance and resiliency testing.
And in, in cloud, you can think about
the sustainable capacity planning.
So these are the ways you
can think about it, right?
Now I'll talk about one more thing, like
web performance optimization, right?
We performance people are very
much interested about it, right?
We always talked about the web performance
optimization and web performance
optimization actually helps in,
reducing the carbon footprint, right?
as I said in, last slide,
there are two ways it does, the
helps in sustainability, right?
the first one I said is if your
application is faster, it uses
less data to solve the request
and eventually it will, omit or
less carbon footprint, right?
So optimizing web pages or web
performance optimization is one such
activity, which can help into, using,
your application faster, right?
The moment.
So you can think about, web performance
optimization by both ways, like whether
it is a client side or a server side.
In the client side, you can think about,
you can think about reducing the initial
page load time or javascript that runs
behind the browser or maybe downloading
all the resources and many more, right?
There are a lot of other ways also you
can do in the in terms of server side,
there will be much more concept, right?
You can think about optimizing your
web servers, app server or DB server.
You can think about,
improving your DB queries.
You can think about, optimizing
your other application dependencies
or third party, components, right?
And there are a lot of best practices
also available, like you can think about,
caching, you can think about, content
delivery networks, you can think about
minification or maybe syncing your file
sizes, you can think about optimizing
your images, you can think about,
replication dependencies or optimizing
the most business critical web pages.
Which is in terms of your user loads
and maybe like the business function or
maybe like you can reduce the number of
resources in the web pages itself, right?
So all these are different ways to
reducing the overall page response time.
The moment your page response time is
It's less, it becomes faster, right?
And when your application is faster, it
emits less data, less carbon footprint
to the less carbon to the society, right?
which is better for
our environment, right?
web performance optimization is actually
helps in, reducing the carbon footprint.
Now, before I talked about the
post digital transformation, let
me tell you a different aspects of
performance and resiliency testing.
So while performance and resiliency
testing assist in sustainability,
however, too many performance testing
or too many resiliency testing leads
to a creates higher carbon footprint.
So let's say you can think about any
types of performance testing, whether
it's a load, whether it's a stress,
whether it's endurance, whether it's
a, capacity planning, or there is
a volume or maybe like whether it's
your game day testing or any kind of
resiliency testing scenarios, right?
All of these are actually driven by
higher workload and higher resource
utilization, because performance
testing does for that only.
Testing does for that only, right?
So it all leads to hired or
maybe like huge workload.
The moment it is having huge
load, that means it creates
a higher carbon footprint.
So too many performance testing
or too many resiliency testing
is also not good for the thing.
So you have to think about it.
You have to reduce the resiliency testing.
And I wrote LinkedIn article
on this specific topic.
Okay.
So organizations should
start thinking about it.
Now let's talk about the
digital transformation.
So while we in the terms of when we
are doing the digital transformation
more organized and moving towards the
cloud and then doing all this digital
transformation activity, their whole
objective was to optimum the performance
and optimum the utilizations, right?
So that they can make their end
user first happy and then by
doing that, they can also save.
Cost and ensuring the
sustainability, right?
But post digital transformation,
organizations are more interested in less
carbon footprint at every stages of SDLC.
Okay, software development, life
cycle activities and which leads to.
More cost savings, which leads to better
for our future generations, right?
But they are all doing it in post digital
transformation without comprising the
quality attributes, because quality
attributes still plays a major role
for post digital transformation.
So you have to think about it, right?
And the moment we are talking about the
sustainability aspect, with performance
and resiliency testing, Post digit and
I think the organization should think
about, maybe, at least 10, 10 points that
I have, wrote down in a form of a article.
so I'll come up with
those 10 points, right?
So first and foremost, Any unnecessary
or unplanned performance or resiliency
testing should be strictly avoided if
you are doing full blown and performance
testing and resiliency testing in a
very low scalable environment or your
hardware or software configuration
doesn't match with your live environment
then please do not do that performance
or resiliency testing it will not help
you in neither you are going to get the
correct performance test result which
you can compare or It is not helpful
for the sustainability perspective.
So both of these are not only helps
in reducing the carbon footprint,
but it also helps in efforts as well
as in cost because that conducting
performance and resiliency takes a
lot of efforts and cost as well as
now organization.
Should not conduct full blown
performance testing frequently
like the earlier days is right.
We used to do full blown performance
testing all the time, right?
So you are what I'm saying
is you should not avoid it.
But what I'm saying is you should
do it in periodically, right?
And also performance
environment should be smaller.
When you are not doing the full blown
performance testing, when you are doing
component level performance testing that
you do all the time, right component
level performance testing, you set
up a baseline, you set up a benchmark
for your component level performance
testing compared the when you have a new
release comes, you Compare the results
with that lower environment itself.
And if your lower environment doesn't
prove you it is good, then you know,
there's no point of going into a full
blown performance testing, right?
So basically, you are not only doing
big performance testing or full
blown performance testing list.
Your environment size
is also getting reduced.
So that is a practice
of green testing, right?
So that you can also think about, right?
And.
You do only full blown performance
testing as and when required,
required and for, periodically.
And it is not only helps in saving
the, the cost, but also in, in
terms of the sustainability.
And time duration of the performance
testing should be also less.
if you're running two hour load
test, try to run it for one hour.
If you are running a long
duration endurance test, think
about, people run it for.
16 to 24 hours, 48 hours
of endurance testing.
You do that, but you do that periodically.
And in, in terms of, if it has
to be done, many times, then you
think about doing it for hours.
So that will be leading to the less
carbon footprint to the society.
So I think the, The workload you
can even think about not always you
have to run with the peak workload.
You can run with your
average workload also.
So think those aspects.
And now the best part is if your test
duration, performance is duration
is reduced and your workload is
also to some extent reduced, you
don't have to create a huge set of.
Performance chase data, right?
So your performance chase data
activities will be also less, right?
So that will also help you in
terms of the, the reducing or
minimizing the carbon footprint.
In fact, when your workload is
reduced, your, load generator, count
the machine or maybe like the load
injector count will be less, right?
Load generator are load injectors are the
machines which generates the load, right?
the moment, you'll be having a less walk.
load or you are not running it
for longer duration, you can go
with only single machines, right?
On those cases, your overall carbon
footprint will be again reduced, right?
It actually helps him and try
to use a cloud load generator
because it will help him.
Rather than the traditional setup.
So that also helps to some
extent in sustainability, right?
So overall what i'm trying to say in
post digital transformation when you are
talking about performance and resiliency
testing you should think about a Overall
impact based, low volume, short duration,
specific goal oriented performance and
resiliency testing, which is not only
helpful in terms of the cost, which is
not only helpful for the organization
to get, or maybe like to ensure that end
users will be happy or maybe ensure end
user happiness and then, it will also
better for our sustainable environment.
You can also think about
conducting performance and
resiliency testing at off hours.
this will lead to a less
carbon footprint, right?
And even a green testing techniques
like optimizing the performance
test scenario will assist in
reducing the carbon footprint.
And if you are using the on premises, on
premises, then try to use your existing
hardware for a longer duration, right?
So this is basically the expanding
the hardware lifespans, right?
Which helps in, carbon footprint.
And if you are using it for a long
duration, your u waste will be also less.
So that is also good for
the perspective, right?
In fact, you can evaluate your
power consumption on the background
applications or the mobiles,
laptops, devices, servers, right?
And if you can actually possible,
you can minimize that, the bad,
those power consumption, right?
Which is another way of, doing
the, sustainability, right?
So and I'll also suggest organizers
would continuously look for reducing
the amount of data transfer.
So and then, the distance they work.
If they do that, their
web pages will be faster.
And then when their web page is
faster, their end users will be happy.
In fact, the organization can start
using the emulator instead of the real
devices, because we all always do a lot
of mobile performance testing, right?
On those cases, it is better to
use the emulator, which is having
the less carbon footprint rather
than using the real devices.
And if you are, no, if you wanted
to do the rewired devices, then you
must think about the device lifespan.
It has to be increased.
The moment it will be increased, it
will be better for the environment.
So overall, in post digital
transformation, organizations should be
conducting performance testing in, so they
had to do continuous performance testing,
but they had to think in a different way.
Now they have to do it in
test early and test only.
When it is required rather than earlier
days when you used to talk about test
always or test often I think that has been
changed in post digital transformation
that we all have to remember it
This is a blog that I was talking
about performance and resiliency
testing for improved sustainability
post digital transformation
The links are available.
There are a few other blogs articles
that i've already published Like
one of them is in euro star.
This one is a global testing
You retread from Agile testing.
these two are from Quality Matters
magazine, sustainable capacity planning
and application performance sustainability
with auto scaling and thought,
and then organization need to
be very serious when conducting
full blown performance testing.
That's the LinkedIn article
I was talking about.
And this was a very old article
I published in 2020 application
do not run fast in cloud with
continuous performance testing.
All links are available.
You can go through those, articles,
as and when you have time.