Hello everyone.
My name is Arvind Kumar Akola.
I work as a staff software
engineer in Guaranteed Rate.
Today my talk is about revolutionizing
incident management with cloud
computing and java technologies.
We will discuss on the introduction to
cloud computing and java technologies
and we will discuss about the challenges
with the traditional incident management
and also we'll see how cloud is taking
the advantage of this particular issue.
And how the synergy between Java and
cloud services, along with microservices,
serverless computing, CI CD integration
helps in incident management.
We'll also discuss about
real time monitoring tools.
We'll see how we can do
automation incident responses.
we'll discuss about how we can
collaborate and communicate better
with the teams, in case, we have
to handle the incident management.
We'll also discuss about some
data driven insights and also a
case study, done by IBM for one
of the e commerce applications.
Introduction to cloud computing
and Java technologies.
We all know the cloud computing has become
the cornerstone of digital transformation.
So the reason is like it, cloud computing
offers many big features which are like
scalability, cost efficiency and agility.
With this, the, with this current
global market, the cloud computing
is projected to reach around 832.
1 billion dollars by 2025, right?
So with this, we can assume that,
that cloud computing has become one
of the modern business strategies.
For most of the enterprise applications
like Netflix, Amazon and eBay and a lot
of other companies use cloud computing
along with that, like Java is one of the
main application programming language.
Which is very reliable, and been used
in enterprise environments, right?
The java's main philosophy was
platform independence, which is
write once and run anywhere, right?
This perfectly fits with the distributed
nature of the cloud computing, right?
Where the this will help the
developers to write portable
applications which run seamlessly
across multiple cloud platforms.
the combination of this platform
independence and the distributed
nature of cloud computing, this is
a powerful synergy which enables
the business to develop robust,
scalable, and efficient applications.
And, Java have an extensive ecosystem.
it have many frameworks.
The main frameworks were Spring
Boot, Micronaut, using which we
can develop in, production ready
application within a few days.
So this makes the ideal technology for
driving the digital transformation.
That's about it.
Let's go ahead.
Here we are going to discuss
about the challenges of the
traditional incident management.
earlier before cloud computing
and, microservices and Java, right?
We were struggling with siloed
systems and slow response time, right?
So based on a study from Gartner,
We found that the, the downturn per
minute cost around, 5, 600 per minute.
So we can assume that, in a holiday season
where the traffic speaks, whenever there
is an outage, it's going to cost that
particular, usage of the customers, right?
We are going to miss
that particular, traffic.
So that's the last which was,
included here by the Gartner
and, the manual process which leads
to the human errors right here.
there are a lot of things which we
do manually where we need to search
logs, copy the, ID, request IDs.
And, we update the, spreadsheets
and contact the team
members individually, right?
There is a high probability
here we, We will have manual
exceptions and manual errors due
to which, this traditional incident
management is not, up to the mark.
And the siloed system, hinders the,
collaboration and visibility, Because
we have a lot of monitoring tools, which
are not like, we used to directly go to
Tomcat and, and other application servers.
We used to Check the errors there
and we don't have an integration
with this particular logger mechanism
with our communication channels.
So that was the issue.
And also legacy infrastructure
lacks the scalability to handle
the modern demands, right?
So the infrastructure which
we used to have earlier.
Let's say we have 10 nodes to serve the
traffic, whenever there is a holiday
season, we need to scale up, and we
need to plan ahead and have a team which
to work on, building up the servers
and deploy the application and make
it ready at that particular peak time.
this all can be avoided
with, cloud computing.
We'll see that in the next slide.
So here we are going to discuss how
cloud, is staying in the advantage
of, and these are the main things,
which already we, we touched just now.
So the solution which cloud
provides is the agility,
scalability, and resilience, right?
See, the on demand resource,
scale up and scale down can
automatically happen in cloud.
And automatically we can, accelerate
the incident responses, and whenever
there is a system or a database or
something is down, we can sell, we can
add the cell feeling, in cloud computing.
And we can have the centralized
platform enhancement collaboration
like integrated monitoring,
logging and communication tools.
We have a lot of examples for this.
We can, we'll discuss in a minute,
like Kibana, Grafana and a lot
of other integration tools, where
we can integrate all the K8,
clusters and the local instances.
We can get all the logs in one place.
And the main important feature here is
the reducing the infrastructure cost.
So whenever there is a traffic, we will
increase the number of resources we
scale up and whenever we don't have, we
can eliminate those particular, we can
free up those resources so that we can,
we can decrease the, maintenance cost.
So here we are going to discuss
how the Java, is going to be
the powerhouse of cloud native
implementation for incident management.
So the platform independence for, is
the main feature where we can write
once and, run anywhere, which will
help for seamless deployments across
multiple cloud platforms, right?
Using this, we can, build a robust,
like we have, A framework like
Spring Boot where we can build the
microservices and we have Spring
Cloud for Cloud service discovery.
We can do configuration management and
load balancing Using, this framework
and we have an extensive library of,
monitoring and logging tools along
with alerting, like log four JSFL,
four J and micrometer from Spring Boot.
So these libraries, will help
us in logging, the application
errors or info messages.
this can be easily, Help for help the
java application and we have a large,
an active community For supporting
an innovation new tech new things,
can be integrated in java, right?
We'll discuss more about this now.
This is about microservices.
How, Earlier right when we were
discussing about this iload environment
Which was a single monolithic
application where, which, which can be
divided into multiple smaller, logic.
So here we'll take a separate example for
this where, we have a framework where we
have a module called user authentication.
We have an instant logging option and
also a notification dispatcher, right?
So we can assume a name.
monolithic application architecture,
whenever there is an issue with
user authentication, we, it is going
to impact the incident logging and
notification dispatching, right?
So similarly, whenever we have an issue
with incident logging, it is going to
impact the user authentication because all
are running in one single instance, right?
So this can be avoided using
the microservices, right?
In microservices, we can isolate each and
every module here has We have incident,
user authentication and everything
has a separate whenever there is an
issue with one particular, incident
logging, it is not going to impact
the user authentication microservice.
Similarly, we have deployment
updates independently without
affecting other services, right?
Whenever we want to scale up, let's say
we in traffic peak hours, we want to
handle the more number of users, right?
So at that point of time, we can
scale up user authentication module.
microservice and then we can handle
that particular, only service
can, and we can save here, like
not increasing the others, right?
and also we,
and, so this will help, during
the high traffic situations.
Yeah.
So coming to cloud computing, we
have something called serverless
computing, where we, where, we can
achieve the similar kind of thing,
whatever we discussed without a,
without we focus on, we can, instead
of focusing on infra, we can just focus
on code and business logic, right?
this is a effortless scalability
and reducing the overall
operation costs, right?
Using serverless, computing.
the best example is, AWS Lambda.
We have one, here, the diagram
which we are seeing here.
We have one AWS Lambda and this can
be automatically triggered instant
responses, when, function to send
the notification whenever there
is an incident created, right?
So this will send a notification.
So automatically scale, the resources
based on the real time demand, right?
This is only, triggers only
when there is an incident.
That means it's only real time, right?
and here we pay only for the
computation time which we actually used.
We don't need to pay whenever
the server is, not used, right?
and also we don't have to worry about
the, number of servers used and we don't
want, have, the users, to use this, right?
this will free up the developer where they
can focus on incident management logic
instead of focusing on the infrastructure.
Here we are going to discuss about CI
and CD pipelines, which will continuously
improve for the faster resolution, right?
the main logic here is like we have
couple of tools in market right
now, Jenkins, Git, Git actions.
And, here whenever there's
a new, deployment happens.
our microservice is, created, right?
We deploy that and, the
automatic code deployment will
happen using Jenkins, right?
And, whenever a build is
deployed, bill is, triggered.
It'll deploy into a particular docker
and COU K eight, and, it'll run.
we can also have the automatic,
automa automated test cases, right?
So this will improve the code quality.
And it will run all the J units and
end to end testing will happen, right?
This will also, the other example
which we can take here is, even
in the case of issues, right?
Whenever there is an issue, the
rollback can happen easily, right?
using Jenkins.
Whenever there is an issue, it won't
be deployed into the server, right?
We can stop the deployment and, the
particular, and also we can rollback
easily in other environments and
we can check, what was failing.
So this is going to help, the,
improve the faster incidence
resolutions using C and CD pipelines.
So here we are going to discuss about
real time monitoring and alerting, right?
We have multiple tools to achieve
this in current, applications.
Prometheus is one of the popular thing.
And, we have Grafana and we have
Dryna Trace, where, we can identify
if there are any CP outages, right?
there are a couple of, scenarios
here where we can, enable alerts.
whenever, the, here we are taking example
of whenever the CPU, usage, exceeds more
than 80%, let's say, create an alert
and, send it to the application data.
So here, we can trigger an alert based
on, based on the, based on this particular
parameters, And also we can analyze data
in, in identify the anomalies, with the
potential issues, With this can easily, we
can easily see the number of spikes also.
We can have this, and also we can,
Have the, collection of the real time
data, with respect to the monitoring
the CPU's usage, memory usage, and
network traffic and error rates.
We can also monitor the user logins.
Whenever there is a huge number of
logins, let's say we want to track
it and we want the alerts to be
sent to the application team, right?
We can do that with this real time
monitoring and, alerting systems.
Here we, we saw about real
time monitoring alert, right?
We want to do an automatic
incident response, right?
Whenever there is an incident reported,
we want to, send it to the particular
application team and we want somebody
to address that particular issue, right?
If they complete this, there are a
couple of examples where we have P0
issues like database server is down or
the vault is down for an application.
For these kind of issues, we, we
need somebody to manually check this.
So for that, we can integrate it with
the pager, so that the notification.
So we can see here the how the
incident are managed and automatically
integrated with pager duty.
and we can escalate based on
the severity of the issues.
And a couple of examples
here is the CPU high usage.
And if some application is
completely down, we can trigger this.
And collaboration and community.
This is one of the, main thing,
which, and has the dream work
with centralized, communication
channels and collaboration site.
Here, main things which we want to discuss
here is, we should have a shared platform
for incident communications, right?
Like Jira, we have Jira boards, and
also we can have, we can have the
team, we can have a group channels.
where we can discuss about the incidents
and we can have, the slack channels
and Microsoft teams, where we can
easily communicate about the issues.
So earlier, whenever we, had issues, In
automatic incident responses and real
time monitoring, we want to send them to
this particular Slack channels, right?
So where we can integrate
them with the Slack channels.
So whenever there is a high priority
issues, we can directly send it to
a particular application team and we
can address to all the stakeholders
related to that particular application.
So this will help in, collaborating
and we can have a centralized
communication for all the teams.
So that we can address the issues easily.
And we can also create a
knowledge base for this using
wiki pages or any of this, right?
Whenever and also we can
have a weekly credence for
discussing this kind of issues.
So here we are going to discuss about,
the data driven insights, right?
So here we have, we can do, detailed
comprehensive, data analysis.
So there are multiple ways to do it.
We can use, use Tableau reports.
We can, we have Elasticsearch
dashboards and we have Kibana.
reports, right?
And, based on this, we can have multi
monthly and weekly meetings where we
can discuss about, what happened when
a production release happens, right?
We can see the Tableau reports
and we can discuss, about,
how the traffic is getting,
communicated with the new release.
Whenever there's a new feature,
released, we can see how the users are,
how the users are, communicated.
And we can identify the patterns,
proactively and prevent the
future incidents, right?
Whenever there is a issue,
we can see those, common root
causes and we can identify them.
the key, metric to track here
is the mean, time to resolution.
which is called as MTTR.
So we can see the incident and we
can see we can track the frequency
of the resolution for this.
So this is how we handle the data.
Going on next.
So here we are going to discuss
about a case study, which is done
by IBM with a, one of the leading
e commerce, application, right?
So this application, e commerce company
was, struggling with slow response
time and frequent outages using,
during the peak up, peak season.
Peak shopping season, right?
So once they're migrated to, microservice
architecture with AWS, are using Lambda
and, for our automated incident responses.
So below the, highlighted, results
they achieved, they achieved 78
percentage of scalability improvement.
And they reduce the, m empty TR by
50 percentage, and they decrease
the incidents by 30 percentage.
See, overall, the scalability
has been improved by 78%.
This is a great achievement, I say, using
both the Java microservices and also
using the cloud based application, right?
So this is the survey result.
So this is a great achievement.
And here are the key takeaways, guys.
the cloud and Java enable the
efficient incident management.
we discussed about how we are, how
both cloud and, Java, doing this.
We are, we already discussed about,
microservices and serverless computing
and has the scalability, how the
scalability, applies for both, serverless
lambda and also mic, boot microservices.
We see the CNCD monitoring ML
drive faster for quicker responses.
And also we discussed about moving
beyond the incident management, right?
Where we can create the dashboards and
we can see the, preventive measures
based on the, historical data, right?
Agility screen here, where we respond
to the incident which, Speed and
efficiency so and also we have we can
take the decisions based on data, right?
So based on this data we can see how we
can continuously improve We can identify
the issues and we can make sure that the
issues cannot Occur the next time right?
So these are the key takeaways guys with
both the cloud and java technologies on
how we can handle the incident management.
Thank you everyone Bye.
Bye