Hello everyone.
Thanks for joining my session.
I'm UD Na Moham, and today's topic on my
session is AI Powered Knowledge Systems
for Resilient Cloud Incident Response.
Today's presentation focuses on the
evolving challenges of cloud reliability
and how modern engineering teams.
Can adapt their incident response
and knowledge management strategies.
As organization embrace digital
transformation, the way engineering
teams operate has changed dramatically.
Cloud native architectures built
on microservices, containers and
serverless technologies have introduced
new layers of complexity and failures
that simplified did not, or simply
doesn't exist in traditional systems.
At the same time, deployment velocity has
accelerated with many teams pushing codes
into production multiple times a day.
This creates a high pressure
environment where reliability must be
maintained despite constant change.
The challenge is that most incident
response frameworks were designed
for slower moving monolithic systems.
They're not equipped to handle
the speed and the scale of
today's cloud native environments.
And with the growing shortage
of experienced engineers, we
cannot rely solely on tribal
knowledge to solve problems.
We need scalable, intelligent systems that
support fast effective incident resolution
and knowledge sharing across teams.
And because of that we have
many challenges and one of
them is knowledge Half-life.
Charlie, this challenge modern
engineering organization on the rapid
DK of technical knowledge, the knowledge
half-life refers to the diminishing
relevance of information about a
particular technology or a system
over time, often becoming obsolete.
Or significantly less useful
within a short period.
There are specifically three challenges.
One is accelerating innovation
where cloud providers constantly
introduce new services, features
altering how existing systems behave
and generate novel failure modes.
And then there is a cascading complexity.
Even with minor changes can
impact multiple system components,
necessities, extensive adjustments
to monitoring, altering deployment
scripts and operational procedures.
And the third one is continuous delivery.
Agile practices accelerate system
change, frequency rendering,
troubleshooting expertise.
Obsolete within months due to frequent
updates and architectural shifts.
Implication of knowledge dq
The accelerating knowledge.
Half-life extends beyond
individual productivity.
Organizations invest significant
resources in training, documentation,
and knowledge transfer initiatives when
knowledge becomes obsolete more quickly.
The return on this investment diminishes
forcing organizations to allocate more
resources to keeping the teams current.
This creates a continuous cycle where
teams struggle to maintain expertise
while the underlying systems continue
to evolve at an increasing pace.
The foundation of AI
driven eco knowledge, if.
AI driven knowledge ecosystems.
The foundation has four layers.
The first one is the foundation
layer, which primarily focuses on
high performance knowledge operations
with low latency access, high
availability, and horizontal scalability.
This leverages the vector database,
optimized for similarity search
and event driven architecture
for real time knowledge updates.
And the second layer is
the processing layer.
The cognitive core raw data
transformations into actionable insights
through advanced machine learning and
natural language processing, extracted
structured data or information from
unstructured sources like logs,
incident reports, communication
threats, and then there is a third
one, which is interaction layer.
Which bridges the AI powered
knowledge processing with
engineering teams, practical needs
through conversational interfaces.
And the fourth one is integration layer.
This embeds knowledge capabilities
into existing workflows through
API, integration with incident
management platforms, monitoring
systems, and collaboration tools.
The processing layer, intelligence
and insight generation.
The processing layer represents
the cognitive core of AI driven
knowledge ecosystems, transforming
raw data into actionable insights.
Through advanced machine learning
and natural language processing,
modern cloud environments generate
vast amounts of unstructured data
containing valuable information.
Like log files, incident reports, and
communication logs and communication
threats all contain knowledge that can
enhance future incident report efforts.
The processing layer employs
sophisticated NLP algorithms to
extract structured information from
unstructured sources like log files.
In traction layer, it's
human-centered knowledge access.
So there are four phases of it.
One is conversational interfaces.
This allow teams to ask natural language
questions about system behavior,
historical incidents, and troubleshooting
procedures, reducing cognitive
load during high stress scenarios.
And then there is a visual dashboards.
This presents complex system
relationships, incident timelines
and diagnostic information
in formats, enabling rapid
pattern and decision making.
And the third one is personalization.
This adapts to individual user
preferences and expertise levels,
providing detailed explanations for
new team members and concise technical
summaries for experienced engineers.
The fourth one is context array delivery.
This detects operational
context based on active alerts,
metrics, and user activities.
Proactively surfacing relevant knowledge
without requiring explicit queries.
Integration layer.
It designed to seamlessly
integrate with workflow embedded.
The integration layer ensures that
AI driven knowledge capabilities
become an integral part of existing
operational workflows rather than
requiring separate tools and processes.
And how do we do that?
We have four steps for that, and
the first one is API integration.
This provides the foundation for embedding
knowledge capabilities into existing
incident management platforms, monitoring
systems and collaboration tools.
And the second one is workflow automation.
This triggers knowledge updates
and distribution based on specific
events or conditions automatically
extracting and distributing.
Key insights when teams resolve incidents.
And the third one is contextual delivery.
This automatically surfaces relevant
knowledge based on current system
conditions, matching anomalous behavior
patterns with historical incidents.
And the fourth and the final one
is real time synchronization.
And this ensures that knowledge based
content system, data and operational
contents are consistently up to date
across all the integrated platforms,
eliminating information, silos and Ds.
Based on this, the real world
implementation and the performance metrics
are shown on this slide, as you can see.
Using this, we can, we have
achieved 99.8% or we could achieve
99.8% of processing accuracy.
This ensures insights and recommendations
are reliable and actionable, meeting
or exceeding human level performance
for many knowledge extraction task.
And this also achieved
90% latency reduction.
What that means is it takes less time
to deliver relevant information compared
to the traditional knowledge management
approaches requiring manual searches.
And this also helped us to achieve
75% reduction in the cognitive burden,
decreasing mental effort required
for engineers to find and apply.
Relevant information during high
pressure incident response scenarios.
Organizations implementing these
systems report significant improvements
in multiple areas that directly
affect their ability to maintain
system reliability and respond
effectively to operational challenges.
Solution generation and
organizational learning.
The ultimate measure of knowledge system
effectiveness lies in its ability to
accelerate solution generation and support
continuous organizational learning.
Traditional approaches often require
teams to rediscover solutions,
but others have already developed.
AI driven knowledge ecosystems can
significantly accelerate solution
generation by automatically identifying
similar historical incidents and
presenting relevant approaches, machine
learning algorithms analyze content and
current incident characteristics and
match them against historical patterns to
suggest effective troubleshooting steps.
The continuous learning capabilities
ensures that insights from each
incident contribute to collective
knowledge base, creating a positive
feedback loop where incident response
capabilities improve over time.
Building organizational
resilience at scale.
The implementation of AI knowledge
ecosystem represents more than
just a technological upgrade.
It constitutes a fundamental shift
toward building organizational resilience
in phase of increasing technological
complexity and operational challenges.
Scalable resilience requires moving beyond
approaches that depend on individual
expertise or manual maintain processes.
AI driven systems provide the
scalability necessary to maintain high
levels of operational effectiveness.
Effectiveness even as complexity
and scope continue to grow.
And because of this, there are two.
Effects.
One is network effects.
As more teams contribute experiences
and insights, the collective
knowledge base becomes increasingly
comprehensive and valuable.
And then there is a cross team knowledge.
This automatically identifies insights
relevant across multiple teams,
breaking down organizational silos and
embedding more effective collaboration,
the future direction and conclusion
and continuous evolution.
The field of AI driven.
Knowledge system continues to evolve
rapidly with the new capabilities
and approaches emerging regularly.
Organizations must adopt strategies
for continuous evolution that allow
to incorporate new technologies
as they become available.
And we can do this in the three steps.
We can have advanced AI models.
Which has large language models and
advanced reasoning systems offer new
possibilities for knowledge systems
and knowledge synthesis at levels
approaching human comprehension with while
operating at machine speed and scale.
And the second one is
structure operational data.
This helps growing availability
of metrics, traces, and logs.
Creates opportunities for sophisticated
analysis, identifying subtle patterns
that might escape human attention.
And then there is a predictive
capabilities, machine learning
algorithms processing vast operational
telemetry to identify leading
indicators of potential issues,
enabling proactive invent interventions.
The key benefits of AI driven knowledge
ecosystem, the first and the foremost
is faster incident resolution.
As reducing mean time to resolution
by automatically delivering
relevant historical solutions.
The second one is preserved expertise.
This helps by capturing and
maintaining organizational knowledge
despite team changes and turnover.
And the third benefit is scalable
operations and by mean that it supports
growing system complexity without
proportional increase in staffing.
And the fourth one is continuous learning.
This improves response capabilities over
time through automated knowledge capture.
And the fifth and the last one
is enhance resilience, building
organizational capacity to withstand
and quickly recover from disruptions.
Conclusion, the path forward.
The transformation of incident response
through AI driven ecosystem represents
a necessary evolution in response
to accelerating technological change
and increasing system complexity.
Organizations that successfully implement
these systems position themselves to
maintain high levels of operation.
And operational effectiveness.
Despite rapid evolving cloud technologies,
as organizations navigate the complexity
of modern cloud environments, AI
driven knowledge ecosystems will
increasingly become a computive.
And competitive necessity rather than
merely an operational improvement.
Success of this approach depends
not only on selecting appropriate
AI technologies and architectural
approaches, but also on fostering
organizational cultures that value
knowledge sharing, continuous learning,
and collaborative problem solving.
The organizations that achieve the,
this integration of technological
capability and cultural transformation
will be best positioned to thrive in
an increasingly complex and rapidly
evolving technological landscape.
By this, we come to the end
of this presentation and.
Again, I'm Hamud Han Mohammad, please
reach out to me and share your feedback.
I appreciate it and thanks for watching
my session and joining with me.
Thank you so much.