So we're going to be talking about
building software prototypes using
AI tools and the programming language
of choice, of course, is Python.
And we will be discussing examples
of time series analysis and the
domain specific area that we will be
talking about is financial analysis.
And we'll be using this kind
of a capability to build an
algorithmic trading system.
So let's get to it.
Now, we are familiar with all these.
Concepts of machine learning, data
analytics, rules based data, driven.
Decisions.
However, the application off
building software using these E I
tools is very recent innovation.
Thanks to impart by the genAI tools
that are now available for us.
So we'll be discussing how we can
adopt and adapt these AI tools in
building these financial applications.
But before we get to that, let's look
into what are the base skills necessary
to achieve something like this, right?
It's not set in stone that we should
follow one approach to the other,
but more importantly, the technical
skills and those and the business
skills that are essential to build such
applications are very much important
because an AI tool is just a tool.
The more the success or the secret sauce
in all of this is the individual or the
human being with the relevant and required
skill sets necessary to achieve this.
So there are certain foundational
skills, there are data specific
skills, there are problem solving
skills, there are professionalism and
collaboration expertise that are required.
And of course there is this
knowledge that a person should have
to be able to build such things.
And.
Not the least interpersonal skills,
because if you're not able to
communicate and not able to collaborate,
we will not be able to build things
at scale that we are accustomed to.
All right.
So the next thing is, we all are aware.
Where we are today, but it's
important to realize how we got there.
So in the 1950s to 1970s,
the early foundations of the
software development was made.
And from there on, we were, we came across
this object oriented programming concept.
And then, of course, there was this
internet revolution in the 90s.
But why I'm discussing this is we have
to realize that this journey that we
have come across where we are today in
this AI revolution that we are in today.
So every stage of every step that we
passed led us to where we are today.
And more importantly, this
is where we have to consider
adopting to such technologies
because over time, things evolve.
So what is, Important to realize is in
the early 2000s to mid 2000s, we had
this cloud transformation journey or
cloud journey that we are now aware of
and how things have turned out to be.
And then from late 2020 tense up to.
Pandemic level.
We were all, using some way or
form algorithms or data driven
machine learning models in our daily
lives without even noticing it.
For example, these recommendation
engines from Netflix or from Spotify.
You were having these playlists
that are being recommended.
And of course, there were a lot of other
things that we were getting exposed to.
But It was very much behind the scenes.
Now, from the advent of this Gen AI
tools that have now come into mainstream,
especially the LLM models that are out
there as individuals, as users, we are
now directly interacting with AI, and
this has opened up A whole new paradigm
of things that are possible with the
possibilities that are endless style.
And I am really excited during this
period because I come from a technology
background and a business background.
So what happens is if a person like me
who understands business problems and
solutions, I can now use these Gen AI
tools to quickly iterate and prototype
without waiting for a large team to come
in and be available for me to do this.
So this is.
Enabling a lot of creativity is
enabling a lot of rapid prototyping.
It's enabling a lot of innovation,
which was pretty much there in the
past, but the space at which we
are doing it now has accelerated.
as I mentioned, beginning in the
beginning of the session, we are going
to be talking about financial analysis.
Which is a specific domain
area of time series analysis.
So some of you may have already
experienced in one shape or form
time series analysis, right?
So the first point, obviously, is
the financial use case of algorithmic
trading and risk management, which
we'll be covering in this part
of this discussion and topic.
In the case of health care, this
patient monitoring and epidemiology.
in the case of, maintenance is predictive
maintenance quality control, which is
used by facilities, industries, process
industries and manufacturing industries is
demand forecasting and industry management
across many different industries.
in the in energy and power generation and
power management, there is energy load
forecasting and smart grid management.
Again, they are based on time series
data that comes in and they are able.
They are managing their
business around that.
We all know, whether it's time driven.
every minute, every hour, every day, every
week, we know how the weather is behaving
and forecast, and we're able to see these
forecasting events day in, day out, and
we interact with them on a regular basis.
Network traffic analysis
and fraud detection.
This is again for the data networks.
so every packet every
information is times timestamp.
fraud detection is also, in the form of
time series where we know the behavior
in the past based on particular time.
And if it's currently not
following a certain pattern.
Based on the time, of course,
we can determine what's going
on, and then we can, behave,
manage the behaviors accordingly.
Economic forecasting and public
health monitoring is also time
based, obviously not at the granular
level, but it's usually on a weekly,
daily, monthly, quarterly, so those
are the aspects of time series.
By the way, if you see there is a
LinkedIn link or details, if you have
any questions around any of these
topics, feel free to drop me a note.
On LinkedIn, and I'll be
happy to respond to that.
Again, we all know AI is here.
It's here to stay.
Now we are accelerating the adoption
and adaption of AI into our daily lives.
Up to 26 percent of the world's
GDP will be increased, will be
contributed, or there will be a
contribution of increase of 26% by
AI in the next four to five years.
we are really in an exciting time.
Of course, some of us are a bit
concerned that what will happen to
the current way of doing things.
As, I mentioned earlier, it's
an evolutionary journey that we
already have been accustomed to.
So we have to adapt.
It's, this into our daily lives, into
our professional lives, and then leverage
it for the next stage in our careers, in
our profession, in our personal lives.
Okay, so what am I doing?
This chart, what does it depict?
I come from a program
management background.
I come from a business
solution background.
I come from a technology background.
So it's important that there's a method
to the madness that we do, right?
So everything has to have a flow.
Everything has to have
a structure this way.
It is repeatable.
It is comprehensible.
People can collaborate in it.
So what I've done is to
build such a prototype.
I have mapped two methodologies onto one.
I've taken the data management methodology
using data science called crisp and
aligned it with the lean development
methodologies, which we all are aware of.
It's in the software development
cycle to come up with this model.
However, Okay.
Why I'm doing this is I'm training my GPT,
which I will talk later on, to recognize
that this is the flow of information,
this is the flow of the method of
interaction that I want it to follow,
so that there's a repeatable discipline
in the AI model that I'm training
to help me, Develop this prototype.
we are.
We are aware that sometimes a I
models and especially in the case
of L and M, they can hallucinate.
They can.
They can go into different directions.
I want to give them a precise
context of how I want to get things
done and use that as an approach.
Use that as a method to give
me the output that I want.
So in the subsequent, slide, I will
talk about what else am I doing?
So I'm using such
approach such methodology.
Sorry to say to, saying the model.
To realize and recognize this
is the flow of information.
I wanted to follow.
Okay, more or what I'm doing is
I'm training the AI model for me
for them to develop the software
prototype that I require realizing
the real world structure that is we
are accustomed to and which works.
So why?
Why reinvent the wheel when we
know a structure works like this?
So I'm giving a team structure, assuming
that there are multiple team members
involved into a program, into a project,
and they're building this prototype.
So I've trained the model to realize and
recognize that this is a team structure.
They should be able to interact with
each other, question each other, and come
up with the right software prototype.
which is validated by all these different
teams that are out there in this.
So we all know there are software
developers, data scientists, data
analysts, domain experts, quality
assurance team members, security
specialists, DevOps engineers,
data engineers, and so forth.
So all of that I've used as an
information and I've trained an
AI model to realize and recognize
and build me a software prototype.
Based on these conditions.
Another thing that I was talking about
earlier is, I've adopted the lean
approach mapped onto a data management
approach to, let the model realize
recognize what process to follow, right?
So it has to follow certain
process to give me the design
output or design out for that.
I'm looking for now.
I've also trained the model to
realize that this is the architecture
that I'm looking for, right?
So there's a data ingestion or data
collection, data pre processing,
there's a strategy implementation
for the algorithmic trading, model
that I'm, system that I'm building.
There's a backtesting agent
that you need to recognize.
There's a risk management, criteria that
needs to follow and how it should be used.
Execute the trades.
What are the optimization
parameter that needs to consider?
And what are the monitoring
and logging capabilities?
I want to be able to debug
and then understand how the
application is behaving.
So I even trained the AI model to realize
the architecture that I'm looking for.
Another thing of what I did was,
if you some of you are from the
computer science background, you
will be aware that there are design
patterns and everything that we do.
So I went a step further and I define
the modules that I'm looking for.
I listed out what the
functionalities I'm looking for.
And.
What potential design patterns
that can be considered.
So even though I'm like prompting
this to the air model that consider
these factors, but I've also asked
the model to continuously learn from
what prompts that I initiate as a
continue as a chain of thought and
engagement that I have with our model.
So as and when the prototype of
walls of the software walls on I
engage in certain prompts with that
model, it should evolve itself.
So even though this is a starting bit,
but I've also kept a room for evolution.
Now, how did I use these ER tools?
Okay.
you're all aware there's
a chat GPT out there.
So chap GPT 4.
0 was the LLM model that I had used.
there's a feature within chat GPT where
you can build your own custom GPTs.
So I built, this custom GPT called
quant lab, which allows me to
research, Allows me to define
certain delivery model methodology
and structures it I can do this.
Use it for requirements analysis.
I can use it for solution
architecture design and I can use.
I then eventually obviously I will be
using it for generating boiler code
or template code, which then goes into
GitHub Copilot using Visual Studio Code.
So in GitHub Copilot, the code
that was generated by quant lab.
Built using the UPD 4.
0 LLM now and get have
copilot the interface.
I'm using a visual studio code.
The code refactoring happens.
The debugging and testing
of that code happens.
And of course, since I'm building an
algorithmic trading system using time
series analysis capable process or the
structure, I have to identify certain
parameters and I have to tune and
optimize them to get the desired output.
Even though I'm referencing an example
of financial services, this time
series based data analysis can be done
on any kind of a time series data.
Okay.
Now, what is the approach that I used?
And this is what I also used to
train my GPT 40 model, right?
using GPT 40 LLM, I provided
certain training data.
I'll talk about that.
I did prompt engineering and I
trained it using certain prompts,
which I will showcase to you.
And more importantly, I also
provided a contextual input.
Now this contextual input is historical
data, which is a time series data for it
to realize and recognize what it's doing.
So instead of it, hallucinating, I gave
it specific data points that it should
consider for building such a prototype.
And more importantly, it's important
to give context to the model.
Now, what are we doing?
We're building an algorithmic
trading strategy, right?
So what's important is
I gave a strategy input.
So there are certain research documents
out there, which I came across what
I felt has a promising, potential.
I used that research document and I loaded
it into GPT 40 LLM into my custom GPT.
And with all that input, And of course, a
lot of iteration and a lot of refactoring.
I came across a boiler code.
This boiler code as a step one eventually
went into the step two, which is the
Visual Studio code and using GitHub.
Go pilot.
I refactored and retested that code.
And it was able to generate process data.
Now, of course, what I did was,
if you remember, there was a data
ingestion and data collection class
or process that I was considering.
So the market data would be, Pulled
out from the broker data source, and
that will be then process and then this
process data goes back into the custom
GPT, which is based on GPT for LLM.
I can do exploratory data analysis
of their data analysis and analytical
capabilities in GPT for all.
I can do visualizations.
I can do insights and based on
those insights, I can understand
what is the behavior of that data.
I can go back into Visual Studio code.
And do a optimization run or
parameterization tuning run and
eventually once I'm happy or I'm when
I feel it's getting the right output,
I can consider this as a prototype,
which is based on and I can take
this, take it next, next step forward.
All right, good.
So one other thing to have.
I did was I had, as if you remember,
there was a system architecture
that I put together, right?
So I trained the AI model using the
system architecture, which is again,
not a hard and fast rule, but it was a
starting point for the model to realize
that this is the output I'm looking for
and follow this architecture design that
I intend to follow, intend to generate.
Okay.
All right.
Some of the prerequisites for
building such an AI model or custom
GPD model was, I had to train it
a lot for over a couple of days.
But it was a week of training, prompt
engineering to and fro, eventually
to a stage where I felt this is okay.
The output of the code is sufficient
enough for me to play around with or
get the necessary desired results.
by the way, this AI model or the
custom GPT, I call it QuantLab.
So the link you see here,
it's publicly available.
You can copy paste this, or you can
follow this link into your GPT, chat
GPT, and it should give you, it should
take you to that custom GPT that I've
built, and you're free to use that.
There's another, thing I need to
highlight is the, You need to provide
certain specific context to the model.
Someone may call it rag.
Someone may call it, context.
I ended up pulling this research
paper, which defined a very promising
trading strategy, but of course,
this is not a, like a talk on
financial advice or on building,
commercial grade, training systems.
This is just for educational purposes,
but using this educational document, I
was able to, give a context to the model
for it to realize and recognize what
are the rules I'm looking for, right?
And it does, it did a pretty good job.
More importantly, I also provided
The model, a starter code from my
previous projects, which I knew works
fine and there were no bugs in it.
So at least it understands that
the structure of the code the way
I prefer to write or before to read
because it's personalized to me.
So these inputs were all provided to the
quant lab GPD model that I had trained.
Now.
Let's see.
Let's do a walkthrough.
All right, enough talk.
Let me show you what it looks like.
All right.
So here we are.
This is, all right, let's
start from the beginning.
Well, a lot of training as you can see.
So I provided like a starter
code, which is a Python script.
I provided certain, I provided
that contextual trading strategy.
To the model.
And of course, it started
generating certain outputs.
I thought I gave all these
different prompts to it.
You can see all these
And eventually, after several iterations,
and by the way, you can see you can even
do graphical visualizations in GPT four.
Oh, so this is an amazing tool for that.
And, You can do tables.
I kept on prompting.
It keeps on giving me different results.
It started giving me a
code that I'm looking for.
And with a lot of to and fro, and
to and fro, eventually I got to a
point where I was satisfied that
this is something I can work with.
And then what?
But before long, before I go to the
execution side of it, let me show you
what this quant lab is all about, right?
So let me just go into this edit
functionality of this custom GPT.
I'm going to configure, right?
So I'm showing you all these
things of how, I had actually built
this quant lab as a custom GPT.
So there is a capability within GPT 4.
0 where you can build your own custom GPT.
I'm sure you can find more details
around it, but just to give you
a summary of how it works, you
have to give it instructions.
There are certain compositional starters.
there are certain knowledge,
inputs that I have provided.
You can see it over here.
And if you remember, these
were the diagrams and charts.
So I gave it tabular information.
I gave it visual information.
so it was able to read and comprehend
what I was expecting from it.
And of course, there were a lot
of prompt exercises or prompt
that I had provided to it.
And eventually ended up giving me
the results that I was looking for.
All right, That's QuantLab using GPD 4.
0.
Now, let's go to Visual Studio.
All right, so in Visual Studio,
eventually, what I did was, the code
that was generated using QuantLab,
this was a Jupyter Notebook, by
the way, I was a Jupyter Notebook.
I could transfer that code over here.
Of course, I executed some of the code
to make sure there are no bugs and
everything, and more importantly, I
was using GitHub Copilot to refactor
some of the code to give me, let's
say, for example, here, I asked it to
give me a project structure of how my
project should be structured, right?
So this is using Python scripts,
but eventually I moved on to Jupyter
Notebook because of ease of execution.
So I had some preferences around that.
And, so all might configuration
document or configuration files on
a configuration is kept separately.
I did not want to pull in to the court.
So the way I designed was tomorrow, if I
interface code or this application with
another front end, the JSON file will
be able to take all that data inputs
that are necessary for it to, take the
capture user determine parameters from
the user and configuration from the users.
And then you can then dynamically
update my code or my trading strategy.
Okay, so that's how I use JSON over here.
yeah, so you can see there are
certain code that's been generated.
I'm doing certain.
And this is a very recursive
and refactoring exercise that
we, when you get to a stage where
the code is sufficient for you,
then obviously you can start.
But in the field of technology
and we're never happy.
We always want new versions,
new book, new features.
So it becomes an.
A very fun exercise where you're
interacting with a GPT and, you're telling
it what you want next, what you want next.
And then over time you build things which
you like, and then you take it from there.
So a lot of to and fro using GPT 4.
0 and of course, good to get up
co pilot to eventually get to a
stage where I'm happy with the
current structure of the code.
And it's giving me the desired outcomes
and outputs that I'm looking for.
And, yes.
Let's get back to where we are now.
Some of my, for me to
wrap up things over here.
It's a new world altogether.
It's a great world altogether, especially
in the field of data analytics in a I, It
has been democratized, to a lot of people
out there who were a bit skeptical or
concerned about using these tools because
now these LLM models that are out there
makes it so much convenient, easier for
a business user, a technical user to
collaborate to build Prototype to build
applications in a very, natural way off
doing things the way human beings do it.
And, and also for software engineers,
it is an amazing capability,
which typically improves their
productivity and generating.
new innovations, new
technologies out there.
So I look forward to this, next
evolution of AI that is out there.
we have to adapt to it.
We have to adopt to it.
And, we will be in, we, this is a very
good, direction that I feel I'm fairly
confident that I'm going to be, I'm going
to be taking a lot of benefit from it.
So go to this quant lab, GPT,
custom GPT that I have built.
It's free to use.
if you have a GPT 4.
0 subscription, you can easily access it.
And, if you need any assistance or any
guidance, please reach out to me on
LinkedIn and I will be able to help you.
Thank you so very much all
the best with your journeys.