Hello, this is Ashwin here.
Let's talk about the future of healthcare
IT and its trends and predictions.
I will be exploring more on
the emerging technologies and
their impact on the healthcare.
And also we will discuss something
about the rapid growth and
trends in the healthcare market.
let's talk about the market overview
of the current healthcare industry.
The current healthcare industry and so
the market like the digital healthcare
market is experiencing an explosive growth
driven by the advancements in technology
and the increased demanding for healthcare
solutions that can deliver care remotely.
So four years ago, just after the COVID
pandemic, the market was valued about, 96.
5 billion US dollars and it is expected
to grow at an compound annual growth
rate of 15 percent between 2021 and 28.
This growth is a great evidence that
the technology plays a very important
roles in healthcare, especially in the
light of COVID pandemic, which acted
as a main catalyst for these changes.
The pandemic paved the way for widespread
adoption of Telehealth services with
the Centers for Disease Control and
Prevention reporting a 154 percent
increase in telehealth usage and after
COVID compared to the previous years.
So the telemedicine and digital
health solutions are here to say
signaling a fundamental shift
in how healthcare is delivered.
And next, let's talk about the role of
artificial intelligence in healthcare.
the AI market in healthcare was
valued around 7 billion US dollars
after the COVID pandemic in 2020.
And it is expected to grow at an annual
growth rate of 42 percent till 2028.
These AI driven tools such as,
image recognition systems, are
playing a vital role in improving
the early detection of diseases like
cancers and other dreadful diseases.
These AI systems have reduced
the false positive by 5.
7 percent and the false negatives by 9.
4 percent in breast cancer detection.
And let's see how the, how AI plays a
major role in personalized treatment.
So AI analyzes patient data to develop
personalized custom treatment plans.
For example, a particular clinic,
the AI guided treatment improved the
remission rates for depression by
6%, enhancing the patient outcomes.
So what is the potential?
so the AI is creating, is a game
changer in the patient care, by making
healthcare more accessible to everyone.
efficient, personalized, and precise.
So from virtual care assistance,
providing 24 cross seven support,
predictive algorithms that foresee
the health risks, the integration
of AI is transforming the patient
experiences and improving the outcomes.
The future of AI in healthcare holds
a promise of continued innovations
that will further enhance the patient
care and overall health industry.
next, let's see about a machine
learning, for predictive care.
So AI can predict acute kidney injuries,
in hospitalized patients up to 48 hours
before the onset, with an accuracy of 92%.
This allows healthcare
providers to intervene early.
potentially preventing complications.
Similarly, the AI algorithms are
being used to detect the early
signs of sepsis, enabling the timely
treatment and reducing mortality rates.
the machine learning models are used to
personalize the treatment plans based
on a patient's medical history, their
lifestyle, and the genetic profile,
improving the overall care quality
and minimizing the adverse effects.
The AI powered tools also help in
monitoring the chronic conditions
like diabetes or heart disease
through real time data analysis
from wearable devices, alerting the
healthcare providers to potential
complications before they worsen.
clinical applications are available.
The machine learning applications
in clinical care extend
beyond just predictions.
So these tools assist doctors in making
data driven decisions that optimizes care
and reduce the risk of medical errors.
So AI powered clinical decision
support system provide real time
recommendations for diagnosis and
treatment, while the natural language
processing tools analyze electronic
health records to identify the trends.
Helping the clinicians monitor the
treatment outcomes and spot at risk
patients Additionally the AI helps
in triaging Emergency room patients
by accessing symptoms by assessing
symptoms and prioritizing those in
need of immediate care Enhancing the
patient outcomes and reducing wait times
and next see let's see the advanced
data analytics in healthcare so
the data analytics in healthcare is
Revolutionizing the transforming vast
amount of data into actionable insights.
So with healthcare data growing at
an annual rate of 48%, the advanced
analytics tools can harness this
exponential growth to drive better
decision making and patient care.
So in population health management, the
data from the Electronic health records
and, wearable devices and other sources
allow health care providers to identify
the pay, patents, predict disease
outbreaks, and tailor the interventions,
improve the outcomes on a larger scale.
So additionally, the analytics
helps in operational efficiency,
optimizing workflows and resource
allocations and reduce cost.
For example, a major hospital
successfully utilized predictive
analytics to reduce emergency department,
boarding hours by 20%, and increase
the early discharge by 21%, which
significantly improved patient flow.
Moreover, predictive analysis is, It's
also useful to foresee high risk patients
for chronical conditions or readmissions,
allowing for timely interventions.
Analytics further enhance clinician,
clinical decision support, guiding
positions with data driven insights
to improve the diagnostics, accuracy,
and personalized treatment plans.
it also in, Supply chain management.
The analytics enables healthcare
providers to predict the demand
for critical supplies and
medications, avoiding shortages, and
ensuring the timely availability.
So these advance advancements
illustrate how data analytics
is reshaping both patient.
and operational
effectiveness in healthcare.
Then, the next topic is like on
the integration of legacy systems,
with the latest technologies.
First, let's talk about the
challenges of integration.
as, healthcare technology
evolves, the seamless integration
of new systems with the legacy
infrastructure remains a challenge.
critical challenge for
the health care providers.
The continuity of patient care depends
on ensuring that new technologies
such as electronic health records,
telehealth systems, and the other AI
tools are successfully integrated to
into the existing IT environments.
The challenge is underscored by the
fact that 19 percent of the hospital
executives cite, integration with the
legacy systems as a top IT priority.
These legacy systems are often outdated,
fragmented, and incompatible with the
modern technologies, creating data
issues that hinder real time access
to patient information and reduce the
overall efficiency in clinical workflows.
to address these challenges, the FHIR and
the other standardized data frameworks
are playing a pr a very important role.
The FHIR based solutions facilitate
a smoother integration by
stabilizing, the uniform protocols
for exchanging healthcare data across
different systems and platforms.
So these solutions can reduce data
integration time up by 75%, accrediting
the process of, incorporating advanced
tools like AI powered diagnostics
or remote monitoring systems
into hospital IT infrastructure.
With FHIR, the healthcare providers can
improve the interoperability, ensuring
that patient data flows seamlessly
between different departments, hospitals,
and even external health systems,
thus enhancing the care coordination.
Let's talk about the blockchain
and the importance of cloud
migration in the next slides.
the cloud, migration.
So the cloud migration is another
key strategy that healthcare
organizations are trying to
overcome the integration challenges.
So the global healthcare cloud computing
market is exported to reach, 65 billion
by next year, driven by the demand for
scalable and cost effective solutions.
So to migrate to the cloud offers,
increase scalability, allowing the
healthcare chains to easily expand their
IT capabilities without the need for large
scale, large scale like, investments.
The cloud based platforms provide flexible
and secure environments that enable the
integration of new technologies such
as telehealth applications or AI driven
analytics at a lower cost and with
faster, time and a faster turnaround time.
So this shift not only enhances system
performance, but also offers real time
data accessibility, supporting more
responsive and efficient patient care.
So bye.
Leveraging the cloud healthcare systems
can reduce the complexity and cost with
maintaining the on premise hardware
while improving the overall integration
with innovative healthcare technologies.
next is a blockchain.
So blockchain for the
another emerging solution for secure
and efficient data exchange is a
blockchain technology, which provides a
decentralized and tamper resistant method
for sharing sensitive healthcare data.
So blockchain has the potential to
save the healthcare industry 100 to
150 billion annually by next year,
primarily by reducing the data breaches,
IT costs, and operational costs.
inefficiencies.
So blockchain ensures data
integrity and security by creating
immutable records of transactions.
A notable example is an pilot project
involving two major healthcare chains,
which used blockchain to synchronize
the provided data across the systems.
So this initiative, showed a 50 percent
reduction in admin costs by emulating the
data and discrepancies, reducing errors.
which really showed the, which really
shows a major, reduction in the cost.
So with these, new technologies,
what is, we have for the future.
invest in the digital infra.
So healthcare organizations should
upgrade their IT systems to work with the
new technologies and allow for growth.
The hospitals that, made a huge investment
in better digital systems saw a 2.
5 increase in profit margins.
So the focus on the data management,
the poor data quality is costing
the US healthcare systems
billions of dollars each year.
By improving the data management, they
can cut down the errors by 30 percent
and make more reliable decisions.
So and also training the workforce
the healthcare professionals
needs to be trained to use
the digital tools effectively.
So hospitals that had a major investment
in digital training for their staff saw
a 23 percent boost in productivity and
an 18 percent in their patient care.
So these healthcare
companies or the healthcare.
Organizations should have collaborate
with the tech companies to speed
up the innovation and provides
access to the latest technologies.
And, here we go for the conclusion
like The healthcare industry is
on the cup of, on the verge of a
major technological transformation.
The AI, machine learning, advanced data
analytics, and blockchains are already
playing a major role in reshaping the
patient care and their operations.
The path forward is
not without challenges.
But the healthcare organizations
must prioritize the integration
of legacy systems and invest more
on the digital infrastructure.
Cybersecurity, data governance,
and workforce upskilling are
crucial for harnessing the full
potential of these technologies.
As we move forward, organizations
that embrace digital transformation
will be better equipped to improve
the patient outcomes, reduce
operational costs, and stay competitive
in the healthcare landscape.
Thank you.