Hi all, my name is Baran Mikhail,
I'm Cybersecurity Team Lead and
today I'm going to talk about how
we reduce costs by millions with
strategic security initiatives.
I'd like to start with a
short introduction of myself.
I'm Cybersecurity Team Lead with extensive
engineering background and experience.
I have over decade, of
experience cybersecurity.
I've led the design and implementation
of global security infrastructures.
I have extensive experience with risk
management in building up a solid and
resilient security teams, establishing
a security operation center, reducing,
cybersecurity risks, and, um.
consistently enhancing security
and the patient efficiency
across international enterprises.
today's agenda today, I'm
going to speak, about my.
experience and how we've managed to
build a solid and resilient cybersecurity
framework and infrastructure within the
corporate investment business, one of
the biggest corporate investment business
in Europe at the times I'm speaking.
And the, All started with the
transformative initiative, that, the
main goal, was to fortify defenses
and, As a result, it also, created
the, revenue, savings for our
management in terms of, risk reduction
and, buffing against the breaches
and, other cyber criminal activity.
today I would like to share, with you
the journey when the took the challenges
we faced, the strategies we implemented
and the insights we gained along the way.
let's start from the
beginning, if it should.
when I first joined the company,
it was clear that the organization
was an, an important turning point
regarding cyber security posture.
at the time when I joined, it was a,
solid and global financial institution
and a billion of dollars in transactions
annually with billion dollars of revenues.
and, though it was only the
question when the cyber criminals
would start to attack it.
by creating a, security, roadmap.
And as we know, cybercriminals were
no longer lone hackers, but organized
groups employing advanced persistent
threats, zero day exploits, and some of
them were even state sponsored attacks.
Existing cyber security framework
wasn't consistent enough and some
of the aspects were overdue to
counter modern security threats.
That was the first critical point we
found out when I joined the company.
The lack of consistent unified approach,
not only created the operational
efficiencies, but also left us
vulnerable to a sophisticated attack
that could exploit this, disparities.
The amount of risks that we found,
during the project and during
the transformation was enormous.
while we were counting the potential
losses, we found out that, it could
be exceeding 500 million annually.
Due to various data breaches, system
downtime, and non compliance penalties.
Moreover, the threat of losing client
trust and market share loomed large.
As you probably know, the larger
organization, the, the more
painful is, such cases are.
I'm speaking about mostly about the
trust and, relationship with the
customers, in terms of, security
breaches and in terms of security.
measurements that we took to protect
their assets and, basically money.
Right.
the United insurgency, we embarked on
a comprehensive project to overhaul
our cybersecurity infrastructure.
we formed out the goal.
The goal was pretty clear.
we need to design and implement a
unified resilient security framework
that would safeguard our global financial
ops and ensure strict compliance to.
internal, international, security
standards such as VFM, PCI,
DSS, as a global, again, as a
global financial institution,
adhering to those international
security standards is a must.
And none of the, companies, operating
globally could not, adhere to them.
the main focus and the goal was that.
then we started to identify
vulnerabilities and the risks.
The first step, as I said, was it, we
conducted a thorough risk assessment,
which involved several key activities.
We involved, A lot of people from
the business side, management,
infrastructure, compliance.
So all the departments were there to help
us, to start our security transformation.
so where to start from, our risk
assessment, was divided by five steps.
Five critical steps, we've identified
those as network vulnerability
scanning, penetration testing,
security configuration audits,
application security testing, and
employee security awareness evaluation.
we started from the network
vulnerability scanning.
Why?
the answer is Pretty simple.
since the, organization is, global,
it should be available from any
point of the global or the globe.
That means everyone could try
to attack us, scan us, whatever.
So we have to be prepared and, secure our
external perimeter as much as possible.
we use the advanced vulnerability scanning
tools like wallets or kinetics to perform
extensive scans of our infrastructure.
Okay.
We've identified over 1, 000
vulnerabilities, some of them
were pretty severe and critical.
I don't want to share those, due
to, ethics and, NDAs and contracts.
but trust me, those was really, severe.
yeah, for instance, we found
system running outdated
versions of operating systems.
the problem was that, those
systems were externally phased.
Which means that, each and every
person out there with malicious intent
could easily start to hack them.
And that means that would result
in a significant damage to the
organization due to breach.
The second step was penetration testing.
Once again, it was conducted
both in external and internal
infrastructure and applications.
First of all, we started with
validation of, discovered and,
identified vulnerabilities.
We conducted a penetration testing
using tools like Metasploit, Blurb, Kali
Linux, and many other testing techniques.
We focused on confirming
the most critical one.
Additionally, our application
security team simulated attacks
to exploit vulnerabilities.
That allowed us to track the
events that occur once the external
attacker would like to penetrate us.
So that also enhanced our security
operation center and security
operation center playbooks.
So we were ready to act if
something like that happens.
Further, we are now prepared, this
exercise highlighted the potential for
a malicious actor to cause significant
damage and, that allowed us to, have
the, management attention as much as
possible to, to close off those risk
or at least to, start remediation.
Then we began with security configuration
audits of our infrastructure.
We performed detailed audits of our
security configurations, including
firewalls, servers, endpoints, pretty
much everything that we had inside.
we even, assessed our Bluetooth mouse
and keyboards and headphones, in the
offices, because those could be also.
A part of, security, security attack
surface, we found several critical
misconfigurations is the low, any
to the, external, destinations.
And this configuration is good.
Have a load attackers.
Concentrate our network and
exfiltrate data without the detection.
It also highlighted us a area
where it should be focused.
On further, to harden our infrastructure.
We've used, advanced tools for that.
I'll speak about them later.
All right.
the first one application security
testing, we had the in house development
team, as part of the development, they,
created the web applications, mobile
applications, and the rest, of course,
external interface, of course, APIs.
facing our customers
and, not only customers.
we started to analyze and test
those in terms of security.
We used, both static and dynamic
application, security tools, Avast ZAP.
We've uncovered several critical
vulnerabilities, like cross site
scripting and secure API endpoints.
I'm speaking mostly about the, Improper
authentication the requests, especially
inside of the, authorized area, right
after the client logins, after the client
enters his credentials and all the stuff.
So inside, mostly those vulnerabilities
were found there, as well as,
improper input validation on several
fields within the registration
form in spite of onboarding.
All right, so the tips.
And the last one, companies consider
people as similar asset as the server,
as the cash on the balance and the rest.
the last point here, but probably the
last point in the risk assessment part,
but the first in terms of defense.
because, as we know, 95 percent of
successful attacks started with social
engineering, which means that, the,
humans are the weakest part in terms of
security posture within the organization.
We started with, basic phishing
tests, and phishing simulations.
the results were concerning.
Most of the employees, 35 percent
of the employees clicked on phishing
links and then provided their login
credentials and fake, login pages.
Which is very bad in terms of,
security, gate, the first security
gate of the defense, right?
Of the defense in depth.
that also underscored the need of
security, advanced training and
security, security awareness management.
After we've performed all those risk
assessments, we needed to present
these findings in a way that would
resonate with the executive leadership.
By quantifying the risks in financial
terms, we've illustrated the potential
impact, and you'd be surprised.
the financial exposure, the potential
losses exceeding 500 million annually
due to breaches, fraud, and downtime.
Regulatory penalties, non compliance
with standards like SWIFT and PCI DSS
could result in fines up to 50 million.
and of course, reputational damage,
loss of client trust could lead to
a 15, decrease in market share and
that's an equity up to hundreds
of millions and loss of revenue.
The question was, how are
we going to mitigate those?
The answer was pretty simple, we had
a strategic cybersecurity initiatives.
Armed with those information, we
developed a comprehensive cybersecurity
strategy focusing on several key areas.
The first one, related to
network, was related to network
segmentation and micro segmentation.
We divided the network into separate
segments based on function and
sensitivity using reliance, subnets.
using additional compliance checks
on the device before they enter
the network perimeter office.
office when the person comes in
person in the office, not the,
working from home, kind of thing.
The second was micro segmentation.
We used software defined networking
technologies like Illumio.
We enforced granular the workload level.
Each application and service was isolated,
and communication was strictly controlled.
This strategy appeared to be a zero trust
model, where no network traffic is trusted
by default, and every communication
is authenticated and authorized.
That was the first break in our
cybersecurity framework and strategy
that allowed to reduce lateral movement
and other risks that were related
to insecure communications within
the network and potential breaches.
So that was more a proactive measure.
Rather than the, detective
then, using the cutting edge technologies,
AI and machine learning, we started
to move forward using the S I M.
we deployed advanced the same
solutions like a, LK with dark trace.
And we integrated them both,
enhance them with machine learning.
Thank you.
And, started using AI, which
was provided by ALK mostly.
We started to analyze the
log data in real time.
This allowed us to detect anomalies
and potential threats that
traditional systems might miss.
And, spoiler alert, several incidents,
haven't happened exactly because of that.
again, since the people, the most, the
biggest asset within the organization
in terms of security, we started to
integrate with the user and entity
behavior analytics, by establishing
baseline behavior patterns for users and
device, we could identify deviations.
Indicating of malicious activity.
For example, if an employee account
suddenly started accessing large volumes
of data at unusual hours, the system
would flag this for investigation.
We started to harden our
endpoints, by implementing endpoint
detection and response, recognizing that
endpoints are common entry points for
attackers with deployed DDR solutions.
And they were installed on all endpoints
without any exception, together without
our CIM providing real time monitoring
and automated response for the threats.
That also allowed us to perform an
automated isolation, again, in conjunction
with, Cutting edge technologies like
ML and AI, if an endpoint exhibited
suspicious behavior, it could be
automatically isolated from the network
to prevent the spread of malware.
identity and access management.
Additional brick in our cyber
security framework and our resilient
To strengthen our access controls, we
implemented multi factor authentication
implemented across all critical
systems to add an extra layer of
protection beyond classic passwords.
Additionally, we've implemented it
with Microsoft SSO and Azure SSO, which
allowed us to control the access at
one point without any problems in terms
of revoking access, providing access,
Role based access control.
Another thing that is pretty much basic.
Ensuring that employers have
access only to the resources
necessary for their roles.
Minimizing the risk of unauthorized
access and privilege creep.
Security orchestration
automation and response.
Another tool that allowed
us to enhance and embrace
automation to enhance efficiency.
Automated incident response using
SOAR platform with automated responses
to commonly security incidents.
As an example, we've created several
scripts for containment after
triggers on endpoints and servers.
Playbooks, that's a common thing.
But when we started, we understood
that we have to dive deep, each,
case to develop a sophisticated
playbook to respond to incidents.
Develop standardized procedures for
handling different types of incidents,
ensuring a consistent and swift
response based on metering matrix.
And especially for our, we've done that
mostly for our SLC operation center.
Compliance and standardization.
To address inconsistencies across regions.
we have to perform, another audit,
but more focused on, compliance side.
policy standardization, that's the thing
we started from because that's the, soil
ground for each and every organization.
to have basic procedures and
policies and standards unified and
aligned within the organization.
We created a centralized security
policy management system.
All regions are required to adhere
to the same security standards,
reducing gaps in our defenses.
And of course, international
standards compliance.
Aligned our control with frameworks
like ISO 27001 SWIFT, customer security
program, and the others like, NIST,
that also improved, security,
but also simplified.
Compliance reporting, those are
worldwide known standards and, those
who are created, by best practices
and, based on security experience
for the past 20 plus years, right?
That's quite a solid, term in
terms of, experience again.
Employee training and awareness.
the first thing it's understanding
the importance of the human element,
mandatory training programs.
So of course, no one likes them, right?
But still there should be some.
We launched a comprehensive cyber
security training for all employees.
We gamified.
our.
Users won't be just staring on the
presentation on pictures, but they
were like games, so they enjoyed it.
At the end, they would receive a badge
and achievement, so they successfully
passed and they could be proud of it.
Then we started to perform regular
simulation just to train our users.
Because even if we, if we see that the
user was, successfully phished and,
entered his credentials to a malicious
website, we still could train him.
So that's like the, a chance for
both of us, for us to change our.
Training system in case it wasn't
successful enough and sufficient
enough, so the user was over the
time, the, we reduced the click rate
and fishing numbers from 35 to 5%.
And you can imagine how happy we
were once we tracked this five
person for more than three months.
So trust me, that's quite an achievement
for any security professional out there.
I'd like to share some cases and successes
within, Our boss to stable and resilient
security within the organization.
So the first one was a part in
an advanced resistant threat.
As I said earlier, that was only a
question of time when, APT will target us.
And try to breach, we found that one
APT group targeted our organization,
attempted to infiltrate our infrastructure
through spear phishing emails,
containing malicious attachments,
exploiting zero day vulnerabilities.
That was, our, one of
our C level employees.
For, some period of time, he
received several phishing emails.
And accidentally clicked on it.
we use detection tools, as I
mentioned, AI and ML powered SIM,
ELK, detected unusual email patterns
and flagged them for investigation.
additionally, we found in our
threat intelligence that, compute
PC of, our employee tried to
reach, IP with a bad reputation.
Our automated SOR playbooks,
for untied the suspicious emails
and alerted the security team.
but only after the email was clicked,
unfortunately, but by neutralizing
the threat before any damage to
cure, we prevented potential losses.
between the.
Email was still open, but after it
was open, it was quarantine and the.
The device was isolated for further
investigation as soon as possible.
So there were no damage.
yeah, that was one of the cases where
all of our bricks, except again,
first one, the people, succeeded.
The second case I would like
to share, it's also related to,
cutting edge technologies, and,
how they, Increasing efficiency
in terms of responding to threats.
an employee inadvertently
downloaded ransomware that
attempted to encrypt network shares.
that was a, I remember it as today.
That was a late evening.
I received the email and, alert
that our EDR system, identified
that no file encryption activities
on one of our, network shares.
devices and, network shares,
try to access network shares,
with, elevation, pre reached.
the infected endpoint was automatically
isolated and files were restored
from, secure backups, storage.
Again, that's the, an example
when the threat entered our
infrastructure by phishing,
phishing, social engineering, right?
later on we've identified that was a
fake, adverts, advertisement about one
of the popular messengers out there.
So yeah, this is again an
example of how ML and advanced AI
technologies could help you with
identifying and react proactively.
to, to issues and to threats that
could reach your infrastructure.
Outcome was pretty simple.
It was pretty straightforward, right?
Zero data loss and no runs on
failed, saving approximately
5 million on potential costs.
Later on in the news, we found out
that several companies in our, industry
faced those issues and, some of them
paid, some of them, faced, significant
disruption of, services provided
to the customers and therefore lost
revenue and customer trust as well.
Through this experience, we
gained valuable insights.
First of all, proactive risk
management is essential.
Automation enhances efficiency.
Standardization reduces vulnerabilities.
Aligning security with business goals.
I'll start with the
proactive risk management.
It's an essential thing
within any organization.
Regular risk assessments and
continuous monitoring are critical.
Being proactive can help you to
identify and address vulnerabilities
before they are exploited.
But what if any vulnerability is
still there and is being exploited?
Like zero day, right?
Automation doesn't replace human expertise
and such, but by automating routine
tasks, responses, basic security tasks,
our security team could focus on more
complex threats and strategic initiatives.
Standardization within the infrastructure,
within the assets, within the
everything inside the organization.
Consistent security practices
across all regions eliminate gaps
that attackers could exploit.
It also simplifies compliance
efforts and audits.
Once again, plenty of the standards
would simplify cybersecurity team life
within the organization quite much.
I'm speaking about ISO, NIST,
and other regulations that are
worldwide known and could be used
in each and every organization.
Those could be tuned based on your needs.
Your organization could start benefit
from those right from the beginning, right
from the start of the implementation.
The fourth one, it's aligning
security with business goals.
Again, security is more a support
department, I would say, right?
Security should not
interfere with the business.
Security initiatives should support
business objectives, not the otherwise.
By demonstrating how security
enhances customer trust and
protective revenue, we gain support
from leadership and stakeholders.
Which means they have, we are able
to prove management that security
really works and saves money.
Saving money is one of the
point in increasing revenue.
So for business, it was
quite straightforward.
We save money, we increase our revenue.
We increase customer
trust, we increase revenue.
If you fail.
That means our revenue goes down.
So the security is quite important.
so by analyzing those, we analyzed
and came to a point where we should
present the financial impact that
was created by security initiatives.
we avoided losses.
Operational savings, downtime
reductions, and return on investments.
The, what it was, this
were over 90 millions.
That was quite impressive, but financial
impact is not the only thing that was
increased and improved after we performed
all those and completed all those.
security initiatives.
Our efforts also bolstered our reputation.
We achieved compliance, we obtained ISO
27001 and completed SWIFT, enhancing
our credibility with our customers and
within the business industry as well.
So we really made one step up in terms
of our maturity as an organization.
Customer retention, client confidence
led to 7 percent increase in customer
retention, contributing to revenue
growth that's related not only to,
business customers, I mean like financial
organization, but regular clients as well.
It's all I've said.
I would like to share the recommendations
for implementation of the sharing
all this journey and all these
obstacles and problems I've mentioned.
So the first and most important
thing is to invest in.
Security and investing
in advanced technology.
These technologies can process
vast amounts of data and identify
patterns that humans might miss.
That's one more important topic here.
I'd like to mention, we
are all people, right?
all people have, a maximum
amount of energy they can spend
during the working day, right?
People can't work 100 percent
efficient, throughout, 8, 9, 10 hours.
This is where technology and
advanced technology like AI and
machine learning comes in handy.
The second one is implement
layered security, of course.
It's adopted in defense
and death strategy.
Zero trust, using multiple, security
measures and, different layers to
protect against various types of threats.
That's That will become basic in, I
would say in one year that will become
base, a basic thing for each and
every organization, even in startups.
The third thing, there
should be a standardization.
You have to standardize security
protocols, ensure that security
policies and procedures are consistent
across all regions and departments.
Of course, there could be deviations
based on, local government,
local government rules, policies,
internal policies, and the rest.
But still those should be
standardized, standardized, this reduce
vulnerabilities and simplify compliance.
The fourth point, foster a
security conscious culture.
again, people is the main asset within
the organization, similar to cash
on the balance, and, as confirmed
by two cases, that's the weakest
part in every security within the
organization, within any organization.
Each company should invest in regular
training and awareness programs,
empowering employees to be the first
line of defense against cyber threats.
And the fifth point, alignment.
Alignment of security strategy
with business strategy.
Strategy and, value of cyber security
should be communicated in business terms.
None of the business representatives
within any department except
technology do understand the risk
of, for example, lateral movement.
my advice here is to demonstrate
how security initiatives protect
revenue, enhance customer trust,
and support growth by quantifying
the risk of lateral movement.
and quantifying the measures that
were, developed and how they support
the business strategy within the
one, two, or maybe three years.
It depends on each and
every organization again.
So I would like to conclude
here, in today's interconnected
world, vast and rapidly growing.
Each and every industry, especially
financial industry, cybersecurity
is not just a technical issue
for the business no more.
It's a fundamental business concern.
Our journey demonstrates that with
a strategic approach, it's possible
to significantly reduce risks and
achieve substantial financial savings.
By identifying vulnerabilities,
implementing advanced security measures,
and fostering a culture of security
awareness, we protected our assets
and supported our company growth.
I hope our expertise provides
valuable insight that you can
apply within your own organization.
Cybersecurity is a continuous journey, and
staying ahead of evolving threats requires
commitment, innovation, and collaboration.
What are your thoughts
about the conference today?
I am happy to answer any
questions you might have.
And thank you for your attention.
It was lovely to have you.
Thank you.