Hello, a warm welcome at Con
42 Incident Management 2024.
Today, I will be speaking about
using generative AI to tackle
API sprawl in enterprises.
But before that, a brief
background about myself.
I'm Anirudh Karandikar, Principal
Software Engineer at Fortune 500 Company.
I'm a full stack engineer with a
niche skill set in API management.
As part of my work profile, I
deal with the entire API lifecycle
from ideation to governance.
The observations, ideas expressed
here are strictly my own.
Now let's take a look at the agenda.
First, we'll discuss about some
history to build a context.
Then we'll talk about the problem
statement, which is API sprawl.
Then we'll take a look at the proposed
construct to deal this problem statement.
Then we'll take a deeper
look at the governance model.
Then we'll explore the API discovery tool.
Then we'll talk about API
documentation and then some strategies
to control existing API sprawl.
So let's dive in.
So roughly about a decade ago, most
of the enterprises started their
move from monolith to microservices.
And for those dealing in APIs, No, what
advantages or benefits microservices
offer, but just to recap microservices
architecture is a software design
approach where application is built as a
collection of small independent services.
Each services focus on
specific business function.
So this is usually known as single
responsibility model, and they offer
wide range of benefits, scalability,
like each individual microservices can
be scaled independently irrespective
of others, depending upon demand.
Faster development.
The modularity leads to faster
development, as in different teams can
work on different set of microservices.
Resilience.
This modular structure offers fault
tolerance, and even if one service goes
down, rest of the services can still
serve other business functionalities.
Easier maintenance.
Again, this modular structure helps
to make maintenance easy, and mostly
there are different teams managing
different set of microservices.
Agility, the faster development,
scalability, resilience, make
microservices agile and the time
to market is greatly reduced.
Technological diversity.
I think this is the key advantage.
Unlike monolith, technology
is not a limiting factor.
We can very well have a set of
microservices developed in Java and
other set of microservices developed
in other language, say Python, coexist
in the same deployment architecture.
And finally, cost efficiency.
I think the whole microservices
architecture is built or geared towards
resource optimization, thus lowering
the infrastructure and operation costs.
If we take a look at some key milestones.
So between 2011 to 2013, companies
like Netflix and Amazon pioneered
the adoption of microservices.
2014, 2015, this term.
became widely recognized
in software community.
And then from 2016 to present, with
the rise of cloud native technologies,
containerization, mostly Docker, and
container orchestration tools, read
Kubernetes, microservice adoption
has grown by leaps and bounds.
That brings to our problem statement.
With the widespread adoption of REST
APIs and microservices, it has led to
an explosion in the number of APIs.
And I'm talking about
tens of thousands of APIs.
Many enterprises adopted distributed
development as orgs within
enterprises moved at different pace.
And this setup provided team
autonomy and reduced conflicts.
So talking about this, like each
individual team maintaining their own
set of repositories, their own standards,
their own guidelines, their own timelines
to deploy these services into production.
However, this setup created
difficulties as enterprises scaled.
And following were the
main contributing factors.
First and foremost of them is duplication.
Different teams creating APIs
that serve the same function.
So at any given point in
time, all the teams needed to
solve for some common issues.
example, location services or address
management or user management.
And to solve for these, everyone
created a flavor of the same solution,
thus resulting in duplication.
Second problem is harder to
exercise security control and major.
So here the problem is twofold
non standard APIs expose different
attack vectors and a large number of
APIs expose greater attack surface.
So think of this from, from the point
of view of horizontal organizations
like cybersecurity or security.
If they want to enforce governance,
it becomes very difficult if the
APIs are scattered and non standard.
Third are operational inefficiencies.
Again, since it's hard to enforce
standards, each, each team can
have different operational needs.
thus creating overheads, operational
overheads and leading to maintenance
and performance issues and fourth,
which is not directly related to the
distributed architecture, but often
found is inconsistent documentation.
So incomplete or outdated API
documentation makes it hard to
find and reuse existing APIs.
So even if the two internal teams were
to collaborate and they are using the
design, contract driven development.
Then, the gap between the
documentation and the actual API
causes a lot of, a lot of issues.
So what's the proposed construct?
Like, how can we solve
this particular problem?
So before we look at the
construct, we need to understand
why centralization matters.
A decentralized approach leads
to scattered APIs, inconsistent
standards, difficulty in tracking
changes or enforcing governance.
By moving to a centralized monorepo
model, we can have a single repository
that maintains all the API contracts,
which offers not only transparency,
but it also improves visibility.
Teams can access, a unified
source of API definition.
This in turn increases collaboration
and accelerates development cycles.
So let's take a look at, this is like
a blueprint of the proposed construct.
There are different parts of the
solution and we'll talk about them.
So the first and foremost
is centralization.
And by centralization, I don't mean
that, like each individual teams
can still retain the implementation
in their individual repositories.
When centralization of the API
definitions or the API contracts.
This certainly needs to be centralized
so that it becomes a single source
of truth for all the APIs within an
organization or within an enterprise.
The second and the foremost step is
defining business rules and standards.
A few examples of this are naming
nomenclature, like, how do you want
to name your APIs, or how do you
want to name the parts of your APIs,
like base path or the actual path.
Most of, what standards do you,
does an enterprise want to use?
Like most of the APIs today,
or most of the companies today
use Open API specification.
beyond this.
Every enterprise can define
certain custom standards.
For example, in OpenAPI specifications,
you can extend the tags.
So enterprises today can have
categorization to identify their domains.
There can be domains like payment,
there can be domains like supply chain.
So you can create separate tags to
classify and further categorize the APIs.
The third is programmatic enforcement, and
we'll see this in the governance model.
But once you define the rules and
standards, there needs to be a
programmatic enforcement of these
rules so that all the API contracts
adhere to these standards and
there is no bypassing of them.
The fourth point is about starter kits.
So let's say we have a unified
definition, like all the APIs are
defined in a certain standard.
Okay.
Now, if we want to extend this to
code, there are libraries today
which can work on your API contracts
and spit out a skeleton of code.
What one team, what the team
should do is, Go one level down.
Like every API today needs
some cross cutting concerns.
Be it logging.
it needs a standard logging format.
It needs standards for observability.
It needs standards for security.
Your auth and auth z mechanisms.
And it needs a standard way of
defining errors and exceptions.
These are some of the major
cross cutting concerns.
There can be others.
In addition to this, if you're
deploying using containers in a
Kubernetes environment, you also
need images and you can, this is a
place to standardize those images.
So the advantages of
this are again twofold.
As an enterprise, you can exercise
controls or set standards on
how, these crosscutting concerns
can be leveraged for it.
For instance, if you want to change
your logging standards, this would
be one place where you change that.
Or if you want.
To add additional policies, on security.
This is the place you do so that
everyone using the starter kits will
automatically inherit, these standards.
And the second point is from
development perspective.
So as a developer, I don't have to
worry about this cross cutting concerns
because I know that the deployment unit,
generated out of the starter kit will
have all these cross cutting concerns.
Standardized cross cutting concerns baked
into it, and all that I have, I would,
I need to care is the functional code.
Okay, so once, let's say we have
established all of these, the next in line
is how do we harness AI on top of this?
So I would feed all of
this rich data into an LLM.
Apart from this API definition, we
can also pair it with the actual
deployment or lives live services data.
Like these are the APIs
that are actually deployed.
And from production, we can get a rich
set of data like on usage patterns,
and other, Other observability metrics.
So this combined with the source
data provides very rich insights.
And we will look into a few use cases,
but then based on that, we can develop
the API discovery to, also, like most
of the enterprises today use dashboards.
so there are two types of dashboards, one
primarily used for troubleshooting and
the other are the executive dashboards.
Thank you for listening.
That provide the qualitative data.
So imagine, the A.
I.
Insights derived from this rich set.
They can provide a rich context to
the already existing dashboards.
Those are the use cases.
Now let's talk or double click
a bit on the governance model,
which we talked earlier again.
There are many ways in which
governance can be applied.
Below is just a sample
based on CICD paradigm.
So let's say we have defined a
centralized repo wherein we are
maintaining our API contracts.
And if I were to check in a new API
contract or, if I were to check in
modifications to an existing API
contract, first and foremost, my
pipeline would check for compliance
policies, like whether my API is
compliant with all the policies.
That have defined.
Secondly, it will run a linter on top
of it and can generate maybe a score.
but basically linter, it will run
linter to check for standards.
The third is, quality gate.
once you have run for standard
and compliance policies,
you can define a threshold.
is this API matching a certain threshold?
If not, you can fail and give feedback.
To the developers and only if and if
it crosses that certain threshold,
then you can allow that contract
to move ahead in the API lifecycle.
Next is the similarity check.
So if you remember earlier, we talked
about API sprawl and duplication
being the number one reason.
Contribute into this problem.
So how can we prevent it
right at the inception stage?
So this is where we check when an
API contract is being committed.
We can do a similarity check
using the LLM to see whether it is
similar to any of the existing APIs.
Now there are multiple criterias
to do this similarity check.
It can be done on your request response.
It can be done on your descriptions.
It can be done on the downstream
domains that you're calling.
But the idea is to check whether,
to check whether you really need a
net new API or what are what you are
trying to achieve can be achieved by
extending any of the existing APIs.
So this presents a simple idea
on how governance, programmatic
governance can be enforced so that
we have a way of enforcing standards.
And also reducing duplication.
Now let's take a look about if
we were to build an API discovery
tool, using AI, how would I do that?
Before that, let's take a
look at the building blocks.
If I, if we were to build this tool,
so first and foremost is the LLM.
This would be your, chat GPT or
cloud or llama or any other model.
we basically need a
natural language processor.
Secondly, we need a vector database.
This can be a Pinecone or FAS, but
basically something where indexed
data can reside and LLMs can do
a semantic search on top of it.
Third, we need an API
documentation parser.
There are many libraries available
in the market, which can parse the
OpenAPI specification or Swagger.
And fourth, we would need a web interface.
This is basically wherein the users would
type in your natural language query and,
would receive the API recommendations.
So if you had this building blocks in
place, These are the high level steps.
So first is the data preparation.
so like I said, we have our
common repo containing all the API
contracts and it's a rich data set.
It has all the endpoint URLs.
It has your request methods.
It has responses.
It has parameters.
It has descriptions.
All that is needed is to organize
this in a structured format,
which is very easy to feed.
The most commonly used format is JSON.
but there is no such restriction.
Second is indexing and context building.
The metadata that is prepared in step
one needs to be indexed and it needs
to be stored as something called
as embeddings in a vector database.
So in AI terms, embedding
represents a real world object.
So whatever So think of this if
you have some nouns in the real
world, those are represented as
embeddings in the vector database.
Secondly, we also need to build a mapping
system that links API functionalities
to the natural language queries.
And what do I mean by that?
So for example, if someone queries or
someone asks, how do I get user details?
Then, the LLM needs to know which
API endpoints to point it to in order
to answer this particular query.
Transcribed Third is
building the query interface.
this is basically creating an
interface for natural language parsing.
And the other part of this is
to craft prompts for LLM based
on the natural language queries.
And the fourth part is
the response generation.
this is where the relevant
information is identified.
LLM will generate a detailed response.
Now, here, These steps, this step needs
to be done in an iterative manner.
Like the first response that is
generated may not be detailed enough
or may not be, may not have all
the information, that is needed.
So we need to ask for more
prompts, ask for more questions,
do it in an iterative fashion and
enhance that particular response.
The other part of it is, like whenever
this response is generated, it.
It can give snippets from the actual
sliders or actual API definitions.
And, this is known as
contextual augmentation.
So if you were to build, or follow
all these steps, The simplified
flow would look something like that.
A user would go to a web interface,
would type in a natural language
query like, give me user details.
This will be converted into a
prompt, which would do a semantic
search on the indexed data.
That's the processing on
the vector DB and LLM.
And the output is the response, which
we could see in the user interface.
With all the necessary details
and the contextual augmentation
going, moving to the next
topic about API documentation.
So let's say we have at
the setup build already.
How can we use leverage the
setup to do API documentation?
The steps are more or less similar.
So the first step is data preparation,
which we have already done as
we have fed our common source.
Common repository data.
The second is we have to define a
document, documentation structure.
So let's say if we want to create
a document, then, what are the
sections that document will have?
It will have an overview.
Let's say it will have endpoint details.
It will have your input
or output parameters.
It would have some examples.
and then it will have an error
handling section, which will describe
what exceptions or errors to expect.
The third part of this is, Prompt
engineering for document generation.
similar to what we saw earlier, we will
have to build prompts for LLM in order
to provide the output needed in the
needed for the documentation structure.
And the fourth is response generation.
The key unlock of this
documentation is with automation.
Again, here there are two
scenarios to consider.
One, it could be like a mass generation.
You already have a centralized
repo or an API documentation
for let's say 1000, 1000 APIs.
And you want to do, and
you want to do a bulk.
processing, and develop and generate
documentation for all these thousand APIs.
And the other use case is if you already
have documentation, how can you augment
or keep it up to date as and when
you make changes to an existing API?
Again, there can be several
ways, but I have provided an
example using CSV pipeline.
So first and foremost is again, like if
I were to do a check in on one of the API
contracts, I would query, that repository
for all these, endpoints and gather
all the information, in that contract.
Secondly, I will create a prompt.
this is a programmatic creation of
prompt and it's, it would be, pretty
easy because the construct for the
prompt is pretty much locked in.
All I have to change, each
time are the endpoint details.
The third important step in the
pipeline would be compiling a response.
So the output that you get from
LLM, it may not be formatted,
like most of the developer
portals that the enterprises have.
Would store the documentation
in, in, let's say, Markdown
or HTML or PDF formats.
So you need that output to be styled,
let's say if someone is using Markdown.
So the third step talks about that,
that the needed styling to be applied
on the data or on the response
that is generated from the LLM.
And the fourth step is to,
actually integrate This generated
document into a developer portal.
So if the developer portal is a Git
repo, the fourth step would, would
raise, an MR to the developer portal.
also, this is the step where
developers can review the
documentation request because the
ones that is generated may not be.
Perfect or may not have all the detailed
information and that would be the
stage where developers can provide
even more context or they can provide
some additional information like links
to existing documentation or links to
existing sites, so on and so forth.
This approach will always ensure that your
documentation stays true to the code or
to your API contract that you have defined
moving ahead.
Strategies to address and
control existing API sprawl.
So above strategies are.
Are good if you're starting new
right when you're starting new You
have all the majors that, that we
talked about, you are controlling the
API sprawl right at the beginning.
But how about the enterprises
or companies that already have
tens and thousands of APIs?
so I think the steps to solve
the first step is still the same.
Like you, you have to centralize your API
definition and establish common standards.
And it can be a gradual move.
It need not be a big bang.
Small organizations, small teams can
start moving towards the centralized repo.
And the more teams adopt this, the
more standardization and better
visibility the enterprises gain.
The second use case is, or the
second important step is identify
unused or redundant APIs.
So this is where that step, which
we discussed earlier, of feeding
the live deployment data into the,
into the LLM would come in handy.
So we can utilize the AI driven insights.
to analyze API usage patterns and
then identify APIs that are outdated,
underutilized, or have multiple
versions serving the same function.
This will help streamline the API
portfolio by either deprecating
or phasing out unnecessary APIs.
So what I mean by that is In production,
if we find that certain APIs are not
used at all, or certain versions of
existing APIs are not used at all, then
the easiest way to reduce API sprawl is
to decommission unused or duplicate APIs.
The third is Cluster similar
APIs for consolidation.
Again, earlier we saw an example
wherein, as in when I tried to check
in an API, it did a similarity check.
That was for one API, but we can extend
that same logic to the whole set of APIs
and then form cohorts of similar API.
Once these cohorts are formed, these
can be then manually reviewed and
we can generate one main API out of
them and decommissioned rest others.
this will effectively help to
control or curb, the duplication
among the existing APIs.
Fourth is implement custom
tagging for better management.
so many a times, in the existing
production, scenario, we teams
or enterprises need to target
one particular set of APIs.
What do I mean by that?
many enterprises can have public
facing APIs and internal APIs.
Let's say, there is a new security
protocol that needs to be applied.
Since the risk is greater for the
public facing APIs, I want to, I want
to apply this to the public facing APIs.
That's where I will use the API
discovery tool, write a natural
language query, that hey, give me a
list of all the public facing APIs.
And if we already have tags for the
segmentation, then you should receive
this list in a matter of seconds.
The other use case is
deployment platforms.
Let's say we have multiple deployment
platforms and we want to retire one.
Migrate all services
from one to the other.
Then again, the API discovery
tool can be used to get this list.
The use cases are endless.
but the idea here is.
Once you have an API construct, once
you have an API discovery tool based on
the AI construct, you can then slice and
dice the API sets to suit your particular
need, to suit your particular needs.
So effectively to conclude or the TLDR
version of this talk is generative AI
can help transform the API landscape
by enabling intelligent API discovery.
Similarity detection and
automated documentation.
Secondly, developers can prevent the
creation of duplicate APIs, effortlessly
find existing solution and receive
real time feedback or suggestion
that can enhance the productivity
and accelerate time to market.
Third, for production or live
systems, integrating AI with API
gateway facilitated continuous
monitoring of API usage patterns.
providing data to optimize,
consolidate, or retire API
based on actionable insights.
Not only this, but if we can go
one step beyond, based on API usage
patterns, we can even drive resource
optimization, further lowering the
operational and infrastructure costs.
So to, so in essence, right use
of AI becomes the catalyst That
empowers enterprises to navigate
API sprawl, turning complexity
into a managed strategic asset.
That's it.
Thank you Con42 for providing
the platform to present my ideas.
And thank you for the viewers
who have made it thus far.
I sincerely hope you found a couple of
ideas that might resonate with you and
which you can apply in your everyday work.
Enjoy the rest of the conference.