Hello and welcome to Con 42.
I am Maxim Kupriyanov.
My talk today is network incidents or
what to know before the chaos strikes.
Few words about myself.
I work as a Site Reliability Engineer,
Production Engineer, before that System
Administrator, For a lot of years,
and I've seen a lot, I'd say, I wish
I see them less, but, yes, that's
true, a lot of different incidents,
and, those of them who were connected
to the, or root cause by the network
services were the most devastating ones.
let's dive deep what is actually
a network incident and, like,
why it's so devastating.
First of all, a network incident
is just an expected event that
disrupts or degrades critical
network services, impacting their
availability, integrity, or performance.
Sounds?
Very similar to any other incident.
But, point is, critical network services.
Let's take a look what they are.
And these are DNS, DHCP, Routing, VPN.
These are infrastructure services.
They are security services including
firewall intrusion detection
prevention, security certificate
centers, physical access control.
These are directory services.
yes, so you can't authenticate or
authorize your users, the cloud
and container orchestration, or
just web services which deliver
your traffic, CDN, load balancers,
or web service architecture.
That's a very sensitive problem.
point sensitive layer of
software for any organization.
And, why this network incidents
dealing with this critical
services are so disruptive.
First of all, they frequent,
I'd say almost every time they
lead to cascading failures.
for example, if a DNS.
server failed, very likely that a lot
of services that are still dependent
on DNS will start to malfunction.
By the way, please never depend on DNS.
If you can avoid it by any cost.
But still, a lot of
services still do that.
then you lose your monitoring
and diagnostic tools.
Not them, but access to them.
Usually it's very fast.
Frequent story, then downtime
affects multiple stakeholders.
Yes People will come to you or
your network engineer or site
reliability engineer with a question.
What's going on?
We can't work.
Nothing is working do something with that
Difficulty in triage modern networks are
very complicated, especially big ones.
It takes a lot of time to find
the root cause to triage it
and to fix it afterwards, time
consuming troubleshooting.
Yes.
Time is just money.
In that case, if your business
is not working, you're losing
money, increased security risk.
that's, can happen for two reasons.
First of all, you can like.
Firewall or whatever can be malfunctioning
and another story is you can make a
temporary exemption for fixing the issue
And it could lead to the attackers to come
in and do something very violent Okay,
of course reduced business operations.
That's basically It's all it, what
it mean, let's, take a look at a
couple of examples of the recently
happened, network incidents, with
the big tech companies happen like in
2020, 2021, there is no 2023 and 24,
because I was not able to find them.
there were no.
incidents, but still some
of them probably happen.
Okay.
let's start from just
briefly cloudflare outage.
It's, happened in July, 2022.
20 minutes.
Basically, it was a misconfiguration
in router, which, lead to
the, router malfunctioning and
overloading one of the sites.
then, Google cloud outage,
authentication issue, Google accounts
authentication failure was in that time.
So services like Gmail, YouTube, and
Google drive were down for, about an hour.
Then, Microsoft Azure and teams outage.
Actually, teams were not
working for three, three hours.
It happens again because the
Active Directory failure.
So authentication, Fastly
CDN outage, bugging triggered
by customer configuration.
You see a one hour Facebook outage, six
hours that happened because the software
was not correctly handled in several
conditions happened in the network.
Just.
Error in developing.
Amazon web service, AWS
outage, 6 hours and 30 minutes.
And again, there's actually
a software issue, I'd say.
what we, can take from this?
In the IT world, network incidents
are as certain as sunrise, so if you
never had them, you probably will
have them at some point of time.
The anatomy of a network incident.
Let's dive inside of how things
usually start and develop.
first of all, initial situation, you
have a very healthy green system.
The network is fine, systems
are fine, everything is working
perfectly, but then, hardware failure.
For instance, it could be a
power supply of your router,
switch, or line card, whatever.
It could be more tricky stuff,
I've seen from my experience like
a malfunctioning central processing
unit which start to mess up data.
Things could go immediately wrong or they
can take some time to develop, but still.
software issue, two
situations could happen here.
First, just the software bug.
Sometimes it happens by
the way, quite frequently.
another story is unsupported scenario.
And that's is very frequent
nowadays because, unfortunately
developers are not, gods.
They don't know everything.
the systems, Sometimes can predict
that they can be put in such a
situation that they just can't handle
and that's also software issue human
error Usually, it's a misconfiguration
story untested configuration or
just wrong configuration Mistype,
whatever it can Security breaches.
It's usually some kind of external
factor, but someone trying to a break
your perimeter or someone trying to
like make a denial of service for your,
for service or just external factors.
This is usually the most
simple to trash things.
It could be, the flat, or it could
be, kind of fiber cut, or Again, from
my experience, I've seen quite crazy
things, with the animal, somehow
got into the transformer, caused the
short circuit, which caused the fire
and it's caused the power outage.
It can happen as well.
Unfortunately, we can do anything
with that, just external factors.
and my favorite market related events.
I was working for several years
for the marketplace and usually
Black Fridays were very hot for us.
And when a Black Friday starts, a
lot of people come to your services.
A lot of people start
to make transactions.
And it, it depends a lot on
how professional you are in
capacity planning before that.
So you are very close to
the overload at this point.
And this can happen.
Sometimes it happens at,
random, unpredicted moments.
It could be.
Market is chaotic sometimes.
first of all, after the initial trigger,
again, it could develop for a week,
but usually it starts right after that.
What do you see?
You see the service outage.
That's obvious.
You, for instance, a file server
can stop working, database,
communication system, anything,
customer facing application, websites.
It can start to fail.
other terms, all the monitoring and other
tools, send out flood of alerts, multiple
systems and services detect failures,
the team could be overwhelmed with, with
these alerts, or it could be even worse.
When you don't start, you don't
receive any alerts at all because like
system is unreachable completely or
just malfunctioning, user complaints.
Of course, employees and customers, the
usual very social media starts to, to
make some, posts, like any other media
can start to join this party, whatever.
So yeah, this happens.
What's next?
unfortunately, network incidents,
they, very rarely remain isolated.
First of all, interdependent
systems start to fail.
For instance, authentication
service goes down.
All the services dependent on the
user authentication authorization
can fail as well afterwards.
And, applications can start, to be slow.
for listening.
or just failing or in the responsive
and, the worst thing about that,
which can happen and that's frequently
happen, they start to retry, if one
operation fail, application start
to retry the operation and the
application before that application
also start to retry the operation.
And they create such a.
big wave of requests that they usually
kill their underlying services completely.
Traffic bottlenecks,
that's a network thing.
So if you, if the network incident,
if it didn't, it happened because of
a road misconfiguration or maybe a
fiber cut or whatever, your links could
be overloaded and it could lead to,
to all the service using the slings.
failing resource exhaustion.
That's what I was talking
about the many retries.
Each device has its own hardware
limits, and if you start to send to a
server, a million requests per minute
instead of a hundred, as you did
previously, yeah, probably it will,
not handle it, it will, it will fail.
Then, you'll lose visibility and control,
and that's a very difficult thing because
first of all, your inaccessible monitoring
tools are become, your monitoring
tools, Solib story becomes inaccessible,
it's a very frequent thing can happen,
and, you just don't know what happened
in your network with your services.
remote access issue, you can just lose
access to your network, completely,
because of authentication, because
of physical failure, anything,
it just doesn't exist anymore.
or a communication breakdown,
for example, email or messaging
applications can be down, it's
difficult to coordinate, to communicate.
Teams just don't know what's going
on like implode like individual
people's people can can't understand
what's going on what to do
and Incident may expose the
network to additional threats.
Why it can happen not only because
of the network incident happen, but
because of the you know How you try
to fix that sometimes for that, some
holes in firewalls are made or just
firewall is disabled or some, simplified,
applications are landed, which can
handle the situation, but it can help,
but sometimes, attackers just Wait
for exactly this to happen to go on.
So be aware, usually it's a very
bad practice to decrease, security
level during the incidents.
And of course, team face
multiple obstacles in terms
of like stress and pressure.
this network incidents, they are usually
very, Now, people get very nervous because
nothing is working and you face a stress
and pressure from, your stakeholders,
and from your team members, whatever, you
have prioritization dilemmas to solve.
So what start to do first, fixing
this or that you'd never don't know
you need someone to consult to, or.
It's difficult.
Communication with stakeholders,
they are being very tough because
you are fixing, the service, you
don't have time to talk to someone,
to anyone else, and stakeholders,
they are, they just, they want the
service to get, to be working back.
They, try to, communicate with
you, but you're not answering.
All this stuff is happens.
what are the key, take outs
from, this anatomy story?
Network incidents have multiple triggers,
so anything can start an incident.
Sometimes you can never thought about
it, like I said, an animal transformer.
How could that be?
Did it get there?
I don't know.
interconnectedness, magnitudes, impacts.
Network services are very critical
because a lot of other services depend
on them and this is a cascading event.
It's a chain event.
things can go pretty bad.
loss of visibility complicates response.
Yes, of course.
If you don't see what's happening
and you, very frequently you
can't even, tell, if the network.
is faulty or something else.
Preparation.
Now, let's talk about, how
can you be prepared for such
a network incident event?
Key steps you have to take.
First, you need a kind
of a network redundancy.
And by that, I not only mean like
just having multiple network path, or,
setting up multiple routers or whatever.
geographical redundancy as well.
because, for the external factory events,
it could, happen that, this particular
area, the you need, to be present
somewhere else to continue the operations.
you have to do this.
You have to, and this have to
exist before, the incident strikes.
Out of band management
network is a crucial story.
if the network is the issue,
it means that you are losing
access to your services at all.
You get access to your devices at all.
And the only way you can, you can do
something with your network services,
devices, whatever, you can, right
to a data center with the console
cable, and fix something from there.
So if you think before, and you,
can build out of band management
network, things can go pretty well.
You just connect, from the.
I'd say opposite side, you make
the changes, you fix the issue.
Data backs up, backups, of course.
Sometimes network incidents can lead to
a data fail, data loss, unfortunately.
And data backups is crucial for this.
Especially, just to remind, data backups
should not be held in the same location
as the system services are working.
Failover systems, that's pretty obvious
story if you know that any server can
fail, You need something to overtake it.
very important step to take is to conduct
regular system audits and health check.
And by this, I don't just mean,
having a PDF with all green marks
checks that everything's fine.
It should be a continuous thing.
and we're talking about network
assessments and hardware
maintenance, capacity planning.
It should be, You should work on this,
all the time, continuously and subset
of monitoring tools and dashboards.
It's definitely must be
accessible out of band.
Just imagine your network is not
working services, not working.
how do you understand what's
going on actually inside of it?
You need something to monitor
this, some access tools.
You can, rent some services.
elsewhere, export some,
part of data there.
usually it's not a kind
of secret thing of data.
You just some, general health metrics.
You need to have them somewhere.
another very important thing
is to develop a comprehensive
documentation and playbooks.
Usually, all the company I was working
with, It's usually a painful thing
to have a comprehensive documentation
because things are, systems are, they
are being, developed, continuously.
They are changing continuously,
and the best documentation
you can have is in your code.
But, For these network related incidents,
you need to have at least playbooks, and
these playbooks and network documentation,
they should be available remotely, out
of band, external backup, whatever, you
need to have it remotely, you won't have
an access to them when systems will fail.
So just have a copy somewhere
else and regularly check that
you, can access this copy.
Because a crazy thing can happen, people
can just, forget their, alternative
password, forget where they store it.
Okay, and, finally, drills.
You need to like to fire
drills in your network.
it's very important.
they should be done on the regular
basis, drills and simulations.
So you need to be able to take
down your systems, components
of it to see how things goes.
For instance, what will happen
if the DNS server will go down?
Just turn it off in some location.
See what will happen.
If you have some, health budget
on your systems, ensure that your
team is prepared and, evaluate
and update the response plans.
Yes, this seems like slightly, a
lot of work, but if you want to save
some, time, money, nerves, whatever,
just mental health during the network
incidents, if you will do this, you will
be prepared for this network incidents.
let's recap.
Preparations is an ongoing process.
Always have a backup
plan, fire regular drills.
And like with all of that,
the benefits outweigh costs.
Yes, you'll spend a lot on this,
a lot of time, a lot of money,
but you better do this than not.
So let me give you, some tips on
how to, better behave during the
incident, to, to fix it sooner, to,
get less penalties from that, and,
first recommendation is stay calm.
It's probably the most important one.
Stay calm.
if you get in panic, into panic, then
probably you won't be as effective.
the, the network incident
will take much longer time.
It will be harder to fix, whatever.
Stay calm.
the second step, so you should take
the gather initial information.
There could be logs, there could
be other from your systems.
And for that to happen, you need
to out of band access or backup.
sometimes you're there still
accessible and available.
It's a good thing.
It's just depending on how lucky
you are, also user reports.
So sometimes they find the problem before
any other systems will come into play.
And you should determine the scope
of the impact, which systems are.
affected and, like how many of them,
then, establish incident command.
This is again, a very important step.
you have to take it.
you need to assign someone
as an incident manager.
It doesn't mean that the key is
the manager, the key, the captain,
whatever, but he is the point of
content contact for everyone else.
And while Some of your team will,
be very deep diving inside the
debugging, triaging, fixing things.
This captain will maintain the
current state of the incident and
will communicate with another teams
or communicate with the stakeholders,
and synchronize the team activity.
So it's very important and it's
better be, prepared beforehand.
and that, I'll talk about training
previously, and drills, so you should
find the way how to, who will be
assigned to this, incident manager role.
then secure communication channel.
Your team need to have an effective
way to communicate during incidents.
It could happen that, for instance,
if you use, company wide messenger
or whatever, it could be broken.
Because of the network incident,
especially it's true for big
companies which have their,
own communication solutions.
You should have alternative one and
it, everybody should know how to
use it and how to get inside of it.
A lot of incidents happened when
like people were just not aware that
they have a kind of communication
IRC channel or alternative messenger
or how to reach other people.
Sometimes they just were not
able to even find the phone of
their colleague to contact with.
So please do this beforehand.
And, inform stakeholders.
here like honesty is the key.
you better Use a very simple, no technical
terms, in a very simple words, you
should describe to them, what's going
on and what's are your, thoughts about
it very briefly, but they should know,
if they won't get the information.
things can get very, worse
for you, after the incident.
So you better be, communicative with them.
then you have to prioritize
what to fix first.
It's also very important.
Identify a critical service, identify
which service, you can sacrifice,
maybe not completely, but just to put
it in the second stage or whatever,
and determine the root cause.
yeah.
Again, everything is important here, so
determine the root cause as well, and
develop an action plan, and follow it.
These three rules to what to do
with this sounds very simple, but
usually it's very difficult to
do, but still, this is important.
Develop action plan and
follow it all the time.
So if, different people from a team start
to do different things, not according
to plan, things could get even worse.
Communication, everyone, who are, working,
not working affected by the incident
internally, maybe sometimes externally.
And external clients, whatever
should know what is going on.
They don't need technical details.
Usually what they want to know is
like the, when you will fix it and,
what are the, could we run something,
even if these things are failing,
or could we do something with that?
Something like that.
So please establish a communication
protocol and do regular updates
with the current status.
That's incident manager is for.
Sometimes there is an alternative role
as a journalist, but it's for very
big companies, for very big incidents.
Usually incident manager
is pretty fine with that.
inform all affected parties, and,
maintain open lines within the team.
First of all, you need to
share the findings somehow,
internal chat, something.
Second, don't be afraid to ask for help.
Don't sit inside of the problem alone.
Just share it with people
and let them help you.
Sometimes you never know, where it can
get help from, but there are a lot of
small, smart people around and they have
their own experience and they can get, the
idea, or sometimes they can like, just the
Hence to help whatever, and stay positive.
Yeah.
that's, like it's hard, I know.
but if you're not calm, if you're
not positive, it just will take, you
will be less effective and it will
take longer time, to fix the issue.
You have to talk about common pitfalls
which can happen during the incident.
Number one is not rushing without a plan.
It will just add more chaos
to your incident situation.
The second one is poor communication.
Either within your team
or with the stakeholders.
Poor communication within the
team will add more stress,
will make you less effective.
Poor communication with the stakeholders,
not giving them information about
the current state, will probably make
them disappointed in you as a service
provider or employee or whatever.
Number three is ignoring
protocols and procedures.
Please don't do that.
Several protocols and procedures
were, introduced, not just for
fun, but for security or legal
reasons and, like avoiding them
could make things even worse.
the fourth one, overlooking the root
cause, if you missed with that, you
can heal some kind of symptoms and
the situation can reappear very soon.
look deeper and the final, but
also very important thing is
neglecting team well being.
And what I mean by that is that if the
incident is quite long, like it could last
hours or sometimes days, the team could be
overstressed, and, like prone to mistakes.
so if you.
can introduce kind of rotation within
the team or something like this,
it could help think about that.
and finally, let's recap.
so first of all, during the
incident, stay calm and positive.
It's the most important rule,
as I said, please do that.
second, effective communication is
critical within the team with the
stakeholders, both very important with
the clients, of course, teamwork matters.
Don't be afraid to ask for help.
Always share all your findings,
just work as a team, work together.
You will solve this story, this
incident faster and most efficient.
Prioritize actions.
you should.
Take the approach the
problem step by step.
Take the most critical, step,
make it, then next one, and so on.
And avoid the pitfalls we
described in the previous slide.
When the incident is over, you still
need several things to be done.
First of all, analyze what went
wrong, and by that I mean that you
need to have a post incident review
procedure and root cause analysis.
You need to clearly understand why the
incident happened, what was done well
during it, and what could be improved.
These three things.
Then create a feedback loop, and
by that You should update all
the runbooks of the systems that
were involved in the incident.
They could be outdated, they could be
wrong, they could be just not present.
Because if you don't do this, you are
waiting for the history to repeat itself.
And finally, Every network incident
is, troublemaking, at least.
It could be very expensive, finally.
But it's an invaluable source
of the learning experience.
Please use it to strengthen your
system, your infrastructure.
to train your team, finally.
And, stay calm, be positive about that.
It's already happened to
you, you already planned it.
pass through the incident.
like I hope network incidents will
never happen to your company, but if
they will, you are now ready for them.
And thank you for your attention.
It was Con 42.
If you have any questions,
you are welcome.