Today I would be talking about
ethical considerations in AI
enhanced marketing automation.
How to balance personalization
and responsibility.
Today there are a bunch of topics
that we're going to talk about.
To start with, the AI
revolution in marketing.
AI tools like machine learning, natural
language processing, and predictive
analytics allow marketers to deliver
personalized experiences at scale.
84 percent of marketing leaders
believe AI will revolutionize
marketing within the next five years.
And this is from a source.
AI driven marketing enhances customer
targeting, improves engagement,
and provides deep insights.
into customer behavior.
And there has been a case study that's
done for a, from a retail company.
A retail company used AI powered
recommendations resulting in a
40 percent increase in conversion
rates and 30 percent reduction
in customer acquisition costs.
We're also going to talk about ethical
dynamics in AI driven marketing.
Key ethical issues in
AI enhanced marketing.
Consumer behavior manipulation.
AI personalizes ads and content based
on individual preferences, but there
are concerns that this could manipulate
consumer decisions without them realizing.
For example, AI driven algorithms
exploit psychological vulnerabilities
to nudge users into making
purchases or engaging with content.
And the massive data collection
that's happening today required for
AI to function effectively raises
concerns about privacy and potential
misuse of personal information.
78 percent of the consumers worry about
AI marketing's aspect on their privacy.
AI can accurately predict sensitive
information like political
views or personal preferences.
Dissemination of disinformation.
AI algorithms, especially on social media
platforms, may amplify fake news and
misleading content to drive engagement.
For example, AI generated content
today is more, is more often shared
across the social media, more
than the verified content leading
to widespread misinformation.
AI personalizes recommendations
and ads based on consumer behavior
preferences and online activity
leading to higher engagement.
Today, personalized AI recommendations
can increase click through rates by
35 percent and conversions by 18%.
And a study suggests that 91 percent
of the consumer are most more likely
to shop with brands that offer
personalized offers and recommendations.
However, the use of AI to influence
consumer behavior raises ethical concerns.
Some argue that AI can exploit consumer
emotions, biases, effectively manipulating
their decision making process.
The need for ethical concern.
AI's ability to nudge consumers into
actions, such as purchases, sign ups,
without them fully understanding the
influence on their decisions, challenges,
the principle of consumer autonomy.
There are, and today we're
talking about privacy breaches.
Data collection consent.
AI marketing relies heavily on
collecting vast amounts of consumer data,
including browsing behavior, purchasing
patterns, and personal preferences.
Statistics say that 78 percent of
consumers express concerns about how AI
powered marketing affects their privacy.
For example, AI algorithms have been
able to accurately predict personal
information such as political affiliations
with 87 percent accuracy, just by
analyzing social media activity.
Privacy breaches such as unauthorized
use of personal data and large scale
data leaks have become more frequent
as AI systems grow more sophisticated.
In 2023, there's a major social
media platform experienced a data
breach that exposed the biometric
data of over 150 million users.
The spread of disinformation, AI's role in
amplifying misinformation, AI algorithms
prioritize engaging content, sometimes
leading to unintentional amplification
of false or misleading information.
For example, AI generated fake news is 70
percent more likely to be shared on social
media than the accurate news stories.
In 2024 US presidential election,
38 percent of Americans encountered
AI generated political content with
62 percent believing it to be real.
In a real world consequence, in
2023, a corporate smear campaign
using AI generated deepfakes led
to a 15 percent drop in the stock
price of a targeted company.
Fact checking AI tools are being
developed to counteract this issue, but
the speed and the scale at which the
disinformation spreads remain a challenge.
Facebook's AI driven fact checking
system identifies and labels 85
percent of false and false content
within 24 hours of posting.
Let's talk about responsible AI practices.
One of the most important
thing is transparency.
82 percent of consumers want companies
to be open about how AI is using
marketing decisions, especially
around personalized pricing, product
recommendations, and targeted ads.
And marketers also must clearly explain
how AI systems make decisions enabling
consumers to make informed choices.
How to mitigate biasing?
AI models can introduce or perpetuate
biases, especially in ad targeting,
pricing and personalization.
Proactive bias reduction
techniques are essential.
And there's a case study
on bias mitigation.
Bias mitigation can be reduced
targeting disparities by 45 percent
in a major advertising platform.
And human oversight is definitely needed
until an AI system is mature enough.
Automated AI systems can make decisions
rapidly, but human oversight ensures
accountability and ethical alignment.
Impact of AI on social media.
AI's influence on social media are
echo chambers and filter bubbles.
AI algorithms isolate users
in one sided content bubbles.
and personalized content filters
limit exposures to diverse viewpoints.
And the solution to these echo
chambers and filter bubbles is to
introduce algorithmic diversity and
user controlled content curation.
I
think going forward there has to be a way
to balance innovation with innovation.
and ethics together.
Finding the balance between
personalization and responsibility.
Companies need AI frameworks that promote
transparency, fairness, and oversight.
Responsible AI practices
ensure personalization without
compromising consumer rights.
Balancing innovation with
ethical marketing is essential
for long term sustainability.
Today, to conclude the rapid
Advancement of AI has revolutionized
marketing by offering unprecedented
personalization and efficiency.
However, as AI systems become more
integrated into marketing strategies,
businesses must acknowledge the ethical
dilemmas that accompany this technology.
Issues such as consumer manipulation,
privacy breaches, and spread of
disinformation highlight the importance
of developing responsible AI practices.
It is critical for companies to strike a
balance between the benefits of AI driven
personalization and the need to protect
consumer rights, autonomy, and trust.
Responsible AI in marketing
requires a comprehensive approach,
emphasizing transparency,
accountability, and humor oversight.
Marketers must ensure that AI
algorithms are free from bias
data collection practices respect
privacy and disinformation is
not unintentionally amplified.
Thank you