Hello everyone.
I'm Ti pdi, pa, currently working
at one of the leading multinational
company as a lead software engineer.
I completed my masters at the
University of Akron, Ohio, and today
I will be presenting at conference
42, incident management, 2025.
Now, retail has always been
about customer experience.
Today, that experience is delivered
almost entirely through technology,
and that technology has to operate at a
scale and speed that is unprecedented.
Black Friday alone can generate over 20%
of annual revenue in just a few days.
That means if your systems fail,
the consequences are immediate and
long-term revenue losses, brand damage.
Customer trust erosion.
This is why Cloudnative
approaches are no longer optional.
They're essential.
In this talk, we will explore how
retailers are using Cloudnative
architecture, not just to survive
these high stakes events, but to
thrive achieving agility, resilience,
and cost efficiency at the same time.
By the end, I want you to
leave with practical ideas.
That you can apply in
your own organizations.
Here is how I have structured our journey.
Today, we will begin with
the digital retail evolution.
What's driving this transformation and
why cloud native is the inevitable answer.
Then we will explore the
architecture foundations such as.
Auto scaling microservices and
resilient patterns that are at
the core of surviving peak demand.
Next, we will look at the real world
impact concrete case studies on
cost efficiency, personalization,
and inventory management.
After that, we will dive into
incident management because
resiliency is only real.
If you can detect and recover
from failures quickly.
Finally, we will cover migration
frameworks, especially the Strangler Big
pattern, which shows how to modernize
without risky Big bang Cutovers.
So this agenda moves us from the
big picture, why changes needed into
the nuts and bolts of how to make it
work, and finally into strategies.
To future proof retail platforms,
let's set the stage.
Retail today operates in a
high stakes digital arena.
Events like Black Friday and Cyber
Monday are no longer just busy days.
They can account for more than 20% of
annual revenue in a single weekend.
That means one outage even for minutes,
can wipe out millions of dollars.
Customers now expect subsecond
response times across all channels.
Mobile web, in store kiosks.
If the site is slow, they
don't wait, they leave.
Inventory visibility must be in real time.
So if someone buys the
last pair of shoes online.
That's instantly reflected
in the store system.
Personalization isn't optional anymore.
Customers expect tailored
recommendations every time.
And let's not forget
compliance and security.
A breach can cause existential damage.
Retailers who can't deliver
resilient experiences using peak
traffic face, both immediate revenue
impact and long-term brand erosion.
So the message is clear.
The retail battlefield is unforgiving
and the only way forward is cloudnative.
With that urgency in mind, let's
explore the first foundation.
Auto-scaling infrastructure.
Traditionally retailers.
Had to prepare for peak events
by massively over provisioning
infrastructure that is very traditional.
To handle Black Friday, they might buy
servers that were three to four times
more than their normal demand, and those
servers would sit idle most of the year.
That's wasted money.
Cloud native flips the model
with elastic auto scaling.
Resources expand and
contract in real time.
Predictive models forecast demand
spikes while real time monitoring
adjusts capacity Minute by minute,
during Black Friday, traffic
might spike 10 or 20 times.
Auto scaling seamlessly adds
servers to meet the load.
When traffic drops back to normal,
resources scale down automatically.
What is the result?
So the result is leading retailers
see 50% infrastructure cost savings
while still maintaining 99.99% uptime.
It's efficiency and
resilience hand in hand.
This is why I call autoscaling
the foundation of agility.
Without it, retailers either waste
millions or risk outages with it.
They strike the perfect balance.
But scaling infrastructure
alone isn't enough.
What happens when one service fails?
That's where microservices come in.
Monolithic systems are fragile.
One bug in checkout could
take down the entire site.
Cloud native retailers avoid this by
adopting microservices in this model.
Each domain, like catalog cart, checkout
payments, is its own independent service.
They can scale individually,
pale individually, and
be updated independently.
Retailers use resilience patterns such
as circuit breakers to prevent cascading
failures, bulkheads to isolate resources,
back pressure to avoid overload.
A synchronous communication
to reduce tight coupling.
The impact is powerful.
Teams can deploy three to five, three
to five times more frequently, and the
blast radius of incidents is cut by 75%.
This means retailers can innovate faster,
recover faster, and maintain stability
even when parts of the system fail.
And this architecture doesn't
just improve reliability.
It enables advanced capabilities
like real time personalization.
Let's talk about personalization.
We all experienced it.
You browse for a product and the site
instantly recommends something relevant.
Today, that's not a nice to have.
It's a baseline expectation.
The challenge is that delivering
personalization in real time across
billions of sessions without slowing
down performance is incredibly complex.
You are running machine learning
models, crunching data, and serving
recommendations in milliseconds.
Cloud native retailers solve
this with microservices based
machine learning platforms.
Recommendation engines are isolated into
independent services scale separately
using GPUs for fast inference and
paid with session specific caching.
This means that even during peak traffic,
the system can deliver personalized
recommendations with sub 20 millisecond
latency, and here is the impact.
Retailers see 25 to 35%
higher conversion rates.
That's customers, not just browsing,
but actually completing purchases, all
without sacrificing the site performance.
So personalization at
scale proves a key point.
Cloud native design doesn't
just keep systems alive.
It actually drives revenue growth,
but to make personalization work.
You also need something equally critical.
The real time inventory.
Visibility
inventory is a nervous system of retail.
If your system says an item is
in stock, but the store says,
shows that it's already sold
out, you break trust instantly.
Legacy systems relied on.
Batch updates, meaning inventory
might lag by 15 to 60 minutes.
That is like one hour 15 to one hour.
In an omnichannel world,
that's unacceptable.
Cloud native retailers move to
an event driven architecture.
The movement is sale have happens.
An event is published into
Kafka or Kinesis streams.
Those updates flow into distributed caches
like Redis across regions, and a graph ql.
API layer ensures fast, consistent access.
What's the result?
Inventory visibility in under
200 milliseconds across both
digital and physical channels.
This reduces talk outs by 40%.
Enables true omnichannel fulfillment.
Buy online, pick up in
store, return anywhere.
Inventory is no longer
a back office function.
It's a realtime digital nervous
system powered by cloud native design.
But even with personalization and time,
inventory failures are inevitable.
The real question is how do you
prevent them from cascading?
Failures happen.
What separates resilient systems from
fragile ones is how they handle those
failures in tightly coupled systems.
A single slow or failing service can
ripple through the entire platform.
That's what leads to checkout
crashes on Black Friday.
Cloud native retailers design.
For failure from day one, they use
circuit breakers to stop endless retries
on failing services, fallback mechanisms
to serve, cashed or simplify data and
rate limiting to control traffic surges.
Here is a simple example.
Imagine the product detail service slows
down instead of showing an error page.
The platform can serve cashed content
or a simplified version of the page.
The customer still completes their
purchase revenue still flows, and
the incident doesn't escalate.
This is resilience in action
keeping critical purchase parts
open even during partial outages.
And resilience isn't just about
uptime, it's also about keeping your
environment secure while moving fast.
Now let's talk.
Security retailers may deploy
hundreds of times per day.
Each deployment introduces risk,
but in a cloud native world,
security must be baked into the
pipeline, not bolted on afterwards.
Here is how leading retailers.
Secure containers by
using immutable images.
Every image is scanned for
vulnerabilities before deployment.
Runtime protection.
Behavioral analysis
monitors live containers for
anomalies, secret management.
So say like credentials
are rotated dynamically.
Only exists temporarily the timeout in
a certain time, like not producing long
lived tokens or anything like that.
Basically we need to produce like
short-lived tokens and compliance
automation, continuous checks for PCI and
GDPR with automatic evidence generation.
This approach allows retailers to stay
compliant while deploying at scale.
In other words, cloud native security
pipelines let you move fast and
safely without slowing innovation.
But even with scaling resilience
and security in place,
incidents will still happen.
So how do we detect and
resolve them faster?
Before cloud native practices, incident
management was slow and painful.
The average MTTD mean time to
detect was over 45 minutes.
The average MTTR mean time to
recovery was over four hours.
That's half a day of lost
sales and frustrated customers.
With cloud native and site reliability
engineer practices, everything changes.
Detection drops to under 60
seconds thanks to automated alerts
and observability pipelines.
Resolution times improve by 75
to 80% with cannery analysis.
Automated rollbacks and
playbooks for partial failures.
The result is that incidents that used
to cripple retailers for hours now
get detected and resolved in minutes.
This doesn't just protect uptime, it
protects revenue, brand trust, and
customer loyalty, and that brings us
naturally to observability the backbone
of rapid detection and response.
Monitoring tells you
when things are broken.
Observability tells you why Cloud
native observability combines metrics.
That gives us like latency, throughput,
error rates with anomaly detection.
And also sometimes like metrics
can include like how many.
API API calls count, error
count which I already mentioned.
And other important thing is logs.
Logs are structured with trace IDs so
you can connect errors across services.
And then finally the traces.
So traces will give us full
end-to-end visibility of a request
through multiple microservices.
But here is the game changer.
Leading retailers align observability
directly with business outcomes.
They track metrics like cart
abandonment, rate against service
latency, or revenue impact.
During incidents, they run
synthetic shopping journeys
to test checkout continuously.
This means incident response isn't
just about restoring servers,
it's about restoring customer
experience and revenue flow.
So what about legacy systems?
How do we bring them along
without breaking everything?
This is where the strangler
fixed pattern comes in.
Inspired by the tree that grows around
its host and gradually replaces it.
This pattern allows us to modernize
without a risky big bang cutover.
Here is how it works, and API gateway
intercepts traffic and routes it to either
the legacy system or new microservices.
New services are built alongside the
old, gradually traffic shifts to the
new services as they prove reliable.
Over time, the legacy system is
strangled and quietly retired.
This incremental approach means you
deliver value, continuously, reduce
risk, and never disrupt customers.
Its evolution, not just revolution.
And to make this possible, you need
the right team structure to support it.
Technology patterns only work if
the organization supports them.
Leading retailers adopt
structures that accelerate both
innovation and incident response.
They use product align squads,
cross-functional teams that own a
business domain, and to end they rely on
platform engineering teams that provide
self-service infrastructure to developers.
They embed, so they integrate SRE,
like site reliability, engineering
best practices within squads, guided
by a central team, and they integrate
security as code into CSCD pipelines.
This structure leads to three to
five times faster incident resolution
because teams own their services
and have the tools to act quickly.
It also enables constant innovation.
Because safety nets are
built into the process.
Now let's recap what
we have learned today.
So these are like four key
messages to leave you with Cloud.
Native is existential, not optional.
Retailers see 50% cost
reductions and higher resilience.
Second one is designed for
failure from the start.
Circuit breakers, bulkheads,
fallbacks, reserve revenue flow.
Third one is observability must
connect to business outcomes.
That is tying metrics to key performance
indicators like conversions and revenue.
The fourth one and last is the migrate
with evolution, not revolution.
The strangler thick pattern lets you
modernize safely and incrementally.
If you remember nothing else from today,
remember, just this cloud native retail
is about survival and competitiveness.
It's about delivering resilient
experiences when it matters most.
And with that, let's close.
Thank you all for your
time and attention today.
Detail is in the middle of
a massive transformation.
Cloud native architecture
is at the heart of it.
I hope this session has given you some
practical ideas, whether you're thinking
about scaling systems for peak traffic,
modernizing legacy platforms, or aligning
observability with business impact.
Thank you all once again.