Hi, everyone.
I'm Rob Kuros.
I'm CEO and co founder of Caber Systems,
and I'm here to talk to you today about
how we can fix the high false positive
rate you all are dealing with every day.
I hope you'll find this talk valuable, and
I invite you to connect with me via email.
Or LinkedIn if you do I spent 30 years
on the vendor side of IT and security
at the likes of Cisco Riverbed Akamai.
And after helping build one of the
first startups in the SAE or Secure
Access Service Edge space, I realized
our approach to cybersecurity
today is completely broken.
In 2023, the false positive rate,
according to the Sands Institute hit 95%.
That was up 20% since 2019.
And also me, we missed 20 percent
of all incidents despite that.
And it can sometimes take years
before we could detect a compromise.
So what's the problem here?
one of the issues is collectively,
companies spend 60 billion on tools
to find and alert us on indicators
that we might be compromised.
And you already know false positives
are when we see these alerts
that are indicators that turn
out not to be actual compromise.
So how do we tell the difference between
an indicator and a true false or a
true positive, an actual compromise?
This goes back to security 101.
It's when the indicator leads us to an
actual compromise to the confidentiality,
integrity, or availability of data.
As information security professionals,
our job is to protect data.
So why aren't we detecting the
compromises to data directly
instead of, Looking for indicators,
the newest version of this cyber
security framework calls out the same
protections for all states of data.
But the only 1 of those states where
we can directly protect data is data
at rest when it's on a storage system.
In fact, when we talk about data
security products and tools.
We're only talking about securing
data addressed, and that's because
the on storage systems, that's
the only place where data and its
ownership and permissions can be
directly linked for access control.
So what do we do for access control
when it comes to our cloud native
applications for data in transit and
data in use inside those applications?
We don't even know what
the permissions are.
We don't know who owns
the data inside the APIs.
Because we don't copy that
information when those APIs copy
the data from storage systems.
Instead, we rely on controlling access
to the APIs, thinking that somehow that's
going to be able to stand in as a proxy
for controlling access to the data.
It's like we're arbitrating access
to bags of sand or bags that are
labeled sand and thinking that
because it says sand on the outside
that it contains sand on the inside.
But we have no idea what the bags contain.
There's no correlation between API
parameters and what the data is inside,
who owns that data, and who can access it.
In fact, we might as well be calling
zero trust network access API.
It's infinite trust zero access,
because that's what we're doing.
We're completely trusting the, these
header parameters and the labels on
those bags to tell us what that data is.
And our so called data leakage
prevention tools aren't any better.
They tell us what data looks like,
not who owns it or the permissions
on who can access that data.
They can't tell you if it's your
data or if it's my data, and that's
where we're getting into trouble.
We have no way of effectively
doing authorization and access
control on data in APIs and the
top security vulnerabilities.
No surprise.
are authorization failures.
So in order to keep you from getting
access to my data, I need to know
what is your data, what is my data.
It can't be just a determination
of, hey, this data contains PII,
or it looks like it's health care
information, because my health care
information can't be distinguished
from your health care information.
My PII could be yours,
could be somebody else's.
What we have to have is
deterministic controls.
Access control has to be deterministic.
We need to know the identity of the
data, its ownership and permissions,
like we know the identity of the
services and users that access it.
That's what we need to
control data in use.
And data, in transit, and that's going to
help us solve this false positive problem.
A lot of people have called this
kind of direct control over data
in use the holy grail of security.
Because with it, we can
solve so many problems today.
We can address broken object level
authorization, privileged articulation,
SQL injections, and other, vulnerabilities
in our applications just by checking
authorization rather than having
to look for chains of indicators
that these things may be happening.
And moreover, instead of it taking
us to Months, or in fact years, like
it was in the case of First American,
to find a compromise in our systems,
we can detect them forthright.
We can detect them as they're
happening because they become
authorization failures.
So why hasn't this happened before?
Why haven't we been
able to do this before?
there's three Particularly hard
problems that have to be solved.
The first I've already mentioned
before, that our APIs don't
send permissions with data.
We read the data, we copy it into
an API or a service, we move it to
another service, and we leave the
ownership and permissions behind.
We're expecting that our knowledge of how
the software works It's going to allow
us to tell whether or not these APIs
are authorized to move that data or not,
but that gets us to the second problem.
service accounts.
These services themselves
hide the end user identity.
If you have an end user that often
that authenticates to a front end.
That front end doesn't use the user's
identity to make a request to the
back end to get data from storage.
So the storage system never
knows who ultimately is going
to get access to the data.
It only knows the back end with
broad access rights read some data
and passed it to the front end.
The front end doesn't know what the
permissions are and passes it to the user.
There's no place within our applications
where the user permissions and the
data permissions and the user identity
come together for authorization.
And the third problem is
a little bit more subtle.
It comes down to data deduplication.
Common chunks of data, byte sequences that
exist in multiple different documents, in
multiple different records and databases.
It that form the data that
we move in these APIs.
We can't actually tell, looking at
the data itself, whether it came
from, say, document A with policy
A, or document B with policy B.
So we need a way to be able to figure
out not just what the object was that it
came from, but the total lineage of this
data so we can rationalize and determine
what those permissions should be, whether
they should be policy A or policy B.
Policy B, and this is the critical
problem that we're actually
facing with generative AI.
We take documents and we ingest them
without permissions and put them in a
vector database and then we expect that
we can do some sort of access control
as those chunks of data are pulled
out of, Out of that vector database
in RAG systems, but we can't and even
copying the permissions, as I mentioned
before, because of data deduplication
means that we're not going to get
the permissions on each chunk as it
should be, we get the permissions on
the last document that chunk was in.
So we may be redacting information from
all of our users that they shouldn't,
that they should have access to.
Moreover, we can mix these chunks
together in a single API call.
And then how do we get to the permissions?
Of the data in aggregate
should actually be.
So we need a new architecture
to fix these problems.
We need to be able to identify data
as it's moving in API payloads,
and we've tried this in the past.
We've gone down the road of
enterprise digital rights management.
Google's come up with their
own solution for this.
My company, cber is
proposing a new solution.
But let's look at the, let's
look at the previous ones first.
EDRM.
So EDRM is a crypto,
cryptography solution.
Basically, we're encrypting the data that
we're moving in these API payloads, and as
they were constituted on the other side.
The users that have the keys
that we've passed out to decrypt
that data can access them.
The ones that don't can't access them.
And it's a pretty effective way of doing
access control on a per object basis.
But now let's shift our perspective
and look at what happens when an API
pulls a chunk of data out of a document
and then moves that chunk To another
API that ultimately gets to a user.
It starts to get pretty messy from there.
You'd have to, the service that,
that extracts the chunk wants to
send it securely to an end user.
it's got to send it back to some
central crypto authority to have
it re encrypted with a private key.
We get that chunk back, then we have
to send the public key to the right
people that have access to those chunks.
Which may not necessarily be the same
people with access to the entire document.
And as the number of chunks
grows and the number of services,
this becomes simply untenable.
So imagine how many
encryptions, decryptions, and
re encryptions we'd have to do.
So Google came up with a
different solution to this.
As they're putting together Google
Cloud, they were thinking about data
security, in their BeyondProd project,
and coupled with Zanzibar, which was
their central authorization engine, they
came up with A new way of doing data
security between their microservices.
So what they've done is effectively
what you would do if you
decided to build data security.
Correct from the first point is you pass
that you actually do pass the permissions
of all the data that you are carrying
in your APIs all the way down to the.
final point where those APIs are accessed
by an end user, and you pass the user
credentials all the way up so that
every point where the data and the user
identity meet, you can authorize access.
Be it the API access or the
user access to that data.
Now, that's a great solution.
The problem is,
the problem is that they
had to re engineer their
service to be able to do this.
And if you think about modern applications
and enterprises that use hundreds, if
not thousands of services, many of which
are open source or third party sourced
services, How are you going to reengineer
them all to pass the credentials of the
users or pass the permissions of the data
for most companies other than Google?
that's a complete barrier to entry.
They won't be able to
make use of this solution.
So that's why at Caber we came
up with a third option based
upon data lineage tracing.
Effectively, what we're doing is we're
looking at the byte sequences in every
API payload around an application,
tracing them back to all the source
objects that could possibly come from,
and then building a map that allows
us to determine which source of that
data should those sequences inherit.
We're leveraging some, Basic technologies
like content defined chunking to make
sure that the sequences that we see
in one API payload is the same as the
chunks that we see in other API payloads.
And that allows us to connect the dots
between all of these APIs to build
those relationships I mentioned before.
And that map is extensive.
This is an example of How we look
at data within an application, the
objects that those chunks of data
themselves, which are the small blue
dots come from the objects that hold
them and the APIs that move them.
And from this, we can
eliminate the junk data that.
It doesn't carry permissions, it doesn't
show us what, or doesn't contribute
to our ability to authorize access.
And we can narrow down to just the
data that we know what the permissions
are and we can authorize access at any
given point within the application.
So based upon doing that sort of
time series analysis or graphical
analysis and coupling that with time
series analysis, looking at event
ordering and eliminating impossible
paths, we can effectively do this.
And the result, if we're looking at, the
management console of Kaber's product,
we can see that we're detecting access to
sequences of data that come from objects.
Even if.
Those sequences are only a small
fraction of the content that came
from the object in the first place.
in this case, we have Bob as a
user, and Bob is accessing some
data from an object owned by Amy.
And it's through an API where they
got 7 byte sequences out of about
10, 000 that came from her document.
this is very powerful.
fine grained access control for data.
We don't need to see hundreds
of kilobytes of data to be able
to provide access control to it.
We can do it on a very fine grained basis.
Even down to
30, 40, 50 bytes is in the case of
this demonstration that I'm showing
here where We're providing access
control directly on the chunks that
are coming out of a RAG system.
And in this slide, what I'm showing is
the user on the top has access to, we're
using Apple 10 Q statements, financial
filings that Apple has made with the SEC.
And the user on top has access to
Every year's financial statements,
but let's just consider 2024 is
material nonpublic information.
That's only accessible by the CFO on the
top and the regular users on the bottom.
They can be asked questions about 2024.
But as you can see.
we can tell the difference between the
data that exists in the 2024 statements
and what exists in the 2023 statements.
Even though those two statements, if
you put them side by side, you see
they have a lot of data in common.
The boilerplate management
discussions, it's really only the
distinguishing characteristics
of these documents that matter.
And that's the sequences that we're
redacting from this user and holding back.
from the LLM that's about to give
them knowledge based upon that.
And this access control is deterministic.
We know for a fact we have a one to one
exact match of those byte sequences to
the data that they contain And the data
and the source where they came from.
So this determinism, we need
two or more observation points.
We need to be able to see the
data in two different places.
And this is unlike what you would have
with DLP, where you're just looking at
the data itself and trying to decide
on the spot, what does it look like?
We need to have multiple sources where
we can connect those sources together
to determine the identity of that data.
But that's the secret sauce for this.
Now,
why, again, we're doing this, is
to be able to detect incidents
without false positives.
Now, I'm going to be honest right here.
These are hashes, and we're
still subject to hash collisions
within a given environment.
But the probability of
a hash collision is 0.
00001 percent or so.
Compare that to the 95 percent false
positive that we have today, and you
see this completely flips the model.
So what can we do with this?
Beyond just being able to detect access
problems, Bob accessing Amy's data, what
we need to be able to do, or what we want
to be able to do, Is to use this data
effectively to help us not just detect
problems, but solve those problems.
And that's what we can do by
tracing the path and the movement
of these byte sequences through
every API call that carries them.
Here I'm showing a call graph of
what happened in that alert that we
generated with Bob accessing Amy's data.
And we can see exactly what happened.
From starting with Amy uploading a
document that gets passed through
this NuCo Next Cloud service stored
in an S3 bucket, we can then see that
there's this service NuCo Disrupt at
the bottom that accessed that data,
extracted some content out of it, and
wrote it back to a different place.
In fact, a shared bucket where Bob can
get access to it and see a preview of
the text of the document she uploaded.
But by being able to trace this
path, we have the full and complete
picture of how the incident happened.
But not only that, we know how to stop it.
We can prevent this just knowing
that the mechanism that he was able
to get access to that data was this.
NUCO disrupt service.
Now think about that disrupt service
as a piece of malware in your system,
or as a bad actor that was able to
escalate their privileges, gain access
to an instance, and then read the data
from one bucket and write it to another.
These sorts of errors go undetected
because they're all authorized access
when you look at them individually, but
they're unauthorized when you look at
them from an end to end data perspective
and know that the data that Bob got
came from an object owned by Amy.
But this ability to trace data
through a series of API calls gives
us an even better more interesting
window into the application behavior.
Beyond just detecting how an incident
happened, think about black box testing,
where you look at the inputs and outputs
of a given software package, To be able
to determine what that software package is
doing, what its function is, and by being
able to trace how data flows and being
able to identify what that data is as it
moves through these different services
gives us the ability to do that as well.
And so what does this mean?
It means that as we're building our
applications and building our policies,
we know exactly what's happening
across all of our services, or we can
know what's happening across all of
our services in terms of actual data
flow, and then use that knowledge to
build the policies that we need to
be able to control that data flow.
In fact, we're able to take
this data along with some high
level policies Prevent Bob from
gaining access to Amy's data.
Feed that to a generative AI.
And get back actual policy implementations
and where to put those policies to
enforce that compliance requirement.
We think the direction that we can take
with this level of data identification,
the granularity that we can provide, And
the rationalization of the authorization
on access to that data everywhere
within an application is going to
open up a wide new arena for security.
We think this is the key to
eliminating false positives
in applications going forward.
Thank you very much for your time.
I really appreciate it.
And I look forward to hearing from you.
If this is of interest.
If you think that this will
solve a problem within your
environments, let me know.
I'd be really interested
in hearing from you.
Thanks again.