Hello?
I'm sorry, Krishna from Visa.
Thank you everyone for joining my session.
In this session, I'm going to explore
how integrating blockchain with cloud
native infrastructure and AI reshapes,
incident detection, triage, and recovery
in high volume payment networks.
I'll begin with why this is urgent.
Then outline the architecture and
automation patterns, quantify the impact
and close with a phase rollout plan and
key takeaways you can apply immediately.
Let's get started.
The urgent payment networks are the
circulator system of the global economy.
When a major institution suffer
disruption, losses cascade.
Today's pain points are threefold.
Firstly, the crippling blind spots, manual
ticketing and spreadsheets based tracking
leave gaps where emerging failures hide.
So teams often discover problems late.
Second extended outages, reactive
incident response, minutes to downtime
every handoff, P, delay and misted
alerts, customer impact, and also loss.
The third one, compliance catastrophes
when reporting is manual and fragmented.
Audits take longer evidence, quality,
suffer and regulatory exposure growth.
The takeaway is very clear.
We need a different operating model.
Mastering unprecedented
resilience set of payment scale
requires comprehensive approach.
First, the high volume processing.
We must seamlessly handle billions
of transactions across the platforms
like Visa and which six latency,
and also high availability goals.
Secondly.
Continuous the 24 crossover monitoring of
health, performance and security events
across services, regions and providers.
Observability must weak signals not only
alarms that already cross the thresholds.
Third, mitigate
catastrophic downtime costs.
Outages can cause millions per
hour through loss, interchange,
chargebacks and reputational damage.
Preventing incidents and accelerating
recovery are business imperatives,
but not engineering goals.
Blockchain cloud.
Transforming incident response.
In this slide I'm going to explain
our thesis is to fuse blockchain's
integrity with the elasticity
of cloud native infrastructure.
This yields trustworthy records,
automated workflows, and scale during
crisis immune immutable audit trails.
Every incident, event detection,
escalation mitigation, and recovery
is captured with cryptographic
verification to provide a tamper proof
history for postmortems and regulators.
Elastic scalable response.
Cloud resources expand and contract
to match incident severity,
ensuring stable performance under
heavy load while controlling cost.
And automated smart contracts,
predefined rule actions like paging,
flag flips, traffic shifting or rollback,
reducing human error, and shrinking.
Time to restore.
Moving on to next slide,
revolutionizing visibility.
Blockchain powered incident monitoring.
So as a step one, the
intelligent anomaly detection.
High sensors and AI models continuously
learn normal behavior across traffic
latency, error rates, dependency and
security events to surface deviations.
Very early.
Step two, immutable event registration.
Each notable signal is timestamped and
recorded to the ledger, producing an
unalterable ordered chain of evidence that
survives tool changes or the human edits.
The third one, predictive
incident prevention with a
complete and trustworthy dataset.
Forecasting models identify leading
indicators such as saturation patterns
or the reverse so we can intervene
before the customer feels the pain.
Moving on.
Automated incident response.
Zero touch.
Operational resilience
with smart contracts.
Autonomous alert escalation.
Severity aware rules, route
alerts to right on call person.
The leadership are also added, and
the partner teams are also added
instantly with deduplication and
suppression to avoid noise floods,
dynamic resource optimization when
signals indicate load or degradation.
Automation skills, replica warm
caches, most workload to healthier
zones, or expand network capacity
without waiting for the manual action.
The near instant system restoration.
When a rollback or failover criteria
is met, contract trigger safe
restoration to the last good known
state, including configure version,
traffic shifting and dependency gating
transforming resilience into profit.
Quantify the operational edge.
Our autonomous incident response
solutions don't just promise resilience.
They deliver measurable,
tangible business value.
We empower you to clearly demonstrate
how zero touch operations translate
directly into the significant ROI.
Reduce costs, enhance deficiency,
and a powerful competitive advantage.
Witness the compelling data that
pro our impact on your bottom line.
Transforming operations driving
measurable impact the precision in alerts.
Fewer positive alert means Internet's
focus on real threats, improving signal
to noise, and also reducing alert fatigue.
The rapid incident resolution.
Automated run books usually shorten
detection, triage, and mitigation.
Compressing mean compressing the
meantime to acknowledgement and recovery.
Stability analytics, maintenance before
end result is customer satisfaction.
Fewer and
go.
Moving on to next slide.
Anticipate failures.
We analyze historical transaction
flows and performance trends to
forecast where the risk is a rising,
for example, a service reaching
saturation during weekend peaks or a
dependency with increasing tail latency.
We red the subtle anomalies during
the drift in the percentile, 50
latency that proceeds to the personnel
99 spikes and correlate them with
deploy feature flags and infra.
We optimize capacity using productive
models, and we schedule automated
preventive maintenance such as node
replacement or canary restarts before
minor issue escalates into an incident.
We usually do all these.
Moving on to next one.
Dynamic scaling cloud native agility
for uninterrupted operations.
The baseline stability.
This runs with right size, capacity,
and budgets during normal periods while
preserving headroom for the sudden
spike the proactive demand sensing,
detect early signs of surge marketing
campaigns, holiday traffic partner
cutovers, and we scale preemptively.
Rapid capacity expansions, elasticity
at compute storage, network
throughput, or regional endpoints to
absorb peak loads without throttling
the efficiency optimization.
As demand subsides automatically
scale back down resources and
keeping unit economic safety.
Accelerating operational excellence
basically by applying this
operational model in high volume
environments, yields concrete outcomes.
Substantial reduction in manual
intervention through codified runbooks
as policy, as code significantly
accelerated incident resolution time
due to automated detection, routing,
and the rollback higher compliance
reporting accuracy, because every
step is recorded in immutably and is
easy to reconstruct during audits,
streamline post incident analysis,
precise timelines, correlated evidence,
and objective and objective metrics.
Implementation.
So assess current
infrastructure map services,
identify integration points.
Firstly, the initial pilot deployment.
Choose a non-critical but
representative service.
Start by recording detection and
response events to ledger, validate
latency and storage overheads.
Develop smart contracts, encode common
playbooks like degraded latency,
rollback, circuit on dependency,
saturation, and surgical scaling policies
with clear guardrails and approvals.
Rollout to the production, expand
coverage to mission critical
services and cross team visibility
dashboards, and tune policy based
on live results under perspectives,
fortify compliance and enhanced
security with blockchain.
The immutable audit trails topographic
proves makes evident tamper evident.
Helping regulators and Foreign Six
trust the timeline of the actions taken.
Automated compliance reporting generate
accurate, consistent reports straight
from the ledger and telemetry, reducing
manual compilation and the human error.
The realtime transfer provide
stakeholders with control, immediate
visible teams into incident status
actions in flight and recovery progress.
Future proofing defense,
staying ahead of threats.
The quantum resistant en encryption
prepared for advances in compute
by adopting algorithms designed to
withstand new classes of attack.
The decentralized threat validation use
distributed conscious to corroborate
emerging indicators of compromise and
reduce single point by US automated.
Propagate valid threat intelligence
across teams and regions instantly.
So defense aligned quickly.
The AI power detection continuously
retrain model on fresh, trustworthy
data to improve precision and
recall as all the landscape evolves.
The key takeaway.
Anticipate sophisticated threats
and them earlier with adaptive
controls and verbal evidence.
The UN reality, decentralized
plus AI assisted operational
availability and recovery time.
S value creation resilience, reduces
the risk, protects revenue, and
improve ROI through lower downtime
and greater operational efficiency.
The proactive threat neutralization
move from firefighting to
foresight with predictive analytics
and policy driven automation.
Rapid and automated response use
smart contracts like rules to trigger
the right actions at the right
time with minimum human latency.
Enhance stress and transparency, immutable
logs and clear operational visibility.
Build conference with
partners and regulators.
Optimize operational efficiency, fewer
manual touch points, standardized
workflows, and better cost control
across the incident lifecycle.
Thank you for watching.
I'm Krishna.