Hey, this is ala from Technologies, and
I'm thrilled to be here at Conference 42.
Today I'm going to present how
we can achieve mastering of
multi-cloud database resilience.
Today we are diving into problem that
keeps a lot of us awake at night.
Keeping our database resilient in
multi-cloud world, if your organization
uses more than one cloud provider,
AWS Azure, Oracle Cloud, you know
exactly how complex things have become.
And if you are not doing multi-cloud
yet, trust me, you will be database
administrator, face a completely different
world than they did few years ago.
We are no longer limited
to single cloud strategy.
Most of our organization now run
hybrid or multi-cloud environments.
Let's talk about how to make that
complexity manageable with resilience,
automation, and observability.
In this session, I'm going
to walk through four things.
First, we'll compare the major platforms.
Like autonomous database, Azure scale
database, and Amazon RDS for a scale
server to see how they stack up in terms
of capabilities, scalability, and cost.
Then we will look at strategies for
resilience, backup, failover, compliance.
After that, I will talk about
automation, how tools like Terraform.
Cloud providers, CLI and scripting
can make life much easier.
Finally, we'll explore monitoring and
observability so we can stay ahead of
issues rather than reacting to them
in this journey.
We'll first go to Oracle
Autonomous Database.
Let's start with Oracle Autonom Database.
This platform really shines with itself,
managing ties like automated patching,
upgrades, tuning building, ma machine
learning for performance optimization, and
automatic scaling for workload changes.
Yes, you can run in it a serverless mode.
Also for variable workloads,
or if you want to decide.
Infrastructure for pre predict,
pre predictable strategy, state
workload and paper use pricing you
can be very costly, cost effective.
Next, we'll go to Azure S SCALE database.
Azure database takes slightly
different approach focusing
on intelligent performance.
It uses AI to provide recommendations
and automatic tuning, and the
hyperscale architecture allows database
to grow up to a hundred terabytes.
Security is very strong with features
like transparent data encryption
and Azure rating integration.
This also has flexible pricing
models, so you can choose DTU
based, eco based, or serverless,
depends upon your workload needs.
Next we'll go to Amazon RDS
for S Scale server, Amazon RDS.
For S Scale server is more about
enterprise grade reliability.
It offers automated backups, pointing
time recovery, and multi easy
deployments for high availability and
read replicas for better performance.
It supports enterprise
features like always on.
Availability groups.
S-S-I-S-S-S-R-S, and let's use save
cost through reserve instances or
stay flexible with on demand pricing.
So we've gone through all the
capabilities of different cloud platforms.
Now let's compare, when we compare all
these three platforms, you can see.
They each have their own
strength and capabilities.
Rack is excellent for self-management.
Azure is great for intelligent
performance, and RDS provides
reliable enterprise grade service.
So Ally, everything.
The key is to pick the right platform
for right workload rather than sticking
to a single vendor out for habit.
So in with this, we completed
comparing three cloud offerings.
Now we'll see the resilient strategies,
how we make this cloud strategies workable
for our real time and environments
resilience strategies in that we'll first
cover multi-cloud backup strategies.
Platform choice is just one piece.
In pail actually, to achieve real
resilience, we need multi-cloud backup
strategies and cross-cloud replication.
And the backup should be taken
when to avoid performance impact.
And we have to also validate
our backups frequently, whether
we have, we should know.
The backups actually
works when we restore it.
Next, we'll cover failover, and
high availability for failover.
We can design active passive steps setups
with the automated health checks and
DNS based routing, or even we can set up
active architectures for zero downtime.
Next we'll cover regulator
compliance across clouds.
Resiliency doesn't end up with uptime.
We also need to be compliant.
So compliant is very critical.
We have to respect data residency
rules, enforce encryption standards,
centralized audit, logging, and consistent
across the controls across the cloud.
This consistency across clouds
avoid regulatory headaches
and keeps auditors happy.
So by this we'll complete
we complete resiliency.
Next major topic is automation.
Automation is one of the key
features in all the cloud offerings.
So how we achieve automation.
This is using Terraforms
Automation is very things vary
depends upon our requirement.
Currently we focus on the terraforms.
For Terraform, we can define
the infrastructure as a code,
keeping everything version
controlled and reproducible with
Terraforms and with A-W-S-C-L-I.
We A-W-S-C-L-I operations, we can
automate backups, scaling, maintenance,
all the regular activities, combining
terraforms with the tools A-W-S-C-L-I
or Azure C-L-I-O-C-S-C-L-I.
We can script snapshot or scaling,
patching everything, and we can
also do the performance check.
Automat automation is
not just about speed.
It's about reducing human error
and avoiding re repeatability.
Let's come to the final
topic of our presentation.
That is monitoring and
observability, so no matter how
well we plan things will break.
The question is, will you know
about it before your customer do?
That's a question we have to
ask for any, every monitoring.
So monitoring and observability
tied together, we need to track
CPU, memory IO availability and
response time, and also security.
We have, we should have a threat
detection system and alerts should be
triggered sensibly and meaningfully.
When there is an issue and it cannot
be a weakness, so tools like AWS
CloudWatch, Azure Monitor, Prometheus,
graph, Datadog, or Splunk, we can
build a unified view of our system.
Even we can use artificial
inter intelligence to predict
issues before they occur.
Finally.
Performance tuning also can be automated.
We can establish we can establish
baselines and using machine learning
learning and trigger, pre trigger,
pre predefined responses for common
issues and continuously optimize.
So the database always performs best.
By automating baseline collection,
using machine learning based anomaly
detection and automated remediation, we
can fix issues before the impact users.
The goal is to shorten MTTR means meantime
to resolution, to point to the point
where incidents are barely noticeable.
Finally.
The takeaways for this presentation
is how we choose best cloud offerings,
how we distribute our workloads
in different cloud platforms.
First thing is pick your database
platform based on workload
requirements, not vendor loyalty.
Second, embrace automation like
infrastructure as code scripting.
Monitoring pipelines will save
you time and reduce mistakes.
Third.
Build for resilience.
Make sure you have cross cloud
backups tested, failover and
compliance build from the start,
start, finally monitor everything.
Observability is what keeps
system healthy and users happy.
The future database management is ably,
multi-cloud and automated and resilient.
The organization that embrace
these principles will be once the
best prepared for what's ahead.
Thank you so much.