Today, I'm going to discuss about
the future of utility management
system leveraging the advanced
customer information systems.
Basically, we are trying to transform the
utility industry using the latest and the
greatest technology that we recently had
AI to efficiently manage the operations
and increase the customer satisfaction.
So here, it's mostly related to the
utilities industry, but we're trying
to discuss more about the technologies
that we used for this conference.
So here is the content, table of
contents that we are going to discuss.
this is all about introduction to
CIS, challenges with the legacy CIS
system, and the benefits of upgrading
the CIS system, and the key components
of a CIS upgrade, the whole CIS
upgrade process, how it can be done.
we'll take an example of Catapult project
that we recently implemented here in
Kansas Board of Utilities, Kansas City.
board of public utilities.
And, the, what are the, all the
tangible outcomes for, the CI
subgrid that we did, the future
proofing of these utility operations.
And then we'll have a small
conclusion for question and answers.
let's talk first about the introduction to
CI system, what CI system, would encompass
and what all the systems that it includes,
to help the We are to help the utility
system utilities to manage the customers.
So this is a critical part of the.
managing, customer interactions
like billing and services, drives
efficiency in utility operations
by centralized, customer data.
And it also enables adaptation to future
technologies like smart grids and IoT.
So whenever the, so for example, you have
a lot of meters connected all together.
To the system and whenever the billing
happens, there is nothing manual here.
So everything is automated from the
grid to the billing system, and how
this automation is done and how this,
customer information system leverages
the whole, collection of data to enhance
the customer, customer satisfaction
is what it is all about in the CIS.
So the modern energy sector demands
responsive and data driven systems.
the modern system where the customers
are using a lot of mobile phones and
they want to get an idea about how much
energy is being used and, how far the
bill is and when did they pay and they
wanted to pay online using the mobiles
and all these, operations which the
customers want to do can be done using
upgrading the customer information system.
So the legacy systems lack
the flexibility and power to
meet growing industry demands.
That's obvious.
and, thus, CIS modernization
enhances the ability to meet
regulatory and compliance standards.
So the most of the public utilities,
they have these regulatory and compliance
standards, which they got to meet
with the, the state's public utility
commission, where they Fix the rates,
even if they want to increase any of
the burden on the financial burden
on the customers, they, these state
organizations, they make sure the
customers are satisfied and there is, they
follow some rules to, in case of they want
to increase the cost for these utilities.
And, what are all the challenges
with the legacy systems?
the scalability issues, and integration
difficulties, poor user experience
inefficient workflows due to outdated
design, maintenance challenges like the
higher cost if you want to go to upgrade
it can't be pushed to cloud and this
the existing legacy systems is all about
in the They're all in the cloud, right?
the latest and greatest technologies
are all in the cloud and, the computing
is all performed in the cloud.
But when you come to the old legacy
systems, the systems are all installed
in the on prem like Linux and other
late, Technologies which sit on the
on premise server room where we have a
server team and a lot of administrators
and DevOps personnel working on
automating all these operations on the
on premise, coming from installation,
upgrades and all the stuff, right?
so we don't want to go with the
legacy system where all these
operations are taken care on site
by the, within the, people, IT
personal staff of the utilities.
So when we go to the new system, all these
are taken care of in the cloud, right?
So that's obvious with the latest
technologies that are going on.
And there are also a lot of security
vulnerabilities with the legacy systems
and Cyber security threats, legacy systems
leads to bottlenecks in operations,
impacting customer satisfaction and
long response times during high demand
periods due to outdated infrastructure.
so what are all the benefits
of, upgrading the CI system?
the enhanced user interface, the
customizable dashboards, improved
navigation for quicker access to data,
improved, data handling, supports
large scale data, processing with
real time insights and superior
customer service where interactive
self service portals and instant
communication via multiple channels.
So it easily integrates with
emerging technologies like
renewable energy and management.
So some, for example, you want to
have a solar farm where customers
wanted renewable energy from the
solar farm, or they want to install
a renewable energy source on their
own, sy on their own premise.
and, the grid can accept, absorb
some of the energy from their
system when they have access.
And, and.
When they want more energy, which they
can't produce, the grid can supply.
So all this is called net metering
system in, the modern system where,
using the latest and greatest
technologies can be configured, right?
and scalability and future proofing.
easily integrating with, integrates with
the emerging technologies like Yeah.
That we discussed, we just discussed.
So data driven insights enables
advanced analytics for productive
maintenance and demand forecasting.
Yeah.
there, there is a system by
name called Maxima within the
CIS utility system where, uh.
where all the meters, all the inventory
and all the personnel that you see during
the outages, the outages, this can be
automated using the preventive maintenance
that we are using the latest technologies.
the cost efficiency obviously reduces
operational costs by automating tasks
and workflows, which the billing
and other teams, most of their
administrative tasks can be, automated.
So regulatory compliance, streamlines,
adherence to the evolving,
evolving, industry regulations.
So the utility system is a wide, more
than, 50 utility systems within the
states and in some states have, so
everything, every utility system has to
follow some rate structure approved by
the, commissioner or something through
Zoom calls to the customers where they
have to, agree with the rate structure
that is prescribed by the utilities, put
forward by the utilities for the future.
all these.
Standards are taken care of by using
the latest and latest CIS upgrades.
So the what about the key components?
So what does these key
components of CS upgrade include?
So the enhanced user interfaces because
of the latest, user interactions, with
the new software takes very less time.
It improves the productivity, making
the system user friendly, right?
Oh, the older system, there are, let's say
if they want to go to a workflow, if they
have 10 clicks to reach the end, to get
to information to respond to a customer.
So with the enhanced user interface, the
time to reach, to get the information
and respond to a customer is very less.
So advanced data handling capabilities
and capable of processing data from
various sources such as smart meters
and IOT devices So all these IOT
devices and this and smart meters, they
produce lots and lots of data whether
it could be testing those meters whether
the voltage is testing is performed
with the without going through the We
thought, sending the personal from the
inventory station to the, location.
So all these, data that we are getting
from, The meters and IOT devices
which are managed by the utility,
can be analyzed within the CI system.
So that's, one of the
major advantage, of this.
So robust integration capabilities,
the CI system can be integrated with
all the GIS information system and
customer relationship management
and, and metadata management.
So metadata management is
some, something like a sucker,
which gets all the information.
And there are some.
capabilities within the MDM system,
which processes before it spits out that
information to the CI system, right?
the, all the integration is between all
these systems and the CI sits like a
heart within, between all these systems.
So when you get real time analytics,
the, it provides operational insights,
helping utilities and manage peak
demand periods, obviously when all the
customers, when there is a game like
an NFL, when all of them want to sit
and watch, and, during such peak demand
periods can be addressed easily with the,
By forecasting the energy demand usage
with this latest information that we are
using, that we are getting from these
smart devices and, and when you have all
this information, so you can predict the
future of the, energy usage and, have,
a lot of initiatives where, with the.
you can propose a time when if a
customer wants to use less energy
during those peak times, you can
reward the customer for that time.
And all these, new features can
be enhanced using the CIS system.
obviously the security and compliance
sits at the forefront of, The CS system
or whichever system we are having now
in the IT world because of the cyber
security threats that we are getting where
all we need to make sure the customer's
data is secured and it's stored in a
reliable place like a dedicated cloud
location like, for a lot of these,
latest, like AWS, Azure, and other.
vendors like Oracle, they build a
separate, data centers for government
organizations so that they don't
have to, worry about the compliance
and, regulatory issues, which comes
with this, data accessibility things.
So what is the whole process
of CIS upgrade process, right?
The comprehensive evolution of current
systems weakness and bottlenecks,
identify pain points through feedback
from end users, understand regulatory and
compliance gaps, planning, obviously the
developer roadmap for technology section,
selection and resource allocation.
All, some of these things are project
management, tasks, where, the technology
roadmap and, resource allocation,
comes under that, align upgrade.
So the strategic initiatives from the
CIO or the, the organization from the
board, needs the IT needs to map and
align our initial, tasks according
to the plan, proposed by their board.
so how the implementation, obviously
it has to be a phased manner.
You can't just, take down the
legacy system and then have
the new system available.
that's how it is, right?
So it has to be a phased manner where
each functionality is moved out and
then eventually a cut, a cutout is done.
so let's say, and we're talking
here about training and support.
it's obvious that, all the new system.
It shouldn't be more easy for the
existing billing clerks and MDM analysts
or the business users to get on as
soon as they were given the new system.
So obviously there is a lot
of training and regression
test cases that they executed.
execute before the system goes live.
That makes them more comfortable in using
this and, and also the risk mitigation
is separate, separate team where they're
identifying the potential risk and impact
upon operations during this transition.
So that this is all about the whole
upgrade process, what all different steps
that we include and different measures
that we take for the smooth transition.
for example, we implemented a
project by name Catapult, which we
call it as because, we are moving
from, existing legacy system for all
these head end MDM, CIS, and Maxmo.
All these systems could be upgraded
at a single shot and Make the,
utility system in the, latest and
greatest technology use usable, right?
so the legacy system, the obviously slow
processing and high operational costs.
the, with an upgraded system, we have
modular design, faster data processing
and improved customer interaction.
What are all the tangible outcomes?
So impact of CIS upgrade, the key outcomes
are Operational efficiency, reduced
processing times, automation, and manual
workflows like we discussed earlier.
The business users can easily automate and
process time and the processing time is
reduced and manual workflows are reduced.
So obviously operational efficiency
is achieved by saving a lot of time.
Faster query selection with comprehensive
customer data at fingertips.
the more easier, the more flexible.
For a business user to get
information, the better he
can serve the customer, right?
The billing accuracy, the more the
number of issues that you get with the
billing system with the cycles that you
run every day are reduced by more than
50 to 60 percent with the new billing
system, obviously, because of the
availability of data and the accuracy and
the dashboards that we discussed before.
The data driven decisions, the use of real
time analytics for data forecasting and
energy management, that's coming from the
smart grid and analyzed at the, Dashboards
that are provided with the new CS upgrade.
There are a lot of cost savings through
automation and modern infrastructure,
improved collaboration, seamless
data sharing across departments,
improves overall energy, operational
synergy, employee productivity,
improved system usability, results in
faster onboarding and fewer errors.
how do we use this as a future proofing
utility operation system, right?
financial services API security access,
success, scalability, designed to grow
with increased customer base, data volume,
In integration with smart technology,
seamless adaptation to smart meters,
electrics, charging stations and renewable
energy sources, regulatory adaptability
and customer engagement enhances customer
facing features such as mobility app,
mobile apps and self service portals and
system architecture allows for incremental
upgrades ensuring long term cost control.
Finally, the modernization of CIS
system is just not a technical upgrade.
It is a strategic improvement for,
utility companies, looking to thrive.
Sorry.
Thriving in the modern energy
landscape, upgrading to a modern CIS
offers immense benefits including
enhanced operational efficiency,
improved customer satisfaction, and a
scalable foundation for future growth.
By addressing the limitations of
legacy systems, utilities can unlock
the potential of real time data
analytics, advanced customer service
features, and seamless integration
with new technologies such as smart
meters and renewable energy sources.
As the energy sector continues to
evolve, staying competitive requires
adaptable, adapting, fixable, future
proof, systems that can grow the needs
of both company and its customers.
Investing in sales modernization
today ensures that utilities are well
positioned to meet rising customer
expectations, comply with emerging
regulatory requirements, and optimize
their operations for long term success.
That's all.
Thank you so much.
And if you have any questions,
you can post me online or you can
post to the virtual conference
question and answer section.
So I'd be happy to answer
all those questions.
Thank you.