Hello listeners.
My name is Gandhi Kumar.
I am a principal incident
commander working for Twilio
based out of Seattle, Washington.
And I took interest in participating
in Con 42, 20 25 to take, to talk
about how incident management's
evolving with the advent of AI and how.
There are so many amazing solutions
available readily out of box in
the tools and also things that,
we can build to make life easier.
And today I'm gonna be
talking specifically about.
How AI is changing incident management,
speci spec specifically on incident
response communications at Twilio
and the reason I chose this specific
topic is because there is so much
about detection, resiliency, SRE,
DevOps, but there's very little
content I personally have noticed on.
How incident response
communication happens.
You gotta remember, this is an absolutely
critical aspect that's often overlooked.
So if you know what incidents are it's
essentially a disruption to service.
And at any point in time whenever
something like that happens,
customers are directly impacted.
And if you have been a
vendor or a customer.
You know that communication is
absolutely critical during an incident.
You want to be notified
of what's going on.
You want to see progressive updates.
You want to have updates on the status
page for that specific product that's
impacted because you probably have end
users who are asking you questions on.
To when the product's gonna
be, up and running once again.
And this is true, regardless if it's
like a degradation or if a product's are
down, communication during incidents is
absolutely crucial because that's pretty
much what builds trust between parties.
So I'm gonna walk us through a few
slides, but majority of this is gonna be.
Me talking because I really love to
share, what we have done and how we've
solved this problem to a large scale.
And then towards the end, I'm gonna
probably, try to do like a deep demo and
address some of the potential questions
that I think, people may be having.
So I'll start off by this,
what is incident management?
CQ probably here you probably
know this, but for folks who don't
know, a lot of this started with
fema, implementing nims, which is
National Incident Management System.
And then eventually as technology
companies picked up, everyone realized
the need for a dedicated team of
incident responders whose job essentially
is nothing but getting service back
up and running and that are so many
other teams that collaborate today.
You have your SRE, you have your DevOps,
you have your product owners incident.
Technology owners and depending on
which product's impacted and all of,
a lot of these teams sit together,
and collaborate on an incident given,
what's impacted and who's required.
And the landscape essentially
is changing because I'll give
one specific example here.
If you have worked with most big tech
companies or if you have at least
spoken to people there, you will see
the common theme is a lot of tools.
It's unavoidable.
Every tool provides something that the
other cannot, and you have to work with
all of these tools during incidents.
That's it's absolutely, you can
cut down the number of tools,
but you can't consolidate all
of that to one single tool.
So what I put there is
like a good example of.
The way incidents run at Twilio,
like we use the vendor fire hydrant
to declare incidents, run incidents.
We have PagerDuty to alert and
notify us during incidents and.
We use Zoom to actually
run an incident bridge.
We use Slack for a lot of Async
Chat, and it's 90% of the incidents
essentially are run on Slack because
you need Async communications with
all the different parties that.
That have to be present use.
We use Datadog for dashboards and,
notifying what product service status is.
Atlassian status page for status page
updates to customers Google Docs for
running our post incident retrospectives.
We use Confluence where
we have a ton and tons.
Theoretical knowledge, inner workings
of products saved over, 15, 18 years.
And we use slack canvas for
tracking, action items that
happened during incident.
So essentially you're seeing it's,
there's a lot of tools that are
working simultaneously at play
during incidents and it's unavoidable
and the challenge starts when.
You end up working the tools
instead of working the incident?
I'll repeat that and I'll let
the listeners think about it.
As an incident responder, your prime
focus is mitigation, bringing the
customer services back up and running.
The impact of products
back up and running.
The challenge starts when you spend
too much time working some of these
tools, trying to gather information,
understand impact, trying to gather
data, start documenting things, which
is, don't get me wrong, absolutely
critical, but when you spend too much
time doing that, as an incident commander
or incident manager, your primary
goal or my primary goal is making sure
teams are working on what is required.
Asking the right questions
ensuring that the conversation or
discussion doesn't go off topic.
And we are stay focused on mitigation
ensuring that if someone's too
opinionated, pushing back on them and.
Having everyone focus on the single
goal, which is mitigation, and all of
this needs a ton of focus attention,
which, if diverted from, it's extremely
hard to drive the incident and
take it all the way to mitigation.
What is the solution?
How can AI help with internal external
incident response communications before,
during, and after incidents like.
That's, as I said, that's the primary
focus that I wanted to talk about today.
Here's like a good snippet that
I found on Atlassian's website.
And the top, what is,
oh, something's wrong.
Monitoring tool alerts and escalates.
The on-call team joins everyone.
Swarms back to normal document.
What failed, remediate, move on, right?
That's what we see, but
here's what our customers see.
Something's wrong.
They don't know about it.
What's going on?
We haven't gotten communications.
The status page is still green.
They start panicking.
They start calling their account managers.
They start filing in those
Zendesk, tickets or any support
tickets that, that they have.
And most companies, seem
to use Zendesk, but.
Just to give an example, and
they start emailing, creating a
ton of, like a flood of support.
Tickets start to come in and
they assume the worst they get
angry, which is very normal.
You are paying a huge amount of
money for those products and services
and for them to be down and you
are end users to, to feel the pain.
It's.
Frustrating.
And they're back to normal, but
less trust in this company, right?
Because here is, I've been working
across different industries
over the course of 15 years.
I worked in carrier avionics banking,
finance and now communications platform as
a service, which is which is with Twilio.
One thing that's common is if
you do not communicate well
enough with your customers.
From the time an incident starts
all the way till it ends, what
you're gonna do to fix it?
Are you making sure this
doesn't happen again?
Future prevention, your
classic idle terminology.
If you don't do that,
customers lose trust.
One incident, two incidents,
three incidents, four incidents.
As time progresses, trust is broken
and once broken it's very hard to men.
So communication during
incidents, absolutely critical.
So one of the hackathon projects
this year that I chose to work
and build for Twilio was a bot.
A bot that can gather information
real time and present it.
With the simplicity of a slack command
since one of the, one of the principles
that I really like to stick with
is when you're running an incident,
as I said at the start, when you're
juggling different tool juggling between
different tools, you lose a lot of time.
What if you could stay in a single
tool, let's say Slack and get
all the answers you need without
having to juggle and bounce around?
I'm not saying the other tools are not
important, but it's the frequency of
how often you juggle and move around is
what determines how quickly and how much
more present you are on an incident.
As the incident commander,
as the incident manager.
So I'll not dive into details, but
I'll try to keep it high level here.
And then if you are curious and
I'll leave a link to my LinkedIn.
We can chat more.
I'm happy to share, how we did
this but for the purposes of,
con 42, I'm gonna share it.
Idea, and I'll give as
much details as I can.
But we used a tool called Windmill
and we ended up building a Slack
app, which makes a call to open ai.
And then, which is again, integrated
to every single tool that we have that
I showed you on the previous slide.
Zoom voice, zoom chat, slack,
chat, everything's in the chat.
Fire had our incident.
A management tool.
Wiki pages because all the theoretical
knowledge about how customers use the
products are on our Confluence and Wiki
pages, which is like a ton of information,
but accessibility, on exactly what
you need when you need in an incident.
That's hard.
And we've integrated it in such a way
where we can tap into that information.
20 seconds.
So simple commands in slack.
Ask what you want and it'll give you
real time contextual information.
And we can even one can even give a
persona, which is what we ended up
doing, where we can give each command
a persona and the persona essentially.
Describes who you are
asking that information for.
So what I did this over here is
created a command saying when I
type this command with an incident
number, I want you to give me.
What a technical customer would want
to know about this incident as a,
somebody, as a somebody and another
command saying, give me a high
level status page post that I can
integrate and post on, status page.io.
And then another command dedicated
to asking questions that I can
literally go in and just ask
the dumbest of dumb questions.
Silliest of silly questions that
people are often reluctant to
interrupt the triage bridge.
And ask, right?
Because if the people who are fixing
it start getting distracted and
start answering you on what's broken
it's a slippery slope because you
are getting updates now, but you're
also losing precious time where
actually something could be fixed.
I'll go ahead and give you a
quick demo, and I'll try to speak.
About, what we thought about and
what was the ideology behind it it
and how we are actually using it.
So for the demos right now, if you see
here, I've created like a public Slack
channel, only for this demo Con 42 demo.
And in this channel and
this is something we.
People also run event, people
run in incident channels as well.
But just for the sake of
this demo I'll show you this.
So right here the three commands that
I mentioned that we ended up, creating
for this, and I keep saying we, because
there's like a team of six, seven
people who worked on it within Twilio,
just for the hackathon to solve the
common problem that, that, that was
in front of us every single incident.
Windmill HVC is for generating
technical summary for customers.
Windmill sp is for status page summary
or, simpler motor genetic explanation.
And then windmill Gen is our gen
command where we can essentially.
Ask questions on what we want.
So for the purpose of this I'll
show you the Vin Gen command.
Let's take an example.
I can simply go ahead and say,
Hey, VIN Gen what are Twilio's core
products and how do customers use them?
Now if you look at it, all
this knowledge and info.
It's present internally
in our help center.
It's tons and tons to hundreds,
thousands of documents.
The accessibility is what this was about.
And in, in the next, I'd say about few
seconds, if you see here, just gave me
a response and it started explaining
for every product what it means, what
customers use about, yeah, not impressed.
I'll show you one more.
What if we go to a partner where, say
email Jan my customer is reporting a 5 0
3 adder on all of their Twilio services.
What could this mean?
Again the reason such features were
important is we have tons and tons
of different teams who talk with
different parties, like customers,
account executives and all of them
have different varieties of questions.
And it's very important.
It was very important to, to be to have
a channel that anyone can literally
ask anything and get answers they need.
So if you see here, it was able to
describe why the 5 0 3 error means service
unavailable common causes, and then it was
also able to point some troubleshooting
articles in our internal product docs
that we have for customers on how they can
solve such an issue or what logs can they
gather when they encounter such an issue.
Now I have a few.
I have a few test incidents right here.
These are incidents we have created on our
incident tool, so I'm gonna be using them
to show you what the and again just to
remind, when I generate these, it's gonna
be static, but during an actual incident.
The information keeps evolving.
So for an example, the way I'm talking
right now, so if this was an actual
incident, everything I'm speaking real
time right here, gets transcribed, is
made available to our AI model, and it
can contextualize between what is being
said, real time on Zoom, what is being
available, what's available in our wiki
pages, in our theoretical knowledge
base, and understand what exactly.
Is the user asking for and
come up with that app summary.
So if I say four slash windmill
HVC 1, 5, 0 8, 9, now it's
actually like a test incident.
And then when I mention, 1, 5, 0, 8,
9, give me a technical verbiage that
I can go speak to my customers with.
And it'll instantly say.
This was a test incident
initiated and quickly resolved
with just over two minutes.
There was no customer impacts.
And then, the best part
is I can quiz it further.
Email Jen, what time did the incident?
1, 5 0 8, 9 start.
And not just the time there's,
there are layers of questions.
One can ask just dive de into extreme
details to what this person did.
When did we find out about this
first, what was the anomaly?
And it'll give exact details of real time.
And this is a lifesaver because
if you have been in incidents and
you've seen incident chats, there are
hundreds if not thousands of messages
in a matter of minutes and hours.
And it's hard to keep track of what's.
It's being said, and what exactly
is the info that you are looking
for, especially when the incident
starts and you are it's chaos, right?
The first few minutes are often chaos
because you're trying to wrap your
head around where the issue is, right?
Who caused this?
Was it a vendor?
Is it upstream?
Is it downstream?
Is it us?
Is it, a carrier?
It's absolutely chaotic.
And the other thing that we found,
this model is super real time.
So it generates responses like in, within
20 seconds, but even like right one minute
into an incident run this model and it
generates answers super, super quickly.
So let's create another one.
I'll say in sp now this
time I'm gonna ask it.
Different example to create
like a status page post for me.
This is one of the things we are
actively exploding and doing,
a prototype testing on to see.
Because the eventual goal is to automate
this directly to our status page.
So when we have an incident we can be
confident enough that we have trained
the model to take the info, filter out
internal stuff versus external, and then
automatically post on the status page.
Imagine how impactful and.
Efficient that would be for
customers to get notifications.
So if you see here, it literally creates
it in a title and body format, which
is very standard and status page.
It'll be a title and there'll be a body
that describes what the incident is.
And yeah.
And it's super, super useful to take away
all the focus, and all the noise out of,
people were actually like troubleshooting
and just put all that all that in a
summarized systemic way for people
to be able to like, question and get
answers to hey, it's, it super simple.
Tool, but it is absolutely effective.
And then the best part is I won't
be able to do it here, but we can
generate post incident retrospective.
We can generate out of four drafts.
We can literally ask what we want and
the model will generate a lot of these
for us to be able to like, use it for
communications internally and externally.
And so coming back.
Yeah, that's how quickly this
model's been responding so far.
It's less than 30 seconds.
And, getting answers
in a real time manner.
And yes.
That's me.
You can scan that QR code,
it'll take you to my LinkedIn.
I am based outta Seattle, so if
you are in the area, let me know.
Would love to catch up for
a coffee, lunch, whatever.
And yeah, I'm always
open to collaborating.
Learning sharing what I know on
how to make incidents better.
Incident response is something
super near and dear to me.
I've been doing this for, as I
said, like 15 years at this point.
And communication during incident
responses is something that I
started exploring, late last year.
And when I realized how important
that is and how prudent it is to keep.
Customers come and earn that
trust or retain that trust
even in the toughest of times.
So once again thank you con
42 for this opportunity and
thank you all for listening.
Have a great rest of your day.