Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining me today.
My name is Kumar.
I'm executer to present on the topic
that is critical for modern enterprise
a power testing preventing SAP
and Salesforce instant before they
happen in the production environment.
Enterprise instance often arise from.
Testing of Complex SAP
and Salesforce system.
But here the good news is this one.
By leveraging artificial intelligence
and mission learning organizations can
identify the potential failures before
the impact to the productions systems.
This approach dramatically reduced the
testing cost while boosting the test
coverage and the accuracy with the, along
with the quality validations, or the next
20, 30 minutes, we are going to explore
why this matters, the challenges we face,
how AI can transform the test strategies.
Let's dive in.
Let's start with the big picture.
SAPS four.
HANA and Salesforce are the backbone
of the countless global business
operations, covering everything from
simple chain management, which is
supply chain man management tool,
customer relationship management.
Now with artificial intelligence,
open this platforms.
Think.
Predict you, analyticals and
SAP, sales and distributions,
metal management, finance.
Transport management modules, so many
modules and our automated code to
cash business process in Salesforce
system, we are witnessing a revolution.
But this revolution comes with challenges.
AI introduce dynamic adaptive
systems that traditionally testing
methods struggling to keep on.
Considering the AI system in SAP
automates the general entry to ensure
with the SO and JXP regulations.
When we are talking about the SO and JX
P regulations, it's a very important for
the complaints and regulator industry.
A single mismatch could lead a significant
financial losses or legal issues
or a picture in Salesforce platform.
Mispricing a contract, it going to
be break the customer trust as well
as it going to impact the revenues.
These are not just possibilities.
These are the real risks
in the current environment.
Today, the tradition testing,
it's a static scripts with manual
process for the shot and automation.
Also, whatever the automation which
we are doing that is also have the
some limitations with the test data
as well as this one, the actions
which we perform through automations,
but because of a algorithm.
Over the time, this demands new approach
with the continuous quality validations.
Along with this one, complaints,
regulations, controls to maintain
the data integrity and system
performance, user confidence and coming.
What does this means?
Intelligent testing to bring in the table.
It's a game changer.
This approach leverages the advanced tool
like Tic Toska Robotic Process Automation.
We also call as A RPA.
Frameworks and a agent simulate the
real world scenario, actively identify
the issues in SAP, for instance,
intelligent testing can monitor aid
driven outputs across all the tracks like.
S-E-M-G-T-S-S-D-M-M, uh, it's gone.
It's, it's, it's, uh, all the tracks
including Salesforce, but catching
the issues before the escalate in
the Salesforce, validating the price,
accuracy and workflow efficiency,
the key factor in the customer
satisfaction and business success.
And does, and it does not stop
here with the raise of generative,
a stakes even get even higher.
The technology capable of creating the
content of making decision requires
testing the beyond the functionality.
Now, intelligent testing, not
only verifying through validation,
but also verify the ethical Aus
aligning with the certifications like.
SAPA ethics and mitigating the biases
that could, that could be otherwise.
It's a compromise of fairness.
Without this, the, we risk the
deployment failure complaints,
breaches, and loss of credibility.
That could be industry back.
Let me share some real time example, my
own experience, um, where I serve this
as, as a senior quality assurance guy,
we design and developed few agents that
generate the test score, execute the
test plans in the tool, the agent will
analyze this one, the changes the live
compare reports, what SAP transports.
Which is changes.
And if coming back to the sales force,
what GitHub, GitHub pull request is it?
How this automatically determines
the regression impacts?
This is one project where the, our
intelligent tool reduce the manual
testing by 40 to 50 percentage.
By reading this one, the SAP changes,
what are the changes they brought?
What are the business
process they're changing?
What are those object and what are the
Salesforce objects has been changing
by going through this one full request.
Our change summary.
By reading this one, our
intelligent tool, well intelligent
testing related automation, ai.
It ensures this one.
We have comprehensive coverage
for the AI and enhanced future.
And, uh, without overlooking the
critical, the complaints is validation.
If I going through further here
on the intelligent testing,
the, um, the RPA bots, generally
RPA bots we create for automating
the repetitive rule-based tasks.
The bots is mainly familiar with this one.
Financial workflows such as general inter
posting, accounting, reconciliations,
various analysis and financial statements.
Scratch check with the high precisions.
But not only that, even, uh, the
eds, electronic data interchange,
electronic data interchange.
Sales order tions the implementing
of RPA bots in controlling testing,
we are minimizing the human error
and boosting the efficiency here.
And the recent audits also
where the bots identified the
discrepancies in SOX complaint
as process and the manual review.
It might be missed on this,
the SOX complaints is that
manual reviews might be missed.
The permitting, the
potential regulation is,
let's not to forget this tic, where the
corner stones of the intelligent testing
I have used to build, uh, automated
regression test cases for multi modules in
SAP as well as Salesforce, for instance,
upgrades and the roll loads where SD
and mm, which is sales and distribution.
Mm. Integrations comes.
With the aid driven automation, the
Toska module based allow us to simulate
the end number of scenarios defect early
escalating, the go live by the weeks.
It's a, in the, especially in the
logistics area, the real world
application, it's not only ensure
the seamless integrations and
transitions from the legacy system
to SAP, but also make them the SOCs
and JXP stakeholders Confluence.
Let's, we'll go with the, some of the
examples here, how the intelligent
testing safeguard the, our operations
dive into this one, into AI much faster
and more reliable in the deployment.
But here the question for all of
us, are we prepared for this shift?
A become more embedded in our workflows.
The demand of intelligent testing
will only grow the organization that
adapts will lead the package while this
don't, may fall behind.
This is not just about technology,
this is about the building trust.
Ensuring the complaints is unlocking the
full potential of AI enterprise solution.
So what can we do first?
Investing in the right tools, platforms
like Tosca, RPA, frameworks at this time.
Second, trying the teams
beyond the tradition testing.
Embarrassing the AI adaptability.
Third culture, which is continuous
improvement, where testing
is, involves the technology.
Now,
the intelligent testing, it's
just a technical requirement.
It's a strategic as well.
Let's we go to the deserve
to shape the future where the
technologies empower us all.
So what will happen if this intelligent,
it'll not serve this one if you're
not covering the major testing.
What will happen on this?
The main thing, this one, it, the testing.
If it's not happened, the impact
will be on the business operations.
It'll damage this when your
relationship with the customer,
it, uh, stick the loss of the
financial, it'll impact the business.
So that is the reason it's a very
critical to have this intelligent testing.
So far, we've gone through this one,
why the intelligent testing is required
and how that makes the difference.
On top of this one, manual
testing and automation testing,
understanding the enterprise
testing challenges.
Now, let's break down
the challenges First.
The complexity landscapes, like
SAP environment, the, the, the SAP
is having a multiple SAP system
and also S four SAP, S four hana.
It has a multiple modules that interact
interdependencies and also it's creating
a cascading failure of potential as well.
In the Salesforce.
On another hand, bringing the extension,
customization, frequent updates, the
system rarely operates isolation.
But this integrate with the
legacy applications, external
applica APIs application program
links and the data warehouses.
The tradition testing has a limits
where the manual testing
creation is a time intensity.
After it misses the full coverage of
the testing of the system interaction.
On top of this one, resource constraints
force the trade off between the thorough
testing as well as delivery timelines.
On top of this one, the statics
test suites become outdated as
system evolves leading graduation
degradation of efficiency.
So they understand here, there's this,
each client, each business operation.
The landscape as well as testing
challenge just will be different.
I'll try to cover a few of them here.
So, as I mentioned earlier, SAPS, Fourna
and Salesforce are powerful platforms.
That drive the critical business
operations and a right now, we are
using to enhance our testing efficiently
become the forbit challenges.
Let's, I'll drill on on this.
First, let's consider the scalability
integrations, which we have discussed
on this one, which is interacting
with the multiple models, which
is thousands of transaction data
flows across the global terms.
Each transactions, which we are,
we are rmi, that will create
a number of, uh, table data
along with this one that will impact with
the SOX and JX P process controls as well.
Salesforce with the CPQ with a multi-cloud
setup, add the layers of customization
where the price rules has been changed.
Now understanding this by going
through this one S four as as
well as Salesforce, they have
challenges in the data dependencies.
Both platform rely on the vast data
sets, like example, SAP, for financial
recognition, Salesforce for customer
analyticals, ensuring this one data
errors production without compromising
the security constraint hurdle.
In my experience, I've since many
project where inconsistent test
data lead to missed defects in the
integrations, which can be any SDMM,
anything, also discovering the post
go live, it'll be costing to the weeks
of rework and the project delays.
The third one, this one, the
face of change adds the pressure
with the continuous upgrades.
SAP has the releases, which is
quarterly or service back upgrades,
and Salesforce has this one
seasonal upgrades, which is winter,
summer upgrades, testing phase, shrinking
windows to validate the functionality
like the certain, uh, duration.
We need to test our entire, uh,
functionalities in those two environments
before it goes to the production
by adding artificial intelligence
and automation into the mix.
The challenges was intensify a
driven futures like predictive
analytics in SAP and.
Automate code generation in
Salesforce evolve dynamically and
making the static steps absolute.
This is evident where recent project,
where a model adjustment in Salesforce
require retesting 70% of the suite
stretching the timeline within.
And what are the example?
We have undergone this one key issues,
this lack of comprehensive test coverage
with the thousands of testation.
With the 5,000 per SAP module,
Salesforce, this critical path is
prioritizing the critical path is tough
complaints requirement like GXP in any
medical, medical or formal, critical.
Financial, uh, industry stocks
demands a hundred percentage accuracy
and, uh, the resource constraints
often limit the testing for 70, 60
percentage or 70 80 percentage coverage.
Leave the risk unadressed on this.
So what can we do?
The first step is this one adapting
the intelligent testing framework.
The tools like toca present, toca, which I
have used, automate the regression suites,
can handle the multi modules in SAP, the
reduce the 50 percentage of efforts, RP
parts, other tools which is implemented.
Automate the reputative validation, ensure
our consistency in financial framework.
The second thing, this one, investing
the robotic test data management.
This test data.
Can mimic the production safely on this.
And that is the shift left testing
catches the defects, a lean CSCD
pipeline to keep the face up the updates.
It is not only the about the
tool, it's a strategy that team
needs to be trying to understand.
These platforms must be ed,
the core investment, not on a
after through the difficulty.
Engaging 30 percentage may prove
very costly after go live on the S.
So by going through this one
E complexity, land complexity
landscape and traditional testing
limitations, the instant to preventive
actions, whatever the points we've
discussed, it's need to be carefully.
We need to address this information
will be held on the our building.
This one AI and machine learning process.
Now, AI and machine learning
testing in the core technologies,
the predictive analyticals for the
risk assessment mission, learning
from test optimization, NLPs.
How we are going to do on this?
So how do we address these
challenges in the real time?
So everyone, the usage of this one, this
core technologies is very, but let me
put in article B, how we can address
these challenges either entering a
mission, learning, let's, I mean, uh,
with the focus of this predictive anal
analyticals for the risk assessment.
Machine learning from test optimization
and the natural language processing
for the requirement analysis.
Testing involved for a manual
checklist for data-driven sciences
and a and machine learning are
the for beaten of the resolutions.
These technologies are reshaping
how ensuring this quality in complex
systems like SAPS four HANA and
the Salesforce, where error can
have far reaching consequences.
Let's debr one by one First, predictive
analytical for the risk assessment.
This technology using a historical
data, it could be the defect data
or the issues in the production
environment, which we coming across.
And AA modules to forecast where
the defects are likely to be occur.
Imagine you are, you're doing SAPS four
HANA upgrade or rollout with hundreds
of modules and tracks, T cores, where
single update could be triggered.
The cascade of issues like a price
example, price issue, or currency issue.
The predictive analyticals trained in
the on the past defect patterns can
prioritize the high risk areas like
complaints, critical workflows under
JXP SOS FDA regulations part level.
In my work, I have been seeing this
action, a predictive model flagged for
potential failures, a enhanced that.
Sales and distribution module and
inventory module to reduce the production
deployment at least for 25 to 30
percentage during a recent upgrade.
The next one, machine learning
and test optimization.
This approach leverages the algorithm
to refine the test suites by eliminating
the redundant and focus what it's matter.
Tradition testing after involves
how and of test cases saying
this one, take this one.
S 400,000 test cases.
Salesforce thousand test cases may
have char the outdated data updates,
machine learning, analyze the ex
execution results to identify the most.
Impactful testing, cutting
efforts by 40 percentage.
As we discussed earlier, when the
changes comes from S four, we are
going to read the one, the changes
about which object is impacting.
Similarly in Salesforce.
We are going to read out on this
one, what is the change summary?
Our pull request is what the score
change for by reading this one.
When we implement mission learning
driven tool that optimize your regression
testing, cutting the unnecessary work,
at least for 40 to 60 percentage.
On top of this one, they're shortening
the test cycle from weeks to days
while maintaining the coverage.
This is not only saves the
time, but also adapt the dynamic
nature of aid driven future.
Finally, the NLP that we call is a natural
language processing for requirement
analysis, NLP, and interprets the
requirement from unstructured text,
email documents, user stories from
xera or any, any pa any format turning
in inputs into pre, uh, six or, uh,
test cases, sorry, precious test cases.
The, the requirement.
You can say this one, there is
a blueprint or FTDs function.
Documents or technical requirement
documents or functional requirement
documents or specs, any format in this.
It'll read this one data and it'll be
convert into this one into precise test
cases in Salesforce CPQ project, where
the client requirements then evolved.
NLP used 50 pages of specs,
either functional technical
specs or user stories.
Identify this key test scenarios
to reduce the at least by 32.
For 30 to 50%.
I've used this in my career to
analyze the SAP notes, GitHub pull
request transports a live compare
reports or the objects list.
Ensuring this one we have have a
clearly articulated our test cases.
Along with this one, the
evident of test conditions.
This technology is crucial for managing
the complex AI requirement where
intent context matters as much as code.
Let's share the real world
example during S four ANA
implementation prior to analyticals.
Identify the high risk areas like a
global trade system co due to a modular
adjustment by focusing the testing.
There we have ed, potential
regulator, beaches.
Um.
The machine learning also, meanwhile,
the machine learning optimized the test
speed cutting down the return test cases.
NLP clarified the requirement from
20 pages change log, ensuring this
one we have the full coverage.
This combination prevented from delay
that could have the cost of millions.
So,
but how does this technology work?
Together we are talking about the
predictive analyticals pinpoint the
risk mission learning, streamline
execution, NLP, ensuring the
alignment with the business needs.
Together they're creating the
proactive testing ecosystem ideal
for AA enhanced platform, where the
tradition method will the challenges.
The integration of this tool required the
skill team to robust the data pipeline.
But the pace off is clear.
The faster releases, uh, fewer
defects and greater confluence.
What next?
Start by adapting this technology
increment, the, perhaps a pilot
with the predictive analyticals
for your next SAP updates,
a power testing strategies
in SAP environment.
We are going to break down
this one, our strategies, uh,
ASAP as well as Salesforce.
First, let's, we'll go with
the focus on SAP environment.
Uh.
So when we are focusing with
this one intelligent module with
integration testing, automate the
con customization, impact analysis,
performance, scalability, predictions.
As we discussed, S four is a very
critical, powerful business functions
we have with the complex integrations,
frequent updates, the tradition techniques
after fails, a shot, a stepping it
transform the landscape, offering
the targeted strategies to ensure
this one reliability and efficiency.
Let's this have a three
key approaches here.
First, intelligent module integrations.
This strategy uses a, a two.
Validate interaction across the,
all the SAP models where change is
one, like updating SD can impact MM.
Or finance a e. A agent analyze the
data flow and predict the integration
points, reduce the manual efforts.
We implemented by using a tool, Tosca Tic
Tosca and RPA, where an A module tested
between SD and finance integration and
SDN Mm integration for a inventory system.
It caught the data mismatch during
the pilot and preventing the.
Post-launch failure and
saves the rework as well.
In the financial point of view,
we, we have caught the defect
on the group currencies and the
conversions and also the reports.
We, we found the defects that was
helped us to avoid the rework,
the production environment.
The next one, the automate the
customization, impact analysis.
SAP environments, often
future custom codes.
Think pricing logic complaints as rules
for air socks and JXPA automates the
assessment, how this customization
reacts for updates and transport.
A recent project, we've used a technology
to analyze this one for live compare data.
Identify this one, what the changes
on this, how this going to affect
in our current business process, and
how many test cases will be impacted.
So we predict this one and we packaged
by doing this one upfront itself.
The regression team was saved 35
percentage of testing time by predicting
and doing the early work on this.
Finally, the performance
and scalability prediction.
This leverage AI to simulate the load,
predict system behavior under stress.
Critical for SA real time demands.
The tradition testing teams might
miss how an AI enhanced SCM module or
CRM module handles the peak traffic.
We deployed Predict Q Model that
forecast the performance during the
high value with the maximum load,
and we are revealing the
scalability of bottlenecks and
adjusting our configuration.
Pre-launch AWAI 20 percentage
slowdown by proving this AI
value, maintaining a up time.
Let's, we have some
real time example here.
AA predicted demand data
in a CM conflict with, uh.
Stocks level.
Automated customization impact analysis
that flagged the custom GXP complaints
as scripted need to be adjusted.
While performance and scalability
prediction ensure the system handle
the 50 to 60% of traffic spike
together, the strategy shaved together.
This strategies shaved up two
weeks of testing cycle and
ensure this one flawless go lie.
Why this matter?
C'S complexity, as we mentioned, and
the thousands of transactions and
few F print updates, a integrations
demands the precise testing,
the A power test strategies.
Reduce the risk, optimize the
resource, align with the business
goals, the change, the integration.
AI required
robust data, the FA pay off the
fewer defects, faster deployments.
Now let's we go back to the Salesforce
specific, a testing approach.
There are three trailer made approach.
Stand out
Salesforce specific, a testing approach,
focusing on declarative configuration
validation, third party testing and
user experience impact prediction.
The Salesforce power custom
centric operations worldwide from
CPQ to multi-cloud deployments
and the integration with ai
transforming how we can work.
But this is brings unique
testing challenges.
Tradition methods often miss the issues,
but by using a aid driven future, let's
explore this targeted strategies to
ensure the quality and reliability.
The first is declarative
configuration validations.
The Salesforce declarative tools
flows, workflows, and the validation
enables the rapid customization.
Often enhanced by AI for automation.
AI testing validates this
configuration for accuracy edge cases.
I used a power tool to test the
CPQ pricing flow where a module
adjusted discount dramatically.
And, uh, the, when I said this one
dramatically or the based on the country,
based on the customer, the setup,
the price dynamically, uh, changes.
And moreover, in the when the
real time to transaction is cha.
Uh, when we are real time when trying
to create the order in the backend
by user, any user has been changing
this one validations that dramatically
the system will choose, um, review
on that and immediately the system
will dynamically update this one.
So we brought, we brought that situation.
Where's the scenario?
And simultaneously we are checking this
one, the how this AA can adjust on this,
this validation caught a logical error.
Sometimes the word is going of.
Some, uh, 15 to 20 percentage.
We, we have prevented a revenue losses
of thousand during this one piloted.
So this approach ensure this one
configuration aligned with the business
rules even adapt, EY and AI adapt stem.
Next third party integration testing
Salesforce after integrated with the
external systems with SAP or payment
gateways or marketing platforms
where AI enhanced the data, syncing
our decision making AI testing
simulate this interaction, detecting
the failures at the boundaries.
In project.
At, in project I implemented air
driven testing for the Salesforce.
Uh.
PAP integration where a agent predicted
data inconsistency during the peak loads.
It's identifies a sync delay
allowing us to adjust the EPA
calls frequency before go live, the
awaiting the customer facing issues.
And finally, the user
experience impact predictions.
A predicts how changes new
future a enhancements are.
Update after an end user from
sales representative to customers
using machine learning modules.
It is analyzed the user
patents and simulate this one.
UI impacts.
I deployed this to access the access,
the Salesforce CPQ updates with the A
driven code generator, the prediction
flag with the uua lag for mobile
user prompting, the redesigning
the improved customer satisfaction
scoring by 22 30% edge post launch.
This ensure this one, the seamless
experience in a augmented environment.
Let's share some live example here
during, uh, rollouts declarative
configuration validation.
Ensure this one, the pricing rules
worked across the region, catching
the currency conversion glitch.
Third party integration testing, validate
the payment gateway link and preventing
the transaction failures during a
high volume sales user experience.
Impact predictions, conforming that
updates did not slow down in the.
Sales team.
This leading a successful launch
of zero deployment complaints.
Why this matter?
The Salesforce flexibility, there's
thousands of configurations and
integrations and user touch plan demands.
These AI approaches reduce the
risk, optimize the deployment,
enhance the user satisfaction.
This challenges lies in the data
quality and tool integration.
This benefits the few
defects, faster releases,
implementing the framework, building
a powered testing capabilities.
Let's outline the framework.
Let's start with this one.
Assessment and planning phase.
Evaluate the existing.
Testing capabilities, infrastructure
readiness and organization maturity.
Only the stakeholders in
objective and success metrics.
Ensuring this one system
support the data needs
the next technology stack.
Tool selection,
excuse me.
Then data strategy, model development,
developing the strategies for data
collection, storing while maintaining
the security using interactive, excuse
me, for the continuous refinement.
Finally, the integration
with the existing workflows.
Ensuring a tool will measure the seamless
with CACD pipeline test management.
Sorry, the assessment
of, uh, planning phase.
So
let, let, let's walk through framework
step by step first, as we discussed
at the beginning, assessment of
planning phase, what is this?
What it does?
Actually, this evaluates your current
testing landscapes and the process skill
gaps and identify the pain point, sorry.
Identify the pain points like manual
coverage gaps, slow regression cycles.
I lead the assessment for the S four
and uncover 60% of test cases where.
Redundant due to outdated scripts.
This phase let's goals says, reduce
the defects by 30 percentage.
Build a roadmap for the
business objects, for the complaints,
SOX or gxp, FDA and speed.
The next data strategies
module, development A. A
thrives on the quality data.
So the steps mainly focus on
gathering and preparing the data sets,
test results, defects, logs, user
behavior, developing the AM modules,
trial and made to your needs, like ing
the risk and optimizing the test cases.
We designed a module using a historical
SAPS four, as well as Salesforce
data to forecast defect prone areas,
improving the test focus by 30 to 40% day.
This phase requires a clean
and secure interactive mod
to reflect the real world scenarios.
The third one is this one, the
technology stack and tool selection,
choosing the AI tool fit your ecosystem,
and we selected few projects,
toka ml, FAT M two, enhance SAP
testing, cutting the execution time.
We did this one and the scalability
of future growth on that.
Finally, the integration
with the existing close.
This step embedded a testing in CACD
pipeline Q processing and the team
practice the seamless integrations, which
is reduce the DF 20 percentage defect.
Quarterly proving of this,
you can ask me this one.
Why does this framework matters?
Building a power testing
is one of the project.
It is a transformation.
Without assessment, your risk
mis, uh, misaligned goals without
data and models a lack accuracy.
Without the right tool,
scalability suffers, and without
integration adaption styles.
The challenge is this one,
balancing investment with the
results, but the payoff, faster,
smarter testing and and level.
How do we start?
Begin with this one.
Some pilot project assessment
phase, focus on single model.
It could be the S-D-R-M-M or finance.
Build a data strategy, the accessible
test data, select the tool and
integrate increment incrementally.
The this phase approach
cut down the data leakage.
2235 percentage showing a major success.
The technical implementation requirement
during the technical implementation
needs the, the robust, robust
data, the key types including, uh,
historical test results production.
Logs, user behavior data
and the configuration.
High quality drives data is crucial
for effective module training
only.
Deduction data preparation, cleaning,
labeling sensitive information ensure
our compliance model, integrity.
The foundation strategies paramount
for a L learning capabilities.
Operationally, the seamless integration,
which is key with the C-E-C-A-D, sorry,
with CACD pipelines, the test tool,
tool management, like you can see zero
or Q test and automation Framework.
Framework like a selenium is critical.
Scalability and performance and data
security is vital, especially for the
large system like SAP and Salesforce.
Adhering to regulator like GDPR must be
core part of the operation framework.
Technical deep, A testing architecture.
Let's take a deep look
into this one architecture.
The core, a engine has a three component.
One is data registration layer collects
cell logs, performance metrics, the
machine learning engine process, the data
testing intelligence, the decision, eh.
Uh, sorry.
The decision engine commands the insights
and generate the actionable recommendation
based on the business practice,
the integration.
API first designed the flexible
tool chain and even driven the
architecture for the real time
response view with the bi directions
by enabling the backbone integration.
So the main thing, this one here,
we, we are doing on this one.
The scalability relies on the
distributing processing of the
various demands, catching the
performance, multi modules tell the
business what they need from this.
So the main thing, this one in SAP and
Salesforce, the core A engines where
you collect the information that's
based on that, we, we are generating
the predictive analysis that will
enhance using this machine learning.
We process this one, that algorithm that
makes this one rule based decision that
the core components will go into on that.
From there, we are going to integrate
this one architecture platform.
Then the scalability
concentration will come
risk based testing and, uh, predictive
and intelligent risk assessment,
predictive failure analysis, dynamic test.
Again,
this will vary based on the,
which project you're working for,
which your client you're working.
Intelligent risk assessment model.
Use that AI to access
the failure properties.
Again, failure probability, it'll come.
Considering this one, the what
data you've been fitted concerning
that complex business process.
Like each, as I mentioned this
one, each application, each
business process critical.
And how you customize by predicting
failure analysis enable the oration,
forcing the failures modules by analyzing
the code changes, integration patterns.
So very important how you are feeding
this one, uh, predictive analytics.
Based on that system start reacting.
Dynamic test A are just the testing
focus in the real time based on
the risk and business needs too.
Ensuring this one, you have
this one given this one, right?
Uh, impact areas and also the mission
learning, especially the corrections
we are naming, enabling the practice.
Interventions.
This will truly chain your,
truly will enhance your ai.
How you are building on this?
So as I told you this one, the
based on your, the predictive
data, which is how you feed in,
uh, how you feed your, uh, system.
Based on that, the algorithm we need
to build based on that, it will be
paid off by cutting the defect much
earlier in the production system before,
uh, going to the production system,
automate the test generation
and smart selection.
Let's talk about the automation here.
A driven test case creates the creation,
uses the machine learning, analyze
this one, system specs, user behavior,
generating the comprehensive test
cases or standard and edge scenarios.
So NLP translates the requirement
to ex executable, at least
for 30 to 40 percentage.
We need to review and we need to
adjust this one, our rules and we
need to review whatever the, uh, test
intelligent tested, are generated.
Put this one the test conditions and
feed our, um, automated, uh, NLP.
And based on that, whatever the
data you are getting, um, make sure
this one that is being maintained
in very sensitive informa.
I mean since to be, um, the ensuring
this one, the integrated works
well, the adapt to test, uh, suite
optimization, continuously defined
suite by identifying the redundant test
cases, coverage gaps, and generating
the additional test cases as we need.
And, uh, this, again, this
is very continuous program.
The system is key on changes.
The new rules will come, some of them
business process will going to be updated.
So this is a continuous implement
activity where you have to make this
one automate test case generation
and smart selection simultaneously.
You're going to bring this money,
your regulation, library, new cases.
At the same time.
You have to make sure this one, some
of the uh, uh, the test cases, which
is not, uh, not u currently not in the
business process and then not, not useful
for, to identify the defect on that.
So you have to enhance this one.
Then only your AA will shine on this
self, self-healing systems track
to monitoring on this here, here
where, uh, where it's exactly, um,
I mean, uh, here where I'm exceeded
here, there's self-healing systems.
So autonomously, uh, issue resolution
uses the machine learning to
identify the issue, and we are
preventing the corrections, uh, uh,
by using a AA vision, detecting the
deviation with that signal problem.
The continuous validation and
monitoring prevents the ongoing health.
Catching this one, the issues.
So when, and this is usually
used to come across this one ey.
Like whenever this one, the position
of this one, the fearless lens has
been changed, our self feeling system
with a vision, it'll go and it'll
be to the corrective adjustments.
And so that, um, without your
communicating the system, system
will, we have driven the rules.
And based on that, uh, it'll be, it'll
go and correct this one and wait for our
confirmation once we confirm on this one.
And it'll be implemented in
this one irrigation library.
So we made the checklist
before implementing.
The one of our review will come on.
This one, and I'll confirm on this, is
again, feedback loop integration enabled
continuous learning, analyzing the test
effectiveness, instant prevent success.
This is how we are preventing even the
instance in the fu um, production system.
This is applicable for both
SPO as well as, uh, uh.
Salesforce integration
with the CSCD pipeline.
Um, as we discussed earlier, the seamless
pipeline integration leverage the existing
architecture tool, standardizing a PA
flexible across the architecture, the
real time the quality gates makes the
intelligent deployment decision based on
the test results and the risk assessment.
Uh, mainly we are covering
the business criticality.
The automated rollback decision
monitors the post deployment metrics
and triggering the rollbacks and the
instant, the safe way decision aggregate.
Um, I mean the safe net supports
the aggressive deployment while
maintain the reliability on this, this
main thing is this one seamlessly.
How you're integrating on that, how
you maintain the real time quality
gate and, uh, automate the roll
practition making on anything, uh, that
safely we can maintain the deploys.
Measuring success and, uh, me, uh, metrics
and ROI, how do we know it is working?
Measuring success involves the quantity to
metrics improve the test coverage early,
um, defect, uh, detections, reducing
the testing time and cycles, fewer
deployment issues and co cost savings.
Quant, uh, quality to and quantitative
we see enhance, uh, developer experience
better per quality, increase team
confidence, improve the risk management.
Long-term value includes the
faster innovations market,
competitive customer satisfaction,
and up to new, new technologies.
This metrics proved the return
on investment of a power testing.
Here we go.
The future of enterprise testing.
Looking ahead, AI testing is shifting
us from reactor to predictive approach.
Advanced mission learning like deep
learning, will detect the substant
failure patterns while cloud navigate the
testing with a scale and microservices
emerging integrations patterns.
API first design, event driven
architecture and low code platforms
will bring the new challenges and
opportunities Organization adapts.
This capabilities will gain the
competitive advantage in the
reliability and deliverable.
The future is bright.
I would like to.
Tell you this brings us Anna end.
Thank you so much for your attention.
I hope you gain valuable insights,
how AA can prevent the instance in S
four SAP Anna, Salesforce environment.
I'm happy to take the questions, but
as this is online, I'm stopping here.
Thank you everyone.