Hello everyone.
My name is Gobin Kaman.
I'm a data architect enable digital
transformations through data strategy
and ea. I focus on ERNI, industry,
sector and specialist and oil and guests.
Today I'll be presenting on how
AA is reshaping the master data
governance in an SAP environment.
And I'll also take you through with the
small use cases, which is an incident
management application as we talk
about data such as customer master.
Suppliers, materials, enterprises,
asset management or HR data such.
For any example, employee
data are considered.
These data are considered a blood line of
any enterprise applications when this data
is inaccurate, inconsistent, or outdated.
This affects the operational SAP
processes such as supply chain, order
to cash, or even infect the finance.
It also doesn't stop there.
It also impacts their downstream
applications, which consumes
this data and use this data.
Any change to the data will, not
just going and updating data,
it needs an incident management
application where you had to submit
an incident to correct the data.
And the data stewards who are responsible
for that have to come and put their
effort to correct the data and replicate
the data to the respective applications.
Today I'll be taking through the journey
from a traditionally MDM to an A driven
cognitive MDM and practical SAP use
cases, implementing that approach.
We will discuss about how AI
brings an A actionable results.
Measurable results, actionable
insights, and forward looking, how
implementing those set solutions.
Let's start with the governance approach
and see how this can be mitigated, but
then instant management applications.
As we all know, data is the backbone
of A-E-S-A-P applications, rather
any ERP applications, right?
It connects to the various business
processes or operations such as
procurement, finance, or supply chain.
Of data.
So data is the DNA for ions.
If the DNA is corrupted, you're
right, everything will go back
and then it'll fall apart.
You cannot uncompromised on this data.
Incorrect data, right?
How these, this has
been done traditionally.
Traditionally, our systems are
built and relied on manual rules.
That means that can be manageable
when the volume is limited.
Or the proactive measures can be taken
through a manual processes, right?
Ghana, the days now things are changing
by a globalization with the imp, with the
inclusion of multi-system environment,
a rule-based approach are fragile,
slow, and prone To understand this
challenge better, let's get to a few
master data maintenance limitations.
How cognitive MDM can address
this challenge, right?
Let's shift into that traditional MDM
limitation so that you'll all understand
how, what is the key challenges
using a traditional md, as we all
know, we talked about that rule-based
validations and a manual fencing impact.
Traditional MDM to be slow as this cannot
cap up, this cannot keep up with the PA
pace when there is a velocity increases
or the variety of data changes, right?
Key challenges includes such static
data that do not adapt to a business
scenario such as consolidations or
harmonization, and also do not support
an extension to a new product line.
Majority of the traditional MDM
were batch managed batch process,
managed that delayed detection
until the, until it is too late.
It has a huge challenge.
It's more of a reactive approach.
The struggle is in the distributed
environment where the correction
need to be started from the MDM
applications and then replicate
to the consumer application.
Research shows that poor data maintenance.
In an enterprise application on an average
impacts $13 million annually, right?
That's not it.
It does not stop with the cost.
It also includes 41% of data,
professional work data, professional
car time is getting wasted.
It can be, which it can be
used for innovating purposes.
Now it's a time to sift how
through an AI transformation.
A transforms MDM to a deterministic
to a cognitive though, right?
How a brings up machine
learning that enables a pattern
recognition and anomaly detection.
Natural language processing
unlocks the unstructured data
and improves the useability.
A sentimental reviews can be read
through that unstructured data
and text can be read through that.
And based on that.
Incident can be created
automatically where incident
management can help with this.
With the preventive predictive analytics
in place, the set of governance
from a reactive to a proactive
can happen when AI arguments MDM
organization move from a firefighting
mode to a preventing them right?
I can give a few real time examples
instead of waiting for a duplicate vendor
need to be corrected in the first place.
Right now what is happening is it's
waiting for them payments to be
failed, and the system flags if the
duration that duration can happen.
Instead.
If we were able to do that well
in advance, this detection can
happen well in advance so that the
correction can be early in advance.
How the evolution happened from a
traditional versus a cognitive brain.
Since we got a good handle of
traditional MDM, as we all talked
about a rule-based workflow, our
rule-based definition has been made.
MDM has a limitations.
Now, traditional MDM has a limitation.
Now let's do a quick compare how
a traditional MDM can be a can
be an issue with the cognitive
MDM against the cognitive M dm.
In traditional MDM, as we talked about
majority death cases, it's all rule-based.
Majority of them are generally
central managed, right?
Which means that somebody has
to come and correct the data
and manually intent process.
It's all reactive and a
batch processes, right?
Which means that you had to wait for the
failure to happen and somebody manually
have to go and correct this data.
This is an which, an impact, right?
In contrast, when we do the cognitive
M DM machine learning algorithms.
Natural language process.
Our predictive analytics can ha
help improving this processes,
you take the proactive measures.
Adapt that and address the realtime
issues on and off on directly.
It's capable of also, it is
also capable of handling a large
volume of data in a sub-second.
This approach from a traditional
MDM to a cognitive M immune is not
just an incremental, you are not
sifting from one system to another.
It's whole paradigm shift.
The data governance evolved
from a static guardrail to an
intelligent self-improving systems.
So the challenge shows that.
There is a need for a smarter
way at adaptive governance
through a cognitive MDM.
This sits from the fundamental MDM
to a powered MDM solution, right?
How organization approach data
governance within the SAP ecosystem.
Now let's understand the impact
of when master data goes wrong.
Data, how, when there is an instant
need to be created and then instant
ripple through the SAP landscape.
There are four areas that need to focus
when incident need to be treated right.
How there are majority of the areas
such as data quality issues, which is
a inconsistency of data which spreads
across the module, impacted areas like
data analytics, where the direct impacts
to identify the right details or reporting
to the leadership of our customer.
Personally, I have seen
many such challenges.
Where involves heavy human
interventions to carry the data.
Obviously this will cost time and
money for any of the human projects.
Majority of the data projects invo
involves in the data quality corrections.
It also doesn't stop there just as the
data, it cascades the are, it propagates
the data into a integration points
such as the data which are created
or updated in the traditionally MDM.
Sends operational, send the data
to integration plans such as
operational SAP systems, or in fact,
to the downstream applications.
For example, if a EA Enterprise Asset
management data replaces the data to
a performance management system, the
rules that in the performance management
need to be corrected are calculated
based on the data, what it receives.
If the data goes bad, obviously the
rules will not match, and then the
performance calculation will go over.
This would impact, hit the preventive
or proactive maintenance or a
reactive maintenance process.
Wherein the wherein the process can go
bad and then it'll create a lot of issues
in the preventive maintenance process,
especially in the oil and gas sector.
It also has a valid velocity changes.
When there is a velocity
that volume changes.
In the global instance, such as the
global Master declaration, the issue
doesn't stop in one location, it
spreads to the other areas as well.
These are the very concerning
for the centrally managed
objects, such as customer master.
It replicates the data to the
all the subsequent applications,
which impacts this data.
It also impacts the operational
resilience, depends on
preventing that failure early.
A single corrupted supplier
data today, no longer, it'll
not just stop the supply chain.
Impact.
It also impacts the foundational
data that cannot be compromised.
The effects can propagate to the
multiple layers of the enterprise
architecture, as you all know, from
the data ingestion to the operational
systems, to the data consumption systems.
Speaking to all these challenges
with the new tools and technologies,
the challenge can be addressed via.
A solution which has an which
enhances resilience by making a data
ance as a proactive ance, right?
Instead of your reactive
or a firefighting mode.
Three pillars of the there are
three pillars which can drive this
transformations, machine learning,
natural language processing,
and then predictor analytics.
These are the three key pillars
which A, can be driven and help this
cognitive implementing cognitive.
Machine learning, for example
it can detect and correlate the
SubT related data predictor.
Lyze anomalies automate the
classifications and it gives
a it gives a good results.
For instance, anomaly detection capability
that far exceeds from the human analytics.
In today's world, what data stewards
are doing it is they're taking a
report out of a Power BI or an Excel.
They scan through the data.
They're finding an anomaly of
this data is very cumbersome.
It's not easy to do a manual
interpretation and try to find that data,
which cost a lot of time and energy.
Further, this can be overridden by
writing in ML languages, whether all
those challenges can be addressed and
anomaly detection can be done within
the Sub-Zero seconds, as you all know.
NLP natural language pricing, right?
There are unstructured data
which relies on customer.
Data can be relayed on the desktop
applications from the users, or it
can be relay on the data management
applications such as DMS or D two systems.
Any of these unstructured data
enables a conversational governance
by leveraging the value through her.
Text extraction wherein NLP will go read
that data and then find that text out.
You can do the sentimental analysis
based on the user's response saying
that, okay, this is a good data.
I helped to remediate by this processes.
All those things, based on their
interactions with the systems, these
sentiments can be read and then future
forward looking it can correct its
own predictive analytics, right?
Helps to identify the
risk very well in advance.
And materialize and focus that issues
in a potential on the potential
these data can, these issues can
happen and potentially instant can
be triggered well in advance, right?
Based on the time series
analysis, it has its own, and then
historical data analysis together.
These create a cognitive layer
over the A PM, dm, S-A-P-M-D-G,
haa and data outs and on.
From 2025 SAP roadmap, adding SAPM,
dg, MDG on B two P applications, which
supports a and ML capability, right?
Analytics, a driven analytics is part
of the SAPM, DG MDG solution with the
data quality controls as they make
it to their a core as a solution.
Looking forward with all the
foundational layout laid out.
Now let's jump into understand how
operational AA is supporting this in M
dm. How this can be implemented, right?
Cognitive MDM for an instant readiness
classified into four different stages.
First, as we all know, we start with the
assessment and find the readiness of it.
The assessment on any data project
starts with the filing of data, right?
Evaluate the.
Current process maturity,
data, infrastructure readiness,
and other parameters.
This can be done through a building a LLM,
small LLM based on the AA to drive the
data profiling work where users can build
profiling dashboards from a live data and
perform appropriate, actionable cleansing
effort, okay, at the source and advise the
transformations logic to be implemented.
I personally have implemented a small
solution, which is a LLM that reads
the data from the live data, from
the systems or the legacy systems,
and generate the profiling dashboard
for the users that this have the
users to go and figure it out.
If there is a data cleansing data is
required when there is a transformation
project in place for them, and
then this will be help for them in
the transformation project across.
How do we approach, right?
We cannot just go and
do the whole deployment.
Instead, we had to go as a modular
architecture, deploy a domain
specific or use case driven modules.
Okay?
Integrating in C framework,
we don't want to just go and
boil the integration, right?
Our focus should be on a priority, our
severity, key use cases on the high
priority and the severity use cases, and
approach those as the priority one items.
Obviously there will
be a human interaction.
AI collaboration is must have, as you
all know, the data need to be the a LM
model need to be trained based on the
use case given by the data stewards and
with the SAP infrastructure framework.
Focus on the objects which are
high, complex logics to be trained,
complex objects so that the A model
can be trained and then enrich their
capabilities on the going forward.
Change management is one of the
key area which you need to focus
on the whole process, right?
It's not just a tool which derives
that or which determines the solution.
It's a mindset of people
also need to be changed.
They have to upskill their upskill,
redesign the process where necessary,
such as implementing a SIP two
implementing smaller solutions.
For example, a SIP two customer,
which today it has been manual
process of, integrating this and
then creating a workflow process
and all those things tomorrow.
We can de devise a plan saying
that if it's a region, it's this
one, and then sold to is this one.
All I need to do is automatic
this, automate this one so
that the STO can be created.
We don't need a manually interaction
attack with that, the structured framework
A becomes a Bolton, just a bolt-on tool.
We don't want to do this so we
need to have structured approach.
It becomes a trans that can be
transformable and help to build
the enterprise and the data set.
Data can be set right.
Unlike the periodic checks by a user,
unlike the periodic check by the
users, the quality reports, a model
can be trained continuously to monitor
and continuously evolve the data.
It can also assess the data and mediate
automatically, assess as needed.
How do we do the real time
monitoring and preventing right.
Given the business category like an
asset man asset manage asset maintenance
process, a realtime monitoring represents
one of the most significant ones in
the eight one management applications,
such as steam analysis, adaptive
thresholds, and pattern correlation.
In an EM based in an EM objects,
object types, and a maintenance plan
can drive a lot of, based on the
object type and the maintenance plan.
The insights of the asset
objects can be collected and
correlate to identify the pattern.
Incident can be caught before
they escalate with this, right?
For example, a sudden spike of an
rejected purchase order might be
a flagged in a real time by trace
of to a faulty vendor master.
This could be, and this can be corrected,
or if you do not correct this one on time,
it's gonna go into a financial process.
A based solutions can help to alter
alert the preventions by assessing
the business impacts, prioritizing
the risk, and escalate this
dynamically with the trend analysis
and this and the seasonal pattern.
Predictive issues, identification,
help to correlate the analysis and
identify the scenarios and respective
capabilities can be achieved.
Now, we talked about a benefits.
Proactive monitoring.
Also, right now, let's find how this
outcome will help how the outcome
a enhanced master data outcomes.
Our capabilities can accelerate the
root cause of analysis by providing an
intelligent investment support automate
the correlation analysis and pattern
recognition can be a future forward.
How do we accelerate the
root cause analysis, right?
A also accelerate root cause analysis
by automating the lineage tracing shows
where they error occurred, where it
started, and how the data occurred.
NLP interfaces allows the data steward
to ask, why did this error occur?
This allows the data steward to
identify and analysis through the
failure curve and predictive analysis.
Based on the analysis, data
steward can remediate the
data and replicate as needed.
This can be a good training
for their data model as well.
Multidimensional correlations
identifies across system impacts,
such as identifying and impacts and
m and the magnitude is very high.
This helps to prioritize the
investigation in RU root cause analysis.
The result of this
analysis is not just time.
It all it just reduce the time from
a days to an hours resolution becomes
smarter by announcing the detection
analysis, as you all know, right?
You detect early so that the analysis can
be done early and then the capabilities
can be achieved for an incident resolution
activities that can be addressed.
Many data related incident
without human information.
This can be reduced 50% of the data
towards time so that they can focus on
innovating the data solutions rather than
wasting the time on correcting the data.
How do we, the intelligent automation of
the resolution can happen when the, when
we say the resolution becomes smarter, but
then intelligent automation process, there
are some processes such as autonomous
data correction need to be established.
For an example, the system may
automatically correct and misclass
and misclassified the material code.
This can be notified to the
approvers and ensure that
compliance logs can be updated.
Predictive strategies based on the
historical impacts helps, which will help
reduce the resource optimization and find
the algorithms, the timeline predictions,
and model the estimate solutions.
Key benefits of routing the workflow
dynamically and artistry the
stakeholders to support their co
compliance and audit integration
with the release of 2025 and beyond.
SAP performs very heavily on the
a, a transformations a forward
for forward looking aid solutions.
SAP is simplifying the architecture,
as you all know, by introducing
the a and ml capabilities in
the areas such as SAP Hana.
In memory computing where ML libraries
and a real time replication can happen
and implementing an S-A-P-M-D-G solutions
where workflow enhancements have
happening, semantic improvements are
added, which includes the analytics.
Predictive analytics reporting has
been built, okay, but today world,
there, there is no predictive
analytics of the dashboard cannot
be done for a data quality reports
that has to be manually built and it
has to be built outside of the MDG.
By introducing the data spare
into the system where cementing
models cross integrate system
integration can be easily achieved.
As we all know, things are moving towards
the cloud of majority of the cases
as services and security can be very
helpful, this ecosystem, and it brings
the ecosystem with the SAP Hana, MDG data
sphere and then cloud enables the A driven
cognitive enables the A driven cognitive
towards scale to scale enterprise value.
Speaking of the functionality and
benefits of a and ML thus far right
now, how a business or a customer
can benefits out of this, right?
Can or measure the success of
this one By bringing such tools.
It's not just you implement the
tool the business or the customer
has to benefit out of this, right?
How do we measure the success based
on the implementation experience.
In several industries such as the
metrics I have captured on the below,
traditional data quality team, data
quality improvements, and the unique value
proposition on the cogniti capabilities.
Here are some of the KPIs
from the implementation, the.
75 percentage of 75 percentage of
the cleansing effort can be achieved
or reduced over the period by
increasing 95 percentage of clean data.
Okay?
When the data model matures, 90%
of the classification 90% of the
classification of accuracy can be
achieved through the ML algorithms, right?
Achieving with the high accuracy data,
as you all know, which is a very high for
any data product, any data applications.
60% of the time can be reduced by
implementing a cognitive MDM solutions.
How this will be reduced when the user
ask them if there is any user they
have to do a manual approach, finding
an anomaly or finding and predictive
analysis on all those things where system
can do that with the 60% less of time,
80% of the incident can be prevented by
well in advanced predictive analysis.
These are very key.
These are some of the key
things which I have learned from
implementing such solutions.
Again, AM is not a is not an A
MDM is not just a static, right?
It has to be evolving.
When the industry grows or the
compliance landscape grows,
it has to grow appropriately.
How do we implement the
future implications, right?
How do we address the future implications?
Looking ahead the future areas where
future implications can be considered
implementing such things, right?
There are some areas
which we need to focus on.
Where autonomous governance
solution have has to be implemented.
This can be a autonomous governance
solution can be a self-correcting data.
With the quantum of quantum computing
integration where the data automatically
corrects it, or create an incident
as in when needed, wherein there
without a manual intervention.
Industry specific implementation
can be a greater help, as we all
know, such as healthcare, finance,
retail, oil and gas, or can be built.
This can have, this can help
preventive or a reactive process.
Implementing and implementing can
be a heavy, as we all know, right?
It's not something small.
And by supported regularities, these are
needed through a transparency ethics.
And global Standard will be
adapted needed to be adapted.
It can't be just lying by its own
or a or a, or individually managed.
It has to be a global status,
standard, data standard to be
established before you propose.
I would suggest before you propose to
the change before you propose for any
of this change, make sure that you bring
the organizational alignment in this.
As these are the key when you
implement any MDM solutions, right?
'cause you need to be defining
a new rules, new structure.
And culturally they have to adapt.
With this.
With this, we can take a look
into the real time world.
Examples where, how this
results can transpire or how
this results can be achieved,
approved for the patients, right?
You had to wait for that.
How this can be evolved, how this
has been evolved from one to another.
With the oil and gas, a global
retailer where I have implemented
a and ML solutions, now 60% less
manual efforts are getting in ed.
This has been implemented in very recent
past where right now data steward not
spending much time on data collection.
This not only just reduce the data
correction, it also improve the supply
chain efficiency by 15% and in turn,
that does mean what improve the.
Dollar value for you, saving
the dollar value for you, right?
Some of the examples on a healthcare
industries, which is a very
critical, the accuracy of the data
correction need to be very stringent.
It cannot be just a point,
0.1 or two, cannot be done.
Achieving this through a manual or
traditional MDM cannot be easy, right?
Because it's a manual intense process.
It has to be a reactive process, all those
things by implementing an a ML solution.
95% or more passion
records has been improved.
And then compliance has been very happy
addressing these solutions as well in the
form, in the financial firm of financial
sectors, like a banking sector, right?
70% of the onboarding a
customer can be has been.
Okay, earlier, they have to start from
the Salesforce all the way to the lead, to
the pursuit, to the creating a customer.
Now with the vetting process and all
those process, it takes a longer duration.
With implementing A-A-M-L-M-D-M
solutions, what it happens is it
reduces this time and the fast,
but can happen within few minutes.
So this revenue, this ha, helps a
revenue gain of about $5 million,
which I have seen very recently.
These cases can be
demonstrated in A and MDM.
It's not just a theory, right?
As I was explaining, it delivers a
tangible outcomes, as you all know
right now since we talked about a
and ml advancements on in an SAP
platform for a conversional for a
conversational governance, right?
Subduction and a quantum inspired
optimization can be a pro, can be a
helpful way in future organization
that can seamlessly integrate
artificial intelligence into their
fundamental business process.
Creates an adaptive and intelligent
business process and operations and
respond to that incident immediately.
And these challenges can be addressed
continuously, improving the performance.
Creating a data incident today world,
creating a data incident, just not
just it's not just stop by taking time,
it impacts through the cast and it is
disrupting the other process as well.
And traditional governance
can keep up with this one.
The solution forward for this one is A
one MDM solution, then makes a governance,
predictive, proactive, and adaptive.
Real world results shows that implementing
a driven MDM shows a cost savings,
compliance improvement, and agility gains.
With this integration of a in, in an MDM
brings a transformation opportunity for
organizations those seek to enhance their
incident management capabilities so that
the incident management can be a very
immediate and very quick, they don't need
to wait for a reactive process to happen.
This will happen as based
on the preventative analysis
or a time series entries.
These can happen.
The incidents can be
created very immediately.
Whenever there is a, the system
understands that there is a
process issue or the data issue.
This clearly shows a paradigm.
S shift evolves from the liability
of a strategic advantage.
With that, I would like to thank you
spending your time with me for about
on this journey of a MDM journey.
Thank you everyone.