Hi folks.
I'm NHI re an experienced
software professional with
over two decades experience in
building large scale distributed
systems and low latency system.
In today's talk I'll talk about managing
regulatory incidents in hipaa, GDPR, and.
DMA environments.
Today's agenda will be split
into five different sections.
The first section about it will
be about the regulatory incident
paradox, which will talk about the
competing needs for quickly mitigating
issue while balancing the need to.
Meet the compliance requirements and
then we'll move on to look at the
regulatory landscape and the shortcomings
of the various key regulations in
place like hipaa, GDPR, and DMA.
Once we understand the lay of the
land, we will move to the compliance
aware framework where I will
introduce your robust framework to
integrate regulatory obligations
while meeting the most important
need to meet the technical recovery.
After introducing the competency
wire framework, I'll move
to balancing priorities and
communications during an incident.
The last part of the talk will be about
building your own incident playbook,
where I'll provide practical tapes for
developing a comprehensive compliance
ready incident response playbook.
Alright let's get started with
the regulatory incident paradox.
When systems fail the responders or
operators face a dual mandate, right?
The first priority is about the
technical recovery, which is mainly
about restoring the system functionality
and mitigating the data laws, and
prevent any cascading failures.
And stabilize the environment
to get back to the steady state.
The competing side of an incident is like
the regulatory obligations where things
like the mandatory reporting timelines and
the documentation requirements come into
play, along with evidence preservation
and the legal and forensic mandates.
So the first part so basically the
technical recovery is more about speed.
We need to recover the system
as quickly as possible, which
competes with the accuracy needs
for the regulatory obligations.
Another aspect is the
resourcing conflict, right?
Most of the times the responder team will
be small and the teams are pulled between
immediate remediation and while, the while
they have the conflicting need to meet
the administrative burden of compliance.
This also brings up the comp
communication challenges.
Balancing transparent, timely
communication with the legal and
the regulatory constraints on
the shared information comes into
picture while mitigating incidents.
Before we understand the,
the.
Framework, it's important to
understand the regulatory landscape.
So the current regulatory landscape can
be split into three broad categories.
The first one is hipaa, which mainly
deals with the healthcare regulations.
The HIPAA mandates that any reporting
of the personal health information
incidents should happen within 60 days.
It mandates, the required notification
is sent to the affected individuals
along with the regulatory bodies like
HHS and potentially media outlets
depending on the scale of the incident.
And thorough risk as assessments
are mandated for accurate
incident classification.
The second important regulation is GDPR,
which is EU mandated data protection.
It enforces a 72 hour breach
notification to supervising authorities.
For any high risk breaches, it requests
the data subject notification without any
UE delay and detailed documentation and
impact essence assessments are essential.
The the last or the
latest regulation is d.
Short form for the digital markets side,
which demands transparent communication
regarding any algorithmic failures.
Imposes continuous service obligation
even during incident responses.
DMA put constraints during
mitigations by establishing strict
rules on sensitive data access.
And usage during recovery efforts.
Now let's dive a little more deeper
into each of these regulations.
Let's start with hipaa.
HIPAA comes into picture when
the healthcare systems fails.
It brings unique challenges like balancing
emergency service availability with
the breach containment and determining
if any personal health information
was compromised during system outages.
Also mandating the forensic
evidence are collected while
restoring critical services.
It also mandate conducting risk
assessments during active incidents.
The breach notification rule from
HIPAA mandates that any breaches
with the PHI incidents are reported
to HHS and potentially media.
Typically within 60 days.
A direct notification to affected
individuals should be sent
without any undue or delay.
Detailing incident information
involved and mitigation steps.
He also involves risk
assessment and documentation.
The risk assessment ensures that
we can classify the breach severity
correctly along with the detailed
documentation of the incident.
Response.
And decision is crucial
for compliance and audits.
Let's move to GDPR.
The key thing to about GDPR is about
racing against the 72 hour clock.
It starts from R zero when the incident is
first reported through an alerting or any
other auto detection mechanisms and asked.
Zero to 24 is where the
preliminary assessment is done.
Determine the most important thing
is to determine if any personal data
was affected and then start, begin
evidence collection for later reporting.
And R 24 to 28 is about
further risk assessment.
Evaluate the risk to impacted subjects
and draft the notification documents.
During hours 48 to 72 can be
classified as the notification period.
During this period, submit the
notification to the supervisory
authority and prepare communication
to the impacted individuals.
Let's quickly take a look
at the DMA mandate as well.
The digital markets Act.
Places a specific stringent
obligations on tech platforms
called gatekeepers, introducing
unique incident response challenges.
It should ensure that it should
ensure that maintaining inter
interoperability during incidents and
transparent reporting of any algorithmic
issues and demonstrating fairness
in service restoration priorities.
Let's look at like where traditional
incident response management
systems fail fall short, right?
Traditional incident and management
system often prioritizes system
recovery as quickly as possible.
And it fails to account for the intricate
regulatory requirement that fundamentally
alter incident response times.
So if you look at this picture, there
are like, areas like timeline conflicts
where regulatory deadlines rarely
align with the technical recovery
timelines and competing priorities.
Balancing immediate business
continuity with str strict regulatory
requirements bring conflicts.
And regulatory requirements bring
in a lot of documentation burdens,
which slows down the recovery time.
Along with the managing the stakeholder
complexity, the responders or
operators will have to navigate the
coordination between the legal and
the complaints and the PR teams.
The regulatory requirements
also put data access limitations
which can hamper the recovery.
A lot of times the responders
need at least some.
Level of access to sensitive
production data before taking an
action which conflicts with the
regulatory requirement to not expose
sensitive data to the responders.
Yeah, and just a quick recap.
So far we looked at the different
regulations and the challenges
during system recovery.
Now we look at how to build a compliance
aware incident response framework.
So we can divide this compliance
aware response framework
into three different phase.
The first phase is the preparation
phase, followed by the recovery
response phase and the recovery phase.
So during the preparation phase we,
the framework should ensure that there
are the pre pre-approved notification
templates and the complaints protocols
in place, and ensure that the team
builds privacy, preserving investigation
and analysis tools and identify
the regulatory requirement mapping.
During the response phase there
should be like parallel tracks
for compliance and mitigation.
And then there should be tools in
place for regulatory triage assessment.
And along with the continuous
documentation protocols as well as
evidence preservation procedures
during the recovery phase ensure
that there are compliance recovery
compliance verification checkpoints.
The checkpoints should ensure
that all the data required for
complaints are collected in place.
Ensure that the progressive
service restoration is in place.
Now let's look about look at balancing
technical and regulatory priorities.
The first part is called
documentation by design.
Ensure that automated in evidence
collection is part of the
technical response workflows.
By ensuring that logs are collected
and auditing is in place, and ensure
there's a single source reporting
for multiple regulatory requirements.
The second aspect is called decision
frameworks utilize predefined criteria
for accurate regulatory classification
and implement automated notification
triggers based on impact thresholds.
The third category is privacy preserving
analysis where we deploy different
initial privacy techniques for incident
investigations and implement data
minimization during law collection.
The next group is called Parallel Work
Streams, where there's like a dedicated
technical and compliance teams working
in tandem and establish synchronization
checkpoints at critical junctures.
The synchronization points shows
that the data is free flowing
between the two parallel tracks.
Now let's look at the communication
protocols for regulated incidents.
The communication protocols can
be put into two broad categories.
Internal communication and external
communications for internal communication
ensure that their dedicated communication
POC is there on all technical calls.
And there is a regular status
updates for the compliance offices.
And ensure that there's illegal
checkpoints for external communication
followed by protected communication
channels for sensitive discussions.
External communication is slightly
different from the internal communication.
Where there needs to be a
tiered communication framework
by the regulatory framework.
And there should be a
regulatory authority.
Liaison procedures external
communication also mandates a data
subject notification, coordination.
Now let's look at implementing
a compliance aware monitoring.
The first aspect is proactive
regulatory alerting.
Ensure that the monitoring systems,
which is used to identify incidents
are specifically designed to detect
compliance related incidents before
they escalate into major breaches.
The second aspect is personal data flow
tracking map and continuously monitor
all systems, which is track which is
processing or tracking sensitive data.
Ensuring heightened visibility into
data moments and access patterns.
The last aspect is automated regulatory
timeline triggers establish automated
notification for critical complex
deadlines triggered by the classification
and progression of incident.
Now let's look at the privacy
preserving incident analysis.
The challenge is incident investigation
often require access to production
data containing regulated information,
creating a compliance conflict.
Investigators need data access to
assess the impact regulation risk.
The flip side or the, from the regulation
aspect is that regulator regulators
restrict access to sensitive informations.
And they which in another word
is like evidence collection
may violate data minimization.
To meet these challenges, modern systems
have different technical solutions in
place to give a specific example, AWS has
something called SSM system Manager, which
is an automated tool to, for operators
to mitigate incidents while preserving
logs and auditing without direct access
to production systems by eliminating
the direct access to production systems.
Directly meets the regulatory mandate
by masking the production data from
operators and oncology engineers.
Now let's look at building a complex
rare ready incident playbook, right?
This can be split into multiple group.
The first one is map peer regulatory
landscape, right document, which
all regulations apply to your
domain and the systems in place.
And create their reference metrics for
notification requirements and deadlines.
And the second aspect is to integrate
with the compliance personnel and
designate a compliance lesson person
for incident teams and train technical
responders on regulatory implications
and develop documentation templates.
Create pre-approved notification
templates for each regulation.
And implement standardized
evidence collection procedures.
The next one is about establishing
a decision frameworks defend clear
criteria for regulatory incident
classification and create decision tree
for compliance related response actions.
The last aspect is
practice combine scenarios.
This is about creating a game day or a
mock testing for incidents involving.
Regulatory data the game day or mock
testing should ensure that the technical
recovery is as quick as possible along
with preserving all the data auditing
and logs needed for regulatory reporting.
The game day should also test the
notification procedures and timelines
to meet the regulatory needs.
The let's to wrap up, let's look at the
key takeaways from this presentation.
The first important takeaway
is integration is essential.
Seamlessly integrate technical and
compliance workflows from the tum,
from the outset rather than attempting
to retrofit from during a crisis.
This can be ensure by using
automated tools which can create
audit logs and eliminating
direct production system access.
The second important key
takeaway is the preparation.
Preparation is key to enable
compliance thorough preparational
laws organization to meet to
regulatory requirements effectively
without compromising the agility of
their technical incident response.
The last aspect is balance,
competing priorities.
Achieving efficient incident
management and regulated environment
relies on skillfully balancing
rapid technical recovery.
With ongoing business continuity
and strict compliance obligations.
I hope everyone found this talk useful.
Thank you for listening to this talk.