Welcome to this conference.
So my name is Rindi Ada, so I
work for Blue Cross Blue Shield,
love Michigan as a technical lead
and then a solutions architect.
So today's session is to cover about
the wise parametrics in the healthcare
right and how secure the vice parametric
is and how can we streamline the
workflows with the new vice paramedics
technology to the healthcare, right?
The healthcare organizations enter in, in
the world, like facing a crisis, right?
So it's, they have a lot of data breaches,
everything that's getting breach as we all
know what is happening in the market and
more of what the data breaches compromised
in millions of patients records, right?
So if you are you'll be surprised
one to see like how much.
The data breaches.
Why healthcare and when
compared with the banks, right?
So if you look at the black market, right?
Whereas for the general card information,
the credit card information, if
it's like $5 but whereas the black
market, so the healthcare record, each
record is around like two $50, right?
So it'll be very surprised to, or
shocking to to know that information.
But it's accurate, right?
So that's why most of the cyber
criminals target the healthcare industry.
So that's where we need to ensure we
have right security, and also we are
maintaining all the security models in
the healthcare to, to ensure the data
related to the to the related to the
U user is accurately available, right?
So we don't want to, we don't want any
breaches into the healthcare environment.
So with that said, so let's
go into more details, right?
So the next one is, what is the need?
Why, what is the critical
need and why do we need that?
In, in, in the enhanced, like with
the, in the healthcare security, right?
So there's, as I mentioned earlier, right?
So cyber criminals are targeting
the healthcare industry.
So because some of the.
Some of the open challenges is like users
having the weak authentication processes
and the practices and password base, which
is very inadequate to protect, right?
It's a older way of authenticating, right?
And when it comes to
unique challenges, right?
So healthcare operation, very
high pressure environment, right?
So where it, it has access to the critical
information, so live death and everything.
All of this information, so the
clinicians required, and whenever,
like it needs to be secured, right?
So these emergency situations like
where traditional authentication
creates dangerous delays, right?
And some of the senior consequences,
like medical identity theft, can
lead to incorrect treatments and
also some of insurance frauds.
Author access can result in the
altering the stolen record, right?
And also prescriptions or
disrupt critical care operations.
So with that, say, let's go to
the next slide, which is the
evaluation of biometrics totally
in the healthcare industry,
specifically to the authentication.
So the biometric authentication
represent a fundamental shift from
the knowledge based security, right?
So if you look at the current market
or a current environment where majority
of the people are, wanted to have the
knowledge base authentication, right?
So we're having the contract numbers,
date of birth, zip codes, all of
that data as a security, right?
But if you all look at it, like
some of the data is already
available in the internet, right?
So anyone would be able to pull the
data and should be, and we'll be able
to authenticate or as you, right?
So that's where we need to.
We need to ensure, like we have
some new methods of authenticating
in the healthcare, right?
So there's are different
types of biometrics, right?
Like the finger fingerprints,
which is leveraged in the,
some of the pharmacy accesses.
And at the same time you have the
facial recognitions and also area
spanning, and the same way, like
a palm in authentication, right?
But out of all of these, so
the interesting one would
be like wise biometrics.
So it has significantly be,
this are significant changes in
the wise biometrics technology.
Which is currently leveraged in
majority of the organizations.
Which can be leveraged for authenticating
the members or authenticating the
employees within the healthcare
and streaming the workflows using
the standard wise of the customers.
So the advantage of this is the
customer doesn't need to carry the.
The traditional contract
number, data, birth, the
employee card everywhere, right?
So it doesn't need to be carried, right?
So some of the key applications,
which can be leveraged which of the
which of these can be leveraged is
like the access control staff, right?
And the same way the fraud
prevention insurance claims.
And at the same time, why metrics
in the contract center, right?
Some of the benefits of this is like the.
Build security, right?
Reduced errors and also the same line.
It does streamline the workflows
and enhance the patient's
trust at the same time.
This is gonna have a lot of
cost savings in the environment.
And I we understand, like when we
look at the broader picture, right?
So there are some challenges, right?
Everything is not like a
smooth in in, in the new.
Technology, right?
We need to look at from different
perspectives and we also need to
understand what are the challenges, right?
So some of them will be like,
there, some of the privacy concerns
and some of them will be bias and
accuracy of the authentication in
the healthcare with these adoptions.
And there'll be some
adoption barriers as well.
And also at the same time,
the regulations and standards.
So the biometric revolution in healthcare
is not, about the security, right?
It's about creating safer and
more personalized and efficient
healthcare so that, that's where
the wise biometrics is getting
adopted in the healthcare industry.
So we need to understand, so there
is a perception how, regarding
the adoption wise biometrics is.
Might have some other
challenges like fraud.
But whereas if you understand
this technology more, right?
So it's not like a wise print, right?
So there's a lot of factors that
are taken into consideration when
this technology create a wise print.
So some of them are like the
physiological foundation, so where
every individual person have a
unique vocal signature, right?
So it's vocal card, like article
gon, there's a lot of variations
in every unique voice, right?
There's a pattern.
So that, that, that's unique
to every person and there is a.
Behavioral pattern, right?
So the habits of pronouncing the pattern
like a speech and innovation that
develops over years of language, right?
So all of these, including some of the
advanced processing behind the scenes,
like the modern security systems will be
leveraged like the fundamental frequency,
like the spectral distribution, all of
these, including the machine learning
in order to create a wide sprint.
So this is going, this is.
With all of these patterns, right?
Or the signs of the technology.
It always the unique voiceprint will
be created for every user, right?
So it's not like someone can
impersonate my voice so that the
false accept would be very less if
you use the wise biometric solution.
So now we also need to look at
it from the enterprise scale
implementation, the healthcare.
So there's a lot of deployments,
processes available, right.
But as we always mentioned,
or we always plan to, right?
We need to secure the wise to make
sure we are going with the right
technology in the environment.
So some of them, like we have to do
some pilot before we move, before
we migrate to the wise biometrics.
Identify all the challenges
because challenges, some of them
are unique to the platform, right?
And our techno and our application or our
environment or our organization, right?
So we need to ensure we learn
ahead of time what are those
challenges are going to be.
So that would be smoother
transition of the implementation.
And we also need to understand what are
the infrastructure preparations, right?
What is the network or the bandwidth
or the, what is the redundancy we
are going to have and at the same
time, continuing the performance
monitoring and the improvements.
And change management, right?
We, it's very crucial, right?
So we need in the environment to make
sure we have the right operational
efficiency and the patient safety.
So the same, if you look at the,
some of the measurable impacts
on the clinical operations.
So the, what are the, so the,
based on a recent survey, right?
So with the wise P implementation
in the clinical operation, there
is a, there is authentication
time reduction of 83%, right?
So generally the knowledge based
authentication as we previously discussed.
So it's more like a traditionally
asking, Hey, what is your unique id?
What is your date of birth?
What is your social security?
All of that.
But with this new.
Wise biometric technology.
So why something can like
manual credential entry.
We don't need to enter the
manual manually, all the
credentials entries, right?
So the, with the wise biometrics,
it's going to leverage your wise to
authenticate and then just keep moving.
It And at the same time, there's
also 67% support request.
Reduce reduction, right?
Some of them, majority of them
are related to the authentication.
So where the member, where the
clinic clinician or the customer
try to authenticate if their
wise is not matching right?
Sorry.
If the member if the clinician
tried to authenticate and some of
these clinician doesn't work right.
So the, basically the knowledge
base, so majority of them will
be calling the customer care.
So for the support to look into the issue.
But with this biometric you'll not be
running into those challenges, right?
So when you have a higher user
satisfaction rate because clinic
clinical operations, right?
So it's very critical for
the, in the healthcare, right?
So it's more like how much
satisfied your healthcare staff is.
And at the same time, this will
increase the overall efficiency
gain in the workflow process.
So there, these are some
of the measurable impacts.
We have noticed in the clinical operations
and at the same time, so we have a
lot of platforms, our customers or the
providers available in the market, right?
So we all need to make sure we
are going with the right product.
So there are multiple products in
the market, so we all need to, so
whenever there, there's a consideration
to make it to the wise biometrics.
We as organization, we need to take
a look at it or assess what are the
products that are available in the market.
And at the same time we need
to see what is what product can
work with our applications or the
integrations within the IVR, right?
Or the self-service.
And at the same time, at the CRMs, which
is like the main critical one for the csr.
So we need to see which product is more
reliable and which can provide more
accuracy with less false positives, right?
So that's the assessment
that needs to be done.
And we also need to look at which
of these providers support some of
the historical enrollments, right?
Some of the previously recordings
available in the previous platform
can be leveraged to enroll the.
Customers or clinicians so that when
they call next time, instead of enrolling
them again, we can be authenticated,
which is trying to gain an efficiency.
So at the same time, we need
to ensure we are following all
the HIPAA compliance, right?
So all that is main critical
for any of the healthcare.
So we need to make sure we are
following all the HIPAA complaints
when we try to integrate the
wise biometric solution, right?
So the next one is the challenges.
So there'll be a lot of technical
challenges, as we all know, right?
None of the product is a
hundred percent perfect, right?
But we need to see which, which
works for our organization.
Some of the technical challenges
is the nice environment, right?
So when you try to authenticate,
if there is background noise, so
then system, sometimes you may
not be I of getting a voice match.
You may get a voice mismatch, right?
At the same time, as we all know, right?
Doing when we are ill or very
great, so Wise will be different.
Little bit at the same system.
We might have some challenges
in authenticating you.
And some of the organization
challenges are, we need to take a
look at it software, like how much
the licensing cost is and how much
is the training and the expenses
and what is that professionals like.
Workflows, disruptions, the
migrations and some of the regular
regulatory challenges is like privacy
concerns wise, web metrics, right?
We need to be very careful and
in attention to the compliance.
Some of the regulatories
are HIPAA and bpa and GDPR.
Some of these there are specific
requirements, so we need to ensure the
organization, we involve the primacy
and security team when we are coming up
with a lot of this strategy discussion.
We all need to make sure there's some
adv, some other mitigations is right?
So we need to balance it out whether we
wanted do threshold with a high match or
whether we wanted to authenticate even if
the response came back as medium or a low.
Which all depends on how
you do the configurations.
And we also need to have
need to see what the.
Business requirement is and
need to look at it like a
multimodal authentication, right?
Providing some of the
backups with the KPAs.
And we need to ensure we are following
all the right privacy policies and the
data requirements and where the data
is getting stored and at the same time.
So we also need to look at deploying
in a phased approach rather than
going in a single deployment.
So some of the best practices
is pre rollout assessment.
So we need to do a, we need to be very.
Planning.
So some of these planning needs
to happen ahead of time, right?
So we need to understand what is the
kind of comprehensive site surveys, so
the infrastructure audits and the user
interviews and technical testing to
identify potential challenges before
implementation and multimodal integration.
So we need to ensure some of the
backup options are available, so when
authentication fails, so in case of
wise authentication fails, we need to
switch back a failover to knowledge
based authentication without impacting.
Clinical staff or the
members of the customers.
And then from the deployment perspective,
we had to go in a phased approach.
So with a very department
selected department for
testing, like a performance.
So there'll be opportunity for
tuning the application, right?
So based on our environment.
At the same time, comprehensive training
needs to be performed to all the
users so that everyone understand the
criticality so that we can have, so the
right ROA is returned with the wise, with
these solutions and some of the, as I
mentioning earlier the security and the
benefits of the compliance advantages.
So it really, it does eliminate
the password vulnerable days.
Wise cannot be easily stolen.
So someone cannot take your voice
and try to authenticate you as you.
So the system has is system would
automatically understand whether it's a
human talking or it's automated mission.
So the same time some of the prevention
of the credential sharing, right?
So whereas some of the credentials
are stolen, are shared.
So that's where now using the
Y makes this a common practice.
So now it is like non
address capabilities.
So it does create an indisputable
records of system access, user
actions, and the transaction
approvals that cannot be disputed.
So some of the complaints advantages
is, so it does provide a detailed
logging for user authentication, like
a granular access capabilities, which
are required for HIPA regulation, right?
So the technology strong authentication
s another unauthorized access.
So to in order to meet the compliance
reporting, so some of the principles of
least privileges system support, fine
grain access controls based on user
identity roles and the time of access in
order to meet the regulatory requirements.
So there are some privacy things
we need to take into control when
we are designing, like making
sure the customers are aware, like
we are gonna leverage their wise
for authentication or enrollment.
So there are some of the templates
which are available, right?
So that can be leveraged for as a
sample and global compliance, right?
So flexible architecture needs to be
planned to require while maintaining
consistent security capabilities
across the global organization.
So some of the future trends and
technology advance advances we are
seeing is like AI advancements,
where that's the buzz word.
We are hitting everywhere, right?
So there would be an, a quick learning on
the algorithm that is getting obtained,
which does improve the wise patterns
in order to reduce the false mismatches
during the when the user is having an
illness or emotional stage, at the same
time, like natural language processing,
it is like more sophisticated, like
reducing the training requirements.
As edge computing, right?
So which does relate to the privacy
concerns by managing any of the
data transmission and IO ot, right?
Like the integrations which does
monitoring the equipment and ensuring
the right controls are available in
order to meet the security requirement.
And the continuous authentication right
system continuously verifies whether the
users are getting authenticated rightly,
or if there is any imposters who are read.
Trying multiple times to authenticate
or impersonate, at the same time,
enhancing the technology, right?
And the next one is the path forward.
So the watch P metrics is a very
transformative opportunity, right?
In the healthcare industry.
The technology is unique combination
of strong authentications, but we
need to ensure we are implementing
the right workflows are getting
integrated, and there is evidence of
from enterprise scale deployments that.
Efficiency, the security and the
user satisfaction justify the
implementation of the investment.
However, successful implementation
requests, careful planning adequate
resources, sustained commitment to address
technical challenges, user adoption
issues, and declaratory requirements.
So why of them is deployment is a very
comprehensive change shift from the
historical knowledge base authentication
and leveraging technology to lever to,
to leverage wise for the authentication.
So this is a very huge shift from
the traditional KB authentication.
So some of the recommendations
is the comprehensive assessments.
So as we need to ensure, we do
evaluate security requirements, right?
We need to ensure the privacy and security
teams are involved and identify all the
use cases and what are the challenges.
We are going to run into
the same time pilot program.
So we need to go in a phased approach
of deploying the capabilities.
That does minimize the risk and
resource commitments and making sure
the regulatory planning engage all
the legal and compliance experts
to ensure the implementation
meets the regulatory requirements.
And some of the strategic planning
is the first rollout with appropriate
resource and executive support.
So that's where we need to be very
good planning so that you don't,
so that implementation will be
smoother if the planning is not good.
We run into a lot of challenges
during the implementation.
So that's all related to
this particular session.
I hope this will be helpful for
you and if you have any questions,
please feel to feel free to
reach out to me on the LinkedIn.
And thanks everyone.
Thanks for giving me this opportunity.