Hello, everyone.
I am Gurgula, and I specialize
in aligning technology solutions
with business objectives.
I will be speaking on digitalizing SAP
HR, migrating legacy systems to a secure,
theory based, user centric experience.
If you are looking to modernize
your legacy HR services, this
talk would be really helpful.
Digitalizing SAP HR services,
migrating legacy systems to a secure
theory based user centric experience.
Before we proceed with the migration
talk, I have a disclaimer to share.
The views and opinions expressed
in this presentation are my own.
and do not represent the views
or official position of my
current and previous employers.
The content is based on general
industrial knowledge and
publicly available information.
No confidential information
will be shared during the talk.
A little bit about my background.
I tailor technology to fit business
needs perfectly with a robust skill set
in SAP advanced capability in SAP ABAP,
WebDN for ABAP, Gateway OData services,
SAP UFI, Fiori, SAP BTP development,
as well as comprehensive workflows.
I have transformed challenging
IT issues to streamline user
friendly automated solutions.
This topic is divided into introduction,
objective, modernizing legacy SAP HR
systems, transitioning to Fiori, advanced
security integrations, optimizing SAP HR
process for efficiency, enhancing data
integrations, ensuring compatibility
with modern web browsers, innovations,
And conclusion introduction, the rapid
evolution of technology demands that HR
systems undergo significant transformation
to meet the needs of modern organization.
Legacy SAP HR systems often struggle
with outdated interfaces, slow processing
times, and a lack of mobile access.
which hinder productivity
and user satisfaction.
These systems are also prone to security
vulnerabilities, making it difficult to
comply with current security standards.
The project is focused on resolving issues
by migrating SAP HR process to a Fiori.
based user interface, which will
provide a secure, responsive,
and intuitive user experience.
The digital transformation will modernize
the system, streamline workflows,
and enhance overall efficiency.
Let's break down what we mean by Some
of the specific issues faced by users
outdated user interfaces.
The interfaces were often
designed decades ago with a little
consideration for user experience.
Navigating these systems can be
confusing, leading to mistakes.
Slow system performance.
Critical processes like recruitment,
onboarding, and performance
evolutions are slowed down.
This not only impacts HR teams,
but also has a knock on effect on
employees who rely on the same systems.
Security vulnerabilities.
Older systems lack the built in security
measures, That we expect from modern
software as data breaches become
more common and more costly lack of
mobile access in an increasingly.
The remote and mobile workforce, HR
systems that can be accessed only from an
office desktop are no longer sufficient.
Employees and HR teams need to access
these systems from anywhere, whether they
are in office, at home, or traveling.
Business impact.
All of these technical
problems have real old history.
Implications for the business.
For one, employee engagement can
suffer when people have to deal
with the slow, inefficient systems.
They lose confidence in the company's
operations and it affects morale.
Delay processing like recruitment,
talent acquisition, and performance
reviews leads to dissatisfaction
and even push the top talent away.
Then there is an issue of security.
Finally, inefficient systems results
in higher operational cost when
HR professionals spend more time
managing the system inefficiencies.
It increases the manual effort and
resources required to maintain operations.
This isn't scalable as business grows
transitioning from legacy systems
modernizing These systems is critical
digital transformation is no longer
optional It's about staying competitive
improving Efficiencies and positioning
hr function to meet future challenges
sap theory That presents a cutting
edge solution to these problems.
We are designed to be intuitive, mobile
friendly, and secure, solving many
of the issues we have highlighted.
Objectives.
objective is to migrate SAP HR
services from legacy system to
a Fiori based user interface.
The key goals of this migration
includes security, and ensuring
compliance with industry standards,
improving user experience through a
modern UI, responsive UI, creating self
explanatory forms that can streamline
process and reduce training time,
enhancements.
One of the most pressing
objectives is security.
In today's digital transformation or
digital landscape, where data breaches are
on the rise, companies are under immense
pressure to safeguard employees data.
Legacy systems built in an era when
data security was far less of a
concern do not meet the stringent
security protocols needed today.
This makes them vulnerable to breaches,
which can result in significant
damage to a company's reputation.
SAP Fiori, on the other hand,
incorporates advanced security protocols.
Let's look at a few.
Data Encryption Fiori ensures
the sensitive data is encrypted
both in transit and at rest.
This means that even if the data were
intercepted, it would be unreadable
without the encryption keys.
Multi factor authentication.
This adds an extra layer of security
by requiring users to verify their
identity using more than just a password.
It drastically reduces the risk of
unauthorized access to sensitive
role based access controls.
Not everyone needs to do the, needs
to do the same level of information.
Not everyone needs to access
the same level of information.
Theory ensures that only
authorized personnel can access
or modify certain types of data.
This is critical for ensuring compliance
with data protection laws like GDPR.
Compliance with regulations like
GDPR is no longer optional for
companies handling personal data.
GDPR enforces strict rules
about how personal data is
collected, stored, and used.
Non compliance can result
in significant penalties.
Fiori architecture is designed
with compliance in mind, ensuring
that HR processes automatically
adhere to these regulations,
avoiding the risk of penalties.
User Interface Improved User Interface
Another primary objective is
improving the user experience.
Fiori offers a responsive and
user friendly interface that
works seamlessly across the
desktop, tablets, mobile devices.
This modernization significantly
enhances the user experience
for both HR staff and employees.
For an example, HR staff can
onboard new employees quickly
without needing extensive training.
Employees can easily access their
personal HR information, apply for leave,
or update their details without having
to navigate through confusing menus.
Self explanatory forms theory also
introduces self explanatory forms,
which guide users through complex,
Process ensuring that they enter the
right information in the correct format.
This reduces the need of for
constant HR support cuts down on
errors, minimizing the amount of
time users spend on each task.
Think about how a form designed to
process a benefit application might
prompt user only the relevant information
based on their previous selections.
This kind of smart interactions
reduce the complexity of data
entry, leading to fewer mistakes.
And quicker task completion.
User centered design.
Another key aspect of Fiori in
its, is its user centered design.
In past, many HR systems were designed
with the assumption that users would be
willing to deal with complex workforce.
Fiori flipped this.
Making the interface simple,
intuitive, and focused on the
tasks that users actually perform.
For instance, processes like
employee onboarding are now
streamlined and HR manager can
initiate the onboarding process.
And the new employee can complete
the forms, upload the documents,
and even start training directly
from their mobile devices.
Use case.
Employee onboarding.
Let's consider a real world example.
Imagine a new hire joining in
your organization using Fiori.
The HR teams can initiate onboarding
process with just a few clicks.
The new employee, on the other
hand, can receive the welcome
email that directs them to a
mobile friendly platform, Portal.
There they can submit the required
documentation, signed forms, complete
training modules, all without ever
needing to step into the office.
This approach not only saves time,
but also ensures a smooth, stress free
onboarding experience for new employees.
transitioning to SAP Theory.
SAP Theory
often offers a modern, intuitive
experience, a consistent user
experience across all the devices.
desktops, tablets, smartphones, Fiori
responsive design ensures that user
can access process from any device,
increasing flexibility and engagement.
Self explanatory forms created with
Fiori reduce the complexity of data
entry, improves user satisfaction,
and ensures higher productivity.
Fiori
Responsive Design One of the standout
features of Fiori is mobile first design.
Today, we are moving away from
traditional office based work environment.
More employees are working
remotely or in a hybrid model.
And they need to be able to access
HR systems no matter where they are.
This is where Fiori shines.
Its responsive design ensures
that same user experience is
available across all the devices.
Whether you are in a desktop computer,
a tablet, or a smartphone, the
flexibility is very crucial for HR
professionals who are on the go.
For instance, a HR manager who is
attending an out of office meeting can
still log in to approve a leave request
or review a performance report directly
from their smartphones or tablet.
This real time access to data improves
overall Cross device compatibility.
This cross device compatibility also
needs to more engaged employees.
Think of an employee trying to apply
for a leave while traveling or HR
professional who needs to conduct
a performance review from a tablet.
Fiori ensures that the experience is
seamless across all the platforms.
Employees don't need to wait until
they're back in office to complete tasks.
This not only increases productivity, but
also boosts employee satisfaction because
they can complete HR tasks wherever,
whenever it's convenient for them.
Advanced Security Integrations
As we're transitioning from legacy SAP
HR system to a Fiori based environment,
security becomes a central focus.
Legacy systems often have
outdated security mechanisms,
leaving sensitive HR data.
Vulnerable to breaches
and compliance risk.
By migrating to Figure U, we are
integrating advanced security
measures, such as SAP's role based
access control, or BAC, which ensures
that employees have access only to.
The information they need.
Additionally, encryption is implemented
across the system to protect
the data at rest and in transit.
FIORI framework also adheres to
industry leading security standards,
ensuring we met compliance
Requirements such as GDPR, ISO.
These enhanced security features
not only mitigate potential threats,
but also provides peace of mind
for both users and administrators.
Optimizing
HR process for efficiency.
Leveraging object oriented, Adaptive
Programming Model, Dialog Programming
Model, and Remote Function Calls.
We have optimized key HR
process for faster execution and
reduced resource consumption.
These technical improvements translate
into quicker processing times,
better system performance, and more
efficient data handling within HR
systems by streamlining operations,
we can ensure that HR systems can
scale further, future business growth,
enhancing data integrations
with SOA and web services
to future optimize the SAP, to
further Optimize the SAP HR system.
We are incorporated.
We are incorporating service oriented
architecture and web services.
These technologies enable seamless
integration between SAP HR and other
key systems within the organization,
such as time, Benefits external vendors
with SOA data can be exchanged in
real time, eliminating the need for
manual data entry and reducing errors.
The services are also enable automation
of routine tasks, such as form submission,
data validation, which enhances process
accuracy and speed of the HR workflows.
The combination of SOA
and web services creates.
a more integrated, automated,
and efficient HR environment,
allowing for real time updates
and quicker decision making,
ensuring compatibility
with modern web browsers.
With discontinuation of Internet
Explorer, it is essential to
migrate SAP HR process to a platform
that supports modern processes.
Theory web based interface is fully
compatible with current browsers,
including Chrome, Firefox, and
Microsoft Edge, providing users with
a seamless experience regardless
of their preferred browser.
Transition, transition not only
address, this transition not only
address current compatibility
issues, but also future proof the
system for upcoming web technology.
As modern browsers continue to evolve
with better security and faster
performance, the Fiori based HR systems
will remain adaptable and up to date,
ensuring a smooth user experience
across the devices and browsers.
This shift also mitigates risk associated
with unsupported browsers and allows
for continuous improvements in user
experience and user interface design.
Innovations, Dynamic Forms,
and Automated Workflows.
Using SAP Floorplan Manager and
Adobe Forms, We have developed
dynamic interactive forms that adapt
based on user input, making them
more responsive and easier to use.
Additionally, we create a custom
utility that automates workflow
delegation, ensuring continuous
process of tasks, even when the primary
department admin is unavailable.
This innovation not only enhances
user experience, but also ensures
process continuity, and reducing
risk and improving reliability.
So finally, the conclusion.
In conclusion, migration, migrating SAP
HR process to a theory based platform
offers a range of benefits from improved
security to a modern User experience.
The enhanced security measures ensure
compliance with industry standards
and safeguard sensitive HR data.
The user centric design of CRE
with its responsive and intuitive
interface increase engagement
and reduce training time.
Additionally, the optimized
system performance can streamline
workflow, contribute to greater
efficiency and scalability.
Preparing the HR systems for further
growth by ensuring compatibility with
modern web browsers and technologies.
This migration feature proves the system
positioning the organization to manage
HR process effectively years to come.
Thank you.