Hello everyone and welcome to Conf42
Incident Management 2024 conference.
Imagine your organization
facing a major security issue.
Time is running out, things are
chaotic, and everyone is scrambling
to fix the problem to fix the problem.
And to make the situation more
interesting, communications
are falling apart.
Does it sound familiar?
As a cybersecurity analyst, we
spend a whole lot of our time
building security controls that
we hope will prevent an incident
from happening in the first place.
But the reality is that the
incident happens or will happen.
What if you have had a clear
step by step guide to tackle any
incident quickly and efficiently?
Which is why a cyber security team or an
organization is expected to have a strong
understanding of what to do or how to
do or what to do when things go wrong.
In today's talk, I'll be exploring
what an incident response playbook
is and how we can implement one.
for listening.
My name is Chinye Chinekizi.
I'm an SUL security analyst
with Saifal Technologies.
And on today's talk, I'll be
looking at master incident response,
elevate efficiency with playbook.
Let's dive into it.
So in order to, drive this talk,
I'll be looking at some outline.
One of them is understanding
what incident response is.
We also be considering the challenges
that in incident management.
What is incident response playbook is,
we also be considering the benefits
of using incident response playbook.
Then the guide to creating one.
We also consider looking at the elements
of an effective incident playbook.
And then we look at an example, the tools
and technology, and then we conclude.
Understanding incident response.
According to NIST, NIST actually defined
incident response as a systematic process
for handling cyber security incidents.
Incidents like data breaches or
malware infection or any form
of cyber security incidents.
Why do we actually need incident response?
One of the reasons why we need it.
It's because it actually helps
to reduce damage and downtime.
It also ensures business continuity
and protects sensitive data from
being exploited by the tracked
actors when there is an incident.
And in order to do this, or to be
able to effectively protect our data
from being exploited, NIST actually
provided us with four guides.
These four guides are preparations.
We have the detection and analysis.
We have the curtailment and
eradication and recovery.
We also have the post incident activities.
We also have the sound incident response,
which actually also states or outline
the steps that could be taken in order
to detect and prepare for an incident.
Now we're looking at the
challenges in incident management.
One of the challenges in incident
management is lack of clear procedures.
Without a clear process, there is a
risk of confusion and delay in response,
especially when something goes wrong.
And also, there is bound to be an error
in the incident management process,
because at that point, The team
might end up working on an assumption
without a clear path to follow.
We also have inadequate incident
categorization and prioritization.
This is a major issue.
Where incidents are not properly
categorized, it can lead to
the team giving top priority to
the least expected, incidents.
Thanks.
Lack of tools and resources, where there
is no tools and resources, it becomes
a challenge to effectively manage
or, quickly respond to the incident.
We have the inadequate training, where
there is no training, it makes it
difficult for the team to effectively,
jump at the incident when it happens.
We have lack of communication
and collaborations.
And now we're looking at what
incident response playbook is.
An incident response playbook
is a detailed, structured set of
procedures that actually outlines
what an organization should do
in an event an incident happens.
It tells them how to detect it, how
to respond to it, and how to recover
from the cybersecurity incident.
One primary goal of incident response
is to help organization minimize
the impact of breaches and to
ensure they restore back to normal.
Or they return back to business
as quickly as possible.
So there are different types of
playbooks that an organization
can actually decide to develop.
And this is based on the potential
threat identified in the environment.
As well as the kind of
operation they are into.
And as well as their sizes.
So there are different playbooks
that they could choose from.
This is a list of some playbooks.
There are more playbooks that
could be exploited, but this
one listed here are just few.
One is the Ransom playbook.
We also have the DataBridge.
We have the Marwell playbook.
We have up to the Zero
Day Variability playbook.
This list are just few.
There are many other playbooks
that could be developed by an
organization based on their identified
traits within their business
operations as well as their sizes.
Then we look at the benefits
of incident response playbook.
One of the benefits of incident
playbook is improved efficiencies.
Because there's already streamlined
process, it helps the team to
quickly respond to the incident
and then reduce the downtime or
the impact of those incidents.
You have the enhanced effectiveness.
Because of the clear procedures that
are already outlined what they to do
and how they are to go about it, it
helps the decision making very fast.
And then they end up making an impactful
action or taking a more impactful action.
It also increase collaboration
where there is a well defined role.
It helps them to be able to know who
to escalate to because they already
have The role metrics that spells
out what school they are to escalate
to in an event something goes wrong.
So it shows the chain of
escalation, making the coordination
of the incident very smooth.
And then we have guides to
creating incidents playbook.
One important thing to note is that
before an organization can go ahead
in, Developing an instant playbook,
there's need for them to actually
understand their security posture.
And this is actually done by, identifying
the potential variability and threats
that are specific to the operations.
And by so doing, they are able
to come up with the strategy to
curtail those identified weaknesses.
And this is done by performing
penetration testing.
Or, We're really assessment.
These two testing actually gives them
an overview of how that environment is
as well as the witnesses and possible
remediation of what they can do to
ensuring a stronger security posture
and you have creates reporting.
Checklist.
would like to also mention before I go
to create a reporting checklist that This
test actually helps them to determine the
severity as well as also be able to define
the priorities because identifying those
vulnerabilities within the environment
will help them to be able to have a proper
categorization as well as prioritizing
those incidents based on their severity
and impact on their businesses.
I move on to the CREATE
REPORTING CHECKLIST.
So this checklist is like a template
that helps the team to be able to
document their findings during the
investigation and be able to enter
the activities that are executed in
order to, curtail those incidents.
They will have defined a clear procedures.
Like we rightly mentioned, there
are different types of playbooks.
And these playbooks should have a clear
process for detecting, investigating
and also identifying the potential
security and then prioritizing them
based on their severity and impact.
This can only be achieved where
the organization already have a
clear understanding of what poses
a threat in their environment.
They have established
roles and responsibilities.
This is very key because it
helps in the escalation point.
Also have developed communication plans.
Then you have tests.
After developing those processes,
there is a need to actually test
to know the effectiveness of those
processes, of those tools that have
been implemented, to detect and actually
help this, the organization's security.
This can be done by performing
a tabletop exercise.
This tabletop exercise helps to
determine the readiness of the
team in fighting against incidents.
And then we have the reform, the refined.
The refined actually helps in
identifying the gaps and possible
improvements of the processes.
When an exercise is done, the tabletop
exercise is done, then you're able to
identify what is not properly taken
care of and you're able to improve on it
by refining those processes as needed.
And taking into account the new
identifying gaps is and how they could
build a stronger security posture.
And then we have the next
four phase explained.
These four steps actually gives
a better understanding to the
organization or the security team on
how they could know be incident ready.
Firstly, I would like to highlight that
for any organization to be able to have
And if effective playbook there is need
for them to have a better understanding
of what needs guideline incident guideline
is, which has a clear understanding
of what needs guideline is, it's very
difficult for them to be able to, take
into account these four phases and be able
to get ready for any form of incident.
So in order to have this incident
properly outlined, and, in
line with the best practices.
It is important the organization
understand this framework and
by so doing, they are able to
build it into this process and
then have an effective playbook.
Now we'll be looking at the key elements
of an effective incident playbook.
So the key elements are four.
One is the initiating condition.
This particular one defines
What the trigger is,
then you have the process steps.
This actually spelled out the
step by step instruction on
how to execute the playbook.
Like I said, there are different
types of playbook and each
playbooks has its unique processes.
The way phishing playbook is actually
different from how the malware
playbook is, because the flow of
the two are actually different.
And so the steps to
curtailing them also differs.
So the playbook actually spelled
out how this can be executed.
Then you have the roles
and responsibilities.
This actually tells you which of the
team is responsible for what, which
must be in line with the best practices.
And then we have the communication.
Here describes the internal and
external communication procedures.
With the communication metrics,
you are able to identify the
escalation points for the escalation.
Line or chain, which helps to the team
to be able to coordinate properly.
Now we're looking at a typical example
of efficient attack response playbook.
This is not the best of it, but this
is just for the purpose of learning.
So I'll be assuming it.
A large organization, a financial
organization, faced a suffocated
phishing attack targeting its employees.
The attacker aimed to steal sensitive
information and gain unauthorized
access to the complaint system.
Remember the first thing we said, trigger,
which is the initiating condition.
The employer, the employee
reports a suspicious email or the
security team detected the unusual
logging attempt and flagged them
as potential phishing attempts.
So this is a trigger.
The employee reports it
as a suspicious email.
Or, the security team are able to detect
it using any of the automated tools.
Now, we'll go to how this can be built
into the NIST Incident Response Plan.
One, we have the detection state.
Or, Remember we said
it's a phishing email.
So the first thing is to verify
that it's a phishing attempt because
the trigger said it's a phishing
attempt to steal information.
in verifying the phishing
attempt, we're going to be
considering looking at the IOCs.
We're talking about the malicious
link, the attachments, and the
impersonated domains using some
threat intelligent platforms.
let's such as Recorded Future or
SODAN or Abuse IDP, IDPX, sorry.
So in such situation, the team
goes in there to check and see
if there have been any reported
abuse on the identified hiruses.
And then we move to containment.
Containment has to do with
stopping this freight.
And stopping this thread is stated that
you block the sender's email address.
You quarantine the affected email.
You also revoke any access that is
granted by the compromise credentials.
So I'll move to the eradication.
So you have scanned the affected endpoint.
You also review the logs to ensure
that there is no other employee who
must have clicked on the, compromised
or interacted with the emails.
If there is any, you reset
their passwords just to ensure
that there is no more spread.
Then we go to the recovery.
Here you are ensuring that
all the compromised accounts
on the system are secured.
You can test by also stimulating
the potential phishing exploits to
be sure that there is no residue
remaining within the environment.
Then you post incident activity.
There you are reviewing
the attack details.
The response efforts and the results,
you're looking at what you've done and
you're trying to identify the gaps as well
as what you can do better to improve on
the pull on the security posture and here
you can determine or begin to consider
looking at strengthening the email filters
and possible also providing possible
trainings to the employee to ensure
that they are actually phishing aware,
especially when they see any of those
emails being sent by the threat actors.
So this is a sample of possible phishing
response playbook that could be developed
to, prevent a spread of phishing attack.
This is not the best of it, but
just to give us an idea of how
efficient response playbook look like.
And then we look at the tools.
These tools are actually used
to automate the playbooks.
One of them is the security information
and events management, which is the same.
And under this team, there are
different, SIM tools that could be used.
One of them is Plum, and
you have the list of orders.
You also have the endpoints
detection and response, tools.
An example, you have the Carbon Black,
you have the Microsoft Defender,
and we have the SOAR, which is
also the Security Orchestration,
Automation, and Response tools.
One of the examples is Microsoft Sentinel.
So there are different tools that
could be used in that regards.
We also have the Incident
Management tools.
So we have different tools within
that square that could be used.
We also have the Threat
Intelligence Platform.
One of them is Recorded Future,
and you have all the rest of
others that could be used.
In using this tool, we cannot rule
out the woman factor or the woman
intelligence, because the woman
intelligence helps to analyze some of
the, identified, threat indicators, and
they are able to, speak to those issues.
Actually, when In especially when
in identifying the incidents, in,
in identifying those incidents,
you either be true or false.
Sometimes you have some incidents
that are false positive.
So with the women intelligence,
you're able to identify and look
at the behavior as well as their
normalities and be able to determine
if they're true or they're false.
This is also the role of
woman intelligence in deter
in playbooks and also in.
Ensuring the security of incidents.
then we have common pitfalls to avoid.
One is outdated playbook.
Due to the evolving nature of
technology, the cyber actors or the
threat actors also keep improving
their tactics on how to get into our
system and steal valuable information.
So organizations need to ensure that
their playbooks are updated and updated.
And they are also up to the
current security, trend.
They have lack of testing where processes
or tools are not tested to validate
their effectiveness in detecting
those abnormalities, those incidents.
It can be an issue and
that should be avoided.
And then we have poor communication
where there is no proper definition
of communication metrics.
It becomes a challenge because You
wouldn't know who to escalate to.
So the chain of communication becomes a
challenge, so that need to be avoided.
And then in conclusion, I will say
that by using a well designed incident
response playbook, organizations are
able to enhance efficiency and reduce
downtime, and also improve on their role.
overall security posture.
Thank you for listening.