Hi, this is Niro.
Thanks for being here.
This talks about one practical idea,
which is to make compliance a built-in
feature of how we design and run systems.
So in financial services the scale is huge
and trillions of dollars move every day.
So when a system pauses even
for a moment real people feel
it and the cost cleanse fast.
So our aim is simple.
A system that rarely fails and when
they do, they recover quickly and leave
a clean trail of evidence as they go.
So that way teams moves faster with
confidence and customers feel safe.
The proof we need is created
as part of normal work.
So if that's the goal, let's round
it to the world we all live in.
The financial services challenge.
So here's the reality.
So millions touch real
balances and real trust.
People expect services to be
there whenever they need them.
So threats move fast and patients is shot.
And when something goes wrong the cost
shows up in both money and reputation.
That, that's why instant management
cannot sit on the sidelines.
It sits where reliability,
regulation and brand meet.
That instant is not only technical, it
can also be business and regulatory.
Our methods must respect
all three at once.
So how do we make a safe
path, also an easy path?
So that's where the the
modernization helps.
So why cloud modernization now
modernization is not only go faster.
It is set better defaults.
So when the safe path is
also the fast path teams stop
negotiating and start building.
So we use.
Repeatable patterns for networks,
identity storage and compute.
We put clear rules in the
build and release steps.
So risky changes never reach customers.
We keep unchangeable logs so the
system can tell its own story later.
The result is fewer surprises
and calm our operations.
Quick proof from the field.
Then we'll keep moving.
So we moved to a fragile service into a
landing zone with strong guard race, same
team, same code, the next instant did
not feel like a fire drill gone wrong.
It felt like a drill we
had already practiced.
We knew what changed.
When it changed and the safe path back
that's the power of good defaults.
Now let's talk about compliance
as a built in advantage.
So think of compliance like seed
belts designed into a performance car.
Now the car still moves fast, but safety
is part of the experience from the start.
For us, that means approved reference
designs reusable building blocks
and evidence that is created
automatically during day-to-day work.
So reviews get shorter and
then rework drops and releases
become more, more predictable.
Customers notice our stability
and regulators notice clarity, and
then leaders see steady delivery.
And this isn't extra paperwork.
It's the system proving
itself while we built it.
If compliance is a feature
what rules are we encoding?
Let's let's map the let landscape here.
So rules are a map of
what society cares about.
Some focus on accurate
reporting and fair markets.
Someone privacy and proper use of data.
Someone banking safety and open payments.
Newer ones focus on operational
resilience and responsible use
of learning systems like ai.
We do not need to memorize
like every chapter return.
Each team into code and steps
label and product sensitive data
from the staff plan, fail and
practice them and keep records.
Person outside the team can
understand in, in minutes.
With the clear data let's look at
how the how in our architecture.
So let's take a look at the
hybrid and multi-cloud strategies.
Architecture is where
promises become real, right?
So we manage policy and visibility
across the company while keeping
sensitive customer data in the
region where it belongs that respects
data rules without losing control.
We designed for small pla radius
clear boundaries between services and
sensible timeouts and retries and fast
ways to switch off risky features.
So we practice failovers
until they then become boring.
For the most critical systems we
run so living more than one place.
For others we keep a warm backup
that can take off quickly.
So one picture to lock it in, then
we'll deliver it to be like, gonna
dive into a, to a two examples, right?
So think of a highway.
Each service has its own lane with
dividers and and the shoulder.
If a tire blows in one lane,
the road doesn't shut down.
Those drivers and shoulders
are your boundaries.
Timeouts.
Retries and feature switches.
Now three short stories that kind
of shows this in action, right?
So regulatory reporting, reporting
move from, or batches to real time
streams instead of finding delays
tomorrow we saw them in minutes.
Each step.
Wrote an unchangeable record.
So the audit story was already there.
So reports that took like
days random minutes audit prep
that took weeks took days.
So when a delay happened, we
could point to the exact stage
that can slow down or show what
was affected and proven recovery.
As finished.
So the accuracy went up and the
cost went down and the trust.
Trust improved.
Alright, let's take a look
at the next case study.
So basically we wanted to
stop bad transactions without
bothering good customers.
The turning point was managing the
whole model lifecycle not the score.
So the data is data, it uses.
Nicholas stayed fresh, so any
change needed the right approval.
So if a new version misbehaved, we
could return to the last version.
Just one, one decision.
And we could explain what changed and why.
So file alarm dropped, losses dropped,
and investigators chased better signals.
We have another example.
So last example here.
This is like speed and
discipline and trading.
So this case study.
So surveillance moved from after
the fact to real time and limits
were enforced as orders flowed.
So unusual patterns were flat as so
the records of this checks traveled
side by side with the with the trades.
So in a market search, the
system did not ask for a meeting.
It followed a safe playbook.
So incidents were shorter and reviews
were clearer and confidence from the
business and from regulators improved.
So following these three case
studies, so what makes these wins?
Repeatable?
Foundation of all these is on the
on the next slide infrastructure as.
Write down how environments must
look and let the platform build
them from that description.
So new plat, new environments
run aligned to standards.
Identities set correctly.
Networks are segmented the right way.
Storage is locked as intended.
Changes happen through a clear
view instead of one-off tweets
if something goes wrong.
Returning to a good known state
is quick because a platform
knows what good looks like.
The rules sit next to the
configuration and the application.
What changed and why, and all question.
Move faster and auditor.
See the exact history.
Now, let's put safety rules into a daily.
Instead of quarterly checklist we place
rules directly into the build and release
steps basically, and into the platform.
If a setting would expose a data or
open a risky path it does not pass.
The system explains which rule
was violated and how, and shows
the approved pattern, right?
This turns long review meetings
with fast, clear feedback while
the work was still in progress.
Most issues are minutes.
Platform also creates detailed
timestamp record of what's fired and
who changed what and how it was fixed.
These kind of records is
like goal for audits and for
learning after the instance.
So let's tackle this in daily habits.
So bring six earlier in the
development when fixes and.
Classified data and applied
privacy controls by default.
So sensitive information is handled
correctly without traffic, keep logs in
a way that cannot be quietly rewritten.
Rehearse resilience like a fire drill
or failover and emergency moves.
Feel familiar and not scared.
Product feels solid to customers and
the platform feels same to operate.
Launches are smoother and incidents
are fewer time spent proving compliance
shifts towards improving the customers.
So even things break motion.
So the instant management and compliance.
So basically just keep it steady practice.
We practice it all.
Let's keep it steady.
Confirm the signal and decide how serious
it's start a clean log right away.
Pause.
Risky change paths.
Use free pre-approved moves,
like switching off a feature or
limiting a traffic or failing
failing out to a safe location.
Communicate in plain
language to right people.
So while you work let the system
collect facts current settings,
recent changes, who had access key
measurements on the trace of what
you know, what and who, et cetera.
And don't call it fixed until the service
holds steady for a meaningful window.
This protects customers and creates
evidence to explain what happened
and why the fixed work what does this
bias, what does this actually buy us?
So let's talk about the outcomes, the
actual outcome or the business impact.
So when safety and compliance are.
Part of the platform.
New environments come online
quickly and predictably.
Recovery is faster and less dramatic.
Conversations with regulators are
clearer because your evidence is
produced as part of normal work.
Customers notice reliability, leaders
see momentum, and every incident becomes
a chance to improve our platform itself.
After the fix works, promoted to
the shared template, so the next
team never meets the same problem.
So over time speed, reliability
and audit readiness race together
instead of, fighting with each other.
So what should you do?
Say next week, right?
Start with one visible win.
Stick a single painful control
that burns time on fiction.
Automate it from end to end.
Place it inside a golden path
that teams can use right away.
Make the path the fastest way to
production, not just the most compliant
with, give the path and owner at a
short public list of improvements.
Each month measure a few signals of
how often you make your service promise
and how long it takes to recover,
how many changes or struggle, and how
many hours you save in audit work.
Share the trend so people can
see progress and repeat it.
The next high value control.
It's really that simple.
Okay, that brings us to
the end of a presentation.
Remember, reliability and
compliance are not enemies.
When we build safety into the path of
production and practice, our response
incidents become rarer, shorter and safer.
Story you tell regulators become the
same story you tell engineers because
both comes straight from the system.
Every time you improve the shared
template, you give a gift to the
next team and to the next customer.
Let's make trust or advantage and.