Good morning.
I'm Kendra Prakash Rojo Senior
software engineer at C and
Property Insurance Corporation.
Today I'll walk you through how AI edge
computing and serverless architectures
are reshaping insurance incident response.
The world is changing rapidly.
Customers expect faster service.
Regulators demand more compliance
and risks like cyber attacks and
climate change events are rising.
This presentation is about how
modern cloud native technologies
can help insurers respond faster,
scale better, and serve customers
with more trust and transparency,
traditional challenges.
Let's begin with the pain
points most insurers face today.
Slow incident detection.
For example, many incidents remain
unnoticed for hours or even days.
Delaying recovery and adding costs.
Manual claim processes like adjusters
are overloaded, creating frustrating
backlogs for policy holders.
Lack of realtime insights, so
without Im Lee, data insurers still
reactive instead of preventing
losses, scalability, bottlenecks.
During disasters, like hurricanes,
systems often collapse,
which are under heavy demand.
They're not small issues.
They directly affect customer
trust, operational cost, and
long-term competitiveness.
AI powered performance.
AI has already started
transforming insurance operations.
In underwriting AI models.
Analyze IO OT sensors, driving
behavior property data to provide
more accurate risk assessments.
This reduces errors and improves pricing.
Claims AI automation speeds up
resolution like chat bots, gather
information, algorithms try out severity.
Thereby human justice can only
handle exceptions in fraud.
Detections AI identifies patterns that
humans might miss catching fraudulent
claims before payouts are made.
These results are very clear that it
provides better accuracy, faster service.
Reduced fraud and improved profitability.
Edge computing.
Edge computing means processing data
where it's created rather than sending
everything back to central service.
For insurers, this is crucial.
Take a flood sensor in a home With
edge computing, this sensor can
trigger an alert immediately, even if
connectivity to the cloud is delayed.
Or think about telematics in cars.
Like accident data can be
analyzed locally, so insurers
can take actions immediately.
This reduces latency, saves bandwidth,
and ensures faster responses that directly
protects customers and minimize claims.
Serverless benefits.
Serverless architecture
is like electricity.
You don't worry about the power plant.
You just use what you need.
For insurers, this means always on
scalability, like claim portals won't
crash during the search In disasters,
faster deployments, new tools like
claim apps can be launched in days.
Customer first service.
Serverless systems handle traffic
smoothly, providing instant responses.
Serverless architecture combines
flexibility and reliability, ensuring
insurers can innovate you quickly while
staying prepared for high pressure events,
intelligent incident detection.
Here is where AI shines
in incident response.
Like real-time monitoring.
AI continuously scans underwriting
and claims data for unusual patterns.
Pattern recognitions like
machine learning detects fraud or
risks early automated alerting.
Once something is identified, the
system notifies the right team with
CVR levels and recommended actions.
This approach shifts ensures
from slow manual reactions to
fast data-driven decision making,
edge driven real-time intelligence.
This slide shows how edge
and cloud work together.
Like connected sensors
capture, react data, raw data.
Each processing provides
instant and local insights.
Cloud intelligence analyzes large
patterns across multiple sources.
Informed actions allows insurers
to optimize decisions from claim
approvals to fraud preventions.
This layered model delivers both speed
at the source and deep insights at scale.
Automated root cause analysis when
incidents happen, understanding
the root cause quickly is critical.
AI gathers data from multiple
systems, analyze patterns, and
identifies the true root cause,
whether it's weather related or damage
equipment failure or human error.
It then generates
recommendations for remediations.
This means insurers not only fix
today's problems faster, but also
learn how to prevent them tomorrow.
Large scale disruptions, major disasters,
put systems under extreme pressure.
Here is how modern systems handle
them, like auto-scaling, which
expands resources instantly.
Dynamic allocations, which shifts
workloads from across regions,
failover and backups that keep critical
operations running load balancer, load
balancing, which smooths traffic spikes.
For insurers, this means
uninterrupted service, even during
catastrophic events, protecting
both operations and customer trust.
Blockchain for reinsurance.
Blockchain has strong use cases in
reinsurance, like smart contracts,
which automate settlements transparency,
which provides immutable audit trials
efficiency that reduces manual steps
and speeds up payouts trust, which
grows between insurers and reinsurers.
By combining automation and
transparency, blockchain simplifies
that, which has traditionally
been a slow, complex process.
Hybrid cloud.
Hybrid Cloud provides a balance.
Insurers need sensitivity.
Regulated data can stay in private or
on-prem systems while scalable workloads
like analytics run in the public cloud.
This ensures.
Compliance with regulations like GDPR
and H-I-P-A-A while still unlocking
the benefits of cloud scale and speed.
It's a practical way forward
for insurers modernizing without
risks, risking compliance.
Compliance and elig agility Compliance
is a cornerstone of insurance.
Modern platforms embed compliance with
frameworks like G-D-P-R-H-I-P-A-A.
Logging and monitoring.
Simplify audits while automated
governance ensure sensitivity data is
protected across multiple environments.
This lets insurers maintain
both agility and compliance.
A combination that used
to be seen as impossible
implementation roadmap.
How do insurers get started?
Access the current state, understand
where systems stand today.
Design a strategy.
Decide how AI edge and
serverless fit into operations.
Pilot programs test in small
controlled environments.
Scale and optimize.
Expand what works continuously improve.
This phased approach ensures
transformation without overwhelming teams.
Key takeaways.
Three things to remember.
Measurable impact AI and cloud
improve accuracy, speed, and
cost integrated approach.
Combining AI and EDGE and serverless
architecture drives transformation.
Strategic rollout hybrid cloud ensures
compliance while enabling innovation.
This is not about adopting one tool.
It's about building an
ecosystem that's future ready,
ready to transform.
The question is, are
we ready to transform?
Insurers who act now will set
the standard in customer service,
compliance, and resilience.
Those who wait will struggle to catch up
with AI edge and serverless architecture.
The tools exist today to
revolutionize insurance response.
The opportunity is to
lead, not just adapt.
Thanking you for joining today.
I hope you this gave you a clear
picture of how ai, h computing, and
serverless architecture can transform
incident response to insurance.
I would love to hear your thoughts,
questions, and challenges you face
in implementing these technologies.