Welcome to this presentation on Identity
Federation, a groundbreaking approach to
industry wide digital identity management.
We will explore how this innovative
concept can streamline user
experiences, enhance security,
and improve productivity.
and drive significant cost savings
across various sectors, including IOT.
So first of all, what is the, why there
is a need for identity federation?
First one is a password fatigue.
Users manage an average of hundred
passwords leading to an unsafe
practices, including reusing the
same password, less secure passwords.
And the next one is
security vulnerability.
61 percent of data breaches
involve credentials, which 85
percent involving human elements.
Next is a poor user experience.
55 percent of consumers
abandon their devices.
Online purchases due to password issues
and last there is an inefficient in
Onboarding repeated identity verification
leads to increased costs for service
providers So this is where I am proposing
the identity federation model where
you will utilize a single sign on
with a seamless access across multiple
providers So this includes four steps.
The first one is establishing the
single sign on and then standardizing
the identity attributes, for example,
industry specific verified information.
and then consent management where
user gives control over data sharing
and consent to usage of that.
Next will be industry specific trust
framework, where we define rules
and standards for participation.
So looking at the technical
implementation, we need
to first extend OAuth 2.
0 scopes and define industry specific
scopes for fine grained access control.
Then we need to federate the
identity providers, institutions.
Act as both idp and sp for cross
provider authentication Next is
an attribute exchange protocol.
So In this we will have a way to
securely share user attributes between
federated members And last but not
least we need to have a federation
registry A centralized place where
the registration for participating
institutions And metadata are maintained.
So where can we see these applications?
First one is banking sector
applications So implementing this
concept of identity federation, it
simplifies the account opening process.
It reduced onboarding time by 80
percent, saving up to 1 billion
annually for large banks, and then
a seamless service integration.
increase of cross selling opportunities
by 30 percent and improve the
customer retention by 25 percent.
This also enhances the fraud detection.
This reduces the identity fraud by
up to 90 percent saving the industry
an estimated 7 billion annually.
And then we can also look into the
same thing where we can apply this
for a healthcare sector applications.
So we can For example, streamlining
patient access records, interoperable
health IT systems could save the U.
S.
healthcare system by 30 billion a year.
And then we can also look into,
in the healthcare sector, we can
improve the care coordination.
so especially when, a patient visits
multiple different facilities or
healthcare providers, They can
basically, coordinate better through
the shared health information that
can reduce the hospital readmissions
by 20 percent by reusing existing
intakes and verified user information.
This also reduces the
administrative overhead.
Which can save up to 30 minutes per
patient encounter by eliminating redundant
data entry identity verification process
Because a user is already presented and
they have their own identify identity
federated Where data gets shared?
across all the healthcare sector And then
we can also do the same thing in education
sector, where portable of academic
credentials, especially, transcript
verification time can go by 90 percent
saving institutions, an average of 150%.
Dollars per student application Which
they actually have to pay to get the
transcripts verified and then there is a
simplified enrollment process basically
because we are federating the user it
increases the adult learner enrollment
by 25 percent by removing barriers to
entry And simplifying credit transfer
process And then come the secure
credential sharing, this reduce hiring
times by 40 percent and improve job
matching accuracy by 30 percent through
a secure sharing of transcripts and
certifications with potential employers.
So looking at the economic impact
of Identity Federation, this could
increase the GDP growth, by 2013
countries that implement this digital
ID systems by around three to 13%.
As I was mentioning earlier,
healthcare savings with an annual
savings for interoperable health IT
systems can save up to 30 billion.
So it reduces the onboarding, potential
risk reduction in onboarding costs for
financial institutions by approximately
90 percent of their costs that were
involved in onboarding a new customer.
Then come the financial inclusion,
because number of unbanked
financial services can use up to 1.
7 billion dollars.
So what are the challenges
and considerations?
So the regulatory compliance
is one of the biggest thing.
So implementations must comply
with industry specific regulations
and data protection laws.
the GDPR finds total 1.
3 billion euros in 2021, a sevenfold
increase from the previous year.
And then the security itself, 45 percent
of the organizations reported an increase
in cyber attacks in the past 12 months.
Robot security measures, including
multi factor authentication and advanced
threat detections are very essential.
Then comes privacy.
43 percent of the respondents were
very or extremely concerned about
the security and privacy issues.
So user centric privacy controls
are crucial for building trust
and encouraging the adoption.
So this is where a standardized,
industry specific IOT standards
needs to be introduced.
and these challenges can slowly
be addressed with working
with respective agencies.
And so what is the, so if you look
at the addressing, the primary
implementation challenge, The first one
is a regulatory Alignment, so we have
to develop frameworks that inherently
align with the key regulations that
This could be a country specific
or a global regulation That various
countries can come because IOTs Get
access across the internet so this would
be very advantage if the regulatory
alignment happens at a global level.
then we have to look into
enhanced security measures.
We have to implement advanced protocol
like biometric authentication or various
other type of secure, authentication
measures like two factor authentications.
Then we have to think in the
terms of privacy by design.
So incorporating privacy enhancing
technologies and granular consent
mechanisms should be allowed.
For example, if you want to allow
permissions only at very certain
specific conditions, so that is where
the granularity comes into picture.
And then the industry collaborations is
very important because we are looking
at an industry specific alignment.
So fostering past partnerships to
develop these interoperable standards
involving various parties in the
same industry in defining those
interoperable standards is very crucial.
Then education and awareness.
is also equally important because,
we need to launch new initiatives
to educate organizations and users,
to, try and adapt these industry
specific standards so that they become
interoperable and they get access to the
larger, Market across various systems.
So in conclusion, the future of digital
identity is definitely very good.
Identity Federation represents a
transformative approach to digital
identity management, poised to
revolutionize how organizations and
consumers interact across various sectors
by addressing issues such as Critical
challenges in identity management
and leveraging existing standards.
It has the potential to create
more efficient, secure, and user
friendly digital ecosystems.
As industries continue to digitalize
and integrate, Identity Federation
standards ready to unlock substantial
economic value, improve user
experience, and pave the way for more
integrated and user centric digital
services across entire sectors.
Thank you.