Hello, everyone.
Thanks for having me here today.
My name is Sudeep Meduri, and
I'm delighted to present on this
exciting topic, transforming fintech
using AI, revolutionizing security,
personalization, and compliance.
Artificial intelligence is reshaping
how financial services operate today.
Making them smarter,
safer, and more inclusive.
So in this talk, we'll explore
how AI drives innovation in key
areas such as fraud detection,
personalized banking, trading
strategies, and regulatory compliance.
We'll also dive into its potential
to redefine operational efficiencies.
and customer experiences while addressing
ethical and regulatory challenges.
So let's get started.
Fraud detection is one of the
most impactful areas where AI
has made significant inroads.
Traditional fraud detection methods
used to rely on rules based systems.
that were rigid and slow to adapt.
AI, however, can identify anomalies
within vast amounts of financial
data with unparalleled accuracy.
let me point an example here.
the JP Morgan's coin system analyzes
over 12, 000 commercial loan
agreements in seconds, saving almost
360, 000 hours of manual effort.
AI also uses Pattern recognition to adopt
new tactics by fraudsters, continually
learning and improving its responses.
These advancements have reduced
false positives by over 60 percent
and also helped increase the true
positive detections by almost 50%.
It provides enhanced security by
reducing fraudulent activities.
And ultimately, it helps with
customer confidence, increasing
trust, and encouraging wider adoption
of digital financial services.
Another area where AI has played a
significant role, is in personalization.
So personalization is at the heart of
modern customer experiences, and AI
is making it possible to personalize
individual user experience at scale.
this is done by analyzing spending
habits, income patterns, and financial
goals, and AI is able to deliver tailored
banking advice to each individual user.
We also now have AI powered robot
advisors, Like wealth front and betterment
who offer customized financial planning
and portfolio management at reduced costs.
these platforms offer customized,
investment strategies, which are
previously accessible only to
high net worth individuals at a
very significantly reduced cost.
Further, ML algorithms create
customized investment portfolios
aligned with individual risk
appetites and ESG preferences.
So this not only improves
customer satisfaction.
but also deepens loyalty and long term
engagement with financial institutions.
Personalization also ensures every
customer feels understood and valued,
which is a very key differentiator
in today's competitive landscape.
let's now look at algorithmic trading.
So this is another area where
AI has shown its transformative
power, in financial trading markets
where even milliseconds matter.
AI provides an edge by analyzing
vast amounts of data, including
historical trends, price movements,
trading volumes, and news feeds.
deep learning models enhance trend
forecasting accuracy, helping
traders make informed decisions.
Additionally, AI also optimizes trade
execution by analyzing market liquidity
to minimize costs and, market impact.
firms leveraging AI have,
reported increased profitability
and improved market efficiency.
Making it indispensable in fast
paced trading environments.
For example, firms like Citadel
have heavily invested in AI,
which provided them a competitive
edge over their competitors.
Let's now look at the role AI plays in
regulatory compliance, which is an area
which is very ripe for description, given
the complexity and volume of financial
regulations coming up day by day.
AI powered compliance tech solutions can
automate a lot of the data collection,
processing, and analysis tasks,
reducing manual effort and also errors.
ML models are able to track
regulatory changes across multiple
jurisdictions, interpreting new rules
and assessing their implications.
Predictive analytics adds another layer
by identifying potential compliance
risks before they even materialize.
And by streamlining compliance, AI
not only helps reduce costs, but
also mitigates reputational risks
associated with non compliance
for these financial institutions.
Operational efficiency is another
critical priority for a lot of
financial institutions and AI has
been delivering on this front as well.
it helps automate routine, financial
tasks, which helps reduce errors
and also reduce processing times.
AI chatbots handle customer queries 24
7, significantly reducing response times.
Similarly, NLP technologies streamline
back office operations by extracting
key information from unstructured
data in financial documents.
And by automating a lot of these
repetitive tasks, institutions can
now redirect human resources to roles
that truly require creativity and
expertise, ultimately reducing costs
while also improving service quality.
AI is also redefining what
customers expect from their
financial service providers.
we now have services such as
voice activated banking, real
time financial insights, and
personalized recommendations,
which are no longer optional.
they are expected now, for
each and every individual user.
For instance, digital assistants like
Bank of America's Erika provide seamless
and intuitive interactions guiding
users through complex financial tasks.
AI powered chatbots are also able
to offer round the clock support
and financial guidance for users.
Innovation is central to the
evolution of financial services,
and AI is at the forefront.
AI powered credit scoring models provide a
more accurate and inclusive assessment of
borrowers, which expands financial access.
AI also supports risk assessment and
market analysis by processing and
synthesizing vast amounts of data sets.
RoboAdvisors and AI powered insurance
products some of the other examples of
how AI is creating new categories of
financial services, making sophisticated
tools accessible, to a broader audience.
So, while, the benefits of AI in FinTech
are immense, many challenges, still
remain, data privacy and security are,
one of the major concerns, especially
with, regulations like, GDPR, et cetera.
Institutions must also implement
robust cybersecurity measures
and transparent data practices
to safeguard customer trust.
Another challenge we see is algorithmic
bias, which can lead to unfair outcomes
in credit approvals or loan disbursements.
It's very important to ensure fairness and
that requires diverse training data sets
and regular audits of these AI systems.
Transparency and explainability
of AI models are also equally
critical to maintain user trust
and regulatory compliance.
So let's now look at what the
regulatory landscape looks like and
the challenges that it can bring.
As AI is more adopted in FinTech,
regulators face the daunting task of
keeping pace with AI advancements.
Adaptive regulatory frameworks
that encourage innovation while
mitigating risks are very essential.
for listening.
Algorithmic accountability will also
likely become a regulatory mandate,
requiring institutions to explain
AI decision making process, and data
privacy regulations are also expected
to become stricter than what they
are now, focusing on how AI systems
manage personal financial data.
There are already data localization
laws in various countries which mandate
that the data that is used doesn't
leave the boundaries of the country.
And these are only going to
become more strict going forward.
And finally, ethical guidelines will
also play a key role in ensuring AI is
used responsibly, balancing technological
progress with societal well being.
So I hope this presentation has shed
light on how AI is transforming fintech,
addressing some of the challenges, and
paving the way for a more innovative
and inclusive financial ecosystem.
Thanks for having me.
Thanks everyone for your time.