Hello, I'm Parth and I lead Mobile Storage
Infra on Android for Meta's products.
Today, I'm here to share the journey
I went through while working in the
R& D department at SAP Labs India.
The topic is regarding the solution
we built for crisis management during
COVID using contact tracing to identify,
notify, and support SAP employees.
Who might be at risk of infection.
So what is contact tracing?
Contact tracing is the method of
identifying and managing people who may
have been exposed to a contagious disease.
During 2020 and 2021, this was
a big problem for businesses.
If even a single employee was exposed
to COVID, it could infect everyone and
anyone else who might be in the vicinity.
Contact tracing involves identifying
people who might be infectious, Notifying
them to quarantine themselves, notifying
others who may have come into contact
with this person, and then monitoring
and providing support and treatment.
During 2020 and early 2021, as businesses
were slowly opening up, keeping
a track of employees who might be
exposed to COVID became a major issue.
A single person could end up infecting
everyone else on campus and cause
a complete shutdown of operations.
SAP had a manual signup sheet for tracking
employees who are visiting office.
If someone called in sick, staff
would go through the sheet, figure
out everyone else who has come
into contact and call them to get
tested or quarantine themselves.
It was a lot of manual effort and
notifying employees took a couple of days.
during which the infection
could spread even more and
this process was not scalable.
This also introduced a lot of false
positives as employees who might be
on opposite sides of the campus would
also be part of the same signup sheet.
From a business perspective, SAP
wanted automation to reduce manual
effort and delay and they wanted to
minimize cost, especially of hardware,
as they believe COVID to be temporary.
We realized the best way forward would be
to use smartphones already on employees.
Everyone had a phone that they
carry with them everywhere, and no
one would share their phones with
each other, especially at office.
We looked into possible solutions,
and the tech we came to use was to
use Bluetooth low energy or BLE.
BLE as its name suggests, consumes
low energy from the device.
It provides a lightweight signal that
does not have extremely high range,
which is perfect for contact tracing.
And it can be used to send small
amounts of data between devices.
BLE technology exists on both
Android and iOS, and it provides a
framework called Generic Attribute
Profile, or GATT for short.
GATT can be used to send and
receive short pieces of data known
as attributes over a BLE link.
Device A can act as a server, also
called an advertiser, and that broadcasts
a unique ID called a scan record.
This ID Is of the service itself,
the contact tracing service device B
will scan for all nearby advertisers.
It will collect all the devices
which have this unique ID, connect to
them, and then read a scan response.
And the scan response can have an
another ID that can be used to uniquely
identify the device or the user.
So every device will act as.
An advertiser and a scanner and basically
will be responsible of sending data of all
other nearby devices that we discovered.
Now let's get to the
limitations of this technology.
On Android, multiple clients
can connect to a single server,
but as soon as a client tries to
connect to a second server, the
first connection is terminated.
This, since connections are
asynchronous, we will have to
queue them, and this can result to
potential loss of nearby devices.
But, Android can broadcast two
IDs as part of the scan record.
Even when the app is backgrounded or
screen is locked and the scan response
will also work properly when the app
is backgrounded or screen is locked.
On iOS, it's a little different.
The scanner API can queue
connections, so we don't need to
queue them ourselves, but it can only
broadcast a single ID for a service.
Also, when the app is backgrounded,
the scan response will return a
null value, making it impossible
to identify the device.
The basis of our contact tracing
solution is that each device tells
our internal servers what other
device it came into contact with.
This helps us build basically a
graph of employees and then notify
them of potential infections.
Our architecture uses three
independent methods of tracing.
Android to Android is done using
only the advertiser and the scanner.
The advertiser will broadcast two IDs.
One for the service and the other,
which represents the device or the user,
the scanner will then scan these IDs,
recognize that it is part of the contact
tracing service, and then register
the second ID as the other device or
the other user, the Android device
will then communicate to our internal
servers in regular intervals with all
the devices it came into contact with.
An example would be if A, B, and C are
Android devices and A is the scanner.
It finds B and C and then
it'll send an edge from A to
B and A to C to our servers.
iOS tracing is done using
GAT server and client.
Every iOS device will advertise the
same ID to all other iOS devices.
And all of the iOS devices will scan
this record that contains a temporary
MAC address of the Gatsby server.
Now, it will use this temporary
MAC address, connect to these
devices, read a property called a
characteristic, which contains the
device identifier and the response.
And same as Android, iOS devices
will upload all of these edges to our
internal servers at regular intervals.
So if X, Y, and Z are three iOS
devices, There'll be an edge saying X
to Y and X to Z from X to our servers.
This means now with these two individual
architectures running, we have Android
devices, which can identify all other
Android devices and iOS devices, which
can identify all other iOS devices.
When it comes to iOS to Android
or Android to iOS detection, the
tracing is done by the iOS device.
Each Android device will also
run a GAT server, which the
iOS device will connect to.
Similar to how it does
with iOS GAT servers.
It will connect to it and it will read
the scan response from the Android device.
If for example, X is an iOS device
and A is an Android device, the iOS
device is responsible for both edges.
Only in the case of
Android to iOS detection.
This removes the limitation that
iOS devices cannot send a separate
scan response while running in the
background, as well as the limitation
that Android GATT clients can't queue.
The results spoke for themselves.
The architecture resolved
platform limitations.
We had 7, 000 plus employees
install and use the app, and
they used it to visit the office.
We also use geo fencing to ensure the
app does not run in the background
when employees are not at work.
So that we do not invade their privacy.
Other technologies that we looked into are
Wi Fi, RFID, NFC, and normal Bluetooth.
Wi Fi had a significantly higher
battery drain, and it was a little
more complicated to work with than
Bluetooth low energy, especially on iOS.
RFID would require higher
hardware investment and NFC
had the issue of low range.
Traditional Bluetooth had changed
their APIs so that the MAC address
being broadcasted by the Bluetooth
device is a temporary MAC address.
This was done so that advertising
companies and malls do not uniquely
identify devices or users based
on their Bluetooth MAC address.
But because of this change, we couldn't
use them for the same thing, identifying
users based on the MAC address.
So we had to go with Bluetooth
low energy because of these
limitations on other technologies.
We have a patent for this as part of SAP
and it's published on Google Scholar.
If anyone is interested, please reach
out to me and I can send more details.
That's all for my presentation
and thank you for your time.
Have a good rest of the conference.