Hello everyone.
I'm Abhishek Vajpayee, and I'm
thrilled to discuss how AI driven
IoT is transforming healthcare.
Together with Ratesh Mohan, we
explored how these innovations improve
accessibility, personalization, and
data integrity in the healthcare space.
Today, we'll walk you through the
evolution of chatbot architectures,
the role of scalable infrastructure,
real world use cases, and future
impacts of these technologies.
Now I will hand over to
Ratesh to get started.
Thanks, Abhishek.
Just to get started, let's first
get a general understanding
of how chatbots work.
Traditional chatbots can be built on
static architectures with predefined
responses or the more modern ones
using generative AI and other
machine learning driven methods.
The aim here is to take input
from a user and provide an output.
These inputs can be text, voice, image,
or user actions such as click of a
button sent through some kind of user
interface or any versions of those.
This input passes through a
processing module that can be as
simple as a rule based engine.
Or could be a complex module
using all sorts of machine
learning driven submodules to
produce and process those outputs.
Backend services have connected to other
peripherals such as knowledge bases,
integrations to other machine learning
services, and other such modules that can
then process these intermediate inputs and
get the final output ready to be served.
In contrast, IoT based chatbots
integrate real time data from devices.
IoT allowing adaptive and
context aware responses.
They connect directly with IoT sensors
to offer precise, actionable insight.
So just like the text or image or
other signals in the traditional
chatbots, IoT devices has an input
layer that can get signals from sensors,
smart devices, and IoT gateways.
This data then is connected to a
cloud and can be readily available
to be processed by the next stage.
This next stage could be an NLP engine, a
voice engine, or a full dialogue manager.
So this should give you an
idea about how IoT chatbots are
different but still follow a similar
architecture as traditional chatbots.
This shift has redefined patient
care, enabling 24 7 assistance
and timely intervention.
One of the biggest advantages
is in the accessibility benefits
that IoT chatbots provide.
IoT based systems are available around
the clock, breaking barriers like office
hours and geographical constraints.
For elderly or disabled patients,
voice enabled IoT devices provide
effortless access to health care.
For example, a voice assistant
can remind a patient to take their
medication or guide them through
managing a chronic condition.
This empowers patients to take charge
of their health, fostering independence
and trust in healthcare systems.
This entire process can be easily
automated to detect events and
deliver the appropriate care.
Add to this a flavor of personalization
and you get a system that is
calibrated to a patient's profile.
AI systems use recommendation
algorithms such as collaborative
filtering and content filtering
to deliver tailored suggestions.
For instance, wearable devices can
analyze your activity levels and
recommend adjustment to your exercise
routine, diet, or medication.
Let's look at some of these
personalization methods.
Recommendation algorithms often fall into
these categories as listed on the screen.
The collaborative filtering ones,
which learns from a user's behavior.
The content based filtering
ones, which tailors suggestions
based on the item attributes.
Or you can have hybrid models, which
are combining both for richer insights.
These are also called ensemble methods.
For instance, a wearable device tracking
your sleep patterns could recommend
lifestyle adjustments or signal a
physician if irregularities are detected.
This real time personalization
ensures care evolves
alongside the patient's needs.
I will now hand it over to
Abhishek to talk about how Scalable
Recommendation Systems appear.
Thank you, Ratesh.
Personalization at scale
introduces challenges.
As user bases grow, systems must
maintain low latency responses
and handle vast datasets.
This is where Scalable
Recommendation Systems shine.
For example, Netflix processes
billions of recommendations daily.
Similar frameworks can be applied in
healthcare to analyze patient data,
delivering timely interventions.
even with increasing demands.
Scalability is critical
for AI and IoT systems.
Scalable infrastructure allows system to
handle increased data and user demands
without compromising performance.
This is achieved through use of
cloud platforms like AWS and Google
Cloud for flexible resources.
Real time Apache Kafka and distributed
computing tools like Apache.
part for processing massive
data sets efficiently.
These components ensure healthcare systems
can scale seamlessly as demands grow.
Now we can talk about some best practices
for building scalable infrastructures.
To build scalable AI ML
infrastructures, organizations
must follow these best practices.
Use data lakes to store both
structured and unstructured data.
Leverage hyper parameter optimization
to fine tune models for better accuracy.
Automate deployment with CI CD pipelines
for quicker iterations and robust systems.
This ensures systems remain reliable,
efficient, and future ready.
AI ML infrastructure doesn't just improve
technology, it also empowers teams.
Pre built scalable infrastructures
accelerate time to value for clients.
Cloud native tools enable
seamless collaboration between
teams working on data analytics.
As the client needs grow,
scalable systems adapt without
requiring complete overhauls.
Now let's look at real world examples.
During the pandemic, AI driven
chatbots managed millions of
COVID 19 related queries, reducing
strain on healthcare systems.
IoT based glucose monitors now send real
time alerts to doctors and patients,
preventing diabetic emergencies.
These examples demonstrate how IoT and
AI enhance healthcare outcomes while
improving operational efficiency.
Now, I'll hand it over to Ratesh
to talk about some key takeaways.
Thank you, Abhishek.
To summarize, we can say that
scalable infrastructure is essential
for handling growing demands as
The best practices like distributed
data storage and automated training
pipelines ensure system reliability
and make your system future proof.
AI and ML infrastructure empowers
healthcare, just as it is providing
to other domains of e commerce.
And these providers help the
patients, driving them with
better engagement and outcomes.
As a conclusion, we can, we'll say
AI driven IoT is revolutionizing
healthcare by making it more
accessible, personalized, and efficient.
Voice interfaces and proactive
monitoring empowers patients while
scalable system ensures healthcare
providers can meet increasing demands.
However, challenges like greater
privacy, seamless integration, and
service reliability need attention.
By addressing these responsibilities,
we can harness the full potential
of these technologies to create a
healthier, more connected future.
Thank you for your time.