Hello, everyone.
My name is Natalia.
I'm a product owner with a
passion for using technology
to solve real world problems.
Over the years, I've led innovative
projects such as building a
serum system for FinTech company,
and creating AI driven platform
for social media monitoring.
One of the most impactful
projects I worked on was a social
media monitoring platform for
brand reputational management.
This project taught me how
AI can turn unstructured data
into actionable insights.
But today I want to explore
how we can take this further.
Imagine how using IoT devices, not just
to monitor behavior, But to actively
collect and analyze client feedback
in real time together, let's dive into
how Internet of Things and artificial
intelligence can bring the gap between
data collection and client understanding.
Here's what I'll cover in today's session.
First, I'll share lessons from the
social media monitoring and analysis
project I worked on, where AI played a
pivotal role in transforming unstructured
data into actionable insights.
Next, we'll talk about the
challenges of collecting feedback
using AI alone, what works, what
doesn't, and where the gaps are.
Then I will explain how Internet of
Things can enhance feedback systems
by combining explicit feedback,
like verbal responses, and implicit
feedback, such as behavioral data.
Finally, I will dive into practical
applications of Internet of Things
and feedback collection, explore the
challenges and opportunities that come
with it, and look ahead at future trends.
So let's take a closer look at the
key question, how can Internet of
Things redefine feedback collection?
Thank you Specifically, how can it
complement traditional methods like
surveys or interviews and address
the limitations of AI only solutions?
Let's begin with the major challenge
I faced when developing the AI powered
social media monitoring platform.
Traditional methods of gathering public
opinion like surveys or focus groups
are slow, expensive, and often lack the
scale needed to capture the full picture.
Social media offered us an alternative.
A continuous stream of opinions, but
this game with its own set of challenges.
The data was massive,
fragmented, and unstructured.
Think about millions of tweets,
posts, and comments in various
languages, tones and contexts.
How do you make sense of
all of that in real time?
We were overwhelmed by the volume of data.
Social media doesn't stop.
It's constant, 24 7.
AI struggles with nuances, especially
sarcasm or cultural differences.
For example, a sarcastic comment like,
Oh great, another amazing update.
could be misinterpreted
as positive feedback.
Another challenge is scalability.
The more channels we monitor,
the harder it became to scale the
system while maintaining accuracy.
We created an AI driven platform that
collected data from multiple sources,
including Twitter, Facebook, and forums.
We used natural language processing to
analyze sentiment and detect trends.
We developed a formula to calculate
reputational risks in monetary terms.
This way, we increased monitoring
coverage from 10 percent to
70, providing a clear and more
comprehensive view of public sentiment.
The response time to critical
incidents improved by over 60%.
We created a formula to calculate
reputational risks in monetary terms.
Stakeholders
This project showed us the potential
of artificial intelligence, but it
also highlighted its limitations.
AI alone can analyze, but can't interact.
This is where Internet of Things
steps in, offering physical and
interactive components to collect
and act on feedback in real time.
Before we explore Internet of Things
solutions, let's sum up why AI alone isn't
always enough for feedback collection.
AI can struggle with emotions and tone.
As I mentioned earlier, feedback
this is amazing, could be sarcastic,
but AI might flag it as positive.
AI system typically
analyze data passively.
They don't ask follow up questions
or clearly ambiguous feedback.
While AI process data quickly, it's
still analyzing what's already happened.
It doesn't collect data proactively,
but Which means opportunities to
address issues in real time are missed.
Why Internet of Things
for feedback collection?
Traditional feedback systems are reactive.
Internet of Things enable proactive,
continuous feedback collection.
Now let's define two key types of feedback
Internet of Things can help to collect.
Explicit and implicit.
Explicit feedback.
This is when a customer directly
tells you what they think.
For example, selecting a rating on a
feedback screen after the transaction.
Explicit feedback is clear and
direct, but it's often limited.
Not all customers take
the time to give it.
Implicit feedback comes with
observing customer behavior.
Examples include how long a customer
interacts with a product or screen,
repeatedly pressing a button on
the screen, the tone of the voice
when saying, this ATM is great,
which could indicate sarcasm.
Implicit feedback is valuable because
it captures data that customers
might not express explicitly.
Let's bring this concept to life
with the practical examples of how
Internet of Things and Artificial
Intelligence can work together to
enhance client feedback collection.
Imagine a customer using a smart ATM.
The machine fails to dispense cash
and they mutter, This ATM is useless.
With IoT enabled ATM, microphones
detect verbal frustration,
sensors monitor repeated button
presses or prolonged interactions.
Using this information, banks can
schedule maintenance or software
updates for specific ATMs.
Insights can also inform
design improvements, like
simplifying the interface.
Potential impacts include
customer frustration decreases,
improving satisfaction.
Banks can see reduced churn and
increased trust in their services.
Now let's look at another example.
In a smart bank office, IoT
enabled kiosks or screens assist
customers with transactions, account
inquiries, or loans applications.
If a customer finds a confusing
interface or feels the service is
slow, they might say, Why this takes
so long or show frustrations through
aggressive tapping on the screen?
IoT devices track voice, gestures,
and touch patterns using pressure
sensitive displays and sensors.
AI detects frustration or dissatisfaction
in tone or interaction style.
It links the feedback to
specific processes, such
as loan application delays.
Artificial intelligence and
Internet of Things together
provide instant suggestions or
fixes via the IoT enabled kiosk.
Bank managers use aggregated
insights to redesign flows or
improve customer support strategies.
The potential impact of implementing
such a system is significant.
It reduces customer churn by addressing
frustrations in real time, making
customers feel heard and valued.
It increases trust in bank
services as customers see
issues being resolved promptly.
It improves overall operational
efficiency by highlighting bottlenecks
and enabling targeted improvements.
Here's why Internet of
Things is a game changer.
It captures organic, unfiltered
feedback during the service experience
and allows for immediate responses,
improving client experience.
It goes beyond verbal feedback to
include touch patterns, interaction
times and gesture analysis, offering
deeper insights into customer behavior.
It identifies trends before they
escalate into larger problems and
helps allocate resources effectively.
This reduces churn and builds trust.
Let's take a closer look at the challenges
and opportunities that come with
implemented IoT driven feedback system.
First challenge is data integration.
Combining IoT and AI data with
existing systems, like traditional
feedback collection tools or
CRMs, can be technically complex.
Each system may use different
formats or protocols, making
Seamless integration, a challenge.
Next, there are privacy concerns.
Customers might feel uneasy about being
recorded or monitored by IoT devices.
Transparency is essential.
Businesses need to clearly
communicate what data is being
collected, how it's used, and ensure
compliance with privacy regulations.
Finally, device adoption.
Encouraging customers to interact with
IoT devices requires thoughtful design.
If the device is too complicated,
customers may avoid using it.
The key is to make the experience
intuitive, non intrusive, and
valuable for the customer.
Now let's talk about the
opportunities that IoT driven
feedback systems bring to the table.
First, IoT allows for a
continuous feedback process.
Unlike traditional methods, which often
rely on periodic surveys, IoT devices
can provide ongoing real time insights.
This makes feedback more
accurate and actionable.
Second, IoT enables
closing the feedback loop.
Systems can respond instantly to feedback,
whether it's addressing the issue on the
spot or making adjustments in real time.
This not only solves problems faster,
but also builds a trust with customers.