Hello everyone.
My name is Andrew.
Today I will tell you about artificial
intelligence and how it's changing
the fintech industry and make it even
more interesting than it was before.
Let's begin.
before we get started, please
allow me to introduce myself.
I'm a professional marketing specialist.
I studied marketing at university and have
been working in the marketing company.
For 20 years, 14 of which I have
been working in the fintech industry.
And right now I am the chief
marketing officer at well trade.
trade is a financial company.
Okay.
So today I will tell you about several
interesting cases that my colleagues in
the industry are doing, and which I have
directly encountered at work with every
day, I will tell you a little bit about.
chatbots, bot agents and how
artificial intelligence is changing the
infrastructure of the brokers themselves.
we will also talk about content
and how content creation is
currently becoming one of the main
jobs for artificial intelligence.
I will tell you about how
AI helps in advertising.
And in acquiring and retaining customers,
I will give you two good examples from my
previous companies, Libertex and Volbi.
And we will finish this presentation
with a short discussion on the topic
of the future of AI and FinTech.
Okay.
So let's start with
chatbots and bot agents.
This is the most obvious case of using
artificial intelligence, in my opinion.
And at the moment I have several
examples when AI completely changed
the entire customer support department.
Many of you already know what intercom is.
Intercom is highly convenient platform for
customer support, where you can connect
all incoming requests from online chats.
Emails, different social
media networks in one place.
they already have a built in AI feature.
And when I worked at crypto startup,
you holder, we were one of the first
company who actually tried their feature.
And we did this with two
different approaches.
The first one, we built bot
that solved the most popular
problems right in the online chat.
It didn't just answer questions,
but actually solved problems.
For example, we, with the searching
of, for a transaction in the blockchain
or with the verification status at
the KYC stage, and this bot instantly
reduced the flow of incoming requests
in the department and actually.
Decrease the workload for the whole team.
And secondly, we connected the AI agent to
all dialects with life support specialists
so that the AI agent could learn.
And then just a couple of weeks,
the bot completely learned
how and what to answer people.
Then we launched it on its own,
but only on night shifts when we
had a shortage of life agents.
And that bot did really well.
The advantages of AI in the support
department are obvious, AI reacts faster,
AI is more accurate, and it's not subject
to emotions because sometimes life agent
can be not in a good mood and person just
can reply something not that politely, or
it's not that accurate and most important
AI can work 24 seven without salary.
What did all this cases lead to?
You can ask.
And I think many have already guessed,
when we just first started this project,
we had 14 different people working
in the customer support department.
Now there are only three left
and they are doing pretty good.
And the last case.
It's about feedback.
when I worked at a Markets, we
created an amazing AI bot on Telegram
for collecting all feedbacks on the
internet about the company for the last
24 hours with automatic translation.
For example, every morning at
9:00 AM I had a notification from
that bot with all the feedback.
That we had on Trustpilot,
AppStore, Google Play yesterday.
That allowed me to constantly monitor
the situation with our customer
service and our scores everywhere.
Okay.
let's move on.
This is the more complex case
of AI application in fintech.
I would call it infrastructure.
I know of several good examples
of AI using compliance and dealing
firstly, this is the very obvious case
with money laundering and screening
of clients and their transactions.
there are several companies that
provide such service for several
thousands dollars a month.
But the good news is you can do it.
Yourself completely.
Today, there are solutions where AI
helps fintech companies check clients
for sanctions lists and analyze incoming
transactions, checking the crypto wallets
and addresses just to make sure that
wallet is a red flag, not green flag.
And secondly, I know several examples
of successful integration of AI into
the dealing infrastructure, even in my
current company, AI successfully tracks
suspicious trading activity, asset price
manipulation, or group bonuses laundering.
The system automatically analyze
when something suspicious happens.
For example, very similar trades from
the same location with the same IP
address, but with different devices.
And finally, AI successfully assists
dealing in daily work, for example,
managing liquidity and order book,
and also helping with price slippage.
Okay.
enough about boring stuff.
Let's talk about customer
acquisition and advertisement.
as many companies have already switched
completely to AI generated content.
as an example of big players,
I can refer to eToro.
I was recently in London at the finance
conference, finance magnets conference,
and I talked to Stephanie, she's the
marketing director at eToro and she
said that almost all the texts on the
web, on their website, all the pictures
and translations were made using AI.
In addition, she said that their latest.
big advertising campaign, which they
launched for the Olympic games this year
was 95 percent made with the help of AI.
You can Google this campaign
and watch videos on YouTube.
It's really cool.
It, it's really amazing.
Another example of successful use
of AI and work is a root stock lab.
you can check their website.
That's the crypto startup from Europe.
And all their content on the website,
including pictures, images, translation
is made with the help of AI.
their latest educational and
advertising campaign, which they
launch in honor of Bitcoin birthday
was made entirely with the help of AI.
What can I say?
It's just, wow.
Okay.
from attracting clients, we move on
to activating them and retaining them.
As an example of using AI, I
can tell you about my case with
Libertex, where I can work, where
I worked for six and a half years.
And for those who don't know,
Libertex is a trading platform.
And like many other offers, large brokers,
they had the resources to support an
entire department called the Academy.
So the trading Academy was engaged
in preparing trading ideas, trading
strategies, writing digests, making
forecasts for various assets and every
quarter releasing large analytical
reports on various markets with
forecasts and price prediction.
So as soon as AI appeared, we decided
to try to use it in daily tasks.
Yes, of course, we had to train the model
first for a really long time, but what
they have now is just simply amazing.
According to statistics, AI
even often gives more accurate
forecasts than a human.
the academy is no longer exists.
now it called Libertex lab and it has
everything for new clients, as well as
experienced traders, as you may know,
one of the biggest pain points for a
newbie in financial markets is opening
the first deal people are just afraid.
To make a mistake.
They are not experienced enough yet.
Yes, they may understand what they
are interested in, for example,
gold or Bitcoin, but they are not
even sure which direction to open
the deal up or down, long or short.
So now this problem completely
covered by trading signals.
If you don't know what
to trade, no problem.
Here is the whole set of trading
signals where you can open several
deals on different assets at once with
just one click and earn money fast
for more attract advanced traders.
AI prepares trading ideas, trading
strategies, reviews, and weekly
digests with price forecasts
for different assets in general.
As far as I remember, out of 12 people
who used to work at the academy, only
two people remain who work with prompts
and constantly generate content.
So that's about it.
AI taking our jobs.
Okay.
So moving next to my favorite example yet.
We'll be, we'll be is the next
generation trading platform,
completely focused on AI.
The idea is pretty simple.
AI will help you to trade better.
And the biggest flaw of a
successful trader is emotions.
Sometimes emotions make a successful
trader, not very successful, and the
person can just lose all the money.
This is the problem that will be solves.
They initially made their
platform based on the AI.
at the very initial stage, a trader
can choose an assistant like a
co pilot who is ready to adapt.
to the trading style and needs
of any person in will be those
assistants, are called bodies.
At the moment, you can choose one
of five different bodies depending
on the assets you are interested
in, the level of risk tolerance that
you have and your trading strategy.
In essence, five different bodies
are different prompts that work
with, within the specific framework.
what's, highly versatile.
They can, they capable of
fundamental and technical analysis.
Roughly speaking, they constantly monitor
what is happening in the news or social
media and give forecasts on how this may
affect the price of a particular coin.
For example, if Elon Musk writes
something positive about Dogecoin
on Twitter, the body will give you
a buy signal almost immediately.
In addition, the body
constantly analyzes the charts.
If any pattern is noticed on the
candles, you will also receive a push
notifications with the trading signal.
When you click on this notification,
you will immediately be offered
a deal, which you can accept
and open in literally one click.
I think this is a very cool.
And as far as I know, this project is
growing and developing really fast.
And at the moment they already have tens
of thousands of active traders per day.
I wish them a very good luck.
Okay.
almost at the end of the presentation,
let me tell you a little bit about
how AI helps, very large corporations
Bloomberg and the Reuters have already
widely implemented AI in their processes.
For example, I know about a unique
technology that helps them to research
and analyze large amounts of data.
The AI based system scans all the
world's weather forecasts, websites, the
system monitor natural disasters, like
droughts, floods, and other events that
can somehow affect the harvest of various
assets, such as coffee, cocoa, or wheat.
If the AI sees something that can
affect the harvest, for example, it
can affect the price of the asset.
AI automatically writes an
analytical forecast based on the
data and sends this report to a
person who can make a decision.
I think this is an amazing
example, how AI can help traders.
So you can take your time
to find all articles.
on Reuters and Bloomberg, where they
predict a rise in coffee prices.
And as you may know, right now, coffee
prices have reached record levels.
okay.
My final slide, let's
talk about the future.
What do you think awaits
FinTech in the near future?
I think there are several
possible scenarios.
Scenarios.
We may be able to fully customize
the interface like Tom Cruise in the
Minority Rapport movie, for example.
AI can completely change our understanding
of Interaction with the interface.
Maybe we won't even need to
monitor the price chart anymore.
Who knows?
I'm A hundred, almost a hundred percent.
Sure.
That's soon more and more
platform will add trading bots.
Each trader will be able to choose any
bot depending on the trading strategy,
risk tolerance, or deposit amount.
And perhaps soon we will see how
brokers will add the ability to
customize the trading platform itself.
For example, someone
may find the buy, long.
By button on the right
side, more convenient than
on the left and vice versa.
Who knows?
Someone needs a minute charts while
someone else doesn't need charts at all.
AI can generate and customize any
interface for the needs of every
trader, as it will be convenient
for him or for her in general.
I think that AI and fintech is
just gaining momentum and the
most interesting is yet to come.
Okay.
So that's all I have for now.
Thank you for your attention.
I hope you enjoy it.
Please.
You can scan if you want to connect
with me, just scan the QR code
and let's be in touch on LinkedIn.
And for now, bye everyone.
Thanks again.