My name is Nandakumar Ramachandran Pejari.
In this session, we'll dive into how
AI and IOT converge to drive real time
optimization in multi cloud environments.
I'll discuss key technologies use
cases that empower organizations
to manage IOT cloud infrastructure
effectively at a lower cost.
In this section, we'll talk about
the industry wide adoption of multi
cloud infrastructure as well as
application deployments And the
challenges associated with it.
Now, most of us work at organizations
or have dealt with organizations.
that have started adopting multi
cloud as a strategy going forward.
Now, this is basically because
organizations believe in flexibility.
They would want, they would want to
avoid vendor lock in and also optimize
performance based on applications which
are best built for certain clouds.
Now, typically customers, big or small,
are adopting and placing applications
across different cloud providers
such as AWS, Azure, GCP, Now, again,
the reason for this is to these that
strategy offers flexibility and the
choice to customers so that they can
put applications and infrastructure
on clouds of their own choice.
However, it comes at
with its own challenges.
in managing these workloads with
the security associated with it and
the cost efficiencies associated.
Now, do hyperscalers
provide a solution to this?
Yes, they do.
for example, AWS offers something
called as AWS Control Tower.
Azure offers Azure Arc.
Google Anthos is one of the other
platforms that Google provides.
But they come with its own complexities
because these tools are meant
for their own specific ecosystem.
And thus, there's a role
for AI to fulfill over here.
On this ecosystem, interconnected
services allow tailored strategies.
For instance, AWS IoT Core enables
edge to cloud IoT data transfer,
while Azure IoT Hub provides
extensive IoT device management.
Now, using Kubernetes and service meshes
like Istio ensures seamless integration
and orchestration across these platforms.
Now, Kubernetes applications tend
to be extremely light because they
don't carry the burden of having
an operating system and thus offer
the flexibility and the mobility of
placement across various cloud providers.
Now, there are other services like
AWS Outposts and Azure Stack, which
offer a hybrid cloud experience
and the flexibility to deploy
clouds on prem as well as on prem.
On in a hybrid cloud scenario
that offer the flexibility.
However, again, these come with
its own limitations as well.
for example, for on prem or for edge
use cases, these are not purpose built.
They are pretty much seen as a bolt on.
Now let's see how AI can be used to solve
multi cloud IOT related optimization.
Now, IOT generates a continuous
stream of real time data.
Now protocols like.
MQTT, COAP handle a lot of low latency
edge to cloud communication for latency
sensitive data edge computing platforms
like AWS Greengrass or Azure IoT Edge
preprocessed data before sending it
to the cloud for advanced analytics.
So while edges are capable of.
data generation, the data
actually gets processed at the
servers located in the cloud.
The flexibility of finding the nearest
server and sending the data to it to get
it processed is key to low latency when
it comes to IoT centric applications.
Now, not just that, keeping the
applications based on Kubernetes
allows for data to be sent to servers
that could actually move across
multiple cloud providers based on
cost and performance requirements.
Now, AI drives optimization
by analyzing IoT data for
predictive maintenance, workload
orchestration, and anomaly detection.
Now, services like AWS SageMaker.
Azure Machine Learning GCP Vertex
AI enable building and deploying
these models across clouds.
AI based orchestration tools like
Kubernetes or, for example, like I
mentioned earlier, which is pretty much
a larger framework of orchestration
ensures real time scaling based on runbook
automation triggered by a specific alert.
These triggers could be based
on data volume at edges.
data processing requirements at central
location and completely based on cost
to spin up more Kubernetes pods or
even for that matter like, spin down
some of the Kubernetes pods when the
time comes to optimize workload on when
there is a leaner workload in this case.
Now the rise of hybrid AI models
combine real time inference at the
edge with cloud based scalability.
For example, smart cities.
leverage IoT protocols like LoRaWAN and
AI platforms like Azure Digital Twins.
to optimize traffic and infrastructure.
Now, Kubernetes further facilitates
seamless deployment in multi cloud setups
with at least, with the least amount
of manual overhead, to put it per se.
as I mentioned earlier, Kubernetes
combined with AI and IoT can simplify
a lot of this workload and application
orchestration for most of these use cases
that we see today across the industry.
That's it.
Let's talk about agentic AI.
Agentic AI is a term we all are hearing
a lot of a lot these days, right?
So let's see how we can leverage agentic
AI to solve some of these Challenges.
Now, agentic AI autonomously makes
decisions based on real time IoT data.
For example, AWS Greengrass combined
with, AI models on SageMaker allows
devices to, to act locally while syncing
with the cloud for broader insights.
That's how it is supposed to be designed.
That's how most frameworks
operate as well.
Now, this flow that you see on this slide.
This flow shows the interplay
of IoT data collection, edge
computing, and cloud analytics.
Now, services like GCP IoT Core
collect real time data, while
edge platforms like Azure IoT
Edge handle the local inferencing.
Now, agentic AI ensures decisions
are made autonomously at the
edge or in the cloud as needed.
Now, as an example, one of the large
manufacturing customers that I've
been working with, used vibration
sensors and MQTT protocol to detect
machine performance and failure
patterns using agentic AI send.
And basically they sent proactive
alerts resulting in nearly like
80, 84 percent of lesser downtime.
Now this resulted in nearly 12
percent cost savings as well as 8
percent of additional production.
Now, if you put it into perspective,
if you put these numbers into
perspective of a large production
setup, this is huge, actually.
Some other real world examples include
predictive maintenance using OCP UA
or, for, Also be UA for industrial IoT
and real time supply chain optimization
using MQTT messaging as well.
Now for smart grid optimization, DDS
enables deterministic communication
between IoT sensors and cloud AI systems.
Now here are some, additional case
studies highlighting AI driven
solutions, in industries like
logistics, healthcare and energy.
For instance, AWS IoT Core, Azure IoT
Hub securely share patient data in
multi cloud setups, while Google Cloud
AI improves delivery routes with real
time traffic inputs from IoT sensors.
In conclusion, I would like to say
that AI is critical to achieving
real time optimization in IoT
related multi cloud deployments.
By embracing hybrid cloud models and
leveraging tools like Kubernetes,
protocols like MQTT and AI services,
organizations can drive innovation, reduce
costs, and gain competitive advantage.
Thank you so much for your time.