Hello, good morning, good afternoon
and good evening everyone.
My name is Gunjan Agarwal and I'm
thrilled to be here to share insights
on crafting compelling AR VR products
and leveraging AI to accelerate
development and improve user experience.
A bit about me, having worked at
Meta, Nutanix, and Amazon, I have been
fortunate to lead some groundbreaking
projects combining technical
innovation with user centric design.
Today, I'll share some of my
learnings to help you as technical
leaders navigate this exciting space.
A quick disclaimer, this presentation
is based entirely on my personal
experience and independent research
with no connection to my professional
roles or responsibilities at Meta.
With that, let's dive into the
agenda to frame today's discussion.
So we'll start by defining XR and why
it's a game changer for industries.
Next we'll examine how XR
development compares to traditional
platforms like mobile and web.
Then we'll explore the challenges unique
to XR and how to overcome them before
concluding with actionable tips for
building scalable products and integrating
AI into the processes and practices.
By the end of this talk, I hope you
leave with both strategic insights and
practical tools to apply in your road.
And for those of you completely new
to this space, I hope you will go back
excited, knowing a bit more about the
possibilities in this upcoming Skibase.
Now, a couple of more points
on what to expect and what not
to expect from this session.
Firstly, given the limited time
we have today, I won't be able
to do a deep dive into all the
integrate details of XR development.
However, my goal is to equip you with
the foundational knowledge and point
you in the right resources direction.
Secondly, while much of my focus today
will center on VR and X, AR development,
particularly with headsets, it's
important to note that many of the
concepts and techniques I'll discuss,
especially from a software development
perspective, are really relevant to
2D game and application development.
Now this makes this knowledge
transferable and valuable across
a wide range of platforms.
With that, let's get going.
So what is XR?
Now XR or Extended Reality is basically an
umbrella term for immersive technologies
that blend the physical and the digital
worlds to create interactive experiences.
It encompasses three key
categories, Augmented Reality,
Virtual Reality and Mixed Reality.
What is augmented reality now AR
overlays digital elements like images
text or example Or animations onto the
real world enhancing what and interact
with For example apps like ikea place
lets you visualize the furniture in
your home Or snapchat filters overlay
fun effects on your face in real time
VR, on the other hand, fully immerses
you in computer generated environment,
cutting you off from the physical world.
Using devices like MetaQuest, PlayStation
VR, we can explore virtual spaces,
play games, or even train for surgery
in completely simulated environments.
Now, mixed reality is
basically a mix of both of it.
It merges the two.
The physical and the digital world
allowing them to coexist and interact
seamlessly Unlike ar which only
overlays digital content Mr enables
users to manipulate and interact
with virtual objects as though they
are part of the real world Devices
like microsoft's hololens are good.
Good example and metacoast 3 are good
example of mr technology Now why is
xr development more relevant than ever
You Now XR is revolutionizing gaming,
healthcare, education, and retail.
Think of PlayStation VR to defining,
redefining gaming, or also VR, enhancing
surgical training in healthcare.
So across the industry, XR is
basically making a huge impact and
bringing about a lot of change.
In terms of market opportunity, with
a projected 250 billion market size
by 2027, driven by device innovations
and heavy investment from companies
like Meta, Microsoft, Google,
Sony, XR is quickly transitioning
from futuristic to mainstream.
Now, but developing for XR brings its own
complexities, which we'll explore shortly.
Many of us here are coming from
software development background.
would have experience with
developing for mobile desktop.
So I thought it would be
useful to contrast the two.
Unlike mobile and web, XR requires real
time 3d environments, which demand for 3d
modeling, complex rendering, and physics.
Advanced spatial awareness and low
latency are a must for seamless user
experience and to avoid discomfort.
Development involves leveraging game
engines like Unity or Unreal, optimizing
for 3D assets, and ensuring secure
and responsive interactions across
devices, and understanding unique
privacy concerns in shared spaces.
With that, let's dive into
the capabilities and tools
that power XR development.
We'll first start by spending
some time understanding the
anatomy of an XMR headset.
A mixed reality headset is an
advanced device that blends virtual
elements with immersive experiences.
Key components include lenses and
screens for displaying visuals, sensors
and cameras for tracking, spatial audio
systems and microphones for audio and
voice, controllers with haptics and
powerful CPUs and GPUs for processing.
High refresh rates, typically 90
hertz or more, are essential to
deliver smooth visuals and minimize
latency, ensuring a convincing
and comfortable user experience.
Now, what gives a sense of immersion
and realism in an MR headset?
A key element of realism in 3D
headsets lies in how they simulate
depth, sound, and spatial awareness
to mimic real world experiences.
As far as realism is concerned, there are
three aspects that we should talk about.
First is Lenses and Depth Perception.
The lenses in a 3D headset magnify the
visuals displayed on the screen and
present slightly different perspectives
of the same image to the eye.
Now this process known as stereoscopy
creates a sense of depth replicating
how our eyes perceive the real world.
Combined with motion tracking, it enables
users to see their environment shift
naturally as they move their heads.
Other aspect is spatial audio,
which gives a sense of realism.
Realism is further enhanced through
spatial audio, which adapts sound
based on distance, direction, and
environmental factors like echos.
Excuse me.
For example, sounds grow louder as you
approach a sound, as you approach a
sound source, or shift position as you
turn your head, providing an immersive
and dynamic auditory experience.
Field of view and tracking is another
aspect which basically give a sense of
immersion and realism in a MR headset.
Now headsets further expand on the
realism by offering a wide field of
view and precise head tracking, allowing
users to explore environments naturally.
As user turn their head, they can see
more of the virtual or the augmented space
just as they would in the physical world.
So all of these things come together to
give a sense of immersion and realism
when someone puts on a MR headset.
Now with that, let's move on to
understand some of the code software
concepts for AR VR development.
With Now one of the core pieces of
software that we need to familiarize
ourselves with is a game engine like
unity or unreal engine A game engine is a
very powerful software framework used in
ar vr development to render 3d graphics
Manage physics process interactions and
more Now we'll talk about some of the key
capabilities provided by the game engine.
Let's start by talking about 3d
graphics and rendering Game engines
are optimized to render realistic,
high quality 3D graphics essential
for immersive AR VR experiences.
They manage lighting, shading, textures,
and other visual elements that help
create a convincing virtual world.
Physics simulation and 3D
lighting is another capability
provided by the game engines.
The game engines have physics
engine that simulate real world
behaviors such as gravity,
collision, and object interactions.
This is crucial in VR to maintain
a sense of realism as user expect
virtual objects to respond to
actions similarly to physical.
objects.
Game engines are also optimized
for real time processing.
Now ARVR requires real time
performance to reduce latency, which
is necessary to avoid motion sickness.
Game engines are optimized
to process actions and render
changes in milliseconds.
So this is another crucial
aspect of game engine.
Spatial audio integration, like we
briefly discussed about earlier, is also a
capability provided with the game engine.
Sound is crucial, as we know, in
AR VR for immersion, game engines
typically support spatial audio,
which allows sound to be positioned
in 3D space relative to the user.
This enhances the feeling of presence,
as user can perceive sound coming from
specific direction and distance, like
we briefly spoke about earlier as well.
Animation scripting is another
capability provided by a game engine.
Game engines support custom animation
scripting, often using C sharp
in Unity or C in Unreal, allowing
developers to create interactive
scenarios and dynamic object behaviors.
Support for interactive.
interaction input is another capability
that the game engines provide These
game engines are designed to handle
user input from vr controllers hand
tracking systems and even voice commands
This enable more natural and intuitive
way to interact with virtual objects
making arvr applications more engaging
Other aspect or capability provided
by game engine is scene management.
Now these game engines allow developers
to organize complex scenes with multiple
objects, layers, and environments.
In AR VR, this is especially helpful
for creating layered experiences
where virtual objects can interact
with the physical spaces and each
other in highly complex ways.
Developers tools and asset store is
another aspect which is very important
and provided by most of the game engines.
These game engines come with a wide
range of developer tools, debugging
features, and asset stores with pre
made objects, textures, and animations.
These tools help streamline AR
VR development, enabling faster
iterations and prototyping.
Now lastly cross platform support
is another big capability generally
provided by game engines Now these
game engines often support multiple
platforms like ios android oculus and
hololens Etc allowing arvr application
that can run on various devices
Now we covered unity which is basically
the core piece of software that one needs
to be very familiar with if they are
developing for arvr Or games But there
is another aspect which we need to be
very familiar with when developing for
AR VR Now for anyone working on creating
immersive experiences like virtual
worlds a deep understanding of concepts
such as shaders and materials Lighting
and cameras vfx and animation is very
important These are particularly useful
for 3d artists involved in creating assets
and the words which basically are used
by engineers to put together the whole
You know experience of the game together
I'll briefly explain these Shaders and
materials, basically, let's start by
talking about shaders and materials.
3D shapes are generally
represented using meshes.
To draw something in Unity, you must
provide information that describes
the shape and the information that
describes the appearance of its surface.
You use meshes to describe
shape and materials to describe
appearance and surfaces.
Shaders, pixel colors for
realistic or stylized visuals.
There's another thing we should
talk about, which is a render
pipeline, which basically process
scene objects for display, right?
They basically look at what is visible
in the scene and cull what is out
of the scene, include what is there
in the scene to continuously update,
render, update and render the display.
There are different kinds of pipelines.
render pipelines like URP, HDRP, or
built in pipelines, which one needs
to familiarize themselves with.
Let's talk about now lighting and cameras.
Now lighting models, real world
light behavior with adjustable global
illumination and lighting modes.
There are things like baked
lighting, real time lighting
which one needs to understand.
Now cameras basically flatten 3D
scenes for 2D screens capturing and
presenting the game world to players.
Okay, so what is vfx and animation now
vfx include particle systems decals
large scale graphical effects to enhance
immersion So for example a fire coming on
the screen or a vfx Effect of emotes and
all of those things are basically the vfx
capabilities which basically are designed
by artists Now animation provides features
like retargeting, runtime control, state
machines, and blend, blend shapes for
lifelike motion and facial expression.
So animation is something which
is also very important for us to
understand when developing for ARVR.
Another crucial aspect that one
needs to familiarize themselves
with is post processing.
Now, post processing is basically
about visual enhancements via
camera applied effects like
filters and image corrections.
Realistic 3D audio support, like
directional sound, distance effects,
and environmental acoustics like echoes
are also part of post processing.
Lastly, UI design and prototyping.
This basically involves tools for
creating user friendly interfaces and
quick prototyping of assets and ideas.
There are various tools which basically
are used by the creative community
to do all of this work, and then
create, immersive 3D experiences.
There are tools like Blender, Unity,
ProBuilder, Maya, which basically
are very popular among the creative
community for creating these assets.
And lastly, let's take a quick
view of different, AR SDKs that
can be used for AR development.
we'll talk a few, talk about a few popular
ones like ARKit, ARCore and Vuforia.
For example, ARKit is provided by Apple,
quite popular among, iOS developers.
ARCore likely supported by Google.
Very famous among Android developers.
Euphoria is another very popular,
AR SDK, and with a very good
integration with Unity, is very,
is another popular, AR SDK.
Likewise, there are many others which,
which can be leveraged to do AR.
Now we covered about, tools like
Game Engine, AR SDKs, and talk
about different creative concepts.
Now, despite these tools,
building XR applications is quite
challenging, which we'll discuss now.
So what are the challenges
unique to XR development?
Now, creating a successful AR
VR product is no small feat.
Let's explore some of these unique
challenges developers face and
techniques to overcome them.
First, let's start by talking
about hardware limitations.
Now, there are several hardware
limitations, such as limited
processing power, battery life,
form factor and comfort, display
quality, etc., that one needs to pay
attention to when developing for XR.
Let's start talking about each of these,
basically hardware related challenges.
So let's start by talking
about processing power.
Now AR VR experiences are
resource intensive, demanding
high computation power to render
realistic graphic at high frame rates.
Developers must optimize their code,
manage memory usage efficiently to
ensure a great, great, result from
the processing power perspective.
Other hardware limitation is
battery or challenges battery life.
Achieving a balance between performance
and battery life consumption is critical,
especially for standalone devices.
Techniques like 4 bit rendering where only
area that the user is directly looking
at is rendered in high detail helps
save processing power and battery life.
Likewise, there are other techniques
which are very important to, which
are very important for taking
consideration of battery life.
Form factor and comfort is another aspect
from the hardware perspective, which
XR developers need to pay attention to.
The physical design of
headset impacts user adoption.
Reducing weight, improving ergonomics,
and balancing the headset are priorities
to ensure user can wear devices for
extended periods of time comfortably.
Lastly, from the hardware perspective,
let's talk about display quality.
Now, fast refresh rates and high
resolutions are necessary to deliver
a smooth visual like we have spoken
about earlier, but they also introduce
challenges like heat generation
and increased power consumption.
Display technologies like OLED, micro
LED are being explored to provide
better visuals without these trade offs.
With that, let's move on to talk about
latency and motion sickness as another
challenge unique to XR development.
Now latency is a
significant challenge in VR.
If there is even a small delay between
the user's physical environment
and visuals being displayed, it can
lead to cyber sickness ensuring.
Now ensuring low latency requires
efficient tracking algorithms.
Now real time tracking and
rendering algorithms are very
important to keep the experience.
This includes head tracking, eye
tracking, and position tracking.
Basically, all the tracking that we
are doing is basically has to be in
real time to avoid any sort of latency.
Otherwise, users generally
get motion sickness.
Another technique which is very useful
to avoid latency and reduce motion
sickness is using predictive algorithms.
Now, predictive algorithms can help
compensate for latency by predicting
the user's next move and adjusting the
visuals accordingly, ensuring that the
user remains immersed without any lag.
Then let's talk about tracking through
multiple sensors, which is challenging
as far as XR development is concerned.
Now, reliable tracking of head, hand,
and body movements is essential.
AR, VR devices rely on sensors like
cameras, gyroscopes, and accelerometers.
Developing robust sensor fusion algorithms
that integrates data from multiple
sensors is one of the techniques that
allow for accurate and responsive
tracking, which is crucial for immersion.
Now content creation in 3D
modeling is another challenge
very unique to XR development.
High quality 3D content is essential
for creating immersive experiences.
However, creating a detailed model
that looks realistic while running
smoothly across different hardware
configurations is a big challenge.
Developers use several optimization
techniques like level of
details and texture compression.
Level of detail reduce the complexity
of 3D model when they are far
away and ensuring performance
without sacrificing visual quality.
Text compression reduce texture
size without, texture compression
reduce texture size without
significant loss in detail to
optimize load time and memory usage.
Now let's talk about debugging
and testing challenges.
Testing AR VR requires evaluating
performance across various environments,
device types, and user scenarios.
Developers use a combination of
simulated environments and real world
testing to address potential issues.
Automated testing tools for stress
testing, the rendering pipeline,
and sensor inputs can also help
identify certain bottlenecks.
The user safety and health is another
challenge which is very unique to XR
development Ensuring the safety and
comfort of user is critical extended
use of VR can lead to eye strain and
physical discomfort as well as Hazards, so
developers need to design experiences that
minimize this effect and encourage regular
breaks Integrating safety features like a
boundary system like guardian can prevent
users from bumping into real world objects
Now, we spoke about these challenges
and some of these techniques to overcome
these challenges, but nonetheless,
overcoming these challenges require a
careful optimization around strategies,
which we will talk about next.
So what does it take to build
a lovable and scalable XR
product?
Now buildings a lovable and scalable
excel product that scales across
devices and user exp, and users and
is loved by customers require paying
attention to several key aspects.
And we'll talk about three key areas,
which is focus on user design and
experience optimizing performance and
focus of inter focus on interoperability
and ecosystem integration.
Let's start by talking about
focus on user experience design.
Now AR and VR is all about
spatial interactions.
The way users move and interact with
virtual objects must feel natural.
Some of the areas to pay
attention to are spatial design.
Developers need to leverage
principles of spatial design to create
intuitive and engaging experiences.
Environment variability is another aspect
which is related to user experience.
Now AR experiences must work well in
diverse settings from bright outdoor
environments to dim indoor ones.
Developers can use techniques
like adaptive lighting and robust
tracking to ensure consistency.
Adaptive UI UX for varied user scenarios.
is another thing which one
needs to pay attention to.
Now, users may switch between indoor
and outdoor setting, or from sitting
to standing, designing adaptive UI UX
ensures that experience remain intuitive
and responsive across varied scenarios.
Now, optimizing for performance, is
another critical aspect of building
a lovable and great, XR experience.
As you've already seen, performance is
a critical aspect for XR application.
We can optimize performance
in several ways.
First is we can adopt a low latency
architecture like edge computing
which can really help minimize delays.
We can also optimize 3d content as
you have seen 3d content is very
computation heavy and have involved
involves a performance penalty.
So we can use best practices in
optimizing the 3d entry content 3d
content which can Ensure high performance
without sacrificing visual quality.
This involves efficient use of textures
shader and lighting We should also pay
attention to minimizing bandwidth usage by
finding ways To reduce the bandwidth usage
without finding qualities, techniques
like adaptive streaming and compression
can be very beneficial in this regard.
Lastly, let's talk about interoperability
and ecosystem integration.
We briefly touched upon the concept of
interoperability earlier, but creating a
robust ecosystem that supports multiple
devices and platforms ensures that the
users have seamless experience, whether
they are on mobile, VR, or desktop.
Interoperability can also
encourage third party developers
to build on your platform.
Encouraging application, you know spread
from this aspect we can focus on following
like You know following like we can start
with we can think about x device and
platform compatibility So for this we
should build using standard methods that
allow your apps to work across devices
and headsets and platforms We can also
adopt standard tools and skill sets Now
allowing use of standards and popular
tools such as unity for development
encourages third party developers
to develop apps And integrations
enriching user experience and enhancing
further reach of your application
So we've spoken about, so far about the
challenges unique to XR development, what
the, what are the key software concepts
of XR development and how can we overcome
some of the challenges we've spoken
about and different tools used, right?
I want to end this, session by spending
some time talking about how can
we leverage AI to basically create
compelling XR experiences, right?
As we've spoken about, creating compelling
XR products demands significant effort.
But AI can accelerate development, enhance
user experience, and empower creator.
So let's start, to look at each of these
aspects in a little bit more detail.
Let's start by talking about improving
AR VR development through XI.
Now there are multiple ways in
which AI can, accelerate or improve
AR VR development experience
for the developer themselves.
First is by automated asset creation.
Now 3D assets, textures and
environments saving time for developers.
Tools like DALI enable creators to produce
high quality visuals from simple inputs.
realistic physics and animations
is another area where AI
can help significantly.
AI powered physics engines can simulate
real world behaviors more accurately,
making AR VR applications feel natural.
Another aspect is procedural generation.
Now AI enables the automated generation
of complex environment, which is useful
for open world VR games and simulation.
Another final aspect is
enhanced testing and debugging.
Now AI can assist in QA processes by
automatically testing interactions and
identifying glitches or bugs in AR VR
environment, which are difficult to catch.
Algorithms, these algorithms can
simulate user interaction, finding edge
cages that humans might otherwise miss.
another area where AI can, significantly,
help improve, the user experience
is, another area is basically
where AI can significantly help
is elevating the user experience.
so there are multiple,
aspects here as well.
for example, personal
personalized interaction.
Now a LL algorithms can personalize
content based on user's preferences
and behaviors, creating more
engaging and tailored experiences.
For instance, VR experiences can adapt in
real time to a user's emotional response.
Tracked through AI based,
analysis of biometrics.
AI can also help with.
Natural language processing.
Now NLP powered AI can enable
natural, conversational
interactions with AR VR experiences.
This is useful for applications like
VR education or training simulations
where users can interact with virtual
characters like, like in a human like way.
Now enhanced spatial audio is
another aspect where AI can help
improve the user experiences.
AI can help enhance spatial
audio, making sound appear to
come from specific direction,
distance, or even specific objects.
Deep learning models can also
personalize audio experience based on
user preferences, immersive experience.
Immersive experience.
Finally, emotion detection and
adaptation is another area in
which AI can significantly help
improve the user experience.
For example, AI can monitor facial
expressions and body language to
direct the user's emotional state
and adapt the experience accordingly.
This is especially useful in VR
training, therapy and gaming.
where real world adaptation can
improve engagement and outcomes.
Lastly, let's talk about
how can AI empower creators.
So there are multiple ways, for
example, content creation assistance.
Now, AI driven tools help creators
draft narratives, creative scripts,
or storylines that adapt to user
choices and behaviors in real time.
For example, a generative model
can assist creators Game writers by
suggesting branching story paths.
AI can also help by, word
authoring, which is basically,
a significant effort otherwise.
lastly, AI can significantly
democratize access to tools, encouraging
more people to create, for AR.
now AI powered low code or no code
platforms like, which basically empower
creators with minimal programming
skills to develop compelling AR VR
experiences, allowing a wide range
of creators to enter the field, which
otherwise would be limited because of
the steep learning curve of tools and
technology in this particular area.
alright, with that we have come
to the end of the presentation.
Hope this was useful as we explore the
transformative potential of xr, the unique
challenges and for of developing for this
platform and the role of creating, role of
AI in creating scalable LAN applications.
With that, I want to thank
you, all for your time today.
Please feel free to connect with
me on LinkedIn if you're working on
or looking to explore this space.
Thank you so much for your time.
Bye.