All right.
Nice that you're all here.
very appreciated.
Oh, let's dive right in.
One thing I learned, giving this
presentation a few times in the past is
that the title slide is very often very
much misunderstood, or, at least say,
it helps people or giving people a laugh
because a lot of people actually read
it as Duke Postgres don't do Kubernetes.
which is not how it meant.
it's actually a good read.
but I think it's the wrong way.
because from my perspective,
Postgres really loves Kubernetes.
And the other way around,
Kubernetes really loves Postgres.
I expect that there is quite a few people
in the audience already that use Postgres.
there is a good chunk of people
that I guess uses Kubernetes.
And there is probably still a
sizable amount of people that
already use Postgres on Kubernetes.
If you don't, I hope that by the
end of the presentation, I actually
got you to the point where ah, that
sounds like a really good idea.
I should totally do that.
So a few words about me.
Just say I'm Chris.
I'm a developer advocate at Simplyblock.
been with a few companies in the past.
some might be more known than others.
Some people might have heard
about this weird little
gaming company called Ubisoft.
If you heard about those, Probably in
the context of copy protection, but,
that was not what I worked on at least.
but afterwards it's very
much all about data.
Hazelcast was an in memory data grid.
meaning that everything was about the
actual, data in memory that you could,
analyze, that you could share state
between different instances stateless.
Stuff like that, right?
it was all about data and Stata
was all about observability.
So it's still all about data, right?
it's metrics.
it's, traces it spans.
It's all about the combination
of different services and how
they work together in the whole
infrastructure, stuff like that.
it's all about data.
Clever bit, was my own startup.
We actually made hot end software for
animal husbandry, measuring like CO2
ammonia levels, trying to correlate them
with like medication and in general,
trying to prevent medication from giving.
from being given to the animals, to make
better meat quality, in general, get
the animals a healthier life for, at
least for the time they actually live.
we all know how that ends, right?
but at least making their lives as good
as possible while they're around, and
timescale, is a time series database at.
Or on top of Postgres, and as you can see
in the picture, that is from last year.
I really like that,
that conference picture.
At a timescale, I love to, to explain
people why I think Postgres is the
ultimate database for time serious data.
And now I'm at SimpliBlock, and
SimpliBlock is also all about data.
It's all about data storage, how you can,
expand storage, how you can scale storage.
so there, there's a little bit of a red
thread through my life, even at Ubisoft, a
lot of stuff in, in, in games these days,
is it about data is about interaction,
how players interact with your games.
so there's like this general thing.
if you want to drop me a message, if
you have questions, you see my socials.
the presentation will be shared.
just feel free to, to drop
me a line and ask a question.
What I learned over the last couple
of years is that you want to start.
presentation with a game, making
it interactive, making it fun.
So for the ones that don't know what
family thought is, it's basically a,
a game show where, two families fight
against each other, trying to guess.
Like the first answers that
popped into people's minds.
So the idea is we asked a hundred people,
what is your first thought when it
comes to X, Y, Z for today, I thought it
makes sense to have, like, why shouldn't
you run a database in Kubernetes?
And because it's hard to do this life
right now, I actually went ahead.
I was nice enough to fix,
to figure that out for you.
So I went to Twitter.
And ask like, why shouldn't you
run a database on Kubernetes?
What do you think?
I please help me.
I need your help.
when you do this things on Twitter,
sorry, X, you have to remember one thing
when you ask, a controversial question
on Twitter, X, I have to get used to
that on X, always ask for a friend.
It's important asking for a friend.
it's not about you.
Obviously you would never do this.
so asking for a friend is like
the most important thing for those
kinds of stuff, there were answers.
and the answers were like, Kubernetes
wasn't designed in with databases in mind.
Which is very much true.
Like when Kubernetes was
designed initially, what is it?
10, 10 years ago, We had the
Kubernetes, yeah, so 10 years
ago, Kubernetes was designed for
stateless systems and stateless only,
but about five or six years ago.
I don't want to pinpoint
to the exact point in time.
Kubernetes has changed.
People started to figure out, okay,
stateless systems are nice, but they're
not easy to do be designed, right?
So they started to integrate
elements for stateful services,
what they call it, right?
So stateful service in general,
true databases weren't Well, thought
about at, I guess at that point, at
least, maybe not like first thought.
but that changed quite a bit.
So if you're stuck in the past, yes,
Kubernetes wasn't designed for databases.
These days, that's not
actually very much true.
then.
Never run stateful
workloads on Kubernetes.
Okay, that's a harsh one.
as I said, stuck, if you're stuck in the
past, that's true, but stateful workloads
aren't always just like database.
It might be the first thing people think
about and that pops into their minds.
But in general, there's a
lot of stateful services.
It's really hard actually to write
a fully stateless service because
oftentimes You have like at least a
minimal, state that might be ephemeral.
So it doesn't really matter if it
gets lost, but you want to keep
it because it makes stuff easier.
It makes stuff faster.
so stateless services are
actually very hard to do.
persistent data will kill
you because it's too slow.
that's a good one.
and, you might be true about that, but
I think that very much depends on you.
Where you go in the sense
of how do I store my data?
this is up to you find
a good data solution.
I might be biased and say,
simply block is a good one.
but I think this very much depends on you.
And there's a lot of options
these days for Kubernetes.
even simple stuff like NFS or
local hard disk, like local
persistent storage, it's all there.
Wouldn't say do this or we'll get back to
that later, but there's a lot of options.
So I think that is not true.
if you, if you say, okay, I want to plug
in a USB stick and I store my database
on this USB stick via persistent volume.
Be my guest.
Don't expect it to be fast.
nobody understands Kubernetes.
And that is a really interesting one.
I had to, hard, really, love to,
really hard when I saw that, that, that
specific answer, because, Yes and no.
there is some truth to it.
I'm pretty sure nobody understands
Kubernetes, including the
Kubernetes developers, including me.
there is still a lot of things in
Kubernetes that I've never used.
And I probably never will.
I think it's a little bit like getting
used to programming languages, right?
You can say you're a proficient in
a programming language, but does
that mean you know every little bit
about those programming languages?
No, you don't.
But if you feel like you're not
understanding Kubernetes at all, please
don't run a database on Kubernetes.
Don't run an application on Kubernetes.
Please don't run Kubernetes at all.
if you feel like you're not understanding
anything about it, just don't use it.
there is no need in your case.
Most probable.
The next one is what is your benefit?
databases don't need to scale
or especially outer scale.
And that one kind of confused me.
it feels This is a person that necess
didn't necessarily run a database,
of a size of a meaningful size.
many databases probably
don't need to outscale.
but especially, things were like
you, you store user behavior,
click click flows, any kind of
iot data, all that kinda stuff.
Databases need to outscale and out
scaling can be a lot of things.
It could be database, it could
be compute, it could be storage.
There's a lot of stuff.
then databases and applications
should be separated.
And I'm very much on par with that.
I totally agree your database
and your applications normally
shouldn't run on the same notes.
and we'll see a little bit of
a solution for that later on.
so yes.
fully agree is not an
argument against Kubernetes.
and the last one is actually something I
very much agree with, not another layer of
indirection and abstraction, abstractions
and indirections can be complicated.
they don't have to be, they're
a blessing, they're made.
They're made in heaven as long as stuff
happens and works, because they take
away complexity, but they can be, a beast
from hell if stuff goes down the cell or
goes down the drain, and now you have to
figure out where stuff is actually broken.
That is really a problem, and Kubernetes
doesn't make things easier using, all
those like extensions for Kubernetes,
like service mesh and all that kind of
stuff, all the things that make your
life easier, actually make it harder.
The second you have an issue and you
try to figure out what is happening.
So the question, I saw those answers and
I was like, ah, oh, how do, where do.
Do I get from here, right?
Like, how do I make this work
out for the presentation?
I wanted to tell you about why
you actually should do that.
and why it's a great idea.
do I have to burn in hell now?
this is complicated.
What am I doing?
I want to go to the happy place.
So let's, how do we, how can we do this?
So my first initial
thought, Hey, let's cheat.
Cheating is good.
I work for Ubisoft, so I know
what I'm talking about, right?
I'm a big gamer.
I know exactly what I'm talking about.
So that is something, that a
lot of the older folks in the
audience might actually know.
it's the so called Konami code.
It's probably the most known or
most well known, cheat of all times.
for the younger generation,
just look it up on Wikipedia.
Konami, like the gaming
company Konami code.
it was a great pleasure.
So now that we cheated, we can
actually go to the real topic, right?
So where do I get from here?
Why do we want to run
Postgres on Kubernetes?
And I think.
There is a good set of reasons.
And first of all, I'm a big
hater of cloud vendor lock in.
I think it's a really big problem.
cloud vendors, especially
hyperscalers love to offer you all
kinds of services, and make them
easy to integrate to lure you in.
But the problem is.
Those services might be nice
and might be good for the first,
iteration, maybe the first couple
of iterations, but at some point.
You're hitting the upper
limit of what is possible.
Those services are meant
for the mainstream.
They only work because they
can be used by a lot of people.
And a lot of people means that
the second you have something
special, there is a problem, right?
There, they don't.
They don't care for you anymore because
you're not part of the mainstream.
and specifically for databases like RDS
and stuff that can come in very fast.
If you use custom extensions
or special extensions.
sure.
like the standard extensions are all
available, like post GIS and stuff.
The second you come to something like,
for example, timescale, you might have
an old version, you might only have an
Apache license version, which doesn't have
all the features, stuff like that, right?
You might actually have quite the issue
really fast, even though you feel like.
You're, you haven't outgrown
the size of something like RDS.
faster time to market, decreasing costs.
I think that goes and automation.
I think that goes all
well, hand in hand, right?
If I have everything automated, if
I have everything easily deployable,
It's super easy to, get to Mac market
fast, do a couple of iterations, see
if stuff works that decreases cost.
I might actually save, one or two people.
that is where automation comes in.
I tell Kubernetes, Hey, or like whatever
I need, a new, postgres cluster, it spins
it up and make sure that everything is
around, that can be a single DevOps person
instead of a team of, database engineers.
I'm sorry.
I know that I'm bashing on
database engineers here.
but don't get me wrong.
You still have a job.
It's just not the boring stuff.
Now you can actually look
into the cool things, right?
a unified deployment architecture.
I think I'm a big lover
of that kind of stuff.
I think, unified, architecture
makes things easy to understand.
we have the databases deployed the
same way as we have deployed our
application, all that kind of stuff.
That's why people love
Terraform so much, right?
Because Terraform gave you
like a single tool to actually
do all this kind of stuff.
Somebody has to write the recipes,
but it doesn't have to be you.
and last but not least, I'm
a big fan of read replicas.
If you have a use case where this like
small performance or a small lack of,
data, through, physical replication is
not much of an issue and that is probably
true for a lot of IOT use cases, like my
own startup, like Cleverbit, we actually
have that we used read replicas quite
a lot, we, we got values or, metrics.
like every 10 seconds, but we averaged
them on a minute scale anyway.
So it didn't really matter if there's one
or two messages being lost or not lost,
but not arrive on a read replica yet.
So what we did is we literally just
spread the query load to all nodes,
writes always went to the primary, but we
had read replicas for query, scale out.
okay.
now that we know why we want to do this.
What do I get from here?
let's get a few things out of
a way, which aren't necessarily
like superior Postgres specific.
from my perspective, the most
important thing, and I can't
stress this enough, enable TLS,
enable data encryption at rest.
You want to make sure
your data is encrypted.
It doesn't matter if you're like a
10 people company and you feel like
everyone can have access to the database.
That is not the point.
The point is make sure that
somebody from the outside.
Can not get to your data, like at
all, like no way possible there's
nothing worse than a data breach.
And luckily to this day, I can
say I've not been at a company at
least, while there was a data breach
of, of any kind, which I think is.
Good.
I know this is not true for other
people, and I know how I can't
imagine how embarrassed that is.
the problem with a software update
that basically killed all Windows
systems just a few weeks ago, right?
if you're on Kubernetes, use Secret,
Kubernetes Secrets used to be certificate
manager, ertman or cert manager.
use, the integration from
cloud providers, for credential
management, all that kinda stuff.
Just make sure you have security
locked down as much as possible, yay,
we, we actually got security, right?
Yoo hoo, okay, the other thing, think
about backups are important, and
when I talk about backups, I don't
just mean a stupid PG dump, don't
do this, from my perspective, okay?
PgDump is not designed
as a backup solution.
PgBaseBackup is okay, but please
don't try to roll your own solution.
when we talk about backups in Postgres,
we specifically, or in most databases,
we specifically mean continuous backup,
meaning the, that the actual writer
headlock needs to be stored, same as.
a database snapshot and there
is great tools for that.
We're in the Postgres ecosystem.
Everything has 10 plus one tools,
because with Postgres distribution
doesn't give you those things.
So everyone started to build their own.
I actually have amazing
experience with PG backrest.
it is the tool that we used, quite a lot.
it's from my perspective, rock solid.
I know a lot of people actually using
barman and that just works as well.
there's PG horde and
there's so many other tools.
my recommendation would be either go
with Barman or PgBackrest, and just use
those tools are, industry proven, rock
solid, they are proven, they just work.
from my perspective, that is the way
to go, and store your data somewhere
that is not, Your own notes don't
store them somewhere in a notes, right?
don't set up a min IO on Kubernetes
and say, Oh, I have an S3 API.
So I can just store my backups there.
that's not how a backup works.
Store it to object storage,
like S3 or, cloud, cloud store
or, blob storage or whatever.
Just make sure they're not on your notes.
and the other thing is test your backups.
please.
I can't stress this enough.
test your backups.
and backup testing doesn't mean like
once a year or once in a while tested
regular, like once a month, once a week,
once every day, with my own startup, we
actually went for like once every week.
and the way we did it, I think
Kubernetes made this very simple for us.
We had a Kubernetes backup, Kubernetes.
Cluster and the cluster was basically,
one primary to read replica.
So what we did is we just scaled
the cluster up and said, Hey,
we need a third, read replica,
basically a four note cluster.
it restored it from a backup.
the notes try to join the cluster.
So it had to set up physical
replication streamed in the remaining
stuff that was not in the backup
and eventually joined the cluster.
The second, it joined fully,
had the cluster fully joined and
was able to service requests.
We knew that our backup
strategy actually worked.
we scaled it down again, and
Kubernetes just deleted the old
node, whatever that was, basically.
So we had a little bit of a rolling,
a restart, a system as well, which
tested a few other things like
cluster health and stuff like that.
so I think Kubernetes makes those things
like very easy and very nice to use.
The other thing that kind of surprised me
initially when I started using Postgres
or setting up Postgres on Kubernetes is
that the actual Postgres configuration
isn't much influenced at all.
you still want to configure like
your shared buffers, workman,
blah, blah, blah, right?
All of these standard parameters,
you're actually changing normally.
but that doesn't mean that they, Are
influenced by how you set up Kubernetes
or how you set up Postgres on Kubernetes.
You need to remember that you have
a container and your container
has like certain size limits.
So you want to make sure that
you're actually, configuring based
on that, but that's about it.
The other thing is if you have no
idea about those parameters, they're
very much, those are the easy ones.
There is like way more advanced
ones worker sizes or worker
numbers and stuff like that.
if you don't feel like you have a good
idea what they mean and how they affect
your Postgres installation, Try to get
his consultant to help you set it up.
don't just play around with it yourself.
I know it sounds stupid to get
a consultant for those things.
but believe me, that
is money well invested.
you, you get to, to a good
point, like much faster, with
much less problems, you not over
configuration, configure Postgres.
The worst problem is that if.
Everything seems to work out and you get
like super fast response times and stuff.
but when you actually put load
on the system, you have it over
configured, you run out of memory,
stuff like that is not nice.
So make sure you have
somebody who understands that.
and the other thing is.
Postgres loves used pages.
so wherever you run Postgres, make
sure you have future pages enabled in
your kernel settings, blah, blah, blah.
With Kubernetes, there is like
a little bit of an issue and
we'll get back to that later on.
Just remember, huge pages are great.
and because we're in the Postgres
ecosystem, much more knowledgeable
people than me actually wrote about
that before, or even recorded a video.
make sure that you
actually listen to them.
they give you a lot of information
about how to, how post, Postgres
should be configured for performance,
how you set up the, huge pages
in Postgres and stuff like that.
the slides are shared, as I said before,
so just follow the links afterwards
and, you're in for a good read.
Then you have, Postgres extensions
and that is where it becomes
a little bit more complicated.
You remember, when I set that, on
hyperscaler setups, you, extensions
might already be an issue if you
have something like timescale.
PG vector is very Common these days
to, to be seen on those setups, but
in the first couple of months, PG
vector was still an issue, right?
So if the second you use
extensions, you might be out
of the scope of hosted setups.
the problem is you might not be
out of a scope in the sense of
when it comes to Kubernetes, right?
So the standard image for Postgres.
does not contain a lot of, extensions.
And to my surprise off the, I think the
standard image doesn't even, support
post JS, which I find very confusing.
but, it is what it is.
that means the second you need
extensions, you actually need to build.
Your own layers, like image layers, Docker
image layers on top of the standard image.
I would always start from the like
standard Postgres, like the official
Postgres image, and then just keep
adding and installing the extensions.
the alternative is that there is
some magic and we'll get to that
in, later on in the presentation,
magic that I really um, the.
Other thing that I find very important, is
to keep an eye on, on, on your versions.
we all know that Postgres versions
can be complicated, especially when
you do major upgrades, and you have to
run something like pgMigrate, but that
is always an issue because you have.
To have both Postgres versions,
the version you're running on
right now and the version you're
wanting to go to PG 15 and PG 17.
that is true when the data file
format actually changed and
you have to run a migration.
for those kinds of things, various.
Two things to consider, as I
said, first of all, you need both
versions of Postgres in your image.
And secondly, you need to
double the storage because
that is not an in place update.
It's actually a copy operation.
So it copies the database in the
new format to a different location.
keep that in mind because for
a while we'll actually double
your storage requirements.
and for Kubernetes versions,
it's the same thing.
it's.
It can be complicated if you use
like a hosted managed Kubernetes,
like AKS or EKS or whatever.
they often only support like
the last three or four versions.
And I think, Kubernetes provides a
new version like every three months.
After a year, you're out of support.
AWS just recently started to provide
extended Kubernetes support, which I
think goes up to five or six versions.
the second you switch from
Kubernetes to extended Kubernetes,
you're paying 10 times the price.
So invest that money slightly better
into somebody can actually help you
with the migration of Kubernetes.
So that means at least
once a year or something.
Around that timeframe you're
in for a Kubernetes upgrade.
keep that in mind.
if you run your own hosted
Kubernetes, you can get around that.
I would not recommend that.
There's a lot of cool stuff that
comes in new Kubernetes versions,
especially related to storage.
So I would.
Try to keep them up and
running as, much as possible.
All right.
So now that we have all of that out
of the way, and there were already
some hints, what is really different?
where do we have to put our thoughts
when running Postgres and Kubernetes?
And the first and most
important one is storage, right?
we heard that people think storage
will kill you because it's too slow.
in Kubernetes, you have the
idea of persistent volumes.
and persistent volume is basically
your virtual storage entity, your unit,
whatever it is, it could be backed by NFS.
It could be backed by local volumes.
As I said, I think they are a bad idea.
Don't do it.
they could be backed by a remote storage.
they could be backed by Amazon
EBS or cloud disk or whatever.
there, there's a lot of options
how to get storage into Kubernetes.
the good thing is, Kubernetes for.
a couple of years now has the CSI
interface, which is the CSI stands
for Container Storage Interface.
It was designed as a pluggable
storage API for, for Kubernetes.
But what it became is that it's now
like a more Container Storage Interface.
Standardized container interface.
a lot of container runtime
supported, Docker supports it.
container D supports, cryo supports it.
Not all providers support all backends.
but I think that is just a matter of time.
but for Kubernetes, CSI
drivers are the way to go.
Make sure your CSI driver supports
encryption address, right?
You remember, always encrypt stuff.
make sure you find something
which is high IOPS.
NFS might be out of the picture here.
go for SSD and NVMe, like storages, you
want something low latency because we
know databases love fast storage, Postgres
loves storage as fast as possible.
so if you really want to do
something, that's a great solution.
again, I might be biased, but I think.
Disaggregated storage, is the best way.
Disaggregated means that
you basically separate your
storage from your application.
I think this is the only meaningful
thing because databases Tend to grow
more in data size when they tend
to grow in, compute power, right?
new queries might introduce a higher
overhead for compute, especially
stuff like reports and things.
if you have something like that,
especially running reports, I would
recommend, using a CSI provider
that can take snapshots and clones.
and spin up a second database on the
data, on the cloned data, and run your
report on that, throw it away afterwards.
that would be my approach.
But because there is so many, CSI
drivers already, I found about 150 and
that is not all, there's way more out
there, but because it is so complicated
to figure out what I actually want.
I built a while ago, I built like
storage class info, that lists all of
the CSI drivers that I found and what
the features I think they support.
it's really hard to read the code
because not all give you all the
information in their documentation.
So you basically look for every single
source code and try to figure out what
they actually support and whatnot.
if you use something and you
find an issue, please raise.
A bug report.
it's a massive YAML file on,
on, GitHub, raise an issue.
I'm happy to fix it.
but what it gives you is like the
option to, to filter, the CSI drivers
by, capabilities by life cycle,
by access mode, stuff like that.
So storage class info, CSI
drivers is the way to go for you.
the other thing is, and I hinted
at that containers, containers
have requests, limits, and
quarters in, in Kubernetes, but.
Are different elements, request,
they all kind of manage resources or
available resource for your database.
they're not necessarily
easy to understand.
And from my perspective, that is
one of the things where you really
have to wrap your head around.
It's not, it's, as I said, it's not easy.
so there's a great beginner's
guide, by Ketamite.
read it, try to understand it.
It was one of the things that
took me the longest to really.
Wrap my head around.
What is the difference
between requests and limits?
What are quotas?
But in general, if you have a
sizable database, Just make sure,
or I would actually recommend just
running the database basically as the
only thing on those specific notes.
we'll get back to that later.
but, that is something you really have
to understand when you're in the world,
even for stuff like Docker, but with
Docker it's slightly different, right?
Normally you use Docker on a single node.
Kubernetes is all about, clusters.
and multiple instances.
So make sure you have that in your
mind and you'll remember pages really
enable YouTube pages for Postgres.
and I said, it's a little bit more
complicated with Kubernetes because
you actually have to configure
it in the host operating system.
So yeah, you have to go into
the Kubernetes host, like the
worker nodes itself, and say,
yes, I want YouTube pages.
tell the kernel about it.
And my recommendation is tell the kernel
also that you want to have a certain
amount of memory, reserved for huge pages,
because then the kernel at boot time will,
reserve a huge chunk of memory just for
you, like a continuous chunk of memory,
and that is what you want for huge pages.
Huge pages are a great thing to
minimize memory, allocation overhead.
The thing with Kubernetes is that
you actually have to configure
it basically three times.
So you have to configure it in
your host operationing system.
You have to tell the, in the
deployment descriptor, in the
resource descriptor, that this
part or this container specifically
is supposed to use huge pages.
So you get access to them because
they basically have to be mapped
into your container around
time or container environment.
And.
Tell Postgres that there is
each pages available, right?
great read from the Percona guys.
people that are much more
knowledgeable in running massive
Postgres Kubernetes, set up.
So those are the guys to ask.
Then there is high availability.
And, as I said, Kubernetes
is all about clusters.
So it's really something
you want to look into.
and I think it's important, right?
now that we have Kubernetes, the
only meaningful thing is to run.
Postgres as a cluster and I
personally have Massive, like
good experience with Patroni.
I think Patroni is awesome.
I think it's also the most deployed,
a high available, high availability
and sorry, and cluster manager, but
there's also rep manager and, PG
out of failover and stuff like that.
just make sure you use a cluster manager.
you want automatic failover.
You want to have.
Primary, promotion, stuff like that.
there's a great set of tools.
I would always recommend
just going with Patroni.
the most interesting thing about
Patroni for me specifically was
that it is developed by Zalando.
Zalando to me was.
a company selling shoes
and clothes, right?
Stuff like that.
it was not necessarily like a high
tech company, but what I figured out
is that basically all of the database
setup at Zalando, is Postgres.
And so it makes sense.
We're pretty deep into
the Postgres ecosystem.
the other thing, and that is one of
the things again, that you can't really
stress enough connection pooling.
I would claim never run Postgres
without connection pooling at all.
connection pooling is basically
a proxy in between your
database and your application.
And the reason you want that is
because Postgres really doesn't like
connections being opened and closed.
connection management is very expensive.
in Postgres, so using a connection pool
or keeping connect back end connections
to the database open, while, having
the option to the front to give to
the clients and say, Hey, just do
whatever you want is, removing a lot
of overhead or resource utilization
from Postgres stuff that shouldn't
really be in Postgres at all, right?
Um, the other thing is.
When you go into the cloud,
especially when you go for like
serverless, environments and
serverless, infrastructures or
application architectures, now
it really becomes a thing, right?
you're starting and stopping functions.
on a second basis.
And now imagine I said, as I said,
Postgres doesn't like connections being
open and close, but if you start your
function and you close it down, you're
opening a connection, you're closing it.
at that point, you really want
to go into connection pooling.
So in general, if you don't use
connection pooling now or as of
now is the time to, to fix that,
schedule a maintenance for tomorrow.
but there's a couple of more things
it actually, together with something
like Petroni, connection poolers
really nicely handle fail overs.
They handle the switching of primaries.
Your application doesn't
need to know about stuff.
they often support like an,
an internal retries of stuff
fails for the first iteration.
They just switch over and go back.
All of that kind of stuff is really nice.
Um, and only give you
like the error afterwards.
But, on the other hand, it also
handles, the read replica setup.
if you have read replicas and
you say, okay, I want to use
those as actual query targets.
all of those tools support
reading from read replicas.
I personally prefer, and I know
it's controversial, PGPool2.
but there's also PGBouncer.
just make sure not everything that
looks like a read only query like
a select query, might actually be
non mutating, with timescale, we
have, create hyper table, which is a
mutating operation, but because it's
a function, it's called by select.
So sometimes you have to tell those
proxies, hey, those are operations,
or those are queries we specifically
want to send to the client.
to the, primary, for write operations.
then you have, Kubernetes features.
We're in Kubernetes, so use
stateful sets, use replica sets.
all that kind of stuff.
Interestingly enough, Timescale
just a week or two ago, promoted, or
released a blog post about how they
removed stateful set with the new
abstraction because stateful sets
are very limited in what they can do.
so go and read that one.
you can find it on the timescale block.
You really want to see that.
then network policies,
you remember, right?
Use network policies that there's
TLS, enable it as much as possible.
Use security policies.
If your setup has role based
access control, that's something
you really want to set up as well.
think about policy managers, various
OPA, the open policy agent, various
Kubernetes, be careful with those.
I would recommend thinking about those.
They're basically sitting in between like
your API client and the Kubernetes API.
and they can prevent stuff like,
Hey, there's some container
that wants to mount a volume.
but it's not one of the
database containers.
so you really want to prevent that, right?
You don't want to have, potentially
arbitrarily injected container,
running, mounting your database volume.
The only problem is, I heard
that at least about Kubernetes.
you want to be careful.
Kubernetes has the, Default of preventing
all access, which we're blocking
all access, which sounds meaningful.
but at least for that person, Coverno,
the Converno containers itself died.
and they couldn't restore it because
Coverno didn't have access to be.
Kubernetes APIs in order to
be Kubernetes APIs anymore.
So there can be problems.
be careful.
then there is, observability and
I think our alerting, make sure
that you have a good monitoring
observability tool in place.
unfortunately for, Postgres, Prometheus
is still the best thing we have.
I hope that this will change in the
future, but it does an okay job.
collect locks, make sure that your
locks are actually, More than, I don't
know, like a gigabyte or the last
10, 000 entries or stuff like that.
If you have an issue, 10, 000
lines of lock messages might
be over really fast, right?
So use one of the tools, the
typical, lock collection tools,
aggregate, analyze, trace.
I would always go for full observability.
You remember I work for Instana,
and, observability basically
gives you an insight into the
whole stack from front to back.
that means don't roll your own.
you might've figured it.
I'm not a big fan of
rolling your own stuff.
use a tool like Datadoc.
I'm not sure about Instana
as it was acquired by IBM.
these days, most of the
development goes to IBM technology,
but there is other things.
There's Steinertrace.
There's New Relic.
There's Grafana.
There's I don't know what
else, use one of those tools.
you're in for a good game.
and then is the point where all
of that comes together, right?
Like the little bit of okay,
here we are, with Postgres.
We have to configure a lot of stuff.
We need to make sure that
we have high availability.
our backups are set up.
we need, automatic failover.
we all need all that kind of stuff.
and while Helm charts are okay, they
are a static setup system, right?
So Helm charts help you with
the initial, static, deployment.
They don't help you with the
day by day operation setup.
And that is where operators
in general come in.
Kubernetes operators, in this
case, specifically a Postgres
Kubernetes operators, they take
away a lot of the tasks for setup.
They make sure that everything runs,
they make sure that, you can scale
out, scale in, they bring this like
feeling of cloud native to Postgres.
Whereas that's a little
bit of a far fetched thing.
And when we see that in the last slide,
but it integrates Postgres really nice
with Kubernetes, where that is also.
Depending on the operator.
So there is a few operators
and that's not all of them.
if you're, but I think
those are like the big ones.
if you're in for a very
old version, like 9.
6, you're, there's no way
around QDB, the other ones
don't even support that anymore.
Zalando again, from my perspective,
CloudNativePG and StackRest
from Ungrost are the ways to go.
those are like the big new.
Commerce or upcomers from my perspective.
we see that all of these standard
features are all supported where it
falls apart a little bit is backups.
And that is something I
really find confusing.
we're all about.
automation in Kubernetes, but Crunchy
and Zalando don't really support
Kubernetes which, backups, which are
nicely integrated into Kubernetes.
I think that's an oversight, might be
fixed in the future, but it's confusing.
the other thing, that I think
are, is important, use, that they
use a default Postgres image,
like the official standard image.
Cloud Native PG doesn't actually do this.
so I'm a little bit confused about that.
you see that stack rest is the only
one that has all the check marks.
If you really need a web UI, I
think that's up to you or to decide.
but as I said, cloud native PG stack
rest, both are great solutions.
both are great options.
very simple.
Absolutely nothing to say
anything against them.
The only things Dekris
has like a cool feature.
You remember the magic for image layers?
they can, they actually have a virtual
image repository where they take the
standard image and then you say, Hey, I
want this extension and this extension.
They spin up virtual image layers
with the extension code, on the fly.
And that even works at runtime.
You can say, Hey, I want this.
And it magically appears in your
image and you can just load it.
but again, There's more people
that actually wrote about that.
in this case, I actually wrote the
first one, but there's Operator Hub.
anything Kubernetes operators,
that's your, first, way to go.
And the, data on Kubernetes community,
created a massive Postgres specification,
operator specification with all
features for Postgres and, and
operators and how they are supported.
And I think there's over 30,
Postgres operators in there.
So you really want to look into that.
It doesn't have a nice UI yet,
but we're working on that.
the last thing, when you have a meaningful
size database, so anything that needs to
scale, make sure that you use dedicated
machines for your databases, use, node
pools, dedicate a certain set of nodes
in an, or dedicate a node pool to
your database, to your primary and to
reach replicas, make sure that those.
containers or the database containers are
pinned to those hosts, taint the hosts
so that nothing else is running in it,
at it except like the standard Kubernetes
services like kube, kube proxy and stuff.
but that's about it, right?
Make sure your database has
basically all the resources and
use Kubernetes for automation, for
orchestration, Not for virtualization
in the sense of over provisioning.
I think your database still deserves
as much resources as possible.
so with that, I think we're at the end.
A lot of you might know Kelsey Hightower.
I normally say when Kelsey
speaks, the world listens.
And Kate Kelsey had a few things to say
about Postgres or databases on Kubernetes,
which is you can run a database on
Kubernetes because it's fundamentally
the same as running a database on a VM.
okay.
So far, so good.
Oh, we can do that.
The biggest challenge is to understand
that rubbing Kubernetes on Postgres
won't magically turn it into Cloud SQL.
So what he's saying is just because
Postgres now runs on Kubernetes, it
doesn't mean it gives you this, Proclaimed
infinite scalability of something like
Cloud SQL or Aurora or stuff like that.
You're getting close and you can
scale out, with the necessary,
correct storage underneath.
You can get very far, but I also say
most people or most companies probably
don't need something like Cloud SQL.
It's a very overhyped, unnecessary thing.
From my perspective, it makes
stuff easy to get started.
I would claim this is
not where we need to go.
Anyway, the data on Kubernetes
community is, anything data,
stateful workloads on Kubernetes.
it's mostly like a lot of the people
that initially started implementing
stateful workloads on Kubernetes and
the stateful set and a state stuff
like that, they eventually, joined
together in the, doc, community.
they wrote an amazing.
white paper on data on Kubernetes,
read it, go with that, and
that's it, thank you very much.