Hello, my name is Elena Budding.
I am CEO of a Pop Finance.
This is learning platform for SM business.
So today we're talking about
the future of Internet of Things
and CM integration, enabling
proactive customer service for SMS.
on the one side, internet of
Things provides real time data
from devices enabling insights into
customer behavior and product usage.
And CRM system use this data to
automate alerts, schedule maintenance,
or resolve issues proactively.
For example, we have smart home
devices triggering service calls
before users notice an issue.
What's benefits for SME is open.
So on the cost safe, this is
definitely predictive maintenance
prevents expensive, downtime.
On the customer retention, proactive
service increases satisfaction.
Personalization.
Internet of Things data tailors offers
and communications to individual needs.
Efficiently, automated workflow
reduces manual interventions.
In retail, we have inventory
management using connected
shelves and automated reordering.
Healthcare, wearables sending real
time health data to alert physicians.
Manufacturing, predictive maintenance
for equipment to reduce downtime.
Which key technologies we have?
first, from one side of Internet
of Things platform, we have
Amazon Web Services, Azure.
Internet of Things Hub, Google Clouds,
and so on, on the Cerium side, Salesforce,
HubSpot, Microsoft Dynamics, with
the Internet of Things integration.
We challenge the open, from data
privacy, ensuring compliance with a
regulation like GDPR, on the security
risk preventing breaches from connected
devices, infrastructure cost, investments
in device networks, and software.
Data management, processing and
integrating large Internet of
Things datasets into CRM systems.
Which best practice we have?
to effectively implement Internet
of Things CRM integration, first
of all, start with a scalable
and modular solutions that can
grow with needs of your SME.
Ensure robust security measures
are in place to protect Internet
of Things devices and CRM
data from potential breaches.
Thank you.
Invest in employee training to help
teams officially manage Internet
of Things and CRM workflows.
Regular audits of data privacy
and compliance standards are
essential to maintain trust and
meet regulatory requirements.
All these steps collectively
ensure a secure, efficient, and
future ready IoT CRM ecosystem.
what's in the future?
AI PowerSRM, machine learning
to analyze Internet of Things
data and predict customer needs.
Real time data streaming, instant
updates for smarter decision making.
Predictive analytics, anticipating
customer issue and addressing
them before they escalate.
In conclusion, Internet of Things
and CRM integration enables Susemi
to offer proactive, personalized
customer service by harnessing real
time data from connected devices.
This approach drives key benefits,
including enhanced efficiency, reduced
costs, and improved customer retention.
While changing, such as data security
and system complexity, persist,
advancement in technology and innovation.
adherence to best practice
provide scalable and pathway
to successful implementation.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.