Hello everyone.
Myself Sai Krishna Paladugu.
I'm a senior iOS developer.
So today my topic is revolutionizing
contactless kiosk integration
with iOS mobile devices.
So everybody in the mobile world
and day to day life, mobile
devices are more important.
So they are playing a very
vital role in everybody's life.
so how we can use this.
For a nice applications where in the
industrial purpose and in a retail
purpose and transportation purpose
there are so many purposes these iOS
devices are useful when we deploy
into the customer facing world.
So these can be powerful contactless
solutions where we go with the
technologies like NFC, Bluetooth, QR code.
So scanning, all the QR codes or
any barcodes, these are all like
touch free interactions for kiosk.
So basically my presentation covers
the key features and also use cases
of iOS based contactless kiosk.
So let me go to the first slide.
So the NFC technology.
So mostly this is very secure one.
So where customer can tap to pay.
It is a seamless interaction.
So where we use the iPhones.
So it's a payment integration, the
framework, which is provided by
Apple that we can embed into the
native iOS app and where can process
these transactions as a touch free.
So this is how we were developed.
And, this is.
So much helpful for the current all the
outside industries so the digital tick
ticketing it's mostly the cinema theaters
and also the the flight Booking and flight
tickets retrieving the flight tickets
using the all this digital ticketing So
where nfc is enabled for quick validation
and access control users can Store
and present digital tickets on their
devices So and also the third one is a
secure authentication nfc technologies
allows secure For user authentication.
This is crucial for personalized
services and data protection so These
are all the three key main features
that is enabled for nfc technologies.
It's a seamless transactions So
next one is the powerful one.
It's a bluetooth where it is a proximity
based service Where we can embed with the,
iOS apps, how iOS apps can be used with
the iOS devices like iPhones and iPads.
So automated check in.
The Bluetooth can trigger automatic
check ins as a user approach.
The kiosk, this streamlines the user
experience and reduce wait times.
It is, it helps automatic check ins.
User can come and check in for their
appointments at the doctor's office
or anywhere, which is applicable
for a check in of the customer.
So personalized greetings, another one.
Kiosk can display a personal
greeting based on user proximity.
This enhances customer
engagement and service quality.
If user wants.
The specific users want the specific
personalized messages where they can
check in and based on the customer
preference and customer, data, it will
be shown the customer, custom greetings.
So location based offers the bluetooth
enables the delivery of a location
specific promotions This increase the
relevance and potential sales conversions.
So basically, in a shopping mall, the
customers are roaming around and, they
can use their mobile and use the iOS app.
To see the location based, offers based on
some Fuma store or Adidas or Under Armour.
So wherever if they push something, they
can easily see based on their location.
So this is something more interesting
when we use a location based services, so
this is a powerful for a sales standpoint
for in a retail, customers like it,
it attracts a lot for the customers.
so that is why I call it as a Bluetooth
is also a powerful technology where we
can embed in with, this kiosk and also
we can use for, iOS mobile apps as well.
the other things, the barcode scanning.
So this is also major, major
significant impact on the current
market, where people are using QR
codes to retrieve their labels.
And, in the transportation, like if
example, like a FedEx or UPS or any
other stores, the the customer coming
with the third party retailer QR
code, they can scan their QR code and
get their label and stick on their
package and send it to the, retailer.
So this is something very unique and
they don't need to print at their home.
And they just come in with the email
where they can see their, unique QR
code for their, return shipments.
So this is absolutely a good
practice for the customer.
It is a hassle free.
So scan, scanning their QR codes
using that initiation, initiating
the shipment labels and all.
So it is a scan.
Another thing is a process.
The process, how that takes place.
The software process, the scan
information that will send to the
backend, like retrieving their data.
Specific to the customer and they
will get the, significant, whatever
the alignment of the product that,
that is lined up with the retailer.
So another thing is
third one is a respond.
The kiosk provides appropriate response
and services based on the scan.
This could include displaying
information and processing transactions
respective to the customer.
So these three steps, Are common for
the QR code and barcode scanning.
So where self serve kiosks are integrated
with Scanners and also the printers the
scanners are capable to scan the barcodes
and QR codes And, yeah, these features
are very helpful, even go to the Walmart
and any of the, the Kroger or any of the
marketplaces, the daily life, these are
all self service are increasing a lot.
so manual becomes automation.
So this is so much.
So much useful for the current,
current anybody in the customer market.
So apple pay integration.
So this is one of the groundbreaking
feature from the apple.
So where I was mobile devices
running on the native app where we
can embed this framework to process
the secure transactions, biometric
authentication, and wide acceptance.
So the Apple Pay transactions are
very secure and ensures encrypted
and also tokenized transactions.
This protects user data and
prevents fraud in kiosk payments.
So the Bluetooth and the And bluetooth is
something is different and where apple pay
Integration is more far advanced right now
for any payment Gateways the face id and
touch id add an extra layer for a security
user can authenticate payments quickly and
security So wide acceptance so the apple
pay is widely accepted across industries
this makes ideal for diverse kiosk
applications so Custom apps for kiosk.
So tailored user interface, backend
integration, multi-language support.
So custom apps offer in and brand
specific interfaces, this enhanced
user experience and reinforce brand
identity, the backend integration.
So these systems are integrated
with, CRM, customer Reporting
Management and ER Pation, program.
these systems can be, equip
from the backend to the kiosk.
Kiosk can get this real time data to
synchronization and smooth operations.
So multi language support.
Custom apps can offer
multiple language options.
This improves accessibility and
caters to diverse user base.
So if something, most, if some locations
where, Spanish speakers are involved
and where english is a common language
So we can enable the spanish for the
based on the customer base so that they
can do their operations So this will be
helpful for the any type of the customers.
So language barriers are no Longer,
stops for kiosk, so it will be a good
approach So these custom ios solutions
are Specific to the market if it is a
retail market is something different
and it is a transportation market.
It is a different and it is a air travel.
It is something different.
it is based on the You know the customer
and how they want to you know process
their Transactions are there, whatever
it is a shipments what we can call it's
a products or whatever So that is very
feasible for developing using i west
based kiosk So in retail use, product
in retail use basically every product
Has their own skew and the barcode
and And also a skilling unit number.
So in product, in the retail use, mostly
the, the customers go with the products
browsing, price checking, self checkout.
So especially in a product browsing,
they can search with the name of the
product and, from the store inventory.
so that they can discover the
product and the customer wants.
So it is very easy, easy without,
going to the, sales representative
or whoever inside the store.
it is easy to know the self service kiosk.
You can get the price.
Even they can scan their barcode of
the product and they can easily get the
price and availability this reduce the
need for a staff assistance So so the
if it is a hundred one fifty customers
inside the store And they are just two
or three assistants inside the store.
It is tough to handle everybody So these
self serve kiosks can help a lot during
that time So so in self checkout the
contactless payments by apple pay enable
Quick Self checkouts, this reduce the
queues and improves customer satisfaction.
The self checkout is
more important nowadays.
every business is integrating
a self checkout nowadays.
So it is very useful.
So in a retail market, the kiosks
are also playing a vital role.
So healthcare use cases.
So the future digital check in.
So I talked about already.
This is reduce the wait
time and paper use.
So if it is, if you go to a lab,
So the lab inside, there are a few
technicians and more people are
outside and they can do their stuff.
it is hard to, serve all the
customers, with more efficient way.
so the digital chickens will help
and they can check out and they
can just call the name, whoever
in the queue for the next service.
Appointment scheduling same thing
they can reschedule and also they can
come and do on their self without,
waiting for the Representative there.
So the bill payments also streamline
financial transactions and
reduce administration workload.
It is also More important, for you know
without going to the representatives,
customer can do on their own It
is easy stuff In healthcare, also,
encouraging more for kiosk development.
This has to definitely has to come
a lot, in the pandemic situation,
people mostly used it contactless
and touch free interactions.
Those are all significant in fact,
importance in the healthcare,
especially than other sectors.
So definitely healthcare kiosks and, IOS.
enabled are more powerful than
any other devices integrations.
transportation use case.
in the check in, I already talked,
some of the information before.
here is a passenger check in and a
boarding pass and gate information.
This is where, in the transpo in
the transportation industry, it is
something different than here, where
they can check in and, boarding pass.
and get information.
So this is something like in air travel.
So the passenger can check in with
their QR codes and their devices
speeds up the boarding process.
So digital boarding passes are
generated and stored on iOS devices.
It eliminates the need of a paper tickets.
So definitely these
things are a very helpful.
So if customer forgot their boarding
pass or everything, they'll, this, the
last, during the, in the hurry, buddy,
last minute, to the, to get to the board.
So it is easy.
It will show all the gate
information, real time updates.
if some gates are changing or
departure times are changing or
any passenger information or,
Passenger information are incorrect.
Everything will be on your digital
Pass so in transportation industry
also kiosks are very helpful And if you
want to add a bag and you don't need
to go to the counter and you can add
yourself We're just paying using Apple
Pay or any of the payment gateways.
You can do it by manual So you can just
download the tag and you just attach the
tag and just check in your luggage so it
definitely, this is also a good, place, in
the transportation industry, kiosk usage.
mostly nowadays the, airports are
more busier after the pandemic.
So definitely the kiosk has to increase
more in, in the airline industry as well.
So hospitality use cases, so
digital room keys, digital
concierge, and express ticket.
So guests can be, use their iOS
devices as their room keys, this
enhance security and convenience.
So in the hotels, some of the hotels, they
introduced, they are sharing their, the
wallet, yeah, they're sharing the token
to the wallet and it will be a created,
one pass and where you can use the pass
to, get into the, your room, hotel room.
the kiosk offers restaurant
recommendations and booking services,
improves guest experience and,
increases revenue opportunities.
the express checkouts.
I covered already some contactless
payments that are quick and,
easy checkout and reduces front
desk use and improves efficiency.
These are also secure, secure
payments and, seamless transactions.
So in hospitality also, there are a lot
of, significant, importance in for kiosks.
So feature of iOS kiosks.
This is very interesting.
So AI, everybody knows, so
artificial intelligence.
So once this is came into the picture,
iOS can incorporate with a advanced
AI and personalized interaction.
This will enhance user experience
and productive services.
this is very advanced, topic and,
definitely need more research, what
needs for the customer and what
are the limitations that we can,
commit while developing the kiosk.
So another thing, augmented reality,
this feature will include immersive
product demonstration and navigation.
This will revolutionize detail
and informational kiosk.
So IOT connectivity, kiosk will
seamlessly integrate with IOT devices.
This will enable.
comprehensive smart environment
control and monitoring.
So now every home has their smart sensors
and every, home has a different sensors
and for heating and HVAC control and also
the light, lights and fans and everything.
it is equipped with a smart home.
the sensors are everywhere.
It is keeping connecting with the iOS
devices and also we can see the cameras
also can be connected to the, iOS
devices and where we can, remotely see
and somewhere we travel also we can see
what's happening in front of our house.
so these iOS devices are, so much
importance in the daily life.
yeah, this is all, mostly covered.
thank you everyone and,
thanks for the opportunity.
And, yeah, the Internet Things 2024.
it is very a great, place where,
sharing the insights and, Yeah,
thanks you once again for thanks
once again for the opportunity and
conference 42 internet of things.
Thanks everybody for joining today.
Thank you.