This is Rajesh Kugila, I am going
to talk about, transforming bulk
oil and gas logistics with IOT,
leveraging, ISOIL TSW for digital
innovation and operational efficiency.
thanks for joining me today.
Here are the things, we are going
to discuss the table of contents of,
this, ISOIL TSW, industry context and
challenges, introduction to, ISOIL
TSW, core functionality of, TSW,
quantitative impact, alignment with
the industry trends, benefits of ISOIL
TSW, case study, operational impact,
feature outlook, and conclusion.
So here we will discuss about the industry
challenges in oil and gas industry.
The oil and gas logistics
landscapes of the global oil and
gas industry is valuated at 3.
3 trillions as of 2023.
Inefficiency in logistics can lead to
substantial financial losses, affecting
probability, sorry, profitability.
A mid sized refinery processing 250, 000
barrels per day, valuated at 20 million.
a daily can incur massive losses from
delays or errors increasing Reliance
on automation and integration to
manage complex multimodal logistics
so introduction to isr tsw So what
is, I-S-R-T-S-W, what are the core
functionalities, that TSW offers?
So we'll discuss here.
the, ISR, traders and s is an advanced
logistics management software.
this basically, will use it for the
nomination and ticketing in the.
Soil, bulk product movement.
So the core functionalities includes,
nomination management for product
scheduling, electronic ticketing for
accurate documentation, multi modal
transport systems, it's also support
multiple multi modal transport system
like rail, pipeline, and marine,
and inventory reconciliation to
prevent discrepancies, integration
with the terminal invoicing system.
Designed to streamline bulk sales,
purchases, and transfers with
unmatched accuracy and speed.
The core functionalities of DSW
are key features and capabilities.
Nomination management, ticketing
system, multi modal support,
inventory, reconciliation.
we'll discuss, detail about
the nomination management.
the nomination management, basically
it's a scheduling, tool for the,
bulk, refined, crude products.
Either as a purchase a sale or transfer.
So in real time updates and coordinates
across the stakeholders So the nomination
management system it's real time updates
and coordinates across the stakeholders
Hinders high transaction value.
So the scalability and the ticketing
system of the automated ticketing
system reduced Documentation errors
by 95 percent and supports processing
of up to 10, 000 daily tickets.
Multimodal support.
Unifield logistics management
for rail, pipeline, and marine.
The inventory consolidation
achieves 99 percent reduction
in Inventory discrepancies.
We will discuss here the quantitative
impact of TSW on operations.
So error reduction, 95 percent reduction
in documentation errors, efficiency
gains, processes up to 10, 000 daily
tickets, inventory accuracy, 1 percent
improvement, translates to 1 million in
annual savings for midsize refineries.
Reconstruction time reduced by 60
percent enabling faster decisions making
invoice processing time reduced by 70
percent improving financial efficiency.
So alignment with the industry
trends, here are the industrial
trends driving automation and
integration, automation technologies,
integration technologies, TSW role.
So automation technologies market
value projected to grow to 22.
1 billion by 2027 Enhances safety reduces
human errors and boosts productivity by
up to 25 integration technologies cloud
applications market expected to reach 10.
9 billion by 2027 tsw role integrates
seamlessly with the existing inventory and
invoicing system reducing reconciliation
and processing time significantly
Benefits of, ISR TSW, the business
benefits, enhanced accuracy, improved
efficiency, better visibility,
regulatory compliance, cost reduction.
So enhanced accuracy reduces human
errors, improving reliability in
operations, and improved efficiency
enables teams to manage more
transactional with less effort.
Better visibility, real time
updates reduce inventory holding
cost by up to 15 percent.
Regulatory compliance minimizes compliance
risk reducing associated cost by 30 to 50%
cost reduction optimizes logistics process
achieving significant cost savings.
Here's the case study for the
operational impact, the TSW in action.
A midsized refinery processing two
50,000 barrels per day requests a
robust logistics solution to overcome
inefficiency in scheduling, ticketing,
and reconciliation improvements.
Improvements achieved with the TSW
inventory reconciliation reduces to.
30 minutes and 10 saved per ticket
with the electronic ticketing.
Real time visibility enhances decision
making and reduces operational delays.
Shaping the future of,
oil and gas logistics.
Digital transformation goals, unlock 2.
5 trillion in value by 2030
through efficiency and automation.
technology adoption trends, greater
reliance on AI, cloud technologies,
and sustainability focused solutions.
And TSW's role in the future.
Continued evolution to meet rising
demands for faster, smarter, and more
sustainable logistics and solutions
is the conclusion of ISOIL TSW, the
ISOIL Traders and Traders Workbench.
is revolutionizing bulk logistics
management in the oil and gas sector
by driving automation, integration,
and operational excellence.
It addresses critical industry
challenges, ensuring accuracy,
efficiency, And complaints while
reducing cost as the industry evolves.
TSW provides the tools necessary to
stay competitive and sustainable.
Join us in transforming
oil and gas logistics.
Contact us today to explore implementation
opportunities and partnerships.
Let us shape a smarter and
more efficient future together.
Thank you.