Hello, everyone, and thank you
for joining today's session.
My name is Siraj.
We'll be exploring how containerization
and Kubernetes have transformed
the way we develop, deploy,
manage applications in the cloud.
This talk is especially important in the
context of IOT, where number of devices is
exploding, data volumes are skyrocketing.
We'll see how these technologies
tackle scaling challenges, improve
efficiency, and enable rapid innovation,
both in traditional IT environment.
And the edge where IoT devices operate.
Let's get started.
we'll, discuss briefly
about the containerization.
what it means is like it packages
an application code, libraries,
and all dependencies together.
Ensuring it runs the same way
across different environment,
development, testing, production.
Think of container as a sealed
box that includes everything
your app needs to function.
For IoT, this means software running
on edge devices or gateways can
be developed and tested on laptop,
then deployed confidently in the
field without compatibility issues.
Popular tools include
Docker, Podman, and CRM.
So, like there are definitely a lot
of advantages using containerization.
the first one would be the portability.
it helps us to move from on premises setup
to cloud or edge environment effortlessly.
And next is consistency.
the application environment is identical
everywhere, reducing it works on.
My machine problem.
What it means is like
before containerization.
The problem was like, once a developer
developed any software, so it was
working fine on his machine, but not
on the real production environment.
So the reason was there might be
some mismatch in the libraries.
So all those kind of issues will
not happen here in dockerite
or in containerization.
And obviously they are lightweight.
Okay.
So they can start within seconds,
enable quick updates and scaling, and
coming to the scalability, it is easy,
easily spin up more containers to handle
additional load from surge in IoT sensors
data during peak time, like festival
or sporting event in the smart city.
These benefits help IoT deployment evolve.
rapidly without sacrificing
stability or performance.
So now, as as the containers are growing,
as the applications are growing, the
containers as well growing, right?
So we need something to
manage those containers.
That's where Kubernetes come into play.
So Kubernetes is the
orchestration layer that automates
managing containers at scale.
It schedules, scales and maintain the
health of containerized application.
Removing a lot of manual overhead.
For IoT scenarios, Kubernetes can
coordinate multiple services from
data ingestion at the edge to
centralized analytics, ensuring that
if one component fails, another is
automatically restarted or replaced.
Key features include self healing,
horizontal scaling based on
demand, And built in load balancing
in the cloud.
Kubernetes simplifies orchestration.
Imagine trying to manage
thousands of containers by hand.
It's error prone and time consuming.
Kubernetes automates scaling
up and down as devices.
As device numbers fluctuate, ensures
resilience if hardware fails,
work across different providers.
For IoT data pipelines, Kubernetes can run
analytics workload in different regions
or clouds, preventing vendor lock in.
This flexibility is crucial as
IoT deployments scale globally.
So yeah, let's discuss, innovation
driven by containerization.
So the first one is
microservice architecture.
Instead of large application, we'll
break it into the small focus on services
in iot that mean, that might mean
separate services for data ingestion,
separate service for pre-processing,
and machine learning, inter interface.
And efficient resource use.
What it means is multiple services share
the same infrastructure without conflicts.
Crucial for resource
constrained edge environment.
and it helps in DevOps enablement.
Rapid and continuous integration
and deployment pipelines keep
IoT software updated and secure.
And it quickly test new IOT, it help
us to like, definitely quickly test
and deploy IOT features like anomaly
detection on sensor data without
worrying about environment setup.
So Kubernetes is widely used
across different domains.
Enterprise applications like banks,
healthcare system, retailers rely on
Kubernetes for stable, scalable platforms.
Kubernetes native development.
So startup leverage Kubernetes to
handle millions of concurrent users
and tools like Spark run efficiently
under Kubernetes helping analyze
massive IoT data sets and it helped
in AI and ML pipelines, model training
and interface scale up automatically
as data streams from IoT devices
increases and IoT deployment.
This is key for our audience today.
As IoT devices proliferate, smart
city sensors, industrial robots,
autonomous vehicles, Kubernetes manages
containerized services at scale.
It can autoscale to handle Growth
in connected device and data, bring
processing closer to the edge for faster
response time, essential in real time
IoT scenarios like traffic control.
Efficiently run multiple applications
on the same hardware, saving resources,
enable rolling updates of software on
thousands of devices simultaneously.
Support hybrid and multicloud
strategies to process IoT data where
it makes the most sense on prem.
So let's discuss about a few case studies.
So while not strictly IoT focus, so
let's focus on this Spotify story
shows the power of Kubernetes at scale.
They needed to handle
millions of concurrent users.
By adopting Kubernetes, they transformed
their monolithic setup into microservices.
They gain the agility to roll
out updates faster, improve user
experience, and control costs.
The same principles apply to IoT.
As your device count and data
volumes grow, Kubernetes helps
maintain performance and reliability.
Despite its benefits, Kubernetes
isn't without challenges.
Complexity.
Kubernetes has learning curves.
Engineers need training
to use it effectively.
And for monitoring and debugging,
understanding what's happening in
large IoT ecosystems spread across
edge devices and cloud requires robust
tools like Chrometheus, Grafana.
And coming to the security,
protecting IOT data is critical.
Ensuring containers and
clusters are secure and up
to date is a constant effort.
Cost management.
So scaling too aggressively or running
unused containers can inflate cloud bills.
Careful planning ensures resource
match actual IOT workload.
In a world where number of connected IOT
devices is exploding and data is flowing
from countless sources, containerization
and Kubernetes form a powerful foundation
for managing complexity and scaling,
scaling efficient, effectively.
As IOT systems become more
sophisticated, combining edge
computing, AI and big data analytics,
this technology ensures agility,
resilience and cost effectiveness.
Thanks.
yeah, a small startup experiment
with a small IoT application
and scale it gradually.
upskill your team.
So invest in Kubernetes training
so your engineers can confidently
manage these environments.
So consult with experts.
If you are new to this,
partner with consultants who
can guide your IoT journey.
Adopt best practices like
follow security hardening.
Monitoring and cost optimization
strategies to realize the full
potential of containers and
communities in iot by embracing
containerization and communities.
You propose your iot project for
long term success, handling growth,
innovation, complexity with easy.
for joining me today.
Thanks.