My name is Neetu Gangwani.
Today I'm going to discuss about
enhancing IoT security and privacy
in cloud environments using
blockchain federated learning for
cross cloud trust and compliances.
So let's get started.
In today's world, when we talk about the
technologies and software industries,
everything is dependent on data, whether
you deal with investment banking,
healthcare, or inventory management
systems, or ERPs, or anything else.
So when we talk about the data,
by default, something comes
into our mind, that's the risk.
Whether our data is secure or
not, is it okay to share the data?
Or what are the challenges when we
talk about the privacy and security,
especially when we are dealing
with a distributed AI system.
So to how we can overcome it,
how we can enhance the security.
So let's first discuss the
problem challenges in privacy
and security in distributed AI.
First of all, data sensitivity,
distributed data sets often contain
sensitive personal and organizational
data that cannot be shared or centralized.
We can't share our personal data
with anywhere like we don't want to
share it and other security threats.
AI systems are vulnerable to adversarial
attacks like model poisoning and Sybil
attacks compromising system integrity.
Trust defects, collaboration across
organization or cloud providers, lack
of transparency leading to mistrust in
the AI outputs, regulatory pressures,
stricter data protections law, such
as JDPR, HIPAA, require systems to
ensure privacy and accountability.
So what are the solutions?
So there are other solutions.
We can use a different methodology.
To combine all these things to make the
system more reliable, secure and private.
So first one is a blockchain,
a decentralized leisure,
provide transparency, trust and
immutable for AI model updates.
Another one is federated learning
and enable collaborative model
training without sharing raw
data, maintaining data privacy.
Cloud AI combines the scalability
and efficiency of cloud platform with
privacy and preserving mechanism.
let's just see each and
every terminology in detail.
So first one is a blockchain.
What exactly meaning of the blockchain?
So blockchain is basically a
decentralized distributed ledger
technology that ensure transparency,
immutability, security of the transition.
So it uses the cryptographic technologies
and to create a chain of blocks Each
contains a set of transaction key feature.
Key features include decentralization
with no single entity has
control over the entire network.
Transparency as all transactions are
visible to the network participants
and immutable, making it extremely
difficult to alert recorded data.
So in blockchain, what exactly happens?
For example, user is sending one
sentence and then over the network it
will block, it will create the, it will
break the sentence into the different
blocks and each block will be combined
after receiving by the participant.
And these blocks, have the private keys
and the, and they are getting transferred
by using the different networks.
Next, what is the federated learning?
Federated learning is a machine
learning paradigm that was built by
Google in 2017 that enables training
models to be distributed dataset
without centralizing the data.
In federated learning, multiple
parties collaborate to train AI
shared models while keeping their
data locally, addressing privacy
concerns, regulatory requirements, etc.
The process typically involves central
server coordinating the learning
process, where local models are trained
on individual datasets and only model
updates are shared with the server.
The server then aggregates these updates
to improve the global model, which
is redistributed to the party server.
participants for the
next round of training.
Next, Cloud AI.
Cloud AI refers to artificial intelligence
service and infrastructure provided
through cloud computing platform.
It encompasses A wide range of offering
from pre trained models and API to fully
managed machine learning platforms.
The current landscape is dominated by
major cloud providers offering scalable
AI solution, enabling our organization
to leverage advanced AI capabilities
without significant upfront investment
in the hardware and the expertise.
So what are the key components?
Blockchain, when we combine these two
technology into the framework, we are
getting the multiple and advantages
like decentralized model updates.
Each update is treated as a transaction
enhancing transparency traceability.
So when we record each and every
transaction, who has performed it,
how performed, and these transactions
should be immutable so that user
don't have the rights to remove
it, updated or do any modification.
In the logs, so that's the beauty
of the system moving to the next
one smart contracts Automates
validations and consequences for
model updates, ensuring integrity.
If something is updated at the one place,
the system has to make sure all the copies
are updated with the correct data and
none of the copies have the older data.
Incentive mechanisms reward
high quality data contribution
and prevent system gaming.
Access control cryptographic identity
management ensures only authorized.
Participants contribute.
For example, when you are dealing
with the mobile at that time, either
you use your mobile passcode or
your fingerprints or your face ID.
So these type of, Authentications are
known as the cryptographic identity,
then audit rail, immutable record of
all the interactions for accountability
and the compliances, benefits,
advantage of integrated approach,
enhanced Privacy keeps data localized
while securely sharing model updates.
So whatever the base model you have,
that will be kept on your on prem servers
or the centralized servers without
having the connection with the internet.
Improved trust, immutable records,
build confidence in collaborative AI.
cross cloud interoperability, enables
seamless use of diverse cloud AI
service, resistance to attack, combines
block check consequences and federated
learning, decentralization for robust
security, regulatory compliances,
providing transparency, audit drills to
simplify JDPR and the HIPAA compliance,
potential applications, so there are many.
Many applications where we can
enhance the privacy and security using
blockchain enabled federated learning.
For example, healthcare collaborates
securely on patient data for drug
discovery and personalized treatment.
Finance trained fraud detection
models across institutions without
exposing sensitive transaction data.
Smart cities optimize urban
planning and resource management
with privacy preserving AI models.
Supply chain improves forecasting
and inventory management without
compromising business data.
Age computing enabling AI.
Enable iot devices to collaboratively
train AI model keeping data secure
and localized Comparative advantages
why this approach is stand out.
So first of all is a privacy preservation
Techniques like differential privacy
and homo Homomorphic encryption
prevents sensitive data exposure.
Select scalability layer 2 blockchain
solution handle high transaction
volume and distributed updates.
Regulatory alignment designed
to comply with JDPR, HIPAA
and other global regulations.
Collaboration innovation
incentive structure encourage
multiple party participation
while preventing manipulations.
Challenges and future direction.
Addressing challenges and
unlocking opportunities.
Scalability.
Research efficient algorithms like
sharding to handle high volume
systems with a great response time.
Advanced privacy, implementing secure
computational techniques to prevent,
to protect even aggregated data.
Incentive device, balancing
rewards for data contribution,
introducing, without introducing bias.
Performance optimization, reducing
computational overhead for blockchain
integration in the federated learning.
Governance, exploring DAOs for
decentralized model and version control.
Let's see a case study.
For example, healthcare use care
secure federated learning problem
sharing data across sharing patient
data across hospital is limited due to
privacy concern and regulatory buyers
solution federated learning enable
hospital to train AI models to local
data and blockchain secures model
to ensure the transparency outcome.
Improved diagnostic accelerated drug
discovery and compliances with the
GDPR and the HIPAA conclusion In the
integration of blockchain technology
with the federated learning in cloud
AI environment represents a trans made
transformative step forward in addressing
critical challenges of privacy, security,
and trust in distributed AI systems
while leveraging the dis decentralized
and immutable feature of blockchain
combined with the privacy preserving
capability of federated learning.
This framework enables secure and
collaborative AI model development
without compromising sensitive data.
Organization can now train model across
distributed data set while ensuring
compliances with regulations like
GDPR, HIPAA fostering innovation in
highly regulated industries such as
healthcare, finance, and smart cities.
Thank you.