Hello, everyone.
I'm Nagapaneet Yeram and I'm
thrilled to represent the future of
IOT and Unified Communications, AI
driven connectivity enhancements.
Today, we'll explore how Artificial
Intelligence is revolutionizing
Unified Communications, blending
IOT and AI for seamless intelligent
communication experiences.
Let's dive in.
So let me introduce to
Unified Communications.
So Unified Communications
or shortly known as UC.
It integrates voice, video,
messaging, and collaboration
tools into one cohesive platform.
This enables seamless communication
across devices and teams.
AI takes UC to the next level
by introducing intelligent
automation, real time analytics,
and data driven decision making.
These advances streamline communication
workflows, improve operational efficiency,
and enhance customer engagement.
In today's interconnected world, AI
powered UC is just not an advantage.
It's a necessity.
So here we're going to talk about the
role of AI in enterprise communications.
AI transforms enterprise
communication with powerful features.
Let's start with intelligent call
routing, which uses the data to match
customers with the most suitable agents.
Real time speech recognition
ensures accurate understanding and
transcription of conversations.
Automated transcription services
make documentation seamless.
These AI driven innovations have
led to a 40 percent improvement in
system efficiency and 60 percent
increase in customer satisfaction.
AI's ability to leverage predictive
analysis further optimizes workflows
and elevates user experiences.
Let's learn about the key AI power
enhancements in unified communications.
Here, AI power enhancements in UC
are game changing like never before.
Intelligent call routing improves
first contact resolution by analyzing
customer data and also matching them
with the best resource available.
Speech recognition and transcription are
now available, which are more accurate
than ever, which is really thanks to
deep learning, which enables effortless
handling of complex conversations.
Predictive analysis anticipates
user needs, automation responses,
and streamlining the process.
These capabilities collectively
create a smarter, more
responsive communication system.
Moving on to the next slide, we'll
talk about the performance metrics.
in any organization or any tool, the
performance metrics is really important.
So here is how AI enhanced UC
outperforms traditional systems.
First contact resolution rates jumped from
45 to 80%, while average response times
dropped from 15 minutes to just 9 minutes.
It's a significant drop.
Customer satisfaction scores rise from
65 percent to 85%, and call routing
accuracy improves from 75 percent to 95%.
Even transcription accuracy
increases from 85 to 98%.
These metrics demonstrate the
tangible impact of integrating
AI to unified communication.
So let's talk about industry benefits
and sector specific applications, where
we can use unified communications with
leveraging artificial intelligence.
AI driven UC offers unique benefits
across industries in healthcare,
HIPAA Transcription enhances patient
documentation and workflow efficiency.
Financial services benefit from
improved compliance monitoring
and secure communication.
In manufacturing, AI optimizes
supply chain communication and
enables remote equipment monitoring.
Finally, in retail, AI driven call
management improves customer engagement.
These applications highlight how
AIUC adapts to sector specific needs,
driving innovation and efficiency.
As every technology, we have challenges.
So I want to discuss more about the
challenges in AI and UC integration.
despite its benefits, AIUC
integration comes with challenges.
Technical integration, particularly
with legacy systems, can be complex.
User option often faces resistance.
necessitating proper training and support.
Resource Alliance is another concern,
balancing time and investment for
implementation, training and maintenance.
These challenges require a
strategic approach to ensure
successful deployment and adoption.
So moving on to the next
slide, let's discuss the best
practices for successful A.
I.
U.
C.
Deployment.
So here we can discuss,
three types of challenge.
three types of successful A.
I.
Deployment.
One is the phased implementation
where you can start with the
pilot programs Scale gradually
based on feedback and performance.
And the second one is, and we need
comprehensive training for that.
Also, it includes role specific
training modules and ongoing
support and official sessions.
The second best practice for implementing
AI in UC deployment is data management.
Implemented structure data
government frameworks.
Privacy first design principles.
Change management is the third.
Press practice for successful a I.
U.
C.
Deployment, which involves
engaging stakeholders.
Thirdly, provide clear
communication and major success.
So let's dive into the
future of a I enhanced.
Do you see?
So the future of a I in unified
communications is exciting.
Advanced virtual assistance
equipped with emotional intelligence
will manage complex tasks like
scheduling and project coordination.
Predictive analysis will
anticipate user needs and
streamline workflows in real time.
The market for AI enhanced UC is projected
to grow with an impressive rate of 38.
4 CAGR through 2028, which is
driven by the rising demand for
smart communication solutions.
in hybrid and remote work environments.
We go to the next slide.
Let's conclude how integrating
artificial intelligence into unified
communications will be helpful.
So here, in conclusion, AI integration
into unified communications is a
transformative shift in enterprise
communication technology.
Intelligent call routing, speech
recognition, predictive analysis.
Improvement of efficiency,
customer satisfaction and
compliance are the key parts here.
Despite challenges like technical
integration and user adoption, thoughtful
planning and execution can ensure success.
AI and UC are the key builder to
build something smarter, more agile
communication systems that meets
the demand of modern businesses.
Finally, a huge thank you for
supporting me and for this conference.
Thank you.
Thank you all.