Hey everyone and welcome and thanks
a lot for being here with me.
so I'm Amanda Hunter and I'm a
digital marketer with a real love for
blending technology and creativity.
And I especially love building
web experiences for IOT products.
Now, I know IOT can feel like a buzzword
that we just really throw around, but at
its core, it's all about making our lives
easier and connecting everything from
the thermostats to our coffee makers.
but let's be real.
These products can also be intimidating.
So if you've ever opened a box and
stared at the manual and thought,
Oh, this is really annoying.
I don't want to deal with this today.
Then So my goal today is to show you
how we can take that annoying note
moment and turn it into something
more wow, this is really easy.
And spoiler alert, it all
starts with a great website.
So let's kick things off with a question.
Why is web such a game
changer for IOT adoption?
And here's the thing, IOT is incredible.
It's like magic in the form of tech.
Your thermostat learns your
habits, your light comes on.
sync with your mood, and your fridge
tells you when you're out of oat milk.
But let's be honest, in
all its brilliance, IoT can
also be really complicated.
And it's not just about getting your
devices to talk to each other, it's about
making them a seamless part of your life.
And it's not always easy.
Devices sometimes don't connect,
settings that don't always save, and
that apps that almost feel like they're
written in another language can make
us Give up before you've even really
started with this amazing technology.
So this is where web comes in.
It's the first stop on a user's journey,
whether they're researching a product,
trying to set it up, or figuring out
why their smart speaker won't just
stop saying, Hi, sorry, I didn't
quite get that, but let's face it.
When something isn't working, no one
pulls out that instruction manual anymore.
It's probably already in the bin.
They go straight to Google.
So your website needs to be more
than just a pretty landing page.
It has to be an ultimate
guide where it's a place where
users can find clear answers.
They're easy to follow instructions there
and their confidence and to keep going.
And that's why web is such
a game changer for IOT.
It's where the relationship between
users and their devices can begin.
And if we get it right with that
great web experience, we can turn
curious visitors into confident users.
So let's explore in the
next couple of slides.
How we can make that happen.
All right.
So let's talk about what makes
a web experience truly magical.
And it all comes down to three things.
First, it has to educate.
It also has to be simple, and it also
has to build trust, and if we can nail
down these three things, you're not
just creating a website, you're creating
a space that feels like a supportive
and helpful friend to your users.
So if we break that down a bit
further, we can look at So before
anyone can love or even use your
IOT product, they need to understand
what it does and why it matters.
And this is where having simple,
digestible content comes in.
Think bite sized, not brain surgery.
Short videos?
Yes, please.
Show people that what your product
can do in 60 seconds or less.
FAQs?
They can become your best friend.
And make them clear, Concise and
make sure that they're covering
users real concerns and not just
fill it up with marketing fluff.
We have enough of that these days.
Also, step by step guides can be an
absolute yes, and make them interactive,
visual, or even gamified if possible.
No one just wants to scroll through
a boring wall of text anymore.
And I think the key here is
really to anticipate questions
before they're even asked.
So if your website truly answers those
questions effortlessly, users will feel
smart and more confident from the get go.
Next, let's look at simplification.
So in your onboarding process
should feel easy that users barely
notice that they're learning.
If they're scratching their heads on
your website, or googling what this
button is even for on a different
website, then we've already lost them.
Not good.
So two web experiences that I really like
to add to websites is having interactive
tutorials and also having virtual demos.
So interactive tutorials are like having
that friendly coach or that friendly
best friend, or even the therapist
guiding you through a step how a
guide on how to use your IOT product
and making sure Everything is simple.
And then virtual demos let you
try products you risk free.
So they're like testing out a
smart gadget before it becomes
even part of someone's life.
Pretty cool, right?
so when you simplify, you're not
just removing barriers, you're
creating moments of delight.
And those aha moments when users feel like
everything clicks are what people keep
people engaged and coming back for more.
so finally, let's talk about trust.
And I think this is where a lot of
IOT products trip up, to be honest.
People love the idea of a smart
connected device, but they don't love
the idea of their data being misused
or their privacy being compromised.
And this is where transparency really
becomes a non negotiable on your website.
So make sure that you're clear
and you're upfront about it.
Make sure you're clear about
what data you're collecting
and why you're collecting it.
Also, how you're protecting it.
So when users, know how to do this,
and also know how they can manage
their privacy settings as well.
And it's all about being consistent.
So if your web experience is polished,
professional, easy to use, users will
assume that about your product too.
On the flip side, if your site
feels clunky or outdated, it
can clearly be a red flag.
So when you build trust, you're not just
earning users, you're earning advocates.
And that's where people will not
only stick with your products, but
recommend it to others as well.
All right.
So let's talk about the secret
sauce to an amazing web experience.
And it includes three key ingredients.
Personalization, interactivity,
and localization.
When these three come together,
your website doesn't just inform,
it connects and it engages.
So first is personalization.
And this is what, helps make
users feel like you're psyched.
was built just for them.
It's not just showing their name.
It's about serving up content and
recommendations that match their
specific needs and their preferences.
So imagine landing on a site and thinking,
wow, this company totally gets me.
I really like it.
and that's the power of personalization.
It makes users feel seen and value.
The next ingredient we
have is interactivity.
Let's be honest, a static site can
be boring, but tools like live demo,
product configurations, quizzes can
make the experience dynamic and fun.
An example could be, being able
to visualize a product in your
own space through a virtual demo
or customize it before buying.
and it doesn't just
inform, it really expands.
sites and makes the product
feel real and quite magical.
and interactivity keeps users engaged
and encourages them to explore your
product and your product suites further.
And then finally, we
have the localization.
If your audience is global,
your site needs to feel it.
and it needs to feel local in all
your different markets and this isn't
just about translating the language
It's about adopting to the cultural
nuances imagery and even tone of the
website to match your different regions
So a site that's designed for spain
should feel distinctly spanish and not
just like it was that american site
Copy paste it into Google Translate.
And when you get personalization,
interactivity, and localization your
website becomes more than a platform.
It becomes a memorable experience
that resonates with every visitor.
Great.
So let's talk about the onboarding process
after someone buys your IoT product.
Because that's where we know the
magic or the disaster can happen.
So a smooth onboarding process can
be the difference between someone
saying this is the best product I ever
bought Or tossing your IOT product in
the drawer and never seeing it again.
I really hope that doesn't happen.
so how do we make the
onboarding process on the web?
Not just functional, but fantastic.
And it comes down to, again, some magic
ingredients of support tools, reducing
that complexity, and boosting engagement.
So let's break these
things down a bit further.
So first up, as I mentioned earlier,
guides and tutorials are amazing.
And I'm not just talking about boring
50 page PDFs that no one wants to read.
Think bite sized, step by step
instructions that feel like your
helpful friend, or that therapist, or a
coach walking you through the process.
Video guides are amazing,
interactive tutorials even better.
And the goal here is to make setups
so straightforward that users barely
realize that they're learning.
They click, they follow along, boom!
They're up and running, and without
ever having to Google, why won't my
smart fridge connect to my Wi Fi?
Then, they're done.
We also have AI, hello AI, we love AI,
AI chatbots, for personalized support.
let's talk about AI chatbots.
They're like the superheroes
of support nowadays.
I absolutely love them.
They're available 24 7 and they
don't get tired or frustrated.
And they're shockingly good at
answering user specific questions fast.
picture this, a user is stuck
setting up their smart thermostat.
At 11 p.
m.
Instead of throwing in the towel
they hop on your site and ask the
chatbot Why isn't this working and
they get instant personalized help?
It's like having tech export experts on
speed dial and it not only solves problems
quickly It also builds confidence in your
users So they feel supported and they're
more likely to stick with your product.
And then finally, let's
look at reducing complexity.
So let's be real.
IoT products can be intimidating.
And if your onboarding process looks
like it requires an engineering degree,
people are just going to bounce.
No, they're not going to be interested.
So reducing complexity is everything.
Simplifying the setup process
so it feels intuitive.
Make sure that you're
using clear language.
and also remove any fluff
or any unnecessary steps.
And, also anticipate where
users might be getting stuck.
So it's all about minimizing
that frustration on your, and
making that information clear.
So you're maximizing those
aha, woohoo, great moments that
just click with your users.
and then, yeah, sorry, I thought that
was the last point, but let's look
into boosting engagement as well.
Sorry, one more in there.
bit of a, Bit of a boost as well.
So now there were things that,
this is where I think things
are really getting exciting.
When you nail onboarding, you're not
just solving for an immediate problem,
you're laying down the foundation
for long term engagement and loyalty.
And when users feel like they bastard
the setup process, they're way more
likely to keep exploring your products
and recommending it to others.
And they're not just using
it, they're loving it.
And that's the ultimate goal, right?
An onboarding experience that
doesn't just encourage adoption,
it creates lifelong fans.
so to sum it up, onboarding isn't
just about getting users through the
door or even looking at your website.
It's about making their first
experience on your site and with your
product enjoyable and empowering.
And these are, with the right
tools, focus on simplicity.
And an emphasis on engagement.
You can turn your head,
even the most hesitant users
into your biggest advocates.
Okay, so that was a lot of theory and
I feel like now it's a good time to
go into some real world examples of
brands that I feel can get it right.
So let's take a look at Nest.
So we've all heard of Nest, love
Nest, and, they've really redefined
their onboarding experience,
for their smart thermostats.
one of the biggest hurdles
with IoT is the setup process.
I think we all know that.
and it can feel intimidating, even
for, the most tech savvy users.
So Nest solves this by offering
interactive tools on their websites.
Love a good website.
And this guide users.
This, provides users with
step by step thorough, guides
for thorough installation.
And these tools aren't just about
showing what you do, they actively help
their users understand how to do it.
For example, their app walks
through how to identify a user.
existing thermostat wiring and
connecting their new Nest device
and how to set it up on your Wi Fi.
And it's hands on and intuitive,
meaning users don't need the experts
to feel confident in the process.
And what's even better is Nest goes beyond
by just helping you install their device.
Their tools also show you how to
optimize the thermostat for energy
efficiency and sustainability and this
might explain, they also explain how
you can use things like eco mode or
suggest schedules based on your habits.
And it isn't just about functionality.
It's about really empowering the users
to get the most out of the device.
Day one looking at their website
being able to figure it out And the
result is a setup process that feels
approachable Not overwhelming and a
product that delivers immediate value.
I love nest as I just said so nest
Has this approach that shows us that
simplifying complexity is not just helpful
It's a it's essential to driving adoption
and user satisfaction And another great
example we have is philips hue and I
think this is awesome these lights now,
especially when it gets dark at 4 p.
m.
It's great to have some
colorful mood lighting here
it's just been amazing as well.
So really like this product as well So if
we just talk about philip You for a minute
and how they've added a seriously cool,
immersive twist to choosing lighting.
So instead of just showing you pictures
and throwing technical specs at you, they
let you visualize how on their website,
how their lights will look in your home.
Even before you buy it's
an amazing virtual demo.
I suggest you go and try it it feels like
trying clothes in a fitting room, but
it's with living room lights you want to
see how that cozy warm glow feels in your
space or you know What bright daylight
can do to your productivity corner?
You can just really go on their site
and experiment and play around until
you get the really Just the right
ambiance for your mood as well.
and this just isn't just about
selling a product to them It's about
removing all the guesswork and making
the experience feel personal and fun
And here's the genius part about it.
Philips hue doesn't just
stop at functionality.
They support making users feel supported
Confident and genuinely excited about
their product and their in their choices.
I genuinely excited about it Now I want
to go and buy some of these lights And
I think it's a perfect example of how to
A great onboarding isn't just practical.
It's emotional and when you
empower users to create something
that feels uniquely Theirs is not
just about offering a product.
You're offering a great awesome
experience as well Okay So now let's
geek out for a second and talk about what
makes all of this IOT magic possible.
And there are three big
players here behind the scenes.
We have, of course, AI, then we
also have AR and VR, and then,
of course, cloud infrastructure.
And together, they create web experiences
that feel seamless and almost magical.
So first we have AI, and this
is the brains of the operation.
AI personalizes the user experience by
learning what people like, what they
click on, and what they ignore, and even
how they interact With the iot products
and also with your website So it's really
like having a mind reader built into
the website and serving up exactly what
your users want From their information
and their onboarding Even before they
know what they want and also we have
ar and vr and these technologies create
an immersive Interactive demos that let
users try before they buy So imagine
being able to you know You we talked
about it with the hue lights But you
could also do this with having a piece
of furniture and how you'd like it to
look in your living room Or house, the
smart light can really change the mood of
your space from all these screens while
you're just like hanging out at home
and again, it's engaging it's fun and
it really removes that uncertainty about
buying a new and quite expensive product.
and finally, there's cloud infrastructure.
And this is the unsung hero that keeps
everything up and running smoothly.
And it ensures that even if millions
of users are on your platform
at the same time, there are no
slowdowns, there's no crashes,
and no frustrating loading scenes.
And these things, when these three
a technology aspects work together.
The result is a web experience
and an IOT product that feels
effortless and intuitive.
Like everything, it's just
working exactly how it should.
and it isn't just about what kind
of experience we want as users.
Isn't this what we want?
and of course, finally.
It's not all rainbows and sunshine.
There are real challenges
in these experiences.
First, handling user data
is a big responsibility.
and it's huge because trust can
be built or completely broken.
based on how you manage privacy
and second, unfortunately, there
are a lot of development costs
when it comes to IOT products.
So building amazing experiences
isn't cheap and it takes
a significant investment.
And then finally, of course,
there's that level of scalability.
So what works perfect for 10 users
might collapse when you have it
for 10, 000, millions, or maybe
even billions at some point.
here's the thing, like with
everything, And These are challenges.
They're not excuses not to get started.
They are opportunities.
And if you're really motivated and
excited, you can make it happen.
So just make sure that
you're tackling them head on.
And you're not just solving problems.
You're setting yourselves up as
a confident leader in your space.
I'm at the end, and let's just wrap up
with a few best practices to keep in mind
when creating exceptional user experiences
for your IoT products on the web.
So first, I'd say, listen and iterate.
So your user is your
best source of insight.
Pay attention to their feedback
and keep improving based on
what they're telling you.
The best experiences are built
over time, not all at once.
Second, let's keep it clear.
Simplicity is your
superpower, so avoid it.
jargon, and complicated explanations.
The goal is to make everything as
easy to understand as possible.
No one should need a manual
just to navigate your site.
And third, accessibility is key.
It's a great experience.
we need that great experience
to work for everyone.
And this means designing for different
abilities, devices, and needs.
So no one feels left out or frustrated.
And the truth is, it's not just about
launching something perfect right away.
It's about building something
that can grow, it can adapt,
and it can evolve over time.
And when you focus on these best
practices, you're setting yourself
up for definitely long term success.
In conclusion, just to wrap everything
up, the future of IoT isn't just
about cool gadgets, it's about the
experiences we build around them.
an amazing web experience that's user
friendly, engaging, and intuitive
can really take IoT from, do I
really need this product, to yes,
I can't imagine my life without it.
And the IoT revolution
is already happening.
And it's on us to make these technologies
accessible, seamless, and why not?
Try and make it a little fun too.
And when users feel empowered
and excited, adoption isn't
just easier, it's inevitable.
so that sums it up for today.
I hope you enjoyed the talk
and learned a little bit.
And I'd love to connect and speak
more about web experiences and IoT.
So thank you so much,
and speak to you soon.
Bye bye.