Hello friends and thank
you for joining me today.
My name is Amod Darshane and today I'll
be discussing a topic on advanced network
security, network segmentation, and zero
trust architecture and how really it
helps to secure the IoT cyber security.
I have about 16 years of
experience in the industry.
And I was fortunate enough to
work with various customers from
pharmaceutical, banking, financial side.
At the moment, I am working for an OEM
partner and that gives me access to
multi technology side of the networking.
Traditionally, I was a route switch
engineer, but gradually I started
working on the security side.
And got my attention to SASE.
in my current role, I work on projects,
on majority of the projects on SD WAN
and SASE, and Zero Trust Architecture.
In today's section, we'll go over
some of these topics, how, it is
challenging to secure the IoT networks.
And then what is exactly the zero trust
architecture is the network segmentation
is And we'll go through the synergy
between the network segmentation and
zero trust architecture And how it
is helping to prevent some of the
cyber attacks on IOT devices So let's
begin the talk In the next 30 minutes
or so, we will cover these topics.
So what are really the
challenges of network security?
With evolving the cyber threat landscape,
the cyber security threats are also
evolving rapidly, with attackers becoming
more sophisticated and persistent.
To give you an example, the AI,
Is not really being used to become
more productive, in your day to day
activities, but modern day attackers
are also getting more productive by
using AI and your traditional, security,
traditional security is not really
enough, to prevent these attacks, right?
Especially with the IOT side, which has
which has increased the attack surface.
Um, and it has, limited security.
built in into these devices.
let's take some of the issues with, with
the IOT side of the network security.
The IOT is, really lack sometimes,
with the robust security
protocols built into them.
their resource constraints, has,
limited processing power and
storage, and that really hinders
the advanced security majors.
the high volume of devices, also
is a challenge in managing and
securing millions of devices.
and that is also very complicated.
and they are very prone to, malware
attacks, DDoS attacks, and data breaches.
Some of the challenges are the
advanced persistent threats.
short form is eight APTs.
Now these remains undetected
for very long period, of time.
It is around nine months to 12, 12 months
before the attacker actually reveals
its identity or you as an organization,
identifies that you are under attack.
so it's really long time.
And in between, they silently gather
all the information of, from your
database and, they can really harm you.
Then there are insider threats.
the threats are no longer
considered only coming from outside.
They are also inside.
for an example, employees or
contractors or even third party
vendors, who has legitimate access
can possess a severe threat to
the organization and your network.
Another challenge is to secure your hybrid
environments, meaning now you have your
footprint, not only in your organization
and your data centers, You also have
your applications running in the cloud.
And not only that, sometimes you
have your applications running
in multi cloud environment.
So now you have to mitigate the risk
at the data center level, at the
cloud level, and multi cloud level.
So your monitoring increases.
so these are the security challenges,
to your network and your specially
IoT networks that we discussed.
Let's take a look at the other side.
So what is exactly the
network segmentation is?
so it's basically ice, part partitioning
a network into smaller isolated segments
and logically, logically mean you
don't really have, a physical devices.
Those are separated, but sometimes
even that is also possible.
Sorry for the glitch there.
the network segmentation is
basically isolating your network
into a smaller, manageable parts.
The traditional network segmentation
example would be VLANs or virtual LANs
where you segment your network based
on the logical broadcast domains.
Another modern day example would be
VRFs or Virtual Router Forwarding.
Now that is, very much in
use, to isolate your, guest
traffic from your corp traffic.
And also you can, use, your IOT
traffic to, to isolate from your,
traditional enterprise traffic.
now you can also have a physical
segmentation of your network, meaning
you can have, the, The corp environment
running, in on a different set of
network, on a physical device and the
IOT, side of network is running on
completely air gapped, environment, so
that is also one of the, segmentations.
Now, how it is beneficial, So it isolates
the critical assets, the sensitive
data and your intellectual property and
critical infrastructure are separated
into secure zones, reducing their
exposure to, broader network traffic.
And it also reduce the attack surface,
segmenting the network helps containing
potential threats and prevent them from
spreading across the entire organization.
Thank you So if you have
some applications, those are
exposed to the outside world.
You can also use a DMZ wherein, those
applications are put behind the firewall.
and then you can.
Only expose certain ports on
or certain, surfaces for that
application towards the outside world.
And that is also isolated from
your traditional corp network.
Now let's look at, let's take a look
at, the ZTA, zero trust architecture.
zero trust is a security model,
and it is based on the principle
of never trust and always verify.
Bye.
What does that mean is, once you
identify a corporate asset or a
user or even a thing like an IOT
thing, then that identity does not
remain valid, for very long time.
So you always verify that
device is who that device is.
and you always keep authenticating
that device over the period of time.
and it also combines with the
authorization, meaning what level
of access that device is granted.
if a user or the device is not
supposed to have access to certain
applications, though, then those
applications will not be accessible
for that user or for the device.
And along with that, if, if users,
and applications, or even devices
required a certain level of access,
only that access will be provided.
And that comes under the
least privileged access.
Though, they will not be getting access.
Any more access beyond what is really
required to function them properly.
and what are the core components?
so identity and access management is
a foundation of zero trust, ensuring
users and devices are verified
through multi factor authentication
and strong password policies.
Meaning, when you log into
your banking account with,
with a username and password.
The next step of authentication is
going to be either an email sent to you
with an OTP pin or you get a message
on the phone, on a, the OTP pin.
That is another level of security
called MFA, multi factor authentication.
Even nowadays, that is also prone for
certain attacks, but that's an additional
level of security that you can, You
can apply, for your applications,
micro segmentation, applying strict
access control policies at the
application level, or workload level
rather than the network parameters.
And then along with these, you continuous
monitoring, or you continue to monitoring
the real time visibility into network
activity, And find out if there is any
abnormal behavior or anomaly detection,
and respond to the threats accordingly.
Another example, which is not really
been given in the slide is, the
network access control systems.
in my, majority of my, previous,
career or previous job, rather, I was
working on, network control systems,
Where you will be authenticated and
authorized, at the network level, you,
before you can access any network.
And that gives the visibility, what
connects to your wired network or your
wireless network, or even VPN network.
a computer or a user or an
IOT device needs to identify.
Okay.
It's identity that could be based on
username and password accompanied by
a certificate installed on the system.
And then that will be authenticated
against your Enterprise Root Certificate
Authority and proper access will be given.
That entity will be put in to the
respective VLANs dynamically in
order to provide the proper access.
Thank you.
Now, in traditional versus modern,
network security strategies, in
traditional network security, the focus
is really on the perimeter firewalls.
and then intrusion detection systems,
are also installed separately
or were installed separately.
The antivirus system softwares,
and it really assumes that the
threats are primarily external.
which is not the case
in today's environment.
And the challenges include
insufficient internal monitoring,
vulnerability to insider threats,
and difficulties in scaling security
for modern dynamic IT environment.
In the network segmentation, we saw
that it divides networks into isolated
segments to control and monitor traffic,
and hence it reduced the lateral attacks.
it is effective for containing
the breaches, but then it
requires complex management and
configuration to ensure that critical
segments are properly secured.
And along with that, the Zero
Trust architecture, it is a
proactive, security model.
We saw Never Trust, Always Verify, way
of implementing Zero Trust architecture.
It validates users and devices at every
access point regardless of the location.
And because of our workloads are
also are in cloud and multi cloud
environments, unlike traditional
models, it adapts the dynamic and
distributed environments as well.
Now let's take a look at how the
network segmentation actually works.
We already discussed
about the virtual LANs.
It is a logical segmentation of
networks into, smaller subnets, to
create the isolated broadcast domains.
And it can be having its
own security policies.
For an example, VLAN, guest VLAN
would be completely separate
than the, corp VLAN, where the
access, is given way differently.
The printers will be provided a
different level of access than your
organization, organizational computer.
the next gen firewalls, now for
last, 10 years or so, the next gen
firewalls are rapidly increasing its,
deployment, in the modern, networks.
there is a reason why, these
are called next gen firewalls.
It not only, detects, capable of detecting
and preventing the attacks at the network
level, but they are now application aware.
they don't only, able to put the
rules, the access rules at the
network layer, but then they can
also capable of identifying the
applications and, you can put the rules.
on them at the application level.
It also, they also capable of doing
deep packet inspection, rather
than just looking at the IP header.
they're also capable of preventing,
the intrusion using the,
intrusion prevention systems.
you can monitor the network for
malicious activity and block
it by using next gen firewalls.
Another feature is the
geolocation identifying.
what does that mean?
you can now restrict, your applications
to be accessed from certain malicious
countries and only whitelist few
countries where you expect your
legitimate traffic to come from.
multi tenancy, the next gen
firewalls can secure multiple
tenants and sub tenants and isolate
the network traffic between them.
they are not just capable
of firewall, right?
firewall features.
They're also.
a beefy, a router, you would say,
and they are also, capable of,
implementing the VRF features on them.
they can also run the SD WAN on
them, meaning, you don't really
need a separate hardware to run
the, software defined networking.
they are, they're capable of, programming,
and giving the greater flexibility to
control the traffic management, along
with that, the security policies can
also be managed, dynamically applied
to various network segmentations.
the software defined networking, it allows
to deploy the devices, the networking
devices, using just one click of a button.
they also call ZTPs or Zero Trust
Provision Provisioning Systems where a
system gets an IP address from a DHCP
server and then it's called home to get
the certificates and the configuration
from the controller and then it
configures on its own using the policies
and the configuration that is, It is
there to be pulled from the controller.
Now let's take, take a look at some
of these zero trust architecture.
now how can you always trust
and never, how can you always
verify and never trust, right?
on the devices or on the users.
you, so you can implement some of these,
features, multifactor authentication.
which ensures the users, who
they say they are, but required
multiple forms of verification.
We saw, an OTP pin, or also you can
use, some of the physical devices, which
can, verify your fingerprints as a MFA.
so those are various options
that you can implement, for
multi factor authentication.
another is the single sign authentication.
Now it really simplifies user access
while maintaining a strict security
policies, and it is integrated with, the
enterprise systems like Active Directory.
So if you have certain applications,
in your organization and you want that
application, Before user access them.
You want that applications to be,
make sure the user is authenticated.
So the, but then the, the user experience
is such that they don't have to log in
to each and every application every time.
So the security token is issued
once they, log in for the first
time and perform their MFA.
And that security token is valid
for certain duration of time.
And for all that duration,
all their access is, valid.
So they can open, and they can access
multiple applications, of course,
based on their authorization profile.
The next is the Role Based
Access Control, or RBAC.
Now, it is really important to
provide, the users with certain
level of access to perform their job.
Um, role based access control or
attribute based access control.
Those are some of the acronyms, are used.
So organization enforced the
principle of least privileges using
these, using these components.
so I, I previously I had given an
example of, network access control.
So by using network access control.
If a device is authenticated and
authorized for a certain level
of access and, at the end of the
day, it's certificate expires.
So that device will no longer have the
full access that can be, used to access
several applications of the organization,
but then it will only be given.
access to mitigate that secure,
that expired certificate and hence
will be put into a restricted VLAN.
so that's the, role based application.
basically what it is, the micro
segmentation, the, it ensures the
security policies are enforced.
at the application level, and it
allows the granular control over
traffic flows, isolating the high risk
application from the rest of the network.
we have seen, the example of, DMZ where
you're highly, exposed applications.
you would put them in your DMZ and then,
only, open certain Ports or certain
services for that application to be
accessed from external, externally.
using, next gen firewall, you
can also put some restricted
restrictions, on the devices within
the same virtual LAN or VLAN.
so those are, some of the key
components of Zero Trust Architecture.
Now, let's see the synergy between
the network segmentation and the ZTA.
these terms are coming over and
over, in my presentation, but
those are really important ones.
So they complement, security strategies.
They help you simplify the compliance, and
help you, their, help you, To, their, the,
compliances like GDPR and HIPAA, because
of their, easy deployment, the security
posture is also increase, increases
the scalability that is required for
the modern IOT networks, and workloads
that also, achievable because of, using
the ZTA and, the network segmentation
and of course the business continuity.
It ensures the uninterrupted operations.
even during the incidents,
because you can implement these
in a high available manner.
so again, the segmentation
alone doesn't solve the problem
of identity verification.
it requires the ZTA to ensure that
even the trusted network segments,
users, and devices are authenticated
at every stage and authorization
follows by the authentication.
and Zero Trust Architecture complements
segmentation by providing dynamic
and flexible access policies.
and the key word here is dynamic because.
You don't put the access policies,
at once, they are always gets
changed based on, based on the
users or devices, compliance.
So that is very important here.
Now, one of the benefits of,
network segmentation and, and ZTA.
So it offers the
comprehensive security, right?
So it delivers the multi layer defense.
it reduces the risk of lateral movement,
meaning, your attack surface is or attack
is not only happening the northbound, but
it can also be east west communication
or an employees or internal employees can
also be present that threat, any phishing
email that, that is open, the attack
can be, unleashed on your organization.
And, present by, by, implementing
the ZTA and network segmentation,
the lateral movements can be
detected and be prevented.
it also improves the
visibility and monitoring.
so with.
The network segmentation organization
can, monitor traffic flow between segments
quickly and detect the potential breaches.
it also observes the behavior
of that user or of that device.
So for an example, if your printer,
is only supposed to talk to a print
server or some of the monitoring
systems, and suddenly it starts talking
to an external DNS server, for, or
try to access some malicious sites,
there is a red flag right there.
And that can be easily,
found out by using the ZTA.
And, which ensures, the behavior is
constantly analyzed for anomalies and,
enabling early detection of the threats.
Now, where you all, where can
be, can this be implemented?
It, these can be implemented
in smart manufacturing plants.
and, malware spreading
through an IoT sensors.
Can be easily identified and detected
and prevented, segmented IOT devices into
VLANs and segmented zero trust policies
for access control, healthcare facilities.
the issue could be like unauthorized
access to medical IOT devices and
the solution is going to be, Use the
network segmentation for devices,
and implement the ZTA for the secure
authentication and authorization
in order to, implement
these, security components.
it's very important to identify
the critical assets, that you
have in your organization and
group the group them logically.
there has to be a single source
of truth, That can be used
to, to verify your, inventory.
the audit needs to be taken annually,
and then accordingly, you can, you can
enhance your security posture and identify
the vulnerabilities, amongst them.
Now, let's take a look at the conclusion.
So for over 30 minutes, I have
been discussing with you, on the
ZTA and the network segmentation.
So these are, these tools are really
powerful and complimentary security
strategies that enhance protection
against modern cyber threats.
By implementing network segmentation,
organizations can isolate sensitive
areas while Zero Trust policies
continuously verify access, ensuring
a more robust security posture.
And to get started, organizations
should conduct a network assessment,
apply Zero Trust principles to
critical applications, and continuously
monitor and adapt security measures
using AI and behavioral analytics.
I would like to thank you for,
being with me and patiently,
listening to the, to the talk.
and again, thank you signing off.