Today.
I will share with you some insights about
IoT and mobile, in particular, how to make
them work together and get the best out
of them to debug and develop application.
So my talk is called unveiling the
vital link between IoT and mobile.
The power of telemetry.
And just before starting, I invite you
to use the chat and drop a message about
if you are using telemetry, which one
and how telemetry solve your issue.
So I'm curious to see telemetry
in action also for you.
But just before starting.
Let me take a just second
to introduce myself.
Ciao.
Hi, I'm Matteo.
I'm a senior mobile engineer.
I start back in days when the first,
beta of IUS was release, to the public.
So as you can imagine, a bit of time ago
and for many years, more than 15 so far.
I work in developing by application,
for iOS sometimes also for Android and
lately back more since 2019 in Flutter
or mobile devices as companion app of
IoT project and with my team, I also
work in developing some, internal tools,
for example, one related to telemetry.
To help our daily job
and make stuff working.
easier, not only for us as developer, but
also for our friend of the QA department.
Last but not least, let me say
I'm an happy and enthusiastic
open source contributor.
So probably you will find some of my
library or awesome collection of links.
One is for sure awesome, swift.
Another is related with awesome BLE.
I'm also the mobile lead of a team.
In intent and intent is a company with
more than 10 years of experience, in
building as you imagine application
companion app or connected device.
So let's say an expertise perfectly
fit our aim, our customer, some
of them are, aura Bosh, and we
are working every day with new.
exception startup, and we're helping
them to start their journey from the
project to the real product on the market.
So let's start speaking
about telemetry now.
Telemetry It is a way to collect
data, but in a very specific way.
Automated, and this is a key
word that I want to underline.
Automation is very important.
The collection of the data
should not be human driven.
And later we'll see why telemetry
is a way to collect a constant.
Stream of data that allow you to see what
happened back in the days in the second
in the minutes and basically add the whole
history of what happened is such important
because as you can imagine, allow you to
have a full reply of what happened and
this one is very useful because it can
happen that you are not Transcribed At
your desk in that let me share an example,
a very high level example, totally, let's
say from a different context, but to
have an idea what telemetry is and how it
works, I share with you one of my passion
that is, building, applying custom drone.
Building a custom drone is not such
a trivial, let's say operation.
And this one already help you to
understand that a telemetry tool is useful
in many different stage of a product.
For a drone is useful when you start
to find how to build that already.
Then when you start to assemble and
put the first screw And then when you
start to do the, let's say, first very
fly, and then when you start to enjoy
flying with that, why is such important?
As you can imagine, a drone has
inside the board that keeps,
let's say, the brain of the drone.
A drone is composed by many components.
motors, at least four propeller,
antenna, GPS, and battery, and
everything has to work smoothly.
Otherwise, instead of having a
beautiful drone fly, we have, let's say
Or in the worst scenario, we have
basically something splashed on the floor.
according to that, we don't
want to do that and we want
to have fun with our drone.
We need to use some specific tool
and drone have many open source
firmware that you can flash.
And this firmware grants you access
to many information in real time.
www.
Flydreamers.
com when you build that, you can use
steel, for example, let's say you
art to install the firmware, but as
you can imagine, meantime, you fly.
there's no way to do that.
So you need data in real
time in a different manner.
And here telemetry comes to help.
Telemetry is able to tell you if
the speed of each of the engine from
this one, you can understand if the
propeller are working the proper way.
If the batteries in the proper, let's
say temperature and how many millivolts
you have still, because if for the first
fly is important to understand that
everything works as expected for the next
slide is important to understand that.
you have battery enough, the battery
is in the proper position, balance, the
engine are not overheating, and you can
collect many of this information, your
position through the GPS, the audio and
video feed from the camera, the propeller
speed, the battery consumption, and
if you put together this one, you have
the full information of your flight.
You can listen, if you can
come back first of all.
That is not such a trivial stuff because
you can even go too far, too high, and
the battery is not able to last that
long, so there is not, let's say, return
home, and this one can be problematic.
You need to know the GPS position
because if anything happens and the
drone falls down, You have to find
that another, not such a trivial stuff.
So let me say drawn is a perfect
example of starting from zero to
reach the final product, how much
a simple stuff like telemetry.
So a full automated feed of data coming
from a device in this case, helped you
to, a different stage, achieve the goal.
One information more.
Is, as you can imagine that we have
different kind of connection, and
in this part, we need to, let's
say in our particular scenario.
So considering that we have a
mobile phone, we are speaking
about indirect way of connection.
Let's play a reversal.
A peripheral that has a standalone
connection, internet connection, can be,
I don't know, Wi Fi rather than NB IoT,
and a SIM on that is pretty standalone.
But you can apply telemetry
over there too for sure.
in a context like BLE,
so we have two options.
Or we have physical gateway.
or you need to ask your
phone to act as a gateway.
So the phone is able to, gather all the
information as a kind of, let's say,
transparent proxy and bring them to, to
a tool where you collect all the data.
Okay, sounds good, I think.
And I think already I catch some
of your possible, let's say, doubt.
So what's the difference
between telemetry and logging?
Good question.
it's pretty simple.
And we come back to the
very, very beginning slide.
Automation is the key.
in this scenario, logging means that
there's a developer that is entitled to
develop some code and drop locks inside
that to double check what's going on.
This one, by definition, can be error
prone, can even be that I did the best
job ever, but I forgot one condition.
And when you're debugging in, say,
special condition, and we'll see this
later, and this one can be problematic.
So telemetry helps a lot because as
I mentioned can be considered as a
transparent proxy that grab the data
and keep them and store them even
locally in the beginning the phone if
the phone has no connection but later
is able to sync To an external system.
And with this external system,
you can have, chronologically
all the what happened and double
check how to make it work.
Why I was saying that is important
and can be risky use logic because
if you are debugging in special
condition, so not next to your desk,
if you figure out that they forgot
to drop a lock, you can It's tricky.
If you forgot that I dropped the log
and the application is being used
to climb a mountain or to swim or
go underwater or drive a fast car.
I don't know if you'll have time to
issue a new version of the app to be
used to debug and catch what's missing.
a tool that grants me
full access to the data.
makes my life easier and
calmer at the same time.
So I don't have to think about, Oh, I
put all the log in the proper place.
Oh, I hope so.
Let's hope that the guy doesn't have
to climb 50 million times this hill.
So it doesn't work like this.
So logging is very important.
What's inside telemetry?
The proper answer probably would
be, and should be, everything.
I tried to put down some of
the log in the proper place.
I thought that usually are used.
So for sure, the connection
status is useful.
More to know if you are connected or not.
There are SSI.
So how much is the signal strength of BLE?
The battery level of the peripheral or
the battery levels if the peripheral has
multiple battery or What do you call it?
Peripheral.
Because even this one
is another condition.
The full flow of the command sent,
received, error, codes, for example,
the firmware version of the device.
So pack all together.
This one is very important.
So give you an idea of what's going on.
And allow you to create a kind
of, let's say, digital twin
reply, the full experience.
And this one is very useful later when
you sit back to your office desk and you
need to the back so you can go check all
the data step by step understand what's
the status of the peripheral understand
what's the mobile phone send and try
to figure out where is the income.
I want to share with you an
example telemetry and let's
call that telemetry in action.
So have a beautiful daily tracker.
It works in the swimming pool and for sure
is not an extreme place, that's for sure.
You need some, pay some attention if
you don't want to make your laptop
fly in the water and start to figure
out, how much it's, let's say.
water, how much is waterproof.
and also, it's a high
humidity environment.
So there are some
precautions that are neat.
And let's say that this device,
for example, is used by a trainer.
So a person that is standing still and
waiting the person that is swimming to
come back and, let's say, start a new lap.
So this is the scenario.
I decided to split that in three part.
So first of all, behavioral debugging,
old school, totally old school approach.
The trainer is checking the phone.
The person is coming.
Noted.
This one is the behavioral debug.
We stop over there.
Okay.
nothing more, nothing less.
Log debugging.
Let's say that we bring our laptop, we
keep connected to the phone or the tablet.
And what we can see, I put some logs
here and there, battery updated.
Beautiful.
Peripheral disk analytics.
Interesting.
But I don't have a clear
idea what's going on.
Telemetry.
So in this case, instead, me as
a developer, I'm in the office.
and I'm looking at the flow
of data coming and I see that
there is a GAN notification.
Good.
This one brings some information
like the firmware version.
Perfect.
But also show me that the battery
drops suddenly to five percent.
very low level.
and then disconnect.
Totally different scenario from, verify
disconnect and, I don't have the data.
Behavior UI debugging.
In this way, I'm in the office,
I can sit, I can try to replicate
the situation and understand
that the sync for sure is intermittent.
So this is the issue.
But the other stuff is that
with the telemetry I was able
to understand that the battery.
After a specific command start
to fall down so much that make
the disconnection in place.
The result, as you can imagine, is
a, the developer doesn't have to
start swimming or learn swimming.
It's not trivial stuff, but as you
can imagine, I am able to debug
that in hour or even less and
staying, for example, in the office.
and much faster.
So this kind of stuff allow me to
have a, let's say really a digital
clone, the device that is in the swim
in the time, have the full flow of
data and they can instruct with the
framework team and the QA team, the
device to replicate the same data and
figure out what's triggering that.
And then I can understand, for example,
that is not a software demo bot.
Issue, but it's more a firmware
implementation that generate the issue,
maybe, and try to address the bug,
how a tool like this works, a tool
like this works in a way, basically
on any device, because user is built
on top of the native implementation.
So in the case of iOS, yes,
it's objective C and in Android.
No, it's not in Java, but
it's a very low level.
So Flutter and React Native
will not have issue with that.
You just import them and that's it.
So you can start to collect the data.
The data can be taken, stored locally,
maybe the device, I'm climbing a mountain.
There is no internet at the moment.
So I can store the whole flow of data.
in a local database.
And then as soon as I have internet
started syncing with a system that
allow me later to browse that.
And later I can browse this data remote.
So in any place, if I'm in the office,
if I'm in a special area dedicated for
testing, and many people can check that
the QA department, me as a developer,
my colleague, I can share snippet
information to the firmware team, and
they can look into that and debug.
So debugging without
telemetry, if you ask me, no.
it's an alley that allows
me to have less to do.
I don't have to remember to cover
many stuff in terms of logs.
So I don't have to make my code, let's
say, full of flux and to catch all
the possible, let's say, nuances, edge
cases, and much more calm, QA team is
much more happy because they have all
the flow of data can even be even too
much, let's say, but we can filter them.
So better to collect the data, most
of them, and then try to understand
on top that what's going on.
We can repeat the scenario as many
times we want because now we have
the data, we know the flow, we
know the steps, and we don't know
only the steps from a behavioral
standpoint or a recorded screen, we
know what's going on under the hood.
So we can have some instruments other
that help us to feed the digital twin
and see how to make it work can be
a digital twin hardware or software.
for listening.
As a simulator, and this one help us
to, shrink a lot, the development.
So why using telemetry?
Save money.
So if I have a prototype and I want
to jump on the market, if it can help,
the firmware team, the hardware team.
giving insights real time on what's
going on, fine tuning and implementation,
catch the bug at the earliest stage
and find the solution much easier,
faster without repeating many time.
Let's say, outdoor test.
For sure.
I'm already saving time and
strictly connected to save time.
I can.
save money so I can cut the
cost of debugging and testing.
Last but not least, I will have
much happier customer and the return
rate risk to perform way better.
So be less, let's say, huge than expected.
So if I have a good stable
product, I don't have to worry
about the product come back.
So this one.
These are very other important
stuff related to the word iot
of iot in particular on BLE.
If you don't believe me, you can check
many on the comments of BLE, related
application that doesn't have a fledge,
let's say overview before the launch.
And you can see in the
comment of the application.
So that's it.
I hope I was able to share with you
an idea of what the limiter is, in
particular in the scenario of BLE.
So how to use a device like a smartphone
to collect data and help improve
the way you are working every day.
And make your own say go to
market in case you are the owner
of the product much easier.
If you want, I'm here.
Let's discuss together, telemetry
and let's explore also your needs.
So if you have any need.
for your IOT device, your IOT project,
and you want to discuss how to improve,
for example, the reliability of the BLE
connection, you are facing an issue with
connection stability, reconnection, etc.
For sure, I think we can help you.
we have the knowledge we have the tool.
So feel free to reach me out on LinkedIn.
You can find me as Teoclipa or you can
drop me an email at grow at winstinton.
com.
And yeah, thank you for your time and hope
we will see and meet each other and can
help you with your beautiful IoT project.
Ciao.