I'm Kaushik Vangarajalapathy.
I welcome you to for this talk on
AI and machine learning in workflow
automation, where enhancing the
efficiency and decision making process
in the rapidly evolving landscape
of business technology, artificial
intelligence and machine learning are
revolutionizing the workflow automation.
These cutting edge technologies
are transforming how organizations
streamline their process.
making the decisions and human
intervention on routine tasks.
This presentation explores the profound
impact of AI and ML on workflow automation
dwelling into these technologies,
not only automate repetitive tasks,
but also enhance the complex decision
making process by learning from data and
continuously optimizing the workflow.
let's see the introduction of the
workflow automation with AI and ML.
Before that, let's step back and see what
is a traditional, workflow automation.
historically the workflow automation
focused on streamlining the repetitive
task through a rule based system.
it like be a business process automation,
case management, decision management.
It's all derived by the
rules, a preset of rules.
this system follows, predefined
parts and request extensive
human oversight for exception.
Or complex scenarios while effective
for basic process traditional automation
lack adaptability and intelligence.
this is when the AI, ML enhanced
the automation flow, where by
introducing an adaptive learning
and predictive capabilities, these
technologies can analyze the vast
amount of data, identify the patterns
and make intelligent decisions.
AI power systems can handle the
complex scenarios, learn from the
past experience and continuously
improve the performance over time.
So the key enhancements, what AI
ML can bring into the intelligent
task management, we can achieve
process optimization and predictive
analytics to workflow automation.
These enhancements enable the system
to prioritize tasks, identify the
bottlenecks, and improve performance.
forecast, potential issues
before they occur, the result is
more effective, responsive and
intelligent workflow ecosystem.
So AI decision powered, making
an automated workflow start from
the data collection process.
AI systems gather and clean
relevant data from various sources,
ensuring high quality of input
for decision making process.
This step involves handling
large volume of structured and
unstructured data efficiently.
Often this has been challenged
because there is noise and outliers.
Getting the right data for, for
the, preprocessing is more, and the
preprocessing is most important task in
any machine learning, in, in, in, Next
is the pattern recognition and analysis.
machine learning algorithms analyze
the historical data to identify the
pattern trends and correlations.
This insights from the basis
for predictive models and
decision making frameworks.
Then the model is being constructed.
AI uses analyzed data to
create a predictive models.
Then, that can forecast outcome
and recommended actions.
models.
These models continuously learn and
improve their accuracy over the time.
Finally, the automated decision
execution based on the predictive
models and predefined criteria,
AI can make and execute decisions
automatically, reducing the need for
human intervention in routine processes.
So the industry specific applications
of AI decision makings are in
various industry and some of
the industries heavily used.
these type of implementations are the
finance, healthcare, manufacturing,
and the retail businesses.
So in the finance, let's see how,
these, APower decision making
are helping the finance industry,
through a fraud detection.
it searches for the transaction
patterns and, user behavior and
historical data to identify the
fraudulent activities in real time.
machine learning models can adapt
to a new fraud tactic and tactics
improving the detection rates
and reducing false positives.
In the healthcare industry, the predictive
diagnostics AI power system analyze
the patient data, medical history, and
current symptoms to assist in early
disease detection and treatment planning.
These systems can predict potential
health risk and recommend preventive
measures in the manufacturing.
Supply chain optimization, places and
places in a benefit, machine learning
algorithms optimize supply chain
operations by predicting the demand and
identifying the potential disruptions
and recommending the inventory levels.
This leads to reduced cost,
improved efficiency, and
enhanced customer satisfaction.
In retail industry, a personalized
customer experience is an important
aspect in the competitive market where
AI analyzes the customer behavior,
purchase history, and preferences
to provide a personalized product,
recommendations, and targeted marketing
campaigns, and even enhancing the
engagement and increasing sales.
how the NLP for automated communications,
and the NLP for automated communications.
we can bring into the workflow
management, email triage and routing.
as in the, any customer support,
we receive, thousands and thousands
of emails where an LP algorithms
can automatically categorize and
prioritize the incoming emails based
on the content center and agency.
This enables efficient routing
of messages, appropriate
departments or individuals.
Reducing the response time and
improving the customer service.
The next is the sentiment analysis.
AI powered sentiment analysis to tools
can process customer feedback and social
media posts and support tickers to gauge
public opinion and customer satisfaction.
This information can be used to trigger
automatic responses or alert human
operators when intervention is needed.
The next is the chat bots
and restore assistance.
Advanced NLP.
enables the creation of intelligent
chatbots and virtual assistants
that can understand and respond
to natural language queries.
These AI driven tools can handle a
routine customer inquiries, schedule
appointments, and even assist with
the complex problem solving tasks.
Okay, let's see how the NLP,
driven task management in workflow.
So the first is the content analysis
NLP algorithm analyze the incoming
communications such as email or support
tickets to understand the content,
intent and urgency of each messages.
This step involves techniques
like entity organization, topic
modeling and intent classification.
The next is a task extraction
based on the content of analysis.
The system identifies and extracts
a specific task or action items.
For example, it might recognize a
request for a meeting, a deadline for a
report, or a need for technical support.
And then the third step is the
prioritization and assignment.
The extracted from the extracted
task are automatically prioritized
based on the urgency, importance,
and available resources.
The system then assign the task
to the most appropriate team
members or departments taking into
account workload and expertise.
Automator follow ups is the last thing
where the AI system monitor task, task
progress since an automator reminders
and escalates the issue when necessary.
It can also generate the
status reports and update state
stakeholders automatically.
Ensuring efficient task
completion and communication.
Okay, so the workflow is
built, but, nothing is perfect
in the first place, right?
And building an adaptive workflow
system with reinforcement
learning, is what making the
automated workflow, even smarter.
At the initial stage, the
workflow system starts with a
basic set of rules and process.
Thank you.
Because it has a limited knowledge
of optimal strategies for different
scenarios Next is the exploration phase.
The system begins to explore different
actions and decisions within the workflow
collecting on the outcomes of each choice
learning and adaption using the reinforced
Learning algorithms the system analyzes
the outcomes of its actions identifying
which strategies lead to better results
And next is the policy optimization.
The system refines its decision
making process based on learned
experiences, continuously improving
its performance over time.
And finally, the continues improvement.
The adaptive workflow system continues
to learn and evolve, handling
the new scenarios and adapting to
changes in the business environment.
So some of the real world examples of
adaptive workflow systems Or, smart
manufacturing, where in the adaptive
systems in the manufacturing use
reinforcement learning to optimize the
production schedules, adjust to equipment
failures and predict maintenance needs.
This system can autonomously reconfigure
production lines to maximize the
efficiency and minimize the downtime.
The next is the algorithmic trading.
Financial institution employ adaptive
AI system for high frequency trading.
These systems use reinforcement learning
to adapt to market condition in real
time, optimizing the trading strategies
and managing the risk dynamically.
The next is the network management.
Telecom company uses the
adaptive AI to manage the network
traffic and resource allocation.
These systems learn from usage patterns
to predict the demand, prevent congestion.
And optimize the network
performance autonomously.
And next is the energy grid optimization.
Smart grid systems employs adaptive AI
to balance energy supply and demand.
This system learned from the
consumption patterns, weather
data, and renewable energy.
Availability to optimize the power
distribution and reduces the waste.
Some of the case studies where
AI ML driven workflow automation,
the success stories, in a banking
setter, AI power fraud detection
system, reduces 60 percent of the
false positives, and, which resulted
in save, 50 million annual savings.
In the healthcare industry, ML based,
Diagnostic support tool improved 30
percent in early disease detection rates.
In the manufacturing sector, AI optimized
supply chain management, reduced 25
percent of the inventory cost and
improved 15 percent of the delivery time.
In the technology sector, an LP
driven customer support automation,
reduced the, support ticket resolution
time by 40 percent and, increased
the customer satisfaction by 95%.
So the future trend in AI ML
workflow automation are the
integration with the IoT.
because IOT generates a lot amount
of data and machine learning models
requires a lot of data to perform better.
The convergence of AI driven workflow
automation and the internet of
things, devices will create a highly
responsive data rich ecosystem.
from the smart sensors and all connected
devices, will provide a real time
data inputs allowing the AI system
to make more informed decisions.
Thank you And automate physical processes
in addition to the digital workflows.
Cloud based AI services, the
rise of cloud based AI services
will, democratize the access to
advanced workflow automation tools.
Small and medium sized business
will be able to leverage the
power of AI capabilities without
significant infrastructure
investments, leading to widespread
of adoption across the industries.
of course we, there are some ethical
consideration and challenges, where
the first thing is always the data
privacy and security as the AI systems
handle increasingly sensitive data,
ensuring the robust data privacy and
security measures become crucial.
Organization must implement a strong
encryption access control and compliance
with the regulation like a GDPR to protect
the personal and business information.
And, in many cases there is an algorithmic
biases, that is under fitting or over
15 over fitting model, where a system
can inver, you to, or amplify the
biases present in the training data.
It's essential to regularly audit AI
models for fairness and implement the
techniques to mitigate the biases.
ensuring equitable outcomes
across diverse user groups.
Next is the transparency
and explainability.
As AI systems make more critical
decisions, the need for transparency
and explainability grows.
Developing the interpretable AI model
and providing a clear explanation
for automated decisions will be
crucial for building the trust and
meeting the regulatory requirements.
Thank you for joining us.
Finally, the work for, workforce impact.
The increasing automation of workflow
may lead to, job displacement in some
sectors, organization and policy.
MA makers must address this challenge
by focusing on reskilling and
upskilling programs, ensuring, that
the workflow workforce can adopt a
new roles in an AI driven economy.
And, thanks for joining this presentation.
hope you learn something.
and I'll see you next time.
Thank you.