Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining me today.
My name is Karthik Valamsetla and
I'm excited to share how modern
web APIs can help us create
incredible user experiences.
These APIs like geolocation, web
notifications, and intersection
observer are powerful tools that let
us make web applications more dynamic.
personalized and engaging.
Over the next few minutes, I will
share some real world examples from
my projects, show how these APIs have
driven user engagement, increased
satisfaction and even boosted revenue.
Let's dive in.
Before we get into the details,
here's what we will be covering today.
First, I will introduce modern web
APIs, why they are essential for
UI development, Then we will look
at how APIs have evolved to become
the versatile tools we use today.
Next, I will take you through
three key APIs, the Geolocation
API, the Web Notifications API,
and the Intersection Observer API.
We will explore how each of
them enhances user experience.
We will also compare their strengths.
Discuss how combining APIs can
create richer experiences and
touch on some challenges and best
practices for using them effectively.
Finally, I will wrap up with key
takeaways and a quick look at what's
next in the world of web APIs.
So what exactly are modern web APIs?
They are tools that let us
bring dynamic and interactive
features to web applications.
Within these APIs, we can create user
interfaces that feel personalized and
responsive, similar to native apps.
For example, in one of my e commerce
projects, we used the geolocation API to
show customers nearby stores and paired
it with the web notifications API to alert
them about flash sales in their area.
The result, a 30 percent increase in
user engagement during the campaign.
These APIs are a critical part of
today's web development landscape.
Especially as progressive web apps
continue to blur the line between
web and native applications.
Let's take a step back and
look at how APIs have evolved.
Early APIs were simple.
They could do things like update text
or hide an element on a web page.
Useful, but not particularly interactive.
Today's APIs are more powerful.
They let us access device features.
handle real time interactions and
even create offline experiences.
For example, in one project we used
modern web APIs to build a progressive
web app for an e commerce site.
Customers could browse products
they have previously viewed even
without an internet connection.
This feature was a hit especially during
high traffic periods like Black Friday.
Because it made the shopping experience
smoother and less frustrating.
Let's start with the geolocation API.
This API lets us access a user's location,
with their permission, of course.
It's perfect for creating
location aware experiences.
In one project, we used the Geolocation
API for an outdoor gear retailer.
Based on the user's location and
local weather, we recommended hiking
gear that suited their environment.
This made the experience
feel personal and relevant.
And we saw a 20 percent
increase in conversions.
But it's not just about functionality.
Privacy and user trust are critical.
Always explain why you are
requesting location data and
ensure it's handled securely.
In another project, we added
a fallback option for users to
manually enter their zip code.
This simple addition helped
retain 15 percent of users who
initially denied location access.
Next up is the Web Notifications API.
which is all about keeping users engaged.
This API lets you send push
notifications to users even
when they are not on your site.
For an e commerce client, we
implemented price drop alerts for
wishlist items using this API.
These personalized notifications drove a
25 percent increase in click through rates
and generated over hundreds of thousands
in revenue during the holiday season.
That said, you need to be
careful with notifications.
Overusing them can lead to user fatigue.
That's why it's important to let users
customize their notification preferences
and to time your messages strategically.
For example, sending reminders during
lunch breaks or evenings doubled
engagement in one of our campaigns.
The Intersection Observer API might not
sound glamorous, but it's a powerhouse
when it comes to optimizing performance.
It tracks when elements
enter or leave the viewport.
making it perfect for lazy
loading and triggering animations.
For a fashion retailer, we used this
API to lazy load product images.
Instead of loading everything up
front, images were loaded only
when the user scrolled to them.
This reduced page load times by 35
percent and directly led to a 12
percent boost in mobile conversions.
This API isn't just about speed.
It's about creating a smooth,
enjoyable experience that keeps
users engaged, especially on mobile
devices when performance is crucial.
Let's take a quick look
at how these APIs compare.
The Geolocation API provides
user location, making content
and navigation more personalized.
The Web Notifications API engages users in
real time, driving them back to your site.
The Intersection Observer API optimizes
performance by reducing resource usage.
Each API plays a special role,
but together, they create a
toolkit for building responsive
and interactive applications.
Now, what happens when
you combine these APIs?
You get powerful synergies that take
user experience to the next level.
For a home goods retailer, we combined
the geolocation API to identify users
near stores, the web notifications
API to send alerts about in store
promotions, the intersection observer
API to animate banners as users scrolled.
This integration increased food traffic
by 30% and boosted local sales by 20%.
It's a great example of how APIs
working together can create a
seamless and engaging experience.
Of course, APIs aren't
without their challenges.
Privacy is a big one.
Users need to know how their
data is being used and must
feel confident that it's secure.
Always be transparent and comply
with the regulators like GDPR.
Another challenge is avoiding
notification fatigue.
Be thoughtful about how often you
send notifications and allow users
to control their preferences.
Finally, performance is key,
especially on mobile devices.
Using the Intersection Observer API to
manage resource loading has been a game
changer in many of my projects, ensuring
speed without sacrificing functionality.
To wrap things up, modern web APIs like
geolocation, web notifications, and
intersection observer have revolutionized
how we build web applications.
They help us create experiences
that are faster, more engaging,
and deeply personalized.
By combining these tools thoughtfully, we
can deliver applications that rival native
apps in functionality and performance.
And this is just the beginning.
Emerging technologies like AR,
VR, and AI powered APIs promise to
push user engagement even further.
Thank you for joining me today.
I would love to hear your thoughts
or questions about these APIs and
how they can be used to create
even better user experiences.