Good morning, everyone.
it's a pleasure to be here today to
discuss an exciting and transformative
topic, the growth and potential
of the Internet of Things or IOT.
IOT is shaping industries, creating
new opportunities and fundamentally
changing how we interact with
technology in our daily lives.
But as promising as IOT is,
It's growth is far from simple.
Today, I'll walk you through the
opportunities, challenges, and
strategies that define the IOT landscape.
We'll explore the
importance of user insights.
personalization, and collaboration.
And I'll share examples that show how IOT
companies are creating meaningful value.
Let's begin by looking at the big picture.
So why IOT growth is complex?
The IOT market.
is expanding rapidly.
By 2030, it's expected to connect 24.
1 billion devices and generate 1.
5 trillion dollars in revenue.
This growth is impressive,
but it also fragmented.
Devices are used in diverse
sectors like media, smart grids,
connected vehicles, and lightning.
Each sector has unique
requirements, making scalability
and integration complex.
Additionally, consumer applications
dominate revenue, but industry Like
healthcare or else is significant.
Interestingly, that 66 percent of IOT
revenue comes from services, but not
hardware showing the need for ongoing
customer engagement, geographically,
China, North America, and Europe lead the
way each with union, unique challenges
like compliance and localization
to navigate these complexities.
Companies must focus on more than numbers.
They must deeply understand user
needs and create long term value.
So what does this focus
on user needs mean?
Success in IOT comes from balancing user
needs, data analytics, and innovation.
First, products must solve real problems,
whether it's ensuring security at home
or streamlining business operations.
Second, IOT devices generate
massive amounts of behavioral
data which can uncover unmet
needs and market opportunities.
And third, these data drives hyper
personalized solutions, enabling companies
to stand out in competitive markets.
In essence, IOT breaches the gap between
data collection and actionable insights,
allowing companies to adapt quickly.
to changing user behaviors.
Personalization doesn't just improve
customer satisfaction, it creates loyalty.
So start with the target audience, really.
Let's dive deeper into
understanding your audience.
IoT users fall into three key groups.
Of course, first of all, families who
want simplicity and safety like smart home
devices, for example, for energy savings.
Of course, businesses.
which prioritizes efficiency and
scalability through industrial IOT
solution and industries such as
health care, for example, focusing on
innovation and workflow integration.
By addressing these groups specific
pain points, IOT products can increase
user satisfaction and retention.
This approach not only builds trust, but
also improves return on investment by
allying solutions with real world needs.
So in this context, of course, behavioral
insights should be a gold mine.
Understanding behavior is a
game changer for IOT companies.
IOT devices generate detailed insights.
like usage patterns and preferences
which can guide innovation.
For example, Smart thermostat
might reveal when user adjusts
temperature, enabling the creation of
productive features that save energy.
Behavioral data also help refine
existing products or Inspired new ones.
With IOT adoption expected to exceed
100 billion devices by 2050, staying
ahead of evolving demands is critical.
Insights ensure that businesses
stay competitive and deliver
hyper personalized experiences.
This brings us to micro targeting.
IOT's superpower for
personalizing user experience.
Think of iot user as a pyramid.
General users want basic functionality
like a smart home system with easy setup.
Segmented groups such as energy
conclusions user benefit from tailored
energy saving features and micro
segments like frequent travelers.
Needs specialized options
like remote device management.
A thermostat company, for example,
could solve general users with basic
features while offering AI drive and
energy saving tools to niche segment
personalization builds satisfaction
and retention across all user levels.
Let's shift gears to another
critical aspect, turning
problems into opportunities.
It's a real great one.
Every frustration users face
is a chance to innovate, is a
chance to create something new.
Listening to complaints helps uncover
gaps and guides impactful solution.
Case study.
For example, Nest, Tramastat,
Nest users often found manual
temperature adjustment tedious.
So Nest introduced auto schedule, which
allows user to Preferences and adjust
automatically the result, a seamless
experience and around 12 percent savings
on heating costs by solving pain points.
Nest didn't just fix a problem,
it create lasting of value.
So to create such impactful products,
engaging with your community is essential.
Users aren't just customers,
they are your co creators.
Regular service, beta testing, forums.
allow companies to listen and
involve users in shaping solution.
For example, when users contribute
ideas or test prototypes, they
feel valued, which builds loyalty.
Community collaboration often leads
to fresh, user centered innovations
that drive continuous improvement.
The innovation process begins with data.
First, collect user interactions and
identify patterns, then translate
these raw data into insights
that highlight opportunities.
Next, align ideas with these
insights to brainstorm solutions,
and finally, test prototypes with
user and inter aid based on feedback.
This build test learn loop ensures
IoT products involve in the line
with users demands and needs.
Stay relevant in dynamic markets.
So I also told about, the behavior
driving innovation from the nest
thermostat, really the result and
the savings, Around 12 percent of
heating cost is a great result.
Behavioral insights allow companies
like Nest to anticipate needs
and deliver meaningful solution.
how do we get from
ideas to market success?
Prototyping is a key.
Of course, so we should start with a MVP
that address one core problem, just one.
Then test it with real users, gather
feedback, and refine based on insights.
This agile approach reduces risk and
ensures solutions align with market needs.
IOT isn't limited to a single market.
It creates opportunity in medicine,
agriculture, energy, automotive
industries, and Lots of different others.
For example, Medtronic uses IOD to enable
insulin pumps to improve patient outcomes.
John Deere optimizes yields
with smart farming equipment.
Tesla enhances vehicle performance
with over the air software updates.
By identifying gaps in these
sectors, IOD companies can
expand the reach of patients.
And impact
on next one is about collaboration.
And innovation.
So innovation thrives on collaboration.
Startups like WiseLabs bring agility
while corporates like Amazon offer scales.
Universities drive cutting edge
research and open source communities
enable rapid prototyping.
Together, these partnerships
accelerate product development and
bring IoT solutions to market faster.
So in general.
About IOT ecosystem approach, IOT success
depends on building a robust ecosystem.
This includes devices that are
scalable, applications with user
friendly interfaces, services that
monetize effectively, and data
that drives real time improvements.
A holistic ecosystem maximizes value
and ensures sustainable growth.
Emerging technologies like AI, 5G, and
blockchain are key drivers of IOT future.
AI and machine learning?
in general, AI processes large
IOT datasets in real time,
enabling smarter decisions and
personalized user experience.
For example, productive maintenance
systems powered by AI reduce
equipment downtime and cost.
Coast 5G connective 5G in
general 5G and 5G connectivity.
5G enables faster, low latency connections
critical for autonomous vehicles and smart
cities where a data transfer is essential.
Blockchain for security for 100%.
Blockchain Ensure Secure
for example.
like health care and finances
where privacy is critical.
Really, this technology
is from the, backbone of
scalable, secure and efficient.
I ought solutions.
The future of IOT lies in
creating a connected, sustainable
and user focused world.
First of all, Hyperconnected ecosystems.
IOT will integrate across
industries and regions.
Smart cities will enhance urban
living while healthcare IOT will
improve remote care and diagnostics.
Sustainability.
Next one, IOT will drive environment
change through energy efficient
devices, smart grids and precision
farming and empowered users.
IOT will anticipate user needs, offering
seamless, hyper personalized experience.
This vision of IOT.
Positions.
I ought to not just connect devices,
but to transform leaves and solve global
challenges, emerging technologies.
And this vision for the future
underscore the incredible potential
of IOT, but leveraging these tools
and working towards shared vision
companies can create solutions that
are both innovative and meaningful.
Now.
Let's conclude with key takes away.
IOT offers immense potential,
but success lies in understanding
user needs, leveraging data,
and fostering collaboration.
By aligning innovation with these
principles, companies can create
solutions that aren't just technologically
advanced, but truly meaningful for users.
Thank you.
I'm happy to take your question.