Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 Internet
of Things IoT 2024.
My name is Dilshan Rabbi Kasani and
welcome to my session on digital twins.
So the session I'll be covering today
is about the transformative role of
digital twins for network resiliency
and fault tolerance in IoT systems.
As IoT systems grow and evolve,
the increasing complexity of
managing the networks for those
systems increases as well.
digital twins can offer solutions.
for these problems.
So let's dive right in.
today I plan to cover, give a brief
introduction about what digital
twins are, what is network resiliency
and what is fault tolerance and
why these are important and how
digital twins can enhance them.
I'll touch up briefly on what
digital twins are, and the role
of digital twins in this, network
resiliency and fault tolerance.
I'll also provide some use cases, in
IOT systems and advantages of using
digital twins and, implementation
challenges of digital twins as well.
and I'll conclude with future directions
and what to use within digital twins.
So let's get started.
so we are currently living in an age of
smart, meaning that every system around
us, we prefer to have it as smart system.
Either it's smartwatch or smart car
or smart city or whatever, right?
as we go towards the smart approach
and smart mindset, there are many
complex IOT systems that are involved.
which need to be always interconnected
with each other and transfer
data to the appropriate systems.
So to support these systems, what we need
to do is to simulate and troubleshoot
any issues with the IOT systems, right?
So coming to the IOT architecture.
So you'll have your usual sensors,
actuators, and smart devices, which
are transmitting always the accurate
amount of data that it's required
to digitally simulate, systems.
So you have, you'll have your gateways
and you'll collect all this data and
store it in a data lake somewhere.
And once you have all this
is a traditional approach in
machine learning too, right?
Where you'll get your data, you'll clean
it and you'll put it in a data warehouse.
And then perform some kind of machine
learning or, build some models
around that, predicting failures or,
predicting any issues with the systems.
So, you'll have your control
applications, your models, your
machine learning, your data analytics.
And, at the end of the day,
What you really need is
everything working together.
so coming to network resiliency.
So what basically network resiliency
means is, the ability of the network
to withstand and recover, quickly
from disruptions and failures.
So in case of a network disruption
or a failure, the network
needs to come back up, right?
Okay.
When you have smartwatch a
smartphone, you know how it feels
when, it goes out of network, right?
So you always need that quick, turnaround
of connecting back to the network.
And, in case of any failures you
need, for it to connect back, as well.
and the capacity of the network,
you need the network to come back
up fastly and adapt and continue.
So not just.
Basically, the same thing
happening twice, right?
So you'll want the system to learn
basically what happened by simulating
it in the backend, either through some
data lake or some machine learning model.
So you'll need this
information in the backend.
So network resiliency, meaning that,
the network needs to withstand and
recover quickly from the disruptions.
So importance of network resilience.
you need to minimize the downtime.
So we all face downtimes.
But, what, the companies need to do
or what the systems need to be in a
shape where it reduces the downtime.
So you want as much downtime,
as minimal downtime as possible.
So you need to reduce the
service, interruptions.
and you need to ensure the
operations are continuous.
you need to protect the
data as well, right?
So once your network is down or
some system is done, there'll be a
multitude of, vulnerabilities that you
will be exposed to, which you need to
quickly, recover, or you'll be subject
to information loss or corruption,
during the outages, data corruption.
So you need to maintain
the productivity as well.
So even though you.
users lose some kind of network,
access, you still want them to
perform some kind of things, right?
And all of this, the things that I talk
about in terms of, a digital connectivity.
So this is a basic digital connectivity
that everyone needs to have.
And I'll discuss later about how
digital twins can enhance this.
So enhance customer satisfaction.
So customers need to have the
uninterrupted service, and
increased customer satisfaction
or you lose customers, right?
And fault tolerance.
So this is similar to, network
resilience, but what fault tolerance
is, even if a part of the system
fails, rest of the system can
function, as smoothly as possible.
So some parts of the system
fail and everything goes on.
That's not a good experience, right?
So you want to minimize the
downtime of, applications as well.
you want to improve the reliability.
So the systems need to be more dependable.
and it's not very easy for IOT systems
to be, simulated because the complexity
of, so let's say if you have, a hundred
thousand or some big amount of a number
of IOT system connected together.
It's hard to simulate all the
systems where failure, happens.
So that's where digital trends can help.
protect protecting, data.
during failures, you want to have a
backup mechanism and, Some kind of
mechanism where data corruption doesn't
happen and, failure doesn't happen.
So role of fault tolerance,
in minimizing disruption.
continued operation.
So you have to enable systems to
function when, some components
fail and, prevent complete outages.
So where you can't even access the system.
you want to reduce the downtime.
So all of the service interruptions
that happen, you want to reduce that.
So this is similar to network resiliency,
where, in fault tolerance, what we talk
about is it's, it's a system's capability
of coming up, even when a component fails.
Right and Reliability, so Overall
reliability and dependability of
the systems are also important and
protecting the Critical information of
the customers when our failures happen
and enhancing the customer experience
This is what the fault tolerance Role
is in minimizing the disruptions.
So coming to the actual core
of the topic Digital twins.
So what are digital twins?
So digital twins are nothing but a virtual
replica of the actual physical system.
So you have your physical system, let's
say that a manufacturing system or a
component or a service or anything, right?
So you have all of the data of the
physical system where you can build
a virtual replica of it in the
cloud or on prem where it digitally.
So it's a digital representation
of a physical object.
so the, thing with the digital
twin is you need real time data.
So continuously, you need to
update the physical, digital system
with the physical systems data.
So all of the data that you have
in the physical system, you'll
store it, in near real time.
And you'll build a digital twin.
digital twin out of it.
So this can help you in
a multitude of reasons.
So you, for any simulation, right?
you can simulate, a failure
happening within a particular
system, digitally without having
any impact on the physical system.
So this way you can set up a feedback
loop where in digital systems, you can,
experiment with multitude of, parameters.
and have the changes implemented
in the physical system.
So this can help the decision making
process where you perform multiple
number of tests in the digital twin
and implement in the real system.
examples of the digital twins are
manufacturing equipment, where
you have multiple number of.
pieces, IOT systems.
And once you get all of the data
in a place somewhere, you can
build a digital twin out of it.
And you can have an exact replica
of your physical system, digitally.
So buildings, infrastructure, supply
chain, human bodies, even in healthcare
can be represented, digitally.
So coming to the types of digital twins, a
manufacturing component or, within an IoT
system are, a simple piece of equipment.
You can have all this together.
in the.
digital realm and have it as a
digital twin of your physical system.
you can have either assets so you
can, it can be a car, an aeroplane
or, some kind of smart device where
you can have it, digitally, somewhere.
So process.
So even the process can be,
digital made as a digital twin.
So for example, you have a manufacturing
process that runs somewhere, from
point A to point B, you can take
all of the steps and all of the IOT
systems involved in that process
and get the data out of the systems.
and make a digital twin out of it.
So you can do it for the systems
and network of systems as well.
So let's say you have a multiple number
of systems that are connected together.
anywhere you can get the data
out of the IOT system, you can
make a digital twin out of it.
So here is a digital twin life cycle.
So as I mentioned, data is at
the heart of the digital twin.
first step is to collect the data.
So any system you have, you'll
basically collect the data.
You'll save the data somewhere,
you'll transmit the data and
you store the data somewhere.
So once you have the data stored for
all of your systems that you require,
you'll evaluate and analyze the
data with multitude of parameters.
So you can simulate
the parameters as well.
So for example, if you have, a
Tesla car or, any car, you can.
crash it a hundred times, right?
So in the digital world, what you can
do is you can run a simulation that
you can, based on the parameters.
So what happens if I crash it in this
way and the parameter of X is something.
So you can have multiple parameters
where you can adjust these
parameters and test it out digitally.
You can evaluate.
The simulations and based on the
simulations, what you can do is
connect back to the physical system.
So now, once you have the results
and you have some parameters, now
let's say you want to make a change.
So you'll link back to
the physical system.
So this is a continuous loop.
Where you're from collection
of data to updating the system.
So this feedback loop, you can automate
the feedback loop as well, where
you have a data linkage in between.
So once the data link is established
and you have all the process set up.
Based on some parameters, you can simulate
something, and you can basically, update
the setting back to the physical system.
coming to the challenges in IoT networks,
as, IoT networks grow and evolve, so the
complexity of the system evolves as well.
so number of interconnected devices.
Now, everything you have, you wanted
to be connected to each other, either
it's your phone, watch, earphones.
and this is, this increases
with the IOT systems as well.
So where you have multiple number of
devices that needs to stay connected
together to perform accurately.
So as it increases, as the
number of systems increase, the,
complexity increases as well.
And the protocols with
which they communicate with
each other differs as well.
And the standards with which
they communicate change as well.
as these interdependencies
increase, the complexity increases.
and all of this can be performed
within a digital world without having
any impact on the physical world.
that's where digital twins really
help in maintaining IoT systems.
real time data dependency.
So some critical applications
within IoT systems require real
time data for optimal performance.
So that is a challenge as well.
that I'll cover in the
digital twin section as well.
So network latency.
So all of the systems to stay
connected together, the systems
need to be connected very fast.
So network has to be.
really fast and the connection
speeds has to be really fast.
network latency is another issue as well.
So some failures, so let's say if you have
a network outage or a packet loss or high
latency, this can disrupt the operations.
for your systems, where you can, where
digital twins help in, simulating this.
So security vulnerabilities.
So all of your security
devices, you can simulate it.
let's say your firewall goes down, right?
So physically, it's really hard for you
to test that out when you have actual
users in the system, where virtually
digital twins make this easy, where you
can simulate a firewall going down and
make choices based on these parameters.
Scalability.
So as IOT systems grow in, scale,
scale, managing and maintaining
these systems increase as well.
and limitations to the
traditional methods.
So rather than having proactive approach,
for fault management, you can have a
simulated experience in the digital
involved and have the systems upgraded
automatically in a feedback loop.
and it's also difficult in predicting
and preventing complex failures.
And if you have a large IoT
ecosystem, it's hard to visualize
the entire system way physically.
So if you have it in digital,
it's easy to, visualize right and
make decisions based on those.
So digital twins in network
resiliency and fault tolerance.
How can this help?
How can digital twins help in network
resiliency and fault tolerance for
the limitations that we saw earlier?
You can do a proactive failure detection
so you can identify any potential
issues, either simulating a variant
error of IoT systems or network
congestion or before they occur.
So you can predict what's going
to happen when let's say 100, 000
users attack your network or use
your network or use your system.
You can simulate that and
have systems ready in place.
and you can analyze the data patterns.
So this is on par with the traditional
machine learning and data science
model as well, where you can use
traditional data science and machine
learning within the digital pins and
simulate those, results and update
the systems back, physical systems.
So predictive maintenance, so forecasting,
equipment failures, and, you can schedule
maintenance proactively without, having
any impact on the physical systems.
So you can, traditionally how
it's done is, you collect all the
data and you have it somewhere,
but that's just a store of data.
and not a physical system within itself.
So a digital, a replica of
the physical system, as such.
But you'll have a big table of data and
you'll perform some machine learning,
you'll predict your analytics and
whatnot and update the physical system.
With the digital twins, what you
can do is to set up a feedback loop.
and have that, help, with the network
resilience and fault tolerance.
So disaster recovery, so you can,
simulate the disaster scenarios where, for
example, a natural, calamity occurs, like
earthquakes or floods, and you can assess,
you can physically, It's physically, it's
impossible to, simulate these rights.
You can, in the digital world,
it's easy to simulate these.
So you can simulate, what happens
when an earthquake or flood happens.
You have various systems, all are
interconnected and assess the impact
of the critical infrastructure.
and use cases, coming to the use cases,
there are multiple use cases for the
IoT systems where you can have, smart
cities, industrial IoT and healthcare IoT.
So within the smart cities, you can
have energy grids where you can optimize
the energy distribution of the grid.
you can predict the, blackouts
or any service interruptions.
and you can integrate, renewable
energy sources as well.
So for transportation systems, you
can improve the flow of traffic.
You can simulate based on the
physical data, physical traffic data.
You can capture all the physical data
and have it, simulate in a digital
environment, a digital twin of traffic.
So remember I mentioned you
can do a process as well.
So all of the traffic that flows through a
certain point, you can have that process.
As a digital twin and simulate what
happens and simulate the number of,
accidents or, anything that can happen.
and you can optimize the
traffic based on that.
You can optimize the public transport
as well, where in holiday time or
in a high flowing area, you can
predict, based on the digital twins.
You can set up simulation scenarios and,
Prevent those, public transport issues
and enhance the roads have safety as well.
So coming to industrial IOT,
coming to predictive maintenance.
So you can, predict the machinery health
or equipment failures based on all
of the IOT systems that are connected
to, a modern machinery system, right?
equipment site so you can predict
all these equipment failures and
schedule the maintenance a accordingly.
so optimizing, process optimization, you
can, improve the efficiency of a process,
reduce waste, or enhanced product quality.
You count this, you call this,
lean manufacturing, right?
Where you have green
manufacturing, lean manufacturing.
where you, improve efficiency, reduce
the waste that you produce, and you
can enhance product quality as well.
So coming to healthcare, healthcare
has some, really interesting, digital
twin scenarios as well, where you
can monitor a patient health remotely
by, creating a physical, a digital
replica of the patient's health.
So this helps you in early intervention.
And, if any critical life support
systems are needed or any medical devices
are needed, this can help as well.
So coming to the implementation
challenges, so there are, some challenges
in implementing digital twins as well.
so data integration and interoperability.
So connecting data from, collecting
and integrating data from different
sources is a challenge as well.
So you have your thousands of hundreds
of thousands of millions of sensors.
you'll have to collect those data and
you'll have to make sure that the network
that the data is transported to is
seamless and store the data somewhere.
you will have your databases,
your APIs and whatnot.
So you have to ensure the
data consistency, accuracy
and interoperability, across
the different systems as well.
So scalability, so scaling digital
twin models, is a challenge as well.
handling the complexity and computational
demands of large scale IoT deployments,
with, Increasing IOT system, it's hard
to manage it in the digital twin as well.
forget about managing it
physically, but, digitally it's
really hard to manage as well.
deploying scalable for complex systems.
So you have a million devices, and all of
those are, in the form of a digital twin.
it's.
It's okay to perform some kind of metrics
or, some kind of simulations based on
that, but it's really harder to have, that
feedback loop, for millions of systems.
So the scalability within the
digital twins is hard as well.
So real time synchronization.
So this is challenged with every system,
not just digital twins, but, you'll at
least have to have a near real time.
data ingestion loop, where you
synchronize the data between your
physical system and the digital system.
So that is a challenge, for
the digital twins as well.
And you have to ensure your virtual
model actually, accurately reflects the
current state of the real world system.
Now you have all of your million
devices or, however many systems
you have in the digital world.
Setting up those systems initially
will be a challenge as well, where
you need to set up the way that
it's exactly in the physical world.
So that can be a challenge as well.
But I think to conclude this session.
let's dive into the future directions
so you can use machine learning and
AI and integrate it into the digital
twins, and, power your decision making.
you can have digital twins that
can make autonomous decision based
on real time data and predictions
and set up a loop for that.
That's a loop that I talked
about where you can, simulate
the systems and you can make it.
take some autonomous stations and
implement in the physical system.
leverage of the 6G networks.
So now, with the ITU, guidelines,
providing for 6G networks, the
bandwidth and, network connectivity.
for these systems will be,
very much faster and, higher.
So to enhance real time, data exchange,
6G can be used for digital twins as well.
exploring, UR LLC, ultra available,
low latency communication for
mission critical systems, mission
IoT systems can be used as well.
So these are some, things that can
enhance the digital twin experience.
And cross industry applications.
So you can have it, in multiple,
cross industries where one of the
system that you have physically is
in one industry and the other system
that you have is in other industry.
So cross industry, can be, another, future
direction for digital twins as well.
So in this talk to conclude in this
talk, we have covered a digital
twins, how they help IOT systems, how
they help reduce network resiliency
and fault tolerance in IOT systems.
And how can you enhance your IOT
systems based on digital twins?
Thank you for coming to my talk and
you can connect with me on LinkedIn.
You can type in Dileesh Chandra
Bikasani and thanks for attending
this conference with me.