Hello everyone and welcome
to Con 42 IoT Conference.
I'm Chakradar Sunkeswala, an
engineering manager with nearly two
decades of experience in building
cloud platforms and applications.
I'm excited to have you here
today as we dive into one of the
most critical topics in tech.
Cloud security with cloud
computing, transforming
industries and driving growth.
It's crucial to understand the
security challenges that come with it.
I'm looking forward to share an innovative
multi layered security framework that
addresses these challenges and ensures
the safety of cloud environments.
Let's get started and I'm and make
the most of this exciting session.
Cloud computing is transforming industries
worldwide, offering unprecedented
scalability, efficiency and innovation.
As business increasingly rely on
cloud technologies, the need to secure
sensitive data and infrastructure
has never been more urgent.
In 2023, global cloud services
spent, spending reached, 545.
8 billion.
and is projected to grow
significantly by 2027.
With this rapid expansion coming, comes a
rise in security risks as well, making the
robust cloud security solutions essential
for protecting modern enterprises.
In this session, we'll explore
a comprehensive multi layered
security framework designed to
address these challenges head on.
As cloud adoption continues
to grow rapidly, Thank you
Organizations are facing a range
of evolving security challenges.
The traditional models are
simply not designed to handle.
In fact, Businesses today experience
an average of 43 cloud security
incidents every month and alarmingly
75 percent of these incidents are
preventable with better security
practices and proactive measures.
Despite this, many companies continue
to rely on outdated perimeter based
security models, which focus on
protecting the network's outer edges.
These models were designed for on premise.
environments and simply don't account
for the complexity and fluidity
of modern cloud infrastructures.
To make matters worse, there is a
global shortage of cybersecurity
professionals with an estimated gap of
around four million skilled workers.
The shortage is putting even more
pressure on the organizations to
secure their cloud environments without
the necessary resources leading to
overworked teams and security gaps.
The combination of these factors,
high volumes of security incidents,
inadequate security models, and staffing
shortages underscore the urgent need
for more advanced, scalable, and
proactive cloud security solutions.
As businesses rely more heavily on cloud
services, They need a robust framework
that addresses these challenges.
One that can scale and adapt
to the rapidly changing
security landscape of cloud.
This is exactly what we are
going to dive into today.
To address the ever evolving
challenges in cloud security, we
have developed a comprehensive
multi layered security framework.
This framework is designed
to provide robust protection
across several critical layers.
Thank you focusing on key aspects that
ensuring the security, resilience,
adaptability of cloud infrastructures.
The framework is built
around four core pillars.
network security, authentication,
authorization, and API security.
Each of these layers is integrated
with advanced security principles like
zero trust, sophisticated detection
mechanisms, and continuous monitoring.
Network security focuses on ensuring that
communication within the cloud is secure.
Implementing measures like segmentation
and dynamic access control to
prevent unauthorized access.
Authentication ensures that
only legitimate users can access
the cloud environment, using
techniques such as sophisticated
profiling and token security.
Authorization enforces the principle
of least privilege, making sure users
only have access to resources they need,
while API security protects the integrity
of communication between services and
preventing vulnerabilities and exploits.
By combining these layers, we create a
holistic defense system that not only
addresses current security risks, but
also adapts to the future threats.
The framework provides a proactive
and a scalable approach to cloud
security, ensuring your organization's
cloud infrastructure remains secure
no matter how fast we evolve.
Network security is a foundational
pillar in protecting cloud
environments, and the concept of zero
trust is central to our approach.
In traditional network security
models, we often assume that once
the user or the devices inside
the network, they can be trusted.
However, with cloud environments being
more dynamic and distributed, we can
no longer afford this assumption.
The zero trust model operates under the
principle of never trust, always verify,
meaning every request is authenticated.
and authorized before granting
access regardless of its origin.
In practice, we implement zero
trust services, isolation,
and dynamic access controls.
Critical components are
segmented into separate subnets.
Front end services, back end services,
and databases are isolated to ensure
that even if an attacker compromises
on one segment, they cannot easily
move laterally across the network.
This approach has resulted
in an 85 percent reduction
in lateral movement attacks.
Furthermore, we enforce dynamic access
control policies where strict IP
routing and traffic rules are applied.
These rules ensure that only
authorized traffic and can interact
with critical cloud services,
significantly reducing the potential
for unauthorized access and R attack.
By adopting these zero trust principles,
we can successfully thwart 99.
97 percent of password and
encryption keys theft attempts.
Providing a robust defense
against common attack vectors.
Beyond the foundational zero trust
principles, our network security
framework incorporates advanced
detection systems to further
strengthen the defense against threats.
One of the key technologies here is
AAML driven traffic analysis, which
continuously monitors network traffic
and analyzes patterns at scale.
By using machine learning algorithms,
we can identify unusual behavior and
potential threats with high accuracy.
These systems have achieved a
92 percent reduction in false
positive, while maintaining 99.
2 percent accuracy in
identifying true threats.
Ensuring that our security team
focuses only on relevant alerts.
Another crucial element in
our detection system is the
implementation of digital tripwires.
These are strategically placed
to detect unauthorized access or
unusual activities in the real time.
When triggered, these tripwires
automatically alert the security
team and the initiate immediate,
containment procedures.
This capability has helped reduce
the threat dwell time to less than 24
hours with automated response systems
neutralizing the threat in less than
15 milliseconds of the detection.
Together, these advanced detection
measures Provide an extra layers of
security that actively identifies
and mitigates risks in real
time, significantly enhancing the
overall resilience of the network.
Authentication is a critical layer
of security in the cloud, and our
approach goes beyond traditional
methods by incorporating sophisticated
user classification system.
Unlike basic username and password
mechanisms, our authentication system.
analyzes user behavior across
multiple dimensions to assess the
legitimacy of the each access attempt.
This includes factors like login
location, device type and usage
path, and even the time of access.
By profiling user behavior in real
time, we can identify the block 99.
7 percent of credential abuse
attempts before they even happen.
We process over 1.
2 million authentication
requests daily with the response
times under 200 milliseconds.
ensuring that the security does not
come at the cost of user experience.
The system is designed to scale
effectively, handling massive
volumes of requests while
maintaining speed and accuracy.
Moreover, our authentication
process is continuously evolving
through adaptive testing.
We simulate new attack vectors and use
AI driven attack simulation to test
and strengthen the system, ensuring
it stays ahead of emerging threats.
This continuously evolution, this
continuous evolution of our user
classification system provides dynamic
real time protection against unauthorized
access, enhancing both security and
efficiency of cloud environments.
Token security is a vital aspect
of authentication, especially
in cloud environments where
scalability and flexibility are key.
Traditional static tokens are
vulnerable to exploitation over time.
So we have implemented a more
dynamic and secure approach using
advanced cryptographic protocols
and distributed trust architectures.
We process over 500, 000 token validations
per minute, ensuring secure authentication
across large scale cloud applications.
Our system uses risk based token
lifetimes, which dynamically adjusts
the validity of a period of each
token based upon user behavior
and other environmental factors.
This drastically reduces the
window of opportunity for
potential token exploitation,
cutting successful exploitation
attempts by 91 percent compared to
traditional fixed lifetime tokens.
In addition to risk based lifetimes,
We manage over a thousand trusted
issuers in real time, verifying
every token as it's issued.
This distributed approach prevents 99.
98 percent of certificate based
attacks, ensuring that only
trusted verified tokens are used to
access sensitive cloud resources.
By combining advanced cryptographic
methods with continuous verification,
we provide highly secure and scalable
authentication that adapts to the
needs of modern cloud environments.
One of the most powerful features
of our authentication system is
the kill switch mechanism, which
provides real time protection
in the event of security breach.
This mechanism allows to instantly
revoke access across all contexts
when suspicious behavior is detected.
It operates in under 100 milliseconds.
ensuring that no compromised credential
can be used to access sensitive systems.
The kill switch works by continuously
analyzing over 30 distinct behavioral
patterns to identify anomalies.
These patterns can include unusual login
times, access from unfamiliar locations,
or abnormal transaction volumes.
When a deviation from the user's typical
behavior is detected, the system triggers
a kill switch, immediately locking
down any potential malicious sessions.
This proactive response has 95.
3 percent accuracy in
identifying unauthorized
activities before they escalate.
The ability to revoke access so quickly
prevents attacker from maintaining a
foothold in the system and significantly
reduces The risk off for their damage.
Additionally, the kill switch is
backed by granular access controls,
allowing us to manage over 1000 distinct
permission combinations, reduces reducing
unauthorized access incidents by 95%.
By combining real time behavior analytics
and rapid access revocation, we add
another layer of defense to protect
cloud environments against Intrusions.
Authorization plays a critical role in
ensuring that users and systems only have
access to the resources they absolutely
need, which is where the principle
of least privilege comes into play.
Our framework enforces this
principle by carefully managing user
permissions and ensuring that access
is continuously evaluated and adjusted
based on real time needs and risks.
We process over 1.
5 million authorization decisions daily.
Ensuring that every access request
is thoroughly checked and validated
against the least privileged standard.
This is especially important in
large dynamic cloud environments,
where the number of users and
resources is constantly changing.
Our system automatically detects
and revokes any excess privileges,
preventing issues like privilege creep,
where users inadvertently accumulate.
more access than they need over time.
Additionally, we ensure audit
compliance by continuously reviewing
and updating permissions to match
the principle of least privilege.
This approach has significantly reduced.
Privilege related audit findings by
95, 91%, allowing organizations to
maintain a secure, compliant cloud
environment without unnecessary
administrative overhead by implementing
granular permission management and
continuous evaluating access levels.
We ensure that users have exactly the
access they need and no more, reducing
the, and, sorry, and reducing this
attack surface and minimizing the risk
of insider threats or accidental misuse.
Reducing the attack surface is critical
part of securing any cloud environment.
And our approach to authorization is
designed to minimize opportunities
for unauthorized access.
By analyzing more than 50 million
daily access events, we can detect
and prevent attempts to exploit
vulnerabilities before they escalate.
One of the key strategies we use
is continuous permission auditing.
This allows us to identify and
revoke excessive privileges
and permissions quickly.
We use advanced segmentation techniques
to limit the scope of access.
Which means, even if an attacker
compromises one part of the
network, they can't easily move
laterally to access other resources.
This access scope limitation reduces
the time it takes to detect unauthorized
access, cutting detection times from
127 hours to less than 3 minutes.
In addition, we employ dynamic privilege
adjustments, processing more than 3
million privilege modifications daily,
based on real time risk assessments.
This ensures that the user is, user
access is constantly aligned with the
current security posture and unnecessary
privileges are promptly revoked.
These measures combined with rapid
privilege revocation have reduced the
average time to revoke compromised
privileges from 12 hours to under less
than 50 milliseconds, significantly
improving response times and minimizing
the window of opportunity for attackers.
APIs are the backbone of modern
cloud applications, enabling
communication between services, but
they also represent a major attack
vector, if not properly secure.
To mitigate these risks, we have
implemented a comprehensive API
request validation system that
processes billions of requests daily.
Our system is designed to prevent 99.
97 percent of attempted exploits while
ensuring minimal impact on performance.
processing 2.
3 billion API requests per day with the
response times under 50 milliseconds.
This is achieved through a combination
of schema enforcement, rate limiting,
and advanced input sanitization.
Schema enforcement ensures that
all incoming requests strictly
adhere to predefined data formats,
reducing the likelihood of malicious
input bypass security checks.
In addition, rate limiting protects
against denial of service attacks
by ensuring that APIs can only
handle a certain amount of requests
within a certain time frame.
This protects the backend system from
being overwhelmed and maintains stability.
Finally, advanced input sanitization is
used to Prevent common attacks such as
SQL injection or cross site scripting.
By ensuring that all users inputs
are thoroughly sanitized before being
processed, by incorporating these measures
into API, into our API security layer, we
ensure that only safe, legitimate requests
are processed, providing a first line
of defense against malicious activity.
While validating API requests is
essential, it's equally important to
detect unusual behavior in real time
to prevent sophisticated attacks.
Our anomaly detection system leverages
advanced machine learning models trained
on more than 500 billion API requests to
identify unusual patterns and behaviors.
These models analyze over 1 million
requests per second, evaluating
235 distinct parameters for each
transaction to ensure accuracy
and depth in threat detection.
One of the standard features of this
system is dynamic baseline monitoring.
which continuously learns and
adjusts thresholds based on
a real time usage patterns.
With 89 distinct API usage patterns
tracked, the system can differentiate
between normal fluctuations in
behavior and genuine threats.
This approach has reduced false positives
by 94%, ensuring security teams focus
their efforts on legitimate incidents.
Additionally, the system maintains a 99.
99 percent detection rate for
genuine security incidents.
Offering Unparallel unparalleled
reliability by proactively identifying
and responding to anomalies.
This layer of framework adds an extra
layer to of security, especially against
zero day vulnerabilities or novel attacks,
attack vector that may not yet be known.
These capabilities ensure that our APIs
remain not only functional and performant,
but also secure against evolving threats.
Our multi layered security framework has
had a profound impact on how organizations
secure their cloud environments.
By combining advanced technologies
with scalable security principles,
we have achieved remarkable results.
For instance, the framework provides a 99.
97 percent detection rate for
sophisticated attacks, reducing
the detection times by 94 percent
compared to traditional systems.
These improvements not only
enhance security, but also
drastically lower costs.
With organizations reporting an average
of 76 percent reduction in the cost.
per security incident.
What makes this framework particularly
effective is its adaptability.
It is designed to evolve alongside
emerging threats, ensuring
it remains relevant as cloud
environments grow more complex.
Featuring features like, dynamic
privilege adjustments, machine learning
driven anomaly detection, and zero trust
principles ensure that the framework
continuously meet, continuous to
meet the security needs of tomorrow.
Looking ahead, the focus is more
on integrating AI driven automation
to predict and prevent potential
threats before they materialize.
This includes leveraging advanced
analytics for proactive threat modeling
and using real time telemetry to gain
even deeper insights into cloud behavior.
Ultimately, this framework isn't just
about addressing current challenges.
It's about setting a new
benchmark for cloud security.
As we continue to innovate, this
adaptable and scalable approach will help
organizations stay ahead of the curve.
Microsoft Ensuring that their cloud
infrastructure remains secure,
resilient, and cost efficient.
Thank you all for taking the time
to join me today and explore the
critical challenges and innovative
solutions in the cloud security.
As we have seen, securing cloud
environments requires more
than just traditional methods.
It demands a proactive,
multi layered approach that
evolves with emerging threats.
I hope this session has provided you
with valuable insights into how our
framework addresses these challenges,
offering a robust, scalable, and
adaptive solutions for cloud security.
If you have any questions or
would like to discuss these ideas
further, feel free to reach out.
Let's continue the conversation and
work together to shape a safer and more
resilient future for cloud computing.
Thank you.