Hello everyone.
My name is Raju and I bring over 18
years of specialized exp experience
in mainframe based core banking
systems with deep expertise in
systematics and vision plus products.
Throughout my career, I have worked
ex extensively on core banking
modernization, credit card processing,
large scale conversions, and high
availability production support
across major financial institutions.
My background includes leading end-to-end
modernization initiatives, designing
scalable mainframe to cloud integrations
and delivering complex migration programs.
Experience that directly aligns with
today's theme of decoupling legacy
banking, modular core strategies that
drive speed, scale, and innovation.
With this background, I'm excited to
walk you through the presentation on how
modular core strategies microservices API,
firsted design, doing driven architectures
and phased migration can significantly
enhance agility, reside, and long-term
growth for financial institutions.
The.
Where innovation goes to die.
So the biggest challenge for
most banks is the overwhelming
dependency on the legacy systems.
These systems were built decades ago,
and while they are served the industry
well, they have become extremely.
Costly and rigid.
A large portion of the IT budgets
is sometimes 60 to 80% is spent
just keeping the systems running.
That means very little funding is left
for innovation or digital transformations.
Legacy architectures also
slow down time to market.
Slow down time.
Slow down time to market.
Every simple changes requires long
testing cycles, and carries high risk.
Traditional banks ends up innovating
at a much slower rate compared
to a digital native companies.
They simply can't move fast enough.
To compete in a world where new fintechs
are introducing products every few weeks,
legacy based banks are often stuck with
release cycles of months or even years.
So the legacy systems becomes
more than a technical burden.
It becomes a strategic burden
that limits long-term good.
To address these problems, we conducted
extensive research across global
institutions, the research foundation.
Our analysis, not theoretical,
it's grounded in global research
involving financial institutions
across multiple countries.
We studied their modernization
journeys, evaluated performance metrics,
and tracked the transformational
outcomes over several years.
Like evidence showed a clear pattern.
Institutions that adopted modular
architectures outperformed those that did.
We measured speed.
Cost efficiency, innovation,
output, digital adoption, and
customer experience improvements.
These insights from this research
from the foundation for the strategies
and outcomes I'll share today.
Now, let's look at what happens
when banks move from monolithic
to modular architecture.
Legacy systems are typically monolith.
So this means everything
is tightly coupled.
Core banking, payments, customers,
accounts, customer accounts, card
systems, and more like because
everything is interdependent.
A change in one component often requires
updates across the entire system.
That increases risk and slows deployment.
So modular outreaches breakdown
this monolith into separate,
confidential services.
Each module handles its own
business capability and can
be updated independently.
This approach enables flexibility.
Banks can adapt to new technologies
without rewriting the whole system.
It also enhances reside
issues in one area.
Don't bring down the
entire core system overall.
Mod modularization of transforms
overall modularization of.
Transforms the way teams works,
or sorry, speeding up delivery
and reducing dependencies.
This shift directly improves deployment
and speed and innovation velocity.
Deployment velocity deployment
velocity is one of the most significant
benefits of modular architectures
like the traditional banks release
updates infrequently, sometimes once
per quarter or even once per year.
Also without modularization
and mo microservices releases
cycles shrink dramatically.
Like teams can push updates
weekly or even daily.
Frequent deployments mean faster
response to customer needs, regulatory
changes, and market dynamics.
It also encourages experimentation.
Banks can test new features on smaller
customer groups, gather feedback
and it rate some things that legacy
system make nearly impossible.
Faster deployment, faster innovation,
high, higher competitiveness.
They all are.
Improve speed also translate.
From a financial perspective
modernization pay off in several ways.
First, total cost of
ownership reduces gradually.
Banks less spends less on maintenance
infrastructure and vendors purport.
Second time to market improves,
allowing banks to launch new
products faster and capture market
opportunities before competitors.
Third, which modular systems,
multiple teams can work in parallel.
This reduces project timelines
and operational bottlenecks.
Fourth, optimized testing and automation,
reduce operational overhead and
increases reliability when combined.
These outcomes delivers millions
in a cost savings and create
room for new revenue streams.
Let's look at the strategies
that successful institutions
adopt to modernize their banks.
There are four strategic pillars
that consistently produce
successful modernization outcomes.
First is strangler pattern In
this pattern replaces legacy
components in small increments.
Instead of risky big bang migrations,
the old system is gradually replaced
while business operations continue.
Uninterrupted domain driven designs.
These are, this ensures that
the technology structure
reflects the business structure.
Like clear domain boundaries
allows team to own and evolve
their models independently.
API first development APIs access
is standard communication layer,
enabling seamless integration with
partners, FinTech and internal systems.
A PA fast banks innovate much
faster and unlock new ecosystem.
Opportunities, microservices,
architecture, microservices allow
fi, fine-grained scaling, flexible
deployments, improved fault isolations.
Each service evolves independently
enabling more agility.
These strategies aren't just
theories, they translate into real
operational invest improvements too.
Operational ex excellence.
Through decoupling dec decoupling systems
results in major operational benefits.
Reliability improves because
failures are isolated.
They no longer cascade
across entire system.
Integration defects reduce because
APIs define clear contracts and
expectations, like compliance
becomes faster and simpler.
Modular systems require smaller
audit scopes and easier traceability.
When operation stabilizes team
can focus less on firefighting and
more on innovation and modernizing
impacts more than operations.
It directly drives revenues,
revenue, and market impact.
Modernized banks significantly outperform
legacy banks in revenue growth.
They introduce innovative products such
as digital banking, instant payments,
personalized offers much faster.
This attracts a larger share of
digital customer, first customers who
are fast growing customer segment.
The customer acquisition cost goes down
while customer satisfaction goes up.
So the difference in this competitiveness
between modernized and non modernized
becomes more obvious year after year.
So the questions most leader ask is, does
modernization deliver long term ROIs?
The answer is yes.
That is returns on the investment.
The business case modernization.
Del was strong, ROI, particularly
over three to five years of period
because savings come from reduced
maintenance, lower infrastructure
costs, and optimized workflows.
New revenues come from
digital pro product.
API partnerships and
expanded market offerings.
Most banks recover their investments
faster than expected because operational
savings accumulate quickly and new
capabilities and partners are added.
The return continues to grow
exponentially, but modernization does
come with such challenges and it is
important to manage them pro proactively.
There are four core
challenges institutions face
during the modernization.
First is organizational resistance.
People resist change due to fear of
description, skill gaps or uncertainty.
Strong communication, leadership,
sponsorship and visible quick help
build trust, regulatory constraints.
Banks must comply with strict.
Regulatory frameworks, so early
engagement with regulators and detailed
documentations help reduces compliance
risk, technical complexity, legacy
system often lacks documentations
and have deeply intervened logics.
So to overcome this we should have
clear architecture, governance,
phased migrations, skill,
developmental residential, clear
documentations is re required.
Budget.
Budget limitations.
Modernizations are expensive.
We know that.
But phased execution and re reinvesting
the savings make it more sustainable.
With the right foundations, banks
can unlock new innovation potential.
API driven ecosystem advantage.
API driven ecosystems are now
central to modern banking.
Like APIs allows banks to
collaborate quickly with
fintechs, merchants, government
services and technology partners.
This means back can add new capabilities
like digital kc KYC, or loyalty programs
or valids without modifying the code.
So API also create better
customer experiences by ensuring
consistency across mobile, BA web
branch and call center channels.
So this ecosystem driven MO model is what
enables modern banks to innovate rapidly.
So to move towards this feature
bank, future bank needs a
clear and practical roadmap.
Modernization roadmap.
So a structured modernization roadmap
helps ensure smooth execution.
Assessment and strategy starts by
analyzing current architecture, identify
pain points, define business outcomes,
and secure leadership alignment early.
Validate, select a small
non-critical domain to modernize.
First, use this phase to build
expertise establish processes
and validate assumptions.
Then scale and optimize.
Expand modernization to core domains like
lending, payments, and customer systems.
Establish governance, automate testing,
and refined deployment processes.
Ecosystem expansion.
This enables partners, integrations and
build new digital product offerings.
This is where the most significant
innovations and revenue growth happens.
Ultimately, modernization build
banks that are ready for the future.
Building innovation.
Ready?
Ready.
Digital banks, the banking landscape
is changing faster than ever, so
customer's expectations are higher.
Competition is tougher.
Regulatory requirements are more complex.
Legacy systems simply cannot
support the speed and flexibility
that modern banking requires.
Model modular architectures
unlocks agility.
Improves efficiency enables come
continuous digital innovations.
With the right leadership and
execution discipline, banks can
transform themselves into the
future Ready Digital organizations.
The key is to start early, move
decisively and embrace a long term vision.
With that, I'd like to close this session.
Thank you.
Thank you for your time and attention.
I hope this session helped clarify the
modernization journey and the strategies
that drive the successful outcomes.
I'm happy to take any questions or
discuss specific modernization challenges
your organization might be facing.