Good morning, everyone.
The automotive industry has always been
a symbol of innovation and progress.
From the invention of the assembly
line to the era of mass production,
cars have consistently shaped
how we live, work, and move.
But today, we are witnessing a
transformation unlike anything before.
One driven, not by
mechanical breakthrough.
But by the integration of cutting edge it,
this, it revolution is reshaping vehicles
into intelligent, connected ecosystems.
One considered a tool for transportation.
The car has now evolved into smart
companion, capable of seamless,
communication, personalization,
and even making after decision.
In this presentation, we'll explore
how the, automotive industry's
adoption of it has brought us to this
point and where it's taken us next.
We'll focus on three key areas,
the rise of smart vehicles, the
evolution of infotainment systems
and the transformative trends
shaping the future of mobility.
This isn't just about technology.
It's about how IT is redefining the
entire driving experience and even
the idea of car ownership itself.
So let's dive into the journey of the IT
revolution in the automotive business.
My name is Maxim, and currently I'm
a part of the engineering team at
Google, where I focus on developing
Android Auto to enhance user interaction
by enabling smartphone projection
onto supported vehicle displays.
And I'm excited to be here.
And, before we dive into the
details, let me briefly outline what
we'll be covering in this session.
At the heart of the automotive IT
revolution are three transformative
pillars, smart vehicles, infotainment
systems, and emerging future trends.
Smart vehicles are no longer a concept of
the distant future, they are here today.
These cars are powered by advanced
sensors, processors, and cloud
connectivity, making them capable of
gathering and analyzing data in real time.
Features like over the air updates.
Predictive maintenance and even semi
autonomous driving are redefining
how we interact with our vehicles.
Think of a car that learns your
habits, adjusts its settings to your
preferences, and in truth, you're
always updated with the latest features.
Just like your smartphone.
On the other hand, infotainment
systems have transformed cars into
hubs of connectivity and entertainment.
Platforms like CarPlay and Android Auto
have reimagined how we use our vehicles.
seamlessly integrating our digital
lives with the driving experience.
Whether it's navigation, streaming
music, or voice controlled assistants,
modern entertainment is designed to
enhance both convenience and safety.
But with innovation comes challenges.
Balancing advanced features with
usability and ensuring distraction free
interfaces remain critical priorities.
And finally, we have future trends.
the promise of reshaping the
very essence of transportation.
From autonomous vehicles that can
navigate without human intervention to
blockchain powered data security, the
horizon is filled with possibilities.
Concepts like mobility as a service,
or shifting focus away from ownership,
And toward shared on demand models.
And as personalization becomes a
key driver, vehicles are expected to
become an extension of our homes and
offices, tailored uniquely to each user.
Together, these three pillars are
not just transforming the driving
experience, they are redefining what it
means to own and interact with a car.
As we move forward, this innovation
will control to blur the line between
transportation technology and lifestyle.
for that.
And to truly understand the IT revolution
in the automotive industry, we need to
take a step back and explore its roots.
The integration of IT into
cars didn't happen overnight.
It was a gradual journey, one marked
by key milestones, that laid the
foundation for today's achievement.
And the earliest signs of IT adoption
in vehicles can be traced back to
1980s, when electronic control units,
or ECUs, began to appear in cars.
These small computers were initially
introduced to improve engine performance
and efficiency, especially in response
to tightening emission regulations.
This was a game changer.
It marked the transition from
purely mechanical systems to
electronically controlled ones.
By the 1990s, IT's role in vehicles
expanded with the introduction
of anti lock braking systems,
ABS, and airbag control systems.
These safety innovations relied
heavily on sensors and microprocessors.
Around the same time, the first
attempts at in car entertainment
systems began to surface.
what started as a simple radio and
cassette players, eventually evolved into
CD changers and basic navigation systems.
Through primitive by today's standards,
these features hinted at a future
where cars would serve as more
than just a mode of transportation.
They would also offer comfort,
convenience, and connectivity.
The early 2000s brought significant
advancement in connectivity.
Features like GPS navigation,
Bluetooth integration, and telematics
systems such as GM's OnStar
started appearing in vehicles.
These technologies allowed cars to
communicate with external systems, paving
the way for today's connected vehicles.
While this innovation may seem
basic compared to today's standard,
they were critical stepping stones.
They not only improved the
functionality of vehicles, but
also shifted consumer expectations.
Drivers began to view cars as
dynamic, tech enabled machines,
rather than simple mechanical tools.
In short, early IT adoption in the
automotive industry wasn't just
about solving specific problems.
It was about setting the stage for
the transformative technologies we
are experiencing today, from smart
vehicles to AI driven systems.
And let's talk about evolution of
infotainment system and connectivity.
This system in cars mirrors the rapid
advancement in consumer electronics.
In the early days, in car entertainment
was limited to AM radios, which
debuted in the 1930s, providing
drivers with a single channel of
engagement during their journeys.
Fast forward to 1990s.
And we saw the rise of CD players
and early navigation systems.
These systems, through groundbreaking
at the time, operated independently
of the broader digital world.
However, they set the
stage for what was to come.
By the early 2000s, GPS navigation
became more widespread, offering drivers
real time guidance for the first time.
This was soon followed by the introduction
of Bluetooth connectivity, which allowed
Handsfree colon and marked the beginning
of car and smartphone integration.
The real revolution began in the
2010, with the launch of platforms
like, apple CarPlay and Android,
after which seamlessly integrated
smartphones with vehicle payment systems.
Suddenly, cars were no
longer just about driving.
They became an extension of our
digital lives, offering apps, music
streaming, voice assistance, and more.
Today, connectivity has
reached new heights.
Cars are equipped with Wi Fi hotspot,
cloud based systems, and even
telematics that provide all the updates.
This evolution has turned vehicles
into connected hubs, blurring the line
between transportation and technology.
And next, let's talk a bit about
smart and connected vehicles.
The concept of smart and connected
vehicles is built on the backbone of
Internet of Things, which enables cars
to communicate with each other external
devices and cloud systems, sensors
enabled throughout the vehicle collect
data from engine performance to driver
behavior and transmit it in real time.
This connectivity allows for smarter
decision making, predictive maintenance,
and enhanced safety features.
One key application of this
connectivity is OTA updates.
Much like how smartphones receive software
updates, modern vehicles can now download
and install improvements remotely.
These updates cover everything
from navigation systems and
infotainment upgrades to bug fixes
on even critical safety patches.
For example, Tesla.
They have set a benchmark in this area,
routinely rolling out features like
improved battery efficiency and advanced
driver assistance systems without
requiring a visit to a service center.
This seamless integration of IoT and OTA
updates is not just about convenience.
It's also about future proven vehicles,
ensuring they evolve alongside emerging
technologies and user expectations.
Next part is vehicle to
everything, or V2X, communication.
It represents a groundbreaking leap in
how cars interact with their surroundings.
V2X technology enables vehicles to
exchange information with other cars,
infrastructure like traffic lights,
pedestrians, and even the cloud.
This connectivity improves
safety and efficiency.
For instance, car can warn each
other about sudden, breaking
ahead, reducing accidents.
Traffic signals can communicate
with vehicles to optimize flow,
cutting down on, congestion.
In the future, this could also
enable smoother coordination for
autonomous vehicles, ensuring
they navigate seamlessly through
complex urban environments.
While vehicle to everything is still in
its early stages, it's a cornerstone of
the smart vehicle ecosystem, paving the
way for safer roads and smarter cities.
Thanks.
Next up is obviously, entertainment
revolution and rise of CarPlay,
Android After, and similar platforms.
The launch of CarPlay in 2014 and
Android After shortly after that,
Revolutionized in car infotainment,
this platform allowed drivers to
integrate their smartphones directly
with their vehicles, providing seamless
access to navigation, music, messaging,
and voice controlled assistance.
It started from the first early adopters.
The first car manufacturers to
adopt Apple CarPlay included
Ferrari and Mercedes Benz.
Founded right after early adopters
were brands like Hyundai and Chevrolet.
They all quickly recognized
the value of bringing familiar
smartphone experience into vehicles.
These integrations not only enhanced
usability, but also set a new standard
for infotainment systems, shaping
consumer expectations and encouraging
further innovation in its space.
As infotainment system evolved,
AI integration became a
major driver for innovation.
In Car AI now powers features like
voice recognition, personalized
recommendation, and predictive navigation.
For instance, AI driven voice assistants,
such as Apple Siri, Google Assistant,
allow drivers to control their car
functions hands free, making the
experience safer and more intuitive.
However, with all the benefits
AI offers, there are significant
user experience challenges.
Infotainment systems have become more
complex, and the balance between providing
powerful features and maintaining
ease of use is difficult to achieve.
Drivers can easily become overwhelmed
by too many options, while reliance
on voice commands and touchscreen
can lead to distractions.
Ensuring that AI adds real value without
complicating the driver experience
remains a key hurdle for automakers.
The future of in car AI will
depend on creative, intuitive,
user friendly interfaces that
enhance safety and convenience
without overwhelming the driver.
And now let's move and talk a
bit about autonomous driving.
Currently, IT and AI are at the core
of the push toward autonomous driving.
Automation in vehicles is categorized
into five levels, from level one,
which involves basic driver assistance,
to level five, where the car drives
itself without any human interaction.
At each level, the role of IT becomes more
crucial, As vehicles rely increasingly
on AI driven systems for decision making
and control, AI driven systems and
autonomous vehicles rely on a combination
of sensors, radar, cameras, and machine
learning to process vast amounts of
data and make split second decisions.
These systems need to understand and
predict the behavior of other vehicles,
pedestrians, and the environment.
SAT and AI technologies
continue to evolve.
We are getting closer to achieving fully
autonomous vehicles, but challenges
such as regulatory approval, safety,
and technology reliability remain.
And while the dream of fully autonomous
vehicles and tantalizing significant
limitations and challenges remain,
before we can see wide scale deployment.
One of the biggest obstacles in
the technology is reliability.
Even the most advanced AI systems
struggle to handle the complex
dynamic environments on the road.
For instance, Weimar.
A leader in autonomous driving
technology has made significant strides
with its self driving cars, but their
vehicles are still not universally
ready for all road conditions.
In fact, Weimar's cars can only operate
autonomously in certain cities where
the environment is highly controlled.
Another major challenge
is regulatory approval.
Countries and regions are moving at
different speeds when it comes to setting
legal frameworks for autonomous vehicles.
For example, Tesla has faced legal
scrutiny over its autopilot system,
with critics pointing to incidents where
the system failed to detect obstacles.
and acted unpredictably.
As a result, Tesla continues to
face challenges in convincing
regulators and consumers that
fully autonomous driving is safe.
Safety concerns also remain.
at the forefront.
In 2021, an accident involving a
cruise autonomous vehicle owned by
General Motors might headlines when
it crashed during a test drive.
This incident highlighted the
difficulty of ensuring that autonomous
vehicles can make real time decisions
in unpredictable situations.
Finally, there is the
issue of public trust.
Many consumers remain skeptical about
handing full control over to a machine.
This trust gap is evident in the market.
Through the technologies advancing,
the public is not yet fully comfortable
with the idea of vehicles driving
themselves in everyday scenarios.
The road to full autonomous driving
is still long, and this limitation
reflects the complexity of the challenge.
Part progress.
It's undeniable, achieving a future
where autonomous vehicles are a
common sight on roads worldwide will
require overcoming these technical,
legal, and societal hurdles.
And automation is not only,
relates to the vehicle itself.
for example, think about Tesla,
they serve as a prime example of
robotics and automation in action.
These robotics are like the Tesla
bot performing a complex task such as
battery assembly and vehicle painting.
Tesla had reduced production
time and cost while maintaining
high standards of precision.
This advanced integration of top
automation is key to the scalability and
success of the electric vehicles lineup.
And let's talk a bit about Mar
mobility service is izing the way
people think about transportability
and set up own in a car.
Consumer can now access a variety of
vehicles through a single platform,
allowing for more flexible and
on demand transportation options.
At the heart of this shift is IT,
which enables ride sharing services
like Uber or Lyft, as well as car
subscription models offered by
vehicles like Volvo and Porsche.
Ride sharing has become a global
phenomenon, powered by mobile
apps that connect riders with
nearby drivers in real time.
IT platforms track vehicles, handle
payments, and optimize roads, all
while providing data analytics.
to improve the service.
This model has reduced car ownership
costs and eased traffic congestion in
urban areas, while also offering consumers
greater flexibility and convenience.
Car subscription services
take Mars one step further,
offering access to the world.
to a fleet of cars for
a fixed monthly fee.
This model combines the benefits
of car ownership with the
flexibility of short term rentals.
For instance, Porsche's subscription
program lets customers switch
between different models based on
their needs, whether it's a sport
car for the weekend or a more
practical vehicle during the week.
SIT continues to improve, Mars is expected
to expand, with more integrated platforms
combining ride sharing, public transport,
bike rentals, and other mobility services
into a single user friendly ecosystem.
This will further reduce the need
for personal car ownership and lead
to more sustainable and efficient
urban transportation solutions.
The rise of mobility as a service
is having a profound impact
on traditional car ownership.
As small consumers turn to ride
sharing and car subscription
models they need to own.
A personal vehicle is stately decreasing.
Especially in urban environments, one
of the most significant changes is the
shift in consumer behavior With masks.
People now have the option to access
a variety of vehicle on demand.
without the financial and
maintenance burdens of ownership.
Services like Uber and Lyft allow users
to have a ride whenever needed, while cars
go through some programs of flexibility
to switch car between, cars as desired.
This is especially appealing
to younger generation who may
prioritize experience over long
communication, like car ownership.
From an economic standard, standpoint,
MAS presents a compelling alternative to
owning a car, especially when considering
the total cost of ownership, insurance,
maintenance, fuel, and lubrication.
As MAS platform became more
widespread, owning a vehicle may
start to seem inefficient and
unnecessary, particularly for city
dwellers, where parking and traffic
congestion add to their inconvenience.
For automakers, the shift toward
mass also poses a challenge.
Companies are now pivoting from
focusing on selling cars to
creating services and platforms.
Arms like BMW and Ford are already
exploring mass, launching their own
ride sharing services and investing
in electronic and autonomous fleets
to adapt to this challenged landscape.
Ultimately, mass is reshaping
the future of transportation.
Traditional car ownership may not
disappear entirely, but it's clear
that mass is often a viable, flexible,
and cost effective alternative,
particularly for those who no longer
see owning a car as a necessity.
And as the automotive industry
becomes more connected and reliant
on IT, it faces growing challenges
in cybersecurity and privacy.
These issues are becoming increasingly
complex as vehicles incorporate
more digital technologies like IoT
sensors, cloud based services, and AI.
Cyber security is a critical concern, as
cars are now vulnerable to cyber attacks.
Hackers can potentially gain
access to vehicle control systems,
putting passengers at risk.
Higher profile attacks, such as the
2015 hack of Jeep Cherokee, where
hackers remotely took control of
the vehicle, highlighted the risks.
With autonomous driving and V2X
communication becoming more prevalent,
the threat landscape will only expand,
requiring automakers to invest heavily
in robust cybersecurity measures.
The opportunity here lies in
developing advanced security protocols
and technologies that can ensure
vehicles are safe from cyber threats
while maintaining connectivity.
Privacy is another pressing issue,
as vehicles Transcripts collect vast
amount of data about drivers, their
habits and their locations, such as
DPR and other privacy regulations
commonly interplayed when factories
must be transparent about data usage.
into that they are storing and
handing customer information securely.
This is both a challenge
and an opportunity.
Companies that can navigate
these regulations effectively
and build trust with consumers
will have a competitive edge.
And finally, the high cost of innovation
presents a challenge for the industry.
Developing advanced technologies
like autonomous driving, electric
vehicles, and connected system
requires significant investment in
research, development, and testing.
Aftermakers are facing pressure
to innovate while balancing
this high cost profitability.
However, the opportunity here is clear.
Companies that lead in innovation, whether
through strategic partnership, tech
investment, or new business models, can
position themselves as market leaders.
In conclusion, while these challenges are
formidable, they present opportunities
for automakers to develop cutting edge
technologies and lead the way in ensuring
that the future of mobility is secure,
private, and financially sustainable.
And looking ahead, several
emerging trends are shaping the
future of the automotive industry.
Among the most promising are
personalization, blockchain,
and quantum computing, each of
which present both challenges
and opportunities for automakers.
Personalization is becoming a key factor
in enhancing the customer experience.
Vehicles are increasingly equipped
with AI driven systems that adapt
to the individual preferences of
drivers, from seat settings to interval
changes and even driving behavior.
The challenge, however, lies in
maintaining The vast amount of data
required to personalize these experiences
while ensuring privacy and security.
Companies that can strike the right
balance will have a significant advantage
in attracting and retaining customers.
Opportunities lie in development
systems that are not only intuitive
but also capable of offering tailored
services such as personalized
roads, dynamic car content, or
AI assisted driving adjustments.
Blockchain is another exciting
trend, offering the potential to
enhance transparency, security, and
efficiency in the automotive sector.
By decentralizing data management,
blockchain can enable secure vehicle to
vehicle communication, streamline supply
chain, and even help track the ownership.
and maintenance history of vehicles.
The challenge with blockchain, however,
is its scalability and integration
into existing infrastructure.
Still, the opportunity for blockchain is
vast, particularly in areas like vehicle
history verification and supply chain
management, where it can help prevent,
fraud, and improve accountability.
Quantum computing tools hold
enormous potential for the future of
automotive technology, particularly
in areas like optimization
and AI driven decision making.
Quantum computers can process massive
amounts of data for faster than
traditional systems, allowing for
advances in vehicle design, autonomous
navigation, and even traffic management.
The challenge here is to make it possible.
is the immaturity of quantum technology
and the need for massive investment to
integrate it into practical applications.
However, the opportunity lies in its
ability to solve complex problems
that current computing power cannot,
such as optimizing roads in real
time for entire cities or enhancing
autonomous vehicle decision making.
In summary, While this trend presents
significant challenges, whether in data
management, technology integration,
or scaling, they also offer exciting
opportunities to revolutionize the
industry and create smarter, more
efficient, and user friendly vehicles.
Or even not to create a vehicle,
but to acquire a new customer.
Audi, for example, uses VR showrooms,
where customers can virtually
customize and view their vehicles
in a lifelike setting, while BMW
integrates VR into its employee training
programs, enhancing skill development
across its production facilities.
To conclude, the automotive
industry's evolution is deeply
intervened with advancement in IT.
We've seen how the adaptation of smart
and connected vehicles powered by IT
and AI has transformed both the driving
experience and vehicle management.
From all the updates to vehicle
to everything communication, this
innovation has enhanced safety,
efficiency, and convenience on the road.
The infotainment revolution has
redefined in car experience with
platforms like CarPlay and Android
Auto, while AI integration is improving
user interfaces and overall usability.
At the same time, autonomous
driving technologies are pushing the
boundaries of what vehicles can do
despite current challenges around
reliability, safety, and public trust.
We also discussed how mobility as a
service is reshaping transportation
models, reducing the need for
personal car ownership, and offering
flexible on demand solutions.
However, this shift comes with its own set
of challenges related to cybersecurity,
privacy, and the high cost of innovation.
Looking to the future, trends like
personalization, blockchain, and quantum
computing prevent both opportunities and
hurdles by leveraging these technologies.
The automotive industry has the potential
to create safer, more efficient, and more
personalized transportation solutions.
In essence, IT is the backbone
of the automotive revolution.
From improving vehicle performance
to reshaping business models, IT will
continue to play an important role.
A critical role in defining the future
of transportation as the industry
embraces these technological advances.
The road ahead is filled with
exciting opportunities that
promise to transform how we drive,
travel and interact with vehicles.
And according to McKinsey, by 2030,
the global, automotive software and
electronic market is expected to
reach around, 462 billion, dollars,
represented, 5.5% car from 2018 to 2013.
As we look forward to the
future, one question stands out.
How will the rapid evolution of
automotive technology redefine the
relationship between humans and machines?
With autonomous vehicles capable of
navigating our roads and AI systems
that anticipate our every need, we are
on the cusp of a new era where cars
are not just models of transportation,
but intelligent, adaptive companions.
Will this technology make our roads safer?
City smarter and the world more
connected, or will the complexity and
risk involved outpace the benefits?
The journey is just the beginning,
and now we embrace these challenges
today, will shape the future of
mobility for generations to come.
The question is not whether these
technologies will transform the
industry, it's how we, as a society,
choose to adapt and evolve with them.
Thank you for your attention today.
I hope you heard something useful
or at least entertaining here.
I'll be more than happy to connect
and answer any question you may have.
Thank you