Hello, everyone.
Thanks for joining my talk today.
I hope you liked my intro from the Alps.
It was quite cold there.
My name is Alex.
I am a product owner in Yandex.
Yandex is one of the largest tech
companies globally, providing a wide
range of services, including search
engines, maps, transportation, e commerce,
cloud computing, and AI technologies.
I'm working on delivery service.
Today, I'm excited to share insights on
how new technologies are transforming
product communications, drawing
from my experience scaling Yandex
delivery and industry leading trends.
Few words about myself.
Years of experience.
Over seven years in
product communications.
Growth impact.
Contributed to the 100 growth of
Yandex delivery, user base, over 18
million users served in 4 years, global
reach, operating in 22 countries.
So why adopting new trends in
product communications matters?
McKinsey report that 35 percent
of Amazon's revenue is driven by
AI based product recommendations.
So the first reason is
Competitive advantage.
Salesforce report that 72 percent of
businesses using AI in communications
report higher customer retention.
Second one.
Customer expectations.
McKinsey report that 80 percent
of customers expect personalized
experience in every interaction.
Third one.
Efficiency gains.
HubSpot says that automating communication
reduces campaign launch time by 30
percent and operational cost by 20%.
Fourth, data driven decisions.
For example, Internet of Things
devices generate 90 zettabytes
of actionable data annually,
driving better customer insights.
And fifth, future proofing.
Gartner report that 96 percent of
companies plan to increase AI and
Internet of Things investments by 2025.
Our discussion will cover four
keys areas, understanding what
product communications are.
exploring how AI driven tools
enhance them and diving into
advanced segmentation methods.
Finally, we will look at
what the future holds.
Okay, let's start by defining
what product communications are.
Product communications focus on connecting
customer with the value of your product.
From emails to internet of
things enabled notifications.
Each channel serves to educate,
engage and convert users.
Here are some product
communications examples.
There are a large number of types of
communications like push notifications,
product recommendations, social
media communications, and chatbots.
By integrating customer data through
CRM systems, These communications
become more personalized and impactful.
When we hear about CRM marketing,
we associate it with different
words like spam, loyalty program,
email newsletter, CRM system, and
WhatsApp messenger, for example.
Let's figure out what CRM is.
CRM is Customer Relationship Management.
The first thesis for today Is
that CRM communications are
communications based on customer data.
In general, any promotion is based on
studying your audience, but CRM systems
take this process to a new level.
Imagine that you can build a sales
strategy, not on hypothesis or
assumptions, but on real information
about your customers, what, to whom, and
what point and through what channel to
offer in order to achieve conversion.
Let's look at how CRM helps to personalize
communication and get more sales.
Here are the channels commonly used.
Email, SMS, push notifications,
chatbots, or even Internet of Things.
Effective product communications
require selecting the right
channels to reach your audience.
From AI driven emails to Internet of
Things enabled reminders on smart devices,
the focus should always be on creating
a seamless personalized experience.
For example, a fitness tracker can send
personalized reminders Keeping users
engaged and boosting retention by 25%.
Part two, how AI driven
tools enhance communications.
If any of you are planning to work
in communications or are going to
connect an agency or hire a manager,
let's talk about stages in the
creation of product communications.
The communication process begin with
data collection and segmentation.
Move through strategy and
creative development and ends with
testing and performance analysis.
This structured approach.
insurance measurable outcomes.
Large CRM companies are increasingly
integrated AI technologies designed to
assist or even replace some of the tasks
traditionally performed by CRM marketers.
This AI driven system can analyze
user data, propose hypotheses, create
personalized communication strategy,
and conduct A B testing, making them
powerful tools in modern marketing.
Let's look at some examples.
Salesforce Einstein.
Salesforce has implemented AI capabilities
that automate tasks such as lead
prioritization, customer segmentation,
and personalized communication.
Einstein can analyze user behavior
and predict customer needs, enabling
marketers to act proactively.
Automation and self service technologies
can give business across all industry
a significant productivity boost,
generate cost savings, and an
increase in customer satisfaction.
Last year, customers using Salesforce
Service Cloud tools, including automation
and self service tools such as AI powered
chatbots, saw a 30 percent increase in
customer satisfaction, and more than 27
percent increase in agent productivity,
customer retention, and case resolution.
If you want to know about Salesforce
AI tools more, please find the
official Salesforce website where
you can find full information about
the tools and also try them yourself.
HubSpot AI tools are another examples.
HubSpot uses AI to power features
like content generation, automated
workflows, and predictive fleet scoring.
The system helps marketers identify trends
and optimize campaigns in real time.
One more example of AI chatbot.
HubSpot integrated AI chatbot into its CRM
to automate early customer interactions.
These bots analyze customer queries
using Natural Language Processing, NLP.
Deliver instant responses,
suggest relevant products, or even
generate leads for a sales team.
Nice.
Let's look at two examples of
successful chatbot integrations.
Sephora, the multinational beauty
retailer, successfully implemented the
chatbot in Facebook Messenger and Kik.
The Sephora virtual artist chatbot offers
personalized makeup recommendations,
allows users to virtually try on
products and provides beauty tips.
Result 11 percent increase in booking
rates for makeover appointments.
Average user spent 10 minutes
engaging with the chatbot.
The second example Luxury Escapes
is one of the biggest luxury travel
agencies in Australia and operates
in 29 countries around the world.
Over 2 million visitors would check Luxury
Escapes website each month for new deals.
and offers, but, but the company wanted
to improve the online customer experience.
Their goal was to offer more
personalization, a quicker way to
find deals and easy notifications.
To reach these goals, Luxury
Escapes partnered with Master of
Code to reinvent their shopping
experience in the form of AI chatbot.
Luxury escapes achieved a 3x
conversion rate using a iChat bot,
generated 300, 000 in just 90 days.
This underscores the ROI of investing
in advanced communication tools.
Part three, ML and other segmentation
which are used in product communications.
There can be a millions of segmentation,
but my main thing is the business goal.
Therefore, first of all, determine the
purpose for which you need segmentation.
On the slide, I gave three
examples of such purposes.
The first one, increase the effect of
communications through personalization.
For example, women are more active
users of retail and Yandex food.
So we use this kind of
segmentation in our communications.
Second one, reduce the acquisition cost.
For example, it's necessary to
optimize expenses on expensive SMS.
And third one, reduce spam.
Do not spam the user.
If you're, if there are a lot of
products in your service, You can't
tell everyone about everything.
So use segmentation.
Let's look at basic types of segmentations
There are some of segmentation models
The first one is demographic like age,
gender, income, education, profession,
material status Geographical.
Country, region, city, district,
and language, for example.
Psychographic.
Values, interests,
incentives, pains, barriers.
Technographic.
Devices, type, operating
system, applications.
Behavioral.
History of using products
or service in your service.
Traffic source.
Interest based.
Products or services that customers
need or are interested in.
Value based.
The economic value of
clients for business.
Average bill and so on.
And there are examples of two and three
vector segmentation that we use in Yandex.
RFM segmentation is created by
recency, how long ago was the user's
last visit to the product, frequency
of the visits, And monetary, how
much money did the user bring?
And the second example is
NPS plus value segmentations.
Using these types of segmentation,
you will be able to understand
what kind of clients your
business currently consists of.
Here are three examples of using
different types of segmentation.
One of our main business tasks in
Super App Yandex Go is converting
taxi users into delivery users.
We have a problem with this task.
We cannot take and communicate
with all users on the super app.
There are two reasons for this.
We need to separate communication
with other services, like Yandex Food,
Yandex Market, within the application.
as not to spam users and if we talk
about ordinary individuals like
you and me, the delivery service is
almost never needed at the moment.
It's needed if you forgot things at work,
for example, or need to send a friend,
for example, a game console or a book.
So we integrated ML segmentation
to select only relevant users for
communications who are mostly like
to need delivery in the near future.
On the graph, you can see the number of
users in the database, depending on the
relevance for delivery by ML scoring.
ML scoring is used in CRM
marketing for forecast.
There can be forecast for the time
of the user's next order, for their
probability of churn, For products
that may be interested to the client
for the time of communication.
In search of new ways to find
relevant clients in Yandex Go, we
made segmentation based on the points
where the user is going to, going by
taxi or where he is at the moment.
Geo segmentation.
Imagine that you are
going to a hardware store.
You order a taxi and at that moment
while you are driving information appears
in your application that if you have
heavy purchases, order a cargo service.
If you suddenly miss this
communication, when you get to the
point B, in five minutes you will
receive a push notification with this
information and on the map in Yandex
Go There will be a track like this.
With the help of such segmentation,
we were able to increase orders by
40 percent in these relevant places.
ML segmentation and Internet of
Things data allow businesses to
anticipate customer needs and
provide value ahead of time.
Internet of Things enables companies
to personalize communications by re,
re, leveraging real world usage data.
Let's look at some examples.
Some smart speakers like
Amazon Echo, Google Nest.
These devices collect behavioral data.
like music preferences or voice
shopping habits to tailor marketing
communications such as personalized
offers via email or push notifications.
It gives an impact in increasing
email open rates by 50 percent
due to hyper personalization.
Nice.
Fitness trackers.
Garmin or Fitbit.
This device is sent personalized
notification based on activity
data, reminders for workouts
or sleep improvement tips,
boosting user engagement.
Impact is improved user
retention rate by 25%.
very nice.
Part four, future of
product communications.
There are my recommendations
what to independently study.
These areas will be actively
developing next year.
The first one is generative
AI like child GPT.
Second one is voice search optimization.
Third one, omni channel personalization.
It's an approach that leverages
algorithmic decision making, powered
by real time customer data across
channels, to deliver a contextually
relevant experience to an individual on
any and all channels of their choosing.
And the last one is, AR powered products.
Gartner's report that by 2025, 50
percent of product interactions will
happen through voice enabled devices.
So to summarize, embracing
new technologies isn't just
about staying relevant.
It's about exceeding expectation,
driving growth and creating meaningful
connections with your customers.
Communications drive results.
When based by actionable data.
AI tools streamline communication work
workflows and enhance personalization.
Every segmentation strategy should
align with a clear business goal.
And that's all from me for today.
Thank you very much for
listening to my speech.
I hope it was useful for you and you will
enhance your product by communications.
If you have any questions, please write
to me and I will be very happy to answer.
for listening.
Bye, bye.