Good morning everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 IOT Conference.
My name is Ilpa plo.
I have over 20 years of experience
in software development and
more than 10 years, 10 years of
experience in payments industry.
Today I would like to talk about how
microservices architecture is transforming
payment systems for iot devices.
Okay.
This topic sits at the intersection
of payments, distributor systems
and connected devices, and it's
becoming increasingly relevant as more
devices begin to act on our behalf.
To understand why this matters,
let's first let look at what's
changing in the payments landscape.
We are in the middle of
an iot payment revolution.
Payments are no longer
initiated, only by people.
Devices themselves are making
decisions and triggering transactions,
sometimes thousands of times a day.
Think about smart meters reporting
energy usage, vehicles paying
tolls, automatically appliances,
recording supplies, traditional
payment systems, assumed human
interaction, infrequent transactions,
and relatively large amounts.
I iot completely breaks those assumptions.
So what happens when we try to support
this new world using old architectures?
Most legacy payment platforms
are monolithic, and that becomes
a serious problems with iot.
First, scalability.
Vertical scaling simply doesn't
work when thousands of devices
suddenly come on our network.
Second deployment, speed waiting weeks to
deploy a security fix is unacceptable when
devices are already deployed in the field.
And third, technology locking older
systems struggle to adopt modern
cryptography, machine learning,
or blockchain based integrations.
And unfortunately, these
aren't just performance issues.
They introduce real operational risk.
In monolithic systems, a failure
in one area can quickly cascade
across the entire platform.
For iot use cases like connected
vehicles or CD infrastructure, that
kind of outage is simply not tolerable.
Databases are another major bottleneck.
They were never designed to handle
real-time telemetry, high volume
micro transactions, fraud signals,
settlement records all at the same time.
So Monolithics are in the answer.
What is
This is where microservices architecture
come in instead of one large system.
We break the platform into smaller
independent services, each focused
on a single business capability,
authentication, authorization,
fraud detection, settlement.
Each becomes its own service
with its own lifecycle.
Let's look at why this architectural
shift works as so well for IO OT payments,
there are four core principles that
make microservices a strong fit here.
First, single responsibility.
Each service does one
thing and does it well.
Second, independent deployment.
We can update one service without
risking the rest of the system.
Third, technology flexibility.
Each service uses the
best tool for its job.
And finally, fault isolation.
A failure in analytics shouldn't
stop payments from going through.
Now let's walk through how
this looks in practice.
Starting with device authentication,
IOT devices must authenticate on their
own often with limited processing
power, unreliable connectivity.
This requires.
Cryptographic credentials
embedded during manufacturing.
Secure elements for tamper resistance.
Full cycle management, including
ownership changes and decommissioning
microservices allow us to manage the
road, manage, and rotate credentials
without physically asking the device.
Once the device is authenticated, the
next step is dev, deciding whether
a transition should be allowed.
Transaction auth authorization must happen
extremely fast, often in milliseconds.
We verify balances,
subscriptions and usage limits.
We access risk in real time.
We validate geographic location to detect
impossible scenarios, and we enforce item
potency to prevent duplicate charges.
All of this happens automatically at
scale and without human involvement.
But there is another challenge
unique to iot transaction size.
Many iot transactions are tiny
fractions of ascent processing.
Each one individually isn't part
practical, so we aggregate them.
For example, a smart meter may generate
thousands of usage records per day.
These are accumulated.
Aggregated based on threshold
or schedules, and then
processed as a single payment.
At the same time, detailed logs
are preserved for transparency.
After authorization and
aggregation, we move into the
most regulated part of the system.
Settlement and fraud detection.
Settlement is where money actually
moves and it requires strong
consistency and compliance.
Microservices support multi-state
settlement flows, continuous
reconciliation and integration
with banking networks.
Running alongside settlement is fraud
detection, powered by machine learning.
We analyze device behavior,
detect coordinated attacks, and
apply risk-based controls without
slowing normal transactions.
To make all of this efficient, we rely
heavily on a synchronous communication.
In an event, written architecture
services communicate through
events instead of direct calls.
When a device authenticates an
event is published, fraud detection
consumes it, analytics streams,
it, notifications react to it.
Platforms like Kafka allow us to scale
this to millions of events per day.
Perfect for iot.
Of course, all these devices
still need a secure endpoint
entry point into the system.
Ivo devices speak many protocols.
MQTT co-op HGDP and automotive protocols.
API Gateway translates these protocols
enforces security, applies rate, limits,
routes, requests to the right services.
This protects backend systems from
spikes, malformed requests and attacks.
Let's, let's see how all of this
comes together in a real world.
In a smart city scenario, thousands
of connected parking meters,
vehicles and charging stations
generate payments automatically.
Revenue must be distributed
across multiple agency, each
with different rules and.
Microservices allow each concern
to be handled independently while
still coordinating seamlessly,
while still coordinating seamlessly.
Running a system like this requires
strong operational discipline.
We
rely on distributed tracing to
follow requests across services.
Metrics and monitoring helps us
spot trends and anonymous anomalies.
Intelligent alerting tells
us when human intervention is
required without observability,
micro visas don't scale with it.
They thrive.
And none of this works without
strong security foundations.
We use multiple layers of security.
Secrets management, service
authentication, data tokenization,
network segmentation, and defense.
In depth, this approach meets strict
financial regulations while supporting
the scale and diversity of iot.
So where does this leave us?
Microservices provide a
foundation that's scalable.
Resilient unactive.
They allow payment platforms to grow with
the explosion of connected devices without
sacrificing reliability or security.
As billions more devices come
online, architectures like,
like this will be essential.
So as a summary, as we have seen today,
iot is redefining how payments happen and
microservices provide the foundation to
support that shift securely and at scale.
This approach allows payments
platform to grow, adapt, and
continue innovating at the connected
as the connected worlds expand.
This is it from me today.
Thank you for listening.