Hi, my name is Javier.
I'm a developer advocate at QuestDB,
an open source fast time series
database, and I'm here today to speak
about databases, but I'm not going
to speak specifically about QuestDB.
I have some demos, but I'm
here to speak about databases.
about a new architecture, the type
three architecture, that we've
seen many databases adopting in
the past few months and why this
architecture is a good thing for you.
But before we start, let
me ask you something.
When was the last time you
wish your database was using a
more proprietary data format?
Think about that.
Did you ever think, Damn,
my database is broken.
It's using a data format, which is so
standard and so open that I can easily
reuse it and share with any other
applications like, I don't know, my data
lake or my, machine learning pipeline,
for example, I don't know about you,
but I've been working with databases for
longer than I care to remember and with
big and fast data for the past 10 years.
And I never thought having data in an
open format in a form which is compatible
with many systems is a bad thing.
If your data is in an open format, you can
easily share across different applications
without duplicating data and without
having to spend time moving data around,
transforming data and using resources.
What's not to like?
On a traditional database,
ingesting data is fairly simple.
But if you want to extract the data from
the database, not just for one specific
query, return a few rows, but if you
want to extract the bulk of your data,
all of your data from one table, and
share that data with another system.
Imagine, for example, you want to
train a machine learning pipeline
and you want to get all the data you
have in your database out so your
pipeline can train from that data.
That's not so easy to do.
It's going to take a while to
export if you have a large table.
You truly have to move the data around
from one server to another, and you
truly need to either transform the data
into another format, or bring just in
the other system to make it efficient.
in the end, you're going to be wasting
a lot of time just extracting data.
in a way, the database, It's acting
as the gatekeeper to your data.
It's hey, you can get in, but getting
out, ah, that's going to be a bit painful.
And I should know about that.
As I told you earlier, I work for
QuizDB, and in QuizDB, we've been
doing that for the past few years.
So why databases behave that way?
You think about that.
20, 30 years ago, databases were
designed for a very different use case.
Today, on IoT, it's very common to
have data, to generate data at, I don't
know, a few thousand rows per second.
I've seen systems even generating
a few millions of rows per
second on a single application.
20 years ago, that was unthinkable.
20 years ago, if an application was
very successful, it would store maybe
a few million records on a database.
In the lifetime of the
application, not in one second,
not in one day, not in one year.
In the lifetime of the application, you
will store maybe a few millions of rows.
And if you had a query that took a
couple of seconds, no one will complain.
The concept of real time we have today,
in which you need to have milliseconds
latency between ingestion and being able
to query the data because maybe you have
a critical process depending on that.
That was not the common case 20 years ago.
So databases were designed
in a different way.
And I don't know about you, but, in the
late 90s, early 90s, I was a web developer
and I heard this complaint very often.
Hey!
The application is slow and the database
is the bottleneck and that was true The
database was the bottleneck and that
happened because By the end of the 90s and
the early noughties the world changed We
moved from a world in which applications
were mostly corporate and databases were
mostly corporate to a world in which, we
had websites for absolutely everything.
Not only that, early notice,
we started getting, cell
phones and mobile applications.
So we have two interesting patterns here.
First, data was arriving faster than ever.
And from many different places,
not from a single point of entry.
And second, we were storing
not only transactional data,
but also analytical data.
We started Analyzing user behavior
and relational databases were
not really designed for that.
And it was difficult for them
to deal with the speed of the
data and the amount of the data.
And then we saw two interesting
trends on databases.
First, NoSQL databases,
super fast to inserting data.
Super fast to query the data in exchange.
Not consistency, no constraints, simple
queries, no indexes, but super fast.
So if you wanted just ingesting
fast data, a NoSQL database
would be a super good option.
On the other hand, if you wanted to
have analytics and you didn't want
to use a corporate data warehouse,
you could use the brand new
analytical databases, OLAP databases.
That were specialized in running complex
queries across huge amounts of data.
Latency was not great.
It was usually in the seconds
to minutes rather than
milliseconds as we expect today.
And they had to prepare the
data in many different ways.
So they were optimized for batch inserts
and batch queries, but still they
could analyze huge amounts of data.
And of course, article
databases, they got better.
They started a train of separating
storage and computations.
So now.
You could use multiple instances
in parallel to query data and
then aggregate, reducing latency.
So still we are speaking about
seconds rather than milliseconds,
but they were way faster.
And they also introduced the trend
of the data lake, in which we have a
central repository of data, in which
you store the data in some open formats.
Might be parquet, most commonly, could
be JSON, could be CSV, basically formats
that different tools can consume without
having duplicate, which is great, which
is what we are talking about today.
And still, even with the data
lake and with the separated
storage and computation, these
tools were mostly for batch.
And one thing that was still a
problem with analytical databases.
It was that they were designed for
immutable data because of the way they
used to prepare data and because of the
formats they were using, like parquet,
maybe storing data in object storage,
like Google Cloud Storage or Amazon
S3 or Azure Blob Storage, because of
that, they were not really designed for
random access and random modifications,
but for append only operations.
And having immutable data was not ideal.
This has changed now, and I
will talk about that later.
But, at the time, analytical
databases were not really designed
for real time, and were not really
designed for immutable data.
But, if you are working in a use
case, In which you are generating a
streaming data, and of course, IOT
is one of the typical use cases like
finance or energy data or mobility.
if you are working with a use
case in which you need a streaming
data, ideally, you want a system,
a database that can do everything.
How hard can that be?
it turns out that working with
a streaming data, it's tricky.
First, because a streaming
data can get very big.
If you keep a streaming data and
every few milliseconds, or every few
seconds, you are getting new data
points from many different devices,
you're going to be getting to a
few billion records very quickly.
And a few billion records is
something that most databases use.
are not going to be able to work with in
a comfortable way and data never stops.
So whenever you need to do any
calculation, data is always,
there is always more data coming.
So you need some way of setting
time barriers or sampling data
by time or something like that.
Of course, the data that you are getting
when you are streaming in real time is
going to, is not going to be constant.
You're going to have.
But of data and you're going to have
some luck because you're going to
have sensors in different factories
across the wall and the network is
going to be a slower in some places.
And just because of latency data that
is generated closer to the server.
It's going to get faster into the
server, even if it was generated later.
that's going to happen.
And devices are going to
be running out of battery.
They are going to restart.
They are going to get disconnected.
So data is going to be
coming out of order.
It's going to be coming late.
And very often, it will come when
you already emit some results.
So you need to be able to
update whatever you did.
So if you're working with immutable
systems, That's going to be hard and you
need to have some way of working with
individual points but also when data is
getting old some way of aggregating data
because aggregations of older data are
more valuable than individual data, which
are more valuable in the recent time
analytics and all of this, of course, with
low latency and queries that show data
as fresh as possible, because very often
you're going to be working with critical
systems in which maybe you are getting in.
Data from a sensor, and you need to emit
some alert if something is wrong, so the
workers, the operator can clear the area.
So you cannot allow for seconds
latency in some use cases.
So that's tricky.
And that's made a new type
of database appear, which I'm
going to call fast databases.
So fast databases will be like a
specialization of analytical databases.
that are designed for real time.
That's basically it.
And in fast databases, a very popular
type of database, of course, in
IoT, is the time series database.
So time series databases are databases
that specialize in very fast ingestion,
in very fast queries, over the recent
data, but also can query data, historical
data, and can use techniques like
downsampling old data, maybe deleting
old partitions, moving data to object
storage, so queries are slower for the
historical data but still available.
But basically, time series databases
specialize in those type of use cases.
as I told you before, I work for QuestDB.
QuestDB is an open source
time series database.
It has the Apache 2.
0 license.
Which basically means you can
use it for any use case you want
completely for free, of course.
And it's a fairly popular project.
We have today almost
15, 000 stars on GitHub.
over 150 contributors already.
This slide is a slightly different one.
Out of date, but yeah,
it's a popular project.
We have thousands of users
happily using QuestDB.
And I want to give you an overview
of which are the internals of
QuestDB and what is QuestDB.
so you can see why we are adopting
now the Type 3 architecture.
Because for the past 10 years, We've been
a traditional database, a fast database,
but with a traditional architecture in
which we were using our own format that is
not proprietary because it's open source.
you can go here and see how we
are storing the data, but no
one else is using this format.
So basically we are not
compatible with any other system.
Until now that we are changing.
So let me tell you a little
bit about QuestDB first.
QuestDB is the fast database.
We store data in column,
in columnar format.
So it's very quick to retrieve the data.
We have a parallel SQL engine custom
made with a just in time compiler.
So every time you execute a
query, we can parallelize.
across many CPUs and
many threads in the CPUs.
The data is always partitioned.
You'll see a little bit about that later.
We don't use indexes.
We have some specialized indexes, but,
we usually They score it using index
sex, except for very specific use cases.
And, in most cases, we are very
fast without having to index data.
So we have very low latency
between ingestion and the
data being able to be queried.
So it's practically immediate.
After you read the data,
you can query data already.
we separate ingestion and reads.
So even if your database is experiencing
a heavy load on queries, you can still
have a predictable ingestion rate.
So if you know with your current machine,
you can always ingest, let's say, I
don't know, 350, 000 events per second.
Even if your server is experiencing
heavy load of queries, You can
always make sure you are going to
be ingesting data at the same rate.
And we have goodies like building
the duplication or updates on absurd.
So basically what you would
expect from a modern database
for time series these days.
Let me show you a little bit
how you can use QuickQuestDB.
I'm not going to do an ingestion demo.
If you want to test ingestion,
you can go to the QuestDB website.
Or to this repository and try on
your own, but I'm going to give you a
couple of things we can do in QuestDB.
For example, this is a public dashboard
in which we have live financial data.
We are ingesting data in real time.
Grafana that is sending
SQL queries to QuestDb.
Every, actually, I'm going
to make this a bit faster.
So now, every quarter of a second,
we are sending queries to QuestDb.
And every quarter of a
second, we are versing data.
So you can see it's quite responsive.
We have another dashboard here, which
for IoT might be more relevant, which
is taxi rides in the city of New York.
So you can see here every time a journey
on a taxi is starting or finishing,
we are plotting this data on a map.
And we also have here some
passengers stats and the correlation
between the tip and the fare.
Of the taxi ride and so on and so forth.
These two dashboards are powered by
public data set we have available,
sorry, in our demo machine.
If you come to this, machine, DemoQuestDB.
io, you can play with this data yourself.
This is the trading data, and this
is the taxi rides, the trips data.
And for the trips data,
it's not a small data set.
It's 1.
6 billion records.
It's not huge, but it's not too bad.
So we have 1.
6 billion records with
a lot of columns here.
And you can do things like, for
example, we have here some sample
queries you can test yourself.
And I'm going to be asking, for example,
the I can see the average distance
on this data set, and I can see the
average distance on this data set.
It's 2.
8 miles, and it took 200 milliseconds to
calculate the average distance over a 1.
6 billion data set.
Of course, if I limit.
this to, just one year, for example,
just the year 2018, now it's way faster.
It took only 19 milliseconds to
calculate the average distance.
And we are still reading
a large amount of data.
Let me see how many trips we have in 2018.
It was 110 million records, not too bad.
And then you can do things like not
only getting the average distance, but
we have extensions to do things like
I want to get the average distance
sampling 15 days interval, for example.
Oh, and actually I'm going to put here
the date so this is easier to see.
So if I execute this query, I'm going
to now get for each 15 days interval,
you can see here, 19, the 4, 18.
So every 15 days.
I have a record here, and this is
arbitrary, I could, I can do every
two, every two months, I can go
to, from years to microseconds, I
can go to any arbitrary, a month
I want here, 22 days, whatever.
So here, as you see, 140
milliseconds to calculate the
average in 22 days intervals.
it's quite flexible and performant.
I don't want to talk much about this.
What I want to tell you is
about the architecture we design
and why we are changing it.
So in the past few years, we've
implemented a lot of things to
make QuestDB super efficient.
For example, a couple of years ago,
We implemented something called the
Parallel Write Ahead Lock that allows
you, QuestDB with the Postgres protocol
that we support, or the InfluxLine
protocol that we support, or CSV, we
ingest data in parallel and apply changes
in parallel, both in the primary machine
and if you have any replicas, so your
data can be read as quickly as possible.
We also store the data partition by time.
So for each time partition, in this
case, I'm partitioning by month.
So for each month, I will have
a directory, and inside the
directory, I have a binary file
with the contents for each column.
So if the column has like a fixed length,
like an integer or a long or a float,
Then it's going to be just one file if
the data type is variable size, like
a string or a bar chart, we use two
different files, one for the data and
one for the offsets to know where each
column, where each row is starting.
But basically, we use our own format to
store the data in a very efficient way.
if you look at the contents of
the database folder in QuestDB,
this is what you will see.
For each table, you will see several
partitions, one for every type unit.
Inside the partitions, you will
see, multiple binary files.
And we have also metadata, like
the transactions and some temporary
folders, with the Grata head log files.
So that's basically the, the
physical layout we have, in QuestDB.
We also realized last year that having
columnar format is very efficient for
querying data, but it's actually not
that efficient for ingesting data because
in real life, we see most applications
are sending data with whole rows.
So even if you query data by columns,
You send the data in row chunks.
So what we do now is when we're ingesting
data, rather than ingesting by column,
as we were doing in the past, now we
ingest data by rows, and we store data
by columns, but we only have to open
files once, not multiple times like
before, so ingesting is a bit faster.
And I'm telling you all these things,
Because basically I want you to see
that in the past few years, even if we
were using our own format, we're doing
everything possible to make the life
of our users as convenient as possible.
We added also multi primary ingestion.
So now you can have multiple machines
in which you write data and we
make sure there are no conflicts.
So you can get higher throughput, or
you can even have a machine in one
region ingesting data and a machine
in another region, and they both
replicate data across the cluster.
So we did every kind of thing to
make the life of our users better.
And we got to the point in which we
saw adoption growing, many users using
QuestDB, and we thought, Oh, this is cool.
Now we are at a point in which we
already implemented everything we
wanted in the engine, and we can
start doing incremental changes.
But then we realize that users
were asking once and again for some
things That we didn't have, and we
realized that the design we have for
the database was getting obsolete.
And why was that?
if you've been paying attention,
in the past couple of years,
there's been a lot of talk about
new file formats for big data.
Apache Hudi, or Apache
IceBear, or Delta Lake.
They have been around for a few years,
but in the past two years, there is
a lot of buzz about those things.
So basically these formats are
formats for big data that allow you
to have data stored in parquet files
and add table behavior to parquet.
They basically allow you to have updates,
deletes, increments, incremental changes.
In your tables on top of a get files.
So the constraints I told you before
on analytical databases about not being
able to update data being immutable
that being removed with these formats,
but more importantly, these formats
are open on as more and more tools.
Are adopting these formats, now,
you can consume data from multiple
applications without any duplication.
We also saw that, more and
more, users want to do machine
learning on top of the data.
So users use QuestDB
for real time analytics.
They use QuestDV for seeing trends
across the historical data, but they
also want to do predictive analytics.
They also want to use, that science
or machine learning to, learn from the
data they have already in the database.
And since we have a data, a data
format, which was not, open, it was
difficult for them to train the data
because they will have to export
data into CSV, as I told you before.
Or read data with tools like Pandas,
row after row, before they could,
they could easily train that data.
So when they're doing machine
learning, there are two use cases.
In one case, users that want
to export the whole data set.
So they can train their models elsewhere.
And in that case, what they
would prefer is a parquet file.
Or a parquet, a directory with several
parquet files that they can just point
their models and train from there.
We have another type of user
on machine learning, which are
users that want to run queries.
maybe they want to do, aggregations
or downsampling directly on the
database to, to then present the
data with tools like Python or R
or whichever tools you are using.
But they want to run the queries
using the database, but they want
the data to get to the client
application as fast as possible.
As of today, we are using
the POSGES protocol.
When you use the Postgres protocol,
or any other traditional protocol,
JDBC, whatever you are using in your
database, you are sending row after
row of data to the client application.
The client application needs to
deserialize that data into objects, and
then they need to use the application.
If you are doing that with a
few thousand rows, you are fine.
If you are doing that with a few
million rows, that's way too slow
and uses way too many memory.
That's basically, that's
the trolling we were seeing.
in order to, to solve this,
we wanted to do something new.
And we are going to be adopting what
we call the type three database,
which is something we've seen
also in other databases, not only
QuestDB, it's a trend we are seeing.
As of today, we don't know of any
other database implementing fully the
type three database, but we see many
databases taking these ideas, these
concepts, and implementing parts of that.
So the first component of a type
three database is distributed
computing, which basically you have.
You have a storage separate from
computation, probably the storage
might be even object store like,
Amazon S3 or, Azure Blob Storage.
And you have a computation
separated from that.
So your queries can execute on
several machines and return faster.
The second part, as I told you already,
It's storing the data in open formats.
If your data is stored in an open format
that many tools can use, whenever you
want to reuse that data for anything,
You can skip completely the database.
You can just go to the storage.
Those formats also are compressed.
So you're going to be, you're going
to be saving a lot of money and you're
going to be saving a lot of time.
It also, it's also interesting
to use these formats and
support semi structured data.
So in most cases, your data in your
table is going to have some structure,
the timestamp and some columns.
But in many use cases.
You might have some optional columns.
You might have some devices of different
types that sometimes they have one
architecture, but sometimes they have
a different one, a different schema.
And for that, it's important to
support semi structured data,
like JSON or in Parquet, you can
support this semi structured data.
So it's important that your
database can use those structured
and semi structured data.
Otherwise, you're not going to
be able to model efficiently some
of the data sets that you want.
And the last part, for a type 3
database, the data ingress should
be as fast as the data ingress.
What we mean by this is that
traditionally, fast databases have
been, focusing on ingesting individual
rows very fast, And outputting
aggregated results very fast.
But they were not designed to output
individual rows also very fast.
And that's something that needs to change.
On the type 3 database, getting individual
rows out of the database should be as fast
as getting rows inside of the database.
And for that, you can
use new data formats.
I told you already about Iceberg
and Parquet for storing data.
And I'm going to tell
you about Apache Arrow.
You probably have heard already
of Apache Arrow because it's been
quite trendy in the past few months.
But if you haven't heard of Apache Arrow,
it's a in memory format that allows you
to share data across multiple applications
without deserializing the data.
So basically, with Apache Arrow,
my database When you are asking me
to send you data, I can create the
data directly on the arrow format.
The arrow format is not a row format.
It's a columnar format.
So I send you data down the
line already in columnar format.
And I send you the data in this
OpenMemory format, which is compatible
with many libraries already.
So tools like Apache Spark, or
Pandas, or Dusk, or virtually
any programming language, they
already have Arrow libraries.
So when I send you the data in Arrow
format, You can directly use the data
from your programming language without
having to deserialize data in memory.
So you are saving time from serializing,
deserializing, and you are also not
having to duplicate data in memory.
So it gets very fast.
Get the data and being able to
use it, especially if you are
working with a lot of data.
And the cool thing about arrow is that
it gives you not only the memory format,
but also a DBC, which is like JDBC.
or like ODBC is a protocol to
work with SQL data, but in which
the wire format is arrow itself.
So basically, if you have a library
that can speak ADBC, you can connect to
MyDatabase, you can connect to QuestDb,
you can connect using the ADBC protocol.
And when you query the data, you
are going to be getting the rows
directly in the columnar arrow format.
So the client application doesn't need
to do any conversions and you have
zero copy memory operations, making
the whole process very efficient.
What this means is that now you can
stream data out of your database as fast
as you can stream data in your database.
So in QuestDB, we're already
adopting this architecture.
we are closing the gap between a time
series database analytical database,
because now, since we are going to be
producing, we are already producing
data on parquet format, we can directly
ingest data parquet, and we can also
read data generated elsewhere, in parquet
and query data using the QuestDB engine.
So we are becoming analytical database.
And a time series database all in one.
Of course, the query engine
is decoupled for storage.
As I told you, we are supporting,
this is still in beta, but this
is going to be early next year.
It's going to be available for everyone.
So we support already ADBC.
So you can have zero copy operations.
If you prefer to use the process protocol,
JDBC, as you are doing today, You can
still do it, but if your client library
use ADBC, like pandas, for example,
or polars, you can just use ADBC to
query data and everything will be fine.
Much more, much more efficient.
When we generate the data is stored
directly in compressed parquet,
which is iceberg compatible.
So you can reuse that data if you
want on any other system without
having to pass through QuestDb.
So we are not gatekeeping
your data anymore.
And as I told you already,
if you have parquet that has
been generated externally, you
can point QuestDb to QuestDb.
To those packet files, and you'll be
able to create data directly from there.
A specific thing we are doing in QuestDB,
which is a bit unique, is that, as I
told you earlier, we have our own binary
format in order to be very efficient.
So what we are doing these days
is When you are storing data, the
latest partition of the data, it's
stored still in our binary format.
The older partitions, if you
are partitioning data by day, so
data from yesterday and before,
it's stored in parquet format.
And even if you have data which is
arriving late, And out of order, if
you have an update on the data, we
are updating the parquet files, okay?
But the recent partition, if you have
a partition per hour, the last hour of
data, it's still stored on binary format.
Why?
Because, as I said before, our binary
format is designed to be super efficient.
When you are working with real
time data, most queries are on
the most recent part of the data.
This means the most recent partition.
Since also those queries are the most
critical for query latency, what we
are doing is we store the the most
recent partition for each table,
it's stored in our binary format.
So the time to query the data,
the query latency, the query
freshness, is as fast as possible.
We don't need to read from
parquet for that data.
We store data in the binary format, and
all the other partitions are in parquet.
When you run a select, if you, if your
select is across multiple partitions,
you don't have to worry if your data
lives on the binary format or in parquet.
Even if you have object storage, you
can define, you have, you can define
multi tiered storage in which the
latest partition is in binary format.
The last month of partitions
is in, in parquet.
And then you might have in
parquet in your local disk.
And then you might define that all the
data, which is over one month, all go
to object storage, for example, to S3.
So you can define three tiers of data,
the recent partition, the data which is
in parquet in your local file system,
and the data which is in object storage.
And QuestDB, whenever there is
a query, it will, get the data.
It will fetch the data from whichever
storage And we'll, execute the query,
but the queries that execute in the most
recent partition, they will be faster
because they are using the binary storage.
So we call this the first mile of the
data in which, with this optimization, we
can still be Super fast for query, super
low latencies, but keep compatibility
with the rest of the systems by storing
in Parquet all the other partitions.
So this is in and of itself
the Type 3 architecture.
As I said, in QuestDB, we are adopting
it, but there are other databases that
are also adopting Arrow and Parquet.
So it's a trend.
We see in many other databases,
and this is our implementation.
You can ingest data using, streaming
systems like Red Panda or Kafka or
Confluent, whatever you are using.
You can ingest data using the Client
Libraries or the Influence Line Protocol.
you can also ingest data
if you want from CSV.
Whichever way you are ingesting the
data, the parallel writers are going
to be writing data To the Quest DB file
formats for the latest partition to
park it for all the other partitions
or all the data with Ravi late.
This packet file can be consumed
directly by any tools like Polars
or Pandas or Spark or d db.
Anything you are using, you can
read directly from Parque without
having to, to use the query engine.
But if you want to run any queries,
of course you're seeing the.
SQL clients with, JDBC,
the POSIS protocol, ADBC.
You can efficiently query data,
either with Arrow or with the
Piggywire, protocol or the REST API.
And again, those reads are
going to be in parallel.
We scale computation
independently of storage.
to get your data as fast as possible.
As a last demo, I want to show you how we
are working as of today with Parquet and
how you can use external tools, in this
case, DuckDB, to, read data in Parquet.
That we are producing from QuestDB.
Let me show you my local QuestDB.
So here I have a table.
It has like public data from
water sensors in Chicago.
It has this, the measurement timestamp.
The beach name, water temperature,
turbidity, wave height, period,
battery life, different things.
And, I can just run a query on this
data, and of course I can do things,
as I told you earlier, I can do things
like, give me, for example, the, let's
say, give me, The time stamp and the
average, actually the time stamp and the
its name and the average temperature and
average to b the T, in, let's say in one
month intervals, for example, on this
dataset and that for each beach name
and timestamp, each beach name a month.
In this case, sorry.
It will give me the average temperature.
So as you can see here, different
month and different beach.
And I have a hundred rows like this.
And if I query independently,
I have 120, 000 rows.
This is public data from Chicago.
And if I go to my, to my file
storage, I can see here, actually.
Oh yeah, here.
I'm here on the directory
from my data set.
And I can see here that the data, all the
partitions, are stored as parquet data,
except for the, last one, which is
stored, as I told you earlier, with,
individual, with the binary format.
So for each different column, I have,
different, a different binary file.
For the columns that are
characters or variable size, I
have two, as you can see here.
And this one is a specific
type, we call it symbol.
It has like different
metadata, but that's about it.
All the, all the partitions are
parquet, and the most recent
partition, what we call the update
partition, it's in binary format.
And something I can do, I can just
open DuckDB, which is a fantastic
database for, batch analytics, and
I can run a query just like this.
I can say, I want to read from
parquet, and I'm going to point to
my directory and all the folders.
Inside this directory, all the
partitions, and I'm going to say,
Hey, this is a partition folder.
And it contains a lot of parquet files.
So find me everything which is in this.
if I don't filter anything first,
I should have the whole data set.
Now, a hundred twenty something thousand.
And now I can run queries like
a only for a specific, point in
time, and I have five, 5,478 rows.
If I go again back to my web
console, I can run the state query.
And actually here you can
see the number is larger.
So if I'm query in for the same
date, the number here is over 5,500.
And in DuckDB, it was
actually 5, 400 something.
Why is this?
as I told you earlier, the latest
partition, the active partition,
is not stored in parquet.
You can see here the partition
corresponding to September 2023,
which is the latest in this dataset.
It's stored in the binary format
because it's the most recent partition.
So DAGDB don't have access to this.
If I wanted, I could export
this in parquet from QuestDB.
But by default, the latest
partition is not available.
So basically, the
difference is in this one.
If I go back to my web interface, and
actually I query the table partitions,
and I see that the latest one is this one.
It's September 2023, as we saw on disk.
And now I'll run my query between
this date and the latest one.
Now I have 5, 478 rows, which is exactly
the number of rows I have in DAGDB.
as we wanted to show, now you can
use QuestDB to ingest your data.
Run your real time identical queries
and still use, any other, system in this
case that DB could be pandas, could be
polars, could be anything you want to
use to query the generated parquet files.
And if you want to use QuestDB, I
told you already is open source.
You can use it for absolutely anything
you want with the open source version.
You can have, up to 5 million events per
second on a single instance was not to
like, but if you want to have enterprise,
capabilities, bring your own cloud
or role based access control, single
sign on with after record or intra ID.
enhanced security on all protocols,
cold storage, multi primary ingestion.
If you need any of those things,
and of course, Enterprise support.
We also have a QuestDB
Enterprise offering.
We recommend most users to
start with QuestDB Open Source.
See if you like it.
And if you like it,
contact us for Enterprise.
And that's about it.
I hope this was informative.
I hope you understand now why the
TypeScript database is a good idea.
And if you want to learn more about
QuestDB, I'm leaving here some links
where you can learn a bit more.
Thank you and have a nice day.