Hello, good morning, everyone.
It's a privilege to be here at this
conference, sharing insights on how
AI in enhanced cloud architecture is
revolutionizing enterprise operations.
I am Babita Kumari, senior software
engineer at Microsoft, where I have
been part of groundbreaking innovations
that transform how business operate.
As the technology evolves, so does
its role in business operation.
From reducing inefficiencies to
predicting future challenges, AI
and cloud integration is at the
forefront of this transformation.
Today, I'll share a comprehensive
journey from understanding challenges
and seizing opportunities to real
world success and future possibilities.
Here is what we will cover.
The challenges enterprises face.
The opportunity in the growing AI
cloud market, our innovative solutions,
their proven impact, and a glimpse
into the future of AI and cloud.
Moving forward,
moving forward to the challenges
in enterprise cloud operations.
What are the main pain points?
Despite the strides we have made,
enterprises still face significant
cloud related challenges.
Some of those are excessive operational
costs, 45 percent overspending due
to inefficient resource utilization
as well as manual optimizations.
Resource management issues that leads
to 38 percent of average resource
wastage, inconsistent workload
distribution, and poor capacity planning.
Security vulnerabilities.
Over 12, 000 cloud security
incidents happens annually.
Unfortunately, but that happens.
With an average detection of 4.
5 hours.
And last but not the least.
Limited predictive capabilities.
37 hours of unplanned downtime monthly
due to reactive management approaches.
So what are the real
world impact for this?
Such challenges not only inflate
operational costs, but also hinder
scalability and compromise security.
What is the result?
The result is huge.
Missed opportunities for
innovation and growth.
So how many of you have
experienced these challenges?
These aren't just technical problems,
they are everyday business problems.
Now, going forward to the next slide,
that is growing market opportunity.
The AI cloud market is
projected to reach 236.
4 billion by 2027.
Growing at a compound annual rate of 42.
8%.
That's huge.
Enterprises worldwide are increasing
their budgets for cloud AI integration,
with 76 percent prioritizing this in
the digital transformation strategies.
So what is fueling this growth?
There are a couple of factors for this.
First is digital transformation.
89 percent of enterprises now
prioritize cloud AI integration.
Operational efficiency demands,
which leads to 67 percent are
actively seeking automated
solutions to optimize operations.
Competitive pressure.
91 percent of industry leaders report a 3.
5 percent competitive advantage
through AI cloud adoption.
So what is the Action we have to take.
The question is no longer if, but how we
embrace this opportunity to stay ahead
in the race of digital transformation.
We have to move forward with an action.
So what we propose here is our solution,
AI enhanced cloud architecture.
So in this model, we'll talk
about the core features.
how it works, and what are the
business values for the solution.
At Microsoft, we have developed an AI
enhanced cloud architecture that addresses
these challenges with many, parameters.
First is productive resource management.
With 91 percent accuracy, machine
learning analyzes historical patterns,
seasonal variations, and growth trends.
Intelligence security framework.
We believe in zero trust security.
Achieving 99.
7 percent threat detection accuracy.
Our frameworks provide real time
monitoring, compliance check,
and zero trust architecture.
Dynamic scaling capabilities, automatic
workload, workload balancing, and
multi region optimization reduce Over
provisioning by 67 percent is that reduce
waste is resource wastage and enhance
the resource optimization and then multi
cloud integration with the possibility
of seamlessly connecting platform with
unified management interface, ensuring
that vendor agnostic deployment happens.
And this helps in multi cloud
integration talking about their features.
But how does it actually works?
So we combine both, cloud, public cloud
services like, Azure, AWS, cloud, Google
Cloud, with private cloud components
for sensitive data and edge computing.
Optimizing performance
across 150 global locations.
So that's been a whole lot of business
values, and these business values
translate into tangible results of a 42
percent reduction in operational cost.
53 percent is increased process efficiency
and 89 percent pure security incidence.
So we will discuss this with
a real, world success stories.
So this is something which I have
talked about the business values.
Let's move on to the real
world success stories.
I'm going to share with you a fortune
500 manufacturer case study with you.
So allow me to share a story about one
of our fortune 500 client, a global
manufacturing company struggling with
operational inefficiencies and high cost.
Here is what they achieved
with our solution.
Cost saving of 4.
2 million saved annually in maintenance.
2.
1 million reduction in
emergency repairs and over 1.
3 million in inventory optimization.
And talking about operational efficiency,
they see a huge improvement that
costs around 52 percent of operational
improvement in resource allocation.
And 47 percent reduction in downtime.
Talking about their metrics, processing
850, 000 data points per minute, achieving
99 percent system uptime, and enabling 17.
4 additional production days annually.
So what are the key takeaways from this?
This case, underscore, how AI cloud
integration is not just solving current
challenges, but creating scalable,
sustainable solutions for the future.
That's it.
Now let's move on to the next slide.
We'll talk about, implementation.
We have talked about implementation,
how we implement it, what are
the competitive advantages.
And let's talk about the future innovation
and how does the roadmap looks like.
More better view.
Okay, this looks good.
what is the near term
innovation in 2024 2025?
We are focusing on quantum computing
integration, achieving 100 to 500
times workload acceleration, and
256 qubit encryption strength.
This advanced cloud orchestration is
something we are focusing on, enhancing
workload balancing efficiency by 94%,
And reducing latency by 67 percent is
our midterm enhancements, 2025 to 2026
will be Our goal here is to achieve AI
driven automation, 100 percent automated
resource management with self healing
system in all the resources, and security
evolution, introducing quantum safe
protocols and advanced threat protection.
Vision for 2026 and beyond.
So we envision a world of autonomous
operation powered by quantum AI
integration, delivering zero touch
management systems, self healing,
based on zero trust architecture
and also everything is automated.
100 percent automated resource management
with their self filling systems.
So now, moving to the conclusion and
summarizing the key insights, what we
discussed, AI enhanced cloud architecture
is just not more than a technology.
It's a catalyst for enterprise
transformation by addressing pain
points, leveraging market opportunities
and delivering proven solutions.
We are helping business
unlock their potential.
This is a call to collaborate.
At Microsoft, our mission is to empower
every organization to achieve more.
I encourage you to think about
how your organization can
leverage these innovations to
drive efficiency and innovation.
And last but not the least, thank you
for your time and attention today.
It's been an honor sharing
this journey with you.
Let's continue the conversation together.
We can redefine what is possible
and I'm happy to take any questions.
You may hear about the challenges or your
team face with, any cloud and AI adoption.
I'm reachable at LinkedIn and also
through this, conference management.
So please reach out to me and let me
know if you have any questions, concern,
or you hear just any challenges your
team's faced with, cloud AI adoption.
So that's all for today.
Thank you so much.