Good morning, everyone.
it's an honor to be here today at
con 42 to discuss a crucial topic in
our ever evolving digital landscape.
So it's exploring multi cloud
and hybrid cloud architectures
of effective data management.
So I'm Prashant Reddy.
And today I'll walk you through how these.
Cloud strategies are transforming,
data management and, enabling the
organizations to meet modern challenges
in LLT and, broader tech ecosystems.
So coming to the agenda, let me begin
my outlining what we'll cover today.
So we will start with an introduction
to cloud architectures and explore
the rapid growth of cloud adoption.
So next, I'll explain what multi
cloud and hybrid cloud models are.
So Are there unique benefits
and their challenges they pose?
So we will then dive into, practicalities
of implementing these strategies.
successfully and wrap up, with
the key takeaways to position your
organizations, for the future.
So let's dive in right in.
So coming to the introduction
to cloud architectures.
So cloud computing has fundamentally
changed how organizations
approach IT infrastructure.
And data management, multi cloud and
a hybrid cloud architectures are at
the forefront of this transformation.
Multi cloud involves using services
from multi cloud providers, offering
the resilience and reducing the
dependency on a single vendor.
So on the other hand, hybrid, cloud
combines on prem, infrastructure
with public and private cloud
resources to balance the flexibility.
And the control so together, these
models enable organizations to scale,
would say optimize the cost and
enhance data management capabilities
in the digital transformation era.
So coming to another slide,
the growth of cloud adoption.
So the cloud adoption is surging globally.
So according to Gartner by
2025, 95 percent of the.
new digital workloads will be
deployed on cloud, native platform.
So additionally, IDC predicts the global
data sphere will expand to 175 zettabytes.
So these figures.
illustrate the sheer volume of data
organizations which must manage.
So multi cloud and the hybrid cloud
strategies provide scalable, I would
say the cost effective solutions
to handle this exponential growth.
So while maintaining
performance and flexibility.
So it's very clear why these architectures
are becoming essential in, in ID strategy.
So what is a multi cloud?
So multi cloud architecture
allows organizations to use
multiple cloud providers
leveraging Each provider strength.
So the key benefits, which includes the
redundancy, vendor flexibility, cost
optimization, performance enhancement.
So performance enhancements
through the distributed workloads.
So however, managing multi cloud
environments can increase complexity,
introduce The security challenges
and require skilled professionals
for effective implementation.
So despite all these challenges, 75%, I
would say 76 percent of the organization
now use a multi clouds highlighting
the growing demand for this strategy.
So coming to the challenges, I would like
to discuss, of course, multi cloud isn't.
Without its hurdles.
So complexity arises from
managing diverse environments.
Security policies must remain
consistent and integrating data across
different platforms can be daunting.
So additionally, organizations face
Skill gaps and cost management issues.
So overcoming these challenges
requires a careful planning.
I would say robust tools and a
team of a skilled professionals.
So in our next slide, we'll
see what is a hybrid cloud.
So the hybrid cloud combines
on prem systems with private
public cloud services.
So this kind of an approach
offers several advantages.
I would say data sovereignty.
So data sovereignty is nothing but
the sensitive data remains secure
on prem or in a private clouds.
So I would say next advantage
would be the scalability.
So the public cloud resources can handle
the peak workloads and coming to another
advantage would be the legacy integration.
So which allows the gradual
migration of legacy systems to
the cloud and the cost efficiency.
So archives less access data in
the lower cost public storage
according to a Nutanix survey.
So 87 percent of the IT decision
makers consider hybrid cloud
in their IT more IT model.
So with adoption expected
to grow significantly.
So coming to our next slide, the hybrid
cloud benefits for data management.
So hybrid cloud is particularly
beneficial of, data management.
So it supports regularity
compliance by keeping sensitive
data secure while offering the
scalability for dynamic workloads.
And moreover, it enables gradual
migration of legacy systems.
Ensuring, operational continuity and
reduces the storage cost by leveraging
cost effective public cloud solutions.
So these advantages make hybrid a
cornerstone for the modern IT strategies.
so we'll see how, the overcoming
of hybrid cloud challenges.
So however, hybrid cloud
adoption also has its challenges.
Integration between on prem
infrastructure and the cloud
services can be a very complex.
So ensuring all the security and
compliance across environments, which
will require the robust frameworks.
And the cost management depends
continuous monitoring like multi
cloud hybrid cloud success on the
skilled professionals and the right
tools to manage the diverse systems.
So I would say the best practices
for the multi cloud and the hybrid
cloud implement implementations.
to maximize the benefits of multicloud
and hybrid cloud strategies, our nation
should follow these key basic best
practices, like the data governance,
integration tools, cloud, agnostic
technologies, the continuous optimization.
So these will regularly monitor
the performance and cost to adapt
to changing whatever the needs.
I would like to conclude.
So in a conclusion, so multi cloud
and hybrid cloud architectures are
pivotal for the modern data management.
So they offer unparalleled
flexibility, scalability and
cost efficiency, making them
indispensable for data transformation.
So while the challenges like the
integration and the security process.
They can be addressed with best practices
and skilled teams as the multi cloud
market grows to a project, projected, I
would say, 46 billion dollars by 2027.
So these architectures will continue to
empower the organizations to thrive in an
increasingly complex, digital landscape.
yeah, so thank you for your attention.
I hope this session has provided a
valuable insights into leveraging
the multi cloud and the hybrid cloud
strategies for effective data management.
So I look forward for
your further discussions.
Thank you.