Hello, everybody.
My name is Shraddha Kohli.
And today I will be talking about
building user trust in conversational AI.
The role of explainable AI
in chatbot transparency.
Today's presentation explores
the application of explainable AI
techniques to enhance transparency
and trust in chatbot decision making.
As chatbots have become increasingly
more sophisticated and popular,
Understanding their internal reasoning
still remains a significant challenge.
Let's first try to understand how do
chatbot technologies actually evolve.
The rapid advancement of chatbot
technologies have revolution,
have revolutionized human computer
interaction, offering increasingly
sophisticated conversational
experiences across various domains.
However, as these AI driven
systems become more complex, they
often operate as black boxes.
making it challenging for users and
developers both to understand the
rationale behind their responses.
This opacity can lead to issues of
trust, accountability, and difficulty
in improving the system performances.
The early chatbots came in around the
1960s, which primarily relied on pattern
matching and predefined responses.
Then came the machine learning era.
With the advent of machine learning
and NLP techniques in the 21st century,
it led to more advanced chatbots
capable of understanding context
and generating human like responses.
With all these, the current
challenges such as transparency,
leading to issues such as unexpected
responses and biased decision making.
In order to curb these
challenges, We did a study.
Let's first take a look at what is the
overview of explainable AI techniques.
Explainable AI techniques aim to
demystify this decision making
processes of complex AI systems.
Three key methods are
explored in this study.
The first one is called LIME, local
interpretable model agnostic explanations,
which help to create local linear
approximations of the model's behavior.
By perturbing inputs
and observing outputs.
The second technique that we used was
SHAP, shapely additive explanations using
game theory to provide a unified measure
of feature importance, offering both
global as well as local interpretability.
Lastly, we used
counterfactual explanations.
Focus on providing minimal changes
to the input that would result in
a different output, helping users
understand key decision factors.
In our research, we, we researched around
150 users across different demographics,
and we employed three state of the art
chatbot models, a retrieval based model,
a generative model based on transformer
architecture, and a hybrid model.
We applied the three techniques that
I just mentioned to these models,
assessing their effectiveness
using metrics such as faithfulness.
stability, as well as comprehensibility.
The three stages were, we first did
a model selection, then we applied
one of the explainable AI methods,
and then we evaluated the results.
Our study revealed that each of the
explainable AI techniques offered unique
insights into the chatbot decision making.
LIME effectively provided local
explanations for individual
responses, while SHAP offered
a more comprehensive view.
of feature importance across
multiple interactions.
Counterfactual explanations were
particularly useful in highlighting
the sensitivity of chatbot
responses to specific input changes.
The impact of our use on user, the
impact of our study on user trust and
understanding was that It demonstrated
a significant improvement in the trust
and understanding when interacting
with explainable AI enhanced chatbots.
Participants reported that they felt more
confident in the chatbots ability and
were more likely to forgive occasional
errors when provided with explanations.
This whole black box sort of
became a white box to them.
The ability to see the reasoning
behind responses led to increased
user engagement and willingness to use
the chatbot for more complex tasks.
Without the explainable AI, they
had very limited understanding
of the chatbot decisions.
And they had low forgiveness of errors.
With explainable AI, this comprehension
improved by 48 percent, their error
tolerance improved by 40 percent,
and their increased use of chatbots
for complex tasks such as healthcare
or finance increased by 27 percent.
Overall, the user trust increased
by 35 percent, and the user
enhancement increased by 31 percent.
These results were very promising.
However, still, there are some challenges
in implementing these explainable AI
techniques for chatbots, such as the
real time nature of chatbot interactions.
You sometimes make it difficult to
generate comprehensive explanations
without introducing significant latency.
Additionally, balancing the level
of detail in our explanations
with user comprehension is also
a challenge as we don't want our
explanations to be too technical.
Such that such as non technical
users cannot understand that model
compatibility is another issue.
Adapting the correct explainable
AI technique to various chatbot
architectures and what model we want to
select is also one of the challenges.
The integration of explainable
AI techniques in chatbot systems
has far reaching implications for
their development and deployment.
Developers can use the insights
gained from explainable AI to refine
the chatbot models address biases
and improve response accuracy.
Furthermore, the explainable AI
can facilitate easier debugging
and maintenance of chatbot
systems, potentially reducing
long term development costs.
So it definitely has an
impact on the developer users.
The ethical considerations
in transparent AI driven.
This raises important ethical
considerations because while we want
transparency to build trust, we also want
to make sure that we are not exposing
any sensitive information about the
underlying models or the training data.
So striking that balance between
transparency and privacy is crucial.
Furthermore, there is a need to ensure
that explanations are presented unbiasedly
and do not inadvertently reinforce
societal prejudices or stereotypes.
Some of the future research directions
is that as our language models become
increasingly sophisticated, there
is pressing need for a more advanced
explainable AI techniques that can
effectively interpret and explain
their decision making processes.
Future research should focus more
on developing methods that can
handle the complexity of transformer
based architecture and other
state of the art language models.
This may involve exploring hierarchical
explanations approaches that can
provide insights at different levels
of abstraction, from individual
attention weights to higher
level semantic representation.
Overall, with this study, we were
able to demonstrate the significant
potential of explainable AI techniques
in enhancing the transparency and
trustworthiness of chatbot systems through
the application of methods such as LIME,
SHAP, and counterfactual explanations.
We have gained invaluable insights
into chatbot decision making processes.
Our research has shown that integrating
explainable AI into chatbots
not only improves user trust and
understanding, but also provides
developers with powerful tools for
refining and improving these systems.
As chatbots continue to evolve,
the need for transparency and
accountability also becomes more crucial.
And there is a lot of future
potential in this area.
Thank you.