Good morning, everyone.
I am Chirag.
I work at Nutanix in
cyber security with AI ML.
so today I am going to cover a
presentation on pioneering AI frontiers
using deep learning based techniques.
So what is reinforcement learning?
So reinforcement learning right now is a
very new frontier in deep learning, and,
Reinforcement learning is, a learning
which involves complex decision making and
there are a lot of reinforcement learning
based models, which involves neural
networks, which are currently in use.
And the current market of,
AI is going to increase.
As you see over here.
It'll increase by one
90 mil billion by 2025.
Maybe by 2030 it'll be.
Almost 10 times more.
And these kinds of deep learning
techniques currently can
outperform traditional ML models.
So that is why deep learning based
techniques are a lot in demand.
These are, used in a lot of applications
like image classification, autonomous
driving, and, many other, techniques.
So the main core over here is a neural
network and reinforcement learning
basically is a technique which involves
interacting with environments and
using trial and error based approaches.
So wherever the neural network works,
it tries to find the errors, then it
will try to minimize the errors and in
turn try to So that is how the algorithm
works and combines deep neural networks
and also it has state space management.
Now we come to the milestones.
The AlphaGo's victory over Lee Sedol
highlighted superhuman strategic planning.
Then in 2018, we saw UC Berkeley,
which enabled robotic kind of
grasping, high success rate.
And in 2023, Waymo self driving cars,
they achieved 35 billion simulated
and 20 million real time miles.
So these are very good achievements,
which have reinforcement learning using
neural networks, which are being applied.
Now we come to.
Accelerating training
using transfer learning.
So what is transfer learning in
reinforcement learning enables agents to
apply knowledge from one task to another.
And significantly, this reduces the.
Timing, training time, and effort.
So this is a key advantage
of this algorithm.
It has faster adaptation
to new environments.
So these kinds of neural networks in
reinforcement learning have a capability
to adapt to any kind of conditions.
And reduce training data requirements.
So machine learning algorithms
work by training the data and then
generating some of the results.
So the more you train the models,
there is a chance of overfitting
and that kind of scenario.
So neural network over here is very.
Optimized and it will try to train the
model with reduced data Requirements
and it will try to provide generation
and output in a short span of time
with high accuracy So that is why these
kind of applications like autonomous
driving, robotics, then game AI, all
these kind of applications, they are
using reinforcement learning and, these
kind of, machines, they leverage, such
kind of neural networks, which will
take some of the training data and
generate proper, kind of output, which is
capable of, Of improving the experience.
So for example, in autonomous driving,
the neural networks are so advanced
that they will be able to detect
anything in the road, any issues which
are happening in the road, and it
will apply the brakes, then it will
accelerate at certain point of times.
And similarly, in robotics, the robots
can detect any kind of boundaries or any.
Places where they are not supposed to go
and games, they perform quite better and
it will help in better game generation
and using less training of data.
So this is where reinforcement
learning is a boon.
And, then we come up over here in this
slide, it, it provides information
about the generative AI market.
So how much is the market
capitalization right now?
And by 2030 maybe the project,
projected, capitalization will be
a lot more, almost around 33.7%.
So it would be, I guess it would
be like, around 40 billion.
30 to 40 billion.
Yeah.
And, over here, we also have GANs,
Generative Adversarial Networks, and
VAEs, which is Variational Autoencoders.
These are two different kinds of
models, so Generative Adversarial
Networks, they focus on generating
data and through training, whereas
Variational Autoencoders, they
are actually, they create compact.
certain kind of data representation
for generation, some kind of
analysis, that kind of thing.
So these two are very
different kind of models.
And let's go over here in
this slide, how they work.
So GANs are two networks, generator,
discriminator, they compete to
improve data generation quality.
And basically it will be utilized
to generate certain kind of things
like for example, image generation.
Then we have video synthesis.
Then we have medical data augmentation.
So which involves classification
and then we have drug discovery.
So all these applications are it's
covering something and using model
training to perform certain kind
of generation, image generation,
video synthesis, then medically
in medical field, it will try
to improve the classification.
which is a very important thing.
Like you, Using certain kinds of
inputs, it will generate certain kind
of patterns and we'll try to find
out the pattern and classify into
better thing or classify a medicine
or classify certain kind of things.
And similarly in drug discovery,
GANs will try to kind of classify
and generate certain kind of modern
molecules for medicine development, maybe
fighting certain kinds of illnesses.
So we see GANs.
will have a lot of capability in next few
years where it will not only improve the
drug discovery, but also help in image
generation and maybe in cyber security or
security and that kind of applications,
it will have a very huge impact.
Now, we come to VAEs and over here
how VAEs work, they encode the data
into latent space and reconstruct
it, and that is how it will learn,
and it will become more efficient.
one good example over
here is anomaly detection.
so whenever certain kinds of
neural network, they find certain
kinds of issues in the data,
it'll classify it as an anomaly.
anomaly detection.
Then we have dimensionality reduction.
So over here it'll have compressed
gene data by 98% and it'll,
reduce the dimensionality.
And thirdly, another use case
would be music generation.
generated, 16 bar melodies and it will
have a lot of, satisfaction rates.
So these, these don't do any
kind of generation, but they try
to do certain kinds of, anomaly
detection and that kind of thing.
And these.
techniques will become popular in next
few years, and it will be utilized
in a lot of other applications.
Now we come to AI in cyber security.
So in this cyber security, it will do
a lot of things like threat detection,
threat monitoring, and vulnerability
assessment and fraud detection.
We do see a lot of, in, cyber security,
we see a lot of, certain kinds of
threats are not monitored properly and
it leads to a lot of, issues and, a lot
of threats and a lot of vulnerabilities.
And there are, Current tools, which
are available in cybersecurity,
they don't detect such kind of
vulnerabilities and threats.
maybe in next few years, AI using GAN
and VIEs with, these techniques, they
will improve the threat detection
and anomaly detection And basically.
in cybersecurity, most of the companies
won't use these kinds of tools and
they will rely heavily in this machine
learning models and such kind of things
to improve their security posture
and, use AI based threat detection.
It can also do maybe in
future AI based techniques.
We can also do threat modeling
and, identifying risks, within
the organization and maybe.
Possibly detecting DDoS attacks
and such kind of things.
Now we come to future trends in AI.
So in future trends of ai, we have graph
neural networks, which can enhance,
AI's capability to process graph
structured data like social networks,
recommendation systems and drug discovery.
So graph neural networks are also very
important kind of neural networks,
which can be utilized in recommendation.
for example, we see in Netflix.
and Amazon prime.
There are a lot of recommendations and
certain things which are being done.
So these company maybe in future can
leverage a graph neural networks and
such kind of sophisticated algorithms to
improve the accuracy of recommendation.
Then try to process text image or video
and certain kinds of applications.
Then we have AI in IoT and
certain, other applications
where AI can have a huge impact.
this is what we have seen
in enforcement learning.
It has a lot of unparalleled capabilities
in doing complex tasks like autonomous
driving, robotics, industrial
automation, and it uses GANs and VAIs
to unlock a lot of new possibilities.
Helping creativity and problem solving
these kind of approaches can help the
organization to improve upon their
security posture, improve the drug
discovery and have a lot of big impact
in decision making capabilities.
Even in cyber security, maybe 30 which
are being used, they might be either,
GANs or VAEs, which can be used to detect
certain kinds of threats and improve the
security posture within the security org.
So that's it from my side.
If you have any questions,
please let us know.