Hello, good morning.
Good afternoon.
Good evening everyone Depending
on where you are joining from.
my name is Akshat Kapoor and I welcome
you to my talk on real time analytics
in IIoT, before we dive in a bit
about myself, I have been in the
tech industry for over 20 years now,
working with some great organizations
like Alcatel Lucent Enterprise,
Dell Labs, and Nokia, my career has
mostly focused on product management.
guiding product portfolios and finding
innovative solutions that drive growth
for the company at Alcatel Lucent.
I am responsible for the full
range of, Ethernet switching
products from campus land and
industrial Ethernet to data center.
Switches.
My current areas of focus are
AI, ML, and industrial IoT.
And that relates to the topic for today.
And that brings me back to the topic.
IoT and industrial IoT are
transforming industries by connecting
devices and creating smarter
and more efficient operations.
Today we will uncover its potential
and go through the journey of how
real time analytics is revolutionizing
the industrial processes.
We will start with some building blocks
of the architecture that enables real
time analytics and go on to see how
all these pieces put together enable
the real time decision making for
predictive preventive maintenance.
for optimizing operations and
saving money for various industries.
So let's talk about IoT or
industrial IoT in modern industries.
The internet of things or IoT has
evolved as a cornerstone of industry 4.
0, which is connecting physical
devices to enable smarter operations.
The convergence of IT and OT systems
drives automation and efficiency,
offering key benefits like predictive
maintenance, operational optimization,
and real time decision making.
Examples of its transformative effect can
be seen in industries like manufacturing,
logistics, oil and gas, utilities such as
electrical utilities, and smart cities.
Real time data processing
and why it matters.
Real time data is critical
in dynamic environments.
where timely insights lead
to competitive advantages.
However, businesses face
challenges like scalability,
interoperability, and handling
diverse data coming from the sensors.
By overcoming these hurdles,
organizations can unlock faster
decision making and operational success.
A manufacturer might use sensors
throughout an assembly line to predict
when a machine will likely break down.
Or an oil and gas organization might
use predictive analytics on data from
sensors installed across a pipeline
to help identify corrosion and damage.
Industrial IoT brings together connected
intelligent devices and analytics in
a way that allows organizations to
monitor Collect, exchange, analyze,
and deliver valuable new insights
about their processes and systems.
Now, we'll talk about some of the benefits
of IIoT real time analytics, and how we
are utilizing zettabytes of IoT data.
Now, as we know that the IoT devices
produces a ton of data, And, data
from these telemetrics about a
device or machine's condition, when
combined with historical performance
records, can offer deep insights that
predict and help prevent failures.
For instance, a common method
to prevent equipment downtime is
replacing a component as it approaches
its mean time to failure, or MTTF.
By leveraging machine learning based
analytics on real time IoT data combined
with product history information, it is
possible to detect early warning signs
of potential issues in parts before
they reach their failure age or MTTF.
More efficient and automated
QA processes reduce cost while
improving product quality.
IoT data can help identify inefficiencies.
that when resolved lead
to increased output.
Now let's look at the basic building
blocks of some of these IoT architectures.
You can call it a three layer
architecture that you see in the blue
on the left hand side, or you can call
them four if you want to follow the
architecture on the right in green.
That includes the application layer
that includes the applications
and all that run on top of
analytics and the management layer.
But the basic three layers
are the same in both of them.
So let's start with the sensing layer.
The sensing layer is the one
which collects data using
edge devices and sensors.
Firstly, there is the issue of data
preparation to harness the value of IoT
and deliver innovation driving insights.
Organizations must quickly prepare
and standardize great volumes
of disparate unstructured data.
This is a common problem across
all any AI ML based system,
which is required for analytics.
But it is more compounded in
industrial IoT because the sensors
from different parts of the
manufacturing line or wherever they
are installed have very disparate data.
It's, some have geolocation
tagging enabled, some have
not, and so on and so forth.
As we all know, the data preparation
takes up to 80 percent of the time and
resources in a data analysis operation.
In heterogeneous IoT systems.
And devices exhibit a wide variety
of characteristics and differ in
their computing, communication,
and storage capabilities.
Now let's talk about
the communication layer.
The communication layer ensures
efficient data transmission
through robust protocols.
The communication layer, supported by
multi service gateways, forms the central
network for IoT data transmission.
Managing both uplink and downlink of
feedback from the, from the analytics
layer due to the diversity of the IOT
devices, various communication protocols
are utilized within IOT systems.
And I'll be talking about this in
another slide further down and finally,
the the analytics layer processes this
data that is coming from the sensing
layer to the communication layer and
using edge cloud or hybrid methods,
balancing latency and performance.
And we will also be talking about
this further in, in this presentation.
Real time analytics in IoT systems
emphasizes designing system architectures
capable of performing data analysis and
delivering responses within a specified
timeframe, referred to as the deadline.
Depending on this application, this
deadline can vary, ranging from
nanoseconds in computer network
communications, To milliseconds
in medical diagnosis real time
industrial iot systems are of two
types predictive and prescriptive.
And they are different from diagnostic
or descriptive kind of analytics
because they have to work in real time.
Traditionally, there are two
types of architectures used in
the analytics layer, which is the
edge, cloud hybrid or the cloud.
There's also a third type of, new
kind of, analytics architecture,
which is based on simulation and
that's the most upcoming and promising
technology that is there today and I
will talk about it in another slide.
So let's talk about the first
layer which is the sensors from
where the actual data is collected.
The specific type of sensors that are
deployed within an IIoT system depends
on the machinery being monitored
and the parameter most critical
for predicting potential failures.
So common type of sensors that are
employed are vibration sensors,
temperature sensors, pressure sensors,
or current and power consumption sensors,
or any, which is required for the type of
environment other than the type choosing
the right type of sensor, the strategic
placement of the sensors throughout
the machinery is also essential for
capturing the most informative data.
Now we talk about the second layer,
which is the communication layer.
which is required for real time analytics.
Automating processes by integrating the
operational technology OT with information
technology IT as mandated by industry 4.
0 brings stringent real time demands for
industrial networks making predictable and
reliable packet routing very essential.
Traditional IP networks which
operate on a best effort basis are
insufficient for these real time needs.
and require specialized protocols
and standards to meet these
performance expectations.
Depending on the type of industrial
network, there are different type of
requirements for the network to perform.
For example, autonomous systems,
such as robots and drones,
require high predictability and
medium to high latency tolerance.
Remote control applications need low
bandwidth, but highly reliable networks.
Data analysis and monitoring require high
bandwidth for sensor data aggregation.
Traditional embedded systems only
have limited computing capabilities
due to power and space constraints.
To this end, currently, especially in
the field of mobile edge computing,
considers the offloading of delay
sensitive tasks to local servers.
Worker safety systems emphasize
latency and reliability to
react promptly to hazards.
Now talking about security, which
is true for any kind of network, but
more so in on industrial networks, not
only the data on the network should
be encrypted, it should be able to
detect network intrusions in time.
And last but not the least, the, as
networks are used to converge IT and OT
systems to build a distributed system,
everyone should have a common and
shared understanding of time and real
time for real time networks to work.
No one single system today is capable
of meeting all the requirements.
And, of course, the type of network
that is chosen is based on, the type
of end system and what its requirements
are in terms of predictability,
latency, bandwidth, so on and so forth.
as I said, real time analytics
requires real time networks.
The current package switch network,
which is based on best effort, is not
sufficient to meet the requirements
of real time analytics in IIoT.
Various approaches can be applied to
improve real time IIoT networking, and
there is no one size fits all here and
depends on the end user environment.
Some of these approaches are
software defined networking or SDN.
As industrial networks grow more complex
with mixed computing systems and real
time demands, SDN offers a solution
for managing this heterogeneity.
Next comes the TSN and this has to do
with the shared sense of time and a common
and more secure way of for networks to
be able to deliver the time across all
the devices whether they are IoT devices
or IT systems connected on the network.
Time sensitive networking or TSN is
a set of IEEE standards for Ethernet
enabling networks to achieve bounded
latency and minimal packet loss for
critical traffic at the data link layer.
It ensures lower jitter and
more orderly packet delivery.
Additionally, it incorporates precise and
detailed quality of service mechanisms.
New standards have evolved that have
improved some of the shortcomings
and the lack of flexibility of TSN by
integrating it with other systems such
as OPC or adding profanate support,
which is a mechanism for visibility.
of IT and OT systems in a common
network or in a common management plane.
OPC or Open Platform Communications
Unified Architecture is an
interoperability standard for
reliable information exchange.
And has gained a lot of momentum
for discussion on IIoT networks now
talking about wireless technologies.
So a very natural step is to,
transition this TSN methods
or time sensitive network.
networking methods to use to be
working with wireless technologies.
similarly, the I iot devices, which
require 5G wireless connectivity.
The network slicing there allows for
logically separated virtual networks
over the same physical 5G network.
And last but not the least, there
are some technologies that have
evolved on the device layer, such as.
MAC layer filtering that mitigates
the effects of best effort traffic
reception on real time tasks.
So you see the technologies on the
networking side have to evolve to
manage the data coming from the sensor
to enable the real time analytics.
And as I said, there is no one size
fits all, and it all depends on the
end user environment to adopt the
right type of network and the right
type of technology to enable this.
Okay, now we talk about the analytics
layer and what are the different
type of architectures that are used
in enabling the analytics The first
one is the cloud based architecture.
The cloud based architecture is a
centralized, processing in remote
cloud servers, provides high
computational power, but there is a
challenge here, which is there is a
high latency, there is a limitation
of bandwidth, and the connection
could be unstable, which may not be
suitable for a real time application.
Next comes the edge cloud collaboration or
the edge cloud collaborative architecture.
This combines local edge
computing with cloud resources.
Edge devices process data
closer to IoT devices.
which reduces latency and
bandwidth requirements.
Cloud platforms handle the complex
analytics and storage tasks, whereas
the edge devices manage the latency
and bandwidth requirements by
being closer to the IoT devices.
This hybrid model optimizes task
allocation for real time requirements
while mitigating the challenges that are
faced in purely cloud based architectures.
these are the two which are, have
been traditionally been used.
And there is a new architecture that
is emerging today is the digital twin.
The digital twins are virtual replicas of
physical systems, which are continuously
updated with real time data to mirror
the actual state of the system.
At that point, they are very useful in
predictive analysis, process optimization,
and data driven decision making.
These are combined with simulation models.
for decision support systems.
There are mainly two types of models
used for simulation in industries.
The first one is the
discrete event simulation.
This models allows for analyzing complex
manufacturing systems by creating a
model and replicating their behavior
over a period of time and then producing
models, producing predictions over that.
The second one is a
hybrid simulation method.
This involves integrating the virtual
model with the real world system.
So imagine a digital twin replica
running, integrated into a
physical system as another node.
And it is continuously monitoring
and provides adaptive control
of the system in real time.
So these, this is some of, this is one
of the new technologies that are emerging
on the horizon and which is very useful
for Real time analytics in IOT, IIOT.
Now we have, gone through
all the three layers.
we have the data coming from the sensors.
We have talked about what
kind of networks are required.
To send this data across with minimal
latency, right amount of bandwidth and,
carrying the time, and being secure.
And then the third approach we
saw how we, the architecture
of where the analytics happens.
Now we want to talk about is.
What AI techniques we can use to
generate the real time analytics.
So there are two approaches here,
which, are machine learning based
approaches and the other one being
the deep learning based approach.
The choice of machine learning, learning
algorithms used in real time analytic
systems depend on several factors such
as, the type of equipment being monitored,
what is the intended functionality.
For example, you want to do anomaly
detection, or you want to do
classification, or you want to predict
the remaining useful life of an
equipment, and so on and so forth.
And also, this is influenced by
the attributes of the available
data set, which may not be the same
for different kinds of situations.
So in the machine learning approach,
we have broadly two methods, supervised
learning and unsupervised learning.
So this is common for
any AI ML based system.
I'm just going to highlight here
what is mostly used in these
terms for industrial IOT systems.
So supervised learning algorithms, as we
know, Excel at pattern recognition and
classification tasks for label data set.
where each data point is associated
with a predefined category or outcome.
Support vector machines or SVMs and the
decision trees, they are very powerful
supervised learning algorithms that are
well suited at classification tasks.
and that can help identify
potential equipment issues.
Okay.
Now, contrary to supervised learning,
unsupervised learning algorithms work
with unlabeled data where data points
do not have any predefined categories.
They are particularly effective
at uncovering patterns and
relationships within the data,
making them well suited for tasks
like anomaly detection and so on.
Within unsupervised learning,
techniques like k means clustering,
which is a popular unsupervised
learning method, is used for data
segmentation and the other one being
the principal component analysis, PCA.
is a dimensionality reduction
method that extracts the most
important features from a data set.
Supervised and unsupervised learning
techniques provide a robust set
of tools for detecting patterns
and anomalies in sensor data
gathered by industrial IoT systems.
Now, utilizing these machine
learning algorithms, systems can
derive meaningful insights from
real time data streams, supporting
proactive maintenance strategies,
and improving overall equipment
efficiency in industrial operations.
But deep learning that utilizes
artificial neural networks with multiple
hidden layers is capable of learning
complex patterns and relationships
within data, which often outperform
traditional machine learning algorithms.
in certain applications.
So it all depends on your end
application, whether you want to
apply the machine learning approach
or the deep learning technique.
Of course, deep learning techniques
are more complex to deploy, but they
do offer several advantages over
machine learning techniques such as.
automatic feature extraction, improved
pattern recognition, real time anomaly
detection, scalability, and adaptability.
Some of the architectures, which I'm
going to talk about, is common with any
other deep learning techniques deployed
in other machine learning algorithms.
But here in industrial IoT, the most
common ones used are convolutional neural
networks, Recurrent neural networks
and of course the hybrid of the two.
The advantage of convolutional neural
networks is to automatically learn and
extract key features from raw sensor data.
Whereas the RNNs, Recurrent Neural
Networks, have the ability to learn
long term dependencies within the data.
Within RNNs, Long Short Term Memory,
or LSTM, networks analyze historical
sensor data combined with equipment
failure timestamps, to learn machinery
degradation patterns over time.
This ability enables them to
accurately predict the remaining
useful life of equipment.
A third model, which is very promising
and a new one, is focusing on integrating
the strengths of CNNs and LSTMs into
a unified deep learning architecture.
CNNs can be utilized for extracting
features from sensor data, while
LSTMs leverage these features to
capture temporal dependencies and
predict equipment health or remaining
useful life of the equipment.
This hybrid approach has the
potential to improve the accuracy and
efficiency of AI driven solutions.
So we have talked about all the three
layers and we have talked about what
sort of analytics to apply to get
the real time digital analytics.
Now is the time to see the IoT
applications in action and how they are
being used across multiple industries.
They span, of course, multiple industries,
smart systems, revolutionize healthcare,
energy grids, and environmental
monitoring, real time analytics,
monitor traffic in smart cities, manage
energy usage, and detect anomalies.
Examples include predicting
traffic congestion using
sensor and social media data.
In smart healthcare, IoT devices
support chronic disease monitoring
and emergency detection.
The edge cloud collaboration architecture
in analytics enables timely responses
as seen in systems for diseases such as
obstructive sleep apnea and dementia care.
In smart electricity grids, Real
time data ensures efficient energy
distribution, and minimizing the outages.
Analytics optimize demand response
system for better energy management
and in industrial IoT, they facilitate
automation, predictive maintenance,
and process optimization using low
latency network architectures to
meet critical operational demands.
And the third one is on the digital twins.
we talked about it earlier.
They are helpful in optimizing
production and supply chain.
And they can be seen in aviation
industry's use of predictive
analytics to reduce the downtime.
Of course, no system is perfect
and there are, of course,
challenges in IoT data processing.
Managing IoT data involves
addressing its volume, velocity,
and variety of different data sets.
Networking demands such as time sensitive
networking and advancements like 5G
are very critical to ensure seamless
connectivity from a network standpoint.
Additionally, there is currently a lack
of standardization across platforms.
which are hindering the seamless
integration and interoperability
of IOT or industrial IOT systems.
So you could have wireless
and your IOT devices could be
connected through wireless as
well as through wired networks.
And there is no standardization across
these two types of networks, for
example, to do time sensitive networking.
for listening.
or to provide quality of
service and so on and so forth.
Now we understand security is
paramount and so is the case
for industrial IoT systems.
The growing threat to connected devices
requires a very robust encryption and
authentication protocols to safeguard
the sensitive data that is carried
through the network from the sensors.
Also, regulatory compliance with
standards like GDPR and ISO 27001
would require would foster the trust
and accountability of these systems.
I'll talk about some of
the future trends in IOT.
So first is on from shaped by
emerging technologies like 5g,
digital twins, and quantum computing.
On the second.
Aspect is the enhanced edge cloud
collaboration, which is required for
optimizing task allocation and requires
communication protocols to balance
computational load and minimize delays.
The third ones are about the
advancements in privacy and security
by protecting sensitive data and
ensuring robust authentication
mechanisms, especially in dynamic
and heterogeneous IoT environments,
such as leveraging blockchain for
decentralized security, for example.
This all will drive further
innovation, making IoT systems
smarter and more resilient.
In conclusion, real time IoT analytics
are revolutionizing industries,
offering actionable insights, and
have a transformative potential.
Collaboration between stakeholders
and continuous innovation are
essential for unlocking the
full potential of IoT systems.
The future lies in adaptive
technologies and seamless integration.
Thank you all for your attention today.
I hope you have a great day and you
enjoy the rest of your conference.
Thank you.