Hello.
Good afternoon.
Good morning, good evening.
Thanks for joining our session.
My name is Guillermo with and today
we're going to talk about how we
build a Roseberry pie super cluster
using Postgres on Kubernetes and all
the journey we've had till today.
It's been like eight months of project and
I would like to introduce you to the team.
today is not Jorge Ano with us.
Jorge is a software engineer on Andre.
The company that created a solution
that we will be deploying today that
it's called Stackgres, Postgres on
Kubernetes, and myself, which is Guillermo
Ruiz, and I'm Senior Developer for AWS.
Before we start in this journey,
I would like to give thanks
to a person and a project.
This has been inspired by Chris Benson,
who is the guy that built the largest
Raspberry Pi cluster that we know
of, with 1053 Raspberry Pi cards, and
also Los Alamos National Laboratory.
Which they had back in 2019.
Moreover, a 750 Raspberry Pi cluster
that was divided in five clusters with
mounted in racks, each one with 150
Raspberry Pis and everything integrated.
It was such a big project that got our
attention and we came and said, why don't
we build a Raspberry Pi super cluster?
why we did this?
first of all, It's supposed to
be affordable computing, and
we will see as we go into the
session that is not the case.
It's much cheaper than having big servers
out there and a lot of compute, but even
though it's a cost that we need to afford.
Also from an educational and practical
perspective, we wanted a hands on
approach for distributed computing.
And we've been learning the hard way, to
be honest, and you will see it throughout
the lessons that we're going to share.
With our audience today, but also we
wanted to have a real world application,
a live demo of a functional stack risk
cluster running on the 63 Raspberry Pi.
So how does it look like?
This is the cluster that we build.
It's on a pelican case, and it's a
way that we can port it to events and
showcasing meetup and many other places.
So Why don't we start and say, why do
we need to build this kind of projects?
First of all, we need a
bunch of Raspberry Pi.
And I want to give thanks to many
people, because this has been a
friend project, asking friends
to lend us the Raspberry Pis.
Thanks to Ongres, thanks to the guys
from the Brain School, Datadobe.
They brought a bunch of
Raspberry Pis, and we'll see.
They were not the latest one.
We will be working with
a 3B which is cool.
Quite a bit old, to be honest,
but that's what we had.
We also had all the electronics, the PDUs,
the fans, all the servers, and you will
see that we had to split and increase
the number of devices for this cluster.
And we had this wonderful Pelican case.
But one of the components that was
really interesting was the 3D printer,
because we use, and thanks to our
friends from Prusa Research that lent
us the MP4 3D printer, We print the bay
where we're going to connect all the
Raspberry Pis, and even how we handle
the fans on the back was 3D printed.
From a software perspective,
we're going to use Ubuntu 24.
04, which is the latest long
term support release of this
popular Linux operating system.
We will also have K3S, which is a
lightweight Kubernetes distribution
that is optimized for resource
constrained environments like
this one that we're talking about
IoT, and it's easy to install.
Although it requires minimal memory and
CPU, but we will see that's going to
be also a challenge during our project.
The second component is the Stackgres,
which is an open source platform for
running Postgres on Kubernetes, and
it combines the power of both tools.
We have PX boot.
We run out of money, so we couldn't
have SD cards for every single
Raspberry Pi in the cluster.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to boot it from the
network and see what happens.
We've seen hardware, software, and
a lot of hours, immensely a lot of
hours to build this whole thing.
Let's start with the engineer
feature, how we plan and how we
see this cluster come in life.
We had a phase of planning and
designing of how we wanted to
connect and how many Raspberry Pis,
which was dependent of the month.
Of raspberries that we could get from
the friends and the people, but also
how we could assemble this into a
cluster and using the 3D printers.
This is mainly from the
hardware perspective.
So we got from unify.
We've got a couple of switches in
a gateway, but we also had, to Two
USB chargers, each of 40 ports, so
the maximum capacity we will have
in our cluster is 80 Raspberry Pi.
So there are the brackets where we had
three rows with 21 Raspberry Pis each.
But there are multiple pieces
on the 3D printed side.
We had to print over 84
pieces just to assemble.
Not just the Raspberry, but also the fans.
As you can see, we're using
five fans per row, which takes
us into 15 in total for this.
let's take an overall view of
the whole specs that we have.
It's Raspberry Pi, it's a 3B we have 63.
On CPU bit quad core ARM with 1.
2 GHz per core.
We have 250 cores and we
have a clock speed of 302.
4 GHz.
Each Raspberry Pi card has one gig.
Total of 63 gigs in this one and
then a bunch of multiple ports that
many of them were not used here.
let's start with the networking.
Once we've got everything assembled
and we have everything in our
Pelikan case, we started with a flat
topology for this 63 Raspberry Pis.
Meaning that all nodes were directly
connected without any hierarchy.
To manage the cluster, we implemented
a central control plane acting as
the brain of the system, and it was
responsible for coordinating tasks,
collecting metrics, and ensuring a
smooth operation across all the nodes.
The network config was kept simple, with
all Raspberry Pi sharing the single 300
megs bandwidth, that is what we have
with these 3B plus Raspberry Pis, which
enable the communication between the
nodes and the central control plane.
this setup allow us to quickly deploy and
test the cluster, but it also highlighted
challenges like bandwidth saturation
and CPU overhead as the system scale.
Here is a bit of how we implemented
the structure topology, where we're
using two switches of 48 ports
connecting the 63 Raspberry Pi, and
the switches handle the intra cluster
communication, ensuring that low latency
connectivity between all the nodes.
To provide external access to manage all
the routing, we integrated a gateway which
connects the cluster directly to Internet.
And additionally, there are small devices
called UCK G2, it's the unified cloud
key generation 2, was deployed to manage
and monitor the network configuration.
It offers us centralized control and
visibility into network performance.
as you can see, very simple setup.
It provides us a manageable infrastructure
for the cluster while we balance
communication and internet connectivity.
I want to show how it looks like.
The Raspberry Pi is connected
to different switches.
We talk about two switches.
This is the bottom switch that is
organized to port the whole strategy.
The idea is to simplify and you
will see that the nomenclature of
every Raspberry Pi is coincident
with the port they are connected to.
It will help us reduce troubleshooting
in case we have Problems.
As you can see, odd number Raspberry
Pis 1, 3, 5 are connected to the
odd numbers ports and even to even.
This cover ports 1 to 42 on the
bottom switch and the remaining
ports were reserved for key
infrastructure components.
For example, port 43 will connect it
to the top of the switch, 44 is to
the gateway for internet, 45 to the
cloud key and 46 to the Pi server.
However, If you want to do it really
well, you should know and understand how
many ASICs your switch has and try to
put the big servers in different ASICs so
they have their own booths and their own
pipelines to move traffic between things.
We place it here in the last part of
the switch because we learned by the
hard way in the old days when Cisco
came with a design that they have
the reset button in port number one,
so when you were plugging the cable,
you were rebooting the whole switch.
So because of that.
We took panic and we just deploy
everything at the end of the switch.
As again, take a look to your ASICs
and see where it fits to ensure that
traffic goes one way or the other.
Here is how it looks on the top
of the switch where we have still
available space for new Raspberry Pis.
As we mentioned earlier, just 80
Raspberry Pi can be fit in this cluster.
Bit of a view of how much
traffic we are moving here.
As you can see, it's not trivial.
We are moving gigs of traffic, even
terabytes, if we go to the Pi server
that is acting as the gateway to
get all the metrics and collections.
And how does this Raspberry Pi
cluster looks like in reality?
Because we show a
picture at the beginning.
Here is a little video of
the whole thing running.
So let's boot up this whole thing.
Let's start with the build.
In this setup, as we mentioned, pxboot,
which is pre boot execution environment,
is used to streamline the boot process
for the Raspberry Pi cluster, removing
the need for individual SD cards.
The process begins when the Raspberry
Pi powers on and requests an IP
address from the DHCP server.
It's supposed that the DHCP server will
handle this with specific auctions.
What we've done is we hard coded
the IP address to ensure that they
always be given the same IP address.
Once the Raspberry Pi receives
the predefined static IP, which
is configured on the dhcp.
conf file, the next step involves
requesting the bootloader
file from the TFTP server.
For the Ubuntu and Raspbian
images served via the NFS mounts.
To ensure and prevent storage
conflicts across the nodes,
overlay file systems are used.
This allows the Raspberry to
efficiently mount their operating
system image and share the storage
while isolating writes, so we ensure
that we have a scalable and manageable
boot process for the entire cluster.
Here we came with a little
bit of how this process goes.
Raspberry Pi comes and shouts,
Hey, I want my IP address.
Which one I can use?
We have the DHCP server, the Raspberry Pi
server, the NAS, which is sleeping because
it doesn't intervene in this process.
We have our router coming and
say, okay, you have this fixed IP
assigned, but now it's okay, but
I don't have operating system.
And here is my serial number.
Who can help me?
The router doesn't know because
it's not configured for that.
So here is where our PX boot server
will come and we'll say, okay, here are
your boot files for your serial numbers.
And then he will ask finally the
NAS on, hey, I need storage here.
Could you please share it with me?
And it will hand over there.
Easy process, three
different devices involved.
But, to configure the Raspberry Pis
for PX boot, With the latest one,
it's enabled by default, but with the
old ones, you have to do it manually.
You have different ways of doing.
You could just go and update the
ware, edit the boot config, and
ensure that you set up the one time
flag to enable networking boot,
which is this 73 0 2 bunch of zeros
and a, and then remove the SD card.
Problem is that you need to do it for
the 63, so you will have to be doing
that 63 times, which is not very fun way.
To get things working
to set up the PX server.
What we found was there's already out
there on the Internet and here's the
link for the GitHub, which will help you.
This solution, it's designed
specifically to run on Raspberry Pi OS.
However, to use it on Ubuntu,
that was our operating system.
We had to do some adjustments.
As the Ubuntu system structure is
slightly different, a key challenges
arise with the new Raspberry Pi OS
that is based on Debian 12, that is
the book one, which is, which isn't
fully compatible with the PX script.
To make it work, we use the older
legacy Raspberry Pi OS based on
Debian which maintains compatibility.
And additionally, the current script
runs in interactive mode, meaning
that it requires the user input step
by step to configure the PX server.
To streamline the whole deployment for
a large cluster like the one we are
building, the script needs to be built.
have minor modifications to run
in non interactive mode, which
will allow the configuration to be
automated without manual intervention.
This is the way we proceed.
Here is how it looks like.
You usually just use three
options, one, seven, and eight.
That is how we install the PX server.
We provision, we get things done.
Here is a short demo on how this works.
Option one we just installed with the boot
capabilities, option seven we create the
image, and option eight we just provision
the nodes by deploying the prepared
operating system over the network.
Looks easy, right?
we face different challenges
even in this first step.
First of all is the manual
MAC addressing collection.
Building this whole thing
and having static IP required
detailed DHCP configuration, how
we predefined the whole thing.
We had also initial configuration
barrier that was difficult without
having a pre configured network settings.
Having this on the PX side just to
boot things came hey, what are the
different type of solutions that
we could have on this whole thing?
There are a few of them.
For example, we could manually,
collect all the MAC address.
You check the MAC address from the
step one where we were enabling
the flag, you can just go and do
it 63 times to see which class
on the Ethernet address you have.
But you can also do it from the
network switch, just getting
the show MAC address table.
Remember that we designed the way to
understand the nomenclature of each
Raspberry Pi that it's correlated to
each port that we have in the switch.
So a couple of times you
will get the whole thing.
Thank you.
As we said, the nomenclature, we use
the last octet and the port number of
the switch, so for bottom switch would
be 1 something, top switch 2 something.
If you see, for example,
this IP address 172.
16.
5.
105, we will set the Raspberry
Pi to 105, which will be located
in the bottom switch on port 5.
Here is a view from the console on
how it looks, the nomenclature of
everything what we have installed.
And now comes the serial number
to provision the operating system.
So there were also different options.
You can do it 63 times again
and just see the CPU info that
will extract the serial number.
This will read the CPU information,
search for the serial line, and
it will extract that number.
Or we can use the device tree
to extract the serial number.
What it does here, it reads the
serial number directly from the
Raspberry Pi's firmware device tree.
And having a, you need to have
a working operating system
and access to the SD card.
Again, we didn't have SD
cards for the whole thing.
So doing 63 times was not
really the way to do it.
So we went with option three.
We check DNS mask logs.
That is what is using this BX
boot script that we just deployed.
There's some manual work and instruction.
You need to manually check the
logs, filter the data using tools
like AWK and GREP, and extract
the relevant, serial information.
This is how it looks.
If you look up there, As you can
see, this is just for a single IP.
So you will have very long
logs to get all the 63.
So it takes a bit of time, but you can
get the IP address with the serial number.
So strategies to tackle all the network
issues because we are sharing just
300 mix for the whole thing there.
One of the things we could do is
traffic segmentations on the villains.
We could implement there.
For example, we can create separate
villains for the px boot traffic.
That would be something that is used just
in the initial phase to provision the
whole information on our Raspberry Pis.
We also have the Kubernetes
communication that is the server to the
Raspberry Pi traffic in our solution.
But we also are going to have the
Postgres API calls on Kubernetes,
which is the data plane communication.
So to prevent this, we could probably go.
And just set up VLAN 10 for PX boot
traffic, 20 for server Raspberry
Pi control plane, and VLAN 30
for Postgres API communication.
We can also configure QoS rules.
For example, we can assign higher priority
to the Postgres API communication and
Kubernetes control plane message, which
is what is the main topic and what's going
to be heavily happening in the future.
In our cluster, and we can set
a lower priority for the PX boot
and other non critical traffic.
As mentioned, we're just going to
do it one time for the setup or
every time you just need to add a
new Raspberry Pi to this cluster.
We could also implement IGMP snooping and
broadcast storm control on the switches.
We could limit the impact of broadcast
and multicast traffic on the network.
To minimize the number of
intermediate switches trying to
reduce the amount of latency that
we can have in the whole setup.
We could have flow control, which
helps manage traffic congestion.
We could have flow control that
helps us manage traffic congestion
by signaling when buffers are
full, but also jumbo frames, which
increase the maximum MTU unit size.
Those allow for more
efficient data transmission.
Set this to 9000 bytes on both
the Bionetwork interfaces and
the switch can reduce the packet
fragmentation and improve throughput.
To be honest, didn't have too
much impact in our deployment.
And then we have also the DNS Kubernetes
clusters are rely heavily on DNS lookups,
so we can ensure that the DNS catching
is configured on both the server and
the Raspberry Pi nodes to avoid repeated
external DNS queries, which can introduce
latency, we can set up a local DNS
cache or DNS forward on our server
to handle DNS requests more quickly.
And last but not least, link aggregation
port channels on the switches.
Trying to load balance across multiple
switches there, and to be honest,
there's always things that we can
just go and upgrade from 1 to 10 gigs
and have high speed connectivity.
now what?
we had the assembling of the Raspberry
Pi, we have the network under control.
Let's go ahead and start this, and
let's see how this whole thing works.
As we mentioned, StackGrid is a PostgreSQL
as a service platform that will simplify
the way you deploy Postgres on Kubernetes.
To be honest, it's just a single
command in your Helm chart.
You put it there and it will have
the whole installation process.
I was surprised because I was expecting
with all the problems and challenges
we had before, that this was going to
be, again, another big challenge and
ended up being the easiest solution.
So We have different
deployment strategies here.
As you can see, we have the running
Kubernetes on Raspberry Pi using tools
like K3S or you can even use the K3S
soup from Alex Elix that has also another
wrapper to make it easier installation.
For this one, we will have from sharding
with Ctools and it will integrate
management of Postgres clusters and
all the high availability features
that we can find on this database.
So here is a bit of the architecture.
It's a modular, and let's break down
a little bit of the key components.
We have a stackgress controller
at the core, which extends the
Kubernetes functionality by defining
custom resource definitions or CRDs.
The stackgress controller will act as
the orchestrator and manage these CRDs.
Cube Control is used to interact with
the controller, enabling the users
to create, configure, and manage
the Postgre clusters declaratively,
using Kubernetes native YAMA files.
We also have the rest API for the
API users IT expose the rest PI for
programmatic access and external use.
The API users can interact with
the Postgres cluster to perform
operations like scaling, configuration,
updates, backups, or monitoring.
Also, the REST API acts as the abstraction
layer of the CRDs, so it will simplify
the interaction for developers and tools.
We have also the distributed
log server for observability.
Stack REST uses Fluentd to
collect and aggregate logs.
The logs are then stored in Postgres
database and enhanced with the TimescaleDB
for time series data management.
And we will save it to persistent
volume storage, ensuring that
it's durable and available for
historical logs for later analysis.
Then we have the service primary,
which is a read write traffic.
This is responsible for handling the read
write client traffic and it routes the
connections from the primary Postgres
instance, ensuring that transactional
consistency and data integrity.
It's essential for applications that
require updates to the database.
We have also the service replica,
which are read only traffic.
This will route the read only client
traffic to the Postgres replica instances.
This setup offloads the read traffic
from the primary instance, so we
will improve the performance and
scalability for read heavy workloads.
And then we have the
Kubernetes pods and replicas.
Each Postgres instance, including
the primary and the replicas, runs
within its own Kubernetes pods.
Stackgres will ensure high
availability and scalability by
managing multiple replica pods.
What else?
we need to introduce the concept of
sharding, that it's a technique to
horizontally scale Postgres databases
by splitting the data into smaller and
more manageable parts called shards.
Each shard contains a subset of the
data and is managed by an independent
Postgres instance or replica set.
What this does, it will help us
to have a better performance for
large datasets by reducing the
load on individual database nodes.
For example, the queries are routed
to the appropriate shard based on
the partitioning key, which will
ensure efficient data retrieval.
This will allow us the system to
handle increasingly workloads without
overwhelming a single database instance.
As we mentioned earlier, Citus acts as
an extension to PostgreSQL, transforming
it into a distributed database.
It splits table into shards,
distributed them across different pods.
A coordinator node will manage the
query routing and parallel execution
ensuring that the queries are
directed to the appropriate shard.
This architecture allows us to
scale of read and write operations,
having parallel query execution and
seamless handling of large datasets.
As you can see.
Each worker has its own replica.
To deploy this whole thing, if you
do it by hand, it can take two weeks.
Probably you would like to do it with
Ansible and it would be like two months.
It's reproducible.
However, and sorry for that line that
should be on the Stackdress side, the
Stackdress you have 20, 30 lines of YAML
with the whole configuration and you
can just start deploying your cluster.
So let's start building.
for the kubernetes setup, we
already talked about k3s, which is a
lightweight kubernetes distribution.
We are going, we found that the control
groups or cgroups That is a feature of the
Linux kernel, which allows you to allocate
resources such as CPU time and system
memory for a specific process or group
of process was not enabled by default.
So we just enabled cgroups and we're
going to use the external etcd instance,
which is deployed on the NAS server as
a single instance using shared storage.
So etcd is distributed.
It has a consistent key value store
that acts as the brain of Kubernetes,
and it will store all cluster
configuration, data, state, and metadata.
So hosting this externally, we
will centralize the control plane
statements management, so we
ensure persistence and reliability.
However, running a single instance
means there's no redundancy.
take care!
Because this must be taken into
account when you deploy into
production challenges, let's
get a bit of the challenges.
We heart we had here.
So we had hardware constraints
running Kubernetes control plane on
a three B plus is nearly impossible
because of the limited memory.
We have 910 mix and under power CPU.
We're running on 1.
2 Gigahertz with four course.
The Pi server intended to handle both
NAS and Kubernetes stacks lacks the
capacity to manage the load effectively.
Additionally, the lack of
local storage further restricts
operations, making resource
management a significant challenge.
We also had all the network limitation
we've been talking around the session
on these 300 megs of network bandwidth.
Which becomes a network bottleneck
for data intensive operations
and cluster communications.
So this whole thing limited
the overall performance and
scalability of our solution.
As a very clever guy said once, there is
no problem in computer science that can't
be solved by another level of indirection.
Which means, Let's just
throw more hardware there.
We added these servers.
We had a Lenovo was using a
Ryzen 5, which, was a bit old.
We had a Slimbook there,
a Ryzen 7 with 16 gigs.
And let's see how this works now.
Let's get our hands dirty.
Let's install the K3s server.
So here's the command.
We're going to curl and
install the version 1 29.
I will define the endpoints.
The TLS and will level the
notes as a service controller.
What's the note 10?
And we will disable traffic
metrics and health controller.
As you can see, we're already
disabling monitoring things.
And it's there's a simple
reason behind the scenes.
There was not enough bandwidth.
To get the node exporters inside
the infrastructure, and we'll
see later how this works also.
let's wait and automate this whole thing.
As you can see, it can take two hours
to get the 63 Raspberry Pis and you can
just go and grab a coffee, have a meeting
with your manager or peers, and two hours
later, get back to get the whole setup.
We got it, everything deployed,
but If we get here and we get our
kubectl get nodes, we see that we
have several that are not ready.
They were flapping and we're
seeing a lot of this happening.
We find out of memory issues,
storage disconnections, high load
and network congestion happening.
Also at the beginning, we found that
The USB charger that was providing the
power to the Raspberry Pi was not working
properly and we had to replace it.
It took us some time to find
that it was the charger that
was giving out all the problems.
What's the solution here?
Hope that you guys like it crowd
because hey, I've been trying to turn
it off and on again and it worked.
We got things back and now the easy part.
Let's get on the stackgres solution.
So this command will start.
Or upgrade the stackless operator
in a new namespace with Prometheus
and Grafana turned off again.
Things that are monitoring and
observability, we will run in with
the basics to see if this was working.
And then we'll get into the next
phase that is observability.
So we try to reduce the
resource consumption.
because of this limited CPU and memory
that couldn't handle additional load for
the monitoring and visualization tools.
We're running version 1.
13, and you just get kubectl,
getpod, stagress, and you
have here things running.
Challenges to get this up and running.
We had a lot of compatibility issues.
running stagress on ARM
based Raspberry Pis.
Requires adapting the software for
ARM architecture and fine tuning the
Kubernetes settings to accommodate
the limited CPU and memory resources.
Default configuration often assumes
more powerful x86 hardware, so be
careful with adjustments where needed
if you want stability and performance.
We'll show.
Improve the storage, so implement a
ZFS pool for shared management and
configuration of the ESCASI volumes
for a reliable and high speed access.
Due to the Raspberry Pi limitations,
we offloaded intensive tasks like
the Kubernetes control plane and
the NAS server to the two AMD64
desktops that we just showed before.
It was a way to ensure that
the cluster remained functional
and at least a bit performant.
Software compatibility.
To overcome these challenges,
we had to recompile the Envoy
component for a better performance.
Now, Everybody can get
because thanks to staggers.
This is public for everybody.
So now you can use the envoy component
in the staggered solution using arm.
Also for networking.
We wanted and tested ceiling,
but we encounter failures that
we require alternative approach.
Initially, he is Cassie targets were
confer using TGT power later switches
to Leo, the Linux input output target.
The idea was to try to improve
the stability in the performance,
but the whole entire process.
Involve extensive trial and
errors to fine tune the setup.
It was not a single shot.
It took us a few weeks.
I would even say a month and a half
to get everything working and sorted
out all the compatibility issue
despite the challenges we achieve.
We were able to successfully deploy
all these taggers, overcoming the whole
architecture limitations and integration
to build this functional environment,
how we started and how we did that can
be reflected in this picture, we were
really eager to start the project.
I'm very excited, but
we end up let's do it.
Finish this as soon as possible.
Let's move to something else.
A lot of headaches, a lot of
hours and nightmares running
this whole thing, but it was fun.
Usually learning the hard way is
the best way to get things done.
let us show you just a quick demo.
And just getting on the patroni topology
and how you can see all the workers.
in the demo, we run the following
command to display the whole topology.
Patroni is an open source cluster
management tool that automates the
deployment and the failover of high
availability Postgres clusters.
Let we just here and this command
will provide a clear view.
Of the clusters set up, it will
show us the node that has as
primary, which ones are replica.
In our case, that we had 20
workers, each with its own replica.
And now comes the fun questions.
You say, what happens with
the whole observability thing?
we found many key problems here.
we had resource constraints.
We had limited CPU, memory, even
disk space on each Raspberry Pi node.
And there was no space
available to install any
monitoring agents or exporters.
We also had this bandwidth limitation of
300 Mbps that become a huge bottleneck.
And we had high data volume
from metrics collation that was
overwhelming the whole network.
Last but not least, we had
inefficient observability data flow.
We were trying to send directly the
metrics from each node to AWS Cloud, and
it resulted in high latency, excessive
bandwidth consumption, and increased
cloud costs for the storage and transfer.
So we were trying to find, hey,
what are solutions that could help
us minimize all these problems?
We look at defining our own
custom metric collection.
We could use a lightweight python script
to collect just essential metrics, CPU,
memory, disk and network using the PS util
tool, we can consolidate and batch data
at the gateway node, one of the servers
that we were using and compressing the
whole payloads before sending that to
the cloud from a bandwidth perspective.
We could reduce the sampling frequency,
collect metrics every 60 seconds,
or even 120 seconds, 1 to 2 minutes.
We could use a lightweight data transfer
protocol, like MQTT, with compression.
And we can send only aggregated data
summaries instead of the raw metrics.
And also, we could implement some
edge processing to analyze and filter
metrics locally, as we did before.
The whole transmission, and we
could send only critical alerts or
anomalies to the cloud for further
action and remove anything else there.
So scaling observability solutions
for a large number of Raspberry Pi
nodes is not feasible with traditional
exporter like Prometheus node.
exporter and so on using
the three B plus cards.
Probably if you use modern ones, you
can feed exporters in a better way.
This is how it looks.
The whole thing.
We had a couple of scripts
that we were using.
One is the metrics collector that collects
the CPU memory and the network metrics.
It will compress the metrics using gzip
to minimize bandwidth and will send
metrics every 120 seconds to the gateway.
Then the gateway script.
We'll receive all the compressed metrics,
decompress them, store them in a list,
and it will aggregate metrics every
five minutes and will send those to AWS
CloudWatch using the CloudWatch API.
Note, if you're going to use AWS,
you need to install Boto3 AWS
Python libraries in the monitoring
gateway for the AWS integration.
You could set up alerts in CloudWatch
for critical thresholds, things like
over 80 percent just send me alerts,
and visualize all those metrics using
Grafana by connecting CloudWatch
as a data source in the Manage.
You have two ways of doing Grafana,
by the way, in the Apple OS.
You just can go and manually install
it on your EC2 instance, or you can use
just the Manage service to make it work.
Here it looks.
How.
Here are the Python scripts used
for both the gateways and the node.
We will use our own AI assistant to
explain the code that we have here.
As you can see, it will create a flash
server, install the metrics, will
accept POST requests, decompress the
data and store metrics that we were
talking about, CPU, memory, disk, and
do the CloudWatch integration out there.
There's some background processing
happening as you can see there,
we'll send them to CloudWatch, logs
the results, and even it tells us
how we should look the output there.
If we go to the metrics collector, as you
can see here, we're collecting different
metrics and sending to the gateway,
we'll ask also to highlight this code
and explain it in different sections.
it looks at the different things we have.
We can ask them to improve by the way.
maybe our function is not.
I'm not a expert programmer.
I just do things for fun.
But maybe you can ask your A.
I.
To improve the quality of your code.
And here we'll send.
Look, we just configured the gateway A.
P.
I.
And it will include the error handling
and the main loop on the whole thing.
a bit of examples of how
the matrix looks like.
And how the scripts.
It takes that it's appeared to
be a larger monitoring system
where multiple nodes will send the
metrics to the gateway compressed.
So the results here, frequent metric
transmission from all these 63 Raspberry
Pi nodes saturated the 300 megs shared
bandwidth, causing latency, packet loss,
and a very huge degradation on performance
for other workloads that we were running.
Also high CPU overhead we had there,
processing this whole thing in
compression was not a very good idea.
Probably would have been better just
to send raw data, but also we had
consistence on the network and led the
server to compress and do the whole thing.
We had some gateway bottlenecks,
so centralized aggregation on a
single gateway, leads to problems.
Processing delays and scalability
limits with risk of getting drop or
delay metrics under a heavy load.
And we had also an
unreliable observability.
So resource constraints result in
inconsistent reporting gaps in data
and potential cardinality explosions,
which makes our dashboards and
alerts less accurate and actionable.
So this is a bit of how we went
with the whole thing of setting
up a 63 Raspberry Pi cluster.
We had some overall lessons
learned out here, mainly on
the importance of planning.
It might take much more time than what
you expect to really design how you
want, not just the hardware, how you
want the software, but also that the
adaptability, how we can merge both
software and hardware to make it work.
As a single unit, recompile many
things that we had to achieve on the
journey to make this work, but also
collaboration because this is not just
Jorge and myself doing the whole thing.
We got people from Stagres helping
us on validating some of the
configurations, helping us with
the compiling of the Envoy proxy.
And we brought other
experts to take a look here.
But moreover, Experimentation.
If you want real production workloads,
you need to have a distributed
storage and other kind of updates
that we didn't consider here because
this is a work in progress so far.
And when I mention work in
progress, we are not stopping here.
It's been like seven, eight months of
project, but we want to optimize Linux.
We were going with Ubuntu, probably try
other alternative like Hokey Linux, also
benchmarking a shared cluster and have
a real world application running on top.
Probably we will need to change most
of the hardware to go to more improve.
Raspberry Pi or even just try
another nodes like the Orange Pi
and, but mainly also how we can
fine tune the kubernetes thing.
And the best part is how we
can bring AI to the edge.
The idea is that we can have a chatbot
for stack grace incident support.
We want to train the chatbot using all
the errors and things that can happen
in our cluster to provide a solution
for other customers in the near future.
And how does the near future look like?
superclusters can be used to train
and deploy lightweight machine
learning and AI models at scale.
So for example, the Raspberry Pis
could process smaller datasets for
tasks like image recognition or natural
language processing, which can enable
a cost effective edge AI solution.
But by bringing Computation closer
to the data source, Raspberry
Pi clusters can serve as a
powerful edge computing platform.
They can enable real time data processing
for cases like smart sensors, video
analytics, and autonomous systems, which
can reduce the latency and reliance
on centralized cloud infrastructure.
And last but not least, IoT management.
I think that they can also act as hubs
to manage large scale IoT deployments.
And they can handle tasks like
device orchestration, data
aggregation, and monitoring.
The ability to process and analyze
IoT data locally makes them ideal
for smart cities, industrial
automation, and connected environments.
And with that, thanks
for joining this session.
Here are our handles if you want
to follow up or just get in touch.
Let us know if you have any questions.
Just throw it out there
and we'll try to solve it.
Thanks very much.
See you in the next one.