Good morning, good afternoon, good
evening, depending upon where you are
and when you're watching this recording.
Thank you for joining me today.
My name is Robin Sarkar.
I'm the director of analytics
and digital at Enstal.
I'm very excited today to discuss
something that fuels our lives
every single day, yet rarely
gets the spotlight it deserves.
Data.
Think of data like water, it's
everywhere, for survival, and yet
too much of it can cause floods,
while too little leaves us parched.
The key is not just having data, but
managing it wisely, turning it into
something actionable and valuable.
Today I'm here to talk about data portals.
I know that name doesn't scream
excitement, but trust me, by the
end of this session, you will see
how data portals can make your
organization smarter, faster,
and yes, even more profitable.
So let's dive in.
Here's what we'll cover today.
First, I'll introduce data portals,
what they are, why they matter.
Next, we'll explore their key features.
Then we'll discuss their key benefits.
Spoiler alert.
It means faster decisions, happier
employees, and improved business outcomes.
But let's be real, it's not all perfect.
I'll also touch on common challenges
organizations face when adopting
data portals, and of course,
the solutions to navigate them.
Finally, we'll end with key takeaways
and some thought provoking questions
to help you reflect on how data portals
could transform your organization.
Sounds good?
Let's get started.
The world is drowning in data.
Fun fact, by 2025, the global data
sphere will hit 175 zettabytes.
That's 175 trillion gigabytes.
Imagine if every byte
were a grain of rice.
We would have enough to bury
Mount Everest several times over.
Yet, despite this abundance, many
organizations struggle to harness
the full value of their data.
It's like having closet
stuffed with clothes.
But never being able to
find your favorite shirt.
That sounds familiar, right?
This is where data portals comes in.
Think of data portal as your super
organized friend, Marie Kondo.
Consolidating all your data into
one place and making it easy.
To find and use.
It's not just storage.
It's about turning chaos into clarity.
Imagine a retail company with data
spread across sales, inventory,
customer support, and marketing systems.
Without a data portal, pulling these
pieces together for insight is time
consuming and often inconsistent.
With a data portal, this data is
consolidating, and Allowing the
company to quickly identify trends
like customer purchasing behaviors,
inventory shortages, or the success of
marketing campaigns, all in real time.
What sets data portals apart is
their unique combination of features
to address real world challenges.
First, there is a centralized repository.
Imagine all your data.
Whether it's sales, customer
feedback, or operational metrics
consolidated in one place.
If you're in the healthcare
industry, patient records, lab
results, or billing information are
often scattered across the system.
A data portal can centralize the
sources, ensuring the healthcare
providers have accurate up to date
information at their fingertips,
which directly improves patient care.
Everything is in one place.
And no more hunting through 10 different
systems like you're in a treasure hunt.
Self service analytics is a game
changer for non technical users.
Remember when you had to call data or
IT team every time you needed a report?
Those days are over.
With intuitive dashboards, Even
the least tech savvy person in
the office can pull insights.
It's like upgrading from a
flip phone to a smartphone.
It just makes life easier.
Third, we have data governance.
As organization grows, so does
the need to secure sensitive
data and comply with regulations.
Sounds boring, right?
But it's crucial.
It's like having a security guard
for your data, making sure sensitive
information doesn't fall into wrong hands.
Then there is search and discovery.
Advanced search capabilities means
employees can find their data in seconds.
Imagine an analyst looking for sales.
data for specific region last quarter,
they can simply search and access
the relevant data set instantly.
Finally, let's talk about
collaboration tools.
Imagine you're in marketing
and you notice sales are up in
one region but down another.
Instead of sending 50 emails back
and forth, you can share your
insights directly in the portal.
Tag your sales team and work
on the solutions together.
All right.
Let's talk about the
juicy part, the benefits.
first up is, it enables
faster decision making.
Picture this, you're a product manager
who needs to decide whether to continue
producing a slow selling product.
Without a data portal, they would spend
weeks gathering the information, but with
one, they can see sales trends, customer
feedback, and inventory levels in minutes,
and boom, a decision is being made.
Next up is The improved data literacy.
You know how most people free data
like it's written in Hebrew data
portals change that they make data
accessible and easy to understand
even for the non technical folks.
For example, an HR manager could use
a portal to track employee performance
and employee engagement and more,
engagement trends without needing
a data scientist on speed dial.
And by automating repetitive tasks
like data extraction and cleaning,
data portals allow IT teams to
focus on strategic initiatives,
boosting overall productivity.
This doesn't just benefit IT, it creates
a ripple effect across the organization.
Collaboration is another big win.
Let's say the marketing team wants to run
a campaign targeting a specific audience.
Instead of guessing, they can pull
customer insights from the portal,
share them with design team, and
create a campaign backed by data.
It's teamwork powered by technology.
Here's the thing about data.
It's only useful if you can
access it quickly and easily.
That's where data portals shine.
First, they simplify data discovery.
Instead of digging through 10
folders or sending panicked attacks,
panicked emails to IT, you can
find what you need in seconds.
They also democratize data.
That's a fancy way of saying
they make data accessible to
everyone, not just data nerds.
A junior employee in customer
service Identifies a recurring
complaint pattern using the portal.
They share it with their manager, who
then brings it up in a strategy meeting.
Suddenly, the junior
employee is the office hero.
Then there is data
quality and consistency.
When all teams draw the data
from same single source.
Source of truth, discrepancy and
errors are significantly reduced.
So finally, let's talk
about real time access.
In today's fast paced world, waiting
for outdated report is like trying
to run a marathon in flip flops.
It just doesn't work.
Real time data helps companies
respond to changes instantly.
For example, If a retailer notices
a spike in demand for a product,
they can restock quickly, avoiding
missed sales opportunities.
Data portals don't just make
your life easier, they transform
how businesses operate.
Let's start with faster decisions.
With all your data in one place, decision
making becomes quick and confident.
Imagine a CEO needing to decide whether to
expand into New market, instead of relying
on gut feelings, they have a portal
filled with market analysis, customer
demographics, and competitor insights.
It enables them to make the
decision faster and quicker.
Now let's discuss data driven culture.
Data portals make it easier for
organizations to foster a culture
of data driven decision making.
Companies that embrace the culture
outperform their competitors financially
by 49 percent and are 178 percent more
likely to achieve long term success.
Why?
Because their decisions are
based on facts, not hunches.
And all we know is that facts don't lie.
Finally, customer insights.
Data portals help you understand
your customers better.
For example, Fitness company could
use one to identify which classes
are most popular, then adjust
their schedule to meet demand.
The result, happier customer
means happier retention rates.
The benefits of data portals
don't just improve process.
They create ripple effects
across the entire organization.
Let's dive into some real world impacts.
Let's talk about customer
acquisition and retention.
Did you know?
Do you know that companies leveraging
data portals are 23 times more
likely to acquire customers and six
times more likely to retain them?
It's like having a crystal
ball for customer behavior.
For example, a telecom company using
a data portal might notice younger
employees, or sorry, younger customers
prefer online support over phone calls.
By enhancing online support, they
make their customers happier.
Isn't that the goal?
Next, let's discuss profitability.
Data driven organizations are
19 times more likely to achieve
above average profitability.
Picture a manufacturing company
using real time data to optimize
production schedules and reduce waste.
Every decision becomes a little
smarter and the savings add up quickly.
And then there is
operational optimization.
Companies report a 30 percent boost
in efficiency thanks to data portals.
Imagine a supply chain
manager tracking inventory and
forecasting demand in real time.
By proactively addressing potential
bottlenecks, they save time,
money, and a lot of headaches.
Smooth operations aren't just
a dream, they're achievable.
Ultimately, these improvements make
organizations more agile, competitive,
and ready to tackle the future.
Data portals aren't just
tools, they are game changers.
Of course, data portals
isn't all smooth sailing.
Every great tool comes
with its challenges.
First up, Data security.
It's a biggie with 67 percent of
organizations citing it as a top concern.
It's clear this issue keeps many I.
T.
Professionals up at night.
Think about it.
Single breach can cost millions of
dollars and it also has a reputational
impact on the organization.
Next is user adoption.
As change is hard.
We all know someone who still
refuses to use an online calendar.
Only 20 percent of employees feel
confident in their data literacy skills.
Then there's data quality.
It's like garbage in and garbage out.
Poor quality data is like
using GPS without dated maps.
You're not going to end up any end
up anywhere where you want to be.
Finally, there's also
an issue of scalability.
As your organization grows,
so will your data needs.
Now that we have outlined
challenges, let's talk solutions.
Every obstacle is just an
opportunity in disguise, right?
we discussed about data security.
it's best to implement a zero trust model.
This means every user and device
Assessing your data must be verified.
No exceptions.
Add encryption and regular audits
to the mix and you've got a security
system Fort Knox would let me.
For user adoption, training is
key, but don't make it boring.
Tailoring the training to different roles.
For example, HR team learns to track
employee engagement trends while marketing
explores campaign performance dashboards.
Everyone feels empowered
and no one feels left out.
Data quality can be tackled with automated
data cleansing tools that spot and fix
errors before they reach the portal.
Combine that with clear data governance
policies, you will ensure your data
remains accurate and actionable.
Finally, there's scalability.
Cloud based solutions are a no brainer.
Imagine you're a retailer
launching a hot new product.
A cloud based portal lets you
handle the surge in data seamlessly,
ensuring you don't miss a single sale.
This solution proves that
with the right approach, data
portals can overcome any hurdle.
Finally, we're coming to end of it.
We've covered a lot today.
Let's take a moment to
recap the key points.
Data portals are transformative
tools that centralize data,
improve accessibility, and empower
organizations to make smarter decisions.
From features like self service analytics
to their ability to drive profitability
and efficiency, they're changing
the game for business everywhere.
We discuss the challenges like
security concerns of user adoption.
But with tailored training, robust
governance and scalable solutions,
these obstacles are entirely manageable.
So before we wrap up, let's
take a moment to reflect.
If this were a live session,
I would invite your questions.
So here's my question to you.
How can your organization leverage a
data portal to foster collaboration,
drive better outcomes, and create
a truly data driven culture?
Thank you for your time and attention.
And I hope this session has inspired
you to explore the possibilities of data
portals and the transformative impact
they can have on your organizations.
Thank you so much for your time.
Have a great day.
Bye bye.