Hello everyone.
I'm gr Malu.
I'm a cyber risk consultant.
I'm super excited to be here today
and I will be sharing the strategies
to secure the digital backbone of
our modern world IOT supply chains.
This presentation is made up of my
research and GRC expertise working
with the highly regulated industries.
Let's move on to the next slides and
learn the practical ex examples and
the strategies to save IOT systems.
In this slide we talk about the hidden
threat and let me start this slide
with an example and a quick story.
A hospital I consulted for a small
four pump from a trusted vendor and
the vulnerability hidden tape in the
ware inserted during the manufacturing.
Which allowed un authorized taxes and one
component one mistake, and the patient's
security safety was at risk, right?
This was, this is what makes iot
supply chain attacks so dangerous
and vulnerable attacks don't break
in through the front door anymore.
And the hitch in the right trusted
software updates or embedded component.
And because the test is implicit and
no one checks the, and no one even
expect that, and the risks, they're
not just limited to one sector.
These attacks affect smart homes,
hospitals, schools, airports,
manufacturing floors everywhere.
And let's move on to the next slide.
Here, let's talk about
the AL security gaps.
Unfortunately, we're
still playing a catch up.
Many companies don't have proper
vetting for their suppliers.
Security testing happens
too late, if at all.
If at all.
And a lot of networks don't
even have real time monitoring.
But there is a hope.
But we, yes.
Seeing powerful tools emerge
in this modern world, automated
vulnerability scams, tamper proof
hardware, behavioral analytics,
that flag anomalies before we occur.
We just have to be willing to adopt these
modern technologies into our environments.
Let's move on to the next slide.
Here we talk about real
world attack examples.
You may remember the Mirai botnet.
It is, it used the default passwords
on baby monitors and cameras
to create a global DDoS attack.
It's not.
Thermostat can become a digital grenade.
I have also worked with the logistics
organization where smart scanners were
hijacked via compromised firmware.
The attackers gained the foothold into
the backend systems, and it's not a
fiction, it's reality, and you can
imagine how huge the impact could be.
Let's move on to the next slide.
This slide, let's talk about
the complex attack surface.
There are major areas.
The vulnerabilities can maintain
things like microcontrollers,
different countries, and often
include hidden and software.
Third party code and open source
packages can be out dated or malicious.
Manufacturing contract factors
may not follow security
processes, updates matching.
Imagine if your device update
server gets hacked and suddenly
malware is pushed as in trusted.
Update cloud services if
attackers breach your backend.
The control, they control
every device connected to that.
So let's move on to next slide.
Here, let's talk about the
evolving threat landscape.
We're not just fighting
solo hackers anymore.
Nation states are involved.
Ransom gangs, target
hospitals through iot devices.
And these devices are quietly required to,
into encrypted botnets and crypto mining.
Botnets and personal data from smart
homes is being sold on the dark webs.
It's our toaster talks.
If our toaster talks to our light
hub and they both talk to our
wifi, that's a huge meh of risk.
Let's move on to next slide.
Here we talk about
fortifying our iot ecosystem.
And what are the, we had talked about
the challenges and problems, and
let's now talk about the solutions.
So we need a design secure
systems from the very beginning.
So that's what secure by design practices,
not patch them after the fact, right?
So think of building earthquake
proof buildings in California.
You don't wait until after the
earthquake to reinforce the structure.
So secure by design practices
testing the vulnerabilities at
each stage would help, really help.
Let's move on to the next slide here.
We talk about secure by design
principles in more detail.
Some must have secure
by design principles.
Start with the threat modeling
when designing the new product.
Use hardware security
features like Secure Boot.
Assess your suppliers like you
assets your new hires, right?
Check their backgrounds and if they
have any secu security breaches history.
So like that and maintain software
will love material, so you always
know what's running on your devices.
Let's move on to next slide, which
talks about zero trust architecture.
Assume nothing is safe.
Zero trust means every device, every
request, every update must prove
its authenticity and legitimacy.
Each device should have a unique identity.
Devices should not talk to
the services they really need.
All communications must be encrypted.
Devices should only get access.
They're absolutely needed.
So technically, the role-based access,
and let's move on to the next slide here.
We talk about behavioral
analytics and anomaly detection.
We can no longer rely on, only
on signature based detections.
Attackers evolve faster
than signature databases do.
Instead, your use behavior modeling, if
your device suddenly sends 10 multiple
multiples of tens, seven hundreds,
it's unusual traffic at 2:00 AM right?
And it's worth checking and
keep monitoring that kind
of, the sudden behavior.
Think of it like in Fitness.
Tracker knows your usual heart
rate, and so when it spikes without
any explanation, it alerts you.
And let's go to the next slide here.
We talk about the incident
response strategy.
You need, every organization need
a strong incident response plan
that works into especially the iot.
And so here, let's talk about
the different steps here.
Let's start with the detection
monitor, both digital and physical
anomaly anomalies and containment.
Don't shut down the whole network segment.
It's segment it smartly, and investigation
use iot specific forensic tools.
Remediation remediate, distribute,
clean will, were securely
and post incidental learn.
From the incidents and share the best
practices, what you have learned from
the incident, and improve your internal
systems and processes and controls.
Let's move on to the next slide.
Implementation roadmap.
You don't need to solve everything
at single step or overnight.
Start with a maturity assessment.
Then follow the steps, eliminate default
passwords, increase the password policy
change the password policy strengthening
the password and do basic segmentation.
Build cross-functional teams across
security, supply chain and product.
Track metrics, live metrics, real time
metrics to detect time time to fix them.
And let's move on to the next slide.
So in previous slides we talked about
the implementation roadmap and here.
Let's talk about proven results of
implementing those security standards
and how that roadmap helps you.
Organizations that adopt these practices
experience fewer breaches, maintain
uptime during, detect issues, early and
significantly reduced tampering incidents.
So these are very helpful.
To detect the issues early,
vulnerabilities early, and to
keep the systems safe and secure.
Let's move on to the next slide,
the path forward.
So we have gone through the issues,
real time examples and the roadmaps,
best practices, and the proven results.
Now let's see the what's next?
Manufacturers need to prioritize security,
even under pressure to cut costs, right?
So the cutting the cost
should not compromise the
quality or security anymore.
Supply chains must
become more transparent.
Organizations must invest in
long term and not cheapest part.
And we need better regulations
and continuous innovation,
especially around lightweight
cryptography for Internet of things.
And let's move on to the next slide
here, securing the connector Future.
Let's talk about how iot security is not
just a checkbox and it's a commitment.
So we need the technical excellence, yes.
But also the collaboration
and cultural shift.
It's, it everyone in the
organization should feel that
it's their responsibility.
It's not just the risk and security
teams to secure the organization.
It's everyone's responsibility.
And being aware of the threats
and risks happening in the
industry is very much important.
We need technical excellence, but
also the collaboration, the cultural
shift, as I discussed the collaboration
with the different teams in the
organization is very much important.
Let's stop waiting for
the next big act to act.
Let's build trust into
our connected future.
And let's move on.
And these are.
Thank you so much for being here today
and I hope this gave you some practical
insights and inspiration towards securing
the IO OT supply chains and I'm happy to
connect and continue the conversation.
Please do connect with me on
LinkedIn and share your thoughts.
Thank you so much.