Hello everyone.
My name is Vanta.
I'm a data engineering leader
working on large scale data platform
across cloud analytics and machine
learning from over the last 14 years.
Over the years, I worked in extensively
with very high volume, high velocity data
systems, and one pattern I keep seeing
is organizations don't fail at iot.
Because they can't collect the data.
They struggle because the cost
and complexity of managing IO
OT data grows faster than the
value they extract from it.
Today I want to talk about how we can
rethink IOT data warehousing using
modern Lake houses, architecture
and Snowflake feature stores.
Not just to scale technically, but to
fundamentally change the cost equation.
IOD data platforms today are under immense
pressure to do more than just scale.
They need to scale economically
as connected devices continues
to grow across industries like
manufacturing, transportation,
utilities, and smart cities.
Organizations are realizing that
traditional data architectures
were not designed for continuous
telemetry at this scale.
In this talk, I'll walk through the
architectural patterns and real world
approaches that help teams reduce cost
while still enabling real time analytics,
machine learning, and business insights.
IOT Data Challenge iot ecosystem
generates data at an unprecedented
scale and velocity sensors stream
telemetry continuously, often at
millisecond intervals as we know.
And within months, this data can reach
petabytes scale at the same time.
This same data must support
very different consumers.
Operation teams want
the real time dashboard.
Data scientists need historical
data for modeling and business
users want aggregated insights.
Supporting all these workloads
simultaneously is where many
iot platforms begin to stream.
Coming to the unique
characteristics of iot data.
What makes IOT data uniquely different
is that the combination of high
velocity, massive volume, and constant
schema evolution device changes.
Firmware updates introduces new fields
and different vendors produce consistently
inconsistent telemetry formats.
Any successful iot architecture
must handle continuous ingestion,
adapt to all the schema changes
gracefully, and retain the large
historical data sets without repeatedly
reprocessing or rewriting the data.
So how are we gonna bridge the gap
by using the Lakehouse architecture?
Traditional data warehouses deliver strong
performance and consistency, but they
quickly become expensive and inflexible.
Due to the semi-structured
data set of iot.
Data lakes are cost effective, but
they lack reliability, governance
and transactional guarantees.
Lake house architecture bridges this gap.
By combining the best of both worlds,
warehouse grade reliability on top of
low cost cloud object storage for iot.
This isn't just an architectural
improvement, it is a cost
containment strategy.
So coming to the core Lakehouse
Technologies, technologies like Delta,
lake Apache Iceberg, and Apache Hudy
brings transactional, semantics,
schema evolution, and efficient
metadata management to cloud storage.
These capabilities are critical for iot
workloads where data is continuously
dependent, occasionally updated,
and queried across long time ranges.
Without these features, IOD platform
tend to accumulate hidden operational
and storage cost over time.
So what does the Lakehouse
physical architecture looks like?
It has.
It separates actually the storage
table formats and compute Cloud
object storage provides virtually
unlimited low cost capacity.
Table formats manage the metadata
and the transactional behavior.
Compute engines like Spark or
Trium scale independently to
process these heavy workloads.
This operation is essential for
IT platforms because it allows
the teams to scale compute.
Only when needed, instead of paying
continuously for the fixed infrastructure.
Coming to the architectural
considerations iot platform must be
designed with streaming at the core.
Data typically flows through Kafka,
Kinesis, or event hubs, and is processed
in real time using Spark or Flink.
Cost efficiency comes from decisions
like time-based partitioning
aligned to IOT's, temporal nature.
Lifecycle management across hot,
warm, and cold data layers for data
storage, retention, and accommodating
the schema evolution without
rewriting the historical data.
In practice, many iot costs overrun
stems from poor decision in these
architectural considerations.
So the medallion architecture
is that place where all
these issues gets resolved.
The Meall architecture provides a
structured way to manage IOT data.
Bronze stable captures the raw sensors
data exactly as received, preserving
fidelity for auditing and replay.
Silver tables apply the validation,
normalization, and standardization,
and the gold table exposes the
business ready data set optimized
for reporting and dashboards.
This layered approach is very influential
because it reduces the redundant
processing and ensures the higher cost.
Compute is only applied
where business value exists.
Coming to the integration, the
realtime and the batch integration
iot platform must support both.
And instead of maintaining separate
systems, modern architecture, increasingly
adopted KAA style approach where a
single streaming pipeline serves both
realtime and the batch use cases.
Incremental processing and materialized
views reduce the operational
complexity and significantly
lowers the long-term cost.
Now the machine learning integration
is a place where we will be talking
about the feature engineering.
Machine learning is where iot data
delivers significant value, but it's
also where cost quietly explored.
Feature engineering often gets
duplicated across teams and pipelines.
Snowflake features stores addresses
this by enabling reusable governed
features that remain consistent
across training and inference.
This reduces the compute cost,
improves the model reliability, and
accelerates the experimentation.
There are a few case studies that I have
included in here, which are directly
ties up with the scalable architecture.
In manufacturing environments, IO ot,
Lakehouse architecture enables the
predictive maintenance by analyzing sensor
telemetry for early failure signals.
Instead of reacting to equipment
breakdowns, organizations can
plan maintenance proactively.
This reduces the downtime, avoid
emergency repairs, and leads to
measurable operational savings.
Another case study which adds which
supports, this is the connected
vehicle fleet optimization
for connected vehicle fleets.
A real-time telemetry supports the
route optimization as we know driver
behavior scoring, vehicle health
monitoring, and demand prediction.
These insights directly improve safety,
efficiency and utilization while reducing
fuel cost and unplanned downtime.
The smart city infrastructure is
another strong case where the data
is used to optimize the traffic flow,
monitor the environmental conditions,
and enable the open data initiatives.
A unified Lakehouse platform allows
governments to manage diverse data
sources and schemas while maintaining the
governance, reliability and cost control.
Utility meter analytics is
another beautiful case study.
It prob, it ingests in, sorry.
It ingests the smart meter from
data from millions of households.
As we know, Lakehouse platforms handle
schema heterogeneity, compress the time
series data, and enable advanced analytics
such as energy theft detection, peak
demand forecasting, and grid optimization.
All while keeping
infrastructure cost manageable.
Looking ahead, iot data platforms
will evolve towards lower latency
streaming warehouse class, time series
performance, stronger governance and
edge analytics that reduce bandwidth
and centralized processing cost.
The most successful platforms will be
those that are not just data aware, but
cost aware by design as well to close.
Iot success is not about collecting
more data, it's about designing
systems that align cost with
value When built correctly.
Iot data platform don't just scale.
They become sustainable strategic
assets that power realtime
decisions and long-term innovations.
Thank you, and I'm open to
take any questions you have.