Everyone, my name is Ramad Rell and
I'm here today to talk to you a little
bit about iot data streaming and the
complexities that come alongside with it.
So let's go ahead and get started.
So let's talk about IO ot, right?
The rise of IO OT is actually transformed
the way we think about data today.
We've got billions of connected devices,
everything from wearables to industrial
sensors that are generating streams
of events that must be captured,
processed, and trusted in real time.
For many engineering teams, moving from
devices, producing data to data producing
value is where the hard problems begin.
And in today's session, we're
gonna explore the hidden
challenges of IOT data pipelines.
Let's go ahead and jump in.
So the challenges that we're seeing
today, they typically stem from the
unique nature of the data source rather
than just standard big data problems.
Key hidden challenges include ensuring
data integrity, managing device
heterogeneity, and navigating complex
security and compliance issues.
So how do you make
streaming data reliable?
When devices are noisy,
unpredictable, or go offline?
How do you enforce security,
governance and data quality
without slowing innovation?
And how can platform engineers give
developers self-service access to
streaming data without creating ca chaos?
So let's dig into it with
challenge number one.
The first hidden challenge is that
sensor data is inherently unreliable.
It's noisy, and it can be inaccurate.
So sensors can produce erroneous,
irrelevant, or noisy data due
to environmental factors such as
temperature of fluctuations vibrations.
There could be hardware limitations
or even just simple malfunctions,
but this creates a lot of
added complications, right?
The data that comes off the sensor is
used for multiple business applications.
So when the data that's coming
off those devices is unreliable,
it's gonna have a entire domino
effect of negative consequences.
So let's go ahead and look at the
manufacturing industry, for instance.
In this environment, data could be
coming off of different robotic arms.
One robot may be placing windows on cars.
Another may be painting the
car, and a third would be
placing the tires on the car.
So what happens when the number of
windows placed is incorrect and that
data that's being captured is incorrect?
This throws off data accuracy completely.
If the transmitted data says 500 windows
were placed on the car, but in reality
is 5,000 windows were placed on the cars.
The chain of command of the
rest of the robots is off.
The data that goes into the procurement
and shipping department is off.
The data that is exchanged
with the manufacturer is wrong.
This calibration drift is throwing
off the entire supply chain.
Then you've got not only calibration
issues but you also have missing
data or packet loss, and they
can have a similar effect.
This is typically, takes place when you
have inconsistent network connectivity
issues, but this loss data leads to an
incomplete picture of what is actually
taking place, and that missing data
can lead to significant disruptions
all the way from production halts
to compromise quality control and
safety issues, which in turn could
cost the missus millions of dollars.
So now as teams moved away from, legacy
architectures and ET l and broken, or I
guess you could say one-off integrations
and onto data streaming, they did it
because there was new business models
that need to be fed this new data.
And with the legacy systems, the
data was always getting stuck.
You gotta ask yourself what's
worse, the data getting stuck
or transmitting inaccurate data.
So both of these things can cause
business disruption and it can
cause the business a lot of money.
So let's dig in, or we will be
digging in just a few minutes
on how we can solve that.
But first, let's get into the
second hidden challenge of
managing iot streaming, right?
And this next thing is about
managing device heterogeneity.
So the primary goal of managing
this diversity is to ensure that all
devices can work together seamlessly
and efficiently towards a common
objective without being bottleneck
by the least capable component.
What does that mean?
While you need a multifaceted technical
approach here to tame the complexity
of all these different systems.
You would need to ensure interoperability,
allowing for different systems to
communicate and exchange information
effectively using standardized interfaces
and protocols, you would have to optimize
performance by assigning tasks of the most
suitable processor, or adapt the workloads
to improve scalability and flexibility.
And of course, you would have to handle
different challenges like addressing
issues with varying performance.
Security vulnerabilities arising
from complexity and power
constraints in different devices.
But the reality is that there is a
system, there are system management
challenges as well, such as.
Performance prediction accurately
predicting the performance of
an application on a complex
heterogeneous system is very difficult.
You have those increased security
vulnerabilities, the increased
complexity in shared resources
and heterogeneous systems expands
the potential attack service.
And then you get data integration
and consistency in environments
involving multiple data sources,
whether it's databases, iot, sensors.
Challenges conclude everything from
schema mismatches, data inconsistency
and ensuring data accuracy and
consistency across all platforms.
So the final challenge of streaming
IOT data is, being able to look
at data providence as enterprises
expand their footprint in terms of
geography, programming, language
languages, deployment types, data
types, and data points of entry.
It's.
Becoming harder to trust the
data's integrity, or even
establish a variable chain of
custody in regulated environments.
Who actually gathered that data?
When was it gathered?
Where was it gathered from?
What did the handoff look like?
What server was used?
Was it was the server actually secure?
What systems were involved?
Which users had access to it?
Did they transform it?
Was the data tested who touched it last?
It's crazy because data Pro, pro
providence data provenance is
more necessary than ever before.
It ensures that there is no
unauthorized access, alteration,
or contamination of data.
It verifies the origin of the data.
It ensures that audits will be passed and
paints a clear picture of who is liable
for the data at any given point in time.
Talked about a lot of
different challenges.
What are the solutions?
How do you tame this iot giant that
has invaded the streaming world?
As iot data grows and flows continuously
from an expanding universe of devices
and system, the real challenge becomes
achieving true end-to-end visibility
across your entire data stream.
This is where discipline
data management stops being
optional and becomes essential.
It's where chaos and failover
testing turn into a routine practice.
Where fast data exploration becomes a
critical workflow and where security
and governance are designed into the
system, not patched on later, this
is where the shift should happen.
This is where your team shifts
from reacting to emergencies
to starting to anticipate them.
So what do you need in place to
be able to anticipate any of the
emergencies that might come up?
How do you deal with these
hidden challenges when it
comes to data integrity, device
heterogeneity, and data provenance?
You need an end-to-end solution.
You need something that's going to
give you a unified look, a unified
control plane to unlock all of Kafka's
full potential, a platform that
provides that single pane of glass
so you can see the entire ecosystem.
Transforming it into a managed, secure,
and efficient enterprise asset, and
that's how Kafka streaming should be used.
So what does that start with?
You've got to have this centralized
management Kafka component.
What that means is you can see
there's four components of managing
data and there's intelligence
scale of how you use that data.
So when we're talking about the core
components of managing data, that's
everything that you want to see in one
central place from topics, schemas,
consumer groups, Kafka Connect, et cetera.
And at the same time, you want
to be able to add intelligence at
scale because there is so much data.
So you can have metadata and labels
to make resources easy to discover and
organize while real time cluster and
broker monitoring provides that immediate
insight into health and performance.
You also need to be able to
give developers what they
need so they can move quickly.
So how do you do that?
You need something that has
self-service tooling in it.
So they can abstract away the
complexity that comes with Kafka, but
you can provide developers with the
tools they need to build tests and
debug applications quickly and safely
without needing to be experts on Kafka.
Of course, it's important that we need
to have end to end zero trust framework
when it comes our data in motion, right?
You need data quality and governance.
You need to be able to have traffic.
Traffic and cluster protection
and make sure that you know who's
entering and using the data and who
has access to what data when it comes
to ensuring compliance and protecting
your most critical data streams.
How can you do that?
So how do you get that?
Let's break it down.
You need to make sure you
see who does what, right?
So giving, having that granular
access control, auditing,
and data centric security.
So on the left hand side here, it's about,
identity and access management teams
can now, define find grade role-based
access for different users and groups.
You can integrate with SSO and
existing L DAP or ad systems and
automatically manage users over time.
Pretty cool.
On the right hand side, you've
got data protection and auditing.
Every user and application is
captured in immutable audit logs
that can actually be exported.
Data is protected end to end with
message encryption, including
field level and schema based
encryption for sensitive data.
And when teams need controlled access,
you've got dynamic data masking, ensuring
that sensitive information is only visible
to those authorized users or obligations.
Together.
This allows organizations to meet
security and compliance requirements
while still enabling teams to
safely self-service streaming data.
No bottleneck, right?
So how do you actually enforce data
quality before data ever becomes
a problem, while also giving the
enterprise a single source of truth
for all streaming data On the left
hand side, it's about what you can do.
You can ensure data is valid
before it enters the system.
Teams can define quality gates,
enforce schema usage, and
apply advanced validation rules
to make sure only compliant,
well-structured data is produced.
If data doesn't meet those standards,
it's blocked at the source, preventing
bad data from propagating downstream.
On the right hand side, it's about
maintaining an enterprise wide catalog.
This gives teams searchable, centralized
view of data streams, topics, and schemas.
It also enables secure sharing through
data sharing in partner zones and
supports chargeback by tracking resource
usage by app, by team or application.
Together.
This allows organizations to scale
streaming with confidence, protecting
data quality, while improving visibility
governance and collaboration across teams.
Finally, it's about protecting cluster
stability by putting automated guardrails
around how data is produced, consumed,
and managed on the topic management
side, all create or alter requests go
through a governed workflow, ensuring
changes are reviewed and approved
before they impact the cluster.
Topics can also be safely renamed without
disrupting producers or consumers.
For producers policies enforce that
all messages have a valid schema
and apply rate limiting to prevent
runaway producers from overwhelming
brokers and causing outages.
And on the consumer side, group
level policies control how consumers
connects and behave limiting group
membership, join rates and commit
offsets to prevent misbehaving consumers
from destabilizing the cluster.
Together.
These automated policies shift Kafka
operations from reactive firefighting
to proactive protection, keeping
clusters stable as usage scales.
So let me leave you with
this one final thought.
What's your disciplined
approach to data management?
Do you have a disciplined
Iot data streaming is only growing.
There's more and more data that is
coming down that needs to be used in for
different business models and be used
to actually drive different decisions.
So as the IO OT bubble keeps expanding,
do you and your team have the right
tools and foundation to ensure that this
increasingly fragile bubble doesn't burst?
Thanks for your time.