Hi everyone.
I'm Harshita Doe from Apex FinTech
Solutions former with Technologies,
and I'm thrilled to be here at
conference 42, data Script 2025.
Today we are diving into how
embedded analytics and data
scripts are transforming enterprise
knowledge systems, turning what
used to be static repositories into
dynamic intelligent ecosystems.
Let's start with the problem.
More than 50% of the enterprise knowledge
systems fail to deliver real value.
We are talking about massive
organizations, a hundred K plus
employees across hundreds of
countries, spending millions on
tools that people don't actually use.
Our journey to fix this took 24
months, two years of transformation
to make knowledge accessible,
contextual, and measurable.
Why do these systems fail?
First, static architectures
legacy tools can't keep up with
how modern themes actually work.
Second, disconnected content information
lives in silos, making it nearly
impossible to find what you need.
And third, poor user experience.
If finding information feels harder than
asking someone on Slack, people won't
self serve, and that's the reality.
So how did we turn things around?
We approach this like a
data-driven product transformation,
not just an IT project.
We embedded analytics to understand
user behavior, mind search patterns,
to uncover intent, built real-time
feedback loops, and enhance SharePoint
with custom JavaScript microservices.
In other words, we stopped guessing
and started listening to the data.
JavaScript was our engine
for transformation.
We built dynamic UI components that
adapt in real time to user behavior,
context aware filtering made sure people
saw only what was relevant to them, and
natural language search allowed users to
ask questions the way used humans too,
not the way research engines expect.
That's how we brought intelligence
and empathy into enterprise systems.
Here's a quick look under the hood.
We use SharePoint online as a secure
foundation, and on top of that, we layered
custom JavaScript, microservices handling
analytics, search and personalization.
The analytics engine processed live data
for insights, while the UI delivered
a responsive, tailored experience.
It's modular, scalable, and measurable.
The results speak for themselves.
We got information retrieval times by 33%.
Self-service resolution jumped 22
points from 62% to 84%, and onboarding
time also dropped by 21% in short.
Employees found answers faster.
Got up to speed quicker,
and less on support.
From a business per standpoint,
the impact was just as powerful.
We saved $3.7 million annually
through efficiency gains support.
Tickets also dropped by 35% because
users were solving problems themselves.
Analytics didn't just improve experience.
It drove measurable.
ROI.
This transformation also
changed how we governed content.
Our dashboards track engagement.
What's working?
Watch it note analyzed where
users abandoned searches to
fix broken experiences, and we
detected emerging needs before
users even request new content.
It's governance powered
by insights, not instinct.
At the core, three engines drive the
system intelligent search powered
by NLPA personalization engine
tuned to behavior and roles and real
time analytics dashboards that kept
everything transparent together.
They formed a living learning system that
evolved with users, not despite them.
If I had to summarize what really made
this work, it's these four principles.
First, modularity build
independent service pieces that
grow without breaking each other.
Analytics first, that is
measure everything from day one.
Third, scalability, assume
success and design for it.
And fourth and finally user-centric
development because tools fail when
people aren't part of the build process.
Here are a few lessons that stuck with us.
Start with user behavior.
Don't just assume,
invest in microservices.
You'll unlock flexibility without even
replatforming and make data visible.
Real time dashboards create
accountability and momentum.
These lessons are universal,
no matter your tech stack.
If you're wondering how to get started,
here's the roadmap that we used.
Assess where you are today.
Lay the foundation with analytics.
Add intelligence with
JavaScript powered features.
Optimize based on feedback, then
scale across the organization.
It's a repeatable, proven approach,
not just a one-off success story.
Let's wrap it up.
First, embed, analytics and everywhere.
Second, leverage JavaScript to make
systems adaptive and intelligent.
Third, focus on measurable
outcomes that prove ROI.
And finally, build modular, scalable
architectures that evolve with
your business, and that's how we
transform knowledge into action.
Thank you so much for joining me today.
I hope this session sparks ideas on how
you can make your own knowledge systems
more intelligent and human centered.
You can find me on call 42 or LinkedIn,
and I'd love to continue the conversation.
Thanks all.
Bye.