Hello, everyone.
My name is Sharon Bar.
I'm going to talk about unit test
today, who likes unit testing.
Actually, most developers
don't like testing at all.
But let's see how generative AI dev
tools can worry about the tests for you.
But first, a little bit about myself.
I used to live 17 years in the Bay Area.
I worked for Yahoo.
I was the first VP of Engineering
at Couchbase, a NoSQL database
company, a CTO at Lifesign, a startup
called Bina Technologies, acquired
by Roche, a former developer.
I recently founded Early.
At Early, we build high quality working
unit tests for pull requests and scale.
I like to call myself the
Chief Test Code Generator here.
I generated over half a million
lines of test code in the past year.
I love travel and do outdoor activities.
Tremont Blanc was one of the
recent highlights and more.
So let's dive into our talk.
We all know CrowdStrike outage, where
a tiny bug leads to a massive crisis.
If you read about it, what happened
over there, a simple auto array out
of bound exception caused the null
pointer exception added to the fact
that the software was running at the
low level of the Windows operating
system caused blue screen of death.
And since then we all know what
happened, the highest cost of bug
ever over 5 billion in losses.
CrowdStrike alone, sorry, CEO of Delta
said that, Microsoft outage cost them half
a million, 500 million dollars in revenue.
if we dive a little bit into the anatomy
of bugs, you can see that the cost of bug
is something that can go up exponentially.
If you catch it early, close
to coding, which is unit
tests, the cost is pretty low.
If you catch it post production, Then
the cost of the bar goes up for the roof
and CrowdStrike is an extreme example.
So let's Look at an analogy over
here, Henry Ford used to say if I had
asked people what they wanted They
would have said a faster horse And
Henry Ford listened to the problem.
People were trying to solve the problem
of moving from point A to point B.
So he invented the car.
And, what happened then, when people
had cars in their hands, they said,
OK, what can I do with a car that
I could not have done with horses?
I could, go work on the next town and come
back and sleep at home with my family.
I can build a travel business.
I can invent a truck and move goods.
And if you look at the, what's happening
today with the new waves of GNI tools
that are focusing on the problem of code
quality, the question is really, are
we, how can we use these new DevTools
that, where we are used to horses, for
example, for test code generation, and
today we are starting to have cars.
How can we use these tools, to
generate test code automatically?
focus on the problem is not the
testing, the problem is the code
quality, and the test tools are really
helping us achieve that end goal.
Now if you look at how developers are
spending their time, developers are, and
this is based on different studies, about
30 percent of the time is spent on new
code, half of it on tests related tasks,
and half of it on the application code.
about 20 percent on maintenance, again,
half on the application, half on the
test on 13 percent time about debugging
and finding issues and fixing them.
A quarter of the time on meetings,
security, and people, like to drink a
lot of coffee and obviously lunch, and
breaks about 10 percent of the time.
So overall, about a third of developers
time is spent on tests or test
related tasks around fixing bugs.
So clearly, developers
want to test their code.
The question is, how can they
spend their time effectively?
And again, if you look at the, what
types of tests exist, we talked about the
functional test, unit test, component,
integration system, UAT, non functional,
security, localization, usability.
Manual test, exploratory, ad hoc can
happen throughout the life cycle.
Automated tests, white box, black box,
and there are many other types of testing.
really, what will bring developers
the highest value for their
time in terms of minimizing the
number of bugs in their code?
So today, let's see unit test.
How, what is the value
of unit test generation?
So as we said, it helps you catch
the bugs early, very early, where
the cost is really the lowest.
It frees up a lot of the developer's
time so you can spend it on, on the
application code, on higher level tasks,
on bringing value to the business.
It speeds up the release cycles
because you have the, you're
catching the bugs earlier.
And it can be used on multiple use cases.
During development, we'll
talk about a few examples.
If you now look at the DevTools, there are
roughly two groups, there are assistant
DevTools for test code generation, like
GitHub Copilot, like Cursor, and there
are other companies that are raising a
lot of money to help solve this problem.
And our test code, AI agents,
and we'll talk a little bit what
the AI agent means down the road.
But first, let's look at
a couple of those tools.
So today, I'm going to show you the
two, maybe more popular or main tools
around these two distinct areas.
So cursor is A fork of a GitHub
of a, visual Studio Code.
It's a, an assistant tool that helps
you generate code, across the board.
It's general purpose, all languages,
all type of code application, front
end backend testing, unit testing.
whereas, on the other side we
have early, which is an AI agent.
and the difference on AI agent
is that it's very specific
to one task and it does it.
trying to do it better than anyone else
in that case, generating unit tests.
So let's switch to an example.
I'll increase my screen.
And we'll start by looking at the
backend code, the server code that
we wrote around the user services.
And, we'll generate unit
tests using, Cursor.
let me, so I install Cursor.
Cursor, you install it, from, you
install any other application,
VSCode, you install Cursor.
What's specific about Cursor that makes
it so popular is that it's very tuned for
AI and using AI for your code development.
So if you look at the configuration,
obviously there are general parameters.
There is a, pro version that is paid.
You can select different
models, or they support most of
the popular models out there.
You can actually plug in your
own API key, and generate,
results that are good for that.
So how do I use it?
I go to my method, so I can, for example,
look at Check Max, number of, users.
Actually, let me just quickly
explain the method we are going to
look at, as an example, check Max,
number of users settings, right?
It's a method that they.
Returns if you have capacity for more
users and throw an exception if you don't.
So if the user is defined, you
don't need to check your return.
Otherwise, you compare the number of
user counts to the max number of users
that you get from a configuration.
And if the user count is above the max
number count, you throw an exception.
going back to the code,
if I, Highlight the code.
I can see here chat and edit.
Chat opens the tab, the cursor tab, that
enables you to interact with the LLM
in a very easy manner with your code.
So over here, I have the method.
I'll ask you to please generate
happy path and edge cases,
unit tests for this method.
And the cursor will immediately
start generating these tests.
As soon as it's done, I
can create a new test file.
So let's apply.
The code is copied over here.
A new file is created.
Let's change the file name to test,
because that's my format on this project.
And what I can see, all the tests
that are generated over here.
Let me close this for a second.
So we can see that the tests, actually
are not, have some compilation issues.
We'll look at them, but
first let's fix those.
So if I highlight an error, I
can do a quick fix, fix with AI.
Over here there is an object, that
the LLM did not get the property
right, so it's fixing the properties.
Let's fix this one, there are a few cases.
It would be nice if there is a feature of,
fix, for all, but, probably doesn't know.
We'll fix this one as well.
Fix with AI, fixing the object.
So those are the three cases of,
it didn't get the object right.
There is another case where
it didn't get the type right.
So this is a big int, and
over here, put a number.
So if we do a quick
fix, we'll fix, the ID.
And now it's, one n.
And then we have a similar problem
to before, that the object is not,
So it's basically editing the object.
And so I'll accept.
And then initialBalance.
Something on the, probably,
needs to be decimal.
So accepting that, and decimal, this is
a simple fix, let's just add library.
So now, we fixed, after generating
the test, we fixed all the,
Issues, Now I can look at, another
extension here that is Jest.
Jest is a test framework
that we are using over here.
and it visualizes all the tests for me.
in this particular case, now
I'm running all the tests.
and I can look at, the user service.
sorry, where is it?
user service dot, test.
where is the file?
Hold on.
Okay, it's not this one.
Oh,
yes, it is.
what I can see over here
that there are four red tests
that are covering the cases.
should, let's see.
Should not throw an error
if the user already exists.
It's basically first initializing the
objects, should not throw an error,
and then should not throw an error if
the user count is below limit, happy
path, and other edge cases we are
seeing if the count is at the limit and
if the count is exceeding the limit.
So that's one way, that is
called, Code Assist, right?
So we asked it to generate a test.
It wasn't completely running.
There are still issues, by the way.
It's not running, more some, dependencies.
But let's pause over here
and try another tool.
But this is an assistant tool.
So the other tool we'll try is Early.
Early, unlike, Cursor, is an extension.
So it's an add on to the,
Visual Studio, or to the IDE.
You install it for the
marketplace, do a sign in.
And then what you can see over here.
is a view of all your files and the
classes and the methods within the file.
So we look at this method, what else I
can see here is, if there is a test unit
test, that was generated for that file,
I can see the test and I can see what is
the coverage of the test at the method
level, not just at the file level, like
most, tools, but at the method level.
So if you look at the check
marks, number of users, now
I can generate test for this.
I can generate test for that method.
I can also generate it for other methods.
when I generate a test, I
can do it through the magic
wand or I can go through the.
And when the test generation starts,
I can also see a window over here that
opens and help me increase the quality
of the code, not just generating tests.
So it can suggest
documentation for the method.
I can decide I choose to
insert it to my method.
It can actually suggest some
improvements to the code.
So consider caching the
max number of users.
Value to reduce database
calls if there is one.
So that's another good idea.
And then the tests are being generated.
Once they are ready, I have a link
over here that says go to test.
And I can see the links over here.
And at the same time, there is
a coverage calculation that is
happening behind the scenes to see
what is the coverage for these tests.
let's have a look at these tests.
Normally, if there is a high coverage,
it means that the tests are actually
compiling and running and are good.
You can see that an agent can actually
do a deeper dive into the code.
It can generate mocks to
generate better tests.
You can see different types of tests.
There is a happy path test.
Probably same.
Should not throw an error
if the user already exists.
which is what we had before.
It's under, it's now grouped.
should not for an error if user
count is below maximum, etc.
if I look at the, Jest extension, I
can actually see the test over here.
what's nice about it is, If I run them,
let's run all the tests over here,
I can see whether they're actually
running, green, red, or not compiling.
Let's see how they are performing.
It takes a little bit of time because
when I record, my computer uses CPU
heavily and that slows down everything.
But when it will finish running, it
should take normally a few seconds.
We can see the number of green tests.
So what I can see over here, that I
have, two happy paths, should not throw
an error if the user exists, should
throw error user limit, and so on.
And that explains why I got 100
percent coverage, if I look at the
method level, for all these three
methods for which I generated tests.
Let's see another thing over
here, I can see, some red tests,
so it means that there might be
an issue with some of the tests.
this could be actually expected anything,
sometimes the red test are an issue
of the test and sometimes the red
test could actually indicate a bug.
Expected email received undefined.
could be a real bug on the code.
So let's, we saw two tools.
One is a code assist, one is an agent.
There is an interesting, let's
say, Let's see how an agent and
an assistant can collaborate.
So let's say I would like to see
if this is a real problem and
let the assistant, in this case
a cursor, try and fix the test.
Understand why is it red.
If it's a problem on the test,
maybe it can actually fix it.
If it doesn't fix it,
it could be a real bug.
And it's worth looking into it, but
that's for a different presentation.
So let's go back And
discuss, what we've seen.
what we've seen is really, the
differences, about the types of, AI
agent dev tools, and the, I would
like to talk a little bit about
assistance versus agents, AI agents.
we hear this terms a lot.
Assistant, is a general purpose, tool
where the user interact with the LLM,
could be really amazing user experience,
like cursor, could be more simplified,
chat GPT is still very good, but the user
ask a question, get a response, ask a
question, get response, analyze it, until
they are satisfied with the results.
As we are transitioning to the world of,
agents, we are starting to look about what
humans are doing, more at the task level.
our daily job, or job in general,
is composed of many different tasks.
One minute task, five minute
task, thirty minutes, all the
way to completing the job.
When we talk about AI agents, the
goal of an agent is not to replace
the human, but replace the task
the human is doing, completely.
in this case, the human is asking the
product, or solution to perform a task.
The solution is now talking to
the LLM multiple times, talking
to itself, improving the results.
When ready, handing it back to the
user, get the feedback, or just build
a trust, continuously improving it
until it gives back a result that is
working, high quality, and completed.
If we now take that approach and
understand how it looks like the
test code agents, how does test code
assistant look compared to test code
agents, if we compare the output, how
The code suggestions, the code assistant
are generating suggestions for code,
as we've seen, where AI agents are
generating working code, everything.
The quality on the assistant is
low to medium, even if you fix it,
sometimes it works, sometimes you
still need to do more logical work.
The quality of agents is
high quality, comprehensive,
happy path edge cases, mocks.
There is still effort behind Assistant.
You need to continuously fix it.
Using the AI is still much faster
than writing it from scratch.
Where agents are closer to completion,
and it saves you a lot of time.
Even if you need the Assistant
after the agent completed its part,
It's trying to complete something
that started at 90%, not 50%.
And the impact is that you can actually
generate not one test suggestion
at a time, but dozens of quality
working tests for your few files, many
methods, all your project very quickly.
So now let's see how it
really helps us as developers.
in the flow, there are various use
cases, and if you use them wisely,
it can help you generate or develop,
much more complicated applications,
high quality at a higher speed.
first, do continuous
testing during development.
Test early and often.
Then test your PR.
You can do it continuously, or when you're
done with your PR, you think it's good,
now generate all the tests, protect from
bugs, find the bugs for the red test,
protect the bug for the green test.
Testing private methods.
Something that could be fairly
complicated if you are trying
to do it for end to end testing.
Your end to end testing have to touch
so many branches of the code, and
whether it's your use cases or your
data, It's becoming pretty painful.
Now you can turn the private method
into a public method, generate unit
tests for it, test it, return it to
private, and you tested it very easily.
And last one is TDD, test driven
development, which is done very
differently in a simplified manner.
In fact, let me talk
about that a little bit.
So we'll use a different example.
In this case, it's a to do app.
So I already made a flow of how
developers are building an update project.
This is an app that
manages different projects.
How they can update builder software.
It starts with a simple method signature.
I called it Simple Docker.
User can generate some documentation.
And they can generate tests using the
chat, or they can generate tests using
the agent, clicking on the magic wand.
That's first step.
What we'll see is that once tests are
generated, they are somewhat basic.
I can now insert the documentation
and try again and generate tests.
And this is where I have an example.
Generate tests that are more complicated.
And then I will start
implementing, let me close this.
I will start implementing my method
and continuously generating tests.
And what we'll see, That
slowly the tests are becoming
better and more, comprehensive.
And finally, I will add all the edge
cases and generate more tests for that.
The outcome for this, and we have,
the examples is, I can see, the
test for, the simplified version.
where I have a very simple
documentation, happy path, edge cases.
I can see how the tests are
becoming more elaborated, right?
If I look at the step 3 and step 4, where
I already started implementing the cases.
So step 3, I still have, where I have
the happy path, I can see actually
the unit tests that are generated for
the happy path green, and the unit
tests for the edge cases are red.
And when I finish the implementation,
we can see that I have four green tests.
So going back, to the presentation, just
to summarize the use case of TDD, you
can see the different, types of, methods.
Step one, very simple test.
when I have, once I have
more documentation, the
tests become more precise.
Instead of just, simple edge cases,
the edge cases of the test generated
are more, should return 404 if the
project is not found and, and so on.
And when I'm ready and have all the
implementations, then I have all
the test cases and also have high
coverage for that particular case.
So that's, another big example.
Again, cars versus horses.
It's very interesting to
see how developers will
start to adapt these tools.
And build different ways and
use them in different ways to
basically solve the problem of bugs.
So all of those examples are just some.
Final step is how do you test the tests?
high coverage does not
necessarily mean high quality.
And for that there are
different techniques.
One I will talk about today
is called mutation testing.
In briefly, what mutation testing
means is that mutation testing are
introducing changes to your code,
like mutants, or bugs, if you will.
And then it runs your unit
test against those changes.
It expects that your unit test will fail.
And if they don't fail, it means
that you either have A bad test
or not even enough coverage.
ultimately it produces a mutation score.
let's, let me show you,
an example of fire run it.
It's, heavy in compute, so I
hope it'll run nicely over here.
So over here we generated,
test for three files.
We have a hundred percent coverage,
and I run, I have the command line over
here to run the mutation test for, the
file user service, which is this file.
And.
And, we'll see, oh, so in order to run
mutation tests, you cannot actually
have, red tests, because if you
have red test, it doesn't run them.
So I'll, I will skip them, skip.
So every time I have a red
test, I will need to skip it.
and when all my tests are
green, let's skip this one.
If you add more times, I
will actually try and fix it.
But, and then those are
the tests from a cursor.
So I will even delete them.
So let's just verify everything is green.
And let's try again, running striker.
What we'll see with Striker is that it's
actually starting to work pretty heavily
to generate mutants for this file.
The file that we saw
over here, user service.
It calculated that there are 34 mutants.
And as we speak, it generates more
mutants and running the tests.
When it will finish it, it will generate
a report that tells us what is a mutation
score for that particular file, given that
all the tests, all the tests that exist.
And, just maybe, to fast forward,
I will show you the results.
actually, it's almost finished.
Nice.
Okay, so what we are seeing over here
is a mutation score, which is 96.
55, which is pretty nice.
Overall, there were 36 mutants.
Only one survived, which
means that we missed it.
And there are some errors
sometimes, and killed 28.
So most mutants were killed, and that's
how it got to the mutation score.
One thing that we'll do over here,
so let's actually delete some
of the files that we created.
So create user test, we can,
we'll generate, we'll remove
that test is current admin.
We'll go back over here and
let's recalculate the coverage.
So you see now I don't have
links to the test files.
I just deleted, and we'll wait to see
what will be the updated coverage.
It was around the 87 for the file, if I
recall correctly, that's how we started.
Let me refresh it again.
Sometimes, so what we can see over here
that now we have, 87 percent coverage.
Those files have lower than a hundred
percent, check max numbers is 66
percent is current user is zero percent.
So three tests are missing for
three methods on this file.
but the coverage is pretty high, 87%.
so running, the mutation,
tool against striker, really
fantastic tool, by the way.
and let's see what score it
comes up with, right now.
Out of the 34 mutants, it's
the same number of mutants.
Obviously, just less tests,
because there are less unit tests.
And we see that the mutation
score dropped down significantly.
Only six mutants were killed.
Seven survived.
Six has no coverage.
almost half of the mutants are
not being tested by the fact that
these three unit tests are missing.
It gives you an indication how
important unit tests for the quality
of the tests, because it really
touches everything on your code.
If we summarize, testing has
never been so easy, right?
Really, go out and try and use
all the AI dev tools that you have
to generate test code for you.
mainly learn how to use
them effectively, right?
how to embed it into
your development flow.
and the outcome is deliver high
quality code faster and become
the 100x engineer of the future.
I hope you enjoyed this talk.
If you have any questions, if you want to
contact me, happy, Sharon at starterly.
ai.
Thank you so much for listening.