Hello, everyone.
welcome to the con 42
JavaScript 2024 conference.
And my name is Ananda Kumar Abellu.
And I am a cloud consultant and
an AI ML consultant at a company
named Sara System, who's a premium
cloud partner with Google Cloud.
We closely work with the Google
Cloud team, and I'm one of the
consultant work for the company.
So today's topic is what I'm going
to talk about is The impact of
machine learning on promotional
strategies, which is like a study of,
AI powered coupon personalization.
so I'm quickly, let's get into the topic.
let me start with the, with what
I'm going to talk about today.
So one is the introduction to AI
powered coupon personalization.
So when I say coupons, it is just that,
You know when you go to any store, they
give you some special discounts for a
product or anything that you buy comes
with an additional discounts so It can be
either you're going to a particular store
or it can be from an e commerce site or
anything that you buy, the discount, that
you get, for that particular product.
So AI powered coupon is how the
AI decides, how much discounts
or anything that can be given,
To a personalized person.
Now the coupon is not for everyone,
you know the coupon when I talk about
is just all in general that we have
but how that particular person or that
individual who's going to buy would get
a discount for that particular product
or whatever he is going to purchase.
the next thing is what is the fundamental
about the AI powered personalization?
Why AI is powering that, how or how it is
going to identify that particular person
and only for that particular person AI is
suggesting for, a coupon or a discount.
So how these, personalized coupons
are and offers are created.
the fourth one would
be what is the benefit?
Why are we doing, this AI
powered coupon personalizations?
And the real world case studies, there
are some companies still follow that
and they have been very successful
doing this, coupon personalizations and
i'm going to talk about that and the
next thing is what are the challenges
and ethical considerations that while
doing this doing this and what are
the challenges that we come up, from
a security, from a data ethicalness,
from data governance, I'm going to talk
about some of the challenges, of that,
and some key performance indicators
when you are doing something, it's
obviously you have to calculate the cost.
KPIs and how we measure that this
particular ai, coupon, personalized
is working for that particular
company and as well as for the
customer who is buying that.
And that, the, and, and also
where are we heading, what is the
future direction for the ai, AI
on these promotional strategies?
And I'm gonna, conclude with some of the
points, why I have been, Consulting or,
consulting this, coupon personalization
for, big enterprise companies as well.
thank you.
And, let's, quickly
get into the, contents.
So first thing, introduction
to the AI personal coupons.
So let me tell you, gimme a small stories.
You remember, like I go to a store
example, like a Walmart or a Kroger or,
the nearby federal market, anywhere.
when you enter the store,
there is always a bit of paper.
Where do you see there are, when you
pick out, you pick two pineapples, that
there will be a third pineapple for free.
you will have a very generalized
way on the new, like a newspaper.
if you buy one kg's of oranges.
there will be another, kg of
oranges for the half the price.
and some, sometimes like you buy
two shirts, you get the third
shirt for 50 percent discount.
you might always think what is
the logical logic behind that.
Yeah.
Logic Behind it is obviously they wanted
you to buy more, but at that time, most
of the time I have seen that you really,
I don't have the intention to buy a
shirt or a pineapple on that particular
day, but the offer is there, right?
But I really don't want
to buy, why would I buy?
Because I just bought, a t shirt.
a shirt or a pineapple from a day before
and when I go the offer will be there
for the next day and it's always a
disappointment that I have encountered.
I'm sure that you might also
seen that same scenario.
Most of us.
Let's do that.
Oh my God.
I just bought this, but today the
offer is on, on, on, on these today.
it is always the advertisement
is, is being wasted.
Some of the time people buy it,
take user, Oh, I think of doing
it, right now there is an offer.
Let me go and grab that.
But it is not the case for all.
and in a retail.
e commerce site or a retail store.
This is how the traditional,
coupons are, working.
so the, there is no way where whether
this coupons that been advertised, or
sometimes you get a mail as well saying
Hey, you go to the store, this is how,
you buy this, there is a discount.
But at that particular time, at a
certain point of time, you don't
need that product or you might
have that product already in store.
But when you want to go and buy, it's
always the discount is not available
at the time that you decide to buy.
I hope that makes sense.
So what, what we are trying to
do is we are introducing the AI
in this coupon personalization.
And, I'm trying to see how this is,
this helps in this, personalizations.
How, how, better this whole strategy
of giving discounts can work.
Okay.
Obviously, AI is being, AI and
machine learning is top in the market.
it is being used, widely
used in every industry.
even I have created myself an AI
bot, which it, which I talk to him.
You can ask me who me, for
every person, AI is big.
Right now being a part of our,
ecosystem right now, in our daily life.
this is again a revolution like how
we cannot avoid phones right now.
So AI is the next move where, we are
going to use the phone for, like phones,
AI will be a part of our, everyday life.
as I explained, the role
of AI in everywhere.
The second, the personalization matters.
I already told you the traditional
way of marketing methods, why this
matters because I, I wanted to, I
really wanted a discount, but at that
time the discount is not available.
Rather, whenever I wanted,
the discount is not available.
Whenever I, whenever I don't wanted
it, the discount is available.
As you see that this is an e commerce
market, it is rapidly growing.
it will reach definitely by end of this
year is a 6 trillion market by 2024.
And how these AI can get in,
AI powered coupon strategies
can really make a difference.
differentiation in this e commerce and the
retail stores, in this current, economy.
So that is what this is all about.
So the key concept, AI
personalization uses customer data.
Pretty simple.
I'm getting the data from, a timely
ma matter from, from a person.
Say for example, I'm using my
credit card, I'm getting, I'm
going to the same store every time.
So it is just like trying to understand
the purchase history of that person
and try to give, the personalization.
so for example.
you remember that is always
I don't drink alcohol.
I don't buy beers, or I
don't buy any alcohol stuff.
So when I go, there is a coupon for beer.
Like you buy one beer, there was
another set of beer or alcohol is there.
free or there is a discounted price.
I don't want that because I
am a non alcoholic person.
Why do I need that?
So try to understand these
kind of criterias based on.
for example, I am an apple lover.
I always buy apple.
It will be better, from, the, from
January till October by this time.
I have almost like bought, Seven
or seven, eight times apples, like
almost every month I'm buying apples.
based on particular this history
Okay, this person likes apples a lot.
So he's been constantly buying
apples So I want that person to
have an offer only, only for him
So he buys two pounds of apple.
The third pound is really free for him.
So You understand where I'm coming from.
It is just personalizing some, for that
person for that particular product.
Say it can be biscuits.
So based on his, based on his
purchase history, this is one way.
And I'm just going to talk about
many ways how this personalization,
works in the coming slides.
okay, quickly, next one.
What is the fundamental?
What is AI personalization as I just,
told you, it involves the, some of the
machine learning algorithms to customize
the market content and promote offer
based on that individual's performance.
Say what I conclude is
based on my health history.
One is health history, my
purchase history, my age, my, my.
what else?
I can say my, based on my search
history in the, in the website, in the
internet, based on my family, members,
it can be of any, any kind of scenarios.
The best is the way, is how much or how
we can collect data from that particular
persons and know that particular
person, through mul various sources.
So the key components are how the data
is collected through these systems.
as I told you from different
ways, from different sources,
these informations are collected.
Then based on that, the
patterns are being analyzed.
as I given you an example of apples.
So if I buy apples every month,
based on my apple purchases, the
coupons, The base, a coupon is
being generated based on my history.
So based on my history, I am a,
since I'm not an alcoholic, I
don't buy alcoholic beverages,
I, we don't need that particular
coupon for that particular person.
Rather this can be given to a
another person just for who's more
interested based on that person.
His purchase history, for example.
So here, there are some of the tools
like how the predictive analytic tools.
so say for the last five years, for every
October I am buying something that only
I buy in October, so it just reminds
these, it, it is just a prediction.
So it can, the purchase history can
deliver, tell, okay, this person,
for the next October he's going to
purchase this, Halloween costume.
Okay, or even the during the
Christmas time or maybe my in
October I was born So he's going to
buy a birthday cake every October.
So why don't we just come give
a five dollar or ten dollar?
offer on that particular cake that he's
going to buy So, you know what, it's
just, it just gives the prediction.
based on your information that you have
already given, this kind of like just
predicts that, predicts, the algorithm
predicts what it would be the preference
for that particular person, to issue
a coupon or, So as I just mentioned,
some of them are the purchase history,
browsing behaviors, demographic mean,
what location he's in, he's into.
I live in a very cold location.
it is right now, it is
45, degree Fahrenheit.
So based on that.
so it just predicts me, okay, this person
might buy a woolen cloth or something
that, that, that just personalized for
that particular, person and contextual
data, consider the time of the day.
the device used or the location, say if
I'm just traveling towards, some couple
of, blocks where there is Walmart, it
just gives me a suggestion, hey, there
is a restaurant inside the Walmart that
gives you an offer, if you go and eat
there, obviously if you buy something, in
there, there is a coupon, that is offered,
you get a free snack, in a subway that
is inside Walmart, something like that.
and also it just shows how data flow
through the AI system and created those
personal, just a feeling that, say if
you go to a store and, there is already,
you wanted to buy something and there
is a coupon that is available for
that particular day, it feels so good.
Okay, it just makes me feel that,
okay, I'm getting from a discounted
price that is not for others.
It's just personalized for me.
it?
Okay, let's quickly get
into, how this has been done.
so here, I think as I already
mentioned in the previous slide
as well, customer profiling is
more important, than everything.
As I told you, the age, demography,
his behavior, Purchasing.
so how, what he would, buy, what he
might be, his interest that he might buy.
say if, he loves, apple, there
might be a chance he might love
a beer or, piers or grapes.
There might be another fruit
that he might be interested.
So based on that, if you keep on
buying apples, why don't, he may have
a tendency to buy oranges as well.
So it just gives us, throws a
suggestion on, that, and this all
comes from, the customer profiling.
Then comes the predictive modeling.
AI analyzes the history of data and, as I
said, forecast, it forecasts which coupon
offer will apply for each engagement.
so say if I, if it is a weekend,
the discounts might be different.
And if I'm going on a weekday,
then it is a different.
different.
so this, these kind of things just goes
in, in, it, it called as a predictive,
modeling, it's just based on that
particular date, time and, and the month.
the real time personalization, it
is a dynamic generation based on
customers current behavior, such as I
mentioned, is about browsing history,
product category that you might, buy,
and ensuring the timely relevance.
That is more important.
And the word timely
relevance is, I don't, buy.
Buy, a log of wood in summer, rather,
a log of wood keys always bought during
the winter, when I'm go for camping.
so this is the relevance and the
relevant discounts that can be
offered during, that the, on that,
on the time, based on the time.
So next case study, one of the.
Best and the pioneer in using
the personalized coupon.
Coupon coupons are, Amazon.
Amazon has been a great, and they
have literally boosted their sales by
31st through personalized suggestions.
And you can al always use, if you're
using an Amazon app, then you will re
realize that, there are some suggestions
which just, really makes you to go
and search for those, search for it.
you might be just.
thinking about it or you might have just
searched somewhere else and automatically
just gives you that particular
suggestions on that particular product.
it's unbelievable.
Like it's all like you might be
thinking, and that, there is a
suggestion based on the app would
just show that particular product.
And, and if you're just wondering how I
was just thinking, how come this is there?
And, I, this is all done
by, definitely by the AI.
Okay.
why are we doing this?
What is, what is my benefit in doing,
AI powered coupon personalization?
one is, your, boost.
Boost is the, engagement, you are giving,
more, more offers resonate that more
to that particular customer leading in
increase interactions and satisfaction.
pretty much close to the customer.
Basically, you're trying to understand
what customer would want it.
if you, understand the sales, you,
you should know your customer.
You cannot sell something
that customer won't buy.
You have to Put in your shoes when
you sell something, it's a so trying
to understand the personage and
it also drives the sales growth
so something that you are keep on
buying and which is not sellable.
You don't buy that You only wanted to
have something in your store that can sell
easily or we can sell in that particular
in that season or particular time.
So it just gives you, a lift in, in,
in the, in your sales, in your sales.
So it persuasively sees 30 percent and,
another important thing, as I said in
the beginning, those newspapers that
you, when you enter, those are all like,
it's useless, for me, I don't grab it.
Or if somebody is.
Just pointing me, I don't go and
buy that, because I feel always
that, it's not gonna help me.
those coupons are not gonna help me
anyways because, always when I get it, I
have seen that, I wanted something that,
that those products will not be an offer
or, there will be no coupons for that.
by this way, 30 retail stores
on the e commerce site have seen
35, 37 percent is increased in
the redem, redemination rates.
So the offers, whatever that been
offered, they have seen that it has been
redeemed, redeemed 37 percent increase.
So increased retention.
Why would I just go to another store
which just gives me a general coupon
rather than I know that this is the store
which gives me more than what I wanted?
I always try to pick that store, right?
That's called personalized experience.
it creates a stronger emotional
connection between the customer and
the brand and increase the loyalty.
I don't, I would just buy a same
kind of product, every time if
there is a discount available.
why would I just choose another brand?
It's quite obvious.
And cost efficient.
always like you are predicting
that customer is going to buy this
particular product and you can,
you can, you can be very, the store
can be cost effective as well.
And it can also, be very efficient for
the customer that he gets, what he wants
what that he wanted to buy for a better
price rather than, rather than a, like
a standard price, from another store.
he knows that he's going to get
discounts when he, whenever he
enters that particular store.
better allocation of marketing resources,
reducing promotional spending waste, and
the best part is the ROI improvements.
And the study shows that AI
personalization would double the
return of investment, obviously,
in the marketing campaign.
So whatever you are, spending on for
marketing and, I, I've never seen that
it is going to really, be in vain.
And the last one is the visualization.
The bar graph, comparing traditional
with the AI is a key performance
matrix, like conversations, rates,
retention, always there is a high
in, in everything that you do.
Okay, moving on to the, next.
Obviously, I told you that
I will be talking about the
real case studies as well.
so, The first and my favorite case
study is always the Netflix, because
Netflix has been a very great in,
in doing this for a long time.
They've been using, before, AI and, ML
has been very popular in the industry.
have you ever seen, Netflix been
recommending, a pattern of movies that
you always say if you're, if you always
like thriller movies, which I love, it
always recommends me like whenever I
turn on, okay, based on your, thriller
movie suggestion, you might also might
like these movies, which just makes me
to either buy or use that particular,
Netflix, channel all the time rather than
me going to another, in a real case study.
I think, Netflix have become an
estimated 1 million annual savings,
because of just by, giving, these
personalized contents to, to, to customer.
And the second, thing is always, Amazon,
I think, I already spoke about Amazon.
I have never seen anyone, who, I'm
being amazed whenever I use that Amazon.
I always use Amazon.
I think I use two apps.
One is Walmart and Amazon.
I can definitely just make out a
difference between Amazon and Walmart
because the recommendations and the
discount that, Amazon offers is fantastic.
Fabulous, because they do a lot of
collaboration filtering and deep learning
algorithms and generate and generates
35 percent of the total sale just by
giving those personalized suggestions.
And always, whenever I go, there
is a coupon available for me if
I'm just going to buy something.
I don't know how, but, just wondering,
I'm sure that the algorithm is the AI and
ML algorithms or the background of that.
And some of the other examples are,
I'm not going to read everything,
Sephora virtual assistant.
It just gives you, it's an app
where, it just gives the leads
like 50 lookup average sessions,
increasing purchase intent.
It's an online engagement and driving
sales, both online and in store.
And there was a takeaways, another
company, which is an e commerce
and, to digital content streaming
and cosmetics, cosmetic retail.
It's just another example.
These are some of the examples
and real time case studies.
Okay, moving on.
challenges.
whenever know, whenever there is
something, even in IT, there is a huge
amount of data is being collected.
and this is all done in an algorithm.
you might, as based on our conversation,
there is a, there are There is
so much of data churning, data
filtering, data being analyzed to
come up with a personalized coupon.
And whenever we deal with data,
there is always challenges and
always data can be manipulated.
Data can be done anything, it
can be used against you as well.
So just make sure we are using
these data in a very useful
way for the benefit of someone.
we just have, to have a few guardrails
and number one would be the data privacy.
The increasing, resilience on,
professional data, data rises concerns
about security because we are not just
going to, randomly just, understand a
person because we are collecting some
personal data as well, based on, like age,
his, spending history, uh, you, because
you need to know the person, right?
some of the health, health information.
Say for example, if a person is diabetic,
okay, you're not going to give, a
coupon to buy more, sugar or, or a
very sweet carving, products, right?
So obviously that, that, that guy
is not going to, based on his.
based on his health, he's
going to decide his, future.
And, and you don't want somebody to
know, that you have some health issues.
Obviously it is just, it's just me.
talking about, you, there are some
security and regulatory compliances
that we want every company to, to have.
to follow.
those are CCPA and G-D-R-P-R and business
must be transparent about the data use and
you're just gonna, give the information
to these companies based on, and, and, and
we also wanted to know that this companies
is using my data, to generate the coupon.
make sure everything is transparent.
algorithm bias.
The AI models can inadvertently
predicate bias based on the demographic
leading to unequal treatment.
Okay.
as I just mentioned, so regular audit
should be made, you don't know that
I literally touch based on something
like, a person from a cold region, what
he wanted from a heart region or from
a race, or he can be from a different,
demographic, location based on that.
you should try to understand, say
if, for example, right now I'm living
in a colder region and I just moved.
My, my, my, I just moved means I've
just moved everything to another place.
So it should understand and should not
be biased based on, okay, this guy, he's
not just going to buy, this, maybe I've
been buying this for all my day, life.
So still the coupon
personalization to work.
So each has to be a constant check.
every time I, we buy something,
just make sure, that.
the algorithm is reading based
on where the customer is buying,
which of the store he's getting it.
So just have a track of the customer.
next one is balancing
personalization and intrusiveness.
over personalization may feel Allow
customers to control their data and
provide transparency on how it is used.
again.
Sometimes you are over personalized,
you may feel very bad, every time, over
personalization, it can be based on the
history rather than giving suggestions
that you may not, say if you're buying
apple, I don't like grapes, why would
I need based on your fruit buying?
History you cannot suggest some Fruit that
might be harmful that for that particular
Person, so just don't over personalize
Personalization is also a bad so make
sure that you have a customer have the
control say there should be something
Invariant an option where it could say,
don't suggest me any of these fruits,
something like, or don't suggest me any
of these products, though I have bought
them in the past for someone, but I'm
not really interested, so there should
be some guardrails on that as well, show
me these, or don't show these products.
products, which are, not relevant.
for example, the product
should know that, I'm a man.
I might've bought something for
a woman or my wife, but it should
not just give me a suggestion to
buy a woman's product all the time.
I'm sure like you, you would understand
what is over personalization means.
I'm just, let's get into that next topic.
Okay.
technical challenges, required
advanced data infrastructure.
skills, AI talents, this is
always a biggest challenge.
Though there are a lot of, AI enthusiasts
in there, but the investments for
doing the data analyzation, data,
data warehousing, data cleaning,
this is all a biggest challenge.
in the recent days right now, until
there is, very high much demand in
the skill set of AI talents, the
person who is deciding on working on
that, who really have to have that
knowledge on what he's trying to do.
there's definitely a significant barrier
for small companies to come up with
these, with these technical challenges
because the infrastructure that is,
that's been built for these are.
are a lot and is expensive.
so highlights, solution approaches
like regular algorithms, audit, data
analyzation and customer consent
management tools should be used.
the solution approach has to be,
audited at least six or three
months every or at least a year.
so these are some of the
ethical, and challenges.
for doing this AI coupon personalization,
let's move on to the next.
whenever we do something, it's always
that you have to measure that, right?
say, I would say the progress.
So this year I have accomplished that.
What is for the next year?
It's I think we are all most
professionals working in those companies.
we are always tied up with
the kpis End of the year.
It's always a question your manager asks
you what kpis are how it is not just
you it's for any product or Anything.
How have you?
done from the past year to this year.
these are the key performance indicators.
One is customer engagement.
Have you really got success on this?
how many click rates that the customer,
click through rates, the time spent
on the page, the interaction in that,
and the, gauge interest that customer
had, this, These are some of the
KPIs that we need to measure, while
introducing this, coupon personalization
for any e-commerce or site.
The next is, conversation rates.
measure the percentage
of personalized offers.
you just have a track on, recipients
who make this purchase comparing with
the non-personalized, campaigning.
That's a good point, see that, How
many people that have really used
this coupon, if they have not used
it, try to educate the customer.
Hey, you have some, something like this
in your app, or when you're buying,
you should, because it's based on
your history, this offer is available.
Maybe they might have not seen
your email, maybe they are
not, but I've used your app.
So educate the customer.
So have that conversation, rate And try
to analyze that particular, particular
subject on, on whether this offers that
are being really redeemed by the customer.
Okay.
Redeem ration rate.
That's it.
so how many recipients do you
use as the postional equipment
indicating the relevance and
appealing, appeal of the offer?
So are these real, really relevant?
some of the times they might show you
something which is not even relevant.
You just go back and check your
data is accurate or is it something
that, that is not correct.
that is something that, you need
to have a valid, validation check
every six or three months here just
based on whether it is working.
customer lifetime value, so whatever we
do, unless otherwise customer is satisfied
There is no, no value on that, right?
So you have a metrics like a KPI
where you assess the impact on
a long term revenue generation.
From a particular customer, how
much the revenue has been generated?
I don't think many of the, many of
them know, or any retail store how
many times I use this go to Walmart
or a particular store to buy this.
And how much, I have generated
for, for the Walmart, because I go
to different Walmarts every time.
I think, there should be a
generalized way to monitor that.
Okay.
Then, KP analysis.
Explain how to send benchmark.
don't be shy to create new strategies.
new KPIs, whenever you see something,
you set your, and start, measuring those
indications against those traditional
coupon and distribution methods.
Okay, talking about
next, what is the future?
the future is pretty simple.
I know the AI is advancing
into rapid growth.
this industry has been rocking
and it is going at a speed.
I would say it's going
at the speed of light.
So there are so many improvements.
Every day you re, you take,
you read a tech newspaper.
There was something or the other, in
the, in, in any corner of this world.
They've been talking about
AI and ML and new innovations
are being reported every day.
So based on that, we need
a future directions where
we got, granular targeting.
A advancements will enable more
precision customer segments
and hyper-personalization.
so we are just getting more
details and how I can offer some
discounts in a very minute manner.
That is, gang, granular targeting,
integration with a, AR and vr.
that's the future, right?
AR and VR is so exciting.
It's a broader chapter again.
so I'm just going to put my
glasses and just say, Hey, I'm
just looking for some apples now.
If I'm just thinking in my mind,
it's almost like just done.
It just gives you the coupon.
Just all the purchases will be done.
And next any moment my apples
will be arriving at my door.
So virtually try on and
argument, the rear end.
argument to reality shopping, you
don't have to go physically inside
the store, but regularly just put up
with your AR and just do the shopping.
And by the time you see something on
the store in your AR, in your, through
the glasses, it's almost like it just
gives you that, particular, okay, there
is an offer rather than you don't have
to do an app search or you don't have
to, go to the website to get a coupon.
The coupon is already shown in your eyes.
how fascinating and why
is activated commerce?
Okay, that's another, common and
everywhere, I ordered my pizza through
my, voice activated, devices at home.
if I wanted, I just tell my
Google home to buy something.
So how about a Google home?
how about checking, whether you have
a coupon or something, in, through
your personal assistant, or your voice
assistant, speaker that can just,
Alexa, just give me, I wanted to buy
something, do you have a discount here?
Yeah, it just throws you
an offer, Pretty cool.
Yeah.
So ethical AI practices, increase
focus on AI transparency and fairness,
expect evolving revolution framework,
and govern AI use in the marketing.
Innovation trends.
Discuss how AI can adapt a new data source
like IoT, wearable technologies, and
provide even more Contact ab, their pro,
promotions that is more important, right?
that's, these are all the, the future,
future, this is all the recommendation,
like innovation trends, right?
which I would really, which is
something that it's very creative,
pro I call this creative promotions.
moving on to next.
We have come to the end
of this presentation.
as I told you, I think my message
is pretty clear on what I have been.
This AI coupon personalization, you
would see in even a very small store,
in any given point, in any time.
You go to a personalization, small shop
and you wanted to pick something, these
personalized coupons will be everywhere.
you can get into an e commerce
site or, or a gas station.
You wanted to buy something, any small,
tiny shops, to retain the customers.
These will, these, AI coupon
personalizations will be pretty common.
in, in the recent, in the recent years
coming, in the coming years, all these,
traditional newspaper, coupons will just
be gone and, you will know from just
looking, you get information, through
your app or it can be from any of your,
devices that there is a coupon available
on what, where you go, by the time you
go to the store, every time you enter
the store, there is something that You
know, you're thinking to buy something.
There is a discount available for them.
It's simple.
is as simple as that.
it can be electronics, it can be
pa paper, it can be, vegetables.
It can be, a meat, or
you want to buy some.
Food, something like, I don't know whether
you, I have, recently I went to a store
where I wanted to purchase something.
I was, though, there, there was a coupon.
They immediately just throws
me another coupon saying that,
Hey, are you having a food?
I said, when I click okay.
And he said, you just throw, Hey,
there is a burger that is available
free for you based on your purchase.
How cool is that?
and somewhere that is linked
to the Amazon, store as well.
so again, advanced machine learning
algorithms, business can analyze
vast amount of customer data to
leverage high, highly targeted.
As I, this is all, conclusion is
just, I'm just talking about, whole
presentation in couple of lines.
So this is how, a personalized
coupon, remediation is done.
And the benefits are very clear.
the business grows.
it really, get, gets you what you wanted.
build, it builds, a very tight,
close relationship with that store.
it just makes the customer happy.
a happy customer, happy buying.
it goes for the store.
It just keeps the
customer for a long term.
and it also help.
it also helps the person every time that
you buy something, there is some other,
it just values the money as well for
both of the customer and the end users.
the rest of the things, it is
pretty straightforward on what I do.
I am not going very technical
on how the, how, what are the
algorithms is all being used.
But in a very general pay, high
level, these are the, these are some
of the, this is going to be, coupon
personalization will be pretty common.
I'm sure like everyone in every
industry might like to, use it.
it can be, it can be, if you want,
can be to, if you right now decide
to go and watch a movie, think
about if there is a discount or a
coupon available for that movie.
How cool is that?
Or if you wanted to go and watch a
game right now, interest and you don't
know whether there will be a coupon
available, if there is a coupon available.
just by checking, just by, based
on your history and based on
your, relevant, how cool is that?
So that cool is what this AI.
Personalization, personalization is,
and I just wanted to thank everyone
for this opportunity to talk to you
and just through my insight and vision
about the impact in, impact of machine
learning in, in coupon personalization.
And thank you and you
have a wonderful day.
See you soon.
Thank you.
Bye.