Hello.
Welcome to AI with JavaScript.
There's a great chance that you've
come to this talk because you want
to learn how to develop your own AI
applications, all with JavaScript.
And there's also a possibility that you
want to be able to use JavaScript because
maybe you don't have much of an experience
with data science or machine learning.
And I want to say to you, that's awesome.
Because.
Although you may not have a, like any
experience with, with machine learning,
or if you're not very experienced
with machine learning, that doesn't
mean that you can't actually develop
applications that can work with ML models.
In fact, I am definitely not an expert.
I'm probably just like you, I work
with people who I consider to be
machine learning experts, but I
am definitely not one of them.
However, the great thing is that so
many libraries exist now, they make
it so easy for us to get started,
to get to learn, to build our own
applications and from there, can like
Catapult us to learning more, right?
Can let us go deeper into learning how
to work with machine learning, how to
create our own models, how to train
or how to retrain existing models.
And so two of the models that, sorry,
skipped over to the code a little bit
sooner than I was supposed to, but two
of the models that, two of the libraries
that, can actually help us with this in
JavaScript in particular are TensorFlow.
js, which was created by
Google and Transformers.
js, which was created by HuggingFace.
Great thing about the both of these
libraries is that they're open source.
They allow for machine
learning on the client side.
So we don't actually have to work with
the server to actually be able to create
our own applications with these models.
Again, the models have been pre trained.
They have Been trained
on an existing data set.
You don't actually have to provide
your own data sets in order to be
able to work with these models.
So depending on the type of model that
you're working with, and depending
on what you need to provide, you
wouldn't necessarily have to provide.
you wouldn't have necessarily have
to create a data set or clean a
data set or anything like that.
also TensorFlow and transformers are two.
Like libraries in Python, so you have
TensorFlow and Transformers, the Python
libraries, and they have TensorFlow JS and
Transformers JS, the JavaScript libraries.
So what that means is that if you
see a model that has been created,
like with the Python libraries,
but you want to try to use them in
JavaScript, it is possible that they
could be converted for use in Python.
In JavaScript really depends on like
the type of, like the type of model
that you want to work with and if
that is supported in a JavaScript
library, however, it is possible in
both libraries actually provide like
a conversion script that you can use.
We can work with these libraries like
we would any other like JavaScript
library by installing them via a CDN
npm package and both actually do allow
for server side inferencing with node.
js as well.
So just to talk a little bit more
about like why machine learning in
the browser could be a good thing.
because, these libraries, they take care
of a lot of the work for us, but it is
a good idea to know exactly, what type
of benefits they potentially provide.
And One is that they can increase privacy
for our users because we wouldn't have to,
Like we wouldn't have to send their data
elsewhere for, use with the models that
have been developed, their data will stay
So, these are all things that you can do.
But the last thing I want to talk
about is that you can do a model
that is running on their device.
And this is something that I think a lot
of people are very much concerned about.
And so it can be really important,
especially depending on the type
of application that you're working
with, and the type of data that you
are, you're working with and how
like you want to keep it secure.
working with a model that is run on
a user's device in the browser could
definitely Be useful another thing.
that's pretty great about working with
models in a browser is that it can
reduce latency because again, you're
not like, you don't have to send,
the user's data, their information
elsewhere, and then get a response to
them, be able to provide them, with.
Whatever that response may be, right?
If you're working with images,
maybe you provide like information
about the type of image or maybe
you provide text about the image.
depending on whatever the response
is, you don't have to worry about it.
Then like being returned
from an API, for example.
Which kind of gets to another great
benefit of working with machine
learning models in a browser is
that, the models can still be run
without an internet connection.
So if you have, an application that
maybe needs to be a progressive web app,
this could be, a really good use for
working with machine learning models in
a browser versus, another, alternative,
like working with it on the server.
Another thing to note is that deployment
could be much easier if you are working
with a machine learning model in this
way, because you would simply, deploy the
application like a static site, like any
traditional static site, you wouldn't need
to develop an API or anything like that.
Could just, run as you normally would.
However, With anything, there's
always going to be some tradeoffs and
drawbacks, definitely, I want to keep
these things in mind when thinking
about, whether or not working with, ML
models in a browser is the best thing,
to do depending on exactly the type of
application that you're trying to create.
So something to note is that once, a user
actually, once like a model is initially
downloaded onto a user's device, it could
be a little slow the very first time
because, to have to download it, it has
to, the initial load can take some time.
that could take a few minutes.
and especially depending on
the type of device that they're
using and the network connection.
That they have or where they are, that,
that initial load could be a little
slow, but, after, some use it, that,
that should go away, models, when they
are running the browser, they could be
extracted or even potentially copied.
great thing is that in this particular
case, we're working with open source.
libraries have open source models.
this is not a concern
with these two libraries.
However, depending on, what type
of models you're working with,
this is something to keep in mind.
Maybe if you're working with
custom models, and you're looking
to be able to work with them in
the browser, that is something
that you may want to think about.
if a model is pretty large, then
it probably wouldn't be best to
use for, I could probably be best
to use in the browser in this way.
just because you could run into
some performance issues, especially
depending on the user's device.
And, something else to note is that when
working with the machine learning models
in this way on the client side, you
have to think about, like, how are you
going to update them because, they are
definitely going to have to, be updated.
You don't want them to go stale.
And then you also want to be able to
keep in mind, exactly how will you
handle version control for those models.
So let's get started
talking about TensorFlow JS.
Three things that you
can do with TensorFlow.
js is, you can work
with an existing model.
as I mentioned, those pre trained
models, they've already been
trained on an existing data set.
You don't have to actually, provide data
in order to be able to work with these.
however, TensorFlow.
js.
There's also the possibility of using
transfer learning to retrain models
into Cisaflow JS with your own data.
So if you see a model and it, it has
like a type of a task that you're
interested in, does something that
you're particularly interested in, you
could potentially retrain it with your
own data so that you wouldn't actually
have to create the model from scratch.
Thanks.
But just actually just
change the data set.
however, it is possible to create and
train your own models with TensorFlow.
js as well.
as I mentioned, you're, as a beginner,
you're probably looking to work
with existing models, get started.
but then as you're becoming more, as you
become more familiar, And more comfortable
with working with, machine learning models
in a browser, or as you just want to dive
deeper into how to, get more familiar with
the different types of models out there
and how to, train them, then you could go
to retraining a model, as your next step.
And then, from there, you
decide, Hey, I am ready to go.
develop my very own model.
And so then as that last like step
there that you can definitely do all
with this one particular library.
Some things that you can do in TensorFlow.
js are like image classification,
object detection, post detection,
and even speech command recognition.
So I'm on the TensorFlow.
js website here at the moment, and
I'm here on the page for the models
page where you can see the different
types of models that are available
for use on, for use with this library.
You see how like different
types of vision models, as I
mentioned, image classification.
Object detection, we have models that
can work in particular with the body.
So you have like face
detection type models, pose
detection, hand pose detection.
There are different,
like text models as well.
So you can, have models that
work with question answering.
text, they have a text toxicity
detector, so you can check to see,
if the content that you see on social
media, for example, the text that you
see on social media, you could actually
use this text toxicity detection model
to determine, is it toxic or is it not?
There's also audio.
So here we have the speech command
recognition and that particular
model, that you can work with.
So there's also, you can go to, the
trends, not the transfer flow hub.
Sorry.
You can go to Kaggle.
com models to see the
TensorFlow JS model hub.
so I'm on the website here and I'm
going to select framework and I'm
going to look for TensorFlow JS.
So these are all the different models that
actually can be used with TensorFlow JS.
and there, there are several more.
I'm going to select this first one here.
It's an object detection model.
And as you can see here, it
provides more information about,
the model and what it does.
there's more details.
click read more.
You can see how this object
detector, how it works.
it shows car, table.
and if you continue to scroll down,
you'll even see like how to work with it.
There's some code examples.
So if I come down to TensorFlow.
js, here we are, and then provide
more information about like
how you can work with it here.
So now what we're going to do
is actually look at a demo, that
I've created for, this particular,
that I've created with TensorFlow.
js for this, for this talk.
And as you can see here, we're going
to start off with some very just
simple HTML, very much what we're all
pretty much used to, here, I'm just
going to have, I'm going to upload
an image and then I have a container
where I'm actually going to, place that
particular image that has been uploaded.
Here you can see we have the script
tags that are installing TensorFlow.
js and then also installing the particular
image classification, image, image
classification, model that I'm using.
Sorry.
Thinking image classification because
I have worked with another one before,
but actually this one is supposed
to be the object detection model.
My apologies.
So here we have the TensorFlow.
js object detection model.
And then here I'm just importing this app.
js.
I'm just calling this app.
js script here.
Here we just have plain
old vanilla JavaScript.
What we're going to do is we're
just going to listen for the
image once it has been uploaded.
That's it.
And then we're going to
create a URL from that image.
And then we're going to, Add the
image to, a container, like the image
container that I showed, in the HTML.
And the reason why we're going to do that,
because with this particular model, it
will not work if you send the, it didn't,
work when I tried to send a file directly
over, it didn't really enjoy that.
we're going to create, an image
element, and then it's going to
give it an ID if I upload the image
so that we can easily, grab it.
And then I have this, this function that
I've created called getImagePredictions.
And so this is where we're actually
going to have the, work with TensorFlow.
js.
And as you can see here, we are calling
the particular model, that was loaded.
So if I go back to the script
tag, you see that name, CocoaSSD.
So here, CocoaSSD, we're
going to first load the model.
And then, from there, we're going to use
this detect method and we're going to
send the image that has been uploaded
and it's going to make a prediction.
And so I want to display
information about that prediction.
I want to display the prediction
information in the, in the browser,
so that the users can actually see,
the information about the image.
And so what we're going to do is,
we're going to take the class.
That's returned from the model.
So the class will be like
the name of what is seen.
So for example, ball would be
class in this particular model.
So that would be part
of the response there.
and then there is a score.
So the score, will, Indicate
like how confident the model
is in its actual prediction.
And then we're just going to
convert that to a percentage.
So it's a little bit easier to, see
and understand, when we look at the
demo and then here we just have some
styling that we're gonna do to be
able to display the predictions.
and in here, we're going to use
information from that response.
in what this particular model is
called, like it's labeled as B box.
So there's, it can be an array,
that has information about each,
like multiple objects in an image.
And inside of that, you'll
have like the B box.
And then we'll provide, the position,
select the left, the top, leave
also the height and the width.
And so we're going to use it
to help us better position, the
predictions inside of the image.
So now we're going to actually,
upload the image into, in this
app just to show how it works.
Upload.
Going to upload this image
of Messi, the soccer player.
he's holding a trophy.
I'm imagining this is probably
after the World Cup win.
and so you can see here, he's like
holding a trophy and that's him.
and so the model returned
the class of person.
So it has detected a person
inside of this image and it has
like a 60, 66 percent confidence.
in this prediction, probably
need to improve to see it.
I need to improve to see it.
It says a little bit more so that the
label, so we naturally see a little bit
more on messy versus the trophy here.
so it looks like this particular
datasets mainly focused on people,
doesn't recognize, a trophy,
however, what can be done then when.
Would be to retrain this particular
model with a data set that has more
images, like images with trophies, or
you can even have one that maybe have
a data set that has like images of
various soccer players, and you could
take this model and train it so that
it could detect various soccer players.
So instead of, it returning this
person, it could return, like messy,
for example, or soccer, if you have.
A data set with players.
If you have one, it's
just maybe with athletes.
Maybe it could determine
that, as a soccer player.
So you could definitely be able to
find a way, to provide like more
details by, training, retraining the
particular model with, a data set
with even more, images to learn from.
Okay, so next we're going to now
talk about Transformers JS and
learn about how we can work with
this particular library as well.
It also works with pre trained models.
So he, these models have already
been, already have been trained on
data set, which is really great.
because again, as a beginner, you
can just choose the particular type
of model you want to work with.
another thing that is really
cool about transformers.
js is that it can be used with custom
models that have been converted.
So I mentioned earlier that, they're
like Python, like there's a transformers
and it's TensorFlow, Python libraries,
and those models can be converted.
But also my understanding is that
with transformers JS, like if you're
working with a team, and let's say
maybe someone actually creates their
own particular model, maybe not even
with transformers, or, PyTorch is
usually pretty common with transformers.
But my understanding is that there
is a way in which you can convert the
models on these custom models that
can be used with transformers JS.
In that particular library,
like in the browser as well,
some of the tasks are
supported by transformers.
J.
S.
or natural language processing or an L.
P.
such, like your test classification, your
translation, you have computer vision.
With image classification and
object detection, automatic speech
recognition and audio classification.
And we even also have like multimodal
tasks that will support it.
So an example of that would be
zero shot image classification.
So with image classification, a model
will be trained on a particular data set.
and so then it will recognize different
types of different types of, what we
just saw with the TensorFlow JS that
demo, like how we recognize the person.
However, with XeroShot, these types
of models could then, also be able
to recognize images that they maybe
haven't been trained on, the dataset
doesn't include, doesn't include.
A particular image in a data set, but
it would still be able to recognize.
So like with that image of Messi, where
he's got the trophy, maybe if we were
working with the multimodal model, maybe
it would have recognized the trophy.
Another thing, to note about Transformers.
js, that I think that makes
it really, beginner friendly.
And to be honest, this is just my opinion.
I think it may be even more, a little
more beginner friendly than TensorFlow.
js.
just a little bit more beginner friendly.
But I still think both are really
great libraries to work with.
but something that I think
that makes Transform.
js pretty easy to work with is
that it has this pipeline API.
And so what that does is that it
groups a lot of the, it groups like
the inputs and the outputs, the pre
processing of the inputs and the
post processing the outputs together.
So as you can see, like in this
example, there's a lot less code
written here in comparison to that
demo, that I had with TensorFlow.
js.
So here, you're just going to, import
this, the pipeline from the library.
and then here with the pipeline, you
can see I have let pipe equal await
pipeline and then sentiment analysis.
So here you're actually going to declare
the particular task that the model will,
will run, like what the model will do.
It is possible.
To specify a specific model as well.
However, if you don't do that, then
HuggingFace, the TransformerJS library, it
will just choose a default model for you.
So here we're doing a
sentiment analysis task.
And so here I'm just going to enter
some text, in this particular example.
So COM 42 JavaScript
is a great conference.
And then it could return And, returned
the, a score and a label here.
And it would be a positive,
in this particular case.
Yes, it is a positive.
it could also like return
like negative, for example.
And then it will return a score
like, how positive or, negative the
particular test is, when using this
particular sentiment analysis model.
Like TensorFlow.
js, HuggingFace also has a hub where you
can actually choose models to work with.
And here we are on the website here.
And so I'm on huggingface.
co slash models.
So the models page and you
can then filter by the type of
library that you're working with.
So I'm going to select transformers.
js here.
So we can only get models that
will only work that we know for
sure will work with transformers.
js.
I'm going to go back to task
and so I'm going to select.
let's see, let's say
text to video hashing.
There aren't any texts to video,
so let's try image to text.
So here we can see that there
are, 14 models that have, that are
currently available to work with.
The transformers JS library that, would,
take an image so you could take an image
and then the model, but then provide
a text description of that, image.
So if I click on, let's see, this
particular model seems to be pretty.
popular.
And here you have like more information.
You can see how, many downloads
is received in the past month.
You can see more information.
this one doesn't have a whole ton of
information about like exactly what this
model would do, but if you click, use
this model, this click on transformers JS,
it will show like an example of how you
can actually, work with this particular.
Model.
So here you see with the pipeline, we're
declaring the task of image to text,
and then we are specifying the model
name, and then from there, we can go
on and work with this particular model.
Something I have noticed is
that hugging face will often
provide a link to maybe like the
transformers version of the model.
If there's not a whole lot of information,
if you need like more details.
However, there are some
that can have more details.
I think I saw like an image text
to text one that provided Yeah,
this one's a really popular one.
So it has like more details again It
also has the use this model so you
can still see how to we're up in this
particular model with the pipeline API.
but then it also has some more code
examples here in the detail as well.
and it even has an example kind of showing
how this looks, when working with this
particular model, which is really neat.
So I have a, demo, so I've created a
demo for, working with transformers.
js as well.
with this particular demo, we are
actually going to upload an image.
I'm going to upload an image and then
we're actually going to, use the text
to, the image to text model, to be
able to provide a text description
of the image that has been uploaded.
Okay.
So a little different from what
we did with the previous demo.
a thing I really like about HuggingFace
is that it has something known as spaces.
And so with a space, you can actually
upload your code and then it will
create the, then it will create app
for you is deployed automatically.
so you don't have to actually do
anything more than just upload your code.
if you're working with.
If you're working with, GitHub, if you
use GitHub to, store your code remotely,
then you can actually, connect your GitHub
repository to a space so that you can
actually just upload it in one place.
in this particular, example, I ended
up just I'm going to be sharing it,
uploading the code directly to the space.
And so you can see it was very
similar to any kind of like remote
repository of like your branch.
have the different files here.
And so start off with my HTML.
it's very similar to what we saw
with the other demo here was have
a place where we're going to upload
the image, have um, container to
show the image, maybe display, an
error message if there's an error.
And then also like the, we want to,
display the description of the image.
As you can see here, I am not actually,
I'm not, I don't have a script.
For the, installation of the transformers
JS library here, actually, when we
get to the JavaScript file, you will
see that it is actually being called.
So here we're using, I'm using the
CDN here again, just, this would
be a little easier to make it a
little bit quicker for the demo.
but you can see here, we're call, we're
importing the pipeline from the, via
the CDN here in the JavaScript file.
So we didn't actually have
to declare it in the HTML.
and then we're also, getting this,
importing this in which, you can see
here, I have a comment that says, skip.
so we're going to go ahead
and create our new model.
And we're going to do a local model check.
This model will be downloaded
from Huggy Face Hub.
So that's why we've imported that here.
we have, allow local models.
We've set that to false just
to be able to skip that.
and now we're calling, we're
going to have the pipeline API.
We're going to specify our
task, image to text, along with
the model that we're using.
And, And then here again, it's like
uploading the image, getting, the
file, creating a URL, and then what
we're going to do is here's how
we'll actually add it into the DOM.
create like an image element, and
then we're going to, have call this
function called get test description.
And so here we're actually, that
image URL, we're actually going
to put that into, we're going to
send that to the function here.
And when the pipe With the, like
the pipe here, when it returns, the
text, that's what we're going to get.
So we have this out, generated text,
and then we're actually going to
display that text inside, like just
below the image inside the app.
So if I go back up and I just
click on app, here, upload image.
So I'm going to click that.
I'm going to click a different image and
have a different soccer player this time.
So here we have Alice Morgan,
celebrating, scoring a goal
several years ago with Rosabelle.
And here it has a description of two
women are playing soccer on the field,
which is a pretty great, it's a pretty,
accurate description, I would say.
And this particular model kind of
has pretty basic, test descriptions.
However, maybe there's another model.
That's in the transformers, like
library that I could convert that
may be able to provide even more
detail about this particular image.
I know that also I've seen in the
documentation that reinforcement learning.
Is a supported task
with, in Transformers js.
maybe it's possible to be able to
take a model, train it, kinda do some
reinforcement learning to maybe kinda
like work with, adding, like working with
your own data set and creating, and like
adding more onto that particular model.
If you'd like to learn more about
how you can work with TensorFlow.
js or Transformers.
js to develop your own AI applications,
here's a link, and send my slides.
And, and if you would like to be able
to view these slides or even the code
examples, you Feel free to scan this
QR code and you'll be able to see, I'll
actually have a link tree where you'll be
able to go directly to the code examples,
the demos and the slides as well.
Thank you so much for watching this talk.
I hope you've enjoyed it.
I hope you've enjoyed the Conf
42 JS conference completely.
I hope you've learned a lot.
And again, remember, you don't have
to be an expert to get started with
working with AI in the browser.
However, once you get going
with these different types of
libraries, such as TensorFlow.
js and Transformer.
js, you can definitely continue to
build upon the knowledge that you gain.
Thank you so much again,
and have a great day.