Hey everyone, my name is Abhijit, I'm a
software engineer at Sentry, and welcome
to my talk, Supercharged Production
Stack Traces with Local Variables.
So a little bit about myself, I'm Abhijit.
I currently work at Sentry,
and I help maintain Sentry's
open source JavaScript SDKs.
Sentry as a product helps you monitor
your applications in production, take
a look at the errors and performance
data that's happening, so you can
understand and fix problems faster.
One thing we've learned at Sentry
is that stack traces are really
important to understand how and when
errors happen to help debug them.
You know this locally, and
they're even more important in
production if your server goes
down or your site doesn't work.
At Sentry, we try to make it
as easy as possible to view
your production stack traces.
And so you can see that when an
error happens on a site, or on a
server somewhere, it gets thrown,
Sentry, the Sentry SDK will capture
it, and then surface it to you, real
time, with the exact stack trace.
So you can see the exact line of
code that's causing your issue.
But, the stack trace
sometimes is an issue.
enough in terms of what it gives you.
There's still a vital piece
of debugging context missing.
That debugging context is what
exactly the arguments or state was
at the time the exception happened.
not just looking at the kind of frames
and what your code was doing, but
what variables or classes were being
instantiated at the time of your error.
there's a solution for this, and a
lot of debuggers give this to you.
It's to allow you to see the local
variables, or the variable state
at the time of when a debugger is
paused or when an error is thrown.
So here is an example, I just attached
a debugger to a really simple Node.
js program, and it gives me the state
of the variables that were defined
at when I paused the debugger.
We can actually grab this
local variable state when an
error is thrown, and attach it.
Alongside the stack frame, so
you can see this in production.
And we support this in Sentry for
languages like Python, PHP, and Ruby.
But, for the longest time, we never
really supported this in Node.
js.
Because there was no built
in method to grab this data.
There's no API for this, exposed by the
Node or JavaScript standard libraries.
And this is really important.
a lot of people kept asking for this.
It's very useful to debug
an error in production.
If you know exactly what the
variables were defined as.
But we always kept saying, hey, no,
we can't do it, because it's just
not part of the standard library.
It's not possible within
the JavaScript runtime.
But, a little while ago last year, we
learned that it is actually possible.
We can leverage the same
strategy debuggers use.
and take advantage of the Node.
js inspector standard library.
And so the V8 inspector is built
on top of the kind of, Chrome V8,
debugger, and allows you to access
a lot of information about the Node.
js process, and manipulate
it in ways to get this local
variable information for you.
So it turns out, via this inspector
standard library, with a little bit
of work and massaging the data, you We
can use it in production to grab local
variables and attach them to Node.
js stack traces.
let's walk through some code
to see how this would work.
here, at the start, we can, instantiate
and start, the inspector and open it.
this will start an inspector
process, essentially a debugger
process attached to, your main Node.
js process.
And In order to grab local variables
from the inspector and attach
it to stack traces that then we
send to Sentry for processing, we
need some kind of worker thread.
So here we can spin up a worker,
that really its job is to look
at the inspector, grab the local
variables and put it on, and give
it to the main thread so that it
can be attached to stack traces.
so here is the debugger,
that's being instantiated.
in this debugger, we listen on a
couple of events, which are exposed
from the inspector standard library.
most notably, whenever an
exception is thrown, it varies
if it's caught or uncaught, we
pause the debugger and handle it.
So essentially what we're doing is, When
an error is thrown in your main Node.
js process, we pause it, grab the
application state, the local variables,
attach it somewhere, and then resume it.
And, although it can be weird, you're
actually pausing the process, it's
actually not that expensive to do this.
here's what happens when
we're actually pausing.
So an error is thrown, the debugger,
via the inspector, pauses the main
process, We, and this is simplified.
There's a lot of edge cases that
you normally have to deal with.
But what we're doing here is,
going through making sure that,
it's a valid error reason.
And then we take a look at the
frames of a stack trace in an error.
Kind of grabbing all of the local
variables for each frame and then
attaching it to that associated frame.
This is actually super powerful because it
means we can access the local variables.
Not just of the topmost frame in
the error, but all of the frames
wherever they're applicable.
We then can use this inspector API
to essentially call a fake function
that will assign these frames and
their associated local variables to
a global variable that then the main
process can then use later on when it's
actually sending an error to Sentry.
we have to make sure we release
the object, otherwise, there
would be memory allocation issues.
what does getLocalVariables exactly do?
It essentially uses, this runtime.
getProperties method to be able to get the
local variables via the inspector, we then
have to massage the data a little bit.
So to make sure that we deal with
objects or arrays or similar, but really
we're relying mostly on the inspector
to do the heavy lifting for us here.
So after we've written the local variables
to an object and then the process resumes,
the error is captured by the sentry SDK.
Okay.
and then transformed into an error
event that can be sent to Sentry.
what Sentry then does is it can look up
on the error in this global here, and
see, oh, were there local variables,
and if they were, attach them to the
outgoing error event accordingly.
And, This all seems pretty complicated
because you have to instantiate
a worker, start the inspector,
set up all these processes.
But to a user who wants to start
using this today in Sentry for Node.
js, they simply just have to add
include local variables true to their
initialization and this all works for you.
And here's what this would look like.
So this is an example.
Express app where I just threw a bunch
of, I just threw an error with a bunch
of local variables in scope, and you can
see them directly attached to the event.
Super powerful because now you know
exactly what lines of code, plus what the
variable state was when an error happened,
so you can debug things even faster.
while we were implementing this, there
were a lot of challenges to work through.
we had problems with worker overhead.
Of course, we were instantiating
a new worker process and we were
instantiating this inspector instance.
So we really had to make sure that the,
memory and CPU levels were manageable.
as we were, Writing things into
the main process and pausing stuff.
We also had to deal with memory pressure.
unhandled exceptions was
also something to deal with.
There's different kind of behavior
for pausing the debugger between
handled versus unhandled exceptions.
So calling new.
error and explicitly handling that
versus, throwing an error and letting it
bubble up to the global error handlers.
ESM versus CJS actually is still a
problem that we're struggling with.
They have, both have different
behaviors and there's actually an
active bug in ESM where, this doesn't
work or local variable support doesn't
work perfectly because of a Node.
js bug.
Currently, the local variables, setup
does not support minified variables.
So if you have some kind of build
process, like transforming from
TypeScript to JavaScript, and then you
also minify, let's say because you're
deploying to a Lambda or something.
currently we don't support this,
but the SourceMap spec is taking
a look at how they can adopt
Minified variables and minified
local state and source mapping that.
And so whenever that, is introduced
into the source map spec, we
can take advantage of that.
If you are using this strategy, local
variables, it obviously will, it's
using a debugger inspector instance.
So if you try to use your own to
debug process, it doesn't work.
So you have to use one or the other.
And, unfortunately, because we're
relying on this V8 inspector
and the Node standard library,
Currently, this only works for Node.
js, so if you wanted similar support
in the browser or for runtimes like
Bunn or Deno, it doesn't work, but
we're always open for ideas to see if
we can make that work for those other.
JavaScript runtimes and that's it.
Thank you so much for listening
in on how local variables
really help with debugging, your
production, JavaScript stack traces.
Hopefully you learned a little, if
you want to see the example code that
was shown off and how this is written.
There's a ton of edge cases,
again, that we have to think about.
this is all available in our
open source JavaScript SDKs,
linked at the very bottom.
I have some links that you can reach
out to me, if you have any questions.
Otherwise, if you're interested in trying
out Sentry and seeing how these local
variables work, you can scan that QR code
and use the code below to get started.
Thank you.