Hello, my name is Gabriel Schulhoff, and
I'll be talking about how we improved
the performance of resolvers at auction.
com's subscription service.
The problem we faced was that, in
the course of operations, the Node.
js process would, reach its heap limit.
so the heap is a data structure that
the JavaScript engine maintains.
and it imposes a limit on it, which
can be configured, but of course you
cannot use an infinite amount of heap.
So we have it configured to two gigs
or so, and it was reaching that limit.
And, that was a problem.
So this is the story of how we
tried different things and we
managed to knock it down a bit.
So the background, at auction.
com, we have a GraphQL service
that serves pretty much.
Like 85 percent of the client's needs.
There are a few places where,
clients issue requests to services
other than graph, but 85 percent
of the time it goes to graph and
we have request response type.
operations with Graphen.
We also have WebSockets,
which serve subscriptions.
The subscriptions themselves,
are mostly not all of them.
some subscriptions, have different
content, but most of them are
basically, rebroadcast Kafka
messages coming from the background.
And for those messages, we perform some
transformations and then we send them to
Redis and if Redis decides that we have
subscribers, then it sends it back to us.
And the reason for that is obviously
because we have multiple pods in, Redis.
in production and the Kafka sends the
message to only one of those pods.
And so if that pod happens not to have
any subscribers for that particular
message, but some other pod does,
then we need Redis to regulate this.
to reproduce this out of memory
condition or rather to investigate Ways
of, reducing memory consumption and,
just improving performance in general.
what I did was to set
everything up locally on my Mac.
Namely, I ran a broker locally, I
ran graph locally, I connected 4,
000 WebSockets locally, and then
I used KCAD to basically flood,
the graph with Kafka messages.
There was only one message, but.
just sent it repeatedly and see
what, see where it gets hung up
and what uses all that memory.
All right.
So this is what I measured at first.
When I first tried this, I broke down the
measurement into three different phases.
The first one is just like run graph.
And that's it, just node and graph,
no sockets, no activity, nothing.
Then, in the second phase, I connected
4, 000 sockets, and you can see that
the memory consumption increased.
And then leveled off to
accommodate 4, 000 idle sockets.
so this is the overhead of
maintaining 4, 000 sockets.
And then two minutes later, I started
sending messages for the next four minutes
and measured how many messages, were,
received or it was able to receive and
how many messages it was able to send out.
And these are the results.
It's not very good.
16 Kafka messages in four minutes.
That's not very good.
That's 15 seconds processing
a single message and sending
it out to 4, 000 clients.
We need to do better.
And so what did we do to make
things better, both memory
wise and, performance wise?
So memory wise, the first
thing that we noticed was that,
this being GraphQL, right?
Answering, the subscription
with a single, response means
executing GraphQL, GraphQL, right?
Performing a GraphQL execution.
Now, every GraphQL execution
has an associated context.
The context is there to store the
information that it, that pertains
to that particular execution.
And in the case of subscriptions, repeated
executions, but either way that it's
particular to the one connection, right?
And one of the things that, GraphQL
sometimes does is, it starts out with
a certain object received by some
means, in this case, Kafka, and if the
subscription specifies that, it needs
certain fields that cannot be found
on that object, but for which there
is a resolver, meaning that GraphQL is
aware of a solution for providing those
fields, even without, even though they
are not on the original backend object.
Then, it will reach out to backends
and it, which are pre configured
to provide that information.
Then it massages that information
and then returns the result
and the client is happy.
we have 32 different backends at auction.
Each backend has, five different,
methods being HTTP and all.
and so we have these wrappers on the
context for reaching out to the backends.
basically the, it looks like this.
so we have a backends object, which
encapsulates all our backends.
And then we, for each backend, we
have it by name and then by method.
And We construct this path
whenever we construct the context.
So every context has 160 objects on it.
And that's a problem because we have 4,
000 contexts coexisting right in our test.
And each one has 160 objects.
That's a lot of objects.
And chances are that, any one,
response isn't going to cause.
the executor to access every single
method on every single backend.
Quite the contrary.
It's usually five, six accesses.
if it's any more than that, then you need
to worry about, Oh, is it N plus one?
am I causing too much traffic?
So either way, you're not
going to need 160 objects.
okay.
what to do?
let's make it lazy.
Why not?
JavaScript has this wonderful
thing called a proxy object.
Which basically is an object that pretends
to have any number of, of, fields set.
But it doesn't really have them set
because what it means for a field,
what it means to retrieve a field
is up to a certain callback, right?
Instead of just being like a property
access, it's actually a function
invocation where it's given the name
of the property and the function
can decide what to do about the fact
that somebody wants that property.
And so you don't necessarily need
to store all possible values.
And that's exactly what we did.
when somebody asks for, UAA.
And they ask for post and we
create the UAA backend on the
fly as they are asking for it.
And then we create the wrapper for the
post method as they are asking for it.
And it's not as if we're delaying
the response by this because we
would have created these things
anyway, when the execution happened.
So the response is not going to be slower.
In fact, it's going to be faster
because we're not creating 160 of these.
We're only creating maybe
a total of four or five.
So we're saving time.
We're saying we're saving memory.
Now let's see what this got us.
turns out that the improvements here are
in terms of throughput, aren't that great.
So there's probably another bottleneck
somewhere, creating 160 objects was not
that expensive in terms of execution time.
But it was pretty expensive
in terms of memory.
Like you can see that we
lowered the plateau here.
because, the, these contexts,
which were causing this rise are
now causing a lower rise because,
we're not creating any, backends.
And in fact, for this
particular subscription, It
doesn't take any backends.
You'll see later.
All it does is basically take the
object that comes in over Kafka and
transforms the keys and that's it.
And then it sends it out.
It doesn't need any backends.
so then, okay, this is maybe a
little optimistic because it's like
maximally reduced, but it doesn't
matter because it's going to be
reduced in pretty much all cases.
All right.
So what else can we do?
We've lowered memory consumption.
Sure.
But can we do more, lower
it in different ways?
So one of the things that, we explored
was, If we make the execution more
efficient, then maybe the memory usage
is going to go down because we're
using, more modern, style code that,
that doesn't require so much support
from the engine might even be leaner.
it might be optimized, whereas
the old code was not optimized.
And so it doesn't need to
create so many temporary objects
to address, the execution.
and so in this particular case,
we have this one function called
convert obj to snake keys.
I told you earlier that,
that we have objects that.
That look like this when they
come in from, Kafka and we need to
convert them basically because our
convention is that GraphQL fields,
output fields are snake case.
So we have this thing that converts
a deep object to snake case.
and that function.
What's using low dash a lot because
it's an old function that nobody has
really touched because it works just
fine And back in those days there was
no like map there was no object entries
that kind of thing so okay, so let's
see if we can speed things up, right?
let's replace all these calls to
load dash and let's use some of the
stuff that the engine has locally and
natively, to accomplish the same thing.
And so we made, we transformed
the code like this.
And the result was that performance
was back into the positives relative
to that 16 message baseline that I
showed you on one of the first slides.
we retained a little bit of a lowered
plateau here because we're still not.
So we're not doing any of those contacts,
but because we're doing more work,
memory consumption in the busy case
has actually resumed where it was.
It's a little tiny bit lower,
but not as much as we'd like.
All right.
Let's see what else we can do.
So I told you that we're using Redis
because we have a situation where we
have multiple graph pods like this,
and they're declared as a single
consumer group by Kafka, meaning
Kafka will partition messages that
are addressed to the consumer group
among the members of the group.
And so let's say, if, If G2 retrieves,
receives the green message, then
G2 can satisfy, C4 and C5 because
they request the green message.
But how can C2 be satisfied?
C2, G1 never got the green
message and yet somehow it still
has to send it to C2, right?
So the way we reconcile that is
we send all the messages to Redis.
And then Redis is does G1 have a
subscriber for, this green message?
Oh yeah, they do.
Okay.
Then I better forward it.
So Redis doesn't just blindly
forward everything to everyone
because then we could just get rid
of Redis entirely and just declare
every graph instance to be its own
consumer group, but it does filter.
And so it does reduce traffic versus
just like the Christmas tree case.
while at the same time, allowing this.
this, GRAF service to appear to be
like a unified service rather than,
being able to tell, Oh, I'm con I
must be connected to pod number two
because I can't see this and that.
So it, it ensures correctness.
It reduces traffic.
and so that's why we use it.
And I figured, okay.
GRAFQL subs GraphQL Redis subscriptions.
It does a lot of, serializing,
deserializing a lot of streaming.
And so So, can we improve
it just by upgrading it?
maybe, folks upstream, doing wonderful
open source work have realized
that there are better ways of doing
what they're already doing without
actually breaking compatibility.
So we upgraded it and no, not quite.
it's okay.
it's worth a shot.
It was worth a shot.
the plateau remains.
This memory consumption,
is pretty much the same.
Performance improved a little bit.
but not spectacularly.
okay.
We tried it.
At least now we have the
latest and greatest GraphQL
Redis subscriptions, right?
Or we did at the time
and that can never hurt.
so then let's see, can we do more
to improve this wonderful, convert
object to snake keys function?
can we make it leaner?
Because to be honest, I keep
coming back to this function
because, I was running node clinic.
on the whole workload, just to see
what it is that's holding up the show.
why is it performing so poorly
with the sort of quote unquote
on ulterior motive to actually
try to reduce memory consumption.
node clinic is not a
memory consumption tool.
It's a, it's an execution
time measuring tool.
It's a flame graph for execution time.
Where is your.
app spending most of its time,
that's the question that it answers.
And time and again, when I ran it, it
came back with convert apps to snake key.
So I'm like, okay, fine.
let's get that off the way.
And so I went back and, was thinking to
myself, we have objects like these, right?
And we're converting them, to Snakey.
So we're not touching the values at all,
unless the value is an object or an array.
And so it's a deep thing and
we recurse, but otherwise we're
not touching the values at all.
we're just touching the
keys all the time, right?
we are a company, we do
stuff with data, right?
Like every other company
that does stuff with data.
And so the data in this case
is key value pairs, right?
And, the keys can refer to all kinds of
like business related things, You can
see right here, for example, fallout
history and, is auction status change.
it's business related stuff, right?
But these words, these are keywords.
These are like variables that
programmers use, to get the data
at that particular location.
And so, these names, they're
not generated automatically.
we agree on them and then we use them,
So in terms of, processing them, into
snake keys, once, once I've read days
on market and I've turned it into snake
keys, and this is what it looks like.
The next time I encountered this
days on market thing, and I need to
turn it into snake case, why do I
need to run that computation again?
I already know how to do it.
I've done it once, right?
So why don't I just record the result
and then not do it the second time?
This is called memorization, right?
and that's exactly where
this is going, right?
just memoize everything.
And then, no matter where you find a
key named external identifiers, you,
you've already done it and that's it.
Then you just look up
the result and reuse it.
So that's what we did here.
We memoized it.
It's, it was a super simple change,
like literally just like practically
two lines, like one, one addition
and one replacement, and that's it.
The rest is just like gravy.
And, Incredibly performance
went from up 20 percent versus
the original baseline to up.
331%, 0.
3.
Okay.
So that was a huge improvement.
and you can see here the curve that, you
can see that it's not struggling so much
to, to deliver these messages because it's
the new curve is like the old curve, but.
And many people are facing that
issue of doing transcripts as well.
And so what we've seen, the problem
with the, and during the process
of delivering those transcripts, we
actually see some errors, a lot of
typo errors, a lot of typos, some
sheets are missing or something,
A plateau, because it's more flat.
And if the height of the plateau
goes down, okay, then we've
improved something across the board
in terms of memory consumption.
Whereas here it's very difficult to
judge, because we don't have a plateau
that we could systematically lower
and observe that it's being lowered.
All right.
So let's see, what did we do next?
okay, we can't, we step back
a little bit and we're like,
okay, so these pods are dying.
Okay.
That's the fundamental problem.
that's what got us started
on this whole process.
So let's see if we can
spread out the load.
we see that the memory
is rising precipitously.
Because, of some activity that is
causing that, that is completely
valid business activity.
And, it's not able to keep up.
okay, let's quickly add more
pods and then maybe now then
it's going to be able to keep up.
And so we did, we keyed the
upscaling on memory consumption
and equally the downscaling.
And, it was okay.
Um, it handled it a little bit better.
Restarts went down a little
bit, nothing spectacular.
so then, okay.
what else can we do about, by the
way, aside from this precipitous
increase and so forth, we also
had a slow memory leak that would
accumulate over like days on end.
And so we also had to address that.
And, the way we did that
is drum roll, please.
just restarted every night.
Cause like we couldn't figure out where
the leak was coming from, it doesn't
matter you, this is a perfectly valid
way of handling it because nobody's
watching their web sockets at like 2 AM.
So why not restart the service?
And besides you, there are
no auctions going on at 2 AM.
Everybody's practically
asleep all over the U S.
And our clients, the, not the people,
but the apps that they use and, the
website that they use, those clients
are designed to reconnect very quickly.
So within a matter of seconds,
they, they would reconnect their web
sockets and continue to get data.
So yeah, we quote unquote addressed
this particular memory leak anyway.
so back to the quest of lowering
memory consumption, one of
the things that I didn't.
I'm going to add in my background
slide is that, the way we deploy
graph is we do a bunch of like
transformations on the source code, right?
Like we, we have TypeScript in there.
So of course we compile that to,
or transpile that to JavaScript.
But we also have this legacy sort of
bundling system that is basically designed
for clients, but that we also use on
the server, which just puts everything
through Babel and generates this one
big file that is the entire server.
And.
that, that the configuration of that
process was such that there, it made no
distinction between whether it creates
a client bundle or a server bundle.
And with this optimization mindset, I went
in there and I was like, okay, so let's
introduce such a distinction because, the
client bundle has to address all kinds of
browsers with all kinds of capabilities
and legacy browsers and all that.
And so it needs to be bulletproof and be
able to function in no matter what level
of ECMA script is running on that browser,
but that's not true for the server, right?
Node.
js, we know exactly what version of Node.
js we're going to have, 20 in this case,
and so the translation algorithm might
as well target that version and leave a
lot of the native stuff in place instead
of replacing it with polyfills, right?
Unnecessarily in this case.
So we did that and you can see that
the curve has gotten a lot flatter.
if you look at this one, the peaks
and the valleys are a lot smaller,
we've improved things a little bit and
the performance went up by another 0.
3 X, right?
We're at 3.
6 X now versus the original.
okay.
it's good.
Memory consumption is a
little more predictable.
Performance is slightly up.
Can't complain.
Except of course that we haven't
really lowered this plateau.
It's still, hovering
around just above one gig.
okay.
Let's see.
What else?
What else can we do?
Okay.
So back to optimizing this guy.
And, If you remember the code, we
had a bunch of like object entries
and object from entries and map
in there and that generates a
lot of temporary objects, right?
because, object entries converts an object
to a map, to, to an array, and then from
entries converts that array back to a map.
An object, and that creates a new object.
Then you have the old
object in the new object.
You have this array,
which then gets destroyed.
Same thing with map.
It creates a new array and
destroys the old array.
why don't, why do we do that?
why don't we just do things
in place whenever we can.
So for objects, it's difficult to do
things in place because with objects.
You would have to replace the keys.
and that's really difficult to do.
Cause you have to insert a new key,
which is snake case, delete the old
key, which is, camel case and so forth.
It's much easier to just create an
empty object, fill it in with the
converted keys, And then return that.
And then that is the object.
So okay, yes, we're creating a new object.
But in the case of an array, we
can completely save ourselves that
because we're not touching the keys.
We're only touching the values, right?
So just replace the values with the
snake case ified version of themselves.
And that's it.
And you can still use that same array.
And so when we deployed this, lo
and behold, performance went from 3.
6x to 6.
3x.
So we tripled performance again.
memory consumption is very
nice and flat now, but it's
still hovering at around a gig.
Okay.
all So then break out the
big guns, so to speak.
this is Chrome DevTools, the memory
tab, as you can see, because we're
looking at memory consumption and it
has this wonderful feature called a heap
snapshot that you can use with Node.
js.
Now a heap snapshot will basically, as
you might think, as you might imagine,
it'll take a snapshot of the heap, i.
e.
it'll tell you all the objects that are
on the heap at that time, by their type.
And then, one of the best features here,
of this tool is not only that it can
take these snapshots, but if you take two
of them of the same process, earlier in
the process, later in the process, then,
you can actually get, the difference.
Like what have I created
since my last snapshot?
What have I destroyed
And so of course you, you'd
want either zero or lots of
negatives, but unfortunately,
that's not what we were seeing.
We took a snapshot at the point where
the 4, 000 sockets were there, but idle.
And then we took another snapshot.
I'm sorry.
We took a, the first snapshot
is where everything is idle.
Node.
js is just sitting there
doing absolutely nothing.
The second snapshot is after, the
sockets were connected, but before
there were any messages coming through.
And the difference is, for example,
among other things that some more
recognizable things is that there
are 261, 968 location objects.
Now, what is a location object and
why do we have so many of them?
it turns out the location object is
an artifact that is created whenever,
an incoming request, such as a
subscription is processed by GraphQL.
It creates a syntax tree for it, an
AST, and unless you ask otherwise,
it will attach to each AST node,
it will attach the location of that
node in the original source codes,
so row five, column 29, that's where
something starts, some kind of token.
And that token is stored in an
object in the AST, and associated
to that token is a location object
that will allow you to go to that
location and do something interesting.
we're worried about,
answering these queries.
We're worried about giving
responses to these queries.
We don't actually care where in the
query string, something is located.
So we don't need these locations at all.
And we configured the parser.
We kind of monkey patched it at
first, but then we found better ways.
We configured it so that, we actually
had to reach into subscriptions,
transport WS at first and basically
just tell it, okay, please don't.
And I can do the same thing with a std.
So I can then say, oh,
where can I convert it?
Or I can give it a
transcription, a transaction.
I can give it a
And that's basically the kind of
thing that we're going to be doing.
And what I mean by that is I'm not going
to be converting that logic into, say,
a translation disk, but I'm going to
be converting it into a transcription
of some sort of, a state definition.
it didn't take very long to get
through the one gig barrier.
Whereas now it barely makes it to one gig.
we got some performance in terms
of memory consumption reduction.
Great.
And the execution performance
hasn't really decreased.
it's pretty good.
In fact, If I think about it,
it's actually gone up from 5.
So, not so bad.
but is there anything else we can do?
let's see how low we can go, all So
the next thing we did was we went
back to the context and we're like,
okay, can we lower this plateau a
little more like in the idle case?
Because if it's low in the idle.
It's going to be proportionally
lower in the case of execution,
or at least most of the time.
we realized that in addition to backends,
the other thing on our context is
something called data loaders and primers.
So a data loader is basically just a kind
of a backend where, you ask it for a bunch
of things and you ask it one at a time.
And it pretends to answer right away.
But really, one of its most important
features is that it batches those
requests and then it issues a single
backend call saying, give me all of
these things, if the backend is capable.
And then when the backend responds, it
doles out the various objects that it was
requested to, to provide as they come in.
And so it's a great tool for
avoiding N plus one situations.
And we have lots of them.
Like we, we load, we use data
loaders for lots of different things.
and we have 50 of them and primers,
which prime the data loaders when
the execution knows that it's going
to subsequently need that data.
of those we have even more.
and we store them all like this.
the name of the loader and then the
function that creates the loader,
then the name of the loader and the
function that creates the loader.
and the result of these function
calls is always an object.
And so again, we were in the same
situation as with backends, where
we were creating like hundreds of
these objects, if not thousands,
for the data loaders, and for the
primers for every single context.
But unlike the backends, this required
a little more subtle solution to, to
transform into a lazy object because,
it's a much bigger sort of object
and it's constructed statically.
So the backends, they're actually
constructed in a loop, but this
object is literally just a big
giant object literal declaration.
And so we didn't want to turn
this into like complicated code
that looks like this, right?
while at the same time, wanting
that, that laziness about it
so that we might save memory.
And so what we did since we're,
since, as I explained earlier, we run
through these build steps to convert
things and run Babel on them and so
forth until it's just one big file.
Babel has these things called plugins.
So why don't we make a that takes one
of these objects and turns it into.
In the end, the output of the
package starts from the statement,
which is something like this,
which is the name of the parameter,
which is the name of the function,
which is the name of the function.
This is the number, which is the
value of this specific function.
So it's basically the
name of the function.
Every function that you have in the
database, and the name of the function,
which are actually one of the properties
in this object is actually primers,
which itself is a, lazy object.
So it gets complicated quickly.
And so better, better to
use that Babel plugin.
And so the Babel plugin works like this.
It looks for instances of proxy.
lazy in the code.
which, proxy is a perfectly valid,
JavaScript or ECMA script, specified,
global, but that global doesn't
have a static function called lazy.
That's fictitious that we
invented that function, right?
But with Babel, that can be turned into
quote unquote, a real function by virtue
of the fact that, we create code to
satisfy this and to turn this into an
object literal, that is really a proxy.
so that's basically our excuse
is to find this word lazy here.
And so that's our hook actually.
And okay.
So then that turns the code into something
like this, where if you're asking for
key one, then you call function one,
if you're asking for key two, you call
function two, but you also memoize, right?
So originally.
You have all the keys because
the object still has to look
like it has all the keys, right?
But each key has only like this the
symbol assigned to it, which is one
symbol that is getting reused for all
keys Instead of having one symbol per key
that's a big savings while not affecting
the look and feel of the object And
then when, you want one of these data
loaders, then you just ask for the key.
It checks, Oh, geez, the key is a, is one
of these symbols, then I better create it.
So it creates it and then it
replaces the symbol with the
result of the function call, i.
e.
memorization.
and that's it.
And let's see what ha what
happened when we did that.
we did another thing first too.
we introduced a query cache.
Because, we didn't want to have 4,
000 copies of an AST if we could
avoid it, why not just have one copy?
And we also added, JITing, which
basically creates a function for every,
document, every AST that comes in.
It creates a function, which when
called will have exactly the same
effect as if you had called execute
with that particular AST only this
being a single JavaScript function,
created from like a string that happens
to be valid JavaScript, that is very
carefully constructed to, to execute.
the JavaScript engine can optimize that
it can actually turn it into native code.
So it really has a very good chance of
being running as native code rather than,
lots of interpretations and then jumping
around on the AST and all that stuff.
So what we did was, okay, we introduced
a cache when the query comes in and we
parse it, we create this compilation
artifact for it And then when it's
time to execute the query, we grab
the compilation artifact from the AST
upon which we stored it during parse.
And, if for some reason during parse,
the creation of the compilation
artifact failed, no big deal.
We'll just go back and run the
query the old fashioned way.
Otherwise we'll run a
JIT and it'll be faster.
So with these two things put
together, this is what we achieved.
So we went from this guy to this guy.
Again, perfect memory savings, right?
The, this plateau genuinely got lower.
and look at the difference between
the original plateau and this plateau.
Like it, it's substantially less.
Like we went from 600 megs to 300 megs.
we have the idle consumption.
performance unaffected
essentially and much lower memory.
we got some ways towards our goal and
that's, the scope of this presentation.
things have happened since then.
And, one of the future directions here
was to upgrade packages and believe
it or not, that actually solved the
problem for us because it turns out
that we did have a package in the
mix in, in, in our supply chain that
was basically, wasteful with memory.
And then after switching to yarn
four, whereupon we upgraded all our
dependencies, that package either
got, shoved aside because some of the
package got hoisted instead, or some of
the version of the package got hoisted
instead, either way, Yarn 4 got rid of
a lot of our, duplicate dependencies in
terms of same package, different versions,
and somehow a newer version ended up and.
it solved the problem.
But that doesn't mean that these
future directions for any sort
of, memory consumption reduction
aren't a good idea, right?
So using heap diffs, see
what else we can shave off.
We could still, just because
a problem doesn't happen
anymore, we don't have restarts.
That doesn't mean that, you
can't improve memory consumption.
It's never a bad idea.
Promise objects.
Okay.
I didn't really cover this in this
talk, but basically we found that.
if you treat promises and primitives,
equally, then you're going to end up
with a lot of extra code that, that
gets executed, and a lot of memory
because all these promise objects
need to live somewhere that, that
gets used that doesn't need to.
So for example, if you
have something like.
Await function call, and that
function call returns something,
anything other than a promise.
If it returns a number five, then you
don't want to await that function call.
You only want to call a wait on a
function or dot then or whatever.
If you can be absolutely a
hundred percent sure that function
is going to return a promise.
If not, then just call it directly.
Don't use await because that creates like
three promises every time you use await.
so that, that will save you memory
and it'll save you execution time.
Upgrading packages, like I
said, That did it for us.
And, this is still good.
creating a realistic subscriptions
load test, not just one
message, have multiple messages.
So you have some heterogeneity,
in your workload.
yeah, we can still do these things,
but of course the impetus now is
a lot less than it used to be.
so these are some of the
insights that we gained.
choose very carefully what
you attach to your context.
That's never a bad idea.
keep your context lean.
and by the way, some of these insights,
they apply to request response graph
as well, not just to subscriptions.
Like the fact that we made all these
things lazy, reduce memory consumption
on the request response side as
well, not just the WebSocket side.
So it's generally not a bad idea to, to
have a lean context for graph execution.
then, Execution efficiency
and memory usage efficiency
are not entirely orthogonal.
Like we saw, we improved execution
efficiency and memory consumption
actually went up instead of
stay, staying where it was.
so yeah, they're not, yeah,
they're not independent.
they are related, which can be related
in a positive way or a negative way.
So improving execution efficiency is never
a bad idea, but if it kills your memory
consumption, then, you might want to think
twice about it or find out why, of course.
Yeah.
node clinic I mentioned earlier, it's
great for improving execution efficiency.
And as a result of the previous statement,
maybe memory consumption, efficiency,
but definitely execution efficiency.
it, it does a great job showing you,
okay, there's a huge plateau here.
You keep calling this function.
Why?
Stop calling it or,
make it more efficient.
It really points squarely at the culprit.
and then heap snapshots
came in very handy.
especially the differential ones, because,
they pointed squarely at the thing that
you could remove, we don't need this.
Goodbye.
it's a great tool for that.
All right.
That concludes my presentation.
If you have any questions, I think we have
a means of answering them, but, either
way, thank you so much for your attention.