Hello everyone, this is Praveen.
Today my topic of discussion is how
artificial intelligence and machine
learning are creating transformative
impact in the life and nanotech space
and how these life insurance companies
are using these two advanced technologies
in predicting consumer behavior.
And also using different data
and doing consumer analysis.
So without any further delay, let's
get started So first, let's talk about
what is life and annuities industry
So the life and annuities industry
is a significant component of the u.
s economy and also the u.
s financial sector Which actually provides
long term risk management services and
also investment options to the consumers
So in this way, the consumers can actually
invest their own money into these life
insurance policies or different indexes.
And after a certain period of
time, they get investment returns.
Which in turn they can
plan for different reasons.
It might be retirement or it might be
For some college tuition expenses for
the decades or for a different set of
reasons So they have different plans
which are actually sponsored by these
life insurance companies And the consumers
can actually invest their money Spying
these policies and investing into
stocks and indexes which are tied to
this particular policies what are the
critical areas of a life and energy space?
So there are two different areas, which
are very critical in terms of Directly
impacting the operational efficiency
and customer loyalty of a particular
process in a life insurance company So
the first day is the claims processing.
The second day is the customer experience.
So these two are the two critical
areas which have a direct impact on
the operational efficiency and customer
loyalty of a particular life and entities
carrier or life insurance company, within
the U S so our next topic is, what is
the role of artificial intelligence and
machine learning in modernizing insurance?
So artificial intelligence and machine
learning are reshaping the L& A space.
by automating so much of, repetitive
tasks, which requires human interactions
in the day to day operational
processing of different patterns
of data and predictive analytics.
So by using of AI and ML, we are
having to achieve an operational
efficiency by automating so
much of tasks, which actually.
It helps these industries in
optimizing the process, removing
any manual and human intervention.
And also it also helps in detecting
anomalies and analyzing customer behavior.
So this is, this actually will
cause, a different approach of
how we have the perspective of
looking at particular things, right?
So by introduction of
these two technologies.
The shift is changing from
being a reactive process, right?
Instead of being respond, instead of
responding to something will be turned
on the proactive mode of management,
which is basically it enables a more
responsive insurance model and these
two advanced technologies, which is
artificial intelligence and machine
learning also helps insurers and.
to optimize their operations and
create personalized user experience,
thereby enhancing both efficiency
and customer satisfaction.
let's take a case of claims
processing wherein we used artificial
intelligence and machine learning
to do automation and efficiency.
there are different tasks or
there are different steps in the
claims management process, right?
once after you get a claim, you
are, you have to, Go through a
lot of documentation, which is
received on the claim, right?
And you have to review the documentation
for accuracy You have to review the
documentation to see if there is any
fraud involved and you also need to
do a different types of data analysis
and Check to make sure that whatever
information is received on a claim is
correct before it is processed, right?
So all these different steps, right the
step one is basically We can automate
all these four different steps of
claims processing using artificial
intelligence and machine learning.
So first, the first step is we
can actually automate the whole
document handling, meaning the AI
will actually extract and processes
information from claims documents,
which will actually reduce the,
excuse me, the manual data entry.
The second step is anomaly detection.
So the machine learning models Are
very efficient in identifying patterns
that may indicate that if it is a
fraudulent claim or it's actually a
genuine claim, if it's a fraud fraudulent
claim, then it allows insurance
companies to take early intervention
steps from being from the claim being
processed and the money going out of
the door and then predictive analytics.
So artificial intelligence also
predicts claims resolution times, right?
Because we have different
requirements For different states
and how we process these claims.
So by using the automation and AI We can
make sure that all these requirements
are met enabling efficient allocation
of claims processing within a stipulated
period of time thereby increasing consumer
satisfaction and then the impact right
the faster the claims resolution is the
lower we have overhead cost or operational
cost because We are if the process is all
automated and then there is also reduced
risk of fraud and you know the And there
is also improved customer experience
because of all the efficiencies which we
gain By using the ai and machine learning
models, you know in the claims processing
for a particular life and energy company
In this way it directly impacts the
consumer satisfaction thereby improving
customer loyalty for a particular company.
Okay, how do we use?
Ai and ml in identifying consumer
behavior analysis, right?
So it is actually used
across four different topics.
One is the data analysis Second is
the proactive engagement And Third is
the personalized offerings and fourth
is the result how do we use the data
what we get from the customer, right?
So the machine learning algorithms
what they do is like they analyze
large data sets to identify What
is the pattern of consumers?
What they are wanting to purchase
the different customer preferences
and the behavior patterns, right?
So this will actually help all the life
and analytic Companies who are using
this machine learning and artificial
intelligent tools to predict consumer
behavior you know, this actually helps
them to tailor insurance products
and Go to market strategies to make
sure that they are meeting individual
customer needs And this also in fact
That turns up into the proactive
engagement of the companies because all
this is predictive analytics, right?
This is all predictive in nature.
So all the insights, what we receive from
the data processing using the algorithms
actually help the insurance companies
anticipate and address potential customer
issues even before they get, escalated.
And as a result of all this,
we see that there is an
increased customer satisfaction.
we have better retention rates and
higher conversion of the personalized
product, offerings from the customers
to the company, ultimately leading
to an increase in sales and customer
loyalty for a particular insurance
company from the customers.
So what are the benefits and challenges
of, Adoption of AI or ML, right?
So the benefits are as we know as
we already spoke about It actually
enhances operational capability.
It improves operational efficiency in a
particular process by automation and the
accuracy of the claims processing and the
fraud detection is also improved because
We are using artificial intelligence
and machine learning In detecting and
reviewing all these incoming documents
and information Thereby if there is any
fraud detected or if there is anomaly,
which is detected We can it gets
reported immediately and the insurance
company can take intervention steps
as a precautionary measure in being
productive in nature rather than being
reactive And it also elevates customer
satisfaction because we are creating
products which are custom made or which
are mostly here Tailored products for
customer needs and behavior patterns.
So these are the main different benefits
what we achieve by using artificial
intelligence and machine learning
and adopting them, in predicting
customer behavior and patterns.
So what are the challenges?
So the data privacy concerns and
compliance with different regulations
is a key challenge because the way we
accept data, the way we gather data,
the way we process data, so these are
all driven by so many regulations.
So we have to make sure that all the data
privacy concerns are up to the mark, and
we are following all the state regulated
or the federal regulated, policies or
standards for the process and gather data.
And it's always a challenge because
whenever we introduce a new technology
in an existing ecosystem, there are
a large legacy systems dependencies,
which we have to take care before we
get introduced to this new technologies.
Because.
The solutioning of these new technologies
and integration with legacy systems might
be a big challenge because there might
be huge chunks of data which are actually
processed through these legacy systems.
And since they are built and these
are age old systems, we have to
make sure that, all these systems
are working from the same component
or the same integration plane.
So that there is smoother
processing of data.
And, as we all know, another big
challenge is finding talent who
can actually support the AI or ML
technologies in this market is a little
bit, challenging because, these are new
technologies and finding resources with
ample experiences who, skilled people.
To develop deploy and manage these
technologies will be a true challenge
let's now look at few industry
case studies So i'll be walking
you guys through a few examples.
The first example is there was this
particular company a which actually
implemented Ai in their claims processing
system and it outrightly You know reduce
the claims processing system by 60 percent
and it also decreased the fraud losses by
30 percent Something similar, excuse me.
Something similar is was used at
company B Where we used machine language
to analyze the customer data and
personalize their offerings resulting
in a 20 percent increase in policy
renewals So the key takeaway here is
these are real world examples, which
are highlighting the importance of
AI and ML You And their potential to
deliver the measurable business outcomes
for a particular insurance company
or a particular insurance carrier So
let's talk about the road map of ai
or ml integration and life insurance.
So before we actually have a
Have an idea of implementing
Artificial intelligence and machine
learning in a particular company.
I would think we need to go through four
different phases So phase one is basically
assessment and strategy development and
Phase two is what I call pilot projects.
Phase three is full scale implementation.
Phase four is continuous optimization.
So in the phase one, we need to identify
what kind of artificial intelligence
and machine learning use cases We
need to implement these models so
that, these are aligned with the
business goals of a particular company.
In the phase two, we might have
to pick a small sample from the
identified use cases across different
capabilities within a company in
order to validate effectiveness.
And, we have to make adjustments because
this is more of a proof of concept
model before we go full scale, right?
So the phase two for me is more of a
proof of concept model, where we have to
pick a particular couple of business use
cases, and then we have to make sure that
we are building the artificial AI or ML
models, and we have to deploy them to see
if it works and if they are aligned with
the business objectives of the company.
So once that POC is successful, then
we move on to phase three, which
is the full scale implementation.
So now the full scale implementation
is going big bang, right?
So we have to roll out the AI
or ML across the organization.
We have to integrate this with different
systems, the core insurance processing
systems, and there's the big part of
the big bang approach or the full scale
implementation is a training aspect of it.
So training the people to use this
AI or ML is a key aspect because even
though we have the systems in place.
If the people or the resources who
are using the systems are not skilled
enough, are not trained enough,
then I think we can't really get the
efficiencies out of these systems.
And the phase four is what we
call as continuous optimization.
So we have to make sure that these
models or the AI or ML models
are trained regularly, refined
regularly, all these algorithms are
clarified and refined regularly.
In that way, it gives us the
scalability to expand the AI or ML.
As technology advances and we gather
more data So these are the four
different steps wherein we integrate
AI or ML in the life insurance company
So what are the future
trends and opportunities?
So I think there are a couple of
topics which are very interesting
here to talk about One is what I
call is conversational AI, right?
So we can leverage AI powered chatbots
for customer services To resolve queries
quickly and efficiently So gone are
those days wherein people have to wait
For the customer, consumer hours, right?
To call into the call center
from nine to five or the regular
business hours today by using AI.
The chatbot is available 24 by 7
and 95 percent of the time all the
questions are answered using the
chatbot and it's very user friendly.
And it's, since it's AI powered, the
customer service factor also increases
because they, all the customers who are
using this chatbots are getting their
answers immediately without having to
actually wait to speak to a person.
And real time risk assessment.
So we can use AI to assess risks on the
fly and adjust the policies dynamically.
Thank you.
And AI underwriting, AI plays a
big part today in automating the
underwriting process, which in turn is
reducing the turnaround times to issue
a particular life insurance policy.
And how can we expand
AI or ML applications?
We can continue to explore new
use cases, such as dynamic pricing
or consumer sentiment analysis
and intelligent automation.
In that way, we can actually predict
consumer behavior and we can create
products which are tailored to
consumer needs and preferences.
So just to conclude about what we have
talked about so far, the artificial
intelligence and machine learning are
in fact creating waves in life and
analytics industry, addressing the
longstanding challenges while creating new
opportunities for growth and innovation.
Especially in the claims processing,
the companies, the life of nanotech
carriers can significantly improve
operational efficiency, they can
reduce the cost and mitigate fraud.
On the other hand, AI and ML's
impact on consumer behavior analysis
is transforming the way insurers
engage with their customers.
By leveraging this advanced data
insights and data analytics.
The companies can gain a deeper
understanding into what the customers
are wanting, what are their preferences
and what are the needs enabling them
to create personalized products.
This proactive approach leads to be better
customer retention, higher satisfaction,
stronger brand loyalty, and also will
place a particular life insurance company
to be the market leader for decades.
thank you for giving me this
opportunity to talk to you guys.
If you have any questions, please
email me on my email address mentioned.
Thank you.