Hey.
Hi people.
Good morning everyone, and
thank you for joining me today.
My name is Linga Ella, and I
am from Fairfield University.
It's pleasure to be here at conference
42 JavaScript 2025 sharing insights
on one of the most transformative
evolutions in in frontend architecture
and how it's fast tracking a
integration in modern web applications.
Over the past few years JavaScript
has become the backbone of
nearly every digital experience.
From the simplest landing page
to complex AI powered platforms.
But as our application has grown so have
the challenges, particularly when it comes
to embedding artificial intelligence in,
into existing and large scale systems.
Today, I will walk you through how
the micro front runs can break those
barriers, helping teams innovate
faster, deploy smarter, and deliver AI
features independently without being
slowed down by monolithic architecture.
Let's go into the first slide.
In today's digital landscape the users
expect applications that are intelligent,
responsive, and constantly evolving.
Whether it's personalization,
predictive analytics are the
nature language chatbots.
AI has become the central to modern user
experiences, but here is the challenge.
Most frontend architectures
weren't designed for this kind
of rapid evolution coming to the
traditional monolithic front ends.
It forces every team to work.
Within the same reliable cycle.
Adding a new AI powered feature often
means touching code basis of a shared
code basis, or retesting the entire
application or regression testing and
waiting for the full scale deployments.
The result, it will slower our
release cycles or break dependencies.
And miss opportunities for innovation.
And as the organizations try
to scale AI capabilities, these
bottlenecks become even more painful.
That's what the micro frontends come in.
Let's go to the next slide.
So here what are the
micro front ends, right?
The micro front ends take inspiration from
microservice revolution on the backend.
Instead of building one massive JavaScript
application, we decompose it into
smaller, independently deployable units,
each owned by specific team or domain.
Think of it as a federation or
self-contained front ends, right?
Each with its own lifecycle technology
choices and release schedules.
Coming to the benefits of
these micro front ends.
They're immediate, right?
So the teams can deploy independently
without waiting for this.
Centralized release.
And developers gain autonomy
focusing deeply on the feature
specific feature areas.
And they have technology freedom.
Let's say if you have to choose between
different frontend frameworks, right?
Such as such as react View,
angular, or whether it is vanilla,
plain vanilla, JavaScript.
You have that freedom Micro frontends
essentially bring modularity and
agility to the frontend world.
And that opens new doors
for the AI integration.
Let's go to next slide.
The AI integration advantages right?
So what are the advantages?
Let's connect the dots here.
When teams are free to develop
and deploy independently, they can
introduce AI capabilities without
touching the core application code.
Let's say for example, a chart
bot it, a chart bot can be,
can deploy conversational AI as
a standalone micro front end.
And a recommendation engine.
A team can integrate personal
personalization independently.
A data analytics team can build
predictive dashboards without
disrupting the other workflows.
So each AI feature can evolve at a, at
its own pace, using their own stack.
And even run experiments in isolation
without affecting the core code base.
This autonomy allows organizations to
deliver ai mul multiple three times
faster, test more variations, and adapt
quickly to what user actually responds to.
That's the beauty of this model.
Faster innovation without
coordination bottlenecks.
And
yeah, this is the real world
impact which I covered earlier.
It's three times faster and the
results speaks for themselves, right?
Like the companies adopting micro
frontend architecture for AI report.
Up to three times faster, the feature
delivery cycles, and they have seen
a 45% increase in the user engagement
driven by rapid a experimentation.
And their AB testing speeds have grown by
nearly 10 times, allowing them to compare
multiple AI variations simultaneously.
When the team no longer waits on each
other experimentation, flourishes, right?
And that's where the AI thrives
here.
Module Federation with Webpac five.
This is how we are going to implement.
This is come coming to
this technical foundation.
Now let's explore how
this works technically.
The foundation of most modern
front-end frameworks setups is module
Federation introduced with Webpac five.
So Module Federation enables
different applications.
Even built with the different
frameworks to share code at runtime.
You can expose a component
from one project and consume it
dynamically from another project
without rebuilding or redeploying.
Here is how the basic flow works, right?
You can configure the Model Federation
plugin and define which module to expose.
And you can expose your AI components.
Say you say recommended recommendation
wi our chart bot consume that module
remotely in another front end.
And and also we can share
common dependencies like reactor
view or, optimize bundle size.
This setup allows truly distributed
development while maintaining
seamless user experience.
This is the edge side
composition techniques coming
to this these techniques.
The next major enable is said composition.
It's a performance focused
approach that assembles micro
frontend at CDN Edge, right?
Traditionally the composition
happens on a client which can
increase initial load time.
But the ED side composition the CDN
stitches together only the necessary.
Microfund for each route.
Whether it's serving a lighter,
faster bundles bundles to
the user this improves time.
Time to interactive enables
independent caching and delivers
an instantly responsive experience
across the distributed networks.
In simpler terms, the user gets
what they need from the nearest edge
node, the movement, they need it.
This will reduce the, bundle size
and make the applications faster.
This is how we do it.
And next step is web
assembly integration for ai.
So coming to this technique one of the
most exciting advances in is how the web
assembly or WASM brings machine learning
directly to the browser by compiling
AI models from frameworks like transfer
flow or pie chart into web assembly.
We can execute interfaces on the
client side, achieving near native
performance as what we do, what
we usually do on the backend side.
This means complex task like predictions,
image classification, or the sentiment
analysis can run instantly without.
Round trips to the server.
And it's not just faster, but
it's also privacy friendly
and cost efficient, right?
Since the sensitive data never leaves
the user device, imagine delivering a
fully functional recommendation engine
directly through a micro front end.
Powered by web assembly
now, the API integration strategies.
So while the web assembly handles local
local inference, most AI systems still
rely on a PA for deeper intelligence.
And micro frontend can integrate
these APIs independently allowing
fine grain control and versioning.
We we typically see two major patterns.
One is the rest, API integration.
Another one is GraphQL Federation.
Coming to this a rest API integration.
We have standard HT DP endpoint that each
micro function manages independently.
Teams can evolve their AI services,
update models or handle retrieve
without affecting the other services.
And coming to this GraphQL Federation
where multiple micro front ends.
Contribute subgraphs for
to form a unified schema.
This enables type safe queries that
span multiple AI services without
precision reducing network overhead.
Together these patterns make AI
communication modular and scalable.
It just like the architecture itself.
And next step is state
management across front ends.
This is one of the most important
pieces in the front end architecture.
So here one of the biggest
concern is distributed front ends
in state is state managements.
And, how do we maintain consistency
when multiple micro frontends
share the same or user context?
So the solution lies in layered approach.
Let's say we can keep local state within
each micro frontend whenever possible.
Or for shared state, we can use custom
events or the lightweight shared store.
Are, maintain consistent UI
updates through optimistic
rendering patterns, right?
And this approach allows each component
to remain isolated, yet responsible to
global events, maintaining a seamless
user experience, even as the AI features
are dynamically loaded or replaced.
Coming to the performance optimization
techniques eventually the build size
we are trying to reduce the build
size by decoupling the monolithic
application into micro front ends.
And then also we can we don't have to
load everything at once in the front
end that makes the browser slower.
So we have four techniques consist
consistently deliver results.
So the first one is the lazy loading A
components dynamically import features on
demand to mini minimize the initial load.
And efficient resource sharing.
So we, if you have common components or
dependencies, we can reuse them to prevent
the code duplication and advanced caching.
So use service workers to
cache the API responses are
predictions intelligently, right?
The next one is serverless deployments.
Deploy via the edge networks
and JavaScript run times
for global reach, right?
And with all these techniques
together, these strategies keep the
distributed front ends performing
like the single cohesive application.
It'll be smooth, fast, and reliable.
This is the implementation roadmap.
So now that's, we have
covered the what and the how.
Let's look into the
implementation journey, right?
So assess your current architecture.
So identify monolithic pain
points, especially where the
AI integration is blocked.
Define clear boundaries like organize
around business domains ensuring
each team owns a meaningful slice of
functionality, let's say features, right?
Implement module federation set
up shade, dependency management,
and deployment pipelines.
Integrate your first AI feature.
The key here is start small, maybe a chart
bot or a analytics widget, and use it as
a proof of concept scale and optimize.
Gradually once once you get a taste of
it, then you can gradually expand, measure
performance, and it rate continuously.
Here the key is to start small,
learn fast, and scale confidently.
These are the key takeaways.
To summarize micro front ends
fundamentally change how we approach
AI integration in modern web apps.
They remove independent bottlenecks,
allowing the teams to deliver a
capabilities rapidly and independently.
They empower specialized teams to
experiment, iterate, and innovate
without waiting on centralized approvals.
And with technologies like module
Federation and edge side composition
and web assembly, they deliver
exceptional performances and flexibility.
Whether you, your tech stack is react,
view, angular, or plain JavaScript, these
strategies can transform your architecture
and accelerate your AI roadmap.
I am experimenting with these technologies
to create an e-commerce application,
which will cover the user application and
also the admin application for the store.
And also we have, we are going
to develop a driver app, which
will evolve, which will encourage
the e-commerce applications.
It is work in progress, but eventually we
will get there and yeah, we'll, it'll be
production ready in few months from now.
And coming to this closing points.
As a, as developers, our mission
is to build systems that can
evolve as fast as our ideas.
Micro sentence give us that
agility, allowing every team to
contribute intelligence, creative,
and innovation without friction.
As you head back to your
projects, think modularly,
think independently, deployable.
And think of how each microfund
can become a building block of
our next AI driven experience.
Thank you all for your time, your
attention and your curiosity today.
I am ling from Fairfield University and
it's been pleasure sharing this with
you at conference 42 JavaScript 2025.
Hopefully we'll catch you
some other time in the future.
Have a good rest of your day.
Thank you.