Hello, everyone.
My name is Alexander Guzenko.
And today I'm going to, I'm going
to talk about architecture, in
particular front end architecture.
Probably everyone faced with such
difficulties when, in large application,
when it becomes larger and larger, it,
It becomes harder to maintain it, and,
that's the problem because, sometimes
we need really large application and
we also want to well maintainable
and well scalable applications.
today We're going to cover such topics
as, key qualities of a good application.
What the difference between
good applications and bad ones.
Then, we're going to talk about problems
of modern front end and why just we
can't write only good applications,
maintainable and scalable applications.
Next, we of course, Gonna cover some
ways how to solve that problems and
in final part I want to tell you
about feature slice design and how
it can help you solve this problem.
That's not the only one solution
but it's my favorite one.
Just a few words about myself, I have
more than eight years of experience in
software development and Several years ago
I realized that many developers don't know
architecture well, and but architecture
is one of the most important part of
whole software development process.
So I decided that my mission is to
popularize front end architecture.
And, so here we go today.
let's talk about key qualities
of a good application.
first one, it's of course business
efficiency because applications needs,
for, receiving, money, to the business.
And, for earning money for the business.
of course, first, and, the most
important one is business efficiency.
Next one is scalability.
Scalability in front end is about,
how fast you can add new feature or
maybe new module to your application.
And, Last one, it's maintainability.
it's about, how easy it is to
make changes and, maintain your
application in the long term.
so first one, business efficiency.
it's not under our responsibility.
It's more about, good and
bad business decisions.
So it's not about software development.
and, We're going to cover
the second and third ones,
scalability and maintainability.
So let's focus on these two.
Why is it important to be well
scalable and well maintainable?
Let's talk about scalability, when
it's easy to add new functionality.
So it becomes cheaper and, we all want to
spend less time releasing new feature and
we all want that it will, that It needs
to be an easy process, not really hard.
so what about maintainability?
when an application is well
maintainable, the increase in
development costs remains small.
So it, it allows for the implementation
of a large application in the future.
And vice versa, it's bad maintainable.
So sometimes it may be some point when
It is so hard to maintain and so hard to
change the functionality that it becomes
easier to Rewrite whole application
and we all don't want this scenario.
So what the problems with that two
main qualities and the problems that
it's one of the most difficult tasks
is, to, release your application
to develop it, that, determine
the balance between scalability.
maintainability, and development speed.
and there are several reasons for that.
First one, unclear
future at the beginning.
We all need to do some important
architectural decisions at
the beginning, not at the end.
of development process, but the
thing that, at the beginning, we
have the least information about the
feature or the application at all.
And, during the development process, we
receive more and more information and
the most of information we have only
at the end of the development process.
the most important decisions we had
to, we have to make at the beginning
when we have the least information.
next problem, requirements may
change too often and unfortunately
we can't do anything with that.
probably everyone faced with, such
problem when, your You are in the middle
of development process and your manager
comes to you and said, we decided to
change the concept of this feature.
just, just to follow the new concept
and you release that, to follow the
new concept, you need to rewrite.
most of your written code and that's
the problem and, next one, lack of time.
Unfortunately, we don't
have infinity of time.
And if we could, to have to do it,
probably we could, create the better
decisions, but unfortunately we
don't have infinity of time, such
as we don't have infinity of money.
and that's the problem too.
But there is another problem,
that every application is unique.
And, the best solution for one
application, doesn't guarantee you
that, it will work for another.
So every time, you need to reinvent.
your architectural decisions for every
new task, new feature, and so on.
But, what we can do with that?
first of all, I want to make a
little mark that for every company,
every person, and every team, there
may be its own, good solutions.
But, here are the most
universal ones, for me.
First one, you need to become
a master in architecture.
this is the longest and the hardest way.
You need to know many
architectural patterns.
Architectural concepts, of
course, you need to make a lot
of mistakes and to solve them.
but, in final, you will so much are in
architecture that every architectural,
task, it will be easier for you and
you will do it really fast, but it
doesn't guarantee you that, your
development team will also have,
such architectural knowledges and
probably, you will need to control them
harder, but this is good, solution.
next one, use the best known
practices, it's easier than first one.
Because you don't need whole
architectural patterns and a
lot of architectural things.
You just need, to know a few of
them and, use them, everywhere.
it's If your only tool is a hammer,
every problems, every problem
look, looks like a nail, that's the
same, it's not, the bad solution.
Also because, using some architectural
patterns is better than not using
them at all, but not perfect also.
And, Last one for me.
This is the most efficient solution
use out of the box solutions.
So What is it out of the box solutions?
let's talk about on the example And
my example is feature slice design.
This is an architectural
methodology and, let's talk about
what is it, feature slice design.
As another architectural methodologies,
it's just a compilation of rules and
conventions on organizing a code.
But it has some, important parts.
First one, feature slice design
based on solid principles.
And, you of course need to
know the solid principles.
solid principles are the
basic in, architecturing.
And if you don't know about SOLID, I
really recommend it to, to learn about it,
about that more, because this is the base.
next one, public API.
Public API, is, is pretty small
architectural pattern, but Also pretty
important, because it can help you to
write, maintainable, scalable code.
Next one, it's low
coupling and high cohesion.
in this diagram, you can
see what does it mean.
on the y axis you, you can see coupling
and the x, you can see cohesion
and, there are different, there are
many combinations of them and the
best one when low coupling and high
cohesion and here you can see why.
It's better.
if you don't know about this
pattern, I also recommend you to
learn about that a little more.
And, last one, it's feature
slide design own rules.
And let's talk what is, what is,
own rules feature slide design.
first one, In the feature slice
design, your whole application
needs to divide into several layers.
There are six possible layers.
Shared, Entities, Features,
Widgets, Pages, and App.
Notice that, in the screen there is,
process layer, but, it was in the first,
version of feature slice design, and,
today we have second version, and,
in the second version, process layer
is deprecated, keep it in your mind.
some layers can have, its own slices.
for example, entities layer
can have some such slices as
user, post, comment, and so on.
And, every slice you can
divide into some segments.
UI, model API and so on.
And, let's dive deep into layers.
let's start with shared layers.
It's the most abstract layer.
And here you need to put some, basic
parts of your application, which don't
know anything about business logic.
for example, it is buttons, selects,
inputs, maybe some layouts, and so on.
Next layer is entities.
And it is, it's a business
entity, and, for example,
comment, post, user, and so on.
Here you can put your, UI, some
methods, how to fetch data,
from the backend and, so on.
Next layer is features.
Features.
it's about actions, about user
interactions, for example, like
comment, repost comment, delete post,
update user profile data, and so on.
actions.
next one, is widgets layer.
widgets layer, it's about
composition, compositioning.
And here you can, compose, your
entities and features together,
to make, for example, in this
exam, here you can see post.
Post contains, from, from entity
post and some features and, repost,
comment, download, and so on.
Next one is pages layer.
Pages layer.
It's easy because it's just a page What
do you want to see inside your page?
It's like also compositioning but
high level compositioning whole
page whole page layer layout, you
can put here in this layer and last
one application or app layer here.
you may put your global objects, global
stylus, global types, some providers like
routing, faming also on, and, Export, your
main, object, your application object,
if we talk, for example, about React.
Of course, at the beginning, it may be
difficult to divide your every feature
to these layers, segments, and so on.
And their core team of Feature
Slice Design, created, some,
decomposition cheat which can help
you to decompose your feature and
you can use it, on their own website.
Yes, they have a website, Feature
Slice Design, has a good website
with a lot of information.
I'll give you a link at the end of,
my speech and, Let's return to the
main questions of my today's speech.
How feature slice design can help me to
achieve maintainability and scalability?
Firstly, this is a good combination
of time tasted architectural patterns
and principles with its own rules
to solve modern front end problems.
What does it mean?
It contains from a lot of architectural
patterns, good patterns, and
they work together in a synergy.
So it's a really good combination for me.
But moreover, it, it was
released, this architectural
methodology released in 2020.
So it's pretty new and it was released
in modern front end era and it, good,
solve modern front end, problems.
Next one, Feature Slice Design
has a big community and a website
that can help on board newcomers.
faster.
You don't need to, to write your own.
Documentation, because it
is, it already, written.
And, if you have a newcomer in your team,
you just can, send a link to feature
slice design website, and that's it.
newcomer will, will read.
that information and we'll
learn what is it next one.
this is a embodiment of the experience
of many experience at development.
it just lies design have,
has a good, good support.
of core team.
Yes, there is a core team in feature
slice design that contribute to
this methodology almost every week.
And I know that guys, they really
put a lot of effort to maintain this.
And, this is really good, experience.
They really experienced guys.
Next one, feature slice design is
suitable for projects of almost any
size from little to do lists to big
dashboard applications with hundreds
or even millions lines of code.
And, Finally, you don't need to
reinvent new solutions every time.
Once you learn about feature slice
design and once you try to use it,
you could use it everywhere in every
project releasing every feature and
this is really convenient, and you don't
need to reinvent solutions every time.
So, For me, that's it and I
really hope, you are interested
in feature slice design and more
interested in architecture at all.
And if you have some questions,
just feel free to write me
down in my LinkedIn or Gmail.
And of course, I really recommend
to visit Feature Slice Design
website, even if you are not gonna
use it, just, to know what is it.
And, this is really important information.
So thank you, and have a good day.
Bye.