Hi everyone.
My name is Kasper Szefcik
and today I would like to
talk to you about TypeScript.
And how TypeScript improves
developer experience.
But before I start, let me just
talk a couple of words about myself.
So I work as JS developer at RSC software.
I work in Wroclaw, which is in Poland.
I specialize in two technologies, Next.
js and React Native.
So as you probably already know, I'm
front end slash mobile developer.
And a curious fact about myself is
that I am ex IT project manager.
I was project manager for almost
five years and for the past three
years, I'm back as a developer.
But that's all about myself.
Let's move to TypeScript.
And today I was, I would
like to start with a story.
A story that starts in 2008 and
in the company called Microsoft.
Maybe you've heard about them and in
the year 2008 in Microsoft, there was
an idea for a new project that initially
was analyzed by business analysts,
architects, maybe somebody else.
And they decided about the
technological stack and the
requirements for this project.
Later on, based on that, one of the team
was selected to work on this project.
And the project manager came to
the team to announce them the
news about their new project.
And he said, dear team, I
have a good news for you.
There is enormous opportunity for you
to work in the project in which you will
utilize not only your beloved C sharp.
But also another new
technology, Javascript.
And when they heard about
that, it was silence.
But after this short, brief moment
of silence, They were mad because
why they require them to work in
this chaotic language, JavaScript,
when on the other hand, they have
their beloved mature language.
S as it is C sharp, but the
Microsoft, they were working
as a professional developers.
They don't regret or just throw
away any challenges they face.
So they decided, okay, we'll do
this project, but we won't write
a single line in JavaScript.
So first of all, they sit
and made their own analysis.
Maybe they were wrong.
Maybe the JavaScript is
not needed in this project.
But in the end, they found
out, okay, it's in it.
It's, it has to be running.
In the browser, the
JavaScript needs to be there.
Okay.
what they can do?
They think, okay.
We know C Sharp very well.
What if We'll write the code in C Sharp
With the whole logic that has to be done
on this browser side But whatever write
it in C Sharp we have all the tools
all the libraries all the support that
we have in the C Sharp and We'll just
write the tool that to translate the C
Sharp code into JavaScript And there was
a tool you That's called script shop,
which was doing exactly as they expected.
So you take the file, the class in C sharp
and just translates that into the function
JS function It was a success for them
They meet the goal They wrote a project
in C sharp, which requires JavaScript,
but they didn't have to write it.
Success.
But were there any problems?
Of course.
I would say that a lot of them.
First of all, even though they
have a beautifully written code in
mature language like C sharp, Maybe
even they have 100 percent code
coverage, but they were testing
the code that is not on production.
That is the first issue.
So even if they have 100 percent certainty
that the code in C sharp works well,
then it was translated by the tool
that maybe not been so well tested.
And then they have to manually test that
when it was actually written in Javascript
So the tests are false positive actually
so they have Certainty of uncertainty,
because they weren't sure that JavaScript
itself is translated correctly.
Maybe the tool itself contains error
that generates errors on the translation.
Maybe even some functions
weren't implemented.
And translate it correctly
from C sharp to JavaScript.
And they have to do it basically
at each time of the release,
each time of the translation that
they have to manually test that.
And if there are any problems, it was
faster and more secure to fix that on
the JS side, rather than fix that the
translator, this script sharp tool.
Why?
Because if they change something in
the scripture, maybe the problem that
they had, they spotted, is fixed,
but they weren't sure if something
else wasn't broken in the meantime.
So they sit again to the table,
started wondering what they can do,
we cannot work this way anymore.
And, one brave team member asked them,
What if you just write it in JavaScript?
We'll do it anyway.
Maybe it will be faster, better
to write it pure in JavaScript.
But the other team member
said, nah, let's not do it.
So this one team member
asked, okay, but why?
Why the JavaScript is so bad
in comparison to ScriptShark?
And they started wondering.
Why?
Why they don't want to
write in JavaScript?
Because everyone said that
the C language is bad?
Probably yes.
But they just try to point out
reasons why JavaScript is bad.
And one of the things that they
highlighted is that they are not
sure what will be the result of the
function that they are implementing.
In the C Sharp they have
to write in JavaScript.
declarer, the types of the parameters,
the output type of the function.
So even if the function, if
you provide the arguments of
wrong types to the function, the
compiler will say that it's wrong.
If they expect different type of
the method after execution, the
compiler will say that it's wrong.
So the application itself is basically
verified even before they start to
click on that or just execute anything.
And they thought to themselves,
what if Javascript will have
that, then we can work with it.
Because the What the keywords like
the special words that they have
in the JavaScript are not very
different from what they already know.
The only this predictability of the
typescript of the JavaScript is.
It's not existing actually.
So later on in 2012, there was released
the first version of TypeScript with
the version number zero point 0.8.
It was the first version that
was publicly opened to the MPM.
And what is very interesting about this
fact that when you, when we compare
the types of other languages that
were released, that were developed
as a new language, new big thing,
then it was, you can see that most
of the languages that were released,
they took one problem or multiple
problems that other technologies has.
I didn't want to improve that, but this
problems that technology technologies
has, I usually connected with, or
maybe different architecture and
that's, we want to solve the issue with
microservices to have better support
in the language for microservice.
Maybe, we want to improve
memory management or, improve
CPU usage of the language.
in any cases, we want to improve
some problem that one language has.
We want to make it better.
But the TypeScript itself
doesn't do anything different.
The applications written in JavaScript
and TypeScript works the same.
They have the same memory usage.
Basically, they are the same application.
What difference?
It's a developer experience in
writing in this specific language.
The type itself was created to
improve developer experience.
It was created for the love,
for the developers, or we can
say for the hate of JavaScript.
And it wasn't a huge success at
the very beginning, at least.
Because TypeScript in 2012 was supported
only by one IDE, Visual Studio Code.
But Visual Studio Code, even
though it's right now, it's quite
popular and many, probably most of
you are using that on every day.
But in 2012, it has one
technical difficulty.
It was running only on Windows.
So it was a huge obstacle to overcome.
But soon it was solved.
Okay, let's leave Microsoft,
and let's move to TypeScript.
And because I started with the
Microsoft, which for me, it's a
company that earns a lot of money.
And I will, I want To stay in the topic
of money because who doesn't love money
and for today examples how Typescript
works with developer experience.
I want to talk about the money that
is provided by scientific grants.
So if you don't know, grants itself
is that the money that is provided
by the government or some institution
or the company to develop some
research, scientific research.
So usually it's like the long time
project that you require, you write
what you wanted to develop, what you
want to discover in your research,
you write some expected results, and
then you proceed with the research.
So usually you need to provide
the document that describes
what your product will be about.
what do you need to buy in case of
the consumables, any materials, any
devices, that will help you to, to
basically make this research and then
write any results that will help you.
you expect to, to be, receiving
or any applications for this
research, if it will be a success.
So this kind of grants grant, contains,
let's say a couple of informations.
and if we want to have a system
that allows to upload this kind
of data, we need to store it.
so the, first of all, we need the
information or the applicant, as you
can see on the right, we have some
name, of the student or the supervisor.
we have some magic number, which
is basically the identifier,
for this specific person.
so we know that he or she, apply
and this is not somebody else from
different university, for example.
We have some new address, maybe
some different information that
is specific for this person.
And the other thing is application number.
so this is something that we'll just
point out the exactly which of the,
application it is, especially the
application number on the contains
information about the Institute, maybe
the funding for which we are asking for,
probably it will contain some year, when
this project is Submitted and so on.
so we also want, it won't be
just, the index from the database.
It has to be something first of
all, a little bit secret, but on
the other hand, quite descriptive.
we'll have some
information of the project.
Of course, we'll have attachments,
which are quite important.
Because it should contain any offers
that we already ask, for the companies
in case of this, devices that we want
to buy or rent, maybe this, materials
that will require for this, research.
We need to have this kind of offers
assigned to the project so they know that
if we are asking, for example, for 100
grants, this is basically the summary of
all the costs that are in the attachment.
and the last part that I wanted to
highlight is the signature of approvals.
because, this kind of project usually
have multiple steps of approval.
in the Europe, And there are
this kind of projects, they are
all, always at least two steps.
The first one is something that is called
formal review, which basically verifies
if the application itself is correct.
all the fields are, filled
correctly, basically.
And if the information that you put
are according to the truth, if you
are applying for the correct project.
And so on.
So on.
And later on, there is, the final review,
which will basically review if your
project are, interesting or needed in case
of the actual situation of the market.
so let's say that you are applying for
the grant, when three years ago, there
was very similar research, done, and you
are basically asking for the money for
very similar, even the same research,
you won't receive this kind of money.
but usually it's on the second
step because it requires somebody
from the industry to verify
if your product is correct.
yeah, so let's start from our
first part, ApplicantData.
We have this kind of basic type that we
will have to, map our applicant data.
So you have some kind of address which
will be used for correspondence or any
other, sending of the letters and so on.
As we have some city, postal
code, country, Let's keep
it simple for right now.
On the other hand, we have this applicant,
which will be our basic, unit of the user.
So we have the first name, last
name, email, phone number, address,
and SSN, which is stands for social
security number, which is the.
Unique identifier for
the people with, the U.
S.
citizenship.
In Poland it's called PESEL, and probably
in other countries it's a similar,
number that is unique for this specific
country and this specific person.
But If for example, I would apply for
the grant in the United States, I don't
have SORA security number I can probably
ask to receive this kind of number but
If I don't have the citizenship, probably
I don't have it, let's say, right now.
So usually in this kind of, in this
kind of applications, we're asked for
a different data that will also allow
us to identify this specific applicant.
So if we don't have social security
number, maybe let's fill up birth date.
So in this case, if we don't
have social security number,
we provide the birth date.
If we have social security number, we
don't need to provide the birth date.
So in this case, let's just put
that both these values are optional.
But this is not the only one who can ask
for a grant because also the companies
can ask for a scientific grants.
So in this case, we won't provide social
security number because we are asking as
a company, not for the specific person.
We won't have the birthdate because
the birthdate of the company
It's not interesting for us.
But what we can ask for is a
company name and their tax ID.
So again, tax ID is something unique
for the company in specific country.
So if you have that, maybe you have
the company name just to fill the form.
Then we have the whole
object of the applicant.
So right now we have four optional
fields, but we require that at
least one field based on the, based
on the type of the application.
we need to, we need that it's filled.
So let's improve that.
so we can start with that.
So we have the private applicant,
which contains all the field
with social security number.
Yeah, that's our basic type.
We can, have the separate, separate
type for private applicant without
social security number, which we
don't have social security number,
but it will have birth date.
Okay.
And the last one, we have
the company applicant.
which will contains, contain the
first name, last name, email,
phone number, address, and the
company name and the tax ID.
And if you want to group that, so
we have applicant will be one of
the three, three types and basically
that will work, but we are repeating
a lot of fields in the types.
Let's improve that.
We don't want to repeat
ourselves dry principle, right?
So yeah, let's improve that.
So we'll create the base applicant
type, which will contains five fields
that we have in all of the fields.
So we have the base, the private
applicant, which will contains base
applicant and the social security number.
Private applicant without social
security number will contain
the same and the birthdate.
And the last one, company applicant
will contain base applicant and
the company name and the tax ID.
yeah, that's basically
what we can achieve.
And we can achieve that
in any other language.
the problem is the solution.
Is that I don't like it.
the biggest problem that I see in this,
in this approach is that we are not secure
from the creating of this, base applicant
type object, because the base applicant
itself is something that is completely
not connected with the business.
So it creates some dummy type.
Because we as a developer, we
don't want to repeat ourselves
because we have a dry principle.
But on the other hand, we are creating
something that's doesn't represent
anything in case of the business.
Like we cannot use base
applicant anywhere.
We'll still need, with social
security number, with birthday, or
with company name and the tax ID.
And apart from that, that this
type base applicant is not
exported outside the file.
This is our, the only security
right now that we won't
create an object of this type.
When you compare that to, for example,
C sharp or Java, In this languages,
we can create interface or abstract
class that we won't still be able
to create the object of this type.
We can create an object which
implements or extends this kind
of interface or abstract class.
So in this case, we said, okay, I know
that this object itself is more complex,
but I want to work only on this couple
of fields with this limited number
of fields, limited number of methods.
And this is what, interfaces
and abstract classes are for.
The typeface itself doesn't allow us to
do So we are creating dummy type, which
are basically just for our convenience.
But the problem right now that we
have some, let's say, base part that
first of all may vary and will affect
private applicant without social
security number and the company
applicant without our knowledge.
Okay.
So let's use something that DevScript
has already in the language.
which will help us solve this
issue with creating a dummy type.
And not repeating ourselves, of course.
So let's start once again for a private
applicant with social security number.
Let's take it as it is.
This is our basic type.
Most of our applications will be
created by private people with
social security number, so we can
say that this is our basic type.
If you want to create a private applicant
without social security number, we
can, for example, use the omit type.
Which basically takes the type
that we provide as a first
argument of this generic type.
And we provide the list of the fields
that we say, okay, skip this field.
And when we have the type that is
declarative like private or pecan
without social security number.
So we just say, okay.
Omit social security number.
It's exactly what we are, we
are, we say that we will have.
And we just add that to
the private birthdate.
So yeah, in the background, we are
actually creating this dummy type, which
won't have this social security number.
But in this case, It's not
access, has access anywhere.
We have to declare that this base
applicant omit private applic, applicants,
social security number to be able to
export that, outside of our function.
This way it's not access, accessible.
In case of the private applicant,
I would recommend us to use PIP.
First of all, because we
are taking specific fields
from the private applicant.
If the private applicant will receive more
fields, I won't expect that the company
applicant will extend on their own.
I want to have in this case, the
full control over what fields
I'm actually putting into company
applicant to have the same type.
The same if it's optional or not.
And so in this case, we just take this
all five fields and let's put them.
So in this case, we create again, the
dummy type with different way around,
but we have a full control over which
fields are actually included in that.
What also, provides us, let's suppose
that the private applicant type
will change slightly that we get
rid of first and then the last name
and change that into the full name.
So in this case, it will affect the
private applicant without social security
number, which also will change its type.
So it won't have full name,
first name and the last name, and
will also only have full name.
But in case of the company
applicant, it will tell us an error.
Because the compiler will say, okay,
there is no first name and last name.
we have only full name.
And of course, this is required,
this requires us our manual log
that we have to update our type.
But if there is situation that we still
want to have for the company applicant,
the first name and the last name
separately, okay, we'll have to do it
manually, but we'll do it either way.
And we have full control,
full knowledge that something
is crushing our application.
That is the advantage of this approach.
Okay.
Let's leave applicant data.
Let's move to application number.
So in our case, let's assume that the
application number is something like that.
So we have some code, some
numbers, slash, and the year.
So first of all, what we can
achieve with the TypeScript?
We can say, okay.
That's.
The application's number
will be just a string.
So we can declare in the type of our whole
application that it will be a string.
Or, we say that okay, we'll
improve that in the future.
So maybe instead of declaring that
as a string, let's say that we
have the type application number,
which right now it is a string.
Maybe at first it doesn't change
anything, but later on if you
change this type, it will also
affect all the types that you want.
And we don't need to search, okay,
where we use string as application
number, because it should already
affect the whole, the whole of our file.
So first of all, we can use
something that we can say that.
There will be like application type
codes that we declare as a list of
the codes And we can declare the years
That will be like this five years.
So the years when this Grant scientific
grant is actually given for the specific
project So if we have something like
that declared We can create a type,
which is TemplarLiteralType, which
will contains of application type,
number, and the application year.
how it looks like.
So if we create this, something
like this literal, Templar,
TemplarLiteralType, it will generate
us all the possible combinations of
our codes, number and slash year.
So in this case, if I, for example, change
that to 2025, it will highlight that this
value that I'm providing is not correct.
in case of the temporary data types.
Again, if I don't put a number,
it will also return an error
that this field is not correct.
So using just this very simple native
mechanism of TypeScript, I can create
already type validator based on that.
I can already set, okay, this is
correct, or this is not correct.
I can verify if this first code after,
somebody puts that manually is correct
with this type of code, because I know
that this type, this application number
will consist of all these fields.
Zinac normally would need to have some
kind of complex regex, just verify that.
TypeScript has regex included in
their language, and that's beautiful.
Let's even improve our, our
application number type validation.
And just play that, play with
it a little bit so we can add
some kind of generic type.
That's, I will just
describe that in a second.
So we have, again, application type codes.
We have year endings, which
generates, the ending.
I have application year.
so we just put something we
don't want to repeat ourselves.
Again, and yeah, we're going to
generate the same code once again.
and how it works basically.
So as you can see, we just provide,
a number, which is this first
argument of our generic type.
We provide that we want to
receive the, array of numbers and
what they are doing basically.
if results of, length of this array
with results, actually extends our.
argument.
So basically that means that
if the results equals our
arguments, return results.
If not, just add additional
result to our, to our array.
So in this case, it just generates numbers
from zero to, to the size of the array.
And yeah, that's how it works.
And as you can see, it's
quite dummy because it can, it
generates us this kind of error.
So in this case, it's better to
use it, until then not higher.
Okay.
Let's move to the attachments.
with the attachments, let's declare that
we'll have three types of attachments.
So again, we'll just use union on
the expenses, income, and the other.
Whatever it is.
And with the attachments, usually we
have two problems in the application.
That the type of the uploading
the, attachments it's
completely different from the.
Type that we receive apartment, because
usually when we upload that, we using
some, multipart request, just upload
the fields and upload the files.
And in case we want to get that,
we receive your, with the file.
so we can download that.
Or if it image, if it is a image,
we just, Render that as an image.
So in our case, we can have attachment
details, payload, which will contains
the file that we'll be able to
upload, using the multiple request.
we'll have the description,
what type of attachment it is.
we'll have the type.
So just this general.
Category of the attachment and maybe
we'll have also the page count which
will be basically the number how
many pages of this Attachment there
is actually is So based on that, we
can verify if all the documents are,
correctly uploaded and when we wanted
to get, the details of the attachment.
So again, we can use the PIC that you
already know, attachment details payload.
We take description type and page count,
and we just add firewall, fire URL.
yeah, based on that, you can handle
both upload and post and get requests
and post and get request data.
Maybe even add some ID in case of
the getting the, this attachment.
But what we can also do.
You can add attachment name, because
usually we'll have, maybe we'll
have some name that attachment
that's also always required, like
CV or some motivation letter.
but any other generic general,
attachments will have probably
this attachment plus number.
So we also have, we want to have
this kind of, assigned for our keys.
And the last part, because we don't want
to create an array of the attachment, but
we can create an object of the attachment.
And in our case we can create an
object of the attachment name, which
will be the key of the attachment.
And attachment details will
just assign the object.
in our case, we'll have
something like that.
So we'll have, okay, so we'll have
just the object of this specific key.
and the attachment details, which just
generates us with the, the attachment.
And based on that, we can, for
example, access the attachment
number two, without iterating over
array or going to the specific.
index of the array, we just ask
for the specific, attachment and we
can say, okay, it's present or not.
And so on.
so yeah, if we group that, that part, so
we have the application, which consists
of the applicant with the applicant
data, we have application date, we have
application number, which we created,
and we have attachments and here I
will use the partial, because once
again, we are not required to upload
always the same number of, attachments.
So we would like to have this
kind of, optional for the keys.
So we just upload only in this
attachments that we actually needed.
And yeah, if we have the
application that has three
actually types of the applicants.
just to remind ourselves, the applicant,
applicant without social security number
and the company applicant, then, and of
course, in other cases, we'll need some
type guards, and how the types that works.
So we can have this kind of
function is object with key, which
basically verifies us if the object.
Is key, if the, the, the argument that
we are providing is actually an object.
We also verify if that is, not nullable.
And yeah, just basically
to, to be sure about that.
So argument that you have provided is the
unknown because we don't know what it is.
And we return that, okay, this is
an object that has some keys and, we
don't know what is the type of the.
of this keys.
So we just return, okay, it's unknown.
so yeah, that is our return type.
So in our case, we just verify if
the applicant that we are providing
is actually a private applicant.
So in our case, We can say,
okay, is a private applicant.
So we verify that if we provide
an applicant, which is unknown, we
can provide an applicant that is
application that will also work.
we say, okay, applicant
is a private applicant.
So in our case, we just
verify if the applicant has.
This object with the keys and
does it has, this property social
security number because it was
unique for our private applicant.
Of course, we can verify multiple
fields, in this type guard.
In our case, social
security number is unique.
And I decided that, okay, the type
that is solved will be sufficient.
If we verify the social security
number, what it gives us, let's
look at a look at the example.
so I make it a little bit simpler
just to fit them on one screen.
so we have a type private
application, which will contains
only the social security number.
So we don't need any other fields.
Okay.
And our applicant will be
private applicant or string.
so yeah, we want to verify that first
of all, it's an object and not a string.
And the first and the second thing
that we wanted to verify if this
is actually social security number.
so yeah, we have the same function.
And what it gives us?
If you have the method that say
printApplicant, it's not very complex,
and we have an argument of this function,
and that is string or privateApplicant.
And we have the if clause, which right now
they know that, okay, it is an applicant.
And, but when we enter on this
method, so inside of this,
scope, the type, you already know
that this is private applicant.
It will say that, okay,
yeah, that's right.
It's a private applicant.
If we, add additional.
line here, and we will say, okay,
applicant, let me just verify that.
Yeah, because it's outside our if
clause, it's actually in the else clause.
It knows right now.
Okay.
It is a string, not a private applicant.
if we just go, beyond that,
okay, I will just remove that.
So again, outside of the, if.
TypeScript doesn't know what
it is, if it's a private
topic on this, of the string.
So again, if we just try to use that,
especially in this complex types, and
then the types we already will say that,
okay, we are not sure what type of method
it is, even though somewhere in the
back, before we execute this function,
we know, okay, this is something else.
the types of itself needs to be certain
and we'll just return those error.
We can fix that before
checking that on the code.
Okay.
so let's look in another helpful,
additional national type.
in case of the hour.
Application will have the fields
that are not changeable at all.
And we want to maintain that.
And to do so we have the read only.
so in, let's say our basic type, so we
have read only and again, we have the
application number if you wanted to.
to change the value, to override that,
TypeScript will tell us we can't do that.
So in our case, We'll have the situation
that we have the whole application
completed and somebody will verify it's
correct and later on just assign, okay,
it's correct, give them money or not.
So we would want our whole
application to be read only.
And only the verification
date, verification status.
And who verified that?
Which are the only fields
that you want to be read?
to be, not read only,
and all of the others.
We wanted to stay at the same.
We want, we don't want anyone to
edit our fields, so in our case,
in our application, we can force
that the argument that we provided,
the methods will be written only.
And only specific fields will be
actually editable inside of this method.
So again, we can make sure that
nobody change, change the fields
that you don't want them to change.
The last thing that I wanted to show you,
is creating a draft because the grant
submissions are usually quite long, to
write that it requires a lot of time.
And even if you start uploading that
into the system, maybe you receive the
information that something is missing and
you have to abandon the process, to gather
the documents, maybe from your university,
maybe it's from somewhere else.
and yeah, you will need to go back
to that after a couple of days.
So in this case, The draft
functionality will be very important
in our case of the application.
So how we can do that with the TypeScript?
so we can create something like that.
So we'll have the applicant, which
will have first name, last name, email,
address, and social security number.
We have the follower application,
which contains applicant, application
date, and some application number.
Let's keep it simple.
and we can create our own type,
generic type that is called Nullable,
which contains null or our, argument.
Later on, we can create a
DeepNullable, which for each.
key in our type, deep nullable
of deep nullable of our, key.
In this case, all of the fields
in our tree will be nullable.
So we can create an object that
will, for example, will be have,
will have, nullable application
date, nullable application number.
Nullable first name, last name, email,
social security number, but in the address
we'll have only field, for example, city.
With these four lines, actually
we create very powerful type that
will allow us to make a magic.
Of course, there are still challenges
how you're going to save that into
the browser or even into the server.
If you have all the fields nullable.
but yeah, from the directory
point of view, four lines and
you have very powerful field.
You can even change that from null to
undefined, and then we don't have to
provide all the nulls, just one field.
Somewhere in the, in the
background that will be filled.
so I have two key takeaways for you.
use advanced types to
create complex types.
Because, there are tools that you
should use, and they are very powerful.
And typeguards allows for
safe and fast typechecks.
Again, If you're, for example, verifying
even the API calls on your local
development, if after verifying the type
that you receive from API, you receive
an error locally, you're still benefiting
because very fast, you received the
information, okay, something changed, some
field is missing, some field changed type.
And you will be able to
update that very fast.
yeah.
Sources.
so first of all is the whole, story
from ScriptSharp to JavaScript.
and the other thing is TypeScript
documentation of TypeScript 5 Minutes,
which contains all the advanced types.
some of them I just highlighted.
I think that there are the most
popular, at least in my code.
but yeah, maybe there is something
else that's, that is there.
And that you feel stuff in that's,
maybe it's useful, it's better to use
something that's already there in the
language rather than write it yourself.
Yeah.
Thank you.
That's all from me.
Do you have any questions?