Hi everyone.
My name is ELA Mo and I'm happy
to be presenting here at the
JavaScript conference 2025.
I wanted to start with a quick
introduction about myself.
I currently work for the Wells Fargo Bank
and I have around 14 years of hands-on
experience in advanced data analytics.
Credit risk strategy and predictive
modeling across financial services,
marketing, and customer intelligence.
I also have extensive experience in
developing machine learning driven
fraud detection strategies, segmentation
models and campaign optimization
frameworks that help improve ROI.
Reduce risk exposure and
enhance operational efficiency.
The topic I'm planning to present today
is client side, NLP, JavaScript, text
Analytics for user Behavior Intelligence.
I'm actually pretty excited today
to be talking about how we are
using client side natural language
processing, NLP, with JavaScript to
understand user behavior in real time
without sending data to a server.
This talk is about rethinking
how we do text analytics, moving
intelligence closer to the user inside
the browser where privacy, latency
and interact with all matter most.
I'll walk you through why this shift
is important, the architecture we used,
the tools and techniques involved, and
that what kind of insights it unlocks
for product teams and developers.
Let's jump to the next slide.
This slide talks about
the hidden data problem.
Let's start with the challenge.
Traditional analytic tools do a
great job of tracking what users do.
Clicks, scrolls and time on each page,
but not why they behave that way.
We are capturing millions of user
interactions, but missing the deeper
layer of intent, hidden in their language.
Every form, submission, chat
message, search query, and feedback
comment contains behavioral signals.
Which are emotion, intent,
confusion, satisfaction.
For example, a user might click
contact support, but the message
they write reveals frustration,
confusion, or even shown intent.
Those insights are hidden inside
unstructured text, and historically
we have ignored them because crossing
language was expensive and required
server side pipelines, that's
the problem we set out to solve.
Moving on to the next slide.
So this slide talks about
why process NLP client side.
So why bring NLP to the client?
There are three main drivers, privacy,
realtime feedback, and efficiency.
We can start talking about privacy
in a world of data regulations
and user trust concerns.
Sending raw text to a server is risky.
Client said, NLP means the
text never leaves the browser.
No data leakage, no compliance headaches.
The next one is real time feedback.
Processing happens
instantly as the user types.
We can detect sentiment, hesitation,
or frustration and adapt the
interference interface in a real time.
Maybe offer help highlight CTA
or are just tone dynamically.
The next one is efficiency.
By offloading computations to the
user's device, we drastically reduce
server costs and network latency.
With GPO acceleration in browsers, users
essentially bring their own compute so we
get privacy, immediacy, and scalability.
The Holy Trinity of modern analytics.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about the
JavaScript NLP toolkit.
Now let's talk about the tools
that make all this possible.
First, natural and compromise.
These are lightweight NLP Libraries
for tokenization, part of speech
tagging and entity recognition
that run directly in the browser
with zero external dependencies.
Second TensorFlows js.
This brings the power of pre-trained
machine learning models to JavaScript
using WebGL for GPU acceleration.
We use it for sentiment scoring
and text classification.
And third web workers and index DB web
workers keep heavy NLP computations off
the main thread, so the UI never freezes.
While Index DB stores results locally
for offline access or historical trend
analysis, together, these tools let
us replicate what used to require a
Python backend all within the browser.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide gives the
architecture overview.
Here's a high level view
of the architecture.
The design goal was to isolate NLP
processing from user interaction
to keep everything responsive.
Web workers handle all the model loading
and text analysis in the background.
Service workers support offline
capabilities, caching models and data,
so it still works without connectivity.
Index DB serves as local storage for
processed analytics, letting us analyze
behavior over time, even across sessions.
And finally, results are funneled back
to a centralized state management layer,
think Redux or context API, which updates
the react components in real time.
This architecture mimics distributed
computing, but at the browser level,
light modular and event driven.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about building
realtime sentiment analysis.
So how does realtime sentiment
analysis actually work?
Here's a process.
The first step, we load a pre-trained
tensor flow dot js model at App startup,
usually a lightweight transformer.
Or LSTM variant optimized for client use.
Next, when a user types into a chat
feedback box or a form, we capture the
input events, but we use debouncing, so
we are not analyzing every keystroke.
The next step is the text gets
tokenized and vectorized into numerical.
Representations and that's passed
to the model for in inference,
which outputs a sentiment score.
Finally, we visualize that score right in
the UI may be a color indicator emoji or
sentiment garge that updates as they type.
This gives immediate emotional feedback
and provides continuous sentiment streams
that pro product teams can analyze.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about user
segments hidden in text.
Once we have enough text, data
patterns start to emerge that
reveal distinct user segments.
There are different types of
user segments hidden in text.
First one is hesitant users.
They use language full of uncertainty.
Words like maybe I think, or questions.
They're undecided and need reassurance.
The next set of segments
are competitive switchers.
These users explicitly mention
other products or pricing.
They're evaluating options and can
be won over with targeted offers.
The next segment is high intent prospects.
They use decisive action oriented
language, like ready to buy,
need integration, start tomorrow.
These are your hottest leads.
The next one is at-risk users
negative sentiment spikes
complaints or cancellation keywords.
These users signal churn risk
early by categorizing users.
This way we can align
messaging and support to each
behavior type in real time.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about topic modeling
with JavaScript beyond user sentiment.
We also want to understand
what people are talking about.
That's where topic modeling comes in.
We use JavaScript implementations
of algorithms like key means or
hierarchical clustering to group
similar messages without any labels.
Each text snippet is vectorized
using T-F-I-D-F or word embeddings
and dimensionality reduction helps
us visualize them in clusters, say
billing issues, feature requests.
Or performance feedback.
What's powerful here is that this
runs dynamically as new messages
arrive, clusters update automatically.
It's like having live market research
running inside your product interface.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about
practical implementation
text, pre-processing pipeline.
Before any model can make sense of
text, we need to clean and structure it.
Our pre-processing
pipeline looks like this.
Normalize, tokenize,
vectorize, and analyze.
When we talk about normalize, it basically
converts everything to lowercase,
strip punctuation and trim white
space tokenize, split text into words,
remove common stop words like the and
is, and apply stemming or limitation.
A vectorize convert words into numerical
vectors using TF IDF, or embeddings.
Analyze feed vectors into NLP models
for classification or clustering.
Each stage is modular and usable, which
means developers can swap algorithms or
add domain specific steps very easily.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about building
responsive react components.
A big part of making this user
friendly is how we display results.
We built reusable react components
that visualize sentiment
and topics in real time.
Custom hooks manage background
communication with web workers,
so react only updates when.
Fresh data arrives.
We use context providers to
share NLP results across the app.
So sentiment data in one component
can influence recommendations
or UI color schemes elsewhere.
For vis visualization, we integrated
D three Js perfect for generating
dynamic sentiment timelines,
word clouds, and cluster graphs.
The focus is on smooth interactivity,
loading states, transitions, and
animations that make analytics
feel integrated, not intrus.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about feature
engineering text to metrics.
Once we process the text, the
next step is to turn linguistic
insights into actionable metrics.
We do this in four layers, linguistic
features, behavioral metrics.
Aggregate profiles and actionable scores.
Linguistic features, so this is basically
sentiment, PO polarity tone, readability,
entity density and emotional intensity,
behavioral metrics, how often users
write, how quickly they respond, and
whether their tone changes over time.
Aggregate profiles, combining text and
behavior into holistic user fingerprints
that capture engagement style.
Actionable scores things like
satisfaction index, churn,
probability or intent confidence.
This allows us to move from raw language
to measurable behavioral in intelligence.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about performance
optimization strategies.
Client side NLP is powerful, but
we can be resource intensive.
We use several optimization
tactics like lazy loading, batch
processing, debouncing and caching.
We only for lazy loading.
We only download heavy tensor flow
models when they're actually needed.
Keeping the initial bundle, small
batch processing, instead of
analyzing text one snippet at a time.
We queue and process in batches
maximizing GPU throughput.
Debouncing.
We avoid reprocessing partial sentences.
Analysis only happens after
the user pauses typing.
Caching results are stored in
indexed DB using hashtag keys.
So repeated text isn't reanalyzed.
These techniques keep the
experience seamless, lightweight
on both CPU and memory while
still providing instant insights.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about data privacy
and security concentrations.
Privacy isn't an afterthought.
It's a design principle.
Everything happens locally.
User text never leaves the device.
Before analysis users give
explicit consent through an opt-in
prompt that explains exactly
what's being analyzed and stored.
We allow users to view, export, or delete
their stored analytics data at any time.
Sensitive text in Index DB is encrypted
and inco in incognito or private browsing
mode analytics are automatically disabled.
This approach shows that
advanced AI doesn't have to
come at the cost of user trust.
We're going to the next slide.
This slide talks about
real world applications.
Let's talk about where this approach
adds value in production environments.
Some examples are
support, chat enhancement.
Search intent analysis,
feedback classification.
For support chart enhancement,
we can detect frustration or
urgency automatically and route
high priority messages to live
agents search intent analysis.
This classifies search terms to
identify what users are truly looking
for and where your content gaps are.
Feedback, classification,
this automatically tags user
feedback into categories like.
Bugs, features and praise.
Saving hours of manual sorting because
all this happens at the client side.
It's scalable across millions of users
without additional backend load, and
every user's data remains private.
The, this concludes the presentation.
Thank you for your time and attention.
Clients at NLP represents a big
shift from centralized data analysis
to edge intelligence where users
browsers become mini analytics engines.
It's faster.
Safer and far more personal.
As developers, we now ha have
the tools to combine NLP web APIs
and frontend frameworks to create
experiences that truly understand users.
In context, I would like to
discuss how you might apply
these ideas in your own products,
whether it's improving engagement.
Personalization or user trust.
I would like to thank thank the
conference for giving me this opportunity
and I hope you all have a good day.
Thank you.