Hi, everyone.
My name is Joe, and welcome to
my CON42 JavaScript 2024 session.
Today, I'm going to talk about the
TypeScript magic, like how to achieve end
to end type safety across the full stack.
First off, please allow me to
introduce myself a little bit.
As I said, my name is Joe
and I'm currently a developer
advocate at Dragonfly.
And I'm a huge fan of K pop as well.
And sometimes I just feel that I
attended too many K pop concerts.
Before Dragonfly, I mostly
do backend development.
So I've been doing that with different
languages, JavaScript, TypeScript.
Go Rust, just to name
some of my favorites.
And from there, I also developed a
very strong interest in databases.
So yeah, today I'm going to talk about,
backend and, like the type safety.
And I'm very passionate about what
I do and I like memes as well.
I'm going to be using memes in this
talk and I hope you enjoy them as well.
Before that, please allow me to
introduce a little bit about the
project I'm working on right now.
It's called Dragonfly.
So Dragonfly is an in memory data store.
it is compatible to Redis.
So it can be used as a dropping
replacement, but the architecture
is built from scratch.
So it's just happened to be compatible.
It's not a fork of Redis, right?
Because of the new modern multi
threaded architecture, Dragonfly is
able to handle 25 times more throughput
on a single multi core instance.
So because of that, because Dragonfly can
fully utilize your multi core hardware.
If you take one If you take the
binary of Dragonfly, you take the
binary and you put it on a multi core,
powerful multi core server and that
one Dragonfly instance is going to be
able to fully utilize your hardware.
Whereas in comparison for Redis, because
Redis is single threaded mostly, Redis
can only utilize, like a single core.
That's why if you put Redis on a
multiple machine, even on that one
machine, some sort of clustering
solution is needed for Redis.
So awesome.
it's a, to me, it's like a great, it's
one of my favorite data store right now.
And, it is like the next chain in
memory, the story, if you have, if you're
interested, yeah, feel free to check us
out and, we have a cloud offering as well.
And, yeah, I'm going to go, I'm
going to be showing like TypeScript,
JavaScript code right now.
just, One more note for the
compatibility of Dragonfly, just like how
compatible we're talking about, right?
So this is a snippet.
You can use this IO Redis library to
create a client and that client will
be able to talk to a Redis instance
and you can send commands from there.
So if you ever want to switch
to Dragonfly, The only code
you need to change is the URL.
So you pointed to a
different, dragonfly URL.
In this case, I'm using a
dragonfly cloud instance.
And that's it from there.
You can start to send the familiar
commands that you use for Redis.
Cool.
And, let's talk about
programming languages, right?
So I do believe in the saying of using
the right tools for the right things.
And, yeah, for instance, Python
has like a huge ecosystem of,
data analysis, AI, everything.
So if you're in that.
domain or sector, it's
natural just to use Python.
But for me, as a backend developer, I
think I personally have a very strong
preference of strong and statically
typed languages because when I
receive, let's say we use JSON, right?
When I receive a JSON payload from
the client, it's so crucial for
me to Make sure that the payload
conforms the request, the shape
of the request that we want.
And we also validate each of
the fields in there, right?
So this strong and static typing
and all the validations we do.
that just makes me feel like
sleep much better at nights.
So let's dive in, TypeScript.
yeah, as you can tell, TypeScript
is, is, strongly typed.
And if you ask me what's the, what
like, what's one of the most important,
project within the JavaScript ecosystem,
I would argue that it is TypeScript
because, it gives like, So many
guarantees, right now than before, right?
TypeScript provides something
called the utility type.
what does it mean?
Let's take a look at the example.
Imagine we are building like
a bookstore, a website, maybe
like the next Amazon, right?
this is a type we can define and we can
define so that we, we can use in our code.
We want all our book record
to look like this, right?
By saying book record, because
we are trying to save this
object in the database as well.
So it needs an ID.
But what if I'm just receiving the
request from the client, like adding
a new book to the store, right?
We don't want the client
to specify the ID, right?
Because, we want to generate
the ID in the backend.
It's more secure, maybe using
a serial, maybe using like
a UID or something, right?
So when that happens, what we
can do is that we can use this
utility type from TypeScript.
One example is called
the omit utility type.
So as you can see, we're using angle.
brackets here, right?
So the mindset would be if we're
using round brackets, that's calling
a function or calling a method.
So we're operating on
the object or the value.
But when we see angle brackets,
we're operating on the types.
like on a higher level, right?
So in this case, we're using the
omit utility type to remove the
ID field from book record and it
returns a new type we can assign
to, a new type called book request.
By doing that, this book request
type has everything in book
record except for ID, right?
So yeah, if you want to add a new
book, to the store, we need all
this information, but we're going to
generate the ID on the backend, right?
So similarly, we can, we have other
utility types in TypeScript as well.
Another example would be the peak
utility type, it's doing the reverse.
In this case, we want to have a new
type called book preview, right?
So what we do is that we
use the peak utility type.
And we take only one field, the title
field from book record, and the end
result will look like this, right?
So we're, operating, playing
with the types, we're using
composition to generate new types.
And, Yeah.
And they can be used like whenever
necessary and appropriate in your code.
And the final example would be the
read only utility type, where if
you use that all the fields within
the original book record type
became read only and immutable.
So yeah.
And, that's just like three of them.
We have like many other
utility types in there as well.
Cool.
So now we have types, but, We
defined the shape of the JSON
objects that we want, right?
But we haven't talked about validation.
For instance, ISBN, that's a
standard for, a serial for the books.
And, it is a string, but it needs to meet.
certain criteria, right?
So how do we do that?
Let me introduce you to one of my
favorite libraries in TypeScript
that is called Zod, right?
So this is general Zod.
And this is actually
the logo of the library.
So what Zod does is that let's take a look
at this code snippet using Zod, right?
So we're, yeah, as you can see,
it's quite intuitive API, right?
It looks.
like similar to our type
definition for book record before,
but, it's actually different.
First off, obviously we import the
library, we import the Zed object.
I'm saying Zed, you can
tell that I live in Canada.
We're importing the Zed object
from the library, right?
And from there, we're using , like
z the string, Z, the date and
everything, and z the object, right?
So we're calling methods, and as
you can see here, it's a account.
So what we get here, the book record is
actually an object, not a type, right?
Because it's a value, right?
And as you can see here, we are
specifying the I-S-B-N-S string as well.
So all this API.
The that object, the that string
and that thing which we're just
telling, using Z that for my book
record, I want it to be an object.
And within this object, I want
to have these fields, right?
And for each of the fields, I want it
to be a string, and not only string
for id, I want it to be UU ID as well.
Similarly for other id, right?
For ISPN, we're doing a string right now.
We can actually do better by
adding a regex validation, right?
I took this from, LLM, I don't
remember which one, it's probably
not the most strict, regex, but,
it's, it's a good enough regex to
know that, your, the stream being
passed in is a valid ISBN, right?
we're not only doing type.
Here, we're on, we're also doing
validation, like how we want the string
to look like when I get the payload.
And again, remember that it is constant.
And this is a value, right?
It is an object, not type yet.
Cool.
So we have, once we have this
object called book record, what
we can do is that we can use that
to validate, other objects, right?
In this case, I'm using
the book record object.
object and I call the
parse function on it.
And then I'm giving it a
like arbitrary object, right?
This object, obviously it
won't pass because first off
it's missing a few fields.
And secondly, the other ID is supposed
to be a new ID, not a one, two,
three, another random string, right?
So if I call book record up parse, and
I pass in this object, the validation
will fail so that we know that this
particular, single field object
with other ID is not what we want.
You cannot send this to
my backend server, right?
Cool.
So we have this book record.
Again, it is an object and we're using
all the magic from the Zot library.
And I'm about to show you
like more magic over here.
So what we can do is that book
record, with the smaller case
letter B, that is the validator
object we can use to validate.
other objects, right?
But we can also use the z.
infer method from the library as well,
and I pass in type of, this object.
It will return me a type.
I'm talking about type Right
now, not object anymore, right?
So Zot can infer a type from the
validator object that we defined earlier.
And the type, as you can
guess, it looks like this.
It has all the field and
type requirements, right?
So, where to use that?
obviously, we use this book record
validator object to validate.
other objects, right?
Whereas this book record with type
capital B, we use this type, we can use
that to specify, in our methods, in our
handlers, where we're never appropriate.
So that we know that we're expecting
such a type in TypeScript, right?
So Zot gives you both the power of
doing validation as well as inferring,
types from those validator objects.
Okay.
Thanks.
Cool.
So another example, similar to
before, what if I'm creating a
new book in the store, right?
So it's very similar to utility
types, but this time around we're
doing again, the object first.
So we already have the book
record validator object, right?
So it has all the fields, including ID.
Right now I can create another
object called book request.
And I'm calling the omit method
from the, the book record object,
and I'm just kicking the ID
field out of the thing, right?
Then this book request, it is also a
validator object that can be used to
validate in this case request, because
in the request, We don't want ID.
We don't want the client
to specify an ID, right?
And then again, we can use the infer
to infer what, infer a type for
the book request validator object.
And that gives us the book
request type, as expected.
so super powerful.
And, that's just scratching the surface.
You, if you go through the Zot
documentation, you see a lot of
like magical combinations, helpers,
different methods that you can use
to, construct your validator objects
and infer type from the objects.
That's awesome.
so far, so good.
What we have right now, we,
by writing the code, we.
We have the request validator object.
We have one for book, you
can define like many more.
So we have the validator object as
well as, the inferred type definitions
of the book record the book request.
So yeah, we're about to, get there.
We have things to validate for,
things like request, And I'm
going to show you how to use it.
So this is a, an API that
I'm going to show you.
It's called drizzle.
And it's actually this drizzle.
it is, one of the hottest, ORM right now.
So let's see what drizzle can do.
So drizzle is an ORM.
So it is supposed to be used
to work with databases, right?
And as you can see, the API is similar.
We're creating like a
book table, called books.
And what should be contained
in this, book table?
We have similar things, the ID,
the title, the other ID, right?
And this API, it's very intuitive
because, it matches what we
would see, in the database.
So we specify the primary key, all the
fields are non null, I like non null.
And, We have like different
mode for, for the types as well.
because this could be a stream,
but we're specifying like,
treat this as a date, right?
Yeah.
So that's cool.
but it is the kind of the table
we define in the database, right?
So yes, database can have like many
constraints, like primary key, like
not no, but It will be a little bit
hard to do the validation, like what
we did with ISBN on the database.
level, right?
Yeah.
You can, in, in Postgres, you
may be able to, define like
a custom type to, to do that.
But, yeah, another way to do this,
to do the things that we add a
validation layer for our table as well.
So again, this is, code
snippet using drizzle and we're
defining the table format.
Once we have the table
format over here, right?
That's the table format we
defined in the previous slide.
We can also use the integration,
Drizzle and Zod, the two libraries,
like they were very considerate.
Drizzle made this, integration
with Zod as well, right?
So we have the table layer, right?
But we can also define an insert
schema that adds more validation
before the insertion, right?
And it will be based on the
table schema that we define.
So again, we're using, we're
manipulating this object.
We're using composition and
we're making them, more powerful.
And in this case, we're building
from the ground up because we
started at the database layer, right?
So we define the table first.
Once we have the table here,
we're adding validation before
insertion for this table, right?
So what we do here.
is that, we specified if the ID is
not provided, the in source schema
will do a default of UUIDV7, right?
We also want the book title to be to
have like at least one characters, right?
And maybe this for some reason,
the online bookstore, we care
about books only after 2000, right?
So it's random, but as
you can see, we can add.
More constraint in code as the validation
layer before we do an insertion.
Similarly, we're doing like
a regex for ISBN as well.
And, yeah, obviously if you want to
add a, new book category in the store,
like a new book title, we want the, we
want to have zero copy or more, right?
Not negative.
So stuff like this, some of them can
be done, in the database layer as well.
But, just to show an example, we're
doing the validation, here in code.
And again, this is the
insert schema object, right?
And we're adding validation, but based
on the table definition that we have.
Cool.
yeah, this is just showing that,
something to remember that the book
insert schema will use a default, UIDV7
and, we won't use, whatever been passed.
And yeah, here are the validations
that I just talk about.
we can add over here as well.
Cool.
So now we have the books, the
table schema definition, right?
From the previous slide.
And this insert schema is what
we have, from the previous slide.
So what, so again, book insert, we
have the ID, using default UIDV7
already, but for the book request,
for a request that is creating a
new book title in our system, we
still don't have And the ID, right?
So that's one thing.
Another thing is that in the
insert schema, we're already
specifying that the publication
date needs to be a date, right?
But when the JSON comes
in, from the request as the
payload, maybe it is a string.
So what we can do is that we, again,
we operate on this object again, right?
So based on the book insert schema,
because insert that's the last step
already, before the insertion, right?
So the request is what's, what
we get, from the, from HTTP, from
the client as the payload, right?
So what we do is that we kick
the ID field again, We also keep
the publication date, right?
Because in book insert schema,
this field is off type daytime,
it's not string anymore.
And then here we reset the key.
This is dumb, but just show like what you
can do with, with Zod and drizzle, right?
So we set the key back
again and we parse it.
From the original string from the request.
And if the parse successful, then
it turns to a date, but if it
failed, then, we reject that, right?
So now we have three objects.
not types yet, right?
So we have this books, the table
definition, we have an insert schema,
that is what we need, what we can,
do validation before insertion.
And we also derived like the request
schema from insertion by, kicking
some of the fields and doing some
like transformation in here, right?
as you can guess, now
we can infer the type.
that from the objects from the validation
objects that we defined before right
for book insert for book request we
can infer the type as book insert and
book request and as you can tell as
you can guess this is equivalent to
this if you write it by hand it has
everything it has the title but it doesn't
have id right yeah, that's amazing.
Let's recap again, what we have, right?
So by doing the, by doing Zod and by
doing Drizzle with Zod, what we achieve
is that we have two layers of validator.
objects and their corresponding
type definitions, right?
So one layer is for request is
like what we get from the client.
And one layer is what
we do before insertion.
one may argue that do you need those
like many layers of validation?
Yeah, it will consume like some
of the computation for sure.
But, depending on like how
paranoid you are or like you're
the system requirement, right?
So I do validation
everywhere when necessary.
And this is just showing that from
the request layer down to the.
Database layer, we all have validators
and their corresponding type
definitions and the type definitions.
We didn't write by hand, right?
They're all inferred from
those validator objects.
Cool.
Next up, let's put this, these things that
we have into a more, into a server, right?
So the server, library I'm
going to use is called Hono.
And, it is, getting traction now
as well, because this framework
uses only standard web APIs, right?
So it runs on all the JavaScript,
TypeScript runtimes, like node,
like DNO, like BOM, right?
Like whole node is like right ones
run anywhere in the JavaScript,
TypeScript runtime world.
Awesome.
So here is a simple, whole new
app and, it's quite intuitive.
We create an app and we define the route
and the handlers for this app, right?
So we have because we've been
talking about the bookstore, right?
We have one endpoint that allows,
maybe our internal user to create
a new book title in our system.
So we accept it as the post method,
and we're using another yet another
integration called the, the whole nose
odd validator integration over here.
So what we're doing here right now is that
we use the, we're buying the validator.
So when the request comes in, It
will validate the JSON payload using
the book request schema, right?
So if it doesn't pass, if it doesn't
pass, the, it doesn't have like
enough fields, and maybe the ISBN
doesn't match the regex, it will get
rejected before moving forward, right?
So that's like the guard here.
Now we feel so confident that whatever
we get out from the C request valid,
Method is a valid book request, right?
So again, here I'm using
the validator object.
And I pass it to the
Zot validator for Hono.
So it does the validation automatically.
And here, this is the book request
that book request type that we
inferred from the book request
schema validator object, right?
This is quite amazing
because we do the validation.
This is just an object, right?
It's just like a validator object, but
we can know that after the validation
is done, we should get a valid object
called, validate the request and it
has to be of this inferred type, right?
Cool.
So that's the request validation layer.
And moving along, we can,
this is automatic, right?
But before insertion, if you're
paranoid, you can use the book
insert schema validator object
to parse this request again.
Remember what this does?
This actually adds the UUID.
for the ID field, right?
Because in the book request,
we don't have that, right?
But for the book insert
type, we have the ID, right?
So yeah, you can say that it is a
parse or a validate, but it's not.
Yeah, it does the, yeah,
it does the validation we
defined for the insert schema.
And one of the things that it does is
to add the UID field there as well.
Cool.
So here I'm not actually doing the
insertion, but you have to grasp, right?
Cool.
So this is the one endpoint server app
that we built and it's folded, right?
So what else we can do?
I talk about the validation and the
request layer and the database layer, but
we're talking about full stack, right?
So that's for this code here as well.
What we can do is that we can actually
export a type and we just directly
call the type of function on the route
that we defined for our application.
In this case, we have only one
endpoint and it needs to, it
accept a request that conforms with
the book request schema, right?
So we can export this type
and that's the server side.
On the client side, Hono also provides
this tool where, this is the server type
we import, from the export over here.
And then Hono also provides
you a client, right?
And with those two things, what we can
do is that we can use this Hono client.
And we specify by using the
angle brackets, the server
type, we just export it.
And then we give it an endpoint.
In this case, the server
was running here, right?
So 3000.
So we specify the endpoint here as well.
What we get this client is a strong
type strongly typed client, right?
It knows that it has
endpoints like dark books.
And you can call post on that.
And, this endpoint only
accept a JSON like this.
So if I make any mistakes, say
if I mistyped, I'm using the S
I'm using a get, or I'm, using a
different field name or whatever.
From a type perspective, it
will immediately know that
I made a mistake, right?
Because again, this type is inferring,
like from the server, like what
I can do, it is that powerful.
So if you code this, from your server
side, switching to client side, all the
validations we just built, you feel so
confident building applications, right?
And again, let's recap.
So before we have this, we have the
request validator object, we have the
record, the before insert validator object
and their corresponding types, right?
And it talks to say your primary
database Postgres in this case.
Now we also have a front
end client object, this guy,
which is also strongly typed.
And he knows like which methods, which
endpoints, It is allowed to call and
what kind of objects you need to pass in.
So yeah, it is that powerful.
Cool.
So since I'm working with dragonfly,
I wonder if, there's such a thing
for cash as well, because we have to
request and, we do the validation and
before insertion, we do the validation
and it goes to the primary database.
What about, what if like we need to cash
some of the data and does it have some
sort of things that's similar as well?
it turns out that we have library, called.
Redis OM, and it is an object mapper
for, in memory data stores like,
Redis, but because Dragonfly is
compatible with Redis, you can use
this library with Dragonfly as well.
But unfortunately, yeah, we can define
schema very similarly, but unfortunately,
we don't have integrations with libraries.
We like Zod at the moment, yet.
So with that said, we can still.
Define a schema and you can do it stores
the data as the Jason data type, in ready.
readies uses modules to support
things like Jason search time
series and those kinds of stuff.
Whereas in dragonfly, Jason
and search are native building.
So you don't need to install
additional modules on dragonfly.
back here, RedisOM is, can be used to
manipulate the JSON type, not the string
type, in, in Dragonfly or in Redis, right?
yeah, so we don't have the validation
integration yet, but I would
argue that, this is also good.
and also sometimes you
don't really need to.
So you need to use like the JSON type
in Redis or in Dragonfly when you need
to manipulate those individual fields.
But if you're doing like a cache, if you
don't care about modifying individual
fields, then the string data type of
Dragonfly might be the way to go as well.
I would argue that So yeah, depending
on your use case, I feel that,
the strongly typed and validated
thing, like across the client down
to the primary database is enough.
The caching layer, we don't have
such a thing yet, it's, it's a
good to have maybe in the future.
And, you can also cache your.
your data as a blob, in a string
data type of Dragonfly as well.
So with that, you have a quite strong
and safe and typed and validated,
safety from your client side to the
server side and then to your data layer
like Dragonfly or Postgres, right?
Cool.
So yeah, if I work in code base like
this, at the beginning, it's a little
bit harder because you're always
thinking about the validator objects.
And then, you use the infer function
to get the type definitions as well.
But later on, you feel so confident
because you know that your code wouldn't.
Like they're always validated, right?
And you can't have a mistake by passing
an object that has a missing value that
will be caught at the type level, right?
if you're doing such a thing, cool.
yeah, those are the tools that I
want to share with you and introduce.
to you today, and, just to, maybe you've
heard like other solutions, as well,
things like GraphQL and Swagger, so what's
the difference between the things, right?
to me, GraphQL, Swagger,
they're awesome tools as well.
And if you're using like
multiple languages, they help.
But given the fact that it uses a
DSL, so they have like their own
domain specific languages, right?
So you need a way to work with them.
Work with the GraphQL, schema, work
with your like Swagger schema and
maybe do some code generation, right?
Whereas in our case, we didn't use a DSL.
So that's one less thing to worry about.
Another alternative is maybe you've
also heard of is called TRPC.
it can do the client
server type safety as well.
but compared to the tools that
I introduced, one drawback of
TRPC is that it doesn't, expose
a standard HTTP API, right?
So what we use like whole node backend,
it still uses the standard HTTP API.
So if you're the only consumer of your
API, then TRPC might be a better solution,
but, in the future, if you anticipate
other people to consume your API as well,
then you know, our way could be better
because, you as the consumer, you still
have the full type safety, whereas other
consumers need to look at your, your API
specification and code accordingly, right?
Cool.
With that said, yeah, I think that's a
small, simple example, but we did indeed,
achieved full stack type safety today.
And, yeah, please try those
awesome tools, you JSTS community.
I love them.
And then finally, if you're
interested in doing in memory data,
like caching, like real time stats,
give Dragonfly a try as well.
yeah, it's a great, awesome
project, very strong, very modern,
multi threaded, Redis alternative.
And here's my QR code of my LinkedIn.
If you're want to get connected
with me, feel free as well.
Thank you so much.