Hello everyone and thank you for
joining this Conative conference.
I'm Juhi SHA IEEE, senior
member and director of
Applications Development at a DP.
Today we will explore how agent
ai, autonomous goal-driven
software agents can coordinate.
The continuous co-evolution of
microservices and micro frontend
in cloud native architectures,
microservices give us scalability,
resile, and independent deployments.
Micro frontend extended those
principles to the UI leader, but the
real challenge is synchronization.
How do we keep dozens of independent teams
and components moving at different speeds
without breaking the user experience?
In this session, I will walk you
through the problem, the architecture
of a agent control plane, a real
world case study and future directions
that move software from automation.
Omi,
let's start with the foundation.
The Morton architecture, landscape
microservices, decompose applications
into independently deployable services.
Each owns a business capability, for
example, payment catalog or user profile.
And can scale or deploy independently.
This improves resilience
and team autonomy.
Now extend that same
principle to the UI layers.
That's where micro frontends come in.
Teams can deploy frontend
modules in React js Angular.
And plug them into a shared container.
This gives incredible speed and parallel
deployment, but as you will see, it
also creates an integration nightmare.
Each team has its own framework,
release cycle, and dependencies.
So when one part of the system changes,
others must catch up instantly.
And that's where things start to break.
As systems grow, we enter what
I call the coordination crisis,
API evolve new endpoints.
Renamed Fields different responses,
structures, framework, heterogeneity teams
use react, angular view independently,
manual bottlenecks, QA cycles,
multiply rollbacks become routine.
In large enterprise, you might
have 25 microservices and 10 micro
frontends spread across multiple teams.
Each change must be communicated,
tested, and synchronized.
That coordination effort
grows exponentially.
With every new component, the result,
frequent integration breaks, inconsistent
UX and deployment slowdowns, even though
we moved to microservices to go faster.
Let's zoom in on what I call
the moving target problem.
Every time a backend service
evolves by adding a new
endpoint, modifying a payload.
Or changing latency profiles.
The dependent micro front ends
must adapt almost immediately
if they don't.
Users see runtime mismatches,
broken interactions.
Or sluggish experiences.
So while our A architecture is
decentralized by design, its dependencies
remain tightly coupled in practice.
This is the core paradox.
Of modern microservice ecosystems,
we have gained team autonomy,
but we have also inherited a
constant chase to stay in sync.
Enterprises running 25 plus microservices.
10 plus micro front ends
phase a mathematical explosion
of version combinations.
That's why traditional coordination
models, emails, tickets,
manual testing, can't keep up.
We need systems.
That can sense and respond
autonomously to this constant movement.
So how do we bring order
to this moving target?
The answer is agent ai.
These are autonomous software
agents with three core capabilities,
perception, reasoning, and action.
They perceive the state
of the system monitoring.
Backend APIs, frontend
matrix, and telemetry.
The reason detect schema drift or
behavioral anomalies and plan adoption,
they act.
Apply validated changes with rollback
mechanism, if anything, violates policy.
Essentially, we are teaching a
software to self-diagnose and
self-heal just as autonomous vehicles.
Perceive and navigate their environment.
Urgent AI agents navigate
code and configuration changes
to keep systems aligned.
The Agentic control plane or a CP.
Is the framework that
orchestrates these agents.
It has four plates.
The first one, observation plane
collects telemetry through open
telemetry, API, gateway logs.
Real user monitoring data.
This is how the system sees itself.
The second one, cognition Plane host the
AI Brains Reinforcement learning agents.
Optimize scaling and configuration.
LLM agents generate
code or config patches.
Contract agents monitor schema capability.
The third one, execution plane.
Applies changes using GitHubs
pipelines and service mesh controllers.
Support cannery and blue green
releases with automatic rollback.
The fourth plane policy
and governance layer.
Defines safety envelopes, approval
thresholds, and auditable logs.
These four planes work together in a loop
of perception, reasoning, and action,
continuously optimizing the system.
In real time.
Let's see how these comes
together in practice.
So the first one is drift detection.
The observation plane notices a
schema change, perhaps an API field.
Has been renamed.
The second one, impact Analysis.
The cognition plane identifies which
UI components consume that field.
The third one, solution
generation, the LLM agents.
Suggest a minimal code diff or
adapter to restore capability.
The fourth one, safe deployment.
The execution plan deploys
it to cannery environment,
the fifth one, validation and rollout.
Service level objectives remains stable.
The change is promoted.
If not, it auto rolls back.
What's important is that no human has
to manually coordinate these steps.
They happen.
Under governance automation.
Here's a real enterprise
example to quantify the impact.
A global e-commerce organization
with 25 microservices and
10 micro front ends adopted.
Agent control plane
before A-C-P-A-P-I changes
regularly, broke front ends
and caused deployment delays
after deployment.
Adaptation latency improved by 35%.
Front-end errors dropped by 40%.
SLO compliance rose to 25% manual
coordination reduced to 50%.
In other words, they moved
from reactive fixing.
To proactive autonomous alignment with
traceable audit logs for every action.
Let's balance the discussion
with both benefit and challenges
the strategic benefits.
Continuous synchronization between
backend and front end, reduced
downtime through auto rollback.
Explainable auto decisions
are logged and auditable.
Enterprise scalability across frameworks.
Teams, what are the challenges?
Training overhead for re
enforcement learning needs.
Quality telemetry.
Trust building for LLM
generated code, it requires.
Sandbox validation.
Complex governance.
We must define policies that
balance freedom and safety.
This is where the human
element remains essential.
AI augment stream.
Not replaces them.
Looking ahead, this convergence of
microservices, micro front ends and
agentic AI is just the beginning.
Three areas stand out.
Explainable reinforcement learning,
ensuring that the reason behind
every agent action is transparent
knowledge graphs, mapping
dependencies across services and UIs
to predict drift before it occurs.
Federated learning.
Allowing different teams to
share adaptation strategies
without exposing sensitive data.
Our goal is not just to automate,
but to create systems that learn
and govern themself responsibly.
To wrap up, the agent control
plane proves that autonomous
coordination is not science fiction.
It's already improving
enterprise reliability today.
By embedding AI agents that perceive
reason and act under governance, we
enable continuous co-evolution between
microservices and micro front ends.
This is the next step
in the DevOps journey
from automation to omi.
Thank you for your attention
and for being part of the future
of cloud native engineering.