Hey guys, welcome to my talk.
Unlike the future,
built in AI in browsers.
Better start learning to
speak robot, isn't it?
AI is rising.
Everybody know AI is everywhere.
AI even in our everyday life, like
virtual assistants, recommendation
systems, autonomous vehicles, even food.
We have Coke with AI generated flavor.
Come on.
AI these days is not just a buzzword.
Everything is focusing on AI because it
is shaping the future of our industry.
My name is Mohamed, Senior Software
Engineer in Netherlands, ING Bank.
This is the QR to my page, so we
can connect on LinkedIn, have a
chat, keep up with each other.
Why not?
I love to connect to enthusiastic
developers, and you are, since
you are here in this conference.
So what's the plan?
First of all, we will focus on local LLMs.
So and compare them to cloud LLMs
because we have two types of LLMs in this
case, and we are focusing on built in
ones, which is some kind of local LLM.
And then we will make everything
technical, focus on the API and
overview what how the API works.
Then we have some live coding guys finger
crossed for me because live coding is
always so next step Yeah, what lies ahead?
So what is the next step that we can take
or what's going on behind the scene later?
So let's start with local LLMs.
So let me um, Define LLM in a simple word
in a simple word LLM is so simple You We
have a prompt, like, where is Amsterdam?
It goes to LLM, and then it gives
us a response, Netherlands, right?
converting a prompt to a response using
LLM is the one that we are going to use.
In a more technical way, LLM
is a large language model.
It's type of artificial intelligence
that uses deep learning techniques
to understand, generate and
manipulate human language.
So this kind of LLM, first of all,
focusing on human language so it can
generate, understand, manipulate.
So yeah, like the question that we ask,
where is Amsterdam is going to tell us.
So let's see, differences
between local LM and cloud LLM.
When we use local LLMs,
LLM is on our machine.
So the whole, neural network
and the artificial intelligence,
all the technologies that lies
behind would be on our machine.
So we are limited to our machine as
well in terms of, the performance.
But the thing is, there are some benefits.
The first thing is privacy.
Why privacy?
Because when we are using local
LLMs, the data stays on your machine.
It doesn't go anywhere else.
So you shouldn't, send data through
the wire to clouds and expect, I don't
know, as your GCP get back to you with
some results or some other services.
So the thing is, yeah,
privacy, which matters a lot.
It's one of the biggest
advantage of local LLMs.
Then low latency, because everything
is on your machine, low latency,
you shouldn't wait for network
and stuff, internet connection.
So nothing is required in this case,
because everything is on your machine.
And then low cost, because no
subscriptions required for this one.
So because the LLM, it's just
imagine there's a database, the
LLM database is on your machine.
So everything gonna work.
some examples I can say Misrall is
one of them and Blama from Meta.
These are local LLMs.
Cloud LLMs.
Yeah, of course with cloud LLMs you have
a superpower as I mentioned So since the
model would be on your machine in terms
of the local LLMs, but the cloud LLM
Yeah, the model is somewhere in the cloud.
So it could be Super big so it means
that they trained it with more data.
They have a better superpower there
So the other one is network latency.
Yeah, it is Up to date with a lot of data.
It can give you better answers,
but it has latency because you
should send the data over the wire.
So bigger data, slower, bigger
data, it should compute more.
And also high costs.
So it has a cost because we are
using third party services like
Azure or GCP, Google Cloud Services.
That's it.
So in this case, we reach.
But yeah, let's have a local LLM
on our machine and thanks to the
browsers which install on all of the
machines and web application, that the
application that we develop lies there.
So it means that, yeah, if we put
an LLM inside the browser, wow.
So some kind of superpower in our
machine, we can perform some magic.
So let's see.
How does the API looks like behind
the scene, first of all, disclaimer.
for the things that you are going to
see no machine learning is required
So don't worry that you don't have any
knowledge of ml and this and other things
so no ml No machine learning is required
No, ai Knowledge is required as well.
So you're going to see how does it work?
So stay tuned the api is super simple
First of all, you should create a
session Since It is asynchronous.
Yeah, definitely.
We need a wait.
So AI that assistant that create.
So if you grab the AI object from window
that assistant that create, you're
going to create a session for yourself.
So in this way, you can start,
prompting asking question from LLM.
Next step is prompting.
As you see, with the session
that I created, Yeah, perfect.
I called dot prompt and then the
text my question actually my prompt
So where is amsterdam in this case?
So do you remember that
in the other diagram?
I showed you Yeah, the
answer is netherlands.
Yeah Based on the data that the model
has been trained for So the answer might
be different and also a lot of different
parameters, but generally, the data
matters a lot so For me In the test
that I did, it gave me this sentence.
Amsterdam is the capital
city of Netherlands.
Nice.
So with two lines of code,
I could ask LLM something.
So just imagine how, creative could you
be in your applications to, interact
with the user in a better way, gives
them better suggestions and stuff.
So we will see some use cases later on.
The other one, the other API that
matters a lot is prompt streaming.
As LLMs are using generative.
Technology, generative ai, technology,
generative ai, it's, it literally
means generating, then you call prompt.
So it just waits from wait
for the LLM to generate all
the content, all the response.
But if you use prompt
streaming, it's different.
It's the same thing, but.
As soon as LLM, predict the next
token, which is the next word,
just imagine in this case, so
it's going to give you the output.
So this is a, a standard,
stream in, in the browser.
So you can, just await for that and
expect some chunks from the stream.
So as you see, the output
would be something like this.
The first answer done.
Then is.
Then is the capital city, is the capital
city of, is the capital city of the,
is the capital city of the Netherlands.
that's how it works.
when you are dealing with prompt or prompt
streaming, just imagine how does it work.
this is a cool API from the
prompt, from the, built in AI API.
Yeah, no NL, expertise required, no AI
expertise required, no neural networks,
some magics, but to be honest, prompt
engineering can make it much better.
So there are a lot of prompt engineering
out there that you can check them out.
First of all, how to write a better
prompt, how to ask LLMs or what
are the tricks that you can use?
What are you know how LLMs
can answer you better?
So these are all the
things that you can learn.
For instance, one of
them is Nshot prompting.
Nshot prompting.
It's like giving some examples to
LLM Please use these examples and
get back to me like I asked for.
Let's start from the top.
I'm using again, AI
assistant that creates.
Then I'm passing two parameters,
temperature and top k.
So these are these two
parameter are so details.
I recommend you to read them
in the documentation that I'm
gonna share the link later.
But generally the temperature, for
instance, in this case is something
like how creative LLM could be.
Most of the time, if you set it to zero,
it's something like it's gonna give you
the same answer all the time somehow.
And then I initiate prompts.
Some system prompts, some kind of
persona, I give a persona to the
system, pretend to be a tour guide.
And then I give some examples.
For instance, for Netherlands,
if user asks, the assistant
says, let's go to Rijksmuseum.
If I talk about Italy,
say, let's do Colosseum.
see, these are well known
museum, tourist places.
what if, now, I ask something new?
tell me something about Iran.
the thing is, since LLM just
learned that, Yeah, my user
expects this kind of sentence.
Let's go to somewhere!
yeah, the answer, the response
in this case would be, Yeah,
let's go to Grand Bazaar.
Why not?
So nice.
That's how it works.
So it's one of the, techniques to improve
your prompts, which is nshut prompting.
So it's time for some live coding.
Finger crossed.
Let's see what do we have.
I have a simple form at blog post.
I'm gonna put my context
and tags for that blog post.
So let's use.
The API that we just learned, just
improve our application simply.
So you remember what was the API, right?
So it means that if I want to run the
API, I should run it on the text change.
So let's see the code that I have.
Really straightforward.
Add event listener on the
inputs of my text element.
Nice.
So far so good.
In the prompt function, I
have an asynchronous function.
I am awaiting to create a session.
Simple.
Then.
I'm prompting my LLM, my local LLM.
So my, my prompt is something like this.
You are an author helping people to find
the right tags for their blog posts.
nice.
Some kind of a persona.
Consider the following text and
suggest tags for it in a JSON format.
Yeah, every developer's
favorite format, right?
Is it?
Yeah, anyway.
So I'm gonna put the text
inside, an html type XML type.
It could be anything.
It could be back tag, backpack
tick or something else.
But to be honest, I prefer in
this format because LLMs most of
the time understand it better.
So I'm awaiting for the response,
getting the response and just like it.
So let's see what do we get from the text.
First text is AI is awesome.
Let's see the console.
Come on Oh, yeah, as you see it
took a little bit time and it makes
sense because it was Computing
on my machine with all the stuff.
Yeah, it is somehow in json format as you
see It gave me in a markdown format, which
we are gonna trim it But yeah, we have an
object full of tags For the AI is awesome.
It detects artificial intelligence.
Nice, an AI tag.
Yeah, nice.
So we are gonna show tags
here for Our application.
I am so happy to be here.
Let's see.
Okay.
yeah, in food.
Come on, because I'm just, typing,
it's gonna run the function
on each of my, pure press.
So that's why you can
see a lot of logs here.
yeah, the last one is
this one, yeah, happiness.
Yeah, it could be.
Okay.
a good tag for my blog post which
contains this text at the moment
Or it has a lot of others as well
sentiment tone emotions nice.
But anyway, this is the last one and
the most accurate one because right?
Yeah at this time it had all the text.
So let's use it.
So I want to extract tags, right?
so My response contains some
backtick and the JSON in the front.
So let's replace them.
I'm going to use regex, find all
the backticks and just move forward.
Everything that you
found, replace it with.
Nothing.
So these are the tags.
Yeah, the tags string.
So let me parse it with json.
parse as well to make
it a JSON, an object.
And let's log tags for myself.
Let's see what do we have in the browser.
So text is happy.
Yeah, nice.
Thanks.
Happiness.
Great.
So far so good.
what else?
So let's have a four loop our tags.
Nice.
I have a UL here.
Name tags.
I'm getting it by.
Id You have tag element.
So let's me create an li.
Oh, nice.
Nice.
Thanks copilot.
We have an li, set the text content to
the tag itself, append it to the tags.
Let's see the result.
Refresh.
Happy.
Yeah, live coding.
You should wish me luck,
but why you didn't?
Anyway, let's see.
Let's see.
What's the problem?
Let me put a log here.
Nice tag element append.
Okay, li create element li.
Yeah, everything makes sense.
I just want to make sure that we
have some content for the tags.
So yeah.
Oh yeah, guys, tags.
It has the property tags.
So yeah, so I'm gonna just put tags there.
So right now we have tags.
So everything makes more sense.
Let me go for happy.
cool, cool.
Yeah, happy.
Yeah, see, yeah, since I was typing.
So yeah, music happiness.
it's all those prompts that
it was doing during my typing.
So I can do two things.
Let me go for tag element
in our HTML empty.
Yeah, because each time
I should clear the list.
So even I can set a loading or something
which doesn't matter in this case.
Yeah, happy So okay.
Oh, yeah, it's working.
It's working.
Anyway, you can see happiness here
So if you want to create a tag, you
can you know Use this suggestion
link to create a tag and also as
these are just redundant, right?
So I have already loaded the
low dash here for myself.
So yeah easily let's use And the
bounce from low dash put it to
200 300 millisecond something like
that to, just debounce all of them.
So happy.
Yeah, just one super fast because
yeah, there aren't a lot of prompt
to my LLM, which is my computer.
So it's going to make it slow.
So on and so forth.
So easy peasy.
So as you see, with just, i dunno,
from 55 to just 85, 20, 25, 30
lines of code, simple codes.
So I just could to, I could prompt
LLM, get some tags for my blog
post and just suggest them to the
user, make my user's life easier.
So everything is great.
Let's try it out for the last time.
AI is.
Awesome, I am presenting at
conf.
Let's see, what are the
tags that it suggests?
Conference.
Yeah, technology, artificial
intelligence, conference.
Yeah, good.
So it means our application is
working in the way that we want.
And yeah, that's it.
So let's move on.
So maybe you wonder how
did I oh, I'm sorry.
So I'm gonna start right now.
Okay.
So yeah after the demo So we can
cut it and right now the second part
So maybe you wonder how did I
set up this API in my browser?
First of all download
Chrome Canary or death.
It doesn't matter for sure latest
version So if you go to this, url,
these are internal urls of the Chrome
colon slash flags and if you search for
prompt api for gemini nano Yeah, just
make it enabled and also another flag
in the flags url optimization guide
and device model So you should enable
that one as well enable bypass perf
requirements Who named it like that?
Anyway, The last Thing that you
should do, and actually it is
one of the most important one,
is downloading the model itself.
if you go to Chrome, URL Components,
so you will find, this name,
Optimization Guide Ion Device Model.
just click and check for the update,
so it's gonna No check for sure.
There is no, model on your machine,
so it's gonna start downloading.
So we just need internal connection
for the first time to download.
So it means that later on, if somebody
wants to use the API, the model
has been downloaded and can use it.
So what's the next step?
What lies ahead?
One of the most important thing
step after my talk after the
thing that we just learned is you.
So I want you to join built in A.
I.
Program from Google.
This is the U.
R.
L.
This is the Q.
R.
Two.
that page just joined the program so we
can, help each other understand more.
Look what's going on.
If you face an issue, because we
are talking about the future, right?
Since we are talking about the
future API that is coming, so for
sure it's not, a stable even from
time to time I face issues as well.
So keep in mind it is very important.
So to, just make your hands dirty
with the code to experiment it.
So this is the URL and QR.
So thanks for joining.
And also, From time to time people
ask me, so how do you see this AI?
Where does it go?
Will AI replace us?
To be honest, I always believe
in this sentence The best way to
predict the future is to create it.
So Right now we have the API, we
have the AI, we have the LLMs, we
have the APIs, everything is there.
Come on guys, we are living in
a world full of, innovations,
APIs, so let's keep it up.
just try to use the latest APIs and
stuff and start learning, create
something, it shouldn't be production
ready, something, or it could be
even one simple page for yourself.
yeah, why not?
Let's start using these features.
And in this way, You
can predict the future.
You can see what are the
features that are coming.
So in that way, yeah, you can
adapt yourself to the future.
So sooner or later, if something happened
to our you, industry because of the A.
I.
So you are ready for that, at
least before that predict that.
So let's see some use cases off this A.
P.
I.
For instance, classification, tagging,
keyboard extraction, helping user,
to compose text summarization,
generating titles, headlines for the
articles, and answering some questions
based on the unstructured data.
So you know that, the data in web pages or
PDFs and stuff are somehow unstructured.
So you can, because LLM
understands it better than us.
So it's not something most of
the time, it's not tangible
to our eyes, but to LLM it is.
Also translation between languages, it
is one of those APIs that is coming.
So a lot of features are coming,
a lot of use cases for this API.
So yeah, it's us that we should
think about it and start innovation.
So if we know that this API exists, so we
can adapt ourselves to the newest changes.
So yeah, AI is everywhere.
Let's be part of it.
Thanks for listening!
If you have any questions, my email
is here, also the QR to my page,
all my social media links are there.
I would be super happy to
have a talk with any of you.
Happy to see you guys!
Hope catch up next time!