Hello, everyone.
I'm Crystal Yang.
I'm the CEO and founder at Automy.
And today I want to take you guys
through how JavaScript can be a
powerful tool to solve social issues.
So during this event, we've been
exploring a lot of the technical
capabilities of JavaScript.
But I think it's also crucial to
see how this language can impact one
of the most important areas today.
Which is social impact.
why am I talking about this?
there are tons of social issues that
could be addressed with JavaScript.
The challenge is actually making an impact
when you only have a technical background.
So today, I want to explore how we can
build ventures that integrate not only a
technical background, but also business
principles to create tangible social good.
So first, why technology?
in my opinion, technology is a
great tool for social impact.
specifically, I believe
it's for these four reasons.
So first, technology is super scalable.
you can build technology,
software that can reach a really
large audience very fast without
any limitations of, geography.
that other impact methods have.
Also, technology is really accessible.
So especially JavaScript, it's
very versatile, very web based.
So it makes it easier to build products
that are accessible to anyone pretty
much with an internet connection, which
can really help in reaching unserved and
different communities around the world.
Also, JavaScript is really efficient.
it can help automate processes, do real
time data, and, allow us just to optimize
resources and improve outcomes for users.
And then lastly, innovation, obviously.
Technovation is the hub, in
my opinion, for innovation.
It's like a breeding ground for
experimentation, and it allows
us to rethink solutions to
long standing social problems.
So we have a technical, advantage,
but how do you take a technical
idea and transform it into something
that actually has social impact?
So to do this, I recommend learning
from our business friends and looking at
how they take their products to market.
So building a successful product is
definitely more than just coding.
It's a lot about understanding
market needs and delivering something
that people actually find valuable.
So I'll share my own experience
with Automy to highlight this.
my startup, Automy, is actually Started
as a small JavaScript project actually,
and now it's transformed into one of the
largest educational game platforms for
blind and visually impaired students.
And today we've impacted over 1000
blind students and partnered with seven
schools for the blind around the world.
So some advice I've had from building
Automy, I think first is to develop
a MVP or as the business people
say, it's a minimum viable product.
So this is a common term in business land.
And what it means is that you shouldn't
build for perfection in the start.
for example, in my case, my first Automy
MVP was pretty crappy, to be honest.
It was definitely far from ideal.
It was pretty much just a program
that regurgitated basic math
problems, and it used text to speech
and automatic speech recognition.
But, I didn't try to make
that product the best I could.
Instead, I took this early version
to teachers that worked with
blind students, And from them,
I was able to gather feedback.
And the insights that they
gave me were really invaluable.
And they allowed me to pivot and create
products that actually met their needs.
So they were able to give me feedback
on educational tools and what I should
do to increase the educational value
of the product, as well as what I could
do to make the product more accessible.
So this helps me build a more usable
and, needed product, which in turn
made it easier to get users and
create actual impact in the future.
So what can you do to
build impactful products?
So first, from that story,
you should build a MVP.
So your MVP should just include
the essential features that
you need to address the core
problem that you're solving.
After you have an MVP, you should
go out and test and gather feedback.
So don't go wait for perfection.
You should launch your MVP to a small
audience and gather their thoughts.
This is because many business startup
founders, especially put in a lot of
effort a lot of work to making one
product and then they realize that users
customers don't actually need this, right?
So people waste a lot of time and
resources into building features that
people don't actually need or even want.
Yeah.
to do this, you build your MVP, and you
have to iterate through this process.
So you build a product, you get
feedback, and then you implement
those features, and then you go back
and iterate over and over until you
are ready with the final product.
This is a great advantage of computer
science and JavaScript, actually,
since it's super, super easy to make
changes compared to other mediums.
So for example, if you're like building
hardware, this would be terrible
because you would have to build a new
prototype and then ship it out and all
this stuff that you would need to do.
When in computer science, for
example, when I was building Automy,
a teacher would just tell me like,
Hey, it would be great if you could
make Automy compatible with screen
readers or with keyboard interaction.
And in at most a week, I would be
able to implement their suggestions.
yeah.
There's definitely a great side to
computer science and that helps a lot
with this idea of product and iteration.
So next, I would love to give some
information on how to build a team.
So building a team is really important
because if you want to scale your
startup or your technology, it requires
more people to do outreach, to do
promotion, to help you build your
platform, all this sort of stuff.
So currently, Autumny's team
is actually made up of over 30
volunteers, which is super exciting.
And they're all dedicated
to the same cause.
And building this team,
was pretty hard for me.
I didn't have any startup experience in
the past, but it was really interesting
and people asked me a lot how I do it.
So for me, I did it through, two ways.
So first I identified my audience.
So I knew who I would need to help
me build my product So I knew I
needed developers designers and
outreach people and social media
teams and other people so I only
looked for this group of Team members.
So a lot of people just Take on all
sorts of volunteers just willing to
do anything Like i've seen like an hr
manager at a 10 person like volunteer
venture, but, yeah, definitely
identify what you need so you don't
waste any time into recruiting people.
And then the second thing is how
do I actually recruit people?
So the best thing about having a
nonprofit is that there are volunteers
out there willing to do work.
So on Google's development course,
they actually have a thing where
they recommend people who are just
starting to learn about technology.
To websites such as volunteer match
and idealify that allow volunteers who
are just learning how to code or have
a little bit of experience but want to
find more experience in the real world.
they show opportunities of nonprofits
that are working to improve their website
or just looking for help in general.
So in my case, I was able to use this
platform, to find a lot of developers
and to find a lot of designers who
were then able to help my cause.
So definitely having a 5013C
helps a lot, especially in the non
profit world where you can recruit
volunteers who align with your values.
So those are my two biggest pieces
of advice on building a team.
But at the end of the day, you
need people to actually have
your product to make an impact.
So here's what worked for us in
getting connections with users.
So first.
Obviously, you have to
know who you're targeting.
So know who will benefit from your
project and know how to access them.
So for us, it was blind students and
their teachers and to access them.
We contacted schools for the blind
and developed with our users.
And they were able to, actually
find value in our games.
Again, the second point,
aligns with the MVP idea.
You should be building for users,
not based off of your assumptions.
So you should always build
with your customers in mind.
In my case, I integrated teachers
within the development of Automy,
and it became much easier to attract
users because we were solving real
problems, not just hypothetical ones.
And a lot of times people can use
different, promotion tactics, social
media, community events, word of mouth,
whatever you've identified your audiences,
figure out how best to reach them.
So next I want to talk
about why JavaScript.
JavaScript is the ideal
tool for social impact.
First of all, it's a website.
There's tons of accessibility
with the website.
It's used all across the internet.
As long as you have internet, as
long as you can access websites,
you can use a JavaScript project.
So this definitely breaks down barriers
to access and allows for people all
around the world with connection
to internet to use your products.
Next JavaScript is super interactive.
It's very user friendly and it
can be customized for people with
all sorts of different abilities.
And lastly, JavaScript is
able to be integrated with all
sorts of other technologies.
So currently, for example, if you want
natural language processing in your,
in your code, you can integrate, chat
GPT API into your JavaScript programs.
if you want to integrate hardware,
you could easily code some sort
of hardware compatibility that
can interact with the JavaScript
backend and overall JavaScript just.
makes it easy to combine
different languages and tools
with back end systems of websites.
this would allow developers to just
create innovative social solutions
tailored towards social impact.
to wrap up, JavaScript is more
than just a technical skill.
It's definitely a great tool
to bridge the digital world and
real world social challenges.
And, by building scalable, and
accessible and innovative solutions.
Combining your tech projects with
business principles can create
products to have true social impact.
So I hope you're inspired to keep
using JavaScript in ways that
are not only solving technical
problems, but also contributing
to meaningful change in the world.
Thank you.