Hey everyone!
Welcome to Conf42, the JavaScript version.
I'm Gil and today we're going
to talk about Playwright.
It's called Playwright in an
hour, hopefully less than an hour.
It's an introduction of Playwright.
If you don't know anything about
web automation, cool I hope you get
impressed by what Playwright can do.
If you have experience with Selenium or
Cypress or something like that's cool.
And I'll talk about, my opinion
about, what you should do if you
do have experience and you have
investment in, Cypress or Selenium
or any other framework as well.
Learn what it can do and then
you can decide whether it can fit
into what you're doing or not.
I'm Gil, I'm a trainer and a consultant
and I work with developers and testers
who want to make software better.
I'm the author of two books.
This kind of thing, playwright,
is something that is usually more
connected with QA or testers.
We think about is anything that's
automating the web as something that
automating the front end and we don't
care about what is going on the back end.
We'll talk about that too.
but I find it also as a tool
to help with developers.
they can not only write unit tests.
and test their own either components
or backend, whatever they're
testing, but also have some kind of
mechanism to, do some end to end test
and play right, fits right there.
Apart from, doing some conferences
like I do here, I also have a
blog, a website, testingguild.
com, and I post, videos on YouTube, on
all kinds of things relating to testing.
Testing and automation.
So go check that out.
So let's talk about a bit of history
of where we are and how we got here.
Playwright is a test framework, really.
It started out as an automation
tool, something as a project,
internal project in Google that
became Puppeteer, but it got stalled.
And then, The developers got stolen.
Microsoft decided to, do something
with the knowledge that Puppeteer
has behind it, which is a bad
automation of the browser.
they decided to build a whole
test framework, for the web.
so they got the knowledge, they got
the people from Google, and they
created Playwright, called Playwright.
Launched in 2020.
If you think about it, Selenium,
Cypress are not full testing frameworks.
So what does make a test framework?
test framework, if you worked
with Jasmine or Jest, you have
something that identifies tests.
when it says, test in the file or
specs or something like that, and
you have describe and you have it.
So these are the keywords
that identify tests.
Apart from that, you have, registration.
Registration is like the fancy name
for when I asked run all the tests
in this module, the test framework
looks at the module, identifies all
the testers, I need to run those.
And if I do run all this testing
module, except the one that starts
with A, that's the registration part.
And again, Jasmine, Jest, they do that.
But if you look at Selenium, for
example, it lives inside Test frameworks.
It doesn't do that just does
the automation apart from that.
Obviously it runs the tests It
reports the results obviously
and have a bunch of asserts.
We'll talk about that as well cypress
has them has those if we worked
with the unit test frameworks like
for react or angular you know about
jsdom which is a part of an engine
that does identification and expects.
So Cypress has those as well.
Playwright has all of them.
So it has a bit more, but
it's a full test framework.
Playwright comes with different flavors.
So I'm going to show the JavaScript
version today, where it started,
but apart from that, it comes
in Java and C sharp and Python.
The main languages that you work with day
to day, Playwright is there to help you.
So how do you work?
You install it through NPM.
It's actually a two step install because
Selenium today, but unlike Selenium a few
years ago, it updates the driver's code.
automatically.
So you first need to install the
pendency and then you have to run
the playwright for the first time to
download the drivers to run the thing.
But then you're all set.
What I'll also show you today is also
working in VS Code and that means I
also work with the extension and the
extension has helped me do Things that
usually I would have to do from the
command line, which I still can do.
So how does it work?
Basically, what you have is,
you have a server which produces
some kind of HTML and JavaScript,
and it runs in the browser.
So far, welcome to the internet.
You know how it works.
If you want to automate that,
then you have to have some kind
of a test framework, a runner, a
playwright, which runs a driver.
This driver connects to the browser
and can, Knows what the HTML, DOM is
so it can query it and find things on
it and run, JavaScript, scripts on it.
That's basically it.
That's what this web
automation does anywhere.
Playwright does it as well.
So apart from that, it
also works cross browser.
So it supports the major
browsers out there.
I'm going to share with you today
with Chrome, Windows, Slash edge,
which is chromium, and it also works
with Firefox and Safari as well.
It has some mobile emulation
features that you can specify like
the viewports and geolocation.
I'm not going to show you
today, but it's a bit of a the
thinking behind playwright about.
Not just having a test framework,
but like something that it's
more of an end to end framework.
We'll talk about that as well.
Basically what we're going to write in
the test is find what we call locators,
things on the screen, and automate them.
One thing to already mention,
that's true not just for Playwright,
but for other frameworks as well.
When we are automating the browsers,
we're running on two different processes.
And that means we are sending
messages from the Test framework
to the browser, click this button.
So it's not a synchronous command.
Things will happen and then sometime
in the future we'll get response.
Yes, it got clicked.
This asynchronicity is baked into
playwright and we'll see that
immediately, but we need to think about
it and understand what does that mean.
We can do something about the browser,
but what happens on the backend
is completely Out of our control.
Okay, so let's start.
I'm going to switch to VS Code.
I'm running a local, as you can see,
a local application that I wrote.
It is a registration application,
not a very smart one.
It loads up like this with the
first name, last name and email.
Checkbox for I want to get promotions too.
Unchecked for I have read the
whole terms sheet and agree.
Now, I'm if I have to check the term box
in order to make this enabled, if I try
to register with one of the boxes empty
or with an invalid email, I'll get an
error here, which was not the beginning.
And if I type everything correctly,
everybody loves live coding.
So if I do that and press register,
what happens that you don't see it
here, but it redirects to another page
tells me, thank you, Gil, first name.
And it also stores these details
in a JSON database locally.
That's what it does.
So we want to automate that.
So before I jump here and show
you the tests, I'm going to jump
into the configuration file.
you get a play rank, play right
config, file, which you can
define all the defaults there.
I'm not going to go through everything,
but what is interesting is the test
deer, where it can find the tests.
It looks for them, which you
can put separately from the
unit test that you're running or
other tests that you're running.
The base URL, which is currently a
local host with port 3000, which is,
will come in very handy in a minute.
it tells other projects you'll
have every browser that you
want to run each test with.
so I have Chromium on and I,
commented out, Chrome, Safari,
Edge, and the branded browsers.
so when I run it once, but it can
run, multiple times and web server,
which is something interesting.
A very cool feature I think is that, if
you can't connect to a remote, server
that's running, you're serving your web
pages, You can run it locally or another
web server, and it does this that if
it finds it where you look for it, it
will run against the remote server.
I will run it locally, of course, but
if it doesn't, it can fall back to a
local server, start its own server,
run the test, and then complete them
and shut it down, which is very cool.
I showed you the base URL
because I'm going to use it in
my Test so I have two tests here.
you can see, I'm test here is not coming
from anywhere else, but play right.
It looks like jest or something like that.
but it's not.
So it's a test.
The first test is, make sure that
everything loads up correctly.
You can see that it has a test name.
Something very weird
here injecting a page.
object, which comes
from Playwright as well.
Now we start working with the page.
The page is basically the main
object that we're working with.
we pay, do page go to, to navigate,
and you see I'm using slash because
I don't need to specify the base URL.
It's in the config, so that's very cool.
It makes a lot, the test
a lot more readable.
I don't need to return
everything with, with every test.
So I navigate to the page, find things,
I am finding the welcome text here.
this is, let's go back.
This is the welcome text and
the checkboxes and the buttons.
And we'll talk about GetByText
and GetByRole in a minute.
And I'm expecting the title to be
visible, promotions to be checked
and the button to be disabled.
If you work with Cypress,
this looks very interesting.
Similar to what we have here.
Same with Js O, awaits because
everything's going to be
as synchronous, by default.
Just works like that.
For the next text, I have
the registration process.
I go to the pay CRL, find
the things, the checkbox, the
buttons, text boxes, and so on.
Check the fo checkbox.
'cause I don't want, I want to
enable the button, fill in the data.
Click the button and you can see that
when I click the button, remember
it, never gets to another page.
the page now at this line points to
the next page to the current page.
So there's no like interim thing.
So the page will always
point at the current page.
I need to remember that as a doing thing.
and expect the thank you
message to be visible.
If you worked with any automation
framework before, this looks pretty good.
Very similar.
let me run this for you.
First page, for example, I'm
using the extension, this code
extension, it translates this into
a command line, it runs it, and
you can see things are not running.
And the reason that you don't see
things running is because by default,
Playwright runs in headless mode.
And that means it doesn't open a
browser, which is, talk about that too.
It's a lot faster.
Okay.
How can I run it?
I run it through the extension.
I can run it from the command line,
npx playwright test to run the tests.
I can configure it with
the configuration file.
I can debug it, put a break point
and, right click debug to debug
it as debugging everything else.
let me talk about the local.
server, which is cool.
How does it find things?
So we already saw the get
by role and stuff like that.
I want to show you, these are
the tests you saw that I'm using
get by text and get by role.
And there are different
ways to find locators.
I'm going to switch to my Browser.
And these are the document.
This is the documentation of
playwright, from the internet.
And this is the thing, but locator,
you can see different ways to find
locators now get by role is the.
preferred way of finding things.
other, we can find text by get by text
or label by label, like placeholder for
text boxes, alt text for images and so on.
Test ID, if you use test IDs, data
test IDs, it will find it for you.
But the preferred way or
recommended way is get by row.
Why is it?
first, what is it?
Imagine that we have a button, right?
The button that we have now.
This can be implemented in different ways.
It can be like an HTML button.
Or it could be an image.
It is like replaced when you click it.
Or different ways.
What I'm using in my application
is a material UI, so it's a
component of a button, which has
like a border and stuff like that.
It has a lot of things in it.
So what specifies a button?
the idea is that when the, we were trying
to write a test as if the user was running
them, and the user can identify buttons
regardless of how they are implemented.
getByRole means that find something
that has a role of a button, which can
be like a button or something with a
role of a button, which, today in most
frameworks that you work with, like react
or view will create this code for you.
So you're looking for the roles as
if the user were looking for that.
And then you will look, start looking
for, things that, Even if they're not
implemented as buttons, they will be.
test IDs, for example, are not
something that the user sees.
These are things that are planted
in the code by the developers,
and they can break, and they will
not, probably will not change,
and there's a problem with dynamic
elements, so it's still recommended
to work with what the user sees.
You can also scroll down.
So if you're using CSS or XPath, you
can still use those with the page.
locator method.
but again, apart from being
pretty straightforward.
Third and fourth languages,
that you need to know after
regular expressions, of course.
These are hard to
maintain or hard to read.
And, while they are supported
and sometimes you will need
to use them, you probably want
to use getByRule or getByText.
So that's about locators.
As we said, Playwright comes with a
bunch of expects as well or assertions.
Okay, what's next?
Assertions.
we talked about, the
assertions that we have.
If you're familiar with JSDOM
and its assertions or Cypress,
it has a lot of those as well.
You're probably familiar with,
expect something to be something.
these are, The just things, for
playwright, it comes with expect
to have text and all these things
here to be empty, to be editable,
to be disabled, to be enabled.
You can have to be
visible and to be hidden.
Makes sense.
But you can also have a
way to expect something.
dot, not dot to be hidden, which
is completely like to be visible.
And personally, I don't like
this redundancy, but it is there.
So you can use not for, boolean things.
If you used a locator to On multiple
objects, it will find you those
and then you can expect put in a
certain the one that you're looking
for, or all of them, and so on.
That's basically it about
locators and expects.
So we talked about locators and expects.
We saw that the tests
were pretty readable.
let's talk about what's cool.
So one thing we already seen,
running, with the browser hidden
by default makes things faster.
And I think this kind of speaks
to the, Sort of philosophy of
what's behind playwright and
quick feedback is one of those.
The idea is that we want to encourage
the user, the writer, us, to run the
test as much as possible and I think
from my experience you can do that as
long as you keep your test simple You
can work without seeing what you're doing
which is like a nice achievement for
something that is a visual test framework.
The next thing is something that
if you're coming from Selenium,
you might be aware slash afraid
of, which is called stale elements.
So in Selenium, if you find a
locator or an element, you hold it
in a variable and you can use it.
Of course, but if the DOM changes, what
you're holding is something that is stale.
It no longer references.
If you try to do something with it,
click or query it, it will break.
That will break.
Playwright takes another
different view of that.
So it looks in my code.
Remember, I put everything here to
find the locators, and then I use it.
them.
And then what happens is the
navigation and then page get by text,
finding the message and doing that.
So this is written in
a way that makes sense.
I go to a page, find everything on it, do
stuff, navigate, find things on a page,
the new one, and do something with it.
But look at the magic.
I can pass this line.
Let's first run this to
see that it works as it is.
So there are no see I don't
have anything in my sleeves.
So this runs Excellent.
It works.
I can take this line here
and just Move it up here.
Okay, I haven't done anything but This
looks weird right because it actually
looks for something that is not there
on the first page, but if I run it
You'll see that it actually
works How does it work?
as opposed to holding something in
my hand when I do get something by
role or get by text when looking for
a locator, what happens is that it
doesn't actually look for the locator.
Whenever I'm doing something with
a locator, it will recalculate it.
So what happens when it gets here,
And it says, Oh, I need to do an
expect with the thank you message.
I need to find it first
and see where it is now.
And this is why it works because
these just put a like a reminder
when something look out for this,
somebody will look for it later.
And when you actually use it in
one line, it will actually do that.
This gives us something of an
advantage in writing things.
But for now, I'll just get it back here.
Just to make sense.
So locators are always calculated
at the point where they are used.
Now, remember asynchronicity?
When I'm pressing the button, I'm
not actually pressing the button, I'm
passing a message to click the button.
So what happens is that it will take
time for the button to click, change
how it looks, go from enable to disable.
Lots of stuff happening.
Like I said, until things happen.
Now, what will happen if
the button is not there?
The idea Playwright takes is that
it will probably be there in by in a
few milliseconds or seconds Whatever
you're doing is really timeout based.
So let's look for example Remember
when I'm opening the page, I
want the title to be visible.
Okay, let's inject some kind
of an error in the test.
Let's do put to be hidden,
which of course will fail.
And let's run it again
and see what happens.
Now you see, as I'm speaking, that it's
waiting for it to be hidden, and it's
waiting for a time out of five seconds.
And it tells me, I waited
five, 5, 000 seconds for that.
I expect it to be hidden, but
the final thing after five
seconds was it was still visible.
Now, that means that a lot of the
errors that you will see or not,
I expect this and receive this,
which is what we're actually looking
for, but timeout based things.
So you have to get comfortable
with this kind of error.
The cool thing about, the 5,
000 millisecond delay is that it
doesn't just sit there and wait.
It does retries.
Okay, so what we are calling, locators
are really, auto wait locators.
It actually waits for the
locators by retrying and seeing
if the status has changed.
Okay, now remember the error I showed you?
Let's see that again.
If I click here, this is a dynamic error.
It's not there at the beginning, but
because of the way locators work, only
at the point where I actually need
to do something, I can write the test
as if it was there in the beginning.
So let's look at the errors.
And you can see that
it's completely the same.
I have the error messages, even
though they don't appear yet,
on, they appear only after the
click, but I can use them here.
And I expect the error
message to be visible.
And the way it works is after
I fill it up, it disappears.
So I can check that it's hidden.
Dynamic elements, Make sense in the way
you actually use them and write them.
There is something that
you need to remember.
That's not a playwright thing.
It's a every test framework.
Let me get back to here.
So this checkbox enables
and disables the button.
. Okay.
Now actually there, there is code
that actually does this of course,
but, semantically this enables it.
This disables it.
Remember that We don't see that in here.
So I need to remember that when
I do this, the checkbox check in
the checkbox will actually enable
the button so I can click it.
So for me, I wrote it with a comment here.
But if you don't do that, and I'll show
you in a second where you don't do that,
this kind of knowledge gets lost and you
will lose it as you maintain these tests.
If you look at this test, like three
months from now, you won't even
remember that the connection between
the different components and you need
to do something about it, rename stuff
or put and to make you feel better
when you're coming back to the test.
Okay, so that was dynamic stuff
and, let's talk about isolation.
When I'm running the tests,
each test runs in isolation.
It actually opens a browser in
incognito mode, so it doesn't have any
cache, it doesn't have any cookies,
starts from scratch, no history.
And Playwright makes it that
each test runs in isolation.
Which is good.
We want isolation because then
we won't have tests running
one on top of the other.
We do have the ability to run, to open
different pages, different browsers.
So I want to show you this.
Okay, so let's open Visual Studio Code
and you'll see that I have two tests here.
The first one runs opening the
same page in the same browser.
So let me run this and this time
I'm going to go to the extension.
And run it with the browsers.
So I'm going to run this.
Okay.
As I run this, you'll see
that a browser window opens.
It's incognito.
And I have two pages of
the same application.
This is good in the same browser window.
Let me Close that and
see what we have here.
what we have here, instead of the
page, I'm getting something called
a context, browser context, which
is basically a browser window.
and you can see that I'm creating a
new page, like a first page here, and
I navigate, and then with the same
context, I'm creating a second page.
It does the same thing.
to navigate here.
So this is how I open
two tabs inside a page.
Both are isolated from each other.
The second test does open two browser
windows and in each one opens a page.
So I can do that as well.
This is different from
Cypress, for example.
Cypress runs inside the
browser so it cannot navigate
or open pages or open tabs.
Playwright allows you to do that.
It allows you to navigate forward.
backwards and so on.
Okay, so far we talked about the
basic stuff, also some advanced
stuff, but it's very cool because
you can write a lot of tests,
simple tests as you go through that.
But like I said, Playwright sees
itself as more than a web automation
tool and it gives us a few features
to work with that even better.
The first one I'm going to show
you is The code generation.
Let me show you how it works.
So Visual Studio.
So what I'm going to do is run the code
generation tool from the command line.
I can do this also from the extension,
but npx playwright code gen will run it.
How does it look?
So it opens up a browser window.
So I'm going to mine it.
application here.
And let's say I am
running very small test.
So I'm going to click on this, you can
see that it identifies where I'm standing,
put something in the first name, and
then I have a small ruler here with
this one, assert text and assert value.
So let's put an assert
value with Gil in it.
Okay, cool.
Now, Let's look at what it created.
So this is the playwright inspector.
It's another window that
is run by npx playwright.
and it is where the code is
generated for what I did.
Now, remember what I did was
clicking on the text box.
First of all, writing the URL, entering
the URL, clicking the text box and
asserting that it has the value.
So this is what I got.
Now, as you can see, it's not perfect.
First of all, The name it gives it is
quite generic, but he couldn't really
know it writes exactly what I typed,
but it's not like the base URL when
you're just putting the forward slash.
Also, it identified the text box by
using it by placeholder and not get
by role of a text box, and it creates
a lot of repeats of these things.
the test It's okay.
I can copy it into my suite.
It works.
Perfect.
But in terms of maintainability, you'll
create something that you probably
don't want to hold on for a while.
You want to refactor that, put the,
find the text box by get by role, put
it in a variable and reuse it later.
Rename the test.
The code gen tool actually works.
It doesn't work.
In a way that you'll probably
want to keep this tested.
So that means that whenever it creates
something for you, you probably want
to go in and refactor the tests.
It is good for prototyping something.
It is good for finding an elusive
locator that you're looking for,
but I found, but whenever I used it,
it is a shortcut, but I had to go
back and change a lot of the code.
So that's the code gen tool.
it also has a trace view, which
you can debug whatever the whole,
test that went through cool thing.
I'm not going to show you, but
you can look for it as well.
I want to show you about APIs.
And this is another thing that,
like I said, the way The philosophy
behind Playwright, which is, it's
not just web automation, it's
a whole system testing thing.
And that is true.
When you're testing a web frontend,
at some point you'd like to at least
check things that are not on the screen.
if you entered my application saves
data in the database so far apart from
passing the information of the first
name to the second page, you wouldn't
know it, and the test frameworks
cannot check it unless it has a name.
Some kind of API access to
the server, which it does.
I wrote it.
I wrote the server So I could write
some code with the fetch or access
to get to the server and find things
but can do that Also with what gets
provided with playwright because it has
some API support in it, which is cool.
So Let's look at that.
Okay, so let's look at a test as you
can see these things here Are completely
the same as the visible stuff that
we saw until now, it's the whole
registration process, which is okay.
I want to have that, as well, to make it
past the test and, make sure that we're
passing the entire, set of visible steps.
But after that, I want to check
that the data was actually
saved through, in the server.
And for that, I can use, like I said,
Axios or, fetch, but I have request.
Okay.
Request from playwright, which
is a wrapper for that as well.
So it looks like using pages, right?
Request a new context and I can get and
post and delete stuff and I can use.
the relative URL because I'm using the
base URL, so it knows where I'm going.
And after I do that, I get a JSON, and
I can write some code to compare the
JSON that I got with what I expect.
this is the expect from, from Playwright,
but it Again, it's a regular expected
values, so it's not like comparing
something on the browser, and
therefore it doesn't have to be async.
You don't have to wait for the result.
very cool.
This complementary, it completes
the system testing framework.
And the other thing is accessibility.
Now, accessibility is very important,
especially we're talking visual
stuff that we're testing, it's a
pass, it's possible to check for,
whether it's the UI works for, people
with disabilities out of the box.
Playwright doesn't do that, but
it integrates with a library
called X that does that.
let me show you.
Okay, this will fail.
So I put it in skip.
Let me unskip it.
And what I'm doing here is
basically, using, XBuilder from
the XCore dependency, but it has
the integration with Playwright.
And when I do that, I can write this.
New XBuilder, initialize
with a page, analyze.
Now I have, let's uncomment this first.
So what happens is that when we
are doing analyze, it creates, it
returns an error of violations.
So if I run this,
what will happen is that
I actually get an error.
Okay, because it found two violations.
What are the violations?
So I can actually Let's comment that so
it will get to this line, rerun it again.
And you'll see, what I got was,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
element is It has insufficient
color contrast element, must minimum
color contrast ratio threshold.
So it can, it brings you the whole
library of accessibility rules that
you can run on your application,
different pages as part of your
regression test with a couple of lines.
It's very cool.
Now, if you worked with Jest or Jasmine
or worked with other frameworks in other
languages, you probably saw that something
was a bit different here with Playwright.
And we don't have Describe
or something like that.
And that's not true.
We do have, we want to
group tests together.
The default way is like putting
things in a module and that
kind of relate to each other.
And since everything runs in
isolation, you don't need to
share information between tests.
The describe doesn't make
sense, but it is there.
let's look at.
So you can actually write test.
describe, which has a test before each
that runs before each and everything
that you're used to before each,
before all, after each, after all.
You can actually write tests for
And use the variable in context
of the describe section and reuse
them, So that's not going away.
You still have that.
And you can play with
that as much as you want.
Depending on the context of what is
important for you, it will come out
in the report as hierarchical results.
Don't worry about that.
What is interesting in Playwright
and Canon U is the fixtures.
Now, usually fixtures are We're thinking
about in terms of test frameworks
are the before each before also.
We already seen that it's there, but
these are not your ordinary fixtures.
If you're familiar with test frameworks
like PyTest or the fixture that we're
going to show you here comes from, or
in TestNG in Java, you'll know that
apart from class tests like describes,
you'll have something that you want
to share across modules or classes.
The idea is to share a common setup,
not just in a file, across files.
That's the idea.
And what is this thing?
This is code that runs before the
test and after the test, right?
If you go to the documentation,
you'll see that both browser and
context and page are already fixtures.
But you can build your own fixture.
So let's say, I'm going to show
you an example with a page object.
our registration, let's look at here.
This is like how the code works, right?
once you have the common
locators here, you can write the
tests without the common code.
Makes sense.
But it still looks like this.
If you're using a page object model, a
pattern which basically takes all the
interaction with the page, the low level
locator stuff and expects, you put it in a
class and you expose that class and use it
in the test, it will look a bit different.
So I can write this page object, the
register page, it, Gets the page in the
constructor, has initialization and then
type last name, type first name and so on.
It wraps the operations by using
the locators and operating them.
If I do this, and I can do the same with
the thank you page, in order to switch to
the thank you page, I also have a submit
thing which returns a thank you page.
If I do that, my test will look like this.
Thanks.
Okay, creating the registration page,
initialize, check the inbox, type
in first name, last name, email,
submit, get the thank you page, and
thank you page has a verify message.
And that's very cool, that
doesn't have anything to do with
fixtures, just hiding the low level
information in the page object.
But, let's use this page
object in a fixture.
first I have to write a fixture.
this is a fixture, you can
see that I have, a test which
extends the register page.
This is my code I have to write and
within it I have some something weird.
This is Creating the page object and
then writing stuff that will happen as a
common setup and then run the tests for
the page and then run stuff under it.
After that, I'm not using it
right now, but this is the place
to write the common cleanup.
Once I have this, I can write
this, which looks a lot like the test
with playwright that we've seen before.
I'm injecting the register page fixture.
Everything hidden, the
common setup, is out there.
And look what I didn't show you.
In the fixture itself, I have this.
I have this line.
Now, remember, let's say I have all kinds
of tests I want to do with different
inputs in the text boxes and so on.
In all of them, I probably
want to check the term box in
order to enable the button.
So this becomes like a common setup.
It's not just like initializing.
So if I want to do that,
I can do that here.
And now I can have multiple taps
tests on different files that can
use this fixture all starting when
the button is already enabled.
It is very cool.
It can also be a bit confusing because
you can play a lot with fixtures.
They're cool.
Don't get addicted to them.
So is it good?
first of all, it is good.
It's a good framework.
It's the cool kids on the block,
but it is stable and it works.
If you're starting out with web
automation, I would take a hard look
at Playwright and will probably tell
you, you probably want to start.
It has All the features that
you want, it's complete.
it gives you a complete solution.
You don't have to look for anything
else because the APIs are there.
API supported there.
Accessibility is there.
So get a lot in the box, nothing.
If you already have an investment in tests
that you have a whole suite of tests with
Selenium or Cypress or something else, I
would still tell you, to look at the tool.
To see if it works, you can always start
writing the next tests with Playwright.
But, to tell you to switch everything?
No.
Selenium is moving forward,
Cypress is moving forward.
I don't see why you should drop
everything that you're doing, or invested
until now, and change everything.
For the new tool, because tomorrow
there's going to be another new tool.
Which is going to be cool, and
you want to switch for that.
Currently, I don't think that
I would recommend leaving
everything that you have.
I would look at something that is
maybe useful for the next thing
that you're doing, an investor.
The tests are shorter,
they're more concise.
It's up to you to make
them a lot more readable.
If you're using the code generator,
you are responsible to actually making
it readable for you and your users.
future you and the other
people on the team.
it doesn't come out completely like that.
If you are working with page
objects, continue to work with
page objects, fixtures, be careful
with them because it is possible to
overuse them, but they are useful.
The final thing I want to say is that I
also use them TDD test driven development,
but more let's call it test first.
It's not like TDD.
So you, it is possible to write
these tests up front and continue
gradually adding elements to
the screen and operating them.
but it's not like regular TDD, so you
probably, if you're like a TDD fanatic
like me, you probably want to place the
elements of the screen first before you
start doing that, but after that you can
add more steps, and making a test pass.
So it is possible to use it for And that's
what I wanted to share with you today.
If you don't find me on discord or,
the chat, you can find me on the
internets, find me on YouTube with Dustin
Gill, go to the site and, read what
I blog about and have a nice con 42.
Bye bye.