Hello everyone.
My name is Annie.
I'm Anthropology Interactive.
Today me and my co-founder Adam
Reheated, will be talking about
Level Up, why TypeScript and
JavaScript for gain development.
A little bit more about us.
We started the game engine on development
with what technologies around two
years ago, and he is a senior software
engineer and also product owners
with experiences from Metri startup
in Sweden and also from Spotify.
And.
Me, Annie.
I am doing public relations, UX
designer research and project management
right now, oncology Interactive.
When we are talking about games made
with web technologies, for example, HTML
five, JavaScript and TypeScript there
are several game types that you will see.
For example, it's most suitable for web
and mobile games, the game genres mostly
related to puzzle games, cozy games,
hyper casuals, FPS and racing games.
Who knows in the future what other
types of games you will be able to
make with TypeScript and JavaScript,
since the technology is getting better.
Now when we're talking about web and
mobile games, a lot of the people
are still thinking about, maybe
a decade ago you're playing flash
games on the website and trying to
hide the browser from your parents.
But today it's actually evolving.
There is upcoming huge numbers of
web and mobile game platforms that
are forming and they're reaching
out to audiences around the globe.
For example, poke.
They have very high monthly.
Monthly player numbers and they're
reaching out to players from
over 100 different countries.
And there's also platforms like Crazy
Games who are pushing the boundaries
of the web and mobile game platforms
This year they actually published
an FPS game on their platform.
There are benefits for making games with
web technologies, especially on the part
of the mobile and instant games areas.
For example, traditionally when
game studios are making games,
they're thinking about PC games
and also console games, and, but.
There is a lot of players
who are on mobile and also on
social media platforms online.
And so your gain, when you are making
your gain for those kind of platforms,
you are reaching out to a whole new
audience out there around the world
and for example, discord activities.
Now you can reach out to people
who are already on Discord and
try to publish your games there.
That's a whole new area that
the traditional game development
studios probably are still in
the process of researching and
exploring the possibilities.
Also games made with web
technologies are actually going
into kind of like a new era.
For example, the cloud gaming services
are projected to reach around $25
billion for the market size by 2027.
And you can also starting to make
games where when people are streaming,
there's an overlay where audiences
can play games in the chats.
That's a whole new level of interactions
when it comes to entertainment.
You can also you can also go
into education, marketing,
and rapid prototyping with web
technologies in game development.
The benefit of developing web and
mobile games is about accessible
platforms, platforms that many people
can access without technological and
financial constraints, for example.
Imagine if you can play FPS or
RPG, the best kind of games that
you've been dreaming about, but
they're mostly on consoles and pc.
But now you can play on web browsers.
And what it does is it eliminates
the installation barriers because
you're starting to notice why
are most of the games nowadays?
They require so much space in your
computers and then they expect you
to buy expensive graphic cards in
order to play the games and also.
It also remove the need to
have to buy extra toolings and
equipments to play the games.
It is also very versatile because
when you're using web technologies
to make interactive environment,
it could be games, it could be
educational, but it could be just.
Another 3D experience on the web, and also
you are more likely to be able to access
the 3D experiences and games anywhere
as long as you have internet available.
If you look at the landscape
of web technologies for.
Gaming.
We've had WebGL for a long time now,
and WebGL two is supported in most big
browsers for last few years as well.
And on top of that, we have
Web GBU now, which is also
supported in all major browsers.
WebGL enables you to take advantage of
the GPU to create a high performance.
Graphics.
While they may not be at the same
level as other native applications,
you can get pretty close.
And I think that the capabilities
of them have not been taking
advantage of to their fullest.
And then we have web gpu, which gets
even closer to native capabilities
for 3D rendering, as well as
paralyzed compute on the GPUs,
which can be used in games as well.
So why would you use JavaScript or
TypeScript for game development?
Starting with JavaScript itself?
It can aid rapid development very well.
You don't have any long compile
times so you can quickly see what
your changes to your code is doing.
It is good for smaller projects as well.
It's quick to get started with
and it's good for prototyping.
Can very quickly share what you've
created as a website or upload it
to platforms like Itch to share with
people to test what you've created.
And it can be used in
more applications as well.
So it's very much a general
purpose language nowadays.
And then we have TypeScript,
which just makes JavaScript
better in cer certain ways.
It's better for larger scale applications
because having the typing makes it
easier to understand code basis.
And it can also improve your code quality
and maintain maintainability as it as
a bit like self-documenting on its own.
And also price type safety, which can
be good for reliability to ensure you're
using correct types, especially if
you're working with libraries, so you're
less reliant on external documentation.
So if we were to compare this to
what's traditionally used in game
development, like c plus and C when
we have static typing, so you have.
That in similar ways
as C sharp and c plus.
And it has similar compiled
time safety for types.
If you using types strictly, so how strict
you want your types is configurable.
So you can have very strict type checking
as you can have more relaxed type checking
as well, depending on what you prefer.
And, yeah, this really bridges
a gap between these the dynamic
nature of JavaScript and these more
statically type checked languages.
So you can get the best of both and yeah,
you can catch a lot of type related errors
and just make your code more reliable.
So one thing it can help with
a lot is hot tree loading.
Because it is a scripting language,
it doesn't need to be compiled and you
can easily run it from within an ex
existing application without having to
recompiled entire application itself.
So this can.
Then be used like we're using it in
our game engine in its editor, so it's
can monitor the code and transpire
the code as soon as it notices,
changes, and execute that code.
And all of this happens within a
couple of a hundred milliseconds.
And this just helps you.
See the changes of your code, which can
be very helpful when learning or when
you're prototyping or experimenting.
So you get that quick feedback.
So one of the selling points for something
like JavaScript for game development is.
That it has a great ecosystem and it has
a great open source culture as well, which
makes it easier to collaborate with others
and to leverage existing functionality.
And this is a bit different
traditional game development,
walrus open source there as well.
It is more common to have
proprietary technologies.
And ecosystems.
Many game engines, they come with
their own programming languages
in some cases, and they have
their own version control systems.
They have proprietary file
formats that are very difficult
to version control or understand
or integrate with other tooling.
And they often come with this big set
of tools that you have to learn that
doesn't translate to anything else.
So what you then have with JavaScript,
you have NPM, which has millions of
packages, and you have a growing number
of tools and frameworks that can aid
you, that also can be applied to other
things outside of game development.
One topic that often comes up
in game development though is
performance and JavaScript is highly
performant more performance than
most people often believe It is.
You can write type type script or
JavaScript in a way similar to C
that can allow you to get very high
performance, especially when you
are using like typed array buffers.
The just in time compilation can optimize
it very well, but if you want to have
even better performance, you also have
web assembly, which sometimes runs just
as fast as JavaScript, but sometimes even
faster depending on what you're doing.
And it can be used for certain
optimizations where you need it.
If you're building a physics
engine or some other library
for simulation in your game.
You often don't have to touch web
assembly, but you have that option.
It just allows you to write code in
different languages, like c plus or
C or even assembly script, which is
the super set of TypeScript itself.
Which can then compile to
web assembly and can run it.
And one thing it also enables
is to integrate other libraries
that you otherwise use in game
development, like path finding
libraries or physics libraries.
So you can get sort of the
functionality and the quality of
these libraries that are already
used in other like AAA game engines.
Thank you for attending our session today
and if you want to learn more about web
gain developments and also interested in
our game engine ology engine made with web
technologies, feel free to connect with
us on LinkedIn or checkout our website.
I have included the QR code here.