Hi, everyone.
Today, we are going to talk about how to
3dify your website using reactive fiber.
So before we proceed, let
me first talk about myself.
So this is Alok, your friendly
neighborhood, full stack developer.
And I love JavaScript.
I code, I blog, I write a box and
give talks whenever I get a chance.
So when I'm not coding, I'm mostly
watching anime or jamming to music.
Apart from that, I love cooking
and a fun fact about me that I once
tried to a mountain in slippers.
Mostly people don't believe
that when I say that.
So I always carry a proof
with me that I'm not lying.
So let's move forward.
And let's talk about, what are the
things we are going to discuss today.
So first we will see what are Three.
js, React 3.
5, WebGL, and after that, we'll start
coding, we'll set up everything.
Then we'll create some 3d scenes.
After that, we'll talk about
environment and staging.
Then we'll talk about models.
And, at the end, we'll
talk about deployment.
So let's dive in.
So firstly, an introduction to Three.
js and React 3.
5.
So before that, let's
talk about what is WebGL.
So WebGL is basically a JavaScript API
for rendering 2D In any web browser
and it allows, like it provides a low
level access to the GPU, which enables
us to render 3d graphics and WebGL, is
the basis of libraries like ThreeJS.
So three, as I said, ThreeJS
is, made on top of WebGL.
So it abstracts the complexities
from WebGL, and it makes it
easier to use those APIs.
This includes graph, geometries,
materials, textures, lighting, and etc.
That we'll see later on.
And it works in all modern web browsers.
And Pages has a good
documentation and support network.
So let me show you some examples.
So you will have a better idea
of what I'm talking about.
How threes can be used in live projects?
What are the different things we can do?
so let's first have a look at a
website that NASA has created.
So you can see here, we have one solar
system, which we can interact with.
You can zoom in and zoom out.
You can also click on, like
satellite and it'll take you to that
satellite and like more, clear view.
You can also interact with
the satellite from all angles.
So it is like now you have a
way to interact with the solar
system, which makes it, more.
Easier and also more informatic and
also a cooler way So also one more
example that I can show you which
is a very basic one that I created
a portfolio of mine using React 3.
5.
It's not much just a laptop, which is a
waving through and It has my resume in
it, which you can scroll down and read
also you can interact with the laptop
pretty much this much So there are
a lot of ways, so you might have
gotten a basic idea of what Three.
js is, what we can achieve through it.
You can use models like this laptop.
You can add interactivity like this one.
You can add animations,
lighting, all other stuff.
let's move forward.
So what
is React 3.
0 Fiber or R3F?
So basically when Three.
js started gaining popularity, So the
React ecosystem wanted to integrate
it, with the ease of, component
based, you can say component based.
So it, R3F combines that,
React's declarative syntax
with 3GS 3D capabilities.
It uses JSX and React
hooks to manage 3D scenes.
Now it, allows us to make a reusable
components of 3D objects and logic,
and the best part is that it can easily
integrate with existing React projects.
So before we, proceed to code, let
me first talk about what is Dray.
So Dray is a community where
people are creating help, helpers.
revolving around three years,
which they have hosted, and you
can easily just import those
helpers and use it in your project.
We'll be also using some
of those helpers today.
Let's start and set up everything.
So for that, we'll need, I'll be
creating one Vite project, and then
we'll integrate React 3 Fiber in that.
So to save time, I have already
started, set up one Vite project
with React configuration.
And I have installed the, packages.
So if you have a look, we have
three packages that I've installed.
One is native three JS that we need.
Another one is, react three fiber.
And the last one is, that
we'll be using, for help.
That's pretty much the packages we need.
rest of the folder structure is
similar as any other react project.
We have our, main JSX, then app.
jsx.
we'll talk about this code later on.
I've also started our server
and it is running in, port
5173 right now it's blank.
So there is a blank screen.
we'll start.
the, how the talk will go is we'll
talk about, topic then I'll show
you some code here and, live, you
can see the effects of those code.
So let's move forward.
So before we code, let's talk about some
of the basic components of, three DC.
So firstly, I've seen it, obviously.
So a scene is something like a stage right
where there are different objects, for
example actors Lighting and everything.
So a scene is something which will
contain objects Then we have an object
which is any object like cube or a
model Or your lighting or anything
then we need a camera so that we can
see that stage So camera will be our
point of view through which we'll be
able to see the scene and the objects
And at the last we need a renderer.
So the use of renderer is to Combine
everything and with the render it
with the Viewpoint of that camera.
So let's talk a bit in detail.
So scene is basically, as I said,
a container to contain a 3d object.
And then a 3d object can be
defined using, two things.
Firstly, a geometry.
So geometry is basically the
shape of that 3d object, whether
it is like a sphere or a cube.
And then the material is the
look and feel of that object,
which is like the appearance.
What is the color?
What is the texture of that material?
And when we combine a geometry and
a material, it will create a visible
3d object, which we call mess.
So let me show that with the help of an
example, so we'll have a better idea.
So right now here, right?
So we have one scene, for example, this
one, this whole, sky color area, right?
So this is a scene and there is a camera
placed in front of that, screen, scene.
So with that, the viewpoint of
that camera, we are just watching
at the front of those, this scene.
And then we have a
geometry right now here.
Which has a spare geometry and then
we'll introduce our, material to it.
So you can see we have a white color
material, which has a smooth texture,
which is reacting to a light source,
which is somewhere around here.
So you can see there's a light,
illuminating this area and the
area that is in the backside,
it is like a bit darker.
So this is now combining a geometry
and the material right now.
This ball is a object
or you can say a mess.
So this is the basic 3d, example of, what
we can achieve using these four things.
So let's move forward.
Finally, we'll start coding
and create our own 3d scenes.
But wait, before we write anything
in React 3, if I was, I would
like to show you how it would
have been done in native 3ds.
Basically, how to, we have done
it in like plain HTML file.
So we'll see first how, how much code
we need to create a small radius in
native 3js and then we'll compare
it with how much code we need to
actually replicate that in React 3.
So let's proceed.
So firstly, we need a simple, a
simple file where we'll have our
body tag, there we'll add canvas,
which is basically canvas is the,
as the name sounds, it's like a.
Empty paper where we'll draw our 3d scene
and then, I have selected that canvas
using document query Selector and I've
stored it in a variable called canvas.
Then we are adding one scene
Then we have our object.
So basically we are as I said object
combines geometry and material So
we have one three box geometry and
then the material is basic mesh basic
material we'll talk about this in
detail in the next few slides You And
then combining those, geometry and
material, we are creating our mess.
And then we are adding
our mess to the scene.
So next we need a camera.
So there are different kinds of camera.
So the perspective camera is similar
to, like our eye, which says the objects
which are in far will look smaller
and the objects which are nearer to
us, This will look, bigger than we
are adding that camera to our scene.
And at last, we have one renderer,
which takes canvas as input.
And then on that canvas, it render our
scene with the viewpoint of camera.
This is, the amount of code we need
in order to create a small 3d scene.
Let's see how this thing can be done
in, React 3 Fiber and yeah, that's it.
That's all the code you need in order
to create a replicate everything that
we have seen in the past three slides.
So let's talk about this one by one.
So canvas is a component that will
be importing from React 3 Fiber.
Canvas comes prebuilt with
camera, renderer, and everything.
You don't need to specify it again
or, write it, add it to the scene.
So it has seen your camera and
renderer with some default settings,
obviously you can customize if needed.
Then, we have our geometry.
So torus knot is also
geometry that we'll see.
And then we have our, mesh basic material.
Once we wrap that around, mesh
or we can, wrap it with mesh.
So mace will automatically
take this geometry and material
and it can serve as an object.
We don't need to like
manually bind it, to mace.
So let's see, using an example.
So here in app JSX, I have
already imported canvas.
You can see right from React 3.
5 and I have For the sake of separation,
I have, I'll write the rest of the 3d code
in experience file, which is experience.
jsx and I'm importing that in our jsx.
Let's go to that file right now.
It's empty.
So as I said, we need, a mess firstly,
the rest of the things are already there.
So I will add one geometry, for
example, Taurus not geometry,
and then a material, which is right
now we are going to use miss basic.
And that's
it.
You can see here, we have our geometry,
but right now we can't see it.
Yeah, now you are able to see it.
So we have one geometry,
but it doesn't look 3d much.
So let's talk about these things first.
Then we'll add a few things in order
to make it look more realistic and 3d.
So let me take you to
the documentation of 3js.
So there are a lot of things like
how to get started and everything.
We'll talk about a few of things rest
you can explore so we have cameras
different kind of so This canvas component
has perspective camera by default if
I needed you can explore other Types
of camera and use it as per your need
then we have our geometries So there
are different kind of geometries.
So box geometry looks like something
like this Then we have, capsule
geometry, circle geometry, and
similarly a different, lot of there.
So what we have just right now use
this, this one, torus knot geometry.
So right now we are watching
it from just one side.
So it's not looks 3d enough,
rather just a plain 2d figure.
But we'll soon make it, more, 3d one.
So let's talk about, lights.
We'll see lights later on in detail.
And then we have our materials.
So there are a lot of materials
like, simple line, basic material.
Or the mostly the one that we'll be
using, or you will be using later on is
one is miss basic material, which is this
one, a material for drawing geometries
in a simple shade, flat, or where a
wireframe way, then other one that you
will be using is a standard material.
So standard materials are those materials,
which basically react with the light.
So when we'll be adding light in
our project, standard materials
are those light, those metals,
which will react to that, lighting.
And, so we have one, miss normal
materials, which is basically,
which, material, which shows the
normal vectors to RGB colors.
It's like maps them.
So that you'll have a, it kinds of look
cool, but rather uses is for different
purpose for basically, what we say, we
need it for during, testing purpose or
well development phase, we need, needed
to, look into the vectors, basically.
So we'll be using this materials,
just for having a cool effect.
So instead of mesh basic material,
let's use a normal material.
See now it's looking more 3d, right?
So still right now we are
not able to interact with it.
And also still the camera
is placed in front of it.
So we're looking at the
front of this object.
So let's move forward and
explore the rest of the things.
So now we have, a small basic 3d scene
where we have a canvas and we have added
one object, which is not geometry and,
with the material, normal material.
So let's talk about XS helper.
So XS helper is basically a helper.
Which kind of gives you a visual reference
of all the three x's we have which is
x y and g in our 3d scene, so let's add
it in our project and for that you can
simply just add Access helper in your
simply import it and just use it So
there Is our access helper, you might
be able to see it is behind our object.
So let me just Comment it for
some time See, let me increase
the size of our access.
And for that, it takes and a prop
called arcs, which will take,
the unit of how much you want
to, keep the size of that access.
So I'm giving it 10 right now.
So you can see the size increase.
So this green one is our Y axis,
red one is our X axis and G is
our, which is of blue blood.
it is our GX, but right now you are not
able to see that, because as I said, right
now our camera is placed in just, vertical
of this one, just at the front of it.
So the, blue line that is coming as GX,
it is like perpendicular to our camera.
That's why it is not visible right now.
So we'll see that blue
line just after this slide.
So the next one is orbit control.
So our orbit right now, as I
said, our camera is starting.
For example, this one is our stage and
our camera just placed at the front of it.
So our camera is static right now.
So orbit controls give you that,
functionality that now you can move
your camera from left to right or
interact, zoom in or zoom out like
you saw in that NASA website, right?
Where we were able to like zoom in, zoom
out, we can just playing with the scene.
So let's add it to our project.
And as I said, for to set up
orbit controls, we need a lot of.
But thanks to the people at
Dray that they have created and
bundled it and you can simply just
import it from Dray and use it.
So I'm adding orbit
controls in our, project.
So it's added.
Now let's try to interact.
earlier when I was trying to click on
our scene or interact with it, it was
not responding, but let's try now.
So now you can see, I can
interact with our scene.
So now you are able to right now, I'm just
moved my camera from front to this side.
So now you can see, we have our
Z axis, which is a blue color.
Let's add our scene, our
object back to our scene.
So you can, just, see that our
objects start at the origin, right?
So from there we can, move it,
which we'll see in the next slide.
So now we have our orbit controls.
for the next few slides or rest of
the project, I'm just changing our,
material, basically geometry, sorry,
to some other stuff, the shape,
which is easier to visualize and
see, which is for now box geometry.
Sorry.
And instead of normal material,
I'm using basic material
here.
You can see right as, the whole surface
is plain or we can say, perpendicular.
So it has the same color.
But when, it has a, it had a
curved surface, in torus nodometry.
So for each of the, perpendicular
lines, there were different colors.
So it was, imitating RGB spectrum,
but right now as all this whole
surface is just a plane and all the
perpendiculars on the similar line.
So it is of same color.
So now we have our basic material.
Let's talk about properties of how
we can add color to our material.
So simply you need to pass color prop.
And whatever the color you need,
I'll go with, medium purple.
So right now we have our box
object, which is placed at origin.
If you can see it is like
at the center of our scene.
So now let's move forward and
talk about transformations.
So for transformations, we
have basically three things.
One is positioning where like
we can change the location of
our object in our 3d scene.
right now it is that you can see at the
center we can move it like in any of
the axis Also, we can rotate that object
around it any of the axis and the last
one is like scaling that object Okay.
so let's see these with
the help of some examples.
So in order to change that, We
can simply pass Position prop in
our object and which takes three,
parameters X, Y, Z respectively.
So let me try to move it, on
X axis, one unit and I'll keep
the rest, as zero zero only.
So now, just see that,
this box moved one unit.
On the x axis similarly, you can make
it negative one and it will go to the
other side of negative x axis Similarly,
you can, add two other Axis and now
you can see Our object is like at
equidistant from each of the axis like
one unit from z one unit from x and one
unit from y Okay, similarly rotation
So just instead of position, you can
pass rotation and similarly, it will
take the parameters for X, Y, and Z.
So let me add.
So if you'll see from this side,
so our X axis is going that way.
So I've added rotation of one.
So our object was like, this
one first and it rotated.
On the x axis one so
you can see the changes.
Let me add it one by one like
incrementally you add one
and you will see the effect.
So two, you can see it rotating rate.
Similarly, I can rotate it backwards.
So this is way on the way you can rotate
or move your object in our 3d sequence.
The last one is scaling.
So as the name, as we did with rotation
and position We need to pass scale prop
which will take one, input Like how much
you want to scale your object for let's
suppose consider right now We have one
unit so we can just make the size double
or we can make it half of our original
So that's how basically scale works.
So these are the transformations
Of positioning rotation and
scaling next one is animations.
So animations, like we all know the
basic definition that, series of pictures
when sewn together at like less interval
of time, it looks like an animation.
So that's the same thing here.
We have a code which will
execute on every frame render.
So for example, our renderer is
rendering some frames one by one
after some certain, amount of time.
So we have, we'll have a code that
will render on each frame, which will
give us an impression of animation.
And for that, we'll be using
a used frame hook, which will
basically give access to each frame.
And then we can animate any
object using, by changing the
properties of transformations like
position, rotation, and scale.
So let's, see them one by one.
So as I said, first, we will need, useRAM.
So this one, has two params.
One is state and another one is delta.
I'll talk about this one by one.
next, in order to, now we have our frame.
Let me talk, let's talk about state first.
So state basically, contains the data.
about the scene, right?
So let me console log it and check it.
So if you'll see here we have details
about camera clock or you can mouse
pointer so we have information about
all the different things or objects
in our Scene that we can use to modify
or customize it And also you can see
right now it is, this console dot log
is being rendered on each frame, right?
You can see it's still being rendering
one by one, one way on after, in
each frame it is being rendered.
It will go on.
so let me remove that.
Okay.
Bye.
Or wait, let me talk about Delta.
So what is Delta?
Delta is basically, you can say
that time difference between the
last frame that was rendered and the
next frame that will be rendered.
So let me console look that
so you can see that.
So this is the amount of times,
which is in a second 0 1 0 1 6.
so this is the amount of time that
is the difference between, let's
suppose if I stop, take any two one.
So this one was the frame rendered and
the next one, the frame was rendered.
So 0.
16 on average is the kind of like the
difference between two frames, the
time difference between two frames.
And if we remove our console.
log, so now we have a frame, a
use frame hook, which will, which
gives us access to each frame.
But now we need to add some
transformations in our object for that.
We'll be using a reference.
So we'll create one ref for our
box, which we'll call box ref, and
then we'll import user, from react.
Now we'll attach that to our object.
So now our reference has
been attached to our object.
Now, we have access to our reference and
it will, it has one property called Which
has, other properties, one is position,
then we can just target any axis.
For example, I'm taking X and what
I'm going to do is that on each
frame, I'm adding one unit to the X,
position of our object in the X axis.
So let's try that.
So you can see that right now, our
object just went in the x axis one unit.
So let me just turn it this side.
So you'll have a better idea.
Let me refresh it and
start our screen again.
So it was too fast to see because
one unit is too much for it.
So let me reduce it to zero one, zero one.
Let me refresh our scene.
So now you can see that
our object is moving.
0.
01 unit on each frame, right?
Similarly, So there is a thing
like a unit about unit side.
So there are different configurations
for example 30 fps or 60 fps So if we are
going with, units, then we'll have a diff,
different experience in, these, system.
For example, let's suppose we have a 30
FPS scheme, a screen, and I'm adding one
unit to our, Object on each frame, right?
So after, we can say 30 frames per second.
So after one second, our object will be
30 units ahead of its original position.
And in 60 FPS screen, what will happen
is that after the end of one second,
now, as we are adding one unit and it
has 60 frames per second, so it will be
60 units ahead of its original position.
So these, the same animation will look
different on, different configurations
to, in order to make a similar, give a
similar experience in all the devices.
We use Delta.
as I said, Delta is the time
difference between two frames, right?
But if you're taking, if you're going
to use Delta, then even after one
second, this object here will, the
animation will not be that smooth
in 30 FPS as like time differences
greater in 30 FPS between frames,
than the time difference in 60 FPS.
Between the frame so the animation in
60 fps will look a bit smooth as the
time duration is less So the object
will go like tick but in 30 fps the
animation will be not that smooth
because the time difference is greater.
So the object will move tick But
at the end of the day means at the
end of one second, the both objects
will be at the same position.
So now, even after, we have a different
configuration, but the animation will
look, the same, in different devices.
For that reason, only instead of
going with plain units, we'll be
using Delta for our animations.
So let me do it.
So now you can see our
object is going similarly.
Similarly, you can target any other axis.
Why let me rephrase my scene, right?
similarly, instead of position,
you can go with rotation.
Okay.
Or along x axis, right?
And similarly, you can
also target scaling.
So let me.
Okay.
Since it's like scaling the object
along the X axis and adding,
Delta on each frame render.
So now we have the monkey
king stuff with us.
So let's move, that's about animations,
like how you can, use, use framework.
To get access to each frame then
using a reference we attach to our
mesh which is basically our object
and then we modified our Properties
like rotation or position scaling in
order to create an emission effect
So let's talk about
environment and staging.
So till now we are only kind of playing
with our object not with the Environment
surrounding it So instead of object,
now let's play with our environment.
So first, lighting.
So lighting is to give more
realism and depth to our 3D scenes.
Till now, we don't have
any light in our, scene.
We can say in our 3d scene, but
still we are able to see the object
because as I said Mace basic material
don't need lighting rather my
standard material needs lighting.
So we'll see that There are
different types of light Ambient
directional point and spotlight which
we'll discuss in the next slide.
Mostly we'll be using today
ambient and directional light rest,
you can use and explore later.
So there are different properties of
lights that we can tweak with color
intensity position, and then when we
add light to our, all 3d scene, it now
gives us access to add shadows to it.
As when there will be lights,
there will be shadows.
So we'll talk about shadows
separately later on.
So let's talk about
different types of light.
Firstly, we have one ambient light.
So ambient light is like a general
enumeration that affects all
objects equally irrespective.
Then we have a directional light which
is like a sunlight or a distant light.
So directional light is as the name
suggests it is somewhere As like
sun and it is directing its light
to our object Then we have point
light, which is I said, similar to
directional light, but a bit different.
So it is it emits light in all
directions from a single point.
And then we have a spotlight.
So spotlight is similar to flashlight.
So imagine, keeping a
flashlight in front of a wall.
You will see a round, light, And
apart from those and those around
circle, the rest area will be on dark.
So similar kind of effect
you will get using spotlight.
So let's see a few examples.
So as I said, in order
to, let me remove our.
Okay.
Now let me also remove
our scale and rotation.
So now we have our initial scene
where we are, with our access
helper and our basic box object.
So instead of basic material,
let's switch to standard
material, which reacts to light.
which needs basically light.
so I just, converted our object
from a MACE basic material
to MACE standard material.
Now you can see our object is there, but
even I have assigned a color of medium
purple, it's in black color because
it's not black, it's actually dark.
So as it is dark, we are not able
to see the color of our object.
Let's add lighting to our project.
And for that, as I said,
we can use ambient light.
So now as I added light to our,
environment 3d scene, you can see
as the definition was embedded
light, illuminates our, the whole
scene, irrespective from all sides.
So you can see, now we can see all the
sides of our, object is illuminated.
Let's see then directional light
also, you can play with intensity.
So if I add intensity on suppose
four, you can see the intensity
of the light is increased.
So instead of ambient light,
let's use directional light.
So now you can see, as I
said, the directional light is
right at the top, like a sun.
So the top surface of our box object,
it is now illuminated, but rest of
the sites, it is like still in dark.
that's why it's like black color.
So let's move our object,
light, position off.
So now, let's, I'm, keeping my light
like equidistant at the positive side
of our origin, which is, one unit.
So let's imagine our light is around here.
Right now.
So that's why the light is coming
from this side and you can see these
three faces They are like being
illuminated because our light is
somewhere around At front right now.
So these three faces are illuminated But
the other three sides, which are away
from the light, they are still in dark.
So this is like how
directional light works.
So let's move forward
and talk about shadows.
So shadows as lighting, add more realism
shadows, add more depth and realism to
our 3d scenes by simulating, like how the
light interact with objects right now.
So we have a object and we have
a light, but we don't have any
shadows or other things right now.
So it also helps viewers to understand
the position and scale of objects
related to other object and environment.
And also one thing to keep in mind
that adding shadows is like, more
will take away some performance.
So adding too much of shadows here and
there, like in every object will make
your website, a bit slower or laggy.
So we'll have to keep in mind
when adding shadows, which are the
objects that actually need shadow
in our whole 3d scene, or which
are the things we can ignore.
Okay.
So let's add some shadow, in our project.
So for that, firstly, you will need
to enable your canvas to have the
functionality of shadow and which is
simply by just giving a prop of shadows.
And now our canvas supports, shadows
and next, so I'll be right now.
We have one object.
We don't have anything in
order to capture that shadow.
Okay.
Oh, so we need something like
a ground, below our objects.
So whenever we'll have a sunlight,
so when there is object, it will
cast its shadow that ground.
So let me add a plane just below our,
let me add it first and I'll
explain, which is not much actually.
We are just using it in a different way.
So right now we have a ground like thing.
Let me refresh it and just okay So
it is a like instead of box geometry.
It is a plane geometry Then we have
mesh standard material which supports
lighting which is of green yellow
color Okay and then I have rotated it
along x axis, perpendicularly or Yeah
Like it was firstly like this, and
then I went, rotated it for like this.
And then I have scaled our, plane and I
have just moved it at the minus Y axis
down a bit so that it is below our object.
Okay.
So now we have our plane.
And our setup is ready
to, add some shadows.
So it is simply, all
you need to do is that.
Don't, Tag, which of the objects
will cast a shadow and which has
the object, which will receive us.
So firstly, our light
will cast a shadow, right?
Then this box will cast a shadow
and lastly, our plane that is the
ground that will receive that shadow.
So that's all you need.
Let's see.
You can see here, right?
We have our light here
somewhere one, one, one.
So it is, like throwing
a light in our object.
And then that object is
casting a shadow on the ground.
But, what if instead of a static?
Box, we have a a revolving
or a moving object.
So will that shadow will,
react to that moving object?
Or will it be static?
so let's see that Let me add rotation so
you can see right so on each frame render
that Shadow is again being rendered so
that is the that is the reason because
of which it's eats away performance from
your website So there are different ways,
right now you can see the edges, right?
Of the shadow.
It's a bit, blurry.
So there are different ways through which
you can make your shadow sharper and, or
more blurry in order to save performance.
So you will, when you will be
using shadows, so you will have
to take care of these things.
So that your website don't
result into a laggy one.
Okay.
So next talk and let's
talk about background.
So till now we have our object,
but the background is still dark.
Or we can say there is nothing there.
So we can add background to it.
So first one is like normal,
any color that you need to add.
So end of the day, canvas
is also one, HTML tag.
So you can simply add any
background color to it.
Let's suppose I'm adding sky blue so
you can see now we have our background
color or you can add gradients
or images or environment maps.
So let me add one picture that I clicked
on my last trip as an environment to our
3d scene and let's see how that turns out.
Let me first remove
this, background color.
And let me, and to add environment
you simply need to, as I said, some
very good, helpful people in Trey
have already created that for us.
So you need that, you need to import
that environment component from Trey.
You need to label it as a background
And then it will take a file which
you will be adding it as a background.
So I have placed one
file here in public, pic.
jpg Which is basically a mountain
picture that we'll be using as
our background So let me put that
Okay So let me remove these things
If we don't need any more, sorry.
Okay, let me remove our box
too and also our access helper.
Let me refresh it.
Okay.
Somehow I messed up something.
Yeah.
So let's keep it this
way and let's remove this
access at least.
So now we have our box.
And our background.
So you can see right now,
It a 360 view of that image.
but that picture was not
made in order to support 360.
So you can see that edges are
just trying to take a paper and
fold it and make it like a cube.
That's why like the edges are like
this way, but that's what you got the
idea of how to use environment maps.
You can easily download different
environment maps from internet.
Basically under licenses are free.
So yeah, that's how we add
environment to our 3d scene.
Now let's talk about models.
So basically the 3d scenes that you
will use in live projects, which will
not be only like you sand planes or
any sphere or torus symmetry, right?
You need models, for example,
images, or like we saw in the
NASA one, there was a satellite.
So that is a model that we'll be
using instead of just simple cubes.
So models can be created
using different ways.
one simple way is using a blender,
software, which using which we can
create, models for our 3d scenes,
and then we can import it and use it.
So there are different, formats of,
Models that are supported in 3js.
the most popular one is GLTF or GLB.
And then we have an OBJ or FBX.
So as I said, models can represent
anything from like characters to
vehicles or entire environments.
Let's add a model in our scene to
have a more better understanding
and for that Okay, we need
to use a primitive component.
Okay, so let me first remove the animation
And let's firstly import our model first.
So I have already downloaded
one model Which is along with
the license and everything.
So we have our scene dot gl tf here
with us Which will be importing and
the rest of these are the like the
supporting files of that, model.
So for that we'll be using, use GLTFO.
So let's suppose our model is here,
which is again, importing from tray.
And it will take the path to our model.
So which is basically slash word.
Last scene.
Dot.
So
now we have our model imported.
Now let's add that to our scene.
And for that, as I said, we
need a primitive component.
Okay, which will take object
which is our model dot scene
Okay, so now I have added that
but it is not visible right now.
Okay, so let's see probably Yeah,
so we have our model right now,
but it is like too bigger to
like Accommodate in our scene.
So let's scale it down So as we
already know about the properties
that you can use So scale is one of
them using which we can modify this.
Uh size of our, model or any object.
So I've tried with it with different,
numbers, like when you will be starting to
create or develop these scenes, we'll have
to play around, use hit and trial method.
To get the correct, size or another one is
like you need to make your models in order
to incorporate in your website, so you'll
have to Make it of that size that you need
instead of then you won't have to modify
it here So i've tried with different
units and one that I could find is like 0.
03 Okay, so now let's
remove this box Okay.
So now we have A scene where we
have an environment, a model, right?
Now, can we do everything that
we did with box with this model?
And that is absolutely yes So as we
added a reference we can add here
Let's name it as box ref Okay And
similarly we can access it like rest
of the thing Okay, so now you can see
You We have this word, which is like
how we used, animation in objects.
Similarly, same thing we
can do with this one too.
Also, we can go with position and
now you can see our bird
is flying in the sky.
So this is the way we can
create a small 3d scene where
like it's more interactive way.
Instead of just plain, simple
cubes and other objects.
So let's talk about deployment.
So I wanted to show you that,
now this don't look like a
simple HTML static site, right?
So we have, we know the normal
ways to deploy any site using
Netlify or WordCell or other stuff.
So can, so is it like a different
process to deploy these kinds
of websites, which are like.
You can have 3d assets and
interactive and, such stuff.
And that is totally no, you can,
as simply you created or deployed
other as plain HTML, static website,
you will can do this one also.
So just, you need to create the build
and you can deploy it as similar as like
Universal or Netlify or GitHub pages.
So as we all know, in a bit,
we can create the build.
using, NPM run build, and I have
already done that.
So it will create one test
folder where you will have
all the assets and like index.
html and every code like
compiled and ready to be served.
And then you can deploy this
folder anywhere like internet.
So I've already done that in Netlify.
you can probably.
Take it if it's still live.
Okay.
Let's wait
it for load.
And yeah So this is the same thing that
we just created in our local, right?
So I just created a a dist folder
and created a build and just
deployed it in netlify And now you
can just access it in your website.
Yes, it's it threejs hyphen Dash
talk dash demo dot netlify dot app.
You can open it your system right
now and can check it You And
say it, and this is just a 3js.
There are a lot of things to,
you can explore on yourself.
And there are a lot of
creative ways you can use it.
Maybe let's suppose you have an existing
react project of airlines, right?
You can add a small aeroplane,
3D aeroplane that is like
flying around your website.
Or in buttons or let's suppose
you have one, hotel website.
So you can add a small window, a
small canvas and place it at your
website at the top corner, small
window from where a 3d safe model
is coming on the window and waving.
Sometimes it's coming with a
different days or just saying hi.
So there are a lot of creative
ways you can think of.
You can use 3js in your website.
Either a new one or existing one.
so that's it from my side.
thanks.
Thank you again for being
a wonderful audience.
And I hope you have learned
something from this talk.
you can reach out to me on the cool
learning, which is my Twitter handle.
I'll be always, love to
interact with you and just talk.
So thanks again.
Bye bye.