Hello guys.
I hope you all are well and
thank you for your time.
today the topic on which I will be
talking, is the memory leaks in Node.
js.
So in this talk, we will deep
dive into the, diagnostic and its
solutions, to fix these leaks.
First of all, I would like to thank
Conf42, platform to, to give me this
great opportunity to talk on this
most important topic in, JavaScript.
so let me start by.
Introducing myself.
So my name is Mohamad Ya Rafik, and
I am working as a nodeJS backend
developer at Find My Facility.
And I am also happy to share that.
I was a featured author on T-Zone
with an article which was titled
as JavaScript Framework, the
Past, the Present, and the Future.
I have around four plus
years of experience in JS
and web backend, development.
So let's dive into our topic.
what is, Memory leak.
So here is a brief introduction.
Like the memory leak occurs when the,
program or function takes memory and
keeps it if it's in no longer in.
Use which results to the, the
creation of the system performance.
So in this topic, we will explore,
like what would cause the memory to
leak in this, in, not just application
and their impact on the system.
so why, Memory leak, memory
leaks matter in Node.
js.
I would say the memory leak, is,
is, The memory leak matters in every
language, if you are using Python
or C sharp or any other language
memory, matters, but why most, matter
in this NodeJS, we will find it out.
as we all know that NodeJS.
relies on an event driven architecture.
the event driven architecture includes,
some event loops and callbacks
and functions, which executes at,
at the same time without blocking
other functions, ease and objects.
due to this feature, it becomes more,
more highly effective for input out
for input, output heavy applications.
So when we talk about even
driven architecture, it's mean.
it means that, there are so much
function execution happening on the
same time at the back end, so due
to which, if they are not properly
handled, so the memory leaks can cause,
server or our application
to crash the response time.
I become slow and even sometime, the
worst happened is application failure.
when, when we talk about the
long, running applications.
so what are the symptoms of memory leak?
Like how we identify that if the certain
problem is occurring again and again.
so what is cause and, Will the
cause be the memory leak or not?
So there are some signs, with the
help of which we can identify this.
So some common size, science includes,
the increasing memory usage, with the
passage of time, which includes the.
application performance slow, and
frequently garbage collection pauses.
So with the help of, with the help of
these signs, we can identify the leaks.
And with the help of this set of
symptoms, we can early, identify
this and we can maintain Our
application, stability on time.
So I will share some like real type,
real life, applicant, examples for
this memory leak in production, phase.
So actually we were working, actually
we, as a team were working on a
project where, we found some memory
leaks, like persistent memory leaks,
it's, in the, Production phase in an
high traffic, no, just application
like, like so much input, output and
processing at the back end, due to
which our server starts again and again.
so we start, debugging the
problem that what, causes the
server to start again and again.
So when we check.
Down the issues, so it, it involves some
deep, analysis of the application memory.
usage patterns over the time.
so at first we were very confused
that from which side we should start
and we should start doing debugging,
whether, it's the server issue or any
function or any, controller issue.
So at the first it was very, messed up.
after that, so it, so as I explained, It
was a challenge for us to identify that
what is the issue and from which point
we should start, debugging, our leak or
the issue, on which we are facing it.
With the help of the memory snapshots
and profiling tools, our team was
able to pinpoint the exact issue
which causes the memory leaks.
So I will explain further this
like snapshots and profiling tools,
that how they work and how we can
identify the, issues, like that.
memory leak inside our Node.
js application.
uh, there are a few common mistakes,
which causes the memory to leak in Node.
js, Node.
js applications.
So these leaks can.
Erased from, unintentional, global
variables assignment, which is a
very common mistake from like from
the beginner, developers and, some
improper, Closures are written,
references in event lister or callback.
I will explain like what are the,
closures, the closures are the
function which, retain the, reference
of an variable from an outer
function and it keeps with it until
the function, execution complete.
but sometimes these, closures are
not, properly handled due to which,
these, those variables are stayed.
Inside the memory for a long time,
due to which it like overloads the,
memory and some event listeners
and callbacks these, if they are
not, properly handled or optimized.
So these, these will
cause the memory to leave.
Okay.
So there are some tools, with the help
of which we can, Identify these leaks.
first of all, I will explain the, using
chrome def tools for memory profiling.
so chrome def tool, is a tool like is
a powerful memory profiling tool to
capture, snapshots, compare heap, Okay.
Location and identify memory leaks.
So what are like, snapshots?
So snapshots, are the timeframes
where we can, check the state, of
the app at any, a specific point.
Like we can check the snapshot of
the application before executing the
function and after that as well, with
the help of which we can identify
the memory usage of the app before
the execution and after the execution
of the certain functions or objects.
With the help of this, we can
identify the, and analyze, if
there are memory leaks and high
memory usage in no J applications.
Okay.
there is an inbuilt tool for no J,
which is called like inspect flag.
like it is, like this tool, helps in
the, in debugging anger, Like this is an
debugging tool, which helps to identify
any leak, and how to, use this built
in, feature to track down memory leaks
and some in efficient memory usage.
So we can also track, track, memory leaks.
if.
If we are encountering any extensive
memory usage inside our app or
after the execution of certain
functions, we can use this inspect
tool to identify, certain issues.
Okay, so heap, snapshot as as I
mentioned earlier, the heap, snapshots
provide a detailed view of the memory
allocation in your application.
with the help of.
Snapshots, we can record the snaps off
of our application at different intervals
so we can, analyze the memory usage
before the execution of certain tasks
and after the execution of those tasks.
So with the help of, which we can
identify, like which object or
function is taking more, memory and
which and after the execution of
which function the memory leak occurs.
Okay.
the memory leak also occurs when objects,
that should be garbage collected,
are, were, Remain in the memory.
after the execution of the functions.
so there might be some variables or
objects which are kept inside, inside the
memory and they are like no longer in use.
so this also cause, the memory to leak.
So it is also important to
track those certain objects
and the event listeners, which.
We are using, so after the
execution, they like, they kept
alive inside the memory, like which,
results the memory to overflow.
Real life solutions.
So actually I was working, on a project,
recently and I like identify after
the implementation of few functions
and some event, listeners that the
execution of like after the execution
of those processes and functions, the,
response was getting slow, time to time.
then, so after that, I, analyze few
functions and few event listeners.
due to which I was able to
identify that there is after
the executions of few functions.
So the, the.
The solution was so, simple, the issue
was the, like there was such an even
listener inside my, functions and
inside my apps, which kept, which used
to keep the references of an unused
objects, due to which the memory gets
full and the execution and it takes A
lot time to, to execute those functions.
So the, it was hard to identify the
issue at first, but once, when it
was, identified, the solution was
simple to make those even listener,
to, optimize and to, remove those
length, listeners, once they are
executed or finished their execution.
and ensure that the proper cleanup
should be done after each execution.
So now I will explain about the, Garbage
collection, the garbage collection,
like what's in a way, it is an V8
engine, garbage collector, within, Node.
js once the execution is, like
the execution of the certain,
functions and objects are done.
So then it, so that it.
Collects those unused objects and,
and even just a little bit are
kept inside, inside the memory.
so it, so the garbage collector frees up
those memory, which no longer in, in use.
uh, this helps, to avoid the
memory leaks in our, application.
Okay.
So using, clinic.
js, it is, it is an powerful, diagnostic
tool, uh, specifically, designed for Node.
js applications.
So it helps to identify any memory leak
at certain points and, see, and if there
are any CPU, bottlenecks and those queries
which are taking time, for execution.
So it also, so it helps to,
identify those issues as well.
So it's better that we should know that
how to use these tools efficiently.
because once we know how to use
these tools, it will be very
easy to identify memory leaks.
At the early stage, like in the,
development stage before going,
into your, production phase
monitoring tools for, memory usage.
uh, previously.
I have defined some tools which we
can use those manually at certain
points, but there are some, monitoring
tools if we use, them, to analyze our
memory usage at the, like from the
start to the end of our application.
So these tools like
help to monitor at each.
Stage like, like at what stage the
memory is going high and at what
stage the memory is going low.
So the tools like new relic and
data dog, they offer some real time
monitoring of, of the memory usage
in production and environment.
So we can use these tools,
specifically if our apps are live.
So we can check, the.
memory usage after the execution
of certain features inside our app.
So with the help of these tools, we
can, proactively identify memory leaks,
before they, they become too big.
so there are some, best practice
and tips I will share with you, with
the help of which we can, Prevent
these leaks in our application.
for instance, like a wide using,
global variables as they kept in our.
Memory throughout our application
life cycle and the other best example,
sorry, and the other best, practice
or tip you can say, to ensure that
the event listeners which we are
using inside our app are properly.
handled and removed when they are no
longer needed, especially in those
apps, which are like long running apps.
So these tips might help you to identify
and remove the any memory leak up to, uh.
90 percent for your Node.
js application.
Okay.
The other thing is, like optimizing
the event listeners and closures.
So as, so as I, mentioned, mentioned
it earlier that the, that due to the,
event, uh, after the execution of
event listener, even listeners like,
and closures, have their variables
and even and even listeners are there
inside our memory for a long time,
due to which the memory leak occurs.
so these are the major sources of.
Memory leaks, I believe, if they are
not, probably be, properly handled.
So by optimizing these, these
elements, we can handle, our
memory usage quite, efficiently.
Okay.
So there is, one method, inside our, no
j which is called process dot memory.
Use it.
So this method is a built in,
built in, method for Node.
js, which helps to monitor
heap and RSS memory.
so the RSS memory here is known as
President said size, which keeps the
footprint off of the application,
that how application is behaving
like before the execution of
the function or certain feature.
And after the execution of certain
feature, the execution of queries or
like taking data or taking request
or getting the response from the DB.
We can say these are the
footprints of the applications.
uh, with the help of this, the
execution of this method, we can check
the logs and we can track like any,
memory growth and identify any issue.
if, if.
If any function is causing the
memory to leak so we can identify
them before they can get escalate.
Okay.
I believe that it would be a
challenge to, detect any memory
leak in our real time systems.
like I believe that it is a
challenge when dealing with some.
Memory leaks, with, real time systems as
they have some, continuous operational
going, going on all the time.
we can, avoid them, by doing some well
defined, infrastructure of the system,
like writing a clean and nice code.
And, like using the tools after,
Using the, diagnostic tools, after the
execution, after the execution of certain,
functions and objects, uh, so this thing
will lead it to, reduce any memory leak.
It's, within our real time systems.
So I would say the, future
proofing, not just applications.
we can, protect them by, by building
the application in a, in an.
defined infrastructure, defining, defining
functions efficiently and optimizing our
event listeners and our closures as well
and a wide, Using global, variables.
So with the help of these
things, we can avoid memory leak.
and also these things help
in the scaling of our Node.
js very easily and efficiently as well.
So what is the, the.
Conclusion of this talk, is that
the memory leak can be a significant
impact on our, performance.
but with the help of the right tools
and right techniques and tips, we
can, Identify them and fix them
efficiently and on time as well.
Sorry.
So this, presentation will cover
some real, life, examples and, some,
tools, and some best tips to help to
tame this, memory links in, not just.
So thank you, for your time.
Thank you.