Hi, today we are going to discuss
about, enhancing utility operations
through human AI collaboration.
And, this is my recording for,
Conf42, JavaScript session.
And, let's dive into, how utilities can
enhance, AI and human collaboration,
to enhance their operations.
and JavaScript is one of the,
key factor within the CI systems.
which enables users to have, predominant
access, having, user experience more
better, compared to the previous
versions of the CI systems, and,
many other use cases of, JavaScript.
But, this is also more, focusing
on, How, AI is used, in the utility
sector for better usability and
experience and enhancing the overall
operational experience of the users
and, serving the better customer base.
And, yeah, so let's dive into it, all
So these are the table of contents,
and, I'm going to discuss about today.
especially the predictive analytics
in utilities enhanced, customer
service, A and MA data, ma management
in utilities, the role of, human
enterprise in AI operations.
And, we'll take a case study of,
the Catapult project, and damaging
trench in AI utilities, the evolving,
a relationship and conclusion.
so most often the utility sector shifting.
the shift in the technology comes
later after a lot of technological
innovation, innovations.
But right now, it's not that it's not
the case because there is a lot of
expectation among the customer base,
within the utility sector, having
to use mobile, more mobile, more of
mobile phones, able to view their
bills, their consumption in real time
and, there are a lot of, programs
that are rebate programs and, energy
consumption programs that are going on.
the utility sector is, facing demands
for reliability, sustainability,
and customer satisfaction.
And that's where, Human AI collaboration
provides solution, combining
AI's data processing capabilities
with, human decision making.
And that's the introduction.
how, we're talking about, how predictive
analytics in utilities, can be used.
to help better customer service and,
JavaScript is one of the, key factor in,
different, business analytics, programs
to show the, user experience, how, they
can view different dashboards and, for
example, there is a tool called WebFocus,
where in JavaScript is predominantly
used to enhance the user experience.
So the AI driven predictive analytics
helps forecast equipment failures
and optimize maintenance schedules.
For example, machine learning
models predict transformer failures,
preventing costly downtime.
So managing the downtime, for the
utilities is the major thing which,
every utility, company has to take care
because, no one wants an outage for the
sake of, some mechanical failure, right?
the, predictive analytics can be used
to find out, where the, beforehand,
before the, failure of a transformer or
whether you're not getting a leads to
a gatekeeper or The hidden system has
failed to send a reads and where user
not able to see the real time data of
the Usage or consumption or the rate
details, etc So So let's go to the next
chapter the enhanced a enhanced customer
service like I said before there's a
lot of expectation among the customer
base to, to use the latest and greatest
technologies that are coming into their
hand to, view the details, the earlier,
you just have to, print out the usage and
other details and build to the customer.
That's when they'll be able to see,
but now the millennial and, Gen Z
generation, they should be able to see.
their details, whenever they
can and, it doesn't matter.
It's midnight till ten o'clock
or, and, there are also a lot of,
programs going on time of use,
net metering, because a lot of.
People now want to shift to clean
energy, so there is, there's a lot
of, focus on, clean energy nowadays,
so all these programs can be
integrated with the help of, enhancing
the great customer care service.
there are a couple of, tools
that we can discuss about in the
chat boards that provide 24 by
7 customer service, like I said.
They want to see in midnight, 12 o'clock,
the chatbot should be able to guide
them to how to retrieve their bills and
how to retrieve their usage details.
AA offers, yeah, so based on the,
to and fro interaction with the
chatbot, the AA should be able to,
provide them energy saving tips and
improving customer satisfaction.
So the, let's say a customer was,
recommended a clean energy program
or a net meter energy program.
or a time of use program
or, various other programs.
And, if he could save money on that
program being used, then there is a
lot of satisfaction that he's getting.
And in turn, there is a great
review for the utility company,
for serving them better and, clean
energy and many other things.
And AI complements human agents by,
handling routine inquiries well.
Human addresses and complex issues
and AI also allows utilities to
participate, anticipate customer
needs and provide proactive solutions.
So it's all about.
replacing the human in this
aspect of the customer service.
so you don't have to run a customer
service team, which would, really have a
lot of customer services team responding
to the phone calls to the customers
rather than, a chat bot would really,
be a replacement for a customer service.
using the latest LLM models, it
can determine, the customer needs
and, a predict like in human
and, the accuracy is almost 99.
9 percent helpful for the customers
in providing a better feedback because
there is no latency, there is no,
difference in the communication language,
either you are Spanish or any other
community, which is predominant within
the, area that Utility is serving.
So area and data management
in Utilities, next slide.
AA processes large volumes of data
from smart meters, sensors in real
time allowing for, quicker insights
and, operational adjustments.
Utilities are able to optimize
power distribution and manage
supply more effectively, improving
the grid stability and efficiency.
Real time analytics provides data
that helps in decision making,
such as when to shift lower power
loads or how to integrate renewable
energy resources effectively.
this is all about, getting
the real time data.
so for the period of time, for
example, there is a MO law where every
year the computing power increases
to access, by every two years.
So, so earlier the cost of computing
different data sources, data, large chunks
of data has been huge cost for, utilities.
Now they can put, I will, cloud and,
AI technologies, which, can provide
scaling to get the data and store them,
storing them, and then processing compute
can be available based on the, demand
that the information they are getting.
So they don't have to
really scale up the original
infrastructure on their on premise.
and, they can really focus on
their operations rather than the.
technical infrastructure.
And once the data is in the system, so
the AI can be fed all the system and
then, predict with using predictive
analytics and, using the large data
that they are getting, they can
easily identify anomalies within
the usage of the, electricity by the
customers, usage of water or anything.
Else, beforehand, really, the
customer will be finding out.
So there are, for example, there will
be a lot of issues like diversions and,
for water and especially for water,
customers because they, some of the
commercial customers I have seen, there'll
be a lot of, sometimes tickets created
because of the high usage and, the
actual bill is really not built for that.
Thank you.
all these kind of, things can be
really discovered beforehand and really
helpful for the, utilities and like
the utility management, the, when they
buy the, electricity from Southwest
Power Pool and different other grids.
They need to make sure their
grid is stabilized and no one is
really attacking them, in terms
of cyber security and other means.
So the endpoint security can
be enabled using the AI and by
checking the data regularly.
let's dive into next chapter.
So the role of human expertise
in AI operations, AI can process
and analyze data quickly.
Human oversight ensures that AI insights
are used ethically and accurately.
Human professionals validate
AI recommendations, ensuring
that critical judgments and
ethical concerns are addressed.
Human experts provide context and
adaptability to AI systems, particularly
in unexpected or nuanced situations.
the, like I said, like we were discussing,
so the AA cannot 100 percent take over
or replace a human being, but there is
a role for human where it can really,
enhance the human's ability and reduces
the time of operations and how this
can be achieved is, really, amazing.
human professionals validate
the AA recommendations,
ensuring that critical judgment.
And Rather than the whole processing and,
com, all the steps that they go through to
end anomalies a can do the suggestions and
humans can really take, decisions quickly.
So there's a lot of, cost reduction
here where, there, where the, a
customer service team or business
analysts don't really have to spend a
lot of time in analyzing the data or.
finding out, anomalies by
themselves, they can depend on
AI to, do the recommendations
and make the decisions quickly.
So for example, let's take a catapult
project is a real world example where,
we did this project in one of the,
local communities in Kansas Board of
Public Utilities where, AI driven edge
computing processes sync data from
smart meters and sensors in real time
allowing immediate response to anomalies.
A enhanced customer service provided
proactive problem solving and
personalized interactions leading
to higher customer satisfaction.
So the customer satisfaction is being
gradually improved nowadays because
of using this latest technology so
that, the, at the end of the day,
every utility company's, response is
to, Help the customers better, save
money for them, and in turn save the
energy cost for themselves so they
can better serve the customers, right?
using these latest and greatest LLM
models and, customer services that
they're, customer service models
that they're using, they just want
to enable the customers, Service
provides, better services, personalized
interactions, and, And in turn get the
higher customer service satisfaction.
So I, I have seen this, within
the lot of utility companies using
the latest technologies to, really
enhance the customer satisfaction.
And, like we mentioned.
AI really has that capacity to solve
a lot of, computing, the computing
data, for, from smart meters and
sensors in real time so that they
can help better the, services.
So what are the trends in ai?
the fu the.
Let's discuss about the future trends.
edge computing moving computations closer
to data sources, enabling faster real
time decision making and grid management.
Advanced machine learning, deep learning
and reinforcement learning models
will improve load forecasting and
failure predictions with high accuracy.
Autonomous systems, AI driven drones
and self healing grids will reduce
human intervention in real time.
dangerous situations, increasing
safety and efficiency.
there is a lot of safety concerns
for the employees who are really
working during the outages and,
during any, roadworks or alignments.
whoever does that, we can use a lot
of, autonomous systems to, really help
them automate the tasks rather than,
mundane things that they really do.
during outages and other stuff.
so the advanced machine learning,
reinforcement models will improve
the load forecasting and failure
predictions with accuracy.
when the grid is really, the, the
commercial customers are really, they're
charged high when the, there is a peak
demand on the, they apply on this grid.
if the, If there is change in the pattern,
it's really helpful for A to analyze
those patterns and really, forecast the
usage based on the customer's, requirement
changes so that, they don't really put
sudden pressure on these grid and so
in turn we'll really help, we'll be
really helping the grid from, failure.
for example, there is a grid
failure in Texas in 2021, where.
the requirement was huge because of,
the, because of the, the snow that we had
and, and the grid was, one of the grids
failed, either should be either because
of the usage or because of the, because
of, the not able to produce the energy
demands that customers were requesting.
in that case, a lot of people, a lot
of people suffer from outages and,
really don't really have their basic
needs because that is the main source
for everything, for any of the tasks.
so in that situations can be
avoided, because of the grid, the,
the grid failures can be really
avoided using the, upfront knowing
the situations using the edge,
advanced machine learning techniques.
The evolving human AI relationship,
the future of human AI collaboration,
AI will increasingly serve a lot of
tools to augment human decision making,
providing data driven insights while
humans focus on strategic thinking.
Continuous skill development
will be required, particularly
in areas like data literacy.
AI collaborative innovation will raise, as
AI frees up human professionals to focus
on creativity and strategic initiatives.
this is.
We discussed this point earlier, the only
major thing here is there should be a
lot of, development and understanding,
learning to the customer service team
and, analysts, because of the A, A.
with, if A is, A is like a
real time processor, right?
there has to be a lot of upgrade
in their skills, to catch up
the, A, advances so that they can
help the, better the customers.
So the integration of AI and human
expertise is rapidly transforming,
utility operations leading into
enhanced efficiency, improved
decision making, and greater, improved
decision making, and, AI leverage.
A for predictive maintenance,
customer service, enhancements,
and real time data management.
While relying on human oversight for
strategy direction, ethical consideration,
and contextual decision making, by
combining the strengths of both AI
and human professionals, utility
companies are becoming more responsive
to growing demands for reliability,
sustainability, and customer satisfaction.
Looking to the future, emerging
technologies such as edge
computing, advanced machine learning
models, and autonomous systems
are set to revolutionize AI.
I'm going to be talking about the,
the new, the new, the new, the new