Hi everyone.
I'm really glad to welcome everyone
to this wonderful event and to share
something new and exciting with you.
In my talks, I usually focus on two
things, either new, lesser known
technologies or old but overlooked ideas
that I believe deserves more attention.
And this topic is no exception.
I'm going to talk about something
experimental, but with a lot of potential.
It is a scheduler yield right now.
This future is still in early stages,
and not all browsers supported yet.
But there's already IL available.
And during the talk I'll also
show some alternative ways
to achieve similar behavior.
These aren't perfect replacements, but
they can still be useful in the meantime.
And before we dive into the topic, just
a few words about myself and why my
viewers listening to what I have to say.
I'm a fronted engineer with over six
years of experience, author of technical
and scientific publications and
speaker at the Global Tech conferences.
I'm a mentor and judge at international
hackathons and innovation award programs,
and I'm also involved in the open
source community program contribution,
including creating my own open
source C success library ton mammoth.
I'm also a member of several
professional associations.
Now that you know a little bit
about me, let's get to the point.
So what is a scheduler yield?
It is a method of the scheduler
interface from the new
prioritized task scheduling API.
This methods allows you as a
developer to post your JavaScript
execution and explicitly yield
control back to the main threat.
So it can handle other pending
important tasks like user interactions,
clicks, typings, et cetera.
In simple terms, when you call scheduler
youth, you are telling the browser.
Wait, take a breath.
Let's put the current tasks and focus on
other, no less or more important tasks.
Once you have done, come back and
continue execution from where we left off.
This makes your page more
responsive, especially when running
long or heavy JavaScript tasks.
It can also help improve metrics like
interaction to next paint called INP,
which is all about how quickly the
browser responds to the user input.
Before we dive deeper, let's quickly
go over a few basic terms that
I'll be using throughout the talk.
I'm sure many of you already
know them, but a quicker press,
never hearts main threat.
This is a central place where the
browser does most of its work.
It handles rendering, layout,
and runs most of your JavaScript.
A long task.
This is any JavaScript task that keep
the main thread busy for too long,
usually more than 50 milliseconds.
When that happens, the page can
freeze or feel unresponsive.
And the blocking task is a synchronous
separation of the main thread that
prevents the browser from processing.
Other important things like
responding to clicks, updating
the ui, usually learn tasks.
Tasks are blocking tasks.
The problem.
To understand the beauty of scheduler
yield, we first need to understand
what problem's trying to solve.
And for that, let's quickly refresh
how JavaScript purchase tasks.
In other words, how the task
processing in the browser works.
I'm sure many of you have seen
diagrams like this before.
The task queue, the event loop.
The call stack.
This one isn't perfect, but
it gives us the big picture.
Let's walk through the
main ideas step by step.
So all in Crohn's code goes straight
to the cold stack and runs line
by line, function By function.
It follows a leaf of principle lasting.
First out, JavaScript runs in a single
thread, which means it can do only
one thing at a time, as in Crohn's
operations, set them out, fetch.
Pro handled outside the ADE by the web
APIs provided by the browser environment.
When they've done, they don't go
back directly into the call stack.
Instead, their callbacks queue
either in the microtask queue,
you can see it here like promise.
Then queue microtask or tasks
queue, set them out or set inter.
When the call stack is empty, they went
loop check the microtask queue and runs
all microtask one by one in order only.
After that, it takes one runable
task from the chosen task queue.
Importantly, the task queue assets,
not strict FIFA queues, they went loop.
Pick the first task that is
ready to run, not necessarily
that one that was added first.
If during the process new microt
tasks are added, they run before
the next task from the task queue.
So microt tasks always get priority.
This loop keeps going All microt tasks.
One task from task queue repeat.
Use chrome code gets into the call stack.
When new tasks arrive, like a user click
in a button and new script being run.
When a microtask or task from
Task Q runs it's callback.
This is a very brief and superficial
explanation just to remind you how it
works, since it'll further close the
inter circuit with the topic, please note
that Event Loop itself is not part of
the JavaScript ECMA script specification.
If you look into the ecma
Script specification, you
won't point it there at all.
The event loop is defined
in the HTML standard.
As a problem description.
Now that we have refreshed our
understanding of how JavaScript secured
tasks, let's take a closer look at the
real problems that comes with this model.
The issue is simple.
When a task takes to long on the main
thread, it blocks everything else.
User interactions, rendering
updates, animation.
This leads to AI freezes
and pure responsiveness.
The obvious forethought might be, just
don't write long or heavy functions,
and that is the problem is solved.
And yes, that's true.
In an ideal world, we will always
split heavy coat into smaller
parts, optimize every sink, and
the avoid blocking the main thread.
Let's be honest, many of us have run
through these issues even if we weren't
that ones who regionally cause them.
Even if you were not the culprit of
this behavior, you have to work with it.
And to make this more concrete, let's
simulate a simple but realistic case.
Imagine we had to process a large
array, and each element requires some
non-trivial computation, something
that takes time and uses CPU, which
in turns blocks the main thread.
For this, we'll create a
function called blocking task.
The task as a block in task for the main
threat for the specified period of time.
The function simulate this kind of heavy
computation on each element of the array.
There's nice and f fancy
about the function here.
All it does, so it accepts an
argument, the number of milliseconds.
This is the minimum time the function
will run, thus occupying the main threat.
Then it creates an empty array.
Then it creates a start time as a
current time, and then runs a while loop
until the specified time has passed.
Inside the loop, it just does random,
meaningless calculation to simulate load.
Finally, it returned the
result of the calculation.
The function doesn't do anything
useful, but it does simulate a
real world scenario of heavy load.
This function will be used
inside another simple function.
Imagine a common situation where we need
to look through an array of data and apply
that heavy work to each item of the array.
To do this, we'll create a heavy work
function in which the following happens.
On line two, it creates an array of 200
items, just numbers from zero to one.
Nine nine.
I want to know that 200 items are not
that many, but it'll be enough that the
to the see the essence of the problem.
Then a new empty result array is
created to store the processed values.
Then on line five declares a loop that go
through the entire lens of the data array.
Inside the loop, we run the blocking task
function, simulating only 10 milliseconds
of work for each element, and the
result is added to the result array.
Once again, I want to remind you that
for the demo, the blocking task function
does not carry any semantic load.
It is simply perform some imaginary
resource intensive work in the real world.
It could be some labor
intensive processing.
Cory Element.
Finally in return, the result
in array, and that's where
the amazing part comes in.
Just 10 millisecond per element and only
200 elements, but together they block
the main thread for two full seconds.
That's enough to cause a
noticeable freeze in the ui.
No clicks, no typing, just a frozen.
It's a problem demonstration.
Now it's time to look at the problem,
not just in theory but in action.
This is not full fledged demo just yet.
Tin of a simplified visual to
help you clearly see the issue.
Here's what you see here.
The left window titled configuration
lets you turn on the main thread block
on and off, meaning whether the blocking
task function is actually running.
You can also toggle scheduler
yield functionality.
We will get to that part later.
The window titled heavy task here on
the right runs the heavy work function.
This is one that process an array
using blocking task on each element.
If the main thread blocking is
enabled and the window typed logger
here, just talk the current time to
the console, including milliseconds.
Let's see what happens when the
main thread booking is turned off.
So the tasks are very light.
It just took over an array of 200
elements without any complex calculation.
What we observe here, the
user click the okay button.
The heavy work function
runs and instantly returns.
This is indicated by the message Heavy
Task done in the console, followed by
the result of an array of numbers here.
Then the user clicks the
log button three times.
They log the time to the console,
timestamps appear immediately
with a slight difference in time.
They run the heavy work
function again and again.
Instant response.
Finally, the user closes two windows,
which actually just remove those elements
from the do no delays, no hiccup.
In this case, everything
feels fast and responsive.
The browser has no trouble
hand the interactions because
the mantra stays free.
Tasks are performed almost
instantly and consistently.
Now let's enable the main thread blocking
so that for each element of the array,
the blocking task function will be called
with a delay of only 10 milliseconds.
And now you can observe that
user interaction with your
elements has become less smooth.
UI freeze, have a period.
Let's break it down to what is happening
here and what we can observe from it.
The user press okay button, thereby
launching the heavy work function.
And the first log that occurs is that
the okay button visually stays pressed.
Why?
Because the browser cannot repent.
While heavy work is still blocking
the main threat, and it is important
to understand that we are talking
not only about the current task,
but about the call stack as a whole.
During this time, the user clicks
the logs button four times.
Nothing happens.
The clicks are registered and
they handles edit to the queue,
but the browsers can't react.
Only after heavy work finishes
do we see the console output
for the heavy workers out.
Then the four time steps.
All printed in a batch and only
after that the okay button changed
its state and became impressed.
Next, the user clicks.
Okay, button again, same
behavior, stuck button.
Then while the heavy work task is
running, he tries to close the window
by clicking the X icon three times.
Again, no visual response, only one.
The task ends do we see
the window disappear.
And finally, one more attempt to run
heavy work and close the last window.
Same freeze.
So you see the press button,
you see nothing happens here.
You see the press button
again, nothing happens.
It's lagging, it's freeze.
What that, this show, the simple demo,
shows how long task block the powers
their ability to respond to user actions.
Even though each block code takes
just 10 millisecond changing 200 of
them to get results in a two second
freeze, the user can interact with the
button, the interface doesn't repaint.
Events get queued up, but not processed
until the call stack is clear.
This is not just a performance
issue, it's a user experience
problem, and that's exactly the
kind of issue we want to solve.
Ideally, without having to manually
split our logic into dozen of callbacks.
It is a problem solution.
Now that we understand the problem,
let's talk about the possible solutions.
Of course, the best strategies to wet loan
task in the first place by keeping code
efficient and breaking things up early.
But as we have seen stuff happens, whether
it's legacy code and available computation
are just not enough time to optimize.
Sometimes we have to deal with it.
Over the years before the prioritized
task scheduling API appeared, various
workaround and tweaks have been come up
is to improve the responsiveness, but the
core idea behind all of them and behind
scheduler as well is pretty simple.
Break a task into smaller pieces is
chunks, and once in a while, post
to let the browser catch it breathe.
In other words, we give the main threat
a chance to run more urgent tasks like
user interactions, rendering updates, and
then we come back to finish our own work.
Here's what the concept of heavy work
function looks like in the pseudo code.
What's happening here?
First, you run a chunk of your task, then
you post allowing the browser to handle
other high priority tasks like UI updates.
Put the current task and task
control that demand threat to
handle other high priority tasks,
and then continue execution.
The function from where it left off.
All problem solving approach.
Before scheduler yield came
along, the most common trick for
dealing with the long blocking
task was to use set time out.
By calling it with a zero delay, you add
its callback task to the end of the task
queue, allowing other tasks to run first.
In other words, you tell the browser,
run this bit of code later, after you
handle everything else, and that's how
we can give the main threat a short
bleeder between chances of heavy work.
Here's what the updated heavy
work function might look
like using this approach.
Let's break it down.
What's going on here on A
Promise is created and it's
executor runs immediately.
Scheduling a set time out with a
zero delay the time article back,
which resolves the promise is
added to the end of the task queue.
Because of a wait, the rest of the
same function is post technically
discontinuation is added to the microtask
queue, waiting for the promise to resolve.
The JavaScript and giant
check the call stack.
Once it's empty, they went loop kicks in.
First it took at the microtask queue,
but times the promise isn't resolved.
There's nothing to run they want.
They went loop.
Pick the task from the queue.
In our example, it is set
time out, called back runs it,
and this resolve the promise.
Now that the promise is resolved, the
Microtask contains the continuation
of the, I think function is run.
In simple terms, line three gives
the browser a chance to catch its
breeze before heavy work begins.
Therefore, by calling this method
before doing any heavy work gives a
browser a moment to rear-end UA updates,
such as unfreezing, a click button.
On line nine, we calculate how often we
want to yield to the main threat, roughly
every 25% of the work, this number can
vary depending on how heavy the task is.
On line 13 through 15 inside the
loop, if the condition for yielding
interval is met, execution is
transferred to the main thread.
That is the set technique is repeated,
allowing the browser process, user
interaction, or draw the interface.
Essentially, this approach works.
It's relatively simple and does improve
responsiveness, but there's a tradeoffs.
One big issue that is set them out
isn't built for precise scheduling.
It puts tasks at the end of the task
queue, and anything already in that
queue can delay your continuation.
For example, let's say some
other part of the page, you set
interval to run task regularly.
Now your own task, the next chunk of
heavy work function might get delayed by
one or more of these interval call bags.
The brow just runs whatever
in is next in line it do.
You don't control the order.
So while set time out lets you
yield, you don't know exactly
when you get control back.
There are other ways to
upload this situation.
It could be the request animation frame
function, which lets you schedule work
right before the next repaint, often used
in conjunction with the set amount and has
similar drawbacks or request idle callback
that runs your code during the browser.
Idle time.
It's not quite an alternative,
but good for background, a less
important work that help the mantra
to be free for more critical tasks.
In general, we could discuss
other strategies for solving
and preventing such problems.
However, to stay on topic, let's
move on and see what schedule
yield brings to the table.
So schedule yield, it's a modern
way to post execution and yield
control to the main threat, which
allows the browser to perform any
pending high priority work and then
continue execution from where it left.
What actually happens under the
hood when the AWAI scheduler
yield expression is reached?
The execution of the current function is
in, which it was called, is suspended,
and the yields controlled is the main
threat, thereby breaking up or posing
the current task, the continuation of
the function, that is the execution
of the remaining part of it from
where it left off is a separate, newly
scheduled microtask in the event loop.
The beauty of scheduler yield that
the continuation after scheduler yield
remains at the front of the queue and
the scheduler to run before any other
non-essential tasks that have been queue.
The key difference from the set
out approach that we set them out,
discontinuation typically run after
any new tasks that have already
been queued, potentially causing
long delays between yielding to the
main threat and their completion.
The following diagram illustrates how
three approaches compare in practice.
Let's look at them in the first example
without yielding to the main thread.
At the first is the long
task one runs uninterrupted.
Blocking the main trend
and UI accordingly.
Then a user event is processed.
A button click triggered during
the execution of task one.
And finally task Q. Task two
is executed, set time out, call
back, schedule it earlier during
the execution of the wrong task.
In the second example, using set
timeout as a yield into the main
threat, the execution use different
at first, the long task one runs.
Then when the yield to the main
threat happens, task one passes
to let the browser breathe and
the button click is processed.
But after the button click is processed,
the set time article back will be executed
first, which could have been scheduled
in advance during the execution of Task
one, and finally only after that the
continuation of Task one will be executed.
And in the last example, using
scheduler yield technology.
After the long task one has been post and
the user click event has been processed.
Then the continuation of the
task one is prioritized and runs
before an acute set amount tasks.
In summary, scheduler yield is a more
intelligent and predictable way to give
the main threat breath in the room.
It avoid the risk of your code being
pushed far too back in the queue and helps
maintain performance and responsiveness,
especially in complex applications.
Priorities.
So what causes such a
difference in behavior?
It's all about priorities.
As developers, we don't usually think
about the order of execution of task in
the event loop in terms of priorities
more precisely, we have a good
understanding what microtask and task you
are and the order image which they run.
But if you look deeper, you'll
notice that there are all
simplicity priorities at play.
For example, a button click
handle, fired by user action.
Typically execute before
a set time call back.
Even though both a task
from the task queue.
As mentioned earlier, scheduler yield
is a part of the prioritized task,
scheduling API and extensive and future
reach interface that deserve its own
separate, full-fledged discussion is
clearly beyond the scope of this talk.
Nevertheless, it's important to
mention one of its key features.
The introduction of Clear Task priority
Model, prioritized Task Scheduling API
simply make these priorities explicit,
making it easier to determine which
task will run first, and enables
adjusting priorities to change the
order of the execution if needed.
Here's a quick look at the main
priority levels it defines.
First, it's user blocking the highest
priority tasks that directly affect user
interaction, such as hand and clicks,
tops, and critical UI operations.
Then user visible tasks that affect
UI visibility or content, but are
not critical for immediate input.
And the SEC and the third background
tasks that are non-agent and can be
safely postponed without affecting
the current user experience and
are not visible to the user.
By default, scheduler yield
has a user visible priority.
Also prioritized task scheduling
API exposes the post task method
designated to schedule task with a
specified priority from the above.
While it won't go into details
about this method here, it is worth
mentioning that if scheduler yield
was scheduled from within a post
task, it ensures its priority.
So how to use scheduler yield, and
once you understand how it all works,
the types of tasks, the problem caused
by long blocking operations and the
priorities, the use of scheduler
yield becomes straightforward,
but it should be used wisely.
And with due caution, here is an
updated version of the heavy work
function using scheduler yield.
Now, instead of set time out, you just
need to call AWAI scheduler yield.
And the rest part ment
change here and here.
Instead of we just call
a wait, schedule a real.
Now when a user starts a heavy work
function using scheduler yield, the
different is immediately noticeable.
Firstly, the okay button does not stick.
And secondly, user click events on the
log button as successfully purchased,
which does not blocked the user
interaction with the page that is.
At first, the heavy work function
was launched and the button was
re rendered without sticking.
While the heavier task was being
executed, the user pressed the log button.
They went, was processed successfully
and the data was printed to the console.
Then the heavy work function
continued and this final result
was printed to the console.
After the completion, the user
press the log button again.
In short, you can give your browser
a break with just one line, so you
can see that there no UI freezes.
We can see the look almost immediately.
Now that we have explored the theory,
let's move on to the practice and
look at the real working demo.
This is a simulated banking complication.
Of course, it's fictional and
simplified, but it captures just
enough of the real world complexity
to help us understand how block and
the main threat affects interactivity
and how schedule yield can help.
Here's what the user
sees in the interface.
Balance section.
By default, the account balance is hidden
behind the plus holder of faster risk.
This is a familiar pattern in the
real banking apps where sensitive
information is hidden unless
explicitly revealed by the user.
A button labeled show
balance to visibility.
Next, a bank card, a visual representation
of a bank card shown from side by
default where some details are displayed.
Card type in the top left corner.
Last four digit of the card holder's
name, and the payment system is
the bottom right of the card.
There are two buttons to the right of the.
Show card details, which flip the card.
One, click the backside of the card to
view sensitive card data like its full
number, expiration date and serial code.
Although the card number is generally
not considered private information,
some applications still prefer not
to show the full number by default,
but only the user initiates it.
However, I know and even use the banks
that generally do not allow you to
see the bank card number even in the
application and generate reports.
By clicking this button, the
feature supposedly generates a list
of transactions on the card and
display them in the table below.
This imitates the real functionality
where a user can generate reports
on the bond card transactions.
In reality, these reports can be
complex tables with many customer
visible filters and the ability to
download their reports as a file.
Such operations might involve heavy
computations process, a huge amount of
data making them resource intensive.
And time consuming for the sake of the
demo, it's simplified under the hood.
The generate report button triggers
a previously discussed heavy work
function, which simply blocked the
main threat using the blocking task
function, which was also discussable.
After that static mock transaction
data, simply render it into the table.
The behavior of the application
can be customized using the various
settings of the configuration panel.
On the left side, you may hear notice its
simplified version in earlier screenshots.
Now it's time to explain what it does.
Main thread blocking determines whether
the main thread will be blocked.
In fact, when this option is enabled,
the blocking task function is executed.
Scheduler yield, toggles where
the scheduler yield is used.
Data Arit controls how many elements
are iterated by the heavy work function.
The more elements, the longer it takes.
Blocking time, durations specifies
how many milliseconds each element
of the race takes to process.
And the yield interval defines how
often scheduler yield is called as a
percentage of progress through the array.
That is the lower this number,
the more often it'll be called.
In earlier example, we used a 200
element array with a 10 milliseconds
delay and the 25% interval.
A good balance for visible impact without
excessive delay with larger data sets,
a smaller interval is often better.
But as always, it depends.
Here and sorted out all the
functionality and configuration.
Let's walk through the real use user
scenario and see how blocking the main
threat affect the user experience.
To start, we enable main threat
blocking and disable schedule yield.
We also increase the array lens a bit,
so the heavy operations take longer
given as the time absorbs the effects.
So the user clicks the generator
port button behind the scenes.
This triggers the heavy work function,
which processes 1000 elements, where
each element takes 10 milliseconds.
Watch what happens.
The generator port button stays stuck.
It doesn't impress, and
the UI doesn't rear render.
While the report is being generated, the
user tries to click the show card details,
then the show balance buttons, but nice.
In response, the interface
is completely frozen.
There is no animation, no
feedback, no sense of progress.
This is a classic example
of a bad user experience.
The app appears frozen, even though
it's technically still working.
The user doesn't know whether
to wait or load the page.
And let's address these short
comments using scheduler yield
by adjusting thumb configuration.
Here's how the configuration now looks.
The main threat is still blocked.
This time, the option to use
scheduler yield is enabled.
The rail lens is slightly
increased just for clarity.
The blocking time remain
the same 10 milliseconds.
The scheduler Ute response is interval
reduced to 5% for tho responsiveness,
and the relevance has been increased.
And now with the updated
configuration, the same user
flow looks completely different.
The third thing that catches the
eye is that after the generator port
button has been clicked, it'll renders
correctly, and the load animation appears
while the report is being generated.
The user successfully
interacts with the ui.
They can flip the card
and toggle the balance.
The application remains responsive.
Even if the animation are slightly
less smooth, it's a huge step forward
compared to the previous freeze.
This is a much better experience.
The user is informed in control
and not let grace in whether
the app is working and all.
It was one method called
just Schedule a yield.
Of course, the actual implementation can
be further optimized, but even this simple
form, the differ difference striking.
And as a conclusion, I want to say that
today you learned about giving your
browser break the importance of yielding
to the main thread that perform higher
priority task, and the advantages and
the disadvantages of these techniques.
There are certainly more nuances to
cover and the prioritized task schedule
and API has other capabilities that will
not code in this talk, but my goal was
to give you a solid foundation enough
to start experimenting and enough to
start thinking differently about how
your code plays with the browser.
Thanks for your attention, and give
your browser a brick once in a while.