Let's talk about the future of healthcare
IT, its trends and predictions.
We will discuss about the emerging tech
and the healthcare digital transformation.
Also, we will talk a bit more on
the healthcare data security and
using blockchain technologies.
let's talk about the global health,
market, global health market.
The digital health market has gone rapidly
with an evaluation of, 97 billion in 2020.
This indicates a surge in technology
driven healthcare solutions globally.
The projected compound
annual growth rate of 15.
1 percent until 2028, that reflects a
strong long term trend as healthcare
becomes increasingly digitized.
This growth is propelled by
increased demand for telehealth,
electronic health records, and other
innovative health records, healthcare
technologies that are streamlined
patient care, improved diagnostics,
and improve the healthcare management.
The pandemic driven shift is a main
cause like the COVID 19 fundamentally
accelerated the adoption of digital
health tools as face to face interactions
become limited and the telehealth
services surged by more than 150 percent.
The pandemic forced the healthcare
systems to rapidly adapt and many
patients become comfortable using digital
solutions for their healthcare needs.
The shift is not temporary.
It's likely to have a lasting impact as
the advantages of digital health like
convenience, efficiency and safety are
clear for both patients and providers.
Let's see what the future outlook.
The healthcare industry is now
looking ahead to transformative.
technologies like, AI, machine
learning and advanced analytics.
So these technologies are poised
to change how the patient care is
delivered by enabling more precise
diagnosis, personalized treatments, and
more efficient healthcare management.
Healthcare operations will benefit
from predictive analysis, making
systems more responsive and
proactive rather than reactive.
Let's see the key healthcare IT trends.
The first and foremost is an AI and ML.
So diagnostic enhancement, the AI
is transforming the diagnostics by
identifying the patterns in medical
imaging or patient data that are
hard for human doctors to detect.
For example, AI can help reduce the
false positives in cancer screenings.
Then how it helps the
personalized statements.
So the AI driven algorithms analyze
the patient data to recommend the
tailor treatment plans for the patient.
And this can improve the patient
outcomes by factoring in unique health
conditions and genetic profiles.
And next, the predictive analytics.
So AI can anticipate the patient
needs, optimize treatment pathways,
and reduce the complications
through preemptive analytics.
And let's see the role of
the advanced data analytics.
So the advanced data analytics
enables healthcare providers to shift
through vast amounts of health data.
to extract actionable insights.
So the better decision making like the
analytics can provide the real time
data for the healthcare professionals to
make informed timely decisions which is
crucial for the patient safety and care.
How it is impacting the population health?
The analytics can be used to make a manage
large portions, identify the trends and
address the health risk proactively.
Let's see about the interoperability
and cloud migrations.
as the healthcare systems integrate
with legacy systems, with the, and
then with the new technologies,
the seamless communications between
the systems becomes crucial.
So the interoperability allows data to
be shared across multiple platforms,
improving the care continuity.
And the cloud migration, the cloud
based solutions offer scalable, secure
storage and enable easier access to
patient data for healthcare providers.
Trying down the cost while
improving the system performance.
Next, the blockchain for security.
This is a major topic, which
we will see in the later part,
but here like a high level.
So the blockchain is making a tremendous
improvement in the security of
healthcare data by creating immutable
decentralized ledgers that ensures the
integrity and privacy of patient data.
with respect to cost saving, the
blockchain technology can potentially
save billions by reducing the fraud,
errors, and cost, with respect to
the managing, healthcare records.
And let's see the power of
AI and ML in healthcare.
So the AI and ML plays a major role
in the accuracy of the diagnostics.
So the AI has demonstrated its potential
in diagnostics with applications like
breast cancer detection, improving
the accuracy by reducing both false
and, false positives and negatives.
This not only saves lives.
But also reduces unnecessary
treatments, with respect to
personalized treatment plans.
So AI helps, craft individualized
treatment plans, which
improves the patient outcomes.
For instance, using the AI for,
depression treatment, so that in 6 percent
higher emission rates showcasing the
promise of data driven, cash outages.
And, let's see the, advanced
data analytics, like how it
is helping the healthcare.
with respect to the population health
management, the predictive analytics
helps in identifying the high risk
patients for conditions such as, diabetes
or heart diseases with high accuracy.
So by anticipating health issues, the
healthcare providers can intervene,
earlier to prevent the complications.
And with operational efficiency,
analytics can optimize the
hospital workloads, workflows.
So improving the resource allocation and
reducing the bottlenecks such as emergency
room boarding or discharge delays.
So this directly leads to better
patient experiences and more
efficient use of the resources.
And in the research and development,
the big data enables faster drug
discovery by analyzing Millions or
even billions of compounds are creating
the development of new treatments and
improving the outcomes of clinical trials.
And, next is an interoperability
and cloud migrations.
The integration of outdated legacy
systems into the modern cloud
infrastructure is a top priority for many
hospitals and healthcare institutions.
So to, ensuring these systems
communicate seamlessly.
is essential for delivering
uninterrupted patient care.
The API solutions like the Fast
Healthcare Interoperability Resources,
FHIR APIs, they drastically reduce the
time required to integrate discrete
healthcare systems, thus improving the
ability to share data across platforms.
The healthcare cloud
computing market is growing.
about to reach like 64.
7 billion dollars by next year 2025.
so the cloud solutions offer
enhanced system performance, cost
savings, scalable data storage,
making it a critical investment for
future ready healthcare systems.
next let's talk about the blockchain,
strengthening, how it strengthens
the healthcare data security.
by offering a secure, transparent
way to manage patient data, the
blockchain reduces the risk of data
breaches, increases the transparency,
and strengthens the patient privacy.
let's see the decentralization
and how it works.
immutability.
So the blockchain technology operates
on a decentralized network, where
data is stored across multiple nodes,
emulating a single point of failure.
So this significantly reduces the
chances of cyber attacks compared
to the centralized databases.
So once data is written on, on a
blockchain, it is immutable, meaning
it cannot be altered or deleted
without the consensus from the
network, ensuring the data integrity.
So next is like the encryption
and crypto cryptographic hashing.
The blockchain uses advanced
crypto, advanced encryption and
cryptographic hashing algorithms
like SHA two six to secure the data.
This provides an extra layer of security,
as sensitive data is encrypted, making
it more difficult for the unauthorized
users to access or tam with it.
The cryptographic hashing ensures
that any changes to the data, will
result in a completely different hash,
making it evident if a breach occurs.
And, next is like smart
contracts for, security.
So the smart contracts self executing
contracts with the terms of the agreement
directly written into the code can
be used in the blockchain systems to
automatically enforce security protocols.
For example, they can ensure that the
data access is granted only to authorized
individuals and the actions are executed
only when predefined conditions are met.
So further securing the sensitive
data like PHI or PCI, anything.
Every transaction or data entry in
a blockchain network is recorded in
a transparent and verifiable way.
So this provides a detailed audit
trail, allowing the healthcare
organizations to track the data
provenance and ensure compliance with
regulatory requirements such as GDPR
or HIPAA in industries like healthcare.
So the blockchain's secure
infrastructure significantly reduces
the potential for data breaches.
So unlike the traditional systems
where hackers may gain access to the
entire database, but the blockchain's
decentralized nature ensures that
even if one node is compromised, the
rest of the system remains secure.
Let's see an real world example
where the blockchain is used.
Estonia's national blockchain
for e health data security.
So the east the estonia is a leading
example of the use of blockchain
technology to secure the sensitive
healthcare data the estonian government
Used the blockchain based system for
managing and securing the citizens
health records in their national So
by leveraging the blockchain, Estonia
ensures that healthcare records are
tamper proof and can be accessed only
by the authorized individuals, which
strengthens data privacy and security.
Additionally, the system allows
patients to have full control over
who can view their medical records.
So Estonia's blockchain based health
system has, Prove that there is a
reduction in their data breaches.
And it has, also improved the patient
trust as they assured that their person
data is being secured, securely managed.
So this real world implementation shows
how blockchain can change the, and improve
the data security, especially in the
sectors handling the, most sensitive data.
Especially in healthcare and preparing
for the future of healthcare IT.
So the healthcare institutions must
invest in the digital infrastructures.
So the healthcare providers must upgrade
their systems to support emerging
technologies and scalable infrastructures.
This is a key to future
proofing healthcare operations.
And second, they must focus
on the data governance.
So the proper data governance policies
are necessarily necessary to maintain high
data quality and security, especially as
poor data quality costs the healthcare
system over, 342 billion annually.
Then.
upskilling the workforce.
The training in the healthcare
professionals in data analytics
and digital tools will be essential
for maximizing the benefits of
IT advancements in healthcare.
then they need to collaborate
with the tech partners.
So partnership with the technology
firms will drive innovation, improve
the outcomes, and Enhance the healthcare
solutions by leveraging the specialist
knowledge and the last and the important
thing is Prioritizing the cybersecurity.
So with healthcare breaches
averaging a cost of like 7.
13 million US dollars per incident
Investing in the cybersecurity
is essential to protect the
both data and patient trust
And next the benefits of embracing
the healthcare IT transformations
So the first benefit is like
the, data security and privacy.
So leveraging that latest technologies
like blockchain and advanced encryption
methods ensures that sensitive patient
data is securely stored and transmitted.
With healthcare breaches becoming more
common, the enhanced data security
measures build patient trust and protect
against the costly data breaches.
Then the personalized patient care.
The integration of AI and big data
analytics allows us, allows for
more personalized treatment plans
by analyzing a patient's genetic
lifestyle and medical history data.
So this precision medicine approach leads
to more effective treatments, minimizing
the trial and error methods and improving
the patient satisfaction, interoperability
and seamless data sharing.
So healthcare IT transformations
facilities better.
Okay.
identify and detect communications between
the desperate healthcare systems through
interoperability standards such as FHIR.
this seamless data sharing improves
the care coordination between
different providers, ensuring that
the patient receives timely and
accurate treatments for regardless
of where they seek the care.
Another benefit is like remote
patient monitoring and telemedicine.
with the rise of telemedicine and wearable
health devices, the healthcare IT enables
real time remote monitoring of patients.
this allows the healthcare
providers to track the vital
signs and other health metrics.
outside of the, clinical settings,
reducing the hospital, read missions and
improving the long term care management.
And the last and the most
important benefit is like a
regulatory compliance of reporting.
So the automated data collection and
analytics tools simplify the compliance
with healthcare regulations, such as
HIPAA, GDPR, or other regional standards.
So the digital systems can
generate reports quickly.
track the data access and ensure that
healthcare organizations remain compliant
and the better clinical decision support.
So with advanced decision support systems.
Healthcare professionals can make
evidence based decisions more effectively.
So these systems analyze a vast
amount of clinical data in real
time, helping doctors choose the best
possible treatment plans and anticipate
complications before they arise.
let's, let's come to the
conclusion like the healthcare IT
is evolving rapidly with AI ML.
for computing and the blockchain at
the forefront of this transformation.
So these technologies offer unprecedented
opportunities to improve the patient
care, increase the operational
efficiency and reduce the cost.
So for healthcare organizations
to harness the full potential of
these digital transformations, they
must focus on key enablers like
interoperability, data security and
infrastructure and infrascalability.
that's it from my end, and thanks
for hearing me on this topic.
Thank you.