Hello, everyone.
I'm thrilled to be part of conf 32.
I have to the chance to share my
insights of one of the most exciting
insertion of creativity and technology.
Algorithmic arts using JavaScript.
This conference brings together
people passionate about tech,
and I hope you will join me.
By the end of this session, you'll
see how JavaScript is not only a tool
for development, but also a medium
of artistic expression as well.
Let's drive into this journey
together and explore a fascinating
world of, we're called, because
Think back to when you were a child.
Remember how naturally
drawing came to you?
However, it was doodles in the margins of
your school notebook, crayons on paper,
or even drawing in the sand at the beach.
What did your drawing
mean to you back then?
For many of us, drawing
as a child was our life.
About pure creativity, a way to
express ourselves without worrying
about rules or being judged.
It was about exploring
our imagination freely.
But as we grow older,
many of us stop drawing.
Why is that?
Does the fear of impression creep in?
Do we become too focused
on what others think?
Today, I want to invite you to
reconnect with that creativity freedom.
It's time to use the power of code.
The table of contents, what I
want to talk with you today.
Get to know me.
I'll start sharing a bit about
myself, who I am, what brought me to
this point, and why I'm passionate
about both technology and art.
This will give you a sense of
perspective I'm bringing to the table.
Understanding algorithmic art.
Next, we'll drive into
what algorithmic art is.
I'll explain how algorithmic creative
coding come together to form an
unique blend of art and technology,
and how this field is transforming
the way we think about creativity.
Exploring JavaScript for creative coding.
After that, I introduce you a
powerful JavaScript library.
P5.
js that you can use to start
creating algorithmic art by yourself.
You'll see how tool enables artists
and coders alike to experiment
with visual interactions.
Resources for experimentations.
I also share some great resources
where you can experiment with
team learning including platforms
like Open Processing that offers
inspirations, tutorials, and examples
from the creative coding community.
Conclusions and reflections.
As we near the end of the talk, I offer
some deep reflection of how algorithmic
art challenge our traditional ideas of
art, and how you can incorporate this
from of creativity into your own projects.
And finally, I'll provide my list of
reference so you can explore these topics
further and see the sources that you need.
begin the concept and
ideas was discussed today.
I'm Francisca Beatriz Medina Gonza, and
you can find me on my social networks.
On LinkedIn, I'm listed by my full
name, Francisca Beatriz Medina Gonza.
But if you prefer Instagram,
you can find me at franny.
b, franny.
b.
Instagram is my platform.
So if you happen to take photos,
screenshot, or whatever during the session
or while experiment with algorithmic
art, I really appreciate if you tag me.
It's always great to stay connected
and share our creative journeys.
My roles.
I'm currently role as UX and front
end leader at LATAM Airlines.
I'm responsible for overseeing the
design and development of user interface
with our data visualization team.
Thank you.
As a speaker, I have the opportunity to
share my knowledge, passion for technology
at conferences like GSCom Chile.
As a volunteer for Women Techmakers,
I support initiatives that empower
women in technology through mentorship,
education, and community building.
Let me tell you a bit more about who I am.
I'm a variety career designer, web
developer, teacher, and now leader.
But beyond the tech, I always love
making art and craft with my hands.
no, I'm definitely not a robot.
I'm cute, emotional person who finds joy
in creative, both digital and physical.
I'm from Santiago de Chile, and while
Santiago is our capital, it's important
to know that Santiago is not Chile.
Chile is a long and diverse country
with so much to offer beyond this.
For those who are wondering,
where exactly Chile?
we are the southernmost country
in the world, stretching all
the way down to Antarctica.
We speak Spanish, so I want to apologize
in advance if my English is not perfect.
Thank you for understanding as
I present this talk in Spanish.
is my second language.
Personal motivation.
My personal journey into the world of art
and technology started in a childhood.
I was a shy kid who loved art and
dreamed of becoming an artist.
That passion led me to study
design at the university.
But during my time at the
university, I had a crisis.
I started to feel like maybe this was
Then I discovered web development,
which rekindled my childhood love
of creative and building things.
That turned me on to my course called
Creative Programming for Design.
I became a teaching assistant
in that class, inspired by one
of my professors, Ricardo Vega.
So this talk is for you, Ricardo.
Through this journey, I made
amazing connections, like my
friend Valentina Gaete, who was
one of the students in that class.
Vale went in to pursue a
master's degree in Germany.
And she always tell me that
this class changes her life.
My own preliminary thesis at draft was
about algorithmic logos, which sparked my
interest in merging art and technology.
Now, as a professor, I strive my
students the same inspiration and
opportunities that I received.
I'm not currently in a full creative role.
My goal is to bring creativity back
to my work and help the students
to involve technology to open
up opportunities for themselves.
My journey to where I am has
not been any fun by linear.
When I start, I didn't imagine I
will become a team leader, a speaker
at conference like this, or even a
volunteer in per woman and girls in tech.
In fact, for a long time, I was
show an introverted person too
afraid to speak up or take On
challenge that feels beyond my reach.
I use it to see leadership in and public
speaking as Things other people did.
People were naturally outgoing and
confident, not someone like me.
But everything began to change when
I realized that growing comes from
stepping outside the comfort zone.
My roles today, whether team leader,
mentorship, or giving talks, didn't come
because I had everything to figure it out.
They became, I took risks and
pressed filters, and learned.
to trust my own voice.
Along the way, I discovered incredible
satisfaction of helping others,
especially women in tech, to find
their place in a world that often
feel like it's not made for us.
That's why I became a volunteer and
a speaker to share what I've learned
and help others on their own journeys.
This sack is part of that mission to
spear You to see how your own potential.
So let's start with the basic.
What is an algorithm?
I'm sure that most of you have
come across this term, but let me
sure we are all in the same page.
An algorithm is essential, a set of
instructions, a step by step process,
solving a problem or performing a task.
It's like a receipt of cake.
There are specific steps to follow
to reach the desired outcome.
In the world of programming.
Algorithms are what make computers
capable of performing complex operations.
Whether you realize it or not, algorithms
are everywhere, from recommending
what video you should watch next to
controlling traffic lights, And even
in the art we are about to create.
Now, there's a, here's a big question.
What is art?
Definitive art is something
philosophers and artists have
been debating for centuries.
And there's no answer.
For some, art is about
beauty and aesthetics.
For others, it's art.
About emotion or making a
statement, art can be way of
seeing the world of expression,
something that world can capture.
Here's are some aspect to consider
creative expression, aesthetic value,
mediums and forms, interpretation
and perception in innovation and
tradition and cultural significance.
The way we create and experiment art.
As involved dramatic in the recent years,
with the risk of digital technology,
art now have access to tools that
previous generations could have imagined.
Today, art is confined to a paint
or canvas or sculpted in marble.
It's pixels, code, and
even virtual spaces.
Digital art allows to blend
mediums to collaborate in ways
that were never possible before.
The boundaries between art, design, and
technology have become increasingly fluid.
And algorithmic art is a
perfect example of that.
This new frontier where
creative meets competition.
Algorithmic art represents a unique form
or artistic expression where technology
and programming play a fundamental
role in the creation of the work.
This type of art is notable for its
ability to transform algorithmic art and
data into visual and sensory experiences,
often challenging or traditional.
Perception of art.
Algorithmic arts is a perfect example
of how art and technology can merge in
a way that is both precise and poetic.
It learns the computing power of
computers to create pieces of art.
That would be impossible or last
extremely time consuming to make by hand.
Artists know as algorithms,
used to code design algorithms
that generate visual works.
This algorithm can produce intricate
patterns, complex geometries, or
even simulation of natural process.
And the beauty lies in the fact that
Often, no two outputs are the same.
The art evolves based on the algorithm,
logic, input, and randomness.
This art pushes the boundaries of
what traditional thinks, of acts,
creative, offering, and so on.
new ways to explore and express ideas.
An algorist is an artist
who use algorithms as part
of the creative process.
But begin an algorithm is
more than just write code.
It's about seeing code
as a tool of expression.
For this artist, algorithm becomes
the paint brushes and the computer
screen They use code to generate art,
creating everything from abstract
design to interact visualization.
An algorithm doesn't just
program for function.
They program for beating meaning,
embracing the unpredictable impression
that becomes with algorithmic design.
In September 1995, the term algorithm was
coined by the artist Jean Pierre Herbert.
He wanted to describe artists
who use algorithms as the
primitive tool for creating art.
At the time, it was a new concept.
Combine the world into one.
For a fine art with the pressure of
computer science, Herbert and others in
the field recognized that algorithms could
do more than solve mathematical problems.
They could be used to explore
creative in neodymamic ways.
His work set a stage for the explosion
of digital art that we're seeing today,
and the term algorithm has become to
symbolize the fusion of these two worlds.
Now.
We have JavaScript, JavaScript is
the one of the most versatile and
widely used programming language.
Today, Origin created for
adding interactive to website.
It had grown for far beyond that.
JavaScript now powers everything
from the web app service.
And yes, it's even because powerful.
Told for creating art.
What makes JavaScript special
for our purpose is flexibility.
It's accessible enough for beginners
to pick up quickly, but powerful from
enough for complex artist projects.
JavaScript is an incredibly
powerful language, but what
makes it even more versatile is
the vast ecosystem of libraries.
There are libraries for everything.
Let's say you work on a website, you
go to libraries like React or Vue to
build dynamic user interface, need to
make, manage massive amounts of data.
there's D3JS for data visualization
or libraries like Loudish for
simple complex data manipulation.
Want to animate?
GreenScogs.
has you covered for six Even if you
need to handle something mundane
as date and times, don't worry,
there's moment, yes, to help you out.
We even have libraries for libraries.
Tools like Webfar or Babel exist to
optimize and bundle all your code
together, making everything run smoother.
So yes, JavaScript developers often joke
that if there's a problem, there's a
probably already a library to solve it.
But what about art?
Yes, even for creating
art there are libraries.
Today we'll focus on one of those, p5.
js.
This library was specifically designed
to bring the power of coding into
the hands of artistic and creatives.
Whenever you design art, Interactive
visuals generate patterns of something
complex, completely unexpected.
P5.
js unlocks a world of artistic
possibilities through code.
P5.
js is a fantastic library created by
Lauren McCartney, and it was designed
to make coding accessible to us.
Artists, designers, educators, and
anyone interested in the creative coding.
Lauren's vision was to make a
tool that allows people to create
visual art with code without
needing to be an expert programmer.
It's built on the top of processing, a
popular framework used by creative coders.
And it brings all of the power
into the JavaScript ecosystem.
There's a story of P5.
Yes.
2001 processing was developed
by Cassy Rian, an artist and
verified data scientists.
In 2001, Cassy Rias and Ben Fried.
Both students at the MIT
Media Lab create Processing.
Their goal was to develop a software
sketchbook and a language that
would serve the electronic art
and visual design communities.
Processing was designed to be an
easy to use language for artists and
designers, convening visual programming
environment with a simple syntax to
encourage experimentation and creativity.
In 2008, Processing.
js was developed by John Reesing.
a programmer.
In 2008, John Risen, known for
his work on jQuery, developed
the developer Processing.
js.
This was a JavaScript port for
processing, allowing processing
code to run natively in web browsers
without the need for Java plugins.
Processing.
js made it easier to integrate
processing sketches into the web
page and brought the capabilities
of processing to a broader audience.
in 2013, P five was developed.
Vale Laura McCarty, artist and
programmer Laura McCarty developed P 5G.
SP five GS is a JavaScript leverage
that aim to make coding accessible for
artists, sinus education and beginners it.
It's a repertation of processing for
the web with a focus on making code
more approachable and inclusive.
McCartney works on p5.
js, empathizes,
interactive and creativity.
Building on legacy of processing.
Will leverage modern web technologies.
Between 2014 and 2015, some Java and
processing updates make it difficult
for processing JS to remain used.
Between these days, updates to Java and
processing itself create incompatibilities
which uses for processing JS.
These updates make it challenging
to maintain and use processing
JS, leading to a decline in Java.
As the community began to shift
towards more robust solutions like p5.
js, which were better suited
to develop the solution.
To evolving web environments.
Processing JS stopped
active development in 2016.
By 2016, active development
of processing has changed.
The community and developers
recognize that P5.
js was more viable option for web
based provisional programming.
P5.
js provides a more modern and
versatile platform, prompting the
focus to shift and turn it towards
its development and support.
In 2018, the PFGS online
editor was launched.
Online editor made it even easier
for users to start coding with PFGS
without needing to start any software.
The editor provides a user friendly
interface, fostering a collaborative
and accessible environment
to learn and creative coding.
It became a significant resource for
educators and learners worldwide.
In 2020, Both Processing and P5.
js continue to be actively
used in development.
Processing continues to evolve
as a powerful tool for creating
code in Java, while P5.
js thrives as its JavaScript
counterpart for web based projects.
The ongoing development of both
platforms ensures that they remain
a valuable resource for artists,
designers, and programmers.
What are the differences
between Processing and P5?
Processing was based in
Java with its own IDE.
What are its strengths?
It's easy to use.
Designed for artists and non
programmers, Processing has a
simple syntax that is easy to learn.
Performance as a Java based platform,
Processing often offers better performance
for more computationally intensive talks.
Community and libraries.
Processing has a large community
and many libraries available for
tasks such as computer vision,
data visualization, and more.
Desktop applications.
Great for creating stand alone desktop
applications and installations.
What are its weaknesses?
Web integration.
Web integration, less straight off to
integrate with technology compared to p5.
js.
Processing is somewhat insulate
from modern JavaScript ecosystem,
which include powerful tools and
libraries for web development.
p5.
js P5GS is a JavaScript library
often used with web based IDE
or integrated into web projects.
What are its strengths?
Web integration.
P5GS is designed to work seamlessly
with web technologies, making it ideal
for interactive web based projects.
Accessibility.
Since it's run in the browser,
P5GS projects are easily
accessible and shareable via URL.
Leverage.
P5GS.
The power of modern JavaScript
ecosystem, including tools, library and
frameworks like React, Vue and D3JS.
Learning resources, extensive
documentation and tutorial, practical
and suitable for Beginners learning
coded through creative problem, weakness.
As a JavaScript library, P5.
js might not perform as well as processing
for more computational intensive tasks.
Creating a standalone desktop
application can be more
complex compared to processing.
With P5.
js, you are still using
the same JavaScript basics.
Functions, variables, loops, and logic.
Just like any other program.
But there's an exception.
exciting part.
Instead of outputting data or perform
calculation, you're creating visual
experience directly on canvas.
When you use V5.
js, it generates an HTML file
with a canvas element and that
canvas becomes your virtual paper.
Everything you draw, animate, or
interact with happens inside this canvas,
allowing you to bring your code to life.
To life in a visual way.
Functions like set up and
draw are essential in define
what appears on the compass.
Set up runs once like setting this
and draw is where the action happens.
It's like the function that gets called
continuously to create animation or
update your visual frame by frame.
Essentially every line of code you write
is an instruction for what gets to draw.
Onto that canvas, making coded,
direct and creative process.
Let's take a look at this template for the
PFGS website that creates a star shape.
The beauty of this code
is in its simplicity.
It uses basic geometric principles and
loops to generate points of a star.
Placing each vertex with.
Precise mathematical accuracy.
By routing and scale, you can create
a pattern that feels both calculated
and organic at the same time.
What's powerful here is that just
a few lines of code can produce
something visually striking.
One of the most exciting aspects of p5.
js is the ability to create
interactive experience.
With just a few lines of code, You can
make your artwork respond to user input.
Whatever is through the mouse,
keyboard, or even the sound.
For example, you can track the
position of the mouse and use that
data to move elements on the canvas
or change colors dynamically.
Imagine Creative a painting that
reacts to where you click or draw
your mouse across the screen.
With P5.
js, interaction is as simple as
using built in functions like MUSE.
X and Muse I to detect the position
of the mouse or key press it to
respond to the keyboard inputs.
You can even incorporate audio input
to visually sound waves or create
artwork that reacts to external sounds.
The potential for creation is
limitless, making your audience
a part of creative process.
P5GS is particular with suit
for creating geometric patterns,
which are often visually captivity
and mathematical presses.
By convening shapes like circles,
squares and triangles with loops
and transformations, you can create
intricate designs that will be
incredibly difficult to write by hand.
Whether it's still in patterns, mandalas,
or optical illusion, the presence of
the computer allows you to play with
symmetry, repetition, and scale in a
way that results in measurable visuals.
And because you are working with
code, you can easily tweak parameters
like size, color, or rotation for
of elements to explore endless
variations of the same pattern.
Fractals and interactive
systems are another fascinating
area to explore with P5GS.
These are patterns that repeat themselves
at different scales, often resulting in
highly detailed and complex structures.
A classic example is the Mandelbrot
set or the Sierpinski triangle.
With P five GS, you can use recursion
where a function calls itself to
generate fractals that reveal infinite
complexity as you zone in or out.
These fractal designs are not only
beautiful, but also demonstrate the power
of mathematical and in creating art.
Data visualization is another
exciting application of 5GS.
exciting application of P5GS.
By mapping data to visual elements like
shape, color, and size, you can create
visual representations of complete
datasets that are easy to understand.
Wherever you're working with scientific
data, social media metrics, or any
type of your information, P5GS can help
you turn that numbers into visuals.
For example, you can create by bar
charts, scatter plots, or even abstract
visualization where data points become
a part of larger artistic composition.
This approach not only makes data
more engaging, but also allows you to
tell story with, through your visuals.
P5.
js can also use to simulate natural
phenomena from the movement of
particulars to behavior of flock of birds.
You can model real world
systems using code.
By applying rules that mimic natural
processes, you can create simulations
that behave in life like ways.
For example, you can simulate the
growth of plants, the flow of water,
or even the way animals move in groups.
They are simulations that are not
only visually interesting, but you
can provide insight into Underling
mechanic of nature, all will pushing the
boundaries of what art can represent.
Randomness is a key ingredient
in many forms of algorithmic art.
By incorporating randomness
into your code, you can create
piece that never the same twice.
For example, you could generate a forest
trees with each tree as a unique shape.
Or create abstract art where
colors and shapes appear in
abstract and predictable forms.
P5.
js makes it easy to add randomness with
functions like random that introduce
variables in size, position or color.
The element of chance in your data adds
a layer of spontaneity allowing for
surprise and often beautiful results.
Beyond just reacting to user input, P5.
js allows for randomness.
Fully interactive generation where
the user can activate the app work.
For example, you can create a
drawing tool that viewers become
the artist clicking and drawing
into their shapes on the canvas.
Or you can build environments where the
user controls the evolution of patterns,
adjusting parameters in real time to
influence what happens on the screen.
This floor, the line between creator
and audience turn the artistic process
into collaborative experiences.
One of the most Famous examples of
algorithmic art is Conway's Game of Life,
which is a tip of cellular automaton.
In this simulation, simple rules detect
wherever a cell on a grid is alive or
dead, and from those rules incredibly
complex patterns emerge over time.
What makes this fascinating
is that it mimics real world
processes, like the growth of a
population for the spread of fires.
From a few basic rules, the game of
life has been a source of inspiration
for artists and scientists alike.
And with P5GS, you can easily create
your own version of the cellular automata
to explore beauty and simplify life.
rule bus system.
Now we have covered a wide
range of possibilities.
I want to share some resources that
will help you drive deeper into the
world of algorithmic art with p5.
js.
Whenever you are a beginner or an
experienced coder, the resource will
provide inspirations, tutorials, and
tools to help you to create your own code.
One of the best platforms to
explore and share your p5.
js creation is Open Processing.
It's an online community where artists
and coders share their projects, providing
inspiration and learning opportunities.
You can browse thousands of sketches,
many of which are open source,
meaning you can see the code behind
the visuals, learn from it, and even
remix it to create something new.
Open Processing is valuable not just
for showcasing work, but for fostering
collaboration and experimentation
with the creative coding community.
Let's look about this
sketch on Open Processing.
This sketch uses basic shape
repetition and randomness to
create an organic looking pattern.
The code starts by definition,
simple shapes like circles and lines.
Then applies randomness to
their position, size, and color.
What do you guess is visually interesting?
Piece that looks like it was
drawn by hand, even though is
entirely generated by code.
Next, we have this example,
which showcases how p5.
js can be used to create
fluid continuous motion.
This script simulates particles moving
across the canvas, influenced by
invisible forces like gravity or wind.
The co release allows us to on vector
to define the position and velocities
of each particle, creating a dynamic
flowing visual that feels almost alive.
It's a great example of how PFGS can
bring movement and energy into your art.
Finally, let's look at that example.
This sketch demonstrates that the power
of convenient randomness with control.
The artist uses randomness to generate
abstract shapes, but also add parameters
that control how the object moves.
How those shapes evolve every time.
The result is a piece that feels both
chaotic and intentional, where every
refresh of the page brings something new.
Yet, grounded, like this.
Same underlying structure.
As we see today, Algorithmic
Arts is a powerful way to
merge creative and technology.
It's also allowed us to explore
new forms of expression where the
artists and the code collaborate
to create something unique.
What excites me most about this
field is that it challenges
the traditional idea of art.
It invites us to see beautiful in
logic, randomness, and in creativity.
in the unexpected.
Algorithmic art reminds us that
creativity doesn't have to be confined
to paint brushes or scoping tools.
It can soon live in the code we write.
I know I've covered a lot of ground
today, and if you want to dig deeper,
there's an excellent resource I have
They've referenced it through this talk.
If you enjoyed this talk and want to see
more of my work, or you have questions
about getting started with Algorithms
VS, feel free to follow me on Instagram.
I love to share, connect, and see what
amazing creations you come up with.