Hello everyone, I'm really
excited to be here with you today.
The topic that we're going to discuss
today is about the next generation
of web bundling with RSPack.
My name is Konstantinos or Kostas
and I'm actually a software engineer
at BIT, where BIT is basically the
simplest way for you to join the
journey to component driven development.
We provide a collection of tools to
build and reuse components really fast.
These are some of my social handles.
You can find them on Twitter or X on
GitHub and also on Bitcloud, where
I will be able to share some of the
resources of this talk with you later on.
But before we jump on to the RS
pack, let's discuss what is a bundle.
A JavaScript bundle is
a very simple thing.
It's a collection of multiple
scripts combined into a single file.
During Sentinel Bundler, what it had to
do was actually a plus equal operation,
like a concatenation for a long time.
And this was a actually what
Everyone was needed then.
I don't know how many of you
are familiar with Browserify.
Browserify is a tool that was released
in 2013 and solved the problem of Node.
js developers who wanted to reuse
their code into the browser.
What it was doing, it was actually
making the common JS module system
work for the browser by crawling
the dependency tree, reading files,
and building a single bundle file.
It also made node built ins and
conventions like, for example,
process, buffer, crypto, etc.
work in the browser by implementing
polyfills and symbols for them.
This was a ridiculous amount
of work that had to go into
building all this infrastructure.
And basically what it was doing was
Webpack was trying to understand
which kind of environment this
module was actually running into.
And depending on this
environment, if it was a Node.
js environment or a browser
environment, would expose this module.
After some time, in 2015, Webpack
was actually, was introduced.
And Webpack's goal was to
create a dependency graph for
all the assets of the website.
It is not just JavaScript
Browserify, but it also includes
CSS images, SBGs, even HTML.
And what this enable enabled us to do
was actually break some node conventions
and introduce code like this where
we were actually able to require CS
files or SVG files into the JavaScript.
And the reason Webpack did that
was for a few different reasons.
Now, website assets can be
expressed as a dependency graph.
And it becomes easy to define
components as a collection of
HTML, CSS, JavaScript images, etc.
As standalone modules that can be
easily reused or even published to npm.
Hot module replacement, which is very
important for the development purposes,
is easy and natural because we are based
on a JavaScript module system for assets.
And even, for example, for stylesheets
can automatically be updated by injecting
and replacing into the DOM via script.
Finally, it is providing a lot of
configurability through loaders
and plugins, meaning we can get the
benefits of an integrated module
system without having to ship gigantic
JavaScript bundle to your users.
And here you can actually
see the adoption of Webpack.
The adoption has been amazing.
most of the web projects
are using web app today.
And you can see that lately has
actually reached 120 million
downloads per month, the last.
Even when I search just for
Webpack on NPM, you can see
that it returns 6, 000 packages.
So you can understand how big
this adoption has been and how
many tools and modules have
been built related to Webpack.
But this actually started
getting a bit out of hand.
more difficult for us because
with web app, we started having
different performance issues like
bundle sizes, really slow hot module
replacement, with some tools like
react and production build times.
And this.
Resulted to a great amount of different
articles of how we can actually
optimize and make the webpack bundling
and development server faster.
This is when RxPack basically came in.
RxPack was initially created to solve the
performance problems encountered by Dice.
Bytance is a very big company,
you can, you might have heard
them before, for TikTok or CapCut,
they're actually building quite
many different tools and products.
And it's basically a tech
company that maintains many large
monolithic application projects
with complex bundling requirements.
The production build times have grown
a lot in Bidens, 10 times to even half
hour in some cases, and cold start
times could exceed several minutes.
This is how RSPack is actually pronounced.
RSPack comes with a
great amount of benefits.
It provides high performance for
bundling, a really fast startup time
for your development server, light
and fast hot module replacement,
for your development purposes.
It comes with Webpack compatibility,
offering backwards compatibility with the
configuration that we provided in Webpack.
And it's also framework agnostic, which
means you can actually use it with
tools like React, Vue, JS, Svelte, etc.
And speaking of performance, as you
can see here, it is really fast.
It's basically compared with a
combination of Webpack and Babel.
It is way, way much faster and
also compared to more up to
date bundling tooling like Vite.
The community is really
excited about RSPack.
You can see that even Repack, a tool
about bundling React Native code
using Webpack, has actually tried
migrating to RSPack and found out
five times faster build times and HMR.
The reason RSPack is so fast
it is because it is based on
Rust and is written in Rust.
Rust language efficiency is designed to
prioritize performance topping benchmarks
for speed and memory management.
it is highly parallelized
architecture, where JavaScript is
a weak support for multi threading.
RSPack's native code takes full
advantage of the modern multicore CPUs.
And this is how RSPack actually
generates binary native code.
So the native code that runs
in your operating system.
And the way that SPAC actually does
that is through a tool that is called
Nappy Rs, which is a framework for
building pre-compiled no JS ADONs in RAs.
And what it does, it actually generates
the native code that you run in your
system, in your operating system, and
an OJS library that you can use in
your application, like an SDK, that can
communicate with the Rust implementation
that has been exposed in this native code.
It comes with a great amount of
features, like built in CSS support,
even for CSS modules, This is currently
experimental, but you can still use it
and it's very good support for built in
support for asset management, like for
example, PNG files, SVG files, JPEG,
even JSON files, also web workers.
And it also provides different
loaders for TypeScript and JSX for
CSS, as I mentioned before, a lot
of plugins for HTML or CSS Extract
plugin, for example, the hot module
replacement is really easy to implement.
Now, for example, with react or
any other tools, it also provides
a lot of optimizations that you
don't need to configure, like
code splitting and reshaping as it
are, they are offered by default.
And of course, module federation
version two, which is actually a great
amount of work, for this ecosystem.
But you might be wondering, that's
all great, but how can I actually
migrate from Webpack to RSPack?
We can start with some of the
dependencies, so you can actually
add RSPack core and RSPack CLI
to your development dependencies,
and then you can actually remove
Webpack CLI, and Webpack dev server.
Then, in your packagation, in
your npm scripts, You can replace
Webpack CLI from using to RSPack
and this is like very simple.
You just change the command that you
run, but you can actually use it with
the same API and configuration options.
And finally, what you need to do
is rename your webpack config.
js file to rspack config.
js.
And I think that's all.
We are, this is the
presentation for today.
That's actually a joke, a
really bad joke, sorry for that.
But still, you can
actually, this is enough.
For you to start using, RSVAP and this
is the magic of it because it is very
simple to, to do it and you can start
getting the performance benefits out of it
very, simply with this kind of migration,
depending on your configuration,
you might need to make some more
adjustments and we're going to see now
what are these kinds of configurations
that, we will need to adjust.
First of all, loaders, RSpack loader,
runner is fully compatible with
Webpack's loader functionality.
It is supporting the vast majority of
Webpack loaders, and, you can use your
existing loaders without any changes.
But in order to get the benefits of RSpack
and the REST implementation it comes with,
you will need, for example, to change.
The bubble loader to
built in SD SWC loader.
This is a loader that is, written in
rust, by our team and, is providing
much, much better performance.
And the way that you can do that, for
example, is you might have such a web
configuration with, A TSX and a JSX loader
using bubble and some presets depending.
on your files and then what you need to
do is basically migrate that to using
the built in SWC loader that provides
support for both TypeScript and JSX.
and using built in SWC loader offers
better performance, as I said, compared
to the Babel loader and the external
SWC loader, as it avoids frequent
communication between JavaScript and Rust.
You will also need to change some of these
loaders like the file loader to the asset
resource, the URL loader to asset inline,
and the row loader to asset source.
Asset resource converts an asset to a
separate file and exports the URL address.
The AssetInline converts an asset
to a data URI using Base64 encoding.
At the moment, no other codings
are supported, but later on
we might have more of them.
And AssetSource converts and exports
the asset file as a raw string.
When we actually say about
plugins, we mean built in plugins
and also community plugins.
RSPack has implemented most of the
Webpack's built in plugins with the same
name and configuration parameters allowing
for easy replacement, and also supports
most of the Webpack community plugins
and also offer alternative solutions
for some currently unsupported ones.
So for example, in Webpack configuration,
if you're using defined plugin,
you can actually Migrate to RSPack
1 by changing the import and also
changing the reference to RSPack 1.
And this is very simple.
Similarly, you might be using, your
HTML, the HTML Webpack plugin, which
is a way for you to integrate HTML
into your Webpack configuration.
This plugin is supported in RSPack as
well, but if you want to get the benefits
of the Rust based implementation of the
same plugin, you can actually reference
to the RSPack implementation of it.
this is implemented in Rust, and its
build performance is significantly
better than HTML Webpack plugin.
There's some differences between
those two plugins, just to be
aware, but for the majority of
the purposes will fit your needs.
RxSpack team has done a great job
in documenting all these, available
plugins that you can use with RxSpack
and you can find them in this page
over here in the documentation.
But like any migration, there
are some caveats and these are
related mostly to SCSS modules.
I don't know if you're familiar
with this error, with this warning.
this is basically happening
when, the default export is not
available when you import a module.
This is usually happening,
in a React project.
For example, when you import the
styles from your CSS module like this,
and then you're able to provide the
class names, to your JSX elements.
Like this.
so by default, this is going to be the
error that you're going to be facing.
This is the warning.
this warning is there because the
compilation will still be successful.
But when you run the application in
your browser, you will actually see the
application without any styles applied.
And what you would need to do in order to
change that is actually change your source
code from importing the default export.
To, to import everything
as an alias of styles.
But as I'm not a fan of basically,
changing your source code because
you're basically migrating to a new
tool from Webpack to RSPack, I would
prefer to do that with the tool itself.
The way that you can do that is by
enabling the built in support of
CSS, which is still experimental in
RSPack, but it's still experimental.
And this is actually how you can
actually, you can enable and try
out some experimental features in
RSPack with experiments object.
Once enabled, RSPack will enable
native support and CSS related
parsers and generator options.
Then you will be able to define this
kind of configuration for generator and
parser by disabling the named exports
when you parse the CSS related files.
And also by disabling the ES modules
For this reason, then you will be able
to define your loaders for SCSS files
by using the SaaS loader, which is not
built in, supported, in our respect.
so you will still need to
define this kind of loader.
And you need to define the type CSS
auto, which helps RSPAC understand
that these, these files can actually
be either CSS or CSS modules, and it
can, actually decide which of them,
should, how it should handle its case.
then you can.
Change your CSS, loader to just type
CSS and, RSpec will take care of loading
your CSS files in the, in your code base.
And since you're actually now
have the built in support, you
can actually entirely remove
the CSS loader for that purpose.
This behavior I would like to
see be supported by default.
And this is something that I have
raised with our respect team before.
And I would be very happy for you if
you're able to support this kind of
approach, because it could be really
important for us To be able to use,
SSS modules without the need to do all
this extra configuration in RSPack.
And, with Bit we basically
have helped a lot of customers
migrate to RSPack already.
We have seen at least three times faster
build times, if not five, in some cases.
And basically the way that
we've done that is with, a tool
that is called Configimitator.
Configimitator.
which helps you migrate to
RSPAC much, much easier.
You can imagine that usually this
is a configuration that you would
need with RSPAC, for example.
But what if, instead of all this
configuration, you were able to write
something simpler, just like this, which
is by importing the RSPAC config imitator.
Then you can actually initialize this
new data and can start creating your
own configuration with a much more
descriptive language, like setting
the mode to development, adding the
CSS, the TypeScript support, and even
React support, if needed, by providing
this extra parameter, adding the CSS
modules without the need to know the
internals of how our Spark works.
is actually working under the hood and,
also providing SCSS support, without
the need to configure the generators,
the parser or everything like that.
And what is the benefit of this tool?
It can even use Your own configuration,
the configuration that you have, you
already, provided, your own custom
configuration and updated based on
your needs, for example, by adding the
TypeScript support, with React or not,
or CSS modules and everything like that.
And, you can actually find
this config mutator, this tool,
it is documented on Bitcloud.
This is a link where you can actually
find out and learn more about how you
can actually start using this tool, how
you can, start migrating using this tool.
And this is basically the way
that we have helped a lot of
customers migrate to RSPack already.
Finally, RSpack is the building
block for a great amount of web
infrastructure that RSpack team provides.
On top of RSpack, we have rsbuild,
rspress, rsdoctor, and rslib.
Which are few different
tools for different purposes.
RS Build is a tool that provides an out
of the box setup for development purposes.
RPR is a static site generation tool.
RS Doctor is basically a great
tool for analyzing and visualizing
the build process and artifacts.
And R Lib is a build tool.
Mostly targeting to lib authors.
And with that, I think
that's all for today, folks.
Thank you for joining me today.
I really appreciate it.
And I hope you learned
something new today.
Thank you very much.
Bye.