Hi, I'm Ajita Bona Chandran, and
I'm a PRI principal machine learning
and a generative AI engineer
in our leading investment firm.
Thank you so much for giving me this
opportunity to present my topic.
In this conference, I'll be taking the
next 15 to 20 minutes to talk about
agent search, powering next generation
insights using multi-agent intelligence.
Let's consider a typical
enterprise scenario.
Maybe there's a financial
organization that manages multiple
terabytes of operational data.
A senior decision maker requires
analysis of declining mobile banking
satisfaction metrics, and strategic
recommendations for improvement.
Traditional search systems return
thousands of potentially relevant
documents requiring extensive manual
review to extract actionable insights.
This process typically requires
several days and may result
in incomplete analysis.
Agent search system offer an alternative
approach, comprehensive analysis
delivered within minutes, incorporating
trend identification, competitive
benchmarking, root cause analysis,
and strategic recommendations through
coordinated multi-agent intelligence.
Today I will demonstrate how JavaScripts
architectural characteristics
position it as an optimal platform
for implementing these systems.
Let's talk a bit about the search problem.
Before that, let's quickly
see what the agenda is.
We will understand what the search problem
is, and then we will briefly talk about
evolution of various search paradigms.
We will also talk about the agent,
multi-agent architecture, which is the
topic of the day and how JavaScript
implementation works in this case.
We'll also talk a little bit
about real world impact and future
considerations that you can take
away from this particular session.
So what is the search
problem that we face today?
Enterprise data volumes have expanded
exponentially with many organizations
managing Pega bytes of structured
and unstructured information.
However, traditional keyword based
search systems remain functionally
limited in their ability to transform
this data into actionable intelligence.
Current search paradigms operate
on lexical matching principles
designed for document retriable
rather than inside generation.
When executors require complex
analytical responses, these systems
return document collections that further
require extensive human interpretation
to derive meaningful conclusions.
Research indicates that knowledge
workers spent approximately
half of the day looking for
information on searching for them.
And maybe only 50 to 60 per 60% of
these searches yield relevant results.
The financial impact in this case is
significant, delayed strategic decisions,
missed market opportunities, and
inefficient res resource allocation.
The fundamental issue here
is very architectural.
Traditional search systems are
designed for information location,
not intelligence synthesis.
The enterprise requirements have
evolved beyond document matching
towards comprehensive analysis,
prediction, and strategy recommendation.
Let's talk a little bit briefly
about evolution of search paradigms.
The first one is keyword search.
Keyword search operates like we
spoke about lexical pattern matching
and term frequency analysis.
This approach delivers documents based
solely on literal word presence, often
producing high volumes of irrelevant
results with very limited precision.
The second generation is semantic search.
Semantic search represents a significant
advancement actually achieving contextual
comprehension through natural language.
Understanding these systems interpret
meaning and intent, driving conceptually
relevant results with substantially
reduced irrelevant content.
The third generation is the topic that
we are talking about agentic search.
It constitutes a paradigm
shift from passive retrival to
active intelligence generation.
These systems deploy specialized AI agents
that understand the problem structure,
plan investigations, and synthesize
findings into decision ready intelligence.
So now let's talk briefly
about what is agent search.
Like we spoke, this is a fundamentally a
paradigm shift from traditional approaches
through several key capabilities,
collaborative processing through multiple
specialized agents coordinating to handle
different aspects of complex queries,
semantic understanding, providing deep
comprehen comprehension of the query
intent beyond just keyboard matching.
Synthesis generation, transforming
this raw information into actionable
insights and quality assurance through
systematic validation of the findings
through multi-agent verification.
Let's maybe demonstrate all these
capabilities with some practical examples.
Let's consider a business query.
Why?
Why has the mobile banking
satisfaction declined over the past?
Keyword search might require, may return,
maybe a thousand documents containing all
the words that are there in the question.
Mobile banking satisfaction and decline.
This includes irrelevant content
such as mobile phone banking,
hardware specifications.
User would receive quarterly reports,
customer service transcripts,
market materials, and so much of I.
Relevant documents that request, manual
review, man has to go through all the
hundreds of documents that has been.
Returned to extract relevant insights.
This analysis might take
maybe a week or even more.
Systematic search understands the
query intent and focuses on customer
satisfaction trends in mobile banking.
It returns maybe to any concept
conceptually relevant document.
About customer experience metrics,
filtering out all the hardware
on all A 11 stuff, and focusing
mainly on user experience data.
This provides satisfaction surveys,
maybe NPS scores and customer feedback
analysis, and then there could
be some manual synthesis on this
data for maybe about a day or two.
Agentic search orchestrates a
very coordinated investigation.
Research agents simultaneously extract
customer satisfaction metrics from
CRM systems, app store reviews,
support ticket databases, and show
social media monitoring tools.
Such a across the time period that we are
talking about analysis agents process this
data to discover that satisfaction scores
have actually dropped maybe 20% during
the last week of November, and there
was a mobile update at the same time.
And it makes correlation between the
user compliance that are received.
To the navigation complexity.
That was that.
That was introduced because
of the new UI redesign.
Domain expert agents contribute mobile
regulatory context, noting that similar
dissatisfaction patterns or satisfaction
patterns have occurred industry-wide
during digital transformation
initiatives, while identifying the
best practices from competitors
who maintained higher satisfaction
during this transition period.
Quality checking agents cross validate
all these findings to potentially
find out if there was any sampling
bias from C seasonal factors.
The system delivers a
comprehensive intelligence.
It reports the problem and also finds
out like what was the primary cause.
It also does benchmarking by comparing
each two other competitors with similar
experience, and it provides maybe some
really remediation strategies on also
a projected timeline for recovery.
Complete analysis is delivered
within maybe 20 minutes.
So now let's talk about the
multi-agent architecture.
We can use the same example in this
case to understand the architecture
agent search systems, implement
collaborative intelligence through
specialized agent rules, each optimized
for specific analytical functions.
Research agents decompose complex queries
into structured search components and
re drive relevant information across
distributor data systems, including
structured databases and unstructured
documents or even external databases.
Analytical agents process this reive
information to identify pattern.
Correlations and insights using
statistical analysis, machine
learning algorithms and domain
specific analytical frameworks.
Domain expert agent applies the
specified knowledge and industry
specific context to ensure analytical
accuracy and relevance within a
particular operational environment.
Quality checking agent validates the
findings through systematic verification,
including bias detection, accuracy
assessment, and completeness evaluation.
So how do these agents collaborate?
The multi Asian coordination.
Operates through four distinct phases.
Query interpretation phase is where
the research agents analyze the
user queries to find out what are
the underlying requirements, and it
decomposes this complex query into
manageable investigative components.
Distributed execution phase where
agents execute a specialized task.
In parallel with research agents
gathering data, while analysis agents
have begun the preliminary pattern
identification, collaborative synthesis
phase, domain experts and analysis agents
integrate their findings to generate
coherent analytical narratives that
address the original query requirement.
Quality validation phase where we
verify the qua, the accuracy, eliminates
potential bias, and ensure an analytical
integrity before the final delivery.
This architecture enables
processing capabilities that exceed
single agent limitations while
maintaining the analytical rigor
and systematic quality AC assurance.
Let's now talk about why JavaScript
and why it is a natural fit.
JavaScript's, even driven asynchronous
architecture provides optimal
support for multi-agent coordination.
The language native capabilities
for handling concurrent operations,
message passing and distributed task
orchestration directly addresses the
communication and coordination challenges
inherent to multi-agent system.
Nor JS serves as an execution environment
for high performance non-blocking
coordination among the agents.
The platform's asynchronous IO model
enables efficient handling of multiple
concurrent agent requests while
maintaining system responsiveness.
Complementary frameworks within
the Java systems ecosystem provide
enterprise grade capabilities.
For example, express JS and NS
js offer robust microservice
architecture foundations.
Event driven messaging services enable
reliable inter communication, load
balancing and fault tolerance, mechanism
mechanisms, ensure system reliability.
So now what are the core building blocks,
line chains, JS function as?
The distributed orchestration,
coordinated agent activities across
microservices using message queues,
even buses and workflow engines.
Systematic query interpretation,
transform the natural queries that are
coming in into structured intent using
embedding models, entity extraction,
and contextual understanding framework.
Dynamic Knowledge exchange enable
agents to share context findings and
state through shared memory systems,
vector database, and real time data
streams, quality assurance layer.
It implements various validation
pipelines that check for factual accu
accuracy, logical consistency, and bias
detection before returning the results.
This slide is a comparison between
agentic and traditional search.
So we see four, four different key
parameters, which is the, they are
the KPIs, context, understanding,
reasoning, capabilities, insight
generation, and quality assurance.
And in all of them we can see that
the agent searches are performing way
better than both synthetic as well
as the traditional search methods.
Now let's talk about the
implementation pathway.
Organizations can implement the
agent search systems through
a very structured approach.
First they have to design
their agent personas.
Define specified roles and
responsibilities and communication
protocols for each of the
agent that they are choosing.
Within the organizational context,
build the architect the orchestration
layer, implement even driven
coordination using JavaScripts famous
and message broker systems to enable
reliable inter agent communication.
Integrate knowledge systems, connect
vector databases, semantic search
engines, and large language model
APIs to provide the agents with the
comprehensive data access capabilities
and deploy quality pipelines.
Establish validation mechanism
including bias detection, accuracy
verification, and completeness
assessment before production deployment.
So what are all the tools that
the JavaScript ecosystem provides?
It provides multiple tools with immediate
access to production ready tools that
make implementation really practical.
Today, the land chain JS functions
as the core engine for land, large
language model orchestration, managing
complex actions, sequences, and dynamic
reasoning through chains and engine.
It uses these chains and agents to manage
complex action sequences and dynamic
reasoning, leveraging the expression
language for a robust streaming and
parallel execution essential for advanced
RAC and conversational AI applications.
Vector databases enable RAC
or the Ag augmented generation
implementation storing embeddings
of proprietary data for.
For ultra low latency sematic searches,
rag injects real time context into the
prompts bypassing the LLM context limits,
and significantly reducing hallucinations.
No JS microservices provide enterprise
grade scalability and resilience.
The asynchronous IO model handles
high concurrency crucial for
simultaneous agent request.
Deploy agents.
As mod as modular services
managed by API Gateways for robust
communication load balancing and
accelerated continuous delivery.
This technological foundation
enable implementation of agent
search systems using established
JavaScript development practices at
existing organizational expertise.
Now let's talk about the real
world impact implementation
demonstrates three business impacts.
Faster decision making agents
synthesize massive data sets in
instantly providing real-time
actionable insights that cut critical
analysis time from days to minutes.
Empowering rapid strategic responses,
improved accuracy by leveraging
proprietary data via rack agents,
deliver highly contextualized and
precise answers drastically reducing.
LLM has hallucinations and data errors.
User satisfaction, highly personalized
and context aware interactions result in
relevant, specific information delivered
on demand, elevating the user experience
for beyond traditional search methods.
Organizations report measurable
benefits, including reduced analyst
time allocation to for information
gathering and accelerated strategic
decision implementation, and
improved accuracy of market analysis.
The technology's ability to process
vast data value volumes while
maintaining the analytical rigor
provides competitive advantages in
time-sensitive market environments.
So what are all the challenges that
we have and that the ones that we
should consider latency management.
Multi-agent coordination introduces
overhead, operational overhead, optimize
with caching parallel execution,
progressive result streaming to
maintain the responsiveness LLM calls.
They usually accumulate very quickly.
Implement robust batching result caching
and intelligent model selection to
balance between the quality and budget.
Debu debugging the distributed
agents request comprehensive logging,
tracing, and monitoring across the
Y entire orchestration pipeline.
Quality check agents must actively
detect and mitigate bias in both
the data sources and model outputs
to ensure equitable results.
These challenges represent engineering
problems with established solutions rather
than fundamental implementation barriers.
So how does the future look like?
Agent search represents the initial
implementation of intelligent
problem solving ecosystem that
scale with enterprise requirements.
Future developments will enable
systems that anticipate organizational
needs, proactively surface the
strategic insights and continuously
learn from operational interactions.
The convergence of JavaScript's flex
flexibility with the multi-agent
intelligence creates opportunities for
innovation across multiple enterprise
domains beyond information re driver.
Organization face a strategic
decision regarding agent
tech architecture adoption.
The technology foundations exist today.
Implementation pathways are
established and the competitive
advent advantages are measurable.
So with that, I would like
to conclude my presentation.
Thank you so much for your
attention, and I appreciate that
opportunity to present this.
Thank you.