Greetings everyone.
Today's presentation is about building
the future applications using the
microservices architecture and the
upcoming edge computing and the quantum
computing, how to develop applications
with the cloud innovation at scale.
And how the, how it is transforming
the JavaScript development through
all these cloud native patterns
and distributed architectures With
this coming to me, I am Surya.
I'm a graduate from JA Ology
University in electronics and
ion engineering, and I come with
around 18 plus years of experience
developing cloud native applications.
And today I am going to, how, explain
how we are exploring the intersection
of JavaScript ecosystem and modern
cloud native architectures to develop
highly scalable digital platforms.
So all through these years I've
been working with many cloud
native applications and seeing
how they're evolving and playing a
major role in today's development
and going to the next slide.
As we all know, all through this
years JavaScript has been one of the
major front end frameworks and how
it's been playing in clear role in
many web applications development.
Today we are going to see how it has
evolved now with the backbone of cloud
native applications and with the global
development and everything being global,
everything, anything, being global
these days, it is highly important to
keep in mind the development of the
application to be highly scalable,
reliable, and easy to maintain.
And so now the JavaScript
developers are now being are.
Protecting using these microservices
and edge computing for solutions
to have the real time responses and
the distributions that can power
how the applications and the digital
platforms can be highly scalable.
The transformation today needs
highly how we build it is highly
impacting how we build and deploy
and manage applications at scale.
With this, I'll try to go to this,
agenda of the meeting, which assumes
which, which looks like this.
Today's session roadmap will start
with the microservices transformation.
How its adoption has a big search, and
what are the architectural challenges
being faced by the development teams.
And then we'll be moving on to the
edge computing and how it is impacting
with a huge latency reduction and
the real time processing of data.
And then we'll move on to the multi-cloud
strategies, how the flexibility versus
complexity trade offs play a key
role in designing and architecting.
Today's applications, and also we'll
look into the serverless, the future
technologies like the serverless and
the quantum computing, which are the
upcoming next generation architectures
with with the technology in its boom.
It comes up with, comes with the
challenges of security as well.
So towards the end, we'll also
discuss how the security also being
evolving with the new models of
the zero trust and how it's being a
major part in the threat deduction.
Sorry, threat detection With this I'll go
into the presentation which starts with.
We'll see how the microservices
architecture has been
evolved with some numbers.
But before that as we understand for
years we have been stuck with monolithic
architecture where everything is being
developed and deployed as a single
unit, which includes all the front end
backend services and business logic.
Everything is single unit being
deployed and as execution.
Executable unit, which makes it
easy for development and deployment.
But as the complexity of the
application grows we have been
facing challenges of updating and
maintaining the application and even
to update to the new technologies.
It's being a great challenge with that.
Became the microservices architecture
as a solution where it's the collection
of individual independent services, each
having its own business logic, making it
easier to develop and deploy, and easy
to update, maintain scalable, what all
the newly trending features of a global
application is required, is satisfied
by this microservices architecture.
And as we see the adoption surge from
2019, which was at 45% now to till
date, it's been surge to 91% as of 2024.
So it has basically changed even
how the, we architect the JavaScript
applications enabling high scalability
and maintainability and easy to operate.
Sorry.
With that, I would like
to go to the next slide.
So let's see how these microservices
performance impacts the applications.
These are some numbers
with some case studies.
We see that there is a six 76% deployment,
time reduction as we understand the
microservices come as a small units and
with its own business logic is where we
can, scale the particular business unit,
which we are expecting more traffic.
So it's easier to deploy
develop and maintain.
So that's what helped to see the 76%
time reduction in the deployment and
through the automation strategies.
And if we see the cost savings,
obviously with the with the.
Monolithic architecture.
With the high amount of infrastructure
involved, we need to be able to
maintain the infrastructure as well.
But with the newer technologies of
cloud obviously the maintenance is
less, and the infrastructure to be
maintained comes down, which brings
the 50% operational cost savings with
all this new optimized containers.
Freely available in the market.
High volume of cloud native
providers are available.
We'll go into the detail details of
that in going forward, but now, and
so we have seen this huge impact
in sense of the positive way.
Coming to the challenges the teams having
today with this microservice architecture
is the clear line of division between
the services of decomposition of the
business logic into the service units is
highly important to design, to high, to
have this highly effective microservice
architecture designed applications.
So that's what we see.
The challenge currently, the teams
have been facing, which has been 67%
absorbed as we go forward with that.
That's pretty much about the
microservice architecture, how it
has evolved, what it means, and
what are the impacts in numbers.
The, another major training
technology is the edge computing.
It brings basically it brings the
computation closer to the data sources
having these JavaScript applications
having the real time processing easily
available and quickly available with
the early, with the, with the quality
and quantity of data is highly critical.
For example, in the healthcare domains or
we be manufacturing where the sensitivity
and quality of data is critical and and
basically the edge computing provides a
high latency reduction as the computation
is done closer to the data sources
with these JavaScript developers.
Now I keep have to keep in mind while
designing to have the edge computing
available while designing and have it
right from the start of the application
design and makes it the applications more.
Effective and delivering
a great user experiences.
As we talked about the edge
computing, let's move on to the next.
So here are some edge computing
performance gains that has now
observed through these years.
With this process improvements, we
see a 45% faster processing times
42% better real time data handling.
And as we talked earlier,
examples, there's a 33%
efficiency boost in healthcare.
Obviously with the right, data
available in a so fast, it's quick
to take decisions and improve the
efficiency in the healthcare provided.
And also we have seen 56 person faster
emergency response in the manufacturing
section where there is huge depend
dependency between different departments
where where they have to go hand in hand
and the data being available real time
between these departments were, has shown
a significant increase in the efficiency.
Now let's talking about now that
we have seen how the microservice
architecture has been playing and
the upcoming edge computing we will
talk about the multi-cloud strategy
and its complexity involved now.
As we all know with this traditional
traditional monolithic, it's, it the
maintenance of the infrastructure being
of hugely complex and also being cost
involved the new mic, the cloud technology
where it's being available in market.
Place from different providers.
It's being a huge impact of this
multi-cloud in designing the
applications and deployment, which
which involves great benefits as
we see the integration challenges.
It was initially when during the adoption
adoption phase, we saw this 52% hurdles
where it is hard to decide between the
hybrid public cloud, private cloud, and
choosing between them and get your right
cloud strategy for your application.
There were some initial challenges.
Which through time has improved a lot.
And as we understand with the
infrastructure being maintained by
providers most of it with the new
the new deployment strategies like
the SaaS pass and infrastructure as a
service, the governance benefits has
hugely reduced in structured cloud.
Cloud governance could lead up
to 41% reduction and helping
the application and the teams to
easily maintain their applications.
And also we understand the cost
optimization as we discussed it.
There's been a significant decrease
of 32% now with moving out from our
monolithic native infrastructure to the
cloud architectures as we understand the
multi-cloud being available in market.
We more on.
To the next slide, which where we are
discussing, I would to discuss how
the cloud architecture is available.
What are the different
types today available?
As we understand there are like the
public clouds which, where you can
share, your cloud space with other
people and other organizations.
With Will It Come, which comes with
much lesser cost as you share your
cloud with others and the private cloud
available, which is specific to you
and which is a little expensive, but
comes with the safety and all the cloud
space available for your organization.
And there's also a hybrid
cloud architecture.
Which is a mix of this
both public and private.
And the right decision and the right
strategy of this cloud architecture
is very important in designing the
today's JavaScript applications.
As we see, the success requires
careful orchestration between public,
private, and edge computing resources.
How critical is the data to be processed
and do we really need the edge computing
and is it effective to our application?
These are the key points to be
taken into consideration while
designing the applications and
the right cloud architecture.
Proof seems to be the mantra
of success these days.
With that, we'll see how this
serverless revolution has come
up as we see these days with the,
everything is available as a service.
Be it, be platform, be it, be
infrastructure, and be it be anything.
There comes the functions as a service.
These serverless architectures have really
transformed the JavaScript development,
the workflows by reducing the complexity.
As we all understand by improving the
scalability, the 33 per, we see a 33%
reduction in the developmental cycles.
Obviously with the lesser amount
of infrastructure worries and
quick date, quick CICD available.
There's a there's a huge reduction
in the development cycles leading
to the faster time to market
for its JavaScript applications.
These benefits include the automatic
scaling the resource manager meant
as this, and also the cost savings
with the paper execution mo model.
If you're not using, there's
no need to pay, so that's paper
execution cost model is showing.
Significant cost reductions.
And with the new CICD technologies
available like the BB Jenkins, the
significantly reducing the deployment
times makes it easier for the business
to contract to concentrate on their
business and grow to be highly scalable
and highly effective applications.
That's how the serverless
revolution plays a key role.
That let me talk on the next topic,
which is the quantum computing.
As we understand it's closely related
to the quantum mechanics wherein huge
chunks of data is processed at a at a
lightning speed, which speeds up by the
25 times in the complex data processing.
So this resulted in the,
a great optimization.
And also the alg, the JavaScript
libraries, being able to integrate
this quantum inspired algorithms.
It's still under research.
We are would say this is the future, the
quantum computing going to be our future.
This is good to know as of now.
But significant results have
been proven until date, but
it's still under re research.
So that's what.
We are seeing here about the quantum
computing, which highly results
in the speeding up of the data
processing at a lightning speed.
After that, I would like to,
as we said earlier, the asset.
Technology is being in great.
Boom.
There comes the issues with the security
as well, which leads us to this zero
trust, security evolution where the
least privilege is being provided to the
users and the security being, security
being very tight, not allowing everyone
to have every access to everything.
The access would've be provided
on the need basis which highly
reduces the threats and having
access to malicious acts.
Activities would highly be reduced,
and we see a 37 improvement with this
threat reduction and mitigating the
security threats with this zero trust.
And as I said this identity
verification provides access to
where and when needed only to the
specific people and least privilege
is being maintained all through the.
Application development.
And this involves the continuous
authentication and authorization
for every service integration.
So we talked about the microservices
architecture and how the edge
computing playing a key role.
And there comes the service less
architecture and the quantum
mechanics, and how we can highly
secure this with the recent zero
trust, security of all evolution.
We'll move on to.
The next slide.
So that's great.
Everything looks good.
But obviously everything
comes with challenges as well.
Now we are trying to see the actionable
insights how JavaScript engineers
have to keep in mind and effectively
use all these technologies to design
and develop their applications.
So the very first point is coming
to the microservice architecture
where we understand it is the
collection of individual services.
Excuse me, individual services
having their own business logic.
There comes the challenge of the service
decomposition right understanding of
the business is key in designing these
services, which is being initially was a
challenge where, with this decomposition
and having a right business knowledge.
But going moving forward, it it
has greatly improved and we are
seeing effective results with
the microservice architecture.
Also, the key component as we
discussed, the highly available
and reliable data is keen.
Critical data critical industries like the
healthcare and the manufacturing, we where
the edge computing has been, has to be put
into place and the first thing to be put
in place while developing the JavaScript
applications right from the start.
Then we understand, also understand,
that the multi-cloud governance, it
should be effective to decide to reap the
right benefits of having the right cloud
strategy designed to decide what you need.
Is it be public or the
cloud or the hybrid?
Having the right knowledge was really
important to, to design the cloud
strategy required and providing a
great governance for, reliability,
benefits, cost and reliability benefits.
There comes also the security which we
discussed, which involves the integrate
the zero trust principles while building
the security into every layer of your
JavaScript and provide leads to privilege.
Policy so that it's tightly secured and
highly effective within with the security.
With this insights for the future
development of the, for the JavaScript
engineers we'll try go to the next.
So that's all about my presentation today.
Thank you and looking
forward for any questions.
Thank you.