Hello, I'm Jo Mundi.
I'm going to talk about reinforcement
learning and how to scale RHLF based
systems for distributed learning
across multi GPU environment.
There's a lot of improvements you
can see recently in the models either
the Sonet models or the OPA models.
Where they have done a lot of instruction
based RHLF based models which continuously
improves the performance of these models.
And, i'm going to talk about the
challenges there and also the, core
capabilities that are being used to
build these platforms and systems.
So the agenda to talk is, the,
a little bit summary about our
reinforcement learning from theoretical
frameworks to production systems
the foundations distributed rl what
are the challenges involved there?
Then, the RHL principles and the,
practices that are normally applied in
a production systems for training or for
inference the cloud native architectures.
Mostly these systems are trained on
Kubernetes with multi GPU set up with
proper networking using and will link.
And I'll also talk about some of the
scaling frameworks that I've used.
So mostly on Impala, really
lightning AI deep speed.
Some of the modern frameworks
that are being utilized and the
challenges of monitoring and
deploying these pipelines at at scale.
So reinforcement learning the previous
version of RL based systems was it
came from MDP, it's called markup
Decision Process, where it was
more of a sequential based learning
algorithm where can maximize the
cumulative reward at each step.
But with deep parallel
deep neural networks.
Now there transformer based networks
it can learn deep processing.
Power how the input gets transformed
is a little, is more sophisticated
with the transformer based networks
compared to just a sequential process
in MDP, so it can learn much more
sophisticated functions and multimodal
either be text image or video audio.
So the foundations of distributed
reinforcement learning are there are some
it can be either done in a multi-node,
multi pod system where, there'll be
a main server which will accumulate
all the weights as the system learns
throughout each epoch and each batch.
The core challenges there are networking.
How does the how does the workers,
where the learning is happening,
how do they communicate along with
the servers, and how does the server
accumulate all the weights to make sure
the weight of the entire network is is
is updated after each learning event?
Now the, there are different kinds of
loss functions and policy optimization
algorithms that will be applied.
DD like PPO or GRPO or DDPO.
These are different kinds of
policies that are mainly applied.
There's also actor, critic models
where where you learn from examples.
And these examples are either hand
labeled or it can be sometimes
generated by the machines itself.
So that is, it becomes a
continuous learning feedback loop.
So learning can happen in multiple ways.
So one is the most common
is the from human feedback.
And that there is that is called
supervised fine tuning, where
you have a pre-trained model that
you train on a large cluster.
But then on top of that, then you
have to fine tune based on your own
instructions which are a basic set
of questions and answers for lms.
For vision models, it can be
the image and the labels itself.
So these are human labels and these are
created by experts in specific domains.
For example, doctors or physicians
or math olympiads, they create
this supervised the kid is very.
High quality data set that can be used
for supervised fine tuning, and that
improves the performance of these models.
So to train this data at scale you have
to also make sure you have a reward
model or reward function defined so
that the, so that the entire network
can optimize for that your function.
The policies that can, you can apply
for achieving the reward functions are
like PPO is one of them, as I mentioned.
There's also, DDPO and the GRPO and all
these policies depends on like some of
the policies can do much better than
the others depending on the type of.
The dataset and reward
functions you have defined.
So you need to be very careful in
defining the reward functions because
you there are challenges involved.
There are reward hacking.
If the functions are not defined
properly, the model might try to do
if you can hack the reward function
and it might lead to un consequences,
which are un which are not desirable.
So distributed implementation of RHLF.
There, there is there is one, one
of them most of them are, did,
are trained on different kinds of
large Kubernetes clusters and their
different kinds of frameworks.
Each of them has their own
advantages and disadvantages.
But the most common is data.
The data parallelism and model
parallelism, data parallelism meaning your
model, same model, which is is distributed
across all the pods in the cluster.
And the data it is very large size.
It gets split across those nodes and
the learning happens in each, the
individual pods which are then accumulated
and the, and that the workers, which
learns after each batch, it sends that
weights back to the server, and the
server accumulates those weights and
the neur network weights are updated.
And it's sent back to the workers.
There, there is a grad, the
accommodation strategies.
There are various kind of accommodation
strategies that can happen on the server
pod which is the main pod, which is
monitoring all all the training and
learning across all these workout pods.
And you also have to make sure the
models are checkpoint because some
of this training can take a long
time to to, to train weeks to train.
And sometimes you don't want to
restart the training after after
let's say 50% of the training is done.
You want to make sure it, it can restart
from that checkpoints so that it can, like
in minimize the compute resource that is
needed for the entire training process.
Human feedback collection is
one of the other challenges.
We have like human feedback.
Sometimes sometimes the
feedback loop can be very long.
So depending on the use case some
feedback loops are faster to collect.
Some feedbacks can take
up to months to collect.
So normally in, generally there is
a lot of companies like scale ai.
And know Marco and few others
which helps creating this kind of
labels based on human feedback.
And if you create millions of examples
these examples then becomes a data set
for training RHLF models at school.
And you can control the
quality and also make sure.
The, the evolution systems that we
have are in line with the controls
and the quality that you want
to achieve after the training.
So that when it goes to inference
it can really highly perform
compared to the previous models.
The, there are different kinds of cloud
native architectures for distributor.
There I'll talk more about it.
There are different kinds of
frameworks that are there.
But most of this is run on top of
Kubernetes orchestrating all the pods.
Of the resource management, the
compute management fail word recovery
based on the checkpoints replay
buffers based on that actor, critic
patterning the stateful management
of, of memory as well as the data.
Which is the, the, it can be in, in
terms of sometimes in terms of terabytes.
So all this state management has to be
done and in the proper way so that it
can restart or it can communicate the
states across all these training pods for
a consistent and reliable training run.
Network optimization is
another very important thing.
Your network needs to be really
optimized for this multi GPU training.
And NVIDIA has NNV link, which is really
provides a highly optimal network.
So that, the multi GPU
communications can be done at scale.
And there a lot of improvements
that are going on for low latency
communication across multi GPUs.
So that it can it can reduce down the
compute time when the data and the
state gets passed across these pods.
There are different kinds of frameworks.
Impala is one of them, really is another.
Deep speech is another.
So there are different frameworks
available, and each of these
has their own pros and cons.
And depending on the use case, you can
decide what framework you want to use.
For multi gpu RL based trainings really
is used if you have it gives a lot
of advantages of of the components.
There's some really available components
and metrics are, it gives you the
metrics of how the training is going
like quickly out, out of the box.
DP another one, which is normally used for
very large scale transformer know networks
when you cannot fit the model in one.
GP like the model needs to be distributed.
The model itself needs to be
distributed across multiple GPUs.
The learning happens across
multiple pods and not just one pod.
So where for very large
networks, you cannot have the
entire model load in one pod.
In that case, you need to have the model
except distributed across multiple pods.
And the learning happens in a distributed
way across all these all these pods from
parts of the, from one part of the network
to another part of the neural network.
This is an example of so gpu, she
link Kate themselves, don't buy
natively, do the GPU shell link.
Nvidia has device plugins, so
you need to install them as part
of as part of the pod setup.
And you can say, okay, how many pods,
how many gps do you want to in one pod?
Normally four is the number, but you
can also go up to eight depending
on the resources that you have.
And the distributed training frameworks
where the training is actually happening.
There are some of the things that
all they mentioned this is there.
DDP is there for data parallelism.
There's deep speed,
which is from Microsoft.
There's Ray Train,
which is from any scale.
And Q Flow also provides toppy jobs
and, TF job operators where you can
use them for distributed training.
The most important thing is also when
you're doing multi GPO training is
the, is the communication for a fast
communication you need to use Nvidia the
NCCL package to make sure the network
is fully optimized for skill training.
So production, deployment strategies like
we need to monitor all these various GPU
usage because some of the GPUs the, if
the data is not properly distributed,
some of the GPUs can really underperform.
And so you need to have like
very close monitoring tools.
They can, you can inter
integrate with any.
Platforms like Datadog and things
like that to understand the GPU uses.
And this meet some trial and error
on understanding what is the data,
right distribution and shorting of
the data that needs to be done so
that now all the GPUs are maximally
utilized and there's no there's no
like imbalance or high imbalance in
terms of, utilization of the GPUs when
you're doing a distributor training.
There are things like, safety mechanisms.
So circuit breaker patterns
for unstable policies.
If there are pots that goes down,
you need to have failover and,
high reliable like robust failover
mechanisms so that if a port goes down.
It does not break the entire training.
It can recover from the specific
checkpoint to it failed, and
it can take it up from there.
And then the entire training across
the cluster can still continue.
So it needs very optimal it's a
monitoring in terms of all the
utilization across G-P-U-C-P-U
your network across the cluster.
So that you have a good understanding
about ization across when the training
is happening, and you can optimize based
on bottlenecks that you did that you see
the bottlenecks can be of various types.
It can be either network, it can be the
data or sometimes it can be like the model
itself is the, it is learning slowly.
So you have to make sure the the
learning parameters are set up
in optimal way and you have to.
Test and tune that multiple times
to, to get to optimal learning
learning for the entire model.
So the loss can be the loss and the, the
loss function that you're applying or the
policies that you're applying are really
like improving the learn, improving the
learning performance of the entire model.
So there are a lot of things like
learning rate parameters, and all those
things that also needs to be tuned
depending on the type of data and the
type of way cluster that you have.
So case studies for rf there
is most common use cases
are large language models.
Which are commonly being
trained using label data.
There's SFT, which is, I talked about
supervised, fine tuning, but also there
is, there now new techniques coming
up, which are like reinforcement based.
Fine tuning.
And that actually can really speed
up the training because it's very
difficult to get labeled data from
experts like, doctors, physicians, or
olympiads or mathematic mathematical
olympiads or cist olympiads.
To get labeled data takes a long time.
If the system can, if you can define
reward functions and if you can
define property or function, the
system, the network can itself come
up with new kinds of la labeled data
that can be fed back to the model.
So in that case, you don't need
a very large set of labeled data.
You can have an initial seed and that
model can learn from that initial seed.
And they can they can generate new
kinds of data sets itself as part of
a training and that can improve our,
improve the speed of your training
and you don't have to wait for long
cycle of getting human feedback data.
So large linguist models is the most
common use case is also use cases
for autonomous vehicles and robotic
applications where these data is being
collected for robotics applications.
A lot of challenges in
collecting data of images.
But as you collect multiple various
kinds of data sets the model becomes
more robust to new use cases.
The challenges I'll talk about is
the human feedback, scalability
human feedback is the golden dataset.
So if you can get that data quickly
on and in a reliable way, in a very
high, that's most high equity data.
But that's the challenge.
I think the next two, three years will
be needed to make sure the human data is
collected across very special tasks that
the model can learn and specialize on.
So that, the quality of the
model can increase over time.
Communication overhead is, how do you
make sure the policy parameters or
the the weight parameters are shared
across the network in a reliable way.
In a in a quick, in a fast way,
so the coordination becomes safe.
It needs a very high network bandwidth
to make sure the coordinate coordination
of this as the model is training, the
coordination of all this state stateful
data needs to happen in a very quick
way as that can become the bottleneck
of for your entire cluster and can
increase the cost of your computing.
Then there are other challenges
like temporal dynamics.
How do you catch how do you make sure your
temporal dynamics in terms of the changing
preferences are caught in the network?
So that de that depends on the
policy that we're trying to build.
And also the loss functions.
It depends on the network
architecture as well.
Then there are consistency grantees
and bias and representation, which
talks about like how do we make
sure this the model is trained?
When it is trained, it gives
consistent results and does not,
give very highly like the certainty
of the results should be within some
bands so that each time you train.
It should improve.
'cause if you have inconsistency,
then you cannot trust the
model every time you train.
So you have to make sure there's
consistency and kind of the data
availability, the know the time,
compute time that is needed to run.
And consistently in terms of the
model performance itself when you're
tr training it multiple times, you
should give the same results close to.
It might not be exactly same because
it's an un deterministic system,
but it should be close enough.
The emerging trends there is also
a new way of doing RHLF, which is
federated based RHLF, federated based
systems, where that means the learning
can happen on the edge itself instead
of on a cluster in a Kubernetes pod.
You can also do learning directly.
On the H devices it can be, there
can be millions of H devices
where there can be the data gets
collected and the training happens.
Some of the training can happen
directly on the, on, on the
devices for privacy preservation.
And then the devices then sync.
They are learning the weights
to the, to a central server.
Accumulates all the learning parameters,
and then it merges it and then it can
send it back to devices so that so that
you don't have to need to have a like
very large training every time there.
Some of these continuous learning can
happen on the devices, on the edge itself.
So that's a feder learning approach.
There's a lot of research going
on, on, on that area itself.
Then there's multimodal which
is like image, audio your text
video and all those other things.
There's automated feedback
based learning where you can
collect the data automatically.
And there is a lot of promise.
A lot of companies are seeing where
the feedbacks are collected within the
product itself and either good or bad.
And that can be used and those labels
that are collected from the product itself
are then used either as a part of the.
Training process while you're doing
fine tuning with with your instruction
instruction based fine tuning with
RHLF, or some people use that as
part of the rag application itself.
Where those feedbacks are are
used as part of the prompt.
And then the, when they call the the lms
those feedbacks are given as references
for chain of thought reasoning.
So the path forward there is
still a lot of work to do.
I think the most biggest the
way to do know, do distributor.
There are a lot of frameworks out there,
but most of challenging part I think
is right now the data collection part
from researchers, engineers like coders
or doctors as physicians or teachers.
Or any professional, any domain.
So we need lots of data, I think high
quality data that needs to be collected
so that the model can continuously
can be trained with reinforcement
learning with human feedback.
And this feedback data are
specialized data gets collected
so that, getting that at scale.
Across all the people in the world
let's say 1 billion people that
can really improve the new versions
of models that are coming out now.
That might not be always possible to get.
So that's why I think the reinforcement
based fine tuning might be might be
one of the new ways where where with
custom reward functions can be the new
way, where the model itself generates
new kinds of data and hypothesis
that can be used for training.
But there's, that's a lot of research
going on this area as well right now.
So that's it.
Thank you so much for listening to me.
I would love to get
any questions and yeah.
And answer them as needed
based on my experience so far.
Thank you