Joining my session at
conference JavaScript
over.
Modernized large scale healthcare
data engineering platforms from CMS
2000 claims submissions to air driven
violation pipelines that process
millions of transactions data.
My goal today is to share how modern
JavaScript frameworks traditionally
used in web apps can be repurposed.
AI Ready Modular E violation systems.
So these talk sites, the interaction
of healthcare data compliance, EL
engineering and software architecture.
So finally, you'll see how we lightweight
JavaScript core can scale to enterprise
with the performance, agility and
transparency our industry demands.
So let's go and deep
dive into our project.
What is the healthcare claims and what is
the current state and what is the impact?
So let go to the current state.
So healthcare organization handles
millions of claims each month.
So each one must satisfy hundreds
of business and compliance rules
under the ANSI X 2 8 37 standard.
So the ANSI X two standard is a separate
format, which we develop the files to CMS.
It has a different structure and
large elements and that need to
be satisfied, then only the file
is going be processed by the cms.
So the challenge is not only the.
Claim formats differ between
institutional, professional, and dental
types, and every payer add its own edits.
So in many environments, validation
is still manual or semi-manual
relying on rules, spreadsheets, or
legacy engines written years ago.
So when new regulations that
are updating the systems can.
Take weeks, sometimes months.
So the results, high rejection rates,
delayed payments and mounting costs.
So staff spend hours correcting
data instead of focus on
patient care or analytics.
So this stage, the stage for
a new approach on that agile
rule drive and technology.
And now what will be the impact?
So a reactor claim does not just
impact accounting, it disrupts
the entire revenue cycle.
For example if you're sending a file
to CMS with 5,000 claims and one fail,
one claim just file because of the
structure or some missing elements.
File will be failed.
So what happens is when we get the we
get a nine, nine written file in which
we need to check and see what is the
failed component, and then we need to
figure out what, whether the strict
structure issue or it's a data issue.
Or, and then we need to send a clip.
So sometimes this may take one, one
day, two day, or weeks or months to
figure out, because if it's a data
issue, we need to figure out from where
the data is coming, need to update
the data from the source, and then
it should flow through the system.
So there's a reason what happens.
The study says studies shows that.
15 to 20% of the claims are denied
of first submission, and roughly one
third of those are never recovered.
That's billions of dollars
lost annually across the US
healthcare system, so each denial.
When claim is sent, which a denial
triggers a chain of manual tasks we need
to review, correct them and resubmit,
and often take 30 to 45 days to resolve.
It may take more also,
so not only certain time.
So meanwhile, provider cashflow
servers and client suffers while
the amount is not going from one
end, one floor to the other floor.
So by building smarter valuation
layers that detect errors before
claims reach the payer organizations.
Can reduce Nels by up to 70%.
So violation is not about compliance,
it's about financial stability
and operational efficiency.
So why is the JavaScript a centric
approach for an approach for
violation so modern than JavaScript?
Frameworks offer unprecedented flexibility
for building healthcare ation system.
Unlike monolithic solutions, a
modular just architecture enables.
Rapid operation, easy maintenance,
and seamless integration
with existing infrastructure.
This approach leverages
declarative business rule engines
that separate violation logic
from implementation details.
Developers can define rules in human
readable formats while a framework
handles execution, error handling,
and performance optimization.
So the metadata driven
designs means violations.
Rules live as configuration rather than
hard code logic, enabling business to
participate in rule management without
requiring deep technical knowledge.
So what are the core violation
capabilities that we are gonna use
in this AI driven 8 37 transmissions?
So the four things we are going
to do is eligibility verification,
provider credentialing.
State logic coding accuracy.
So let's deep dive.
What is eligibility verification?
What is provider running?
And the other two things.
So let's explore the core validation
capitals and make this frame for
powerful practical for healthcare users.
So we begin with eligibility
verification in many claim system
error start because patient coverage
is not verified in real time.
Here a JavaScript player
connects directly to payer APIs.
Confirming active coverage, benefit
limits and service eligibility before
a claim ever lose the provided system.
Think of it's an instant checkpoint
that reduces preventable den
denial right at the source.
So if anything is missing or anything
is wrong in the claim, so in the
initial ation itself, we don't
even send the claim to the CMS.
So that way we initially check
from our system and then we rectify
that, and then we deliver to the.
CMS.
That's how we save the time and money.
And next is provider credentialing.
So this step automatically validates
NPA numbers, licenses, tax, money
codes, and vector status using
data from NPS or CAQH directories.
So when a provider's license
expires or the out of network, the
framework flags it immediately.
So manual lookup, no surprise later.
So that's fair.
If any NP is missing or NP is wrong, or
NP addresses missing or NP is unknown,
issues may be present in our system or,
but when you're directly calling the APIs
from NPS or cqs, so that way they'll be
always active and there'll be always a
primary address and physician address and
also the secondary address for those NPIs.
There be, there will be a little,
very little chance of failing the
claim with a missing NP or missing
address or missing tax money codes.
That way we can figure out the issues
before sending it to the CMS itself.
So then we have data logic violation.
This is where hundreds of common
timeline errors are caught.
It checks the dimension, dates
come before discharges, that
the dates of birth is realistic.
And that services fall
within timely filing limits.
Suppose if an encounter happens in
something of 2020 December, but he's
not he's enrolled somewhere in 2025
due to the system entry or something.
So basically the claim will
not be accepted because of
some data entry or somewhere.
Some mismatch has been happening, so
we need to fix the date logics also.
So these small details often
make or break claim acceptance.
So the last comes the coding accuracy,
the engine coex, isolated 10, diagnosis,
C, pt, S, and HCPCS codes against
official code sets and modifier rules.
It even supports.
For example, making sure a C PT code
that requires A always includes and every
claim, whatever we are submitting, CMS
should have a C PT code, which is valid.
So these CCPT codes or ICT
codes every year, CMS changes.
A few reschedule your non-schedule.
Sometimes every year.
CMS also saves you.
I CD codes are retired, so we need to
make our system to be always updated.
So that's the reason we bring it to the
configurations and we order, we add as
in a violation check so that we don't
submit the invalid i CD codes here.
CP should be a valid C PT code.
Collectively, these
modules form a 360 sheet.
They don't detect the problems.
Explain so teams.
So now we'll go to the
architectural design.
So now let's step back and
look how all these capabilities
fit together technically.
So at the bottom sits the data ingestion
layer, the component read raw, a DA
thousand files, those long test streams,
full loss segments and loops, and converts
them into structured Jason objects.
Once that happens, every
downstream service can read the
data like standard key value.
Frazzling with Iio syntax.
So as we told in the beginning,
the ANSI 8 37 structure, so that
structure is very tough to read unless
who has a lot of experience in the
healthcare system or the claims level.
The system has lot of loops and structures
that no one could understand easily.
So converting into the J object.
That makes the user to read easily and
they can find out what data elements are
missing or some segments are missing.
So now next, go to the rule engine code.
This is a brain of the system.
It pulls the right set of the
rules based on the claim type,
payer and line of business, because
the rules are metadata driven.
You can add, remove, or prioritize
them without touching the code base.
That flexibility is crucial
when regulations change.
So what happens is every year, as we told.
The iicd code will be changing some
np iicd code changing sometimes
some code from risk adjustment
to non-risk adjustment code.
Some iicd code will be retiring.
So all these made as a configuration
that would be easy for the,
for our system to maintain.
So then we have an integration service.
So these are external connectors.
Reach out to third party APIs or
databases, for example, to verify
eligibility or NP details in real time.
All of them run synchronously,
so even under heavy loads.
And finally comes the response handler.
Once violation is complete this module,
format the results to j XML or flat file
and route them back to clearinghouse
data warehouse or B dashboard.
So what's this?
So once everything is done, all the
violations, vault IC code verification
is done, integration service.
Then what this is again, the
j changes the it's file to
the A 37 standard file format.
And then send the file to the
clearing author, and the clearing
author will send the file to CMS.
And same data we can use in your
dashboards and the warehouses.
So the anti designs follows a
microservice philosophy, so each component
scale fail or evolve independently.
That makes it future proof for
cloud deployments on AWS Lambda
Azure functions all Kubernetes.
So now let's go to.
How as we discussed before, there
are like three multiple claim types.
So out of them they're institutional,
professional, and dental.
So when you go to institutional hospital
and facility claims with complex
billing hierarchies, revenue codes,
and service line details requiring
sophisticated violation rules.
So what are the rules?
They're having?
Revenue code violation.
Board and discharge statistics.
So same way when you go to,
when you're coming to eight 30,
professional claim generation.
So physician outpatient services claims
with procedure codes is a mandated thing.
Procedure mod should be M and
place of service requirements.
Leading size violations shows
what requirements for institution,
what requirements for professional
and what requirements for dental.
So in the professional also,
place of services is mandatory
and modify combinations.
So because as our, as in the
COVID, we got telehealth.
So we have a, for a telehealth,
we need to specify, we have, we
are having spec specific modify.
Then only the CMS knows
this is a telehealth claim.
If it's not, if it's something like
blank or, no, the CMS knows, okay,
it's not a telehealth claim, it's
an, it's an electronic or assessment.
That's how they, we can figure out how
it's, and the rendering provider checks.
So whether the NPI is there or not,
and coming to Dental 8 30 70 dental
procedure claims with tooth numbering
surfaces and specialized code requirements
unique to dental practice management.
So it's tooth surface violation, CT
code accuracy, treatment plan logic.
So each claim type requires specialized
violation rule while sharing
common infrastructure components,
making modular essential for.
So now here comes the real
time and batch processing.
So once architecture set, the
next question is how do we
run it effectively at scale?
That's where our dual
processing approach comes in.
Let's go to the realtime API valuation.
So process claims as they're submitted
through restful APIs with sub-second
response times ideal file clearing hoses,
integration practice management systems,
and immediate feedback scenarios where
providers need instant violation results.
So the API layer supports.
Both synchronous and asynchronous
patterns, allowing system to
choose between immediate responses
or queued processing based on
complexity and volume requirements.
Now get into the batch processing
engine, how it works, so it handle
engine volume, claim files during off
pick covers with parallel processing.
Perfect for end of day submissions,
large provider groups and
scenarios where throughput patterns
more than immediate response.
So the batch engine optimizes resource
utilization, truly inline job shape
during automatic logic and complement.
So error reporting.
That groups issues for
efficient remediation.
So another, what want to say is there's
two more design properties, flexibility
realtime, for instance, feedback and
batch for large scale operation loads.
So together they make the
system both fast and reliable.
So critical qualities in a 24 by seven
healthcare environment where ways the
data processing is going to be done.
We can also do for the further
preparation of AI integration.
So once we have a metadata driven
foundation, we can seamlessly add AI
capabilities without rebuilding anything.
So the first step is
intelligent rule adaption.
We can train machine learning models
on historical claim outcomes to
identify patterns if a certain rule s.
Recommend turning it or merging
it with contextual conditions.
Over time, the frameworks
learns from experience.
So the second is directive analysis.
A models evaluate incoming claims
and estimate the likelihood of
payer acceptance before submissions.
So high risk claims can be
flagged for manual review.
Suppose if you're getting a
high risk ED code or claim, or
h ccc, we just make this flag.
To double check, and
then we send it to CMS.
So while low risk ones flow strike
through, so this reduces manual
intervention and accelerates
payments, supply cycles.
The beauty is that the, a conce use the
same metadata as the rule, so the results
remain reasonable and auditable a must
in regulator industries like healthcare.
So in a healthcare.
Any claim is submitted or any once
after you submitting the claim.
If return the ance and the ICN,
everything needs to be auditable because
it all depends on the federal and
state government ities and everything.
Each and everything need to be audited
so we can also use our
future ready extensions.
The validation framework can
integrate with blockchain networks
to create immutable trails
of claim violation decisions.
This transparency builds trust between
payers and providers while ensuring
compliance with regulatory requirements.
Smart contracts can automate certain
violation steps and trigger payment
workflows when claims meet predefined
criteria, reducing processing
time and administrative overhead.
So decentralized violation rules can be
shared across the healthcare ecosystem.
Creating INDUSTRYWIDE standards while
maintaining organizational autonomy.
So let's go through, as we wrap
up this session, let's pull
everything together and reflect
on the key ideas we have covered.
First, JavaScript has evolved
for beyond its front end rules.
In this framework, it becomes a powerful
engine for healthcare data, forced,
modular and complexity, customizable.
It's non-blocking, runtime,
and rich ecosystem.
Make it perfect for real time.
And more than JS frameworks provide
foundation for building a scalable
8 37 violation that adapts to
changing business requirements
without architectural rewrites.
Just based on the confis, we can do this.
And second is metadata driven design.
Separate rules from the courts.
Business users can, MAL, can validate
law can manage validate logic
through configuration, reducing
it dependency and accelerating
response to payer rule changes.
Third, API first architecture
is what ties it all together.
It lets this validation capabilities.
Plugs seamlessly into
clearinghouse practice management
systems and payer gateways.
So whether data moves in real
time or in it batches, the system
build consistent and predictable.
So fourth is the AI Ready Foundation
unlocks strategic transformation.
AI brings break to intelligence,
learning from past outcomes to flag
potential denies before they occur.
So while blockchain introduces verifiable
transparency, eliminating disputes,
and building trust between payers
and the providers, what it does is,
so if anything feels, it's like any.
It's a higher risk code or it seems
like it's a highly billable code.
So before sending it to CMS, we
just take a stop flag it, send
it to double review, and once it
is reviews done, we send the CMS.
That way, if it rejects, it
takes a lot of time to again.
Redo this so it's better before sending.
We do as a mechanism, we build a
mechanism where we can check before
sending the claim to the CMS.
So ulti ultimately this approach
transform this approach transforms
violations from a routine comprehensive
check pointers strategic capability that
drives financial performance, operational
efficiency, and patient satisfaction.
The bigger message here is
that technology choices matter.
When we design systems that are modular,
explainable, and intelligent, we future
proof not only our software, but also
the organizations that depend on it.
Thank you again so much for
being part of this session.
I encourage you to experiment to think
differently about where JavaScripts
fits you in a data engineering world
and to connect with, and you can connect
with me in LinkedIn for continue to
further discussions on the healthcare.
Thank you so much for
giving this opportunity.