Hello, everyone.
A warm welcome to CON42 JavaScript 2024.
Thank you for joining me
today for my presentation.
I'm honored to be speaking here.
My name is Prakash Oja, and the topic
of my presentation today is AI driven
code review and quality assurance
revolutionizing software development.
In the last few years, AI capabilities
have grown rapidly and they have, now been
applied to various fields from medicine
to self driving cars to even farming.
And it offers a promise to
revolutionize software development
and quality assurance in particular.
My presentation will cover the
following develop contents.
Introduction, the shift in software
development, the current state of
code review and quality assurance.
How is AI revolutionizing code review
and QA, the key benefits of AI driven
code review, its real world impacts,
what are the quantifiable improvements.
How is AI used in quality assurance
and how is it transforming testing?
we'll go through some case studies,
success stories with AI driven code.
Then we'll discuss challenges
and consideration in AI adoption.
And finally, I'll be
presenting concluding remarks.
Introduction, the shift
in software development.
The software industry is witnessing a
fundamental shift driven by advances in
AI and machine learning technologies.
Traditional development methods
involve manual code reviews and
QA processes, which are time
consuming and prone to errors.
AI is not just enhancing these
processes, it's transforming
them by automating code analysis.
predictive issues and providing
insights that are difficult
for human reviewers to catch.
This shift represents a move towards
more intelligent and data driven
software engineering practices.
The current state of code
review and quality assurance.
Manual code review relies heavily
on individual expertise, leading to
inconsistencies and varying qualities
because different individuals
may have different skill sets and
level of quality and expertise.
The bug detection rates are limited,
with studies showing that around
60 to 70 percent of defects are
found using the traditional methods.
Which means 30 to 40
percent are not found.
And the cost of fixing this defects
grows exponentially when the issues
are discovered later in the development
life cycle, and especially post release.
QA is a resource intensive process.
It requires significant manual effort
to maintain and update the test switch.
An example, a study by Cisco systems found
that traditional code reviews typically
uncover only about 60 percent of defects
leading to significant technical deaths.
How is AI revolutionizing
code review and QA?
AI tools can analyze fast amounts
of code with speed and accuracy
that far exceeds human capabilities.
Techniques like natural language
processing, NLP, allow AI to understand
code documentation and comments.
which enhances the review process.
Pattern recognition helps identify both
common coding issues like memory leaks
and more subtle security vulnerabilities.
Real time feedback that AI offers
enables developers to detect and fix
problems as they code, reducing the
chances of technical deaths piling up.
The key point here is that AI
doesn't just automate tasks.
It enhances them by applying
sophisticated analysis to detect
issues earlier and more effectively.
What are the key benefits
of AI driven code review?
AI driven code review
enhances code quality.
AI tools can identify potential bugs,
vulnerabilities, and code smells
leading to higher quality code.
Accelerated development life cycles
By automating code review and testing,
AI reduces the time needed for
this task, allowing for more rapid
iteration of development iterations.
Reduction in technical debt.
Early reduction of issues means
fewer problems down the road, saving
cost and time in the long run.
Predictive analytics.
AI can anticipate potential bottlenecks
and project completion times more
accurately, allowing for better
planning and resource allocation.
Personalized assistance.
AI driven development tools offer real
time solutions and auto completions.
Helping developers maintain
consistent coding standards.
Real world impact, what are
the quantifiable improvements?
First of all, bug detection rate.
Using AI increases detection rates of bugs
from 70 percent to 95%, which is a 35.
7 percent improvement.
Demonstrating more comprehensive
issue identification.
Development life cycle time.
AI was found to reduce development
cycle from 12 weeks to 8 weeks,
accelerating time to market by
33%.
Code review time.
AI cut code review from 8 hours to
2 hours per 1, 000 lines of code,
showing a 75 percent time saving.
Test generation time was decreased
from 24 hours to 6 hours.
which resulted in 75 percent
reduction in the time it took
to generate the test cases.
Prediction accuracy for
project bottlenecks.
It improved from 60 percent to
85 percent helping avoid delays.
Developer productivity increased
from 100 to 150 lines of code
per day, boosting output by 50%.
Test coverage.
The test coverage was raised
from 75 percent to 95%.
achieving a 26.
7 percent increase in
comprehensive testing.
The key takeaway here is that the
integration of AI significantly
enhances efficiency and quality
across software development metrics.
How is AI in QA transforming testing?
AI automates test generation.
It can automatically create test
cases based on code changes.
Ensuring thorough coverage
with minimal effort.
Like we don't have to keep on
going back and adding, code,
as the code base changes.
AI can do that for us.
Self healing test.
As the user interface changes, AI
power tools can update test scripts
to reflect these changes, which
reduces the need for manual update.
Intelligent test execution.
AI can prioritize test cases based
on the likelihood of bugs, optimizing
testing efforts and reducing time.
Predictive analytics in testing.
By analyzing historical test results, AI
can predict the areas that are most likely
to have defects, which allows QA teams
to focus on critical parts of the code.
Finally, the impact.
Organizations using AI for QA
have reported up to 50 percent
reduction in testing time and
a significant decrease in bugs.
reaching production.
Case study involving some tools.
Amazon CodeGuru.
This AI powered code review tool helped
Amazon reduce application downtime by
50 percent by detecting critical issues
that would have otherwise gone unnoticed.
Static code analysis in
continuous integration pipelines.
By integrating AI tools in CI
CD processes, companies have
seen a 60 percent increase
in defect detection rates.
leading to more stable deployments.
Deployment failures reduced by 60%.
Organizations using AI powered
analysis to monitor code changes
have reported significantly lower
failure rates in production releases.
Takeaway, AI is not just a theoretical
solution, it is delivering concrete
measurable results in the real world.
What are the challenges and
considerations in AI adoption?
The initial challenges are initial
setup cost, implementing AI tools,
required investment, upfront investment
in new technology and testing,
and training, which is expensive.
Learning curve, development teams
will need to, they will need time
to ramp up and learn new ways
of, testing and adapting to new
workflow and AI powered tools.
Data quality requirement.
The effectiveness of AI tool depends
on the quality of AI data available.
initially we will need a good quality
and quantity of data for training.
What are the solutions to overcome
these challenges in early adoption?
Start small.
Start by with small automated simple
tasks like coding, code linting,
or generating small test cases.
Continuous learning.
Choose AI tools that improve as more.
Data becomes available, ensuring
better accuracy over time.
Hybrid approach.
Combine AI automation with human
oversight to achieve better results.
The best of both worlds in code
review and quality assurance.
Conclusion, while there are
challenges, the benefit of AI in
software development outweigh the
challenges and, make, overcoming
these challenges worthwhile pursuit.
Conclusion, the future
of AI driven development.
The key takeaways, AI is revolutionizing
software development by enhancing
quality, accelerating cycles, and
enabling more productive insights.
Thanks.
Development teams can focus on creative
problem solving and innovation as AI
handles routine and complex tasks.
Early adopters of AI driven methodologies
gain a significant competitive advantage
in the rapidly evolving tech landscape.
Call to action.
Embrace AI to revolutionize your
software development process
and stay ahead of competition.
Thank you for joining me
today for my presentation.