Hey everyone.
Thank you so much for being here today.
I'm Anad Ahmed, and for the next
30 minutes we are going to be
talking about something that
sounds complicated but actually
beautifully simple, and that is it.
Aria.
We're going to try as much as possible
to like, introduce what Aria concept
is just like a guide for developers,
share certain tips and, insights
as to how best to understand Aria.
And my goal is simple.
In 30 minutes, you'll
not only underst this.
Stand what area really does, but
also know when not to use it.
So let's get started.
Yes.
What we'll be covering today in my talk
we are gonna be covering
the invisible problem.
We are, we're gonna look at the
invisible problem that makes some
websites hard to use, and then
we'll go over area fundamentals.
What is it?
What it is, and how it works.
Then we'll unpack the three co
concepts of Aria, which is the
rows, properties, and state.
And then we'll also talk about
show we'll also show some coding.
Examples, a few of them.
And then we'll wrap up with the best
practices, common mistakes, testing
tools, and testing and tools, sorry.
And then action plan.
So by the end of this talk, you work
away not just with the knowledge,
but with the things that you can
actually apply in your next project.
Okay?
Yeah, so the invisible problem, right?
Accessibility issues are
really visible actually.
And that's one tricky part about it.
There are when we have
two pieces of code, right?
Which literally does the same thing.
They can look identical, but then they
be behave completely different for
someone using assistive technology.
For example, the screen reader, right?
An example of what we have
here, what you can see here is,
a very simple click me, right?
Which is designed to be a
button using the div element.
It has a class of fancy button and
unclick to do something right, but
it actually looks like a button.
Lets just put in that consent.
It was written to look like a button, but
then a screen reader would just see it
and just say announce it has clickable.
Click me, but there's no
context, no role, no meaning.
So why we see a nice button, someone using
a screen reader gets almost like no useful
information because it just says click me.
It has no idea.
A screen reader has no idea
if it's actually a button.
It doesn't know what happens when you
just, when you click it, it just knows
that there's something clickable there.
Alright?
And that's that's the gap between
what we see and assistive technology
understand, and that's the real
problem Har helps to bridge.
Okay going over to the next slide.
Like I said earlier, what is Screen
Reader one knows is like clickable
click me and it's going to translate
it as, oh, there's something you
can click here called Click me.
But I have no idea what it actually does.
Or if it's even a button, like that's
like the translation it's gonna have so
why does it really matter to actually
like, have a proper understanding of area?
In actual, in general context
accessibility itself is really about
helping users gain proper understanding
of how to like, use the elements we've,
created on our website, for example.
And it's just really about clarity, right?
Regardless of how a user eased.
Interfacing on interacting
with our website content.
And it's not just about trying to click
check out a compliance checkbox or
something, or trying to avoid a lawsuit.
No, it's not just about that.
It's about making sure that every.
User, regardless of how
they access our websites can
understand and use what we build.
So when we build accessibly, we're not
just doing, we're not doing extra work.
It's not an extra work.
It's a us doing our job properly.
Okay?
And, because a product that's confusing
or impossible to navigate is not complete.
People would not be able to use it, right?
So that's why it's really important
for us to understand certain
practices in accessibility.
We should not see it as an extra
work all or is it nice to have or
I would just come, I would just
add that feature to my website.
No, it should not be seen as that.
Okay.
So that's the essence of the stock.
Like just to introduce certain
concepts that can help us bridge gaps.
So now what I'll be talking about
next is this H TM L as you can
see from my slide is I wrote it,
like at ML speak two languages.
So that's like a kind of an analogy I
want to go with in trying to explain
the gap between a visual language, the
visual content user sees and say for
example, a semantic structure or semantic.
Content that will help assistive
technology properly interpret contents
to users who are using assistive
technology to interact with your site.
Like I said, the visual language is, the
visual language is, let me put it this
way, it's what sighted users see, right?
There, there could be like colors,
the brand colors you have on your
site, the layouts, the animation,
the beautiful animation over effects
and things like that have been
added and the way things behave
naturally in terms of how you could.
Du those content on your website.
And then the second language I want
to go with is semantic language
which is what most accessibility
advocates always preach about.
It should not just be about, how
pretty your website is, but how
well structured your website is.
So the second language are
we talking about is like the
semantic language and it's what
assistive technologies interpret?
Say for example this is a
button assistive technology.
When it interfaces with a button,
it's going to interpret it as a
button, a well structured button
when it interfaces with a proper.
Heading level, say for instance a
heading, this is a heading level one.
It's gonna announce it as this is a
heading level one, this is a navigation.
Things like that.
So that's like the second
language, HTMO understand.
Screen reader uses most often.
Experiences, the semantic language.
That's really what helps them
in interacting and navigating
properly with our website.
And this actually, this, the crucial part
is these two languages, I would say are.
They need to say the same thing.
They should not speak, they
should not be different.
They need to say the same thing
so that regardless people would
be able to understand the content.
So when they don't say the same thing,
but they look, when something looks
like a button, say for example but
doesn't say it's a button semantically
for assistive technology that's when
we can have an accessibility problem.
Exists to make sure that those two
languages always say the same thing.
It's gives extra context to elements
when playing HTML is not enough.
It's how we had more, let me put it
this way, semantic meaning when HML
alone is not enough, and that's what
area is not some, complicated framework.
We need to like hard to make accessibility
to help us, do some accessibility fixes.
No, it's just like a. A, a way
to just bridge the gap between,
that's why I use the analogy of two
languages, the visual and the semantic.
So where HMO is not sufficient area.
Can come in and then, had more
meaning to ensure that the ish, the
amount starts missed, makes sense
for assistive technology users.
So then let's like just I'm saying aria.
Aria actually stands for, accessible
rich internet application.
Alright.
Aria is is a set of attributes
that tell assistive technology.
That what something is what it
does and what state it's in.
That's where the three core concepts that.
I mentioned in our agenda earlier comes
in so we'll be touching base, we'll be
touching on that later on in this talk.
Just think of, I want you to
think of area as translation notes
for screen readers that when you
like how do I want to put it?
They're just.
They're just notes that don't change
how your code should look like, but
they they're just like additional
information, like I said earlier, for
assistive technology to really understand.
So when I say role, what is that
role Is like defining what an element
is, like having more definitions,
what an element is, right.
It's announces the names and
descriptions to things like A label
by things we'll be covering later on.
And it also by communicates the
status and say, for instance, is
the accordion expanded or is it,
or if is the button selected?
Things like that.
It's just like hiding more more.
Notes for to help assistive technology
to understand better what an element is.
Like I said, think of Aria like a
translation notes, aria attributes
are, they just had more context
to, what you have as your elements.
So without translation
notes, that's the first code.
From what you're seeing on the screen.
The first code is, it's
designed to be a menu, right?
And it has an unclick event.
Now that is an element, a deep
element without without aria, sorry.
And the second one is
with translational notes.
That's harrier.
In this case, we're talking we're
trying to like, give a proper
understanding of Aria by saying,
okay, aria, similar to a translation.
So when you see that, just know
that's what I'm trying to explain.
So the second line, the second div
elements, which you see there, you can see
that more things are being added there.
So the purpose of those things
are to define, a menu would
be like a button, right?
So the.
The essence of hiding area to this,
and this many element is to properly
help assistive technology to understand
that, oh, when it encounters this
menu, it should behave as a button.
That's the role we are defining to be.
And then the we're giving it a
label of, okay, open navigation,
that's, what is it called?
Like an open navigation menu.
And so that's this is to help
more, to add more context.
So we are going into, like diving
into the three core concepts
that we can see at first here.
So the first concept is the role.
The role like defines what the
element is, like I said earlier.
So for example, like we showed in the
earlier code, it defines the code below
as a button, even though it's a D, right?
We added the button into the code for
it to be able to be like a button.
So the next core concept is properties.
Properties is like a set of
characteristics that we've added for,
elements to provide more details,
like to describe it, say for instance
you're trying to describe your.
Your anti blue light glasses,
you're going to have it described
to someone, oh, it has a blue frame.
It has a blue, lens
when it's being set up.
That kind of description, that more
details you had to your elements.
That's where the property
concepts come in.
So for example, in this
code, the button is given.
A property of area label and
we are telling it that, oh,
this is a closed dialogue.
All right?
And that's like the property we are giving
it just to had more characteristics to
help describe what that element is doing.
Okay.
The next one is the states.
All right.
The states kind of de defines what is
currently happening with that element.
So for example, it took, it could tell
if a button is currently being selected
or, that's, if the button is active
or if, if it's press, kind of thing.
So that's where we add the states and then
we can use that attribute there, which is
the area pressed to be true to, to tell
that okay, the current state is what true.
That's just like a very simple example of
how the three con concepts play together.
Okay.
I, I've been mentioning, the
example I've been given is okay, a
div created to act like a button.
The reason that was used mostly
is because that is like a common
mistake so many developers use.
They try to use D to build everything
when you can just actually go
ahead to use semantic HTMO.
So that's like the golden
rule here that I'm trying to
explain that no area is better.
Is better than bad area.
So the first thing first is to
always go first with the native HTML.
Always go ahead to before you
try to use div to play around
and customize setting elements.
Try to see if those elements
already exist in semantic HMR.
Okay.
Use buttons for buttons.
Use navigation nerves for navigations use.
Inputs for inputs.
Don't try to design a D to
look like an input field.
All right?
So that's like the first step to avoiding,
future, accessibility problems because
there's some instances where we might be
trying to fix an issue an accessibility
issue, but in the actual sense, we are
even creating more accessibility issues.
So the first golden rule is to use
native HMO first and reach, only reach
for Aria when there's no like semantic.
Elements available and don't, like I
said earlier, don't try to re employment,
build in behaviors like, like I said,
buttons, inputs and things like that.
I. When you actually really need
Aria, so use Aria components when HML
alone is not enough to describe it.
So for example, there's no
actual HML elements to say.
Carousels to, to create a carousel.
Unlike the way we have a button
that can be used to design a
button, a semantic HMO button.
That's the buttoning elements that can
be used to like, build out a button.
Not nothing like that exists for tabs
or carousels or, models or navigation
notifications and things like that.
So this is where we try to build out
some things with Ds and then style it
into, style it for it to look like a
model or what, it could be whatever
elements we are trying to build in mind.
Avoid area for standard controls or
certain case cases, always test first.
Those are also part of the things
that we need to consider when.
Actually deciding on when to use area.
So the first thing first is to use
area components when you don't have an
alternative means to design an alternative
semantic HML, to designing that element.
So that's like a very brief
introduction to how you can really
actually know when to use area.
A few code examples.
This is a, this is an
example of, without Aria.
So as we can see here, the div element
is created to display a notification
message saying message sent successfully.
But in the actual sense, no announcement
will be made if an an assistive
technology is trying to like, or.
If an assistive technology comes
in contact with this element
on a website there's no way.
For.
For a user without disability, they'll
be able to like, okay, see that.
Okay, that's the message, a
message successfully sent.
But a user using this assistive
technology, like a screen
reader would, like I said, would
definitely get no announcement.
So now looking at the second
version we've had it like three.
The three area attributes we
talked about earlier, the role, the
description, and the the states, right?
Here we had the role to
be a notification, right?
To give that, to.
Status sorry, that status
notification that this is a status.
So we're trying to tell we're trying to
de define the role of this notification
that we're building to be a status.
All right, so the next
one is the area life.
So the area life is
another attribute to that.
We used to announced sweat.
Was subtly telling that this
should be announced pro politely.
So that's like a characteristics
we are trying to like,
define for that notification.
And then the last one is just just
tell, okay, message send successfully.
So that's like the actual,
content of that notification.
And these two attributes that we've
added would completely like change the
experience of for an assistive technology.
Like it's going to give more content.
Now the message is gonna appear, this
screen reader automatically analysis
to be like a message sent successfully
compared to the first version that we
have on the left side of the screen.
For, users, any for users, say for
example, a user without a visual
impairment can read the first one to
be like message sent successfully, but
then it's not helpful in any way if
a user using the assistive technology
cannot does not get any feedback.
No response.
No, sorry.
No announcement.
So this is why, this is what we are
trying to explain earlier on that those
simple changes can really make a huge
difference in how our users, our diver,
diverse range of users get to experience,
our web content and how they're built.
So one line of code can,
really make your heart work for
everyone, so for that's for the.
Notification and then
we have for our models.
That's another example that I
have today to like use to further
explain this introduction to area.
And there's always one
problem with models.
The problem is that when a model open,
a screen reader user would not like.
Often realize that, okay, that model
has been opened or probably what
the model is for or how to close it.
All right?
And visually.
When we talk about the
visual language, it's there.
Okay.
It's opened, but then on, for, on the
screen reader side, it'll not see it.
There's a, there's an X to close it,
but then the screen reader will not also
see it if it's not properly announced
correctly or the rules are not giving.
They're not like added or not even, or.
Or they're not added, or they're
added and not added correctly.
So that's another case, right?
The solution here is to like,
add a couple of area attributes.
So the first one is here
we are given a model here.
Role of a dialogue.
So that's like the role we are defining so
that whenever a screen reader encounters
that element, you don't understand
that, oh, this is a mod dialogue.
Okay.
And then the next one is the area
labeled by, which is, which falls
under the properties concept.
So this is the, like the characteristics
we're trying to define for it, and we're
saying that, oh, the aerial labeled by
points to the heading the selves as the.
Dialogue title.
So we are going to be pointing
like that property to the heading.
Alright, so then the, another
description we're giving it is the
ariel described by, so those are like.
Pretty much setting quick references.
At the end of this talk, I'm going
to show some quick references that
you can always like, follow through
to help you further understand that,
okay, yes, this is what this is.
And there also a couple of more resources
that I'm gonna be sharing so that I can
have more, context to aerial elements.
For the area described by
Yeah, we are saying that.
Okay.
This p elements would serve as the
description for our, for our model,
so that when it's announced, the
screen reader knows, okay, this
is what this model is meant for.
And, with the title the screen
reader, user can, get a preview
idea or, a short idea of, okay.
What this model is about.
And that will be like,
okay, confirm the needs.
So when it announces it as confirm,
delete model the screen reader user
knows and it's prepared that, okay,
this is for me to delete something.
Alright.
And then it gives that more
context to description of the.
Dialogue to be, okay, are you
sure you want to delete this item?
So that's really helpful.
Just those two descriptions is adding
more context to help, improve the
experience of a screen reader user.
And then a couple of other elements
there is just cancel and then delete.
So if the user is still gonna go
ahead to delete, they know like how
to move their, cause how to move
their keyboard around to help them
navigate to the delete section if they
still want to delete or just go back.
So just those few things helps,
compared to not even hiding
any of those things at all.
And just having your div and then.
H two and then a P tag and
then the two buttons and style
beautifully in the modal box.
It's cute visually, but then functionally
it does not help, screen reader users.
Yeah.
That's like the purpose.
And then we are, trying to provide more
context for screen reader as like I
said, so the common mistake, I think I
mentioned one common mistake earlier,
but so many developers aside from okay.
I think I mentioned the common mistake
the other time I remember now the common
mistake I mentioned was using Ds to
create buttons and we've already talked
about how not to do that, so we should
always use like semantic, some of us.
So that's great.
Then another common mistakes
is adding Harry to everything.
Every single element.
And that's not great because when you
add Aria or use Aria when you're not
supposed to, like I said earlier, that's
like adding more accessibility problems,
like creating more accessibility problems
rather than fixing those problems.
Another one is adding
I interactive elements.
Like I sometimes when I like click
on the, I inspect of certain website,
I see area eating true and I'm like,
no, that's like a common, that's
one mistake that people also make.
Developers not.
I lo like forgetting keyboard support.
Aria usually doesn't have
keyboard functionality.
So we still need things like, our on click
events and keyboard atlas and things like
that to help, with keyboard functionality.
So we should not think Aria
is going to like, have those
things for us automatically.
They're not, they don't work that way.
We already explain like.
Why, what area does just
adding more context, right?
So we should have that notes like
adding more context to help screen
reader understand certain elements that
are not built with semantic H demo.
So that's like the best
way to break it down.
Also, I think I mentioned this
conflicting rules or invalid states.
Maybe for a button we are.
Assigning is a role of a dialogue, right?
That's like creating an
accessibility problem.
Or, giving a dialogue role of a bot team.
There are other different rules that
we can always like reference on the MDN
documentation or altering practices yeah.
By Y area.
Yeah.
Like I said, those common mistakes,
yes, they're, they have solutions.
So the fix will be to always use the
semantic H number and then we test with
our keyboards to ensure that, users
can also can, navigate with a keyboard
without the mouse and then test with
screen without, to ensure that okay,
these things are announcing correctly.
So there are tools and tests
tools and technologies that we
can use to do those testing.
Like I put here, we should
do the keyboard test first.
Navigate without your mouse
and ensure that the focus is
visible and logical, right?
Yeah, that's just unplugging your mouse
and try to navigate with your keyboard.
Can you navigate everything?
Can you activate it?
Yeah.
And then are they focus around
your elements, like your buttons?
Does they have enough focus that that will
help, assistive technology users as well?
Also there are screen readers
you can always download NVDA, you
can download on Windows, but Mark
itself comes with a voiceover, so
you don't need to download those.
Just listen, just use this screen reader
tools to help you listen to how your
page is being announced or described.
And then there are also automated
tools that you can use to check
where check for errors on your site.
Maybe just to check and spot if you
can find area errors or no area errors.
And it could be any other errors, right?
So you shouldn't wear,
you're testing your site.
Don't just test for the area, okay?
Just go through everything and
ensure that everything works.
Okay.
So yeah, baby steps.
Slow.
Like I used to hear, slow progress
is better than no progress at all.
So it's not like a one day thing
to get it all right all at once.
It's tiny changes that could yield
remarkable results that could, provide
impactful changes to help, improve
the experiences of our users, right?
So automated tools like, ask step tools,
wave a Lighthouse could help spot those
issues and then you can look at how to
fix them and, try to retest again manually
and see if everything works correctly.
I was talking about quick references.
There are a couple of roles that.
These are like common area attributes
that you mostly use all the time
buttons navigations, dialogue, alert
status, remember, don't go first
using a div to create a button.
Okay?
Always go for the semantic
way of creating a button.
Okay?
That's like a quick reference for roles,
a quick reference for labels, for,
properties, adding properties like, we
had the A built by in one of our examples.
And then we use our IDs to target them.
I think I, we have that
in one of our examples.
The area described by, like I said,
we had in our example, a mod example
where we had a Peter to provide
more context, more description.
So we use the area described
by and target targeted.
It's using the ID and added
that inside of our, that's that
a quick reference for state.
Okay.
Is it an expanded one?
Is it open?
Do you get it?
Is it closed?
Using are expanded setting to
true or false or are selected
certainly to true or false.
These are, ways, these are quick
references, like the Area Aid
true or false that we mentioned
for interactive elements.
That is so that's why I said that it's
a common mistake because there's so many
elements that developers can, would just
go ahead to put Area Aid to be true.
Just so that it's to fix to fix maybe
an accessibility issue they're trying
to encounter something like that.
That, that area, ed didn't mostly say,
oh, should query reader ignore it.
It should always be used
correctly and right.
This is the, another one quick
reference for live regions.
That's all still on the properties.
The area live should be announced.
It's politely or ative, like
announce immediately or announce
when I do just to provide more
characteristics to that element.
We're trying to create where
plain HTMO is not sufficient.
Alright so when we are trying to do
these steps, this, baby steps, we're
learning, we're growing, we are, trying
to, as much as possible ensure that.
Our websites are content accessible.
We also, it's also very important
to build an accessible workflow.
We should not always make accessibility
to be something that should be considered
when our site has launched and our users
are complaining that, oh, they cannot
access certain things in our website.
No, it should always built, it should
always be built from the very beginning.
Start semantic, then hands with Aria.
When you want to build elements
that plain HCMO does not suffice.
Then also adding, accessibility
checkers to to accessibility checks,
sorry, to our pool request should
also automate certain things.
And why you automate is also important
to also test mal d. Just like going
through checking manually to see
if everything announces correctly.
And it's also important to like,
include accessibility testing into
things like our design system.
So when all of this is part
of our process, it stops
looking like an extra work.
Oh, it's an extra work.
I can't do that, kind of thing.
So yeah, so that's why
it's really important.
So another thing is another action
plan, I would say aside from building.
Accessibility into our workflow
is that we should keep learning.
We should read why area practices,
authoring practices about area,
to learn more and build more.
Nobody knows it all.
Quick insights, knowledge
about certain things is really
helpful than not knowing at all.
So it's very important as professionals,
as developers, we should learn about this.
Best practices.
We should also audit and we
should test our keyboard flow.
We should run, ask step tools.
We should, fix stuff with, I impact
issues like, issues that you know,
that are really impacting our users.
We should start with those.
We should also like sustain, keep.
Accessibility into our
PR and review processes.
It's just like those small steps
that will really make a huge impact.
So my key takeaway, the key takeaways
here is what I want you to really
remember is that area should not be
like, or, checklist or, things like that.
It's about respect.
It's about respecting that people
use the web in different ways
and it's about ensuring that.
What you build is usable by everyone.
Okay.
And it's not just the web has
we personally experienced.
It's like it's about building
for the real diverse users.
Alright?
Every area attribute you
write is an act of inclusion.
Those done the right way.
Okay?
So it has to be done the right
way for you to write something
that's an act of inclusion.
That's the art of accessibility, making
sure that every user's feel what included.
Yeah that's it.
And then we have a couple of resources,
like I said, that would be added
to the end of this co this talk.
The Y area altering best practices.
You can always visit that to see a
list of more area properties road.
Yeah, states that you can, learn to use.
We also have the MDN area documentation
is also a very detailed documentation
that explains, more area concepts.
We also have the web aim article
on area, like I think web aim
had a very detailed at school and
area, which I've included here.
And then I also linked to a couple of
resources sorry, a couple of tools that
was mentioned earlier, which is like
the Ask Dev two, the NVDA and the Wave.
Okay.
That's it for me.
If you have any questions,
just send it to me.
I'll be more than willing to
answer to the best way I can.
Thank you so much for listening.