Hello everybody.
This is Sund.
I am working as technical
architect in UBS.
Prior to that, I worked with
Cognizant and I worked with different
clients like Amex X, Broadridge,
like financial organizations and
especially in wealth management.
System.
Okay, so today I'm going to give a
demo on Java script vulnerabilities.
Let's start,
let me share the screen.
So here is my screen.
So securing JavaScript, which means how.
We need to protect our
code from external attacks.
So it may be either front end related
or it may be either from backend related
or it may be either from any other tools
or libraries, any other components that.
Security challenges here.
Okay, so nowadays many people are
using frontend applications as well
as backend server side components.
The attack can come from any point in
the sense like from the front end or.
From backend front end, React,
not backend, like no js.
So there is a lot of opportunity
for the attackers to create a lot of
attacks and vulnerabilities across
our different frameworks across our.
Different APAs and across the
different components that we are using.
So the normal, traditional
security approach.
So they do not address
all the vulnerabilities.
Definitely we need a. Some sort of
patterns, some sort of mechanism to
address all these vulnerable system.
Let us see.
Okay, so we will cover java
script attack landscape.
So which means what are
different ways of threats?
And second vulnerability
management framework.
How we can mitigate those issues frontend.
And third one, frontend security patterns.
Definitely we can protect
our code by following some
patterns like design patterns.
No fourth one, no GS security.
So how we can manage our backend code?
With using some sort of specification.
And fifth one, automation and integration.
Also, automation and integration means
everything is like automated, so it's like
workflow and components are integrated.
So that is process and risk
based patch management.
If there are any issues immediately
identify that and apply some
patches, something like that.
Okay.
As I said, common Java
script attack vectors.
So if you consider Dom based excesses.
Cross site scripting.
So this is one of the major vulnerability
attack that our code base is facing.
What it means.
So it means.
For example in JavaScript, our
frontend code, if we are retrieving
some value from the URL, for example,
a name or designation or anything.
Okay.
And you are including that
as part of inner HTML.
You are making those values into
some document and you are trying
to execute the application.
So this is like not a bad habit of coding.
There is a lot of scope that
external attacks can happen.
So this is one of attack that can happen.
And second thing, prototype pollution.
So prototype pollution means for
example so you are creating a
Java script for example in the
sense window, dark location.
So in that case it is harm to read
those values and definitely, and there
may be attack from external site,
external pupil dependency, confus.
Dependency confusion is like, for example
in our application, lots of components
we are downloading for Maven website.
So lots of components we are downloading.
So attackers want to create a
confusion between the original
component and a harmful component.
So they want to.
Make use of similar name pom xms
components and try to now expose those
components into the public websites.
And in turn people can download that
and try to install and try to put
their components in the application.
So obviously that's a big attack.
And another one is server side injection.
Server side injection is nothing
but the core will execute at.
To interact with the database.
So definitely there is a lot of scope.
If the code is not written
properly, there's a lot of code.
They can manipulate SQL
queries and they can include.
The values, whatever they want.
And even non SQL also, they can
manipulate and they can attack the data.
They can get the data, they
can manipulate the data.
They can delete the data.
So there are lots of possibilities.
Like this.
The externals can attack.
Okay, so now what to do?
We can.
We can get a vulnerability
management framework.
We can use some sort of frameworks good
frameworks where we can it can handle all
these sort of things in appropriate way.
So it.
First it assessment, so it identifies
and quantifies the risk across our
JavaScript stack and prevention.
Im, so it it implements some security
patterns and some controllers, some
security related admin, admin roles.
Something like that.
Detection, so it continuously monitors.
And automated the scanning.
For example, if there is any code which
is vulnerable immediately, it gives alert.
So it continuously monitors and it
gives an alert if there is any issue.
And instant workflow and patch
management, which is in the sensor.
If there is any incident happened
immediately it applies related.
Batch.
Now, let's see.
Quantity to risk assessment for some sort
of depend system, evaluation criteria.
So vulnerability history.
It tracks the fast security
issues and resolution terms.
How many issues are reported what
are the resolution time within
what time it has been resolved.
So it gets the, all the history of that
vulnerabilities, maintenance activity.
So monitor, commit frequency.
Issue response and active maintenance.
So it frequently monitors
what is the code committed?
Who is the code committed and
when it is committed so what
are the impacts of that commit?
So whether it can be a. Removed or not.
So dependency chain chapter
SSS translate to dependencies
and their security posture.
Download metrics, evaluate community
adaption and security levels.
Another one is automate auditing tools
enable consistent data driven security
editions across the JavaScript projects.
Front end sec. Coming to the point of
front end security, client side defense.
So how these are all the points how
to mediate or how to manage those
vulner vulnerabilities, sir? So if you
consider accesses right, cross script.
Cross set scripting.
So these, for example, these
externals can attack by giving
some dummy values or some images.
Or some path to image in the
URLs, so when the code traced
to get that particular value.
The attacker included an
image which is n. Not secure.
And our code tries to get that
image, load, that image, or
it may be something like that.
Any link or something.
Which is obviously it is under attack.
So second one, secure API communication.
So we have to use proper
HTPS implement proper VO RS.
Policies and especially
validate all the data.
So what is that data input, validation,
simple input, validation, what it contains
what are the re required values or
what are the mandatory values that can
contain, you cannot simply pass through.
So definitely how to validate all the data
received from the external source input.
Third one, input sanitization.
Which means before you do document
or using any others so use some
validation libraries spec and use
some specific formats where the user
can give and, and we can validate
the data, especially the fourth one.
Authentication security.
Security token.
As you can use certificates.
You can use tokens.
Okay.
So using that, we can definitely
not secure our website item.
React modern frameworks.
And we need to consider a word
dangerous self inner HTML.
This is very high.
Very important point.
Okay when there is a necessary to use Dom.
Okay, we can use purify or similar any
other libraries which can San sanitize
data before we render to any other
webpages or to backend and validate.
Prototypes are type scripting
to enforce type safety and
prevent unexpected data flow.
Okay.
Carefully manage the data
flow between components.
And validate the data at Bond raise,
sir. Okay, so no GS back in security.
Secure coding practice.
There are lots of things here, so
input, validation, whatever the value
received from your request parameters
or URLs you need to validate and
especially parameters, queries.
They can in query parameter, they can
give some value ease admin through.
Or they can give some account
number, wrong account number.
They can put some account
number to deposit money or to
withdraw or something like that.
They can manipulate the SQL queries and
then trace to execute at server side.
So definitely we need to validate
all the input data that we received.
And proper exception handling especially
without exposing whatever it comes to.
Before exposing, we have to put proper
exception handling, mess message and
secure authentication authorization and
on rate limiting and request throttling.
So runtime production
environment variable, securely.
We can use different
environment variables.
So we have to use all
those in a secure way.
Okay.
And principle of list, er.
And if there is a need,
then only give the roles and
responsibilities roles in the sense.
Okay.
So secure dependency management and
regular security areas with NPM Ator.
So container security for
JavaScript application, minimal
base images use airplane or on
images to reduce attack surfaces
and eliminate unnecessary packages.
Non user run node js process
as non-privileged users within
containers to limit potential damage.
Integrate vulnerability
scanning into CACD pipelines.
To catch issues before deployment even.
CICD pipelines is a major workflow
management system, so definitely we
can automate all the code to avoid
any issues before the deployment and
never break the secret symptom images.
Use orchestration platform
secret management instead.
Okay, so automation
throughout the development.
Pre-committed in the sense before
we commit the code into Git
report or whatever it may be.
Scan for secrets, you have to make
sure that there are no credentials
or PA passports related issue
issues, vulnerability issues
before code goes to repository.
Okay.
And pull the request.
Automated dependency audits the security
and test execution for every submission.
And C-A-D-C-D pipelines integrated
into build and deployment process,
and then continuation monitoring,
runtime, application build log
analysis and deployment to production.
So risk patch, risk-based
patch management, mattresses.
These are many things here.
Okay, so critical zero day, immediate
patching within 24 hours active.
Two, exploration in the wild, which means
if there are any instance or anything
immediate, immediately we can apply patch
so that it can come to normal position.
How high severe.
Severity, so patch within seven days.
Non exploit, high severity score
effects production, medium risk should
within 30 days low prior, include a
run term maintenance, minimal impact
of the required local access, so
types of scripts, role in security.
Type safety prevents common
vulnerabilities, which means static typing
ca. Caches type country issues prevent
prototype pollution through sticker
objects handling and enforce interface
contact atel time enhanced code quality.
There are lots of sonar, for
example, sonar, sonar cube.
Okay.
Sonar cube, it gives all the correlated
issues before we commit the code.
So if it passes, then only we have
to put a condition in the pipeline
stop deployment or stop proceeding
to commit if it identifies any
issues, vulnerability issues.
Okay, not a silver bullet.
Light TypeScript does not replace
random validation, secure testing,
or secure coding practices.
It's one layer of the
defense in depth strategy.
Okay, so these are the
points that we cover.
Adopt a framework mindset.
Okay.
Secure is NAIA checkbox.
It's a systematic approach
spanning assessment, prevention,
detection, and response.
Automate everything possible.
Yes.
Avoid manual processor, for example.
Do not use any manual created passwords.
Automate it.
For example, if you consider cloud it.
Automatically creates the password.
No knows it.
It automatically creates,
it automatically works.
That's it.
Nobody knows the password.
Okay.
And especially nowadays even that
is go, that is also going away.
There's no password just based on
the user entitlements user roles.
We can go for the website browsing.
Prior that intelligently use risk-based
patch management to focus efforts where
they matter most without security.
Think full stack JavaScripts
security requests protecting
both front end and backend.
It's not know only front end,
it's not like only background
from end-to-end application.
And contrast the each thing.
Thank you very much.