My name is Gian Wild.
I'm from Accessibility O, and I'm here to
talk to you about accessible JavaScript.
It's easier than you think.
There are three types of
JavaScript functionality.
First, binding functionality to
existing interactive components such
as links, buttons, and text fields.
Two, non-interactive functionality
that presents information.
Three, creating custom components that
are both interactive and informative.
There are 10 accessibility principles
when it comes to JavaScript.
First, all functionality must take a
form that can be interpreted as text.
Second, all functionality must be
accessible to all input devices.
Third, information and structure
can be programmatically determined.
Fourth, a meaningful sequence and
logical focus order is maintained.
Fifth instructions Do not rely on sensory
characteristics or nonsensical characters.
Sixth timed activity can be controlled.
Seventh, provide mechanisms to help people
find and interact with content correctly.
Eights do not cause a change of
context or content unexpectedly.
Ninth, identify components
consistently and tense.
Identify and describe errors
and error suggestions in text.
Now this is quite a complex presentation.
There's a lot of information in
here, but don't fear all this
information is in what we call the
accessibility Oz JavaScript fact sheet.
And if you go to the Accessibility Oz
website, you'll find that there is a
section called fact sheets, and underneath
it there is a JavaScript fact sheet.
There's also a heat more on other
topics that you might be interested in.
And if you go to this JavaScript
fact sheet, you'll see there's
a section here on accessibility
principles and the impact on users.
So you know what happens when
your system is not accessible.
Manage a checklist, which is
basically a testing checklist, and
you can actually go through this and
determine, does all dynamic visual
information have a text equivalent?
Eg. A visual progress meter
also shows a percentage figure.
And if you're like I don't really
know how to do that, then if you
have a look at the developer.
Checklist.
You'll see that there's
some correct examples.
There's also some incorrect examples
in some cases, and if you go to that,
there's an appendix and there is actually
a live demo with all the code available
that you can copy and paste as required.
And this is what the live demo looks like.
So there's lots and lots
of information there.
Don't fear if I'm going a bit
fast or you're a bit worried that
there's just a little bit too much
information in this presentation.
The presentation slides
will also be available.
They are, if you go to the accessibility
Oz website and you go to about, and then
conferences, you'll find that here we've
got the Comp 42 JavaScript conference.
Once the.
Conference has finished.
It will end up sitting under this, heading
past conferences and events 2025, and I'll
add the PowerPoint presentation there.
So let's talk about the types of
different JavaScript functionality.
Type one, as we said, binding
functionality to existing
interactive components such as
links, buttons, and text fields.
So assistive technologies
can derive information from
their attributes and text.
For example, a dynamic
menu would be made using.
Organized with nested lists in which
the menu levels are denoted by the
hierarchy and by the use of structural
labels around each top level link.
Type two non-interactive functionality
that presents information.
So this must be implemented in such a way
that the information can be derived from
associated text as I just showed you.
A visual progress meter would
also show a percentage figure or
JavaScript might be used to identify
and highlight form validation errors.
And type three, creating custom components
that are both interactive and informative.
So these components must be implemented
using elements that are already
understood by assistive technologies
so that their content and interactions
can be programmatically determined.
For example, a calendar widget would
have a label to describe it and a button
to trigger it while the calendar itself
would be made of table markup, which
assistive technologies can understand
and interpret as structured text.
Principle one, text alternatives.
People with disabilities may rely
on assistive technologies such
as a screen reader, a braille
reader, or a speaking browser.
These technologies represent all
information as structured text.
If visual information has no
text equivalent, assistive
technologies will not be able to
relay that information to the user.
And also if interactive components
do not have a descriptive label.
People who use assistive technologies
or who have a cognitive disability
may not understand what it.
Now, if you got to this part of
the presentation and you've gone,
what are assistive technologies?
I don't really understand all this
accessibility stuff, then the best
thing to do before you watch the
rest of this webinar is to watch
the Accessibility Basics webinar.
It's on YouTube, www.youtube.com/watch.
Question mark v equals.
YS, capital T, capital D, capital A,
lowercase U, the number two, lowercase
Z, uppercase V, lowercase I, and
uppercase M. And if you like me and
you actually don't like watching
videos too much, you can also read the
Accessibility Basics article, which
is at TinyURL com slash a1 y basics.
Of course the worst example of
this principle is they capture in
case you don't know what a capture
is, this is what a capture is.
Basically some gobby book test that you
need to type in, and it's inherently
inaccessible for a lot of reasons.
Even if it has an audio version,
and yes, Google's recapture.
You know that little ticky
thing that it just determines
automatically if you're a bot or not.
That's also inaccessible because
the recapture thinks that people
who use technologies are bots,
so of course it doesn't work.
And then it says, Hey, pick the buses
out of these nine images, and people
are blind and they can't see the buses.
Anyway, that's a whole nother story.
If you wanna learn more, have a read
of the article I wrote recently.
Gold, the inaccessibility of capture.
The URL is tiny url.com/
2 0 2 5 dash capture.
This is a better thing to
use instead of a capture.
Basically something like
a human test question.
You can also have honeypots where you
have a field that has to be left empty
and you can have that in the field label.
You can hide it so people can't
see it, et cetera, et cetera.
There are a lot of things that you can do.
Multifactor authentication, as
I said, I could talk forever.
Just don't use capture.
If you only take one thing
from this presentation, it
should be don't use capture.
The other issue is
visually dynamic content.
Of course, we saw the visual
progress meter that the
accessibility of fact sheets have.
I just wanna show you an incorrect
example, and this is an incorrect example.
As you can see, it does display
the status, but it does so using.
Only a visual medium and color
contrast doesn't really work either.
This is a much better progress bar.
As you can see, you've got text.
Of course, it changes quickly,
but that's okay and that is a
more accessible progress meter.
Another thing to be aware
about is image buttons.
I know people don't use them a lot
anymore, but there's still a few.
Once again, your correct example.
Of course, I know they aren't used so much
anymore, but this is a correct example.
You can see the image button has the
text of search, incorrect example.
The image button has a text of sub.
Not very useful.
Complex content, functionality
that can't be made accessible.
Must have a long description that
provides the same information.
This is an example, once again
from the JavaScript fact sheet.
Very complex information, a
Google map, and it has directions.
Now, it's important when it comes to
creating alternatives for complex content.
It's not about providing all the
information that's in the image, it's
providing the relevant information.
So this is about.
Having directions from
Sydney Road to Smith Street.
So the long description says one head
South on Sydney Road State Route 55
toward Mary Street for 550 meters.
Turn left onto Brunswick Road State,
route 38, then proceed for 1.6 kilometers.
Turn right onto Nicholson Street,
then proceed for 1.5 kilometers.
So this is basically
something that you need to do.
It's not a JavaScript thing so much,
but if you have something complex,
can't make it accessible, provides
a lot of information, make sure
you have that long description.
So basically, the text alternative
requirements are image buttons
must have a valid alt attribute.
Any images conveying information
Submit button is an image.
Then it must have an alt attribute.
Captures shouldn't be used.
If they do, you need to have multiple
sensory modalities and complex systems.
Must have a long description if you're not
really sure about this whole interactive
maps, creating a long description.
We do have an interactive maps fact
sheet at www.accessibilityoz.com/fact
sheets slash interactive dash maps.
Two, all functionality must be
accessible to all input devices.
What are input devices?
The standard input devices are a mouse,
a keyboard, and a touch screen, whether
it's on a mobile device or on a laptop.
And then there are assistive technologies
that mimic input devices so that
people with disabilities, they cannot
use a particular input device because
of, say, a physical disability.
They use what is called an assistive
technology, which often mimics
one of the standard input devices.
So for example, the joystick mimics
a mouse, an onscreen keyboard mimics
the physical keyboard, external
keyboard on a mobile device, mimics
the keyboard thumb switch, mimics the
keyboard, head wand mimics a mouse.
Principle two is about
input device accessibility.
Assistive technologies are usually
controlled with a keyboard rather than
a mouse or a pointing device, and there
are many people who are simply unable
to use a mouse or a track pad or a
keyboard because of a motor impairment.
If interactive content.
Can't be operated with a keyboard.
It will be entirely inaccessible to people
who can't use a mouse or pointing device.
There are also people entirely reliant
on other input devices, so it's
essential that all the site functions
using only one type of input device.
So let's talk about the keyboard.
When you are using the keyboard, people
use tab to move between actionable items,
escape to close a feature, and arrow
keys as well, to move amongst things.
If you have a complex feature and
there's an unusual way to close
the feature, then you must document
what that feature is before people
actually get to that feature.
You should also be able to tab
from start to finish, not be
trapped in some kind of component.
That is one of the most serious
accessibility issues is the keyboard trap.
So all interactive content should
be accessible to the keyboard
using common keystrokes like tab
and enter and arrow keys, and you
need to be able to move through.
In the late two thousands, it was
very common that any video player
in Firefox was a keyboard trap.
Users would tab into the video player
to play it, or just because it was
on the screen and they couldn't exit
the video player, so they got to the
end of the video player and the tab
key just basically stopped working.
And so what they would have to
do is they'd have to close the
browser and reopen the page
and try and avoid that video.
That's a major accessibility issue
that you absolutely want to avoid.
To learn more about keyboard,
there is a keyboard fact sheet.
Have a look@wwwaccessibilityoz.com
slash fact sheets slash keyboard, and
there's also a video on keyboard focus.
It's at www do accessibility
oz.com/resources/videos/keyboard-focus.
So some examples.
First off, we talk about
keyboard focus indicator.
Do not use events to restrict keyboard
access or remove focus indication.
Therefore, don't use on
focus equals this blur.
And I'd like to show you
a correct example in the.
If we start at the top of the page,
you can see that the keyboard focus is
now on skip to the content, and then
it goes to language login site, map,
a SL videos on the right hand side.
The next thing to get focus is the logo.
The search bar.
The search button, and
then we have the menu.
So you can see it's very obvious
where your keyboard focus is.
It is very easy to move around the site.
So dynamic menus need to be fully
accessible to the keyboard using
tab and arrow keys, and I'll
just show you an example of that.
Now, here we have the Accessibility Oz
website, and once again you see where the
keyboard focus is and you can tab across
the main menu items in the navigation.
And if you actually wanna look at
sub items under the menu item, then
you just press the down arrow key
and you can move through the items.
Another example here, JSNA one.
So this is part of the
JavaScript fact sheet.
Basically, you can use the tab
keys or arrow keys to move around.
I'm using tab at the moment, but I can
also use the down arrow if I want to.
Keyboard requirements, there must be
no keyboard traps when creating a motor
window dialogue box focus, et cetera.
The keyboard focus must be
trapped within that dialogue box.
You must of course, also have a
way to close that dialogue box
once the user has finished with it.
Dynamic menus must be
fully keyboard accessible.
Anything that has mouse only
functionality needs to have a keyboard
equivalent and make sure everything
has a keyboard focus indicator.
So that's about keyboards.
There are a whole different bunch of
other requirements around touch screens.
When you think about a mobile device,
you do a lot of things much differently
than you would do if you were using
a mouse, for example, two Pink zooms,
swiping up and down, et cetera, et cetera.
There's quite a lot of rules and
regulations to make sure that mobile sites
are accessible, including native apps.
Best thing to do is have a look at
the mobile accessibility guidelines.
It goes into a lot of detail
into how you can make things
accessible, and that is available at
www.accessibilityoz.com/resources/mobile-testing.
Information be
programmatically determined.
If scripting is used to implement
standard functionality, technologies
will not understand it and be or provide
the appropriate if custom widgets are
built, using technologies will similarly
fail to understand what they're.
When content requires user input, labels
or instructions should be provided to
assist the user with completing their
task and to minimize mistakes made.
For example, if labels and instructions
are not provided and associated
with a form input, a blind user will
not know what information to enter.
Similarly, labels and instructions that
are not visually located closely to a
form input can prevent users of screen
magnifiers and people with cognitive
disabilities from seeing this information.
Labels and instructions that do not give
examples of expected user input can reduce
the likelihood of users with cognitive
language and learning disabilities
entering the correct information.
Keyboard.
Users may submit incomplete forms
if required fields are not labeled.
Trying to find the incomplete
input is a tiresome task when
information is not provided to assist.
So let's talk about labels and field sets.
Fields must have an associated
and coded field label.
A good example of this is Amazon.
So if you go to the Amazon website
and see we have a field here, and if
we right click that field and select
Inspect, you can actually see the
code at the bottom of the screen.
Here you see we have input type
email because it's an email address.
And it has an ID of AP email.
If we look at the label, it has a
label four of AP email, and that
is how the two are associated.
Another thing to be aware of when
creating forms is the use of field sets.
So field sets are for
grouping fields only.
There are three ways
fields can be related.
First, they belong in
one particular group.
So for example, you're searching
and there's a bunch of search
options that you can choose from.
All these search options,
they're the same thing.
So actually having them
grouped is a good idea.
Another reason why you might wanna use
field sets is because a field doesn't
make sense without another field.
So here we have a phone
number that has two fields.
The first field is for the area code.
The second field is for
the phone number itself.
Of course, without an overarching
phone number field set, those
two won't be clear to the user.
Thirdly, they only make sense in
conjunction with an overarching heading.
For example, if you have a list of states
and you have a list of check boxes, then
all those check boxes are related and they
have an overarching sort of name of state.
So you want the states to be grouped
with a name of state territory.
For more information, have a look
at the accessibility Oz forms fact
sheets, www.accessibilityoz.com/fact
sheets slash forms.
A series of videos on forms
on the accessibility website.
The URL is www accessibility
oz com slash videos.
And if you go to the accessibility
S website, you can see there's a
resources main menu, and then there
is the link C, C, C developer videos.
And if you go there, you can
see that there are videos
on H, TM, L forms, and Aria.
The videos on forms include explicit
and implicit form labels, which we
just talked about field sets and
legends, which we also talked about.
Check boxes and radio buttons.
Required form fields, accessible form
instructions, error messages in forms,
and accessible session timeouts.
Next we're gonna talk about accordions.
This is actually a requirement
under bypass blocks, which is
used an expandable collapsible
menu to bypass blocks of content.
And I'll show you a couple of examples.
Is the Transport Accident Commission
website, and you can see here
they've got an expandable menu.
So a couple of things
about this expandable menu.
As you can see, the arrow changes
when it's expanded and when it's not.
If you use the tab key, you'll find
that you can access the accordion
using the tab key and all the
content underneath using the tab key.
It meets accessibility
requirements, et cetera.
This is another expandable, collapsible
menu from the JavaScript fact sheets.
This code, you can actually use yourself
if you would like to, and so once again,
it is accessible via the keyboard.
You can open and close
it when it's closed.
You can't tab to the sections underneath.
When it's open, you can.
There's also a great section in the Aria
Authoring Practice Group about creating
accordions and doing so with Aria.
The URL for that is tiny url.
DO com slash a1 y dash accordion.
And remember, accordion is spelt with
an O and that's what it looks like.
Once again, no aria is better than bad
aria, so make sure you know a lot about
Aria before you start playing with it.
But here is an example, talks about the
role states and properties and keyboard
information, and it has quite detailed.
Code as well can help you.
Principle four, a meaningful sequence
and logical focus order is maintained.
The visual reading order of
form content or your JavaScript
content should be presented in a
meaningful and logical sequence.
IE left to right and top to
bottom, assuming of course,
a left to right language.
Screen readers will read form
components in the order that it
appears in the source markup.
In fact, they read everything in the order
that it appears in the source markup.
When meaningful sequence is not
maintained, form content may be displayed
incorrectly when presented in alternative
formats for assistive technologies.
Users of assistive technologies
sometimes do not have access to
the entire page at once, so changes
before the user's current focus or
elsewhere on the page may be missed.
Navigating with the keyboard is
a one dimensional process, and
users who rely on speech output
can only hear one thing at a time.
So content that is not in a logical
order is harder to comprehend and use.
When a keyboard user presses a button and
new interactive content appears, they'll
expect that content to be immediately
next in the tab order not to have to
jump around the page to get to it.
The other thing to remember is that
websites are accessed by a variety of
devices, including mouse, keyboard,
touchscreen, switch, joystick,
and assisted technologies such
as screen readers and magnifiers.
When the source order, keyboard
focus, order and visual reading
order of a webpage are inconsistent
with each other, this can greatly
impact people's ability to navigate
and access a webpage effectively.
So there are basically three
orders that you need to be aware
of when creating a webpage or a
native app or anything like that.
The first is the source order, which
is the order that the underlying
HTML or other markup is written.
Secondly is the keyboard focus order,
which is the order of interactive
page elements such as links and
form controls when accessed by the
keyboard, IE, the order in which
items receive keyboard focus.
You can easily find out what
that is by going to the address
bar and hitting tab and.
Heating tab again and
going through your page.
And thirdly, visual reading order.
The logical and intuitive
order in which a cited user
naturally reads the page content.
This is generally left to right and top
to bottom, and all content should be
presented in a meaningful sequence so that
any relationship within the data is clear.
If you'd like to learn more, there
is a source order fact sheet and
the accessibility Oz website.
You can go to www dot accessibility oz
com slash fact sheets slash source order.
There's also a video about this
called source order versus display
Order versus Keyboard Focus Order,
and you can get to that by going to
tiny URL com slash three dash orders.
Now when we're talking
about visual reading, order
sequence also really matters.
This is an example where visual
reading order is very problematic.
As you can see, you've got the ability
to purchase tickets to the Lion
King, but it doesn't say anything
about say, accessible tickets.
It's because that information
is after the submit button.
Here you've got request accessible tickets
and a whole bunch of other information,
but information should never be after
a submit button because of course,
the submit button is when people, they
leave the page, and that's for everyone.
Screen reader, users,
visual users, et cetera.
This is another example where
visual order is problematic.
You've got a book here, all the
light we cannot see on Amazon.
And you have these prices, but these
are not links, so you can click on it
many times and nothing will happen.
And only if you look over here on the far
right hand corner does it say This title
is not currently available for purchase.
Now this information should be first up.
People will often miss content that's on
the right hand side, especially magnifier
users, but visual users as well, and
screen reader users because they're
gonna have to read all this content
first, all the way down the page through
the comments and other things that you
might be interested in, et cetera, et
cetera, before they get to the about how
you can't actually purchase the book.
Let's talk about focus order.
So it's important that when you
do insert dynamic content, you
insert it into the dom immediately
following its trigger element.
Let's have a look at an example.
This is an example from the
JavaScript dependencies, and
here you have a live demo.
You have a link here, structural
labels, which if you click
on, you'll actually pop.
As you can see, the additional
information appears immediately after
the link that generated the change.
Another example is this re sortable list.
Once again, let's have
a look at the content.
If we expand it, you can see here.
Lauren Ipsen is first said,
probably said that wrong, is second.
Pre-order the content and then
you can see the said is first
and the Lauren Ipsen is second.
This is another example where you
can move items with the keyboard up
and down the list as you can see.
And once again, if we
have a look at the dom.
At the moment, you can see New South
Wales is first, but let's change that.
And now we've got South
Australia as first.
This is how you make sure focus order
is correct when you are creating forms.
You don't validate on
completion of a field.
You validate only on
submission of a submit button.
So you can see here someone's
put in a desired login name,
they've hit check availability.
This is done by JavaScript
so the page doesn't refresh.
But immediately next in the dom,
have they added this content?
Janet Whitman is not available, but
they're following usernames are,
and then it gives some examples.
Next is principle five.
Instructions Do not rely on sensory
characteristics or nonsensical characters
when sensory characteristics, color,
shape, and location, or nonsensical
characters, asterisk, dashes, et
cetera, are used instead of text.
Users of screen readers may not be able
to understand the meaning of the content.
Often these are ignored by
the screen reader, which means
information is omitted completely.
So let's talk about fields.
This is an incorrect example.
Basically, the fields that are
in error are marked in red.
Now, that's gonna be really problematic
because the reader doesn't read out color.
But it's also gonna be problematic for
people who are blue, red, colorblind.
They aren't gonna be able tell
the difference between red text
on a white background and black
text on a white background.
So they aren't going to be able to
tell which fields are mandatory.
Next is principle six.
Timed activity can be controlled.
Users of assistive technology often take
a lot longer to read a page or undertake
required functionality, either because
of a cognitive disability or because they
can only focus on a few words at once.
Or because it takes longer to listen to
synthesized speech than to visually read.
It would be confusing and disorienting
for people if content were to
change while they were reading it.
Continual animation or flickering
effects may trigger a seizure in
someone who has photosensitive epilepsy.
It's also more difficult for someone
with a cognitive disability to
ignore these effects, which makes the
actual content harder to focus on.
So let's talk about flickering.
This is an example of if you fail a
particular accessibility requirement,
you can actually physically hurt someone.
The best example of was back in 1997.
An episode of the anime series Pokemon
was shown was the 38th episode of the
Electric Soldier Pogon Series broadcast
in Japan on December 16th, 1997.
On 37 stations to 4.6 billion households.
There were repetitive visual effects,
flashing red and blue, effectively strobe
at a rate of 12 hertz for six seconds.
Basically no flashing, flashing
images, especially those with
red, should not flicker faster
than three times per second.
If the image does not have red,
it should still not flicker
faster than five times per second.
Flashing images should not be
displayed for a total duration
of more than two seconds.
Stripes, swirls and concentric
circles should not take up a
large part of the web screen.
Now, of course, you might read that
and go I dunno what that means.
So the best thing to do to determine if
your content has flickering is to use
the peach tool, the photosensitivity
epilepsy analysis tool, and this is the
output of that particular Pokemon episode.
As you can see, there's quite a
lot of red, not so much green.
You can access for free at
traced edu PT. And if you wanna see
an example, which I'll not show you,
the Kickstarter campaign for LX has
some flickering content that fails.
It's a campaign for light bulbs, and also
if you have a look at this Teletubbies
image, you can imagine if it was
moving, it would be fairly problematic.
Next we wanna is time limits one user
when a time limit is about to expire and
provide a mechanism for extending it.
This is also from the
JavaScript dependencies.
There is a time limit, as you can see,
says your session is about to expire.
Do you need more time hit?
Okay.
And of course, the
JavaScript code is there.
Another example here is incorrect, and
here it says, these are currently the best
available tickets that match your request.
These tickets will be held up to
eight minutes for you to complete
your purchase after which time
they'll be returned to sale.
So that doesn't allow anyone to extend
the time, and so that is a failure.
This is another example.
Make a donation.
Your session has timed out.
You need to start ag.
Good luck starting one of me and complete
the members form within 20 minutes.
Which really begs the question, why does
anyone have a timeout on a donation form?
It's give us your money, but
only within the next 20 minutes.
Next is movement.
Use scripting to scroll content and
provide a mechanism to pause it.
And this is the JavaScript
appendices example.
As you can see, the flickering content,
which stopped within five seconds.
So if you really need to use
some blinking information, you
can do so using JavaScript.
Do not use the blink element.
And then there's the
Accessibility Odds website.
You can see we have a slideshow.
It's fairly slow, but you can pause.
It can move things across as you like.
You can move through it and
you can pause or play it.
Incorrect example.
So this is basically just scrolling
content that just keeps moving
from one thing to another.
The first one says traveling
halfway around the world,
just hang out with other.
And the second is bid proved
we're not ready to host the globe,
but there's no pause button.
This is a correct example.
Monash University as you can
see, it has play button, a pause
button, and the 1, 2, 3, 4.
So you can choose one of those options.
Another way to deal with this is
to provide alternatives to moving
content, so you could use scripting
to create an alternative static
version of scripting content.
Once again, this is the JavaScript
appendices, and as you can see,
we have some scrolling content.
Very difficult to read for a number
of users, so you can pause it.
You can even expand it so
it's all written at once.
Once again, you have the
code there if you need it.
Redirects are okay if they're on
the server, but timed redirects
on the client side an absolute no.
So the rules are timed,
server redirects not allowed.
Timed client side redirects not allowed.
Non timed server redirects are okay.
Animated GIF must stop
moving within five seconds.
Do not use Blink or marquee.
Make sure you can stop moving content
with the user agent stop button
or the escape key and or reloading
the page stops the blinking and or
there is a link to stop content.
And of course, you also need to be able
to stop that content using the mouse.
Principle seven provide
mechanisms to help people find and
interact with content correctly.
People rely on mechanisms
to find information that are
most suited to their needs.
On a large website, if a search
is not provided, blind users
may find it cumbersome to tabs
through a large navigation block.
Or visually impaired users may
find it difficult and confusing
when doing the same with a screen
magnifier or screen reader.
Providing a search benefits everyone by
allowing information to be found quickly.
In addition, it may be obvious to
you how a system works, but that's
not always the case for everyone and
for people with disabilities, often
contextual information like imagery.
May not be available or
an alternative presented.
Therefore, it's important to always
provide instructions on how to use
unusual content or functionality
or on how to use functionality that
does not operate as the user expects.
So instructions are really important.
Even if you think it's really clear
to you, that's not necessarily
gonna be the case to everyone.
So this is a magazine and it provides
quite in-depth instructions on how to
turn the page, et cetera, et cetera.
Just remember that all this
content needs to be accessible
to the screen reader as well.
One example of this is functionality
that can't be presented in text
must be descriptively identified.
This is an example of functionality
that can't be presented in text.
Button will appear below this
text within the next 20 seconds.
You should click the button as soon as
it appears to test your reaction time.
And of course, this is only
affected for sighted mouse users.
It's not gonna be great for someone
using a keyboard or someone who
uses screen reader Principle eight.
Of context or content unexpectedly.
Navigating a document or inputting
data into a form should be a
predictable experience for all users.
People with visual, cognitive, or motor
impairments may become disoriented.
If changes in context or content occur
unexpectedly, such as a new window popping
up, or the focus being moved to another
form component, the user may not be aware
that change has occurred as a result of
their actions if they were not adequately
informed or did not initiate the change.
So one example of this is
opening content in new windows.
Make sure you use an actuation
event rather than focus or
load to programmatically open
links or trigger popup windows.
This is another JavaScript fact sheet.
Now, it's not gonna actually open a popup
window because I have them disabled, but
basically if you click on this, you'll
end up getting a popup if you have that
kind of stuff enabled on your site.
Next is use progressive enhancement
to open windows on user request.
So this is the JavaScript pen, and
if you click on this link, it opens
up in a new window and you can have a
look at the JavaScript content there.
Let's talk about change on user request.
So make sure that you do not
use the change event of a
select element for navigation.
Let's have a look at an example.
If we look here, we've got a jump to.
And we can go down and
we can select something.
Now, it's not common usage to select
something and it automatically submits.
If you have a select box like this,
users expect there to be a submit button.
But if you select an option, you can see
it takes you to that page immediately.
Another example here is if you select
your area, it will open a new page
immediately instead of giving you a
submit button so the user can choose
when they wanna move to a new page.
Another is do not automatically
refresh the page without
user confirmation or control.
And you can actually do this is a failure.
This is incorrect code.
The link will take us to a page
containing a large number one, and then
redirect to a page with number two.
And as you can see, that
was a client side redirect.
Very bash.
This is an example.
I've only seen this once, but
I have to use it as an example.
You can see here you've
got rollover for video.
So if you just move your mouse over that,
all of a sudden this entire video pops
up, which is very distracting and will
be incredibly inaccessible for users.
A correct example where you are
doing the automatic filtering
is when you enter content into a
field and it filters automatically.
This is not something that users
expect, so you shouldn't do it.
But if you're gonna do it,
you need to absolutely include
instructions prior to the form field.
So here it says the list of outages
will automatically begin to filter
once you enter some text in the filter
outages by suburb field, and the
field is immediately after that text.
This is a popup, so we've put
in some content for Twitter.
I refuse to call it whatever
the other name is, and it says,
Hey, your tweets being posted,
and this is a popup on a page.
And then after a couple of seconds it
just disappears completely inaccessible.
Do not do that.
Principle nine is identify
components consistently.
Functionality that is similar or
used more than once on a website
should be labeled consistently to
create familiarity and ease of use.
This improves a user's ability to find
information or use similar functionality
on other pages without having to relearn
how this is an incorrect example.
Basically inconsistent pagination.
These are from the same site, and you
can see that they look quite different.
The first is all just text, same color.
The links that are
actionable are underlined.
The second, none of the links
are underlined, and you also have
what seems to be a next button.
So this is the kind of example of
inconsistency that you want to avoid.
When it comes to forms, then you
also wanna avoid inconsistency as
well, whether it's buttons or shape
of fields or things like that.
But this is another example where
the contextual help is inconsistent.
So the very first contextual help
is just text under the field.
The second contextual help is a little
information icon that you can click
on and get additional information.
And the third contextual help is
just a popup that appears randomly.
You need to make sure this is consistent.
And finally, principle 10,
identify and describe errors
and error suggestions in text.
When an error is detected, it
should be identified in text and
described in detail without specific
information about the error.
Screen reader.
Users may believe a form is not
functioning and may abandon it altogether.
Errors that are identified with
color alone or symbol or icons may
not be understood or recognized by
users who are blind or colorblind.
This may also be the same for users
with learning or language disabilities,
or other cognitive impairments.
When error messages are provided, they
should include suggestions on how to
correct mistakes such as examples of the
correct user input without suggestions.
People with visual or motor impairments
or cognitive language and learning
difficulties may not understand what
the required input is and may not
be able to correct their mistakes.
After repeatedly trying to input the
correct information, which can be
very tiresome, users may ultimately
abandon the form altogether.
When a form is used to initiate a
legal or financial commitment, or
to modify or delete user data, a
step to reverse check or confirm
the user input before submitting the
form should be provided to prevent
users from making a serious mistake.
Users with visual or cognitive language
and learning difficulties may have input
incorrect characters or users with a motor
impairment may have hit incorrect keys.
Field errors is one example.
Form validation should always be
triggered by submission rather
than individual field events.
Form validation should trigger an alert.
Then set focus on the first invalid field.
Validation error.
Messages should be programmatically
inserted directly after the field.
They relate to using functions of
the dom and in the label element.
So let's have a look at some examples.
If you enter some text, let's enter some
text and then tab to the next field.
You can see there is field validation
immediately after the field.
This can be very confusing for screen
reader users, especially if you then
trap users in a field that isn't correct.
This is another example.
If we just enter some random
content and then hit submit.
There's some text at the top that tells
you what's wrong, but the focus is
actually still on the submit button.
So you wanna move focus
to where the errors are.
We have some information in
the JavaScript fact sheet about
this, and this is correct.
You can enter some text and then
leave the other one empty and you
can see it will say, Hey, you got
some errors and it's moved you to the
field in error and given you an error.
Error form.
Submissions should be bound by the form
submit event, not to the submit buttons.
Click event.
Incorrect example is
input type equals submit.
On click equal return validate this
correct example would be form action
equals search on submit equals return.
Validate this and do not force
focus to remain invalid fields.
Let's have a look at an example here.
We have a field.
I'm gonna type in some text.
I'm tabbing, and as you
can see, it won't let me.
Where form fields require a
specific format or range of values.
Contextual help text can be
programmatically inserted
directly after the field.
It relates to using functions of
the dom and in the label element.
So let's have a look at that.
As you can see here, as you
tab from item to item, you get
a popup with some information.
So when it comes to error identification,
the error must be in text, be it
the relevant field, be included in
the relevant label four element.
This is an incorrect example.
As you can see, the fields have not
been completed, but the form has
been submitted and all the errors
are underneath the submit button.
This is absolutely problematic
if you're gonna do everything in
JavaScripts because as we said before,
no one looks past the submit button.
A much better example.
Once you have submitted an
empty field, you can see that
every single field that requires
information has some field labels.
Now, all this information is in the
forms fact sheet@wwwaccessibilityoz.com
slash fact sheet slash forms, and
we do have a series of forms videos,
www accessibility oz.com/videos.
And if the information isn't there, it'll
be in the JavaScript fact sheets and
associated appendices, www accessibility
s com slash fact sheets slash JavaScript.
In conclusion, as we talked about,
there are really three types
of JavaScript functionality.
First binding functionality to
existing interactive components such
as links, buttons, and text fields.
Non-interactive functionality that
presents information and creating
custom components that are both
interactive and informative.
There are 10 accessibility principles.
All functionality must take a form
that can be interpreted as text.
All functionality must be
accessible to all input devices.
Information and structure can
be programmatically determined.
A meaningful sequence and logical
focus order is maintained.
Instructions do not rely on sensory
characteristics or nonsensical characters.
Timed activity can be controlled.
Provide mechanisms to help people find
and interact with content correctly.
Do not cause a change
of context or content.
Unexpectedly identify components
consistently and identify and describe
errors and error suggestions in text.
Now, I know that was a lot of information,
but there are lots of places where
you can find additional information.
Have W3C Aria Authoring Practice
Guide the Patterns section.
It has information on how to create
accessible accordions alerts, alert and
message dialogues, breadcrumbs, carousels,
check boxes, combo boxes, dialogue models,
sliders, switch tables, tabs, toolbar,
windows, splitters, and many more.
The Authoring Practice Guide also
has practices section, which has
information on landmark regions,
providing accessible names and
descriptions, developing a keyboard
interface, grid and table properties,
communicating value and limits for range
widgets, structural roles, and hiding
semantics with the presentation roles.
All that information is available
at www w three org slash
slash apg.
And of course there are the
accessibility odds fact sheets.
We have them on a range of
topics, including images, P video,
interactive maps, H two ml five,
content, JavaScript tables coding,
keyboard source order, and forms.
Those are available at
www.accessibilityoz.com/fact
sheets, and then there are the
accessibility OZ developer videos.
In the HTML section, we have HTML headings
well-formed and valid markup, keyboard
focus, source order versus display
order versus keyboard focus order.
In the form section, we have explicit
and implicit form labels, field sets
and legends, check boxes and radio
buttons, required form fields, accessible
form instructions, error messages in
forms, and accessible session timeouts.
And in the Aria section, the
videos are what is Aria and why
use it, how not to use Aria.
Aria Landmark roles, aria labeled
by versus Aria, described by versus
Aria label and using Aria Live.
All those videos are available on www
accessibility oz.com/resources/videos.
And then there are the mobile
accessibility testing guidelines.
There are guidelines on both
native app and mobile site.
Devices capture error technologies
and step by step instructions with
examples that's available at www
accessibility resources mobile testing.
Thank you for coming along.
You can access these slides
at www accessibility oz com
slash about slash conferences.
Just look for the comp 42 heading and
I'll have the presentation slides there.
And please if you have any questions.
Please do reach in
QE and if you have accessibility,
please do reach out.
We're always happy to help.
Thank you very much.