Hi, my name is Amar and today I will talk
about the modern infrastructure security
that is zero trust container security.
We will dive into how it works,
why it's needed, and practical
steps you can take to implement it.
But before we get started, I would
like to talk about a little bit
about our, company and, myself.
We are Oxygen Security based in Maryland
and we have been around since 2018
and we have been able to help over
50 different customers to build out
their digital transformation journey
from on prem to hybrid to multi cloud.
We have been able to help them
integrate DevOps including, test
and interactive testing and security
validations of the networks.
I am a cloud and DevOps engineer
working across major cloud
platforms like AWS, Azure and GCP.
I specialize in crowd security
assessments, cost optimization, and
microservices orchestration with a
focus on automating DevSecOps process.
Currently, I work as a senior DevOps
engineer at Oxygen Security, where
I design and implement secure,
scalable cloud infrastructure
and streamlined CI CD workflows.
So what we'll be discussing today,
we will explain how DevSecOps works.
for containers, how to apply zero trust
principles to containers, integrate
it into development life cycle, and
see the practical examples of how
it works in real world scenarios.
Let's dive into the zero trust.
Zero trust is a strategic approach that
eliminates implicit trust in your systems.
in the traditional security model,
we used to assume, we assume to, we
assume that everything inside the
corporate network could be trusted by
default, but, this model is outdated
given today's cyber security threats.
Instead, zero trust is based on the
principle that trust should ne should
never be guaranteed by default.
if you look at the second point,
trust is neither binary nor permanent.
This means trust is not something
you give once and forget about.
it must be continuously earned
and verified, which is the
essence of the zero trust.
Now you may ask where we
can apply the zero trust.
the answer is almost anywhere.
It's applicable to nearly all
organizational functions, from
securing cloud workloads to container
environments, and even endpoints
like laptops and mobile devices.
The Zero Trust process can be
broken down into four steps.
Establish trust by
enforcing authentication
and authorization mechanism.
Enforce security policies
across your environment.
Continuously verify, continuously
verify by, by the constantly checking
if trust should still be maintained.
Respond to threats in real time using
automated incident response mechanism.
Zero trust, in, container security
means that we don't automatically
trust any part of the system, whether
inside or outside the network.
Everything must be continuously verified
to ensure the security containers face
several challenges just like underlying
host system which means if the system is
compromised the containers are at risk.
Another issue is securing the container
registry as the images used to create
containers may have vulnerabilities.
Additionally containers can
be attacked while running if
they are not well protected.
it.
And using third party container
images could introduce security flaws.
This is why security zero trust
is crucial for containers.
It allow for, fine grained access control,
ensuring that, the authorized users.
that only, the authorized users,
only, only the authorized users,
authorized users or the systems,
can access the, containers.
It also enforces the principles of
least privileges, least privileges,
it means, It means that enforces
the principles of lease privileges,
meaning that, the containers are given
only the permission they have needed,
zero trust prevents attackers from
moving between containers, monitoring
activities in real time, and helps with
security standards like SOC 2 and GDPR.
The process involves establishing
trust, through authentication and.
Forcing it by protecting data, regularly
verifying container activities, and
being ready to respond to any threats in
let's move to the new slide.
in this, today's world,
everything is everywhere.
We are no longer in an era where we
are applications or services are neatly
contained within a single data center.
Modern architectures are distributed.
We have microservices, cloud native
applications, and geographically
distributed deployments.
All of these factors add complexity and
increase the, and increase the attack
surface, making security more challenging.
Additionally, the workforce has changed.
Remote teams are now the norms, and
employees are working from home,
offices, or even the coffee shops, all
accessing networks from various devices,
securing these diverse environments.
becomes essential.
Nowadays, nearly every application
we use, whether for business or
personal use, relies on the multiple
internal and external integrations.
These integrations connect different
systems and if any one of these
points is insecure, it can serve
as a gateway for cyber attacks.
We must consider the global supply chain,
which includes open source, open source.
Softwares and components that
many organizations depends on.
These can be a security risk because
vulnerabilities in widely used open
source libraries can affect the
countless, application globally.
As we discussed earlier, the zero
trust process involves establishing
and forcing continuously verifying.
and responding to the trust.
Here is the map each of these zero trust
principles for container security to
the respective stages of the process.
Segmentation, this is about dividing your
environment into smaller manageable zones.
And it's quickly controlling
the communication between them
in containerized environment.
Microsegmentation ensures that even if
one part of the system is compromised,
the attacker cannot easily move laterally
to other, to the other containers.
You control which containers can
communicate with each other and
restrict unnecessary traffic.
The second is runtime security.
This principle ensures that containers
behave as expected once they are deployed.
You monitor container
activities in real time.
Looking for any suspicious action such as
unauthorized, or unusual network traffic.
If a container tries to run a
process, it was not intended.
So we need to detect and block
that, action immediately.
The next is network security.
This is the backbone of The any of
the zero trust approach, we must
secure the network communication
between the containers, whether they
are running on the same machine or
across distributed environments.
This includes implementing strong
encryption and securing all communication
channels, ensuring that traffic between
services is trusted and authenticated.
The fourth one is IEM.
Here we strictly control who has access
to which resource in a zero trust.
Until every request for access must be
verified, IAM ensures that users and
services are only given the minimal
level of access they need and access is
revoked as soon as it's no longer needed.
The fifth is image security.
The foundation of any container, In the
container image and securing these images
is critical image security involves the
scanning images for vulnerabilities before
they are deployed, enforcing sign images
and ensuring they have not been tampered
in this slide, how we can discuss
how we can, how we can implement
zero trust container security.
throughout the DevOps lifecycle
and map the principles which each
of the DevOps lifecycle stages.
starting with the build phase, this is
where, we focus on the vulnerability.
We implement build scanning
to detect any vulnerabilities
early on in the development.
And we also enforce
security policies as code.
This ensures that our security
standards are embedded from the start.
Next phase is test.
We scan our container registries
to check for vulnerabilities.
This followed by security automation,
which help to streamline our
security checks and testing.
We also implement admission controls
to ensure that only trusted and
secure components make it through.
As we move to the staging phase, we focus
on the compliance, which is CIS benchmark.
are used to ensure we are meeting
industry security standards.
We introduce a container firewall
at this stage, adding an extra layer
of defense to protect our workloads.
In the production phase, we
continue to ensure compliance with
frameworks such as PCI and NIST.
Container's workload security is our
priority, which includes protecting
running applications from any threats.
We have runtime protection.
This is where runtime scannings and real
time alerts are critical for detecting
and responding to threats immediately.
Immediately as they happen by
applying the zero trust approach
across the life cycle, from a build
to production, we can ensure that
continuous security protecting both our,
microservices infrastructure and data.
Let's move to the real world.
here we can compare the before and
after ZeroTrust security changes.
Before ZeroTrust, we see that
applications are deployed without
consistently verifying container images
leading to potential vulnerabilities.
After implementing the Zero Trust,
every application, regardless of
version, undergoes image scanning
to detect vulnerabilities and
ensure trust before the deployment.
This continuous verification
process strengthens security by
ensuring only trusted applications.
Secure images are deployed using
the risk of breaches in our, in
our microservices environment.
Verifying the image at, at,
deployment time ensures that only
trusted and verified images are
used in our production environment.
This process ensures that security is
not just a one time task, but, continuous
and ongoing activity, in your pipeline.
The next, example is micro
segmentation before zero trust.
All containers within the application
can communicate freely with each
other, which increases the risk of,
lateral movements during an attack.
After implementing zero trust, micro
segmentation containers are segmented
into isolated groups, each with a
specific security policies applied.
This limits communication only to
necessary components, reducing the
risk, reducing the attack surface,
and containing potential threats.
With micro segmentation, we can apply
fine grained security controls, ensuring
each container is protected individually.
This approach isolates the backend
containers and only allow ingress traffic,
from the, Name space selector, which is
backend services by applying this strategy
We limit the movement of attacks within
the system reducing the attack surface
and minimizing the risk before zero
trust IAM containers have broader access
which increases the security risk or
unauthorized actions can occur across the
environment After implementing Zero Trust,
fine grained access control is enforced.
Each container is granted the least
privilege necessary to function.
And access is tightly coupled,
tightly, controlled based on
the specific rules and policies.
This ensures that only authenticated
and authorized actions are permitted,
minimizing the attack surface, and
safeguarding sensitive resources
within the microservices environment.
In this harness pipeline, an IEM role
can securely pull the container image
from the AWS Elastic Container Registry,
ensuring that only authorized users and
process have access to critical resources.
Before Zero Trust, all containers
one, two, and three are,
unsecure and vulnerable due to
unprotected communication path.
But after Zero Trust, container
network security for every container
benefits from consistently applies
security policies and dinners are
isolated and protected by secure
network policies, reducing the risk of
unauthorized access and natural movement.
This comprehensive network security
ensures a consistent, secure
environment for all the containers.
Here we enforce strict policies,
continuously monitor traffic and
respond to any anomalies by coding the
mauth service as part of the service
mesh in this, in this manifest file.
We ensure that authentication is applied,
at, broad namespace, helping to, helping
to protect, our environment from.
from the unauthorized access.
Before Zero Trust, we use security
policies to manually enforce
the containers that are used it.
And after Zero Trust, we enforce policies
as code on every container to protect
runtime container from security threats.
if a shell is started as a root and alert
will be sent to the, immediate action.
This real time enforcement and the
monitoring, ensures that we can respond
to any security threats that, that
arise, during the runtime, protecting
the system while it's operational.
thank you for joining me
today for this conversation
about, I hope you had enjoyed.
this conversation.
If you have any further questions or
you would like to, have a questions,
feedback, feel free to contact us on
www.dot io and, on my email info at
dot I, and han at io and I am always
happy to respond your feedback.
Thank you and have a great day.