Greetings, everyone.
I am Jubin Thomas.
I work as a technical
architect at Signet Jewelers.
I'm also a senior member of IEEE.
Today, the topic which I would like
to discuss is building scalable e
commerce backend with microservices.
And before I start with my presentation,
I would like to thank Mark and all the
organizers of JavaScript Conference
2024 Con 42 to invite me as a speaker.
As you all know that there are a lot of
pioneers in the world of microservices
and some of them are listed over here.
Netflix, Spotify, eBay, Amazon
Web Services, Airbnb, Uber, Nike,
Twitter, Walmart, and Verizon.
the agenda for talk today is going
over the overview and infrastructure
architecture, like what are microservices,
when should I use them, what is
the right size for a microservice,
Why is microservices better than
monoliths infrastructure architecture?
Then we'll go through the testing
strategies like microservices, testing
strategy, and the testing tools used.
We'll go over the Docker
and Kubernetes architecture.
What is the docker?
What is Kubernetes?
What is the, Kubernetes architecture
and the Kubernetes concepts?
Finally, we'll go through
node js expressed in MongoDB.
We will see what are the
different types of Node.
js available, the
advantages of using Node.
js.
then we will go through what is MongoDB
and what is the requirement for a Node.
js based microservice platform.
Then we will see a simple
application using Node.
js.
So what are microservices?
it's an approach to engineering focused
on building single function modules with
well defined interfaces and operations.
It minimizes the risk and scope of change.
It is easy to deploy and easy to
understand across the various business.
So as you can see in this image, the
left, side is basically the monolith
architecture, which is a typical,
architecture for a monolith system
where there's a user interface and
then we will have a business logic and
a data layer, and a data layer is a
layer which connects to the database.
With the implementation of microservice,
the same user service, is actually
connected to multiple microservices.
So the whole monolith business
logic is actually divided into
multiple microservices and we
will be having different databases
for each of these microservices.
Now a question comes that what is
the right size for a microservice?
The business function domain of the
service determines more important
than its scale which means that
rather than focusing on the scale of
the microservice or the size of the
microservice, it is more important to
understand what is the business function,
which that microservice will perform.
one microservice might have a dozen
entities and the other will have a
couple of dozen ENT entities For every
bounded context from, DTD enables
you to break down a big multi-domain
monolith into a microservice.
Emphasizing user stories will
enable us to precisely outline
the limits of the business domain.
Now, why is Microsoft
better than monoliths?
As you see that monolith is actually built
as a single unit as we saw in the diagram.
It's basically a database back
end code and front end code.
And at the same time, any feature addition
requires the entire unit to be deployed.
On the other hand, in microservice,
we basically do a small autonomous
services that work together.
It's loosely coupled with bounded context.
Now the image what you see here is a
typical microservice example where we
have a UI layer and then in case of a
e commerce world we will be having four
different entities here like shopping
cart, order, customer, inventory and
this is a bare minimum things which is
required for an e commerce background and
we see here There's a database over here.
but at the same time, in the microservice
world, we will be having a customer
order shopping cart inventory as totally
different services and it could be
connected to different other databases.
as you see, customer could be connected
to Redis and order could be in
MongoDB, shopping cart in Microsoft
SQL server and inventory in Oracle 12c.
Now, what is a capability centric design?
Usually in a monolith manner, the team is
splitting depending more on the technology
or skill set than corporate goals.
In business centric development,
it basically focuses on
business capabilities.
The entire team is aligned
towards business capabilities.
For example, here we have three different
capabilities listed over here and,
the product team is defined based on
the number of capabilities we assign.
Now, understanding the root, an
aggregate will have one of the
component objects be the aggregate root.
So for example, here in this case,
order, is connected to various different
entities like customer, shipping
address, payment strategy, and payment
strategy is actually connected to
credit card, cash, bank transfer.
So this is a typical shopping menu,
if you see over here, where there
are entities there are service
ports and utils and the adapters are
something which helps, to implement
the database access services APIs.
Converters are used to convert
an enum value to proper
integer value in the database.
As you see the, there are different
adapters like order repository, order
service, order web service, order
query web service, shipping address
web service, and so on and so forth.
as we all know that CRUD, which is
basically create, read, update and
delete has its own disadvantage.
a mismatch between the read and
write representations of the data, it
risks data contention where records
are locked in the data store in a
collaborative domain and it can make
managing security and permissions more
complex because each entity is subject
to both read and write operations.
Let's go through the
microservice testing strategy.
So as we all know that there are many
testing components, like unit testing is
the smallest piece of testable software.
Component testing is something having
a scope of exercise software to a
portion of the system under test.
Integrated testing defines the
communication paths and interactions
between components to detect errors.
interface defects.
And, finally, we have an integration
contract testing to see, whether
the contract is matching.
And finally, we have an end
to end test, which tells that
the system meets the external
requirements and achieves its goal.
there are many microservice tool
out of which some of them, which
I listed over here, they are
pretty famous and pretty known.
So as we know that JUnit, is one
of a great testing tool, in, the
combination of Cucumber and also
we have Mockito, to define the unit
testing and the component testing scope.
Now let's go through what is a Docker.
So Docker, as you all know, it's an
open source platform for developers and
assist admins to develop and deploy,
and run applications with containers.
so it works on the principle
of build, ship and run.
And this is a typical docker architecture
where there is a client and then we
have a docker host where a docker
host has docker daemon and there are
multiple containers within that and
we do have a registry for this docker.
Going through kubernetes overview,
kubernetes is again an open source
system for container orchestration.
It is focused around scheduling, scaling.
and self filling.
This is a typical Kubernetes architecture
where we have an API, connected to the
user interface and Kamala interface
and which is actually connected to
the Kubernetes master and a Kubernetes
master could be connected to multiple
nodes as we could see in this image.
And Kubernetes works
with the concept of pods.
So a pod is basically a
logical application with one
or more containers and volumes.
It is having a shared
namespace and one IP per pod.
And a service is basically a thing which
basically connects to multiple pods.
In this case, if you see a service
connected to three different pods.
now let me go through, the
microservice framework using Node.
js and what is the
advantage we have with this.
So the advantage of creating
microservices with Node.
js is, as listed over here, it is a
single threaded microservice and then
we have bufferless atmosphere over here.
It's asynchronous, highly
scalable, extremely quick,
event driven and licensed.
the most popular Node.
js microservices are ExpressJS and
NestJS and, in this, presentation I
have used ExpressJS to build a simple
application which I will be displaying
in the later part of the slides.
Now, what is a MongoDB?
As you all know, MongoDB
is no SQL database.
And what are the benefits out of it?
It is schema less, it has a lot
of scalability, and it gives
us a great performance benefit.
Now, the requirement to
write microservices is Node.
js.
as we all know that writing a
microservice which also includes a
producer, message broker and a consumer.
and, with this, we will be having certain
requirements, like installing the Node.
js, installing NPM, installing
Docker and RabbitMQ if you
are using a message broker.
No, I am actually
covering, a separate video.
creation of a simple application, which is
basically to order a product using node.
js.
So as part of this, we
have five different files.
And I'm going to the details of these
files as I explained in this talk.
So we have db.
js, Product.
js, and another product.
js which is basically
launching as a server.
Then we have an order.
js and to launch order.
js we have another order.
js which is basically
the server for order.
js.
So what is db.
js?
You know it is a creating a
database connection using Mongoose.
As you can see on the right side, we are
using Mongoose to connect to the database.
And if the connection is successful, it
displays a connection successful message.
Otherwise it throws a
connection is failed.
now what is a product or JS?
we are creating a product service over
here, so customer should be able to
order a product using this microservice.
So in this case, we have a product.
js where we have product description
as one attribute and product
name, product ID and brand.
And similarly, we create products.
js, which is basically creating
a server for product service.
So in this, to launch this.
We have a port, 3000
and as you can see here,
there are different, app.
post here, one for the product
and products and then we have app.
get for product ID and, app.
delete for deleting a product.
Now what is order.
js?
it is basically giving a
platform to create, orders, or
basically to order a product.
So in this case, we have a product ID.
initial date and the delivery
date as part of the order schema.
And order.
js is another, file which we create
into, to, create as a server for order J.
So in this case, we see, that we have
a new order do saved to save an order.
If an order is actually
saved, we basically say new
order has added successfully.
And if there is a connection
error, we basically say that it's
an internal server At the same
time, we have, app dot get for.
Fetching the orders and if we have
a specific order to be fetched,
we can also pass the order ID to
fetch their respective product.
In conclusion, I would like to
say that microservices in Node.
js are really good for
developing applications.
We can modify without
affecting other services.
Thank you so much for
listening to my talk.
That's pretty much what I have to share.
And that is my contact information, jupin.
thomas at i3p.
org.
I would be very happy to
connect with anyone who would
like to send me a request.
Thank you so much.