Hello everyone.
I'm Ti Ira Herrera an independent
researcher based in Canada.
Today I'll show how cross cloud campaign
analytics and modern JavaScript come
together to deliver past trustworthy
in insights for marketing and growth.
So if we, if you have ever waited
on a slow dashboard or try to
connect data that lives in different
places the session is for you.
So here's our path.
I will outline the real
problems, team faces, and then
the end to end architecture.
I will open the data engineering layer
and connect it to the browser, explain the
react patterns, show how we handle large
data sets, discuss embedding business
intelligence and end with storytelling,
role-based views and performance
disciplines, collaboration and concise
takeaways before a brief set of questions.
So here the modern analytics challenge.
So the marketing teams collect more
data than ever, and yet struggle
to answer simple questions quickly.
Channels report differently.
Schemas drift and extract arrive late.
So the confident erodes when
two dashboards disagree.
So what decision markers want
is fresh, reliable number
that respond as they explore.
JavaScript is the bridge between
the distributed computation
and the human understanding.
It turns, aggregates and applications
into an interface that invites discovery.
Imagine a campaign manager asking
which creative drove a stronger re
returns last week in major cities
after a specific budget share.
So the backend may already hold
the truth, but without a responsive
interface, it stays locked away.
Our aim is to reduce the distance between
the question and a trustworthy answer.
So here is the architecture of
the fueling market intelligence.
So a picture of flow from ingest to
transform to serve to visualization.
So data first lands in the
durable object store that welcomes
partitioning by date and by the source.
Orchestration service schedules,
movement and health checks.
So late or missing data is obvious
rather than mysterious, scalable
compute performs a transformation
and model scoring, producing tidy
queries which have like ready table.
We expose only the shapes that the
application needs through the guarded
application programming interface with
strict limit caching and Page Nation.
The React application is the translation
layer that turns small, precise payloads
into filters, narrators, and chart.
Each stage is optimized
for a different constraint.
Storage focuses on cost and durability.
Compute focuses on
throughput and correctness.
Serving focuses on safety and latency.
The browser focuses on
clarity and the flow.
Why do we need cross-cloud?
Cross Cloud is a choice to combine
strengths while keeping options
open storage lives where economics
and ecosystems are stor strongest.
Transformation runs where
entity identity, governance,
and managed sparks you the team.
We reduce data movement by processing
close to sources and returning aggregates
that the user will actually consume when
prices, compliance and scale needs change.
The system can shift workloads
without rewriting the entire
product because the contract to
the front end remains constant.
When we are deep diving into the
data engineering, we majorly focus
on the storage layer history,
Azure Data Factory for ETL and
Azure Databricks for processing.
So in the lake we partition by
day and by source, so queries
scan only what they need.
Lifecycle rules push cold data to
cheaper triers without breaking lineage.
Incoming drops are checked with
manifest files, so missing partitions
and record count mismatches surface.
Early in orchestration, we run
batch and micro batch pipelines.
These have the parameters
for the dates sources.
So one pattern covers many feeds.
Let's include the failing step,
the impacted partition, and a list
link to the run, which shortens
the recovery in the compute layer.
We store curated tables in columnar
formats with constrained schema evolution.
Deterministic, transforms, make
outputs, reproducible, attribution,
logic, and deduplication
happen here not in the browser.
And aggregates arrive at the
cranes that product managers
actually use, such as daily by
geography, by channel, by creative.
So role level security applies at the
query time using user identity claims.
So each tenant sees only their own groups.
The serving layer enforces payload
caps and compresses responses.
Hot endpoints benefit from
short server side caches.
So surges do not herd downstream systems.
What reaches the browser is small and
honest and reliable and repeatable.
Processing scale in numbers, these have
like the daily data volumes even per
day and query response and the uptime.
SLA.
So the daily data volume can be
anywhere between one TB to number of
gbs and even per day individual user
interactions are like tracked and
analyzed across like all the campaigns.
So the SLA time is maintained to keep
guaranteed availability of the dashboards.
So from backend to the browser is the
point where the understanding happens.
We request only what we need,
render quickly, and design
interactions around real questions.
A small initial payload confirms that
the system is responsive, deeper details
arrive when the user shows intents.
The feeling should be of the
focus rather than the noise.
Here is the React dashboard architecture,
which has four major components like the
component library, state management, API
integration, and the performance layer.
In React, we separate data
state and presentation.
So the code base stays
calm and the features grow.
Reusable.
Chart components share the same grammar,
so title access, and empty states.
Feel familiar filters such as date,
geography, channel, and creative.
Live in the central store
with memorized selectors that
prevent unnecessary updates.
Network re requests automatically
include authentication.
The retry with care and still requests
are canceled when the user changes direct.
The interface updates immediately
when the, when a filter changes and
the data fills in a moment later.
This patent gives confidence
that every action was understood.
So handling the large data sets on
the client side, large data sets
do not require heavy interfaces.
We virtualize long tables, so the
document only contains what is visible.
We load progressively sending
a high level summary first and
fetching details on demand.
Small roll ups, run in background worker,
so the main thread stays responsive.
Rapid filter changes are ou, so
only the final intent triggers work.
Payloads are cabbed and compressed.
So ordinary laptops on
ordinary networks feel fast.
Coming to the integration pattern with
the power ai, many organization rely on
the existing business intelligent assets.
We embed those reports so they
feel native single sign on
carries identity into the frame.
Event handlers keep filters synchronized
in both directions, so a choice in react
reflects in the embedded visual in visual,
and a selection in the visual updates.
The surrounding state exports to
portable documents and spreadsheets
are initiated from application
itself, which keeps people in one
place while sharing the results.
So visualization, storytelling
with the data, every chart
should speak in full sentence.
The title states the conclusion rather
than the category such as Creative
B outperformed creative A by 18% in
cities with population above 1 million.
A timeline shows what changed before
and after the key end benchmarks.
Provide context for whether
a number is good or may.
Really loud and annotations connect
movement in line to business decisions,
which is how numbers become actions,
role-based analytics view.
So executives need a comp summary
of return on investment spend,
pacing and notable movers.
Campaign manager, on the other hand,
would require a tactical surface
that crosses channel, creative and
geography with a clear next step.
And analysts need freedom to
slice and export the data.
We present distinct entry points
that share a single source of truth
performance of optimization strategies.
There are majorly four strategies we could
focus on starting with the code splitting.
Smart caching data page Nation
debouncing and trotting performance
is not a finishing touch.
It is a promise.
We split codes, so heavy
areas load only when visited.
We cache on the server and in the
browser with lifetimes that match
how fast the data changes, we page
it on the server and prefetch the
next page while the user reads.
We track time to interactive
first content, full paint and the
95th percentile of application
programming interface latency.
And we treat regression alerts as
product bugs to fix immediately.
Speed comes from alignment, and we
write interface contracts first, so
the front end and the back end build.
In parallel, we review payload sizes,
query patterns, and frame rates together.
We keep a living page for
decisions and objectives, so the
newcomers join the story quickly.
After incidents, we write short
harness notes about what changed
that freedom keeps us shipping.
So the key takeaways that I got from
this project is that JavaScript is
the bridge from complex cross-cloud
analytics to human decisions.
Performance is not negotiable.
The biggest wins appear when platform
data and design teams works as
one and measure their promises.
I am happy to take a few questions if
you are deciding what belongs on the
server and what belongs in the browser.
Keep joins and heavy aggregation
on the server and leap only small
roll-ups to the background worker.
If you are thinking about tenant safety,
enforce roll level filters on the
server using identity claims and never
rely on the client provided filters.
If your stack uses a different
warehouse or cloud, the architecture
is still portable because the contract
to the browser remains the constant.
Thank you for your time.
I'm ra and if this session sparks
some ideas for your ATech stack,
your friend and performance or
your cross cloud strategies, I'm
glad to continue the conversation.
Enjoy the rest of the conference.