Hello everyone, myself
Sai Krishna Paladugu.
I'm an iOS developer.
So today my topic is contactless
integration for kiosk and
iOS devices using JavaScript.
So basically the technologies
I'm going to cover here NFC,
Bluetooth and QR code technologies.
Basically the implementation for the
kiosk for the various industries.
Yeah, let me go to my table of contents
and Yeah, here is all the contacts
I'm going to cover about today.
the iOS kiosk integration, WebView
in native iOS development, With
javascript nfc technology for seamless
transactions bluetooth for proximity
based services qr code and barcode
scanning for contactless integration
payment integration with apple pay custom
ios apps for kiosk and use cases of ios
kiosks in various industries mdm tools
for easy device management So let me go
to the first topic So the first topic
is introducing, the kiosk integration.
So basically, the kiosks where
outside industries use iPhones
and iPads, basically in the kiosk
wise, they need a big screen.
The people can come and
they can do their, tasks.
from themselves, most preferably
iPads would be the best option.
So basically these iPads and iPhones
are increasingly being used in the self
service kiosks due to their intuitive
interfaces and powerful hardware.
so these are all, very efficient and also
we don't see any much lag and it is all.
prompt and it will be more effective.
these contactless experience are becoming
essential for reducing the spread of
germs and enhancing user convenience.
Basically, the people are experienced
a lot in the pre pandemic situation
where this interaction, to the people
to people will be, more concerns.
So where we come up with the solution
called a contactless integration for
kiosk where people can come to our store
for a shipping and they can do their
self scanning the packages and printing
the receipts and things like that.
All the stops they can do for
themselves without waiting for the
team member to assist what they want.
So Basically, this is all these
devices are very fast and secure and
touch free interactions Industry like
retail healthcare and hospitality.
So let me go to the another slide.
So WebView in a native iOS development,
Swift and Objective C with JavaScript.
So basically in our current
application where we integrated,
JavaScript for one of the function,
which is, to load, the web page.
these are all the steps, We followed
and we implemented a webpage
inside of a native iwas container.
So in the current project, we
just creating a project and just
adding a WK web view to your
current com, view controller.
If it is a start view controller,
when you are starting a view, the
first you there, you can integrate
the W controller where you want to
navigate to the specific webpage.
So there we can import a web.
Kit and create a outlet for web
view and write a code to load
page using url request So run
the app to test the web view.
So optionally Enable the javascript handle
navigate events load HTML pages content.
This simple process allows
display web content within
the iOS app using WKWebView.
Basically, this web view is more helpful
when your primary application, is a web
application where you want to use the
same features into your application.
Native iOS, on the iPad.
So this will be more useful where you
can, inherit all the features using
this WKWebView and you can just load
the URL and just access the features.
this is, the functionality where,
web developer can develop and, iOS
developer can use, using a WebKit.
let's see how the code
and how we have to create.
basically, this is a iOS one of
the view controller where you
have to import UIKit and WebKit.
In the particular view controller, you
just have to extend a view UI, view
controller, and a script message handler,
the WK script message handler and
where you have to initiate a variable.
And, in the, when view is loading, in
the first time, it'll call the web view
configuration that you have to load where,
use user content controller and add.
So here the self is.
self is the thing where, you have to,
call the current, view controller.
where you have to mention
the name of the application.
and where you have, Later on, you just
have to initialize your web view, how you
have to add and the configuration as well.
So if for example, I take
a url of our conference42.
com slash javascript2024.
I just want to load this url inside the
native app That we can do it using this
request and URL request, where you have
to load all the features and requests.
So these function, basically,
user content, controller, where
you have to, in, where you
have to create and just, pass.
the WK user content controller and in the
did this you just have to Message the WK
script message and here if the if you want
to receive a message and you just have to,
call the message equal to your application
name and just where you can print the,
whatever the message you want to print.
So basically this is an interaction
where JavaScript, that we can,
use for loading the webpages
inside of a native iOS container.
So the next slide is about NFC technology
for seamless transaction, basically
for the kiosk in our, shipping stores
where customer wants to, pay with
their Apple Pay, they can do it.
So basically we designed this
using the predefined libraries that
is provided by Apple and, where
you have to integrate the NFC.
frameworks and, just have to send
the token, the sensitive token
to when some customer wants to
pay at the end of the shipment.
this integration helps a lot.
this is again, does not require any,
team member help in, inside the store.
So this allows users to make secure
transactions and authenticate
their identity by simply tapping
the driver's device on a kiosk.
Apple Pay facilitates contactless
payments, making process fast and secure.
So useful in various sectors like in
retail and transportation healthcare.
These are all the industries where
this NFC technology is used a lot.
Even, I think this uses everybody
knows in, in current, outside
space, so everybody knows.
So how this is more useful.
So next topic is, Bluetooth
for proximity based services.
So basically in our kiosk application,
basically, we use, Bluetooth
services, BLE functionality, and,
where we have to discover our
printers and to, print the receipts.
So we use a Bluetooth technology and we
use an accessory in the iOS where you
have to fetch the particular device,
the Zebra, if it is something like a
Example of a zebra device that we have
we will just fetch that particular
printer and we will connect and These
printers would help to print the receipts.
So basically these proximity
based services like Inside
the store it will be used.
So basically These actions these are
for triggering the print printing the
customer receipts and shipping labels
so So these, these are all ideal for a
service kiosk and even it is useful for,
useful for hotel check ins, healthcare
systems, where the interactions can
initially, initiated automatically.
So this is like a, process
of integrating for a kiosk.
for customer usage is a lot, when team
member assistance is not required and
customer usage is a lot where we have to
use a proximity services, is required.
next thing is, QR code and barcode
scanning for, Contactless interactions.
So basically scanning a QR code
nowadays, like it is very popular.
it's a, every iOS device has a,
it's a built in camera where, it
is a capability to scan QR codes
and barcodes for contactless ways
for user to interact with kiosk.
So easy to, and also if.
If it is a more faster system where we
can integrate third party scanners, the
third party scanners gives more, more
faster and it will be more accurate scans
where we can do that using the libraries
provided by the third party suppliers.
That is also doable for
kiosk implementation.
and, the currently the kiosks are
like using a lot in the airports for
ticket scanning and product information
retrieval and contactless check ins.
as I mentioned, it is, Used in the
different sectors retail healthcare
and transportation sector So when
coming to the qr code creation and
barcode creation the barcode creation
will be happen on there Based on the
business logic under the likewise
The same thing is for QR code.
So basically the creating the strings
when somebody scan the QR code, there
will be a string that will be sent to the
backend and backend gives the response.
That response we will be going to print
or we will going to show to the customer.
so this is something more, useful
for the contactless integration.
so these barcode and QR codes usage
is a lot even in especially in the
movie tickets or in the various
places for a passes and also.
So next topic is payment
integration with Apple Pay.
So this is very booming thing in United
States or everywhere and overall the
Overall all the countries so apple pay is
consumed a lot like, you know for secure
contactless transactions using face id
and touch id This is also integrated
and In our Self serve kiosk, so this
is Reducing risk of both business and
customers like this is a good solution.
for Consumers retailers business
holders and customers are everybody
in the industry so Common use cases.
This is also helped a lot this
technology in the restaurants and public
transportation ticket purchases so in
our applications, when we You Involved
in coming to the coding part in our iOS
native library where we have to Use the
predefined libraries provided by apple
and we just have to integrate passing
our sensitive access tokens and all
the next thing custom ios apps
for kiosk so Basically based
on the business requirement.
So every industry has their own
own way of serving people so
It is based on the requirement.
We just have to Do a custom solution using
ios and based on The devices that we're
going to control in the enterprise level
so the We can develop the ios apps to
create a specific kiosk experience that
integrate with back end systems like crm
erp and customer loyalty programs if we
If somebody goes to the example to the
casino or they have a membership they can
just you know Swipe the card and just can
check their points and all same thing.
This loyalty is applied Lte
programs are applied everywhere.
So basically these kiosks are helpful and
we just have to create them library and
just, we just have to manage what, based
on the business requirement, how the, how
their business want to serve the people.
So these features like, tap to pay,
push notification, digital receipt,
enhancing self service experience.
This is all the, so many advantages.
using the iOS space so custom apps
can offer multi ingredient support.
personalized interactions, user friendly
interfaces for better engagement.
Yeah.
Next slide.
Use cases of kiosk for
various, industries.
Basically, these kiosks in a retail
sector, the customers can browse,
scan and purchase products, without
physical contact and stream,
streamlining the shopping experience.
basically, this, in retail
industry, the customers are more.
And, the service, of service of
customers, like giving a best if
they are waiting on the lines.
So it will be a, big
headache for the store.
so it, it depends.
It is a huge traffic.
It will be a, more wait time.
Customer satisfaction is very less.
If it is a self service kiosk,
so they can come and shop around
and just scan their stuff and go.
As, easy so in the retail
industry, the, the satisfaction
of the customer will be more.
So now everybody like in the outside,
all the stores, retail stores, so
reducing the human, power and just
increasing the kiosk where, serving
the people is very better way.
in the healthcare, these kiosks
are, helpful for patient check in.
If they can go and just enter
their confirmation, they can check
in themselves, and the technician
would know the patient is here.
And, without asking and just,
checking with the, whatever the store,
representative or the, lab technician.
In the transportation industry where,
in the, in airports and transit systems
use kiosks for contact solicitating.
So boarding pass retrieval
and, Journey planning.
So basically that would help.
So in the hospitality hotels use kiosk
for guest check ins, room selection,
contactless payments and improving
efficiency and guest satisfaction.
So MDM tools for easy device management.
Basically in our space we use MDM to
manage our enterprise mobile applications
to Install on our enterprise devices.
So these MDMs, tools are allow
business manage and update I was
remotely ensuring smooth operations.
because we will, Manage by pushing
from our MDM console without
asking the team member or the store
representative to install app or
update the app and Take care the iOS
updates and also we just use MDM too.
This is very helpful and even in
the low staffed areas This would
be useful and small Fixes that
we can perform over the MDM tool.
So basically if something stuck, we
can just remove, reboot, over the MDM
tool, that would be helpful managing
remotely instead of, somebody going
there and checking what happens.
So these tools are, we always
track the devices when it is on
online and it will go to offline.
So MDM tools can push software
updates, monitor performance
and security compliance across
large networks of kiosks.
So ideal for kiosks with multiple kiosks
in different locations, ensuring seamless
and secure service across all points.
The main more advantages using MDM
is, in my experience, So if something
happens, if the device is not
responding, or if we know this particular
location ID, we can just track the
particular serial number of the device.
And we can see if the device
is interacting correctly or
not, we can check the logs.
And, that way without asking the customer,
we can just help, over creating if
somebody create the ticket and just, we
can just, fix as, as soon as possible.
This will be a very convenient solution.
So there is so many tools outside
where, MDM solutions, available
for enterprise, mobile devices.
So especially for iOS, is.
helps a lot.
these are all that.
Yeah.
this is all about I'm going to share.
today.
basically, I just want to let everybody
know that, using iOS devices and creating
business solutions For contactless
integration would be a, going to be
a greater deal in the near future.
and also we can gain more
customer satisfaction and also
it will be helpful for everybody.
In the, pre pandemic situation
and a pandemic situation.
So where these, interaction is
not required, with the people.
So thank you, for giving this
opportunity and thanks for joining
everyone conference 42 JavaScript, 2024.
Thank you.