Hello everyone.
Good morning, good afternoon,
good evening, depending on
where you are joining from.
My name is Dne j Prakash, and I'm a senior
application developer at Address Calls.
It's a real pleasure to be here
at Count 42 JavaScript 2025 track.
I'm really excited to speak about
this topic, API, integration with
JavaScript, scalable, secure,
and a future ready system.
Over the last few years, a P have
become the backbone of modern software.
Connecting the applications, platforms,
and users more seamlessly than ever.
But as systems keep growing and
getting more complex, making sure these
APIs are integrated in a way that's
scalable, secure, and ready for the
future has become a real challenge.
Today I will be sharing some practical
strategies for building a Level
API, integrations, using JavaScript
approaches that can help your system
handle skill, maintain security, and
stay adaptable for what's coming next.
The A PS driven visual transformation.
That means APOs have come a long way
from being just simple data connectors.
Today they serve as the backbone
of modern digital ecosystem in
our JavaScript driven world.
APIs, orchestrate microservices,
facilitator, real time data
exchange, and integrate diverse
cloud platforms effortlessly.
In this session, I'll share a
data driven blueprint for building
an enterprise grade API systems.
System that's not only scalable unsecured,
but also agile enough to keep a pace with
constantly evolving technology landscapes.
In our today's journey, we'll
start by looking at restful API
architecture, understanding the
core principles and why it remains
the backbone of modern development.
Then we'll compare API paradigms
rest, so GraphQL and even some hybrid
approaches to understand each makes sense.
From there, we will dive into.
From there, we'll drive into the
middleware solutions exploring how modern
platforms simplify integration complexity
and a isolates enterprise connectivity.
Next, we'll cover the security
framework, focusing on what API
gateways and how a layered defense
help protector critical data.
We'll then walk through some production
best practices and that ensures
the reliability per performance
and a great developer experience.
Once your API go live.
And finally we'll look ahead at the
future trends, including even driven
architecture and ER assisted testing to
see where the industry is headed next.
So by the end of this session, you
will have a complete end-to-end
view of how to design secure and
a future proof your API ecosystem.
Why restful API dominates.
Let's talk about the why Restful
API continues to dominate
the modern API landscape.
Even with the rise of newer
technologies like GraphQL and GRPC,
first and foremost, rest is simple.
It's uses standard HTP protocol methods
like get put post and delete, which every
developer is aware of it and understands
that simplicity makes it easier to build,
test, and scale applications quickly.
Test APAs are also stateless, which
means each request contains all
the information the server needs.
This makes them highly scalable,
perfect for cloud native
and a distributed systems.
There is also a massive ecosystem behind
rest because it's been around for so long.
There are countless tools, frameworks,
and libraries that support across
every language and platform.
Tell.
Now we spoke about why API dominates.
Now we'll see what are the
architecture benefits of it, which
is scalability, interoperability.
Flexibility and performance.
Let's compare the three A P paradigms,
which is rest soap, GraphQL, to
understand the ENT and trade offs.
Let's start with the rest.
It's resource based, lightweight
and widely rafted it.
It mainly uses a JSON and for
data exchange and works great
for web mobile applications.
Its stateless design also
makes it easy to scale.
On the other hand.
SOAP is more traditional
protocol based approach.
It's heavier because it lays on XML
and as a step may say structures.
However, it's still used in the
enterprise and legacy systems where
reliability and builtin security like
wwe, service security are crucial.
Then we have a GraphQL, the
newer query based model.
Unlike rest, you get fixed data
from each endpoint graph, queue led.
Client specify exactly what data
they need, no more, no less.
That makes it very efficient for
modern applications that handle
complex or nest data structures.
In short, rest is simple and scalable.
So is a robust but heavy.
Now, graphic is flexible and modern.
The best choice really depends
on your projects context
and needs, when to choose.
And approaches now that we have
compared rest, soap and graph, let's
talk about when to choose each one.
In a real world scenarios, SOAP still
matters, especially in industries.
Security really takes a key role.
Reliability and compliance
on non-negotiable.
Think about banking,
healthcare, government systems.
These environments play on soap
because it enforce strict standards
like web service, security.
And support reliable messaging and
formal contracts between the services.
So even though REST dominates most
modern web APIs, SOAP continues to be
the backbone for a mission critical
and regulated workflows that can't
afford a failure or inconsistency.
On the other hand, we have a graph
QS rise, particularly in the modern
JavaScript world, frontend applications.
GraphQL gives the client.
Fine grain control over
exactly what they really need.
Reducing the number of round trips
to the server that makes it ideal for
mobile applications where performance
and a bandwidth efficiency are key.
Instead of fetching
too much or too little.
Data GraphQL allows you to get
precisely what's required, which
translates directly into faster,
more responsive user experience.
So to summarize, SOAP is still the choice.
For a strict enterprise
grade transactions, rest fits
the most general purpose.
APIs and graph cure shines when
you need a flexible, efficient
data fetching, especially in a
modern web and mobile applications.
Middleware platforms reducing
integration complexity.
How was it doing?
As organization build more and more
APIs and connect more systems together?
One of the biggest challenge they
face is integration complexity.
Traditionally integrating multiple
system meant writing, a lot of
custom code, dealing with different
data formats, maintaining fragile
connections and between services.
Middleware platforms have
completely changed the landscape.
These platforms have come with a visual
tools and a prebuilt connectors, for
example, to say connectors to Salesforce,
S-A-P-A-W-S, or databases, which can
reduce integration time by nearly a.
Instead of spending weeks, months,
coding, point to point integrations,
teams can now configure, map and
deploy connections through intuitive
interfaces, and it's just not just
about the speed that I'm talking about.
These enterprise middleware platforms
also provide elastic scalability
to handle reading workloads and
real time monitoring to ensure the
reliability and the performance.
In other words, middleware has turned
integration from a painful manual
process into a strategic exercise
focused on configuration and optimization
rather than a raw development effort.
Key middleware capabilities.
Now let's look let's look some of the
key capabilities that make a modern
middleware platform so powerful.
Firstly, a pre-built connectors, the.
Platforms come with an extensive
libraries of ready to use integrations,
for example, connected to connect
us to Salesforce and SAPA Ws, or
databases, which I mentioned earlier.
These eliminates a reputative
coding and dramatically accelerates
time to market because teams can
focus on configurations rather than
building the code from scratch.
Next, elastic scalability, middleware
platforms automatically scale up or down
based on the traffic or seasonal demand.
So whether it's an end of year sales
spike or an unexpected surge of
traffic on the API calls the system
maintenance consistent performance
without a manual tuning, then we
have a real time monitoring system.
These tools provided deep observability
tracking metrics, logs, and
alerts across distributed systems.
That means team can detect the
issues way ahead and fix them
before they impact the users.
And finally, visual design tools.
This is where the low
code revolution comes in.
Middleware now allows developers and
even a technical business users to
design, test, and deploy integration
workflows visually with a minimal coding.
This tool bridges a gap between
a technical and non-technical
teams making an integration,
a shared collaborative effort.
All together, these capabilities turn a
middleware into a true integration engine.
Simplifying complexity while
boosting speed, scalability and
reliability, security that plays
a non-negotiable foundation.
Now, let's talk about something
that's ab absolutely non-negotiable
in any API ecosystem.
Secure API ecosystem too often,
security is as afterthought.
That means we all think that we can
build in security later in time.
Once a P is all complete design and
double, but that's really wrong.
Something.
That which really need to take it at the
first priority than being at the end.
But in reality it has.
It has to be designed in every layer
of your a p architecture from day one.
When we combine measures like what for
security authentication, robust API
gateways for managing and filtering
your traffic and comprehensive
lifecycle management to track
every stage from the deployment and
deprecation, we can dramatically
reduce endpoint vulnerabilities.
These layers work together to protect
sensitive data, ensure regulatory
complaints, and maintain trust,
especially in the industries like
finance, healthcare, or government else.
Rest rest on without its
skill, performance and
innovations, we don't matter.
Multi-layered security framework,
modern APIs rely on multi-layered
security framework to stay safe.
We use OAuth for secure token based
access API gateways to handle the
rate limiting validations and the
threat detections and lifecycle
management to enforce versioning,
deprecation, and continuous auditing.
Together these layers form a defense
in depth strategy, predicting
against evolving threats while
keeping APIs usable for legitimate
clients production best practices.
When it comes to running an a p in
prod, what do we really need to do?
Following making an A PIA best
pro best followed approaches.
These are the following best practices,
ensures reliability, security,
and a great developer experience.
First is standardizing
pandemic conventions.
Consistent your patterns.
Clear resource hierarchies,
unpredictable endpoints makes an
API easier to understand and foster
for new developers to onboard next.
Rigorous testing that plays
a key role where we can catch
the major defects beforehand.
Automated integration tests,
performance benchmarking and security
vulnerability scans catch issues
before they reach a production,
reducing a downtime under risk.
Finally, a detailed documentation
interacted API explores multi-language
core examples, and a clear visualing log.
Help developers adopt your APIs
quickly, and then user support overhead.
In short, standardization testing
and documentations are the pillars
of producing production ready APIs.
They make your APIs reliable,
secure, and easy to use and scary.
Emerging trends.
Event driven architecture.
What do you mean?
What do you mean by event
driven architecture?
The key, a key trend in modern JavaScript
ecosystem is event driven architectures.
Unlike a traditional request response
models, event driven systems, decouple
services and use a synchronous messaging,
enabling a real time data flows
improve resilience and dynamic scaling.
How does it work?
We all know we, we pub there,
there are ways where you can
just publish it and subscribe it.
When of any of the event or
any change on that state?
So firstly, the event producers
service emits the event whenever
there is a change in the state.
Second message Brokers tools
like Kafka topic, rapid mq.
Route these events to
the right subscribers.
Event consumers, other services react
independently to the events they
care about without tight coupling.
By adopting these patterns,
system can respond.
In a real time scale, dynamically
under load and isolate of failures,
making an architecture more robust
and flexible for modern applications.
Now coming to the AI assisted testing
and a Future innovations, the biggest,
the big wave in API development and
an operations is AI assisted testing.
And it's already reshaping how we
ensure a quality and a reliability.
We are now seeing a machine learning,
models that automatically generate test
cases, predict potential failure points
and optimize the coverage strategies.
This means less manual testing effort,
faster release cycles, and higher
bug detection rates, especially in
a complex multi-service integrations
where human testing alone can't keep up.
Looking ahead, we are moving
towards even smarter systems.
Imagine a self feeling, APIs that
automatically adapt to failures
or intelligent rate limiting that
are just based on usage behavior
rather than fixed thresholds.
We also see a automated security patching
and predictive performance optimization
where AI can identify potential
bottlenecks before the impact users.
In short, AI isn't just.
Helping US test better.
It's redefining how APIs evolve, recover,
and optimize themselves in real time.
Building a future ready API Systems.
To wrap up my talk, let's look at what
it takes to build a future ready api.
API System First Skill takes
the first priority designed
for growth from day one use.
Stateless architecture, elastic
infrastructure, so your APIs can
scale seamlessly as demand increase.
Secondly, security by design.
Like I said, security takes a key role.
Make security an integral part of
every stage of the API lifecycle.
Implement multi-layered protections
and proactive vulnerability
management and stay ahead of threats.
And finally, the future
adapt, adaptability.
Stay competitive by embracing emerging
patterns like event driven architecture
and AI assisted tool testing.
These innovations will shape how
API APIs evolve and interact in
the ES ahead with these strategies.
Strategies you are ready to design and
operate APIs that are scalable, secure,
and interoperable and resilient, even
as technology continues to change.
I would like to conclude
my talk with the statement.
The APIs we build today are
the connections that powers
tomorrow's innovation.
Let's design them not just to
function, but to evolve, adapt,
and inspire what comes next.
Thank you for listening to me for.