Hello and warm welcome.
I'm Courtney Otto and I'm excited
to talk to you today about one of
my favorite topics, gamification.
Now we're going to see how gamification
can transform your react applications
into immersive and engaging experiences.
Now, when we talk about gamification,
it's more than just points and badges.
It's really about how we create
these applications to make users
want to come back for more.
Now think about the last app
that you couldn't stop using.
It had probably gamification elements
that you kept, that kept you hooked.
Apps like Starbucks, Duolingo, Headspace.
These take what might otherwise be
routine or even difficult tasks,
ordering coffee, learning a new
language, or managing anxiety, and
really making them a bit more enjoyable
by adding in these gamified elements.
So whether it's rewards for purchases,
progress tracking or daily challenges.
These features really do tap
into our desire for achievement
and keep us coming back.
Now, React's component based architecture
makes it a natural fit for building
these kinds of gamified experiences.
It's flexible, it's efficient, and it
lets us create reusable, interactive
components that elevate user engagement.
Now throughout today's session,
we're going to explore how you can
leverage React to build apps that
are not only functional, but are
also really fun and truly engaging.
And before we jump in, let me
introduce myself real quick.
I'm Courtney Yato, and I'm currently
a developer advocate at Esri, a
company that specializes in geographic
information systems, or GIS for short.
Before joining Esri, I was a high
school math and computer science
teacher, and I really got to see
firsthand how gamification can
motivate students in the classroom.
For my master's project, I focused on how
technology can enhance learning, and I
explored how gamified digital experiences
can really increase engagement.
As a developer advocate, I have been
applying some of those gamification
principles to the world of development.
Particularly in GIS technology.
And one of my goals is to help
developers understand really how
powerful gamification can be, not
just in education, but really in
all different kinds of applications.
So our agenda for today, throughout
the next bit, I'm going to
take us through five different
gamification principles, specifically
tailored for react applications.
And for each principle, I'll
show a real world example of
how this has been implemented.
So Then to make things interactive,
I've prepared a mini workshop, like
coding demo, where we're going to
build a simple gamified app together.
And if you'd like to follow
along with that in a bit, you
can find the starter code here.
Now that we've set the stage for a
discussion, let's go ahead and jump into
the first principle of gamification.
Now this acronym that I came up
with, GAMES, The G in the game
stands for Gamify Components.
These are the core elements
that turn ordinary tasks into
really engaging experiences.
Gamify Components can be anything
from experience bars to badges,
progress tracking, or even
rewards for completing tasks.
These elements do create a sense
of achievement, motivating users
to continue engaging with the app.
Now let's look at how this concept
comes to life in an app like Codecademy.
A Codecademy uses several
gamified elements to drive
user engagement and motivation.
XP points reward users for completing
lessons, providing instant feedback,
and incentivizing progress.
Badges mark milestones, visually
representing achievements, while
progress bars track advancement
through different courses.
Additionally, weekly target trackers
encourage consistency by setting
measurable goals using visual
cues to help users stay focused.
Now these elements are nicely
integrated to enhance the learning
experience and maintain user motivation.
All right, so next we're going
to move on to the letter A, and A
stands for Advanced State Management.
Now, as apps grow in their complexity,
keeping track of state across multiple
components really can get a bit tricky.
So this is where React's
Context API shines.
It allows for us to manage state
globally and ensures consistency
throughout the application.
So So by using centralized state
management, we can handle things
like user progress, settings, theme
changes, et cetera, in a scalable
and really maintainable way.
Now let's go ahead and see how an app like
Headspace uses advanced state management
to create a seamless user experience.
Headspace uses React's Context API to
centrally manage the theme UI components
dynamically, The context provider
encapsulates styling, all the styling
for the properties for the various UI
elements like the buttons, the cards,
progress bars, which really enables
the consistency and the scalability
of the styling across the application.
Now, this approach allows for
theme variations and responsive
design changes throughout the
app without repetitive code.
All right, now let's move
on to the M and games.
The M stands for memoization, and
the key to this really is the key
to ensuring our apps run smoothly.
So memoization helps us
prevent unnecessary re renders,
improving performance, especially
in dynamic applications.
Now, looking ahead, and this
is really where that modern
optimization comes into play.
The new React compiler, which is
currently in beta, will take this further
by automatically optimizing our apps.
without the need for manual memoization.
So we'll analyze component trees and
apply performance improvements seamlessly.
Now a good example of using memoization
is Grammarly, where it is strategically
employed in the suggestions section
to enhance the efficiency of the
real time analysis of the text.
The component responsible for rendering
suggestions is wrapped with React
Memo, which ensures that it only re
renders when they, when there really
are necessary, when there are changes to
the prop, specifically the typed input.
Now, by doing this, Grammarly maintains
high performance as it delivers instant
feedback and suggestions, which really are
crucial for a seamless user experience.
All right, onto the E in games.
Now the E in games stands for efficient
rendering, which really is all about
the right components at the right time.
So with React Lazy and Suspense,
we can load components on demand,
reducing the initial load time and
really improving the performance.
Now efficient rendering techniques
can help us manage heavy assets or
really complex components in a way
that doesn't block the user experience.
So let's go ahead and see how an app
like Duolingo uses these techniques
to deliver smooth animations.
In Duolingo, efficient rendering
is achieved through react suspense
component, which handles the
loading of character animations.
So suspense ensures that animations
only render once when they are
fully loaded, preventing for the
that incomplete or laggy visuals
during different interactions.
All right, let's move on
to the final letter S.
S stands for social interaction,
which brings a new dimension
of engagement to apps.
Adding social features allows
users to do things like share
achievements, compute with each other,
and feel this sense of community.
So social interaction encourages
users to return not just for
the individual rewards, but also
for the fun of the competition.
So let's go ahead and see how Duolingo
does this exceptionally well with their
leaderboard and social sharing features.
For social interaction, Duolingo
enhances user engagement.
Additionally, Duolingo integrates a
social aspect by allowing users to follow
friends and see their language milestones.
Alright, now before we go on to the
live demo, I want to go through one
application that really encapsulates
the essence of my game's acronym through
each one of the different elements.
Starbucks, primarily built with React.
It uses a progress bar to
visually represent customers
earning stars from purchases.
And React State Management It
dynamically updates this bar,
reflecting real time progress.
Now, challenges within the app
encourages users engagement by offering
bonus stars for specific actions,
like visiting several days in a row.
And these are managed through
React components, ensuring
that progress and rewards are
accurately tracked and updated.
Additionally, seasonal
games are also integrated.
offering prizes from
bonus stars to vacations.
And these utilize react for timely
updates and interactive elements
during promotional periods.
Now the next letter a is advanced state
control and Starbucks effectively utilizes
reacts context API to manage the global
settings such as locale and currency.
It's approach ensures that regardless of
where in the world the app is accessed,
all of the current or the correct currency
and the language adhere to the preferences
due to the location of the user.
The context API, it allows Starbucks
to centralize state management for
these settings, enabling a consistent
and flawless user experience.
Alright, on to M.
The memoization, Starbucks
does optimize its application
performance by using memoization
through React Memo and Use Memo.
These techniques are useful for caching
data that doesn't change very often, such
as currency formats or menu item prices.
And by preventing the re, by preventing
these like redundant renders,
re renders, Starbucks enhances
the responsiveness of its app.
And it ensures that users experience
a quick and smooth interactions,
even during the high demand periods.
All right, on to the E.
Again, this is efficient rendering
and Starbucks faces the challenge
of managing high volumes of user
interactions, especially during
its fun promotional event times.
the app likely employs React strategies
like lazy loading and suspense to
handle these scenarios efficiently.
using split coding techniques, Starbucks
can load only the necessary pieces of
code depending on the user interactions.
And finally, let's move on
to S, the social elements.
Starbucks does encourage
participants to send gift cards
to their friends through the app.
Additionally, some games users
are encouraged to share their
progress on social media during
those provisional game periods.
Okay, now that we've discussed
the theory behind games, here's
where we get to the fun part.
we get to do some coding together.
For this coding session, we're going to
build a very simple app that will evolve
into something a bit more engaging,
with react and gamification techniques.
So we're going to start small and we're
going to add one little feature for
each of the letter in games, my acronym.
And by the end, we'll have a fun
little gamified app with elements
like experience, and social sharing.
So to kick things off, we're
going to start with this basic
map app that I built in React.
I've set up a new project here using
Vite, and in this project I've cleaned
up the default files a bit, so to
keep things simple, for example,
I deleted the Vite SVG file, and I
emptied out the default styles in app.
css, and I actually just got rid of index.
css.
Now here's what the
project looks like now.
So I have a simple app.
css where I've set the app to have
no predetermined margins or padding.
And then I have a basic app.
jsx where I've imported one
component, which is my map component.
And then of course I
have my map component.
Now inside of this map component,
It uses Esri Leaflet to display
a simple map of Washington, D.
C.
Now, Esri Leaflet is, if you're
unfamiliar, it's a lightweight
set of plugins that allows
you to easily integrate maps
using ArcGIS basemap styles.
it really opens up the space for
you to use different ArcGIS styles.
It also actually allows you
to use many other different
ArcGIS capabilities as well.
Now in this map component, I first use the
use rough hook to store the map instance.
And this ensures that the map is
initialized only once and doesn't
get like rein initialized every
time that the component re renders.
By checking if, the map ref is null,
we do ensure that the map is created
only on the components first mount
next, inside the use effect hook.
I initialize the map when
the component first renders.
And the map, like I said, is
centered on Washington, D.
C.
with a set latitude and
longitude, as we can see here.
Now, Leaflet does go
latitude, comma, longitude.
Other mapping libraries do
longitude, comma, latitude.
Just depends.
Now, I will then add the
ArcGIS community base map here.
To the map, and I, in order to do
that, I have to use the vector basemap
layer method from Esri leaflet.
And the API key required to access the
ArcGIS services is securely retrieved
from the environment variable, Vite
ArcGIS API key, using the import.
meta.
env.
So I have my API key
stored in my env file.
And I pass this API key as a token
to authenticate the request when
adding the base map to the map with
add to and then map ref current.
And finally, I return a div with an
ID of map where the map is rendered.
And the height of this
map, I've set it to 70%.
Of the viewport height to ensure
that it takes up a good portion of
the screen with leaving some room
for our gamified elements below.
At this point, we have a fully
functioning basic map of DC.
And let's go ahead and
run this and check it out.
All right, so you'll see that the map
center, the map centered on Washington DC
here is displayed in our map container.
And yeah, now that we
have our map in place.
We can start incorporating the gamified
elements to enhance our user experience.
Okay, so we're moving on to, the
first letter in our acronym, which
is G Games, our gamified components.
in order to incorporate this,
I'm going to start small.
We're just going to add a
progress bar to our app.
this progress bar will track a user's XP
and give them a sense of, progression.
The concept is pretty simple.
it's really just when the user performs
some action, in this case we're just
going to put in a button, that they'll
then gain some XP or experience points
and the progress bar will fill up.
And once it's filled up, it will
refresh itself, like leveling up.
Alright, so in order to build this,
we're going to start with a very basic
progress bar component in our app.
And inside of this component, the
progress bar will take in one prop.
And that will be the current
XP, or the user's score.
Now, we can calculate the
percentage, filled by calculating
the XP, out of the max XP, which
in this case is going to be 100.
And we'll use that value to set the
width of the inner, what will be a div.
and this will visually
represent the progress.
So after every 100 XP,
We'll have it, reset.
So next, we'll use a simple HTML
structure for our progress bar.
And this'll contain, this'll be
two different divs that we'll use.
One for the border, and one to
show progress with a green filling.
And next in my app, JSX, I'm going
to import the progress bar component.
and also to keep track of the user's
XP value, we'll need to use states.
So I'll set the initial state to
zero, and then I'll add a simple
click handler to update the XP.
And when we click on the button,
we'll add 10 XP each time.
Now, below the map, I need to make
sure I display this button and
give it the click functionality.
And I will also display
the current XP value and my
progress bar with the XP prop.
Now let's go ahead and test this out.
When we click gain XP, the button,
we should see the XP increase.
And the progress bar will fill
up accordingly, resetting after
every 100 experience points.
Now this is a really simple example
of a Gamify component, but even with
this basic mechanic, users can feel
a greater sense of engagement through
the progress that they're making.
gaining.
Now to add more value to this, especially
in a map app like this, I would say you
could tie this kind of functionality
to locations that, say, maybe the user
discovers on the map, rewarding them with
some XP for each place that they discover.
So click on a place on the map,
and they gain some XP points.
All right, now that we've added our first
gamified component, the progress bar.
we're going to start thinking
about managing state in a
bit of a more scalable way.
So right now this progress bar is
handled locally using useState,
which is fine for a simple app.
However, as you scale your app and
add more features, say levels, badges,
maybe multiple map styles, sharing
the data across multiple components
will become a little bit tricky.
So this is where advanced state
control is going to come into play.
And we're gonna use React context, API,
and this will allow us to manage the
state globally, making it accessible
across all the different components.
So we're gonna refactor our code.
We'll first start by creating
a new file called Game Context.
And first we use the create
context to create the game context.
And this will let any component
access the global state.
Then we're gonna.
define our initial state for
our application, which is the XP
value set to zero in this case.
Alright, now we're going to the
reducer function, and this is
going to be handling, managing
the state for our experience.
Now, inside of the reducer function,
we're going to have it listen
for two main types of functions.
First, this is going to be
when we increment our XP value.
It's going to preserve the current
state using the spread operator, and
then we're going to update the current
XP by adding the amount provided in the
action payload to the existing XP value.
The second action will be reset
XP, and this will really just
reset the experience, or XP
value, back to the initial state.
And then, finally, we'll have a default,
so any other actions, not recognized,
we'll simply return the current state.
Okay, almost done with our context.
now that we do have the context and
reducer set up, the next step is to
wrap the app in the game provider.
And this is going to make the
global XP state, accessible
to all components in our app.
Okay.
So we'll start by setting
up the GameProvider.
And inside this provider, we
use the UseReducer hook, which
takes two different things.
The Reducer function we created
earlier, and the initial state.
The Reducer, that will help us manage
state transitions based on actions,
like adding XP or resetting the state.
Alright, now next we are going
to wrap the GameContextProvider
around the Children component.
It's passing in state and
dispatch as the value.
And this step is critical to allow
that, access to all of the children, all
components to have access to the state.
All right.
Now in the original version of our app dot
JSX, we were managing the XP using the use
state hook locally, and then we defined a
local XP state and a handle click function
to increment the XP by 10 each time.
And the updated XP was then
passed to the progress bar.
But now we're switching to this
global state management, which
is managed by the game context.
first to do this, we're going to,
instead of useState, we're going
to use useContext, and I'll also
need to import the game context.
Now, we'll use the global state
objects containing the XP.
And the dispatch.
Fun dispatch function, to
trigger state updates through
the context of game context.
Alright, next we'll go ahead and
update the handle click function.
So instead of directly updating the
state with set xp, we dispatch and
action with the increment xp, that
type, and then a payload of 10.
And this is handled by the
reducer endgame context.
All right, finally, we're going to replace
the local XP reference with state dot XP.
Okay, now that we've done all of this,
the final step is to make sure that the
game provider wraps our app component.
So this is important because the game
provider makes the global state available
to all the components within the app.
So we're going to do this by
going to the main entry point of
our app, which is main dot JSX.
I'm going to wrap the app
component in the game provider.
All right, so in summary, now that we've
done all of this, it's going to allow us
to seamlessly pass XP to any component
in our application that needs it.
all right, so now that we've
got our foundation with gamified
components and advanced state
control, we're going to move on to M.
So the M, as we learned earlier,
is membozation, and this focuses
on optimizing the performance.
So I'm going to do this
in my progress bar.
And again, this will prevent any
unnecessary re renders from happening.
So in my progress bar component, I'm
going to bring in Memo, React Memo,
and then wrap the component in Memo.
So it will only re render
when the XP prop changes.
This really is a simple
way to boost performance.
components.
And while it might really have a big
impact in a small app like this, it
really would be essential in larger ones.
For instance, if we add a bunch
more features like leaderboards,
animations, multiplayer interactions,
memoization can be really valuable.
And of course, as we learned earlier,
react recently introduced the react
compiler, which will automatically
optimize these components.
So with a little bit of configuration
there, all, we won't have to go in and
manually use this react memo anymore.
Now onto the E, which it
stands for efficient rendering.
And this is where we look at loading
different components more efficiently,
as the user interacts with the app.
So again, we're going to do this,
with one key strategy, which is
lazily loading different components.
And this really just means that
we only load them when they're
needed rather than all up front.
and it does help with some code
splitting, improving load times and
that kind of thing in larger apps.
Now for our example, we're going to just
lazily load our progress bar, just to
show kind of the functionality of this.
So to do this, I'll use React Lazy to
dynamically import the progress bar.
However, React won't know to actually, it
won't know what to display while loading.
So we will need to import suspense and
wrap the progress bar in a suspense
component as well and show a fallback.
And this fallback will be whatever
shows while the progress bar is loading.
So for instance, I'm going to go ahead
and say loading progress bar here.
So when we run the app, you'll
see the loading progress bar.
message briefly as React fetches
the component asynchronously.
We can see it there.
All right.
Finally, we're on to S.
So now that we've optimized our app's
performance, it's time to bring in
a little bit of social interaction.
Now this step adds some fun engagement
by allowing users to share their
progress with friends on social media.
So to achieve this, I'm going to
create a social share component.
And this will let users share
their XP on X, or formerly Twitter.
Okay, so the component accepts XP
as a prop, representing, again,
the experience of the user.
And this will be dynamically
inserted into the social media post.
So inside the component, we will
define a shareOnX function, and that
will generate a URL That will, be pre
filled with the message for X, and
it will also open it in a new window.
Alright, so next we're going to add a
Share on X button that when clicked,
it's going to call our function prompting
the user to share their experience.
finally, we are going to
export the component, and then
we're going to integrate it.
So we import the social
share component into our app.
jsx.
We're going to render it just below the
progress bar, and of course we're going
to pass in the XP prop with that as well.
Okay.
Let's go ahead and open up
our app and test that out.
Okay, clicking on the share button
here, we see that X comes up, and
it's filled with my experience points.
Awesome.
Okay, so we've covered the games
framework, adding features like
XP tracking, progress bars,
social sharing and optimizing,
the performance, state management.
And so all of these techniques are
really, again, essential as our app grows.
to wrap things up, I've compiled
some resources for you guys.
So we've got documentation
for the links for React, Ezri
Leaflet, and the React Compiler.
and I've also got some links here to
the code for the demo that we just
did, the starter and final versions.
So to access these links, you
can use the PDF version of these
slides at this QR code here.
And that's all I've
got for you guys today.
So thank you guys for joining.
I really hope that you feel inspired
to add some kind of gamification.
into your applications.
Thanks and happy coding.