Let's start this talk
by setting the scene.
You're a JavaScript developer.
Maybe you're working by yourself, maybe
you're working with a team, or maybe
you're even leading a team, and your
goal is to use AI for real impact.
Now the challenge is, do we
really know what that means?
How do you use AI for real impact?
What does it mean to use AI effectively
and what are the measurable benefits
that we're expecting to achieve here
before we actually achieve our goal?
We have to have a vision of how we're
gonna use AI in order to be effective.
And once we understand that, the
next step is to think about those
hallucinations that we all suffer
from, and we have to figure out what
are the best practices that we need to
agree on in order to make sure that AI
is accurate enough to be trustworthy.
Because our teammates aren't gonna
buy into it, they're not gonna wanna
use ai, even if we promise them real
impact, unless it actually works well.
Hi, my name is Sharon Nik.
I'm Senior developer Experience and
API content writer in Cloudinary.
And tonight we're talk, gonna
talk about making API, docs and AI
work together, improving context
accuracy and agentic coding in IDE.
I hope you enjoy this talk
and I hope you find it useful.
Over the past year, I've had
what I can only describe as
a transformative experience.
I was on a team, a very large
team in Cloudinary that worked on
turning Cloudinary APIs into model
context, protocol MCP servers.
That process completely reshaped
how I think about documentation
accuracy and where AI truly
fits in a developer's workflow.
So today I wanna share the takeaways
that changed my way of thinking.
First of all, if we set up our environment
correctly, we don't have to leave the IDE.
We can code, we can search docs, and we
can apply other tools from our tech stack
from directly within the IDE without
having to leave it and without having to
change context to do all of those tasks
that we used to have to juggle with.
I also learned that the big problem
holding AI back is not only accuracy.
But the context that we provide ai,
we'll talk about that a bit more later.
And finally, I discovered the magic that
happens when we connect documentation
directly to AI clients in the IDE.
So onto our first question of the night.
What does using AI
effectively actually mean?
Our talk is about using AI within the IDE.
So from now on, we're gonna
call that using the LLM client.
The LLM client is the AI inside
the IDE that reads documentation
reasons and performs actions.
And we're gonna talk about two use cases.
I think the central two use cases that
you can actually perform within your IDE.
The first is code
generation and refactoring.
And this is of course when you're working
in your IDE and you have your AI panel
open and you ask the LLM client to
please create code for you or generate
code for you that does X, y, and Z
for your app that you're working on.
And the second use case is
to actually perform those
agentic tasks within your IDE.
And this is the AI executing
actions like uploading assets
or configuring environments.
Something that's actually more like on
the backend or more like configuration
that you wouldn't do within your program,
but you would have to leave your IDE
in order to do it somewhere else.
So instead of having to leave and do
this elsewhere, we're gonna use MCP
servers to handle authentication,
validation, and execution so that the
AI can actually act safely for you.
So when we created the MCP servers for
cloudinary, our goal was simple to enable
ides like cursor, cloud code, and VS.
Code copilot.
Not just to suggest code, but to also
use cloudinary directly managing images
and videos, adding metadata, configuring
environments, and automating workflows.
So now that we understand how to
actually use AI effectively within
the IDE, let's talk about some of the
measurable benefits that we can expect.
So first of all, I'm not gonna go
through all of the statistics here.
You can have a look at it yourself,
but lots and lots of developers are
using APIs, third party APIs in order
to perform tasks within their apps.
And the statistics are high on that.
So from these statistics that we see
all of the APIs being used so heavily
from next to author, to Stripe to
cloudinary, and much, much more.
APIs are the connective tissue that
make modern JavaScript apps work.
And when we use the LM LLM client with the
APIs, we absolutely streamline their use.
In combination with that, let's
look a little bit at what is
happening in AI development.
Developers are saying that
it's speeding up their process.
They're saving time.
They can do the work that they usually
do in a day, in a few hours and.
This is not only for code generation, but
this is also like we described before,
the agentic tools that allow you to
actually perform actions that you would
normally have to leave the IDE to perform.
Now, of course, here comes the caveat.
We've got poor stats on how much
developers distrust API tools.
Only a small share of developers,
just 3.8% report experiencing low
hallucination and high confidence.
So this is really not so happy yet.
We need to find ways in order to boost
the confidence and boost the accuracy.
Also AI agents are still a minority.
People are not catching on
yet to using MCP servers.
And you could look at the stats
about how many developers are
using these agents already.
And you can see that maybe that has to do
with some of their worries on accuracy,
some of their worries about data security.
And this shows that we're still not
using AI agents and we're still not
utilizing AI to its full benefit.
Finally, the data is clear that
missing context is the problem.
Hallucinations are not the root problem.
It's just a symptom, and the core
problem is that we're missing context.
The AI doesn't know the
details of my project.
It doesn't know the
details of my architecture.
Naming conventions.
The product that I'm using, the API
documented rules and it just guesses
every time it makes a guess and it's
hallucinating and it erodes the trust.
So we can look at this negatively or
we can say that this is an opportunity.
We have an opportunity because
we know that once we get our
engineers to have high confidence,
the stats on enjoying and.
Improving and how AI
makes jobs more enjoyable.
All these stats go up.
Confidence creates adoption.
And the lesson is the better the context,
the better the LLM client performs and the
easier it is to get buy-in from the team.
So how are we gonna do that?
How are we gonna improve
context within our LLM client?
The solution is documentation in the past.
Documentation used to give developers
what they needed instructions for
setup code, snippets, and examples.
And now our LLM clients are gonna
consume them right inside the IDE.
The LLM client needs documentation as
its source of truth, just the way we
do reading them, interpreting them, and
using them to figure out what to do next.
And without them, the LLM
is working a bit blindly.
So what best practices that we should
agree on in order to make sure that AI
is accurate enough to be trustworthy?
The best practices that we're gonna
talk about apply to all of these APIs,
auth O Firebase, super base, slack,
Shopify, Cloudinary, and many others.
We're going to use Cloudinary for the
purposes of demonstration, and we're gonna
revisit the other APIs at the end just
to review what you could do with them.
So we're gonna start with the basics of
just adding Cloudinary MCP servers into.
My id, I'm gonna show this to you in
cursor, but of course you can go to
any of the other IDs and you can look
up their documentation and see how to
add MCPP servers in those IDs as well.
So I'm gonna copy and paste.
These are three of Cloudinary for
remote MCP servers that are offered.
And I'm going to copy this code
and I'm gonna jump into the IDE.
It's a cursor.
I'm going to open cursor settings.
I'm gonna open tools and cps
and I'm gonna add custom MCP.
And right within these two brackets,
I'm gonna the code save it.
And if you look at the
co cursor settings, I'm.
C I'm connected.
Now I'm connecting to these three
servers, but I need to authenticate,
so I'm gonna click on this, which
reroutes me to my application.
Login.
I'm gonna log in.
I'm gonna choose my cloud name, my
product environment, gonna accept
access, and now I'm connected.
Okay, I am gonna do the same
authentication for the others,
and now all my tools are enabled.
Great.
So once that's done, I can go ahead
and dogen tasks right within my IDE.
Okay.
Back to the slides.
What's the next thing?
Next?
I'm gonna reference the IPEs
doc site in my ip, in my IDE.
So we're gonna do this for Cloudinary.
We're gonna go to cursor settings,
indexing in docs, and we're going
to add the URL for Cloudinary
documentation to the docs in the IDE.
And every time I make a request,
I'm going to remember to add
context and select those docs.
So let's see how this
is done within the IDE.
Okay, so we're already in settings.
So now let's just click indexing in docs.
Let's go to Add Doc, and we're gonna
type in Cloudinary documentation.
Let's call this Cloudinary
Docs and we're gonna confirm.
So the next best practice that we're
gonna talk about is contact seven.
Contact seven provides an MCP server
that indexes the code snippets and
examples from the API documentation.
This means that your LLM client has
access to all of those examples and
therefore its auto complete and generated
code are accurate, derived from the
documentation and not from guesses.
So not all products are yet
indexed in context seven.
So when you do work within a certain
API just make sure that your.
Product is already registered
together with context seven.
And don't underestimate your influence.
If users really want to use context,
seven APIs will start considering that
and using context seven more and more.
So how to add context seven in cursor.
What you're gonna do is you're gonna
go to cursor settings again, you're
going to go to tools and integrations,
and you're going to add the MCP server
for context seven to that M-C-P-J-S-N
file that we saw before and since we've
already had a chance to add MCP servers.
So let's not demonstrate adding the
contact seven one and just assume
that you can do that on your own.
Copying and pasting this code here.
Okay, so what comes after contact?
Seven.
Tip number four.
Last but not least, is leveraging rules.
Rules.
Files are how we move from AI that
guesses to AI that follows your standards.
In cursor there MDC files, but the
same concept exists in other IDs.
For example, JetBrains uses MD and VS.
Code uses Jason or yaml.
The format doesn't really matter.
It's just the principle that does.
These are short example rich rules that
your LLM client reads before it writes.
So every suggestion it makes, fits
your conventions and runs correctly.
Some APIs already provide rules
or compatibility references
that you can use right away.
For example, Cloudinary includes a
document that explains how to create
transformations correctly, including
how the order of transformation
parameters affects the results and
which combinations are invalid.
You can also create your own rules
files to help your LLM client perform
tasks independently, for instance.
In our docs as code setup, we created
a rules file that teaches the LLM
client how to create a new markdown
page, migrate an article into it,
and apply all the required formatting
and configuration automatically.
Of course, the human eye has to
review all that and make sure that
everything's been done correctly.
So let's talk about how to do it.
If you've got a rules file that's been
provided by the API, you could simply
add it to the documentation, just like
we did with the Cloudinary General Docs.
For example, we've got the
Cloudinary transformation
Rules file which is an MD file.
And you can just add it
the same way we did before.
So I'm not gonna show it
to you in the IDE again.
You'll go to cursor settings,
indexing and documentation.
In the doc section, you'll add the doc and
you'll enter the name of the rules file.
We'll see a little bit later how when
we actually see an actual example.
Every time we ask for a prompt,
we're going to add context and
we're gonna add that particular
doc to the request that we make.
Okay.
Now even more powerful is that you
can create your own rules file.
In cursor you're going to put your rules
file in the doc cursor rules folder,
and if you want it to be project wide,
you'll just put it in the doc cursor file.
It's gotta be formatted as a markdown
with clear headings plus lightweight
examples that the model can copy.
Okay, so when you are creating your rules
file, here are a few tips and tricks.
When writing rules think in terms of
the four Cs compatibility note, which
parameters, SDKs or ais play well together
conventions Explain what your name naming
folder or architecture standards are.
Constraints, meaning what
the AI must never do.
For example, exposing secrets or
calling admin APIs from the browser.
And canon meaning copy, give it
short, correct examples and code
snippets that the model can be used
in other scenarios and guardrails.
Give the idea a range of what it
can or can't do, what it always
should do or should never, ever do.
Here are a few cloudinary examples.
We always want format auto and quality
auto to be applied so that our images
are always delivered optimized.
We want our text overlays to
always look legible, and so we're
going to give it a standard.
We're gonna give it instructions
for how we want that formatted.
We're going to forbid GFE to be used
with CPAD because those are incompatible.
And with this, I have safeguarded
my code that gets generated by the
LLM to make sure that I'm not going
to have bugs, that I'm going to
have a really hard time finding.
And finally, maintenance tips, keep
rules short, one to three pages,
review it often and include links
to the official documentation.
Now I'm gonna show you a
rules document that I created.
And we're actually gonna soon see how
we actually apply it in a real use case.
But we can see that some of the
things we talked about are here,
for example, using auto format and
WA quality on all image deliveries.
Here's a new one.
I want my IDE to always.
Apply name transformations.
When I'm transforming images
of a certain type, for example,
hero images or thumbnails.
I don't want it to apply
ad hoc transformations.
I want it to either apply an existing
name transformation, which is like
a template, or if none exists for
that type that I'm requesting.
It should create the name
transformation and then apply that.
In that case and in all subsequent
cases, and so I've got a little
bit of a description here, a little
bit of an explanation of what I'd
like it to do in the case where I'm
transforming images of a certain type.
Yeah, so we'd like G Face to
always be used with sea auto
in order to get the effect.
That is most close to my standards
of cropping, cropping around the
face and an automatic crop that
keeps the main subject in the middle.
Here's my text standards, my
text overlay standards that I
wanted to always keep along with.
A little bit of a example a code
example of how to achieve the
requirements that I set out here.
Okay, so finally here's a
little overview of other ides.
The file extension that you need to
use for the rules, files in those
ides and location that is required for
those rules files can review it on your
own later if if you don't have cursor
and you use one of the other ites.
Now we've made it to our finale.
We're actually gonna go through a
cloudinary use case right within my
IDE, and we're gonna see how results
become more accurate when you've got
all of those best practices in place.
So let's go through the scenario
first, and then we're gonna go into
the IDE and actually implement it.
So first we're gonna genetically upload an
image and then we're gonna use that image.
So Genically uploading it is
going to save me that context.
Switching, I'm staying in the IDE and
using the MCP servers instead of switching
tools and going to the cloudinary console.
So once that image is uploaded,
I'm gonna go ahead and use it
as the hero image of my website.
The original image is portrait,
so I'm gonna have to apply a name
transformation in order to make
it a landscape orientation so that
it could fit as my hero image.
Next, I'm going to take that
or original image and I'm going
to apply a text overlay to it.
We're gonna see how the best practices
are implemented from my rules file.
And finally, we're going to transform
that same image into a thumbnail.
And I'm gonna, again, use the
transformation required in the rules file.
So let's go right into the
IDE and see it in action.
So here I've got my index html file,
which already has some code in it.
I've got a placeholder for the hero
image, and I've got the source that
is not yet populated, but it's going
to get populated by the code that
I'm gonna put into my index js file.
Over there, I'm going to transform
that original image that I'm
going to upload to Cloudinary.
Right now.
I'm going to ask Cloudinary to upload
this image to my product environment.
The public ID should
be Father's Day banner.
It is giving me a prompt and I'm
gonna allow it to run the upload.
And there we have it.
I've got my image, and it even gave me
my image, URL that just got uploaded.
Now for the Euro image, I want
the LLM client to, first of
all, genetically create a name
transformation for hero images.
Then I wanted to apply the
name transformation in index as
to the image I just uploaded.
And finally, to use the
generated URL as the source for
the hero image in index html.
Let's add all our docs as content.
First.
Click the Ampersand docs, Cloudinary
docs, and the transformation rules file.
I don't have to add my
rules file that I created.
And that's because I already
said it to always applying.
Now let's add the prompt
and see what happens.
Transform the specific image, make it a
hero, type with an height specified and
apply the transformation in index g js
and uses at a source is in index html.
Okay.
Checking if a transformation
like that already exists.
It found one,
but it's not quite what I specified,
so it's going to create a
new transformation, plus it
added the code to apply it.
Amazing.
So let's take a look and see
how it did, and this is what our
gorgeous HTML page looks like.
Now let's go back and add something.
Let's add another image below that,
which will contain a text overlay.
So I'm gonna add the prompt again.
Add another transformed image under
the hero image same public id and add
a text overlay with a text specified.
Again, generating it in index js
and rendering it in index html.
Let's see what happens.
Remember, it should take the instructions
that I gave it for how a text.
Overlay should look and
apply it in this case.
Okay, so it added the information
and the code to index js
it, added it to index html,
and let's see if it worked.
So let's have a look
at our updated website.
We've got our hero image and we've
got our text overlay example, and
here's the text that we added.
It looks good.
It's the right font, nice clear font.
It's white and it's flushed to the bottom.
And that's what we asked
for in our rules file.
Okay.
So let's do one more.
This time we wanna crop a
thumbnail around the face.
We had a rule for using G face only
with auto crop, C auto, so let's see if
we can trust it to do that accurately.
Okay, so let's paste in our prompt.
We're gonna add another transformed
image under the text overlaid image.
We're gonna use the same public id.
We're gonna crop the image to focus on
the face, and we are going to add upscale
effect for even sharper looking images.
Okay, let's see what happens.
Okay, we've got C Auto and G face.
Great.
And let's see what our
updated website looks like.
Okay, so let's find our thumbnail.
And there it is.
It looks just right.
It's little bit big, but we didn't
make any rules about making it smaller.
Okay, so let's get back
to our PowerPoint slides.
Just to sum up.
Here is a list of APIs that you
can use along with MCP support
and also contact seven indexing.
All of them have a few examples of
how you can use them age genetically.
Let's just take a look
at one or two of them.
We've got OAuth where you can set
up login and authentication flows.
You can manage test users or
refresh API keys securely.
With Shopify, you can add sample
products, draft test orders, or
connect webhooks for your stores.
Here are a few ideas of rule
files that you can create.
You can set API fetching rules, for
example, how to call APIs using fetch
or axios with consistent error handling
and no hard-coded keys, and you could
create form handling, handling rules.
You could set preferred validation
libraries structure for controlled
inputs and submit patterns.
So hopefully after today you can
leverage your LLM clients accurately
and effectively use it for code
generation and I ident agent tasks.
Be confident that it's correct when
implementing dog-friendly techniques.
What's coming up next?
Docs are about to stop being reference
pages and start being runtime components.
There'll be adaptive,
dynamic and self-improving.
We're already seeing a lot of that,
how adaptive and dynamic they are.
Self-improving, not yet, but soon.
The next generation of docs will live
inside our ides, which they do already.
They'll have power of re reasoning
and execution, which they do
already, and they'll evolve
dynamically from real usage.
And that I'm really
looking forward to seeing.
So thank you.
Feel free to email me.
And I hope that this was
a useful session for you.