Hello everyone Welcome to
Conf 42 JavaScript track.
I'm really excited to be
speaking about this topic.
It's called mission
performance, impossible real
time chat web app performance.
My name is Zubair.
I'm a software engineer at Mattermost.
So a little bit about Mattermost.
It's an open source collaboration platform
for communities, enterprises, teams.
We have been, very focused on Mattermost
being an entire suit of platform tools
for entire software development cycle.
Now, before we begin with the,
with the topic, let's first
understand the architecture.
of the web app matter was web
app uses react as it's, front end
library to make the web application.
So as everybody's already aware, react
is more efficient when we have a lot
of updates and indeed learning the
components which have changed only,
change only have the difference.
in visualization of what components
have actually are supposed to re render
instead of re rendering the complete.
And the state manager which we
are using is Redux, Redux with
Thung's library separately.
It's, and it serves, as I've
said, it serves as a state
manager of the application.
And, I think everybody is aware of Redux.
It's a very predictable state
container library for React.
It also answers, handles asynchronous
logic for interaction with networks
and all the other core features.
The next is technology which
actually makes the web application of
MatterMost real time is WebSocket API.
This WebSocket API enables us
to have real time communication
between the client and the server.
And this obviously is very crucial
for the chat application to
be able to serve in real time.
And, yes, all of that, the application
is a single bit application, which
enhances the user experiences by reducing,
frequent page loads and all that.
It's it's entirely modular design, and
if it's open source, feel free to just
check out the repository and the code
behind that, everything is modularized
into components, actions, selectors
and the UI component library, all that.
And as I've already mentioned, real
time updates with AppSocket, that
maintains a persistent connection
to the server, allowing for the
instant data push and updates without
requiring, much user interaction.
With this, let's try to understand
what the, what are the challenges
of real time application.
Now, when I say challenges real time
data, I'm purely talking about in
respective of the client performance.
The real time application on the server
side is again a completely different
story, which needs its own talk,
but this talk is concerned about the
client performance, by client the web
application running on the browser.
Now when things are real time, there
is a high volume of incoming network
requests with WebSocket events.
And most of the times, this
incoming network events also must
be followed up by more by the
client by more network request.
For example, if you have a post coming in,
we usually don't send the user's complete
information who's sending the post.
Now it's up to the client if it's, if
it has that user ID particularly stored
in the Redux, it's well and good.
If it's not, then again, it
has to go back to the server to
fetch the user details for you.
Now, in high elevated environment,
this could lead to a lot of, network
traffic when your client is constantly
responding to the new incoming, WebSocket
events with more network events.
We get to this one of the problems, which
this is one of the problems we have faced.
we'll get to that problem in a bit.
Now there's always a constant battle
between what to fetch and what not
to fetch or what to fetch later on.
So with the real time data, there
is always, you have to may have this
balance of overfetching or underfetching.
Keeping all of this There, your
UI has to be responsive, has to be
interactive, by the user, because user is
concerned about using the, application.
It has, it just, your
app has to support that.
Now, there were a lot of performance,
optimizations which we had, which
had to wet in to, elevate the load
bearing capacity of the client.
We'll get to some of the PRs,
not all of them, in a while.
But before that, let's try to understand
how can we simulate this, right?
Because you, if you are
testing on a local environment.
You won't have this many users
signing up, these are sending
the, these many users sending the
post, people joining the channel,
people reacting to the post, people
commenting on the post and all that.
Matomos has an inbuilt tool called
Matomos load testing engine.
which it uses to test, test,
test the server environment.
A little bit about the architecture
of this particular tool.
It's an in house tool
developed by Metamast.
We have, I think you're already
seeing the architecture over here.
Just a very big, very high level view.
There are two main components that
we should be, we should look out for.
That is, the first one
is a user controller.
Now, this component is actually in
charge of driving or controlling a user.
By user, a simulated user, right?
It is, its implementation is what defines,
what exactly the behavior of the user is.
Its action could include, what the user
might do when it opens the Matterport.
It might go to type in post,
switch channels, switch teams,
open a new thread, a reactor post.
So all of this is implemented
in the user controller module
which you can see over there.
And then another thing which we should
also be aware of is the coordinator.
Now this coordinator is in charge of
managing the cluster of load test agents
by load test agents and then it's trying
to figure out what is the maximum number
of concurrent users the particular
server or active server can have.
So again, this is, if you can see there
is a looping, there's a loop going on
from coordinator directly to Prometheus.
It's a loop back, a simple feedback loop.
So when the load test starts, the
coordinator We'll begin increasing the
number of users and at the same time,
we'll also start monitoring, or acquiring
the Prometheus server by collecting
its server metrics and seeing are
we reaching our target limit or not?
Then based on that, it will
start decreasing the active
number of users slowly.
And once the equilibrium
point is reached, it'll stop.
By equilibrium, when no more
active users can be added.
And that would indicate that these are
the maximum number of supported users
this particular Matomo server can have.
With this, these are all
happening on the server side.
What we would like to do is have an
extension of this for the client.
So into the one of this app instances,
we are going to connect our client and
see how the client performs when all of
these user controllers are working in
tandem, doing all sorts of things, all
expected user behavior, because that is
how we would, that is how the application
would be used eventually, right?
So for this, what we did is we
have, automated test running on
the client, which will open the
web application when the load test
is being run on the background.
And again, the front end, load testing
tool, which start interacting with the
application, the real time application.
Now you must be confusing how you said the
user controller is doing the interaction,
but yes, user controller is doing.
On the server side, but we need
a client side metrics, right?
So that's the reason we need to connect a
client and then run an automation, loading
tool to get the actual browser metrics
and what the actual user is seeing.
And for that, we need to
connect it to a browser.
So as you can see, once we
start doing that, it runs whole
suits, it runs for some time.
It runs whole suits of tests.
And with this, we are, getting,
we are piping all the data to the
Prometheus, which is already there
in our load testing instance.
And, with that Prometheus, we are
scraping, Grafana is scraping for
us to, get us the useful analytics,
which we would like to see.
Now, I told about this, like
analysis, like what the metrics are.
Let's try to understand
what these metrics are.
Now, before going to the metrics.
How can you compare two versions
of a metadata application, right?
So what we do is, within the, for
the version number A, we run the
load test, wait for the equilibrium
to set in, get the app node,
run the client automation test.
Run it for some time, see the graph
dashboard, take the metrics from the
browser, and then we run it again
with the equivalent or exactly the
same environment variables, which
we have done for the past test.
Now with the new, with the
different client version.
And then that is how, after again,
running the same steps, then we
compare, have we improved or not?
And that is how we analyze,
okay, are we improving the.
performance of web app or
are actually degrading that.
Now, with this,
let's, as I've mentioned that the
metrics which we are talking about,
let's try to understand what are
these, what are a few of the metrics
that we track in the client side.
Now, this is important.
Now, even before going to the
actual metrics, we need to, the
reason there are a few things
that we first need to understand.
This client side metrics are very
much dependent on the hardware.
And because the hardware is
constantly changing with any
number of clients, right?
Because each one of them have a different
browser or have a different hardware.
All the users, even them, Although
they all of them are in the same
Matamoros instance, so we need to
be, that's the reason I've said that
comparison is the key over here, not
the absolute values this metrics.
So with that, the first thing which we
do is we, use the Chrome dev tools to
see if there are any memory leaks or not.
So we do the memory profiling.
And with this, what we are basically
trying to see is, are there any
memory, leakages or are there
any inefficient memory users?
With this, what we can see is, will
this memory excess, excessive memory
leads to crash or slow performance.
once we do find out, okay, there are a few
things that we need to do, then we have to
follow up with efficient data structures,
if you would like to see the structures
or efficient calling of functions so
that our memory allocation optimization,
if we Optimized memory allocation.
We also monitor CPU usages.
So this identifies us if there are
any processes bottlenecks because
high CPU usage can slow down the
complete client affecting response
times or application performance.
Not only batteries application
performance, it also degrades
other applications which are open.
under the user's computer.
So we profile, the CPU, and see what
cause, if there are any spikes, then we
can go back to it and see what caused
this additional computational overheads.
Another metric which we also see is what
is the frames per second when the user
is interacting with the application.
Now that is on the top left, as
you can see, Again, available in
the Chrome DevTools, it's, it's a
measure of how smooth the animations
or interactions are being happening,
are taking place in your application.
Obviously, low FPS leads to
choppy visuals, delayed responses,
very bad user experience.
So we identify which process
is causing lower frame rate per
second and concentrate on that to
see how can we improve that, how
can the re renders be improved.
And all that.
Another useful tool, which we
also take a snapshot of is the
network, HTTP archives or apps, hr.
What is, this is what this will,
allow us to see is are there any,
long pending network requests which
are being carried on by the client,
which we might not be aware of.
That client is making that.
and see how other web assets are loading.
Are there any network bottlenecks?
Because what happens is, although the
browser does not have any limitations
on number of requests being sent, but
all, but this network request, when the
response from this network request comes
in, the client has to get this data, do,
understand where to, where in the place
of redirect that has to place this data,
do a lot of pre rendering and all that.
So although network request doesn't
cost us the memory usage, but the
following processes after we get
the response is, are the heavy ones.
optimized, network loading
is, very much appreciated.
And, the next thing is we have the Web
Vitals, library from Google as well,
which helps us to understand various,
stable, industry recognized metrics.
For example, FCPs, LCPs like FCP is the
first content and contentful paints,
cumulative layout shifts and all that.
there's a amazing library by
made by the Google, which you can
incorporate to, and which would
track all these numbers for you.
So measurement of these vitals
and also comparison is one of
the vital, performance tool
which we have in our arsenal.
Running Lighthouse is another,
process which we have.
it gives us an holistic view,
said by, Google Lighthouse tool.
It has, again, not only the metrics, which
we talked about earlier, but also other,
other metrics, which are very useful.
For example, the accessibilities
and, it also gives a very helpful
recommendation on how to solve
this performance, bottlenecks.
So we have.
the FCP, which is the
first contentful paint.
It's the measurement of time when the user
first navigate, have navigated the page.
And, and if the part is rendered on the
screen, that's the first contentful paint.
And the largest, LCP is the largest
contentful paint is basically the
time between the, one of the largest
element on the page, which appears.
And then we also have interaction
to NextPaint, again, which is
a very core, web vital for us.
It basically measures how much of the
latency we have with the user interaction
when the user first lands on the page.
And then we also have other
things like total blocking time,
speed index, all of that here.
Then we also have a specific set of
custom Matomost metrics, for example,
channel switch time, like how much time
does it take for, on an average, for
the user to change from one channel to
another, or from one team to another,
all this, these are custom metrics
which we have defined, in Matomost.
And yes, we are, we keep on defining
or developing this custom metrics
as a part of performance analysis.
Now with that, I think now
we have, understood like what
all metrics which we can use.
look out for and how do we do the
comparison and what is the process that
we follow to the load test on the client.
Let's look, quickly look at a few example
PRs just to get an understanding of how
the actual process of work is being done.
So this is one, one of the things which
we have seen, when we ran the load test on
the client is there was a very high memory
usage of one of the, one of the reducers.
And we have seen that it was like,
what, 34 percent of the memory usage,
in that particular interaction.
We had to reduce that, but
why is that even happening?
It turned out that we were not correct.
to say we were not actually,
getting, we were getting objects.
We were not, which were not being
recycled by Chrome and they were
having some dangling, objects, which
were not being garbage collected.
And if they were dangling objects,
We had to, usually what happens is
when you run a garbage collector,
it stops the whole application
and then runs garbage collector.
So GC run by the browser
is intensive operation.
I need to avoid that as much as possible,
not completely avoided, but yeah.
as much as possible.
So this was a one of the thing which
we, which we had and we were using few
of the arrays, patterns, which solved
the issue and we were able to get down a
significant usage by this particularity.
So
there was also another one which
was causing from the issues was
that we were using a library for the
profiles, profile popover and all that.
So which were causing a significant memory
leak, which we were able to find out.
So one of the methods was to
either, either have it custom
built by ourselves or replace the
complete library, an existing one.
So we had the base library changed,
to a more, new and supported
library without these memory leaks.
And yes, we did had a lot of improvement
when we actually changed the popover
library and performance that.
And what another, another,
investigation, which we also did was
the, we had a lot of, network calls
been sent to get statuses and user
IDs, when the new message was posted.
Now, agreed, there is a little
bit of, what you can say, we
don't have a web socket event
when someone changes the statuses
because there are some performance,
bottlenecks we have from the server.
And that is one of the,
limitations which we have.
That's the reason we don't have a,
we don't send out a WebSocket event
when the user status is changed.
So what we had to resort for is manual
fetching after some amount of time,
fetching again the user statuses.
Now that was repeatedly hammering the
Redux store, updating that, the whole
application was very much freezing.
We had to do something about that.
what we ended up doing was we created
a simple, data manager for statuses
and also varieties, which, which would,
keep a queue of the statuses and then
execute after a certain amount of time.
that solved the issue.
And yeah, that, after how much
interval that this particular
queue has to get cleared, that
is again, configurable better.
application.
And there was also another, I'm
sorry about the network request.
So we also saw like an unwanted
network request, right before.
So the, again, there was one of the thing
which we saw is, we, it was unnecessarily
fetching complete thread when we are
not seeing that particular channel.
So as you can see, We, if you have noticed
all of these PRs and not only this PRs,
but any of the performance PRs have, a
very good backing of reasoning of why
this particular performance improvement
is important by having a sound comparison
between before and after effects of
the PR so that we can see visually.
Okay, this has improved by this particular
percentage or by this particular metric.
and, not only, it helps for the,
but also it helps in the future as
well, when we go back to this PR
and see, okay, why did we do that?
At that particular point of
time, we saw, okay, this was the
improvement which we have seen.
Now, let's get back to
now, by, we have seen a few of
the examples, work, which was done
on Matamoros, the client side.
Now, obviously there are a few caveats
with this, no matter how much performance
improvement you do, network latency
will eat away all your hard work,
Because that's just a hard reality.
So even if you have improved
like 30, 30 milliseconds of your
improvement, if you're a server,
if you have a large latency, all
of that performance goes to waste.
And then.
client, as I've also mentioned
earlier, client side performance
is, has a lot of dependent factors.
Now, for example, what kind
of hardware are they using?
What kind of browser they have?
What kind of other application
they have running alongside
the Matterport application?
So yeah.
So that's the reason I've said comparison
is the key in load testing client.
And it's, it so happens that, the
performance, for example, it so happens
that when the user loads the application
and the first time it is slow, the user
perception is that application is bad.
So user perception regarding
performance is very much different.
That's the reason that you have to do
your own load testing on the client,
or not rely on server's feedback,
or you know what, channel switching
is slow, channel team is slow.
We cannot rely on that information solely.
And then we have to just replicate
exactly what exactly is happening.
with our load testing tool to understand
where and when the problem is arising.
And not all your performances
improvements will be linear.
It might be some might
give you a lot of gain.
Some might give a very less gain.
So that's always there.
Now, with this, I'd like
to conclude my talk.
If you have any questions, please,
reach out to me and I'm available
at my, website over there.
Thank you so much for listening.
And once again, it was lovely.
It was lovely talking,
presenting all of you.
Thank you.