Hello everyone.
I am Amud Yado, and it's truly a pleasure
to be speaking at Con 42 JavaScript 2025.
I have spent over 13 years in the
IT industry working across a variety
of sector, including IT, telecom,
discrete manufacturing, oil and
gas, NGOs, and higher education.
Currently I'm with a medical college
in the higher education domain where
we are exploring innovative way to
reduce administrative and clinical
workflow for our healthcare staff.
That's where my journey with
JavaScript took an interesting turn.
I started seeing how it's evolving
capabilities, especially when paired
with artificial intelligence could make a
real difference in healthcare operation.
So today, without further delay, let's
dive into our topic, how JavaScript
and artificial intes are transforming
healthcare operations, not as a buzzword,
but through miserable real world outcome.
In this season, we will bring
together two powerful worlds.
Healthcare operational challenges
and JavaScript AI driving potential
to see how technology can truly
enhance the way care is delivered.
The Healthcare operations Challenge.
Let's take a moment to look at the
reality of healthcare operation today.
Clinician and staffs are under immense
pressure, not because of patient care.
But because of everything around it, a
staggering amount of their time goes into
administrative work, such as updating,
record managing, handling billings,
juggling multiple disconnected system.
Most of these processes still
rely on legacy platform that
are slow, soiled, and prone to.
Error and the result is frustration,
inefficiency, and less time for
what really matters patient care.
Now our goal here is to
replace people far from it.
The real opportunity lies in augmenting
human capability using technology to
take the burden of their shoulder.
By integrating intelligent JavaScript
based AI tool, we can automate
those repetitive manual tasks,
reduce operational friction, and
allow human to focus on what.
They do best judgment,
compassion, and empty.
So why JavaScript?
The simple answer is
because it's everywhere.
Think about it, whether it's
your browser, your phone, or
even a tablet in a hospital room.
JavaScripts run on all of them.
There's no complex setup,
no heavy installation.
It is just work.
And with powerful framework like
React, angular, and no js, we
can develop, deploy, and update
solution faster than ever before.
What really makes JavaScript
special is massive ecosystem.
Thousands of ready to use module for
data visualization, API integration
and intelligent automation.
And if you have your.
Worked in healthcare, you know how
critical those capabilities are.
Pulling data from multiple system, showing
it clearly and acting on it in real time.
And speaking of real time,
that's another strength.
JavaScripts truly science
in live communication.
Powering dashboard alerts and
notification that keep operations moving
smoothly when seconds really matter.
So JavaScript isn't just convenience.
It's the language that meets healthcare
where it already is connected,
fast and accessible to everyone.
At the heart of modern healthcare,
AI integration lies one powerful
combination, the nod js and react stack.
Let's start with nod js.
Microservices architecture allow
every healthcare module, whether it's
scheduling, billing, or analytics to
grow and evolve independently without
bringing the whole system down, and then
thes react, which ensure a consistent
and intuitive front-end experience.
Whether a user is managing appointments,
viewing patient data, or reviewing
reports, when you bring the two
together, you get flexibility,
scalability, and maintainability.
Three things.
Every healthcare IT system
struggle to balance.
And the best part, this modular
approach means hospitals don't
have to rebuild everything at once.
They can start a small, maybe pilot
a single service like scheduling,
and once it is successful, expand to
inventory, finance, or even analytics,
all without starting from scratch.
That's the real power of this stack
it grow with your organization.
One service.
At a time impact area.
Let's talk about one of
the toughest challenge in
healthcare operation scheduling.
It sounds simple, but it's actually
one of the most complex puzzle
hospital deal with every single day.
You have got to balance staff ability,
skill mix, patient demand, regulatory
rules, and of course all those last minute
changes that never stops coming Now.
Here is where JavaScript
based interface comes in.
They can process all these constraint
in real time, automatically optimizing
rosters and suggesting assignment.
Still keeping the human scheduler
in control for the final decision
In one pilot project, this
approach reduce over time by 25%
and cut schedule revision by 40%.
And that's not just about efficiency, it's
about happier staff, better cost control.
Ultimately improved patient flow
because when people aren't exhausted
or overbooked, patient get better care
and the whole system run is smoother.
Inventory is one of those
silent pain point in healthcare.
When supplies run out,
patient care suffer.
When we overstock valuable capital
sales and used on the selves, it's
a delicate balance and for years,
most hospital have been managing it
with fragmented system and casework.
Now with React based dashboard, powered
by JavaScript and DI that is starting
to change these system provide real
time visibility across department so
everyone from procurement to nursing
unions can see what's exactly available.
Predictive analytics, health forecast
usage strength, automated alerts
makes your restocking happen one
time and cost optimization algorithm
can even suggest better supply deal.
The outcome, a self-learning supply chain.
One where data drives both saving
and Sept, because in healthcare,
right item at the right time can
literally make all the difference
impact area financial automation.
Now let's talk about another big challenge
in healthcare, financial workflow.
From claim to reimbursement,
the process is complex.
Every steps involve layer of
validation, coding, and compliance.
And even a small error can
delay payment or trigger rework.
There is where JavaScript drive and
automation start to make a real impact.
With AI model running behind the
scene, the system can automatically
flag missing information, validate
billing code, and even optimize
claim before they are submitted.
The result speak for themselves.
We have seen up to 35% faster
claim processing and nearly
18% higher revenue capture.
And it's not magic.
It's simply consistency and
error prevention powered
by intelligent automation.
When accuracy become automatic efficiency
and revenue flow naturally the human
experience, we often think of success
in term of ROI or performance metrics,
but the real measure of success
is pupil when AI and JavaScripts.
Come together.
They take on the busy work, the
form, the admin task, freeing the
staff to focus on what truly matter
Patient care, AI helps surface the
right insight at the right time,
boosting confidence in every decision,
and cutting down on costly error.
And when there is less
rework, there is less burnout.
That means caregiver have more energy,
more focus, and more heart to give.
So yes, technology drives efficiency.
It's the real success is measured in the
wellbeing of the people who use it and the
better care they deliver every single day.
Design principle, user experience
in healthcare has to be clear,
con, contextual, and safe.
Visual clarity has basic clinician
move confidently through complex task.
Contextual action.
Bring up the right option at the right
moment based on each person's role and
workflow and proactive validation catches
error before they ever reach to patient.
That's why modern JavaScript framework
like React and VU are so powerful.
The enable responsive, intelligent
interfaces that adapt seamlessly to each
user in every critical moment of care.
Because in healthcare, a well design
experience isn't just convenient.
It's life saving technical architecture
from an engineering standpoint.
There are three key pillar
of a robust architecture.
First, microservices.
They decouple complex system like
scheduling, billing, and analytics,
so each can evolve independently
without breaking the rest.
Second, state management with
tool like Redux, all the context
API, and data stays consistent and
reliable across every workflow.
No matter how complex and third, real
time synchronization using web socket
or servers sent event, keep dashboard,
live, responsive, and ready for action.
Together these principle build an
architecture that's not just efficient,
but resilient, ready to scale and
perform in mission critical healthcare,
envir environments, integration
challenges and solution integration is
often the hardest part of healthcare.
It not the AI itself.
Legacy PIs comes with inconsistent
format, and that's where abstraction
layer make all the difference.
They unify the kiosk behind the scene.
Then comes data synchronization with
even driving architecture update flow
seamlessly across multiple system, keeping
everything accurate and current security.
That's absolutely non-negotiable.
End-to-end encryption, role-based
access and detailed audit log.
Protect every piece of patient data.
And finally, performance.
Techniques like laser loading,
ation and smart casting.
Keep the experiences smooth even when
we are working with massive dataset.
In the end.
Great healthcare tech.
Agent, just intelligent.
It's secure, reliable, and effortless
to use implementation framework.
Here is a structure four phase
framework for implementing AI and
JavaScript Phase one foundation.
We start by assessing existing system,
defining clear success metrics, and
ensure full compliance with healthcare
Standard phase two development.
This is where we build modular
macroservices, create re react component,
and test every piece thoroughly.
Phase three deployment.
We launch a pilot within a single
department, gather feedback and
refine the system based on real
world use and phase four scale.
Once proven, we expand, gradually
enhance the AI model and share the
outcome across the organization.
This phase process strike the right
balance between agility and governance,
and that's exactly what's sustainable.
Healthcare transform is
and require key takeaway.
So first takeaway is JavaScript is through
truly production ready for healthcare.
Its framework.
Deliver both speed and reliability.
Powering real world system
that clinician can trust.
Second, augment, don't
replace the best AI solution.
Amplify human capability, this
support professional rather
than trying to replace them.
Third, the start is small, er
everything and scale strategically.
Pilots build confidence metric, build
credibility, and together they create a
solid path towards sustainable growth.
And if you remember just one
thing from today, let it be this.
Progress in healthcare technology
comes from empathy paired with
precision, because when innovations
are both the heart and the mind, that's
when a real transformation happen.
AI plus JavaScript in real
world healthcare use case.
So I have seen few use cases.
Let's look at a few real world example
of how AI and JavaScript come together
to make a difference in healthcare.
Chatbot trash, assistant
AI powered agenda that.
Pre-screen symptom and guide
patient to the right care path, real
time vital dashboard, continuous
monitoring, and instant ly
detection through connected devices.
Predictive appointment management,
forecasting cancellation, optimizing
schedule to keep clinic running
smoothly and AI driving image leveling.
Escalating radiology and research
by automating repetitive analysis
task Each of these example blend
AI's intelligence with JavaScript
accessibility, turning complex technology
into tool that deliver real miserable
value of patient and provider alike.
Getting started your next step.
So how can you begin this journey?
Step one, identify the pain points.
Talk to your staff.
Find out where time is being lost
and where frustration builds up.
Step two, build your team.
Bring developer, clinician and
security expert together because
transformation only works when.
Every voice is heard.
Step three, choose your stack.
Select framework that align with your
existing skill and system, so innovation
fits seamlessly into your workflow.
Step four, launch a pilot.
Start small, irate, quickly measure
your result, and then scale what works.
Remember, the path to
transfer isn't a giant leap.
It's a small, measured step that move
healthcare forward with confidence and.
Purpose.
Thank you all for the time and attention.
I hope today's session offered a
fresh perspective on how JavaScript
and AI can come together to create
meaningful challenge in healthcare.
Let's keep pushing forward building
system that truly help people, system
that make care faster, safer, and smarter.
I would love to continue the conversation.
Feel free to reach out afterward
for question, discussion, or
collaboration idea because together
we can turn innovation into impact.