Hello friends, a very warm welcome from my
side to conf42 JavaScript 2024 conference.
Today, I will be presenting on Kubernetes
security for JavaScript applications.
I will talk about myself.
I'm Manpreet Singh Sachdeva.
I work for Walmart Global
Tech in United States.
I'm an industry expert in
DevSecOps, MLOps, incident
management, and quality assurance.
So I have experience in Asia, in
Europe, as well as in North America.
I've worked on various technologies,
cloud technologies, different cloud
providers, AWS, Azure, GCP, as
well as on open source technology
like OpenStack, Kubernetes, virtual
machines, containerized applications.
So I'm really excited to share my thoughts
on this topic and I hope we learn together
and take some key learnings with us.
So let's get started.
this is all about securing our JavaScript
applications on the Kubernetes clusters.
I'll share some best practices and
strategies we use in the modern era.
So we'll talk about how Kubernetes
became so important and so
necessary in today's world.
we'll go a bit, around in the area
of 2015, where we were just started
to containerize the applications.
So the Docker became popular.
And we saw many applications like
Java, JavaScript applications, and they
all sort, sorted, their, apps and we
started deploying on the containers.
So the advantage of having containers is
that it becomes platform agnostic and the
application really becomes lightweight.
You can deploy.
locally in your machine, you can
take it to production, you can
scale in and you can scale out.
And there was a lot of
flexibility around containers.
Then we started, thinking about the
orchestration of containers that how
to make applications work on scale.
So that was the next
challenge the industry had.
Then we started using Docker
Swarm, where we could use.
to scale out the applications, do
networking between all, the containers,
communicate and secure container, you
know, workloads, but that also there
was a disadvantage or set of a sort of,
issue while scaling on Docker swarm.
So it couldn't support large scale
applications where we had to.
Run, production workloads for
a very high intensified apps
using memory as well as CPU.
then came Kubernetes and really became
popular because, the way it handled
the Docker orchestration, the way it
handled all the container containers
in a, distributed environment, we
could see the applications being
scaled in, scaled out and, a massive
workloads being supported, then.
There was, networking
between the applications.
How can we restrict the app to
communicate or how can we, allow an app
to communicate to the outside world?
And then came the most important
part, which was how to secure the
communication among the applications,
how to make sure that we are covered
on the vulnerabilities and the cyber
threats we have in the, on the internet.
So cyber security, as is one of the most
or the hottest topic nowadays where there
are so many cyber threats causing so much
damage to the reputation, financial damage
and so much, customers suffer so much
at the stake of cyber security threats.
So today we'll focus on how to secure
our JavaScript applications and how to
run them, efficiently using Kubernetes.
So guys, let's get started.
as I talked about containerizing
the JavaScript applications, so
why should we on the first hand
containerize an application?
So containers provide a very
lightweight, portable, and consistent
environment for applications.
As we just spoke about, Docker is one
of the most popular containerization
platform, which allows the developers
to package their applications
with all their dependencies.
So that's what we do in Node.
js or Java applications, we package
them with their dependencies.
So the other advantage is, that there is
a consistency across all the environments.
We ensure that the applications runs
the same way in all the different
environments, like dev environment,
testing, pre staging or a pre
prod kind of environment, and then
actually on a production environment.
So we can do all the cycles of testing,
starting from the dev to our pre
prod and make sure that, we are well
accustomed with all the scalability.
And the networking perspective of
our applications, and then, deploy
the application on production and the
other important factors, the, all the
containers are totally isolated, all
the applications, they run all the
services they run without conflicts.
in their own storage space, so they
do not interact or interfere with the
other apps which are also containerized.
Then we spoke about scalability
already where, it's very easy
to scale the applications
horizontally as well as vertically.
So we will talk about the horizontal
pod auto scaling on Kubernetes that
how easily we can scale the application
when there is an increase in the
surge in traffic and we can also
basically scale in the applications.
Where if the traffic is less and
you're going to, we can, make sure
that we are running on less number of
containers to, do cost optimization.
And, we already spoke about the
Kubernetes, which is, one of the
most popular container orchestration
platforms, which helps the
applications to run at scale with
different, Cloud providers nowadays.
So we also have a hybrid kind of
a cloud environment, which most of
the companies nowadays support that
they have their native inbuilt cloud
platform and they leverage the,
cloud providers in a hybrid way.
So talking about now Kubernetes,
which has actually transformed the way
we deploy our applications, the way
we, scale our applications and it's
so easy to manage the applications.
just with few commands and, just on,
even if I have a UI to manage very easy
to manage, all these applications in
just one click, but we, that, we've
given such a big, or a powerful tool.
Now we also have a big responsibility
to make sure that, we protect
our internet world or all the
applications which are hosted.
We protect them.
from all the kind of cyber
threats we are having now.
So we'll talk about different kind of,
security implementation for Kubernetes.
How can we secure our, applications,
especially what are the best practices and
some tips for the JavaScript applications.
I'll also share some of
the examples for JavaScript
applications later in the slides.
Yeah, we'll just go through, one of, one
of the examples, and I also share some
resources at the end of the presentation
where you can refer it for later.
So this presentation will mainly outline
a multi layered approach to secure
it, securing our Kubernetes clusters.
So we'll focus on the different
planes where the security
vulnerabilities can catch us.
So first will be the control plane.
then we'll talk about the.
Securing our node, securing
actual applications, which we
call as workloads in Kubernetes
world or the containerized world.
And then we'll talk about how we
can secure the communication of
all these apps on the network side.
So we'll give, give you a real
world examples and best practices.
And, try to demonstrate how to
protect Kubernetes environments and
vulnerabilities from the vulnerabilities.
So when we talk about security, there
are mainly four C's, which we talk about.
So first C is the cluster, where,
how can we secure the cluster
where our, application is hosted.
Then the container.
Container is nothing but
the workload security.
How to secure the container which is
running, our JavaScript application.
And we'll talk about the
security on the cloud.
Then we'll talk about that how can we
leverage the cloud providers such as AWS.
As your, as well as GCP, and then
we'll talk about the actual code
vulnerability and the code security.
So just give an example of cloud
securities like, AWS, Azure, they
have some network policies and they
have their own kind of security,
mechanisms, which they support.
So we'll not go in, in depth of those
security mechanisms, but there's
a lot of cloud security measures,
which these cloud providers take.
and we can definitely leverage,
on our Kubernetes clusters.
So moving forward, why does
Kubernetes security matters that much?
So as we were talking about the
Kubernetes, it's now very popular
in container orchestration and
mostly all the big applications.
They use kubernetes, at the
back end of the cluster.
So kubernetes has become the backbone
of our modern cloud infrastructure
with adoption growing rapidly
across industries like, healthcare,
finance, retail, telecommunications.
So organizational organizations
are totally relying on kubernetes
for mission critical operations,
like running big websites, retail
websites, healthcare systems, and even.
even the defense or the, different
kind of industries like, AI industry
and healthcare industry, all are
using Kubernetes on large scale.
But again, with the increased use comes
the threat of cyber attacks, targeting
vulnerabilities with Kubernetes clusters.
We all are aware of the log4j
vulnerability which happened
a couple of years back.
And there was another threat in 2021,
which, a hacker was able to access a
Kubernetes cluster through, like an
admin and able to, destroy and delete
so many apps, which were really mission
critical supporting, the payment systems.
And it hit a lot of
reputation of that company.
And, also a lot of financial damage
happened, which the company had
to pay back to the customers.
So that is the reason, prime
reason why the Kubernetes
security matters so much now.
So failing to secure Kubernetes
environments can lead to severe
consequences, the kind of
one which we just discussed.
So including data breaches, right?
Service disruptions, you can completely
delete the running application pods and
just do a complete service disruption.
You can filter out the
secrets, the username passwords
of the actual customers.
And which is a big data
breach for any company.
And then there, the financial
losses, that, that can actually
cripple the, the operation centers.
So the stakes are especially
high for organizations undergoing
digital transformation nowadays.
Properly securing Kubernetes
clusters will basically ensure trust,
reliability, and safety, not only for
the business, but also for the end users.
Who rely on these digital services?
Suppose, customers are using a banking
app customers, like last week, there
was a big outage on the bank of America.
The user not, we're not even
able to log into the app.
So all of these, apps are hosted on
Kubernetes and at the end, the end
users are suffering and it's bringing
so much loss, to these digital services.
So now we'll talk about the multi layered
approach, which we will follow to secure
our Kubernetes clusters and workloads.
as I was talking that we will talk about
different kind of security planes where
we need to, apply the security measures.
securing Kubernetes requires
a layered security strategy.
Addressing vulnerabilities
across different components.
So each layer is crucial here for reducing
the attack surface and mitigating threat.
So we constitute, all these layers
constitute a attack surface.
So we will see where are attack surfaces
and how to mitigate, the attack area.
So first up, first of all, we'll talk
about the control plane security, how
we can protect the cluster's central
brain where, you know, all the logic
lives, then we'll talk about the node
security that, we, the node, the host
where our application is running, how
to secure that node, then eventually
we'll talk about, the workload security,
which is nothing but securing our
JavaScript applications, that how the
applications run within the cluster.
can be protected, right?
And then we'll talk about the network
security at last, that how we can control
the traffic inflow and, which we call the
ingress traffic and the egress traffic.
How we can, control the inflow and
the outflow traffic and manage the
secure communications among the apps.
basically we'll have a holistic approach
to ensure that, all the vulnerabilities
are addressed from all the angles.
first we talk about
control plane security.
what is control plane security?
It's the API server authentication
and authorization, happens
on the control plane.
control plane is the brain
of your Kubernetes cluster.
Some of the, terms we use, we
call it as the master component.
or the one which is
running the control, plane.
So we also call it as a control plane
component or a master component where
are, all of the API servers are hosted.
So the Kubernetes API server
is the core interface for
managing the cluster operations.
Secure it by using strong authentication
methods like OAuth or OpenID.
So these are all open, source way
of, providing an authorization,
to the cluster level.
And we can also use RBAC policies.
So RBAC is nothing but Role Based
Access Control policies by which we can
limit the access to critical functions.
So every org they implement RBAC, what
is RBAC is like, with our, user ID,
they will tie us to a particular group.
And through a particular group, we
will have a role based access that if
I'm part of a developer group, I can
only, do a read only on the cluster.
If I'm part of a DevOps or a like
incident management group, I will
have access to production as an admin.
And if I'm part of some testing group.
I may not even have access to production.
I may only have access to pre prod
or a staging or testing environment.
So that way we can secure, the
user making it part of a certain
group through RBAC policies.
Then we have to, encrypt the etcd.
So etcd is nothing but a database
is a key value database like Redis.
It stores, the cluster sensitive
data, including some secrets
and configuration details.
So these configuration
details, are very sensitive.
They are actually, storing very sensitive
data about the, secrets as well as
the keys, as well as the certificates,
which are used by the API server.
So it's very important to encrypt
all the etcd data, at rest and, only
certain users with admin access be
able to access the etcd database.
Then we will talk about the
network policies by default.
Kubernetes networking is open, which
can expose the cluster to risk.
So that is the way
Kubernetes has been designed.
the networking is open.
We have to make sure that
these network policies are not
accessible by external users.
So we can implement the network
policies using tools like Calico
or Cal, Cillium to control the
communication between the ports and
minimize our potential attack surfaces.
So we'll talk about network policies
in details that how can we make
sure that we have network policies
to secure our infrastructure.
So next we talk about the node security.
so node is how our kubelet, interacts
with the API will be hosted on a node.
So there are, certain aspects
we will talk about here.
So first is the operating
system hardening.
How we can show, make sure that
our operating system like Ubuntu
or wheresoever our application is
hosted, how we can make sure that all
of the operating system is secure.
So nodes should run a minimal hardened
OS version with regular security patches.
Adopting standards, such as the CIS
benchmark, which is the standard
benchmark for security, it's help
reducing vulnerabilities at the OS level.
So important thing here to.
you know, notice that there is
always a security patch, update from
the OS level supports Ubuntu, 20.
04 is secure at a certain level,
which supports a particular
version of Kubernetes.
Once, the Kubernetes patch new
patch comes, it might not be secure.
And that on that particular OS
version, it's always, you have,
we have to make sure that we have.
Updated the OS or the kernel
version with the latest security
patches so we don't open our node
for any kind of vulnerabilities.
So operating system hardening
is really important.
Then we talk about the
container runtime security.
The container runtime security like
Docker or ContainerD with what kind
of, the runtime environment we use is
responsible for managing our containers.
So enforcing security
controls like AppArmor.
AppArmor or SE Linux can limit
the actions containers can take
protecting the host system.
So we'll talk about AppArmor.
we can make a profile and upload
that profile or link that profile to
AppArmor and make sure that only these
kind of rules are allowed in our node.
Like only these kind of rules
we will be allowing on the
node to run and certain rules.
Which are not associated with
the profiles will be discarded.
So we'll create a profile and,
filter all the rules based on the
profile kind of profile we have.
So we have security
measures like app armor.
I will share the resources that
how we can use our app armors.
really cool tool.
it's an open source.
And we can maintain our profiles
with the help of AppArmor and,
secure our run, container runtime.
Then we talk about the kubelet security.
The kubelet, which is an
agent on each node, it runs
as a daemon set on each node.
Each of the node handles the
communication with the control plane.
the node interacts with the control
plane with kubelet, with the kubelet and
that also on a TLS secure communication.
So securing the kubelet with
TLS and restricting the API
access prevents attacker from
manipulating the node operations.
So securing our kubelet is also really
important because I've seen some teams,
they will secure the API server, they
will secure the workloads, but the kubelet
security sometimes is discarded and,
ignored, which, which will allow the
hackers, to make any changes on the node
level and it can create a lot of damage.
Now we spoke about the node security.
Let's talk about the actual
workload security and coming
to the JavaScript applications.
How to secure a JavaScript application
is, part of the workload security.
suppose a JavaScript application is
containerized on a Docker container and
then, is orchestrated on Kubernetes.
that JavaScript container
running application will be
running as a pod inside, and a
pod will be having containers.
initially we had used to.
Call something called
port security policies.
They have been deprecated, but now
we use, something called PSA, which
is port security admission, which
allows the admins to enforce security
policies such as privileged baseline
restricted kind of access on the port.
So the basic fundamental on
securing a workload is give least,
privilege to a running container.
means you give a least privilege that the
user is not able to exec into a container
and run commands on the root level.
Because if any user is able to execute
inside a container and run commands
on a root level, that can even disrupt
all the running applications that
can destroy the network policies and,
the user can you eventually, just do
anything if they have the admin access.
So the least access principle always
is applicable on the workload while
we are talking about security.
And then we talk about runtime
security that we can use tools
like Falco or Aqua security.
To detect some suspicious
activity within the containers.
So what we can do in Falco is create some
rules and if we, if, if those rules are
met, like we have, triggered that if we
see some 5x kind of errors or, 3x kind
of redirects in a container, traffic,
which should not be ideally happening.
So we can actually,
write some Falco rules.
create a Falco policy, write some rules
and, trigger real time monitoring.
If we see those rules are getting, break,
so we can trigger alerts and notify the
users with the help of runtime security.
Then comes the most important
part of securing our, workloads,
which is managing of the secrets.
So secrets are in general, some,
workloads have exposed secrets, which is.
Not a good practice.
So we should always be using, tools
like HashiCorp Vault or maybe, AWS
Secrets Manager or Azure Secrets, which,
whichever cloud provider you're using.
So storing secrets directly
in plain text with Kubernetes
manifest is a common mistake.
it is actually a very big mistake.
if you do, and it can cause,
it can expose your secrets and
anybody access to that secrets.
Can, run your APIs, on the cluster
and, can even, change the data
inside the applications and even,
delete some of the important
configurations in the application.
So secrets management on the workload
security is one of the most, important
way of, securing our applications
and always use, something which has
been provided by the cloud provider,
or, we already have HashiCorp Vault.
they're, ultra secure way
of, managing the secrets.
So now at last, we will talk about
network security, how we can secure
our communication with the outside
world or with the other apps.
So we have something called service mesh.
So like service mesh, most of
the, organizations use, where they
will limit the incoming traffic.
And from there they will distribute
the, traffic based on the network rules.
commonly used service mesh are HTO or
Linkerd, which add an additional layer
of security by enabling a mutual TLS.
So mutual TLS is very secure way of,
communicating, over, a secure protocol.
They encrypt the service to service
communication and they make sure
that, there's a very fine grained
access control given to the user.
So they also use their RBAC policies
on the STO level and they make sure
that the communication is very secure.
So one is using service
mesh on your network.
Second is like you can use
ingress and egress control.
So you can control what traffic can enter
and leave your, cluster by deploying
an nginx ingress controller, which
is a very common ingress controller.
You can define your ingress rule
that you want to, talk to this app.
You don't want to like you
restrict the traffic from this app.
You can create your ingress
rules on the Kubernetes cluster.
So like ingress, controller also
have their inbuilt network policies.
So where you can restrict the external
or internal, IPs, whichever IPs
you want to, allow traffic to, or
you don't want to allow traffic to,
you can just create your network
policies using the ingress control.
Then we'll talk about the DDoS protection.
Kubernetes clusters that are exposed to
the public internet are susceptible to
distributed denial of service attacks.
It's a very common attack
nowadays in the cyber world.
So implement DDoS protection mechanisms
like, again, leverage your cloud
provider, use AWS Shield or there
is Google Cloud Armor as well to
defend against DDoS kind of attacks.
So this was all about, network security.
We Now, talking about the global
impact of Kubernetes security.
basically, what security
does it, it enhances trust.
So securing Kubernetes clusters,
JavaScript applications running on
Kubernetes clusters, we secure them, it
directly impacts the trust that customers
and stakeholders have in digital services.
Security incidents can lead to
significant reputational damage,
As we, talked about before as well
and erode confidence in the digital
transformation efforts of organizations.
So it's so important to, enhance
our trust, in our end users.
So protecting our critical infrastructure,
Kubernetes is now a very critical
part of managing infrastructure
in industries like healthcare,
finance and telecommunications.
A security breach in these
environments, suppose, some
person's health data is breached.
Such a, big data loss and such a, Big
thing to, lose the confidence of customers
providing their health data so it can
actually have catastrophic effects.
Global sec, cybersecurity contribution.
As Kubernetes becomes, more widespread,
its security becomes a vital part of the
global cybersecurity ecosystem as a whole.
By enhancing Kubernetes security, we
protect our, broader digital landscape.
working on security, cybersecurity.
Sometimes I feel, I'm a
cyber warrior protecting.
The internet.
I really feel proud of, I'm part
of, securing something and helping
users to, protect their data.
So it's a big ownership, cyber security
engineers carry with them and, working
on such, cutting edge technologies
like Kubernetes and learning how
to leverage all this technology to
protect the data is actually, amazing.
open source standards like
Kubernetes also is open sources.
Most of the things are,
actually free to use.
like so much code is, posted on
GitHub where we can leverage that
code and secure our clusters.
It basically sets a security standard
for the broad and open source community,
encourages them influencing the
security practices of other projects.
Being this open source is actually
a very much, an inspiration for
all to, even, use the code and even
contribute to the open source community.
So now, We'll do some examples on
the JavaScript applications, some
security considerations, which I
spoke about, but I want to give
some examples on that as well.
So always run containers
as non root users.
That's a rule of thumb that, if I, if you
see that always create a non root user,
and never give a root kind of access.
So here I've used user called app user.
So I'm not giving a root kind of access.
To the user implement network security,
policies like restrict traffic between
the ports, leverage namespace and
labels, which are Kubernetes properties.
And even with, using the labels,
proper labels and namespace, you can
secure applications like the way,
examples shows that we have used,
something, metadata called name allow
node js, and we have pod selectors.
We will match the labels.
With the help of these, pod selectors
and we can define rules like ingress or
egress where we can, make sure that, the
only this kind of namespace is allowed
or only these kind of pods, which have
those labels matching are being allowed,
to serve the traffic and then manage
secrets securely, already spoke about
Kubernetes secrets and, never expose
your secrets in plain text, at least
have a base 64 type of encoding for
your secrets and use HashiCorp Vault.
They will, there's a very super
way of securing your secrets.
also we'll go through some
security best practices.
Always do or perform regular audits on
your infrastructure, perform, audits
of your Kubernetes configuration
and ensure that all the components
are configured securely, do a MFA,
enforce MFA in your projects, in your
organizations, encourage people to
use MFA for, enforce MFA for accessing
critical systems like the Kube, Kube API
to add in regional layer of protection.
Monitoring and alerting
is always important.
We can use.
Leverage tools like Prometheus,
Grafana, Kibana, and integrate
runtime security solutions to detect
any kind of suspicious behavior.
So we can use our Falco rules, integrate
them with, Prometheus and the user,
an engineer on call can get notified
of any, rules getting, if the rules
are getting, break during and we can,
detect vulnerabilities in that case.
Also, again, pointing out, apply the
least privilege principle always,
always give a least privilege to any
users or systems, having, they should
have the minimum access necessary to
perform their basic functions until and
unless they're part of the admin team.
Stay updated, always stay updated
with the security patches.
even the OS level patches and, the
Kubernetes, kernel patches because,
the security patches will make sure
that the vulnerabilities are removed
from the latest security patch and all
the dependencies with the underlying
OS match with those security patches.
really important to focus on.
Then, sharing these additional resources
for you to check on like official
documentation from Kubernetes, some
Falco related docs, some cheat sheets
of Kubernetes, sharing resources about
AppArmor, SecCom, and encrypting the
data at rest, really crucial for,
securing, our, JavaScript applications
running on these, Kubernetes clusters.
also listed some couple of really,
vital books, which helped me gain
knowledge and, apply that, implement
that knowledge, on my projects.
so this is Kubernetes up and
running by Kelsey Hightower,
really, big, fan of this book.
And then this is Node.
js design patterns by, Mario.
This also is a really good book
if you want your expert in Node.
js applications, it can really help you
leverage what kind of, security measures
as well as the scalable measures you can
take for the JavaScript applications.
And then feel free to join these
communities because these are
open source communities like the
Kubernetes community and the Node.
js community as well as the
Kubernetes public slack.
It's really handy to, give you the, what
are the latest developments going on and,
what kind of, people, issues people are
having in their JavaScript applications,
as well as, what kind of issues they're
having in deploying these applications
and running them on Kubernetes, platform.
now I like, I'm almost at the,
conclusion part of my talk.
We have discussed a lot about
security, how we can prevent our
applications, from vulnerabilities,
how we can at least secure our
JavaScript applications running.
And we also went through some examples.
So concluding my talk, I will talk
about, leveraging Kubernetes with
JavaScript empowers developers
to build scalable, resilient, as
well as efficient applications
by embracing containerization.
Automated deployments and robust
orchestration JavaScript applications
can actually meet the demands
of modern dynamic environments.
Whether we are building microservices,
real time applications, or serverless
functions, the synergy between Kubernetes
and JavaScript offers a very powerful
foundation of innovation and growth.
We saw, so much growth is possible
and there's so many options
for these applications to run.
Kubernetes security is not just
about protecting a single cluster.
It's about safeguarding the
critical infrastructure that
businesses and societies depend on.
As the adoption of Kubernetes continues
to rise, securing these clusters becomes
paramount to ensuring trust and security.
Reliability and scalability,
stability in digital systems.
So by this, I'm coming
to the end of my talk.
I hope you guys learned here and you
will take key learnings with you.
it was really a privilege
to speak on this conference.
I just thank all the organizers to giving
me an opportunity to present my thoughts.
And, also thank you all my listeners
who were there to, witness my talk.
I hope.
You really liked it.
And if you have any questions, you
can reach me out to the email, which
is being showed on your screen.
Again, it was, really a wonderful
experience giving this talk and hope to
connect with you guys soon in future.
Thank you so much.