Good morning, everyone.
Welcome to CONF42.
My name is Alon Mironik and I work
for Blackduck, where I manage the
R& D efforts for the Seeker agents.
Seeker, in case you haven't heard
about it or rather haven't heard
about it yet, is probably the
best IAST tool out there today.
But as fascinating as IAST is,
it's just not my topic today.
So this is the last time
I'm going to mention Seeker.
Instead, Today, I want to talk about
DOS attacks, what they are, and how
we can prevent them in our Node.
js applications.
Now, if you're my age or older, when
you hear DOS, you're probably thinking
of a really outdated operating system.
One would argue that running your Node.
js application on this operating
system is a vulnerability as of, as
in itself, but this isn't the type
of DOS I'm talking about today.
Today I want to talk
about denial of service.
For those of you unfamiliar with this
concept, let's go straight to the source
and see what OWASP has to say about this.
So the denial of service or
DOS attack is focused on making
a resource such as a site, an
application, or server unavailable
for the purpose it was designed.
And of course, a lot of you, when thinking
about DOS, instinctively think about DDoS.
distributed denial of service, which is
an attack where you hit an application or
server or whatever with multiple requests
from multiple sources and essentially
crash it or bring it to a grinding halt
just by the sheer volume of requests.
This is a very real problem.
And a very interesting topic to
discuss, but since we are in the
JavaScript conference today, I will
not be talking about DDoS at all.
Today, I will be focusing
on the application.
What can we do from the
applicative side in our Node.
js applications?
to prevent for argument's sake
a single request from creating a
denial of service or DOS effect.
Now, this won't fully
solve all of our problems.
Our applications may still be vulnerable
to distributed denial of service
attacks, but by making our application
secure from DOS attacks, first of all,
we are reducing the attack surface for
distributed denial of service attacks.
And secondly, we try to follow
the principle of solving the
right problem in the right place.
On the application side that we
will discuss today, we will see how
to make our application resilient
against a single request that causes
a malicious denial of service.
Solving distributed denial of service
attacks is usually done not in the
application level, but in the deployment
level, with rate limits and size limits
and load balancers and things like that,
which again is just not the topic today.
And we will not focus on that too much.
let's reel it back in and
let's focus on the application.
Specifically, our Node.
js application.
let's start with a quick
reminder on how Node.
js even works.
And this is a gross oversimplification.
There's actually really good
documentation in the Node.
js project about this.
So if you want all the gory details,
please don't take my word for it,
but read up yourself, but very
briefly and very oversimplified node
is designed to scale really well.
The basic design for node is a single
main thread called the event loop, which
should handle all of your user requests.
And the design tailors to applications
where you have really small chunks of
work on the event loop, and anything
that takes a longer time, usually
IO, but not necessarily, is delegated
to a worker thread, which is then
executed by a limited number of
threads out of a given worker pool.
Now, this design helps node,
excuse me, scale in two ways.
First of all, by having a limited
number of threads, We don't waste system
resources on opening and closing and
managing threads like older designs
and older web servers might do.
Second, and what Node got right here
in my mind, is the responsiveness.
When a request comes in, you want
to handle it really quickly, be
able to take it in, understand what
you need to do, and then delegate
whatever long work you have, and maybe
respond a bit later, asynchronously.
But the idea is that every chunk
of work, every tick on the event
loop needs to be really small.
And that way you can always get a
new one whenever a user request comes
in, you are not blocking anything.
This is something crucial to remember.
This design is the core
of Node's performance.
That is the core of why
Node can scale this well.
And, unfortunately, it's also the
core reason of why Node can, Node.
js applications at least, can be
really vulnerable to DOS attacks if
you don't write them the right way.
Just to hammer this point back home,
a lot of people when they think about
DOS, they think about performance.
Thanks.
which is a good correlation to make.
But preventing DOS attacks is
not about speed, or at least
it's not just about speed.
Of course, however faster your
application is, it's more difficult
to create a DOS attack on it.
But the core point here isn't
slowing things down, It is
blocking other requests, legitimate
requests, from being served.
So if a malicious request takes two
hours to fulfill, that might be okay.
The core issue here is not that it
took two hours, but whether during
these two hours, we are able to
serve legitimate user requests.
how can we block a Node.
js application?
How can we tie up the event loop?
it sounds really fancy and really
dangerous and really far fetched.
It really isn't.
We will see a few examples of
really common practices, things
we are used to find in virtually
any application that could tie
us up if implemented incorrectly.
Probably the most obvious
example is JSON parsing.
We get the JSON, we get, sorry,
we get a request with a body.
This body is in JSON format.
the HTTP client will save
that, of course, as a string.
And then we want to parse it.
In this example, we have the
express middleware doing it for
us, but that's beside the point.
The body is parsed into a
JSON, and here we have a simple
application that just prints out
the number of keys in this JSON.
Now, this is a sneaky example.
It isn't obvious here.
Our callback function in the post
handler is running very fast.
It doesn't do anything.
The sneaky part here is the JSO passing.
That happens in the express
model way, and the obvious way
to overload this middleware is
to just send a really large JSON.
Now, I was trying to figure out
how I can illustrate this and
show you how bad this really is.
And as a DOS geek, I was
struggling to find a way.
But then I remembered I'm
not really a DOS geek.
I'm a DOS nerd.
The difference is a geek will tell you
about something they're passionate about.
A nerd will tell you about
something they're passionate about.
With a graph.
So indeed, I graphed this out.
I graphed out the time it takes to serve
this request as a function of the length
of the body of the JSON in the body.
in kilobytes for argument's sake, and
we can see it is more or less linear.
Now, I know I said it isn't about
speed, but again, the key point here
is that this JSON passing, which
under the hood, under all of Express's
bells and whistles, just calls Node.
js's JSON.
pass is executed on the event loop.
however long this takes, It will
block any other requests from
being served during this time.
as an attacker, if I can have my
application handle an arbitrary
long JSON, I can tie it up
for a linear amount of time.
depending on the size
of the JSON I send over.
As defenders, as application
authors, what can we do about this?
quite a bit.
First of all, obviously, if we don't
allow tainted input or user controlled
input to be parsed as JSON, no problem.
This is great.
It's not really realistic.
JSON parsing is ubiquitous.
JavaScript is in general and Node.
js in particular, a lot of applications
or services pass information
between them in a JSON format.
So just saying never pass any string
you get from an outside untrusted
source as a JSON is not realistic.
More realistically, you
can just limit the size.
A length check is a very cheap operation,
and if you can just limit the size and
double check the length before you try
to pass this long string as a JSON,
you have solved a lot of the problem.
The key here is to know your applications.
Get to know how your applications behave.
Get to know what a reasonable,
valid user input is.
Maybe Add some buffers for
extreme cases, but limit the size.
Don't allow the application or
the model way in this case to
just pass arbitrary long strings.
This is a real example I saw in
a customer a couple of years ago.
They had a very
straightforward login screen.
You type in your username, your password.
The front end takes these values,
puts them together in the jsun,
sends over to the backend.
The backend either authenticates
or doesn't, and sets a cookie.
They had eight character
usernames and I think passwords
were limited to 12 characters.
Let's say the JSON
format has some overhead.
For argument's sake, 40 characters
together, 50 to handle extreme
cases, and I don't know what.
Why in the world would you allow your
backend for a simple username password
login screen to parse a 2MB long JSON?
Absolutely no reason.
The only reason to do
that is just carelessness.
It's forgetting to set a size limit.
set your size limits.
Where you can't set your size
limits, where you do expect really
long, big JSONs, because this is
the protocol, this is how your
application shares information.
Maybe don't do it on the event loop.
Don't use express.
json.
Definitely don't use json.
parse yourself.
But use a different library
that can process large JSONs.
In the background as an asynchronous
task libraries like JSON stream or
BFJ that stands for Big Friendly JSON
and no, you will not convince me the
F stands for anything but friendly.
Now, just to hammer this home
again, this is not necessarily fast.
Using BFJ for argument's sake is
explicitly slower than using JSON.
parse.
They even say so themselves
in the documentation.
But, speed isn't really the point here.
We don't care if this parsing takes
a bit longer, as long as it's done
in a worker thread and does not
prevent us from accepting or serving
the next request that comes in.
But okay, enough about JSON.
This was boring.
An attacker can only get a linear
effect to the size of their input.
It's a threat, it's not a terrible
threat, and it's still pretty
hard to do damage like this.
Let's look at something a bit different.
Let's say we aren't just overloading
our parser, we're bombing it.
And the classic example is XML.
So again, I have a very
simple application.
It takes a request, a POST request,
retrieves the body, parses it
as XML, and returns the number
of child nodes in the payload.
Thank you.
Not super interesting, but I
threatened that we are going to
bomb our parser, which sounds quite
serious, actually too serious.
It's frightening.
So let's relax.
Let's have a couple of laughs.
In fact, let's have a billion laughs.
This is the XML variant of an attack
called the billion laughs attack.
And what this attack essentially
does It takes advantage of, if
you'll excuse the phrase, XML
being too smart for its own good.
XML isn't just about angular
brackets, it's a really smart
format with a lot of functionality.
One of the things that allows you
to do is define entities, and even
worse, it allows you to reference
these entities by other entities.
So this really small, textually
wise, really small XML has a
content of the lol9 entity.
But if we look at the definition,
lol9 is made out of, made up,
excuse me, out of 10 lol8 elements.
lol8 is made up of 10 lol7 elements.
And so on and so forth till you go back
to the 10 by the power of 10 elements.
And it's really hard.
It's really not hard to imagine
that with a textually really
small XML, you can expand this to
something really large in memory.
So once again, I'm not a DOS geek.
I'm a DOS nerd.
So I graphed this out, and in this graph,
I have two, two lines, the size of the XML
as a function of the number of LUL levels,
and the size this expands to in memory as
a function of the number of LUL levels.
And we can see the discrepancy
here really quickly.
Okay.
Up to four low levels.
It's really small.
Nobody really cares.
Six, it starts kicking up.
With seven levels, you still have
a tiny, teeny, tiny textual XML.
It's just 650 bytes.
It doesn't, not even a kilobyte.
But this expands in
memory to about 30 megs.
If you continue this graph in your
imagination, which I didn't do because
it would just be impossible to see,
eight levels kicks up to about a gig, nine
levels kicks up to something ridiculously
large with a really small payload.
So what can we do?
Again, let's start with obvious solutions.
If you don't use XML, you are
not vulnerable to DOS attacks
that rely on XML expansion.
If you can do this, great.
If you're designing a system from
scratch, just decide that you
will not use XMLs and you're fine.
Quite often can't do this because
your system or service is part of
something larger, some whole flow,
a new microservice in an Existing
mesh of services, and the XML
transport is predetermined for you.
Similarly, even if you absolutely have
to parse XMLs because that's how your
configuration is built, that doesn't
mean you need to allow XML parsing from
tainted, external, untrusted sources.
Again, if possible.
If an attacker can't inject an
XML into the system, even though
the system uses XMLs in other
places, you're probably fine.
But again, this is not
always possible or plausible.
If you can't do this,
Learn about the parser you use,
learn about the library you use.
Quite often, you can configure this
library and switch features on and off.
For example, if you don't need the
capability to define entities, And I must
admit, I've been a software engineer and
an engineering manager for about 24 years.
I think I remember one case where I saw
a system that really needed to define
entities like that on the fly in XML.
So if you don't need it, switch it off for
the common libxml wrappers like libxml.
js in our example.
You can set no int to false or
huge to false and you're good.
Of course, you can always use a library
that just doesn't support these features.
Again, if you can, if you don't
need these features, just do it.
If you don't need the power
to define entities, don't give
your attackers this power.
And of course, the cardinal
law of application security.
If you're getting any tainted input from
an external source, input that you do not
trust or should not trust, sanitize it.
Go over it, make sure there's
nothing funky or malicious
there before you try parsing it.
Not after, that would be too
late, before you try passing it.
And I know this is a recorded talk,
but even if, even though it is, and
even though I'm just sitting here in my
study recording this with no audience,
I can already hear the Snickers.
of people writing more modern applications
in modern formats who don't use xml
and never used xml and never wish
to use xml and think they are safe.
you are safe, of course, from any attacks
based on XML if you don't use XML, but
I'm sorry to be the harbinger of bad news.
If you are using YAML, you probably
have the exact same problem.
YAML also allows defining entities, again,
parser, of course, but generally speaking,
the format also allows defining entities.
It allows recursively.
referencing entities from other entities.
And just as we have XML
bombs, we have YAML bombs.
Luckily, the same tactics we discussed to
prevent DOS by XML or DOS, or excuse me,
XML bombs will of course work for YAMLs.
But okay, enough about annoying
formats that we all love to hate or
hate to love, your dealer's choice.
Let's talk about something even
more ubiquitous to JavaScript.
Let's talk about regexes.
I dare you to write any good sized
application without a regex somewhere.
And if it isn't in your code, It's
probably in some third party you're using.
In fact, even this most basic
Express application, even without the
callback, has regexes baked in there.
Because Express needs to take the
URL, break it up, and understand
what handler to match this request.
So the regexes are there.
But anyway, let's talk about,
let's focus on the user code here.
The user code.
It's really simple.
It takes two query parameters, regex and a
text to test this, to test by this regex.
Performs this test and returns whether the
text matches or did not match the regex.
Sounds straightforward enough.
The problem here is that, and this
is a recurring theme, regexes can
be too smart for their own good.
Or more importantly, too
smart for your own good.
Javascript tricaxes, which are PCRAs,
Perl Compliant Regular Expressions,
have a feature called backtracking.
You can define a capturing
group, and then a wildcard, that
applies to this capturing group.
And this capturing group
can have its own wildcard.
So consider for example a regex
like the regex in the comment here.
Open, open parentheses, a
plus, close parentheses, plus.
Now this regex in layman terms means
A series of one or more As, one
or more times, which, excuse the
language, is a really stupid way
of saying a string made up of As.
We could have defined this as just
A But for the example's sake, we
purposely define it like this.
Now, think about the poor regex
engine that needs to take a
string and test with this regex.
Consider your input is 10 characters.
The poor regex engine will need to
test if it's 1a followed by 9a's,
if it's 2a's followed by 8a's,
2 groups of 1a's followed by a
group of 8a's, 2 groups of 1a's.
Followed by two groups of four
A's and so on and so forth.
It gets really ugly really quickly.
How ugly?
How quickly?
Again, as I said, I am a DOS nerd.
we graphed it out.
In this benchmark, I took a string
which is made up of a series of A's
followed by a single B character.
This is to prevent the Regex
engine from failing fast and saying
there's no possible combination.
By doing this, I have forced the Regex
engine to check all the permutations
up to the length of the string.
And I just tied this regex with
increasingly long strings, so a
followed by a b, two a's followed by
a b, three a's followed by a b, and so
on, and graphed out how slow this is.
And again, I am, I want to emphasize,
this Speed itself isn't the issue.
the time itself isn't the issue.
The issue is that evaluating Techn,
RegX happens on the Event Loop.
So however long or short list takes
will type up the event loop and make
you make your application at least
unable to serve other requests.
So how bad is it up to about.
28, 29, let's say, for argument's
sake, even 30, 31 A's followed
by a B, it's not too bad.
under half a second,
we can live with that.
And of course not.
50, 000 milliseconds is 50 seconds,
but under 50 seconds, under a minute,
we can probably live with that.
But at about the 31 A's
mark, it really kicks up.
In 33 seconds, it takes 50
milliseconds, which is almost a minute.
Okay.
With 35 As, it takes a bit shy of 300.
milliseconds, which is 300 minutes,
300 seconds, which is about five minutes.
As you can see, this presentation
has lost my ability to do math.
So I will rephrase in 35 characters, we
get about 300 seconds, which is under
five, but under 300 seconds, which is
a bit under five minutes, which is It's
slow and annoying and let's say it's
the outer edge of what you'd be able to
expect when I'm trying to go up to 36 A's.
This simple Node.
js application just took up so much
memory, so much CPU power, it completely
killed my computer to the point where
the music I was listening to while
making this graph started lagging.
So I just killed the benchmark
and said, okay, that's it.
And if you think about it, An
attacker being able to send a
payload that is 35 or 36 characters
long has not that far fetched.
It is not a big payload.
This is a really easy attack if your
application is vulnerable to it.
So what can we do to prevent this?
First of all, if you have a regex,
baked into your application.
Just check your regex.
Make double sure, triple sure,
quadruple sure that this regex does
not have a backtracking part in it.
There's tons of tools to do this.
Generally speaking, SAST,
static analysis security testing
tools, are really good at this.
Test your regexes.
make sure that you don't have
something super dangerous
baked into your application.
Now, if this isn't your regex, which is
hardcoded coded in your code, if it's
some valuable input, first of all, If
you can, don't allow tainted input,
user controlled input, as a regex.
This isn't always possible, especially
if you think about applications that
have search capabilities with wildcards.
It isn't always possible, but if you are
going that way, maybe don't allow the end
user to input a straight up regex, but
have some a simplified wildcard syntax
like allow asterisks and that's about it
where you take the string and convert it
to a regex in the back end in your code.
So clearly it's still affected by
user input but you can't say it's
completely controlled by it and if a
user can't input any arbitrary regex
with backtracking It could be okay.
Kind of following up on
that, if you to have a regex.
Maybe don't allow a regex that
you know can be dodgy to evaluate
user input, tainted input.
Okay, this is usually not possible.
We usually don't use regexes to
evaluate data we know, but data
we don't know, which usually
comes from some external source.
But if you are doing this, and you can't
avoid having a tainted input, dodgy
regex, at least, again, use length limits.
We've seen in the graph that the
time we tie up a regex is really
dependent on the length of the input.
So even if it is a really bad regex,
but you limit the length of the input,
a user, or in our case, an attacker can
fail it on this regex, it could be okay.
And of course, as always, maybe don't
use regex, maybe use some alternatives.
First of all, still in the Regex realm,
instead of using JavaScripts built in
Regex, you can use a package like RE2.
RE2 is not a PCRE.
It is not a Perl compliant
regular expression.
It is much, much less powerful.
But, if you don't need all of this power,
and you can suffice with the functionality
that RE2 gives you, RE2, because it
doesn't have all the bells and whistles,
because it doesn't have bell tracking,
backtracking is not vulnerable to Redos.
So maybe that's a valid
alternative in your use case.
Also, maybe don't invent the wheel.
A lot of the times you don't
need a general purpose regex.
A lot of the time you use
regex for really scoped tasks.
Like checking input, if something is
a valid email, valid address, valid
URL, then write your own regexes.
Use proven tools that someone else
wrote and tested and verified are safe.
Validator.
js, for example, in the Node.
js ecosystem, has a ton of
regexes, a ton of regexes.
validators.
Most of them are implemented by regexes
to check inputs for a ton of needs,
including All sorts of ISO standards, I
admit, I never heard about, like standard
for shipping container identifiers.
If you can avoid writing your
own regex, by all means do Now,
the last type of DOS attack is
something near and dear to my heart.
Having done storage professionally
for a lot of years before
moving to application security.
this again is a really simple application.
Once It gets a request, it
reads the file from disk.
There's no user input involved here.
Reads the file from disk and
returns it back to the response.
Now, of course, this is a
really stupid application.
If this were a real use case,
I'd read this file once,
store it in memory, cache it.
But for the demonstration's
sake, This is a valid way to
implement such an application.
And if this weren't a demo, you can
think about an application that has
various files to read or whatever.
Now, the Tosya is really sneaky.
Who's If we think about storage
in no js, there are two ways
we can do storage operations.
We have the Async way, such as FS three
deal, or Fs right file, which delegates
the IO to a worker thread and all
sorts of third party libraries like F.
S, extra Graceful Affairs, A
DMZ also have the same patterns,
perform a call.
You provide a callback, the IER happens.
In a worker thread, in the
background, does not block the event
loop, and once the IR is done, you
get a callback with the result.
Now, if the first way of handling
storage is the async way, the
second way is clearly the wrong way.
So any API and specifically storage
that declares that's a sync API,
so FS read deal sync, FS write file
sync, same goes for ADM zip APIs, for
FS extra APIs, for any API, frankly,
not even necessarily storage related.
is explicitly telling you that it will
be performing its work on the event loop.
Now, it's often more convenient to code
like this because you aren't messing
around with callbacks or promises and
everything is just straightforward.
But the price you're paying is that
you are blocking the event loop.
Now, this Sometimes can be okay,
especially in the context of the
application starting up and it's
not serving user requests, etc.
But if you are in the context of a user
request, any API that declares that it's
synchronous and blocking the event loop,
should simply be out of the question.
Should be something that you don't
use and don't even consider using.
Now, this form of DOS is sneaky because
we have become very accustomed to
personal computers, which have SSD
and NVMe and all manner of really
fast drives, that we don't always have
this in the forefront of our mind.
But storage can be slow, and especially
outside of our development environment,
while we deploy our code to some third
party cloud provider, which uses some
third party storage, which we have no
control over and no idea how fast or more
often than not slow it is, don't trust it.
Don't give it the chance
to block your event loop.
Delegate everything to async APIs.
And yes, it is a bit more complicated.
It does arguably make
the code a bit uglier.
It does arguably make it a bit
harder to debug and maintain.
But from a DOS perspective, this isn't
just a better way of writing code.
It's the right way of writing code.
Don't make your users suffer
because As a developer, you were
a tad lazy and wanted to just call
a sync API and be done with it.
Put in the extra couple of minutes.
It usually isn't much more than that.
Couple of minutes of effort and do
your storage calls or do whatever call.
If there's a sync and async variant of
the API do it with the async variant.
Your users will thank you
with this, I think, Nearing the end.
So just want to sum up here and give
you some takeaways from this talk
when we're thinking about application
security, especially if we are web
developers or application developers
that don't usually focus on application
security, we focus on our applications.
of course, we want them to
be secure, but we focus.
first and foremost on functionality.
We usually think about instinctively
about injection attacks, about our
SQL injections and XSS malicious
payloads, doing malicious things
to applications, which is all true.
And if you're thinking about those and
defending against those, That's great.
But don't forget about DOS.
Don't forget about denial of service.
Quite often, from an attacker's
perspective, it is considerably
easier to exploit DOS vulnerability
than an injection vulnerability.
It takes considerably less
skill to do so successfully.
And while it might not be possible to
steal all your data by DOS vulnerability,
it is relatively easy to Bring your
application to a screeching halt where
it cannot serve its legitimate users.
So you may have not lost anything,
nothing was stolen, but your
business isn't working anymore.
How do we defend against DOS applications?
There's a couple of really
simple takeaways to remember.
First of all, if we already are thinking
about security, we do not allow user
inputs or tainted inputs to places
where they have no business to be.
If we do, we sanitize them, specifically
in the DOS perspective, we sanitize
them against attacks that might exploit
our parser, being XML, YAML, whatever.
Regardless of sanitation, we use
length limits and size limits.
These are really easy to implement.
They won't prevent 100 percent of the
attacks, but they do make DOS attacks
considerably more difficult to pull off.
Also, even regardless of DOS
attacks, mistakes happen, users
do crazy stuff, don't allow them
to bombard you with huge inputs if
there's no business value for it.
And lastly, think about the libraries,
think about the APIs you're using.
Think about whether they're running in
the event loop or in a worker thread.
And if they are running in an event
loop, in the event loop, chances are
there's either a different library or
a different API within that library you
can use to delegate to a worker thread.
and learn the configurations quite
often really easy to set up an
application that would just work
with the default configurations.
Quite often these configurations
aren't only not geared towards
security, they aren't geared
towards production usage in general.
So once you have your prototype working,
take a minute to review the configuration.
Maybe you want to switch
off feature flags.
Maybe you want to add a length limit.
Maybe you want to add
some built in sanitation.
Get to know your project.
The APIs and libraries you're using, it
won't only make you more security aware,
it will make you a better programmer and
it will make your application better.
With that, I am really done.
If any of this resonates with you,
I do invite you to keep in touch.
I am not a hard person to find.
Can reach me on LinkedIn, on X, Twitter,
by email, by all means, reach out.
Let's keep this conversation going.
And thank you.
Thank you for listening.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you for considering the
security of your applications
and not just the functionality.
And have a great conference.