Welcome to today's talk about
building real-time feature
pipelines and JavaScript's role in
modern data-driven applications.
In the next few minutes, I'll walk through
how JavaScript can power the entire
feature lifecycle for ingesting events,
computing features, caching them for
sub millisecond rates, and running ML
inference at the edge and in the browser.
Coming to the evolution of web
applications, we've moved from batch
driven server rendered pages to
dynamic personalized applications.
Modern users expect real-time updates
and context aware UI that shift requires
features, computed now not overnight,
and delivered with predictable latency.
In traditional architecture, as you
can see, we've had server rendered
pages, batch data processing,
and the feature updates were
consistently and delayed by a lot.
So in modern data driven applications,
the users are expecting more realtime
feature computations and instant model
inference and hyper-personalized content,
which is modeled according to their needs,
their activity, and their preferences.
To the feature pipeline challenge in
this, the real time pipelines face.
Three hard problems.
Past feature computation, fresh,
yet efficient caching and consistent
logic across node servers,
edge workers, and browsers.
In feature computation we have steps
like processing raw data into useful
features that to at scale with as less
data garbage as possible and maintaining
low latency and high throughput.
Within caching, we want to balance
freshness with performance.
We want to have as close to real time
data as possible, but at the same time,
inter with intelligent storage and
retrieval mechanisms, we need to make
sure that the performance stays intact.
If we miss any one of these, we get stale
experiences, training, serving SKU and
jittery performances which eventually
results in cross environment consistency.
Now coming to why we need
JavaScript for feature pipelines,
JavaScript is universal.
The same modules run on node at
the edge and in browser it has
rich ecosystem for streams, caches,
inference, and syco aate maps cleanly.
So that map cleanly, that maps
cleanly to event driven workloads.
So when we come to native ing support,
it's about built in JavaScript has
built in ing and evade patterns
and event prevent architecture.
That means that, it's readily suited
for realtime ingestions or realtime data
streams, and there is a non characteristic
of non-blocking IO operations, which
is essential for low latency pipelines.
Coming to the ecosystem JavaScript
leverages mature libraries for data
processing, streaming caching, also from
Apache Kafka clients to TensorFlow js.
The JavaScript ecosystem
provides production ready
tools for every pipeline stage.
So when it comes to as I said
previously, when it comes to streaming
data with Kafka, Evenflow looks
like this, it, it starts with an
ingestion and then to transform and
then to publish With Kafka in Node JI.
We consume user events, compute rolling
counts or session stats, and publish
features to red our downstream topics.
We keep transformer, we keep transforms.
Item, pot and window, so retrace and
back pressure, don't corrupt results.
Here's an example and you can see in the
slide which is about consuming new events
or creating events for downstream topics.
And use this Kafka, we try to build a
real time feature serving architecture,
which contains, which essentially
contains four building blocks.
One is a future competition
service in node, where Node just
microservices process the incoming
data streams and compute features
using the con corresponding business
logic and corresponding statistical
transformations, which we build as
data engineers or data scientists
based on the needs of the company.
Two Redis feature store with sensible tls.
We where with the register, we, the
computed features are cash in red
with a configurable time to live
values enabling sub millisecond
retrieval for online inferences.
And coming to three, it's about the
importance of web sockets, which
push updates instead of polling.
And fourth is the edge or browser in.
So the UI reacts instantly because that's
the end goal of interacting and app.
The where the application
interacts with the user.
And that browser applications used
cached features with TensorFlow JS
or O-N-N-X-J js, and any similar
libraries to run ML models locally,
eliminating the server round trips.
So when it comes to.
Let, when it comes to implementing
efficient caching, caching strategies
within Redis or similar tool like a pub
sub server we use multilayer caching
by access pattern, browser memory.
For OnPage hot features, Redis for
shared online reads and edge cache
for global reach, we balance freshness
and cost with TTLs plus pops up or
web sockets to refresh just in time.
As you can see in the diagram, we have
a browser memory cache, and between
the CDN and the actual browser, we
have a distributed cache, which is
distributed across regions and is
readily available for users based on
their needs, based on the activity and
based on the traffic through, from and
through the server for that website.
Because some websites or some
applications do have like peak
times, off peak, et cetera.
So when it comes to adhering to client
side ml inference with JavaScript we have
today browsers and edge runtime can run
realtime ml. We have lot of browsers.
Like recently, Chad GPT released a
browser called Atlas that was completely
built on top of charge GPT and running
AI models within the system locally.
So we want to load a lightweight
model, read the cached features.
Call predict and render.
So what happens with this is
it reduces latency, it protects
privacy and lower serving costs.
Here we have an example of using Tanza j
TensorFlow gs, which actually runs a model
locally on the system, on the computer.
And then it it performs feature
engineering, extract the features
and does a prediction based on the
user activity or user usage patterns.
So when it comes to ensuring server
client logic, consistency we, one
of the biggest challenges in feature
pipelines is maintaining identical
behavior across different environments.
And removing a, like we want to remove
inconsistent feature competition, which
leads to training, serving skew, and
the model performance degrades despite.
Like already we are deploying a
lightweight model onto the system.
So we want to keep the data as pristine
or as clean as possible so that we
avoid unpredictable user experiences.
So for, and we want to ship isomorphic
modules for the feature logic.
We test with same fixtures in node and
the browser, and we locks schemas with
TypeScript types or J schema and monitor
distribution to catch the drift early.
So these are the four steps which
we perform to make sure that we want
to en to ensure the server client
logic is performing consistently
across different environments.
And once we do this performance
tuning, we want to make sure that
we monitor the perfor performance.
So for that, we use a different me
like important metrics like track.
Where we track throughput, error rates,
resource usage, feature freshness, and
end-to-end latency from ingestion to ui.
We use these signals to tune
window sizes, cash details, model
size, and fan out strategies.
I. So some of the key metrics to track
over here are in within the latency
distributions which is very important.
We have the P 50, P 95 and P 99 latency.
We which for like feature competition
retrieval and inference operations.
We watch these latencies and also other
attributes like features per second, cash
hit ratio, web socket delivery success
and skew between training and serving
These metrics will actually help us
to understand where to optimize first.
So in some cases we might need to increase
the resource utilization as I said,
during peak on, off peak times, or in
some cases we need to scale it down to
save some costs, or in some cases we might
need to understand or tweak the feature
engineering so that we can create fresh
features rather than using stale features.
So when it comes to practical application
patterns we generally think about
three common wins recommendations that
update with every interaction which are
highly used in recommendation engines,
be it streaming app or any e-commerce
applications, et cetera, where we
build personalized product or content
recommendations based on user interaction,
item similarity, computations, and and
different AB testing, Strat strategy.
And there's also a thing of personalized
UI and predictive prefetching.
What that does is it does dynamic
content filtering, and it does ui
contextual UI adaptations and based
on the user's next step or the
prediction, it does the local model do.
It fetches it fetches the
data or it fetches what the
user might need in future.
And does adaptive notification timing.
We also have live analytics with
client side aggregations, which
are streamed over web sockets
for us to monitor in the backend.
Some of the architectural best
practices to achieve these goals
are decomp, compute, decouple
compute from serving so you can
scale the end version independently.
Designed for failure with fallback
values and grateful TTLs version.
Features like APIs to roll forward
are back or roll back safely.
So to achieve this, when it comes to
implementation roadmap, we start simple.
We ship offline features with the
cache, and then slowly start adding
real time computation with Kafka.
And then we start by introducing
client side inference.
With small models, which can
be installed locally or which
can understand user patterns.
And then we scale based on observed
metrics which is completely data
driven, D data bag and not assumptions.
Coming to some of the key takeaways
when it comes to building this
end-to-end pipelines using JavaScript.
JavaScript is basically a one language
across the stack that reduces friction
because it can be used on the UI side,
on the client side, on the server side,
so it can be used across the entire stack
so that, it reduces friction within the
engineers and also the makes the code
readable, makes the maintenance easier.
And streaming plus caching delivers
fresh, low latency features.
Client said ML is production
ready and privacy friendly.
Together, these enable
hyper-personalized experiences at scale.
Thank you so much.
I'm Chen Shekar.
Shari Kuri again, and I'm happy
to connect and discuss more.
Thank you.