Hi everyone.
I'm Amala Han.
I work as a principal data engineer
at a management consulting firm.
I have over a decade of experience
in leading the data architecture
and digital transformations,
building scalable and robust data
pipelines at an enterprise scale.
Thank you for joining with me Today we
are going to talk about how generative
AI is reshaping the healthcare
insurance workflows, particularly in
claims processing and fraud detection.
This is a space undergoing massive
transformation, and gene AI opens
a door to possibilities we couldn't
reach with traditional automation.
Let's dive into the topic to begin
with, let's start our problem.
The healthcare ecosystem is massive.
Tens of millions of claims are
submitted, reviewed, processed and
cleared every day across several payers,
providers, and insurance companies.
Claims processing are
still heavily manual.
People reading clinical notes, checking
codes, line by line, and the data.
It's everywhere, like
in papers and portals.
EHR systems attachments that
does not talk to each other.
Fraud detection is also based on rigid
rules that don't evolve fast enough.
All these issues cost the
healthcare industry over a
hundred billion dollars annually.
Combine all that with other
regulations every year.
We have hit a point where complexity
is outpacing the human capacity.
We need a technology that can
understand the context, learn the
patterns, and scale, and that's
where Genea comes into picture.
Genea is revolutionizing the
healthcare industry by establishing
scalable, secure data architectures
and EA models that power the
clinical and operational advances.
They also enable transformative
claim processing by automating the
complex adjudication processes,
reducing manual errors, and
accelerating the payment cycles.
Advanced gene AI models strengthen the
fraud detection through patent analysis,
anomaly identifications, and predictive
alert on suspicious claims driving
cost containment, and system integrity.
Responsible AI implementation also
ensures that gene AI deployments
are transparent, fair, and
compliant with ethical standards.
Supporting trust and
accountability in care delivery.
In practical terms, gen I tools are
already enhancing productivity and
outcomes across care continent driving
measurable improvements in efficiency,
accuracy, and patient experience.
This isn't just efficiency, it's a
reinvention of how insurers operate.
To make Janea Ashley useful inside
an organization, it needs structure.
This five layer architecture brings order
to the kiosk, the data ingestion layer.
This is where we ingest the data and
pre-process them, and then we understand
the clinical language, leveraging
the natural language processing and
validates it with medical standards,
make intelligent decisions and
automate the workflows end to end.
This is how we get intelligence
into the operational core.
Let's look at each one closely.
The first layer is the data
ingestion and pre-processing.
The biggest barrier in any data
pipeline is a data fragmentation.
Claims come in several formats, like
PDFs, hhl seven messages, or even DCOM
messages, images, generic consumes data
in all of these formats and converts into
structured data for downstream processing.
The ingestion pipeline performs
data cleaning, d deduplication,
and enrichment as part of the data.
Pre-processing steps.
Think of it as laying a solid foundation.
Without clean unified data, no AI
models can deliver reliable outcomes.
Once it, once we have the clean data,
the next challenge is understanding
what that data actually means.
That's where the NLP takes over.
Many of us would've heard or even seen
medical data, and it's not simple text.
It's full of medical codes, aggravations
context, and clinical nuances.
This second layer leverages the
NLP to extract meaning from these
codes and a observations gene I
reads, physician notes, discharge
summaries, and claim negatives.
Then it identifies entities like diagnosis
codes, procedures, and medications.
It doesn't stop there.
It goes on to build
contextual understanding.
For example, it can distinguish
between a follow-up visit for diabetes
versus a new diagnosis of diabetes.
There is a subtle difference that
affects the building accuracy,
and the result is a claim that's
enriched with semantic intelligence
ready for automated de positioning.
These remaining layers focuses on
validating the correctness, which means
the goal here is not to reject the bad
claims, to improve the equality before it,
before the submissions, and then detecting
risks and automating the smart routing.
The final orchestration layer ties
the entire ecosystem together.
Claims that are high, confidence
can auto approve and questionable
claims get escalated.
Humans focus, humans can focus where
human judgment is needed and everything
becomes faster and more consistent when
it comes to processing the medical claims.
Transforming this process with
gene AI in healthcare is a game
changer for day-to-day operations.
By using a advanced AI models to
read, understand, and automate claims
documentation, healthcare organizations
can dramatically cut down on manual
paperwork, streamline the approvals, and
reduce errors that often slow things down.
Gena also helps spot inconsistencies
or missing information instantly
flagging claims that need attention and
freeing up the staff to focus on cases
that really require human judgment.
This means claims get
processed much faster.
Sometimes in minutes instead of days
leading to quicker reimbursements for
providers and less waiting for patients.
On top of that, AI driven automation
brings transparency and removes the
guesswork from the whole process.
Teams gain better visibility into claim
status, bottlenecks and operational
metrics, allowing for smarter resource
allocation and continuous improvement.
In short, Genea delivers significant
efficiency gains that save costs, boost
productivity, and enhance satisfaction
across the board for the patients
healthcare workers and payers, all alike.
Now, let's talk about the
real differentiator, the fraud
detection, how fraudulent claims
are captured in traditional systems.
The answers to this question depends
on codified static business rules
that capture the thresholds like.
Flag the claim if an amount
is greater than X dollars or
duplicate claims within 30 days.
However, frauds evolve so quickly,
often just likely changing
patterns to bypass those frauds.
January brings multimodal analysis.
This means it combines the structured
data, claim narratives, and behavioral
signals simultaneously in order to detect
the suspicious activity proactively by
integrating these different data types.
The system gains a more
comprehensive understanding than
any single source could provide.
Leading to more accurate and
efficient claims education, it
can identify sophisticated fraud
patterns even before human auditors.
Notice them and send notifications
to the right personnel to act upon.
For example, the most complex and hard
to detect patterns are often buried
in structured data, unstructured
data such as clinical nodes, doctor's
letters, and claim description.
NLP could actually reveal a hidden
pattern in these unstructured data.
Multimodal fraud detection in healthcare
is getting a major upgrade thanks to the
advanced AI techniques that pull insights
from different kinds of data to spot
suspicious activities more accurately.
With graph neural networks, the system
maps out the relationships among claims
patients, providers and transactions.
Think of it like building a
social network for claims data.
If certain providers, for example,
are unusually connected to clusters
of questionable claims, the network
highlights those as red flags right away.
In temporal pattern analysis is all
about watching for the odd timing
the AI looks at when procedures,
prescriptions, or billing events happen
and can quickly spot if someone's
submitting claims and patterns.
They just don't make sense, like
frequent charges at strange hours
or burst of identical procedure,
which is a classic sign of fraud.
Document Authenticity assessment goes
further by letting AI review paperwork,
invoices, and digital documents
for signs of tampering or forgery.
Gene AI can detect subtle differences
in wordings, formatting, or signatures,
alerting the investigators to documents
that look doctored or generated by bots
instead of genuine human submissions.
Last but not the least, anomalies,
scoring models, crunch all
these clues and assign risks.
To each claim on transaction when claims
stand out statistically, whether due to
the networks timing or document content,
the system prioritizes them for review.
Ensuring team tackles truly
suspicious activity first and don't
get bogged down by false alarms.
Together with these techniques,
meet faster, smarter, and more
comprehensive fraud detection.
Making it much harder for bad actors
to slip through the cracks and helping
healthcare organizations protect
their resources and patient's trust.
This gives insurers a 360 degree
defensive shield against fraud.
I love this one.
The synthetic fraud scenario
generation AI can create water fraud
scenarios that haven't happened.
This lets insurers train their systems.
Before a new tactic shows up
in production, we move from
reactive to predictive defense.
Here it's like having a
heads up on future fraud.
Using generative modeling, we
can simulate fraudulent claims to
stress test the detection pipeline
to protect against future threats.
This approach helps the system to
learn from possible future fraud
events even before it occurs,
thereby improving their resilience,
adaptability, and system integrity.
Talking about responsible AI in
healthcare, accuracy is important,
but trust is essential and
responsible AI is not optional.
It is the foundation of adoption.
We must keep all the personal information,
the PHI information private and we
need to explain the decisions clearly.
We need to monitor for biases, and
we also need to comply with the
HIPAA and other audit requirements.
Explainability is equally essential
decision makers and patients should
be able to understand how AI reached
its conclusions, whether about claims
denial, or risk ratings or fraud alerts.
Responsible AI frameworks encourages
transparency, feature important analysis,
and ongoing testing so that any biases
are supported and corrected by com.
By combining the compliance
and explainability insurers,
build trust and accountability.
Which strengthens the relationship with
your customers and support better fairer
outcomes in the healthcare sector.
Organizations in healthcare face big
hurdles when rolling out ai, especially
when it comes to data fragmentation.
Keeping models up to date and
helping the workflow adapt.
New technologies, it's not about
just technology, it's people,
process and change data silos,
workflows, readiness, and model drift.
All of these require strategy.
Data fragmentation is a classic challenge.
Health information is scattered across
electronic health records, insurance,
databases, labs, and even old paper files.
This makes it tricky for AI
systems to get a complete picture,
potentially missing important
signals or even causing redundancies.
The solution, investing in secure
data integration platforms and
robust interoperability standards
so that different systems can talk
to each other, and AI has one clean,
unified data source to work from.
Model maintenance is another roadblock.
AI models need regular updates to
stay accurate as new diseases emerge.
Regulations change or patient
populations shift, many organizations
struggle to set up automated
monitoring and retraining pipelines.
The best fix is to build strong ML
ops team and use continuous monitoring
tools, making sure models are retrained
with fresh data, evaluated for biases
and version for accountability.
Then there's workforce transformation.
Staff needs training and support
to trust what AI is doing and uses.
It uses its results effectively, but
fear of job loss or lack of technical
skills can cause resistance the
way forward is ongoing Education.
Change management and bringing clinical,
operational and tech teams together so
everyone's included in the AI journey.
Upskilling programs and transparent
communication make the workplace
more resilient and ready for future.
By tackling these challenges head on
healthcare organizations can unlock more
value from ai, improving the healthcare,
and empower their teams for what's next
when implementing the AI roadmap.
Jena in healthcare insure
space, breaking the journey
down into four easy step phases.
The first phase is a foundation.
Think of this as laying the groundwork.
Teams focus on setting up secure
pipelines for collecting and handling
data, picking and configuring the
natural language processing models,
and building initial validation
frameworks to make sure everything runs
according to existing business rules.
The next phase developers get fraud
detection models up and running.
But start in shadow mode, managing the
models alongside the current systems, not
replacing them existing ones just yet.
This phase also involves creating helpful
explainability tools for claim adjusters
and setting up AB testing infrastructure.
So model performance can be accurately
evaluated in the integration phase.
Gene systems are connected
to core insurance platforms.
Workflow orchestration gets
attention with automated routing
and escalation for claims processes.
Monitoring dashboards are also introduced,
so stakeholders have visibility into
the key metrics and can keep an eye
on model performance in real time.
In the optimization phase, the focus
shifts to continuous improvement.
This includes building pipelines
for ongoing learning, expanding
AI coverage to more claim types.
Boosting capacity for handling more
claims and crafting advanced features
like synthetic fraud generations and
federated learning to make the systems
smarter and more robust for the future.
This roadmaps makes complex AI
implementation feel manageable by
breaking it down into stage by stage
priorities, ensuring progress is
measured, and teams know exactly what
to tackle next as they move forward.
So here's the big picture.
Healthcare insurance is entering a
new AI era and is incredibly exciting.
Here are the main takeaways and
practical steps for leveraging the gene
AI in healthcare insurance context.
All in a clear and structured way.
Architectural thinking genea
isn't about algorithms.
It starts with a solid foundation.
Five layer architecture that we talked
about ensures a structured rollout,
balancing cutting edge innovation with
all important regulatory requirements
that keep data safe and systems
in check and beyond automation.
Gen A goes way beyond that.
It brings new capabilities to the
table, like improving fraud detection,
risk assessment, and making smarter
decisions, all things that move business
forward and add major value and success
with AI means doing things ethically.
That means focusing on explainability,
protecting privacy, minimizing
bias, and staying compliant with
all relevant laws and standards.
To really see the benefits,
the organization should also
start small and focused.
Pick use cases that they can show clear
incremental value, then build up bigger
technical capabilities as expertise
and their confidence grow altogether.
These points offer a roadmap for
organizations work, wanting to make
GI work for them in the responsible,
effective, and forward thinking way.
Thank you so much for your time
and let's together explore and
experience the advancement of
technology for the good cause.
Have a good one.