Hey, hello, everyone.
I am a full stack web engineer, and
thank you for joining my session on
optimizing AEM performance and user
experience with a single page application
before we proceed with the discussion.
I have a disclaimer to share
the views and opinions shared
in this presentation are my own.
And do not represent the views
or official position of my
current and previous employees.
The content is based on
general industry knowledge and
publicly available information.
No sensitive or confidential information
will be shared during this talk.
Today, we'll talk about the importance
of AEM single page application,
issues, advantages, and resolutions.
And how it will improve the server
performance and user experience.
A little bit background about
me before starting into, talk.
I'm a technology professional with
more than 10 years of experience.
Developing software
for, various industries.
I hold a master degree in computer
science from the University
of Central Missouri, USA.
As a full stack developer, I bring
exceptional proficiency in both front end
and back end development, adding value
and innovation to every project I work on.
In this talk, we'll talk about
introduction to single page
application, before SPA, how it was in
a traditional multi page application,
how single page application work,
traditional multi page application
versus single page application.
How SPA integrated in the EM
issue software, SPA implementation
resolving SPA issues In the EM
overview of single page application, a
single page application is a modern web
application architecture where users
load a single page initially, and that
page dynamically updates the content
without requiring a full page reload every
time the user interacts with the app.
Unlike traditional websites, the reload,
each time you navigate to your new
page, SPA remains on the same page.
and make small data requests
behind the scenes, updating only
the relevant part of the page.
before talking about the
single page application, let's
talk about a few minutes for
traditional multi page application.
a multi page application is a traditional
web architecture where every user action,
for example, clicking a link or submitting
a form, result in a full page reload.
Each interaction sends a
new request to the server.
Then the server sends back
a complete new HTML page.
Let's look into the
flow here in this slide.
When the browser requests to go to server
and it responds with a complete HTML.
Each request it will go to the server
and respond back with a complete HTML.
Like a full page reloads.
Every time the user navigates to a new
page or performance in action, the browser
make a request to the server and it
will respond with a complete HTML page.
or performance in action, the browser
make a request to the server and it
responds with a complete HTML page.
and it responds with a complete HTML page.
which process the request and sends
a full rendered HTML page back.
Client server interactions, each time
the user clicks a link or performs any
actions, the server generates a new page
and the client loads it from scratch.
Let's take an example like, think
of a traditional e commerce site.
you browse through categories,
select a product, and each
click requires a full reload.
Every new product page sends a fresh
request to the server, making the
experience feel slower and more segmented.
Let's talk about some common issues
before SPI implementing in AEM.
Like a slow navigation, every time
the user clicks to go to another
section, a full page reload occurs.
leading to slow transition
and a fragmented experiences.
SEO challenges for interactive
or frequently updated websites.
Multi page applications generally
work well, but SEO optimization
becomes challenging when rich
interactive content is delivered,
especially with client side rendering.
Complex user interactions like
creating smooth and complex
user interactions in multi page
applications is often challenging.
Especially for applications that require
real time updates like online chat
systems or live dashboards increase
server load With every user interaction
triggering a new server request,
every new server request, there is a
heavier load on the server, leading to
potential slowdowns and scaling issues.
Impact user experience lag.
With every page refresh, the
user may lose their context.
Example, form data might disappear
if they navigate away and come back.
And higher bandwidth usage.
Reloading full page, including
redundant parts like header and
footer, consumes more bandwidth,
increasing the data sent and received.
Let's consider an example like a in
traditional new site where every click
on a new article to get a full page
reload over time, this can slow down
navigation, interrupt the user experience
and increase the workload on the
server, especially when traffic spikes.
Let's talk about, how single
page application works detail.
Now let's talk about
technical structure of SBA.
SPA are primary built using modern
JavaScript framework such as React, js.
These frameworks manage the
applicant's behavior and user interface
directly in the browser instead of
constantly communicating with the
server to reload entire web pages.
SPA work by dynamically updating
only the necessary part of the page.
The core difference lies in the
shift of logic and rendering
from the server to client.
When we talk about technical
structure of SPAs, we talk about
a JavaScript as a controller.
The framework act as a controller that
respond to user action like clicks, form
submissions, and navigation changes.
The JavaScript is loaded initially
and dynamically manage the state
of application, ensuring only the
relevant content is fetched or updated.
Asynchronous data fetching.
SPS use Ajax or Fetch API to send
asynchronous requests to the server.
These requests retrieve only the
necessary data like a specific portion
of text, image, or product details.
Ajax or Fetch API is And update the page
instantly without requiring any updates.
Complete reload.
Browser side logic.
SPA shift most of the rendering and
navigation control to the client side,
the browser, which result in smoother
transition and less load on the server.
Let's talk about how, SPA load data.
In initial load, when a user first visits
the SPA, a browser download a single HTML
page and associated JavaScript files.
This include all necessary code
for the application's layout,
structure, and initial logic.
Then dynamic updates instead of
reloading the entire page, when the
user interacts, example like clicks,
clicking on a link or submitting a form.
Only the specific part of the page
that need to be changed or updated.
This could involve fetching new
content from the server without
disturbing the rest of the page.
Server interaction.
Unlike traditional multi page
applications, SPA do not send full
page reload request to the server.
Instead, asynchronous data requests
are made, fetching only the required
data and displaying it instantly.
These reduces overall server load and
ensures fast interactions for the user.
Let's give you an one example like
considering gmail when you open an email
the rest of the interface the sidebar
header all those things remains unchanged.
Only the content of
selected email is updated.
This allows the app to feel fast
and responsive as there is no
need to reload the entire page.
This is a core benefit of SPA
reducing unnecessary page reloads to
create a seamless user experience.
Let's talk about the some key benefits
like a drastically reduced load time
in traditional websites like a multi
page applications navigation to your
new section or page involves reloading
and JavaScript from the server.
This can result in.
Noticeable delays, especially, for a
website with heavy content or media.
In SPAs, only the necessary data
or, content is fetched and updated,
leaving the rest of the app intact.
This leads to faster interactions
and a more responsive application.
Improved user experience, like a
user expects immediate response from
modern web applications with SPA.
Actions such as clicking links,
submitting forms, or updating
content happen instantly.
because the app does not
reload the entire page.
SPS creates a user experience similar to a
native mobile or desktop applications with
fast transitions and fluid interactions.
Example on, example on Facebook,
liking a post or leaving a
comment happens almost immediately
without reloading the entire page.
This creates an engaging and
seamless experience for users.
As I talk about reduced server load,
traditional multi page applications
place a heavy load on the server
because each user interacts requires
generating a new page from scratch.
This can slow down the performance,
especially when many users are
interacting simultaneously.
Since SPS shift, much of the
rendering to the browser.
The server only needs to provide
data, not full HTML pages.
This makes SBA more scalable,
especially for applications
with heavy user interactions.
Real time updates and interactions.
SBA is very good in applications
requiring real time data updates.
For instance, messaging apps,
live dashboards, and project
management tools, benefit greatly
from the ability to update.
Content without page reloads.
Let's give you like some
real time examples like,
Gmail, Google Maps, Facebook.
when users zoom in, search for a
location, or, or across the, or pan
across the map, Only the relevant
part of the map updates, the rest of
the page, search bar, menu bar, etc.
remains static.
Even in the Facebook, scrolling
through the feed, linking posters,
or commenting happens without
any noticeable page reload.
The content updates dynamically
as you interact with it.
SVAs are ideal for applications that
need to handle real time updates.
dynamic content, and a
high level of interactions.
SBAs are commonly used in applications
like dashboards, project management
tools, social networks, video platforms.
Let's talk about differentiations
between the traditional multi
page application and SBA.
Imagine a traditional website
is an old online store.
Every time you click on a new
product, the whole page reloads.
which can slow and frustrating.
With an SPA, when you click on
your product, only the product
details update, making for a
smoother and faster experience.
Even if you see in this slide, we have two
diagrams where one represents traditional
application and one is for SPA.
In traditional, each request going
from the client, it's coming out like
a complete HTML and regulates the page.
But in SPA, Only portion of Ajax
call went to the server and get
that JSON and update the page.
Let's compare tabular format
side by side to make it more
understand like a navigation.
in multi page application, each
click lead to new page load causing
slower transition and higher latency.
In single page application, handle
navigation inside the browser fetching
only the required data so the user
experience fast and seamless transition.
Server request.
Multi page application sends a new request
to the server for every interaction.
While in single page application, only
load the full page once, then make
subsequent data request as needed.
This reduces server load
and bandwidth usage.
User experience.
In multi page application, can
feel sluggish as users wait
for entire page to reload.
In SPA, on the other hand, offer
a more app like feel, where
interactions feel immediately.
Performance and, in multi page
applications can be slower
because each time you click
something, the whole page reloads.
which puts more work on the
server and takes longer for users.
SVO only loads what's needed after
the first load, making them faster
and reducing the strain on the server.
Coming to SVO perspective, in traditional
multi page applications are naturally
more SEO friendly, because each page
has its own distinct URL and content.
The search engines can easily crawl.
SBA requires additional techniques like
server side rendering or dynamic rendering
to make their content searchable.
Development complexity.
Multi page applications are more often
simpler to develop since they rely on
established server side frameworks.
SBAs introduce more complexity as they
require mastering JavaScript frameworks.
client side routing and
handling dynamic data.
Coming to caching, multi page
applications use simple caching
where entire page or static content
can be saved and reused easily.
Single page applications like however
need more advanced caching methods.
like serving workers because they
load data dynamically, making
caching a bit more complicated.
Coming to best use cases, as I
mentioned, multi page applications
work best for websites with a lot
of content like blogs or news sites.
SPS are perfect for interactive
apps like social networks or online
stores, when users expect real time
updates and a smooth experience.
Let's talk about how we can integrate
in, Single page application in
AEM like a client side rendering
SPS in AEM use modern JavaScript
frameworks like React or Vue.
js to handle rendering the browser.
Edible templates.
Even though single page application
or JavaScript based AEM allows content
author to still create and edit
pages easily integrated authoring
experience in AEM content authors can
edit single page application content
dynamically seeing the changes as
they make them without needing coding
knowledge like in react based single
page application integrated with AEM.
Content authors can add a new sections or
images in real time with the JavaScript
handles the page updates instantly.
Current issues after the SPA
implementation, even after integrating
AEM, we have some issues to talk
about, like SEO optimization.
By default, heavily on client side
rendering, which can cause search
engines to struggle with indexing
dynamically generated content,
leading to poor SEO performance.
Debugging complexities, SPS are heavily
dependent on JavaScript, making them
harder to debug compared to standard.
traditional application.
And as I mentioned that caching
difficulties SPA fetch data
dynamically and this can be tricky to
implement proper caching strategies.
Compatibility issues.
Some older AEM components might
not work as smoothly in SPA.
Require development to
create custom solutions.
Content authoring experience.
Initially, content authors faced
challenges managing content in
SPS because traditionally visual
editing tools and in context
editings were difficult to implement
in client rendering applications.
for example, with an SPA might offer
a sleek experience troubleshooting
a bug related to dynamic data.
Loading can be much more complex.
And compared to traditional website.
Let's talk about how we
can overcome these issues.
Like a SCVO solution like
a server side rendering.
Pre render pages on the server to help
search engines index Content effect
efficiently, dynamic rendering use
tools like a Google dynamic rendering
to show pre rendered content to
search engines while still delivering
an SPI experience to user debugging
techniques like a source map.
These map compile JavaScript
code back to the original source
code and make it easier to debug.
Like a caching strategies.
These allow us to cache dynamic
content more effectively
enabling offline capabilities.
And, API caching.
So frequently access data can be
cast to minimize the load time.
Also coming to compatibility, custom
components, build components specifically
for SBA to ensure smooth functionality,
hybrid approach, use a mix of SBA and
traditional multi page application
where necessary to maintain flexibility,
content, authoring, underwriting.
AEM SBA editor is designed
to overcome this, but it
required proper configuration.
ensure that SPA editor is
correctly integrated to content
authors can use in, in context
editing and preview functionality.
This requires a close coordination
between front end developers
and the AEM implementation team.
Now let's talk about a case study
like a large e commerce site
faced issues with slow page loads.
Taking up to three seconds
after implementing an SPA
load time drop to one second.
Additionally, server,
request were reduced by 20%.
improving overall performance
and user experience.
Let's see the, let's see, revisit
the advantage and everything what we
discussed so far, like in conclusion.
So SPA role in modern web development,
like a performance boost, a single
page application offers faster load
time and smoother interactions,
enhanced user experience, fluid
navigation and real time updates keep
user engaged, Developer flexibility.
JavaScript frameworks give developers
the tools to build robust applications.
Competitive edge.
Businesses that use single page
applications deliver content
faster, ensuring they stay
ahead in the digital landscape.
As the AEM continues to evolve, single
page applications will become even more
integrated, helping business creating
faster and more dynamic, and, giving like
a very smooth and, great web experience.
By addressing challenges like SEO and
caching, SPA can offer you a future proof
solution for modern web applications.
Thank you.
I hope you enjoyed the talk.