Hello everybody.
Welcome to Conf42, Kube Native 2024.
Hello everyone.
We are truly to be here to talk
about KubeVirt and how it brings
virtualization into the KUBAN as world.
This is our first talk at Conf42,
and we are very excited about that.
Hope it won't be our last talk.
Today we'll dive deep into the how you
can leverage keyword to run virtual
machines alongside your containers.
giving you a unified platform
for managing both of them.
By the end of the session, you'll know how
to get started with KubeWord and integrate
it into your Kubernetes environment.
But first, let's introduce
ourselves, Batuhan.
Hello again, my name is Batuhan,
and I am working as a platform
engineer here at TrendVault.
For those interested in software
supply chain security, you might know
me as one of the early contributors
of SIGSTOR, for which I was selected
as best SIGSTOR evangelist at 2022.
I am proud to be very first
astronaut from Turkey.
I am also CNCF ambassador and the captain
and one of the organizers of KCD Istanbul.
And my name is Koray.
I work as a cubanist consultant and
technical trainer for Cubomatic.
I am also CNCF ambassador
and cube astronaut.
I also contribute to the
cubanist project on CKC infra.
To start with but on you're a platform
engineer and I know that you've worked
on a few migration projects from
virtual machines towards containers.
Let's start by looking at the
fundamental difference between
containers and virtual machines.
Yeah, sounds great, right?
People might know that containers
are lightweight, right?
Designed to run isolate applications
with minimal overhead by sharing
the host's kernel and resources.
This makes them incredibly
efficient for modern workloads.
On the flip side, VMs virtualize entire
operating systems, including the kernel.
So each VM running its own
operating system, right?
They require a hypervisor adding
more overhead, but offering a
full isolation, which is a good
thing for a security perspective.
While containers are ideal for
microservices and stateless applications,
many companies still rely on VMs,
especially for legacy systems that haven't
transitioned to the container world.
For those cases, VMs remain
to go to choice due to the
need for full OS isolation and
compatibility with older workloads.
The real challenge is that some
applications still require the
VM model due to dependencies or
architecture, but also Want to take
advantage of benefits of continuation.
Koray, what do you think
happens in those scenarios?
This is where the
KubeWord comes into play.
So why KubeWord?
Why do we need to bring
virtualization into Kubernetes?
KubeWord allows you to manage
both containers and VMs within
a single Kubernetes platform.
So instead of managing a separate
infrastructure for VMs and
containers keyword provides a
way to unify your workloads.
This is especially helpful
for teams in transition.
The ones that are moving from VMS
containers or for those who want to mix
both type of work workflows for for the
flexibility you can run traditional VM
based applications while modernizing
other pies of your parts of your stack
with containers and they can run all
under the same orchestration layer.
Batuhan, what do you think you
can actually do with kube word?
Yeah, that's a good question.
First, you can manage VMs just like
any other Kubernetes resource like
deployment, port, services, etc.
Meaning that you can scale,
restart, and manage VMs using
familiar Kubernetes tools.
So this allows you to run legacy
applications that aren't easily
containerized, which is particularly
beneficial for organizations needing
to support both modern and traditional
workloads on a single platform.
Qubit also supports live migration,
which is quite helpful for enabling
you to move running VMs between
nodes without any downtime.
Crucial for maintaining
uptime during maintenance.
Plus, you can manage the full life
cycle of VMs provisioning, starting,
stopping, and deleting using the
standard kubernetes commands like
kubectl create, kubectl scale, etc.
So yeah, that's, this is lots
of virtualization, right?
Exactly.
Let's look at how keyword
works under the hood.
So at its core keyword is real
top on communities, leveraging
its native API for VM management.
And that means, as you mentioned before,
scheduling, networking and storage.
These are all responsibility
of responsibilities of the
underlying Kubernetes cluster.
So how it works.
There are several key components here.
We have the Kuber operator, which
installs and manages the life
cycle of other Kubert components.
There is weird controller which watches
for the VM resources and creates the
necessary virtual machine instances.
VMI's there we have with launcher
it's a per VM pod that launches
and runs the VM workload.
So each VM runs inside the
pod on a Kubernetes node.
Yeah.
Obviously kube word uses lib word to
handle VM interactions with the hypervisor
like camo or any other hypervisor.
And we have the weird handler that
component runs on each communities
note and it's responsible for handling
VM related requests, such as the.
life cycle operations and migrations.
This architecture allows communities
to treat VMS as just another
workload alongside the containers.
Batuhan, if you can
simplify it a little bit.
So yeah here is the simplified
version of the previous diagram
by highlighting the key points.
The main takeaway is that Kubernetes
integrates seamlessly with Kubernetes.
In this setup, VMs are treated
as pods running on Kubernetes
nodes, meaning that they follow
the same scheduling and resource
management processes as containers.
Kubernetes also leverages the
Kubernetes API alongside libvirt
qemu, enabling seamless VM Lifecycle
management while taking an advantage
of Kubernetes features like auto
scaling, networking, and storage.
This integration simplifies the process of
deploying and managing both the apps and
containers within the same environment by
eliminating the need for separate tools.
Yeah.
This brings us to running
also workloads on Kubernetes.
It's quite easy as our
friend Mark says, right?
So it's demo time.
Before we start a special
thanks to metal stack cloud.
They provided their bare metal
Kubernetes many service to us to use.
So if you want to run cube word on public
cloud providers you have to enable nested
virtualization because it's a another
virtualization layer on top of VMs.
So in the case of, for example, AWS.
You also have to use metal instance types.
Then here we'll be using
another bare metal service.
And for the demo, we have a a repo
where we include both Flux and Argo CD.
installations or scenarios.
If you prefer more UI based stuff
you can also try out Argo city, but
today we'll be working with flux
and we'll be creating our VMs on
keyword using in with GitOps approach.
So I have already bootstrapped
the flux in the cluster.
Let's check it out.
And you will see that flux is already
deployed and now I would like to
start deploying first with cube word.
So I will be exporting
some environment variables.
This could so this one needs
to be V version one to zero
and create a director for it.
And in that directory,
I'll be copying the.
Q word operator and Q word
custom resources manifests.
If now we take a look, as you see in
my getups configuration directory,
the flux system is there, and there
is also another manifest for Q word.
Eventually we'll be deploying RVMs using
some ham chart that I just created.
Which will be handling some other stuff
include creating some SSH keys for the VM.
So you can also do such stuff or
copy things from here as well.
The VM provisioner is app that that
is used in the Argo CD scenario.
You can also take a look at this one.
So first I would like to push these
things and let Flux create the, or deploy
kubert for us if I do start checking out.
So here Flux first will deploy kubert
operator, and then it will be responsible
for deploying the other components.
Like a weird launcher and with handler.
Let's wait flux to
To do it or maybe we can just manually
trigger the reconciliation on flux side
Let's try it flux reconcile source
kit flux system Now if we check the
pods as you see the weird operator is
being deployed and then it will start
deploying the other components to
the system when it's up upon running.
And we can also check the here like this.
So as you see the it's being
deployed now and we can also wait
for cover to be to be deployed the.
So right now the phase is is
deploying and then we'll wait until
the kube word part is up and ready.
I hope this will be fast.
Meanwhile, we can also check again.
What's happening with the pause.
If there are any failures.
No, there are no failures.
So we're tender virtual operator
controller, a virtual API.
They're all deployed and it's ready.
If again, you check for the yeah.
Now the condition is met.
And if we check all the resources in
cube word namespace Yeah, we'll see
that weird controller, weird handler,
weird API and operator are deployed.
There are a few services.
Yeah, also the weird
handler is a daemon set.
So they're all running.
Yeah.
To be able to interact with with
kube word VMs you need to install
virtctl or virtctl binary or kube
plugin virt to be able to do that.
Yeah, I've already installed
them, so I will not try those, but
Essentially, you will need them working.
As I said, I've already created a
Helm chart and pushed it to some OCI
repository on GitHub GitHub registry.
So I'll be using that
One, two, create a VM.
First again I create the VM there,
so I will create virtual machines
directory and put all my virtual
machine related manifest there.
And now I would like to create a source.
Yeah, my, from my GitHub registry
and create a source here.
And then yeah, you can check what is
created in the values YAML file, but
simply I'll be providing a memory
for my VM, the host name of my VM and
which container disc will be used.
So I'll be using Fedora and I
can also provide some user data.
like a change password,
like a password is federal.
And you can also provide some more
information with SSH keys or other stuff.
So I'll be creating this values file and
then I will be creating the helm release.
I will use VM chart.
The helm releases test VM one.
I'll use this ham repository
that I just created.
When I push the code, it will be created.
I will create a virtual machines
namespace and then use the values
file that I also created here.
So if we check now or so on the
virtual machines, I have the kube
virt vm ham, ham repo, and also
one VM YAML to create the VM.
So let's again push those to Flux,
or for Flux to work, and then watch
again the pods, what's happening now.
So I'll, I'm expecting a new namespace
here called virtual machines which will
have a pod for my test VM one hopefully
soon, or maybe I can reconcile it again.
Manually yes.
Flux reconcile.
Yeah.
So as you see, the virtual
machine is being started.
So this is a Helm chart.
It will first create some
SH keys for me and then.
It will start the Virt Launcher.
So Virt Launcher is working.
So this is the pod that contains my VM.
And It's being initialized.
I think it's running.
And if we check the virtual machines
so I have some, I have a virtual
machine running on that node.
It's in running phase, so it's I
think it's ready to be connected.
As I said, I'll get secret
dash and mutual machines.
So it created a private and
public key for me this ham chart.
So I will need to
download those to connect.
So I simply create these two files,
public, private key, and then the
command to connect to the VM is kubectl
weird ssh I'm using your identifier.
So this is the private key
that I just downloaded.
I will use the local ssh
Connection type to With federal
user to test vm1 and it's running
on the virtual machines namespace.
So if I do that yes, I accept the key
and then now I am on my fedora machine.
So this is a a VM that runs all the stuff,
it has its own kernel and everything.
You name dash a, you will see that it's
running my record kernel and everything.
This is a vm and the good part is
that now from this VM, I am able
to connect to the Kubernetes API.
So if I try to connect to Kubernetes
default service or Kubernetes
service on the default name
space, yeah, I wanna authorize.
I know that, but.
I was just able to interact
with the Kubernetes namespace.
So the application you have running
here, whatever that is, it can
connect to other services inside
your Kubernetes clusters so that your
virtualized application can just connect
to your containerized applications.
Simply that brings you that information.
So some.
Other companies, some companies like
Rattat or Qubermatic they provide
some other approaches, approaches
to Qubeword for example, Qubermatic.
Creates communities clusters
by using keyword VM.
There are VMs on the keyword cluster and
using those VMs we create a communities
cluster and you can check that sort
of information from the documentation
to conclude to make it easier
to manage hybrid workloads.
So you don't have too many.
You don't have to choose
between VMs and containers.
With its simplest integration into
Kubernetes, Kubernetes opens up new
possibilities for legacy modernization
and workload consolidation.
So thank you for joining our session.
You can reach both of, if you have
any questions, we have both on
LinkedIn and X and also GitHub.
Thank you very much.
Have a great conference.