Hey.
Hi.
Good morning everyone.
This is Krishna Ula.
I'm excited to share about my recent
recently implemented a successful
Oracle migration to the Amazon Web
Services, which navigating to the future.
I'm here to explain little bit more
about like this migration is not
just about moving the data, but
about transferring your business
operations for the greater efficiency,
scalability, and agility in the cloud.
I'm happy to give you
more information on that.
And if in the economical and technical
transformation recently historically
on databases, infrastructure was.
Capital initiative and required
significant in investment in hardware.
And it s organizations were often
beyond by complex maintenance
schedule and regular hardware upgrade.
Now the cloud has completely
transformed this module with
AWS and other cloud platforms.
You can, scalability, flexibility,
optimization, cost, structure, AWS custom
consumption based pricing, especially AWS
is providing consumption based pricing
means you can only pay for what you use,
making it highly cost efficient solution.
The cloud migration process
is not just about technology.
It's about enabling business
transformation by migrating to the cloud
business can unlock your level of agility,
accelerate innovation, and gain in a
significant competitive a advantage.
Here we, if we like in, in, in the next
slide for the pre-migration assessment.
A a comprehensive approach is a successful
migration beyond these two pre-migration.
Pre-migration assessment.
Let explain the three main concepts, which
is strategic workload, performance and
analysis, and de dependency mapping and
the migration read reading evaluation.
For the strategic, for the s workload
performance analysis over 62 of enterprise
enterprise report difficulties due to
the data complexity during migration, by
analyzing your existing workload existing
workload, looking at computational
requirement, data integration and system
capabilities, you will gain valuable.
Sites into the potential migration
challenges, dependency, migration,
many migration falls failures steam
for insufficient understanding
of system interdependencies.
And 47% of the organization experiences
failures due to this gap under.
Understanding how different system in
interacts allows as a better plan, the
better plan the migration and avoid the
disruptions, the migration readiness
evaluation here in this, organizations
with s pre, pre, pre-migration
assessment for three to five more
likely to achieve successful migration.
We need to at least three
to five iteration to perform
these successful migration.
The most throughput, the preparation, the
smoother the migration process would be
for the next slide.
Here one second.
Yeah.
These are one, yeah, these
AWS hosting options for the
Oracle Micro Oracle databases.
When the migration Oracle databases
to AWS we have two primary options,
which is manage database solutions,
self-management database solutions.
For example, Amazon, EC2, manage
database services like a Amazon RDS.
Are the go-to solutions for the most
organizations offering a fully managed
environment by moving to the A-S-R-D-R-D-S
68% of the enterprise reports, reducing
operational complexity and database
maintenance who are heading by.
Up to up to 45%.
The RDS automations we
administrator to task, including
backups, patching, and scalable.
Scaling allows your team to focus on
innovating rather than maintenance,
like patching, upgrades and everything
for the self-manager databases
like EC2 for the enterprise.
Which specific complex
requirements, customs, database
solutions deployed on EC2.
Maybe more suitable.
These options allow you to fine tuning
the configuration, including using the
Bring your Own license model, where
you need to get your own license model,
which offers a greater flexibility.
Essentially if you all
already have Oracle licensing.
Here for the network and security
configuration we have like
for these security and network
configurations are critical
aspects of any migration nowadays.
The comprehensive security
framework, enterprise connectivity,
architecture, BPC, infrastructure
Design, cloud Secure Foundation.
Foundation if we go to the comprehensive
security framework implements
encryptions or encryption at rest and
in transit, access control policies and
continuous monitoring and essentials
to secure the data for the enterprise
connectivity architecture using the AWS
Direct Connect for the data dedicated.
Private connections to the AWS
provides both performance and
security for adding security.
VPN tunnels can be used for
encryption communication.
VPC infrastructure design.
VVPC means virtual private clouds
allows you to create isolation.
Network.
Network environments by essentially
provides subnets and security groups.
We gained gradually control over.
Or who can allows your data, allows your
database that resource connect to it.
Cloud Security Foundation addressing
Oracle specific security challenges.
Security challenges, which is like
AWS provides NATO security cha
mechanism to address Oracle specific.
Concerns such as database level
encryption and access level control.
These ensure that your data remains
protected through throughout
its journey in the cloud.
Let's go to the next slide here,
the database migration strategies.
There are four key
strategies in this migration.
There.
These are assessment.
Preparation, migration
validation in assessment.
Map, map out your current database
architecture, identify dependency
and access the potential risk
of your mi potential risk of
migration to AWS preparation.
Align the migration plan with organization
objectives and establish a clear path.
This strategy is about setting up the
groundwork for the actual migration.
If you go to the migration, use AWS
database migration services to perform
the data with minimal downtime.
These services is ensure that your
database migration is both effect
efficient and cost effective.
Validation once a migration is completed.
Validate the data integration
performance, and functionality
in the cloud environment.
Ensure that everything works
as expected in crucial for
the for a smooth transaction
in the migration technique.
News the migrations are not always
simple, and understanding the
right technique is essential.
Homogeneous migration.
There are like three, three types here.
Homogeneous migration, heterogeneous
migration, and hybrid migration.
Homogeneous migration is, which
we usually do, Oracle to Oracle
SQL to SQL Al Progressor port.
That's how it works for
the homogeneous migration.
This is where radio you migrate
migration between similar
databases like Oracle to Oracle.
It it's the comp it's the least
complex and as it's minimal co
compatibility issues and risk
reduces the risk reduce process here.
Heterogeneous migration.
These heterogeneous migration is diff is
different database platforms like Oracle
to MySQL or SQL or Oracle to Mongo.
These are called hydrogenous migration.
It requires schema conversion.
Before we start any process, we need
to convert schema and create the same
schema in the conversion we in the target
database, like in MySQL from Oracle two.
Then the data transformation, but
offer the opt opportunity to modernize
your database infrastructure.
In hybrid migration.
In hybrid migration in a way, in a phase
approach that combine both homogeneous
and heterogeneous migration techniques.
This approach allows for incremental
implementation, reduce, reducing
the risk, and improving the
overall flexibility of the process.
So we always follow for the high
hybrid migration, which is it
has to be an incremental way.
For the post migration optimization
which is management efficiency, security
efficiency or risk mitigation in the
management efficiency improves the, in
database management efficiency through the
manager solution by 45%, security is 50.
Reduction will be 55% reduction in
potential security vulnerabilities through
advanced network isolation, 60% risk
mitigation potential data, ensuring the
risk which mitigates through comprehensive
encryption strategies, which is data.
Data exposure risks are significant,
reduces through encryption strategies
and access the control mechanism
mitigates the risk by the 60%.
The same way the security enhancement
by utilizing AWS advanced network
capabilities indicates private subnets
and BPC com companies can reduce a
potential security vulnerabilities in
efficient improvement with the manager
solutions like RDS operational tech.
Typically see a 45% improvement in
the database management efficiency.
Yeah.
If we go to the cost optimization
strategies here we all think to
make a note of reduce ana reduce
analysis, continuous refine
refinement and performance monitoring,
excuse me, dynamic allocations
for the cost strategies.
Cloud cost management
is continuous processes.
Here are the most
strategies to optimize your.
Cloud spending, reduce
analysis continuously.
Evaluate your resource to identify
underutilized accesses and
areas where you can scale down
without impacting performance.
Dynamic allocation.
Use automated scale, automated scaling to.
I just resource between, I just
resource based on real time demand.
This ensures that you
only pay what you need.
Performance man.
Performance monitoring, track,
key performance metrics using
tools like Amazon Cloud was.
This enables you to identify bottlenecks
bottlenecks early and make just before
you, before they affected performance.
Continuous refining the cloud is
dynamic and so should be you should
be your cost optimization approach.
Regular assessment allows you
to make informed adjustments
that maintain efficiently while
keeping cost under control.
And in the best practice for the
successful migration is to ensure
we follow several best process.
First one is comprehensive
risk mitigation.
Develop a proactive risk medication
plan to address, address, and divide
challenges that comes with my migration.
The strategic migration plans thoroughly
plan your migration strategies, aligning
it with business goals and expected
output outcomes, and testing validation.
You use strategic environment to
simulate real world migration scenarios.
Allows you to identify issues
before the migration occurs.
And do like multiple testings, like
we usually do, like from we started
from Dell, UAT pre-prod and pro, so
we did multiple levels of testing
before we go to the production.
That's how we need to validate everything
is working from according to the business.
Need continuous monitoring, implement
robust monitoring tools to track the
performance for your system in real time.
This allows you to detect the, and
detect and resolve issues early,
ensuring business continuity,
strategic consideration
for long-term success.
For the long term success
dependence are on more than.
Just a successful migration.
It support continuous alignment with
the business goals, strategic alignment,
organization readiness, and continuous
implement, and in strategic alignment,
ensure that migration directly
supports your core business objects.
This ensures that cloud infrastructure
delivers measurable values,
organizational readiness, cultivate.
Internal internal expertise by
training teams on a Amazon web
services and cloud management.
Teach management tools, changing
management tools are essential
to minimize ception during the
transactions continuous improvement.
View the migration as an ongoing journey.
Regular assessments for the performance
and emerging AWS compatibilities
will enco encourage new opportunities
for the arga optimization.
And thank you for your a attention.
This migration to the AWS
offers the significant
benefits beyond just technical.
Efficiency.
It's about the transforming your
business for the future by following
a strategic and well-planned migration
for framework you will set to organize
on a path towards a long-term success.
I'm happy to answer any
questions from you guys.
Thank you for giving me this opportunity.
Thank you.