Hi everyone.
I'm bna.
Thanks for joining me for the session.
Today I'm going to talk about how
to accelerate your data science
career via experimentation.
Think of the session as a field guide.
We'll hit experiment design patterns
that work in the wild and the platform
pieces that make experimentation fast
and trustworthy and the career moves
that turn your work into impact.
My goal is to leave you with a playbook
that you can start using this week.
Before we jump into agenda let me
introduce myself and take a minute to
talk about why this topic matters to me.
I've spent over a decade helping teams
design and scale experimentation using
data to build products and solve business
problems, not just to report on them.
My core craft is experimentation
and casual inference, choosing
right design for the constraint,
me measuring impact, credibility,
translating results into decisions.
On systems side, I design and
operationalize cloud native
experimentation platforms.
So Tessa, reproducible,
observable, and cheap to run.
And strategically, I'm obsessed with
connecting insights to outcomes,
turning analysis into decisions leaders
can trust, and building a culture
where being data informed is default.
That combination, methodology,
platform, and business impact is
what I'll share with you today.
Let's jump into the agenda.
We will start by looking at why AB
testing matters for your career,
where experimentation can create
value, and some basic concepts about
experimentation and some common pitfalls.
After that, we will jump into how
can you leverage this concepts
to accelerate your career?
And few tips on interview strategy.
Then we will end with an action plan.
Okay, let's get started.
Why AB testing matters for your career?
It's a high demand skill.
It's highly sought after.
Companies across industries
are desperately seeking for
professionals who can design,
implement, interpret experiments
that drive real business outcomes.
And this is not only valuable for
somebody who is a data analyst.
This skill understanding of the
skill can help engineers build
smarter, experiment ready systems.
Product managers can make
evidence-based features and roadmaps.
Also, it'll bridge gap between data,
engineering, design, and product.
Helping you communicate insights
effectively and influence decision
making across organization.
This skill makes you indispensable
as a translator between technical
complexity and business value.
Now let's look at where
experimentation can create value.
The short answer is every organization
and every department every
department in modern organization
can leverage experimentation
to make data-driven decisions.
You can see some examples
here on this slide.
This is just like maybe 50 percentage
of examples that we covered here.
The key is understanding which
experiment approach work best for
each use case and business context.
Okay.
And how do we choose
right experiment design.
Now let's look at commonly
used experiment designs.
Let's start with AB
testing between subjects.
This is a classic approach.
This compares variance simultaneously.
This is great for feature
releases and UI changes.
Multivariate and factorial is used to
test multiple elements and multiple
variations where we can learn
and capture interaction effects.
Holdout studies are used in long-term
experiments to measure effects
that AC occur over weeks and years.
Business constraints should pick the
design, not the other way around.
When traffic pattern or platform
complicates things, switch designs.
And now let's go to
switchback experiments.
Switchback experiments rotate treatment
by time, so the unit cycles through.
A and B ideal for marketplaces
and two-sided platforms.
This is mostly leveraged by companies like
DoorDash, Uber and Lyft, geo experiments
randomized by region when user level
randomization risks spillovers useful for
location based features and marketing.
If true randomization isn't
possible, use credible alternatives.
For example, something like
Difference in Difference Interrupted
Time Series and Synthetic Control.
These are called cultural
inference methods.
I have three of them here.
Difference in Difference compares
before and after changes in the
treated group against similar control
group that didn't get the change.
Interrupted time series
look for structured.
Structure break right when the inter
intervention happens, if the level
or the slope jumps at that point and
not anywhere else, that's the signal.
Synthetic control.
When you.
Change something in one big
unit, say a state or city build
weighted virtual control from the
other units that didn't change.
So the pre pret trend matches yours.
Expert judgment matters.
Choose design based on constraint.
Technical capabilities,
intervention nature.
Know when to deviate
from pure randomization.
Now let's look at some basic
concepts of experimentation.
I wanna take a different direction in
talking about basic statistical concepts.
There are a lot of excellent
resources online if you wanna
learn about the topics here.
But today I wanna spend some
time talking about trying tying
these concepts to business.
And why it's important for business
and how you can think in those lines.
First hypothesis testing.
This drives clarity.
Knowing how to form good hypothesis
teaches structured thinking.
It's not about is it better,
but what outcome and why.
The mindset helps align experiments with
business strategy and ensures TE has
clear success criteria before the launch.
Confidence uncertainty builds.
Trust.
Communicating uncertainty transparently
builds stakeholder confidence.
Leaders don't expect perfection.
They expect honest ranges
and risk awareness.
This scale separates a strategic
thinker from report generator.
F, exercise and power.
Understanding these concepts helps
you prioritize impactful changes,
not statistically trivial ones four,
which is multiple testing disciplines.
Today we run hundreds and thousands
of experiments every month.
With the number of experiments and
variance we test, there comes a need
to control a false positive rate.
This protects the business from
false winds and bad rollouts.
The last but not least, is
sequential and patient methods.
In today's world, we see the
need for faster experimentation.
To improve the velocity of experimentation
and get continuous learnings.
We need modern techniques like sequential
and patient to support adaptive learnings.
We have looked now that we have
looked at sequential aviation, which
drive experimentation velocity.
Let's also look at other techniques.
In a traditional experiment setup,
we have to wait for larger samples.
This delay is the experiment time and the
insight, and thereby product development.
But if you look at the formula here
for calculating the sample size is
directly proportional to the vari.
If you reduce the variance by half, you
effectively have the required samples.
By implementing variance reduction
techniques, you have you can
achieve statistical significance
faster with fewer users.
This translates to QCA decision
making, accelerated product iterations
and more experiments run overall
driving rapid innovation and growth.
Now that we have looked at the concept
of the variance reduction, let's look
at some variance reduction techniques.
Variance reduction techniques broadly
fall into five different buckets.
The first one is regression
adjusted with pre period covariates.
This is the umbrella for Cupid and coa.
Pre, pre-post we.
Pick one or two strong pre-treatment
predictors, adjust the outcome.
This will help lower the variance.
We will touch Cupid from this
umbrella in detail in the next slide.
The second one is balanced
assignment at launch.
This can be achieved by blocking,
stratify, randomization,
or pay matching for geos.
So treatment and control start
equal on the stuff that matters.
And the third one is metric engineering.
Noisy numerators and denominators
and heavy tails blow up variance.
So instead, aggregate per
user or cluster level.
Ize the extreme outliers log, transform
the right skewed metrics Cluster.
Cluster aware estimations.
Cluster aware estimations are mainly
used for geo and switchback testing.
Analyze at the cluster or block level and
use the cluster robust standard errors.
The last one is more of
operational thing where you.
Make sure only count truly eligible
and actually exposed users and
freeze the definition of the events
before the experiment starts.
These are few variance
reduction techniques.
Now let's look at QPI in detail.
Cupid is one of the vastly used
variance reduction techniques In
Cupid, we reduce the variance by using
pre-ex experiment data that can help
explain the variance post experiment.
Let's look at an example.
Say we wanna run a test to see if people
run slower with weights attached to them.
The experiment, mild time.
It's a metric that we get when we run
the experiment and corresponding row will
tell us if the weights were added or no.
By looking at the data on the right
side, you can see you can see that the
experiment mile time is already influenced
by how fast of a runner they are.
And you can adjust the experiment mile
time by using average base mile time.
And the average means base mile time
from the pre-ex experiment period
can explain some of the variance.
If you use the change column, which is a
difference between experiment mile time
and base mile time, that can help you
estimate the impact of adding weights.
So what we are doing here is using
pre-ex experiment data to reduce
the variance that was explainable.
Okay.
Some of the best practices for Cupid are
using variables that has high correlation
to the variable of the interest.
When we are applying Cupid, there is
no need to stick with just one variable
from the pre-ex experiment period.
We can use multiple variables if
we believe that could reduce the
variance, effectively, use baseline
that reflects the normal behavior.
Make sure to use the data only
prior to the experiment not
impacted by the experiment.
You can handle the missing values
by imputing the values a color
for people who are interested.
There are some advancements for QPI
methodology called QA where in place of
regression model and single or multiple
covariate from the pre-ex experiment
period, PAC uses machine learning
models to predict the baseline metrics.
By leveraging multiple variables
from the P experiment period.
For those interested, I've
attached a attached link to this
at the end of the presentation.
Please feel free to take a look.
Now let's look at common pitfalls.
If something seems too good
to be true, it probably is.
Whenever you find results that
are extreme, it's always good to
check against common pitfalls.
This can be broadly divided into four
sections technical implementation issues.
Technical implementation issues,
cover sample ratio, mismatch logging
gaps units of randomization mismatch.
When the unit of randomization is
different from unit of analysis,
it inflates the variance.
The second bucket is
experiment design flaws.
This is mainly cost because of
interference and contamination
between the units in the control and
treatment, having impact on one other.
Statistical AL analysis, if you have.
If you need to peak, adjust false, a
positive rate so that there is no room
for p hacking contextual challenges.
There are some additional challenges
in the contextual challenges
like meta drift and seasonality.
Now that we've covered some basic
concepts of AB testing let's look at how
to use this to accelerate your career.
Understanding and practicing
these concepts will enhance
your analytical maturity.
You shift your mindset from reactive
to proactive experimentation strategy.
This will help you challenge
opinions of leaders with evidence
and guide strategic decisions.
You will become a person bridging the
gap between cross-functional teams,
translating stats into business impact,
and these will differentiate you in
the market and make you invaluable.
To do this repeatedly, you
need a platform support.
Okay, let's walk through end-to-end
Cloud native experimentation.
Architecture, a successful a
testing strategy relies on robust.
Scalable cloud native architecture
that supports entire experimentation
lifecycle from initial idea
to validation and iteration,
enabling continuous learning path.
A general cloud native architecture
of end-to-end experimentation flow
can be categorized into few layers.
First.
We could have an infrastructure
which acts like a bedrock for
getting compute building services.
The second layer, we could categorize
this as data layer, where typical
processing, along with the checks
and bounds are set in place.
And the final on the top, we would
have experimentation platform, which
would enable us to control the test
design routing, feature flagging.
And this could run hypothesis testing
to enable us to make informed decisions.
And itrate.
Now let's jump into tips on
building experiment portfolio.
The key three key steps in building
experimentation portfolio, working and
documenting on realistic scenarios.
Document the process showing problem
identification, hypothesis development,
experimental design choice, and
statistical methodologies with
clear business rationale contribute
to open source, contribute to.
Experimentation frameworks and statistical
libraries like STA Model PMCQ, flow Show
Business Impact and recommendation about
next steps to complete end-to-end flow.
Develop a mindset to iterate on the ideas
instead of one and done experiments.
I also want to share some success
strategies for interviews.
Interview.
Success in experimentation fields
requires not only technical expertise,
but also mastery of the concepts
and being able to explain it in
simple terms to the stakeholders.
Prepare specific examples where
your experimentation work drove
measurable business outcomes.
End-to-end experimentation
knowledge on how experimentation
fits larger ecosystem and how.
How to run experiments at scale
will definitely add to this.
A combination of these three would
help you be successful in interviews.
Now that we have a look, now that
we have spoken about the interview
success strategies, let's look at how
the career trajectory of an IC in the
field of data science specializing
in experimentation looks like.
An entry level candidate is expected
to have rock solid EBIT s fundamentals.
Clean hypothesis, reproducible
analysis, and clear writing.
A mid-level candidate is
expected to lead multiple tests.
Mentor analysts, have knowledge
about sequential testing and patient
testing, standardized guardrails.
A senior would be setting
experimentation, strategy,
partnering with engineering to drive.
The platform experimentation platform
drive cross org decisions with a
quantified impact, a principal or
staff would shape the system by
platform roadmaps contributing to open
source conference docs, teaching the
organization on how to learn faster.
To summarize there are
three key takeaways.
One is develop the technical
expertise, pair it with strong
business acumen, master end-to-end
experimentation ecosystem.
Together these form foundation
for a successful career.
I will end my talk with the action plan.
Start today.
Start today by building something small.
Engage with the community, share the
learnings, and learn from the community.
Stay current with emerging
trends and experimentation.
These three will differentiate
you from the rest.
Okay, that's all I have for today.
Thanks for joining me.
Please reach out to me on LinkedIn
if you have any questions or simply
wanna chat about experimentation
or any advice on your career,
I'll be happy to connect there.
All the best to everyone
for all the future yours.
Thank you.