Hello.
Good day.
My name is Victor.
And today I'll be taking you on a
topic called encrypting your way to
safety, data security in kubernetes.
So kubernetes is a popular open source
platform that is being used to deploy,
scale and manage containerized because
of its wild use, because of its good
use, because of how flexible it is,
and self healing, features it has.
Cubanet is widely used
across organizations.
So in this particular presentation,
we're looking at ways you can actually
perform encryptions when your data is
at rest, when your data is in transit
and other security measures you can take
to ensure that there is adequate data
security in your cubanet environment.
Okay, so Why is data security even
important in in Kubernetes environments?
Because Kubernetes being a platform
that has, containerized applications,
it actually has unique challenges.
And for different organizations, from
financial organizations to manufacturing
organizations who use Kubernetes for
their day to day activities when there's a
data breach, this could lead to financial
loss, but potentially not damage.
And also legal consequences,
different continents across the world
have different data privacy laws.
And if an organization doesn't take out
time and take adequate technical measures,
in place to secure data within the
environment, especially customer data or
personnel data or personnel identifiable
data and information, then they could
be liable to get, find and all that.
So it's very important to take
data security seriously when you're
using a Kubernetes environment.
So we're talking about that.
And we're also talking about, we've also
spoken about Compliance requirements.
And also the fact that sensitive
information, some people might
be storing sensitive information
within the Kubernetes environment.
So you probably want to know why it isn't.
This is also, these are some of the
reasons why it's actually important
for you to actually take your
data security seriously from data
breaches, which can also lead to a
downtime to violating customer trust.
to compliance requirements.
So it's very important.
Just a couple of slides and we'll be
looking at the different aspects of,
encrypting your data in kubernetes.
In terms of encryption techniques
around kubernetes, the common ones
we have are symmetric encryption
for symmetric encryption.
For instance, you have, you use the
same key for encrypting the resource.
and also decrypting it.
This makes the process a bit faster
than what we have when than the
asymmetric encryption with because
with symmetric encryption, you use the
same key to encrypt and you also use
the same key to decrypt is faster and
it provides some level of security.
Then we also have another type of
encryption called the asymmetric
encryption where there's a
different key for encryption and
there's also a different key for
decrypting the system, the resource
You are trying to keep secure.
It is more secure, but it has
slower performance due to the fact
that it takes like a longer time.
Then we also have another
type of encryption called
the homomorphic encryption.
Yeah.
You can actually perform some
computations on some, on the
resource that is encrypted, even
though without decrypting it.
So that's another level of encryption.
We have, this can help you to
enhance your privacy and security.
So for you to have access to a particular
sensitive resource, you might actually
perform some, you can perform some
activities on that particular resource,
but you wouldn't decrypt it before
performing that particular process on it.
So that is for homomorphic encryption.
But in the next slides, we'll be looking
at how to keep our data safe when
in the kubernetes environment, when,
sorry, when your data is unrest and when
it is in transit in the next slides.
So there's something called secure.
There are different secure
storage solutions for kubernetes.
that are offered by different providers
like AWS, Microsoft Azure, Google
Cloud, Box, Dropbox and the likes.
We have different secret management
solutions in that can help you keep
sensitive things like your API keys
and your database credentials safe.
You don't really want your database
credentials to, you don't really want
your database credentials to be open.
And for everybody to access
it, anyone who wants to access
it, you want them to be safe.
So there's a secrets
management tool around that.
There's also encrypted volumes
where you can also have an encrypted
storage to store sensitive data.
We'll talk about this.
This is around when your data is at rest,
then there's also secure cloud providers.
Okay.
We have secure cloud providers.
Like I mentioned, Google cloud
storage, AWS, Microsoft Azure.
They also provide secure storage
solutions for different organizations.
So how do you protect your
data when your data is at rest?
So one of the ways to, these
are some ways, this are not,
this is not all the way.
The three we've listed here is not all
the ways you can actually protect them.
Protect your data when it has rest.
This is just the high level
view of how you can protect
your data when it has rest.
So we have the Dixie encryption.
So when fiscal security is a concern
when I talk about fiscal security, I'm
talking about the environment where
your cloud system is set up, when fiscal
security is, compromised and somebody
has access to your disk, you want to
make sure that your disk is encrypted
so that they don't, they will not
have access to the files in your disk.
The next level will be the
file system encryption.
So even though, if even though somebody
is able to have access to your disk,
The files in the disk are supposed to
be encrypted, that's the file level,
the file system encryption, then
also have something called the data
encryption within the storage layer.
So this one talks about encrypting things
around your database, encrypting things
around your API keys, your system storage.
Will be encrypted.
So this your data that is as ready.
This is data actually means that data,
the type of data that are available
when you are not, these are the data
that is available when you are not
actually, making like a transaction and
all that, you have a static data, then.
You have to also try to secure
data when your data is in transit.
Okay.
That is when your data is
moving from point A to point B.
And there are a couple of
ways to actually do this.
One of the ways to actually secure
data in transit between Kubernetes
components, like your pods and your
services, the pods in Kubernetes is the
most basic unit of the Kubernetes system.
And we also have services that define,
how you can actually access The pods or
a container, of pods, then, and the issue
is that resources like pots and services
are actually vulnerable to attacks like
if dropping money in the middle attacks
and interceptions and things like that.
So one of the ways to actually secure
your data would be to use what we'll
call the transport layer security.
The transport layer security protocol is
a cryptographic protocol that provides.
An encrypt that provides an encrypted
communications between the pods and the
services and it will provide some level of
protection from malicious actors getting
unauthorized access to your device, to
your communications or to your data.
Then taking it a step further, we have
something called a mutual TLS, which
is a mutual transport layer security.
This deals Zero trust for
the most for the mutual TLS.
We have things that are
authentication in this particular one.
Like I said, it has to do with zero trust
the sender, the client and the server,
but then have to authenticate themselves
through means such as maybe sending
certificates, sign certificates and things
like that to ensure that It is a right
sender and it is a right receiver that
is actually having access to the data.
We also have things around
network segmentation.
This is can be managed around your network
policy by the network administrator
in Kubernetes and you can design your
Kubernetes system in such a way that
you can design, you can divide it to the
front end, the back end and the database.
With that, you can design in such a way
that only the front end can back end and
only the back end can interact with the
database when you segment your network.
It actually means that when somebody
attacks a section of the network, all
parts of your network will not be down.
Because you've segmented just maybe your
front end might be down, but the back end
needs to be up and it's easier for you
to be like resilient and actually come up
again, so very important to have network
segmentation when you're trying to secure
your data in transit, very important to
isolate certain parts of your network.
Then we have.
There are also other in terms of
data security as a whole, there
are practices, general practices
around cubanet data security.
Like I mentioned, zero trust.
So you have the multi level.
We talked about the mutual transport layer
security, where we have zero security,
where We treat all traffic as untrusted
and it requires strict authentication.
Like I said, we'll have, we'll describe
the client, how to send the certificates
and verify the senders and all that.
Okay.
The verified is the sender and all that.
Then security auditing, they should be
in one of the cutting edge practices for
Kubernetes data security would be for you
to have adequate for you to have adequate.
Security auditing, where you can
regularly monitor and log network security
events, and check who logged into.
And when, that would actually help you.
We also have we also have automated
security tools like Claire, SYN, SYNDX
like Claire, SYNDX Encore, we have
different types of automated security
tools that can be deployed in to
help you, do continuous monitoring,
in order to help you stay on top of
your security game within Kubernetes.
Then what are the ways to
actually fortify your Kubernetes?
actually fortify your Kubernetes
cluster against data breaches?
The way to actually do this would be.
Different.
There are different ways to
actually do this, but I brought
out, I just listed five.
So there are other high level
ways to actually do this.
One of the ways would
be for access control.
Remember the privilege of list, the
principle of list privilege access, right?
So where You only assign access to
a sensitive resource if need be.
Okay.
Individuals who have no need to
actually access the system should
not be accessing the system.
You have to regularly audit who
actually has access to a resource.
There should be security best practices
like ensuring that you use strong
passwords, multi factor authentication,
and you should also update your
secure update your system so that if
there's a security patch that needs
to be done, if there's a vulnerability
somewhere the security patch is going
to help you fix that vulnerability.
And of course you need to also regularly
scan for patches for the releases.
I mentioned about things like systems
like stack rocks uncle and likes, this can
help you regularly monitor your systems.
Okay.
And you should also make sure that you.
Get software that can help you monitor
your security events, analyze for
suspicious activities and the likes.
We mentioned a couple of software that can
help you do that in the previous slide.
Then security training
cannot be overemphasized.
So when you talk about security
training in your system you need
to actually educate your users.
Around best practices, for instance,
your users should not be posting
sensitive information about your
Cuban a system on social media.
There are certain things,
social engineering techniques.
They shouldn't be disposing
of sensitive documents.
Without shredding the documents, you
know when you're when your staffs are
actually working remotely They should
make sure that nobody's watching over
their shoulder when they're on the trains
when they're in the bus things around
social engineering very important to
actually nudge your employees to do the
right things and with regular security
training you can actually Have a cyber
resilient workforce very important.
Most organizations are guilty of Only
having technical security measures,
but ignoring the human security
factor of actually training their
employees around human security.
So in conclusion embracing data
security is something that is going
to like data security in kubernetes
is not something that you actually
just do once and just leave.
It's something you continually do.
Is it ongoing process and requires
adaptation and you keep on implementing
robust data practices in order to protect
your sensitive data in your kubernetes
environment so that you can have the trust
and the confidence of your customers, and
of your partners, so that they know that
their data is actually safe with you.
You don't want a situation whereby the
sensitive data you have in your kubernetes
system leaks, or you are, You become a
victim to ransomware attack or something
and you have downtime and it affects your
brand reputation and you might also be
a subject of, legal issues and all that.
So I hope that with what I've shared
today, you understand the importance
of data security within a Kubernetes
environment and also understand why
encryption is important in your system.
Thank you for listening.
My name remains Victor.
I hope you have an amazing day.
Thank you.