Hello, everyone.
Welcome to my talk on simplifying
multi cloud observability.
In this presentation, we'll talk about
multi cloud observability and why
observability needs a different type
of approach in the multi cloud world.
My name is Sriverma Vegiraju,
currently working as a
software engineer at Microsoft.
I'm a freelance contributor
and a book reviewer as well.
This is my LinkedIn and email.
Please feel free to reach out to me if
you have any suggestions or any questions
regarding the talk or if you want to talk
about software engineering in general.
Let's get started with the agenda.
First, we'll talk about what is multicloud
and why is it gaining a lot of traction.
Second, we'll look into
what is observability.
Third, we'll look at observability.
Why is observability complex in
the multi cloud architecture?
Then we will look at how to simplify
it and then we will conclude the talk.
So what is multi cloud and why
is it gaining a lot of traction?
Initially, when cloud was just
getting started, organization
hosted their services on prem.
Once cloud became mainstream, organization
switched to using both On prem and cloud.
This is what we call as hybrid cloud
then companies Only started using
cloud and if I as an organization
use more than one Cloud provider to
offer my services that is when i'm on
a multi cloud strategy As part of a
recent survey 98 percent of enterprise
customers are either switching to or
are already on a multi cloud strategy.
And the main motivations,
first, data sovereignty.
If I have customers worldwide serving in
different regions and different countries,
I have to abide by the country's data
privacy and data protection laws.
For example, London has its own GDPR.
European Union has its own GDPR.
Similarly, United States, India,
China, Japan, all of them have their
own data privacy and protection laws.
It's my responsibility
to abide by these laws.
And if I find that my cloud provider
does not suit my needs, I might
choose an additional cloud provider.
This is one reason why I would
switch to a take out strategy.
Second, cloud vendor login concerns.
Imagine I am using a particular
service from a cloud provider, and
somehow the provider decides to either
increase the cost of the service, or
change the service drastically,
or deprecate the service.
I want my business to be
resilient to all these factors.
This is the second reason why I
would choose a multi cloud strategy.
Third, cost optimizations.
Every organization or every provider
has their own strong offerings.
Some offer free egress and ingress.
Some offer cheap compute
network or storage.
If I am in a position to utilize all
these strategies, I can reduce the cost
of running my service on the cloud.
So to summarize, data sovereignty, Cloud
vendor lock ins and cost optimizations
are the main reasons companies are
switching towards multi cloud strategy
So what is observability Put it simply
it is the ability to measure the current
state of my system Is my duration high?
Is my availability low?
Am I matching or am I?
Reaching my SLAs, SLOs, SLIs Observability
helps me answer all these questions.
And the three main concepts
in observability are
metrics, logs, and traces.
With metrics, it is a numerical measure
of the current state of your system.
For example, is my availability two
nines, three nines, or four nines?
What is the millisecond latency
at which I'm serving my request?
And what is the error rate?
What is my CPU utilization?
All these answers I
can get from my tricks.
Logs are nothing but your
diagnostic information.
For example, a request failed Then
I have to look at the stack trace
and additional metadata to debug the
request This is what logs will give me.
Traces on the other hand are becoming
popular in the microservices world
Let's say I have this request that
has to pass through 10 different
microservices And it fails in one of
or one of the service You Traces will
help me debug these kind of requests.
Now, let's look at why observability
needs a different approach in the multi
cloud world and what are the changes
that are mandating this mandating this.
What you see here is a code snippet
where I'm just using one cloud provider.
What I have is a monitoring SDK that I'm
using to emit metrics to a dashboard.
Everything is simple because I'm
just in a single cloud world.
There is nothing complex here, right?
Now, in, in this case here, I am using
two or three different cloud providers.
So I have three different SDKs and
on the right I have two or three
different kinds of dashboards Just
looking at this we can understand the
complexity that we are getting into.
So let's look at that Because
i'm using multiple clouds.
I have multiple SDKs And because
I have multiple SDKs I end
up maintaining all of them.
It is either versioning or deprecation
or schematics I'll have to Keep tabs
of all this information for the SDKs.
Second, each cloud provider dashboard
is different and the way they do
aggregations is also different.
Some sample at five minutes,
some sample at one minute.
Now, I have to document all this
information so that my on calls understand
how to debug a particular dashboard.
Now, there's an interesting nuance there.
The on calls In addition to be
debugging the service outages are
also debugging the dashboards now.
By just hearing that we know
things will get easily out of
hand once there's a big fire.
Last but not the least, the cost.
Now we have to hire more experienced
developers who don't come cheap
and also train them, which is also
not, which is also very expensive.
So how do we get out of this problem?
How do we make things complex
for our developers is what
we'll take a look at now.
If I summarize the problem here,
what I want to offer is one single
pane of glass experience for my
customers, for my developers.
And if I have to offer one single
pane of glass experience, I should
also be cloud or provider agnostic.
And this is where a lot of open source.
Tooling has been helping us,
and it is also helping us now.
What we are going to take a
look at is OpenTelemetry, which
is one such open source tool.
It is under the Cloud Native
Computing Foundation umbrella.
And what it simply states is, it
is a single open source standard
to emit your observability data,
your metrics, logs, and traces.
Second, it is already supported by
major cloud providers like AWS, GCP
and Oracle already support this.
And the more, and the best
part, it is vendor agnostic.
So let's look at how what are
the critical components in this
cloud native in OpenTelemetry.
First, we have the specification.
The specification comes into
picture when you're implementing
OpenTelemetry for a specific language.
Because we don't do this daily,
we will not get into details here.
Next, we have semantics.
Remember we discussed about one
single pane of glass experience?
For that, one important thing
you need is a unified schema.
With semantics, you can get that.
Open telemetry SDK is what we will use
to emit the metrics, logs, and traces.
Before we were using a provider specific
SDK, now we will use open telemetry SDK.
By the way, it is available
in many different languages, C
sharp, Java, Go, Ruby, and so on.
Fourth, what we have is the exporter.
Exporter is responsible for
translating the metrics that we
Translating the observability data
from OpenTelemetry SDK into a language
that the provider understands.
AWS has their own exporter.
GCP, Microsoft, all of them
have their own exporters.
And what these exporters do is
query SDK to get the observability
data and emit to the backend, which
is our last piece in the puzzle.
The backend is nothing but
the cloud provider themselves.
AWS, Azure, GCP, or they can
be Prometheus, Jaeger, also.
To summarize, specification required
mostly when you are implementing
OpenTelemetry in a specific language.
Semantics are the way you achieve
one single schema, one single schema.
OpenTelemetry SDK is what you use
to emit the observability data.
Exporter is what you use to
used to translate the the
OpenTelemetry observability
data into vendor specific data.
And then you have the packets.
Let's look at architecture.
So what on the left is on,
what on the left here is before
OpenTelemetry, we have our VM, our
service, and the Azure Monitor SDK.
Because we are tied to Azure.
Azure backend, we are using their
SDK to EMIT metrics, which we
know is a problem on the right.
What is the Open Telemetry one here.
What ends up happening is instead
of the Azure Monitor, SDK, use the
open telemetry SDK to emit your
observability data, and then you use
the Azure telemetry exporter, which is
readily available for us to consume.
Just to clarify.
The exporter is not a sidecar.
It is just another package in C
sharp or a dependency in Maven
that you import into your service.
And then the exporter does all the
heavy lifting of translating the metrics
or observability data into a way that
the Azure backend can understand.
And then send it to Azure.
Now, what we have done is consolidated
Now, what we have done is
consolidated our code from
multiple, using multiple different
SDKs to one SDK to send the data.
What you see here is a code snippet of
how, when we are using the OTEL SDK.
What we have here on the top is
the namespace and then what, and
then here we have the exporters
and then on the last year.
Is where we are sending,
emitting the metrics.
Now, if I want to add one more exporter
I just add it to the set of extensions
here and I don't change any of the
names space the way I emit metrics.
So the whole process
has become simplified.
This is an example of how we could, how
how using open telemetry would look when
in, when using multiple cloud providers.
So here, none of the VM service or the
SDK changes, they all remain the same.
The only thing that
changes is the exporter.
Remember we also discussed single pane
of class experience to see the dashboard.
This is where we can use Grafana to
export all the metrics data from different
providers to the to Grafana so that
we can offer developers once we can
offer developers unified experience by
while debugging through the dashboards.
So
this is how.
We can simplify the whole observability
stack for our service and make experience
seamless for our developers As multi
cloud architecture keeps growing it is
very important that organizations make
vendor agnostic strategy part of their
architecture and part of their culture.
This is how organizations can keep
scaling without any bottlenecks
and offer seamless experience to
both developers and their clients.
Apart from this, there are a ton of other
open source tooling also available that
have their own exporters and can help
Query open telemetry sdk, for example
with prometheus you are able to export
Metrics to your own bucket With Loki,
it is a log search experience that
Grafana offers in addition to Metrix.
Previously, they only had the Metrix,
the dashboards only used to show Metrix,
but now with Loki, you can also see logs.
With Zepkin and Jaeger, you can export
traces out of traces from the SDK
to the Jaeger or Zepkin backends.
With this, I conclude my talk.
Thank you for taking the time to
listen to the, to listen to this
talk on simplifying multicloud
observability and hope you enjoyed it.