Hi myself, Manu I would like to
discuss, speak about autonomous ops
for cloud native financial services
engineering, cost governance at scale.
So myself I'm manure kako, so I currently
work at a leading global technology
company where I specialize in customer
electronics and cloud-based services.
Where I lead initiatives in site
reliability, engineering and platform
automations and cloud cost optimizations
with experience in building, scaling, and
automating cloud native infrastructure.
My expertise with Kubernetes and
CICD cost cloud cost governance
and infrastructure code.
So with a strong focus on reliability
performance and compliance in high
regular, in industries such as
financial services, where I specialized
in designing resilient audit ready
platforms and implementing autonomous
monitoring for cloud related activities
and remedies for the workflow.
I am presenting this automation finance
for cloud native financial services.
Why I'm presenting this.
So the presentation is about this.
Financial services are at crossroads.
So they are under immense pressure to
modernize with cloud native technologies.
We, while facing raising costs
unpredictability, scaling,
and strict regular demands.
So traditional finance ops models are like
largely retrospective and manual, so are
no longer sufficient to keep up with the
speed and complexity of the Kubernetes
space multi-tenant environments.
So as a lead of engineers, so I am.
Working as a DevOps.
So I see a an urgent need for
embedding a financial intelligence
directly into the engineering cycle.
This session is about showing how
autonomous fan ops with automation
and air driven anomaly detection and
policy enforcement and auditory design.
Can deliver a scalable cost governance
without slowing the innovations.
Today's agenda is going to be on
the finance service cloud dilemma.
So traditional fin financial
operations limitations, platform
engineering with finance ops.
And autonomous capabilities and
implementing the blueprints.
As a financial institute modernization
on cloud architectures, right?
So the cost governance become
both on regularity requirements
as a business imperative.
So traditional and manual financial
operation practices cannot keep up Peace.
With dynamic and multi-tenant Kubernetes
environments, unpredictable scaling
and raising cloud provider cost.
And autonomous finance introduced
intelligent automations, right?
So AI driven detection and embedded policy
enforced to deliver real time visibility.
And continuous optimization and
audit ready compliance by by
integrating the financial control
directly to the development
pipelines and operational workflow.
So the financial service and
organization can achieve scalable
cost covenants predictability and cost
spent on strong regulatory alignments
without slowing the innovation.
So let's go to the next slide.
So this slide is about the like
financial service cloud dilemma.
And expand overview on this is so the
financial service cloud dilemma like
financial institutions are accelerating
cloud adoption to modernize services and
stay competitive, but face major hurdles.
Legacy systems make migration complex
while regulatory demand strict
transparency and cost attributes.
Multitenant Kubernetes environments
at scalable but complicate
the cost monitoring, right?
So especially with unpredictable
scaling driven by the market violations
and raising cost provider cost and.
A, a skill gap in a traditional IT finance
and cloud native operations further
intensify the challenge and unchecked.
These urist financial stability and
compliance to succeed institutes
must combine real time visibility
automated optimization and strong
collaboration between IT finance and.
Compliance teams to balance that
innovation and the cost governance.
So this slide is about acceleration.
Digital transformations while
managing complex legacy systems
and, budget constraints,
significant skill gaps complex and
multi-tenant Kubernetes environments
suffering thousands of workload.
So coming to the next slide,
traditional finance is falling behind.
I'm gonna discuss about the
reactor analysis disconnected
systems and slow feedback loops.
Traditional finance financial
operation practices are no longer
sufficient for today's cloud native.
Fast moving.
Financial environments, right?
So they rely heavily on reactive
retrospective and cost analysis.
So like reviewing the cloud bills
after the fact rather than providing
real time insights disconnected
financial and engineering systems
create operational slowness.
So making it a difficult to align,
speeding with actual workload.
As a result, like feedback loops
are slow, often taking weeks to
detect the address cost anomalies.
So in highly regulated financial systems.
So they delay in more
than budgeting problems.
It continues a governance failures
exposing institutions to both
financial risks and compliance issues.
So the violation of cloud de
developments has outpaced traditional
financial operations, living
institute vulnerabilities to cost
overrun and regulatory scrutinies.
So by the time caused spikes the cost
spike is detected in traditional financial
operations, the financial damage.
Is already ineffective.
So in the high regulator
financial sectors, this isn't
the merely a budget concern.
It represent significance
a governance failures.
So coming to the next slides, we'd like
to discuss about the platform engineering.
And the financial evaluations
from reactive monitoring to
proactive monitoring, right?
So reactive monitoring has post factor
cost analysis manual works limited
developer bilities, low feedback
on cost anomalies coming to the
practical governance from reactive.
We have in Incre integrated cost
optimizations for software development
lifecycle real time automated insights
empower development, manage speed,
and automated anomaly automation.
So platform engineering elevates
financial operations from
react to, to proactive focusing
functions to the governance model.
Like practical models.
So this ambit across the entire
engineering life cycle start off relying
on cost monitoring and slow workflows.
Financial intelligence is
integrated directly in developing
pipelines are given in real time
automated insights and cost impact.
This approach empowers developers
to manage and optimize optimize
spend a as they build while
automated system remediates
anomalies before they escalates.
So the results is a balance model
where financial institute gains a
ability of cost adoption without
sacrificing the cost control,
compliance, and financial stability.
So unlocking a greater efficient and
predictability and long term value
creation for the evolution process.
So coming to the embedded
financial intelligence.
So here we are gonna discuss
about infrastructure as the code
templates and continuous integration,
continuous deployment, financial gates
Kubernetes administration controls.
And real time telemetry.
Embedded financial intelligence means
building cost awareness and governance
directly into the engineering workflow.
And rather than treating it as a after
true this is achieved through like
these four mentioned qualities like
infrastructure as a code templates.
CICD, KU administration,
real time telemetry.
So by waiving financial control
into development and deployment
process, financial interest can
achieve continuous cost, governance
and proactive anomaly detection and
predictability cloud span like all
while maintaining compliance process.
So coming to the
pre-deployment cost estimation.
Technical implementations
involves averaging static
analysis for infrastructure as
a code templates for precious.
Our resource cost calculations utilize
historical users datas for accuracy
integrating directly with a cloud provider
like pricing, APIs and realtime stuff.
Optimizing costs through reverse instance
and saving like scale down and stuff.
Financial government benefits
includes enabling proactive budgeting
validation prior to the development.
Providing cost estimation confidence
intervals for better financial planning.
Faculty Accu Curate project
level financial forecasting.
Maintain a clear audit trail for cost
of brewers, so pre pre-development,
cost estimate, and based like financial
accountability early in the software or
development lifecycle by predicting cost
spend before workloads are launched.
Technically this involves
analyzing infrastructure code.
Templates using historical
usage pattern for high traffic
or high user data patterns.
And pulling the real time pricing data
from cloud providers on enterprise cloud
subnets, or to calculate expected costs.
Optimizing strategies such as or as
mentioned rivers instance and savings
plans further refine these estimations.
For financial governance perspective,
these these enables institutions to
validate budgets proactively, right?
And produce a confident base
forecasting and maintain an
audit trial to cost approvals.
So this results in more predictable
financial planning and reduce
their risk to unexpected cl cloud
financial burdens or expenses.
Moving on to the slide of
policy-based budgeting gating.
Define budget policies.
So I'm gonna is about implementing
enforce points build approval workflow
and create a feedback mechanism.
So policy based budget getting enforce
financial guardrails throughout the
software or development pipelines, right?
So by defining.
Granular YAML based budgeting pro
policies to the project team, or
application level organizations can
ensure spending limits are respected.
These policies are enforced at a
critical stage of code commits, bills,
deployments, scaling events to preview.
To the previous comments are
reviewing the level of compassion.
So to prevent the audit runs
before they occurs, right?
So automated approval workflow
handles exceptionals with proper
authorization and audit logging.
So while real time dashboards are alerts,
provide continuous visibility into the.
Compliance and budget consumption.
So this approach ensures cloud
spending stay on predictability avoid
cost surprises, and maintain regular
compliance in the financial services.
So coming to the next slide, we have
automated tagging and compliance.
So automated tagging and.
Compliance of automated finance.
So financial operations ensure
every resource is accurate, tracker
and allocated and completed.
So this includes enforcement managed
tag schemas at creation enabling tagging
inheritance to consistent line age.
And dynamically applying tags
based on the deployment context.
Tag validation gates with continuous
integration kind deployment pipelines
previously non-compliant deployments
while remediation bots automatically fixes
untagged or mist tagged resources, right?
So comprehensive compliant report.
Provider audit readiness, visibility and
accountability, supporting both financial
transparency and regulatory requirements.
Yeah.
Coming to the next slide, we are going to
discuss on real time anomaly detection.
So this involves time series
analysis, resource fingerprinting.
And cultivation detection
and predictive forecasting.
Real time anomalies that users machine
learning to move beyond static alerts
and provide adaptive, pro and proactive
monitoring for cloud spanning right
by applying time series analysis.
It identifies Devi station from
historical usage and seasonal trends.
Resource fingerprint creates a
behavioral baselines for workloads
while co correlations with detection
line cost spikes for the deployments
and as well as the application
events or external triggers.
So additionally proactive forecasting
projects future costs, right?
So with confidence interval enabling
terms to anticipate issues before
they escalate they approach ensure
financial institutes can rapidly detect
it or, they can investigate, right?
And remediate the anomalies.
By maintaining cost control,
compliance, and operational stability
by maintaining the governance
in dynamic cloud environments.
How like self-healing cost
for remediation works.
So it can help out with anomaly
detection, root cause analysis remediation
workflow, and automated actions.
So typically, self-healing remediation
action includes right size over provision
resources automatically applying these
computer reservation discounts suggesting
and executing storage to your operations.
Recommending face id architectural
changes for sustaining savings.
So self-healing cost remediation
represents the next stage of
intelligence financial operations.
So where cloud environments not
only detect the anomalies, but
also resolve them automatically
to prevent financial leakages.
And compliance risks.
So the process begins with a machine
learning driven auto anomaly detection
which identifies unusual cost patterns
are policy violations in real time.
So once flagged automated
root cause analysis pinpoints
the exact resource workloads.
Or even the deployments
change behind the issues.
So based on the severities of the
clarifications a remediation workflow is
triggered using a predefined playbooks.
These workflows may execute in
self-service mode or with developer
improvements or in a full automated
fashion with approvals And, complete
audit trials to maintain the governance.
So these are the common selfish
self-healing action included in the slide.
So by by combining AI driven
insights automatic and governance,
self-healing remediation allows
financial institutions to continuously
optimize and the cloud environments.
That do not only reduce costs, but also
enforce compliance improves predictability
and enhance operational resilience.
Ensuring financial stability
is high, highly dramatic.
So they dynamically want to reduce,
regulate the cloud ecosystem.
Oops.
So coming to the audit audit
ready infrastructure design.
This eng includes immutable cost
logs metadata governance audit
reporting, so critical capability
providing the financial controls
where enforce consistently across
all cloud resource of at all time.
Audit ready infrastructure and financial
operations, financial services.
So in highly regulated financial
environments cloud infrastructure support,
a comprehensive audit or auditability.
And strict fi, financial ance automation,
financial operations solution address.
These need to be provided Im immutable.
Cost logs standardization, metadata,
schemas tamper proof recording
for all the financial conditions.
Approvals, cost at attributions,
so those system enable automated
reporting aligned with regular
frameworks such as GDPX SOX compliance.
PCI compliance DSS.
So ensuring these financial controls
are constantly enforcing across
all cloud resource at all times.
Prebuilt reports and structural
governments framework simply
compliance reduce the risks and provide
verifiable evidence for the audits.
That helps.
Yeah.
Coming to the next slide, building
up the financial platform for
technical implementation blueprints.
So the core components involves cost
estimations, service integration with
infrastructure as code policy engine
for budget enforcement financial,
elementary collection and storage machine
learning pipeline for anomaly detection.
Remediation workflow and orchestration.
So integration points involves
but not less than version control,
pre-commit hooks, integration,
energy deployment, pipeline stages.
Kubernetes administration controls
cloud provider APIs and even streams
existing observability platforms.
Building your financial operation
platform for a technical blueprint
is a robust platform financial
operation platform that combines costs,
services, and strategic integrations
to manage cloud cost efficiently.
And core components includes a
cost estimation service integrated
with infrastructure as a code a.
And a policy engine for budget
enforcement as mentioned.
So not only the financial telemetry
collection and storage, but the mission
learning part, anomaly detection pipeline.
So to max the, to maximize impact
organizations should focus on high value
integration point points first, and expand
to the platform integr integrations.
And to ensure scalable and sustainable
financial operation systems.
Coming to the next slide, so we are gonna
discuss about measuring financial success
for cost reduction cost predictability
policy compliance and response time.
Measuring the financial success
is in financial services, right?
So efficiently evaluating the
financial success requires a
multi-dimensional approach that
goes beyond simple cost savings.
One key metrics is cost reduction, which
measures the quantifiability savings.
But achieving through the autonomous
optimization and intelligent cloud
management like also come back to
the traditional manual work manual
methods complementing these to a cost
predictability, which tracks percentage
to cost spend that constantly aligns
with predefined forecasting range.
That enables organizations to plan
budgeting with a greater accuracy
and reduce financial uncertainty.
Another critical measures is policy
compliance where to ensure that all
cloud resources are currently tagged and
allocated to the respective cost centers.
This is not only maintains, ad hoc
to the financial governance, but
also provides clear visibility to
audit and regulatory reporting.
Beyond these direct financial
metrics, a successful financial
program financial operations
program, I would say also delivers
broader organization value, right?
Improved financial governance
reduced the risks to audit
discrepancies and regular penalties.
So enhanced self-service capabilities,
imports developers to developers
and the cloud team to operate more
efficiently forecasting involving
while maintaining cost discipline.
By combining measure measurable
savings and predictable budgeting
and regulatory compliance.
Also, I a rapid anomaly response.
Organizing these can historically
access the impact of their financial
operations initiative and ensure
the cloud investments deliver both.
Finance and the benefits
of the organizations.
Coming to the final
slide on the takeaways.
So the key takeaways are shifting
finance operational lift empower,
engineering automated governance
design to design for the compliance.
Coming to the key takeaways for efficient
financial operations implementation.
So this is important because to
achieve maximum impact for financial
operation initiative organizations
must adapt a strategic, proactive
approach that embed financial
intelligence throughout the software.
Delivered life cycle.
And shifting financial operations
left insurers the cost valuable and
financial controls are integrated
earlier than the expected.
So in this development and deployment
process so allowing teams, also
allowing teams to anticipate
and migrate cloud spending risks
before they escalate, right?
Also equally important in empowering
engineering teams while self-service
tools and actionable insights are
in action while developers and
excuse me, and operations have
ability to make information cost
conscious stations without bottleneck
necks and, and other issues.
So organization benefits from
fast innovation cycle improve
accountability and risk reduced for
budget over automating governance.
In other critical is the other critical
pillar for this financial operations
initiative by moving from manual
reviews to automated policy enforcement.
So financial.
Controls can be considerable
applied across all cloud resources
at scale reducing human errors and
ensuring compliance with internal
policies and external regulations.
So finally designing for compliance
is essential in regulator industries.
So systems must be architect for
audit readiness with immutable logs
of transparent financial records
and standardized report framework
that demonstrates add all to
regular regulatory requirements.
So by combining proactive cost
management developer empowers automated
governance and compliance focus designs.
Organizations can optimize cost
investments while maintaining
financial discipline operational
affectiveness and regulatory assurance.
So this is about the financial
operations initiative, and thank you.