Hello, everyone.
I'm Ravi Kamambatti.
I'm very excited here to talk
about designing resilient and
scalable network infrastructure
at the, for the digital age.
I'm an engineering manager at Realize
with strong focus in networking,
predominantly in the areas of routing,
switching, firewalls, telecommunication.
Over the next 30 minutes, we will
cover on these following topics
related to layer two and layer
three networking technologies.
Then advanced networking concepts
like road distribution, quality
of service and security protocols.
Then how automation and AI are
shaping the future of networks.
And we'll end up with industry
applications, key for future trends.
And my conclusion on it.
So let's dive into the introduction.
As we all know, in today's world,
network infrastructure is the heart
of every digital transformation.
It acts as the backbone for seamless
data communication, ensuring
businesses can operate efficiently
in this fast paced environment.
The goal of this presentation is take you
through critical components of the network
design with a focus on how we can make
networks, both resilient and scalable.
These two factors, resilience
and scalability are the crucial
because we need networks that not
only cover from these issues, but
also to grow with evolving needs.
Next let's talk about in detail with
regards to the switching technologies.
At layer two of the OSM model, we
have the switching technologies.
Layer two is basically
responsible for local transmission
within the network segment.
And it plays a critical role in how data
is handled and moved across devices.
One key concept here is the VLANs
or the virtual local area networks.
VLANs allow us to virtually segment
a network, meaning we can group
devices together based on a logic
rather than their physical location.
Their segmentation enhances the
security by isolating sensitive data,
improves performance by reducing
unnecessary traffic over the network.
For example, in the enterprise
setting, you could group the
accounting department into one VLAN
and HR department into another.
Even though they may share the
same physical network, the VLAN
ensures that data is separated.
Now we talk about trunking.
This is where we allow multiple VLANs
to share single physical network link.
By doing this, we optimize resources.
Simplify network architecture trunking
allows the VLAN to communicate
with each other efficiently while
maintaining the distant boundaries.
And finally, a spanning tree
protocol or STP is a critical
piece of layer 2 technology.
It prevents network loops where
which can be a major issue,
especially in large networks where
data could potentially circulate
endlessly clogging up the network.
STP or Spanning Tree Protocol ensures
that there is always a primary path for
data and a backup in case the main path
fails, adding much more needed redundancy.
Now let's talk about
the routing protocols.
Now let's shift the gear to layer three.
This is where routing comes into play.
While Layer 2 focuses on switching within
the network, Layer 3 enables communication
across multiple networks through routing.
One of the most well known
protocols here is OSPF.
Open shortest path first.
OSPIP is a dynamic routing protocol,
meaning it constantly updates itself to
find the best path for data transmission.
It's highly scalable, and it's highly
used in large enterprise networks.
Then we have the BGP.
The Border Gateway Protocol is
essential for managing how packets
are routed across the internet.
It allows the data to travel between
different autonomous systems or
networks, especially those controlled
by different organizations.
Think of BGP as a
backbone of the internet.
It ensures that data finds its
way across diverse networks.
Finally, we talk about MPLS multi
multi protocol label switching.
Streamline the routing process by enabling
label rather than long network addresses.
This improves speed as an efficiency,
especially in large networks
where there is a lot of traffic.
By understanding this layer 3
protocols, we can see how data moves
it between individual networks and
across the border broader internet.
Now let's talk about the synergy
between Layer 2 and Layer 3.
So how do Layer 2 work work together?
The answer lies in their synergy.
These two layers are not
stand alone technologies.
Rather, they complement each other.
with each other to create a seamless
and efficient network efficient network.
At layer two, we use a VLAN for
segmentation, creating isolated
segment sections within the network.
At layer three, we use routing protocols
like OSP of BGP to connect these
segments, route data between them.
This ensures that both isolation
and connectivity were key
components in modern network design.
Let me give you an example.
In a corporate environment, you need
to You might use a VLAN to isolate
the marketing, finance, HR department.
However, we still need to communicate
with each other at certain points.
Layer 3 routing protocols allow
this for this communication while
maintaining the isolation of
each department sensitive data.
This integration between Layer 2 and Layer
3 reduces latency, maximizes throughput,
ensures that data moves efficiently across
the network without unnecessary delays.
This It's about achieving
the right balance between
segmentation and performance.
Now let's talk about the
advanced networking concepts.
Let's explore some advanced
networking concepts.
These technologies enhance networking
performance, security, and efficiency.
First, let's talk about
the route distribution.
In many large networks, multiple
routing protocols are used.
Route distribution enables these
protocols to coexist by sharing
route information across them.
This ensures cohesive network operation
even when different parts of the
network uses different protocols.
Then we have quality of service or QoS
is basically crucial for prioritizing
certain types of traffic over other.
For instance, in a video conference,
you may need to make sure that video and
audio packets are given priority over.
Less critical traffic like background
background downloads by doing this
QoS maintains a performance standards
even when network is congested.
Finally, let's touch down on
security concepts like access
control lists or ACLs and IPSec.
ACLs control who and what kind of
certain parts of the network can
access certain part of the network.
For example, ACLs can be used to
ensure that only authorized personnel.
Can access sensitive financial data ipsec
on the other hand is a suite of protocols
Used to secure communication by encrypting
and authenticating each IP packet is
commonly used in vpn to secure remote
communications All of these advanced
networking tools play a role in optimizing
and securing modern networks Now let's
discuss a security in network design
security is a critical, in every aspect
of network design without robust measures
Even the most efficient network can
fall victim to breaches and disruptions.
As I mentioned earlier, ACLS or access
control lists are used to define the
define which users and systems can
access specific parts of a network.
ACL access are filter based on criteria
like IP addresses or protocols.
Common use cases is is like
restricting access to a to a sensitive
data in a corporate environment.
For instance, in a financial institutions,
ACL might allow only the financial
team to access certain database while
keeping others their departments out.
Another key in for security feature is
IPSec or Internet Protocol Security.
IPSec ensures secure communication
by encrypting and authenticating IP
packets in a communication session.
This is particularly useful
in virtual private networks.
We are secure data sense
between remote workers and and
corporate network with IPSec.
You can ensure that the data remains
private and unaltered, and even if
intercepted by many malicious actors
in today's increasingly complex
network environments, securing
every layer is crucial.
Network design needs to needs
to account for both internal and
external threats, making sure
the security is the top priority.
Next, let's discuss about
the industry applications.
So far, we are so how are these
applicator technologies being
applied in real world industries?
Let's look into a few case studies
that I would like to describe.
In a financial operation or an enterprise
level operation, network resilience is
key for critical business functions.
For instance, in financial
services, companies rely on
high availability networks to
ensure uninterrupted operations.
Let's take a look at a few examples.
By using layer 2 and layer 3 networking
concepts, financial firms can create
highly resilient networks that minimize
downtime and ensure business continuity.
In the telecom industry, 5G
networks are a new frontier.
With high speed and low latency
capabilities, telecoms are implementing
5G to provide enhanced service delivery.
Here, layer 3 protocols like BGP play a
critical role in managing the flow of data
across large and distributed networks.
Another exciting area is the Internet
of Things or IoT in smart cities,
for example, IoT manages the device
connectivity and data flow between
thousands of sensors and devices.
These network needs to be highly
scalable and secure to ensure
the safety and efficiency of the
network city's infrastructure.
These examples highlight the real
world impact of well designed,
resilient and scalable networks
across different industries.
Next, let's look into some of the future
trends in networking and discuss about
some of the automation or recent AI
upcoming or developments in networking.
So let's start with automation.
Automation is a quickly becoming essential
in network management as network becomes
more complex and large managing or
manually conferring and monitoring a
large scale network is no longer feasible.
Bye for now.
Especially when increasing number of
devices and the complexity of the modern
networks Automated tools now handle
many routine tasks such as configuration
management Network monitoring and
troubleshooting this reduces the human
error and improves overall Operational
efficiency for example rather than having
to manually configure every device and
automation Tool can basically apply
configurations across multiple devices at
once ensuring consistency and saving time.
Moreover, automation helps
with faster issue resolution
when network problem arises.
Automated monitoring systems can detect
and apply pre configured fixes without
the need for human intervention.
Now let's talk about the AI and machine
learning and network management.
Building on the concept of
automation, AI and machine learning
are now playing an increasingly
critical role in network management.
AI and ML have introduced proactive
analysis, allowing networks to
anticipate issues before they occur.
For example, ML algorithms can analyze
historical data to identify patterns that
might indicate potential network failures,
enabling protect proactive maintenance.
Anomaly detection is another
key area where AI shines.
AI powered systems can continuously
monitor traffic, identify unusual
behavior that could increase a security
breach, or assist a malfunction.
Once detected, these systems can
automatically apply corrective measures,
minimizing the downtime and reducing
the impact of the potential threats.
AI and ML are also improving network
efficiency through automated decision
making by continuously analyzing network
performance, And these technologies can
significantly adjust configurations to
optimize traffic flow, ensuring networks
are always running at peak performance.
The perform the future of networking
will heavily rely on intelligent systems
to manage increasingly complexity
of the network of modern networks.
Now let's look into the
evolving security trends.
As network becomes more distributed and
complex, security must also, you want
to keep the pace with the new trends.
One of the biggest shifts we are seeing
in the move from traditional security
models to a zero trust architecture.
In a zero trust model, we no longer
assume that trusts are only external.
Instead, we treat every part of
the network as a potential target.
This means every user device and data
must flow through authentication,
authorized, and continuously validated.
It is more rigorous approach, but
one needs to be one needs to make
sure it's really important or
necessary in today's threat landscape.
Within this, we are seeing an adoption
of more sophisticated and encrypted
methods and enhanced identity management
systems, advanced encryption ensures
the data is encrypted and encrypted.
It is cannot be read or
altered by any means.
Meanwhile, the identity solution
management ensures that only authorized
users have access to sensitive data.
Network security is no longer
just keeping threads out.
It's about protecting the network
from both internal and external.
Risk while maintaining
performance and resilience.
Now that we are at the conclusion and
we are trying to wrap up the session.
As we wrap up this presentation,
let's take a moment to recap
the point, the key points.
We have explored the foundation of routing
and switching, looked at how layer 2 and
layer 3 technologies work together to
create resilient and scalable networks.
We also discussed the advanced networking
concepts like route distribution, quality
of service, and which are critical
for optimizing performance and complex
environments security has been a recurring
theme throughout the today's talk from
access control list ipsecs to Evolving
landscape of zero trust architecture as
network continues to grow in complexity
security must remain a top priority We
have also test on importance of automation
Ai machine learning in shaping the future
of network management These technologies
are not only and not just in the future,
they're already transforming how we
design, build, and manage today's network.
Finally, we looked into the real world
application of these technologies in
industries like financial services,
telecom, IOT, and discussed some of the
trends that will continue to prevail
to shape the future of networking.
As we move forward, the key
takeaway is that the resilient.
And scalable and secure networks
are foundation of any successful
digital transformation.
The decisions we make today in in
designing these networks will shape
how businesses will operate together.
Thank you for all for
your time and attention.
I hope this talk provided you with
some valuable insights and into the
future of networking infrastructure.
I'm always happy to take any
questions that you might have.