Okay.
Hello all.
I'm Gita Ola, and I'm so hap, so happy
to be here with all of you today.
I'm a healthcare technologist specializing
in cloud native architectures and
interoperability solutions, and
I'm deeply passionate about using
technology to make healthcare more
equitable and accessible for everyone
no matter where they live, right?
So with the last few years, I've closely
worked with healthcare organizations,
modernizing their systems using
Kubernetes, FHIR, and microservice.
Mainly bridging the gap between
technology, innovation, and
real world patient care.
Today my talk is titled about
Reimagining Healthcare Access with Data
Integration and Microservices at Scale.
In the next 35 minutes,
I'm going to talk with you.
All about how data integration and modern
cloud architectures are transforming
healthcare, improving outcomes, and
driving efficiency, especially for
rural land underserved populations.
The healthcare data crisis, the
modernization imperative, the cloud
native architecture, evolution, real
world impact stories, and finally, the
design principles that make healthcare
systems resilient and scalable.
So healthcare data crisis.
So when we talk about healthcare
modernization, the first thing we have
to acknowledge is the data crisis.
Today in nearly 80% of critical
patient data remains siloed across
disconnected healthcare systems.
That means that patient records, lab
results, and even prescription data
often live in separate databases
that don't talk to each other.
So this fragmentation doesn't
just create inefficiency.
It directly impacts patient
safety, for example.
Imagine a diabetic patient who
visits a rural clinic, then a city
hospital, and later a specialist.
If these systems can't share data,
doctors end up repeating tests, missing
critical history or delaying treatment.
So this is an just a technology issue.
It's a human issue.
When data is fragmented, care
becomes fragmented, right?
So globally, this lack of data integration
inflates operational costs and slows down
every aspect of the healthcare system.
So the question becomes
how do we break this silo?
This brings us to the
modernization imperative.
So the modernization imperative is
the healthcare systems today are under
enormous pressure to scale, integrate,
and respond faster than ever before.
So we need infrastructure that can
handle massive data of volumes and
simultaneous users, doctors, patients,
insurance systems, all at once.
So we need interoperability where
data moves freely and securely between
providers, payers, and patients.
And finally, we don't do we need to think
about rural access in many parts of the
world and even parts of United States.
Access to specialists or diagnostics can
take weeks simply because of geography.
Technology has the
potential to close that gap.
So modernization isn't
just optional anymore.
It's essential.
So we need scalable infrastructure,
we need interoperable systems,
and we need solutions that make
healthcare systems accessible limits.
So this is where the cloud native
architecture comes into play.
It's the cloud native
architecture evolution.
So in the last few years, we have
seen a revolution in how healthcare
systems are being built, right?
So cloud native, Kubernetes based
microservices are now redefining how
hospitals and health platforms operate.
Instead of one giant monolithic
application, which we are trying
to do everything microservices,
allow us to break that system into
smaller, independent components.
Each one focused on a
specific function like patient
management, billing, scheduling.
So these services can scale
individually, heal automatically,
and communicate through standardized
APIs such as FHIR, which is Fast
Healthcare Interoperability Services.
What does this mean is that we can finally
achieve true interoperability where
every system speaks the same language.
Yes.
I like to describe it as a turning
giant rigid block into a set of flexible
Lego pieces that can be rearranged,
reused, and scaled in independently.
And Kubernetes acts as the conductor
orchestrating all of these services,
making sure they're healthy,
resilient, and always available.
So this architectural shift
is fundamentally reserving
healthcare inefficiency.
Is creating, the systems are scalable,
resilient, and interoperable.
Now comes the HIEs on something
about health information exchanges.
So now let's talk about the real
world impact of data integration.
One of the best examples is the success
of health information exchanges or HI.
When systems began sharing patient data
across hospitals, labs, and clinics, we
saw immediate measurable improvements.
Integrated HIEs have use preventable
hospital readmissions by 30%, and also
have cut duplicate lab testing by 52%.
So that's not just efficiency,
that's saving lives.
So these integration mean.
Patients don't have to repeat their
story every time they enter a new clinic.
It means few errors, faster
diagnosis, and lower costs, and it
shows us what's possible when we
truly connect healthcare systems.
But data integration alone isn't enough.
We need a common standard
for communication.
That's where the FHIR comes in.
FHIR standards adoption growth.
The adoption of FHI standards has
been a major turning point for
healthcare interoperability, right?
So what happened in 2017 is
FHI adoption was just 14.8%.
By 2022, that number had jumped
to 58.3%, a nearly a four
full increase in five years.
Wasn't that a great thing?
Yes.
So this search has made extra
data exchange between electronic
health records, telehealth systems,
and mobile applications, far
more consistent and reliable.
FHAR gives healthcare data a
common grammar and structure, so
information flows like language
rather than being locked in silos.
So it's one of the quiet revolutions
behind the scenes that's enabling
everything from smart health apps too.
Cross hospital analytics.
So there are many analytics, right?
So now we will see how our performance
benefits come through, which is nothing
but Kubernetes performance benefits.
Let's talk performance because
healthcare systems cannot afford delays.
So when we move to containerized
Kubernetes native to microservices, we
saw 62% higher transaction throughput
under normal operations, and 47% faster
response times during peak loads.
Those are massive improvements
in environments where
every second counts, right?
So now coming to infrastructure cost
optimization, the cost dropped up two
57%, and deployment times improved by 74%.
Meaning we can scale equally when
demand spikes like during a pandemic.
This efficiency proves that microservices
don't just make systems flexible.
They make them financially
sustainable too.
Now, let's take COVID-19
telehealth transformation.
So the pandemic really put
all of this to the test.
Before 2020, telehealth accounted for
Bailey 1% of all healthcare visits.
Now within months, that
number just jumped to.
35.3%, which is a huge change, right?
So that explosive growth was only
possible because of cloud native,
microservices based architectures.
Healthcare systems that had already
adopted Kubernetes and standardized
APIs were able to scale almost
overnight, onboarding thousands of
virtual consultations without downtime.
This was a defining moment that it showed.
Scalable architecture equals
healthcare resilience.
Now the mobile health
applications impact, right?
So it enhanced medication adherence rates,
better chronic disease, self-management,
and increased patient empowerment.
Data access.
Now rural healthcare success story.
So let's take this idea to
the field rural healthcare.
In one implementation in rural India,
Kubernetes based telehealth platforms
improve specialist access by 58% and
reduced urgent care delays by 43%.
That's transformative, right?
So it means a patient in a remote
village can consult with a cardiologist
hundreds of miles away instantly.
This isn't just about
technology, it's about equity.
It's about bringing healthcare to people.
Who were once beyond reach cloud native
systems are not just improving efficiency,
they're creating fairness in access.
Now, design principles
for resilient systems.
So what can we learn from all of this?
If you're building a modernizing
healthcare systems today, there are
four design principles to remember.
Cloud native architecture,
standards, compliance, scalability,
security and compliance.
Cloud native architecture, build on
ized microservices with Kubernetes
orchestration standards compliance.
Implement FHIR, and other
interoperability standards from the start.
Scalability.
Make sure your system and expand
elastically as demand rose.
Security and compliances throughout
the entire development SI lifecycle.
These principles aren't
just technical check boxes.
They define how resilient, safe,
and equitable our healthcare
systems will be in the future.
Now, next comes the key takeaways.
The key takeaways are mainly first
data integration is critical.
So breaking down silos through
standardized APIs and health information
exchanges delivers measurable
improvements and inpatient outcomes.
Now, the second is
microservices enable scale.
It's nothing but Kubernetes.
Native architectures give healthcare
the performance, agility and cost
efficiency desperately needs.
And the third is equity Through
technology now, native solutions
can bridge healthcare systems.
Access gaps between and bring
world-class care to deserved communities.
The future of healthcare won't be just
about data, it'll be about integration
of data across every system and
every patient anywhere in the world.
So thank you so much for
your time and attention.
Hope this session is helpful for all of
you, and I'm happy to take any questions.
Thank you.