Hi, I am Maia Pshi.
I am from Manipal University
India, currently working at Meta
Platforms, and I'm happy to be
speaking at count 42 Co native 2025.
I have a lot of experience on ai and
we have developed some very interesting
AI tools here at Meta, but this is my
own research on building resilient ai.
Something which most of us may not
think about is about an enterprise
for, about a framework for
enterprise security and governance.
So we are transforming AI security
and governance from a compliance
burden to strategic advantage.
So let's look about it.
So the first one is the AI
transformation challenge.
Artificial intelligence
isn't just changing.
Business is basically fundamentally
redefining enterprise operations.
This is from streamlining automated
decision making to supercharging,
predictive and analytics.
AI systems are now critical
engines driving productivity and
innovation across every industry.
So we all know this, but what are some
of the security risks related to ai?
Let's talk about that.
In a bit detail now.
So what are different areas?
What I've found is the critical AI
security risk, so this can be classified
into data leakage, model manipulation.
Compliance features, bias and fairness.
So wherever there comes ai, we
know that there could be a data
leakage issue, which is unauthorized
exposure of sensitive data, which
is PII, trade secrets we know about.
We know all about the different
unauthorized exposure to the PII data.
Now, the next one is the
model manipulation, right?
It's a malicious alteration
of the AI behavior.
Because it's in the hands of
who is developing it, how it is
being developed, and what are the
different sources to which it has
some access to compliance failures.
Of course someone is developing ai.
It doesn't mean that they have done
all the compliance checks on this,
and of course the last one, but
not the least, is the bias and the
fairness, which we all know about.
There could be bias in the ai.
Now talking about the innovation risk gap,
okay, so let's talk about the traditional
security frameworks are proving like
critically inadequate for dynamic and
complex landscape of the AI systems.
And the laing disconnect is, generates
the significant vulnerabilities for this.
Next we are going to talk
about the framework foundation.
Which consists of four core pillars.
The first one is the governance
structures, which is establishing
robust governance frameworks with clear
roles and responsibilities to ensure
accountable oversight and strategic
decision making for AI systems.
The next one is the technical
safeguard, which is like deploying.
Advanced technical safeguards
including cutting edge encryption
and granular access controls to
fortify AI environments against
evolving threats and data breaches.
Compliance alignment is the next
one, the operations seemingly with
the global regulatory compliance
and proactively doing it.
And the next one is continuous monitoring.
Without continuous and dynamic monitoring.
That is also one of the, one of the core
pillar of the framework of the foundation.
Moving on the comprehensive AI governance
framework, so AI governance code,
which is comprising senior executives
and cross-functional leadership.
This board bold spearheads
the strategic direction.
Gratifies critical policies and
optimizes resource deployment
for all AI initiatives.
That's the board which is primarily
responsible for it, AI ethics committee.
Now, this becomes very important when
there are like cross-functional teams and
there are legal counsels, which who needs
to be involved in the AI development.
Because when you are developing
something, the ethics has to be
kept in mind and there has to be
finally a review panel, right?
So review panel consists of
like expert engineers, security
specialists, compliance officers, and
the panel forms rigorous technical
evaluation of the AI systems.
The engineers may not be equipped
enough for all of these, so that's
why there needs to be all of these.
Framework.
Let's look at the fortifying.
AI excellence, strategic
identity and access management.
This is how do you get access?
How?
How does everyone get access to this?
And who are the people
who gets access to it?
And this is like implementing a
robust and multifactor authentication.
We all know it to secure the
critical AI systems access.
Defining and enforcing granular rule-based
access meticulously tailored to dynamic
AI development and deployment functions.
Now, streamlining the operations
is the next big thing.
Dynamic access policies.
We talked about that and the
traditional IAM identity and access
management frameworks, which often
fall short of and struggling to address
complex dynamic access platforms.
The focus is.
On development of the AI and nobody
thinks about identity and access
management, and this point of mine is
fortifying all of these for AI excellence.
Next is something which is real
timely detection and how do we do it?
Is data ingestion like it consists
of this, all of these things,
data ingestion, then response,
coordination, pattern analysis.
Alert generation.
So data ingestion is seamless
real time ingestion and continuous
monitoring of the critical AI systems.
And then comes to response
coordination, which is coordinated
incident response and remediation.
And the pattern analysis, sophisticated
machine learning algorithm.
Proactively detecting and pinpointing
subtle deviations and critical anomalies
from established operational baselines.
Alert generation is the last one, but
not the least, which is AMA automated
high priority alert generation for rapid
notification of security incidents,
curricular performance issues, and of
course potential compliance violations.
So this forms the real
time anomaly detection.
Then automated compliance
workflows towards that.
Let's look at it.
So that is like regulatory mapping,
identifying applicable regulations,
G-D-P-R-V-C-F-C-C-P-A, industry
specific requirements and MAP
requirements to AI operation.
The second one is control implementation,
deploying automated controls for
data handling, consent management,
and audit trail generation.
Next is continuous assessment.
We talked about it, which is
compliance checks, C analysis,
and remediation tracking.
And next is the reporting generation.
Automated compliance reports,
regulatory submissions, and
stakeholder communication.
Oh, let's look at monitoring
and explainability tools.
So model performance monitoring comes
under it, which is real time accuracy
and drift detection, performance
degradation alerts, resource
utilization, tracking output quality
assessments, and explainability
features, which is decision pathways
importance analysis and mitigation.
So comprehensive monitoring
bills stakeholder trust by
providing transparency into
AI decision making process.
And ensuring consistent,
reliable performance.
Next is building stakeholder trust.
So you know, here is where the stakeholder
comes into picture and how do we build
that trust with the stakeholder and the
executive Confidence is the first one.
Well-defined.
Governance frameworks and robust
risk management strategies provide
leadership with comprehensive oversight.
And strategic control.
All AI initiatives enabling
informed decision making.
Then there is regulatory readiness,
which is efficient compliance workflows
and through audit trails ensuring
consistent clearance to regulations.
Employee assurance, which is
also important, is transparent.
AI operations and clear ethical
guidelines cultivate a workplace
where employees confidently integrate.
AI augmented processes fostering
innovation and collaboration.
Now let's talk about some of the benefits.
Fortified risk mitigation is one of the
benefits, which is proactive monitoring
and robust controls, which drastically
reduces scale security incidents.
Next is accelerated cost
Efficiency is one of the benefit,
which is automation slashes.
Manual compliance efforts and ex
expedites incident resolution.
And the next one is enhanced
stakeholder trust, which is transparent
and accountable governance, which
cultivates unwavering confidence
from regulators strengthens customer
loyalty and empowers internal teams
fostering widespread adoption support.
Expedited AI deployment, integrated
security controls and streamlined
approval pathways, which accelerate
the launch of new AI initiative.
You don't have to go back every
time and do this all over again,
every time when you're doing it.
This is like once, once it is established
and all the things are in place that
we have expedited AI deployment.
And then there is strategic
competitive advantage.
Of course, there's a lot of competition
in the industry and implementing
some advanced framework like this
is basically redefining AI security
and governance, transforming it
from a more compliance burden into
a powerful strategic differentiator.
And this framework is engineer engineered
to fuel sustainable innovation,
providing crystal clear guidance
for the responsible AI development.
Organizations can now boldly
pursue ambitious AI initiatives.
Assured that comprehensive safeguards
are firmly in place and with
this strategic approach, the AI.
This positions the AI security and
governance as a potent enabler of
innovation and not em impediments.
It's basically in the right direction,
the positive direction for this now
future proofing your AI innovation.
It's elevating your AI security
and governance from a challenge to
a distinct competitive advantage.
And this consists of three points here.
How it does it, future proof is
strategically assess AI readiness,
activate the core component, core
framework component, and cultivating
unwavering stakeholder trust.
We all talked about this in detail,
but these are, this is future
proofing your AI innovation.
Alright, so that's the
end of my presentation.
And thank you very much.