Hello, good morning.
I am de Kana a senior data engineer
with experience in cloud native
infrastructure and data platforms.
My motivation for this research
came from seeing firsthand how cloud
workloads are growing more dynamic
and complex, especially in large scale
environments like retail and e-commerce.
I have worked on projects where
traditional Kubernetes resource management
simply couldn't keep up with unpredictable
traffic and changing business needs.
This inspired me to look for
smarter and AI driven solutions.
Let me share a quick story.
In one of our retail systems, we
experienced a certain spike in
online traffic during a flash sale.
Our Kubernetes cluster was
set up with Static Horizon and
report auto scheduler thresholds.
The static policies
couldn't react fast enough.
Some services were well provisioned
based in cloud resources, while
others were under provision
causing slowdowns and even outages.
Manual intervention was needed to
adjust configurations, which isn't
capable, scalable, or reliable
in fast moving environments.
This is highlighted the limitations
of static resource management.
Today I'll show you how deep
reinforcement learning can help
Kubernetes clusters learn and
adapt in real time, making smarter
decisions about resource allocation.
We'll see how AI can recognize patterns
in workload behavior, optimize for
cost and performance, and reduce the
need for manual tuning, et cetera.
By the end of this talk, you'll
understand how intelligent automation
can futureproof your cloud infrastructure
and unlock new efficiencies.
Let's proceed today.
I outlined my presentation in such a way
that to take you on a journey where we'll
start by understanding the core challenges
in Kubernetes resource management.
Then move to why deep reinforcement
learning is promising solution.
Next, I'll share a research
foundations and specific optimization
areas we targeted, followed by
look at the RL algorithms we
used and how we implement them.
We'll discuss the unique challenges
of multi cluster environments,
the C-N-F-C-F tools to support
our approach and how we validated
our results through benchmarking.
Finally, I will cover production
deployment considerations and
outline practical next steps
so you can see how these ideas
translate into real world impact.
While we dive into some
technical details like algorithms
and integration strategies.
I'll make sure to make you
better understanding on that.
Whether you are a data scientist, DevOps
engineer, or a cloud architect, you'll
live with both a deeper understanding of
the technology and concrete ideas where
you can apply in your own environments.
Let's discuss about the challenges.
Let's imagine a scenario.
Your company launches a new
product and suddenly thousands
of user floods your website.
The Kubernetes cluster configured
with static resource limits
can't scale up fast enough.
Some services crash due to lack
of resources while others are
running with excess capacity
leading to wasted cloud spend.
This is inges a theoretical problem.
It's something many organizations
face during peak events, sale
or unexpected viral moments.
When these pipes happen, DevOps team are
forced to jump in and manually adjust
configurations often late at night
and during critical business hours.
This firefighting takes time away
from innovation and strategic work
and increases the risk of human error.
Manual tuning is not only
stressful, but also unsustainable.
As system grow more complex and
workloads become unpredictable.
These challenges are widespread,
and they're exactly what we
are aiming to solve with this
intelligent and adaptive solutions.
Now, why deep reinforcement
learning traditional orders curling
in Kubernetes relies on fixed
thresholds and reactive policies?
When a metric crosses a certain
timeline, the system responds, but
it doesn't anticipate or leave from
past, learn from past behavior.
In contrast, deep reinforcement
learning enables Kubernetes to
continuously learn from its environment.
Our agents observe the pattern,
predict future needs, and
proactively adjust resources.
They shift from reactive to adaptive
management, means cluster can handle
unpredictable workloads more efficiently
with less manual intervention.
RL algorithms excel at uncovering
complex relationships in data.
Patterns that are often too subtle are
multidimensional for humans to spot.
For example, a L can detect
cyclical traffic spikes, seasonal
trends, or correlations between
different microservices that
static rules would overlook.
By learning from historical data and
realtime feedback, AL can optimize
resource allocations in a ways that
manual tuning simply can't achieve it.
Reinforcement learning has already
revolutionized fields like robotics,
where agents learn to navigate
complex environments and gaming.
Where AI has mastered games like Go
and StarCraft, these successes show
RLS power to solve dynamic, high
dimensional problems just like those
we face in cloud infrastructure.
By bringing R to Kubernetes, we
are leveraging proven AI techniques
to make our clusters smart.
More resilient and more cost effective.
Now, let's discuss on
some research foundations.
Our approach was inspired by several
pioneering studies in the field
of cloud resource optimization
using reinforcement learning.
For example, research from leading
universities and tech companies has
shown RL can outperform traditional
auto scaling in dynamic environments.
Benchmarks from these studies
demonstrated significant improvements
in CP utilization and response times,
which motivated us to explore RL
for Kubernetes workload management.
We also looked at open source RL
frameworks and their application
in real world cloud scenarios
to guide our methodology.
One of the most powerful
aspects of RL is its ability to
continuously learn and adapt.
Unlike static policies, RL agents evolve
as workloads and infrastructure change.
This means your Kubernetes
cluster can stay optimized even
as new applications are deployed.
Traffic patterns shipped
or hardware is upgraded.
Continuous learning helps future proof
your infrastructure and reducing the need
for frequent manual reconfiguration and
keeping your systems resilient to change.
During our experiments, we found that
RL driven clusters not only improve.
Resource utilization, but also reduce the
number of scaling events, making resource
management more stable and predictable.
One.
A surprising result was the ability
of RL agents to anticipate traffic
surges before they happened.
Thanks to the pattern recognition
in from historical data.
In literature, there are cases where
RL reduced cloud costs by up to 40%
compared to traditional autoscaling
highlighting the real world impact
of intelligent optimization.
So what are the core optimization areas?
Let's break down the core
optimization areas where machine
learning can make a real impact.
First POD scheduling.
For example, ML can predict which
notes will have the right resource
available and place pods accordingly.
Reducing bottlenecks and improving
performance resource allocation.
Instead of fixed to CPU and memory
assignments, ML models can dynamically
adjust resource based on predicted
demand preventing both W and under
provisioning traffic routing.
In a service, mesh Amil can optimize
routing decisions in real time,
sending requests to the healthiest
or most cost effective endpoints.
Multi cluster orchestration, Amil
can help distribute workloads across
clusters in different regions or clouds,
balancing load, and minimizing late
density by automating complex decisions.
ML driven optimization reduces the need
for manual tuning and constant oversight.
This means DevOps team can focus
on strategic tasks rather than
fire fright, resource issues.
Efficiency improves because
resources are allocated precisely
when and where they are needed.
Minimizing, wasted and maximizing
performance, real-time feedback is
crucial for effective optimization.
ML models rely on continuous
monitoring of cluster metrics
and application performance.
This feedback loop allows the system to
quickly adapt to changing conditions such
as traffic spikes or hardware failures.
Ultimately, realtime feedback ensures that
optimization decision remain in relevant
and effective even as workloads evolve.
Let's see how deep Q networks
for containers orchestration.
DQ networks or dqn are particularly
effective for problems where decisions are
discreet, such as choosing which node to
place a PO or selecting a resource tire.
In Kubernetes, many resource
management actions are not
continuous, but involve clear choice.
DQN can evaluate the current state
of the cluster and select the best
action from a set of possibilities.
This makes DQNA natural fit
for orchestration, container
placement, and scaling decisions
in a dynamic environment.
One of the biggest challenges in
applying DQN to Kubernetes was
designing a reward function that
truly reflects the business goals.
For example, we had to balance
performance, cost, and reliability.
If the reward only focused on
CP utilization, it might ignore
response time and efficiency.
Cost efficiency.
We experimented with multi object to
reward functions and found that waiting
different metrics appropriately was key
to achieve the decide outcome experience.
Relay is a technique, sorry.
Experience replay is a technique where
the RL agent stores past experiences and
samples then randomly during training.
This helps break the correlation
between co experiences making
learning more stable and robust.
Especially in dynamic environments
like Kubernetes, where
conditions can change rapidly.
By revisiting a diverse set of
scenarios, the agent learns more
generalizable policies and avoids
over fitting to the recent events.
Proximal policy optimization in
action PPO, it is also known for its
stability during training, which is
crucial when making continuous resource
allocation decisions in Kubernetes.
Unlike algorithms that can make
abrupt changes, PPO uses a clip
objective function to ensure updates
to the policy are gradual and safe.
This stability means resource adjustments
like CPU and memory allocation are smooth
and predictable, reducing the risk of
performance spikes or resource starvation.
It enables regular benchmarking
and AB testing to ensure the RL
agents decisions are actually
improving the cluster perform.
We track key metrics such as
application response time, resource
utilization, and cost efficiency
before and after policy changes.
Regular benchmarking and AB testing
help us validate that the agent is
learning effectively and not just
over fitting to the recent data.
Safe exploration is critical in production
environments and our agent must try
new actions to learn, but reckless
experimentation can disrupt services.
We use techniques like reward, shaping,
circuit breakers and canary DI deployments
to limit the impact of risky decisions.
This ensures that learning
continues without compromising
reliability or user experience.
Soft factor critic for multi
objective optimization.
SAC is a state of art, deep reinforcement
learning algorithm designed for
environments where actions are continuous.
It is especially valued for its ability
to balance exploration and exploitation,
making it highly effective for complex
real world optimization problems like
Bernet, workload management, entropy,
regularization ease, A technique used in
SAC to encourage the RL agent to explore
a wider range of actions rather than
settling too quickly on a single strategy.
In cloud environments, workloads
and resource demands can change
rapidly and unpredictability.
Exploration helps the agent discover
new, potentially better resource
allocation strategies that static
or overlay conservative approaches
might miss by maintaining a balance
between exploitation and exploration.
SAC ensures the system remains
adapt, adaptable, and can
respond to novel situations.
One of S's strength is its ability to
handle multiple objectives simultaneously.
In Kubernetes, we often need to
optimize for cost, performance,
and reliability All at once.
SSE allows us to define a reward function
that incorporates these different goals.
So the agent learns to make decisions
that doesn't, that don't just maximize
one metric at the expense of others.
This holistic approach leads to smarter
resource management, where clusters
run efficiently, applications stay
responsive and cause TER control.
In our experiments, we found that
SAC was particularly effective in
scenarios with highly variable workloads
and complex resource requirements.
For example, during a multi-service
deployment with fluctuating traffic,
SAC consistently achieved lower response
times and better cost efficiency.
Compared to DQN and PPO, its ability to
adapt to continuous change and optimize.
Across multiple objectives made
it the best choice for our most
demanding cloud native applications.
Integration with Kubernetes
controllers integration.
Integrating reinforcement
learning models with Kubernetes.
Controllers present several challenges.
One major issue is latency.
RL agents needs timely data to make
decisions, but delays in metric collection
or a PA calls can impact performance.
API Compatibility is another hurdle.
Kubernetes APIs evolve and custom
controllers must stay up to date to
ensure smooth communication between
the RL agent and the cluster.
We also had to consider security
and access controls, making sure RL
agents only perform safe authorized
actions within the cluster Custom
Controllers act as translators
between the RL models and Kubernetes.
They colored cluster metrics, feed them
to RL agent, and then convert the agent's
recommended actions into Kubernetes.
API calls this architecture allows
us to leverage the intelligence of
RL while maintaining compatibility
with existing Kubernetes workflows.
Controllers also handle error
shaking and rollback procedures,
ensuring that any action taken by
the RL agent is safe and reversible.
Monitoring oral driven actions is
critical for both safety and transparency.
We learned that deep integration with
existing observability tools like
promises and Grafana helps track the
impact of oral decisions in real time.
Debugging.
Oral agents can be tricky, especially
when decisions seem counter initiative.
We found that logging details, state
information and reward calculations
were essential for diagnosing issues.
Regular audits.
And automated alerts for unusual
behavior helped us catch problems
early and maintain trust in the system.
Let's discuss about some multi
cluster environment challenges.
Synchronizing state across
multiple Kubernetes clusters
is a complex challenge.
Each cluster may be running in a
different region or different hardware,
or even in different cloud providers.
Ensuring that all clusters have
a consistent view of workloads,
resource usage, and policies request.
Robust coordination mechanisms.
We found that network partitions, version
mismatches and a synchronous updates
can easily lead to inconsistencies.
Making reliable
synchronization a top priority.
Latency is a critical factor
in multi cluster environments.
Decision about workload placement or
scaling must account for the time it
takes to communicate between the clusters.
High latency can delay resource
adjustments leading to suboptimal
performance are even service disruptions.
Our approach includes latency
awareness, algorithms that factor in
network delays, helping ensure timely
and effective resource management
across distributed clusters.
Federated learning offers a
promising solution for scaling
reinforcement learning across clusters.
Instead of sharing raw data, each
cluster train its own oral agent
locally and only shares model updates.
This approach preserves data
privacy and security as sensitive
information never leaves the cluster.
Federated learning also enables
collaborative optimization, allowing
clusters to benefit from shared
insights while maintaining autonomy
and compliance with data regulations.
So implementation of
framework with CNCF tools.
CNCF tools.
CLOUDNATIVE Computing Foundation
tools are open source projects and
technologies hosted by Cloud Native
Compute Foundation, designed to
support cloud native infrastructure,
application development, and operations.
These tools help organizations build,
deploy, and manage scalable, resilient,
and observable cloud native systems.
I have listed below some
common CNFC tools promises.
It is essential for RL training
because it provides a comprehensive
and real time view of cluster
metrics, CPU memory network uses,
and customer application metrics.
These rich data streams allow
the RL agents to make informed
decisions and continuously learn
from the actual state of cluster.
Without accurate and granular metrics,
RL models will be flying blind, unable
to adapt to changing workloads or
optimize resource allocation effectively.
Istio as a service mesh gives us
fine grain control over traffic
routing between microservices.
By integrating RL with TO, we can
dynamically adjust routing policies
based on real-time performance feedback.
Sending requests to the healthiest
endpoints are balancing load
to optimize latency and cost.
This level of automation helps maintain
high availability and responsiveness even
as traffic patterns shift unexpectedly.
Helm, it simplifies and
standardizes the deployment of RL
optimized workloads by packaging
configurations into reusable charts.
This reduces manual errors,
speeds up rollouts, and ensures
consistency across environments.
Whether you are deploying to a
single cluster or multiple region.
With Herm updates and rollbacks are
straightforward, making it easier to
manage complex deployments and maintain
reliability as you iterate on oral models.
Let's talk about the performance
benchmarking strategy.
Benchmarking is essential to
objectively measure the impact
of R driven optimization.
By comparing cluster performance
before and after oral deployment,
we can quantify improvements and
identify areas for further tuning.
It is important to establish a baseline
using traditional auto-scaling methods
so we have a clear reference point
for evaluating our ALS effectiveness.
Consistent benchmarking also helps
ensure that changes are beneficial
and don't introduce new issues.
In our RL optimist clusters achieved a
30% reduction in application response
time compared to static auto scaling.
We also observed higher CP utilization
and fewer unnecessary scaling evens.
Which translated into better resource
efficiency and lower cloud costs.
These concrete results demonstrate
the real world value of
intelligent workload optimization.
Benchmarking isn't just about numbers.
It's about building trust.
Stakeholders need to see clear,
repeatable evidence that RL
automation is safe and effective.
Transparent reporting of performance
metrics, REASSURES teams that the
system is making smart decisions
and not compromising reliability.
Regular benchmarking and
sharing results with the team.
Foster confidence in adopting R driven
solutions for critical workloads.
Now let's consider some production
deployment con considerations
as we move from research and
benchmarking to real world deployment.
Safety and reliability become paramount.
First, we implement safety mechanisms
like circuit breakers, where these
prevent RL agents from making
destructive or risky decisions
during training or model updates.
If the agent starts to behave
unexpectedly, the circuit breaker
Hals its actions protecting
the cluster from instability.
Next, we use a gradual rollout strategy.
Instead of deploying new RL policies
cluster where we start with Canary,
Dell deployments rolling out changes
to a small subset of workloads.
If performance degrades, automated
rollback mechanisms quickly revert
to the previous stable policy.
Minimizing risk model
versioning is also critical.
We maintain a comprehensive versioning
and AB testing framework allows
us to compare the performance of
different RL models side by side.
This ensures that only the best performing
models are promoted to production.
Finally, observability
integration is essential.
We deeply integrate with existing
monitoring tasks such as promises and
Grafana to audit RL agent decisions
and model performance in real time.
This transparency built trust and allows
for rapid troubleshooting if issue arises.
In summary, by combining safety
mechanisms, gradual rollout, robust
versioning, and strong observability.
We ensure that RL driven optimization
is not only effective, but also
safe and reliable for production,
kubernetes and environments.
Next steps.
What are the next steps for
implementing RL Optimiz?
Optimiz Kubernetes?
When adopting RL driven optimization,
it's wise to begin with pilot projects
targeting noncritical workloads,
and this approach allows you to
validate the benefits and iron
out any issues before scaling up.
Pilot project help teams gain hand-on
experience with AL tools and workflows,
building confidence in the technology.
By starting small, you minimize risk
and ensure that any expect unexpected
challenges can be addressed without
impacting core business operations.
Before deploying AL solutions, it's
crucial to establish baseline metrics
for your current system, such as resource
utilization, response times, and cost.
These baselines provides a reference point
for measuring improvements and help you
set realistic goals for RL optimization.
Tracking metrics before and
after implementation, ensure that
changes are data driven, and that
you can clearly demonstrate the
value of RL two stakeholders.
The Kubernetes and RL communicates
are vibrant and collaborative.
Sharing your learnings, challenges and
successes can accelerate progress for
everyone contributing to open source
a frameworks or Kubernetes tools.
Not only help others, but also
brings valuable feedback and
innovation to your own projects.
Community collaboration
fosters best practices.
Drives new features and helps
build a more robust ecosystem for
intelligent workload optimization.
So what are the key takeaways
from this to wrap up?
RL Optimist Kubernetes
delivers three major benefits.
Efficiency resources are used
more effectively, reducing
waste and lowering costs.
The second one is adaptability.
The system learns and responds
to changing workloads, keeping
applications running smoothly, even
during unexpected spikes or dips.
Third, it's a future proofing rls.
Continuous learning means your
infrastructure can evolve with your
business needs, new technologies,
and shifting user demands.
So successful adoption.
Adoption of RL in Kubernetes
isn't a one step process.
It's best approached in phases, starting
with pilot projects, establishing
baseline metrics, and gradually
expanding to production workloads.
This phased strategy helps manage
risk, build team expertise, and
ensure that each step delivers
measurable value before scaling up.
Ultimately, our optimist, Kubernetes
is more than just a technical upgrade.
It's a strategic advantage.
It empowers organization to be more
agile, resilient, and cost effective in
a rapidly changing digital landscape.
By embracing intelligent
automation, you position your
infrastructure and your business for
long-term success and innovation.
With this, I conclude my presentation.
Thank you.