Hi everyone.
First of all, thank you all for joining
the conf42 Kube Native 2024 conference,
and a big thanks to Mark Bakowski for
hosting this event and accepting my talk.
My name is Alexander Tronick.
I work as a customer solutions engineer
at Systdig, and in today's session,
I'm going to show you how we can use
Open Source project file Sidekick to
detect threats in Kubernetes workloads.
I'll provide some initial context
using slides, after which we'll
jump into the lab environment.
A little bit about me.
I have a technical background in
telecommunications, and I've been working
for 10 years in various engineering roles.
At the time when I completed my electrical
engineering master's degree, cloud
computing and container technology
weren't covered by any of the programs,
and I totally side quested into these
fields as a hobby by following along
content creators such as NetworkChalk.
and doing the training on platforms
such as RangeForce and TriHackMe.
I'd say a major lesson here would
be to never stop learning, invest in
yourself, and find an ethical hobby with
a great return on investment potential.
From this slide, you can conclude
how I enjoy spending some of my time,
and where you can find me online.
From making YouTube walkthroughs, blog
writing, participating in AWS Community
Builder and Cisco Insider Champion
Communities, and staying current
with cloud and Kubernetes security.
Right now, I'm going after
success coachings, customer
success manager certification,
so it's never a dull moment.
And if any of these I've mentioned
so far sparked your interest,
connect with me on LinkedIn and
we can continue the conversation.
Speaking on ROI, cloud and Kubernetes
are currently known as fields with great
opportunities that connect you with
the most amazing people and pay well.
Cloud and Kubernetes go great hand in
hand, from creating highly available
and resilient services, working on
internal developer platforms, to
innovating with large language models.
You will frequently find that applications
served on public cloud are behind
the scenes built using Kubernetes.
So in this day, age, and economy, that's
something you can expect to see and hear.
Cloud and Kubernetes skills wanted
across software and security
engineering, sales, and customer success.
Related to my badges from the
previous slide, here I highlighted
open job roles from these vendors,
including my employer, Sysdig.
So this is something for motivation to
start looking into Kubernetes and cloud.
because the times are hybrid and
it's not very realistic to center
your technical skill set solely
around services that work on premise.
So let's say that any service that
has to be developed and offered to a
wide audience should be secured too.
In cloud security, there is this concept
of cloud native application protection
platforms, CNAP solutions, capable of
securing infrastructure and applications,
whether based on full blown virtual
machines or microservices, from the
moment of their local development,
while still being available only in
manifest files, to their runtime.
where you can actually
access an application serving
a certain web page live.
Not all malicious actors will rely on
common vulnerabilities and exposures,
CVs for short, to cause damage and gain
unauthorized access to our offering.
Some might try to leverage identities
not being configured according
to the least privileged practice.
And, Compliance failures.
When we rely on reports as snapshots
in time to prove our offering's
adherence to industry's best
practices and relevant benchmarks.
And then, there could
be insider threats too.
Using a job relevant analogy, It's like
a candidate who looks good on paper,
interviews well, and gets inside a
company, but has a malicious intent.
So this is where threat detection
is of utmost importance.
Speaking from my personal experience
working with Sysdig Secure CNAP, its
threat detection engine is based on
an open source Falco project capable
of detecting early indicators of an
attack in containerized environments,
such as using reconnaissance
scripts or other open source tools.
malicious actions across MITRE ATT&
CK framework as obfuscation, privilege
escalation, log deletion, downloading
binaries to containers, exfiltration
attempts, shell history deletion,
bulk renaming and recreating data.
files extensions, and other actions
connected with ransomware campaigns.
A bit on Falco.
Falco is, as of this year, a CNCF
graduated project, meaning it's
considered stable and it's used
successfully in production environments.
Not going deep into architecture weeds
right now, for this session just know
that Falco hooks into the Linux kernel
via a driver, either a kernel module or an
eBPF probe, and can collect system calls.
All these events are parsed from
kernel space to user space, where
Falco rules, which are essentially
filters of your interest, are
applied, and the final outputs can
be delivered to certain locations.
Falco can associate each kernel event
with the exact container attribute, like
container ID, name, image repository,
tags, as well as Kubernetes attributes,
such as namespace or pod name.
And on the right side, there is an
example of a microservice build.
based architecture, leveraging
Falco to understand what is causing
anomalies within a Kubernetes cluster.
So when speaking innovation, container
runtime insights are important to consider
because traditional security tooling
for event management wasn't built with
potential malicious Kubernetes events
and short lived container logs in mind.
Falco is usually associated with a command
line, but there is this public page,
as seen on the left and middle part of
the slide, where you can conveniently
browse through existing Falco rules in
detail, including rules description,
condition when the rule will be
triggered, output content, and rule tags.
On the right, SysTick's 2024 Cloud
Native Security and Usage Report
lists top triggered detections.
In any environment, Where containerized
workloads are being experimented with
locally or served publicly, there
should be tooling in place to detect and
potentially safeguard from such actions.
Falco natively provides just a handful
of destination for its outputs.
And this is where Falco Sidekick
open source project comes in handy.
It can fan out Falco's output to over
60 destinations across web, Falco.
chat ops, logging, streaming,
alerting, and observability platforms.
As for the web output for Falco Sidekiq,
there is Falco Sidekiq UI, a user
friendly way to track Falco events
across triggered rules, event severities,
tags of interest, and comes with
Swagger documentation for API queries.
So that would be the core of our Thread
Detection hands on lab for today.
The link here and QR code will send
you to a Google Drive to download the
virtual machine pre installed with
all the tools for today's session.
Let's say the last few words on the
lab environment and then start the VM.
VM's operating system is Kali Purple.
A community project focused on defensive
tooling structured around the NIST
cybersecurity framework to identify,
protect, detect, respond, and recover.
The project aims to become the
most comprehensive security
operations center in a box.
kind of solution.
On top of Kali Purple, first
installed are several tools to easily
manage local Kubernetes cluster.
And in the cluster, Kubernetes Goat as an
interactive learning platform with real
world Kubernetes misconfigurations is
spun up and we will leverage one of its
scenarios for falco sidekick detection.
kube nomicon Was created to document
offensive and defensive Kubernetes
techniques inspired by Microsoft's
Kubernetes threat matrix, which provides
a framework for understanding Kubernetes
tactics in a MITRE ATT& CK style.
While the Microsoft Threat Matrix focuses
on educating around Kubernetes tactics,
techniques, and procedures through
definitions, KubeNomicon expands on it
by aiming to offer practical commands
for both exploiting and defending against
attacks in Kubernetes environments.
For example, some of the tools that
can be used to enumerate a Kubernetes
environment are nmap and metasploit.
We will also use Atomic Red Team
containerized project to simulate real
world attacks aligned with MITRE ADT and
CK framework in a Kubernetes environment.
These Atomics tests are in general
immensely helpful to refine and enhance
coverage by addressing any detection gaps.
As we trigger Atomics test, we
will monitor Falco Sidekick UI
for real time thread detection.
Now, let's switch to the VM.
As a next logical step moving forward
from today's session, I suggest
looking into recently officially
published Falco Talon project, a
response engine for Falco detected
threats in Kubernetes environments.
Just to name a few actions that can be
automated using Falco Talon, invoking
an AWS Lambda function on a triggered
Falco rule, then enforcing a Kubernetes
network policy, and labeling a pod
as suspicious or terminating it.
I hope you enjoyed today's session.
And that Mark will accept my
future COM 42 applications.
Linked on this slide, you can
find Falco training that should
enable you to start contributing
to Falco and create your own rules.
If you find today's topic interesting,
join the Falco Slack community and let's
stay in touch until the next session.
Bye for now.