Hi.
Hi hi.
Good morning everyone.
My name is currently I'm working
as a tech lead at fifth Third Bank.
Based on my experience today, I'm going to
talk about the architecting, secure, and
scalable integration for transfer FinTech.
Based on my experience, I'm going
to talk it, I have around 17 years
experience as a Java backend developer
with the cloud and various database.
So in, in this today agenda is the FinTech
integration challenge, current integration
landscape security compliance framework.
Advanced data protection, scalability,
architecture patterns, balancing
act, security complaints, performance
implementation roadmap, and key takeaways.
So basically in the FinTech
integration challenge, understanding
the unique demands and evolving
requirements for integration.
For example, while developing
microservice development, communication
between two microservices, sometimes
the communication is a synchronous
or a synchronous communication.
It is a big challenge and the current
integration landscape, exploring
the existing ecosystem, key trends
and modern FinTech, for example the
legacy application was developed
in any other technologies, but the
modern applications were using.
Developing latest technologies and
also deploying to cloud is also one
of the integration challenge security
complaints frameworks, implementing
robust identity access control, AP
security images, and advanced data
protection statuses for encryption,
tokenization, data masking to safeguard
system information, for example while
while trans while doing transforming, any
payment transaction, for example, we want
to mask, we don't, we want to encrypt
the account numbers, send that account
number and receive your account number.
So in that case, we can, we are
going to implement encryption,
tokenization and masking the data in
the while printing logs in the server.
And scalability architecture patterns.
Designing the high ment systems
with synchronous processing service
misses, event driven approaches.
Example, if you wanna increase
the scalability based on
the application, we have to.
Increase the scalable the
component size will be increased.
Then only we can balancing act security
complaints, performance achieving
optimal integration solutions that
meet all integration challenge.
Provide co to multi-agency support
for diverse financial products.
Ensure data integrity, consistency.
Across distributor system seamlessly
integrate legacy core banking system with
modern microservices architectures process
high volume financial transactions.
With the robust security measures
dynamically scaled to efficiency,
manage peak transaction volumes,
facilitate rapid innovation and
feature delivery while getting risk
guarantee complaints with dynamic
regulatory frameworks, for example.
PSG two G-D-P-R-C-C-P current
integration landscape.
Traditional challenges, modern
requirements, the imperative for
robust integration platforms in
the traditional challenges, high
operation costs, drain budgets for
innovation, 0.2 point integration
hinder maintenance and scalability.
Monolithic middle layer slows
developments and market response.
Outdated perimeter security
leaves internal services while.
In modern requirements, zero.
Trust, security,
authenticates and authors.
Every request embedded complaints
supports dynamic regulators actions with
automated ing real time fraud detection
integrates a ML for immediate response.
Elastic scaling leverages
clouding autoscaling for volume.
A PA first approach enables seamless
third party and open banking integration.
The imperative for the robust
integration platform, a robust FinTech
integration platform must enforce
security monitor confluence and optimize
it needs to protect data, ensure
regulatory adherence, and maintain
low latency for critical transactions,
all while fostering innovation.
Distributed identity
access control 2.0 open.
Id connect JWT JS and implementation
considerations while while using WA
2.0 and authorization frameworks,
grants third party applications.
Limited access to services without.
User cred by using Springboard.
I implemented WA two Pan zero Open
iConnect and authentication layer
built on WA two zero enabling client
to verify user identity through
essential profile information.
JW Jason, A compact, self-contained middle
first security, transforming information
in between parties as Jason object.
Implementation considerations are establ.
Key rotation schedules and secure
key management practices and
optimizing broken lifetime for balance
between security and usability.
Implementing scope
based authorization for.
Granular access control, ensuring
a financial grade a PA complaints
for enhancer protection, integrating
multifactor authentication.
These frameworks facilitate a zero
trust model ensuring every service
to service call is authenticated and
authorized, irrespective of network.
Applic.
A PA gateway Security controls, essential
security functions rate limiting secure
breakers, request validation, web
application firewall authentication.
Authorization enforcement, TLS
termination gate limiting control
request is to prevent dust attacks,
ensure fair resource distribution and
protecting services from overload.
For example, while implementing rest,
we can implement this rate limit.
Secure breaker prevents cascading failures
by quickly failing request to unhealthy
services, maintaining system stability
during high load request validation.
For example, in the restful services.
While sending payload, we have to
validate the request violation,
which are which fields are mandated,
fields, which will list our
option values in the re violation.
We can implement those
validation for all the fields.
So validated to block mal form
request and injection attacks.
Ation secure communication and offloads
encryption, centralizing certificate
management, and optimizing performance
authentication authorization,
validates identity tokens and
applies granular access policies.
Ensuring only authorized access to
APAs by using this only authorized.
Third parties only can access
our services by using this
authentication authorization, even
if it is a internal application.
Also, we can implement authentication
authorization web application firewall
integration provides defense against
common vulnerabilities, OWS AP by
detecting and blocking threats.
So by using a web application firewall,
we can project the application
if we can secure the end plan.
So data production methods, data
production, we can I implement by
using encryption tokenization, data
masking encryption, utilizes AEs 2 5
6 for data rest with HSM backend key
enablement, TLS 1.3 for data transit.
Implement forward secrecy
to protect data with.
Non tokens that retain operational
utility without inherent value.
This is crucial for handling
primary account numbers.
For example, we can organize SSN account
numbers, user id, those things we can,
by using tokenization we can implement
data masking, employee dynamic masking
for non-production environments.
Enabling realistic testing
with anonymized data.
Applied techniques like format,
preserves, encryption, red
reduction for the highly fields.
So in this access control, for
example, code data production,
encryption to tokenization and data
masking, pro protective perimeter
network security monitoring and TLS.
Asynchronous processing architecture.
In the asynchronous flow, we can implement
a P gateway, mobile pay, mobile Q energy
violation, service analytics engine,
and transfer and notification service.
So in the the benefits for financial
transaction for asynchronous
decouples transaction, ancy from.
Processing.
Improving responsiveness
enables batch processing for
efficiency when appropriate.
Facilities, retries and ator cues for
resilience allows back present mechanisms
to handle drop traffic spikes supports
com compensation transactions for all.
Failure scenarios, implementation.
Note financial transactions require
guaranteed delivery and exactly
once processing, choose message
brokers with a strong durability,
guarantees and item consumers.
Service Miss architecture.
So by you in the service Miss, we can see
observability security, traffic management
policy informers a service Miss provides
an infrastructure layer for handling
service to service communication offering.
Critical capabilities
for FinTech platforms.
For example, observed offers
comprehensive metrics, logs, and traces
essential for regulatory audit trails
and in-depth performance analysis.
Traffic management enables sophisticated
routing, load balancing, and
fault tolerance without requiring
application level change changes.
Security facilitates.
Mutual DL authentication
and streamline certificate
management at the platform level.
Policy enforcements ensures consistent
access control and rate limiting access.
All services within the mesh,
even driven architecture.
Even driven architectures are ideally
suit for financial transaction
flows where every state change
represents a critical business event.
For example, saga pattern coordinates,
distributed transaction across multiple
services, even sourcing store state
changes as a immutable sequence of events.
QRS separates read for.
Optimizing performance, even
streaming enables real time processing
for immediate fraud detection.
This approach enables highly
responsive systems that can scale
orally while maintaining a complete
audit trail for regulatory complaints.
Balance in security,
compliance and performance.
Striking the right balance among
security complaints and performance
is a paramount for FinTech platforms.
Either chart to demonstrate
a hybrid approach.
Combining event driven
architectures with is service.
Miss offers the most effective strategy
to achieve robust security, comprehensive
complaints, and exceptional performance.
So the balance security, we
have the traditional monolithic
basic microservices, a P gateway
service mesh, event driven mesh.
So the key elements for balance,
proactive complaints, head
security optimization, performance,
observability, and traceability.
Implementation roadmap.
The phase one implement API
gateway with W2 YDC authentication.
Establish secure CACD pipelines
with automated security.
Deploy basic observability stack
metrics, lack traces, and phase
two Security Harding implement
encryption and inion services.
Deploy C Clearance management
solution established.
Key rotation, schedule
and pro saleability.
Introduce message brokers
for a synchronous processing.
Implement service miss for
interservice communication.
Develop after scaling policies based
on demand patterns, advance patterns.
Implement event source for event
sourcing for critical transaction flows.
Deploy CQRS for a highly
volume read operation.
Establish Charles engineering
practices to verify resilience.
Two takeaways.
Adopt a Zero Trust Security Model.
Leverage WA two, YDC, and J for end
security across all integration points.
This requires continuous verification
and least privilege access at
every relay critical for protecting
sensitive financial data, embedded
comprehensive observability into
the platform to ensure operational.
Excellence and streamline
regulatory complaints.
Robust logging metrics and tracing
provide deep insights, enabling quick
in issue resolution, performance
optimization, and complete audit
trail for financial regulations.
Implement layer data protection
with encryption tokenization, and
make masking to safeguard sensitive
financial data, effectively protected
data address in transit and in use
with the robust encryption tokenization
for desensitization and masking.
For secure testing, leverage, event
driven architecture and service, meh.
Highly scalable and secure FinTech
platforms, even driven flood
patterns, enable realtime processing
and auditing wireless service.
MIS provides consistent
traffic management, policy
enforcement, and mutual TLS.
Thank you.