Welcome, everyone.
And thanks for joining us today at
Conf42's kube native 2024 conference.
Today, we'll dive into how CircleCI's
field engineering team uses Kubernetes
and Terraform modules to revolutionize
the way that we present enterprise demos.
We're going to explore some of the
challenges we face, the solutions we built
out, and the impact it's had both on our
team and our customer interactions since.
Firstly, let's introduce ourselves.
My name is Eddie Webinaro.
I am the Senior Director of Field
Engineering here at CircleCI.
We are a global team supporting North
America, EMEA, and the Japan ANZ region.
I'm joined today by Mualanian,
who is a Senior Enterprise
Field Engineer with the team.
He's got a really interesting
background, embedded firmware devices,
deploying software into submarines.
Myself, I spent a career in
software development as well,
but lamer tamer traditional
cloud infrastructure type stuff.
But we're both really excited to be here
today and present this conversation.
What is that conversation?
We're going to do a a brief overview of
what we're talking about today, and I want
to give you a quick demo of the product.
Then we're going to dive deep into,
and take a step back, and really
talk about what the problem was, what
the challenges were we were seeing,
how we came up with the solution.
And really how we built it out
to make it to easy as deploy as
possible, whether locally in our own
environments or actually for demos
out in a customer's environment and
giving them the chance to get hands on.
We'll then wrap up what Sarah
looks like today, how it changed
the way our field engineering team
interacts with potential customers.
So that all sounds good.
Stick around.
Let's get started.
Now, I got to give a little
credit here to one of my former
solutions engineers, Aaron G.
He once told me you always
got to start the conversation
with a finished cake, right?
If you think about those traditional
cooking shows, here's the beautiful dinner
that we're going to make tonight, right?
And they put it away and then
they jump into the conversation.
And so that's what I wanted
to do with y'all today, right?
And so in our case, The finished
cake is doing a demo with a globally
distributed customer, right?
And it just works.
All the magic's there.
It happens right out of the box.
We're talking sleek, ready
to wow enterprise clients
without skipping a beat.
Our solution mirrors those enterprise
environments of customers, enterprise
type infrastructure controls and concerns
and set up with just a few clicks.
And so by the end of the presentation
today, you'll understand how we built this
powerful system and how it impacts the way
that we deliver demos here at CircleCI.
So before we hop into the demo,
I want to take a look at what it
is we're going to show you here.
I'm going to show you triggering a
deployment Through CircleCI pipeline
to roll out new releases to an EKS
environment across multiple regions.
So we've actually got clusters deployed
across North America, EMEA, and Japan.
We're going to show you how the
CircleCI releases dashboard.
We'll go through a series of steps.
to incrementally roll out these
new features as they're released
or automatically roll back when an
error is encountered when possible.
This is just a quick demo to show
you what the application developer
experience is like, how they
would interact with CircleCI in
a typical enterprise environment.
The key here is that we're deploying
an app automagically without ever
needing credentials that a developer
might see, leak, or be exposed
to, and without the need to have
manual intervention if something
goes wrong during the deployment.
So it's demo time.
And so this is the finished product.
This is our Sarah and
enterprise environment.
And what's going on here is a
deployment demo that just showcases
a few of those capabilities.
So as you can see, we have
three windows upon the screen.
On the left hand side is a
circle CIS pipeline page.
I'm actually going to trigger
a deployment to run a build and
deployment pipeline to run against these
environments in North America and a Mia.
which are the two windows
on the right hand side.
The app we're using is a
colloquial named Doctor Demo.
It's a deploy and release
demo, hence the Doctor DR.
And it's actually going to show
you how we can incrementally and
progressively roll out these features.
So the left window you'll
see now has updated.
We're actively building these
applications across two different
jobs, one for the North American
region and one for the MIA region.
As these jobs Progress and
actually start to introduce this
environment into those versions.
You'll actually see the colors
on the right hand side change.
So the colors represent
the current app version.
And you'll see us introduce a new
color to each one of these screens.
And you can see that on the top we're
already introduced a yellow version.
And on the bottom we're going
to introduce a green version.
And there it goes.
We can jump over to CircleCI's
release dashboard that I mentioned.
On the left screen here and
actually see those releases as well.
So now this is being monitored from
the Kubernetes cluster and sending
information back to CircleCI about
how those rollouts are progressing,
whether they're succeeding or
failing or needed to be rolled back.
I'm actually going to intentionally,
you can see on the right hand side, I've
dragged the error rate up to this 200%.
So I'm intentionally causing this EMEA
instance to send bad bad results back to
the server, basically invoking failures.
This should be enough to trigger
Our analytics to say, wait a minute,
something is wrong with this release.
I'm going to leave the North American
release up top healthy, so that
one should continue on normally.
And the window here we're looking at
is that yellow release, it's coming
online, we're about halfway through,
and it's basically increasing the
amount of traffic that is going
to each one of these applications.
Now I'm clicking into that failed release.
It was a failed release because I
intentionally set the error rate high.
CircleCI's release agent detected
that in the rollout and said,
Wait a minute, we've exceeded our
error limit for this application.
And so now on the bottom you can
see the traffic was incrementally
increasing the amount we were
sending to this new version.
It actually completely stopped that
and rolled back to the prior version.
Meanwhile, in North America, though,
we didn't encounter those same errors.
Whatever was different
in the environment, i.
e.
Eddie mucking around
with it it's succeeding.
And so we're going to let
that rollout continue.
And you can see that both in the
CircleCI releases dashboard, as
well as the environment there.
So this is just one of those apps
that we can use with customers to
drive that kind of demo conversation.
Now, to elaborate a little bit more
on what we saw and go deeper into what
our solution actually looks like, this
is a point I'm going to go ahead and
hand it off to Mu to walk through how
we went through this process as a team.
Thanks, Eddie.
To elaborate a little bit on what Eddie
showed us there, this environment is
fully built on infrastructure as code.
Everything is automated and
repeatable, except for the initial
domain purchase and IAM role setup,
which are one time manual steps.
Thanks, Eddie.
It runs on Kubernetes,
specifically on EKS, giving us
the flexibility and scalability
needed for enterprise level demos.
We've implemented Istio as our service
mesh and Ingress controller, with tools
like Kiali, Grafana, and Prometheus
to manage, monitor, and visualize
what's happening in the environment.
Now we've showed you the solution,
but we didn't start there.
Let's go back to the
problem we wanted to solve.
Now, the problem was clear.
Each demo needed to be unique, which meant
we were constantly reinventing the wheel.
music ends We lack standardization,
and that caused friction
amongst customer trials.
And guess what?
It was a mess.
Repeated work with too much manual
effort led to demos that were missing the
mark with enterprise clients, big time.
Without infrastructure as code,
security was a concern, and the
manual steps slowed us down.
Enterprise teams expected better,
and we knew we had to step it up.
We have two main goals when
building this demo environment.
First, we wanted to reduce the
amount of effort that it took to
deliver clean, consistent demos.
This meant creating a highly available
demo environment that could be spun
up quickly, without needing manual
intervention or endless preparation.
The more reusable we could make the
environment, the less time we would spend
reinventing the wheel for each demo.
Second, we wanted to elevate
the conversation we were having
with customers instead of just
showing them a static demo.
We needed a dynamic, scalable
platform that mirrors the kind of
infrastructure that they're running.
By doing this, we're able to
provide a more consistent experience
across different enterprise
roles, whether it's the dev team,
security team, or operation teams.
Everyone can see how our platform
fits their specific needs.
How did we get all of this started?
Let me tell you, it wasn't
an overnight process.
It took a lot of collaboration and
late night discussions across teams.
We started with technology chats, where
our team, spread across North America,
Europe, Middle East, and Asia, and
Japan Asia Pacific worked together to
select the right tools and technologies.
We had to ensure everything aligned
with customer needs while fitting
seamlessly into our own ecosystem.
Next, we had vision shots.
These were more strategic, where
management and field engineers focused
on defining the impact that we wanted
to achieve with this environment.
It was about telling the right story, one
that demonstrated real value to customers.
Initially, our goal was to create a
reference architecture that customers
could trust as a close reflection
of their own infrastructure.
Now, while we worked on this,
the team continued their regular
duties, generating leads and closing
deals using our existing methods.
But as the architecture took shape, it
became clear that this new environment
would become central to how we run
demos going forward here at CircleCI.
And personally, in my own deals, it
has really changed the way that I
interact and engage with prospects.
Having this consistent.
And scalable environment to demo in real
time has removed a lot of the friction
and made my conversations more impactful
and relevant to potential customers.
So what did we come up with?
After laying out the solution, one of
the key discussions we had was whether
to create a multi tenant environment
or to provide each field engineer
with their own demo environment.
On one hand, a multi tenant environment
would be more cost effective and aligned
with how shared environments are used
in the real world enterprise settings.
However We also considered giving
each field engineer their own
isolated environment to eliminate any
potential conflicts between demos.
Ultimately, we decided that while
individual environments were attractive,
the cost didn't justify the need,
especially since enterprise teams
typically worked in shared spaces already.
This decision helped us to
maintain consistency while keeping
the infrastructure efficient.
We also explored the possibility
of building versus buying a
dedicated demo automation tool.
While we found some tools that partially
covered our needs, they didn't really
offer the flexibility and control we
needed to mirror customer environments.
We stuck with our modular
infrastructure as code approach,
which allowed us to customize on a
per region, per demo basis without
deviating from the core architecture.
Now, building on that decision to
go with a multi tenant environment,
we designed the architecture to be
modular and layered to handle the
complexity of demo environments
without creating unnecessary overhead.
At the top, we have the global layer.
This covers the foundational elements
like DNS and IAM policies, which
are shared across all regions.
It is a single source of truth for global
resources that every region can rely on.
Next, we have the region core.
This layer handles region specific
infrastructure, like the EKS clusters,
networking, routing, and certificates.
It's designed to be consistent across
regions, so no matter where a demo
runs, the core setup is the same.
And finally, we built out
the region platform layer.
This is where the customization happens.
It includes components like Vault for
secrets management, Nexus for artifact
storage, and the app namespaces where
teams can deploy their demo apps.
Each demo is isolated, but still
follows the same core structure,
which means we can easily replicate
it for different regions or use
cases without starting from scratch.
Now, by using this layered approach,
we ensure that the infrastructure
remains consistent across regions,
while still allowing flexibility
for specific customer needs.
You have you may have noticed,
The load vault credential
step in our earlier preview.
Let's talk about how we tackle
secrets management because
that's also super important.
One of the biggest challenges in
any demo or production environment
is managing secrets securely.
We wanted to ensure that our
infrastructure not only mirrored
enterprise setups, but also adhere to the
best practices for secrets management.
Our approach begins with single sign on
or SSO for initial AWS operator access.
Once that's in place, we use OpenID
Connect or OIDC assumptions, which
means our pipelines run securely with
web identity to provision the entire
stack without exposing credentials.
For added security, the root
key for Vault, which is the
backbone of web is stored in AWS
Key Management Services, or KMS.
This allows Vault to auto unseal, adding
another layer of security during setup.
Now, the operating operators
themselves are given limited,
unique roles that restrict their
access outside of the pipeline.
This ensures that no one has
unnecessary access to the
sensitive parts of the system.
Meanwhile, our development pipelines
rely on predefined policies within
Vault to load any additional
credentials or tokens so that the
secrets are only retrieved as needed.
In short, our setup ensures that
sensitive information is protected
at every layer, from initial
provisioning to ongoing operations.
By keeping the secrets out of developers
hands and automating access through
Vault, we're able to secure the
environment without slowing things down.
Now that we've figured out all the details
and ironed out all the kinks, let's talk a
little bit about how things are going now.
When we first rolled this
out, adoption was a bit slow.
While the environment was
powerful, it lacked the polish
to really grab attention.
It was functional, but it didn't
have that wow factor, just yet.
Now, as we improved the demo apps
and incorporated more eye catching
features like modular microservices,
firmware testing, mobile releases,
things started to change.
The addition of visual deploy tracking,
which is what we demoed earlier,
also added some much needed flair.
Customers really like that.
Teams could now see the
deployments in real time, which
was also a huge selling point.
Now, initially, contributions to
the environment were slow, and
we realized the architecture was
a bit too complex and entangled.
Each new field engineer who used
it, though, slowly cleaned up the
process, little by little, making it
more user friendly and accessible.
Over time, the environment became
widely adopted, not just by
our team, but by teams outside
of field engineering as well.
We even have some customers that
have deployed it locally for their
own testing and trial purposes.
It's now the go to demo platform,
and its use has become consistent
across the organization.
Now, speaking of customers that are
using Environment, we had a real
light bulb a ha moment when one of our
customers came to us and asked, Hey!
How do we get our own access
to your sandbox environment?
That was a real game changer because
up until that point we were focused
on using the environment for internal
demos or internal demos to customers.
But this request really opened
up a whole new perspective and it
showed us that customers aren't
just interested in seeing the demo.
They wanted to get hands-on with the
same infrastructure that we were using.
And on top of that's a really
powerful selling point to be
able to tell your customer, Hey.
You can go ahead and use, our tool
within your infrastructure, right?
So this was a pivotal moment because
one, it validated all the work that
we had put into making the environment
scalable, modular, and secure.
And two, now we're not just
showing off the platform.
We're actually getting to offer customers
the chance to test drive it themselves
in real time, which is super powerful,
especially in the sales process.
But naturally, this also meant
we had to make some changes.
Quite a few, actually.
First off, we had to remove any hard
coded IDs or paths from the environment to
make it flexible enough for external use.
This wasn't just about running demos
anymore, it was about giving customers
the ability to use the environment
themselves, which meant it needed to
be adaptable for their unique needs.
We also needed to fully document
the provisioning process.
We knew if customers were going to
dive into the environment, everything
had to be clear and straightforward.
Thankfully, we already had a solid
document in place, which was about
80 percent of what we needed.
So going through and patching
that up before we gave it to the
customer wasn't too difficult a task.
From there, it was all about refining
the architecture, making it truly
implementable for external use,
while still maintaining the security,
scalability, and modularity that
made it so powerful to begin with.
Now, adapting the environment for
customer access wasn't just about
making it usable for them, it also
opened up new opportunities to
make our deployment more portable.
Like I said before, we shifted from hard
coded elements to a mostly parametrized
setup, which allowed us to deploy
the same architecture across multiple
environments, regions, and customer
specific configurations with ease.
This meant that we can now spin up
environments not only for our internal
demos, but also for customer POCs, sandbox
environments, and even full scale trials.
By modularizing the core components,
we made it easy to tweak or scale
the deployment based on what
the customer actually needs.
And the benefit is the architecture
now adapts without requiring a
total rebuild, which is awesome.
And this portability has given us and
our customers the flexibility to deploy
the same powerful infrastructure in a
variety of contexts, saving time and
ensuring consistency across environments.
Now that you've seen it all, let's
recap everything we've covered
and the impact that it's had.
First and foremost, the
consistent demo experience.
By using a modular and layered
infrastructure built on Terraform and
Kubernetes, we've removed a lot of
the friction that came with setting
up one off environments for each demo.
Now, no matter which region or
customer we're dealing with, we
can spin up the same reliable
environment with minimal effort.
Next, the platform is reflective of
our customers own infrastructure.
From multi region deployments to the
integration of tools like Vault for Secret
Managements and Istio for Service Mesh,
the environment mirrors what enterprise
customers are using and what they're
using right now, which allows them
to really see themselves in the demo.
Which adds a lot of value and helps
them better understand how our
solution fits into their own ecosystem.
We've also implemented better
controls, particularly around security.
Password list deployments, IAM
policies, and secret management with
Vault mean that sensitive information
is handled automatically, securely,
and with minimal human interaction.
This setup aligns perfectly
with what customers expect in an
enterprise setting, helping build
trust during the demo process.
Beyond that, the adaptability and
portability of this environment
have been real game changers.
We can customize the deployment
for different customer use cases,
or even hand it over to them
for sandbox or trial purposes.
Something that would have been
impossible with our previous setup.
This flexibility has opened up new doors
for how we engage with customers and
accelerate their path to production.
Finally, this process has allowed us
to streamline internal operations.
The environment is not only more
efficient for demos, but has
been widely adopted across teams,
reducing the need for manual setup.
Improving speed and ensuring that
everyone has the access to the
same high quality environment.
In short, this architecture has
transformed how we deliver demos, making
them more consistent, secure, and tailored
to the enterprise needs of our customers.
And with that, we end.
Thank you for joining us today.
We hope this walkthrough gave you a clear
understanding of how our demo environment
has evolved and the impact it's having
on how we deliver value to our customers.
We're excited about what's ahead and
looking forward to seeing how this
continues to improve our ability
to meet customer needs with greater
consistency, security, and flexibility.
Thanks again for your time, and we
hope you enjoyed the presentation.