Hey everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 Q Native.
I'm Rs and I work as a senior
Dere engineer at Metal Bill.
In this talk, I'm going to be covering
a very important problem, and that
is the rising number of Kubernetes
clusters in an organization once
they decide to adopt Kubernetes.
I'm going to show you that how when you
as an organization make a decision to
move to Kubernetes, you start with a
couple of clusters, and then the number
of clusters just exceed exponentially.
Don't worry, I'm not just going to be
talking about the problem in this talk.
But I'm also going to give you a solution
using which you can reduce the number of
Kubernetes clusters in your organization,
thereby reducing your cloud costs, and
just making the lives of your DevOps
teams and developers a lot easier.
So let's just get right into it.
First, I wanna walk you through
how things happen when you as an
organization decide to adopt Kubernetes.
So it starts out with a
lot of excitement, right?
You have heard good things about
Kubernetes, and you realize the benefits
you will get, and you decide to adopt
Kubernetes for your production workloads.
So this usually means creating
one cluster, which you'll use to
deploy your production workloads.
Then you realize that you cannot
ship changes directly to that
production cluster, right?
Because sometimes your changes might
break that cluster, and because of this,
you add one or two staging clusters,
which help you, you know, test changes.
And then.
You ship them to the
production cluster too.
So at this point things are
still manageable and I feel like
it's, we are at an okay point.
Then you realize that deploying to
staging actually takes a lot of time
and developers don't want to wait
that long just to get that validation.
If there are changes in a poll
request are working or not.
At this point, you start spinning up
clusters in your CI setup because you
want to run tests and give feedback
to developers early on instead of them
having to wait for staging deployments.
Also, when one team is deploying to
staging, it becomes unusable for the other
team, which is also another reason why
the demand for CI clusters start growing.
At this point, things have, you
know, started to get a little.
Out of control.
You are realizing that your cloud bill
is slowly rising, but it's still okay
because you recognize the benefits
Kubernetes is giving you and your team.
Then one day you hear a complaint
from your developers that even CI
is so slow that staging and CI both
are inaccessible because of how long
they take, and your developers want
a faster way to test their changes.
At this point, you start thinking
about personal environments and
personal clusters, which mirror your
production setup so that developers
can test out immediately, and
you are still able to ship at the
speed that your business demands.
Now you can clearly see
your cloud bills rising.
Now you're thinking about finops and
how to optimize cloud costs because
you are hearing pressure from everyone
in your organization that we really
need to cut down a cloud bill.
But the story doesn't stop here
because personal environments
also now seem insufficient.
Your developers want ephemeral on
demand environments, so you either
resort to provisioning a lot of clusters
or start provisioning a huge cluster
and partitioning it by different
namespace, but the outcome is the same.
You now have way too many
clusters or namespace.
Then your DevOps team can manage,
and your cloud bill is just enormous.
Anyone who has, you know, dealt with
personal dev environments on Kubernetes,
I'm sure you will relate to this meme
where your cloud bill has reached a
point where it's just not sustainable to
continue with personal dev environments.
It might have been obvious from
the stuff we talked about earlier,
but let's still take a detailed
look at some of the downsides of
having multiple Kubernetes clusters.
First of all, your cloud bill is just
enormous and your costs are rising.
Secondly, managing all these environments
takes a huge chunk of time and effort
from your DevOps team time and effort,
which could be better spent on other
things had they had that flexibility.
It also sometimes means you need
to expand the size of your team
and and hire more people to manage
these clusters, which further adds
to your costs as an organization.
The other downside is that if you decide
to do ephemeral environments, these
environments still take time to provision.
So even when a developer wants to, you
know, test a code change or you spin
up a cluster in ci, the developers end
up waiting like 15 to 20 minutes each
time before they're able to get that
feedback and validation that the latest
code they have written is working or not.
And lastly, at one point you just have too
many yams and too many clusters to manage.
That you start to think why you even
went down this path in the first place.
Okay?
I know at this point you might
be thinking that you're doomed
and there is no way out of this.
But there actually is.
What if you could use your
staging environment for your
CI and your dev environments?
What if you could safely share that
environment instead of having to
provision individual environments or
having to provision more clusters for
each developer or each CI runs needs?
This is where our open source project
called Medi comes into picture.
Medi lets you run your local process in
the context of a Kubernetes environment.
So while your process is running on
the local machine, you actually get all
the benefits you would had you deploy
to staging without going through the
pain of actually deploying to staging.
This also means that you don't
have to provision more clusters
because your developers can safely
run in the context of one staging
cluster instead of requiring their
own personal clusters, ephemeral
environments, or things like that.
Let's see how this works behind
the scenes so that you start to
understand what I'm saying here.
With Medi, your application runs locally,
but the traffic, the file system, the
environment variables, all of that gets
mirrored from the Kubernetes cluster.
So your local process thinks that it's
running on the cluster, whereas actually
it's still running on your local.
This way you're able to test in
a realistic environment without
provisioning more environments or
without having to, you know, wait 15,
20 minutes for your code to get deployed
to a staging or dev environment.
This diagram here should give you
a better idea of how this works.
So you see that the local process is
running on your laptop, but medi mirrors
incoming and outgoing traffic between
your local machine and the cluster.
So let's suppose your process needs
to talk to some other process or
microservice, which is deployed on the
cluster, but not on your local machine.
Then any outgoing requests which your
process makes, they get mirrored.
To the target service, which
is deployed in the cluster for
that process and other services.
See those requests as if
they were coming from the.
Target service.
Similarly, any traffic you send to
the target service in the cluster gets
also mirrored to your local machine, so
you are able to test out the behavior
of the code you have just written
without having to actually deploy it.
If things aren't super clear from this
diagram right now, trust me, when we
see the demo, everything will connect.
Before we go to the demo, I just wanna
sum up the things Medi enables for you
so that when you see the demo, you're
able to recognize what is happening.
With medi incoming traffic to
your cluster is mirrored to
the locally running process.
Similarly, outgoing traffic from the
locally running process is routed
via the cluster, so it appears as if
it's coming from within the cluster.
Finally, instead of mirroring
requests, you can also choose to
steal certain targeted requests, so
you can set filters that you know,
if this request matches a particular
header, you want that request stolen.
And just send to your local process
instead of being mirrored between the
cluster and the locally running process.
And you're also able to read and
write to the files in the cluster in
case your application requires that.
And at the same time, you can mirror
environment variables, which are
there in the cluster to your local
machine so that the configuration in
which your application runs remains
entirely the same, allowing you to test
it in a production-like environment.
Okay, it's almost time for the demo,
but let's look at the architecture
of the demo application so that you
understand when we actually see the demo.
So we will be working with the IP
visit counter service, which when you
send it a request, it returns back
the IP the request was from, and the
number of times the request has been
sent from that IP behind the scenes.
How it works is that anytime a
request comes, it saves that request
to a Reds database, and then it.
Talks to another service, which is the IP
Info Service, and it gets some information
about the IP from that service.
And then finally, it sends messages to
Kafka, which get consumed by IP visit
Consumer Service, which is for login.
We won't be seeing the logging part in
this demo, but we will be working with
the IP visit counter service, making some
changes to that and seeing how we are able
to test out those changes without having
to wait for our code to get deployed or
without having to provision a cluster
or a separate environment for this.
So the setup will work with
would look like this, that.
You know, we assume that this application
is deployed to a staging cluster by
the DevOps team, like the standard
staging cluster where you used to
test, but we use the staging cluster
to actually test a locally written
code without having to commit the code
or without having to, you know, go
through pipelines and all of that stuff.
Now, when I usually tell people this,
these are some of the responses I have.
I'm often met with a sort of disbelief
or just straight up, you're lying,
but a lot of people have questions
about, you know, is this safe?
Can you actually safely share the cluster?
What happens if my process accidentally
writes to a sensitive database?
I'll answer all of these questions
after the demo so that once you've seen
Meridian action, a lot of things would
just start making sense themselves.
Cool.
So now let's see the demo.
Okay, so I have my application cloned
here, and we are in the IP visit counter
service, the main dot go file there.
And the way this application works
is that if you, it has been deployed,
first of all on the Kubernetes cluster,
and this is like a staging cluster.
So if we get a list of all the deployments
on that cluster, you'll see that the
IP visit, counter service, the consumer
service, it talks to Kafka, Redis.
Everything has been deployed on
the cluster, and none of this
is running on my local machine.
So this solves the first problem where,
you know, developers need to set up their
dev environment or wait for a ephemeral
dev environment to get provisioned where
all of these things take time to deploy.
If you use a staging cluster for
development with medi, like I've been
suggesting, then you skip all of that
because all the dependencies, databases,
queues, whatnot, are already deployed
on the staging cluster and you can
directly talk to them using this method.
So to give you an overview of the
application, the way it works is
that you can send a request to the
endpoint and then it will give a
response showing the IP address.
The request was sent from the number
of times we have sent a request and
some text, which says, remote is fun.
A. Plus high appended to it.
This text remote is fun, is not
hardcoded in the application.
It is being read from a file which
is on the cluster, and this high is
hard there in the application code.
So if I Google here, so
searcher you'll see that.
We get this response string and
then append a high to it, but this
response string is being picked
up from a file which is on the
cluster, and we will soon see that.
But if I were to send another
request here, the account should
get updated to two like we see here.
Cool.
So now we are ready to test Medi out
in the context of this application.
And the easiest way to test Medi
Out, so I'm in Cursor, but Medi has
a code editor extension for Cursor
via code Windsor JetBrains IDs.
So you can search for medi
extension and install it here.
But if you don't want to use the
extension for some reason, we also
have a CLI available, which is which,
which lets you achieve the same
functionality you'll see me do here.
Cool.
So once you have the extension
installed, you should see written here.
And now we want to select
an active configuration.
So configuration for the service
we are going to be working on.
I'll walk you through the
configuration later on.
But since we are working for the
IP visit counter service, I'm
gonna select that configuration.
So I go here, select active configuration.
I choose IP visit counter.
After that, I just simply enable
my extension by clicking this dot.
Cool.
So once it's enabled, what we are
going to do is set a break point.
So now we saw that, you know, when
we send a request to the end point of
the cluster, nothing was happening.
Now what we are going to do is we are
going to use Medi and see that when
we send a request to the endpoint,
that request does get mirrored.
To our locally running process.
So to see that, let's add a break point.
I've added a break point in the
main function where we load some
config and then I go to the run
and debug section of my corridor.
I click run and debug.
You see, it says that using
medi binary found and.
Shortly it should ask us
for a target on the cluster.
So this target is the target
whose requests we want to mirror
to the locally running process.
So basically we wanna establish a
sort of connection between our IP
visit counter service, which would be
running locally on the machine and the
IP visit, counter services deployment.
So I come here and I'll choose the
IP visit counter deployment, and.
After that, ity would basically
establish that connection for us.
Okay, now things are running and we
can go to a debug console and see that
like this connection is established.
And now when we send a request to the
same end point, we'll see that our break
point here on the coordinator gets hit.
So I'm sending this request
and we should get a response as
expected, but here you'll see
that our breakpoint would get hit.
Once a break point gets hit, we can
actually step into this function and.
Here you see that we load
some environment variables.
So once these environment variables
get loaded, the thing I want to
show you is that you know, the con
final conflict which we return.
So I'm gonna like just continue
till we hit this break point.
And here in the final configuration,
you see that we load all of these
environment variables and they
get loaded from the cluster.
So I have not set any of these locally.
And here you see that we are reading
a response file, which is at app.
App slash response txt.
And this file does not
exist on my local machine.
It exists on the cluster.
And this is a file which has the
remote and remotes fund text I
was telling you about earlier.
So if we return from this function, go
here and we, you know step down here,
you'll see that we are reading this file.
The file is app slash response txt, and
from here we are loading the file content.
Which when we passe here in a response
string, which is empty right now, but
like if we go here, then it gets populated
and response string is now remote is fun.
So you saw how our locally running
process is actually able to communicate
with the cluster, read that file,
and see the contents of that file
without us having to, you know,
deploy this particular code like.
We have not made any changes to it,
but without us having to go through
pipelines or set up our own environment,
we are able to leverage the environment
of the existing staging cluster.
So here we saw how we can mirror
requests and basically test out our code.
So assume you had made some change
and you wanted to test it out, you
could just mirror the request and
then that request would get forward to
your locally running process and you
can test it out, but that's not it.
With mirror D, you can even
test the response of your code.
So here you saw that the response we
were receiving, this was being sent
by the counterpart of the service,
which is in the cluster already.
But if we want a locally running
code to, you know, respond to
requests, we can do that as well
with the steel mode in mirror team.
So the way to enable steel mode is by
editing your ity dot con jason file, which
is what I was talking about earlier here.
Our mode was set to mirror and
I'm gonna change it to steel and.
I don't wanna steal all requests
because one of the main benefits
of MERIDIA is, is that it allows
multiple developers to share the same
Kubernetes cluster for development.
So what I can do here is add an
H two TP filter with my name.
And now basically all the requests which
have this filter set would get stolen
by medi to my local machine, and all
other requests would remain untouched.
Now, this is really important because
it ensures that other people or other
developers or even AI agents can
continue using that staging cluster,
and I do not, you know start stealing
all the requests through my locally
running process, thereby breaking
the cluster for everyone else.
This way, I'm able to work independently
while sharing the same staging cluster
for development as everybody else.
So once we have this filter set, I'm
also gonna make some small code chain.
So we saw the text high earlier, right?
I'm gonna change this to high people from.
Gone 42 and now this is part of
our response, and this is really
important because we want to test
out that if Medi is allowing our.
Locally running process to respond to
requests and thereby allowing us to test
our locally running code without us having
to deploy it to the cluster or provision
another cluster where this gets deployed.
So with that said, I've set a breakpoint
as well in this GetCount function.
And now I am going to run
and debug again with Medi.
I will choose the IP visit
counter service again.
And I forgot to remove this break point.
So this first break point was hit
immediately, but we can continue.
And now when we go back here, right,
and we send a request to this end point.
Nothing would happen.
And that is as expected.
So our remote process is still
replying and giving us a response.
We see the text, which is not showing
the change we made, and that's
expected because we are not using
the HGDP filter, which we had set.
But if I sent a request which
has that HT HTT B filter, we will
see that a break point gets hit.
So you see the break point here
gets hit and we are able to, you
know, check the same ip, which
is the IPFR machine, and now.
We are also not getting a response here
because the request has been paused by
our locally running code, and now if I
let go of this request and go back to
my terminal, I should see a response,
which SH shows our updated string.
So you see here we got our
response and it says, remote is
fun plus high people from Goth 42.
So this is very important to
understand how Medi allows you to,
you know, test out your code changes,
including the response of your code
or anything else in an isolated
manner, but in a shared environment.
So you share the same cluster as
everyone else, but you're able to safely
and independently test out your code.
Okay, so that was a demo which showed.
Some features of Medi, but I also wanna
touch upon other features which make
sharing a cluster really easy with Medi.
So first thing which we saw is that
you can set HDP filters, which ensure
that you know each request is handled
once and is routed to the right
process, the right developer who's
working on that particular thing.
If a request hits the remote service
in the cluster, DY will look for the
right HGDP filter and then forwarded it.
To the right developer.
This way, developers don't end up
interfering with each other's work
and are able to work independently.
Secondly, if your application, you
know, consumes messages from a Q service
like Kafka or SQS, Medi supports q
splitting, which enables concurrency.
So Q Splitting is a feature in Medi,
which allows multiple developer.
Purse to safely consume messages from
the same queue without disrupting
the environment for other people.
Now, I won't be going into the details
of this, but you can check out our
documentation or our YouTube channel
as well where we have created short
videos explaining each feature.
Third feature melody has are things
called policies and me Policies help.
Prevent forbidden action.
So if you have a sensitive
database, which you don't want your
developers accidentally writing
to, you can set up a mey policy,
which prevents that from happening.
So this gives you the peace of mind that
your shared staging environment will not
be broken down by any single developers
changes or when they are, you know,
using that environment for development.
Lastly, if you do not wanna use some
staging resources, let's suppose
a database, which is in staging
for any reason you can choose
to run those services locally.
So Medi gives you the flexibility of,
you know, using some services from the
cluster or running some on your local
machine, like databases you might want
to use because you're testing out a
migration or you just don't wanna affect
the staging database or talk to that.
So these are some of the features
which make sharing a staging
cluster for development using
medi completely safe and possible.
And this is how you can avoid creating
ephemeral dev environments or personal
environments, or even spinning up
clusters for your CI process because
you can use Medi CLI in the CI itself.
So.
This brings me to the conclusion
of my talk, and I just wanna sum
up everything we have seen so far.
The gist is that once you as an
organization adopt Kubernetes, if you
are not careful the amount of Kubernetes
clusters, you start provisioning,
just go out of hand because you're
provisioning clusters for ci, you're
provisioning clusters for devs, you're
provisioning on demand clusters for
future branches and all of that stuff.
Medi helps you avoid that by letting
multiple developers and your CI
use the same staging cluster for
development instead of provisioning
clusters for each and every one.
This gives your developers and
your CI tests a production-like
environment to run in.
Whereas it also saves your DevOps
team the time and hassle of
provisioning and maintaining multiple
clusters which look like production.
So with this, you have one production
cluster and you can have another staging
cluster, which looks exactly like
production and that staging cluster.
Is the only thing the DevOps or the
platform engineering team has to
just take care of, you know, making
sure that looks like production
because all your developers and your
CI can just then use that cluster
for development or testing purposes.
It's much better than having multiple
clusters, which you have to manage and
which increase your cloud bail and.
Make for a really bad developer experience
because of how slow they are, because
of the time they take to provision.
When you go with this approach, you
have one cluster which is already
ready and nobody has to wait for
things to provision and they can
instantly access and test out.
The code changes as we
saw in the demo as well.
So to sum up with medi, your cloud costs
are lower, you ship way faster, and most
importantly, your developers are happier.
Thank you for watching this talk, and
I hope you really found this useful and
helps you reduce the number of Kubernetes
clusters you have in your organization
for development and invest purposes.
If you want to try that out, you
can check out our website, metal
bear.com/medi to learn more about me,
or if you want to get hands on and try
out Medi for yourself, you can check
out the open source project on GitHub,
the link you can see on the slide.
And if you have any questions about
the talk, if you have any feedback
or if you wanna set up a call to
understand how Medi works, my calendar
is always available to talk about Medi.
So you can send me an email
at at the red metal bear.com.
Thank you for watching and I
hope you all have a great day.