Hello everyone, welcome to the session
on streamlining API governance.
Kubernetes native API management.
My name is Puputhugunathilaka.
I'm a senior technical leader at WSO2.
My experience extends across the
API management landscape, as well as
the cloud native technologies that
include, contain orchestration systems,
service measures, and many more.
In this talk, I will highlight the
Kubernetes Gateway API, exploring its
transformative impact, not only in the
Kubernetes ecosystem, but also in the.
broader API management landscape.
We'll dive into how this new API is
reshaping the way we Approach API
governance traffic management and service
extensibility within kubernetes ecosystem
Let's kick things off by diving into
what a typical application architecture
looks like in kubernetes Here I have
a design and architecture for movie
ticketing system where users can book
tickets through the platform The system
consists of various services like order
payment, movie, and theater services.
To make the application accessible
to external client applications,
the Ingress Controller is used.
However, you will need to implement
essential functionalities such
as security, rate limiting, and
others within the service itself,
as the Ingress Controller does not
inherently provide capabilities.
Let's dive into the ingress
resource in Kubernetes.
Here is an example of how you can define
a service within an ingress resource
to make it accessible externally.
Typically, host based and path based
routing are the most common methods
used to set up ingress routing.
You will need to specify the service
name and the port for this approach.
For advanced functionalities such as path
rewriting, course configuration, session
management, and timeout settings, you will
need to leverage annotations provided by
the specific Ingress controller in use.
In this case, this annotation
handles path rewriting.
request to a target path like order list.
While annotations offer flexibility,
they can become difficult to manage as
the configuration grows more complex.
This approach does not scale well
as handling numerous annotations
across various services can lead
to maintenance challenges and
increase operational overhead.
Let's take a look at some challenges
with the Kubernetes Ingress when it
comes to managing traffic and providing
advanced functionalities for services.
One of the key constraints is that
Ingress is primarily designed to
handle HTTP and HTTPS traffic.
It lacks native support for
other protocols like TCP,
UDP, WebSocket, likewise.
This means if the application
requires protocol flexibility, you
will need to use additional tools or
controllers to manage that traffic.
Ingress only supports basic
routing configurations such as
host based or path based routing.
It does not have out of the box capability
for more advanced capabilities such as
traffic splitting, which allows you to
do distribute traffic between different
versions of your applications or
header based routing, which can direct
traffic based on the specific route.
While Kubernetes is highly
flexible, the Ingress resource
itself isn't very extensible.
If you need additional features,
you often have to rely on custom
controllers or third party tools.
This makes the setup more
complex and harder to maintain
as your requirements evolve.
Security configurations within
Ingress are quite minimal.
For more advanced security features
like mutual TLS, you will need to add
extra configurations or use custom
implementations which increase the
complexity and maintenance burden.
Ingress lacks built in tools
for detailed observability.
It does not provide native metrics or
traffic monitoring capabilities, making
it harder to get insights into the
performance and behavior of your services
without adding extra monitoring tools.
Lastly, Ingress does not offer granular
control over traffic behavior, such as
retries, timeouts, or rate limiting.
These are crucial for fine tuning the
performance and reliability of your
services, and without native support,
you will need to configure these
features manually or rely on additional
tools, which can complicate your setup.
Overall, while Kubernetes English provides
basic functionality, It has several
limitations when it comes to more advanced
traffic management and observability.
You will need to adapt tools
or configurations to fill
these gaps as your applications
grows and become more complex.
In 2019, the Kubernetes community
introduced the Kubernetes Gateway,
a PIA significant evolution in the
landscape of API gateway management.
Within Kubernetes, this new API was
developed with the specific goal of
addressing many of the limitations found
in the traditional ingress resource.
The Gateway API offers a more
robust and flexible set of features.
providing greater extensibility
and the functionality than
the ingress specification.
It goes beyond simple routing by
incorporating capabilities often
associated with API management
such as enhanced traffic control,
security, and observability.
In essence, it brings API management
like features natively into Kubernetes,
enabling more granular control over
traffic routing, protocol handling,
and advanced configurations,
making it a powerful alternative to
Ingress for complex applications.
The Kubernetes Gateway API specification
introduces role oriented kubernetes
custom resources are extensions of
the kubernetes api which provides the
ability to users to define their own
definitions in kubernetes for their use
cases in this context infrastructure
providers manage gateway class while
kubernetes cluster administrators
oversee the gateway custom resource.
API or the application developers
play a pivotal role in crafting
HTTP routes incorporating essential
information related to the API.
This representation of roles ensure
a streamlined and efficient workflow
within the Kubernetes environment.
The primary aim of the Kubernetes
Gateway API is to standardize and
simplify the entire API gateway
management process within Kubernetes.
It offers a user friendly,
configuration approach streamlining
the overall management experience.
The collaborative nature of this
initiative ensures that gateways,
regardless of their implementation,
can seamlessly collaborate,
communicate using a common language,
and function as a single entity.
Integral components of a unified system.
Through the standardization of
APIs, the Kubernetes Gateway API
unlocks the potential for dynamic
configuration, efficient scaling,
and seamless service discovery.
Furthermore, this standardization
facilitates smooth integration with
the broader Kubernetes ecosystem,
extending its capabilities to
include tooling, support for diverse
frameworks, application management,
security, monitoring, and logging.
One notable advantage is the
cohesive and collaborative
community serving as a driving
force behind continuous improvement.
This community ensures that
standards evolve and adapting
sync with the dynamic needs of
ever growing Kubernetes ecosystem.
Here is an example of how an
equivalent gateway API definition
would look when compared to
ingress resource for order service.
In this case, the application developer
takes the responsibility of writing
the HTTP route for the service.
This HTTP route consists
four key sections.
In the hostname section, you can specify
the hostname for exposing your API.
The rules section allows you
to define rules for the API.
In this instance, a rule for
the pause method of the orders
resource has been created.
Moving on to the filters section.
Two filters have been defined here.
URL rewrite and the
request header modifier.
The URL rewrite filter transform
the order's path to order list while
request header modifier adds a new
header called XOREDID to the request.
Under the backend refs, the backend
service name and port are specified.
The flow is structured such that if the
request lands with the pause method Of the
orders resource path these two filters are
then applied and the request is ultimately
routed to the back end service which
is in this case is the order service.
When we compare the two Kubernetes
resources, the HTTP route resource
stands out as being far more
structured and flexible than the
traditional Ingress resource.
HTTP route allows users to define detailed
filters or execution paths for each
routing role, providing much better Create
a control over how traffic is managed this
increased flexibility enabled application
developers to implement more fine grained
access control and apply additional
quality of service features which are
not as easily achievable with Ingress.
In the context of API management,
these filters can function as a set of
policies applied to the resource or to
the API, such as rate limiting, traffic
stripping, or even security policies
like authorization, authentication.
Likewise, this level of control makes
a HTTP route a powerful way of managing
complex traffic scenarios enhancing
performance and security for your
APIs within Kubernetes environment.
One of the standout features of the
Kubernetes gateway API is the flexibility
it brings to service management.
From the start, the project was
designed with extensibility in mind.
For example, in this HTTP route resource,
you can specify the Kubernetes service
name and port used in the backend refs.
However, there are scenarios where
more detailed configurations are
required, such as defining the
service protocol, timeout settings,
and other backend specific options.
In such cases, the Gateway API allows
implementation providers to create
their own custom resource definitions.
For instance, you can define a custom
resource called backend, where you can
include the additional information not
covered in the default configuration.
Once this custom resource is in place, you
can reference it under back end refs in
the HTTP route for more detailed control.
This same extensibility applies
to filters, enabling developers
to define custom API policies
tailored to their specific needs.
Whether it's traffic management, security,
or performance enhancement, The Gateway
API's ability to integrate custom
resources offers a much richer framework
for managing Kubernetes services.
WSO2 APK is an implementation built
on top of the Kubernetes Gateway
API, extending its capabilities
with additional custom resources.
These custom resources have been
designed to address gaps in the
default gateway API, providing
more comprehensive configurations.
This includes definitions for backend
services, as well as policies for rate
limiting, authentication, scopes, and
more, allowing for enhanced control
and functionality within the platform.
With the Kubernetes Gateway API,
the Ingress Controller is replaced
by an API Gateway, enabling users
to apply more advanced quality of
service features to their services.
In contrast to the Ingress Controller,
where developers had to implement security
rate limiting and other quality of service
features within the service itself.
Making it difficult to scale, but with
the Gateway API, it allows the API
Gateway to handle these responsibilities.
This shift enables service developers
to focus on their core business
logic, while leaving quality of
service management like security
and traffic control to the gateway.
So if you look at some history
context of API gateways.
Early gateways functioned as converters
where it enables communication between
different network architectures.
Then there were proxy servers,
hardware load balancers.
In the early 2000s, application
delivery controllers such as Nginx,
Citrix, and Fi were introduced.
With web services APIs, SOAP gateways came
into the picture by enabling integration,
protocol conversion, and security
enforcement for SOAP based services.
As web APIs and service oriented
architectures gained prominence,
REST API gateways were introduced.
The evolution continued with
the surge of microservices, edge
computing, and IoT, leading to the
introduction of micro gateways.
In the present landscape, we witness
the emergence of cloud gateways.
Equipped with advanced AI and ML
capabilities, making the latest chapter in
the evolutionary journey of API gateways.
With the Kubernetes Gateway API,
we move forward one step further.
API gateway is the crucial runtime
in the API management architecture.
Envoy has emerged as the preferred
solution for re architecting API
gateways, since it is specifically
designed for cloud native environment.
Being open source, it benefits
from community driven approach.
With developers worldwide contributing
to its enhancements and making it
a dynamic and ever evolving tool.
A noteworthy point is the adoption
of Envoy as a runtime for English
controllers in Kubernetes.
Several existing controllers leverage
Envoy as a production ready edge
proxy, solidifying its reliability and
performance in real world scenarios.
It does not just stop at being a
proxy, it comes packed with essential
API management features such as
authentication, authorization, rate
limiting, response caching, etc.
Envoy also comes with the support
for REST and gRPC services.
Extensibility features includes native
filters, Lua filters, Wasm modules, etc.
where you can write your own
code and plug with Envoy.
Envoy is incredibly versatile,
fitting into different deployment
scenarios effortlessly.
Whether it's serving as a sidecar in a
service mesh, Hosted in TOL as a front
proxy, Envoy adapts with the architecture.
In a nutshell, and no isn't
just tool, it's a game changer.
In the API management scene,
the API gateway is a central component
of the API management platform, but it is
just one part of the larger architecture.
The platform is divided into two planes,
the control plane and the data plane.
The control plane includes the
API management portals, while the
data plane consists of runtime
components and your microservices.
The control plane sends control
instructions to the data
plane, guiding its behavior.
The architecture offers flexibility,
allowing you to deploy multiple
data planes across different
cloud environments, regions,
or even in on premise setups.
A major advantage is that with a single
control plane, you can efficiently
manage and govern all the data planes,
no matter where they are deployed.
In this setup, the API developer or the
application developer is responsible for
creating services and configuring the API
gateway using Kubernetes custom resources.
However, the key control instructions
such as subscriptions, applications,
and other various policies still
come from the control plane.
These artifacts are essential because
without them, the APIs are not accessible.
The control plane ensures that API
governance is centrally enforced,
managing critical aspects like access
control, security, and traffic management.
It acts as the back office for API product
managers, providing a platform where
they can enhance the API with additional
features such as documentation, policy
enforcement, rate limiting and more.
This centralized governance
allows for streamlined management
and consistent application of
policies across all services.
The Kubernetes Gateway API
specification ensures that all
gateways adhere to a unified standard.
The standardization enables a
single unified control plane
to effectively manage multiple
API gateway implementations
within a single installation
regardless of their implementation.
This underlying approach simplifies
governance, streamlines operations
and enhances the overall manageability
of diverse API gateway instances.
With the Kubernetes Gateway API
standardization, API gateways
evolving into a vital but commoditized
part of the infrastructure.
I hope you can remember in the early days
You were worried about the file format
of your file system that is FAT32 or NTFS
Today you are not much worried about it
Sooner or later this will happen to the
api gateways as well As it becomes a
commoditized part of the infrastructure
once the api gateway becomes commoditized
part of the infrastructure developers
are freed from The complexities of
gateway management they can focus
more on building and managing apis
and other core development tasks with
this Focus will be moved to the api
management aspects which includes api
lifecycle management api governance
api marketplace version management API
productization, API insights, and more.
Although these features are available
on the existing API management solution,
to fully leverage the benefits of the
cloud native ecosystem, many of these
features will need to be redesigned.
This will involve seamless integration
with various third party services
available on the Kubernetes to
enable more comprehensive and
robust API management solution.
With that I would like
to wrap up my session.
I hope you found it
informative and engaging.
Thank you for your time And
I trust you gained valuable
insight from the discussion