Hi everyone.
I'm Manisha Otti.
I'm so glad you're joining me
virtually today I work on designing
modern cloud-based systems that blend
artificial intelligence with strict
regulatory needs, especially in
healthcare, banking, and insurance.
Today I'll share how we can build,
aI systems that are fast, scalable,
and still safe and compliant.
We will explore how Kubernetes helps
us automate compliance, cut manual
work, and build a trust in ai.
Let's start with the real world
problem we are trying to solve.
In almost every organization I
have worked with, AI is everywhere.
Predicting risks, automating
tasks, personalizing services.
But in industries where lives or money
are at stake, AI has to be responsible.
Let me give you a few examples.
In healthcare, we can't just predict.
Patient outcomes.
We must show why the model
made that prediction.
In banking, fraud detection has to be
fast, but also explainable to regulators.
In insurance, every automated claim
decision must have a trial that says
who change it, what, when, and why.
So the paradox is simple.
AI wants speed.
But regulators want control.
So how do we innovate
without breaking the rules?
That's where Kubernetes comes in.
So think of Kubernetes, like Canada, a
traffic controller for your applications.
It tells each plane, your
AI model, where to go.
When to take off and how to land safely.
So this brings four big
advantages, self-healing.
If a model crashes Kubernetes
restarts it automatically.
Automation, you define the
desired state and the system
keeps it that way and security.
Workloads are isolated.
So sensitive data, stay safe.
Cloud independence run everywhere
on premises or in the cloud.
For example, in one of our projects,
a healthcare data matching service
used to take engineers hovers
to redeploy if something failed.
After moving to Kubernetes, failures
fix it themselves within minutes.
Zero human action.
Let's ground this in three sectors
where compliance truly matters.
Healthcare.
Imagine a global clinical trial
platform analyzing the patient data.
Daily rules require full privacy
encryption and also the audit trials.
Also for banking, a fraud detection
model flags suspicious transactions
in milliseconds, but it must also
store why each flag was raised Also
for insurance and underwriting.
Engine predicts risk, but must
explain its reasoning to both
regulators and also to the customers.
In all this, Kubernetes helps maintain
isolation, separating the sensitive
data and applying security rules.
And also on top of it, keeping the
deployment history for every version.
Here is a simplified, look at
the architecture, like how we
use each AI model is packaged as
a container, like a neat little
box holding everything it needs.
Kubernetes, deploy, deploys these boxes
managing version upgrades automatically
and state full sets like which.
Makes sure models that store data can
roll back safely if something breaks.
Then comes key tops where
every configuration and model
change is stored in kit.
That means when an auditor
asks, who approved this change,
you can show them instantly.
We once had a regulator request
the exact deployment history for
a patient data matching model.
Because of GitHubs, it took
us seconds to show, not days.
With Kubernetes complaints is in intent
afterthought, but it's part of the design.
The main is a. Security rules like force
containers to run in safe read-only mode.
Network policies, block any
communication, not explicitly allowed.
Admission controllers reject anything
that violates policy before it ever runs.
And also the persistent logs automatically
stores the Uneditable audit trials.
So instead of humans manually verifying
every release, the system does it.
For example, when one developer tried to
deploy a model that wasn't code reviewed,
the controller blocked it automatically.
So that saved us from a compliance breach.
Tops turns the compliance into automation.
Every change starts as a pull
request and automated checks validate
security fairness and data rules.
Then once approved, Kubernetes
applies it safely and traceable.
If something goes wrong, we can roll
back instantly in one bank's deployment.
Updates that use two take five hours now.
It's taking just 12 minutes
with zero manual steps.
Every log, every version, every
approval is automatically captured.
Visibility builds trust, so we use
service mesh technology to watch how
each service talks to one another,
just like a traffic camera system.
This lets us do gradual
rollouts and instant rollback.
If something misbehaves for
explainability, we integrate simple
model explanation tools that visualize
what influencer each prediction.
So when a doc, when a doctor asks, why
was this patient flagged high risk, the
system can actually show the reasons.
Monitoring dashboards powered by
Grafana, and similar tools give live
insights into a performance and cost.
Everything is transparent.
AI systems can burn money
fast, especially with the GPUs.
Kubernetes helps by scaling
GPU, no notes when needed.
Assigning GPUs to critical jobs.
First, using cheaper preempt servers
for bragger background tasks.
In one insurance project, we cut
compute costs by 40 percentage
simply by letting Kubernetes decide
where to turn GPUs on or off.
We built a global patient record matching
system before Kubernetes matching
was slow and error prone as well.
So after migration it handled 10
million requests daily and inference
speed improved by 73% Compliance.
It's fully automatic.
The system enforced healthcare
privacy policies at the deployment
and stored immutable logs for audits.
It's a great example of performance
and compliance coexisting.
A multinational bank used
manual deployments that took
covers and were error prone.
After moving to Kubernetes
pipelines, releases drop put
from hovers to just minutes.
Fraud detection became four times faster,
and traceability satisfied the payment
industry regulators automatically.
So speed and safety in harmony.
For a larger insurer, running
models across regions, data
isolation was the biggest concern.
We used Kubernetes namespace to
separate clients auto-scaling, to
handle claim traffic, and built in
explanations for every AI decision.
The result is cost savings.
Transparency and happier regulators.
So these are the patents
we follow repeatedly.
Complaints as code like policies
or return like code submissions,
enforce them, immutable audit
trails, logs can be altered.
Safe rollouts.
New models start with 5% of traffic.
Then scale layered.
Security training and
serving are fully separated.
Following This ensures consistent
success no matter the industry.
After years of deploying these systems.
Here is what stands out.
Automate compliance early.
Build visibility from day one.
Scale smart.
Avoid over provisioning.
GIS is a cultural shift.
It blends transparency and also the trust.
These lessons came from real
teams, not just theories.
What's next?
We are moving toward policy
driven runtime compliance where
systems self-correct instantly.
If a rule breaks, we are exploring
serverless GPUs, pay per prediction
instead of perha, and we are
testing federated learning training
models in multiple locations
without moving the private data.
The future is compliance that's
intelligent, automatic, and invisible.
To wrap up, Kubernetes gives us
scale, compliance and efficiency.
We have seen 90% faster deployments,
10 million daily requests, and
four times faster detection.
All in regulated environments,
compliance doesn't slow innovation.
It strengthens it.
When it's built in, it becomes
your greatest advantage.
Thank you all for spending your time.
I hope this session helped
you see that compliance and
innovation can truly work together.