Hi, everyone.
Welcome to Conf42 kubernetes event.
I am glad to provide this session.
This talk demonstrates how to
build a real time data processing
pipeline with serverless
infrastructure from your day one.
I hope you will like the session and
it will be helpful to, for you to
understand the different technologies
and tools for real time data processing
nowadays in modern streaming environment.
So with that, let's get started.
Let me introduce first myself.
My name is Babur.
I am a developer advocate at
Glassflow, and also I am a
Microsoft MVP for Azure AI services.
I like to build recent AI
applications, and I am also an
evangelist for data streaming tools.
If you would like to connect with me,
you can always request on LinkedIn.
Please, if you have any questions
about this session or after this
session, I would be more than
happy to address your questions.
So let's start with our story.
Our story begins with
a data engineer, Bob.
Dreamer who works at a medium sized
company called dream together with more
than 50 his colleagues and they are
building an innovative car selling online
platform where I like you can register
and announce your vehicles to buy or sell.
Bob was actually highly motivated
by the reason AI hype, since
everybody around him talks about AI.
He comes up with a brilliant idea
of creating a real time price
recommender solution for their existing
website using modern data tools.
Let me explain how that works.
As new cars are registered in their
primary database, such as it can
be NoSQL database, the app should
suggest the price for the vehicle
using the AI and this application
need to show in real time recommended
price on their website so users can
quickly receive appropriate feedback.
Bob presents his idea to the team.
And the team was curious about the
outcome and the team that gives
him to prove some time to Bob
to provide the proof of concept.
And Bob starts his investigation by
understanding what is batch processing and
real time data processing because with his
background in using the tools for batch
processing, he discovers that in practice
bots collect, they collect and process
data for using downstream applications.
The only real distinction between
batch and stream processing is
that they, how they operate at
slightly different time intervals.
For a long time, like in flexibility
of batch orchestrators and schedulers,
keep the data teams to maintain
a separate set of systems, like
one system for batch processing,
another system for stream processing.
But it doesn't have to be that way.
Nowadays, a real time data streaming
pipelines can solve this problem and
combine for both batch processing and
stream processing into one workload
so that you can use the same tools
and technologies infrastructure.
to process and transfer your data.
Here, as you can see in the
diagram, how the real time
data streaming pipeline works.
Actually, this solution is
essential for some applications.
They need to up to date, bring
some up to date information,
like monitoring live events or
updating dashboards in real time.
As you can see, we have the data source
and we have the data destination.
And in the middle layer, we Where all the
transformation happens as data changes,
change happens on the source side.
These changes are in the real time
captured from the transformation
part and then you, in the
transformation, you can do aggregation.
You can do filtering, enrichment, maybe
introduce ML or AI models to train
your model, then send the output to
intended destinations like data lakes
that can be data warehouses or any
analytical services in even a real
time application and microservices.
And then Bob once understanding the about
the string data streaming, pipelines.
He thinks of his first solution for
the real time price recommendation
system where he uses Debezium to
capture data changes, as you can see
in the diagram, and stream those events
via Kafka to the prediction service.
And the prediction service, actually
just a Python application that connects
to the OpenAI API to calculate the
suggested prices and sends and reaches
output to the web application or to
the analytics tool to see how the price
is changing, how often and understand
Which users are buying or selling and
so on, but however Bob face it with
several solution in his first solution,
let's say he lacked the experience.
First of all, with Kafka, because
he has a Python engineer, a Python
background, and he didn't want to do
with the infrastructure complexities
because he doesn't have enough experience
in DevOps or learning Kubernetes.
Due to time concentrates to build
this a simple proof of concept
and bring it to the production.
His goal also to implement everything
through Python, obviously, because
there might be some data scientific
approach to call some ML models
to calculate predicted price.
And he also make sure that multiple
data engineers in his team could
collaborate on one pipeline.
And in addition to this, he needed
the product service to notify
the web application or their
other systems at the same time.
And Bob continues his discovering
by searching on Google or asking
GPT, also asking his friends.
about their experiences with Kafka or
any real time data processing tools.
And Bob hears some stories from Kafka
users about taking nine months to
implement production ready Kafka based
data pipelines if they are self managed.
They see the customers having 50 teams
relying on a single Kafka cluster.
Memory is only by one person and
sometimes data engineers cannot
simulate easily production environment
without initial complex setup.
And also we see that data scientists
struggle with data integration, like
building offline ML pipelines, experiment
and reproduce some models without
pushing it to prod or debug them locally.
There are many problems using this
Kafka related infrastructure, and then
he also determines that there are some
problems with self managing Kafka that
presents, let's say also it's difficult
to determine which team or individual
actually responsible for Kafka operations,
Bob or DevOps team or software engineering
team, or configuring Kafka correctly
from the scratch is also problematic.
I think you need, you
don't know like how many.
Clusters you need for your
organization or you need single
block cluster or multiple clusters.
Also deploying changes continuously to
Kubernetes to or to other environments
and bring some also additional problems.
Also upgrading Kafka brokers
always is challenging.
Sometimes you don't know how
much you want to scale your
Kafka broker or how much storage.
You would like to give
to the topics and so on.
And another big topic is, of course,
monitoring Kafka performance and health
is quite challenging when you are,
have a self managing Kafka environment.
Managing Kafka clusters, as we said,
can be expensive, both in terms of
infrastructure and operational costs.
At this point, you start to consider
using some managed Kafka providers.
As you can see in the screen, I
highlighted some well known managed
Kafka providers like Red Panda.
We have the Ivan for Apache Kafka
Confluent, one of the biggest
one, and we have a new startups
coming up like Warpstream.
But however it does so it doesn't solve
the data engineers like both problem
because they need still dedicated engineer
who understand this, his physical use
cases and business needs and spin up
the Kafka environment in the cloud
providers or that's in the confluent.
Also, choosing providers should
be also secure enough, you need to
make sure that everything is secure.
Also, you need to additionally watch out
over provisioning or fluctuating costs,
because If you don't manage this cost you
made you may end up with a high costs.
You need to understand cost
of model that you are managing
inside your Kafka providers.
One of those drawbacks once you start
to use you need to bring some data
transformation logics dynamically.
But to use it in data transformation,
you need to use a separate
environment in your Kafka provider.
Let's say Amazon MSK also offers quite a
good useful tool for managing your Kafkas.
But if you would like to do
some transformation, You need
to use and also the pay for
additionally using Lambda functions.
So we said he starts also understands like
data engineers or often depends on other
teams to maintain data infrastructure.
Sometimes data engineers need to ask
DevOps to assist the provision cloud
resources to manage Kafka or deploying new
data pipelines for just sake of a proof
of concept they are all creating delays.
So commonly Bob wants some self
efficiency, self sufficiency in Python.
He can just take care of his logic for
the data pipeline and orchestration.
But the rest, when it comes to
infrastructure, do do it while,
by maybe any other technologies.
Bob combines all the problems and I said,
the data engineers and scientists are
facing in 2024 and he writes a blog post.
If you scan this quote, you can understand
more about other problems data scientists
and engineers are facing nowadays.
My advice is actually, you can
also start by discovering options.
First of all, without
using any Kafka providers.
Nowadays there are other tools
from the cloud providers like
Azure or Google or the Amazon.
Or instead of some other message
brokers coming up like a nuts which
is open source used by many people now
a days gaining a lot of popularity.
And Bob, as he's a dreamer, one of his
dreams, he so said, there's also some
stream processing frameworks in Python.
That can solve his existing problem.
So he starts to investigate this
stream processing frameworks in Python.
Let's focus on when and why
we can use a stream data
processing frameworks for Python.
First of all, we know that
Python is go to language for data
science and machine learning.
As you can see in the diagram.
Python based framework can unify the
streaming data platform and stream
processor components in the given
streaming data pipeline architecture.
You can connect directly
to any data source.
Using built in connectors that provides
these frameworks within your application
code without knowing like how Kafka
or other Message brokers work and you
can focus only on your business logic.
In other words, stream processing
frameworks Combines both Kafka and Flink
environment for let's say stateful data
stream processing operations and then
Bob asks himself, okay, why used to put
Python frameworks for data streaming?
There are other several reasons.
If you are a Python developer you
can use frameworks out of the box
with any existing Python library.
No JVM, no wrapper, no orchestrator
or server side engine you need.
You can bring pandas or any libraries
or you get used to deal with.
And if you are a data engineer, you
don't need to deal with infrastructure.
You can start this framework
without any complex initial
setup, such as creating clusters.
And Python frameworks offer zero
infrastructure environment for you.
If you're a data scientist,
no need to learn Kubernetes.
You can run your local code right from the
Jupyter notebook to try out your pipeline.
And if you're worried about your data,
your original data also stays where it
is in your primary database, and then
the framework just runs a transformation
layer on the top of it and sends
data to your output destinations.
Like you can use change data capture
settings like Debezium by directly
connecting to the primary database and
doing the computational work, and save the
result back to the your primary database
or send the data to output streams.
So with that, our team also, we build this
stream processing framework to do with
real time data or even the driven data.
It's called it's called Glassflow.
Glassflow is also serverless,
Python centric real time
data processing pipeline.
You can build your data pipelines
within the minutes without
setting up any infrastructure.
With just simple clicks or using the CLI,
you can bring your first data pipeline,
let's say, in the first 15 minutes.
And actually, Glassware excels in real
time data transformation of your events.
So that application can immediately
react to the new information.
In other words, data, real time
data pipelines creation process with
Glassflow is as simple and casual
as Yusuf shoots at the Olympics.
No infra, no Kafka, or
the flink is required.
How we build data
pipelines is very simple.
You just connect to your data sources,
which you send some real time data
information using built in integrations.
Without writing any code in a low
code environment, or if there is no
any built in integration, you can
build your own integration without
spending much time by implementing
custom connector using GlassLove SDK.
And you write the code to implement
in Python data transformation logic.
In Python, once you deploy this
transformation function to your
pipeline, and this transformation
function runs in autoscalable serverless
infrastructure, You can easily deal with
the billions of log records in real time.
And also, Glassdoor built using the
modern technology, or the technology
you get to use like Docker, NANTS,
and Kubernetes under the hood.
That just abstracts for you to
make it easy not to manage this
infrastructure under the hood.
And let me show you some real
time examples of pipeline.
I built myself using the log glass flow.
For example, you can build a real
time clickstream analytics dashboard.
You can use, let's say some data
analytics API, like a Google
analytics in Python to collect some
clickstream data from your website
and sends them to glass flow pipeline.
And your transformation function might
analyze data to calculate additional
metrics and you can use this metrics
or energy data to visualize something
using some visualizing tools like a
stream lead or a plot lead in Python.
Or another example is I build a
data processing pipeline to enrich
some classified ads in real time.
You can use Glassflow to process like
website ads and reach them with additional
information or categorize them using
a long chain or open AI and store this
enriched ads in some A quick and advanced
search database like Redis so that the
website is always aware of real time
ads as they are coming into your system.
Or what about like processing,
for example, Airbnb listing
data in some sub base, database?
And you can enrich this data with
your AI and continuously update the
vector databases, such as we will wait.
So this example pipeline can be used also
to create some personalized recommendation
solutions or generate some targeted ads
based on the real time data information.
Last example I would like to
show is a data transformation
pipeline that demonstrates some
log data anomaly detection.
With AI and ML models to monitor your
server logs to detect some unusual
patterns or the activities and send
some notification to the notification
systems or stores in long term storages.
To understand these logs in the future.
So let's just scan this QR code.
You can see all the other use cases
with code examples, tutorials, and
architecture explanation in which use
cases you can apply, or you can use them
as a template for your future projects.
So let's back into our topic
of Bob's about building real
time data price recommendation.
Here's a second example of real time price
recommendation data pipeline architecture.
He As he provided and he developed, but
it is you can see this there are some
components to process car price data.
He ends up with using the super base
because of it is simplicity, open
source then also he would like to,
that when every vehicle is registered
in the PostgreSQL, or you can say, or
Support Base Database they would like
to send the output to to Glassflow
Pipeline using a webhook connector, so
that we are, Pipeline can capture every
change, every insert, every delete, or
every update operation on Support Base.
In, within a milliseconds, this data
will be arrive to the pipeline and the
pipeline can connect to the open AI API
and to to provide some insights from ai.
And then predicted car prices can
be sent to the output destinations.
As you can see tools we use is first
of all starting from super base is
pretty much like a fire base or Heroku.
But it's open source SQL database.
It's 100 percent portable
with your PostgreSQL as well.
You can easily bring your existing
PostgreSQL database or build real
time data applications on top of it.
SuperBase in our architecture
triggers event whenever new entry
with the car data added in the
car price database, let's say.
Then it sends directly to that Glassflow
pipeline using a webhook data source
connector, as I mentioned earlier.
Then we use a Glasswalk web app,
which is one way to, you build a
pipeline Glassflow without writing
any code, just a UI interface.
You put the specified data source
transformation and data destination.
You're going to see it soon in my demo.
Then your pipeline is ready.
Then we are gonna use open AI
obviously to use AI models like GPT
to predict future car price based on
some information we got from superb.
So once the use case is clear, let me
show you demonstrate how that works and
how you can build your first pipeline
within the your five or six minutes.
If you're scanning this QR code, you
can also find the project on GitHub.
You can give a try.
There are some samples code for
transformation and also sample
codes for you to set up some queries
on the SOPA base site and so on.
So let me dive into the demo.
Assume that you have a primary database
like a super base and you have project
inside the project some databases and
we have also car price table with some
attributes belong to the car announced
for the selling or buying and then also
you have sample data for some car prices.
Let me dive into the demo
of creating the pipeline.
Navigate to GlassLaw webapp.
Using the GlassLaw webapp you can create
a pipeline with easy step within a minute.
Start by creating new pipeline
using the Glassflow.
I will provide my pipeline name for the
new pipeline and like a cut price data.
Click next.
And for as a data source,
I'm going to use a webhook.
Because a webhook, we're going to
set up for server based to push some
every data changes to the Glassflow.
Then next step third step, I need
to define my transformer function.
You can use it existing templates
or write Python code to define your.
Transformer function.
I have my already defined transformer
function that you use OpenAI, and the
call makes the call to Chat completion
endpoint to predict the car price for
the upcoming car product event changes.
So I'm going to copy this
transformation function and put
into the editor of the web app.
You can also find the transformation
function code on our GitHub repository.
So we don't have to also
use our own OpenAI API.
We provide the free OpenAI API
account to try out OpenAI use case.
Next step, I'm going to set up
the destination as a webhook.
That can be your real website or any
external website to build a custom
workflows for the demos cases.
I'm going to use webhook site
to create some random webhook so
that the Glassware Pipeline can
send the output to the webhook
once we data is enriched
in the transformer stage.
I click next and finally check my
transformation function pipeline setup,
then click next to create my pipeline.
Now.
Everything's good.
My pipeline is created.
Now I will need only my access
token and pipeline ID to access
push some events from the database
or from your primary database.
In that case, you can also create some
webhook connector for the super base.
You can create a click put
some webhook connector details.
And in this case like it's a core
quality, the car price data and change.
Super base detects every change when
we do in sorts, then push the event to
the Glassdoor pipeline automatically,
you can also push your events.
To the Glassflow pipeline using Python
SDK and write some custom code to push
from any data source to the Glassflow.
So let's define also some HTTP type
and I put also HTTP request header to
define some access token for my pipeline.
I'm going to copy and add
the access token header.
For the pipeline, then put the value
to make sure that we are securely
pushing the events to the pipeline.
Now, the webhook is ready.
Once the webhook is starting to push
events, you can immediately see a
transformed output on the Glassflow side.
Let's go to the next step.
Once again to some sample data in source,
and I'm going to insert some sample
data into the, my primary database.
If I run this SQL query command, I
will gonna add four more in source
with some simple color prizes.
Then, as you can see, as output,
we will have Some logs are coming
from the price collected on API.
Wow, here is, you can see some failures.
In that case, you can also show with
a web app requirements, dependency
requirements for the Python.
I'm going to specify OpenAI and
using inside my transformer function.
So now, if I try once again, as you
can see in the logs, I should get all
of the transformers and processes that
events from the, our primary database,
like server base, as you can see, one
hour, four events out for transformers
and class will immediately send the
transformer data as output to the
webhook we defined it when we create
the pipeline this is the magic of the
pipeline that reacts on real time data.
As you can see, creating pipeline
is quite easy when you're
using tools for for your need.
As you can, Bob made his Python code
that runs in real time mode with a
serverless infrastructure from day one.
Compared to challenges he faced,
he now Have a simple solution.
So a few words about glass flow itself
when people, other people use a glass
flow for, let's say, if you'd like
to have a blood jobs batch jobs Might
take a minutes or hours to execute.
Glassflow enables you processing
your data in milliseconds to seconds,
making the real time analysis
for reality from your day one.
And also if you would like to reduce
the costs connected with running
a spark, like a similar jobs.
That consume your big amount
of competing resources.
Glassdoor offers more
cost efficient solution.
As earlier, I mentioned that like
you can both combine data streaming
part and data transformation part
in the side of the same price.
You don't have to run separate Lambda
or in Azure or functions to run.
Transformation part and launching
new data project with Glassflow as
you can see easy Also integrating
with real time data sources.
So this nation is also quite fast
Glassflow excels in real time data
ingestion and processing of your events
and so on You can have a look Our
documentation and blog to learn more
about this in summary You here few inside
to what we have learned along the way.
So Bob understand that we understand
that engineers face a problems
nowadays with JVM, basic real
time processing tools like Kafka.
And Bob as a data engineer or a
scientist maybe his team, or he
needs to maybe data analysts they
want to self sufficiency in Python.
And then there are some stream processing
frameworks in Python nowadays so that you
don't have to learn some GVM environment.
And so Bob also find out some serverless
stream processing solutions and tools.
To apply to his first pipeline.
So with that we are
about to finish the demo.
Now, if you have any questions
after the session, I will be
more than happy to address them.
So thank you for attending my session.
See you soon.
Thank you.