Hi everyone.
My name is Ola Modi and I'm
happy to be presenting here at
the Cube Native Conference 2025.
I wanted to start with a quick
introduction about myself.
I currently work for Wells Fargo Bank
and I have around 14 years of hands-on
experience in advanced data analytics,
credit risk strategy, and predictive
modeling across financial services,
marketing, and customer intelligence.
I also have extensive experience in
developing machine learning driven fraud
detection strategies, segmentation models,
and campaign optimization frameworks that
help improve ROI reduce risk exposure
and enhance operational efficiency.
The topic I'm planning to present today
is container native ml scaling predictive
customer segmentation on Kubernetes.
Today I'll be sharing how we re-engineered
a traditional monolithic analytics
system into a cloud native machine
learning ecosystem built on Kubernetes.
Our focus was on predictive
customer segmentation, identifying.
Behavioral patterns in real
time at Enterprise Scale.
This session is about
more than just technology.
It's about how containerization
and orchestration can transform the
way organizations operationalize
ml, making it faster, more
efficient, and more cost effective.
Moving on to slide two.
Let's start with the challenges.
Most enterprises face traditional
analytics platforms were not designed
for real-time large scale prediction.
They rely on monolithic pipelines
that struggle under heavy
workloads as data volumes grow.
Performance degrades, leading to longer
processing times and slower insights.
Scalability becomes a bottleneck.
You can't just add more servers.
You need horizontal scaling
elasticity and automation.
Operationally, managing diverse ML
workloads on rigid infrastructure is
complex data scientists, ML engineers
and dev DevOp teams often work in silos.
We need an architecture that could adopt.
Adapt dynamically to business
load, self-heal, and scale.
Predictively, not reactively.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about container
orchestration solution.
So this is where Kubernetes
changed the game for us.
Kubernetes provides the
flexibility and reliability that
monolithic architectures lack.
It allows you to deploy ML workloads
as microservices, which are loosely
coupled and highly scalable.
We implemented horizontal pod auto
scaling, so during peak customer
activity, pods automatically
spin up to handle the load.
Intelligent resource orchestration
distributes workloads, efficiency
efficiently across clusters, and with
built-in fall tolerance, even if one
node fails, another sly takes over.
The result is a system that's
always on, always fast and always
efficient, the backbone of a
real time predictive analytics.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about native
ML architecture overview.
This slide basically gives you a bird's
eye view of the full architecture.
We structured it into four layers, data
ingestion services, feature engineering,
model training, and interference services.
So the first one is data ingestion
services, containerized pipelines.
Pull customer data from multiple sources
like CRM, digital interactions and
transactions using event driven ingestion.
Next one is feature engineering,
independent microservices,
clean, validate and convert raw
data into ML ready features.
This ensures every model
uses standardized inputs.
Model training is the next one.
Distributed training runs across
Kubernetes clusters enabling
parallelization for algorithms
like gradient boosting neural
networks and clustering.
And the last one is interference services.
This layer basically provides
real time predictions.
With Redis caching, we achieve millisecond
response times for customer segmentation.
In short, this architecture
makes the ML process continuous,
modular, and highly responsive.
Moving on to next slide.
Breaking the pipe ML pipeline into
microservices was a turning point.
Each stage ingestion, feature
engineering training, and
inference runs independently.
This means if you're training jobs.
Spike, you scale only that part.
If your inference layer needs more
compute, you add pods just for that.
It reduces resource waste stage
accelerates deployments and simplifies
debugging, and most importantly, it
allows different teams to iterate
without breaking the entire pipeline.
So data engineers, ML developers,
and DevOps can all work
concurrently a major boost.
This is a major boost to HGDT.
We on to the next slide.
This slide talks about
deployment management with Helm.
When you have dozens of microservices
deployment, consistency becomes
crucial, and that's where Helm comes in.
We use Helm charts to define
and version our deployments.
This ensures every ML service, data
processing, training, or inference follows
the same standard configuration pattern.
Helm also supports environment
specific overrides.
So the same chart can be
deployed in development, staging,
or production seamlessly.
Seamlessly.
If something breaks.
Rollback is instant.
We extended Kubernetes with customer
resource definition, CRDs for ML
specific needs, like scheduling, model
training jobs, managing GPU resources
and automating, retraining lifecycles.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about event
driven processing, architecture.
Customer behavior changes constantly
promotions, seasonal campaigns or new
product launches can all shift patterns.
We implemented event driven retraining
to keep our segmentation models are.
To date when our monitoring system
detects data drift, meaning customer
behavior is no longer aligned with
the model, Kubernetes automatically
triggers a model retraining pipeline.
So the new model is validated and
deployed automatically without
manual intervention or downtime.
This approach ensures that ACA
segmentation remains accurate
and responsive even as customer
behavior evolves in real time.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about container
based feature store implementation.
A consistent feature layer is
critical for reproducibility.
We created a container based feature
store that centralizes all engineered
features used by our ML models.
Every service, whether it's training
or inference accesses features through
this store guaranteeing consistency.
We use red caching for sub millisecond
feature retrieval, and with feature
versioning, we can run AB tests on
new features or rollback to previous
versions efficiently, effortlessly.
This ensures full traceability and
confidence in our model outputs.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about
advanced Kubernetes patterns.
So we leverage several Kubernetes
native design patterns to
make the system more robust.
It's, some of them are in IT containers,
sidecar containers, and multi
container pods for the in IT containers
before a main container starts.
These run checks verifying data integrity,
dependencies, and environment readiness.
The next one is sidecar containers.
These monitor performance collect metrics
like latency or drift and push them to.
PROEs or Grafana multi container
pods for components that need
to share resources closely, like
pre-processing and model serving.
These pods offer efficiency and isolation.
These patterns improve observability,
ensure reliability, and made
troubleshooting much easier.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about resource management
strategies, efficiencies, efficiency.
At the heart of container native
ml, we introduce GPU scheduling
policies to ensure deep learning
workloads get prioritized GPU access.
Without idle cycles, we also optimized
memory allocation for large scale
clustering, preventing out of memory
crashes, and improving throughput.
The results that we saw were
remarkable, 85% GPU utilization.
And.
Three, three times more or
better, more memory efficiency.
These are the two remarkable
results that we achieved.
These aren't just performance stats.
They represent cost savings,
unsustainable scalability.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about product
production performance improvements.
After a full deployment,
we saw measurable impact.
There was a 60% cost reduction,
containerization and auto-scaling,
drastically reduced idle infrastructure.
The next one is 99.9% uptime.
The automated failover, redundancy kept
services continuously available, and
it also increased the processing speed.
It is 40% faster, so it distributed
computing, cut training and
interference timing significantly.
These improvements directly translated
to faster campaign turnarounds,
better personalization, and ultimately
higher ROI for our marketing teams.
Okay.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about
implementation strategy, roadmap.
Here's the roadmap.
We followed a structured
four phase approach.
Phase one is containerization.
We converted, monolithic.
ML workflows into
dockerized microservices.
Phase two orchestration.
Kubernetes was implemented for
automated scaling, resource
optimization and workload management.
Phase three was optimization.
We layered on advanced techniques, feature
stores, event driven retraining, and CRDs.
Phase four was production.
This was a full deployment with
monitoring, alerting and CI or CD
integration for continuous improvements.
Each phase was iterative,
allowing us to learn and refine
before scaling enterprise wide.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about the key
takeaways for platform engineers
for platform and ML engineers.
Here are three lessons
that really stand out.
Adopt microservice architecture,
automate with event driven processing,
and focus on resource optimization.
We can talk about adopt microservice.
Architecture first.
So to break your ML pipeline into
modular independently scalable
units, it accelerates development
and improves reliability to automate
with event driven processing.
Let Kubernetes manage lifestyle
events, lifecycle events like
restraining or redeployment.
Focus on resource optimization.
Use Kubernetes native tools
for GPU, scheduling, memory
optimization, and auto-scaling.
These principles turn ML systems from
brittle and reactive into adaptive,
intelligent and cost efficient ecosystems.
Okay.
Moving on to the next slide.
This slide talks about how cloud
native ML is the future now.
The future is now container native ML
is not just a trend, it's the foundation
for scalable enterprise analytics.
We have moved from static centralized
systems to dynamic modular architectures.
That evolve with business needs.
Kubernetes and microservices are
enabling ML teams to deploy models
faster, adapt to data changes instantly,
and deliver real business impact.
The future of ML infrastructure
is cloud native, even driven
and continuously optimized, and
that future is already here.
I think that concludes our presentation.
Thank you so much for your attention.
I hope this session gave you practical
insights into how Kubernetes can
be leveraged for scaling machine
learning in real world enterprise.
Settings, I'd be happy to take
any questions, whether it's
about architecture, automation,
or implementation specifics.
You can also connect with me afterwards to
discuss use cases or share any experiences
with your own ML infrastructure.
Thank you everyone for giving
me this opportunity and I
hope you have a good day.