Hi everyone.
My name is Zaki.
I work at V Cluster Labs.
We are the creators of V Cluster.
We like Kubernetes so much that we
put Kubernetes inside of Kubernetes.
Today I want to talk about.
Kai Scheduler or Kubernetes AI scheduler
from Nvidia and how we can use virtual
cluster technology to make scheduling
easier and more multi-tenant friendly.
The setup I'm currently running
will be available in the
description or in the video notes.
You can run it yourself if you have
an Nvidia graphic card and A GPO.
I already created a cluster.
This setup is a little bit involving.
It configures the docker for
GPO pass through installs all
the components on local cluster.
This of course can be run on
any managed Kubernetes cluster
wherever GPU workloads run.
So let's talk a little bit
about the scheduler itself.
In Kubernetes, we schedule
workloads on different nodes
depending on various conditions.
Kubernetes comes with a
pre-configured scheduler that
works out of the box for CPU notes.
This has been a space.
Heavily developed.
You have tools like Carpenter or others
to make the scheduling process easier.
However, in GPU we would like
to schedule workloads that are
running on graphic cards that
require GPU to run on the notes.
The idea is the same, but the
technology is slightly different.
Nvidia open sourced Kubernetes AI
scheduler or Kai Scheduler in 2025, and
now everybody can use this scheduler to
run GPU workloads on Kubernetes cluster.
So first of all, this scheduler enables
fractional GPU allocation, meaning that
having a single GPU on a node can split
the workloads such that each workload
can just have a fraction of GPU usage.
It enables queue based scheduling,
so we can schedule workloads based
on a queue mechanism that Kai
Scheduler comes pre-configured with.
It has various advanced features like note
topology awareness and other elements.
So first of all, this is a live demo
and hopefully everything will work.
So let's verify that we
actually have access to our GPU.
So indeed, I have pretty old NV
graphic card on my computer one 60,
and we just run this simple cube
catalog command to verify that my
computer actually exposes the GPU card.
Into my kind cluster, which worked,
and we can see it from inside
of the Kind Kai Demo cluster.
So with this out of the way, let's
talk a little bit about V Cluster.
V Cluster enables us to create
essentially a fully fledged
Kubernetes cluster inside of a port.
An easy way to think about it is
to imagine that V cluster enables
containerized Kubernetes inside a port.
So we have a team one here that run their
own workloads inside of a cluster pod,
but they share services from host cluster.
So maybe we have third manager,
Istio Ingress or others Istio
Service Measure ingress controller
or others, and the team can use it.
However, we can also have a separate G
cluster that install everything inside
of the virtual cluster namespace.
So there's a quite interesting use case
here where we can have different teams
using virtual clusters in different ways.
So I cluster provides a
full Kubernetes API server.
It's a fully certified Kubernetes
distribution like any other.
We actually run Kubernetes inside of
a pod to regular Kubernetes binaries.
This enables us to have
very flexible isolation in
various multitenant scenarios.
We're gonna talk about Kai scheduler
in this talk, but obviously all kinds
of other interesting multitenant
scenarios are available as well.
It makes the resource utilization
much more efficient, which
contributes to limiting cost and
better managing existing resources.
Instead of creating a full Kubernetes
cluster like EKS or a KS you
actually can use virtual cluster
for various purposes because its
provisions much faster than regular.
Host cluster or Kubernetes
managed cluster.
You can use it in test dev ci,
but also production wherever
performance is important.
So a little bit more about
technical architecture.
V Cluster creates a pod that
encapsulates Kubernetes binary.
So we have Cube, API server.
We have a data store inside of a pod.
This is where we start with
open source, V cluster.
It's of course very easy to.
Connect V Cluster to existing
Ed, CD cluster or other data
stores outside of the pod for
redundancy and high availability.
We have components such as controller,
manager, API server, optionally
we can in install scheduler.
We are going to obviously
do this during this talk.
And the key component
of V cluster is sinker.
Sinker enables essentially.
Dynamic and con, highly configurable
synchronizing of resources between the
pod of virtual cluster and host cluster.
This opens up all kinds of interesting
scenarios, but for now, it's important
to know that this works like that.
So host cluster will provide.
At the beginning, all services think
of them as shirt, low level services.
Again, we can have V cluster running
in different modes and have their
own services, but for the sake of the
stock, we can think of host cluster as
providing a base of the shirt services.
So we have API server.
Which is fully k Kubernetes compliant,
which is about a hundred megabytes.
So the whole virtual cluster port would
be about four, 400 megabytes or so or
even less depending on the installation.
So the key insight here is that
we use containerized control
plane with intelligent resource
sinking back and forth between the
virtual clusters and host clusters.
Little bit more about Syner.
Syner runs in a reconciliation loop,
so it's bidirectionally synchronizes
resources running inside of virtual
cluster, which means they talk to Cube
API running inside of virtual cluster
Pod and talk to QAPI running in the host.
API pod Syner does things like making
sure there are no name collisions,
synchronizing various resources.
All this is very highly configurable.
We'll look at it later a little bit.
Coming back to GPUs obviously
AI is the current hype and.
Most of the resources, most of the
workloads that run on gpu, SRAI.
But not only, so obviously we have
model training, things like fine tuning,
lms, deep training, base training.
This is, can be extremely costly.
And this will run.
For weeks or months on end,
depending on the model.
And this utilizes GPUA hundred percent.
So in this case we would have specialized
equipment that needs to run on GPU.
So that's one use case, stable diffusion
image generation, but also inference.
All of us now interact with ai.
So whether we do this through API
or web interface inference would
also be mixed workloads based
off of GPU and CPU resources.
But it's not only ai.
We have also video processing
and all kinds of GPU heavy.
Processing that still
requires GPUs as well.
Depending on the workload, it
can be also to a hundred percent.
We have Cuda development
Jupyter Notebooks.
All kinds of older workloads
that Kubernetes can help us run.
And finally, scientific
computing with batch processing.
And we can utilize GPU
here very effectively also.
So GPU workloads are not only about ai.
Obviously we are focusing on AI on this
talk, but there's a lot of legitimate
use cases where we would like to run
GPU workloads and use Kubernetes to
help us schedule them and manage.
So just for fun, we are going
to deploy a very simple pod and
we'll see how V Cluster can help
us with synchronizing this pod.
So this pod is just a really silly
demo to show what we can do with GPU.
So you can see now the port has
been deployed and since this is
a recorded talk, you will not
unfortunately have access to this link.
But if you will run this
presentation by yourself, you will
be able to also see this link.
So we have used service called NRO
to essentially create this pod.
And here we can scan the QR code.
I will do this on my phone
and we are gonna have some fun
here with the demo in a second.
So now for the demo, we're just
going to see how GPU scheduled web
application can run AI inference.
So here we have different kus For now we.
Didn't generate any kus.
This is my favorite topic
site reliability, engineering.
I'm generating on my phone haiku now.
And we can see AI is helping
us create this various horror
stories, haiku, like poems.
Obviously this is mix of inference
from ai, but also runs on my kind
cluster utilizing GPU as well.
So it's not that hard to also mix
and match various resources as
well as various types of workloads.
Wrong context.
Pots vanish into devoid 3:00 AM despair.
That's very relatable.
All perfect.
So this was the G Ps. Let me
just swap to this real quick.
So now I. Let's talk a little
bit about how would we upgrade
schedulers in production.
If you have host cluster set up and
you use any scheduler, we are obviously
talking about the Kubernetes AI scheduler.
You will need to upgrade it at
some point and it will it can be a
significant risk when there's a lot of
teams depending on the same scheduler
version, so testing, it must be.
Significantly more disciplined.
We need to have a very good rollback.
Procedures and teams are often
blocked on a single scheduler.
Maybe there is a new version
of, in our case, k, a scheduler
that the teams are waiting for.
And we are going to go
through the upgrade process.
So let's talk a little bit about risk.
So if we have a single scheduler on
a big cost cluster where we share the
same scheduler across multiple teams, if
there's a bug in a new scheduler version,
obviously all the polls that depend on it
will crash or pending being pending state.
And the recover time depends
on, what are we going to do?
What is the problem?
So it might be a few hours, it might
be more we, at this point we might
be able to revert the change and
be okay with it, however because we
are using host cluster deployment.
We use typically CRDs for
managing the installation of the
scheduler and related operators.
If this goes wrong and there's a
namespace corruption or CRD corruption.
This can be very costly.
So I've seen scenarios where CRDs of
operators that using Kubernetes manage
external resources like databases or
infrastructure were incorrectly upgraded.
And this resulted in data
loss or, some older disasters.
So this is a critical risk scenario that
we have to take under consideration.
And of course, the bigger the
cluster is the larger the amount
of teams that we are serving, then
the more critical this becomes.
Version mismatch is
similar to scheduler bugs.
Maybe our pods require a feature that is
in specific version, so we have to test
all of them before creating an upgrade.
And finally maybe a new version has
a resource leak, something that is
difficult to detect instantly, but
after it will be deployed, we will
maybe detect it in a few days or hours,
depending on our observability setup.
So according to New Relic 2024 report,
the enterprise downtime cost can be.
Up to 1 million per hour, obviously,
depending on the size of the company.
So we definitely want to avoid
having upgrades of critical
infrastructure like Kubernetes
schedulers and hopefully be able to
compartmentalize it and isolate it.
So that's where can help.
You can think of virtual cluster
Pod as something that encapsulates
your scheduler inside of it.
So we install special we
set up special setting.
You will see it in a moment.
And what it results with is that
we can start from single visual
cluster, we can schedule some pos.
Just using this very isolated and small
blast radios and perform AB testing,
making sure that the new version of
the case scheduler in our case is
correct and everything works well, which
also limits the cost of the testing
infrastructure significantly because
we can have a very small cluster and
just have several virtual clusters
kind of testing various scenarios
that are important for our business.
So the idea here is that virtual
cluster will create an isolated
Kubernetes cube, API and other machinery
including Kai Scheduler inside of it.
So we don't need to additional
host cluster for testing at all.
We can do this right in production
because it's all isolated.
So one more time,
reiterating on the risks.
We can obviously there are other risks,
like we slow down innovation because
the teams must wait on the upgrades.
And all of all upgrades in Kubernetes
are pretty costly and stressful.
So how can we cluster help?
I'm going to run this
in the background and.
To talk a little bit about how V Cluster
uses the configuration file that we see
here at the Top V cluster essentially
provides us a very highly customizable
way of synchronizing various resources
back and forth, but also creating virtual
clusters in a way that serves our needs.
So this first group of settings.
Make sure that if we want to use a host
cluster scheduler, like in one of the
demos we want to use the set owner flag,
which essentially tells Kubernetes or V
Cluster specifically not to take ownership
of the deployed pulse in the V cluster.
This is how Kubernetes works
by tracking ownership plugs.
In the second demo, we want to make sure
that our control plane, which is the
Kubernetes API and Kubernetes machinery
that we deploy inside of virtual cluster
Pod also has virtual scheduler enabled.
And thanks to this virtual scheduler
enabled, we can use Kai Scheduler.
And you, as you'll see later,
we need some other settings.
We need to be able to synchronize nodes
from host and also runtime classes
so that we can synchronize n video
runtime class as well as node labels.
So we will see how, we can use it just to
target only special nodes that are labeled
with the GPU so that our future cluster
synchronizes those things correctly.
So the benefit is obviously that we
will now have independent Kai scheduler
versions, so you can think of it.
Each team can come with their own.
Scheduler version.
We have an older version here,
seven 11 or nine two or others.
So that's already a huge benefit.
Now we completely isolate scheduling
so we can target different
no pools and different nodes.
And we achieved sch autonomy by teams.
And this of course.
If you add a little bit more advanced
use cases that VLA supports, you can
schedule on all kinds of infrastructure
and you can support you can support
very flexible multi-tenancy scenarios.
Let's see if this works correctly.
So we still have some problems.
Which image?
This is probably will take a moment.
Because of my connection.
Oh, now it's running.
But you can see we are inside of virtual
cluster here and we have actually created.
This new virtual cluster
with all the settings.
So we don't have any demos here.
We don't have any pods running.
But I just wanted to
show you that this works.
So this command Create Kai Isolated,
created a new virtual cluster using
those settings that you can see here.
And I opened Canine s, which is a,
just a terminal Kubernetes viewer
to show you that we are connected
currently to the virtual cluster.
Okay, so now if we refresh
this, you can see that we are
connected to our virtual cluster.
It's a pretty long name that we
cluster builds based off of various
variables, but we are essentially
running inside of my kind cluster.
There is an actual virtual
cluster running there.
So just a quick recap.
We cluster components.
We have an API server, which is
a normal Kubernetes cube, API.
We have a syner, which enables us to
be directional syncing, and it's at the
heart of how virtual cluster work we have.
A. Our complete isolated backend.
In our case, it's SQL Light.
As I mentioned earlier.
You can also use set CD and you can
also use external backend so that we
have high availability and redundancy.
And in our case, we are going to
soon install the Kai Scheduler
for independent scheduling.
So currently our virtual cluster.
Which is this pod uses 370
megabytes and 4.6 media CPUs, and
we have the database right here.
Okay, perfect.
So now we will make sure we are connected
to RV cluster and inside of it we are
going to install the Kai Scheduler.
So let's do this right now.
So you can see we have
connected to virtual cluster.
It gives us friendly warning here
that there's a newer version,
but we are already operating
with the correct version.
So what I am doing now, I am
installing the same Kai scheduler
that we have on our host cluster.
But I'm installing it
inside of virtual cluster.
So we are moving one level of
abstractions up, and I'll show you
in a second how it looks in a pod.
But from our perspective, you can
install inside of the cluster anything.
It's a normal Kubernetes cluster.
You can install a web app
like we've seen earlier.
You can install scheduler like
in our case or other components.
This is done and now we
can see how it works.
So we've connected again to our
virtual cluster here, as you can see
by the context name, and you can see
that we have now several components
from Kai Scheduler, which is Port
Grouper Q Controller, and others
running inside of our review cluster.
Okay, this is great.
So let's do a quick recap.
We now have.
High scheduler inside of virtual
cluster with A GPU sharing.
So we should be able to install some
kind of GPU demo and make sure that
we are actually able to schedule pods
from this demo on our virtual cluster.
So how are we doing it?
There are several things that
we have to configure inside of
our pods, so you can see here.
First of all, we are labeled it with
appropriate queue from Kai Scheduler.
I have created it earlier.
So this is Case Scheduler internals,
but this one is interesting.
Inside of Case Scheduler, we
use fractional GPU scaling.
So in this case, 20% of GPU
can be taken by this pod.
So GPU Demo two and 10% of GPU
can be taken by GPU demo one.
And another important setting
here is schedule name.
We are selecting case scheduler
and runtime class and video.
So those bots don't do anything
interesting due to sleep, but we are able
to schedule them inside of the cluster.
So let's give it a try.
I'm going to apply those things and we are
currently connected to a virtual cluster.
I'm making sure I'm applying the
queues, and I just applied those two
pos that we've seen earlier, and as
you can see, they correctly take the
fraction of the GPU as we configured.
So this was pretty easy.
So now let's imagine that we want to.
Change our Kai Scheduler version or
maybe we did just a simple experiment.
We install all those pos, we
tested it, we've installed
Kai Scheduler and we are done.
So v clusters are very ephemeral
if you want them to be.
It's very easy to create a V cluster pod.
We've seen this is around 300 megabytes
and a very small fraction of CPU.
And you can quickly delete
them if you're done with them.
That's why they're so helpful.
When you do AB testing or when you
upgrade various components, you can
use virtual clusters to test behavior.
And here we can see in 39 seconds, we
were able to completely remove virtual
cluster as we are done with our testing.
So let's demo one more thing.
So imagine you have, you're supporting
maybe machine learning team that
needs a specific new Kai version.
But the research team is
still stuck on the old one.
So you definitely don't want to upgrade
the host cluster scheduler version.
And also dev team uses the
default host cluster scheduler.
They don't really care about any version
here, and we are able to support.
All three use cases simultaneously.
So first of all, let's create
two new virtual clusters.
We are creating one for team
stable and one for team beta.
Both of those virtual clusters are
going to be separate pods, which you
know by now, and we just have the same
configuration, just with different names.
Okay.
So now if this is done, we can actually
connect to each of those clusters
and we can install Kai Scheduler
version different per each cluster.
So in our case, team stable
have 0.7 version, and Team
Beta has 0.93 and we are now.
Doing like an AB testing.
We are creating two separate scheduler
versions and we are, once this is done, we
are going to disconnect from the virtual
clusters and we are going to explore
how it looks on the host cluster itself.
So while this is still running it'll take
a moment to install and we will soon be
able to, test the virtual cluster test the
host cluster and see what happened here.
So this is still going, and we can
now connect to each virtual cluster
that we deployed and we can create the
same demos that we've seen earlier.
So pod one and PO two.
We can of course, imagine
that those are different pods.
Maybe they have different allocation here.
Maybe we are using completely
different allocation strategy
for other V clusters and so on.
Other virtual clusters
and so on and so forth.
This shows the flexibility that virtual
cluster provides us alongside the Kai
Scheduler and can give us this really nice
middle ground for supporting various teams
without having a headache of upgrading
the Kai versions or other components.
So this is done and the
result of this is that we have
currently two V glasses running.
One team better.
One team stable.
They both run on 0 27 virtual or
cluster version, and we've achieved
isolation that we talked about.
So let's look at how it is
actually on the host cluster.
So remember, our host cluster is
just a kind cluster running clock
on my machine, but this can be.
Any cluster managed cluster
bare metal future cluster does
not require any special setup.
It would work anywhere because this
is just a Kubernetes distribution.
So here we can see the
future cluster pods.
So we cluster team beta in,
team stable, they're running,
and those pos are going to.
Our cube, API and if somebody wants to
connect whether using cube kettle or V
cluster CLI or just consume web app or any
other workload virtual clusters running
here will provide the isolation level.
And here we can, of course,
other components from the
previous demos as well.
What we have achieved,
let's bring it home.
From my perspective, I think as platform
engineer or SRE, that's where I've worked
for most of my career, and I know that.
Upgrades and updates are always
painful, especially in distributed
systems like Kubernetes.
Those things are not glamorous.
They are behind the scenes, but
they have to happen and they are
very stressful and often costly.
They require a lot of planning and
errors or risk that they carry can
be very significant to the business.
So testing, scheduler, upgrades.
We, instead of creating a new host
cluster, maybe a new EKS or having a
test environment that we have to pay
for, which would typically take several
hours, we limited it to few minutes when
we were able to create a separate virtual
clusters and install scheduler there while
configuring V cluster in a specific way.
So we've reduced the risk literally
to 0% because if something doesn't
work in our future cluster, we
don't care which is deleted.
And there's no impact on
other production workloads.
All backing changes we've seen
from potentially several hours.
We were able to lower this
time to about 39 seconds.
We just deleted the virtual
cluster and nothing happened.
And my favorite, we've enabled
very strong AB testing.
So we can now see which versions work.
We can gradually introduce them and we can
split this IB testing across time as well.
So from pretty high risk if we would
be using if we would be upgrading
scheduler in place, in host cluster,
we went to a very low risk or
almost zero per team schedulers.
This is obviously.
Multi-tenancy benefit.
But other than that, we were able,
we wouldn't have to essentially talk
to the teams and making sure that
we have this middle ground version.
We can essentially.
Satisfy each team's need for specific
virtual cluster and Kai scheduler
version, which is super powerful.
And as is as an SE I'm always amazed
that this works and makes this blast so
small and in the same time enables me
to serve the teams that I'm taking care
of in exactly the versions and software
that they need without impacting others.
And we've also seen that even our
simple demo can use proper GPU sharing
and you could run it at home if you
have a powerful enough computer on
environmental, or of course, in the
business application at scale as well.
So let me just change
the settings real quick.
A little bit of resources here.
You can go to v cluster.com/docs and
there's a dedicated article about
using Kai Scheduler with V Cluster, or
you can explore order configuration.
There's also a case scheduler
page on GitHub as well.
And the specific integration
with Kai Schedule, as I mentioned
earlier, please join our Slack.
We would love to have you and talk
about Kai V Cluster or any other topics
related to multi-tenancy and Kubernetes.
You can connect with me on LinkedIn.
I would love to hear your experiences.
With similar setups and how
you're using whatever tools
you're using to help yourself.
We have also Office Hours, which is
an event hosted by our marketing team
which can give you first experience
with future Cluster and it's technology.
And this is in our Lage events page.
Perfect.
So that's it.
I hope you enjoyed it.
Again, please feel free
to contact me on LinkedIn.
I would love to chat with you about
virtual cluster and related technologies,
multitenancy and other things.
Please feel free to reach out.
Thank you everyone and have a
great rest of the conference.