Hello everyone.
I hope you are enjoying
the conference so far.
Let me introduce myself.
I am Manisha San Gupta and I have
spent around 18 years in the world
of technology, of which more than a
decade, I work at the intersection of
finance and technology modernization,
helping organizations mostly modernize
their systems while still keeping
trust and risk as their top priority.
Today I'll be covering my topic,
securing AI driven finance.
Before I start, lemme ask a question.
Have you ever heard about this?
A popular smartphone smart home app
that use of AI in the cloud to detect
unusual activities like, notifying you
if someone enters your house, such as.
To make the system scalable, the
AI model runs on a cloud platform
and communicates over public APIs.
One day, a user unknowingly exposes their
API key by syncing with a third party app.
And guess what?
A hacker discovers it and starts
sending queries to this a IP learning
patterns about how the home is empty,
how and when the home is empty.
Now what happens, et cetera.
Suddenly this very technology that's
meant to protect the user becomes a tool
for inclusion, all because cloud native
AI wasn't secure enough end to end.
Now, when I thought about this, it hit me.
The real threat isn't
always the big obvious hack.
It's the quiet patterns
that we often overlook.
As financial institutions, we experienced
world revolution in modern world,
while AI systems now power fraud,
detections, credit scoring, trading,
customer engagement, et cetera.
At the same time, cloud native
architectures like containers
and microservices are replacing
our traditional systems.
This creates opportunities, no
doubt, but also raises risks like
financial losses, reputational damage,
regulational penalties and whatnot.
Evolution of AI in finance
has come a long way.
Detections sophisticated machine
learning models now analyzing
millions of transactions per second.
Enhanced capabilities learning are
powering personal services in rapid
speed and functionality out basis.
Guess what?
Security.
And then that leaves us with blind spots.
Cloud native technologies such as
Kubernetes, microservices, even driven
architectures, and say, serverless
computing allow numerous flexibility,
no doubt, and scalability, starting
with flexible deployment, loosely
coupled development options near
real time processing and et cetera.
But at the same time, they also create
risk limiting visibility into model
behavior, poor testing of advers
scenarios, weak governance in place, and
too often a focus on speed over security.
These threats are clear
and growing every day.
Advers attacks that treat can
models into making bad decisions.
In fact, one of the most dangerous
threats come from adversial attacks.
This involves carefully crafted
inputs designed to fool the AI model
into making mistakes while still
looking very legitimate to human.
Imagine a fraud detection system where
an attacker could craft transactions
like the AI believes are safe.
While in reality, they are frauded
and as methods evolve, attackers don't
even need insider knowledge anymore.
Black attacks, black box attacks now can
succeed even with limited information.
Data poisoning.
That corrupt training data
sets is another problem.
Subtle but devastating.
Attack is data poisoning during
training, attackers sleep,
malicious data into data sets.
The learning process
itself from the starting.
For instance, a poisoning credit score
model might unfairly discriminate
against a certain group of people
while still looking very effective.
Overall, such attacks can persist
unnoticed for really long period
of time, quietly undermining
both fairness and compliance.
Model extraction or inversion
that steals algorithms and
sensitive data is also increasing.
Attackers can reverse engineer the
AI models by analyzing the outputs.
What do they do?
They extract the sensitive data such
as customer spending habits, our
prietary trading strategies, et cetera.
This is more than a breach of security.
I say this is a breach
of privacy and trust.
And with AI models increasingly
offered via APIs, the attack
surface expands dramatically.
Let's not forget cloud vulnerabilities
itself, like container escapes
or configurations, et cetera.
Kubernetes has become the
backbone of cloud native
finance, but it's complex and.
Complexity invites risk.
These configured, role-based
access control can give
attackers access privileges.
Container images from public repositories
may already include vulnerabilities in it.
Weak network policies can allow
lateral movement between containers.
When everything is interconnected,
one small misstep can open
the entire cluster to attack.
Containers, Kubernetes and ephemeral
infrastructures definitely bring
flexibility to us, but also brings
complexity overly permissive, access
misconfigured roles, and the difficulty
of monitoring short-lived containers
makes it very hard to secure AI workloads.
This means.
Auditability and rapid
response are major challenges.
Here is a real world fraud
detection attack scenario.
Imagine this attackers compromise
a developer's account exploits
weak network policies, corrupt
transaction data, pipelines and
launchers, real transactions that can
successfully bypass fraud deductions.
All this could happen without
raising any alarm if security isn't
embedded throughout the system.
Or take trading systems, adversarial
study algorithm outputs so they
can reverse engineer the logic and
manipulate the market in front.
Run the institutions own trades.
In distributed cloud native
systems, such manipulations can
very well look like normal activity,
making detections even harder
where comes the human factor?
Yeah.
Humans are another important
factor in this equation.
Technology isn't the only risk.
Human factors play a major role.
Data scientists focus on
accuracy, not security.
Common oversight can happen like
using unvalidated public data sets,
insufficient data sanitization, et cetera.
Developers may even overlook secure
practices in shared environments, overly
broad permissions, vulnerabilities
in open source libraries, et
cetera, can come into the picture.
DevOps.
May cut corners under pressure.
Performance over security.
Rapid development testing cycle
can lead to cutting these corners.
Lastly, critical skill gap is present.
There is a global shortage right
now of professionals who are skilled
both in AI and cybersecurity.
Do.
How do we build resilience?
In this case, four pillars
that we have to abide by.
Zero.
Trust.
Yes.
Zero.
Trust across all AI pipeline is essential.
Strong model governance with versioning
and security checks must be in place.
Robust data security can ensure
integrity, privacy, and lineage tracking.
Infrastructure security in place
with defense indepth principles
tailored for AI can help.
In short, we need to establish
multilayer defense system.
No single security measure is enough.
We need defense in depth,
application security, data
security, AI specific controls,
infrastructure, security, everything.
By layering defenses, we can protect
our AI driven finance evolution.
As AI takes a center role in
security, it's not enough for
our models to be accurate.
They must also be explainable.
Implementing explainable AI or AI
allows us to understand why a system
flags a thread, helping build trust.
Speed up investigations
and reduce false positives.
Insecurity, clarity isn't just a feature,
it's the necessity in that front.
Xai is a powerful ally for us.
It also helps us detect anomalous,
expose hidden biases, and meet
any regulatory requirements.
However, we need to be very
careful with that as well.
As it must be implemented
cautiously balancing, transparency,
performance, and security.
We need to think about multi-layered
defense for anomaly detection as well.
Security must work across
layers, infrastructure, model,
behavior, and data layers.
By correlating anomalies,
say network spikes.
With model drifts and data shifts,
we can distinguish benign glitches
from genuine coordinated attacks
Beyond technology, governance is must,
risk management should be in place
for both technology and business risk.
Define clear accountability and
ownership for development, deployment,
monitoring, maintenance cycles.
Continuous audit and compliance should
be in place to safeguard, include
specific provisions for AI related
security events, ethical safeguards,
ethical safeguard procedures should be
established as well, like bias testing.
And fairness, evolutions, et cetera.
These frameworks keep institutions
secure, compliant, and trusted
To move forward, organizations must
assess current systems and their risks.
Prioritize critical systems, high
income, high impact vulnerabilities.
Choose technologies that are
compatible with cloud native needs.
Important human factor, develop
skills and possibly create new teams
focused on AI and security together.
And also we must prepare for
future challenges such as quantum
threats, evolving regulations,
and an expanding AI a surface.
With this, I will conclude my talk.
I hope you enjoyed.
This session and I hope you
enjoy the rest of the conference.
Thank you.
And you can reach out to me in LinkedIn.
Look up Manta.
I am based in New Jersey and thank
you again for listening to Mike.