Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Conf42 and welcome to
my session on ballerinas on lake,
which is, we are talking about
code to cloud mastering communities
deployments with ballerina.
And I'm going to discuss about the code
to cloud journey, the challenges, as
well as how application development
and also the deployments can be
simplified by using ballerina.
First of all, let me introduce myself.
I'm Anupama Pathiragi, currently working
as director and head of engineering.
at WSO2 and I'm leading the development
efforts of Ballerina as well as
the developer relations effort.
So without taking much time,
Let's start the discussion.
So I thought of starting
the conversation with this.
So this is an AI generated image.
You can see there's an
application developer.
And also there are so many
complexities around him when
it comes to the deployment.
There are cloud components and
there are many different endpoints.
applications, services, which are
connected together and also the
deployment aspects and the things
were deployed in different places.
Then you might wonder why the
application developer has to think
about all these things, whether the
application development and deployments
are two separate things, but actually
in the reality, it's not the case.
So the journey from code to cloud, we
have to think about how applications
are developing When we think about
the cloud as well, because with the
rise of the cloud native applications,
things have evolved and transformed
actually how we build applications as
well as how we deploy the applications.
In the modern application
developments, we need integrations.
It's an unavoidable part because we
have to talk to multiple different
services, endpoints, and having
seamless integration is key thing.
And also scalability aspects and
reliable deployment strategies.
All these are key components
in application development
in the modern world.
So Kubernetes has emerged as a standard
for gestating the complex cloud
deployments and also it's simplifying most
of the deployments and almost everything.
So this process like planning the
application, Implement it, build it,
test, release, deploy, operate, and
finally monitor, all these are connected
and there should be seamless process.
That's why we say cloud code to
cloud is very important when it comes
to modern application development.
And also, although cloud deployments are
comparatively easy, there are so many
challenges in the cloud integrations.
The first thing is multiple services.
Cloud integration means we have to
involve or talk to different services
and interact with different APIs and
those will have to work together.
And this inherent, complexity
imposed by these services and data
formats protocols we have to handle.
And also the dynamic environments
when it comes to the deployments
because cloud environments are highly
dynamic with containers, autoscaling,
and also microservices, how the
security is handled and so on.
And also the configuration overhead.
Managing deployment configuration is a
key thing in the cloud deployments and
how we autoscale and how we monitor.
Those things can be time
consuming if we have to manage
all these configurations manually.
And also the security compliance, ensuring
the data is flowing securely and also
the compliance requirements are achieved.
Likewise, there are so many things
when we, when we, when we think about
the cloud or integration applications.
So that means application
development is not isolated.
We have to think about all
these challenges as well as the
deployment aspects when designing
and implementing the applications.
So in today's session, I'm going to
discuss how ballerina can help you, with
this thing, not just the development
and also the deployment aspects.
So first of all, what is ballerina?
In high level, it's technology for
simplifying cloud integrations.
Let's look at a little bit more details.
So it's an open source cloud
native technology, which is
optimized for integration.
In a way we can think of it as a
programming language as well, but more
or less it's a platform for integration.
It's developed by WSO2.
It's an open source project,
completely open source project.
And the first version is released.
in February 2022, which we called
Paladin Aswan like version.
if you think about the key
thing, key aspects, it has rich
ecosystem of different services,
data formats, and connectors.
And also it has both textual
representation as well as graphical
requisite representation as sequence
diagrams and flowcharts, which is
very much helpful when it comes to
maintainability of the application.
And also it has many safe to primitives,
which helps the developers, for example,
efficient concurrency mechanisms.
The compiler itself can detect some data
races during the compile time because it
is very difficult to handle these data
races and, concurrency related problems
in the runtime because integration
applications are inherently concurrent.
And if we had to deal with concurrency
issues, it's not that easy.
Thank you.
So this is a brief
overview about Valarina.
So let's look a little bit deeper.
So it's all about cloud
native integrations.
And I said it's a programming language,
but it's not just a programming language.
It's more than a programming language.
It's a full framework.
So if you compare it with other
languages, many like C Java, Go, etc.,
Valarina syntax can fall into
the same family of syntaxes.
We can think it's a programming
language, but which is highly
optimized for, integration needs.
We can do any general purpose
application development using Valerina,
but when it comes to integration
application development, there are
so many abstractions and other,
tooling capabilities and so on to
make the developer's lives easy.
So the abstractions are the
important or playing key thing here.
right level abstractions, having the
right level of abstractions is very
important because It will improve
the developer productivity and
understandability of the code as well
as the maintainability of the code.
And also this is not a research
product and it's heavily used
in production environments and
it's an open source product.
Anyone can freely use it as well.
There's a huge open source
community around us and we
are working collaboratively
with open source community.
So I say Balena provide the right
abstractions for integration.
There are three levels,
or three types, actually.
First thing is data.
When it comes to integration
applications, data is a key thing,
because we have to represent data.
We have to think about different
data types, formats, and how we
manipulate data, and how we communicate
data from one service to another.
Likewise, data plays a key role.
So Valerina provides so many
abstractions, data type support,
and type checking, serials.
semantics to make it easy and also the
network representing the network, how
we define client, how we define service
beyond different network protocols.
All these things should be
very easy without going into
the very low level details.
The application developer should be able
to get their network requirements done
very easily and also the concurrency.
As I mentioned before,
the concurrency safety.
During the application
development itself can be.
Very helpful, when it comes
to integration applications.
So there are three stages mainly
in the application life cycle.
First thing is the deployment
and the maintenance.
And after that, we had to
think about deployment aspects.
And finally, the monitoring
or the runtime aspects.
So let's quickly go
through all these things.
And I will showcase
these in my demo as well.
But before that.
Let's go through some high level
overview of all these aspects.
So if we look at the development
and maintenance, what we are
talking about is a full life cycle
of the application development.
Since ballerina is A language,
we can use VS Code as the IDE
and with the familiar tool set.
So you can commit the source code
to a preferred source control system
like GitHub, GitLab, whatever,
and also can use existing CI, CD
processors and deployment can be done
into any environment that you want.
And when it comes to the runtime aspects
of monitoring, logging, et cetera, you can
connect your existing tools and systems.
to the running ballerina applications.
So if you think about how you start
with ballerina first, you have
to create your ballerina package.
So there's a CLI
associated with ballerina.
Once you install ballerina.
You can go to ballerina.
io website and get the download install
installers of the ballerina distribution.
And once you install it, you
can get the ballerina CLI.
With that, you can create new
packages using ballenew command.
So these are like the big details.
I'm skipping those things as you
can try those things by yourself.
And once you do that initial ballenew
command, you will get a ballerina package.
Which contains the minimum set
of files needed to identify
it as a package and run it.
So it contains bel files, which
are the source code files.
So like any other programming
language, these are the files
where you write your application.
And there are some other
meta files like ballerina.
toml file.
Which identifies a given
directory as a ballerina package.
It contains the metadata about the
package, like the package name,
version, and many other information.
So this is like a
structure of the package.
By looking at this, you should get the
sense that, okay, this is like any other
programming language and how you start a
project and how you start your application
development journey is very simple.
And then the next thing is how we
design our application, especially
the integration applications.
In Ballerina, we have integration
designers for the various protocols.
For example, REST based applications,
you can start by defining services
and then defining resources
and finally add the data types.
Return types and so on.
So here you can see the graphical
view of the service designer.
You can use both code view or either
code view or the graphical view.
Both will do the same thing and
as per the convenience, or what
preference, you can select, either
code view or the designer view.
So that is an easy mechanism for
the initial skeleton development.
And same with GraphQL, you can
design and visualize your GraphQL
applications using GraphQL designer.
Likewise, these service designers
are very much helpful to start with
your application design process.
And after designing your application,
the initial stages and the skeleton,
it is just a matter of developing
your business logic accordingly.
So I mentioned about the graphical view.
And also for all the pro, any programming
application, any application that you
are developing with ballerina, you
will get visual representation as well.
That is in terms of sequence diagram,
you can see a left hand side is
a code view, right hand side is a
visual view or the graphical view,
which is the sequence diagram.
So without looking at the source
code, you can understand everything
by looking at the sequence diagram.
As it says, there are two.
endpoints, GitHub and Google sheets.
And this application is getting some
information from GitHub and then,
some from, Google sheets and writing
to the Google sheet at the end.
So if your application is very complex
or having a lot of source files, lines
of codes, going through each of them
to understand who are the different
endpoint, what are the different
endpoints, how we are going to interact
with each of them is very difficult task.
And with this feature, you can visualize
your application without any additional
efforts because every application that
you develop, you will get automatically,
you will get this diagram automatically
if you are using the VS Code plugin.
So this is very important or very helpful
when it comes to the understandability of
the system as well as, maintainability.
And also you can edit this diagram.
You can see plus buttons,
in the diagram nodes.
Where you can add additional
constructs as needed.
So if you prefer to continue in
the diagram side, you can do it,
but most of the time developers
prefer to use the code editing.
So if you edit the code, that
will reflect in the diagram side.
And also documentation.
It plays a very important role in
the application development and
especially enterprise application
development because those applications.
are having complex code and also
maintainability point of view those
applications should live longer.
So this matter, Bellarina supports
Automatic documentation and you can
see the code comments get appended
to the documentation of your
service or application and there is
sophisticated documentation generation
Framework where you can convert
the ballerina inline commands into
documentation of your application
as API, document API specifications.
So this is an example view of how
the commands got converted into the
application or the documentation.
And the other thing about data
transformations, because in the
integration applications, we always
have to deal with different data formats
like XML, JSON, CSV, and many different
formats and also different, even from
JSON to JSON conversions or XML to XML
conversions can be very time consuming
if you have very large payloads.
In Ballerina, we have data mapper,
which is simplifying this process.
You can use.
you can load the left hand side and right
hand side information from where to map.
To which, construct this is
what we call record in Valerina.
We have a type called record in Valerina,
which is the canonical representation
of all the data types like JSON,
XML can be represented as records.
And then it's just a matter
of mapping the record fields.
And also in between you can do multiple
expressions at multiple expressions
to do additional calculations.
And you can map multiple fields
into one fields like that.
without writing any line of
code, you can visually map and
generate the code automatically.
The next thing is about debugging.
In application development,
you always have to troubleshoot
your application code.
Then that's what we need, debugging.
Since Balogna is a programming language,
you can always use usual debugging
capabilities comes with VS Code plugin.
And use the debugging functionalities
like any other programming language.
Then since Balanizer is an integration
technology, it comes with a
distribution which contains the support
for all of these protocol types.
There are so many protocol types when
it comes to integration applications.
We can, we have to deal with different
types of applications, different
services, different clients, like
gRPC, REST, GraphQL, WebSupp.
FTP and so on.
So Ballerina has support for all
these protocol types and you can
define services or clients as
needed using these protocol types.
Not only these protocol support,
Ballerina comes with Ballerina library,
which contains library packages for
utility functions like time, cache,
things like that, and also packages
to support various protocols.
So all these things comes with
the Ballerina distributions.
And you don't need to do
anything explicitly to have
those things in your application.
Not, not just the connect app, library.
Then what we have is the connectors
because integration application means
you always have to connect with different
systems, different endpoints, SAS
applications, data services, and so on.
Belinda has more than 600 plus connectors,
which can connect seamlessly with
these different types of systems.
And if there's.
A system which we already which we are
not supporting at the moment Generating
a connector for such service also very
easy We have open api tool which can
get an open api specification as input
And then convert it to a ballerina
connectors within very short time.
And then the other thing is handling
Data modeling and persisting is also
an important thing ballerina has
module called persist, where we can
use it to model your data, like entity
relationship diagram that you see here.
You can define the relationship
between your entities and then it will
automatically map to different data
types, data sources like databases.
Redis stores or maybe Google
sheets, or in memory data types,
in memory data stores and so on.
It is like ORM that you can see in
some other languages and this persist
capability is very important or very
helpful when designing applications with,
which has data integration capabilities.
so far I have discussed so
many visual capabilities as
well as tooling capabilities.
If I summarize this, we have various
integration tools built with the
distribute inbuilt, in the distribution,
like EDI tool, which can convert
various EDI formats into the other
data formats and also open API tool to
convert a given open API specification
to a service and vice versa.
And, GraphQL tool, health tool
to work with various health
data protocols and formats.
Likewise, all the required tools or
CLI commands are available with the
Ballerina distribution so that you
can work easily with different data
formats, protocols without looking for
alternatives or different external tools.
After application development, the
next thing is about testing or else
you have to think about test when
designing the application itself.
If you think about test
driven applications, so
it's a very important thing.
And ballerina as a language support
all the testing capabilities, you
can generate test reports and see
the coverage numbers and so on.
So your application will not, behave
unexpectedly if you have better tests.
Then the last thing is
about AI capabilities.
Without AI, now we can't survive in
the modern application development.
Balerna as a language has
a GitHub Copilot support.
If you have GitHub Copilot, you
can see the suggestions like this.
It is very much accurate and, Copilot
is aware of Balerna syntax and so on.
And also we have inbuilt AI assistant.
Which can generate unit tests with copilot
and also document the given Application
code which is very much helpful with
the documentation aspects as well as
testing capabilities And also we have
automap feature, which is also AI built
AI based thing which can map the left
hand side of the construct of the record
into the right hand side Which is very
useful in the data mapper When you are
mapping different data formats and types.
So those are some AI capabilities
that we have introduced to make
the developer's life easier.
so far we discussed the development
aspects and the maintenance aspects.
The next thing is about deployment,
which is the key thing in
today's discussion as well.
deployment point of view, you can
build a self contained jar by using
the build command, and then you
can run it using the run command.
It will create a jar file executable,
which you can use to run the application.
But when it comes to cloud deployment,
Ballerina has designed in a way
that it allows the developers
to write code without thinking
about the deployment platform.
So Ballerina developers don't need to
worry about it because that is very much
too much complexity for the developers.
And that greatly simplifies the
experience of developing and deploying
the application in the cloud.
You can use the Belknap commands and
other tools to generate the required
cloud artifacts without much hassle.
So let's see how that is achieved.
You can create a docker image very
easily using bel build command.
You can see dash cloud
with the parameter docker.
It will create the docker file
with all the required dependencies,
docker image, To use with your
deployments and same with kubernetes.
You can use the same command with
the kubernetes flag A parameter
and it will generate the kubernetes
artifacts Where you can modify if
needed or you can use the cloud.
toml file to configure during the build
time itself So the compile is aware
of the resources and other support
definitions configurable variables
And other things available in your
application code and will generate You
the deployment artifacts accordingly.
And then the final thing is about
operation, how we handle things in
the runtime, but now support, all
observable capabilities, including
metrics, tracing, and logging.
And it can be observable by any
open or telemetry supported tools.
So these are some examples of metrics with
Grafana, and this is tracing with Jago.
And distributed login
also supported with that.
I have covered some key aspects
of ballerina and I hope you got
some understanding about what is
ballerina and how we can use it in
the application development as well
as the various deployment aspects.
So I'm going to do some quick demo
around this so that you will get some
understanding about how ballerina
application looks like and how we can
use it during the development time.
As well as how we can use various
deployment capabilities built
in the banana distribution.
For this demo, I'm using a
very simple service related
to hotel management service.
You can see the highlight hotel
backend service, which is accepting
some incoming reservation request
from the hotel web portal.
And it is contacting the room service
to see the availability of the rooms.
And after that it is written.
Returning the confirmed reservations
after doing some calculations and
few other transformations in between.
So it's a very simple service, but this
will help us to understand how well
now application development looks like.
This is the already developed
hotel management application
that I have described.
So I'm using the VS Code editor with
the Balena plugin installed already.
You can see I have installed the
Balena plugin, which comes with all the
visual features that I have explained.
So once you open your application,
you can see multiple files here.
And these BAL files are where your
application programming code is.
Is at.
So once you open those source files,
you can see the source code lines
And also this is the balanatuml
file that I explained which contains
some metadata about the package and
so on So if you look at the main.
bin file, which contains the source code
of the application Let me go through
some of the abstractions I explained
in my slides So this is the service
abstraction, which is very easy to You
define a service in Valerina because it
is a syntax, Valerina support service as
a first class thing in, language syntax.
And when you attach a service with HTTP
listener, it will become an HTTP service.
And if you attach it with
a GraphQL listener, it will
become a GraphQL service.
You don't need to deal with
underlying complexities.
You can provide additional configuration
parameters to configure your listener.
But other than that, you don't have to
worry about the underneath complexities.
And also that every service
can have resource functions.
And if you look at these resource function
signatures, those are very intuitive
because those looks like normal function
calls where we have a function name,
input parameters, return types, and so on.
And after you design the skeleton of
this application, how the services,
what are the services, What are
the resources within each services?
It is just a matter of, implementing
the business logic carefully.
So all these things comes with the
visual, representation as well.
So if you open up the visual, panel
of the ballerina application, you can
see the summary of your application.
It has, one function, one service.
Many records, many global
variables and so on.
So these are the records that I
mentioned, which is a canonical
format for representing your data.
And when it comes to the service,
you can go to the service designer.
So this is the service designer.
You can see how many resources are there.
What are their types?
HTTP, POST, GET, DELETE and so on.
And you can edit these
resources graphically.
And also you can, use the.
this is some summary.
And if you look at one of these functions,
for example, bookings, you can see the
associated sequence diagram as well.
Let me.
Reduce the size a little bit.
So you can see the full logic and it
is not that interesting because it is
interacting with only one other endpoint.
But if your resource function is
talking to many different endpoints,
data services, databases, and gathering
data, you can see all these things.
As a nice sequence diagram where
you can understand the code easily.
So these are some, interesting
things about Valerina.
And let me expand the source code.
So this is already implemented, simple
service which gets the reservation request
as set of payload, arrays in the payload.
And I'm just iterating it to
check the room availability
with the external service.
And do some conversions in between
using this transform function and then
return that transformed message So if
we look at this transform function that
is also A bit interesting because that
contains the data mapper because I need
to convert one type into another So along
with some other additional calculations
and other things in between for example
You can drag and drop these fields into
each other using the, visuals panel.
And you can see, I combined the first
name and last name using the, expression
editor, and you can do any other
calculation in between if you need.
So this is the Balena data mapper, and
we have auto map feature as well, where
we can, use AI support to generate
these mappings based on the names
of the fields and types and so on.
Now, let's see how we can
run this application locally.
To do that, you can use balerun
command line, balerun command.
It will compile the application
and run it in your local machine.
You can see I have attached
the port 9090, so it will start
the service in the port 9090.
So you can invoke the service.
By using the curl
port 9 to 90 and you can see in the
service path is hotel and let's invoke
a resource like, rooms or bookings.
You can see we don't have any
bookings at the, as of now.
And if we look at rooms, it is.
Let me prettify it.
You can see the room details
response, which is adjacent.
So now the service is up and
running in your local machine.
And also you can use the try it
feature available in ballerina
itself, where we have a swagger
like view to test the application.
You can use the try out command
here and you can see no bookings
and you can get the rooms.
Thanks.
You can use a tryout, execute, you
can see the same response here.
I hope that you got some understanding
about how the Balena code looks like, and
we already compiled it and run it locally.
Now, as the next step, let's see how we
can run the application in the cloud.
Before doing that, let me add one
more resource, that is to check
the readiness of the application
by adding a readiness function.
So to do that, I added
another resource function.
as health readiness, which
is just returning HTTP.
Okay.
Then we need to add this
as a readiness probe.
so to do that, we need to open the cloud.
tuml.
Cloud.
tuml file is a configuration file where
you can use to modify it to, use to
modify the generated cloud artifacts.
You can see we already have
the container image details.
And in addition to that, let
me add the readiness probe.
You can see the values and
parameters are auto suggested.
So I'm using them and
the path is readiness.
And in addition to that, I need to
add the base path as the slash hotel.
Now it's all good.
Let's use the build command
to build the application.
Compile it and then generate
the cloud artifacts.
do that, I'm using the build command
with the cloud option as Kubernetes.
it will compile the source and it
will generate the cloud artifacts.
can see there's some error
in the readiness probe path.
That means the compiler understands
the resource file, the implementation
as well as the cloud toml details.
Let's see what's the difference.
Here we have the name as readiness
and my function name, resource
function name is different.
So let me fix it and quickly
do the belpair command again.
Now you can see the
artifacts are generating.
And finally you can see
the commands to execute.
Before that, let's explore what
happened in our target directory.
You can see under docker.
Now we have the docker file generated with
all the dependencies required to run this.
And also under kubernetes, you
can see the yaml file with all the
details like service versions and
other metadata, number of replicas,
the image name to be used with this
and also the readiness probe details
with the initial delay of 30 seconds.
So now everything is ready.
We didn't write any ml file manually.
All these things were generated
by the command itself.
And we can use the cloud.
toml to configure some
these values if you need.
Now let's try to run this.
I'm using Rancho desktop in my
local machine and before running
this, let's see the docker images.
You can see the hotel API.
With the tag of 1 0 0 is generated
about a minute ago now the Docker file
is available and let's use this command
to deploy the Kubernetes artifacts and
You can see the service created deployment
created and Then let's use this command to
export Or access the service via node port
hotel's this log service is now exposed
as a node port Now, let's see our
kubernetes services and deployments
can see the deployment is created
Let's see the services And the
services are created and you can see
it's mapped to the This port 30517.
Now instead of localhost 9090 port
that I used earlier, which is not
working now, we can use that port
which is deployed in
our Kubernetes cluster
to invoke this application.
Now you can see the same response.
So we have deployed the application
in the cloud without writing any
ml file or without generating
the docker files manually.
So this is basically the end of my demo.
And this will give, I hope this
gave an understanding about how we
can write the application and use
the existing or built in commands
to generate the required artifacts.
With this demo, I hope you got a very
good understanding about how Balerna looks
like and how we can use the various built
in commands to handle the deployments.
I would like to wrap up my
session by introducing you into
the Balerna community as well.
We have a very vibrant community and
active, so you can visit balerna.
io community page.
And get to know various efforts
and community activities, including
tech talks, training, university
programs, and almost all of these
are very much, freely available for
various audience groups and feel free
to join with us in the community.
And these are some images from various
conferences, activities, meet hubs
that we have done in the recent past.
And you can subscribe to our events.
and get, be active on those as well.
And also if you are interested
about learning ballerina,
visit ballerina website.
We have learn examples, learn pages,
and we have a youtube video training
where you can get more in depth or
hands on experience about ballerina.
And also we have ballerina certification
if you are interested in gaining
more knowledge about ballerina.
And If you are using Balena feel
free to raise your questions or any
clarifications in Balena discord
channel as well as tech core flow.
Our community is very active
in those channels and you
will get responses rapidly.
And also if you're open source
contributor, feel free to join with us in
the Balena language hub repository and all
our repositories are open source and you
can be part of the contributors as well.
So with that, I'm wrapping up my session.
Thank you very much for joining with
this session and hope you have enjoyed.
Thank you.