Hi everyone.
I'm honored to be here.
My name is Kiran Otti, and today
I'll be talking about swarming LLM
agents for real time market insight
in cloud native trading systems.
This talk brings together three key areas,
financial markets, large language models,
and Kubernetes native architectures.
My goal is to show you how cloud
native swarming agents can transform
the way we process and act on
financial data in real time.
Okay, let's start with the challenge.
Financial markets generate
more than 2.5 quintillion
bytes of data every single day.
What's more striking is that nearly
80% of this data is unstructured.
Think about news articles, social media
chatter, analyst reports, or SCC filings.
Traditional models struggle here.
They can't keep up with the scale.
They are, don't adapt well to complexity,
and the latency of analysis often means.
Opportunities are lost in trading.
Seconds matter and missing
signals buried in noise translates
directly into missed opportunities.
To address these challenges
we developed self adapting
financial sentiment, Oracles.
It's built as a cloud native framework
designed to ingest massive streams of
unstructured financial data in real time.
It uses warm intelligence,
meaning multi LLM agents.
Each with its own specialization
working together to generate insights.
Think of it as a team of experts,
collaborating instead of single
generalist agent, and importantly,
the self adapting financial sentiment.
Oracle provides privacy,
preserving, federated learning,
powered by homomophic encryption.
This allows institutions to collaborate
without ever sharing sensitive raw data
a must in today's regulatory environment.
Okay.
Now looking at the technical
architecture, at the heart of the
self adapting financial sentiment,
Oracles is the dual model architecture.
Finberg is used to extract precise domain
specific sentiment from financial texts,
such as earnings calls and reports.
Robot large complement it by providing
broad contextual understanding
from market news and social media.
The system runs this containerized
microservices orchestrated by Kubernetes.
HPA handles dynamic
scaling while Kubernetes.
A self-healing ensures reliability.
As a result, we continue, we consistently
achieve sub fortify millisecond latency
even during extreme market volatility.
The agent swarm itself
is structured like this.
We have the news agents which analyzes
breaking news and press releases.
We have the social media
sentiment analysis agents.
Tracking investor conversations
across social media and different
other forums, regulatory filing
agents passes, SEC, filings and
disclosures for critical updates.
Market data agents link the sentiment
to actual price, action and order flow.
Each agent is domain specific, like I
mentioned, but together they provide a
rich multidimensional view of the market.
Because of this distributed
architecture, the self adapting
financial sentiment, Oracles processes
around 1200 documents every second.
Equally important, the end-to-end
latency from ingestion to insight is
still under fortify milliseconds in
the world of high frequency trading
where every millisecond counts.
This combination of throughput and
speed is really transformative.
But how do we bring all
of these agents together?
That's the role of the consensus.
Oracle, it uses a 16 head
attention mechanism to weigh
predictions from different agents.
It applies dynamic confidence
scoring to quantify uncertainty,
and it continuously self calibrates
as the market conditions shift.
This means our predictions
are not only fasted, but also
robust and adaptive in nature.
We've also implemented these self
adapting financial sentiment, oracles
across 47 financial institutions.
Each institution's train models
locally on their private data.
Instead of sharing raw data, only
encrypted model weights as sent
back to the central orchestrator.
This federated setup improved accuracy
by almost 15% compared to isolated
models, all while meeting the strictest
of privacy and compliance requirements.
In terms of the performance metrics,
here's what the system is able to achieve.
We are able to achieve around 95%
directional accuracy, predicting
whether the market goes up or down.
We all also achieved 87% magnitude
accuracy, estimating how the markets move.
21% analyzed returns over five years of
back testing a sharper ratio of 1.67.
A strong measure of risk
adjusted performance.
In short, the self adapting.
Financial sentiment.
Oracles is in just theoretical,
it consistently outperforms
traditional sentiment systems.
All of this is, of course, made
possible by cloud native design.
Each agent runs in a lightweight
container, auto-scaling, adjust
to incoming data surges and STO
service mesh provides a secure,
resilient interservice communication.
And Prometheus monitoring is
used that delivers real time
health and performance metrics.
It's a Kubernetes first design
ensuring both scalability and
resiliency beyond just prediction,
self adapting financial sentiment.
Oracles also act as an
early warring system.
It can identify market stress
events up to 36, 36 hours in advance
with over 96, 90 2% precision.
It also detects coordinated
manipulation patterns.
For example, when the social media
campaign attempts to influence the
market sentiment, this makes it
powerful tool not just for profit,
but also for risk management purposes.
Of course, it wasn't easy.
We faced four key challenges, latency
management, balancing model complexity
with speed, data privacy and compliance.
Meeting the G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A
and other regulations.
The model drift, keeping models
accurate as the data was.
And resource optimization when it comes to
tuning Kubernetes clusters to balance out
cost with performance, these challenges
pushed us to innovate not just in models,
but also in the infrastructure space.
In terms of looking ahead for the future
development roadmap, we are expanding
the self adapting financial sentiment.
Oracles with multi-language support,
cross asset correlation, audio
sentiment analysis from earnings calls.
ESG factor integration and
few other innovative features.
The goal is to make the sentiment the
self adapting financial sentiment.
Oracles not only smarter,
but also future proof.
To summarize swarming LLM agents
outperform single monolithic models.
The cloud native architecture is essential
for the scale and speed of modern trading.
Federated learning delivers
accuracy while protecting privacy.
And the consensus mechanisms ensure
more reliable predictive insights.
Together these elements provide the speed,
intelligence, and trustworthiness needed
for the next generation trading system.
Thank you all.
Please let me know if
there are any questions.