All right.
Welcome everyone to our session on Amazon.
E.
K.
S.
Are also known as Amazon Elastic Compute.
Kubernetes services cost optimization.
I'm Dariush and with me
is my colleague Piyush.
Hello everyone.
We're very excited.
To share some insights on how you
all can optimize costs while running
Kubernetes workloads on Amazon EKS.
My name is p and I'm joining Dru.
We both are dialing in
here today from SoCal.
I'm, yeah, as well here
in the office today.
Zach, so before we dive into cost
optimization strategies, let's
start with a brief overview of.
Amazon EKS.
Piyush, could you give us a
quick overview of Amazon EKS?
Absolutely.
Do we, if we have a slide,
yeah, let's point to that.
So Amazon Elastic Kubernetes
service and you see the high level
architecture diagram here Amazon EKS,
it's our managed Kubernetes offering.
It makes it easy to run Kubernetes on AWS.
without needing to install,
operate and maintain your own
Kubernetes control plane or nodes.
Absolutely.
That's right.
So with Amazon EKS, AWS manages
the control plane components
and you can focus on deploying
and managing your applications.
It integrates seamlessly with
other Amazon AWS with AWS services,
giving you a secure and scalable
environment for your workloads.
Yes, and as organizations adopt Kubernetes
for container orchestration, Amazon
EKS offers a reliable and efficient
way to run Kubernetes at scale.
Absolutely.
But with great power comes
great responsibility.
So in this case, potential for high cost.
If not managed properly, I would say
Kubernetes abstracts away much of
the underlying infrastructure, which
can sometimes make Cost management,
a challenge, would you agree?
Yes, of course, and that's where
a cost optimization strategy comes
into play Understanding where costs
are incurred and how to manage them.
It's crucial for running
efficient operations Exactly.
Now, in today's session, we'll
explore tools like CubeCost for cost
visibility, and we'll discuss scaling
solutions like Cluster Autoscaler and
Carpenter to optimize resource usage.
There was a keynote back
in reInvent 2023 by Dr.
Werner Vogel where where he emphasized
the importance of building cost aware
workloads, particularly relevant
for Kubernetes cluster on AWS cloud.
Yes, I remember watching that ocean.
That's what inspired our session as well.
When it comes to kubernetes cost, maybe
if you can transition to the next slide,
that is where we showcase the overall cost
and The control plane cost it's fixed at
10 cents an hour So even when you scale
up your amazon eks cluster to hundreds and
thousands of node, there's no additional
control plane cost Which is great the
main cost component is on the data plane
which comprises of Workload cost which
includes your pods your containers your
auto scaling parameters and we'll cover
some of that In this session next within
the data plane for some workloads, you
incurred network cost, which includes
for data transfer, your elastic container
registry cost, your load balancers and
costs doing your NAT gateway deployments.
And then finally, you incur logging
and monitoring cost on the data plane.
Good points.
Maybe I should, maybe we should go back to
the slide that we had Just the back here.
So when you mentioned the control
plane, I see two boxes here.
Would you say the control plane is the box
on the left hand side and the data plane
is on the one on the right hand side.
So which part is really managed by AWS?
I would say the other one that the
control plane runs on the AWS cloud,
whereas data plane runs in your VPC.
So over here, what we showcase is a
couple of options within data plane.
You have self managed options,
there is a manage options, and
then there is Fargate as well.
So yeah, so it's, so AWS is managing
the the brain of Kubernetes, right?
So to speak the control
plane, the orchestration, and
it's on the right hand side.
And that's where we have the label.
If you can see customer VPC that's
what we mean by the control plane.
Other way around AWS cloud.
Oh, there you go.
Yes.
AWS Cloud.
Absolutely.
I was looking at the left hand side.
So managed self-managed note groups and
managed note groups on my left by customer
VPC and on the right is AWS Cloud.
Alright, so as you can see, this video
this recording is not really scripted.
Alright.
So if you look at the recent CNCF
studies study on the Kubernetes
cost back in December of 2023,
that's something that we looked at.
Yes.
Yeah, if you can move to that
study on the deck, yeah, perfect.
Yeah, the study confirmed that
Kubernetes cost are indeed increasingly
for increasing for many of the
organizations that we work with.
Further, this survey revealed that
a number of human and technology
factors were blamed for the increase
in both spent and unwanted and
unexpected cost in cloud environments.
Over provisioning is by far the most
common issue, likely due to difficulties
in accurately estimating resource needs
in dynamic Kubernetes environments.
Failure to deactivate unused resources was
cited as another issue and the presence
of the technical debt, not to forget.
So the workloads which have not been
optimized for cloud native environments
really leads to inefficiencies.
Piyush, would you agree?
Yes no, I think this is a
very useful survey from a.
Reputed organization cncf I have
some more surveys if you can
go to the next slide I think we
covered this reasons for overspend.
We covered the over provisioning
and the presence of technical debt.
So if you go to the next one where
we look at the tooling survey I'd
say if you look here, cloud native
default tooling came in first, like
AWS cost Explorer in case of AWS cloud
in terms of purpose built tooling for
Kubernetes cost cube cost came in first.
What we see many customers using
KubeCost along with AWS Cost Explorer or
traditional cloud cost management tooling.
So while AWS Cost Explorer will
perform overall cloud cost and
optimization, KubeCost would be
hyper focused on Kubernetes or Amazon
Elastic Container Service, EKS, our
managed offering for Kubernetes.
Absolutely.
Great points here.
All right we talked about the cube
cost, and that's something that
probably we can do a quick overview.
Is that something that
you want to start with?
Or do you want to go into
a demo on a terminal?
Yes.
No, let's bring up the dashboard.
And now that we've set the stage.
Yeah.
If you can discuss more about cost
visibility and why do we need it?
And what's the sense of it?
Yep.
Awesome.
Can you see my screen?
Yes, I do.
Okay, perfect.
So what you see here it's a view
of KubeCast that's been deployed or
rather installed on our EKS cluster.
Now that's a demo version that
we're using, but you can also deploy
this on your own EKS platform.
The reason I'm using the demo,
it's got a lot more features than
I would have with the free version.
Comes into two tiers.
One is the free version
was the enterprise version.
Here, I'm looking at the at this cost.
Yes, you're going to mention something.
Yeah.
No.
So maybe so Darush, what's the challenge
here that KubeCost is addressing?
Is it the busy getting the cost
visibility, understanding where cost is
coming from within the Amazon EKS cluster?
Is that what it is or something else?
Absolutely.
So it's really within EKS or Kubernetes.
It breaks down the cost
by namespace, pod, teams.
If you have set up labels, for
example, for your deployments.
It really, that, and that breaks,
that breakdown is what what some
of our customers are looking for.
Yes, and it's particularly important
because kubernetes resources as some
of our viewers will know they're
very dynamic They can scale rapidly.
So it makes it difficult to track costs
associated with let's say specific
applications specific teams And that's
where that's the space kube cost fills
in or that's why kube cost exists, right?
Yeah, go ahead And moreover, with the
integration of AWS split cost allocation
data, Q cost can provide even more
insights into cost attribution in EKS.
Good.
And for those who may be unfamiliar
with this new term that Darush used,
AWS split cost allocation data, what
it allows for is the distribution of
shared costs like data transfer and EBS
volumes across various AWS resources
giving a more precise cost allocation.
Exactly.
So maybe we should talk a
little bit about AWS split cost.
Allocation data.
Good.
Yes.
Yeah.
Happy to.
So I would say AWS has introduced
some amazing features to help enhance
cost visibility for your Amazon.
Eks cluster including the split
cost allocation data feature.
So this feature, it allows you to break
down the cost of shared resource, like
EC2 instances, networking and storage
into individual Kubernetes workloads.
What does that really mean for you?
Traditionally, if multiple pods
are running on a single EC2
instance, You just see the overall
cost of that instance in a W.
S.
Cost Explorer.
But with a W.
S.
Cost allocation, you can now break
down the cost of that instance and
attribute portion of it, a portion
of it to each workload, if you will.
Based on their actual resource usage,
this makes it easier, a lot easier, I
would say, to identify which workloads are
contributing most to your overall costs.
Yes, I think that's a good point.
And if you were to combine tube
costs, real time visibility.
Where the AWS is split cost allocation.
You get a powerful way to track
and optimize your cost, right?
You'll be able to precisely see
where your spend is going, whether
it's what CPU memory storage network
and it allows you to take the right
actions to optimize your cloud spend.
So together, these tools
give you the level of detail.
You need to make informed
decision about your infrastructure
and resource management.
Great.
Yeah, absolutely.
So next we're going to look at going
back to cube costs and see how it really
helps identify underutilized resources.
Look at some of the recommendations
that you can see on the dashboard.
We'll walk through some of how to
spot some of these opportunities
for optimization and review the
actionable insight cube cost provides.
So let's jump into a quick
demo and see how it works.
All right.
So we can see that we have the
overview for the cube cost dashboard.
Under monitor, you have a number of
filters, and those filters could be
by namespace, nodes, pods, controllers
and containers, or in some cases,
environments and deployments.
We have here some examples of those.
And the more environments you have or the
more departments you have with the labels
deployed, you'll get to see it here.
One area that I really like is
the reports where you can have a
different number of reports created
based on what matters to you most.
And, or, last but not least, the
most important one to me right now
is the savings, where I can see,
as you can see, number of options.
For example, here, right
sizing the cluster nodes.
And if you click on it, it
comes back and there's a lot of
details where we can get into.
But at a high level you can see that, yes,
we are running a series of CPU families
instance families, I should say, and the
recommendations which are most important.
Going back to instance.
Yes.
And I'm just curious, what is cube cost
basing all these recommendations on?
So what data does it have access to?
Is it some specific data within EKS
cluster that it is tapping into and
coming up with this recommendation?
Good questions.
I don't have the insight of how
it really delves into the details
of putting the data but over time,
this is an example of a demo.
If you had installed it on our own, E.
K.
S.
Could be probably looking
at a lot more insight.
I would say it looks at the load and
the load that is running on the E.
K.
S.
And make some intelligent decision.
In one case, we are running, for example,
carpenter carpenter auto scaler, where
it decides the What is the best family
type of easy to instances or compute?
That's really suited for your workload.
But that's a good question.
That's something that you should.
Yes.
No, what I see in the, I was just
speaking at the documentation.
What I see is that there are
a couple of different options.
One it queries metrics from Prometheus, as
some of you may know, it's our open source
monitoring and time series database.
It's installed by default when KubeCost
is installed on an Amazon EKS cluster.
So KubeCost will query
metrics from Prometheus.
In addition.
It uses API calls to retrieve some
public pricing data for AWS services.
And then there are some other integrations
like AWS cost and usage reports to
further enhance the accuracy of pricing
information specific to a given account.
So it relies on all of these
information and then I'm sure
there's some intelligence built in
and that's how it's coming up with
this recommended savings for you.
And You mentioned Prometheus.
I think we also have a managed, I
believe we have a managed service
of Prometheus and Grafano on AWS,
where you can also take advantage of.
All right.
This was a great demo.
Yeah, this was a great demo.
You should have more time to get
into a lot more details, but I
just want to introduce some of the
capabilities that cube cost gives you.
And it's a free there is a free
version that users can deploy on their
EKS platform and really give it a
spin and see how it works for them.
All right.
Next topic we want to talk to is
about auto scaling strategies.
Let me move that away and go back
to our auto scaling strategies.
And we are introducing carpenter
as one option, but we talked about
the cost optimization and, but I
think while visibility is crucial.
Optimizing resource usage is equally
important for cost management.
Let's discuss scaling
solutions in Amazon EKS.
You
should.
Yeah, I can take that.
A lot of folks are a lot
of customers we talk to.
They're familiar with cluster autoscaler.
That's how we started.
And so cluster autoscaler
automatically adjusts the number
of nodes in your cluster based on
the scheduling needs of your pods.
Thanks.
Now, that's helpful, but I
think it has its own use cases.
But in some instances, I see some
feedback where it's somewhat slow in
scaling times and less flexible with
instance type selection, if you will.
Yeah, and we don't make it easy.
We have hundreds of instances, and
they're always launching new instances.
So just amplifies that
limitation quite a bit.
And that's where Carpenter
comes into picture.
It's one of our newer, open source,
efficient node provisioning tool.
It was built by AWS.
And we donated Carpenter to the team.
as part of Kubernetes auto scaling
special interest group SIG.
So Carpenter aims to improve
the efficiency and speed
of scaling operations.
It's Kubernetes native.
And and what I mean by that is sometimes
your Kubernetes workloads, they may
be required to run in certain AZ.
Certain instance types part on
demand so how do you do that?
You need mechanisms like node
selector node affinity gains and
toleration topology spreads Right,
all of these are kubernetes concepts
So carpenter works with your part
scheduling constraints and that's what
makes it kubernetes native Exactly.
Carpenter can provision new nodes
in response to unschedulable pods
within seconds, optimizing for
cost and performance really by
selecting the right instance types.
On the fly.
Yes.
And it also supports features like
consolidation and bin packing which
can significantly reduce costs by
making better use of resources.
So let's jump into a quick Devos
Carpenter in action and see how it's
really operates when we try to scale
up and down some of the resources.
Is that a good time to go
into the terminal perhaps?
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
Maybe if you could start with what's
your starting state, I see two windows.
You can provide some more
background, what it is.
This is essentially the, I have an EKS
cluster deployed on AWS and I've logged
into the, I've set the context for the
cluster that we're using the top window.
It's an EKS node viewer.
It's an open source tool that
you can download and install
on your Kubernetes On your E.
K.
S.
Cluster, and it really gives
you a live view near real time.
I would say view into your E.
K.
S.
Cluster on that first line.
It shows three nodes in the space.
I'm running three nodes and 51
parts on the right hand side.
It gives you an estimated cost off
per nodes per hour and or per month,
which is to some extent helpful.
It's not an exact answer.
Yeah.
Price, but it gives you
an estimate below that.
It also shows you the instance
families that are used both by E.
K.
S.
For the main cluster and other resources
that you need for your deployment.
The screen below just a terminal
screen where and take a look at
You get deploy, and you can see
here I have three deployments.
One is CPU Memory Hungry app, named after
Angry app and next is Inflate and Nginx.
Each one of them, starting
from the top, we have seven
replicas, 13 replicas in one.
So in this case you can scale up the
replicas on the Hungry app, from seven to
something else, So that we can scale up.
So let's say scale up
in late or rather CPU
memory from seven replicas to 125
replicas on while, or I click.
Yeah, before you hit
enter, I'm just curious.
So up in the top window, we see.
Like 48 parts running and then at
the bottom we have three applications
So looks like there are more parts I
think that's an interesting one and
part of it is because carpenter has
visibility into the control plane
and carpenter recognizes kubernetes
resources Which are on the Kubernetes
control plane, and that's where those
additional resources comes into play.
Exactly, because within the within EKS
or Kubernetes in general, they have a
number of different namespaces based
on what applications you deploy and the
namespaces that you as a user you create.
Now within the cube system
namespace on Kubernetes or on EKS.
There are a number of pods
that are spun up to support the
Kubernetes infrastructure, be it
the control plane, the scheduler,
the proxies, the core DNS and so on.
That was a great point you
brought up because looking at the
number of pods and looking at the
screen below, it doesn't add up.
But that's why those are
pos that are not showing.
'cause I'm only looking ads.
A deployment, the number of
deployments that I have got it.
Yep.
So let's scale up your hungry app.
All right.
And as you can see on the top dynamically,
it's creating the parts and wait.
So pending running within a
few seconds or pretty fast.
Yeah, it is pretty fast.
Yeah.
It's pretty fast in terms of response, and
I really took a big number here, Piyush.
Yes.
The demo gods are with us 25 pending.
It's really a simple app, but I can,
we can take a look at some of the
some of the one interesting thing.
The other one is, so of the three nodes,
I see two are on demand and one is spot.
That's interesting to me.
And perhaps if we can Take a look at the
configuration, node pool configuration
because there was something in the node
pool configuration that made pot pointer
decide to spin on demand and spot.
And yeah, for the benefit of our
viewers, if you can bring it up.
I have a couple of deployments.
One is the high priority yaml file,
which essentially shows the deployment.
The other one is the hungry app.
Let's see hungry app.
And so when you say couple of,
you mean you have multiple node
pools and then there is a way to
run them in parallel, assign some.
Wait to it and then, okay, let's
take a look at one, if you want
to hi, just be mindful of time.
I'm not sure how much time we have left,
but in this case we have a note pools.
We have selected specified different
families of instances that are
available to Carpenter and one
on line 40, the operator, the
values are spot and on demand.
So Carpenter can pick and select depending
on the workload that's on Carpenter.
Got it.
And what happens is there is this trade
off for spot where if you just choose
the lowest price, sometimes, You get
a very small capacity pool, a pool
that's almost unavailable, and it's
at a very high risk of interruption.
So what Carpenter does is it uses EC2
fleet API feature, which relies on
price capacity optimized strategy.
So it gives us.
It gives you the cheapest instance
type, but then it doesn't give you the
one which is about to be interrupted.
So there's a bit of balance in
there and Carpenter relies on
fleet API to make that trade off.
Great point.
Yeah that's a great point to bring up.
And we have also a parameter
called weight within Carpenter.
Here I have set the weight for 20 for
high priority workloads versus a lower
number for lower priority workloads.
All right, so let me scale
down in this case and see, okay, scale
down, going back to example five replicas.
And in this case,
if the demand on the application that we
have deployed, the hungry app, it doesn't
really consume a lot of resources, but
if you had an application that would
consume a lot more resources, it would
spin up additional instance family type
like spot instance and if required on
demand instances in the interest of time.
Probably it's a good time to talk
about a few takeaways from our
discussion as we have seen effective
cost or cost optimization in KS.
Involves both visibility and action use.
Yes, and there are tools like
cube cost that you should
give a presentation on that.
And it gets you visibility to
understand where your spend is going.
Very granular level parts,
namespaces and whatnot.
Yep.
And scaling solutions like Carpenter
allows you to act on that information
by optimizing resource allocation in
somewhat near real time, if you will.
Yes.
And what we recommend at Amazon is don't
treat this cost optimization as a one off
thing, something that you do only at the
time of migration or when you cut over.
Continuously monitor your cost,
regularly review your resource
optimization or your resource
utilization and then adopted dynamic
scaling solutions we saw carpenter.
Yeah, and also don't forget the
importance of right sizing your workloads
and cleaning up unused resources.
Small adjustments can lead to significant.
savings over time.
Yes.
And like we discussed cost
optimization, it's an ongoing process.
So stay proactive and leverage
the tools at your disposal.
We showcased cube cost carpenter, but
then, yeah, there are more out there.
All right.
So thank you all for joining us today.
We hope you found this session
valuable and that you can apply these
strategies in your own environments.
Yes thank you everyone and feel
free to reach out to us with any
questions or any further discussions.
And perhaps we can, before we wrap up
and let's do a quick recap if we go to
this slide, do we have a slide on that?
Yes.
Yep.
Do you want me to take it or okay.
Yeah, I can do that.
So as a recap, what we did today
was we we started out looking at the
breakdown of your Amazon EKS cost.
We positioned cube cost as a way
to get granular cost visibility
within your Amazon EKS clusters.
And then we highlighted different
auto scaling strategies and Did a
sort of deep dive demo on carpenter,
which is an efficient cluster
node autoscaler for Kubernetes.
In between, we highlighted how
important it is to ensure that
these cost optimization strategies
are sustainable over a long period,
which requires you to establish
the cost governance, so to speak.
Yeah, that's all we had.
Once again, thank you very much
for joining and see you next time.
Thank you all.