Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 Cube Native 2025.
I'm S Ula.
I work as a principal
full stack engineers.
Today my presentation topic is
architecting resilient risk governance.
Let's go to the today's agenda.
Today we'll introduce the modern
risk landscape and we will discuss.
The challenge with the current system,
and then we will discuss the three
pillars of resilient risk governance.
Once after that, we will discuss the
implementation and adaption strategy.
And finally, we'll discuss
measuring success and the feature.
Let's come to the introduction.
So this presentation is about building
a smart and strong immune system for the
banks and for the financial companies.
So we have three challenges as
part of these like regulatory
complexity, technology evolution,
and third sophisticated threats as
part of the regulatory complexity
rules and reg regulation.
Sir. Frequently changing.
It is difficult to adapt.
And also the second one, technology
evolution, which is very first
and very quick for adapting
the digital transformation
demanding architectural agility.
Third one is sophisticated threats.
The fraudsters are smart and they're
exploiting system vulnerabilities.
That is also another
third challenging one.
Let's come to the fragmentation problem.
Majorly, we have a fragmentation
problem in most companies.
We do have the different departments
like customer department, trading
department, and compliance department.
Each department, they're
maintaining their own dataset.
Because of that, we will have like
major impacts and also nobody can see
the full picture of the data flow.
Because of this, it makes slow down
to identify the risks, and it is
very easy to miss some important
rules and further to overcome.
Enterprise architecture
as a strategic backbone.
Just think of it as a model
blueprint for the entire company.
It connects all the disconnected
parts, making sure data rules and
technology work together smoothly
as one powerful system that is the.
Main advantage with enterprise
architecture coming to three
pillars of resilient risk.
Governances like first pillars,
integrated data ecosystem.
It means it's connected
data, which everyone.
Should share the information instantly.
And second one is adaptive compliance.
As part of that adaptive compliance, it's
like nothing but automatic compliance.
The system checks file
rule breakdown 24 by seven.
And third one is a driven
fraud defense that is like
smart software that learns to.
Spot Nikki Freight.
Let's discuss little deep for
each pillar in our next slides.
See here is the one
integrated data ecosystems.
One is a trading systems, and
another one is a customer data.
Another one is a compliance
platforms and unified risk review.
These all four are majorly.
Further integrated data ecosystems
like this is about breaking down
the walls between departments.
We connect the data from trading
compliance and customers to create
one single real-time dashboard
that shows all the risks clearly.
Breaking down data silos like traditional
approach, isolated departmental
database and manual data reconciliation
and delayed risk vulnerabilities.
Inconsistent reporting standards
for this traditional approach.
I can say the best example is that
three people are in a separated.
In separate rooms and each one trying to
communicate, but they cannot because the
wise is slow and because of that, walls
and three people are in a different rooms.
The wise is messy and the error in the
prawn while talking, while discussing
sharing, but that is a traditional
approach, can say the example and.
Architecture LED integration is unified
data, fabric architecture, real time
data synchronization, instant risk
assessment capabilities, standardized
government governance frameworks for that.
Best example I can say is like
everyone is in one platform and
one room and live group chat with.
Because of that, everyone are in one room.
One group chat so that
what is the outcome?
It is very first and accurate, and
everyone will be on the same page.
That is what it's an perfect example
for the architecture lead integration.
Second one, adaptive compliance framework.
Adaptive compliance framework,
mainly like embedded controls.
And automated reporting, continuous
monitoring, regulatory adoption.
These four are the major things for that.
Here in, instead of having people manually
checking thousands of transactions
for rule breaking, we can build the
rules directly into the system so that
it automatically checks the rules.
And everything.
It generates a report and it gives
alerts immediately if something is wrong.
That is a major advantage with adapting
or automating compliance framework.
Let's go to the third pillar,
which is most more interesting one
AI driven fraud defense as part
of the AI driven fraud defense.
We have four.
One is a. Pattern recognition.
And third one is a realtime analysis.
Third one is a legacy, SY
legacy systems integration.
And fourth one is a human oversight.
So what is that pattern recognition?
If anything happens abnormal behavior,
like you know something differently,
then we can identify using mission
learning algorithms so that the pattern
recognition plays a very vital role.
Realtime analysis if anything
is strange, the realtime
analysis, it'll give the flag.
Coming to the legacy integration,
this AI driven fraud defense if you
integrate our system with the ai, it
automatically works with our world system.
Says that final one is a human oversight.
Human oversight is needed to make
sure the final call on tricky cases.
And what are the implementation
challenges and solutions?
So basically organization
organizational resistance.
Basically the people are
not liking the change.
They just want to continue
with the established process.
So that is one major
challenge, how we can welcome.
Such a challenge.
Only solution is we need to train them
and we need to roll out challenges slowly.
Not like in not everything at once.
Technical depth is another challenging
Legacy systems integration is very
complex compared to modernize technical
things like what is the solution for
legacy systems integration capability.
Complexity is we need to use the modern
connectors to link them step by step.
Another one is cost justification.
Cost justification.
We need to show like how much
we are saving from the less
frauds and how much we are saving
based on the lawyer compliance.
That we need to overcome that.
Another one is phase adaption strategy.
Like we have first four phases.
One is a foundation phase, which
is a very key, and we need to
establish data governance standards
and basic integration capabilities.
We all need to agree
on how to manage data.
And the second one is a integration phase.
Integration phase is a, it needs to
connect critical systems and important
systems, which is a most powerful one.
Another one is a intelligent phase.
Intelligent phase.
We need to turn on the AI and AI models.
The fourth one is a optimization phase.
It makes.
Continuous improvements need to happen
and it keep making it better and bigger.
That's the one.
And measuring the success, key
outcome of this one, like I
can say 60% faster complaints.
Reports that used to take a weeks.
With this, it can take only days.
And GT 5% of the better fraud detection.
We can catch almost all fraud attempt,
and another one is 40% cost saving.
It is a very huge success.
I can say.
We spent less on manual checks and
mistakes, 99% system availability.
The system is always up
and running and reliable.
Conclusion, the future of risk governance.
Basically by using this blueprint,
like enterprise architecture
companies become strong, agile,
and ready for whatever comes next.
They can grow safely, follow rules
easily, and stay ahead of criminals.
Which gives, they may use
advantage over competitors.
Let's take the key takeaways.
Like I can say, enterprise architecture
is the key to managing risks and connector
connect our data to see the whole picture.
EI enhances fraud detection.
And adaption ensures the success.
That's all pretty much
about my today presentation.
It's time for the questions.
If you have any questions, please feel
free to reach out to me through LinkedIn.
Thank you.
Bye-bye.