Hello everyone and welcome
to Con 42 Cube Native 2025.
My name is P Shaker and I am delighted to
share my experiences on a topic that sits
at the heart of modern Cloud operations.
On how large language models are
transforming observability and
accelerating resilience in platform
as a service architectures.
I've spent more than 14 years
working across cloud native
technologies, site reliability,
engineering, and software delivery.
Over this time, I have witnessed
how the scale and complexity of
cloud systems have outpaced the
traditional monitoring approaches.
LMS are not just a trend.
They are rapidly reshaping on how
we detect, understand, and recover
from issues in dynamic environments.
Today we will talk through the key
challenges of observability in modern
platform as a service, how LLM driven
innovations are changing the game, and how
providers can deliver observability as a
native service rather than just an add-on.
So let's dive in without
any further delay.
So talking about the challenge
of modern cloud observability.
Observability in today's cloud
world is anything but complex.
Even though the ask might be simple,
with great power comes great complexity.
Hope everyone agrees with me on
this, especially if your mission
is to build resilient platform
as a service architecture.
Organizations are pouring investment
into public cloud platforms to
gain agility and scalability.
Teams are now embracing microservices
and moving workloads onto cloud
native platform as a service offerings
to ship features faster, but with
this evolution also comes with the
steeper price complexity, skyrockets.
Legacy monitoring tools often just
dump vast amounts of raw data,
leaving engineers with dashboards
full of noise, but few actionable
insights when the systems fail.
The gap between an alert and a fix can
keep stretching, slowing down recovery.
In the meantime, in platform
as a service environments.
This complexity is further magnified.
Services are deeply distributed
and dependent on each other
in an unpredictable way.
A single issue can ripple through
an entire ecosystem, right?
And alerts frequently arrive
without enough context for the
engineers to respond quickly.
And let's talk about
the dynamic workloads.
Think about a platform as a
service offering with Kubernetes.
Think auto scaling Kubernetes pods
spinning up and shutting down.
Within seconds, they make the
failure landscape even more harder
to track and resilient and to
identify where the exact root causes.
Now let's take an example of a FinTech
platform as a service, which is handling
a very high volume trades application.
Imagine a sudden spike in traffic hits
and or a single service flatters, and
that causes transaction delays to cascade.
Now your SRA team is flooded with alarms,
but lacks the correlated insights.
Recovery slows down, downtime
grows, and resilience suffers.
I've seen the scenarios play out
repeatedly and they have convinced
me that embedding smarter self
observability directly into the platform
can fundamentally change how fast
we can bounce back from disruption.
So let's deep more into the distributed
platform as a service environments.
Imagine a healthcare
platform as a service.
Managing electronic medical records.
Patient scheduling and clinical
notifications are the core services of it.
Services now must integrate flawlessly
because it depends on the patient.
It directly depends on the patient
experience and even sometimes
safety and other protocols as well.
Seemingly a small update.
To one of the service can suddenly
overload the event streams.
It can choke dependencies and can
also trigger caca cascading failures.
Meanwhile, underlying
infrastructure is also ephemeral.
Container scale in and out, and the IP
tends to change, and all troubleshooting
assumptions are no longer whole.
Good.
So this reality underscores the
urgent need for observability
to evolve platform as a service.
Offerings can no longer treat resilience
as a bolt-on feature or something that
the customers can figure out themselves.
Instead, observability must be integrated.
It should be always on.
It should be context aware and
also be capable of accelerating
detection and recovery the
moment this disruption begins.
Now, with that, let's jump on to
the evolution of observability.
Observability has come a long way,
but it's been a very slow climb.
We started with basic infrastructure
monitoring where CPU graphs.
Memory usage charts and
simple alerts were in place.
These worked well and good when
the systems were monolithic and
failures were easier to isolate.
Then came the three pillars approach
in the DevOps era where metrics,
logs, and traces gave us more
depth, but still required human
correlation and interpretation.
So tools like distributor tracing
and chaos engineering improved
proactive testing, but they
still demanded manual effort.
Now with AI and lms, we are
entering into a new era.
These models can ingest and
interpret massive telemetry streams,
correlate events in real time, and.
Explain what, why, and how an
incident took place rather than
humans tackling this all alone.
So for platform as a service
providers, this locks a new value
proposition, observability as a
built-in int intelligence service.
The platform itself can proactively reduce
downtime and it can guide recovery with
no separate stack for customers to manage.
Now let's take a look at the land LA
large lang language models, which is the
new Paradigm lms break the traditional
rules based approach to monitoring.
Instead of static thresholds or hardcoded
alerts, they understand the context.
They excel at correlating diverse
data sources like metrics, traces
and logs, even deployment histories
to explain why something is
happening and how to resolve it.
Imagine an e-commerce
platform as a service.
During a Black Friday, rush latency
spikes in the checkout service.
A conventional alert tells you only that
the latency is high, but on the other
hand, an LLM can however, dig deeper,
linking a recent deployment, a sudden
memory spike in one of the service and
an abnormal error pattern in another.
Then surface a clear, actionable
remediation to roll back or scale up.
So in this case, the recovery
time shrinks dramatically.
This agility also enables platform
as a service vendors to often
offer tenant specific LLM powered
insight right out of the box.
Customers don't need to build
or fine tune their own models.
Resilience becomes a part
of the platform itself.
Now let's take a deeper look into
the key capabilities that an LLM
enhanced observability model can offer.
So they can offer automated root cause
analysis, correlating telemetry across
layers to rapidly pinpoint why a failure
occurred, a remediation guidance.
We are suggesting or even executing
recovery steps based on learned
patterns and continuously improving
as it observes your workloads over
time by adaptive learning and comes
in and it can also decide when to
escalate to humans versus self.
Ha cutting the manual delays
with intelligent automation.
Picture a logistics.
A company hit by a routing outage
and LLM not only flags the anomaly,
but it can also help to analyze
the patterns and propose or even
auto execute rerouting strategies.
A recovery that could have taken
hearts might now just take minutes.
So let's take a look at how this can be
implemented in an implementation approach.
So we, this can be implemented in
the following ways, like where you
can start by integrating your alerts.
You can feed your LMS with existing
monitoring signals and enrich them with
context, so alerts become more meaningful
narratives rather than just being noise.
And the LLM models can also be trained
based on specific domains, so it can
be fine tuned based on your platform's,
telemetry, or deployment histories and
failure patterns to improve accuracy.
And it can also do predictive
insights where moving away from
reactive alerts to forecasts.
And also catching failing
nodes or bottlenecks before
they impact the tenants.
You can also give engineers a chat
like interface to ask why this latency
is spiking and get a clear context
rich answer with a conversational
interface and you can also correlate.
Or link seemingly unrelated signals
like API errors, pod churns, or
config changes to stop cascading
failures early with deep correlation.
I have read articles about this
that in a media streaming platform
as a service environment where LLM
connected playback reaches to recent
API throttling helping engineers to fix
the issue in minutes instead of house.
Now after the implementation,
the important part is what
is the actual outcome?
What could be the benefits of it?
So before an LLM integration, the
meantime to resolution was taking
long alert, fat fatigue was real, and
the recovery relied heavily on expert
engineers piecing the clothes together.
And after LLM adoption resolution
times drop down dramatically, in
some cases to under even 10 minutes.
And where it also had a positive impact
on less false positives due to which,
like the product productivity increased
and the overall reliability improved.
By baking this into a platform as a
service, managed service providers
can now standardize resilience
gains across all tenants, not just
those with the light SRE teams.
Now, let's take a look at a
technical implementation framework
work that can outline the steps of
what can be done to implement this.
So start with your data
ingestion and normalization.
Where you can pull your telemetry from,
metrics, logs, traces, and even CICD
events, clean and sanitize the data
with a rich metadata, and also choose
models and fine tune for platform
specific workloads, for example, like
scaling patterns or Kubernetes churn,
and ensure low latency inference.
Where you can optimize the LLM and
you can also do insightful insights
on delivery via where tailored outputs
for each persona, instant remediation.
Hence for sre, where summarized health and
trends for developers or even managers.
And in the most important part is the
technical tool chain integration where
you can expose the results via API
dashboards or even platform consoles that
the users can consume insights natively.
And let's talk about a more important
topic, which is the evaluation methodology
when introducing LLM Driven observability
into platform as a service architecture.
It is always essential to
have a structured evaluation
approach to prove its value.
Before wide adoption, a practical
evaluation offers can offering can
include four complementary methods.
One is controlled experimentation
where you stand up a test or a staging
environment that mimic production.
In a multi-tenant Kubernetes cluster
or like a service mesh and real, where
real telemetry pipelines are present,
and you can inject these failures such
as like PO crashes or cascading service
degradation, or even traffic surges.
Now you can compare the performance
of your existing observability stack
with the LM announced system under the
same controlled events to even get a
more clear or reproducible results.
And once you have that in place, next is
to do a quantitative analysis where you
collect hard metrics like mean time to
detection and mean time to resolution.
And also the false positive rates
to actually understand the accuracy
of the root cause detection.
And you should also monitor how
quickly the system detects the trigger
and correlates the signals together
and guides or executes remediation.
A well instrument, a well
instrumented test often shows
significant reduction in MTTR.
That is the mean time to reduction
when ellam insights are added.
Next comes the qualitative analysis.
Where you engage the SRE and the DevOps
teams who work directly with the new
system, you can use structured feedback or
sessions or surveys to capture changes in
alert clarity or even the cognitive load.
And trust in recommendations.
This human-centered lens highlights
whether the AI explanation are
actionable and understandable,
which is critical for adoption.
Then comes the statistical validation
where you apply the statistical testing,
example, T tests, or you can do a AB
testing one with the traditional model and
the other one with the LLM enhanced model.
And also can do effect size calculations
across multiple incidents to ensure
observed improvements aren't just random.
And this step transforms raw results into
credible data backed evidence so that the
new approach truly accelerates resilience
by combining controlled experimentation,
quantitative KPIs, and human feedback.
The platform as a service providers
can confidently validate that an
LLM powered observability delivers
measurable resilience gains before
scaling it as a core service.
So another important feature that we
need to talk about is the privacy,
security, and ethical considerations.
Once evaluation is complete, more
focus should be given to privacy,
security, and ethical implementation.
Trust us as essential, right?
So when we talk about privacy, collect
only what is actually necessary,
anonymize it wherever possible and
designed the data pipelines to comply
with regulations like HIPAA or GDPR.
And in terms of security guard, again,
guard the model against misuse or
data hallucinations or data leakage.
Keep the critical remediation steps human
verified, wherever it is appropriate.
And the most important part is ethical.
As we all know, like AI and LLM has
its own governance, and most of the
systems specifically in healthcare,
government, or financial finance,
they have their own regulations
on how AI and L LMS can be used.
So in this case, mitigate bias in
model training and ensure that the
outputs are explainable so engineers
can trust the recommendation by
addressing these from the start.
A platform as a service provider
can confidently offer observability
as a service without compromising
compliance or user trust.
So let's talk about the future
directions on where we are headed.
So looking forward, we are heading
towards a fully self-healing platform as
a service capability except multi-model
input inputs like logs, metrics, traces,
video or voice to enrich the diagnostics.
And industry specific models will
give domain tuned resilience like
for example, healthcare versus
FinTech or versus gaming, et cetera.
And let's talk about federated learning.
We will allow sharing intelligence across
tenants without leaking sensitive data.
And let's talk about edge aware
observability where computational is
computational aspects and reachability
is limited, where it can adopt to a
hybrid model and a very lightweight
LLM based model that can serve
edge aware observability as well.
In terms of resilience, it'll
become proactive and predictive by
default and no longer a reaction.
But it should be an intrinsic
platform capability.
Now let's talk about a practical
implementation guideline.
So for those planning to
implement the first step is to
prepare your infrastructure.
Always ensure that you have enough comu,
compute and memory for LLM inference
workloads and strategize on your data.
So you need to prioritize clean labeled
telemetry, sanitize the data in such
a way that can be fed into the model
as a baseline in vector databases.
So that the model can seamlessly
respond back by looking at
the semantics of your data.
Next is training your teams
whereby upskilling the ops
team on a driven workflows.
And before you get started, you need
once you have a baseline ready, the
next step is to pilot by starting
small one service or a failure
mode, and then expand gradually.
You can also minimize dep disruption
with well-planned change management.
With smooth integration and also
keep measuring gains and refining
automation with continuous monitoring.
So these steps help a platform as a
service vendors embed LLM Observability
without detailing existing operations.
So now let's wrap To wrap up,
let's talk about like how LMS are
not just improving observability.
They are redefining
resilience at a larger scale.
By embedding these capabilities
directly into platform as a service
offerings, we can now dramatically
cut down downtime, reduce operational
burden, and can also deliver reliable
self-healing platforms to every tenant.
Thank you for joining with me today.
I would love to continue the conversation.
Feel free to connect with me on
LinkedIn if you are exploring or
implementing LLM Driven Observability.
Thank you.
I.