Greetings everyone.
This is Vela.
I'm working as a senior
BI developer at Coach Vti.
I have 10 plus years of expertise
in leading highly technical
MicroStrategy, Tableau, and
healthcare data warehousing projects.
So my today's topic is.
AI Ready Healthcare data
revolutionizing fraud detection with
scalable data centric intelligence.
So coming to the healthcare fraud crisis.
So as you all might know, the
healthcare fraud crisis is a significant
and growing issue that impacts
the healthcare systems worldwide.
And most notably in countries like
United States, where a large sums
of money flow through both public
and private healthcare systems.
Healthcare fraud not only results
in billions of dollars lost.
In financial losses, but it also erodes
trust, compromises patient care, and
influences healthcare costs to everyone.
So if you see here, there is
almost like annual US fraud losses
is almost like $300 billion.
The healthcare fraud range as estimated
of $300 billion from the US system
annually, and it represents up to.
The 10% of total healthcare spending
and diverting critical resources.
And if you see there is almost
75% of unstructured data that is
impacting the healthcare's staggering.
Three quarters of healthcare data
remains unstructured, severely hindering
automated analysis and the efficient
detection of fraudulent patents.
And.
There are almost like 80% of the
coding errors, so this is alarmingly.
So there are four out of five
medical bills that contain errors,
creating significant vulnerabilities
and opportunities for fraudulent
activities, the healthcare fraud
process, and immense and escalating
financial threat to the industries.
And the she scale and complexity of
this challenge are gently demand a data
driven solution to protect the vital
resources and ensure equitable care.
Going to the next slide.
So the main challenge here in
the healthcare fraud crisis
is the data quality challenge.
So despite like significant advancements
in AI and mission learning, traditional
fraud detection in healthcare
remains alarmingly in effective.
The fundamental flaw lies not
only in the sophistication of
our analytical models, but it is.
In the deeply compromised data
foundations, poor data quality is rampant
and manifesting as inconsistent formatting
across disparate systems and incomplete
patient records written in duplicate
entries and critical coding discrepancies.
Let me come up with few scenarios
where the data quality undermines
detection, like how poor data quality
is causing healthcare fraud crisis.
So there is a scenario where
a provider might bill multiple
insurers for the same service and a
slightly different patient, right?
In such scenario, the
consequence might be.
It is missed as a duplicate because
due to the inconsistent identifiers
and in the second scenario.
A machine learning model, which
is trained on incomplete data.
So this produces inaccurate
risk scores and biases.
And the third one is a telehealth session
is bill, but patient data is incomplete
or mis miss missing from the conversation.
So in such case, a fraudulent
billing may go unnoticed.
So these healthcare organizations.
Frequently find themselves lock in
a frustrating cycle where increasing
computational power and model
complexity diminishing returns.
This is not an algorithmic challenge.
It is a foundational data quality
crisis that undermines even the most
advanced machine learning approaches.
So the two potential of
sophisticated AI for fraud
prevention will remain unrealized.
Coming to the AI models, so there are two
types of AI models in my current analysis.
One is the traditional model and the
other is the data centric AI model.
In the traditional model, the front
detection focuses on refining algorithms
and increasing model complexity.
Viewing the data as an unchangeable input.
This model centric approach is
inherently limited by data quality.
Even advanced AI struggles with
inconsistent and erroneous regards
leading to diminishing returns
despite computational investment.
Whereas the data centric AI seems
to be unlocking true potential.
It shifts the focus, it improving data
quality is the most effective path.
To robust ai, this approach prioritizes
systematic data governance, continuous
quality monitoring and proactive data
enrichment By ensuring data integrity,
we are building a strong foundation
for AI success in fraud detection.
So if you see the.
The picture here, so it stating
the fundamental shift from a model
centric to a data centric mindset
is not just an optimization, but
it's critical reevaluation of
how we approach AI challenges.
For healthcare fraud detection, it means
moving beyond React algorithm tweaks
to pro two data excellence, and finally
enabling AI to deliver on its promise.
So why it matters.
In healthcare, in sensitive
and high stake domains.
The healthcare fraud
crisis plays a major role.
So it is occurring recurring.
It is giving like more recurring
losses to the companies.
So there is potential for a true
data-centric AI model to get rid
of all these inconsistencies.
The bigger impact is on the performance
than the small model improvements.
A well labeled high quality data set
can enable a simple logistic regression
model to outperform a deep neural
network trained on MC or a biased
data, the transformational results.
The impact of data-centric ai.
Below are the main metrics that
define the results in the data-centric
AI elevated model accuracy.
So here.
Achieving 95% accuracy enables
unprecedented precision in identifying
fraudulent activities and thus
protecting the vital resources
and ensuring equitable care and
significant false positive reduction.
So an 95% reduction in false positive,
it cons the investigator overhead
and allows the healthcare teams
to focus on legitimate threats and
process the claims more efficiently,
saving the valuable time and money.
And the third one is the
accelerated investigation cycles.
A 70% foster fraud detection and
resolution process allows healthcare
organizations to quickly mitigate
ongoing losses, recovers funds swiftly
and streamline operational workflows
through enhance data arability.
And the final one is the substantial fraud
loss reduction organizations realize.
A 76% reduction in financial losses
due to fraud, directly attributable
to enhancer detection capabilities
stemming from superior data quality.
This translates into millions saved
and reinvested in patient care these
are the four key factors and continuous
data quality improvement framework.
It is essential to ensure that
AI systems remain accurate,
reliable, and fair over time.
Unlike traditional software systems,
AI is highly sensitive to the quality
of data, and this directly influences
performance bias and outcomes.
This framework treats data as a living
asset, not a static input requiring
ongoing monitoring, evaluation, and
refinement through the AI lifecycle.
So coming to the first part, it's
data profiling and assessment.
The analysis of these data assets,
identifying qualifying gaps,
inconsistencies and structural issues
across all healthcare data sources.
The second one is the quality
metrics definition, establishing.
Quantifiable standards for completeness,
accuracy, consistency, and timelines that
align with fraud detection requirements.
And the third one is automated monitoring.
The real time quality monitoring
systems that flag deviations have
correct to actions before the take.
Data quality es, and the final
is the iterative improvement.
So implementing these feedback loops
that continuously refine the data quality
processes based on model performance and
the detection outcomes coming to the.
Machine learning model
performance, and these frameworks
treat data as a living asset.
It's not a static input requiring
ongoing monitoring, evaluation, and
refinement through the AI lifecycle.
So if you see here with high
quality, meticulously governed
healthcare data, the methods like
random forest accelerate uncovering.
Complex fraud patterns and
leveraging multiple decision trees.
This model, the random forest offers
robust pattern recognition and crucial
interpretability essential for regulatory
compliance and audit trails in healthcare.
If you see the rest of the model models,
they're like little underperforming
when compared to the random forest.
These strong performance metrics, they're
very vital for healthcare organizations.
High accuracy ensures reliable
distinction between legitimate
and frontline activities.
Superior precision minimizes false
positives, preventing unwarranted
flagging of valid claims.
Strong recall reduces false positives,
this blend of advanced analytics
and quality data and purpose
organizations to detect fraud and
improve the speed and the data quality.
And coming to the methods, the blockchain
for data integrity and in immutable audit
trails, blockchain technologies provide
99% of data integrity assurance through
cryptographically secure transaction logs.
Every data modification creates an
immutable record, and this enables.
Comprehensive audit trails
essentially for healthcare complaints.
So the TAM proof transaction records,
the real time integrity verification,
distributed consensus mechanisms, and
the regulatory compliance automation.
And this approach basically eliminates
the data manipulation vulnerabilities
while maintaining the transparency
required for effective fraud
investigation and regulatory reporting.
And the auto machine learning
pipeline acceleration.
This process involves the data addition
where the automated pre-processing
and feature engineering reduce
the manual intervention by 90%.
The model selection, intelligent
algorithm selection optimizes
performance across diverse fraud
patterns, training acceleration.
So the model training time through
optimized resource allocation,
so there is like a 78% reduction
in the model training through.
Optimized resource allocation deployment.
So there is a seamless integration into
existing healthcare IT infrastructure.
So these are all the advanced fraud
detection capabilities, and this
enable healthcare organizations to
deploy these sophisticated AI models
and give them extension, extensive
machine learning expertise in house.
Coming to the cloud, NATO architecture
benefits for healthcare fraud
detection, the elastic scalability.
So our cloud NATO solution dynamically
allocates resources to precisely match
the varying fraud detection workloads.
So this means the healthcare
organizations can effortlessly
scale from routine monitoring to
intense investigation periods.
This ensures optimal performance.
And optimized cost efficiency.
Leveraging paper use pricing
models, our architecture aligns your
expenditure directly with actual usage.
This significantly reduces the total cost
of ownership by up to 60% when compared
to the traditional on-premise solutions.
Robust security and compliance built
upon enterprise grade security frameworks
with continuous automatic updates.
Our platform ensures unwavering
compliance with critical healthcare
data protection like HIPAA and GDPR.
This comprehensive approach safeguards
sensitive patient information
and thus reduces the regulatory
risks and frees up your IT team
from manual security patching.
Seamless integration.
So effective healthcare is dependent
on deep seamless integration within
organization's, existing critical
systems, including electronic health
records, claim management system,
and health information system.
Our sophisticated approach
leverages standardized APIs.
Robust healthcare interoperability
protocols to ensure the data flows
effortlessly without dis disrupting vital
clinical and administrative workflows.
This integration strategy directly
addresses common challenges that often
hinder proactive fraud detection.
We also overcome issues such as
disparate data formats, limitations
of legacy systems, and the crucial
demand for real-time data processing
by rigorously adhering to fast
healthcare interoperability resources,
and HL seven messaging protocols.
Our platform empowers healthcare
organizations with comprehensive and
timely data access, and this not only
maintains operational continuity.
But significantly enhances the
accuracy, the speed, and enables
P to identification of suspicious
patterns and immediate response.
The governance and compliance framework.
So if you see the regulatory complaints.
The data privacy and security, the
quality assurance, the operational
controls, the technical infrastructure.
These are the five main topics under
the governance and compliance framework.
This ensures these five ensure that the
fraud detection system meets stringent.
Healthcare regulatory requirements while
maintaining operational efficiency.
This hierarchical approach addresses
compliance obligations from technical
infrastructure through to regulatory
reporting, creating a sustainable audit
ready fraud detection capabilities,
and coming to the implementation
roadmap In the phase one is this
is an assessment phase, which is
estimated to be one to two months.
There is a comprehensive data audit,
stakeholder alignment and infrastructure
readiness evaluation, and coming to
the phase two, there is a deployment,
sorry, the phase two is the foundation,
so the phase two, the data quality
improvement, governance governance
framework, establishment, and initial for.
Model development, this is estimated
to be around three to five months.
Coming to the phase three is
a deployment phase where there
will be a pilot implementation
system integration and performance
validation across key fraud scenarios.
And this is an estimation
of six to eight months.
The phase four is scale, which
is around like nine to 12 months.
It is comprises of like full deployment,
continuous monitoring, implementation,
and advanced analytics integration.
To measure the success below are some
of the key performance indicators.
These are essential in measuring
the impact of our fraud detection
and safeguarding the healthcare
resources and driving efficiency.
So the financial metrics are reduced
fraud losses where it prevents
fraud claims, preserving healthcare
projects, and optimized investigating
costs, increased fund recovery,
and lower total cost of ownership.
This demonstrate economic
efficiency and return investment,
and the operational metrics are.
Enhance detection accuracy rates.
It measures precision in identifying
fraud and minimizing false
positives, significant fall, false
positive reduction, accelerated
investigation cycle time, and robust
system uptime and reliability.
This guarantees consistent
availability and optimal performance.
And beyond these metrics, our success
ensures regulatory complaints.
Boost productivity and improves the
patient experience the path forward.
By unifying ai data governance and cloud
native technologies, organizations can
replay billions in lost revenue while
restoring trust in the healthcare system.
And the immediate next steps would be.
Conducting comprehensive data quality
assessment across your organization,
establish the cross-functional
governance communities with clear
cross now fraud detection mandates and
begin a pilot implementation until a
partnership with technology providers.
So the AI healthcare data requires
commitment, investment, and strategic
vision to justify the effort
required to implement this next
generation fraud in capabilities.
Thank you all for giving
me this opportunity.