Hello everyone, and thank
you for joining me today.
My name is Asif Anwar and I serve as a
principal engineer at Walter Stewart.
My background, I hold a master's
degree in information technology
with a specialization in software
engineering from Illinois
Institute of Technology, Chicago.
Over the course of my career, I have
gained extensive experience as a
software engineer with a focus on
building cloud native applications
and architecting event driven systems.
I'm passionate about designing
scalable, resilient solutions that
leverage modern cloud technologies,
and I look forward to sharing some
of these insights with you today.
I'm excited to share how we can
scale Kubernetes native system
using even driven patterns on Azure.
You might be wondering why this matters.
Our world is moving faster than ever.
Customer expects instant response
system must scale on demand and
downtime is no longer an option.
Today we will explore how combining
Kubernetes with event driven
architecture help us meet these demands.
We'll examine our real world case study,
how we built a fraud detection system
that responds in unjust under two seconds.
By the end of this session, you
will understand not only the
underlying principles, but how to
apply them in your own environment.
Let's start with the imperative of
cloud native and event driven systems.
In today's landscape, agility,
fault tolerance aren't
just nice to have features.
They are pretty much non-negotiable.
Customer expects a seamless
experience, real time responsiveness,
and they won't tolerate any
outages of service performance.
Unfortunately, traditional monolithic
architecture make it hard to keep it up.
They are rigid.
Scaling is course grade and any change
or failure risk taking down the whole
systems here is what, why Kubernetes
steps in to address these pain points.
By orchestrating containers, Kubernetes
provides a self-healing, automatic
scaling and service abstraction.
This means we can deploy microservices
independently, recover from
failure automatically, and scale
individual services based on demand.
But Kubernetes isn't just a silver bullet.
It's primarily an infrastructure
and an orchestration layer to
achieve the real time agility
that modern applications require.
We need to embrace event driven patterns.
In essence, Kubernetes gives
us the foundation, but events
makes the foundation come alive.
Why focus on event driven architecture?
Because it changes how
services communicate and scale
in an event driven model.
Services are loosely coupled.
They communicate all
synchronously through events.
Imagine sending a letter
versus making a phone call.
You dispatch the letter and move on with
your day instead of waiting on the line.
This decoupling reduces dependencies
and make systems easier to maintain.
Even driven architecture also enables
scalability, workload expand and contract
naturally with the flow of events.
If your traffic spikes during
a scale or a news event.
Your system scales up to meet
the demand and then scales back
down when the rush is over.
Resiliency is another benefit
by isolating components.
Even driven architecture
prevents cascading failures.
If one service goes down, the rest
of the system keeps it running, and
perhaps most importantly, event driven
system enable real time interactions.
Services response to events.
The moment they occur, there
is no polling or waiting.
In an event driven mindset events
are its first class citizens.
Instead of building a web of
synchronous API calls, we build a
network of listeners that respond
when something meaningful happens.
To implement event driven architecture
effectively, we need the right tools.
Microsoft Azure provides a
comprehensive event driven toolkit.
The first piece is event rate.
It's a hyperscale event routing service
that filters routes and deliver events to
subscriber with near real time latency.
Then there is a service bus message
broker that offers enterprise grade
durability and first, first out ordering
if an even grid is the nervous system.
Service bus is the circulatory
system that reliably transport
message across the body.
The third component is Azure
function, which gives us serverless
compute to handle events on demand
function, scale automatically and
charge only for what you consume.
Finally, Azure Kubernetes
Services, which is a KS.
Ties everything together by orchestrating
containers and integrating natively
with this messaging services.
What is remarkable is that these
services work seamlessly together.
There is no need to stitch together
disparate open source com components.
Azure provides an integrated
ecosystem that speeds sub
development and increase reliability.
Let's dig a bit deeper into event rate.
At its core, even Grid is a highly
scalable published subscribed
service, which is a pub sub model.
It supports massive fanout
delivering events to many
subscriber with real time latency.
Advanced filtering lets you route events
based on attributes such as subject
type or even custom metadata Built
in retype policies and dead lettering
handle transient failure automatically.
You can think of event data as a central
nervous system of your architecture.
It routes millions of events
per second across your services
performance skills to handle millions
of events with Subsecond delivery.
This makes it ideal for scenarios
like IOT Telemetry where thousands of
sensors produced data simultaneously,
or from micro based architecture
where many components need to
interact with the same event.
Now let's look at service bus.
When even grid excels at high
volume broadcast service bus focus
on reliable message delivery.
It provides you with cues and topics
with guaranteed persistence, so message
aren't lost even if a consumer is offline.
Service bus supports sessions to
preserve fast first out order, which
is essential when your business logic
depends on processing events in sequence.
Error handling is another key feature.
Dead letter queues captures message
that can't be delivered, allowing you
to analyze and reprocess them later.
This is critical in industries
where audit trails and message
durability are mandatory.
For example, consider a very
high value financial transaction.
If a message is lost or processed out
of order, the consequence would be.
Service bus is the one which
ensures that this never happens.
So how do we execute code
when these events arrive?
This is where Azure functions come in.
Functions are serverless
units of execution.
They react to a variety of triggers.
Event grid service bus, rest
based HTTP block storage and more.
They automatically scale from
zero to thousandths of concurrent
execution, and you only pay for
the resource you consume functions.
They really shine at lightweight
transformations and orchestration.
You can enrich and even filter, transform
it, publish it to another service.
They are perfect for rusty workloads
or glue logic that connects
different parts of your architecture.
In other words, functions are reactive
glue that holds your pipeline together.
Now let's look at some of the
architectural patterns with
event driven architecture.
It is not just about tools.
It is about using the right patterns.
Azure supports several reusable
architecture pattern that help
manage complexity at scale.
This is my favorite.
The first is CQRS, which
stands for Command Quality
Responsibility Segregation.
With CQRS, you can separate read and
write operations into different models.
For example, in an e-commerce
site you write such as placing
orders, updating an inventory can
be fast and eventually consistent.
Separating them optimizes
performance and scalability.
The second pattern is event sourcing.
Instead of storing the latest state
of an object, you store the sequence
of events that led to that state.
This approach provides a complete
audit trail and allow you to
reconstruct any past state.
Then there is a pattern saga,
basically coordinates complex business
transactions across multiple services.
Imagine booking a trip or you need to book
your flight, you need to book hotel, and
you need to rent a car, a saga pattern.
Ensure that if any of these step fails,
the previous steps are compensated.
Let's say for an example,
your flight is canceled.
Finally balance between
choreography and orchestration.
In a choreographic system, services
reacts to events independently, which
promotes autonomy in orchestrated systems.
A central controls tells
service what to do.
Finding the right balance improves
coordination without creating a bottleneck
to see how these patterns come
together, let's examine a real
time fraud detection case.
Fraudulent transactions cost financial
institution billions of dollars every year
in direct losses and regulated penalties.
Legacy fraud detection systems often
took minutes or even hours to identify
suspicious activity, far too slow when
criminals can exploit weakness in seconds.
The goal was ambitious, reduce
detection time to under two seconds
while achieving 95% accu accuracy.
Meeting this goal would not
only protect customers, but also
transform fraud detection from a
reactive process to a proactive one.
Here is how we built the system in Azure.
First, every transaction generated
in our payment services running
on Azure Kubernetes services.
It's an event.
The event goes into an event grid,
which immediately routes it to a
service bus for reliable ordering.
Processing.
A dedicated Azure function wakes up
and enrich the data with customer
history and contextual information.
The enriched event is then passed
to a machine learning model
running in GPU, packed a KS pods.
The model evaluates the transaction and
returns a fraud score within milliseconds.
The final Azure function interprets
the score and makes a real time
decision, approve the transaction,
reject the transaction, or flag the
transaction for review, delivering
a response in under two seconds.
What makes this architecture
elegant is how each Azure
service plays a distinct role.
Event grid dispatches event instantly.
Service bus guarantees the order
of transactions, functions handle
enrichment and orchestration.
Azure Kubernetes Services a KS
runs the resource intensive machine
learning provider models, thus
providing the compute together.
They form a pipeline that
captures every transaction.
And reaches it, evaluates it,
and responds at all cloud scale.
During implementation, we
had to plan for the worst.
Think of it as a Black Friday
when transaction volumes
spike down dramatically.
Even grid, it can handle millions of
events per second, so it doesn't become
a bottleneck during those peak hours.
Service bus provides automatic
retries and dead lettering queues,
ensuring that zero messages are lost
even if something has gone wrong.
Azure function scale instantaneously from
zero to thousand of concurrent executions.
Meanwhile, the machine learning model
run on GPU backed Kubernetes part that
scale horizontally to meet demand.
What was the result?
Through elastic scalability.
During peak shopping periods such as Black
Friday or any other weekend festival, the
system processed millions of simultaneous
transactions without any downtime and
maintained sub two second response time.
This is the power of even driven patterns
when it combined with Kubernetes.
So what did we achieve?
We reduced the average response time
from minutes to under two seconds,
which means suspicious transactions
are flagged almost immediately.
We also call cut false positive by
15%, improving the customer experience.
The system achieved a hundred
percent uptime during peak periods,
meaning no outages or degraded
performance beyond this metrics.
It also gained full observability
with correlation ID that trace
each event through the system,
reduced operational overhead through
automation, improved compliance by
maintaining comprehensive auditors.
All of these benefits translated directly
into cost setting, increased customer
trust and competitive edge in the market.
So what did we learn from
building this system?
We learned some important lesson that
apply to any event driven architecture.
First design item, potent flows.
Your handler should produce the same
result, even if they are processed
the same event more than once.
This prevent duplicate charges.
Ensure consistency using retries.
Second plan for schema evolution.
Use semantic versioning for
your events so consumers can
handle both old and new version.
Third, always include correlation IDs.
They are essential for
debugging and tracing events
through distributed systems.
Finally, implementable strong security
pipeline, leveraging managed identities
and role based access controls from the.
Azure Ensure service communicates
securely without hardcore credentials.
These elections aren't
specific to finance.
They apply across any industry that
requires scalable, reliable event
processing systems, even driven patterns.
They unjust limited to fraud
detection or even finance industries.
In healthcare event driven telemetry
monitors patient vitals in real time.
Systems can achieve 99% of time and
trigger instant alerts when readings
deactivate from safe range in retail or
synchronous inventory synchronization
across multiple stores, reduce lag
by 85%, and prevents talk outs during
sales in insurance, automated claims.
Adjudication combines document
processing with fraud detection
to speed up reimbursement.
These examples demonstrate the
versatility of event driven
architecture across drivers industries.
Now, as we near to end of our journey,
let me summarize the key messages.
Event driven patterns combined with
Kubernetes deliver scalable, resilient,
and efficient systems at enterprise scale.
Microsoft Azure provides a comprehensive
toolkit, event grade service bus, Azure
function, and Azure Kubernetes services,
which is KKS, that lets you build event
driven systems without the glue code.
Fraud detection case study shows real
world value sub two second latency,
zero zone downtime, and improved
accuracy and success in healthcare,
retail, and insurance prove the broad
applicability of these patterns.
Importantly, even driven architecture
isn't just a theoretical, it is
battle tested in production, handling
millions of transactions every day.
So what's next?
If you have a legacy system, consider
modernizing them with event driven design.
If you're building a new microservices,
start with events and choose services
like event grid, service bus and
serverless compute, like Azure function.
The sooner you adopt these
patterns, the faster you will
reap the benefits of real time.
Thank you for your time and attention.
I hope you have a clear understanding
of how Kubernetes and event driven
architecture can transform your systems.
I'm happy to answer any question
or discuss how these concepts
apply to your organization.
Thank you so much for your time today.