Hello everyone and thank you for joining.
My name is Vive.
Koda and I work at Aryaka Networks.
I have spent my career working on
secure and scalable identity systems
for enterprises operating across Globe.
Today I would like to explore with you how
we could scale identity for Secure Access,
service Edge, or SE using Key Lock and the
model known as Regional Hub deployment.
If you have ever waited several
seconds for a login page to load.
You know how frustrating at
agency can be at a global scale.
Those seconds might apply into
our self loss productivity.
So let's explore how we could
design identity infrastructure
to avoid that problem.
Here is how we could
structure this discussion.
First, let's talk about the challenges
SE presence when it comes to identity.
Then we could look at regional hub
model, how it might work, and why it
could solve some of these challenges.
From there, I will show how Kilo
could be used as an identity
solution in this architecture.
Finally, we will walk through how we could
think about automation operations, and
the challenges we expect along the way.
By the end, you will hopefully
have a clear idea of what steps
you could take in your own magnet.
Traditionally, security
looked like a calendar model.
If you were inside the
network, you were trusted.
That model doesn't really work anymore.
With the remote workforce applications
spread across the cloud and edge and
regulation tightening across regions, the
perimeter has effectively disappeared.
So instead of thinking about
securing networks, we could shift
our thinking to securing identities.
Identity could be the new
parameter, the factor that it
remains, who gets access under what
conditions, and from which device.
SE brings networking and security
together into cloud delivery service.
Think of it like building
a network of airports.
Instead of routing all travelers
through one central hub, we could have
local airports where passengers check
in, pass through security, and head
to their destinations more quickly.
At the center of SASE is a zero
trust model, always redify our trust.
And identity could act as the
passport in the system, the thing
that makes or breaks access.
By consolidating policy and access
decisions around identity, we
could ensure consistency across
users, devices, and locations.
By scaling identity in a global SAS E
environment could introduce challenges.
Latency could be a big one.
A Singapore user authenticating against
US based identity provider could face 200
to 300 milliseconds of delay per request.
Availability could be at risk.
If a centralized system goes down, you
users across worldwide are locked out.
Data sovereignty could complicate things.
The regulations like GDPR or CCPA
could require local processing
and storage of identity data.
The scale itself could
become a bottleneck.
A centralized identity and access
management systems might not
be designed for the throughput
demands of global traffic.
So the centralization might
look neat on paper and practice.
It could introduce serious friction.
One option could be to distribute
identity using regional hub model.
In this model, we could deploy autonomous
key cloud clusters in major regions.
For example, one each
in EDAs, EMEA and apac.
Each hub could authenticate local
users independently reducing
reliance on a central system.
The same time the hubs could coordinate
with each other to synchronize
policies and use of data globally.
It's like opening a branch
office for identity.
Each office could handle its own
local users while still staying in
alignment with the overall organization.
By moving to regional hubs,
we could see several benefits.
First, latency could be reduced
since users authenticate
closer to where they are.
Second, availability could improve because
the regional outage wouldn't necessarily
impact users in other parts of the world.
And third, we could optimize
cost by handling authentication
locally, reducing close and
traffic and cloud ingress chargers.
So overall, the user experience could
improve while the operations remain
more resilient and cost effective.
Now, why Key clock?
Key clock could be a
strong fit for this model?
Because it's open source and
Kubernetes native, which makes
it flexible to deploy anywhere.
It support multi-tenancy through
rounds, which could be for separating
business units or customers.
It's standard compliant supporting OIDC,
both to SAML and web authentication,
so it could, it easily integrate with
modern applications and it is extensible.
There are special requirements,
custom extensions could be deployed
through SPS or even listeners.
So as we evaluate identity platforms.
Key Cloud could provide the flexibility
needed for a distributed hub based model.
Let's imagine what a regional hub
could look like at the center.
There could be a key cloud
cluster handling authentication
and single sign-on behind it.
A database could store user
information and configuration.
A load balancer could distribute
incoming traffic across key
clock nodes for scalability.
We could have direct desynchronization
to keep our user accounts
aligned with corporates users.
And finally, an observability
layer could give us insights into
performance and security events.
Each hub could follow the same
standardized pattern, but still adapt
to local compliance requirements.
How could we decide
where to place the hubs?
We could start by
analyzing traffic patterns.
Where are the users?
We could align hubs with existing SSE
point of presence to minimize the hubs.
We could consider regulatory
zones grouping res with
similar compliance needs.
We could look at cloud provider
capabilities, choosing regions with
strong service and resilience, and
we could validate all this with
latency test from real user locations.
A practical starting point
could be three or four hubs
across major business regions.
Expanding as usage and metrices group
synchronization would be key.
We could synchronize usage and
policies through shared directory
services like A DRL app or even
through database replication.
Policies could be kept consistent
using ops workflows for
token and session management.
We could enable cross cluster token
validation, use distributed caches like
infinite span, or allow token exchange
between hubs for operational consistency.
We could manage configuration through
CICD centralized mattresses and stream
events for auditing in this way.
Each hub could operate
independently, but still remain
in step with global architecture.
To make this manageable, automation
could play a central role.
We could adopt ops to treat all
key cloud configurations as code,
ensuring consistency across regions.
We could use Keylock operator
in Kubernetes to simplify
deployment and scaling.
We could apply Canary deployments
to rollout updates safely.
We could implement observability
tools to track authentication flows,
latency and errors across regions.
With automation in place, a
distributed system could remain
both reliable and predictable.
Of course, this model
could bring challenges.
Data consistency could be
difficult across regions.
We could mitigate this by defining.
Authoritative sources and conflict
resolution strategies, operational
complexity could increase.
We could address this with infrastructure
as a code and centralized monitoring
failover coordination could be tricky.
We could use health aware global load
balancers and automate failover testing.
Cost could rise.
We could manage this with autoscaling
and play full placement of hubs and
complaints could get complicated.
We could embed compliance checks
as code and automate audit trace.
So while this is in without
challenges, the potential benefits
could outweigh the complexity.
To wrap up, let's reflect on
the key points we could take
away from this discussion.
First, identity could truly become the
foundation of SSE if it thinks about
zero trust, it's only works and identity
is consistently verified and enforced.
Without identity at the center.
Zero trust is just a
theory, not a practice.
So strengthening identity could
be the single most important
step in making SASE effective.
Second, we saw the regional hubs
could be a practical solution
to the challenges of latency,
availability, compliance, and scale.
By moving identity systems closer
to users, we could dramatic.
Reduce dependency on a single
centralized provider and stay compliant
with the regulations that we reach.
And by reaching this distributed approach
might feel more complex at first,
but it could solve video problems.
And finally, Kiler could be an
excellent enabler for this vision.
It's open source, Kubernetes native,
and is already designed to integrate
with modern cloud native environments.
With its extensibility and standard
compliance, it could give us flexibility
to tailor identity to SASS e needs
while keeping core central control.
So the main idea here is simple.
In a well architectured SASS E model
usage shouldn't feel the distance
between themselves and their additive
provider no matter where they are.
Access should feel fast,
secure, and seamless.
So what next steps we could take?
We could start by evaluating our
current identity architecture.
We could map where our users are
located and identify hotspots.
We could pilot two region key
clock deployment and validate the
improvements, and we could build
automation practices early to make
operations smooth and repeatable.
Thank you so much for your time today.
I hope this session gives you some
practical ideas for scaling identity.
In a global SSE environments, I would
like to hear your questions and then how
you are approaching these challenges.
Thank you all.