I am Chris Gallivan.
I work for PlanView as a flow advisor.
I've been looking for flow for
the past three years along with my
clients, and I've learned a ton.
And today I want to share with you
some of the learnings we've had
along with our clients as we look
for flow in large organizations.
Before we, we talk about, where to find
flow, where people are looking for flow.
I think we should define flow
because I don't think we all
have the same definition.
It's not even obvious to me sometimes.
So since it's 2024, I figured
we would ask you at GPT.
The first time I asked you at GPT what
flow is, it came back with the answer
that was the industry definition of
flow in terms of a state of being.
So this is that idea that a person could
be in flow Where they're performing
their best, where they can do no wrong.
Anyone who's ever been an athlete
or a musician hopefully has
felt this at some point in time.
You have good days and you have bad days.
Sometimes you have this really
good day where you can do no wrong.
That is what we mean by flow
in the first definition.
However, when I work with my clients,
generally a different definition of flow.
What I generally mean is this
idea that we could bring valuable
software to users faster.
And how do we do that?
And that's the second
definition on the right.
So which one is it?
Is it the first definition or
is it the second definition?
From my perspective,
the answer is it's both.
If you think about it.
You can't actually be in
flow as an individual and not
produce something of value.
If you can do no wrong, that means
that your instincts are right,
you're thinking very clearly,
you're thinking about your customer.
That's, I think that's always going to
produce faster value for your customer.
And on the other hand, if you, in order to
get your organization truly bringing value
sooner to customers across the board,
you have to enable flow for your people.
If your people don't feel it,
they're not going to do it.
So you need both.
I think the answer is both.
So now that we've defined
it why do people want flow?
What is it about flow that,
that is attractive to people?
Why is everyone talking about
this for the past few years?
There's a lot of reasons why pretty
obvious, but the reason that I think
we're really interested in it is that I
think as humans we're fixated on time.
From the moment we're born
we're always chasing time.
We never have enough time.
We always want to do more
with the time we have.
So I think there's something about us
that, that's always looking for flow.
And that's why I think it, it's something
that resonates with so many people.
The thing about time that's
interesting is a lot of times we try
to think of time as counting time.
So we count the amount of time we spent on
something and we want to shrink that time.
But when you really look at time,
not all time has equal value.
So in this example, the first picture
is a picture I love, that's my youngest
daughter and I was making pizza with
her and I was so caught up in the
moment that I didn't realize the way
that she was experiencing that moment
and the picture kind of captures it.
It was priceless and it was
about 10 minutes of my life.
The second picture is a picture of my
pizza oven that my wife and I built
together and it took three summers, so it
took a significant larger amount of time.
They both mean a lot to me.
But I think you would understand
clearly the first one means more.
So just because something takes more
time doesn't mean that it means more.
Not all time has equal value.
There's a book called
Saving Time by Jenny O'Dell.
And in it Jenny says, Time has felt the
most expansive and I have felt the most
alive when I was in an encounter with
something or someone that was surprising.
Something that I didn't
necessarily expect.
And this is similar to the last slide.
This is basically this idea
that time has a quality to it.
There's good time, there's bad time.
And what makes something a good time?
Often it's something that
happened that you didn't expect.
Something surprising.
Something where you learn something.
It turns out that you feel the most
energized when you create your best
work in the shortest amount of time.
So that's the idea behind Flow
and why I think Flow is exciting.
A lot of our thoughts today are influenced
by things that happened before us.
So if we're going to talk about
where people look for Flow,
And where do they find flow?
I thought we would take it
back to the industrial age.
Cause I think some of the way we think
today came from the industrial age.
So back in 1909, Frederick Taylor, most
of you have probably heard of Frederick.
He published the principles of scientific
management, and these are four of his
principles that he published at that
time, discover the most efficient way
to perform tasks that makes sense.
Everyone wants to be efficient.
I'm sure they still want
to be efficient today.
Clearly defied responsibilities.
Not quite sure what he meant by that, but
on the surface, it seems to make sense.
Pay according to performance.
I think we all work in companies
where we're paid according to our
performance, we would all want to be
paid according to our performance.
I think rigid hierarchy and
strict surveillance of employees.
That one kind of stands out.
I don't think many people.
Would want to work somewhere where
there was a rigid hierarchy and
strict surveillance of their work.
If you read a little bit more about
Taylor, my take on Taylor is he's the
guy who invented the manager role.
The actual role of managers.
I think it came from Taylor and he also
invented, it seems, the consultant role.
I think that also comes from Taylor's
thinking and also racy charts.
And I'm sure there's many other
things that came from Taylor.
My take on him is that he had a tremendous
influence on the way people work
over the past hundred years or more.
I want to drill in a little bit to one
of his principles and it's this idea of
dividing the work from the responsibility.
This is a quote from Taylor,
which I found shocking.
In most cases, one type of man is
needed to plan ahead and an entirely
different type to execute the work.
The fact that he uses the word man is
a little bit offensive to many people.
But even the concept is a little offensive
because it suggests that only certain
type of people are fit for planning
and the rest are fit for working.
And I think, now that I think
about it, my career, I've been
working now for over 30 years.
A lot of the thoughts of the people
that I've come across, I think,
have been influenced by some of
these ways of thinking, and I
challenge these ways of thinking.
Out of Taylor's work, a simplistic view
of an organization has emerged, and it
still remains in many parts of the world.
This idea that we have this tower, and in
the tower sit the management, and then in
the rest of the company sit the workers.
In this sort of two step company.
I challenge this concept.
So that's that's the industrial
age, but I think it would make sense
that we also spin forward to the
digital age and evaluate, how do we
think about flow in the digital age?
You can see that many of our thoughts
have been influenced by the past.
If I think if you're like me,
so we're a hundred years past Taylor,
actually more than a hundred years.
And I've asked some managers
that are clients of mine, why
do you think work is delayed?
So you want to improve flow.
Why do you think flow is getting held up?
And here's some of the
answers that came back to me.
Inefficient processes, so we
have processes that aren't
as good as they could be.
We have unproductive people.
That's interesting.
I think they mean unproductive
workers when they say that.
We have people not following the process.
Okay, so that's a case where the process
isn't bad, but people aren't following it.
And then we have this one,
which is one of my favorites.
People taking on too much whip.
Suggesting that people actually are
doing it to themselves, and they just
need to lay off taking on too much work.
I think you can see from these four, four,
these are the four primary answers I got
when I asked this question to managers.
These are almost directly attributable to
Taylor's scientific management principles.
It's amazing how closely they match.
If you're looking for these things, if
it's not evident, I don't think this
is where you're going to find flow.
So there's this thing called the
spotlight, the streetlight effect, or the
spotlight effect and the picture shows
it here, and I think a lot of managers
and many of us fall into this trap.
The picture shows a police officer
asking someone who's on the
ground, did you lose your keys?
And it's under this big streetlight.
And the person says, yeah, I lost them
over there, but the light's better here.
So the way I take this, it's the idea
that we measure what's easy to measure.
We don't always measure what we need
to measure or what we should measure.
We measure what's easy to measure.
And as a result we often wind
up getting false signals.
We measure the wrong thing.
So if you take that idea and you think
about the last 30 years and where
we've tried to shine the light and
make improvements we had the agile
revolution started over 30 years ago.
And then we had the DevOps revolution.
Maybe that started 10 years ago or so.
And basically what that did is it shined
a light on a piece of the value stream.
An important piece, but a piece.
As a result, we have lots of ways of
measuring this piece of the value stream.
We've made a lot of
improvements to this area.
But the natural question is, what
about the rest of the process?
When you look at where time actually
goes, if you were thinking like a
customer, You make a request, and
then it comes in 120 days, 100 Plus
20 plus 50 under 90 days later.
You get your request fulfilled.
So yeah, good job IT You sped
up the last 70, but what about
the first hundred and twenty?
What's going on there?
In order for us to really go after
that and understand it We need to put a
streetlight there and we need to start
measuring there and try to understand What
can we do to speed up that part of the
process after all that is the longest?
Amount of time that's
elapsed in this example.
So just like I asked the managers,
why do they think work is delayed?
I asked the same question to the workers.
Sometimes these are
developers and Skrull masters.
Why do you think work gets delayed?
And the top answers are on the board.
These are some of the answers
that came back from those folks
were working on the wrong things.
So we're not even working
on the important things.
We've got too many disparate
demands coming at us from different
parts of the organization.
in.
We've got scope creep, so we ask,
they ask for one thing, we implement
it, then they ask for something else,
and it's slightly different, and
then we have too many number ones.
I think you can see, if I ask a role in
that two, two role simplistic view of
an organization, where's the problem?
The problem's never in
the person I'm asking.
The problem's always
someone else's problem.
Someone else is doing a bad job.
I came from both sides
of this in my career.
And in my, certainly from the worker
side or the development side, my response
to their answers here is poor babies.
I think that's an immature thing
to do, point to leadership.
See, the thing is essentially what IT
or what the workers are saying is I
can't keep up and it needs you to dial
back the demand so that I can keep up.
And while there might be some
truth in that, I think there
is actually some truth in that.
I've never met one business
person that I could say that to.
And they said, sure,
I'll dial back to work.
Actually I might've met one, but in
general, that's not a good approach.
If we need to dial back to work,
we got to figure out a better
way, a better message to send.
I think in general, those of us who have
been involved in the Agile and DevOps
revolution, we've allowed ourselves
to become task focused over the past.
15, 20 years instead of value focused,
I think agile started off focused on
value, focused on customers and what
our customers need and how can we make
customers lives better, but somewhere
along the line, we became much more
focused on the work itself and the
tasks that we're doing instead of
the value that we bring to the world.
And when we go far enough
in this state, we eventually
become comfortably numb in red.
This is a quote from Domenico de Grandis.
It's basically that type of person, and
I know you've met people like this, I've
met people like this, I've even been
like this, I think, at points in my life,
where someone comes to me with some new
change that's going to make things better,
and my response is pessimism, apathy.
I've tried all these things before,
none of them work, this will
never work, is the response that
you get from this type of person.
And a lot of these people are
people that we work with every day.
The question I always have for
someone like that is, Are you
sure you tried the right things?
I know you tried some things,
but were they the right things?
Often times when I ask that question,
I find that there was something a
little bit wrong with what they tried.
So now that we've talked a
little bit about, How do we think
the way we think about flow?
And how did we get here?
Let's just examine quickly some places
that I find people looking for flow.
So some corporations focus
extensively on features.
They move from one feature
to the next, and they have a
huge backlog full of features.
And when you try to talk to them about
the other types of work and the other
things that it takes to have a healthy
product, they just brush it off, and
they want to talk more about features.
If it isn't obvious, This
is not where you find flow.
This is not how you find flow.
So you have a company that's obsessed
with new features, but when you
really look at the work, 90 percent
of the work they're doing, And
the more you build features,
the 90 percent goes up to 95%.
It actually keeps getting
worse and worse and worse.
The question arises, what are the
hidden costs of adding more features?
So to illustrate this, I want
to do a quick demonstration of
something we call the debt spiral.
So there's companies like this, as
we know, that push out feature work.
As their primary mode of operation
over and over year after year.
As you do that, debt and risk and
toil pile up in your software.
It's just a fact.
You write code intending it
to do something and something
else happens in the background.
Toil as well as quality going down
because defects are piling up.
We've known this for over 50 years
and we still haven't solved it.
You can do this for a while and
you can keep your head above water,
but eventually get to the point.
Where there's so much defect work and
there's so much debt and risk built
up into your system that it's very
hard to build any new features and
your feature work slows to a crawl.
This actually happened to Nokia and
they actually went out of business.
This is actually what killed Nokia.
How do you get out of this?
How do you actually get out of
this debt spiral and pull out?
What you have to do is you have to put
your feature work on hold for a while.
And this is a difficult move to make.
Because most people that, that feed the
feature work into the system at top down
companies, they get incented and promoted
based on pushing out feature work.
So when you're asking them to pause
feature work, there's a personal
reason why they don't want to do it.
But those companies that are
forward leaning and strategic,
they do find ways to do this,
including our company at PlanView.
When you do this and focus on
debt work for a period of time,
You can make a big difference.
And when I say a period, I don't
mean like a week or a month.
Sometimes this could be six
months or a year of focus.
I have one client that it
seemed to focus on debt work and
modernization for two or three years.
And it was their strategic area
of focus for two or three years.
That was their strategy.
The idea is if you do that for the
long enough time, you can actually
get to the point where your defects
go down almost to zero and your debt,
your risk and your toil go down.
And Which, of course, gets you the
results you were after in the beginning,
which is your quality goes up and your
feature work goes up and everyone's happy.
This sounds too simple.
Many people haven't done it.
Those that have are
doing quite well with it.
A lot of other people tend to look for
flow in developer productivity dashboards.
The word productivity has been all over
the market for the last several years.
And I hate to say it, but I don't think
this is where you find flow either.
As I said before, 90 percent of
software costs are maintenance.
So if 90 percent of software costs are
maintenance, and 70 percent of your
coding effort is understanding the
code, most of the time we're spending
is just trying to understand what to do.
So if we really want to make a
difference, if we really want to make
people productive, wouldn't we just
make the code easier to understand,
which could be a tech debt initiative?
Makes sense to me.
Another thing about productivity,
and this is going back to the very
beginning, humans feel the most
energized when they feel some sense
of agency over the work they're doing.
They'll run through a wall for you if
they have a say in the work they do.
If 90 percent of the work at your company
is dictated by the management, how much
do those people feel they have a say?
So if you really want a
productive workforce, give them
a say over the work they do.
Stop telling them what to do.
Give them some say.
Let them come up with the way they're
going to solve these problems.
And what problems are they going to solve?
If you're really after productivity
and you refuse to give them a say as we
all know, 70 percent of what we build
our users probably won't even use.
So my prediction is 70 percent of your
software won't be used by your users.
But of course, that's not the kind of
predictability you're probably after.
Another place I see people looking
for flow is in scrum dashboards.
30 years later, we're still
trying to get scrum perfected.
Still not a good place to look for flow.
I find a lot of companies that are
really trying to adopt rigid scrum,
and they pride themselves on delivering
stories to an artificial cadence.
But when I ask their customer how
long does it take you to get value,
I find a lot of dissatisfaction.
One of the customers actually
said our delivery of value looks
the same as it did 20 years ago.
And from my experience, that's
really not that far off.
I wouldn't go through all these
different, detours if I didn't
think there was a better way.
And I'm happy to say that I
think there is a better way.
But it's quite a bit different where most
people think they need to look for flow.
I actually think flow and the way
companies should be organized looks
more like this picture than the original
picture with the two separate circles.
Demand generation and
demand fulfillment Demand.
Can't be separated.
Strategy and execution,
they need to work together.
There is an overlap between the two.
And the more that you figure that overlap
out, the better off you're going to be.
If you don't figure it out,
flow eventually gets lost in
the seams between the people.
While this is a simple way of
looking at it, it's far more
complex than this, obviously.
So if you look at a typical software
development process that takes ideas
and takes them to impact with customers,
you'll see that there's a lot of
different people and stakeholders and
groups involved from sales, marketing,
business owners, product managers, product
owners, designers, front end engineers,
backend engineers, different teams.
We even have engagement managers
managing the developers and product
owners giving the developers work.
So this is.
These are a lot of different
people involved in this.
We have release engineers.
We have support engineers.
Everywhere you see a bubble on
this chart, you have a seam.
There are seams everywhere.
And if you don't manage the seams,
that's where flow goes to die.
So the real reasons The reason why
flow is impacted, the reasons that
actually cost us the most money are
the things that happen on the seams.
These are things we can't
figure out by ourselves.
The first one is we haven't
figured out how to schedule our
work in a way that delivers value
the fastest to the customers.
Engineering can't schedule
work on their own.
Product can't schedule work on their own.
This is something we have to do together.
And we don't do things together very well.
We have poor handoffs from
product to engineering.
We make bad choices, both
on the technology side, as
well as the product side.
We have unplanned work that comes up.
That unplanned work comes from both sides.
And we're not very good
at figuring that out.
And we have quality issues.
Quality is everyone's problem.
It's not just engineering's problem.
So we need to figure out how to, how do
we work together to solve these things.
A long time ago, 2001, a paper was
written called Nobody Ever Gets Credit
for Fixing Problems That Never Happened.
In the paper, the authors
described two loops.
The first one on the left is called the
Working Harder Loop, and the one on the
right is called the Working Smarter Loop.
Every company has a gap
with their competitors.
Every company wants to close that gap.
The problem is, gaps never stay
closed, because everything that comes
together eventually falls apart.
This is the second law of thermodynamics.
It's just the way the world is.
So you're constantly trying to
close gaps with your competitors.
The working harder loop closes
the gap by working harder.
Trying to get people to work
weekends, and work extra hours
and do the right thing, you know.
That can work, and it does work.
The problem is, it doesn't work for long.
The second side is the
working smarter loop.
So instead of trying to close your
gaps with your competitors by working
harder, You're trying to close it
by investing in new capabilities, by
improving your processes, by doing
debt work, and improving your software.
The problem is, when you work smarter,
there is a longer time to feedback.
Much longer time to feedback.
You can see the loop
is a little bit longer.
And you have to be patient.
If you're not patient, and you
can't wait for that feedback, you
short circuit the loop and you go
back to the working harder loop.
There's a lot to this paper.
It's available on the internet, but I
think they knew in 2001 why continuous
improvement isn't sticking in companies.
It's pretty much outlined here.
It's mainly because humans
don't do well when feedback
is distant in time and space.
We need to find ways to encourage
people to be more patient.
Now, it's easy to say it's hard to do.
I understand.
I used to be a musician.
I played in a band for a number of
years that was going to be my career.
And then I got a real job working
in it and the rest was history.
Miles Davis, Chopin, others
spoke about this concept of
the space between the notes.
So everyone wants to divide things up.
You do your part, I do my part.
The racy says I do this, you do this.
The problem with that is that there's real
things of value that happen between us,
or at least that could happen between us.
Musicians know this.
If you look at a jazz band, you take a
jazz band in first grade and you watch
how they're playing their instruments.
Each person is focused so
much on their instrument.
They want to do their part.
That's the only thing they're focused on.
They're not listening to how can
I interact with the person next
to me and make something better.
If you go to a club and you find a really
good jazz band, let's say in Detroit where
I'm from, they're doing the opposite.
Those guys are more listening
to each other and interacting
with each other, and they're not
trying to stay in their own lane.
They're trying to create something
that's never existed before.
That sounds a lot like software to me.
That sounds a lot like what
we're really trying to do.
The surprises.
Remember from the beginning of the
talk, that's where the real value is.
So my advice is resist the urge to
break everything down into pieces
and lose your focus on the whole.
It's okay to break things down,
but you still got to find a way to
keep the focus on the whole because
that's where the real value is.
That's where the real surprises are.
Focus on the customer.
I've got a few tips to leave
you with here at the end.
I just have a rolling list of tips.
These are some things that
I'll provide you with.
I think value measurement and
measurement of work is really important.
And if you look at the way we measure
value, it's changed a lot over the years.
So back in the waterfall days, we had
these big bulky projects and we had
these statements of work and we knew
what we were delivering to customers.
We were pretty clear eyed on that.
Everyone on the project knew what it
was cause it was big and it was bulky.
And then we swung the pendulum way
over to the left and we started
measuring stories with Dora and
other measurement approaches.
And people lost sight of what it is
we're trying to bring to the customer.
We're so focused on our
cadences and our iterations.
I think the pendulum needs to swing
back a little bit to the middle.
Like a happy medium, where we have
features that we deliver to customers.
We know why we're delivering
them to customers.
And that's really where our
focus of measurement is.
This idiom can be thought of in a lot of
different ways, measure twice, cut once.
Most of the time we spend doing
software development is thinking
about what to do, and a small
amount of time is actually doing it.
The same is true of design of software.
Make sure you put your best
people on the thinking.
Don't have someone else doing the thinking
and someone else doing the development.
Put your best engineers on the thinking.
That's where you're going to get
the most benefit out of design work.
Identify and track dependencies.
We've never been good at this.
www.
microsoft.
com www.
com We still need to do it.
It's going to be required
for us to improve our flow.
Focus less on prioritization,
more on sequencing.
If you've started something, try to
finish it before you start something new.
We call this fastest value first.
Pay attention to unplanned work.
Find ways to signal it.
Once you have signaled it,
find ways to remove it.
This is one of the biggest drains on
flow that we see with our clients.
Understand your variability.
Average numbers, like average flow time,
Averages of any sort can be misleading.
Look behind the variability to see
the lanes in your traffic and try to
understand what's really happening.
And last but not least,
you make choices every day.
Are you going to work your people harder?
Are you going to point
your finger at them?
Or are you going to work smarter?
If you're going to work smarter, you need
to encourage people to be patient and
wait, because the benefits of investment
in the right thing are worth the time.
Thank you very much for
listening to me today.
Have a great conference.