Hello, everyone.
Today I'll be talking about Perseus.
Not just today.
You can watch me whenever you want.
The GitOps native dashboard
visualization tool.
Now I think about it.
When you're watching
it, it's always today.
First of all, I want to say
congratulations to Perseus.
They've been accepted into the CNCF.
At the sandbox maturity level, which
basically means that it's not just a hobby
project from some developers anymore.
It's now officially a CNCF project.
Then about me this is me.
And there I'm Erwin de Keizer.
I'm a CNCF landscaper, as I like to
call myself, or a developer engineer.
And I'm with Fullstack, one of the
first KCSPs of the Netherlands.
And a big thank you for them for
supporting me in my Strange, odd
obsession with talking about cloud
native projects in a word purple onesie.
Also, just to be clear, I
have no affiliation with the
Perseus project whatsoever.
I'm just someone that is enthusiastic
about it and likes about it.
Likes to talk about these kinds of things.
Also, sorry, this is the only time
I'll be using this template for the
slides, because it takes forever.
And, so these are Percy's goals.
. Let's summarize them a bit clearer.
Also from the get go, I
need to say these are goals.
They are not achieved milestones.
We'll get to that later.
So they want to be the standard dashboard
visualization tool for Prometheus.
They want to be GitOps compatible,
which is Perfect, because
we all love GitOps, right?
And they want to provide
different NPM packages, which
on the surface sounds a bit odd.
Is it a goal to provide NPM packages?
Apparently it is, because they want
their advances in visualizations to
also benefit the entire ecosystem.
Even Prometheus, the Prometheus UI could
use their visualizations in the future.
It's also aiming to be Kubernetes
native, which means that they adopt
the same data model as Kubernetes.
And it should provide native CRDs
for, to create visualizations.
How awesome would it be if you just
deploy your service monitor together
with your Percy's dashboard and it gets
automatically provisioned in Percy's.
And they also want to support a
static validation of the dashboard
format which is great especially if
you combine it with GitOps and CICD.
So you know that when you're
provisioning your dashboards and you
have a pipeline that the dashboard will
actually work or at least not break.
And they also want to
support plugins, which, okay.
And now I will show you a live demo.
First of all, we have
a Docker compose file.
that I would like to show you.
So we do tfc.
As you can see, we're just
starting at Prometheus.
And at Perseus, we'll do the latest
without a version, because YOLO.
We do docker compose up.
And
I'll open Perseus.
As you can see, some data persisted.
I'll throw it all away to show
you how everything is done.
First of all, if we go into the
admin area, we have global variables.
We have global data sources and global
secrets, which are basically these
things that can be used by all projects.
And when you add a project,
let's call it ClickOps.
Good suggestion.
You'll see that we also have
variables, data sources, and secrets.
So everything can be defined on a
global level and on a project level.
We can also see the config
that it was started with.
And we have the devils button right here.
We'll Just ignore that exists.
So in the kit, in the ClickOps
project, we're going to add a Toyota
source, because we started Prometheus.
Let's call it Prometheus.
Make the default, no proxy access,
because we can reach Prometheus on
the Prometheus hostname from within
Perseus, but not from the browser.
We'll save it.
And we'll try to create a dashboard.
I'll just quickly go through
things go back later.
And here you can see which panel group.
So you can have multiple panel groups.
You add a name.
We have a time series chart, which is
basically the default chart everyone uses.
And check go routines.
Instantly get a visualization.
If you go into settings you can
see what you have to change.
You can add the legends.
It's only for meters in this case.
There's multiple options here.
Can bars line with.
I think the defaults are quite decent.
It actually looks good by default.
So if we add this, we can also
make it bigger and then save it.
And as you can see, it immediately
made the count of coroutines go up.
And there's also this button that can
instantly make one panel full screen.
And if you want, you can also see the
JSON that was created for this dashboard.
And that's about it for the interface.
We'll get back to it later.
But there's also a sea light tool.
It's like Cube, CTL,
cube Kettle Cube Control.
I don't know.
But then it's for Percys, personally,
I think it should have been called
Per Kettle 'cause it just sounds fun.
But they went with per CLI,
I'm not sure if it's per CLI or
Berkeley for the sake of this.
Presentation, I will call it
Berkeley because that's just
a lot funnier to pronounce.
And here we'll go through these files.
So we have some files here.
We have a data source.
We have a project.
First of all, we should
create the project.
Because everything else
depends on the project.
And that's why, this one is a bit
more clear, it's numbered like this,
which makes sure that everything
gets applied in the correct order.
So when we now do
Berkeley apply MD, you see that project,
data source dashboard have been created.
And if you go back to the homepage, we
now also have a Persis 2024 project.
And then we can go into
the black box monitor.
And here we see some extra things that
are possible with for the dashboards.
So these variables, they are created by
reading labels from Prometheus itself.
And so we have the gauge charge, we have
a single stat which nicely translates
seconds into a human readable format.
Because if you take a
look at this raw data,
if I make this a decimal,
you would see that it's fine.
5.
96 million seconds,
which is not something that I
can instantly translate in my
mind into a normal duration.
But if you make it seconds,
it makes a lot more sense.
I'll also, I show you the variable.
So we created a variable ourselves,
which is a list it's created
from Prometheus label values.
So it uses the default Prometheus.
The label name is instance.
And we select the series by using
the job black box, because I have a
black box monitor attached somewhere.
You can also allow multiple values and all
options, but for now we didn't do that.
And then you can see that.
The toggle works and automatically
gets updated with new values as well.
Here you also have the things that you
normally see when you use Grafana as well.
So you can have the date interval.
If you're interested in another
interval, you can also select that.
You can set that auto refresh.
And again, you can see
the dashboard itself.
We also have other dashboards, which
basically amount to the same thing.
So are not that interesting.
Something I could show
you is if I edit this
panel group, it's not very descriptive.
I call this usage charts and This
one can be a bit more like this.
And we'll make this a bit bigger.
This is where the magic happens.
And then we save the chart.
And if we now go back to the command
line, we can directly get dash.
I think we call it per 2024.
We see these dashboards that are available
and if we do Berkeley, describe dashboard.
We updated Wirecard per,
sorry, 2024 and we do it
in the Wirecard dashboard.
We can also see that a div was created.
If we check out the div you'll see that
the white space has changed quite a lot.
We'll just save this one.
And for the sake of the
demo, we'll do it again.
because it's a lot easier to
see the changes that were made.
If the whitespace doesn't
change, we'll save it again.
We'll do the same this
and then we do a kitch.
And now you see that the div is quite
small because we actually only changed
the width and the alignment and you
also correctly see the revisions.
So if we commit this,
we now have these changes in code.
Big question, of course, is how
does it stack up against Grafana?
I think this is a question of personal
preference because customization
wise, it's a lot more limited.
Grafana right now.
It's, there are just many features.
I think the most essential
features are there.
But the thing I really like
about Grafana is the explore tab.
There's nothing like that right now.
Style.
I think the default dashboards
of Precise look better than the
default dashboards of Grafana.
That's a matter of personal
preference, of course.
The ease of use I think
it's about the same.
I've used Grafana a lot.
I think for the past 10 years, that's
been the go to dashboarding tool for me.
Thank you.
So I know my way around it, but
I've only recently started using
Percy's and it's actually quite
easy to learn and understand.
The GitObsability is very nice, as you
just saw with the Berkeley CLI tool.
And the future I don't know.
It's bright, I think.
It's been accepted into the CNCF.
There's a lot going on with the project.
There's a lot of potential, but it's
also still a bit murky, if you ask me.
I don't know what level it
will reach in the coming time.
I think we also need to talk
about dashboards as code.
The Percy's project itself really pushes
the dashboards as code concept or DAC.
And right now they have
two solutions for it.
Excuse me.
You can use Q or the Go SDK.
And what is Q anyway?
The, it stands for
configure, unify, execute.
So it allows you to validate, define
and use dynamic and text based data.
So it's basically a better toml.
I don't know.
It's like YAML and toml and Python and
Go had a four way and this is the very
odd baby it is possible to generate
Q templates or schemas from Go types.
It's what the Percy's project does.
So there the Q definitions are
always aligned with the actual code.
And Q also allows you to have
if statements, for loops.
So it makes it easier to use some kind of
programming language which is Maybe you
shouldn't call Q a programming language,
but it does have a lot of similarities,
more than TML or YAML, and allows you
to generate dashboards from there.
So if you want a uniform style across
all your dashboards, it's quite easy to
achieve, especially if you have multiple
environments that you're monitoring, like
development, acceptance, and production.
If the only change is the data
source, then you can just use the same
dashboards across all those environments.
If there's some naming conventions
or labels that are different across.
environments, you can use Q with a
for loop and some kind of if statement
to make sure that the same dashboard
gets deployed to all environments
with the changes that are needed.
I also have an example of
what the Q format looks like.
So we go to Q.
We have a dashboard.
Oh,
yep.
For people that are familiar with
Go, this looks very familiar at
least the package and the imports.
So it uses imports from GitHub as
well, the queue schemas to know the
schemas of the things we're using.
And.
This is what a dashboard will look like.
It looks very similar to the YAML,
but then with more pound signs.
And if we do Q export out YAML,
we actually get the same YAML out
that was generated by the Q file
that can be understood by Perseus.
And of course, this was the queue.
There's also the Go SDK.
I also have a demo for that.
If you go to Go in this project then
we have a Go file, which looks very
similar as that what we just saw.
So this is the Go to
create a new dashboard.
And if we do Berkeley Duck
Build
Oh, sorry, Berkeley Duck
You will see it will output it here
And if we do bot build main output We
again get a YAML  you can also just
run the project The main go file.
It will also give you a
YAML output that you can
use with the Percy's CLI.
Okay, now for the gotchas.
Dashboards and panels don't
save unless you click save.
This is something that will annoy
you especially because it's not
that clear that you're in edit mode.
Now you're in edit mode.
You can easily think, okay, let's go here.
But if we go back to the wire
guard, that this chart that
we just deleted is back again.
If you refresh, it's instantly back.
This can be very annoying, especially
if you were busy adding a lot of
panels and then just decide to
refresh, you will lose work that way.
The names don't match
the names in the CLI.
If you create something
in the user interface with
spaces or special characters.
They get replaced with underscores
in a way that could surprise you.
A lot of units are missing
and not customizable.
I think this is the biggest one.
It's very cloud native.
oriented.
So you can have bytes, you can
have time, you can have rates,
but stuff that's missing is like
currencies or even SI units.
So I also have a dashboard
that monitors my power usage.
There's no option to use the kilowatt
or kilowatt hours as your unit.
The entire Kubernetes
integration is still missing.
There is a Kubernetes operator GitHub
repository, which does have some
activity, but there's the Kubernetes
integration doesn't exist yet.
They also have a concept that's called
ephemeral dashboard, which is basically
a dashboard that has a TTL, which sounds
like a great idea for CICD workflows.
But if you try to use it it
doesn't work with Berkeley yet.
The documentation still is limited.
And by default, the Berkeley doc setup
to set up dashboards as code fails on
macOS because of some permission issues.
They are fixable.
It's not the end of the world,
but there's still some way to go.
Also, because we're all SREs, and
DevOps engineers, and software
engineers, this is also an invitation
for all of you to get involved.
I think this project has a lot of future.
And if you want to improve this project
and want to use it, please contribute.
I will thank you a lot personally.
Send me an email if you've
contributed and I will send you a
personal thank you note as well.
For the rest, this is it.
Thank you very much for taking
the time to watch all this and
hopefully see you next time.