Good day, everyone.
I am Jubin Thomas.
I work as a technical architect at
Signet Jewelers, having 14 plus years of
experience in supply chain and retail.
I'm also a senior member of IEEE.
Before I move on to my topic, I
would like to thank Mark and all the
organizers of CubeNative Conference
2024 to invite me as a speaker.
Today, I would like to discuss
about architecting order management
systems with scalable microservices
with the help of Kubernetes.
So as you all know, microservices has
taken the world by storm and order
management system is one of the systems
where microservices has actually helped
to scale in a very some of the companies
who already have the implementation
of microservices are Netflix, Spotify,
eBay, Amazon Web Services, Airbnb, Uber,
Nike, Twitter, Walmart, and Verizon.
The agenda today is basically to go
over the overview and infrastructure
architecture of microservices.
What are microservices?
When should we use them?
What is the right size for a microservice?
Why is microservice better than monoliths?
Infrastructure architecture.
Then we will go over the software
architecture and design capability
centric design, understanding the
route and a small example of a
shopping menu or a shopping cart.
The microservice scalability,
the disadvantages with the CRUD.
And then we will also discuss about the
testing strategies with microservices
like microservice testing tools.
And finally, we will discuss about
what is docker and kubernetes and
we will go through the kubernetes
architecture and the kubernetes concepts.
So what is a microservice?
Microservice is an approach to a
Engineer focus on building single
function modules with well defined
interface and operations and It basically
minimizes the risk and scope of change.
It is easy to deploy easy to
understand across the business
And the diagram which over here
is something which gives us a good
comparison between a monolith architecture
versus the microservice architecture.
So if you see the image on the left
hand side, it says that there is a
user interface which connects to the
business logic and which connects
to the data layer and data layer is
actually connected to the database.
So there is a monolithic structure in
place, which gives a very hard dependency
of deploying any particular new feature.
But at the same time, if you look
into the microservice architecture,
The same user interface is actually
divided into multiple microservices
and these microservices are actually
connected to the respective database.
So this gives us a flexibility to deploy
these individual components separately.
So that is basically a great advantage
which microservices provides to us.
Now what is the right
size for a microservice?
Now this question comes that, what kind
of size we should have for a microservice
or how can we define the business
logic of a particular microservice.
So the answer to that question is the
business function or domain of the service
determines more important than its scale.
So you know, for example, I was talking
about the order management system.
So like payments is the one of
the module of order management.
And then we have.
checkout as one of the different
module of the auto management system.
These module itself is actually playing
a more important role comparatively than
the scale of these individual modules.
So one microservice might have dozen
of entities and the other the dozen
of entities, more importantly, it
is a part of the microservice play.
And emphasizing user stories will
enable us to precisely outline
the limits of the business domain.
Now, why is Microsoft is
better than monoliths?
So as we discussed in one of the previous
slides, this monolith architecture
is built as a large single unit.
It has RDBMS, which we
call it as database.
Then it has the backend code.
It could be in Java or any other language.
And then we have the front end
code like HTML, JSP and ASP.
And these features additionally
requires the entire unit to be deployed.
See, this is the dependency
which you were talking about.
Okay.
When we need to scale, we have to have
multiple copies of the entire application.
And on the other hand, the
microservices is small.
autonomous services that work together.
It is loosely coupled with bounded
context, and it is a natural consequence
of applying SRP at the architecture level.
And this is a typical flow diagram of
how the monolithic app is in picture
versus the microservice architecture.
So on the left hand side,
the image what we see is.
Basically for a monolith app wherein
we see that there's a UI layer and
then the, business layer, database
layer, and the front end, everything is
all together as a single application.
And as I was talking about the order
management system, so these four
functionality, like the shopping
cart, or basically the checkout
functionality, then the order system,
which basically places the order.
Then we have the customer system, which
basically maintains a track of different
customers for that particular brand.
And then we have the inventory system.
So all of these four systems
is all together binded in a
single monolith application.
But at the same time, if you look
into the right hand side, these
four different applications like the
shopping cart, order, customer, and
inventory, it The dependency is actually
broken here and all these four are
four separate entities altogether.
So customer is a separate entity,
order is a separate entity, shopping
cart is a separate entity, inventory
is actually a separate entity.
And this is the greatest advantage
which microservice provides that it also
helps to dependency of the database.
So if you see customer is actually having
a radius and order is basically in MongoDB
and shopping cart is in SQL server and
inventory is actually the oracle database.
So it gives us the flexibility to
have multiple entities, multiple
databases, but at the same
time it can talk to each other.
Now I will actually go through the the
capability centric design, which is one
of the design technique in microservices.
Basically the business centric development
focuses on business capabilities.
So the microservices is actually
built based on capabilities.
So as we saw the example, which I
was previously telling the example
of order being a separate entity
inventory being a separate entity.
So these are different capabilities.
which this monolith system, which is
order management system can provide.
And the responsibility what we have
right now is to break this monolith
system into multiple microservices.
And each of these individual systems.
functionalities like the inventory
or payments or checkout, all
these are different capabilities.
So here in this case, we see that
each capability is having the
front end back end in the database.
And then there is a product team
which basically operates these
Now understanding the root.
So An aggregate will have one of its
components objects be the aggregate root.
Any references from outside the aggregate
should only go to the aggregate root.
The root can thus ensure the
integrity of the aggregate as a whole.
And if you look into this, the order
is actually connected to all these
different microservices like the payment
strategy and the payment is actually
having credit card, cash, bank transfer.
At the same time, order is actually
connected to the customer because the
customer is the one who places the order
and then the order can have multiple
line items and it has a shipping address.
So this gives us a better picture of
how this is actually divided but at
the same time connected to each other.
Now this is a typical shopping
menu or a shopping cart.
So we have the order being the primary
microservice, and then we have the
do domain layers wherein we have
different entities like order or
item, shipping, address and payment.
And then we have the service port.
Which is Order Repository, Order Service,
Order Web Service, Order Query Web
Service, Shipping Address Web Service,
Payment Web Service, and then we have
the utilities like Order Factory, Order
Status Converter, Record State Converter.
What are these adapters?
So we have these several adapters
which helps us to connect to the system
individually like the order repository
adapter, order service adapter, order
web service adapter, order query web
service adapter, and so on and so forth.
So these adapters, which basically
consists of actual implementation
of the ports like database
access, web services, API, etc.
And the converters are actually
used to convert an enum value to a
proper integer value in the database.
For example, order status
complete is mapped to an integer
value 100 in the database.
Now CRUD, as we all know about CRUD,
CRUD is is basically create, read,
update, and delete functionality.
So it basically has a presentation layer,
then a service layer, then business
logic layer, and the data access layer,
where we can basically query the database
and push the updates to the database.
So what is the disadvantage with CRUD?
It is basically doing a mismatch between
the read and write representations
of the data, It risks data connection
while records are logged in the
data store in a collaborative domain
where multiple actors operate in
parallel on the same set of data.
These risks increase as the complexity
and throughput of the system grows.
It can manage security and
permission more quickly.
complex because each entity is subject
to both read and write operations, which
might expose data in the wrong context.
Now we will discuss about the different
testing strategies with microservice.
Just like the other systems, Microservice
also has the various testing like we
have the unit testing is basically the
smallest piece of testable software
in the application to determine
whether it behaves as expected.
Then we have the component
testing, which basically helps
us to do component level testing.
Then finally, then we also have
the integration testing, which
defines the communication paths and
integrations between components to
test and detect interface errors.
defects.
And then we have the integrate integration
contract testing, wherein we basically
do a contract Test within the boundary
of an external system verifying that
it meets the contract expected by a
consuming service And finally there is
an end to end testing which basically
tells that a system meets external
requirements and achieves its goals
Testing the entire system from end to
end And some of the tools which we can
actually use for microservice testing
is Cucumber and JUnit, which helps us
to do a mock, and then we have Mockito,
which is a great tool to basically mock
the service responses when each service
is actually connected to the other one.
Moving on to the side of deployment land.
Now, I actually spoke about microservices.
I spoke about the monolith systems.
Now, when it comes to the
deployment, there are a few things
which microservice comes handy
with, and it really helps a lot.
Especially when we work with docker.
Now, what is a docker?
Docker is an open source platform
for developers and sysadmins
to develop, deploy and run
applications within the containers.
It works on the principle
of build, ship and run.
As you all know that build is a
command, build container images on local
laptop or automated through continuous
integration pipeline ship container images
through container registry, et cetera.
And run is to run anywhere
on cloud and on prem.
So this is a typical docker
architecture where we have a client
side, which basically does a docker
build, docker pull and docker run.
And then we have a docker host,
within that we have a docker daemon
and the containers with the images.
And at the other hand it has a
registry, and all of these are
actually interconnected to each other.
Now let me talk about kubernetes.
Kubernetes is an open source
system for container orchestration.
So we spoke about the
docker and the containers.
So kubernetes is basically a platform
which helps us to manage these containers.
containers in an effective way.
And it is focused around scheduling,
scaling self healing and auto repairing.
So this is a typical Kubernetes
architecture where we have an API, which
basically connects to CLI interface.
And then we have a Kubernetes
masters, which connects to multiple
nodes and the image registry.
And there are.
certain kubernetes parameters which
I would like to talk about and
when we talk about kubernetes, we
definitely talk about these things.
So one is pods.
So pods is one or more
containers and volumes.
It has shared namespace.
one IP, it has one IP per pod.
And then we have services.
Services is something which gives
us a stable network endpoint and
it has a label selector and also
the load balancing within it.
This is what I would like
to share as part of my talk.
I thank you so much to listen to me.
This is my email ID, jubin.
thomas at itriplee.
org.
I request you to please reach out
to me if you have any questions.
And once again, thank you for having me.