Hello everyone.
I'm am Kris, a technical architect
and lead data engineer at for
with over 16 years of experience.
My research paper is titled De-Mystifying
Modern Data Pipeline Architecture from
regional ETL to Cloud Native framing.
Think back to a time when you had
to wait all night for business
report to process that was of ETL,
but today the digital factory never
sleeps and our data can either.
My career, I've been on the frontline
of this dramatic evolution, and today
I'll share how we are moving from
batch oriented mindset to the world
of cloud native framing and what that
means for how we turn data into value.
Here is a look at what will cover today.
We'll start with evolution of
data pipeline architectures.
Discussing the limitations
of legacy systems.
Then we'll dive into modern
art pattern that emerged.
We look at the two evolution landscape,
examine critical design integration
for building resilient pipelines, and
finally look at emerging brands and
practical migration s for organiz.
The key takeaway of modern data
engineering revolution is the shift
from batch to realtime processing.
The recent approach relied
on schedule batch processing
using centralized systems.
Now, modern reality involve distributed
realtime and cloud native architectures.
Two main factors, drivers
is the business driver.
Has an intense need for immediate
insight and operational intelligence.
The technical driver is a demand
for greater scalability, better
cost efficiency, and overall
flexibility in our data systems.
Traditional EDL limitations,
why change was inevitable.
There is an EL framework facing
significant constraints first batch
crossing in windows, typically third
overnight to avoid disruption operation
systems, which severely limited data
availability when businesses started
demanding real-time monitoring.
Second, the design meant single point
of failure with limited recovery.
Option that often require
completely rep processing the data.
Third, rigid infrastructure meant
performance improvement depending
on expensive hardware upgrades
involving high upfront cost and
complex cap capacity planning.
Fourth systems were built primarily for
structure data and second to handle the
explosion of semi-structure logs and
streaming data for new sources like.
Device, devices and web application.
Finally, they also
suffer from vendor login.
New to proprietary query extensions,
the cloud storage revolution,
decoupling storage from compute,
the introduction of cloud storage,
specifically object storage like Azure
block storage or Google Cloud storage.
What.
Fundamental to enabling
modern data architecture.
The most profound change
was the opening of mechanism
between storage and computing.
Before the loud revolution, storage
and computing were tightly funnel,
inexpensive switch capacity warehouses.
If you needed more crossing
power, you usually had to buy
more storage and vice versa.
After the shift, we gained
access to practically unlimited.
Extremely cost effective object
storage, which can scale independently
of our processing cluster.
This adventure Freedom
delivers several key benefits.
First, the pay as you go.
Principal model shift cost from large
capital expenditures to variable
operation costs, making data scale
accessible to every organization.
Second.
Enable schema on read flexibility.
We can now store raw data in
its native format, applying
transformation later, preserving
native integrity rather than forcing
it into rigid redefined ular front.
Finally, cloud storage offers native
redundancy, durability, and it
inherent needs support all formats
such as semi-structured unstructured.
Which was impossible.
With regional databases,
modern artificial patterns, overweight
as data systems make mature to
handle modern cha challenges, several
key artificial patterns emerge.
These patterns represent different
philosophies for how we secure
and process data on a scale.
Explore the five most influential.
First, the medallion architecture.
The pattern defines transparent,
quality layers, bronze, silver,
and gold for data refinement and
curing, governance and quality.
All are built into the pipeline.
The Lambda architecture.
This is a dual path approach using a batch
layer for complete historical accuracy
and free layer for real diamond sight.
Copper architecture cation of Lambda.
This pattern adopts a steam first model
using a single processing engine and
an even log as a source of truth for
both realtime and historical views.
The lake goes paradigm.
This unified approach brings the
transactional feature and performance
of data warehouse directly onto
the low cost storage of data link.
Finally, data match.
This is a less AL architecture
and more organizational structure,
decentralizing data ownership and reading
data product owned by Nomen teams.
Now I would like to discuss
about the medallion architecture,
the medal architecture model of
Olympic medals organizers, data
requirement into discrete all levels.
Bronze laser layer is where raw data lands
into lands without motivation, ensuring
complete source fidelity, its validation
focuses usually on completeness.
A single layer.
Is that what the foundation here?
Raw data is informed by standardizing
format, fixing inconsistencies, and
applying quality and governance rules.
The goal layer, is a data
shape for business assumption.
It includes purpose build
structures like star S schemas,
and pre aggregated metrics.
The main benefit is that it is
clear quality boundaries and
ensures productive processing.
This makes it ideal for organizations
with strong governance requirement.
Now, I would like to discuss
about the comparison between the
Lambda and the KA architecture.
Lambda and KA architecture represent
different philosophies for handling both.
Historical and realtime data.
The Lambda architecture uses
batch and stream processing path.
The batch path handles comprehensive
historical analysis while the
speed path provides immediate.
If preliminary insights, its main
downside are higher complexity and
the necessity of dual code based
maintenance for transforming logic.
Architecture simplifies this by adopting
a stream processing first approach.
It uses a single app and only event
loss as the definitive system of record
batch processing is re ized as just
naming with an unlimited time window.
This result in simpler maintenance
and unified processing model.
Now I like, I would like to
discuss about the lake cost.
The lake of patterning
represents a powerful conversion.
It addresses the historical fragmentation
of having separate data lakes for
raw storage and aware of analytics.
It augments lake flexibility, low cost
storage with data warehouse performance.
S features include implementing
warehouse capabilities like asset
transactions and schema enforcement
directly on cloud storage objects.
It supports multi workload
support for bi ml and streaming
and provides unified governance.
The business impact is is the elimination
of data lubrication, fragmented
governance and integration headaches.
Now I would like to discuss about the
data match domain oriented approach.
The data match pattern is less about
technology, more about organization shift.
Its core principle is to read data
as a product owned by domain team.
This is designed to solve the scaling
bottleneck present with teams key.
Domain oriented ownership, self
serve data platform, federating
governance and data products with clear
interfaces and quality assurances.
The primary benefit is or, and
scalability and better alignment
with specific business domain.
The primary challenge, however, is that
requires significant organization change.
It's a social technical transformation.
I would like to discuss about
the Tool Evolution timeline.
Let's look at the tool evolution Pipeline.
We can segment this journey into four
areas in nineties and two oh, and
the focus was traditional ET tools
like IBM Data stage and Informatica
visual interfaces and mon monolithic
batch oriented design characteristics.
From 2010 to 2015, distributed
processing framework like Hadoop and in
horizonal scaling and old first approach
between two, 2015 and 2013, we saw
the rise of open source orchestration
tools like Airflow and Perfect.
Alongside early cloud services, these
enabled processing and serverless
executions from 2020 onwards, the
landscape was stream first, unified
processing, and ML integration.
We now see real time capabilities,
integrative interfaces, and specialize
system for virtual learning.
Modern tool categories.
The current landscape has four main
categories of tools, orchestration
framework like Apache, airflow, and
perfect focus on scheduling, depending
scheduling dependencies, and monitoring
the apple from actual data process.
Cloud native services such as AWS Glue
and Azure Data Factory offer serverless
execution and consumption based pricing,
fitting well with variable workloads,
saving platforms like Apache Kafka
and Spark streaming, or essential
for low latency realtime inside.
And finally crossing engines like Apache
Bar Link provide the power of complex.
Distributed computations US selection
criteria was choosing a tool must
extend beyond features to include
team skills, operational requirements,
cost model, and integration needs
critical design consideration.
Moving to modern distributed
system introduces a new set of
challenges and operational necess.
We must address five critical design
areas, data governance, and lineage.
Lack racking, data provenance
across complex environments, quality
validations, shifting from periodic
checks to continuous assurance and
performance optimization, leveraging
distributed techniques like
partitioning, security and compliance.
Implementing data centric production
and access control in indonesia's
challenges, managing the coexistence
of real time and bad workloads,
data governance and distributed
systems in distributed hybrid
and multi-cloud environments.
Maintaining visibility is a significant
c. Governance had evolved from
checkbox to an operational activity.
Our solution must include automated
and linear tracking at multiple levels
from dataset to column and even record
levels of provenance for environment
with in complete instrumentation,
emergent techno techniques include.
Lineage that uses statistical methods
to infer transformation relationships.
The business value is clear, rapid
impact analysis during values, simplified
troubleshooting of inconsistencies
and necessary audit rating,
failure, audit rail for compliance,
quality validation framework.
Data quality assurance must be must
now be an continuous and automated
now, not just periodic and manual.
Modern framework implement
multidimensional validation,
syn and correctness.
Semantic validating contextual
appro appropriateness.
Implementation architecture has evolved
to distributed opponents that exhibit
checks at each transformation boundary.
Streaming and this is achieved to
specialized operations that implement
validation logic directly within
the execution model related in an
pattern in continuous data flow.
Emerging ran serverless data processing.
Looking forward.
Serverless data processing
represents profound paradigm shift.
Key characteristics include elimination
of expressing infrastructure, provisioning
di, dynamic resource allocation, and
a shift to consumption based pricing.
This has a significant design impact,
encouraging architecture, nature,
some of smaller focus crossing unit
with easier boundaries rather than
monolithic transformation jobs.
The benefits are powerful, automatic
scaling, significant cost optimization,
and operational simplicity.
AI ML integration data
pipeline meet machine learning.
The integration of AI and ML has
driven specialized natural innovation.
Features stores have emerged
as digital component.
These are specialized systems that
manage lifecycle of machine learning
features, providing versioning access
control, and ensuring consistency between
training and serving modern service
pipeline, integrated time inference,
delivering the core data pipelines.
A key requirement is point in time
feature accuracy for valid modern
learning and lineage lacking for modern.
The business impact is faster model
deployment, consistent feature engineering
and unified infrastructure supporting both
traditional BI and advanced ML workloads,
data contracts and EMA management.
Formal agreement for data exchange
and data and data ecosystem.
Centralized data contracts and
formalized EMA management are
critical for maintaining sim.
The purpose of these contracts is
to establish explicit agreement
between data producers and consumers.
Components specify data structure, quality
characteristics, and delivery patterns.
The main benefit is enhanced
ability in distributor systems
by setting clear expectations.
Implemented via version schema
registries, and with sophisticated
compatibility, checking that validate
proposed change against historical usage,
prevent breaking downstream consumers
migration strategies, practical
approaches to modernization.
Stable approach, risk,
timeline, and e factors.
Finally, migrating from legacy
architecture is a significant
under undertaking and a whole cell
replacement is really feasible.
We must adopt in incremental strategies,
enable outline a few proven approaches,
patent based modernization, identify
more common crossing patterns.
System and analyze usable modernization
approach for each hybrid execution
uses gateway component to maintain
and sustain interface while
underlying implementation transition.
Gradually.
Specialize connectors allows
modern processing framework to
efficiently integrate with existing
data sources through adapter,
patent, and format bridges, and.
Domain by domain starts with
non-critical businesses domain and
expand progressively this low risk
and low risk phase approaches.
Minimize business disruptions,
sorry, and allow organizations to
demonstrate value incrementally.
Key essential insight for data leaders.
To summarize our journey,
here are the key.
Here are essential
insights for data leaders.
There's no single architecture
that future lies in thoughtfully.
System that aligns with specific business
context, adopt incremental migration to
modernize and minimize risk gradually.
Governance is critical line,
lacking in quality management
or operational necessities.
In distributed enrollments,
real time is standard.
Naming is a becoming
basic business responsive.
Finally remember that organization
change is essential as a technology
recommendations action
items for organizations.
For those looking to embark on this
modern modernization journey, I offer
this actions action items as this current
state inventory or existing architecture
and identify the key pain point.
Event target state, use artificial
patterns like medallion or Lake Earth that
align with your strategy business needs.
Start small.
Begin your migration with noncritical
domains or workload activities.
Invest in governance, implement
lineage tracking and quality
framework early in the process.
Build skills.
Develop the necessary cloud
native and streaming processing
bilities within your teams.
And with this I conclude thank you.
This transformation is ongoing and
by embracing cloud native principles
and thoughtful design or nations
can build the resilient, adaptable
data pipeline necessary for future
of operational intelligence.
I note and thank you for
giving me this opportunity.
Thank you.