Good evening everyone.
This is Karthik Red, a senior society
level team engineer specializing in
cloud native platform modernization
and event driven architecture.
Over the past decade, my work has
focused on building resilience,
scalable, and self-healing system
on Azure Kubernetes services with an
emphasis on automation, observability,
and zero downtime operations.
My journey in SRE has been about
transforming large traditional
systems into high availability
realtime platform using open source
technologies and modern DevOps practices.
Today I'll be sharing insights
from the recent work on Kubernetes
native platform modernization.
So before getting into the topic,
so I would like to share how the
current industry has been evolving.
So over the last decade, we have seen
cloud architecture evolve from the static
VMs, two dynamic container workloads that
can respond to change in a real time.
Kubernetes has become the
backbone of this transformation.
Not just as a container orchestrator,
but as an enabler of declarative
automation, resilience, and portability.
What's exciting today is how teams are
rethinking reliability, shifting from
reactive firefighting to proactive
engineering, where the platform itself
anticipates and recovers from failure.
This evaluation is not just
technical it's cultural.
It's about empowering developers,
automating recovery, and bridging
observability with operation.
So what we are gonna learn today,
so one is the battle tested design
patterns, real world deployment insights
and comprehensive pattern catalog.
In the battle tested design patterns
the, we discover proven patterns for
building self-healing, cloud native
streaming systems that ensure throughput
consistency and availability at scale.
In the real world deployment insights,
we gain critical insights from higher
volume, even stream deployments.
Processing mission critical
data in production environment.
Whereas in comprehensive pattern
catalog, we acquire concrete tactics
and the robot toolkit for designing
streamlining pipelines that withstand
failure and recover gracefully.
So let's get into the architecting
for resilience streaming, foundation,
resilience, streaming systems, demands
and architecture built to withstand
the unpredictable nature of distributed
environment such as architecture.
Simultaneously uphold three
properties, which are critical.
One is throughput,
consistence, and availability.
So the throughput which sustain
high volume message crossing without
performance degradation, whereas
consistency which preserve data integrity
and message order despite failures and in
the availability, which ensure continuous
service operation, even emits component
failures, these critical properties,
empathy, the cap, the trade off.
Inherent in designing any
cloud native streaming systems.
So let's discuss about the ready
streams which, which is replayable
event log and observe downstream
failures and coordinate consumer groups.
So in the REPLAYABLE event, log the
ready stream maintenance and append
only lock enabling deterministic
event play messages persist with
unique it and timestamp precisely
reconstructing sequence after failure.
In the absorb downstream failures,
this resilient buffer absorbs temporary
downstream failures, preventing
data loss, automatic back pressure
management, safeguards against memory
exhaust during extended outages.
And the coordinate consumer groups,
which built in consumer group management
ensures load distribution and automatic
failover failed consumers resume
processing from their last acknowledged
positions, maintaining so on top of this.
So we in current, the
platform has been modernized.
In large enterprises, especially those
with decades of legacy systems, the
modernization is not, it's not just about
containerization, it's about transforming
anti delivery models from moving from
nightly batch jobs and static AP PS to
event driven scalable services that can
handle millions of requests per day.
So the challenge often lies in
maintaining service clusters while
ensuring compliance and security.
That's where reliability
engineering principle intersects
with Kubernetes native design.
So let's discuss about the
circuit breakers, which is
mitigating cascading failures.
So the close, there are three states,
close the state open state, half open
state in the closed state request flow
normally while the system monitor error
rates and response times for animal.
In the open state, when failure
thresholds are exceeded, the circuit opens
causing requests to fail immediately.
This prevents resource exertion
and cascading failures.
Half open state.
So this periodic health checks are
conducted to assert service recovery.
Traffic is gradually restored
as downstream service stabilize.
So let's discuss about the reliable event.
Replace for system consistent.
So in the, in this event
replay, we have three aspects.
One is preserve message, order,
restore system, state efficiently
ensure item potent processing.
So preserve message, order where
employee partition keys and sequence
numbers to ensure deterministic
message ordering during replay.
This is crucial for maintaining
state consistency across distributed
systems in the restore system.
State efficiency where harness
event sourcing patterns.
Combined with snapshots and incremental
replay so quickly, restore system
state after failures, minimize recovery
time while ensuring data item, potent
processing design message handlers to
be item Putin, allowing safe replay of
duplicate messages without side effects.
This guarantees exactly once processing
semantics in distributor environment.
So now let's discuss about the
Kubernetes microservices partition.
And data scaling and service integration.
So in the event of ing use this ing to
distribute load among consumers while
preserving message order when we talk
about this event driven architectures
one of the most overlooked critical
competencies like the event of, so the
event of partitioning plays a major
role in parallelism and auditing each
partition as an independent commit law.
Allowing multiple consumers to
process events concurrently while
preserving order with that partition.
The key is finding the right
balance between the partition
count and consumer scalability.
In one of in one of our implementations,
which you partition comes dynamically
based on throughput trends.
For example, billing events, speaking
during business hours are synchronous
reasons after nightly basis.
This approach helped.
Maintain high rates without
hitting throttling limits of
our provisioning resources.
From a site reliability engineering
perspective partitioning is not just
about performance, it's about resilience.
It isolates failure domains.
If one consumer group are partition
experiences, select the other, con,
the others continue processing.
Seamless.
In short if it well planned
partitioning gives you both
scalability and fault isolation.
Twin pillars of reliability
in any streaming system.
The second one will be that clear scaling
is Kubernetes event driven auto scaling.
Which is traditional auto scaling
in Kubernetes is often metric
driven, like CPU memory orent.
But in event driven systems, the real
indicator of Lois Q Depth or event
plan, this is where cada shines.
So CADA allows you to scale
workloads based on external metrics.
In our case, the event of consumer lack.
So when the queue backlog increases,
new pos are automatically spawned as the
queue drain, they gracefully scale them.
This dynamic responsiveness eliminates
ideal computer and reduce cost while
maintaining near real time process.
What I like most about Qda, it's
about bringing operational simplicity
created with the HPA, which is
horizontal port autoscaler, and
works natively with Prometheus metal.
From an SRE perspective,
it's a perfect balance of
performance and cost efficiency.
Scaling, not by guesswork, but by data.
It's also highly observable friendly.
You can actually trace auto scaling
events alongside system metrics,
which helps correlate scaling behavior
with real user or bachelor pack.
Next comes the service mass integration.
So this Service MES integration
is one of the most transformative
ships in Kubernetes networking.
As microservice grows, so does the
complexity of managing communication
authentication which retries,
encryption and observability.
So a service mesh like Linker Deep
are abstracts these concerns out
of the application and handles
thems the infrastructure layer.
For example, by enabling
MTLS, which is mutual TLS.
We ensure secure service to
service communication without
changing a single line of code.
From a reliability standpoint, servicemen
gives you like powerful management
circuit braking with backup and
canary routing are all policy driven.
Observability is another major advantage.
With built-in telemetry, we
can trace latency per identity
bottlenecks, and detect cascading
failures before the impact end user.
So now let's hear about the automated
failure detention, like as we discussed,
which is liveliness, probs, readiness,
probs, container restart policies, and HPS
scaling response in the liveliness pros,
which verifies the application help via
HT TP endpoints, trigger container restart
for unresponsive services, set appropriate
timeouts and failure threshold, whereas in
the readiness groups, use startup checks
to remove unhealthy pots from service.
Discovery until ready to
serve traffic prevent routing
requests to degraded instances.
Container restart policies utilize
Kubernetes built in restart mechanism
with exponential backup of for automatic
recovery from transition failures.
Eliminating manual intervention HPS
scaling response, configure horizontal
port autoscaler policies to swiftly
scale replica based on CPU memory.
Customer metrics, like as we discussed,
the event of messages and processing,
like observability with Prometheus.
And so establishing the baselines for
anomaly detention which is establishing
robust baselines of normal performance
metrics is crucial for identifying
deviations that signal potential issues.
Pay close attention to
these critical indicators.
One is message throughput.
Second one will be the consumer lag, or
third one will be the error rate results.
And the fourth one is
resource utilization.
Message throughput, which monitor volume
and processing speed, consumer lack, which
is tracks consumer delays and message two
error rate results which define acceptable
error rates and alert on breaches resource
utilization, which observes CPU Memory
network and this usage for animal.
This regularly update baselines
for effective automated and
scaling discussions when
it comes to observability.
So one of the biggest breakthroughs for
me personally has been operationalizing
observability, which is going beyond logs
and metrics to actual actionable insight.
For example distributor tracing
combined with real time dashboards
allows us to visualize transaction
journeys end to end instead of treating
incidents as isolated problems.
We now view them as signals to improve
system, device, and observability is
embedded into the platform from day
one, meantime to detection and recovery
drops dramatically and engineers gain
confidence in continuous delivery.
Visual bottleneck identification,
which is here we are using
heat map analysis techniques.
The harness Grafana advanced
visualizations to create
comprehensive heat maps.
Pinpointing performance, bottlenecks and
capacity constraints across your stream.
Streaming pipeline, the visually
identity which processing hot
spots and uneven load distribution.
Temporal patterns in CRO microservices
network and storage I your bottlenecks.
The color coded intensity maps provide
intuitive understanding of system
behavior, writing optimization efforts
based on actual performance impact.
So architecting resilience in this
is the pattern catalog where we have
modernized legacy ETL build NextGen event
platforms and ensure SLA compliance.
So when it comes to the resilience, so
where the automation plays individual
in, in achieving this zero downtime
operating pipelines and progressive
delivery techniques like Bluegreen
and Canary Argo rolls we which can
control risk while maintaining velocity.
Automation is not only about
deployment, it's also about recovery.
Self-healing systems that restart
parts, rotate secrets or failover
seamlessly having have become
the foundation of reliability.
The ultimate goal is to make
failure, protein predictable and
recoverable so team can focus on
innovation instead of firefighting.
So the in the modernized legacy ETL, the
transform traditional batch pipelines
into resilient streaming architecture.
Leveraging event driven patterns
and cloud native orchestration.
Whereas in the Build NextGen event
platforms, we have architect autoscaling
event driven systems with comprehensive
observability built in from day one.
And in the Ensure SLA complex, we
implement proactive monitoring and
automated recovery to meet strings and
availability and performance requirements
for mission critical environments.
So let's get into the architecting
resilient streaming system.
Which is like production ready
patterns automate with Kubernetes
comprehensive observability.
The production ready patterns,
which leverage proven pattern for
registry, circuit breaker, and
deterministic replace strategies to
mitigate real world failure scenarios.
And in the automate with Kubernetes,
which utilize liveliness props, readiness
checks, and HPO policies to create
self feeling systems ensure graceful
recovery with minimal intervention.
In the comprehensive observability,
which implement Prometheus and Grafana
monitoring with metric baseline lag
detection and visual heat maps to
uphold SLA complaints in critical.
And so as we look ahead, the future of
SRE and Kubernetes is heading toward
even greater abstraction as and in the
serverless orchestration, policy driven
automation and AI assisted operations.
The combination of AI based
anomaly detection with even driven
remediation will reshape how we
approach reliability at scale.
The next phase is not just about,
it's about the system intelligence.
Platforms that learn from
incidents predict, degradation,
and adapt autonomously.
This is where the boundary
between human insight and mission
position to truly start to.
Blood and so that's it.
Thank you for, thank you
all for joining today.
I hope the session gave you a
practical view of how Kubernetes
native design, automation, and
observability can truly elevate
reliability in modern cloud platforms.
It's been great sharing my experience and
I'll love to continue the conversation.
Feel free to contact or reach out.
Would like to discuss resilience,
engineering, or cloud native
modernization further.
Thank you again for your time.
Thank you.