Hi, hope you've been
having a great day today.
My name is Shiva Kumar.
I'm a senior cloud engineer
at an insurance technology
startup called Realtic.
Today I'll be talking about
enhancing healthcare Processing
reliability with Kubernetes.
So this is going to be our agenda.
We'll be talking about introduction
to healthcare data challenges.
We'll talk, spend some time
on the Kubernetes itself.
What kind of impact Kubernetes can
have on the healthcare industry,
how it is doing right now.
We'll go through one case study, how A
specific company was able to reduce the
downtime and enhance their reliability
and we'll talk about Key kubernetes
features that are useful for healthcare
processing and we'll talk about how
a different Implementation strategy
how different healthcare companies can
implement kubernetes and how they can
use it And we'll also talk about some
future outlook and that's it talking
about healthcare data challenges, as
you can imagine, we'll be dealing with a
lot of sensitive patient data in there.
And a large number of health care
companies process health care data and
the reliability and availability of this
systems is very critical and you need it
for the patient safety and well being.
And any downtime or data loss can
potentially lead to delays in the
treatment, compromise patient outcomes and
significant operational disruptions for
these companies and also for the patients.
So talking about healthcare let's spend
a little bit of time on why we need to
talk about healthcare industry at all.
So this is one of the largest
industries In the united states
in 2022, it was equivalent to 4.
5 trillion dollars and Also usa in usa.
It's one of the highest healthcare
spend per person in the world.
So there's a lot of money here a
lot of Infrastructure companies are
working on healthcare area so when
we talk about healthcare, industry
It all includes all these areas like
healthcare We are talking about hospitals
the softwares they use Apps they use
and then the small small facilities
where there are individual practices.
We are talking about insurance
companies and data processing
behind these insurance companies.
When we send the claims, what happens
behind the insurance companies.
And it was talking about medical
device companies and also the
health education how the Doctors
are being trained what kind of
software they are using and all that.
When you're talking about healthcare
industry It encompasses all of
this stuff, but today we'll be
focusing on a small area So this
is where our company works as well.
So i'll be talking about healthcare
insurance claim processing because
this case study is based on one such
company that I am familiar with.
So let's look at the overview of what
happens when a patient goes to a hospital.
So when a patient goes to a hospital
providers be it individual doctors or the
hospitals they file a claim to insurance
companies based on the care they provided.
And these insurance companies
are technically called providers.
payers within the healthcare industry
when they receive these claims they go
through a bunch of policies different
healthcare policies and make sure
the process or procedures that are
performed on the patient for the
specific use case are actually valid.
There could be some
simple rules a person cannot have
three knee surgeries Because two
needs, you can only replace two needs.
So that's one example.
So it could be a simple basic rules
or could be a complex multi step rules
based on healthcare policies of different
states and different kind of is it
Medicare, Medicaid or different process.
So, they go through all the, each for
each claim insurance company goes through
all this and they also take care of
take help from different companies,
which actually goes helps the insurance
providers process all this data.
So our company also works in this area.
We receive claims from the insurance
companies, we process them, and
then we send it back to them.
So this is how the whole.
processing works for
the healthcare claims.
Since we're talking about advantages
of using Kubernetes in this space
we'll go through a little bit of
overview of what Kubernetes is.
So Kubernetes is an open source
platform which can help automating
the deployment, scaling and operation
of the containerized applications.
So we are basically placing our
Applications inside Docker containers or
other type of containers and Kubernetes
helps us deploy them and manage them
across different multiple nodes.
So it is designed to manage complex
applications across multiple
nodes, ensuring the consistency,
reliability, and scalability.
The key features of Kubernetes which
are really helpful for managing the
applications are like automated scaling.
So there are features like Horizontal
order scaling, where based on the resource
usage, Kubernetes itself can create
multiple replicas of the same application.
Where it can handle more traffic.
And it can also, we can also do vertical
autoscaling, where a single port can
take, can vertically scale increasing
the CPU or the memory of a single port.
So different types of scaling.
And if there are any issues in
the underlying infrastructure,
Kubernetes can automatically bring
up a new instance of the application.
We call that self healing.
And when there are new changes to the
application It's possible to do the
rolling deployments where there are
say 10 instances of the application.
You can slowly roll the new
version of the application easily,
like you roll Say there is a 1.
0, we have 10 pods already present,
we can so each pod would go through
so a new pod will come up with a 2.
0 and one with 1.
0 will go down, then slowly all
the pods will transform into 2.
0.
So that's a rolling updates are plausible.
And we can also do the canary
deployments where we can send a
small percentage of the traffic.
To the new version of the application,
make sure things are looking great.
And then we can, and then we
can do the rolling deployment.
And it's also possible to do all of
this securely, using the inbuilt RBAC
role based access control, where we
can define Which users and which roles
can have what kind of access, what
kind of actions they can perform on a,
on the Kubernetes cluster or in this
different resources like namespace.
We can restrict what a user or a
role can do in specific namespaces
or in specific type of resources.
So those are the small
introduction to Kubernetes.
So
this use case is based on a
conversation with a colleague or friend.
At a conference this is a large
health insurance company where they
were, where they had a different
setup before, and they were able to
transform to Kubernetes infrastructure.
And these are the, actual numbers
with what improvement they had seen.
It has led to 50 percent reduction
in their downtime, especially when
they are doing the new deployments,
they were able to have a very
shorter maintenance windows.
And they're also able to overall
increase the reliability because
of the self healing nature of the
Kubernetes where some instance goes
down and they're able to bring back
a new instance and take the traffic
without any interruption to the service.
And automatically scaling the loads
different use cases where they're able to.
process the batch batch claims.
And yeah, self healing.
We already talked about that.
So this is, this was a setup.
So previously it was an on premise
setup where it had a couple of data
centers and they were deploying these
applications directly on the bare
metal instances using the Ansible.
So using Ansible, all the.
Build was going on in GitHub and the
images are being built there through
the CI CD within the GitHub and
the Docker image was stored in the
Docker registry, not Docker registry.
So they're actually building the binaries
Java binaries, and then they were
able to pull these from the registry
and then deploy them directly in the
instances like bare metal instances.
That's how they've been doing it.
It was also a patchwork of both
Ansible and some shell scripts.
There were several challenges doing
this, uh, one of the challenges
was it was difficult to maintain a
lot of code, especially since they
had a microservices architecture.
It was clear to them after some time,
it would be better to transform into
a Kubernetes based infrastructure.
So they moved to
kubernetes infrastructure.
Kubernetes was being managed
on they were using the EKS,
AWS managed kubernetes service.
And they moved to the github architecture
where they were using the Argo CD.
So that all the manifest, helm charts
and everything was written in the,
was stored in the github.
And Argo CD was directly deploying
these applications from docker
registry to the cluster based on
the manifest in the git repository.
So any changes they had a clear change
control where any changes are going
through this, but previously through
Ansible they were running these
Ansible scripts from local and people
had to make changes in their local.
Sometimes those changes were not
committed that led to some problems.
But through Argo CD through GitOps
stuff it was very easy for everyone,
like it was more transparent.
So this has this whole transformation
has led to a like 50 percent reduction
in their downtime and they were
able to reliably and consistently.
Do the deployments other than great
advantage they had was especially when
they were doing the batch processing
because typically the way health
insurance industry works is They take
all the claims throughout the day and
send it as a batch over the night to the
sent, not sent, yeah, they sent to
the processing companies and also do
their batch processing at once per day.
So they had to scale these infrastructure
once a day and they don't need that
infrastructure throughout the day.
So through using the AWS EKS auto scaling
groups and that stuff and Kubernetes,
they were able to get much cost savings.
So other features that were really
useful for them, the, what these
rolling updates previously they
were only able to use do the.
Deployments once per week, and when they
were doing the deployments they had to
take down the data center and then do
the deployment and then get back the
data center in the maintenance windows,
but using the rolling updates, they
did not have any downtime, especially
for the web applications where the With
the application had to be available
for the whole time and they were able
to do the canary deployments, test
their stuff before completely deploying
the new versions of the application.
And the spark jobs is interesting.
So I started using Airflow.
So in Airflow, when you're writing
the DAGs, there are some Kubernetes
operators where you can actually
run your jobs within the Kubernetes.
While Airflow manages the jobs and
yeah, obviously the it's easy to
implement integrations like Datadog
for real time monitoring of it.
And also easy to maintain the security
and compliance using the RBAC stuff.
And obviously CNCF has a huge
landscape where there are new
applications are coming up, which are
very useful for different use cases.
So apart from this based on this, even if
any new healthcare companies wants to use
Kubernetes because of these advantages.
So this is, this would be
an implementation strategy,
how they can think about it.
So any company has to go
through the assessment.
Kubernetes is not really
useful in all the use cases.
Especially if your
application is very small.
A specific use case, and you don't have
many microservices kind of architecture.
It may be simple to use other
services, like directly deploying
them on EC2 instances, or use Elastic
Beanstalk, or even AWS Lambda.
So we have to first assess If Kubernetes
is the right solution for the use case
one to determine and then start planning
it, there are different ways of doing it.
First, you have to take care of
containerizing your application,
having the proper pipelines to
create this containerization.
And then start writing the Helm
charts and then automating the
deployments using the GitLab GitOps.
So plan all that stuff and then
start with one microservice.
And then do the pilot deployment
with small scale stuff.
And then you can start Moving all
your microservice into it, and then
you can scale your application.
And obviously we have to implement
the monitoring to make sure
everything is working as planned.
The future of Kubernetes looks great,
especially considering how active the
whole community is around Kubernetes.
That also includes Most of the
AML applications helping health
industry obviously comes with a
lot of data and having insights
and using them to reduce the.
Healthcare costs would be very nice.
And a Kubernetes at the forefront
of all this AI and that stuff.
So it's great to move on to
this architecture build that.
expertise within your company
so that it will be useful when
you are doing AML stuff as well.
And it's definitely very easy to
implement security stuff using Kubernetes
and the lab with the CNC landscape
growing, there are many use cases
that you can implement on Kubernetes.
So yeah, now I conclude saying
for healthcare industries for any
company in the healthcare industry,
it will be very beneficial.
to use Kubernetes with all its benefits.
That's all for today.
Thank you for listening to this talk.
Have a great day.