Hello everyone.
I'm Ashish Lia, managing director and
principal Data architect at Webster
Bank, where I lead large scale data
and AI initiatives across regulatory
reporting, enterprise data platform,
and intelligent financial system.
I'm delighted to be here to share
insight on AI data governance for
scalable compliance in modern banking.
At con 42 Cube native 2025 conference.
So AI is no longer an
experiment in banking.
It's a mission critical
from fraud detection to risk
assessment to customer engagement.
AI is enabling in every layer of
the modern financial institute.
But with this power comes a set of
governance challenges that we must
address quick glimpse of the agenda.
We will begin with the context
and introduction, why modern
governance has become imperative.
Then I'll walk you through
the evaluation of ai.
Next we'll mine the limitation of
the traditional governance model.
From there, I will introduce to
unified AI data governance framework.
And we'll explore compliance and
regulatory alignment, followed
by a real world case studies.
And then we'll close with the future
roadmap and some key take of this.
So first part of the session,
introduction and context.
Banking operates in one of the most
banking operations is one of the most
regulated environment in the world today.
Compliance failure don't just
bring financial penalties.
Sometimes it is billions.
They also damage the reputation.
And at the same time, bank face
intense pressure to innovate rapidly
deploying AI to meet the customer and
market demands traditional framework
designed for static data warehouse.
And predictable.
ETL simply cannot handle the complexity
and the dynami dynamism of AI system.
So this dual pressure one,
the compliance on one side.
And then innovation on the other
side make it essential to rethink
the whole governance process.
Jumping onto the next segment of of
our discussion that is AI evaluation
and containerization in the banking.
So over the last decade AI in banking
has grown from a small, isolated pillar.
Into an enterprise scale
system that basically enables
a core banking operations.
Think about a fraud detection model.
They take input from dozens of data
sources, analyze them in milliseconds,
and continue to learn in the real time.
So AI is no longer a tool, it
is a backbone of the modern
banking infrastructure nowadays.
Talking about the containerization
revolution to support this
scale bank has embraced the
centralization or containerization.
Kubernetes enable AI workload to run with
incredible flexibility deploying across
the hybrid cloud scaling dynamically
and updating seamlessly through
blue screen or cannery deployments.
But here is the trade off.
While the containers bring agility,
they also bring complexity.
The complexity of workload, dynamic
service meshes distributed clusters,
traditional monitoring and governance
tool struggle to keep up with all of this.
And that's where the governance
challenge become more
prominent or deepens basically.
Quickly talking about the challenges
with the traditional governance model.
Traditional governance model
falls short in four key ways.
If you just broadly look at these
four segments, it is going to
cover the challenges with the
traditional governance model.
The first one is the metadata management.
So AI produces massive amount
of constant changing metadata.
Then the second is lineage tracking.
Understanding where each feature
of the model input comes from
is nearly impossible at a scale.
Third, real time compliance.
So regulators demand continuous
monitoring of biased drift and quality.
And fourth is regulatory comp complexity.
Laws now demand explainable
fair and bias-free ai.
These are not just check boxes,
they are the continuous obligation.
As of now, just moving on to the
next segment of discussion that is
unified AI data governance framework.
So this is where new approach is required.
The unified AI data governance
framework is built for cloud native
containerized infrastructure.
It deploys governance as microservice that
is scaled dynamically, deeply integrated
with the Kubernetes orchestration.
And it uses a seamless metadata
architecture, which enable the capturing
and analysis of events in real time.
Ensuring governance isn't lagging
behind ai but operates alongside it.
The framework has three
critical components.
The first one is the metadata
orchestration engine.
The central nervous system
collecting the basically the managing
collection of managing thousands
of metadata events per second.
A second part is the intelligent lineage
tracker using the graph algorithm and
instrumentation to trace dependencies
across our distributed AI system.
Third one, the real time.
Compliance monitor monitoring constantly
evolving AI decision against internal
politics and regulatory requirement.
Together these components make governance
containers automated and intelligent.
Quickly jumping on to the next,
topic, which is to make this work.
Metadata management itself
must be high performance.
We use distributed storage.
So relational and graph databases
optimizes optimize for different queries.
Frequently access data is kept in memory
for sub million second response time.
Then a specialized index support,
time-based graph and full text queries.
And obviously metadata federation
enable queries across multiple source
without centralizing everything,
reduces reducing the cost and latency.
Tendency
Automation is crucial.
Draft the drift detection monitoring
monitors for shifts in the data concept
and performance biased detection
ensures basically the fairness across
demographic demographic groups.
And it is, it protects attributes.
And anomaly detection powered by
unsupervised machine learning spot
spots, unusual behavior in model of data.
Or maybe in other words,
governance is no longer passive.
It is active, intelligent,
and evolving alongside ai.
Security is built in from ground up.
In this case, we apply defense in depth
in depth integrating with the enterprise.
IAM system.
Access isn't just role based.
It is attribute based allowing
for the fine grained permission.
Every governance operation is no longer
with full context and all metadata
is protected through end-to-end
encryption with support for field
level encryption and tokenization.
This result compliance and security
by design not as afterthought.
Jumping onto the next segment of
the discussion, which is compliance
and regulatory alignment, which is a
crucial part of the whole equation.
The framework directly aligns with
the major regulations for GDPR.
It supports consent tracking
right management and.
The right to be forgotten.
Identifying every model trained on a
person's data for CCPA it automates
consumer right consumer rights require
and data sharing, tracking for basal
three, it supports risk modeling,
validation, tracking, and stress testing.
And it anticipates the EU AI
Act, which is classifying the AI
system by risk label and applying
the right governance controls.
This isn't reactive com compliance.
It is in a nutshell all proactive
compliance enforcement or alignment.
Just quickly looking at some
of the cases, studies, roadmap,
and maybe the conclusion.
So let's look at some real world example.
Global tier one bank rolled.
This out in phases, beginning
with the fraud detection, credit
risk, and regulatory reporting,
the results were transformative.
68% faster time to market for new AI
model, 70%, 75% reduction in the audit
preparation time through automated
reporting and 42% fewer risk events.
And thanks to early detection.
This proves that governance
does not slow innovation.
It actually accelerates it and keeps
everybody in the organization safe
looking at the future roadmap and
some of the emerging technologies,
which kind of addresses some of the
need when it comes to data governance.
So the roadmap looks ahead
to emerging technology.
Serverless compliance monitoring
functions, the trigger in the real
time as even dockers centralization or
containerization, policy enforcement.
Basically deploy directly.
So policies are deployed
directly alongside workload,
then advance explainability human
readable inside in AI decisions.
Coming next is a federated governance,
which is critical for multi-cloud,
multi organization ecosystem.
And again, this isn't just
about today's compliance.
It is in a nutshell about
preparing for tomorrow's AI
system or AI ecosystem as well.
To wrap up, AI governance is both
necessity and competitive advantage.
The unified AI governance framework shows
that bank can stay compliant, secure, and
resilient, while still innovating rapidly.
But success requires more than technology.
It needs organization commitment,
investment in skills and alignment
between governance and business
strategies bank that embraces this
balance will lead in the age of ai.
With that, I'll wrap up my session.
Thank you for your time and attention.
And I'll be happy to take
any question which might be
appropriate for the discussion.
Thank you so much.
I.