Welcome everyone.
I'm excited to be here.
Thank you for joining me today.
So imagine that you are hosting a
party and you're not sure how many
people or how many guests will show up.
You could reserve a fixed
number of table, but what if
more people come than expected?
Or what if just half people show up?
So you either be headache fighting
some for more space for more people
or stuck with empty table And waiting
resources that you reserve for So that
is a lot like traditional kubernetes
capacity scaling is working today
You allocate capacity upfront, but
the reality is things always change.
Hi, my name is Jacques Ri, a
solution architect from AWS.
So I'm here to walk you through some
capability of Carpenter and demo as well.
So let's dive in.
So now what if the table that
we mentioned at your party can
automatically be expanded or changed
based on how many guests arrive?
No S, no scrambling.
And yeah, so always the right side.
That is what exactly how
Carpenter does for our cluster.
So let's see some of the challenges
that we have today in the current test.
And also Amazon EKS with
cluster also autoscaler.
So here you have Like deployment
and also you have the existing node
already that run two parts, right?
So we have two vcpu here for m5 large
and then the Scaling up mechanism
kicks in maybe come from data or HPA
depending on the cluster and we have
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 7 parts in pending state
so Some of the parts will be scheduled
on the existing node and some of the
parts will need additional capacity.
So that's why we need cluster autoscaler.
And cluster autoscaler works
with autoscaling group.
So here.
We can have a new instance here,
which are m5 blush for two instances.
Some of the pending part will go to
the second one and just one more part
will go to the third instance here.
We can spot two things
here for the challenge.
The first thing is that it takes
longer time to spin up a new
instance for scheduling the pods.
Because cluster autoscaler
needs to work with autoscaling
group and then autoscaling group
needs to work with EC2 API.
So there are multiple steps
to spin up a new instant here.
This is a program number one and
the program number two, if you
can notify or observe that on the
third instance, we have only one
part running and we still have 1.
5 CPU left.
This one is underutilized.
So we would like to.
try to find the right size of the node
that fit the parts that we need to run.
So that is the thing that we
will will need to be solved.
And coming into the third
challenge that we have for exiting
cluster with cluster autoscaler.
So if you can see here, this is the
deployment that we already deployed.
At this based on the CPU
requests and CPU consumption.
But how about when we
have a new deployment?
That need a GPU workload or
another type of instance.
So now so this part or this
deployment cannot be scheduled
because this capacity that we have
doesn't support the GPU workload.
So the things here is that for
platform team, they need to create
a new compute, new node group.
So the first one is for
the compute node group.
And another one is for GPU node group.
So here, after that the autoscaling
can spin a new type of instance
to support a deployment which GPU.
Now it's done.
So we have Three main challenge challenges
here and we would like to see what kind
of things that carpenter can make it
Like more efficient or better let's see.
So this is the exiting one when we have
pending part and we don't have enough
capacity cluster auto, autoscaler
kicks in and then cluster autoscaler,
we work with autoscaling group.
After that autoscaling group,
we'll spin up a EC2 instance by
calling the API to EC2 fleet.
So multiple steps, just like I
mentioned, but for Carpenter.
So we don't need these two components
anymore and we don't need to go
through the auto scaling group.
Also the node group concept will be gone.
And we can bypass that by replacing
those two modules by Carpenter.
And Carpenter can spin up
their EC2 on our behalf.
The instant that Carpenter spin
up, it will be always the cheapest
one depending on the configuration.
And also it will be always the
right size for the pending parts.
So let's see how it works.
So here we have two instants that
running nine parts of our deployment.
The type of the C5 to Eclash.
And now we don't.
We don't run cluster autoscaler and
autoscaler in our cluster anymore.
We have EKS and also Carpenter installed.
How about now we have the GPU workload.
So now if we configure the Carpenter
configuration correctly, so Carpenter
can spin up a new workload which
support the GPU workload automatically.
And you don't need to do anything.
You just configure in the node pool
configuration, which we will go
through in the couple of slides.
So here the new workload can just
be scheduled in the new instance
that coming up from Carpenter.
The, I think this one is
the third problem, right?
But we can see the first and.
The first one is already solved
because we bypassed auto scaling group.
But this one is the third one, but
we will revisit the second one later.
So here is the configuration
that you can do.
That I mentioned.
That you can configure the
node pool for Carpentry.
How it will behave in your cluster.
You can have multiple not to as
well, but depending on the situation.
So here we have the configuration
that we can choose from the
different types of instance.
So you can.
Use y card here like you can use
only C or C5 or C6 or something
like that You can use M.
You can use R and you can also specify
the size like nano, micro, smaller,
large, X large Something like that.
So So depending on the use case, you
can specify wildcard or a specific one.
And how about the availability zone?
You can also specify here that you
allow Carpenter to spin up a node inside
that particular availability zone.
Or you can choose either
architecture for the CPU.
By using xic or 64 here, or you
can also use the arm 64 A MB 64.
Sorry.
And you can also use ARM 64
which is Graviton on AWS.
So Graviton provide better price
for performance compared to X.
So if your application is already
tested that it supports arm, so
you can use ARM here as well.
And the final one is the capacity type.
You can either go with on demand
or you can utilize spot as well.
If you specify both of them, it
will try to prioritize the spot.
And then you have the limit here.
The limit specify that that this node
pool can spin up maximum 100 CPU only.
When it exceeds 100 CPU, it
cannot spin up a new node anymore.
Okay, for the node pool, you can
have a single one for one cluster.
So this one is quite simple, maybe
in the test environment or dev
environment, or you have a unified
node pool configuration that supports
all the workloads in this cluster.
So it's quite simple for the
single one, single node pool.
But for a multiple one, you can have maybe
multiple team that need the different
requirements for the node configuration,
or you have the accuracy hardware.
Some of the team need the TPU workload
or like you have different image or a
MI in your workload, like one workload
use battle rocket and one workload.
Just use EKS optimize.
Or something like that.
So you can have multiple one to
support different kinds of workload.
And you can also put the
weight on the notepad as well.
If you try to prioritize the higher
weight notepad first, and then when
it run out, when it reached the limit,
maybe the first one can spin up only
like 10 CPU, depending on the, maybe
saving plan or reserving standard you
bought from AWS, and then other than
that, maybe utilize spot or on demand.
So you can use where the node pool
as well Okay so here is the Challenge
number two that we have some of
the node that are in underutilized
status so you can notice here on
the Two instance on the right side.
We have only one pod running and
it's the m5 They are m5 egg large,
which is quite big compared to the
workload is running then inside
these two workloads So in carpenter
configuration, you can also specify
that When will you do the consolidation?
Consolidation mean that it will try
to move the workload together Try to
bin packet to save the cost for you.
And you can also specify the time
that it will do the disruption
or move the workload for you.
So here I specified as zero second.
So if you try to do consideration
every time that it sees that
the node is underutilized it's
quite aggressive here, but for.
Demo purpose I just would like to spin
it up quite fast or do the consolidation
quite fast You can also specify
like one hour or 24 hours or one day
two days depending on the use case.
So now it can group together for those
two pots to inside the exiting capacity.
And this is the first que first
case, and here is the second one.
So the same you have here M five
egg large and two two of the
pots are running separately.
And when you enable the
consolidation, you try to find.
A node that fit these two parts and spin
that up and try to drain these two parts
to a new instant to save you some cost.
Let's see here.
If we group together those two parts
and then you try if we move to the
new instant, which is M5 blush.
So if we reduce the
overall cost of cluster.
Yeah you can see that we solve.
All of the three challenges
that I presented back then.
So how about some other features as well?
Recently we launched
a carpenter version 1.
0.
So this feature also support that as
well, that you can do automatically
upgraded by detecting drift.
Of the cabinet configuration There is a
custom resource another custom resource.
It's called ec2 node class for here you
can specify the image that you are that
you would like to use the security group
and also the Availability zone as well.
Here this, under the spec, we
specify that we would like to use
the latest image that it comes out.
So it means that if AWS
update the EKS optimized a MI.
For the new version, Carpenter will
try to upgrade every workload under
Carpenter and upgrade to the new one
and also try to drain the pods for us.
So this is, this can be done
automatically and it will force every
time that we have a new, um, AMI for
The ami that you are using so the
new version comes and then it will be
Automatically upgrade but sometimes
you can also do something like this.
You can pin the version that you would
like to use this one when the updates
come out, it will not be automatically
updated and then you can change the
value inside the EC2 node class later
when you would like to do the upgrade.
And this one can be specified with
the custom AMI that you have as well.
So quite flexible for this one.
So now coming into the demo
that I prepared for you.
So let's see here.
What do we have?
Let's see.
So for the nodes, we have two nodes here.
The type is a three, three,
three large, two nodes.
And I think, so let's see the workload.
What kind of workload that we have.
Okay, we have coordinates in kube system.
We have carpenter.
This is the controller.
So I spin up for two pods for under
the deployment because I would
like to provide the resiliency and
Then I have the my workload here.
The name is inflate and the replica
is zero now let's see What kind of
configuration that I have in that
inflate deployment So it's quite basic.
The name is inflate, and
the name space is inflate.
And the CPU request here is one CPU.
I didn't specify the memory requirement.
And it will just pull down
from the public ECR repository.
And it did nothing it just reserved
the cpu that's all I think for
now and How about the node pool
configuration that we went through?
So what kind of thing that I configure?
Let's see Okay, I think
Yeah, we have only one node pool here.
The name is the default.
You can have multiple
just like I mentioned.
And the version is version one, of course,
because we launched as a stable version.
Consolidation policy now is when
it's empty and we change later.
And the consolidation
time is five seconds.
The limit here, this node tool can
spin up only 10 CPU only, after that
it cannot spin up a new instance.
Architecture is x86.
The capacity type is on demand only and
Instant type here this node tool can
spin up a C type, M type, and R type.
So let's see What type of
things that it will happen
when we scaled up our workload?
Yep.
So we spin up five replica here.
And so we have five
pending pots now or so.
You can see it's detect quite fast
and it's spin up a new one for us.
It's C six a two X large.
It's not ready yet because it take
some time for the node to be ready,
but yeah, it's super fast to detect
and this one is faster than auto
scaling group and cluster auto scaling,
so it takes some time for that.
So now, it's also spin up two parts.
It is the cool proxy and also couplet.
Yeah, so all of them already scheduled
five parts and it's the flat right
side for This kind of pending parts.
So let's see the logs to understand it
further this is the log from carpenter.
So here you request for five parts that
we see in the pending parts, right?
And then Carpenter, we try to come
up with the right size instant.
So here we request for five CPU,
the number of part is seven because
it include kubelet and kubeproxy.
So we try to search through the
instant type that we specify in
the node pool, like 45, 46 yeah.
It's in that time and it came
up with c6a2xlash in this
availability zone with on demand
type and this one support 58 pods.
This one is depending on the number
of elastic network interface.
Now it's already registered and
ready to to host the pods for you.
Yeah, that is a lot.
How about now we scaled up to 20.
So some of them can be scheduled
in the existing node, and some of
them will be scheduled in the new
instance that's coming up here.
So it comes up to C6a
large, but we still have some
pending pods there, 13, right?
I think C6a large maybe can
support like one or two.
Let's see now it's not ready yet.
So we need to wait until it's ready
to see what kind of pending part
that we have Yeah, just speed just
schedule just one pot inside the
new instance and we still have 12
parts that is in pending state here.
Yeah, you can see here as
well and So can you guess?
Why character don't spin up anyone because
it reached the limit that we specified
that this node pool can spin up only
just like 10 CPU only and now it reached
the limit so How about we increase that?
Let's see Yeah, we will increase that to
1000 from 10 then hopefully it can spin
up a new node to support 12 pending parts.
So now it's quite fast.
You can see so now it's
been up a C6A4XLarge
here.
The limit already changed is 1000.
C6A4XLarge and it will fit
over the 12 pending parts here.
Soon, so I need to wait for a
cool plan and cool proxy here
Okay.
Yeah, it's there.
And it's all the pods is running.
I would like to add arm as well.
The ground, we don't
want to set some costs.
And I also would like
to add the spot as well.
For a spot, you need to make sure that
your workload can tolerate for the risk
disruption that we call back the spot.
Okay.
Let's check the configuration that
we add the spot and also the arm.
I just architecture as well.
Okay.
It's up there somewhere here so you
specify X86 which is AMD 64 and arm 64.
Yeah crowd it on one and Spots as well.
I think something will comes up here
when it fight a spot for us because
it's cheaper It's deleting this note.
So it's right try to drain some pots
out Already drain to the extinct one.
Maybe the lower one And
coming up with the spot soon.
Okay.
Let's wait a little bit.
Let's see.
Okay here.
So we have C 60 G means Graviton, which is
arm and from on demand, we change to spot.
Here is much cheaper, like up to 70%.
Cheaper than the only one.
Okay.
Just wait to it to be ready and then
it will try to drain the pods for us It
will call it on and also drain for us.
Yeah
Okay, now it's working for a spot
and grab it on which help us to
save some cost of our cluster Can
we it will delete the old one here?
How about we change the consolidation
policies policy from when empty to
when empty or underutilized Let's
see and here Consolidation policy
from when empty to when empty or
underutilized under five second
As I say you can specify like one hour
or 24 four hour do the consolidation if
you don't want to have any disruption
Okay, I will try to Reduce the number
of the workload here so that we have
some underutilized node here we have one
five pots and 20 percent of consumption
for CPU and It will try to come up
with a new node and drain for us No
to make sure that our cluster is like
a more utilized Yep Now we have it.
This one is also underutilized.
So we'll try to spin up a new one
and then move all the parts for us.
Yeah.
Deleting the other one
that don't need anymore.
So this is how it works for
consolidation and also some other
things like architecture, spot and
also the type that we can select.
How about now we would like
to do 10 and toleration.
So we specify that Carpenter will
spin up a part, a node with a 10.
The key is my name is Chakri.
Here, so the node that spin up
by Carpenter will have this 10.
So the deployment need to have
the toleration for this one.
I will try to increase the
number here of the workload.
Oh, unfortunately that it will
fall into the node that we have
already, then it can be scheduled.
So now we add some more.
So these some of the pods
here will be in pending.
Because The Carpentry cannot
spin up a node for it.
Deployment doesn't have a
toleration for the 10 key chakras.
So cannot spin up here.
So now we would like to add the
toleration into the deployment so that
Carpentry can spin up a node for us.
So let's see.
Okay.
Just add the toleration
here in our deployment.
Let's check.
Oh, it's just spin up a new one for us.
You can see ccgs for Eclodge.
So let's see in the deployment
that we have the iteration.
That I just added.
Okay.
Here is the iteration.
That's why Carpenter can
spin up a new node for us.
And yeah, schedule our parts.
Boop.
Okay.
Okay, that's all I think I think the
final one Is about the ac spread so
carpentry will respect anything that
you configure in your deployment So
here I would like to spread my ac.
From each other And you can see
that a lot of things that happening.
So you try to spin up a new node
for supporting different ac So this
one will ensure that your workload
will have higher resiliency.
So this one is the configuration that
I specify in the deployment that I
would like to use topology spread.
That if it cannot satisfy,
will not schedule.
You can see that do not schedule that.
You can schedule anyway as well,
but this one I would like to show
that Carpenter, we respect anything
that we put in a deployment.
So we would like to check when
it's done that we have multiple
AC for our workload here.
So you can split, you can,
okay, it's deleting one of
them, maybe just wait for it.
So here we have AC1A, 1B, 1C.
So let's see again because it's deleting.
Yep, I think we have all of the AC here.
A, B, C for our workload.
Yeah, you try to balance the AC for us.
That's all I would like to show.
A lot of things that you
can explore by yourself.
You can also read to the best
practice that we have online.
So for onboarding to Carpenter, so
you can install Carpenter by using
Hamshark and One best practice here
that do not run the Carpenter on the
node that It's managed by Carpenter.
Otherwise, it will just delete the node
that runs Carpenter and stop working.
You can run Carpenter on Fargate
or different node groups.
And you can also migrate from
Cluster, Autoscaler as well.
The guide is there.
And you can explore.
So let's sum up.
Also, CloudHunter is fast, it's quite
simple, but it's quite powerful.
It's cost effective because it will try to
reduce the cost for you by consolidation.
And also it's Kubernetes because
it's open source and now we have,
we support multiple cloud already.
And yeah, I think it's awesome.
Thank you so much.