Hey everyone, my name is Jeru.
I'm currently serving as ASAP
integration Arctic Manager at PWC.
So over past 14 plus years of
experience, I have specialized in AI
driven integration middleware solutions
and enterprise IT transformations.
Working with global enterprises on
some of the most complex digital
inter integration challenges.
My career journey spans leading AI
power, SAP integration strategies
enabling multi-cloud transformations,
ensuring regulatory CO across GGPR and
H-I-P-A-A and driving cent acquisitions
technology integration for Fortune.
500. Firms.
So today I'm excited to share
with you all a case study that
demonstrates how Kubernetes need
to AI integration is transforming
SAP mergers and, acquisitions.
So if we go to the agenda,
this is what we cover.
What we will cover today is the
challenge landscape, the revolutionary
approach, the technical architecture
business impact strategic implications.
So by the end, I hope you will
see how AI and Cloud Native Tech.
Technologies are fundamentally
reshaping enterprise integration.
So the traditional mergers and acquisition
or integration challenge, so mergers
and acquisitions are among the toughest.
It challenges.
So when two, a large organizations
match their SAP landscapes spanning
multiple regions customizations
and data volumes must integrate.
Seamlessly, the traditional approach
brings long timelines, sometimes
years massive consulting cost business
disruptions that risk customer experience.
So add to that regulatory
complexity, GGPR.
So H-I-P-A-A and, need for
zero downtime and it creates.
The perfect strom of complexity.
So these are all the, challenges.
And if we go into the complex
the integration landscape, let's
break this down further, right?
So the technicality complex so multiple.
Multi different layers of systems
like legacy, SCP, some databases,
and then legacy migrations and
the data volumes in terabyte.
So these are all the technical complex.
Cities we face on daily basis and
regulatory complex, requirements like
global compliance frameworks and then
business continuity, like keeping
the lights on with no disruption.
So this is why traditional integration
models often fail to deliver efficiently.
So if we take about the revolutionary
approach Kubernetes native ai.
Integration.
Instead of treating integration as a
slow manual process, we reimagined it as
a cloud native workload powered by ai.
We used Kubernetes
orchestration for scalability.
Containerized AI modules like the
flexibility in deployment, mission
learning automation for mapping
analysis and migration continuous
learning models that improve over time.
So this distributor intelligence
means AI could handle multiple
integration tasks in parallel
cutting time and effort dramatically.
So how it works, right?
So in, in theory, we know I have
explained like these many things
like ation the modules, mission
learning, continuous learning modules,
and the distribution intelligence.
But in this is the theory, but in
practice, you know how it works, right?
So AI models deployed as a micro, if
you see the picture here it act, it
deploys as a microservices in congen,
each specializing in mapping data
validation a code analysis, and then
transformer networks identified a
complex master data patterns and CNNs.
Analyzed AAP code for business logic.
Graph neural networks optimized
SAP dependencies, also Kubernetes
orchestration, ensure fault, autoscaling,
and high performance because the system
process for 500, a hundred thousand
records per second across 10 terabyte
data sets a scale traditional approach.
Couldn't match it all.
So that is the, technical architecture
we have in in, in, in a practice.
And then what is the timeline?
The accelerated timeline, if
we follow this, the impact was
like transformational, like the
timelines reduced by 50 to 70%.
What once took like 12 to 18 months.
Now we took four to six per six months.
Also the processing speed if
half a million record per second.
Also, the automation eliminated
manual mapping, like reducing
human errors and cost.
Parallel processing ensure
rapid rapid conflict resolution
and continuous operations.
He some of the live examples of,
the recent examples, what we have
had here, we have had like terabytes
of data migration, so master data.
When it comes to master data, many of we
migrate materials, vendors, customers.
Vendor banks, profit center, cost
center, the PTM related, like
the batch traceability metrics.
Bill of ma, bill of mapping and
the routing, the employee id.
So many master data objects we have
to migrate during the master data load
period where, it has it terabytes of data.
So I know or we all know business
usually provides the data to the
consultants, but what if the data
quality is not up to the mark?
So we it's very simple to say, Hey,
that is the data you have given.
So that is how we load it.
But instead out of the box, we.
Utilize these AI modules, these
mission learn, learning tools that
will check the data quality as well.
So from each functional consultant,
we have taken the prerequisites
of, the checks, what we need to do.
For example, vendor master.
These columns are mandatory.
Or maybe the delivery date should
be, between these time zones.
It shouldn't be the past two.
It's a very minor example, but.
It would make a lot of sense if you
get all the world data, if you work,
if you go through this workflow, you
would get the errors on spot in instead
of waiting for longer period after
go live and impact the operations.
So that is how we have created a
workflow based on the inputs that we have
received from functional and business.
So we will cover that in future also.
So here the key is business.
IT collaboration is a key for any.
Successful project.
So with all the inputs we
have created a workflow.
We have checked the data quality.
So it's called like preload sign off.
So before loading the data, we got
the preload sign off from these
AI tools and using the mission
linear technologies and then.
We started loading the data, which
resulted, a hundred percent data quality.
Also when it comes to critical operational
transactional data, yes, you need
open sales order, open patch order.
When you are dealing with the ERP
customers you need the customer number.
Shipped tools, all those details
we load as part of the critical
operational transactional data with these
checks, again, using the AI modules.
And when it comes to financial
transactional data loads, of
course you have to load AP, ar,
fixed assets, gl, non GL balances.
Stuff and you had to
match the trial balance.
So that is a key in any of
the digital transformation.
So we have used these a, AI tools
the, using the SAP integration and
Kubernetes, to help functional and
business it people, to speed up and, to
have a smooth digital transformation.
So he, this is his like, smallest
example, like how we accelerated the
integration timeline and then how it
impacted the cost and efficiency, right?
So beyond speed, the AI automation, it it
up, it deliver like massive cost benefits.
For example, 78% reduction
in integration cost.
85% reduction in manual effort
replacing armies of consultants,
and 92% reduction in rework cycles.
Thanks to AI driven quality
validations, like I mentioned,
the tools that we have used.
So this was not just faster, it was
smarter, linear, and more reliable.
So this is how we have optimized the
cost and also increased the efficiency.
And then AI driven data
mapping and transformation.
So the AI.
Could recognize data patterns and
automatically suggest mapping and generate
transformation logic for conversions,
integrity checks and business rules.
It provides continuous validation,
correcting errors in real time.
Also it predicts potential risk and even
resolve certain issues automatically.
So in fact, 93% of potential issues were
caught before impacting the operations.
A huge leap from traditional
reactive approaches.
So what are all the strategic
implications, of these?
Using these ai kuber net SAP
integration tools, right?
So this is not just about one project.
It's about rethinking mergers and
acquisition integrations entirely.
So integration becomes innovation,
a source of competitive advantage.
A company's gain reusable AI
framework for ongoing transformations.
Also, employees can move faster with
greater acquisition flexibility.
So in essence, AI transforms integration
from a cost center into a growth
enabler, so as we look forward,
companies must invest in data quality
and governance build internal,
enterprise in ai, especially in,
we have, we all know that there are
so many cloud native technologies.
So they, there should be
a dedicated in general.
Ize in AI and cloud native technology.
We are, the technologies keep on changing,
likewise, we have to brush up our, coming,
these new technologies and get up to this.
Speed with the as, as we are growing,
as we are changing and make sure
we have we usually, build internal
expertise in ai, cloud Native Tech.
So not just by tools, right?
So the team should be up.
Speed to match with the technology
that is rapidly changing.
Also, like I mentioned before we
encourage business IT collaboration
since AI needs real business.
Context as a it yes, you know
about your tool, how the technology
is changing how the ai, is can
definitely helpful to to succeed.
Yeah.
Or to avoid certain issues, right?
So as a it, but what issues
you need to concentrate.
Like you have 1, 2, 3, 4 out of four.
What is P one out of four P ones, right?
So those important details and all the
knowledge has to come from business.
Hey, this is what we have.
During this digital transformation, these
are the complex requirements I have where
I need these as a first phase, and maybe
out of these three, these two are very
business critical where we need to see
how ai, this Cuban and SAP integration.
Can be useful.
So it's all business IT collaboration.
Since AI needs a real business context and
then approach integration as a long-term
capability, not a one-off project.
So when you as a integration consultant
or as integration architect, when
you develop any of the logic for
one of the requirements, so you
need to think big out of the box.
Okay.
For simple example,
okay, so this is a EDI.
PO mapping where we need to
map one field to another field.
And this is the logic I have.
What if.
Another customer comes, is
this mapping sufficient?
Or maybe I need to, develop the mapping
a new way that it would be accommodate
or easily maintainable when new customer
comes in, utilize the similar mapping.
So that is how the approach integration
as a long term capability, not just
for one of the project, so those.
Who do this will be a best
position to lead the next wave
of this digital transformation.
So thank you for your time.
I hope this session showed you how AI
forward Cunet native SAP integration
is changing the game for enterprises
during mergers and acquisitions.
Then I would be very happy
to take your questions.
Thank you.