Hello everyone.
Today I'm going to share practical
insights on scaling Kafka on Kubernetes
to handle extreme streaming workloads,
specifically how to architect and optimize
for over a hundred thousand messages
per second in production environment.
I'm an independent researcher
focusing on cloud native
architecture and distributed systems.
This presentation draws from real
world implementation experience with
high throughput streaming platforms.
Let's start with the problem space.
Modern containerization application are
generating unprecedented data volumes.
We are talking millions of messages per
second that need real time processing.
The challenge isn't just about raw volume.
We need Kubernetes native streaming
platforms that can scale dynamically
with workload demands while maintaining
stateful streaming workloads with
low latencies and high throughput.
This intersection of stateful
applications and container infrastructure
creates unique architectural
challenges that we will address today.
So why Kafka Kubernetes
in the first place?
Firstly, continued ization.
Kubernetes gives us automatic
scaling, self-healing, and
sophisticated resource management.
For Kafka clusters.
These capabilities are built
into the platform rather than
requiring custom tooling.
Second cloud native benefits.
We get seamless integration with cloud
services, persistent storage solutions,
and service mesh architectures.
This integration reduces operational
complexity significantly.
Third, dynamic scaling horizontal pod
auto scaling lets our Kafka deployment
adapt to traffic patterns automatically
while maintaining streaming performance.
This elasticity is critical
for cost optimization and
handling variable workloads.
The foundation of any successful
Kafka on Kubernetes deployment
rests on three pillars, stateful set
configuration, which is essential.
We deploy Kafka brokers as stateful
sets, ensuring order deployment,
stable network identities, and
position storage attachment.
This is critical because Kafka
brokers are inherently stateful.
Our persistent volume strategy
uses optimized storage classes,
specifically SSD, backed volumes with
high IOPS to meet Kafka's demanding
log segment performance requirements
and low latency access patterns.
Finally, service mesh integration
provides secure interpod communication
with traffic management and
comprehensive observability.
This gives us encrypted communication
and detailed metrics without
modifying the application code.
Resource allocation
requires careful tuning.
Here's what works in production.
CPO requests should be two
to four cores per broker.
This provides this, provide
enough processing power for high
throughput workloads without.
Over provisioning memory
allocation is critical.
We typically configure eight to 16 GB
heap sized optimization per broker.
The exact size depends on your
platform count, partition count,
and message retention policies.
Resource limits are equally
important to prevent noisy
neighbors in multi-tenant clusters.
We use the guaranteed QOS class
for critical Kafka workloads,
ensuring resources are in
preempted under cluster pressure.
Proper resource allocation ensures
consistent performance under varying loads
while preventing resource contention.
This is specifically important in shared
cluster environment Storage is where
many Kafka on Kubernetes deployment fail.
Let me walk through our three part
strategy First storage classes.
We use SSD based storage
classes with high.
IOP is specifically log segments.
Kafka's sequential right patterns
benefit anomalously from fast storage
and the low latency access patterns are
essential for the consumer performance.
Second volume configuration.
Persistent volume claims must be
sized according to your retention
policies and replication factors.
Undersizing here leads to frequent disc
pressure issues and broker instability.
And the third one, the performance
tuning file system optimization and mount
options dramatically impact throughput.
For example, using XFS with specific
mount options can improve right
performance by 30 to 40% compared
to the default configurations.
Network performance is often
an overlooked bottleneck.
We address this through three mechanisms.
Network segmentation uses isolated
network policies for Kafka clusters.
This ensures security without performance
degradation a common issue when
network policies are too restrictive.
Load balancing configuration
is optimized for streaming
workloads with session affinity.
This is important because Kafka
clients benefit from sticky
connections to specific brokers.
Bandwidth optimization involves
network performance tuning for
high throughput message processing.
This includes TCP buffer tuning network,
plugin selection, and sometimes dedicated
network interfaces for Kafka traffic.
Auto scaling stateful applications
like Kafka requires a nuanced approach.
Custom metrics are key standard
CPU and memory metrics.
Don't tell the full story.
We implement HPA based on Kafka
specific metrics like consumer-like
and partition throughput.
These metrics directly indicate
when more capacity is needed.
Our scaling policies use intelligent
algorithms that account for the
stateful nature of the Kafka brokers.
You can't just terminate
brokers instantly.
Partition leadership
needs to be transferred.
Replicas need to be reassigned.
The scaling policy must respect
these operational requirements.
Admins traffic adaption also ensures
dynamic adjustment to varying
message volumes while maintaining
partition balance across the clusters.
Unbalanced partitions can create hotspots
that negate the benefits of scaling.
Okay.
Multi cluster deployment.
Enterprise deployments typically
require multi Kafka clusters.
We manage this through helm charts,
which provide the standardized
deployments across environments
with configurable parameters.
This consistency reduces
operational lenders and enables a
rapid deployment in new regions.
Global distribution implements like
cross region application for disaster
recovery and reduced latency users
in different geographic regions
can consume from the local clusters
while maintaining data consistency,
ease maintained through mirrormaker,
which provides reliable cluster data
synchronization with exactly one somatics.
This is critical for maintaining
data integrity across regions.
Operational excellence requires
treating infrastructure as code.
Our GitHub's workflow
has three components.
Infrastructure as code means all Kafka
cluster configurations are managed through
kit repositories with version control.
Every change is tracked,
reviewed, and audited.
Automated deployments use CICD
pipelines that trigger cluster updates
based on configuration changes.
This eliminates manual deployment
steps and associated errors.
Rollback capabilities are built in.
We implement safe deployment
practices with automated
rollbacks on configuration errors.
If a change causes cluster instability,
we can automatically revert
within minutes rather than ours.
You can't manage what you can't measure.
Our monitoring Slack
stack has three layers.
Prometheus integration, which
export JMX metrics for comprehensive
cluster monitoring, we track broker
health partition metrics, consumer
group lag and resource utilization.
Grafana dashboards provide real
time visualization of throughput,
latency, and resource allocation.
Operators can quickly identify
bottlenecks and trending issues.
Alerting rules, implement proactive
notification for performance
degradation and capacity thresholds.
We alert before users
experience issues, not after.
This includes alerts on consumer
lag, spikes under replicated
partitions, and this space thresholds.
Now let's talk some numbers
in production deployments.
Using these patterns, we
consistently achieve hundred
thousand messages per second.
Sustained throughput with
optimized configurations.
This isn't burst traffic.
This is a continuous processing
under production load.
Less than five millisecond P 99 latency
maintained even under very high loads.
Low latency is very critical for real-time
applications and achieving sub millisecond
P 99 at the scale demonstrates the
effectiveness are optimization strategies.
99%, 99.9% availability With zero
down to deployments, we can perform
rolling upgrades, scale clusters,
and handle load failures without
dropping messages or causing downtime.
These metrics demonstrate the
effectiveness of Cloud Native Kafka,
deployments in production, environment
handling, demanding streaming workloads.
This isn't theoretical.
These are real production numbers.
Disaster recovery isn't optional.
For critical streaming infrastructure.
We implement a layered approach.
Kubernetes operators provide
automated backup restoration
and failover capabilities.
These operators understand Kafka's
operational requirement and can perform
complex recovery procedures automatically.
Cross region backups ensure we can
recover from regional failures.
We maintain topic configuration,
consumer group offsets, and ECLS in
specific regions or in separate regions.
Automated recovery procedures
are tested regularly through
kios engineering practices.
We deliberately fail components to ensure
our recovery mechanisms work as expected.
Data, application and consistency
guarantees ensure that failing
over to backup cluster doesn't
result in data loss or duplication.
This requires careful configuration
of replication factors and
acknowledgement settings.
Together these capabilities
ensure business continuity for
critical streaming applications.
As we wrap up, I want to emphasize
three key points, strategic planning,
proper resource allocation and
storage optimization aren't optional.
They are critical for sustained
high throughput performance.
Many deployments fail because they
underestimate these requirements.
Second, embrace cloud native approaches.
Leverage Kubernetes native
platforms for scaling, monitoring,
and operational excellence.
Don't fight against the
platform, use its capabilities.
Third, be production ready from day one.
Implement comprehensive monitoring,
GitHub workflows and disaster
recovery from the beginning.
These aren't things you add later.
They are foundational requirements.
Building Kafka on Kubernetes at scale
requires careful attention to these
architecture patterns, but the result
is a resilient, scalable streaming
platform that can handle massive
workloads with operational simplicity.
And thank you all for your attention.
I'm happy to take any questions about.
Any aspect of scaling Kaf
Kubernetes from regional specific
configuration recommendations to
troubleshooting any common challenges.
You can connect with me after the
talk if you'd like to discuss your
specific use case in more detail.