Okay, so hello everyone and
thank you for watching my
session about the perfect time.
I am Christoph Gig, a cloud
search architect at Hagi Group,
and also I'm MVP Microsoft.
Before going deep into, at that point in
time, let me just remind remind me, remind
us what is a microservices architecture?
Why do we often choose a
microservices architecture?
First, we want our microservices
to be focused on a specific
business aspect of our solution.
This allow us to gain.
More autonomy, flexibility,
and scalability.
And it allows also the teams to be
more flexible independent into the
development and the deployment.
In summary, what we want smaller
services, but more efficient.
Of course, this comes also
with some difficulties.
So for example, the debugging
process and the testability.
For example, you want to debug a
feature or a fix a bug that implies a
lot of services of your architecture.
You have to run all your services
in your local environment.
This increase the complexity of
your architecture and, you also
have some difficulties with the, in
interdependencies of your service.
At the end, you just doesn't
understand what is going on in
your solution and also you don't
master and you can manage properly
the flows inside your application.
To summarize this, it's difficult
to migrate from a monolithic block
to a microservices architecture.
And today the languages and the
framework that you use are not
natively oriented for microservices
at the end, about hosting model.
It's not so much true today,
but application tied to a
specific infrastructure.
Platform with limited
portability to cloud or Edge.
And that's why Dapper
comes to the landscape.
Dapper is the acronym for distributed
Application Runtime, and it's it's
portable, even driven runtime for
building distributed application.
And you can run it in
the cloud or in the edge.
Dapper comes with very specific objectives
for you and for developer teams.
It comes with best practices
and some building blocks.
So for example if you install dapper
on the local machines, it'll on the
shelf comes with some blocks that you
can already use for your applications.
We will go through it
just a little bit later.
You can use any language or
framework that you want with dapper.
And it's C Driven, it's a
non-commercial initiative and it's
into the CNCF ecosystem today.
It'll allow us.
To adapt some standards
into our architecture.
I will come to it just later also.
And it's built on a consistent
portable and open APIs.
That means that you can very easily
interact with the run time if you want to.
It's platform agnostic from cloud to edge.
That's because it's built on
containers technology and it's really
sensible with pluggable components.
Today they are more than a hundred
components that you can use on the
shell with de but of course you
can create your own components with
the extensible aspect of dapper.
About the basis of dapper.
First you have to understand that
dapper implements the sidecar pattern.
That means that when you launch
your service automatically,
dapper sidecar will come in live
just aside of your service and.
With this side care partner, that means
that every interaction that you do outside
of your service will be handled by dapper.
That means that your code only
knows about dapper as an external
dependencies, and that's.
That's only that your call will know.
For example, when you want to invoke
another service or you want to
store some data in the database, you
will go through Dapper to perform
this action and your call will.
Your code will be agnostic from
the the technical implementation
of the component and the end.
For example, we have here two example.
You can interact with Daer through H TT
P or GRPC, and the first example will
tell Daer to store some data into the
state that you mentioned into the URL.
So you tell the pro.
To store the data and dapper will
take care of the implementation
details of the database at the end.
It depend, in fact it's everything
about configuration into dapper about
the component you have at the end.
The second example is service
to service invocation.
So here the example it said that I
want to invoke the service, my app
and the method new order in that.
In that service, that's mean that
dapper will automatically perform a
service discovery process and it'll
automatically also call that method in
the right declared service into dapper.
Like I said, you can use any languages
or framework you want with Dapper
because it built on ER technology.
And then you will call some H-T-T-P-A-P-I
or G-R-P-C-A-P-I to perform some
external interaction that you could
needs to perform for you business logic.
So you can do.
Service to service, invocation,
state management, pop sub resource
binding and triggers and actors
pattern if you want to distributed
tracing and the secrets and so on.
So what you need to keep in mind is
that dapper his a set cap pattern.
And when you want to perform some
external operation, you will go
through dapper to perform that action.
So you code, your code will only focus on
the business aspects of your solutions.
And everything else will be handled
by by dapper all the external Interac.
So here is an example of the
sidecar model I just mentioned.
So when you have one service, one
sidecar will appear just aside of your
application, and then you will call
some API to perform some some action on
the, so you can invoke another method
in another application you can store.
Or retrieve some states stored in a
database that you configure into daper.
You can publish a message, so you can
publish and receive messages with Daper,
and you can retrieve some secrets that
are stored and handled by by dapper.
For example here is a local example of
a very simple architecture with daper.
So I have a service A and a service
B, and each of those services ha
has a side car, a dapper sidecar
just aside of tool service.
And then after that, I
will configure dapper.
About the state store I want to use, or
the event broker I want to use, and so on.
For example, for the state store,
you could use a DBE or Cosmo
DB or Redis for the purpose.
You could use Arabic MQ
service Boost what you want.
So the implementation details is only
into the dapper configuration, but your
service doesn't know about this detail.
It only knows about how
to interact with dapper.
And I can just show an example of of that.
So we'll just switch to my vs.
Code editor and then.
Here I opened one of the repository
GitHub repository of Daper, which
is the QuickStarter repository.
And inside of it you have a lot of example
that you can reproduce for you solution.
Here, what I will show you is
a very simple example so that
you can understand how it works.
For example, here I have
an not GS application.
That not GS application expose a
very simple a i to get an order
and to create here a new order.
In for the application to get the
data, it'll store a new order and get
a new order from a particular database.
But here the application
doesn't know about the database.
It only knows about Daper.
So here with the URL, we will
use to store and retrieve.
Do data.
We are working locally,
so we will use local host.
The DA Power is by
default 3000 and, oh no.
3000, sorry, is for the
no GS application port.
It'll use 3,500 ports for the
for the port for Daper, in fact.
And then I will use here the statue RL
and I give to Daper a name of the state.
That was configured for Daper so that he
will know that this particular database is
tied to a particular name, and that's what
I will use in my code to store the data.
In order to launch the.
The application with dapper,
I will use the dapper CLI.
So first you have to install the
dapper CLI in your local machine.
Everything is explained
on the documentation.
I will not.
Deep dive into it because it,
it's really simple and everything
is explained on the website.
And then you have to launch the
dapper in it common line in order
to install everything you need
on your local machine for dapper.
So I've already done it in the past.
So then when everything is set
up, you can use the Dapper Run.
Command with the app ID option.
This tells dapper what is your ID
of this particular service into
your microservices ecosystem.
And this ID should be unique
per service, of course.
So here I will use the option
with the Node app value.
The app is like I said 3000.
And I will, just to be sure,
I will use this option to tell
us which poor Daper will use.
So Daper, HTT, PPOR.
And at the end, I will just tell Daer
which command he need to use in order
to launch my no just application.
So to launch a no J application,
I will just use node.
App es So this is the
command I need to use.
I'm just not in the right
in the right folder.
So let me just jump into the right folder.
Hello world,
and no.
So I will just copy past.
The common line, so dapper
run up Id upper and not ab Bs.
When you launch that command
you have a lot of logs.
In fact I will not go into everything,
but just to show you what the portal
tells when you launch the runtime.
So first you have in blue
the logs of your application.
So for example, here I can see that my.
Applications is correctly
running on the, on this port.
And then about the dapper logs, you can
see that it's loading a lot of components.
So the state store components here, we
have a Redis component, which will be
used by the example to store my orders.
What you need to know actually is when
you launch dapper the first time, it'll,
when you launch an install dapper the
first time, it'll install some container
images on your local machine, and it'll
in fact install a Redis container.
In in your machine.
And when you launch the dapper or
runtime, it'll automatically launch a
new container, a new Redis container,
and that's what is configured by default.
When you launch dapper and by default,
this will use the Redis State Store.
So here is the component for the state
store, and by default, there is also
another configuration into Daper for.
Pop sub component.
And this is also release.
So if I check the log, I can see
that everything works correctly.
Application discovered on this pro
not app, everything sh sounds okay.
Daper initialized that you running.
Okay.
So apparently everything is good.
I will just show you.
Something else.
Yeah, I will create a new terminal here.
And what does that sample do is?
So we have one microservices
in in in no gs, and we have
another one in Python here.
This Python is only a simple client
for the node node application.
And it'll only create new
order in a loop infinitely.
Indefinitely.
And this will use Daper as a sidecar
for the patent application in order
to call the nudges application.
So the patent application
doesn't know or doesn't call
directly the no G application.
It'll.
Only called dapper and dapper will
forward the request to the right service.
I will launch that, that
that application too.
So
tutorial hello word,
Python, and also for Python.
I will also use the Dapper Run app
id Python app, and then I will just
tell Dapper which command will he
should use to launch the application.
So Python app from pi.
Like I said this is just an infinite
loop that call the API in no Gs.
And then I can see that in my log from the
NO GS application, the Python application
correctly reach the no GS application
to create new order in the loop.
So that's really easy.
So let, as you can see, my code is really
clean in term of external dependencies.
I only use Daper with standard API.
So here it's HTTP and when I want to
perform some external action service
to service invocation State store for
the Knowledges application, I only use
Daper and I don't know implementation
detail of my infrastructure dependencies.
Okay, so I will just stop this and
then we can go again to the slide.
This is just a recap of
the the demo I just showed.
So we have a frontend application
and a backend application.
Both has their own side card app and
when I want to invoke one service from.
From the first microservice.
So for example, the front end I call
dapper through a standard a PA, and then
dapper will automatically forward the
request to the right microservice behind.
That's how the service invocation works.
Of course.
At the end, the ultimate goal is
to deploy in production DAPER.
And then the recommended
way is to use Kubernetes.
So when you initialize DAPER on
Kubernetes, it'll install four
system pods into Kubernetes.
So I won't go.
In deep details into each pod because it's
well explained into the documentation and
it's not the the goal of this session,
but you have the actor placement pod.
The sidecar injector po the century.
This is for security and operator.
For example, the sidecar injector
will handle all the injection of
the sidecar pattern into each po.
Of of your microservices architecture.
So each each container that he's deployed.
Into Kubernetes.
It'll be added to a pod, and that pod
will have a new sidecar instantiated
into the pod with your container.
And then when you have this setup
you just have to configure Daper
like you will do in the local mode.
You configure Daper to tell.
Which infrastructure component
you want to use for the resource
binding state store and so on, and
you code into your microservice.
We only talk to dapper into your cluster.
In order to perform some
external external operation.
And then with that architecture,
you can deploy Daper and your
service everywhere you want.
It could be Azure, double ES, or
on the Edge OnPrem as you want.
So about dapper components.
So we have plenty of component for
each category that dapper supports.
The configuration is done through ML
file files, and you will put here every
details, in fact, every implementation,
details that dapper needs to needs to
to get to connect to those components.
So you have a dedicated DML file
for state store, for purpose
broker, binding SE store, and so on.
And for example, for State store, if
you choose A SDW db you have one YML
file that will handle or will get all
the connection details to in order in
order for Daer to connect to that db.
It's the exact same principle for
everything about daper components.
Here is an example of a
pop pattern with Daper.
So here I have three microservices.
That needs to exchange messages
between those microservices.
So first on the left, your application
will post a new message or publish
a new message here to Daper.
Daper will forward.
The message to the correct broker
that is configured with the YAML file.
So here is, it's already c
and then all the service that
listen to that particular.
Topic will get the message.
How it works is in that way your service
a b will expose an a p that Daper will
call when he when he when it receive
a new message that, how it works.
So it'll push a message to a
particular API declared in in taper.
For the telemetry, it's mostly
the same the same principle.
So dapper implements the
open telemetry standard.
So all the tools that that
implement that standard a site,
Datadog premises and so on.
You can use any component you want.
Link it, linked it to to Daper.
And you can just, in your application
log what you want in your call, in your
code, and DAPER will gather the log
and send it automatically to your tool.
So it's and then with that principle,
you can change the tool whenever
you want, because you have that
standard open telemetry in the middle.
Just to finish this session,
just a reminder about the
projects in the CNCF context.
DAPER was accepted as a graduated
CNCF project in November, 2024.
And as you can see, the community
is very big and a lot of big
company already added this.
Technology in their stacks and
already using it in production.
So it's a very big project today
and very solid and reliable in
term of cloud deployment today.
If you have any question or
feedbacks, don't hesitate to reach me.
On Blue Sky or on LinkedIn.
I'm very open to, to question about
dapper and I really encourage you
to check the GitHub repository
and the community around dapper.
And why not make some contribution
or use it in production for
your microservices architecture.
Thank you for watching
and have a nice day.
Thank you.