Just off the subway, up to work.
I'm checking in like CNN
on the schedule first.
Roll call, we all
sitting down at stand up.
Head into our desks and I grab a banana.
Do a git pull, NPM build.
Two terminals, the question
is, will the loader control us?
Reaching out, branching a tree as it
graphs through the sea of packages.
It's crawling and searching, logs rolling
out, now it's stalling and lurching.
It's pretty clear this is
severe and it is plain to see.
I can't work, can't
pull a main dependency.
Real talk, how many times has it been?
Thank you.
That you roll up on Tuesday and maybe
even just came back after lunch and
like some open source dependency rolled
out and maybe you're trying to clone a
repo that somebody built like last week.
And like suddenly it's not building.
It's like something has flipped up.
Something has changed on you or you're
getting an error that somebody else
isn't getting on their machine because
your operating system is different or
it's conflicting with some C library
that you built to fix some other
similar problem, like six months ago.
And this is just a massive headache.
I want to talk a little bit about
packaging today with the goal
being that we contextualize Nix
for the cloud native practitioner.
Just pull up a little bit
of my slides over here.
We'll just pop over to different layout.
So I'm here chilling in Colorado.
My name is Lee Kapili.
And I'm a long time cloud native type
person contributed a good number to
Kubernetes and to projects like Flux,
like the continuous delivery project Flux.
I'm not talking about Flux today.
I'm talking about Phlox.
I still don't know how I'm
going to deal with this.
But Phlox is the startup
that I'm working with.
And because I joined the Phlox
team, I have a bunch of teammates
who know a lot about Nyx.
So I'm learning Nyx getting
a lot more context in it,
trying to become not ignorant.
And I want to Use my context in the cloud
native world to maybe try and share a
little bit of what I'm learning about
next and some of the revelations that I'm
having because I think that there's a lot
of opportunity for cloud native people
to employ next in their infrastructure,
in their systems, we're going to talk
about going from workflow to artifact.
To run time today, we're gonna
spend a lot of time on workflow
because I think there's just a lot
of cool things that we're building
that are very concrete here.
But cloud native next, let's get into it.
Got to click this.
Here we go.
Software is complicated.
But what we're really trying to do at
the end of the day is take assemblies
of things and then build some really
cool tools, some cool systems, you
Some access to information, right?
We're like trying to change the shape
of the world and we get together with
people a lot of the time and are like,
Hey, let's collaborate on some software
so we can do something valuable that
prints money for shareholders or
makes the next like ride sharing app,
but for dogs or something like that.
And each.
Kind of software project has its own
annoying collection of stuff that stuff
comes in a couple of different shapes
It comes in tools It comes in libraries
right like things that other open source
developers Builds because they have a
lot more domain knowledge on something
like how to calculate elliptic curves
or you know do some other cryptography
stuff or like I don't know, munch big
integers or even just the standard
libraries from all of your programming
languages that are, really good at
recursive sense or walking file paths
and, sanitizing inputs and stuff, right?
Just things that you don't
want to mess with it.
You need libraries for that.
You could put enough libraries
together into an opinionated
workflow and you call it a framework.
And then we have to figure all this stuff.
And so there's a little
bit of a software project.
We've got to combine a bunch of things
together, but each project has its own
annoying collection of stuff, right?
Okay.
And when you have annoying collections
of things it becomes even increasingly
annoying to share them with other people.
But remember, a lot of software is
collaborative, so this is just like
a constant pesterence in our life.
And then you get into the thing with
what if I want to work on a thing
that I was working eight months ago?
And reproducing that annoying collection
of stuff on a brand new machine or even
just like reinvigorating on machine
because you're like you deleted it or
like trying to run CI for something.
It's just like these things drift and
they break because they're pulling
from public sources and the builds
themselves are not structured in a way
that is going to last the test of time.
So planning for the future is tough.
So this is some of the.
Problem space that we're trying
to think about with flocks, right?
And so flux is a company, but it's also
the name of an open source project, right?
You can just go to github.
com slash flocks.
That's a GPL V2 licensed open
source project written in
rust and You just clone it.
And if you install flux as well,
you can start up the dev shell
really easily and just contribute
on a real cool breast project.
And we're trying to make it so
that your dev environments are
reproducible and not just across time.
But that for each of your projects,
like they stay relatively contained
and that you can work on all
your projects, regardless of what
platform is in your hand, right?
If you're on Apple, Silicon Mac that
you would have success reproducing
the software environment necessary to
collaborate on something as somebody who's
on that weird arch Linux framework 13.
And that once you get that working,
it'll still work three years from
now or five or even 10 years.
Yeah.
Which that seems a little
bold, that's the idea.
So in order to do this, we have built
the open source tool, which is a package
manager on top of this other sort of
package manager technology called Nix.
Nix is really a functional programming
language that you can write these
input output expressions in.
And those expressions then end up
becoming declarations of packages
or descriptions of packages.
But Nix doesn't work like
most package managers.
See, most package managers, they're
taking these amalgamations of things, and
then they're distributing the different
kinds of things that you find in a
package across this standard hierarchy.
Folders that you find in
the Unix ecosystem, right?
So on a Mac and on the Linux machine
very Unix y you'll notice that I'm just
ignoring Windows because Nix doesn't work
on Windows, even though Windows is also
a Unix y heritage, and then it got weird.
But package managers, in
order to be able to manage.
this.
They have to do a lot of bookkeeping.
And then the shortcoming that you run
into here is actually not so much in
how we distribute stuff across folders,
but how we assemble environments.
Since our environments, like where
we look for all of our C libraries or
where we look for all of our secure
binaries or where we look for all of our
regular binaries, since they all come
from roughly the same folders, then our
environments, they get a little bit.
Hard to namespace that means that you
can't install two different versions of
my sequel because now you're going to have
two different binaries, that have the same
name and they both can't go into user bin.
So next fixes that by hashing.
Every package either the inputs or
the or the actual content itself.
And it's a lot like a
container layer, right?
Once we hash the package, we can
store all of the things related
to that package in one folder.
And we'll put it into this
thing called the Nix store.
The packages are cleanly
factored away from each other.
And then the real trick comes into how
to cleverly assemble these different
folders into environments that work on a
computer so that it feels like your normal
style of development where you can, run
a program and link into five different
C libraries or something like that have
some stuff on your path and so dynamically
managing the things that let it.
Programs find each other in a Unix
y way and let libraries link up
into things and let dynamically
loaded things load into things.
Managing the loader path is
part of what Nix is really
concerned with being clever about.
And it gives you a lot of tools to
be smart about that by having this
functional programming language, which
is notoriously hard to use, right?
And so Nix does more than just like manage
packages, it gives you like this whole
build system and you can like configure
your operating system with it if you
use this distribution called NixOS.
And you can manage your home directory if
you use a community project, and you can
manage your Mac if you use a different
community project, and so it's really
grown beyond just I need to hash libc.
Now it's this fully declarative system
for building reproducible distributed
computing things, but it's hard to get
into and honestly, pretty academic.
And I will say the stack
traces are super gnarly.
That's why we are building flocks clocks
is aiming to make it easy for you to
build these virtual environments that are.
And it uses Nix under the hood, but
with an interface that isn't really
scary for people who are just like
getting out of code school, or who are
a little bit more junior, or even all
of you incredibly senior folks out there
who just want to Don't have any more
time to learn one more thing, right?
We want to be able to promise that when
you install Phlox on your system, which,
there's a macOS installer, you can get it
from Brew as well, you just go to Phlox
dev website, then to our install docs.
Yeah, apt, we have an RPM for it on YUM
systems, and you can do a generic Nix
install if you're already a Nix user.
But we add some verbs, right?
So we want to change the shape of
the package manager a little bit.
If you really think about it, computers
they used to be more for one thing,
and they had a long life cycle.
Now our computers are
meant for many things.
Sometimes, a server is hosting
10 different projects with some
virtual hosting in front of it, or
it's a node in a Kubernetes cluster
that's running 40 containers.
And that server Has many jobs that need to
be split up into different environments.
But then it doesn't
live very long as well.
And on the other hand, like your laptop,
you might have it for 3 to 5 years and you
might work on 10 to 15 projects a year.
And the package manager being built
for one system and mutating your system
globally it, it doesn't really fit
really well anymore with the things
that we carry around in our backpacks.
And it doesn't really work for servers.
Very well either, because now
you can't install two different
versions of a database or something.
And so that's why we've containers have
been the saving grace, for everything.
But containers are primarily
a virtualization technology.
It's not a distribution technology,
and it certainly isn't a cross
platform technology, right?
A Linux container is going to force
you to use Linux as an abstraction
anytime you want to use it anywhere.
That becomes a little bit unfortunate
when you have a very fancy, 3, 500
Apple Silicon MacBook because that
chip is really nice and has like
a unified memory architecture that
allows you to run programs on the
GPU and do all kinds of fun stuff.
And it's got like really fast
access to memory and to the flash.
Where running a database on that
thing actually makes a lot of sense.
So why pretend like it's a Linux computer?
Unfortunately, it's because
it's the best option right now.
How can we get beyond that?
Let's let's just get into
demos, I'll pop over here.
Maybe do one more layout change,
and let's go here.
Alright, we are at the happy place here.
You can see that I've tried another
take of this recording before,
and I wasn't really that happy
with it, so I'm doing this again.
Okay.
Here, if flocks is a package
manager, we must be able to do
package management things, right?
So let's flocks list.
This is all of the packages that I have
installed in my default environment.
My default environment happens
to live in my home directory.
You can see here, Michelle, I have a
little integration that's just showing
me where I am in my environments.
So this is active, which means
that I should be able to run it.
H top, and I should be able
to like blocks, remove, go,
and then that should be fast.
And now I, don't have go from flocks.
I actually do have go
from a version manager.
So this is coming from a gimme
apparently it's go one 21.
5.
Except I don't know why this
is, but for, Oh yeah, it is.
Okay.
Yeah.
But if I Flux install go,
get that back and now I have
a newer version of go maybe.
Oh, this is actually unexpected.
What did I do?
Okay.
So here you guys get to see
a little bit of debugging.
I'm not sure why.
Go is not coming from the right place
because Flux should be higher in the path.
You can also see brew is linked
in something weird into my path.
You can see here my Flux environment has
a dot run, dot Flux slash run directory
with my operating system and architecture.
So this is arch64 Darwin.
And then there's a bin directory.
And presumably in here
there should be a go binary.
Yes.
And that is the version of Go that I want.
And presumably, it should be the
version that's getting executed too.
But for whatever reason, the path search
is not behaving the way I would expect.
Okay, I don't know.
Maybe it's something weird with zshell.
Anyway there you go.
Go is installed and I have it.
new version of it.
I also have age top, right?
And that is also coming from
flux as is, bat and I think
even my version of curl, yep.
Might be coming directly from
flux as maybe I don't have
bash or anything in here.
Do I?
Yeah, no, it's just mostly command
line tools and then core utils.
So maybe even No, not said rock.
These are still the Mac versions.
Cool.
Anyway, that's the default environment.
This is all actually coming
from a manifest, right?
So I feel like I'm actually removing
these packages imperatively, but it's
actually being done declaratively.
And this is a really big idea here.
We pretty much stole this directly
from language package managers.
which totally have this figured out.
You can imagine that if there is a
manifest that lists packages and other
attributes about the environment,
like I get to define environment
variables here and activation hook
which runs as a script in my shell
of choice, profile hooks as well.
I can also restrict my environment to
particular systems and architectures.
Like if I only want to run on Linux
then I could remove the Darwin.
Systems from there but that gets
into a very important point when I
imperatively say Flux and Stalco, this
is declaratively editing my manifest and
that manifest actually also immediately
produces A flux in the manifest lock.
And in here it is that manifest file,
but then all of the information that
you need to get the exact bit for bit
reproducible version of that package.
And when I say that this package
is reproducible, I don't just mean
that it was built and that it's
saved in a binary cache somewhere.
I mean that somebody Really smart
wrote a Nix expression to make sure
that this package every time it's
built is bit for bit the same exact
thing every time you build it.
And that means that like the time by
which the package like was built doesn't
affect like the bits and the hash of it.
And that is a pretty profound
concept that lets us do some funky.
Caching of builds later on in this story.
Now this is pretty boring, right?
We were locking some packages.
So this is good.
Now we have a manifest and a lock file.
So you can imagine we could
check this into a repo.
Let's go ahead and look at one.
If I go into this Terraform repo I have
a log, and you can see I have a commit
here that says add OpenTofu with locks.
Okay, let's go ahead and show that commit.
And there's a lockfile update, and
then if I scroll all the way down,
you can see the manifest update here.
There is an install.
It adds OpenTofu.
The reason that there's a left hand
and a right hand side of this is I
could rename this and have multiple
versions of the same package.
You can also add version
numbers right here.
It's just like at and
then the version number.
And then here in the hook section,
oh, anytime this environment is
activated then we'll run tofu init.
So what does it mean to
actually activate something?
Let's try.
Box activate.
So I'm in this folder, and then
you'll see now it's actually
run that tofu init for me.
And then I'm inside of this environment
as well as my default environment, right?
So which H top is, Oh my
gosh, what is happening?
What on earth
is happening?
I uninstalled
that earlier.
Yeah, that's why
I'm just going to flux install H top.
And then I'm going to do that
to a particular directory here.
And that'll immediately fix
what I was not expecting there.
Thanks for for suffering through
that moment of confusion.
Cool.
So I still have my default
environment, right?
It still works.
And still, and then I also have
the tofu command line tool.
Alright, so here we can see that
I'm OpenTofu182 on DarwinARM64
and I have a provider that has
been downloaded for me as a result
of activating this environment.
I can exit.
And then I can try to do the same exact
thing, and it's not going to work.
But notice I'm just in subshells,
I haven't been starting
containers or anything like that.
And all of these binaries are natively
compiled for my architecture to fully
utilize the entire address space
of all of the flash memory and or I
should say all of the memory on the
chip, as well as all of the flash
storage available and all of the CPUs.
without relying on any
sort of virtualization.
It's just binaries.
There's just some environment variables
and some clever mounting of read
only folders and stuff like that.
So there's good isolation happening here.
But this story is boring without also
then going over to a Windows box.
So let's go ahead.
And go to my rog ally.
I'm going to ssh in there
and start a WSL environment.
Let's go ahead and pop into
a Phlox activated zsh here.
Go into our home directory.
Try not to mistype too many things.
You can see over here I've got a little
bit of a different list of things.
drenv, git gnupg, pin entry,
for committing with, some
signatures stuff like that.
Let's go.
I cloned this repo earlier over
here and just tested that it worked.
So I'm get show same flux
environment and I just flux activate.
And again, we are
on the same open tofu version, but this
time compiled natively for Linux AMD 64.
So different operating system, different
architecture, and still getting that.
Yeah.
Provider pulled down for me by Terraform's
own built in package management.
Like this is starting to
build a really cool story.
Now I have a simple way for me and my
teammates to get to the same dependencies.
And I can stack them on
top of each other, right?
If I hop back out to the Mac.
Let's get out of all these shells.
And let's go over to, an example
environment.
I have a Go application here.
There's a little bit of source
code here for a small HTTP server.
What kinds of things
would I need for this?
Maybe I would want to build a
Go application and then push it
to Kubernetes, and generate a
deployment manifest for it, and
then syntax highlight some of the
things that come back from kubectl.
Naturally you're going to end up
with a longer dependency to the
list than this, but it's like a
nice, simple example environment.
And this would work perfectly on my Mac.
It works great, you can just activate
it and I can put this just get commit
the flocks folder and push it and
somebody can pull it and activate
and it'll work on their machine or
on a CI server, or even in a system
D unit on a production web server.
Totally would work just fine the last
environment that's just worth demoing
here before I get to talking about
moving forward beyond the workflow is
here's another kind of infrastructure y.
You'll notice here that since
I have so many environments
activated, Phlox is really double
checking that I know where I am.
And here I've got Google Cloud SDK,
Bitwarden CLI, and the Oracle Cloud CLI.
Now, I can't tell you about the number
of times that I've been frustrated
with the Python that's been built into
the brew distributed Google Cloud SDK.
It's just because it's on the global
path and like you have to modify
your shell RC to do things with it.
I've even had a lot of instances
where like Google Cloud SDK itself
breaks by having some strange Python
issues that I don't understand.
And then I just have to go and look
it up and find somebody's comment on
a GitHub issue to mutate the files
on my file system to make it work.
so that I can log into a virtual
machine or talk to a Kubernetes cluster.
And so having this be just pulled from a
binary cache and built by the community
and validated in a reproducible,
bit for bit reproducible way.
I've uninstalled gcloud.
I don't have it on my system anymore.
From brew and all of my problems are
gone now because I can just activate
in this environment and the analogy in
my head of what this feels like for me
is it feels like this whole time I'm
usually just trying to crochet like I'm
usually just doing a little bit of fine
electrical soldering and then like right
next to be in my garage on my workbench
there is a table saw and it just plugged
in and I am one moment away from or one
collaborator away from having an accident
and or just it's just in my way, it's
just a mess and I'm tripping over the
cord and just put the table saw away,
so like right now I'm actually, you can
see that when I type a G cloud, power
level 10 K is noticing that it should
probably tell me what environment I'm in.
So I'm over here just
in my main account and.
I can just talk to the cloud and I can
spend money now and now I just type
exit and I can no longer spend money,
or at least I can no longer change the
amount of money that I'm spending, it's
just a beautiful thing to be organized
and to be able to put stuff away.
Back to our, let's just go to
the
go environment, right?
Okay.
We have this a couple of commands
that are a bit under construction.
Right now there is flocks build
and we have a little message,
a little playful message here.
But this is actually functional
it's got a help message and you can
pop some build commands into your
manifest and you can start wrapping
your build in a way where the outputs
will be shoved into a Nix store.
The thing that we are working on
here is to also give you a ladder.
So that you can't just you can take your
impure software that relies on public
sources and the Internet and, reaching out
to all of the resources of your system,
and then you can start to constrain it
a little bit, maybe turn the Internet
off and then also not be able to access
every single file path on the system.
That would be good because then
you can start to reel in the clock
and Turn on all the build flags to
make your build fully reproducible.
How do we make that easy for you so that
you can get the full power of Knicks and
then start having an incredible cash hit
ratio inside of your inside of your build
systems to where like maybe your builds
are two seconds that would be awesome.
And the other thing that
we have going here is.
If you actually, this is a
public repo Fluxenvs Verba.
This is also available on FluxHub,
which is a service we provide.
You can just like, Fluxactivate
rflux verba to get to this.
But I'm just gonna activate here.
And actually.
I'm going to add the start services flag.
Cool.
I have a service running, and I'm just
going to prepare going to local host 8000.
So you can see that I've got
this this retrieval augmented
generation application.
We have a stack of a couple
of services running here.
If you look at Phlox Edit Python
3 Weaviate Vector Database Olama,
which is in charge of pulling
generative AI models for us locally.
A couple of pre printing things make
sure Bash and Curl are just pinned.
This, I love this because like this, you
can actually write a bash script that will
behave expectedly on somebody's machine.
And you don't have to worry.
And then same thing like the version
of curl on somebody's machine, like
you can make sure that it has the
HTTP 2 protocol in it or something.
You can pin like sed and awk and not
use the BSD version of tar ever again.
And it would, it just
makes your life better.
But yeah.
So some variables.
Hop into hooks over here, so you can
see that we're starting to feel a little
bit like Docker Compose, but just in
a TOML format and with no containers.
It's just going to run
processes on your machine.
In the services section here start
a vector database, start a llama
conditionally wait if a certain
environment variable is set.
If not, just immediately start the
Verba UI service for talking to
the RAG application and then also
waiting for Elamit to be ready and
then pulling some models into it.
There's a couple of long
running services here and then
one kind of one shot service.
And you can see that we're
intending to run this on ARM
Macs and any Linux machine.
It's also a Python virtual
environment being activated there.
If I do box services status you can
see our models have completed and
we are running the VectorDB Olama
for our model execution and then our
frontend and you can get the logs.
So it feels a lot like Docker
Compose, but with no containers.
Here's what doesn't feel
like Docker Compose.
Let's open some
other shells here.
Let's make sure to just activate those.
We don't have to start services
again, because Phlox already knows
that this environment is active.
What Phlox also knows is that if I
close the first one and then I close the
second one, the third one, or whatever,
like I'm still working on things.
Thanks.
But that I just make a, just
so I don't lose my window here.
If I close the last active environment
the services will immediately go offline.
So that's a really sweet feature
because now you don't have
databases eating up your battery.
It's just the benefit of working
on a computer and actually using
it instead of pretending that
it's a Linux virtual machine.
All right.
Last here's the first bit
that doesn't work on a Mac.
Let's go to
the box end for Go.
And let's try to containerize it.
We're done with our workflow.
We want to get to the artifact part.
It says error.
Containerized is only supported on Linux.
So we're trying to fix this.
It's probably going to require
some sort of kemu thing.
But at some point maybe when It's possible
to execute Nix with Wasm or something.
Maybe that could be interesting, but for
now we'll probably need a Linux virtual
machine or like some sort of path.
You can always start your own VM, but I'm
just going to ssh over back to my Windows
machine and let's pop back into Zshell.
Let's find,
so I built this like little
Phlox environment, just,
initialize to get repo in here.
And I have a couple of dependencies
and I can containerize this.
What this is doing is it's taking the
environment that has been built with
Nix which you, let's see, I guess I
can show that in a few seconds, but
we inflate this all the way through.
And that environment has a bunch
of other dependencies in it.
And it is putting each of those granular
dependencies into a container layer.
This is really awesome because container
layers are already content addressed.
And all Nix store paths are also content
addressable inside of a binary cache.
So you could get to a world where
every single Nix package is stored
inside of an OCI repository.
And you could even have a pull through
cache that's like right next to your
cluster that only pulls layers that
are each individual packages, right?
And we are trying to construct
a perfectly efficient container.
Container image here that can be fully de
duplicated in storage and then have the
highest cache hit ratio possible, right?
You're no longer having like
multiple versions of bash stored
across 30 different images.
There's just The versions of bash
in your registry and your images
linked to the one that they want.
And if you get container D to
unpack these layers, just like
any other container image, then it
ends up in an overlay file system.
And what's going on with this?
So this is a little bit sad.
Unfortunately, there is a layer limit.
In, with normal Docker containers.
And it comes from the Linux kernel's
inability to construct an Overlay2 file
system with more than like 127 mount arcs.
And so here we're capping at 99
just so that there's more, another
20 or 25 layers of space, for you
to stack on top of it before you're
getting close to that layer limit.
But in once we get to the end, we
have to heuristically pick a list
of packages to combine into layers.
And this completely messes up with,
the cash hit for all of these things
because it will probably be a different
list for different containers.
So this is unfortunate.
How do we fix this?
The folks at PDT Partners have built
a Containerd snapshot or plugin
that integrates directly with Nix.
And I have a pretty bare bones
NixOS configuration here, but if
I go to Etsy NixOS Configuration.
nix, you can see that I have added
a a Nix snapshot or import here.
So this is Nix expressions
in the Nix language.
It looks sort of JSON y, but then
it's, the stack traces are terrible.
That's the difference
and yeah, we've so we define an import
for the Nix snapshot or project from PDT
partners that's just on their GitHub.
They have a great readme, I pretty
much just copied and pasted this
right in from it into my NixOS
config to just customize it.
And you can enable the systemd unit
from the NixOS package and module
for container D and then use their
module to patch next snapshot or on
top of it and then enable it, right?
So that's what's happening here.
And the end result is that
if I pseudo nerd CTL info.
Then you'll see that in
storage, Containerd now supports
native overlayfs and Nix.
And what this means is that we've, if
we build a special OCI manifest that
points to Nix store paths, that instead
of Containerd pulling layers from an
OCI repository, it will talk to the Nix
daemon, and the Nix daemon will pull
just derivations, like directly from
whatever Nix store and whatever binary
caches it can get to and then it will
fulfill like sort of its promise to
container D and container D will take
that Nix store path and it will bind
mount it into our container for us.
And because bind mounts are
a lot cheaper than overlays.
The Linux kernel is happy to do
lots and lots and lots of them.
The, I think that in the rough research
that I did recent Linux kernels have a
limit of a hundred thousand bind amounts
which seems like it would be enough
to maybe run a thousand containers or
something with a hundred bind amounts of
different packages, Or maybe a hundred
containers with a thousand bind amounts.
Yeah, the math seems to check out
there and that it might scalably
be something interesting to do.
Another idea that I had here is
that maybe it might be possible
to tombstone the next door somehow
with an overlay in a creative way.
I'm not sure fully if that would
work yet because you would have
to update the tombstones while the
next door was being updated and that
could maybe get race conditioning.
You wouldn't want store paths
showing up in containers that
were not supposed to be there.
But there's a lot of opportunity here.
Because you could potentially
like, I don't know, de
duplicate all of Docker Hub.
If we could just get the ecosystem
to move towards a little bit
more organized packaging.
And you certainly could just like
very much de duplicate your own
Elastic Container Registry account.
Huh.
Or reduce the number of hard
drives that you have for your
local harbor installation.
There's a lot of opportunity
here as cloud native.
As far as building these images goes,
you actually need to Read the README
and then learn how to do Nix right now.
And so there's opportunity for us
as the Phlox project to make it
simpler for you to basically call
this helper function that's included
in the NixSnapper Shotter project.
The schema is fairly simple
and then you can see here that
the entry point is being set.
To a package that's coming
from Nix expressions.
That's how this Docker image is
ultimately being constructed as a tarball
and then exported from this flake.
But in this example, and maybe there
are some simpler interfaces that
we can build to that in the future.
The last thing that I would like to
highlight here that really contextualizes,
like going from artifact to run time out
of the changed habits of workflow by using
Nixie tools to get cleaner dependencies
that are factored for your system is
that we could make Nix stores potentially
fairly native to OCI repositories.
And this is really attractive because
if what is going into the container
image are runtime dependencies that
are actually factored as Nix packages.
And those are the things that Containerd
is actually reaching out for and
then we could potentially even teach
Containerd to support non conflicting
layers because you don't need overlays.
And maybe it wouldn't be fully
dependent on Nix anymore, so there
would be like a non conflicting layer
snapshotter or something like that.
That way you wouldn't have to
have a Nix daemon everywhere.
Then, we could just throw Nix
packages in an OCI registry.
All of them, even.
And, when you work on Nix stuff, Nix would
know how to pull from the OCI registry.
And, when you Are then building, you
don't have to push anything back because
it's already there in the OCI repo.
So you just push a tagged manifest that
references the things that you need.
It's like maybe a couple of kilobytes.
And then now you're done.
Kubernetes cluster, all 100 nodes
or whatever have immediate cache
deduplicated access to those things, and
you can start your containers instantly
with no pull difference or anything.
And then when you need to update a
package, you change something in a
flux manifest, and it updates on all
of your developer workstations and
CI automatically builds it, and then
it just gets pushed out and there are
these very small layer differences.
And you can see a world where.
The software supply chain is so much
more maintainable, that could be a
really cool place to get to, and maybe
that would free us up for the cyclist to
actually pay all of the maintainers to
keep the supply chain secure, and then
we can trust the updates because we can
install the proper social machinery,
to build a cleaner ecosystem instead
of This sort of workaround that we've
gotten to with docker containers, where
a virtualization technology has become
a distribution and packaging format
but without the packaging discipline.
I think that there's so much excite.
It's exciting opportunity here.
Consider this a preview of some of
the things that we are building and
looking to talk about at KubeCon and
at Regex and coming into the later part
of this year and into early next year.
So we're building a private catalogs.
We're finishing up the pure builds
portion of the Flux build experience
looking at export operations for
containers and that kind of thing
and getting into the runtime.
I'm trying to do my best to bring
my Kubernetes context to all of
my teammates who know so much
about Nix, and I'm learning a lot.
It's very humbling.
But if you heard me said if you
heard me say anything spicy anything
that resonated with you, let's start
a little bit of public discourse.
I can't wait to field your questions.
And there's so much to be
excited about in this space.
Thanks for coming in and hearing
about Phlox a little bit.
You can go to phlox.
dev and install and change your workflow.
And hopefully those workflow changes
will produce a little bit of ergonomic
efficiency for your team and can produce
habits that produce more cleanly factored
dependencies for your artifacts and
that eventually paint a long term story
for changing the runtime and maybe even
reinventing the container image format a
little bit, getting past the layer limit.
Thank you friends.
And I will see you on the
internets and at the conferences.