Greetings everyone.
I'm Surya Busi coming with 18 plus years
of IT experience and currently working
as technical lead for an automotive
industry for the past 11 years.
So I have been closely looking and working
with the emerging cloud technologies.
So the topic for today's conference
is how to be future ready for the.
Cloud which includes discussions
about different architectures like
the monolithic microservice and the
concepts of edge com, edge computing.
And also we will look into
the future technologies, the
emerging technologies at scale.
So with this, my agenda for today.
Is, comes with the cloud evolution, how
the landscape has shifted from monoliths
to the futuristic distributor systems.
And next we'll look into the microservices
how they have brought a big difference
and also their adoption trends, benefits,
and the implementation challenges.
Later we'll be looking into the edge
computing, which is a process of bringing
the data and analysis closely to the
source of data instead of relying on
the centralized cloud data centers.
And to the very end, we'll be
looking into the future technologies
like the hybrid clouds, serverless
architecture, and quantum computing.
With all this in view, let's
begin our presentation.
Join me for the actionable insights
from the real world implementation
and the practical strategies for
your organization's cloud journey.
With this, we'll move into the
very first part of our agenda.
Which is the cloud native evaluation.
So for years we have been stuck with
the monolithic applications where
it's a software system where all the
features and the functionality is
developed as a single unit and with all
its features and functionalities like.
The user interface, the business logic
and the data access layers are all
being developed as one single unit
and one exec executable application.
So this single unit of application
enables us to have a simple deployment
and development and deployment.
Whereas going, moving on,
it'll have impacts on the.
Maintainability and update maintainability
of the application and any updates
related to technologies as the,
everything is tightly coupled as one unit.
So the key characteristics of this
monolithic involves the unified code.
Pace, tight coupling, single
deployment and simplified development.
So looking at these, the
advantages of monolithics are
the simplicity, the performance,
and the centralized management.
But it has the disadvantages as
well which are with the, as we
mentioned, the full scalability.
The limited flex flexibility since
being a sim single unit of application,
any technology upgrades has to be
done to the entire application, which
might cause a significant delay in
the releases and the challenges in
maintenance, which also adds to the
deployment risks of being a single unit.
The typical use cases of the monolithic
applications include a small and
small applications where with little
complexity and also an a startup
applications where the prototype with
simplicity as the paramount that's the
typical use cases of the monolithic.
With all these challenges with the
monolithic architecture, we move
on to the microservices, which
gives a greater advantages which is
basically a collection of, collection
of autonomous units with their own
individual responsibilities, business
responsibilities and its own data store.
So the complexity being divided
into multiple units which can
be maintained by themselves.
And these services communicate
through the different protocols,
be it BHTP or through the.
Message queues or different sources.
And this enables this being
smaller units, it's easy.
It enables the easy maintenance and
gives us the flexibility, scalability,
and all these advantages when compared
to the legacy monolithic applications.
With that the typical use cases of both
the microservices are the large and
complex applications which involves
complexity to be dealt with ease.
That's about the microservice
architecture, the key use
cases, as I mentioned.
Involves the enterprise systems, the
e-commerce platforms example, and
the streaming services where high
availability and resilience are critical.
And the upcoming and technology is the
edge computing which involves processing
data closer to the source of generation,
such as I OT devices, sensors, or local
server, rather than relying solely on
the centralized cloud infrastructure.
We'll look into it closely into
the later part of the presentation,
but for now, edge Computing is a
process where the data and analysis
are close to the source of data.
With this, I'll move to the next.
Which is with the benefits we
have seen with the microservices
architecture this driving pri, this
being driving the enterprise agility.
So we look into the various, advantages
of the micro ARC microservices
architecture in detail here.
With the widespread adoption, we have
seen huge surge in the industry where the
microservices adoption has increased from
45% in 2019 to the dominant 91% in 2024.
So this is clearly indicating
the industry shift.
With all the proven advantages
of microservices, as we explained
earlier, this smaller units
enable the faster deployments.
With that being said, we have
seen a significant 76% reduction
in the deployment time, enabling
faster iteration cycles and
quicker delivery of new features.
Which also includes the cost efficiency.
So organization, organizations can
achieve up to 50% reduction in the cost
as we scale only the resources we need.
The services being
independent of each other.
And then comes the enhanced
scalability which contribute to the 62%
improvement in resource utilization,
allowing high demand components
to scale precisely what as needed.
These go, the enhanced scalability
and the cost efficiency
goes hands in hand in hand.
As we will be scaling only the units which
need, which is receiving huge traffic.
Whereas the, which comes with the cost
efficiency of unnecessarily wasting the
resources which need not to be scaled.
Then comes the better fault
isolation as a critical advantage.
We have seen 83% reduction
in the system-wide failures.
The failure of a service, one individual
service easily can be pinpointed with
the with the with the business lodging
being scaled into different services.
With all these advantages will
move to the next, which is.
As we have seen the pros, now we
have to look into the cons of the
microservice architecture with
its implementation challenges.
The first being is the technical depth
because 60%, 67% of the enterprises.
Are all stuck with the legacy code
where code integration, which has
the complexity of understanding and
trying to divide into the simple units
with the microservice architecture.
So this huge technical depth is causing
the impediment of the moving to.
Moment to the microservice implementation,
then comes the service decomposition.
As we understand the business logic
in microservice architecture is being
divided into autonomous units, it's
highly critical to better understand
the business and to the level it has
to be optimally set the boundaries
and being divided into the units.
So without.
A good business knowledge and the
boundaries to be set on the domains.
It makes it difficult for a proper
design of the microservices.
And with all this in mind, the
operational complex complexity,
which says that 71% report increased
complexity in monitoring, debugging,
and maintaining the service depend.
As we understand microservices are
different services which communicate
and and can grow in number as
the complexity of the application
grows, and the difficulty of
maintaining them as well grows.
That's what the optic.
Cost, operational
complexity being increased.
And also with the different services,
having different data stores, it becomes
great difficulty with the data management.
As we see, there's a 64% struggle
with data consistency between these
different single units and the
distributor transactions and the data
accuracy between these several units.
This what we understand about
the implementation challenges of
the microservices architecture.
Now let's move on to with all.
This knowledge as we move to
the next step, which is the
architecture foundations needed
for the microservice architecture.
This involves the infrastructure
components to be understood, the
design, different design patterns
available as of today to better
implement the microservice architecture.
When coming to the infrastructure
components, we have the container
orchestration with which the greater
scale and the management of this different
business units is, would be possible.
As we understand, as the application
grows to be complex, it's very key.
To be able to deploy and scale with a
greater accuracy in the performance.
So the Kubernetes Container
Organization orchestration is one
of the key components when come,
when it comes to the infrastructure.
Similarly with the huge traffic
as we expect it to be scaled to a
huge level of the traffic expected.
It is important to have a proper
traffic routing, load balancing, and,
observability between the services
where in this scenario the service
mesh for this traffic management
is a good option available for
as an infrastructure component.
And the proper routing
enables proper performance and
deliverance of the results.
So the API Gateways for client
service communication is one
another infrastructure component.
So this gives us a controlled way of
organizing the request, routing them and
handling them with the authentication
necessary for the proper security.
Then comes the centralized logging
and monitoring which is very key
in where the complexity being
properly managed and to provide a
accuracy of the information provided.
This relates to the aggregating the logs
metrics from all the microservices to
enable the e debugging and operational
visibility at a higher level.
So as we see the inspir sector components
moving onto the design patterns which
comes with the domain driven design for
service boundaries, as we understand
the business complex complexity to be
divided into an operatable single unit,
it the domain driven knowledge is very
key to set the boundaries and to develop
the individual services and maintaining
them properly and held complexity.
And similarly, the event driven
architecture decoupling uses events
of, like we, as we mentioned, where the
responses need not be synchronous, where
the event driven architecture helps
with the loose coupling and the per
increase in performance and scalability
and the improved responsiveness.
So these are the key while designing the
microservice patterns architecture and
the CQRS for complex, as we understand.
As the scalability increases the data
being to be operated becomes complex.
So separate, read and write operations
to manage this data and the the
performance with this complex data
is being achieved with the QRS.
As we all know with this many point
touch points and the network ops we
take with the microservice architecture,
a proper circuit breaker is much
more important for the resilience.
Which prevents the failures at a
certain point and not cascading
it to the respective systems.
So with these architectural
foundations needed for the microservice
architecture, we'll move to the next.
So now we understand the legacy challenges
with the legacy monolithic obligations,
and we overcome what we've overcome
with the microservice architecture and
the different challenges implementing
the microservice architecture.
We'll move on to the next emerging
technology, which is edge computing, which
is a process where, the huge data involved
today with this, all these applications
need to be processed efficiently.
So edge computing is a process
where the data is being brought
closer to the for analysis to the
source of the data, and which has
proven to be providing many results.
So here are some numbers
proving its efficiency.
So with the data being, analysis and it's
being closed to the source of the data.
It, the latency reduction, the 45%
latency reduction, decrease in processing
delays, and for very time applications.
And which with which there's
a 42% real time improvement.
Enhanced data handling capabilities for
mission critical systems, as example such
as healthcare and manufacturing, and which
also comes with the 78% bandwidth savings.
As we understand the data being close to
the source, the bandwidth the reduction
in the network hoops being decreased
greatly increases the bandwidth savings.
And the response acceleration is proven
to be 56% increased with the emergency
response, wherein all it's needed.
As I mentioned in the healthcare
applications and the manufacturing
applications and need not be
necessarily the same, we, it can
be applied across multiple domains
like banking and e-commerce or
where the response is critical.
It.
Looking into the numbers,
we'll move on to the next.
Which is the edge computing applications
where it can be applied in different
industries which involves the two
examples being mentioned here.
The manufacturing and the healthcare.
As we understand manufacturing, were huge
volumes of data is being processed to
pro efficiently run the production lines.
There has been a 33% efficiency boost.
Seen and the realtime quality control
of the different data and to provide
any defects is being the de defect
detection being increased by 87%.
So this predictive maintenance
this cost to the predictive
maintenance reduced by 41%.
That's what we see in the
manufacturing industry.
Coming to the healthcare, there
was there's been a significant
increase in the response up to 56%
faster emergency response with a 93%
accuracy, which is very key where
the life of the patients is online.
Where immediate data processing is
very critical for taking for the
medical staff to take decisions.
So edge computing is very proven to
be very valuable in such environments
where time sensitive data is key
for the day-to-day operations,
and we move to the next, where with
this edge computing with all that
we learned there are definitely some
architectural considerations to be made.
Where with this as mentioned,
different sources of data with
the quality and quantity of data
being processed, it is key to
understand the resource constraints.
With the hardware limitations
of the CPU storage.
It is key to understand the amount of,
hardware needed to process such data.
So as of today, the K three s
and the Micro Ks are designed for
these environments, optimizing
and giving a huge results.
Same with the connectivity
where it need to be considered.
The emergency of, and the criticality
of the data need to be presented.
It is important to have a
reliable and high performing
connectivity, network connectivity.
So Kubernetes architecture is
being proven to be a solution
with all these in consideration.
As we mentioned, with all the huge data
and the critical data being over spread
on the attack surface is being increased.
Security becomes the paramount with the
amount of PIA and SPIA being on net.
So the robust.
Security process necessities, like
the zero trust models, hardware based
security features, and the strong
encryption is very much needed for all
this communications over the network.
So when it comes to edge computing
these concentrations are need to be
made when designing the applications.
Now that we move to the next.
So with all the current solutions
available in market today for this
hybrid and multi-cloud approaches,
which involves the Amazon Web services,
the Microsoft Azure, the Google Cloud
and on-premises are proven to be in
different, providing great results in
different business areas like the AWS
being, the production and scalable
services and Azure being good for the
enterprise apps and identity integration.
And whereas Google Cloud is coming up
with the data analytics and ml workloads
being proven with the on-premises,
the latency sensitivity and the
legacy systems are being well handled.
That's what the solutions available
helps us to understand better
design our applications as of today.
With that, we'll move to the next slide.
So with all this available in the
market, it makes us easy to have a
development focus on the key business
logic rather than worrying about
the infrastructure where all this
infrastructure as service is providing.
In the, by many organizations
in the marketplace, this leads
to the constant cost efficiency.
With the zero cost as it's paper per
use with all the services provided,
if not in use, we need not be paying.
As we mentioned, it's a zero cost for the
ideal resources and the, and with the old
being small and the market being growing,
the auto-scaling plays a key role, which
is hugely enabled with this flexibility
of opting the paper use models available.
Which enables of instance,
scaling whenever depending
on the traffic automatically.
This enables organizations using
serverless architectures report
61% shorter development cycles and
45% reduced operational overhead.
With all this emerging
technologies, we move on to.
Another very futuristic application,
which is the quantum computing.
So quantum computing is basically
implement, makes use of the quantum
mechanic concept of quantum mechanics
to process information using quantum
bits or qubits which can, which enables
computers to perform at much higher
speed than the classical computers.
City has a great potential
and this can help.
In various key areas like the material
science, pharmaceuticals, and machine
learning by solving problems with a
with a much more higher speed with this.
But coming to the disadvantage of
quantum computing, it's still under
development and it's still emerging.
It's in the very early stages.
And with, with the amount of speed
we are expecting, the infrastructure
involved comes at high cost.
So these services as we
understand are still emerging.
As we understand this all being in the
cloud, there are certain concerns with
the security of these distributed systems.
Proper mechanisms have been in
place with like different mechanisms
like the zero trust architecture,
the runtime protection, the secret
management, and the service membership.
Security and the supply chain security.
So coming to the zero trust architecture,
it's like the least privilege being
provided and the fine-grain identity
controls being set in place to avoid any
security concerns and secret management
is encrypting and storage of the necessary
secrets in a more secured area and
providing a least privileged access.
And GP Secret Manager is one
of the examples for this.
Similarly, the SEC service mesh
securities at the network layer, the
TLS layer providing the certificate
management automation at a great level.
And the runtime protection being
detecting the any behavioral analysis
anomaly with the container workloads,
the health checking, the timely health,
and providing dashboard with the analysis
and the supply chain security is where
the verifying the bills, identifying
the dependency vulnerabilities in
advance to avoid any disturbances.
With all this security and distributed
clouds, we'll move to the next.
So what we have understood with
the legacy monolithic applications,
the micro upcoming microservice
architecture and the hybrid cloud and
the edge computing, and the very much
emerging quantum quantum computing.
Now we have all the tools with
her within us with our hands.
We are trying to understand how
we can apply all this to be a
future ready cloud strategy.
So with all these technologies
available and having having them in
our radar enables us to assess and our
organizational requirements and try to.
Use the proper tools for designing
the organization requirements.
So with this, we can enable the
progressive adoption patterns with the,
by adopting the less clear critical
requirements and trying to use the
tools and prove the value of them, and
then expand whatever we learned to the
different areas of the organization
which enables us a progressive
adaption instead of, a bulk modulation.
And that involves.
That involves investing in the platform
engineering as well, where a developer
platform where we can put all the
learnings in one place and then, and
enabling the rest of the development
teams utilize what we learn and making
and enforcing the best practices.
To have the learning curves
being reduced at a high level.
So not just learning.
And definitely the performance
need to be measured.
Measured what matters with all the Dora
metrics and measuring the cost efficiency
and setting up the key performance
indicate indexes enables us to build
a very future ready cloud strategy.
Hope this all helps, and with this.
Oh.
We come to the key takeaways of this
presentation of what we learn and what
are supposed to be our next steps.
So coming to the what we
learn microservices adoption.
Has reached the 91% delivering proven
benefits as we understand with the
huge benefits of microservices, it
being adopted and has been growing
widely throughout the industry.
And Edge computing being delivering 45%.
Latency reductions.
As we understand in the very time
sensitive industries like the healthcare
and the manufacturing and the hybrid
cloud approaches, reducing downtime
by 41% as the infrastructure is of a
less burden now and the key business.
Focus is being increased with all
this emergency, and we understand the
emerging technologies like the serverless
architecture and the quantum computing,
which greatly benefits in research areas
and helps in the growing industries.
So with all these understandings,
our next steps include SS or.
Current requirements of our industry
and the better design applications
using the emerging technologies against
the cloud native patterns and identify
the opportunities of analysis of the
data using the edge computing and,
setting up the right tools, having
the right technology radar within
set within the organization help us
develop a much business focused and
much and highly performing applications.
And with this it helps the
organizations grow at a great level.
With this, I end my presentation
and thank you for this opportunity.