Hello everyone.
I'm Dhruvesh Talati, a senior software engineer
with experience in cloud infrastructure
and DevSecOps Engineering, and I'm glad
to be here at Con 42 Cube Native 2025.
Today I want to talk about
something that's becoming
increasingly important in the world
we live in building cloud native systems
that are resilient by design, especially
for crisis response and recovery.
Instead of just reacting when
things go wrong, what if we could
design systems that are ready
for disruption from the start?
In this session, we will look
at how distributed, elastic, and
highly available cloud native
architectures can help organizations
stay operational during emergencies
and bounce back faster afterward.
If you look at the world right now
with increasingly complicated and
frequent events like climate disasters,
cyber attacks, and health emergencies,
it is evident that the traditional
approaches are no longer sufficient.
The traditional on-premise
infrastructures that many organizations
still depend on are too slow.
When a crisis hits, they take too longer
to recover and constantly break down.
This simply isn't sustainable
when the threats are this serious.
The limits of these older systems
create big vulnerabilities that
can quickly spread and cause
problems across entire industries.
At this point, resilience isn't
just an IT issue, it's a matter
of global and societal stability.
We absolutely need infrastructure
that can flex scale and recover
as fast as modern crisis demands.
So what does this new
infrastructure need to do?
I believe there are three
pillars to true resilience.
First, uninterrupted availability
during an age of constant crisis.
This isn't a choice.
Basic services ranging from
medicine to emergency calls,
need, near perfect uptime.
That is 99.99% availability to keep
people alive and maintain social order.
Second dynamic scalability crises
are not predictable and can cause
stupendous, unplanned surges in demand.
Our infrastructures must have the
agility to dynamically scale up
in seconds, absorbing 10 times
capacity increases in minutes.
This presents, a stark deviation from
the latency prone and operationally rigid
nature of legacy systems, which struggle
to adapt efficiently to dynamic condition.
And third, seamless interoperability.
Effective crisis response requires
coordinated action by different
organizations, public, private
sector, and international aid groups.
Resilience rests on effective
realtime collaboration, and
sharing of data without delay.
This is not merely an upgrade, but
a foundational strategic imperative.
To build the resilient and adaptive
infrastructure that our future demands.
So how do we build this?
We build resilience with
cloud native architectures.
First, microservices architecture.
This pattern releases developer from
the limitation of monolithic approach.
It deconstructs complex applications into
small, independently deployable units.
When a service fails, it does
not take the entire system down,
which provides unprecedented
resilience and quick recovery.
Second container orchestration.
We employ tools like Kubernetes
to automatically and dynamically
manage our infrastructure.
This provides us with dynamic scaling,
self feeling, and performance optimization
across distributed environments.
Keeping your services up and
running and perform optimally and
third infrastructure as a code.
By coding and managing our entire
infrastructure with version controlled
code, we eliminate human error and
deliver consistent, predictable
deployment in any cloud or region.
This accelerates provisioning considerably
and enhances security beyond the roots.
We use specific distributed
resilience patterns to build
actually fault tolerance systems.
The circuit breaker pattern shields
your system from catastrophic crashes.
It detects and isolates failing
services to cut off cascading failures,
leaving core functionality intact
and operational timeout controls.
It prevents the resource exhaustion
condition by actively terminating
long labeled or hung requests.
This keeps the entire system
stable and allows for a
smooth, quick user experience.
Even under high load retry and back off
is a master of transient network issues.
It uses intelligent retry methods
with exponential back off to retry
unsuccessful operations gracefully
without overwhelming your infrastructure.
And finally, bulkhead isolation.
Prevents critical services from competing
for resources with resource partitioning.
Failure in one service can't
exhaust the resources that your
most critical operations depend
upon assuring the continuity,
availability, and performance.
One of the biggest benefits of cloud
native architectures is that they are,
they inherently have elastic scaling.
They offer unpowered resiliency.
With dynamic resource scaling, this allows
organizations to automatically ingest
massive traffic spikes in a disaster
without having to incur the cost of over
provisioning pricing infrastructure.
This is supported by three key
abilities, vigilant real-time monitoring.
We have a continuous pulse on the system
with realtime insight into performance
data, user behavior, and emerging threats.
Which enables a proactive approach.
Smart automated scaling our
infrastructures are able to scale up
or down automatically using dynamic
thresholds and predicted analytics
optimally adapting to changing demands
and optimize load distribution.
Smart traffic routing, maximizes
workload distribution between
availability zones and regions.
Bypassing bottlenecks and providing
maximum performance beyond
scaling uninterrupted service is
maintained by building for high
availability with redundancy.
We utilize strategic multi-region
deployment to safeguard mission
critical applications by
distributing infrastructure across
geographically distant locations.
We provide unflinching continuity of
service even in case of local disasters
or catastrophic infrastructure failures.
This architecture uses seamless failover
through active configurations, which
enables seamless zero downtime failover.
Strong data integrity is provided with
advanced data application technologies
that provides strong consistency in
all regions and efficient traffic flow.
Is achieved with intelligent
cross region traffic steering.
This forward looking paradigm
transforms disaster recovery into a
proactive capability from a reactive
scramble, making it a seamless
always on experience for end users.
The integration of artificial
intelligence in cloud native
architectures is revolutionizing crisis
response by enhancing situational
awareness and predictability.
AI enables predictive analytics.
Machine learning algorithms can analyze
historic trends and real-time information
to foresee crisis escalation and resource
requirements before they turn critical.
We may also get automated
decision support.
AI systems provide evidence-based
recommendations on resource
allocation, evacuation routes,
and response prioritization
under high stress situations.
And finally, real time data
Fusion, AI can combine different
sources of data from social
media and satellite imagery to
sensor networks into consolidated
operation intelligence dashboards.
In cases of degraded central
cloud connectivity, edge computing
offers edge site resilience.
Assured operational
continuity is a key benefit.
Edge Sites guarantee the uninterrupted
operation of vital systems enabling
critical functionality even when
Central Cloud connectivity is lost.
This foundational autonomy ensures
resilience in the direct scenarios.
Edge computing offers life savings
speed two local processing offers
less than a hundred milliseconds
near realtime responsiveness.
This is what's needed in
life critical applications.
Such as emergency and instant
medicine monitoring where differences
are all in the millisecond order.
It also enables unburdening network
infrastructure with server side
intelligence and data processing
locally at the data's point of origin.
This mitigates network saturation and
ensures that critical communication
channels remain operational and
performant during high demand.
Crisis scenarios.
In a crisis situation, perimeter
security frameworks fall apart.
That's why a zero trust
security model is critical.
This architecture is built on three
pillars, continuous verification.
It enforces intense continuation,
verification upon all users,
devices, and services everywhere.
This eradicates implicit trust
and defeats unauthorized access.
During dynamic crisis scenarios, strict
least pur privilege, each user and each
system possess just exactly the rights
necessary to carry out their function.
This restricts lateral movement
almost entirely and reduces the
effect of potential compromise.
UBI Twitters encryption.
It offers end-to-end encryption while
data is in transit at rest and processing,
your sensitive data remains protected even
when the nearby surroundings are hacked.
Moving to a crisis, resilience
enabled cloud native architecture
does not occur overnight.
A phase migration method is a paramount
to success, causing the least disruption
while developing capabilities.
It begins with assessment and planning,
which involves the evaluation of
existing infrastructure and the
specification of the resilience needs.
Second, a proof of concept phase
entails running pilot projects on
non-critical systems in order to
prove the architecture decisions.
Next, start the core service migration.
Moving code services with
known patterns and practices.
Lastly, integration and optimization.
Linking your legacy and cloud
native applications with continuous
performance optimization.
Effective management of a crisis
also demands unwavering government
agencies, business community, and global
cooperation across partner organizations.
Cloud native architecture
is the enabler here.
They also maintain shared infrastructure
via shared cloud platforms.
This minimizes duplicate work and
provides instant scalable resource
allocation during emergencies.
They use standardized APIs to
unleash realtime intelligence
and better decision making.
APIs facilitate convenient
and secure data sharing across
various organizational systems.
With critical information flowing
without dealing, and finally, they
advocate collaborative governance.
Adaptable shared responsibility
frameworks ensure common security,
effective compliance, and
effective operational management
across all partner organizations.
Developing trust and
collaborative behavior.
Adopting this approach leads to
tangible, measurable outcomes.
Accelerated recovery, we can
significantly reduce recovery times
and accelerate operational restoration.
Far surpassing the capabilities
of traditional infrastructure.
Dynamic scaling.
It enables unparalleled scaling velocity,
rapidly expanding capacity to meet
critical demands, guaranteed availability.
It ensures continuous uptime for
mission critical services, even a
mist of major disruptions, and it
leads to strategic cost savings.
By maximizing resource utilization and
automating management processes, you
unlock substantial cost optimization.
Ultimately, this is about
more than just technology.
Cloud native architectures
transform crisis response.
From reactive damage control to
proactive resilience management, this
shift enables more equitable service
delivery, ensuring that vulnerable
populations maintain access to
essential services during emergencies.
Enhanced interoperability breaks down
traditional silos between agencies
creating coordinated response capabilities
that can adapt to evolving threats.
This result is just not technical
resilience, but societal resilience.
It creates communi communities that
can withstand adapt to and recover
from disruption more effectively.
Cloud infrastructure is no
longer just an IT strategy.
It's a cornerstone of societal
stability, the convergence of
cloud native architectures, AI edge
computing, and zero thrust security.
Offers crisis resilience
possibilities such as never before.
The question isn't whether
organizations will adopt these
approaches, but how quickly they
can transform their infrastructure.
I urge you to start with resilience
first, design principles, build
distributed, elastic and self-healing
systems from the ground hub.
Invest in cross-sector partnerships
to create interoperable platforms
that strengthen collective resilience.
And embrace continuous improvement.
Treat resilience as an evolving
capability, not a one-time implementation.
The time for resilient
infrastructure is now The cost of
inaction grows with every crisis.
Thank you.