Hello everyone.
This is RA Maria, and today I'll
be talking about cloud native MDM
utilizing Kubernetes orchestration
for enterprise data quality.
At scale Master data management
system is evolving from monolithic
systems to cloud native architectures.
This transformation leverages Kubernetes
orchestration to deliver enterprise
grade data quality at unprecedented
scale, combining the reliability of.
Traditional MDM with agility
of modern cloud platforms,
why master data management must evolve?
Traditional MDM systems are heavyweight
stateful and slow to scale in
modern distributed environments
with hybrid and multi-cloud
deployments, it they demand flexible
portable data management solutions.
No, we are into microservices era.
Distributed architectures
require MDF systems.
That can integrate seamlessly across
services to meet the real time demands.
Modern enterprises need immediate
data quality and availability
for critical business decisions.
The enterprise IT landscape
has fundamentally changed with
containerization, making workloads,
portable and dynamic cloud native MDM
Rethinks data mastering principles to
work seamlessly in Kubernetes ecosystems
providing a single source of truth.
For customers, products, suppliers,
and financial accountants.
Cloud native MDM represents
a complete redesign of data
mastering for distributed, elastic
and automated environments.
It's not simply ization the legacy MDM
products, but fundamentally rethinking
how data quality and governance
work in modern infrastructure.
With microservices first, design
each MDM capability like matching.
Merging validation.
Governance operates as its own
containerized service with clear
boundaries and responsibilities.
Kubernetes manifest provide declarative
infrastructure, helm charts and GI tops,
manage deployments and configuration
through code-based approaches.
Horizontal part autoscaler.
Handles variable data loads automatically
scaling resources up and down based
on demand, providing elastic scaling.
The backbone of orchestration pods
and deployments encapsulate my
MD microservices, like matching
engines and data quality validators
in managed scalable units.
State full sets help in managing
ordered stable PO pod identities and
persistent data for core MDM stores that
require state consistencies persistent
volumes provide durable storage beyond
ephemeral containers, ensuring data
service PO restarts and failures
with enforcing the secure, reliable
interservice communication through
tools like T and linker service mass
integration can be easily achieved.
Kubernetes transforms MDM into fragile
static deployments to self-healing,
dynamically scalable infrastructure
config maps, and secret manage
governance rules and credentials.
With horizontal port auto scaling responds
automatically to data processing spikes.
How?
How Help charge help in streamlining
MDM deployment with seamless single
command deployment for integrated
multiple components in MDM architecture.
Dynamic Parameterization for precise
environment specific configuration,
robust dependency orchestration
for interconnected sub charts.
Assurance of safe and reliable
roadblocks for control updates help
revolutionizes the deployment of Complex
M Indian systems by encapsulating
them as version ParaBit rise packages.
This allows teams to consolidate
all critical events from
data matching and cleansing.
To user interfaces and APIs
into single manageable chart.
The result is unparalleled consistency
across development, staging, and
production environments drastically
minimizing configuration drift and
accelerating time to value, which is hard
to achieve In monolithic MDM systems.
Handling stateful workloads in Kubernetes
requires sophisticated patterns to
ensure data integrity and consistency
across the distributed environments.
Stateful sets provide stable network
identities and order deployment
for critical MDM components.
Abstract cloud pro storage providers
like A-W-S-E-B-S, Azure Disk, and GCP
per certain disk provide persistent
volume so that data can be lost.
Tools like ETCD or CockroachDB
ensure consistent state across
nodes and prevent data corruption,
providing consensus protocols with.
Cloud native MDM, it's relatively
easier to scale for millions of records.
99.9% availability can be
achieved even when processing
millions of records per day.
Organizations can run 24 7 operations
with continuous data processing with
automatic scaling, and up to a million
plus record can be mastered at enterprise
scale with this infrastructure.
Kubernetes native MDM handles massive
data loads through horizontal port
autoscaler, sharded data stores,
and even driven architecture using
Kafka and pulse resources quota scale
prevent service starvation while
maintaining optimal performance.
This architecture provides a
self-healing and resilient system.
Likeness and readiness probes
automatically restart unhealthy
pots, ensuring continuous
operation and monitor health.
Continuously circuit breakers
prevent cascading failures between
independent services through
intelligent failure isolation.
Stateful sets smooth workloads to healthy
nodes with persistent storage intact
during failures, providing automated
failover mechanism tools like chaos Mash.
Validate that MDM survives unexpected
disruptions and maintains data integrity.
Data quality without visibility is a
black box, which is one of the major
problems in existing MDM solutions, but
with cloud native MDM, which integrates
deep observability to transform
MDM from an opaque system into an
actionable data operations platform.
Prometheus exporters publish matrices
for data validation, throughput
matching latency, and merge accuracy.
Grafana dashboards provide at a glance
view of MDM Health and Performance
with customizable visualizations.
Jacker or Open Telemetry can be used
for distributed tracing to follow
data records across microservices.
Intelligent alerting can be placed
with notify, which notify DevOps
teams to f fulfill data loads.
Still governance rules or degraded SS
managing configuration manually error
prone and lacks audit auditability,
tops brings discipline, traceability
and agility to MDM, which is a critical
requirement in regulated industries.
With version control rules, every
change in update to data matching
survivorship or validation policies
is tracked and get with full history.
Automated deployments using CSCD pipelines
apply Kubernetes manifest date, relatively
reducing human error and deployment time.
We can revert to known good
configurations if governance updates
cause issues, ensuring system
stability and providing safe rollbacks.
I would like to talk about
enterprise system integration.
In this way, we can integrate with
API gateways using Kong A PG index,
which expose master data to application
securely with rate limiting and
authentication Streaming platforms
like Kafka and Puler can ingest raw
data and broadcast master updates in
real time across in the enterprise.
With for the legacy systems, integration
can be achieved using adapters and bridge
services, which can bring mainframe or ERP
data into cloud native fabric seamlessly.
DBT Airflow and Blue Feed data
warehouses and analytics platform
with high quality master data can be
leveraged using ETL and ELT pipeline.
By using standard APIs and event driven
patterns, MDM becomes an integrated
hub rather than an isolated silo,
enabling comprehensive data governance
across the enterprise ecosystems.
Data mastering often involves
sensitive and regulated information.
Cloud native MDM enforces comprehensive
security measures while maintaining
cloud agnostic compliance capabilities.
We can ensure security with zero trust.
Networking where mutual tail is between
services via server mash ensures encrypted
communication and identity verification.
Kubernetes secrets integrated with
vault systems like HashiCorp Vault or
secure for secured credential handling
can help in secured management.
End-to-end encryption can be achieved
and data can be encrypted in transit
with TLS and rest using cloud
provider KMS or CSI Drivers fine.
Green access controls and comprehensive
audit logs to meet the G-D-P-I-C-C-P
and other industry requirements can
be achieved with RPAC and audit.
In one of the studies,
the our global retailer.
Was face facing the a huge roadblock
with when they had, like with millions
of products and customer records with
daily ingestion peaks During seasonal
sales, legacy MDM downtime was affecting
order fulfillment and customer experience
to get away with this problem, they
deployed MDMS microservice with he state
full sets backed by cloud block storage.
Kafka for ingestion and still were
secure interservice communication.
As a result, they achieved 99.9% uptime,
including Black Fridays in the peak
load, 30% cost reduction using elastic
scaling during off peak periods, and
the rule deployments were easier like
never before with new governance rules
via GI tops being deployed in minutes.
With this.
In this slide, I would like to talk about
some common best practices and pitfalls.
Best practices include start small.
Begin with one domain, like customer
data before expanding to other entities.
Choose databases and consensus strategies
upfront to avoid costly refactoring later.
Automate everything using C-A-C-I-C-D
for both application and data governance.
Configurations, observe
relentlessly build comprehensive
dashboards before going live.
To ensure visibility, the most
common pitfalls which we have
observed are stateless assumptions.
Treating MDM like a stateless app
leads to data loss on PO restarts
storage latency, ignoring storage
performance flows, matching and merging
under load network complexities.
Underestimating service match.
Operational overhead and
configuration complexity may
be a nightmare on later stages.
Missing observability, skipping
monitoring, making debugging
makes debugging impossible,
but data quality degrades.
So all these things should be
in place before we go live.
Cloud native MDM continues
evolving as enterprises modernize
their data infrastructure.
The future promises even greater
automation, intelligence and
integration capabilities.
Machine learning will improve identity
resolution, matching accuracy and survival
survivorship decisions automatically.
With serverless extensions, we can
offload specific data transformations
to fast platforms for cost
effective event driven processing.
MDMs deployment with multicast deployment.
Nearer to closer to the data regions.
Through edge computing and distributed
cluster architecture can be achieved.
We can build self tuning systems
with automated data Pipelines with
anomaly detection will minimize
human intervention requirements.
Kubernetes and cloud native design have
redefined how data mastering can scale,
heal, and integrate in modern enterprise.
By embracing these technologies,
organizations achieve resilient,
observable, and scalable MDM platforms
capable of supporting the next
decade of data driven innovation.
Thank you for your time.