Okay.
Hello everyone.
I'm Karti Gain ami.
Today I'll be presenting my work
on Cloud Native Defense in depth
security for mission critical
services in managed Kubernetes.
This presentation focuses on how mission
critical services can be securely deployed
in managed Kubernetes environments.
Let me walk you through the key
topics I'll be covering today.
Here's the roadmap for today's talk.
I'll begin with an introduction that
sets the context for why BER security
is important, especially in managed
services like a KS, EKS and GKE.
Next, we will define mission
critical services and explore
examples from industries like.
Finance, healthcare,
defense, and supply chain.
Then I will highlight the security
challenges in managed Kubernetes,
such as insider threats, runtime
exploits, and misconfigurations.
We will move on to the cloud native
securities forces cloud cluster
container and code, which form
the layer, the defense model.
We will then look at practical
security measures for each layer.
First, the cloud boundary, then
cluster boundary, container boundary,
and finally, the core boundary.
At the end, I will wrap
up with key takeaways.
Kubernetes has become the foundation
for modern cloud native infrastructure.
It allows organization to deploy
and scale applications efficiently.
Most enterprises today use managed
Kubernetes service such as EKS Azure,
Kubernetes Services, EKS, Amazon
ela, elastic Kubernetes Service,
and GKE Google Kubernetes Engine.
While these managed services simplify
operations and use managed or management
overhead, they also introduce new
security risks, especially for.
Sensitive or mission critical workloads,
for example, control plane exposure,
mis misconfigurations or insider threats
can have serious consequences in these
environments to address these challenges.
The work, this work proposes a
defense in depth security model based
on four csof Cloud Native Security
Cloud cluster container and code.
HC represents a layer of defense
that builds on the one below it.
Creating a defense creating a comp,
sorry, creating a comprehensive
layered protection strategy.
It helps the system more secure.
Now that we have set the context,
let's take a closer look at what I
mean by mission critical services.
And why securing them in Kubernetes
environments is so important.
In this slide, I define what I
mean by mission critical services.
These are software systems
that are absolutely essential
to an organization operations.
If they fail, the business
faces major financial safety
or reputational consequences.
For example, in finance, this includes
payment processing platforms or fraud
detection systems that must operate
securely and continuously In healthcare,
mission critical systems include
electronic health record platforms
and medical monitoring software
that directly affect patient care.
In different sector, we are talking about
secure communications and intelligence.
Al systems that must remain confidential
and resilient, and in the supply
chain examples include system
responsible for code signing, security
scanning, and package verification.
Each of these use cases handles sensitive
or regulated data, so deploying them in
a managed Kubernetes environments demands
and extremely high level of security.
Now we have understand what
mission critical services are.
I will move on to discuss the security
challenges organizes organization
faces when deploying them in
managed Kubernetes environments.
Now let's look at some of the key security
challenges that we, that arise when
deploying mission critical workloads
in managed Kubernetes environments.
First, there are insider threats from
administrators, whether they are cloud
admins, cluster admins, or tenant admins.
Each level has privileged access, and
if any credentials are compromised,
it can expose sensitive workloads.
Second misconfigurations and weak
authentication, or very common simple
mistakes like using overly PERCY rules.
Public control plane endpoint or missing
encryption can open up large attack
surfaces, the third attack attacker.
The third attackers can inject
malware into containers.
This can happen through vulnerable
base images, compromised registries
or during the CACD pipeline.
Next runtime exploits and
privilege escalation allow.
Attackers to escape from
containers and game control over
the host or cluster resources.
Finally, supply chain compromises are
becoming more frequent adversaries,
target build systems, image
registries, or dependencies to insert
malicious code before deployment.
These challenges highlight why managed
Bernet security requires more than just.
The default protections
offered by cloud providers.
We need a layered defense
in depth approach.
Now let's talk about the defense in depth
of security architecture, which forms
the core of my proposal proposed model.
The idea here is simple but powerful,
rather than relying on a single
layer of protection, we apply.
Multi multiple layers of controls across
all four domains of cloud native security.
The cloud cluster container, and code.
Each of these layers reinforces
the others, creating a cumulative
defense that significantly reduces
the chance of successful attack.
This model also follows a zero
trust approach, which means.
Every request user and workload
is verified regardless of
whether it is originates inside
or outside the environment.
By enforcing zero trust principles
at every layer, we can prevent
unauthorized access and lateral movement
within the Kubernetes environment.
This layered security design
helps mitigate key risks such
as insider threats, supply chain
attacks, and runtime exploit.
Which are common in managed
Kubernetes environments.
What is also important is that this
model leverages built in security
integrations available in managed
services, meaning organization can
strengthen their security posture
without adding excessive complexity.
Next, I will begin breaking
down this architecture by layer.
Starting with how to secure the
cloud boundary, which is the
outermost layer in the four Cs model,
this section focuses on
securing the cloud layer.
The first C in the cloud
native security model.
The hubs spoke network technology,
sorry, network topology, provides
centralized control and visibility.
The hub Virtual network manages routing,
inspection and security policies.
While spoke virtual networks
isolate workloads for stronger
segmentation and reduce the risk.
Strict firewall rules are
applied to restrict both inbound
and outbound connections.
Only authorized communication parts
are permitted, reducing exposure, and.
Limiting potential attack vectors.
Together these measures establish
strong perimeter production.
They minimize external exposure, shrink
the attack surface, and enforce zero
trust principles at the network boundary.
Together these measures
establish strong pyramid.
Using private clusters and endpoints
ensure that control planes and container
registry communicate only through
internal IP address keeping sensitive
management traffic of the public internet.
With the cloud boundary secured,
the next layer of protection
focuses on cluster boundary where.
Access control and internal communication,
secure security become critical.
Before we talk about the next c let's
quickly, recap, what security gaps
still exist after the foresee Cloud?
The cloud layer focuses primarily on
securing the external network boundary.
It provides protection from internet
based threats through firewalls, network
segmentation and control connectivity.
At this stage, all inbound and
outbound communication is monitored
and validated to ensure that
only trusted traffic flows into.
Are out of the Kubernetes environment.
However, this protection is
limited to the network perimeter.
While it successfully reduces the exposure
from external lacs, it does not address
risk that exist inside the environment.
The next layers cluster container
code contain components that remain
vulnerable to internal threats mis
privileged misuse, and time exploitation.
Therefore deeper security measures
are required to harden these inner
layers, which will be in the following
sections of the architecture.
The next focus area is the cluster
boundary where the goal is to
protect internal components such
as a PA server ETCD storage nodes,
and interport communication.
Securing cluster boundary represents
the second layer of defense in
the cloud native security model.
At this layer, the focus shifts
from external network production
to securing internal Kubernetes
components such as AP server, ETCD,
storage, qbl, and port communication.
First, a private AP server combined with.
Rback integration limits control plane
exposure by using private endpoints
and enforcing strong authentication.
With role-based access controls,
one, authorized users can interact
with cluster resources following
the principle of least privilege.
Next ETCD storage, which stores all
the cluster configurations on secret
must be secrets must be protected.
Encrypting ETCD data addressed
using key management service.
KMS ensures that even if storage is
compromised, sensitive data remains
inaccessible to protect and node access.
Anonymous access should be disabled
ports restricted and network policy
supplied to prevent unauthorized
interaction with lower level services.
Implementing network segmentation
through Kubernetes network policies
are cloud native firewall limits,
part to part and known space
communication effectively reducing the
lateral movement within the cluster.
Finally OPA gatekeeper admission
control controller enforces
compliances compliance and policy
rules before workloads are admitted.
Examples included blocking privileged
parts, ensuring image signatures or
verifying configuration standards.
Together these controls strengthen
the internal security posture
of Kubernetes environment by
safeguarding its most critical
management and operational components.
With cluster layer secured
attention now shift to next layer.
What security gap still exist
after the second C cluster?
At this stage, both the cloud layer
and cluster layer have been secured.
The network perimeter is protected
and strong controls, such as
private endpoints or back encryption
admission policies are in place.
However, these controls primarily
protect the infrastructure and
management components of Kubernetes,
not the workload themselves.
The next major security challenge
lies within container layer where
vulnerabilities can still be exploited
even in a well secured cluster.
Attackers may attempt container breakouts
exploiting kernel vulnerabilities,
or injecting malicious code into.
Running containers through compromised
images or runtime downloads.
The following section explains how
confidential VMs confidential containers
enhance container isolation and
prevent host or admin level tampering.
Cut securing container boundary.
This section focuses on
the container boundary.
The third layer in the cloud
native defense in depth model.
While the cloud and cluster layer layers
are addresses into external and control
interest, the container layer deals
with risks inside the workload itself.
Pos and containers or address of
breakout or kernel exploitation if,
if a container is compromised, it
can potentially escape to the host,
exploit kernel vulnerabilities, or move
laterally across workloads, threatening
the integrity of entire cluster.
To mitigate this confidential
virtual machines cvms or used
to protect node level workload.
C VM CVMS utilize hardware backed
trusted execution environments.
These to encrypt memory and CPU to
isolate a virtual mission from hypervisor
and host preventing unauthorized
access from infrastructure layers.
Building on that confidential
container, extend this protection
to individual containers.
They run inside Secure enclaves ensuring
that application code and data in use
remain protected even if the kernel
container runtime or host is compromised.
Together, these confidential computing
technologies prevent host or admin
tampering ensuring that even privileged
users, cloud operators, or compromised
system components cannot access or
alter these sensitive workloads.
This approach brings a new level
of assurance to running mission
critical services by safeguarding
the runtime environment from both
external and insider threats.
With the container boundary secured,
the next focus is on the final layer.
Before that let's recap.
What security gaps still exist
after the third C container layer?
At this point, most of the
external and infrastructure layer
threats have been mitigated.
As you see, as you can see in this
picture, protections from the hypervisor
host, or guest agents and peer
ports or containers are already in
place through confidential computing
and strong isolation controls.
However, the remaining risk
lies within the code itself.
The application logic running inside
the container, even with the strong
TCB test computing base provided
by the confidential containers, the
code that executes at runtime can
still introduce new vulnerabilities.
Examples include code that
downloads external packages, bonds,
unauthorized processes, or execute
unverified scripts at runtime.
All of which can bypass
inte security boundaries.
This residual risk highlights the need
for controls that protect not just the
container environment, but also the
behavior of the code running inside it.
The next and final layer, the fourth
C code, addresses this exact half gap
by applying runtime integrity control.
System called restrictions and
continuous monitoring to ensure
security ensure secure execution.
So the following section explains
how the code layer uses measures
like trusted image signing immutable
containers sec com and fall code two
completely mitigate the runtime threats.
Securing code boundary.
The code boundary represents
the fourth and final layer of
of the defense in depth model.
This layer focuses on securing the
code that executes inside containers
to ensure that runtime behavior
remain controlled and trusted.
First using tested image registries
and signing ensures that 1D verified
and cryptographically signed
container images are deployed.
This step significantly reduces
supply chain risks by preventing
the use of unverified or tampered
images for Linux workloads.
Aless image provide an
additional safeguard.
These images do not contain shells
package managers or other utilities that
attackers could exploit, reducing the
attack surface to one leak components
required for the application to function.
Next, immutable containers prevent
any modification after the deployment.
If updates are needed, a new image
must be rebuilt and redeployed,
ensuring that runtime, tampering, or
unauthorized changes cannot occur.
The second security feature adds
another layer of protection by
restricting system calls that processes
or mounting file systems et cetera.
Secom helps block
malicious runtime actions.
Finally, file Code Protect provides
a realtime runtime monitoring.
It continuously observes
container and system activity.
Detecting an anomalies such as
privilege, escalation attempts,
unexpected file access, or the
execution of unknown processes.
Alerts are generated whenever the
suspicious behaviors occurs together.
These security controls ensure that the
code running inside containers remain
verified, immutable, restricted in
behavior, and continuously monitored.
Effectively closing the final security
gap in four Cs model with all four layers.
Cloud, cluster, container,
and code secured the defense.
In depth architecture now provides
comprehensive protection across
the entire Kubernetes environment.
What gaps, what security gap still
exist after the fourth C code?
At this stage, the defense in
depth model has fully implemented.
Every layer from cloud to code now
has its own set of protections.
With immutable container system
called restriction and real time
monitoring in place, the code layer
effectively closes the last known gap.
At this point, there are no remaining
vulnerabilities within the defined layers.
All the major attacks, surfaces
from the infrastructure to
runtime have been addressed.
The overall security posture becomes
significantly stronger because each
sea reinforces the one below it
forming a continuous chain of trust.
This means that even if an attacker
somehow breaches one layer, the remaining
layers continue to protect the system.
In other words.
The combination of all four layers, cloud,
cluster, container, and code delivers
a comprehensive end-to-end defense
model for mission critical workloads.
Next, let's move on to the key takeaways
where I will summarize the benefits of
this defense in depth approach and how
it enables strong protection without
compromising the developer agility.
Key takeaways.
So to wrap things up, here are the
main points I want to leave you with.
First, mission critical services,
whether it is payment system, healthcare
applications, or defense workload
need more than basic protection.
Their defense in depth approach
gives these workloads the level
of security they truly require.
Next.
It's important to remember that
the default cloud provider, se,
provider security, things like
IM firewalls, net and network
rules is only part of the story.
Those features are great, but they
don't fully address modern multi-layer
attacks that target the supply
chain are runtime environments.
That's where the real strength
of defense in depth comes in by
layering controls across all forces,
cloud, cluster, container, and code.
And combining that with zero trust,
confidential containers and runtime
monitoring, you can close every gap
from infrastructure to application.
In short, defense in depth gives us
a way to protect mission critical
workloads without slowing down
innovation, that software today.
Thank you for listening.