Hi, welcome to Automation for Equitable
and Resilient Digital Public Services.
I am Mahi Kuri.
I'm accepted to be part of CNET 2 20 25.
In this talk, I will walk you through
how Kubernetes need to automation
is changing the way the government's
deliver the digital services.
My goal is to show you not just the
technology, but the social impact, how
this transformation can make services
more accessible, more reliable, more
equitable for citizens everywhere.
The digital public service RESO
revolution, governments across the
are rapidly digitizing citizens.
Expect 24 by seven service
availability, quick updates.
And inclusive experiences,
regardless of language or geography.
Traditional IT systems are not
designed for the scale or speed.
Kubernetes native automation enables
government to meet these demands.
For example, think about applying for
benefits online at midnight or during
a national emergency where millions
of people log in simultaneously.
With modern automation the
experience doesn't collapse.
It scales up seamlessly.
Why Kubernetes Native Automation matters.
So why does it matter?
Scalability ensures governments can
handle certain spikes like tax filing
deadlines or vaccine registrations.
Reliability ensures services
stay up during the movement,
citizen need them the most.
Equity is about fairness.
Everyone should get the same
quality of service whether they're
in major city or a remote village.
And efficiency matters because
governments must do more with less
optimizing taxpayers resources.
Taken together all these four pillars make
Kubernetes native automation, not just
technical solution but pub, but for public
good 37% system availability increase.
Our research showed that public sector.
Organizations used Kubernetes
Automation achieved a 37% increase
in the system's availability.
That means fewer disruptions of fewer
disruptions and more trust from citizens.
Imagine healthcare portals, emergency
response apps, or welfare systems staying
up consistently during the critical times.
This improvement is more than a number.
It's about ensuring the citizens rely
their government when it matters the most.
Cross sector impact analysis.
We studied the impact across healthcare,
legal services, and public utilities.
The three domains highlight how
broad and deep the changes can be.
Healthcare benefited from telemedicine,
scaling legal services, improved access
and reduced backlogs and utilities,
improved resilience in rural areas.
The theme here is simple
automation transforms not only
how efficiently systems run, but
also fair how fairly services are
delivered to diverse citizens.
Healthcare transformation
results in healthcare.
The results were dramatic.
Telemedicine consultations grew by 430%.
That's not just a statistic.
It means patients who couldn't
get an appointment in person had
new options to access the care.
Few rollout times dropped from, future
rollout times dropped from 45 days to just
seven in public health, those weeks can
mean the difference between controlling
an outbreak and letting it spread.
Kubernetes automation gave
systems the agility they needed.
Legal system, digital equity gains
in legal system, digital automation,
reduced code backlog by 23%.
That means cases got resolved faster.
He's pressure on courts and
providing justice more quickly.
Equally important, multilingual
automation, improved access for
non-English speaking by 52%.
That's a huge step.
Ensuring equity, everyone,
regardless of language, can
navigate the legal system digitally.
Infrastructure, resilience, ments.
Emergency services achieved
99.999% uptime thanks to air
driven self-healing infrastructure.
The level of reliability is
crucial when lives are on the line.
In rural areas, it deployments
reduced outages by 76%.
Imagine a small community
relying on consistent power or
water automation ensures these
essential services don't fail.
This demonstrates how resilience is not
just a technical but deeply human in
its impact, financial impact, and ROI.
Automation also delivered financial
value organizations reduced cost by up
to 34% within the two years and 42%.
By the year three, these savings.
Aren't about cutting corners.
They result from systems running
more efficiently, scaling
smartly, and reducing downtime.
This creates sustainability.
Governments can invest those
resources into new initiatives while
maintaining high service quality
staff innovation capacity growth.
More automation.
Only 23% of staff was
available for innovation.
Most time was spent on
firefighting and manual processes.
After automation, that number grew to 58%.
Think about that means what that means.
Staff can now focus on creating
better citizen experiences,
designing new programs, and
thinking strategically instead of
trouble troubleshooting servers.
This shift is where technology
directly improves human potential
implementation challenges.
Of course, no transformation
is without challenges.
The first is a skill gap.
Kubernetes expertise is limited
in many public sectors requiring
targeted training and partnerships.
The second is legacy.
Integration.
All systems don't disappear
overnight, so careful migration
planning is very essential.
And the third is risk of a digital divide.
We must ensure that automation
includes vulnerable populations
rather than excluding them.
Policy recommendations.
To address these challenges,
we recommend four key actions.
First.
Establish cross agency standards
to align security and operations.
Second, invest in workforce development
with structured training programs.
Third practice inclusive design.
So accessibility built into every project.
And finally, foster private partnership
that brings in expertise, but keep
public control over essential services.
These are practical.
Actionable steps
governments can take today.
Implementation framework.
Our implementation framework breaks
the journey into four phases.
The first three months, assess
infrastructure and establish baseline
metrics in months four to eight.
Pilot Kubernetes in
low list risk services.
In months nine to 18, scale
up the critical services
with citizens feedback loops.
Finally, continuous optimization ensures
system adapt with AI and evolving needs.
This phased approach reduces the risk
and builds confidence at every step.
Building institutional
trust through technology.
Successful automation does
more than improve uptime.
It strengthens the relationship
between governments and citizens.
Transparency in service status
con, consistent quality, proactive
communication, and accessible design.
All of these build trust.
Andrus in institutions is vital
for Democrat democratic engagement.
When citizens see reliability, unfairness,
and digital services, they engage more
and believe more in the institutions.
The next steps.
So should organizations do next,
start by assessing your infrastructure
and mapping the citizen's journey.
Then build your team.
Invest in Kubernetes training
and cross-functional groups.
Finally, start small, but scale
smart pilots in low risk areas,
build momentum and confidence before
tackling mission critical systems.
The important thing is to begin
transformation doesn't have to be massive.
One day, small wins accumulate
into systematic change.
And thank you for joining this session
on Kubernetes Native Automation
for Digital Public Services.
I hope these insights inspire you to
think about where automation can make the
biggest impact In your next context, I
would like to continue the conversation.
If you'd like to continue the
conversation, I'd be glad to connect
on LinkedIn or during q and a. Together
we can build more resilient, equitable,
citizen focused services for the future.
Thank you again.
Bye.