Hey everyone.
Firstly I would like to thank.
Thank queue for this opportunity
to present my research on LLM
powered self-auditing frameworks
for healthcare data pipelines.
So this presentation will share how
fundamental breakthrough in healthcare
data quality assurance has been achieved
using LLMs with novel prompting strategies
that represent a paradigm shift from
traditional auditing approaches.
So coming to the problem I would like
to discuss about the problem first.
So currently healthcare organizations
manage incredibly complex data ecosystems
like modern healthcare institutions
process millions and billions of.
EHR electronic health records lab
results imaging studies prescriptive
data and admin data through intricate
webof interconnected systems
like Epic, Cerner, and so on.
As these systems grow in complexity
maintaining data pipeline integrity
has emerged as a critical challenge.
The consequences extend far beyond
technical inconveniences data
pipeline inconsistencies can directly
affect patient safety treatment
efficacy, and regulatory compliance.
So current research shows that
manual audits examine only 35%
of trans transformational logic
while manual methods detect
merely like 52% of known pipeline
issues in controlled environments.
This represents a substantial gap that
this LLM based framework addresses.
Coming to current limitations
we discussed about the problem.
And also I would like to highlight
about the current limitations.
So traditional auditing approaches
face significant limitations.
Manual reviews are incredibly labor
intensive, requiring specialized
expertise spanning clinical.
Knowledge database architecture
and statistical analysis.
So they typically examine only a fraction
of the total data transformations.
And rule-based verification systems
offer greatly greater scalability,
but focus primarily on structural
and syntactic validations rather
than complex semantic relationships.
Or clinical appropriateness.
So most critically, these methods
consistently fail to detect logical
inconsistencies related to clinical
guidelines and business rules.
Precisely.
This is where the highest risk errors
occur in the healthcare settings.
Now since we have discussed about the
problem and the re limitations, now I
want to highlight the solution part.
So this LLM powered framework
addresses these limitations through
sophisticated prompt engineering that
enables expert level semantic analysis.
The core innovation is a hierarchical
prompting strategy combined with
a chain of thought reasoning
workflows that systematically
decompose complex healthcare auditing
tasks while maintaining awareness
of cross domain dependencies.
The methodology achieved a 42% improvement
in error detection sensitivity, and a 35.
Percent reduction in false positive rates
compared to standard prompting approaches
with along with this, there is a
remarkable 58% growth in detecting complex
multi condition clinical protocols.
Now I would like to talk about
the framework architecture.
So this framework implements a
multi-layered architecture with
five integrated components.
So the data extract layer interfaces
with existing healthcare systems
using read-only connections
and API based interactions.
The Prompt Generation engine formulates
contextually appropriate instructions,
incorporating clinical guidelines
historical data patterns, and
organization specific business rules.
The LLM orchestration service manages
model interactions and response
parsing the analysis, interpret
interpretation module, and translates
LLM outputs into actionable insights
while the audit management system
tracks findings, recommendations,
and remediation activities.
This comprehensive architecture processed
substantially more distinct data
transformations per pipeline compared to
the traditional sampling based approaches.
So that's about the architecture.
Now I would like to highlight
the prompting strategy.
So there is a three tier prompting
hierarchy represents a significant
methodological advancement.
Structural prompts guide the LLM to
analyze syntactic and architectural.
Elements like SQLs and taxes,
validation, ETL, pipeline connectivity
and data type, consistencies and so on.
And semantic prompts focus on clinical
appropriateness, like guideline adherence
verification, temporal logic validation,
and cross domain consistency checking.
So the comparative prompts evaluate
consistency between components
through version comparison and
cross system reconciliation.
The chain of thought technique
enables structure reasoning that
mirrors expert analysis patterns
significantly improving complex
logical inconsistency de detection.
That's about the prompting strategy.
Now I would like to discuss about
the results implementation results.
So the quantitative results demonstrate
transformative improvements.
The trans, the fa, the framework
achieved, and 87% detection rate
compared to 52% for manual methods,
which is like a 67 person improvement.
And also 63% for role-based
systems, which is like a 30.
38% enhancement.
The resource requirements decreased
by 70%, like from 2,400 to 720% hours
annually, while simultaneously increasing
pipeline coverage from 35% to 92%.
So this represents four 85% compound
efficiency gain economically
organizations achieve around like.
$340,000 in annual savings with
a 4.4 month ROI payback period
which by delivering a two 72%
annual return on investment.
And.
There are some case study highlights
that I would like to discuss.
So the implementation across multiple
healthcare organizations revealed
the frameworks real world impact at
Northeast Regional Health System.
The audit discovered.
Incomplete medication reconciliation
logic affecting patient safety alerts.
Which is a critical issue that
had evaded routine manual reviews.
Western academic medical centers
sepsis bundle compliance dashboard
contained discrepancies between
documented specifications
and implemented calculations.
And the Southern Community Health
Network had outdated heart failure
protocols that did not reflect latest
a HA or a CC guideline updates.
So these findings demonstrate the
frameworks ability to identify high
impact issues across diverse healthcare
environments that I just mentioned.
Coming to the comparative analysis
performance comparisons reveal
superior effectiveness across all
categories for complex logic detection.
The framework achieved 94% accuracy
compared to 34% for manual auditing,
and 41% for rule-based approaches
which is like a 176 percentage
improvement over manual methods.
Perhaps Bo.
Most importantly, guideline update lag
decreased from 47 days for rule-based
systems to just two days for this
framework, which is like a 96% reduction,
that prevents an estimated five 40
days of cumulative exposure to outdated
protocols per organization annually.
So that's about the comparative analysis.
And there are some ethical
considerations and integration.
Responsible implementation requires
thoughtful govern governance.
The research developed an ethical
framework comprising human oversight
with clear responsibility delineation
transparency in model limitations,
equity and pipeline coverage,
and robust privacy protections.
Privacy impact assessments demonstrated
full HIPAA compliance with no
protected health information exposure.
Integrated strategies focused on
enabling within CICD pipelines
for automated audits and alignment
with existing governance committees
achieving positive return of investment
most quickly with the CICD approach.
So now I want to talk about
the future directions.
So the future research directions
expand capabilities in several areas
like realtime monitoring through
streaming, streaming architectures,
which enables continuous validation
rather than periodic assessment.
And domain specific fine tuning
using healthcare specific data
sets shows, promise for further
performance improvements.
The research also explores shift left
approaches that identify potential
is issues during design phases rather
than like post implementation stage.
These advances position the framework
for broader application beyond healthcare
to other regulated industries as well,
requiring rigorous data governance.
So we can use the same framework
for other industries as well.
Not, yeah, that's that's
the future direction.
So finally, in conclusion this LLM.
Auditing framework represents a paradigm
shift in healthcare data governance.
The four 85% compound efficiency
gains exceed typical healthcare id
project improvements of 15 to 25%
performance, places the framework
and top 5% of the healthcare data
quality tools and also beyond.
Immediate benefits implementation
catalyzes broader organizational
changes, which increased cross-functional
collaboration, improved documentation
quality, and cultural shifts toward.
Continuous quality improvement and
this methodology enables healthcare
organizations to ensure data
integrity at a scale and consistency
impossible with traditional.
Approaches directly supporting
better patient outcomes
and operational excellence.
Yeah, that's about it.
Thank you so much for your attention
and questions about this research
and its implications for healthcare
data governance are welcome.
Yeah, thank you so much.