Hi, I'm Daniel Fedotov.
I'm a senior open source engineer in
custom by Veeam and today I'd like to
talk about how can we use cloud native
approach and tools to organize data
protection in our applications deployed
in cloud native and talk about using
Kinesis CEO is which is, CNCF project
and an open source tool to do that.
starting from why do we do that, right?
Kubernetes deployments have come a
long way, since first introduction.
But there's still some, myths around
data on Kubernetes, such as everything
is stateless, which isn't true because
Kubernetes itself has a state and,
it changes and there's something new
being added, something being removed.
And also, stateful workloads, people run
stateful workloads on Kubernetes because
they need state in their applications.
And if you want to run the application
as Kubernetes, they need state.
the myth being that why would I need
to protect my data when I can just
recreate my application, which is true.
You can recreate your application,
but the application has data and apart
without this data, it could be, useless
to the point plus all the, security audit
requirements, forensics, all those things
require you to actually save your data.
And more than that, it might require
you point in time, snapshot of your
data, or point in time recovery, even
for disaster recovery, for example.
the, common myth in the
cloud development is that.
My cloud provider is going to do
the backups, which is again, true
only partially because your cloud
provider might just lose your account.
That happened.
your cloud provider explicitly
says in the, all the, instructions
on how to, backup your data.
They say, please do some
sort of export, of your data.
and.
That's something that they
can't really do for you.
and finally, there are some tools
which can back up the etcd database
in your Kubernetes, but recovering
it, restoring it into something
that works is almost impossible.
And there's literally almost no
evidence that it might actually work.
Although backups are still possible.
still important for, for tracing and,
forensics, with all that, amount of data
we have in the Kubernetes deployment
and the cloud native deployment
is growing more and more users are
adopting, data services, volumes,
databases, on the Kubernetes over time.
And the most, one of the most
common applications, run on
Kubernetes is Redis, right?
Or Boster, elastic Search.
All of these things need some sort
of a data, storage disks, et cetera.
and people actually run those.
So this is the, this is something that
you want to do and this is something
that, really needs, management because
all of this data is running on this.
on disks, which are vulnerable, which
needs to be secured for many reasons.
and finally, another thing that we face
in another challenge that we're facing
with cloud deployments is that, in order
to follow the three to one backup rule,
which says that you have multiple copies,
have them in different media, and you have
them, at least one of them is off site.
this is additional challenge for a
Kubernetes deployments because we
need to move data out outside of the,
cluster that we actually run it on.
so some extra challenges of the,
Kubernetes deployment in particular
compared to other types of deployment,
like VMs, being that, with, The
way how with how easy it is to
create, heterogeneous apps, right?
You can run microservices.
They can have access
to some data services.
They can include multiple, span over
multiple domains, have many moving
parts, use different cloud, backups,
cloud, backends, So managing all this
backups, which could happen in your
cloud infrastructure, or which may not
happen in the cloud infrastructure,
managing disks, managing the workloads
and, application life cycles, such as
your application can actually be slowed
down and backup can be performed and
then application can be, restored again.
this is all getting more
and more complex as we.
actually have very different ways
of deployments, for our Kubernetes
application and the ways that
our deployments access the data.
so we could have deployments,
which access some cloud database.
We can have some database in the cluster
in separate namespace, or we can have
Namespaces, data services, co located
with the actual application code.
All of these things exist and
all of these things need some
approaches to backup and restore.
and on top of that, there's another
challenge, which is, again, being
more and more pronounced with the
Kubernetes, more microservices, is that,
we can't just have, a VM with all of
our application, slow down, shut down,
data collected and restarted, right?
We have all the microservices.
So running things like
application centric, backups.
in which your application should be
consistent with your data backup,
in which you can have multiple data
storage, all taken, all backups
taken at the same moment, that
becomes, that becomes a challenge.
and a lot of Tools that we have, in the
cloud services, they would just do one
thing like, an RDS snapshot or, volume
snapshots in, Kubernetes or in the, on,
in the cloud providers infrastructure.
So how do we manage that?
And, to manage that, I'd like
to introduce the canister.
Canister is a product, created by Kasten.
it is currently CNCF, sandbox project.
So it's.
It's officially a part of CNCF org and
it's moving towards, incubating stage.
what Canister contributes is essentially
a framework, which can, which is open
source, which can be used by anyone
and which, can have integrations with
all these, different data services.
And, different data storages and
this, integrations, can be shared
between different organizations
and can be, they can be reused
between different organizations.
And this really just putting
a standard on the Kubernetes,
a soft standard, I would say.
Similar to how, Istio was introduced as
a soft standard, to just teach people
how do they, how can they organize
their, the backup and restore process
and give the tools out of the box.
Here's your tool, how to back
up the passwords, for example.
How does it work?
So how can we achieve all these
things with application consistency?
With supporting multiple, topologies
and multiple services, right?
How would you do that?
In home, in your custom bespoke
scripts, you would have a script which
would call all the, data services,
disk APIs, and they will perform some
sort of a snapshotting operation.
And then it will collect all
the data, all the artifacts from
them, present them in some way.
Then you need to run the script somehow,
somewhere and some at some point in time.
And then you need to store
your artifacts somewhere.
What Estu does it, it
moves that to Kubernetes.
so what we have there is a bunch of
custom resource definitions, which is a
way that, you can interact with canister.
first one being the blueprint.
blueprint is a description of how
do you want to perform a backup or
a store, such as I want to, let's
say scale down the application.
I want to back up the disks.
I want to back up the database.
I want to scale up the application.
These are several phases you
would have in your script.
They just described in a slightly
different manner, in the blueprint.
Then action set is a custom resource
definitions, which runs the backup or
restore operational cleanup operation.
which.
Upon creation, performs an operation,
records the status of this operation,
and records the artifacts which
were, produced by this operation.
So this is your, essentially log
of actions, the action sets in your
Kubernetes, they will be stored
in the Kubernetes database, right?
And there will be a log of the operations.
And finally, profile is a configuration
which allows us to point to different.
destinations for data, such
as, S3 buckets, Google objects,
storage, Azure objects, storage.
so we can export data into
different, destinations.
now this is roughly how it works, right?
Your blueprint describes what kind
of actions do you need to take.
you would create an action set.
canister controller will pick this
action set up, find the blueprint,
build an execution plan, run all the
operations on Kubernetes runners.
the operations would do some, do
some extraction of, let's say from
MySQL app or some application,
some data storage, and they will
save it into some object storage.
And finally.
They would report an artifact,
the status of the artifact.
Back to you to the action set so
you can read it from the action set
And if you look closer into The blueprints
essentially are custom resources which
can be created in your Kubernetes
database There are some, example,
blueprints in a canister, repository,
those, custom resources includes actions.
So actions could be something like
backup or restore or cleanup or delete.
In this case, each action would
execute, several phases, one or more.
And those phases.
Execute, sequentially and they would
do each phase would do something
like run a pod or, create an RDS
snapshot or do something else.
what blueprints provide is a template.
For what needs to be done.
now in order to fill in the template
variables, we have the action set.
Action set is a command to
execute a certain action.
And it fills in values of the template.
It could reference an object such as
config map or stateful set or deployment.
It points to a profile, which
essentially points to a destination
where data will be saved.
And it's, describes the actions, which
actions needs to run and what values, what
template values needs to be, filled in.
in there, then action sets also
this important thing that they
track the status of the operations.
So if a phase fails, the action
set will have information of which
phase failed and with what error.
And, if phase completes, it contains
information about the artifacts that this,
phase, and then we have the, resume of all
the artifacts produced by the phases in
this and this action set, so action sets
in this way becomes your log of operations
and blueprints are your definitions
of, which operations need to be run.
yeah, we can continue with
the more concrete example.
I'm going to run.
An RDS backup, and I'm going to
describe what I'm doing in the process
of, setting up a canister, creating
a blueprint, and then, performing
a backup of RDS Postgres database.
as, set up in this, demo, we have an
RDS database, we have our Kubernetes
cluster with database client.
There's going to be a config map
pointing to this RDS database.
then we'll have canister installed
in the Kubernetes cluster.
And this canister would
have access to an S3 bucket.
The important note here that.
Although we use S3, it could be
actually any object storage, it was
just easier to set up for the demo,
but, RDS and S3, in this case, don't
really have to be, in the same, cluster,
in the same, data center or anything.
These are separate things.
Our, or S3 could be not S3, but we will.
and.
Okay, let's run the demo.
I have it pre recorded, so sorry for the
aspect ratio and for the mouse movements.
as mentioned, we have an RDS database,
we have a Kubernetes cluster, we
have our test app deployment, and
We have our S3 bucket, which we want
to actually save our backups to.
So now let's populate some
data into the database.
Let's have some just Postgres tables.
we have some, we have some
data we want to protect.
so next step would be to install kinister,
which is, pretty straightforward,
what it takes is just, install on Helm
chart and that's, it's pretty standard.
so we have a Helm repo.
then we have, actual
Helm releases installed.
we create it in the kinister
namespace in this case.
all the defaults, for, canister,
usable out of the box, there's some
additional parameters you can configure
such as cluster role bindings, maybe.
security, what cuts us to the
namespaces, but this works out of
the box just with Helm install.
We see there's an operator running
and we have a few custom resource
definitions such as blueprints, section
sets, and profiles that we're going
to create as a part of this demo.
so in here we create
a blueprint, which is.
In this case, we take it from canister
repository, ideally you would, maybe
take some example blueprints, as an
inspiration and create a blueprint
for your infrastructure, because you
might have more than one moving part.
I might want to, actually
coordinate, so one executes first,
another executes next, et cetera.
Blueprint here was created
as a custom resource.
It's there.
now our cluster contains
information, how to.
backup, RDS databases, and as you can see,
it's all template variables, which needs
to be filled with, with the action set.
next step, we want to create the
profile, which is a reference
to the, S3 bucket essentially.
and, profile ID, we'll need that just in
order to reference it from the action set.
That's why I'm creating
profile here in the demo.
finally, we want to create an action set,
which will perform a backup operation.
So as, as soon as action set is
created, canister, controller.
Will perform the backup
operation in this case.
We're using con CTL tool, which comes
with canister Which is just a helper
tool to create custom resources.
it's all it does It's just more
convenient to do it with a bunch of
parameters than to create A young
file with all the definitions.
That's why we're using it here,
but you can create the young file
So with, with the definitions and,
with the right spec and just create
it as normal Kubernetes resource.
we reference, the blueprint, we
reference the profile, we reference
the objects, which is, which is our
database config in this, particular case.
In some other cases, it could be a
deployment or a stateful set, for example.
So now as we get our action set created,
we can, get its action set ID, which
a record in your Kubernetes database,
for which action set can be identified.
pretty useful in order to, create restore,
for example, from backup operation.
And we're going to look into what's
going on in there while it's running.
And so while it's running, we have,
the current running face and we
have the artifacts in the status.
And as you can see, those are
currently not populated and I will
get populated as the action actually
gets executed as phases get finished.
And they put, artifacts information
into, into the artifacts of, in
the status of the action set.
So here, when everything is
completed, of course, there's, I
did some editing here because this
particular action runs for some time.
after it's all completed,
we have a state complete.
We have, the time when actions were
each phases, each phase was executed
and we have, artifacts, which
were produced by all this phases.
So this is our complete operation.
so we could take the artifacts and combine
them with a profile and the blueprint to
then create or store operation, because
this action set contains everything
you need to know about the operation,
like what blueprints was there.
what profile, where do we send the
data and what was the artifacts
named and also when it was executed.
So this is like full
information of the operation.
so in the S3 bucket, now we have
this file, which is our artifact
that we created from this operation.
so now.
Let's say something happens
With our table in this case.
I'm just gonna do very simple thing.
I'm just going to draw table
Which something that happens more
often than these corruptions?
Really in the real world people drop
tables all the time So that's one of
the main scenarios for a cover really
but of course there are other scenarios
possible for backup and restore is
just, going to go for the simple one.
And, in this, command, I'm also
using const TL tool to create one
action set out of another action set.
That's, even more convenience
for this const TL tool, because.
we will need to create the YAML file
and then fill it up with output from the
status of the action set resource that
we just seen for the backup operation.
While this one can do that automatically.
All it does, again, is just, creates
a custom resource as a result, it's
just a simpler command in here.
And here we select, action and we
point to, a previous action set
from which it gets the blueprint.
so now we can take a look at what
this, restore, action set, looks like.
so it exists, it completed, has
a time when it completes it.
And of course we can take a look
inside of what it looks like.
So inside of it, you can see that it got,
Input artifacts in the spec, which were
populated from the backup, action set.
We have a blueprint in the spec,
which was populated from the backup.
We have a profile, which was
populated from the backup, action set.
And we have a operation name, which is
restore, which is something different
that we specify in the arguments.
then in the, status of this action set,
we see an operation that was performed.
some output that it produced, which
is not really too relevant right now.
and then we have a status
that it's complete.
this is our restore operation session.
And, yeah, now what we want to do is
to verify that our table, is back.
gonna just check the table.
Here it is.
so we do have a bug.
so that's pretty much it for the demo.
the only last thing, is that, we have
the action sets in our both action
sets for backup and restore in our.
Kubernetes database.
So this is our log of operations.
and it contains all you need to know
about what was performed, right?
It has a reference to blueprints.
It has reference to artifacts, reference
to profiles, and it has a log of
all the phases that were executed.
so that's.
Let's go back to the presentation.
so what we just did right in this
demo, we created an RDS snapshot.
We exported it to an object storage, S3
in this case, but could be something else.
we run everything, all the
operations in the Kubernetes runners.
So don't need any provision, any new
machines or run anything locally.
we have blueprints describing what exactly
we did, which stored in the Kubernetes
database, or it could be in your
GitOps, which are there documented and,
could be well, represented and tested.
and we have all the operation
log in the, form of action sets.
So all the action sets.
give you an idea of what was running.
So this way, what was running,
what was the output of it?
when it was running.
So you can really have a holistic, view
on your, process of backup and restore
for your application design specifically
for application user blueprints.
canister right now has a bunch of
functions that you can run, kubexec
and kubetask are quite useful
because they run pod with a command.
So that's quite universal for
a lot of things you can do such
as database, dumps, for example.
we also support some, resource life
cycles, such as scaling up, down.
workloads, PVC operations to get files
from PVC, pro from volumes, volume
snapshots, Amazon RTS, custom function,
which we demonstrated in this demo.
And we support a whole bunch
of, object storage destinations.
yeah, and that's it.
thank you very much
for, joining this talk.
here's some links for, our GitHub
repo and our Slack channel.
please take a look, download the
blueprint, try it out yourself.
Thank you.