Hello everyone.
I'm Gar Siner.
I work at Google Cloud and I'm
excited to talk to you all today about
building intelligent retention engines
that can help with real time churn
detection using AI on Kubernetes.
As part of my prior experience, I have
worked across multiple organizations.
Mainly dig digital marketplaces.
In the past that would
be eBay, Walmart, StockX.
One of the common themes that most of
the digital marketplaces had was trying
to understand and reduce customer churn.
You'd say, why is that important?
I would say for four major reasons.
One, organizations want to make sure
that they're able to increase revenue.
Which is based on customer lifetime
value, which basically goes back
to making sure that the customer
is retained in the system.
Next, they also wanna make sure that the
customer acquisition cost or CAC is low.
It normally costs higher to acquire
a new customer as opposed to
retaining an existing customer.
Third, to make sure that we are
able to have targeted retention
campaigns, having a system that's
able to identify and reduce churn.
Ensures that marketing and customer
success teams can deploy highly targeted
and personalized offers or interventions
instead of broad, un targeted campaigns.
And I would say lastly.
Improved operational efficiency.
A system that's able to automate the
process of identifying at-risk customers
and even trigger automated workflows
can free up bandwidth to focus on more
strategic and important actions that can
evolve the customer journey even further.
Alright, so without further ado,
let's chop straight into it.
My agenda for today is gonna be firstly
talking about the churn challenge,
which will focus on addressing.
Why traditional retention models fail
and what makes them insufficient in
today's dig, digital marketplaces.
Next, we'll touch upon AI power
detection, and how does AI really help
scale up where traditional models fail.
Third, we'll talk the technical
infrastructure where I
detail my proposed solution.
We'll talk about what this means in
terms of successful implementation
and deploying into production.
Fourth, we look into
ethical considerations.
Whenever we talk about AI fairness,
model accuracy, user privacy, consent are
very important terms that come in handy.
And so we need to make sure that
we are able to address those, and
then we finally close and look
at what the future looks like.
All right, so touching upon why
traditional retention models fail.
I would say there's a couple of
reasons why these models aren't
necessarily well set for today's
modern digital environment.
One, they're reactive,
not necessarily proactive.
What this means is by the time they
have processed patterns and got an
output, it's generally too late in
the game and a customer has already
churned and we can't necessarily
do something retroactively next.
They generally are based on core
segmentation logic, which makes sure.
That they are focused on homogeneous
cohorts of customers, but aren't
necessarily able to take in unique
customer characteristics or behavioral
tra trajectories into consideration.
Third, they anomaly are based on
unlimited data, which is generally
transactional, so they are missing.
Attributes such as customer
communications, support,
tickets, even payment requests,
product behavior patterns.
So those are things which I think
are essential to make sure we have a
holistic understanding of the customer.
And lastly, they are
necessarily very flexible.
They have fixed rules and they are
built on very static thresholds
that make it hard to evolve in the
new modern environment to adapt
to marketplace dynamics, even on
different seasonality aspects and
changing customer expectations.
So then talking about how
does AI help in this case?
This is a new age of ai.
I would say there's three major
advantages that AI can offer here.
One instantaneous response times.
So we want models that are able to detect
churn signals and trigger interventions
right when the behavior happens.
And so they need to be
proactive rather than reactive.
Second, we want these models to be very
dynamic, so we wanna make sure that
they're able to continuously learn from
different data streams, they're able
to adapt their detection algorithms and
also evolve to more changing customer
dynamics as well as market dynamics.
And lastly.
These models need to be multi-source
capable, which means that they're
able to look at not just transactional
data, but they're also looking
at support interactions, product
usage metrics, engagement patterns.
So what all this would enable us to do is
to have a very holistic and comprehensive
churn risk assessment, and that's
where it can really scale up versus how
traditional models have normally worked.
Alright talking about the Kubernetes
Native AI Architecture Foundation, right?
Building this real time system
requires a cloud native foundation
that can scale dynamically with
data volume and model complexity.
So this is where
Kubernetes comes in, right?
Kubernetes is the essential
orchestration layer.
For these containerized AI workloads.
Let's break this down
for simpl simplicity.
What do we mean by
containerized AI workloads?
What do we mean by orchestration layer?
Let's think about this, say
like an orchestra, right?
So musical orchestra that most of you
have, or many of us must have attended.
We have different musicians playing
instruments, but then we have a
central conductor who is coordinating
across these different people.
He's making sure that the music
that we listen to is melodious.
Not c He makes sure that when
the drums are playing, the banjo
is probably gonna be silent.
Or when the flute is playing, the guitar
is not gonna be playing at the same time.
So orchestrating these different
aspects, what is an essential
element of hand of a conductor?
So think about Kubernetes as that
conductor in this cloud native
environment which is able to scale,
deploy, and automate different
workflows and different apps.
In this case, different containers.
And it basically is able to make
sure that we have a very scalable
infrastructure to deploy different
machine learning algorithms.
Alright, so then touching upon the
machine learning techniques itself
that I would say are more used, are
more essential for churn detection.
As of today I would say there's three
that I would want to touch upon.
One is recursive or recurrent
neural networks ENSs.
So ENSs are able to process
sequential customer behaviors, right?
They're able to identify patterns
based on a more continuous timeline
and they generally look at certain
aspects that would help flag if
behaviors change in log in frequency.
But then given that they our
focus more on recent behaviors and
necessarily aren't able to track
historical behavior patterns.
We also have L SDMs, which is
long short term memory models.
And how they differ is they're able
to actually capture both immediate
as well as distant behavior signals.
They're able to actually detect
gradual disengagement that can
happen over weeks or even months,
but then bring it all together.
There are ensemble models which are
random forest gradient boostings.
These models actually integrate
deep learning with traditional
machine learning for a much more
comprehensive risk assessment.
So think about this as a customer who
has been logging every week and then
suddenly they don't log in certain weeks.
Trying to understand if that
behavior is normal or truly out
of the ordinary is something that
these models can help detect.
Okay, so the next few slides, I'm actually
gonna touch upon the core technologies
and orchestration that's needed to
implement the system that I'm proposing.
So starting off with the different
data sources and feature engineering
data is an essential element of
any machine learning model, right?
So when we talk about data, what
data are we truly looking at?
We did reference transactional data in
the prior slides, but then trying to
understand session based data the session
duration, frequency feature adoption.
Cart abandonment add to cart
behaviors, interaction with
support tickets, payment typings.
All these, I would say are important
aspects or important data elements that
need to be also captured to make sure
that we are able to really get a holistic
understanding of the customer behavior.
Crucially, we need to also analyze
micro interactions, which could be
click-through rates, navigation patterns,
because these granular signals can
actually often proceed very visible
churn patterns or indicators by weeks
and months, and this really gives us
that intervention window to make sure
we're able to act at the right time.
Talking about the system or the
proposed architecture itself, I would
say there's three major components
that I'm going to touch upon.
Here we're gonna look at Apache Kafka.
We'll talk about Cube flow next,
and then key Native after that.
But then starting here with Apache Kafka.
So Kafka is the heart of the real
time system, and it helps to stream
all customer interaction events.
That could be from mobile apps, it could
be web applications, backend services,
and it helps create a unified event.
Log Kafka Streams.
API is a real time feature
extraction and aggregation system.
That helps detect anomalies and actually
enable pattern recognition based
on how the data is flowing through.
And then these process events and
patterns, trigger model inference requests
that enable instant churn, risk scoring,
and automated intervention workflows.
So again, putting it all together
in the example of the conductor.
Kafka is basically the system that is
enabling, picking up everything that's
happening all around, and making sure that
information is available to the conductor.
As the musicians when needed.
All right.
The next part of this system
is cube flow for machine
learning pipeline orchestration.
Cube Flow is an essential
orchestration framework for managing
complex machine learning workflows
that we had talked about earlier
with the RNN and LSTM models.
Basically think about this as the brain.
Of the engine.
And it enables us to really build very
complex and specific algorithms that
are able to understand and adapt to
different customer behavioral patterns.
The advantage that Q Flow offers
is it is able to automate model
training pipelines that retrain, churn
detection models as new data arrives.
Also, make sure that the
predictions remain accurate.
As the customer behaviors
evolve, and then it does support,
experiment tracking, hyper parameter
tuning, even model versioning.
All of these are critical and
essential aspects that are needed to
maintain a production ready system.
The other thing that it enables us
to do is data scientists can work on
testing and building new algorithms
of frameworks in the backend while
DevOps can actually manage deployment.
And then the third part of
the system, which is K which
enables serverless AI deployment.
Again, what does this truly mean?
So in the example of our orchestra,
although the conductor is the person
who is responsible of making sure
everything works as expected, you
also need a stage manager, right?
What does a stage manager do?
A stage manager is looking at
how the audience is reacting.
Are people leaving?
Do we need the lights to be on or off?
Do we need to make sure that.
A certain musician needs to
go on or go off the stage.
Certain aspects and just ability
to scale based on behavior patterns
is what a stage manager does.
So in this case, K native is that
kind of a stage manager, right?
So it enables automation, deployment,
and even scaling of these workflows
in a very dynamic manner without.
Interaction from a human person, right?
So in a e-commerce kind of environment
or a digital marketplace setup, what this
means is, say on a Black Friday or a Cyber
Monday, you need to make sure all systems
are up and running and able to scale up.
And this needs to be really agile, but
at the same time, on certain days where
there is really less customer interaction.
It should also be able to scale down
and basically be very efficient at it.
So this is where K comes in handy.
K actually integrates pretty
seamlessly with Kafka and it can
trigger model inference functions.
Only even specific behavior events occur.
So this truly makes the
churn prevention system.
Very robust.
Alright, so before we go to the next
slide, I just wanted to summarize
the few things that we talked about.
We looked at Kafka, cube flow, and
K. So again, Kafka is the system
that enables collecting signals.
It could be across different
data sources, clicks, payments,
logins, transaction data.
Kafka Streams, which integrates
with Kafka, helps process patterns,
cleans and aggregates the data.
Cube flow is what enables us
running the AI models LSTM, RNs
ensemble models, and these are run
using cube flow and Kubernetes.
And then finally, K native
enable serverless deployment.
Ability to interact with CRM systems
and make sure that the whole system
works in a very automated manner.
Okay, so let's talk about what
this means in terms of production
infrastructure requirements.
I would say there's three aspects that are
essential having unified data platform.
So this is something that should
enable both batch processing as
well as real-time processing.
And so we need a good unified
customer data platform.
Second is having an API for CR CRM
integration, so restful and GraphQL.
They actually enable real time
synchronization and ensure that
these intervention workflows
have complete customer context.
And then the third thing is
having scalable compute pipelines.
So this helps containers have automatic
resource allocation and scale up or down
as the workload requirements change.
So all these three, I would say essential
elements to make sure we're able to
make this a production ready system.
All right.
So putting this into what it means in
terms of model performance and monitoring.
Although the system should work in
an automated manner, once it's set
up, we need to ensure that we are
able to monitor for model accuracy,
prediction, latency, and even data drift.
The advantages that Kubernetes native
tools like Prometheus and Grafana.
Actually provide these insights upfront.
And to maintain reliability.
We also need to make sure that any
kind of updates that happen need to
be done in a safe and accurate manner.
Again what Kubernetes allows us to
do is to make sure that we're able
to validate any new model versions
against production traffic without
impacting customer experience.
And that's truly where
it sets itself apart.
All right, so bring it all together.
Let's talk about what this means and then
in terms of an implementation roadmap.
So there's four steps to implement the
system in a production environment.
First is the foundation setup, which
is making sure that we are deploying
the Kubernetes clusters with tube
flow, establishing data, pipeline
architecture, and having basic event
streaming with Kafka to make sure that
real time data is getting into the system.
The second aspect, which is basically
having the machine learning model
constructed or created all the system
would eventually run with these models
and automate and update as they go along.
The initial aspect of developing and
training these models using historical
data, implementing feature engineering
pipelines and establishing model
validation frameworks are aspects that
essential in the model development stage.
Once the model is developed, the
production deployment is done
using can, as I mentioned, this is.
Serverless is allows for scalability
and automation of these workflows.
It also helps integrate with CRM systems.
It implements monitoring and
editing for production workflows.
And finally, over a longer term, I
would say optimization and scaling is
an essential component of the system.
So implementing a b testing for
model improvements, enhancing
real-time processing capabilities
and scaling infrastructure
based on production testing.
Are very critical aspects to make
sure this system continues to operate
as expected over the longer term.
Alright, let's talk about model
fairness and transparency.
A truly an efficient system
must also be an ethical one.
So bias detection and ability
to make sure that we are able to
mitigate it is an important aspect.
So we need to regularly audit predictions
across different customer segments
to make sure that there's equitable
treatment and no discriminatory outcomes.
What could this mean?
Say there are certain customers who
don't necessarily log in very frequently.
We don't want to.
Exclude these customers just because
of certain behavioral patterns.
Wanna make sure that it is all
encompassing and able to address
certain aspects of behaviors.
Second, having an explainable
AI implementation, right?
Integrating tools like SHA and Lyme.
They basically provide interpretable
explanation for churn prediction.
Why?
Why this is critical is it
helps customer success teams to
understand if a customer is at risk.
How do they intervene effectively and
finally having good documentation.
So algorithms can run in the backend,
but we need to make sure that there's
enough logging of model decisions and
intervention triggers, both for compliance
purposes as well as to make sure that we
can continuously improve the system and
our retention strategies as we go along.
All right.
Talking further on the aspects of
ethics in terms of user content and
privacy management retention systems
must adhere, I would say, to privacy
by design principles and comply
with regulations like GDPR and CCPA.
Retention is not just about
keeping customers, it's about
actually keeping their trust.
So the ML models need to be flexible
enough to adapt future feature
selection based on individual
customer consent preferences.
This is where, again, Kubernetes
really shines because it can automate
compliance workflows like consent
verification, data retention policies
as part of the ML pipeline in Cube flow.
So what does this all mean
when we talk about the future?
Before we talk about next steps,
I just wanted to recap what we
talked about and give the roadmap
of how this all would come together.
I would say there's four steps to
building the system having the foundation
set up using Kubernetes Kafka and Cube
flow training and deploying our models.
This could be R ns, l sst m. Ensemble
models using again on cube flow and then
production deployment using K native,
making sure there's CRM integration there.
And then optimizing and scaling these
models using AB testing and monitoring
over the longer period of time.
So in summary, I would say intelligent
retention engines are a convergence
of advanced machine learning
techniques or algorithms, cloud native
infrastructure and real time data.
And then by leveraging this
Kubernetes native AI architecture
that I just proposed.
I believe organizations can actually
build systems that are not just
predictive, but truly intelligent.
They are scalable, ethical, and
also responsive, so they're able to
detect churn signals much earlier
before they become irreversible.
So what I just reviewed is essentially
a blueprint for building a super
smart, productive customer service
engine that can run on cloud.
Its main job is to make sure that
customers stop churning or don't leave
before we even know that they're unhappy.
And this can truly help transform
customer tention strateg.
Using Cloud native ai.
So again, thank you so much for your time.
I hope you found this helpful.
It's been a pleasure talking to you all.
If one of you wants to connect with me,
feel free to reach out on LinkedIn, my
at LinkedIn dot coms slash in slash ker.
Or I'd be happy to connect to
discuss further anything at all.
Thanks again and have a great day.