My name is Yuri Besonov, and I'm a
Partner Solution Architect at AWS.
I work with different AWS
customers and partners and help
them to build solutions on AWS.
One of the areas where I'm involved more
is containers, especially Kubernetes.
Kubernetes on AWS is delivered
by Amazon Elastic Kubernetes
Service, in short, Amazon EKS.
And today, I will share with you how
we can build and scale production
grade Kubernetes multi cluster
environment using GitOps on EKS.
But before we go multi clusters,
let's start from the very beginning,
from one cluster and define why do
we need cluster management at all.
We generally see customers with a
Git source control system, some kind
of infrastructure as a code tooling
like Terraform, CloudFormation,
CDK, Pulumi, some infrastructure
as a code state like S3 bucket
for Terraform, and then resources.
And EKS cluster.
In the pipeline, customers usually do
some checks on the source code, they
build an application, then run unit tests,
enforce policies, and after that they
need to deploy application in the cluster.
And as they grow, they may add
additional environments, like for
development, staging, for test
purposes, or for different projects.
It is still manageable.
If growth continues, this
can become unmanageable.
To many versions, to many clusters,
to many pipelines to track, which
cluster is up to date, which cluster
has which version, which needs to be
updated this quarter or next quarter.
And this is even without taking into
account what is inside the clusters.
What are the applications,
what are their update policies.
And it is uncommon, not uncommon,
It's not uncommon to see so many
pipelines in an organization.
Why do we have so many clusters?
Because we have different light
of businesses, we have different
applications, and different workloads.
We could have back end application
system, web application for front
end, or even state workloads.
Workloads to host databases
or streaming workloads.
There are plenty of legacy applications
which are running in the clusters and
also up to date modern applications
like artificial intelligence,
machine learning to work with machine
learning and training and inference.
And besides deploying the clusters, we
also need to think how teams will access
those clusters and will share resources.
How we will configure each clusters
with add ons, maybe with different
configuration for developing and prod.
For example, different number of
replicas in developing and prodding
environment, and also how to deploy teams.
different workloads to different clusters.
So there are plenty of challenges
when you need to work with containers,
with EKS, with Kubernetes at scale.
And of course, our pipeline could
help us to manage the add on,
deploy the infrastructure, and
enforce our compliance and security.
It is possible with pipeline, and in this
case, the actual model will be push model.
We trigger the deployment manually each
time when we decide that we need to
deploy a new version of an application.
But what happens in case of
some issues in the chain?
Or what will be the state of truth?
If there are some problems arise, do we
consider git as an initial state of truth?
Do we consider terraform state
file as a state of truth?
Or do we consider pipeline
itself as a state of truth?
Or maybe it's EKS etcd
database is a state of truth?
With this setup, environment cannot
match what your intention was.
It is not source of truth anymore, and
it's more, I would say, source of hope.
And with this architecture, you need a
lot of auditing and compliance mechanism.
And what about if we need
to integrate new services?
In this case, we need to, for example,
we would like to use generative
AI services like Amazon Bedrock.
In this case, we need product manager
for pipelines who need to integrate this.
And if we have many business units
that they can be overwhelmed and maybe
new services, will never be deployed.
If we rely on GitHub tooling for fleet
management, we can have a process that
will constantly try to reconcile the
source of truth in the Git repository
with the actual state of the cluster.
So we can, and we should solve those
problems which we had with the push model.
In this case, Git becomes a source
of truth instead of source of hoax.
Hope, and it will enable reproducible
automated deployments, cluster
management, and monitoring.
So we can use GitOps and various tooling
to solve our problems with deployment.
And we also use a principle
of GitOps to achieve it.
Those principles are declarative.
We define what do we want to achieve,
not how do we want to achieve.
It's reduce complexity.
The second principle is versions.
All the configuration are in
Git, versionable and immutable,
and it enhance auditability.
We know who did what and when.
We also use pull model, whereas an agent
in the cluster which pull desired state
from the git instead of pushing this
state to the cluster from the pipeline.
And also, we have an agent which is
continuously reconciles it to the cluster.
Agents know how to translate declarative
configuration in the git repository
to the real state of the cluster.
And do it constantly so after each change
we always have the consistent environment.
And let's now go deeper and
talk how we deploy the clusters.
Most of the customers are using
many of the customers using
Terraform to deploy EKS clusters.
We have a nice accelerator called EKS
Blueprints that can help you to achieve
your deployment goals quickly by allowing
you to rely on maintaining and best
practices pattern of EKS deployment.
It can bring you some patterns
like fully private cluster.
Clusters which use APV6 with
Node Group or Carpenter for
analytics or machine learning.
For various purposes, we have various
patterns already developed for you, which
you can use in your own environment.
Let's see the process to deploy
an add on, like a load balancer.
Because the cluster itself,
it's just compute environment.
And in order to use it, you need various
components, like a various add on.
For AWS load balancer, for example in
order to make it work, we will need a
role and a policy which gives a controller
to possibility to access application AWS
resources, such as AWS load balancer.
The role will reference a pro
policy with appropriate right.
If we decide to addon to install the
addon Helm chart with Terraform, we can
configure it with previously created role.
Then Terraform installs the
configured Helm chart into the
cluster, and the service account
can reference the proper AM role.
Then it's again push model from Terraform.
We still hit the problem of of which
Terraform state is a state of truth.
And Terraform apply, it's only
applied when we manually when
we'll be manually triggered.
Can we do better?
Of course, we can do.
Can we use, for example,
Git approach and Argo CD?
We can ask Argo CD to talk to Kubernetes
and do the Helm install on the addons
via creation of application object
that reference the Helm chart repo.
But then, we still need a way to provide
it with appropriate configuration.
In this case, the AM role
for load balancer controller.
With Argo CD we there is a
notion of application set.
Application set allow us to
dynamically create or generate
Argo CD application objects.
Application set are able to read a secret
in the cluster and apply its configuration
to some of the labels of the secret.
But first, we need a way for our Teraform
to create the secrets and then the
specific annotation for that secret.
In this case, Teraform creates a load
balancer controller IAM role, reference
this role as annotation in the secret
and create the secret in Kubernetes.
This way, Argo CD should have
all the necessary materials
to create an application and
install properly the add on.
Once Kubernetes has the secret configured,
Argo CD can create an application for its
application set manifest with appropriate
configuration and install the add on.
So we have complete cycle.
To recap, Terraform creates a role.
Terraform creates the Kubernetes secrets
with appropriate annotation for this role.
Then Argo CD creates the
application from application set.
This is what we call the GitHub bridge.
It is fully integrated with EKS blueprints
and you can rely on this pattern to
keep your Terraform infrastructure as
to keep your Terraform infrastructure
as code management but shift the
Kubernetes deployment part to Argo CD.
So in this case, Terraform will be
responsible for creation of the clusters
and creation of the secrets, but
after that Argo CD will take over and
deploy all the workload and all the
necessary add on using application set.
This can be used for add ons, but
also for workloads when your workloads
can be configured dynamically from
the metadata created by Terraform.
From there, we have different options for
managing Argo CD, our clusters and GitHub
repository for add ons and workload.
We can have a different cluster pointing
to the same Git add ons repository, where
we will store the generic application set.
Each application set can then
be transformed by Argo CD
in different applications.
which can have different values depending
on the target cluster we are running on.
So you have a set of application sets
which are acting like a template and
after that you could have specific
parameters for specific clusters
which can be generated on the fly.
We can also use, in this case, centralized
Argo CD instance in a hub cluster that
will be managed that that will be able to
manage application deployment in different
target cluster from a centralized place.
This is what we call
a hub and spoke model.
When you have a hub management cluster
and you have workloads cluster for
different environment to different
projects to let's say which will be
controlled by one instance of Argo CD.
We can leverage Terraform to create
our hub and spoke clusters with
a simple hub and spoke topology.
We can also leverage Terraform workspaces
to manage a different Terraform
configuration for our different cluster
but reusing the same Terraform code.
With this setup, we need many
secrets created in the hub cluster.
One secret for each of that.
Target cluster, like a hub cluster dev
clusters staging, or production clusters.
Argo CD will be able to leverage
those different secrets when we need
to communicate with each cluster.
So Argo CD will help necessary, will have
necessary credentials to access workloads
cluster from the centralized hub cluster.
Application sets stored in
Git will generate different
applications in the HUB cluster.
We can also specify different add ons
versions and other configurations by
matching labels on the target clusters.
Within the single repository,
you can still control different
versions of the HUB cluster.
to be deployed on different cluster
and centralized in one location.
So you have a benefits of centralization
of configuration, but after that
flexibility to have different different
parameters, different specific
parameters for various clusters.
Clusters, then you can scale
this with many other clusters.
So you can have several clusters
for staging or for example, complete
set of clusters like dev staging
and production for various project
or various lines of business.
As I said, many of our customers are
using Terraform and e Ks blueprints for
Terraform to create their infrastructure.
While Terraform is really powerful
tool for Token to AWS, we have
seen several issues when letting
Terraform manage Kubernetes resources
inside the clusters, like a Don
and workloads and what we just saw.
We can delegate some of the Kubernetes
stuff from Terraform to Argo CD using.
GitOps bridge.
Terraform will still create resources,
AWS resources, and Kubernetes secrets
with with metadata indentation.
From there, Argo CD is able to
configure and install the Kubernetes
add on, like external DDS, GitTip, or
SearchSecret to one or many clusters.
With the GitOps approach, we
could also manage the teams.
We can create with ArgoCD namespaces.
We could enforce role basis access
control and policies and everything
using GitOps and using configuration,
which is stored in ArgoCD.
Some customers are even
able to do one step faster.
further, for example, and let Argo
CD sends to tooling like ACK or cross
plane to also create necessary AWS
resources from VPC to EKS clusters.
In this case, we don't talk about
Kubernetes as container orchestration
system, but as a platform framework.
We are building a fabric for
people To bring different pieces of
infrastructure together using native
constructs like mutating admissions,
Hema validation admissions, and all
those benefits of Kubernetes API.
With that, with the help of GitOps,
Kubernetes API, we could be able
to deploy not only workloads to the
clusters, but also the clusters and
all the necessary resources which you
require in AWS, for example, for your
application to run, like SRE buckets,
databases, and so on and so forth.
Of course In these clusters,
we will need some workloads.
For that workloads, we will need
configuration management for
different applications, for different
versions of those applications.
We also can use one Git
repository to store configuration
for different applications.
Like in this case, for example, as you
can see, you have some UI application,
you have some database application.
And if needed, you can also
differentiate the configuration needed
for different clusters or environment
of clusters in the Git repository.
So you may have different values
for your development clusters and
and for example, for production
clusters, of course, you will have
different, for example, parameters
for secrets or access to the database.
But also you could have a various
number of replicas or other
parameters, which will be different
from environment to environment.
RGCD could reconcile the
appropriate directories.
The directory is dependent on
the target clusters, so you could
have a configuration of specific
cluster in specific directory.
With this, you can create different
configurations like version, scale, and
optimize cost for compute and storage.
As we we saw, you may also choose
to create additional resources with
GitOps using manifest and add ons
for AWS controllers for Kubernetes
or cross plane, for example,
to create Amazon RDS databases
associated with specific application.
So you could have a configuration
for application, but also for
resources which are necessary for
this application in AWS cloud.
And of course, any talk.
cannot be complete without
some mentioning of security.
Security is top priority for AWS and
clusters are not exceptions from it.
You, or you would want to store
the secret materials for your
application, for example, a private
SSH key, keys or secrets in secure
location like AWS Secret Manager.
Then the controller like external
secrets operator would create and
update the secret bases on the
material from AWS Secret Manager.
When external secret operator creates the
Kubernetes secrets with git credentials.
Or and URL hostname, it can be also
validated by Kiverna, by policy agent.
Kiverna can have a policy that only
allows credentials for Argo CD to be
type, for example, type of SSH only.
And it also could check if those
credentials are coming only from
specific Git repository or Git
server or from specific region.
It could be could be quite secure.
And Argo CD, of course, with Argo CD
another let's say tip you should never
access remote EKS clusters using service
account tokens that never expire.
You should never use those tokens.
Argo CD controllers like application
controller, API server, or report server
should always be configured to use IAM
role using IRCA or EKS pod identity.
When adding another remote
cluster, specify the IAM role
that Argo CD should assume when
connecting to the more cluster.
This also could be stored
in the Kubernetes secret.
A Kibernet policy can be configured
to ensure that your cluster secret
created only contains IAM role to
assume and never, uh, KubeConfig token.
Of course, you can replicate this,
the same approach with many clusters
and use it to access not only for
example, staging clusters, but also
production clusters and any other
required clusters in a secured way.
To sum up, AKS blueprints.
and GitOps bridge give you a possibility
to create and manage multi cluster
environments with security and
at scale using GitOps principles.
You can check those QR codes and the links
if you want to dive deeper, get additional
information, or even you can try.
hands on in your own on AWS account
the Argo CD on EKS workshops,
which we prepared for you.
With that, I would like to say thank you.
I hope you enjoyed the session
and please feel free to reach out
on LinkedIn and have a discussion
about platform engineering,
containers application modernization.
I would really appreciate that.
Also, if you spend one minute and
answer on a short survey on the
session, your feedback is very valuable.
Thank you.