Good morning.
Good afternoon, everybody.
My name is jd. I'm here to talk about
one of the significant transformation
happening in the financial industry.
Let's get into the presentation.
My screen is visible scaling
AI driven financial services.
So simplifying.
We are, we will be deep diving how we
use a technology like Kubernetes to
build and manage the powerful systems,
those arely driven and at massive scale.
The core challenge we are facing is not
just making AI work, but making it work
responsibly for everyone everywhere.
So we are in the midst
of financial revelation.
The world, the financial world
is changing at the speed.
And AI is the engine.
It's a driving factor.
This transformation it's
creating an incredible new
opportunities for first time.
We have tools accurately assist
the risk and provide the services
to unbanked population that
has not been historically and.
Under the governance or was
excluded from the financial system.
And the biggest example we have seen
back in India in 2014 when Han accounts
were being opened at the scale.
But this power brings complexity, right?
How to scale the fraud detection
systems handle millions of
transactions every minute.
How to ensure the credit scoring
models are fair across dozens of
countries and cultures, right?
This is where the cloud
native services comes in.
They provide the architecture foundation
we need to build the AI systems on
that are not only powerful, but are
scalable and responsible and ethical.
Today's journey.
When we look at it like first, if we
look at the first challenge that we could
define here in the roadmap is scaling,
of course and scaling the AI solutions.
The second we will explore here
the container solutions like
Kubernetes orchestration patterns,
and that forms the backbone of.
The model system.
And third, we will focus on ethical
integration, discussing how we
embed the governance into our
technology, workflow, et cetera.
And finally, it comes to putting this all
together in the real world implementation
and see how this concepts bring together
the best practices at the scale.
Let's skip cracking.
So the core challenge as
we discussed is scaling.
The financial market
is incredible dynamic.
All AI system must scale instantly
to handle sudden market volatility
or transaction spikes during
the peak hours while maintaining
the response times measurably
in microseconds or milliseconds.
That's a big challenge.
The traditional monolithic system
simply cannot scale or keep on.
Imagine a single, massive application
that is trying to handle fraud
detection at a global sales like
Thanksgiving or Black Friday, right?
And while simultaneously running
the credit algorithms for millions
of users, it becomes a bottleneck.
Elasticity just isn't there, right?
So what's the solution for that?
The solution to this problem is scaling
scaling, using content orchestration.
With Kubernetes as a leading platform,
it's built on key principle First
is microservice architecture.
We here we break down the massive
monolithic systems into a smaller,
independent, scalable services.
Think of it like a giant entangled
ball of yarn and set for netting
instead of that, an individual
falls, which can do better, right?
Second is dynamic scaling
Kubernetes can automatically add
or remove resources in real time.
It's like a horizontal scaling,
upscaling and downscaling
possible at the peak hours.
Imagine at the start of trading session
in NASDAQ or New York market opens,
it's sudden spike in the market required
massive resources, but then eventually
it goes down and we need to have a system
that withstands all those load and.
Dynamically scales itself and that
all is possible using Kubernetes.
And the third is multi-region
deployment which allows us to distribute
our services across the global.
It's critical because of globalization.
And it is critical for performance,
resilience and meeting the regional
compliance policies, which we will
be deep diving in, in, in a while.
Serving the unbanked.
Now let's connect the technology that
we just discussed back to people, right?
This scalable cloud native is
what makes it possible to serve
previously unreached population.
We can build mobile first credit
scoring models for emerging markets.
We can process alternate data like
mobile phone, using utility and payments
or user patterns, et cetera, to create
a financial profile for those who
traditionally don't have a credit history.
And we can use containerized, NLP and
natural language processing models to
offer support for dozens of languages and
making it more reachable to the people.
You of a different culture, different
language background, et cetera.
This is a financial inclusion in action,
a power of smart architecture, and
this is exactly what we need, right?
Ethical challenges.
If we look at it like as our
AI system expands, any small
underlying bias in our model gets
amplified across millions of users.
Think of it, a model that
unfairly penalize a certain
demography in one city, could now.
Do it across the entire continent,
countries and this distributed
environment, environments,
ethical government stops being
just a design consideration.
It becomes critical.
It's like now you need it.
You must have it like and think, right?
Infrastructure concerns should be
managed consistently and constantly.
So let's look into that,
how we embed our ethics.
So how do we build the governance
into our infrastructure?
We can use cloud native principles.
What is that like?
First is policy as a code, we embed our
ethical rules and fairness guidelines
directly into our deployment PowerPoints.
This means the more that model
doesn't meet, our fairness criteria
can be automatically blocked.
Even before reaching the production,
second is automated mon monitoring.
We build continuous bias detection,
fairness, checks directly
into our monitoring checks.
It is like having a smoke detector,
which is always on for biases, right?
And third is audit trails.
It's very vital to have an
immutable unchangeable logs that
can be for every model decision.
Governance action taken.
And this provides a very high level
of transparency and even meets the
regulatory requirements, which are
critical in banking or financial industry
technical implementation.
Plat, and let's get bit
more technical here.
These governance principles are
implemented through specific patterns in.
Model lifecycle management.
We use CICD pipelines to manage our
models from deployment to production, from
staging to productions and transition.
This includes GitHubs Jenkins, like
pipelines to clear versioning of a
model to have clear versioning running
automatic fairness test before they.
Testing staging environment
before the reach to production.
And we use cannery deployment to roll new
models to small subset of the users to
monitor the bias, fairness, and limit the
back to limited people, and then fully
release it into the production, right?
This is tried into observability.
We tie this all steps into what is
called as continuous monitoring, right?
And observability.
We don't just track CPU
and memory utilization.
That's a traditional way of doing things.
But we build the custom metrics
that can track the model fairness
and and in real time, and.
We can use distributor tracking to
understand the entire path of decision
making as well, and set up an automated
alert if the biasness metrics crosses
certain predefined thresholds.
So
multi judiciary compliance as in a
financial, global, financial world, right?
You have to deal with the complex
web of international laws.
Kubernetes provides a tool to manage
this for region data re residency.
It's one of the very critical, or
very much a strict law of land, right?
We can use the rule to ensure that
the data for specific countries
stays within the specific countries.
Like for example, Germany, Zurich
they want their data to store
geographically on the same servers.
Residing on their own land as very
much possible for regulatory reduction.
We can configure our Kubernetes
services that are for regional
laws and policies without having to
rebuild the entire stuff from scratch.
That's a massive leap actually.
And.
Cross border coordination.
Now having a global system, financial
organizations do need some coordination
in what do you say, cooperations or
collaboration between two regions.
And this technology like service
mesh can manage secure communication
between different regions and we can
achieve the coordination of cross
border while abiding to all the
rules and regulations of the country.
Let's see.
Put together all of this and see
the real world case study, a global
financial fraud detection system.
The challenge is massive processing,
say a hundred million transactions a day
across more than 30 countries with with
with response times, which is under.
A hundred milliseconds, all while
ensuring that the models are
fair and not being flagged for
certain user groups of Biasness.
That's a massive challenge.
The solution architecture is exactly
what we have been discussing.
Kuber clusters are deployed
in each major region.
The real time model serves the
Easter service like mesh to
have a secure communication
between two different regions.
The the model monitoring systems like
Prometheus or Grapha or AppDynamics
can handle the biasness and track
the model's, fairness and other
customer metrics in real time.
Finally a ops workflow or Jenkins
workflows that automates the
deployment with built-in Gates
to check ethical validations.
Before the new models are being live
performance resilience, of course,
in the financial organizations,
the system must be rock solid.
This architecture provides high
availability through multiple zones,
deployments, ensuring near perfect uptime.
It delivers elastic scaling.
We have discussed that for handling
transactional spikes or without
overspending on infrastructure.
And it has security integrated built
in every layer from network policies
to the port security standards to
protect the institute financial
information or financial data,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
These are all critical factors that
needs to be considered in performance
and re part of your architecture
key implementation strategy.
If you remember just three
things from today, right?
Let's let them be like three
keys or three strategies, right?
Start with governance now.
Don't treat ethics as an afterthought,
as we already discussed, how
badly it can impact, right?
Build your fairness frameworks before you
scale because the problem can replicate to
global population and it can become a very
massive, big problem and amplify itself.
Monitor continuously.
That's the second key, right?
Deploy comprehensive observability for
both technical parameters, fairness, and
all of the custom parameters that you find
in must have for the entire framework.
Automate everything.
Think of it as.
As using GitHubs or Jenkins and
policy as a code is enforcing
governance and consistency across
each and every environment.
It becomes more reproducible
and replicable also.
All of these things will just bring
a lot of efficiency when you want to
deploy these things or this architecture
in different geographical region.
Think about it.
Without automation, it's highly
impossible to achieve all the leaf
that we discussed in a given time.
What's the path forward, right?
So the cloud native technologies like
Banes are no longer just about efficiency.
They are essential infrastructure
for scaling, AI driven
financial services responsible.
By integrating ethical governance
directly into our technical workflows
we can finally build systems that
serves global population while
maintaining the transparency, fairness
that the future of finance demands.
And we have seen them in detail, right?
To leave you with one thought, right?
The future of financial inclusion depends
upon the ability of scale AI systems.
There are both technically
robust and equally sound.
With this, I would like to
thank you all for attending
and giving your valuable time.
I am happy to answer all your questions.
You can contact me with my email on
the screen or with my LinkedIn account.
Thank you.