Hello everyone.
Welcome you all to this session,
generative AI Transforming
Healthcare Claims Processing.
I'm Amala Ala Oma.
I work as a junior principal data
engineer at a management consulting firm.
I partner with our clients in leading data
architecture and digital transformations
by building scalable and robust data
pipelines at an enterprise scale.
It's a pleasure to be here
at Con 42 Q, native 2025.
Today I'll be sharing my views on how
gene AI is transforming healthcare
claims processing space, especially
in speeding up operations, improving
accuracy and detecting frauds in ways
traditional systems simply cannot.
Let's dive into the challenge first.
The healthcare claims
ecosystem is massive.
Tens of millions of claims are
submitted, reviewed, and processed.
Every single day across several payers,
providers, and insurance companies.
Unfortunately, the system is so
fragmented, slow, and highly error
prone due to the fact that how these
systems are built and managed claims
essentially move through multiple layers
of processing, like eligibility, coding,
validation, adjudication, and audits.
Each step introduces potential
for errors or delays.
According to recent studies, nearly
15% of claims are either denied or
delayed because of various reasons like
incorrect data, missing documentation, or
inconsistent codes, and then this fraud
ranging from upcoding to phantom billing
to collusive networks of providers.
These issues cost the healthcare industry
over a hundred billion dollars annually.
Traditional rule-based systems
cannot adapt fast enough to
detect evolving patterns.
That's where gene AI comes into picture.
Gene, I introduces a paradigm
shift almost in every industry.
The healthcare industry is no exception.
Unlike fixed rule automation, gene, I
systems learn from vast and diverse,
unstructured and semi-structured data.
Like claims text, EHR, records,
image, billing nodes, et cetera.
It also generates context
aware and explainable insights.
Let's break it down to see what makes
it transformative in top three aspects.
Number one, the speed AI agents can
process and validate claims in seconds
nowadays, it streamlines the most time
consuming manual process like data entry,
verification, and prior authorization.
This reduces the administrative
burden on providers and expedites
the payments in one case.
Generic model, increased
automated claim processing by 30%,
resulting in faster approvals.
Number two, accuracy.
General leverages natural language
processing and contextual understanding to
reduce coding errors and mismatch entries.
This ensures coding, accuracy and
completeness before a claim is submitted.
This minimizes human error
resulting in higher first pass
claim rate and fewer denials.
And third, the proactive fraud detection.
AI analyzes large data sets.
To correctly identify the subtle and
suspicious billing patterns or anomalies
in the data that even humans or rule
engines often miss in traditional road
based systems By flagging questionable
claims in real time, genea helps
insurers prevent financial losses
and strengthen system integrity.
So instead of humans chasing anomalies,
the AI continuously watches and
learns, making it a dynamic and
innovative and regulated system.
Let's look at the five
layer architecture here.
Each layer contributes to speed,
accuracy, and explainability.
Before we dive any deeper, here's a high
level of these three, these five layers.
The first layer is the data
ingestion and pre-processing.
In this layer, the workflow cleans
and normalizes the fragmented inputs.
The second layer is the intelligent
semantic under understanding.
This is the core layer.
Here.
The gene AI interprets the data
using natural language processing
to build accurate claim context.
Third layer is the decision engine.
Here, the workflow automates
the adjudication recommendations
and flag any outliers.
The fourth layer is the
validation and explainability.
This layer ensures transparency,
auditability, and trust, enabling
comprehensive compliance.
And the final layer is the
integration and analytics.
This layer connects the pipeline to
enterprise systems and dashboards
to deliver real time impact.
Let's look at each layer
a little more deeply.
The biggest barrier we know in any data
pipeline is the data fragmentation.
Claims come in several formats,
like PDFs and hhl, seven
messages or even DICOM images.
Gene consumes data in all of these formats
and converts them into structured data
for downstream processing the ingestion
pipeline performs data cleaning,
deduplication, and enrichment as part
of the data, pre-processing steps.
Think of it as laying a solid
foundation without clean, unified data.
No AI model can deliver
real reliable outcomes.
Once we have clean data, the next
challenge is understanding what
the data actually means, and that's
where the NLP comes into picture.
Many of us have seen or heard medical
data, and it's not a simple text.
It's full of medical codes, aberrations
context, and clinical nuances.
The second layer leverages natural
language processing to extract meaning
from these codes and aberrations.
JI reads, physician notes, discharge
summaries, and claim narratives.
Then it identifies entities like
diagnosis codes, procedures, and
medications, and it does not stop there.
It goes on building the
contextual understanding.
For example, it can distinguish
between a follow-up visit for diabetes.
Versus a new diagnosis for diabetes.
There is a subtle difference that
affect the billing accuracy in these two
scenarios, and the result is a claim that
is enriched with semantic intelligence
ready for automated decisioning.
Next is the third layer that
is validation and enrichment.
Here JI validates claims against
coding standards like ICD 10 CPT,
and Ed ct it crosschecks medical
necessity provide credentials
and historical patient patterns.
The enrichment process then adds
auxiliary data, like clinical references,
lab results, or previous medical
encounters, thus creating a 360 degree
view of each and every single claim.
The goal here is not to just reject
back claims, but to improve the
equality before shop submission.
And the fourth layer is
a decision intelligence.
This layer handles what's known
as AI driven adjudication.
Let's see how this happens.
Once the claim is validated, the
decision engine determines whether to
approve, deny, or flag it for review.
It uses reinforcement learning to
get better with each iteration,
meaning the system improves
continuously from expert feedback.
We also use precision exception
handling, which means identifying
those edge cases that cannot be
decided or acted upon confidently
and routing them to human reviewers.
This brings human in the loop
along with the AI workflows.
The hybrid approach of AI with human in
the loop ensures both speed and trust.
This brings to the final
layer orchestration.
In this layer, the entire
ecosystem is tied together.
Consider this as a control plane that
coordinates the various AI models.
External data sources and business
rules required to automate and
expedite the claims adjudication.
It manages the APIs, the performance
metrics, and integrations with enterprise
workflows, whether that's paper payer
systems, or EHRs or analytic dashboards.
The orchestrator incorporates
quality control measures.
It can flag claims with high
risk factors for human review.
Compare AI generated summaries against
source documents for accuracy, and even
create a feedback loop to continuously
improve the model's performance.
It provides continuous monitoring,
auditing, and traceability, which are
the key requirements for regulated
environments like healthcare.
Now let's talk about the real
differentiator, the fraud detection,
how fraudulent claims are captured
in the traditional systems.
The answer to this question depends
on the codified static business rules
that captures thresholds like flag if
the amount is greater than X dollars or
duplicate claim within 30 days, et cetera.
However, fraud evolves so quickly,
often this slightly changing patterns.
To bypass those rules, genea
brings multimodal analysis.
This means it combines a structured
data, claim, narratives, and behavioral
signals simultaneously in order to detect
the suspicious activity proactively.
By integrating these different data types,
the system gains a more comprehensive
understanding than any single source
could provide, leading to more accurate
and efficient claims adjudication.
It can identify sophisticated fraud
patterns even before human auditors.
Notice them and send the notification
to the right person to act on it.
For example, the most complex and hard
to detect patterns are often worried in
unstructured data, like clinical notes,
doctors letters, and claim description.
NLP could actually reveal a hidden
pattern in these unstructured data,
like when the description of a
patient in the insurance claim uses
inconsistent language, conflicting with
the factual medical records or hidden
linguistic cues such as repeated use
of qualifying statements, et cetera.
The emerging fraud schemes,
frauds and fraudsters have
evolved well over the years.
In our study, we identified three major
classes of these evolving fraud schemes.
Number one, the pattern evolution.
Fraudsters modify known scams
just enough to slip through rules.
Example, scammers now use gene AI to
create falsified medical records, such
as altered MRI scans, x-rays, or clinical
nodes to support your fraudulent claims.
This makes detecting fraud much
more challenging as the supporting
documentation appears so legitimate.
Using realtime monitoring the JI
workflows claims as they're submitted,
allowing for immediate intervention
before fraudulent payments are dispersed.
Next is the collusive networks.
This means the providers and patients
coordinate claims across institutions.
In this case, we use network
intelligence where this technology maps
relationship between the providers.
Patients and clinics to
identify collusive fraud rings.
It can detect patterns like multiple
providers sharing the same address or
referring patients in circular patterns.
And third one is a behavioral anomalies.
Tiny shifts in billing or diagnostic
frequency that reveals the abuse of fraud.
We use behavioral analytics to
capture these types of fraud schemes.
Example, a machine learning model.
Identify anomalies in billing patterns.
By establishing a baseline of normal
behavior for each provider, any
significant deviation from that baseline
such as a certain spike in claims
for a specific high cost procedure
can be flagged for investigation.
JI continuously monitors for these
signals using unsupervised learning
clustering and pattern evolution analysis.
Another innovative capability is
synthetic fraud scenario generation.
It involves creating a fake identity
to submit a claim for reimbursement.
The synthetic identity is typically
created by combining a stolen
social security number with
fabricated personal details, making
it difficult for the automated
systems to even detect the fraud.
Using generative modeling, we can
simulate fraudulent claims to stress
test the detection pipeline to
protect against these future threats.
This approach helps the system to
learn from possible future fraud
events, even before attackers,
thereby improving resilience,
adaptability, and system integrity.
Let's look at the challenges
in implementing the AI
at the enterprise scale.
Nowadays, AI has become a
part of life for many of us.
Building a prototype using
AI is quick and easy.
However, building a sophisticated AI
system to work for us at an enterprise
scale doesn't come in a most magical way.
Implementing gene AI in
enterprise healthcare environments
comes with its own hurdles.
Number one, the fragmented data
silos stakeholders use multiple
legacy systems, which has complete
interoperability between the systems.
Making it hard for the data
to interact with each other.
That's breaking the data pipeline.
We have to overcome these
challenges case by cases.
For example, building a custom connector
to resolve the issue in this case.
Number two is a model explainability
healthcare decisions, demand
transparency, for example.
Everyone is interested in knowing
why a claim was denied as opposed
to if the claim was approved or
denied or flagged for review.
Number three is a cultural readiness.
We have made AI capable enough to
build complex workflows, and it's super
critical for our human teams to have
data and AI literacy to seamlessly
navigate the intelligent pipelines
built by these AI applications, and also
interpret the AI argumented outputs.
Overcoming these challenges mainly
requires strong data governance,
standard interfaces, and human oversight
built into these AI enabled workflows.
Compliance and privacy.
Compliance is not an afterthought in any
industry when it comes to healthcare.
It's even more essential and critical
than it has to be embedded by design.
When using gene ai, we need to ensure that
the AI outcomes has a following trait.
Number one, explainable ai.
Where every decision should
be traced and explained.
And number two is a federated learning.
Here models train across institutions
without sharing raw data,
thereby preserving the privacy.
And number three is the bias
mitigation, continuous monitoring
for demographic fairness, leaving no
room even for the unconscious bias.
And number four is a regulatory alignment.
Here full adherence to the industry
regulations like HIPAA for us, GDPR, for
Europe, and emerging AI ethics framework.
These principles will make the system
both responsible and trustworthy, thus
still holding the humans accountable.
Let's look at the future
of healthcare claims.
Gen AI is reshaping the healthcare
industry at a larger scale in terms of
intelligence, efficiency, and performance.
Looking ahead, we could leverage AI to
have increasingly massive positive impact
with the revolutionary processing speed.
The end-to-end claim cycles could be
reduced from weeks to hours and minutes,
and it also supports a substantial
cost reduction by automating cuts
manual review and re rework there
by reducing the cost significantly.
And finally, the unraveled fraud
detection self-learning models
that evolve with threats to handle
them effectively and securely.
To conclude, we are witnessing how
GNI enables s smarter, safer, and more
transparent healthcare payment ecosystem.
By improving trust between providers,
payers, and patients, all alike
organization must proactively address
the pressing challenges to ensure
safe and responsible deployment
of gene AI at an enterprise scale.
With that gene AI can revolutionize
healthcare claims, but combining data
intelligence, automation and fraud
analytics, all under one explainable
and compliant framework, that
brings us to our end of our session.
Thank you all for your time and interest
in listening to today's session.
I hope you got a better understanding
about the role of Genea and what
it holds in the future of claims
processing in the healthcare industry.
You all have a good day, have
a great learning, and cheers.