Hi, everyone.
First of all, thank you all for joining
the CONF42 Kube Native 2024 conference,
and a big thanks to Mark Pawlikowski for
hosting this event and accepting my talk.
My name is Aleksandra Drobnyak.
I work as a customer solutions engineer
at Sysdig, and in today's around 30 minute
session, I'm going to show you how you can
use open source Project Falco Sidekick to
detect threats in Kubernetes workloads.
I'll provide some initial context
using slides, after which we'll
jump into the lab environment.
A little bit about me.
I have a technical background in
telecommunications and I've been working
for 10 years in various engineering roles.
At the time when I completed my electrical
engineering master's degree, cloud
computing and container technology weren't
covered by any of the programs, and I
totally side quested into these fields.
as a hobby by following along content
creators such as Network Chuck and
doing the training on platforms
such as RangeForce and TryHackMe.
I'd say a major lesson here would
be to never stop learning, invest in
yourself, and find an ethical hobby with
a great return on investment potential.
From this slide, you can conclude
how I enjoy spending some of my time
and where you can find me online.
From making YouTube walkthroughs, blog
writing, participating in AWS Community
Builder and Cisco Insider Champion
Communities, and staying current
with cloud and Kubernetes security.
Right now, I'm going after
Success Coachings, Customer
Success Manager certification,
So it's never a dull moment.
And if any of these I've mentioned
so far sparked your interest,
connect with me on LinkedIn and
we can continue the conversation.
Speaking on ROI, cloud and
Kubernetes are currently known as
fields with great opportunities.
that connect you with the most
amazing people and pay well.
Cloud and Kubernetes go great hand in
hand, from creating highly available
and resilient services, working on
internal developer platforms, to
innovating with large language models.
You will frequently find that applications
served on public cloud are behind
the scenes, built using Kubernetes.
So in this day and age and economy, that's
something you can expect to see and hear.
Cloud and Kubernetes skills wanted
across software and security
engineering, sales and customer success.
Related to my badges from the
previous slide, here I highlighted
open job roles from these vendors,
including my employer Sysdig.
So this is something for motivation to
start looking into Kubernetes and cloud.
because the times are hybrid and
it's not very realistic to center
your technical skill set solely
around services that work on premise.
So let's say that any service that
has to be developed and offered to a
wide audience should be secured too.
In cloud security, there is this concept
of cloud native application protection
platforms, CNAP solutions capable of
securing infrastructure and applications.
Whether based on full blown virtual
machines or microservices, from the
moment of their local development,
while still being available only in
manifest files, to their runtime, where
you can actually access an application
serving a certain web page live.
Not all malicious actors will rely on
common vulnerabilities and exposures,
CVs for short, to cause damage and gain
unauthorized access to our offering.
Some might try to leverage
identities not being configured
according to the least privileged
practice and Compliance failures.
When we rely on reports as snapshots
in time to prove our offering's
adherence to industry's best
practices and relevant benchmarks.
And then, there could
be insider threats too.
Using a job relevant analogy,
it's like a candidate who looks
good on paper, interviews well,
and gets inside the company.
But has a malicious intent.
So this is where threat detection
is of utmost importance.
Speaking from my personal experience
working with Sysdig Secure CNAP, its
threat detection engine is based on
an open source Falco project capable
of detecting early indicators of an
attack in containerized environments,
such as using reconnaissance scripts,
or other malicious actions across
MITRE ATT& CK framework as obfuscation,
privilege escalation, log deletion,
downloading binaries to containers,
exfiltration attempts, shell history
deletion, bulk renaming and recreating
files extensions, and other actions
connected with ransomware campaigns.
A bit on Falco.
Falco is, as of this year, a CNCF
graduated project, meaning it's
considered stable and it's used
successfully in production environments.
Not going deep into
architecture weeds right now.
For this session, just know that Falco
hooks into the Linux kernel via a
driver, either a kernel module or an
eBPF probe, and can collect system calls.
All these events are parsed from
kernel space to user space where
Falco rules, which are essentially
filters of your interest, are applied.
And the final outputs can be
delivered to certain locations.
Falco can associate each kernel event
with the exact container attribute, like
container ID, name, image repository,
tags, as well as Kubernetes attributes.
Such as namespace or a pod name.
And on the right side, there is
an example of a microservice based
architecture leveraging Falco to
understand what is causing anomalies
within a Kubernetes cluster.
So when speaking innovation, container
runtime insights are important to consider
Because traditional security tooling
for event management wasn't built with
potential malicious Kubernetes events
and short lived container logs in mind.
Falco is usually associated with
a command line, but there is this
public page as seen on the left
and middle part of the slide, where
you can conveniently Falco rules in
detail, including rules description.
Condition when the role will be
triggered, output content, and rule tags.
On the right, SysTex 2024 Cloud
Native Security and Usage Report
lists top triggered detections.
In any environment where containerized
workloads are being experimented with.
locally or served publicly, there
should be tooling in place to detect and
potentially safeguard from such actions.
Falco
natively provides just a handful
of destinations for its outputs,
and this is where Falco Sidekick
open source project comes in handy.
It can fan out Falco's output
to over 60 destinations.
across web, chat ops, logging, streaming,
alerting, and observability platforms.
As for the web output for Falco Sidekiq,
there is Falco Sidekiq UI, a user
friendly way to track Falco events
across triggered rules, event severities,
tags of interest, and comes with
Swagger documentation for API queries.
So that would be the core of our thread
detection hands on lab for today.
The link here and QR code we will send
you to a Google Drive to download the
virtual machine pre installed with
all the tools for today's session.
Let's say the last few words on the
lab environment and then start the VM.
VM's operating system is Kali Purple, a
community project focused on defensive
tooling structured around the NIST
cybersecurity framework to identify,
protect, detect, respond, and recover.
The project aims to become the
most comprehensive security
operations center in a box.
kind of solution.
On top of Kali Purple, first
installed are several tools to easily
manage local Kubernetes cluster.
And in the cluster, Kubernetes Goat as an
interactive learning platform with real
world Kubernetes misconfigurations is
spun up and we will leverage one of its
scenarios for Falco sidekick detection.
Was created to document offensive
and defensive Kubernetes techniques
inspired by Microsoft's Kubernetes
threat matrix, which provides a
framework for understanding Kubernetes
tactics in a MITRE ATT& CK style.
While the Microsoft Threat Matrix focuses
on educating around Kubernetes tactics,
techniques, and procedures through
definitions, KubeNomicon expands on it
by aiming to offer practical commands
for both exploiting and defending against
attacks in Kubernetes environments.
For example, some of the tools that
can be used to enumerate a Kubernetes
environment are Nmap and Metasploit.
We will also use Atomic Red Team
containerized project to simulate real
world attacks aligned with MITRE ADT and
CK framework in a Kubernetes environment.
These Atomics tests are in general
immensely helpful to refine and enhance
coverage by addressing any detection gaps.
As we trigger Atomics test, we
will monitor Falco Sidekick UI
for real time thread detection.
Now, let's switch to the VM.
Okay, now this is the login
screen you expect to see when
you boot up the virtual machine.
If it doesn't work from the first
time, shut it down and boot it
up again until you get to this.
Login panel and enter credential sidekick,
same password.
So now for the sake of time, I
already went through a couple
of system setting up commands.
I'll walk you quickly through.
So when you first boot up the system,
you will run command groupctl get pods.
through all namespaces.
And you'll see this kind of output,
unable to connect to the server.
That means that you
have to start Minikube.
So I'm running this virtual
machine with over 20 GB of RAM.
Add at maximum 2 GB less
than the virtual machine has.
So in my case that's 16 GB.
Try not to go less than 8 GB.
And at least to vcpu for
the whole virtual machine.
Then after that, you'll check again,
kubectl get pods, and wait a bit
to see okay, now we get a different
output, and we can notice majority of
pods we expect to see in the running.
Something to notice is that a couple
of pods in the default namespace
that are coming through Kubernetes
Goat project are in error state.
So from previous experience what
resolves this issue is to tear down
the project and set it up again.
Commands to do that are
into documents directory.
In the documents directory,
you will notice a directory
kubernetes goat over there.
There are a couple of commands.
First, you'll run the teardown.
Then when that finalizes,
you'll run the setup one.
And when that finalizes,
you'll check the pod status.
All should be in running state.
And then you'll run the access command.
So teardown,
then setup,
check the pod status.
All are running.
In running state, then access
and you'll be provided with
the local URL to access it.
Okay, it works locally, that's great.
We'll later use one scenario from here.
And for the Falco Sidekick
UI, you'll run this command
to be able to access the web UI locally.
So do we have, yeah here I
bookmarked relevant projects.
You.
can dig deeper into after
this fast paced session.
So for the Falco sidekick
UI, we'll use this URL.
Okay, great.
Now it works.
Default credentials are admin, admin.
Okay, now we see some rules
triggering from my previous work.
But this is something to
expect to see in the UI.
So Falco Sidekick UI is just one
of the 60 plus possible output
destinations for Falco Sidekick.
So any output from Falco Sidekick
you can forward to, for example,
another SIEM tool, let's say.
But for this session, we'll move on.
Keep our focus on Falco Sidekick UI
and we'll monitor reported events here.
Okay, let's now try
from KubeNomicon one simple
scenario to see if Falco
Sidekick UI reports on the event.
From, let's say, execution
section, exec inside container.
And here we are provided
with a practical command.
We don't expect to see in Microsoft,
as we said, Kubernetes threat metrics.
So let's say we'll exec into one
of the available pods over here.
Let's pick one from the, let's say,
secure middleware namespace, this pod.
Let's adjust command a bit.
We have to add a specific namespace
and the pod name is this one.
And let's monitor Falco sidekick UI
for when we exec into the pod.
Okay, it's now reported.
Terminal shell we see in container.
So with the default rules, Falco
rules installed this command is
recognized and you can see here
bookmarked additional Falco training.
Thank you.
This is a link.
Okay.
Here you can find courtesy of Sysdig
free Falco training that should
enable you to create your own rules.
Next, for the sake of time, let's
switch quickly to Kubernetes
code and let's try one scenario.
RBAC least privileges misconfiguration.
So let's access the scenario locally.
Okay.
And let's follow along
the provided instruction.
On public website.
Scenarios.
RBAC list privileges misconfiguration.
And the story is that we can only see
in the real world where developers
and DevOps teams tend to provide
extra privileges than required.
So let's see what we
can dig out from here.
Let's leverage a couple of commands from
this page, but, for example, this command
you'll recognize also in the provided
official Kubernetes documentation, for
example, to access the service account.
This is what's bookmarked.
So please go through these commands
at your own pace after the session.
But let's see how this works.
And let's monitor OK Falco if
it will recognize anything.
So this scenario, let's
copy paste the commands.
This is being read from
environment variables, so let's prove it.
Okay,
and let's see if we will get the
server address as seen on the
screenshot by using this command.
Okay, great.
Now we are, we got the server address.
So for example let's copy paste
it directly into our browser to
see what we'll get with that.
Okay, let's accept potential risks.
Okay, and we see now
some output over here.
For example, if we got an assignment
to scan locally a certain CIDR range
with Nmap and recognize this port open
with this kind of output available,
we could easily kind of Google it.
And that would point us to Kubernetes.
For example, let's see if what's
happening in the Falco site QI.
Bye.
Yeah, it recognized that Kubernetes API
server was contacted from container.
Okay, let's proceed with SPLT,
let's say, because SPL has a
Kubernetes focused module to see
what we can discover with that.
So to use meta split module, you will
need, server address, port, and token.
And we already found, already
found the token.
Let's cut it out.
Okay, we now have the token.
And let's see what we can get
with Metasploit using this token.
Let's exit from here.
Let's search for Kubernetes.
Okay, let's start from this zero.
And then we'll try Metasploit.
Let's see what our options are.
Okay, let's add a host,
address, port, and token.
So we see here address.
Let's set.
Okay, and it's recognized
that we can add a token.
For example, get list watch resources
in this big monolith namespace.
For example, we cannot create resources
with this specific token we found here.
But let's say We found another token.
Let's say we found this one.
Great.
Now Metasploit reports that we
have, we can do all actions across
all namespaces, all resources.
So let's try the other
available Metasploit module.
So we use the enumeration.
Now let's use the exploit exec.
Was it 10?
Yeah, it was 10.
And let's see options.
We have to set up again, a
host and port token also,
and token.
And one more thing, let's monitor pods.
We have available.
Kubectl get pods.
So these are the pods we
currently have on the host.
And when we run exploit in this case,
we see another pod is created.
And we got a show.
We created a pod on the host and
now we are inside that pod, right?
Let's check.
We are root.
That's that pod name.
Let's see if it's reported over here.
Yeah, it's seen as
created and running state
and we can proceed from here.
And quickly let's go
through one atomic scenario.
We see it here in the running state.
Let's exec into it
and let's invoke the module
so we can browse through.
Available atomics tests.
See what we have available.
And let's see here, for example,
let's pick the rootkit one
and let's monitor valko sidekick UI.
Great.
We see now that one of the
default rules was triggered
and we can see here details.
That's all for the demo.
I hope you enjoy it.
As a next logical step, moving forward
from today's session, I suggest
looking into recently officially
published Falco Talon project, a
response engine for Falco detected
threats in Kubernetes environments.
Just to name a few actions that
can be automated using Falco Talon.
Invoking an AWS Lambda function
on a triggered Falco rule.
then enforcing a Kubernetes network
policy, and labeling a pod as
suspicious or terminating it.
I hope you enjoyed today's
session, and that Mark will accept
my future Conf42 applications.
Linked on this slide, you can
find Falco training that should
enable you to start contributing
to Falco and create your own rules.
If you find today's topic interesting,
join the Falco Slack community and let's
stay in touch until the next session.
Bye for now.