Welcome everyone, and thanks
for joining my session on
Transforming Knowledge Systems.
I'm Haida Dube from Apex FinTech
Solutions x Dell having a patent as well.
And today we'll explore how embedding
analytics within cloud native
architectures, specifically Kubernetes
can revolutionize knowledge management.
This session is inspired by real
enterprise challenges where static
repository is no longer made
dynamic data driven business needs.
Let's start with the current state,
or 50% of the enterprise knowledge
management systems are failing
to meet their performance goals.
It's about 15,000 plus employees
across the global offices.
Many organizations are.
Are struggling with
knowledge accessibility.
What's the key issue here?
It is traditional systems were
never designed for today's
distributed cloud first environments.
They are slow, siloed, and
difficult to scale, hindering
productivity and innovation.
So what are the root causes
of knowledge system failures?
There are three.
That.
Those are the main ones.
The siloed design where teams and
departments operate in isolation, creating
the fragmented knowledge repositories,
outdated architecture that is monolith
systems that cannot adapt quickly to
changing business or user demands and
poor adoption, where users abandon tools
that fail to deliver relevant results
or provide an intuitive interface.
These issues make it clear that
traditional knowledge management needs
a complete architectural rethink.
Now this slide contrast two
paradigms, the static repository
versus the containerized ecosystem.
Traditional tools like SharePoint served
as a static document, source and contrast.
Kubernetes enables a
dynamic adaptive ecosystem.
A Kubernetes native approach
supports automation, embedded
analytics and continuous learning.
Helping systems evolve with user needs.
So what is the goal here?
The goal is to move from
infl inflexible systems to
intelligent, responsive platforms.
Here's an overview of the architecture
where SharePoint Online serves as the
content source, containerized services,
managed analytics, search and automation.
While Kubernetes orchestration ensures the
scalability, resilience, and continuous
deployment, this layered approach, as
we call it, decoupled services, allowing
independent scaling and modernization
without disrupting the base content layer.
There are three main components to it.
User behavior analytics, which will track
engagement, clickthroughs and navigation
patterns, search pattern mining that
identifies how users query and where
searches fail, and real time feedback
loops that adapt search results and
recommendations based on user actions.
Now this roadmap outlines how to
evolve from setup to intelligent
optimization during the foundation phase.
Teams deploy Kubernetes
clusters, design microservices,
and integrate SharePoint APIs.
During the analytics phase,
you roll out analytics tracking
and early AI recommendations.
During the intelligence phase, introduce
NLP and predictive analytics and the
most important phase, and last but
not the least, is optimization phase.
That is when you automate governance
and scale enterprise wide.
After full implementation, which we
saw were impressive, there were 33%
faster information, retrieval rate,
35% fewer support tickets, and 22%
boost in self-service resolution rates.
These outcomes mean users find answers
faster, support load decreases,
and also knowledge flows freely.
The key takeaways are embedded
analytics makes systems smarter
and self-improving over time.
The impact extended to
user experience as well.
The metrics like user satisfaction
was increased by 37.5%.
The onboarding time dropped by almost 25%.
Thing that was taking 14
weeks is now taking 11 weeks.
And content relevance
improved significantly.
These gains comes from integrating
feedback loops and relevance
tracking proof that a better system
directly enhances productivity
and employee engagement.
Smart features powered by Kubernetes.
Kubernetes powers
intelligence layer with NLS.
That is natural language search
by understanding intent beyond the
keywords, context aware filtering
where de delivering the results based
on user rules or project context and
predictive analytics By anticipating
user needs before even the search,
these capabilities turn a passive
repository into an active assistant.
Automation is not limited
to content delivery.
It extends to governance as well.
User data, track engagement, abandonment
metrics, detect friction points,
training insights, identify popular
or missing topics, and the continuous
optimization automatically curates and
promotes high value content in the loop.
This governance loop
ensures sustainability
without manual intervention.
The transformation delivered measurable,
ROI, which is $3.7 million in tangible
gains has come from efficiency
improvement and using the metrics like
we already covered in the previous slide.
Here's how you can start.
If you would like to have the similar
blueprint in your organization first
designed for Observa observability
by instrumenting everything,
embrace the microservices,
modularize analytics components.
Prioritize feedback by gathering real
time user insights, automate governance,
where you just let data manage
content cycles and measure everything.
Everything means everything.
By defining and monitoring
the success metrics.
To summarize, evidence-based systems
powered by Kubernetes and analytics
enhance the engagement and agility.
Transitioning from static to dynamic
ecosystems unlocks the continuous
improvement and real world implementation
delivered both measurable ROI and
Tulsa transformation, as you saw.
So the key takeaway is Kubernetes
when combined with embedded analytics,
leads to resilience, scalable
human-centered knowledge system.
Thanks all for joining here, and I'm.
I would love to hear your questions,
whether about implementation,
scaling analytics, or integrating
these ideas in your own environment.
Let's discuss and connect on LinkedIn
how these concepts can fit your
enterprise's unique challenges.
I'd love your feedback.
Thank you so much.
Bye.