Hello everyone.
I am pri today I'll be walking you
through how cloud native technologies
can fundamentally reshape EV charging.
The goal is to show how we can
scale, optimize, and make charging
smarter, supporting not only drivers,
but also the grid and the broader
push towards sustainable mobility.
Before we dive into technology,
let me introduce myself.
My name is Pri Ali, and I'm currently
working as a senior technical program
manager at Ford Motor Company.
With my nine plus years of experience,
I have been fortunate to lead several
initiatives at Ford and other companies
that bring together cloud native
infrastructure and electric mobility.
My background is in scalable systems
and program management, which means
that I sit at the intersection
of technology and execution.
This helps me help businesses turn
strategy into working infrastructure.
My focus has been on making ev
charging not just available, but
intelligent and user friendly
from an educational standpoint.
I have a bachelor's and a master's
in electrical engineering, and I'm
pursuing my PhD in systems engineering.
As far as cloud native infrastructure
goes, this is becoming more important than
ever because ev adoption is accelerating
faster than an infrastructure can keep up.
Last year alone, 14 million
EVs were sold globally.
That's a huge leap.
Nearly one in five cars were
sold worldwide and electric.
This shift is more than a trend,
it's a revolution in mobility, but
with it comes new expectations.
Drivers need reliable, predictable
charging, just as they have always
expected gas stations to be available.
Without scalable infrastructure
adoption could slow.
So the challenge is not just to build
more chargers, but to build smarter ones.
And that brings us to the reality
of today's charging infrastructure
and the pain pointed faces.
There are three main hurdles
that I would like to call out.
The first one is scalability.
Traditional networks weren't designed for
exponential growth or global coverage.
Secondly is grid integration.
Legacy systems don't adapt well to dynamic
load management or to renewable energy.
And thirdly, user experience range anxiety
remains because availability is patchy.
Visibility is poor, and
downtime is just too common.
These are the gaps that we must
address if EP adoption is to
continue at its current pace.
So how do we solve this?
The answer lies in the principle
of cloud native design.
Cloud Native gives us modularity
and flexibility, microservices that
helps us break down complex systems
into smaller, more manageable
services like for payments, for
routing, user interfaces, et cetera.
Kubernetes that orchestrates them.
Scaling automatically as the
demand spikes and open APIs allows
integration with vehicles, utilities.
And even third party
applications together.
This creates an ecosystem that's a
dynamic, scalable and resilient, exactly
what EV charging needs at the moment.
Now let's see how this foundation
translates into practical improvements,
starting with reliability.
Charge downtime has been one
of the biggest foundation
frustrations for drivers.
With predictive maintenance, we
can cut downtime by as much as 40%.
Iot sensors that continuously
monitor health machine learning that
predicts failures before they can
even happen, and cloud-based systems
schedule repairs automatically.
The result is fewer surprises
for drivers and more efficient
use of technician resources.
Reliability builds trust and trust is
what drives adoption Beyond reliability,
drivers also care about convenience,
and that's where smart routing and
load balancing comes in Picture.
Now cloud services bring
real-time visibility into
charger status and even Q lens.
Intelligent routing algorithms
can then guide drivers to the PEs
station based on traffic speed
of charging and availability.
At the same time, distributed load
balancing insurers chargers are used
optimally while minimizing grid strengths.
This creates a system that
feels responsive put to the
driver and to grid operator.
Together, this innovations
tackle the most persistent worry
for EV drivers range anxiety.
Now with live data and smart
routing drivers don't have to guess
or hope that a charger is free.
They know before they get there.
Routing adapts dynamically
even considering traffic.
And on the grid side, load
optimization prevents bottlenecks.
All of this means a predictable
stress-free charging experience.
Once drivers stop worrying about being
stranded, EV adoption becomes seamless.
Of course, smart charging
isn't just about drivers.
It also plays a major role
in how we manage energy.
Demand charging patterns can
put immense stress on the grid.
If unmanaged.
Cloud native scheduling solves this by
shifting sessions to off peak times.
It uses pricing grid conditions and
user preferences to automatically
schedule charging when it's
cheapest and least disruptive.
This lowers cost for consumers, reduces
stress on the grid and benefits operators.
So it's a win-win for all.
And once vehicles themselves are seen
as assets, not just consumers or power,
the possibilities expand even further.
Let's talk about vehicle to
grid or V two C as it's called.
This turns EVs into mobile batteries.
Imagine millions of cars
acting as distributed storage.
Cloud native platforms can
orchestrate this at scale, absorbing
excess solar or wind when supply
is high and feeding power back.
When demand spikes, it supports
renewable, strengthens the grid, and
creates new value streams for owners.
This is where mobility and
energy ecosystems truly converge.
Scaling this vision, however,
requires a phased approach.
So what we can do.
Rollouts typically start
with core infrastructure, the
essential charging platform.
From there, Kubernetes, make horizontal
scaling across sites seamless.
Once the network is stable, we can
layer in advanced features like B two
G, AI driven optimization, et cetera.
This waste model keeps cost manageable
and ensures reliability at each stage
of growth and scale matters, especially
when we consider global targets For 2030,
the International Energy Agency projects
a need for four times as many public
charges by 2030, which is very close now.
That's a massive expansion.
Traditional systems would struggle, but
cloud native approaches make it feasible.
They simplify deployment, standardized
management, and allow operators to
square quickly while maintaining quality.
This is how we keep pace with
EV adoption at a global scale.
And underpinning all this is
the ability to see, analyze,
and act on data in real time.
Analytics gives operators
visibility into performance.
Consumption and usage patterns.
Edge computing enables faster decision
making, locally reducing latency.
Meanwhile, machine learning continuously
improves predictions for routing,
maintenance, and load balancing.
Over time, the network learns and
adapts becoming more efficient
without manual intervention.
This leads us to the bigger picture, the
path towards truly intelligent mobility.
The journey unfolds in three steps.
First, build a strong
cloud native foundation.
Then integrate smart systems like
predictive maintenance and dynamic
opting, and finally optimize and
scale with real time analytics and ai.
The outcome is an infrastructure that's
not just scalable, but intelligent,
capable of adopting to changing demands,
technologies, and user needs to close.
Let me bring it all together.
Thank you for joining me today.
Cloud native EV charging is
more than just technology.
It's the backbone of intelligent,
sustainable mobility.
By addressing scalability, reliability,
and grid integration, we enable a
future where electric vehicles are
not only viable but preferable.
I look forward to hearing from all
of you on your thoughts, and if there
are any questions, thank you again
for giving me the opportunity to speak
at com 42 Kubernetes 2025 conference.
Thank you.
Bye.