Hello all.
Hope everyone is doing fine
and welcome to this session.
Today we'll explore how generative AI in
maintenance for automotive manufacturing.
We'll look at the journey from
downtime to data-driven up.
This patient presentation will
highlight key concepts, technologies,
and implementation strategies.
The automotive factories constantly
struggle with an unexpected equipment
breakdowns that hals the production
line and creates substantial unplanned
equipment expenses emerging generative ai.
Definitely provide a solution to bridge
this gap by decoding complex signals
and data coming from sensors on the
production line and analyzing that
information, create some cool results,
which we will look at in details as we
move through this product presentation.
So with that note.
Let me move forward
now.
Quick introduction about me.
I'm Abijit Joshi.
I'm a supply chain
transformation specialist.
I'm currently working at Deloitte
Consulting and I have total 20 years
of experience in leading digital
transformation initiatives across
and across different automotive
manufacturing sites, as well as I
have also work in other industries.
I specialized in data-driven
operation excellence and
predictive maintenance solution.
Through my journey of 20 years, I have
seen multiple different implementation
for maintenance and as in firsthand
experience, I started my career with the
maintenance module in the manufacturing
industry for five to six years.
I have had hands-on
experience in the maintenance.
Situation for my old company, and
then I moved to the ERP consulting.
So that was just a quick
introduction about me.
Now let's move forward, jump into
the concept and understand what we
are trying to achieve through this.
Now here is the abstract and overview.
Now what challenge we
are here to solve today.
Based on the recent data, unplanned
equipment, downtime cost automotive
manufacturers up to 22,000 per minute,
as in loss, and the traditional
manufacturing strategies are inadequate.
Address this challenge now.
What is the solve, which we are
gonna see through this presentation
now with recent AI developments?
Applying generative AI to predictive
maintenance in ERP system can
reduce your planned downtime by 40%.
This session explores the approach
of how any implementation, how
any maintenance application
implementation can leverage this.
How AI can help to analyze
data provided by sensors on the
production line and this data.
Arranged into a structured
workflow pattern can fed into a
maintenance system to generate
the preventative maintenance work.
So that's the solve which a
new technology can bring in.
Now as we move forward, we will
see what are the different ways
of achieving this outcome Now.
There are few more points where this
advanced computing system identify early
signs of ation that are often missed
by a standard monitoring equipment
or even by a human interaction.
There is a chance it can be missed.
Now, car manufacturers integrating
this capability directly into their
enterprise resource planning system,
which has fundamentally changed.
We create the work order in
order to act on these problems.
So with that note, let's move
forward and see that how we
can go through this journey.
Now let's talk about the
traditional maintenance methods.
Typically, there are three
ways of handling maintenance,
calendar-based maintenance.
Based maintenance or
condition based maintenance.
Now, even if we take our day-to-day
examples, like having your own
card, it needs some maintenance.
So you can either go by one of
these three methods during my
visits to different industry.
These are three methods which I
have extensively seen getting used
in the traditional maintenance.
Whether it's being a manufacturing
plant, it's being oil and gas refinery.
These were mainly three interfaces.
Now, let's talk a little bit about them.
When we say calendar based, it's
a fixed interval that after three
months, I'm gonna maintain, I'm gonna
do some 1, 2, 3, 4 activities for
this specific piece of the equipment.
What are the challenges?
It can be premature.
It can even am expected failures
because you're just following the time.
You're not looking, was the machine
utilized enough in this time period?
Now, next is a usage base.
Now maintenance based on some run
cycle or account better understand.
How long it has been used.
So after that specific time, you do
the maintenance, again, this is not
a right way of doing the maintenance.
Third is the condition base.
Let's say you monitor some
parameters and based on certain
life of that parameter you create.
Work order.
So these are three typical
traditional maintenance methods.
Now let's move forward and look
at what are the challenges of this
traditional maintenance method.
First challenges, this is
the reactive maintenance.
This is not a proactive approach.
So the traditional maintenance system
is basically reactive in nature.
That based on certain problems, you
try to solve the problem and it's
very much disruptive to the production
lines and the production flows.
Then there are fixed schedule
limitations, so there could be a chance
that equipments are service too early
or too late, and it's also a vestige
of resources and risking of failures.
Which is a typical challenge
of the traditional maintenance.
And third and the most important
is lack of data driven decisions.
So the moment we say we are doing it
by fixed time interval or calendar
base, we are not utilizing any past
data, which is a typical challenge.
Now let's move forward
and see is there any way.
We can convert this reactive
into proactive approach.
Now, this slide talks about that, how
we can convert a reactive approach
into a proactive approach, and that
is what the maintenance team needs,
which will help them to proactively
use to right use their resources.
So generative AI plays a wider
role in this room for patients.
It can transform maintenance from
reactive firefighting to proactive
optimization to a data-driven
insight and predictive analysis.
Now, let's see, how can we achieve this?
So typically there are three drivers
for the approach which we are proposing.
So one is the iot.
So when I say iot, it's
internet of things.
It's a kind of bridge between
what is happening at the equipment
versus how it can translate to
the signal, a kind of transducer,
what we had in the earlier ages.
So one of the driver to achieve
this proactive approach is the iot
integrations where your equipment
will talk and generate data signals.
The second driver is the ERP.
So typically, most of these industries, a
car manufacturing industry, have some kind
of system behind the scene, which tells
them how much is their inventory, what
is their work order, how many times they
have to do a certain kind of activity in
terms of maintenance of that equipment.
So these are handled through a ERP system.
Third is the generative ai.
Now, generative AI is the most important
driver out of all this, which sits on top
of IOT and ER to generate the research.
Now, we talked about the three
important drivers in this approach.
Now let's move forward and
look at what framework we are
suggesting in order to move.
Reactive to proactive approach.
Now, generative AI for
predictive maintenance framework.
If you see on your left hand side picture
at the top, that we are suggesting let's
collect the data from different sensors.
Look at your maintenance history.
See your performance metrics.
Now you have this huge data.
Now this data has to be read and analyzed.
Before sending it to the ERP system,
so ERP should get the important data,
which it needs to do certain actions.
Now, gen AI engine comes next to this.
It sits on top of ERP where it
analyze that data and give ERPA signal
rather than some predefined engines.
It tells that, hey, this is a
time that you have to create
the maintenance work orders.
These are the times based on the
equipment deterioration or the
capacity it has been utilized.
You should be performing your
maintenance, and that is what goes to
your manufacturing system within ERP, and
that generates the real time information.
Now there are possibly three
actions which can happen.
System one is automated action,
which is creating a maintenance work
product, which tells technician that
he was, he's supposed to go and do a
maintenance on this particular equipment.
Secondly, deriving a plan becomes
a very optimal because now you can
plan your future work order based
on your downtime of the machine.
Third is generating multiple
KPIs outta this information.
So this is the approach which we are
proposing, which can convert your reactive
maintenance into a proactive maintenance.
Now let's move forward and see what
is the role of each of this component.
In this process.
So the first is iot, internet of Things.
Now, what is its role?
Its role is to collect the data
from all different production lines.
Imagine you're working at the car
manufacturing facility and you have
tons of data coming from everywhere
initial stage, from building
different parts till the last stage
where you do a painting of your car.
There is lot of robotics
used in this production line.
Given the demand which this
industry is seeing, there is a lot
of automation happening on each
of the phase of manufacturing.
This automation definitely triggers a
lot of information, which is basically
internet of things, where you collect
all that sensor information and
translate into a respective signal.
So if you look at the three points
mentioned here, realtime sensor data,
the sensors embedded in the machine
capture the realtime data such as
vibration, temperature, pressure,
it assess the entire equipment.
Health predictive analysis,
analytics foundation.
This is.
To analyze that information.
Continuous monitoring IOT networks
provide continuous monitoring,
which is not possible for any human.
So that is the first aspect
and the role of the iot.
Now let's move forward and look
at the second important component
in this workflow, which is ERP.
So what is the role of ERP integration?
I mentioned before, ERP is used for
having all different aspects of the
company, whether it's a pro purchase order
production, work order, or your inventory.
So apart from creating a maintenance work
order, it also facilitates a data which
is required to fulfill that work order.
What parts you need, what instructions
are there for performing that operation or
maintenance and what resources you need.
So the idea here is IOT provides
that information to ERP, and rather
than having a traditional engine
of preventative maintenance based
on the calendar, it reads that data
and try to generate a work order.
If there is a situation where maintenance
is required, it can predict that ahead
of a time based on the current equipment.
So if we read two or three points
here, which is the predictive
maintenance management, this is
the ERP system management module.
Automated work order generation
ERPA automatically creates a work
order and allocates the resources.
When AI detects any potential issues
and continuous improvement feedback,
ERP feedback refines AI module
improving predictions and accuracy.
Now let's look at the third aspect,
the role of generative ai, which
is the most important aspect
in all these three parameters.
Now, what AI does, AI is
modeling equipment behavior.
It generates equipment behavior
to understand and predict
the potential failures.
Secondly, synthetic data generation.
It generates a synthetic data
scenario to simulate different
operational condition for the analysis.
It also keeps learning based on
the real time data as we have seen.
IOTs constantly providing your data.
Now generative AI has capability to
self learn from the history as well
as with the new data, which is coming
and understand the failure pattern.
Third is proactive maintenance forecasting
based on a data it's reading, it can
forecast what are the maintenance lead.
It's not just about maintaining
any equipment, it's also about
making sure you have enough.
Perform that activity.
You have enough resources,
they're at the right time.
Execute that activity so
Gen AI can perform all that
activity behind the scene.
So we have looked at the three aspects
of this process and what is their
role in performing this operation.
Now let's move forward.
And see that what are the target
application, which we think, again,
the possibilities are endless, but
we think that these two are very
important applications within the car
manufacturing, like the robotic system
and the pen application line, where the
solutions can be implemented because
these are the most prone things in the
process, which can lag the productivity.
If there is a maintenance failure,
so early failure detection in
automated assembly and welding
robots through continuous
monitoring of operational patterns.
This can be achieved through generative
AI with the continuous monitoring
paint application lines, predictive
maintenance for paint, booth equipment
and spray system to prevent any
quality issues and any downtime.
So these are some target applications.
Now let's see, what is our
implementation strategy?
Now, this is pretty high level view
of the implementation strategy.
Definitely if you are running any pilot
program, you have to have much details,
but we categorized into three steps.
One is leveraging existing infrastructure.
So the point here is.
Do I need to create the entirely new
infrastructure or I can leverage existing?
So answer is you can leverage
your existing infrastructure, use
your current sensors, your data.
The only thing is now it'll
go to a certain data warehouse
where it'll get, analyze and
translate into a readable format.
Now step.
Integrate predictive intelligence
seamlessly into existing workflow and
create the preventative work order
and assign them to the technicians so
you can start leveraging your data.
Third step is scale, gradual adoption.
So the approach we're
trying to suggest here.
Go stepwise, go a phase wise.
If you have 10 plans, go with one plant
first or possibly even a one product line.
So then there are minimum disruption
to the existing process, and once you
prove your result, then you can move
to a larger scale of implementation.
So once you implement this
strategy, what are the results?
You can expect, somebody can
ask that, okay, I'm implementing
this, but what are the results?
So we have studied this implementation
across the industries, and these are
some proven results from the deployment.
Again, it'll be very for some of the
companies versus other, but this is a
kind of ballpark which we can expect.
So your downtime reduction should
at least go to 40% because now
you have put intelligence into
the system, which will help you to
reduce unscheduled time, downtime.
Secondly, forecasting accuracy.
Now, the earlier forecasting
was based on the calendar dates.
Now you're using system
intelligence to do a forecasting.
So definitely we see.
Around 85% improvement in that accuracy.
Your equipment deterioration is utilized
to predict what maintenance you need.
Third is reduction in the false alarm.
With the traditional method, you
can do a maintenance based on,
again, the calendar days, right?
So there could be a chance of the fall.
Now with AI integration and the pattern
recognition, it can reduce to 50%.
Now, when we say we have this fabulous
result from our deployment, definitely
what are the outcome in terms of
cost and efficiency I can measure.
So again, we did study based
on our prior implementation.
These are the results we see.
Again, just to call out.
This may not be specific
to one client to other.
It's based on what is the expected
outcome, a kind of ballpark.
So your maintenance cost should
reduce by 30% by optimizing
scheduling as well as resources.
And secondly, since you
have lot of historical data.
From prior corrections, from even if
there is some first time fixed rate,
it should be improved to the 90%.
That is what we expect as an
achievement with this implementation.
Now let's move forward and see
what are the key benefits we are
getting with this implementation.
So when is plant repairs?
Now since you have intelligence,
you can very well plant your
maintenance schedule without pausing
instead of emergency shutdowns.
So you reduce your emergency shutdowns
due to the better monitoring of
equipment, you enhance the reliability.
So transform maintenance into a
strategic driven of production stability.
Third efficiency, which we have
seen on the earlier slide, that
you achieve significant cost saving
to optimize maintenance operation.
So there are multiple benefits of having
this implementation, but this three we see
as most prominent benefits from performing
this reactive to proactive transformation.
Now the next slide and the concluding
slide in this discussion is what should
be our vision if we implementing and if
we are on the journey of implementing this
methodology, our vision should be zero.
Downtime.
Factory vision with growing
gen, AI acceptability across
multiple industries and even in
the car manufacturing industries.
That serves as a core enabler to achieve
the zero time downtime factory vision.
Even the future automation system,
we can expect that they will
self-diagnose, self repair, and enhance
reliability and the cost effectiveness.
So with that note, let thank
to everyone for listening.
And giving.