Hey guys, thanks for joining in.
Today, we're going to talk about a less
common approach to production monitoring
called business driven monitoring.
But before I begin, I
want to ask you something.
Do you know that exciting
feeling of yes, it works.
That feeling is why I
love developing software.
Some people get this thrill from looking
at a task pass after multiple failures.
But me, I get it from looking at Grafana.
Seeing traffic from real users
going through a brand new process I
created and getting new experience.
It's something that gives
me tremendous satisfaction.
The way I see it, monitoring is
the gift wrapper you put on before
you ship the feature to production.
And I bet some of you are thinking,
we don't need to worry about that.
Monitoring is out of the box.
And in many cases, it's true.
In large tech companies like Wix, there
are great out of the box production
monitoring solutions, but they tend
to focus on a single microservice.
Or even a single pod.
Now, I hope that by the end of this talk,
you will see monitoring a bit differently.
Instead of monitoring latency
and errors, you will switch your
focus to monitoring business KPIs.
I will guide you step by step in creating
your first business driven dashboard.
That's how you'll become a true owner of
the product, and not just a developer.
Hi, I'm Oren.
I've been creating Grafana
dashboards for the past five years.
In the past two years, I've been
working as a backend developer at Wix.
com.
There, I'm part of the Wix e commerce
platform, a platform for building
e commerce sites and stores online.
For those of you who don't know Wix, Wix
is a site building platform that powers
over 10 million sites across the internet.
One million of them are e commerce sites.
In terms of monitoring, Wix microservices
expose over 150 million unique metrics
per hour and half a trillion logs a day.
So huge scale, huge global impact.
And that's why I come to work every day.
When I say business driven, what
do I'm not talking about devs
doing analyst's work, not at all.
Business analysts, they set KPIs and
measure them monthly for business growth.
But what I'm talking about is end to end
monitoring of product funnels, tracking
business KPIs to identify crucial bugs
that affect users before they notice them.
When you look at a single service and you
examine its stats like latency and errors,
You have no idea if users get the wanted
experience from your product as a whole.
But if you change perspective and think a
bit like a product, you can find metrics
that will tell you the full story.
Alright, now that we know why it
matters, let's get into the how.
As developers, we have two
main ways to gather live data.
Logs and metrics.
Logs capture what happened, while
metrics capture how well it happened.
Logs are great for debugging and
tracing specific issues, while
metrics are ideal for monitoring
system health and performance.
They are both trimmed into graphs
that compose meaningful dashboards.
And there are so many tools out
there for any of these purposes.
But today we're going to focus on these
three, Loki, Prometheus, and Grafana.
I know this sounds a bit like characters
from a Marvel movie, but from the very
beginning of my career, these were the
tools I used for production monitoring.
They're all open source, so even when
I worked at a low budget startup, I ran
them on premise with Docker Compose.
So you don't have to be a
big company to be monitored.
Now let's present them.
Loki is your log aggregation system.
It consumes the logs
and stores it in its DB.
Prometheus does the exact
same thing for metrics.
They are both integrated into Grafana,
where we create visualizations and alerts.
Now that we've got our tools lined
up, it's time to put them to work.
Let's break down the implementation
process step by step.
Alright, so the first step is to define
the business KPIs and product funnels.
Then, we'll light things
up with logs and metrics.
Alright.
And finally, we'll create
visualization in Grafana.
Imagine walking to the office, you've
got the keys, you're in charge.
The system is already in production and
you want to know how well are we doing.
But there is zero monitoring.
So how the hell will
you know where we stand?
You'll start out by mapping your
business funnels, identifying crucial
flows, breaking them down steps.
At this phase, you should already
know what you expect the system to do.
You should be able to
define your business KPIs.
This is the part you want your product
and analysts on board because they
will enrich your tech perspective
with more business oriented goals.
Each funnel should have at least one
business KPI or else why it exists.
For example, in e com platform, our
main KPI is checkout conversion,
but within this huge funnel until
checkout conversion, we have
more specific per step KPIs.
So now you know what you
expect the system to do.
But more importantly, you should notice
what you're not seeing, what data is
missing, where are your dark spots.
And that's where it gets interesting.
Because once you got the funnels, you can
start to get intimate with every step.
If you see a dark spot, you
can light it up with matrix.
Now don't stick to what could go
wrong and the error flows, but
think about your business KPIs.
Think about what will make
you happy with the product.
Light up those paths as well.
My advice here is to be generous.
Add so many metrics, so you'll feel
like you know every corner of the flow.
For those of you who never used
Matrix, once you did the hard
work of integrating Prometheus and
Grafana, adding one is super easy.
You only need one line of code and
one line in Grafana, and you got it.
I repeat, one line of code
and one line in Grafana.
Mind blowing, right?
Behind the scenes, there is a library that
takes this log of Matrix and translates
it to low key and Prometheus clients.
But also without a proper infrastructure
in your company, there are super
friendly client packages that will
make your production ready in no time.
Prometheus, for example, has
client libraries in almost any
programming language that exists.
So now that we've got a metric
set up, let's visualize the data.
That's how it looks in the most basic way.
What you see here is a time series that
shows the value of the metric per minute.
But
Grafana offers so many
visualizations and unitypes.
Feel free to mix and match till you find
the right ones for your specific step.
Now, I know it looks a bit intimidating,
all these graphs, but in a few
minutes, we'll dive into the demo
and you'll see how easy that is.
Okay, so up until now, we created
a dashboard that is measuring
KPIs in our business funnel.
Before we jump into the demo, I
want to share with you some other
tips to light things up, and I
will do it by a real example.
In the Wix delivery system, we serve
as a platform, so we call delivery
carriers like USPS, for example, to get
real time delivery options and costs.
Now, if you remember earlier, I said
that the Wix e commerce platform
main KPI is checkout conversion.
But within checkout, there is a delivery
step where buyers choose how they want
the product to be shipped to their house.
Now having delivery options is
crucial to completing checkout.
So we must monitor that USPS
returns good options to the buyers.
So we need to let up this flow.
We need to add metrics.
But when we did that, we
got a very blurry picture.
Because we saw success, but we don't
know which delivery carrier succeeded.
We saw a failure, and we don't
know which one failed and why.
And that's where labels come in hand.
Once we added the identifier of
the carrier as a label, we got in
seconds, dozens of flows monitored.
One per delivery carrier.
What down below is identifiers
internally to different delivery
carriers like USPS and pickup locations.
And that's the power of labels.
They allow you to expose multiple metrics
from a single one with different labels.
And all I need to do is to add
the by and the label name at
the end of the Grafana query.
Labels are super useful when it
comes to an open platform because
every site on Wix can have different
delivery carriers installed.
And I need to be open and flexible.
But at the same time, this
is a crucial business flow.
So I must be monitored and
labels allow me to do just that.
So I guess I convinced you that
labels are great, but with great
power comes great responsibility.
Labels can make your service blow up.
Every new value you pass to a label
actually generates a new metric.
And the more metrics your
service exposes, the harder it
works on just being monitored.
So you need to make sure you control
the values of the labels you're passing.
Because if you incidentally
pass an infinite label, your
service will exponentially
expose more and more metrics.
And at a certain point in time, it
will work too hard and it will just
stop being monitored completely.
And later on, it will stop working
completely, which is crazy.
So we want to keep our microservices safe.
We want to control the metrics we're
exposing, and if you can see above, Wix
actually exposes a monitoring alert on the
number of metrics we use for monitoring,
which is a monitoring cannibalism, if
you ask me, but it's for this very reason
we want to safeguard our microservices.
But at the same time to
monitor them properly.
Okay.
It's time for a demo.
We're going to dive into the system
I've been working on in the past
year, the Wix delivery system.
Our goal is to allow stores to offer
diverse delivery options for each of
their products so that every buyer will
find the right one for their needs.
And I'm going to walk you
through its main business flow.
The first step is where a buyer opens the
checkout page and wants to buy a product
that will be delivered to his house.
The next thing we want to know is
how many options the store offers.
Do they offer pickup, local
delivery, maybe USPS shipments?
We want to see how diverse the delivery
carriers that operate in the store.
Because the more diverse they are,
the higher the chance the buyer
will find one that suits him.
The next thing we do is actually call
these delivery carriers through API and
get from them the options and the costs.
So we want to see that they
display good options at checkout
and that they don't fail.
And finally, we want to see them click.
We want to see buyers completing
the delivery step at checkout
and continuing to payment.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to create four
steps and four visualizations.
In Grafana, but before we do it,
there are some things we need to know.
What we're actually going to do is we're
going to query on top of Prometheus DB.
And Prometheus offers some
functions and some special syntax.
So what we're going to use is we're
going to use sum to sum the metric values
across different pods in a production.
Because the microservice and Twix
is deployed on multiple pods and
all of them expose the same metric.
But for our use case, for business
driven monitoring, we don't
actually care about a single pod.
We care about the business flow.
So we want to monitor them all together.
The next thing we'll use is M1 rate,
which is the one minute average
of the metrics we're getting.
This average will help us see graphs more
smoother and will enrich our perspective.
Okay, the next thing we'll use
is the Wix internal labels.
We'll use two of them, service and method.
Service is the microservice that exposes
this metric, and method is the specific
endpoint that exposes this metric.
Alright, I guess we're ready.
Let's dive into the demo.
Alright, so we're starting from
a blank page, an empty dashboard.
And we'll create our first visualization.
We're going to use Prometheus as a data
source, and we're going to do the first
visualization, which is the top of the
funnel where a buyer creates checkout and
wants delivery, and we'll measure it by
the calls to the delivery system entry
point, which every time a buyer creates
a checkout and wants something delivered.
It triggers a call to this endpoint.
So the traffic will signify the
amount of buyers that want delivery.
Okay.
So let's start, we'll do service, which is
the microservice that we're working on and
this microservice is called delivery
rates and what we're going to do
is we're going to use the method.
Which is the entry point to
the entire delivery system.
It is called get delivery options.
And now if I run just that, you can see,
I got a lot of pods that are sending the
same metric, but I don't actually care
about different pods in my production.
I want to see the entire
microservice as a whole.
So I'll use the M1 rate we
talked about and the sum,
and now I'm seeing a clear graph.
Side note on that, don't mind the
numbers because we're using test data.
On the left hand side, there is a
number of calls and It's a time series.
So you see it throughout
the time, six hours.
So the next step is the
delivery carrier diversity.
We want to measure how many carriers
are available for each request we get.
So we're monitoring the same microservice.
And we'll use now a custom metric.
I defined my code.
It is called active delivery
carriers for requests.
And in this metric, I actually calculate
how many delivery carriers are active
pair requests that I get from checkout.
And again, I'll use the
M1 rate and the sum.
But if you think about it, I don't
actually care about the trend here.
I care about the value.
How many active delivery
carriers do I get per request?
So I'm going to switch from
a time series to stats.
And here I can decide how this value will
be calculated on the right hand side.
There is calculation and currently
the default is the last value,
but I don't want the last value.
I want the average.
Across this time frame.
So we'll use mean instead.
The next step, we're going to
check how many delivery carriers
display options at checkout.
And the way for us to measure it is to
take the API calls we do per carrier and
to check how many successful there were.
So we're monitoring the same microservice.
And we're using the custom metric again,
that is called successful
delivery rate SPI calls.
So we'll do the same thing,
M1 rate, and then sum.
So again, sum is sum across pods,
and M1 rate is one minute average.
But if you remember, when I talked
about labels, I talked about
exactly these kinds of graphs.
Because now I get a blurry picture.
I don't know which delivery
carrier displayed at checkout.
So I want to break it down by carrier.
So I'll add the label by, and carrier
is my label that I wrote in my code.
And now I get multiple graphs,
one per delivery carrier.
These IDs you see below are identifiers
internally in our system to different
carriers, for example, to USPS.
Or to pick up locations, etc.
Cool.
Now, let's do the same thing for
failed carriers, which I think
personally is more interesting because
successes are nice, but if I see a
failure, I can do something about it.
Okay, so we'll change the tile to
Delivery carrier failed to display,
display options on checkout.
And now all we need to do is
to change the metric, because
I have the same label there.
So we'll, oh sorry about
that, something went wrong.
Okay, again, failed, false, nice.
And now I get the same
graph, just for failures.
And as you can see There is a certain
app that fails pretty frequently,
and that's something I can act on.
I can talk to this app, I can debug the
issues, which is super powerful because
it actually affects the bottom line.
Alright, the last bit, the
actual delivery step conversion.
So for this one, I'm not going to
use regular from exist metrics.
I'll use ones that are used
by our business analysts.
So what you're seeing here, it's a bit
different syntax, but it's the same thing.
So I have that delivery method
completion in checkout and I divided
by the contact details, which is
the previous step at checkout.
So it's a good approximation of
how many buyers actually go through
filling up the details and then
continue to delivery and find.
A good option and then
continue to payment.
All right, we did it.
It took us a few minutes and we
actually visualize the entire business
funnel of the delivery system.
I hope you're excited because
I am now let's continue.
Now that we've got a kick ass dashboard,
there are some things that can make
us more alert and attentive to it.
The first one, you got it, right?
Alerts in a week or two, everyone
will forget you built this dashboard.
The most proven way to make it relevant.
is to integrate with your regular
production on call alerts.
Here you can see I added an alert to one
of the graphs we created in the demo.
The alert will be sent to
our on call channel with this
custom message I defined below.
Now remember, our goal in this
talk is to find crucial bugs
that affect users quickly and
solve them with minimal impact.
And alerts, they help us to do just that.
To identify the issue before users
start complaining, troubleshoot
quickly, and find the root cause.
So now that we have actionable alerts,
the most common thing we do, straight
after we jump, is to investigate deeper.
And a great thing you can do with Grafana,
It's to provide an investigation dashboard
to really drill down because you start
from a business issue and now you need
to understand it and quickly resolve.
So if you have a dashboard with
pre made investigation, queries,
filters, and latest logs, it can
make you super quick in finding the
issue and actually solving it faster.
So just to quickly recap,
ownership is a choice.
For me personally, it made
development much more interesting.
Now, if you are ready to ownership,
monitoring is the ultimate tool to
help you get intimate with the product
and lead it in the right direction.
To monitor a business, you should start
out by mapping your business funnels,
then light them up with metrics and logs.
So you'll know every corner of the
flow and you can quickly troubleshoot
every issue then add alerts.
So you'll know in time that an
issue arises, and that's how
you become a true owner of the
product and not just a developer.
Thank you so much for listening.
Feel free to reach out and enjoy
the rest of your conference.
Bye.