Hello everyone.
My name is Arvind Kumar.
I work as a staff software
engineer in Guaranteed Write.
I work mainly on Java
and cloud technologies.
My talk today is on empowering
digital transformations using
cloud and java technologies.
Let's start
So this is my agenda today where
we talk about synergy between
cloud and java features Overview
of both the technologies.
We see what is serverless
and CI CD pipelines.
We'll have a demo and we have the summary
introduction The cloud services, so
the cloud technologies, this represents
a transformation approach where
we manage and deliver IT services.
So this is by providing
the on demand access.
To all the IT resources such
as servers the storage like S3
or the storage storage and the
databases over the internet, right?
So traditional approach was we
earlier read before cloud computing,
the IT infrastructure it requires
a lot of upfront investment.
We need to first decide what, how many
servers we need and everything, right?
And then we need to, we used to
build the applications, right?
So in cloud computing,
we can decrease that.
So we can start small and over
time we can increase, right?
So this advantage this is giving a
big benefit to the organizations which
are leveraging this flexibility and
efficiency of using the cloud computing.
So Java role in modern
software development.
We have the java's philosophy, right?
One of the main pillar is
portability where you write one
java application and you can run it
anywhere where we have a jvm, right?
You can run the application in
java, you can write an application
in windows take the class file or
bytecode and you can run in any of
the jvms like in linux or mac os.
You can get the same output.
So this portability is one of the main
features and there are very robust
frameworks for java applications like
where we have a Spring Boot, Micronaut.
Here we can simply develop
scalable applications which are
having high performance, right?
So the TIOB index this is the indicator
where we can gauge a programming language.
So the java is consistently high in this
and the, Java has been the preferred
choice by enterprise applications.
The reasons is behind the extensive
library support and the community support.
So if you see the cloud and Java growth we
talked about it just now the reasons why
cloud computing are being very adaptive
for the business and organizations.
This has become the backbone
of the digital transformation.
And enabling the business to
scale they can innovate more
because they can optimize the
cost like never before, right?
So based on this, there are staggering
numbers of the future prediction,
like we are reaching about 832.
1 billion.
The global cloud computing
market is going to reach 832.
1 billion and the growth
rate is around 17.
5 percent annually.
This reflects that business how the
business are relying on cloud computing
for their operational and strategic needs.
So here we'll talk about
Java's endurance relevance.
Enduring relevance.
So simultaneously, Java is going
to be the cornerstone of the
software development ecosystem.
Even though this is very old
programming language, we still see
that enterprise environments are
being using Java because of the robust
ecosystem, the platform independence
philosophy, and it can be seamlessly
integrated with multiple other systems.
They have a lot of support
for Java based libraries.
So the synergy between
both Java and cloud.
We'll see we have a lot of other things
we just now talked about scalability
and portability, so we'll see how
how it actually works here, right?
So when we say scalability cloud have
something called as auto scaling option.
Where the ability to automatically
scale based on demand, we can
do easily in cloud, right?
And similarly in Java, we have multi
threading concept, which is a very high
performance where Java can handle many
users at same point of time, right?
How it handles?
It has something magical called garbage
collection mechanism where any Java
application, if there are unused objects.
Or unused items it automatically
deallocates the memory for other requests.
To happen right whereas in c and c plus
you need to do it manually in java jvm It
does automatically so the cloud elasticity
is nothing but how the All the cloud
providers said how they do auto scaling
It will be explained in a few minutes.
So here we take an example of e commerce
application, how it handles huge traffic
surges during holiday seasons, right?
Automatically they can increase the
number of then the number of replicas they
need for the application to handle the
request for that increased traffic, right?
So once the traffic is down, then
we can automatically decrease the
config parameters so that you don't
have, you can decrease the cost.
without even manual intervention.
So here we, in this depiction, we
show how autoscaling is handled using,
we have a load balancer, we have two
nodes and Route 53 and we have the
load balancer which handles the traffic
request, it goes to the applications.
We have three Java
instances in the right side.
We'll see the features and the
overview of both cloud and Java here.
So we briefly talked about the
philosophy, write once, run anywhere.
Similarly, this kind of philosophy is
going to complement when we use cloud.
Because we write a Java application,
has the right ones, run anywhere
philosophy is there, you can run in
any of the cloud platforms, right?
You like this increase the
redundancy and cost optimization.
You can deploy the same Java
application in AWS and GCP as well.
So there is one example which we
are talking here about a financial
institution which uses both AWS
and cloud platform for redundancy.
And the core principle of Java is
write once run anywhere, right?
So this is going to complement it.
Here we are seeing the portability
in both Java and cloud.
We have one AWS cloud where we
have a Java application deployed.
We have Google cloud and also the Azure.
Okay.
All of them are having
the same java application
Going next we have the next feature
which is resilient this ensures
the highly availability and fault
allowance of the cloud services, right?
So in cloud platforms This is
inherently built how it build we'll see.
We'll see some examples so java
platforms when they combine with
cloud native architecture, we
can get the Design features like
automatical recovery from failures
handle unexpected surges in demand.
It automatically increases the
number of lift costs we need based
on the incoming traffic, right?
And cloud enabled resilience.
This is using the regional failover and
auto restarts and backing up the systems.
Whenever there is a Java based
application is deployed in AWS or
Kubernetes, it can take the advantage
of all these features and self heal.
Similarly, in Java, we have a strongest,
robust application programming language
where we can do exception handling in a
very great manner and we have a lot of
support for logging frameworks like log4j.
In Spring Boot also we can have we
can integrate with a lot of other
tools like Kibana and Elasticsearch
where we can debug the issues.
We can also also use Grafana for
alerting whenever we have a, let's
say there are 500 when we are
getting 500 exceptions, right?
We can handle it if there are three,
500 errors in a particular timeframe.
In we can raise our alert to
the servicing team, right?
So those kind of things we
can do here in the logging.
Similarly, in AWS side, we have
in cloud side, we have AWS,
Azure, and Google Cloud logging.
We can have, we can monitor
this and combine it.
It makes a very resilient application,
the combination of both cloud
and Java applications, right?
So here we have a healthcare application.
which is running 24 by 7.
So here we have this has been deployed
in multiple geographic locations.
So this is going to be resilient
application by default.
If you're using cloud you don't have
to do anything manually because it
will take care automatically where you
have, you can see here in the example.
US East, it has been deployed
to services and invest.
If there is any problem, the,
with the failover will happen
without manual intervention.
Similarly, we are seeing the diagram
here on the exception handling, how we
are going to handle the AWS CloudWatch
and we can watch the CloudTrail to
see what are the exceptions happening.
So we talked about this, right?
This is nothing but cloud
cross cloud deployment scenario
where we can deploy the java
application multiple clouds, right?
So If you see that in real world
scenario, we can adapt this multi cloud
strategy for below reasons, right?
So one thing is we can avoid vendor lock.
We don't have to stick for one
particular vendor for a long time, right?
And also This will enhance the
resilience to geo redundancy.
How it happens is let's say we have outage
on one particular vendor on one particular
Google let's say, cloud platform.
We don't have to stick to that so that
impact will be completely impacted.
If you deploy the same application
in cross cloud deployment scenario,
we'll have that advantage of having
the redundancy for this, so we'll
having a backup on other cloud platform
or application will be available
through even though there is an
outage on the current platform, right?
And the Java's role in cross cloud,
the same philosophy, Vora philosophy
makes it like very advantageous
where we have the same application
being deployed in different clusters
using Docker and Kubernetes.
We will see that example in few
minutes on how we can containerize
an application and deploy it in K8.
And below the steps how we will develop
it in Spring Boot we will deploy we'll
containerize, package this complete
application using Docker and we'll
ensure it runs consistently with
other, with across the environments
and we deploy this in Kubernetes.
So the here we talk about
this in an with an example.
So let's say we have a big retail company
which is running in North America and
also in European operations, right?
So here we wanted, we are choosing two
different platforms, AWS and Google Cloud.
So by using this we can deploy it in
both different cloud platforms, which
enables the cloud, cross cloud deployment.
So there is no vendor lock here.
We don't need to be tied
to a particular vendor.
Resilience and redundancy
is happening here.
Even though there is an
outage, we don't have to worry.
And cost is optimized based on
whenever there is, let's say there
is an offer on European side.
So the customer can take that advantage.
Here this depiction shows how it happens.
Docker Hub and we have two different
regions with two different cloud platforms
deployed in same Java application.
Let's see the overview.
So we have AWS, Microsoft, and GCP.
Each of them are master
in their own features.
Most of them are common but Google
is specialized in big data, machine
learning, and data analytics.
Same goes with Microsoft and Amazon
has been a leading cloud provider
with a lot of extensive global
support and advanced features.
In coming to microservice architecture,
this is an architecture style where
one big application can be composed
to several independent tasks, right?
Which can be accessed over network.
So if we do comparing to monolithic
architecture and microservices, we
have the following advantages, right?
We have scalability.
flexibility and fault tolerance fault
solution, where we can take one example
where like if one of the active, one
of these small activities failing
in monolithic architecture, entire
application is going to be down whereas
let's say we are running a report
and it is in monolithic architecture,
because of that there might be Lock on
the db and it might impact the entire
application whereas in microservice.
We don't have to worry about it, right?
The reporting or any wire transfer or
any kind of banking activity, right?
Everything can be divided into
small independent service And one
service if there is a failure, it
won't impact the other services.
So that's where we get this fault
isolation And we have a flexibility,
let's say, there are more number of
users using a particular service.
We can scale up that particular
service, so we achieve flexibility
and scalability using that.
And using Spring Boot, we can
create these kind of applications
very easily, within no time.
Yeah, we talk about we're going to
talk about serverless computing.
Here serverless computing is we run the
code and based on the two events without
even managing Or provisioning the servers.
We don't we'll not have any server, but
we can run the code using so that's the
reason it's called serverless computing.
One good example is aws lambda, right?
We can execute a java code or python code
Based on the events or a hdb request.
So I can take an example here, right?
So let's say if you're using aws dynamo
db lambda as your database server So
let's say for every new user login you
want to do some reporting stuff you want
to update something on when did this
user log in or any other extra reporting
kind of activities from the backend.
So you can enable a database
stream and we can create a Lambda.
You can do the business logic there
and we can store that in an RDS.
So that's one of the example where
you can use this without no need
to worry about the infrastructure.
We just focus on the
business logic, right?
And it is very cost effective because
we don't need to worry about it because
cloud provider is going Take care of this
C and CD integration.
So this is one of the primary thing
which is going which is happening
in all the organizations where
we have cloud and Java services.
So the, this benefits faster
development and quality.
We'll see how it happens, right?
So there are many tools like Jenkins.
So they can let's see the definition
C and CD stands for continuous
integration and continuous deployment.
So this practice enabled frequent
code changes and deployments for your.
Git repos, right?
Let's go to the old example.
We have whenever there is a new change In
our traditional approach we used to create
a bill and we used to manually deploy it
In a server on a particular day and let's
say if you want to do it on Production,
let's say you have eight nodes.
You need to do everything manually, right?
So after cloud computing and integrating
with ca and cd whenever the developer
changes the code You An automatical
build can be triggered using Jenkins,
and it can be zilli integrated to gida,
GitLab which automatically builds the
application and deploys it in a particular
environment, let's say dev or qa, right?
This will improve the
faster development cycle.
This automatics automates the
testing and deployment process.
Which will reduce the development time and
so it would be easy for the team to find
a Early bugs before even going to product.
So there are two real world scenarios
here both are different, examples
where financial institution is using
a cloud And e commerce application is
using microservice architecture, right?
The outcomes are simple, right?
We saw the examples before.
We have an improved
scalability and performance.
Using cloud technologies and faster
development and deploy reduced
reduction in the operation cost
when we use the cloud services.
Similarly, in micro services,
there is a system readability and
reduce the time to the market.
Using the new features because if
you come, if you like integrate
microservices with CNCD, so the
deployment lifecycle will be decreased.
So these are the key takeaways
for the for the key concepts and
takeaways in the entire talk.
So we will, so this is
virtualization, contamination
and serverless computing, right?
So virtualization abstracts the
physical hardware and creates virtual
machines optimize the resource usage.
This will, this is happening using
virtualization and containerization.
Dockers will have the applications for
consistent developments and K eight will
have the container and ate deployment
and management here using K eight.
So this server is computing.
We focus main on the business
logic without even worrying about.
How to manage the server.
And so this is using, leveraging
the cloud platform infrastructures.
So we'll see a demo on how we are
going to achieve this in a simple demo,
right?
So here we are seeing a
spring boot application where
we have a rest controller.
So this is nothing but a Spring Boot app.
We have a get mapping.
Which is slash hello.
So whenever a SDP request is
coming, so this will be called and
the request has been processed.
We see a docker file here.
So this docker file is nothing but
the containerization, A Docker file.
This is used to containerize,
this Spring Boot app.
It's used to package the enter application
and it dependency into a container.
The first line says from OpenJDK.
This line specifies the base image
of the container and it, it's
making sure that it is available
to run the application, right?
And we are setting the working
directory to slash app and copying
the jar file, which is created on
the above, the Spring Boot jar.
And we expose 808.
8080, this is the port number
where we are running it.
And the enter point just specifies
the command to run the container.
Going next, the Kubernetes
deployment yaml.
This deployment YAML file here
we are talking about we are just
defining the type of deployment.
If you see, and we.
We have the the most important
confirmation is in this specification
we have replicas, right?
So this replicas will tell the
Kubernetes application how many
instances of the Java application
is going to be deployed, right?
So in this example, we set two
where there are two appli two.
This signifies that there are two
replicas of the J same Java application.
So this is the application which
is running and this ensures
the highly availability of
the of the application, right?
And also, if you see the spec and
container, so here we are taking what
is the application name and the image.
So here, when we talked about
cross cross platform deployment
cross cloud deployments, so we
talked about we can deploy multiple
application application in multiple.
So here in the image, we mentioned the
docker image used for this container.
This is now pulled from AWS,
but you can change it to Google
cloud or whatever we need, right?
So this signifies which which
particular provider we need to use.
So this relevance of this Kubernetes
deployment like this automates
the management of containerized
application, which so here we will
tell where to be deployed and how
many replicas are should be installed.
And this can be automatically scaling
automatically scaling is being added here.
So this can be used for that.
And this YAML file here, this
Kubernetes service YAML file, here we
define the application API version.
And that's it.
The name of the application and the load
balancer here the kubernetes service
file takes the responsibility of exposing
our service to the public, right?
Where whenever a HTTP request
comes kubernetes load balancer
will take that and it will decide
which replica to be called, right?
If there is any issue with one of
the application, it automatically
goes to the second one.
Kubernetes like load balancer
will take care of that.
And the target port
number, we define it here.
And the Terraform script here
this is making that complete
infrastructure has code.
We define, instead of doing
the configuration every time,
DevOps engineers use this and the
developers write Terraform scripts
using Terraform command in it.
And once everything is
verified, they'll do apply.
Here we are defining
the source AWS module.
We have the cluster name, the
cluster version, and we define
the node groups here, right?
So what is the desired capacity,
max capacity, and min capacity?
At least one node, maximum three nodes,
and the like desired capacity is two.
So this here we are defined
whatever we wrote there we can
have the infrastructure as code.
Whenever is needed, we can run the
script and it will create all the infra.
This is nothing but infrastructure.
The final output of this demo is
like we are running a K8 cluster
with a load balancer and the final
output will have a response from
the Spring Boot microservice.
Has already.
Yeah.
So a spring, a simple springboard
microservice using docker.
We ize that and it is deployed in
a E Ks Cooper Andes cluster, and we
are exposing using the load balancer.
The final output is a very highly
scalable, and scalable very
available and scalable application.
Which is applicable, which is
accessed via public URL, right?
So here this architecture if you see the
Spring Boot microservice along with along
with the Docker K8 and cloud service,
this makes this architecture ensure
that application is resilient, scalable,
and portable access around the world.
All the cloud platforms.
So the conclusion is Java represents
a powerful synergy, right?
The application is made, the microservices
developed using Java, which is a
which is a powerful programming
language, which we discussed, and
this drives the digital transformation
across multiple industries, right?
You take Netflix, e commerce
applications like Amazon, eBay.
And many financial banking
organizations use this combination.
So this cloud computing offers significant
advantages, including the scalability,
cost efficiency, and operation agility.
This will enable most of the applications,
most of the organizations, right?
By leveraging AWS, Microsoft,
and Google Cloud, right?
So that's all I have.
Thank you guys.
All the best.
Bye bye.