Hi everyone.
So this is Derek from Broadcom.
So today we are going to talk about
the quantum resistant Kubernetes.
So how to secure the cloud native
infrastructure for the post quantum era.
So basically we are preparing
the distributor systems for the
quantum computing revolution.
So that will fundamentally
change how we approach the.
Cryptographic security and cloud native
enrollments, the quantum thread landscape.
So today, so the classical
cryptography protects our systems.
RSA and E-C-C-R-S-A-E-C remains
secure against traditional
computer computing attacks.
But now we, in this quantum era,
the quantum computers emerge with
sufficient powers to break the RSA
and ECC using shorts algorithm.
So what next?
So the post quantum era tradition,
traditional encryption becomes obsolete.
Organizations need quantum
resistant alternatives.
So how are you going to do that?
Let's see.
So first of all, let's analyze why
Kubernetes exposed Kubernetes security
is fundamentally built on public key
infrastructure, PKI and transport layer.
Security TLS.
So every critical communication path
relates on classical cryptography
that quantum computers will break.
Example, the A PA server, which clone
cluster state communication protected
by TLS advocate vulnerable to quantum
attacks and the pod to pod communication,
which is again a service mesh.
So the mutual TLS connections
between microservices rely
on RSA and ECC key exchanges.
Then the Ingres client traffic.
So the external traffic that enters
through the TLS terminated load balances
using quantum vulnerable certificates.
And the final is the registry cluster,
which contains the image pulls
and pushes authenticated through
classical cryptographic signatures.
So what's the impact on
cloud native security?
So when quantum computers break
PKI, they enter Foundation of
Kubernetes security collect.
The consequences extend far
beyond simple data breaches.
So what are those?
So it's basically, it is the
compromise, TLS expose secrets, fake
identities and vulnerable backups.
So what is compromised TLS
Man in the middle attacks
become trivial or encrypted.
Communication can be intercepted
and decrypted in real time.
And the exposed.
Secrets.
So what are those?
Is the database passwords?
API?
Keys and the service tokens
stored in Kubernetes.
Secrets become readable by the
attackers and the fake identities.
Malicious parts can impersonate
legitimate services.
Service identity verification
becomes impossible without
quantum safe signatures.
Then the vulnerable backups, historical
data and backup systems encrypted
with classical algorithm based.
Future decryption threats.
So Kubernetes without secure PKI
is like a bank without one dose.
Trust becomes impossible
to establish or maintain.
So now entering the post quantum
cryptography, PQC, the National Institute
of Standards and Technology, the NIST has
completed its post quantum cryptography
project providing standardized.
Algorithms resistant to quantum
attacks, so they are called the
ber de lithium hybrid cryptography.
So the key encapsulation mechanism for
the secure key based on the lattice
cryptography problems that remain
hard even for quantum computers.
Then the digital signature algorithm
providing authentication and non creation.
In the post quantum era, the transition
strategy, combining classical and
post quantum algorithms for backward
compatibility and enter in security.
So this standardization provides a clear
path forward making transition from
optimal to inevitable for organization
serious about long-term security.
So let's now see the PQC in Kubernetes.
The post quantum cryptography
must be itegrated at.
Every layer where Kubernetes
relates on classical encryption
and dig and digital signature.
So basically on the ingress controllers,
service mesh, the ETCD, the container
registries, so in the ingress controllers,
the TLS termination points where
external traffic enters the cluster.
So ETCD is the encryption at rest
and EAP communication for cluster
stage storage and the servicers.
It is the mutual TLS connections
between the micros and sidecar proxy
container registries, image signing, and
verification for supply chain security.
And now let's see how the
quantum safe ingress works.
So ingress controller serves as the
primary entry point for external
traffic, making them the most
critical component to secure in
the quantum resistant transition.
The client which initiate the support
hybrid TLS handshake with both
classical and post quantum ALS ingress.
The P replaces RSA and ECC while
maintaining backward compatibility,
the part which receive the
quantum safe, secured intricate
traffic from INGOs controller.
Implementation support is already
emerging in open SLPQ branches.
NY proxy and engineers.
Starting with ingress provides
immediate protection for the
most exposed attack surface.
So how hardening the
service mesh can happen.
The service meshes like HTO and link.
It relay heavily on mutual TLS
for part to part communication.
This makes them both critical and
challenging for post migration.
Step one.
It is the NY proxy integration.
So integrate pq enable crypto
libraries into NY side cars for
quantum safe MTLS connections.
Then the certificate management
update service certificate authorities
to issue hybrid certificate
supporting both algorithms.
Then the backward ensure hybrid
mode allows seamless communication
between upgraded and legacy
workloads during transition.
Then the performance monitoring.
Track latency and throughput impacts
as PQU algorithms have different
performance characteristics.
Securing mesh MTLS is critical because
it forms the foundation of part to
part trust in zero trust architectures.
Now the third place to secure it, so
it's the secrets and E-T-C-E-T-C-D
stores, all Kubernetes cluster
state, including sensitive secrets.
Protecting this data is essential, but
post quantum certificates introduce
new challenges to re challenge pq.
Certificates are significantly
larger than R-S-A-E-C-C impacting
E C's performance and replication.
KMS integration.
So leverage pq safe key management
services like Vault or a WS PQ km. Pilots
for external encrypt rotation strategy.
Implement automated rotation for.
For long lived secrets to
minimize exposure windows.
Now let's see, the key challenges
post cryptography adoption is
indeed just a simple algorithm,
swap or organism, face, significant
technical and operational huddle.
So it is 3.2 Yex handshake overhead.
And 10 x the certificate size
and 60% library maturity.
Now coming to the handshake overhead.
So performance penalty compared
to the classical algorithms doing
during tailless negotiation and the
certificate sizes are really larger.
Certificates, stress, ETCD,
storage and replication value.
And now coming to the library
maturity, estimated readiness of
production grade PQC limitation across.
So now the algorithm, key size and
handshake, time and compatibility.
So the RSA 2048, the key size is
two kb and handshake time is one x
and the compatibility is universal.
And the ECPP 2 56, key size is 0.5
kb handshake time 0.8 x, and the
compat universal compatibility.
And the 7, 6 8, the key says four kb.
Handshake time, 3.2 x and it's limited.
The challenge extends beyond technical
merits, polyglot, microservices,
enrollment, face inconsistent PQC
support across programming, language,
and frameworks, migration strategies.
Successful post quantum migration request.
Careful planning and phase implementation.
Organization must balance security
improvements into operational stability.
Phase one, hybrid crypto.
Implement dual algorithm handshakes
supporting both classical and post quantum
cryptography for maximum compatibility.
Phase two ingress first begin
with external facing ingress
controllers where quantum
resistance provides immediate value.
Phase three service,
miss extent to internal.
Service to service communication
through gradual proxy updates.
Phase four core infrastructure.
Secure ETCD and core
Kubernetes CP communication.
As the final step, always maintain
rollback options, ca Canada
deployments and feature flags,
or essential for managing pq.
Workload transition.
Safety Kubernetes operator approach.
Kubernetes operators provide the
ideal mechanism for managing post.
Quantum cryptography at scale
treating security policy as code.
Their custom resource definition define PQ
policies declaratively using Kubernetes.
Ensure PQ save certificate
requirements automatically.
Same charts.
Simplify PQ deployment with
templated configuration.
So here is the sample.
For your reference.
Now let's see the observability.
So monitoring cryptography health
becomes a core observability
requirement in post quantum enrollments.
Organizations need visibility into
algorithm adoption and performance
impacts, handshake algorithms in use.
So the track with DL handshake
use classical wishes.
Post Quantum as a hybrid versus the
algorithms across your infrastructure.
The PQ adoption rate monitors the
percentage of connections successfully
post quantum cryptography to
measure the migration process and
the performance metrics measure.
Ance increases error rates, and
throughput impacts from larger certificate
sizes and competition overhead.
You cannot secure what you can't see.
Monitoring Cryptography Health is
now core observability task for SRTs.
So let's see.
In some of the early adapter case
studies, financial service, such
organizations running on bks and GK
are pioneering post quantum Kubernetes
implementation, providing valuable lessons
for broader adaption, high frequency
trading, PQ MTLS implementation in
microsecond sensitive trading systems,
performance trade off, required,
careful algorithm selection and hardware
optimization, regulatory complaints.
Hybrid cryptography helps meet
emerging regulatory requirements
while maintaining compatibility
with existing systems and partners.
Let's slice and ice to the steps.
So first, test certificate
distribution at scale.
So large certificate sizes can
overall system distribution
mechanism in high no count clusters.
Second, expect performance trade off.
Budget for two to four x latency increases
during handshakes and plan capacity
accordingly, then the roadblock plans
are critical in case something happens.
Incompatibility issues can emerge
unexpectedly, always maintain
classical fallback options.
And now the road map and open source, the
post quantum transition is supported by
a growing ecosystem of standards, open
source projects and community initiative.
In 2024, NIST PQC started, finalized
early implementation in open and major
crypto libraries in 20 25, 20 27.
Production ready, PQ implementation.
Major cloud providers offer
PQ enabled services and the
future from 2028 to 20 20 30.
We are expecting to see
widespread adoption.
Classic algorithm deprecation in
favor of quantum safe alternatives.
The key projects are open quantum
safe, O-Q-S-C-N-C-F Security, SIG
Kubernetes Announcement Proposal.
So these are the three key projects.
Now, what is the call to action?
The post quantum era is
approaching faster than many.
Ians realize the time to
begin preparation is now.
While quantum computers remain
in development, so the inventory
dependencies, experimenting, staging,
adapt, hybrid crypto, so catalog
all your cryptographic dependencies
in your Kubernetes infrastructure.
Identify all say ECG, usage patterns
and certificate license, circuit,
experimenting, staging, set up test
environment in pq, enable ingress
controller and service measures, measure
performance impacts, and compatibility.
Adopt hybrid crypto.
Begin implementing hybrid
cryptography for new deployment.
This provide quantum assistance while
maintaining backward compatibility.
So the resources, so the NIST post
quantum cryptographic standard open
quantum safe project documentation,
CN CF Security SIG PQ working group,
Kubernetes PQ announcement proposal.
The future is quantum safe,
the cluster you run today.
Maybe vulnerable tomorrow.
So start small experiment with
post quantum cryptography and
prepare your infrastructure for
the quantum computing revolution.
Saying in, in cyber, in cybersecurity,
being late to adapt this in just
inefficient, it is catastrophic.
The post quantum transition is
not a question of if, but when.
Begin your quantum in Germany today.
Your future self will.
Thank you for the ForSight.
Thank you.
Thanks for watching my session.
Thanks a lot.