Hello everyone.
Welcome to the session on cloud
native hyper automation that's
transforming compliance and risk
management in financial services.
I'm Ma Swami.
I work as an architect
at Microsoft Corporation.
And I have worked with
financial services industries.
For several years now.
In this presentation, we will explore
how hyper automation powered by
AI and Kubernetes is fundamentally
transforming compliance and risk
intelligence across financial systems.
The financial services industry
faces mounting pressure to process
exponentially growing transaction
volumes while maintaining
rigorous compliance standards and.
Mitigating the emerging
risks in real time.
Traditional approaches to compliance and
risk management are no longer sufficient.
We'll examine how cloud native
architecture enables scalable,
resilient, and fully auditable workflows.
We'll look at certain use cases
like know your customer, KYC,
verification, fraud detection, and some
sophisticated credit risk modeling.
All of these use cases, as we will talk
further through the session, are supported
by machine learning models that can be
containerized, and we will talk about
how GI tops and certain methodologies
can help with these use cases.
Throughout this presentation,
I'll share key architecture,
design principles, implementation
strategies, real world lessons.
From having worked on building
adaptive regulation of your systems
that evolve seamlessly with rapidly
changing financial landscape.
Alright, let's dig in.
So the hyper motivation refers the
strategic convergence of artificial
intelligence, machine learning,
robotic process automation, and cloud
native technologies to transform.
Manual error prone enterprise
operations into these intelligent
self optimizing systems.
The transformation enables financial
institutions to process thousands
of compliance checks simultaneously.
It can also adapt to changing
regulatory requirements and.
Be able to generate the re
required reports in a matter of
couple of hours instead of months.
It can also help in maintaining
consistent policy enforcement
across global operations.
The core technologies that power
hyper automation are machine learning.
Which has these deep learning models
for pattern recognition, anomaly
detection, predictive analytics,
deployed as containerized services.
Now, these models continuously learn from
transactional data, identifying subtle
patterns and credit risk indicators that
traditional rule-based systems cannot
detect natural language processing.
Provides these large natural
language processing supported
by these large language models.
Help with say document analysis,
regulatory, text interpretation,
and automated report.
Generation NLP systems extract
critical information from unstructured
regulatory documents and generate
compliant reports in multiple languages.
RPA, which has these intelligent bots
handle routine compliance tasks, do data
validation and regulatory submissions.
These RPA systems work 24 by seven,
processing thousands of transactions
with perfect consistency while
lots of freeing up human analyst
for complex decision making.
Computer vision on the other hand,
helps with document verification,
biometric authentication, and
visual fraud detection capabilities.
Kubernetes serves as this
foundational orchestration layer
for all of these technologies to
come together and support hyper.
Automation Kubernetes is able to do that
as it is able to consistently scale and
provide secure systems for every component
from machine learning and inference
engines to workflow automation bots.
We'll talk about the architecture details
a little more as we discuss the use cases.
It's modern.
Financial institutions leverage Kubernetes
to orchestrate complex compliance
workflows, which are distributed across
these microservice architectures, the
containerized approach fundamentally
transforms how financial systems
operate, enabling elastic scaling during
peak regulatory reporting periods.
Seamless deployment and versioning of
machine learning models and fault tolerant
processing of hypersensitive financial
data that is geographically distributed.
A critical Kubernetes features enable.
Truly adaptive systems.
This horizontal pod autoscaling
dynamically adjusts the resources
based on the transactional value.
The service mesh technology
provides zero trust security between
microservices and ops workflows to.
That allows teams to deploy policy
changes across global infrastructure
in minutes rather than weeks.
But these capabilities all allow
financial institutions to build systems
that respond dynamically to changes in
the regulatory requirements or market
conditions while maintaining unwavering
compliance and operational resilience.
This architecture fund provides the
foundation for truly cloud native
financial operations where infrastructure
adapts automatically to business
needs while maintaining rigorous
security and compliance standards.
Now let's look at a couple of use cases.
The first use case that I've got
here is how KYC can be transformed
with multimodal authentication.
The multimodal biometric verification
combines facial recognition, document
authentication, and behavioral analysis
with containerized microservices.
Computer vision algorithms
powered by computer vision
or open CV and tensor flow.
Validate identity documents while
machine learning models assign,
assess the risk profiles in real time.
This approach uses biometric APIs
like say Azure face API for precise
identity matching, coupled with
behavioral analytic models that detect
anomalies in user interaction patterns.
Each verification T runs as independent
containerized microservice on Kubernetes,
enabling truly parallel processing of.
Identity verification steps.
So when a user uploads the identity
document and a selfie, for example,
for this picture, Kubernetes
orchestrates simultaneous document
verification or validation, and the
facial matching with the behavioral
scrolling, delivering a comprehensive.
Confidence core for risk assessment
in seconds rather than hours.
That dramatically reduces the customer
onboarding friction while exceeding
regulatory compliance standards.
The other use case that we have is
streaming analytics for fraud detection.
Now, real time fraud detection requires
processing millions of transactions per
second while identifying subtle patterns
that indicate fraudulent activity.
Streaming analytics,
leverages even driven.
Can, it's even driven architecture
and Kubernetes to create a resilient,
scalable fraud prevention system.
This architecture can process transactions
with latency measured in milliseconds,
enabling institutions to block fraudulent
transactions before they complete,
while minimizing false positives
that frustrate legitimate customers.
So what I've represented on screen is
just four different steps and where that
ingestion is being done by this event
driven architecture which are listening
to the signals and Kubernetes is leveraged
for the containerized implementations.
The models are helping detect the patterns
and alerts are the ones that help.
Financial systems, financial
services organizations
detect and manage the frauds.
Now, AI driven customer service
is another scenario, which you
must all be very familiar with.
Or at least anybody who has
tried contacting customer
service in the recent past.
So any powered customer service agents
deployed across Kubernetes clusters
can provide consistent compliance
responses while dynamically adapting
to the changing requirements.
These agents leverage natural language
understanding to resolve complex
financial queries without human
intervention, maintaining conversation
context across multiple interactions.
As an example, these can be built on
Azure OpenAI services and deployed
through Azure Kubernetes service.
These virtual agents
understand customer intent.
They can access account
information securely and provide
personalized financial guidance.
All this can be done while
maintaining strict compliance with
privacy and regulatory standards
in the financial services industry.
Alright, next one that we have here is
QAPs driven compliance automation, large
language model based compliance pipelines.
Deployed through GitHub's workflows
ensure consistent, auditable regulatory
processes across all of the environments.
Essentially, infrastructure as a
code principle can extend beyond
the traditional DevOps to compliance
rules themselves, enabling version
controlled regulatory logic, and
fully automated policy updates.
Today most financial and
regulatory enterprises struggle
with fragmented manual compliance
processes that creates significant
operational land operational risk.
And these compliance rules are
often managed in spreadsheets,
word documents, and siloed systems.
Making it nearly impossible
to ensure version control,
consistency, or even traceability
across streams and geographies.
So in the traditional systems.
When regulatory frameworks change,
updates to policies or workflows are
applied manually by different teams
leading to implementation deals that are
measured in typically months to years.
Human errors in policy interpretation
and dangerous gaps in audit
coverage are not uncommon.
These.
There's also extremely limited visibility
for the compliance teams that they're
unable to easily verify whether the
applied systems are fully aligned and the
reg with the latest regulatory standards.
Now, that's where GitHubs can help.
It can.
Draft dramatically reduce the operational
risk because everything is traceable
and auditable With compliance updates
deployed in hours instead of weeks, it
can completely eliminate the drift between
environments and automated validation
that all of the systems comply with the.
Current regulations, it simplifies
certification of the systems within
the financial services industry.
Credit risk sorry about the typo.
It's not revolution, but evolution
mission learning algorithms.
Analyze vast data sets include including
comprehensive transaction history,
behavioral spending patterns credit bureau
data and external risk factors to generate
sophisticated, multi-dimensional credit
scores that far exceed the predictive
power of traditional FIO based models.
Containerized model serving architecture
enables sophisticated AB testing of
risk models in production environments
that allows continuous improvement
of credit positioning, accuracy.
Models are deployed.
Models can be deployed as independent
microservices, enabling real time
scoring of loan applications while
maintaining strict regulatory compliance
and extensibility requirements.
Advanced techniques like gradient
boosting natural neural networks and
ensemble methods identify complex
linear relationships in credit data.
They can improve default default
predict prediction accuracy.
Now one thing to bear in mind when
thinking about credit risk evaluation
using these technologies is the
potential bias in these models
it's a significant challenge that.
Models may unintentionally favor or
disadvantage a loan applicant based on
the factors that are correlated with
protected characteristics such as gender,
race, geography, socioeconomic status.
For example, this often occurs when
the training data reflects historical
lending patterns that embody the past
discrimination rather than objective
financial behavior or creditworthiness.
This comprehensive approach of detecting
a bias, having explainable ai, knowing
which models are used and being cognizant
of the models that are being selected,
and continuous monitoring of what these
models are resulting or showing the
results will help in reducing the bias.
Reducing the bias is essentially
important to ensure fairness while
also ensuring that you are able
to assess the risk accurately.
It is also important to be able to
explain how a risk is determined to
be compliant with regulations and
ensure transparency and accountability.
Looking at some of the implementation
strategy and best practices.
Firstly I would suggest looking at high
impact use cases, these high impact use
cases, for example, say KYC verification,
which is which is very much required in
financial services industry, but it's also
one of the critical processes that impact.
The customer of the financial
services industry in addition to
the operations teams internally.
So essentially, these high impact
use cases will help showcase a return
on investment that will that'll
help the firm adopt these, latest
technologies that can help them
become one of these frontier firms.
The second best practice is to firstly
build the cloud native foundation
that is required to support these
forward looking technologies.
Kubernetes infrastructure, for example
with proper security controls and
monitoring and alerting can can help.
We saw all of these core technologies
that power hyper automation.
The third one is to make sure
these changes are gradual and
not happening all at once.
Using cannery deployments, which is
essentially some, a type of blue-green
deployment to reduce their risk involved
in, in rolling out these technologies or
also consider using AB testing framework
to validate what these machine learning
models are how these machine learning
models are performing in production and
how you could reduce risk if required.
The last one I have on screen is to
ensure that there is regulatory alignment.
This is most important, as you all know,
within financial services industry.
All of the systems that are used.
It is highly recommended to maintain
comprehensive audit trails and ensure
that there is explainable AI capability
and automated compliance validation
built directly into the architecture.
So these considerations should
be taken right at the beginning
of your implementations, right
when you're designing the
system, not as an afterthought.
And successfully implementing hyper
automation requires these strategic
phased approaches that balances
innovation and operational stability
alongside the regulatory compliance.
Continuing with some of these best
practices, technical risk mitigation
is, can be achieved using multi-region
deployment for your business continuity
and disaster recovery capabilities.
And monitor your models and retrain the
pipelines to maintain model accuracy,
ensure that are circuit breakers built
in to have fail safe mechanisms for the
ML or machine learning service failures.
We've talked about reducing bias,
and that's a very important factor.
Compliance considerations, explainable
ai, privacy, preserving machine
learning, immutable audit logs
that cannot be altered essentially,
and data quality monitoring.
These are some of the factors that
we do wanna make sure are taken into
consideration, followed through the
implementation to ensure excellence.
They essentially create technically
robust and compliant system when you're
evolving in ensure the sustainability
of these hyper automation initiatives.
Wrapping up with the future
of hyper automated finance.
Finance hyper automation represents
a fundamental paradigm shift from
reactive manual compliance processes
to proactive, intelligent risk
systems By, and you achieve this like
we've talked about by strategically
combining the AI capabilities with
cloud native architecture patterns.
Financials institutions can build
truly adaptive systems that evolve
seamlessly with regulatory changes while
maintaining exceptional operational
efficiency and customer experience.
The convergence of machine learning,
containerization and automation
technologies creates unprecedented
opportunities for financial
innovation organizations that.
Successfully implement these
comprehensive strategies will gain
substantial competitive advantages
through dramatically reduced operational
costs, significantly improved
customer experiences in enhanced
regulatory compliance posture, and
the ability to respond to market
changes with speed and accuracy.
And to wrap it up.
I would like to say that the
future belongs to institutions
that embrace transformation.
Building systems that are not
just automated, but are truly
intelligent and adaptive.
Thank you for your time.
I appreciate you
listening to this session.