Good morning.
Good evening, everyone.
Thanks for joining this
Conative event today.
My name is Chara.
I'm a technical leader at Cisco.
Today I'll be talking about
architecting CM resilience.
How technical solution architects enables
scalable, secure, KUBER native system.
So let's start as enterprise continues
to evolve their CRM or customer
relationship management platforms,
the demand for resilient, scalable,
and secure s has never been greater.
So technical solution architects are,
we call it as TSA, simply play a pivotal
role in bridging strategy and execution.
Over the course of the session, we
will explore how the leadership shapes
modern CRM transformations as inda.
Here is what we'll cover today.
First we will, looking the
evolution of the SA role and
why it becomes so critical.
Next, we'll explore the business impact
of Kubernetes native CRM architectures.
Then we'll dive into architectural
frameworks and principles
that drives resilience.
Finally, I'll share implementation
strategies, challenges that we face,
and the roadmap for the transformation.
Let's begin with the
evolving CRM landscape.
So the CRM landscape.
The CRM market is undergoing
a master shift projected to
reach over 106 billions by 2028.
Most of the solutions are now cloud
native and the Kubernetes become
the default authorization layer.
So our nations are moving away from
monolithic platform towards containerized
environments, which demands strategy
architecture to ensure performance,
resilience, and scalability.
So this is exactly where technical
solution architect steps in
the strategic command post
TSS acts as a strategy command
force for CRM modernization.
They serve as the business translators,
ensuring the technical design
aligns with organizational goals.
Most importantly, they are the
visionaries and designing a
scalable Kubernetes native system.
They manage technical depth.
Ensuring today's solution don't
becomes tomorrow's bottleneck.
And most importantly, they are
transformation leaders guiding our
nation through complex adoption journeys.
Architecture principle.
Here are few major architecture
principles at architecture level.
Resilience comes from the
code design principles.
Microservices, architecture
ensure flexibility, declarative
configuration brings consistency.
And our state full service management
address, CRM, data Persistence, API first,
design and integration and zero trust.
Security model protects
the system end to end.
So these foundational elements are
what makes Bernet native CRM truly
enterprise ready system complexity,
how TSA reduces system complexity.
TSS are just not architects.
They are simplifiers to be shot.
They reduce the complexity by
identifying the source of technical
depth, designing the streamlined
architecture, using a modular
approach for scaling and establishing
observability for proactive management.
This is how CRM platform stay
high when a wide NE block.
So what are the benefits of doing that?
Once these principles are applied,
the business benefits are very clear.
Foster delivery cycles through
automation, improved reliability,
that's more important with
the self-healing capabilities.
Dynamic scalability to meet the
fluctuating demands are where an
error of asylum these benefits are why
Kubernetes is reshaping the CRM landscape.
Economic impact.
Let's talk about economic impact.
According to the Forester, Kubernetes,
CRM architectures can generate millions
in cost savings over three year horizon.
They also reduce downtime significantly
and boost development or developer
perpetuity and lower infrastructure cost.
So this is just not a technical upgrade.
It is a business value
accelerator for sure.
So let's talk about
leadership practice here.
So before TSA involvement, many
or nations face monolithic CRMs,
manual deployments, inconsistent
environments, and security gaps.
After TSA LED transformation, the
picture changes dramatically here.
So microservice based CRM on Kubernetes
and automated CSCD pipelines,
security embedded by design and full
observability, the shift illustrate the
transformative power of DSA leadership.
Okay, metrics for CRMs.
Architecture success is just about design.
It's about measuring the impact.
We focus on challenge, change, value rate,
and meantime to recovery, deployment,
frequency, and lead time for changes.
When these metrics improve, we know
the architecture is truly resilient.
Security considerations.
No CRM is complete
without robust security.
That means strong identity
and access management.
Secure secret management.
Enforcing the network policies
for microservice communication and
continuous container security scanning.
This measures ensure that resilient also
means security implementation roadmap.
So the roadmap for
transformation has five stages.
Assessment.
Understand the current pain
points in your organization.
Design, create the Kubernetes native
blueprint, how you want to approach pilot,
prove out of core functionality, nothing
but you're making some kind of A POC.
Make sure you are achieving
what you really want to scale.
Deployment, migrate progressively
and continuous optimization.
Adapt to our business evaluation.
This faced approach balances
speed with stability challenges.
I believe a better secure product
comes with a lot of challenges.
So challenges exist everywhere
and here as well, like stateful,
workload management and latency
integration, database performances
and multi-tenant complexities.
But TSS mitigates these
with proven strategies.
We'll use stateful sets or caching.
Service MIS adoption
and namespace isolation.
So what's the final result?
A practical pathway
through technical huddles.
Key takeaways to summarize my
session today here TSS are strategy
leaders, not just technical enablers.
Architectural framework matters.
They simplify complexity
and accelerate delivery.
And most importantly, Kubernetes
NA CRM unlocks real business value
through efficiency and resilience.
So what can you do after today's session?
Next up that I suggest evaluate
your current CRM architecture.
Consider Kubernetes expectation
for resilience, and invest in
arbitrator ship to guide your journey.
So finally, thank you.
Thank you all for joining the session.
Once again, a big thank you to Con
42 for providing this opportunity.
I hope it has given insight.
Into how TSA shape CRM
resilience in Kubernetes era.
I would be happy to answer any questions
or discuss any specific scenarios
relevant to your organizations.
Thank you all.