Hello, everyone.
My name is Abhinav Chunchu.
I've been working as a software
engineer from past 10 years.
Currently, I'm working as a senior
software engineer in Lowe's.
Today, I'm presenting on cloud
native and Golang's power in the
Kubernetes orchestrated architecture.
In this presentation, we'll be going
through the rise of cloud native
development, why Kubernetes, the role of
Golang in Kubernetes, Go in containerized
environments, data driven insights, Go in
Kubernetes development, Go's concurrency
model for scalable systems, real world
applications of Go in Kubernetes,
and the future of Go on Kubernetes.
So the rise of cloud native development.
cloud native development leverages,
cloud computing to allow applications
to be developed, deployed,
and managed at a large scale.
Thank you.
Kubernetes plays a crucial role
in the stabilization, powering
85 percent of containerized
production workloads globally.
These features, like portability,
scalability, automation, make it backbone
of the cloud native architectures.
Golang has become a key language for cloud
native systems because of its, Efficiency
in handling concurrency and low resource
usage crucial for the cloud environments.
Why Kubernetes?
Kubernetes is highly recommended
for its ability to automatically
manage containerized applications.
Features such as self healing,
auto scaling, rolling updates and
rollback make it ideal for the
handling cloud native demands.
Kubernetes is designed to manage billions
of requests per day, making it scalable
and reliable for high demand applications.
the role of Golang in Kubernetes.
Kubernetes itself is built on Go.
This emphasizes the Go's importance in
orchestration cloud native environments.
Go's lightweight, compiled nature ensures
that applications built in Go are quick
to deploy and have minimum startup time.
These are essential for the
containerized microservices.
its concurrency model like Goroutines,
make the Kubernetes to efficiently
scale, manage thousands of microservices
with minimum resource consumption.
The currently services like in Java
or Spring Boot or other, PySpark,
other features from the other
frameworks are very heavy loaded
and heavy duty, applications where
they have the more startup time and
scaling those high microservices
is much harder compared to the Go.
Go small binaries.
and efficient resource management
make it ideal for the containerized
environments where fast scaling
and minimal overhead are required.
And Go excels in networking, file
input, output and memory intensive
tasks with these environments
enhancing the performance.
And Go's native concurrency enables
it to outperform many other languages
in multi container setups where tasks
need to be executed in parallel.
Data driven insights.
Go in Kubernetes deployments.
70 percent of Kubernetes controllers
and operators are built in Go, as shown
by the CSN of Kubernetes Survey 2023.
Companies using Go for
Kubernetes native tools report
better operational efficiency,
automation and easier scalability.
Organizations prefer Go for developing
a Kubernetes native tools because
it reduces the development time
while ensuring high performance.
Go's concurrency model
for the scalable systems.
Go's lightweight Go routines, which
used around 2 KB of memory, enable
highly scalable distributed systems.
Channels in Go ensure safe
communication between Go routines.
Avoiding the data races
distributed in Kubernetes setup.
Allowing the system to handle
high concurrency without
excessive resource usage.
Data driven insights.
Oh, we already went through this.
Okay.
Go's concurrency model for the, oh, sorry.
Real world applications
of Go in Kubernetes.
Case studies, the several case
studies highlights the Go's
impact in real world scenarios.
Google used Go based controllers, leading
to 30 percent improvement in scaling time.
PayPal used Go based
operators to maintain 99.
99 percent uptime, showcasing the
reliability and performance benefits.
The future of Go and Kubernetes With
continuous improvements, Go is expected
to enhance Kubernetes abilities, to
maintain, manage the increasing complex
workloads, including the edge computing
and the multi cluster management.
The simplicity, speed, and
concurrency model of Go are likely
to play a major role in the next
phase of cloud native development.
Ensuring Kubernetes remain at the
forefront of cloud architecture.
Integration with the future Kubernetes
projects like kube edge, Kubernetes
cluster API will expand the Kubernetes
functionality in edge computing
and multi cluster management.
Conclusion Finally, I would like
to conclude the combination of
Go and Kubernetes is a key to
unlock a cloud native excellence.
Go's performance, scalability,
lightweight nature make it ideal
for the modern cloud native systems.
Kubernetes in turn leverage the
Go strength to efficiently manage,
containerize the applications,
ensuring the resilience and scalability
in large scale cloud computers.
Thank you.