Hello everyone.
I'm Sai Deepak.
I'm a staff software engineer at Google.
I lead the Maps quality team, where we
deal with a wide range of challenges
related to auction algorithms modeling
advertiser conversion quality,
and the overall quality of ads.
I did my bachelor's at Indian
Initiative of Technology and after
graduation I started working at Google.
I initially worked on the business
software and then for a year and a half.
And then from then onwards, I have
started I've worked on the map sets.
Today I'm excited to talk to
you about leveraging artificial
intelligence for medical cost,
transparency, and consumer empowerment.
I think this is a topic I'm deeply
passionate about, as I believe
technology can play a transformative
role in making healthcare more
affordable and accessible to everyone.
And I'm pretty sure everyone in
their life, Had to go to a doctor,
had had a medical emergency, had
to had to look up costs for either
a procedure or or a medication.
And this is actually a pretty big issue
in United States and even in other other
parts of the world, where people can
get pretty big surprises on the cost.
In this in this in this in this
article we have explored like how we
can use artificial intelligence and
how we can try to resolve this resolve
the issue of consumer awareness.
Yeah, let's face it.
The U.
S.
healthcare system is extremely
complex and often opaque.
It's it's whole working is not even
understood like by the doctors and
certainly not by the patients or
medical care providers or anyone.
The patients frequently find themselves
in the dark when it comes to when it
comes to understanding medical procedures
and the cost of medical procedures.
This lack of transparency often leads
to a significant financial strain
for millions of Americans, but also
results in delayed or avoided care.
And it, it the the delayed or avoided
care can lead to making the issue even
worse and driving up the long term costs.
For example, one of my friends had when
he was studying, like one of my friends
had an injury in his leg, but because
he was he, because he did not have a
good medical insurance at this time,
at the time he delayed the care till
till he graduated and until he was able
to get a job, but that delayed led to
exacerbation of the injury to his leg.
And ultimately ultimately long term long
term issues and the long term costs.
As a professional deeply involved in
the intersection of the technology
and healthcare, I'm hoping to
use cutting edge innovations to
solve these critical challenges.
Today I'm excited to announce like a AI
driven platform that has a potential to
revolutionize the healthcare affordability
and transparency by empowering customers
with much more accurate and much
more personalized cost information.
This platform uses the the newest AI
techniques such as like artificial
intelligence, ability to process
like large amount of textual data.
And integrating them with analytics
and it it changes how patient interacts
with the healthcare system and it
can improve the quality of the the
care and make the information more
accessible and affordable for all.
There are various problems in
the problems in the healthcare
health healthcare transparency.
One is the high and another is
the unpredictability of the cost.
Basically the pricing is very opaque.
Sometimes the insurance
covers it, sometimes it don't.
Like sometimes one one
provider charges one one price.
Sometimes another provider
charges another price.
Sometimes the prices can change
with zip code and the cities
leading to unexpectedly very high
medical bills, lack of transparency.
Consumers don't have a clear
way or dashboard or a software.
To understand like the clear and
accurate cost for the medical procedures.
This leads to a significant number
of financial stress and poor decision
making in the absence of like complete
accurate picture to the users.
Financial strain the burden of the medical
costs like often leads to delaying or
completely avoiding the care together.
And we have various studies which
shows that for example, like having
regular care or the or the yearly
checkups like can actually reduce
like the the much the long term costs.
Much more significantly inefficiencies.
The inefficiencies in the market
contributes to like inflated prices and
reduce competition among providers One
of the biggest cause for this is just
the lack of transparency in this area
where where very few people have access
to the prices unlike in other systems,
for example If you want to buy clothes or
if you want to buy buy any electronics,
you can just simply go to amazon.
com or google.
com or any other, like any
other aggregator websites.
And you can simply look up like the
properties of all the electronics goods.
What is the price?
What is how much does it
take to deliver everything?
Everything is everything is pretty
pretty well exposed to the users.
So they can take all this information
and make the decision for themselves.
However, in healthcare, like
everything's very opaque.
All this information is hidden
away and known to very few people.
Comparison difficulties.
Obviously this lack of transparency
makes it very challenging to compare
the costs and the quality across
different healthcare providers,
limiting their ability to make
an informed, educated choice.
Solution.
Our AI driven platform has
three has has three pillars.
One is the AI power transparency.
So our platform uses newest LLMs and
machine learning to deliver accurate
personalized medical cost estimates.
We have integrated data from
multiple sources, including hospital
charge masters, insurance claims,
and user reported costs to create
a comprehensive pricing database.
This way we have used LLMs to
basically like ingest the data
and pass the data and Or put the
data in a much more formatted way.
And we use this we can then use this
use this data and run analytics and give
personalized information to the user.
Real time estimates.
The system provides like real time, like
personalized cost estimates within seconds
using all the data that we have extracted.
And it is tailored to individual specific
situation, individual's area, and
the insurance the coverage they have.
How it works.
We have an A Web powered
cost estimation process.
So first we collected the data
from various aggregators, either
hospitals or the insurance
claims, or the user reported.
A user can also themselves
report cost of the cost, and
using all these various sources,
pretty robust pricing database.
And then we with respect to the machine
learning algorithms, we have like advanced
machine learning algorithms where it takes
all this data and we train models on it,
with various features such as regional
variations, like provider specific
pricing, user specific insurance coverage,
and various various other other signals
to train a model to to understand like the
the, to understand the landscape of the
pricing real time estimation and based on
the model we have trained, we can provide
like a cost estimate for for the user with
based on based on their own issues, their
own geographic area, their own insurance
provider and validation the real time
data validation techniques ensures that
the estimates are correct and accurate.
Okay.
And the user can themselves give feedback
to us and help us in iterating and
improving the the data output we provide.
Some of the key features of the platform
are the personalized cost estimation.
Giving the personalized cost estimation
with with a variance of plus or
minus 50 percent for the common
procedures and plus or minus 30
percent for the complex procedures.
This allows the user to plan for their
healthcare expenses more effectively.
Even though this this pan might seem
pretty big, this is actually much,
much better than the current blind
the current the current Peace out.
The current complete
lack of data that exists.
This at least like users this at least
gives an estimate to the to the users.
And the huge thing is provider comparison.
It enables users to compare like
prices and the, the quality ratings
across multiple healthcare providers.
This significantly increases the
competition among them and obviously
like people can take the prices and the
quality in order to make that decision to
whether to go to the healthcare providers.
AI provides negotiation support.
It uses assist users in negotiating lower
bills creating creating letters, attaching
information, attaching the billing data,
attaching the comparison data, and the
users can leverage to to identify the
areas where the cost can be reduced.
On average some users saw 18 percent,
more than 18 percent reduction in
their medical bills by using these
the generated support information.
And we have to we obviously want to
make sure that there is a fairness and
transparency in the cost estimation.
We have a significant number of
mechanisms in place to mitigate bias
and ensures that all the reasons all
the users receive equitable treatment
and we don't use any signals which can
distinguish between for example way
where we distinguish between two users.
This in this slide, we shared
the impact and results from the
impact and results from this.
And we have seen significant cost
reduction for the users who have
used the negotiation support feature.
They saw 18 percent reduction
in the medical bills and
significantly decrease low out of
lower out of market expectancies.
You also see an increase
in improved access to care.
Now that like users have like an
estimation of like how much How much
it will actually cause, they can do a
better budgeting of the finances and
and actually and actually use, and
actually try to get the cost sorry try
to get get the care and budget for it.
And users are now more confident in their
ability to afford the necessary treatment.
20 percent reduction in the
avoided or delayed care.
This this this also obviously led
to like more better health outcomes.
Reducing these financial barriers people's
health outcomes have improved, they're
able to save more costs in the longterm.
They're able to have a more healthier,
happier, and healthier life.
And we hope that this will have a
significant impact in the market.
This has the potential to disrupt the
healthcare by increasing the competition
among the providers, driving down the
overall healthcare costs improving the
transparency in this area, reducing the
anxiety that is faced by everyday people.
There are significant challenges while
we were doing the implementation of this.
One, I don't think this would
have been possible without the
breakthrough technologies that have
come in the last two and three years.
For example, the context for
example, analyzing the textual data.
And generating more structured output from
the textual data would have an extremely
hard without the use of without how good
the large language models are now, which
can pass through hundreds of pages of
the document and output the structured
data that we are accurately asking for.
With respect to the data and the privacy
we use advanced encryption techniques and
secure computation to product user data.
Differential privacy measures ensure
that individual data points cannot
be traced to the specific users.
In fact, we don't even
keep any individual data.
as soon as we train the
data is just thrown away.
With respect to the data accuracy,
we use a federated learning.
It allows the platform to
continuously improve this algorithm
without compromising users privacy
by mainly not taking any user
use of personalization signals.
And the real time data validation
ensures that the estimates are
based on the more current and more
accurate information available.
So to do this, like our models train
trains continuously on on the latest
data on the latest data points.
And we give we we force the model
to give like lower and lower, lower
weightages to the to the older data.
So that like for example,
the prices are based on like
the 2023 and 20, for example.
The cost estimates for 2024 are
based on 2023 and 2024 data,
not based on the two 2016 data.
The model like automatically uses the
old data for generalization, but it
uses the more new data for giving more
accurate data points to the users.
I think ethical AI, we have a
robust ethical AI framework in
place to ensure the fairness and
transparency in cost estimation.
We don't take any we don't take any
users identifying input features or try
to differentiate between two people.
The platform actively works to
mitigate the bias and ensure
equitable treatment for the all users.
This, we mainly do this by not
having any users any user personal
IIS identifiers and treating like
two people with the same with the
same condition and in the same way.
Okay.
Here I want to go a bit into
the future and enhancements.
So we wanted we wanted we
have a few other ideas for the
future that we would like to do.
We want to integrate with the
electronic health records.
This way we can provide like
a more comprehensive view
of the patient outcomes.
And the patient costs, it allows for the
personalized long term financial planning.
This data can be integrated into
the other the financial tools.
And this can this can let people, for
example, plan their retirement, plan the
costs that will plan the general costs
that they will have in the long term.
And and also more help them in
the saving for the long term
for the health health costs.
We want to have predictive
health spending models.
This this platform will develop
predictive models to help users anticipate
future health care costs based on
the medical industry and lifestyle.
This will lead to enabling better
budgeting and the financial planning.
For example, let's say
someone has diabetes.
This this model can use that information
to know for example, what is the
cost on average they will be using
they will be seeing one year from
now, five years from now, 10 years
from now, and during the retirement.
What kind of what is the rough estimate
of the medical cost they they might see?
What, how much is the, how much is how
much money they should save right now?
And it may, it can even help give
suggestions to to reduce and reduce
the amount of money that is needed.
Feature expansion currently the
ongoing development is focusing
on expanding platform capabilities
to cover more complex processes
and broader datasets, ensuring it
remains relevant and useful across a
wide range of healthcare scenarios.
With respect to the market opportunity,
we see a significant the potential
in the market and the growth.
Obviously, this is like a, this is like
a multi trillion dollar multi trillion
dollar area where even if we can make like
a 1 percent dent, we'll be very happy.
And that'll be a significant impact
on both in terms of the costs saved in
terms of the anxiety saved by the by
the users and overall improvement in
the health and happiness of the users.
There is significant growing demand as
the healthcare cost continue to rise
above inflation, there is significant
demand for tools that can provide
like cost, transparency and help and
consumers to make informed decisions.
This data will help everyone
like this, will help consumers
as will help businesses.
This will help everyone to make
a more informed decision markets.
As the market for AI driven
healthcare solutions is
projected to grow significantly.
Especially with the new technologies such
as large language models, which which
can which can understand like the medical
information much better, which can which
can transcribe the medical information and
generate like more actionable information.
So there are substantial opportunities
for these platforms to focus on the cost
transparency and consumer empowerment.
Consumer competitive landscape
we are acknowledging that our
platform, it's it's not unique.
It stands out in the crowded market due to
its unique combination of the personalized
cost estimate, provided compassion
and AI powered negotiation support.
However, we do want to do well and
give better service to the users so
that this can help them in their life.
With respect to the partnership, we
would like to have forged a strategic
partnership with healthcare providers,
insurers, technology companies, and also
to create new streams and expanded reach.
To conclude the cost of
healthcare has has has risen
significantly like about inflation.
And this is one of the significant
significant financial financial
issue that people people face with.
And this is one of the significant
things that people fail to account for
account for their in, in their life.
And this leads to a significant number of
anxiety significant number of significant
amount of impact in their life in the,
during financial and budgeting and so on.
There is a significant need for
the transparency and consumer
empowerment because this this
area is extremely opaque.
Extremely unknown and extremely complex
and bureaucratic, unlike many of the
sectors, for example, like financial
sector consumer and electronic sector
services sector, where there's a
significant number of you can just go and
look up online to get all the information.
This is extremely extremely
opaque and this is screaming for
more transparency and openness.
The AI driven platform addresses
these pressing issues by
providing users with the accurate
personalized medical cost estimate.
And it helps them to make informed
decisions about their health care.
And our project also would not have been
possible without the The large language
models that have come in the last two
and, two and a half to three years.
Because most of the, most of our
work involves transcribing like
large amount of textual information.
With which, which also includes the
cost of specific procedures, the
cost of pharmaceuticals, and so on.
This would not have been possible
to do with with the previous with
the previous textual understanding.
But with the new LLMs, such as with the
new the new, with the new advanced LLMs
this becomes much, much more easier.
We also integrate the data
from the diverse sources,
including charge hospital,
charge masters, insurance claims.
And also we also let the users
themselves report the cost and our
platform creates like a comprehensive
pricing database, which offers real time
insights into all these medical expenses.
This level of transparency is designed
to elevate the financial stress that so
many Americans face when navigating the
complexity of the healthcare system.
We hope that with this project we make
we make impact and let let consumers
understand the cost of the healthcare cost
of the procedures, cost of the general
cost that they are paying and make.
more informed decisions in their life.
Feel free to let me feel free to
contact me if you have any further
questions and thank you for your time.