Hello everyone.
I'm Satish Pangan.
I'm working as a platform administrator
in Zurich North America, USA.
I have overall of 15 years of
experience in data platform engineering
with a specialization in enterprise
data integration on automation.
Today I'm going to present the topic,
a driven data integration at scale,
real time compliant, and cloud native.
This topic, A driven data integration,
transforms enterprise data workflow
across hybrid cloud environments
through this AEA power engine to
perform orchestration and automation.
That's,
let's see.
The evolution of cloud native data
architecture and the challenges, the
traditional method, which we face now.
So as the legacy systems struggle
with the real time operations, manual
processes create several bottlenecks.
And on top of it, the compliance
requirements add complexity to
the existing data and workflows,
which challenging the process time.
Kubernetes reshapes the
cloud NATO architecture.
Which having a, which mounting
pressure to modernize their data.
So this shift to containerized
environments demands a new
approaches to data orchestration,
governance, and scalability.
The traditional integration
platforms cannot scale and
provide the required output.
Let me introduce Claire, the A engine
behind intelligence data management.
So Claire is provided by the
Informatica service provider, which
represents the next generation of
data integration intelligence, which
powers the intelligence data management
cloud IDMC, which is a cloud native
solution provided by Informatica.
This sophisticated platform transforms
how enterprise approaches data
workflows across hybrid environments,
including AWS Azure, Google Cloud,
and on-premises infrastructure.
The SCL a driven approach fundamentally
changes the data integration, which
instead of reactive maintenance
to a proactive optimization and
intelligent automations that add
access to the business request.
Now let's see how multi-cloud
integration can be seamlessly
integrated with the cloud.
Our supports AWS Amazon Web Service
of Azure on this, which supports
native integrations with AWS
services, including S3 relational
databases, Redshift and Lambda.
And it also leverages AWS Native
Security and Compliance Framework
while maintaining data governance
acceler Azure entire cloud stack.
So coming to Microsoft Azure, the IT
integrates with Azure Data Factory for
all the integration needs and Azure
Data Lake storage for all the storage
needs and synapsis for analytics.
WS.
It also supports Azure SQL database
and it also seamlessly connects with
the existing Microsoft ecosystem
while extending capabilities
through a powered automations.
Now let's talk about the on-premises ra.
So it builds the legacy between the
on-premises and the cloud, modern
cloud native infrastructure, and it
provides real time synchronization.
It also seamlessly integrated our data
all across the hybrid environments.
Now about the data integration on the
task automation, revolutionize traditional
data integration by automating the
most time consuming and error pro task
through machine learning algorithms.
Pattern recognition.
The platform identifies optimal
integration path, such as the
transformation logic, automatic and
automatically generates mapping and
workflow recommendations so that
it'll be easy for the developers to
see where they need to look into the
logic, transformation or mappings.
This intelligent automation extends
beyond simple task execution.
To include, prevent predictive
maintenance, anomaly detection, and
self-healing data pipelines that adapts
to ever changing business requirements,
and also without a manual inter.
Metadata discovery and
data classification.
So Class A power metadata discovery
engine automatically scans and
classifies data across all your entire
ecosystem, enterprise ecosystem.
Using that ones the patent
recognition, semantic analysis.
It identifies sensitive data
personally, personal information
like PIA, and regulate.
Content with unprecedented present.
The system continuously
inter learns from the user.
Feedback through a continuous monitoring
and regulate updates, ensuring that
classification accuracy improves over time
while adapting to the new data types and
sources as they imagine your organization.
Now let's see how the
real-time integration and
intelligent routing takes place.
So when stream data ingestion the
process, it process high velocity data
streams from several iot, internet
of things, devices, applications, and
external APAs with minimal latency
and to intelligent parts selection.
AI algorithm automatically
selects optimal route parts
based on the network condition,
data sensitivity and performance
requirement while enting the data.
It also takes the real time
decision making, so enabling instant
insights and rapid response to
the changing business conditions
through continuous data processing.
Let's see how these algorithms self-learn
and performs the anomaly detection.
Claire has a self-learning capabilities
continuously monitor data quality
patterns, identify any deviations before
any of the downstream is getting impacted.
Are the processes getting impacted?
The system builds comprehensive baselines
of normal data behavior and uses
statistical models to flag any potential
issues when anomalies are detected.
The A engine not only alerts
administrator, but also statist
the character actions based on the
historical resolution patterns.
As I mentioned earlier,
it has a continuous.
Monitoring and pattern
identification methods.
So it keeps, it is very easy to
check the historical resolution.
This proactive approach to data
quality ensures consistent, reliable
data across all integration points.
Now, let's see how Kubernetes
native orchestration for
containerized data services.
So container orchestration native.
Kubernetes integrations enables
automatic scaling, loading, BA load
balancing, and resource optimization
for data processing workloads.
So when considering the data processing
workloads, it performs like PO level
scaling based on the data volume, and it
allocates the resources and optimizes it.
And if there is any there of failures it
performs the failure recovery automation.
And when it comes to micro
microservices architecture.
So the data services that can be
independently deployed, scaled and
maintained within container services
can be performed with service mesh
integration, a PA gateway management
and secure breaker patterns.
And it also has a cloud NATO
security integrated security controls
that leverage Kubernetes native
features for comprehensive data
protection, like network policies
and segmentation secret management.
It also supports a
role-based access control.
Now let's see how the A engine
dynamic auto optimizes the
workload and cost management, the
predictive resource allocations.
So Clare has a predictive algorithm
which analyzes the torical usage
patterns, seasonal trends, and
business cycles to optimizes
resource allocation automatically,
the system anticipates demands.
Spikes and scales
infrastructure proactively.
This intelligent approach to
workload management ensures optimal
performance during peak load, while
minimizes the cost during when
there is less much of a demand.
Through it, it'll auto scale and
de provisioning the resources.
Now, compliance automation for regulated
industries in highly regulated industries.
Claire automates the complex processes
of governance, policy enforcement,
and audit trial generation.
The platform maintains comprehensive
lineage tracking automatically generates
compliance reports, and ensures
that the data handling practices
aligns with industry regulations.
Through intelligent policy enforcements,
class monitors, data access
patterns, flags, potential violations
in real time and automatically
applies the remediation measures.
This proactive approach to compliance
management significantly reduces the
risk of regulatory violations while
streamlining audit pro processes.
Now let's see the real world
successes in the regulated industry.
Let's take, let's talk about
financial s services, transformation
like a banking sector where.
Major investment bankings implemented
class to automate a risk data
aggregation across global trading
systems, achieving real-time regulatory
records and reporting capabilities.
So Clay Class A engine uses machine
learning to analyze millions of
transactions across accounts rapidly.
Spotting unusual.
Spendings suspicious transfers or
deviations from typical customer behavior.
This enables banks to flag the
potential of fraud transactions in
real time, sending instant alerts
to investigation, and even trigger
automated interventions like temporarily
placing a hold on the accounts.
So for complaints, cloud
continuously scans activities.
For regulatory breaches adapts to
policies and generate audit ready
reports all in a real time in all
in real time keeping institution
compliant without manual efforts.
Now let's talk about the healthcare in
the large healthcare system change data.
Integration to create unified
electronic health records while
maintaining HIPAA or CG or CPDA.
Compliance now come to
the insurance industry.
So in the insurance industry, they are
leveraging CLA to automate cleaning.
The A can automatically ingest,
classify, and route claims based
on complexity, urgency, and risk.
Enabling foster settlements and
tries on high priority cases.
So this a powered engine analysis,
submitted documents, extract required
information and cross reference it
against the policy historical claims
to validate each submission, reducing
manual intervention and review time.
So this a detects claims
anomalies such as language
pattern associated with the fraud.
Flagging suspicious cases for a deeper
inspection, which result in cost savings
and reduce the payout on fraudulent camps.
So these are some real world success
stories, which is already implemented
in the industry using the cla.
Now, let's talk about how DevOps and data
architecture can use this class A and
how it can be leveraged for the future.
Class A driven streaming pipeline.
Unpredictable planning capabilities,
empower DevOps teams and data architects
to build scalable, secure solutions
that adapts to changing business
learning approach ensures that your data
integration strategy evolves with the
organization, providing the foundation
for sustain the digital transformation
in a containerized cloud Native neurons.
Thank you so much for your time and.
Have a good day.
Thank you.