Hi, and welcome to my talk today.
It is unleashing the potential of cloud
native open source vector databases.
It would have been longer,
but I really can't fit that.
I'm Tim Spann.
I'm the developer advocate here at
Zillow's along with my partner in Berlin
and other people coming all over the
world, I cover Milvus, the open source
vector database, which is pretty awesome.
We're going to show you a bunch
of slides as we tend to do.
Kube native is complex.
You're trying to get everything running
natively in the cloud in Kubernetes.
But we'll show you the easy way
to run an advanced open source
distributed vector database.
But we'll show you some cool
demos first, really easy.
Is there anything special going on?
We're including a chatbot we created
to use Milvas and let you chat with
a lot of different documentation.
Why is that a thing?
There's a lot of unstructured data.
And let's show you some of it now.
It could be something like, I
want to do something with Kafka.
A popular streaming system.
If you're down in Austin with we've got
some of my colleagues down there and
some of my friends from StreamNative and
from a bunch of other cool companies.
If you're in Austin, I definitely say
check out Current, pretty cool event.
And here's a really easy way
you can learn how to use it.
Very easy project all running on
Milvus and we give you the source code.
Now, if you want to do something
like a search, you could do that.
What is Milvus?
If you didn't know, it's also
a bird, but we're talking about
the database, high performance
vector database and other demos.
You could see these are all public URLs.
You don't need any special
thing to get there.
You can also do something like
get a cat, but you should have
one and search by the cat.
Oh, those are pretty cool cats.
You get the idea.
Also, we could do a little
smarter cat and ask a question.
Show me ceiling cats.
Let's see, that one
might be a little hard.
But we've got text and we've got an image.
Oh, actually, they're doing pretty good.
Now, the one thing we could do
is use a re ranking algorithm
to adjust them algorithm.
based on percentages.
It's pretty cool.
One is doing a search by the
vectors for my cat picture and one
is doing the vectors of my text.
It'll re rank them here and
that is the best one because
you can see it's a ceiling cat.
So that's pretty awesome.
We've got a tutorial you could follow,
do your own just to give you an idea.
Let's get back to the
slides for a little bit.
Then we'll go to my custom
demo and source code.
But, any of this data that's not
typical, maybe it changes, maybe it's
variable, maybe it's things like images.
They change a lot.
One pixel changes, it's
a different encoding.
Videos.
Text molecules.
There's a lot of it just getting more and
more, and most of it's never analyzed.
You don't query it.
You don't use it to find things.
Now you can, which is pretty awesome.
This state is growing
will continue to grow.
But what's nice is thanks to the power
of these new deep learning models for
the last couple of years, we could take
this unstructured data applied deep
learning models, map it to vectors.
Thank you, neural networks,
and then make it available in
a vector database like Milvus.
Or if you want it fully
Kubernetes, fully managed for
you, Azilis Cloud does all that.
You don't have to worry about
setting up your own Helm
charts and doing all that work.
But what is a vector database?
It's built so you can store, index, and
query all these vector embeddings of
whatever these unstructured data is.
But it adds things on top of what you
might get from other ways to do this.
So you get filtering.
You get a hybrid search like you saw.
Dense vector, some text.
It's durable.
It's going to be saved.
It's going to make sure
you don't lose data.
Things can be replicated.
Highly available in a cluster.
Things that make sense
for native Kubernetes.
Sharding, aggregations.
Things will be backed up.
You could do full crud.
You can create, you can
update, delete things.
Indexing, re indexing, multiple
people using the same app.
These are cloud things we all know about.
Vector search libraries, you can
do vector searches very quickly
with a lot of options there.
And there's a lot beneath the covers to
support things like GPUs and custom chips.
And to be able to scale
out to billions of them.
Be able to insert and delete fast.
Be able to handle a lot of
people querying at once.
And regardless of what
that unstructured data is.
We mentioned the fun ones, images and
video and your emails and all kinds of
PDFs and random documents and audio.
But it could be logs, can be any data.
Maybe it's data that doesn't
doesn't always look the same.
Maybe it changes.
Maybe it's semi structured.
Maybe it's structured, but
maybe there's an image with it.
There's a lot of different data that
works well on a vector database.
A lot of reasons why you may need
to use this data as part of a RAG
approach against a large language model.
So having a vector database makes sense.
Again, take the data, make it a
vector embedding, get it in the vector
database so it's available and safe.
Perform an approximate nearest
neighbor similarity search, get your
results, and then people can query
it and do what they need with it.
Very often, like we said to use in
various applications, especially in AI.
Now, could you get by with something else?
There are some really good libraries
out there, and we know this because
we use them underneath the covers.
The ones from Facebook.
The the Small Worlds one.
But these are really designed for
Writing your own little apps, testing
things out, learning, working with
a couple hundred thousand vectors.
A lot of functionality
there, but it's a library.
You could take some, existing
database that does something else,
add one of those libraries, and
that kind of does a little bit.
Does it scale out as big as you need?
No.
Does it support the full
life cycle of a vector?
Do you get real time search?
Top K results, range searches, hybrid
searches, multi modal, multi vector.
We could have 10 vectors in a
single row in our collection.
Fully distributed, fully compute and
storage separated, so you could easily
do Kubernetes, that's what Milvus does.
Now, Milvus has been
around for a while here.
It is part of the Linux
Foundation AI and Data.
It is Apache licensed.
A lot, almost 30, 000 stars.
A lot of people using this.
Download numbers go up all the time.
You could start off with just
a pip install in a Jupyter
notebook and be ready to go.
Code is very reusable.
Write it against something
that just runs on your laptop.
Then run out to the biggest
Kubernetes cluster ever.
And it integrates with all the things
that you're used to using already, whether
it's OpenAI, LangChain, Llama, Index,
whatever it is, all the features you
expect from the modern vector database.
Dense and sparse encodings,
filtering, re ranking, as new
things come out, it is added there.
Very scalable, very elastic.
Again, using the power of Kubernetes
to shrink down when you need to.
Also, you can prototype in Docker,
run with Milvus Lite in your
notebook, and while not incurring
that cost until you're ready.
Which is nice.
Support for all the hardware acceleration
that's available in all the different
clouds, different ways to search,
different ways to tune the consistency.
So depending on what your needs
are, you have a lot of options.
If you need to improve
performance regardless of
anything else, you could do that.
Support for all the big indexes, things
like sparse indexes, Disk space indexes,
GPU indexes, especially with NVIDIA.
They're doing some great stuff with Cagra.
The hierarchical, navigable
small worlds one, which is very
fast, does a lot of things.
Different types of searches and
ability to group them and filter them.
Really important to optimize, speed
things up, and get just what you need.
Again, multi people using everything.
All the hardware you need.
Very straightforward there.
And there is someone out there with
almost a hundred billion vectors.
And it can be done.
Ten billion vectors.
with a 1500 dimension vector in there that
exists in a single instance on the cloud.
Again, decoupling compute and storage
as we expect in everything here.
And it is done because we
need to scale everything.
A proxy to access thing.
Be able to log all the coordination
of what's going on with all the
elements in your cluster, whether
it's data querying or indexing.
All those workers making sure
you get your All your queries
done no matter how many you need.
Scale up more if those slow down.
Index as data is coming in.
Make sure it's indexed and ready to go.
Make sure your data is
processed and then stored.
And permanently stored without being lost.
We store this in native storage,
whether it's S3 or what have you.
Support for all the major
vector index types out there.
Approximate nearest
neighbor search type stuff.
Everyone's used HNSW, it
is very good, graph based.
The Kaggler one by NVIDIA is a
GPU version, which is incredibly
fast, which is important.
If you want things super accurate,
might not work on a super
large one, you could do flat.
There is a GPU version of that.
The quantization based IVF flat is a
nice balance, a little faster there.
Accuracy is not as high as the pure
flat SQ8 quantization reduces your disk
load for PQ, again, another one of the
quantized base indexes, you want a high
query speed, and you're willing to take
a little bit of accuracy off, again, You
get those options, what you want to do
again, being able to do by disk is nice.
So you don't have to put
a lot of stuff in RAM.
Traditionally, things have to go in
RAM to be able to get to a high level.
As you can see, this will look pretty
familiar to people who run Kubernetes.
Having the separation
of different services.
And stores like we mentioned
workers so we can scale out as large
as we need or shrink back down.
We have messaging in the middle,
your choice of Kafka or Pulsar, and
both of those are very powerful.
This again makes sure you don't lose
data, makes things are distributed,
makes sure things aren't stuck
waiting for something, which is great.
And again, getting those workloads
distributed and out to however many
people need them, keeping separate
indexing, querying, and data processing
and storage, so things can scale out.
We have etcd in there great
for coordination and metadata.
You really need that.
And again, etcd is really good
in our environments there.
So we use that again, a
different way to look at it.
Obviously, we're running on Kubernetes
here on top of different servers,
but we could take advantage of
different processors and different
systems, depending on where you're
running and showing you a little more
of how they connect to each other.
Again, keeping things separated so we
could scale them out pretty easily.
Remember I said the install?
That is the full install.
And that will give you the libraries
to talk to Docker or the cloud or
your, wherever your cluster is running.
And also give you the ability
to run on your small device.
Just in a notebook.
Don't need anything more advanced.
Under the covers it does all the magic.
Like I said, magic is taking unstructured
data and turning it into something that
AI can understand and find quickly is what
these various embeddings are used for.
Retrieval Augmented Generation, RAG,
you're going to hear that term a lot.
A ton of people are doing
this because it's helpful.
It saves you money.
It makes your results more accurate.
Gives you back more relevant results.
Reduces significantly hallucination.
And you can provide, Something
specific to a domain, like I gave
it air quality data, gave it just
articles about Milvus, so we get better
results if someone asks a question.
I send that to the vector similarity
search first, search my collections to
get domain specific data, things that
maybe are private to me or that I know
you're going to need for that question,
use that to Give you the better answers
from all the major models out there.
Whether you're hosted on Allama, or
OpenAI, or Hugging Face, or Google,
or Microsoft, or Cohere, or Mistral,
or all those great options out there.
Get your answers back to your actions.
Pretty straightforward.
And again, what's nice is,
you can keep your data secure.
No one has to see it.
And you can even run your own
local models, so you don't have
to worry that the model will be
retrained on your specific stuff.
Data sovereignty is a cool
word, meaning I own it.
I'm not having my data leak out
somewhere, if it is my secret sauce there.
And you got options.
Now, if you are a Kubernetes expert,
which I'm imagining we have some
people on the conference that
are, you could set up everything.
Everything's open source, including
things to make it even better.
I'll show you AddTo is a nice
GUI for managing it, so you
don't need to pay for anything.
Nowhere is a vector search engine
embedded into Novus to use all those
popular libraries, make it so it
can be expanded out to support more.
I made things run fast, again distributed,
and again another open source project.
When you saw that OSS chat, we found out
that calling models like OpenAI is pricey.
GPT is not cheap.
So we came up with a good way to cache
your queries and give you optimal results.
Save money with a very
simple open source tool.
If you want to know how fast things
are, we publish a benchmarking
tool in the open source.
You could do it if you just
want to create collections and
let someone else do the work.
Not a bad idea.
Have things a hundred percent secure.
Have Zillow's cloud do it.
They'll put it where you need to put it.
To store it.
Or if you already have things built
out, you can run on top of that.
All the embedding models
we mentioned before.
All the resources.
I'm going to go into demo next.
I want to get the slides out of the way.
If you're watching this later.
Fast forward until the demos if you want.
This is important information.
Give us a star to make sure we're on the
right track for the open source project.
A lot of other databases
are not open source.
Also, if you got problems, Discord
is where we usually hang out.
We've got engineers in there.
I'm in there.
Our friends all over
the world are in there.
other community members, power users.
We also have a really good AI
chat bot that has been trained
on our stuff, trained on these
problems, is exceptionally good.
So definitely check us out
on Discord if you're having
problems, if you're in New York.
or near New York or Princeton or Philly.
I run a meetup.
Now I do record this, sometimes stream it.
We try to stream it on zoom or YouTube
depends on network traffic and, the
whatever's going on at the time.
Sometimes it's easier than others, but I'm
running one in a couple of days, usually
once a month definitely check it out.
We also have ones in California
and in Berlin and in Asia.
So check those out.
If you want to learn more about
Genitive AI, we keep a really good
selection of knowledge articles with
notebooks and how to get started
regardless of where you want to run it.
We are friends with everybody.
So like I mentioned before,
all those different names,
we've got examples with them.
I like to do a Llama so I can
run it on the laptop for free.
Don't have to pay anyone.
I've got a ton of articles
on how to do this.
I've got an interesting one on using
street cameras data in New York.
That is not AI.
That's mine.
And I got some other one on showing
you that we don't just store vectors.
We have a ton of support for different
numbers and other fields because
you'll see Vector is important, but
unstructured data is often next to
structured or semi structured data.
You want to put a whole
chunk of JSON in there.
Maybe you've got a couple of
metadata fields really important.
If I have an image, I might want
to link to the original source.
Some metadata about the size.
Maybe a description.
Things we don't need, but nice to have.
The more data you have, The better.
If you have data about
an image, why not use it?
Pre compute things, make
things faster, easier.
Again, if you want to see the new Milvus
Lite, and how you can use that in a
notebook, we've got an article there.
And, I'm doing some cool
stuff with Milvus at the Edge.
Whether it's a client or
running Milvus Lite there.
Or even the Docker version.
We could do that.
In this one I'm doing some stuff
with some AI kits, and it's fun.
You could check that article out.
I put out a weekly newsletter.
Covers everything.
All the fun stuff in open source.
Plus some streaming stuff and some other
stuff I've worked with in the past.
If you want to reach out,
this is where we are.
You can always find me on LinkedIn
more than I would like, but I'm there.
Same with Twitter.
Let's get into some demos.
Hopefully everything in
the world didn't time out.
We showed you these demos.
As you can see, you can go right to them.
Let's see if all our
other stuff timed out.
I hope it did not.
Okay, so I have a cluster here
hosted on Zillow's for free.
I'm using the free plan for myself here.
And I have a couple of collections.
It's pretty easy to get to.
You can also use add to, remember
that one, regardless of which version.
So if I want to connect to
Docker one, I can do that.
If I want to connect to
Zillow's cloud, I can do that.
And this shows me all the fields I have.
You can see here, I've got one
vector field with the with the flat,
but I also have a bunch of fields
here, and these are important ones.
I've got a text field in here, so
I can chunk a big piece of text
in there, so I can directly get
that, and I can do vector searches.
If you don't know what to search
on, this will let you figure that
out, or you could just browse the
data, which is pretty helpful.
What's nice with this tool is I can
pick how consistent I want the data.
Right now I don't have anything inserting,
so that's fine, but if I wanted to
query on stuff as it's coming in, I
could just weaken my consistency there.
Again, don't have to think
about that if you don't care.
Like for this one, let
me find ones where the.
Doc source is, you can see here, we
can look inside Jason is me about that.
Can I do that?
Yes, I can.
Okay.
I still got a couple of results here.
You can add another condition.
What if I want the primary
category to be vector database.
And now we've limited that further.
Which is nice, and you can copy
all these things, pretty easy.
You can also add data here if you want.
If the data is partitioned, As you can
see here, this one is, it tells you
how many entries in each partition.
This is for performance.
This one is partitioning based on a
key, and that key is that category,
so there's a bunch of different ones.
Now we can do a vector search
based on a specific thing.
As you saw with those examples,
you upload an image, and that'll
be your vector to get turned into
The appropriate size number and we
can limit however you want here.
What's nice with this one is
this will give you the code.
So if you want to use an app to run
this, you can just grab that code.
You can also export the data
as a comma separated value.
Pretty easy.
Just to give you an idea how
you can browse your data.
Let's go to our other thing here.
Hopefully I didn't make this too big here.
Let's get out of here.
Okay.
So you could see, I could search it a
couple of different ways, import data.
This one's nice is with
the Zillow's cloud.
There's a REST endpoint.
So you could try things out looking
at a query, see what you'd get
back, however you want to do that.
You could also browse the data.
This is cool as you find data
you want and use that to search.
And when I do this search, you could
see back what's got the number one rank?
This one.
Because it's an exact match.
Because that's the one I searched on.
That sort of thing.
Now we have a bunch of different notebooks
here that do a lot of different things.
Again, like I said, they're documented
to make it straight forward.
Show you what libraries you need.
Here, the stuff for Milvus.
Here, I'm saying where
I'm getting my data from.
Connect to my Melvis.
If you're connecting to Zillow's cloud,
we have a token based system to log in.
So I've got that in my environment.
Check to see if I need my collection.
This is how we add fields.
You could add a ton of them.
I add some indexes, create my
index, see what the partitions are.
I've got a thing to take out my HTML.
I'm looking at changing that
for a model that's coming next.
Then I go through here
and I iterate through.
The top feeds from Medium, which is RSS,
parse that out, get the fields I want.
This is all it takes
to insert into Milvus.
Again, you'll notice here, using
the model function to vectorize.
That was listed up here.
And that is a very simple one.
That's using this smaller
model and my CPU, running on a
laptop, and using Hugging Face
Sentence Transformers to do that.
Ton of different models, doesn't
look any different to you.
And then you could check the
results, run a query, run a search
here, very straight forward.
You can also do things
like a RAG, very simple.
Again, for this one, LangChain.
Connect to make sure I use the right
things in LangChain, connect to Milvus,
there's my embedding, there's some text,
primary key, make sure we connect, and
then we just go through a loop and then
we can ask questions, if you look here,
when I get the result, I send those
to a Slack channel, you can see here,
question, answer, you can see here, Pretty
straightforward to do that and not hard.
We will give you all the source
code if you go to my GitHub.
You'll see I have a lot of examples.
Lots of cool stuff whether you're
interested in partitioning data, air
quality, street cameras, I got a knowledge
base, parsing news, doing multimodal.
Doing stuff on a Raspberry Pi, looking
at Olympics data, running on a Jetson,
doing travel advisories, running on
some other devices, looking at, oh, I
forgot about the vehicle collisions.
That one's interesting stuff in New York.
If you saw what you like,
definitely reach out.
We are always trying to help people
get started, whether it's at the
meetup, a webinar, or in person.
Definitely check it out.
Thanks for coming to my talk here.
See if I could search,
show you the medium here.
Got a ton of articles.
Check them out.
If you want a deeper dive into
the Kubernetes internals, we've
got some materials on that.
If you really want to
see it, but they work.
All the Helm charts are available.
Everything you need to get running.
And it's pretty straightforward.
So thanks a lot.