Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining me today.
My name is Jmir Sink.
Today I'll be sharing how predictive
manufacturing analytics can be scaled
using Kubernetes powered CRM systems.
The big idea is this, when companies
move from reactive service models to
predictive proactive ones, they can
unlock massive value, including the.
The potential for dramatic revenue growth.
Now let's dive right into it.
I'm gonna start sharing my screen.
Manufacturers face a big
challenge after market services.
Things like maintenance and spare
parts represent a huge revenue
opportunity, but most companies
don't capture it effectively.
Why?
Because they're reactive.
Equipment breaks, then they respond.
Even with digital initiatives, many can't
scale predictive service models, but if
organizations shift towards predictive
analytics driven operations, they can
move from firefighting to creating
real time enterprise scale value.
Traditional CRMs weren't built for this.
They were designed for tracking customer
interactions, not billions of iot signals.
They're monolithic, so scaling is hard.
They struggle with velocity.
The speed of realtime streams and
volume of customer data explodes, and
it all leads to a lot of problems.
So if manufacturers want predictive
insights, they can't just
rely on old CRM architectures.
They need systems that scale natively.
This is where Kubernetes
really changes things.
By moving to Kubernetes native
architectures, we can break
analytics into containerized,
microservices, small modular pieces
that are easy to reuse and scale.
When demand spikes, Kubernetes
automatically scales resources
up when demand falls.
It dials them back down.
That means performance when you need it.
Cost saving when you don't.
So what does a realtime
pipeline actually look like?
It starts with iot ingestion,
sensor streaming, nonstop capturing,
captured by containerized collectors.
Then comes.
Service history, all the maintenance
logs and repair records analyzed in
distributed fashion to surface patterns.
On top of that machine learning
models, inside Kubernetes pods model,
customer behavior and usage trends.
Finally, predictive insights
are delivered in real time
through auto-scaling services.
So you're taking raw sensor noise,
combining it with history and behavior,
and turning it into actionable insight.
If we go a little deeper into the
architecture, we've got containerized
pipelines with helm managed machine
learning deployments, auto-scaling
services, keep things responsive.
While even driven architectures
react instantly as data comes in
on Kubernetes itself, jobs handle
batch analytics, CR jobs schedule
recurring tasks, custom operators
streamline machine line workflows and
state full sets manage persistence.
Each piece has a role, and
together they form a flexible
backbone for predictive analytics.
When companies design systems
like this, the impact is clear.
Customers stick around longer
because service is proactive.
Downtime drops sharply thanks to
predictive maintenance, and most
importantly, service revenue grows
because resources are allocated at
the right time in the right way.
There are a few orchestration
strategies worth highlighting.
Use persistent volumes for stateful
data, so context isn't lost.
Distribute model training across multiple
pods so it scales efficiently and use
event driven triggers inside Kubernetes.
So predictions handle happen
the instant data arise.
Resource allocation is where
performance really lives or dies.
CPU allocation should be dynamic.
Workloads get compute
power when they need it.
Memory should be managed with limits
and affinity rules, so no single pod
hogs, the cluster and for storage.
Persistent volumes handle model
artifacts you need to keep.
While a femoral storage takes
care of temporary workloads,
A typical orchestration
flow looks like this.
Data comes in from manufacturing
systems, goes through EDL for
cleaning, then analytics for
feature engineering and inference.
Finally, predictions get pushed out
through APIs, into CRMs and dashboards.
Simple flow data comes in, gets
cleaned and enriched, and delivered.
Of course, monitoring is critical.
On the application side, you should track
accuracy, drift latency, and data quality.
On the infrastructure side,
it's about monitoring.
Monitoring PO resource use, scaling
events and storage performance.
Without good monitoring, you won't
catch issues before they spiral.
There are pitfalls to watch for
if you don't set proper resources.
Resource requests and limits workloads
will compete and slow each other.
Each other down if you
don't design data access.
IO bottlenecks creep in fast, and
if state isn't managed properly,
models and intermediate data
can disappear during scaling.
These are avoidable, but
only if planned for upfront.
Finally, resilience production
systems should be able to
handle failure without breaking.
That means multi-zone deployments,
circuit breakers for fall tolerance
and horizontal scaling policies to
balance workloads automatically.
And of course, persistent
volumes and backups.
Keep data safe.
Resilience is what turns and experiment
into something the business can rely on.
So to wrap up scaling predictive
manufacturing analytics isn't just about
analytics, it's about architecture.
Kubernetes native arch native systems
give us the scalability, efficiency,
and resilience needed to move from
reactive service to predictive
operations, and that's where the
real business impact comes from.
Thank you so much for joining me today.
I'd be glad to continue this
discussion and answer your
questions after this session.
Thank you.