Good morning everyone.
It's great to be here at Q 42.
2025. My name is Xi and I'm part of
Microsoft Cloud infrastructure team.
Over the past several years, I've
worked on scaling hyperscale data
centers across multiple regions.
What I'll share today is shown directly
from real world experiences, the success,
some mistakes, and the lessons learned.
Our focus is simple, how we can
accelerate data center build outs.
Not by cutting corners, but by improving
coordination, panelization and ness
across every layer of the infrastructure.
This is increasingly relevant today
as organizations push for faster cloud
expansion, lower time to market, and
more efficient resource utilization.
Let's dive in.
Here's a quick overview of the flow today.
We'll start with the foundational
readiness, where we'll discuss
why early planning and segregating
critical workloads from the
backbone of acceleration.
Then we'll cover dependency management,
essentially, how to identify and
visualize interconnections between
the tasks that are often invisible,
but have massive downstream effects.
Next network connectivity, one of the most
time sensitive areas in any build out.
I'll show how to manage the underlay
and overlay networks in parallel.
I'll then move to server and service
deployment where the automation and pre
staging really make the difference between
a three month and a nine month ramp up.
Finally, we'll tie it all together
with integration and scaling and
close with some key metrics and
takeaways that you can apply to
your own data center projects.
Let's start by grounding
ourselves in a core challenge.
Modern data centers aren't
single threaded project.
The highly interdependent ecosystems
involving land power, cooling, networking
compute compliance are moving in parallel.
The problem is a delay in any one of these
domains, cascades into everything else.
For example, a late fiber trench
permit, delays and network
installation, which delays testing,
which then starts production rollout.
The insight here is simple but powerful.
We can't think linearly anymore.
Acceleration requires breaking
the chain of sequential dependency
and moving towards parallelism.
The rest of this talk will
unpack how to do that exactly.
Foundation readiness is
where acceleration truly.
Site selection, land acquisition,
and permitting, those need to
start at least 18 to 24 months
before you target operational date.
If you're waiting for design
approval before starting
zoning utility negotiations,
you're already lost valuable.
Physical construction
likewise must be modular.
We are seeing a shift towards designs
that support phase expansion, smaller
faster deployable modules rather
than single large build and power and
cooling shouldn't be afterthoughts.
There should be parallel streams.
Teams working on utility agreements,
backup systems and ancy planning should
operate independently, but synchronously.
The main takeaway, segregate
early plan parallel, and never
let one workflow block another.
That mindset alone can shave off
months of the project timeline.
Once your teams are operating
in parallel, you need a way to
keep visibility across the chaos.
That's where the dependency
metrics comes in.
It's essentially you have
blueprint for cooperation
coordination between various teams.
It maps every component, every
milestone, and their interdependencies.
For example, power readiness affects
lag delivery, which in turn of X
network turn up and validation.
By visualizing this network of relations
project managers can identify bottlenecks.
Before they materialize, and
this matrix is not static.
It must be revisited and updated
continuously as conditions evolve.
Think of it as a single source of truth.
It's what separates reactive
teams from proactive ones.
Our infrastructure is often the pacing
item in data center construction.
Utility coordination alone can take
over 18 months from negotiating,
creating the connections to
securing substation permits.
That's where those
conversations must start.
Almost as soon as society selected.
Power sufficient and redundancy
planning need to factor in
future expansion and density.
We are not talking about a 15 to 20
kilowatts per rack in many cases.
And with the ai tracks this
power demand will be going
up in an exponential fashion.
One of the biggest acceleration levers
here is pre-ordering long lead time
components like generators, transformers,
and UPA systems, even before final
electrical design is locked down.
Yes, it's a gas letter risk, but the
alternative is waiting months for
delivery and losing your schedule buffer.
Slide o provisioning cost is far
cheaper than a six month delay.
Network is another critical bottleneck.
Fiber installation alone
can take six to 12 months.
Competing agreements of right of way
permits can drag that even longer.
So network design and external carrier
engagement must begin at the same time
as land and power planning, not after
assess existing fiber infrastructure
before final site selection.
This can be the difference between
a one year and a two year build out.
Also, consider alternative models
like dark fiber or IGOs can
bring you flexibility and time.
Remember, connectivity delays are
preventable if addressed early.
Network build out doesn't have to
wait for construction completion
while the building is going up.
Design and vendor selection
can happen in parallel.
Network design can be
based on different stages.
They can be on different architectures,
like a class fabric leaves, spine
architectures but it should be validated
at a modular system designed to scale.
Modules can be built in panel, and this
parallelism endures that network readiness
aligns with physical completion, and we
can compress the scheduled timelines.
Traditionally teams waited for the data
center to be complete before installing
servers that's slow and inefficient.
Instead, the pre-stage and validate
servers offsite ship ready to deploy racks
and US automation to configure the racks.
This transformation basically
brings in the deployment timeline
from months to weeks, which is
an enormous efficiency gain.
Acceleration continues at the software
layer with infrastructure as code.
All configurations, network
storage, compute are defined
programmatically, versioned, and
tested through the Ci CD pipelines.
Containerization abstracts services
from hardware dependencies.
11. Deployment and development
in parallel tracks.
Then comes automated testing thousands
of checks across clusters to ensure
everything behaves predictably at scale.
Finally, progressive rollouts can utilizes
and stage deployments, allow services
to go live in small controlled phases.
The net effect, your data center
isn't waiting for the perfect moment.
It's gradually becoming productive,
even as the final construction finishes.
Complaint is often viewed as a bottleneck,
but starting early flips that dynamic.
For instance, embedding security and
compliance experts from the day of
one ensures your design processes and
automation all meets STAs for the start.
Preliminary audits during construction,
automated policy validation and real
time compliance documentation all
minimize surprises, filter early
compliance equals faster, safer co lives.
The traditional commissioning
is sequential and slow.
The fast track approach performs
component level testing During
installation, multiple teams can work
in commissioning different availability
zones in panel and independent motor
sections of the data center can
be hone handed off progressively.
This method reduces post-construction
testing from months to mere weeks.
Accelerating time to service availability.
Integration is where
acceleration becomes real.
Every system lacks power cooling, network
compute need to interlock seamlessly.
The most effective approach is
cross-functional integration teams.
Engineers from all domains collaborate
regularly with shared dashboards
and lack dependency tracking.
Integration isn't just
technical, it's also cultural.
When every team shares ownership
for readiness, you eliminate silos.
A clearly defined handoff and
testing process ensures smooth
transitions into operations.
Measuring acceleration is crucial for
continuous deployment and improvement.
Tracking metrics.
Like overall project duration, time
to production can showcase the time
based acceleration improvements.
ROE Acceleration shows how data
center stack generating value,
percentage of parallel execution shows the
efficiencies of our acceleration strategy.
These indicators reveal how well
your acceleration strategies are
performing and where to focus next.
Continuously measuring this
helps you refine your approach.
Every project should get slightly
fast, faster, and more efficient.
To summarize, let's recap
what you discussed so far.
Early workflow segregation
prevents dependency bottlenecks,
dependency metrics, keep your
team aligned and adaptive.
Network and power planning must
happen in paddle, not sequentially.
Server pre-staging and automation
drastically reduce time to like
compliance and commissioning when done
early accelerate instead of delay.
So these are our key learnings.
So for your next project, your workflows,
identify your top bottlenecks and
establish parallel execution paths.
Hope the session is useful.
Thank you for your attention.
I'd be happy to discuss
how these strategies can be
applied to your environment.
Thanks and have a great day.