Good morning.
Good evening to everyone.
Welcome to conference 42.
Today I'm here to present a
project that I've been working on,
which is called Dragon Copilot.
It's a AI provide clinical assistant
and transforming healthcare
workflows and patient care.
Let me introducing myself.
My name is Ku Lato.
I'm a senior software
developer here in Microsoft.
I've been doing the software
development for past 10 years.
From this 10 years I had experience
working with automobile, with a TS state
government, and also with the telecom
and healthcare, especially in healthcare.
I've been working five to six years,
either with Nuance Communications or
Microsoft As part of this healthcare,
we started on initiate initiation,
that's called Dragon Copilot.
Before I dive into more on what
this abstract of this project, let
me start by saying a story of this
project nearly starts before COVID.
All of you guys know how
the COVID pandemic affected.
Especially healthcare doc
patients, there is lot of patients.
The doctor has to visit each patient.
Once they completed the visit, doctor
has to go fill the documentation,
prescribe the medications,
and come back next patient.
So because of this burdensome
work, doctors cannot able to
concentrate on the patient and they
cannot able to help more patients.
Per day because they have to
spend after hours work as well.
Again they have also family.
They have to go to the family and
take care of the family as well.
That thought especially
helped this project in a way.
How can we do much better so
that we can help both healthcare.
Doctors and even the patients as well.
So let me give you, based on the story,
let me give you guys a small abstract.
What it'll do, streamline documentation,
it'll assistance, simplifies the clinical
documentation, reduces the administration
task for healthcare provisional
and also advanced AI technologies.
We use a ambient recording and LZ national
language processor, which can perform.
Process between conversation
between doctor and patients, it'll
improve the patient care as well.
Reduces the admin burden,
allows doctors to focus more
on patient care and outcomes.
Workflow integration and compliance.
Seamless integration ensures
timely, accurate documentation and
compliment with healthcare standards.
Let me give you guys problems
that they're facing today and
the solutions as well for that.
As I said in the story it's more on
what problems the doctors are facing.
Time consuming documentation.
Yes.
As I said before, doctors
have been doing documentation.
They have to con, it'll con consume
significant time, and there will
be a documentary as it'll not be
perfect and patient has to come again.
Doctors has to visit them again.
And also all doing this
physician will burn out.
Doctors will get burned out easily.
So that to help this, we need
to automate this process.
That's where the third part, that's
where the thought began and we
brought that back to life solution.
What we did as part of
Dragon Copilot is ai.
It's AI proper clinical documentation.
Dragon copilot automates the clinical
workflows using ai, enabling physicians
to focus more on patient care
and enhanced patient interaction.
93% of patients noted physicians seems
more at attend to and personally with
the dry copilot support, so they don't
have to go do the documentation so they
can spend more time with the patients.
And another one is melting wheel and
secure solution supports melting wheel
transcription, secure data migration, and
accessibility complaints for healthcare.
So what it means is either doctor or
patient in a different, talking different
languages or probably from different
regions, it can help them as well.
It can transcribe it
in different languages.
It can show you the note, it can show you
the transcription, how doctor wants it.
It'll also solve the problem.
Let me give you guys the technical
architecture and technologies,
technical architecture.
As I said, we have the ambient recording
that is much more ai driven flow.
It'll capture the real time conversation
between physicians and patients using
advanced ambient recording technology.
So it'll grab that conversation
that'll send you to the NLG process
and NLG will process it recording
between doctor and patient.
It'll generate the note.
Transcript and then deliver back to
the doctor so the doctor can easily see
what they have recorded, what what they
have got the note and what prescriptions
they have ordered for these patients.
If they want to review,
they can do it as well.
And also here we are using wise dictation.
Doctors don't have to type if they
want to, if they see that note.
Some error, some something is there.
They can do the wise dictation
and a summarization without
doing any hands keyboard work or
doing any work with the hands.
They can easily talk.
They can modify the note,
they can edit the note.
And then HR integration Security.
We helped this solution to be part of EHR.
Health systems as well, so that
that proves he HR is a major
role playing in healthcare today.
So that proves the how This Do com project
is evolving in real healthcare world.
Key technologies.
We talked about ambient
recording, how it works.
We talked about an LNL lu, how it works.
It'll capture the recording
between doctor and patient.
And LU will enable the accurate
interception of the spoken language to
external relevant medical information.
Effectively.
Why is dictation allows doctors to dictate
and edit note if something seems wrong.
If they want to add more,
they can voice dictation.
They don't have to type anything.
Generate a models, transform unstructured
input into structural clinical
documentation, improving accuracy and
efficiency, implementation and security.
Let's talk a bit more on the
implementation, how we did things, and
how we focused on security as well.
Implementation details, project life.
Cycle management, managed entire
project lifecycle, including designing,
implementation and quality, assistant
coordination, technical contributions.
We focused on mobile web
development, user interfaces design.
We use restful APIs development,
and Epic high code testing
because it's been part of Epic.
So we have to make sure Epic
customers also feel secure.
Frameworks and design
patterns that we have used.
We have used cocoa frameworks, react
frameworks, and we have designed in
M-V-M-M-U-C in designing patterns.
We have used Java script, REDX type
scrap as well, code management tools.
As usual, everybody uses.
We use SV and GATE for efficiency
via washing controls, security and
compliance, especially when it comes
to healthcare Security is major concern
and we have to, how to follow hipaa.
Security rules.
And also we have to follow the
compliance so we don't leak any data.
We don't leak show one doctor's
information to the another doctor, to
another doctor that's against HIPAA rules.
So data security and encryption.
We have data from voice dictation and
ambient recording, as you guys know,
is encrypted, completely encrypted.
Nobody.
Can decrypt that it's securely
stored and protected confidentially.
Regular regulatory of compliance,
the platform compliance with
healthcare regulations like hipaa.
As I said, ensuring legal and
ethical documentation, standards,
accessibility and includes.
If you see Microsoft, it's much more
focused on accessibility drives,
user needs, and also we can help
the usually impaired users as well.
They can use this app still
and they can benefit from it.
When we, when I say this, it's
not, it seems easy, but there
is lot of changes, challenges,
impact and contributions to it.
Let's talk about challenges and solutions.
We said, this will help doctors and
patients to, in even multilingual
AI support, or even it'll generate
the note and transcript, you
can use AI models and whatnot.
But the challenges here is multilingual
AI support, robust AI models developed for
accurate transcription in multi-languages,
enhancing usability across.
Diverse use, diverse users.
Secure data migration.
Data migration is very
much painful process.
Here we have to ensure integrity,
unsecurity, minimizing risk of data
loss or breaches during the transfer.
Healthcare compliance frameworks work
integrated to met healthcare regulations
and accessibility standards, ensuring
system reliability results and impact.
Yes, we have challenges.
We have problems.
But we've come to a point where we
have shown how this project work and
the results of the project is we have
improved the document efficiency.
Dragon Co enhances clinical documentation,
improving recording quality and
operational efficiency, significantly
increased physician patient interaction.
Yes, as I said before, IT, physicians
spend more time with patients and
less an administrative during Dragon
Co palate, better work-life balance.
This system contributes to improve work
life balance for healthcare providers
by reducing administrative burden.
Doctors can go spend time with it.
Families and they can take care
of their families as well and
has patient per perception.
93% of patients feel their physicians are
more responsible under attentive, using
the Dragon copilot personal contributions.
This is a big project.
A lot of teams came
together and developed this.
And what I, personal contributions I have
done is leadership in product development,
lead end to end development of features
on mobile and web platforms, driving
innovations and cross team collaborations,
cross platform and native development.
I have been heavily invested into the
mobile with different technologies
like shift and Object you see and
web react to, and TypeScript as well.
Software architecture and AI
integration focused, scalable software
architecture, because we are part of
a big company, Microsoft, whatever we
design, it has to be scalable to the
million of customers, and we have to
integrate AI solutions to enhance this
healthcare technology applications.
As I said, this is much more
focused healthcare plus ai.
That's the major core
concept of this product.
Conclusion.
So let me come giving, give you guys
some conclusion about how it uses
AI enhances healthcare efficiency.
Automation of clinical documentation
improves efficiency and supports
healthcare providers in delivering quality
Note advanced AI technologies, future of
patient care in a way to area solutions
like Dragon copilot shape the future.
Of patient care and clinical
operations, collaborate on excellence.
Success highlights that importance
of the interdisciplinary
collaboration and technical
excellence in healthcare innovation.
Yeah, this is, I'm done, but this
project is much more, as I say, much more
worth in future prospectives as well.
We our plan is to deliver this to
the, all the doctors across the
globe so that they can use it.
And we may come out of the situation
that we have been in the pandemic.
Because of, very much physician burnouts
that happen with this, we can save
lot more patients, doctors can visit
a lot more patients within the day.
Thank you so much.