Good morning, good afternoon,
good evening, everyone.
I'm Kumar End from Chicago, Illinois USA.
First of all, thank you for investing
your time to join this conversation
with me here at conference 42.
The topic of this conversation is beyond
production, how generative AI is reshaping
the future of a smart manufacturing.
Over the past decade, we have
heard the worst industry 4.0 and
artificial intelligence so often that
the risk sounding like yesterday's
news, yet something fundamentally
new is happening right now.
Generative AI is moving us beyond
prediction and dashboards into
a world where machines create
new designs, new workflows, even
new business models every day.
This talk is not a technical deep dive.
Instead, I want to paint a clear
business picture, why generative AI
matters, what results are already being
achieved, what challenges you must
anticipate, and how to get started
without ing day-to-day presence by
the end of the next half an hour.
You will have a tested framework
you can take back to your team.
Let us begin with the outcomes that
matters most and that make executives and
shareholders sit up and listen when the
board asks why Now, why generative ai?
There are some numbers that becomes
important and which cannot be ignored.
Almost 40% sort of product
development timelines is achieved
at an aerospace supplier.
We studied digital parts.
Once took almost 18 months
from concept to certification.
After embedding generative design,
generative AI design, that cycle
failed to almost 11 months.
And in another case, it was almost nine
months while still meeting FAAA standards.
Almost 35% improvement has been seen
in overall equipment efficiency.
A consumer package goes CPJ, planned to
use a generative AI scheduling agent.
That sequence sqs hour by hour and planned
downtime drop by roughly a third, and
overtime costs fell right alongside it.
Almost 40 per 42, 40 to 42% lift in
successful innovations have been seen.
Think of this as an
idea to impact velocity.
A tier one auto supplier did not
merely brainstorm more concepts.
They commercialized more of them
because generative as simulation
flagged and factor ability issues
before the first prototype.
These gains are not edge cases.
In meta-analysis across more than
60 plants on three continents, we
see similar order of magnitude.
The takeaway, generative AI
turns marginal, kaizen gains
into step change performance.
Two, appreciate why
the gains are so large.
Plus, compare conventional
AI and generative ai.
Conventional or traditional AI works
with the boundaries of past data.
It forecasts outcomes
based on historical trends.
It is predictive and reactive in nature.
However, genetic AI, on the other
hand, explores what could be.
It models multiple alternative features.
It synthesizes novel solutions
and a number of them.
In manufacturing, this means
designing a new process, a new
product configuration or even a new
materials before a problem arises.
That's for illustration.
A predictive model wants that a press
break is likely to fail in next 24 hours.
That is valuable information.
A generative model asks.
What new process or press break
configuration would boost throughput
by 20% and minimize maintenance
events in the first place.
Then it produces a 3D Toolpath while you
can send a straight to your CAM system.
In short, generative AI collapses the
gap between analysis and creation, and
that is game changing for manufacturing.
Environ.
Now let's take this to production floor.
Let's zoom into three day-to-day benefits.
Every plant manager cares about number
one, eliminating the bottling, realtime
layout engines, EST sensors, feed,
and automatically surfaces between
metal flow, canon position, and even
a MR that is autonomous mobile robot.
Routes.
Plants report almost 30% fewer
micro stops, and a visible
is smoothing off at times.
Number two is cutting
energy by almost 20 to 25%.
A European glass manufacturer
used a generative AI energy
optimizer that predicted furnace,
thermal inertia, hours in advance.
Power drawn now rises and falls
with the heartbeat of demand rather
than staying flat out a savings
of almost 2 million euros annually
and a happier ESG scorecard.
A third and most important aspect
is hours, not weeks in changeovers.
That's quick changeovers
between processes or operations.
During Covid, one electronics line
needed to swap from automotive
sensors to medical ventilator boards.
Historically, that would have been
at least 14 to 15 day revalidation
Generative VA process planner
produced new SMT recipes overnight
Fast pass yield was
97% the next afternoon.
Individually, each metric is impressive.
Together.
They create an operational operations.
Flywheel throughput funds
more AI plots or pilots, which
uncover more savings and so on.
Manufacturing strength means very
little without a robust supply chain.
There is some example where
generative AI science, knowing
about disruptions in advance, for
example, by blending weather feeds.
For traffic, APAs and supplier
health indicators, the model can
flag the material shortage week, two
weeks, or even a month in advance.
Prompting, preemptive action that can
be taken to streamline or smooth in
the supply chain process, identifying
alternative vendor or supplier instead
of a static approved vendor list.
The generative AI dynamically compiles
and risk scores, new suppliers worldwide.
Complete.
Complete those with the compliance
documents that can be clicked through.
Last but not least,
logistics auto rerouting.
There is a possibility that
traffic is closed or there is a
closed place or some accidents.
The AI agent rerouted or optimizes
the routes reax containers by
cube key utilizations and reissues
updated to ETS to customers.
This all happens before
a human planners logging.
Ultimate result is this, all
pivot happens in our not in weeks.
In a world where a stuck container
can cost billions of dollars,
that agility is priceless.
The scholars and practitioners
are converging fast.
Let's picture a simple batch out here.
Research publications
on one axis and industry
implementations on the other axis.
Research publications almost tripled
from 2023 to 2024, and during
the same timeframe, pilot project
implementations nearly doubled.
How has this happened?
This is simply because simulation
to software friction is falling, and
there are three main reasons for that.
Number one, foundation models trained
are trained on massive engineering.
Data sets are now available
and accessible via APIs.
Number two, industrial iot maturity
finally provides the volume and
velocity of data generative systems.
Last but not least, cloud costs are
sliding, constantly making per flow
scale, training economically viable.
The bottom line is sandbox phases
over and we are in the mainstream
adoption phase, and late movers risk.
A structural disadvantages.
The next question is what separates
the leaders from the laggards?
Step four.
Typical behaviors.
Number one, leisure focus
on high value use cases.
Leaders start with one pain
point worth, multimillions, not
a skunk works science project.
Convergence of informants and
technology team and operations team.
In such scenario they get the CI and the
plant engineers in the same room early.
So MES or manufacturing execution
system data meets cloud AI without
endless middleware battles.
Third objective and transparent KPIs
like overall equipment deficiency,
OE scrap and energy KPIs are
published daily on shared dashboards.
Turning an anecdote into accountability.
Last but not least,
playbook driven scaling.
Once one line works, they replicate
the same tech stack, same change
management rituals across plants,
regions, and business units.
So what is the payoff?
At least 35% faster time to market
and 42% higher innovation hit
rates versus peers sustained over
a five year, five year horizon.
So are these implementations
smooth without any challenges?
No.
Let's not sugarcoat the hurdles.
Then you will generally
face three big challenges.
At the top of the list is
data quality and governance.
Governance main gap will be missing
sensors on your legacy equipment.
There is another possible
noise that is PLC.
Time stamps are out of sync, so
that data needs to be corrected.
Ski semantics here is, there are
10 ways to spell the part IDs.
Each company has different way.
Each team may have different way
of work, spelling or naming apart,
so this needs to be solved with
the modern data fabric layer and a
single owner for data towards it.
Second biggest to challenge
is security and IP protection.
Generative models may
ingest CRL process knowhow.
Without a strict access controls
and federated learning options,
you risk leaking trade secrets.
Zero.
Trust architecture and secure model
incls are must have not a nice to have
in any genetic AI implementations.
Last but not least, algorithmic
bias and model shift any historical
data set Under underrepresents new
recyclable design, the AI may prefer
old plastics sabotaging sustainability
targets continuous monitoring
and periodic model code reviews.
Keep the system honest.
Companies that invest in these foundations
upfront, consistently capture higher
ROI and face fewer boardroom surprises.
Next million dollar question is what is
the return on investment and which is most
important on any project implementation?
Return on investment
is not just impressive.
It is exponential in this
kind of implementation.
In the first three months, companies
invest in a strategy and system set up.
By month four to five, they begin
saying miserable process improvements.
By month seven to eight, they typically
reach some kind of breakeven, and by
end of the first year, many companies
report a hundred percent plus ROI
without with continuous compounding,
as the system learns and evolves.
This is intelligent automation that pays
for itself quickly and continuously.
Now, let's talk about some
implementation approaches, to
achieve successful implementation,
there are four phase playbook that
can be implemented or utilized.
A step one is our phase one is assessment
process, which can be between two to
four weeks or six weeks, depending
on the nature of an implementation.
In this process, map data sets rank
pain points by value and feasibility
and secure leadership sponsorship.
Phase two is data preparation, which
can be between six to eight weeks in
this phase, clean level and integrate
sensors manufacturing, SY execution
systems, ERPO, that is enterprise source
planning and supplier data into common.
Data warehouse.
Next phase is pilot deployment,
which can last for eight last
between eight to 12 weeks run.
One contained use case for high high,
highly high important business process.
For example, generative is generative.
AI is scheduling on a
single packaging line.
With crystal clear success
criteria and measurable KPIs.
Fourth phases is scaling,
which is ongoing flow.
The stack and new use cases
are basically identified.
Institute AIOps for continuous monitoring.
This needs to be then needs to be put
some guardrails, which are basically
change management training, fortnightly
stakeholders demos and rollback plan.
You hopefully never use need to use, but
in case you have to, that comes handy.
Let's talk about the next steps.
If you remember nothing else from
this discussion or for some reason.
Take these three action.
Back to the team.
Number one, conduct a readiness assessment
in this assessment or audit data,
talent, culture are to be included.
The gaps are need to be identified and
what are quick wins are hiding in plain
sight that needs to be identified.
Number two is basically
select a lighthouse pilot.
That is the key business process where
it can be implemented, which is of high
value and low political resistance.
Let's think about packaging line, not the
company's flagship process on day one,
and then draft a 12 month
roadmap that links milestones to
financial KPIs and ESG targets.
Share it widely and publicly on company
dashboards which basically talks about
transparency and that creates momentum.
You start a smart major
ruthlessly scale fast.
That is the recipe for durable
transformation implementation.
I'd like to thank you for your attention
and engagement during this discussion.
We are at an infection point.
Where factories are no longer constrained
by yesterday's data, but powered by
tomorrow's possibilities, those who
act now will set the pace for the
next era of industrial leadership.
I look forward to your questions
and to discussing how we can partner
on your own generative AI journey.
Thank you very much.