Hello.
Very good morning.
So this is Lakshmi RN gta.
I'm working in the Starbucks
as a senior data engineer.
So today we are going to talk about
hyper personalization, transforming
digital experience through
advanced data analytics and ai.
So the, firstly, the hyper personalization
represent a paradigm shift in customer
experience operating on the principle
of dynamic identity recognition.
So the concept that consumer preferences
exist in constant contextual facts
rather than their fixed attributes.
So this approach leverages real time data
analytics, AI and mission learning to
deliver precisely tailored experiences.
Organizations implementing
hyper personalization strategies
achieve substantial improvements
in conversation rates, customer
retention and operational efficiencies
through algorithm architecture.
President engagement systems and
signal intelligence ecosystems.
So the inquiry demonstrates how
organization es incognitive computing
frameworks, multi-dimensional
attribution attribute systems and
privacy, enhancing computation to
balance improved customer experiences
with ethical consideration and.
Ultimately achieving this measurable
business value to more precise
targeting, enhanced customer journeys,
and strengthen relationship durability.
Okay, next the next we'll go
with what the concept framework.
The the very first thing is
algorithm edition architecture.
So the Salesforce customer 360 platform
processes, 80 plus billion AI predictions
dialed through algorithmic edition
architecture where AI systems continuously
recalibrate customer interactions
based on micro feedback loops.
These clients there 20% in conversation
rates and 27% higher average order values.
Hardwar Business School
research identifies four pillars
underlying this transformation.
Integrated data ecosystems, talent
hybridization, ethical governance,
and continuous experimentation.
Companies expecting these characteristic
percent higher shareholder returns by
fundamentally changing how decisions
propagate through organizations.
Okay, and the next one is the
precision engagement systems.
A prominent software companies
experience platform employs computational
contextualization process in
environmental, behavioral, and historical
variable simultaneously explaining how
a pharmaceutical company achieved 8%
higher perception earlier and through.
Patient specific adopt to messaging
organizations with unified
customer data platforms achieved
personalization maturity scores
2.8 times higher than fragmented
architectures by ably cross contextual
consistency across touch points.
And the next one, the
mechanism based value creation.
A streaming services recommendation
system influence 75% of the content stream
through preference cascade modeling.
So the tracking, how initial choices
create ripple defects across the
preference I heard is, so this
explains there 90% retention rate
work, 8.5 billion annually as a
system minimizes such friction while
maintaining perceived choice anatomy.
An e-commerce company applies elastically
fingerprinting, identifying unique
price sensitivity patterns at individual
levels, explaining their 28% increase card
conversation as prices aligned with the
individual willingness to pay thresholds.
A digital audio platform
utilizes a multimodal preference
interference to extract insight
from seemingly unrelated behaviors.
Driving 3.0 times higher customer
engagement through computing
relevance effects where each
person's interaction increases the
accuracy of subsequent experiences.
The financial institutions develop
financial behavior, twins as simulations
of individual making, explaining
why organization transitioning to
AI has a core competency, realize.
22% operational efficiency by preemptively
addressing like service needs.
So retailers, employees
behavior compounding.
Understanding how past packages create
future poten propensities expanding
at 24% increase in digital sales by
targeting micro edition points where
purchase in trends, intent criticizes.
Healthcare provides, implement
behavior notes architecture in
identifying psychological barriers
to optimal health behaviors.
How one consortium user reduce appointment
no shows by 30% through contextual
amplification where AI identifies factor
overlooked in the standard protocols.
Okay, next.
We'll go with technical.
What is that?
What is the technical infra
infrastructure of this one?
The technical foundation of hyper
personation relies on sophisticated
signal intelligence ecosystems, so it
is integrated framework that collect
process and activate data in real time,
enabling genuine individualization beyond
traditional segmentation approaches.
And then in here the first one is
multi-source data orchestration.
The foundation layer employs
the Signal Fusion architecture
systematically integrating
heterogeneous data systems to create
comprehensive customer understanding.
The Twilio segments research across
3,450 business leaders found that made
sure organization collective data for
data from 6.2 different sources versus.
2.34 less sophisticated ones.
This multi-source approach enable
enables dimensional identity resolution,
connecting fragmented customer
interactions into coherent profiles.
A leading beauty a leading beauty
retailer implemented this concept by
capturing 80 distinct behavioral signal
through its loyalty program, increasing
repeat purchases rates by 65% through
more accurate preference recognition.
While 65% of organization reduce third
party cookie dependencies dependence,
72% increase investments in privacy,
compliment, complement alternatives.
Those successfully navigating this
transition achieve 75% higher satisfaction
scores through consent based intelligence
framework that respect privacy preferences
while maintaining personalization quality.
And the next one is like real
time processing frameworks.
So this real time processing framework,
the automation implement contextual
trigger systems that respond immediate
situational factors, each archive.
Two x the higher response rates.
This reflects the concept of movement,
relevant computing, delivering
experiences at precise decision points.
A financial services company applies
this by processing location data
and transition history by context
advice, increasing mobile engagement
by 35% through timely interventions.
So data integration is challenging
with 83% of organizations.
Say setting it as their primary obstacle.
The healthcare leader,
unified data architecture, centralizing
70 plus data sources and reducing
preparation time from weeks to
hours, improving medication a by 25%
through more timely interventions.
And then the algorithmic, the next
layer is algorithmic intelligence layer.
The machine learning forms that the
core intelligence layer with companies
implementing advanced ML reporting a 35%
average increase in conversion rates.
This reflects a concept of algorithmic
vision optimization, continuously
improving choice architecture.
Through automated experimentation.
A media company employs 16 distinct
ML models contributing to a 12%.
Increase in per guest spending
through what experts call experience
orchestration, coordinating multiple
personalization dimensions simultaneously.
Deep planning models enable pattern
recognition at scale with organization
implementing these capabilities, achieving
2.5 x higher engagement rates, digital
audio platforms, neural networks, process.
Acoustic futures to create recommendations
reducing churn by 20% through preference
prediction, understanding future desserts
before customers recognize themselves.
Okay, and next real time
implementation strategies.
So by transforming data insights into
personalized experiences requires
latency optimized delivery systems.
So the framework, it was that minimized
the gap between signal detection and
experience delivery according to head
sales softwares analysis of 500 plus
marketing initiatives, organizations
implementing real time personalization
achieve 35% higher conversation
rates through the what exports term?
Temporal romance maximization.
So delivering content
precisely well, customer.
Receptively peaks, companies with a
major capabilities deliver experiences
within 1.8 seconds of trigger during
event versus industry averages
exceeding 10 seconds capitalizes.
In on the attention decay principle.
The concept that personalization
effectiveness diminishes exponentially
with the delay, the out of strategies.
The first one is.
The content orchestration systems.
So the Dynamic Content Assembly
represent the most visible
implementation access aspect.
Employing modular content architecture,
so breaking experiences into independently
personalized components and charges.
Analysis of 18 1 18 50 Growth Market has
found that companies with sophisticated
delivery infrastructures experience.
28% higher engagement rates through
contextual context adaption,
automatically adjusting message
string based on situational factors.
A hotel chains implementation enables
personalized delivery across 18 brands
through identity anchored experiences,
maintaining consistent recognition, and
despite fragmented customer journeys.
So this approach yields a 25%
improvement in direct booking rates
by employing distribution channel
optimization intelligently steering
customers toward warn booking parts.
And the next one,
adoptive pricing systems.
So this dynamic pricing mechanisms
optimize offers through willingness
to pay elastically model.
So determining.
Individual price and security thresholds,
companies implementing AI driven pricing
experience outage revenue increases
of 10% by addressing the perception
of succession value gap, aligning
prices, individual value perception,
and airline realtime engine analyzes
millions software combinations daily.
So incorporating one 50 plus variables
to improve eel management by 6%
through demand forecasting position.
Accurately predicting
fluctuations in travel intent.
A retail corporation address 1.2
plus million price points daily,
improving margin by 1.8% points
while increasing market share by 3.0
points through competitive response.
Elastically, understanding
how specific customer segments
react to competitor pricing.
The next one, the cross channel
experience architecture.
This de the consistently experiences
across touch points through cross
contextual identity resolution, the
maintaining recognition as customers
travels, channels, organizations achieving
this capability report customer lifetime
values, 2.5 times higher than those
who those with fragmented approaches.
A department store chains unified
framework maintenance profiles
for 43 million customers.
Reconciling identify ident identities
across eight plus channels with 90%
accuracy, increasing repeat purchase
rates by 30% through friction
elimination, removing barriers
created by disjointed experiences.
And the next one, decision system.
The real time interaction management
systems like Millisecond Edition
about optimal content through
edition velocity architecture.
The frameworks optimized
for speed critical choices.
Organizations implementing
these capabilities achieved
2.8 x higher marketing, ROI.
So the next one, next topic
is advanced AI applications.
So by using ai artificial intelligence
has fundamentally transformed
personalization capabilities through
cognitive computing frameworks.
The systems that stim simulate human
taught process to anticipate needs
and preferences according to tech
novio market analysis, the global.
AI-based personalization market is
projected to grow by 7.43 USD billion
from 2025 to 2029 with a c year of 23%.
The growth reflects the transition
from rules rule-based personalization
to autonomous welding systems capable
of continuous self-improvement.
Next first one is like
anticipatory intelligence.
The Medallia research shows organizations
implementing sophisticated forecasting
achieve a 30% reduction acquisition cost
through precision targeting, efficiency,
eliminating wasted expenditure on
low probability conversa conversions.
The financial services corporation
analyzes approximately $1.2 trillion
in annual transaction using models.
Incorporating 8,000 plus
variables per customer predicting
churn with 92% accuracy.
Eight.
Tele communications companies
implementation s 7,000 plus customer
attributes in the real time through
attribute correlation discovery.
Identifying obvious relationship
between seemingly unrelated variables.
This increased camp time response
rates by 35% by addressing micro
movement perceptivity ly matching
efforts to psychological states
where customers are most receptive.
Value intelligence.
The lifetime value forecasting enables
pre organization through future value
projection, allocating resources based on
potential, rather that historical value.
So companies implementing AI driven CLB
forecasting achieve a 25% increase in high
value tension through precision investment
allocation, optimizing resources
towards highest written relationships.
A coffeehouse company's platform
analyzes 400 plus billion data points
annually through consumption pattern
modeling, identifying subscale.
It signals that predict
spending trajectory.
This approach increased high value
retention by 15% by enabling preemptive
value protection, addressing satisfaction
risk before the impact behavior.
So the next one is
linguistic intelligence.
So the natural language processing
enables unprecedented customer
understanding through semantic
intent extraction, describing
meaning beyond literal expression.
Organizations implementing NLP powered
personalization achieve 38% higher
satisfaction scores through conversational
context preservation preservation.
Maintaining understanding
across fragmented interaction.
Voice recognition systems enable
personalized experiences through
local identity verification,
authenticating users through unique
speech PLA patterns, a bank's voice
biometrics, authenticates 4.7 million
customers monthly with 95% accuracy
through multifactor local analysis.
Examining over a hundred speech
characteristics simultaneously.
This reduce handling time by saving
$25 million annually through friction
minimized authentication, eliminating
cumbersome verification process.
Next one, emotional intelligence.
Sentiment detection systems
represents an emerging front
tide through effective computing.
So the technologies that recognize
and respond to human emotions,
companies implementing emotion
detection achieve net prompter
scores 18 points higher by addressing
emotional context misalignments,
that disconnect between customer
emotional states and generic responses.
Next privacy and ethical consideration.
As personalization capabilities
advanced or the organizations much
navigate the trust utility tension.
So the balancing enhanced experiences with
the privacy protection seven production,
75% of consumers express concern
about data usage with a 40% reporting
avoiding brands due to privacy issues.
The study identified the
personalization paradox.
Consumer simultaneously desired pilot
experiences while expressing anxiety
about the about the necessary data
collection, creating a fundamental
challenge for implementation.
So here the first two are, first
one is trust based governance.
The organization now.
With the average of 5.2 distinct
privacy regulations with multinational
enterprises navigating more
than 14 separate frameworks.
This regulatory complexity has catalyzed
the concept of privacy by design
and embedding protection mechanisms
into system architecture rather than
applying them react retroactively.
So in the United States, so 70% of the
companies have restructured process
for CCPA, CPRA through jurisdictional
personalization frameworks.
Geographically specific approach
organizations with prior to compliance
issue, 35% higher trust scores
transfer through transparency,
first design, prioritizing clear
communication about data practices.
The next one is geographic
privacy adoption.
The regional compliance architecture
addresses international to via variation
through regulatory localization, adopting
data practices to geographic requirements.
According to George, mark mark, 68%
of global enterprise have implemented
specific frameworks for different regions
and American technology companies app.
Tracking transparency fundamentally
altered the landscape with only
18% of users opting into tracking
this prompt of the customer goods
corporation to develop first party
data transformation strategies,
systematically replacing third party data
with consent tech direct relationships.
So the next ethical AI systems,
so explainable AI approaches
make decisions transfer.
Interpretability mechanisms translating
complex algorithms decisions
into understandable explanations.
So organizations implementing these
frameworks issue trust codes 50%
higher than those with OPAC systems.
The bank developed narrative narrative
explanation, generation for recommendation
systems, increasing acceptance rates by
30% through comprehension gap resolution,
addressing customer uncertainty
about recommendation reasoning.
Their approach creates 18,000 plus
unique explanation combinations through
decision logic transition, converting
mathematical models into natural language.
I. So next inclusive design, the
organizations implementing formal
methodologists achieve the 40%
higher satisfaction among diverse
segment segments through demogra
demographic performance parity,
maintaining consists quality
regardless of user characteristics.
The LinkedIn fairness toolkit
reduce gender by asked by 12%
through counterfactual testing,
evaluating outcomes when only
protected characteristics, chance.
Their approach includes validation
across 27 dimensions, increasing
diverse applications rates through
accessibility, enhanced personalization,
adoptive experiences for users
with different abilities and needs.
Next, privacy preventing technologies.
So the organizations implementing
these techniques achieve 35% higher,
35% higher trust scores through
data minimization architecture.
So using only essential
information for specific purposes.
If finance purposes, if finance companies.
Differential privacy implementation,
reducing privacy risk by 70% while
maintaining recommendation ance
within 5% of non-private baseless
through privacy utility optimization.
Finding the ideal balance between
protection and personalization.
There are three methodologies.
Guiding adoption includes federal
learning, the 45% of organizations.
Dis distributing computation
across devices to avoid
centralizing sensitive data.
Differential privacy.
These are 40% data of adoption,
adding calibrated noise to protect
individuals while maintaining a
aggregate insights on device processing.
Which is 60% adoption.
So keeping personal data on
user devices through edge
computing personalization Next.
The ROM measurement and business impact.
So the quantifying the business
impact of ization requires the
attribution intelligence frameworks, so
sophisticated measurements, approaches
that isolate true value creation.
So according to according to apps
Flyer organization implementing
advanced frameworks achieve 35%
highend marketing our way through
signal isolation methodology.
So distinguishing personalization effects
from background conversation noise, the
customer journeys now span off average
of 7.3, touch points across 4.2 distinct
cha distinct channels, creating what
experts term attribution complexity,
the challenge of accurately crediting
influence across fragmented interactions.
There is a different industries.
We have several impact on this.
The first one is financial
services impacts.
So it has four 24% higher conversion
rights through targeted financial
product recommendations and
personalized financial guidance.
So the next for retail Go, if you
see the retail growth, so which is
increased, like 20% increased purchase,
got increased frequently frequency
through customer specific product
offerings and pilot shopping experiences.
So if you, if we can see like
travel industry, so it increased
25, 20 6% higher bookings values
through destination specific offers
and personation travel packages.
Then attribution attribution intelligence,
so that what was measurement frameworks
yield 35% or 35% higher marketing our
way through signal isolation methodology.
So distinguishing personalization
effects from black room conversion noise.
So next the measurement
architecture models.
So here out of this, like the first
one is multidimensional attribution.
So the multidimensional attribution
systems provide visibility into conversion
influences through touchpoint valuation,
modeling, assigning proportional
credit across customer journey stages.
BGS 2024, global Consumer
personalization Survey.
Indicates organizations implementing
sophisticated attri attribution
models achieved return 2.5 times
higher than basic approaches
through casualty identification.
So the dis distinction, correlation from
true influence, the multitask attribution
frameworks enable friction conversion,
credit dividing value, cross contributing
touchpoint based on influence magnitude.
So this provides.
Visibility into three times
more conversion influences than
lost touch models by solving
the terminal bias problem.
Overvaluing the final interaction
while ignoring earlier influences.
So the next one, the casual
validation frameworks.
So incrementally the testing
incrementally incrementality testing
provides the rigorous validation through
control, experimentation, design.
The measuring lift again, as true
control groups, companies implementing
systematic testing achieve RA
3.2 times higher than correlation
based measurement By addressing
attribution inflation incorrectly
climbing credit for conversation
conversions that would occur naturally.
A coffeehouse company conducts
more 400 incrementally incre
tests annually demonstrating.
Personalized recommendations yield 2.5
x higher conversion rates contributing
to a 5% increase in same store.
5% increase in the same store sales
through preference match discovery.
Connecting customers with our
previously previously unconsented
option organizations typically identify
that 25 per 25 to 38% of conversions.
Previously contributed to marketing would
occur ar organically revealing significant
investment optimization opportunities
through more accurate measurements.
Next the customer journey in
intelligence, the customer journeys
now span an average of 7.3 touch
points across 4.2 distinct channels.
The creating what experts
term attribution complexity.
The challenge of accurately
accurately creating influence
across fragmented interactions.
Organizations with comprehensive
measurement achieve outcomes 2.8 times
higher than those with limited metrics.
The generally analytics frameworks,
the gene based gene based attribution
identifies 28% more conversion
influences than traditional models by
solving the interaction F blindness.
Failing to recognize how touch
points amplify each other.
An insurance company tracks over
eight 50 distinct journey patterns,
increasing personalized comp com
completion rates by 25% through
friction point personalization, the
targeting interventions at abundant pr.
Organizations with comprehensive
measurements achieve outcomes 2.8
times higher than those who limited
metrics through holistic impact
visibility, understanding effects
beyond immediate immediate conversion.
Next the relationship value architecture,
so the customer lifetime value, if
frameworks measures long-term impact
through relationship durability modeling
quantifying how the personalization
sentence the customer connections BCG
found that eight 68% of consumers develop
stronger brand loyalty when receiving
consistently personalized experiences
with 60% willing to pay premium prices.
Relationship impact presents the most
significant value driver with the
long-term loyalty, contributing 2.3
times more lifetime value than initial
conversation improvements through
compounding preference, satisfaction,
where each positive personalized
interaction increases future receptivity.
A beauty retailer measures 19 distinct
relationship metrics, increasing
customer return retention by 24%
through loyalty, trigger identification,
pinpointing specific personalization
element that strengthen relationships.
The next organization
enable implement systems.
GAR Nation implementing agile
testing methodologies achieved to
time to market three times faster
through rapid learning cycles.
Quickly interacting based
on continuous feedback.
The high performance conduct
seven point seven, seven times
more tests than low performance.
By adopting experimental mindset
cultivation, treating all First Nation
as a hypothesis requiring validation,
a financial services company developed
40 plus personalized journey.
E 28% improved computation,
completion rates through micro
movement intervention design.
Precisely targeting the points
within complex per processes.
Customers with hyper personal experiences
demonstrates 2.2 x higher net pro prompter
scores through x. Expectation, experience,
alignment, closing gaps between
customer hopes and actual experiences.
So then see next we can see like how
the future of hyper personalization.
So it has a two point five x returns for
organizations who, with the sophisticated
attribution models and the 35% higher RY
through at once attribution frameworks.
And a 22% revenue uplift average
across customer lifecycle.
So the hyper personation has
emerged as a critical competitive
differentiator across industries.
The fundamentally transforming
how organizational engage with
the customers through surface
care, technology, access, and ai.
Do what frameworks in as organization.
Navigate the complex balance
between enhanced experiences
and privacy considerations.
Those implementing comprehensive
attribution frameworks,
ethical AI governance, and
the specialized organization
structures demonstrate superior.
Venous outcomes.
So moving forward, the hyper robustness
will continue evolving toward AM means
indigenous with privacy, preserving
technologies and cross-functional
collaborations models by coming
increasingly essential elements of
successful customer engagement strategies
that create measurable venous impact
across the entire customer lifecycle.
So the hyper personalization as
emerged with the critical competitive
differentiator across industries,
fundamentally transforming how
organization engage with the customers
through sophisticated technology,
extra and AI develop frameworks.
The multi-factor value creation mechanisms
underlying successful implementation
from real-time data orchestration
to relationship durability modeling.
As organizations navigate the complex
balance between enhanced experiences and
privacy considerations, those implementing
comprehensive attribution frameworks
framework ethical AI governance and
specialized organization structures,
demonstrate superior business outcomes.
The article highlights how concepts lie.
Preference Cascade modeling, conceptual
trigger systems and privacy by design.
Frameworks create sub sustainable
comp competitive advances through
a improved customer understanding
and experience delivery.
Moving forward, the hyper person
will continue evolve toward ambient
intelligence with the privacy preserving
technologies and cross-functional
cross-functional collaborative use.
Now collaboration modeling becoming
increasingly essential when Microsoft
successful customer engagement strategies
that create measurable business impact
across the entire customer life cycle.
So that's how about the
hyper personization.
So thank you.
Thanks for giving you this opportunity.