AI isn't just a tool,
it's a cultural force.
And despite technological
advancements in ai, a constant
remains, and that is the human.
Now, this talk is about those humans
and the cultures they inhabit.
So today, I'm gonna take you back
into the 1980s when the research
in this book was being conducted.
This is Diana e Forsyth and
anthropologists who for about eight
years during the eighties and nineties,
there was a fly on the wall in four US
labs observing AI research in action.
Now these labs specialized in
creating medical AI tools like
building systems to help migraine
sufferers cope with their symptoms.
The question will be, has much changed
about the way we de design our AI systems
40 years later, I. This is what we're
gonna explore through the lens of Diane.
So Diana e exposed the power
dynamics at play in these labs,
and she gave us insights around the
perception of what tech work is.
Now, this talk isn't a historical
C, but it's going to be a warning
that if we don't change the way we
build this technology soon, we may
be doomed to make the same mistakes
that our grandparents of AI did.
So together today, I hope we can
cover the key lessons for building a
more inclusive, more responsible ai.
A little note about anthropology, just
in case you're not familiar with it,
it's not what Ross did from friends.
He's a paleontologist, and it's
not what Indiana Jones did.
He's an archeologist and a
pretty dubious one at that.
Hey, Indy, I hear the British
Museum is still hiring.
Now anthropology is the study of
human experience, so that's culture
and communities, including all
the work and tools that we use.
And then when you add tech
mix, this is called digital
anthropology or techno anthropology.
So digital anthropology is the
study of how we use and live with
technology from a cultural perspective.
Now, most of the work is done.
When conducting anthropology is things
like field work, so observing and
interacting with people to get a better
understanding of a person or a group.
And this is what Diana did.
So she would come into these AI
labs and she would observe them and
interview with 'em while they worked.
Oh, and if you can't cope with
not listening to an ai, talk
about picture of the Terminator.
I present you with an alternative
Lady Terminator, a 1980s Indonesia
film, where the main character
starts off as an a anthropologist.
Before turning into the Terminator.
It's a fantastic film.
Highly recommend it.
It's absolutely crazy.
Iman, in this day and
age, you speak of legends.
I'm an anthropologist.
Huh?
Iman, in this day age,
you speak of legend.
My ai an anthropologist, huh?
In this day and age, you speak of legends.
Anyways, I'm an anthrop anthropologist.
As Diana's research developed through
those eight years in the lab, she
became increasingly concerned about
the power dynamics influencing
the end product of that ai.
Namely that there was a lot of voices
missing from the creation of it.
So she explained that in conducting
anthropological research in these labs,
she was exposing key absent voices, as she
described this as speaking truth to power.
It wasn't always well received as speaking
truth to power, however, so while her
work earned her lots of accolades from
her fellow anthropologists and people
working in academia, it ruffled a lot of
feathers amongst the AI researchers that
she was observing in the lab as we'll.
See, perhaps if they paid a bit
more attention to the observation
she was making, maybe we'd
have better AI capabilities.
Now from one anthropologist
to another I'm Leanne Potter.
I'm your time traveling guide here
to connect Diana's work with the work
we're doing today in AI creation.
Aside from being an anthropologist,
I've also worked in tech for the
last 10 years versus as a software
developer and then pivoted into
cybersecurity, and I'm now currently
doing an MSC in AI and data science.
So Diana was once told that those
who ca code shouldn't be in the Lao.
Unfortunately, I think many people
in text still feel that way today,
but the danger is as soon as you
exclude, you delete the social.
But what does it mean
to delete the social?
Humans are intricate beings.
We're all layered.
We have history and culture.
We belong to multiple communities.
There's the family communities,
our friendship groups that
are local and national groups.
And of course work.
Going to work is a community
and a cultural event.
So whenever we interact with
anything or anyone, we carry all
this cultural tapestry around others.
And sometimes our cultural
experiences align.
And sometimes they clash.
And this also influences how
we engage with technology.
So to delete the social is to
remove what makes us human.
And those creating the tools that are
part of the social fabric too, they
have a significant impact on this,
even if sometimes they don't see it.
So Diana explored how the
researcher's own assumptions were
woven into the tools they created.
But she asked them how
they viewed their work.
Their answers were often very telling
there was doing AI and not doing ai.
So to them, this was doing ai,
which was writing code, problem
solving, building systems, but get an
anthropologist to observe for a while.
Then you are presented with this picture.
So this in order is what the AI
researchers actually did all day.
I'll give you a moment
to look through that.
So you can see it's there like lab
meetings research seminars, more meetings.
It looks like my diary.
At work, going to conferences.
And then on, on the other
side in the black background.
Teaching courses, taking courses,
writing papers doing admin.
This is what they actually did all day.
And as you can see, they were pretty
selective with what they called work
because right at the very bottom, even
though they themselves prioritize,
this is what they mainly do, the
thing they did least was writing code,
building systems and solving problems.
So all the social elements
of work were neglected.
The meetings, the engaging with other
people, they didn't see that as.
Doing real work.
So what does this omission
mean for the social elements
for the systems they've built?
Now, typically when you don't
value something like being social,
then you don't put any F into it,
or you can be really bad at it.
There was no good for the very and
this is like no good for the very
social tools that these technologies
will bring because these researchers.
Became often very shy and introverted
and describing an interaction.
She said, one expert even said, they
have dreadful communication skills
and that the technical skills far
exceed their need to be social.
In my experience, and probably in
yours too, we've all met technologists
who prefer tech over people.
But can you really succeed in delivering
good tech without good communication?
I. Now Diana's insights suggest
that better communication could have
prevented a lot of shelfware, and
we'll go into more of that later.
So if these AI researchers
didn't see meetings as work,
then what actually was work?
It was hard science and
seeking universal truths.
So anything outside the scientific
method wasn't valid for ai 'cause they
were building quantifiable codifiable.
Testable systems, believing only
technical solutions could solve
problems, coding and building were the
only legitimate AI work in their eyes.
With one research going researcher,
going so far to suggest that AI research
is something that you do sitting alone
in front of the computer for our zone.
So I say anything outside that
was considered pseudo work.
Sorry.
Meetings and discussions, for example.
Disciplines like anthropology, psychology
philosophy were all dismissed as soft
science or even unscientific with
no place in the lab's AI development
with this mindset that made Diana an
anthropologist work very challenging.
Despite being a highly educated doctor
herself, her work was seen as lesser.
One lab member even described
her as a Dictaphone with legs.
It wasn't easy being an anthropologist
in a technical space, and from
my experience, it still isn't.
So how does viewing their work as
a purely logical and scientific
endeavor delete the social?
It's twofold.
They fail to recognize that their
work is inherently social and it
takes place in a highly social
setting, which is the institution.
Their worldview is.
Decontextualize and idealize, they only
see their work for the aspects they
enjoy most and ideal not the reality.
Now, we all do this to an extent, but
this was skewing their worldview and in
turn influenced the products they were
building because their approach raised
the nuances of the human experience,
which is crucial for creating meaningful
AI systems, which are supposed to
replicate the human experience.
So the question is, if they don't value
the social elements of their own work,
what's stopping them from raising the
social aspects of other people's work?
Turns out not much.
And that's exactly what happened.
Now this brings up to the
section on power dynamics.
Now, the researchers were mostly male,
white, and from privileged backgrounds.
In the 1980s and nineties, they were
known as knowledge engineers and their
aim was to duplicate human expertise.
They saw knowledge as something to
extract, like a mineral or a disease
tooth and make that machine readable.
But how did this knowledge ac Accusa Accu?
How did this knowledge acquisition work?
Without today's masses amounts of
data, these researchers relied on very
manual data extraction, which often was
delivered through face-to-face views.
So these sessions, these interviews
would last for about one or two hours,
occurring once or twice a fortnight.
And they typically involved
a single expert coming in.
So maybe a heart surgeon, for
example, which was often another
white man in power whose expertise
was then taken at face value.
They relied on one specialist to reflect
the knowledge base of the entire topic.
So as a back to that heart surgeon
example, getting a heart surgery to
tell you everything they know about
heart attacks and building a system
from there, as you can imagine,
this opens up the potential of the
knowledge gaps, but also a lot of bias.
Researchers treated knowledge
as something that could be easy,
accessible with direct questions.
They weren't interested in what
really happened during heart surgery.
They wanted to know what
heart surgery was by the book.
Now Diana observed that even the
warmest of personalities would adopt
a really cold style during this
knowledge of citation or interviews.
And she would ask them, why
was em empathy switched off?
When you're interviewing people?
And one researcher replied, it just
seems like we're doing a technical task.
There isn't room for empathy.
The knowledge gathering process
for them was transactional.
It wasn't collaborative.
It was medical questioning.
It was really task orientated,
treating the expert as a brain to
be mind, not really to be engaged.
As I said, they weren't often very
good at interviewing, and some of the
experts that came in to give their
expertise often felt mistreated.
One, this is a direct quote,
someone saying that they felt
like they'd been treated like a
dog during the interview process.
Using cold methods to gather
data from people was ineffective.
The engineers blamed the experts
when they didn't get the desired
knowledge as well, and they failed to
recognize that a lot of knowledge isn't
universal or rule bound like coding.
Humans are stable entities
to be codified in absolutes.
We're just not.
And today, much of the data is
great from the internet and it's
sought by others and we know how
reliable online information can be.
And then, obviously we
have to make a judgment.
If you've seen the thumbs up, are
you happy with that response or not?
It's very easy to train a model
with reinforcement learning to also
give really rubbish answers because
the whole process of getting a good
response out of AI or a suitable
response is incredibly subjective.
Who am I to say that when I,
that what I've heard about.
Or given information about heart
surgery is good enough or not
good enough to go into the system.
For example, who am I to click?
Yes, well done.
Gemini.
Can you make sure you keep doing this?
And then that influences
everyone else's experience.
These activities in the ones Diana
observes are form, again, of deleting
the social because it's making judgment
calls about whose knowledge counts.
Creating a significant power dynamic,
a small group deciding what's important
for us to know is a form of power.
And these knowledge engineers
were very aware of that power.
But their end users were not.
So the doctor down the line who
was supposed to be using these AI
tools didn't know that this whole
software, this AI software, was
based on just a handful of sources.
And really that was best
endeavors, a handful of sources.
Usually it was, one
person or one textbook.
The knowledge engineer's power
was invisible to the end user.
And that is just like it is
today with black box models.
Imagine building a medical diagnosis
tool today that's based on that kind of
data set and that lack of transparency.
But maybe we're not too far off.
We might have a lot more data points, but
as the old others goes, shit in, shit out.
We don't always know of these
models we're interacting with
today are deleting the social until
there's a scandal, like the Amazon
recruiting tool or many other cases.
Now I think power is at its most insidious
when you can't see it or challenge it or
when we're given a false sense of security
that it's working in our best interests.
The knowledge engineers that Diana worked
with viewed knowledge in absolutes.
They were very comfortable
with sweeping the perspective
of others under the AI rug.
Not only that, actual end users,
clinicians who would eventually be using
these tools day in day out, were not
a part of the data collection process.
Nurses, for example, were not considered
value expert sources for medical
informatics According to these researchers
had absolute power in delineating who
counted in the build process and spoiler,
it usually looked like them, came
from the same schools and backgrounds.
They did.
So in doing so, they raised
various cultures, races, classes,
and genders to name a few.
Muting.
These voices caused both
ethical and practical issues.
Introducing challenges were still
contending with as we build AI today.
They didn't see their power as a problem.
However, the issue was a
problem with user acceptance.
After the 1970s AI winter labs were
thriving with funding and possibilities
build, building medical AI for clinicians
and patients with really few constraints.
And it sounds perfect, but it's
not quite because when you have
no constraints, you have no rails.
You don't have to adhere
to any guidelines.
And when you don't have any guardrails
or guidelines, you don't care about what
you build because if the money's gonna
come in anyways in your head, it's all one
step towards scientific mastery, right?
Just keep breaking things.
If the money's gonna keep flowing,
one, one of these things will land.
The consequence of blue Sky building
was that they didn't care if the
end users liked their products
or thought they were very useful.
Because at the end of the day, their
main goal was that they were doing ai.
As a result, nearly everything
that Diana witnessed in these
labs that these researchers built
ended up completely untouched
AI automation promises
today, as it did back then.
Quicker diagnosis is lower costs,
but nobody want to use these tools.
So when Diana asked about this,
why is all the tech that you know,
this AI tech that they've been
building not being used, where is it?
She was told it's all on the shelf.
They had literally built shelfware.
They were also looking in the wrong
place, is for answers to why this
kept happening, or as Diana said,
they genuinely were baffled by him.
She pointed out, but if the
physicians need these systems so
much, why aren't they using them now?
The problem was, is that these
systems just weren't seen as useful
either the researchers weren't
building the right systems or
not building the systems, right?
So Diana spent a lot of time
trying to figure out why.
She found that instead of
examining their own mistakes, the
AI researchers blamed the user.
They would call them things
like naive or computer phobic.
It was an end user problem, not
a problem with the tool itself.
So they believed because they
believed that these systems work fine
if you just know how to use them.
Diana pointed out to them, however,
that instead of blaming users, maybe
they should, realize the problem
is with the systems themselves,
not the people trying to use it.
That suggestion was dismissed.
So Diana observed that the researchers
blamed user acceptance instead of
recognizing the unusable systems.
And this is because of how they
perceived success and what success
was, because success did for them.
Wasn't tied to real life use usefulness.
One.
Scientists even claimed that
usefulness is not quantifiable.
So seeking feedback from users
was rare and the users weren't
observed using the systems.
What do you have?
Then?
You have a system that's
going to remain on the shelf.
Now, if you recall, I said earlier
that work is a social aspect.
It's a cultural social event.
It really is, and it's very nuanced.
So yes, a Dr.
May do heart surgery, but there is more to
their job than just doing heart surgery.
They have meetings, they
have consultations, they see
patients, they update records.
None of this stuff was any of
interest to these researchers.
However, despite the very activities,
creating barriers to making this actually
a successful soft pace of software.
Now you speak to a cian today.
They don't wanna be bogged down
with steps in an IT process.
They want to help patients.
This is a disconnect between AI
designers and real world users
deleting the social realities of work.
Remember, data gathered was often a
clinical engagement, pun intended,
between experts, medical question out.
And, they rarely set foot
in clinical settings.
One time I read in the book, she
asked a designer of one of these
AI systems and she said, have you
actually visited a hospital site?
'cause they were building
stuff in before this site.
And she said, have you
been to go see them?
And the researcher in astonishment said,
oh no I can't stand the site of blood.
So the clinician's real job processes
weren't part of the design either, and AI
teams rarely observed real life problems.
The AI tools that were built on engineers
knowledge or a single user experts
input, not specific data on in the
individuals who will actually be using
the systems and facing these problems.
Remember, humans aren't
like computer programs.
But I work like, think about if you were
to describe your day job, you'd miss so
many steps, would you be able to remember
that most of your day is meetings?
Would if you're a coder now or someone
working in ai, do you say that you, you
do more coding than going to meetings,
doing admin, little things like that.
Now, remember the AI researchers in this
case, the ones that Diana was observing
during the eighties and nineties.
They can't even grasp the
realities of their own day jobs.
So how are they going to imagine someone
else's that they've not even seen?
Now, work, as we all know, doesn't
follow official procedures.
We, I'm sure HR would love
them to, but they don't.
And these systems.
Miss the tactic knowledge and
like workarounds, and they lack
accommodation for real life complexities.
And as a result, knowledge falls off
a cliff, which is a term that the AI
researchers used when their systems hit
limits and faced unanticipated situations.
For example, one system suggests that a
male patient had an infection of post.
That can only occur if in pregnant
women, so they forgot to code
in that men don't get pregnant.
So Diana's conclusion was that
these engineers could choose what
goes into the knowledge base,
but focused on an ideal scenario.
And this made their systems fragile,
just like they only focused on the
ideal aspects of their own work.
They didn't recognize that humans.
And not typical.
And as such, systems need to be designed
knowing that people will deviate from
the ideal, will deviate from the script,
will deviate from the happy path.
Doing AI in the end really meant
that this powerful group was able
to delete the social and as a
result, limit this tool's potential.
But what else were they deleting?
Now the lab wasn't the labs that data
research weren't just made up of men.
In the 1980s and nineties, women
made up 8% of the academic computer
science profession in America.
Today, it's 15% go progress.
Women in the lab were often treated
as other in this male dominated field.
And I experienced something very
similar on a podcast recently where
they introduced me as Leanne Potter
female cybersecurity expert, to
which I responded, do you refer
to your male guest that way?
They quickly changed the introduction.
Now, Diana observed that women in these
labs were seen as second class citizens
and face teasing and sexual harassment.
In one instance, a file was placed on a
female worker's desktop that played the
orgasm scene from when Harry met Sally
on the loop and could not be stopped.
When Diana asked the woman
about it how she felt, she just
said, it's just male territory.
When Diana highlighted this gender divide.
Male lab workers often denied it or
dismissed their female colleagues
as being overly sensitive.
After all these scientists believe that
science was objective and culture free,
arguing that science is gender neutral.
Ergo, because they're scientists,
they obviously can't be sexist.
Yeah, surely we've made some progress
in recognizing women as significant
contributors to tech and the AI space.
Here is a snippet that really
hit home from the book, and
this is Diana commenting on
gender initiatives at the time.
So this is probably early nineties.
So she says, public efforts to
increase the proportion of women
in computer science is often
treated as a pipeline issue.
The idea is that encouraging more
girls and young women to study
science will solve the problem.
However, this overlooks the fact
that there are already women in this
field who face unequal treatment,
pipeline problem, getting girls
into tech and why women are
leaving tech is the culture.
How is this an issue still after
40 years, I. I would argue it
is more than disappointing.
It's actually dangerous.
Nothing much has changed, and with
AI technology moving so fast, we
don't have the luxury of another
40 years to get this right.
So we need to act now.
Now, Diana.
The anthropologist tragically passed
away in 1997 during a hiking accident,
and I feel like we are definitely
poorer for not seeing her work
continued in today's AI landscape.
I'm sure she would have
so much to say on that.
We need anthropologists to help
AI researchers who focus solely
on theoretical data by immersing
themselves in AI development.
Anthropologists can provide crucial
insights into the social, cultural,
and ethical dimensions of ai.
This bridges the gap between the technical
aspects and human experiences and
preventing harm because an outsider's
perspective is always valuable.
Diana said this about her work as an
outside observer, I have a different
perspective on the source of this problem.
Medical information systems are
not being accepted because they
do not meet the needs of the
consumers, and that the difficulty
in turn results in the way that.
In which the problem formulation,
system design, system building
and evaluation are understood and
carried out in medical informatics.
What I take away as an anthropologist
from Diana's Worth is that the main
problem of user acceptance was that
those creating the AI systems valued
the technology and its potential
more than the humans using it.
Let's not keep making that mistake
because we stand at a crossroads.
We should learn from the AI pioneers
of the eighties and nineties
and embrace this exciting air
landscape with the human in mind.
Otherwise risk not only AI harms and power
alignment, but also a lot of shelfware.
Now I'm hoping, ensuring your insights.
Showing her insights with you
today that you'd be tempted to
pick up a copy of this book.
This book is called
Studying Those Who Study Us.
I was lucky enough to start this
project with the blessing of
Diana's widow, who has been a great
source of support, insight, and
this is a picture of me and him.
He came to go see this talk we
presented for the first time.
And to prove that it's
a really small world.
After all, I was posting about the
work I was doing, do doing a deep
dive into Diana's research and
her niece got in touch with me.
She's a software developer and she's also
doing an AI safety course at the moment.
So it's great to see that AI
family tradition continuing.
So I had a call with Diana's niece,
and she was reading Diana's book at
the time, and I said, you know what?
In Diana's research really resonates
with her as a person working
in tech, but also someone who's
witnessing this new AI revolution.
And what she said was that the hypocrisy
is that a mostly male tech elite are
the ones telling us how dangerous AI is,
but they're also the ones in control.
The real danger then answer is
now isn't AI itself, but that
the people who have the power to
build it have great power indeed.
Diana said her work was about
speaking truth to power.
Now it's your turn.
Go build better.
Ai.
Thank you very much.