Speaker 21: All right.
Let's talk about how agile
transformation can help for a scalable
healthcare IT in the regulated IA era.
Healthcare organizations are under
immense pressure to modernize.
They are implementing interoperability
solutions, AI-assisted clinician decision
support, digital health pro- platforms
and regulatory initiatives, federal
mandates at an unprecedented pace.
The challenge now is that many
organizations are still using delivery
models designed for a slow, much
slower and more predictable world.
Today, we will explore why traditional
approaches are struggling and how agile
principles are evolving to support
the healthcare-specific needs, and
why agile has become a foundational
capability for safely deploying
AI-enabled healthcare solutions
Let's talk about
The challenges that healthcare IT is
experiencing is one of the largest
transformation in its history, right?
Organizations are simultaneously
managing electronic health record
modernizations, FHIR interoperability
initiatives, prior authorization
automation, population health programs,
AI-assisted clinical decision support,
regulatory compliance mandates.
Historically, organizations could spend
years together gathering requirements
before the implementation even begins.
That no longer works anymore.
Clinical workflows change, the regulations
change, the provider expectations
change, and technologies change.
All of these changes are occurring
at a fast pace where the existing
methodologies cannot scale up.
By the time a traditional project
reaches deployment, many assumptions made
during planning may already be obsolete.
This creates a significant
delivery challenge.
Now, how do we build a system fast
enough to keep pace with healthcare
innovation while also maintaining
compliance and patient safety?
Let's talk about the
cost of standing still.
Let's look the consequences of
maintaining traditional delivery models.
Many large healthcare programs
experience substantial schedule overruns.
Long implementation cycles often mean
that the organizations wait years
before realizing clinical value.
Meanwhile, requirements continue to
evolve throughout the project lifecycle.
In healthcare, a policy update, a
regulatory mandate, or a clinical
workflow change can invalidate
months of development effort.
The result is expensive rework
and delayed return on investment,
frustrated stakeholders, and missed
opportunities to improve patient outcomes.
The risk, the real risk isn't
simply the project delay.
The real risk is in delivering the wrong
solution after spending years or months
in building it Now let's talk about how
we can transition from Waterfall to Agile.
When people hear Agile, they often
think of stand-up meetings or two-week
sprints or the other ceremonies
that go with the word Agile.
But Agile transformation
is much larger than that.
It's a change in the work culture.
It's fundamentally changing how
organizations make decisions.
Waterfall assumes we can
predict everything upfront.
Healthcare, for that matter
of a fact, any or any other
domain doesn't behave that way.
Agile acknowledges uncertainty and
creates mechanisms to learn continuously.
Instead of waiting until the end of
the project to gather feedback, Agile
incorporates feedback every few weeks.
Clinicians, administrators, architects,
and compliance teams can evaluate
working software early and often.
This dramatically reduces the
risk of delivering something that
does not help-- m- that, that
doesn't meet operational needs.
Now look at-- let's look at the Agile
sprint cadence in the healthcare IT world.
This illustrates the
heartbeat of Agile delivery.
Every sprint follows a predictable cycle.
During planning, the team selects
the highest priority work.
Execution focuses on building
working capabilities.
Review sessions allow stakeholders
to evaluate actual functionality
rather than status reports.
Retrospectives create continuous
improvement opportunities.
What's important is healthcare-- in
healthcare is that clinical stakeholders
participate throughout the cycle.
Instead of seeing a solution after twelve
months, they see progress every few weeks.
This significantly improves
align- alignment between
technology and clinical operations
Agile just does not mean ungoverned.
There is a biggest misconception
across the industry that
agile reduces governance.
In reality, mature agile organizations
often achieve stronger governance
than traditional organizations.
Compliance is not something
that happens after development.
Compliance becomes part
of the development.
Some to code are the HIPAA controls,
access management, audit logging, data
lineage, and security requirements.
All of these become backlog
items and acceptance criteria.
When compliance officers participate
throughout delivery, organizations
avoid the costly cycle of building first
and discovering compliance gaps later.
This approach is especially critical
when deploying AI solutions where
explainability, traceability,
and accountability are essential.
Let's look at the
cross-disciplinary collaboration.
Healthcare IT projects are unique
because success depends on collaboration
across multiple disciplines.
Clinicians understand patient care,
developers understand technology,
data analysts understand information
quality, compliance experts
understand regulatory obligations.
None of these groups can
succeed independently.
Agile creates a framework where
these stakeholders collaborate
continuously rather than sequentially.
When clinicians validate workflows
sprint upon sprint, organizations
identify usability concerns early.
When compliance teams participate from
day one, regulatory risks are reduced.
This collaboration is one of the most
powerful benefits of agile transformation.
Let's look at the agile architecture
for AI-enabled clinical systems.
Now, let's connect agile with AI and
the large language models, which is
also popularly known as the LLMs.
AI introduces entirely
new delivery challenges.
Models can drift, predictions
can change, and bias can emerge.
Clinical recommendations may
have patient safety implications.
Unlike traditional software,
AI systems require continuous
monitoring and validation.
This makes iterative deve--
delivery even more important.
Agile provides just the right
framework needed to test assumptions,
validate outcomes, and continuously
improve AI-assisted workflow
Validating, how do we validate the AI
assisted workflows in short sprints?
This may be the most important slide
for an LL-- LLM conference audience.
Many organizations are
eager to deploy AI quickly.
However, deploying AI as a single
large release is extremely risky.
Imagine introducing an AI-based
clinical engine without clinician
feedback until the launch date.
The consequences could include
alert fatigue, workflow disruption,
or patient safety concerns.
A better approach is
incremental deployment.
First, shadow mode, then limited pilot
programs, then controlled expansion.
Each sprint becomes an opportunity
to validate model outputs, gather
feedback, and improve performance.
Agile effectively becomes the safety
mechanism for responsible AI adoption
Let's talk about the
incremental capability delivery
across the architecture.
Large healthcare transformations often
fail because the organizations attempt
to deliver everything simultaneously.
Agile encourages layered delivery.
Perhaps patient portals can be
delivered first, then comes the
interoperability AIs, then the
analytics ca-capabilities, and then
comes the AI-powered decision support.
Each layer creates value independently
while also establishing the
foundation for future capabilities.
This approach reduces risks, accelerates
adoption, and allows organizations
to demonstrate measurable progress
throughout the transformation journey
How do we build an agile-ready culture?
Technology transformation is
ultimately a people transformation.
The biggest obstacle is rarely
the technology itself, it's
the organizational behavior.
Successful agile transformations
require executive sponsorship, coaching,
training, and psychological safety.
Teams need the permission to experiment.
Leaders need to reward learning
than to punish the failure.
Organizations that celebrate small
wins create more mement-momentum.
Over time, those small wins will
compound into significant organizational
transformation Scaling agile
with the scaled agile framework.
Agile work exponentially well for
smaller teams, but healthcare programs
often involve hundreds of stakeholders.
This is where scaling frameworks such as
SAFe, which is also called as the scaled
agile framework, becomes more valuable.
SAFe introduces release trains, agile
release trains, which is called as ART,
and program increments to coordinate
multiple teams around shared objectives.
Instead of independent group working in
silos, organizations synchronize planning,
delivery, and dependency management.
For large healthcare initiatives
involving interoperability, AI,
analytics, and clinical operations,
this coordination becomes essential
The common pitfalls in healthcare
agile transformation is
something that we will look at.
Not every agile transformation succeeds.
Several common pitfalls emerge repeatedly.
Few of the top pitfalls to quote
are resistance to change, misaligned
stakeholder expectations, insufficient
DevOps capabilities, and treating
compliance as an afterthought.
Organizations often adopt agile ceremonies
without embracing agile principles.
They conduct stand-ups but still make
decisions using waterfall thinking.
True transformation requires changing
mindset, governance, and organizational
culture, not just the process terminology
How do we measure success in the
healthcare IT using the agile framework?
If we can't measure success,
we can't manage transformation.
Traditional projects often focus
solely on schedule and budget.
Agile introduces additional metrics
some of them to code our time to
value, sprint predictability, defect
escape rates, and compliance coverage.
For AI-enabled healthcare systems, we
may also track model accuracy, clinical
adoption, alert acceptance rates, false
positive rates, and provider satisfaction.
The goal is to measure
outcomes, not just the activity
The key takeaways and next steps are
something that we can walk through.
If you remember only four things
from today's presentation,
then let them be these.
First, healthcare delivery
environments are changing too
rapidly for traditional waterfall
approaches to catch up and react.
Second, compliance must be
embedded throughout delivery
and not reviewed at the end.
Third, AI-enabled clinical
systems require incremental
validation and continuous learning.
And fourth, scalable healthcare
transformation depends on an
architecture and operating model
designed for iterative delivery.
Agile is no longer simply
a software methodology.
It is becoming the operating model
that enables healthcare organizations
to innovate safely, rapidly, and
responsibility in the age of AI
Thank you for your time and attention.
As healthcare organization continue
adopting AI and LLM-powered
solutions, the question is no longer
whether we should move faster.
The question is how we move faster
while preserving tus- trust, safety,
compliance, and clinical effectiveness.
I strongly believe Agile
provides the framework that
makes that balance possible.
I would be more than happy to answer
any questions you may have, and thank
you for giving me this opportunity.
Thank you.