Hi everyone.
my name is Marish Bal and I am going
to talk about agent automation and
how it's going to change, the world
of business process operations.
today.
Excited about the topic and a
pleasure to be in front of you.
Let me tell you a little
bit about, myself.
I'm currently based in Texas,
had an opportunity to work with,
various firms, global system
integrators, as well as startups.
In India, Australia, and here in the us.
like most of you, I
started off as a developer.
Probably I'm, I was not
as good as you guys are.
and switched over to consulting
very quickly after my MBA and then,
had, stints in account management.
As a sales hunter, here in the US
for, it's been about close to 12,
13 years that I've been, in sales
and, and, business development.
The current role that I have
is probably a mix of everything
that I've done in the past.
I'm a GTM lead for one of the key
generative AI agent tech, automation
offerings at, AWS Excited to tell you.
More about it and what, this, this
technology is going to unfold in the
sphere of business process operations.
On a lighter note, I feel, it's time.
From the point where we are, to a
point where toasters start talking
to you and potentially, start
giving us relationship advice.
but it's not too far too.
so let's be prepared with that.
now I. Going to a little serious problems.
Right?
what's happening in enterprises?
I have a chance to work
with lot of, customers and,
companies that, that are large.
And what I have seen over the past few
years is that most enterprises have
tons of applications, and some of those
applications are productivity apps.
Many are ERP apps.
Off the shelf apps, custom apps,
you name it, and they have it.
unfortunately many of these
applications don't talk to each other.
And how do we solve that problem?
we absolutely need to
integrate these applications.
So how do we do that?
The solution is people.
Let's throw people at the problem
and let people act as a glue and let
people run the applications and the
processes that layer on top of that.
But what happens because of this is the
fact that, the people get frustrated.
They are stuck in mundane, repetitive
jobs, which they don't like.
and they really don't have any
time for process improvement.
They don't have time to talk to
their customers and, think about
what more they can achieve for them.
And as a result, everyone
becomes an, less productive.
So how do we solve that problem
has been, one of the key issues
that's been grappling the large
enterprises all over the world now.
There has been a solution.
We have been thinking about automation,
and when I'm talking about these,
processes, I'm talking about the,
the processes that enterprises run.
So I'm talking about the
white collar processes.
I'm not talking about the industrial
processes and industrial manufacturing.
I'm talking about processes like.
An invoice process.
For example, I'm talking
about sales order processing.
I'm talking about claims processing
in healthcare and in insurance.
I'm talking about those kind of processes.
Now, automation has always been a
solution and there are various flavors
of automation, When I say various
flavors of automation, what I mean is
there is robotic process automation.
Many of you probably have
heard of that technology.
it's, it's a great technology if you
want to solve a simple problem and
you need some rules based engine to
automate a business process, fantastic.
but then RP has its challenges.
It is fragile in nature.
It doesn't lend well itself for.
Complex processes where there
is unstructured data requires
a big infrastructure footprint.
API integration is of course a
domain of, developers when it
comes to adopting API integration.
One of the biggest challenges is the
legacy apps don't even expose API.
So how do you deal with that?
document processing?
All of us know that in the last few years.
Document processing has increased
and has unfolded like a beast.
and what I mean by document
pro, what I mean by document
processing is processing of.
PDFs to clean insights from
those PDFs, from images that are
circulating across, enterprises.
And then there are, low-code,
no-code technologies.
Data integration has
been there for a while.
machine learning models have been
existing and now, LMS are also being used.
interestingly in back office,
front office, and middle office
processes, which is where most of the
productivity is locked now because
of all this, it's a challenge.
How do you make it simple?
And that's when you know, we
have agents to the rescue.
What are agents that, this is what, talk
of the town is, everyone wants to talk
about agents, but what are these agents.
In the simplistic terms, and most of
you have probably, dabbled in this space
and you are trying to, work with agents.
For me, I have a very simple example.
This is a beautiful, graphic that I found
on, vectorize.io, thanks to the creators.
what this graphic shows in the
simplest of terms is there is an
LLM as a foundation of an agent.
And think about LLM as a brain.
there is, an orchestration,
which means there is an input
that you need to provide.
And that input can come from a web
app, can come from chat, it can
come from a mobile app, wherever.
And then there is the last layer where
you need to provide tools for the
agent to actually accomplish something.
Just like how, you need
a ax to cut the wood.
For the lack of a better example here,
in this case, you would need tools.
And the tools in this
case can be, a web portal.
It can be an application, it
can be a knowledge base, it can
be some business logic that's
embedded, can be a SaaS platform.
It can even be user interaction.
This is how the agents are structured.
Now, it sounds fantastic on
paper, but is it easy to deploy?
that's a question mark.
Again, you have, APIs, who's
going to build those APIs?
Are there common standards?
No, vector dbs.
Some of us may be, really ninjas at
Vector db, but what about the others?
the commoners.
so it's a complex technology to implement,
easy to understand, because all the magic
is anyway done by the LLM reasoning.
But then there are a lot of issues that
we need to understand before we go about
implementing the agent architecture.
And the next thing is, are
these agents sufficient enough?
Can you just implement agents
across the organization and.
Let them, do their trick and automate
very complex business processes that
are, executed by hundreds of people.
That's another question mark.
So how do we take it to the next level?
And that's where.
Lamb, comes into the mix.
What is lamb?
Lamb is a large action model.
what is a large action model?
I try to keep it really simple, right?
LLM is, the brain.
and if I call LLM, the brain, the large
action model is Braun and the whole,
gist of a large action model is in
its name that it takes actions, LLMs
understand, understands and summarizes.
another thing about lambs is that.
Many of the lambs and a great
example of that is computer use from
anthropic operator from open ai.
these are trained with specific
integration with certain tools like
browsers, to automate and execute
certain tasks, based on natural language.
So lamb absolutely sounds more powerful.
But the problem is, if you tell the
lamb to perform certain actions in
a series of steps, like 70 or 80
steps, it may not be able to do it.
A four or five step process like book,
me, a nice Italian dinner in a restaurant
in New York at 7:00 PM on, right before
Thanksgiving, when the week is crazy.
And then also book me a couple
of tickets for a Broadway show.
It can very well do it.
It may also even ask you follow up
questions and get clarifications.
But when it comes to executing
a complex business process,
then it becomes challenging.
And, then how do we do that?
How do we even, crack that puzzle?
Now, that is where, What we need to do
is we need to think about orchestration.
How do we execute processes with lambs,
with LLMs, with document processing,
with API, integration with, low code,
no code, and put all of that together.
And that is, I think, the secret sauce.
And as developers, we need to think about
how do we put that mechanisms together?
Are there any solutions in the market?
Because if we are able to do it, we
can automate very complex processes.
something of what I've written
here, invoice processing, claims
processing, and these processes sound
simple, but in large enterprises.
Fortune 500 fortune thousand companies,
hundreds, if not thousands of people
are engaged in these processes.
you will not believe, there are banks
and financial institutions where 300,
500 people, thousand people are engaged
in doing just, anti money laundering
checks, know your customer checks.
Those are the processes where
productivity is absolutely required.
what is the value?
McKinsey estimates the value to
be garnered from automation of
these processes using generative
AI is close to 2.6 to 4.4 trillion.
They, of course, estimate, estimate
the total economic potential, but
it, these are staggering numbers
and this is all achievable.
If you think about the US healthcare,
there is the whole, the money spent on
healthcare in the US is $4 trillion.
Guess what?
How much of that is waste?
$1 trillion because of inefficient
processes, and if we are able
to use agents and generative AI
technology to its maximum potential.
We should be able to cut that down.
And that is precisely what we want.
So these are the things that
we need to be, cognizant of
that the impact is massive.
We can do a whole lot with
the Asian tech technology.
it may sound complex, but the best part
is the technology's getting mature.
The price of, the foundational
models is dropping.
So it's a no-brainer that we got
to use that in what we are doing.
I just want to leave you as, developers to
think about some of the key challenges of
putting all these technologies together.
The large action model, LLMs with a
view to automate a business process.
The first one I mentioned earlier,
orchestration of services.
while you have these multiple tools.
How can you seamlessly orchestrate
them to achieve the desired
impact and the business outcome?
Because if I am a business user who's,
worried about, managing the benefits
administration process in, my HR role.
I really don't care what
technology am I using.
I care about the outcome
and how it is orchestrated.
What is the transparency in the process?
Can I check how my work
item is progressing?
What is the output
that's coming out to me?
What are the analytics?
Am I measuring the right metrics?
That's what I care about.
I don't care about technology.
As developers, we need to make sure
that we need to put, an orchestration
layer, which can make these,
technologies integrate together.
Complex, no, no doubt.
While LLMs mask a lot of complexity, but
putting the governance, the responsible
AI and the guardrails is absolute must.
Without that, you cannot really
build the trust that is required with
your business partners as well as,
the leadership and you will never
be able to execute key processes.
Think about it.
Will you be okay with a 90%
accuracy in a process that
processes your monthly paycheck?
You will not be, these are
deterministic processes.
I. You will have to have the trust
that every single time the process gets
executed and you get your check, the
numbers are right, every single cent is
appropriate, and that is where you need
auditability, governance, responsible ai.
And lastly, all these processes.
While great, we understand that
LLMs have a tendency to hallucinate.
We need human in the loop for certain
edge cases so that we understand,
humans, verify the output and then
let those transactions through.
And lastly, the most important thing
in this whole agent take automation
initiative, if at all, you embark on that.
Is the fact that we need to have
appropriate change management.
This is a cultural change.
We need to advise, your
leadership, what kind of, Approach.
They need to take, they need
to be open to technology.
Some of the earlier govern governance
principles, archaic, security
policies, they will not work.
We need to work top down, bottom up to
change the culture of the organization
to welcome agents into the workforce,
and we should be okay to work
alongside certain digital employees.
who are going to assist us, make us
more productive and make us deliver
more for less for our customers.
That is the message that
I want to leave you with.
if you want to connect with
me, please ping me on LinkedIn.
I'll be happy to chat.
always love to contribute
to the community.
And, lastly I want to call out that what
I presented is all my personal opinion.
I have, had that
disclaimer, right up front.
none of this reflects my
employer's, stance on any of
these technologies or the markets.
this is entirely my personal opinion.
Thank you again for the opportunity and
look forward to engaging with you again.
Truly appreciate, this, thank you so much.