Speaker 29: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Conf forty-two.
I'm Prateek Mittal, director of product
at Harness, and we have been a keynote
sp-sponsor for many events working
alongside Conference forty-two this year.
And today, I'm excited to talk
about shipping with context and why
knowledge graphs are becoming backbone
of AI-first software delivery.
AI is changing how software is
getting written, but writing code
faster is only part of the challenge.
The harder question is whether AI
can understand what that code means
inside the context of an organization.
For example, the services it touches, the
risk it introduces, the teams responsible
for it, the policies it need to follow,
and the production systems it may impact.
In this talk, we will explore
why knowledge graphs are
becoming a foundational layer
for AI-first software delivery.
As engineering environments become
more complex, critical context is
often fragmented across SDLC such
as CI/CD pipelines security tools,
observability platforms, cloud infra,
various types of ticketing systems.
Now, without that connected context,
AI agents can generate outputs,
but they struggle to make reliable
and well-governed decisions.
In this talk, we will discuss how
knowledge graphs differ from traditional
observability platforms, and how they
help AI agents reason across the software
delivery life cycle, and why shared
context is becoming essential for DevOps,
SecOps, FinOps, and platform engineering.
We'll also cover the role of policies,
guardrails, RBAC, and governance in
making enterprise AI systems trustworthy.
The next bottleneck in AI
adoption will not be model
capability, it will be the context.
So let's dive in.
Today, the biggest challenge in
enterprise AI is the context.
So if you see in this particular slide,
there are four different sections, right?
The data is siloed and only
trapped in disparate systems,
which is inaccessible to AI.
Sometimes that is by process or
sometimes due to technical constraints.
Even though, let's say, you have
the data exposed, if your AI agents
does not understand the domain
knowledge, then generic LLM- LLMs
don't understand those company-specific
jargon or unique processes, which
creates a risk of hallucination, where
ungrounded AI can lead to incorrect,
misleading information, right?
And also, all this data which is
getting exposed can also cause a
sensitive data with external models,
which is going to impose a significant
compliance threats to the end enterprise.
So these are like big four challenges
which we feel are very important
and we see them in our day-to-day
conversation with our customers.
Now, there are two patterns
of DevOps been emerging.
One is AI-assisted DevOps, and
another one is AI operational DevOps.
Now, AI-assisted DevOps is where AI
is helping humans to writing code,
configs, runbooks, and also injecting
those context manually via prompts.
And human is becoming the
primary safety system on that.
But to leverage the most value out
of this AI agents, now AI should
act within that delivery system.
AI should be able to pull that
context automatically from a
shared model and should be able
to perform checks, simulation, and
policy evaluation before acting.
Now, with the power of knowledge graph,
the context will become queryable,
not conversational, and that safety
layer will move away from humans,
but it will become a system default.
Think that AI will become partner
to you, and knowledge graph is an
enabler in that Now let's understand
what does a knowledge graph means
or what does a context means, right?
So the way we understand knowledge
graph is there are different
core entities, the nodes.
So think about your data such
as service, pipeline, build,
deployment, incident, cloud cost.
These are all nodes which are disparate
systems disparate nodes in your system.
And your events becoming the connectivity,
the tissue connection between these two.
So for example, build event,
a deployment event, a runtime
action which has happened.
But your information just not get
built just in this first-party
data, but you will also be
needing some third-party data.
Think about the data coming
from your GKE or your GCP for
your logs and others, right?
And that's where the critical
relationship, the edges have to be
connected, and that's where the services
is depending on another service.
Deployment is triggered by a
commit which has been executed,
and then service is owned by teams.
All these critical relationships
need to be built and understood.
And that's the power of knowledge graph.
It's not just these entities sitting
in silos, but then there's a semantic
layer which is actually powering
this connectivity between the nodes,
and then you are able to get that
data and able to execute upon.
Now, there are m-- as we saw about
what are the context of that knowledge
graph is, then there are, like, some
method to build that knowledge graph.
So for example, the initial
part is to extract the entity.
So for example, think of
your services user incidents.
Then you can actually enrich that
with the metadata such as who owns
that service, who owns that users who
owns that incidents, and then what are
their version, what are their policies.
On top of that, we need to provide
the relationships, the links
between those relationships.
For example, who owns what
and what depends on what.
Once we are able to do that,
you can expose those via
graph API for agents to query.
And we believe that if context is
the new code, knowledge graph is
the compiler in this AI agentic era.
So we have seen that how knowledge
graph can be very successful,
but let's see how and where the
knowledge graphs can fail, right?
The primary reason for knowledge
graph to fail is incorrect use cases.
For example, when you are able to build
a knowledge graph, but if you don't
know what are the well-defined use
cases you're able-- you're trying to
solve, that will be always going to give
a wrong ROI or you'll not be able to
extract the complete value out of it.
Now, those not well-defined
or incorrect well-defined use
cases can lead to over-modeling.
You might be able to build a beautiful
ontology, but there will be zero usage.
You can also do under-modeling, which
could be you have flat data, no meaningful
relationships between those data.
Or your data could be stale, which means
a user is looking for a da- for an output
of current context, but you are actually
providing context thirty days prior or
maybe six months prior, which, which is
not the ideal input to your AI agent.
And that's where we feel these are the
areas where knowledge graphs can fail.
Now, maybe let's jump into how
this knowledge graph can be--
has been built inside Harness
and what we are looking into it.
So we'll quickly jump into our demo.
So this is one of my account, and then
what I'm going to do is we have an AI
agent here, and then what I'm going
to do is I'm just going to ask for
it to run some queries for me, right?
So initially when I come here, I can
ask saying that, "Hey, can you list
all my pipelines inside this account?"
This is my demo account where I'm
able to list all these pipelines.
So if you think here we have integrated
with different LLMs here, but what's
happening here is it's trying to reason
between saying that, "Hey, I can try
to list the organization first, then
projects," and then based on that, it's
able to identify what is my what is
my default project, and based on that,
it's able to bring those pipelines.
Which is good, right?
It is a simple API call or from that
perspective, able to figure that out.
But let's say I have more and more
pipelines which are across accounts.
It could be that, hey, I have
more than thousand pipelines in
my particular account, and it is
disparate or distributed among
multiple teams, multiple organizations.
That's how the big enterprises
are are structured.
In that case, I can come up saying that,
"Hey, I am a a exec," or, "I'm a CTO,
and I want to understand hey, what are my
different pipeline executions happening
in my current account, and also, what are
those pipeline execution with the highest
failure rates and common failure pain
point-- common failure points so that
I can actually go ahead and act on it?"
So let's see if we are able to identify
those kind of insights from Harness.ai
as well as using knowledge graph.
So here, if you see it's able to
understand this is a complex query,
and it's saying that, "Hey, I need to
query the knowledge graph with SQL,"
which means it's able to understand
that I need to go across the different
accounts, and then I also need to
understand which are the pipelines
with the highest failure rate and what
are the common failure point-points.
So it is actually able to
understand the question.
It's invoking the knowledge graph tool,
what we have, and it's going through
different orgs and different projects
inside that account to understand what
kind of pipelines are being failing.
Now at this point of time, it is able
to validate those queries, and then
it's able to execute these queries
individually to get the detailed results.
Yeah.
So it's able to figure it out a bunch
of pipelines and then bunch of issues
why those pipelines are failing.
So let's go into the output.
So it has actually thought for sixty-nine
seconds, and based on that it has come up
with… in this particular project, I have
these two pipelines and which are failing
a hundred percent, which means I can--
I should go and-- go ahead and fix them.
And the most common is it's missing
those connectors, then it is
also having some build failures.
The best part is I have not
asked for recommendation, but
it has also come up with some of
the recommended actions, right?
That why these pipelines are failing and
will you be able to go ahead and fix that.
So it's also asking, "Would you
like me to help you diagnose any of
these failed execution in detail or
create the missing connector?" We can
actually diagnose further, but in the
benefit of time, I would like to take
you guys to another section of this.
Let's say, once we have this kind of
data out, you want to visualize this.
Then we have another offering
inside Harness where we call it
as dashboard, and it's the same
output which we have seen here.
Now we want to visualize this, right?
So what I'm saying is okay, fair,
you have given me these many
pipelines, and this is the output.
Can you help me create a
dashboard out of this data?
In the benefit of time I have already
created a dashboard beforehand
for that particular prompt.
And it's actually gonna do, say me like,
"Hey, what are these different executions?
What are the failures?
How many time it has failed?
What is the execution?" Now, the
best part about this is I've actually
did this for over thirty days.
That's why the data you are seeing
on the chat versus on the dashboard,
it's a little different because I'm
actually creating a time series of
all the pipelines executions which has
failed over the thirty days, right?
And just to explain how
this dashboard has come.
It's still invoking our
knowledge graph agent.
On top of it, we also have a dashboard
agent, so it's actually orchestrating
these agents to understand the queries.
Sorry, to build the queries and
then run the queries, and then after
that, it's actually build a thirteen
widgets dashboard here, right?
And it is-- this is a prior one, but
it is actually creating a new one.
So this is the new dashboard
it is pu-putting around, right?
Now let's say if I don't want to…
if I want to change this, I can
actually go ahead and change it
the executions to three months.
So for example, I can always go and
say that, "Hey, change the executions
to three months," so the executions
type and number of executions
which has been done will vary.
So this is one of these method where
I can understand what has happened
inside my account, specifically across
modules, across entities, across nodes,
and able to decipher what is going
wrong and if I need to remediate as
well as if I am a-- if I need to fix it.
Another thing I just wanted to point
out, this particular instance is more
about our first party data with Harness.
But to work the knowledge graph
end to end we shall-- we should
be we should be doing more and
more integration with other tools.
What I mean is we should… Let's say we
need to integrate it, we have to integrate
it with things like Jira, ServiceNow
GKE AWS for Kubernetes logs and others.
So if you are able to do that, you will be
able to bring a really powerful knowledge
graph, and that will really be a powerful
system to solve your customer use case.
So I just wanted to thank Conf forty two
for this opportunity, and hopefully this
was interesting to all the listeners.