Speaker 27: Hi, everyone.
I'm Vijay Lakshmi Narsimhan.
Today, I'll be speaking about responsible
AI product management for production
large language model life cycle.
The key idea is simple: LLM products
cannot be managed exactly like
traditional deterministic software
because it's totally undeterministic.
Once they move into production, we
need product practices that account
for uncertainty, trust, safety,
compliance, and continuous monitoring.
Over the next thirty minutes, I'll
discuss how product managers can balance
innovation with governance while building
AI products that users can trust.
All views and opinions discussed in
this presentation belongs solely to
me and do not reflect any views or
opinions of the company I represent.
Many organizations are moving fast from
LLM experimentation to real production
use cases because the real challenge comes
in when you push the code to production.
But the product life cycle
often has not caught up.
Traditional product development life
cycle assumes predictable outputs,
stable behavior, and clear paths of fail.
LLM systems behave differently.
Their outputs can vary, drift over
time, and create risk around biases,
explainability, privacy, and user trust.
If you look at last few years, almost
every enterprise has followed the same
journey: build a chatbot, proof of a
concept, impress stakeholders, and then
face the real challenge of deploying
the code safely to production at scale.
A hallucinated answer in
the demo may be acceptable.
A hallucinated answer in production
can become a compliance, finance,
or even a reputational problem.
The core problem is that LLM introduce
probabilistic behavior into products
that is totally undeterministic.
You cannot predict the behavior.
This means we cannot only
ask, does the feature work?
We also need to ask, is it fair?
Is it safe?
Is it explainable?
Does the user of this particular product
can trust the data that we represent,
the behavior that we represent?
Can we audit it?
And can we explain to somebody on the
metrics that we monitor even after launch?
Traditional fo-- software is--
follows certain steps, which is very
deterministic to answer these questions
while building the product itself.
The same input usually
produces the same output.
LLM behaves differently.
Prompts, context, different sources, the
model setting can influence responses
across different model that we're using.
Product teams must learn to
manage uncertainty rather
than assume predictability.
Product managers do not need
to become an ML engineers to
understand the LLM characteristics.
However, they need to own the
product level risk, understand the
end-to-end system, the user journey
associated with it, the behavior that
LLM is gonna emit based on the use
cases and the intent they define.
That includes defining use cases
clearly, ident-identifying failure modes,
figuring out all the safe compliance,
trust li-related requirements that
user's gonna trust the data, experience,
as well as the overall behavior that
LLM is gonna converse with the user,
aligning with the s-stakeholders,
and making sure governance is built
into the roadmap from the beginning.
This is truly shifting left by
design, trust, safety, security
should be part of the roadmap as
we design the systems using LLM.
This represents a shift from the
feature ownership to outcome ownership.
Success is not simply shipping features,
success means delivering trustworthy
outcome that users can depend on.
That's purely working
on based on reputation
Responsible AI across the product
life cycle, development life cycle
should appear in every stage.
We identify user needs, problems,
risk associated with it.
During planning, we define
safety, fairness, and compliance
requirements along with the problem.
During development, product manager
has to build controls and documentation
around the controls to evaluate
the risk around the behaviors.
That also plays a crucial role as an
evaluation framework to validate whether
are we satisfying the requirements or
are we satisfying the requirements safely
so that we meet all the requirements.
During the validation, we test
our biases and robustness.
After launch, we continuously
monitor the behavior and user impact.
Consider there is an assistant.
Discovery identifies safety risk.
Planning identifies all
the requirements around it.
Development adds all the evaluation
criterias while implementing it,
making sure those criterias are met.
Validation includes validating those
criterias against the behavior.
Monitoring includes recommending
the quality, learning through the
experience so that it is continuous.
Responsible AI spans across entire life
cycle For LLM products, requirements
should go beyond functional behavior.
A strong AI requirement might say
the system must provide explainable
responses, cite sources where
appropriate, and protect sensitive data.
This allows to use both human
intelligence decisions and also
log decisions for auditability.
This also helps human to
validate how the system behaves
based on different responses.
Even if the sources are changed,
the behavior should be appropriate.
The data behind it need to be secured.
LLM, which is accessing the data,
should have proper access control
on what interpretation it could do,
what kind of outcome it can take.
Many organization then makes a
mistake writing only the functional
requirements because traditionally
non-functional requirements are not
prioritized over functional requirements.
However, defining an LLM system and the
product around it, trust, compliance,
security is a functional requirement
because that has reputational trust
and user user behavior is purely depend
on how LLM is gonna provide the data,
how the LLM is gonna behave based on
the user inquiries and the responses.
Trust-aware requirements transform
abstract concepts such as
fairness, explainability into
measurable expectations Compliance
should not be something we add
after the product is built.
For AI systems, compliance is by design
means identifying regulatory, privacy,
security, and ethical constraints early.
This is purely depends on the behavior
that LLM is gonna emit based on the
requirements and the constraints.
Even though you're gonna use different
models across Claude, GPT, Flash,
any different models, even the local
models, identifying the intent and the
behavior associated with the problem
is the best way to solve, instead
of only relying on the LLM, the best
option to choose an LLM, and it is
gonna behave according to the needs.
The PM job is to translate these
constraints into product decisions,
acceptance criteria, and also gates for
AI to be evaluated across each and every
requirements and the intended behavior.
For example, we have a financial ad--
we have a financial advisory assistant
may require more data around the
transaction, domain context, audit
logs, and decision traceability.
Designing these capabilities early
is significantly less expensive than
retrofitting them later because auditing
from end to end is a really challenging
aspect, especially when the AI comes in,
because there is a combination of AI and
human as part of this journey to validate
whether AI is taking a right behavior.
So audit should be continuous audit
emitter, so to differentiate between
what AI is still doing, what are
the decision that AI is taking, is
it against the evaluation criteria,
and whether it's satisfying.
Governance artifacts
help create transparency.
Model cards can describe intended
use cases, limitations, evaluation
results, and known risks.
Data ex-- data should explain
the origin, how it was collected,
the purpose, the limitation.
And it does not only explain what
data it is, there should be clear
documentation and semantics around
what this data can literally do
and what AI can do with that data.
AI can simply read the data, provide that
as a response or lot of LLM models does an
interpretation based on the based on the
meaning, based on the attention vector.
Simply the meaning that is
closely associated with the
data, LLM does interpretations.
Different LLM models does different
interpretation, so this semantics
around the data is crucial when
user is gonna use a product where
the data is heavily involved.
This way, the user who's gonna use the
product also can make a better decision.
But the people who is building the product
also know this is safe, the data is
leveraged in the way that is intended to
be, and it shows transparency and support
accountability across the organization
Traditional validation is not
enough for the LLM products.
We need use case-based, scenario-based,
behavior-based validation, totally biased
test- testing across different behaviors.
Certain behaviors that is operating
within internal data might
be really safe and risk-free.
However, if that internal data is
reference-centered in some way where
external agents are gonna use it,
that's where the risk comes in.
So behavior is a key.
So the scenario-based validation helps
us to test different scenario, the
behaviors that LLM emits, and also
this is a good way to validate the
overall quality of the LLM responses
based on different scenarios.
And this will help to validate one more
bigger challenge, which is hallucination.
Recent models including Claude, GPT,
the hallucination is far better because
of the temperature tuning and the
reasoning behind the data training.
However, if you have enormous amount
of data, LLM still tends to hallucinate
because of the interpretation and the
semantics that I mentioned earlier.
So scenario-based testing is heavily
involved in understanding the use cases,
scenarios that a LLM has to understand
so that this interpretation is right.
That's one of the behavior
constraint as well.
A useful question is not whether the
model will fail, but how will it fail?
What are the reasons for the failure?
What LLM can do to rectify those failures?
Can LLM learn to do that so
that the interpretation and
there is a continuous learning?
Teams, product teams who is
building the products around LLM
need to test all the edge cases.
Typically, we ask LLM to provide
all those edges, edge cases as
well to ensure the coverage.
Provide ambiguous prompt, ask LLM to
rectify it because we cannot expect the
same prompts across different users.
Context and perspective for a same problem
might be different for different people.
As a human, we have a logic and reasoning
skill, so the prompts that we provide
to the LLM might be totally different
and LLM ha- might have different
responses for the same problem, so
ambiguous prompt testing is very crucial.
Adversarial scenarios.
Take complex scenarios, even
trivial scenarios, trying to see
the outcome is not perfection,
but the behavior is predictable.
We are all, We, we know that it's
gonna be totally undeterministic.
However, we wanna make sure
that LLM has behaved in the same
way for the same scenario, even
it is repeated multiple times.
The responses that it's formulated might
be different, but the outcome is all same.
LLM behavior can change because
models are updated, prompts evolve,
data changes or user interaction
in an ex-- unexpected way.
Like we quoted before, for a same problem,
different people would have different
prompts because their perspective on
that problem is totally different.
One can say a simple query, provide
me answer for this particular
problem, and they can provide
a very detailed information.
This is my problem.
This is what I know.
These are the information that I
do not really know, and I also want
to tell you from your perspective.
LLM is gonna behave totally different
for the same problem, but two different
contexts, because one person has only
provided a simple information and asking
LLM to provide more context around it.
Another person has provided
their insight on what they
understood, what they don't know.
So now LLM has more information
to try it out and figure it out.
This is why even after launching the
product, monitoring is very crucial.
Monitoring is not just not
figuring out how the product
behave, the user engagement and
and how they use the system.
It's purely related to
the behavior of the LLM.
Evaluation.
During the requirements itself, we have to
clearly call out these are the criterias,
behaviors, and the risk associated with
the behaviors for every scenario need to
be validated and their metrics around it.
What are the crucial points that
LLM can go beyond that behavior
is accept-acceptable or not?
We should track the model performance,
token usages, sometimes trust signals
from the users as well for a same
prompt or for a same scenario.
LL-LLM might have behaved differently,
whether user is trusting those
behavior across different scenarios
or across the same scenario, but
a different behavior is emitted.
And there's a huge challenge with the
harmful outputs as well, including
the language it replies, the intent
it provides, and also the context
it is trained, even if you're using
open source or a public models
or even the proprietary models.
One of the biggest challenge is
the responses that need to make
sure we have correct context that
is interpreted in a right way.
Even if the model itself remains
unchanged, business policies,
regulations, and user expectations evolve.
Yesterday's validation result do
not guarantees tomorrow's success.
Monitoring should include both
technical and product metrics.
Technical metrics include latency,
cost, error rate, hallucination
rate, and retrieval quality.
Product metrics include task
completion, user satisfaction,
trust, adoption, and business impact.
Many organizations monitor
infrastructure health through the
performance, latency, and error
rate, but ignore the trust signals.
Trust signals are the pure signals that
tells about how the model behavior behaves
in the same scenario with a different
behavior and interpretation based on the
prompt, based on the user interaction,
based on the responses that LLM can offer.
The trust signals often is not truly a
quantifiable metric that you can measure.
It also goes through conducting
feedback, co-conducting a dogfooding
experience for the people to try it out.
Use the same scenarios, same use
cases, but intent might be different.
Ask them to actually try
it out to see whether
they… do they really trust the
responses, and if they don't, ask the
user what would take for them to trust.
Is it a data problem?
Is it the responses?
Is it the experience, or
is it the LLM behavior?
Technical success, only measuring
the performance without the trust is
still a pr- failure for the product.
Responsible AI requires both perspective
to be reviewed together along with the
technical success and the trust and safety
of the usage of the data, experience,
behavior, and the risk associated with it.
As AI systems move into production,
organizations need structured
governance frameworks rather
than relying on intuition alone
The OECD AI principle defines what
a trustworthy AI should look like.
They emphasize on human-centered
value, transparency, robustness,
accountability, and inclusive growth.
For product managers, these principles
can be translated into requirement
templates, vendor evaluation criteria,
and ongoing monitoring standards.
On the contrary, NIST's risk management
framework provides a practical way to
operationalize these ideas into multiple
stages, including govern, establishing the
policies, accountability and oversight.
This is very crucial.
The framework a-around the governance
will guide the behavior and the
risk associated for any of the
responses that LLM is behaving.
This is a best way to validate
as well if company has a strong
policies that LLM has to stick to.
Mapping, understanding the use cases,
stakeholders, and the potential
risk based on different use cases,
how the def-- output gonna behave.
Measure, evaluate performance,
biases, robustness and safety.
Manage, implement controls,
monitoring, and continuous improvement.
This continuous improvement is
across technical performance, model
performance, as well as the trust
signal like we discussed before.
Responsible AI is not
about blocking innovation.
It's about making innovation sustainable.
When team build trust, transparency,
and safety into the life cycle, they
reduce rework, avoid reputational risk,
and create products user can rely on.
Governance is often viewed as friction.
In reality, it is frequently preventing
costly redesigns and incident response
effort later in the product life cycle.
As the organization adopt AI
life cycle, one principles
become increasingly important.
AI should augment human decision-making,
not replace human judgment.
Human-centered AI design focus on ensuring
that technology remains aligned with
human needs, values, and accountability.
The goal is not to remove humans from
process, but to empower them with a
better information and better tool.
Human intelligence is crucial to evaluate
the behavior, the risk associated with
it, and also the instinct that make
sure we can trust the model behavior.
One critical aspect of human-centered AI
is maintaining meaningful human oversight.
For a low-risk task, AI may
operate with minimal intervention.
However, as the decision became more
impactful, such as healthcare, sensitive
financial advices, hiring decisions,
we need stronger human involvement and
the judgment to evaluate whether the
behavior is right, risk-free, it is
safe for LLM to behave in that way, even
though the data set data semantics are
ordered to interpret it in the right way.
This means there need to be
constant review mechanism
before decisions are finalized.
LLM should be continuously
learning and human-in-loop to
make sure the judgment is right.
Override capabilities when user
disagree with AI recommendation.
User can totally tell that, "I do not
agree with this answer or information.
I would like to make sure
adjustments are right," and they
can totally disagree with it.
LLM model should be receptive to
understand made changes, and human-in-loop
would definitely make sure these
recommendations are taken care of.
Verification checkpoints for high impact
outcomes and also all the different
escalation paths that human would take
that LLM should interpret as well.
So human-in-loop can make sure
LLM is covering… the coverage
for the LLM is end-to-end.
It is not missing the the scenario that
need to have complete end-to-end coverage.
The biggest lesson is that
LLM product management is not
a one-time launch activity.
Responsible AI, it should be part
of the product operating model from
the day, from the ideation to the
release and continuous monitoring.
The product, model, data,
users, risk, all will evolve.
However, treating governance framework
around the safety, trust, compliance,
monitoring, and continuous learning
for the product, not only building
the product and have a static
documentation, but continuously
monitoring and evaluating with a proper
human-in-loop is where the responsible
AI will shine and be successful.
Organizations that succeed with AI are
often those with strongest operational
discipline rather than simply having
largest models trying to respond the way
that we want it for different scenario.
In-- to close, production LLM system
requires a new product mindset,
different behavior in building the
product development life cycle.
We need to move from can we build it to
can we build it responsibility, operate it
safely, and maintain user trust over time?
I'll leave you all with one final thought.
Every technology generation changes
what product managers must manage.
The web products, it was scalability.
For mobile products, it was
clearly user experience.
For AI product, it should be trust.
However, we tend to focus on
prototyping, vibe coding, and we
enjoy the tangible outcomes that AI
product produce when we have-- when we
have something to play around because
that's where conceptually we know
this might be very interesting to do.
However, for building AI products,
trust and safety is the fundamental
building block as part of the
functional requirements itself.
It's not any more a non-functional
requirement that can be built
on top of it after the design,
after the implementation.
And also continuous monitoring.
Human-in-loop to evaluate the behavior
for the certain scenario is according
to the intent, which is risk-free.
Over the time, different LLM
models will behave differently.
Even the versions of LLM model
will div-- behave differently.
So this continuous monitoring is
crucial to understand which behavior
is emitted, which has a lot of risk so
that we can assess the impact and make
the product more safe and trustable.
Trust is becoming the
first-class product requirement.
Organization that embed trust into
design, governance, and operations will
be positioned to succeed in the AI era.
Thank you so much for listening.