Hello everyone.
Good morning and good evening.
I'm api.
I have about 14 plus years experience
working in the payment industries.
Currently I'm working as a staff
software engineer in PayPal.
Today I will be giving a talk on
revolutionizing payment security
and user experience, AI driven fraud
prevention and realtime personalization
in the modern payment systems.
We'll discuss how AI is
transforming the payment, security
and personalization through the
realtime case studies and metrics.
Payment security has evolved a lot.
Let me give you a few examples
in which payment security plays a
crucial role in the payment platforms.
Most of the customers
forgot their password.
The platform need OTP and email
based authentication to have
those customers, the customers.
They want to, they will type their
credit card information, name, address,
first time, but they don't want to
put all those details again and again
while doing the future purchases.
They want those details to be auto-filled
for them next time so that they can
just click next and then they will
be able to complete the purchases.
The customers they want to use crypto.
They want to use different
funding instruments.
For example, gift calls to make
the purchases customer want to
have buy now pay later capability.
They don't want to pay
the amount immediately.
They want to pay the amount
in future in installments.
Customer want to use coupons,
discounts to make the payments.
So all in all these scenarios, there
will be some information that will
be collected by our payment platform.
All that information, for example,
the credit card information, the
crypto related information, the
name, address, all those details
need to be encrypted, need to be
stored in the PCI compliant format.
So that customer will feel
safe while using your platform
and doing the transactions.
So with the global online transactions
surpassing 6.3 trillion annually, cyber
criminals are deploying increasingly
sophisticated attack methods.
This unprecedented volume of
digital payments create complex
security challenges that traditional
systems struggle to address.
While robust security measures
are essential, customers demand
friction free transactions.
Modern payment systems must strike
the perfect balance between the
stringent fraud prevention and
seamless authentication that keeps
legitimate users moving smoothly
throughout their payment journey.
AI driven fraud prevention plays a crucial
role as well in the payment platform.
Let me give you a few examples.
Consider a customer who is a bad customer.
He's a terrorist, he's purchasing
bad items using your platform.
We don't want to allow that
customer to purchase the items.
A customer who is a fraudulent customer
and who is doing transactions on
behalf of a real customer and he's
doing transactions at an unusual
location, at an unusual time.
A customer who is making a large
payment, large international payment
at an unusual time, a customer.
Who has bad records registered
against your platform?
So we want to stop all those customers.
We want to analyze the behavior for those
customers, and if it devi deviates from
the normal behavior, then we want to stop
all those customers using our platform.
So our cutting edge AI engine
harnesses machine learning to analyze
over 1 billion transactions daily,
identifying suspicious patterns
that traditional systems will miss.
Through sophisticated dynamic risk
scoring and continuous model optimization,
we have delivered exceptional result.
A 76% reduction in fraudulent transactions
while slashing false positives by 92%,
dramatically improving both security
and customer satisfaction by processing
more than 200 distinct data points.
Paul transaction in real time.
Our system makes highly accurate
fraud prevention decisions in
under a hundred milliseconds
faster than the blink of an eye.
There are few more scenarios.
Consider a customer who has
been onboarded on your platform.
He did not submit it, his driver
license, social security number,
and we have allowed that particular
customer to use our platform,
so the onboarding should
be smoother and all that.
Driver license social security number.
Social security number.
The biometric authentication,
all those things require ai.
And using AI we can do the smoother
onboarding for the customers.
Let's go through the few case studies are
a retail giant fraud prevention success.
The challenge is 15% monthly increase in.
Fraudulent transactions led to 2.3
million quarterly losses severally
impacting customer confidence in this
major North American e-commerce platform.
Our AI powered solution implemented
sophisticated fraud detection, analyzing
200 plus data points by transaction,
including behavior patterns, device
fingerprinting, and geolocation mapping.
The results are dramatic.
82% reduction in fraud, 95% fewer
false positives, 1.8 million recovered
revenue, and 23% boost in customer
satisfaction within three months.
Let's go over few more case studies.
Our AI powered solution has also been
used for few crypto companies who got
bankrupt and when they partnered with us.
They can go out of bankruptcy,
and they were profitable.
Also, our AI powered solution has
been used for few small business
businesses in Australia and Canada.
They were seeing about a hundred
chargebacks every month, and when they
partnered with us, the chargebacks were
reduced to zero and they were able to
expand globally and they were profitable.
Revolutionizing customer experience,
AI powered personalization.
Our sophisticated AI engine
processes, transaction patterns
from 50 million users globally.
Creating detailed behavior profiles
that reveal deep insights into
purchasing preferences and habits.
By delivering intelligently
personalized payment options and
targeted recommendations at critical
decision points, we dramatically
reduce friction in the checkout process
while increasing customer confidence.
The impact is clear.
Merchants using our AI
personalization have seen checkout
completion rates search by 34%.
And customer satisfaction scores climb by
28% driving substantial revenue growth.
Let's go over one more case study
where our AI powered solution has
transformed our travel booking platform.
I. Our leading travel booking platform
faced a critical 68% call abandon a
abandonment rate, resulting in 2.4
million in lost monthly revenue.
Customer feedback revealed that generic
recommendations and complex checkout
flows were driving potential buyers away.
We deployed our AI personalization
engine to analyze past booking patterns,
price sensitivity, and seasonal
preferences across 500,000 users.
The system delivered real time,
personalized travel packages,
optimized pricing displays,
and streamlined payment options
tailored to each customer behavior.
The outcome is the card abandonment
rates dropped dramatically by 36%
while conversion rates sold by 42%.
The platform saw.
Our dollar 1.8 million monthly revenue
increase, 28% improvement in the customer
satisfaction scores and 45% higher repeat
booking rates within the first quarter.
Let's go over the power of a
h chatbots and how they are
enhancing the customer support.
Let me go through the few use cases
where AI chatbots play a crucial role.
Consider a customer who has
purchased an item using our platform.
He want to return it, and
he's facing some problems.
A customer who is a fraudulent customer
and who has done the transactions
on behalf of the real trans, real
customer and the real customer, want
the refund for all those fraudulent
customers and he needs some help.
A customer who is finding difficult
to onboard to in our platform, a
customer whose transactions have been
declined and they are not successful
again and again, and they need help.
From somebody within our team.
So in all these use cases, the AI
chatbots play a very crucial role.
Our advanced AI chatbots, they
process over 200,000 daily customer
interactions across 12 languages,
providing 24 by seven support with an
average response time of three seconds.
We are leveraging natural
language processing.
These chatbots successfully
resolve 89% of customer queries
without human intervention handling
everything from account inqueries
to complex troubleshooting.
This automation has led to 42%
reduction in support cost while driving
customer satisfaction scores up by
35% and decreasing average resolution
time from 24 hours to 15 minutes.
Beyond the fraud prevention, AI
impact on transactional value.
Real time fraud detection.
Advanced AI algorithms analyze
transactions in millisecond,
establishing a foundation of trust
by blocking 99.9% of fraudulent
attempts before they impact customers.
Adaptive risk scoring, machine
learning models continuously evolve
risk assessment capabilities,
reducing false positives by 42% while
maintaining robust security measures.
AI person power personalization.
By analyzing purchasing patterns and
preferences, AI delivers tailored
payment options and recommendations that
resonate with the individual customers.
Enhance customer experience.
A smooth transaction and intelligent
assistance create a frictionless payment
journey leading to 28% increase in
customer satisfaction scores, increased
transaction value, the combination of
enhanced security and personalization.
Drives a 34% higher transaction value
and 45% increase in repeat purchases.
The future of payment security and
personalization, AI will revolutionize
the payment systems through the
real time fraud detection, smart
authentication, and predictive risk
assessment, advanced biometrics,
quantum safe block, blockchain, and as
computing will create an ultra secure
yet frictionless payment ecosystem.
So in future, how the
payments will happen?
Let me tell you, based
on my thought process.
So the payments right now, those
are happening through the cards
and those are made of plastic and
they're harmful for our environment.
So in future, what will happen is
all those payments will be done.
through the fingerprinting, through the
facial authentication of those customers,
and those will be tied to the cards.
And with that customer will
be able to make the payment.
Customer will have the smart
homes, they will have the small
devices inside their home.
They can feed the data of how
frequently they want groceries to
be delivered, which items they want.
they want to be delivered to their home.
How, what time?
Those grocery items should come and
they will have the subscription.
They'll put all those details and
groceries will be automatically
delivered to the customer address
and automatically the payment will
be made from those smart devices.
Customers when they are going to the
gas station to fill the gas, there
will be small devices inside the
car through which the, automatically
the payment will be done and the
customer will be able to fill.
The gas
customer will use all the
voice assistant systems.
For example, Alexa, Google
Assistant, shitty assistant.
So all these systems, they will just
instruct about, like about the payment
and which items they want to purchase,
and automatically those items will
be delivered to their home address.
So we'll experience hyper pro
personalized payment journeys that
adapt to individual preferences while
maintaining bank graded security.
So the key takeaways and the next steps.
AI is revolutionizing
the payment security.
Advanced algorithms and machine learning
are creating unprecedented levels of fraud
prevention while reducing false positives
and enabling smoother transactions.
Personalization drives
miserable business value.
AI powered personalization doesn't
just improve customer experience.
It delivers concrete results
with higher transaction values
and increase customer retention.
Partner with us to
transform your payments.
Let's explore how our AI solutions
can enhance your security, reduce
cost, and create exceptional payment
experience for your customers.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.
I.