Are you looking to accelerate
well architected reviews and saved
countless hours on manual assessments?
Hello everyone.
My name is Sha Bustani and I'm a
Senior Solutions Architect at AWS and
I welcome all of you to my session.
Accelerate AWS well architected
reviews with generative ai.
In this session, I will talk you through
practical ways Amazon backrock can support
your architectural assessments, right?
From identifying potential
areas of improvement to
streamlining your review process.
When you are building systems at your
organization, how confident are you
that those systems are being built
using the best practices for the cloud?
And this is where AWS well architected
framework plays an important role.
It'll help, it helps you understand
the pros and cons of decisions you make
while building these systems on AWS.
By using the framework, you learn
architecture best practices for
designing and operating, reliable,
secure, efficient, cost-effective,
and sustainable systems in the cloud.
The AWS framework is based on
six pillars that helps you build,
stable and efficient systems.
On AWS it is a set of questions
and design principles that are
spread across these pillars.
Operational excellence, security,
reliability, performance efficiency,
cost optimization, and sustainability.
Alongside the pillars are AWS well
architected lenses, which provide
guidance with a focus, on a specific
industry or a technology domain.
For example, data analytics and
financial services industry lenses.
To evaluate the health of your
workload, you essentially answer a
set of foundational questions based
on the framework, pillar and lenses.
In addition to align with your own
organization's, operational plans,
internal processes, or maybe industry,
you could define and manage custom lenses.
Creating a technology solution is a lot
like constructing a physical building.
If the foundation is not solid,
it may lead to structural problems
that may undermine the integrity
and function of the building.
Similarly, if you neglect
any of these, six pillars.
Operational excellence, security,
reliability, performance efficiency,
cost optimization, and sustainability.
When architecting technology solutions, it
can become a challenge to build a system
that delivers, functional requirements
and also meet your, expectations.
On the contrary, if you incorporate
these pillars, it'll help you produce
stable and efficient systems, allowing
you to focus on functional requirements.
There are three parts to wafer framework.
First is the content, so the framework
with the design principles, pillars
with the questions and best practices
along with the white papers that
gets published on AWS website.
Next is the self-service tool.
The tool, that uses the framework to
carry out, the reviews of the workload
in the form of question and answers.
This is embedded within AWS Management
console, as is own dashboard.
It allows you to generate the PDF reports,
for improvement plans, and then you
have got the data that you have from
doing the reviews, including metadata,
and identified improvement plans.
As organizations expand their cloud
footprints, it brings challenges
and opportunities to scale.
When it comes to adhering to well
architected framework, for example,
manual reviews may become time
consuming and resource intensive.
Different teams may apply the
well architected principles
inconsistently across the
applications or across the teams.
Keeping pace with the latest
practices may get tricky, especially
with the new services and features
being released continuously.
And do remember V four
is a continuous activity.
And the scaling reviews for
numerous or large architects,
architectures can become difficult.
To overcome these challenges, builders
like me at HWS have come up with a
vision to accelerate AWS well architected
frame of gloss and enterprise adoption
by leveraging the power of gen EI and
provide organizations with automated
comprehensive analysis and recommendations
for optimizing their AWS architectures.
The proposition here is to use the
wafer content tool and data with
generality AI to drive well architected
assessments, and this approach brings
multiple benefit to the enterprises.
For example, the rapid analysis cuts the
amount of time spent on WA four reviews
resulting in time efficiency gains.
AI powered analysis ensures
consistent and thorough evaluations
and reviews across workloads.
Optimizing resource allocation and
reduced manual efforts result in
increased, stop productivity and also
shift alert mentality, which result in
overall cost saving for the organization.
And you can perform more, frequent
reviews or time refining feature
assessments and improving feedback loops.
The other benefits too as well, so
we talked about scalability in the
beginning, so ability to run multiple
reviews simultaneously would be a
good thing, for the organization.
Also taking it to the next level,
interactive exploration through
chat interface to dive deeper into
the assessments, asking follow
up questions and getting a better
understanding of the recommendations.
This interactivity enhances
engagement and promotes, thorough
comprehension of the results.
So when it comes to building,
such a system, you would, using
Geni, prompt driven approach,
appears as trivial choice.
the prompt is your interface with the
model, and, crafting, the right prompt
is crucial for the output generation.
So prompts are similar to decision
process of, human beings by
learning, from analogy, by tweaking
the inputs or the prompting of the
words, you get the desired output on
completion and the slight changes,
or tuning to the prompt can have a
significant impact, on the outcome.
Of course, it takes trial and error,
and also an artistic FLA to it as well.
But effectiveness also depends
on how model was framed.
When it comes to prompt engineering,
there are multiple types.
You have a zero short prompt,
or prompt by instruction,
which uses, LLM out of the box.
It allows you to, language
models to perform on the task.
They have not been explicitly trained on.
Then you have one shot
or a few short prompts.
What it means in here is that you
provide one or more pairs of problem
and solution, solution pairs, as
short, as, to the input prompt.
And this helps to guide model performance.
And then you have chain
of thought prompting.
It addresses mul multi-step problem
solving challenges in arithmetic
and common sense reasoning tasks.
It generates intermediate reasoning steps.
We are making human review of tho
human train of thoughts before
it provides the actual answer.
in principle, you would think, that,
in the way, in the current context of
well architected framework, you could
create a series of, prompts from the
framework, questions, and sequence
through LLM to solve the problem.
That sounds straightforward.
However, there are limitations,
with the prompting.
they, they have a poor memory,
but work with very limited context
and then accessing, and it relies
on accessing extra knowledge
sources to complete this task.
And this is where the retrieval,
augmented generation, or rag
or architecture offers more.
Retrieval, augmented, generation
or re is a process for retrieving
facts from knowledge basis to ground
LMS with up to date, accurate and
insightful data supplied in the prom.
It has three stages in the retrieval.
In the retrieval stage, the
relevant content is fetched from
the action, knowledge base or data
sources based on the user query.
The retrieve, context is then added to
the user prompt, which goes as an input
to the foundation model as part of the
augmentation, and then the generation, the
response from the Foundation Mole model
is now based on the augmented, prompt.
Now that we know the basic,
basic functioning of rag,
how does it actually work?
First, you need to optimize the data,
for rack to work, and it is done as
part of the data ingestion layer.
First of all, the data is sourced,
from the relevant data sources.
Then that data from the data sources
chunked, wherein the large pieces
of text are converted into a small
segments, then stored in the vector
database using embedding models.
Then during text generation workflow on
receiving the user query or question,
a semantic search is done and retrieved
passages into bracket R are ranked and
pause as a context that is augmentation
or augmented into bracket A, into an
A model, which in turn generates a
response complete the G aspect of it.
So based on what we have seen so far and
learned so far as part of the session,
we are to now talking about an improved
approach, wherein we come, we take,
the content, data and tool and combine
it with Amazon bedrock and knowledge
basis for Amazon Bedrock and LLM to
drive well architected assessments.
Building on this approach,
I'm excited to share that.
we, builders at AWS have, developed
our comprehensive one click,
click or few click deployable
solution to facilitate and expedite
AWS well architected, process.
It uses workload documentation.
It means you can upload your own solution
architecture documents or technical
design documents, to the application.
It uses mainstream inputs, data sets, so
it accepts a PDF file format that you can,
convert your documents into and upload
it to the application it uses or ingests.
AWS well architected documentation
from AWS public website, into the
internal knowledge, knowledge base.
And it's accessible.
You can extend it to include
your own organization or industry
review standards using custom lens.
So entire stack is created, as
infrastructure as a code with, AWS cloud
deployment kit, CDK in shop that you can
deploy with a few, one or few clicks.
And there are a number of artifacts that
get created, or used as part of the stack.
So we are using Amazon Bedrock with
Anthropic Cloud, LLM, for the LLM, and
then we are using open source serverless
as the Amazon Bedrock knowledge base.
Alongside we use, DB and which is
our, code database for storing,
the review run information.
In addition, we use Amazon's
SQS EC2 instance, which host the
stream rate front-end application.
In addition, there are other
services such as, S3 buckets, and
Amazon Kognito for user management.
The heart and the core of, the reviewer
is based on AWS Lambda and step functions,
which manage the wafer analysis runs.
In addition, we use cloud mode
distribution, with, a LB and initial
web rules for you to improve upon.
Let's see how it works.
I. For the demo, I have created
a fictitious payment solution for
a fictitious company, any comp,
any company that receives an,
process, payment files to drive its,
downstream systems, and ML workload.
The wafer accelerator sample
does not require the documents
to be in any particular format
or a template where it's working.
However, the quality of the
documentation that's uploaded for
assessment is an important factor.
Detailed architecture documents
will result in better influences
and hence better assessments.
However, in this particular
example I have, created a solution
architecture document for the Fictious
solution that I described, earlier.
and this is a pretty
comprehensive document.
It's page, 37 pages long.
which is typical with
these kind of documents.
And we will provide this as an
input to the wafer tool, wafer
accelerator tool, which would review
and provide, architecture assessment
in the context of this document
and the wafer driven knowledge base
built, from the AWS well architected
framework of build documentation.
This is, the landing page for
the wafer accelerator sample.
So I have already created a
fictitious user, so I'm going
to log in using that user.
I. Before I proceed any further,
the user, that I use to log in is
part of the Cognito user pool that's
provisioned as part of the CDK stack.
All you need to do is go and create, or
provision the users in that user pool.
So this is the welcome page.
So you have got a few options in here.
The most important one are.
New way for review and existing
review for review links.
They're available here as well, so I
will start with a new way for review.
There are two analysis types in here.
One is a quick one and the
other one is a deep with well
architected tool integration.
So quick mode is, as the implies is
a quick mode wherein we club all the
questions for a particular, pillar into a
single prompt to speed up, the inferences.
But it's a good starting
point for the submitters.
for example, if I am a solution
architect, if I want to submit, an
architecture document for review to
potentially, architecture review board.
Then I would like to mark my own homework
and I could come to this, generate a
quick, way for assessment and see how far
I am from, or my documentation is away
from the well architecture best practices
and the responses, or the assessment in
this particular mode beside completely
decides completely within the application.
And then you have got the deep with
well architected tool integration.
This is a d as a name implies,
is a deep review wherein we, draw
inferences for each and every question
separately from the selected pillars.
And it's also integrated with
the AWS well architected tool.
It means, on completion of, your
review, we do get the review output
in the application as well as
you have got a workload that gets
created in AWS architected tool,
and we'll see it a little bit later.
So in the interest of time, what I'm going
to do is I'm to going to, create a sample,
create a quick review, and I'm going to
call it wafer accelerator, quick demo two.
Okay.
Give it a description, then
you can select the environment.
Industry type.
So in this particular case, because
a payment solution, I'm gonna recall
or mark it as financial services.
I'll interrupt fictitious name for
the reviewer and select the lens.
I would like it to be reviewed.
So right now at the time of demo,
we are supporting three lenses, the
core AWS, architected framework lens,
and then data analytics lens and
financial services industry lens.
So for this particular demo, I'm going
to select AWS well architected framework.
The user is, created, biofield
is populated by the username.
I used to log in the application.
Now I could go and select the
pillars I would like, it to
be, for, for it to review.
So I have the option to
select, all the pillars.
However, you don't have
to select all the pillars.
You can only select the
pillars you are interested in.
For some of the customers, if
they are, interested only in
security and reliability, they
could select those pillars.
But for the demo purpose, I'm
going to select all the pillars.
And then upload the document
I mentioned earlier.
At this point, I have
populated all the fields.
I'm going to create a way for
review, and as the MEA says, it
has been created successfully.
So if I go back to this, okay,
it has commenced the processing.
So let, I would let it complete because it
takes, a little white for it to complete.
but in the interest of time and for
showcasing purposes, I've already
created a few, demos, in the past.
So let's select one of them.
So this is the metadata that
you, that we entered, when,
creating this particular review.
So the first step is to
create a solution summary.
So we use a document that has
been uploaded and use the geni
to, create a solution summary.
It means the reviewers don't have to
read or the entire document, or not.
All the reviewers need to
read the entire document.
They can read the solution summary.
And this is, followed by, the.
By questions for all the
pillars that have been selected.
So for this particular one, I had
selected all the pillars, and hence you
can see all the pillars, in the tab.
So starting with this, you have
got the question at the, top.
This is followed by, quick assessment
and then it tells you which best
practices have been followed,
recommendations and examples.
In this particular case, document,
doesn't, did not have enough information
on this, and we have devised the
prompts in such a way that we can't
find the relevant information.
It calls back and says, we
don't have enough information
to provide the assessment.
So coming back to the recommendations,
it gives you a list of recommendations,
to improve your architecture, followed
by risks that it, gen I has identified
and citations from the AWS well
Architected Framework documentation.
And it does it for all the questions,
in the pillow as you can see.
And it does the same for
other pillars as well.
So in this particular case, it did
identify the best practice, from
the well architected framework
in the document, which was to use
separate workloads using, accounts.
And in here it gives you citations and
risks, and it does it for all the pillars
that were selected for the review.
Let's have a quick look
at, the Deep Review.
The deep review works, in a
similar fashion you have called
the summary or metadata information
followed by solution summary.
then you, it gives, it responds with,
the same, kind of structure answering all
the questions for the selected pillars.
One thing that it doesn't do is
the risk because we want the well
architected tool to reduce the risk
based on the choices that get selected.
Otherwise, it's pretty much the same.
Okay?
And it does it for all the pillars.
And let me select, the quick demo
too, which is just kicked off.
So that's still in progress, but
as you can see, it has already
created the solution summary.
So it's created a summary.
Now it's trying to answer individual
questions, and it's, take a
little bit, time to do that.
Okay.
Another feature I wanted to
showcase to you, let me select,
the deep, I can select any of them.
Let me select the deep tab.
Okay, so we talked about ability to
chat with the content and to understand,
better understanding, have a deep dive,
of the review that has been carried out.
And this is where this, chat
functionality is, super helpful.
So let me select, the solution summary.
So I would like to check with the
content that was, in the summary.
So for example, I could say
which AWS regions are used.
So as you can see, this information
isn't there already, so it should
be able to reduce this very quickly.
So that's fine.
This is good, but if I say,
which AWS EC2 instances are used.
Then of course this document, this con
this information is not then in the
summary and ans is not able to find.
So I could switch to the document
and ask the same question again
and let's see what it does
because, this is, this has been documented
in the solution architecture document
is able to pick up that information
and provide me that, that data.
This is quite a handy feature and this
you can do for, do it for, all, all of
the sections that have been generated.
Okay?
So one of the things which I mentioned
earlier was, integration of the deep
mode with, the well architected tool.
So let me go to the well architected
tool in the AWS Management
Console and show it to you.
So this, I'm back, in the
console after sign out.
If I go to the workloads, I can see
a workload and the name matches, with
the review that we had carried out.
So if I search for it, I
can see it's the, oops.
Oh, I'll do the other way around.
I'll select it from here
and search it there.
Just to prove the point.
yeah, so it's essentially the same.
So if I click on this.
This was purely generated
by the Vapor Accelerator.
the sample itself, we didn't do anything.
We just created a review
in the application.
And this is what it has done.
And if you see, what it does is,
it goes in and creates a workload,
answers, all the questions or tries to
on, try to answer all the questions,
and then it creates a milestone.
for it as well.
this was a baseline, version that
was created in Geni and you could
start to build on it as part of your
human review, human review process.
So I could go in there.
There's an, I want to show
you a, an interesting feature.
So I will go in there and
I'll look at the review.
So in the very beginning, I told you that
you need to answer a set of foundational
questions as part of the review, and
each of these questions typically
have a number of choices underneath.
So this is not something I've done.
What we have done is we ask the
LM to say, Hey, when you are doing
an assessment or trying to answer
this question, can you also answer?
in terms of, or select the choices that
are applicable based on your assessment.
So these, tick marks or these choices
were actually, done by the l and m itself.
And as you can see, not all
of them have been selected,
and it does it for all of them.
And the good feature or another
feature is that the population notes.
So you, you get the assessment in the
application, but at the same time, the
generated assessment is also populated,
in the node section as you can see.
And it does it for all the
questions for the pillars.
So let me go back to, the review.
So what I could do in here is.
Go back to that and generate a report.
Okay, so this is the report which
I've generated from console.
So if you look at this, it has
made some choices based on the gen
assessments and as a result of that.
Those are all the questions.
So going back to the console.
So if we look, the choices have resulted
in a number of risks, in response to
the choices that gen AI things, are
applicable or have been, implemented.
And as a result of, ruling out the
ones which have not been selected by
Geni, the tool has generated risks.
So if I go and, click on that, I
can see those risks underneath,
the individual questions.
So just to summarize, what I
did was, I went in, I uploaded
an architecture document.
I carried out, a deep review, it,
and after a while it created an
assessment, in the UI as well as it
has created a well architected workload
with a milestone that you can use as
part of your human review process.
Let's go back to the presentation.
Let's see what's happening
behind the scene.
You've seen the ui now.
This is, the overall architecture
for Wafer Accelerator.
So if you recall, we talked, we looked
at the basics, of, rag architecture, and
the first step is to do a data ingestion.
So as part of this, what we do is, we
download the files, the PDF file format
from AWS public website, put it into
an S3 bucket, and use, a Amazon Bedrock
knowledge base, and ingest it into that.
And the way it works out is, the
embeddings are created and they are stored
in Amazon open search for serverless,
which acts as the vector database.
So the embeddings are stored within the
open search serverless, vector database.
And this is done as part of
the CDK, deployment itself.
So you don't have to do it
separately unless you want to
update, to a later version, of well
architected framework, in the future.
So the second part is, which
I just showed it to you.
So we have developed an application
using a streamlet, which runs on
an EC2 instance, and it's fronted
front, front-ended by, application
load balancer and cloud front.
We have created, we have integrated
the web with the initial set of
rules, which you would like to
enhance based on your requirements.
and then you have got the
Amazon cognitive user pool.
So if you recall, I log in the
application using a fictitious user,
but I had to provise in that user.
So that pool is created as
part of the IEC, but, you need
to park provision the users.
So once the document, is, uploaded.
or submitted for review.
It gets uploaded to an Amazon
S3 bucket and an S3, and the
application sends an SQS message
out to trigger the WA for review.
This message, SQS message is received
or, received by a lambda function,
and that in turn, invokes, the
wafer review, step functions, which
is the heart of this, reviewer.
And, if it happens to be a well
architected, sorry, a deep, review
in that case, what it does is at this
point in time, it goes and creates
an empty, workload in the tool.
The next step, in the process is to get
the cont extract the document content.
For this, we are using Amazon, text track,
and, Once the data has been extracted,
it goes to step six, which is about in
working, retrieve, and in work APIs.
So this is where, the query generation
happens, and we'll look at it in a
little bit more detail in the next slide.
But the idea in here is to retrieve
the relevant in buildings, based
on the question in context.
And then, argument the query the
prompt or say that we have developed
with that information and the uploaded
document content, and ask the l and
m to answer those que the question.
So let's, take an example, of, the first
SEC question from the security pillar.
when this is, this, is, being reviewed.
first step in there is to find
the relevant, data from the
data, from the knowledge base
for this particular questions.
And all the passages that have been
found are then ranked based on the
relevance, and then this is added, to
the context, as a context, in the query,
which is passed on to the l and m.
The review progresses, the staff
function keeps on updating,
individual, questions, within the tool.
If it's a deep, review.
If it's not a deep review, the
information is stored purely in Dymo db.
in case of D Deep, it's
stored in both the places.
The next step there is
to, refresh the screen.
as you were saying, and I was checking
the status so the UI can, user users
can always refresh the screen and
check the progress of the reviews.
Then I showcase you the chat
functionality wherein I went in
and asked a few questions and it
answered for me based on the content,
that was generated, by the review.
And it also created a milestone
in the well architected, tool.
I showed it to you earlier, and
that becomes a starting point.
It could become your starting point,
for, in the human review process.
So this is, the overall,
architecture, for, way for
accelerator with, Numbering around it.
Let me show you a couple of things there.
so in terms of resources,
we have created a. in here.
So I've co-authored a blog
with my colleagues, British
Patti and Rohan, goosh.
we have also released, this way for
accelerator sample under AWS samples.
It means, if you want to explore more,
you can read through the book, which
provides a lot more detail than the demo.
And then, you can download
the samples and, explore that.
So let me show you that blog very quickly.
So this is a blog, I've
shared the link for that.
You can have a look.
And this is the AWS sample, which
has got lot more, and detailed
information on how to go about
deploying and, exploring the sample.
So this is, the block.
I'll just show it to you.
So before we conclude,
let's, have a quick recap.
We started with, AWS well architected
framework, the pillars and
lenses, scaling opportunities as
you expand your cloud footprint.
And how generative AI could provide
answers for some of the scaling,
opportunities for the reviews.
And we, I showcased you the way for
accelerator, which, demonstrate,
the art of possible, when it
comes to, reviewing using Gen ai.
So this brings me to the
end of this presentation.
I thank you all for, joining the session.
Thanks.
Bye.