Speaker 10: Let me start with
a scenario that plays out in
engineering teams every single week.
The model is ready, output looks
great in testing, and the team
excited to ship, and then the
whole thing stalls out completely.
Not because the model failed, but because
nobody actually knows who is supposed
to sign off on what happens next.
I'm Lakshmapriya Gopalasamy.
I lead engineering teams and have spent
the last 20-plus years building and
running large-scale distributed systems.
Lately, I have been watching a very
specific failure mode showing up in
enterprise AI, one that our traditional
reliability framework completely miss.
It's exactly what I want to talk today.
Shifting the bottleneck.
Let's be honest, LLMs have made
the execution part of writing
software incredibly fast.
A task that used to take an engineer a
full day, now AI draft a code, generate
test cases, writing a documentation
now happens in seconds and minutes.
That part is real, and it's impressive.
But here is the flip side.
Every single AI output that actually
touches production still has to
cross a series of human checkpoints,
like model approvals, prompt review,
data governance, security and safety
checks, and incident response.
Except those checkpoints didn't get
the seconds instead of days memo.
Nobody re-redesigned them for this space.
So if you look at the contrast here,
we have seconds on the left and days
or weeks on the right side We did not
actually eliminate the bottleneck.
We just moved it.
It is no longer about how fast
the machine can do the work.
It is about the human
deciding what to do with it
I want to introduce two concept that we
need to stop treating as afterthoughts.
They should be first-class properties
in how we design AI platforms.
Treat, treated with the same weight as
throughput, error rates or availability.
The first is the decision latency, the
elapsed time between AI output being ready
and a human actually making a call on it.
That is not just calendar time,
it's a decision throughput.
How fast is the governance
loop actually moving?
The second is cognitive load.
Because LLMs let us move so quickly,
engineers end up juggling an expanding
stack of choices and operational
responsibilities all at once.
Without deliberate platform design,
that complexity just piles up and
is exactly how you get burnout.
And burnout engineers build fragile
systems Traditional SRE thinking
asks, what happens when system fails?
I want to ask a different question today.
What happens when system succeeds
faster than human can govern it?
Okay.
Every production LLM has a life cycle.
At some point, a human has to step in.
That's not a bug.
That's just a governance
working as intended.
The real problem starts when those
decision points turn into invisible
queues with no clear owner and no SLO.
Think about your team for a second.
When model needs an approval,
who actually signs off?
How long does that take?
Do you have a P95 metric for it?
When a safety validation
fails, where it should go?
Is there any runbook or you are
just winging it on a Slack channel?
For most teams I talk to, the honest
answer is, "We are totally sure." I
understand we are still evaluating
all this and trying to learn more
and see wherever we can improve.
But we tend to treat human reviews as
a one-step, one-time st- setup cost.
You go through it once when you launch
the feature, checkbox and move on.
But it is reoccurring operational
process, and it needs to be measured
like everything else you run.
What I have seen work at scale is
shifting governance from manual
approval queues into policy as a
code with automated enforcement.
The latency doesn't magically
vanish, but it becomes legible.
And once you can see it, you can manage it
The weight engineers carry.
Let's get real about what we
are asking teams to manage.
Just in last month, think about
how many of these your team had
to resolve it simultaneously.
Choosing a model, which version
for which use case, who will be the
provider, and what evaluation framework
to trust, and figuring out what good
even means for a better output, and who
gets to make a call And hallucination.
Balancing retrieval, augmentation,
output validation, confidence threshold.
Then prompt engineering.
Are we handling prompt versioning
or caching any regression?
There is no automated regression
test against this prompt engineering.
Security and compliance.
Managing prompt injection, data
leakage, access control, and
audit trail for regulators.
Any one of these on its own manageable,
but all of them at once at the
speed LLMs allow without platform
support, this is a recipe for burnout.
I have watched genuinely great engineers
hit a wall, not because tech was too
hard, but because the operational
complexity around it was not managed.
Cognitive load is a reliability property.
When people are overloaded, they
cut corners, and in AI systems,
cut corners turn into production
incident or security violation
Let's apply the distributed
systems lens here.
As SREs, we already have an excellent
vocabulary for dealing with uncertainty.
We use error budget, SLOs, toil,
on-call rotation and runbooks.
But we build that language
with machines in mind.
What I'm proposing is that we stretch
that same language to cover human
decision loops in our AI platforms.
Traditional reliability says machines
fail, so design for redundancy, measure
error rates, latency, and availability.
AI reliability says human
bottlenecks, so d-design for
decision throughput, measure decision
latency and cognitive load, and
set SLOs on those human loops.
Think about error budgets.
Your team only has so much capacity for
manual governance decisions per sprint.
How much of that is getting
eaten up by things that could
be automated or pre-approved?
If you burn through the, through
that capacity, quality drops.
Think about toil.
In SRE, toil is manual work that
scales linearly with growth.
Manual AI governance is exactly that.
Every new model, new prompt, and
new use case adds more manual
overhead unless it's automated.
If you have SLOs on your APIs, you
need them on your human loops too.
How long does a safety review or
data classification call take?
If you're not measuring
it, you cannot improve
Explicit decision boundaries.
So how we-- do we actually fix this?
The first fail pattern is foundational.
Run implicit habits into
explicit written policy.
Right now, the default setting
in most organization is to send
everything to human review queue.
That simply doesn't scale.
Instead, we can use three-tier model
borrowed straight from the access control.
The first one, pre-authorized When
there are low stakes, easily reversible
choices, think well-tested prompt
templates or internal tooling suggestions.
These should run straight
through the pipeline without
human gate Second, async review.
Medium stack changes reviewed within
clear SLU, say four hours, not
whenever someone gets around to it.
This fits customer-facing but correctable
outputs or new prompt patterns
within an approved model family.
Explicit approval, high risk, irreversible
actions like a new model families, data
classification changes, or public-facing
API with regulatory exposure.
This is what genuinely earns a human
gate Think of it like a circuit
breaker in distributed system.
A circuit breaker doesn't wait for
manual sign-off to handle an overload.
The response is built in.
Your design boundary should be code
policy, not something three people happen
to remember from meeting two years ago
Clear ownership models.
We have all seen what happens in
platform engineering when nobody
owns a piece of infrastructure
or system incidents drag on.
Tech debt piles up quietly, and nobody
has the authority to make a call.
AI systems make this worse
because of the layer of ambiguity.
Who owns the model?
Who owns the prompt?
And what is the evaluation
framework behind it?
The classic trap is kicking off an
AI initiative with a cross-functional
committee where no single team actually
owns product- production reliability.
When something breaks, the
incident goes to everyone,
which in practice means nobody.
The fix is basic engineering
management discipline.
Assign ownership to a specific
team, not a committee.
We always try to add more
committees, more reviewers.
Instead Assign a team, give the
ownership, give them a pager on SLO they
are on the hook for, and the authority
to make the calls in their domain.
For every LLM running in
production, you should be able
to answer four questions clearly.
Who wants it?
What is the SLO?
And who gets paged when it acts up?
And how do architectural
decisions get made?
Write those answers down
Policy as a code guardrails.
This pattern is where I have the most
hands-on experience or-- and I've seen the
changes actually happening much faster.
When we built out a generative AI support
system for a data platform which serves
thousands of internal users on top of
platform running over hundred K Spark jobs
a day, we made a deliberate call early on.
If a governance decision should be
written as a rule, it lived in the
pipeline, not in the Slack channels.
Look at the traditional approach.
An AI output goes into Slack thread.
Someone eventually reviews it.
Maybe days go by, and
maybe it gets approved.
You cannot test, audit, or version
that process, and it scales without
headcount rather than usage.
Now, look at the pipeline approach.
Prompt boundary checks
happen in milliseconds.
Data classification rule
runs in milliseconds.
An output safety threshold
is enforced in milliseconds.
The decision happens automatically,
and you will have audit log capturing
the model version, timestamp, and
policy version is generated right along
with it Policy as a code means your
governance decisions are versionable,
testable, and deployed like a software.
You cannot unit test a Slack
approval, but you can absolutely
unit test a policy engine.
This is what makes compliance
trackable at scale.
When an auditor asks how a
decision was made, you point to
a versioned policy document and a
log, not a scattered chat history
Opiniated golden paths
like model selection.
Cognitive load goes through the roof
when every product teams tries to
build their own LLM stack from scratch.
Everyone resolves the evaluation
problem, everyone builds their own
safety boundaries, and everyone
re-discovers the same prompt
injection vulnerabilities over again.
The golden path fix this, not as
a rigid mandate, but as a default
option that is much easier to use
that teams actively choose it.
A solid golden paths provide approval
model catalog with the version pla--
pinning standard evaluation framework,
pre-built prompt templates with the safety
checks and built-in observability hooks.
Adoption here is not a
cultural problem, it's a math.
If the golden path gets an engineer
to production faster because someone
else already handled the security
they evaluated the solution and
documented guardrails, they will use it
because it's makes their life easier.
The hardest thing in a golden path
needs to encode in model selection
because that's where many teams stumble.
The common failure mo-mode is
running few evaluations, picking
whatever scores highest on a
public benchmark and shipping it.
That misses critical
operational realities.
Task profile, structured data
extraction job needs a small
desi-deterministic fine-tuned model,
not an expensive frontier model.
An agentic multi-step workflow needs
a model that holds up across a long
chain of reasoning Risk profile.
Consider reversibly consider
reversibility versus impact.
The higher ta-- stacks, the tighter
your approved model list should be,
and the more mandatory evaluation
gates before it goes to prod.
An operational constraint, your
latency budget of or strict data
resi- residency rules might rule out
cloud-hosted frontier models entirely.
So every model version bump
is a new selection event.
It is not a standard dependency upgrade.
It is a governance moment.
If y-if your process doesn't treat that
way, you will ship a breaking changes
into production and have no idea why
it happened or what had happened.
Teams can always opt out of the
golden path, but making that opt-out
explicit It forces a va- a valuable
architectural conversation, right?
When a team genuinely
needs something custom
Okay when you bring these four patterns
together the effective is multiply.
Design boundaries ensure human
review only happens where it's
actually required, so latency drops.
Clear ownership distributes the
operational load, eliminating the
ambiguity around responsibility.
Policy as a code allows
governance to scale with the
system usage, not headcount.
Golden paths mean nobody is starting
from scratch, which drives up
reliability because the well-known
path is the well-tested one
When you get out, the other end
is sustainable AI velocity, fast
enough to know fast enough to keep a
pace with the industry And reliable
enough to trust with core production
workloads, and clear enough to
keep the auditing or auditor happy.
No maximum-- Not a maximum speed, not
maximum caution, but sustainable velocity.
That is the design target
Okay.
I want to leave you with four
practical things you can do next week.
No new budget just a standard
engineering discipline.
Map your decision loops.
Find every spot where a human is
wai- human is waiting on AI output
or AI pipeline is waiting on a human.
Time it.
You will find hidden latency.
You cannot fix what you cannot see.
Give every LLM in production an owner,
not just your primary model, all of them.
Identify the name.
When I say the owner, its team.
Who should-- who will own it, and who will
take accountability, and who will define
the SLOs, and what is the escalation path?
If you cannot answer these questions
for running model today, start there.
Automate just one governance
decision this sprint.
Find your highest volume
manual review setup write it
as an automated policy rule.
Ship it.
Measure the latency delta.
Build build out from there.
Start from there.
Document a single page golden path.
For most common use cases, write
down the approved models, evaluation
criteria, and security boundaries.
Make it easier to follow than to ignore
Distributed system engineering and
platform teams have been solving
ownership, governance, and scale
problems for years We already have
the tools and the mental models.
The teams that successfully build
reliable LLM systems at scale will
simply be the ones who treat human
decisions capa-capacity as a core design
constraint rather than after a thought.
Thank you very much for this opportunity.
If you have any questions or if
you want to catch up after this
conference, you can find me in LinkedIn.
If you would like to read more about
my research papers on this area, you
can find the articles from my website.
Thank you.