Speaker 24: Hi, and welcome to
my talk today on database DevOps.
Today we're gonna be automating
different database operations
and actually anything with the
platform or other platforms or AI.
Lots of different operations with
Cortex code and my friendly cat
This is just my stuff, my opinions.
This may not be the way you're supposed
to do it, but this is what works for me.
I'm Tim Span.
You've seen me around if you're in
New Jersey, New York, or Philly,
doing a lot of AI, data, streaming,
open source, closed source,
fun source, all the cool stuff.
Every week I put out a newsletter.
It's everywhere.
LinkedIn, Blogger, you'll find it.
If not, go here
Now, to be able to have a tool
that does all this automation and
easy DevOps without being a super
genius fortunately Snowflake has an
architecture that makes this very easy.
It's got all the things plugged
in, so even if we didn't have AI,
just using the command line tools
and reading, we'd be able to do it.
But now with the power of Cortex
AI underneath everything, and
the models of our choice from
any of the major foundation model
providers, we can do a lot of stuff.
A lot of things are built in, and there is
a way to do that quickly, cheaply, fast,
with all the governance and things that
you need to be doing to do this safely.
So what is Cortex Code?
What's the architecture look like?
We're gonna do as many demos as I
can get away with And give you some
resources so you can continue on.
Now, after you download and install
Cortex code, and by now there'll
be some announcements at Snowflake
Summit telling you about some cool
new changes and fancy features
and probably you get a free puppy.
It's gonna be awesome.
So you- hopefully you'll have
seen those announcements.
If not, start querying those now.
So but there's a couple of things
and there are standards that
make doing AI-powered DevOps
much better and consistent.
As data practitioners out there,
consistency, really a big deal.
Set up an agent's markdown file and
I'll probably publish my example one.
I just gotta sanitize it 'cause you can
put things you wanna use like usernames
and directories, all that, everything
so that it knows this is what I use.
Tim tells me this is what he likes.
Use that.
Your AI is your friend, but you got to
give him some guidance and information.
MCP, great way to connect stuff.
If you saw the announcement, just
added a cool set of MCP advanced
platforming, so that's even better.
But make sure in Cortex code, you've
connected all the ones you wanna connect.
Ones to Google, ones to Glean, lots
of cool stuff you could connect to.
Connect to your Databricks,
get all those things together.
Obviously, it'll walk you
through the Snowflake connection.
Add skills.
Now there's skills to do everything.
We've got a bunch built in.
There'll be more in the public.
Creating your own, there's
a skill to create skills.
But again, skills really make things
consistent with all the best practices.
That's what makes this great.
So let's, Keep moving.
AI is powering this, but you help set the
goals, rules, any of the context you need.
And fortunately, using Snowflake,
you got all the data in there.
We got all this through one place and
everything together that, that's why
it's very easy for us to do the data
DevOps here, but to work in here in
general, again, regardless of what
format you wanna build within the
database, and we can actually also build
Postgres, we can also bu- build things
in Databricks and in the cloud providers.
Now, you could do that through Cortex
code, or you could use something
like a Claude code, very similar, and
Claude can code Cortex code, and they
work together as part of a big agent
swarm, all cool stuff, or sub-agents.
Again, I like staying in my lane, staying
in Cortex code, just working with the
wider ecosystem within Snowflake, where
everything is managed by the same catalog,
same RBAC, same security, same guardrails.
So I know everything
here is tested and safe.
It's not gonna do anything dumb.
First thing I'll tell you, set
up your account that you're gonna
use in Cortex code to only do
things that you want it to do.
If you don't want it to drop things, put
it in a role that cannot drop things.
If you want it only in one
database, one schema, do it.
You want it read-only, you could do it.
So make sure you set that up first
before you type one line of code, test
things out, give it proper permissions.
Don't just give it yours.
Don't just give it full access.
Be careful, okay?
It's the internet and
AI, things can happen.
So why we like Cortex code for this?
It knows Snowflake.
It has access to all our documentation.
All of our people have helped train
it, build the skills, test it.
We've gone through this for the last
year, and there's a thousand of more
of us working on this every day, and
sometimes when we're not even there, we
have our own crab style connector where
I s- have it on task running on its own.
Usually, it's just when I start
in the morning, start my things
up, start the backgrounds, 'cause
it helps me with actual work and
also database work and cool demos.
So it knows Snowflake, knows
all, everything in there.
And you can connect it with the
right permissions, so it'll know
everything about your environment.
And you can have it explore it, you could
have it fix things, test things, and it
knows where you are and you can continue.
I have 100 projects.
I'll just go back and continue them.
Now that's local to the
machine I'm doing it.
I've got one main machine here
that's Cortex code on the Mac, on
my PowerBook, but I also have one
on a big Raspberry Pi 500, and
I've got one on a on a Jetson Orin.
It can run in different environments,
even a Windows box, whatever you got.
And again, can automate these tasks
whether you wanna run it through Cortex
code, have Cortex code build up things
and deploy it and have it run, have it
build scripts, have it build Python,
Java, whatever code you want it to
build, DBT projects, DCM projects.
Build them, make them tasks, get
them automated or push them into
open flow, use that scheduler.
Or just in a Linux style
environment, use Cron.
All RBAC for everything.
Can't do anything outside of that.
You can also lock down what it
can do on that box, or run it in a
virtual box, or run it in a sandbox.
Or like I said, I put on a
Raspberry Pi that's got nothing
Its own secure network,
nothing else there.
Has no root access, can't do much
of anything other than call Cortex
code and do that back and forth.
So do things as appropriate for your
environment So what is Cortex Code?
Now, there's a couple versions of this.
One lives inside of Snowflake in the web
UI that's in the Snow site you're used to.
It's a little icon guy in the corner.
He will pop up and suggest things.
It's like Clippy, but actually
works, and it's not annoying 'cause
not a weird animated clip there.
But it's helpful, especially you're
running a query and the results don't
look right, or it fails, or you have
a typo, Cortex Code there got you.
It'll fix it for you.
Or start from scratch.
Literally, it created,
create a mart from this.
Here's a file, get going.
It knows everything about your enterprise
data context that's there already,
knows the proper semantics, knows how
to make things fast, and can iterate,
test, constantly improve, document
everything, get approval from you.
And we just added Claude 4.8,
and we just added Gemini 3.5,
new models coming all the time.
Stick with the standards, good stuff.
So What kind of stuff?
Now, obviously, database DevOps,
that's a lot of different stuff.
As an admin, which you're probably an
admin or part-time admin or developer
who's got to do half their own admin work
or do it beforehand in dev or in your own
virtual environment or sandbox or Docker.
Do your, You gotta do some data discovery,
see if something's out there already.
Sometimes someone will ask you for
something, it may exist already, or most
of it may exist, and maybe you can piece
it together and Cortex code can find
it, label it, identify the things in it.
So if you think this is the only
source of customer, can find you
others, can help you build things
together with semantic view that adds
layers so AI knows what you're doing.
You may know what you're doing.
Your AI might look at your tables with
their weird names and go, "What are you
doing?" Semantic views help that, and
that is a person in the loop technology
that can build a lot of it for you
automated, and then have you make sure
it's right, which is a good way to go.
It could do any of those tasks you
need, lock down permissions, check
costs, tighten up security, change
governance, build tables, everything.
You build your AI agents and do whatever
they need to do, build analytics,
Streamlit, which you're used to.
We've got new Jupyter notebooks for
real data engineering with Spark,
whatever you want, Ray, pipelines.
Use containers or not,
wherever you want to run that.
Build your pipelines, whether they use
Snowpipe, DBT, DCM, lots of things.
Do it for you.
Optimize ones you have already.
Test them, run them through the
rigors, look for security problems,
clean up the credentials, migrate
code from other systems into
Snowflake, refactor things, and again,
iteratively, constantly improving.
Boom boom.
Uses the skills that Snowflake gave
to you, your own, some you found
online, gets you source data, can build
streaming pipelines, Cortex code powers
it all, could have Cortex AI things
on the end, connect to MCP, work with
other agents, build your own agents.
What I usually do is give it a
source Have it build tables, have
it build the schemas, tests around
it, functions, procedures, tasks,
backup dynamic tables, decide if
it's iceberg or is it interactive
table or hybrid, or it's in Postgres.
Have it build it, validate it,
write tests, clean that up, write a
semantic view on top, watch a Cortex
search for any big chunks of text.
Create my agents on top
of that and an MCP server.
Build all this, add a
dashboard, maybe a React app.
Boom, hour later, it is amazing,
and I've just watched it test,
validate, and tell it yes or no.
So much easier than before.
What used to take me weeks to
build a demo sometimes I'll write
a demo 10 minutes before a talk
and go, "Here's another one."
Or you can even do it during a
talk if they give me enough time.
Most of the time, they don't
give you that much time.
Maybe next time we'll do a two-hour thing.
So all the tools it can interact with,
obviously it can do all the SQL for
you, do things through the Snowflake
native interfaces, build up all the
things you want, and use multiple
accounts if that's what you wanna do.
'Cause I have accounts
on my demo Snowflake.
I also have them over there
for our corporate one.
Maybe someone wants you to
test something in theirs.
Maybe you set up a trial.
You can move right between them, integrate
whatever you need to integrate, get
any of the documentation from anywhere.
Plus, we feed in the latest into this,
so you don't have to worry about that.
Obviously, access to the shell, which
you can block, give it access to
local files, Git, all those things you
expect to do And in a cool, modern way.
Agents, tools, files, build
all these things for you.
Install it on your own here.
This is the most common way.
Like I said, this'll work on a Mac.
There's also a downloaded
install you could do.
This also works on a
Raspberry Pi and a Jetson.
You can see my articles about that.
There's not much for you to do there.
You might have to install some libraries.
As you may have done already, in the
old way of connecting to Snowflake, you
probably got a connections file there
that maybe points to a key pair or a
PAT or an OAuth through the browser.
We can reuse that, so if you've got
the Snowflake command line interface
there already, you're good to go.
Otherwise, you need to install that.
We use that tool, shows you cool
things you could do with that.
Definitely install that first.
All you gotta do is type
Cortex, and it's ready to go.
I'll show you in the command line,
I'm not gonna go too long into this,
but yeah, the resume one, great.
Just be able… I'd worked on something,
came back tomorrow or came back weeks
later 'cause, oh, there was a bug.
It could fix its own bug, thank you.
Use natural language.
I may not remember all the
Snowflake syntax 'cause we've
got a lot of SQL support.
There's so much stuff in there.
You ever wanna go down a rabbit
hole, start going into in-depth all
the possible options for a Snowflake
SQL, Cortex code could help you.
Cortex code could also help you study
for the different Snowflake exams.
It is smart.
It helps you out.
Like literally create some schemas.
It knows what the medallion architecture
is, or you could tell it what kind
of architecture you want, create all
the statements, apply all the best
practices, do that for you very simply.
Again, if you've got some kind of
rough draft of what it looks like, or
maybe you've got full documentation
but it's not in SQL, it's just a big
Excel sheet that's got the names of
what entities should be, what should
be their columns, it can do that.
And then it could take a look and
get all the things you need from
your schemas, can push whatever
you need into version control.
Really easy to do.
Create dbt projects from scratch
or from partial ones you have now.
Reverse generate them, go from a
GitHub repo, whatever you got, build
all the proper layers, get that ready
to run, whether that's in Snowflake
hosted dbt projects or open source
runs running somewhere else or on dbt
Labs cloud, wherever you wanna do it.
It can make some amazingly advanced
SQL and then keep iterating it
till you get to the level you want.
Include all the windowing functions and
all the things that are, like I mentioned,
hard Optimizes queries, debugging, all the
things you need to do right to the tool.
I want… It-- I asked it to
create a procedure for me.
We had a new feature out
for doing video analytics.
Handled it for me, even though
it's structured JSON in there.
And then call to AI Complete, and
it's gotta pick the right model.
No problems.
And you can call sub-agents.
This is great, so when it's
running, do things independently,
so get things done faster.
Use some of the simpler models for
lighter weight tasks, or just have it
do activities, make a directory, and
you can run this all in the background
while you're, maybe running a query.
Lot of skills here.
All kinds of stuff you wanna explore.
Data quality is a great one to look at.
There's a lot of new features in that.
You can look at all your Cortex
skills, or all your Claude skills.
Use different skills, add them together,
have it commit things, do all the
version control, all the security.
Again, you'll get all this
with all these things.
Let me get into code.
Now, while I'm in here,
I talked about that.
So it created this sequel for me,
which uses the new Gemini 3.1 Pro.
Hopefully, I'm gonna be updating
in next couple days to 3.5 Flash.
I think that'll do it a little better.
So I've uploaded a video to a Snowflake
stage, and I asked for that model.
That's my prompt, and this is the
structured format I want returned.
And as you see here, it has
returned that format, so I got
all those fields telling me 25.
Wow, in that video, so 25 vehicles, it
was busy in New York on that street.
Just to show you how easy it is, this guy
over here is my Cortex code embedded in a
platform, and as you can see, it'll solve
questions, even if you spell things wrong.
Thanks, Tim.
And then you could run the things or just
copy them, depending on how brave you are.
Gives you options on things.
You could tell it, "Yeah, I liked it, I
didn't like that. Try again." You can have
that so you could trace it really easy.
Now, the main environment you're
gonna be in is the command line.
And once you have it
installed, Cortex is available.
You can see the different
things we have here.
You can add different profiles, like if
you have a data engineer or a data admin.
Somebody's just gonna run queries.
You could take a look and see what's
running with, My system, do an update
or set it to update automatically.
It updates almost every
day, which is crazy.
I can run a search through the documents.
I can run different
things in Cortex Analyst.
I can look at my agents.
Do I have any agents running?
Let's do a list.
We may have some agents running.
Now, you can interact non-automat-
You can see I've got a lot of
agents in different schemas.
So you can have Cortex run, one-off
commands if you wanted to connect
this to some other system to do it.
Same like you can do with the Snow CLI.
But the interactive version
is probably the nicest.
It's got the cool penguin.
And if I don't know what I'm
doing, I can browse through
the… Wow, I've got 102 skills.
They keep adding them.
They do a lot of stuff.
So you can figure out if there's one you
really like here, something you wanna do,
or you could just ask questions like show
me the top how about the five largest
tables in the demo, demo database schema?
So I'm connected here SQL to the
Tim TSPAN1 account, which in my
connections is my Snowflake demo
account, which sits behind a VPN.
Small, I try to keep
the cost savings more.
And I also use, are using that
same connection as my agent so that
it has permissions to do things.
So it's found my five largest tables.
Wow, 22 million rows, that's not too bad.
And that is my New York
MTA bus tracking table.
I got one for Citi Bike.
Has that many?
Wow.
New York City traffic.
Do some stocks.
Wow.
That's not too bad.
So you see how easy that is,
what is the most recent 10
rows from MTA bus real time?
And I could spell it wrong
and it'll figure it out, but
give it a little hand there.
Obviously, I can copy and paste.
Obviously, I could also set it in
an interactive mode where it'll
go back and forth in a question.
That's something you might wanna set
up in a skill and show it exactly
the best way to do something.
So it's looking at the table,
trying to figure out what is
the right column for timestamp.
And I don't know which one that is, but
I could, as a person-- There's timestamp.
Ooh, I gotta run this again.
Haven't done that in a couple of months.
And it's giving me the 10 most recent
rows, and it's telling me the date.
Pretty cool.
But it can do any of those things.
If you had a broken query,
you could paste it in there.
What?
Or you could just ask anything silly.
But we're talking about databases here.
So you could do anything SQL.
Yeah, see, I could build a SQL.
If you don't know how Iceberg
works, you can help create or
manage your Iceberg tables.
Is there anything cool
here we might wanna do?
Know your data?
What is that?
Discover your data.
Oh, interesting.
So we could use that skill
Let's get out of there.
Know your data
And we'll load that skill, and
it'll prompt me with some questions.
Some have really nice
formatting and prompts in them,
depending on who set them up.
And while you're running it-
what data are you looking for?
I got a lot of… All
data's gonna take a while.
I have a lot of transit data.
Data exploration, let's look at that.
Now, I'm in safeguard off mode
because I'm fancy, and I have
extra permissions, 'cause otherwise
you're gonna get a lot of prompts.
Now, these are good, so you know it's
not gonna do anything without asking you.
Can it… Is it asking me, "Can it
do this?" And I can answer the way
I want, or I can go into auto mode,
and it's not gonna ask me anymore.
It's just gonna do it.
Because I've put it in a safe environment.
This isn't real data.
Keep your level of safety.
It's using my Kafka Guy account, which
is my, one of my key pair ones that I
have specific access for doing Cortex
code on my demo data and nothing else.
And it's the warehouse I assigned to
it, so it's very easy for me to track
costs, which I can do with Cortex code.
While that's running,
I can run another one.
I can run as many as I want.
I could even ask it to
resume an existing session.
All tables are fully accessible.
Okay.
And it gave me lots of ideas.
Very good.
Query a table, profile…
Oh, how about that?
Profile Full table data
quality and freshness.
How about that?
While we're doing that over here, we
can restart one of the ones I had going.
As you see here, I've got 121 sessions
some more specific than others, and we
could just… Oh, yeah, this one's cool.
I was like, "It'd be cool to have my
own cloud outage detection system,"
so I had to build it, and it looked
at all the things, created notifica-
It does a lot of cool stuff.
But just to give you an idea there
lots of things you can do here,
and you could just do silly things.
I'm gonna do a new session just
'cause I don't wanna break that one.
So it's running, and it makes
silly names while it's doing it.
It made a plan.
It has six tasks it's gonna do, 'cause
it's looking at multiple tables here.
And if it has a problem,
it'll fix the queries.
It'll keep doing that for you.
While it's doing that, we can
figure out other things to do here.
No, we don't need to quit.
We can figure out what we wanna do.
Okay, file completion, table completion.
Yeah, you can see I've got a
lot of them that I've loaded
so it knows what they are.
Oh, what is that?
I don't know if I ever look at that data.
Oh.
Yeah, it'll let you browse
real easy, which is helpful
when you're looking through.
Let's keep going here.
Okay, we're getting a
little long on the timing.
I probably shouldn't spend 10 hours
just randomly looking through here.
Agents.
Oh, let's see what agents are running.
Should be- show me my agents going on.
Sure list running queries.
Again, while this is
running, it should see that.
I don't know if I have any other
processes running anywhere else.
I may.
So it's gonna connect, make sure
the connection is refreshed, get me
access to what queries are running,
figure out what's going on there.
Oh, what model are we using?
Oh.
Oh, does that query look good?
Yeah, you wrote it.
You try it.
So model, what model?
Right now I'm in auto pick.
We'll let it do auto.
That's probably right just for this one.
But if we wanted to change it,
the only one running is this
guy over here, which is nice.
Now I've had it write monitoring process,
and I could say, "Hey, build a Python
script that does that," or build a
skill that does that, or a shell script.
However you want to do it.
Build a task that runs
in Snowflake to do that.
Show all services dynamic tables,
tasks, pipelines, search engines
And jobs that are currently running.
That's a big one.
We'll see what happens there.
So over here… Oh, it finished.
Okay.
These are all healthy.
Use these.
Oh, ran once in, last year.
Ooh, should probably drop those.
Completely em- empty on those,
so I must not use those.
That one.
Yeah, I don't think I use that one.
Again write these findings
to a markdown document.
Now, it's all in this context of
memory, so if I resume, I can come back
here, but I like to have a document.
Oh, here you go.
That's a nice report,
so that's good to have.
Let's see.
So it's writing those to a markdown.
This guy is checking everything.
Yeah, if you saw that Neo4j
talk, that was pretty cool.
I have that suspended, though.
That's not running right now
'cause I'm not using Neo4j.
Save that money.
Don't leave things running.
What's nice is if you're not
sure if something's running,
Cortex code could do it for you.
Okay.
We are going a little long here.
I should probably take you back
to our slides here to say thank
you, and I'll see you at the next
one, maybe the next one in person.
Love these Count 42 guys.
Thanks.