Hi, my name is PN Senior Benefits
Configuration Product Manager
at Delta Dental of California.
It's a pleasure to be here today to
discuss how rule-based AI systems
are transforming the way dental
insurance claims are processed.
As we know, insurance claims can be
tedious, time consuming, and prone
to errors, but AI driven automation
is revolutionizing the space today.
I'll walk you through.
The key components of rule-based ai, its
operational mechanisms and the benefit it
offers to various stakeholders and some
of the challenges organizations need to
overcome when implementing these systems.
By the end of the presentation,
you'll see why AI is no longer just an
option, but necessity for the future
of dental insurance claims processing.
Let's dive in and explore
exciting transformation.
Traditional claims processing involves
extensive paperwork, manual data entry,
and human decision making, leading to
inefficiencies and inconsistencies,
errors and delays, not only frustrate
patients and providers, but also increase
administrative costs for insurers.
Rule-based AI introduces a
structured approach to automate
and standardize these processes.
AI achieves this through
four key functions.
Rule ENC coding.
It converts complex policies into
structured machine learning, readable
rules, ensuring compliance and insurance
regulations, pattern recognition.
AI can analyze past claim data to
detect common trends and improve
the accuracy of claims assessment.
Consistency, like human assessors,
AI applies the same decision
criteria to every claim,
eliminating bias and variability.
Adaptability.
As policies and regulations change, AI
driven systems can update their rule sets
dynamically without major disruptions.
These capabilities collectively
streamline claims processing, reduce
costs, and enhance the overall
efficiency of dental insurance workflows.
For AI to function effectively in
dental insurance claims processing,
it relies on three essential
components, a policy driven rule
engine, a multi-stage claims validator,
and an advanced analytics engine.
These components work together to ensure
accuracy, efficiency, and compliance.
the policy driven rule engine transform.
Insurance policies into
structured algorithmic rules.
It codifies eligibility criteria,
current limitation and reimbursement
policies, ensuring that every claim is
processed based on predefined guidelines.
This minimizes discrepancies and
ensures fairness in decision making.
The multi-stage claim validator
automates the validation process,
checking each claim against multiple
criteria such as patient eligibility,
treatment history, and policy terms.
Meanwhile, the advanced analytics engine
leverages AI and machine learning to
flag potential fraud, identify anomalies,
and optimize processing efficiency.
Together these components create
a seamless, highly efficient
claims management system, and we
understand the core components.
Let's break down how rule-based
AI actually processes claims.
The workflow can be divided into four
main stages, each improving efficiency
and reducing manual interventions.
The first step is claim submission and
initial processing where AI validates
patient and provided details, ensuring
eligibility before proceeding next.
The system applies predefined
rule, application and validation,
analyzing treatment codes and
checking benefit calculations,
and verifying clinical necessity.
This eliminates the need of
manual cross-referencing.
In the cross-checking against previous
treatment stage, AI ensures that
claim aligns with the patient dental
history and treatment patterns.
Finally, frequency limitation processing,
which enforces policy restrictions such as
annual visits, cap, or lifetime maximums.
The structured approach ensure that claims
are handled quickly, accurately, and
in compliance with insurance policies.
Tough rule-based AI on dental
claims processing is profound.
These systems significantly reduce
manual work and improve accuracy
and accelerate decision making.
Studies show that AI powered claims
processing can reduce administrative cost
by 50% while improving accuracy rates.
By up to 30%.
One of the key benefits
is accuracy improvement.
By applying standardized rules
and validation criteria, AI
ensures that claims are processed
correctly the first time, reducing
disputes and range submissions.
Processing time is also dramatically
reduced with approvals happening
in us instead of days or weeks.
Ultimately, this technology benefits
all stakeholders by reducing costs,
minimizing delays, and enhancing
trust in the insurance process.
With fear, manual errors and greater
consistency, both patients and
healthcare providers experience
a smoother claims experience.
Compliance with insurance
regulations and industry standards
is critical for insurancers.
Rule-based AI ensures that claims
adhere to American Dental Association,
a DA guidelines, HIPAA regulations,
and state specific insurance policies.
These systems are designed
to adapt to evolving laws and
prevent compliance violations.
The ability to dynamically update
rule sets in response to regulatory
changes is a game changer.
Traditional claim system require
extensive manual updates leading
to delays and inconsistencies.
AI driven rule engines, however, can
seemingly integrate new policies,
dental procedure codes, and
reimbursement criteria in real time.
Additionally, the system enhance
compliance by providing automated audit
trails, ensuring that every decision made
by the AI is traceable and justifiable.
This not only reduces legal
risk of insurers, but also
fosters greater transparency
and trust in the claims process.
Rule-based AI benefits multiple
stakeholders from insurers and policy
holder to healthcare providers.
Insurers experience a 50% reduction in
processing cost while managing a higher
volume of claims with existing resources.
Automated processing
enables 24 7 claim handling.
Significantly reducing turnaround
times for policy holders.
Faster approvals and greater transparency
improve the customer experience.
AI ensures that claims decisions are
based on clear rule-based criteria,
minimizing confusion and frustration.
Policy holders can also
receive real time updates.
On the claim status, reducing
the need for follow ups.
Healthcare providers also benefit as
AI-driven claims Processing leads to
faster reimbursement and fewer rejected
claims by reducing administrative burdens.
Providers can focus on patient
care rather than paperwork,
despite its many advantages.
Implementing rule-based AI in claims
processing present several challenges.
The initial setup cost can range
from 200,000 to 500,000, making it a
significant investment for insurers.
Additionally, integration with
existing legacy system can
take up to six to 12 months.
Another limitation is the
risk of system errors.
While AI can process structured claims
efficiently, unusual or incomplete claims
may still require human intervention.
Striking the right balance between
automation and human oversight
is essential to avoid incorrect
denial or misinterpretations.
Lastly, ethical considerations
must be addressed.
AI systems must be designed
to prevent bias and ensure
fairness in decision making.
Transparency in AI driven
decisions is crucial to maintain
trust and regulatory compliance.
The future of AI in dental claims
processing is incredibly promising.
Emerging technologies like natural
Language Processing NLP can
enable AI to interpret clinical
nodes while deep learning can
analyze dental x-rays to assess.
Treatment necessity.
Additionally, blockchain integration
could enhance transparency and
security in claims documentation.
Beyond dental insurance, AI framework can
be expanded to other healthcare domains,
including medical, pharmaceutical,
and behavioral health claims.
Processing these cross-industry
applications could create more unified AI
powered healthcare reimbursement system.
Predictive analytics will also play a
key role allowing insurers to detect
fraudulent claims, pattern, assess
treatment, risk factors, and forecast
patient outcomes with greater accuracy.
As you can see in this graph, AI is
trending and 90% of the dental insurance
companies will adopt, AI by 2028.
In conclusion, rule-based AI
systems are transforming dental
claims processing to improve
efficiency, accuracy, and compliance.
With AI driven automation, processing
times are reduced by 50%, and error
rates are minimized, creating a more
streamlined and reliable system.
As AI technology continues to evolve
its role in healthcare, financing
and insurance administration will
only grow the future holds exciting
possibilities, and from AI driven
imaging analysis to blockchain.
Powered claims verification.
Thank you for your, thank you
for your time and attention.
Hope you liked the session.