Thank you for tuning in.
Hi, myself Niraj.
I build security infrastructure
for production AI system that The
kind of systems where the decision
actually matters downstream.
I believe in zero trust systems,
which keeps me bringing back to the
line where I wanted to emphasize
immutable log is a testimony, a
verifiable receipt is an evidence.
What exactly do I mean by that?
Most AI governance programs
run on the testimony.
Let's say policies, dashboard,
model cards, approval tickets.
I'm not saying they're worthless, they
are useful, but there is a structural
problem hidden inside all of them.
The organizations that build the AI
system also control the system that
describe what it did afterwards.
If a log can be rewritten by the same
person whose work they are auditing
at this point of time, you are j-just
asking the reviewer or auditor to
just trust you not to verify you.
That's the gap, and that is what I wanted
to talk about in next 20-ish, 25 minutes.
The pipeline on the screen
that you see is the setup.
A user prompt flows into the retrieval.
The user prompt flows in, it goes through
a retrieval tool, then the tool layer.
There is an action or an executor
that runs on top of the tool data,
and then the validation output.
What runtime Guard AI adds
is the receipt at the end.
A signed-- A structured, signed, and a
hash chained record which actually runs.
We know what was the user,
what was the tools that were
retrieved, what was the decision.
We'll talk more on this in the next slide.
I wanted to spend this time
over here talking about it.
So let me start with the threat model
because this conversation goes off
track when people treat AI as some com-
some completely new category of risk.
I don't see it as a complete
new category of risk.
The losses that shows up, at least
in la- in the last one year or
so, all the AI adjacent incidents
they're still the same ones.
The same credit abuse, the credentials
abuse, the same phishing the same
misconfiguration, the ransomware,
unmanaged data sitting in the wrong place.
What changes is these
three things The autonomy.
Basically, agent acts without a
prior action or human confirmation.
Velocity.
They act thousands of time
before we even notice that.
And the tool access.
They can reach systems that human users
cannot touch through a normal channel.
If the agent has compromised
credentials or if it's been manipulated
by a prompt injection, the blast
radius is faster and wider than the
equivalent human-operated failure.
That's what I'm trying to highlight here.
The organizational losses travel
through AI-amplified path.
That is it.
That's the threat model.
Which is why the control goal
isn't just log more data.
The goal is a verifiable evidence at the
moment delegating authority is exercised.
When an agent crosses a tool boundary,
calls an API, produces an output
downstream service which it relies on
the moment has to become a receipt, not a
log entry before I de-- before I describe
what the runtime AI guard does, I want
to be clear what it actually isn't.
It's not a substitute
for the security basics.
It doesn't replace the identity controls.
It doesn't add any additional
patching, the prompt defensing,
sandboxing, or a human oversight.
If these controls are weak, cryptographic
evidence will faithfully record the
poorly secured system behave badly.
So basically, the goal here is
that everything that exists right
now is going to be the same.
There are just going to be
the three different layers.
At the base, there is this cyber
hygiene, where-- which I call it
as an IAM or patching, network
isolation, cloud config, backup.
In the middle, there is this AI and
application security, where there are
things that is checked around prompt
injection control, the retrieval
argument, the sandboxing runtime, the
output validation, the tool scoping.
And at the top, we have
the governance layer.
That is the risk assessment, the decis--
the decision rights monitoring, incident
happen-- how an incident is being handled.
The runtime guard AI is the vertical
rail that runs through all the three.
One question at each layer.
What a control made is a-- When a
control actually made a consequential
decision, did the decision become a
structure, signed, verified event?
The policy engine blocking a prompt,
the verdict enters the chain.
So typically, how it happens is the
policy engine blocking a prompt, that
verdict enters the chain, a human
approves an override, s-signed event.
A tool call authorized
under a scope delegation.
It's a record.
Basically, the runtime guard
doesn't add a new control.
It makes the decision-- decisions on
your existing controls that is already
made inspectable after the fact.
Those are different
things worth separating.
So here is what the architecture
gets specific to agentic system,
where most teams here ha-- I see
most teams here has the bigger gap.
When an AI takes action, that is
the tool calls modify statement,
interact with an API, the prompt
isn't the right unit of governance.
The acting mission identity is
the right layer of the governance.
So basically the acting machine
identifies with its delegated authority
is what it delegated authority is that's
the thing that needs to be
signed, scoped, and verified.
In practice, a lot of teams run agents
under shared subaccount or under
ambiguous credentials I know-- I
understand why, because it's obviously
fast, but it's a governance dead end.
After an incident, you cannot answer
who acted on a specific decision.
You cannot isolate privileges.
You cannot prove whether it was
a specific, whether a specific
action was authorized under
a specific human decision.
You are left with trust
as your only instrument.
The best model has three components.
The meaningful agents get a distinct,
distinction identifiable account, which
is completely different from the human
account or the human accountable owner.
It receives boundaries delegation, a
scope token, tri-tied to a proposal,
a risk tier, a data class expiry,
and a runtime authorization check.
Action against the active constraint.
So the execution receipt record all
of it, identif-- agent identity,
delegation digest, active policy
version, tool action digest.
Now extend this into a
multi-agent pipeline.
From a front-end, a front-end agent
passes a result to an orchestrator.
The orchestrator calls
the retrieval agent.
The agent calls the tool.
If every hop silently trusts the previous
hop, one poison input travels all the
way to the consecu-consecutive actions.
We have built a delegate-- delegation
chain with no in-internal checkpoint.
You can assume it like a
services-- microservices a thing.
Like when a microservice A calls
microservice B and a microservice C,
we do authorization-- authentication
and authorization in all the three
services, not just that, okay, A
trusted, so I'm gonna trust on it.
So basically, the rule is
trust is not transitive.
Identity and authorization context travel
with the request, but the downstream
component still revalidates it.
The s-the source, the identity,
the delegation authority, what
are the policies that fit to it,
the freshness of the context.
Every handover emits a record, and
in, in a multi-agent system, every
consequential edge is a trust boundary.
Treat it like one.
Here is a pattern I see basically
in every governance program.
Someone writes a decision decision write
metrics,  who can approve which action.
The another team writes a constraint
catalog, what the agent can and cannot do.
The third team maintains a
validation rule registry.
Those artifact lives in a wiki and a PDF.
They look thorough, but they don't run.
From an runtime guard AI
point of view, the governance
artifact only matters if the
If there is an execution that happens
during the runtime, that is the basic
principle that I wanted to enforce here.
The decision right matrix
becomes a delegation digest
in, in the execution token.
A field that travels with the request
gets verified at authorization time.
The constraint catalog
becomes the policy version.
So basically, we are going to maintain
the policy version has the gate-gateway
execution and the validation rules
that existed at that point of time.
Everything is a version control.
The shift is from documenting
a policy to executing a policy.
That's the whole game.
Here, when an auditor ask whether a
specific constraint was enforced on a
specific transaction, the answer cannot be
a screenshot of a wiki page saying that,
"Okay, we have a policy A, then we have
the rule A which executes on activity C."
The answer shouldn't be a receipt.
Here is the policy version.
Here is the control verdict.
Here is what actually
happened during the runtime.
Here is the component that signed it.
Here is the chain pointer that places
the event in a verifiable history.
The governance document is not a control.
The runtime field is a signed output one
of the most common objection that I see in
this kind of architecture is the latency.
Engineers hear the cryptographic proof
and assumes every user-facing request
is going to block while-- block during
the inference time, something like a
ZK circuit that grinds every request.
If that were true, no production
team will ever adopt it.
So the run, runtime Guard AI
actually avoids that by splitting
it into multiple concerns.
One is when there is a request,
it passes through a gateway which
runs through a policy engine,
which is a Rust-based policy engine
that always emits a decision, uh,
basically the verdict or response.
And each of the verdict could be approve,
deny Or need an addi-additional human
verification, escalate it or block it.
The verdict drives the response.
This is mostly in line with our overhead.
The prototype-- During our prototype stage
the latency had gone up from two-- gone
up from two point three percent all the
way to four point one percent which is a
latency overhead that I would add here.
But I think we should be good in
term we should be good in terms
of this latency because we are not
adding the cryptographic signing
for every user prompt that comes in.
The next one is the evidence path.
What do we mean by evidence path?
The background lane.
So once all this action happens,
the request comes in, passes
through the gateway, the Rust
policy engine does the policy
verification, and there is a verdict.
And based on the verdict, the
next sequence of action happens.
There is going to be an asynchronous
process which runs in that, that
I called it as evidence path.
After the verdict is issued, the policy
engine emits a compact compliance record,
which is mostly a non-blocking dispatch
and a return and returns immediately.
So it is going to have
a background attester.
That's the name of the module, the
background attester, which consumes
a record, the hash chain, the Merkle
tree, the signing checkpoint, And
the generator with the zero knowledge
proof of the previous chain.
We are-- At any given point of time,
every verdict is always going to have
a reference to the previous chain, not
the exact content of the previous chain,
running entirely on the background.
This is something that
I want to highlight.
The prototype numbers, why it matters
What it matters is the 1.4 seconds
that, that is being added as part
of the Groth16 prover time, which is
something that happens under the hood,
which is going to be a compute cost,
not a not an inference time cost.
And the 1.4 seconds is on an incremental
incremental number of 50,000.
We'll go to the next one, the next slide.
Everyone already has a log.
This w-- this is what the final
log that is going to be emitting.
Everyone basically has a logs.
So what I want to be precise
here about why-- what makes a
receipt different from a log.
A log line records events on an
operational purpose, timestamp, request
ID, status code, maybe the model name
written by an application stored in
a system controlled by some admin
domain exported on every request.
It's useful for debugging, but not
good enough evidence when there is a
review in terms of adversarial impact.
A compliance receipt commits
to a full control story.
A receipt, when I say
receipt, it's a record
Record that acts as their signature,
the non-human identity, the delegation
digest, the active pers-- active policy
version, the input and the output
digest, the retrieval context digest,
the timestamp, the cryptographic pointer
of the previous record in the chain.
If a human approved it, rejected
or overrode the output, the
action becomes a signed field.
Notice what not on an audit surface.
We don't have the raw prompt, the raw
customer data any proprietary model or
model temperatures or model configuration.
The receipt commits to… commits all
those information within a private leaf.
If a specific auditor later requires
a private review, the operator can
present it present the underlying
context of the authorized reviewer.
Every receipt is a leaf
in a Merkle structure.
Edit an order record
and the digest changes.
One, one record changes the whole
digest, which makes the sequence
or the workflow invalidated,
saying that it is being tampered.
So this is the architecture
will-- which will make things
tamper-evident, not as a tamper-proof.
Infrastructure can still be
deleted or attacked, which is
exactly What we are looking at
here is why the anchoring matters.
Why I'm coming back to this slide
on… There are two versions
at which we are looking at.
Let's talk about this in this slide.
So the reasonable objection to a
cryp-cryptographically signed auditability
is we cannot show auditors everything,
and I feel for the most part it is right.
The most real numbers real systems,
the prompt include customer data,
retrievable context the private document.
Model configuration includes the
proprietary implementation details, the
governance architecture that requires
a full disclosure of everything to
everyone is not going to be adoptable.
I, I have been in most of these
rooms, and I know how it works.
So the runtime AI runtime guard
AI is designed around that
constraint from the start.
Private records are committed
into a Merkle leave.
Those leaves roll up to the root.
The root is a compact fingerprint of that.
It cannot be anchored externally as
a public evidence without exposing
the individual record context.
So at this point of time, we are
not revealing any information
about what exactly happened
during that point of time.
Where full disclosure isn't acceptable,
a Groth16 type of a zero-knowledge
proof can be shared as an attestation.
Basically, the signature layer
handles the accountability.
A reviewer signature attaches a human
oversight action to a named person.
A service signature attaches
a policy verdict to a specific
component that produced it.
An anchor a root basically what
exactly happened during the node.
One caveat I wouldn't worry is ZK.
That's the encryption algorithm
that is being used here, proves
that the encoded statement.
It doesn't prove that the policy is
good or fair or legally sufficient.
If the policy is flawed, ZK will
faithfully attest saying that,
"Okay, this is the policy that was
implemented." So we need to have the
differentiation between the encryption
alg-algorithm and the policy by itself.
So typically I just-- this is one of the
stages where we want to have different
flavors of AI governance to be applied.
If a control button is too heavy for a
low-risk workflow, the team just goes
around and finding some workarounds.
So here it's divided into
three different tiers.
For the low-risk internal assistant
advisory use, reversible actions,
internal audiences the policy is just
going to be an, in an observed state.
Distinct agent identif-- we store-- We
can still choose to store distinct agent
identity, basic audit trail, sample
evaluation with a shorter retention time.
We still want the accountability not just
the maximum or the best that we have.
For medium-risk customer-facing workflows
or bonded consequential action verify,
pro-- the action is going to be verified.
Prompts, the tool validation, the
sandbox runtime, the re-reviewable
records, the retained evidences
the periodic verifying drill.
Those are like different set of things
that we want to apply for our medium tier.
The high-risk or the high tier where
there is a real money movement involved,
the identity ch-- there is an identity
change that is being involved, it's a
production system written regulatory
data, or if there is a real time--
real downtime consequences we design
to have more stricter guardrails on it.
We would require more signature
approvals, overrides, mandatory human
gates where-- which is appropriate
for most of the external anchoring.
The lesson-- So basically, the lesson
isn't cryptography everywhere, it is
partial control that is pretty much it.
The implementation
sequence is pretty similar.
Simple over here, the first
record first record inference time
facts as a structure evidence.
I don't want an audit to
restructure what actually matters.
Capture the prompt prompt digest,
the context digest, the policy what
did the model version output digest,
the tool calls, the handoff checks,
and the human review decision.
Obviously, the human re-review
decision while the system runs.
The second, which is attest every event.
Sign them, chain them.
The goal isn't more logging.
It is evidence that survives
adversarial reviews.
The third one is anchor.
The chain outside the normal admin domain.
If the same privilege can change
the application, change, change the
log, and rewrite the checkpoint, the
system is still asking for trust, not,
Not producing a concrete evidence.
Anchoring option are some s-- a
few of the samples that were tried
were warm storage, the transparency
log, notarization service.
The principle is the same.
The checkpoint must be harder to
rewrite the application database.
The fourth one, and this is the one that
doesn't happen until after an incident
if you are not deliberate about it.
Verify before you need to.
Build the verifiers early.
Run audit trails against past event.
Confirm the path works before
you need it under pressure.
A ver- a verifier you are not
exercised is pretty much a dashboard
with always green signal in it.
Most team should start with the
boring schema signature, hash chain,
retention policy, verifier, dashboard,
and then adds the zero knowledge where
disclosure constraint makes it worth the
implementation cost not because it sounds
impressive, but keep the limits honest
I want to end here, and this is a paper.
I can attach the paper link.
This is the paper, and I would love
to have you go through my GitHub
repository and feel free to do your
contributions, and PRs are welcome.
Thank you