Today I'm going to discuss on a
topic called anti-money laundering,
which is very important in banking
and financial institutions.
Let me bring my presentation doc.
So today we are gonna
discuss in detail about
cloud-based anti-money laundering
implementation using nice optimize tool.
Okay.
My name is Vi Kumar.
today context is majorly we'll explore how
the implementation of cloud-based and a ML
solution has former compliance operations
at a major financial institutions helping
its streamline regulated adherence, reduce
cost, and improve investigation of CNC.
High level.
This case study will discuss the
challenges faced by financial
institutions, the adoption
of a closed based solution.
The modules implemented the data
migration process and the benefits
related to post implementation
compared to the traditional systems.
The need for change.
First of we, we'll understand
what is the problem with, the
legacy, the traditional systems.
Then we walk, we'll walk
through you on the benefit of
a ML using nice optimiz, tool.
Okay?
The global regulatory demands are
becoming increasingly complex.
Regulatory bodies are introducing
Know your customer, KYC protocols,
due diligence checks, and expanded
reporting requirement to come back.
Financial claims such as money ing and.
Financial institutions must add
ahead to these regulations across
multiple jurisdiction, each with
its own compliance standard and the
framework with the legacy systems.
Traditional A ML system often rely
on outdated technology creating.
Silos of fragmented data and involves
cumbersome manual processes, meaning that
even though this world legacy systems are
there, basically this is not competing
with the latest times which is happening
and the financial banking system.
These systems frequently generate
high volume of false positive,
burdening compliance teams
with unnecessary investigation.
Furthermore, the systems struggle to adapt
to emerging financial pre tactics and the
rapid phase of regulatory change and bring
and effect.
New threats.
This is what we understand why we need
to change our, what are the problem with
the traditional legacy applications.
That's where we got a nice
optimize cloud-based a ML system
to overcome the problem, which
is facing by legacy systems.
I will give you an overview.
What exactly ni NICE Tool NICE is a
leader in financial crime and compliance
solutions, which is strong track
record of innovating technology and
the expertise in financial regulations.
It's often next generation
cloud-based platform tailored
for financial institutions.
To me the demands of modern
A ML complaints, key modules,
suspicious activity monitoring.
So majorly this, nice act, key modules,
Continuously analyze transaction in
real time to detect suspicious patterns.
Money ing or fraud watch list filtering
integrated with global sanctions and the
regulatory list screaming transaction.
A known individuals
companies are countries with.
Gather and assess information
from clients to evaluate the
risk levels, helping financial
institutions assess the potential
for fraudulent or illegal activity.
Now, obviously to do this all the
thing for anything, we needed data.
We needed data.
That's where we are first focusing on
data integration and the standardization.
So data sources.
Obviously for any investigation,
we needed data, so that's what
we used to call data sources.
Successful integration
of data from what tool?
Critical sources such as code banking
systems, high frequency trading platforms,
and the global payment networks.
The integration helps to create a
consolidated, comprehensive view
of customer under transactional
data enhancing complaints,
capabilities, standardized data model.
Now you are extract the
data from different sources.
Now it is there in a single platform.
Now we need to.
Unified schema was designed to
harmonize over 1 million transactions
per day across multiple data sources.
This model ensures the consistent
data formatting reduces latency,
and the facility is faster
and more acuity analytics.
Critical data points over 200 essential
data points, including customer profiles.
Transaction patterns and risk
indicators are integrated to
create robust complaints framework.
This mapping has in identifying
suspicious activity, ensuring complaints.
And the future proofing are
gonna changes in the regulation.
So this model is helping to integrate
the data from different sources, which
is required for banking or financing,
institute regulations, standardized
data model, using a unified data schema
and critical data points, which is.
Ensuring compliance in the banking system.
There's the data integration
understand model will help for us.
Next benefits of cloud,
cloud implementation.
Now majority of the applications
are moving towards cloud because
of there are some advantages.
For implementing nice active
solution in the cloud come rather
than on-prem implementation.
Reduce infrastructure cost by
migrating to the Clay Cloud.
The Financial Institute eliminate $2.4
million in annual hardware maintenance.
Data center print by 60%, 60%
the cost they're saving by moving
this a ML applications into cloud.
Look at the benefit 60%
they're saving in their.
This reduction in cost enable the
organization to allocate resource
more efficiently and invest in
strategic complaints in C two.
Now improve based upon the volume
in all offerings, a concept.
The more you are getting the data volume
you can add to scale, meaning that at
the time you can ask more resources,
more computation resources, so that
once it is processed, then it can,
you can, bring the down the cost up.
You are hardware and processing cost.
That's the meaning of scalability.
Cloud implementation, significantly
reduced system maintenance by 75%.
So they are taking care of
all your maintenance activity.
You don't require to
bother about that one.
You only focus on your business logic.
Rest, cloud, cloud providers
taking care of that.
Coming to advanced and
suspicious activity detection.
Basically our OPTIMIZ and NICE Ed AM
system is integrated with the four 15
global regulatory watch list, enabling
instance, cleaning of transactions.
say it is like a sniper,
it'll go and monitor what is
happening on the transactions.
This ensures immediate detection
of potential risk and enhance
the institution ability to meet
regulatory compliance standards.
Again, advanced analytics.
The system uses ML algorithm them
to process and analyze millions
of transaction daily, and it
can detect the sophisticated
ing patterns out of the data.
So that you can focus on
most critical investigations.
Most of critical investigation
reduce investigation time.
By automating the prioritization
of our, and streamlining the
everyday gathering process.
The solution reduce.
Regulat time by 50% allowing
compliance aim to focus on the
most critical investigation, custom
scenario development, the institution
developer lower 75 custom detection
scenarios tailored to its business
model and the regulatory environments.
So now our NICE am L system application.
So they, I adminis the study.
Most of the regulation, they made
very robust so that it can tailor
a particular country or particular
financial I misute requirements.
So it is so much robust solution.
Okay.
So you can plug and play anywhere you.
Scenario testing Each detection scenario
underwent rigorous testing to ensure
the acute greatly identify suspicious
behavior while minimizing false positives.
This validation process ensures
high levels of compliance
accuracy now continuous.
Money laundering tactics
and regularity changes.
The scenarios are regularly
updated, feedback from analysis
systematically collected, and the
use to refine detection capability.
See now today our nice optimize
solution can face all the
challenges, but tomorrow this money.
We take the feedback from the
different regularity authorities
and we keep updating our system
so that it can meet the financial
and banking regulatory complaints.
That's the meaning of wherein
our NICE optimize is having
capability to improve the latest
and greatest challenges, which are.
In the system.
Okay, now post implementation
system availability.
So the financial institution achieved
19 9.99 uptime for a ML system ensuring
that no compliance monitoring gaps exist.
This is IE availability supports
real when the system is available.
99. So it can capture real time fraud
while monitoring the system, and
immediately it can give alerts so that
banking agents or financial issues can
take necessary actions on that one.
Automated reporting or 75% of reports
are already automated, and, with a few,
based upon the regularity, the small
harassment, they have to take care.
User interface.
The redesign user interface boosted
analyst productivity by 40%.
It features one click access
to essential data, customizable
dashboards, and in intelligent
workflow automation, making compliance
task faster and easier to manage.
The solution reduce false sellers
by 40%, meaning that I, so even
though the transaction is really
a legitimate transaction, but the
traditional world Legacy a ML system
used to give false positive pulse
positive analyst, our compliance team.
On that, transaction and, finally
they found it's a legitimate,
it's a good transaction.
So it's all our, a ml, I say a ML
system is taken care to remove the
pulse positive alerts so that it is
saving 40% off the compliance team time.
Was improved by 60% through Advanced ml,
enabling the system to uncover complex
money handling patterns more effectively.
Basically now, 60% whatever really,
fraud transaction out of hundred 60%
of the transactions are really, it's
a transactions where our NICE is.
Infrastructure Cloud optimize resulted
in 35% reduction in infrastructure cost,
while also improving systems scalability
and performance implementation.
Speed.
Full implementation was kept, completed
in eight months, four months ahead.
The industry standards
demonstrating the efficiency of the.
Says Bio A ML implementation.
S partnership.
Faster collaboration between business
units compliance and IT team through
regular training committee and to
integrate with a ML system data
standardization wherein establish
strong data governance framework and.
Standardizing data models to improve
consistency across systems leading to more
accurate analytics and improve regulatory
monitoring, continuous improvement.
Already we discussed on that one.
So a proactive approach is essential.
A proactive approach is essential.
Scenarios, compliance process and
technology performance help to
adapt to emerging risk and ensure
compliance with evolving regulation.
What is meaning?
Meaning that there is a change.
There is a risk.
this money will come with.
Money illegal, transfers,
relink, transactions.
So we are always practically
monitoring and adapting to the
challenges implementation roadmap.
Begin by assessing your current
a ML system and work with Niel.
Optimize to create a tailored
pro migration strategy.
This approach, and ensure that your
institution can realize similar benefits
such as improving detection, accuracy,
and reduce pulse past use consultation.
Schedule a consultation with nice
expert to learn how you can improve your
compliance operations while ensuring
regularity and operational excellence.
Conclusion.
Thanks audience for attending my talk
on the A ML system implementation
using NICE act Optimiz tool, which
is very robust and cloud-based.
thanks.