Good morning everyone.
I'm happy to be here today.
I'm Navin Kado.
I've been working in the field of
automations and cloud technologies for
many years, and I'm excited to share
with you how AI is revolutionizing
financial reconciliations.
In today's work where speed,
accuracy, and complaints are
paramount, AI plays a critical role.
But also the human expertise
is still very necessary.
We are gonna explore how AI and
human collaboration can drastically
improve our financial processes.
Let's jump right end.
So let's start by looking
at where we are today.
Large enterprises rely on complex
ERP systems, and this systems make
reconciliation a tough processes because
they don't always integrate smoothly.
I. You have teams handling a
different systems manually,
which often causes bottleneck.
For example, a 30% delay in month
end closing is not uncommon,
especially in companies that is
still heavily on manual processes.
As global digital transactions
grow exponentially, the volume
of data the companies needs to
reconcile will become overwhelming.
Without automations in this
rapidly evolving landscape,
the traditional approach to
reconciliations simply can't keep up.
So how AI come into the play.
First, AI can actually detect patents
like spatting, duplicate invoices
faster than human ever could do.
AI driven patent recognitions through
mission learning and natural language
processing can identify issues
within seconds that would otherwise
take days or even weeks to detect.
And we also can have RPA robotic
process automation tool pair with
ai, and this automations can reduce
MA many manual touch points by
60%, which speeds up processes and
significantly reduces human errors.
Imagine a system where a routine
reconciliations are happening
in the background without
constant human oversight.
And finally, AI shines
in exceptional handling.
With predictive analytics, AI can
forecast animal with up to 85%
accuracy, drastically cutting down
the time needed for resolutions.
This allows your human team to focus
on more complex value added task.
Now let's talk about the benefits of
combining human intelligence with ai.
And this is not about AI replacing jobs.
It's about empowering humans
to do more meaningful work.
First, we see improved accuracy.
AI can reduce false positives
by 40%, which means fewer errors
and cleaner financial records.
In a world where we, even a small
mistakes can cost million, this is
crucial in terms of efficiencies.
The AI power reconciliation systems
can reduce month and close cycles
from 10 days to just three days.
That's a huge time saver, especially
for larger organizations where even
delays can have ripple effects.
And finally, ai.
With the risk management, regulatory
compliance risk drops by 50% because AI
assisted audit catches potentials issues
before they become more major problems.
It ensures your always head of the
CO when it comes to the compliance.
Let's dive into the technical
implementation strategy.
To implement a AI in a
financial reconciliations,
you need a clear strategy.
First, we start with a system.
Integrations.
We can utilize IPAs tool like MuleSoft
with the API LED architecture and
queuing mechanism enables a faster and
real time reconciliations across ERPs.
This ensures seamless communications
between different systems.
Next, as training programs resulted in a
91% eruption rate, this shows how with the
right training, the teams are benefited.
Phase implementation is a key where
we can achieve a scalable deployment.
And with the AI driven proof of concept,
we can accelerate the go live time by 64%.
Lastly, the feedback loops are essential.
We found that biweekly sprint reviews
improve system utilizations close to 67%.
This iterative feedback ensures
the system is always improving and
adapting to their business needs.
This numbers really sparks for themself.
The companies that have adopted AI
for reconciliations, I've seen of 45%
of cost reductions, saving millions
of dollars annually by automating
their reconciliation processes.
Reconciliation times, which used to
take five days are now reduced to just
hours, gaining almost 67% in efficiency.
So this matrix shows how AI is not
just nice to have, but a must have for
companies looking to stay competitive.
Looking forward for ai, AI will
continue to have a transformative
impact on financial reconciliations.
Processing times will drop by 70%.
Making gig, making it easier to manage
even larger volume of transaction
without overwhelming the team.
However, the key to the success is
man, maintaining a balance approach.
While AI is incredible at handling data,
it still requires human insights to
make sure AI outputs align with business
needs and regulatory requirements.
That human oversight is crucial
in maintaining accuracy and
relevance as regulatory evolve.
AI systems will also need to evolve
adapting to new laws and guidelines,
which ensures long-term compliance.
Thank you all for your time today.
I truly hope this session provided a
valuable insight into powerful potential
of AI in financial reconciliation.
I. My goal was to highlight not
only the technical possibilities,
but also the real world benefits of
leveraging human AI collaboration.
As we move forward.
I encourage you to explore how these
technologies can transform your workflows
and help your organization thrive.
I'm excited about the future of AI driven
finance, and I look forward to seeing
the innovation we will create together.
Thank you.