Speaker 3: Hi, everyone.
My name is Andrei Shcherbinin.
I'm a machine learning team
leader at Social Discovery Group.
Today, I'll talk about building a
machine learning auto moderation system
for LLM-augmented online platforms.
The main idea of this
talk is really simple.
Moderation is no longer just about
detecting bad words in user messages.
Moderation platforms deal
with human-written messages,
AI-assisted content, and in some
cases, even agentic interactions.
So the question becomes, how do we
build a moderation system that is safe,
scalable, cost-efficient, and still
flexible enough to handle gray zones?
I will walk through the full system, from
policy design to hybrid model architecture
and monitoring the whole system.
The goal is not to show one magic model.
The goal is to show how moderation
works in a production ML system
When people hear auto-moderation,
they often imagine a classifier
that receives a message and returns
something like safe or unsafe.
But it's a real product,
especially in a dating platform.
This is only a small part of the story.
A production moderation system has to
answer several questions at the same time.
Is this message a violation?
How confident we are?
How severe is the risk?
Should we block it immediately or send
it to a reviewer, lower its priority,
or just lock it for monitoring?
And what happens when user
behavior changes next week?
This presentation, I'll focus on the
engineering side of moderation, how
we move from raw production messages
to policy-aligned labels, then to
models, thresholds, reviewer queues,
monitoring, and continuous retraining.
The key message is LLM-powered
moderation works best when it's designed
as a system, not as a single model.
This slide shows why moderation changes
when platform become LLM-augmented.
On the classic platform, we mostly
moderate human-written messages.
Abuse patterns are often repeated:
links, spam templates, obvious
harassment, simple obfuscation.
Rules and keyword filters can
catch a meaningful part of this.
But when LLMs enter the system, the same
intent can appear in many more forms.
The content becomes more diverse,
more fluent, and more paraphrased.
A scammer no longer needs to
copy-paste the same message.
They can generate a hundred polite
variations of the same manipulation.
And the next stage is even more
interesting, agentic platforms.
Here, AI is not only writing text, but
may help perform actions, summarize,
browse, generate images, contact users,
or assist with multi-step workflows.
At that point, moderation is no
longer just text classification.
It becomes risk assessment over text,
context, tools, and possible actions.
Old school spam was at least
polite enough to repeat itself.
LLM-assisted abuse is more creative,
which is very inconvenient for us.
So the core shift is this: LLM don't
only increase the amount of content,
they change the shape of abuse, and
that requires a moderation system that
understands context, not just surface
patterns Now let's talk about why this
matters specifically for dating platforms.
In dating, safety is not
a back-office function.
It's a part of the
product experience itself.
Users come to the platform to communicate,
build trust, and often share private
or emotionally vulnerable content.
If they feel unsafe, the product fails,
even if all technical metrics looks fine.
There are three dimensions here.
The first is emotional trust.
Users need to believe that the person
on the other side is real respectful
and not trying to exploit them.
The second is financial risk.
Dating platforms are a natural
target for romance fraud, scam,
payment manipulations, and attempts
to move conversations off-platform.
The third platform-- The
third is the platform health.
Bad actors increase support
load, damage conversions, reduce
retention, and harm the brand.
This is why I like the phrase
on the slide, "Moderation is
part of core product quality." In some
products, bad content is inconvenience.
In dating, it become the central
reason why users leave And the
hardest cases are not always obvious.
Manipulation, grooming-like
behavior, coded language, and
indirect harassment often look
harmless in one isolated message.
This is why the system has to
combine ML, LLM reasoning, human
judgment, and product context.
Moderation is not a normal
classification problem.
In many categories, violations are rare.
The majority of messages are normal.
This creates a strong class imbalance.
If you optimize for accuracy,
you can get a very good-looking
number or by doing almost nothing.
For example, if only one percent of
messages are violations, a model that
predicts normal for everything can
already look ninety-nine percent accurate.
It's actually useless, but it
looks great on a dashboard.
This is the kind of magic that
makes everyone happy until
production starts burning.
The real problem is the cost of mistakes.
A false positive means we
wrongly affect a normal user.
Maybe we hide a message, block an
account, or send something harmless to
review that creates product friction.
A false negative means we miss a
harmful message that creates safety
exposure, and depending on the category,
the cost can be very different.
Missing mild toxicity is not the same as
missing grooming-like behavior or scam.
So the goal is not accuracy,
the goal is controlled risk.
We need category-specific thresholds,
severity-aware evaluation, and good
understanding of reviewer capacity.
This is why precision, recall, Q quality,
and false positive analysis matter much
more than one global offline score.
In moderation, policy is not just
documentation around the model.
Policy is part of the model specification.
Model cannot learn bad
behavior in the abstract.
It learns a specific taxonomy,
specific labels, specific definitions,
and specific decision rules.
So if the policy is vague, inconsistent,
or not mapped into ML terms, the
model will inherit that ambiguity.
The table shows how policy objects map
into ML objects and production objects.
Evaluation time becomes a category label.
Severity becomes a risk score.
Confidence becomes a
probability or threshold.
Context becomes features
or prompt information.
Reviewer decisions become corrected
labels and retraining data.
This means that policy design, labeling
instructions, and production routing
are not separate from machine learning.
They are part of the ML system.
For example, suspicious of platform
behavior is not enough as a label.
We need to define what exactly counts:
direct contact exchange, payment
redirection, external messenger
invitation, manipulation, urgency,
or only some combination of this.
The better the policy definition,
the easier is to label data,
train models, calibrate
thresholds, and explain decisions.
So before we ask which model should
we use, we should ask what exactly
are we asking t-the model to learn?
The main point of this slide is that
auto moderation is an operating system
for safety decision, not one classifier.
We start with rule charts Then we
clean the data, de-duplicate it.
Sample examples, use LLM labeling,
validate with humans, train models, run
online inference, apply thresholds, route
cases to review queues, and finally,
use feedback for the next iteration.
The arrows at the bottom are just
as important as the main pipeline.
Reviewers' decisions go back into sampling
prompts, thresholds, and retraining.
Monitoring also feeds
back into the system.
This is important because
abuse is not static.
If we build a one-time
classifier and never re-revisit
it, performance will degrade.
Users change wording, scammers
test boundaries, product
surfaces change, policies change.
Even the meaning of the bottom
line case can shift over time.
A useful way to think about it is
the model is not only one component.
The system includes data
engineering, policy mapping,
annotation tools, review operations,
dashboards, and retraining loops.
So when someone say, "Can we just
use a strong LLM for moderation?"
The answer is maybe for one layer,
but not for the whole system.
The whole system is where moderation
quality actually comes from
Now let's zoom into the data layer.
Raw messages are not just training data.
They become training data only after they
are cleaned, filtered, aligned the policy,
and connected to the right context.
On the left side of the slide, we have
sources: user-to-user messages, user
reports, reviewer decisions, metadata,
and historical moderation actions.
The middle part is alignment.
We remove test traffic and obvious noise.
We map examples to policy categories.
We preserve user type and context.
We split by language, product, and
platform because behavior can be
very different across segments.
On the right side, we can get the
output, a clean candidate corpus,
policy-aware samples, and rare
class candidates for labeling.
This step is less glamorous than
model training, but it defines
a ceiling of model qua- quality.
If the data is noisy, duplicated, stale,
or poorly aligned with policy, even a very
strong model will learn the wrong thing.
In dating platforms, context
is especially important.
The same phrase can have different
meaning depending on who sends it, how
often it appears, what happened before.
So data collection is not
just give me all messages.
It is the first safety decision design
Without deduplication, the
model often learns templates
instead of abuse semantics.
This is a very common
trap in moderation data.
Models may learn bad signals.
Imagine we have thousands of
near-identical scam messages.
Hey, babe, help me with my phone bill.
Hi, dear, I need help with my bill.
Can you send me money to help me?
The model may become very good at
recognizing these exact templates, and
then we celebrate high offline quality.
But in production, when the
wording changes, the model fails.
So deduplication is not only
compression, it is evaluation hygiene.
It reduces memorization,
reduces train test leakage, and
helps us preserve diversity.
The goal is not to remove
everything similar.
The goal is to collapse
repetitive templates while
keeping representative variations.
In our pipeline, this means
exact deduplication, normalized
deduplication, and then broader
methods for near duplicates.
For wider semantic clusters,
we need to be careful.
If we merge too aggressively,
we lose meaningful diversity.
If we merge too weakly, the
dataset stays full of templates.
If you train on the same scam
template ten thousand times, you
have not built a moderation model.
You have built a very expensive
template historian The key idea here
is that for rare violations progress
should be measured by positives
found, not by rows processed.
If the positive class is around
one percent, then random labeling
is extremely inefficient.
Most of the labeling budget is
spent confirming normal messages.
That may be useful at some point, but
it's not the fastest way to build a
training set for a rare violation.
So the pipeline works like this.
We sample a batch, we remove
texts that were already
evaluated using a hash journal.
We retrieve few-shot examples from golden
set, then the LLM classifies each message.
The label can be zero for clear
normal, one for cla-clear violation,
or two for borderline, meaning the
ca-the case should be reviewed.
This is a very practical
engineering principle.
We don't want to label everything,
we want to find enough signal.
The hash journal is important
because labeling is expensive.
We don't want to pay repeatedly
for the same text across
restarts or dataset updates.
Few-shot retrieval is also important
because the system improves over time.
As humans validate examples, those
examples become better context for
the next LLM labeling iteration
LLMs are extremely useful
for pre-annotation.
They can read text, produce a label,
explain the reason, and highlight the
fragment that supports the decision.
This reduces the cognitive load for the
human reviewer, but we should not train
the final production model directly
on raw LLM labels without validation.
If we do that, the model
may learn the LLM's mistakes
instead of the actual policy.
So the human-in-the-loop process works
like this: The LLM gives a suggestion,
a reason, and a supporting fragment.
The human accepts or rejects it.
The validated result
goes into the golden set.
The golden set then becomes training data
for the production model and also improves
few-shot retrieval for future labeling.
I like to describe the LLM here
as a very confident intern.
It's fast, useful, and often
right, but you still don't let the
intern define company policy alone.
So the rule is: LLM pre-annotates,
human validates, and the
golden set belongs to humans.
S-- thi-this slide, I would like
to tell you about gray zones.
The hardest violations often don't look
like violations in one isolated message.
They emerge from context,
repetition, coded language, or the
relationships between messages.
Examples include grooming-like behavior,
indirect harassment, or platform
manipulations scam, and romantic
fraud a generic moderation model may
perform well on obvious toxicity.
For example, direct insult or explicit
threats are easier, but dating safety
often depends on subtle signals,
trust-building, emotional pressure,
urgency, requests to move to another
platform, financial manipulation,
or repeated boundary pushing.
This is where
context-dependent risk appears.
One message might look harmless.
Ten messages in sequence
might show a clear pattern.
This is why gray zones
require a hybrid approach.
Rules can catch obvious cases.
Lightweight models can handle
high-volume categories.
LLM can help reason over nuanced
cases, and humans should remain
the final authority for the
most sensitive decisions.
So the purpose of the LLM layer
is not to replace all moderation,
it's to help identify and explain
context-dependent risk A hybrid stack
wins because harms differ structurally.
At the bottom, we have rules and keywords.
They are fast, cheap, and explainable.
They are good for links,
obvious abuse, obfuscation, and
deterministic policy checks.
Their weaknesses is
that they miss context.
Then we have lightweight machine learning.
This is useful for high volume categories
where we need scalable online inference.
These models are much cheaper and
faster than large LLMs, but they need
strong labels and good evaluation.
Then we have LLM or LLM judges.
They are useful for gray zones, reasoning,
context, and more nuanced cases.
But they are more expensive
and slower, so we should not
use them everywhere by default.
And at the top, we have a human review.
Humans are the policy authority,
especially for edge cases, appeals,
and high severity categories.
But human capacity is limited.
The important point is that the
stack is not a competition between
rules, ML, LLMs, and humans.
It's a division of labor.
Today, BERT-like and other
lightweight classifiers are still
very practical for online moderation.
They are fast, predictable,
rela- relatively cheap, and
easy to deploy at high volume.
But I think the direction is really clear.
LLMs are becoming faster, cheaper,
and stronger at reasoning.
So over time, more moderation tasks
will naturally move from classic
lightweight classifiers towards
specialized LLM-based moderation layers.
This doesn't mean that rules or
small models will disappear tomorrow.
For obvious cases, deterministic
checks and lightweight
models will still make sense.
But for tasks where context, nuance,
explanation, or policy reasoning
matter, LLMs are much better fit.
So this hybrid architecture is not
only a current production design,
it’s also a transition path.
We can use lightweight models where speed
and cost matter most, and gradually move
more complex reasoning-heavy moderation
tasks to LLMs as the technology becomes
cheaper and more production ready.
Not every moderation tasks requires
expensive LLM inference, but
not every moderation task can be
solved by a regex or a BERT either.
The system works when each layer
handles the type of risk it's best
suited for The model score is not
the final moderation decision.
It's only one input.
In production, a message
goes through risk signals.
These signals can include model
probability, category, severity, user
risk, conversation context, language.
Then the decision layer chooses an action.
The action can be allow, review,
priority review, block, or escalate.
This is where moderation
becomes product engineering.
For example, the same model
score may lead to different
actions depending on severity.
A medium confidence spam case
may go to a low priority review
queue or be automatically handled.
A medium confidence grooming-like case
may require escalation because the
cost of missing it is much higher.
Review, reviewer capacity also matters.
If the review queue is overloaded,
thresholds and prioritization
become operational controls.
We need to decide which cases
deserve attention first.
This is why moderation system cannot stop
at model predicted zero point eighty-two.
The system must define what this number
means for this category, this user, this
context, and this operational state.
So the phrase describes my message.
Prediction is machine learning.
Decisioning is product engineering
Thresholds are operational controls,
not fixed machine learning constants.
On the slide, we have a score
distribution from zero to one.
Low scores go to allow.
Medium scores go to review.
High scores go to block or urgent review.
This looks simple, but the important
part of the threshold should be
category specific and risk specific.
For spam, we may want higher
autom-automation because the category
is less vigorous and the cost of
false positive may be manageable.
For harassment, the decision may be more
review heavy because context matters.
A common mistake is to search for the best
thresholds once and then forget about it.
Unfortunately, thresholds are not
a Wi-Fi password that you write
on a stick and never update.
Thresholds need re-recalibration when
policy changes, when the abuse mix
changes, when a model is updated,
or when review capacity changes.
So thresholding is not just
model tuning, it's an ongoing
operational process for us.
Offline metrics, of course,
important, but they are not
enough for moderation quality.
On the left, we have metrics such as
precision at low recall, recall on high
severity classes, false positive rate
by category, Q precision and others.
These metrics reflect the
reality of moderation better
than one global F1 score.
The loop on the right
shows how system improves.
First, the model makes predictions,
scores, categories, or risk signals.
The reviewers make decisions and provide
human labels rational and actions.
Then we analyze error buckets,
false positive, false negative,
disagreement, borderline cases, and drift
After that, we can improve
different parts of the system.
Sometimes the policy needs clarification.
Sometimes the prompt needs
better instructions or examples.
Sometimes the thresholds
needs calibration.
Sometimes we need to
retrain with new hard cases.
The important and the idea of that
disagreement is not only noise.
In subjective and high-risk
tasks, disagreement is signal.
It tells us where the policy is
unclear, where the model lacks context.
So evaluation is not a final exam,
it's a continuous diagnostic system
A moderation model should be rolled
out like a safety critical system The
timeline starts with offline validation.
Then we use shadow mode when
the model makes predictions
but does not affect users.
This allows us to compare model
decision with existing processes.
The bottom part of the slide shows
that we need to monitor traffic volume,
category distribution, review load,
backlog, SLA, latency, error, drift.
Production ML often fails silently.
It doesn't always crash.
Sometimes the service is healthy,
latency is fine, error rate is
zero, and the model is simply
making worse decisions than before.
This is why monitoring include model
behavior and downstream operations,
not only infrastructure metrics.
In monitoring, a dashboard should
answer not only is the service
alive, but also is the system
still making good safety decisions?
In many machine learning systems, drift
means that the data distribution changes.
In moderation drift
has additional meaning.
Users are adapting against the system.
Scammers and bad actors actively changing
wording, use coded language, avoid obvious
keywords, and move to indirect behavior.
They are not a passive data distribution.
They are an adversarial population.
The diagram shows several types
of drift around the model.
Language drift means users
change words, slang, or language.
Evasion drift means users learn
how to bypass known checks.
Policy drift means definitions
and enforcement rules change.
Platform or product drift means the
product itself changes: new surfaces, new
communication formats, new user flows.
Reviewer disagreement drift
means reviewers start disagreeing
more often, which may indicate
ambiguous policy or new patterns.
Multimodal and agentic drift means
that risk moves beyond plain text
into images, generated contexts,
tool use, or multi-step actions.
The key sentence for me here is that scam
evolves faster than static benchmarks
The system reduces manual load
while preserving safety coverage
there are three main numbers.
Millions of messages per day, minus
sixty percent reviewer load, and
ninety percent plus violations caught.
But I want to be careful with the, with
impact atric- metrics in moderation.
Big numbers are really attractive,
but they can also be dangerous.
Dashboard can become convincing
before it becomes meaningful.
So the methodology box is very important.
When we say violation caught, we need
to define which policy classes we
mean, what time window we measure,
how borderline cases are counted, and
whether the reviewer denominator changes.
For example reducing reviewer load by
sixty percent is meaning only if we
still preserve safety coverage and don't
simply hide difficult cases from review.
Similarly, ninety percent plus
violations caught might be tied to
specific violation categories and a
clear definition of caught, blocked
automatically, sent to review confirmed
by reviewers, or detected after the fact.
The goal is not to replace reviewers.
The goal is to spend reviewer
attention where it matters most.
So the real impact is not just automation.
It is better allocation
of scarce human judgment.
So let me summarize the main takeaways.
First policy first.
A moderation model can only learn
what the policy defines clearly.
Taxonomy, severity, labeling
rules, and enforcement logic are
part of the model specification.
The second one, hybrid architecture wins.
Rules, machine learning
classifiers, LLMs, and humans solve
different parts of the problem.
The best system is not the one with the
biggest model everywhere, but the one that
uses the right layer for the right risk.
Rare class thinking matters.
Sampling, labeling, metrics, and
thresholds must handle imbalance.
Accuracy is not enough.
Controlled risk is the goal.
The fourth queue design matters.
Reviewer attention is
the scarcest resource.
A good moderation system must prioritize
cases, not just classify messages.
The feedback loop is a product.
Abuse evolves, policies change,
and model quality degrades without
being monitored and retrained.
So the final message is this:
LLM-powered moderation works
when it's designed as a system.
The model is important, but the system
around the model is what makes moderation
safe Scalable and useful in production.
Thank you.
I will be happy to be connected
with you on my LinkedIn page.
So there is a QR.
Thank you for your attention.
See ya.