Hello everyone.
my name is Hamad VAAs.
I am a lead technical
product manager at Quali.
Qua is basically a game
development and publishing company.
we work both in mobile console, PC and all
the other platforms including Nintendo,
and, any other platforms that support
games, whether it's web games, as well.
I have, almost more than seven years of
experience now in product management.
I am a software engineer basically, and,
I have devoted my entire professional
experience to product management.
and, this topic, leveraging LLM, For
your data-driven product management
is something that I am, myself
learning and trying to implement
that in my own company, and I'm
seeing, terrific results already.
So I'm very excited for this session.
so let's quickly jump
onto the session itself.
So I'm gonna move to the session.
so the topic itself, leveraging
LLMs for data-driven.
Decision making, in product management.
this is something that, as I said,
I'm learning myself, but I've
seen, some amazing results to,
use a large language models and
to understand how natural it is.
It's something that even
I was surprised as well.
So let's go through.
So let's start with what is, large
language models, as a brief, and
the most simplest definition is
that LLMs are advanced AI models,
that are trained on diverse data
sets to understand and generate the
next sequence of humanlike text.
So for example, if I'm saying, if my
answer to how are you is I am fine.
So the model would understand that
a normal human talks like that and
then they would try to, imitate.
and try to generate text
as humanly as possible.
That's the most simplest of
definitions of LLMs, however.
It has so many vast usages, and you
can now see, like chat, GPT, deep seek,
Claude, all these, ai tools and AI search
engines are now trying to imitate how
a normal human would respond to a text.
So it doesn't sound like a machine
originated text, and that's how.
LLM used the powerful, natural
language processing to make
sure that it's very human.
you can use that in your AI agents, you
can use that in your normal, conversations
as your first point of conversations,
as well as your entire, your entire
customer management can just be used, can
just be managed using the powerful LLMs.
That's the brief definition of it, but we
will, we'll dive deep into that later on.
Now, the other part of this, session is
data-driven decision making right now.
Product management is taking a huge turn
towards using large sets of data, plotted
in very user-friendly graphs, and funnels.
this is very crucial when you are
planning your roadmap, when you're making
sure that your product has the feature
that the people will actually use.
So it's very critical.
That not just, in the roadmap, you
use this data driven decision making,
but once you have deployed this
feature, you make sure that your
customer touchpoints are properly
implemented and that you make sure
that once you have deployed a feature.
You know that what KPIs I'm going for.
Those might be retention,
those might be conversion rate,
those might be engagement rate.
Whatever your KPI is, someone has
revenue, number of orders, number of
clicks, number of conversions, whatever
you're going for, you have to make sure
those touch points are the ones that is.
making an impact in your decision making.
That is your data-driven decision making.
This approach heavily relies on metrics.
Now, imagine data-driven decision
making combined together with LLMs,
LLM, bringing huge sets of data that
basically define that how a human
would emulate your features before
even you deploy that in the market.
That's how powerful this can be.
So that's the.
The use and the importance of data-driven
decision making in these times, basically.
So now.
When you have understood LMS and
you have understood the need for
decision making, with proper data,
let's combine together and understand
how LMS can enhance your product
management and your decision making.
The first thing and the very,
very important is market
research and trend analysis.
Now, when I'm doing it alone
with just my own research, I can
probably find 50 competitors, right?
Or even a hundred competitors
if I have enough time, but.
LMS can now scan large data sources
because it is, it has a vast data sources.
it can help you using your competitor
updates, sorry, updates, industry reports.
Your news, identify key trends.
you might even get real time insights.
So for example, if I am.
If I'm building an e-commerce website,
for example, with, a specific niche of
products, LLM would tell me that what is
the segment of users you should target?
How they would behave in the market
with this spec specific audience that
you're going for, and whether you have
to make early decisions before going
into the market and understanding.
The next is customer feedback analysis.
So once your market is done,
market research is done, then you
have to understand how you are
collecting your customer feedback.
Now LLMs can again give you, some proper
categorization, whether it's sentiment
analysis, whether it's, highlighting
your recurring issues with the customer.
for example, you have 10 million users and
your LLM can eventually tell you that what
is the issue that is constantly occurring
for a specific audience, and then you
can actually make decisions without
scanning all those customer feedbacks.
Your feature prioritization.
This is very crucial as a product
manager and I hope the product
managers would agree with me that when
you are prioritizing features, you
have so many different influences.
Your CEOs, your COOs, your lead
product, your business analysts, they
all will try to influence features.
As they want.
But when it comes to decision driven,
data-driven decision making and LLMs,
you actually have the data in front
of you where you can prioritize.
You can actually emulate how your features
were due using the LLM dataset, and
then you can eventually give them the
data even before going into the market.
It can give you historical
feature management, like how
historically this feature.
This kind of feature has
behaved in the market.
and also what's the customer demand?
LMS can even predict the potential
impact of new features on your product
before you release the product.
And you can actually show your C-E-O-C-O
CFOs that this is how the data.
is talking, so you wanna listen or
not AB testing, again, no product
manager can survive in this industry
without properly ab testing.
The, your features before you,
like when you launch them.
LMS can actually automate the
interpretation of test results,
identifying which variations
perform best and viable.
Not just the, with the current data, but
actually the historical, the predictive
data and the current data that you have.
So if I'm a product manager, I only
make decision with the current data,
but LLN can give me predictive analysis,
historical analysis, and current analysis.
Automating the reporting part, again,
is very crucial that LMS can generate
ex executive summaries, dashboards, key
takeaways is pretty self-explanatory.
Speaker notes, again, by leveraging lms,
product managers can actually automate
market research, analyze customer
feedback at scale, and generate meaningful
insights with minimal manual effort.
that's very crucial that you're
actually talking at scale with LMS
and not just your current data set.
Moving along, what kind of tools
or technologies LMS are being
used currently in the market?
First thing is you have OpenAI
your chat GPTs, your, all the
buzz in the market with the chat
g bt that they all are using, for,
they're used for text generations.
They're used for summarizations, LLMs.
This literally are the data sets that
actually give you the human output.
You have your Google Bird.
again, optimized for natural
living, lang natural language
understanding using the LLMs.
you can use Claude Ro, you can use,
again, hugging face transformers.
that's basically up to you what kind of
combination of tools you're going for.
You can even go for your
custom LLM integration that's.
That's a bit, resource heavy, but
if you want to make your own use
case, you can actually use open
source APIs and then you can make
it in and in the way that you want.
I would suggest to start very simple
to use like, let's try chat GPT.
Try and understand how
the data set's working.
Just make sure that your features
are prioritized properly with chat
g bt, for example, or Google Bird.
And then slowly and gradually.
Start about, a humiliating your
ab test, your insights, trends,
your predictive analysis.
Just make sure to start small, but make
sure that you are using historical and
predictive data for your future planning.
What challenges and considerations you
need to make whilst you are, transforming
to normal product management, to data
driven LRM based product management.
the quality, the data
quality, and the bias.
One thing that I always say is
you cannot a hundred percent
rely on large set of data.
You have to make sure that.
the quality of the data and the
source of the data is validated.
If it's not validated, you are
basically planning to fail.
Just make sure that the sources of
your data is properly validated.
You know that the, where the data
is coming from, and once your
entire segmentation of data is
ready, only then you make decisions.
Otherwise, you will go towards very biased
features, biased results, and inaccurate
predictions, which is something that.
The, some product managers
like are actually making this
mistake in the market right now.
Interpretability is very crucial
that you have to understand the data.
If you cannot understand the data,
make sure that you have a data
engineer, you have a data scientist,
you have a, an analyst who can
tell you, what this data means.
So just make sure that you understand
the data, scalability, and cost.
As everyone knows, it's not cheap
to, to, to use these models.
Just make sure that you start small.
You have to make sure that it
is actually useful for you.
Don't just jump into the bandwagon.
Make sure that this is
actually useful for you.
If it's not, if you have the data
and you only need to use the current
data and real data, you don't need
to, go towards this direction.
Ethical and privacy concerns.
Some data sets are not properly, sourced.
just make sure if your organization is
going towards this route, your legal,
actually check the data sources as well.
some best practices.
Again, this is.
Purely subjective, purely
coming from my side.
It might be different for you.
It might be different for anyone else.
some guidelines for, from my side,
for success in this, in this domain
is clearly define the problem.
Just don't give the problem.
Like customers are not logging in.
That's not a problem.
That is an outcome That is.
An outcome of a problem, make sure
your problem is very well defined.
Only then start talking ai.
AI is not step one.
It's not step two.
It's not step three.
It's probably step five.
Step six, make sure all your steps
before AI are properly sorted.
Use high quality, unbiased
data for model training.
Make sure that your data is
properly vetted, properly validated.
Treat AI as an assistant,
not a replacement.
that's something that I
can just make a headline.
AI is not here to replace anyone.
People who use AI will replace
the people who don't use ai, but
AI will not replace anything.
Make sure that AI is your assistant.
It's not making decisions for you.
Continuously test, monitor and
refine models to improve accuracy.
Again, let's face self-explanatory.
Communicate AI insights transparently to
stakeholders, but make sure your analyst
actually agrees with the data as well.
Sometimes when you're talking
with large data sets, some of
the data will not make sense.
So your analyst might cut down garbage
data and give you a proper graph, and then
transparently show it to stakeholders.
What future I see of AI
in product management.
I think it's quite clear.
Your bis, your proper business
inside should properly be using ai.
It's very crucial that you
have predictive models.
You have current and anana model
and you have historical models.
They all should work seamlessly
merging with business intelligence
systems, real time AI, decision making.
That is something that is still quite far
away, but I have seen intelligent CEOs
referred to as I CEOs who are actually
CEOs, but an AI and who are making
business decisions or actually just
suggest suggesting business decisions.
So it can be happening in real
time, but still a bit far away.
But I think.
AI should still be vetted, should still
be properly managed, but there will
be a point where AI will constantly
be making decisions without actually
involving anyone else, but that's
still quite far away right now.
As I said, AI cannot replace
anyone at this point.
Improved explainability, AI models
will become more transparent
in how they generate insights.
Fully AI driven product management, still
quite far away, but that is the future.
it might not be, an automated
solution, but product management,
product development, product
management is different.
Product development is different,
but product development will heavily
be influenced with AI code sourcing.
So AI might be writing code for basic
models, but still you need software
engineers to properly validate that code
and actually improve that code as well.
So that is everything from my side.
As I said, this topic is still
something that I'm learning as
well, but it's a need of the time.
You have to make sure that your, your
product management is properly, improving
with these emerging technologies.
You like lms.
and make sure to be, on track
for yourself to be improved.
And, for improving not just yourself,
but your product, your company, and make
sure that your customers are getting
the best out of your product using the
LLMs and using all the technologies
that the current industry has to offer.
Thank you so much.
I'm very thankful to, the Con 42
conference, for inviting me to speak and,
please feel free to connect with me on
LinkedIn and, I'll make sure to respond
anything that you guys have to ask.
Thank you so much.
Have a wonderful day.