Hi everyone.
My name is Homan Ortega.
I'm going to talk about security auditing
tools in network in less language models.
less language models, basically category
of the learning models based on networks
and other that language processing, the
tall aim to analyze the security of these,
language from the developer point of view.
Analyzing the ities.
That can include in, in the edition
of these models, among the mo
the main points to be discussed.
We can highlight introduction to LM,
introduction to thewas, 11 to 10,
auditing tools and applications that
handles these models, and, explain a
use case with the test attack tool.
we start with introducing
these kind of models.
this kind of models, the base of
these models are transformers.
Transformers are a type of,
neural network architecture, use
in natural language processing.
Tax, like machine translation, test
generation and test generation.
They were introduced.
They were introduced in the paper.
A test is all you need in 2017.
The key of transformers is the
sales, attentions mechanisms,
which allows the models to weigh
the importance of different work
incentives when making, predictions.
Citation, each word or token in a sentence
can attend to every other word, allowing
the model to capture two, relationships
between these 10 words, more effectively.
This helps transformers and
understands context, the context,
better than previous models like
recurrent network neural networks.
Original transformer
have two main components.
Encoder code the encoder, process
the input data, like a sentence
and create a representation of it.
And theod, use the encoder
representation to generate.
Then they put translated sentence.
In the case of card of tax, like
translation, the input is processed
by the encoder under theod.
The translations, the translation
buys on the encoders output.
The training process of these kind of
models is generally, divided into stages.
The pre-training and fine tuning
stages, the pertaining stage is where
the model is trained on, on, on large
test ra to the, this word in a center,
in a sequence or complete sentence.
This.
Alert and general representation of the
language and the file tuning, stage.
After the pre-training stage, the
model is fine tuned with a specific
data and allows for particular tasks
such as tech specification question
answering on generate or generating
according text in a specific context.
with the groaning property of this kind
of models such as GBT, JAMA among others,
always, eh, has publish a specific list
of ities for this kind of applications.
The, comes, in response to the rapid
adoption of these kind of models in,
in, in many industries with the aim of
High lane, the main security problems
associated with this, emerging technology.
In this table, we can
see the minimal where.
We can highlight in that we can
highlight in language models.
Now we analyze some of
them in more detail.
For example, one of the
talk of the top rank Es, if.
Involves manipulating input prompts
to achieve unintended or malicious and
model outputs regarding investigation.
This of this Ed is recommended to
validate all inputs before processing
them with the LM command while
least could also be implemented, and
the types of data can be process.
Will be limited.
For example, in a element scenario
stating input from external
sources such as website or files
controlled by a user, in jection is
obtained need in which an attacker.
Manipulate external inputs such as
web or web content or user data,
which are then processed by the model.
This can lead the model to behave in
ways not intended by the developers,
compromising the security and
the integrity of applications.
For example, Ali Pro could be generated
a summary of the provided document by
an attacker and manipulating external
source in jets, hidden pro prompts,
include confidential information
from other files, for example, or
from a specific web page for example.
Of external manipulation, the model
generates content can generate content.
Incorporating sensitive details
from un outsized sources leading to
data leakage and security breach.
Another res example of Jection is,
in the people with tiptoe, GPT-4
is too smart to be safe, still
chart with elements via thier.
This research, explored how these
models can be manipulated to engage in
conversations with, In conversations
using encryption or coded message,
thereby of scoring, the true intent.
This method called, bypass Monitoring
Systems Design into the Technic user.
A common example, might be the use
of the of C test or simple scrambling
in incoming message, which an
attacker can use to generate a code.
Responses, responses or the code,
sensitive information without it
paying all used to a no server.
Injection is also, this attack
is also known as yearly.
Breaking involves in this attack
involves directly in manipulating the
commas that are sent to these models.
This research with the detailed
do anything, no charity
machine, and evaluating, in the.
Jailbreak prongs on less language
models, analyze and evaluate
so-called jailbreak prongs, which
are common the same to bypass TI
restrictions impose of these models.
These prongs allow users to obtain answers
that goul normally may be blocked due to
ethical, illegal, or security constraints.
The study investigates how these lib
pros work and how effective they are,
by passing, words, the researchers
co and gala side and collective size.
several samples of jail that has been
created and shared in the community
without economy of industrial integration.
In element deploy development
that is crucial intraining
for language compression.
five tuning for quality ment and
embedding no demand specific knowledge.
However, these data sets, can be,
susceptible, allowing attackers to
manipulate them, this manipulation.
no known as po poisoning can
compromise the mother's performance
and lead to generate content aligned
with malicious intentions during
pre-training and attacker Introduce.
misleading language and sample and
samples shaping the models in or
understanding of a specific subjects.
Consequently, the model might
produce outputs reflecting the
inject the injected bias when used
in practical app applications.
One of the attack, one of the attacks,
that has been investigated in last
years, it attacks, this attacks,
reference to, deliberate attempt to
manipulate or deceive an artificial
intelligence or material learning
model by providing it with credit.
Carefully craft input data designated
to cows, the models to make in,
to make incorrect predictions or
decisions these attacks exploit.
Try to exploit es in, in, in the models
decision making process typically by
introduces a small in person table change
in the input app, in the input data.
These are the key
characteristics of albe attacks.
For example, smart, per bats alax
typically involve adding a small pho
crop per perturbations to input data
of 10 imperial tables, two months.
modern vulner.
These attacks exploit specific weakness
in the mature learning models such as.
Eh, it's inability to, to general
generalize well, to, to new and
in data or the sensitivity of the
model to certain types of input.
we can classify guy,
eh, with two, two types.
White box and black box.
White box.
Eh, assume the attacker has
full knowledge of the model.
Including, its a architecture
parameters entering data.
They are the attacker.
Use the information to generate samples
that are most likely to receive the model.
And on the, and on the other side, we have
black box attacks in black box attacks.
the attacker doesn't have direct
access to the models internal workings.
in.
Instead, the attackers rely relies on
observing the model's output in response
to different inputs, and using this
information to graph adversarial samples.
Machine learning systems are
vulnerable to, to wide rights
of many adversarial, attacks.
Many of them employ class machine learning
models like linear regression and superb
machines, as well as the learning systems.
The majority of attacks.
often try to reduce classified
performance on particular tasks.
the area of machine learning
investigates a class of assault
mean to degrade classified
performance or on a particular tax.
At this point, we regard,
different, classify adversarial
task in different types.
Eh, these are the six we call
highly, six adversarial strategies
and the need for these defenses.
The jection, as I comment before,
basically jection in attacks involved
crafting input to manipulate the
behavior of these models, cautioning
them to, to produce harmful.
Or unintended by splitting their
reliance on, on, on usher prompts.
Another kind of attacks
is the bastion attacks.
This kind of attacks,
involve, modifying inputs.
to mislead, models at inference time,
making them, still see an effective
means of bypassing a costal system.
The tax objective of the kind of, this
kind of tax is to generate an input that
is misclassify misclassified without
needing to understand the artificial
intelligence models internal mechanism.
Making a taxi still here,
particularly difficult to go under.
Another kind of attacks
is poisoning attacks.
target the training files of, artificial
intelligence models, injecting malicious
data into the training sets and training
sets to compromise the models, behavior
manipul by manipulating the training data
or is labels that can come, made the model
perform poorly during the deployment.
Another kind of attacks is the
modeling inversion attacks.
Eh, I'm still reverse engineering
artificial intelligent models to
retrieve sensitive information
about the training data.
In these attacks, malicious
actors, analyze their
predictions they made by a model.
In response to, to, to many inputs.
Using this analysis helps them in
fair sensitive details about the
data the model was turning on.
For example, by sharing how the model
reacts to different input patterns,
attackers can review features or even
t portions of the OR training data set.
Another kind of attack
is mod model extraction.
Model extraction attacks aim to replicate
the functionality of proprietary model
by quoting it with numeral inputs and
observ and observing its output, it's
outputs this attack when attacker
elicited appropriate the training model.
typically involving regressing engineering
where the attacker receivers the system
and parameters to replicate his full
san once in possession of the replicated
system, the attacker can exploit it
with, for values, malis issues, activity.
finally, the member cease inference.
Inference attacks involves an adv
adverse to the use sensitive information.
Sensitive information from
an artificial inte model.
By meaning it outputs and behaviors.
For instance, an attacker might
use the confidence levels of
a. To determine if a person was
part of the model training data.
Typically, a model training or on a
specific data point will generate high
confidence predictions for that data point
if it goes in the training data sets.
And by introducing slight modifications
to the input data and observing
fluctuations in the models confidence
levels, an attacker can make educated
guesses about somewhat precise
presence in the training data set.
at this point, I'm going to commend
some tools that I interesting to
evaluate the model robustness.
For example, the Pro J framework, that
is a tool that design need to study.
Whole language models like GPT
can be manipulated using rooms, eh
port pair that is Aron on of prone
automatic interactive refinement.
It is an automated, methodology
for iteratively refining problems
with the wall of jailbreaking
of jailbreaking L lms.
Jail breaking, refers to 10 that
bypass security restrictions and
lanes imposed by language models.
And another, tool,
interesting tool is stop.
That is a framework that explored
how to perform attacks on MLMs
using a decision three structure.
Another interesting tool is, is
failing indication, indicators.
This are, it is an open source tool for
detecting and evaluating fairness metrics
across data and models in particular.
This tool includes the ability to
evaluate the distribution of data sets.
It will evaluate the model
performance, feel confident about
the resource with confidence in
intervals and multiple three cells.
And also, with these tools, we can,
explore, root causes and opportunities
for improvements in our models.
now I'm going to talk about privacy
and security As commented before,
this kind of models might, may leak
sensitive information or be to,
to attacks such as pro injector or
adversarial manipulation at this point.
Focus on ensuring data privacy
and security audits focus on
detecting and addressing vulner.
For example, we can find some auditing
tools like Pro, pro request to a set
of strategies, tools or techniques
design need to save what the behavior
of these kind of models for, from
malicious or on intent on intended.
Pro use a models with, t 6 million
parameters that has been training,
on a less data set of attacks and
branch from phone, any on internet
to test.
the three model is as, as going to
the repository to repository in.
And using it with the free inference,
API, that the platform, offer us
basically, this tool is a, Offers like
the capacity to prevent harmful of all
malicious interactions by filtering,
monitoring, and responding to adversarial
inputs, ensuring that the models
behavior remain safe, ethical, and
aligned, line with the intended use.
We have other, other tools like Jamma
word reference to a security tool or
the strategy design, for wording layer
less language models like Meta jama.
Against potential is
and adversarial attacks.
This tool offers a table solution
to protect s against a pro injection
and breaker attacks by combining
different techniques or in filtering,
normalization and monitoring.
I'm monitoring the and input.
I'm monitoring the input of the user.
Essentially this model employs a. At
multiple levels to mitigate the risk
of jection and break attacks using
techniques like dynamic impulse filtering,
pron normalization and con, con and
contextualization, response policy
and active monitoring and a response.
To test this model, we can do
it with the hugging face site.
Jamma.
Jamma ES will not only tell us
whether the content is safe or not.
But we also classify the content
into 14 different categories.
These categories have been straight from a
taxonomy, introduced in the following, in,
in the following, in this investigation.
Finally I'm going to comment, tool
for, this design need for adversarial
attacks, that augmentation and
model robust robustness testing
in natural language processing.
Basically this attack is, to a framework
for the detect for testing attacks,
using techniques like data augmentation
and natural language processing.
This tool, allows user to test.
To test how model is to the samples
and helps to improve it ness,
choosing the sentiment analysis model.
for this case, we'll use the
Pretrained bare Model train, train
it on the EMDB mobile review dataset.
I commonly use dataset for
binary sentiment classification.
Data tax provides a variety of attack,
attack strategies for this use case.
Will use the text attack.
A popular attack 10 that replace
words in the input test with
pseudonyms, the full, the model.
Without changing the
semantic, meaning of the text.
Now you can ruin the attack on a
simple input to see how robust the
analysis model is against the sample.
After ruling the attack, you will
receive a al samples where mine
change to the input test, have
altered the model expiration.
In this case, the model or in,
or originally predict positive
sentiment for the original test.
However, after replacing
words like love with like it.
And really with griping the model
match incorrectly predict negative
sentiment de, despite the fact that
the overall meaning remains, positive.
Once you have identified witness
in the model, you can use the Cyac
data augmentation capabilities to
retrain the model with adversarial
samples to improve it robustness.
This step allows you to augment
your data set with adversarial
samples and retrain model, making
it more resistant to such attacks.
I am finally commenting what the
interesting resources that we can
find in, in, in Bush, for example.
These are the bush that have
been blue published in the
last year, with this topic.
And these are, specific, you
have resources for with, uh.
with the papers that I commented, and
this is another interesting resources
that we can, when we can, for extend
information provided in this presentation.
this is the final of the
presentation, I think.
Eh, that has be, can be hobby.
Interesting.
for developers and secreted researchers.
And that's all.
Thank you very much for attendance in
the con go 42 language models in 2025.
thank you very much.
Bye.