My name is Oma and I'm
joined by my colleague Nain.
We're thrilled to be here at the Con 42
lms discussing one of the most exciting
and transformative topics in our field.
Generative ai.
Data science has always embraced
innovation, but the emergence
of generative AI presents a
truly transformative shift.
Before we dive in, we're gonna
quickly introduce ourselves.
I'm a platform engineer IBM within the
client engineering team, working mainly
on automation pilots helping clients
achieve their transformation goals.
Nin.
Hi everyone.
I'm Nin.
I am data scientist in
IBM Cloud Engineering.
Same team as O Omar and my daily
does involve trying to understand
client's problem, trying to solve
them with data and ai, and now while
trying to solve them with Ative ai.
Thank you.
Darin.
Before we dive in, I'm gonna
quickly just walk you through
what we've been covering today.
I'll be.
First talk, walking through the
evolving landscape of data science.
I'll then pass on to Darin, who
will share her practical experience
with genes and then her the impact
of Genes VI on data scientists.
And I'll then look at the future of data
science with genes and finally share
some actionable next steps at the end.
yeah, let's dive in.
Generative AI didn't appear overnight, as
you can see from the chat on the right.
Is market size, has shuttle over
the past few years and will continue
to do so over the next decade.
However, several key technological
breakthroughs have enabled its rapid rise
in recent years from the introduction
of transformer architecture to the
access of massive data sets, and now
even advances comput computational power
like NVIDIA's, GPUs and TPU have made
large scale AI trading more feasible.
But how exactly is generative AI
different from traditional AI that
we've seen over the past few years?
traditional AI focuses on analyzing
existing data sets while generative
AI is focusing on creating new
content like your images, your
text, even our music and code.
And you are all accustomed this,
accustomed to this with models like
G PT 4.5, that can now even create
synthetic data sets that preserve
static statistical properties
while also protecting pro privacy.
And this is something that an army will
touch upon with our experiences later on.
However, to fully grasp the scale of
this transformation, let's explore
how AI workflows have shifted from
this prediction to generation.
I.
For years, AI and data science primarily
focused on prediction based models.
classifying data, making forecasts
and optimizing processes on based
on historical patterns, right?
However, with generative ai, we're
moving beyond just prediction
creation, like I mentioned before.
synthetic data, image,
text, all that good stuff.
This shift, introducing a new way
of thinking about AI workflows.
Let's break it down.
on the left side, we can see the data
science lifecycle before this shift.
And this, showcases the traditional
data science lifecycle, which
involves, your business understanding,
defining the problem to be solved.
Data mining and cleaning,
gathering and pre-processing this
data, feature engineering and
exploration and understanding
these patterns and relationships.
Relationships and data.
Predictive modeling, your
traditional training machine
learning models to make forecasts.
And finally the data visualization,
where you're presenting these insights
to stakeholders and your clients and
whether they might be, while this
workflow is well established and all good,
it's really centered around structured
data and predictive ana analysis.
Now, let's see how this is.
Com is, Is in comparison with
the right side, which looks
at the generative AI workflow.
Generative AI introduces a different
approach focusing on creation.
Like we mentioned before,
we still have the business
understanding, which is crucial.
We need to know, how to, forecast
this understanding of the data.
But now we frame these problems in terms
of generation, not just prediction.
And prompt engineering.
The new feature engineering, let's
say, crafting prompts effectively
to guide these AI models, we also
have to give it relevant context.
So instead of your traditional labeled
data sets, gen AI relies on context
embeddings and training data relevance.
And we also have this.
Fine tuning element, which, we fine
tune these AI models, to give outposts
to our domains that we, highlighted.
And finally, we do this evaluation.
New ways of assessing AI generated
content, ensuring coherence,
correctness, and ethical consideration.
So just to summarize this, AI
workflows are evolving from predictive
analysis to generative capabilities.
And understanding the shift is
the key to leveraging AI's full
potential in real world applications.
More on that later.
However, with every breakthrough
comes concern, let's address some of
these biggest challenges data science
face in this new AI driven world,
and even some of these workflows.
This slide really addresses
the elephant in the room.
Many data scientists are genuinely
worried about how genes AI
might impact their careers.
how we share, shared that the slide before
on how it's really automated this process.
Some might fear that is doing
everything that, that we're doing
essentially, but that's not the point.
And some of the points that data
scientists have put across is, These
models can analyze complex data sets
and produce insights in minutes that
might have taken days previously that,
we used to, without even seeing cases
where companies are using models to,
to replace custom machine learning
models that data sets used to work on,
for certain tasks like classification
or sentiment analysis, for example.
And, from the slide earlier, once again.
And the routine tasks like, data cleaning
and analysis, and even feature engineering
are increasingly becoming more automated.
While some fair AI could
replace data scientists, the
reality is quite different.
I'm going to pass onto Nain who will
showcase how generative AI is proving to
be an incredibly powerful partner rather
than a competitor over to, Thank you Umer.
So there are a lot of concern related
to generative AI and rightly Generative
AI is a powerful technology that
can do a lot of tasks we used to do.
It can fill in the missing
values in data, find anomalies
in data, and even label the data.
But think about it, it can do
all of this mundane tasks, thus
leaving us data scientists time to
focus on actual model development.
And even more, it can help us in
accelerate the model development,
for example, by suggesting
us some hyper parameters.
It can help us reach optimization faster.
And let's be honest, how many times
we have been in this scenario where
we did not have enough data or the
right data, but now that we have
generative AI was able to generate
data, we can bring ideas to life sooner.
So I'm here to say that data scientists
and JF AI are a powerful dynamic duo.
And I'm gonna go through some of the
project where data scientists have used in
native AI to accelerate the project build
and open opportunities for our clients.
Let's dive in.
Our first project, example is
WA, is was with a finance client.
The client had a marketing team
who tested out different marketing
strategy with different focus group.
The problem was that finding right
people for a focus group was difficult.
And furthermore, the marketing team
had to test all the strategy, multiple
time with different focus group, and
getting those people were hot overall.
This was a very time consuming
and resource intensive process.
So how did we help them?
While we use generative AI to, create
customer personas on the writing
side, you can see one of the example.
We have Sandy, who is 28 years old, single
mother, and she's a teacher assistant.
This persona was generated
by generative ai.
And how did we achieve that?
we had a team of data scientists,
firstly, who identify appropriate
model for this problem.
We use IBM Grite model for this.
Then the team gathered real customer
data and fed it to the model.
The generative AI was able to analyze
the trends in behavior of the customer
data and create the different personas.
And lastly, we had the data team,
again, validate the persona to
make sure they represented or they
were near the CU real customers.
And now that we had a model able
to generate personas, a client can
simulate multiple, focus group.
They can take out, try out their
board and innovative strategy with
this simulated focus group and thus
open lot of opportunities for them.
second example is something we all come
across commonly not having enough data.
for this, we had a client who
dealt with heavy machinery on
site and they were ready for,
focus on the hoisting operation.
They had large lift who offload and,
unloaded heavy materials, and they were
concerned that these lifts were not used
efficiently and thus it was costing them.
They was also concern that these, lists
were used by personnel and they wanted
to make sure, safety of these personnels.
And they wanted our help in that.
So how did we do it?
Firstly, they gave us some sensor
data and images of the site.
And when we analyzed the, images, we
realized we don't have enough data.
So what we did, we
augmented the images we use.
IBM Max Visual Expect, max Maximum
Visual Expect is a platform that have
computer vision and deep learning
and it allows you to train label.
And deploy models.
we had a data team who
augmented these images.
Of course, they choose what
kind of augmentation appropriate
for this project, and then we
were able to create new images.
Now that we had new created images
and sensor data, we were able to
simulate scenarios and identify
future risk and thus have a threat,
threat detection mechanism in place.
And also with these scenarios,
we were able to identify the most
optimized way of using this lift,
thus increasing efficiency and
reducing cost for our client.
Next example is not related to a project,
but I do it for any project in IBM.
We have to work with different domains.
For example, one day we
are working with retail.
One day we are working with
finance, and one day we are
working with telecommunication
and getting my head around the
domain can be very overwhelming.
I remember a particular project, it
was for a telecommunication company.
They gave us cell tower data and
they wanted to predict future
congestion, cell tower congestion.
They also give us a large document
and a mathematical formula on how they
manually calculate congestion currently.
And for me to understand those,
that document was very difficult.
It had so many terminologies
I never heard of.
what does QOS means?
So over here I use generative AI
to simplify the complex concept.
I also use it to summarize the
mathematical formula and make it more
understandable for me and even give,
do initial analysis of the data.
And because of that, I got my
head around the domain quite fast.
Seeing that generative AI did help give
me basic level of guidance, but I still
had to use my expertise to make decision.
For example, when I ask you what are the
KPIs that I should use for cell tower
congestion, it said, one of the kpi, like
successful handshake, but the data in
our, that we received wasn't relevant.
So again, you still, I still had
to use my expertise to make the
right decision for the project.
For our next project, and this is
very close to me, it is, was with a
company that dealt with contracts.
So they wanted to use generative AI
to generate clauses for the contracts.
The way it happened was the company
had templates for a contract,
for example, it'll have a start
date, end date, termination
clause, culpable, and so forth.
And based on the different client,
they would alter the contract.
For example, they might have a client
that does not need ANM ity clause, so
they won't need to add it in the contract.
So they were, they wanted to use
the native AI to make these changes.
So how did we do it?
We, again, we had a data team who
provided generative AI with the
temp, template of the contracts
and write the appropriate prompt.
What we were analyzing was,
what we observed was that the
generative AI was too wordy.
It was adding extra
information that wasn't needed.
And again, over here we need data.
scientists who kept on improving
the result iterated throughout the
project to get the final output.
So we do definitely need data science.
Don't be.
Generative AI is a incredible,
powerful and transformative
technology revolution the way we work.
But we still need the human
oversight and expertise to get
the most out of the generative ai.
And we need the human creativity
and insight to make appropriate
decision for a project.
And overall generative AI is here
to elevate us, nor replace it.
And now I will pass it on to
ER, who will talk about the
emerging trend in generative ai.
Thank you, Darin.
Now that we've touched upon some of
the experiences and impact lessons
with generative AI as data scientists,
it's to see what the future holds
and what's next with generative
AI and emerging trends within it.
One we're seeing quite often and more
recent is the use of multimodal models,
but for specific use cases, for instance,
watsonx, our own data and AI platform
is able to host many AI systems that
can analyze both texts and images.
and one example was with a project where
we had to utilize medical reports to
create more comprehensive DI diagnosis,
and we were able to pick out the right.
Multimodal model for that use case.
Another one was the, another one.
Trend is the reinforcement
learning in Geneva.
And this is where, reinforcement
learning acts as a feed feedback
mechanism that allows the generative
model to continuously improve this
output by learning from rewards and
through trial and error essentially.
and we're seeing this, for example, in
a lot of these models like deep Seek
and Chat GBT, that use reinforcement
learning to improve responses over time.
Offering more, a more comprehensive and,
contextually relevant answer to the user.
And finally, the most important
one I think, is open source
ai, the increased availability.
And, I. General accessibility and
collaboration to these models is what will
create the gap and allow those to really
make use of, the future of generative ai.
and really the future of generative
AI is going to be more interactive,
adaptable, and multimodal, allowing new
possibilities and applications across a
variety of industries that we've covered.
Now that we've looked ahead,
the real question is, what
should you do to stay ahead?
As a call to action, I can say
collaborate with ai, not against it,
not compete with it, or rather to
utilize it to invest in your skills,
whether that can be in research or
development, wherever it can be.
Invest in your skills in both AI and
utilize it to invest in your skills.
Gene AI continues to evolve.
It's clear that the future
is full of possibilities.
How will you embrace this change?
And with that, thank you very
much and we hope to see you again.