Hello everyone.
I'm Balaji today.
I'll be talking about securing l ls.
Let's get into the topic.
So today I'm dying diving into a
pressing issue in artificial intelligence
securing launch language models.
To prevent leaks on sensitive
code, critical data, and valuable
intellectual property, these leaks
can undermine business and trust.
A, as the LMS become indispensable,
tools across the Indus industries
from tech to healthcare, protecting
them is no longer optional.
It's a necessity.
So let's start this journey
to understand and fortify.
artificial intelligence
systems against these risks.
So what are s elements are cutting
edge AI systems designed to
understand and generate human-like
text with remarkable accuracy.
Take GPT with its staggering.
One 75 billion parameters.
It's a pioneer in natural
language processing.
These models drive tasks like content
creation, language translation, and
even customer support automation.
They act like digital's, linguists,
interpreting and crafting languages
in ways that revolutionize
technology interactions.
So the problem, so the real
problem that we're facing right
now with LLMs is data leaks.
The thing is the data leaks happens
even without knowing that it happens.
So despite these powers of L
lms, LMS can leak sensitive
information in several sneaky ways.
Leaks can stem from training data
where private details like names
or emails might linger unnoticed.
All from prompts where users
accidentally input this data.
And also from model, inversion, a
technique attackers used to reverse
engineering data from LM outputs picture.
And LM as a leaky bucket sends sensitive
code data and IP spill out, unchecked,
threatening privacy breaches, intellectual
property theft and competitive losses.
So I ask, are you, are your
A tools truly secure against
these vulnera vulnerabilities,
data leaks and their impact?
So the real world example that
we can go with is with Samsung in
2023, the employees inadvertently.
Leaked proprietary source code
by using Chad GBT exposing trade
secrets to potential rivals.
A healthcare provider lost pat,
patient data through L-N-L-L-M,
bridging trust and regulations.
A startup saw its intellectual property
vanished due to sloppy prompt handling.
IBM picks the average
database cost at 4.45 billion.
Which is a really hefty price.
The stable lists, these incidents,
their fallout and lessons like enforcing
strict input policies and sanitizing
data to avoid these costly mistakes.
Technologies for securing L lms.
Thankfully a new technologies can share.
can.
Shore up the LMS against these leaks.
Differential privacy, add statistical
noise to the data set, masking
the individual details while
keeping overall pattern consistent,
which is ideal for privacy.
Second option is federated learning,
which trains models on decentralized
devices like phones and servers, so
the raw data never leaves its source.
The third option is homomorphic
encryption and emerging model that
lets the LMS process encrypted
data without even decrypting it.
So it's a true frontier.
Things of these, things like these act
as a study ball and then it helps, for
the, companies to protect their data.
Data privacy solutions for L lms.
So beyond these core technologies that
are in use that we can use, we have got
specialized tools also in play data.
Privacy walls like those
from Sky Flow Act as secure.
repositories tokenizing the
data, like credit card numbers.
Before LMS really cease them.
LM Shield developed by patented AI
that filters user inputs in real time,
catching personal and proprietary
info before it really leaks.
Imagine a digital vault.
You were secrets.
Stay locked tight inside, and only
safe anonymous tokens can reach the.
These solutions are really
pivotal for complaints and also
for safeguarding our assets, best
practices for using LLM securely.
So that is tech technology that
is available right now, but that
alone won't cut it, that are also,
complaints that we need to make sure.
so the best practices that could be used.
Or, sanitizing the training data and
restricting access to limited people
and not to everyone, and who is training
the data and who can use the data.
And also conducting regular
audits and training employees
to handle, a responsibly.
So these four things will definitely
make sure that the best practices
are implemented in, each company
that could make LLM secure.
Next is, regulatory, complaints.
regulatory complaints talks about, how
standards can be set, which can, prevent.
data leaks.
So GDPI from, European Union in insists
on data rights, which becomes tricky
when models can memorize this, data.
HIPAA safeguards, health information
in the US demanding highend cloud
protection for patient records.
CCPA gives California consumers,
control over their data.
Pursuing for transparency,
the staple ties.
These, laws of strategies like
differential privacy of A-G-D-P-R
walls for HIPAA complaints, isn't
just a, just a checkbox, right?
It's the legal foundation for
safeguarding the AI deployment.
next is implementing a secure alarms.
So since we have seen, everything right
now on different ways we can, Secure lums.
We can see how to implement it.
So to put it in practice first,
assess, assess your data, what's
sensitive and what needs, guarding.
Then select the tools like privacy
walls or shields to protect it.
Set up, access controls to
limit the exposure to the data.
Train your staff on secure,
a use and audit systems
regularly for any weak spots.
This flow chart maps, out
your path to a leak proof LLM.
It's a clear actionable plan that turns
security theory into real world results.
Future trends and conclusion.
So looking at future trends, privacy,
preserving, AI is the need of the heart,
and that is what we see in the future.
And also there will be new protocols that
could be implemented, which can act as,
secure a on its own secure agents that can
help, to preserving the data on its own.
In summary, secure L LMS will help
to protect the assets and, the
companies need not have the fear.
If their intellectual property is
really lost to any of the other
companies and potential rivals.
the real priority right now is to secure
our lums to make sure that the data that
we want is not left out in the open so
that anyone can access it as they want to.
Thanks for listening.