Speaker 7: what you are watching is a
software pipeline with no people in it.
Requests come in as cards, agents
pick and move, analysis code, test,
and move them toward production.
Right now work is flowing across
this board runs are firing, and
nobody's touching the keyboard.
No human wrote this code, agents did.
But the interesting part isn't
that an agent can write code.
You know that.
It's everything around the code that
makes shipping it safe hi and welcome.
My name is Dennis, and what you
just watched is real software
pipeline with no people in it
Yeah.
Agents AI agents moving real work
towards production and the live
app they built NoteChick, and this
talk is about how that's built.
It's called a continuous agentic
deployment, and by the end, you'll
have a blueprint you can clone.
Definitely.
A quick word on who's talking.
I'm a principal engineer, and for
years before then, I ran delivery
as a process and people manager.
I spent a long, a l- a long time thinking
about h- how work flows through a team.
Now I am thinking about how it
flows through a team of agents,
and that turns out to be a CI/CD
problem, not a prompting one.
Here is the claim for the
next forty or less minutes.
Getting a model to generate code isn't the
easy ten-- i- i-- the easy ten percent.
The other ninety percent, the part
that decides whether you can do this
in a real workflow is the structure,
retries, validation, cost control, a
clear point where human stays in charge.
That the part nobody demos.
So that's the part I'm going to show
you as a framework you can clone.
Let me see.
One renames-- one rename
organize the whole thing.
CI/CD, continuous integration,
continuous delivery.
When the delivery is produced
by agents, I call it CAD,
continuous agentic de-deployment.
And for every stage of the pipeline,
I ask the same two questions.
First question is, what does this
stage become when an agent does
it, and second, and what the new
way to fail does they introduce?
Because every new capability, comes
with a new failure mode, and the
framework is mostly about the second one
I agree it.
Here is a whole pipeline on one screen,
and since we have a part of wife
demo, let me sh- let me have a look
at at what's going on our pipeline.
Yeah, it's working.
I want to feed it with
a few more features.
And next, I, I'll… And next
I'll explain what I've just done.
Yep, here you are.
Here is the whole pipeline on
the-- on one screen eight stations.
We call them silo in
Kanban in Kanban approach.
Each piece of work, one request
flows left to the right.
Yep from the left to so we
have the following s- silos,
to do, ready, SABA, dev, test,
human review, deploy, and done.
And let me walk it once because
everything later refers back to this map.
To do to do and ready are just columns.
The backlog and the commitment point.
The, so to do is a backlog and
ready is a commitment point.
SABA stands for system
analysis, business analysis.
The, that's play the analysis agent work.
It reads one line request.
Let me show you the one,
one, one, one line request.
So like that.
Add a faster feature… A fa--
Add a fastest feature highlight.
Show a KPI card naming the quickest
shipped feature and its cycle time.
So you can see that look
that looks like pretty…
That single single human-like
request, not a user stories you may
familiar with in Scrum as a role.
I want to see something because
I have the because I'll got
the following following value.
So that's just single
lined requirements Yep.
Let me see.
And let me switch on to my deck.
Here we go.
So it re-- SAB agent writes a one-line
request and r-write the spec files to
touch approach acceptance criteria.
And dev is the coding agent test
agent writes and run tests, obviously.
And human review is a person, that's me.
And deploy, merge, and ships.
Done is what is life.
Now the most important distinction in
this whole talk, look at the colors.
Look at the colors.
Some stations agents,
stochastic model decides.
One is a human, and the deploy is
deterministic plain code, no model.
I'll come back to why that
mo-- line matter why the,
that line matters a bit later.
And one more boundary drawn
with a da-da-dashed box.
Here are the whole this thing
drawn with a dashed box.
Everything inside it is i-it's f--
the framework, the engine, and the
app is built in a self-observant
dashboard called CED Console, which
visualize the very this very pipelines
sits out box outside the box.
But that separation is the difference
between a framework and a clever
repo, and I'll defend it near the end.
CED is the engine.
CED Console is just what it happens
to build today yeah let me bring
back to to, to our project board.
It f- one of the testing items is done
and I expect it in film review soon.
I'd like to feed this pipeline with
a few more a few more working items.
But let's continue with with
the presentation with decks
because it's important for
now how how it works exactly.
What did I build to run all this?
Almost nothing.
There is no orchestrator service,
no Tempo, no Airflow or no
database, so GitHub is the runtime.
GitHub project project is a state machine.
The boards the board columns are the state
and move, and moving card is a transition.
Actions is the agent runtime.
Every agent is a workflow run,
we'll see it later, with secrets
and logs you already trust.
And issue comments are the context bus.
Each station leaves its output as
a comment the next station reads.
That comment thread is
also your audit trail.
So let me show you the actual file
because this is the where it gets real.
I need to switch my browser to Cursor ID.
So I'd like to show you a dispatcher.
Here we go.
This dispatcher, the ca- the
core the heart of the framework.
It decides what to do next, how to pull.
There are there are transitions.
Yeah.
You will call on it later
and examine it yourself Yeah.
Let me continue.
On every tick it looks at the board,
checks each station WIP limit with
a work in progress limit limits.
And for any free slot, it
dispatches a card which spo-
spawns a fresh workflow run.
That run is the agent.
To prove my board let me show
you what's going on in the
browser on the top with action.
So each agent is a workflow
run is a action run.
So you can see this agent SAB dispatcher,
which called quite quite often.
Dispatcher, dispatcher, agent
SAB, agent dev, which just
stopped work- stopped working.
Yeah.
We'll examine it later.
What's going on there?
Yeah, pipeline is working.
SAB… Oh the important thing you
can see here SAB agent has a WIP
limit equals two not more than two
working items could be placed here.
And SAB agent couldn't pull any new work
from the left, from ready for the, for
work because it's, it has no capacity.
Why it has no capacity?
Because nothing still… No- nobody
pulled the card from it on the right.
So why?
Because dev agent and a dev silo has WIP
limit work in progress limit equals one.
So only one card could
be here in dev Yeah.
Once it's done the test agents which
capacity is or work in progress,
which is equal here equals two pulls
the card from the left freeing the
stored and dev agent at the same time
pulls new card from… done card from
SAB silo from the left because it,
it has a capacity right now and SAB
agent in a time pulls from the left
because dev agent just pulled from it.
So this pipeline runs as a pull system.
I can refer to combined approach
while the pull system is matter
here, but we should continue with our
deck because that's quite important.
Let me see
Yeah.
Capacity or capacity on demand.
Capacity on, capacity is on demand.
There is no pool of i-i-idle
agents waiting around.
A station's worker is conjured when
the, this the, when there is a work and
free slot, and it's gone when it's done.
Idle cost nothing, yeah.
In which model does each station use?
There is no buried that's not
buried in code, it's a config.
Let me show you.
I want to switch onto settings.
Yeah.
Action secrets and variables right here.
So you can here, you can see here model
model definition model dev, model fix,
which is used by by a fixer agent.
I told I, I to- I talk- I told you,
I tell you about that a bit later.
Model resolve the merge conflicts
and some other conflicts
resolver, which is Opus 4.8.
Model SCBA, the most interesting,
which we have seen in a, in live.
Model SCBA use Cloud Sonnet 4.6.
Model test use Cloud Sonnet 4.6.
Most expensive is dev and
error problem resolvers.
Also we can see WIP limits here.
WIP dev is a config one.
WIP SCBA two.
WIP S- WIP test two as well.
So you can config it on your own.
Yeah changing verba- variable and
the lens economics change so you've
no-- there is no code attached, and
cost decision sitting in plain sight.
Yeah agents.
Agents is Agents agents are actions
which runs onto GitHub runners and they
leave all agents leave audit trails.
Let's see it, audit trails.
Let's say we have some in human review
which we will proceed with a bit later.
At the throughput counter, let's
say so there is audit trail for ACBE
analys- analysis affected fi- files.
You can see that's something
that agent ra- wrote.
Approach, it decide about approach.
Acceptance criteria, what should be done.
That's instructions for a dev agent
and for for test agents as well.
Edge ca- cases for test
agent dependencies possible.
N- And notes, free notes.
So there is implementation re-
where dev agent was working
and test support of course.
We have some issues in review.
I'll review them later but I… the
thing I want to do is approve some cards
blindnessly but I needed to kick a deploy
Yep, the most important thing in this
whole pipeline that I get decisions.
I get decisions.
Say I get them just just just now, and
let me kick the agent deploy agent.
I go to actions.
Let me check if you can see it.
Yeah, you can see it.
I want to take deploy agent, and I
want to run a workflow what there is?
Two, two minutes ago.
Who did kick deploy agent?
Nobody kicked.
Let me kick one more time.
Up So deploy agent is in progress.
Yep.
We just checked cards.
Yeah, we just checked cards.
Let me see some since it's live
Yeah, let's talk about the stations
station contract, contracts.
Yeah.
Now, why specialized agents?
Why not one big agent
that does everything?
Because roles give you control.
A different module per stage,
a different prompt you can tune
and version, a separate working
progress limit, of course.
And when something breaks, you
can see which station broke.
One mega agent is a black
box with a single bill.
And here is the part that
makes this different.
Work node script.
Every station in the same
shape, is the same shape.
Five parts.
Let me see.
Workflow, assistant prompt, WP
limit, and model, and bore column.
The dispatcher doesn't know,
okay what the station does.
It just runs the shape.
And the behavior, what the agent actually
does, lives here in a Markdown file.
And let me switch on Cuso idea again.
Yep.
S- sorry, I just found it.
So there is a SAB agent and what
we can h- see here you are a
SAB analysis agent definition.
You are a system analyst, a
business analyst for a software
developer, development team.
Your job is to analyze any future
requests bug report, and produce
a structured analysis what a
developer who is also an AI agent
can follow to implement the solution.
Describe a deterministic process which
re-results are not deterministic.
Could be read the issue, read the
code MD or generic for project.
Explore the code base, identify the scope,
consider edge cases, write the analysis.
You've already seen all those
parts in audit trail and comments.
Produce your analysis in the, in
this exact markdown structure.
Affect first approach, and so on.
So you've seen it.
I've I've showed, I've shown
you this a bit some time ago.
And now let me let me now to
bring us back to to, to DAG.
And later we will scan what's going on.
But now I just want to feed my
pipeline with one the rest features.
Let them both work
Yeah.
Let's proceed with slides.
The behavior is the config is the config
reprompt file, and we have three of them.
And because every station, Every station
is the same shape, the line is extended.
Say I wanted a new stage, a security
review of diff or something else,
a security review or I don't know,
any other reviews, and sitting
between test and human review.
I'm n- not going to build this
lab, but here is all it takes.
A prompt that says that to check
a workflow copy from any existing
station because the shape is identical.
A WIP limit, work browsing,
a column on the board for
things and the new work exists.
The one bit of plumbing I won't
hide you write into the flow with a
single new hope in the dispatcher.
Yeah, let's see the dispatch again.
Let me show you the dispatcher
Oh, sorry
Let me show you the this pattern
Once again
Now, let me show you the dispatcher
Here it is.
Dispatcher, dispatcher I need to,
This is sh- dispatcher, dispatcher.
Here's dispatcher.
So you who- you should wi- wire it
in dispatcher, but it's one one hop.
I can't find.
Yeah.
That's quite easy.
AC.
So we can download and see it later.
And, let's get back to new station.
So you know how to do the station.
Yeah that's the whole point.
No existing sta- no, no
existing station changes.
You don't change any existing station.
You add a worker to the
line by describing it.
I prompt a copy workflow.
Copied workflow.
One hope not to rewrite in the factory.
That's inversion of control, and that's
what makes this a framework, not a script.
Yeah
Let me to proceed with, let me to proceed
What's regarding re- reliability?
Which, What's the most
re- reliable part of it?
And agents are not deterministic.
They get things wrong, so how
do you build something reliable
out of an unreliable part?
Same mechanism we have.
First, the spec lives in the test.
So this AB agent writes the
acceptance criteria, the test agent
turn them into a suite, and the
code only moves forward if it pass.
Not does it look right, does
it satisfy satisfy the spec?
Yeah.
Let's show, let me show you test agent,
so you can see how test agent work.
We're most interested in we're
most interested in in the prompts.
Yep, in the prompts.
Yeah.
Here match the test and style.
Use descriptive names, test name.
Don't test implement- implementation
detail, test behavior.
Don't mock.
Don't write.
If a test requires specific test data
data, create it in the test setup.
Don't rely on exist- external state.
Run the full test suite before
finishing or just few new test.
And that was that was a prompt,
and what regarding YAML.
So we can as you can see… Yeah, as
you can see let me show a bit more
Yeah
Let's re-resize it for
you so you can see more
One more
Great.
I think you can see more right now.
There is a, there are there
is some self-bailout, so
the script won't go further.
The cart won't go further while
it satisfied requirements.
So each test agents have t-
three tries, three tries.
We can see it a bit later.
Let me show.
Yeah, bounded self-correction what it was.
But when the test fails, the line
doesn't panic and it doesn't ask me.
It fixes one revoke the cart in place,
and reruns the suite up to three times.
Three, not infinite, because
infinite is just a way to burn
money and stack the problem.
After three, the line
stops and hands it to me.
Third is isolation.
Every cart works on its own branch,
agent issue say, agent issue
seven, agent issue nine, so on.
Parallel agent can stop each other
because they never share working copy.
Conflicts, if any, surface later under one
control place, the merge, and I will show
what happened then the the, in a moment.
Let me see.
Let me check the screen.
Yeah here we are.
And let's check what's
go on with say, here.
Yeah, I open so you can see pull request
At le-- at the live book
column view, pull request.
No, it's not pull request.
Pull requests are there
Let's check the snapshot freshness.
Yeah, and you can see there main from
agent issue one hundred seventy f- four.
So each agent work works
on its own br- branch.
So let's proceed.
We've seen deploy.
So let's check what's on the
production site right now.
Yeah, here's some production
features, real numbers.
Median cycle is quite long for deployed
for shipped items, and it became
bigger for items that stuck in human
review because they they lead time is
account straight now because I talk and
they are seat- they're sitting here.
Yeah.
Let's get to the, let's get to the end.
The two honest things I owe you about the
last step about keying kick deploy kick.
Both things Sharp View
work has already spot.
They are not gaps, they are design.
One, the word continue.
The deploy i- in this system
isn't auto-fired the instance
something something's approved.
It's a human kick.
I press bar, and that's deliberate.
The abstract for this top promise,
promises three points where humans stay
in control, and this is that point.
I can fire, it's it fully continues with
one trigger, and you show, I show you
where but I choose to keep a hand on it.
Two the deploy itself has no
agent in it, no, m- model or
dock compose in production.
The agent own the deploy, the analysis,
an analyzed code tests resolve
conflicts, but n- the release is plan
determine the code, merge, build,
deploy, and the version pins more test.
One more I show, I have to show you.
Cursor
and I want to show you agent deploy
Yeah, there is agent deploy.
So there is no any call of LLM.
It's just a deterministic script.
Yeah, you can see it.
Agent deploy is just
deterministic script Great.
It merged the approved work, builds
an image, ships it to my own server
and whenever you want, and then
makes one assertion, the version
live on the URL, URL must call the
exact commit that it just built.
It supports API health until that's
true, and then it's deployed.
What about observability?
There is observability.
You can manage what you can see.
So two things are
instrument from the start.
The bot itself is observability layer.
As you can understand the bot itself
is an observ-observability layer.
You can observe it each moment.
Every agent run logs that it's been.
One script rolls it up into
numbers that actually matter.
And let me run that script in
the in the, in, in the cursor.
I want just run that script
so it will gather the costs
right here Sky Agent run logs
Yeah.
While we are waiting, I'll
just, I want just click… No
I don't want to click anything.
We have to wait, and we will have
our numbers live in this file.
Yeah.
A bit later.
But it's working.
Let me bring us back
Yeah, Here we are in the
Great
While we are waiting the costs are
gathering let me proceed with, the most
maybe most important part where it fails.
And because blueprint that only shows
the happy path isn't blueprint, it's
an advert, and I'm not speculating
everything he happened while the agent
built the dashboard he's been looking at.
And gi-- the problem number
one is ambiguous request.
Give the agent a work card and it wonders.
The fallback is the ana- the fallback
is the an-anal-an-analysis GitHub front.
The spec becomes the contract
everything else is checked against.
No spec, no good outcome.
It, n-next problem, two
features touch the same file.
Two of these digits can both
edit the dashboard style sheet,
a real merge conflict at deploy.
Isolation kept it hidden until the
merge, and then a resolve agent agent
rebased, fixed it, and ran the deploy.
No human.
The conflict became a step, not a crisis.
A step a stage stalls on yes.
Sometimes items just stage in
its column and alert files and
redispatch resumes the same branch.
Nothing is lost, nothing
ships nothing ships broken.
The line stopping itself is a feature.
And the owner's boundary of war,
agents are excellent at small,
well-scoped, test-baked changes.
They struggle with ambiguous specs
and big cross-cutting refactors.
The real bottleneck was never the model.
It's good issues on a code base
where features are additive,
a-additive so agent don't collide.
Now fix that and the bigger
model is reliable to me.
Yeah.
Six reason why it's the
w-why it's a framework.
I called that this framework
and here is six reason.
One, the dispatcher owns the loop.
It calls your station,
not the other way around.
That's the inversion of control.
Two, every station is
in the same contract.
Yeah.
And three, behavior is an
ex-externalized prompt library.
Four, the board is the state machine.
Five, the liability lives in
the conventions, branch per
card, tests, and the spec.
Tests is the spec.
Items that stay put on failure.
Six, modules and limits
are config, not code.
And one honest gap.
So you hear it from the-- me first.
Today, the engine ship
fused to this one app.
Kate is the agent.
K-CD is the agent.
CD console is the e-example it builds.
Pulling them fully apart is the next
step, and that work is in the repo.
So I guess that's it.
That's continuous agentic deployment,
CACD, with agents in the loop.
Yeah.
And a human on the gate.
It's all open source, and the
links are on the screen, and the
apps is app is live right now.
Thank you, Conf42, and
thank you for watching.
And I'm Dennis, and go
building factory, guys.