Speaker 30: Okay.
Hello, everybody.
Today I want to talk
about the voice agents.
Not the chatbots with the microphone,
but systems that actually reason
while we are talking to it.
We'll try to explore the pipeline
layer by layer and look on modern
architecture, how it works under the hood.
Quick intro.
I'm a Bogdan, founding engineer
right now at Soleia.ai.
We are building AI operating system
for the home service businesses.
Before, worked in Wix, Revolut and
other big companies, and co-founded
several startups before, and
overall have 13 years of experience.
Yeah, but let's dive deep
into the-- our problem.
Main statement, it's voice
becoming the production interface.
Why?
It's because voice is pretty natural
way of communication, and it's not
requires any UI or user interface.
Moreover, voice works where
text chat actually slow.
It's unnatural or detached from the task.
Moreover, because it's not requires
user interface, it could be plug and
put it into the different context of
the business: sales support, healthcare,
education, internal operations, whatever.
For our home service businesses,
we actually also offer a voice
agent on top of our field service
management system that actually helps
our clients to work with end users
so voice is not a chat with audio.
Most people can actually think about it
as just a chat with audio on top of it.
But conceptually, it's different.
Text is a sync readable
way of communication.
You can edit before sending.
Plus it's a request-response semantic.
So for engineering, it's just more or less
classical way of working with the system.
We can do different operations
and just return the response.
But voice is a synchronous, so the user
hears it once and timing is meaning.
If you pause too long, the
user thinks you're confused.
If you respond too fast, you cut them off,
and there is no undo button, actually.
Conversation, it's a real time thing, and
it comes with complexity on top of it.
Let's dive into it.
At the simplest level, voice
agent does five things in a loop.
So listen, understand,
reason, act, and speak.
This look clean on the slide, but each
step actually much harder when it must
happen in real time and under five hundred
milliseconds, because everything above,
it's already awkward in the conversation.
We're going to explore
a classical pipeline.
The simplest architecture here
is a three models in a row.
So a speech-to-text, LLM for
reasoning, and text-to-speech.
Clean modular, you can swap any
component and observe any stage.
The problem, every stage
waits for the previous one.
Yeah, obvious.
So in reality, it should
be streaming in general.
So every stage actually streams the
every chunk, and every another stage
consumes this chunk and produce it.
So this is a whole streaming thing.
We cannot wait for some step plus there
is a family of models as alternatives,
kind of speech-to-speech models like
GPT real time or Gemini Live that
actually do everything from one thing.
It's lower latency, more natural
feel, but we're losing control,
observability, and easy to use.
Plus we can do different
tricks with this set of things.
Moreover, we don't have ability to
switch providers because, for example
for different languages it could be
different or we want ElevenLabs voice.
But if you're using ChatGPT, for
example you have just everything
that gives nothing more.
Usually the stack follows the
three steps or kind of cascade path
because it's the most production
systems actually people using.
First challenge comes actually not
from LLMs, but before any model
runs, we have a problem of real time.
We're getting audio and from and to user.
It requires WebRTC, jitter,
echo cancellation, packet
losses et cetera, et cetera.
Audio arrives as 20 milliseconds
frames and classical engineering here.
And yep it's even before a single
token is generated, we need
to solve everything like this.
However, it's solvable, and majority
of work already done by platforms
that's worth using in this case
Another hard problem actually
it's when should the agent talk?
This is a turn-taking
problem in another words.
Let's see three scenarios, for example.
First scenario, it's too early, so
agent starts replying somewhere in
between conversation just because
there was a pause in user flow.
It's already not good experience.
Another example, it's, for example,
it waits too long and conversation
becomes the same awkward.
Ideally, that's needed is just right
moment when we decide it's w- it's a
time to turn role and reply to the user.
It should be well-timed, so kind of
response when the caller is done.
It's important to do, and
actually it's a pretty reasonable
for quality of conversation.
Voice activity detection, it's
the first part of this problem.
We need to understand when, speech or not.
Just simple answer of the question,
is there the speech right now?
Yes or not?
For every 50 milliseconds frame, just
because we are working with WebRTC.
This is already a good start,
but it's actually not enough
for the whole conversation.
Some systems already
have everything included.
For example, for Deepgram, it's built in.
It's not answering the questions,
it's has the user finished the
thought or should the agent respond?
Just at least detecting of the detecting
of the speech so the next step, it's yeah,
there is several ways how people using
this, so several kind of technologies.
In general, it's just either WebRTC voice
activity detection or voice activity
detection based on simple, small deep
learning model that actually do the same,
more higher accuracy, but consume CPU.
So just need to consider something.
Silo, it's more or less balanced choice
and by default recommending this.
Another step as we described, after we
are able to actually detect activity,
we need to answer another question.
It's is there the conversation complete,
does the user finished his thought?
And to detect the turn, should the agent
take the turn actually at this moment?
It's pretty important and pretty hard
problem in general just because it's
influence the conversation quality.
If we end pointing too early,
the agent start answering
somewhere between the user flow.
Ideally, it should be start
when we finished our thought.
So after we assemble all these things
the final pipeline looks like this.
Voice activity detection and pointing
and turn detection, then speech-to-text,
LLM reasoning, and text-to-speech.
This is the overall
pipeline, classical pipeline.
However, there is additional constraint.
It should be done under
five hundred milliseconds.
Beyond this, the conversation
starts to feel unnatural.
Usually the best case or best
scenario distribution looks like this.
Every part of the pipeline
requires specific time budget.
Of course, LLMs need more time, and
it force us to use fast LLMs because
otherwise the conversation and the
whole time budget not within SLA that
usually nice to have However, another
problem could be here, it's tool calling.
Because we want to make these
agents to actually be smart.
CRM lookup or calendar check or
payment call, something like this.
So 500 milliseconds to five seconds.
So it's way beyond the speech budget.
There is several strategies
how it could be maintained.
First one, it's acknowledge
with a kind of filler speech.
"Let me pull that up," or, "Let me think
about it." Another one, it's a slow pass.
So just run the tool
asynchronously in the background.
And it could be repair pass.
For example, slice the result back when
it's ready if it's relevant, of course.
In this case, never let the tool
call block the conversation.
It should be covered with a speech,
run asynchronously, and injected
back during the conversation flow.
This is pretty actually nice idea,
and idea of running something in
background and injecting this into the
conversation actually reuse- reused in
the further architectural decisions.
Overall ecosystem for voice
agents, not small actually.
A lot of services on top of it.
LiveKit actually pretty nice thing.
It's SDK where we can build
this pipeline from different
components, plug-and-play feeling.
Silero, for example, for
voice activity detection.
Deepgram actually pretty good.
OpenAI, Anthropic, et cetera, for models.
ElevenLabs, et cetera, et cetera.
Plus different orchestration
platforms Retail, VAPI, just in
case we need everything on top of
it with observay- observability
and different kind of patterns of
agents or combination of agents.
Of course, with the
price, they not so cheap.
But overall, ecosystem pretty big How--
There is a next step in our conversation.
As we spotted before, there is
a tension in the voice agent
architecture, speed and kind of how
model smart, so depth of reasoning.
If we use the reasoning models
in our real-time loop, it becomes
slow because we have SLAs.
If we're using these fast models, the
whole conversation pretty s-- fast
model is not so good, and in reality,
we cannot just avoid something.
We cannot pick one.
Voice need both actually, speed and depth.
And here is some architectural
decisions actually could be done to
make it actually reasonably good.
This is one of arch-architecture
example that makes this interesting,
LTS voice agent architecture.
It has two tracks, the foreground, the
real-time path that user actually hears.
It's streaming ASR, s- and in
general could be called a speaker.
This is a conversation flow that
never blocks and responsible
for real-time interaction.
And background, it's a reasoning path.
It has several important
kind of components.
First one, it's a semantic trigger.
Idea pretty simple.
We need to consider only reasoning
pa- re-reasonable parts of
the transcription, just not to
trigger thinking for every word.
We need to trigger thinking in
a case when it's depth enough.
And thinker, it's actually powerful model
responsible for reasoning for the current
context and producing a state corrected
text, maybe some next actions based
on the conversation, maybe predicting
some actions or some planned decisions.
And then this state actually injected
into the speaker conversation.
So the speaker actually guided or
supervised with additional important
context that makes conversation smart.
Semantic trigger, as I
mentioned, it's idea of is
there is enough meaning to sync.
It's important just because it's
expensive to sync on every chunk, and
the overall state becomes pretty fast,
freshness of state also important because
conversation goes going forward, and
we need to consider only reasonable
parts of the conversation, not to
re- not to reason for every piece.
Syncer, as I described, it's
a del- delta state updates.
So it doesn't speak.
It maintains a structural state and
kind of correction overwrites of it.
For example, we are talking
about the change of the address
and then change of the time.
And this thing actually produce the
intent and a mission of the conversation.
It's a new address, new time.
So the speaker actually knows what the
mission of this conversation, or at least
what planning actions it's interested in.
This is already good start,
but Here is the example of it.
If we go in and following the timeline,
we will can consider next set of actions.
The user start talking about
some cancellation, yeah.
Trigger actually can catch particular
important information, so it's a
cancellation of the subscription.
Thinker can reason on top of it,
understand the intent, sentiment, and to
have the account information, and then
to make a kind of a plan of actions in
addition to the policies of the company
or whatever exist for current context.
So it could inject additional state
into the conversation with offering a
20% discount just as a kind of trying
to Tra-trying to offer the discount,
but not to cancel the subscription.
This is interesting behavior
and actually pretty good.
In reality, from people who are
talking about this architecture,
sometimes it cover 80%, 80, 90% of
all cases, so it's pretty interesting
one coordinator manages both roles.
It's another idea that
actually could be used here.
When it starts the syncing on semantic
trigger, injects state into the
speaker, and if the user changes
the topic, it cancels the speaker
but preserves the syncer state.
In some way, syncer becomes a supervisor
for conversation, and if the syncer
start talking about something not
relevant to the current state, it
could be canceled or interrupted.
So LTS is not just a streaming,
it's a stateful stream in reality.
Another big problem, it's bargain.
So when to kill the speaker
and when to keep the syncer.
As I described previously, the idea,
it's actually to find the moment
in time where the speaker start
talking about something not relevant.
We need to kill the conversation
and actually add additional kind of
information already relevant to it.
There is a different patterns
how this could be done.
For example when we can start generating
from another speaker just because it's
a pipeline and we have a speech-to-text.
For example, we have different priorities
between different speech-to-text streams,
and some stream becomes more on top of
priority of previous one, and we can juct-
actually interrupt it in s- this way.
But in general, the idea is like this.
The speaker is disposable,
syncer, it's durable.
And in general, it's a pretty hard
problem, and maybe the main kind of,
the main complexity of the really good
voice agents are here actually another
interesting concept that actually
could be, it's just to have not one
thinker but set of kind of sidecars.
Instead of just trying to reason on top
of them, we can have specific roles for
every small, cheap models responsible
just to understand something from
the kind of part of the transcript.
It could be intent, semantic it could
have additional retrieval or notes.
A simple example is just to understand,
are user complaining or not?
Based on this information, there is
a reducer, expensive model that can
reason on top of it, that uses all
this information as additional kind
of metadata about the transcript.
And based on this, it can produces the
output state with a clear intent and
maybe the next action that we should do
as a kind of aim for the conversation.
In this example, it's
next action offer 20% off.
So the voiced agent going into this
direction and offering this off for the
next couple of months, for example, yeah.
So this is the overall architecture
that actually makes sense.
Another interesting part of it
actually, it's freshness of the
state in addition of it, because
background reasoning takes time, and
by the time it sidecars finishes,
the conversation may have moved on.
So guidance that arrives too
late is worse than no guidance in
reality, and maybe harm-harmful.
There is several controls of top of it.
It could be TTL, for example.
It could be turn match.
So we're trying to generate some
specific identifier for every turn,
and this way trying to actually see
what state produces for each turn.
And maybe just, never snapshot
replace the stale one, and that's it.
But overall, the additional complexity
comes from the freshness of the state.
And as I mentioned, if we start
building this conversation stream as
a stateful we need to keep the state.
But the price of it, it's a good
quality of conversation with
different reasoning and routing.
Thank you.
So to close this we started from
the three models in a row speech
to text, LLM, text to speech.
We added transport, turn detection
and we moved to the LTS architecture,
as we described separately, where
we're separating thinking from
speaking and use semantic triggers
and different state manipulations
to actually enrich the conversation.
And then we scaled this from the
thinker to actually the parallel
sidecars with a reducer that merges the
output and predicts the next action.
The reason of it is just to have
a quality of conversation near or
at least as much as possible near
to the real human conversation.
So thank you, and yeah