Hello, my name is Rahul Basu, and today
I'm gonna talk about ai, Hollywood, and
Metaverse, and how we can find synergy in
these two technologies and one location.
as we know, historically in the
entertainment industry, we have
seen, technology be at the forefront
of the advancements, whether it
is CGI or virtual reality or VFX.
So Hollywood has always been at the
forefront of, any cutting edge technology.
the.
The rapid development of AI lately
is now, creating a transformative
force in Hollywood, including,
the immersive metaverse.
We can already see that AI is
revolutionizing multiple aspects of
content creation from script writing,
and digital actors to audience
engagement and film marketing.
Similarly, metaverse is enabling
immersive storytelling, interactive
experiences, and dynamic digital worlds.
So what can AI do for filmmaking?
we see that AI is revolutionizing
filmmaking by enhancing content
creation, performance simulation,
storytelling, and distribution.
It assists in script writing,
pre-visualization, and post-production
tasks like VFX and sound engineering.
we also see that there are AI driven
digital humans, voice synthesis
and casting recommendations.
To improve performance realism?
the other point is about AI generated
NPCs or non-player characters and
metaverse world building tools are
enhancing, the ability to create
interactive storytelling in the metaverse.
Content distribution benefits from
AI based recommendations, real time
dubbing and predictive analytics.
And at the same time, neural networks are
enabling immersive interactions, including
gesture recognition and eye tracking.
AI is also helping enhance music
composition and background scoring,
enriching cinematic experiences with
dynamic and adaptive sound design.
What would probably never be happening
in the future, we would probably
never see a fully autonomous AI
generated movie as AI will probably
only serve as an assistive tool.
For human creators rather than a complete
replacement of creative individuals.
And there are some really big
people, who are known for the movies
they make, the movies they direct.
we do see that neural networks, sorry,
neural interfaces like brain computer.
Interaction.
They, have been a long term inspiration,
but direct brain to AI integration is
probably beyond scope in the tech, in the
current technology, realm of technology.
we'll never see something like a daydream
get converted to a movie or a TV series.
Now, how do we even build something
like this that includes, ai, metaverse,
and yeah, good old filmmaking.
It'll probably have three.
primary layers and the
two software components.
So the three primary layers would be
content creation, production layer, the
first one, which would include AI powered
tools for filmmaking and creative media.
The second one would then be a.
Metaverse experience layer that focuses
on AI driven storytelling, non-player
characters and immersive environments.
And the third one, we would probably have
something like an AI distribution and
personalization layer that would enhance
user engagement with recommendation
engines and adaptive storytelling.
The key software components would
include an AI script writing engine.
Ai, pre-visualization and storyboarding
interactive storytelling engine and
AI generated environments for VFX.
Additional features include
post-production automation, digital
humans, real-time dubbing, personalized
recommendations, and predictive
analytics, ensuring a fully integrated
and dynamic content experience.
A lot of this was already happening today.
this is, a tech stack slide that I tried
to, Accu accumulate through my research.
a lot of these tools are new.
A lot of these products probably would do
something else in the future, than what
they do today, or they would probably
be even better at what they are today.
but if you wanna take a look
at the technologies that, that.
Cater to all of these layers individually.
This would probably be the slide for you.
So I'm gonna leave, just a
couple of seconds in case you
guys wanna have a look at it.
And I'm happy to answer any question
that you might have later on these.
Now, Hollywood is all
about creativity, right?
So how do we streamline this process?
we do see that, AI is transforming
Hollywood by streamlining
filmmaking processes, from script
writing to post-production.
there are tools in the, that have
been built using AI that are analyzing
scripts and identifying audience
preferences based on that analysis,
suggesting dialogue and story arcs and
assisting writers in brainstorming.
These pre-visualization technology,
products help directors and producers
generate scene previews, thereby
reducing costs for complex projects
in the post-production world.
AI automates, tasks like color greeting,
visual effects and sound editing.
Machine learning software can also
help DH actors remove unwanted
objects and enhance audio seamlessly.
All of these currently happen
and the latest movies use
all of these technologies.
that being said.
it's important to remember that AI
will never probably replace creatives.
it'll only serve as a tool
to improve efficiency.
cutting costs and optimizing
the filmmaking workflow.
And I'm a strong believer of this.
So now the important bit,
the casting and performances.
AI is revolutionizing casting and
performance technology by offering new
opportunities for filmmakers and actors.
virtual actors and AI generated
characters are enabling realistic
performances without human presence
even as much as portraying roles
impossible for real actors.
Facial recognition advancements
are allowing studios to create,
to, recreate actors as well, for a
scene in the flashback or new roles.
though there are some
ethical concerns around that.
but overall AI driven costing tools are
helping analyze audience preferences.
Past performances and character
requirements, thereby helping
directors, find the ideal actors.
These innovations enhance storytelling
possibilities, expanding creative
horizons in the film industry.
So the important people, the audience,
the viewer, streaming platforms
are known to use AI to analyze
user behavior, providing personal
recommendations to keep audiences engaged.
We probably already do that really well,
but AI would also enable interactive
storytelling, allowing viewers to
make choices that shape the storyline.
Introducing a gamified and
entertainment experience.
Additionally, there would be tools.
There are already tools that help
generate real time subtitles and
dubbing in multiple languages.
So every movie is good to go in China,
in Japan, in European countries,
even if it's shot in English.
So this helps, improve accessibility
and fostering culture and exchange.
yeah, that's already happening.
So how would now AI impact
film marketing distribution?
We have made the movie, it's beautiful.
How would it impact film
marketing and distribution?
I believe that, AI would, Provide more
than the data driven insights that
are currently done because predictive
analytics would help studios forecast
box office success, identifying
target demographics, and optimize the
marketing strategies based on that.
And this would help reduce
financial risks for studios.
AI can also help you in generating
multiple tailored versions of trailers,
for different audience segments
and maximizing engagement and an AI
power translation and localization,
would appeal to global audience and
expand films marketing potential.
These things would help, in turn,
streamline marketing efforts, improve
resource allocation and enhance
audience connection, making films more
accessible and appealing across diverse
cultural and linguistic barriers.
So thereby making every film a global
success, I believe that should happen.
yeah.
What does the future.
AI hold in Hollywood.
we do know that AI is transforming
Hollywood, by enhancing storytelling,
production, and creativity while
maintaining the human touch.
The industry's challenge is to balance
innovation with artistic integrity.
AI is also playing a pivotal role
in shaping the metaverse, powering
immersive experiences and dynamic
vir vi virtual environments.
It's rapid evolution, which is
driven by deep learning, and
mainly transformers is revolution
revolutionizing multiple fields.
So the early applications such as
voice assistance and autonomous
systems were impressive.
But the next generation, of AI
products including, which are
probably built with the GPD four,
which showcase exponential growth.
I believe that AI's role in
entertainment and technology will
only expand, redefining how stories
are told and experience in the
digital and the physical worlds.
So what would immersive interfaces
add to the movie watching experience?
I believe that it would, help
transform human interactions, and
include them in the virtual world.
So things like gesture recognition,
emotion analysis would enhance
natural communication, making
digital experiences more intuitive.
I. we all know that eye tracking
technology is optimizing VR rendering
by focusing high resolution visuals
where users look improving immersion
while reducing computational demands.
So overall, I would say that, the
metaverse is a transformative shift
in human technology interaction
with AI as its foundation.
AI is definitely powering storytelling
guide to creation infrastructure, and
immersive experiences shaping every
aspect of the metaverse world, right?
But as AI advances its influence,
will expand, merging human creativity
with the machine intelligence to
build unprecedented digital worlds.
The synergy between AI and the
metaverse unlocks in the middlest
possibilities behaving the way for
innovative experiences and opportunities.
This evolution signals the dawn
of a new era where imagination and
technology converge, redefining how
we engage with virtual environments.
The journey into this AI driven
metaverse is probably only beginning.
Thank you so much.