Speaker 26: Welcome, everyone.
Thank you for joining this session.
Today, we are going to go deep into
RAG, which is Retrieval-Augmented
Generation but through a very specific
lens, which is data engineers.
Most RAG talks are aimed at
machine learning engineers or AI
engineers, or even data scientists.
This one is different.
We are going to talk about data
engineering, how data engineering
has a natural advantage of when it
comes to LLMs actually using the
RAG, and why your metadata is the
secret ingredient which can extract
more and more power from the LLMs.
So let's get into it.
Here is the roadmap for next
twenty, twenty-five minutes.
We will start with the fundamentals
of what RAG actually is and
how it works under the hood.
I'll keep this fast because I believe
most of you already know what RAG is,
but I want to make sure we are all
working with the same mental model.
Second point, we'll talk about
why data teams are more uniquely
positioned as compared to maybe
software development or data science
teams to utilize the qualities of RAG
to produce higher quality results.
And then why it matters more
for data engineering teams.
Could be that you are sitting on
exactly the kind of structured data
that you need, but you are not using it.
So we'll explore that in this talk.
Next, we'll talk about four Use
cases in your day-to-day workflow.
These aren't hypothetical ones, but these
are some things that teams actually see
during during their day-to-day work.
And then we'll close the gap I see
most teams are failing to do, and
we-we'll also share some practical
steps that you can take away.
So now we'll talk about the
fundamental problems with LLM.
Let's start with the core tension.
Large language models like GPT-4,
Claude, or any of the other open source
models, they are remarkably capable.
They know SQL syntax, they know Python,
they know every language that is available
there, and they can reason about with
the data structures in the abstract.
But here is one thing where they
are, or there is one thing which
is holding them back from being
utilized completely, and that is
they have never seen your database.
They do not know the context behind your
database or complete data warehouse.
They do not have the idea about what
does this order fact means, how many
dimensions your data warehouse has what
is the definition of the columns that
are being used, or what is the actual
grain on which your business model works.
So they don't know customer
ID, they don't know order ID.
This is the niche knowledge which
is only known to your organization.
They do not know that two columns in two
different tables may have similar name,
but they may be completely different.
And this is exactly where most of
the LLMs fall apart in practice.
The model gives you a beautifully
created query, but only when
you run it, you get to know that
this table doesn't even exist.
And this has happened multiple
times with me in my experience.
RAG, which is Retrieval-Augmented
Generation, is the architectural
pattern that closes this gap.
It lets you inject your specific
proprietary con-context and
right at the inference time.
So you can consider LLM, which is a master
at everything in terms of creating it
through a given language, but it doesn't
know exactly the context of your business.
And when these two things combine, then
you will have a powerful solution which
can produce efficient and quality output.
Now let's talk about how does RAG
works, what happens under the hood.
So the key insight here is that
the model weight never changes.
You are changing what goes into the prompt
dynamically at the query time, and this is
what makes RAG easy to update and operate.
So the main point is that RAG is th-that
tool in the architectural pattern
that closes the gap, and it lets you
inject the proprietary context of your
business Now we go deeper into the
how RAG works with these four steps.
So for in-- so if you see the step one,
the user asks a question, something
like what columns are in orders table,
or if this column exists in particular
table, or what is the reason behind
a revenue pipeline failing last week.
So the question gets embedded, and
then it is converted into a vector.
And then we do a similarity search
against the vector database that
contains embedding from your
documentation schema files Slack incident
threads, whatever you have ingested.
The top key relevant chunks come back.
They get stuffed into the prompt,
and it will actually show you here
is the relevant schema, and this
is the answer to the question.
It'll also give you the reasoning behind
the answer that it is sharing with you.
And then in the last step, the LLM
generates its answer using that context.
Crucially, the model's
weights haven't changed.
We haven't retrained anything.
We just changed where--
what's in the prompt.
So this is the key insight I want everyone
to take home, that RAG is fundamentally
a prompt engineering pattern at scale.
It is cheap to update because
you just re-index your docs.
It is fast to deploy because
there is no fine-tuning.
And the greatest and the most important
thing is that it is auditable.
You can you can see exactly what
it retrieved and why it retrieved.
Now we move on to the next slide, which
explains why data teams are uniquely
positioned here in order to utilize RAG.
So data engineering teams have
four structural advantages that
make RAG better-- w-work better for
them as compared to other teams.
First is y- the schemas for all
your tables are already machine
readable, easily can be extracted
by any LLM that you are using.
You have DDL files, you have column
descriptions available in data
dictionary, and you have a data catalog.
This is the context that LLM needs to
understand your whole business, and it
also understands the access rights, who is
accessing what reports are being generated
by certain tables, and what are your
customers in need of And as we move on to
the second one, it is the lineage graphs.
So you know the dependency structure of
your data, how the data is flowing from
the, maybe the source software development
teams to data engineering team, and then
to data science and the reporting teams.
You have data catalog, and you
have data catalog as well, and it
is incred-incredibly valuable for
questions like, "If I deprecate this
dimension table, what report will
break?" A RAG system can traverse
the graph and answer this question.
And think about doing this without RAG.
You will have to go manually
through maybe hundreds of jobs to
figure out where the failure is.
And in many systems, you have
10 or 20 different data sources
that are coming through, and
one of them is causing an issue.
So doing it manually generally takes
a lot of time from my experience.
But this can be easily converted into a
minutes task with-- when you utilize RAG
with any of your coding or LLM assistants.
Next one is the query history.
Your warehouse logs are a
corpus of real analyst intent.
Every query that was run in is
the evidence of what questions
people care about, what KPIs
your stakeholders care about.
There is a training signal and a
retrieval corpus all available at once.
So now if you look at those three steps
that we have talked about, your And
through RAG you have access to structure,
source, and also the historical trends.
And the final part is the documentation.
I know a lot of people or a lot of
teams in industry do not have great
documentation, but still there are certain
level of documents which are created, or
internal wikis which are created that can
help in incident portmor-mor-postmortem
confluence runbooks model descriptions.
So it's-- The RAG is the one which
will connect all these together and
help you solve so many different
problems which are being done manually
today, or which once tackled through
this mechanism will produce high
quality results in a faster way.
Now let's get into the meat of it.
So there are four places where RAG fits
naturally in data engineering workflow.
First one is that I'm going to walk
you through all these four places
in data engineering workflow.
And these are not speculative, but
these are the steps which are followed
by every single data engineering team,
or they are applicable to every single
data engineering team in the world.
So the use case one is the schema Q&A.
Being able to answer what does this
table contain without having to
hunt through s- a stale catalog.
Consider a new data engineer joins who
does not have any business context.
How much time does it take
for him today to ramp up?
It could take months for him to even
understand maybe two or three entities
or dimensions and related reporting.
But he may not-- he or she may
not be able to understand the
whole data warehouse so easily.
But having this RAG available where
you can do the question and answer,
he can actually get into understanding
any table whenever he has to work or
whenever he or she has to work for it.
Now, second is the SQL agent grounded
in your SQL s- actual schemas.
The difference between a SQ-SQL
agent that hallucinates column names
and one that does not is usually
that did it give you the real DDL?
So that's the second case where
you are able to generate that code
using the RAG with LLM The use case
three is the incident response.
I think this is something which is
already being used in a lot of teams
where old tickets are being used as
a input to existing systems where the
knowledge base that has been accumulated
over past multiple years is being
used for responding to new issues.
When a pipeline breaks at 2:00 a.m.,
the on-call engineer needs to know has
this happened before, and if it has,
then what was the fix that was done?
You no longer need to depend on that one
SME from your team who knows everything,
but he cannot be on call at all the time.
So this solves a lot of problems.
Now you talk about the use case
four, which is tribal knowledge Which
is connecting to my example that
I gave, that every team has senior
engineers who are walking encyclopedias
of why things were built and why
they were and where they are used.
RAG is how you externalize that knowledge.
You reduce that dependency, and
you make the team move much faster
Now we move on to the next slide,
which is where we go deeper
into all these four use cases.
So the first one, schema QA, q- question
and answer without a stale catalog.
So first question again,
schema, it sounds boring.
It seems like it's pretty
straightforward thing, but if you have
worked with data engineering teams,
it is actually one of the highest
leverage things that you can do.
Walk through, Yeah.
So the en- the engineer who finally
answers the on-call questions, or
if you look at the pane today on
the left, every data team I have
worked with had this, these problems
where, what is the grain of a table?
An engineer has to dig through the
Confluence page updated in twenty
twenty-one, asks Slacks, asks in Slack,
waits for multiple hours but now they
are blocked waiting for the response.
And you do not have the answer.
And even if you have the
answer, they-- maybe that's
correct or that's not correct.
The engineer finally is able to answer
that, and it has already taken fifteen,
twenty, thirty minutes of your time.
But with RAG, what happens is on the
right side here, that if you index
your DDL files, your DBT ML DBT YAML
descriptions, your data catalog exports,
you now have a system that can answer
these questions in seconds with the
actual current schema, not stale doc.
The indexing pipeline is not complicated.
Export your DBT manifest JSON, parse
your DDL, chunk by table, embed
it, store it in a vector DB, done.
This is like a two or three-day project
that can give you dividend for years,
and not just for one person or a team,
but helps the team go from issues to
the res- resolution at a faster pace.
Now, the question that you would ask
yourself is, okay, what sources to index?
Which files to export?
Which data c- catalog to look at?
And what tables do you want
to use for the lineage?
So that is the question
which will tie back to your
requirement of the final use case
For this one, we move to the second
second use case, which is SQL agents
grounded in your actual tables.
So this one is close to my heart because
I have seen it fail visibly so many times.
SQL agents are one of the most common
LLM use cases in the data space.
The promise is great.
You ask a question in plain English, you
get a SQL query back, but without schema
grounding they fail consistent constantly.
You have seen they may make up their
own table which does not even exist.
It's-- it happens a lot with system
tables where they get confused on
what system you are working on.
And if it cannot handle the system tables
which are fixed, it is so hard for it
to actually give you the right answer
on the actual business tables that you
have created, which are closed or which
are particularly for your business.
SQL agents the model invents,
table names, and it invents column
names, join keys, and the query
that you get is completely wrong.
But with RAG, with that knowledge
already… And when I say knowledge
it's filtered and regulated
knowledge that is ingested.
It's not some it's not trash
that you are feeding RAG.
You are, you're giving it the
knowledge that is completely checked
and confirmed that this is right.
And once you use RAG through the RAG
information that is injected, the Same
question that you have asked before.
It ran, it runs through a vector
search finds out all the relevant
tables, create the, user's query.
And if you-- even if you look at
it here it gives you the correct
query when the same question is
asked, and it is able to use the
RAG knowledge which is the back end.
Now you look at the example
and the results of both.
In the second part where RAG or
the schema is injected, the table
knows which-- the ra-ra-system knows
which table you are referring to.
It is not asking you, "Hey, is it
dim customers or not?" Or, "Is it
total revenue that you're looking at
or not?" But it knows that it has to
go to dim customers, look at certain
columns, and provide the feedback
or the result-result query to you.
It-it's using the semantic similarity to
find all tables that might be relevant
to the question, even if they don't
literally have customers in their name.
So the pro tip here is that inject
your tests with relevant tables.
Even if-- for example, if you have
defined customer ID in multiple places,
and this is the RAG is able to see that
it is a primary key and non-nullable,
it knows it can use it for join as well.
So it's going beyond a
simple query to a join.
So that-that's something also which
you can achieve through this RAG.
Now we talk about the incident
response with pipeline history.
This is the use case that I think has
the most immediate ROI for most teams.
Like I said, it's already being
implemented in my team, and I think
it's getting better and better
day by day It's too f-- it's late
at night pipeline alert fired.
In the old world, on-call engineer has
to, check the logs, try to understand what
failed, search through the, Confluence,
hopping through maybe 10, 20 documents,
trying to find some relevant details
and going through maybe Slack messages
and piecing together the solution.
But in the new world, the-- they query
the system with the error message and
context, and they query the RAG system,
and within seconds they get back the
pattern of incident from maybe March
and root cause of late arriving data.
And fix was to maybe, wait for 30
minutes and then let the other job catch
up, and you will not have the issue
again, or you will be able to fix that.
So it probably takes maybe
10 minutes rather than going
over and going over documents.
But-- And I don't think so anybody can
actually go over all the issues manually.
So this is where it just
increases your solution timeline.
The key thing here is that
the knowledge existed before.
Someone wrote the postmortem, but it
was buried in Confluence, and nobody
thought that we should search it at,
two AM, three AM when you are fixing it.
RAG actually makes it institutional
memory accessible under pressure
when it matters the most.
Now, you would ask yourself, "Okay
what do I need to index? There
is so much information," right?
So you need to index every
postmortem that you have written.
You need to have runbooks which
are-- which clearly define what
is to be done in which case.
And also give your Slack channels data
to RAG where they understand what was
discussed and maybe there were multiple
solutions tried and the Sl-Slack has
the final one or what was checked.
So you can easily even
give logs to the RAG system
Now moving to the tr-- capturing
the tribal knowledge before
it walks out of the door.
I have been in this situation where
I worked for a healthcare company,
and they had data engineers who
were there for 30 years, and the
information they had, nobody had.
It was not even allowed to touch
some pipelines for, new engineers
who are three, four years into the
company, which was very strange.
Now you have a dependency.
On a weekend, you are on call.
You cannot really fix it without getting
a go-ahead by that particular engineer
who has been there for 20, 30 years.
And how do you solve that problem?
You solve that problem by
this particular RAG system.
And one example that I can give you is
that, which-- what actually happened
is that why does a orders pipeline,
run at six AM and not midnight?
The answer was that it was designed
maybe seven years ago to avoid the
billing win- billing system window.
And everybody knows this conversation,
but n- only one or two people who
designed it know the reason behind it.
The person leaves, and the
answer leaves with them.
This isn't just about reducing the bus
factor, though it is about that too,
but it's about making your organization
accumulated knowledge queryable.
Think about what this
knowledge looks like.
Why does a table have the grain it does?
Why does the pipeline
run at a particular time?
Why was the sort key used?
Why is this table partitioned
by a certain certain column?
These decisions were made and
no-- maybe there is documentation,
but nobody's really going back
to a five-year-old, four-year-old
documentation to check it, right?
So the right sources to index here
are less obvious than schemas.
Architecture decisions recalled are gold
if you-- if y- if your team writes them.
PR descriptions are underrated.
Engineer often explain
their reasoning there.
Design docs, even stale ones
capture intent that is still valid.
And here is a concrete
strategy that I recommend.
Structured Q&A sessions sitting down
with, tenured engineers and asking
them "What are the ten things new
engineer should know if the system goes
wrong?" You have to record it, index
it, feed it to the RAG system so that
it becomes institutional knowledge
and not a single engineer knowledge.
Now, why is the metadata piece missing?
Why is metadata is the missing piece here?
This is the core thesis of this talk, and
I want to make sure it lands perfectly.
If you have been nodding all along to all
these four use cases thinking, "Yeah, but
that sounds like a lot to build or a lot
of work," I want to push back on that.
So do you look at this diagram here
in front of you, schemas and DDL
dbt model YAML, lineage graph, query
history, and runbooks and postmortem.
If your team has been doing data
engineering for more than six
months, you are almost certainly
already have most of this.
It exists.
It is just scattered across your
data catalog, your Git repo,
Confluence, Airflow logs, et cetera.
If your team has been doing-- if
your team has created these, the gap
is not about creating new content.
It's-- The gap is about connecting the
existing content in your LLM layer.
This is fundamentally an
integration problem and not
a content creation problem.
I think we are all are writing documents
every day and solving issues and
creating COEs to share with our team.
The integration is exactly what
data engineers are good at.
When you think about it that way,
building RAG system for your team is
less like building AI project and more
like building a new data pipeline.
Because this is your home turf.
You have knowledge about all these pieces,
and you need to just bring them together
Now, where do you start?
Where do you start this month?
Which can give you maybe a quick result.
So all right let's make this actionable.
If I had to prescribe a month-long
plan, here is what it looks like.
Week one, audit what you really have.
Don't write any code yet, just
list your metadata assets.
How many dbt models do you have?
Do they have descriptions?
Do you have… And I keep talking about
dbt because I have used dbt a bit, so
that's why I'm using it as an example.
Do you have descriptions?
Do you have the data catalog?
Or what were your postmortems?
How many of them you have written
in the last maybe two, three years?
Use them.
And the audit will reveal a lot more than
you would imagine because I think a lot
of documentations just go into abyss after
one or two reviews whence they are used.
Week two is build minimal schema
Q, I want-- minimal schema Q&A.
So you export your metadata files.
Maybe it's like a JSON file that
already exists if you're running a dbt.
You parse it, chunk in the model, embed it
and build a simple query that you can get.
And you store that in a Chroma DB
which is a vector database, and
you can start using it immediately.
Third one is add your
first agent use case.
So you can pick a SQL agent or
incident response based on what
is your highest pain point.
If your analysts are struggling or
incident response for your on-call
burden is high, inject the RAG
context into the agents to make the
case more of an higher investment.
And you can feed this, and then
the agent should be able to
respond with correct answers.
And the week four, which is--
which brings to the end of the
month measure and socialize.
Now you have made three things,
you need to audit them and see how
good or bad they are doing or what
improvements are needed in order to
make them better and share it with, the
whole team or the or the organization.
If you are wired up if you're wired up
incident response, you can compare the
timing taken to fix the issues, and this
number makes case for more investment.
The total engineering time for the first
month is probably 15, 20 engineering days,
but the payback is reduced interruptions,
faster resolution, and reduction of
dependency on, certain engineers.
Now let's talk about the
key takeaways from this talk
Let me-- So I'll try to divide it into
five points that you can walk away with.
RAG is not magic, it's a pattern dynamic
context injection at inference time.
So you're not training a model, you
are just giving it vetted quality data
to answer your engineer's questions.
Second, you are in a better
position than you think.
Data engineering teams are the ones that
understand the data business context.
They know where the data is produced,
who is producing it, and who is using it.
Not everybody has this knowledge,
not even the software development
teams and not the-- They don't
know who is using their data.
And the data science or data reporting
teams, they care about the final results.
They do not know what's
happening in the middle.
So data engineering teams
are best positioned.
The structured machine-readable artifacts
you produce as a data engineer are exactly
what makes RAG work, and most teams build
RAGs are-- most teams building RAGs are
struggling to create the right content.
You are generating it as a byproduct
of your day job Now, there are
four natural points where it
fits like we went deeper into it.
And you should pick one
that addresses your pain.
Incident response, could be
tribal knowledge, could be SQLi
The gap here in the fourth point
is integration, not creation.
You just have to integrate
the knowledge that you have.
It's already created day-to-day.
And the last point would
be start this month.
Path is clear.
I believe we data engineers can have a
great agent which can answer pipeline
failures or even the knowledge about
business through those-- through
that RAG system that I think easily
doubles your output I would love to
hear your comments and maybe questions
for me, Definitely connect with me
on LinkedIn if you have any question.
I'm happy to answer.
Thank you so much.