Speaker 8: Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining this
session at CON forty-two Large
Language Models twenty twenty-six.
My name is Kandaswamy Selvaraj.
I'm a principal architect, a performance
engineering leader, more than nineteen
years of experience building the scalable
and resilient enterprise platform.
Over the last few years, I am focusing
on building and supporting the production
scale LLM and agentic AI system.
Currently, I lead a performance
engineering at ADP, where our systems
support and process extremely high
volume transactional workloads.
Today, I'll be discussing a topic,
the shift left performance engineering
for RAG and LLM platforms with
a CI/CD performance signature.
The framework that you will
see applies across the LLM
inference, agentic AI workflows.
If you are building any one
of this talk is for you.
So let's start with the problem.
If you look at this pipeline, if you
look at this pipeline, every engineering
team already does four of the steps.
They write a prompt, commit
the code, build a pipeline,
and execute the inference.
What most team are missing is the
fifth one, gate, which that-- which
it protects everything before it.
So this is what today we are
going to talk about most.
So without further ado,
let us get started.
Let me go to the next slide
So LLM performance defects.
What is different in
LLM performance defects?
The LLM performance defects do not behave
like a traditional software defects.
They hide and cascade.
And some of the research data from CES
Key twenty twenty-two tells the defects
found in the production cost sixty to
a hundred times more than the defect
found in the development environment.
And also similarly, one of the
research finding from CRM Arena Pro
twenty twenty-five, where multi-step
AI agents fails to complete the
task correctly more than one third
of the time in a complex workflow.
Even the same research confirmed the
failures are not in the LLM itself,
they are in the orchestration, the
tool call sequencing and the trace.
So that's what the framework
is going to focus today.
I wanted to focus on these five
problems for the LLM team today.
The first one is the LLM latency
variability, which makes the
post-deployment debugging nearly
challenging and impossible.
With-- Now with every model update,
it's shifting your baseline, you
cannot tell whether your time to first
token degraded because of your code or
your provider has changed something.
And the second one, the RAG pipeline
failures surface directly in the
production without no warning in
the lower environments because
there is no gate exists between your
commit and your production users.
And the third, the token throughput.
The LLM dimensions are different than the
regular HTTP or your APA level metrics.
For example, in HTT-- in your LLM,
the token throughput, time to first
token in the inference latency.
So all this dimension requires
a different instrumentation than
the traditional APA level metrics.
And this is the most challenging one.
The fourth one, agen-agentic AI is
probabilistic, not deterministic.
Without guardrails, the failures
cascade across agent chains silently.
And the fifth one, the developers
get no continuous feedback loop on,
on your LLM performance as soon as
they make a code commit So going to
the slide three, since we understand
the problem, so how do we fix this?
So in order to fix this, what organization
really need is to incorporate a
continuous performance feedback directly
within the AI-driven SDLC process.
The before column on this slide
describe every LLM team that has
not implemented this framework.
Meaning the LLM performance validated
once during the model selection and
never re-evaluated later in the stage.
And also as the team making multiple
code changes on their prompt and the
rack configuration, so these changes are
being shipped between no gate, between
your lower environment and production
environment, and the most importantly,
your feedback on the inference latency
issues arriving days after your model
change was deployed So the after column
is what this framework exactly delivers.
Meaning your LLM performance validated
at every commit for any of your prompt
changes or any RAG configuration update or
any of your model version changes or even
including any tools changes sequencing.
You have an automated statistical
performance signature on every
dimension of the LLM, including
time to first token, the token
throughput, and the retrieval latency,
and the tools calls response time.
The most importantly with this framework,
your AI learned baselines that evolve
as the model prompt and your data
changes over a period of different
commits over the m-multiple quotas.
And the last but not least, the
actionable feedback of your performance
to your developers within twenty
to twenty minutes they make the
commit to the AI-driven pipeline.
So that's the developer promise So
since now developer understand the last
commit and he gets a feedback within
this shorter period, he knows exactly
what he changed, and now he knows
exactly what to fix since the framework
provided that automated root cause
analysis of where it needs to be fixed
So how to operationalize this?
In order to operationalize
this concept, we implemented a
production-grade six-layer architecture.
The first one is the developer
self-service, meaning your developers
can trigger a parameterized performance
pipeline directly from the Git-based
workflows for any of your prompt
changes or RAG configuration updates
or any of your model version changes.
And the layer two is our CI pipeline
orchestration, meaning your CI/CD
tool manages the distri-- manages
and distribute the text execution,
doing the pipeline coordination and
enabling the automated performance gate.
Think of this as a rule
book your pipeline reads.
Instead of your engineering, engineer
deciding what-- whether the time to
first token metrics is acceptable,
your pipeline reads a rule.
For, in this case, if the time to
first token deviates beyond two
sigma, the pipeline is smart enough
to know it needs to block the build.
And the best part, the pi-pipeline
enforce this on every commit.
And the layer three, LLM load generation.
The synthetic LLM workload generation
using your favorite performance
tool, covering the realistic scenario
of concurrent prompt execution
and RAG retrieval simulation of
different agentic AI workflows.
And the layer four, the most critical
one, the connecting the dots is an
observability engine So think of this way.
Now, every LLM request carries a
footprint of the build that triggered
it, meaning in-injecting the build
context into every LLM request.
So when the LLM performance degrade
or whenever agentic AI performance
degrades, you know exactly what--
which commit, which prompt, and
which model version to blame.
And the layer fi- five
is the data persistence.
The historical performance baselines
are being maintained and continuously
recalibrated and showing the trend.
And the sixth layer is the most
important one, is the AI decision layer.
This is where your pipeline
stops being re-reactive and
becoming an intelligent system.
The AI decision layer replaces the
static threshold with an ML power gate
that evaluates each build performance
signature against a learned baseline.
It issues an autonomous go or no-go
decision with a root cause analysis.
This is what turns the pipeline from
a process into a self-governing system
Moving on to the next slide The biggest
challenge of adding the performance
pipeline within your CI/CD gate is
defining the pass-fail criteria and how to
avoid your false positive and the noise.
In order to resolve this, we have come up
with a concept deviation score, and that
is the intellectual core of the framework.
The deviation score formula shown
here measures how far the current
performance deviates from the
normal historical learned baseline.
The formula is simple
Your observed build performance metric
minus your baseline performance divided
by the baseline standard deviation.
The result tells you whether the number is
normal Look at this first example The 90
percentile increase of fifty milliseconds
response time increase with a twenty
millisecond of standard deviation is being
flagged against the SLO of two sigma.
It is not flagged because fifty
milliseconds is always backed, because
it is two point five standard deviation
outside of what the system normally does.
And then another example, your
time to first token baseline is two
hundred milliseconds, and the standard
deviation is an one fifty milliseconds.
After some model version changes,
your time to first token jumps up to
sixteen fifty milliseconds, and with
your deviation score going above the
SLO of two sigma is being flagged So
the deviation score tells you whether
the number is normal, whereas the
old way of static threshold tells
you whether the number is acceptable.
So the deviation score is going to
tell you whether this number is normal.
And most importantly, your
baseline evolves as the model
prompt and the data changes.
So you are always keeping your
baseline up to date as you are
making these commits on a daily basis
We will move on to the
agentic AI dimension.
So for the production scale, for the
production scale agentic AI and LLM
platform, the one dimension of time to
first token is not enough, where the agent
executes multiple LLM calls, multiple
tool calls, and multiple memory lookups.
So here we will go through the five
different agentic AI dimension.
To get started, the first dimension
is the trace total latency.
The end-to-end agent execution time
across all the LLM calls and tool
invocations, meaning one slow tool or
one slow LLM call then can degrade the
whole trace As a next dimension, moving
on to the tool call response time.
Here, the baseline of 90 percentile is
being tracked per each indi-individual
tool, like a different tools like
a-- in this example, I'm going by
search, some DB work, and some code
executor, and file writing operation.
So here, each tool has
its own learned baseline.
Any performance issue in one tool is
caught before your agent degrades.
And the third one is the
LLM call count per trace.
Any agent looping or failures can cascade,
or context loss show as an extra LLM
calls, and which is directly associated
with your cost as well of our infra.
Because the number of reasoning steps
can change, a agent can take to complete
this one user request So think of this
as your baseline is two LLM call count.
So here LLM call count of three is
being flagged and four is being blocked.
The statistical gate catches the
drift, your absolute ceiling.
For example, in this case,
when it comes to the production
implementation, we implement
along with this absolute ceiling.
So that means anytime it goes
more than two LLM calls to
three, it is being flagged.
Anytime it goes from two LLM calls to
four LLM calls, it is being blocked.
And the fourth dimension is
the token count per trace.
So the token cost in the agentic
AI system does not grow linearly.
One small change that adds two hundred
extra output tokens per LLM call across
the agent that performs three LLM
calls part of the trace with a volume
of sixty thousand requests per hour
can become an additional thirty-six
million extra tokens per hour.
So with this, your gate catches at the
commit time, not after your finance
team ask why your bill cost doubled
And moving on to the fifth dimension,
the tool error and retry rate.
So any failed tool calls, any
agent retries, any context window
breaches can cause your force--
can force your agent to retries.
Example, the tool call fails, your agent
retries, and user eventually gets the
answer what you wanted and no alerts.
But your 90 percentile response
time grew up an extra eight hundred
milliseconds, and your token
cost doubled due to the retries.
So this also should be flagged
as one of the dimension.
So your all five dimension must pass,
and the best part, each dimension
has its own statistical tolerance
Moving on to the next.
So this is what a real agentic AI
performance signatures looks like.
So let's talk about, about a
real agent trace, how it is going
to look like inside the gate.
We received a user request hitting the LLM
API gateway and making a first LLM call
with a time to first token of eight twenty
milliseconds, and which is under the
threshold of two sigma, and it's passed.
And now the agent moves on to the another
tool calls, the search API and DB lookup.
The search API stays under
the two sigma threshold.
It's passed.
Whereas another tool called the DB
lookup goes slightly above the two
sigma, and it is being flagged.
Now, after this, the agent moves on
to the second LLM call, where the
time to first token is nine forty
milliseconds and which is stays under
the two sigma standard deviation.
And but another tool called the
code executor going way above the
threshold and which is being flagged
as four point three sigma outside
of what the system does normal.
So looking at the trace signature.
Looking at the trace signature, now- The
total trace took about 4.2 seconds, which
is three times of standard deviation
above what that system does normal.
That means the full agent
journey took about 4.2 seconds.
Where the LLM count per trace to complete
the task is-- took two, but the baseline
is three, so the agent is not looping.
Clean.
The token count per trace is under the
threshold, so well within the baseline.
The tool call response time is the one
which is being flagged here, so which
goes above the standard deviation of
two sigma since it is being flagged.
And coming to the tool error and
retry rate, there are no failed
calls, so agent does perform all
the steps without any fallback.
So out of this five dimension,
every dimension must pass.
Since these three dimensions
are being flagged and triggered,
now the build is being blocked.
The gate does evaluate each individual
metrics, and also it evaluates
as a complete trace signature.
One slow tool blocks the entire build
Moving on to the next slide.
So this is what our typical
CI/CD pipeline looks like.
LLM coming to a performance verdict
in a fifteen to twenty minutes.
And as you can see, everything
starts with a code commit.
The step one and two are standard, where
the code commit triggers your Git webhook
and CI compiles and build a unit test.
Only this step is successful, and then
it proceed on to the step three, your
thirty-day LLM baseline is being queried.
Now your pipeline understand what your
system looks under a normal scenario.
And the step four, from the pipeline
performance, now simulating the
realistic LLM load execution for the
concurrent prompt and RAG simulation
reflecting the realistic pattern And
meantime, and pro-pro-producing the
load against the system under test.
And the step five and six, where during
the load on the system, the different
metrics are exported through Prometheus
exporters and visualized in Grafana,
including the time to first token,
the overall token count per trace,
the LLM call count per trace, and
overall the total agent trace time.
It is all visualized in Grafana.
Then the final, the step seven.
Now the system aggregates the metrics
from different sources and perform the
statistical analysis across all the
five different dimension, like a time
to first token, the token throughput,
and the overall tool call response time.
Now your gate evaluates and decides
if it's successful, your baseline is
being updated with the latest numbers.
And if it's a fail, it provides
a root cause analysis with
a plain English explanation.
And some of this, in this CI/CD, some
of the steps from step three to eight
can be deployed as an agentic AI chatbot
app, where as the developer making
a code commit, even before he blocks
the CI/CD pipeline, he can evaluate
the, he can evaluate the performance
feedback with the chatbot app.
So your chatbot performs almost
exactly the same step, and now
once he feels confident, then he
can de-- he can evaluate the same
within the CI/CD pipeline as well.
So this one I will plan to demo
also at the end of the session.
So for the framework to work
effectively, the integration
between the systems are critical.
The tools here are shown here on example,
but these patterns can work with any
observability tool that you may have.
The first pattern is an orchestration
pattern, and second pattern is an
observability pattern, and third
pattern is a visibility pattern.
So the orchestration pattern,
your pipeline tool triggers an LLM
workload execution and parsing the
inference results and the different
metrics, and engaging the performance
gate part of the every build.
The observability pattern,
this is the differentiator.
So the performance pipeline tag every
LLM request with a correct build context.
Meaning, now every LLM request is injected
with a build context of what build ID,
what commit ID, what model version changes
are, and what is the prompt hash changes.
Now, any of the APM tools like a Langfuse
or LangSmith RRAs can capture the
LLM trace and correlate a performance
bottleneck against a specific prompt
changes and specific model updates.
The root cause surface automatic.
And the third pattern is an visibility
pattern, where your metrics from
different sources are exported through
Prometheus and visualized in Grafana,
including all the five different agentic
AI dimension that will allow you to
trend the LLM performance over the last
ten to thirty commits or over the last
thirty days, whether your performance is
improving or is, performance is degrading
So this is the most important part.
Tag every LLM request
with a build context.
Now, with this information, your
observability tool can trace the
latency issues back to the exact
prompt change or a model version
And this is for, this is
how we did in eight weeks.
And this was implemented o-on a
production scale LLM and agentic AI
microservices architecture on a cloud
The LLM AI gateway is where it receives
the user request, authenticates, and
routes to the corresponding models and
executes the different tools calls.
Where LangChain sits behind the
gateway, act as an orchestration layer.
So it decides what needs to
happen to answer this request.
Whether making an extra tool call,
retrieving the memory, or making
calls to the vector store And this
entire app is hosted on the Kubernetes
on the cloud with a managed LLM
inference via the Cloud AI Gateway.
Whereas the PostgreSQL act to use--
being used for the database persistence
and Redis for caching for a faster
memory retrieval for the conversations.
On all t- on top of all of that, there
is a multi-agent orchestration where
multiple agents working with each
other, sharing the memory, making the
tool call, handing off tasks with one
with e- each other So this is how--
this is the journey looks like, part
of the eight-week implementation.
So the week one, where we started
with the critical AI workflows,
where this can be considered as a
foundation to set up this framework
the five critical LLM agent workflows.
Whereas the week two and three, where
we took the OpenAI specs, feed that
OpenAI specs to LLM to generate the
synthetic prompt workload, the scenarios,
and the scripts and scenarios, and the
test data, and the conf-configuration.
And the week four to five, the
infrastructure as a code being
provisioned, so they, it helped us to
provision the infrastructure being live
with all the AI-assisted configurations
and template for LLM observability
with the integration of all these tools
and correlate one with each other.
And week six, the performance gate was
harmed, the signature got deployed,
where adaptive baselines are being
established, and now every commit
carries a performance verdict.
And week seven to eight, with the
AI-generated runbook, now it was helping
to onboard the pilot teams to get
familiar implementing this pi-pi-pipeline
performance part of their CI/CD pipeline
And let's measure the outcomes before
and after implementation The result table
tells the before and after implementation.
The results are substantial.
As you can see, the performance issues
happening per month reduced significantly
about thirty to forty percent, and
the defects found in the development
increased by another two hundred percent.
That means most of the issues are
being identified in the development
with this implementation of framework.
And the m-most importantly, the meantime
to detect a performance issues which
used to take more than multiple hours
or almost a day, which has come down to
less than one hour because now with the
performance signature, the observability
stack exactly tells where is the issue.
So this fundament- this fundamentally
changes the operational efficiency.
Now the every developers,
instead of reactive firefighting,
now they proactively resolve
issues before they deploy
Moving on to the next slide.
And one of the most important outcome
was the developer productivity.
It increased confidence to each AI
engineers on their own LLM and AI code
performance, allowing them to do the
faster feature delivery and improving
the overall application performance,
meeting all the SLO and SLO compliance.
Because then now that ninety-one percent
of the failures came up with an automated
root cause analysis, now the system
told where to look and what to fix.
For example, one of the root cause
breakdown, here the thirty-eight
percent slowness due to the database
queries and vector store inefficiencies
some additional duplicate LLM calls.
There are some thread and contention
issues which is causing the
slowness, and there are some fourteen
percent infrastructure constraints.
When they trust the feedback loop,
they stop avoiding performance,
rather they start doing the
performance on every commit
And no framework is perfect, and
some of the lessons that we learned
part of this implementation, so
which we did not account for.
For example LLM non-deterministic was
one of the critical challenge when
compared to the traditional performance,
where identical prompt producing the
different response, the statistical
gauge needs a different additional
sigma band for the LLM metrics than
the another deterministic services.
Plan this for day one.
For example, we did not,
so we spent additional few
weeks to tune this threshold.
And your cold start.
So before we enable the gate, your AI
needs some data, so it can gate reliably.
So we had to come up with a statistic
manual threshold for the first few
sprints, so plan for it and budget for it.
And even though we have the AI-assisted
runbook and template, still, we need
an interactive two to three-hour
session for every team part of the
onboarding process, and make sure
this is key for the framework success
part of their development pipeline.
And some of the proven best practices
is pick the top five critical AI
workflow that would cost the most if
the latency issues are identified and
addressed before it reach the production.
Prove the value there first, then
expand to other AI workflows.
And establish a consistent baseline
with more than ten to twenty
runs before enabling the case.
Otherwise, you will have a lot
of frustration in upcoming weeks
having more false positive.
So here, achieving a consistent
baseline performance is a key to your
success of the framework.
And another thing, these lower
environments, like a dit and fit
environment, are not equally sized
as your performance environment.
They are really small environments.
So understand the environment
and infrastructure constraints.
The goal is here is not
to stress the environment.
The goal here is to achieve the
consistent performance and evaluate
against the performance signature
to avoid the false positive
So the overall summary of outcome.
So the response time improved by more
than 40%, and the defects found in
the development improved by another
200%, and the meantime to detect a
performance issue is reduced by 99%.
And this metrics can
be applied everywhere.
Only the metrics can change,
but the methodology does not.
So coming to the next generation,
how can we improve more?
The AI-enhanced test generation.
The leveraging the LLM to read
your OpenAPIs specs to generate
the realistic load pattern,
data setup, and configurations.
And a predictive analysis
scanning the each PR request even
before it tests the pipeline.
For example, now the issues are
identified after the test runs.
So with this, you can scan every PR
request even before it tests the pipeline
and score against the performance risk.
And replace the proprietary
instrumentation with a kind of
a neutral term tracing like a
LangSpyder, Langfuse or arrays, so
that way it can work with any open
stack And shift right integration.
The shift right is an
extension of shift left.
The shift left pipeline caches
the performance issues before
it reach the production.
Shift right is an approach where we
evaluate the changes in a controlled
manner via synthetic monitors,
trigger an automated rollback
when there is a signature drift.
The same performance signature which
gates your pipeline, now it can
guard your live environment as well
And before I go on to the demo, I
want to be direct about something.
The shift left pipeline testing is
an add-on to full-scale performance.
It is not a replacement.
What we built here, a developer say
faster feedback at commit time, which is
the pipeline performance, which catches
the LLM regression issues at commit time
before they compound, and giving the
feedback to the developer in twen- fifteen
to twenty minutes for every LLM build
suitable for dit and fit environment.
This is like a really
lightweight performance test,
not a full-scale performance.
Giving, increasing the confidence
to AI engineers on their own
application code performance.
Whereas what your performance
engineering team does is
something fundamentally different.
This is where the real time real
platform-wide degradation happens because
this is where the system being stress
tested ten times of more of production
LLM load, which is not possible to
stress in the pipeline environment.
And this is where, like your soak
test fails, the memory leak happens,
and where you expose the-- where
you it can expose the gradual LLM
degradation due to the memory pressure.
Because the same query, when
it executed with the terabytes
of data, your query slows down.
Whereas when this test executed
in the pipeline with a small,
like a fifty or a hundred GB of
data, this is hard to replicate.
So this is still a, this is still
a mandatory process, part of the
deve- development life cycle.
So think of this way.
Your pipeline performance catches the
change, whereas the full-scale performance
engineering validates the whole
system under the real world condition,
replicating the real-time traffic.
All right?
The shift left gives you the speed,
where the pipeline, the full-scale
performance gives you the confidence,
and you need both to ship with integrity.
And I wanted to take a five
minutes to go over the demo.
So without further ado, let
us get started with the demo
So this demo is all about the performance
signature against that LLM application.
And this is the video
recording of this demo.
So what we are going to see
is the framework is in action.
We're going to see two scenarios,
two commits, but different outcome.
The first scenario, all your
metrics meeting against the SLO and
approving the build successfully.
In the second scenario, same pipeline
identifying the token budget breach
and blocking the build with a clear
explanation of the root cause analysis.
And also, as I was mentioning, with a deep
integration with an observability, the
users can navigate to the Langfuse traces
directly from the SLO report as well.
So let's go with the first
scenario, approving the deploy.
Let me play the video recording.
In the first commit, I'm starting
the performance gate by asking,
by, by prompting /perf gate.
It will take the latest commit, and it
will trigger a performance signature,
and it will evaluate the outcome
against all these different SLO report.
So meantime, while it is running, let us
go ahead with a different metrics here.
The first one is the
average response time.
The second one is the slowest ten
percent, and the third one is the re-
number of requests that failed, and the
fourth one is the throughput, and fifth
one is the average tokens per request.
And here from where like people,
the developers can navigate to the
Langfuse traces as well to understand
the prompt information, the input
and output token details as well.
So coming back, it is still running, and
for demo purpose, I set this to a minute.
Let it finish So, okay,
now it is completed.
As you can see now all the file,
five dimension are successful.
So pretty much for this demo purpose, and
it gave a recommendation, it is safe to
deploy this commit ID, all performance
metrics passed, all the response times and
error rate within the acceptable limits.
And for the demo purpose, I'm
going to focus more on the
average tokens per request.
So this is the dimension that I'm going to
consider for both pass and fail scenario.
In this case, our SLO threshold is five
hundred token, and average tokens per
request is two hundred and eighteen.
So hence it is a successful build since
all dimension meets under the SLO.
And from here, the developer can
navigate to the LangSee's trace
and look at all your user queries,
analyze your prompt input and output.
In this case, eighteen input
and two hundred prompt, total of
two hundred and eighteen prompt,
which stays under the threshold of
five hundred tokens per request.
And and this is completely dynamic.
Based on the metrics, it
gives a clear recommendation.
Basically, all these are running
under part of the Trance agents.
And I'm going to trigger
another scenario shortly for a
different commit, performance
gate two for a different commit.
And in this case, let's identify
whether the same pipeline
catches this issue or not.
And this time I'm typing
a different prompt.
Should we promote this build?
Performance perf gate,
should we promote this build?
So it takes the latest commit.
So in this case, the
commit ID was different.
In this case, the commit ID is
different, and it is going to run.
As I was mentioning, since the LL--
for this LLM app, I'm primarily going
with average tokens per request.
And similarly, you can enforce the
number of tool calls, number of LLM
calls per request and like this,
you can add multiple dimensions
similar to this dimensions here.
For demo purpose, since I'm restricting
to average tokens per request.
So since it is running, now you'll
see shortly the pipeline will catch
here will identify the budget token
breach, because now for the demo, I have
reduced the token threshold to hundred.
Since the average tokens per request here,
it is going to take more than two hundred.
And now as you can see, the limit
count is one hundred per request,
but for the-- in this perform build,
the average token per request took
about two hundred and eighteen tokens.
So it is flagged, and it is triggered,
and it is blocking the build.
And it is giving a clear recommendation,
even though the response time is an
error rate within the acceptable, the
excessive token usage is the concern.
It is not safe to deploy the build
So to connect the dots between
the scenario one and this also.
So what are we connecting?
So the scenario one showed what a healthy
commit looks like through this framework,
and scenario two shows you what the
framework identifies this regression
issue before even it reaches the user.
The same pipeline, different
commit, and different outcome.
So that's the end of this demo.
Let me go to the, let
me go to the last slide
Your LLM pipeline has no memory.
We need to fix that this week.
When I say no memory, it's no record of
what a normal performance looks like.
We need to fix it this week.
So starting this week one, pick your
top three critical agentic workflows
where the latency is very sensitive.
So start it there, then expand
others and iterate, add one by one.
And second one, tag every LLM request
with a build ID, commit ID, and your
prompt changes and the model changes.
So any LLM observability tool can read
them and correlate the performance
bottlenecks against commit ID.
And set the gate with one dimension,
iterate, and here, for example, start
with the time to first token, ship
it, iterate, tune it, then add other
dimension one by one in the upcoming
sprint So the AI accelerates the work.
It does not replace the
understanding of our system.
When it comes to the platform
engineering and observability and
reliability, we still need engineers
who think deeply And this is my
LinkedIn, please stay connected.
And all this project I'll
be shortly uploading into
my GitHub repo link as well.
Please take a look and try to
contribute to this project as well.
And thank you for your time and attention.
Hope this session provided you a practical
insights to modernize the performance
engineering and pipeline performance
engineering and performance signature
within your development pipeline.
Again, thank you for
your time and attention.