Speaker 5: Hi, fellow
survivors of the AI age.
My name is Andrii Veremiienko.
I'm an Android developer
currently working at Revolut.
Over the last few months, I've been using
AI in two very different environments,
enterprise Android and my own indie
apps, including Loggia and Paddle Coach.
Though I will mostly show you the
Loggia because I have more insights
from there, more test cases, and
so on, more screenshots even.
This gave me a chance to compare how
AI behaves when you need to move fast,
and how it behaves when you to f- need
to follow strict production standards.
In this talk, I will share what AI
actually changed in my workflow, where
it helped me the most, what problems
it created, and how to use it without
losing ownership of your code base.
The main idea is simple.
AI can help us ship faster, but
production quality still comes
from engineering discipline.
So AI is taking our jobs, or is it?
Every few months we hear the same story.
AI is coming.
AI will write all the code, and
developers will become optional.
And yes, every Android developer has
either already touched AI-assisted
development or will touch it very soon.
The way we write software is changing,
from implementation to testing, to
documentation, to code review and so on.
At first, it looks like our
responsibility should go down.
If the model writes code, maybe we
just approve it and move faster.
But my experience was the opposite.
I started writing and shipping more
code than even before, and it was,
like, pretty hard, to be honest.
It means more code to understand,
more code to review, more product
decisions to validate, and
more architecture to protect.
AI did not make engineering
discipline less important.
It made it more important.
The developer role is shifting from
pure coding to controlling context,
constraints, product quality,
and long-term maintainability.
So be ready, guys.
There will be much more to do Let's
discuss two of our product-- projects.
Over the last months, I've used
AI in two different environments.
On one side, I work on my own
apps, Loggia and Paddle Coach.
You can see the screenshot from
the right, it's Loggia for the One
Piece collectors, arts collectors,
and the other side, it's Revolut.
In my own projects I could move fast,
make architectural decision myself,
accept some temporary technical debt,
and validate ideas directly with users.
It was all in my power.
On the other side, I also used AI
via developing Android features
in a large fintech environment at
Revolut, and it was pretty hard.
I won't share internal details,
features, or implementation specific,
but I can safely talk about the
engineering constraint, large code base,
established architecture, strict review
culture, test design system, ownership
boundaries, and production safety.
Everything you can find in a
big enterprise, it was there.
These two worlds are very different
but the end goal was the same, right?
Deliver useful features faster
without breaking production.
The interesting part is that AI created
different symptoms in each environment
but the root problems were more or less
the same And let's jump to the next one
and let's jump to the actual difference
that AI bring to our developing world.
The first obvious change was the speed.
Pelogia and Paddle Coach, I
would estimate that a traditional
implementation could easily take
around six months for each of them.
With AI assistance, the first production
version was built in roughly two months,
and testing take, took even more than
that, and not even as full working days.
I was just working on my
weekends and after the job.
AI also changed UI development.
Android developers do not
always get to build fancy custom
animation, charts, or mathematical
canvas-based com-based components.
Who work with that, you can
imagine that Android apps are
often not that fancy than iOS one.
Before AI, I could spend days
building a custom animation and
then write an article about it.
With AI, the same type of work
became dramatically easier.
Testing changed as well.
In an India project, I probably would
not have written many tests before
because you just need to ship as fast as
possible and test in production, right?
With AI, the cost of basic tests became
low enough to include them much earlier.
In enterprise work, AI also helped
generate test cases faster, but the
important part is still human judgment.
Are these tests meaningful or just noise?
And finally, AI-assisted review improved
the technical quality of implementation.
I think it's more about the big
projects because in my own project,
I didn't add the agent to review
my PRs again because of the speed.
The bottleneck moved from writer code to
understanding and validation of the code.
Now let's see what mistakes happened to
me in Revolut and in my own projects.
So the first mistake.
My first mistake was giving
the model too much freedom.
In the beginning, my prompt was basically
build a feature, a few screenshots,
a short description, and let's go.
And the feature was built.
That is the very dangerous part.
The output often works.
It compiles, the screen opens,
the heavy pass is fine, and you
feel like magic just happened.
But after a few weeks,
the cost starts to appear.
The model chooses its own abstraction,
creates new managers, introduces
slightly different UI components,
and solves local problems without
understanding the global architecture.
And after that, I started to understand
that I need to change something.
And my workflow evolved step
by step, slowly, but it did.
First, I ask AI to build, then
I ask to build using MVVM,
some architecture patterns.
Then I ask it to reuse
existing components.
Then add architecture rules.
And later, I start asking to
explain decisions before coding.
The more experience I gain, the
less freedom I gave to the model.
That sentence is probably
the main lesson of this talk.
You need to… The less freedom you gave
to the model, the better code would be And
in terms of the enterprise project because
the issues there was a bit different.
In a large enterprise code
base, I cannot be the architect.
The architect is already there.
The problem is not that it
writes obviously bad code.
Often the code makes sense in
isolation, but reduction code that
does not live in that isolation.
There may be several ways to solve
the same problem in a large project.
Some are modern, some are legacy, some
are load only in specific modules, and
some should not be applied anymore.
Finding the right approach is a
developer's responsibility, and
it's super important for you to
know which approaches are existing.
Because without that context, AI may
generate code that looks reasonable but
would not pass a serious code review.
I also saw over-testing.
Unit or UI tests that are technically
valid but too complicated, too
implementation-specific or not
variable enough, and, it's taking
energy to validate them, and it's
taking energy to run them again
and again during compilation time.
So you need to be very careful
with what AI is testing, because
AI to write a lot of code.
Another risk is stress plus AI.
When you are under pressure, it is
tempting to accept code you do not
fully understand because it works and
it looks like perfect implementation.
But there is… can be a lot of issue.
It may call internal libraries correctly
and to reduce your ownership, but at the
end of the day, later, when something
need to be changed or fixed you will
pay the price because debugging will
take a lot of time But enterprise
is not the one that had issues.
Also, we have our indie projects, right?
And indie projects had also the
scope of different specific issues.
The first thing is anarchy.
AI build an anarchy inside my
project, especially at the beginning.
There is no existing architecture
forcing the model to behave.
So you are the architect, and if you
don't have the whole picture AI will
happily invent one for every task.
In my first project, I gave AI
agents a lot of freedom and mostly
validated the product results.
Does the screen work?
Does the flow match the design?
Does the feature behave correctly?
And the product moved fast.
As I said before, it moved super fast.
But the code started collecting duplicates
and strange architectural decisions.
The same type of task could
create its own manager instead
of using a shared solution.
I call this solid suffering because
these single responsibilities was
separated, and there was, like, a
lot of things doing the same issue.
It sounds funny, but it's
really painful to debug later.
Debugging becomes harder, and you do not
know on how it… You do not only need to
fix the product bug, but you also need to
understand and fix the generated structure
around it, and it take it can take one
day just to debug some simple stuff.
So be very careful.
AI can move fast, but without
architecture, it moves in every
direction at once Another thing is UI.
UI should be consistent before
you begin image implementation.
Because one of the most visible problem
is AI-generated, in by AI-generated in
the application is UI inconsistency.
AI is very good at building a screen
from a screenshot or a description, but
if every screen is treated as a separate
task, every screen may get its own
style, and it happened with me a lot.
I had different back buttons, different
navigation animations, different bottom
sheets, and different ways to show errors.
Sometimes it was a toast, sometimes
a snack bar, sometimes a dialogue.
Each decision looked small.
Together, they made the
product feel less coherent.
This is where product vision matters.
You need to know how your app should feel.
Navigation, loading, error
handling, empty state, spacing,
colors, typography, animation.
AI can build UI components, but it
does not automatically understand
the tactile feeling of your product.
If you do not define the style,
the model will define it for you
one screen at a time, and at the
end of the day, it will be a mess.
And again, debugging sessions, finding
each components, it will take ton of
time from you another huge problem,
but it's hidden, especially from the
beginning, it's understanding of the code.
It's the biggest f- problem
I found with the code because
it wasn't the code quality, it
was understanding of this code.
Sometimes the code works.
Tests are green, the AI looks fine, but
you do not fully understand why it works.
In enterprise, this reduces ownership.
In the project, it creates painful
debugging session, and both of those are
huge pain and very important to have.
You may need to read thousand lines
of generated code to understand why
one feature behaves differently on one
screen and different on another one.
As Android developer, I could recover
from this because I know the platform,
architectural patterns, coroutines,
compose, testing, and common failure
modes, because again, years of experience.
But if someone builds an app with
AI without the domain knowledge,
the speed can become a trap.
My rule now is simple, do not
allow code you cannot explain.
If you see an unfamiliar function,
library call, or architectural
decision, stop and understand it.
Ask AI to explain it.
That's pretty easy.
AI know context better than you sometimes.
Take notes.
Add the lessons.
You can add a lessons MD to your project
and mention it there, or add rules,
memories, whatever suits you better.
The extra ten percent of time spent
understanding can save days of debugging
later And that's it with the problems.
So let's jump to the solutions,
because for each problem
we can find the solutions.
And the first one would be build
context before implementation.
So the first solution is in context.
The better examples you give to the
model, the better output you get.
This sounds obvious, right?
But in practice, it changes the
developer workflow, development workflow.
Before implementation, analyze
similar models, if we're
talking about the big projects.
Find how the same problem
was solved before.
Check which tools are used, what
is legacy, what is deprecated, and
where trade-offs are acceptable.
Then save this knowledge in model
memory, project notes, architectural
documents, or your own daily notes.
It feels slow, yes.
You will want to skip it and just
implement the feature, but that extra
hour of understanding project the next,
will save the next ten hours for you.
A good workflow is notes,
understanding, plan, implementation.
Do not ask AI to write code first.
Ask it to understand the
system first, summarize the
patterns, and propose a plan.
Only then let it generate the smallest
reasonable change Solution number two.
Remove AI freedom with rules.
Yeah, freedom is bad in our case.
The second solution will be
removing necessary freedom.
In the project, this is especially
important because there is
no existing code base, so AI
can write whatever it wants.
So you need to constrain the model.
Create rules before the
project becomes big.
And here's like a few practical
ru-rules that you can use.
Choose the architecture, MVVM,
MVI, clean architecture, or
whatever fits your product.
Define package structure like
data, domain, presentation.
Define libraries for core
responsibilities, coroutines,
dependency injection, networking,
persistence, background work.
Define how repositories,
services, handlers, managers,
and so on should be used.
Where are you using them, and
which one should be singleton,
which one is not, and so on.
That's super important.
Define error handling, Toast, Sn
acknowledgementBar, popup, inline,
maybe some wrappers for that, up to you.
Define navigation, bottomSheet,
screens, dialogues.
Again, you are the one who
will need to choose that.
Define offline behavior because
adding offline later will be
close to impossible or just super
painful if you will do it with AI.
Define light and dark theme expectations.
Very often, AI just like missing
this part and not adding any
styles for the second one.
Store these rules in files
like rules MD, architecture.
I said about this before, so choose
the one you like more or just memory.
Cloud codecs, whatever you need.
So yeah, at the end of the
day, freedom sounds creative.
In AI-assisted development,
freedom is expensive.
Good constraints are not bureaucracy,
they are product safety next one.
About the test that I said before,
AI to write a lot of tests.
So AI made the testing much easier,
but easier does not always mean better.
Enterprise of work test
coverage matters because small
changes can impact many users.
I can generate UI tests, unit tests, edge
cases, and regression tests super quickly.
But it can also over-test.
I saw tests that were complicated,
fragile, not very meaningful.
The solution is to give the
model a strict testing prompt.
Explain what a good test
means in your project.
Ask for behavior-focused test,
not implementation-focused test.
Ask it to avoid testing private
details or duplicating production
logic inside assertion.
After a few iterations, turn those
preferences into reusable testing rule
or skill, and basically it will solve
everything for you with just one skill.
But always review the basics.
Does the test name match
what it actually verifies?
Did the test fail to the right reason?
A useful-- useless test generated
quickly is still useless, remove it.
AI reduces the cost of writing tests,
but developers still own test quality.
Another one, super important for
the indie projects, it's build
core UI before the features.
For AI-assisted Android development,
a core UI module is one of the highest
return investments you can make.
Before building dozens of screen,
define colors, typography, radios,
spacing, standard buttons, text
fields, loaders, alerts, bottom sheets,
error pop-ups, back buttons, bills,
drop-downs, and navigation animations.
That's everything that I faced in my app.
So you can add your own,
but that's the base.
This is useful in any app, but with
AI, it becomes even more important.
If the basic decisions are already
made, AI stops inventing them.
It reuses, it follows, it becomes
faster and more consistent.
In Logi, Logia, users love
the UI, and AI made fancy UI
dramatically easier to implement.
But the best results come when the
model has a design system to work with.
Screenshots are still extremely useful,
especially when recreating an iOS-oriented
design in Compose, what was my task.
But screenshots alone are not enough.
Each screenshot will be
interpreted by AI differently.
So a screenshot tells AI what to
build, a design system tells AI how
your product should behave everywhere.
So this is super important to build
a core UI module at the beginning.
And what AI still cannot do for you
because AI is still not super powerful.
AI is a very strong technical tool.
With good prompts, it can implement
tasks at a high level, but it
does not replace product thinking.
That's why I put this guy at the
beginning, AI took our jobs, but in
reality, product thinking is getting
more and more important, and this is
why I think development still will
be on top, at least for a few years.
So with a good prompt, it can implement
a task at a high level, but it
does not replace product thinking.
It does not see the full
product picture the way you do.
It does not understand how users
feel when an animation is slightly
too slow, when a button feels wrong,
or when a feature technically works
but does not solve the real user
problem, and it's up to you to do that.
It doesn't know which legacy system
is still there for a reason, which
trade-off is acceptable, or when you
should push back on a requirement.
I think this is where
development is moving.
We are becoming product developers,
not only coding developers.
Our value is in trade-offs,
alternative pushback, architecture,
technical depth, and connecting
product needs with technical reality.
The more context you have, the better
your cooperation with AI becomes.
AI can write the code, but you still
need to decide what code should exist.
And getting close to
finale, what do we have now?
My role did not become smaller.
It just changed.
Delivery increased, but the need to
have for control increased with it.
You can validate product
ideas faster than before.
You can build UI faster.
You can write tests faster.
You can ship faster.
But you can also lose
ownership super faster.
You can get lost in generated
code that works but does not
belong to your architecture.
You can end up with a product that moves
fast for two months and then become
painful to maintain, and you will need
to just rewrite the whole project.
The main lesson is to teach AI and
learn yourself at the same time.
Do not sacrifice understanding
in the race for delivery.
It's hard, I know.
It's hard to push back,
but it's the price you pay.
You control the process, not the model.
AI is a tool that can move you to
a completely different level of
development, or it can create a
code base you no longer control.
The choice is still yours.
That is also why I would not present AI as
a junior developer that simply needs task.
I see it more as a very
fast production multiplier.
If your process is clear,
it multiplies clarity.
If your architecture is
messy, it multiplies mess.
If your product vision is strong,
it helps you reach it faster.
If your vision is vague, it will generate
a lot of code around the vagueness.
And just to summarize what we
discussed before if I need to do it
in one sentence, it would be this:
The more experience I gain, the
less freedom I gave to the model.
That may sound strange in the current
AI hype cycle, where everyone talks
about giving agents more autonomy.
But in production engineering, autonomy
without cost on context becomes risk.
AI did not make me write less code.
It made me responsible for
more code than ever before.
And that is why understanding ownership,
architecture, and product thinking
matter more than they ever did.
Shipping AI feature that do
not break in production is not
about trusting the model more.
It's about designing the system,
the workflow, and the constraints,
so users do not have to care how
unpredictable the model can be.
This is the mindset I
want to leave with you.
Do not ask how much code
AI can generate for you.
Ask how much reliable, understandable,
maintainable product you can ship
with AI while still keeping ownership.
This is a much harder question
and also a much more useful one.
So yeah, build a good project, improve
your product thinking, improve your
technical skills, and you will still
be on a tap top of development.
Good luck with your journey, and
thank you for your attention.