Speaker 33: Hi, everyone.
My name is Marco Antonio Silva.
I'm part of the GPP team in Microsoft,
so the Global Black Belt team.
I'm a senior engineer and a senior
solution engineer in this team, and
today I have the pleasure of talking
to you about spec-driven modernization.
My team is part of the EMEA
migrate and modernize team.
I'm exactly dedicated to this topic,
and today I want to talk to you about
two approaches for modernization.
How to modernize your repositories
both with Spec2Cloud and with
GitHub Copilot Modernization CLI.
Talking to you a little bit about
what is the problem that we're
facing now, and honestly it's
it's an interesting point here.
There's a huge amount of legacy
code, and I think this is general
knowledge that everybody will
agree upon that that the legacy is
becoming a pro- a hu- a huge problem.
It's not easy to pay this technical
debt that we've been accumulating
through building a lot of new
solutions and adopting new
technologies that then become legacy.
And the biggest problem I think and
that I feel that my customers are
experiencing is we see these legacy
projects as a very long and m- and
expensive project to modernize.
So it will take you probably to pick
up all of those code bases three to
five years to, to modernize all of it.
And normally, that's three to five
years of not producing new features
or producing way less features because
you're dedicating your time to that.
And they… that budget, both in time and
money is a killer and has been a killer
to all of this this modernization effort.
But it's not that w- we are not able to.
It's it's because it's not net
positive in terms of the business case.
And that's why maybe we should be thinking
about using these new AI and these
LLMs to do most of this heavy lifting.
And if this happens then maybe we
have a chance to pay this debt.
And so in, in that sense,
today it's not a vendor demo.
I don't want to come here and say
and talk about technologies, more
about approaches and how to use
this, these approaches, maybe some of
these frameworks to accelerate this.
Because honestly I love to do new stuff,
and I want to continue to do new stuff.
Emerging technologies, always being in the
cutting edge, and I can only do that if
the legacy applications cease to exist or,
and are modernized, 'cause otherwise we're
just accumulating more and more depth to
the point where it will not be possible
anymore to continue to produce new stuff.
I'm here to make sure that we
all enjoy the rest of the years
building these new things.
So let's talk about this concept
I don't know if you all know this
concept about spec-driven development.
So this is basically an idea to where
you use these LLMs in a different way
than maybe if you don't know spec-driven
development, maybe you've been using.
You probably know the term of vibe coding.
So vibe coding is where you
talk with your LLM and you
give him tasks to produce code.
And sometimes, and it's not that great.
Code isn't that great.
Many times it's good, but
also many times it's not.
And maybe you already heard about,
oh you're doing your code with an LLM
and with that LLM it's not that great.
The end product is not that great, so
it's the LLM's to blame or you're to
blame because you're you misused it,
but-- and you didn't do the right prompt.
All of that it's not totally true.
May- maybe it's a matter of approach.
And this is where sh- the shift happens
when you're moving from vibe coding,
where there's a lot of hallucinations,
where you have a lot of more-- a lot more
risk to the code that you're building.
And basically, you're only prompting
your way through the process.
Instead of doing spec-driven,
where Spec is the centerpiece.
So you're building human-readable and
machine-readable LLM-readable documents
that are not the code, but are the list of
features and the acceptance criteria and
all of the specifications like we do as
humans for a team to, to build that code.
And this creates an incremental
approach that is very much grounded
way more than if you're just prompting
your way through, through this code.
And th- this is not new, okay?
Spec-driven development is not new.
We as humans also produce documentations
to-- before we start producing code.
And normally, if this documentation
is good and well-specified, then
we hit the target really easier.
And an incremental approach like we do
with agile development, for instance, is
also very interesting and very powerful.
So this is why we start building these
documents that are both behaviors,
business rules, all of those definitions,
as well as your schemas, APIs,
endpoints, and structures before you
start building the code, as well as
your architecture, your data flows,
your dependencies, your tech stack.
Do all those decisions before
start producing the code.
Build those specs, then with it the
model will be more grounded, will be less
likely to hallucinate and more probable
to achieve the goal that you want with
all the practices and the tech stack and
the decisions that you are thinking of.
And you can iterate with
the… It's not one shot.
You can continuously iterate these
specs to improve your outcome.
So if this is true, then you can
apply this to modernization as well.
So i- instead of going to the code, that
is a lot of code, normally, especially
in legacy applications, and say,
"Modernize me this," and just prompt
your way through the modernization, you
can ask the model to start to build,
analyze, assess, and plan your specs
and your modernization into tasks.
And all of this gets structured for the
LLM agent as grounding to iterate and
and iterate through your tasks, basically
your modernization tasks the things that
you need to do and achieve to get to the
new version of the application completely
modernized, as well as have acceptance
criteria that is clear that he can then
loop through and continue to retry to
achieve the criteria with will improve
a lot of the quality of this output.
So this is a very simple
approach if you think about it.
And if you know a little bit of-- a little
bit deeper how these LLMs work and how
these agents work then this has a very
good basis of truth and very probably
will achieve you a better outcome.
So this is basically the mantra, right?
So specs now become the oracle, become
the main point, the centerpiece,
and not the code and w- way far
away from the prompt itself.
So the prompt becomes less relevant, the
spec becomes more relevant, and the code
now is a byproduct of those specs, and
you can reverse engineer specs from code.
This is really a lot of fun.
And I- I'm gonna talk to you about one
tool, a very deterministic tool called
GitHub Copilot Modernization CLI.
So the GitHub Mo- Copilot Modernization
CLI is a tool that is very much grounded
in some deterministic assessment
tools like AppCat, for instance.
And it will leverage a bunch of
skills that were built as part
of this tool to achieve all of
the steps in the modernization.
These skills, not only… They
are agentic, so they use the LLMs,
but are very grounded in the best
practices and and the knowledge of
these frameworks, both Java and .NET.
So this tool is can be used to modernize
both Java and .NET applications.
And this… Think about this as
a modernization pipeline, very
grounded that that you could use.
The code will be the grounding and
it will basically use those tools
to do assessments and then plan your
modernization into tasks, and then
start transforming all of your code.
And then finally have so- the validation.
So building your code running tests
performing even security assessments
to your code, and then tagging
all of these problems, iterating
until you get a final solution.
So that's… this is basically it.
So I would I would love to show you guys
simple .NET application that I have here.
He-here you have Con- Contoso
University application.
It is old .NET 4.8 application.
You can see it here.
So it's version 4.8 in the CS proj.
And it's a very simple application.
I can run it here to show you
guys how it works, but you can see
that it uses very old libraries.
If you've been developing in .NET for a
while, you probably know some of them.
You also have the Entity Framework,
a very old version in the .NET
framework not the core one.
Or you can use dependency injection in
the old framework, and this was completely
redid- redid when they went to the core.
And you have the typical MVC format
for models and model view controllers.
But I can show you how this works.
Still running on IIS.
I can build it for you.
Here you go.
So there's the old framework,
but I'll just run it for you.
So this is the Contoso
University application.
Okay?
So running on my local host.
Give me one second.
It's it's old and it takes a
little while to, to load up.
But it's, it has a SQL Server as well
a local instance of SQL Server here.
And this is basically your application
reading your data from the SQL Server.
You have a bunch of student data.
You have your courses here as well.
You can even add a course.
Let's just build something
here, like here, an ID.
Doesn't matter.
It's a sample here.
Here we go.
Like math.
Yeah, go.
So done.
And here you go.
Here it is.
It was built into the database.
You got a notification up there as well.
You have more instructors
as well, departments.
There's a lot of tables here.
Simple, very old application.
N-notifications, if you guys remember
this uses Microsoft message queuing.
It's a very old way of applications to
talk to launch notifications locally.
It's a Windows feature that w-was there.
So yeah, basically a lot
of old stuff here running.
So let's start modernizing.
If I want to modernize this
application using the the
modernization CLI y- you just need
to install it, and I can show you.
So y- you have a bunch of commands that
could run headless, so meaning you can do
the phases assess, plan, and everything.
But I can just run the default
command here and just go and open.
And I'm not gonna go headless, so
meaning I will have a user in- a
small user interface in the CLI.
So this way, the first thing that it
will ask me here is to here we go.
So to do the assessment.
So I have my, my Copilot version
here running and my CLI as well.
So I can do, first step is to do an
assessment So the assessment will
be very much deterministic, okay?
I just need to run it
on my current folder.
I could run it on a different time
folder, but I'm already in the correct
folder, and I can run it remotely and
delegate it on an agent or run it locally.
So I'm gonna run locally,
and I want to assess my cloud
readiness of my application.
So I want to make it modern and
containerized and everything.
So here we go.
This is what I want to do.
I… He will output me the assessment to
my .github modernize assessment folder.
I'm good with that.
And here we go.
He will start downloading the
assessment tools, the necessary
assessment tools for this.
These tools are, again, deterministic,
so it's not an LLM looking at code.
It's a bunch of tools that understand
these frameworks and understand the
dependencies and can run the assessment.
That assessment will be the grounding
for the agent then to understand
the task that it needs to do.
So this is ver-very much a simple thing.
If you guys remember doing .NET
modernizations in with the .NET migrations
for the tools for different versions
of it's been very old for, from .NET
framework to core and everything.
We would be launching those migration
tools that was 100% deterministic
but didn't do code refactoring.
And although they were very powerful,
sometimes you would be using
some practices that then needed
human refactoring to to be done.
It's not a problem when the changes
were small, but what I'm, what I want
to do with this very old framework is,
a very old piece of code is move from a
very old framework To a very recent one.
So I'm I'm at .NET 4.8, guys,
so I want to move to the-- to
.NET 10, so that's complex.
So it found me a couple of
mandatory issues here, but
let's look at the assessment.
Just pops up here, and I can look at this.
And as you can see, you-- there's, to be
cloud-ready, there's local file systems
in the the Microsoft Message Queuing
that needs to move to a new Service Bus.
You have Windows AD needs
to move to Microsoft Entra.
There's a bunch of stuff here.
The .NET framework that needs to migrate.
And then it creates a migration plan
and three waves that it wants to do.
Gives me some T-shirt sizes and
importance of each of the components.
And this is the assessment.
This is the first step of my migration.
Now I understand what I need to do
This in itself is already valuable.
So now I know where I
need to put my money in.
So the next step is,
okay, I want to continue.
I want to create a migration plan.
So I want to pick these items
up and start to create a plan.
So again, I need to name my plan, where
is my output for this plan, and and done.
I'll- it will start to use now a skill, an
agentic skill for from my agent to go and
put my modernization plan documents there.
So you have the report of
the assessment that's here.
The report itself is stored in,
in, in the file system, meaning
I can commit this to the repo.
And then there's the folder for the
marga- m- the modernization plan
that you will start to work on.
So this is the, th- this is the cool part.
This is the… where I would
probably spend a lot of time after
the assessment to start and plan
the tasks that need to be executed.
And this way I'm delegating this
into an agent that has a skill,
that understands these frameworks,
understands this o- assessment
output, and start to plan these tasks.
And it it's really powerful
if you think about it.
Because with this, I don't need
to take care of the planning.
I only need to read outputs, give
feedback to the agent, and, a-and
figure out what's the best approach.
Sometimes, and the plan can come
and you have to read the plan.
So you're in the loop.
You're in control of w-what's the
direction that you want to do with
the modernization, because there's
probably practices and frameworks
that you prefer because of This long
change that you're gonna do from a very
legacy system to a very recent one.
But you c- you're in control.
So we will figure out these tasks.
So here we go.
So we figured out the five
main tasks that you want to do.
This has basically the main points, right?
So the MS Microsoft message queuing here
that needs to migrate the authentication,
the SQL Server that also needs to moder-
be modernized, the local file systems to
Azure Storage, and finally the migrate the
connection strings to a secure Azure Key
Vault because I want to be cloud ready.
So all of this is in the plan
MD file that I can go and look.
And when… There's more detail.
So you have here the five tasks,
but there's more detail in the, in,
in the plan MD file than there is
in the in the output of the window.
So you have here all of the…
So part one, task one, details.
Task two, details, success criteria.
You can review this.
You can change it.
You can ask it to change as well.
You can go there and see
the tasks and what each task
states and success criteria is.
And you-- And he will use
this as grounding, and you
can change it if you want to.
So now what I can do is I can execute
this plan let's put this to work.
So I could have changed the plan.
I could have made changes, but
yeah, I'm not gonna do that.
I'm just gonna go and execute this.
And here we go.
I could create a new branch for this
and it would just keep my old code still
in this branch because I'm working on
main or I can just change it on main.
In, in, in this case, because I'm
just doing a demo for you guys
I'm just gonna change it on main.
Okay.
Here we go.
And now we have all the five
tasks are now executing.
Will take a little bit of time,
but he will continuously show you
what he's doing here and evolve
through each of these tasks.
The way that he, he sees this
as well is very interesting.
He would see the most critical ones,
try to figure out the critical path
when he did the planning, and if
there's dependencies between o- one
task and another, he will try to from
the knowledge that he has, he will try
to figure that out and then do first
the critical path and then parallel
the execution of the remaining pieces.
So he will figure out things like
explore the ISP.NET MVC project,
see and search for all the items.
He will also he… for the MS MQ
dependencies for notifications, he
now needs to refractor that as well.
Here we go.
He's, he found some… Here's
the key findings for the
system messaging dependencies.
See he will keep you in the loop, iterates
and continue to improve on on the task.
Always by the end of the task, he
will always try to build your code
and make sure that it still works.
If he finds errors after the change,
he will look at the error output
and, Do the changes, the, all the
necessary changes to, to fix those
issues, then iterate and iterate.
So it's a very grounded loop
on both best practices as
well as validations and tests.
Okay?
So this is oh, build,
build is succe- succeeded.
And now it's remaining is the
bindings redirections, okay?
And some warnings, okay?
So it's gonna continue to
run this, and here we go.
So all of this succeeded.
Cool.
And now I can just go here.
Maybe this is a little bit too small.
Let's, Okay.
So done the- The assessment
is done, the planning is done,
and the execution is done.
So now I can start and think about
running this in, Let's make this
a little bit bigger for you guys.
Here we go.
So now I can… So here is my project.
Project is modernized.
You have the app settings
in JSON and everything.
Here we go.
So I can now use .NET Run
because now I'm in a… It's not
a it's a .NET 10 application.
You can see it here running completely
different in the program.cs.
It's still the same more or less layout.
It had to evolve, but it's still the same.
Continues to work, has a database,
now a modern connection database here.
Running locally still,
but completely modern.
And it's, it simply works.
It's very cool.
Here we go.
So let's say departments as well.
So it's the same code that you
will see before, but now if
I go here to my app settings.
Here we go.
So now we have an app settings,
a modern app settings, and if I
scroll up here we go, .NET 10.
So completely new reference packages.
Everything is new, .NET 10,
and it's completely running.
Simple and cool, right?
So this is this is my
first part of the demo.
And now we have here another
framework that I want to talk
to you guys about is Spec2Cloud.
So Spec2Cloud is where is
a different approach, okay?
We you want to go from a legacy code
That you don't have any documentation.
And maybe it's not a .NET nor a
Java application, therefore you
don't, you can, you can't use the
GitHub Copilot Modernization CLI.
Or it is, but you want
a different approach.
Then maybe you sh- you should think
about picking up that legacy code and
building human-readable, machine-readable,
LLM-readable specifications that will
be the bridge between the code that you
have and the code that you want, okay?
So you want to modernize
application with a different…
w-with a lot of refactoring.
And it's not just modernization,
maybe it's just deep
refactoring that you want to do.
So then it's interest- you can
go and analyze that code, scan it
to build all of these data flows,
business logic, all of these specs,
and generate all of those documents.
And then you as a human can validate
that easier than a very old legacy
code that you don't understand,
because now it's a structured document
that you can understand, and you
understand how the application works.
Maybe, may-maybe you're a user
of that application, but you
don't understand the code.
That's why it's hard.
And there's no documentation, or
there wasn't, and now there is, and
that can be a good starting point.
So let's look at what what the Spec
to, Spec2Cloud can can do for you.
I'm gonna use the same application, okay?
And but this time it's
a new repository here.
So here we go.
This repository is the same.
I'm just gonna go to source.
Here we go.
And there's the Contoso
University that you saw.
Same .NET application.
It's still the old version
in this folder here.
And it's .NET 4.8, the same
one that you saw just now.
What I want to do now is I want
to enable Spectre Cloud here.
NPX this Spectre Cloud.
Yes, I want to proceed with the packages.
And now I need to decide if I want
to go greenfield and start a new
project from scratch or brownfield.
I want brownfield.
So it installed me a bunch of
files and forty-six skills.
So now what I'm gonna use is Copilot.
Okay?
I'm gonna go YOLO because,
yeah you only live once, right?
Let's go full-on YOLO mode.
And now I have all of this loaded.
So I have this set of skills
and files of the framework here.
So if I list all of my skills Here we go.
So here you have bunch of skills here.
Let me see.
Here we go.
So yeah.
So Spec Validator there was PRD
generator from Spec to Cloud.
So you have all of these skills.
And here they are, 48 skills all
loaded into my GitHub Copilot.
So what I can do now is, in the similar
fashion that I did before I can just do…
I can use a skill directly and ask
it to do a modernization assessment.
So what I'm expecting here is for it
to run through this m-modernization
this code and do me a modernization
s-session s- assessment.
And and with it, you will start to
understand what are the main points
that need modernization in my code.
You will start exploring the code for me.
I don't understand the code.
Maybe this is a very legacy application.
You can imagine, right?
So with this y- you get the
same as you did with the CLI the
GitHub Copilot Modernization CLI.
But in this case it's
completely agentic, okay?
So it's not a a tool that is running.
It is grounded on skills,
but non-deterministic.
Very grounded, but non-deterministic.
This is a different approach,
but also very valuable.
Imagine that you don't have… it's a code
base that you don't have tools for, or
frameworks that you don't have tools for.
Then this could be, a v-a very
interesting and a-and strong approach.
So he will start creating
the ADRs for this.
So you already found a
comprehensive view of the code base.
So it's a .NET 4.8 ASP.NET MVC 5
application with Entity Framework Core
3.1 and MSMQ notification systems.
So the main points that you saw in, from
a deterministic approach were possible to
be extracted from a non-deterministic one.
So that's very interesting.
This gives you-- proves, proves here a
point that you can use these documents to
sorry, this approach to extract from the,
ex-extract from the code, the documents
that n-are necessary for the specs and
do a very good modernization approach.
So this is gonna create me the
modernization output assessment and
gonna put me there all of that in, in
an MD file that I can then have a human
read it, myself or someone from…
or s- a senior person from the team
that can run through what was assessed
and possibly even change some things.
Many times he will give you
options to what to do in the in
the different steps and decisions.
So it gonna… the main points here,
see the framework migration, the
replacement of the MSMQ messaging
system, and the authentication
strategy for the application.
So he will then output all of this.
Spec2Cloud also uses a state fi-
a state file and audit log so that
it has all the context stored in
the repository, so you can continue
on a different session if need be.
And here we go.
There's the main highlight points,
critical, high, medium, and low.
And all of this, if I can just go here
and run Visual Studio Code and get it.
Here we go
What?
Where is it?
Here we go.
Oh, maximize.
Yeah.
Okay.
So you have… Oh, wait.
Yeah, I trust this
So you have all the
audit logs and the state.
So where things that he found
in the modernization, so it can
continue the state from where he is.
It's all source control,
and you have the ADRs.
So each of the, these ADRs have
different options pros and cons,
and y- you're asked to do decisions.
He does a recommendation, so there's
a preferred step on all of these.
And and basically, this is, Whoops.
Oof.
Whoops.
And here we, y- you have all of the
the different options approval that
you could do and his own recommendation
of how to achieve this goal.
You have this for the au- the
authentication part as well.
So these are the main points
that he wants you to address.
I, I will not change.
So this would be a part where I could
change, but I won't change the ADRs.
I'm gonna just leave it as it is,
and I'm gonna ask him to build me
all, generate me the specs here.
Yeah.
So- Now, what I want it to do is it
will use the set of skills that it
has to start building me the PRDs
and the FRDs for my, m-m-my project.
So in, in truth, would be reverse
engineering all the user stories
and everything from the code.
This is very strong, and this
is, has a huge value in itself.
Imagine that you don't even
need to modernize a code.
You got some code that i-it is
already modernized, for instance,
but you n- you need to understand it.
And you want to produce new features
or add a new user story, but you
don't have any user stories built.
So if you want to generate the
code, you need the user stories.
Otherwise, if you only have one
user story, you will not be able
to add that user story on itself.
But if you have all the specs, then you
just add a new FRD and you have the new
feature definition there, and you can ask
him to now implement me the new feature
on top of the rest of the features.
And you can rebuild the entire code even
if need be on a different framework.
So it's not a m-modernization,
could be a full-on refactor or
re-architect of your application.
So this in itself, for both legacy
code or non-legacy code, is a
way for you to achieve a greater
knowledge around your application.
And this is amazing.
This for me is really
strong and very cool.
So y-you will start producing me
now the PRDs and FRDs and and with
this, I'll have more knowledge of my
application than I had before because
I couldn't understand the code.
Imagine this in a very…
this is a very simple application.
But imagine that you're running this
on a very complex one, very high-risk
one, or even, or core for your business,
but the people have left, or it was a
partner that built you the application,
and you don't have the documentation,
or there's so many reasons for code
to be lost in translation between the
time where it was built and where you
need it now to have to evolve to either
a new framework or some new features.
And yeah it's a tough position to be.
Oh so here we go.
It's almost there.
So you have-- He's creating all
of the FRDs, if you take a look.
So you understood main features like
student management, course management,
instructor management, department
management, enrollment statistics.
So all of these features, you saw
it when we were navigating through
the old application, and then you,
to be honest, they were still there.
So he created these PRDs
for all of these features.
And and one FRD for each of the features.
So if you go now into my specs, if
you go to features, for instance…
if you go to the FRDs, here we go.
FRDs are here, and you have
the user stories, each of them.
You can go to the other
one, more user stories.
And you have for each acceptance
criteria of this FRD, multiple
acceptance criteria defined and
where the current implementation is.
Okay.
So where these features are implemented.
And you have the PRDs with some
mermaid diagrams of the product
processes, who connects to what, which
features connects to where what's
the workflow, non-functional features
known limitations that he found.
So you have all of this really
well-built and very well-specified,
so it's very simple for you to use.
Another cool thing that I
can now do is do a plan.
So- Now I have a lot of
context, and I decided to go
through with my modernization.
So I'm using the Modernization Planner
skill to build me this roadmap from
the assessment findings and generate me
this plan, the steps that need to go…
it needs to go through to
achieve my my modernization.
So it's similar to what you saw in
the GitHub Copilot CLI but in this
case, the assessment wasn't from
AppCat from a deterministic tool.
It was built by the agent itself.
It has all of those options and
recommendations that I could have
changed or just go with it like I did.
And with this he will be able to now start
and plan tasks that he can then execute
to, to achieve this this modernization.
He will go here, start using the
Modernization Planner tool and
start to build me the, a plan.
So the plan is basically an
MD again, an MD file with all
of the m-modernization tasks.
So here we go.
He estimates effort in
terms of human effort.
It's a very fun thing as well.
So he thinks he's a little human here.
But it, it is good to understand both
complexity and and effort of each of
these tasks that he tries to plan.
He figures out the critical
path which parts he really needs
to do first and rollback plan.
So now I have my incremental plan.
All right, here we go.
And now I have my incremental plan
with all of the different tasks.
It set those criteria for each of the
tasks in a very strong and grounded
des-description of w-what it addresses
and what the scope, where the files that
it needs to change, what, how to test
this and he can now start and use this as
basically its own prompt, for instance,
with this context of what it needs to do.
So now I'm happy with this, so
I'm gonna start the the migration.
So let's implement this to, to the end.
And here we go So, now what I'm expecting
him to do is work in sprints, iterations
to, to close me with the critical path
and then the rest of the iterations.
So you already saw one
modernization going to the end.
I'm not gonna bore you with
a very long modernization.
In this case, I think you f- the… In
this part, if the plan is good, then this
is very similar to what you were seeing
with the GitHub Copilot modernization.
He will start to reflect or to, to
reason using the reasoning models.
Try to reason through the plan and
understand what needs to be done.
And then here we go.
So he's showing me the reasoning here
from all the critical path parts.
Evaluating what the decisions
were, and here we go.
Start to address the modernization plan.
The first increment is
the mod zero zero one two.
And here we go.
So he's adding those tasks to
the… It added seven tasks
for him to do, and here we go.
It starts to implement them.
So now he's gonna go through the
code base based on the tasks and
the scope of each of the tasks, and
start just to iterate until he can
have a good understanding a good
positioning of the task, meaning it…
The acceptance criteria will be
met, and then he can close the
task and move to another one.
So this is how this is basically done.
And here we go.
Launch the migration agent.
The heavy refactoring in all the tasks.
Background tasks are running.
Migration build was
successful, and build success.
Okay.
So nice.
This build succeeded for
the first part and and yeah.
So program running.
So w- he will always see-- he's trying
to do verify .NET build succeeded, so
he will always try to do a .NET build
to make sure that it has no errors.
And if he had found errors, so
it's zero warnings, zero errors.
If he'd found errors, he would look
at the output, look at the errors,
and then use that as the basis to
fix the problems, iterate again
until he can successfully build this.
So he's now confirming if the
legacy files are gone, and the key
controller structure is correct.
So he's looking… it's basically that's
part of the acceptance criteria, so he
has to do this because it's part of the
task itself so that it gets accepted.
This is basically a Ralph approach,
where he he plans it executes and
validates, and then evaluates if the
validation was successful or not, if
all the acceptance criteria are met.
If not, he again now plans for the
next iteration and then continues
to loop until it it is done.
So completed all the four main tasks
of the first iteration, and here we go.
So it's just finalizing the stuff.
So I'm not like I said, I'm
not gonna run this final point.
He will now update the state.
I think you get the picture.
You could just do the other
three iterations, but I
think it's more of the same.
Instead of that, I want to show you
guys exactly what the Spekto Cloud is
because I was telling you about this.
So this is Spekto Cloud.
This is a open source repo.
You have it here in the
EMEA AppGBV team, my team.
I c- we contribute to this project,
but you can just come here and use it.
So you have the three phases that we want
to basically build this framework for.
You have the greenfield approach,
where you're building from scratch.
You start building the specs from
prompts and then build the code.
Or the brownfield, where you have code,
and you want to build the specs, either
to modernize or to build new stuff.
And then you have the delivery pipeline,
where you f-fully deploy the application.
So it really is, as the quick start,
it really is a solid framework for
you to use for a lot of scenarios,
both greenfield and brownfield.
You have the examples.
You have all of this.
You have the catalog of skills if
you want to learn more about it.
And it's completely open source
and runs anywhere try it out.
And for these demos and a lot more
modernization demos that you want, you
may want to use you can go to this this
agentic labs repository that I built
for the team, where we have a bunch of
labs where you can use many frameworks
both Spekto Cloud and as well as GitHub
Copilot CLI, and even SQUAD to build more
deeply your applications check this out.
There's a bunch of labs here
that we've been building.
I think it's… You're gonna have fun
here hopefully and find something that
matches what you need, and hopefully
will help accelerate your your adoption.
So This is mostly what I wanted
to show you guys in terms of demo.
So I th- I hope that you understood
some of these core principles.
We're using the LLM itself to
validate and use deterministic
tools to output some really good
solid grounding for your agents.
So this is asking the LLM itself to
do the validations of the acceptance
criteria and the PRDs and the FRDs and,
or running tests to get outputs, build
call the APIs, and have integration
end-to-end tests, perform regression
tests of the, of your frameworks.
All of these are great practices
that are already built into these
frameworks, but if you're want to use
it from scratch, keep this in mind.
This is this is powerful stuff for
you to have good quality outputs.
Also having multiple layers of
validation is very strong as well.
I'm not saying that everything
needs to be agentic.
There's there's a bunch of
stuff that aren't not agentic.
Building your code, compiling
your code, linting your-- having
linters run in your CI/CD pipeline,
and your in, in your commits.
So all of this if you're already
doing this for your y- human users,
you should continue to do this for
your AI users and your AI agents.
Also all of the validation of the specs
is very human-led and very human-readable.
So it's a very good point
of validation as well.
Then you can put the acceptance criteria
and make the LLM judge itself and have
output and ask for feedback if need be.
And then in the final point you
have your human sign-off on the
PR if need be and all of that.
So this is how you d- you can
get good quality out of this.
And hope, hope that this was
interesting for you guys.
I think Some of the points that these
approaches really shine is when y-you move
away from the vibe coding and into this
spec-driven or deterministic approach.
You have all the grounding in the,
in, in the correct files and build
them from the code, and code becomes
less and less important, and the
specs become more and more important.
And all of this can
solve a lot of the work.
I'm not saying it's gonna
do 100% of your work.
This is not full-on autopilot mode, but
it does a lot of the boring stuff that
I honestly as a developer didn't…
d-don't want to… This is why
the legacy still exists, because
none of us want to do this.
But AI doesn't complain, and we
still have to do some validations.
I know none of us like to read
documentation, but what I showed
you guys is not deep documentation.
It's the minimum for you to understand
the code, and if you understand it then
it can be built to that specification.
If you still continue to use your
deterministic approaches, your CI/CD
pipelines your tooling to ground the agent
then you're in the, you're in the clear.
So hopefully you'll invest in
high-quality specs in-instead of just
vibe coding your way through the thing.
You can have More domain
specific knowledge in the team.
Validate all of those iterations,
your, those FRDs, those user stories.
And start small.
Don't go into the bigger.
If you never did this go small.
Let's start with some samples.
Pick up a smaller applications.
Test this out.
You'll gain experience, and then
you can move incrementally to, to
the, your big parts of your core.
And hopefully you can have
this in in a very good way.
Also track, track, track your progress.
Track your costs, and because
don't lose yourself in doing
iterations and iterations.
Try to ground yourself a little bit.
Also, be mindful of cost.
I think it's important.
And and yeah.
So hopefully you got some, also some
things that you can take home with you.
Both the frameworks, the Spektro Cloud
and the GitHub C- Modernization CLI,
and all of these structure for less,
for more grounded agent development.
And hopefully you can understand that
it's not 100% agentic, but it is way more.
I was gonna say 95%,
but it's just a number.
But it's very large amount can be done
by the agent, and it's the most boring
and most long and complex and heavy
in terms of cost for hours, number of
hours of effort from the migration.
So hopefully you see the value here
of accelerating this modernization,
and we can all start to focus on
new stuff and more cool stuff here.
If you want to learn more check out
the GitHub repositories for the Spectre
Cloud that I showed you and the a- app
modernization labs portal if you want to.
And also all of the labs are open
source and al- also if you want to
check out the modernization CLI you
can go to… It's also in GitHub.
You can go and check this out as well.
So hopefully this was interesting for you.
It was a pleasure to
present to you guys here.
Hopefully we all-- we will all have
a lot more cool stuff to do as soon
as we get rid of all of this legacy.
Feel free to ping me.
You have my GitHub and my
LinkedIn, Marco N. Silva.
It's-- I'm the same handler
basically everywhere.
It was a pleasure and have a great event.
See you guys later.
Cheers.