Hello, my name's Ed Fullman.
Our topic today is harnessing large
language models for customer experience.
We're going to look back at the past
a little bit and then forward into AI
and new technologies and their impact
on customer experience management.
A little bit about me.
I've been working in
technology for over 40 years.
I'm an engineer.
He started as a programmer.
I. Many years ago, my focus now is mainly
on innovation and new product introduction
and specifically product management and
lead leading, global engineering teams.
In the past, I've been more
directly involved with call
centers and CX operations.
the largest was A BPO
that I was a leader of.
For a large telecom, and their broadband
support where there were 4,000 agents
in seven countries from multiple
vendors, that I pulled together and,
That was a experience that obviously
was very informative about some of the
opportunities and some of the challenges
that call centers have to deal with.
But I've also worked on the
technology side of call centers
and, CX in general, multimodal.
a lot of my focus, in the two
thousands and 2010s was about, the
technology to deliver the calls.
voiceover IP and other things like that.
And then in, in more recent years, in
the last 15 or so, machine learning
applied to, targeting for loyalty and
sales and also for trying to personalize
calls and personalized offers.
So a lot of the stuff we're gonna talk
about today, I've done with one technology
or another, or set of technologies.
And I've done it in multiple industries.
Today at Veritas, I'm Chief Product
Officer and our focus is on, cloud Native
Edge and distributed architectures running
various kinds of technologies to deliver
high value automation for customers.
Veritas means truth and automation.
the kind of problems that we're
after have a need to, they range
from solving problems that involve
hardware to fully automated solutions.
what's probably different at some
level with what we do is that, we're
not just building these things.
We're operating also these
kind of platforms and, those
platforms have generated.
Billions of dollars for big brands that
we work with through our, partners.
And, we've generated billions
of transactions each year, that
are processed by our systems.
So there's a lot of, customer
involvement, consumer involvement as well.
And, we're, we have a lot of familiarity
with that and a lot of focus on that.
So some of the technologies and areas
of development that we focus on are,
everything from staff supplementation
and building applications to more
process and project and product
oriented solutions that we deliver.
the, we're involved a lot in
development of AI and analytics.
we specialize in, cloud native
solutions involving Kubernetes.
from the cloud to the edge, we
have expertise in bare metal.
we've had specific expertise using
blockchain and digital chain of custody
applications, not so much, payment or
crypto, but using blockchains to do other,
kinds of supply chain oriented things.
And then.
we've implemented these kinds of
solutions altogether to create product
frameworks that we use with clients.
So this chart gets us to, the blend of
my career and the world at large around,
customer success and, and how you.
Drive different kinds
of customer experiences.
So I started out in live call centers
in the nineties and, specifically for
telecoms focused on sales and service.
in the two thousands I worked on, as I
said before, one of the largest BPOs of.
Of customer experience management.
And this involved, broadband technical
service for, technical support
for, one of the largest telecoms.
And in that environment, we were,
I was working in seven countries.
And we had people also in the US
and we had people, spread out around
the world and we were trying to deal
with, keeping the unit cost down
through, broader scheduling across
multiple vendors in multiple countries.
And, a lot of tactics that, have
been upgraded over the years with
the advent of machine learning and
ai, different kinds of AI solutions.
So the first two, boxes on this chart,
really the focus was on, call routing.
some work on, improving the
personalization of the experience
and routing around that.
a lot about scheduling and training,
because the difference between the
BPOs and the live call centers and the
web self-help was a huge difference.
the work I was doing at the time
was creating time, reducing costs
and creating time for web self-help
to be built and rolled out by,
by teams that I was working with.
web self-help was all about, getting
in the getting calls captured into a
process without a call center where,
the users could find answers to problems
that they, wanted to find and move on,
or use some kind of system that could
actually create some kind of settings
change or something like that would,
Enable the service to work better
for the client in one way or another.
So that kind of avoidance was an
enormous cost, savings for call centers.
It diverted, calls away in a very
large way, and it still does today.
So web self help, which has
become AI enhanced is now.
Essentially eliminating calls and
turning calls into other kinds of things.
And the AI and LLM addition to
that is just really taking it to
another level rather than have it be
structured and following a flow chart.
Now it's, it's derived by a chatbot or
some other kind of technology around,
that ai, which gives us many more points
of data to do things like scheduling
workloads or, understanding sentiment
or, some kind of call avoidance in,
in a multimodal way that, really is
designed to, to get the customer.
To a point where, they're
happy with the experience.
And, and this has been the last 40 years,
the last 30 for sure, is on this chart.
So the strengths and challenges of call
centers are pretty well understood,
but for the broader audience, The value
proposition of a call center is really
the personal touch, real time support
from the perspective of you're actually
talking to somebody who's working with a
system that is going to change something
for you, change settings, make a payment
happen, reverse a payment, whatever.
So the The value is real because
someone's there doing something for you.
that's your sense when you're
talking to someone on the phone.
The challenge is it's a
very high cost solution.
If it's, if your call center is handling
all kinds of calls, including calls that
could be avoided, the attrition is very
high and it's, very hard to deal with.
certain types of call centers
like collection call centers
are extremely high attrition.
and the issue here is that, as a
product manager, it's very hard
to use your call centers or,
it's the only way to deal with.
A customer encountering new features
that have been released into software or
SaaS or some kind of solution like that.
without some way of diverting calls that
relate to customers, especially those
dealing with a new service or a change
in service through a new feature being
released, the cost is extremely high.
The value is not as high
either because you've got.
Low value calls mixed with high
value calls, and that's what actually
causes the attrition in a call center.
Nobody wants to do that work.
The era of AI has different
opportunities and challenges.
AI takes away some of these issues we
just discussed around call centers, mainly
by diverting it away from the call, but.
Also assisting or helping the agent be
better informed, doing the right thing,
and using AI to get that to happen.
So it creates scalability, interactions
become more cost effective.
The flip side is the technology
implementation costs.
the training of models to be
effective and not misleading or
provide misinformation and the
management of trust of that situation.
So, customers are not, I'm sure some
are unaware that they're working
with ai, but customers are not blind
to the what's happening, so they
need to feel like these are the
right answers that they're getting.
the idea that they could be ideas
that adapt based on who the person
is exciting at some level, but it
also means it's not deterministic.
In other words, the answer is
not the same for every customer.
So that leads to trust, issues
that have to be like focused on,
and mainly, what that means is.
In the end, even though the
message might be different, this,
the problem needs to be resolved.
The issue needs to be resolved.
And if it is, then the trust goes up.
So what's the role of AI and the
transformation of CX to be this way?
so here's a few of the things that
we're gonna go through in more detail.
personalized customer
interactions, proactive resolution.
These two are really the, the holy grail.
This is what we're all after, right?
If we can create an interaction that
is specific to the, the consumer's
problem, if we can get in front of it
and use some kind of mode other than
a call center to actually deliver.
an issue resolution or inform
someone of a problem that they
may have and how to resolve it.
These are really, this is
the, all the value we want
from the customer experience.
enhancing self-help.
Is a huge opportunity, and making it
adapted to the customer based on their
skill level with technology and so forth.
These are all things that are
possible, and, being done at some
level by different companies.
efficient resource allocation is an area
as well, and sentiment analysis has been
upgraded through the latest AI technology.
So let's take it apart.
personalized interactions.
mainly what we're talking about here is
chat bots, that people get a response
from based on their question, which
makes it a personalized interaction.
it.
It's able to be used as well by
support, by the actual call center
agents, so it gets to faster
resolution for their clients, right?
If they can see what they've done and.
They understand what they've
been shown and the problem was
figured out properly, then you can
accelerate the whole process here.
so the chat bots, as we discussed
before, they avoid call volume, right?
So there, it's an avoidance
strategy, which is, has been a good
one in general for, many decades.
So the opportunity here is to really.
Supercharge again, the whole experience
around virtual assistants and chat
bots, and it's got a lower cost, and
it delivers a personalized experience.
So all around it's, this is why all
this excitement exists in this area.
From a perspective of proactive issue,
re resolution, what we're talking about
is detecting patterns to prevent customer
complaints, to actually get in the way
of an escalation and stop it before it
starts by being proactive in an outreach.
An outreach that doesn't have to
be a phone call, but it could be.
in the right situation, that
might be the choice, but
generally the, this is multimodal.
So it could be text or some email or
some other method that gets, issue
escalation stop before it starts.
So this is an area of, Prediction, right?
So predict prediction of potential
service failures based on reviews
of calls coming in and, finding like
backtracking to some kind of bug
that's been released or, and in other
cases just avoiding a certain kind of
configuration which causes problems,
competing configurations in software.
So predicting these service failures
based on, customer experience interactions
and what's going on with your software
solution, for example, is a way that,
that this technology is applied here.
alerting businesses, before
customer escalate is a goal here.
and reducing negative experiences.
So the other area here
is, enhanced self-help.
So what we're talking about is going
from, the web health that started to
emerge in the 2010s to where we are today.
And the last, decade or so is the
application of, machine learning
to find patterns and then.
More recently chatbot to create,
dynamic FAQs, dynamic responses to, that
are designed to be aligned with, the
skill level of the, consumer involved,
continuous updates based on other queries
that customers are making, which indicate
some kind of pattern, like an outage or,
Some other kind of problem that's emerged
as part of a new feature or something.
So AI powered Certs is designed
to improve the efficiency.
it's going to look across a larger set of
data points and basically pull together.
based on all of that, including the most
recent information, what's going on, and
try to deliver a more efficient solution.
And it reduces the need for
human agents at some level.
human agents are gonna be informed
by this technology as well.
although this topic isn't specifically
about the agents, and there's another
topic about that, this is how.
They'll become more efficient
if they get on a call.
efficient resource allocation is
something that's enhanced by the,
increased number of data points
that, the latest AI can look at.
There's been a lot of work for
decades on scheduling efficiency
and, that kind of baseline backend
process is pretty stable right now.
What's the input to that
is really what's changing.
chat bots and other kinds of technology
that are more AI and machine learning
oriented are able to figure out new
patterns and lay those on top of
existing ways of, Displaying scheduling
information and figuring out, peak
support times and figuring out routes and
inquiries, and generally leading to better
balance of workload in the call center.
And I think, some of this, again, from
product management's perspective is
including in your data that you're looking
at, New features that have been deployed,
new features that have been pulled back
in a continuous delivery environment
where you can see maybe there was an in,
there were calls coming in on something
and then it was pulled back, right?
Something was like being tested and
some type of AB testing and, maybe
there were a group of failures.
So.
the new AI technologies are
able to consider those and
then, wait, the response.
and from a product management perspective,
you're going to probably want to have,
the customer experience that's handled
by the AI to be influenced by what you're
doing as far as releasing new features.
So workforce optimization, as I had
mentioned before, it's an area that's
received tons of investment and
there are numbers of companies that
are very good at this kind of work.
And now AI is being blended
in at a significant pace.
They're basically see
themselves as AI companies.
Now from an CX perspective, But generally
the goal here is to reduce operational
costs, to flex calls and have workforces
optimized to not only take calls from
customers, but also, in some environments
play a role as, reinforcement learner,
people that are focused on grading
and reinforcing learning from the ai.
these are some of the biggest experts.
That exist in these companies as
far as how things should operate.
So looking at, proposed AI responses and
grading them is, a realistic role for
the call center to play, in my opinion.
And this is the way that you get
them involved in reducing calls that
they don't need to take, where the
answers are somewhat deterministic
and you can get to something that
will solve people's problems.
Sentiment analysis is another area
that's had tons of investment already.
and AI is just a new enhancement as it
gets to a place where, more can be done.
So in the NLP area where you're
actually listening to calls with ai,
which has been going on for some time,
the improvements are substantial.
And the opportunity to figure out tone
and sentiment, not just in calls with
NFP, but also analyzing text, and text
responses and chat bots is something
that is key to avoiding frustration.
here's a couple of case studies.
This one is actually one in which
I worked, that I mentioned before.
And, this is a very large, technical
support, set of call centers and,
actually web self-help and some
chat, that was, deployed to basically
deal with problems with broadband.
what was interesting for me about
this particular experience is when it
started, this was, an engagement I was
involved with for about five, six years.
when it started, the early, we were still
into the early adopters, and those were
mainly technical pe people that understood
the technology at some level, not people
that, were afraid of the technology or.
Didn't even buy it.
Someone else bought it for 'em.
So as time went on though,
that's who we started to serve.
So a, a very common thing that you
see in call centers is that as you
bring up a new service or a new
technology, or as you introduce new
features, you as a product manager,
you end up with situations where call
center satisfaction goes down because.
The problems aren't well understood
that they're gonna have to be solved.
And then there's a little bit of
adjustment that has to happen.
AI dramatically speeds that up enormously.
So the call avoidance is very
high in those spaces, like telecom
because a lot of it's technical.
There's only a few ways to do something,
so it's relatively deterministic.
And the opportunity here is substantial,
as with this particular company.
this is talking really about their
last five years or so, five to 10.
And, they've had major reductions of
basic call volume, really beginning in
the, two thousands and early two 2010s.
And now they're just getting farther and
farther into eliminating call volume.
So where they were thousands of agents
in let's say tier two and tier one.
now that's been reduced substantially.
And my ex, my expectation it would
be that the cost of individual agents
has gone up, but the specialization
that they do and the value that
they create has gone up as well.
And they, they can target very carefully
who needs to talk to an agent and at
the same time have good exit paths
from their, process so that if someone
needs to escalate out 'cause they
don't understand what's going on or.
The chatbot doesn't, has never seen
their problem before 'cause it's new.
those kind of exit paths are easy
to get, put in place and just
generally faster issue resolution.
in, in this environment, in the telecom
environment, especially broadband where
you're talking about configuring a
router to, to some extent, in the past
it was much more detailed than it is now.
getting off the phone.
was very difficult, but there
was just a lot to tie down.
So the opportunities with AI are
really resolved as offline, not
in a call, in an actual call or
something, and drive a big, a faster
resolution, which is what people want.
another that is, I've experienced
more as a consumer than an operator
is, proactive call rebooking.
When a flight gets canceled or it's
late or whatever, this is truly
where everyone wants to get to as
far as the ability to find ways to
avoid a call and resolve a situation.
through technology,
there's nothing better.
This is the kind of the highest value.
So while reducing call
volume is a great thing.
essentially avoiding it through ai.
What would be even better is to resolve
the problem before, the customer has to
deal with it, because that frustration
is gonna be what causes churn.
Or in this case, somebody
choosing one airline or another
in the future, banks have also.
Had a kind of experience that
is similar in some respects to
the previous two, but different.
this first line AI assistant
handled 1 billion plus interactions.
It's extremely unlikely that those 1
billion interactions would've occurred.
Without, online web self-help or
chat bots or something else, right?
No one would.
It's unlikely that people would
check their balances often.
It's unlikely that, people would have
interactions with their individual
transactions as much as they do
now without AI and chat bots.
So this is actually.
An example of increasing, satisfaction of
customers and along with that, increasing
the volume of interactions, but dealing
with them in a low cost multimodal way.
30% call re reduction is on what
they had coming inbound on calls.
So they still get that big
lift that you saw in telecom.
and then they have this additional,
Volume, which is all customer,
success that is focused on how
the people use the service.
So improved high value service
interactions, really the result.
So here are a few of the metrics
that you want to, be tracking.
if you're not measuring it, you're not
gonna be able to do anything about it.
So.
what's new here is really AI deflection
rate, first call resolution and
CSAT have been in place for decades.
agent retention has been also measured o
obviously, for especially, large ca call
center ops or operations with outsourcing.
The cost of retraining and bringing
agents online is super high.
So whether you were a call
center outsourcer, or.
The owner of the call
center, both time, both ways.
This was a big focus.
Satisfaction of agents is also
something to be monitored here, in my
opinion, because I think that you're
gonna end up with learnings from that.
That are gonna show you where
you're, where you need to tighten
up on communication and so forth.
Like what you're communicating,
coming out of, software development,
for example, and into production.
How you're communicating that and what
the training is associated with that.
A lot of that is, is hard to
understand unless you're looking
at satisfaction of agents.
As we look forward to AI being included
into our operations and figuring out ways
to do some of the big value prop, prop,
big value propositions, how we're going
to, proactively get involved in resolving
problems and other things like that.
You wanna start with something small as.
is always advised pretty
much in all technology.
So start with a small project that's gonna
have measurable value so that you can
actually see some kind of improvement.
ensure that you have human escalation
paths well figured out, especially if
you're going to do something that's
got, potentially lots of steps involved.
anything like that ensure that
you've got a way to jump out of the
process, because what you'll be able
to see is where the process is weak,
depending on where people jump out
and, maybe where it has to be enhanced.
So if you provide good escalation paths
out, then you won't have people hang up.
For example, mid.
Mid interaction or kill the text
in the chat bot, what you'll see
is where the problems got too
complicated and the user was not able
to get the answer that they wanted.
So escalation paths out of the
process that you're trying to
implement is pretty important.
And then just focus on feedback, which is
also hard to get, which is why you want
to focus on these human escalation paths.
What comes out of those human
conversations with people about like
why they couldn't get it to work is
gonna be much more easy to pull out
then, even though it's anecdotal,
then real world feedback where
people are doing, survey responses.
So pretty typical red map here.
The focus here is just that this is a
technology deployment and even if you
buy a third party service, you need
to follow, a reasonable path here.
So that you don't create, paths within
your customer experience management that
are half finished and unable to really
deal with the problems that are going on.
So a lot of monitoring of chatbots,
for example, a lot of, reinforcement
learning going on with your agents is only
gonna help move this along because it.
Where AI differs a little bit is that
you are, you're managing the growth
of a model and a knowledge base of
a model and the true ups of a model.
it's a different kind of iterative,
almost research oriented work.
So the more data that they can get during
the early phases, is pretty critical.
And then as it gets into production.
You need to be focused on getting
feedback both from escalations as well
as after action feedback from a survey.
So what's the future of
where all this is going?
AI plus some kind of hybrid
human service where a person
can jump into a call based on.
Priority or, re relative to, product
management that's going on, like
new features getting released,
tying those more tightly together.
That's pretty much the future.
doing things in multiple modes has
been happening for decades as well,
and that's only gonna continue.
And then really the focus, the
opportunity is predictive and
proactive customer support.
So as some takeaways, I would
say generally that AI is not
in a place where it's designed
to replace human interactions.
AI is here to help enhance them.
so you know, where we can replace
human interactions is where we've
been replacing human interactions.
So basic call volume.
questions that have very
deterministic outcomes, right?
So they're always the
same answer every time.
Tho those are gonna be the
places where we're gonna get call
avoidance and they always have been.
So the opportunity here is to really
focus on that with the new technologies.
But it's not gonna eliminate
call centers 100% unless your
business is that deterministic.
Right where there's complexity,
you're gonna need people.
And without those people you risk
losing high value, customer interactions
or even losing the customer.
AI is going to help improve efficiency
and satisfaction to customers.
So that's what you should be
looking for and measuring.
And product managers need to more tightly
integrate what's going on in product
management to this CX environment.
There has to be a very tight integration
so that if people are reporting problems,
that it becomes very clear to the product
managers as quickly as possible what those
issues are that they're encountering.
And almost in real time you
should be looking at it.
so even if your product is, has a high
touch deployment with the clients,
and you get feedback from those kind
of deployments and installations,
at least the early ones, you, as
you get into more of a steady state
and you're changing features out.
Releasing new features, you really
need to be tied together with your CX
and you should expect that you can get
these kind of responses from it, which
are gonna be super valuable for product
management and overall customer success.
thank you very much for the time.
if there's questions, please send 'em our
way and I'll be glad to get back to you.
Thank you again for your attention and
feel free to reach out to us or me.
You can use this QR code to reach.
Thank you.