Speaker 11: Hello and welcome
to my talk, Clean and Controlled
AI with API Management.
I'm Leo Visser.
I'm a consultant at OGD.
Soon we will be the Build Beyond
Technology Group from the Netherlands,
and I'm in AI automation and cloud.
I'm also the product lead for AI
Foundry and other AI products.
I'm also the organizer for the
Dutch PowerShell User Group.
I'm also a PowerShell Azure MVP.
If you like PowerShell, contact me.
If you like anything
else, also contact me.
I like all kinds of technologies
to play with and try things with.
And this brings me straight into the case.
So as a consultant, I work with
many different companies, and
one of the companies I worked
for had a very specific case.
Now, I can't use their-- them
specifically, so I altered the case
just slightly and made it into this
case where let me welcome you to
the Nature Reserve Management Group.
They are a group of people who manage
different nature reserves, and they ask
me, "Hey, we want to use AI. We want
to use an AI chatbot to interact with
employees and with different systems."
And yeah, they just wanted to use AI to
make their life easier, but they don't
want to overuse AI systems, and they
also want to prevent certain topics from
being talked about because not everything
has to be you-- you don't have to use
AI for everything, and certain topics at
the moment are are politically unstable.
Let me put it that way.
So their main question to me was actually
how can we make AI more sustainable?
Because as a nature organization, they
were often also dependent on donations.
They needed the money, but the people who
will support them, if they hear that all
this money just goes to AI, they're like
why do you use AI while it's also so much
emissions, uses so much water," and so on.
So they ask me, "How can we make our
system in a way that we can still use
it because it definitely has its perks."
We can make things faster, we can make
things easier, we can do more with less
people, with less resources, especially
things like this get also budget cuts, so
trying to make sure that they can still
maintain all the different nature reserves
and so on, the same amount of people,
make sure that everything is monitored.
It's hard.
So using AI could make sure
that they keep doing this.
So can't really ask this question, but I
would love to hear in the comments later
online if you ever had this question about
limiting certain AI topics, please let
me know because for me it was the first
time a company asked me about limiting
this and it actually made me think yeah,
I can understand why you would do this.
So if you ever had this
situation, please let me know.
Or if you a company and you would--
or if you work in a company and you
would love that some topics would
have been limited, also let me know.
I would love to hear, to
read your responses later.
And the same if anybody else has ever
had this question about making AI
more sustainable, I would love to hear
your experiences in the chat, in the
comments, or on the Discord later.
Please let me know.
Contact me on LinkedIn, on my socials.
You can find my socials in
the bottom of the slides.
My LinkedIn was on the introduction
slide and will be at the end again also.
I would love to hear your stories
because this is a topic close to my heart
So there's many different
ways of doing this.
I've worked with them on making
policy and so on, but there's
also technical ways of doing this.
And this brought me to API management
and AI endpoints So when we build
our AI apps for whatever, to do video
analysis, to do generative AI with text
or whatever, in most cases, we have
our user talking with our application,
and it interacts with some kind of
model, and there's like a back and
forth between these different systems.
I've used the im- the logo
for Microsoft Foundry here.
I hope it's still the logo.
We've had Microsoft Build very
recently, so I haven't read
the whole book of news yet.
It's quite possible that the logo has
been changed again, as Microsoft tend
to change their logos n- every now and
then But here now you see that an extra
logo has been added in the center, and
this is the logo for API management.
So this back end with AI Foundry, we can
actually make it whatever, especially
if we put API management in between.
API management, it's also
now called the AI gateway.
It's an in-between.
It's where we can manage our different
AI back ends, our different APIs
all together, so our application
can more easily talk with it.
It has a lot of different options
to use, a lot of different features.
We're only gonna look at a couple of
features it has in this talk And the
first feature is actually quite simple.
We're just gonna connect our AI
endpoint to the API management.
So here we are in Azure
And I've got my AI Foundry
I can go to the Foundry
portal, for example
It takes a short moment to load
And when we're in the portal
We can go to build, to deployments,
and here we see different
models which have been deployed.
For example, the GPT 5 mini model
Here I am in my API Management
instance, and I can go to APIs.
And there's actually create an API
specifically for Microsoft Foundry.
There's also the language
model API, the A to A API.
I believe the A to A
is actually quite new.
Once you do this, you can select
your subscription, and you can
select the API management or, sorry,
the Foundry instance you're using.
You can give it a name.
So this is the name which will be used.
A base path, so this is the path
of the API which is being used, and
you can select different API setups.
So depending on which one you pick, your
API actions will be translated into this.
It also shows you some examples
of how it looks, and I can, for
example, select the Azure AI.
We go to review and create.
We could create this.
Now, I've done this already.
So if I go back to the APIs,
here I've got the AI Foundry.
When it's created, you will see
that we have a… for example,
generate an image, get a chat
completion, return an embedding.
Return embedding, one is for images, one
is for text, and there's something else
for some information about the AI model.
What else you have is you've got
the inbound processing, and here
I've select all operations, and
there's set up backend service.
So this will connect it to my
AI Foundry, while on the front
it shows me something else.
And sometimes different operations
can also have their own processing.
We can actually test this.
So we can go for example,
get the chat completion.
Shows you the API version we're
using, and here it shows a body.
Now I was using gpt-5-mini, and
here it shows a small query.
So the system query, "You're a helpful
assistant." And then the user, "How are
you?" Now, because I'm using gpt-5-mini, I
have to remove the max tokens one because
this is not supported in gpt-5-mini
And normally you would also have
a query parameter or a header
for a specific subscription key.
In this setup, I've removed these ones
to make the demos a little bit easier.
And I can trace this one just so I can
show you what will happen afterwards.
We will get a response, which is 200 okay.
This is the response we're getting,
and somewhere in here we've got
the message with the content.
I'm just a virtual assistant, so I don't
have feelings, but I'm ready and working.
How can I help you today?
We can also go to the traces, and there's
no trace at the moment available Now,
I've also created a simple Power App
for the different demos I'm gonna do
And here when I start it, I've
already ran this one just to test
it, but we can change the query.
We can say "What do you know
about Conf42?" for example.
This LLM is not connected to the internet,
so we're just checking its base large
language model so we can see if there's
anything in GPT-5 mini about Conf42
in general And it gives me a response,
not sure which com42 you're meaning.
A conference?
I think at least it's
doing something right
So this is how you can connect to your
large language model And this will bring
us instantly into the rate limiting demo
So when setting up
our Foundry model, there were
multiple options in here.
And for example, I can set up
the managed token consumption.
I can, for example, say that it
has to… that you can only use a
certain amount of tokens per minute.
I can also set a token quota, for example,
two hundred per hour, per day, per
week, per month, per year or whatever.
And I can also limit it by either
subscription or IP address.
Subscription, they're like API keys.
You can generate subscription keys inside
API management, and people can use them.
So for example, if you're making an
app, you could give every different
app a subscription key, so the apps can
only use a certain amount of tokens.
You could have like different processes
in the app, have different subscriptions
keys, or if you have, for example, a
system for many different areas you're
monitoring, every area could get like
a subscription key so you can limit
how many tokens a certain area can use,
so you don't have too much overuse.
You can also say to estimate how many
prom-- how many tokens a prompt will
use and add things to the header If you
do this, it will show up like this one,
where now if we look at all operations,
we have a LLM token limit added as policy.
And these policies,
they're written in XML.
So we've got our backend service,
and here we've got the token policy.
So there's some stuff about the
header names, and I've set it
to 60 tokens per minute And here
there's some more information.
If we go back to our Power
App and we go to the limited
one, I'm gonna run this one.
I'm asking it to explain Azure Cloud
Foundry services in less than 30 words.
And when I start it, it's now gonna
request this one three times in a row
And that it says it consumed 301 … 91
tokens, so zero remaining, and with the
other ones actually a little bit more.
The thing is that this token
limit, it's like every minute, so
it takes a whi- while to kick in.
If we would call it again now,
we would get the reaction that
the token limit has exceeded.
So when we run it again, you
will see that now it shows that
the token limit has exceeded.
This is because the request has been
sent before the response has been
sent, so three requests have been
let through before the responses
were done, so it didn't know exactly
how many tokens were consumed.
Once these were true, it now knows it,
and it gi- lets me know that I have
to try again in a couple of seconds.
So let's continue
The next one is content safety
So with content safety, this is
where we can limit certain topics.
The first one was really
about the use of the AI.
We want to limit how often the AI can
be used, so it's not overused too much.
We can limit the amount of energy
being used for these systems.
If we add the AI again, the next one is
the setup AI content safety, and here you
can select a content safety endpoint, and
you can, for example, say detect and block
prompts containing specific keywords.
You can add a block list like this
We go back here.
This content safety endpoint, this is
a resource you can create in Azure.
And once you created it,
there's not much you can see.
It has some things in there,
but not much to configure.
If you want to configure this further, you
actually have to do this via API calls.
So I've created, for example,
a CSV with a blocklist.
Ignore the second part
of this, the exact match.
This was a different experiment,
but I used the same list.
So for example, I said terms like virtual
machine, App Service, Azure Functions.
I just took some things in Azure.
And what we do is we go to the
cognitive services to our endpoint.
And first of all, we're
gonna create a list.
So we're doing a patch request to
the content safety text blocklist,
and we're gonna create a list.
Then I'm going to loop through
this list of items, and for e-
every item, I'm gonna give it the
description string and the text.
And then I'm gonna go to the blocklist,
the name, add or update blocklist item,
and I'm gonna add this to the blocklist.
You won't see any of this in the
portal, but once you've done it,
you will have this blocklist.
Via the API, you can also
query what's in the blocklist.
If you've done this correctly and you've
set it up like this- You will have an
API like this with a block list, and in
all the operations, you will now have
the LLM content safety policy, where
it has like a connection to the block
list, which is just a certain name.
The shield prompts is false.
You can also add things to
shield your prompt, for example.
And here it says the block list
and the name of the block list.
And the rest is again the same.
So if we now go to our safety one
And here we are asked to explain
what Azure Arc is in 60 words.
We will have the normal query,
and we will have the safe query.
And when we run it, it will first
do the normal one, and it gives me a
nice description, and then the safe
one where it says, "Failed." Now,
the nice thing is that API Management
handles this, so it doesn't even
go to the large language model.
So this is a lot less tokens used.
I can do stuff like this in an agent.
I can do stuff like this in system
prompts and so on, where I will say
what to use, what not to use, but
it will go through the whole LLM.
It will go through the agent or whatever.
It will do reasoning.
It will use a lot of energy.
While in this way, it handles it
in the API Management, and it's
handled a lot more energy efficient.
So I like using this technique
Next up is caching.
Now, caching, you may think, "Why would
I need caching when using something like
AI?" And when I first started looking into
this, I was also like, "Caching for AI?
Why?" But if I'm like a user and I'm
using this application, I will probably
use it for many different things.
But now imagine we have some kind
of AI system to determine or to ask
questions to a archive, where we have a
big archive with all kinds of answers.
Once you've figured out this answer
to the question, you don't really
have to change it that must-- much.
Is if the information is static.
So if we could cache this,
then we don't have to run the
whole LLM again every time.
Now, if the information is
not static, then at one point
we need to update it again.
The same goes for, say,
a financial system.
If you have some kind of AI agent
which has to run like a whole lot of
checks on a financial system, it might
question a-- it w- might ask a certain
question multiple times in a row for
different situations to figure it out.
Even with dynamic data, if the dynamic
data isn't updated like every second
or whatever, with these large queries
and large operations, it's often okay
if it just gets the same answer back.
So in these cases, it's quite nice
to have caching to just make sure
our whole LLM is called less often
if we know the answer already.
So how API management does this is
before it sends your query to the
LLM, it just sends it to a small
model, which is an embedding model,
which factorizes your question.
And then it looks in its cache database
to see if there is an answer which is
close enough to this question already.
So these questions, they are
stored factorized in your database.
And just the same as with a normal vector
search, it will look at these two vectors
and determine if they're close enough
together, and if they are, it will just
give you the answer from the cache instead
of sending it to the completion model.
If it's not in the cache, it will
send it to the chat completion
model and send back the response
and then store it in the cache also.
So let's see how we can configure this
To set this up, we need a Redis cache.
So I've used the Azure managed Redis.
You can create this.
You do need to make sure that when
you're setting this up, and I do
need to check exactly where it is,
That you enable the right thing.
So you do need to have
an enterprise cluster.
And let me just create one for
you because I forgot where we
can find this in the settings.
So if we're gonna make
a Azure managed Redis
We're gonna create one
And you go to the advanced one,
there's like models you modules you
can select, and you need to make sure
that the ready search is also enabled.
And if you enable ready search, then some
options are not available or whatever, so
you need to make sure that you're on the
enterprise because else it's not valid.
So this is why you need to be on the
enterprise version So once you created
this, you can go to your API management
And you can go to the semantic caching You
have to select your OpenAI or your Foundry
instance, and this is for the embeddings.
So you saw that I had a GPT-5 model,
and I've also got the text embeddings
too Ada-002 model deployed Here we have
to select this one, and then we can
give a similarity score, where one is
very strict and zero is not so strict.
So this is how similar do the
answers-- do the questions have to
be for the same answer to be sent.
This is something you to
tweak by trial and error.
And the same as the cache duration.
Do you have static data?
You can have quite a long cache
duration because the data on the
background doesn't change very often.
Do you have dynamic data?
You can-- You have to probably
reduce this cache duration.
If you're only querying an LLM and
there's no rack involved or whatever,
you can probably also go by quite a high
cache duration because the LLM, if it
doesn't go on the internet, if it doesn't
have any skills, MCP servers connected,
it will give the same answer back.
But as the more you connect to
this, the more you connect to
your back end, the lower probably
your cache duration will be.
So once you've set this all
up You will get one like this.
And now we see that we
have the cache lookup here.
I've given it a threshold of 06
N
We've got our backend ID
here, and here we've got the
cache duration of 60 seconds.
So now
So if we're gonna look at how the
cached system works, I'll go to the
cached version in my Power App, and
I'm gonna run this query asking me
the AI system to explain about myself.
And I want to you to take a
look at how the answers appear.
So the non-cached version will go first,
and it will go three times in a row.
So the first time it will give
an answer, and the second time it
will give me probably an answer
which is slightly different.
That it looks quite similar, but if you
look more closely, it's different, and
it takes a while in between the different
answers before they've been generated.
Now we go to the cached
version, and the first answer
will take a while to generate.
And once it done, the other two answers
will almost be there instantly, and
they're exactly the same because
they are from the cache instead of
just being generated by the LLM.
So this cached version doesn't only
give you the same answer back, but it
always also will speed up your system
if you use the, if you use this cache.
Now, there are a couple of things
to keep in mind if you set this up.
If you set this up, your Redis cache
will be connected in the external caches
You have to make sure that you
keep an eye on the instance
location and the used from.
For example, my API management is
hosted in Sweden Central, and the cache
is hosted in West Europe for reasons.
So used from, you can set which
cache is used for which location.
You can actually set up a
cache for different locations.
So if you would set up like a multi
region system, you can have the same
API management for different regions
and say which cache has to be used for
which region you also need to make sure
that the connection string is saved in
a named location In the named values.
And this connection string, it
will also host a port number
to connect to your Redis cache.
Now, there seems to be a bug in Azure
which sometimes pops up and sometimes
it doesn't, where if you connect this
and you go to your connection string,
this port number will just be empty.
You can find this port
number in your configuration.
If you go to your Redis cache, you
can find the endpoint here, and
if you just make sure that this
port number and the endpoint is
correct, it should probably work.
In the authentication part,
you can also find access keys,
which you can use to connect.
At the moment, API Management doesn't
support connecting via a different way
than access keys, so you do need to use
the access keys to set this connection up
Bad money Because money is always a thing.
And to use all these different
options, you actually need to
use the API Management Basic v2.
At the moment, a lot of the options
for the AI gateway are not yet
available in the consumption tier for
API management or in different tiers.
As far as I know, they will be
eventually, but no guarantees here.
And it could be by the time this
talk is out, things have changed
already due to a lot of releases
have been posted at Microsoft Build.
And like I said, I haven't read all of
them yet, and also things keep changing.
So if you're looking at this talk
later, please check because things
are moving fast in this space.
Now, the B- API Management Basic
v2 is about 150 euros per month
If you don't use the basic V2 and you try
to set up some of the AI gateway options,
you will get this error, which is quite
confusing the first time you see it
with the role assignment already exists.
This is due to reasons, so just keep
in mind that this means probably
that you're using the wrong tier.
I've seen it sometimes also give errors
about the tier and it seems to get better
Now, if you would use API management
purely as the AI gateway to do some of
these some of these things like caching
and so on, it might be a bit overkill.
You can also do a lot of this in Azure
Foundry, in some of your models and so on.
But if you also use things like
MCP servers or you want to host
MCP servers, the AI gateway has
options to set up an MCP server.
So if you have some tools, you want
to collect an MCP server, some Logic
Apps you created or some other Azure
functions you created, you can very
easily add them all in an MCP server
and host this via API management.
It also allows you to check
for things like authentication.
You can add a policy to the ch- to
the API management, which checks,
for example, your JWT token, so you
can make sure that only authenticated
users can use this or only users
p- in specific groups or whatever.
And also it can be managed centrally.
So you could set up an API management
centrally, then give different teams
the option to make their own models,
to make their own foundry instances or
whatever they want, and just route it
all through the API management and add
some of your own policies in this API
management, making sure that just some
things are set up like blocked words,
like caching, like token limiting, just
to make sure that you get some control
over your APIs and your AI systems.
Now what's next?
Things I'm working on at the moment is to
see if I can also set up a system where I
use AI search and API management together.
Because more and more fine-tuned
models and smaller models become
more interesting, small language
models, fine-tuned models.
So if what I want to see is if I can
make some kind of a custom model router
with the help of AI search, where in AI
search, which is a vector database, I
store for every model what it is about.
So if a question is asked, it will first
check which model fits best with this
question, and if so, send it specifically
to this model to also reduce the amount
of energy being used as these smaller
fine-tuned models will use less energy
than the big LLM It could also just check
in general what kind of model is best
for the type of question you're asking.
Are you asking a question which
asks for a lot of reasoning?
Maybe then you have to go
to a big reasoning model.
Are you just asking a very
simple what is this question?
You might be able to go to a very simple
model, which might have some skill to go
to the internet to look it up for you.
In in Azure Foundry, there is a model
router available now, which is becoming
better and better, but I'm also looking
into if I can make this even better
myself or add some extra options to it.
This is how it would look where the
user interacts with their app, goes
to AI API Management goes to the
AI search, searches their index,
goes back and sends it to Foundry.
So these are some future
things I'm thinking about.
I hope this talks inspires you, makes
you think a little bit more about how
you can make your AI more clean and more
controlled so by using API Management
and other tools I was Leo Visser.
I hope you enjoyed this talk.
I hope you will let me know in the
comments and in the chat or in the Discord
your answers to the questions I asked you.
And if you have any questions, you
can ask them in the comments too.
You can connect with me on LinkedIn,
and thank you very much for listening