Speaker: Hello and welcome.
I'm Abdul Basit Iqbal, a senior
software developer engineer at Amazon,
where I currently serve as a lead
architect of the company's global tax
engine, the system that determines how
taxes are calculated for hundreds of
millions of transactions worldwide.
Today, I want you to take you on a
journey into a problem that doesn't
get nearly enough attention in the AI
community, enterprise tax compliance,
and show you why is it in fact one
of the most compelling frontiers for
agentic large language model systems.
The title of my talk is Agentic AI for
Autonomous Compliance in Enterprise
Tax System using LLM-driven Tax to Code
Pipelines to Transform How Enterprise
Responds to Regulatory Change.
By the end of the session, I want you to
walk away with a concrete mental model for
how a multi-agent AI system can collapse
a six-month compliance cycle down to
hours when wide the government governance
architecture around that system matter
just as much as the model themselves.
So this is the-- let's talk
about the scale of the problem.
Let me start by grounding
us in the problem.
If you are in a multinational enterprise
or build software that serves one,
you are operating across dozen of tax
jurisdictions simultaneously, and the rule
in those jurisdiction don't stand still.
VAT threshold changes, transfer pricing
rules shift, new digital service tax
emerge, and each time a jurisdiction
updates its law, your compliance system
or your team has to interpret that change,
translate into your policy rules, hand it
to developers to implement, validate it
through QA, and deploy it to production.
That cycle from legal change
to system implementation takes
an average three to six months.
Trust me.
While that process is
underway, you are exposed.
You are either over-collecting
tax, under-collecting tax, or
applying the wrong rule entirely.
The exposure shows up as
a regulatory penalties.
It shows up as audit risk.
It shows up as margin erosion
from ma-manual overhead, and it
shows up as reporting gaps when
subsidiary systems are out of sync.
This is what I call compliance drift,
the silent risk multiplying across every
jurisdiction your enterprise touches, and
it's structure problem that traditional
engineering cannot solve at speed.
The hidden operational gap.
The slide on screen is to illustrate
what I call the hidden operational gap.
There are four handoffs in the
compliance pathway: legal interpretation,
compliance translation, developer
implementation, and QA testing.
Every one of those handoffs introduce
latency, and each handoff is a
human-to-human transfer, meaning
it's slow, lossy, and inconsistent.
The core tension is this regulatory
chain moves at the speed of government,
but enterprise systems move at
the speed of engineering sprints.
That mismatch is the gap, and as the
enterprise scale across more jurisdiction,
the gi-- the gap widen exponentially.
At Amazon, I live this reality directly.
Our global tax engine serves customer
in every mar-- major market on Earth.
When a jurisdiction updates its
rule, say, a new First Nation tax
on em-exemptions in Canada or a ZIP
code boundary shift in Tennessee,
we cannot afford months of latency.
We need hours
So why can't we just automate this
with traditional rule engines?
We have rule engines for decades.
Why isn't-- why hasn't this been solved?
The answer is that tax law was
never written to be structured.
Ambiguity is inherent, not incidental.
Consider three structural changes.
First, ambiguous language.
Sorry.
Consider three structural challenges.
First, ambiguous language.
The tax statuses uses phrases like
reasonable commercial term, substance
over form, the language that court have
debated for decades without resolution.
A traditional rule engine
cannot handle that.
It need deterministic inputs.
Second, cross-reference rule.
A single regulation might reference
five treaties, two prior rulings, and
a jurisdiction-specific exemptions
buried in an administrative guidance
document from nineteen ninety-eight.
Tracing those dependencies manually is
a research project, not a coding task.
Third, context-dependent logic.
The same transaction, the same
dollar amount, the same product
carry cannot be taxed at a completely
different rates depending on the legal
structure of the entities involved
or where the buyer's billing address
falls within a ten-meter boundary.
Traditional rule engines require
someone to pre-enumerate every case.
That's not scalable, and that's exactly
why this problem was waiting for LLMs.
Large language models are the
first technology capable of reading
unstructured legal text and producing
structured executable outputs.
Let me be pri-- Let me be precise about
what that means in practice, because
LLMs can read text is an understatement.
An LLM can ingest a statutory
amendment written in legal prose
and identify which prior rules it
modifies, which exemption it introduce,
what effective date it carries, and
what jurisdiction it applies to.
It can resolve cross-references by
retrieving and reasoning across multiple
source documentation simultaneously.
It can generate a structured
machine-readable outputs, policy objects,
decision trees, code stubs directly
from that legal text, and it can do
all of this in minutes, not months.
The result is a compression of the
compliance timeline from months to
hours, not by removing human judgment,
we'll come back to that, but by
eliminating the slow manual hand jobs
that dominate the current process.
This is a founda-- This is
a foundational insight to
everything I will show you next.
LLMs don't just accelerate compliance,
they change its architecture entirely
Now let's get into the architecture.
What I'm presenting here
is what I call autonomous
compliance infrastructure or ACI.
The critical design principle is
the ACI is not a single AI model.
It is a coordinated multi-agent ecosystem
where each layer handles a distinct
function in the compliance pipeline.
The pipelines flows in four stages.
First, the system continuously ingests
the legal text and regulatory updates.
Second, a s-- a legal NLP layer
extracts semantics from that text.
Third, those rules are encoded into
domain-specific language, a DSL, that
capture the logic of the regulation in a
structured technology-independent form.
Fourth, a text code engine
converts those DSL rules into a
production-ready implementation code.
Each agent in the system is
purpose-built for its function.
Each is independently auditable,
and each has defined boundaries for
when it escalates to human review.
The reason this multi-agent
design matters is isolation.
If the NLP layer makes a low
confidence interpretation, it escalate.
It doesn't pass a bad rule downstream.
If the code generation layer
produce output that fails
validation, the pipeline stops.
Failures are contained, not cascaded.
This is architect-- this is
architecture pattern I would
encourage everyone building
enterprise AI system to internalize.
Purpose-built agents with
isolated failure models and human
escalation at every decision point
First agent in the pipeline is responsible
for continuous regulatory monitoring.
The layer, this layer watches government
gazettes, official registers, tax
authority website, treaty databases, and
regulatory guidance document across every
jurisdiction the enterprise operates in.
It does this continuously, not
on a scheduled batch cycle.
When it detects a change, an amendment,
a repeal, a new enactment, it classifies
the change done by-- change by tax type,
by jurisdiction, and by effective date.
And when it does something traditional
monitoring system cannot, it scores the
confidence of its own interpretation.
Confidence scoring is the
mechanism that keeps human in
the loop for the hard cases.
If the NLP layer reads stature--
statute and produce a high confident
interpretation, say a clear rate change
from eight percent to ten percent with
a specific effective date, it pro-it
proceeds to an extraction automatically.
It's nominal.
But if the status statute uses ambiguous
language, if it reference a contested
prior ruling, or if the change applies to
a jurisdiction with complex carve-outs,
the system flagged is for human
review before any rule is extracted.
The ambiguity is surfaced, not suppressed.
Once a regulatory change has been ingested
and classified, the next agent encodes
it into what we call domain specific
language The DSL is the strategic
center of the enterprise architecture.
Let me explain why.
Natural language is ambiguous.
Code is implementation-specific.
It is written in Java or Python or
TypeScript, and it is coupled to
a particular system architecture.
The DSL sits between these two worlds.
It captures the full logical structure
to a tax rule, the condition, the
thresholds, the applicable rates, the
exemption, the conflict resolution
logic in a format that, that is
human-readable and technology-independent.
Think of it as a single source
of truth for what rule means,
decoupled from how that rule will be
implemented in any particular system.
The strategic advantage
of this is enormous.
A single DSL model can generate
compliant code for a Java-based billing
system, a Python microservice, and a
TypeScript front-end simultaneously
without redundant development cycles.
And because a DSL is a,
a version control like source code,
every rule has a full audit history.
You can always trace back, what did
this rule look like on January first?
What changed on March fifteen, and why?
Text to code engine is where the
TSL models are converted into a
production-ready implementation
code This is done using a fine-tuned
coding LLMs, the models that
have been specifically trained to
understand the enterprise architecture
standard, target language convention,
and system-specific constraint.
The key architecture advantage, as I
mentioned, is that a single DSL rule model
can generate a compliant code for multiple
systems and jurisdictions simultaneously.
This eliminates what I call redundant
development cycle across subsidiary.
The expensive error-prone process
where each regional engineering team
re-implement the same rule independently.
But, and this is critical, generated
code is never deployed directly.
It enters a rigorous multi-stage
validation pipeline before
any production release.
I'll describe that
pipeline in the next slide.
The reason this constraint is
architecturally important is trust.
An enterprise cannot state its
tax compliance on AI-generated
code that hasn't been validated.
The pipeline is what earns that trust
The four validation layers are
herein, we are talking about
the four validation layer.
This validation pipeline are structured
for the production rollout process.
These four validation layers are
static code analysis, syntax, logic,
and standards compliant- compliance.
Regression testing, verifying that the
new rule doesn't break any existing rules.
Differential testing, comparing outputs
between old and new rule versions to
identify unintended behavioral changes.
And formal property checks, a mathematical
verification that the rule satisfies
boundary condition and extremes.
Only after all four layer pass
does the code move to production
rollout, and even then it doesn't
go live everywhere at once.
We used a stage deployment model.
Shadow deployment first, where
the new rules runs in parallel
without affecting live transaction.
The canary testing, activating for
a small percentage of traffic, then
gradual activation, expanding the
rollout with a continuous monitoring,
and finally full deployment with rollback
capability remaining active throughout.
The stage approach means that a
rule error will affect a fraction
of transaction, will be detected
immediately by monitoring, and
can be rolled back in minutes.
The blast radius of any
mistake is bonded by design.
Autonomous compliance does
not mean unchecked automation.
Humans govern policy.
I want to address something directly
that I know is on the mind of every
compliance professional in enterprise
architecture in the audience.
Does autonomous mean unchecked?
The answer is no, and the
architecture is explicit about it.
Human always control the three category
of decision that carry the highest stake.
First, ambiguous or novel
regulatory interpretation.
Situation where the NLM confidence
score is low or where the regulation
is genuinely new territory.
Second, high-impact rule
changes that affect multiple
jurisdictions simultaneously.
And third, active audit jurisdiction and
disputed tax position where any change
could affect ongoing legal proceedings.
The
governance dashboard gives compliance
professional full visibility into the AI's
interpretation and reasoning, not just the
output, but the source regulation it cited
and why it reached the conclusion it did.
They can approve, modify, or reject
any rule with a single action,
and every decision is logged
immutably for audit purposes.
The philosophy here is
human govern policy.
AI handle implementation.
The system is designed to
escalate, not override human
judgment on high-stake decision.
Auditab- auditability is not an optional
feature for enterprise tax sy-systems.
It is a regulatory requirement.
Tax authorities don't just want the
right answer, they want to see the
chain of reasoning that produce it.
The ACI provides three interlocking
layers for explainability.
First, transaction-level traces.
Every tax calculation is logged
with the exact rule version and the
specific inputs that were applied.
You can replay any transaction and
see precisely what logic was executed.
Second, rule pro- rule
provenance tracking.
Each rule in the system is linked
back to the specific regulatory text
that generated it, the statute, the
guidance document, the effective date.
There is no rule in the system that
cannot be traced to its legal source.
Third, system-level observability.
Drift detection, SLA monitoring, and
error tracking by jurisdiction, and
automated rollback triggered when
an- when anomalies are detected.
These three layers together mean
that when a tax auditor asks,
"How did you calculate this?"
The answer is always available,
always traceable, always defensible
I want to share five hard-won lessons
from real enterprise dep-deployments
of agentic compliance system, including
the work we have done at Amazon.
Lesson one: confidence estimation
matters more than accuracy.
The ability of the system to know
when it doesn't know and to escalate
pro-appropriately is what separates
a prototype from a production system.
Uncertainty quantification
drives self's safe escalation.
Lesson two: DSL design is a
strategic intellectual property.
The quality of a domain-specific
language determines the quality
of everything downstream.
Invest early in getting the DSL right.
Lesson three: regulatory data inputs
vary significantly by jurisdiction.
Some governments publish
machine-readable regulation.
Other publish PDF scanned from paper.
Your ingestion layer need to
handle both and needs to score
its own confidence accordingly.
Lesson four: identify-- identity
and access management integration
is essential for audit.
Every human approval action in
the governance dashboard must be
tied to an authenticated identity.
The audit log is only valuable
if it is tamper evident.
And lesson five, the most important
governance maturity determines deployment
success more than model accuracy.
You can have a state-of-the-art LLM.
If your organization hasn't defined
who approves rule changes, what the
escalation thresholds are, and how
rollbacks are authorized, system will
stall at the first high-stake decision.
My practical recommendation is
start with simple generation, single
rate, wet regimes to build your
organizational confidence before
tackling the cross-border complexity
Let me be concrete about the business
case, because the ROI here is compelling.
Faster updates, compliance changes
that previously took three to six
months are implemented in hours.
That's not incremental improvement,
that's structural change in how
enterprise respond to regulatory risk.
Lower cost.
The manual compliance workflow, legal
review, policy translation, developer
implementation queue is expensive.
Automating the implementation layers
significantly reduce that overhead,
freeing compliance professional to
focus on judgment-intensive work.
It reduces audit risk.
When rules are applied and consistently--
rules are applied consistently and
traceability a-across all entities and
jurisdiction with full provenance, the
audit exposure is dramatically lower.
This is not a theoretical benefit.
It directly mitigates the kind
of class action litigation we
have seen in the market recently.
And perhaps more strategically,
compliance becomes a competitive
advantage when your system can observe
a regulatory change overnight while a
competitor is still in planning meeting.
That's a moat.
My recommendation, ROI path, begin
with VAT and GST automation, where
the rules are more structured and
the confidence level will be highest.
Then expand to cross-border pricing,
digital service tax compe-complexity
as your gove-governance maturity grows
I want to close these three observation
about where this is going and why it
matters that you are paying attention now.
First, AI augments human
expertise, it does not replace it.
The vision I have described today is
not one where compliance professionals
are automated out of exis-existence.
It is one where the mechanical,
time-consuming work of implementation
is handled by AI, freeing experts to
focus on the judgment calls, the policy
interpretation, the strategic tax position
that require genuine human expertise.
Second, agentic architectures scale
governance without scaling head count.
As your enterprise expands to
new jurisdiction, the compliance
surface areas grow linearly.
But with a multi-agent system, that
implementation co-cost goes-- The
cost does not grow proportionally.
That's a fundamentally different economic
model for a compliance and scale.
Third, explainability drives adoption.
Every conversation I have with enterprise
compliance teams come back with
the same question: Can we trust it?
The answer is not trust the model.
The answer is you don't
have to trust the model.
You can see exactly what it did and why.
Auditable AI is a deployable AI.
The organization that responds
deploy AI-driven compliance system
today is-- will define the future of
enterprise tax operation tomorrow.
Tech-- The technology is ready.
The question is whether the governance
framework, the organizational
maturity, and the willingness to
make the investment are ready, too.
Thank you.
I look forward your, to your questions.
I'm happy to go deeper on any
part of the architecture or the
real-world implementation challenge
we have encountered at Amazon.
Thank you for watching this
session at CON42 LLM 2026.
If you'd like to connect, you
can find me on LinkedIn at
linkedin.com/in/AbdulBIqbal, or
you can also reach me directly
on email, reachabiqbal@gmail.com.
I'm always happy to d-discuss
enterprise AI architecture, tax
system or intersection of the two.
Thank you.