Hi everyone.
This is Sand.
hope everybody having a good time.
Today I wanna talk about the how
to enhance our payments using ai.
I'm gonna give some important
points here, important notes, and
then I wanna run through, how we
can utilize the ai, and then, how
to make our life easy, basically.
And then how to make our
payment sector very secure.
yeah, after this session, I hope
everybody get, knowledge and then
so that, we can make, All secure.
So I wanna start, with, enhancing the
digital payment secure with ai, basically
the global digital, payment, market is
supposed, exponential growth, but that
comes to the i security risk basically.
Um, you can do, with within the,
if with this presentation, I wanna
go ahead and then, basically.
Show what kind of revolution payments,
security that we can run through,
and then so that we can do the, fraud
detection, productivity, analytics
and adapt to, threat mechanism.
yeah, I'm going through the, my second
slide so that, we can go further.
The growth challenge of
digital payments, fraud.
Nowadays, there are two high risk that
we can do, or, the two components that
we have to take into consideration.
Number one is rapid growth.
that's what happening in digital world.
And then second thing, rising
in threats whenever you see.
There are a lot of growth that
are happening in any sector.
At the same time, we see the other side
of the coin, there is a rising threat.
So when it comes to the growth, what
kind of dis payment we, we are seeing,
the growth and then, we are, we're
experience unprecedented, expansion
in the, product search and then.
The projected, the surge
behind 15 trillion, by 2027.
This is a huge number.
And then this is the expensive
growth, basically field, where set
of odd options like, whatever the
contactless payment that we are doing.
And then, mobile wallet pairing,
payments, and then imaging
technologies like blockchain.
Transforming how billions of people
worldwide, conduct in the transaction.
So the rapid growth happening with
all these things, but other side we
have a, a lot of, threats are rising.
The rising threats.
However, these, disablement
resolution as, attract sophisticated
cyber, cyber criminals,
basically, and then leading alarm.
rise in a fraud.
So experts predicted annual loss, from
payments fraud will be skyrocketed.
48 billion, dollars by 2 25 with,
attacking become increasingly complex,
harder, detecting using the traditional
security measure what we have right now.
What do we have to do to get this,
payment secure and then to make the
things better for the human life?
so AI power of, power of fraud
detection, is a, usually a game changer
where we can detect the threats,
with using the AI automatically.
So the one, the three things that we
could do, one is a deep learning model.
basically AI power fraud
detection model, leveraging the.
Deep learning and behavioral bio
biometrics and having demonstrated
an 80% of improvement in detection,
the suspicious transactions compared
to traditional rule methods.
And second thing, what we
can do enhance accuracy.
So machine learning algorithm.
So using the mechanism, machine learning
algorithms, analyzing the, vast data
sets, identifying the MS and unauthorized,
access with the 98% of SIG significantly,
reducing false positive basically.
So we see nowadays is a lot
of false positive situations.
And then using the, enhancing the
accuracy using the machine learning,
algorithm so we can basically.
detected these things, very easily.
And then the third one we can
think of is productive analytics.
AI driven product analytics
helps financial institution and
anticipated fraud threats, right?
So reducing the potential losses
by up to 12 billion annually.
So this is how we can do
the productive analytics.
more to the next slide.
the a, another thing, what we can
achieve is realtime transaction
monitoring and bio metric authentication.
So realtime monitoring.
So using the advanced AI power
transaction, monitoring has slashed.
Fraud incident by 30% across
the financial network.
So what the ability to analyze
over 20,000 transaction per second.
The flags suspicious
activity within milliseconds.
So that's what we can do
with the realtime monitoring.
And then another stuff we can do,
biometric authentication, next generation,
biometric identification, combine.
AI with the multiple verification
methods, so including, facial
recognition and, fingerprint
scanning, and then wise patterns.
So with this, we can achieve 99
points of, 99.9 accuracy with
a reducing, authentication time
to under almost two seconds.
So this is multimodal approach
that, cut, parental access and
attempt by 85% of while maintaining
the seamless user experience.
let's move on to the next one.
the main thing is the
blockchain, a new, frontier.
For securing the digital payments.
So there are two things, right?
So zero knowledge, proof,
and then, you know, learning.
So Revolution AI powered blockchain
security protocol utilizes zero
knowledge proof to validate transaction
with a hundred percent accuracy.
That's huge number, that's like
a perfect a hundred percent while
maintaining the complete data privacy.
This breakthrough is the
technology enabling the financial
institution process over.
10,000 transaction per
second, that's fast.
And while ensuring the sensitivity
customers information remain
fully, encrypted and protected, so
using this zero knowledge proof,
you can achieve good things.
Another one, federated learning,
through advanced learning system
bank and payment providers.
Can now collaborate to strengthen their,
collective defense again, against fraud.
So sharing AI model improvement
without explanation customer data,
this distribute approach has helped
and better institution reduce fraud.
65% while maintaining street data.
and regulatory complaints.
So those things we can
achieve, with the blockchain.
And then, the, I wanna move on to the
next slide and explain the industry
success stories, demonstrating
the AI impact, what we could do,
using the AI and then the industry.
Success stories.
number one is reduce charge.
chargeback, leading a financial
institution have, reported
dramatically 40% of reduction
in chargeback fraud through,
sophisticated, AI driven detect system.
That's a huge number.
So we are now, we're getting the
40% reduction in chargeback fraud,
and the major credit card provides
implementing the solutions save over 2.3.
Billion in fraud climb while
maintain the customer trend
satisfaction rates about 95%.
So that's a huge numbers there.
And then second thing is the
enhanced transaction speed.
So the success story,
another success story.
We can do enhanced transaction,
by 28% using the AI algorithm.
And then if you look at the
crossing time, it is 3.2 seconds.
just eight minutes, seconds.
A leading 30% increase in
customer, compliance, completion
rate and significantly higher
merchant satisfaction score.
So yeah, reduce chargebacks and
then, enhanced transaction speed.
Those are, big things that, you
know, we can achieve with the ai.
And then let monitor next one.
And merging AI trends shaping
the future of payment security.
So what is a. The trends that we are
seeing right now for the future of secure
the payments, any kind of payments.
So quantum security, encryption, and
then advertiser, ai, defense mechanism.
These two we can use.
And then that's the AI trends
that we are looking right now.
The advent, of quantum computer necessity,
quantum secure encryption algorithm
to protect the IGN potential attacks.
And then AI plays a big role in this.
so dial up and then, use
the encryption method.
Those are things.
And, AI driven.
The second one, aal AI defense
mechanism, AI driven defense mechanism
are evolving to proactively combat
arisal attacks, such as defects and
knowledge, ensuring, less resilience of
payment system, sophisticated threat.
Okay, let's move on to the
important thing, AI role.
Building a safer digital
financial ecosystem.
So what we could do to build a
safer digital financial ecosystem
using the ai, what is the AI role?
So the, we can think of
three, three things right now.
the enhanced security, improved
efficiency and has a customer experience.
So by the looking at these things,
With using the ai, the financial
institution pro proactively detect
the payment fraud, and then it'll help
the financial institution and then
consumer and everybody, the customer,
everybody, and then improve efficiency.
So AI driven automation, seamless
process leading to faster transaction,
reduce the cost, and then more
efficient financial ecosystem.
And then the third one is
enhance the customer service.
So end of the day, the customer,
customer experience is a main priority.
So using the AI power solution
improved, you can basically, the
customer can feel more secure and
then, we can do like a seamless payment
processing and while minimizing the
friction and enhancing convenience.
The future payment security, how it
is looking in future payment security,
a collaborative, what we could do
to achieve this, and then, what
is our approach we should follow.
Across industry partnership.
Let's establish a dynamic partnership
between the banks and then FinTech
companies and cyber security experts
to create a integral different,
defense security that rapidly
share the, intelligent at best
practice and practices basically.
And second thing is
breakthrough technologies.
Investing a cutting edge in
cutting edge ai, and then
machine learning solution that.
Predict the, imaging cybersecurity threats
and while adapting to evolving payment
technologies, and consumer behavior.
And third one is smart governance.
developing the, flexible yet robust,
regulatory, standards and the
balance, innovation with the consumer
protection, ensuring AI system remains.
Transparent, accountable.
And then, it is make sure that the
global compliance requirement met.
So that above all, there, the, what
are the key takeaways from this,
and then what are the next steps
we have to do to make it, this ai,
works good for us and, it's good for
the make it, the cybersecurity safe.
The AI revolution in action, the first
thing that we discussed and that AI
technologies have demonstrated transform,
result direction of fraud, by cutting up
to 63% while processing the transaction
for faster and making, the account,
the account register payment platform.
the second thing is power of,
partnership, success, demand, strategies,
collaboration between the financial
institution like I, like we discussed,
and then expertise, cyber security
expertise, ensure defense, in depth.
And then using the AI methods, and
then, partnership between the FinTech
companies, we can achieve this.
And then building tomorrow's
trust by implementing a driven
security solution today.
We are creating a future while digital
payments are not just faster, more
efficient, but fundamentally secure,
trustworthy for all participants.
So by coming to the conclusion
towards, the secure and, the future,
all the stuff, what we discussed so
far, what is the conclusion about ai?
How we transformed?
AI has transformed from theoretical
concept to the powerful.
Four, reshaping and then using the
AI technologies and then intelligent,
there are a lot of mechanism
that AI doing right, right now.
like we discussed, fraud
detection, realtime monitoring,
and intelligent authentication.
So these are stuff we can use and then we
can use this AI in good way where it'll
ease our transactions with a secure,
and then basically the future of digital
payments isn't just bright, so it's here.
So digital payments, we wanna
make the digital payments bright.
So it's here, it is being
safeguarded by the unstoppable
combination of human expertise
and, artificial inte intelligence.
So that's conclude my presentation.
hope you know, everybody got
some knowledge and and thanks
for the opportunity here.
And then, have a good day.
Thank you.