Speaker 23: Hello everyone.
Good morning, good afternoon,
and good evening, based on
the locations you are from.
Myself, Sushant Kumar Sahu.
I have been working as a site
reliability engineer for the past
twenty years in the various company.
One decade I spent in India and Singapore,
including some of the great companies
like SAP Lab, Yahoo, Goldman Sachs,
and Apple, and later on I spent my rest
of the another ten years in Bay Areas.
Some of the great companies I have
been working on is the Verizon
Wireless, Autodesk, and Zscaler.
Currently, I'm working as a principal
engineer in site reliability engineering.
Almost in all those past company,
I have been focusing in my
roles and responsibility, just
focusing on the resilience,
reliability, and recoverability.
We do tons of things to bring
the customer trust and make the
architecture high available, zero
downtime, and so on and so forth.
All those twenty years experience,
I have seen how SRE functions
have been evolving, and currently
we are in the AI and LLM era.
So now let's focus on in this talk
how LLM Copilot for SRE literally
transforming the incidence response and
how it help us to auto remediations.
So let's quickly go back to
the slides we'll talk through.
LLM Copilots.
Earlier was the day when people used to
troubleshoot, look around the different
matrices, different information systems.
Now, how LLM is helping us and how LLM is
resetting how SRE team detects, diagnose,
and resolve incidents in the modern
distributed systems, we will look through
in the various slides They literally
bridge the gap between the overwhelming
telemetry and the actionable insights.
So the more challenging one
is drowning in telemetry.
If you look at the current trend and
the current architecture, every company,
everybody needs zero downtime and
high available, high recoverability.
Everything we need, there is no downtime
be- because the business need in that way.
Some of the… Not some of
the, most of the company, they
don't care about the revenue.
However, they just care about their
availability so that they bring the trust.
And in those situations, the architecture
go on and on, spinning across clouds,
across Kubernetes cluster, and even
sometime it goes from region to maintain
high availability and disaster recovery
to avoid all those zero downtime, right?
So in those situations, we have tons
and tons of infrastructure we spins
off through various Terraform, various
tools we use over the industries.
And that leads a lot of confusions,
lot of data, and there is a very little
clarity what we look at today right now.
If someone wanted to zoom in and
understand what's going on inside
the infrastructure in terms of the
log, metrics, traces, and what sort
of deployment happens, if you imagine
there is so many data centers, so many
Kubernetes clusters, so many applications
running, so many dependents in the
upstream and downstream, then we need
a vigilant system which will track
through, get all those intelligence,
and understand what's happening.
So it's very tough for someone
to visualize and analyze
all those and diagnose.
So that's landed us in such a situations.
We are having lots of… and they are
literally flooded with the incidents and
so many alerts to understand through, so
that literally delayed the diagnosis, as
well as that fragmented visibility is not
enough for humans to cope of actually.
Engineers often spend more time
filtering noise versus what the
fix actually they wanted to do.
So the new paradigm, LLM Copilot,
unlike rule-based automation, LLM
reasons across multiple data sources.
It doesn't matter how many data
center, how many Kubernetes cluster,
how many dependency we have.
All of them can fit it into the knowledge
base, and LLM is capable to handle and
summarize all those operational context
and assist engineer in the real-time
decisions without making any delay.
So those decisions are augmenting
human expertise rather than
replacing human actually.
So we are shifting From reactive
firefighting model to the proactive
and even predictive model we are going.
So these are the way our incidence
response have been evolved.
There was a era when I remember we
used to do manually everything, get
into the dashboard display, look
into all of them, look at the alerts,
what we get, and then to whom it
got escalated, who took the action.
So how they are interrelated, and
then we'll come up a solution.
Okay, these are the fixes we need to
do, and it takes a lots and lots of time
and bringing the impact to the customer
and the trust is in the jeopardy.
So now when we landed into the AIOps era,
lot of things has been improved actually.
In terms of anomaly detections,
we started correlating different
events and root cause analysis
also it started helping us AIOps.
Now, that model we are taking
to the further level, which is
the natural language reasoning.
No more we are going to look for,
systematical model to solve the problem.
We will just talk to the LLM model like
we are casually and normally talking to
a human, and LLM model will understand us
and find out all those contextual behavior
across all of our knowledge base and
let us know what we need to do actually.
So example, what changed
before the outage?
Let's say we had a incidence and
we would like to understand this
incidence is just because of some
recent past incident outages, or is it
because of the recently some release
happened we wanted to roll back?
We can ask, "What changed
before this outages?
Is it related to me?
And was there any release happens?" We can
ask recommended rollback options for this
incident so that LLM model can go look
into the past knowledge base and figure
out the similar incidents happened in
the past and tell us, "Okay, in the past
incidents, we handle the situations like
this." So these are the recommendations
you can look for that help us expertise
to reduce the mean time to detection as
well as the mean time to recovery so that
the customer will be having more trust
and the bleeding will reduce actually
So if you look at the model, the
way LLM copilots are built these
days, the very primary important
things is the telemetry layer.
We need to have a very solid understanding
architecture of the log, metrics,
traces, and the various deployment layer.
We need to clearly understand what
deployment's gone through, what
is the histories, everything need
to be fed into the knowledge base.
On top of it, out of all of those, we
need to have a very visible dashboards
for the entire platform, starting from
engineer levels to the leaders level,
all the way to the business level.
Three layers of the visibility
in terms of Grafana, Datadog or
Splunk or any other platform we can
utilize to plot all those graphs.
So that all those informations
can be fed into the LLM
intelligence engines to understand.
These days, these LLM engines, they
can get into the dashboards and
correlates with the logs, metrics,
traces, and events on its own actually.
And automatically, it just runs
different StackStorm and Rundeck through
different Kubernetes APIs, cloud APIs.
How can we solve that?
If you recall, in the past, we
used to do follow a runbook, follow
certain commands to solve the problem.
But these days, automatically, all those
StackStorm, Rundeck or, Kubernetes API
calls has been triggered automatically.
But again, we need to be very careful
what we are solving automated unless
it is trusted and proved step by steps.
So I would recommend to go from
the lower level risk all the way
high level, which we'll be talking
in the further slides, right?
So human oversight remain critical for us.
Engineers still validate recommendations
and approve the remediations
actions throughout actually
How the intelligence
detections helping us.
Okay.
These are the various layer
our LLM model correlate.
There is a lot of things.
Couple of examples, actually.
We did a recent release, and after
the release, what's happening, these
LLM models can automatically go and
figure out was there any API latency
spikes up after the recent release, or
DB saturation happening, or any slow
query going on inside the DB, or any
of the node is instability, or front…
upstream or downstream dependency.
So this list goes on and on, actually.
However, LLM is capable to summarize all
of those and auto-generate the incident's
timeline, what time what happens.
All those sequence will
come up automatically.
What are the service affected?
What are the business unit impacted?
What's the incidents raised by
the customer versus us versus
any of other dashboard telemetry
we have, which was giving clue?
So those are very much helpful to
generate all sort of hypothesis, actually.
This is dramatically helping us to
reduce the impact for the customer.
These are, again, through the
natural language queries we can
form actually during the incidents.
Yeah, auto remediations, right?
So this is a very big thing, actually.
It depends on how much practice, what
are the models we are following, and
how we trend our team culturally, right?
There are a lot of things to
do to achieve all of this.
However, in my past experience from the
chaos engineering, we have implemented
certain process to figure out the strength
as well as the weaknesses You know,
strength is the strength, which is very
good, and weakness is again weakness.
That's also very good to find
out what sort of weakness we
have in the infrastructure.
Beyond that, we also try to find
out what else we don't know.
That's called unknown category.
So these are some of the practices,
some of the process we need to follow
to understand what certain things we
know in our control, and we have enough
knowledge in our LLM model, they can go
and auto-fix it, rather us getting up
over the night and looking into the Pfizer
duty and understand what's going on.
So couple of examples here.
If some of the containers are
not healthy, just restart it.
Rather struggling, going for
rusting memory and restarting
is gonna take time, right?
So what happened, there was a deployment
and immediately the f-f… immediately
post-deployment, we are getting all
those alerts, all those incidents,
all those issues from the customer.
Just without waiting, just roll back
fast, get the customer back into
the infrastructure, let the business
continue, and then we can figure
out in the back end what happens.
Why did it happen?
How to avoid all those
situations in the future.
Certain situations, scaling
infrastructure is also not limited.
We, we focus on that.
If because of the scaling having a
problem, we not only scale the pods,
we also scales the nodes into the
Kubernetes cluster, as well as any
possible nodes we can automatically
add it as part of the autoscaler.
And sometime if we have the DR,
disaster recovery, another region
ready for us, they also auto-failover
from one region to another regions.
But keep one thing in mind, out of, let's
say, a company having 30 applications
running, and one application is having
problem and failover from one region
to another region, then look at the
latencies it's gonna bring into for the
other regions because are… when we are
doing failover from one region to another
region, is that particular app is failing
over or the rest of the app failing over?
That we can do the chaos engineering
test and understand, and then gain
those knowledge of those latency
and then if those added latencies
okay for us to continue, then we can
implement one app is gonna failover.
Otherwise, let's call for the entire
infrastructure failover from one
region to another regions, and they
are automated too through the LLM
Deployment outages.
This is one of the examples, step by
steps, we can go detect the latency.
How was the latency for us before
the release, and how is right now?
Relate with deployment, relate
with any other dependence apps.
If somebody else did some
change, was there anything
change on the infrastructure?
Was there anything change on the network?
Was there any cha-- Was there
anything change on the internet layer?
Out of all of our traffic, how
much coming through the internet
versus, private versus public?
So all of these we can correlate and then
verify and execute for the rollback steps.
So monitoring and notify is the very
critical piece in the backend layer,
as well as involvement of the humans
and taking all those decisions Okay,
so PagerDuty and LLM together is a
different ballgame together these days.
So if you look at few years back when
there was no LLM, we used to flood
it with so many PagerDuty alerts, and
then some engineer literally pause
the PagerDuty and focus one by one,
go get in to figure out what is the
problem out of the flooded alerts.
These days, this LLM is literally
solving, "Hey, your broadcaster
issue out of these areas.
So focus on this particular area." It just
literally gives us, summarize everything
in a couple of lines and tell us, "Okay,
problem might be in this area." We are
in a different level right now, right?
So summarizes incidents overview and
the alert as soon as you open it, and
probable affected services and dependency
maps, it just gives us immediately.
It just correlate with the related
deployment, historical similar incidents,
what happened in the past, which I already
talked about it, and then it can suggest
some diagnostic commands for us also.
So what is the improvement, right?
Faster incident triage, root cause
a-a-analysis that reduces cognitive
overload actually, and improve the
cross-team coordinations, collaborations
with the different team through the
Slack, Team, Zoom call, et cetera, and
enhance incidents documentation quality.
LLM itself can generate a lot of
documentation quality correlating all of
these, and that can be future referenced
if the similar issue is gonna happen.
First of all, we are gonna
avoid all of those incidents.
Always, we are keeping human in control.
I believe the LLM models are not
yet ready, so we are going through
that era, but still there will be a
lot of back and forth conversations,
correlations in between human and by AI.
So most of the situations, we are
still going through high-risk task
required explicit human approvals.
We can't give all this control.
As I said, e-- through the various chaos
engineering, we need to start stepping off
from low risk to the high risk and give
control one by one from our development
environment all the way to the production
environment in a various test phases.
So that we'll come to know how safely
we can give the control to LLM, and
they can take the con- take the actions
while we are sleeping in the night.
We need peaceful sleep.
Lot of policy we need to enforce actually.
Operational policies restrict
which system LLM can touch versus
human who can control, and what
level of access we need to provide.
LLMs retrieve various knowledge
from the trusted internal sources
those knowledge base are critical.
And audit, logging, and
feedback, of course.
We need to have this AI actions need
to be reviewed every aspects, every
time, and continuously give the
feedback and improve our existing
model to get into the next level.
But still, there is a
problem in solving actually.
Yes context window constraint, actually.
Vast telemetry volume, like I
was explaining, we are going…
There is no limit, right?
There is no limit.
We are going even… We-- I built
architecture which was across the cloud.
I remember in previous to previous
company, I built one architecture.
It was in GCP cloud.
It was a separate data center.
Few of the component was still there
because we were in the middle of
migrating three, four Kubernetes
cluster from three different GCP
account as well as AWS account.
So all those, when it comes to a lot
of data to digest through, right?
Vast telemetry volumes make efficient
context selection and these are
the key technical challenges
which we need to go through.
And real-time performance, right?
The model inference is importance.
If model inference latency, that
can reduce the effectiveness
and performance, right?
And data privacy and model drift.
Sensitive telemetry requires
secure governance fully.
Yes, agree.
These are real important part of
the company, so they can't expose.
So we, we need to handle those sensitive
data in a separate model, actually.
Of course, the moment we have all
those luxury to move various different
tools, various components, various
places, then cost is important factor.
We always focus on how much
we are spending versus how
much we can gain out of that.
So that is another important factor.
Always our focus goes on there So this is
the future of the reliability actually.
In reliability engineering we definitely
need to work on multi-model analysis,
where, our LLM models can go across
the areas, across the architecture,
and then cross over, understand logs,
metric stresses, and visual dashboard
automatically, simultaneously in
the same time and in real-time.
We need all of those.
Predictive remediations, right?
Proactive reliability improvement
before failure occurs.
Right now, we need to
go very innovative way.
Before even incidents
happen, we need to solve it.
We need to find out beforehand, resolve
it, nobody-- before nobody noticed it.
And then digital twin testing.
I was talking chaos engineering, right?
Safely simulate remediation strategy
before applying them in the productions.
We need to test thoroughly in
various way, from low risk to
the high risk, all the way from
non-productions to the productions.
And federated intelligence share
anonymized reliability insights across
industries while preserving security.
Every company should share
their experience and expertised.
Keep all of your confidential, however,
the experience need to be shared so
that the industry need to adopt, people
need to learn so that we can move into
the next level actually These are the
best practices for getting started.
No matter what, we need to have
a solid observability first.
Without observability, we can't even
think, LLM can't do anything because
LLM depends on the lot of knowledge
base, which is trusted knowledge base.
As long as we have a organized
observability platform, one platform
is recommended rather than I have
seen companies, they use Splunk, they
use DataDog, they use New Relic, they
use Dynatrace, different teams go
with their budget priority, though
they get into multiple things, and
when there is a incidence happen, we
wanted to understand what's going on.
We can't go from Splunk to New
Relic to all sort of things.
Maybe some other model need to develop.
We can connect to multiple observability
platform, no matter you are using DataDog,
Splunk or anythings our LLM model need to
connect to everywhere and figure out that.
We need to improve that also.
Yes, gradual automation is very important.
I already talked through in the
various phases, so we need to move
actually, we need to move further step
by steps from low-risk to high-risk,
continue automating all of them
so that the toil is gonna reduce.
Yes, define the policy, governance
policy those boundaries, escalation
procedures is very important, and
continue doing that constantly.
In terms of the efficiency,
alert quality, every areas
need to be evolved continuously
Human plus AI, that is how we can
do the better together actually.
LLM copilots definitely augment
human prioritize, reducing
repetitive cogniti-cognitive task
while engineers still today retain
the strategic decisions authority.
The goal is the collaborative resilience.
The more and more we trend AI, the lesser
and lesser responsibility for the humans.
However, like I said, the
strategic decisions still we
are doing from the human side.
The goal is collaborative resilience,
not the replacement actually.
The most resilient team will
use AI as a force multiplier,
not a substitute for the human.
That's for sure actually.
Trust is built incrementally through
transparency and explainability,
so people can understand and
validate how AI decisions are made.
Remember, trust is very important.
Quick example, when you call some of
the customer care or anything, talk
about phone or a banking system or
anything, the moment you see the AI
interacting with you, your frustration
comes into your mind, and literally
you tend to drop that call and find out
is there any direct agent I can talk.
That's what the trust is.
So never break your trust.
Introduce AI, but make sure that what AI
is doing, every steps is being validated.
Without doing that, this will be
a big mistake for the companies.
Again, together human judgment and
AI supports enable definitely faster
innovation and more reliable system for
scale.
The intelligent SRE future.
LLM copilots bridge the gap between
massive telemetry volume and
actionable operational insights,
enabling faster detection, smarter
remediations, and improved resilience,
which we already talked through.
And success definitely depends on the
responsibility governance we built, human
oversight, as we talked through, and
carefully designed automated boundaries.
Absolutely.
These are the golden statement actually.
And finally, it just ends my slides.
However, I wanted to thanks all of
you for watching my slides and talks.
And if you have any questions, please
reach out to me and definitely I will try
to answer all of you from my experience.
And thank you.
Thank you a lot for
watching these sessions.
It was wonderful.
Thanks all of you.
Bye.