Hello everyone and welcome to Con
42 Large Language Models 2025.
I am Andre bso.
I serve as both CFO and CLO, and my
background includes engineering, web
development, and of course finance.
Today I am excited to be here
and I'm excited to talk about
how large language models are.
Changing the way we do
finances for our companies.
Okay.
Let's start with a small introduction.
I have been working at the intersection of
finance and legal operations for a while,
and I've seen firsthand how emerging AI
technologies are transforming the way.
Companies manage data, optimize
cash flow, and ensure compliance.
And this presentation will explore how
LLMs are not only automating routine
processes, but also how they can unlock
new strategic possibilities like.
Freeing up capital and,
empowering businesses to make
faster and smarter decisions.
So let's dive in by looking at
what the financial landscape
looked like before LLMs.
To understand the impact
of LLMs, it helps.
To look back at how we did things
in finance not too long ago.
We lived in a world that revolved
around spreadsheets and reports.
Our data usually sat in silos,
whether in separate departments
or across outdated databases that.
Didn't play nicely with each other.
This made it nearly impossible
to get a real time snapshot
of, our financial health.
So we would wait for our month
and or quarter end close.
We would see what happened, and only
then we could decide how to respond.
It wasn't just the reporting
cycles that slowed us down.
We also faced a challenge in dealing
with unstructured information,
regulatory documents, contracts,
emails, invoices, and even social media.
Comments about our company often
stayed outta reach for analytics.
Because traditional finance and
finance tools just, just were
not built to handle natural text.
That was the environment I
worked in for many years.
When data was stale, by the time we got
it, human bias was always in the mix.
And compliance frameworks were
so rigid that we always worried
that we might miss something.
Then came the rapid development
of large language models and what
sets large language models apart
is their ability to process.
And interpret massive amounts of text,
everything from invoices to emails,
and even complex legal documents.
More importantly, LLMs can do this
in a way that captures the context
and the nuance of human language.
Instead of handling only structured
data like numbers and columns, LLMs
can, can let us leverage the huge
amount of text-based data that was
previously off limits or too time
consuming to pars for finance.
That's a remarkable shift.
Now we can look beyond a single
spreadsheet or a single dashboard.
We can gather insights from the
natural language we produce every day.
When you feed enough relevant data to your
LLM plus the right instructions about how
your business operates, you get nearly.
Real time guidance on potential risks
or bottlenecks or opportunities.
And, you also get a system
that keeps learning constantly.
This is not just about generating
reports faster, it's about noticing
patterns and issues that their
human eye could easily miss.
Which can lead to more
proactive finance operations.
Okay.
One of the first areas where
I saw LLM Shine was in fraud
detect detection, running online
platforms that process millions.
Our transactions a day.
I have seen many fraud attempts.
These fraud attempts ranged from, from
the usage of stolen credit cards to
really elaborate identity theft schemes.
And, later we used to rely
on rule-based systems.
Those systems were basically sets of if
then conditions and, the systems could
flag transactions that seemed suspicious.
if they fall under any of those
conditions, for example, it can
be unusual purchase amounts.
Foreign IP address or a mismatch
in location, et cetera, et cetera.
Such systems were easy for bad
guys to outsmart because fraudsters
adapt quickly, and our rules had to
be manually updated all the times.
LLMs by contracts, by contrast, can digest
both structured and unstructured data.
This means they can analyze user
interactions, user transactions,
user behavior, everything, even the
text of messages a user generates.
this can be analyzed to find subtle
warning sites, signs of fraud.
LLMs don't just rely on a single rule.
They can spot differences in writing
style or detect discrepancies in
someone's transactional history,
all of which might suggest fraud.
Or some other system abuse.
What I love most is how these models
learn from each new data block.
they take, constantly refining
what suspicious looks like.
Since we started using an LLM based
system to detect fraud, we've seen a
significant drop in fraud in fraudulent
transactions while also cutting down on
false alarms for legitimate customers.
That was a win on both fronts.
Another transformation
involves cashflow management.
If you are into finance and if you've
ever tried to figure out exactly where
your money is at any given moment of
time, or if you try to predict where your
money will be in a few weeks, you know
how critical the cashflow management is.
In many businesses, we used to rely on
monthly or quarterly forecasting, which
meant we didn't always react quickly
if something, if something went wrong.
For instance, we couldn't react
quickly if, key suppliers started
shipping late or if our sales
suddenly spiked beyond expectations.
But with an LLM driven approach, we
can integrate data from our resource
planning system, from supplier
websites, from the markets, and even,
from the world news that might affect
our money flows because the LLM
understands language and it can parse.
Any emails about delayed shipment, LLM
can see, the changes in contracts or
agreements, and this information then can
be fed into the bigger financial picture.
It's like having a continuous
conversation with your cash flow.
It updates you the moment something
changes instead of weeks later.
For my companies, this has allowed us
to keep just the right amount of cash on
hand and we could invest the rest of our
cash where it can, generate some returns
or we could, for instance, support.
New ventures with the rest of
the cash, which we don't need.
Okay.
given that I also oversee legal
compliance in our company, I'm
especially enthusiastic about
using LLMs in this domain.
because managing compliance is hard,
especially if you operate across borders
with different laws and regulations.
in other words, if you operate in
different jurisdictions, companies
usually have entire teams devoted
to reading the latest updates.
Check in.
Checking if they apply to them and
then modifying policies or procedures.
This is expensive, time
consuming and prone to errors.
But now imagine an LLM that constantly
monitors official governmental websites
news, some re some regulatory bulletins.
And the moment your LLM sees something
relevant, like a change in data
privacy law or a new payment regulation
or something similar, your LLM can
match that against your existing
policies and highlight areas that
might need updating or adjustments.
it can, your LLM can even draft a first
version of those changes, saving your
legal team hours and hours of manual work.
Of course, we still need human
oversight to confirm final decisions
and maintain accountability, but.
The reduction in manual search and
repetitive tasks is significant, and
that translates into cost savings and
the more secure compliance posture.
I don't want to paint you a picture.
That's too bright.
Integrating LLMs into financial
operations has its, share of hurdles.
One of the biggest is data preparation.
If you are financial information is
scattered, unprepared, and distribute,
distributed across different systems
or poorly document, poorly documented.
You will need to clean it and
standardize it before any AI model
can deliver any reliable results.
In my experience, this foundational work
can take much longer than you would think,
but anyway, it's absolutely necessary.
Another challenge is, model transparency.
For example, company stakeholders may want
to know why the AI system is suggesting
a particular action or decision, and
we can just shrug and say, it's ai,
it's smart, and we have to trust it.
No, but to solve this problem we've
incorporated explainability tools that
show which data points and which patterns
infl influenced the final LLMs decision.
It's not always perfect, but it
works and it's a good start Then.
There is human factor.
Of course.
We had to train our staff to work
with LLMs in a collaborative way.
We have to make them learn how
to put questions so the, so
that the system understands them
well and training my own team.
It took some time, but once people saw the
benefits, they became really enthusiastic
and they accepted the new approach.
Putting these elements together,
you get a new model for
running a finance department.
routine processes are mostly automated.
Data analysis is continuous rather
than sporadic, and staff members
focus on higher value tasks like
strategic planning and collaboration
with the other parts of the business.
It feels less like we are just keeping the
books, it feels more like we're steering
the organization towards its goals.
Being informed by real time
insights and guided by advanced ai.
I can't overstate how freeing
this can be for A CFO.
Instead of drowning in a sea of everyday
tasks and trailing behind the business,
you find yourself anticipating obstacles.
Allocating resources more
efficiently and spotting profitable
opportunities sooner than before.
And, this change from reactive to
proactive approach extends across the
entire finance team and elevates the
role of finance within the organization.
As LLMs and related technologies
continue to advance, I think
we'll see even more interesting
possibilities in the near future.
LLMs will likely to be able to
handle more than just natural text.
LLMs might interpret visual data,
audio streams, and other media all
at once, giving us an even better
understanding on of what's happening
both inside and outside our companies.
LLMs might act as collaborative
agents that interact with
different departments in real time.
Offering budget adjustments or
compliance checks right on the fly.
We could also see more
autonomous finance features.
Autonomous finance means that for some
simple tasks, like approving a common type
of invoice or transferring funds between.
Internal accounts and AI could, act
entirely on its own without supervision,
but under well-defined rules and, human
intervention would come in only for
more complex or unusual situations.
While that might sound futuristic now.
Many large companies are already
testing the waters here and, the
benefits in terms of speed and
accuracy are really compelling.
all of this means that the
role of the CFO is changing.
It's changing in fundamental way.
We are no longer just the keeper.
Of the historical records.
Instead, we are the designers of
financial intelligence systems.
The overseers of complex data flows
and the architects of risk management
strategies that adapt in real time.
We have the chance to build our companies
more effectively, blending financial.
Aspect with the technological
aspect, but that opportunity
also brings responsibility.
As CFOs.
We need to ensure that AI is used
ethically and transparently, that our
data is secure and that our decisions
remain fair and human centered.
We can't just.
Pass the book to an AI system if something
goes wrong, but it's up to us to put
governance and all necessary structures in
place and maintain oversight at all times.
All right, in closing.
I believe that large language
models represent one of the most
significant shifts in financial
operations in the last few decades.
they turn unstructured data
into actionable insights.
They give us near real time
oversight of cash flow.
They supercharge fraud detection
and prevention, as well as
reduce the burden of compliance.
While there are hurdles like data
preparation, and sometimes model
explainability and sometimes team
training, the payoff is fantastic
and the insights are really useful.
as someone who's had the privilege
of building the AI systems in my own
project, I can't imagine going back to
the old ways of separate spreadsheets
and endless manual checks with lms.
our finance department is more proactive,
more collaborative, and better informed.
And that opens the door to
new strategic possibilities.
Okay.
Thank you very much for spending this
time with me exploring how LMS can
revolutionize financial operations.
I look forward to hearing
your questions, experiences.
And perhaps even your skepticism.
After all, it's through open conversation
that will continue to define these
AI tools and, ensure that they
service responsibly and effectively.
I really appreciate your attention and I'm
excited about the journey ahead for all
of us in the finance world being assisted.
By LLMs, thank you very much.
Goodbye.