Speaker 18: Hi, everyone.
Welcome, and thank you so
much for joining me today.
My name is Rakesh Kumar Jha,
and I work at DXC Technology as
Senior Manager Solution Architect.
I want to start by saying I
genuinely appreciate your time.
What I am going to share with you today
is something I work on every single day
and something I believe matters a great
deal for future of insurance finance.
Over the next few minutes, we are going to
talk about how the artificial intelligence
is transforming general ledger systems.
Now, I know that phrases can sound very
technical, but I want to make you a
promise right now that by the end of this
session, we all will have a clear picture
of how this technology actually works, why
the numbers behind it are so compelling,
and what it means specifically for a
life and annuity insurance companies.
So let me start with one simple question.
How long does your company's
month-end close actually take?
Three days, five days, or even more?
If your finance team is working
late nights and over the weekend
to get those numbers ready,
trust me, you are not alone.
And today, I am going to show you why
that does not have to be the case anymore.
So on your screen right now, you can see
three pillars: operational efficiency,
processing speed, anomaly detection.
These are the three areas where AI
is making the most and immediate
and measurable differences in
insurance financial operations.
And I want to talk you through
each one of these carefully.
Because behind each of these pillars,
there is a very real story about
what changes of the people who work
in insurance finance every day.
So let us start with
operational efficiency.
So right now, in most insurance
companies, a significant portion of
accounting work is done manually.
People are matching transactions, checking
numbers, comparing spreadsheets, and
investigating all the discrepancies.
So when you bring AI into the
general ledger, a large chunk of
these routine work or repetitive
work gets done automatically.
Many research shows that the companies
using AI in their general ledger
have reduced manual intervention in
routine accounting work by up to 40%.
Believe me, 40%.
So that's nearly half of the routine
reconciliation work handled by the
system now without anyone touching it.
The second portion of this, these
pillars is processing speed.
So in life and annuity insurance,
you are running actuarial calculation
at the same time when you are
closing your financial month end.
That is a lot of pressure
on lot of people.
Companies using AI-enabled GL
systems are closing their books
now 35% faster And while still
maintaining or improving the accuracy.
The third and the biggest
pillar is anomaly detection.
So the system catches unusual pattern,
errors, and potential fraud far earlier
than a human reviewer would identify.
We will go into deep all these pillars
later, but for now, let us look at the
numbers So here I want to show three
hide-- headline numbers, and I want to
take a moment with each one, because
numbers without context are just numbers.
Thirty percent, that is the reduction
in the time your finance team spends
on routine reconciliation task.
Think about what that actually means.
If your team currently spending sixty
hours a week on a reconciliation
activity, thirty percent means like
eighteen of those hours will come back.
Eighteen hours a week return to your
team so that they can do more important
analysis, planning, and the work
that really require their judgment.
Forty percent, that is the decrease
in the manual intervention of
the routine accounting task.
So I want to be clear here,
which is very important.
This does not mean that the
forty percent fewer people.
What it means is that forty percent of
the work that was consuming the resources
time is now handled automatically.
And the best organizations I work with
use that freed-up time or capacity to
make their team smarter, not smaller.
Thirty-five percent, that is the
reduction in the month-end close time.
Thirty-five percent faster close.
And here is what I want you to
understand about that number.
It is not faster at the
expense of the accuracy.
It is faster because the system
is doing the continuous validation
throughout the entire month.
So when you arrive at the month-end,
most of the work is already done.
There is far less to
investigate, fix, or to resolve.
These figures come from a KPMG-published
analysis and research on AI in insurance.
So these are real implementation
and real meas-measured outcomes
Now let's get into how this works.
Before any AI can do any useful
or anything useful, it needs
data, a clean data, a reliable
data, and up-to-date data.
And in the most organizations today,
getting that data into the GL cleanly and
in the real-time is genuinely difficult.
So thi- on this slide, I want to
show you the four layers of the
modern data in- injection systems.
Think of these as a foundation.
Anything, everything we talk
about For the rest of day-to-day
sits on top of these four layers.
So starting at the top of the
pyramid are real-time processing.
Traditional GL systems, we all know
that collects data throughout the
day and process them all over at the
overnight in one big batch cycle.
So what does that mean?
That means in the morning,
your data is already hours old.
Decisions are being made
on yesterday's number.
But with the modern system, these
transactions will be processed on
the real-time, the moment it happens.
So for the life insurance carriers,
think about what this means.
When a policy lapses or a reserve
release posted immediately, when a
death claim is filed, your accounting
entry happens right at that moment.
Or when the annuity payment goes out,
your GL reflects it right instantly
there, not one day or 18 hours later.
Right now.
The technology making this
possible is called Apache Kafka.
This is an event-driven
streaming platform.
So how does that work?
That treats every financial
transactions at that event.
Financial companies which are using Kafka
handles millions of event per second while
maintaining complete data consistency.
So that is a infrastructure
headroom that lets a insurance
carrier handle the quarter end
volume spike without slowing down.
The third layer is the data normalization.
Your data comes from many different
systems: a policy admin system,
investment platforms, claim systems,
workflow systems, or reinsurance files.
Each one stores data in
the different format.
So data normalization converts all
that data into a consistent format.
And at the base of that
is the buffer management.
So we all know that on a normal day,
we might see a 200,000 transactions
But on the last day of the month or the
quarter end, we can see a spike up to
two to three millions of transactions.
So what buffer management does,
it absorbs that surge, processes
everything in orderly way, and ensure
that not a single transaction is lost.
So now that we have a clean, a
real-time data flowing in, the
machine learning pipeline takes over.
Think of this as a
four-stage production line.
Each stages transform the data
and process to the next stage.
So stage one is feature engineering.
So in feature engineering, this is
where the system extract the meaningful
information from each raw transaction.
Not just the dollar amount, but the
full context of the transaction.
Some of the examples are the
type of policy, what is the time
of the month the transaction is
coming, or transaction history.
Stage two of this is model architecture.
So in model architecture, this
is where the AI actually learns
the patterns and make the
prediction about each transaction.
Is this normal?
So when any transaction is coming,
the AI model is looking at the
transaction and making sure, is this
transaction a normal transaction?
Does it match what we expect?
Which account should it post it to?
Stage three of this is
the interface engine.
This is where the model's prediction
become an actual decision.
So this interface engine also
applies a regulatory compliance
rules at exactly right at the moment.
So you get AI intelligence and
the rule-based compliance working
together in one single step.
Stage four.
So stage four is the analytics platform.
So what the analytics platform does,
this is basically tracks how the entire
system is performing, identifies where
the accuracy can be improved, and feed
those improvements back into the models.
The system is continuously learning
so that it get better every time
it's processing the transactions.
And critically, all four of these
stages runs like simultaneously at a
real-time, not overni- overnight or
not through a batch processing, right
at the moment for every transactions.
So let us go deeper on the
various stages which we disc- we
discussed in the previous slide.
So stage one is the feature engineering.
Because this is the step that
most people overlook, but it
is the step that determines the
quality of everything that flows.
Here is the thing about
machine learning models.
They do not learn from the raw numbers.
They learn from the meaning you extract
from those numbers, the context,
the history, the relationships.
Let me give you a simple
analogy to make this a concrete.
Imagine that you receive a phone
call from an unknown number at
3:00 a.m. Just the phone number
alone tells you almost nothing.
But if you also know that this is the
third call in the last 10 minutes, and
this is from a country you never had
contact with, now you have a context.
Now you know something is not right.
So feature engineering does exactly
that for every financial transaction.
It does not just look at the amount,
it asks, "What time of the month did
this happen? How old is this policy?
Is this running a payment?" Or this
payment is coming on every month, or this
is a one-time kind of payment coming?
What does the history of
this amount look like?
A premium payment posted on the first
of the month looks very different
from the same amount posted on the
28th The dollar amount is identical.
The context is completely different.
Feature engineering captures
all those differences.
It also handles something called
categor- categorical encoding.
So what does that mean?
Making sure that AI understand
the relationships between
different transactions.
So it categorizes all the different
transactions toge- together, like
surrender charges, annuity elections,
or waiver of the premium, modified
endowment, or any other financial
transactions for the insurance--
life and annuity insurance.
Each one has different accounting
treatment, different compliance
requirement, or different risk.
So this is profiling
all those transactions.
Now we have come to the model
architecture itself, and here is
something critically important that
I want all of you to understand.
Modern GL systems do not use one
single AI model that tries to
do like-- so one single model
AI which tries to do everything.
They use a team of specialized models,
and each of those models are optimized to
do the things what it does at the best.
This approach is called ensemble, and
it is the reason these systems are so
much more reliable than the earlier
generations of the financial AI.
Think of it like this: you would not ask
one person to be your doctor, your lawyer,
and your financial advisor all at once.
You get the right specialist
for the right task.
That's exactly what an ensemble does.
The first specialist
is called LSTM network.
So LSTM network means Long Short-Term
Memory, and the keyword here is a memory.
This is the model that remembers
what has happened before.
It looks at the sequence of the event
over time, and it uses the history
to spot the-- when something changes.
Here is a simple example.
A policyholder has paid their
premium on the fifth of every
month for the eight years.
That is 96 payment All of
those payments are on fifth.
Suddenly, one month, that payment
comes on 28th To a system without
memory, this is just another premium
payment, nothing unusual, right?
But to LSTM, that is a pattern break,
and that gets flagged for review In
life insurance environment, this kind of
Pattern recognition is extraordinarily
valuable So reinsurance settlements that
should arrive on a predictable schedule.
Reserves movement that should
follow the actuarial assumptions.
Investment incomes that should
match the portfolio schedule.
Everything is important on the schedule.
So LSTM learns all these rhymes and
alerts you the moment one of them breaks.
The second specialist
called a random forest.
Think of it as a model that votes.
So random forest builds hundred
of small decision trees.
And on different samples of your data,
each tree look at the transactions
from slightly different angle.
And then they all vote for a
answer, and the majority wins.
So random forest work especially well
in the classification of the data.
Given these transactions,
which amount does it belong to?
Or which account does it belong to?
In this-- If this is a legitimative
surrender charges or a processing
error, should this be classified
as a claim or a policy loan?
And they work well even with the
imperfect data, which honestly
describe most insurance environments.
The third specialist is the isolation
forest This is one of the finds or this
particular specialist finds the odds
from from the transaction, anything
odd which is look, looks odd or not
normal, it will find that odd one out.
The logic is beautiful and it's it's in
It's in its simplicity also.
So normal transactions look like thousand
of the other normal transactions, and they
are very hard to separate from the crowd.
But any ambiguous transactions which are
different from everything else, those
transac- transactions can be separated
here So one suspicious death claim in
the pool of three million transactions,
the is-- it's very hard to find normally,
but the isolation forest finds it.
So in next few minutes, I want to
talk about the reconciliation because
in every con-conversation I have
with CFOs or controllers in life
insurance carrier, this topic comes up.
It is the source of more overtime hours,
more weekend work, more audit findings,
and even more stress in the insurance
finance than almost anything else.
So let me describe something and tell
me if this sounds similar to you.
So it is a Friday afternoon and
your reconciliation team sits
down with a massive spreadsheet,
thousands of items which needs to be
matched, investigated and resolved.
Some of these items go back to
Monday, the last Monday, and
here is the plain-- painful part.
The older the discrepancy
gets, it's harder to track.
Your team work through Friday night
and they work on weekend and Saturday--
Sunday evening they will be able to
clear most of it, and then again the
Monday starts and the same story starts
again this is not a people problem,
this is a system design problem.
The system was designed to accumulate
the differences over the time
and then fix all of them at once.
Continuous reconciliation system
changes that design completely.
Instead of accumulating differences
all week and reasoning them or
resolving them over the weekend, the
system checks that every transaction
right at the real time, right at the
moment it gets posted into the GL.
If something doesn't-- does not match, it
flagged immediately, not five days later.
It-- That get fla-flagged right away.
So the research on this is striking.
The transition from manual batch
reconciliation to automated continuous
reconciliation can reduce processing
d- time by approximately 80%.
In practice, a process that uses
to take a team three people working
all weekend can now be handled by
one person on one single day because
the system is already automized
90% percent of time all the time.
The sliding window analytics
component of the reconciliation system
learns you the pattern over time.
So if your reinsurance treaty constantly
produces a timing difference of fifteen--
timing difference on the 15th of each
month because how its seeding schedule
works, the system learns that and it,
it stop flagging that as an exception.
It builds institutional knowledge
about your business, and the
longer it runs, the smarter it
gets about the specific operations.
Now let us move to the anomaly detection,
and I want to be very specific here.
Because in life and annuity insurance,
anomaly detection is about much more
than catching data entry errors.
Think about what a life insurance
carrier financial data cons- contains.
Actuarial reserves calculation, and
that needs to be exactly matched
with the underlying assumptions.
Complex reinsurance treaties,
where even small dis-
discrepancies compound over time.
Death claim, surrender request,
policy loans, each one with its
own pattern of expected behavior.
A mistake caught today cost far less than
the mistake caught at the quarter end.
So the anomaly detection
framework works in two layers.
The first layer is the
statistical analysis layer.
This layer applies rigorous mathematical
models on every single transactions
continuously on all the time.
It never get tired.
It never loses focus on Friday afternoon.
So G-score analysis ask that if this
transaction significantly outside the
expected distribution f- for its type.
If September time life-- term life
claims are 3.5 standard-- with the
3.5 standard deviation above normal,
the system flags it immediately
before it goes any further A large
reinsurance settlement might not be
unusual by size alone, but large and
earlier than expected on a policy
cohort that normally settles late.
That combination is
anomalous even if no
single number looks wrong
And the machine-- the other l-layer
is the machine learning layer.
Basically, it adds the
semi-supervised learning.
It takes the anomalies you have identified
or you have already identified, the fraud
cases, the reserve errors, everything
which was already identified, learns
the shape of those problems, and catches
new transactions that look similar.
So machine learning is like learning
from your previously errors, and any
new transactions coming, it basically
catches those transactions even before
Or even once it is never seen before.
So moving next, if-- we all know that
if you are operating life and annuity
carrier across multiple US states, you
know the regulatory compliance burden.
NAIC model regulations, state-specific
accounting requirements, Sarbanes-Oxley,
if you are a public, publicly
traded company, FATCA or AML
requirements if you have international
reinsurance re- relationships, and
all of these changes over time.
The traditional approach to
compliance look like this.
You build a control, you test them
periodically, and you find out
about the gaps when the regulators
or auditors finds the- them first.
That is a reactive model.
So an AI-enabled GL system makes
compliance continuous and proactive The
accounted or the automated compliance
framework means that every transaction
is validated against the current
regulatory rules before it ever posted
to the GL, not after the month-end close.
So it's basically automated and before
the processing the transactions, it's
checking with all the rules and making
those entries immediately on every
transaction and every single time
So are you calculating the assets
valuation reserves correctly
for each investment category?
Is the modified coinsurance reserve
updating with the each premium payment?
Th-these checks runs automatically on
every transactions and the technical
control implementation, specifically the
immutable logging creates a permanent
unalterable record for every transactions,
every automated decisions, every
reconciliation matches, every anomaly
flag So these are the technical controls
which will continuously tagging everything
So for the external auditors, whether
it's a KPMG, Deloitte or PWC or any else.
These transactions or these
like automatic technical control
transforms the audit process.
So instead of audit request going
back and forth over the weeks, the
evidence is already assembled, already
traceable, already implemented.
Audit cycles get shorter, finding gets
fewer, and the version control ensures
that when the regulation changes,
the system changes exactly what rules
were in the effect at every point.
So this audit trail is not
something you build for auditors.
The system builds it for
continuously for itself Now let's
talk about the engineering that
makes all this work at this scale.
Because here is a very real challenge
in life and annuity insurance.
Your transactions volumes
are not consistent.
On a normal Tuesday You might process
200,000 transactions, but on the last
day of the business of the quarter,
quarterly premiums comes in when the
automated premiums loan processes
and annuity distributed go out, the
number of-- number can jumps from
two to three million of transactions.
So a traditional system
strains under that load.
It slows down, back up, or
something drops the data.
None of those outcomes are acceptable on
a regulated financial environment So the
performance optimization architecture
solves this with a few components.
Distributed processing.
The system spreads work across
every C server simultaneously.
So what does it mean?
When the volume increases,
capacity increases also, and it
distribute the work on different
servers through load balancing.
So load balancing is like the
intelligent traffic management system.
Ensure the priority of the transactions
are always, and then the priority
transactions are served the first.
Multi-level caching.
The frequent accessed financial records
are held on the fastest storage.
So system answer those query in
milliseconds, even at the scale.
The intelligent parti- partitioning.
Ten years of policy transactions
history organized on that queries
run in seconds, not minutes.
And how that is done?
That's the architecture is built on
the moments of the highest pressure
because those are exactly the moments
when you cannot afford the failures.
We all know that any technology
is only worth implementing if it
delivers the real re- real results.
So there are like four different
categories I have identified
where the AI and GL can bring op-
operationals improvements, and it
will bring ROI on the implementation.
So first big category
is enhanced efficiency.
The number we have talked earlier, thirty
percent, forty percent, thirty-five
percent, these numbers are real.
But I want to say it again, the most
interesting results isn't cost reduction.
It's what your finance team gets to do
with the time they are going to get back.
They do analysis, strategic planning,
exceptional review, the work that actually
requires human intelligence and judgment.
The other big factor
is process automations.
Now, with AI, system runs
twenty-four hours, seven days a week.
It doesn't slow down at eleven PM in
the night, or at the last day of the
month, or at the Friday afternoon.
For carriers processing transactions
around the clock Like international
reinsurance, overnight premium
collections, that continuous
availability has a direct
operational benefits and value.
The other big factor is risk management.
This risk management is often a
most variable part and also the
hardest to put a nu- a number on it.
Catching a reserves miscalculation
or a reinsurance discrepancy on the
day it happened versus finding it on
the quarter-end audit, the financial
differences are huge And avoiding
restatement or regulatory finding or an
audit delay that has its own value goes
well beyond the operational savings.
The last but not the least, the
important feature is data quality.
So with AI, I want to emphasize the longer
the system runs, the better it gets.
It learns your patterns, its accurac-- and
with the patterns, its accuracy improves.
Its false rate or f-falsely, its rate
to identify the transactions in error
falsely will drop significantly.
The ROI increases over time,
which is opposite of the most
tech-technology investments.
So we know that over the time,
with the traditional technology,
servers will go down, the tech-
the technology will go outdated.
But with AI, it will
improves over the time.
So with this-
I want to bring-- There are few future
technologies which I am watching very
closely for the life insurance GL
systems in the next two to three years.
The first one is
blockchain for reinsurance.
So right now, reconciling between
the ceding company and the reinsurer
is one of the most complex and
time-consuming processes in
insurance carriers throughout.
Now, both side maintains their own
records and reconcile periodically.
Blockchain technology could bring both
the sides on the same shared record.
Element-- Eliminating much of
that reconciliation entirely.
It can remove that
reconciliation process entirely.
The other technology which I am looking
at is the natural language processing
So NLP can read and extract the
structured information from documents
like reinsurance treaty language,
actuarial opinion letters, policy
contracts or other-- any other documents.
Instead of reading a human reading
those documents or contracts or manually
entering the key terms into the system,
NLP does it automatically for you.
That's a significant time saver in
the industry that runs on contracts.
The third and another bigger
technology is edge computing.
So edge computing is about
processing transactions closer
to where they are originating.
So for example, at a agency level,
at the point of sale for carriers
with the large field agent networks,
this reduces delays and make a real
time premium processing possible
even in the distributed environments.
So from my perspective, I think
these three upcoming technology
will play a huge role in terms of
general ledger system processing.
So to conclude, at the beginning we
started with a simple question, how
long your month-end close takes?
And with that question we just
walked through the technology that
changes the answer of that question.
So event-driven data processing, machine
learning and continuous reconciliation
that works around the clock, this
time frame can be reduced a lot.
Anomaly detection that
catches the problem early.
Compliance check built
into every transactions.
All of it running together all the time.
The insurance companies that are
investing- in this technology
today are not just becoming more
efficient, they are building a more
confident, a more reliable, or more
auditable financial operations.
That's a competitive advantage,
and it compounds over the time.
So with time, that advantage will
increase, and it will go into multifold.
Thank you so much for your time today.
If you would like to discuss any
of this further, I would love
to continue the conversation.
Thanks again.