Speaker 16: Hi, my name is Pavel Shokhov,
and today we'll talk about building
LLM voice agents for people who don't
trust AI or for those who do trust AI.
First of all, I'm a founding
engineer at Sofi Connect and a
co-founder at DENG Solutions.
Today, we'll mostly talk about
my experience at Sofi Connect and
the stuff that we built there.
So What we wanted to do is to give a,
our users a curated experience, not
just an app with a menu, something
that feels exclusive, personal,
and closer to a concierge service.
And for this, we chose voice
AI as our main feature that we
were building in the dating.
The assumption was that this kind of
interaction could increase retention and
make users more involved in the product.
At the beginning, we had two
options we wanted to test.
It's voice AI inside the app,
the more conventional and common
approach, and voice AI over the phone
Why phone?
The reason we chose phone calls was
based on our target demographic,
which was like 55 plus, 60 plus
years old people in the beginning.
And our assumption was that our
users were already used to the phone
as a calling tool, and it would be
easier to onboard them this way.
They would not need to learn app
mechanics, download anything,
create an account, or go
through registration, et cetera.
They would simply call the number and
they would already be inside the service.
After that, we could call c- call
them back or text them when we needed.
The idea sounded great in theory,
but in practice we faced several
problems So first group of problems
was connected to perception and trust.
Many people do not want to talk to robots.
Many people also do not like the word AI.
For some users, just
knowing that something is AI
already creates resistance.
There were also issues with
accents where speech-to-text could
fail or misunderstand the user.
Another major issue was scam fear.
When someone receives a call from
an unknown number, especially if the
service is new, it can feel easily,
it can easily feel suspicious.
The next group of problems was
connected to unexpected human behavior.
Some users also did not fully
understand what they were talking
to, who they were talking to.
They were talking to AI, and because
of that, they went off script, asking
related questions, shared personal
stories, even some of them started
flirting with the AI and all of these
unexpected interactions cost us money
as we need to continue talking with the
users, but get them back on, on the track.
So we had to introduce some
guardrails for that A very
important thing is designing trust.
The first was the voice.
The voice should be calm,
pleasant, and trustworthy.
We chose a neutral female voice from
the latest ElevenLab models at the
time because they sounded less robotic.
The second thing was giving
the bot a neutral name.
It humanizes the experience,
and we named our bot Sophie.
At the same time, it is important to
say at the beginning that this was AI.
Also it is regulated by certain local
laws in the US, so you had… you have
to tell the user that they are not
talking to to a person at the beginning.
And we worked carefully on the
phrase because the goal was to be
transparent without scaring people away.
We also decided not to have any
visual reference of Sophie anywhere.
If you decide what the assistant should
look like, you may build trust with some
users, but lose others because of their
expectations or their beauty standards.
Think about Siri, Alexa, or
other popular voice assistants.
There is a reason they usually do not
have a human-like visual representation.
Another trust-related detail
is caller identification.
We ask users to add our number
to their contacts so they see who
is calling them or texting them.
We also added calling name presentation
so that when we called users, they
could see who was calling even if
they didn't have us in their contacts.
Finally, memory is extremely important.
We used Memzero for that, and if you
build memory, the bot can talk to the
user based on previous conversations.
That makes a real difference between a
simple script and personalized experience.
For example, when the user can pull up
some some d- some small details from
the old conversations, so the user
feels that the bot remembers some small
personal think about things about them,
and it feels it feels great for anyone
The next thing we had
to work on was scripts.
Every word said to the user should be
thought through and every phase every
phrase should be replayed out loud.
When you look at the phrase in the text,
it may seem short, but when the bot says
it out loud, it can feel much longer.
To reduce off-script dialogues,
you also need a guardrail system.
It should detect when the user
starts talking about something
unrelated and politely bring them
back to the dialogue scenario.
As I said earlier, every off-script
dialogue costs you money, but
you cannot interrupt the person.
You should politely bring them back
Another thing we had to work
on is phone infrastructure.
It's like a second group of problems,
technical problems, while previous ones
were more connected to the product.
These are connected to the tech
issues with using phone calls and
text messages as the primary way
to communicate with the users.
For example, machine answers and voicemail
detection, calls being blocked by
providers, people calling from landline
phones where you cannot send them a text
message back, SMS delivery not being 100%,
not having an app, which means you lose
some control over the user journey, and
of course, the costs that are connected
to using such way of communication.
There are many technical issues
you can face, and first and most
obvious o-of them is latency.
It's a technical challenge, but at
least it has relatively clear solutions.
You can optimize networking, optimize
your code, your database, move your
infrastructure closer to users, use
faster AI providers, and if you can
run speech-to-text models locally,
you should absolutely consider it.
A good benchmark is having end-to-end
latency around 500 to 700 milliseconds.
That is usually sufficient,
and it feels like talking to
a real human over the phone.
This includes VAD detection, then the
LLM starting to stream the answer and the
first text-to-speech audio chunk arriving.
It's all of top all, all on the
top of phone network latency.
But some phone specific
problems are harder to solve.
For example, calls can be blocked by
local providers or you can get sudden
drop-offs and in some cases, there
is not much you can do about it.
One of the most interesting problems
Was machine answer detection.
It's like one of the most
unexpected problems, I would say.
At first, it feels like a problem
that should be easy to solve, but
in practice, you still get mistakes.
When you call a person in the
US, you may reach voicemail.
In our service, it was crucial to
detect voicemail correctly because
undetected voicemail could heavily
influence other people's experience.
In the simplest case, undetected
voicemail is just a loss of money,
but in other cases, it can be a
ruined user journey and just a overall
bad experience and a lost customer.
The easiest solution is to activate
AMD, it's automated machine detection.
It is included in most
telephony providers.
We used Twilio's AMD as Twilio
was our telephony provider.
However, it was not perfect, of course.
So the next layer that
we added was heuristics.
For example, we looked for short phrases
or markers of a machine answer, such
as many numbers being said one after
another, like you're re- you're trying
to reach one, two, three, four, five.
Like when the voicemail system
reads out the phone you have called.
We also looked for phrases like, "You have
called," "You have reached," "Can answer,"
and similar voicemail style phrases.
Then the next layer was
running LLM-based detection.
It was possible only after some period
of time when we have collected a lot
of different examples of the machine
answers, yeah, specific to our users,
so we could build an LLM-based detection
system We also worked a lot on our text
agent and it had its own specifics.
So we had text agent that what,
that, that was talking to the
users over the text messages.
First, every message costs you
money and SMS is charged not
per message, but per segment.
And each each text message
consists of several segments,
like from one to five mostly.
And one segment is around 160 characters.
On top of that, some punctuation
symbols and emojis can take more space
and be counted as several characters.
So while you need to communicate clearly
with the user, you also need to count
every character you use and try not to
use the characters that take too much
characters that take too much space.
Then you need to combine this
with delivery problems because
your delivery rate depends on
whether you include required
phrases like send stop to opt out.
It's required for like normal
delivery so the u- the user can
send you just a message stop and
you stop sending them any new texts.
Also, whether your message looks like
spam and whether it includes content that
may be considered sensitive or toxic.
For dating, which was our industry,
it's especially easy to get flagged.
Another problem was payment links.
We had no app, but we still need
to get payment somehow, and we sent
the payment links by SMS and these
messages had a pretty low delivery
rate and we were fighting with this.
Honestly, it makes sense receiving
app payment links, receiving payment
links by SMS can look very scammy.
So SMS delivery was one of the pains
we had to continuously improve.
We had to rebuild prompts,
rules and guardrails around it.
In more traditional apps, the
paywall is already one of the
biggest drop-off points and teams
spend a lot of time optimizing it.
And now imagine if you get additional
drop-offs just because your
payment message is not delivered
The last major issue is cost.
This is one of the main problems with
this kind of interface because every
interaction costs you money, every
additional minute the user talks, every
message they send, every message you
answer, all of that has a direct cost.
And because phone-based products
have additional drop-offs poi-
drop-off points, blocked calls,
machine answers, failed SMS delivery,
costs can pile up pretty quickly.
Unlike a traditional app where
many interactions are almost free
and the user after the user is
onboarded, with the phone calls and
SMS, every step has a marginal cost.
Overall, I would say that this
was a great experience and a very
interesting product to build.
A phone call can be a powerful
interface, especially for users
who do not want to download
another app or learn a new product.
This can definitely be a differ-
differentiation point, but anyone
who wants to try this should
keep in mind the downsides: trust
issues, perception problems,
infrastructure, SMS delivery, et cetera.
The biggest lesson for me was
that building a voice agent is not
only about making the AI smart,
it is also about making the whole
experience feel trustworthy,
reliable, and natural for the user