Speaker 20: Hi, my name is Sergey.
I'm a senior infrastructure platform
engineer at the Social Discovery Group.
In this talk, I want to look at LLM
workloads from the infrastructure side.
When teams move from experiments
to production, reliability is
no longer only about the model.
It also depends on the
Kubernetes platform.
It depends on how workloads are scheduled,
how traffic moves through the network,
how failure works, and how quickly we
can understand problems under load.
My main point is simple: LLM services
become reliable only when the
platform under them is reliable.
LLM workloads make platform
weaknesses visible faster.
They are different from
typical web services.
A traditional web service
is usually CPU-based.
Requests are short, and it's
often possible to scale the
service by adding more replicas.
LLM service depends on
expensive GPU capacity.
They need a lot of memory, and requests
can run much longer Latency depends
not only on the network or CPU.
It also depends on model size,
prompt length, generated tokens,
batching, and queue time.
So infrastructure mistakes become
more visible, bad scheduling, unstable
networking, or unexpected restarts can
quickly become user visible problems.
Many LLM projects start as experiment.
At that stage, it is normal to run
everything on one node, deploy manually,
and debug problems directly on the server.
But production changes the requirements.
One node is no longer enough.
One network path is no longer enough.
Unexpected restarts become expensive.
Default networking may work,
but when something breaks, it
can be hard to understand where
the traffic actually goes.
The problem is not that Kubernetes
cannot run LLM workloads.
The problem is that production expose
weak assumption in the platform design.
So before looking at the separate
components, let's start this
simple reference arch-architecture.
This is a simplified view of the platform.
A user request enters through gateway API.
Th-then it goes to an LLM
service running on GPU nodes.
The service depends on model
storage or model cache.
The whole path also depends on platform
services, monitoring, CI/CD, networking,
and the Kubernetes control plane.
The important point is that reliability
is not owned by one component.
If gateway API, GPU scheduling, storage,
networking, or secrets are unstable,
the LLM service become unstable too A
reliable LLM workloads need capacity and
redundancy in different failure domains.
Now we move from application
architecture to cluster architecture.
For LLM workloads, failure
domains are very important.
GPU nodes are expensive
and usually limited.
If we lose one node, one switch,
or one rack, we can lose a large
part of available GPU capacity.
The control plane should
be also protected.
etcd needs quorum, so control
plane nodes should be placed in
separate physical failure domains.
For GPU nodes, the goal is to
continue running or rescheduling
workloads with predictable capacity.
This means spreading replicas, avoiding
single network path, and keeping
some spare capacity for failover.
If the control plane is unstable, the
whole platform becomes harder to operate.
The control plane is not used
for every user request, but it's
critical for operating the platform.
If the API server or etcd has problems,
scheduling, reload, and auto-scaling
become unreliable this is especially
important for LLM workloads because
GPU capacity is limited and expensive.
In my preferred design, the Kubernetes
API endpoint uses a virtual IP.
This virtual IP is announced
by BGP Anycast from all
healthy control plane nodes.
It's each node check its local API server.
If the API server is healthy, the
node advertises the virtual IP.
If it's not healthy, the
node removes the route.
So the network sends API
traffic only to healthy nodes.
This gives us active access to Kubernetes
API and simple network level failover.
I also prefer BGP routing to run
on the host, not inside Kubernetes.
The reason is simple.
Kubernetes needs networking to start
pods, so basic networking should
not depends on Kubernetes pods.
For production, the network path
should be visible and predictable.
In many default Kubernetes network
designs, the data path is hidden
behind NAT or overlay encapsulation.
This works, but during incidents it
can make troubleshooting much harder.
We may see node IPs, translated
addresses or encapsulated traffic
instead of the real pod-to-pod flow
In a routable design, pod CIDRs are
known by the data center network.
Traffic flows normal layer 3 routing.
This makes the path easier to
understand with standard tools like
iproute, traceroute, and tcpdump.
For LLM services, this matters because
latency, packet loss, and network
instability can directly affect users.
In this network design, each
Kubernetes node peers with two
top-of-rack switches using BGP.
The node advertises its pod CIDR
into the data center fabric.
Because of this, pod can be routed
dir- directly without overlay or NAT.
ECMP allows both uplinks can
be used at the same time.
This gives us not only redundancy, but
also active-active network capacity.
BFD improves failure detection.
If one link or one switch fails, BFD
helps BGP remove the failed path quickly
instead of waiting for long BGP timers.
I prefer running Bird on the host,
not as a Kubernetes pod, because
routing is part of node bootstrap.
It should not depend on
Kubernetes already being healthy.
GPU nodes should be managed
as a platform infrastructure.
Before we schedule LLM workloads GPU
nodes must be prepared correctly.
It needs the correct NVIDIA driver
container runtime integration
Kubernetes device plugin, node label,
monitoring, and a safe upgrade process.
Kubernetes use device plugins to expose
special hardware like GPUs to the kubelet.
After that, the cluster can expose
GPU resources In practice, many
teams use the GPU NVIDIA operator.
It can manage drivers, the
device plugin, container toolkit,
node labeling, and monitoring.
Kubernetes schedules GPU workloads
only when GPU resources are
explicitly exposed and requested.
Kubernetes doesn't schedule a
pod to a GPU au-automatically.
The GPU must be exposed to Kubernetes,
usually by a device plug, plugin, and
the pod must explicitly request it.
For a simple service, a normal
deployment can be enough.
Each replica request one GPU, and
Kubernetes schedules replicas only
on nodes with available GPU capacity.
For training, fine-tuning, or
batch workloads, a deployment is
usually not the best abstraction.
Jobs or queues are often a better
fit because these workloads
are finite, expensive, and
need controlled concurrency.
The operational point is simple.
GPU capacity should be planned
and scheduled explicitly.
Scheduling policy decides whether
GPU capacity is reliable or fragile.
For GPU workloads, scheduling is
not only about finding any free node
requests, tell Kubernetes how much CPU,
memory, and GPU capacity the pod needs.
Node selectors or affinity help place for
LLM workloads on the correct node pool.
Anti-affinity and topology spread
help avoid putting all replicas
in the same failure domain.
Taint and tolerations are
especially useful for GPU nodes.
They prevent normal workload
from consuming resources
on expensive GPU servers.
At the same time, they allows
approved LLM workloads to run there.
The goal is simple, use GPU
capacity efficiently, but
not create fragile placement.
One node, one rack, or one switch failure
should not take down the whole service.
Reliable reload is part of
reliable infrastructure.
For LLM services, reload
strategy is very important.
A new model version, prompt template,
runtime image, or configuration can
change latency, cost, and error rate.
Gateway API gives us a clean
way to manage external traffic.
With HTTP route, we can split traffic
between two versions of the service.
For example ninety percent of traffic
can stay on stable version, and ten
percent can go to the new version.
If metrics looks good, we
increase the percentage.
If something goes wrong, rollback
can be done by shifting traffic back.
The last point is observability.
For LLM services, it's not enough
to measure only application errors.
We also need to see GPU utilization,
GPU memory, pod scheduling problems,
network behavior, GPU state, API
server latency, and etcd health.
The final checklist is simple.
Make the network path visible, keep
the control plane stable, plan GPU
scheduling, use a safe reload strategy,
and collect metrics before production.
The model is important, but
the platform decides how the
model behaves under failure.
That's it for today.
Thank you for listening.