Hi, I'm Anton Denisov.
I work at the Dwelli.
It's a tech native real estate operator in
the UK where I lead the revenue function
and built our product and data systems.
Today, I'm talking about a
sentiment analysis system that
we build and run in production.
It reads landlord emails and phone calls
and flags the ones where the customer is
unhappy, so we can act before they leave.
I'll cover how we built it, the
data, the model, and what we found
Dwell is a tech native real
estate operator in the UK.
In plain terms, we manage rental
properties end to end on behalf of
the landlords thousands of them on
our own software stack rather than
a traditional high street agency.
This talk is about a system we
built and run in production.
It reads our landlord communications,
emails, and phone calls, and flags the
ones where the landlord is unhappy,
so we can step in before they leave.
I'll walk through how we built it, the
data, the model, the prompt engineering,
which took most of the time and work
we learned running it on real messy
conversations The title promises British
sarcasms, and that's a real problem.
I'll get to it.
The harder question sitting
underneath is the engineering.
How do you build a sentiment system
that actually works when your customers
are real people on the phone who
don't always say what they mean?
Here is a core problem
in a single message.
Our landlord wrote to
us, "No problem at all.
I completely understand your visit.
Whenever you get a chance to look
in the boiler, that would be great.
Thank you so much for all your help."
Run through most of the off-the-shelf
sentiment models, and it scores positive;
no problem, great, thank you so much.
However, i- and it looks
like a happy customer.
That landlord moved their
property to a competitor about two
weeks later after this message.
A generic model would
never have flagged it.
Building something that does
is the subject of this talk.
A bit of context first.
Retention drives the
economics of this business.
A managed property is a multi-year
recurring relationship, and
replacing a lo-lost landlord
costs far more than keeping one.
You are paying acquisition
costs again just to stand still.
One thing surprised us
when we looked closely.
A big part of churn is
unpreventable, though not most of it.
Landlords sell the flat or they
move back in themselves, and for
a real share of cases, nothing we
did would have changed the outcome.
If you're ever handed a reduced churn
target, that's w- worth knowing upfront.
It stop you chasing the wrong number.
But the rest of it, landlords switching
to competitor or deciding to manage
properties themselves, it's service
driven and therefore preventable.
It's also the expensive kind.
It reflects disfact-- dissatisfaction
rather than a live rent.
Those are the people you
actually have a chance to keep.
So the problem wasn't
really measure sentiment.
It was narrower.
Can we detect the preventable
churn early enough to act on it
inside tens of thousands of mostly
ordinary, mostly polite interactions?
The signals we needed were
rare, and they were easy to miss
Standard sentiment analysis,
lexicon scoring, classic fine-tuning
classifiers, NPS surveys, all
rest on the same assumption, that
the strength of the emotion words
track the strength of the feeling.
More terrible, more furious,
more explanation marks, the
more negatives in messages.
British professional communication
doesn't follow that rule.
A lot of complaint here is
expressed by removing the
emotional signal, not adding it.
A few real examples: " I'd have thought
someone would have called me back by
now." That's a complaint. " A little
disappointed with how this was handled."
A little usually means quite a lot.
"When you get a chance" often means
this is urgent and already overdue.
The dissatisfaction is fully
present in all the three.
It just been toned down because
saying it directly would feel rude.
And the keyword model reads every
one of them as neutral or positive.
There is no angry words to catch.
NPS makes it worse, not better.
The people most likely to quietly
leave are exactly the ones who are
too polite to give you a low score.
They give you seven, and
they then don't renew.
There is a second half to this that's easy
to overlook, and it matters just as much.
A large share of the dissatisfaction
wasn't caused by something we did.
It was caused by something we didn't do.
Silence on our side, and landlord
emails that no one replies.
They leave a voicemail, no one calls back.
They chase, and the chase goes unanswered.
From the model's point of view,
that's a hard case because the
triggering event is an absence.
There is no angry message to classify,
just a follow-up that is slightly shorter
or slightly cooler than the last one.
But it was one of the biggest
drivers of churn we had.
People often don't leave because
they got something wrong.
People leave because we went quiet.
So the task was never detect anger.
Anger is the easy case.
It announces itself.
The real task was to detect
dissatisfaction that has been deliberately
understated, and in some cases to
infer it from what wasn't said or what
wasn't done Let me walk you through
the dataset, because this is where
the introduction starts to matter.
We pulled together around eleven
thousand landlord interactions over
about a seven-week window, roughly
two thousand unique landlords.
It spanned four channels, and
the channel mattered a lot, so
these are worth holding onto.
Email through our CRM,
structured and logged.
Email outside the CRM, and landlord
just emails the person directly.
Calls through the CRM, usually
our team calling the landlord.
And an inbound calls outside
the CRM, where the landlord pick
ups up the phone and rings us.
The calls were the most valuable
and the hardest to work with.
About eleven hundred of them
transcribed with Voximplant.
People are more candid on the phone
than in writing, though that's where
a lot of the real signal lived.
But the transcripts are messy:
overlapping speakers, tangents, speech
recognition error, no structure.
If you work with the call
data, you know it's a different
problem from a clean text.
Then labeling, which I which I would
encourage any team to overinvest in.
We did not start by prompting the model.
We started by reading.
We hand-labeled around two hundred
borderline negative cases from the
actual transcripts, and we wrote
label definitions as explicit
decision rules, not judgment calls.
The schema had three axes: severity,
four levels, green, amber, orange,
red; topic, maintenance, payments,
move-out, compliance, seven find
or other; and intent, about ten
categories, and this is where most
of the value was: communication,
failure, self-management, signal,
decision, dispute, et cetera, et cetera.
The severity rules were
deliberately mechanical.
Amber need an explicit signal.
Orange need two independent strong signal.
Red needs literal termination language.
We wrote them that a way for a
reason-- that way for a reason.
So two different people would land on
the same label and saw the model would
match the humans rather than drift.
That hand label set did double duty.
It was both our evaluation benchmark
and our source of few short examples
We used this language model, a large
language model, Cloth Sonnet, and the most
important design decision was to make it
as two-step pipeline rather than one shot.
Step one is narrow.
Is this message negative at all?
A three-way call: positive,
neutral, negative, nothing else.
Step two runs only on the message
that come back negative, about
six or seven percent of the total.
On those and only on those, we extract
the full structure, severity topic
intent, and the routing decision.
There are two reason to this matters.
The first is the cost and latency.
Step two is expensive reasoning,
and you run on seven percent of
the volume instead of all of it.
The whole pipeline came in
around a third cent per message.
The re- the second
reason is more important.
Splitting the steps let us tune
recall on direction separately
from precision of classification.
Those are different objectives.
Trying to hit both in a
single prompt made both worse.
Once they were separate, we could make
the detector deliberately sensitive
by store catching the quiet, polite
cases, while keeping the severity
classifier conservative, so it doesn't
turn every mild grumble into the red
alert Then the prompt engineering,
where the real interaction went.
Three problems worth naming
because I suspect they generalize.
One, the model rewi-rewarded politeness.
Out of the box, it did exactly
what the keyword models do.
They saw lovely, thank you so
much, and scored it positive.
The fix was to tell it to treat
the courtesy as a wrapping and
classify on the substance underneath.
What is this person actually asking for?
How many times have
they had to ask for it?
Is the politeness covering frustration?
Then we fed in the hand-labeled
polite but negative case a few
short anchors, concrete examples
of sounds nice is not nice.
That only… That one change moved the
results from anything else we did…
more than anything else we did.
Two, problem number
two, it over-escalated.
A sensitive detector wants to label
everything orange, so it pushed the
strict rules straight into the prompt.
Orange requires two strong signals.
Red requires explicit language
and nothing else, nothing less.
Severity became a checklist,
not a feeling, and the
false red largely went away.
Three, telling went in apart from blame.
Landlords would call up annoyed about a
tenant or a contractor or some external
mess and explicitly not blame us.
I know it's not your fault.
A naive classifier reads a negative
tone and routes it to a ser-service
failure, and a manager spends
their afternoon apologizing for
something they did not cause.
So external issue became its own
intent, and the prompt had to separate
two things that look identical to
a keyword model, the tone of the
message and who it's aimed it at.
Negative but not at us is a
completely different action.
On the production side, none of
these were one-off batch job.
Emails streamed in from BigQuery, calls
came through Voximplant translation,
the models scored continuously, and
the scores were written back into the
warehouse for the rest of the business
to use So what were the key findings?
First, people are more guarded in
writing and more direct on the phone.
Calls ran meaningfully more negative
than email in order of 50% more.
Second, and no survey tool can do this,
switching channels is a leading indicator.
When a landlord who'd been emailing
us suddenly starts phoning,
escalation usually follows.
The switch itself is a signal.
Third, communication failure was
the single largest category, about
36% of all negative interactions.
Not maintenance, not money, not
being able to reach a human.
More than a third of neg- every negative
case reduced to, "I tried to contact
you, nothing happened." Fourth, the
polite customer point, now with numbers.
We match the sentiment data against
the landlords who actually left.
The ones who left to sell
ran around 4% negativity.
The ones who switched to a competitor,
the preventable, expensive chore, ran
several times higher But here's what
matters for how you build the model.
They didn't express it by shouting.
They expressed it by in measured,
polite, slightly formal language.
And the fifth, the more data
sources mean b- better output.
One agency looked like the top
performer, very low negativity, about 4%.
Then we checked the pipeline.
We were only capturing a small
fraction of that agency calls.
Most of its phone conversation
were not reaching the model at all.
Once the call feed was complete,
the number fell right in
line with everyone else's.
So the point is simple.
The quality of the output is
bounded by the coverage of the input
Detection on its own doesn't do much.
A classifier that produces a
dashboard nobody acts is just
a report with extra steps.
So each intent mapped it to a
defined action, what an owner and
response time agreed in advance
with the people who'd carry it out.
Communication failure, a manager
calls within twenty-four hours.
A self-management signal, a personal
call, a conversation about the value, not
specific repair, et cetera, et cetera.
The cleanest example of the loop closing,
once we quantified that communication
fai-failure was the single biggest
driver, chasing landlords one by
one was obviously treating symptoms.
The cause was structural.
We were not answering
the call, phone reliably.
So the finding led directly to a second
build, an agentic voice assistant
to handle inbound landlord calls.
The detection system didn't just flag
the problems, it told us what to build
next with the volume data to justify
let me pull together the lessons.
I think generalize whatever
you're classifying.
One don't reach out for
off-the-shelf sentiment.
Two, split the problem.
Achieve sensitive detector first,
expensive structured classification
only when, what it, on what it flags.
Three, put your effort into
labeling at prompts, not the model.
Four, detection is
worthless without action.
Map every category to an
owner and the response time.
Five, coverage bounds quality.
Feed feed it every channel you
have or your confident-looking
output is quietly wrong.
Do those five things, and the British
sarcasm problem is a little title stop
speed courtesy, and it becomes something
you can actually catch in production
early enough to keep the customer.
Thank you.