Hello everyone and welcome
to CON42 LLMs 2026.
My name is Petros Bazdaras, and today
we are going to confront a fundamental
shift happening right under our noses
in the software engineering landscape.
The title of my talk is Reading is the
New Writing: Why the AI Era Demands
Absolute Mastery of the Basics.
Let's dive straight in.
We are living in an era where raw code
syntax has become an absolute commodity.
What used to take hours now takes seconds.
But make no mistake, the engineering
bar has not lowered, it has risen.
Think about the workflow before AI.
Developers spent hours writing
boilerplate, managing scaffolding,
and repeating design patterns.
Back then, output was a
decent proxy for skill.
Now, it takes seconds to write a
prompt, and the LLM generates the code.
But the real work begins exactly
when the model stops typing.
Raw coding output is no longer
the metric of a software engineer.
This paradigm shift has brought
a dangerous industry-wide
threat, the black box, and a
massive delusion of productivity.
We frequently mistake compiled
and working for good engineering.
And let's be honest, shipping code
you didn't write and fully don't
understand is a liability, not a win.
This manifests in two major ways.
First being cargo culting AI output,
accepting patterns that look completely
right on the surface but embed subtle
anti-patterns, deep security gaps or
highly inefficient logic underneath.
Second, blind trust at scale.
Every accepted suggestion blindly
compounds technical debt you didn't
choose and may not even see until it
breaks in production As developers in
2026, we now spend roughly ninety percent
of our time auditing, debugging, and
maintaining what the model generated.
Reading code has officially become
the primary engineering act.
Right now, the industry is
split into two behaviors.
First, we have skim and accept.
The generated code looks correct at a
glance, so a developer clicks Merge.
This is exactly how hidden
assumptions, edge cases, and so
bugs slip straight into production.
We have to move to the second
approach: read and verify.
This means tracing the logic line by
line, actively testing the behavior,
questioning the output, and deeply
understanding the trade-offs.
Because the hard truth is
right there in the yellow box.
If you can't understand the code deeply
enough to catch what the LLM missed,
whether that's security flaws, performance
issues, or architectural misalignment,
you cannot responsibly own the code base.
The LLM writes, you must understand,
validate, and own every single line
that ships This brings us to core
argument one, the autopsy problem.
When the system inevitably fails
under heavy load, you're performing
an autopsy on logic you didn't write.
Relying blindly on probabilistic
code generation completely
bypasses the developer's internal
mental mode of the system.
Because you didn't actively
architect it, the intuition for
debugging is entirely absent.
These systems fail unexpectedly.
Edge cases, race conditions,
and resource leaks only surface
in production under real load.
And remember, the on-call pager doesn't
care who or what wrote the code.
The incident report has your name on it.
You own the outcome.
We must remember what LLMs actually are.
They are pattern matchers, not engineers.
They lack contextual empathy for
your system's long-term trajectory.
Without a human guardrail, subtle security
vulnerabilities slip through undetected.
Outdated library versions or depreciated
APIs are introduced, and algorithmically
inefficient logic scales poorly.
They have zero awareness of your specific
team's architectural constraints.
This is why human intervention
is vital across three pillars:
security, performance, and context.
Foundational mastery is the
ultimate filter that catches
exactly what the model misses.
So how do we define the basics
in an AI-dominated world?
It's not about memorizing syntax anymore.
It's about the computer science bedrock
that lets you evaluate any code,
regardless of who or what wrote it.
This bedrock relies on three core pillars.
First, data structures and
algorithmic complexity understanding,
Otrade-offs, memory layout,
and why they matter at scale.
Second, concurrency and memory
management, catching the race conditions,
deadlocks, and garbage collection
issues that LLMs notoriously introduce.
And third, system design and secure
coding, architectural reasoning, threat
modeling, and the engineering principles
that outlast any trendy framework.
Using AI to escape learning the
fundamentals doesn't make you faster.
It makes you entirely dependent.
Problem-solving is a cognitive muscle.
Stop exercising it, and it weakens.
Look at the fork in the road.
On one hand, you have blind reliance,
skipping fundamentals, accepting
all suggestions, and ending up
unable to debug generated code while
accumulating massive technical debt.
On the other, you have AI-assisted
mastery, applying CS fundamentals to
order every output, catching errors early,
and building truly maintainable systems.
The real risk of blind reliance
is a severely weakened debugging
intuition, an inability to reason
about unfamiliar code, and a growing
critical dependency on the tool.
The career path for software
engineering has fundamentally shifted.
We are moving from code
typists to system reviewers.
AI amplifies leverage, but only
for those who already know how
to code exceptionally well.
Our role now mirrors that
of a managing editor.
We must order every line the model
produces with a critical informed eye.
We must secure systems by applying
the security fundamentals the
model doesn't inherently possess.
And we must scale architectures
that hold up under real-world load
because we understand why they work.
AI does not replace the
need to know fundamentals.
It makes knowing them your
primary differentiator.
To close things out, I want to leave
you with this final call to action.
Don't just use AI to write faster.
Use your mastery to audit,
secure, and scale better.
Reading code is officially the
highest leverage skill in the AI era.
Master it.
Thank you so much for your time.
Let's connect on LinkedIn.
My name is Patches Bazdres,
and enjoy the rest of Conf
forty-two LLMs twenty twenty-six.