Speaker 25: Hello, everyone.
My name is Varsha Shah.
I'm an enterprise technical
architect at Tata Consultancy
Services working for Microsoft.
I'm focused on AI-driven compliance,
automation, intelligence, governance
platform, enterprise-scale
risk management solutions.
Over the past several years, I have worked
on designing and delivering the enterprise
platform, supporting payroll compliances,
employment tax monitoring, procurement
control, audit automation, policy
governance, and financial risk management
across the global organizations.
One observation I have consistently
seen across the organizations is
that they are surrounded by data, yet
they continue to struggle with the
compliance violations, audit findings,
increasingly sophisticated fraud schemes.
Why does this happen?
The problem is not lack of information.
Organizations today generate
enormous amount of data.
Every payroll transaction, tax
filing, procurement request, vendor
payment, financial adjustment
leaves behind a digital footprint
Payroll system know one part of the
story, tax system knows another.
Procurement and financial
system know something else.
Yet this system often
operates in isolation.
The reality is that modern compliance
risk rarely exist within a single
document or a single system.
They emerge across multiple data sets.
The payroll record may
look perfectly valid.
The tax filing may look perfectly valid.
The procurement transaction may look
perfectly completely normal for us.
But when these records are connected
together, they can reveal a hidden
compliance risk that no traditional
system would have detected.
That observation ultimately inspired the
work I am going to share with you today.
Today, I'll share how the large
language models, graph intelligence,
and probabilistic reasoning can help
organizations move beyond the traditional
compliance monitoring and towards the
predictive compliance intelligence
or proactive compliance intelligence.
My goal is not only to show you how
the technology works, but also why
this approach represents a significant
shift in how enterprise will emerge the
risk and compliance in upcoming years.
With that, let's begin.
So before we dive in, let me
briefly outline the journey
we are going to take today.
We will start by looking at the compliance
challenge facing modern enterprise and
why traditional rule-based approach are
increasingly struggling to keep the pace.
We will then explore a three-component
AI architecture that combines the graph
intelligence, probabilistic risk modeling,
and jurisdictional-aware normalization
to create the compliance intelligence.
Next, we will walk through a practical
compliance scenario and examine the role
of the large language model plays in
understanding the context, connecting
the information, and generating
the explainable insight out of it.
Finally, we will review the results,
discuss the deployment consideration,
and explain how the organizations
can move from reactive compliance
monitoring to preact prod proactive or
the predictive compliance intelligence.
With that content, let's begin
by understanding the challenge
we are trying to solve here.
So enterprise compliance has
become the significant more
complex over the last decade.
Organizations today operate across
multiple jurisdictions, regulatory
framework, and business system while
processing millions of records every year.
The challenge is not lack of data.
In fact, most organizations
have more data than ever before.
The challenge is that
information exists in silos.
Payroll system contains one view of the
business, the tax system have another.
The procurement and financial system
contain additional piece of this puzzle.
Unfortunately, the compliance risk rarely
exists within a single document or system.
They often emerge across
the multiple datasets.
A payroll record may appear correct, a tax
filing may appear correct, a procurement
transaction may appear normal to us.
But when those records are
connected together, they can
reveal hidden compliance issue
that would have gone undetected.
The problem is no longer collecting data.
The problem is connecting
data and transforming it
into actionable intelligence.
And that's exactly what traditional
approach begin to fall short.
So how have organizations traditionally
tried to solve this challenge?
For many years, the answer was
rule-based compliance system.
But as we will see next, the
approach is reaching to its limits.
So for many years, the organizations
relied on rule-based compliance system,
and those system provided significant
value by automating repetitive checks
and enforcing the standardized controls.
However, today's compliance
environment is far more complex.
Traditional system operates
on predefined logic.
If threshold is exceeded,
generate a alert.
If the filing is late, generate a alert.
If the policy is violated,
generate a alert.
The challenge is that modern
compliance risk rarely appear within
a single transaction or document.
They often emerge across multiple
system and business processes.
This creates three key limitations.
First is limited cross-document reasoning.
Rule engines struggle to connect
information across the payroll, tax,
procurement, and financial systems here.
Second is high false positive rates.
Compliance teams often spend valuable
time investigating alerts that turns
out to be legitimate business activity.
Third is the static lo--
static rule or logics.
Rule do not learn.
They do not adapt or evolve.
Fraud patterns and regulatory
requirements are changing.
So rules are effective at finding the
known problems, but identifying the
hidden relationship emerging the risk
required a different approach, and
that's where the AI-driven compliance
intelligence begins to create value.
So if traditional rule-based system
are reaching to their limit, what kind
of architecture is needed to address
the modern compliance challenge?
Let me introduce you to the framework
So we have discussed the problem and
limitation of the traditional approaches.
The next question become is what
kind of architecture is required
to solve this kind of problem?
The framework is built around
three simple questions.
First is what is connected?
Second one is what is risky?
And third one is what does the
risk mean within the specific
regulatory environment?
These questions directly map to the
three components of this architecture.
The first component is graph-based
entity correlation engine.
Its role is to connect the information
across the payroll, tax, procurement,
and financial system and creating a
unified view of enterprise activity.
The second component is the
adaptive probabilistic risk model.
Once the relationship are identified, this
layer determines which pattern actually
represent meaningful compliance risk
and prioritize them for investigation.
The third component is the
jurisdictional normalization layer.
This layer provides regulatory context
by aligning the currencies, tax code,
reporting requirements, and the compliance
frameworks across the jurisdictions.
Individually, each
component provide value.
Together, they transform the
disconnected enterprise records into
actionable compliance intelligence.
Instead of asking whether a single
document compliant or not, we begin to
ask much more powerful question here.
What does the collective evidence
across the enterprise tell
us about the compliance risk?
And that's the f-foundation
of the framework I'll walk you
through in the next few sl-slides.
Now that we have seen the architecture
at the high level, let's follow
the journey of enterprise data
and as it moves through the entire
compliance intelligence pipeline.
So the process begins with the
enterprise data from payroll
system, tax filing, procurement
platform, and financial transaction.
The records are ingested, validated,
standardized to create the
consistent foundation for analysis.
Next, the entity correlation layer
connects the information across the
system, creates the relationship
between employees, vendor, transaction
filing, and other business entities.
Once those relationships are there,
the risk model evaluates the signal
and determines which patterns
represent meaningful compliance risk.
Those findings are then passed
through the normalization layer,
where they are interpreted within the
context of applicable jurisdictional
regulation and reporting requirements.
At this stage, the large language
model helps providing the context,
explanation, and human rele-readable
insights that supports the auditors,
investigators, and the compliance teams.
Finally, the intelligence is delivered
through the alert dashboard reporting
and investigation of the workflows.
Perhaps the most important aspect of
this process is the feedback loop.
Every audit outcome and investigation
result helps refine the future risk
assessment, enabling the system
to continue improve over the time.
What starts as a raw enterprise
data ultimately becomes actionable
compliance intelligence.
We have now seen how information
flown through the system.
Let's take a closer look at how these
three components work together to
create the compliance intelligence.
So many organization invest in individual
technologies, a graph database, a machine
learning model or LLM, and expect that
the intelligence emerge automatically.
In reality, intelligence
come from orchestration.
The graph-based entity correlation
engine create a context by creating
the information across the system
and revealing the relationship
that would otherwise remain hidden.
The adaptive probabilistic risk model then
evaluates those relationship and determine
which pattern deserves attention.
Rather than relying on the single
anomaly, it combines multiple signals to
prioritize the highest risk ca-cases here.
Finally, the jurisdictional
normalization layer provides a
regulatory context, ensuring that the
risks are interpreted consistently
across the different countries' tax
structure compliance frameworks.
What important is that these components
are not operating independently.
Relationship intelligence
feeds the risk assessment.
Risk assessment feeds the regulatory
interpretation, and the audit
outcomes continuously improve all
three layers through the feedback.
In other word, this is
not a linear process.
It is a continuous intelligence
loop that becomes more
effective over, over the time.
The result is greater visibility,
better prioritization, and ultimately
better compliance decision.
Everything we have discussed so far
has focused on how the system works.
The next question is that every
executive gonna ask is: What
business value does this create?
So the organization doesn't inv-- the
organization actually doesn't invest
into AI because it's innovative.
They invest in AI because it
helps reduce the risk, improve the
efficiency, and enable better decisions.
The first benefit is
earlier risk detection.
By correlating information across
multiple system, organization can identify
compliance issues before they become
audit findings or re-regulatory events.
The second benefit is end-to-end
compliance visibility.
Instead of monitoring payroll tax
procurement activities independently,
organizations gains a connected view of
the compliance risk across the enterprise.
For global organizations, other
major advantage is consistency.
The normalization layer helps
apply a common compliance framework
across jurisdictions, reduce
manual reconciliation or improving
the regulatory alignments.
The framework also improves the audit
readiness by providing the connected
evidence, contextual explanation,
and audit-ready reporting here.
And finally, it helps investigator
to focus on the risk that
actually matters the most.
Rather than reviewing thousands
of low-value alerts, team can
prioritize case by case with the
highest genuine compliance exposures.
Ultimately, this architecture
help shifting the compliance from
reactive reporting function to
proactive intelligence capability.
To make this more tangible, let's walk
through a practical example and see how
the co-- how this component works together
to uncover compliance risk that would
remain hidden in the traditional system.
So imagine an employee who recently
moved to a different jurisdiction.
The HR system correctly records the
new work location of the employee.
The payroll system correctly process
the empl-- employee's compensation,
and the tax filing system submits
the required filing as well.
If we look at each system
independently, they are perfect.
No alerts, no error, no obvious issues.
However, when the AI correlation engine
connects those records together and
the different pictures bring to us,
the employee's new location place them
under the different tax jurisdiction
with the different reporting requirement
and filing deadlines Although the
payroll record is correct, the fi-- tax
filing was submitted, and the filing
was based on the previous location of
the employees and not the current one.
What appeared compliant is isolation
now become a potential compliance
exposure, and that's the key insight.
The organization did not lack the data,
the organization lacked correlation.
The information already existed,
the intelligence was not.
The framework identifies the relationship,
evaluates the risk, applies the correct
regulatory context, and generates a clear
explainable investigation to the auditors.
This exactly the type of hidden
compliance risk that traditional
document-level system often misses.
Everything in this example started
with one capability, the ability to
connect information across the system.
Let's take a closer look at the first
component that makes the… that
makes it very much possible, the
graph-based entity correlation engine.
The first component of the framework is
the graph-based entity correlation engine.
The purpose is very simple: to create
a connected view of the enterprise.
Most organizations store the
information across the multiple system.
Payroll system knows employees,
procurement knows vendors,
financial system knows transaction,
tax system knows filings.
Each system contains the part of
the story, but no single system
contains the complete picture of this.
The correlation engine connects
these pictures together.
It links the employees to payroll
record, payroll to tax filing, vendors to
procurement activities, and transaction
to broader business processes here.
As these relationships are established,
pattern begins to emerge that would
be difficult to identify through
the document-level analysis alone.
This is particularly valuable when
the investigation complex compliance
issues, fraud patterns, or the hidden
relationship across the multiple system.
Large language model further enhance
this process by helping resolve the
ambiguous references and connecting
related entities that may appear
different across the documents.
Ultimately, this component provides
the foundation for everything that
follows Because before we can determine
whether something is risky, we first
need to understand how it is connected.
Once those relationships are established,
the next challenge become prioritization.
Not every relationship
represent a compliance risk.
So how do we determine
which ones actually matters?
Let's see the next component So the
large enterprise generates the thousands
of signals and anomalies every day.
The reality is that the compliance teams
cannot investigate each and every of that.
The objective is not
finding every anomaly.
The objective is identifying
the anomalies that represents
the highest compliance exposure.
This is where the adaptive probabilistic
risk model comes into picture.
Unlike traditional rule-based
system that rely on binary, either
it's fail or pass, the model
evaluates multiple signals together.
So let's take a example Unusual
transaction pattern jurisdictional
inconsistency, entity relationship,
historic behavior, and the prior audits
are the well, well-known examples of this.
Individually, these signals may indicate
a problem, but when combined, they can
reveal a meaningful risk pattern here.
The model then assigns a confidence
based on the risk score, helping
the investigator to focus on
highest risk priority cases first.
Perhaps the most important
capability is continuous learning.
Every audit outcome and investigation
results provide the feedback that helps
improve the further risk assessment.
As a result, the system becomes
more accurate over the time.
The goal is not to generate
more and more alerts.
The goal is to generate better decisions.
At this stage, we know what is connected,
and we know what appears risky.
But the-- but then there is the only final
challenge is understanding what that risk
really meaning-- meaningful within the
regulatory environment where it is occurs.
So at this the next challenge is
understanding what that risk mean within
the appropriate regulatory context.
Large organizations operates across
the multiple countries, currencies, tax
structure, and reporting frameworks.
As a result, the same transaction
can have a different compliance
implication depending on where it occurs.
Without normalization, organizations
often struggle with the inconsistent
interpretation, manual reconciliation,
fragmented compliance reporting.
The purpose of the jurisdictional
normalization layer is to
solve this kind of problem.
It standardize the currencies, align
the tax codes, maps the regulatory
requirement, creates a common compliance
framework across the ju-jurisdictions.
Think of it as a transaction layer
for the compliance intelligence.
It ensure that risky that risk
identified in different regions can
be evaluated and cons- consistently
and compared meaningfully.
This is especially important for multiple
organization that needs a unified view of
the compliance risk across the enterprise.
Risk across the enterprise.
Because identifying risk is valuable,
but understanding the risk within the
correct regulatory context is what
enables informed decision-making We
have now explained the three core
component of this framework, but
there is one capability that enhances
all three layers simultaneously.
That is nothing but large language models.
Let's take a look at the role they
play in the transforming data into
explainable compliance intelligence.
So throughout the presentation, we
have discussed graph intelligence, risk
modeling, regulatory normalization.
Now let's talk about technology
that enhances all three layers.
That is large language models.
When most people think about large
language model, they think about
chatbots and content generation.
But in the enterprise environments, their
value goes far beyond conversations.
In this framework, LLMs are not
being used as a user interface.
They're being used as reasoning layer.
Traditional system work well with the
structured data such as transaction
dates, identifier, financial records.
However, the c-compliance
investigations also evolves contract
policy, document, audit notes,
regulatory guidance, and other type
of unstructured information as well.
Historically, much of this information
was difficult to analyze at the scale.
The LM-- LLM here changes that.
They help understand the context,
connect the related information
across the documents, resolve the
ambigu-ambiguity which is happening,
and generates the clear explanation
for auditors and the compliance teams.
Perhaps their most important
contribution is explainability.
Finding a risk is valuable.
Explainability-- E-explaining why
that risk exists is essential.
By transforming the technical signals
into human-readable insights, LLM
helps bridging the gap between the
data and the decision-making here.
In other words, the LLM is not
replacing compliance expertise.
It amplifies the compliance intelligence.
Of course, any architecture is only as
valuable as its real-world performance.
So the question become is: How well
does this framework perform when
applies to the enterprise-scale data?
Before discussing the result,
it's important to understand the
evaluation of the environment.
The framework was tested using
approximately three millions of records
spanning payroll, tax, procurement,
and transactional datasets here.
The evaluation covered four jurisdictional
and five years of historic data,
reflecting the complexity typically
seen in large enterprise environments.
The objective was not simply to
test the individual components.
It was to evaluate how the architecture
performs when dealing with the large
volumes of interconnected data,
diverse regulatory requirements,
and real-world compliance scenarios.
Importantly, the dataset include both
the structured and un- unstructured
information here, allowing us
to access not only the detection
capability, but also contributing of
the large language models in providing
the context and explainability.
In short, the
goal was to determine whether
this approach could generate
meaningful compliance intelligence
or not at the enterprise scale.
With that context established, let's
look at the outcome and more importantly,
what those outcome means from a
compliance and the business perspective.
So now let's look at the results.
While metrics such as precision and
recall are important, they are not
they are not the outcome that matters
the most to the compliance team.
Compliance team are cared about
reducing risk, improving efficiency,
focusing on resources where
they create the greatest impact.
The first result was stronger detection
across the multiple boundaries.
The framework was able to identify risk
pattern that only become visible when
the information from the multiple system
was connected and analyzed together.
The second result was
reduction in false positive.
This is significant because compliance
team often spend a considerable amount of
time reviewing the alert that ultimately
represent a legitimate business activity.
By incorporating relationship
intelligence, contextual analysis,
and probabilistic score, the framework
improving signal quality and reducing
the unnecessary investigations here.
The third result was reduced
audience effort audience or
audience the auditor efforts here.
So providing connected evidence and
explaining explainable insight helpful
auditors and investigators spread
less time gathering the information
and more time making the decisions.
So less time gathering the information and
more time making the decisions, that means
they can evaluate more and more audits.
Ultimately, the value of the framework
is not simply that it finds more
anomalies it's that it helps the
organization focus on anomalies that
matters the most for the organization.
When we step back and look at the outcome
together, a larger trend becomes clearer.
This isn't just about improving
compliance monitoring.
It's about fundamentally changing
how compliance is performed.
So when we step back and look
everything we have discussed so
far, a large shift become visible.
For decades, compliance has
largely been a reactive function.
A transaction occurs, a filing is
submitted, an audit takes place, and
then only a potential risk is identified.
AI is changing that kind of model now.
By continuously connecting information
across the system, learning from outcomes,
identifying the emerging patterns,
organization can begin detecting the
risk at much earlier in the process.
Instead of asking what went wrong,
organizations started asking,
what is likely to go wrong next?
And that's the fundamental shift.
The goal is no longer simply to
monitor the compliance activities.
The goal is to anticipate risk,
prioritize actions, and make more
informed decision before issue
becomes the regulatory events here.
In many ways, this is different
this is this is difference between
the compliance system and the
compliance intelligence system here.
One records one records what happened
and the other helps organization
understand what may happen next.
And I believe this shifts from reactive to
more of a proactive compliance, represent
one of the most important opportunity
for AI in enterprise risk management.
Of course, realizing that vision
require more than just a technology.
Enterprise deployment brings
important consideration around the
scalability, governance, and trust here.
Before organization can realize the
full value of the AI-driven compliance,
there are several important deployment
consideration they have to make.
First is scalability.
Enterprise environments process
millions of records across the
multiple system, so the architecture
must scale without sacrificing on the
performance or accuracy of the system.
Second is governance and data privacy.
Compliance platform often handles
sensitive financial and employee
data, making security, access
control, and regulatory compliance
critical requirements of this system.
Third is explainability.
Auditor, investigator, and regulators need
to understand why a risk was identified,
not just that it was identified.
Ultimately, successful enterprise
adap-adoption requires balancing
the innovation with the trust
because the goal is not simply
to build an intelligent system.
The goal is to build an intelligent
system that organization can actually
trust, govern, and scale with.
And while these opportunities
are sig-significant, it's equally
important to recognize the
challenge that the organization
must address when applying the AI in
high-stake compliance environments.
While the opportunity are significant,
it's important to recognize that
no AI system is without challenges.
A consideration is LLM hallucination.
In compliance environment, find
findings must always be grounded
in verified evidences and not rely
solely on the generated outputs.
Another challenge is data
quality and system heterogeneity.
So enterprise data often exist across
the legacy system with inconsistent
formats and varying the levels of quality.
Finally, the regul-- the regulations
continue to evolve and compliance
framework, reporting requirements, and
regulatory expectations change over
the time, requiring organizations to
continuously adapt with this For this
reason, AI should not be viewed as a
replacement for compliance expertise.
It should be viewed as a force
multiplier that helps the compliance
professional process the complex
complexity, identifying the patterns,
making the better-informed decision.
Ultimately, the most successful
implementation will combine the human
expertise with the machine intelligence.
So as we conclude, I would like
to leave you with the three key
takeaways that summarize the central
message of this presentation.
The first one is the compliance
risk increasingly exist between
the data sets, not within them.
The most significant risk often emerge
within the information from the payroll,
tax procurement, and the financial system
is connected and analyzed together.
The second one is the large language model
create the value far beyond automation.
Their ability to understand context,
connect the information, and explain
the complex finding, making them
powerful reasoning layer within
enterprise compliance system.
And the third one is the compliance
is evolving from the reactive
function into more of a proactive or
predictive intelligence capability.
By combining graph intelligence,
probabilistic reasoning, regulatory
context, and the large language model
organizations can more, move beyond
monitoring what happens and begin
anticipating what may happen next.
Ultimately, the goal is not simply
to process more and more data.
It's to transform the disconnected
enterprise information into the
actionable, explainable, and
predictive compliance intelligence.
Thank you for your time today.
I appreciate your attention and
look forward for your questions.
Please feel free to reach out
to me with your questions and
your enthusiasm on this email.
You can connect with me on my LinkedIn.
I'm happy to help if you are
building or trying to transform
compliance system using AI.
You know where to find me now.
Before I close, I would like to sincerely
thank to Conference Forty Two team for
providing this wonderful opportunity
to share my work and engage with such a
talented global technical community here.
Thank you all again,
and see you next time.