Hello everyone.
I am excited to be here today
at 42 to talk about something
that affects all of us, how AI
is changing our work and skills.
AI coding assistant, Chachi, pt,
GitHub copilot, cursor winder.
They have made our development faster and
easier, but they bring real challenges.
So we need to ensure that as AI
takes over repetitive tasks, we
don't lose our ability to think.
Critically or creatively and to
be en to ensure that if we are the
ones that are solving the problem.
So that's exactly what we
are going to explore today.
So let's get started.
AI makes coding easier, let's be honest,
but it can also make us mentally lazy
if you are not really careful about it.
So there is something called
metacognitive laziness.
It happens when we rely too much
on something, in this case, ai,
and we stop thinking critically
and engaging with our work.
So this is actually an issue I. And,
researcher learned about, something
called ai, chatbot induced cognitive
therapy or short for ai, C-C-I-C-A.
This is where developers, lose their
critical thinking skills over the time.
So it's not just on a
day, but over the time.
Just like muscle, we can without
exercise our coding and problem
solving skills deteriorate when
AI does all the work for us.
Another big problem in addition to
laziness would be skill degradation with
AI providing instant answers would skip.
The why and the how of coding, which
is very important in learning process.
beginners in particular would
risk developing a shallow
grasp of programming concept.
Debugging is another issue.
AI often finds and fixes the
bugs, especially with the new
tools such as windsurf and cursor.
So this means developers do not get
their hands on practice like they
used to, and, they wouldn't have
the tendency to improve themselves.
So over the time, I believe our
mental muscle memory would be getting
weaker and weaker, and it would
make really hard for us to solve
complex problems independently.
So a real world studies are
already showing skill degradation.
this is due to the AI reliance.
So think of yourself, how often.
Do you use chat g pt? three years
ago we're using any tool, AI tool,
maybe other than Grammarly to check
your grammar or something like that.
So as a new modern individuals,
we are getting more reliant on ai.
So actually a study found.
That nearly 69%, students reported
laziness and, 27 lost their decision
making skills because of ai.
So experts have drawn.
Pilots to aviation because when pilots
rely too much on, autopilot, their ability
to fly manually, fly a airplane or any
sort of aircraft such as, helicopter,
it would decline significantly.
So the same could happen to,
developers and engineers.
If we led AI to thinking for us, and
we would be just, Additional tool
for the AI to handle the system.
So how do we combat this?
One solution is to build a culture
of, continuous learning, which is
very important on individual level.
many companies provide
e-learning platforms.
And sponsors professional certifications.
And another one would be knowledge
sharing, like tech talks,
forums, would help developers
keep learning from each other.
And, another one would
be like, something like.
hacker rank, which is a platform
or lead code, which would allow our
developers to practice real world
coding challenges and stay sharp.
this is just for developers, right?
But think of AI engineers.
We don't have to many provide coding.
We can provide different questions where
they would actually go and, practice or
do their best or challenge themselves.
In this case, hacker rank and
lead code would be suitable,
for example, developers.
another effective strategy is focusing
on hands-on projects that would
push developers to think critically.
passion projects, r and d prototypes
and internal coding competitions.
These would keep developers
actively engaged.
So hackathons, are great way to
force developers and not only
developers who are going and attending
as, a team, but also as a judge.
It would, encourage them to solve unique,
challenges or observe people who are,
solving unique challenges and judge
them and learn from their, practices.
And, someone who's joining, hackathons.
I believe the individual would be
under the pressure and they would
practice working on under the pressure.
So it is very valuable.
The key takeaway is that we
are learning by doing, right?
So it is a best way to maintain,
unless, in the future we're gonna
have chip in our head, we are
gonna just install the information.
But at this stage, learning by
doing, is the best, follow of us.
Now one of the best ways to keep
developers sharp is, mentorship
and collaborative, work.
It can be coding, it can be brainstorming.
So when experienced developer guide
a junior through problem solving,
both part would be learning.
a way, person who is, for example, a
senior developer, they would, revisit
their knowledge and at the same time,
a junior would be learning from the,
team member and try to understand what
are the best practices in terms of.
Coding or programming or in, in
terms of architectural decisions.
For example, in pair programming,
one person would question the AI
generate code and that would lead
to a deeper discussion in team.
Another one would be, code reviews.
If code reviews, require developers,
either if the individual is a junior
person, mid-level, or senior, it would,
give them a opportunity to explain
their understanding from generated code.
And obviously as a business owner or
who, who is less technical, they would
feel a more confident on, Written
code where we literally used, AI
as a co-pilot rather than co-pilot.
So it is very important to have code
reviews, pair programming, collaborative
communication and practices, as a team.
So the key is to use AI responsibly
without becoming dependent.
I would say try solving problem
on your own first before using ai.
all this would ensure you to engage in
what would be the potential solution.
And then re reflective practices like, how
would solve without ai, would help and may
maintaining your critical thinking skills.
Also, AI should enhance, right?
It shouldn't replace you You
do not underestimate human
intelligence, although it works
completely different in comparison
to AI or artificial intelligence.
But it is there for you to
support you, not to replace you.
That is why, make sure that
you use it as a co-pilot, you
being pilot at the same time.
One of the most effective ways
to keep developers, engaged and
sharp is by exposing us developers
to different projects and ideas.
So it doesn't have to be
project at the same time.
we have different problems for
same domain, and we've got same
problem in different domains,
but applied differently.
So project rotation.
Would help developers work on different
code bases and, it would, help problem
solve with the problem solving skills
and preventing them from, other
specializations, which is, very important,
especially at this time and age.
tech workshops, hack days, dojo, sim,
would simulate continuous improvement.
and they would give the opportunity to
have hands-on collaboration with others.
Systems like, by Spotify and
ais, they created the communities
where developers practice skills
together and share best practices.
So the key is to encourage peer
learning, ensuring that, developers
remain adequate and capable of,
first of all, understanding,
then solving the new problems.
AI has significantly boosted, developed
productivity and the big deal.
We all know that, but especially when
it comes to, coding tasks or coding
related tasks, it really helped us like.
Documentation, writing and refactoring.
a McKinsey study found that a developers
complete programming task up to two x
faster than using AI coding assistance,
documentation writing, which is related
to coding but not coding itself.
a factoring of documentations.
They were improved by 50
to 67% with, AI assistance.
So it really reduced the
time spent on low value.
Tasks in, stack Order flows 2024.
Developer survey 81 personal developers
cited increased productivity.
I, myself, personally, I think it's great.
It helps with the, writing
and understanding of the code,
and you are becoming fast.
But while AI speeds up the development
process, it is crucial that we use
it wisely to ensure that we are
still building and refining, our
problem solving skills, which is
very important in the long run.
AI is powerful and valuable tool.
But it should complement, not replace.
To structure the right balance, we
need to use AI as a learning tool.
Developers should always review
the AI generated code to understand
the why and the how behind it.
So deliberate practice is a key.
Maybe a code might work AI generat
code, but you should, as a developer
or engineer, you need to understand the
why and how behind, that specific code.
So deliberate practice a key solving
problems without ai critically.
To maintain the strong
problem solving is case.
Do not just jump on the copilot chat,
g PT or rec cascade from the venture.
Just try to understand the
error, on the terminal.
I. Critical, review of AI generic code
is essential maybe with a team member
or by yourself throughout development.
So treat AI like a junior developer
that is there for you forever, right?
So make sure that you actually go
and verify the work of the junior.
Now, finally.
Please use AI as a upskilling tool.
Learn new techniques and programming
patterns from AI suggestions, but do
not blindly accept them because there
is an idea of HA hallucination in ai.
So make sure you actually
verify and understand the
whatever AI is talking about.
I personally believe that.
These new innovative tools that we
are using on a daily basis, they
actually affect our feeling and
impression toward our day-to-day job.
So on positive side, AI
removes the tedious fork and
tasks and prevent burnout.
That's great.
But on the negative side, too much
reliance on AI can, it would lead to
disengagement in a way or boredom or.
Job insecurity.
So it is important to have that
nice balance and, continuously work
on yourself as an individual and
learn the creative thinking and
let the AI do the tedious stuff.
So I. To keep ourself engaged.
I believe we need to keep the
work, challenging and meaningful.
And, other day I told my colleague if
we need to find a meaning in our work.
So we cannot just blindly create
a, I'm just giving an example,
API endpoint or a new button in
front end or new AI model version.
No, we need to find a meaning and
the why behind of every decision.
Now encouraging ownership is another
point where AI outputs are drafts
that developers need to refine rather
than accept them straight away.
So it would keep the
developers in control.
And lastly, a growth mindset
helps developers see AI as a tool
for learning, not as a thread.
Think of AI as a, your teacher
where it's available, right?
You write and it text backs, instantly,
but you wouldn't want your supervisor
or teacher to do the job for you.
So you need to understand the
concepts and, go deeper the why
and hows of the, technology.
Rather than just use it as a
pilot to ensure developers stay
competitive in AI driven world,
companies must actively invest in
upskilling and reskilling programs.
Major tech companies have already
taken steps to address this.
Amazon, for example, launched a 1.2
billion upskilling 2025 initiative aimed
at retaining a workforce in software
engineering, ai, and cloud computing.
At and t has committed 1 billion,
to its feature ready retaining
program, which provides, training
in ai, data science and software
engineering and software development.
Many companies, including IBM,
Google, Microsoft, have also
established AI development, ensuring
workforce remains skilled and
adaptable as technology evolves.
In this non-technical session, we have
explored the negative impacts of ai.
It is very important.
you are not a software engineer.
Even if you are not a
technical individual.
It is very important to
balance out your AI usage.
Use AI for efficiency purposes.
I. But continue practicing
your core skills.
It can be coding.
It can be accounting.
no literature writing a poem.
I don't know.
Make sure that you do
practice your key skills.
Number two is it is very
important to learn continuously.
Always encourage yourself for new
projects, for new ideas and challenges.
Another point would be
psychological engagement.
Now.
Keep work meaningful and challenging.
just for the sake of it.
Find meaning and challenge itself, and
then start working on why and then how.
And lastly, for business owners,
they should invest in, upskilling
and reskilling programs.
It is very important to make the
non-technical and technical staff aware
of AI and the impacts that it is bringing.
So this is the, understanding that
I have in terms of the impact of ai.
And if you have any
questions, just let me know.
Thank you very much.
have a great and wonderful day.