Speaker 28: Yep.
Hi, everyone.
So my name is Yaroslav, and so a
bit of context before we start Yep.
So for the last two years, I worked with
LLMs in production across three companies.
So it was Thread, which builds ad
infrastructure inside conversational AI.
It was Cesar Labs in San Francisco.
It is large OpenAI-backed
multi-agent neo lab.
And now I'm in early stage multi-agentic
startup where I'm a founding engineer.
So alongside that, I'm studying at
King's College London, doing mathematics
with finance, and also I do executive
education in data science at Imperial.
So I'm not here to talk
about building agents.
There are plenty of talks about that, and
I think you heard a lot about them today.
So I want to talk about the part almost
nobody designs on purpose, the part
that gets bolted on at the end, treated
as plumbing and then quietly decides
whether your entire system can be trusted.
And yeah, this is verifier, the judge,
the thing that decides whether the agent's
output was any good And the uncomfortable
thesis I want to defend today is that
the judge is the hardest component
in a genetic system, not the easiest.
Yeah.
What we have built our intuition about
it backwards, and so that almost every
production verify I've seen is in a
precise sense, it's rotten, degrading
in a way that pr- produces no error,
no alert, no signal until one day
you realize the number it's been
emitting for months meant nothing.
And let me try to earn that
claim So yeah start with what
actually happens on a team.
You build an agent, it
worked on in the demo.
Someone, usually, like someone
sensible and kinda precise ask how
you know the output is correct.
And yeah, of course, you
will add the verifier.
In practice, this means a second model
call with a prompt that say something
like, "Rate the quality of answer," or,
"Is it following the same like guardrails?
Explain your reasoning.
Check the reasoning," and stuff like that.
So you wire it up, you set a threshold,
you call it quality control, and you ship.
For a while it seems fine, and
here is the first subtle thing.
It seems fine precisely because
in the early days you're still
reading the outputs yourself.
The judge and your own eyes agree, so you
trust the judge, and you stop reading.
That is the exact moment the rot begins,
not when the judge gets worse, but
when you stop being able to see whether
it was never as good as you thought.
Because a broken judge and a working
judge produce the same artifact,
a number, a verdict, looked good,
like 8 out of 10, 10 out of 10.
There is no exception thrown when
a judge approves a bad answer.
There is no stack trace
when it rejects a good one.
The failure mode of a verifier is
like really the silence, and silence
is the one failure mode our entire
engineer culture is bad at detecting.
Because every tool we have, logs,
alerts, dashboards, is built to
surface events, and a silently
wrong verdict is not an event.
It's absess of, absence of one.
So the first idea I want to plant in
this, the ver- the verifier is the
only component in your system whose
failures are invisible by construction.
The agent fails loudly, wrong
output, angry user, broken test.
The judge fails silently.
It just keeps agreeing with
things it shouldn't, and the
cost lands later somewhere else
where you can't trace it back
And yeah, let me get specific about
why this happens, because we judge is
unreliable, is too vague to act on.
There are concrete measured reasons.
When you ask an LLM to judge, you
imagine it evaluating quality.
It isn't, or at least not only.
It's evaluating a blend of quality and
a set of biases that have nothing to
do with whether the answer is correct.
These are not res-speculative, I will say.
There are some of
the most reproduced
fi-findings in this field.
Position bias.
Show a judge two answers, and it
tends to prefer whichever came
first independent of content.
Second one is verbosity bias.
It tends to prefer the longer answer,
even when the extra length is padding.
These were in the original LLM as a judge
paper from Zhen and colleagues back in two
thousand and twenty-three, and they have
survived every model generation since.
But the one that should generally
unsettle you in a self-pre-- preference,
a judge systema-systematically favors
text that looks like its own output.
Watilola and colleagues measured
this carefully and found something
revealing about this mechanism.
The effect tracks perplexity.
The judge prefers text it finds
easy to predict, text in its own
style, its own rhythms, its own
habits of phrasing and the structure
of sentencing and stuff like that.
Not text that is correct.
Text that is familiar.
The judge is, in a sense, grading
on how much the answer sounds
like something it would have said
And yeah, how big is this?
On one public benchmark, Arena Hard, maybe
some of you heard about that, it's kinda
popular right now, the self-preference
effect across different judges ranged from
- 38% to +90%.
Sit with that range for a second.
That is not a small bias around the truth.
That is a verdict that can move by
more than 100 points depending solely
on who wrote the answer being judged.
If you if your agent and your judge
come from the same model family,
you are not getting verification.
You're getting a model nodding
as its own reflection Yep, and
there's a human version of this, and
close of the obvious escape route.
The obvious fix when I don't trust the
judge is to put a person on top of it.
It's like the human loop, have a
human review the judge's verdicts.
But Dietz and colleagues documented
what they called the rubber sum effect.
When you ask a person to
verify an LLM's judgment, they
disproportionately just agree with
it, even when it demonstrably wrong.
It's the Asch conformity
experiment run with a model as
the confident voice in the room.
So the human safety net has the same
hole as the judge it's meant to catch.
You've stacked two correlated verifiers
and called it defense in depth.
Now, none of these biases
show up in your demo.
That's the cruel part.
In the demo, you have 10 examples,
and you read all of them.
The biases are statistical.
They emerge at scale, in
aggregate, exactly in the regime
where you've stopped looking.
The judge doesn't rot
because the model degrades.
It rots because the condition that masked
its biases, your attention maybe, or
your temporarily, and the biases were,
like, for all time And yeah here's
where I want to push against a piece of
received wisdom, because I think it's
not just wrong, but precisely inverted.
Most teams use a weaker,
cheaper model as the judge.
The reasoning feels, like, all right.
Judging is easier than doing.
Checking an answer is
simpler than producing it.
So spend your expensive tokens on
generation and economize on verification.
Put the big model on the agent
and a small o- model on the judge.
So I want to argue that backwards, but I
have to be careful here because there is
a real result that seems to support the
conventional view, and the interesting
part is exac- is exactly where it breaks.
The supporting result is
verification asymmetry.
There is a genuine deep fact, or maybe
Jason Wei wrote about it recently,
and it shows up across mathema-
mathematics that verifying a solution
is often easier than producing one.
Okay, let's think about
the prime factorization.
Finding the factors of a large
number is brutally hard but checking
whether two proposed factors
multiply back is trivial, right?
In convex optimization, a dual certificate
lets you validate that a solution is
optimal far more cheaply than finding it.
So in these domains, yes, a weaker ver-
verifier can check a stronger generator
because the verification problem is
generally a smaller problem But here's
the catch, and it's the whole game.
But the symmetry only holds when
verification has a cheap certificate,
when there is a shortcut to checking that
doesn't require redoing the work, right?
Or factorization has one, multiply, right?
Optimization has one, like we do.
Code has one, sometimes run
it, and yeah, that's it.
So but most agentic task has,
have no certificate, right?
Was this l-legal summary
faithful to the contract?
Did this research synthesis
represent the sources honestly?
Is this multi-step plan actually
going to achieve the goal?
There is no cheap check to this.
To verify the answer, the judge
has to do essentially the same
reasoning the generator did.
Reconstruct the argument, find the
load-bearing step, and know what correct
answer often without an answer key at all.
So yeah, when there is no
certificate, the asymmetry collapses.
Verification becomes as hard as
generation, and I will think I think that
sometimes even harder because spotting
the one subtle flaw in a plausible-looking
proof is harder than producing a
plausible-looking f-proof, right?
So and there is a measured
failure mode behind this.
Sometimes called limited reasoning bias,
a judge cannot reliably catch a mistake on
a problem it could not have solved itself.
If your agent is operating at the
frontier o-of what the strongest model
can do, a weaker judge isn't checking it.
It's rubber-stamping it with
extra steps and confident tone.
That's it.
So the principle I would offer
is conditional, and the condition
is the interesting part.
Ask does this task have a
cheap verification certificate?
If yes, if you can run the code,
check the tool, execute the query,
so yeah, when a cheaper judge plus
that tool can absolutely verify a
strong, a stronger generator, right?
And you should lean on the tool hard.
If no, if verif-- if verification requires
the same reasoning as a generator when
your judge must be at least as strong as
your agent, and probably even stronger,
and the place you cut cost is not here.
The mistake isn't using a weak judge.
The mistake is using a weak judge on a
task with no certificate, which is, I'll
say, most of them And now I want to go
one level deeper into a finding where
it generally surprised me and that I
think very few teams have internalized.
You might assume that as the models
get more capable, more high in
quality, or they get better at judging,
including at judging themselves, more
intelligence, like better verdicts.
It turns out this is not what happens,
and the gap is like structural.
There is recent work, a paper on
self-verification dynamics from earlier
this year in the clearest, like showing
a persistent asymmetry between a
model's ability to generate and its
ability to verify its own generations.
And the striking part is
the direction of the arrows.
Training a model to generate
better, does not improve in
self self-verification, right?
The two capabilities
doesn't move together.
You can scale generation all you,
like all you want, and the model's
ability to check its own work
doesn't come along for this ride.
Verification is a distant capability,
not like byproduct of being smart.
Worse, when researchers looked
closely at what models do when they
appear to self-verifi-ver-verify,
they found a lot of it is what they
bluntly called fake verification.
The model emits the words of checking
like, "Let me verify this step,"
but verification step has almost no
causal effect on the final answer.
It's performing the ritual of
checking without doing the work.
From the outside, in your,
like in your logs this looks
identical to real verification.
Model says it's checked, the
trace contains a checking step,
but nothing was actually tested.
So this connects to an older
finding from the critic work.
Without external feedback,
a LLM self-correction can
actively make things worse.
The model asks to reject its own
answer with no outside signal.
Will sometimes talk itself out of
correct answer into a wrong one.
The summary line from that research has
stuck with me: Language models don't
reliably know what they know, and if
a model doesn't reliably know what
it knows, when asking that-- the same
model to be the judge of its own work
is asking the blind spot to inspect
itself And yeah, here's why this matters
for architecture like concretely.
It means you cannot get verification
for free by adding a now check your
work step to your agent's own prompt.
That's the cheapest and
more tempting design.
Same model, one more turn, self-critique,
and research says it's largely a feature.
Real verification has to come
from somewhere the generation
didn't: a different model, an
external tool, a ground truth
signal or something like that.
So verification you can trust is
verification that has independent
purchase on the problem.
Self-verification di- done by the same
model is the same context, mostly tells
you what the model already believed.
So the deeper principle is this,
verification is not a weaker form
of generation that you can bolt on.
It is an orthogonal capability
that has to be sourced completely
independently from a different model,
like a tool or a measured outcome.
So the moment your verif- your verifier
shares the generator's mind, it
shares the generator's blind spots,
and it will constantly miss exactly
the errors the generator was prone
to make And yeah, if one judge can't
be trusted, we-- easy to-- instinct
is to use several and vote, right?
This is right in spirit and
usually wrong in execution, and
the reason is worth dwelling on.
So if you take three judges from the
same model family and average them,
you have not built a robust verifier.
You've built three correlated copies
of the same biases and averaged
them which sharpens your confidence
without improving your accuracy.
So they share self pre- preference
they share position bias, they
share the same holes because
they share the same training.
Averaging correlated
errors doesn't cancel them.
It launders them into a number that looks
more trustworthy, and yeah, it isn't.
We think what actually helps
is we think teams instinctively
try to suppress disagreement.
So when judges from generally
different families, imagine like
Claude, GPT, Gemini, or maybe some
Chinese models, disagree about
an output, that disagreement is
not noise to be smoothed away.
It's the most informative
signal in the whole system.
The cases where all three agree are
almost by definition the easy cases.
The cases where they split and we are
one sitting on the real boundary, like
general ambiguity or a place where
one judge specific bias is very hard.
So those split cases are where
the entire question of trust
lies, and the disagreement is
not random, it's systematic,
and that's what makes it usable.
A Gemini judge leans toward
Gemini-flavored answers.
A GIN model has a characteristic
verbosity profile.
These are stable, measured tendencies
which means you can do something most
teams never attempt, m- like model
each judge's bias explicitly as a known
quantity and correct for it, rather than
pretending the judge is like a neutral
instrument and being silently wrong.
And the cleanest practical rule
that falls out of the literature
is almost embarrassingly simple,
and almost nobody follows it.
Never let a model be the
sole judge or… of itself.
If your agent runs on GPT, GPT should
not be the only thing grading GPT.
Pair it with judges that doesn't
share training and treat the places
where you disagree as a live map
of where your system risk actually
is, and the disagreement isn't a
problem with your verification.
It is your verification So the
unit of replication isn't a judge.
It's a panel of deliberately different
judges plus a model of how each one is
wrong, which raises the question that
actually has to be solved in production.
Which judge do you call on
which task at what cost?
You can't run, you can't run a full
panel of frontier models on every
single output and survive a bill.
Calling everyone every time is
the static answer, and it's both
wasteful of I don't know, and naive.
It spends your most expensive
judge on the easiest cases
and learns nothing over time.
The better frame is the one I want to
leave you with technically is to treat
judge selection as a multi-armed bandit.
This setup maps almost too cleanly.
Each judge or each combination
of judges is an arm.
When you route a task to an arm and
gets a verdict, you eventually learn
whether that verdict was right.
A human spot checks it, and downstream
test passes or fails, a customer
escalated or doesn't So a better outcome
is a reward, and now you're in classic
exploration/exploitation problem.
Explore enough to learn which judge
is reliable for which kind of task.
Then exploits that knowledge throughout
each task to the judge that has earned
it And yeah, the tool I would reach
for is basically Thompson sampling.
It dates to 1933 and has aged better
than almost anything in this field.
The idea is to pick each arm in proportion
to its probability of being the best
one, given everything you've seen so far.
And yeah, early on, when you know
little, it naturally explo-explores.
It tries different judges
and watches the outcomes.
As evidence accumulates, it naturally
concentrates on the judges that
keep being right for each task type.
Agrawal and Goyal proved it achieves
logarithmic regret, as I remember,
which in plain terms means the cost
of learning is small and bounded.
You stop wasting calls on bad
judges quickly, yeah, not slowly.
This isn't exotic.
There is a solid body of recent work
using exactly this machinery for model
routing, framing which model do I call as
a bandit balancing cost against accuracy.
The same machinery transfers
directly to which judge do I call.
And for this, an even more pointed
prece-precedent, a variant called
QOC-aware Thompson sampling was built
specifically for runtime verification
for the case where you don't merely
want the best arm on average, you
want to guarantee a quality threshold
is met with high confidence.
That is the verification problem
stated in the language of bandits.
Someone already wrote down the algorithm.
It just wasn't pointed at the judges yet.
But the reason I care about the
bandit framing isn't the algorithm.
It's the stance it forces.
A static Ansible encodes an
assumption that you already know
how to verify, and you're frozen
that knowledge into a config.
A bandit routes encodes the
opposite, more honest assumption,
that you are still learning how
to verify on live traffic forever.
Because the agent changes, the
model ver-version changed underneath
you, the task distribution drifts,
and the judge that was perfectly
calibrated last month is already
subtly miscalibrated this month.
So routing is what keeps verification
honest, and the ground moves.
The config-frozen version isn't simpler.
It's just wrong more slowly and silently,
which is the exact failure we started
with And yeah, let me be honest about
the economics because everything I've
said point toward an expensive answer,
and pretending otherwise would be
the same dishonesty I'm criticizing.
If your judge is as strong as your
agent, which I argued it must be, or
any task without a cheap certificate
when verification roughly doubles your
per task inference cost at, as a floor.
Run a panel of three strong judges
and you've triple or quadruple it.
So verification done seriously is not a
rounding error on the top of generation.
At full strength, it can be the single
largest line in your inference bill.
This is the real unspoken reason
teams switch for a weak judge.
Not because they believe it worked
better, but because the honest version
looks alarming on a spreadsheet, right?
And its failures are invisible until
much later and some-somewhere else.
This is exactly the problem the
banding dissolves, and it's why the
routing isn't a nice to have thing.
It's what makes the honest
version economically survivable.
You don't run the full
panel on every task.
You run it on the task that need it.
The ones near a decision boundary,
the ones where the judges have
historically disagreed, the ones
where a wrong verdict is expensive.
On the high agreement, like low stakes
cases, one cheap judge suffice, and
the router learns to recognize them.
So the true cost of verification
isn't like the strongest judge
time every ti-- times every task.
It's the strongest judge times the
fraction of tasks that generally need one.
And discovering that fraction per
task type is precisely the thing
that banding is built to Yeah.
And there is a cost of the other side
of the ledger that's easy to leave
out of the spreadsheet entirely.
The most expensive verification
failure is never the compute.
It's the wrong verdict that ships.
The bad output your judge made
through, the bad reach to customer,
like that someone has to discover,
explain, and unwind usually after
it's caused the damage real damage.
So measured against that,
paying for a strong judge on the
generally hard cases is not a cost.
It's insurance against being
silently, expensively wrong at scale.
You're not spending on verification you're
buying down the probability that your
whole system is confidently lying to you
And yeah, let me compress all of this
into the things I would generally hold
to building one of these systems today.
I would design the verifier
be-before the agent, not like after.
If I can't articulate how I will know the
agent is right, I don't have a system yet.
I have a demo with good lightning.
The verification strategy
is the architecture, not
like a layer on top of it.
I would ask for every task type whether
it has a cheap verification certificate.
If it does, code I can run, like
a query I can check, a tool I can
compute, I would lean on the tool hard
and let the cheaper judge wield it.
If it doesn't, I would make the judge
at least as strong as the agent and
accept the cost because a weak judge,
a certificate-free task is just hope
with a confidence score attached.
So I would source verification
independently of generation.
None of the same model checking
its own work in its own context.
That's mostly fatal, if the research
is clear, but can make things worse.
Verification has to have independent
purchase, a different model, an external
tool, or like a real-world outcome.
And yeah, I would build the judge as
a panel of generally different model
families, and I would treat their
disagreement as the primary signal rather
than inconvenience to average away.
The split cases are the
map of where my risk lives.
I would route, not vote.
Treat judge selection as a bandit.
Learn from life outcomes which
judge to trust for which task and
let the system keep relearning as
everything underneath it drifts.
And above all, I would measure the judge
continuously, forever, like against
ground truth, human review, downstream
tests, real outcomes on a sampled schedule
that never stops because the judge is
the component, like one component whose
decay is invisible and the verifier you
are not verifying is already rotten.
So you simply can't see it yet And
yeah, I want to end on the asymmetry
that I think justifies all of this
because it's the thing I would
want you to carry on of this room.
So when you, your agent
is wrong, you lose a task.
When your judge is wrong, you
lose the ability to know that
anything is wrong at all.
So one failure is local and loud,
the other is global and silent.
And we have spent the last two years
pouring our attention into making
agents more capable while leaving
the component that decides whether we
can trust any of it as afterthought.
A cheap model, a quick prompt,
and no- b- nobody audits at all.
The teams whose systems still mean
something in a year will be the ones
who inverted that who treats the
judge as the hardest problem, not the
easiest, who made it strong, made it
independent, made it plural, made it
adaptive, and never stopped watching it.
So who understand that
it's the part of the stack that
decides whether you can believe your
own outputs or you do not get to be
cheap, and you do not get to look away.
So stop bolting verifiers
onto finished agents.
Build the judge first.
Build it stronger when we
think it does, and never, ever
stop verifying the verifier.
So yeah, this is some results
read in full, so if you need
that, you can screenshot.
Pretty useful things to read.
And yeah, thank you.