Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 LLM 2025.
My name is, I'm a tech engineering leader
specializing in cloud infrastructure,
SRE, and AI driven innovations.
My career spans from Microsoft
and fast pace startups.
For this talk, we will focus
on observability, SRE, and
how this is implemented in s.
Agenda will be introduction to AI
LLM Trends, understanding LLM, SI
fundamentals, observability in AI systems,
SRE, roles in managing LMS case studies.
And we'll conclude with
some open discussions.
AI is your needs.
So we are right now experiencing
an exponential arc in ai.
We started in 2012 with AlexNet and
slowly we trending towards GPT GPT-4.
We are planning to gain a GI, which
is artificial journal intelligence
within the next five years.
Okay.
And hopefully with this, progress in
next more than 10 years, maybe we can
have artificial super intelligence, also
current LLM market trend.
So we are expecting 37.2% growth
rate by 2030, and this will
focus mostly on LLM side of it.
Introduction to LLM models.
So what is L-L-M-L-L-M are advanced AI
systems trained on vast data sets to
understand and generate human like text.
Their applications are content
generations, customer support, research,
coding assistance, and a couple
of examples of LM GPT-4 and palm.
L and M have transport so many
industries, including healthcare,
education, software developments,
overview of SRE, so introduction of SREs,
SRE ensures reliability, scalability,
efficiency in software systems.
Key practices include proactive
monitoring, automation
and incident response.
So SRE has some core principles,
S-L-I-S-L-O, service level, objective,
service level, indicators, error, budget.
All these are guiding principles
of SRE, but the high level focus
is how we can balance reliability
with innovation and speed.
Next part is observability.
So how observability can ensure.
In AI system, so basically observability
is more like a system behavior, which
is measurable and understandable.
We have three key pillars of
possibility, metrics, logs, and traces.
Metrics are continuity values, which is
like CPU usage, memory utilization, API
response times and logs are detailed.
Timestamped records of system events.
Traces are, visualizing the flow of
requests through your various services
of to identify bottleneck traces
are very helpful in for developers.
Basically challenges in observing
lms, so LLM operates own enormous
data sets, creating challenges
in performance monitoring.
And, LLM has a dynamic behavior.
LLM adapts based on the inputs, make
their response non-deterministic
in case transparency.
black box nature of LLM complicates
understanding their internal
decision process and scalability.
Monitoring and managing LM require
robust and scalable infrastructure.
So how we can implement
observability in LLM.
So it's a step by step process.
Step one is we need to define our
key metrics, monitor prediction,
latency, throughputs error rates.
Step two is integrate advanced
logging, so collect logs for input,
output, and model resilience.
Once that is done, we
use distributed tracing.
So map end-to-end interactions
for pinpointing your failures.
Okay, and deploy real time dashboards.
Dashboard can be Grafana or any
other visualization tools we can use.
Now, what's the role
of SRE in managing lms?
So SRE responsibility and LLM include
ensuring 24 by seven availability through
automated failover systems, developing
runbooks for common incident scenarios.
Automation is definitely a key.
So automate scaling up resources
during high demand period.
And this also involves tackling the
use case of toils and other things.
Collaboration with AI team is very
important, so providing feedbacks on model
performance for iterative improvements.
we have multiple case
studies which will focus on.
One of the case study is AI chat
bot monitoring response latency.
To ensure the user experience
healthcare AI is there, you can ensure
compliance of medical guidelines and
reduce false positive fraud detection.
This can be in a security
or banking system.
Continuous monitoring of
prediction accuracy is identified
fraudulent transactions.
So conclusion of my talk is basically
focused on observability and SRE and
these two concepts observability, SRE,
are vital to ensure we have reliability
and scalability of l and m. As AI
system involve adopting innovative
practices and prioritization, reliability
practices will be the key to build
resilient and trustworthy AI system.
This drives value across industries.
And finally, I have a
recommendation on the books.
So for SRE, definitely SRE Handbook,
which was written by Nile Murphy.
It, this is a on SRE dot, Google
Books, and it's, free over there.
That is very helpful.
And another book, which I recently
completed is about engineering.
This book will definitely go beyond
and help in implementing all the
concepts that we just learned.
Thank you for listening my talk.
Yeah.
See ya.