Speaker 19: Hi, welcome to the session
of Large Language Models of 2026.
Today we're going to explore a topic of
compliance by construction for scalable
privacy-resilient credit applications.
A technical deep dive into embedding
regulatory security and privacy
controls directly into co-branded credit
card ecosystems without sacrificing
throughput, latency, and user experience.
A brief introduction of me.
I'm Rander Rajsekar Kavuru.
I'm a software engineering
manager at ExpediTech Group.
And a disclaimer before
we delve into the topic.
The views and opinions expressed in
this presentation are my own and do not
represent the views or official position
of my current or my previous employers.
The content is based on
general industry knowledge and
publicly available information.
No proprietary or confidential information
will be shared during this talk.
Now let's get into the topic.
Stakes.
Kubernetes credit card ecosystem,
where two worlds collide.
Kubernetes credit card platforms
sit at the intersection of
regulatory banking infrastructure
and high-volume consumer platforms.
This dual nature creates compounded risk.
Every transaction must satisfy
both the throughput demands of
consumer tech and compliance
obligations of regulatory finance.
Security breaches in this
space carry outsized financial,
reputational, and regulatory
consequences, often in that order.
Average cost of financial data breach
is estimated at nine point five
million dollars, among the highest
of any industry sector globally, and
two hundred and seventy-two days to
identify and contain average breach
life cycle in financial services.
Forty percent of breaches
leave no traditional log.
Standard logging misses a significant
fraction of failure events What
is compliance by construction?
Rather than retrofitting controls
onto existing systems, compliance
by construction embeds regulatory,
security, and privacy requirements
directly into system design, making
non-compliance architecturally
impossible or prohibitively difficult.
So there are four phases to it.
Let's get into phase one.
That's a design phase.
Regulatory constraints encoded as system
invariants, not post-hoc checklist.
Phase two, that's a build phase.
Enforcement mechanisms woven into
service contracts and data flows.
And phase three, runtime phase.
Continuous policy evaluation with
real-time telemetry and adaptive response.
And phase four, audit phase.
Immutable structured evidence
generated automatically as
a byproduct of operations.
This approach shifts compliance from a
cost center and annual checkbox exercise
into a structural property of the
system itself, one that scales with the
platform rather than lagging behind it.
Economic security modeling,
aligning investment with risk.
Security spending decisions are only
as good as the models that inform them.
This framework grounds investment
allocation in breach pro-probability
estimation, and expected loss
calculus, enabling organizations
to optimize security expenditure
related to actual risk exposure
rather than perceived threat.
Expected loss reduction.
Quantify the marginal risk
reduction achieved by each security
control expressed in dollar terms.
Investments are prioritized where
reduction in expected breach
costs exceeds control costs.
Breach probability modeling.
Leverage historical incident data,
threat intelligence feeds, and
system topology analysis to assess
probabilistic breach like-likelihoods
to each component and integration point.
Marginal cost analysis.
Identify the point of diminishing
returns for security controls, preventing
over-investment in low-risk areas and
under-investment in high-risk areas.
Behavioral compliance.
Governance beyond technical stack.
Technical controls alone do
not guarantee compliance.
Behavioral compliance research that
demonstrates that policy adherence is
jointly determined by organization culture
and enforcement mechanisms, and that
neither is sufficient without the other.
Empirically validated predictors of
compliance behavior include perceived
detection probability improv.
Employees comply more
consistently when they believe
violations will be identified.
Norm internalization.
Cultures where security is a shared
value outperform those relying
solely on penalty enforcement.
Friction reduction.
Compliant paths must be the path of least
resistance, not the most burdensome.
Feedback loops.
Rapid specific feedback on near misses
drives sustained behavioral change.
There are four blocks to it.
First block is culture.
Shared security norms reduce policy drift.
And the second block, enforcement.
Automated controls eliminate
reliance on manual adherence.
Incentives.
Align individual incentives with
organizational security posture.
Measurement.
Quantified compliance metrics
and hidden governance.
Event-driven microservices and
advanced logging architecture.
Async event streams.
Decoupled event buses, for example
Kafka, absorb telemetry bursts without
backpressure on core transaction services.
Every state change emits a
structured immutable event.
Structured audit logging.
Logs are schema enforced, tamper
evident, and routed to append-only sinks.
This addresses the forty percent
of failure events invisible to
traditional unstructured logs.
Correlation and enrichment.
Events are enriched with session
context, risk scores, and regulatory
tags in-stream, enabling real-time
compliance assertion without downstream
reprocessing Microsegmentation
containing the blast radius.
PCI DSS aligned microsegmentation
enforces the principle of least
privilege at the network layer,
ensuring that compromise of any single
service cannot propagate laterally
to the cardholder data environments.
Each microservice operates within a
defined security domain with explicitly
enumerated ingress and egress policies.
East-west traffic between services
is authenticated, encrypted, and
logged, eliminating the assumption
of a trusted internal network.
Microsegmentation reduces PCI DSS scope
by isolating cardholder data flows to a
minimal auditable surface, dramatically
simplifying QSA requirement assessments.
Define security domains.
Map services to PCI scope zones,
CDE, connected, and out of scope.
Enforce mTLS everywhere.
Mutual TLS between all service-to-service
calls, no explicit stuff.
Again, policy as a code.
Network policies declared in
version control manifests,
validated in CI/CD pipelines.
Runtime enforcement, serious
mesh-side guard enforces.
Policies at the data plane
without application code changes
Event-driven microservices and
advanced logging architecture.
We are done with that.
Sorry about that.
AI-assisted tokenization.
Security without overhead.
Traditional tokenization implementation
imposes significant computational
and memory overhead, creating a
tension between strong cardholder data
protection and low latency requirements
of real-time credit decisioning.
AI-assisted tokenization
resolves this tension.
Adaptive token vaulting.
ML models predict token access frequency
and pre-position high demand tokens in
low latency memory, me-memory tiers,
reducing vault round trips by up to
sixty percent in traffic scenarios.
Format-preserving efficiency.
Format-preserving encryption, FPE,
generates tokens structurally identical
to PANs, eliminating downstream schema
changes and reducing integration
friction across partner systems.
UX preservation.
Tokenization occurs transparently
in the request path.
Cardholders and partners interact
with stable token representation,
consistent, predictable, and
privacy-preserving by design.
High-performance networking at
the transaction scale should
be less than one millisecond.
P99 latency target.
End-to-end transaction latency, including
fraud scoring and compliance assertion.
Five hundred thousand plus TPS throughput.
Sustained transactions per second
across distributed processing nodes.
Finance of availability.
Availability SLA should be finance
uptime target enforced through
active-active regional deployment.
Distributed transaction protocols
for compliance integrity.
The core challenge at extreme
throughput distributed transactions
spanning multiple services must
maintain atomicity, consistency,
and compliance state simultaneously.
A transaction that succeeds financially
but fails to record a required
compliance event is a regulatory
liability, not just a technical path.
Standard two-faced commit introduces
unacceptable latency at scale.
The architecture employs saga patterns
with compensating transactions and
outbox-based event publishing to guarantee
compliance event delivery without
synchronous coordination overhead.
And coming back to the
initial sa- initiating a saga.
Transaction coordinator publishes
intent event durable outbox,
local state committed atomically.
At number two, participant execution.
Each service executes its local step
and publishes a result compensating
transaction defined upfront.
At number three, compliance assertion.
Compliance service consumes
events, validates against policy
engine, emits audit records.
At number four, compensate on failure.
Rollback chain executes in reverse.
Compliance record captures both
attempt and compensation Real-time
underwriting and fraud detection.
Compliance by construction does
not mean slower decisioning.
The architecture supports real-time
underwriting and fraud scoring with
the transaction latency envelope by
co-locating risk models with transaction
data and leveraging stream computation.
Real-time underwriting.
Bureau data, behavioral signals, and
partner data fuse at the decisioning time.
Models execute on
pre-computed feature vectors.
No synchronous bureau
calls in the critical path.
Streaming fraud detection.
Stateful stream processes
maintain per cardholder risk
context across a rolling window.
Anomaly scores computed in-stream
trigger syncro-synchronous
holds or async review routing.
Partner integrations.
Retail and co-brand partner data
ingested via event-driven APIs.
Compliance controls applied
at ingestion boundary partner.
Partners cannot inject
non-compliant state into the CDE.
All three capabilities operate
with-within a unified compliance envelope.
Fraud dec-decisions, credit decisions,
and partner data are each governed
by the same policy engine and
produces structured audit trails.
AI LLM-driven observability and
adaptive policy enforcement.
Anomaly detection at scale.
Traditional rule-based anomaly detection
degrades at high transaction velocity.
Too many false positives, too
many hand-tuned thresholds.
LLM-assisted models learn normal
behavior envelopes from streaming
telemetry and surface statistically
significant deviations with natural
language explanations for analyst review.
This reduces mean time to detect, MTTD,
for novel fraud detec-- for novel fraud
patterns and compliance viol-violations
that evade signature-based rules.
Adaptive policy enforcement.
AI-driven policy engines evaluate
regulatory intent, not just
rule literals enabling adaptive
enforcements that responds to emerging
threat patterns without requiring
manus-- manual policy updates.
Policy diff detection identifies
when operational behavior
diverges from declared policy.
Explainable decisions.
Every enforcement action
carries a human-readable
rationale for audit purposes.
Regulatory change ingestion.
LLM components parse regulatory updates
and propose policy diff candidates for
human review And architecture summary,
the compliance by construction stack.
And looking at the pyramid, we have
at the bottom of the pyramid, the base
layer, high-performance networking,
kernel bypass, RDMA, zero copy buffers.
On top of the second layer of
the pyramid, we have distributed
transaction layer, Saga patterns, outbox
publishing, compensating transactions.
The third block of the pyramid is
event-driven microservices, Kafka
event bus, structured audit logging,
correl-correlation enrichment.
And at the fourth layer of the
pyramid, we have security controls,
micro-segmentation, mTLS, AI-assisted
tokenization, PCI DSS scope isolation.
At almost at the top of the fifth
layer of the pyramid, we have
real-time intelligence, streaming
fraud detection, real-time
underwriting, partner API compliance.
And at the top of the pyramid, we have
sitting at the top is observability
and governance, LLM anomaly detection,
adaptive policy enforcement, and
behavioral compliance monitoring.
Key takeaways and next steps.
Compliance as architecture.
Embed controls at design time.
Retrofitting compliance onto
production systems is exponentially
more expensive and less effective
than building it from the start.
Align security spend to risk.
Use economic security modeling
to prioritize investments.
Not all controls deliver equal
marginal risk reduction model the
math and allocate accordingly.
Culture and code is equal to governance.
Technical enforcement is
necessary but insufficient.
Invest in behavioral compliance
programs alongside automated controls
for durable governance outcomes.
AI augments human governance.
LLM-driven components accelerate detection
and policy adoption but require human
oversight for regulatory accountability.
Design the human-in-loop
explicitly, not as an afterthought.
Slides, architectural diagrams, and
reference implementation notes will
be shared with the session attendees.
Reach out to continue the conversation
on implementation pat-pattern
specific to your platform context.
If you have questions to
me, please reach out to me.
I'm happy to answer everything.
And thank you for coming to the session
and listening to the session throughout.
And have a nice rest of your day.
Thank you.