Speaker 15: Hey, good day everyone.
My name is Mohandras Vadath Raj.
I'm a lead software engineer at Lowe's.
I have over fourteen years of experience
building enterprise backend systems
using Spring Boot microservices and
streaming tools like Kafka and Flink.
Today I'm going to talk about
building real-time AI decision
systems with large language models.
And we're going to talk about how
enterprise systems are combining the
LLMs and analytics, and also modern data
platforms to support scalable operational
intelligence across complex environments
So in this session, we are going to
talk about four different key things
from that, that helps us moving from AI
experiments to operational intelligence.
So today, obviously pretty much
like all enterprises are using AI
as an inter-experiment system, and
with the concept that we are going
to talk about, we can make them
into operational intelligence to
help us making real-time decisions.
So the challenge that we see in
the modern sy- enterprise systems
are no longer deploying AI models,
which pretty much I think, all the
enterprises are doing these days.
But then integrating them into a
reliable real-time decision systems
at scale are the challenge, right?
So this session covers the
architectural, operational, and gov-
governance dimensions of that shift.
So we have four key concepts that we
are going to talk about in this session.
Coming at number one, the state of
enterprise LLMs and the architectural
patterns, implementation challenges,
and production reliability, right?
So under the state of enterprise LLM
we are going to look at like where
the organizations stand today and
why the current approach, which is
like static reporting, that fall
short, that is not really helpful
in making any real-time decisions.
And coming into architectural patterns,
so integrating the LLMs, it is going to
talk about how we are going to integrate
the LLMs and streaming data and how we are
going to use the retrieval-based system to
help us get this operational intelligence.
And at three implementation challenges.
So we are also going to talk about the
different challenges in implementing
this operational intelligence.
So different issues like fragmented
data or like what is the problem
with governance and what are the
challenges in scalability and trust.
And at four we have this production
reliability in which we are going to
talk about observability, performance,
and operational best practices
So if you look at the real-time
decision intelligence, right?
So how it used to happen or what
is then and what is now, right?
When we are looking at then, so basically
so far all the enterprise systems have
accumulated or collected data across
multiple years or, weeks or months,
and then they use that information
in a batch processed analytics.
And they ran the AI, but it all ran in
siloed deployments, which again could not
help with making a collective decision.
And then when it comes to
decision-makings, it was
pretty much manual handoff.
Meaning you have a system that
collects the input, that generates
a report, you take that, and then
you make a decision based on that.
All happens manually, right?
And all these approaches
basically caused delay.
Basically a decision that can be taken in
minutes, it's still it's still taken weeks
or days to to make with these inputs.
Now, when we look at op-operational
intelligence using the AI, right?
So what are we trying to achieve?
We are going to get to the phase where
continuously evolving AI systems are going
to be in place, put in place, and that
uses the streaming data and LLM models
to to look into the data and then make an
automated real-time rec- real- real-time
recommendations, which helps us making
this decision or make this decision in
sub-second rather like even minutes right?
As of human is doing, So coming to
the core architectural components
that is involved in this presentation
are like data ingestion layer LLM
reasoning layer, and decision engine,
and then the observability layer.
So if you look at the data ingestion layer
so how are we going to get the data that
is going to feed into this AI systems?
So we can make use of the streaming
pipelines such as like Kafka Kinesis or
Flink that can take the data, normalize
it, and route all the different events
from the fragmented en-enterprise
source-- enterprise sources into a
single event and in real-time, right?
Coming to LLM reasoning layer where
we are going to have large language
models that is going to have this
RAG system or retrieval-based context
system that's going to generate the
structured recommendation from live
operational signals, which is just
received from the streaming pipelines.
Coming to the decision engine we are
going to have this orchestration logic
that evaluates all these LLM outputs
against the business rules that are in
place and with confidence threshold and
governance constraints before it, it
acts, meaning it makes the decision.
So that's where the decision
engine comes in place.
At last, we have this observability
layer, which is going to help us
log and trace all these decisions.
And if there is any drift meaning so
the AI is not going as it should, in
the path as it should, rather it is
just distracting from the original
intent, then that is also that also
have to be logged or traced right?
And then like it is also going to--
we also need to trace the latency and
quality of the decisions over time.
So that's where the observability
layer comes in place.
So looking at this static pipelines to
continuously evolving systems, if you
look at that road map that little road
diagram, you can see the current approach,
or maybe not current approach, a little
recent approach static reporting right?
So which involved periodic
dashboards and manual insights.
Basically the different systems in a
particular enterprise collected data from
different tools or different applications.
And then it put together a dashboard
where which was then referred by a human
and insight was built upon that, and then
the decision was made using that, right?
And then the the other approach
was batch ML, where scheduled model
predictions used the input datasets
and helped us making the decisions.
Now, at third, we have the streaming
analytics which is basically it
is used to collect the inputs
from different fragmented systems
into a in a single event source.
And that processed the events and created
the alerts, which is close to real time.
Yet again the decision ends
up in human hand, right?
So yes, we are getting close to the real
time, but still the input is not going
to be processed immediately, right?
It still needs human intervention.
Now, coming at last, we have this
real-time LLM, where using the data that
is collected using the streaming analytics
the real-time LLM is going to use that,
build the context, go through the context,
make a decision and then use this LLM
in the loop so that it can improve the
decision, decisioning logic over time
looking at the problem so what is the
problem with data, first of all, right?
So let's talk about any big org, right?
So definitely, I think, there will
be different systems that will be
collecting different information.
Sometimes that information can overlap
or may overlap, and that overlapping
information is not saying the same thing.
So first problem, schema
inconsistency, right?
If you are looking at any
retail systems, right?
The same business entity a customer
transaction or a product SKU exist
under different schemas, right?
In different places of the organization.
And when we are trying to feed
that information into an LLM to
make any context out of it to help
making any decisions, the LLM is
going to get confused because,
it is seeing like different
information from different systems.
So that's the problem with the schema
inconsistency and latency mismatches.
So if you are looking at real-time
event systems with batch updated
reference data it's going to introduce,
temporary inconsistencies, right?
So basically, the example is or the
idea is like you cannot take the input
or the inventory from yesterday and
look against today's demand, right?
Which is not going to be like accurate.
It is going to cause some
bias-biased outputs right?
So that is the latency mismatches.
And coming to ownership gaps, so it is
little relevant to the first point, right?
In a bigger organization
like I said, right?
So the data is collected
across multiple areas.
Now, when the data comes from multiple
teams or like multiple application, we
don't know the quality of the data, right?
How fresh it is, right?
And who maintains that
quality, obviously, right?
So which is all going to lead a problem
with the LLM recommendations, right?
So basically, ba-bad
data, bad outcome, right?
Or more data, it's going to confuse
the LLM and thus causing like drifted
outcomes Now, looking at this slide
where we have the governance trust
and the human-in-the-loop question.
So basically when we are going
to involve LLM-driven systems
moving from an experimental to
operational so the governance become
definitely non-negotiable, right?
So we cannot-- and, without enough inputs
or enough training in place, we cannot
let the AI make its decision autonomously.
So that is where this governance
process comes in place.
And if you look at this three-tiered
approach where the tier one talks
about assisted, so which basically the
decision is in human's hand, right?
So the AI is going to suggest
some outputs, human is still
going to make the decision, right?
It is definitely low stake right?
So there's no-- not a lot of risk
because human reviews everything.
However, this is going to cause us--
cost us the operational delays or
decision-- de-delay in making decisions.
Number two or tier two we have
the supervised, where we let the
AI act, but then human is going
to review the exceptions, right?
So the AI is going to make decisions
but then human still heavily
involved reviewing any issues or
remain-- reviewing a particular
decision for example, if not all.
And this is, I think,
classified as medium risk.
And looking at tier number three
where we have this autonomous where
the AI acts completely independent.
But then we are going to make use
of the audit trail for any decisions
that is made by the UI and with
that, we gain more confidence.
And this also, low risk.
Reason is, if anything that--
anything goes wrong, should anything
go wrong we still have the audit
trail so that can be used to identify
what went wrong, and we can still
intervene and address the problem.
Coming to the infrastructure
scalability, right?
So how the how or where the
system breaks today, right?
LLM inference definitely is,
it is an expensive and stateful
latency sensitive model, right?
So making a enterprise system to
a real-time sc- scaling it to a
real-time decision-making systems
requires lot of good infrastructure
choices and that needs to be
maintained at different layers right?
So right from choosing the model
or context management and how
we are going to share the, share
that with the downstream systems.
So looking at the common bottlenecks
here so there are four that I could think
of, and I put together here Which are
like, token through- throughput limits
context window management, cold start
latency, stateful versus stateless, right?
So what is token throughput limits?
So if you are, like, dealing with AI in,
in your organization or if you are already
into AI, you would already understand that
any query or any prompt that you make,
that is going to require tokens, right?
So basically, your input sentence
is going to be split into multiple
tokens and the tokens will be used
to look into the context right?
So limiting the-- So
the problem here, right?
So LLM APIs import rate
limits that collapses under
enterprise request volumes.
Yes, as a individual we would be probably
trying ten, twenty request, for example.
Whereas when we are looking at
enterprise systems, they make hundreds
of thousands if not millions of
the calls to the LLM that would put
a heavy use of the tokens, right?
So limiting that again is
going to make things go worse.
Meaning so you wouldn't
get the full output.
And then the context window management.
So here comes the RAG, the
Retrieval-Augmented Systems that should
carefully control what context is injected
to avoid latency spikes and cost overruns.
So again, the critical thing here
is making use of the proper data
or normalized data which then helps
the context window management or RAG
systems to avoid any latency spikes
or looking around multiple schemas or
multiple things that can cost us, right?
And then at third, we have this cold
start latency wherever we don't have
servers basically we go with serverless
LLM deployments that can introduce
unpredictable warm-up delays right?
So that's causing like a sub hundred
millisecond SLAs impossible, right?
So the systems that requires sub
hundred millisecond decisions are
like, the outputs that can't really
use the cold start latent cold
start and the next thing we have is
stateless versus stateful trade-offs.
So maintaining the conversation or
session context across distributed
services significantly con--
complicates horizontal scaling.
Again when we are involving multiple
systems that talks to each other, right?
So we are going to introduce a lot
of context, which is going to take
lot of sc-scalability issues, right?
So how do we avoid this?
So here are the few design
principles to avoid this bottlenecks.
So basically, we need to make sure that,
we are going to decouple the inference
from orchestration, and we gotta cache the
deterministic LLM outputs aggressively.
Meaning we are dealing with the
same problem, and that requires
same decisions that can be cached.
And then we have to use this async
patterns for non-critical decisions.
Set hard latency budgets
per decision type, right?
Thus avoiding latency
and overuse of tokens.
And then building the circuit breakers,
which is a critical piece meaning
we cannot let LLM run forever which
is going to take time and money.
So we gotta have circuit breakers in
place to cut off the request Now, so
let's talk about this retrieval augmented
generation in operational context, right?
So how does it work?
It has the vector store, and then
it needs a retrieval precision and
also index update cadence, right?
So when we are talking about look-looking
at like vector store design so the RAG
systems are require-- going to require a
low latency vector retrieval index design,
chunking strategy, and embedding freshness
all directly impact the quality context
due to the LLM inference time, right?
So it all matters, like when it
comes to the vector store for RAG,
we need to store the data in a way
that it is easy to and in a indexed
way so that, we can do a easy lookup.
And retrieval precision, right?
When it comes to the retrieval, right?
So we want to avoid like
over-fetch and under-fetch, right?
So basically, over-fetching
would create noise.
Meaning you are just looking for some
information for example so you're asking
the AI system like, what is the weather?
So you just want the weather for now for
right now in wherever you are, right?
You don't want the system to be
like, getting the information
like for next ten days, right?
Or the past five days or like how
the weather is going to be, right?
All these projections are
basically considered as over-fetch.
Now, what is under-fetch?
So you are asking for the same
information, but you are not getting
what you are expecting, right?
So basically like in the model
under-fetched information.
So hence to avoid this, we need to go
for the hybrid retrieval model where we
combine the com-combine the output with
reta-- re-ranking this decisions, right?
And the relevancy to, to
retrieve any data, right?
So the RAG does that.
And index update cadence, right?
So this talks about like how frequently
we update the indexes and what
triggers the index update, right?
So meaning whenever the data changes, we
have to update the indexes in order to
like, indexes in the vector store design
in order to make the retrieval precision
high or high retrieval precision Now
coming to the reinforcement learning
for continuous decision improvement.
So here we have this little I
think the in-infinity loop, right?
Where you can see different stages, right?
So basically we have this LLM that
generates a recommendation which
then goes to the output measure.
And based on that, we are
going to make the decisions.
From the decision, if something is
not good or something is off, we can
provide the feedback to the LLM model.
Then the LLM learns and then
again so it improves and you
measure the output, right?
So it's basically a loop how you're going
to force the LLM to learn and then improve
the decision-making capabilities Now,
the other thing that we talked about a
few minutes ago are observability, right?
Like I said, observability in any
production systems are non-negotiable
because, we want to know what is--
what happened and what is going on,
and if-- what if something went wrong
where to look to-- look at, right?
So these are like, very critical, and
this is achieved-- When it comes to AI
models this is achieved at different
levels like model monitoring right?
So we can look at like the output
distributions and the confidence
scores and token level latency, right?
If there are any latency
that is going around.
And then if there is any
deviations in the outputs, right?
So those are like, model monitoring.
And coming to the decision tracing
so every AI decision AI system that
we build to make the decisions should
have the traceability implemented so
that, you can take the outputs back to
the input and the context that is used
and the model that is used in making
this decision, which is very critical.
In order to understand when or should
something go wrong, we need to know what
went wrong and what-- how to correct that.
So that is where the decision
tracing comes in play.
And drift detection I think we
discussed about it briefly, right?
So when you are giving some input, you
don't want your system to drift from the
context and then bring the noise, right?
So that is something
that we need to monitor.
And then explainability of logs, right?
So yes, when-- like any production
system, when we involve AI, we still
need the logs that is explaining
like the reasoning behind any
decisions executed or taken, right?
Yes, we did everything, right?
And yet the systems fail, right?
So hence, we have to have the fallback
and fail-safe mechanisms in place, right?
When can real-time systems,
AI systems can fail, right?
Yes, when there is a latency spike
or it just meets with a new edge
case or some model failed, right?
So in any of these can cause
problems in the AI system and the
system can can be stopped, right?
So if that happens, we should have
like fallback mechanisms in place.
I put together, a couple different
approaches that works out well
as a fallback or fail-safe
mechanism, which is deterministic
fallbacks and graceful degradation.
So deterministic fallback uses a
known tested engine that takes this
inputs and responses fast, and it is
still predictable and safe, right?
And graceful degradation, when a primary
model goes down, it should route the data
to the base models or simple models that
helps the system to continue continue to
work without blocking the users, right?
So that is graceful degradation.
And as I highlighted here,
silent failure is a bigger risk.
Safe fail must be designed in, right?
We don't want our systems that
is making decisions to fail
without our knowledge, right?
So we need to have the fallback mechanism
or fail-safe mechanism in place.
Now, coming to the guardrails and
evaluations so there can be like,
different guardrails that we can put in
place to stop any pre and post inferences.
So basically input guardrails we
can block bad prompt injections
or toxic inputs, right?
Or the inputs that are not in scope.
Hence, we can help the RAG systems
to focus on valid context avoiding
the latency delays, right?
Or keeping the low latency, right?
So that is possible with
the input guardrails.
And output evaluation, which is
again a critical step where like
whenever any decision is made, we
have to have some schema or rejects
validation to make sure that the
outputs are out-outcomes are under
compliance or meeting the compliance.
And also we need to make sure that,
it meets the quality assurance, right?
So that score needs to be measured
and evaluated So coming to the
cost and latency budgeting, right?
In real-time production systems, cost
and latency shape very critical it, it
shapes every architectural choice, right?
So we have to define both upfront.
And the couple approaches that can help us
with cost and latency issues are semantic
caching and the hybrid model routing.
So what is semantic caching, right?
So you receive like similar inputs
over and over again, then you don't
have to send that information to your
RAG system to go and spend a lot of
tokens and look through the same context
and come back with the same decision.
Rather, we can cache it so that
we can respond fast, and we
don't have to use all the tokens.
We don't have to make use of the context.
Hence we are going to achieve
the very low latency, right?
And when it comes to hybrid
model routing it uses like local
models rather complex ones.
Meaning the same common problems comes in.
You can use a local model to
make the common decisions, right?
Only the problems that goes beyond
this are like, edge cases, we can send
it to the larger LLMs, thus avoiding
like, the money spent on that so the
key takeaways or next steps, right?
So yeah, definitely we have to audit
your data foundations first, right?
Making sure that we are not
introducing any fragmented data.
And then define decision
tiers before you build, right?
As I-- as we just, looked at, right?
So we need to decide what we
want and decision tiers that we
want before we build our systems.
And then we also have to build the
observability from day one, right?
This is not something that you run a
system and then after so and so days,
you go and build your observability
a-and then trying to track the
decision from the beginning, right?
So you don't wanna feedback
your audit trail to the
system to improve that, right?
Which is going to be a very complex
task and also it is going to
cost a lot in this model, right?
And then the-- close the feedback
loop intentionally, right?
So yes, I think, feedback loop
is again very critical thing
in improving the AI systems.
So we need to static-statically deploy
this systems that takes the feedback
loop and then measures the outcome and
and ingest that into the decisions that
are like, about to be taken, right?
So that is-- this is again the closing
the feedback loop intentionally
is also a critical thing.
I think with that said my,
my topic has come to an end.
And since this is a online presentation
I couldn't take any live questions,
but I'm definitely happy to take the
questions on, email or you can ping
me on my LinkedIn so I can respond.
Thank you so much for taking
time and listening to this.
Thank you.
Have a good one.