Hello everyone.
My name is Kata, and today I'm excited to
talk about something that can radically
improve how we manage operational cost in
urban mobility and logistics, AI power.
Pricing for street-based tasks.
If you're dealing with task-based
operations, whether it's fleet
deployment logistics, or on demand
workforce management, you already
know that strategic and strategic
pricing models don't work efficiently.
They lead to cost inflation, poor
task distribution, and inefficiencies.
Over the next 10 minutes, we'll
walk you through how AI can solve
this problem using real time data
to dynamically adjust pricing,
improve efficiency, and reduce costs.
Before we dive into AI powered pricing,
let me briefly introduce myself and share
how I ended up working in this space.
I actually started my career in
construction industry working
at mr, which is one of the
biggest developers in the world.
I was a structured, it was a structured,
process driven industry, but I was drawn
to something different, fast paced, high
growth businesses that led me to move to
London where I transitioned into startups.
And I initially joined Oya, which
is a SoftBank backed hospitality
company known for its aggressive
growth strategy across the globe.
It was an intense high speed environment.
I learned a lot about scaling operations
quickly after Covid, I piloted.
Back into Property Invest, investing
industry in the uk joining Brick
Lane, which is a company that is
using AI power decision making to make
property investment decisions within
the UK and optimize these decisions.
This was where I developed my
understanding of AI in business
strategy and how it can be leveraged.
Finally I joined Lyme where
I'm now the general manager.
I oversee operations, one of the lar
world's largest micro mobility markets.
One of our biggest challenge
today is ensuring that task-based
operations, like moving and
rebalancing bikes and scooters are.
Priced fairly and efficiently.
This challenge isn't just unique to Lyme.
It's a problem across the entire industry,
and that's why AI powered pricing is a
such a game changer for this problem.
Let's take a look at why pricing is
such a critical issue in micro mobility.
Micro mobility is one of the fastest
growing transportation sectors.
Worldwide.
Cities are embracing shared mobility
because it offers affordable, convenient,
and eco-friendly alternatives to cars.
Governments are pushing for
sustainable transportation options,
and we are seeing cities build more
bike lanes, pedestrian forni zones,
and smart mobility infrastructure.
But with this growth, operational
complexity is also increasing.
Managing thousands of scooters
and bikes across large urban areas
is challenging and inefficiencies
in deployment, retrieval and
maintenance at significant costs.
So where is this industry heading next?
The micro mobility industry is
projected to grow from $61.5
billion in 2024 to 223.6 billion.
By 2033.
That's nearly a four times
increase in less than a decade,
but this massive growth doesn't
automatically mean profitability.
Many micro mobility companies are
struggling with high operational
cost, pricing inefficiencies,
and logistical challenges.
So what does the future of
micro mobility look like?
To sustain this level of growth, micro
mobility companies need to become
operationally smarter, not just bigger.
The industry is evolving beyond simple
vehicle sharing, into data-driven,
AI powered urban mobility networks,
fleet efficiency, task automation,
and dynamic pricing will be key
factors that separate successful
companies from that fo that fail.
But how do we actually achieve this?
The answer lies in AI
driven decision making.
Companies that use AI to optimize
pricing, task allocation, and fleet
management will outperform competitors.
But before we talk about solutions,
let's first have a look at the biggest
challenges the industry faces today.
There are four major challenges we
face in micro mobility industry today.
Number one.
Parking and infrastructure limitations.
City struggle with poorly
accommodating fleets as there's
simply more demand and no more
fleets than parking infrastructure,
and that needs to be improved.
Number two, fleet and rebalancing
issues vehicles pile up in low demand
areas instead of being where they
needed to be to increase the usage.
So that requires incre
rebalancing the fleet.
To optimize where vehicles are at
the point where they need to be.
Three, high operational cost, manual
decision making leading to inefficiencies,
especially in the logistics industry
where it, which is the backbone of
the whole micro mobility industry at
the moment, which causes us to move
vehicles from one point to another place.
And last point is the pricing
strategies start static.
Pricing does not reflect real world
condition, and that needs to change
so we can actually in include the
real time data while giving prices.
One of the biggest levers that we
can pull to fix these inefficiencies
and easiest one solve is the pricing.
Pricing affects everything.
If it's too high, costs
inflate unnecessarily.
If it's too low tasks go
unfilfilled, because workers
won't take them and complete them.
Dynamic pricing is crucial because
it ensure tasks get completed
efficiently at the lowest possible cost.
Now let's talk about how AI pricing works,
that we understand why pricing
is crucial in micro mobility.
We are taking a deeper look about how
we are using AI in pricing and how we
are solving the problems that we are
facing in terms of pricing in micro,
multi industry traditional pricing
models assume that every task is equal,
but in reality, not all tasks have
the same complexity, urgency, or cost.
For example, moving an e scooter
two blocks away in low traffic
area should not cost the same as
retrieving a broken scooter from a high
congestion, high demand city center.
A rush hours there is, this is
where we are using and leveraging
AI powered pricing, and we are.
Getting into play, AI uses real-time
data to analyze demand fluctuations,
worker availability, and geographic vi
variables to adjust pricing dynamically
instead of a flat, inefficient price.
AI ensures that each task is priced
at its optimal rate to encourage
fulfillment while controlling costs.
But why doesn't fixed pricing work?
Let's explore the key flows of the
static and fixed pricing models.
Fixed pricing model has been in
the industry and has been the
standard for many years, but
there are major flaws with that.
Here's couple of four of the main
problems that we are seeing with it.
Number one, it ignores
real-time labor a avail.
If there are too few workers tasks pile
up and the work, the works will get into
delayed if there are too many workers.
And with the same pricing, we
will be paying the same price.
And that means we'll be overpaying
to workers for simple jobs by
looking at labor availability.
And similar to what Uber uses with
on the demand, comparing demand and
driver availability, excuse me, driver
and demand availability, we are able
to adjust the price accordingly.
So that's why it's important
to include the real time labor.
second one or least overpaying and
underpaying pricing doesn't change based
on location or demand, meaning some of
the workers reject low pay tasks while
others get overpaid for low effort jobs.
Going back to the example which we talked
in the previous slide, moving a scooter
from two blocks away versus moving
a scooter in a high congested area.
It's not the same job, so they need
to have a different pricing depending
on the situation that they're in.
Third one, first to consider task density.
Some of the areas need urgent vehicle
stri distribution, but workers have
no pricing incentivize to prioritize
these areas over these jobs.
That's one of the areas we can solve
by using AI pricing strategies.
Last one does not adjust for
real world demand shifts.
Mobility, demand changes based on
weather, traffic, and events, but static
pricing ignores all of these factors.
Clearly we need a better way to price
tasks dynamically and efficiently,
and this is what we are trying to
achieve, and this is where we are
using AI powered pricing changes.
AI powered pricing is designed to
adapt real world changes in real time.
Instead of setting one fixed price,
AI uses real live data, to adjust
pricing automatically based on a set
of key factors that is predetermined.
Again, think of it like Uber's
search pricing model when demand
is high and drivers are low.
Prices go up when demand
is low, prices are down.
The same princip applies
and the prices go up.
And the same thing happens in
the micro mobility task pricing.
But how exactly does AI determine
the right price for each task?
Let's take a look at the
key inputs AI considers.
AI pricing models don't just
make random adjustments.
They analyze multiple real-time factors
to calculate the most efficient price.
These include task density, how many
tasks that exist in a given area.
If there's a backlog, AI increases
payouts to attract workers.
Worker availability if
there are too few workers.
AI raises task prices to balance
supply and demand time sensitivity.
Urgent tasks, example, retrieving the
scooter from no parking zone are priced
at a higher priced to ensure fast
completion, environmental conditions.
AI are adjust pricing based on
weather, traffic, and city events
that affect the operational costs.
By combining all of these data points,
AI pricing ensures that every task is
priced at optimal level balance, optimal
level to balance, cost, and efficiency.
Now let's look at, let's
explore how the system actually
improves operational efficiency.
Number one, optimizes labor costs.
AI prevents unnecessary spending
while ensuring tasks are completed.
Number two, balances, demand and supply.
AI raises prices in underserved areas and
reduces them where work availability side.
Number three, incentivizes urgent tasks.
Critical jobs get higher payouts
to ensure quicker fulfillment.
Number four, eliminates
pricing inefficiencies.
No more overpaying for simple task
or underpaying for complex ones.
Last one, scales with business growth ai.
Pricing adapts automatically as fleet
size expands or changes or decreases.
instead of manually adjusting and
manually setting prices, AI automates
the process to keep costs low while
improving task completion rate and times.
let's break down the AI pricing
model and how it actually works.
AI pricing model follows a structure four
step process to continue optimize pricing.
Decision number one is data collection.
As you can imagine, AI aggregates
real time task worker and
citywide data collects them.
number two, predictive analysis
machine learning algorithms forecast
upcoming demand fluctuations.
Number three, dynamic adjustments.
AI updates pricing automatically in
real time based on the predictions.
Number four, continuous learning.
AI refines pricing strategies based on
historical data and performance outcomes.
The same AI driven pricing model is
being used in other industries as well.
Let's like a look at, Uber, how
Uber is using, similar strategies.
As Uber is one of the most
well-known examples of AI
powered pricing optimization.
Their search PRI pricing model
automatically increases right
prices when demand high, ensuring
the better, driver availability.
Uber uses AI to adjust first
based on realtime demand spikes
when rider demand is high.
Prices increased at truck
drivers, geographic hotspots.
Pricing adjust for airports, pickups,
stadiums, events, specific events
zones, weather based adjustments, bad
weather reduces drivers, so prices
tries to compensate, and Uber isn't the
only company using AI powered pricing.
Amazon also applied
dynamic pricing strategies.
Amazon continuously adjust product
prices based on market demand,
competitor pricing and inventory levels.
Their AI pricing model works
by analyzing competitor prices.
AI scans, competitor prices and
adjust Amazon prices accordingly.
Demand-based adjustments.
If demand for a product
rises, prices automatically
increase personalized pricing.
AI tracks customer behavior to offer
customized discounts on recommendations.
Now we ex explored how AI is pricing
works in different industries.
Let's wrap up with the key, takeaways.
Summarize, here's what we cover today.
Fixed pricing models are outdated.
Static pricing creates inefficiencies.
AI optimizes pricing based on real time
data, balancing cost and efficiency.
AI pricing is already used in
multiple industries, proven
successful in Uber and Amazon.
That concludes the presentation today.
Thank you very much for your time,
and thank you for joining the session.