Speaker 13: Hi
So think about the last time you took
a frontier model, AI LLM model, and
dropped it basically into a repository.
It felt like magic, right?
It understood the code.
It automatically indexed everything,
and you could ask questions, write
features, and debug issues, right?
Now think what happens when you
ask the same agent to fix a bug
that spans six microservices.
All of a sudden, it's flying blind.
So hi, my name is Lior, and in
this session, I'd like to talk
to you about how I went about and
solving this issue of enabling AI
on a large microservice system.
Okay?
I did it in a very practical way
without too many external tools
and how I think this can be applied
and used in other cases as well.
Now, this question comes up when we talk
about LLMs in a multi-repo microservices
kind of systems, where we like to leverage
AI to do more than just coding a specific
feature in a specific repo, right?
And we would like to use AI to help
us reason about the whole system,
the dependencies and the flows and
things that go around between the
different services in the system.
The reality of modern microservice systems
is that many of the flows in the systems
involve several disparate services.
It's often nearly impossible to
understand what goes on and, to
trace the dependencies and the
order of events or the flow of
calls of APIs between the services.
Even figuring out where the data
is used or how it's manipulated.
It's not that it's impossible
to figure out, it's just takes a
lot of time and energy to do it,
and it's definitely not scalable.
Now, this isn't an AI
problem, it's a human problem.
It existed before AI, but
AI highlights it, right?
Coding agents that we know
are becoming very good.
They are very good, especially if
you use them with frontier models.
When you connect a coding, such a coding
agent like CloudCode, Codex, Cursor, et
cetera, to a given repo with the right
harness, you're pretty much good to go.
They're doing a fine work.
But scaling this to a
complicated system often fails.
And coding agents, while they can
pretty easily index a given repo or a
small set of repos, what's known as a
workspace, this doesn't scale very well
or very easily to a larger system, right?
The gist of the answer usually
lies in providing the right
context, meaning documentation,
or at least a way to retrieve it.
The problem is that documentation
is hard to keep consistently.
Humans are notoriously bad at
documenting the system, at least over
any moderately long periods of time.
LLMs can help us understand and even
document a single repo, but this is not
enough for a system-level understanding.
We know that humans are historically bad
at documenting code, and on the other
hand, AI is hungry for such documentation
in order to operate effectively So while
the problem isn't inherent to AI, AIs
because of the scale and the expectations
on velocity and productivity that we have
of them actually highlight the problem.
At the same time, they also help
us with the solution because
handling text, matching semantics,
finding patterns is actually one
of the strong points for LLMs.
And because at the end of the
day it's a machine, it opens up
the possibility to scale this.
In a sense, the same AI that's hungry for
context can also produce that context.
If we design the extraction process
well, we can have agents that produce
documentation that is actually useful.
Humans are bad at maintaining
documentation, but AI is consistent,
it's tireless, and therefore scalable.
And this is essentially
the architecture hub.
It's a system where AI is used to extract
information from all the necessary
repos to extract useful information in
a useful way and do it consistently.
AI is also used to access that
information and connect the
different bits of the documentation.
At its core, from a technical
point of view, it's a simple Git
repo with a set of markdown files.
Each such file documents some aspect, and
this is done over a set of repositories.
There's nothing very fancy about it.
It's just files stored
in a shared Git repo.
This is actually by choice,
given the constraints and
principles we wanted to follow.
These are the core principles and
constraints that we went about
when building this, so we can
achieve the desired outcome with a
reasonable sort of time to market.
Zero infrastructure means that
there's no servers, there are
no servers to set up, right?
It's just a Git repo that's there.
It's accessible.
There's nothing to
monitor, nothing to set up.
It doesn't cost beyond
the Git repo, of course.
AI native means that there's no
special tooling as well, right?
It's just reading and writing files,
grep, and combined with shell scripts
or Python scripts, we can pretty
much do all we want with these files.
Diffables means that you
see exactly what changed.
You're basically relying on Git log, and
you can see exactly what changed and when.
You have a clear trace of changes of
the evolution of each of the repos
that you're documenting and following.
So you're just relying on Git log And
this also means that humans can review
the changes, can follow the change and
this helps in building trust, right?
Because humans view it.
It's important to be able to monitor
these changes, how the documentation
evolves, make sure it's accurate, right?
So we can build trust.
And of course, we want to scale
this, so this is how we scale it.
It's just a Git repo.
Let's review some of the
design decisions that we made.
First of all, we actually started out
considering databases, specifically
graph databases, in order to model
the system because that was natural
at first i-in terms of the intuition.
We actually did some POCs.
We also considered wiki platforms
and other documents embedded
in with the code itself.
But it turned out that flat
Markdown files, they won because
AI agents work natively with them.
No need for some extra tooling
for a graph da- graph database.
Git already gives you versioning,
gives you pull requests, so
you're able to review it.
The whole mechanism is there for free.
And Markdown is definitely
accessible to LLMs, very much easily
incorporated into context windows.
There's really zero
operational burden here.
It's just a Git repo.
There is a temptation to build a proper,
robust architecture that will handle
load or whatever, but we realized fairly
quickly that we are prematurely optimizing
here, and there's no real need for that.
So we went with the simpler more
accessible and faster method.
The next thing is about
modeling of the data in the hub.
So the unit of ingestion is a single repo.
This is what gets ingested into the hub.
But the documentation itself is
decomposed by different aspects
or facets, as we call them.
Each repo has several facet files,
each focusing on a different
aspect of the code of the service.
So we have domain models, APIs
exposed, events, dependencies,
and so on and so forth.
Now, we c-- y-you can think
of these lenses as different
lenses onto the same service.
They all read-- derive from the
same code and therefore they,
they are connected in some way.
Now, this is useful because questions
to the hub tend to focus on specific
aspects across different services,
which is the point of the hub, to
give us this system-level view.
So for example, if you're tracing a bug,
you should probably access the events
and the API documentation for the set
of services that you're looking at.
If you're trying to assess a blast radius
of a change or a new feature, for example,
you should probably load the dependencies
information for the given repo.
Okay?
Another consequence of the facet model is
that it allows us to ingest in parallel.
We-- I'll talk about this later, but
it basically allows us to ingest each
of these facets, and if something
went wrong with a specific file,
we can just re-ingest that one.
And to be honest, it's a natural
evolution of how this was built.
We actually started with documenting
just APIs, then events and domain models,
and it's just easier to add another
facet for all the documented repos
than-- rather than modifying a lot of
different files each for a different
repo when you add a new information.
Now, this simple organization of the
repo allows us to enforce a very simple
convention that translates directly
to a deterministic function, right?
Basically mapping a given facet and a
repo to a specific file in a repo name to
a specific file in the architecture hub.
There's no need to search a database.
There's no lookup that needs to be done.
There's no indirection.
If you know what you're looking for,
you already know the file name and
just go ahead and read it, right?
This is a simple heuristic, and because
it's simple, deterministic, it's really
cross-cutting, and it appears in all the
relevant skills ingesting and querying.
It's also part of implemented in different
scripts in the repo, in the architecture
hub, so it's useful and it's easy.
The ingestion itself, meaning
creating the documentation or updating
it, is actually where we start to
leverage the power of LLMs, right?
So we have an orchestrated agent
which does the ingestion, and
it invokes specific agents when
triggered, of course, and it takes
care of ingesting a given repo by
invoking different sub-agents, right?
Each sub-agent reads the same code of
the targeted repo, but it is guided to
extract slightly different information.
The agent, each su-such sub-agent
writes its own file to the architecture
hub, and the orchestrator basically
focuses on dispatching the work,
providing the relevant context,
reporting and validating the results.
Now, because each agent is independent,
they run concurrently, and this allows
me-- this allows us to run in parallel.
Of course, it's mean, it means
it's faster, and each sub-agent
does not pollute the context for
other sub-agents as well, right?
It also means that if one sub-agent
fails for whatever reason, it does
not interfere with other agents.
The orchestrator can identify
that this sub-agent has failed,
and it can retry that specific
facet instruction, extraction.
Okay?
The sub-agents are very
focused on a specific task of
extracting one specific facet.
Okay?
Now, the first problem we need to
tackle in order to make this useful
and of course scalable, is verifying
that documentation is correct.
Now, rechecking every claim in the
documentation automatically is hard.
It's really a lot of things to do.
I'll get to how we tackle that later.
But we first focused on
more technical verification.
For example, verifying that we indeed
have the documents in the right place,
that links are not broken, that metadata
that needs to be there as a front
matter in the file is actually present
and it's correct, that it aligns with
where the file is located, et cetera.
Now, at first, we built this into the
ingestion skill, basically instructing
the agent, the LLM, to verify itself.
This resulted in a sort of a
linting process that was unreliable.
But since each, in this case, every check
in this case is mechanical, basically,
we changed this linting process to
be implemented in code, in a script.
So now it's deterministic, it's definitely
more reliable, and it's cheaper.
It can run on every update, making
sure we're not missing or degrading
the state of the hub, right?
And this is an old lesson.
Don't use AI where you don't need
to use AI, and it works fine.
Now, an important part of making the hub
consistent, and like I said, scalable,
is to make sure it's always up to date
with code changes The CI process is a
natural fit for triggering these updates.
Since we already have a GitHub action
workflow running on commits and merges,
it was pretty easy to trigger the hub
update process on every merge to master
or main for the relevant repos The process
updates the documentation and runs the
lint Now, it's important to know that we
deliberately create a PR, a pull request,
that can be reviewed by humans, especially
at the beginning when we started.
Establishing people's trust in
documentation is important, and this
is where human review matters, right?
We actually spotted some issues and
fixed them as part of these reviews.
For example, we had a non-standard
pattern for sending events over Kafka
between services in some repos, right?
And this resulted in those
events not being documented.
They were missed.
So of course, after we identified
that, we fixed, we updated the
skill to recognize this non-standard
pattern, and voila, it works.
Of course, once we gain more confidence
and we see over time that this updates
is done and it's reliable, we can
automatically merge these changes.
So not necessarily strictly…
We don't necessarily need a PR
review by humans on every update.
Now, querying the hub is where we
actually start to get the value,
and this is where it's delivered.
Because we already have the documentation
in the hub, and i-in fact, it's
actually useful to have it there, and
people have started to look at it,
browsing the different documentation.
That in itself is already useful.
But we now have the option to provide
more elaborate and more focused answer
based on these documents, right?
The documents, to a large extent,
are a fundamental substrate, right?
The answers to queries is where
we actually get the value.
That's the, sort of the actual
product that we're giving.
So we have a query skill.
It has some variants That instructs
the LLM how to navigate the
architecture hub, how to connect the
information between different files,
and of course, how to report it.
These skills can now be used in
different scenarios and in systems that
are built on top of the hub, right?
Humans can of course use these skills
in IDE or any kind of AI-based tool
to get answers to whatever questions,
and this happens quite a bit.
But also other AI agents can
leverage the same skills.
For example, we have a separate
incident troubleshooting and analysis
agent that tries to understand, given
an incident, what's the problem,
analyzing what's going on in the system.
It has different tools to access
logs, to query logs, to access Jira
tickets Slack messages, et cetera.
But it also uses the architecture hub
to find out more information about the
system's architecture and guided where
to look information or what information
to look in other places as well.
Like I said, we have different
query skill variants.
The difference, the main difference is
the ability to run the query locally
if you have a local copy of the local
clone of the architecture hub, or the
ability to leverage Git-based tools
like GitHub command line interface or
GitHub MCP tools to read in places where
you don't have it cloned, so you can
read it remotely based on GitHub APIs.
So I touched this, upon this also
previously, and one challenge we had,
again, was that there was some variance
between the, in the documentation
itself between updates, right?
Of course, LLMs are probabilistic,
they are stochastic in their nature,
and so we… and therefore, they
provide different results on every
run, slightly different results.
So we had to implement some measures
to reduce the hallucination or major
changes that happen between files.
Changes still happen, but they're
more correct and more consistent now.
So one thing we did was to build, to
have the ingestion tool use templates,
structured templates, so the structure
of the documents is enforced and enforced
better, of course, and more consistent and
aligned between the different documents.
We also gave it instructions.
We insisted on every claim in
the documentation to include a
precise reference to the code,
a file name and line numbers.
And actually, this is probably the
mechanism that gave us the best results in
term of reliability of the documentation.
Now, a consequence of that is that once
this is available, this is also-- this
also allows humans, when reading the
documentation or given some answers,
to act-quickly find a place in the code
where this documented fact is relevant.
For example, where an event is
published or event is consumed,
or an API is called, et cetera.
It also provides a higher-level querying
agent the ability to identify the actual
code reference and to go and read the
actual code if necessary, or if required
to do some deeper dive into what's
going on or to a design, et cetera.
Of course, other mechanisms
play a part here as well.
I mentioned reviewing, I
mentioned linting as well.
And where possible, we'd like
to leverage as much as possible
deterministic code parsing.
For example understanding where
calls are made one factor that's
important to consider is the
uniformity of the code, right?
Repos that use internal libraries
consistently and patterns, or that
use established very structured
frameworks like NestJS in our case,
they will almost always have better
results in terms of consistency and
correctness of the documentation.
It's easier for the LLMs to
understand what's going on there et
cetera, and understand the pattern.
Older repos that are less
consistent or use less structured
framework, they usually give
the LLMs sort of a harder time.
So this is another factor to consider.
Another challenge, of course,
is with the cost, right?
Scaling, basically.
Sometimes API usage as well.
Now we know that each ingestion
consumes LLM tokens, right?
Full ingestions of o-over a hundred
repos becomes pretty expensive.
So we created the updated skills, and
the d-- what it does is basically diff
the documentation and of course, looks
at the difference of the code against,
and it diffs the c-- against the current
state of the architecture hub, and
it rewrites only the changes, right?
Other measures we put in to control
cost and allow better scaling is
to selectively, of course, trigger
the hub updates, so not on every
commit, only on merges to master
only to relevant repos as well.
We also have skills that focus
on ingesting a single facet.
So for example, if we change, like
the example I gave earlier about the
new pattern for identifying events,
if we change the specific facet, we
can just ingest that specific facet
over all the repos in the hub, right?
And this is a consequence of the design
decision I mentioned earlier about how
to let's say how to organize the hub
Of course, in case you want to ingest a
large number of repos, for example, you're
onboarding into the hub a set of repos,
then we have a script that organizes
the ingestion process, times it, so we
avoid rate limits of the API, et cetera.
Of course, when it comes to cost,
model selection plays a role as well.
And there's a sort of a balancing
act between choosing the most
expensive model which gives good
results and using a cheaper model
that gives good, still good results
or good enough at a much lower price
Now, so far we have discussed
technical challenges, and these are
all either solved or solvable in a
sense, or on the road to be solved.
But probably the biggest challenge
is getting people to trust and
use the hub effectively, right?
This is a people problem.
And to gain adoption, we need the hub
to show value, to save time and enable
processes today, not some based on some
a future promise or something like that.
We try to address the adoption by
meeting the developers where they
are, namely their IDEs, right?
So we have skills, which I mentioned
for querying and they are automatically
distributed as a plugin to the
dev team's cursor installations.
Like I said, we have code citations
in the documentation itself that are--
makes it easy to verify a chain of
provenance and link to therefore other
design or agent planning activities
Of course, the cursor harness provides us
with a natural language interface, chat,
agent chat, and easy access to available
tools, to the relevant tools like file
system reads and writes, searches as
well as Git tools, MCP tools, et cetera.
This in itself results in immediate value.
People just have it in their IDEs,
they just query the hub, and they use
it to, to do their feature designs.
And of course, once people adopt
it, it's easier for people to start
directing other agents that they are
building to use it because they see
how useful it is and start using it.
The demand is definitely there, and
given the right tools and valuable
and up-to-date information, the
learning curve is pretty low and
people can leverage it right now.
Another way to encourage the adoption is
to have what I call ready-made reports,
templates basically, as part of the hub.
These are essentially ready-made prompts
that are common and useful in different
scenarios that people often invoke.
They provide, the prompts provide explicit
workflows basically instructions for
agents on how to extract and connect the
information of the hub in these cases.
For example, we have a dependency
map report, which given a specific
repository name, it scans the hub
and provides a comprehensive report
on all the dependencies incoming
and outgoing, to and from this repo.
This includes any clients making
HTTP calls consumers of events
from this repo or events this
repo consumes from other repos.
It even traces dependencies between
i-- with other repos using im-- by
identifying implicit data dependencies,
where data is written and read from the
same database by different services.
Other examples of reports are specifying
or analyzing a complete flow, right?
Both a de- a technical detailed
flow as well as a sort of a
product-focused description.
This product focus description, what's
called here a plain English explainer,
is actually a nice example of the power
of this approach of u- and using LLMs.
It allows the product manager to
understand a complicated flow across
domains without diving into the different
technical details like Kafka topics API
input and output shapes, DB schemas.
Usually, these are irrelevant
for the product manager trying
to understand a given flow.
It's also a nice example for how
using LLMs, this report actually
combines information from other sources
as well, help pages configuration
of feature flags, et cetera.
Another example of a report is to
get a comprehensive architecture
overview of a given repo, right?
A developer onboarding joining a team
can easily just, query, "Give me the
architecture overview of this repo,"
and it gets a comprehensive architecture
view, including dependencies to other
places in the system and where this
repo and its functionality is used.
for this service.
All the reports result in
human-oriented, in a sense, reports
which should be easy to consume.
Some of them even have HTML variants
with diagrams and everything, and
these HTML di- variants sometimes
are even interactive, so it's
very easy to follow and consume.
Now, this provides, of course, like I
said, another adoption incentive, right?
People use them to understand the
system better in a very focused
way, what they're looking…
the information they're looking for.
By default, the reports do
not cover actual code, okay?
Though you can prompt it
to include code details.
But it provides a focused index
to a specific problem or piece
of information which you can then
use to further investigate or have
your agent investigate further.
But I think what's most important is that
these reports, because they are backed by
the architecture hub that is updated from
the code, means that we eliminate this
problem of documentation drift that we
usually have with documentation and code.
And this is an important point
because documentation is traditionally
thought of as a human-focused
activity, both producing documentation
and consuming it, of course.
And the demand for, accurate system-level
context by AIs and the drive to
have AI tackle more complicated
problems autonomously, right?
Coupled with the LLM's ability to follow
natural languages, this highlighted
the problem and made this also a
machine problem, not just a human one.
And while the original and main motivation
is for AI to use the architecture hub,
it's also extremely useful for humans.
But it's more than just useful.
In a lot of ways, it's critically…
It's critical that it's usable by
humans because it provides us with
a way to more easily verify what the
AI is doing, and also to verify our
understanding of the system itself,
not just what the AI is doing.
So we can trust the AI better, but
also we can understand, verify our
understanding as well and check ourselves.
Just the mere fact that it's written
down and it's up-to-date and correct
gives us a lot of benefit and helps
our understanding Now, so far, we
discussed the architecture hub as mainly
a technical documentation hub and we
already realize its value in that respect.
The need, however, for accurate
information on how the system works
goes beyond the technical details
or the API shapes, like I said,
or Kafka topic names, et cetera.
It's not just developers who are looking
to understand that the way things actually
work, not how they are supposed to work.
And having a consistent and up-to-date
machine-processable information hub allows
us to leverage it in other functions.
The impact can actually be wider
than just code or system design.
For example we can have the UX designers
or product managers or customer
support team interact with the hub to
understand how the system is currently
behaving or how it can behave, not
just how it's supposed to behave.
Of course, when we're talking
with non-developers, the less
technical people, we need to,
again, meet them where they are.
This usually means translating
the technical domain to a more
business-oriented language, a
focus on business terminology.
This is another case where the LLM
strength in understanding semantics
enables us to more easily bridge this gap.
Okay?
Now, when we turn to integrate
this, we already have had our own
constraints as well, because product
managers and designers already have
their own agents helping them to do
their work, and they have their own
modeling of the business domains.
Similarly, customer supporting have
their own agent working on triaging
tickets automatically, right?
So the business domain is already
pretty much established at this point.
Our work, in this case, was to
provide a sort of an automatic
mapping between the business domain
language and the technical domain.
And the business domain is
maintained outside the hub, right?
So we established another documentation
aspect, so to speak, in the hub, a
mapping of business concepts or business
terms to the relevant technical repos
with the respective role that these
repos play for example, for these roles.
For example the financials service is
the owner of the fees concept, but it
is a consumer of a reservation concept.
This mapping is done
automatically by LLMs.
But note here that the validation
of the mapping is slightly more
tricky because we're not-- we can't
anchor it b- immediately in code.
It's basically anchoring some business
concept or term to a technical domain.
So we've established an audit
process and any mappings that are
of low confidence, guessed by the
LLMs, are to be audited by human.
But once a human actually reviews
this and confirms these mappings,
they survive future updates.
They don't need to be audited again.
Now, of course, given that we have
these mappings, the query skills are
updated to take them into account.
So when asked a question about a general
business term without an explicit
mentioning, without an explicit mention
of a repo or a service the query skill
of course consults these mappings and
can help and find a more reliable answer.
Okay?
These mappings basically
provide extra information,
extra intelligence to the hub.
And this opens the door for the
hub to be used in other places in
the software development lifecycle
beyond code design, right?
And hopefully also allow for
bigger productivity gains
And this is here a sort of a
summary of the key takeaways, I
think, from this presentation.
Things that I've talked about
and mentioned that I think are
key to creating such a project.
Starting with flat files and
leveraging Git helps us to start
fast, and it's pretty good enough.
It has a lot of the capabilities
that we already need.
Decomposing by facets, I mentioned why
it's useful and helpful, especially
in a hub that is supposed to bridge
between different repos, right?
Of course, making as a consequence
of this, making the mapping of the
finding the information pretty easily
and computable in a sense, right?
Using AI for reasoning, but leverage
scripts as much as possible as
deterministic code to verify things.
Automating this in order to scale
this, of course, and keep it up to
date so it's useful, but allow for
humans to review this easily so it's
more reliable and trusted there.
Citations, so references to
the code, is actually, I think,
critical in this kind of job.
It reduces hallucinations, and it's very
useful for humans and other agents when
querying or looking for information.
Okay, and querying is actually really
where the value is, because it's not
just about having the documentation
and being able to browse it, it's
being able to connect the dots, and
this is an important step of this.
Okay?
Just to give you a sense
of the implementation these
are roughly the numbers.
This was executed mostly
by a single person.
And of course, this includes a lot
of back and forth, some wrong turns,
rewrites, learnings, and troubleshooting.
Okay?
And there are actually more
features that I did not mention.
The initial prototype took about one
or two weeks, and most of the time
was spent on iterating on extraction
quality, adding facets building
the automation layer, et cetera.
So this is roughly how long it took.
Now, if you want to follow a similar
or the same path and pattern for
implementation, this is how I
would suggest to execute this.
Start with a design foundation, right?
How to organize the hub which
facets you want to attend.
You don't need to necessarily list
and create all of them at once,
but start with one or two or three.
Okay?
Start by writing specific
extraction prompts and iterating
and making sure that they are good.
Next, you need to provide a way to run
your queries and access the data easily.
So you need to establish your
index, how it's organized or
routing in the hub, how to actually
use find and use the information.
You should, at this point, write your
query skill, basically instructing agents
how to find and use the information.
And of course, the final
step is to establish a way to
scale it, how to consistently
extract the information, okay?
And verify that it doesn't drift,
and the structure remains consistent
because it's also important for
querying, reliability of querying.
Okay?
So thank you, and I hope you
find it useful and enjoyable.
You're welcome to contact me.
I'll be happy to hear feedback
and other points, notes, thoughts.
Thank you very much.