My name is.
Today we're gonna discuss about
realtime data analytics in the
cloud, enabling enterprise making.
We're gonna discuss about how, modern
cloud architecture and scalable
infrastructure can revolutionize your
organization's ability to harness data
and enhance operational efficiency and
deliver superior customer experiences.
So the global cloud analytics market
is experiencing a rapid growth valued
at 22 point 23.2 billion in 2020, and
projected to, expand at, CAGR of 24.3%.
Increasing adoption of cloud-based
business intelligence tools across
various industries, particularly in
banking, finance, and insurance sector.
So the core components of realtime
analytics are data ingestion layer,
data crossing, layer, storage layer.
So we're going to talk in
detail about how these layers,
will perform their operations.
So in data ingestion, layer sing,
seamlessly, integrates real-time data,
streams from iot devices, applications,
and third party source, as while
maintaining data quality and consistency.
So in the processing layer, we leverage,
a distributed comp computing and in
memory processing to execute complex
analytics ML models and business logic
with millisecond latency in the storage
layer, it implements hybrid storage
architecture, combining in memory casing
and persistent storage to optimize both.
Speed and durability.
Modern real-time analytics systems are
built on three, interconnected pillars
of functions in perfect synchronization.
The data ingestion layer acts as a robust
front door, handling massive throughput of
up to millions of events per second while
ensuring data integrity and for format.
Consistency this continuous stream
flow into processing layer while
sophisticated distributed algorithms
and machine learning models transform
raw data into business insights
within milliseconds, the storage layer
completes the, this architecture by
implementing a hybrid approach combining,
blazing fast in memory processing.
persistence towards to maintain both
performance, and data durability.
This carefully orchestrated system
empowers organizations to make
precise, data driven at speed
of their business operations.
So it's
performance.
So Max Throughput is about 800 K. Stable
throughput is about 300 K and utilization
threshold around eight per 80%.
The data ingestion layers serves
as a critical foundation of
realtime analytics success.
Advance streaming platforms
like Apache Kafka deliver ex
exceptional throughput capabilities.
Which perform with performance carefully
balance between message volume and size
to ensure consistent service quality
organization should implement proactive
monitoring and maintain utilization below
ET threshold, which allows, headroom
for unexpected traffic spikes while,
System pon, responsiveness processing,
layer optimization, horizontal scaling.
we have three components here,
horizontal scaling, resource allocation,
consistent performance, horizontal,
scaling, es, cloud native, elasticity.
To automatically scale,
processing capability kept up
to 300% higher workloads while
maintaining consistent performance.
This ensures response times stay
within 10% of baseline event
during peak demand periods.
efficiency by.
Targeting 60 to 70% CP
utilization in normal operations.
This creates a safe buffer zone as
performance degrades rapidly when
utilizing exceeds 85%, leading to, missile
processing deadlines and, potential system
bottlenecks, consistent performance.
So implement robust scaling mechanisms.
Guarantee, stable response times
within one 50 milliseconds, window.
During dynamic scaling events,
this architecture ensures,
performance with 95% of, requests
completing within 2200 milliseconds,
even at a maximum system load.
Storage layer, considerations.
So while, we discuss about the
storage layer consideration, we
mainly consider three points.
Yeah.
Throughput performance, tied data,
retention and scaling and late Z profile.
So in right throughput performance.
distributor storage systems maintain right
throughput of up to, 100,000 events per
second, per node when properly configured
with the performance, heavily dependent
on data, partitioning strategies.
tide data retention systems, implementing
tide storage, strategies, demonstrate
30% improvement in query response
time, compared to our single tire
implementation, particularly for data
less than 24 scaling latency profile.
so storage systems, maintains consistent
latency, profiles up to 85% capacity
threshold beyond this point, right?
Latencies increase by approximately
20% for every 5% increase in.
85, 80 5% to monitor the system to
80%, 85% of the capacity threshold,
event driven architecture.
So there are four, key points
we need to discuss here.
One is handles, five 50,000
plus, concurrent events per
second with zero message losses.
So low latency sub, hundred
milliseconds response.
Time for real, time making improved
efficiency, 35 per percent.
Faster processing with 40%
lower, resource utilization.
So optimal, batch size.
So 25 event, micro batches.
Maximize throughput, latency, balance,
event driven, architecture serve as
a, cornerstone for modern realtime
analytics enabling, data processing
and immediate business insights.
empirical testing demonstrate,
35% improvement in processing
speed while reducing.
Infrastructure costs by 40% compared
to traditional batch processing system.
By implementing a precise micro
batch sizing and intelligent
event, routing organizations can
achieve the optimal balance between
system response and, resource
efficiency, security, and compliance.
Encryption overhead.
enterprise grade AEs encryption
provides robust security with a minimal
impact, adding only 2.3%, to crossing
time while ensuring complete data
protection across distribution system.
So with, with less,
process processing time.
We can incorporate, encryption.
So second authorization,
authentication performance.
So on high performance authentication
systems, deliver exceptional
reliability, with 99.5% successful
verification rates while maintaining
rapid sub hundred millisecond response
time for seamless user experience.
When it comes to compliance monitoring,
advanced distributed monitoring
capabilities handle thousand events
per second in real time, maintaining
95 per 95% accuracy, and, compliance
verification across all regulated
frameworks and internal policies.
So realtime security, enforcement
processes, thousand or 10,000, compliance,
rules simultaneously identifying, and
flagging violations within 2.5 seconds
to enable immediate, corrective action
and maintain continuous compliance.
Performance considerations.
So latency management, network
latency, in distribution systems
includes trans transmission delay
of 0.0 4.42, 3.3 millisecond.
Prop delays between, 0.5 milliseconds
per hundred, km Processing delays
is between 0.522 milliseconds
per no, querying delays 5 2 50
milliseconds, about 80% utilization.
Processing or optimization.
Adaptive resource management systems
maintains the, stable performance
when processing load varies between
42 80, 80 5% of maximum capacity.
Optimal resource utilization is
achieved when processing tasks are
distributor distributed across.
For both, computational and bandwidth
resources, scalable patterns,
system, implementing dynamic
resource, allocation can achieve
25% better resource utilization.
Then static allocation
approaches, maintaining resource
utilization between 60 to 80%.
provides an optimal balance between
performance and scalability, monitoring
and, observation, observa variability.
One is, when it comes to system health
monitoring, machine learning based
monitoring systems can achieve, prediction
accuracy rates of 87% of system.
Reducing files, positive rates to 0.3%.
This approach has demonstrated a
40% reduction in system downtime
compared to traditional threshold
based monitoring, business metric
monitoring organizations implement,
implementing a comprehensive real time
monitoring issue at 25% improvement.
Making, speed and reduce response time
to, market changes by an average of
15 minutes, compared to traditional
batch processing, approaches.
observe, observability,
implementation system, implementing.
Full Stack Observatory can achieve 94%
visibility into system behavior patterns.
Distributed, tracing with a 5%
scalable rate, provides, statistically,
significant insights while
maintaining system or below 1.5%.
Conclusion.
so critical enabler, cloud-based,
real time analytics can revolutionize
enterprise decision making, transform,
transforming raw data streams into
actionable insights within seconds, which
enabling organizations to respond strictly
to market changes and customer needs.
Balanced approach.
success in realtime analytics demands
a holistic strategy that, integrates
high performance data ingestion,
efficient processing, architecture,
robust security protocols and continuous
compliance monitoring, all working
in harm, harmony to deliver reliable,
actionable, and, intelligence.
Future outlook.
as cloud infrastructure continues to
advance, realtime analytics will become
more sophisticated and, democratize
empowering organizations of all sizes too.
harness, predictive insights,
automate processing, and drive.
Their operations.
Thank you for watching.