Hi everyone, and welcome.
I'm LIC Pass from Marto ai.
ATO is a platform for
managing your gen AI assets.
This includes your prompts, model
configurations, data sets, and events
from the minute you write your initial
prompt testing and experimenting with it
to make sure it performs as you expect
to the time it's running in production
with detailed observability and metrics.
In this session, we will take a
look at the key role evils play in
bringing your Gen AI up to production.
We'll see the process of designing,
evaluating, and refining prompts
for an LLM based application.
So let's start.
So what are evils?
Evils are a systematic method we
use to measure the performance
capabilities and basically the
replies that we get from AI models.
They are key in determining how well
a prompt or a model output meets the
specific objectives that we have.
The key features for evals are being
measurable, being able to quantify
various aspects like accuracy, relevancy,
structure, repeatability, meaning
consistent assessment across different
iterations, and being actionable,
provide the insights we need to refine
the prompt and to improve the outcome.
So what have changed?
Software testing had
been around for decades.
Why are we talking about
a new method of testing?
The first thing is the boundary.
We move from a very well-defined
and structured output and error
format in traditional APIs
to complex and unpredictable
formats, errors and mistakes.
We are moving toward a non-deterministic
world where even similar and
sometimes identical input receives
or might receive different outputs.
So we are moving from a very clear pass
or fail criteria to a world where we
would measure different aspects of the
replies that we get, and we will compute
some kind of a scoring that will tell
us if we are hitting the target or not.
EVAs transform prompt engineering
from guesswork into a scientific
process by making interactions
measurable and repeatable.
They will ensure LLM output aligns
with our business objectives, enable
data-driven decision making and
prompt refinement and reduce the risk
of unforeseen issues in production.
So let's take a look
at an example use case.
This is our demo application.
Imagine that you were given a task
of developing a technical support
bot for a company called upma.
The app Master Support bot
is designed to help technical
users find answers efficiently.
It pulls information from various sources
and a knowledge base, and it aims to
provide an accurate, concise response.
Our challenge is to craft a
prompt that will ensure the bot
delivers high quality answers.
So let's take a look at our initial
prompt and the app master support bot.
Here's the first version of
our app Master Support bot.
Let's try to ask something.
We got a very simplistic reply and not
something that would really help our
users, so let's see how we can improve.
So we got our vote up and running,
but how do we measure success?
We'll need to define criteria
for each business requirement.
We got, for example, response relevancy.
Its ability to build on the knowledge
we pass in the context, et cetera.
We'll use different evil
methods for each criteria.
We'll see some examples in a minute, and
we will build test data, which we can use
to iterate and have a complete test case.
We've seen that good evils are aligned
with the business goals that we have.
In our specific example, that master
support bot evils could measure
accuracy, politeness, response
times, and the expected output
format that our code expects to get.
So let's first analyze the
different types of evils we can use.
In the first category is
the content-based events.
In our example, we have a data
set with samples for expected
input and expected output.
We can compare the actual
responses that we will get in our
experiment with the expected one.
Such a comparison will use vector
similarities, which is a mechanism
for determining the contextual
distance between two text box.
Other content-based evils might be
checking for existence of certain
words, maybe checking for the
absence of sensitive data, et cetera.
The second category is the format.
It's very often a requirement to return
a response in a very specific format.
It can be that our code depends on such
a structure or fits the user expectation.
Either way, we will need to
look at the format and validate
it against our requirements.
In our example, the code
expects a certain JSO schema.
We will see in a minute how to verify it.
Third category is various qualities
like making sure that the bot is using
the documents that we are passing as
part of the context and is grounding
the answers based on these documents.
And of course, other guard rails or
non-functional aspects like politeness.
In our use case, which is one of the
requirements we got for building the bot.
We can use different mechanisms
for running our evals.
This can be deterministic or rule-based
evals for checking, text matching,
for example, or regular expressions
or model-based events that can use LLM
as a judge or other models for other
capabilities like vector similarity.
In our example, we will combine both
mechanisms where possible we will
be using a rule-based one and where
required we will use a model-based one.
The pros and cones are quite obvious.
The deterministic ones will be
very fast, very cheap to use,
but sometimes limited and rigid.
While the LLM based ones will be
very flexible, we can basically
ask any question we would like.
They will be relatively easy to use,
but they can be expensive and they
themselves are non-deterministic.
So we need to be very careful
of how we measure or how we look
at the answers that they reply.
So let's see a few examples we will
use to optimize our app support bot.
The first one, vector similarity.
As part of the requirement for our
support bot, we got an example of how
an expected output should look like.
This includes both the structure and
the content we expect to get for a
specific set of inputs or user question.
When we run the actual experiment,
we get a reply back from the LLM.
We can read all this text
and try to evaluate ourselves
if they are similar or not.
But in our case, we will
use vector similarity.
That will save us the trouble of
going through all those details.
The response that we got back is very
similar from a contextual point of view.
The second evil will be
a response format eval.
Here we can use a very simple,
deterministic based evil for checking,
for instance, certain regular
expression that will match the expected
J schema that our code requires.
And lastly, we will use
some LLM based evals.
In this example, we wanna verify
that the bot answers in a polite
manner and mentions that it is the
friendly app master support bot.
So we will use another
model to verify this.
So how do we put those evils into action?
We've defined our evils criteria.
What's next?
We will now experiment with our prompt.
We will first make a template out
of our prompt putting variables
or placeholders in the places
we wanna inject dynamic data.
We'll prepare test data, which will be our
data set, and we'll iterate over it with
the evil metrics that we've just defined.
We mentioned the need
to prepare test data.
What makes a good data set
for such an experiment?
The data should represent real world
scenarios, meaning the inputs that we
expect users will enter in our upma
support board app, but we should also
make sure to include data that represents
edge cases and unexpected inputs
that users might enter into our app.
So let's see a live experiment of
everything that we've just defined.
So this is our app support bot notebook.
It includes the prompt and
the instructions that we give
the LLM, the dataset that we
will use for our experiment.
And we already have a couple
of evals that we've defined.
The first one is using for validating that
the bot is answering in a polite manner.
The second one is a simple deterministic
one, making sure that we create the user.
Let's add a couple of others who
will pick the relevancy evil for
making sure that the results are
grounded with the documents that
we've passed, and we can even validate
the JSON schema that we require.
In a deterministic manner
using a regular expression.
We'll run the experiment and
see the results that we get.
So as we can see, we get a relatively
poor results on several of our
ours, including the Jason Schema.
And we can see the individual
failures and specific inputs.
So let's go ahead and improve the prompt
and the instructions we gave to our bot.
We will include a more detailed
example for the response format
as well as strengthening other
instructions, and we'll run it again.
We can also pick another model
and see if that will have any
effect on the results that we get.
So we'll pick CLO and we'll run it again
and let's take a look at the responses
that we got and the evil results.
So as you can see, we got a much better
results this time, and all of our evals
have passed with 100% success rate.
This is true for both
models that we've tried.
So the improvement we did to our
instructions made the difference.
Let's compare all three
experiments that we've run.
And as you can see, we improved
the instructions we gave.
We still get very high similarity
score comparing to the expected results
that we gave as part of the dataset,
but this time we have a much higher
success rate, actually a hundred
percent success rate in our events.
So let's push our new prompt
into production and see
how the new bot behaves.
We'll ask the same question,
and this time we get a much more detailed
answer with various options that would
assist the user in solving his problem.
So to sum up, we've seen how we can
use evils to iterate and improve
until we reach a prompt that
satisfies our business requirements.
Thank you very much for your time today.
I hope this session had been insightful.
If you have any questions,
comments, or would just like to
keep in touch, please follow us
on LinkedIn or visit our website.
And you are welcome to
try us out at arra ai.