Speaker 2: Hey.
Hi, everyone.
Thank you for joining in.
I'm Ananya, and I work as a
GenAI developer advocate at AWS.
My primary role not only relies
on building AI solutions, but also
helping developers and innovators
build and ship their AI products
from prototype to production.
So I'll start with a
small confession today.
I actually built a game, and I assumed
the hardest part of it would be reasoning.
And I had this AI agent running on modern
LLMs, access different tools, load game
state, have retrieval of information
from different sources, and everything
we usually associate with intelligence.
Still, my game failed
eight of the ten times.
At first, I blamed prompting, then I
blamed model, then I blamed architecture,
but after digging into failures, I
discovered something very surprising.
So my agent wasn't making bad decisions.
It was making decisions based
on the bad memories it had.
And that is what my talk is all
about today, where I show how
to make agents more smarter.
How do you make them remember the
right context at the right time?
So to study these memory failures,
I built a Horcrux hunt game.
And if you are familiar with the Harry
Potter series, the objective of Harry
is to find and destroy Horcruxes,
whereas Voldemort's objective is
equally different: to make Harry believe
wrong things and hide the Horcruxes.
So for my game, there are 50 turns
actually, and every turn Harry
gets to collect signals, update
beliefs, and every turn Voldemort
will introduce some uncertainty
through relocations or dis- decoys.
Now, notice something very important.
This problem is not a search problem.
It's how you reduce uncertainty.
So Harry wins by reducing entropy,
and Voldemort wins by increasing it.
That makes memory the central
challenge of this game.
So if Harry forgets useful information
or remembers a false one, the game
is effectively lost on his end.
These are the actual observations
I have from the actual failures.
The interesting thing is that none
of them were reasoning failures.
The model knew how to think.
It simply had the wrong
information available.
For example, Harry destroys a location
that was once valid, but Voldemort
has already moved the Horcrux.
That's stale memory.
Another example where Harry revisits
a location thinking there's a Horcrux,
but it's already confirmed empty.
So the signal existed, but it was buried
under the tokens That's retrieval failure.
And perhaps the most common issue
is that agents remember everything,
which sounds good until context
becomes so large that the generation
becomes slow, expensive, and costly.
So the key lesson here is most
agent failures are because of memory
architecture failures, which are
disguised as reasoning failures.
Now, when people talk about
context windows, they usually
think of them as a storage limit.
I think of them as compounding tax because
you have 50 turns, and every turn you are
replaying the context again and again.
Now, imagine reading an entire book,
but every time you want to turn a page,
you are rereading the whole book again.
That's effectively what many
agents in production do today.
As the game progresses in my example,
the context is growing, latency is
growing, therefore, the cost also grows.
And when you add multiple agents,
the problem becomes worse.
This is why memory design becomes
a scaling problem long before
it becomes a reasoning problem.
So now I want to introduce a slightly
different way of thinking about
memory through information theory.
So at the start of the game,
Harry knows almost nothing.
All 15 locations that he has to
search the Horcrux is equally likely
Uncertainty is at its maximum.
Entropy is high.
But as and when turns keep on playing,
the game is being played, observations
arrive, and entropy should decrease.
The agent becomes more confident, more
focused, more certain that a Horcrux
is hidden at a particular location.
But Voldemort actively injects entropy.
Every relocation and every decoy
increases the uncertainty in the game.
This led me to the realization that memory
architecture is really entropy management.
Every memory decision answers
just one question: Does this help
reduce uncertainty or increase it?
And that's the lens we'll use
for the rest of the talk today.
So after studying the failures, I ended up
with a simple three-layered memory model.
Layer one is working memory.
This is what the LLM sees currently.
It's expensive, it's limited,
it's precious, but it also helps
finding the current context.
Layer two is retrieval memory,
where the information what agent
can access is when it is needed.
Not everything, only the
relevant information.
And layer three is the persistent
memory, the long-term memory that records
everything the agent has ever experienced.
The most important idea here is
to separate the responsibilities.
Each layer has its job.
The first one gives the current
context, the second one gives the
retrieval context, and the third
one saves information over time.
And when these layers start doing
each other's job, your system
becomes expensive and fragile.
But if they stick to their lanes,
that's when your system is optimal So
my first optimization is very simple.
Stop sending everything to an LLM.
Most agent systems treat context
as historical transcript, but the
model doesn't need your history.
It needs state.
So instead of sending information
of all the 50 turns, observations
of all the 50 turns, I send a
compressed representation, a small
belief map, valid actions, remaining
budget, the information of cooldowns.
And the result is ninety-seven
percent token compression.
But here's the surprising part.
Performance also improved because
now the model has stopped getting
distracted by irrelevant details,
and it is becoming better at context.
The second one was probably
the biggest breakthrough.
So instead of asking the LLMs to
remember probabilities, we let the
maths remember the probabilities.
There's a belief map which updates outside
of the model, so the LLM receives only
the output which has highest probability.
For example, instead of sending remaining
information and also history information
from 50 turns, the model sees the next
probable location is Hogwarts with
thirty-four percent probability or
Chamber of Secr-Secrets with fifty percent
probability Eight to 15 tokens, not 5,000.
That's the powerful design pattern.
And whenever memory can be
represented as structured state,
use structure instead of language.
Because language is
expensive, math is cheap.
The next insight was not that every
decision deserves the same memory budget.
Not every decision is worth an LLM call.
Sometimes the answer is obvious,
so why do we need to spend tokens?
Why even call an LLM for that matter?
When uncertainty is genuinely high,
that's when richer context becomes
valuable, and we definitely need
to call an LLM for that reason.
We route the memory dynamically
based on the entropy.
So if there's low
uncertainty, use heuristics.
If the uncertainty is medium,
use compressed memory.
And if the uncertainty is
high, use richer retrieval.
For example, if Harry is after destroying
the Horcruxes and he finds a particular
Horcrux in a location, the obvious
action by Voldemort would be either
to hide that particular Horcrux in a
different location, that is relocate,
or maybe deploy a decoy instead.
So this particular action is obvious.
We don't need to, again and again,
take an LLM call for this reason.
So what happens as a result?
The system spends memory
only where it matters.
And the final one, the persistent memory.
So this layer solves the problem many
agent systems generally struggle with.
Like, how do you remember everything
without sending everything to an LLM?
The answer is persistence.
Store abundantly, retrieve selectively,
present to the LLM minimally.
Everything lives in persistence.
You will save all the information,
but only the relevant information
gets passed on to the LLM.
This prevents two common failure modes.
First, you do not overload
the model with whole history.
And second, you forget
everything between turns.
So persistent memory gives
you the third option.
So if you want to remember just
one architecture diagram from
this talk, let it be this one.
Notice where the LLM sits.
It's actually a very small component.
Most of the intelligence
happens outside the model.
The belief management, the constraint
solving, entropy calculations,
persistence, compression of tokens.
The LLM is not the memory system.
The LLM rather consumes the memory
system, and that architectural
distinction actually changes everything.
So now let's look at the outcomes.
The same game, the same agents, and
having the same reasoning capabilities.
Only the memory architecture has changed.
Now, the results are dramatic, where we
have ninety-seven percent fewer tokens,
seventy-five percent lower latency, and
more than eighty percent cost reduction.
Most importantly, the win
rate has also doubled.
This is why I argue memory deserves
more attention than model selection.
Often, the biggest performance
gain come from memory architecture
and not larger models So let me
leave you with five principles.
The first, an LLM should consume
memory, not produce memory.
Second, match the memory
depth to decision difficulty.
Third, compression belongs at
boundary, not inside the model.
Fourth, persist abundantly,
retrieve selectively, and
present minimally to an LLM.
Finally, less context often leads to
better decisions because attention
is a scarce resource, even for LLMs.
So the systems that win won't necessarily
be the ones with biggest context windows.
They'll be the ones that know
what to remember and what not to
remember So I end where I started.
My agent had reasoning, it had
tools, it had retrieval, and still
it failed because intelligence
wasn't the bottleneck, memory was.
And as we build increasingly
agentic systems, memory
becomes infrastructure for us.
And the question no longer remains: How
much context can I fit and remember?
The question becomes: What
information deserves to be remembered?
Because your agents don't fail
because they cannot reason.
They fail because they
remember the wrong things.
With that, I say the future of
agents isn't bigger context windows.
It's better memory architectures.
Thank you so much for listening.