Speaker 22: Hey there.
Welcome to this talk on Your AI
Has Too Much Access: Deterministic
Authorization for Coding Agents.
My name is Sohan Maheswar.
I'm a lead dev advocate at Authzed.
I've worked in the industry close
to 17 years now, and in fact, I've
spent about 10 years in the world
of AI, first at a natural language
processing startup back in 2015, and
then also in the Amazon Alexa team.
So I've really seen the
change in how we use AI.
And right now, all of us are using
coding agents for our day-to-day work.
But I think, and I'm pretty sure this
is pretty sure everyone thinks this, but
your AI coding agent has too much access.
I'm here to tell you about why
security and authorization is important
for what your coding agent can do.
Let's get started.
The new normal.
Oh, let me just share my screen.
The new normal basically is to have
Claude Code or Codex plan with it
and then let it run unattended.
In fact, there's a flag on Claude also
called something like dangerously skip
permissions, where Claude will skip
almost all of the permissions that it asks
you to do something, and it just goes.
I like to call it YOLO mode.
Really wouldn't recommend
doing that, especially if you
work in enterprise, et cetera.
Because without any boundaries,
something like a Claude Code can take
any action its context suggests, and
this could lead to security breaches.
In fact sure, I might say this because I
work in a startup that does things like
app permissions and security, but if you
look at OWASP's list, for those of you all
who might not might not be familiar, OWASP
is Open Worldwide App Security Project.
It's an industry body, and every
four years or so, they make a
list of top 10 risks to web apps.
And guess what has been number
one in the last two lists?
Broken access control.
It was number one in 2021, and
in November last year, just a few
months ago, it was number one again.
And here's the scary stat: 100%
of apps tested had at least one
broken access control issue.
That is scary.
And this w- this maybe predates
AI a little bit as well.
Maybe we just got the end of
the huge wave of generative AI.
So with everyone using autonomous
agents and coding assistants,
this can be very dangerous.
And in a blog post written by Anthropic
few months ago, so I think sometime
earlier this year, I've linked it at the
bottom they actually did a test on Claude
Code's auto permission mode, and they
found that 17% it had a false negative
rate on dangerous actions which is a
pretty scary trade-off if you think about
it, where it, it-- you give permissions to
what it thinks, is okay to run, but then
it actually causes some problem, and 17%
is not really a great number for that.
So the key takeaway from the session
today should be to actually really
think about what permissions you're
giving your coding agent, and I'm going
to tell you how you could do that via
code using open source code And here's
the key reason why you should do this.
LLMs and AI is inherently probabilistic,
which means it is looking at probabilities
and giving you the best possible outcome.
It's not what is called deterministic,
where 100 out of 100 times you ask
a question and hun- sorry, 100 times
you ask a question and 100 times it
should give you the same answer back.
That is deterministic.
That being said, you can use deterministic
enforcement with your probabilistic
AI to get maximum benefits of your AI
and to maintain, security boundaries
and guardrails and privacy, especially
in enterprise So before we jump into
like the weeds and the technical
details, a very quick primer on
the world of authorization itself.
And when we say the word auth, we
conflate it with authentication,
which is identity, who you are, and
authorization, which is once we know who
you are, what permissions do you have?
And over the last, I'd say decade or so,
authorization's becoming more and more
of a buzzword in the industry and an
important buzzword because our systems are
being, are getting more and more complex.
And with AI and agents, I think
that complexity is just, it's
going exponentially higher.
In the past, we have modeled access
control or permissions in different ways.
We started with access lists.
Say you have a document called Document 1.
You have a list of all people
who can edit this document.
S- now you also have to have a
separate list of all people who
can write or read this document.
What about people who can comment?
That's a new list, and not very
scalable That changed in the
industry to something called roles
or role-based access control or RBAC.
And this is very popular, and
I'm sure you've used it at your
workplace as well, where everyone's
assigned a role, and based on that
role, you get a set of permissions.
So for instance if you are a software
engineer, you can check in code
or you can read code repositories.
If you're in sales, you can
read sales reports, et cetera.
Now, this is simple and works
until it doesn't, because
this again does not scale.
What if someone from the software
engineering team has to check a sales
report for something to do with code?
You have to create a new role and
more and more, and suddenly you have
a role explosion that you can't audit
that can lead to security issues.
And the minute something changes, you need
a new role or an old role becomes stale.
There's also attribute-based access
control where you have rules and
things are broken down into attributes.
So if I'm trying to access a file, it
looks like, it looks at my attributes
like name email ID, location, department,
workspace, and based on all of these
attributes, I get a yes or a no.
Again, this again works till it
doesn't 'cause it is very rule-heavy,
and it can be hard to audit at scale,
especially if you're using AI agents.
The sort of new kid on the block
is something called ReBAC or
relationship-based access control, where
the idea is you can express relationships
between different things in your system.
So for instance, there's a user
and a resource, like a document,
there's a relationship between them.
And this seems to be the predominant
model right now in, in enterprise
and in the world of AI as well.
And in the next few slides,
I will tell you why that is.
Before that, a little
bit of a history lesson.
ReBAC was actually popularized in
something called Google Zanzibar.
See the word mentioned there.
Now, in 2019, Google released this
white paper called Google Zanzibar,
and in it they described their
internal authorization system,
also called Google Zanzibar.
And this was a groundbreak- groundbreaking
paper because for the first time a
company at the scale of Google, we're
talking billions of objects, hundreds
of millions of users in every part
of the world, describe in detail how
their authorization model worked.
The idea is it was globally distributed
and even back in 2019, the system could
do more than 10 million checks per second.
I am so sure that number has
exponentially increased by now.
If you have used any Google product like
Docs, YouTube, Maps, Photos, whatever,
this is the system that actually is doing
the authorization behind the scenes.
So if you have ever clicked on
a Google Docs link and you've
seen access denied that is the
Google Zanzibar system working.
And the cool thing is, at Google,
if you're just a developer
it's just an API then, right?
You don't have to worry
about how it works.
You call an API which answers a
simple question: Is an actor allowed
to perform an action on a resource?
For example, me, Sohan.
Is Sohan allowed to edit document one?
And you get a yes or a no.
And in effect, you're basically
checking for permission.
This is authorization.
Let's dive a little bit deep into
this ReBAC, because it's key to
understanding how you can use that to add
authorization for AI and coding agents.
Essentially, in ReBAC, you
have an actor and a resource.
So in this case, say a user…
I'm gonna get my mouse here.
A user and an object or a resource,
which could be a doc, it could be a
folder, a code repository, map, whatever.
There has to exist a relationship
between the user and that object, and
that relation could be something like
user is a member of a group, or user
is an editor of a document, or user
is an owner of folder named Plans.
So object-resource
relationship between the two.
Once you have this, you basically tell
the system that this relationship exists
in the form of something called a tuple.
This is the format of a tuple Start at
the right, and in this you would say user
number three is the owner of document 123.
So say you've created a new link or
a new Google Doc file, something like
this has actually been written in
the backend system where it says user
345 is the owner of document 12345.
And this is how a system knows that
this relationship exists So after
the creation of all these tuples,
what are we doing with this data?
This is where it gets interesting because
the Zanzibar system basically, or any RBAC
system, essentially constructs a graph
from all of this relationship data, and
the graph would look something like this.
The idea is once you have a lot
of relations between objects
and resources, you can construct
something called a directed
acyclic graph or a directed graph.
And to check permissions, you have to
just check if there's a way to go from the
object to the resource via the permission.
In the graph, you will see that each edge
or each node in the graph is either the
object, the resource, or the permission.
Say you have some document, and
you have readers, Fred and Kim.
You have writers that are Jill and Niv.
And say you have an organization
called Acme with an admin, Niv.
Here are the key things, which is
the little dotted line that you
see between reader and writer.
Now, this indicates if you can write to
the file, you can also read the file.
This little dotted line here from
writer to admin indicates that if you're
a admin, you can write to the file.
And we know that if you can write to
the file, you can already read the file.
So say a check comes in.
Can Jill read some document?
I want you to take a look at this
diagram and tell me if there is
a unidirectional way to go from
some document to Jill via reader
Now, the answer, of course, is on the
screen, but the answer is yes, because
you can go from some document to reader
to writer to Jill, and hence Jill
has permission to read some document.
Here's another question.
Can Fred write to this document?
If you see, there's no unidirectional
way to go from some document to writer
to Fred, and hence Fred does not have
permissions to write to the document.
Essentially, this is a graph reachability
problem, and that's what ReBAC is, and
this is how ReBAC works behind the scenes.
You d- you draw all of these relationships
between the different objects in your
system, your users, your agents, your
documents, your code, and then when you
check for permission, you can traverse
this graph and check for permission.
And this is useful because in the
world of role-based access control
You can't actually say a path or a
command or a domain, for instance.
You will just give a role
like a developer, which what
we call very coarse-grained.
It's not fine-grained, it's
coarse, it's very broad.
So a developer accesses
all the code or nothing.
It's not the developer can access just
the code that they are working on.
And again, this is important in the
world of AI agents because what a coding
agent need is something like write only
to your SRC file or run only Go test
or fetch data only from github.com.
These are the things that keep your
data safe when using a coding assistant
Zanzibar, of course, is an internal
Google tool, so you and I can't use
it unless you're working for Google.
So how do you use a Zanzibar
model to actually do RBAC style
fine-grained permissions for your
app or for your coding agents?
About five years ago, there was a popular
open source now popular open source
piece of software called SpiceDB that
was an implementation of Google Zanzibar.
SpiceDB, which is something that
I work on, is an open source
implementation which tries to be
as faithful to Google Zanzibar.
Essentially, as the name suggests,
it's a highly parallel graph database
optimized only for authorization queries.
And for you and me as devs, think
of it as a gRPC or HTTP API.
It's written in Go.
And SpiceDB answers questions
such as, "Can a subject take
an action on a resource?" The
thing that I just spoke about.
You'd be surprised to know that
SpiceDB is very popular, about
close to 7,000 stars on GitHub.
It's also used in enterprises
such as OpenAI, Zoom.
It, it has contributions from
companies like Netflix, Google,
GitHub, et cetera, on its features.
And in my opinion, it's becoming
like an industry standard when
people think about RBAC permissions
or fine-grained permissions.
So if you're building an application
and you need fine-grained permissions,
you could look at SpiceDB.
It's completely open source.
I'm here to talk to you about
a dev tool that's built on top
of SpiceDB called SpiceBox.
Now, SpiceBox is very new.
I'd say it's less than a month old,
so you're literally maybe the first
people that are hearing about this.
And the idea is you can use SpiceBox,
which is a combination of SpiceDB and your
OS sandbox, and hence the word SpiceBox.
The idea is, again, to take this concept
of relationship-based access control
and fine-grained permissions, but apply
that specifically for coding agents.
And you can just install SpiceBox.
It's completely open source on GitHub,
or you can use Homebrew to install it.
And the idea is you can, for now,
use it with Claude, and we'll soon
have support for Codex as well.
And you can tell Claude what you want--
what permissions you want to give your
coding assistant, and I will show you
how that actually works The key thing
here is your permission checks are still
deterministic, how it would work is you
would decide in English what permissions
you want to give your coding agent.
So something like read and write Go
files in the src folder, which means
it would read and write files only
in that folder and nothing else.
Spicebox basically uses Claude internally
to translate that into permissions.
File read write source Go.
Again this a deterministic thing.
Bash go test web github.com.
So there's a translation layer which
uses AI, but key point, the checks or the
authorization checks are deterministic.
So this is not probabilistic.
It-- the security still
needs to be deterministic.
So every time you will get the same
answer to the same question, right?
It's not… It won't change over time.
This is how it would work, and I'm,
I'll show you a demo very shortly.
So say your product manager asks
a question, or your engineering
lead says, "Hey, add retry logic
to the Go API client." That's
what's there in your GR ticket.
And you're like, "Okay, but I'm using
a coding assistant, but I don't want
to expose it to sensitive data."
So what you would do is six steps.
You would first describe this
in Spicebox in plain English.
You will say, "Hey, I'd like to edit Go
files in this folder, run go test and
web only github.com." Keep it simple.
Spicebox will call the Claude API to
translate that into, from English into
something that a computer can understand.
So file read, write,
bash, go test, et cetera.
And this is where a human,
you and me, would review this
and, approve the permission.
So if you see something
that's off, you would say no.
If everything looks good,
you would approve all of it.
So there is a human in the loop here.
And then Spicebox will
enforce this with Spice DB.
So it would auto add all
of these relationships.
It would use the hook that Claude code
has, along with your OS sandbox on
macOS, and it would create a local proxy
for you to reach out to github.com.
Once you run this, yeah, you can
edit anything in src, you can
read anything in the src folder,
but nothing outside of that.
If you try fetching data from
pypi.org, for instance, you
will get sorry it's blocked.
And of course, at the end, Spicebox
automatically cleans up everything.
So it removes hooks it tears down the
local proxy that was used for this, and
it was also running an instance of Spice
DB in memory, which is pulled down.
And the cool thing is it's
just one command to launch.
So you would just do something
like Spicebox Claude, which you
will see right now in a demo
and, let it take over from there.
How it works is basically there
are three layers of enforcement.
There is a hook server that
hooks into Claude Code.
So basically Claude Code checks
against Spice DB before it runs it.
Any sort of prompt injection also is
stopped by that There is an sandbox
on the operating system level, and
this is right now Mac only with
Windows and Linux we're working on,
like a different type of system.
But for now, this is Mac only.
And also there is any egress, so any
traffic that's going out or coming
back in, this filters through a proxy.
If you worked in the AI and security
space, you might have heard of this
thing called the lethal trifecta,
which essentially this sort of is
based on, which says that if you have
a tool that has access to, say, a
bunch of documents, can communicate
externally, and has exposure to
an, untrusted what's it called?
Let me see.
Through ex- untrusted external content,
that is what's called a lethal trifecta,
where, some data can be exposed.
And with the-- with this gauntlet
of a hook server, of an operating
system sandbox, and a filtering
proxy, you're locking it down
on every level of that trifecta.
So until you give it permissions,
everything is denied by default.
You have to explicitly give permissions
for everything, and any layer can
say no For instance, let's do a
deep dive into each of these layer.
The hook server will always check against
Spice DB permissions before any call runs.
So even something like read or
glob or greb grep, sorry, running
locally on your system is checked
against Spice DB, for instance.
And by default, everything is denied.
So even if you do an LS and you've
not given it permissions, your Claude
code will be locked down and it won't
be able to read your local directory.
This is also cross tool, so
read glob, grep, et cetera, will
all check the same permission.
So only if it's allowed it'll be there.
And the model can't reach or
rewrite the rules because that is
running in a different process.
So even if you try to prompt inject
the AI into faking these requirements,
it won't because that's running in
a completely different process that
it cannot access Level two is the
kernel, essentially, which is the
sort of back, backstop as we call it.
It's a sandbox E- exec or a sandbox
executive execution profile that restricts
cloud code process at the kernel level.
This is on Mac for now, so it'll work
if you're using a Mac essentially,
which is what I'm using on our demo.
And if there's no write permission granted
then your working directory is read-only.
And old bash tricks to get
around this like echo file are
blocked by the kernel anyway.
And layer three is egress, which is
traffic going out of your system.
You have to specify an allow list,
so you can say allow github.com and
it'll allow only that and nothing else.
You can, I think I'll talk about
this later, but you can also specify
one-time grants, which is suppose
you're doing something, all of your
data is being read from GitHub, but
suddenly you have to read from pypi.org.
You can give a grant, like a
temporary grant to read from PyPi,
which after a certain timeframe
is elapsed, that grant goes away.
So you can also have that option.
There are five permission types
of what you can scope with
SpiceBox for your coding agent.
The first one is category-wide access,
where you can say read-only from this
bash commands or web search, et cetera.
So very wide category access.
You can specify path prefix and
suffix filter, so .go, .ts, .py,
et cetera, or only in this folder,
for instance, so you can do that.
All bash commands you can do like
NPM Run Build is allowed, but NPM
something else is probably not.
You can do that.
Everything to fetch data from the web,
so d- domain-based URL filtering, look
for GitHub, docs.python.org, et cetera.
And of course, m- MCP tools like
tool prefix or parameter value.
So tool when an argument starts
with an X, for instance, so you
get only the right kind of traffic.
Remember, MCP servers are self-updating,
so sometimes you want to be vigilant
about what MCP server you are connecting
to and what data you're receiving from
an MCP server, and SpiceBox allows
you to do that And there's a, there's
good type of approval control as well.
Each permission independently
controls approval.
So anything that's auto-approved
will proceed silently.
You don't have to worry about that.
But some things that need
confirmation will prompt the user.
There are sensible defaults built
in, like reads are auto, writes and
executes will require confirmation,
and you can also override permu- per
permission in a natural language.
This is important because OWASP
also has a list on top 10 risks to
coding AI, no, to AI agents and to
LLMs, and a lot of it revolves around
things like prompt injection, data
exfiltration, and privilege escalation.
All of this is taken care
of by a tool like SpiceBox.
Assume your model is compromised,
say it's been hijacked, and say
someone tries a prompt injection.
Because there is a check
against the hook it's denied.
Say someone tries a bash tool workaround,
where they try like a bash command
to work around this particular thing.
The kernel will block the write
that the hook missed earlier
because there's an OS-level sandbox.
Say someone wants to get
data out into something else.
The host isn't allowed on the allow list.
We're allowing only, say, github.com.
So there's a network proxy, so
no data is being exfiltrated.
Privilege escalation cannot happen because
this is running on a separate process, so
you can't take over the SpiceBox process
and, use that as privilege escalation.
And of course, alternate tool access is
also blocked by the hook because grep
can't read when read itself was denied
There are a few things that SpiceBox does
not check against or does not protect
against, and this is where the human
that's actually running SpiceBox makes
a lot of difference and, is important.
We're not saying AI is going to replace
every coder in the world, et cetera.
Because Bash is Turing complete, so
broad Bash prefixes can be abused.
There is an OS level backstop,
but, watch out for that.
The tran-- There is a AI level layer
of translation which depends on Claude.
So you tell Claude something,
Claude translates that into
computer speak, so to say, but you
have to review before approving.
And in this paradigm of AI, we are
saving a lot of time in actually
writing code, but we should be very
in these processes where you're
reviewing things like permission.
It's about, I think, being very
intentional and using your time
well to make sure that is actually
safe, because all it takes is one
mistake for data to be exfiltrated
and boom, you're in trouble Sandbox,
of course, I mentioned is macOS only.
Other platforms will still get the
hook-based enforcement and the network
level enforcement, but no OS Sandbox.
And as of now, there are
no suffix exclusions yet,
read all files except .env.
For s- for some reasons for some reason,
LLM still find that a little challenging.
Even if you speak to Claude directly
and ask it to do like an exclusion.
As humans, we understand this,
but LLM still find that a little
hard, so that does not exist.
So you'll have to manually maybe
mention everything that's allowed
or everything that's denied
as opposed to all files except
Cool.
Let's see a live demo.
We'll scope maybe paths
and a network isolation.
We can also do like maybe
a mid-session grant.
Let's see how that goes.
I basically have a folder here.
It's a simple Vercel template, right?
Nothing too fancy.
I'm just going to open SpiceBox
Claude, and I can give it permission
saying write TS or TSX files
in the components folder only.
No sub-agents fetch from GitHub.
I will say curl tool search
or web search allowed.
This is what we need to actually
make a call using Claude
to, fetch data from GitHub.
So what this does is SpiceBox will use
the Claude API to translate this into,
again, computer speak, so you will
see each of those translated there.
GitHub has an MCP server, so
you will see that in action.
Yeah, we're translating
the permissions via Claude.
Always fun to do a live demo, and you
can see here, perform web searches,
which is blanket read and write
.ts, .tsx files, run commands with
curl, run commands starting with
tool search, which is a Claude code.
So I'm going to approve this for now.
I've reviewed it.
So I'll say create .py file, test.py
file in the components folder This
should not work because we're not
giving it permissions to do so it
says, yeah, I can't create this file.
If you want, you can
create grant permission.
We won't do that now.
Create test test.ts in
the components folder.
This we have permission to do or we
have given permission to do, so it
says, yeah, create this and, it's done.
So it was scoped down that way.
Let's, fetch data from, and
maybe I'll just add like a list.
This is Oddset Spicebox fetch.
Let's say fetch README, README from here.
And this actually you might see
something interesting for now.
It's a case of this tool actually
working really well because tool search
is blocked, so web fetch is blocked,
but I can Curl is allowed, so it'll
try and curl, but it curls from a
local proxy, which we have not allowed.
So it will throw an error for
now and then give you an actual
And all of this in reality is
about adding like a context file.
So if you constantly get
from github.com yeah.
So it says, can't get it.
So you have to add grant web fetch
and tool search so that you can
actually get from github.com.
I can actually do Spicebox grant.
Oops.
And say grant web fetch and tool search.
And this is a temporary grant that
works for, if I'm not mistaken, 15
minutes, and again, that uses like
a cryptographic token exchange to
ensure that this tool grant works.
Now it runs curl again and
yeah, let's see if it works
I'm calling now
Yeah, so it's hitting through
a local, yeah, granted.
I'll retry the README fetch
And you can see the tools search is
still blocked, so it'll try curl instead
And sometimes you have to
explicitly give it permissions
to the local host too, right?
So all of this can be written
into a sort of like context file
or like a secure agents.md file
that… Yeah, now it'll work.
Yep.
Then if you're doing like a particular
thing, so README covers blah, blah, blah.
Yeah, so this is the README
from the Spicebox file, right?
So yeah, that was essentially a live demo.
I need to iterate that Spicebox is
fairly new feel free to go to Oddset
dot-- sorry, github.com/oddset/spicebox
to contribute, to try out the
project, and give us your feedback.
Yeah, I just gave you an
example of all of this.
And yeah, some people have asked
us why not just use settings.json?
But settings are in Claude code,
and that does have a bunch of gaps.
For instance, there are
no cross-tool policies.
It's allowed by default in Claude,
whereas Spicebox is denied by
default and explicitly allow.
There are no parameter constraints, no
network control, so all of these actually
can be played around with in Spicebox.
And just the four things to like
as key takeaways here, model
judgment is not enforcement, right?
What a model judges to be safe
versus a security problem can is--
it can't be trusted basically,
so keep those two separate.
You need a deterministic
out-of-process check, to hold
against things like prompt injection.
Don't ask the model to decide
if something is safe or not.
That check has to be deterministic.
Re-Rebac allows you to scope
by path, command, and domain.
Traditional authorization methods
can't, so Rebac is well-suited to
build authorization for agents, for
RAG, for coding agents, et cetera.
And lastly, let AI draft the policy,
et cetera, but a human is still
being used in the loop to approve it.
Some key takeaways, Spicebox.
Yeah, check out SpiceDB as well if
you wanna build app permissions.
And yeah, join our community on
Discord if you have any questions.
And thank you for listening to this.
Feel free to connect with me on
LinkedIn if you had any questions,
and enjoy the rest of the conference.
Bye.