Welcome everyone to my talk on
agent ai architecting, scalable and
reliable AI agents for the future.
This is Bitler working as a senior
software development engineer at Adobe.
Before I get on, get onto my talk,
I want to make a quick disclaimer.
All views expressed here are my own
and do not reflect the opinions of
any affiliated organization today.
We.
Tools to become active participants
in solving complex problems.
By the end, you'll understand
the key architectural principles
for building AI agents that
are both scalable and reliable.
Let's deep dive into it.
If you really look at
historically, AI has fundamentally
transformed over the past decade.
If you look at it, we started with systems
that simply responded to queries, think
early, search engine or basic chatbots.
Then we moved to more
sophisticated interactions.
That the systems that could generate
content or solve specific problems
when prompted right, and now we're
entering the era of agentic AI systems
that can take initiatives, make
decisions, and execute multi-step plans.
This represents a fundamental shift
in human computer interaction.
From tools we used to
partners we collaborate with.
So that is the power of evolution that is
happening, and that is the transformation
that we are going through To understand
agent ai, first of all, we need to
define what makes system a truly agent.
If we look at it, there are four
qualities that I categorized here.
A systems to act as an agent.
Ai, the first goal is directed behavior.
The system should have the ability to
pursue specific objectives rather than
just responding to immediate inputs.
That is the first goal.
And the second is.
Operating with minimal human intervention.
Once your goal is established,
they should automatically perform
all the tasks that are given.
And the third one is
environment awareness.
The ability to perceive and interpret
the context in which the agent
operates and the adaptability.
Learning from outcomes and
adjusting strategies accordingly.
So if these four capabilities are there
in any system that we can say it as a
agent system that can actually plug and
play with any other bigger system, right?
Let's look where already making an impact.
There personal assistance, like advanced
versions of tools that can proactively
manage schedules for any individual
filter information and coordinate their
tasks with other agents are humans.
In software development, we are seeing
agents that can not just generate
code, but plan implementations,
debug issues, and performance.
So in software development, we see in day
to day, like you have, Microsoft Copilot,
GitHub copilot, and also uc, cursor ai.
These are amazing tools where you can
actually leverage for code generation
and couple more tools to perform.
all of these tasks I mentioned,
and if you look at the research.
Design experiments and
analyze the results.
So for research agents, you have so
many other types of things to take care.
So now agents are there to solve all of
these problems and in physical domains,
robots, which are going to help you in
industrial systems that can adapt to
changing conditions and requirements.
So that's where you can see the
robotic agents in the manufacturing
and in other support areas.
So here, what's notable is the increasing
scope of agency from narrow specific
tasks to broader domains of action, right?
So adaptability.
willing to collaborate with the agent
AI to perform their multitasking
things without any stress, right?
So now let's break down the
essential components that
enable the agent systems, right?
So if you really look at the system
here at the core, in the foundation.
Typically large language models,
which are going to provide a
cognitive engine to break down the
prompts and give the instructions.
Then the planning frameworks comes
into the picture for strategic
decision making where the ability to
map out the steps towards a goal to
achieve the goal that is defined for
the agents to integration systems.
That can extend the agent's capabilities
through APIs and external services.
So that's where the integration
comes into the picture.
Then the memory systems for
maintaining the context and history
beyond immediate interaction.
So see the storage related information
comes where it can, where the agents can
retrieve the information based on the.
The system is able to learn from
the success or failure and then
try to, take the corresponding
actions and the feedback mechanism.
Also make the system so get corrected,
process dynamically and stores the,
information for the future usage.
These are the typical key
components of an agent system.
So now.
If you really look at this whole diagram
in the centralized area where you have
the total, the processing capability,
like how the processing is going to
be taking place, and there you have
the lms, the large language models,
which is the core of the system.
And then these, there
are multiple components.
You see the bidirectional mapping
between all of these tasks, right?
That includes the planning and reasoning
module where you see, how LLM need to,
communicate within a different kind of,
sub components and tool connectors, right?
The a p connectors are the
tools that can actually interact
with between these, components.
And the memory storage, right?
So where you can store the outputs
of your agent based on the kind of,
information that is processed, right?
And based on the historical data that it
can actually keep it in, respond back.
And then you also have monitoring
and feedback where you have the
feedback loops to see whether
the system is, giving you the.
And then the safety guardrails
where you see like how the systems
are actually, safe to use or not.
So all of this information
you can see through this
technical architectural diagram.
And then the challenges in
scaling agentic ai, right?
So as we move from prototype to
production, there are several challenges.
Increase dramatically with both
model size and task complexity, then
the latency becomes very critical.
Users expect rapid responses
even for complex tasks.
So if you really look at the users the way
they are coming up to the system, right?
So you need to understand
like how the agent is actually
supporting what kind of complex.
And then you see the reliability.
Reliability, it must be
maintained across an expanding
set of use cases and age cases.
And the multi-agent systems
introduce new complexities in
coordination and communication.
And of course cost
scales with huge, usage.
And
so these are.
Are possible, but they require through
the architectural approaches of agent
AI and reliability concerns, reliability
deserves a special attention as it's
often the make or big factor for adoption.
Because if without reliable systems,
it's very difficult to, use it.
So Hall.
When agents generate convincing,
but incorrect information remain
a significant challenge, right?
So if every information is coming
as hallucination, it is very hard
to soak that information and you
can't really use it in the real time.
Rule misuse occurs when agents
apply available capabilities
inappropriately or inefficiency.
So that's where, to see where
the tool is getting misused.
Planning failures happen when
agents create ineffective or
nonsensical action sequences.
So this is, planning is
one of the crucial point.
Context limitations.
Context limitations lead to
agents losing track of relevant
information during extended tasks.
So these are the major concerns, and apart
from that, the last and final one is the
feedback loops, which can trap agents
in unpredictable patterns of behavior.
So if the feedback loops are not giving
you the proper feedback, if there is
a chances of 20% errors information,
and the feedback is actually going as
a storage, eventually the system can
give very information to the end user.
So that's where you need to be very
careful on what kind of feedback
mechanism is there and what
kind of corrections are getting.
So here we, we have three solutions, so
I want to go through one after the other.
The fastest solution here is modular
architecture, so by decomposing complex.
We reduce the cognitive load
on any single system, right?
You're breaking down into multiple
components and that's where you are,
trying to give a task for each of
the component in an isolation phase.
This enables specialized agents
for specific domains, leveraging
expertise where it matters the most.
Modularity facilitates easier
updating of individual components
without disrupting the entire
system, and it supports distributed
processing, spreading computational,
and load across the resources.
Perhaps most importantly, it
allows for graceful degradation.
If one component fails, other
can continue functioning it.
This approach has prevent successful
in other complex software domains.
So here, if you look at any kind of,
banking system, how you can break
down into multiple, agents and each
agent can take care of its task.
And ultimately they align
with the centralized system
to give the end results.
And second solution is robust
planning and framework.
In this case, there is a hierarchical
planning, which where the structure
is break down into complex goals
and into know manageable sub goals.
So the ultimate goal is to, provide the
solution to an end user with so many,
interactive kind of processing that
are needed for agents to work on it.
So in this case, you may need to have
verifications at multiple stages.
Ensure that plans are logical and
aligned with the common goal or
the objective that is defined.
In this case, you may see some
uncertainty, estimation, uncertainty,
which can help the agents to
recognize when they may be operating
with incomplete information.
So this is where you may need
to see like what is going wrong
and which kind of scenario.
So that's where the
fallback mechanism provides.
What are the alternate you have
when the primary approach fails?
So that's where you see here, this
may be the common goal, but these
agents are connected and everywhere
you have a fallback mechanism
where there can been corrective
action, can be taken care, right?
So again, when something goes wrong,
there will be a dynamic planning.
So the adaptable planning, Together, these
approaches create more resilient planning
for handling real world complexity.
The third key solution in
comprehensive, in comprehensive
evaluation is it is like how you
wanna test the quality of your agent.
So in this case, you
may have several test.
However, not just common cases, but cases
where failures are more likely, right?
So continuous monitoring, which will
allow us to detect the performance
degradation before it becomes critical.
So you may need to monitor, like whether
is there any kind of underlying system
is, going through any, performance
bottlenecks or degradations.
Real time failure detection
enables immediate intervention when
necessary, and also human feedback
in cooperation ensures that technical
metrics align with actual user needs.
So human feedback is very essential
because you can't really rely on a
hundred percentage of the systems
be.
So this is what in the third solution,
which you may need to, see like how
it actually helps the, real user.
So combining these three solutions,
definitely you may get a better agent to
use it as part of your implementation.
So let's start with a case study.
So here an example of a bank manager.
So if you really look at an enterprise
knowledge agent, how this works on
the left hand side of this image,
you can see in the current scenario
how the bank manager is actually,
working with the, in the real world
scenario and on the right hand side,
a knowledge agent that is enabling or
using it for processing their tasks.
Excuse me.
So here, yeah, he's dealing with a lot of,
started documents, databases, and systems.
So he doesn't have any kind of
a proper mechanism to handle
the, current scenario here.
This.
This solution definitely a kind of
a complex thing to really, handle,
and he'll be stressful to, at the end
of the day to handle, so many tasks.
So that's where he got the
knowledge agent in place.
Okay.
So this knowledge agent,
what does it do for him?
the solution implemented is a
modular approach, where you got
the, dis from different systems.
And generation.
So this way he is gonna get a scalable
agent system with specialized components,
which can be, implemented for documents.
documents in a sense for reading,
for writing, for any such kind
of matters, any interpretation,
like what kind of information is
coming and how we need to process.
And.
Agent so that way a bank manager can relax
and let the agents do the task for him
and he can take the decisions as needed.
The results, if you really look at
both of these systems, these are,
these results were remarkable.
You can see 40% reduction
information, re time.
He doesn't need to really go personally,
check the systems for report generation
and all, and 65% improvement in accuracy.
So there are no human errors and there
is no kind of rush kind of a thing.
So that way you can see, the systems
are giving, like the improvement
in accuracy and the reduction
in information retrieval, right?
This way people can relax and
another case study is autonomous.
The challenge.
Where you can have, like with
very minimal human oversight
while maintaining their quality.
So that is the objective.
So if you wanna implement a solution
to cater this need here, you can see
like you can implement a agent system,
which can perform a different roles.
One agent could be for coding, another
agent could be for testing, right?
And another agent could
be for integrating.
Of course, integration testing.
So if you use these agents, the
results demonstrated out of this
system would be a three x developer
productivity and 50% reduction in bug.
So developer can actually give quality,
outcome, but using these agents and
you can also be more efficient, right?
So this is the outcome of agent, usage,
especially in the autonomous software.
General purpose agents.
So these are like general purpose
agents need a lot more information,
lot more storage, lot more,
processing capabilities, right?
So here these move beyond narrow,
specialized to handle diverse
tasks across different domains.
They maintain long memory and
accumulate experience over extended.
So they should have all the
sophisticated information to
maintain and to serve the clients.
They transfer learning across
domains and applying insights
from one area to another.
The domain includes, it could be banking,
to insurance, and banking to, The
trading systems, it can be of anything.
They engage in meta reasoning about
their own capabilities and limitations,
and they also develop sophisticated
understanding of human intent and
beyond the explicit instructions.
So these agents in the real world
can solve a lot of problems where
a common human can, struggle with.
While we're not there yet, especially for
the general purpose agents, architectural
editions today will determine how quickly
and safely we approach this horizon.
Let's wait and see how
soon that we can get there.
But, and if you really look at, the
agent AI or any a system for that
matter, ethical considerations are very
values.
And ethical considerations.
So how we can actually balance right?
What is more important?
So especially when it comes to the
age and decision making, it's the
transparency which is very essential
for an appropriate oversight.
And then the accountability
mechanism we should ensure.
Which should be built into a data
usage and memory systems, right?
You can't really use data for any reason.
So the user data should be protected,
and we need robust safeguard to
prevent harmful emergent behaviors.
So these are the things you may
need to consider when you're.
in successful systems, you
need to see what can be
incorporated, what shouldn't be.
So separation of reasoning and
action allows for specialized
optimization of each function.
And you should also have explicit
verification steps, which
should prevent cascading errors.
And you should also
have strategic human in
bottleneck.
If you use agents for everything,
if agents stops doing mistakes, so
if every time, if they're making
20% mistakes with five repetitions,
you may see only the faulty system.
So that's where human in the
loop checkpoints always needed
and graceful handling of
uncertainty, which will avoid the.
So anything that comes uncertainty, right?
You should have always have the,
modes to correct the system.
And continuous learning from
operational data, right?
Which will be an ongoing improvement.
So you should always
incorporate that, right?
So these are the imaging patterns
you can use and directions.
So if you really look at it as tasks
become more complex, specialization
becomes increasingly valuable.
This requires a sophisticated
communication, sorry, sophisticated
communication protocols between
the heterogeneous agents.
so how these agents can communicate.
a bank manager to process, currents
and current account details and savings
and loan account related information.
So you may have the agents to
process all of these information from
different, distributed agents and
giving that information to the, the
bank manager to ensure that how the
specific tasks are being performed.
So you have the centralized
information processing.
Capability.
And at the same time, agents are
actually interacting with the
central system and they're actually
informing the bank manager to, use
that information in an effective way.
So this is the distributed,
multi-agent, system that you can build.
And ultimately one information
will float outside.
So in this case, the resource
sharing and allocation mechanism
becomes for efficiency.
So they need to, like what kind
of resources they need to share,
like GPUs and memory or whatever
it's, and conflict resolution.
That is very important for any kind
of agentic system to ensure that they
are, prevented from deadlocks and
any kind of contradictory actions.
So they have to do, they
should actually generate.
Here, the ultimate goal is to emergent
collective intelligence systems that
can solve problems no single agent
could solve with these kind of issues.
So that's where you need to
have the, collective agents to,
process the information, future
directions and adaptive systems.
So these can dynamically
adjust the capabilities based
on the task requirements.
And they improve themselves
through operational excellence and
not just leaving from data, but
learning from their own mistakes.
So this is the beauty
of the adaptive systems.
They automatically detect and mitigate
weakness without human intervention.
They may manage resources
based on environmental
constraints and opportunities.
They implement context sensitive
safety mechanisms that, that
adapt to changing risk profiles.
The result is system that become
more capable and renewable over
time through their own experience.
So these are the systems you may want
to see in the futuristic way, right?
the self-learning systems are.
Better.
But at the same time, there should
be checkpoints to ensure that, as
I discussed in my previous slides,
the human feedback loop mechanism
we should definitely incorporate.
But the self adaptable systems,
you don't need to sit there and
then train and they can learn by
themselves and become more efficient.
But at the same time, human
feedback loops also, we should.
Building for the future and the
key principles for agent ai.
To summarize the architectural approach,
I advocate first, embrace modular design.
So how do you wanna break down the
whole systems into sub components?
Second is prioritize the observability.
So you should ensure that the systems are.
Debug, if there is any kind
of a system comes, system
failure comes into the picture.
Third is implement the controlled autonomy
with clear boundaries for agent decision.
And the fourth one is develop
the scalable evaluation, the test
system under diverse conditions.
because you don't want system to, so it
should be tested in diverse conditions.
Pass engineering and see if the system
is still reliable enough to, answer
the, the questions asked by the user.
Finally, integrate feedback continuously
from deployment to, to develop
and, improvement related things.
So you should have the, con
consistent feedback mechanism on the.
Agent A represents a fundamental shift
in how we interact with technology.
So this is essential, like
how you want to interact.
these are the, whatever we discussed so
far, these things really makes, agents
are like more, when you maintain all
of these things in a systematic way.
So if you really look at now we are
moving from tools we operate to partner
with, and to partner with the agents,
and also we also collaborate with them
to ensure that, we get the, productivity
improvement and accuracy improvement.
This transition request, thoughtful
architecture that balances
capacity with reliability.
So this is very essential
transitioning, like when.
Human based.
So you have to, maintain it.
And success purely depends on
finding the right equilibrium
between autonomy and oversight.
And finally, the future belongs to
composable, adaptable agent systems
that can evolve with our needs.
Thank you.
Reach on.