Hello everyone.
Welcome to my talk on AI as Strategic
Asset Building Competitive Advantage
in financial services and enterprises.
I'm excited to be speaking at Con
42 on large language Models in 2025.
I'm jja a software engineer with
extensive experience in ai, cloud
computing and financial technology.
In this session, I.
Particularly in financial services.
Before we dive in, let me
briefly introduce myself.
I have over 17 years of experience
working in financial technology,
specializing in ai, cloud
computing, and software engineering.
Throughout my career, I have worked
in on AI driven transformations
for financial institutions, and I
also hold patents in this space.
A quick disclaimer.
The opinion shared in this
presentation are my own and do
not represent my employer's views.
This talk is intended to share
industry insights, trends, and best
practices based on my experience
agenda for the talk, how AI
enables business predictions.
Real world industry use cases, application
of AI and financial services, a case
study on AI driven income verification
for loan applications, key strategies for
successful AI implementation, challenges
and considerations in adopting ai.
And finally a look into the future of ai.
Let's start with the fundamental question.
What makes someone intelligent?
We recognize patterns, learn from
mistakes and develop gut feelings based
on the experiences and the knowledge.
Similarly, AI systems are designed to.
Learn from data experiences, refine their
understanding and improve over time.
This learning ability makes
AI an invaluable tool for
the business and this world.
The AI landscape is remarkably
diverse as you can see.
It encompasses multiple layers of
technologies from broad artificial
intelligence concepts at the top
to machine learning approaches in
the middle neural networks below
that, and specialized areas like T
Learning and gen AI at the foundation.
Each layer builds upon the previous one.
Creating an ecosystem of technologies
that solve different types of problems.
The possibilities with today's
AI tools are virtually endless.
From GitHub co-pilot assisting
developers to chat GPT conversational
abilities, clause nuanced responses.
Deep seek specialized functions.
Google's Gini for creativity and
growth approach to problem solving.
Each represent different capabilities
that organizations can leverage
for specific business needs.
Business predictions.
AI is not just about technology,
it's about vision and.
Strategy.
Companies that successfully
implement AI will gain a significant
competitive advantage according
to industry response reports.
AI has the potential to double workforce
productivity with help of AI agents.
Surprisingly, surprisingly, only 20%
of AI models actually get deployed
in production, and that's sad.
Why?
Because of various technical,
operational, and strategic barriers.
Understanding these roadblocks is
crucial for AI and our success.
Here's the breakdown of the main reasons.
AI models do not make it to production.
More than 30% is because
of decision makers.
Resist changes to
existing operations, 35%.
Face technical integration Challenges
in the existing system, 25%.
Do not see strong enough
Model performance.
This highlights that leadership
buy-in and seamless integration are
as important as the AI model itself.
Industry use cases, AI driven
object detection is transforming
multiple industries in auto IT
auto in autonomous vehicles.
AI enables real time decision
making with help of YOLO models.
You look only once.
A retail object detect
transforms inventory management.
AI systems can automatically identify
products on shelf, detect stockouts,
verify planogram compliance, and
monitor real time inventory levels.
This reduces labor costs.
While improving accuracy and
enabling faster restocking decisions
in financial services, document processing
represent a massive opportunity.
Applying AI in financial services
document processing is one of the top
AI application in financial services.
It encompasses loan applications with
complex forms and supporting materials,
invoice and receipt management for
both customers and internal operations.
KYC compliance, document verification
and detailed analysis across multiple
formats and legal frameworks.
Another critical financial application
is fraud detection and prevention.
AI systems Excel at NMU Detection,
identifying unusual patterns
that might indicate fraud.
Real time transitions monitoring allows
for immediate verification of suspicious
activities, dramatically improving
security while reducing false positives.
AI is also enhancing customer
service through AI powered bots
and virtual assistants that
can handle routine inquiries.
And transactions.
Automated fraud alerts provide timely
notification to customers about
potential security issues, improving
both protection and customer experience.
Financial institutions are increasingly
leveraging AI for personalization.
This includes dynamic pricing.
As well as customized long terms
based on individual risk profiles.
Apart from that AI powered financial
planning tools that can provide
tailored advice based on customer
data and financial behaviors,
investment management is another area.
Being transformed by ai, machine
learning algorithms can analyze
market trends, optimize portfolio
allocations, and identify investment
opportunities far more rapidly than
human illness while maintaining risk
management parameters and conditions.
Now I will walk you through a
case study of how AI transforms
in income verification in
the loan application process.
We are focusing on optimizing
loan processing through ai,
augmented document handling.
Income verification is a crucial
part of our loan processing.
Let's examine mind why income
verification matters so much.
It's not just about confirming
numbers, it's the foundation
of responsible landing.
For financial institutions, accurate
verification ensures risk management and
compliance for customers, it determines
their boring capability and terms.
Now let's address the pain point.
The traditional manual verification
process creates multiple problems.
Errors when human mystery documents delay
that frustrate customers and increase
abundance rates, inefficiency that cost
financial institutions millions annually.
These three problems, errors,
delays, and inefficiencies.
Represent significant
business opportunities.
Our solution objective is straightforward.
Automate income verification through
ai augmented document processing.
This is not about removing humans
from the equation entirely.
But rather using AI to handle repetitive
tasks while allowing human experts to
focus on exceptions and complex use cases.
This objective addresses
all three problems.
We have identified
the document processing
component more closely.
We have six key.
AI pipeline is starting from data capture
document, move through classification,
extraction, enrichment of the extracted
data review and validation, and
finally consumption by the downstreams.
Each step plays a crucial role.
Aggregating documents, classifying type
of document, extracting information,
enriching data from that information,
incorporating human validation when
and where needed, and sending verified
information downstream for consumption.
Implementing AI Strategies for Success.
Some are, some of the
best practices are here.
First one is identifying
key problems AI can solve.
The first step in AI implementation
is identifying where AI
can bring the most value.
AI works best for automated
automating repetitive tasks,
improving decision making.
And analyzing large, huge amount of data.
Examples include fraud detection
in banking, demand forecasting in
retail, and document processing at
scale Planning, and bolting for AI
integration is the second best practice.
Implementing AI requires investment
in data tools, infrastructure,
and talent organizations.
Should cons consider the cost
of cloud computing, AI software,
and ongoing model maintenance
planning should also include security,
compliance, and ethical considerations.
Best practice best Choosing the right
AI ML model is important and very
important to select the right AI ML
model based on the business need.
Some applications work best with
simple models like decision trees.
While others requires deep
learning models, businesses must
consider accuracy, scalability.
And ease of implementation
when choosing models.
And the last one is utilizing
ai, ml, SDKs and APIs.
Many AI solutions don't have to be
built from scratch cloud providers
like AWS Google and Microsoft offers
ai ml SDKs and a PS that can be.
Speed up the development.
These tools help business integrate AI
without extensive in-house expertise.
Of course, implementing AI
is not without challenges.
Key considerations include data
privacy, security concerns, specifically
with financial information and data.
Ethical implications, regulatory
compliance requirements, and perhaps the
most important managing organizations
change, which often proves more
challenging than the technology itself.
Looking ahead, the AI
landscape in financial services
continue to evolve rapidly.
Key trend include multi-model
document understanding,
agenting AI document processing.
Increasingly personalized
services and embedded AI.
Throughout the customer journey,
organizations should prepare
for continuous innovation.
Than viewing, rather than viewing
implementation as a one time project.
Thank you very much.