Speaker 6: Hi, everyone.
I'm Arun.
I run cybersecurity and infrastructure
operations at General Reinsurance.
Today, I want to make one
argument and back it up.
Identity is no longer an IT
administrative function; it's the
primary control plane for securing AI.
So every enterprise here is
racing to put LLMs, copilots,
and agents into production.
The security model most of us
inherited was built for a world
that doesn't exist anymore.
So by the end of next fifteen minutes,
you'll have a framework for treating
IAM as infrastructure security and a
checklist of the failure patterns that are
quietly burning organizations right now
So the expanding identity attack surface.
So four things broke the
old model at the same time.
So what changed?
Every inference boundary is now a
trust and authorization decision.
The model is talking to data, tools,
and other services on someone's behalf.
Autonomous agents.
These don't just answer, they act.
So they call APIs, move
data, spawn sub-agents.
They carry delegated authority,
and delegated authority that
isn't scoped is a liability.
Machine-to-machine APIs.
Orchestration frameworks and
service meshes create dense
webs of inter-service trust.
Most of it is implicit.
And then the final one is
cloud-native automation.
Serverless functions and workload
identities run at scale with credentials
almost nobody audits in real time.
So no-- Did you notice what's
common across all four of these?
So none of them are human sitting
at a laptop behind a firewall.
So it's a different problem we are
solving here So why the perimeter
is no longer the boundary?
The old model assumed a trusted
internal network, static
firewall rules, human-centric
policies, and periodic audits.
So every one of those
assumptions is now wrong.
So it's completely different.
So the new reality is, regardless of
location, authorization decisions that
are dynamic and context-aware, non-human
identities dominating your workloads and
verifications, that has to be continuous.
So it's not like login once and
the session can exist forever.
So it changed completely.
So in, in a environment, no single network
boundary can enforce a consistent policy.
So identity is the only control
plane that travels with the workload.
Okay?
So that was not the case before
all these non-human identities
So what's the agenda here?
So let's look at it.
So five quick stops, right?
So identity as a control plane,
least privilege at AI scale,
continuous verification, the
non-human identity problem, and
resilience through governance.
Let's look at it one by one.
So identity as the primary control plane.
So we should all stop thinking of
IAM as the team that just resets
password and manage user credentials.
So in an AI architecture, identity
governs six things at once, like
authorization authentication, privilege
boundaries, trust relationships,
audits, and revocation and recovery.
So these are all not tools
which are like combined, right?
So they are like spokes on one hub.
So if the if the hub is fragmented,
every spoke inherits the same gap.
So give the identity same architectural
rigor you give networking or compute,
and it deserves a design phase.
So any identity you bring into
a environment, it should have a
identity life cycle, so there should
be a design behind it, how it is
going to be managed continuously.
So the next key item we are
going to discuss about is the
least privilege at AI scale.
So this is applicable for any
identity, not specific to AI.
So least privilege is your
single most lever for shrinking
blast radius of the attack.
So least privilege has
three things in it, right?
So it's granular permission scope
to the exact resource and data
classification, and apply the same way
to humans and non-human identities.
So context-aware.
So it should be aware
of the context as well.
A static role assignment
is not required anymore.
So like you can assign a role just
in time to execute the job and
then scale it back when needed.
And then it has to be time-bound as well.
It doesn't need to be
like twenty-four/seven.
A agent which summarizes
documents at 2:00 p.m.
should not have read access or
any access like twenty-four/seven.
It can be provided with a just-in-time
access where it can elevate its
access, get the data, write the
data, and then the role can be
removed from the agent or identity.
So continuous verification
across AI pipeline.
So how it can be achieved?
So here is the failure
of the old model, right?
So you authenticate once at a session,
start, and then the agent goes hopping.
APIs, vectors, databases,
servers, compute.
So anywhere, right?
So every hop is a new trust boundary.
Authenticating once and
trusting everything after is
how lateral movement happens.
So what do we need to do?
So authenticate identity, authorize
the action, monitor the behavior,
and then revoke or escalate.
So it's not a one gate.
It should be like a continuous
loop where it has to be vetted
at each and every bound.
Continuous verification directly
attacks two most dangerous
post-compromise behaviors.
So lateral movement and privilege
escalation through stolen
tokens or misconfigured trust.
So this has to be embedded at
every layer of the stack, so
not bolted onto the one layer.
Okay?
So the non-human identity problem.
So the non-- So let's be all frank.
So lo-- so one thing that keeps me up
at night is the modern AI environment
and the non-human identities.
Agents, automation services,
machine-to-machine workloads significantly
outnumbered human users at this point.
And here is the uncomfortable
truth for everybody.
Most organizations cannot
even enumerate them.
You can govern what you can count.
Do we do the best?
Every organization has a life
cycle for all the AI agents they
are bringing into the environment.
Is there an onboarding process?
Is there a vetting process?
Is there a management process and
is there a decommission process for
those agents and AI agent identities?
What are the risks here?
So let's look at it.
So non-human identity,
scale, risk, and governance.
So service accounts, API keys, OAuth
tokens, workload identities that's
your largest and fastest-growing
identity population, and historically,
that's the least privileged.
So this is going to apply for
your AI agent identities as well.
So why they are a high risk?
Long-lived credential that we never
rotate, over-permissive scopes granted
at creation, no MFA, no behavioral
baseline, orphaned accounts that
outlive the service, and they are
hard to correlate across systems.
So the governance answer maps one-to-one.
Discover and inventory everything.
Automate the rotation.
So issue a short-lived
token for any identity.
Run anomaly behavior for all
the agent identities, non-human
identities, and tie the credential
lifecycle to the service lifecycle.
So when a service dies or
when a process dies, right?
So the identity should die with it.
So to do that, we should have a
sound lifecycle management of the
service and its identity tied to it.
So in most organizations, we are
like, "Okay, the application has to be
decommissioned, the w-- process workflow
has to be decommissioned." But are we
focusing on the identity tied to it?
Is the identity decommissioned
non-human identity specifically, is
decommissioned after the application
or service is decommissioned?
So that's a huge gap which needs to be
fixed in each and every organization.
And for-- f-from agent identity
perspective, that's key.
So A-AI agent identity,
trust delegation at scale.
So what does that mean?
So there are three pillars for
agents: agent authentication,
scoped authorization, and
audit and trace-traceability.
So agent authentication.
So every agent gets a verifiable,
non-shareable identity.
Shared credentials between agent instances
create accountability gaps that you
can't investigate after an incident.
So scoped authorization.
Permission scoped to the task under.
So re-- so a summarization
agent should never hold write
access to a production database.
So it should have only read access.
So similarly the role and access
should tie to the specific task
the agent is going to execute.
Audit and traceability.
So every agent action should be
audited traced across what it is
doing so that it can be used for the
investigation or for the compliance
purpose So if you cannot answer which
identity did the task then there is
no agent security in the environment.
Or even if you further say-- if we
cannot say that if the agent was
supposed to do it or allowed to do
it, then we don't have a sound agent
life cycle policy or agent governance.
So centralized-- so how we can achieve it?
So centralized identity
governance, resilience by design.
So distributed siloed identity creates
blind spots you cannot reconcile.
So-- And the moment that matters most
of it is the moment of compromise.
So we need to make sure there is
detection containment, and recovery.
Okay?
So centralized telemetry spots
anomalous behavior, which
helps you with the detection.
So-- And then for containment, you
should have one governance plane
where you should cut it down.
I, I would term it as a AI kill switch.
So unless there is a governance plane,
you cannot revoke the credential or kill
the AI agent to stop the compromise.
And then recovery.
So there should be pre-staged
playbooks reissue and re-scope
without manual coordination.
So organizations with centralized
governance contain breaches in minutes,
fragment one measure it in days.
That gap is your lateral exposure window
So let's talk about infrastructure
level impacts the three pillars, right?
Everything I have described here produces
three infrastructure level outcomes.
Reduced attack in surface.
So least privilege limits what a
compromised identity can reach.
So limited lateral movement and
then continuous verification
stops stolen credentials from
traversing the pipeline undetected.
Fastest incident recovery.
So centralized governance
enables system-wide revocation
and pre-built playbooks.
So unless you have that, you cannot
recover from a incident faster.
So pretty much it's if it is like less
reach, less movement faster recovery.
That's the whole thesis
in the three words each.
So let's discuss the
architecture principles.
Identity by design.
So define boundaries, trust relationships,
and scopes before you build the pipeline,
not after the production failure, right?
Not after onboarding your
pipeline into production.
Zero implicit trust.
So every component authenticates and
authorizes independently regardless
of network location or prior sessions.
Continuous enforcement.
So replace point-in-time decisions with
single signal-driven authorization.
Unified governance.
Human services and agents under
one framework with consistent
policy, audit, and lifecycle.
So lifecycle is very critical
in this process So what are the
common patterns we need to avoid?
So let's look at that.
Rapid fire.
So over-privileged service accounts.
So broad access granted for convenience.
Never scope down.
One token can take down your whole
platform or your en-whole environment.
So that should be avoided.
So over-privileged service account should
be reviewed and it should be scaled down.
The permission should be scaled down.
Credential sprawl.
So keys and tokens hardcoded in code,
config, and environmental variables
ungoverned and in-and invisible.
So it should be governed in a proper
way that we have all the inventory and
it's visible to, to the whole admins.
Implicit agent trust.
So framework passing identity
context without re-authentication.
So a compromised sub-agent
inherits the parent's trust.
And then siloed identity operations.
So what it means?
So humans owned by IT, service
accounts by DevOps, agents by nobody.
So none of these are like zero
days, they are governance gaps.
So it, it is not like somebody is going
to release a a zero-day vulnerability
alert that you have to fix it.
It's a governance gap which has to be
leveled up when AI infrastructure or AI
agent or AI's application is brought into
your environment So those are some of the
common failures which needs to be avoided.
So what are the key takeaways here?
One, elevate IAM to a
infrastructure status.
Same rigor as networking or compute.
So it's not just so you, you-- we
are focusing more on firewall rules
and network bound-boundaries, but
identity is the new perimeter.
So you have to focus on
designing and applying governance
controls on the IAM plane.
Govern non-human identity.
So in most of the organizations
today, there is a governance process
for human identities in fact.
So we have MFA, we have audits,
regulatories which governs it.
But for non-human
identities, it's different.
So inventory and scope them
properly, and then make sure the
least privilege and rotation is
happening for all the credentials.
Architect for continuous verification.
So again, the same point, right?
So for non-human identities, there
should be a continuous verification to
make sure if the service or application
which it was supporting is still active.
The final takeaway is the network
perimeter can't follow your
workloads, but identity can.
So build identity first before
you scale AI, before retrofitting
governance after an incident.
So we should be defining life cycle,
making sure there is governance process
against all the AI identities before
even you bring it into your environment.
And if we are not doing that, the
lessons are going to be expensive.
So we should be careful in this.
So with that I'm closing my slides.
Thank you.
Thank you for everybody.
I'm Arun Muthuramanlingam.
You can find me on LinkedIn.
Happy to keep the conversations going.
Thank you Conference
forty-two for having me.
Thank you.