Greetings, everyone.
This is Krishna, and today we are
diving into how AI is not just
changing, but transforming the
product lifecycle management.
Think of it less as a technical
upgrade and more like giving
your PLMA superpower AI break.
Systems and lead into a future
where innovation is faster,
smarter, and more efficient.
So, what's PLM?
What really it is, it's a story of a
product from its first spark of an idea.
Retirement as.
Is the backbone of product
development, integrating people,
data processes, and business systems.
Imagine you are building
a complex machine.
PM is the blueprint that guides
every step from the initial
sketch to the final assembly,
and even to how your you service.
The aftermarket part of it.
Now let's talk about the challenges
many of us are dealing with,
what I like to call as a legacy.
The document here highlights
the understanding of legacy a.
Let's think it this way to inherit
a house with a complex plumbing
system, but no one left you a map.
You find files are going in all
directions, some are disconnected,
some are leaking, and you are dealing
with a situation, something similar
to, legacy PLM, can feel like.
The document also mentions the difficulty
of tracing an engineering change order.
So just think you're trying to
recall a change that you have made
to a product to a complex machine
10 years back with records scattered
across different departments.
Some in paper, some in software.
It's like trying to piece.
Together a puzzle with
missing pieces into it.
These issues lead to errors,
delays, and it's mainly because of
the undocumented travel knowledge.
Have you ever had a situation
where only person who knew
how to fix a critical issue.
awards on a vacation and
no one else had a clue.
That's the tribal knowledge that's
in action, and it's a huge, big
risk, especially in the product
development, product management, area.
Now let's see how AI shines here.
It's like bringing an expert
plumber with a digital map.
Tools to fix, that complex
AI can help us analyze,
making them and efficient.
It can also help us the,
that we providing a.
Why, when was it approved?
What change was made from one
change order region to next region?
it's clearly traceable.
It can capture the tribal
knowledge turning into
accessible and searchable data.
Now let's talk about some of the benefits.
Benefits of, the artificial
intelligence, the real world wind.
That's what we call document mentions.
Here, the AI powered PLN solutions
are projected to reduce time to
market by 30% while improving the
product quality metrics by up to 35%.
Lemme give you a reliable example.
Imagine you are developing
a new smartphone.
Traditionally, you have teams working in
silos, passing information back and forth.
With ai, you can have a centralized
system that and allows the data from
all stages of development identify
the potential issues earlier.
you can catch design flaws before
they reach to manufacturing,
saving time and money and effort.
Another, relatable example is
the predictive maintenance.
Imagine a wind turbine with sensors
connected to an AI powered system.
The AI analyze data predict when.
It's likely to gonna fail alarming or
proactive maintenance and preventing
the cost of downtime and any unwanted,
loss of efforts and applications.
no.
Let's talk about, let's talk about
the implementation strategies.
How do we bring these vision in life?
Start with the small and focused projects.
Identify the areas where AI can have
the biggest impact and build from there.
Remember, it is not about technology.
It's about people.
In training and chain management
to ensure everyone is on board,
essentially addressing the organizational
transformation or chain management,
challenges here, and of course the
data security is most important.
It's paramount.
Implement the robust data
protection frameworks and.
And conduct regular security, audits.
Also, the emphasis is on
maintaining the ethical standards.
And of course, the data
security comes along with that.
So let's talk about, how.
Some of the key studies that we have here,
for example, Boeing, one of the leading
aircraft manufacturer maintenance company
through AI driven, PLM, the process around
two terabytes of data from their sensors
across more than thousand aircraft flake.
And, with that, they achieved a 35%
reduction in unplanned maintenance and
also the decrease in the part replacement
cough because, upfront, proactively,
what's gonna happen, where things
can go wrong, where things can fail,
and the proactive maintenance helps.
to reduce the maintenance and component.
Similarly, Tesla, they,
they use, AI power.
Is reducing the downtime line by 40% and
cost and a.
No, definitely the future
of AI is, is very strong, is
very prosperous, with ai, you.
So these air power digital pins,
you can simulate the product
behavior, with the 99% accuracy.
for example, when you manufacture a car,
an airplane, you create, the models,
you do some tests and see how it works.
But with these.
Digital pins, you don't need to do that.
You can create the virtual models,
try do some tests, validations,
and which are like 99%, accurate.
Accurate.
And also this AI powered.
Solutions will are giving you operative
maintenance and automated design
that is helping you to optimize
and make your supply chain more
intelligent and more, more powerful.
And at the same time, there are
some widespread challenges we
have seen in the industry, like
data quality and integration.
Have legacy systems.
Data model that you have for the
legacy systems may be different
from the modern systems.
For example, the mismatch between bill
of materials formats, the data models
between your PLM systems and say for
example, your ER PSAP system can lead
to a, decrease in, accuracy and even,
it'll the cross function collaboration
between engineering and procurement.
Another important factor is a skill gap.
We need a person who understands
PLM and as well as the artificial
inclusion AI technologies.
This gap is evident.
It's difficult to find such
professionals, and that's one of the
challenge in adopting AI for PLM.
The other factor is the
implementation cost.
Implementation cost is very high.
It varies between $500 to $5 million.
and of, and often justifying that
initial investment in infrastructure
and licenses, is always a, challenge.
Another thing is the perceived complex.
May not.
Recommended, options, AI
recommended, opportunities while
making a critical decision.
So these are some of the challenges,
you need to keep in mind while
adopting AI in, in, in, in p and m
in general, the future looks bright.
AI is not just a tool, it's catalyst.
Break free from the limitations of the
past and build a future where innovation
is faster, smarter, and more sustainable.
So with this, future is
definitely bright and, looking
for your comment and feedback.
Thank.