Speaker 9: Hello, everyone.
My name is Karishma Velasetty, and in
today's session, we'll cover practical
AI-assisted workflows in soft audit
shops and the governance controls
needed to make them reliance grade.
We'll move through nine use cases,
map them towards the risk, close
with a governance framework that
your team can act on immediately
Here's the quick agenda that
we'll walk through today.
Bulk of our time will be spent
on discussing on these nine use
cases and the risk profiles, and
the governance section will give
you more on the practical controls
The three categories of AI tools that
are right now currently being actively
used in SOX environment are here.
I've listed out in three sections.
The first one is code
and analytics assistance.
These are the ones… These are tools that
are being used by data-savvy auditors or
engineers that are either used to build
scripts, any develop, write any code
or any applications review any code.
And then we have language
and document AI tools.
These are m- majorly used for either
drafting, reviewing, summarizing
whether there are any documentation
or any test sheets for SOX.
And then we-- the last one
is specialist a- audit AI.
These are the most integrated
tools that directly work
with your SOX workflow hooks.
Or the different-- there
are different types of tools
right now available in market.
I have listed out a couple of the
most popular tools that are being
used by internal audit teams.
But there are ob- obviously there
are many more also available.
And all three groups here
carry distinct risk profiles.
So we'll go over that in
in the following slides.
So nine use cases in total.
The first five you'll-- what you'll
see on the screen, the code review,
contract review, invoice reconciliation,
control narrative, and test sheets.
These are mostly right now being
widely adopted, and you'll see that
mostly the adoption is pretty high
in large internal audit functions.
And the remaining four, like journal
entry testing user ac-user access
review, the flux analysis, and
walk-through docs are pretty much
right now in the earlier stages,
but they're rapidly growing as well.
Let's dive into each one of them
The first one is reviewing
audit analytics scripts with AI.
Basically code review.
This is the most common use case
for code generation AI, like
whether we use tools like GitHub
Copilot, Cursor, Claude, ChatGPT.
And the biggest SOX risk
here is the over-reliance.
If an auditor starts accepting
the AI review findings or the code
explanation or the code description
without even understanding what
the output is, what the code is or
understanding the logic of it, the human
review becomes like a rubber stamp.
You've lost the control over here.
So it's very important that whatever
output the code the tool has been
generating, whether which-whichever
tool it is, whether it's a code ex…
and it's generating a code explanation
or gen-- identifying any findings,
deficiencies, it's very important that
we review a human reviews thoroughly
to the output of that tool or the, or
whatever output has been generated.
The another key aspect here
is the auditory requirement.
Auditory requirement is very critical
for PCAOB compliance and also from
an external auditor point of view.
So external auditors could ask
you who has reviewed the code?
When was it generated?
What tool was it u-used?
What was the logic behind it?
And so on.
So having an auditory
requirement is also a key step.
Yeah.
So just a couple of things to remember.
Whatever type of the code it is, make
sure a human is formally reviewing
it doing a proper sign-off of any
AI review findings or any AI code
explanation before even it's approved.
And then the log AI review session,
that's basically making sure what tool
it was used, what is a finding, and all
the aspects for an auditory requirement
make sure that's been well documented.
And lastly, the second-level reviewer,
either by a CPA or an audit lead or a
senior team member, is also required
because it helps us to make sure that all
scripts used in the SOX reliance purposes
over the analytics is all accurate.
Second use case is reviewing contracts
and agreements for SOX relevant clause.
SOX review was a, in SOX review
purposes, we u- a lot of times use
have contract reviews as controls,
and AI adds a very huge value.
It will-- But with that adding
a huge value, it's also carrying
a very significant risk.
Contracts almost are universally
confidential, and many contain
material non-public information,
particularly pre-close M&A or
uncommitted revenue arrangements.
So since you know a con… The rule is
simple, a consumer AI never touches the
contracts, and the enterprise AI with
a DP can be used for the non-public
material non-public information contracts.
But they also make sure that it
requires to be an on-premise and
in a private deployment area.
Few risks here are whether
AI could misread a clause
contract or a legal nuance.
So make sure it's been thoroughly
reviewed, whatever the AI tool
generates an output or findings
based on the reviewing contracts.
Since contracts are confidential,
make sure the contract data is not
being sent to a uncontrolled AI API.
And hallucination, another big risk,
so make sure it's not hallucinating any
complex ASC 842 terms or any contractual
standards or any terms in the files.
So as previous use case, make sure
a human review is manually done, and
we're not blindly following the output.
And third one is invoice matching,
exception detection and reconciliation.
Invoice reconciliation is one
of the highest ROI application
of AI in SOX testing.
With that we-- the key aspect
in invoice matching and
reconciliation is the population.
So population completeness is the
first thing that we should make sure
is intact, and it's the first thing
that external auditors are gonna test.
So if you cannot prove your… If you
ran the, if you, the-- If you ran the
output against an incomplete population,
so if the population is not correct, the
results are not going to be re-reliable
as an audit evidence, and it's just
not the best output for you to use.
And it will have to, it'll
have to basically have a…
You will basically have
an unreliable output.
So make sure the population
completeness is definitely there.
And also the control descriptions
cannot be like an AI has got it.
They make sure the logic has
been very well-written, the
rules are very well-written we
understand what the flags are.
So a well-written logic should be, is
also very key aspect while doing any
invoice matching or exception detection
or any reconciliation task in SOX.
The other use case is drafting and
updating SOX control narratives.
This is where I see the most
enthusiasm and the most risk of
unintentional quality degradation.
AI is very good at producing
professionally sounding prose.
The danger is that it sounds
right without being right.
So make sure the…
whatever out-- whatever control
narratives are being used, it's based--
whether it's based on recordings or
files, is very apt and clear, so it's
producing the right narrative or the,
or producing the right documentation.
The fix is mandatory
process owner validation.
Not just reviewing it, but like formal
sign-off of the described steps that
match to what actually happened.
So maybe in the walkthroughs or in
the control narratives, we might
have not covered the entire steps.
We have just the control process owner
or the control owner might just explained
some of the steps that they are, they
think are the key, but may not exactly
be going over the entire detailed
control description of the process.
So making sure the control narratives
are based on a very rich and a
solid documents and as used for
input, that's very important.
So make sure process owners, you don't
validate only with process owners, but
you also thoroughly review it and make
sure they are complete before you use
it for your SOX documentation purposes.
So cross-references is
the most required step.
Test sheet generation and
for client audit workpapers.
This is the highest leverage use
case because it's most repeated among
hundreds of controls in each cycle.
The risk that concerns me the most
is the COSO assertion coverage.
The AI generates test steps that
makes logical sense but may not
conver-- cover all the assertions
relevant to a specific control.
For example, like a sample size.
AI may just suggest a number, but
the number actually needs to be
grounded in your organization's
sampling policy and material levels.
So don't blindly follow any thresholds
or any test attributes that AI provides,
but make sure that you are providing
your thresholds, numbers or control
attributes and test attributes.
So hence the key requirement here is
have your all audit documentation,
test sheets, audit workpost being
reviewed by an senior auditor or a
manager, and you take a sign-off.
And before even you actually
document that, do not make sure…
do just self-approve it since
the AI tool has generated it.
Make sure you do all
the validations as well.
And comparatively the other four risks
are put in a category which are more
emerging, such as the journal entry
testing, the user access review, the flux
analysis, and walk-through documentation.
Journal entry testing and the user
access review are some more mature
comparatively of these four, and
many specialist audit tools have
been using this for quite many years.
But what's new here is now they're
using it outside some dedicated platform
where with the help of AI, and which
means that the platform's built-in
governance controls no longer apply.
Flux analysis is a comparatively
new term, but it's basically where
AI is performing period-over-period
anal-analysis on the GL data.
Basically drafts management control
explanations or any unusual movements
or any outlier that it sees, and
highlights any items that it should be
investigated or looked much into detail.
And walk-through documentation is
also similar-- a very-- a little
bit similar to what we spoke in
the… on the control narratives.
But they both, flux analysis and
walk-through documentation, they're
both mostly a newer AI applications
very high value, but also to note that
could be a risk of high AI-generated
content making into SOX documentation
without much of a proper validation.
Again, great use cases to use
in SOX, but validation thorough
validation much is needed.
Journal entry analysis is again one
of the most powerful application of
AI considering it's been so manual and
one of the most common Public Company
Accounting Oversight Board, that's
PCAOB findings where if done poorly.
Standards such as AS2401 standard or
most SOX general journal entry testing
proce-procedures usually call for a
full population analysis, and AI makes
it genuinely feasible at that scale to
perform that analysis at first time.
Again, the most critical aspect is
population con-completeness in this.
So if you cannot prove that AI ran against
the full population, the results are not
going to be reliable as an audit evidence.
So make sure the population is complete.
But again, this is a great example
of using AI to do the analysis
AI assisted user access review and
segregation of duty conflict detection.
This is a very high volume of SOX controls
that rely and that AI can be meaningfully
accelerate, especially for large ERP
environments with thousands of roles.
The segregation of duties role
matrix is most common important
governance artifact here.
If the matrices-- the matrix is
stale, the AI analysis is gonna
be built on false foundation.
So make sure that's more
accurate and up to date.
And the role owner sign-off
is non-negotiable from PCAOB
perspective, so the certificate
decisions cannot be delegated to AI.
So make sure and that's accurate as well.
A role owner formal owner formal
sign-off is usually required for
every access certificate decision.
So AI can flag, but also a
human to actually certify it.
AI assisted period over period
variance and analytical review.
This is a case where financial
statements flux analysis as well AI's
ability to draft explanatory languages
that creates a productivity trap.
AI is very good in producing plausible,
soundable explanations, but the
risk is that these explanations is
not same as accurate and complete.
So a management representation letter risk
is high… representation risk is high.
And I've seen that AI drafted letters
that are very well written but
contain assertions that management had
actually not reviewed or not supported.
So make sure all the AI drafted
management representation letters are
working documents only, and the final
sign off documents or representation
require full management approval cycle.
So making sure again, like with
similar previous use cases these are
the certain risk where we actually
m-need to make sure that a management
or a human has been reviewing
AI assisted interview capture
and process documentation.
Walkthrough documentation adoption
is also accelerating very fast,
driven by the rollout of meeting AI
tools like whether it's like Google
Meets or any tools that are you
using for in within your enterprise.
And but with recording and with these
meeting tools, the most important
aspect here is the legal issue that
recording consent in many jurisdictions.
So not just the audit quality issue, the
policy needs to be explicit about this
before any walkthrough bes-- begins.
It should be you your organization
and the external auditor agree with
recording before any walkthrough
or any meetings happening.
The AI memo is the starting
point not substitute for a
fieldwork, but if documents are…
In documents what process owner said,
not necessarily what actually happens.
So make sure for walkthrough documentation
you have the right amount of whether
it's recordings or files that could
be used to document well-structured.
And again, few risk here are there are--
there could be errors in transcripts,
the meeting transcript notes or
there's no recording consent from the
process owner or the external auditors.
Make sure that you have that as well as
like any audio or transcript data that's
been stored in a non-compliant AI systems.
So making sure the documents are
also well-stored is also key aspect.
The lastly, the governance framework
applies unif-uniformly across all
these nine use cases that we spoke.
For example, for the code review
and analytics, the technical
controls are the most critical.
Whereas for like contract review
and narratives, the people
process controls are the priority.
And monitoring and assurance is what
keeps the framework honest toward
all the time, so it applies to all
of the nine use cases that we spoke
Some key takeaways from all the use cases
that we spoke and all the approaches or
what the or whichever tools that your
organization been using is that make
sure… The first one is like the AI
tools now span across the full audit
lifecycle, so make sure that you are
accurately using them, managing the risk
by thoroughly human review making sure
the documents are safe, making sure the
rules, the logic are being defined widely.
Second is the confidentiality.
Confidentiality is non-negotiable.
So one MNPI incident in a
consumer AI tool creates basically
regulatory and legal exposure.
So making sure your data has been
secured you're using the right
approved tools, that's very important.
And thirdly is the validation.
As I said, validation
is not same as a review.
So formal sign-offs from a person
accountable or a senior auditor
or a senior manager is must.
So make sure you get that and not
just rely on the output from the tool.
That's it from my side.
Thank you very much for your time today