Hey everyone.
Welcome to com 42 on
large language models.
My name is Peter Deten, technical
trainer at Microsoft Live,
presenting from Redmond, Washington.
My session today covers using
Azure AI Foundry to manage all
your large language models.
With that, I would say
welcome and let's go.
Over the next 45 minutes to an hour, I
will cover the following topics, starting
with a quick overview of the future
of work with ai, followed by domain
section, how Azure AI Foundry is used by
Microsoft itself to run AI solutions and
obviously how you can leverage the same.
And then last, how to bring in a rag
architecture, meaning using all the beauty
from Azure AI together with AI Foundry.
Generative AI using large language models,
but then also integrating your own data.
And then for each of these topics,
you can expect quite some live
demos during the session as well.
So again, my name is
Peter d Tander originally.
Originally from Belgium, but ated to
Redmond, Washington to continue my
job as a Microsoft technical trainer.
I've been a Microsoft trainer
for about six years now.
before I joined Microsoft in a full-time
employee position, I was already working
for them as a partner and vendor out of
my own company for about seven years.
My Azure background has always been on
the infra and in architecture side, but
gradually I shifted more into DevOps
developing Azure solutions, and nowadays,
obviously a lot about AI and copilot.
Feel free to reach out if you
should have any questions using
any of the listed methods.
Good.
So with that all out of
the way, let's jump in.
Now.
When I talk about AI in any of
the Azure and AI workshops I'm
teaching, I always like to start
with a quote from our CEO Satya.
He explained it as follows.
Organizations are asking not only how,
but also how fast they can actually
apply this next generation of AI to
address the biggest opportunities
and challenges they are facing.
Good with that all out of
the way, let's jump in.
Now when I talk about AI in our
workshops here at Microsoft, I always
like to start with a quote from our CEO.
Satya.
Organizations are asking not only how,
but also how fast they can apply this
next generation of AI to address the
biggest challenges, but also opportunities
they face safely and responsibly.
Now the core of the quote will
become more clear by the end of my
session, so that, let's start with
the foundation, understanding what
the future of work with AI looks like.
For the last two years, give or take,
organizations have primarily been
experimenting with different models.
I think it is safe to say that OpenAI
with Jet GPD revolutionized the world
with Jet GPD again, end of 2023.
But from there, several other players
came into the market like Gemini,
from Google, and Tropic with Claude.
deep seek from China, Microsoft
having the five, models, menstrual,
hugging, face, and so many other.
Now what this slide represents is how
many different models are actually
being used by an organization.
The average, you could say here
is, 3, 2, 5, so probably four as
the average where no one on the
interviewed organizations was just
relying on a single large language
model for any of their AI solutions.
Now also important to highlight is
that about 80% of early AI projects
actually fail because not meeting
expectations and not meeting them
because they're too complex now.
Complexity and the fact that
especially generative AI is
still rather new technology.
And also providing a breadth
of large language models to
choose from, but then also.
The fact that applications are
changing, moving from single models
into orchestrated systems, allowing
to learn and adapt continuously.
Customers and users are expecting
AI influenced, or you could
say AI inspired capabilities.
In almost any kind of application
today across different industries
and across different use cases.
Now, even amidst these challenges, it's
clear that generative AI is what makes
applications through the intelligent,
but that's also a paradigm shift.
AI is moving from this, I don't
know, autopilot phase, which was all
about narrowing purpose-built tools
that use machine learning models.
To now come up with
predictions recommendations.
also just automating to now having this
co-pilot era where there's tremendous
opportunity to really revolutionize
how just about everything can start
using those intelligent applications.
You can now enable natural language
interaction, constantly improving user
experience and quickly delivering new
features and capabilities to the market.
So with that, let's shift gears
a little bit and talk about
Azure AI Foundry specifically.
By the way, one of the reasons Microsoft
has moved such fast pace over the last
few months is because our Microsoft
AI solutions within Microsoft are
all running using Azure AI Foundry.
Now we've built our Microsoft
copilot reaching in meantime,
millions of users across the globe.
Informing them across different platforms
using, for example, just copilot on
the mobile device in the browser,
using copilot web, using copilot
within Microsoft 3 6 5 applications,
security copilot dynamics copilot,
Azure co-pilot, and GitHub copilot.
All of these co-pilot are a hundred
percent begged by Azure AI Foundry.
Which now also becomes available to you.
So you might have heard about Azure AI
Studio before, where it's still the same
foundation, I would say being the one-stop
shop, like a management portal for
developers IT sales admins, cloud admins.
If you want to create your own custom
copilots leveraging ai, Azure AI services.
So insured Azure AI Foundry is a
trusted, integrated platform designed for
developers, IT admins, cloud architects,
allowing them to design, customize, and
manage AI applications as well as agents.
Nowadays, it offers a rich set of AI
capabilities and tools, and yes, I'll
walk you through a few of these in a demo
using an easy to use, easy to navigate.
Portal, but there's also a unified SDK
providing you APIs to really accelerate
the path from developing to production.
Now, what sets Azure AI Foundry apart
is the accessibility through the world's
most loved developer tools, meaning
GitHub Visual Studio and co-pilot studio.
This really integrates with
a lot of other scenarios.
So what we see here is continuously
building up on Azure AI Foundry being this
open, flexible, modular platform, sorry,
with a lot of the tools a developer needs
in a single platform to build multi-agent
solutions, integrating third party tools.
Just like we've done with our own models.
This also means that developers now get
access to Quick Start AI application
templates to support their development
cycle and really shortening that
complexity that I talked about before.
Any of these templates can be customized
using a wide area of already existing
models and tools, making your applications
future-proof development investments.
Another part I wanna talk
about is it governance.
So IT governance at scale, like
what we call here, enterprise
setup is baked in AI foundry.
It allows you to provide a comprehensive
approach providing self-service
experiences, customizable configurations,
and overall enhancing agility, security,
but also keeping compliance in mind.
So to give you an idea, there's
obviously prebuilt baked in.
Azure and Azure AI Foundry, role-based
access control, including like owner
having you, giving you all permissions,
including changing security permissions.
They're a little bit lower
permission contributor, but there's
also reader ai, developer and AI
inference deployment operator roles.
Little bit complex there.
but what it means is like for
any kind of responsibility as
part of your development cycle.
You can have, a corresponding
role-based access control.
Next to that, all these roles, are
accessible from within the same AI
foundry where we now use a topology called
the hub and projects out of the hub.
It's like the highest
level in the topology.
You're gonna allocate one or
more projects, and within a
project you're gonna define.
The different, permissions On top
of that, you can think about other
features, mentioned here on the diagram.
Identity, access management,
network security, data protection,
encryption, compute, storage,
quota, access to the models.
All that is now becoming available
within a project and within a hub.
Mainly avoiding that each and every
developer when they're working
on an AI inspired application
that they have to deploy, like
the full architecture themselves.
So you would almost say that your cloud
team is now building the hub and project.
And developers are consuming the
services, the building blocks within
a project, and then on the outside.
And then on the outside
we have our business it.
And from there we could also expand
with IT security because in the
end, it's still part of the broader
Azure world, which means that
everything you might already know.
From Azure Tenants, Azure subscriptions
management groups, like the whole
governance layer around it is now
also still valid once you start
deploying your AI foundry and
corresponding Azure Resources.
Apart from the core AI services
dependencies extended with other
Azure resources like E Vault,
private networking, and the like.
You can now also easily, I would
say, provide access to those external
resources from within AI Foundry
using a feature called Connections.
So again, it means that instead of needing
to provide access to your development
team, your IT Cloud admins to all those
resources, it's now becoming just another
aspect of your AI Foundry landscape.
And these connections are
typically already linked to
multiple projects within a hub.
And with that, let's shift to a first
demo here where I'll walk you through the
base deployment of Azure AI services, as
well as a first look at Azure AI Foundry,
showing you the hope and project, as well
as how to add and manage your connections.
So my starting point here is my Azure
subscription, and I got everything inside
my, sample com 42 Foundry resource group.
I already deployed most of the
resources that I need, but my
assumption is that you already know
how to deploy some resource in Azure.
So not all that important.
for now.
One of the building blocks
I have is an Azure AI hub.
I'll talk about that a
little bit again later on.
Within, we got a project, the core that
I'm using here is Azure AI Services,
and I got a few site services over here,
like a container registry and Azure Key
Vault log analytics for my monitoring.
So the starting point will most probably
be your AI service, which means that
you would go into the Azure portal.
From there, you would deploy
a new service called Azure AI
Service, and that's pretty much it.
Now, from a development perspective, there
are a few things that you need to keep in
mind for connecting to your AI service.
Primarily, I would say here,
endpoints and your keys.
So when we move to endpoints, what
we have is obviously depending
on the different AI use cases.
In my example here, I'm using OpenAI
to really have that generative AI
capability available as an endpoint
allowing me to integrate later on
my large language models and so much
more out of my foundry interface.
I. If I wanna interact with
other AI services like the
more traditional ones, right?
Compute, vision, content, safety,
language, translator, I can again
find all that information up here.
Now, the reason why, we have our AI
Foundry as a portal is because in
the end from here, what I'm doing is
just managing the Azure resources.
So you could almost say
that this should be a part.
That maybe your developer is
not really seeing anymore.
Why not?
Because for them, everything
that is related to management
is now moved into AI Foundry.
By the way, if you navigate back
to the starting point AI service,
you can see down here there is
the Azure AI Foundry portal link.
So let me move over to that one,
and that's where we are now,
landing in our Foundry portal.
Now, there's a few different ways you can.
You'd end up here.
So I talked about the
hub and project, right?
But when within my setup here,
you won't really see that.
So depending a bit how you get
there, you're gonna see that.
Right now here I'm in my Azure
open AI service because for
this scenario, I started from
deploying an open ai Azure service.
now if I navigate to my other scenario,
I'm now in my Azure AI foundry, homepage
you could say, which by the way, you
can navigate to from ai.azure.com.
And within.
As you can see here, I do
have my hub and my project.
When I navigate to my hub,
you're gonna see some highlights
from my Azure subscription.
So down here I can still
see my Azure subscription.
I could switch back to manage it in
my Azure portal, but now I can also,
as a developer, picking up the AI
endpoints and keys that I need from here.
So instead of now just having
my open AI service, it's not.
Now switched, you could say, to
Azure AI Foundry Management Center.
Within the management center,
we have obviously the overview
of our hubs and projects.
And again, the logic is that you
would create one or more hubs as
the higher level in the topology
and underneath you would create
one or more projects within a hub.
So that's the relationship
you can see from here.
I got my AI project as part of my.
AI hub.
That's the logic behind it.
Staying within the hub level for a minute.
I talked about RAC, role-based access
control, where now you can see I got
my AI admin and a little bit lower.
I got my Azure ML data scientists
replicating that you have someone
managing the AI service and you might
have some data scientist on the other side
interacting with the storage, providing,
the data endpoints most probably.
And then from there, allowing my
developers to start interacting.
You can manage your quota.
So if I switch back up here,
one of the, I would say.
Configuration options
you have within Azure.
Later on when we start deploying
our models is that you need to
know a bit about the models.
First of all, you need to know how much
tokens, like the virtual AI currency,
I would call it, your application
would need, but also knowing that each
and every Azure region together with
the models, also provide you a quota.
So in my setup here, I already
have a few scenarios like models
deployed and I'll show you in there.
Next demo how to actually do this.
But what you can see here
is that I deployed GPT-4 oh.
This is the version I'm using most,
probably the latest one, and I'm
allocating 8,000 tokens per minute.
We're now, for the total of my Azure
region, there's 450,000 available.
So depending on the needs of
your application, you're gonna
allow less or more numbers of
tokens or thousands of tokens.
Because they heavily influence, the
richness, I would say, of the prompts
your users can run, but also, how complete
the actual, prompt response can be.
Where at some point you might actually
run out of tokens, and that's where
now in the quota you need to validate
what your Azure region, provides.
So that's the first, I would say
high level scenario on how to
actually navigate across your.
AI foundry starting from the Azure
portal, deploying an Azure AI service,
and within navigating to Foundry.
Where next you have the option to use the
hub and, project topology allocating REC.
And then in the next step, we're gonna
allocate our actual, language models.
But for now, back to the presentation.
While most of my demos will happen from
the AI Foundry portal, I understand
that most developers will probably
like to interact from a, I don't know,
development interface, and that's
where an SDK comes into the picture.
So the good news is that there is an
Azure ai, SDK specifically available.
To equip developers streamlining
AI integration and really enriching
that user experience and building in
functionalities into their applications.
This toolkit supports multiple programming
languages, Python, c sharp.net,
Java, you think of it, you name it,
and it is supported, really enabling
developers to select the language of
choice and making them more productive.
While developing, generative
AI inspired applications.
So from there, developers can
efficiently build, evaluate,
deploy those AI components.
The SEK integration is obviously
part of the already trusted
development environments, mentioned
before, GitHub Visual Studio vs.
Code, and you're gonna interact
with your AI Foundry not from
within the portal, like I'll show
you in the demo, but obviously from
within the SDK integration directly.
With the base Azure Services
and AI Foundry up and running.
Let's talk a bit about the large language
models, which by the way is the topic
of the conference overall, right?
With Azure AI Foundry, you
get access to an extensive
list of large language models.
Really allowing you as the developer
or obviously your customers,
to choose the models that make
most sense for your solution.
Now, while this list here on
screen might not feel extensive.
Know that there are more than
a thousand different models.
Yes, more than a thousand to choose
from available today, which can all
be deployed within your AI foundry.
Even I would say deep seek.
One of the more recent, large
language models integrated
only a couple of weeks ago.
It's already available, and we got more
on the list coming out in the near future.
So for that, let me jump back to my
demo environment and show you how
easy it can be to search for models,
deploy the models, and also covering
a few other, I would say, baseline
tasks once you start using models
and all from within AI Foundry.
All right.
So with that, let's have a look at,
the actual large language models can be
deployed again from within our AI foundry.
So I'm still at the screen where,
I finished my previous demo.
There was actually one
part I forgot to show you.
And that's, the connectors
or connected resources.
Now, if you think about how
a developer interacts with.
The AI service, as I showed you, there's
the endpoint, but there's also the keys.
And later on we'll talk about rag
architecture, which means you're
probably gonna integrate, like AI search.
And then in the last part there's a
little bit, I'll talk about content
safety, making sure that your
application is following our Microsoft
responsible AI framework guidelines.
So all of these are standalone
services, standalone resources
in the Azure platform.
We're now again, in that mindset
that your developer will probably
need access to all those resources.
Instead of giving them access from
an Azure perspective, you could now
allocate them as an available resource
for the hub or an individual project.
And that's mainly what you
could manage from here.
So just to clarify the interface, if
you've never really seen, AI Foundry
in action, the highest level AI foundry
is available from ai.azure.com and
underneath you're gonna create a hub.
Within the hub.
You later on gonna create a project
that we already talked about,
and then from there we interact
with our connected resources.
So from here I could interact with new.
I talked about Key Vault.
I didn't really, deploy it yet, but you
could interact with OpenAI, with your
speech and other, some other services.
And if you want, you could actually
directly connect to other service
building blocks in Azure or
even outside of Azure as well.
Now, from here, we can
shift to our models.
Now, there's a few different ways, I
would say within the portal to do this,
depending if you are active on a project,
active on a. Are active in the open AI
services that I showed you at the start.
From here, I navigated inside the hub
and I'm now inside this specific project
where you can see, as you already
know from my previous demo, I already
have some of my connections available.
So what this means is that, for example,
my cloud admin pre deploy the connections
and they're now becoming available.
But imagine that I also
wanna deploy my own specific.
That I only want to use
within this specific project.
So I could do this again from here
since I'm already in the project, right?
I could manage it all
from here, or why not?
I could open up my project
in a separate blade.
And then from here I get
again, my models and endpoints.
So it looks about the same.
It just depends on how
you're gonna navigate to it.
So let's show you how we can
add a new model, and this is now
giving me access to all possible
models within our environment.
So you can see I talked about, a bit
more than a thousand, and we actually
have almost 2000 available in there.
So you can start with
pre-built collections.
So if you want, you could filter
based on only the ones from OpenAI.
Like an easy example and then the list
will only obviously present those ones.
Or if you wanna filter based on what
I can do with them and then maybe
some specific features, like I only
wanna have the ones supporting chat
completions and overall completions.
Then you can see that
there are, open AI ones.
The Microsoft five one, there's minus
one, there's Lama from Meta, and again,
all the other ones showing up here.
So the next step now is
selecting your model.
It always provides you a pretty detailed
description, what that model actually
represents, and then you could also
define some of its, capabilities.
From there, you would confirm, now, since
I already deployed this, it's not gonna
allow me to deploy this anymore, so let's.
Try and select another one here, GPT-4 oh.
Still one of the more recent ones.
Again, explanation, sharing information
about the latest, version you could
say, and then some description
what it actually allows you to do.
So I'm gonna confirm, and the next
step is now defining the specifics
for my project so I can choose the
deployment type global standard.
It means that you're
gonna pay per API call.
And if you want, if the model supports
it, there's a few other ones as well.
I would say if you wanna know more
details, then please consult our,
Microsoft documentation, because
I don't have the time in this
demo to expand on all of these.
But it has a lot to do with.
The high variability aspects of the
Azure architecture in the backend.
Next, in our deployment details, we can
fine tune, customize this a little bit, so
you've got the different model versions.
some versions up and down.
You could say typically, my guidance
is to use the most up-to-date version,
but there might be specific use
cases where maybe you don't have
to or you don't want to do that.
If you wanna integrate it with
one of your previously discussed
connections, you could do that as well.
And then defining the tokens
per minute rate limit.
And again, this influences the use
cases of your application if you
wanna integrate content filtering.
So again, the content safety, right?
That's where, you could at least for now,
pick the default, because I'll talk about
this, a little bit more towards the end.
So you pick your model, use,
confirm some of the settings,
and from there you're gonna.
To run the deployment.
So pretty easy.
I would say pretty straightforward.
Once we have a model deployed,
like in this case, we typically
provide you some starting points.
And again, we're targeting
developers, right?
So what do you need here is.
Azure credentials.
Installing like Python example
in this case, and how to actually
start testing, validating, and
it's almost literally copy pasting.
If Python is your, language of choice.
If you go oh, actually I want to use
another language, I'm gonna do C sharp,
bam, within just a split second, it's
gonna give you the different steps,
how to import the necessary packages.
To install Azure AI and then obviously the
identity, and then from there, creating
a point to your AI service endpoint.
What's important here is the name of your
endpoint together with the deployment
and the name of your deployment.
And then you're gonna tune
your chat conversations.
I'll talk about this
a little bit later on.
And then if you want some additional
samples, how to interact with,
conversational context, how
to keep the history and so on.
Another angle to validate some
model information is now I
moved from project into the hub.
The way to deploy is obviously,
a hundred percent the same.
So if I wanna search for LAMA
instead of using any of the
pre-built categories and filters.
You could now interact
with, any of these models.
So the baseline is the same on the
hub level, on the project level,
so nothing really different.
Another scenario that I would like to
highlight here, this is the playground,
but I'll talk about the playground,
a little bit later on, is inside.
Our model catalog.
From here, it's basically
giving you the exact same view.
Now, where it is slightly different
is that again, here I'm inside the
open AI service specific option.
And again, I like to highlight that
it's all based on AI Foundry, but
every now and then, depending on
the model you deploy, it might show
you more or less, integrations.
If I now move to another open model here.
You can see that it also
allows me to deploy it.
It still provides all those details,
but now I could also look into why
should I maybe deploy this if one of my
colleagues already deployed this scenario?
So giving you, again,
quite some, some options.
Another question that we
sometimes get about the model
is getting access to metrics.
Now this is not showing you, like
specific details I would say about
the model, but more about how your
applications, how your developers
are using, targeting this model.
I just deployed this without actually
having a sample app in the front
of it, so that's why my metrics
are not really impressive, right?
But it should give.
You some idea that auditing
monitoring is also baked in.
And then a bit on our Microsoft security
framework or the responsible AI framework.
We have, since I deployed my model
using a default filter, it's already
having, some content safety as
part of my language model baked in.
And obviously for now, because I
didn't use it, there's no violations,
there's no abusive use and so on.
But again, giving you a pretty nice
idea about, what you could use it for.
Another example I can show you
is using the model catalog.
And again, this is the same catalog,
what I showed you before, it just giving
you the full list and a different view.
Why did I switch yet to another view?
Because there's another question
that we can answer from here
and that's what is, the model?
Supposed to help me with, or
also answering the question,
what model is better for a
specific purpose than another?
Since I got deep seek up here,
I'm gonna check out that model.
And same as before, providing
a description, but now it also
gives me a link to benchmarks.
So by design, what it's gonna do
is looking at, I would say its
own, core competition, right?
'cause as a developer.
You need to think about all these
different language models, and I'm
pretty sure that the conference sessions
will help you with a lot of this.
But then within our AI Foundry,
knowing that you get access to
more than, 1800, now, how do you
decide across those language models?
So that's where now you can easily
select any of the models and
there will always be benchmarking.
In this case, it's comparing the deep
seek feed three that I selected with
some of the other popular counterparts.
Parts, but nothing blocks you
from also integrating a comparison
that you can manage, that you
can tune with some other models.
I think with that, you should have
a pretty good idea about, using
different parts of the AI Foundry
portal, how to deploy the different
models using open AI service, using
other services within the hub and
project, and then also talked about.
The higher level model, catalog,
and the benchmarking, so that, let's
switch back to the presentation.
Nice.
So we're now at the point where we have
our large language models deployed.
We did some benchmark testing
and I briefly talked about some
other capabilities, like the
fine tuning I briefly touched on.
So I can hear your next question already.
coming up.
okay.
AI Foundry is the go-to portal I use for
generative AI with large language models.
But what about all the other more
traditional AI services that we had
in the Azure portal in the past?
I would say that's
actually a great question.
Now remember in the introduction
section we talked about the paradigm
shift in application development
where customers and users somewhat
expect to have AI capabilities.
In basically any kind of application
they're building or using.
While generative f AI seems to provide
a lot of those capabilities, all other
AI services you might know from the
past existing in Azure already are now
also gradually moving into AI Foundry
as that management, AI services portal.
For example, AI search for architecture,
although I'll talk about that later on,
but also talking about AI speech, AI
Vision, document intelligence, language
translator, all those services have been
around in Azure for close to 10 years
and can now gradually be integrated and
managed from within AI Foundry as well.
Now the magic behind the scenes to
manage all this is Foundry playground.
I already showed you a little bit
of this from within our AI Foundry
portal, especially around a large
language model deployment, but there's
actually a lot more you can do with it.
I would say let's have another look.
In this next demo, I'm gonna walk you
through AI Foundry, showing you some
of the capabilities around playground,
allowing you to test and validate
your models, and also switching to
some more traditional AI capabilities.
Good.
So we have our models deployed in the
previous part of the presentation,
which now means that we're ready
to actually test and validate.
So the way to do this is from
within once more AI Foundry,
we're now selecting playgrounds.
You could do this directly navigating
to ai.azure.com/playgrounds, and
then it's gonna pull up your project.
And allowing you to actually
build out your playgrounds.
Remember, we're primarily focusing
on generative AI using chat co
conversations, but remember that we
do have other AI services as well.
So if you wanna integrate with like speech
or the newer agents based, like auto gen
alike syns, or you wanna integrate with
like images using, for example, Dali or
some other large language model using.
Language playground.
And again, there's so many different
ways to start testing interacting.
The most obvious one is
using the chat playground.
So in the previous part of the
demo, we deployed our GPT model
as part of our hub and project.
I got two of them linked
to different connectors.
So again, emphasizing that all
those building blocks from the
start are still nicely coming
back here, I could start easy.
I got an AI assistant pretty.
Generic message here, and I'm gonna
ask something like, what is the
typical weather in Seattle mid-March?
now it's nicely responding
in mid-March and so on.
Obviously it's not about, the details,
although in a real life scenario, I
would obviously encourage you to really
validate and verify the actual response.
Now, again, based on your model, what
do we get as a confirmation here?
Is that the model is working,
it is responding well.
Now, if I would ask something like,
can you provide Belgian food recipe?
Remember my Belgian roots, it's gonna
come up with some ingredients, and again,
it's still doing a pretty good job.
Let's see.
It came up with a, so mussels and fries.
Perfect.
Like a typical Belgian dish.
It provides me the ingredients,
and next to that, it also provides.
The instructions and I'm actually
getting a little bit hungry now out
of that, but not there yet because I
need to show you a few other things.
Now, back to our starting point.
I got another project here, so
quickly switching where this time I
got two different language models.
Now remember, the language
model is trained on public data
up to a certain point in time.
Easy set.
GPT-3 five is.
Less up to date than GPT-4.
An easy example I can use to
show you how this works is who
is the Prime Minister of the uk?
now it's gonna tell me based on a date.
October 21.
The Prime Minister is Boris Johnson.
Pretty cool.
I got my answer.
Where now if I switch to my GPT-4 model
and I'm gonna run the same prompt,
I'm just gonna copy it from here.
You can see that now the
answer is different and not
only different in context.
Like the actual answer I would say is.
More up to date, but also just
by switching the model, you can
see that now I get access to
more tokens, a short answer, a
pretty, little bit longer answer.
And if you wanna tune all this a little
bit more, that's where you can go back
to, the previous part of the demo.
Another thing that's pretty
cool is interacting with what
your chat actually can do.
So right now I used an easy example.
This could be used for I dunno, writing
an essay on UK politics or something.
I don't know where.
Now we could tune this a little
bit more, where I could do
something like, you are, Microsoft.
Technical trainer with
expertise in Azure and Azure ai.
You can answer questions as long as
you keep it polite and professional.
There we go.
You cannot answer questions about
Amazon AWS or Google Cloud platform
to apologize in those scenarios.
Offer a Belgian beer
flavor to try out instead.
So now what I'm doing here is
tweaking, fine tuning if you want.
I use case where this could almost be like
a virtual Microsoft technical trainer.
I'm gonna run a new chat conversation
and from here I could do, can you explain
a bit about Azure Kubernetes service?
So it comes back as expected
with a nice detailed prompt.
I'm using GPT-4 oh latest version,
quite some tokens available in my
subscription when Now from here I could
ask, what is the use case for AWS Beans
stock, like an existing AWS service.
When now it tells me like, oh, I'm sorry.
So I asked it to be
professional and polite.
I think that's, pretty well covered here.
Unable to answer questions about AWS or
any other AWS service and then however.
To make up for it.
Again, being nice and professional,
I could recommend a Belgium beer.
How cool is that?
You can actually tune your environment,
your chat conversations, using by the
way, what we call the system message.
And then as a developer you
would integrate that, obviously
as part of your code as well.
And then allowing the chat
conversations, going back and forth.
So that's pretty much it.
Out of this demo showed you.
How to interact with the playground,
specifically this one for chat or
going back to the previous part of
the demo where you can choose across
different playgrounds depending on use
cases for images, integrating audio,
integrating other, assistant alike
scenarios back to the presentation.
Sweet.
This brings me to the last topic in
today's session covering rag architecture
or retrieval augmented generation.
Now, we heavily discussed large
language models and how they
enrich your applications with
generative AI capabilities.
For example, conversational
context, natural language,
and primarily chat driven.
One main characteristic for most LMS
is that they're trained using public
internet data, which obviously is
totally fine, but what if your app
needs to know about your organizational
data specifically, or your customer?
Your user can only use internal
company specific information, not
using the context from public models.
That's exactly what RAG or retrieval
augmented Generation is about.
Starting from a large language model
approach, you are now augmenting
enriching if you want the dataset your AI
application is using within your own data.
Which can be images, documents,
knowledge bases, and they can be
stored within the Azure backend.
And that's really the next step, right?
So if you are wondering like
where does this data come from,
like how do I integrate it?
There's a lot of different options.
So the easiest one I would say
is using Azure blob storage.
But nothing blocks you from
integrating with, for example,
Amazon S3 buckets as well.
And yes, I can show you also how
to upload files manually in the
Azure portal, although I don't
think it's like an enterprise
recommended approach to do that.
The backend interaction happens
out of Azure AI search, building up
what we call vector information for
each and every of your data sets.
And then once the indexing is done, your
AI application will be able to respond to
prompts in the same way you expect from
your large language model, but now using
knowledge coming in from your own data.
And you can expect it also brings me
to the last demo here, showing you
what this rag architecture looks like
and how to use it from within ai.
So regarding the, rag architecture,
the main idea we wanna do from
here, and again, I'm just using
the playground again, is importing
or linking it to our custom data.
So I'm, inside my project and I'm gonna.
Select here a new section where I
could define other system messages, but
that's not specifically to re anymore.
So we're shifting down to the next
section, and that's using your own data.
We can add new data sources and for
now, I'll make it a little bit bigger.
You can choose from any of these using
Azure AI search a service that's been
around in the platform for a couple of
years already and now nicely integrating.
With, the generative AI capabilities of
what an AI solution is, offering today
Azure blob storage, where obviously
the idea is to have your data sets
like, PDF documents, images, word
files, any other text files, json
alike scenarios in Azure blob storage.
Remember, you could link this to your
hub and project, making sure that not.
Everyone needs access to the blob storage.
I would also recommend using, role-based
access, preferably managed identities
to interact with those data endpoints.
Azure Cosmos database, our non-relational
database here, which could be a
perfect, data set or database endpoint
interacting with elastic search.
If you want, you could straight
point to your web address
connecting to, a knowledge base.
Website, intranet, maybe SharePoint
alike scenario, or, why not uploading
files and then still allowing
you to turn them into an index.
So quite some options.
So imagine we are gonna
go for blob storage.
You need to identify your
subscription, the storage container,
the BLO storage, obviously.
And then if you wanna use a specific Azure
search, you're gonna define the index.
And then from there.
How frequently is my information
changing, which influences my index?
So from here, pretty straightforward.
You point to the data endpoints
and that's pretty much it.
If I switch here to uploading files,
it's still gonna ask for storage.
So you still need to have that storage
background where now it's gonna enable
cross, origin to allow me to interact from
my AI service here, my playground into.
My, blob storage container, I would
still need to identify the index,
so this could be the live PDT index,
where now I can basically from here start
uploading my files like a Word document.
Where for some reason it didn't pick
up my REC that I specified like a
few minutes before the recording,
so I'm gonna save this for now.
But you probably get the idea, and again,
most probably you're not gonna do this
from here 'cause you're gonna ask your
data team, your data admins, your data
scientists, maybe to upload the data in
the Azure storage or in a Cosmos database.
But then the way to interact with it
from here would be basically the same.
That's, I would say mainly
what I wanted to show you.
Different capabilities, different
ways to interact your GPT alike
scenario, at least in this case,
your overall AI inspired scenarios.
Instead of just using the large
language model, how to interact with
your own custom data, where again,
you got a multitude of sources.
I am close to running out of time, so
I guess I'm gonna switch back to the
presentation for the last couple of words
before closing the session boundary.
Now, before we wrap it up here, I wanted
to highlight one other actually crucial
aspect in developing AI solutions.
And that's our Microsoft
responsible AI framework.
In short, we keep responsibility
high across all levels of our
AI development cycle and also
in our AI and copilot solutions.
Now, for example, we
don't train on your data.
We also do not use your prompts to
train the models, and eventually
your data remains your data.
Specifically within AI Foundry, you
can manage an integration with our
responsible framework out of Azure
AI content safety, which is, robust,
safe content moderation platform.
Leveraging AI to ensure that whatever
you are building keeps safety, in mind,
and also enhances user experiences.
It integrates with a lot
of powerful AI models.
Allowing you to detect, but also
eliminate inappropriate content.
For example, hateful, sexual, violent,
or self-harm inducing responses.
Using filters and safety thresholds,
organizations can tailor content safety
measures to, again, make sure that once
the application goes live, a lot of the
safety measures are already in place.
This brings me to the end of this session
where I would like to highlight several
of our top use cases for Azure AI Foundry,
starting from deploying your Azure AI
services and AI foundry hubs and projects.
Starting the development
project governance.
You would use AI Foundry to
deploy, test, validate your
large language models of choice.
From there, you're gonna primarily
use it, out of the playground that
I talked about and showed you.
To validate the models, configure system
messages, validate your prompt responses,
and then last fine tuning the model,
and then obviously integrating your
safety net, your responsible AI as well.
I hope with this session I managed to walk
you through a sneak peek of what Azure
AI services using AI Foundry can do for
your organizations, especially when you
are thinking about developing your own
custom co-pilots, as we like to call it.
I wanna thank you for having
joined me in this session.
I also would like to thank the com
42 team for having invited me as a
speaker to present at this conference.
I hope you enjoyed the rest of com
42 large language model conference
and hopefully we'll meet again
soon in any of the other com 42
conferences in the near future.
Take care for now.
Have a great day and don't
hesitate reaching out if you
should have any more questions.
Take care my friends.