Speaker 31: Hi, everyone.
My name is Liliya Mashova, and I'm
excited to share here with you today
the work that we have been doing here
at Paralin together with Michael Banf.
Our work is connected to validation
of the LLM-related tasks.
In this case, we consider summarization
in high-stakes environments.
But similar principles could easily be
applied to any other LLM-related task.
So let's start.
The challenge that we are facing
is to evaluate summary quality.
Our goal here is to detect whether
summary quality stays stable or quietly
degrades when we change any of the inputs.
If we upgrade the model, for example,
or if we want to apply our summarization
pipeline to a new dataset, or if
we simply want to scale it up.
Why it matters?
In a high-stakes environment, a single
flawed summary carries real consequences.
We simply need consistency
that we can actually measure.
And the qu- key questions that we
are asking here are is performance
improving with each change?
Are the summaries getting
closer to human-level quality?
How do we even measure the scores of
the automated validation and how we
compare it with the expert validation?
What we were presented with was the
data set that was evaluated by experts.
The data set already had the
summary created by the summarization
pipeline, and these summaries
were scored in five dimensions.
Dimensions are the following:
completeness, correctness, conciseness,
harmlessness, and readability.
All of these dimensions were were
defined in a lot of details and
experts followed these descriptions
to evaluate the summaries on a
Likert scale from one to five.
For each summary, we have
five scores from one to five.
These are the same scores that we are
later going to hand to the LLM as a judge.
Then we have two ways
to evaluate the summary.
We first tried traditional metrics
which are reference-based scoring.
We considered ROUGE, BLEU,
BERTScore, and cosine similarity.
Basically, in these cases, we compare
the summary to a reference text by
word overlap and semantic similarity.
And the second way is to use LLM as a
judge, which is criteria-based scoring.
An LLM reads the summary and scores
it on our five custom dimensions,
and then it also explains the
reasoning behind each score.
One of the key differences between
these two ways is that for traditional
metrics, we get one continuous score,
while for LLM as a judge, we get
five scores and for five dimensions.
So for each summary, we have five
dimensions, and for each of these
five dimensions, we get one score.
And we also get reasoning
for why the score was given.
We faced the following problems while
dealing with traditional metrics.
They simply performed poorly on our task.
But the most important challenge
was that these metric scores are
continuous, while the human ratings
that we have are categorical.
They are from one to five on a
Likert scale, so we cannot really
compare the two, as can be seen here.
So the continuous metric score is
just a number, and we don't have a
clear way how to assign it a category.
Therefore, their comparison is not really
meaningful, or more like it introduces
another uncertainty to our approach.
How do we map this, How do
we map this continuous metric
scale to the Likert scale?
That is just additional uncertainty.
And moreover, also traditional
metrics reward surface overlap
with a reference, which is not
really what we're looking for.
We want a summary to be mostly
evaluated as correct and safe
Therefore, we were presented with a
question, "How do we measure alignment
with the human feedback when we have
LLM as a judge scores?" If we have
exactly the same criteria for LLM as
a judge, we also have one to five.
But in this case, we also don't expect
the exact matching between the numbers.
Basically, what we want is to
separate good quality summaries
from bad quality summaries.
So we want to see the trend if the
good quality summaries percentage
is increasing or decreasing.
So for this we don't need exact matching.
Therefore we take our five-Likert scale
and we translate it to two categories.
So to a binary scale one to three.
The scores one to three are considered
to be bad quality, while four to five
are considered to be good quality.
And then we measure the agreement
with the expert validation scores.
So how often the pipeline's
verdict matches the experts.
Here is the example.
So we have one summary.
Let's say expert's evaluation,
expert score was five, while the
LLM as a judge pipeline was four.
But both of them are good this
is considered to be a match.
The same is for the B summary,
where we have bad quality.
But again, the scores are different,
but the general consideration that it
is a bad quality summary is correct.
So it is considered to be a match.
The difference arises here, where we
have a good quality summary evaluated
by experts and a poor quality
summary evaluated by the pipeline.
Then we have a mismatch.
So for this data set with these
five summaries the agreement
between the expert validation and
the LLM-as-a-judge validation will
be calculated as eighty percent.
That's how we measure it What
goes into LLM as a judge?
What goes into the pipeline?
What kind of degrees
of freedom do we have?
First of all, of course,
we have LLM model.
We can replace it.
We can make it depending on our task.
If we want a very quick evaluation, then
we also need to take that into account
choosing a model that we are considering.
Then we also have hyperparameters, of
course such as temperature, top P, top
K. All of these can also be adjusted,
can be changed trying to find a better
way trying to find a better agreement
with the expert validated scores.
Then we also have prompt and
what goes into prompt are-
is the dimension definition.
So basically, when we have the criteria
let's say, correctness, we have a very
detailed description of what it means,
of what we expect, and then all of this
description goes also into a prompt,
where in the prompt we have a placeholder
for all of the of these descriptions.
And that changes from, so the prompt
stays the same while the placeholders
are changing f- depe-depending on
which criteria we are considering.
The next thing that we have
here is few-shot examples.
So we are giving to the model
to our pipeline, we're giving
the examples of what we expect.
We give both positive
and negative examples.
Moreover, we also have negative
control examples that I will
be talking more about later.
And simply to validate all
of it, we need the dataset.
We need to know what we expect.
We need to have dataset, like a
baseline da-dataset that we will
be like checking our results on.
Basically, for us, it's the dataset that
has the expert validation results in it.
Okay.
And then all of it goes to LLM as a judge
that scores each summary with reasoning.
As an output, we get the quality verdict.
So we have five scores from
one to five per summary.
And this we compare
with the human feedback.
As a final number, we calculate the
agreement score of the agreement between
LLM as a judge and human feedback.
In our work, we tried many things to
improve the validation pipeline, to
improve agreement with the human feedback.
So we tried prompt engineering
that was also where we also
used the help of the experts.
And we also tried the
hyperparameter tuning.
We tried the model changes, model
upgrades, and all of these led
to marginal gains in the quality.
And here I want to mention three
main things that did most of the
work for improving the results
of our validation pipeline.
First of all, we included
the few-shot examples.
What we did, we need to include both a
positive example and negative example.
So at least two examples
have to be included.
We need to set the limits
for the model what we expect.
So what we saw is that we can include two,
three examples, maybe four, but more than
four is already only confusing the model.
So just picking two or three good
examples that really represent good
quality and bad quality is really…
It has shown to improve
the results significantly.
Moreover, we also added negative controls.
So we constructed them in a different
way that I will also show a bit later.
And we also asked the model to
provide the reasoning, why does
it give a score that it gives.
Therefore, the model kind of is forced
to think more about it and also to
justify the scores that it gives.
So all of these three things led to
a strong expert agreement The data
set that we have is w-was the, was
constructed with the synthesized
summaries that were evaluated by experts.
This is our ground truth for
what good and bad actually means.
This data set was augmented
by negative control examples.
We created it with basically
a third of the test set.
So we took the summaries that were
already evaluated by experts, and
then we deliberately broke them.
And we want a good judge or our
LLM-as-a-Judge pipeline, we want it
to catch the bad quality summaries.
For negative controls,
we have three kinds.
We have most of all we
have negated summaries.
This is the most tricky ones,
therefore we have more of them.
That's when we have a summary, and
then we just pick a few facts from
this summary, and we negate it.
So if it says something happened
on that day, we simply add
something not happened on that day.
So therefore, summaries like this
would potentially be harmful,
and they would not be correct.
But this is also difficult for
LLM-as-a-Judge to catch because it
matches original summary quite closely.
Then we also tried to pick the numbers all
the numbers that we have in the summary
and just replace it with random numbers.
And we also tried scrambled summaries,
just simply scrambled texts.
This is the easiest for the
LLM-as-a-Judge to catch.
Therefore, we have these different levels
of our the quality of our LLM-as-a-Judge
this is the example of the results.
Here we compare the validation
pipeline results of the before
the last step, so ask for the
reasoning before this and after this.
And on the y-axis, so the bar
represents the percentage of the
agreement with human feedback scores.
The gray ones is before the
improvement, and the orange
one is after the improvement.
In high-stakes environment, our highest
priority is correctness and harmlessness.
So we mostly look at them, and
we see that the quality improved.
Especially for correctness, it
was actually greatly improved
for more than ten percent.
While completeness was decreased
slightly by three percent, but
still stays above 90 percent.
Readability and conciseness in our
high-stake environment is something
that is nice to look at, but it's
not the most important for us.
Okay.
And here I want to also mention why
expert comparison matters that much.
So the pipeline is only
trustworthy because it is
validated against human judgment.
The expert involvement can shrink
over time, but it could never be
zero, so we still need a clear kind
of definition of what good actually
means, and we need basic sanity checks.
So reliable baseline this
lets you improve the real task
summer… So the summarization.
So when we want to improve the real task
in an automated, repeatable way, we want
to use, This, we want to use the baseline.
Yes.
And what's s- one of the
strength of our approach is we
use exactly the same methods.
We use exactly the same metrics for human
evaluated scores and LLM as a judge.
So therefore, the comparison
between them could be meaningful.
And I'm already here at my end.
So the key takeaways that I want you
to pay attention to is that LLM as a
judge can be a very useful evaluation
tool if you set it up properly
and understand its limitations.
Good practice is to customize
your metrics to the task.
So depending on what task you have at
hand, you can customize the metrics.
Then you also want the score humans and
the judge on exactly the same dimensions,
then the agreement is meaningful.
And the last point here is that
we need experts in the loop.
We need a human in the loop.
Their involvement could be decreased,
could be shrinked, but we still need them.
We are not yet at the point where
we can eliminate them altogether.
So that would be all from my side.
Thank you very much for your
attention, and I'm open for questions.
Thank you.