Hello, my name is Robin, and
today we'll look at the topic
of how to test AI using ai.
First, a little bit of introduction.
I'm Robin Gupta, co-founder
and CEO at Te Zeus.
I have three plus years of
leading product engineering pride,
AI teams of up to 45 members.
I'm a published author on the topic of
software testing and automation, and
I'm also an open source contributor.
Here are a few logo where have in.
And on the large QR code, you
can find more details about us.
First and foremost, let's look at the rise
of the IA or intelligent applications.
So for example, large
damage models themselves.
Examples like open ai, GP 4.5,
deep C carbon, and other Ls tend
to in an intelligent fashion.
The second bucket is.
Rag applications, retrieval, augmented
generation, or even chat bots, which
are wrappers on top of these models.
And the third is agents.
Agents like TE New or hardware ai,
which have agency inside them or
which can perform tasks autonomously
using planning, memory and tools.
So these are just a few example
of intelligent applications which
need to be tested in novel ways.
That being said, let's look at these
changing needs for software testing.
As you can see on the table over here,
I divided this into three columns.
The first six.
Second is the comparison between
traditional software and the
third one, element based apps.
The first example is behavior.
For example, the traditional software
behaves in a very predefined way
based on the rules that it has.
Think of it as a program
having if else, if.
However, on the other hand, airline
based apps give the behavior
of probability and prediction.
The second criterion is output.
For example, if you log into an
application like Salesforce, it'll
determine stickly log you in,
and they will always be that one
output for that funding input.
But in the case of real based apps, these
could provide non-deterministic outputs.
You can get different outcomes
for the same question.
Last, but not the least.
The testing strategy for traditional
software was only about the
evaluations of it being right or wrong.
On the other hand, for airline based
apps, they need to be evaluated on
accuracy, quality, bias, consistency,
and last, but not the least, toxicity.
That brings us to the automated evals.
Now that we know what our
evals, let's understand the what
and when of automated evals.
So what should you.
You must focus on context adherence,
context relevance, correctness bias and
toxicity in all intelligent applications,
and when should you evaluate it?
Now that can be taken as cues
from traditional software.
For example, you can check
after every change, bug fix,
feature update, or data changes.
You can have the pipeline steps and
evaluations as part of predeployment in
your SIT or UT environment wherein you
check after mergers to broad branch, end
of sprint or prior to shipping hot fixes.
And last but not the least, it
wouldn't hurt if we do a little bit
of smoke testing post deployment,
for example, based on the demand
from business or internal team needs.
That brings us to today's.
Demo application Under test, what
we'll do is we'll build a small
rack based application, which
will act as a quiz generator.
We'll provide it with a sample data
set around topics like physics and
science, and then we'll ask the LLM
to generate quiz questions for it,
which can be provided to the user.
So here is an example.
Let's say we ask it to
write a quiz about science.
It'll respond back with some
science questions for us
with right and wrong answers.
And for this application we'll use
AI to perform the automated evals.
So let's look at the pipeline.
So from the starting point,
we have the Quizit app.
We'll supplement it with the small
quiz bank, and we'll also give it the
user input and the prompt template.
The prompt template defines
what kind of outputs it should.
The output of a skills generator
will go through the first ring of
fire for rule-based evals wherein
we'll check if it generates answers,
which contains specific words or not.
If yes, good, if no fail the test case.
The second gate is around formatting.
Does it generate the quiz in the
right format as specified or not?
And then last but not the least, we'll
look for things like hallucination.
Wherein we'll check it against
negative prompts and see the
kind of output that it generates.
We'll also ask an AI based automated
eval system to reason about the
answer and tell us whether the quiz
generator app is working fine or not.
That being said, it's time to roll
up your sleeves and let's go onto
some hands-on coding examples.
So first and foremost, as you can see on
my screen, we are using Google collab.
So these notebooks are I Python
notebooks wherein you can write snippets
of Python code and run them online.
This is free and even you can use
it for these experimental purposes.
First and foremost, as we can see, we
can run each of these cells individually.
And in the second cell, we
are highlighting my OpenAI,
API key being imported.
Over here you can use OpenAI or any
other lys that you're comfortable with.
For the same I Python Notebooks.
These resources will provided
right after the session for your
reference, so don't worry about that.
First and foremost, we are
highlighting the human template as
the question, and as mentioned, the
app that we're testing today is a.
Which uses the quiz bank or the data set
and large language models to generate
quiz questions for Lexi students.
So here the quiz bank is being run and
it has, subjects around DaVinci, Paris
telescopes, study nights, and physics.
Each of them have a
category and a few facts.
So I, when we ask this
Ative app, it should use an.
Two, look at the data set of this
question bank and generate a quiz
for us, and that is how it performs.
Retrieval augmented generation based
on the data that we have provided it.
Now what we'll do is we'll
build a small prompt template
as part of this demonstration.
Today we'll be using Lang Chain as the
core framework, and in the construc chain
we have to highlight the prompt template.
So the prompt template that we're
following for the quiz generator
app is very simple learning To
complicate it, we are asking the LLM
to follow the below steps and generate
a customized quiz for the user.
It must identify the category which
the user is asking, determine the
subject, and then generate a quiz
for the user based on the format.
With a few question, what
we'll chain is an open source.
Which acts as a wrapper on
top of large language bottles.
So we have provided the input as
a human and the prompt template,
and from there we'll move forward.
So for example, if we just
print the chat prompt, this is
what goes through blank chain.
So as we can see, this is the same
quiz bank and the prompt template
that we had highlighted earlier.
Now we'll use GPD four oh
with the temperature as zero.
And choose that as the large
language model for us today.
As highlighted, you can use
other large language models
as well for the demonstration.
Now, from LAN chain, we use the
schema par so that we get appropriate
parts outputs from the open language.
Now we'll take all these components and.
We'll make them reusable as one piece.
Okay, so nothing too complicated.
Over here we're creating an assistant
chain, the system message, the
human template, and the LLM with
the prompt template that we have
provided and the name of the model.
So let's experiment with that
quiz generator application.
So we are asking it to a quiz about
science, and then we'll print the answer
what we are getting back from this.
So what it has done is.
It has understood that the user is asking
about the category signs, and then based
on the tags and labels that we have
provided in the data set, it has generated
quiz about telescopes and physics.
All good so far?
So now we create an eval for
expected words as a first example.
So what we are doing over here is we
are creating a small quiz from the quiz
digital application that we have created.
And the output must be evaluated
to contain certain expected words.
So it is a very rule-based eval system.
There is nothing magical,
there is nothing AI inside it.
We'll come to the AI once in the
second example, so just keep up.
Now what we are doing over here is
that in the expected words, we have
asked it to have a few expected words.
And it's as simple as generating
a quiz and then checking that the
output should have the expected words.
Okay, so when we run this with the
eval, and then as expected, we should
see that it creates a quiz about
science, which picked up the scope
and physics generated quiz, and then
it had the right words inside it.
However.
Let's create an accurate test
case or evals for refusal.
So in that, what we are doing is
that we are just asking our system to
create a quiz and then invoking it on
the question that we have asked for.
And if we ask it to generate
a quiz about bread making the
decline responses, I'm sorry.
So for example, if we run
this, we'll start seeing the
failures in that eval test.
So we expected the assistant questions
to include this, but it did not.
Is the idea very simple?
You ask the quiz app to generic
a quiz based on a topic.
Look for specific words inside the answer.
Nothing fancy, all simple python overhead.
But a key problem with limb
based applications as we saw
earlier, is hallucinations.
So now what we are doing is we
are asking the quiz janitor app
to write a poem about conferences.
Let's see what it does.
So when we invoke the assistant
application, it actually
wrote a poem about conference.
Now, a key failure point for this
is that we had created a app, not
a. But when we asked it to create a
poem about conferences, it broke all
the rules about format and its system
prompt and went ahead and wrote a
small poem about conferences not cool.
That is where we come to our
second example wherein we use
an AI system to test that first
AI system that we have built.
So the first AI system which we
had built was this question app,
and we'll use another AI system
with a system prompt to check out
the responses from the first one.
Very simple.
So let's start running the
same example from the top.
As I earlier, we are
setting up the open IPI key.
In the second block.
We are also setting up the quiz
bank, so nothing changed over here.
It's the same quiz bank
as from the previous ones.
Which has topics covered about
telescopes, starry nights,
physics, science, so on, so forth.
Now what we are doing is that we
are creating the assistant chain as
our sample application data test.
Basically, we are building the
quiz generator app overhead.
So we are asking you to follow the
steps, need a customized quiz for
the user, just as we saw earlier,
it should follow a certain format.
Now what we've also done is we've tried
to harden the system prompt a little bit.
We are asking it to own, include questions
from information in the quiz bank.
Only use explicit string
matches for the category name.
And if the user asks a question
about the subject, you do not have
information about the quiz bank, just
say that you do not own the answer.
So we can also sort see
that on the right side.
And it says it should say, I'm
sorry, I do not have information.
Ask you to write a poem.
It should not do that, is the idea.
So we've run that small cell, it has
done the setup for us, and then we'll
build a prompt that has the LM to
evaluate the output of the quizzes.
Now, this is the second
evaluator AI system.
So it has this very simple system
prompt, which says you are an
assistant that evaluates whether
or not an assistant is producing.
And then it should give the answer.
So the idea as highlighted earlier,
was that you have the quiz app,
which is an LLM or an AI based app,
acts as a rag application retrieval.
Augmented donation takes the
quiz bank based on the system
prompt provided it should.
Id create the quizzes as the
output, the second evaluator, ai.
Is, as we can see over here,
has a system prompt acting as
an assistant that evaluates the
responses from the first one.
So that is how we are using
AI to test another AI system.
Very simple.
So moving forward, we similarly
little response to make a first
small test and we set the prompt for
testing agent as you are evaluating
a based on the context assistant.
And an interim response.
Read the response carefully determine
if it looks like a quiz or not.
Output y if the response to a
quiz output, n if the response
does not look like a quiz.
So that is where we are
doing that assertion of the
response from the first ai.
Using the second AI.
As an evaluator, we use blank chain to
build the prompt template for evaluation.
We'll choose.
And we'll import the parser
to have readable response.
We connect all these pieces
together in the variable chain, and
we'll test the positive response
by invoking the email chain.
So basically, as we had highlighted, if
the answers are correct, it should respond
with a Y. If we don't get the proper quiz
back it, it'll respond back with a no.
So combining all these pieces
create an chain, using chain,
and then what we also do is.
We'll check for a negative response.
Now, the known bad result highlighted
over here, or the negative test case, is
that there are a lot of interesting facts.
Tell me more about what
you'd like to know.
Now, this will not donate a quiz,
and that is what the second AI
should catch and fill the test case.
So let's run that and
see what's happening.
So it also generated a small end.
What we'll do is we'll compress the
pieces of these systems into a test.
So that we can run by test
or test fixtures around it.
So we are running the code for
the test assistant, setting
up for all these scenarios.
And then there is a specific
method which will look for sub
stringing of the message, and
it'll also decline the response
if it is not the correct response.
So when we run that, we'll ask it
around some facts which we had provided.
And then if it is outside
the knowledge base, as we can
see, the is also responding.
I'm sorry, I do not have
the information about that.
We'll create the test release valves and
when we run that, as we can see for the
assertion, we've got an N where it should
have got a why, because we have input
the known bad result as we saw earlier.
So that is how you can use the second
AI system to check the first AI system.
It is as simple as the secondary
system has prompt, which checks
that the quiz generator is
generating the right outputs or not.
Now, the same could be applicable
for your customer support scenarios
or outbound sales scenarios.
For example, in the case of a customer
support scenario, let's, your AI system is
supposed to act as a customer service bot.
It should ideally not reveal
any secret information or should
not go into hallucinations.
So when you're building that bot or that
AI application, you can have another
AI evaluator with known bad results
and then check for the behavior of
that first customer support AI part.
That is how you can test AI
systems using secondary AI systems.
But let's not stop there.
Let's make it more fun.
What if not only could we find
the deviations on the format, we
could also find the deviations
from the context adherence.
And what if we could reason
about the bad responses?
So last but not the least,
let's perform some automated
evals with advanced examples.
First and foremost, we
have the OpenAI key set up.
The quiz bank is the same as earlier,
and we'll create the assistant
chain wherein it can act as a quiz
generator for us using GPT-4 oh.
What we'll do is we'll create the
second AI system with a system prompt
and give it a very specific direction.
Asking it to act as an assistant
that evaluates how well the quiz
assistant creates quizzes for
a user by looking at the set of
facts available to the assistant.
So we are asking the second AI system
to look at the same question bank
given to the first one and see that
the quiz generated by the first
one adhere to that context or not.
So we are asking it that your primary
concern is making sure that only facts
available are used if you focus here.
Only is accurate in bold.
So what we found is that text written
in bold, in system prompt is acted
upon strictly by large language models.
So we'll highlight that we learn that
small cell, and we'll also ask it to
compare the content with the question.
And if a fact is in the quiz, but not in
the question bank, then the quiz is bad.
So we are specifically asking it
to check for context relevance
as part of the system problem.
So we are asking you to output why if
the quiz contains facts on the question
bank and output N if it contains
facts that are not in the question.
So we'll create a function
which will check for the
evaluation and hallucinations.
So in this case, when we run it.
We will find that while the glass
chat opener is deprecated, when we
ask it for a bad one, it says, I'm
sorry, but books is not a part of the
categories I can generate a quiz for.
So as you can see in the question bank, we
actually don't have anything around books.
It has topics about telescope science,
study night physics, and DaVinci.
So that is how, in very simple words,
it can check the context relevance.
But let's improve the
system prompt a little bit.
So we are asking it to act an
assistant that evaluates how well
the quiz assistant creates quizzes.
Your primary concern is making sure that
only facts available are used and helpful.
Quizzes only contain
facts in the test set.
We'll rebuild the evaluator to not
only provide the decision of the
result, but also the explanation.
So that is the fun part over here.
So for example.
We are not only asking it to
compare the information in the
quiz, the question bank, we are also
giving it a few additional rules.
Over here in line numbers 28 to 32,
we're asking it to output an explanation
of whether the quiz only references
information in the context, make
explanation brief and only include the
summary of a reasoning for the decision.
Include a clear yes or no, and
then reference facts bank if the
answer is yes and explanation.
For example, if there will
be decision, and then there
could be a small explanation.
So we'll rebuild that whole
check prompt with the new prompt.
And what we'll do is we'll also run
it with a few small test data set.
So for example, there are topics
about science, about geography
and bread making or cooking.
So ideally it should pass.
The topics that we have in the quiz
bank, and it should fail the ones around
bread making because we did not cover it.
So what we'll do is we'll
create this function data set
and invoke the quiz generation.
We'll use a library from Python called as
Pandas to help us display the results in
a more format once we run this end piece.
The data set and the evaluator ai, what
we'll see is for the positive test cases,
not only will it pass the test case or
evaluation for the negative funds, it'll
not just fail them as highlighted in the
system prong for the evaluator ai, it'll
also try to look at the data set and
then reason or explain its results to us.
So for example, in the
first row, we are asking it.
To generate a quiz about science and can
you gimme a quiz to test my knowledge?
So I generated that.
So the quiz generator app created a small
quiz for the user, but then the evaluator
AI checked the quiz based on the data set
and highlighted that yes, the decision
is right, the quiz is good, and give an
explanation of why it believes that the
quiz was generated is accurate or not.
Similarly, we ask it about geography.
And last but not the least, when we ask
it about bread making, not only did the
quiz generator app replied, I'm sorry, I
cannot give you a quiz of bread making the
evaluator, AI also had a decision as No.
And then explain that the quiz does
not reference any facts from the
question bank, and it has nothing to do
with DaVinci Paris telescopes, so on.
so in very simple ways.
What we have done is.
We created a small quiz generator
app, which takes a question back,
talks to the LLM generates quizzes.
What we then did was part one, look
for certain rule-based evals that the
generated quiz from this first AI based
application contains a few words or not.
Second, we checked for the format, and
last, but not we created this evaluator.
Which not only checked for the context
adherence and relevance based on the same
data set provided to us for the quiz,
it also gave us the app explanation of
why it passed or failed the test case.
So that is how you can build AI
systems to check other AI systems.
Let's get back to our presentation.
I'll put this in slide mode and time to.
Okay.
Jokes aside, moving forward, let's
zoom out a little bit and compress
these concepts into a CI CT pipeline.
Continuous integration, continuous
testing pipeline for AI applications.
Let's say you are doing some changes
you must do per commit evals on the dev
feature branch from there merged to me.
After that, you can do pre-release evals,
like the second test around formatting.
That we did move it to deploy, and
then last but not the least after that.
You can also check it for a few smoke
scenarios with the evaluator AI that we
had created and look at not just the pass
fail responses, but also the explanations.
It is very important to highlight
that, not just the pre-release
eval, but the post release eval.
Must go through conferences.
When I highlighted that you can use AI
systems to check the other AI systems,
someone very smart in the audience
asked me then, who checks both of these
AI systems are working fine or not.
The answer, as you can imagine,
is today and forever Humans.
That being said, let's
look at a few differences.
Infosys recently released a
responsible AI toolkit, so I.
This can help you do red
teaming for AI applications.
GitHub publishes their opens and then last
but not least, is very nice research paper
on evaluation of large language models.
That brings us to the
closure of our session today.
Feel free to show us questions, and
you can also check out the world's
first open source testing agent at
the GitHub report highlighted below.
Thank you so much.
Have a nice day.
Or a nice evening.
Stay curious.
Stay smart.
Take care, and byebye.