Speaker 14: Hello, everyone,
and thank you for listening.
Today, I want to talk about a topic that
many organizations are actively exploring.
How do we move beyond AI experimentation
and successfully deploy LLM-powered
agents in production environment?
The title of the session is LLM Agents
as Copilots for Scalable Decision
Systems in Production Environments.
Over the past few years, we have seen
organizations adopt LLMs through chatbots,
assistants, and content generation tools.
But moving from a demo to a
production-grade system introduces
a very different set of challenges.
The focus of today's talk is not
just what LLMs can do, it's how we
can architect that allow them to
operate reliably, safely, and at scale
A little bit about me.
My name is Mastul Hassan Choudhury.
I'm a staff product manager at Walmart.
I've spent several years building
enterprise products across retail
operations, supply chain fulfillment,
and also AI-enabled systems.
Over the course of my career, I have
worked on large-scale operational
platforms, user onboarding systems,
mobile commerce solutions, and most
recently, GenAI-powered products.
What I've learned is that technology
succeeds when it fits naturally
into the operational workflows.
The perspective heavily influences the
architecture that I will share today
Now, many organizations have adopted
LLMs, but most deployments stop short
of delivering operational values.
Why?
Because production environments
demand far more intelligent responses.
They require reliability, they
require consistency, and they require
integration into real business processes.
The challenge is no longer whether
LLMs can answer a question.
The challenge is whether it can support
thousands of business decisions every
day while meeting cost, latency,
governance, and stability requirements.
That's the gap we are trying to solve
Now, I believe the most effective
way to think about LLM agents is as
co-pilots, not as replacements for
people, not autonomous decision-makers,
but systems that augment human expertise.
A co-pilot gathers information,
evaluate options, highlight tasks,
and surfaces recommendation.
Humans still own the judgment.
Humans still own accountability.
The agent simply helps them
process complexity faster and more
consistently To make this concept
concrete, let's use forecasting and
operational planning as an example.
Now, forecasting is a great test
bed because it combines structured
and unstructured information.
So we have demand signals, we
have operational matrices, we
have external events, market
conditions, human expertise.
This is exactly the type of
environment where agents provide value.
And while we're using forecasting
as an example, the same architecture
applies across supply chain,
capacity planning, risk management,
operations, and many other domains
Now, when organizations start
AI initiatives, they often
focus on the model itself.
I believe the architecture
is far more important.
This framework that I'm presenting
over here consists of three layers.
We have a signal ag-aggregation layer,
we have a LLM agent reasoning layer,
and we have a human interaction layer.
Each layer has a distinct responsibility,
and each can evolve independently.
The separation creates resilience
and makes production deployment
significantly ea-easier Now let's talk
about these three layers separately.
The first is the signal aggregation layer.
Everything begins with context.
Now, the signal aggregation layer
continuously collects information
from multiple sources: structured
data such as transactions, forecasts,
operational metrics, and also
unstructured information such as
documents, reports, logs, communications.
The goal is to create a unified,
queryable context layer.
Without high-quality context, no
amount of model sophistication will
be able to produce reliable decisions.
The second layer is the
LLM agent reasoning layer.
Once the context is assembled in the
first layer, the reasoning begins.
This is where the LLM evaluates
information, generates forecasts, detects
anom-anomalies, and recommends action.
Importantly, the output
is not just an answer.
It includes rationale.
It explains why a recommendation was made.
This explainability is critical for trust
and governance and also for adoption.
If users cannot understand the
recommendation, they won't act
on it And the last layer is
the human interaction layer.
This is where the humans
interact with the system.
Users ask questions, explore
various scenarios, validate
assumptions, and provide feedback.
The interaction layer transforms
the system from a black box into
a collaborative decision partner.
This is where trust is built, and trust
is often the deciding factor between
AI adoption and AI rejection Now let's
talk about some of the production
realities, some of the hard problems.
For example, b-building an architecture is
one thing, but operating it in production
is a completely different ball game.
Four challenges consistently appear.
First, we have hal-hallucinations.
Second, decision consistency.
We have latency issues,
and then we have cost.
These issues won't disappear
simply because the model
performs well in testing.
Production success requires
deliberate engineering choices
to manage all four simultaneously
Now how to solve these problems?
The s-single most important technique
for reducing hallucination is grounding.
Agents should not rely
solely on model knowledge.
They should operate using enterprise data.
Retrieval augmentation-- augmented
generation, structured queries,
and authoritative internal sources
dramatically improve reliability.
Grounding is not a
one-time implementation.
It becomes an ongoing operational
discipline focused on freshness, quality,
and monitoring Now many business decisions
cannot be solved with a single prompt.
Instead, they require
multi-step reasoning steps.
First, retrieve context, then create
a plan, then execute tools, and
finally synthesize the results.
This orchestration process
resembles how human analysts work.
The difference is that agents can execute
these steps continuously and at scale
One of the biggest mistakes
organizations make is trying
to replace existing systems.
A better strategy is additive integration.
Use adaptive layers around
existing systems, deploy in shadow
mode, and maintain deterministic
fall, fallback mechanism.
This allows organization to innovate while
also preserving operational stability.
The goal is not evo-evo-evolution.
The goal is evolution and not disruption
This slide captures the core
philosophy of the presentation.
Agents handle monitoring, synthesis,
pattern detection, scenario
generation, and summarization.
Humans still retain judgment.
Humans still retain context.
Humans retain accountability.
The future is not human versus AI.
The future is human plus AI
Now, most AI initiatives fail because they
jump quickly from prototype to production.
A better path is progressive maturity.
Start with focused prototype, move
to shadow deployment, introduce
human-in-the-loop validation, then
scale with monitoring, governance,
and continuous evaluation.
This approach reduces risk
while also increase, increasing
organizational confi-confidence.
Now, key takeaways for practitioners.
If you remember only four things
from today, remember these.
First, architecture comes before models.
Second, ground everything
in enterprise data.
Third, integrate additively rather
than replacing existing systems.
And fourth, continuously measure
performance across accuracy,
latency, cost, and human trust.
These principles are what separate
successful production deployment
from impressive demonstrations.
So thank you for your time.
I hope this framework provides
a practical perspective on how
your organization can move beyond
experimentation and build scalable AI
systems that create real business value.
I would be happy to take
questions or answer any queries.
My email address is mazdul,
M-A-Z-D-U-L, @gmail.com.
I'd be happy to connect offline
and talk further on this.
Thank you for your time, and I en-
I really enjoyed talking about LLM.
Thank you.