Hello everyone.
So my name is Kumar Mala.
Thanks for joining my sessions
on optimizing data pipelines
with Azure Data Factory.
In these sessions, I will walk you
through how to improve your data
flows for faster processing and
loss cost, and less manual work.
Let's get into the session.
So today's data challenges, as you
all know, that today data is huge.
So we are getting the data from multiple
systems like I streaming systems.
And different files and file
systems and different sources.
So to handling this much huge data is
nightmare and complex and challenges
and integrating all of these systems
is definitely complex because there
is no relations between these systems
and they don't talk each other.
So to integrating these many systems
with volume of this much volume
of data is complex and challenges.
And because of that,
our process gets delays.
And getting the right insights and
decision making gets poor and it's
it's like main maintenance cost
is more effective, so more cost so
to to overcome these challenges.
I'm trying to introduce, I
will introduce new technology.
So that is Azure Data Factory.
The Azure Data Factory is
one of the Azure services.
It's a cloud data integration tool.
So there is a lot of advantages
of the Azure Data Factory.
I usually call it as a DF, so a DF
because it's, it's supposed to integrate
as many as data sources, like it's
supposed to add RBMS and NoSQL databases
and file systems and realtime systems.
And API systems it'll integrate,
it'll integrate all of the systems and
it'll load into your desired system.
So let's get more insights about the.
So basically Azure data factory
architecture depends on four more
components four or more components,
but the main components are the four.
One is the linkage services.
The linkage services is like
connections between your data
sources and your target systems.
For example, if you are, if you like
to connect your Azure data factory
to Salesforce systems and you want to
extract and transform and load into your
data lake, so you need to create the
linker services to connect your source
system so that you know it'll like a
bridge connection bridge between your
source systems and Azure Data Factory.
And then another component is data sets.
Data sets is the real data structures.
It's like your tables or files,
data structure, what table, what
columns you need to for your
target systems and activities.
The activities is the main configurable
data transformations where you use.
Actually your transformations and
business tools and then pipeline.
Pipeline needs nothing but like
end-to-end solution from where your
link services, data sets and activities
altogether, orchestration, sequence of
end-to-end solution is called pipeline.
Let's get into another slide.
So it's not only provides these
many benefits and it's also reusable
templates, pipeline templates.
Suppose once you create one, one pipeline,
you can use that for another requirements.
Suppose if you have a Salesforce
data, sales data and HR data,
you can use the same pipeline for
that, but with little tweaks, but
you can reusable that pipeline.
So because of that, you can
reduce your manual work and cost.
And another advantage is
dynamic orchestrations.
If, suppose as I said, an example,
suppose if there is a new data comes
into your source system or there is
a data is edited, updated in your
source system, the Azure data factory
pipeline will automatically figure
it out and it'll runs the pipeline
and load into your target system.
So there is no manually you need to
log into the system and you no need to
rerun the pipeline or run the pipeline.
So it'll automatically detect and
it'll load into your target systems.
So we call it that event triggered.
Execution because of that.
So there is no manual intervention
and it'll reduce your cast.
And another thing is error handling.
So when a system, when a pipeline
handles huge data with the different data
sources, definitely there is an address
handling mechanism should be there.
So the data factories also
handles the errors very smartly.
There is a retrain mechanism in case if
your pipeline fails in between, so it'll
retrace where it failed and from the
checkpoint, and it'll process it further,
even in case if it is fails, and it'll
send to alerts through your emails or your
messages or your teams channels so far for
your prompt response to fix the issues.
And because of these advantages, the, when
you use the A DF and it'll improve your
business and faster processing, 78% faster
processing and cost reduction goes to 63%.
And resource efficiency can use be 42%
and you can make 90% of automation.
So there is a case study,
like a financial services.
There is an ETL pipeline with
the legacy tools and that
was running for eight hours.
And when we introduced the A DF pipeline
and with the same transformations
and business logics, it got down
to 45 minutes because of that.
And the processing time dramatically
registered eight from eight hours
to 45 minutes, like 91% improvement.
So because of that, the maintenance
cost register at 70% and
delivering significance within
quarters and within timelines.
Implement these pipelines.
So the best, we should follow the best
practices organize your pipelines.
I just said if you, if your organization
has the sales data and HR data or
other CRM data, so you organize your
pipelines accordingly and always often.
Check in your code into the gate and
leverage runtime integrations and
also enable your Azure Monitor Azure
monitoring system so that so for a
prompt response in case of any failures.
What I would suggest to the
organizations is so looking at your
current pipelines and analyze what
it slows and why it's cost, and then
introduce Azure Data Factory for
better, faster performance, for the
lower cost, and more efficient way.
Thank you so much for
watching and joining my show.
Azure Data Factory has helped me a lot
and as well as my team as well to better
to build a better and faster pipelines.
I hope it helps you too, so feel free to
connect me if you would like to chat more.
Thank you so much.
Have a nice day.