Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining.
My name is Ari Koli and I'm excited
to talk take you on a journey through
the next evolution of data management.
In today's talk, AI-driven data
platforms, the transition from manual
management to self-optimizing systems
will explore how artificial intelligence
is transforming data platforms
from manual reactive setups into
autonomous self-optimizing ecosystems.
In other words, we are looking at how
to build a self-driving data platform.
We will discuss why this change is
necessary, walk through the four key
pillars that make the, make it possible,
see some real world use cases and metrics
for each, and then envision the future
where data systems manage themselves.
My goal is to keep this clear,
conversational and practical.
By the end, you should see how these
AI driven approaches can free us from
a lot of data grunt work, and let
us focus on getting value from data.
Let's dive in
the data explosion challenge.
First, let's talk about why we need AI
driven automation in the first place.
We are living in an era
of explosive data growth.
Consider these numbers by 2025,
the world's data is projected
to reach 1 75 zetabytes up
from only 33 terabytes in 2018.
That's an annual growth rate of
about 61%, which is astounding.
It's hard to even imagine 1 75 terabytes.
Some put it in perspective by saying if
you stored art on Blu-ray disks, the stack
would reach the moon multiple times over.
What's more, a huge portion of this data
will need to be handled in real time.
By 2025, 30% of all data generated
will require immediate processing.
Think of sensors and iot streams where
you can't wait hours or days to react.
In fact, IOT devices alone are
expected to generate about 90
terabytes of data annually by 2025.
So not only is data bigger, it's.
Also faster and more complex.
The takeaway is that traditional
manual data management can't keep
up with this volume and velocity.
We simply can't hire enough
people or write enough static
strips to manage 1 75 terabytes.
Much of it's streaming in real time.
Automation is no longer a luxury.
It's a necessity.
We need smarter AI driven
systems to handle data growth,
or we risk in data we can't use.
This sets the stage for why we're
explore exploring AI driven data
platforms to tackle the scale
and speed in a sustainable way.
Now let's talk about the four
pillars of AI driven data platforms.
So how do we actually transform our data
first?
The first pillar is metadata intelligence.
This is about making data
about our data work for us.
The platform uses AI to understand
and organize metadata, essentially
knowing what data we have, what
it means, and how it's connected.
Think of it like a brain and
nervous system that senses where
everything is and helps the whole
platform respond intelligently.
Second one is self-healing data pipelines.
These are your data workflows
that can fix themselves.
If something breaks or an anomaly
occurs, the system detects it
and resolves it automatically.
It's like an immune system for your
data operations, handling problems
without waiting for human intervention.
The third is predictive optimization.
Here, the platform for casts,
what resources like compute,
storage, et cetera, will be
needed and adjusts in advance.
Instead of reacting after a slowdown or
outage, it proactively tunes performance.
This is akin to a smart autopilot
that adjusts scores before turbulence
hits, keeps things running smoothly.
And the final one is
the embedded governance.
The platforms.
The platform has governance, security,
and compliance driven in from the start.
AI helps enforce policies like privacy
rules or data quality standards
continuously and transparently.
Think of this as having a diligent
guardian or compass inside the
system, ensuring everything stays
on the ethical and compliant
part without manual checklists.
Each of these pillars address a
different aspect of the data platform.
Together.
They create a system that can
adapt, optimize, and govern
itself with minimum manual effort.
Next, we'll dive into each pillar
one by one with examples and results
to show how they work in practice
metadata intelligence.
Let's start with that.
Often call the nervous system
of modern data platforms.
Metadata is essentially data about data.
Descriptions of what each data set
contains, where it came from, who
owns it, quality stats, and so on.
In traditional setups, metadata is
often passive documentation, but
with AI driven metadata intelligence,
it becomes an active component
that helps the whole platform
understand and organize information.
In plain language, metadata intelligence
means the system can automatically
catalog, tag and discover that data sets.
It's like having a smart librarian
for your data, who not only catalogs
everything, but also knows in context
how it's used and can instantly
direct you to what you need.
This dramatically improves
how we find and trust data.
Here are some outcomes.
Organizations have seen
62% faster discovery.
Teams can find relevant data more than
twice As fast as before, imagine searching
for a dataset with AI curated metadata.
It's like a supercharged search engine.
So what used to take hours of
digging is done in minutes.
People spend less time hunting
for data and more time using it.
72% fewer data quality issues.
The platform catches
many data errors upfront.
AI tags data with quality
metrics and flags anomalies.
Leading to a dramatic reduction in
data incidents in practice, this
means far less time spent cleaning
data or dealing with broken reports.
43% higher trust in data.
When data is well-documented
and consistently reliable,
business users gain confidence.
In fact, organizations reported a
43% increase in business stakeholder
confidence in their data file.
People trust the dashboards and insights
because they trust the underlying data.
Thanks to that intelligent
metadata management.
And lastly, 2.7 times faster
project delivery with quick
discovery and fewer issues.
Analytics and data
science projects finish.
Projects finish almost three times faster.
Teams are in bo down by data angling.
The data is ready to go so
they can deliver insights to
stakeholders much more rapidly.
In short, metadata intelligence
makes the platform data aware
and accelerates everything.
It's the foundational layer
that ensures the right data is
easily found, understood, and
trusted across the organization.
Now to make this concrete,
let's look at its case study of
metadata intelligence in action.
Consider a large e-commerce
retailer that implemented AI driven
metadata for their product database.
All the descriptions, attributes,
customer reviews, the rich
information of our products.
The results were impressive.
They saw 37% better search relevancy.
Customers found that they were looking
for much more what customers found, what
they were looking for much more easily.
By automatically tagging products
with detailed attributes using AI
to generate and refine metadata, the
site search engine could deliver more
relevant results, which resulted in a
37% improvement in search accuracy and
relevancy In practice, if you search for
waterproof jacket, the system understands
context like synonyms related features,
and surface as the best matches.
And they saw 24% higher conversion
rate because shoppers were
finding the right products faster.
More of them ended up making purchases.
This retailer saw a 24% increase
in conversion rate, meaning a lot
more browsers turned into buyers.
And people can quickly
find what fits their needs.
They're more likely to hit add to cart.
Third, 19% fewer product returns.
Rich metadata meant product pages
had better information, accurate
specs, usage details, comparable
items, leading customers to buy items
that truly met their expectations.
The result was 19% drop in return rates.
Fewer returns indicate customers
are happier with what they bought.
They got what they
thought they were getting.
Lastly, 29% larger auto value.
Enhanced discovery didn't
just help find one item.
It helped.
It often helped customers find
additional or related items.
The retailer saw the average
order size grow by 29%.
This might be because AI driven
recommendations powered by metadata,
exposed more relevant add-ons or
complementary products, and people
felt confident adding them to the cart.
This case study shows that.
Metadata intelligence isn't
just an IT improvement.
It directly boosts business outcomes
better search and data understanding
led to more sales and happier customers.
It's a great example of how making data
more intelligent pays off intangible ways.
Self hailing data pipelines
Now onto the second pillar.
Data pipelines are the processes
that move and transform data.
For example, an ETL job that pulls
sales records from a database and
loads them into a data warehouse
nightly or a streaming pipeline that
collects sensor data in real time.
Traditionally, pipelines are brittle.
If there is a slight change in input or an
error, same as in file or schema change or
a server outage, the pipeline might break.
Then data engineers get paged
at 2:00 AM to fix it manually.
Troubleshooting and patching the issue.
With self-healing pipelines, we
add AI and automation to make these
workflows resilient and autonomous.
The platforms will detect issues and fix
many of them automatically without needing
a human to intervene for common problems.
Here is how it works in plain
terms, detect anomalies.
The system continuously monitors
pipeline behavior and data quality.
It knows what normal looks like.
If something odd happens, example,
a data patch is 50% smaller than
usual, or an unexpected file doesn't
arrive, it flags it immediately.
Early detection means we can
address issues before they
cascade into bigger failures.
Second, adapt to changes.
Suppose an upstream system adds a new
column or changes the data format.
Normally that might break the pipeline
because the code wasn't expecting it.
A self-healing pipeline.
Can automatically adjust to certain
changes, for instance, by using metadata
to map the new schema or by ignoring extra
fields until it learns how to handle them.
It's as if the pipeline can
evolve on the fly to stay
compatible, remediate problems.
For issues that have known issue success,
the system can apply them instantly.
For example, if a pipeline fails
due to a timeout, the platform might
automatically retry it on a backup
server, or if data arrives corrupted,
it could switch to a secondary source.
These automated corrections handle
mini routine failure patterns
without human involvement.
Learn and improve.
Every time the system encounters a
new issue, it learns from it over
time, it builds up knowledge of how
to handle various failure modes.
This means the more it runs,
the smarter and more efficient
it becomes self-healing.
It's similar to how our immune
system learns to fight new pathogens.
Each incident makes it
stronger for next time.
In practice, self-healing
pipelines drastically reduce
downtime and firefighting.
Imagine far fewer nightly
alerts and emergency fixes.
The data keeps flowing.
E, even when hiccups occur, because
the platform resolves them, or at
least contains them until a permanent
fixes applied, it turns a fragile
data pipeline into a robust immune
system that keeps your data moving.
So what is the impact of self
hailing pipelines on operations?
In short, significantly higher
reliability and lower maintenance effort.
When your data pipelines can fix
themselves or at least handle issues
gracefully, you can see benefits like
increased uptime and reliability,
fewer pipeline failures mean data
is available when people need it.
If your dashboards are
updated by 6:00 AM daily, they
continue to be updated on time.
Because the system has handled any
overnight glitches automatically,
this consistency builds trust
with users who rely on timely
data, lower maintenance burden.
Your engineers and DA data ops
team spend a lot time, a lot
less time reacting to problems.
One study by McKensey found that
advanced self failing systems can
cut operational costs by up to 30%.
Through reduced downtime and
more efficient fall management.
Think about that.
Nearly a third of the effort and
cost that used to go into manual
troubleshooting can be saved.
Your team can redirect that time to
more strategic work, like improving the
platform or building new data features
faster recovery when issues occur.
Even when the problem happens, the
systems can't fix fully by itself.
The automated detection and
preliminary action means the eventual
human intervention is quicker.
The system might already have isolated
the issue or tried common fixes, so the
meantime to recovery drops dramatically.
You're looking at minutes instead
of hours for many incidents.
Greater scalability of operations.
As your data volume and complexity
grow, a self-healing system scales
much better than a manual one.
You don't need to grow your
ops team linearly with data.
The AI copes with the growth
by learning and automating.
This makes the platform more scalable
from an operation standpoint in an, in a
sense, we move from a situation where data
engineering teams are constantly putting
out fires to one where the platform
autonomously handles routine issues.
That shift not only saves time and
money, but it also gives developers
and analysts confidence that the data
pipeline won't be the bottleneck or a
single point of failure in their projects.
Our third pillar is predictive
resource optimization.
This is about managing the computational
resources of the platform, things
like CPU Memory Storage Network in an
intelligent, proactive way using ai.
Traditional systems often either
overprovision resources just in
case, or you reactively scale up
after you notice performance lag or
high load, which can be too late.
Neither is ideal.
Predictive optimization uses machine
learning to anticipate demand and
edges resources ahead of time.
Here is the breakdown of how it works.
Learn patterns.
The platform looks at
historical usage data.
For example, it learns that every
weekday at 9:00 AM there's a spike
in dashboard quiz, or that end of
month processing uses a lot of CPU.
By analyzing these patterns over
weeks and months, ML models learn
the typical workload cycles.
It's similar to how a smart assistant
might learn your routine forecast demand.
With these learn patterns,
the AI can predict future.
For instance, it might forecast
that tomorrow's web traffic will
be 20% higher due to a marketing
event, or that in December you'll
need extra storage for air end data.
It anticipates both regular
cycles and unusual events.
If it is fed the right signals,
optimize resources based on the
forecast, the platform proactively
allocates or adjusts resources.
This could mean spinning up
additional server instances at 8:50
AM just before the users login.
So performance stays smooth or
automatically scaling down some
services during weekends to
save cost when demand is low.
Essentially, it tunes capacity in
advance as instead of waiting to
react, it's like packing an umbrella
because the weather forecast said
there is a high chance of rain.
You were prepared ahead of time.
Measure results.
After acting the system watches
what actually happens and
compares it to the prediction.
Maybe it's predicted a
20% spike, but it was 25%.
It then learns from the discrepancy
and fine tunes its model.
This is a feedback loop.
Over time, the predictions
get more accurate and the
optimization strategies improve.
The system continuously learns and
adapts to changing usage patterns.
In non-technical terms, predictive
resource optimization makes your
platform run like a well oil machine,
always sufficiently power for
what's coming, but not excessive.
It's the difference between always
driving your car with the pedal to the
metal just in case, versus using cruise
control and predictive GPS that knows
a hill is coming and accelerates a bit
beforehand than eases off and coasting.
The result is smoother performance
and far better efficiency.
What benefits can we actually get from
this kind of predictive optimization?
Let's look at some real results achieved
with AI driven resource management.
Utilization improvement systems
have seen around 43.8% improvement
in resource utilization.
In one comparison, using ML based
workload forecasting, outperform
traditional threshold based.
Auto scaling by that margin Concretely,
this means the hardware and cloud
instances you're paying for are
being used much more efficiently.
Before maybe servers sat idle 60%
of the time as a safety buffer.
After implementing AI predictions
over provisioning dropped from
about 61% to just 12.3% while
still maintaining performance.
The platform isn't holding a bunch of
extra capacity that never gets used.
It's closer to a just in time model For
compute, this efficiency is a direct
cost saver, cost reduction, because of
better utilization, companies saved a
lot of money on our, on average midsize
deployments, saved about 476 K per
year by using AI to optimize resources.
In fact, the investment in the, in
these optimization algorithms paid
back three 80% in the first year.
A three 80% return on investment is huge.
Essentially, for every dollar put into
implementing the solution, they got back
three 80 back in savings within that year.
This kind of ROI indicates that
the optimization not only covers
its own costs, but generates
significant net savings very quickly.
Performance enhancement, it's
not about cost, performance,
reliability improved too.
SLE violations drop by 76.2%.
That means far fewer incidents where
the system's performance fell below.
Agreed targets.
Like slow response time or downtime.
By predicting and preventing
resource bottlenecks, the
system can meet its performance
targets much more consistently.
Over three quarters of the issues that
used to break as is were eliminated
handling 3.2 times workload variability.
The platform became much more
robust against traffic spikes
and variability in tests.
It could handle 3.2 times
more variations in workload.
Without performance
degradation compared to before.
So if your user load suddenly triples,
think flash sale or a wire event,
the system can absorb it gracefully.
This is a big deal for scalability.
It means fewer emergencies when load
searches unexpectedly because the
system likely already scaled itself in
anticipation and can react fast enough
thanks to the predictive head start.
Overall, these results show a win-win.
Greater efficiency and better performance.
Often.
In the past we had a trade
off cost versus speed.
You'd overprovision to ensure speed
or save cost, but risk slowdowns AI
lets you get both lower cloud builds
and a faster, more reliable system.
It's a great example of
optimization done right
now let's talk about the fourth pillar
embedded governance and ethical ai.
This is all about trust, security, and
compliance built into the data platform.
Traditionally, data governance,
ensuring the right people
have access to the right data.
Data is issues used ethically,
privacy is protected, et cetera, has
been a very manual set of processes.
It often feels like a gatekeeper
that slows things down.
Example, waiting weeks for approval to
access a data set or big audits to ensure
compliance with regulations like GDPR.
In a AI driven platform, we turn
governance from a hurdle into an
integrated automated safeguard.
The platform itself helps enforce policies
and ethical guidelines continuously so
that it's not all manual checkpoints.
Let's break it down.
What the entails.
Automatic detection.
The platform automatically identifies
and classifies sensitive data.
For example, it can scan incoming
data and recognize this column looks
like social security numbers are.
This dataset contains personal
health information using ai.
It can even detect things that aren't
just based on simple rules, say it
learns to flag a combination of data
fields that together are sensitive.
By knowing where all the sensitive
or regulated data is, we have the
foundation to handle it properly.
Policy enforcement.
Once data is classified, the
system can apply the appropriate
protections automatically.
If something is tagged as confidential,
the platform might automatically
encrypt it, mask it, and analytics
or restrict who can query it.
The idea is that rules like financial
data X can only be seen by those
roles or mask out customer names
when data is used for analysis, are
enforced by the system at runtime,
not just written in a policy document.
This reduces human error and
makes compliance consistent.
Continuous monitoring governance
isn't a one-time thing.
The platform continuously monitors
data usage for compliance risks.
It watches for unusual access patterns.
For instance, if someone is s querying
an abnormal amount of sensitive
data at 2:00 AM it might flag or
block that as potential breach.
It also ensures that as new data comes in.
As regulations change, it keeps
everything in check in real time.
This is like having a security
guard on duty 24 by seven
inside your data platform.
Always alert, transparent decisions.
A critical part of ethical
AI is transparency.
The system provides explanations
for automated actions.
If it blocked the user's access
or encrypted a data set, it'll
log or even inform you why.
This day-to-day set contains
HIPAA protected data, or so
direct access was restricted.
The transparency is key to trust both
internally, so data teams understand
system behavior and externally.
Imagine how regulators or customers
clear audit trail of how data is handled.
We don't want a black box governance, ai.
We want a glass box that
shows its reasoning.
Ultimately embedded governance
means compliance and ethics
are not an afterthought.
They're bake into the daily
operations of the data platform.
It ensures that as we
automate more, we are doing so
responsibly for the organization.
This means safer data, fewer compliance
nightmares, and a strong ethical stance
by default, rather than depending
solely on periodic manual checks.
It turns out doing governance
right with AI and automation
doesn't just avoid problems.
It can actually speed up your
organization and build trust
becoming a competitive advantage.
Let's look at some metrics that
companies have reported after
embedding governance into their data
platforms, operational efficiency.
Automated governance dramatically cuts
down the bus, busy work and compliance.
For example, companies saw a 67% reduction
in audit prep time, preparing for audits,
used to take months of gathering records,
permissions, data, lineage information.
Now, a lot of that is available on demand
via the platform's, logs and catalogs.
They also saw 43% improvement
in audit success rates.
Meaning far fewer findings or
issues since the system was
already keeping things in line.
Another impressive figure.
94.8% sensitive data
classification accuracy.
The AI is identifying sensitive data,
almost 95% correctly, which is better
than most humans could do at scale.
High accuracy here means you really mis
tagging something that needs protection.
Giving you confidence that nothing
is slipping through the cracks.
Agility and compliance
embed, embedding governance actually
makes the organization more agile
in how it can use data because
the guardrails are automated.
One metric data access requests
that used to take nearly nine
and a half days on average.
All the approval sticker checks now
can be fulfilled about 12 minutes, in
about 12 minutes, basically in near real
time, once the proper criteria are met.
That's a game changer for analytics
or scientists who need data now
rather than two weeks later.
Another metric, adapting to new
regulations went from 97 days to 26
days when a new law or policy comes out.
Because much of the governance logic
is in software, you can update rules
in the platform and achieve compliance
in a few weeks instead of a quarter.
And importantly, unauthorized
access incidents went down 82%.
The continuous monitoring and automated
controls shut down a lot of opportunities
for mistakes or malicious access.
So there are far fewer security incidents.
That's a huge risk reduction market trust.
Strong governance boosts
your external reputation.
Companies with this autonomous
governance measures got
regulatory approvals 28% faster.
For things like new product
launches or certifications,
regulators trust them because they
can see robust controls in place.
So the approval process, speed up customer
confidence in how the data is handled,
jumped from about 51 to 74% in surveys.
That's a big leap.
When customers know you take
their data seriously and have the
systems to protect it, they're more
comfortable doing business with you.
And notably, legal challenges and
disputes related to data dropped
by 76% fewer lawsuits, fines, or
public relation issues occur when
you are on top of privacy and ethics.
In summary, good data governance
isn't just about avoiding penalties,
it's about it builds trust
with customers and regulators.
Which is invaluable for business
continuity and brand reputation.
So this pillar turns what used to be seen
as a check boss or drag on productivity
into a source of speed and trust.
It empowers the organization to use data
more freely and to confidently show the
world that it can be trusted with data.
It's absolutely a competitive advantage
in today's data-driven market.
We have talked through the four pillars,
metadata intelligence, self-healing,
pipelines, predictive optimization, and
embedded governance, and seen how each
improves a part of the data platform.
Now let's zoom out and conclude by
painting the picture of the future, the
truly autonomous data platforms the.
The theme across all these pillars
is moving from manual reactive
ways of working to automated,
proactive, and intelligent systems.
On this slide, we sum it up as
a series of transformations from
documentation to active intelligence.
Metadata is no longer just passive
documentation sitting in a catalog.
It becomes an active
living part of the system.
In the future when new data comes in,
the platform doesn't just note it down.
It actively understands it,
organizes it, and even uses that
knowledge to automate processes.
It's as if your documentation comes alive
and start doing some of the work for you.
From brittle to self hailing
pipelines, data pipelines today can be
fragile, breaking with small changes.
We are moving to a world where pipelines
are self-healing and resilient by design.
This means a minor schema change or
a spike in data volume won't bring
things crashing down The pipeline
adapts or recovers on its own.
The future pipeline is like a
robust organism that can heal wounds
quickly rather than a house of guard.
This drastically reduces failures
and maintenance effort from
reactive to predictive resource
management instead of the ops team
reacting to outages or slowdowns.
Chasing after issues, the platform will
predict and prevent many of those issues.
Resource management and tuning
will largely be on autopilot.
The systems will know, for example,
that end of quarter is coming, let's
allocate more capacity now, or,
this query pattern looks like it
could cause a bottleneck tomorrow.
Let's opt optimize it now.
We move from always being on the
back foot to being a step ahead.
The result is smoother performance and
happy users who don't even realize how
much foresight is happening behind the
scenes from control to empowerment.
Governance shifts from a strict control
mindset to an empowerment mindset.
Yes, you can use this data because
the controls to do it safely are
already in place and automated.
In the future, governance is
an enabler, not a roadblock.
It gives people confidence to explore and
use data freely within safe boundaries.
This means data innovation
can flourish because the
platform is both open and safe.
People get to work with data faster,
and the system widely ensures it all.
It's all compliant and ethical
when you put it all together.
Future autonomous data platform is
one where a lot of the heavy lifting,
like finding data, fixing errors,
tuning performance, checking compliance
is handled by the platform itself.
It's analogous to how modern
cars app lane assist, automatic
braking and self parking.
We are adding those kind of
intelligent features to data systems.
We, as data professionals get to focus
more on strategy, analysis and innovation.
Rather than babysitting pipelines, or
chasing now issues, this transition
from manual to self-optimizing
systems is already underway.
As these pillars mature, we will see
data platforms that can run with minimal
human intervention With us, providing
high level guidance and handling the
exceptions, it's an exciting future,
one that turns the growing data uch
from a challenge into an opportunity.
Because our AI driven platforms
will be ready to handle it.
Thank you for listening.
I hope this gave you a clear
picture of how AI can fundamentally
improve data platform management.
With that, I wrap up and I'm happy to
take any questions or discuss further.
Thank you.