Hi folks.
I'm Santos.
I'm a senior database administrator.
As a senior database administrator.
I spent so long talked to service,
started to understand my jokes,
mostly the s ql o and stuff.
So today I'm gonna talk about
AI driven anomaly detection
for cloud data pipelines.
So picture this you got
all this amazing data.
Flowing into your company, right?
It's like a Jane Digital
River powering everything from
showing you relevant cat videos.
Okay?
Actually running the business now, keeping
that river clean and flowing smoothly,
that's where the things get tricky.
So think about it.
We are talking about tons of data coming
from everywhere, going through all sort
of twists and turns into the cloud.
Is that trying to manage the plumbing
in a city like City of Texas?
One little clog, one tiny leak, and
suddenly your reports are garbage.
So your decisions are based on who knows
what, and you're potentially facing some
C ds Oops moments with the folks in suits.
Traditional ways of checking
if things are going wrong.
They're like having a guy with
checklists standing by the river,
looking for a specific types of trash.
But what if the problem
isn't obviously trash?
What if it's just a water turning
a weird shade off green, slowly
poisoning everything downstream?
So that's where our
superhero comes in, ai.
Over next 20, 25 to 30 minutes,
I'm going to show you how we have
built this smart system that's like
a superpower water quality expert
for your driver, data drivers.
It use all the fancy AI stuff,
machine learning that actually learns.
What normal water looks like.
Deep learning that can spot even
the subtle changes in the flow, and
even some brainy stuff that tries
to understand what the data means.
This isn't just about finding big,
obvious errors, it's about getting a real
healthy report on your data so we can
fix things before they become a disaster.
Think of it as a preventative
medicine for your data.
We are better than waiting
for a data to get sick, right?
Hey.
Again, my name is Santos and I'm
still chatting with you all day today.
I'm gonna talk about the data
changes of modern data pipelines.
Where why AI superheroes so necessary in
the first place of modern data pipelines.
They're not your grandpa Grand hose.
They're more like a massive,
interconnected networks of pipes,
pumps, and filters spread across
and entire digital landscape.
And that complexity, it brings
a whole heap of headaches.
So complex architecture, the web of
interconnections, think of it as a game.
Digital Spa Monster data comes in
from a million different places.
Maybe it's just customers like a
website, sunsets in a factory, sales
figures from a dozen different systems.
Then it gets tossed around between
all these different cloud services.
One thing transforms is another store.
It.
And another analyze it, and then
it gets sent to even more places.
Each time it jumps from
one system to other.
There's a chance to think to go wrong.
Maybe the data gets transferred
incorrectly, maybe the little
bit gets lost in the transit,
or maybe the system just have a
different idea about what a data.
Date or a number even means this
tangled web of connections is just
begging for subtle errors to sneak it
and trying to track them down the old
school methods is like trying to find a
specific knowledge in what whole mess I.
Good luck with that.
So difficult detection, finding
the needle in a haystack.
So you've got this crazy complex system
with tons of data whizzing around how do
you even know when something goes wrong?
Traditionally monitoring is
setting up a few basic alarms.
If the water pressure drops
below this point, some the other.
But if a problem isn't a certain drop,
what if the gradual decrease over time?
Or a slight change in our color that only
trained, I would notice this subtle shift.
These tiny deviations from the usual
flow might not trigger any of those
basic alarms, but they could be early
signs of much bigger problem brewing.
And with the sheer volume of data we are
dealing with manually, looking for these
little clues is basically impossible.
You need any army of, you
need army of data detection.
Starting at endless streams of
numbers made a smart system that
can learn what normal look like, so
it can automatically flag even the
quietest something, not right signals.
So it can automatically flag those
without, with those, a little bit of
tiny minute, something not right signals.
So financial impact, the
hidden cost of bad data.
Now we are, we might be thinking,
okay, so some data gets a little wonky.
Big deal.
Wrong.
So bad data ist just a technical problem.
It hits the company where it really hurts.
The valid and the numbers
are actually pretty scary.
Studies shows the companies
can lose around 20% of their
revenue due to poor data quality.
Let that sink in for a second.
That's like throwing one out of every
$5 straight into a digital garbage care.
And where does this money go?
Wasted time, compliance, nightmares,
dumb decisions, and a angry
customer and a missed opportunity.
It all adds up.
So yeah, good data is
in just a tech thing.
It's a straight up business necessity.
So few of the key
features of our solution.
So how does our AI power system
actually step in and save the day?
It's, it got a whole toolbox of
clever features designed to be
ultimate data quality guardians
and advanced detection algorithm.
The multilayered approach to intelligent.
We don't just throw one type of AI at
this problem and help hope for the best.
We got a whole team of digital
detectives each with their own specific
skills, the old school smarties, using
statistics to spot obvious awareness
and the modern brain using deep
learning to catch the real subtle stuff.
Adaptive learning, continuous
implement to experience this
system is in just one trick pony.
It actually learns from data, it sees
the feedback it gets from your smart
humans consistently getting better at
knowing what normal and what's not.
So real time processing, immediate
insight and actionability in the cloud.
Things move fast and
then so does our system.
It's spots problem as they happen,
letting us jump in and then things fix
things before they cause real chaos.
Our AI driven.
Anomaly detection system tackles
these challenges head on with a
suit of sophisticated features
designed for proactive and
intelligence, data quality management.
So when it comes to advanced
data detection, I. Advanced
detection algorithm and multiple
layered approach to intelligence.
Our system doesn't rely on single
magic bullet algorithm Instead.
Instead, it employs a careful
curated combination of techniques
to provide comprehensive and
accurate anomaly detection.
Traditional statistics techniques.
We leverage a. Establish statistics
methods like control charts for
monitoring data distribution over time.
I identifying out outliners
based on standard deviations and
employing time series analysis to
forecast expected values and detect
deviations from these forecasts.
These provides a strong foundation for
identifying well-defined anomalies,
modern deep learning models to
capture more complex and new.
Nuisance patterns.
We integrated cutting edge deep learning
models, variational auto encoders,
learning the underlying structure
of normal data, and can identify
subtle anomalies by detect instance
that are difficult to reconstruct.
Long short term memory networks
are crucial for understanding
temporal dependencies.
In sequence.
Networks are crucial for understanding
temporal dependencies in sequential
data, allowing us to detect anomalies.
That manifest as usual sequence of
events or shift in trend over time.
Assembly methods, the wisdom
of crowd to further enhance the
accuracy and robust offer detection,
be utilize assembly methods.
This involves combination of predictions
from multiple different algorithms.
By leveraging the strength of each
individual model, we can achieve
higher oral accuracy and reduce
the currency of false posture.
For example, a statistical model
might quickly flag a larger outliner,
while a deep learning model might
detect subtle but persistent drift in
a complex data relationship, so real
time processing, immediate insight.
In immediate insight in the dynamics
of the cloud data pipelines speed
in the Paramount, our system is
engineered for realtime processing as
data streams through the pipelines.
It is con, continuously analyzed
by our detection algorithm.
When anomalies identified, an alert
is generated or almost instantly.
This is realtime capability is
crucial for several reasons.
Preventing error propagation, faster
incident response, enabling realtime
decision making for applications that
rely on realtime data immediately.
Anomaly detection ensures that
decisions are based on most
accurate and accurate information.
Adaptive learning, continuous
improvements through experience.
Data.
Pipelines are leaving.
Breathing systems.
That consistently evolve.
Our system is designed to adopt
these changes through continuous
learning, learning from historical
data, incorporating user feedback,
implicit learning through remediations
dynamic threshold adjustments.
So based on continuous feedback,
observation, data patterns,
the system dynamically adjusts
its detection thresholds.
This ensures that system remains s due
to genuine anomalies while minimizing
false alarm as underlying data
characteristics exchange over time.
Now, system design and architecture.
Alright, let's speak.
Under the hood and see how we are
actually build the brainy system.
We designed it specifically for the
cloud, thinking about making it flexible,
able to handle huge amount of data and
easy to maintain, flexible and scalable
adapting to diverse cloud landscapes.
We know you folks are in all using
the same brand of cloud, so you may.
We made sure our system plays
well with all the major players
and can handle your growth.
Growing data needs, it's container,
containerizing, microservices,
independent unit of functionality
instead of one big complicated thing.
We got a bunch of smaller
independent parts like Legos,
each doing a specific job.
This, make it easy to deploy,
scale the right parts, and makes
the whole system more reliable.
Modular components,
adaptability and evolution.
This Lego like approach means we
can easily update, replace, or
even customize the parts of systems
without bringing everything down.
So in depth in the cloud.
The challenges and opportunities
of cloud environment in mind,
emphasizing flexibility,
scalability, and maintainability.
So adapting to the diverse landscape,
recognizing that our users operate
in diverse cloud environments.
We are architecting our system to
be highly flexible and adaptable.
It's designed to integrate seamlessly with
major cloud provider like AWS, Azure and
GCP, as well as hybrid cloud deployments.
This flex.
This flexibility extends to the
type of data sources and pipeline
components it can monitor.
Furthermore, scalability is
a core tenant of Artisan.
As your data volume and the processing
demand grow in the cloud, our system can
scalable scale horizontally by adding more
instance of its microservices, enduring
consistent performance without bottleneck.
Containerizing microservices.
Independent unit of functionality.
We embrace a microservices architecture
where system is broken down into
collection of small independent services,
each responsible for a specific function.
Data ingestions features engineering,
statistical analysis, deep learning
interference, alert management,
and a feedback processing.
Those microservices.
Are a package into a lead lightweight
container using technology like Docker.
This container offers several key
advantages, simplified deployment,
independent scaling fault,
isolation, technology agnostic.
So microservices allows us to
choose the best technology stack
of each specific function promoting
innovative innovation and efficiency.
Modular components, so the modular
design of our system goes hand in
hand with the microservices approach.
Each microservices represents
a distinct replaceable module.
This modularity provides significant
benefits for a long time.
Maintainability, and
evaluation simplified updates.
Individual module can be updated or
passed without requiring a complete
system redeployment, minimizing
downtime and risk technology upgrades.
As a new and more efficient algorithms
are technologies become available,
we can seamlessly integrate them
by replacing existing audios.
Customizing and extensibility The
modeler design allows for potential
customization and extensions of system
to meet specific user requirement.
In the future,
new modules for specialized data
types or detection techniques
could be added without affecting
the more functionalities,
data ingestion, and traffic.
Okay, so before our AI brains
can do their magic, they need
good clean data to work with.
Think of it like a chef
needing good ingredients.
This slide is about how we grab the data
and then get it ready for the analysis.
So data capture, comprehensive
monitoring coverage.
We like, we are like thorough
detective gathering all the source
of clue, not just like a main data,
but also the data about the data.
How the pipeline is behaving and even
little snapshots of data itself, and
you can tell us what clue are most
important to collect Data captures
comprehensive monitoring coverage.
Our system is designed to a
holistic monitoring solution
for your data pipelines.
This means we don't just focus on raw
transactional data, we also collect
a rich set of contextual information.
Metadata, operational metrics, sample
data, configuration collection.
So this includes information about
the data such as source schema,
data types, timestamps and lineages.
Changes in metadata can often be early
indicators of the problem, so we also
gather performance metrics from various
components of data pipeline itself,
such as processing time, CPU, memory.
Network latency and error rates.
Anomalies in these operational
metrics can often correlate with
even precise data called tissues.
So to understand the actual
content and structure of the data,
we strategically sample data at
various points in the pipeline.
This allows our algorithm to learn
the normal patterns and identify
deviations in the data values themselves.
The specific data points and metrics we
collect are configurable, allowing you
to tailor the monitoring to the most cri
critical aspect of your data pipeline.
So feature engineering, e extracting
meaning the raw data is often messy.
Feature engineering is like our expert
chef, taking those raw ingredients and
prepping them just right, so our AI
models can actually understand them.
The raw data is just a native format,
is often not directly suitable
for machine learning analysis.
Feature engineering is a crucial
process of transforming this raw
data into a set of meaningful
features that are anomaly detects.
Models can effectively learn from.
This involves several techniques, data
cleaning, handling missing values,
correcting, inconsistency, and removing
noise from the data transformation.
Scaling numeric features ENC coding,
categorial variables, and applying
mathematical transformations to
make the data more suitable for the
algorithm creation of new features,
deriving new features from the
existing data from the high highlights.
Potential anomalies.
For example, calculating the rate of
change of a metric over time, or creating
interaction features between different
data points, dimensional direction
in the high dimensional dataset.
The techniques like
principle component analysis.
Also, CALS, PCA, can be used to reduce
the number of features while preserving
the most important information, improving
model efficiency and reducing noise.
Next, coming to the format optimization.
So different AM models are picky, so we
make sure that the data is in the perfect
format for each one of its best work.
It's all about making sure it's
good data, good insights out.
Our pre-processing pipelines ensure
that the engineering features are in
the I format for each of the anomaly
detection algorithm we employ.
This might involve
normalization and scaling.
Enduring.
All numerical features are on a similar
scale to prevent certain features from
dominating the CER learning process,
data type conversions, converting data
into appropriate data types except.
Expected by the models structuring
data for specific models.
For example, formatting time series
data into a sequence for LSGM networks,
or creating input vector for VAEs.
This meticulous data tion and tree
processing data is fundamental to
overall accuracy and efficiency
of our anomaly detection system.
Garbage in, garbage out.
We ensure that our AI are working with
clean, relevant, and well formatted data.
Anomaly detect detection algorithms.
Alright, let's get a
little more technical and.
Talk about the actual brains behind
our anomaly detection system.
The algorithms, we got a whole stable of
different mod models working together.
Statistical model, there are more
reliable workhorses using classic
methods to spot unusual stuff.
Variational auto encoders.
These are the deep learning art.
Artist learning to
recognize complex patterns.
LSGM networks, these
are the memory experts.
Great for spotting weird
sequences in the data.
Over time.
Assembly assemble methods.
We combine the strength of
all these different brains to
get the most accurate results.
It's having a team of specialists all
working together to solve the case.
It's a time series analysis.
For time dependent data like pipeline
metrics, these models forecast
expected features, values based on
historical trends and seasonality.
Deviations from these forecasts
are flagged as potential anomalies.
Con control chats.
These visually tracked
data points over time.
Agne, statistically calculated
upper and lower control limits.
Points failing outside these limits are
considered statistically significant
anomalies, distribution based methods.
Example gas and mixture models.
These models learn the underlying
probability distribution of the data
points with the lower probability
of belonging of the learning
distributions are flagged as anomalies.
Proximity based methods.
These methods identify anomalies
based on the distance to their nearest
neighbors in the data space, the data
points that are significantly far
from other data points are considered
unusual assembly methods, combining
strength for superior performance.
Our assembly approach strategically
combines the output of these diverse
statistical models and our approach.
Advanced deep learning models to achieve
more accurate and reliable anomaly.
Detections weighted averaging, assigning
different weights to the predictions
of individual models based on their
historical performance and expertise in
detecting specific type of anomalies,
working, combining the predictions
of multiple models through major.
Majority voting and other
aggregation techniques.
Stacking using a metal learner model
to learn how to best combine the
predictions of base level models.
So these strategies helps to mitigate the
weakness of individual models and leverage
their strengths leading to a more robust
and accurate overall detection system.
So variational auto encoders, unsupervised
learning for complex anomalies are
powerful class of deep learning models.
Particularly well suited for
unsupervised anomaly detection in
complex, high dimensional data,
learning latent representations.
So VAEs learns a compressed, low
dimensional representation and latent
space for normal data distributions.
So continuous feedback and adaptions.
So now our AI system isn't just a set.
Set it and forget it kind
of thing to keep it sharp.
We are built.
We have built in a way for it to
consistently learn and improve
detection, the system flag.
Potentially the system flags
for potential weird feedback.
You are smart humans.
Tells it is a right or wrong adaption.
The system uses the that feedback
to get back over time, adjust
its rules, and getting smarter
at what that normal looks like.
What the normal looks like.
It's like a training, a puppy
deployment, scaling strategies.
When we rolled this out, we didn't
just throw it at everything at once.
We looked at careful
approach, isolated testing.
We started small, testing it
out on less critical pipelines.
First, education, educate, identification.
We use these initial tests to figure
out any weird edge cases, like
sudden changes in data structures
or very new pipeline startups.
Gradual expansion.
Once we are confident, we started rolling
out to the bigger and complex systems.
Full implementation.
The goal is to have this smart
monitoring across the entire companies,
keeping all our data reverse clean.
Alright, so all that fancy AI stuff
and cloud engineering, it's actually
delivered some pretty sweet results.
So we are not just talking theory here.
You have seen some real world wins, the
40% reduction in data quality issues.
Think about it.
That's like a cutting down the number
of oops movements with your, with our
data by almost half fewer corrupted
files, fewer inconsistencies, fewer time.
Someone says, wait, is
this data even right?
It means our reports are cleaner,
our analysis are more reliable.
And we spend less time chasing
down data governance, basically
less headaches for everyone.
So 97, 99 0.9, 99.7%,
reduction in reduction times.
So this one mind, this
one is mind blowing.
Mind blowing.
Before, when someone went
wrong, something went wrong.
It could take hours, sometimes even
days or manual digging through logs
and trying to figure out what happened.
Now our AI spots is where things
almost instantly, it's like going
from snail mail to instantly may
messaging for finding problems.
The speed means we can jump on
issues before they can cause
bigger problems downstream, and
84, 80 4% fewer false postures.
Nobody likes getting a bunch of
alerts that turns out to be nothing.
It's like a car alarm that
keeps going off for no reason.
You start to ignore it.
Our system is much better at
telling the difference between
a real time problem and a just a
normal, slightly unusual data point.
That means our team can trust the
alerts they get an then focus on real
fires instead of chasing shadows.
Overall, this AI system has really made
our data environments way more stable.
It's like we have got dedicated data
health monitor that always on the lookout
catching the problems early and letting
our talented teams focus on building cool
stuff and getting real insights from data
instead of just constantly firefighting.
I.
So to give you a taste of how this works
in the real world, let's talk about big
financial institutions we've worked with.
You can imagine in the world of real time
trading, even the tiniest data glitch
can have massive financial consequences.
Think millions of dollars
in the blink of ice.
They needed a way to monitor
this increasingly fasting moving.
Data streams and catching
more anomalies immediately.
So we plugged our AI
driven system into their.
Trading data pipelines, the
results are pretty dramatic.
43.7 reduction in data issues.
They say a huge drop in number of data
quality incidents that meant fewer errors
in the data, trading data leading to more
reliable operations and fewer moments.
So this freed up their highly skilled
expert from spending time on tedious
data cleanups and let them focus
on what strategic high value task
3.27 mil million annual savings.
And here is a kicker.
All that early detection and
fewer data problems translated
into some serious cost saving.
This came from a few different areas,
less time spent on manual monitoring
and fixing errors, avoiding potentially
huge losses from bad trading decisions
based on faulty data, and even
reducing the risk of complicated
analysis due to inaccurate reporting.
That's real money back in their pockets.
All thanks to our smart data watchdogs.
Now we are pretty proud of what we have
built, but we are not planning on just
kicking back and watching the data flow.
We are always looking for a way to make
our system even better and smarter.
Here's a sneak peek of what we are
working on, concept drift management.
Imagine the normal of our
data slowly changing our time,
like the season changing.
We are working on making our AI even
better, recognizing these long-term
shifts so it doesn't start flagging
the new normal as an anomaly.
It's like teaching it to understand the
changing weather patterns of our data.
Enhancing computational efficiency.
We are always looking for a
way to make our algorithms run
faster and use fewer resources.
Think of it as masking our AI brain
even more efficient so it can process
more data without getting a headache.
This might involve smart algorithms
or even using specialized computer
hardware real time remediation.
This is the holy grail, the feature
where you, our system doesn't just
tell you that there's a problem.
But actually fixes it automatically
without needing a human to step in.
Imagine a self feeling data pipeline.
That's the direction we are heading.
Creating a closed loop system that
keeps your data flowing smoothly
and minimal human intervention.
So to wrap things up, are AI driven.
Anomaly detection system is a
significant leap forward in keeping
your cloud data healthy and reliable.
Just smart.
It's, it learns, it scales.
It delivers critical results.
It gives business a powerful tool.
Not only catch problems early, but
also build more trustworthy data
foundations improve how they operate
and ultimately make better decisions.
We are excited about the future
of this technology and the
potential to make managing complex
cloud data environments a whole.
A lot less chaotic.
Thanks for your time.
I'm happy to answer any
questions you might have.
Thank you.