Everyone, good afternoon, good
morning, and good evening.
Whatever the time is on today.
I'm pretty much so happy that we are going
to discuss about the quantifying RIRI,
TE management and how AI implementation
transform of financial in 2025.
So this is the one of the
pretty good topic, which I'm
pretty much looking forward and
looking pretty much interested.
To see how it's going to help
the human kind or humans or
whatever, whoever is going to get
the more benefits using this ai.
Okay, which one of the
primary example is myself?
Which I'm getting benefit through AI
all the time with respect to the system.
At the same time, how is helping me in the
real time at the same time, how is helping
me in both personal and personal ways?
Which we can discuss in
this making decision.
The primary focus should be on
the financial services, how AE is
helping the banking sector or other,
any other tech sector, which we are
going to discuss in this meeting.
Okay, thank you.
Let's delve into this one.
If we can see the, my
first slide quantifying RI.
If you see the synopsis here,
the financial service industry
has witnessed unprecedented.
Transformation through strategic
AI implementation with the global
enrichment facing 1 42 0.83 billion.
This is reflecting year's crucial
to in aging traditional financial
operations and driving industry
enhancements why AI tion so rapidly
simply, let's put the next slide.
Okay.
Yeah, simply put it
delivers tangible deals.
A driven automation has imposed
operational efficiency by 35%,
streamlining the routine process such
as account creation, consolidation,
transaction processing, and data entry.
Financial institution like JP
Morgan Chase, for example, have
successfully deferred a to automate
loan approvals and account verification
process, significantly reducing
manual labor and human error.
Just think about this.
Within this year itself, we are
seeing 33% of operational efficiency,
as we discussed about right now.
The example of JP Morgan Chase has
a split A to automate loan approvals
and the verification process,
it used to take so much of time.
Previously we go for any loan approval.
The initial process surface, they
used to take minimum two weeks, the
maximum of four weeks or five weeks.
Now it came down to less than a week.
It is saying so much of time for the
bank at the same time saying so much
time for that end user customer.
Also at the same time ation
process, but this having so much
of manual labor and human error
that is cutting so much of term.
Okay, coming back to the next finance,
what I'm saying is much of 15%.
Okay.
In general, the financial forecasting
will be done by the most of
the companies across the world.
Out of that.
We can see right now in this effect
25 25, we are seeing the 15% with ai.
Like for example, if they take
Goldman Sachs, but it's one of the
biggest company to market fluctuations
and budget needs unprecedented.
Additionally, a systems have reduced
data processing errors about 20%.
Is your team taking
example of Goldman Sachs?
Everyone will follow.
The Goldman says Complete what?
They provide their predictions
about the market, either or contract
India, sorry, these are Nasdaq here.
Do here about the New York where
we, everyone eagerly wait to see
what's going to the predictions for
tomorrow or day after the next week.
Other we everything.
So instead of Goldmans has used to spend
so much of manual hours, now they onboard
with a. They're able to provide the
accurate information with AI and then the
pressure also so accurate and so good.
That's the reason a is going to be
the game changer or the path breaker,
whatever your name, it's going to help
the humankind in much better ways.
Okay.
Let's go to the next slide.
Ex, exactly.
And then let's go to.
When we are talking about all this
technical architecture about how A is
going to help, I dive into three parts.
Generative A and security protocol.
That's because I was a. How it
going to help central to these
achievements is sophisticated technical
architecture anchored by the generator.
A systems capable crossing over
1.2 million tokens per second.
We're talking about 1.2 million
tokens per second, transform
customer interactions and ending
into deeply present experiences.
Banks like HSBC's now employ advanced
chart bots for customer service,
providing immediate tire response
based on a real time, and also customer
profiles and financial behaviors.
Okay, so think think about what we are
doing with the h SBCs Bank and they
have any number of transitions, all time
going on the general way we can validate
and monitor, we can remove the analysis
and we can develop so many agents.
I can talk about so much of AA
agents, which we are right now,
the going on across the world.
That agency is going to help.
And then with the agents, we are going
to processing 1.3 million to per second.
It being said, it cannot be done with
the human, can be done with the A only.
So with the help of aa, because we see a
kind of, banks are using the third parts.
For customer service.
I'm saying a agents, which is going
to change, but we can talk about chart
parts or agents, whatever you name it.
Those going to provide that providing
immediate tire responsibility
on the real time of customer
profiles and financial bills.
Seriously, if you're doing something
right previously, if you send any
request to the bank, it'll take
24 to 48 hours or more than that.
To get a response with the chart parts,
what we are going to develop with the
generative AI and agents, what we are
going to go and discuss more of what
we're going to see much more in future.
Those will change the banking sector
completely like how the processing like
one point million tokens per second.
Let's go to the one more
called creative analytics.
Where predict actually in general
water about what's going to happen
with the data water we have with the
actuals, what we call the actuals.
So with the actual set we can see,
okay for three years or four years, it
used to take so much of time and the
human interactions at the same time,
lot of labor and then everyone need to
spend so much of time to analyzing the
what happened for the past three years
and then come up with the numbers.
What's going to happen
in the next three years.
And then we don't know how much
that with the ai, if you're
providing that predictive analytics.
Okay.
Approximately, there's 2.5 petabytes
of data financially, daily.
In respect of any bank, the number
you can at number 2.5 petabytes,
it's equal to thousands of digital
libraries for entrance enrichment.
Firms like BlackRock utilize breakthrough
analytics to swiftly identify emerging
trends, anticipate marketing shift
and manage risk culturally securing
a robust portfolio performance.
Even market, BlackRock is one of the
biggest emission firms, which they're
using a breakthrough analytics they
used to do previously as well, but
with a lot of human intervention.
The lever now with leveraging
this analytics with a. It's
pretty much game changing.
And then the title also
so good and accurate.
And if you need to think about that as
a language, you're doing the everything
like generative ai, creative analytics,
you should not forget about security.
Security is one of the key factor
where whatever things you're doing,
you need to be under secured.
Otherwise you'll see so much of anomalies
and their data and everything will
go to the other spaces and it'll be.
The world as well.
So that's the reason we
need to consider security.
It's a paramount in financial
services, AI implementation in
corporate advanced, multi-layered
encryption and quantum algorithms
to secure sensitive information.
Institution like Visa have AI
driven cybersecurity protocols,
drastically reducing security breaches
and enduring strict compliance
with the global financial ions.
So we need to make sure if you're
using generative AI or analytics, the
security must be for all the time.
So that means you need to think
about security when you're
thinking about generative aid.
Either it's chat bot or agents,
whatever you are going to use.
To ease the process, you need to
think about security because you're
talking about the individual PI data.
We need to always should be SOX
compliant and then we should make
sure we are under security guidelines,
like how each company is spending
some billions of data and security.
That's where we to make sure our end
users are stakeholders that should be
much more secure and nothing can be
done with them, any of these anomalies.
Okay.
The next one, anti money laning impact.
So maybe right now we are seeing some AI
has notably anti-money Laning AM practices
a power a m Returns now bo, over 83.5.
Catalyst accuracy in threat detection,
identifying social security financial
crimes that previously went unnoticed.
We are, right now, we are seeing so, so
we're seeing so many financial crimes.
But even we don't know what's going to
ha what's going to happen, what happened
previously because of, we don't have a
at the time, but the AI is on board now.
We are seeing 83.5% of the protection
identifying so sophisticated financial
crimes that previously went unnoticed.
Financial institutions such as CD Bank
have significantly reduced false by
65% stimulating complaints, operations,
and improving customer experiences.
Additionally, risk assessments at
major banks have accelerated by two
40% turning lengthy investigation
into efficient rapid response process.
Okay, this, we need to talk about this
A ML anti-money laundering practices.
That's where we know about money
landing, what kind of so many things
we had previously with the ai.
We can get rid of all this money
landing practices because AI is more
powerful and secure if you follow
all the security process with that.
We can see that 83.5% of the reduction
and followed by the identifying the
financial crimes, which previously
completely unnoticed even.
We don't know some financial crimes
are happening because of how much good
there are about all these things, but
with the a for should we can get rid
of all of these things so that the
transactions should be pretty clean and.
All the way we have transparency in the
address between the banks to the customer
B2B, B2C are technical companies, whoever
the companies is going to leverage this.
A entry, money landing practices
that will help them a lot.
And then looking forward
let's go next one.
Okay.
What will be the future
of the banking system?
That's one thing.
Pretty much I'm looking forward.
Okay.
The looking forward is influence will
continue to expand by 2027, maybe nearby,
or it may take much little bit more time,
but A is projected to handle approximately
85% of 14 banking transactions.
For example, Wells Fargo, for instance,
is actively moving forward this future.
Implementing advanced automated
systems to manage routine transactions.
Freeing financial advisors to
focus on personality, financial
planning, and complex customer needs.
So right now, if you go to any of the
bank, you may see multiple people and each
person have that so many responsibilities.
And sometimes you may feel that, okay, why
am these guys are not helping me a lot?
Because they have so many other
things to take care because
they're working for the bank.
The bank will have so much of protocols
they to follow each and every protocol.
Then only they can be secure.
With the help of aa, like routine
banking transactions, like the tele
transactions, the other customer
questions either you can go, we can
send it to aa, like chat bots or agents.
The other way around you can directly
go to the kiosk or directly talk to
the kind of robo, which I'm expecting.
You may see be 20%.
For example, like Wells Fargo is
actively working with the future.
Implementing advanced automated
systems to manage routine transactions.
Freeing the financial advice,
like if you want to go for the
bank, for the loan process, okay.
It should take so much of paperwork,
the initial discussion, everything.
Now the advisor, not only to what you
approve the time he or she can spend
so much of time with you currently,
or personal finance planning, and.
Customer needs, complex customer needs.
The complex customer should be anyone.
If you're trying to do something different
and you want to understand about how the
bank is working on everything, maybe you
might not get the information right now
with the A, with the bots and everything,
but you can get the same information
with the from the in human, which they're
able to focus only on those things.
That is a groundbreaking and
changing for the banking sector,
which we may see by 2027.
That's one thing I'm pretty
much looking forward.
And not only Wells Fargo, which I'm
thinking about the Bank of America,
chase, our key bank, or what are the
bank, you name it, across worldwide.
We have almost more than a hundred
thousand plus banks, which I am
giving you some pretty much gold
some information of contract banks.
But where we have one 90 plus countries,
each country will have different banks
and the common bank, private bank, whoever
they need to follow the guidelines of.
Cary Rules, bank Rules, and with
that all the financial advisor will
have so much of button on them.
So if you're able to automate the routine
task so that they can concentrate mainly
on this advising the end user customers
like you and me will go to the bank.
We'll get all the information, or
if you call them Financial Advisor,
you can take the card, they can
provide you all the information.
Pretty much I'm looking
forward to see, going to help.
Exactly.
And then the same thing
about the risk models.
The risk models issued extraordinary
accuracy, which so many of lms
are going to see in future.
Right now we are pretty less, this means
still companies are working on the lms.
With that, we can get 97% of
enabling fair lending practices.
For example, FinTech companies like
Aman Square use advanced models to
accurately assess clear risk, offering
equitable financial products to
historically deserved populations.
See this?
So what are the transactions?
What are the take an exam?
If I'm going to apply for the
loan, okay, I need to fill
all recommendation by default.
Our banks are tied with
the Affirm are square.
They'll pull all the information off
you and they'll send us to the bank
so that bank can do the, all the ities
and everything with the A immediately.
Right now all Affirm are Square is
leveraging the advanced AI models so
that once they get the information,
they're doing all the checks right
away so that the banks are able to
spend pretty less time on this, in
this, on this application, everything.
The ation making will be much faster.
With this, we can find anomalies or
something or someone is trying to do
some bad things or anything with AI
can pretty much easily so that the
bankers cannot approve the loan or the
persons who are in the pretty genuine
information so that they can get the
loans pretty much easy and even we need
to talk about the, a social benefits
as well, how it is going to help
the V and operational enhancements.
YAYA driven initiatives have actionable
banking service to 1.7 billion
previously unbanked users globally.
Mobile payment platform like AM and Kenya,
which is a one of the country in Africa.
Maybe some part, maybe still into the
old traditional ways there to go with
the advanced technology, but still come.
Some banks are coming back and saying
that, okay, we are going to leverage
ai, which helped them pouring millions
with secure and can banking services.
Okay.
What about the community impact?
So this is one of my sector where we can
see the community, how it's going to help.
The AI has strengthened consumer
protection with advanced fraud detection
systems preventing approximately
15.4 billion in consumer financial
losses, like pay for instance, and
plus AI ActionAlly to in a time
safeguarding millions of ways in ware
from sophisticated digital threats.
If you're talking about the global
financial inclusion where we are
talking about the Kenya Bank, which
they're going to leverage a enable
financial access and pouring with
secure banking services, so we know
about so many people in the operating
don't about the banking and everything.
With this, they can understand
easily how AI going to help
them in their own language.
In their own understable language
so that they can go through each
and everything in the, and they
can listen and they can take ation
instead of going for the middle mass.
And the middleman can
simply take everything.
And if they left okay, that they can
simply, whatever they have, the mobile
or anything, they can go to the bank
and with all these things with the air.
And one more thing about
the small business medium
and business entrepreneurs.
How it's going to help the
small and medium business?
Business success is right now we are
seeing with the a enhancement, we are
seeing 40% of increase loan approval.
Enhancements, like companies like Kaba
or Fund Box utilize a efficiently SME
credit witness supporting academic
growth and innovation in our understand
communities, undeserved communities.
Okay.
That's the thing.
Finally how it is going to
implement effective aid deployment
in must s planning clearly find
objectives, measurable outcomes,
and comprehensive talent and skill.
Government, robust governance and
ethical guide in due responsible use,
continuous monitoring and adaptive
improvements aligned with evolving
regulated frameworks all the time we are
talking about how we can improve the ai.
At the same time, we need to
think about how statistically
it's going to be planned.
Clearly identified objects,
measurable outcomes, and comprehensive
talent and skill development.
These are the things we need to think
about is AI improvement, robust governance
and ethical guidance in general,
responsible use, continuous monitoring,
for sure, how you monitor the all the
services in the cloud infrastructure the
same way we should have wanting about
the A and implement evolving frameworks.
Finally, in conclusion,
what I want to say is.
Strategic a deployment is
fundamentally transforming financial
services, delivering measurable,
ROI miserable, ROI and RI.
Enhancing human roles and positively
impacting communities globally.
A, the parents a unique opportunity,
not mely as a technical advancement,
but as a powerful tool of creating a
fair, more inclusive financial level.
And what if you see the compliance
automation, a motor religion is across
justification, complaints, documentation,
generation, audit, ation, this scanning,
if you see about documentation, we to
spend so much of time previously to
create a document the meaningful way with
the help of a in less than our, I don't
know, not an hour, less than 10 minutes.
We are able to create a document,
which is helping everyone.
Okay.
I'm one of the example where I'm going
to, I'm using it right now with the
a. Previously I need to spend hours
and hours on the documentation to
put everything in a proper order.
Now I'm ING synopsis and everything.
What I want to create a document, the A,
is helping me to create a document so that
I don't need to spend hours and hours,
like every day, like two, three hours.
I need to spend a documentation.
No, I'm spending less
than hour or maybe less.
And that's the way how the document
generation has changed over period of last
two years with the AI audit practitioner.
Previously for the audit, we used
to spend so much of time to putting
all the documents in one place
and go to each every document.
And the boring and worrying and
all the time, okay, yeah, sorry.
We need to document instead of that.
Now with this ai, those
activities much more.
Easier and I can spend much more
time on how I can improve the other
financial systems, how I can help the
other stakeholders and everything.
I can spend some more time
there instead of sending the,
doing the routine activities.
Yep.
Finally, the key measurable impact.
How is going, how ROI, how is the
a going to implement ROI across
multiple financial domains?
S implementation, how,
implementation strategy.
Define clear optics.
Envision talent.
Okay.
How I going to envision the talent?
Like enhancing the human growth
and points impact in community.
And then stablish governance.
Measure RI continuously.
Other.
We need to measure the how.
What is the R way with the
A. That will help a lot.
These are the key takeaways,
which I always benefit.
Measurable impact, strategy,
implementation, human, a
partnership and community benefit.
A implementation, RIA success request
through all the global planning come
from combining a capital expertise,
a transformation beyond ROI to
create a broader social impact.
Finally, thank you.
Thank you for joining this
con particular session.
Let's continue Leveraging yes,
transformative power to shape
a brighter, more equitable
financial future for everyone.
This is what I want to discuss with
you all about this AI implementation
with respect to the financial world.
Hope this helps everyone.
Thank you.