Hello everyone.
My name is Max, and today we're
gonna talk about the aggressive
optimization of large scale language
models in order to make sure that we
can make them work on tiny devices.
So let's start with a few words
about us, me, myself, I'm Max Roski.
I'm senior software engineer VGS.
While my cos speaker today is Alexander
Gev, the professor of software engineer
at Lud National Technical University.
Also shout out to my.
Why that helped me arrange this
beautiful presentation here.
So yeah, my thanks.
Okay, let's start from the challenge.
Why actually do we need optimize those
LLMs for big devices By today's standards
the all new large scale variations
of those models actually require
significant competition resources,
which may result, as you may guessed
in, overlooking the possibility of their
practical deployment of low end resource
constrained devices, which may include.
Field operations, offline systems,
and better device and such.
Our resource goal today is to find out
whether the aggressive model optimization
techniques such as architecture
streaming, pruning quantization, can
enable the LMS to operate efficiently
under the extreme hardware constraints.
So as you may guess, our
demonstration approach will be.
To use practical task in order to
evaluate our optimization strategy.
The task will be, we'll try to
fine tune and use our model to
generate ISO compliant software
requirements basically without it.
Not any product can start properly
and finish not only software.
We thought of it as a great task to
evaluate the, and measure the trade
offs between model compression, resource
consumption, and output stability.
Alright, so before we start optimize
pretty much anything else, we need to
find out which model will suit the best.
Beside of the different alternatives
there, we have been looking on the model
that A is open source B is not already
compressed not already compressed, not
any techniques has been applied to it.
So we need something that is kinda blank
sheet, but already with a small size.
So as you may guess from all the
alternatives we stopped on GPT two.
Why as I mentioned before, it's
open source so we can play around as
much as we want without encountering
licensing or API limitations.
Second is relatively lightweight,
both on parameter size with
117 million parameters.
Oh, and by the role model size,
it's only 500 megabytes which is
not that much as you may guess.
Critically also that we have
been looking for the GP D two.
Is really great at generative
possibilities despite the fact
that it's buzz gen and it had
been released in two 29, 20 19.
It's actually really good at producing
coherent, dramatically sound.
The does aligned outputs, so it's actually
very good, real solid for fine tuning
for speci, specifical demands domains.
And finally as a bonus point, pretty
much it's actually have a transparent
and well-documented architecture,
which allows us, allowed us to dive
deep into finding out the limitations
of those optimization techniques.
So it was actually great.
So to sum up, if we had only one
model to carry with us into forest
on an old laptop, it'll be GPT two.
Let's start with the plan.
So it'll be really simple one.
First of all, we'll go.
We are going to cover up the theory, then
the practical results and conclusion.
So let's start with theory.
First of all, we are going to look for.
It's a student model concept.
The core idea basically student model
is a instance of the basic model
by, but the difference that you can
play around as much as you want.
So basically you can screw it up.
Maybe you will need to redo the things,
but it won't affect the original.
So consider this something like a clone,
but you can work with as much as you want.
So yeah, that's pretty much it.
Metrics by which we are
going to measure the success.
It's four of them.
First of all, perplexity, the
model accuracy, whether can
it output things correctly.
CPU memory usage, as you may guess, it
will be really critical for measuring
success for like of performance
on low resource, low end devices.
Inter interference speed, faster
response time, pretty straightforward
and model size basically.
The smaller, the better general
pattern here, as you noticed is
the smaller better, the smaller
faster equals better usually.
Let's start with defining what
we actually define as aggressive
methods and non-aggressive methods.
Let's start with non aggressive
methods, because there are really
only one that we can specify
today is a knowledge distillation.
Is the technique when student mimics
teacher tissue model closely, like without
any changes at all to architecture.
While aggressive methods, as you
may guess, is those methods there
will interfere with model like
architecture layers, count and stuff.
So there are three of them.
Architecture, treatment they will
have, like this technique is all
around reducing layers in neuro count.
Pruning, remove less important
parameters in weights and ization.
Basically changing the AC accuracy
of the weights from like fourth
float 42 into integer eight.
Standard.
Okay, cool.
So let's start with covering up the
basics of the each optimization technique.
So with architecture, treatment,
the main concept here, if it's
too big, just make it smaller.
So I would say, you should imagine
this, our model as a building.
So like every floor and room can be
considered as layer and neurons here.
And pretty much we just, in
those technique, we just remove
unnecessary layers and neurons.
That's it.
With layers, we, when we remove
layers, we just reduce the number
of protesting stages in the model.
While with neurons, we decrease the number
of computational euros per layer, right?
So also we have a glossary
on the bottom of the slides.
So feel free to pause the window
and check it out, like the better
definition of layer in euro.
So that's pretty much it.
Pruning.
If it's not important, just cut it off.
I think we can imagine for this
purpose, we can imagine a model like
a tree when every branch is connection
between neurons and even each branch has
leaves, which is parameters and weights.
So with pruning, we can actually
decide which weights we can
disable and just not use it all.
Interesting thing here that while
we disabling and turning off some
parameters and weights, it also can.
Like indirectly affect the neurons because
when you delete and turn off some of the
neurons some of the weights in parameters,
it may just turn off some neurons.
So it's really interesting here and here.
Quantization.
Basically the main concept here is you
may see heat precision isn't critical.
We do not need use heavy tools.
Basically speaking we are turning off.
Like changing the basic float 32
standard and like into integer eight.
So it will be less, our model
will be less precise, but it'll
be great in like CPU performance
and much more easier to work with.
Yeah.
So we just make sure that our
weights are, turned, turned
into smaller, lightweight ones.
Those effects, as you may see
on the graph, it affects only
weights and parameters here.
And for the non-aggressive
optimization methods here
distillation can be considered as a
mutation of the teacher model here.
So it's the student that copies
from the experienced teacher.
Very important note here.
This thing, this method is non
aggressive because it does not
interfere with model architecture.
Therefore, we do not need to be worried
about performance de degradation here.
Good.
Also the most important know that
we want to live here is that.
Distillation is really, will work on it.
It'll work good if only the
student model has not anything
changed in the architecture.
So the, both the student model and teacher
one should be pretty much the same.
And here, as you may see in the
graph it's not affecting anything
in the architecture, but it
just learns the outputs and the
weights from the tissue once.
So it's all in once.
Okay, cool.
So as you, we noticed those three
aggressive methods, architecture,
dreaming, proving quantization
are playing with models,
architecture in different way.
One in, for instance, for
archite architecture dreaming.
We just remove some of the layers
while pruning, for instance, just
remove not layers, but weights.
And quantization just reducing
the accuracy of those weights
but not removing them.
So they're really the
same, but in different way.
Alright, so yeah, that's the
summary for you if you want to
pass out video and check it out.
So let's start with part
two, practical research.
As you may guessed, we already
have an order of experiments here.
So first of all we will our, like this
part will switch in several steps.
First one, we are gonna fine tune our
model because without fine tuning,
it does not make much many sense.
And therefore we'll continue with
architecture, treatment, distillation,
pruning, quantization, and then
we're gonna combine those methods.
We are gonna explain later why we do
this methods in this specific order.
So let's start.
But before we start, we need
to get the basic benchmark of
training the base role, DPT two.
So it's pre-trained.
Non-specialized and it'll struggle with
any task specific like structure there.
Those, some metrics on the left that we
specify before, perplexity usage, memory
usage, inference, speed, and model size.
And therefore they are prompt results.
So you can see like visually what is
going on, as you may see on the output.
It's not hallucinating, I would
say, but it's not that semantically.
Correct.
Which may result in, the possibility
and the requirement of actually fine
tuning our model to do specific tasks
like iso requirements generation.
Okay.
I think the first step after comparing
with the role GPT two we need to
fine tune the model basically.
I'm sorry.
Basically this model will, there
will no optimization applied first.
Our model is fine tuned towards ISO
compliance software requirements
that I set and it'll useful
GPTT architecture and it'll the
reference point for our comparisons.
As you may see, after we fine tune
it to our, to to our specific task,
the output is much more better.
So that's I would say reference point.
Yeah.
So with fine tune, with fine tuning
model, everything got better there.
Only perplexity got a little bit worse.
I would say perplexity value starting
from one up to one and five are really
solid, and we'll provide you the quality
of the model that we're, that you will
see that is good visually at least.
Okay, so let's start with the first step.
I think the most mandatory
one, architecture dreaming.
In our practical research, we remote,
we removed half of the GPT two layers.
And reduce hidden size.
Basically, we shifted from 12 layers
to six from like 768 dimensions
to 384, which means same inputs,
but just lighter architecture
and fighter and faster execution.
You may also ask about how did
we pick which layers to trim?
The strategy there was
actually really simple one.
We just removed layers
symmetrically from center.
Which allows us to preserve bottom
layers that are responsible for basic
syntax and token level understanding.
And also we preserve top layers, which
are for higher level structure, for
context, you know what I'm saying?
Basically speaking, this allow
allowed us to maintain both low level
and high level processing there.
Awesome.
So let's compare the performance here.
As you may see, perplexity
gone a little bit worse.
Because like it's gone.
Not that accurate, but as you may see,
the output to the prompt is really solid.
It's pretty much the same.
It hasn't changed.
But here we also notice here that
the memory usage actually increased.
Why?
When we.
We reduce our CP usage.
Somebody has to pay and
this somebody is wrong.
Basically speaking.
We with optimizations like quantization
layer treatment, we reduce processing
time, but they will compensate in tensor
sizes, caching, parallel processing,
which will increase their wrong memory.
Why this matters.
CPU time equals the energy cost
on battery powered by the devices.
And most of the time CPU U
is the biggest power draw.
While RO is something that we
can neglect and it's generally
more available, but not limited.
So it's actually, we consider
it as a cheap to access.
But a little bit limited on the
old laptops and microcontrollers,
which is, in our use case.
It's not that problematic as we more lean
towards providing the proper experience
with CPU in order to make sure that
they can work on embedded devices.
Yeah, so in this graph, it's pretty
much the summary of all the things
that we talked before with the graphs.
As you as you may see on the x. Axis we
have starting from the Rob GT two and at
the end you will, we will compare also
combine sensors there, the RAM users
there changed by almost 200 megabytes.
Not that big, but something
that we have to consider on.
Okay, let's continue.
You may also ask, but why
don't we apply distillation
and therefore it's break point.
The thing is that we student
modeled it's trained.
In this process, the student model trained
to mimic, make a bigger teacher model.
But after we chopped hard, the
student model it just too small
to understand the teacher.
It means that student just can does not
have enough layers to understand teacher
outputs, which means that our student
model will try to compensate it and it'll
result in hallucinations and repetitions.
Yeah, this graph pretty much
basically represents the effect that
we are trying to represent here.
While at some point, student model
will just stop, basically understand
what model tries to learn and to teach.
So it'll do the only thing it's possible
to do with architecture when LLMs.
Hallucination and repetition.
As we mentioned before.
As a result, we finishing critical
failure point and here there's
nothing we can do with distillation
and we need to drop it off.
Yeah.
As you may see with a performance
snapshot for distillation, the
output is straight up non-usable
with propensity well is for it's.
As you may see by output, it's not usable.
So yeah, we just skip it all together.
That's why it's called non
aggressive, as you may see.
As a quick conclusion here, non
aggressive methods are not working
right with aggressive ones.
Okay?
Yeah.
So let's continue with pruning.
With pruning.
As we mentioned before, the theoretical
part, really more parameters
that have low or no contribution.
How do we choose those weights?
We just rank all weights by
getting their absolute value,
then just remove the one one.
Yeah, it's pretty much simple.
It's not that hard.
We just muting the quietest voices
in the nose, noisy room, and why it's
working, because many weights are
in large, more are close to zero,
which allows them to balance out.
Some like context and for the larger
models, it'll be really great in
order to have general context.
But in our use case, the le less memory,
faster competition, but only slightly.
Yeah, from the benchmark here,
perplexity here is pretty much the
same as for architecture training.
But the memory, use it really hard.
Like going really like big, I would
say as you may see it sometimes it
hallucinates and just does not do
anything, but no worries will get better
results after we combine those methods.
Quantization quantization, as we said
before in theoretical part, when we
convert them, model weights, accuracy from
flow through the two into enter eight.
We make sure, like we don't
delete anything but just make the
model a little bit less precise.
So here we'll get a huge benefit
of less CPU load and basically
no work actual changes needed.
So pretty much no performance
degradation there.
Okay, so when we go to performance,
you will see that the memory
usage there is pretty much
almost non didn't change at all.
While the model size is produced
drastically with the CPU usage at 12%,
12 and a half percent, while basic
RGBT model will occupy like 45% of your
like low end device, which is huge.
And you'll see, and you'll see you later
see by, see it by yourself, by at the end
of the talk while we get the conclusion.
So we are coming up to the combined
optimization here and, in those
optimization methods, we are combining
treatment, pruning and quantization.
So at the end, we'll have fine tuned
model, fine tuned, GPT model for one,
task, three model to six layers, prune 40%
of smaller weights, and we'll quantize.
Two in eight from flow through
the two for CPU Efficiency.
As as you may see, we don't use
distillation at all because it just
does not stack neither work with
aggressive methods combined about in
this case, there are no methods that
will allow distillation work with
aggressive methods as architecture.
Defense is too drastic.
Okay, so with the performance snapshot
of our best combined methods here,
perplexity changed by really little bit.
While CPU usage there got almost
twice as small while memory usage,
as you may see, is almost like 200
megabytes higher with inference
speed really perfect, almost newer.
Perfect, I would say.
And the model size shrunk into like
almost five times of the original.
Yeah, it's really perfect.
One.
So let's see how it's gonna
represent in different metrics.
So we'll we can see here by using
the company combined optimization
methods those, our students, our
student model will reduce CPU load by
almost a half compared to row G PT two
which makes it significantly more
suitable for battery powered CPU only
devices where energy is critical.
Basically it means less CPU, faster
response times, lower energy costs,
everyone's happy memory usage.
As you may see, the change there is
not that big, but it's a kind of trade
off that we pay for lower CPU costs.
It's acceptable, especially in Muslim
low end laptops and body boards.
But this, there is the thing that we
should consider of a memory usage.
This is the thing that pays
off for the all optimizations.
Perplexity actually remained the same.
So we were really happy with the results.
So it means at the end we can conclude
that the optimization, the combining
optimization techniques are not equal
degradation if fine tuning done right,
model size as you may see it shrink
almost in five times of the original,
basically smaller model, same brain.
We are going to part three conclusions.
So you might also thought if their
methods are so good, why should
we like not always use them?
It me, like basically we omitted
the fact that it's work perfectly
only on fine tuned models.
So actually why fine tuning map
like fine tuning technique matters.
Fine tuning aligns the model
to a single atomic task.
Therefore, that specific focus make the
model resistant to aggressive compression
While out of the box models are kinda
generalist and they're like not good in
anything else, like jack of all trades.
And they basically, they're trying to
do everything and they will be really
fragile towards like applying any of them.
Yeah.
So with the League of Mind,
Alexandra, we defined definition
of Reist model resistance.
It means that it defines how well
model maintains output quality
after aggressive compression.
So by high resistance, we define
fine tuned models for one clear
task, which means strong internal
signal, the translation to low
dependency on full architecture.
When quality drops really slowly, even
heavy pruning on quantization and for
the lower resistance, we define this
and the, as the general purpose model
that has like many overlapping skills
and even the smallest optimization there
would result into breaking the visual
results and the performance metrics.
Also, we have a graph to we also
applied the same methods to the raw
G PT two, and the results were not.
Usable at all.
So as you may see for the fine
tuned models it's almost changed
like it hasn't changed at all.
While for BT two it
changed really drastically.
So as you may see, the re resistance
team here is really important.
So fine tuning models here
is really important by as
treatment stable perplexity.
Almost grow slowly or not growing at
all while general purpose models break
fast and perpetuate their skyrockets.
So it's, it is great.
While fine tuning mon, like fine
tuning models allows us to focus on
the single task which is kinda reducing
general noise and general models
in the controversy are too broad.
Even small cuts will disrupt everything.
So basically speaking optimizations.
Combining the optimization
methods work best, but the model
knows what it's supposed to do.
Yeah.
Without fine tuning, pruning will
break meaning of general model.
Quantization will introduce
noise, which also affect the
visual represe of the output.
And trimming also deletes
the clear within the path.
So at the end with fine tuning,
everything stays coherent even.
And 75% of compression as you
may see, basically fine tuning
isn't a just an extra step.
It's what makes optimization possible.
So yeah, that's pretty much finishing
slide with the final takeaways.
First of all, fine tuning
is the true enabler.
It makes compression possible
without the collapse of the model
while we apply those techniques.
Architecture driven reduces,
depths and size brilliant
remotes, low impact weights.
Quantization boosts CPU Efficiency
while distillation fails when applied
to aggressively minimize students.
Resistance here is a key.
Fine tune models resist degradation,
far better than general models.
So basically speaking, we didn't
just shrink a model, we built
a focused, efficient specialist
and fine tuning may possible.
Thank you very much.
It was my pleasure.
Great pleasure to provide a talk here.
Thank you.
Have a nice day.