Speaker 35: Hello everybody.
My name is Tim, and today I'm gonna talk
about AI driven engineering quality.
So a little bit about myself.
I'm working in the IT
industry for over five years.
I've been building
games most of my career.
For the first three years I worked as
a software engineer and I worked on
apps that have over 10 million users.
And for the past two years I switched
to product management and I worked on
an app that has over 800,000 users.
And on average the apps that I
shipped, they have 200,000 plus users.
The problem I've been facing for my whole
career is the wrong time estimation of,
the delivery time, how long it's gonna
take the feature for the engineering
team to build and put into production.
About half a year ago I am I realized
that AI is good enough to estimate
the time and I decided to work
on the implementation of AI into.
Discovery and engineering workflows.
So the solution that I've built internally
in the company I work at is a predictive
pipeline that estimates delivery time.
So before the coding is done, the
discovery team come to meet a delivery
team and they can discuss the time it is
gonna take for the feature to be coded
and delivered, put into production.
So before we could only use engineers
knowledge to estimate it and also the.
Past Jira sprints to
correct their estimation.
But now we can use AI to estimate
these discovery documents.
And also this tools helps developers
because when developer commits something
the AI gives feedback on every commit
and every PR and, if engineers find the
information useful, he doesn't have to
wait for the review by another engineer.
He can just work on the AI review and
make changes to the code and commit again.
So the architecture is the first
step is feature extraction.
The we provide the Git history and to.
AI model that then analyzes this.
And also it uses rug retrieval
to see the past work.
And if it can relate the new feature
to one of the previous features,
then the estimation is gonna be
better than LLM analysis step where.
It reasons about complexity, risk
factors, and then it outputs the
the key findings that are the time
estimation with confidence, risk
scores, and actionable recommendations.
For this demo, I built, the pipeline from
scratch and it's not production ready.
So if you want to use this tool
that I'm talking about you can't put
it into production straight away.
You'll have to build on it.
To make it production ready.
I didn't use the tool that we use in
the company and also the repository.
I've participated in hackathon
two months ago and I decided to
take this hackathon repository as
an example to deliver this demo.
The project I worked on it.
It is made out of three different
repositories, the backend, the
front end, and the smart contract.
It's what was a Web3 hackathon?
Study code analysis the first step
AI gives us the number of files,
lines of code, complexity and risk
score of each of these repositories.
So the backend is an SJS and
Postgres, and it has a good
architecture and risk is very low.
The front end I use coco game Engine
and and, in this environment you have
to manually connect UI to scripts
and do something on the scene.
And AI is not very good
at understanding that.
So this the risk is higher.
For example, if I use React as a front
end, then it would be 15, 20 points lower,
probably if the code was written in like
with a good architecture and et cetera.
So the next step is when Discovery
team comes to you and asks you how long
it's gonna take to build this feature.
So instead of talking to developers
and going to meetings the product
manager, like marketing product
manager, can use this tool.
And they just write down the task they
want, like the what, the feature that
they want the delivery team to deliver.
And then AI find similar past work and
analyzes it and gives like the estimation,
estimated time, then complexity.
So moderate complexity because
it involves backend front end.
And also it's advise here the
query optimization, then the risk.
It's not a high risk.
Then this rack for retrieval for
previous features that are somewhat
similar and some recommendations.
So that's the first part of it.
Now we're moving on to the
second part is the code review.
For example, like this,
commit with NFT service.
Not gonna go through the code again
at the end of the presentation.
I have links.
You can have a look at it.
But yeah, it's not very well written.
I used actually some AI to write it,
and now AI is running the analysis.
It reviews the code.
And here is, here are the insights.
So risk score is high, and quality
is low, changes are needed.
Here is the summary.
We have critical security
issues and lots of warnings.
So in production, if AI score is higher
than 50% or quality is lower than 50%,
then the team leads, they get notification
and also the stakeholders, they know
about it and they're gonna ask about
it during the demo of the feature.
So engineer is likely go and work
more on this feature but maybe
0.1% of the time around like
that certainty AI gets something.
Wrong.
And if engineer actually proves that
AI made a mistake, then can go on
with the feature and just ignore ai,
then we'll have to fine tune the ai.
So it does make this mistake again
but it is 100% worth it because 99.9%
of the time, AI gets things right.
And after we train it more and
more, it gets even better accuracy.
So this is pretty accurate.
Let's go on to the next example.
So here is the bed code example.
I'm just gonna run it for AI to analyze
and meanwhile we can have a look.
It has like secret, key exposed hardcoded.
Then.
No input, validation, then
like command injection.
Both bypass, so lots of
issues with this code.
And yeah AI runs the
analysis and say 100% risk.
It's unsafe for production.
It's very low quality changes
needed, obviously critical warnings.
Security.
Yeah.
So if you get this code into
production, it's gonna be a nightmare.
Yeah.
Also we can, as I mentioned before, we
can compare the AI estimations to actual
time it took to deliver the feature.
So it's in this demo, it's simple.
It filters the eight hour gaps.
So during the nighttime when
developer was sleeping, it kind of
filters these gaps and then counts
everything else as the working time.
And based on.
This and based on like comments
and when the feature, when the
work on the feature was stopped, it
can give pretty accurate estimate.
And as you can see, it
gets everything right.
Apart from backend setup.
Yeah.
But because it was done with the
help of ai, it went much faster.
So to summarize what we built we built ai.
We built a tool that uses AI to
extract features from Git history.
Then it can analyze the code.
It uses rack to retrieve the.
Previous features and compare
them to the new feature.
It uses estimation LLM, powered
Estimation and Code Review
detects code vulnerability.
And yeah, that's about it.
In terms of results, when the
team started using this tool.
We got delivery estimates
up to 80% from 60%.
So that's a lot.
And we can catch security issues
before merge and PMs can prioritize
tasks themself without doing long
meetings with delivery teams.
Also it helps engineers to work because
they can see something that AI advises
that's probably they didn't think about.
And it saves time of other
engineers who have to review this
code because in general, prs they.
Became much better after
this tool was used.
And in terms of tech Stack, we, for
this demo use Python Fast, API, chroma
DB and Cloud API, and we use pretty
much the same thing in production.
Yeah, it's just the code quality and
security is better in our production
than in this demo, but the basis are.
The same.
So thank you very much.
Here you can see GitHub
repository of this demo.
You can run it with git clone, just copy
and paste this inside your terminal.
But also you'll have to use the
cloud API key or open rotor, API key.
Otherwise the LLM is not gonna work.
Thank you so much for your time.
I hope it was useful.
Bye.