Speaker: Hi everyone.
Welcome to my session, minimum
Viable, A IMS ISO 42 0 0 1 Required
Documentation Artifacts for beginners.
And thank you to the com 42
organizers for having me here today.
I'm really glad to be part
of this lops focused edition.
My session is built around how I saw IC 42
0 0 1 is actually implemented and audited,
not just how it's written in the standard.
On whether an artificial intelligence
management system truly exists in practice
and whether that can be proved with
quality evidence Today, when you hear
me say minimum viable, A IMS know I'm
talking about the minimum set of required
documentation artifacts let auditors
expect to review, to conclude that an
organization is managing AI systems
in a controlled and repeatable way.
This is not about creating the
perfect documentation, it's about
creating clarity around business risk,
ownership change, and accountability,
meaning auditable clarity.
So AI systems can scale without
crumbling as individuals change.
And that's what I'll
walk you through today.
So let's get started.
A bit of context on why I'm talking on
this topic from this particular angle.
So my background is a combination
of hands-on security, engineering,
and formal audit training.
I spent over 10 years across various
engineering roles, including system and
solution engineering, multi-cloud, and
securing containerized environments.
Along the way, I worked extensively
with vulnerability management, threat
detection, monitoring, incident
response, and what's most relevant
for us today here, compliance.
Over time, a large part of my security
engineering role has involved supporting
internal and external audits, preparing
reports, gathering evidence, and
coordinating improvement efforts for
management, self-assessment of controls,
as well as I saw and SOC two audits.
From a security engineering
perspective, there's also very
practical connection to lops.
For example, the Cloud Security Alliance
outlines key stakeholders across the ML
ops lifecycle, and security engineers
are explicitly named as one of them.
Among others.
We're expected to plan and act on threat
modeling, data protection, access control,
and incident response For ML systems,
I'm also trained as an ISO 2 7 0 0 1.
And I saw 42 0 0 1 lead auditor
through Mastermind Assurance and I'm a
certified information systems auditor.
CSA exam Passer through.
I worked with GRC platforms
like to operationalize auditor
evidence as well as with Microsoft
Purview data protection solution.
Outside of day-to-day work, I'm
nowadays active in the community
as an AWS community builder.
A woman in cybersecurity business
mentor and hack the box meetup host.
I also enjoy publishing blog
posts and practical walkthroughs
on my YouTube channel, which is
the large image on this slide.
So ultimately, this talk comes
directly from the intersection
of all of this making systems
operable, defensible, and auditable.
I'm here as someone who's had to make
governance work in practice without
unnecessarily slowing teams down,
while focusing on prevention, early
detection, and using tactical pauses to
reassess and stabilize so the business
comes out stronger and more resilient.
And that's the mindset I bring today.
Now let's briefly level set on
what an artificial intelligence
management system A IMS actually is.
And what I saw, IC 42 0
0 1 brings to the table.
I saw IC 42 0 0 1.
Moving forward, I short it to, I saw
42 0 0 1 is a voluntary certifiable
international standard, published in 2023.
And it's the first one focused
specifically on managing AI systems
at the organizational level.
It doesn't prescribe models or tooling.
Instead, it shifts the focus
away from individual models and
toward how AI systems are owned,
monitored, and improved over time.
It takes an organizational view
of AI focusing on how systems are
governed across their life cycle
from experimentation and deployment
to use monitoring and continuous
improvement Structurally, ISO 42 0
0 1 contains 10 clauses in total.
This clauses four through 10
defining the auditable requirements.
The documentation artifacts I'll
walk through are derived from the
auditable clauses four through 10,
and all clauses are supported by
NXA, which outlines 38 controls
total across nine control objectives.
Importantly, not all controls are
mandatory organizations select
applicable controls based on their
risk profile, scope and context.
Standard follows the plan, do check ACT
PDCA cycle, which means it's designed to
mesh well with other management system
standards, especially is O 27 0 0 1.
Information Security Management System.
ISMS.
Auditors are not looking for
perfection or automation everywhere.
They're looking for consistency,
intent, and evidence that controls
are applied relative to risk.
ASSO standards commonly describe
maturity, progressing from incomplete
to performed, managed, established,
predictable, and eventually optimized.
The goal is not to jump to the highest
level immediately, but to demonstrate
controlled progress over time.
ASSO 42 0 0 1 also serves as
a standalone within a broader
ecosystem of AI focused standards.
For example, supporting standard ISO
2 2 9 8 9 defines AI terminology and
roles such as providers, developers,
and suppliers, which is why ISO
4 2 0 0 1 is relevant even if you
consume ai, rather than building it
and supporting standard ISO 42 0 0 5
addresses AI system impact assessments.
From a certification
perspective, what it follow?
A clear chain international
accreditation forum.
Two accreditation bodies,
two certification bodies,
two oddity organizations.
So I have two abs to CCBs, to Oddity.
On I have searched search
the global database for
accredited ISO certifications.
You can look up whether an organization
certificate is still valid.
Certification typically involves passing
a stage one documentation readiness audit.
Out by stage two, control effectiveness
audit, and then maintaining and
improving the system through
annual surveillance audits within
a three year certification cycle.
Finally, I saw 42 0 0 1 exists alongside
other major AI governance frameworks
to highlight a few USA's NIST AI Risk
Management framework, which provides
voluntary guidance but is not certifiable.
Use AI Act introduces mandatory legal
applications for certain AI systems,
and I saw 42 0 0 1 here serves
organizations globally to proactively
and voluntarily demonstrate AI readiness
through independent verification.
And this is increasingly relevant
because people are experimenting
with ML and AI everywhere.
While intentioned enthusiasts can
unintentionally create shadow AI
using corporate data on corporate
devices, ISO 42 0 0 1 provides a
structured way to bring that activity
back into visibility and control.
One final note here.
For copyright reasons, I'm not displaying
the standard itself as it must be
purchased from the official ISO store.
Instead, I'll focus on explaining why the
required documentation artifacts exist and
how they connect to real world challenges
and why these matters right now.
Recent industry data
shows a clear pattern.
A majority of organizations that
experienced breaches either don't
have an AI policy at all or are
still in the process of defining one.
Even among the organizations that do have
policies, only a small fraction regularly
audit for and sanctioned or shadow
AI use and the impact is measurable.
One in five organizations has
reported a bridge linked to shadow ai.
And when these kinds of incidents
happen, the damage can be larger.
Incident involving shadow AI tend
to explore more sensitive data and
intellectual property, and they
come with significantly higher
remediation and reputation costs
and traditional security incidents.
At the same time, we're seeing a
rise in public cases related to
unfair or discriminatory AI outcomes.
The AI discrimination case tracker,
those legal cases where AI systems
are relevant to discrimination bias,
or equality issues, particularly in
areas like hiring credit decisioning,
and even arrests caused by inaccurate
facial recognition systems.
These cases rarely come down
to a single bad line of code.
Instead, they expose gaps in
oversight testing, monitoring, and
accountability across the AI lifecycle.
This is one of the key problems I saw.
42 0 0 1 is designed to address.
It doesn't exist to slow innovation
or block experimentation,
and it doesn't guarantee that
incidents can't and won't happen.
What it does provide is operational
clarity that strategically prioritizes the
response when things go wrong and gives
stakeholders confidence that AI systems
are being managed maturely over time, that
translates into more efficient operations
and stronger trust from customers.
So 42 0 0 1 focuses on how organizations
govern and respond to AI risks in
practice, and it also works alongside
technical frameworks like OS Machine
Learning Security Top 10 and MI Atlas,
which help teams understand what can
go wrong at the technical level, such
as data poisoning, input manipulation,
and AI ML supply chain attacks.
And there is an upside
beyond the risk reduction.
Organizations that implement structured
AI governance report tangible benefits.
The so 42 0 0 1 batch on product
marketing pages draws attention,
increases credibility in the eyes of
prospects, shortens pre-sales and due
diligence questionnaires, and help
move conversations toward monetary
investment quicker, as an example.
Several AI powered services you
may likely use today operate within
certified management Systems.
As an AWS Community builder, I would
highlight ISO 42 0 0 1 certified business
units behind services like Amazon
Tech Extract, which is ML service that
extracts data from scanned documents.
Then Amazon transcribe for speech to text.
Amazon Bedrock for building gen AI
applications and Amazon Q Business
as an enterprise AI assistant.
As a small site quest, you can access this
ISO certificate through pre-service a WS
artifact, grab the certification number
and then verify yourself on IF search.
It takes just a couple of
minutes, and it's a great way to
see how this works in practice.
Feel free to reach out to me on LinkedIn
afterward and tell me how it went.
I'm genuinely curious
who actually tries it.
Ultimately, the longstanding
case for standardization still
applies to AI management systems.
As AI systems scale, the cost of
not knowing, not measuring and
not improving grows faster than
the cost of practic planning and
putting the right controls in place.
Now zooming into the artifacts in lead
auditor training, the requirements
of ISO 42 0 0 1 are often distilled
into required activities and
required documentation artifacts.
Today I'm focusing on the documentation
side, and you can think of these
16 items on this slide as 16 points
where clarity is required across the
auditable clauses four through 10, four.
Context of the organization,
plus five focused on leadership,
plus six on planning.
Seven, support eight operations, nine on
performance evaluation, and 10 focused on
improvement or C-L-P-O-P as an acronym.
So context leadership planning,
support operations, performance
evaluation improvement, CLP.
So P. Each one exists because without it,
something important tends to fall apart.
As I go through them, I want to
show full documents today since
they can get quite lengthy.
Instead, I'll highlight their significance
from an audit perspective and connect
each one to the real world problems.
Teams run into one AI
ms. Scope, clause 4.3.
Defining scope answers
are very simple questions.
What exactly are we going?
This artifact exists for one reason
to make sure everyone understands
which AI systems are governed,
which are not, who is responsible
before something goes wrong.
This artifact depends heavily
on two things, organizational
context and AI use cases.
This specific organization identified
without a dose scope becomes guesswork.
In ML Ops, this problem usually appears
the moment experimentation gets popular.
A model starts as an notebook, someone
connects it to a pipeline, and suddenly
it's influencing final workflows
before anyone has defined whether
it belongs inside governance or not.
Very public example of this kind of
situation involves engineers based
proprietary material into unmanaged
AI tools of their personal choice.
During daily work, rarely, let's
say there is malicious intent.
Often it's just an attempt to speed
up repetitive tasks or analyze
large spreadsheets with AI so it
doesn't look like an tech at all.
Organizations need to clearly
define which AI tools are
approved for corporate workflows.
What data can be used
where experimentation,
ads and production begins?
And what happens when acceptable
use rules aren't followed?
'cause without that clarity,
governance only exists on paper.
Very often individual unmanaged AI
accounts come with default data control
settings that allow user content to be
used for model improvement, sometimes
phrased as improve the model for everyone.
These settings may not align with
corporate governance expectations
if they're used on business
devices or with company data.
That's why many organizations
prefer centrally managed enterprise
plans or tools like Chat, GPT,
copilot, cloud, and others.
These enterprise plans typically
include stronger governance features,
role-based access, audit logging,
custom data retention policies.
Content safety, guardrails and
centralized administration, making it
much easier to align with corporate
security and regulatory requirements
without a clearly defined scope.
Teams naturally drift toward
whichever tool feels most
convenient, even if it's default.
Governance model doesn't
match organizational goals.
In many companies, acceptable
use guidelines, even recommend
avoiding unmanaged personal
accounts on corporate equipment.
So it's always worth checking with
internal points of contact before
self choosing an AI tool for work.
We've also seen real infrastructure
issues where lab environments were exposed
externally or experimental tooling and
adapt reachable from production networks.
These weren't sophisticated AI attacks.
They were ordinary infrastructure
mistakes applied to very powerful systems.
This configuration exposure drift and
unowned pipelines are still more common
than advanced adversarial techniques.
From an audit perspective, this is
exactly where the scope artifact helps.
Speed forces explicit scoping of
which ML tools may run in production,
and which environments require
authentication, logging and approvals.
Exposures involving platforms like Jupyter
Cube Flow or ML Flow are still common.
And sometimes a CV appears where
everyone internally says, oh,
this clearly wasn't checked.
I can see how this was
supposed to stay in the lab.
Clear scope of boundaries help
prevent these situations from
quietly reaching production.
Defining an AI policy Sounds abstract
at first, but in practice it can
answer a very close to home question,
what approach and what high level
rules does this specific business
support when working with AI systems
without a clear policy, every team
ends up inventing its own workflow.
One team retrains weekly.
Another deploys directly from
notebooks, and someone else exposes
an endpoint with default settings
because nothing explicitly said not to.
From a governance perspective, this
inconsistency becomes risk very quickly.
This artifact depends heavily on
demonstrated leadership commitment
and organizational strategy.
The policy is commonly approved
by executive management because
it defines the organization's
stance on the responsible AI and
how risk is handled at scale.
We see stricter AI policies
frequently introduced just after
incidents involving sensitive data
exposure or regulatory pressure.
The technology itself is
really the sole issue.
Gaps in governance, oversight and
communication are often at the center.
Policy helps establish shared
expectations across teams and
demonstrates accountability, which
regulators increasingly expect,
especially on their frameworks like GDPR,
focusing on personal data protection.
From an MOPS perspective, this artifact
actually makes engineering easier.
It can give you the authority to
say, these tools are approved here.
These defaults are forbidden, and these
models require additional approvals.
Engineers already know insecure
defaults are dangerous, but without
policy backing, they often lack
the mandate to enforce changes.
We are now in clause six, planning,
CLPP planning more precisely.
Clause 6 1 1.
Planning for risks and opportunities.
The question here is what actions will we
take once we know specific A risks exist?
We know this pattern.
Risks get discussed, even documented,
but nothing changes operationally.
Nothing changes.
If nothing changes, nothing turns
into backlog, work on the board
or real controls because nobody
translated them into engineering tasks.
This artifact exists to drive that
planning and translation into action.
Each risk or opportunity must have
an owner, a decision, and a concrete
next step, such as implementing bias
reviews or developing a resource plan
to address insufficient resources
for A IMS activities In practice,
this enables proactive risk handling
and demonstrates that risks are
acted upon, not just identified.
Before teams can control AI risks,
they need a governance structure that
actually works across leadership support,
resources, training, and clear ownership.
And this document tracks
planning for exactly that.
It also reminds us that governance
isn't only about preventing problems.
Organizations use this artifact
to pursue opportunities as well.
Plans for improving reputation,
accelerating market entry, or reducing
client led queries and questionnaires
by demonstrating mature AI governance.
But just through is O 42 0 0 1
6 1 2 a risk assessment process.
Risk assessment in ISO 42 0 0 1 is
fundamental for identifying and evaluating
risks associated with AI systems.
These risks may include harm
to individuals, bias, lack of
transparency, safety issues,
misuse, or unintended public impact.
The assessment allows the
organization to prioritize risks
based on likelihood and impact.
Results of risk assessments directly
inform risk treatment decisions,
and the selection of NXA controls.
Without a proper risk assessment,
the effectiveness of the A
IMS cannot be demonstrated.
But this artifact answers is simple.
How do we evaluate AI risk consistently
before models move forward?
This process depends on two foundations,
a clearly defined scope and agreed
methodology for risk criteria.
Without those risk decisions
easily become subjective.
One team treats a model
change as a low risk.
Another blocks deployment entirely,
and suddenly governance feels
inconsistent rather than helpful.
A repeatable risk assessment
process changes that it introduces
a common language impact.
Likelihood stakeholder review.
Some model updates are evaluated
using the same logic across pipelines.
The purpose here isn't to
predict every possible outcome.
A risks evolve as models are retrained,
reused, or deployed in new contexts.
What auditors want to see the structured
way to evaluate risk before promotion, not
only after an initial reaches production.
This becomes even more important because
model artifacts aren't just data.
They behave like executable components,
serialization formats, dependencies, and
retraining workflows introduce risks that
traditional teams might overlook when
teams treat promotion as just another
commit vulnerabilities, language toxicity,
and bias can slip through unnoticed.
6 1 3 artifact covers AI risk treatment
and statement of applicability.
What you're seeing on the right is a small
example from an SOA specifically control A
55, which looks at societal impact of ai.
And when people hear that phrase
societal impact, it could sound
abstract, but in practice it
becomes very concrete, very quickly.
First, it implies an environmental impact.
Modern models don't
just live in notebooks.
They run on infrastructure,
consume energy, and create
a real carbon footprint.
Organizations are starting to
track that lifecycle impact,
especially as going green.
Sustainability, environmental,
social, and governance.
ESG, regulations and reporting.
Standard expectations evolve.
Second implied economic impact.
This isn't only about the job
displacement, it's also about who
gains access to new tools, who gets
included, who excluded, and how
organizations support reskilling or
responsible automation decisions.
Third, governance and recourse.
A system makes a decision.
Can it be truly understood or challenged?
Explainability and traceability are no
longer just technical, nice-to-haves.
They're becoming core audit evidence.
Then there's health and wellbeing.
That includes not just safety issues,
but subtle harms like stress caused by
automated decisions or biased outcomes
that could affect access to services.
Finally, cultural cohesion and values.
ISO 42 0 0 1 brings fairness, diversity
and rights into scope in a way that
can be audited, not just discussed.
Plus six two, a objectives
and plans to achieve them.
Very often this section actually
lives inside the broader AI policy
because it translates leadership
intent into something teams can
track and improve over time.
The core question, this artifact answer
is what targets are we aiming at with
our controls and ML ops practices?
In many organizations, monitoring exists,
dashboards exist, alerts exist, but just
in case they are undocumented or not
disseminated and openly discussed among
personnel within A IMS scope, it can
remain unclear what success look like.
So 42 0 0 1 requires objectives to align
with the AI policy and where practical to
be smart, meaning specific, measurable,
achievable, relevant, and timely.
This means things like reducing
model related incidents, detecting
drift faster, or ensuring secure
patching timelines for infrastructure,
supporting ML business units.
This also creates alignment across levels.
Stop management sets direction
and teams translate that into
operational goals, tied to pipelines,
deployments, logging, and monitoring.
From an audit perspective, this
artifact is powerful because it
converts intention into proof.
Instead of seeing, we care about
responsible ai, that is our objective.
You must show measurable
target and the review cycle.
That's how continual improvement
becomes concrete and visible over time.
We are in clause seven Now
support and more precisely 7.2
artifact on personnel competency.
Personnel competency is one of those
artifacts that could sound administrative
and preachy, but in practice it
directly addresses the risk at the
human layer, the core idea is simple.
People operating AI systems
need competence that matches
the risk they influence.
That does not mean everyone
becomes a security expert.
It means role appropriate.
Awareness is intentional and documented.
This art effect depends on clearly
defined roles and responsibilities
and understanding of training needs.
Competency can span areas like
mops, engineering, bias awareness,
data protection, and AI incident
handling, tailored to how each
role interacts with AI systems.
From an ISO 42 0 0 1 audit perspective,
what matters is evidence such as training
records, certifications, or workshops.
The goal isn't perfection.
It's showing that competence is planned,
tracked and aligned with AI lifecycle
and roles responsibilities, 7.5
artifact on all documented information
for the specific organization.
Can answer.
What documentation do we actually need
to operate our AI systems safely beyond
what the standard explicitly lists?
Clause 7.5 gives
organizations flexibility.
It recognizes that real lops
environments generate critical
knowledge that doesn't always fit
into predefined standard templates.
Things like model release notes,
prompt updates, vendor change
tracking, or pipeline hardening.
Steps often start informally
laying in Slack dms across emails,
or kept just in someone's brain.
The risk is that when documentation
leaves only in tribal knowledge,
businesses tend to lose track.
Reproducibility suffers and after
staff changes, nobody knows why
a model behaves the way it does.
This artifact legitimizes documenting
what teams already rely on making
sure critical operational knowledge
survives beyond individuals.
Auditors will look for evidence that
the organization recognizes what the
documentation is necessary for its
own maturity level and AI complexity.
And that those documents support
consistent operation was eight
operations and 8.1 more specific
on operational documentation.
This artifact exists because the
planning we had in clause six
doesn't prevent incidents by itself.
Execution does.
Teams may define change,
management steps, approval
workflows, or rollback procedures.
But if those steps are undocumented
and executed consistently, unexpected
delays can happen and recovery may be
costlier and take longer than expected.
Clause 8.1 in operations in general seems
to ensure that activities like change
management testing, impact assessments,
and rollback procedures are not just
defined, but actually operationalized
and carried out as planned.
Auditors look for evidence that operations
are repeatable and that recovery
actions are prepared before deployment.
Now, a risk register artifact without a
risk register, ML risks tend to scatter
over time and teams lose visibility.
The same issues get rediscovered
repeatedly because there is no
ownership over the full risk picture.
The A risk register creates a single
source of truth and only evaluated.
The risks are recorded here.
After going through the
risk assessment process.
A common MOPS example is data drift.
Teams might notice performance dropping,
but without a central register.
Nobody tracks whether mitigation
actually worked or who is
responsible in the next quarter.
Risk register solves that by
turning individual observations
into organizational memory.
Auditors want to see that risks
are not only identified, but
actively managed over time.
8.3 specific plans for a risk treatment.
Once a risk is identified, how do we make
sure something actually happens next?
And what happens to it is
transferred mitigated or accepted.
Many are good at identifying risks
and even planning mitigations.
What follow throughs is where
things often break down.
An AI risk treatment plan
focuses on that exact pain point.
It links directly to the risk register and
the statement of applicability defining
which controls are applied, who owns
them, and when progress will be reviewed.
8.4 AI system impact assessment artifact.
Models can perform exactly as designed,
but their broader real world impact
isn't always evaluated holistically.
Recommendation engines, decision support
tools or automation workflows may
reduce social, ethical, or operational
consequences that only appear once
systems scale in real world environments.
This artifact exists to make those
effects visible early, and it
complements risk assessments by
focusing on outcomes and potential harm.
Documents intended use affected
stakeholders and known limitations
while also encouraging teams to think
about wider areas like environmental
footprint, economic impact,
explainability, and long-term wellbeing.
Auditors here want to see
that organizations considered
impact deliberately and
documented their reasoning.
Clause nine, performance evaluation
now and 9.1 on results of monitoring
and measurement activities.
Organizations Start by defining what
needs to be monitored, usually through
clear key performance indicators, such as
model accuracy, response time, fairness
indicators, or compliance metrics.
Just as important is defining how the
data is collected, how often is it
reviewed, and who is responsible for
analyzing it Without clear ownership
and a defined review, cadence monitoring
becomes passive data collection
rather than effective governance.
Once data is collected, clause 9.1
requires analysis and evaluation.
Teams compare actual performance
against objectives, identify trends
or emerging risks, and feed those
insights back into decision making.
This creates a continuous
feedback loop in which monitoring
drives tangible improvement.
Auditors also look for
documented evidence.
Monitoring results, analysis,
outputs and performance reports
need to be retained, version
controlled, and accessible for review.
The goal is not to create more dashboards
or more reporting that is not actionable.
It's to show that monitoring leads
to informed action and measurable
progress across the AI life cycle.
9.2 internal audit.
As pipelines evolve,
responsibilities shift people move
on or grow into new positions.
Retraining schedules shift and
controls can get bypassed temporarily,
and over time, the documented
process no longer matches reality.
The gap is what internal audits
are designed to service early.
Artifact depends on all implemented A IMS
documentation and operational records.
And auditors look for evidence that
controls are reviewed periodically.
Findings are tracked, and improvement
actions follow internal audits.
Act as an early warning system.
They identify weaknesses before
customers, external auditors
or attackers expose them.
The audit results, support management
review, and corrective actions.
Internal audits are essential for
maintaining the effectiveness of the a
MS over time, and they also prepared the
organization for external certification
audits 9.3 Management Review.
Management review records demonstrate
that monitoring results, internal
audit findings and AI objectives
are actively reviewed by leadership.
These discussions lead to
decisions about priorities,
resources, and strategic direction.
This is how AI governance moves from
reactive to strategic and intentional.
Management carries responsibility for
ensuring the A IMS achieves its intended
outcomes, which means understanding
trends like drift incidents, recurring
findings or performance changes, and
deciding what needs to adapt Next.
Management review results also
feeds directly into corrective
actions and continual improvement.
They ensure AI governance stays aligned
with business clause rather than
operating as a siloed compliance exercise.
And the last documentation artifact from
me today from clause improvement 10.2
nonconformities and corrective actions
a nonconformity simply means something
did not happen the way that was planned
and documented, or the management system.
Maybe a control was skipped.
Monitoring results were not
reviewed or deployment moved forward
without the required approval step.
The critical part is not the
mistake itself, it's how the
organization responds to it.
Clause 10.2 focuses on structured
response and it closes the loop
of the plan door check act cycle.
When a non-conformity is identified,
the auditor documents the gap
and the supporting evidence.
A mature organization
then takes ownership.
It analyzes the root cause, evaluates the
impact, and defines corrective actions.
So the issue does not repeat.
Not following up on the agreed
upon timelines for fixing or fixing
symptoms that appear on the surface
without addressing the root cause.
Tends to lead to repeated failures,
and in some cases may be interpreted
as organizational negligence.
You'll often hear auditors distinguish
between minor and major nonconformities.
A minor one is typically an isolated gap,
such as a missing approval record, while a
major nonconformity signals a significant
breakdown in the management system.
For example, missing processes or an
entire clause not being implemented
as expected or repeated failures
that suggest systemic negligence.
Feature findings can delay certification
or even suspend an existing certificate
until corrective actions are verified.
Ultimately, auditors expect to
see ownership timelines and prove
that actions were implemented.
If corrective actions from a previous
audit are ignored, the issue may
escalate into a major nonconformity
signaling, a deeper breakdown in the
management system, and potentially
impacting certification status.
The.
And with that, we wrapped up all 16
required documentation artifacts.
Something I'd highlight as a
key takeaway right now is this.
When organizations start implementing
this minimal viable set of A IMS
document artifacts, they tend to see
disproportionate benefits right away.
Knowledge and information gaps
are brought to light, so effective
discussions and actions are sparked.
Boundaries between experimentation
and production becomes visible.
Releases become safer because fewer
assumptions are left undocumented,
and when something goes wrong, the
response is faster because at any
time, they are not stakeholders.
Know the documented information already
exists, where to find it and how to
conveniently follow the outlined steps.
Another important lesson is
that advanced models rarely
cause problems by themselves.
Most issues are governance, failures,
missing ownership, missing traceability,
and missing feedback loops.
Problems emerge when assumptions go
unchallenged, and no one can answer with
certainly simple questions like, who
approved the change, what data was used?
Whether the system is
still behaving as intended.
A third lesson is that ISO 42 0 0 1
works best when integrated into existing
practices, not after the fact and
siloed as a checkbox exercise, adapting
existing processes across product
planning, risk management, audits
and security reviews, and extended to
cover A IML specific risks works best.
One thing that comes up repeatedly is
the importance of people and leadership.
Training matters not just for
engineers, but also for product
owners, sales decision makers.
Executive sponsorship of ISO 42 0
0 1 certification efforts is often
the difference between AI governance
existing on paper and actually being
followed in practice with evident
and positive behavior changes for
the organization and its people.
There's also a very practical
fact worth stating clearly
certification is almost never free.
It requires time.
Attention and budget, and it
carries other opportunity costs.
That's why organizations that succeed
tend to take a risk-based approach.
Prioritizing controls proportionate to
this specific business impact instead
of trying to boil the ocean all at once.
Finally, the strongest takeaway is this.
Organizations that approach ISO 42
0 0 1 as a strategic investment, not
just a compliance exercise, serial
returns, and these include improved
customer trust, better internal
clarity, smoother audits, and more
confidence when scaling AI systems.
I'd like to finish by thanking you
all for being here and also the
organizers for the Warm welcome as
well as the sponsors and everyone else
supporting this event behind the scenes.
I welcome your feedback and I'd be
glad to continue the conversation.
Feel free to connect with me on LinkedIn,
and hopefully I'll have the opportunity
to share more insights with you at
the future edition of the conference.
Greetings from me until next time.