Speaker 7: Hello folks, this is Ash.
I work as a software engineer in Meta.
I'm located in Seattle location in
Washington, in the United States.
So today I'm presenting this topic,
unifying Online and Offline Worlds, a
machine learning framework for cross
channel attribution and marketing.
ROI.
So we'll start with the
modern consumer journey.
So the challenge today, consumers,
they move fluidly between digital
and physical touch points, creating
increasingly non-linear parts to purchase.
They research products online.
They visit stores to experience
them and engage through social
media, and ultimately they convert
through unpredictable channels.
Traditional attribution models
fails to capture this complexity.
Leaving marketers blind to the
true drivers of conversion and ROI.
So why the traditional
attribution falls short.
First one is channel sales,
separate analytics platforms.
They create fragmented views,
making it impossible to see our
touch points influence each other
across the customer journey.
Second one, linear assumptions.
The most popular, the last click
and the first click models,
the oversimplify reality.
Ignoring the crucial mid
funnel interactions that
shape purchase decisions.
And last one, the offline blind spots
point of sale data and in-person
experiences that remain disconnected from
digital behavior, creating massive gaps
in the enter in attribution accuracy.
So we have a unified
attribution framework.
This is a machine learning, enables us
to bridge the online offline divide.
By synthesizing disparate data sources
into coherent attribution model, this
framework integrates website analytics,
social engagement, email behavior, point
of sale transactions, and in-person
transactions, interactions, revealing
pattern, invisible to traditional methods.
The core components of this framework
first one is data integration.
We unify the touchpoint data across on all
channels into a centralized repository.
Second one, ML modeling apply advanced
algorithms to quantify channel
contribution and interaction effects.
Third one, identity resolution.
We connect anonymous and known
identities to track individual
across devices and context.
And fourth one activation.
We surface insights to
optimize budget allocation and
campaign strategy in real time.
So the cross channel identity resolution,
so effective attribution begins with
identity resolution, its ability to
recognize the same individual across
devices, sessions, or physical location.
Probabilistic matching techniques,
combined deterministic identifiers
with behavioral signals to
create unified customer profiles.
This pro.
This process involves sophisticated
graph algorithms that weigh
evidence across touch points,
balancing precision with coverage to
maximize the attribution accuracy.
So for the key techniques, we
have deterministic matching.
We are logged in states istic matching,
using device fingerprints, graph
based entity resolution, and then
privacy preserving hashing methods.
Next feature.
Feature engineering transforms the raw
touchpoint data into meaningful predictors
of conversion, temporal features.
They capture recency and frequency while
the interaction features the model.
Cross channel synergies that
drive purchase behavior.
Machine learning approaches
significantly out outperform the
rule-based attribution methods.
Assemble models that combine gradient
boosting neural networks and survival
analysis, capture complex interaction
effects and nonlinear relationships.
These model quantify incremental
contribution by channel while accounting
for synergies and diminishing returns.
Next one.
The true value of unified attribution
lies in revealing cross channel synergies.
Social media engagement may not
directly drive conver conversions,
but it amplifies the effectiveness
of subsequent email campaigns by 34%.
In-store visits proceeded by website
browsing convert at 2.8 x the rate of
walk-ins, these interaction effects
remain invisible when channels are
analyzed independently leading to
systematic budget, location mis.
Next one attribution models.
They do generate value only
when insights flow directly
into the marketing decisions.
Automated budget optimization systems
continuously relocate spend based
on the updated attribution rates.
While AB testing validates model
recommendation, campaign activation
platforms, the integrate attribution
scores to personalize, creative
and timing across channels.
Closing the loop between
measurement and execution.
Next, future.
Proving your attribution practices.
You start with the privacy
First architecture.
You design a system compatible with
emerging regulations through all
device processing, federated learning
and differential privacy techniques.
Second is adaptive modeling.
You build continuous retraining
pipelines that are just to evolving
customer behaviors and new channel
dynamics without manual intervention.
And third one, AI integration.
We leverage large language models
for automated feature discovery and
casual inference to stay ahead of
rapid advances and machine learning.
So measuring success attribution.
ROI.
Budget efficiency, gain, average
improvement in marketing, spend efficiency
through optimized channel allocation.
Second is ROI Improvement, typically
increase in ROI marketing investment
after implementing unified attribution.
And third one is insights
accuracy improvement in predictive
accuracy compared to traditional
last click attribution models.
So last your roadmap to
resilient attribution.
You start small, begin with two channels,
and expand incrementally as capabilities.
Mature.
You invest in identity, prioritize
crosswise, cross context, ident
identity resolution as your foundation,
and then build coalition, skip
care, cross-functional support
early to overcome organizational
behaviors, and then iterate rapidly.
Launch an MVP measure impact.
Refine models based on
real world validation.
Yeah, that's all for today.
I hope this is informative and useful.