Hi everyone.
My name is Uncle Big B. I'm
a software engineer at Ash
o and a technical educator.
Today I'm really excited to be talking
to you about AI powered productivity,
which involves boosting productivity for
software engineers using open source lms.
So let's get into it.
This is going to be our agenda for today.
We are going to begin by understanding
why developer productivity matters,
and then take a look at what if
coding wasn't the bottleneck anymore
in our workflow, and then dive
into AI adoption among developers.
And we are also going to take a look
at why open source lms and then.
What you can actually do with these lms.
And then we'll explore architectural
overview of how things work
locally in our LMS development.
And then we are going to take a look
at some use cases of these LMS as well.
And then we are going to take
a look at AI tools that you
can use that are beyond charge.
We are also going to take it at
setting up an open source AI dev tool
locally, and we'll take a look at the
performance and caution of using open
source LLMs on your local machine.
And we are going to end it with best
practices for productive AI usage.
So let's begin with the first one.
Why developer productivity matters.
Developer productivity isn't just
about writing more code faster,
but then it is about building high
quality software with less friction
shipping features faster, and spending
more time solving reward problems.
Rather than getting stock on repetitive
tax, and the first point on why developer
productivity matters is faster shipping
of high quality software, because as
teams scale and product demands grow,
engineers are expected to deliver more.
Collaborate better and
maintain quality all at once.
And with this developers are going
to be able to spend less time on
boiler plate and repetitive work.
And with an effective productivity
approach, developers are also
going to be able to focus their
energy on solving reward problems.
Rather than spending a lot of times
on bola code and repetitive work.
And with this point, this proves that AI
is going to help amplify developers that
leverage ai rather than replacing us.
So when you leverage ai, it's
going to amplify your skill and
not immediately replace you.
So with this, I'm going to
leave you with this false quote,
which says, AI is not a threat.
It's a productivity amplifier, so
AI is not coming for your job, but
if you leverage on AI and position
yourself rightly with ai, AI is
going to amplify your productivity.
I'm also going to leave
you with this question.
What if coding wasn't
the bottleneck anymore?
Let me ask you something.
What slows you down the
most in your workflow?
Is it the boiler code or
repetitive boring stuff?
It is not always the hardest part of the
code that slows us down, but basically
the repetitive, the boiler played
the setting up of state management
by redox or things along that line.
What if we could move past that friction
and focus more on the real business
side of things that solve real problems.
And that is where AI comes in,
especially the open source lms,
where they can do all this repetitive
work for us in a very short time.
And they're not here to replace us.
Like I said, they're here to remove
that bottleneck from our workflow.
So according to the chart put from the
2024 Stack Overflow Developer Survey
ai has been becoming deeply integrated
into the way we build software today.
And this survey shows
that about a year ahead.
Most developers agreed that AI
tools be more integrated into the
key part of their workflow, which
is coming into existence in 2025.
More companies, more developers are
leveraging more on AI for documenting,
for testing, for generating UIs,
for generating designs as well.
Even designers are also using this to
generate a lot of things there as well.
These are not basically side tax
but then AI is already building the
backbone of a lot of engineering effort.
This shows that in 20 24, 20
23, a lot of people are already
adapting it and 2025, a lot of.
More people are already
making use of this.
This shows that AI is not the future
to come, but then it is the future
that we are currently living in.
Now let's talk about AI
adoptions among developer and.
AI is no longer an experiment in the,
like the previous years, but then it
is already becoming the mainstream.
It is already becoming the normal team.
Just the way we use Git and GitHub.
And now in AI adoption among
developers, we have 76.
Percent of developers who are already
using or planning to use AI tools in
their development process in 2024.
So you can see the numbers.
The percentage of developers are already
using it or planning to use it in 2024
compared to the numbers of developers
that are already using it in 2025.
So the number is already increasing.
So the question is you ask yourself
is what is holding you back
to leverage most of these lms?
Either open source or not open source.
And also based on the survey as
well, 62% were using AI tools
in 2024 are up from 44% in 2023.
So now imagine the numbers that we have
in 2025 where the survey is run again.
So this shows an increasing numbers
of adoptions among developers.
And you should also get on the train.
And then we also have.
On the same survey that 81%
sites increase productivity as
the top benefit of AI tools.
So this also shows effectiveness
amongst the developers.
And like I said, these
are not just small tasks.
They're critical part of
shipping quality softwares.
So AI is already writing
like back backend, the full
front end of applications.
And developers are realizing
that using AI isn't optional.
If you want to stay efficient.
So in this age that we are now,
our reality is that if you want
to move fast, if you want to
get things done faster, you.
Have to leverage AI in some ways.
Since you already know what you
want to do, you can just leverage
AI to achieve that faster.
And AI is quietly becoming a different
layer in the modern developer
workflow, just like the way we have
GI and we once have stack overflow
in our mainstream of our workflow.
Now let's discuss about why open source.
LMS when it comes to using AI
in developer workflows open
source LMS are a game changer.
And here it's right.
First you get full
control over the models.
You are not limited by API,
quotas, written means, or vendor
decision because they are basically
running on your own luer server.
And then you can also save host this
and opensource LLM also provides
us with flexibility to customize
pipelines, which you can run locally.
And it is also great for speed cost.
Data privacy, you can also fine tune
them for your specific use cases.
And that's basically incredible
powerful in engineering teams, right?
So that you can basically customize
them to your own use case.
And lastly, you can deploy
this open source LMM.
Anywhere with less or no API cost,
you can also deploy them on your
Looker hardware without having
to pay for any cloud charges.
Examples of these LMS are and LM Studio
among others, which you can basically.
Download them on your system and
then run them locally without
having to pay any extra charges.
So let's talk about what you can actually
do with Open Source LMS as a developer.
These modules are not
just for charge bot with.
Gone beyond being impressed
with chatting with lms.
They can also help us across
multiple parts of your workflow.
They can help with code generation.
You can use them for refactoring functions
writing unit test and validating of
logic which is what is our reality now.
AI can do most of these things.
They can talk to database.
They can leverage integrations
with super base using MCP.
They can leverage with any other
application using their A API or MCP.
Then this makes things a lot faster.
And also AI is already helping with the
bogging like we see in the use case of
Chrome Console ai, which helps you to.
Deb Bug Network is used, which epi
to debug errors in your console, and
you don't have to switch between your
development browser and LLM, so it's
already integrated into your console.
And this is very helpful.
So another one is that you can
leverage LMS to basically learn
about an open source project.
You can learn about.
The GitHub repository, you
can learn about the structure.
The Wes are being done on the
repository, just like for onboarding.
So LMS make things very easier
for you when it comes to like code
base, question and answer as well.
So another great thing that these LMS are
great at is for documenting your code.
You can leverage the local
lms, you can fine tune them for
your own use case, and then.
Use them to document your code.
And because you are using them
locally or via open infrastructure,
you can, build your own dev agent or
even plug them into your id like via
code or know them or three editor.
And it's not just about.
Answering que questions.
It's about automating workflow as
well, so you can plug these LMS
into your workflow directly through
documentation support for your developers
and for your consumers as well.
So now.
Let's break down how local LLMs actually
fit into your development workflow.
So we'll take a look at the architectural
overview of LLMs in local development.
Now, imagine you are coding in via
code, and instead of rea relying on
a cloud service like open ais, API.
Which has rate limit, you can
basically run your own LLM locally.
And this is all thanks to Ola Man, LM
Studio or VLLM which you can explore.
What you just need to do is to basically
pair them with extensions like Continue
Dev, which is greeted by the way, which
you can basically use to integrate
these LMS directly into your id giving
you the co-pilot like suggestions.
But powered by your local model.
So these tools allows you to basically
fine tune things into your own use
case into your own preference so that
they can do what you want directly,
and that is what they will focus on.
And this also gives you
control over the prompts.
You can control the prompts,
the models, and the context
that are available to these lms.
Only for your own use case and
your own data your own code base.
So the LLM is going to basically run
on your machine it's going to respect
your memory and keeps your code base
private as well based on how you want
it, since it's already running on
your looker infrastructure or your
own cloud infrastructure as well.
And these architecture are
usually very fast, right?
So they're very.
Fast, they're cost effective
and gives you the flexibility to
build intelligent features without
leaving your local dev environment.
And then let me introduce you to a
few tools that brings Open source
LMS right into your workflow.
And the first one here is
the Ola Man for Loam model.
Serving so you can explore this,
you can visit their website.
It is a very great tool to run lms
locally for your local development.
And another one that you can pair with
the Allman is the continued the dev
which is a vs code copilot alternative
that allows you to run and, AI native.
LMS are directly from your VS code, and
the next one is A-V-L-L-M for optimized.
Serving and scaling of LLMs.
So if you want to run and optimize LLMs
locally, you can also exploit these tools
as we've discussed in the previous slide.
Now that we've have an idea of the
LLMs and the tools that we can exploit
and now we can exploit them and
what we can achieve from using them.
Now let's take a look
at the use cases of ai.
Boosted developer tax.
Yeah.
These are the things we are
probably doing every day.
Not totally different, but then
this is going to help you to see
how you can leverage AI or integrate
AI into most of these use cases.
So the first one is good generation and
you can make use of continu to death.
To for this and AI can help
you in writing repetitive code.
Think of good endpoints or UI components.
They can do it for you effectively.
And writing of UI test is also.
Something they're very good
at writing prompt templates.
And then they can help you
to write this unit test in a
particular language that you want.
And they are also very good in generating
Aries and commit, which are going to be
auto-generated and much more organized.
And you can also learn from
these as an engineer as well.
And they also helps you
to generate architectural
diagrams for other developers.
If it is an open source project, it can
help you to generate the architectural
for your read me for the documentation.
And all of these things
are basically not Turing.
They are our re live use cases and
that our teams are already using.
So all of these use cases are already,
being used in real life project.
And then you can basically.
Build these workflows using tools
that we've already mentioned from
continue Dev to long chain with local
hosted models like we've been saying.
Ai, is already becoming our sidekick
and it's part of our pack of today.
So now let's talk about
open source AI tools.
That you can basically use
if you are excited about
integrating AI into your workflow.
The good news is you don't need
expensive subscription or closed API.
There's a growing ecosystem of open source
tools built for developers like you, like
me, and they are designed to run locally.
It can be customized and you can.
Keep you can keep the
control of how things works.
So here are some of the best open source
AI tools that you can start using today.
And you can basically just mix them
together like we've been saying.
So the first one is the continuum.
Do dev which you can basically pair
with your editor such as via school
trade and any other editor that.
Support lms.
And another one that is more
popular is the causal and it is a
VS code for built ally around ai.
So you can also leverage this one as well.
And you can also leverage the Tabby ml,
which is basically a lightweight open
source auto complete for developer.
Two.
And you can also take a look at the LM
studio, which also run local module,
and it makes your work very smooth.
So the last two I have here is the
open deving, which is very good
for building autonomous dev agent.
So if you want to build your own
custom dev agents that can do specific
things for you the way you want
it, with your own prompting, with
your own rules, with your own data.
Then you can also leverage this.
This is a table that list
the tools and compares them
based on their own use cases.
If you don't know what tool to
use for what here is a table that
basically give you a summary of that.
You can check out older man if you want
to work if you want to manage your local.
Model.
You can also check out LM Studio
which is a UI driven local lms
basically for frontend engineers.
And then you can also check out
continue the dev which is a vs.
Code AI assistance.
So you're already using VS code.
You can plug this in as an extension.
And then we have the 30 ml, which
is a code completion alternative.
That you can also leverage on.
And we have the VLLM which
solves LLMs effectively.
So if you want to run your LLM
locally, you can also leverage
the VLLM implementation.
So we have the launch chain as
well, which is basically used
to build intelligent apps.
Yeah, so that's basically all these tools.
Now let's take a brief look at setting up.
An open source AI dev.
Workflow.
So far we've talked about why AI
matters and what you can do with it
now let's take a deep look into how
all of this actually works with the
open source AI workflow for developers.
And the beauty of it is that you
don't need a cloud subscription to
get started, like I've been saying.
So first, you are going
to choose a runner.
So it can be an old LA man.
And LM Studio they're basically great.
So you can pick this, and then you can
then integrate them with an id using
tools like Continue Dev or tab ml.
And then from there you can expand.
To configure this to match,
your local model endpoints.
And then you can also fine tune
these for your own use case.
Then you can have a prompt template
basically for your stack if you're
making use of next G'S view.
Or any other stack or just
be it like H-M-S-C-S-S.
So depending on what you want to use this
for, maybe for backend, for front end,
you can basically craft this effectively.
All of these runs on your machine, so
you don't really have to like host it
and then even make more sense if you are
a solo developer working on a project.
So you don't really have to
worry about the downtime.
Or the slow or the limit.
So you basically own the environment
and you can customize it to
suit your workflow with prompts,
template for any of your tasks.
So now let's take a look at the
performance and caution, because
why open source LMS offer a
lot of power and flexibility.
It's also important to understand both
the performance you can expect and then
the cautions you need to keep in mind.
So there's a table on
the performance side.
Majority of the models are,
surprisingly fast and accurate already.
And especially when you run them
locally using optimized tools
like VLL VLLM or like we've
mentioned in the previous slide.
And for most developer
productivity tasks writing code.
Writing tests, summarizing or generating
docs, they are more than enough, right?
So these tools are more than enough.
And they are great tools for
everyday day of workflow.
And there's no vendor locked in.
You can basically own these.
You can also it whenever you want.
It can live on your machine locally.
Yeah.
So some of the questions that you should
take note is that AI can hallucinate
which means that it can generate.
Wrong or misleading
outputs with confidence.
So it might be blind to
its own mistake basically.
So that is why you must
validate its suggestions.
You must always review it.
And then especially when you
are working on sensitive logic,
and you should remember that.
If you are using tools or even
local logs, you should be consigned
and mindful of data privacy.
Be mindful of sharing sensitive data,
input like production API, keys, all
this basically your own responsibility
of taking care of data privacy.
So don't just paste in API
keys or internal code basis vs
without understanding the risk.
Take some time to learn how
this LLM works, like what their
code base looks like, what the
community is saying about them.
So this will help you to better
understand how things works as well.
So now that we've gone through the
performance and caution of these
lms, now let's take a look at best
practices for productive AI usage.
So before you jump in and wire LLMs
into everything into your code base,
because it can definitely be exciting.
Here I feel best practices
to get the most out of ai,
especially as a software engineer.
I. Which ones to run things locally.
But first I would recommend that you start
with re bottlenecks in your workflow.
Don't just use AI just because it is cool.
Identify the places the gap that
AI can fill in your workflow.
Use it where you are wasting the
most time, like maybe every time.
You want to set a new project, you
need to set up some bullet plate or
to develop a feature or ui component.
You need to do some repetitive work
see if AI can come in or if it is
something you can optimize yourself
even without using ai, but then identify
where to use AI and where not to.
So one of the best
practices is to basically.
Remember to prompt, thoughtfully
write clear, intentional, prompt.
You are pairing with a machine,
so you have to be specific.
AI shines when they have the right data.
So if they don't have enough data
through your prompt, then they
might not give you an effective.
Results or output that you expected.
You basically get better results when
you give better context, when you
give good context samples clarity,
and basically treating your prompting.
Skip.
This is going to assist you to
make use of this LLM effectively
and also validate everything.
So this is very important.
Always review the output.
AI might be confident and
still be wrong, right?
You just want to ensure that you are also
in the process and not blindly accepting.
The changes.
So always read and test
before trusting the changes.
And now don't share sensitive code.
Be smart about privacy.
We've discussed it earlier as well
in the caution, so you want to
ensure that you're not sharing.
Sensitive data in the L lms because
it can be exploited at some point.
So you just have to basically
be careful with the data that
you are sharing with it as well.
The next one is to basically pick two.
Match your stack.
And you have to think long term because
the base developers are not just using
tools, they're building systems around it.
So you want to build a system that
works for your stack in a very
long time as a Python developer
or as a JavaScript developer.
So you want to ensure that your usage
of AI is not for just short time,
but it is for long-term use as well.
With that to wrap this
up, I will leave you with.
This code, which says that AI is your
turbo charger and not your brain.
This means that AI is not
just a cool tool anymore.
It's fast becoming essential which
is becoming a foundational part of
how than engineers work smarter, ship
faster and right more reliable code.
We already having augmented engineers.
So if you haven't already started using
AI to support every one of these area in
your workflow, even if it's just one, I
think now is a perfect time to experiment
with all of these open source lms.
And the more we understand our AI
fits into our workflow, the more
strategic we can be about boosting
our efficiency not just with tools.
But with intentions.
So try to spend some time to
understand where these LMS can fit
in, especially running it yourself
and tuning it for your own use case.
And then let a AI a. You move from
idea to output faster, and now my
challenge to you is to try just one
open source LLM two this week and
see how it changes your workflow.
Leverage it, think about what it can
solve for you, and then see how you
can integrate this into your workflow.
Okay?
And that's it from me.
Thank you so much for your
time and intention and for
staying to the end of this talk.
I hope this session spark a few ideas
and gave you something practical
to take back into your workflow.
I'm happy to chat more after this.
Feel free to say hi or connect with
me on LinkedIn on X. You can check
out my YouTube or check out my
blog and leave me a note as well.
Until then, stay curious
and keep building smarter.
Bye-bye for now.