Speaker 13: Good day everyone.
My name is Marav Koff and today we
are going to talk about how to build
secure services with AI agents.
If you ask security engineers
about AI agents today, you
usually get one or two reactions.
The first one is excitement.
The second one is terror.
I work@booking.com where we, I built and
maintain our payment system in our world.
Move fast and break things
isn't a motto, it's a f threatt.
If you break things, people
don't get on flights.
How to won't get paid.
So naturally, the idea of letting
AI agents write new features to our
production services sounds insane.
A year ago I would agree with you.
Let me tell you why I started
experiencing this agent experimenting
with agent on my local machine.
I gave it a very basic task.
Updated dependencies in
this project, run the tests.
Simple, right?
I watched the logs.
It filed pox ml, updated versions.
It ran Maven test.
But build failed, and then instead of
asking for help or try to do something
else, it decided to fix the environment
because it fought environmental issue.
It.
I looked away for 30 seconds.
When I looked back, the agent
wasn't editing the project anymore.
It had navigated out of the project
folder to my home directory, and
I was attempting to rewrite my
Global Maven configuration to force
a different local repository path.
It wasn't malicious.
It was just super, super
helpful because this is how it.
Trained to be aggressively helpful.
It was trying to solve the
problem no matter what.
I stopped it in time, but that
moment left me with a choice.
Give up or build the system
where it doesn't matter if
agent can make a mistake.
My first mistake was thinking that
I could talk agent into being good.
I thought I just need to
better skills, rules, prompts.
I. Let's look at the first slide.
So my first idea was I will
taught agent how to behave.
I will taught it how to work with coso, do
not make mistakes, never hardcore secrets.
Follow PCI requirements we trying
to talk agent into being good.
A reality is that prompt
injections are always possible.
Agents can act.
Agents are not deterministic.
They can hallucinate at any
time and bypass all the rules
and do not make mistakes.
Unfortunately, doesn't work.
Prompts are guide
guidelines, not guardrails.
If you rely on a prompt to stop
an agent from hallucinating your
library or putting a bag into
your code, you don't have security
strategy, you have hopes and prayers.
Models are not deterministic.
No amount of instructions
make it 100% reliable.
So if we can just trust the
brain, we must contain the body.
So we should build a playground.
Simply Playground is a Docker
container with restricted file system
that was one of the restrictions.
Second restriction is command wide list.
Here, it's up to you where to draw a line.
I usually doesn't allow agents to
check all websites they want, so
I have a wide list of websites.
I do not allow them to do some
destructive commands, such
as removing files and stuff.
So it's up to you to decide.
You don't want it to be very harsh,
but you don't want it to be you don't
want this list to be too narrow.
So your agent should.
Be autonomous but not destructive.
And third most important one, you should
always have a credential secret manager.
So credentials should not leave should not
leave the secret manager and credentials
cannot end up in the agent context.
When you treat your environment as
hostile, the agent's intent stop matter.
It can try to be malicious.
Work can be stupid.
The result, the same acts is denied.
So we have an agent in the box.
It cannot burn the house down, but
it still can produce buggy code.
And this leads us to leave.
Number two, AI will
replace security review.
Some people think that AI is so smart,
it can do security review for me.
Just let agent check my code and ship it.
Othering thinks the opposite that.
Humans cannot be replaced and only
humans should conduct a security review.
Both are wrong.
The answer is a cancel,
not a single authority.
Let me explain what cancel is.
I use multiple LMS to review important
code because one model can start reward
Hawking without doing any review at all.
The pattern school, the council,
you probably heard about it.
Andre car talked about it.
It's very interesting concept.
Think of it as a medical consultation.
You don't trust one doctor
for a serious diagnosis.
You want a second or
maybe a third opinion?
I have agents with different
roles, A PCI expert.
That follows the Sta PCS standards.
The reviewer, a code quality model that is
explicitly prompted to be mean an arbiter.
The person who wa weights their
opinions of other roles and
decides what should be done.
Each role ran some different LLM
model, they discuss, and then
arbiter decides what should be done.
If they can't reach consensus on time,
they all produce reports with their takes.
And let human to decide what we should do.
So human makes the final call.
Let's talk about the
whole feature workflow.
First of all, we go to
the brainstorm session.
We receive a feature request,
and then agents wants to know.
What we want to build and
how we want to build it.
So it starts asking questions,
and you as a developer should
provide knowledge for the agent.
When agent has nothing else to ask.
It goes into plan, so it breaks the.
Brainstorm session that you had.
It breaks this design documented
to small bite-size pieces and
creates an implementation plan.
Now goes the most interesting part.
The execution agents creates a subagents.
They produ, they execute tasks one
by one until everything is done.
Also, important step here
that after each task is done.
The small review is concluded, no,
not the whole council review, but
small review by one Subagent funnel,
and then the last tab, everything is
implemented, so we should give it to
the council, and council will review it.
But important thing is that we still in
the loop, so agents won't replace human.
At least for now, but they
will amplify our capabilities.
So I am present in all of those sections.
I maybe, I don't want to be, but I have
to and it amplifies my input to it.
But we have a playground to
contain the blast stratus.
We have a console to check the quality
of the produced code, but I've worked
in FinTech for 10 years and I know one
truth, something will eventually go wrong.
We need to be ready for.
And this leads us to like to the
most important piece that you
should always audit everything.
When agent make mistakes,
you cannot debug it like a.
Regular program.
You need to know what it was thinking.
You need to record a chain of thoughts.
You need to record a session.
If agent tries to escape playground, I
want to know exactly what protocol that
so answer is out it and log as much as
possible and all keep all those logs.
This leads us to myth number three,
that it might be too much to implement.
So it's all complex.
What if I know what you think.
Like playgrounds, councils, Audis sounds
like a massive infrastructure project
and it's hard to invest into that.
But you don't have to start big.
You can start small.
You can start with super simple task.
It's a create agent and
describe your project.
Most of agents has this
feature already onboarded.
You just need it.
But don't be lazy.
Please review it.
Then you can gradually
increase your automation.
You can discover problems or not problems.
You can discover routine tasks in your
team and create the skills for that.
This way, you'll have
a predictable results.
Then you move forward for
cancel, or for agents or for
formm of agents, you name it.
Because this is a very
rapidly changing environment.
And you want to experiment
and we now at the stage where
we can automate automation.
And stage three may be unique.
You can shape it as you want.
And let's talk about the checklist.
To recap everything we should
say, like no secrets should
be present in agent's context.
Please let me be clear about that.
You can.
Let agent work with secrets, but what
you cannot do to let the secrets end
up in the context, next step is build a
playground, not just rules and prompts.
So you want to physically
restrict agent to, to harm you.
Doesn't matter what they thought
about, they might think that they are
helpful, but you have to restrict that.
And third one.
Keep human in the loop for critical
actions because without human we still
need humans to apply important decisions.
You cannot blame LLM because
you as a human approved it.
Cross validate everything
as much as possible.
LLMs, it's an electricity for thoughts,
so you can outsource this thought process.
You don't have to think about it,
but you can as a philosopher said
that truth bo burn in the argument.
So use that and let council to Bernie to.
Bo Burn your Truth.
So yeah, how did everything,
this will help you with possible
incidents and with debug and with
iteration and improving your skills.
And start simple, create
MD and that will be it.
And don't let the Great
Escape help scare you.
Because as every new technology at
the beginning is dangerous, but the
more you think about it and work
without visit, the better it becomes.
Thank you everybody.
You can add me on my LinkedIn
if you're interested.
Have a good day.