Speaker 6: Hi everyone.
Good morning, good
evening, good afternoon.
Hope all of you're doing good.
So my name is Annu Aurora and I'm here
to present today's topic, which is
Zero Surface Task, how we are applying
machine learning and automated workflows
to achieve autonomous IT support.
My, I'm a director for
Enterprise Systems at ServiceNow.
My role basically revolves around
how better we can use our own
products internally to achieve.
Better operational efficiency.
Productivity and basically
be that customer zero.
So that we can be the first to try our
own products, give feedback, and that
really gives us an opportunity to have
a better product, which eventually gets
to the market for all of our customers.
So let's talk about Zero
Service Desk and what were the
challenges for a traditional.
It and why we thought of moving
towards zero service desk, right?
So the first one, and the most important
one is reactive workflows, right?
We always wait for something
to happen before we take
action as an example, right?
Hey, some issue happened, this
particular server is down and let's
take some action now because it's down.
Is there a way I can identify
it beforehand that it was.
Something is going on so that even
that server doesn't get down the user
gets help and, that what incorporated
or that eventually evolved to
incident volume increase as well.
So if, let's say, if I have reactive,
I'm waiting for people to ask for
help, ask for questions, what they need
help with, then the volume of tickets
will eventually increase over time.
Because every company's growing.
We have more employees, rather what
we have five years back, right?
So to serve the same number of employees
or same number of people, then I have to.
Think about maybe do I need to increase
my support staff more because now I have
more people to help day to day and is the
only job is to work on tickets, right?
So that are some of the limitations.
If we work on and ask people for
help and doesn't provide a way to
them to self solve or self-help,
then this becomes a pattern.
And then, okay, incident, people
growing, employees growing
incident volume, growing.
Now, okay, that's, we think maybe we need
more people to support the wider audience,
but that were some limitations, and that's
how we thought, okay, we need to scale.
If the employee base for our company
is increasing every year, doesn't
mean that I have to have always
hired more support guys as well.
And that's where this idea originated
and that's where we started
moving towards Zero Service Desk.
Now, I know for some of them you
might have already heard it, but
for some of them it might be new.
What does Zero Service Desk really
means for us specifically at ServiceNow?
It means how best we leverage
our own platform, ServiceNow.
And get help to the employees,
which is my user base, right?
Faster, more proactively and within like
I would say, minutes or seconds rather
than they waiting for hours to get help.
It doesn't mean that we don't have
a service desk or there's no concept
of service desk, but it basically
means rather than human agents, we
do that support, help or provide
help to the employees or my users.
How I can best leverage ai, my own
service, net platform, own workflows,
orchestration, integration between
third parties, so that to provide help
to our employees or a user base, I
don't need any human agent in the loop.
So that is the whole idea about, and
it majorly focused on self-service,
how much we can enable our
employees to self-help themselves.
That was the idea.
Now key machine learning features
that were part of the overall old
architecture or overall concept?
Concept was the first one is
the classification, right?
We need to categorize, be able to
efficiently help the employee, right?
What kind of issue it is?
Has it happened in the past?
Is it something new of a case?
If it has already happened in the past,
can I apply same metrics and same data and
just help the user as an example, right?
Someone feel back, Hey, someone asked
for an HR policy which is related
to holiday leave or maternity,
and this is user was helped with.
Can I apply the same rules and try
to help the user in the same way?
Then we don't need any
human in the loop, right?
The other is obviously the important
is an intent, dis intent detection.
So if I'm coming for help, right?
Just based on how questions I
type, I'm taking help of let's
say, virtual agent, right?
What questions I'm typing, is it
something information readily available?
Can I help the user?
Right now, the user is asking, Hey,
I need access to this particular.
Role, or I need access to this
particular environment, can I
provide that access right away?
So all these right pillars are important.
And last but not the least,
is the anomaly detection.
This really helps us in
being predictive, right?
Being proactive if, hey, on
my laptops especially, right?
I see for this particular user, I
see his CPU spike is happening every
day and maybe specific time duration.
I think as a system of records, I
should reach out to the end user
and let them know, Hey, something
is wrong, something is unusual.
Maybe it's time to do this, or upgrade
your system or restart your device.
Anything it can be right that avoids
the user to come to service desk,
or relevant agent will ask for help.
Hey, my laptop is down.
I don't know why.
If we detect the issue beforehand,
then we can reach out to the employee
and the user and help them beforehand.
So think about it, right?
It's how much being proactive
and how much being reactive.
That's what has changed over time.
We are not waiting for
users to provide me access.
Hey, somebody will come and give me
access to this thing, and then I will
start working or do my day-to-day job.
No, it's not the case anymore, right?
How the services that you're
expecting, your L one or service test
to provide, how we can automate it,
how we can better detect those issues
and how we can better help is what's
the norm And it's still evolution.
I think that the evolution
is the way right.
Gen K is already there, so how we
incorporate gent KI is definitely
important to everyone in it, whoever
is in IT technology these days.
Now what our approach has
been as an IT organization.
And when we started thinking about
Zero Service Desk, how we started, what
is our focus area, what we try to do
that now we are calling ourself as a
zero service desk organization, right?
And again, it trading Zero Service
Desk really means how we are using our
own platform service now to provide.
The help or support that users
need from the support task or
from the elephant support, right?
So if you see on the screen
there are four pillars.
Prevent, deflect, automate, augment.
So let's talk through it one by one.
The first one is the prevent, right?
Everyone wants to be in the
prevent phase for everything.
Are we there in the prevent
phase for everything maybe?
No.
Some of the things we
today cannot prevent.
But we still are monitoring, we still
have observability in place, right?
We are monitoring how our laptops
are performing, how we are laptop.
We are monitoring how our infrastructure,
how our network devices, servers, right?
How our applications are performing.
There are different pillars of
observability and monitoring, right?
We always want to be there so that
we don't have to maybe eventually do.
Others.
But yes, we still have to do
others based on the use case,
based on the environment criteria.
What kind of help?
Now let's more dive into
deflect or automate.
These two are the places where
we definitely want to be, even
if we are not implementing it
at any organization, right?
So from an infra point or a hardware
point or an application point,
definitely observing and monitoring
will help prevent the issues.
Very sweet spot.
We don't want incidents to be
coming in, issues to be created.
Okay.
We identify, okay, I see there's a
something wrong with this laptop.
It needs an upgrade of a Zoom client.
Okay, let me reach out to the user,
let them know we will do this at
this particular time if you're okay.
Yes.
Good preventive, nothing happened.
Now there are scenarios for
deflect and automate, right?
And let me explain that with an
example, because then it becomes more.
Meaningful.
So let's talk about deflect.
Now I talked about this or give an
example before, but I come to ServiceNow
platform or the portal and I need help.
And what the help I need is with,
I need to know what is the HR
policy for semi tenant leave in
US region or in California state.
And I'm searching for it.
It cannot be preventive, right?
How you can prevent me from.
You cannot read my mind when I'm
gonna search next, but yes, it's an
opportunity of deflection because
somewhere there's a knowledge article,
which will have this information.
Any company will have a policy or a
guidelines, what you all are eligible for.
If I can automatically search that
content and provide it to you handy,
then I don't have to talk to anyone.
I'm just checking policy.
Do I need to talk to anyone to say hey or
otherwise I'll reach to our support staff,
say, can you share this policy with me?
I need to know the policy.
They'll attach the K article to the ticket
or incident I created and say, Hey, this
is what you were looking for closed.
He's not gonna sit on a
call and explain that to me.
So similar to that, do I want even my
users to create such tickets or incident?
Maybe?
No.
And that's a perfect example or a perfect
case of deflection, how we can deflect
something which doesn't necessarily need
to be created as a ticket or an incident
and provide faster help to the user.
For example, another I would just say is.
Somebody comes to a virtual agent
or a search and say, Hey, I need
or maybe my laptop is running slow.
I need help.
Can I have some automation in place,
which can already check the health of
my machine and tell me, Hey, we noticed
that your machine is running up to
date and all the patches are upgraded.
Nothing wrong.
You might have observed a CPU sky spike
or performance issues because it hasn't
been restarted for almost a month.
Can you please try restart
and maybe it works.
Okay, person restarts the machine.
It's working all good.
Plus one deflection.
So these are some of the
example of deflection.
Hey, how we can best deflect the issues
that people don't even create them.
And then next, from the automates,
just by sharing some information,
troubleshooting on behalf of me, you
cannot deflect me from creating an issue.
But these are the categories where,
which are more like requests.
You can think about it, right?
How AI can automate it.
Workers can be the part,
workflow automations can do this.
Simplest example would be anyone needs
a software or access to something
to perform their day-to-day jobs.
Let's say I'm new to the company, right?
I have to start working
on ServiceNow platform.
I don't have access and
I have to request access.
You cannot deflect.
You cannot prevent, this is not a
prevention case or this is not a
deflection case, so I need access
and I, I definitely need access to
day to perform my day-to-day duties.
So how you can automate it as an
end-to-end workflow so that rather
than waiting for somebody to give me
access to the environment, and then
asking me multiple questions, which
role you need, which access you need.
It identifies my intent, which
organization I'm part of.
What is my role based on my profile?
Okay, you need access to
ServiceNow environment.
Is this what you need based on your role?
You're eligible for this.
I'm going to brand this good
if in case it depends, right?
What kind of access it is.
If it needs approval, you
can always bring in approval.
But that think about it as
an end-to-end automation.
Somebody is requesting access,
this person is getting an access
without any human agent involvement.
That is a perfect example of automation.
The next is augment.
Let's say we cannot do any of these three.
So what we, what can we do
augment how we can do it?
Let's say I'm not able to prevent, I'm
not able to deflect user needs help,
I'm not able to automate because it's
not one of the cases or repetitive
tasks which we have automated yet.
So then we augment.
That means.
The person still came, asked for
assistance, asked for help, but
couldn't self solve it by any
other ways, so he still could then
goes ahead and creates a ticket.
That is, how much we say is how we
can augment that user or the support
agent who is working on that ticket by
using ai, gen, ai, any other features,
machine learning so that they can
better and faster resolver that.
So the request or an
issue that a user created.
Which took 30 minutes to be
resolved or troubleshooted earlier.
With all this AI in picture and all
advancements, it just hardly takes
five to 10 minutes now maximum.
So that's like meantime
to resolve reduction.
You are, almost all of you
were, are familiar with this
term, and that's what it can do.
Maybe it cannot avoid an incident or an
issue to be created at the first place.
But it definitely will
help to close it faster.
So that's the overall idea about,
obviously you want to prevent, deflect
or automate, but at least if you are
not able to do any of these, please
try to augment so you can at least
increase operational efficiency and more
productivity gains for your support staff.
So when we talk about this when
we are talking about approach, I
want to highlight one thing, right?
Because.
Many customers ask me this question,
Hey, if you are saying you have
achieved service desk and this has
been your approach, are you saying that
you don't even have a service desk?
People?
Where did, where do those people go?
So those are leveraged
for other tasks, right?
They don't have to do this L one support.
Either they can be all two one
way, or they can be part of some
another organization based on
their interest in something, right?
Or you provide a premium support
to all your VP VIPs or your
employees because there will
always be one of those scenarios.
Which you cannot automate request.
The best value or the biggest
value that we have achieved with
this is a flat support staff.
So from last five, six years the employee
growth for ServiceNow has been like this.
Like it's really growing at a fast pace.
Now, am I hiring the same number of
people or support staff so that I can
have that scale so that I have ample
amount of support staff to support
those employees on my user base?
No.
We used to have 2030 and the organization
remained flat for so many years,
and now we don't even have, right?
So it is an evolution of it, of time, and
when we call ourselves zero service desk.
I always say for every
company it can be different.
For our words, if I hit the target of 90%
self-service, we will call ourself zero
service desk for other company, maybe
bigger than us, smaller than us different
objectives, different leadership, right?
They can have a different number in mind.
Hey, when we achieve 85%
self-service, maybe then we'll
call our zero service desk.
So it can be different, it can vary.
But yes, the ultimate goal is
to enable more self-service.
By ai, by automation, by orchestration,
by bringing all these tools together
and how that we achieve it so that
users can help get, help faster.
That's the overall idea.
How you can help your employee base,
help your support staff to better
evolve with evolution of technologies,
with the evolution of platforms
and evolution of our era, right?
Like where we are today.
So let's talk about
now what all things we.
Highly dependent on, or how we integrated
to achieve the zero service desk.
From an architectural standpoint,
I think I briefly touched upon it
is the predictive analysis, right?
Understanding the intent of the
user, what user needs whether it's
just by helping them to get some
knowledge to them, whether I need to
have an automation inflow, because
that's what they are requesting.
So understanding the intent
becomes really important here.
And one thing, which I call
about, if you see in the middle,
it's ServiceNow platform, right?
All our work happens in the
platform as a ServiceNow.
Being a company, obviously we use
our platform very extensively.
So the first thing we did was make
sure, but there were different ways of
how people will try to get help, right?
Either they will call the service desk or
they will try the virtual agent, right?
I know you have all heard about it.
And just start a conversation
with the bot and try to get help.
But if people start calling
and they have multiple ways of
communicating, then it becomes really
challenging to achieve this goal.
So the first step was how to consolidate,
have everything and just to have one
standardized way of how people will get
help or how our user base will get help.
That was the important because that was
not just a technology focus, but that was
a human behavior change focus as well.
How we, change the behavior of
people where they always come
to watch agent for help, right?
They don't call the help desk
or a human agent for help.
That was the first driver that
helped us achieve this and
ServiceNow platform, right?
It has it incident management problem
and all those it and some features,
plus it has workflows, right?
Like knowledge base, all that is
maintained in ServiceNow platform,
plus an integration with other third
party as well, let's say SharePoint.
Or you can have automation workflows
with any other software vendor if
it is for software or anything.
But that was, but the core of everything,
I would still call it a ServiceNow
platform and that's why I call it when
we call zero service desk, that's where
I say how we are using our own platform.
Providing that L one support
to the customer or the employee
rather than having a human agent.
And by doing all this, what
I'm getting is obviously.
Being healthy environment, I can
audit how everything is working.
And I can achieve greater successes
with having a platform, right?
I don't have to invest
in support staff more.
So overall, the idea is how we can
incorporate ServiceNow platform, machine
learning, ai, and bring it all together
so I get better results in term of my
performance, my health, and eventually
get to that self-service model.
Because that was the real crucial
thing is getting to the zero service
desk, but definitely having governance
in place to manage and monitor it.
Now, I think a little bit touched upon
it when I was describing the previous
slide, but governance is important, right?
Especially when you're using
ai, especially security is
a big thing today, right?
With AI in picture.
So definitely we have to make sure we
govern all our processes, we govern
all our tools, all our policies,
and especially the ai, right?
So different types of governance, if
you see on my screen, are listed there,
especially the first one, very important
one is the AI and decision governance.
We have to have ethics and proper
guidelines in place before even we
start implementing any use cases for ai.
Especially when before, at least
before even you take it to production.
Some organization I know do a
small POC to test it, whether it's
possible, those are mostly internal
resources, but definitely right.
If there are no guardrails in
ai it can harm any company their
reputation value in a biggest way.
So definitely make sure you
have proper security in place
before you leverage an AI.
Here at ServiceNow, we definitely
go through AR b approvals.
Our products are already certified,
what have been launched in the market.
But when we are implementing anything
entirely, we make sure we go through
the data governance team and like
ERB Architecture Review Board to
make sure they approve whatever
integration or outcomes we are looking
for, and they sign off on, Hey, we
are going in the right direction.
So that is really important here.
And then obviously risk
and compliance, right?
Definitely every company should have a
compliance and governance team, right?
Everyone is spending so much on
investing in security these days.
Definitely.
Do we need to have a risk review,
security review just to make sure.
Especially the permissions, right?
Even if let's say you have to integrate
two systems, you, everyone uses service
accounts or secrets to integrate.
Now how and what roles you
provide to those secrets.
Even like what is just having
a guardrail around what that
integration or workflow is gonna do.
So that it doesn't disrupt what,
whatever that system is supposed to do.
If I'm just as an example, I give
you, if this particular automation or
integration is only supposed to, let's
say restart let's say Zoom client on
my machine it isn't supposed to do a
look at my Outlook data or my actually
meeting details of a Zoom, right?
But just restart privileges.
That's it.
Nothing else.
Then we should verify.
And some security review, compliance
review should happen that yes, it is
actually doing what it is intended
to do and nothing more than that.
So that piece is really crucial.
And last piece, but not
least, is governance from a
performance standpoint, right?
I was talking about zero service
desk and I talked about self-service.
So now specifically in that
scenario, if I talk about
self-service, how we measure ourself.
The important step here is when we
started this Journey to Zero service
Desk, we we wanted to obviously monitor.
We had a target.
Hey, we want to reach 90% self-service.
How did I pick that 90% number?
If I don't know how I'm performing
today, it's very difficult
to measure in future as well.
I need to know how, what are my
performance indicators today, like
as an example, I said, like you see
on the screen ticket deflection rate.
Is there any deflection happening
today or it is zero, maybe 10%, 5%,
but something might be happening?
Or if there is nothing, that's fine too.
But I should know the way
how I should measure it.
I should need to have a proper
formula being reviewed and then make
sure how they are like leveraged
across organization, how everyone.
How everyone understands it,
how it is trending over time.
So at least when I reach 90%,
I should be able to say with
confidence, yes, I'm 90% right.
So we have definitely have dashboards,
reports where every day we are
monitoring these KPIs because these
gives us a an ability to continuously
improve and innovate as well.
Because once I hit 90%,
I'm not like, done, okay.
I'm sitting, I'm not doing anything.
We have to evolve, and that numbers,
that validation, that KPIs, if we track
those KPIs, they'll help us to evolve.
And if something goes wrong,
they'll help us to get better.
Now, today, if I, let's say, achieve
90%, doesn't mean I might not go to 80%.
It might happen, right?
If something breaks.
So if I don't govern my workflows, if
I don't have performance indicators,
and if I don't measure how it,
how is my self-service doing,
then I won't be able to scale it.
So that type of governance, your
performance governance is really crucial
and that's how we are doing it today and
hopefully you'll always need to do it.
Metrics is really important.
Measurable outcomes that we achieved
as of s out of service desk first.
And the more important I really like it
is the incident reduction, and that's
where I talked about scalability, right?
If the employee base is growing or the
user base who needs support is growing,
doesn't mean I hire more people to
just support those employees, right?
So that's where we have to think about
scalability, which will eventually,
if I self-heal, I'll self automate.
The ultimate value I'm achieving is
I have incident reduction, so I don't
need more people to work on tickets
because whatever I built, especially the
self-service model, it'll help you scale.
If I have built a model or an
automation, say anytime anyone
get, ask for an access to Adobe.
This is a workflow which should
add, like run, execute, and then
people will not raise tickets.
Now, even if I have 20,000, 30,000,
50,000 employees, it doesn't matter
that workflow or the automation, the
predictive analysis, any, everything
will work the same way and maybe even
better over time with more learning.
So that's what the overall idea was.
Now think about it, you
have a reduced incident.
You're not hiring more people
with, as your organization is
scaling, what does it bring?
Cost savings.
We are, you don't need to invest more
in people or organization just to
support those employees because they
might be doing more important tasks
just than providing them L one support.
Then overall, this helps us achieve the
user satisfaction because everything you
do, and we also, when we did everything,
we made sure the employee experience or
our user experience is not disrupted and
that actually improved over time because
they are now getting the faster help.
They're not waiting in the queue
for somebody to come and help them.
It's a faster response
time, better result.
So definitely not only just, it helped
us get that user fix satisfaction or
experience, but even improved on it.
And obviously with user satisfaction
and everything, less downtime.
Greater productivity.
That's without any doubt, right?
If no incidents you're you can use that.
People are more innovation task
and rather than just providing the
L one support you have, you are
directly getting productivity gains.
And overall, everything of this will
help any company's business grow.
So last let's briefly touch based upon
it, what's the future of us, right?
If we have already achieved
this autonomous IT service desk.
What is the future?
I think more companies are, I would say
diving into this one our ServiceNow,
our focus is autonomous enterprise.
And I think for many
companies it's the same.
Specifically, what interests me and what
I am the driver for is the autonomous it.
I know everyone is thinking like others.
We are thinking Autonomous
service desk, we did it.
Now we are thinking about.
Complete autonomous it, whether it's
network space, in fraud space, everything
that operations touch should be in
some way or fashion, autonomous, right?
So that, that's the north side of the
future and I hope we definitely reach it.
People are investing, like especially
in hr, finance, legal, everyone
is investing in autonomous space.
So definitely like others, we are also
and, the second part is AI ops, right?
We are doing it.
We had to do it a little bit of predictive
to get this zero service desk, but we have
to be more predictive and less reactive.
Reactive, obviously, I wouldn't
say we are reactive at.
This stage, but we are still some
of the use cases, I would still say
we are proactive like we identify,
but we have to be predictive, right?
Which is more important and that
comes in observability area.
So we are deep double downing on
that and just making sure how we
can be that predictive organization.
And then obviously embedded
flows into it, right?
We are using machine learning, we are
using ai, but now we have to double
dive on how we can incorporate our
agent workers gen workforce origin
framework, I would say, into all
these workflows that we are trying
to automate so that we can really
reach that autonomous enterprise goal.
And then obviously continuous improvement.
That is the key that will never
go anywhere, wherever we reach.
Continuous improvement.
Next level should always be there.
And same way for me, for us, for
the company, we are definitely
investing again and double diving
and obviously always work on this
continuous optimization and improvement.
So I'm hoping this helped everyone of you
to understand what is Zero service desk,
what we have achieved, where we are going.
So thank you so much for your
time and listening to me.
Have a good day.
Thank you.