For being here, I'm Pril Marni,
senior DevOps professional with
around 10 years of experience.
Today we are going to talk
about harnessing Kubernetes for
scalable AI ML workloads, using
insights from Tesla and open ai.
Over the next few minutes, we'll explore
why Kubernetes has emerged as a defacto
platform for container orchestration
in ai, and we'll dive into two real
world implementations that leverage
Kubernetes for AI ML workloads.
I share architecture patterns, operational
metrics, and lessons learned that you
can apply in your own environments.
First up, let's discuss how AI
workloads differ from traditional
computational workloads.
AI workloads, as are resource
intensive, require elastic scaling and
are failure prone when thousands of
GPUs are pushing petabytes of data.
24 7 analysts project the market
for AI platforms will search
from five $15 billion in 2023
to over $2 trillion by 2032.
So the stakes are huge here.
Traditional static clusters can't keep up.
And based on recent surveys, 61% of the
enterprises site capacity bottlenecks as
their number one blocker to production.
Ai.
Considering this, Kubernetes has emerged
as a critical solution for addressing
these challenges through dynamic resource
allocation, intelligence, scaling
self-healing capabilities, enhanced
monitoring and workload portability.
Coming to some of the common AI
infrastructure challenges, resource
intensity is one of the top
challenges faced by AI infrastructure.
Modern AI models demand extraordinary
computational resources with training
requirements increasing exponentially
modern AI training and inference
pipelines demand a compute.
Driven model training can consume over
61% of the data centers total power
budget, leaving less headroom for
networking, storage and non-AI workloads.
Scaling complexity, data volumes and model
par parameter counts are exploding at
around a 36% compound annual growth rate.
This means a cluster sized for
last year's workload will be under
provision today and obsolete tomorrow.
Static infrastructure simply
can't keep up with the pace of
growth that we have seen here.
Resource inefficiency.
Without proper orchestration,
organizations struggle to
optimize resource allocation
across varied workloads with
fluctuating demand patterns.
As pipelines become more distributed,
spanning object stores messages, andous
compute failure modes multiply and
increase potential points of failure.
Without automated recovery,
mean time to repair can stretch
into hours or even days.
This is extremely concerning in large
scale distributed training environments.
These challenges together combine to
slow down, model iteration, inflate
costs, and undermined re reliability.
Next, let's see how Kubernetes
directly addresses each of
these issues as a solution.
Alright, let's see how Kubernetes
as a solution for us here.
According to CNCF research, 88% of
organizations are running containerized
AI ML workloads in production with
70% leveraging Kubernetes as their
primary orchestration platform.
This widespread adoption is driven by
Kubernetes, is comprehensive feature
set that directly addresses the
unique requirements of AI workloads.
Kubernetes comes with
declarative provisioning.
In a single yaml, you
get to describe GPU type.
The driver, CUDA base image and Kubernetes
device plugin automates the rest.
No more handbuilt bare metal clusters.
It has great resource
optimization and scalability.
It provides tools like horizontal
power autoscaler, which can combine
with NVIDIA metrics exporter.
Allows Kubernetes to adjust replicas
in mere seconds while vertical port
or autoscaler right sizes, memory,
or CPU based on the requirement.
CADA adds event driven bursts that can
help with sudden spikes in traffic.
Kubernetes has self-healing and
rolling updates for an improved uptime.
If A GPU node panics the scheduler,
restarts the pod on healthy hardware
and respects pod disruption budgets.
So training jobs keep their core.
If any update needs to be deployed
to the model, Kubernetes control
loop based resource management
ensures that the new changes are
rolled out without any downtime.
Kubernetes offers multi-tenant
isolation using namespace resource
quotas, thas and node selectors.
It lets you guarantee say that 40 a one
hundreds are for team A and 40 H. One
hundreds are for production inference.
You can divide your own GPU hardware.
Allocate specific services, specific
workloads onto each type of hardware.
It also enables for batch AI workloads to
be deployed onto selective infrastructure.
So to summarize, Kubernetes provides
dynamic resource allocation, allowing
organizations to optimize resource
utilization across variable AI workloads.
As you can see from CNCF research, these
percentages are not a smaller percentages.
They reflect broader industry adoption.
Underscoring that Kubernetes
is production hardened for ai.
Okay, let's continue our discussion about
Kubernetes capabilities for AI workloads.
Let's dig deeper into how
each functionality helps with.
Running AI workload dynamic
resource allocation.
In the previous slide, we had already
covered a little bit about how Kubernetes
allows for enhanced resource optimization
and scalability through the GPU device
plugin and custom scheduler extensions.
Kubernetes can share GPU devices across
parts or carve them into partitions.
In practice, 63% of the organizations
citing resource optimization as a primary
motivation for adopting Kubernetes
intelligent scaling.
Kubernetes provides multiple
scaling mechanisms that address
variable resource requirements.
The horizontal pod autoscaler and vertical
pod autoscaler augmented with custom
metrics such as GPU, memory pressure
or Q Depth allow training and inference
pods to scale up and down in real time,
which such scaling 78% of the
organization are to adopt into ku.
To self-healing capabilities of
Kubernetes, Kubernetes provides
critical reliability improvements like
liveliness probes, readiness probes that
can catch hunger or crash processes.
Cluster autoscaler can be used to
replace unhealthy nodes automatically
without any manual intervention.
A 72% reduction in failed training
runs across organizations.
Kubernetes provides enhanced monitoring.
Kubernetes offers granular
visibility into resource
utilization and performance metrics.
It's out of the box.
Integration with Prometheus and
Grafana provides dashboards for
GPU, temperature power draw, PCIE.
Throughput and network IO
teams achieve 76% faster.
Mean time to recovery because anomalies
are detected and visualized immediately.
These aren't marketing claims
that I was just showing you.
They're aggregated from production
telemetry across hundreds of deployments.
That said, let's continue on to our
case study of one of the prominent
car manufacturers innovations Tesla.
Tesla represents one of the most
sophisticated implementations of
Kubernetes for AI ML workloads, leveraging
container orchestration to power.
Its autonomous driving technology.
The company's autonomous driving system
processes data from eight cameras
that collectively capture 360 degree
video generating approximately 1.5
terabytes of data per car annually.
Tesla processes over a hundred
thousand video clips per day through
its computer vision pipelines.
With each clip requiring analysis
across multiple neural networks,
Kubernetes orchestrates thousands
of container instance instances
that collectively analyze these
inputs during training period.
By contain their 360 degree camera
inference, pipeline deployment time
from two weeks to under four hours.
Tesla employs a hybrid cloud approach
for its training infrastructure,
which is very important.
Cloud brings you that reliability
and flexibility, whereas On-Prem
gives you that high performance with
Kubernetes, managing workloads across
both on-premise data centers and cloud
resources for from multiple providers.
The hybrid approach did enable Tesla to
optimize for both cost and performance.
Let's see how they have built
their Kubernetes implementation.
Let's go through each component and see
how each component serves which purpose in
their whole architecture, AI m pipelines.
Tesla used PY and TensorFlow for their
AI ML pipelines to to do neural network
training and used Triton inference
server for their realtime inference.
And all of these were running inside
Kubernetes parts and the time inferencing
for each camera orientation is done
using these AI ml. Infrastructure
approach is hybrid cloud, as we
already discussed with on-prem and
cloud to optimize cost and performance
coming to hardware accelerators, Tesla
used Nvidia GPUs and some other custom
AI chips built for specific use cases.
And these are used to power
their neural network training
model training and inferencing.
The training technique they
adopted is data parallelism.
And they have achieved this by
distributing workloads Kubernetes into
Kubernetes across multiple GPUs, and
they leverage Kubernetes to achieve this.
Deployment mechanism they have a
unique style of deployment mechanism
compared to traditional use cases.
Since they have a fleet of cars that
have to function and do real-time
inferencing, they use something
called over the air updates to
deliver their model improvements.
Pull new container images
and rotate parts seamlessly.
So every car pretty much runs
their latest neural net weights.
The architecture, this architecture
that they have employed.
Decouples model development from
infrastructure, accelerating
Teslas iteration route.
Now let's discuss
the case study of one of the
cutting edge AI platform.
That brought this whole AI
frenzy to the market open ai.
Open AI represents a prime example of
how Kubernetes can be leveraged to manage
extraordinary computational demands
of cutting edge AI research training.
Modern LMS like those developed by open AI
requires massive computational resources.
GT three featuring one 75 billion
parameters and G PT four estimated to
have more than 1 trillion parameters.
Kubernetes provides open AI with
the ability to define sophisticated
scheduling rules that consider
complex variables like data locality.
Interconnect bandwidth
and power constraints.
The platform's native support for GP
resources allows for precise allocation
of specialized computing resources.
Kubernetes provides distributed training,
so open AI leverage HO Award on Q Flow,
which runs on Kubernetes, and they used it
to orchestrate data parallelism to reduce.
Their workloads across
hundreds of GPU parts.
Data processing Spark on Kubernetes
was used by OpenAI to handle ETL
of petabytes of text tokenization,
filtering, and feature extraction.
For model serving, they used Triton
plus custom Kubernetes operators
and use them to route thousands
of inference request per second.
Sub 50 millisecond latency,
which is pretty low.
And this was only possible
because of using Kubernetes.
Now,
let's see what other capabilities that
OpenAI has leveraged using Kubernetes.
As you all know, as we already discussed,
the resource management is one of the key
aspects that Kubernetes triumphs over.
OpenAI has leveraged Kubernetes for their
GPU resource management for efficient
allocation of hundreds of thousands
of GPUs for distributed LLM training,
optimizing them for performance and cost.
For example, their high priority training
jobs preempt lower priority workloads,
ensuring SLAs for critical research runs.
So there are high priority training
jobs run on parts that get scheduled on
GPUs that are more powerful that way.
Kubernetes gives you that flexibility
of resource management to ensure
performance and efficiency.
Swarm based ML orchestration.
Coordination of multiple AI
agents working on different
aspects of the MI ML pipeline.
Breaking down the training process
into discrete containerized
steps is key for open ai.
Custom controllers treat hundreds
of parts as a cohesive form,
packing GPUs to maximize efficiency.
Dynamic scheduling is one of the
important aspects for achieving
higher throughput with lower latency.
Think of it, adjusting resource
allocations based on changing
requirements across different
training phases from CPU intensive
pre-processing to intensive training.
Parts can migrate between CPU only ETL
stages and GPU accelerated training
inferences stages based on demand and can
be scheduled onto specific type of node.
This dynamic scheduling scale up and
scale down aspects of Kubernetes,
which is automated, gives open ai.
Edge over the other AI platforms.
This Edge made them choose
Kubernetes over as their primary
infrastructure platform for ai.
Okay, now the last aspect is
monitoring and observability.
Who doesn't need monitoring
across their workloads?
Be it traditional
workloads or AI workloads.
Monitoring and observability
is a key aspect for maintaining
uptime and product efficiency.
Tracking resource utilization, model
performance, and system health across
distributed infrastructure to identify
bottlenecks and anon anomalies
is key for any product lifecycle.
They have implemented distributed
tracing of RPCs, GPU Sims, SM metrics and
Network Telemetry triggering alerts in
under a second for anomalous patterns.
This gives them that edge that can
help with monitoring their AI workload.
These capabilities altogether allow
open AI to operate at a scale few
organizations can match, and they
have achieved this high growth
using Kubernetes while maintaining
high utilization and reliability.
Alright, let's discuss.
AI Ecosystem
Q is one of the end-to-end platform
for orchestrating sophisticated
ML pipelines provided, providing
streamlined model training and
hyper parameter tuning using CIB and
metadata tracking with ML MD and it is.
Very important tooling used by
many organizations for their
production deployment workloads.
Coming to TensorFlow operators, these
are custom Kubernetes controllers
that auto automate TensorFlow
distributed training configuration,
dramatically simplifying resource
allocation and internode communication.
TensorFlow operators and
media device plugins.
Natively expose GPUs and
multi-instance GPUs to parts
coming to model serving production.
Grade inferencing frameworks
like Kerv, kf serving seldom core
and Triton deliver auto scaling,
canary rollouts and AB testing.
For inference.
They provide auto scaling and
deployments for seamless AI delivery.
Importantly, Kubernetes provides
enhanced security frameworks using,
which are S-P-I-F-F-E, SPIRE for
Workload Identity, GRPC, mutual TLS,
and Network policies for Zero Trust.
They also provide advanced
isolation technologies.
Like Carta containers that create hardware
virtualized environments for high value
AI models, protecting intellectual
property and sensitive data altogether,
the Kubernetes ecosystem has matured
into a comprehensive AI ML platform,
evolving from basic container management
to offering specialized tooling that
addresses the entire machine learning
or lifecycle with enterprise adoption.
Accelerating the global cloud
native platforms market is projected
to reach $62.7 billion by 2034,
growing at A-C-I-G-R of 16.5%.
As organizations increasingly
leveraged these technologies
for competitive advantage.
Together.
These projects fill every stage
of the AI lifecycle from data
ingestion to model deployment, all
taken care of within Kubernetes.
Alright, let's look at some of
the common industry adoption
in Kubernetes for AI workloads.
Industries are adopting cloud native
platforms like Kubernetes at different
kinds of rates with healthcare and
financial services leading the way.
Healthcare is currently sitting
at 18.2 CIGR Genomic sequencing
pipelines and MRI Ima image analysis
are running on Kubernetes clusters
to achieve high healthcare needs.
The healthcare sector's adoption is
particularly notable because of the
stringent regulatory requirements
and sensitive patient data.
Banking, financial services and insurance
are sitting at 17.9% annual growth rate.
Growth driven by driven the need
for secure AI infrastructure with
technologies like Carta containers
that we have already discussed about,
has been especially valuable for
processing sensitive financial data
and algorithmic trading strategies.
Finance industry has seen a
rise in AI adoption for realtime
fraud detection using streaming
inference, and Kubernetes has been.
Telecom around 0.8 annual growth.
It is leveraging Kubernetes to
manage complex networks and deliver
innovative digital services at
scale with high reliability.
For example, one of the top use cases
for telecom is to achieve superior 5G
network analytics and edge AI in micro
data centers powered by Kubernetes.
Coming to manufacturing.
It's currently sitting at.
But the experts are expecting that
this could be become one of the prime
sector for AI adoption and that AI
adoption calls for Kubernetes adoption.
So implementing Kubernetes to
orchestrate iot devices, optimize
production lines, and enabling
predictive maintenance using AI systems.
Which run on Kubernetes has been the
has been the motive for manufacturing
growth rate, AI driven visual inspection,
and predictive maintenance via GPUA.
Accelerated vision models that run
on Kubernetes is another top use
case that drives this adoption.
Alright, let's wrap up and
discuss what we have already gone
through in the last few minutes.
Kubernetes provides great
infrastructure foundation for
scalable reliable AI infrastructure.
It delivers the elasticity,
resilience and portability that
modern AI ML workloads demand.
Kubernetes has an expanding ecosystem
that has specialized tools for
enhancing capabilities for AI specific
requirements, and it is ever evolving.
C and vendor extensions
continue to evolve.
Filling gaps in security, pipeline
orchestration and serving.
Accelerating innovation is one of
the top drivers in Kubernetes and
top requirements for AI organizations
gain try to gain competitive advantage
through improved resource utilization.
By standardizing on Kubernetes teams shift
their focus from infrastructure, plumbing,
to model development and data science.
As AI models grow in size and
complexity, Kubernetes will remain
the orchestrator of choice, enabling
continuous experimentation, rapid
ation, and cost efficient operations.
Alright.
Thank you for the attention.
I hope these insights help you
architecture and operate your own
Kubernetes based AI platforms.
And they, I hope that they gave you a good
depth, in depth look at how Kubernetes
can help with running AI ML workloads.
Thank you.
And have a.