For many of the data engineers,
ETL has been the backbone of
data engineers for decades.
You extract the data,
transform it, and load it.
We have built pipelines, batch
jobs, and data warehouses, but what
I've seen is that data engineering
is just about moving data anymore.
We are being asked to deliver
data faster, more reliable, and
at bigger scale and smarter too.
It's not enough to simply.
Pipeline data into a
warehouse and quality data.
What's happening now is AI and
machine learning are no longer just
a downstream consumers of data.
They're moving up upstream into
our engineering process itself.
AI is becoming embedded inside our
pipelines, detecting lys, generating
transformation logic, auto-scaling
infrastructure, and automatically
automating the data quality checks.
Suddenly we weren't spending
days combining through bad data.
We are getting real time alerts with
anomaly explanation explanations
that freed us up to focus on
deeper improvements rather than
constantly fire fighting data errors.
Before we go deeper into this topic,
let me quickly introduce myself and
why this journey into AI powered data
engineering has been so meaningful for me.
I am Jonathan and I've been working as a
lead data engineer and solutions architect
for over a decade with hands on, hands-on
experience building and modernizing
data platforms at organizations like.
Capital One, FINRA and F-M-C-S-A.
It is an entity of our depart
DOT Department of Transportation.
At Capital One, I was part of a
major modernization effort moving
away from legacy mainframe systems
to micro based microservice based
cloud platform to support credit
card applications like acquisitions,
approvals, and risk decisions.
This gave me firsthand exposure to
transforming complex nested Avro data
into clean analytic ready data mods
while having no while having to deal
with the schema drift, realtime data
ingestion, and the data quality at scale.
And at finra, I have worked with one of
the largest data pipelines I was ever
seen, ingesting over two 50 billion daily
trade events across the US stock market.
It.
We weren't just pro processing
huge volumes of data.
We had strict regulatory timelines
and need and needed zero data loss,
high accuracy and fast availability.
That's where I saw AI and automation
set up in, not just as an add-on for
analysis, but as a core part of the
engineering process, helping us monitor
data quality, detect ly in ingestion
and auto tune processing pipelines.
And most recently at DOT fm F-M-C-S-A,
a late data initiative focused on
safety and compliance reporting
for commercial motor carriers.
And when you are supporting public
safety decisions, you can't afford manual
errors or delay in the data pipeline.
Like here we had to deliver inspection
and violation reports for all 50 states
based on millions of records per month.
From various inspection systems, we
implemented tools like P DQ for automated
data quality checks, and even explored
using ML models to PLA flag suspicious
inspection records in real time.
What I've seen, what I've learned
across the these roles in is that
data engineering is no longer just
about pipelines and warehouses.
It's about reliability,
scalability, and increasing
increasingly about intelligence.
Let's talk about the reality of data
engineering today and why EA has become
such a critical piece of the conversation.
When I first saw these numbers, the
reality hit home 68% of it and engineers.
Time is spent on maintenance
rather than innovation.
And four and a half hours a day is spent
on debugging and fixing pipeline issues.
And 23% of data quality problems
are discovered until they
are already in production.
Honestly, that feels about right
because I've seen, I've been in
those trenches a lot of time.
A lot of time wasn't spent
building new features or
optimizing for business outcomes.
It was spent answering questions
like, why did this pipeline fail?
Now last night, is this a schema
issue or a data quality issue?
Did something happen upstream
change that no one told us about.
And when pipeline breaks,
the pressure builds fast.
Our, for decades, ETL has followed a
very traditional, very rule-based model.
You extract the data from source systems,
you map it to, into a target schema, you
transform it with predefined rules and
tho then load it into a data warehouse.
Sounds simple enough until you are
dealing with hundreds of source systems
constantly evolving schema, dirty
data, and complex transformation logic.
Here is what the traditional
ETL world looks like.
Time consuming manual mapping
between complex data schemes.
A very rigid rule-based transformation
that struggles to adapt to change, like
transformation that are hardcore logic.
Or pre predefined logic.
If X is Y effects, then Y else a Z. But
what happens when upstream data changes?
No new columns, different formats.
These rigid rules break and require
manual inter interventions to patch
them, and reactive error handling.
In traditional world, you don't
find out about errors until
they have been already broken.
Your pipeline are corrupter
corrupted your data.
Data stream data, downstream data.
Either way you are reacting
after the damage is done.
Static performance tuning, and let's
not forget the over suspended, manually
tuning sparko configuration or query
parameters to try and optimize runtime
for a specific data set or a workload.
Once tuned, it's static.
Now compare that with the AI powered ETL
approach, automatic schema discovery,
and intelligent hands-free mapping.
Instead of developers manually mapping
every field, AI algorithms can scan source
data in for data types and recommend or
auto map fields to the target schema.
Even for complex nested J or
evolving source schemas, adapt
to transformation, powered by.
Machine learning rather than static rules.
AI models can learn transformation
patterns from that data, proactive
error de detection and resolution.
AI doesn't wait until the
pipeline fails at runtime.
It proactively analyzes incoming
data before execution, predicts
potential errors and can either
auto resolve or flag issues.
It's a shift from reactive to
predictive pipeline management.
Self optimize, optimizing real time
execution, and perhaps most exciting AI
can monitor job execution in real time,
automatically tuning configurations
like partition partitioning, parallelism
memory allocation based on current
workload and resource conditions.
So you are always operating near
peak efficiency without manual 20.
So beyond just the technical
improvements, let's talk about
the strategic impact AI brings to
ETL and data engineering Overall.
First,
self-optimizing.
Realtime execution means our pipelines
are just on the fly, whether it's
handling sudden data volume spikes, or
adapting to infrastructure bottlenecks.
No more endless manual tuning
or constant babysitting.
But more importantly, it redirect it.
It redirects engineering effect.
Instead of spend spending our days
fixing failed jobs or remapping schemas,
engineers can focus on innovation,
new features and high value of work,
and the numbers speak for themselves.
85% reduction in manual schema
mapping, which speeds up
project timelines dramatically.
92% of data analysts are
intercepted proactively before
they ever reach production reports.
And 43% reduction pipeline
maintenance score freeing up
both budget and bandwidth.
When I think about my experience at
Capital One and capital where even
small data IRS could ripple into
complex risks, having AI practically
catch issues before the surface is in.
Just a time saver.
It's a risk user.
This isn't just about automation.
It's about elevating the entire
role of data engineering into a
more strategic, proactive function.
Oh, first, like AWS Glue, S Serverless,
ETL platform that uses, machine
learning to automatically detect
data schemas and generate mappings.
This drastic drastically reduces
the need for manual coding,
accelerating the time it takes to
integrate and prep, prepare data.
Next Databricks Auto Loader, which
brings intelligent data ingestion
with built-in schema evaluation.
Handling this tool ensures that changing
data structure doesn't break your
pipelines by dynamically adjusting to
new fields or formats as they arrive.
And finally, anomaly detection system.
These leverage machine learning
to continuously scan data
flows for unusual patterns.
They proactively identify anomalies
and potential issues before they impact
business decisions or downstream systems.
If you look at the chart,
you'll see dramatic improvements
across four key areas.
Inquiry query creation time
was cut by more than half.
Debugging time dropped from nearly
90 minutes to about 30, 30 minutes.
Error rates also reduces significantly,
and performance during tuning time was
slash from two hours to under an hour.
Overall, the firms are seeing 65,
60 4% of productivity increase.
This demonstrate how AI not
only speeds a protein task.
But also improves accuracy and performance
in SQL development workflows, or the
transformation development workflows.
This slide shows how AI is
transforming pipeline maintenance
with self-healing data pipelines.
It starts by automatically detecting
anomalies, machine learning models,
fla unusual data patterns before
they snowball into bigger issues.
Then the system moves to diagnose
the issue co using root cause
analysis to classify what went wrong.
Once the cost is are identified,
it moves into the apply fix stage,
pulling an automated correction
from a prebuilt library of solution.
No manual intervention required.
Finally, it enters.
A learn and improve where
the solution is recorded.
So the system keeps getting
smarter and faster at fixing
similar issues in the future.
Future.
This closer loop approach reduces
downtime, boosts reliability, and
shifts engineering engineers away from
firefighting towards strategic work.
We are looking at quality validation
frameworks, which are critical for
maintaining trust in our, in the data
pipelines, especially as we scale with
ai, it starts with defining expectation,
setting rules, either based on domain
expertise or even automatically
discovering patterns from the data itself.
Then we test continuously, not just at the
end, but validating data at every stage.
Like ingestion, transformation and
pre-published, if something fails, those
checks we don't have to jump in manually.
Instead, an auto remediate layer
kicks in, applying machine learning,
recommended fixes for common issues.
And finally, we monitor metrics over
time to track both data quality scores
and how effective our fixes really are.
This process.
Shifts us from react to firefighting
to P to continuous data quality
assurance, something that's incredibly
value in high stakes environment
like a finance or the government.
Let's talk about where we are
and why, where we are heading.
This slides lays out an industry adoption
timeline for ai powder data engineering.
In 2023 to 24, we have seen AI
equal assistance and automated sche
mine inference becoming mainstream
tools in many organizations.
Moving into 24 and 25 were on top
for self-healing pipelines, automated
anomaly detection and correction,
reaching about 60% enterprise adoption.
By 25 and 26, the industry
shifts towards self.
Optimizing systems where infrastructure
dynamically scales and allocate
resources based on business priorities
and looking ahead into 26 and 27.
The big milestone is fully autonomous
data platforms, autonomous data
platform systems that monitor,
monitor, optimize, and remediate
with a minimal human oversight.
The key takeaway, the AI is.
In data engineering isn't
theoretical anymore.
It's a fast moving wave that's
fundamentally changing how we design,
operate, and scale data platforms.
Now that we have seen the potential
of AI in data engineering,
let's talk about how to actually
implement it in a structured way.
This framework has four key steps.
First, assess opportunities.
Look for the RE two hire
first task in your workflows.
This could be manual schema
mapping, tedious data
validation, or re two debugging.
Next, start small.
Don't try to automate everything at once.
Pick one critical pro pipeline or the
process and test a automation there.
Third, measure impact.
Track time, save
improvements in data quality.
And even team satisfaction
to prove the value.
And finally, once you have shown success,
scale gradually expand what work to more
pipelines and parts of your data pla
platform retrospect your like, previous
experience from existing pipelines.
This approach helps.
Reduce risk while ensuring adoption
is sustainable and measurable.
The key takeaways
of this presentation, the first
one is Yay, is transforming ETL.
From manual to autonomous, we are seeing
up to 85% reduction in schema mapping
effort, and 43% cut in maintenance cost.
Second, a self failing pipelines
proactively catch 92% of anomalies
before the cost downstream issues.
That's a huge boost in
data quality and trust.
Third, start small, but start today.
Pick one high effort repeated to process
to automate for quick wins and momentum.
And finally, free your
team for strategic work.
Okay.
Every hour saved on maintenance is an hour
unlock for innovation and business value.
Thank you so much.
Excited to see how we all move forward in
this AI driven future of data engineering.
Thank you so much.