Speaker 26: Hello everyone.
My name is Sapna and I'm ASAP
consultant with Ansen Young's
Technology Consulting practice.
During today's talk, if you have
any questions, please feel free
to reach out to me via LinkedIn.
Today's topic in discussion is
governing data som in distributed
multi-cloud machine learning systems.
As organizations scale machine
learning globally, the question is
no longer whether we can run machine
learning across clouds, but how do
we do so while staying compliant with
increasingly stick data sovereignty laws?
Multi-cloud machine learning has
fundamentally changed our how
organizations process and analyze data.
By leveraging mul multiple cloud
providers, companies can tap into
the best of the breed services,
improve scalability, and build
redundancy into machine learning.
This approach reduces vendor lock-ins,
strengthens disaster recovery, and
allows teams to dynamically allocate
resources based on real time demand,
often reducing the overall costs.
At its core, multi-cloud machine learning
enables faster innovation and greater
resilience, but that flexibility comes
with a new layer of governance complexity.
Now increase in data sovereignty
regulations the same time that
multi-cloud adoption is accelerating.
Data sovereignty
regulations are tightening.
Worldwide governments are increasingly
asserting control over where
data is stored, processed, and
assessed, especially when that
data crosses national borders for
organizations running distributed,
mul, machine learning workloads.
This creates real tension between
global scale and local compliance.
There are three major challenges
that consistently emerge.
First, ensuring lawful data, residency
and control across mult multiple clouds
is non-negotiable for compliance.
Second, organizations must
maintain full auditability of
data movement and processing.
In mul, in a multi-cloud
environment, tracing data lineage
can quickly become complex.
And third, regulatory consistency
is difficult to achieve when
global laws differ sometimes
significantly across regions.
Let's look at some of
these different laws.
Several legal frameworks shape
how organizations govern data.
Today.
The GDPR or the General Data Protection
Regulation Act mandates strict standards
for data privacy and protection across
the European Union, and has influenced
data governance practices worldwide.
In the United States, the Cloud Act
allows law enforcement to access data
held by US based companies, even if that
data is stored overseas, introducing
additional cross border considerations.
Meanwhile, China's cybersecurity law
enforces strong data localization and
cross-border transfer requirements making.
Compliance essential for
operating in that market.
Together these laws force organizations
to think carefully about where
their data lives, who can access
it, and under what legal authority.
Let's look at the legal mandates and
governance data residency mandates, direct
influence, cloud architecture decisions.
Organizations must design systems
that ensure data is stored, processed
within defined geographic boundaries.
Equally important are
robust access controls.
Limiting data access to
authorized personal only.
Not only strengthens security, but
also aligns with legal and regulatory
requirements across jurisdictions.
Now, what are the key standards
for multi-cloud governance?
To operationalize compliance organizations
rely on established standards.
IO 2 7 0 1 8 provides guidance
for protecting personal data
in public cloud environments.
CSS STAR or the Crowd Security
Alliance Star Program offers a
structured framework to evaluate
and certify cloud security controls.
NISG 853 serves as a foundational
reference for security and privacy
controls, especially for regulated
industries and government aligned systems.
These standards provide a
common language for governance
across diverse cloud platforms.
Now what happens when organizations
lack are lacking data flow visibility?
The visibility gap in data flows.
Despite these frameworks many
organizations still lack clear
visibility into how data moves across
providers without end-to-end visibility.
Risks increase.
Whether that's unauthorized access.
Accidental cross-border
transfers or failed audits.
Visibility is a prerequisite
for effective governance.
Now, how do we tackle this?
One emerging solution is the
use of sovereign cloud zones.
These zones localize data storage and
processing within specific jurisdictions,
helping organizations meet regional
compliance requirements while still
benefiting from cloud scalability.
Sovereign cloud zones enable
global expansion without
sacrificing data control.
They also will trust with local customers
and partners by demonstrating a clear
commitment to regional privacy standards.
As cloud architectures mature, sovereign
cloud zones are becoming a cornerstone
of compliant digital infrastructure.
Zero trust framework.
Another critical frame pillar is
the zero trust data framework.
Zero trust assumes no implicit trust.
F. Every access request
is continuously verified.
This approach ensures data remains
protected throughout its lifecycle, even
if it moves across clouds and regions.
In distributed machine learning
systems, zero Trust is essential
for minimizing exposure and
enforcing least privilege access.
Compliance automation for
scalable go governance.
Now, manual compliance simply
doesn't scale in a multi-cloud world.
Automation enables real-time
monitoring of regulatory requirements
and immediate response to changes.
Automated policy enforcement ensures
consistent controls across cloud
providers reducing human error.
Equally important is automated audit
trail generation, providing transparent,
detailed records of data access
and processing that sorry, support,
accountability, and simplify audits.
Along with this balanced governance
ensures effective governance architectures
must align with regional regulations
while preserving operational efficiency.
At the same time, governance
frameworks must remain flexible to
support innovation, scalability, and
rapid response to regulatory change.
Compliance should enable the
business not slow it down.
Cross region machine learning governance,
cross region machine learning governance.
When machine learning pipe pipeline
span regions and provides providers,
governance becomes even more critical.
Organizations need unified frameworks
that manage data residency, access,
security, and compliance across.
The entire machine learning lifecycle
from training to inference, to retaining,
retraining, strong cross region
governance ensures machine learning
remains both powerful and compliant.
In closing, governing data
sovereignty in distributed multi-cloud
environments is no longer optional.
It is strategic.
By combining legal awareness, strong
standards, sovereign architectures,
zero trust principles, and
compliance automation organizations
can unlock the full potential
of multi-cloud machine learning
securely, responsibly, and at scale.
Thank you for your time today.