Hello everyone.
My name is Swap Neil, and the
topic of today's discussion is
going to be to cover one of the
critical use cases in conversational
ai which is AI summarization.
Generative AI is the process which
ingests large amount of data.
Mostly for the scope of this discussion,
we are going to cover actual data.
And AI summarization is a technique
used to generate some insights
from large amount of text data to
summarize certain topics that are
covered as part of any communication.
The textual data can be of variety
of formats and a variety of
applications generate textual data.
But for the scope of this.
Discussion.
We will deep dive into utilization of
generative AI for business use cases.
So when we talk about business
communications any communication that the
business handles is between the consumers
of the business and then let's say the
sales, marketing or customer service
departments of that business in addition.
For the business to run smoothly.
The business representatives and
employees would also be interacting
with their coworkers for variety
of different business processes.
So we can think of it as an internal
conversation between the business as
well as an external conversation that
the business has with its customers.
So we can think of customer trying to
reach customer service representative
for a business using a chat bot that is
offered on their website, or they write an
email to the customer service department.
Or sometimes there might be a
shopping assistant that is there on
the website and the person might be
interacting with the shopping assistant.
And then asking for
product recommendations.
And eventually when they're ready
to make a payment, they might have
a question and they might reach
out to an expert to seek opinion.
So they might write an email
or they might continue chatting
with a customer service agent.
So a variety of different
business use cases.
Generate business conversations.
And the data is mostly text based.
So for the scope of this presentation,
we will cover some of the architectural
challenges in developing AI
systems for summarizing message
and email channel content across
different business communications.
So to get started, we'll explore
some of the critical hurdles in
building an AI summarization system.
Some of those hurdles I've listed here
are model hallucination, inherent biases,
data distribution shifts, information
preservation, and then contextual
understanding and contextual awareness.
So we will present certain
architectural approaches and
methodological frameworks that you can.
Adopt to address these
business challenges.
So the focus would be on developing
robust AI summarization system that can
operate for a single thread communication,
multi-threaded communication between
multiple people or even cover
different departments of a business.
Let's look at how the digital
communication have evolved for
business interactions and what
areas they affect for a business.
So for a typical day a customer service
agent who is interacting with business
customers might be interacting on.
Social channels, they might be interacting
with customers for email or they might
be having a live chat with the customers.
So on an average they spend about
five and a half hours out of a eight
hour workday on active communication.
So it is a significant portion of
the day at a contact center for a
customer service department spending.
This much amount of time managing digital
communications drafting documents,
generating invoices, exchanging
emails with the customer, sometimes
escalating things to their coworkers
or business partners, and then doing
a wrap up of their interaction with
the customer to give them a summary.
So a variety of different use cases.
Can be solved with AI summarization
and introduction of instant
messaging through Facebook Messenger,
WhatsApp, iMessages, et cetera.
Just increases the kind of applications
that are generating text for businesses.
Why it is important for
mediums size businesses.
To focus on digital communication
channels is because it is crucial not
only to have a good customer service
interaction for loyalty purposes, but
also making sure the customer needs
are resolved at the end of the day.
As well as having the right tools
at hand definitely leverages certain
improvements in the business.
That can be driven by ai.
If AI summarization is introduced
as part of the business, the use
case become even more complex when
we talk about multi-threaded emails.
So imagine you reaching out to a customer
service representative regarding your
concern, exchanging emails with them,
attaching proofs or your concerns, and
then having transferred over to another.
Customer service represe, and then
having them to go through all of that
over again and then having you to repeat
all the information it's an frustrating
customer experience, and this can easily
be solved by utilizing AI summarization
for emails, especially multi-threaded
emails where multiple people are involved.
There's a long trail of emails
and then some key information
is being exchanged in the email.
Customers are looking for
a speedy resolution without
having to repeat themselves.
So what's the impact of the AI
assisted Communication management
systems in the businesses today?
So it has been proven that businesses
have reduced the time spent on routine
communication tasks significantly.
Which allows more focused time for
the business representatives to
attend other strategic initiatives
for the business and run the business
for essentially driving it forward.
Whereas before more time would
be spent on active communication.
So this can be even leveraged
further with AI summarization.
The key challenge here is maintaining
the right balance between.
So summarization efficiency and
information retention so that
the context gets carried from.
Now let's take a look at how we
can achieve and highly efficient
AI summarization system.
So I would like to break it down into
three major layers for data processing.
Firstly, at the bottom we
have a strong foundation.
Of text processing.
So this is crucial for any
ization system to have a very
strong text processing pipeline.
It involves multiple activities
such as text, normalization,
text organization, and filtering.
So let's look at what
text normalization is.
So it involves a variety of techniques
such as converting uppercase to
lowercase, removing punctuation marks.
Expanding on certain abbreviations that
might be present in the conversation.
Converting numbers, currencies,
and dates into words so that it
is relevant for text processing.
Normalization is crucial for a variety
of applications like search engines or
text-based workflows and machine learning.
And this is.
At the high level an overview of the
text normalization, and the main goal
of this is to reduce ambiguity and
improve the overall model performance.
Now let's talk about text tokenization.
So tokenization kind of simplifies
complex text by dividing it into smaller,
manageable components, which allows
easier processing of the natural language.
So there are different
types of text tokenization.
We can split individual
words into characters.
We can split a sentence into words.
We can split a paragraph into sentences.
So a variety of different tokenization
techniques can be utilized depending on
the use case that you're trying to solve.
So the next layer about
that is semantic analysis.
So semantic analysis analyzes
the grammatical format of the
sentences, including arrangement
of words, phrases, and clauses.
And the main goal behind semantic
analysis is to establish relationships
between the independent terms
identified as part of text processing.
So this is something you can think
of it as identifying the actors.
The system who are actively
participating in the conversation.
And then what is the relation
between those actors whether your
text is semantically correct.
So all that is crucial.
Before we can attempt generating a
summary based on the text at the very top
we have the summary generation aspect.
So this is largely
dependent on the efficiency.
Success of the bottom two layers.
So if we take this heretical
approach and if we combine this text
processing with certain optimization
techniques like data caching,
reducing latencies with multithreaded
systems, and those four significant
advantages or mono architectures.
While maintaining superior accuracy.
So we'll cover this in more
detail in the upcoming slides.
So one of the key considerations for a
highly efficient AI summarization system
is that the analysis of a large scale
messaging data require certain data
flow architectures to handle complex.
Threading patterns while
maintaining the data consistency.
So we need certain components as part of
architecture, and those would be scalable
message processing systems or message
use, essentially that can be utilized to
effectively manage concurrent processes.
And this is like a divide
and conquer strategy where.
Complex tasks can be broken down into
multiple threads, which can be executed
in parallel, and then we can have
a governing thread that can stitch
together all the insights driven by the
different threads, and eventually present
complete picture for data integrity.
Now let's take a look at the next.
Key challenges.
So here I'm covering top
three considerations.
One is hallucination detection,
other one is quality metrics,
and then performance accuracy.
And what are the trade offs?
So let's take a look
at hallucination first.
So hallucination as the word indicates
is something that is not factual.
In the world of generative
AI hallucination is an
important problem to solve.
And having the right systems in place to
detect hallucination is also critical.
So just to give you an example, if
we want generative AI to be very
creative, let's take an example of
using chat GPT for composing a poem.
From certain text that you have.
So for such a use case, we require high
level of creativity by the generative ai.
So we would allow
hallucination in that use case.
However, when it comes to business
conversations and business communications,
we want to minimize any risks of
hallucination because if there is
hallucination it would mean that.
It is not factual for the business,
and then it can lead to significant
consequences for the business,
which is why we have to have
hallucination detection techniques
as part of the architecture.
Now, regarding quality metrics,
evaluation of any national language
processing system for that matter,
requires like comprehensive frameworks
that can effectively assess.
Multiple aspects of
the system performance.
So we need some sort of structured
evaluation techniques that can accurately
measure both the accuracy of the AI
summary that is generated, as well as it
can gauge the practical usage or practical
usability of the AI summarization system.
So while reviewing the quality
metrics, it would be apparent
to review any hallucination.
Scenarios and then flag them so that it
can be solved and avoid hallucination
for the future implementations.
So one of the considerations you
should also think of while doing
the ity analysis is introducing
automated regressions so that let's
say you are fine tuned AI summary.
To be generated for a particular
use case and you want to update
the large language model prompt.
You don't necessarily want to
break anything that you have built.
So it is important for you to
have automated digressions so
that you can catch any new issues
that may arise by prompting.
And in addition, it is
also important to have.
A human in the loop for doing any
manual reviews because you cannot
totally rely on automated regressions
if you are doing prompting.
Now let's take a look at the
performance accuracy and trade offs.
If you can think of improving the
summary accuracy, you would think.
What if I try to scale horizontally
and just add more capacity and
processing power so that my AI
summary quality is improved?
However contradictory to that
understanding research demonstrates
that the lean, the relationship
between the computational resources
spent for AI summary generation versus
the output quality is not linear.
So what that means is.
Even if you spend additional dollars
scaling horizontally, adding more
computational capacity, it does
not solve your s quality issues.
So there has to be a robust, functional
component as part of your architecture
to review the air summary quality and
then have different quality checks
as you are tuning your prompts.
Another key challenge to solve the AI
summary like fairly is generating the
output such as such that it is relevant
to the business use case, but also
it shouldn't be skewed introducing
bias against one of the metrics.
So let's take an example.
If there's a business use case, which
is about offering different pricing
models for iPhones, and depending
on the color of your iPhone, you
would be paying a different price.
So if we give this task for, to
ai some AI models it is likely
that based on the data that.
Is fed to the large language model.
It can be heavily biased towards
one gender versus another.
And then the pricing, if it
is set based on AI algorithms,
can be biased by the gender.
So this is just one of the example of
bias, but there can be a variety of
different attributes that can generate
biases for the AI summarization systems.
So how do we solve these kind of problems?
How do we solve the bias in the
A SMR and the model outputs?
So one of the key techniques is
ha carefully selecting your data.
So when you're training your
model, your data has to be neutral.
It shouldn't be skewed in favor
of one trait versus another.
That is one way of
achieving unbiased output.
The next is having sufficient data
cleaning so that any noise in the data
doesn't introduce any inherent biases.
In addition, pre-processing the
data to neutralize the dataset.
So those are some of the techniques.
Now let's take a look at one of
the most critical challenges,
which is context management.
So having the right kind of context
for any communication is critical,
whether you're talking to a robot
or you're talking to a human.
So with AI summarization, what is
critical is whatever context is there
for the communication, it is preserved.
After you summarize the text.
So identifying the right actors who are
participating in the communication and
then effectively parsing the data based
on the actors, establishing the core
relationships, and then identifying the
hierarchy of the communication based
on the timestamps, based on the actors,
based on their roles for the particular
business use case is very crucial.
For achieving a successful summary
for complex use cases such as
summarizing multi-threaded emails.
So one of the key challenges
is having logical output.
So as you are building your AI
summarization architecture, you can
have different logical checkpoints
in the system necessary for
optimizing the context so that.
The context is relevant
for your communication.
So for instance, if we come, if there
is a con conversation about an upcoming
flight reservation and a customer
is reaching customer service on a
date prior to their departure the
context is about an upcoming flight.
However, in the same conversation,
if the member sends a
follow up email a day after.
The flight reservation, most likely
they're contacting about a flight
that they missed or they had to cancel
or they lost baggage or something
related to the flight after the fact.
So with this contextual awareness, AI
summarization systems should modulate,
and the way this can be achieved
is if you have logical checkpoints.
As part of your architecture,
you will be able to achieve that.
So when I say logical checkpoint,
it means introducing certain
metadata as part of your text.
So when you're processing your
text, you could introduce certain
checkpoints based on the timestamps
in the conversation or based on who
the actor is in the conversation.
Now, if we compare.
The performance of how these AI
summarization systems perform
for different use cases if it
is a single threaded topic.
For instance, I send an email
to a customer service department
inquiring about a refund for
something I did not receive.
It is a single thread where I have a clear
intention about inquiring about something.
Then the AI summarization system detect
it as one actor and then it efficiently
summarizes the conversation, whereas for
the same email, if the customer service
respond with some information and I
send a follow up response, challenging
the outcome of the discussion, and then
the customer service agent escalates.
The conversation to a supervisor.
Now we have three actors essentially
playing a role in this conversation.
So for these multi topic threads it
is getting more complex to process
the text and identifying the actors
and establishing relationships.
So you can see that when the
complexity increases, the accuracy and
contextual awareness dips slightly.
Now let's continue the same example
and think about this use case where
the supervisor is not able to solve
the customer problem and the refer
the customer to another department.
So in this scenario, there is another
fourth factor that is introduced.
In addition, there's also a different
department that gets introduced
in the mix of the conversation.
So it is important.
For it to factor in the right kind of
expectation for the accuracy when there
is multi-threaded conversations that
span not only across different actors,
but also across different departments.
So you can see the accuracy dips even
further for cross department threats.
And then lastly, for
time critical threats.
So whenever there, there are time
critical conversations, like messages
for instance, those tend to have slightly
less amount of text to be processed.
So whenever the delta between
conversations is less, that would
mean that the model would have more
contextual awareness and then higher
accuracy, and it can finish processing in.
Now let's take a look at what drives the
success for AI summarization systems?
So having a good deployment strategy
and pushing for operational excellence
is very critical in achieving success.
So the system deployment strategies
can be having A-C-I-C-D pipeline.
Having checkpointing system, having
automated regressions, having inherent
bias detection techniques, having
hallucination detection techniques, so
all this can be streamlined as part of
your architecture as a data pipeline.
And it has proven that organizations
that invest in coming up with
a comprehensive strategy.
Planning for systematic implementation
and approaching the use case as it fits
the organization has proven like higher
success for the summarization use case.
In terms of performance optimization,
we did talk about it briefly earlier.
With multi-threaded architectures, we
can reduce the execution times and.
Wherever needed, we can have a
trade off in the storage between
caching versus long-term storage.
So there is no single strategy
that suits all use cases.
So depending on the use cases definitely
have the flexibility to implement a hybrid
architecture where you can have the best
of both worlds higher performance with.
Faster memory access with caching
versus long term storage and
reducing the processing times.
Lastly, security and scalability.
So developing a scalable security
framework is very crucial for
maintaining the system integrity
while supporting the organized growth.
For more use cases, AI related use
cases for generative ai, and as the
business is evolving, it is crucial
to come up with some AI governance
strategies so that the security of the
conversations remains intact as well as
there is a, that there are, there is a
railroad established for your use case.
So that it follows a certain pattern,
and then you've identified all the
security constraints for your risk case.
Lastly to conclude, if you want to address
hallucination bias mitigation,
dynamic data adaptation and context
preservation, then you need.
Data pipeline for it, which factors
in this as part of architecture and as
businesses rely more and more on digital
communications, these summarization
systems are going to play a very crucial
role in enhancing the overall productivity
of the organization as well as how
the information is managed across the
organization and how data is exchanged.
So by implementing these strategies
and frameworks that we discussed today.
I hope you have the tidbits needed for
creating a summarization system that
can effectively balance accuracy and
efficiency as well as it is contextual
aware to understand the customer
needs to solve the business problem.
And since this is an evolving
area, definitely have a
robust AI governance process.
Where your security of the
system does not get compromised.
Thank you very much.