Hello everyone.
I am Sunil Yadav.
I am a seasoned database administrator
with the years of experience on Oracle
E-Business Suite, Oracle Code databases
implementation upgrades, tuning.
Migrations maintenance, patching cloning
in different industries like telecom,
banking retail and various other places.
I worked on many non-oral data
databases as well, like MSSQL
server, MySQL server MongoDB.
Little bit of data analytics golden Gate
ODI and some other integrated software
technologies across different continents.
So here I am I'm going to talk
about this topic of ml, which is
machine learning powering databases.
Resilience via predictive
analytics for 99.98 percentage
of Oracle Cloud availability.
Now, as a fact, I. Database downtime,
cost any, any huge enterprise more than
9,000 US dollars per minute, which is like
typical outage goes beyond NR when we talk
about production databases, which are big
in size and complicated in architecture.
So it takes about 60 minutes to fix a
problem that cost about more than 700,000.
Dollars per incident if we
calculate the math per minute wise.
So the, our machine learning solutions,
they transform the, the Oracle cloud
reliability based on the implementations
across, you know, hundreds of
enterprise throughout the globe.
So we are going to talk about it.
So as an introduction.
Yeah.
This is what it is.
So.
Like I said, the cost of the downtime
is more than $9,000 per minute
for average production issues for
a database and which lasts for.
More than 60 minutes.
Even if it's a small problem, the,
the limitation and, you know, the
mitigation to solve the problem,
the finally fix and implementation.
And, you know, that takes this much
time, which costs more than $7,000
per incident as a total finance
impact of running a database with 99,
more than 99 percentage of uptime.
Now what is actually machine
learning based anatomy detection?
So there are three pillars
of this entire concept.
First is early detection of a problem.
So they say that more than 70% of the
problems can be identified within like 30
minutes or before they're happening, like.
Space getting filled.
CPU getting choked to more than 99%.
So there are different examples like that.
So if we detect that early,
we can prevent that early.
Okay.
Preventive action.
So, you know, it can, can that
preventive action be immediately?
Followed and to get the fix available.
That's the, the action to be taken now,
improved uptime is the solution, the
outcome of pillar one and pillar two.
So if we do one, two, we have the
improved uptime for our database.
So for machine learning,
what we need is we need to.
Ensure the deep learning of the
performance matrix is done by the database
and the entire solution to, to deliver.
So there is a pattern.
Recognition is the first step into it.
Like I mentioned in the few slides before,
pattern recognition, like if there is a
month end or quarter end, or there's a.
Peak load of application
workload going on.
So space or, you know, gets
transaction log or archive logs
start getting filled up quickly.
So if there's a patent to it, like
on few days of a month or a week,
if something like had happens.
So recognize that patent
do the action immediately.
Do and recognition should
not be in a delayed manner or
like 30 minutes or one hour.
It should be quick enough, like an
interval of five to 10 seconds so that
the pattern recognition can be identified
and action can be taken immediately.
There are invisible signals also, which
is called you can leverage the neural
networks of the entire solution to
detect the correlated pattern from the
monitoring logs to fix the problem.
Now when we talk about the entire
database, the solution is a machine
learning for uptime of 99.9.
We have different technologies like
Oracle, RAC, which is real application
clusters which provide availability
and scalability both for the entire
database platform to be available
throughout the tough times of month and
close and, or, you know, if there is a.
Disaster somewhere, or one server crashes
or something happens to the network, the
other cluster nodes are able to cater.
So, and with that, to re informance
learning of the rack will
optimize the entire solution.
So basically there are four parts to it.
One is monitoring, then
learn, optimize, and validate.
So to begin with.
The monitoring of the log
should be continuous performance
tracking of each and every log.
Like when and what happens.
When the logs are generated, what
information is GA gathered into it?
Learn from those information, the logs
which are generated and generate analyze
the pattern that anomalies into it.
Like what happens when something.
Happens like in the log, which
can be related to a patent.
Then third is to optimize when
you identify this happened.
And because of this, this
was the analysis done.
So what could be the remediation
to, to fix the problem and then.
Once that is delivered, you validate
for the res of the database that,
okay, because of this, we did this
and did that solve the problem.
So it's like feedback of the
solution and, and that's how we,
we, we reinforce the, the learning
to the entire database solution.
Now moving on to the, one of the
points which we discussed was.
Neural networks for data guard tuning.
So data guard is one, like most of you
know, who are into database technologies.
Data guard is a terminology used
by Oracle databases primarily
with for the standby databases.
So they basically.
Keep a synchronous or asynchronous copy
of the primary database to a standby
site or in the terms of replication so
that if anything happens to the primary
side, the stand back can be activated.
In case of failure, disasters or
crashes and also neural networks
for data guard tuning is basically
synchronized replication like.
Archive system should be very minimum
delay between primary and secondary, like
in sub milliseconds for the replication
lag between primary and standby databases.
So this will only ensure there is a net
zero data loss during fail or events.
Like the solution is only suitable
if there's no data loss, right?
We don't want any transaction
to be lost if there is a data.
Failover, a database failover
between primary and secondary.
Otherwise, the solution holds no
value if there is a lag, which
results in transaction loss.
So the most important thing is
there should be milliseconds of lag
between primary and second secondary.
So as soon as any transaction is
committed on the primary, it should be.
Committed or, you know, rollback or
whatever happens in the primary, it should
be image of it should be on the secondary
side within milliseconds of the gap.
And second important factor is if you
want to achieve this data guy tuning
like with milliseconds of gap, it
does not mean that the primary should
be, it should take a performance hit
because of this kind of a a millisecond
replication between primary and secondary.
So with the minimum performance impact
on the primary, the secondary should
be in sync without any data loss.
That is the most important thing,
again, after a minimum data loss.
Then of course.
The third key point is
ultra fast recovery.
So, like in Oracle there is
something called, called fast MMDR.
So like, which is whenever there is
a failover happens, it, the failover
should be quick enough that the
secondary should be available if the
there is a failover, failover occurring.
To keep it simple, we don't want.
The application to be unavailable
while the failover happens.
Now, a few seconds or a few minutes.
Of downtime probably is agreeable to
most of the enterprise applications
because there are very less enterprise
applications which demand a hundred
percent uptime because there is
always a few minutes of downtime.
So it's like 99.99 percentage
of uptime is agreeable, so.
Like I said, so ultra fast recovery
on the standby side is going to still
give you a few minutes of downtime, but
it should be happening quickly enough
so that the secondary or the failover
database should be available within
few minutes, if not less than a minute.
So yeah, that is about
the data guard tuning.
Now, moving on to,
another important point.
It's called ROI, which is rate
of, sorry, return on investment of
machine learning based resilience.
So.
What, what, what is the, the return on
investment for any enterprise company
on all this kind, this kind of machine
learning and modeling and all it, there
has to be a value to everything, right?
So with the machine learning based
resilience of databases in cloud,
Oracle Cloud they, they claim more than.
To 80% of return of investment,
meaning it delivers exceptional
financial return across enterprise
implementations over a three year period.
So whatever investment is done to today,
it's going to give more than 280% of
return within three years of time.
What does it mean?
It means the value.
Any enterprise or any organization derive
from the investment they do on this Oracle
Cloud infrastructure database as a service
or disaster recovery or any solution.
So there is a pretty nice
return on investment.
The second point is 8.4 month payback.
What does it mean is within
like accelerated investment
recovery with measurable costs,
saving from prevented outage.
So like I said, 99.9
percentage availability.
That means there are
outages which are prevented.
By using machine learning, by doing
pattern analysis, by digging the
logs, by making the analysis of the
outages that what can be prevented,
what action can be taken 30 minutes
before a pattern is recognized.
So it takes about eight months to
start paying back on this machine
learning based Oracle Cloud solution.
Again, 99.98 per availability is
ensures the, the, all the critical
systems, they are operational for 8,758
hours annually, which is like only a
few minutes of downtime is allowed.
Across the industry wide, and there are,
there are agreeable parameters through
SOC and all, all the compliance where how
many minutes are allowed of downtime to
achieve that standard of availability of.
Databases in Oracle or
any other technology.
So it basically cost, minimizes
the cost of disruptions.
So that's the plus point.
So moving to the next important
point is what actually, how
do we do machine learning?
In, in Oracle cloud computing.
So overall it's predictive
autoscaling benefits.
So what, what is predictive
autoscaling benefits?
So before going into the technical slides
and all, I'll just share one example.
Like when, when a month end happens,
we know that there will be lot of
transactions, there will be lot of
reports running in, so there'll be lot of.
Hit on the CPU of a, a
database of database server.
So autoscaling is as, as the
month had approaches and as the
system recognizes that, okay, CPU
started getting hitting the peak.
Autoscaling can enable add.
Few CPUs more as the demand grows.
So that's the predictive
auto-scaling the for a database.
Similarly for memory similarly
for storage, if there is a store
growth of databases happening
very high, at a very high rate.
So the system should be autoscaled
enough to add more space or at
least give the alerts for the system
engineer to provision more space.
So that gives some prediction for it.
So that actually helps
in avoiding many outages.
So.
Coming to the, the, what we have in
the slide is for auto-scaling benefits.
So one is resource optimization,
second is cost reduction.
So resource optimization is
machine learning models reduce over
provisioning by 47% while ensuring
capacity for unexpected workloads.
Like I said, we don't want to auto scale.
24 by 7, 365 days, right?
We want to auto scale only when the
peak load comes, which can be predicted.
So by doing this, by machine
learning models, we can reduce o
over provisioning by almost 50%,
if not LA more while ensuring the.
Unexpected workloads can be catered.
So not always provision higher,
CPU memory compute to the server.
But whenever the production is
there, then it should be there.
Otherwise it should scale down.
Second is cost direction.
So everything has a value, right?
So when we do auto scaling, it's.
Per CPU per memory any cloud organization
will charge accordingly if it is not done
predictive auto scaling or down scaling.
So by using machine learning,
we can reduce the cost depending
on the predictive workload.
So intelligent storage tier based on
access patterns decreases cost by 60%.
So if there is no load on the servers,
there's no workload, there's no
prediction, downscale the infrastructure.
That's what it means.
It helps in reducing the overall cost.
Moving to the next.
Slide.
So here we are discussing about the
case studies of 99.98, availability
of the enterprise solutions, so
finance, services, healthcare, retail.
These are, you know, few of
the top industries where Oracle
cloud compute is utilized and.
There are benefits of it, like more than
99.98 availability, which helps all these
organization meet finance, healthcare,
retail, grow their business on day-to-day
basis because there are no outages, they
can cater to their customers around the
clock, 24 by seven across the geographies
because Oracle provides, multi region
cloud-based solutions where there is
no outage and things are available in
the matter of few seconds or minutes.
Moving to the next slide, so
scalable AI framework, so this is
what we are talking about, right?
So cross architecture compatibility.
So it's not only Oracle Cloud, which
is to be, point of discussion here.
There are multiple solutions
like Azure AWS Amazon Cloud
GCP, Google Cloud IBM Cloud.
So machine learning runs through, cuts
through all these scalable AI framework
to get what information is required for.
The enterprise solution to
work efficiently, effectively.
Second is automated anomaly detection.
So it's not that manually they,
these have to be analyzed by
DBA or a engineer sitting there.
But there are automated jobs which
can, which are, which can be scheduled
to capture the logs and information,
and later on analysis is done.
For, to be able to publish the reports
and boost the operational efficiency.
Overall, it's all about efficiency, right?
Thank the next point is
engineering productivity.
So it frees data I. Teams
from manual process.
Like I said, it's all automated jobs.
Once the jobs are there, you can
customize the jobs as per your need,
and you can enable the focus on
high priority task and innovation.
Right?
Other than the mundane manual jobs.
Now coming to the last topic of
the discussion, so transforming
data base resilience, so.
There are four steps to it.
You discover the problem, identify the
the pattern, you implement the solution
using deploy machine learning driven
monitoring and optimization tool.
Tools, then you optimize what you have
learned from, from there, and then you
archive you, sorry, you achieve your
99.98% availability while reducing
the overall running cost of the
entire enterprise architect solution.
Yeah.
So team this is about the presentation.
I thank you for all your
time and listening to me.
You have a good day.
Thanks.
Bye.