Hello and welcome.
I'm Kota and I'm excited to share
with you our work on real time fraud
detection for e-commerce platforms.
Specifically, we focus on stopping
fake reviews, which have become
a major threat to customer
trust and marketplace integrity.
I always read reviews before
I buy something online.
Once I saw a toaster review,
which has five stars because
it changed someone's life.
Now that's a powerful appliance
or it's really a bad fake review.
Jokes aside fake reviews
like that can really mislead.
People.
And today I'll walk you through
challenges we face, the system
we that was built and how it's
already making an impact on scale.
Let's go.
Go ahead.
So now we are in marketplace
integrated challenge.
E-commerce thrives on trust today.
Every time you buy something online,
you probably check the reviews first.
You trust those reviews are
harnessed, written by real people
who actually use the product.
But fake reviews actually break the test.
Imagine buying something highly rated only
to find, it's nothing like the reviews.
You feel cheated and you might think again
twice before shopping on that platform.
This is a real danger.
And it doesn't just affect customers.
Harness sellers are even pushed down by
the competitors who achieve the system,
and even platforms lose credibility.
I. Now frauds.
These fraudsters are not just
writing random fake reviews.
They're running some coordinated
campaigns using many fake accounts.
These accounts are often well planned
with detailed profiles and the post
reviews in a way that they look
natural and the faster they post.
The more damage they cause.
That's why speed is critical if we don't
catch these fake reviews as they happen.
They influence buying decisions and can
lead to major financial lo losses for
both sellers and as well as platforms.
Now, how do we solve this?
In order to solve this we built a
system designed for speed and scale.
First, we use Apache Kafka to
handle the flow of reviews.
Think of Kafka as a
real time data pipeline.
It can handle like millions of
reviews per second, and it's even
fault tolerant, meaning even if
something goes wrong, it keeps working.
Next we process the
data using Apache Flink.
Flink is a powerful, is very
powerful for stream processing,
allowing us to react to new data
with like sub millisecond latency.
This means we can even detect
fraud as it's happening.
Then our fraud detection model kicks in.
These models are deployed in
a horizontally scalable way.
As traffic increases we just add more.
Server and predictions still
happen in just a few milliseconds.
Finally, to find more complex fraud,
like group of fake accounts, we can
actually use a custom graph database.
This database helps us map
relationships between accounts
reviews, products, allowing us to
uncover all the hidden patterns.
That suggest a coordinated
fraud that's happening.
Now let's talk about so this is, now
that we have seen an architecture
behind that system, let's dive deep
into how we actually detect the fraud
specif, specifically how our systems
make decisions about whether a review
is genuine or fake, use a hybrid
approach, and why a hybrid approach.
Fraud isn't just one dimensional.
It doesn't always look the same.
Some fraudsters even might use simple
and repetitive language interviews.
Others might try to behave like
normal users, but post at really
strange times or coordinate on groups.
Because of this, relying on just one
detection method would leave gaps.
That's why we use a
hybrid detection approach.
Combining several powerful techniques
that together create much more
reversed and accurate detection system.
Let me walk through the key
components of this approach.
First ensemble edition models
like we use ensemble learning.
Think of like team of specialists
where each model and the and symbol
focuses on different kind of signals.
One model might specialize in
detecting unusual posting times.
Another might analyze the content of
the review, yet another might look
at the history of that user account.
These models work together and
combined result is often more reliable
than any single model acting alone.
Example, one example would be like,
imagine one model says that this review
is fake because of the timing, but
another says this language looks okay.
When combined, the ensemble can weigh
these opinions and decide more accurately.
This method helps us reach high precision
rate, meaning we can make fewer mistakes
when flagging something as fake.
Next we bring graph neural networks.
This is where we move from looking
at individual reviews, to looking at
connections between users and reviews.
Fraud is often coordinated.
A multiple accounts might work
together to boost a product
or even damage a competitor.
Janin help us analyze
who is connected to whom.
They look at pattern across entire network
sporting clusters of suspicious activity.
For example, if 10 accounts are frequently
reviewed, reviewing the same products
around same times, and they're giving very
similar ratings, that's the sign might
be part of a coordinated fraud Group.
Journals allow us to visualize and
analyze this behavior effectively.
Behavioral analytics is the next one.
We also look at like the user behavior.
How often the user is posting reviews?
Do they really post at times
when users, most users don't?
Are they interacting with
products in ways that.
Don't make sense.
This helps us catch anomalous behavior
that might be visible in the text
or in the network connections.
Example, if if a user suddenly posts
reviews in 10 minutes or only ever
reviews products in one category from one
seller, it actually resists a red flag.
Behavioral analytics.
Analytics is very crucial
for early detection.
Often we can catch fraud starts
as they begin their activities.
Next is natural language crossing.
Finally, we analyze the text
of the reviews themselves using
natural language crossing.
Fake reviews often use overly
positive language, like they
follow similar pattern across.
Multiple reviews contain generic
or template like sentences.
I. Our NLP tools analyze the structure
of review, like syntax, semantics,
used word choice, even identifies signs
that it was generated or manipulated.
If for example, like if fire reviews are
poster on the same product, I'll say this
is the best product I have ever bought.
Highly recommended in
nearly identical phrasing.
N LP can flag this as likely fake.
We can also detect a machine generated
text, which is becoming more common
as fraudsters use AI tools themselves.
Putting all these four together
each of these methods like enseal
models, gnn peer analytics and NLP
brings a unique perspective alone.
They can miss things together, they
create a multi-layered defense.
This hybrid EPO approach allows us
to be faster, more accurate, and more
adaptive as fraud techniques evolve.
And most importantly, this layer method.
This layer method helps us to
reduce false postures, so real
reviews don't get wrongly flagged
and it also improves recall, so
we catch more of the actual fraud.
Let's dive a little deeper into how
our hybrid detection system performs.
When we talk about performance we are
mainly looking at three key metrics,
precision recall, and F1 score precision.
This tells us out of all the
reviews that were flagged as fake,
how many were actually flake.
Fake, sorry.
A high pressure means that we
are making fewer mistakes and
we say something is fraudulent.
Recall.
This actually tells us out of all
fake reviews out there, how many
we actually caught a high recall
means we are not missing much.
And then there is this F1 score.
Which is a balance between
precision and recall.
It's a great, like a great measure of
the overall effectiveness of the system.
Now, why this is important, like
'cause many fraud detection systems
might be like too strict or too loose.
A strict system can actually catch
a lot of fake reviews, but also flag
real ones that's bad for user trust.
A loose system might let too
many fake reviews slip through.
That hybrid approach, we
strike a right balance.
Our ion is high.
So when we say a review
is fake, it usually is.
Our recall is also strong, meaning we
catch more fake reviews that are out
there together, gives us an F1 score
that is significantly better than
just using single detection method.
For example, like when we compare just
using NLP alone, we notice that it's
struggle with detection, detecting
more fraud, like when fraudsters were
slightly more natural sounding text.
Behavioral models alone might f mis fake
accounts that don't just post often.
Graph based models are strong,
but need more data to kick in.
By combining all these three, we
cover each other's blind spots.
That's why our performance
is better across the board.
Next is one of the most complex and
dangerous types of fraud we face
are coordinated campaigns, fraud,
fraudsters don't always act alone.
They often operate in groups.
They've been set up multiple fake
accounts, often over weeks or months,
and then launch an attack, like
pushing fake reviews all at once
to promote or damage a product.
Now many systems can only detect
this type of fraud after it
becomes very obvious, like when
hundreds of accounts are involved.
But our system is designed
for early detection.
We can even catch these campaigns
when there are as few as eight
accounts working together.
How?
How do we do that first?
We actually set thresholds for
what's considered suspicious.
For example, if eight accounts post
reviews on the same product within short
time window and they never interacted with
that product before, that's suspicious.
Then we use graph analysis.
We create a map of relationships,
who posted what, when, and where.
If we see the tight clusters
of that activity that don't
match normal user behavior, that
can be treated as a red flag.
Now, what's unique is that we don't need
massive data to start detecting fraud.
Our systems use temporal pattern analysis,
which allows to spot fraud from minimal
activity, giving us major advantage.
This early detection reduces the
impact of fraud instead of reacting
after the damage is done, we prevent
it from spreading in the first place.
Now, let's shift gears and talk
about privacy, which is a huge
concern today, stopping fraud.
Is very important, but doing
it while protecting user
data is even more important.
Users trust pla these platforms,
not just with their money,
but with their information.
We use several cutting edge techniques
to keep the data safe, use federated
learning, like instead of pulling all
the user data into one central place
to train our models, we train these
models locally in defense service.
This means like sense two data would
never go of the original system.
The model learns from the data,
but the data itself stays put.
Differential privacy.
Even when we aggregate results, we add
bit of mathematical noise to the data.
This ensures that no one can trace
a result pack to a specific user.
The balance here is key, where we maintain
high accuracy but without risking privacy.
Encrypted inference.
This is really advanced.
Using homomorphic encryption,
we can actually process
data while it's encrypted.
Imagine being able to check for fraud
without ever seeing the raw data.
This protects users even further,
especially in a regulated environments.
Why is this important?
'cause many fraud detection systems
compromise privacy by needing
access to detailed user data.
Us doesn't we respect users'
privacy while still keeping fraud
detection fast and even accurate.
Now let's talk about scalability.
How well our system handle growth.
E-commerce platforms face
huge spikes in traffic.
Think like on Black Friday or even holiday
sales or flash deals during these times.
The volume of reviews can
increase by five times or more.
Our system is designed
to scale seamlessly.
It can handle five x more traffic
without any slowdown, even at peak times.
It keeps the response time
low around 10 milliseconds.
We achieve this near linear scaling.
This means if you double our
servers performance almost doubles.
Just about 5% overhead.
Also, as the traffic doubles, CPN memory
usage only grows by about 1.5 x times.
This keeps the system efficient.
This is very important because
fraudsters also strike during bus
busy periods, knowing that detection
systems might be overwhelmed.
Our system, we can confidently say
no matter how big the traffic search,
fraud detection continues smoothly with
no compromise on speed or accuracy.
Next, moving to production deployment,
I. This system isn't just in a test
environment, it is actually running live,
and the result speaks for themselves.
It's deployed across like 12
major e-commerce platforms,
handling like billions of reviews.
We have even seen a 78% drop in fake
reviews, meaning that our detection system
is working in real world conditions.
We have also seen a 94%
reduction in false positives.
Which means real reviews are staying up
and users aren't being wrongly penalized.
High availability is key.
Like our system runs with 99 per
0.99% uptime, even if something goes
wrong in one part of the system.
We have this redundant infrastructure
and geographical distribution,
so the systems keep running and
we just don't stop improving.
Our models are retrained daily basis.
When we detect these new fraud patterns,
the system adapts within 24 hours,
keeping us ahead of evolving threats.
This kind of real world performance
shows that system is reliable,
adaptable, and effective at scale.
Now let's take a closer look at how
we build a system to be flexible,
efficient, and able to evolve over time.
Fraud patterns are generally
constantly changing and our system
needs to adapt quickly without
d downtime or performance loss.
Here is how we have designed for that.
First, we're using mic microservice
based architecture like our system is.
Built on microservices.
This means like each component, like
data ingestion, fraud detection, or
graph analysis, it's de developed
and deployed independently.
If we want to upgrade just our
NLP model, we can do that without
touching the GNN or behavioral nce.
It also makes the system resilient.
If one part needs maintenance or scaling,
the other keeps running smoothly.
For example, we recently introduced
a new detection algorithm spec
specifically for flash shell fraud.
We rolled it out just that part of system
without disrupting the entire platform.
Next is data structure optimization.
To make the system not only scalable,
but even resource efficient,
we optimized our data handling.
We use customs Pass Graph
Representations, which means like we
don't store unnecessary connections.
This reduces our memory footprint by 40%
with allow, allowing us to handle
more data with fewer resources.
And it also improves query
performance by three three x. So
when we need to check a suspicious
user connections, it happens fast.
Stateful Next is Stateful
Processing with Apache Flink.
Many fraud patterns emerge over time.
We use stateful processing with Flink
and R DB as a backend to store user
actions and context over extended periods.
This lets us detect fraud that
develops gradually, like an account
that behaves well for months.
Then suddenly act it
becomes act two in fraud.
We don't just look at
these isolated events.
We even track the behavior
over time, adding depth to
our detection capabilities.
Next is deployment pipelines.
We use use rapid updates.
Rapid updates are really critical
in frightening this fraud We have.
Set up an automated continuous integration
or continuous deployment pipelines.
This means every time we improve
a model or add edition rule,
we can test it, validate it,
and deploy it without downtime.
We use AB testing framework to test all
these new features on a small percentage
of data before rolling them out.
Widely canary deployments help also help
us monitor new changes in production,
ensuring stability and performance.
Next, developer productivity and rapid
experimentation like this architecture
also supports rapid experimentation
where data scientists can deploy and
test new models in a sandbox environment.
Once these are validated, those
models can be integrated into
production pipeline very quickly.
This kind of architecture
keeps our system future proof.
Now, as fraudsters develop new tactics,
we are equipped to respond faster with
minimal overhead and with confidence that
we can say we can deploy safely at scale.
Now let's talk about highlight
about key takeaways from everything
that we have discussed today.
Speed matters.
Fraud detection needs to happen instantly.
If fake reviews linger,
they impact trust and sales.
Our system directs fraud in under like
10 milliseconds, ensuring users only
see high quality trustworthy reviews.
Realtime detection is in just a feature.
It's a necessity in today's
fast-paced e-commerce environment.
Accuracy through multimodal detection.
No single model can capture all fraud.
Our hybrid approach uses and simple
models, nns Behavioral Analytics
and NLP imp, where it improves
detection accuracy by up to 38%.
We have reduced false positives so
that real users aren't penalized
and we have improved recall.
So we catch more fraud than the
existing traditional systems.
This is Privacy by design.
Federated learning ensures
that data stays local.
No raw data moves.
Differential privacy is next thing,
which adds noise to aggregated reserves,
so individual users remain anonymous.
Homomorphic encryption allows analysis.
Without decryption, offering
another layer of protection as user
trust is more than catching more
important than catching a fraud.
It's about safeguarding the
data every step of the way.
Next, scalable architecture.
Our system handles billions of
reviews even during five traffic
surges such as Black Friday or
even major product launches.
We achieved this near linear scaling.
We add capacity smoothly
without compromising performance
even as traffic grows.
CPUN, memory usage grow efficiently.
And finally, this is a
proven impact in production.
This isn't even a theoretical.
We are alive on 12 major platforms,
where with 78% fewer fake reviews
and 20% fewer false positives
with 99% plus percent uptime even
during failures or traffic spikes.
Daily model retraining with
24 hour eruption to new.
Fraud trends
only in short, our system is fast
enough to act before fraud spreads.
Accurate enough to detect complex,
evolving fraud, private enough to
protect our user data without compromise.
And scalable enough to serve
the world's largest e-commerce
platform without a hitch.
Thank you so much for your attention.
I hope you found this presentation
valuable and that it gave you a
clear sense of how we are advancing
fraud detection for modern age.
Wrapping up, if you need any
further information or explore
this topic deeper, feel free to.
Reach me out.
Thanks again for watching and I hope
you enjoy the rest of the conference.
Thank you.