Hey everyone.
I'm Portola Senior product Security
engineer, and today I'll be talking
about how machine learning is
transforming security in DevOps
pipelines for cloud native applications.
We are facing a critical inflection
point in cybersecurity with 94% of
enterprises now using cloud services
and AI powered cyber attacks.
Increasing by 63% since 2022.
Traditional security approaches
simply can't keep the pace anymore.
What I'll share today is how
the machine learning algorithms
integrated into DevSecOps.
Pipelines are revolutionizing the cloud
security while allowing the organizations
to maintain rapid development cycles.
The data is compelling that organizations
using machine learning powered security
tools experience 71% fewer security
incidents and deploy the secure code
three times faster than those using
the conventional security models.
Now let's dive into the
changing security landscape.
Let's first understand that
evolving security landscape that's
driving this transformation,
we are seeing an unprecedented.
Cloud adoption stage with 94% of
enterprises now using cloud services, this
creates complex security challenges across
increasingly distributed architectures.
At the same time, cyber attacks
leveraging artificial intelligence
have increased 63% since 2022.
Outpacing the traditional defense
mechanisms, the attackers are
getting smarter and we need
to match that intelligence.
This creates what I call the
security development gap.
Conventional security models simply
cannot match the speed of modern
development cycles, creating the
dangerous vulnerability windows.
And the good news is a new defense
paradigm has emerged machine
learning enhanced security tools
provide a 71% reduction in security
incident while enabling the
three time faster deployments.
This is the transformation
we'll explore today.
Now coming to the machine learning
enhanced security tools performance
metrics, the data behind machine learning
enhanced security tools is compelling.
Let me walk you through the
key performance metrics.
The organization's implementing
machine learning powered security tools
have witnessed dramatic improvements
across the key performance indicators.
The most significant gains have
been in container security with 89%
reduction in vulnerabilities and the
meantime to remediation, which decrease
from 38 days to just over four days.
That's an 89% improvement.
These are in the theoretical numbers.
These metrics are based on the
data collected from over 500
enterprise implementations.
Notice the development speed bar.
It's off the charts because these
tools enable security to become an
accelerator rather than a blocker.
So supervised learning for
vulnerability detection.
Now let's look at these specific
machine learning approaches.
Starting with supervised starting
with the supervised learning models
that are trained on mass data sets
of known vulnerabilities, code
patterns, and the associated risks.
These models learn to identify similar
patterns in new code flagging potential
security issues before the deployment.
The crucial advantages that by
continuously learning from new
vulnerability data, these systems
improve detection accuracy over time and
adapt to the emerging threat patterns.
Let me share a concrete implementation
example with Snyk In 2024 Snyk Machine
Learning enhanced scanning detected
78% of vulnerabilities before the
production compared to just 31%.
With traditional static analysis
tool, the tool is analyzed both
application code and the dependencies.
The integration into Series CICD pipelines
allows for automatic vulnerability
detection, identification, using
commit and build phases, allowing.
Developers to address
the issues immediately.
Now, let's dive into the unsupervised
learning for an anomaly detection.
While supervised learning is excellent
for non threats, unsupervised learning
excels at identifying previously unknown
threats by detecting deviations from
the established behavioral patterns.
This approach involves four key
elements, which is behavioral
analysis, identifying the patterns
outside normal operational parameters.
The baseline establishment, creating
normal operation profiles across
the environments and the continuous
monitoring, the real time inspection of
applications and infrastructure behavior.
And the last one is self-learning models
adapting to evolving the environments
without explicit programming.
Unlike the rule-based systems, these
models can spot novel attack vectors
and zero vulnerabilities by recognizing
when the systems behave abnormally.
This approach has been particularly
effective for runtime threat
detection in container environments.
So the machine learning,
enhanced container security.
Speaking of containers, organizations
implementing machine learning,
enhanced container security solutions
have reduced vulnerabilities by 89%
compared to the traditional approaches.
This comprehensive prediction covers the.
Entire container lifecycle from
build to runtime and ensuring that
micro microservices remain secure
without sacrificing the development
velocity, the production span.
So like four critical areas.
First thing is image scanning.
Machine learning analyzes the container
images for non vulnerabilities
and suspicious patterns.
Second one is the runtime protection.
The behavioral analysis identifies the
anonymous container activities in real
time, and network security monitors the
container communications for unexpected
connection patterns, and the configuration
analysis evaluates the configurations
against the security best practices.
So natural language processing for
ISE security infrastructure score has
revolutionized cloud deployments, but it
also creates a new security challenges.
Natural language processing techniques
have now transformed ISE security by
understanding the semantic meaning
behind cloud configuration files.
So this approach enables
security systems to identify the.
Misconfigurations risks that
traditional rejects based scanning
might miss, such as overly permissions,
the access policies or insecure
default settings in cloud resources.
The NLP approach involves like four
steps, which is the code analysis, the
passing infrastructure code to understand
resources and the relationships.
Context understanding, grasping
the infrastructure intent beyond
the simple pattern matching
and the risk identification.
Identifying the mis configuration risks
and compliance violations, remediation
suggestions, providing the code level
fixes for identified security issues.
Now let's dive into the machine learning
augmented CICD security pipeline.
When we bring these technologies
together, we get comprehensive
machine learning, augmented CICD
security pipeline that covers every
stage of development in the code.
Commit stage, pre-commit hooks, the
machine learning powered code analysis to
catch vulnerabilities before they enter
the code base during the build stage,
container measures and dependencies are
scanned by supervised learning models for
non vulnerabilities in the test phase.
Automated security testing users,
machine learning to generate test
cases that target likely vulnerability
points at the deployment stage.
Infrastructure scanning with NLP
ensures secure cloud configurations
before provisioning during the runtime.
Unsupervised learning models monitor
application behavior to detect
anomalies and the potential breaches.
Organizations implementing
machine learning.
Augmented CI CD pipelines reduced
meantime to remediation from 38 days to
just over four days, and a dramatic 89%
implement in vulnerability response time.
This acceleration stems from
earlier detection and more
accurate vulnerability information.
Now let's deep dive into a case study.
So a financial service organization
implemented one of the security measures.
Let me share a real world case study.
So a leading financial services company
struggled with releasing updates to their
mobile blanking platform, which secure
peer reviews taking an over like 27 days.
This created a significant
challenge for their business after
implementing and machine learning
security pipeline that cloud con.
The cloud that could prioritize
vulnerabilities and automatically
generate full request for common issues.
They reduced security review time to
just two days while simultaneously
improving their overall security patterns.
Most impressively, their automated
remediation system now handles 76% of
common security issues without human
intervention, allowing the security
team to more focus on more of the
complex threats and the strategic.
Improvements.
Now let's deep dive into the
implementation framework.
If you convinced and want to implement
this approach in your organization, here's
a practical implementation framework.
Start with assessment and planning.
Document the existing
security controls and gaps.
Define the success metrics
aligned with the business goals.
Build a cross-functional
implementation team.
Then move on to the
initial implementation.
Implement the code scanning
in the CI pipeline.
There are a lot of tools in
the market that we could use.
Deploy the container security
monitoring, establish the feedback
loops for model improvement.
Finally, advance to advanced integration.
Deploy unsupervised models for runtime
protection in form of automation.
Implement the automated remediation
workflows, create customized
machine learning models too.
For the unique environments.
Key takeaways and next steps.
Let me conclude this with a key
takeaway from our discussion today.
Performance advantages.
If we imp if we are able to implement
this, we will likely be having 71%
fewer security incidents, three
times faster security deployments
close to 90% reduction in M TTRs.
Which is meantime to remediate the
vulnerabilities from like 38 to just
over four days, 43% lower security
remediation costs, and the implementation
strategy, as I discussed earlier.
Start with the supervised learning
for non vulnerabilities layer in the
unsupervised models for anomaly detection.
Implement the across entire
pipeline from code to runtime.
Establish.
Machine learning model evaluation metrics
to use by 87% of high performance teams.
Next steps for you after this presentation
is to just assess your current security
automation maturity, identify high impact
integration points in your pipeline.
Start with one machine learning
security tool and measure the results.
Build internal expertise
through hands on implementation.
By integrating this machine learning
into your DevSecOps pipeline, you can
achieve the same contribute goals of
enhancing security while accelerating
the deployment and the development.
The key to implement machine learning
power tools strategically across
your entire development lifecycle.
So that it'll allow you to shift
from reactive security measures
to predictive protection.
Thank you all for paying
attention to this.
Thank you.
Have a great day.